<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Polish <hi rend="italic">pans</hi>  and the attempts of the Jesuits to introduce the Roman Catholic religion ; (3) the period of the Haidamaks, who formed the nucleus of the national party, and prolonged the struggle. The gradual break up of tho military republic of these sturdy freebooters has already been described.</p><p>The foundation of the Little Russian literature (written, as opposed to tho oral) was laid by Ivan Kotliarevski (1769-1838), whose travesty of part of the <hi rend="italic">Æneid</hi>  enjoys great popularity among some of his countrymen. Others, however, object to it as tending to bring the language or dialect into ridicule. A truly national poet appeared in Taras Shevchenko, born at the village of Kirilovka in the government of Kieff, in the condition of a serf. The strange adventures of his early life he has told us in his autobiography. He did not get his freedom till some time after he had reached manhood, when he was purchased from his master by the generous efforts of the poet Zhukovski and others. Besides poetry, he occupied himself with painting with considerable success. He unfortunately became obnoxious to the Government, and was punished with exile to Siberia from 1847 to 1857. He did not long survive his return, dying in 1861, aged forty-six. No one has described with greater vigour than Shevchenko the old days of the Ukraine. In his youth he listened to the village traditions handed down by the priests, and he has faithfully reproduced them. The old times of Nalivaiko, Doroshenko, and others live over again. Like Gogol he is too fond of describing scenes of bloodshed. In the powerful poem entitled <hi rend="italic">Haidamak</hi>  we have a graphic picture of tho horrors enacted by Gonta and his followers at Uman. The sketches are almost too realistic. Like Burns with the old Scottish songs, so Shevchenko has reproduced admirably the spirit of the lays of the Ukraine. All those familiar with his works will remember the charming little lyrics with which they are interspersed. The funeral of the poet was a vast public procession ; a great cairn, surmounted with a cross, was raised over his remains, where he lies buried near Kanioff on tho banks of tho Dnieper. His grave has been styled the “ Mecca of the</p><p>South Russian Revolutionists.” He is the great national poet of the Southern Russians. A complete edition of his works, with interesting biographical notices—one contributed by the novelist Turgenieff—appeared at Prague in 1876. Besides the national songs, excellent collections of the South Russian folk-tales have appeared, edited by Dragomanoff, Rudchenko, and others. Many of these are still recited by the “ tchumaki” or wandering pedlars. A valuable work is the <hi rend="italic">Zapiski o Yuzhuoi Rossii</hi>  (“Papers on Southern Russia”), published at St Petersburg in 1857 by Panteleimon Kulish. After he got into trouble (with Kostomaroff and Shevchenko) for his political views, the late works of this author show him to have undergone a complete change. Other writers using the Little Russian language are Marko-Vovchok (that is, Madame Eugenia JIarkovich), and Yuri Fedkovieh, who employs a dialect of Buko-vina. Fedkovich, like Shevchenko, sprang from a peasant family, and served as a soldier in the Austrian army against the French during the Italian campaign. Naturally we find his poems filled with descriptions of life in the camp. Like the Croat Preradovid, ho began writing poetry in the German language, till he was turned into more natural paths by some patriotic friends. A collection of songs of Bukovina was published at Kieff in 1875 by Lona-chevski. At the present time Eugene Zelechowski continues his valuable <hi rend="italic">Dictionary of Little Russian,</hi>  of which about one half has appeared. This promises to be a very useful book, for up to the present time students have been obliged to rest satisfied with the scanty publications of Levchenko, Piskunoff, and Verchratzki. There is a good grammar by Osadtza, a pupil of Miklosich.</p><p>In the White Russian dialect are to be found only a few songs, with the exception of portions of the Scriptures and some legal documents. A valuablo dictionary was published a short time ago by Nosovich, but this is one of the most neglected of the Russian dialects, as the part in which it is spoken is one of the dreariest of the empire. Collections of White Russian songs have been published by Sheiu and others. For details regarding this and the other Russian dialects see Slavs.    (W. R. M.)</p><p>RUSTCHUK (RusCuk), a city of Bulgaria, Turkey in Europe, on the south bank of the Danube, opposite Giurgevo, at the point where the river receives the waters of the Lorn, a fine stream from the northern slopes of the Balkans. Since 1867 it has been connected by rail (139 miles) with Varna. The town was nearly destroyed by the Russian bombardment from Giurgevo in 1877, and the military works have since been dismantled in terms of the treaty of Berlin. Its position on the river frontier of Turkey long made it a place of strategic importance. In 1871 the population was about 23,000 (10,800 Turks, 7700 Bulgarians, 1000 Jews, 800 Armenians, 500 Gipsies, 800 Wallachians and Serbs, 400 Western Europeans), and in 1881 it was returned as 26,163.</p><p>In the time of the Romans Rustchuk was one of the fortified points along the line of the Danube. In the <hi rend="italic">Tabula Peutingemana </hi>it appears as Prisca, in the <hi rend="italic">Antonine Itinerary</hi>  as Serantaprista, in the <hi rend="italic">Notitia</hi>  as Seragintaprista, and in Ptolemy as Priste Polis. Destroyed by the barbarian invasion, the town recovered its importance only in comparatively modem times. In 1810 it was captured by the Russians, and on his departure next year Kutusoff destroyed tho fortifications. In 1828-29 and again in 1853-54 it played a part in the Russo-Turkish War, and in 1877, as already mentioned, it was nearly destroyed.</p><p>RUTH, Book of. The story of Ruth, the Moabitess, great-grandmother of David, one of the Old Testament</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>