<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>translated from HTML to TEI</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-23-r03-0367-02"
                facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0390.jp2" type="entry">

                <p><label>RITCHIE, CHARLES THOMSON RITCHIE</label>, <hi rend="smallcaps">1st
                        baron</hi> (1838-1906), English politician, was born at Dundee, and educated
                    at the City of London school. He went into business, and in 1874 was returned to
                    parliament as Conservative member for the Tower Hamlets. In 1885 he was made
                    Secretary to the Admiralty, and from 1886 to 1892 president of the Local
                    Government Board, in Lord Salisbury’s administration, sitting as member for St
                    George’s in the East. He was responsible for the Local Government Act of 1888,
                    instituting the county councils; and a large section of the Conservative party
                    always owed him a grudge for having originated the London County Council. In
                    Lord Salisbury’s later ministries, as member for Croydon, he was president of
                    the Board of Trade (1895-1900), and home secretary (1895-1900); and when Sir
                    Michael Hicks-Beach retired in 1902, he became chancellor of the exchequer in Mr
                    Balfour’s cabinet. Though in his earlier years he had been a “ fair-trader,” he
                    was strongly opposed to Mr Chamberlain’s movement for a preferential tariff (see
                    the articles on <hi rend="smallcaps">Balfour <hi rend="sub">j</hi> A.</hi> J.,
                    and <hi rend="smallcaps">Chamber-lain,</hi> J.), and he resigned office in
                    September 1903. In December 1905 he was created a peer, but he was in
                    ill-health, and he died at Biarritz on the 9th of January 1906.</p>            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
