<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>translated from HTML to TEI</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-23-r03-0401-01"
                facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0424.jp2" type="entry">

               <p>                   <label>ROBERT OF AUXERRE</label> (<hi rend="italic">c.</hi> 1156-1212), French
                    chronicler, was an inmate of the monastery of St Marien at Auxerre. At the
                    request of Milo de Trainel (1155-1202), abbot of this house, he wrote a <hi
                        rend="italic">Chronicon,</hi> or universal history, which covers the period
                    between the creation of the world and 1211. For the years previous to ri8i this
                    is merely a compilation from Prosper of Aquitaine, Sigebert of Gembloux and
                    others, but it is an original authority for the period from 1181 to 1211. It is
                    one of the most valuable sources for the history of France during the reign of
                    Philip Augustus, and it also contains information about other European
                    countries, the Crusades and affairs in the East. Molinier, in fact, describes
                    the author as one of the best historians of the middle ages. Robert was
                    evidently a man of great diligence and of sound judgment. Two continuators took
                    the work down to 1228 and it was extensively used by later chroniclers. The
                    original manuscript is now at Auxerre.</p>               <p>The <hi rend="italic">Chronicon</hi> was first published by N. Camuzat at Troyes
                    in 1608; the best edition is in Band xxvi. of the <hi rend="italic">Monumenta
                        Germaniae historica. Scriptores,</hi> with introduction by A. Holder-Egger.
                    Robert has been identified, but on very questionable grounds, with a certain
                    Robert Abolant <hi rend="sub">1</hi> an official of the monastery of St Marien,
                    who died in 1214. See A. Molinier, <hi rend="italic">Les Sources de l’histoire
                        de France,</hi> tomes iii. and iv. (19O3-1904).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
