<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>translated from HTML to TEI</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-23-r03-0451-02"
                facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0484.jp2" type="entry">

                <p><label>ROE-BUCK</label> the smallest of the British deer (a full-grown buck
                    standing not more than 27 in. high at the shoulder), the typical representative
                    of a genus <hi rend="italic">(Capreolus)</hi> in which the antlers lack a
                    brow-tine and belong to what is characterized as the forked type, while the tail
                    is rudimentary (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Deer).</hi> The antlers are short,
                    upright arid deeply furrowed, the beam forking at «about two-thirds of its
                    length, and the upper prong again dividing, thus making three points. The coat
                    in summer is foxy red above and white below; in winter this changes to a greyish
                    fawn, with a white rump-patch. The roe-buck or roe-deer <hi rend="italic"
                        >(Capreolus caprea,</hi> or C. <hi rend="italic">capreolus)</hi> inhabits
                    southern and temperate Europe as far east as the Caucasus, where, as in Syria,
                    it is probably represented by another race or species. It frequents woods,
                    preferring such as have a large growth of underwood and are in the neighbourhood
                    of cultivated ground. The latter it visits in the evening in search of food; and
                    where roe are numerous the damage done to growing crops is considerable. Pairing
                    takes place in August, but the fawns are not born till the following May.
                    According to one theory, the germ lies dormant until December, when it begins to
                    develop; but it is now believed that this long gestation is due to slow rather
                    than arrested development. Roe were formerly abundant in all the wooded parts of
                    Great Britain, but were gradually exterminated, till a century and a half ago
                    they were unknown</p>
               <p>south of Perthshire. Since then the increase of plantations has led to the
                    partial restoration of the species in the south of Scotland and the north of
                    England; and it was reintroduced into Dorset early in the 19th century. These
                    deer take readily to the water, and they have been known to swim across lochs
                    more than half a mile in breadth. The Siberian roe (C. <hi rend="italic"
                        >pygargus),</hi> which is common in the Altai, is larger and paler than the
                    type species, with shorter and more hairy ears, a larger white rump-patch, and
                    small irregular snags on the inner border of the antlers. The Manchurian roe <hi
                        rend="italic">(Capreolus manchuricus)</hi> is about the size of the European
                    species, with antlers of the type of those of the Siberian roe, but more
                    slender, and the coat shorter. Although described in 1889 as a local variety of
                    the Siberian species, the Manchurian roe really appears, both as regards
                    stature, hairiness and the black and white markings on the muzzle, much more
                    nearly related to the European animal. This is the more remarkable seeing that
                    the habitats of the two are separated by such an enormous tract of country. (R.
                    L.*)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
