<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="chi.28490924-1526168109_Page_0892.jpf" type="entry" xml:id="eb07-20-s05-0745-02" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>STRAIN</label>
or <hi rend="smallcaps">Stress,</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Mechanics,</hi> are terms indiscriminately used to express the force which is excited in any part of a machine or structure of any kind, tending to break it in that part. Thus every part of a rope is equally strained by the weight which it suspends. Every part of a pillar is equally strained by the load which it supports. A mill axle is equally twisted and strained in every part which lies between the part of the wheel actuated by the moving power and the part which is resisted by the work to be performed. Every part of a lever or joist is differently strained by a force acting on a distant part.</p><p>It is evident that we cannot make the structure fit for its purpose, unless the strength at every part be at least equal to the stress laid on, or the strain exc∣ted in that part. It is no less plain, that if we are ignorant of the principles which determine this strain, both in intensity and direction, in relation to the magnitude and the situation of its remote cause, the only security we have for success is to give to every part of the assemblage such solidity that we can leave no doubt of its sufficiency. But daily experience shows us that this vague security is in many cases uncertain, if we are thus ignorant. In all cases it is slovenly, unlike an artist, attended with useless expense, and in machines is attended with a loss of power which is wasted in changing the motions of a needless load of matter.</p><p>It must therefore greatly tend to the improvement of all professions occupied in the erection or employment of such structures, to have a distinct notion of the strains to which these parts are exposed. Frequently, nay generally,, these strains are not immediate, but arise from the action of forces on distant parts, by which the assemblage is strained, and there is a tendency to rupture in every part. This strain is <hi rend="italic">induced</hi> on every part, and is there modified by fixed mechanical laws. These it is our business to learn ; but our chief object in this investigation is to determine the strength of materials which it is necessary to oppose in every part to this strain, and how to oppose this strength in such a manner that it shall be exerted to the best advantage. The notions of strain and strength therefore hardly admit of separation ; for it is even by means of the strength of the intermediate parts that the strain is propagated to, or excited in, the part under consideration. It is proper therefore to consider the whole together under the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Strength of Materials.</hi></p></div></body></text></TEI>