<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="chi.28490924-1526168109_Page_0926.jpf" type="entry" xml:id="eb07-20-s05-0779-07" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>STROMNESS</label>,
a town in the parish of the same name in the island of Pomona, Orkney, in long. 3. 38. W. and lat. 58. 58. N. The town is situated on the western side of the island, and was formerly an insignificant village, dependent on the borough of Kirkwall, which kept it completely under; but by a decision of the House of Lords, Stromness and all other villages were declared free from being assessed, and otherwise independent of royal boroughs. The present town consists of one long rambling street, built round the bay on which it is placed. The greater portion of the houses are built so close on the water that they require to be defended by bulwarks, jetties, and quays, to keep them from being overwhelmed by<pb facs="chi.28490924-1526168109_Page_0927.jpf" xml:id="eb07-20-s05-0780"/>
the sea. At these small vessels load and unload. The harbour is formed by the bay, which is about a mile in length, and half of that in breadth. It forms one of the most secure harbours in the north of Scotland, and affords safe anchorage for vessels of 1000 tons burden ; and it is the chief resort for shipping in the northern isles. The wealth of the inhabitants is chiefly derived from the Greenland whalers, which touch here to complete their crews from the sailors belonging to the place, as well as to supply the vessels with provisions and stores. The Hudson Bay vessels also touch here. A number of ships and boats are built at Stromness ; and the manufacture of straw-plait is carried on to a considerable extent. It was erected into a borough of barony in the year 1817, and it is governed by two bailies and nine councillors. The population in 1831 amounted to 2182.</p></div></body></text></TEI>