<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="chi.28490924-1526168109_Page_0947.jpf" type="entry" xml:id="eb07-20-s05-0800-04" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SULPITIUS <hi rend="smallcaps">Severus</hi></label>,
 an ecclesiastical writer, was born in Aquitania about the year 363. His father was a man of superior rank. Having received a suitable education, the son applied himself to the practice of the law, and distinguished himself by his learning and eloquence. He married a rich wife, and was thus placed in a state of greater independence. He chiefly resided at Toulouse, and at <hi rend="italic">Eluso</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Elusio,</hi> near Carcassonne. The death of his beloved wife weaned his affections from the world, and he is supposed to have devoted himself to an ecclesiastical, if not a monastic life. He had recourse to the instructions of Martin bishop of Tours, whose life he has written ; and he likewise contracted a friendship with Paulinus bishop of Nola. The invasion of the Vandals impelled him to seek a place of refuge at Marseille, where he entered a monastery, and is supposed to have died about the year 410. His principal work is his <hi rend="italic">Historia Sacra,</hi> deduced from the creation of the world to his own time, and written in a style superior to the standard of that declining age of Lati- nity. The first edition was published by Flacius Illyricus. Basil. [1556] 8vo. Various editions of his works subsequently appeared ; some of which were illustrated by the notes of Sigonius, Vorstius, Horn, and Le Clerc. A more elaborate edition was undertaken by De Prato, Ve- ronæ, 1741—54, 2 tom. 4to. He promised a third volume, which however did not make its appearance.</p></div></body></text></TEI>