<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="chi.28490924-1526168109_Page_0931.jpf" type="entry" xml:id="eb07-20-s05-0784-06" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>STUKELEY, <hi rend="smallcaps">William</hi></label>,
 an eminent antiquary, descended from an ancient family in Lincolnshire, was born at Holbech in that county, on the 7th of November 1687. From the free school of his native town he was removed to Corpus Christi College, Cambridge, where he was admitted on the 7th of November 1703. Having chosen the medical profession, he took the degree of Μ. B. in 1709, and that of Μ. D. in 1719. He first settled as <hi rend="italic">a</hi> practitioner at Boston; but in 1717 be removed to London, and was admitted a fellow of the College of Physicians in 1720. By the recommendation of Dr Mead, he was chosen a fellow of the Royal Society. He contributed to the re-establishment of the Society of Antiquaries ; of which he officiated as secretary for many years. In 1726 he left the metropolis, and settled at Grantham in Lincolnshire, where he soon obtained extensive practice. In 1728 he married Frances, the daughter of Robert Williamson, Esq. of Allington, a lady of good family and fortune. Being much afflicted with the gout, he found the exercise of his profession very laborious, and therefore meditated a retreat into the church. On the 20th of July 1720, being then in the thirty-third year of his age, he received ordination from Archbishop Wake ; and in the ensuing October was presented by the lord-chancellor King to the living of All-Saints in Stamford. He became a widower in 1737, and, in the course of the following year, married the only daughter of Dr Gale, the learned dean of York. In 1739 the living of Somerby near Grantham was bestowed upon him by the duke of Ancaster. In 1747 the duke of Montagu presented him to the rectory of St George, Queen Square, and he then vacated his other benefices. He survived till the 3d of March 1765. On the 27th of the preceding month, he had been struck with palsy, after attending a full vestry on a contested election for a lecturer. The apartment was much heated ; and on returning through his garden, accompanied by Serjeant Eyre, “ they both caught their deaths, for the serjeant never was abroad again, and the doctor’s illness came on that night.” By his first wife Dr Stukeley bad three daughters, one of whom died young, and the other two survived him. The one was married to Mr Richard Fleming, an eminent solicitor, and the other to the Rev. Thomas Fairchild, rector of Pitsey in Essex. They both died in 1782. Of his second marriage there was no issue.</p><p>Dr Stukeley was a man of varied learning, but was chiefly distinguished by his knowledge of antiquities. His writings are numerous, and partly relate to medical, as well as theological subjects ; but we shall confine ourselves to an enumeration of the most important or curious of his antiquarian publications. An Account of a Roman Temple near Graham's Dike. 1720, 4to. Of the Roman Amphitheater at Dorchester. Lond. 1723, 4to. <hi rend="italic">Itinerarium Curiosum ; or,</hi> an Account of the Antiquitys and remarkable Curiosities in Great Britain. Lond. 1724, fol, Lond. 1776, 2 vols. fol. Stonehenge ; a Temple restor’d to the British Druids. Lond. 1740, fol. Abury: a Temple of the British Druids: with some others described. Lond. 1743, fol. <hi rend="italic">Palæographia Britannica ;</hi> or, Discourses on Antiquities in Britain. Lond. 1743-52, 4to. An Account of Richard of</p><p>supposed negociation he apparently refers to the year 1783, or some period subsequent to the appearance of the English Review. The degree had very honourably been conferred upon Stuart many years before; and Julin Whitaker, on whom it was never conferred, was a B. D. of Oxford.<pb facs="chi.28490924-1526168109_Page_0932.jpf" xml:id="eb07-20-s05-0785"/>
Cirencester. Lond. 1757, 4-to. The Medallic History of Marcus Aurelius Valerius Carausius, Emperor in Britain. Loud. 1757-9, 2 vols. 4to.</p></div></body></text></TEI>