<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>translated from HTML to TEI</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-23-r03-0401-05"
                facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0424.jp2" type="entry">
               <p>                   <label>ROBERT OF TORIGNI</label> (<hi rend="italic">c.</hi> 1110-1186), medieval
                    chronicler, was prior of Bec in 1149, and in 1154 became abbot of Mont</p>                <pb xml:id="eb11-23-r03-0402" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0425.jp2"/>
               <p>St Michel, whence he is also sometimes called Robertus de Monte. He died,
                    according to Potthast, on the 29th of May 1186. He wrote additions and
                    appendices to the chronicle of Sigebert of Genblours, covering the period <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">a.d.</hi> 385-1100, and a chronicle in continuation of
                    Sigebert, extending from 1100 to 1186, of great value for Anglo-Norman history.
                    Robert was in a good position to obtain information, for the Mont St Michel was
                    one of the four great centres of pilgrimage in Europe. But he was excessively
                    timid and cautious, and hardly mentions events, like the murder of Becket, which
                    were subjects of controversy. Besides, his style is that of the driest annalist.
                    It is for continental affairs between 1154 and 1170 that his information is
                    especially valuable. His notices of English affairs are slight and sometimes
                    misleading.</p>               <p>The best modern editions are the <hi rend="italic">Chronique de Robert de
                        Torigni,</hi> &amp;, edited by Léopold Delisle for the Soc. <hi
                        rend="italic">de l’histoire de Normandie</hi> (Rouen, 1872-1873), and <hi
                        rend="italic">Chronicle of Robert of Torigni,</hi> edited, with an
                    introduction, by Richard Howlett (Rolls Series, No. 82, iv. 1889).</p>            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
