<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>translated from HTML to TEI</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-23-r03-0399-01"
                facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0422.jp2" type="entry">

               <p>                   <label>ROBERT III.</label> (c. 1340-1406), king of Scotland, was the
                    eldest son of King Robert II. by his mistress, Elizabeth Mure, and was
                    legitimatized when his parents were married about 1349. In 1368 he was created
                    earl of Carrick, and he took some part in the government of the kingdom until
                    about 1387, when he was disabled by the kick of a horse. It was probably in
                    consequence of this accident that his brother Robert, earl of Fife, and not the
                    crown prince himself, was made guardian of the kingdom in 1389; but the latter
                    succeeded to the throne on his father’s death in May 1390. At this time he
                    changed his baptismal name of John, which was unpopular owing to its connexion
                    with John de Baliol, for that of Robert, being crowned at Scone in August 1390
                    as King Robert III. Although he probably attended several parliaments the new
                    king was only the nominal ruler of Scotland, the real power being in the hands
                    of his brother, the earl of Fife. In 1399, however, owing to the king’s “
                    sickness of the body,” his elder son, David, duke of Rothesay, was appointed
                    lieutenant of the kingdom; but this event was followed by an English invasion of
                    Scotland, by serious differences between Rothesay and his uncle, Robert, now
                    duke of Albany, and finally in March 1402 by Rothesay’s. mysterious death at
                    Falkland. Early in 1406 the king’s only surviving son, afterwards King James I.,
                    was captured by the English; and on the 4th of April 1406 Robert died, probably
                    at Rothesay, and was buried at Paisley. He married Annabella Drummond (c.
                    1350-1402), daughter of Sir John Drummond of Stobhall, and, in addition to the
                    two sons already mentioned, had four daughters.</p>            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
