<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>translated from HTML to TEI</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-23-r03-0510-02"
                facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0551.jp2" type="entry">

                <p><label>ROMAN EMPIRE, LATER</label> . The reign of Constantine the Great forms the
                    most deep-reaching division in the history of Europe. The external continuity is
                    not broken, but the principles which guided society in the Greek and Roman world
                    are replaced by a new order of ideas. The emperor-worship, which expressed a
                    belief in the ideal of the earthly empire of Rome, gives way to Christianity;
                    this is the outward sign that</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-23-r03-0511" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0552.jp2"/>
               <p>a mental transformation, which we can trace for 300 years before in visible
                    processes of decay and growth, had reached a crisis.</p>
               <p>Besides the adoption of Christianity, Constantine <hi rend="sup">i</hi> S reign
                    is marked by an event only second in importance, the shifting of the centre of
                    gravity of the Empire from the west to the east by making Byzantium a second
                    capital, a second Rome. The foundation of Constantinople <hi rend="italic"
                        >(q.v.)</hi> determined the subsequent history of the state; it established
                    permanently the division between the eastern and western parts of the Empire —a
                    principle already introduced—and soon exhibited, though not immediately, the
                    preponderance of the eastern half. The eastern provinces were the richest and
                    most resourceful, and only needed a Rome in their midst to proclaim this fact;
                    and further, it was eastward that the Empire fronted, for here was the one great
                    civilized state with which it was in constant antagonism. Byzantium was
                    refounded on the model of Rome, had its own senate, and presently a <hi
                        rend="italic">praefcctus urbi.</hi> But its character was different in two
                    ways: it was Christian and it was Greek. From its foundation New Rome had a
                    Christian stamp; it had no history as the capital of a pagan empire. There was,
                    however, no intention of depressing Rome to a secondary rank in political
                    importance; this was brought about by the force of circumstances.</p>
               <p>The Christian Roman Empire, from the first to the last Constantine, endured for
                    1130 years, and during that long period, which witnessed the births of all the
                    great modern nations of Europe, experienced many vicissitudes of decline and
                    revival. In the $th century it lost all its western provinces through the
                    expansion of the Teutons; but in the 6th asserted something of its ancient power
                    and won back some of its losses. In the 7th it was brought very Iow <hi
                        rend="sup">r</hi> through the expansion of the Saracens and of the Slavs,
                    but in consequence of internal reforms and prudent government in the 8th century
                    was able before the end of the 9th to initiate a new brilliant period of power
                    and conquest. From the middle of the nth century a decline began; besides the
                    perpetual dangers on the eastern and northern frontiers, the Empire was menaced
                    by the political aggression of the Normans and the commercial aggression of
                    Venice; then its capital was taken and its dominions dismembered by Franks and
                    Venetians in 1204. It survived the blow for 250 years, as a shadow of its former
                    self.</p>
               <p>During this long life its chief political rôle was that of acting as a defender
                    of Europe against the great powers of western Asia. While it had to resist a
                    continuous succession of dangerous enemies on its northern frontier in
                    Europe—German, Slavonic, Finnic and Tatar peoples—it always considered that its
                    front was towards the east, and that its gravest task was to face the powers
                    which successively inherited the dominion of Cyrus and Darius. From this point
                    of view we might divide the external history of the Empire into four great
                    periods, each marked by a struggle with a different Asiatic power: (1) with
                    Persia, ending <hi rend="italic">c.</hi> 630 with the triumph of Rome; (2) with
                    the Saracens, who ceased to be formidable in the nth century;</p>
               <p>(3) with the Seljuk Turks, in the nth and 12th centuries;</p>
               <p>(4) with the Ottoman Turks, in which the Roman power went down.</p>
               <p>Medieval historians, concentrating their interest on the rising states of
                    western Europe, often fail to recognize the position held by the later Empire
                    and its European prestige. Up to the middle of the nth century it was in actual
                    strength the first power in Europe, except in the lifetime of Charles the Great,
                    and under the Comneni it was still a powær of the first rank. But its political
                    strength does not express the fulness of its importance. As the heir of
                    antiquity it was confessedly superior in civilization, and it was supreme in
                    commerce. Throughout the whole period (to 1204) Constantinople was the first
                    city in the w <hi rend="sup">r</hi> orld. The influence which the Empire exerted
                    upon its neighbours, especially the Slavonic peoples, is the second great rôle
                    which it fulfilled for Europe—a rôle on which perhaps the most speaking
                    commentary is the doctrine that the Russian Tsar is the heir of the Roman
                    Caesar.</p>
               <p>The Empire has been called by many names* Cireek, Byzantine, Lower (Bas-empire),
                    Eastern (or East-Roman). All these have a certain justification as descriptions,
                    but the only strictly correct name is <hi rend="italic">Roman</hi> (as
                    recognized in the title of Gibbon’s work). The continuity from Augustus to
                    Constantine XI. is unbroken; the emperor w <hi rend="sup">r</hi> as always the
                    Roman emperor; his subjects w'ere always Romans <hi rend="italic"
                        >('Ρωμαίοι:</hi> hence <hi rend="italic">Romaic—</hi> Modern Greek). “ Greek
                    Empire ” expresses the fact that the state became predominantly Greek in
                    character, owing to the loss, first of the Latin provinces, afterwards of Syria
                    and Egypt; and from the middle of the 6th century Greek became the official
                    language. <hi rend="italic">“ Lower</hi> Empire ” <hi rend="italic">(Later</hi>
                    is preferable) marks the great actual distinction in character between the
                    development before Constantine (Haut-empire) and after his adoption of
                    Christianity. “ Byzantine sums up in a WOrd the unique Gracco-Roman civilization
                    which was centred in New Rome. <hi rend="italic">Eastern</hi> is a term of
                    convenience, but it has been used in tw <hi rend="sup">r</hi> o senses, not to
                    be confused. It has been used, <hi rend="italic">loosely,</hi> to designate the
                    eastern half of the Empire during the 80 years or so (from 395) when there were
                    two lines of emperors, ruling formally as colleagues but practically
                    independent, at Rome and Constantinople; but though there were two emperors, as
                    often before, there was only one Empire, lt has also been used, justifiably, to
                    distinguish the true Koman Empire from the new state founded by Charles the
                    Great (800), which also chimed to be the Roman Empire; <hi rend="italic"
                        >Eastern</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Western Empire</hi> are from this date
                    forward legitimate terms of distinction. But between the periods to which the
                    legitimate and Jllegitimate uses of the term “ Eastern Empire ” apply lies a
                    period of more than 300 years, in which there w’as only one Empire in any sense
                    of the word.</p>
               <p>A chronological table of the dynasties will assist the reader of the historical
                    sketch which follows.</p>
               <p>                    <hi rend="italic">Succession of Emperors arranged in Dynasties.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>1. <hi rend="smallcaps">Constantinian Dynasty.—a.d.</hi> 324-363.</p>
               <p>Emperors (founder of dynasty, Constantius L, 305-306): Constantine I. (306, sole
                    emperor since), 324-337.</p>
               <p>In west—Constantine IL, 337-340; Constans, 337-350. In east—Constantius IL, 337-
                    .</p>
               <p>Sole emperors: Constantius IL, 350-361; Julian, 361-363. lNTER-DYNASTY.— Jovian,
                    363-364.</p>
               <p>2. <hi rend="smallcaps">Valentinianean Dynasty.—a.d.</hi> 364-392.</p>
               <p>Emperors:</p>
               <p>In west—Valentinian L, 364-375; Gratian, 367-383; VaIcntinian 11., 375-392.</p>
               <p>In east—Valens, 365-378 (Theodosius L, 379-392).</p>
               <p>3. <hi rend="smallcaps">Theodosian Dynasty.—a.d.</hi> 392-457.</p>
               <p>Emperors: Theodosius I. (379), 392-395..</p>
               <p>In east—Arcadius, 395-408; Theodosius IL, 408-450;</p>
               <p>Marcian, 450-457.</p>
               <p>In west—Hononus, 395-423; Constantius III., 422; Valentinian III., 425-455;
                    (non-dynastic) Maximus, 455; Avitus, 455-456.</p>
               <p>4. <hi rend="smallcaps">Leonine Dynasty.—a.d.</hi> 457-518.</p>
               <p>Emperors:</p>
               <p>In east—Lco L, 457—474; Lco IL, 474; Zeno, 474-491; Anastasius L, 491-518.</p>
               <p>In west—non-dynastic, Majorian, 457—461; Severus, 461-465; (Leo I. sole emperor,
                    465-467); Anthemius, 467-472; Olybrius, 472; Glycerius, 473-474; Julius Nepos,
                    474-480; (usurper, RomuIus Augustulus, 475-476).</p>
               <p>5. <hi rend="smallcaps">Justinianean Dynasty.—a.d.</hi> 518-602.</p>
               <p>Emperors: Justin L, 518-527; Justinian L, 527-565; Justin IL, 565-578; Tiberius
                    IL, 578-582; Alaurice, 582-602.</p>
               <p>                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Inter-Dynasty.</hi> —Phocas, 602-610</p>
               <p>6. <hi rend="smallcaps">Heraclian Dynasty.—a.d.</hi> 610-711.</p>
               <p>Emperors: Heraclius, 610-641; Constantine III., 641; HeracIeonas, 6J.1-642;
                    Constans IL, 642-668; Constantine IV. (Pogonatus) 668-685; Justinian II.
                    (Rhinotmetus), 685-605; (non-dynastic) Leontius,695-698 and Tiberius III.
                    (Apsimar), 698-705; Justinian II. (restored), 705-711. II.</p>
               <p>                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Inter-Dynasty.</hi> —Philip Bardanes, 711-713 ί Anastasius
                    IL, 713-716; Theodosius III., 716-717.</p>
               <p>7. <hi rend="smallcaps">Isaurian (Syrian) Dynasty.—a.d.</hi> 717-802. ,</p>
               <p>Emperors: Leo III., 717-740 (alias, 41); Constantine V. (Copronymus), 740-775;
                    Leo IV. (Khazar), 775-780; Constantine VI., 780-797; Irene, 797-802.</p>
               <p>                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Inter-Dynasty.</hi> —Nicephorus I., 802-811 ; Stauracius
                    (son of Nicephorus), 811 ; Michael I. (Rhangabe <hi rend="sub">l</hi>
                    father-in-law of Stauracius), 811-813; Leo V. (Armenian), 813-820.</p>
               <p>8. <hi rend="smallcaps">Phrygian or Amorian Dynasty—a.d.</hi> 820-867.</p>
               <p>Emperors: Michael II. (Stammerer), 820-829; TheophiIus, 829-842; Michael III.
                    (Drunkard), 842-867.</p>
               <p>9. <hi rend="smallcaps">Macedonian Dynasty.—a.d.</hi> 867-1057.</p>
               <p>Emperors: Basil 1. (Macedonian), 867-886; Leo VI. (philosopher) and Alexander,
                    886-912; Constantine VII.</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-23-r03-0512" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0553.jp2"/>
               <p>(Porphyrogennetos), 9 <hi rend="sup">I2</hi> “959ï RomanusL(Lecapenus), 920-944;
                    Romanus IL, 959-963 ; Basil IL(Bulgaroctonus) and Constantine VIII., 963-1025;
                    (non-dynastie) Nice-phorus II. (Phocas), 963-969, and John Zimisces, 969-976 ;
                    Constantine VIII., alone, 1025-1028; Romanus III. (Argyros), 1028-1034; Michael
                    IV. (Paphlagonian), 1034-1041; Michael V. (Calaphates); 1041-1042; Constantine
                    IX. (Monomachus), 1042-1054; Theodora, 1054-1056; Michael VI. (Stratioticus),
                    1056-1057.</p>
               <p>                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Inter-Dynasty.</hi> —IsaacL (Comnenus), 1057-1059;
                    Constantine X. (Ducas), 1059-1067; Michael VIL (Parapinaces), Andronicus and
                    Constantine XL, 1067; Romanus IV. (Diogenes), 1067-1071; Michael VIL, alone,
                    1071-1078; Nicephorus IIL (Botaneiates) <hi rend="sub">1</hi> 1078-1081.</p>
               <p>10. <hi rend="smallcaps">Comnenian Dynasty.—a.d.</hi> 1081-1204.</p>
               <p>Emperors: Alexius I. (nephew of Isaac L), 1081-1118; John IL, 1118-1143; Manuel
                    L, 1143-1180; Alexius IL, r 180-1183; AndronicusI., 1183-1185 ; Isaac II.
                    (Angelus), 1185-1195; Alexius III. (Angelus), 1195-1203; Isaac II. and Alexius
                    IV., 1203-1204.</p>
               <p>                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Inter-Dynasty.</hi> —AlexiusV. (Murtzuphlus), 1204.</p>
               <p>Capture of Constantinople and dismemberment of the Empire by the Venetiansand
                    Franks, A.D. 1204-1205.</p>
               <p>11. <hi rend="smallcaps">Lascarid Dynasty.—a.d.</hi> 1206-1259.</p>
               <p>Emperors: Theodore I. (Lascaris), 1206-1222; John IIL (Vatatzes or Batatzes),
                    1222-1254; Theodore" IL (Lascaris), 1254-1259.</p>
               <p>12. <hi rend="smallcaps">Palaeologian Dynasty.—a.d.</hi> 1259-1453.</p>
               <p>Emperors: Michael VIIL (Palaeologus), 1259-1282; And-ronicus II. (Elder),
                    1282-1328; Andronicus IIL(Vounger), 1328-1341; John V., 1341-1391;
                    (non-dynastic), John (Cantacuzenus), 1347-1355; Manuel IL, 1391-1425; John VI.,
                    1425-1448; Constantine XL, or XIL (Dragases), 1448-1453.</p>
               <p>                    <hi rend="italic">Historical Sketch.—</hi> Diocletian’s artificial experiment of
                    two Augusti and two Caesars had been proved a failure, leading to twenty years
                    of disastrous civil wars; and when Constantine the Great <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >(ç.ï&gt;.)</hi> destroyed his last rival and restored domestic peace,
                    he ruled for the rest of his life with undivided sway. But he had three sons,
                    and this led to a new partition of the Empire after his death, and to more
                    domestic wars, Constans first annexing the share of Constantine II. (340) and
                    becoming sole ruler of the west, to be in turn destroyed by Constantius II., who
                    in 350 remained sole sovereign of the Empire. Having no children, he was
                    succeeded by his cousin, Julian the Apostate <hi rend="smallcaps">(ç.îî.).</hi>
                    This period was marked by wars against the Germans, who were pressing on the
                    Rhine and Danish frontiers, and against Persia. Julian lost his life in the
                    eastern struggle, which was then terminated by a disadvantageous peace. But the
                    German danger grew graver, and the battle of Adrianopde, in which the Visigoths,
                    who had crossed the Danube in consequence of the coming of the Huns (see <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Goths</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Huns),</hi> won a great
                    victory, and the emperor Valens perished (378), announced that the question
                    between Roman and Teuton had entered on a new stage. Theodosius the Great saved
                    the situation for the time by his,Gothic pacification. The efforts of a series
                    of exceptionally able and hard-working rulers preserved the Empire intact
                    throughout the 4th century, but the dangers which they weathered were fatal to
                    their weaker successors. On the death of Theodosius the decisive moment came for
                    the expansion of the Germans, and they took the tide at the flood. There were
                    three elements in the situation. Besides the Teutonic peoples beyond the
                    frontier there were dependent people who had settled within the Empire (as
                    Visigoths in Moesia, Vandals in Pannonia), and further there were the
                    semi-Romanized Germans in the service of the Empire, some of whom had risen to
                    leading positions (like Merobaudes and Stilicho). Λ Germanization of the Empire,
                    or part of it, in some shape was inevitable, but, if the rulers of the 5th
                    century had been men of the same stamp as the rulers of the 4th, the process
                    might have assumed a different form. The sons of Theodosius were both incapable;
                    and in their reigns the future of the state which was divided between them was
                    decided. The dualism between the east (under Arcadius) and the west (under
                    Honorious) developed under the rule of these brothers into antagonism verging on
                    hostility. The German danger was averted in the east, but it led in a few years
                    to the loss of many of the western provinces, and at the end of ninety years the</p>
               <p>immediate authority of the Roman Emperor did not extend west of the Adriatic.
                    The reign of Honorius saw the abandonment of Britain, the establishment of the
                    Visigothic kingdom in Aquitaine, the occupation of a great part of Spain by
                    Vandals and Sueves (Suebi). Under Valentinian III. the Vandals founded their
                    kingdom in North Africa, the Visigoths sharcd Spain with the Sueves, the
                    Burgundian kingdom was founded in S.E. Gaul. The last Roman possession in Gaul
                    passed to the Franks in 486 (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Goths; Vandals;
                        Franks).</hi> It is significant that the chief defender of the Empire
                    against the Germans who were dismembering it were men of German race. Stilicho,
                    who defended Italy against Alaric, Aetius, whosc great work was to protect the
                    imperial possessions in Gaul, and Ricimer. It was also a German, Fravitta, who
                    played a decisive part in suppressing a formidable Gothic movement which menaced
                    the throne of Arcadius in 399-400. It was characteristic of this transformation
                    of Europe that the Germans, who were imbued with a profound reverence for the
                    Empire and its prestige, founded their kingdoms on Roman soil in the first
                    instance as “ federates ” of the Emperor, on the basis of formal contracts,
                    defining their relations to the native provincials; they seized their dominions
                    not as conquerors, but as subjects. The double position of Alaric himself, as
                    both king of the Visigoths and a <hi rend="italic">magister militum</hi> of the
                    Empire is significant of the situation.</p>
               <p>The development of events was complicated by the sudden growth of the transient
                    empire of the Huns (ç.t&gt;.) in central Europe, forming a third great
                    power, which, reaching from the Rhine to the Caucasus, from the Danube to the
                    Baltic, might be compared in the extent of its nominal supremacy, but in nothing
                    else, to the empires of Rome and Persia. The Huns, whose first appearance had
                    precipitated the Germans on the Empire, now retarded for some years the process
                    of German expansion, while they failed in their own attacks upon the Empire. On
                    Attila’s death (453) his realm collapsed, and his German vassals (Ostrogoths,
                    &amp;c.) founded important kingdoms on its ruins.</p>
               <p>After the death of Valentinian III., the worst of his house, the Theodosian
                    dynasty expired in the west, and the authority of the western emperors who
                    succeeded him in rapid succession reached little beyond Italy. For most of this
                    period of twenty years the general Ricimer, of German birth, held the scales of
                    power in that peninsula, setting up and pulling down emperors. After his death
                    the western throne was no longer tenable. First there was a usurpation; the
                    general Orestes set up his child-son Romulus Augustulus against the legitimate
                    Augustus, Julius Nepos, who was acknowledged by the eastern emperor; but this
                    temporary government was overthrown (476) by a Germanic military revolution
                    headed by Odoacer, who appropriated part of the soil to his. German soldiers and
                    founded an Italian kingdom under the nominal supremacy of the emperor at
                    Constantinople, who, however unwilling, recognized his position (after the death
                    of Julius Nepos).</p>
               <p>The escape of the eastern provinces from the fate of the western illustrates the
                    fact that the strength of the Empire lay in the east. These provinces were more
                    populous and presented greater obstacles to the invaders, who followed the line
                    of least resistance. But it was of immense importance that throughout this
                    period the Empire was able to preserve a practically unbroken peace with its
                    great eastern rival. The struggle with Persia, terminated in 364 by the peace of
                    Jovian, was not renewed till the beginning of the 6th century. It was of greater
                    importance that the rulers pursucd a discreet and moderate policy, both in
                    financial administration and in foreign affairs; and the result was that at the
                    end of a hundred years the diminished Empire was strong and consolidated.
                    Theodosius II. was a weak prince, but his government was ably conducted by
                    Anthemius, by his sister Pulcheria and by the eunuch Chrysaphius. His feign was
                    important for the Armenian question. Theodosius I. had committed the error of
                    consenting to a division of this buffer state in the Roman and Persian spheres
                    of influence, Persia having much the larger. The</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-23-r03-0513" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0554.jp2"/>
               <p>Sassanid government tried to suppress the use of the Greek language. But the
                    government of Theodosius II. officially supported the enterprise of translating
                    the Bible into Armenian (Mesrob had just invented the Armenian alphabet), and
                    this initiated the production of an abundant literature of translations from the
                    Greek, which secured the perpetual connexion of Armenia with European culture,
                    and not with Oriental. This reign is also distinguished by the building of the
                    great landwalls of Constantinople, by the foundation of a university there and
                    by the collection of the imperial laws in the Codex Thcodosianus, which is a
                    mine of material for the social condition of the Empire. It reveals to us the
                    decline of municipal liberty, the decay of the middle classes in the West, the
                    evils of the oppressive fiscal system and an appalling paralysis of Roman
                    administration which had once been so efficient; it shows how the
                    best-intentioned emperors were unable to control the governors and check their
                    corruption; and discloses a disorganization which facilitated the dismemberment
                    of the Empire by the barbarians.</p>
               <p>In the reign of Zcno it seemed probable that an Ostrogothic kingdom would be
                    established in the Balkan peninsula, but the danger was diverted to Italy (see
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Goths).</hi> The kingdom which Theodoric founded there
                    was, in its constitutional aspect, a continuation of Odoacer <hi rend="sup"
                        >i</hi> S regime. He, like Odoacer and Alaric, held the double position of a
                    German king and a Roman official. He was <hi rend="italic">magistcr militum</hi>
                    as well as <hi rend="italic">rex.</hi> His powers were defined by capitulations
                    which were arranged with the emperor Anastasius and loyally observed. The right
                    of legislation was reserved to the emperor, and Theodoric never claimed it; but
                    for all practical purposes he was independent.</p>
               <p>In the 6th century the emperor Justinian, whose talents were equal to his
                    ambitions, found himself, through the financial prudence of his predecessors, in
                    a position to undertake the reconquest of some of the lost western provinces.
                    The Vandal power had declined, and Africa was won back in one campaign by
                    Belisarius in 533. The conquest of Italy was far more difficult. Begun by
                    Belisarius in 535, it was not completed till 554, by Narses. A portion of
                    southern Spain was also won from the Visigoths, so that the Romans again
                    commanded the western straits. Justinian, possessed by large ideas and
                    intoxicated with the majesty of Rome, aspired to be a great conqueror, a great
                    lawgiver, a great pontiff, a great diplomatist, a great builder, and in each of
                    these spheres his reign holds a conspicuous place in the annals of the Empire.
                    His legal work alone, or the building of Santa Sophia was enough to ensure him
                    immortal fame. But deep shadows balance the splendour. The reconquest of Africa
                    was thoroughly justified and advantageous, but Italy was bought at a ruinous
                    cost. In the fir&amp;t place, the Persian empire was at this time ruled by
                    one of its greatest kings, Chosroes I. <hi rend="italic">(q.v.),</hi> who was
                    Jar from peacefully inclined. Justinian was engaged in a long Persian and a long
                    Gothic war at the same time, and the state was unequal to the strain. In the
                    second place, it was all-important for his western policy to secure the goodwill
                    of the Italian provincials and the Roman bishop, and for this purpose he
                    involved himself in an ecclesiastical policy (see below) which caused the final
                    alienation of the Syrian and Egyptian prövinces. The reconquest of the West was
                    purchased by the disunion 'of the East. Thirdly, the enormous expenses of the
                    Italian and Persian wars, augmented by architectural undertakings, caused a
                    policy of financial oppression which hung as a cloud over all the brilliance of
                    his reign, and led to the decline which ensued upon his death. Nor is it to be
                    forgotten that he had at the same time to fulfil the task of protecting the
                    Danube against the Germans, Slavs and Bulgarians who constantly threatened the
                    Illyrian provinces. He spared no expense in building forts and walls.
                    Justinian's name will always be associated with that pf the gifted Theodora, an
                    actress of doubtful fame in her early life, who shared his throne. Their mosaic
                    portraits are preserved in the contemporary church of San Vitale at Ravenna. She
                    possessed great political influence, and the fact that she was a heretic
                    (monophysitc), while Justinian was devoted to orthodoxy, did not mar their
                    harmony, but only facilitated the policy of extending secret favour to the
                    heretics who were publicly condemned, and enabled the left hand to act without
                    the knowledge of the right. The events of the half-century after Justinian's
                    death exhibited the weakness to which his grandiose policy had reduced the
                    Empire. It was attacked on the west, on the north and on the east, and at all
                    points was unequal to coping with its enemies. (1) Italy fell a victim to the
                    Lombards <hi rend="italic">(q.v.),</hi> and in a few years more than half of the
                    peninsula had passed under their sway. (2) The Avars, a Hunnic people who had
                    advanced from the Caspian, took possession of Pannonia and Dacia, and formed an
                    empire, consisting of Slavonic and Bulgarian subjects, which endured for about
                    sixty years. Their chief occupation was to invade the Illyrian peninsula and
                    extort tribute and ransoms from the emperors. So far as the Avars themselves
                    were concerned, these incursions had no permanent significance, but the Slavs
                    who overran the provinces did more • than devastate. These years saw the
                    beginning of the Slavonic settlements which changed the ethnical character of
                    the peninsula, and thus mark the commencement of a new period. Slavs occupied
                    Mocsia and a large part of Macedonia, even close to Thessalonica, which they
                    besieged; they penetrated southward into Greece and made large settlements in
                    the Peloponnesus (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Greece,</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">History,</hi> “ Roman period/’ <hi rend="italic">ad
                        fin.).</hi> They occupied the north-western provinces, which became Croatia
                    and Servia, as well as Dalmatia (except some of the coast towns). In the
                    northern part of the peninsula the Slavonic element remained dominant, but in
                    Greece it. was assimilated to the.Greek (after the 9th century) and has left
                    little record of itself except in place names. (3) The Empire was simultaneously
                    engaged in the perennial strife with Persia. A short interval of peace was
                    secured when the emperor Maurice assisted Chosrocs II. to dethrone a usurper,
                    but after Maurice’s death (602) the final and mortal struggle began (see <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Persia,</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">History,</hi> section viii. “ The Sassanian Empire ”).
                    Throughout the incompetent reign of Phocas the eastern provinces were overrun by
                    the Persians, as the Illyrian were overrun by the Slavs. The unpopular rule of
                    this cruel usurper was terminated in 610 by the intervention of the governor of
                    Africa, whose son Heraclius sailed to Constantinople and, welcomed by an
                    influential party, met with little resistance. Phocas, murderer of Maurice, was
                    -murdered by the people, and the victor was crowned emperor to find himself in
                    presence of a desperate situation. Antioch, Damascus and many other great cities
                    were captured by the Persians; and in 614 Jerusalem was destroyed and the Holy
                    Cross, along with the patriarch, carried off to Ctesiphon. This event produced a
                    profound sensation in Christendom. In 616 Egypt was conquered. The army had
                    fallen into utter disorder under Phocas, and HeracHus so deeply despaired of
                    saving Constantinople that he thought of transferring the imperial capital to
                    Carthage. But the extreme gravity of the situation seems to have wrought a moral
                    change among his subjects; the patriarch Sergius was the mouthpiece of a
                    widespread patriotic feeling, and it was not least through his influence that
                    Heraclius performed the task of creating a capable army. His efforts were
                    rewarded in a series of brilhant campaigns (622-28), which, in the emphasis laid
                    on the contrast between Christianity and fire-worship and on the object of
                    recovering the Cross, had the character of crusades. Heraclius recovered his
                    provinces and held Persia at his mercy (decisive battle at Nineveh, end of 627).</p>
               <p>This war is remarkable for the attempt of the Persians to take Constantinople
                    (626) in conjunction with the Avars and Slavs. Soon afterwards the Avar power
                    began to decay, and the Slavs and Bulgarians shook off their yoke. It seemed as
                    if the Roman government would now be able to regain the control in the Illyrian
                    lands which it had almost entirely lost. It seems probable that Heraclius came
                    to terms with the Slavs—Croatians and Servians—in the north-west; their position
                    was regularized, as vassals of the Empire. But fate allowed no breathing-time to
                    do more; the darkest hour had hardly passed when a new storm-cloud, from an
                    unexpected quarter, overspread the heavens.</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-23-r03-0514" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0555.jp2"/>
               <p>At this point we have to note that the Hellenic element in the state had
                    definitely gained the upper hand before the end of the 6th century, so that
                    henceforward the Empire might be described as Greek. Justinian’s mother-tongue
                    was Latin, and he was devoted to the Latin traditions of Rome, but even he found
                    it necessary to publish his later laws in Greek, and from his reign Greek was
                    the official language.</p>
               <p>Many of the Latin official terms were already represented by Greek equivalents
                        <hi rend="italic">(ύπατος=consul, ίπαρχος = praefectus,</hi> &amp;c.), but
                    they were preserved in great numbers, transliterated and oftcn corrupted <hi
                        rend="italic">(e.g. κόμης, μάγιστρος, άσηκρήτης = a Sccretis, KayKtWaptGs,
                        πραιπόσιτος, κνίστωρ— quaestor, σάκρον παλάτιον, όφφίκων, όψίκιον =
                        Obsequium). *Ρηξ,</hi> rex, was always used of barbarian potentates, <hi
                        rend="italic">βασιλεύς</hi> being reserved as = the emperor (but also
                    applied to the.Persian king). Inmilitary drill many Latin words of command
                    continued to be used.</p>
               <p>It is to be noted that the year 630 marks the beginning of a period of literary
                    (and artistic) sterility in the Greek world (see Greek Literature, section <hi
                        rend="italic">Byzantine).</hi>
               </p>
               <p>With the rise of Islam (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Caliphate; Mahomet)</hi> two
                    universal religions, for the first time, stood face to face, each aspiring to
                    win the universe. The struggle therefore which then began was not only a new
                    phase of the “ Eternal Question,” the strife between Europe and Asia, but was
                    one in which the religious element was fundamental. Fire-worship was only a
                    national religion and did not present the danger of Islam. The creation of the
                    political power of the Mahommedans was so sudden that it took the world by
                    surprise. Bostra, the fortress of Roman Arabia, fell into their hands in 634,
                    and before the death of Heraclius in 641 they had conquered Syria and all Egypt,
                    except Alexandria, which opened its gates to them in 643. The religious
                    alienation of the Syrian and Egyptian peoples from Constantinople, expressing as
                    it did a national sentiment antagonistic to the Greeks, was an important
                    political factor in the Mahommedan (as in the previous Persian) conquest. Thus
                    the Mahommedans definitely cut the Empire short in the East, as the Germans had
                    cut it short in the West; Egypt was never recovered, Syria only for short
                    periods and partially, while the integrity of Asia Minor was constantly menaced
                    and Cilicia occupied for many generations. By their conquest of Persia the
                    Caliphs succeeded to the position of the Sassanids; this led to the conquest of
                    Armenia <hi rend="italic">(c.</hi> 654); while, in the West, Africa was occupied
                    in 647 (though the conquest was not completed till the capture of Carthage and
                    other strong places in 698). Thus within twenty years from the first attack the
                    Empire was girt about by the new aggressive power from the precincts of the
                    Caucasus to the western Mediterranean.</p>
               <p>Fortunately Constans II., grandson of Heraclius, was a man of eminent ability
                    and firmness. The state owed to him the preservation of Asia Minor, and the
                    creation of a powerful fleet (see below) which protected the Aegean coasts and
                    islands against the naval power which the Mahommedans created. He was
                    responsible for completing a new, efficient military organization, which
                    determined the lines of the administrative reforms of Leo III. (see below). In
                    his last years he turned his eyes to Italy and Africa. He dreamed of restoring
                    Old Rome as the centre of the Empire. But he did not succeed in recovering south
                    Italy from the Lombards (Duchy of Beneventum), and having visited Rome he took
                    up his residence in Syracuse, where he was assassinated, having lost two fleets
                    which he sent against the Arabs of Africa. The strain lasted for another fifty
                    years. Constantinople sustained two great sieges, which stand out as crises,
                    for, if in either case the enemy had been successful, the Empire was doomed.</p>
               <p>The first siege was in 673-77, under the caliph Moawiya; his fleet blockaded the
                    capital lor five years, but all its efforts were frustrated by the able
                    precautions of Constantine IV.; “Greek fire” (see below) played an important
                    part in the defence; and the armada was annihilated on tne voyage back to Syria
                    by storms and the Roman fleet. The second crisis was at the accession of Leo
                    III., when the city was besieged by land and sea by Suleiman for a year
                    (717-18), and Leo’s brilliant defence, again aided by Greek fire, saved Europe.
                    This crisis marks the highest point of Mahommedan aggression, which never again
                    caused the Empire to tremble for its existence.</p>
               <p>The Heraclian dynasty, which had fallen on evil times and rendered inestimable
                    services to the Empire, came to an end in anarchy, which was terminated by the
                    elevation of the Syrian (commonly called Isaurian) Leo III., whose rcign opens a
                    new period. His reforming hand was active in every sphere of government, but the
                    ill-fame which he won by his iconoclastic policy obscured in the memory of
                    posterity the capital importance of his work. His provincial organization was
                    revolutionary, and his legislation departed from the Roman tradition (see
                    below). From his reign to the middle of the 10th century the continuous warfare
                    by land with the Caliphs consisted of marauding expeditions of each power into
                    the other’s territory, captures of fortresses, guerilla fighting, but no great
                    conquests or decisive battles. The efficiency of the army was carefully
                    maintained, but the neglect of the navy led to the losses of Crete (conquered by
                    Moslem adventurers from Spain 826) and Sicily (conquered by the Saracens of
                    Africa), Panormus taken 832, Syracuse 878 (see <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Sicily).</hi> ^The Africans also made temporary conquests, including Bari,
                    in south Italy. This period saw the loss ol the exarchate of Ravenna to the
                    Lombards (750), the expansion of the Frankish power under Pippin and Charlemagne
                    in Italy, and in close connexion therewith the loss of Old Rome.</p>
               <p>The inconoclast emperors pursued a moderate foreign policy, consolidating the
                    Empire within its contracted limits.; but under the “ Macedonian ” dynasty,
                    which was of Armenian descent, it again expanded and became the strongest '
                    power in Europe. The 9th century also witnessed a revival of learning and
                    culture which had been in eclipse for 200 years. The reign of Basil I. was
                    marked by an energetic policy in south Italy, where his forces co-operated with
                    the western emperor Louis II. The Saracens were expelled from their strongholds,
                    Bari recovered, Calabria saved, and the new province (Theme) of Longibardia
                    formed. This secured the entrance to the Adriatic, and the increase of dominion
                    here at the expense of the Lombards was a compensation for the loss of Sicily.
                    Leo VI. did much for reorganizing the navy, but his reign was not fortunate;
                    Saracen pirates plundered freely in the Aegean and, under the able renegade Leo
                    of Tripolis, captured Thessalonica and carried off countless captives (904). But
                    a great tide of success began fifty years later. Nicephorus Phocas won back
                    Crete (961) as general of Romanus II., and then as emperor recovered Cilicia and
                    North Syria (with Antioch) 968. Cyprus was also recovered. The tide flowed on
                    under his equally able successor, John Zimisces (of Armenian race) and under
                    Basil II.; these reigns mark the decisive victory of the Empire in the long
                    struggle with the Saracens, whose empire had been broken up into separate
                    states. The eastern frontier was strengthened by the active policy of Basil II.
                    in Armenia, which was more fully incorporated in the Empire under Constantine
                    IX.</p>
               <p>The reign of Basil II. marks the culmination of the power of the Eastern Empire,
                    for it also witnessed the triumphant conclusion of another conflict which had
                    lasted almost as long. In the reign of Constantine IV. the Bulgarians (see <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Bulgaria)</hi> had founded a kingdom in Lower Mocsia,
                    reducing the Slavonic tribes who had occupied the country, but less than two
                    centuries sufficed to assimilate the conquerors to the conquered, and to give
                    Bulgaria the character of a Slavonic state. The reign of Constantine V. was
                    marked by continuous war with this enemy, and Nicephorus I. lost his life in a
                    Bulgarian campaign. This disaster was followed up by Prince Krum, who besieged
                    Constantinople in 815. His death was followed by a long peace. Prince Boris was
                    converted to Christianity (reigm of Michael III.); a metropolitan see of
                    Bulgaria was founded, dependent on the patriarch of Constantinople; and the
                    "civilization of the Bulgarians, and beginnings of their literature, were
                    entirely under Byzantine influence. The conversion was contemporary with the
                    work of the two missionaries Cyril and Methodius, who (while the field of their
                    personal activity was in Great Moravia and</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-23-r03-0515" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0556.jp2"/>
               <p>Pannonia) laid the south-eastern Slavs under a deep debt by inventing the
                    GIagolitie <hi rend="italic">(q.v.), not</hi> the so-called “ Cyrillic ”
                    alphabet (based on Greek cursive) and translating parts of the Scriptures into
                    Slavonic (the dialect of the Slavs of Macedonia). The most brilliant period of
                    the old Bulgarian kingdom was the reign of Simeon (893-927), who extended the
                    realm westward to the shores of the Adriatic and took the title “ Tsar <hi
                        rend="italic">li.e.</hi> Caesar] of Bulgaria and autocrator of the Romans.”
                    The aggression against the Empire which marked his ambitious reign ceased under
                    his successor Peter, who married a daughter of Romanus I., and the Bulgarian
                    Patriarchate founded by Simeon was recognized at Byzantium. But the Byzantine
                    rulers only waited for a favourable time to reduce this formidable Slavonic
                    state. At length Zimisces subjugated eastern Bulgaria and recovered the Danube
                    frontier. But while Basil II. was engaged in contending with rivals, the heroic
                    Samuel (of the Shishmanid family) restored the Bulgarian power and reduced the
                    Servians. After a long and arduous war of fourteen years Basil (called the “
                    Bulgar-slayer ”) subdued all Bulgaria Avestern and eastern (1018). He treated
                    the conquered people with moderation, leaving them their political institutions
                    and their autocephalous church, and to the nobility their privileges. Some
                    Bulgarian noble families and members of the royal house were incorporated in the
                    Greek nobility; there was Shishmanid blood in the families of Comnenus and
                    Ducas. Greek domination was now established in the peninsula for more than 150
                    years. The Slavs of Greece had in the middle of the 9th century been brought
                    under the control of the government.</p>
               <p>In the reign of Basil II. the Russian question also was settled. The Russian
                    state (sec <hi rend="smallcaps">Russia)</hi> had been founded before the middle
                    of the 9th century by Norsemen from Sweden, who were known in eastern Europeas
                    Russians (’Ρώΐ), with its centres at Novgorod and Kiev. They did for the eastern
                    Slavs what the Bulgarians had done for the Slavs of Moesia. The Dnieper and
                    Dniester gave them access to the Euxine, and the Empire was exposed to their
                    maritime attacks (Constantinople was in extreme danger in 860 and 941), which
                    recall the Gothic expeditions of the 3rd century. In 945 a commercial treaty was
                    concluded, and the visit of the princess Olga to Byzantium (towards the end of
                    the reign of the learned emperor Constantine VII., Porphyrogennetos) and her
                    baptism seemed a pledge of peace. But Olga’s conversion had no results.
                    Sviatoslav occupied Bulgaria and threatened the Empire, but was decisively
                    defeated by Zimisces (971), and this was virtually the end of the struggle. In
                    988 Prince Vladimir captured Cherson, but .restored it to the emperor Basil, who
                    gave him his sister Anna in marriage, and he accepted Christianity for himself
                    and his people. After this conversion and alliance, Byzantium had little to fear
                    from Kiev, which came under its influence. One hostile expedition (1043) indeed
                    is recorded, but it was a failure. IvIuch about the same time that the Russians
                    had founded their state, the Magyars (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Hungary;</hi> the
                    Greeks called them Turks) migrated westward and occupied the regions between the
                    Dnieper and the Danube, while beyond them, pressing on their heels, were another
                    new people, the Petchencgs (Patzinaks). The policy of Byzantium was to make use
                    of the Magyars as a cheek on the Bulgarians, and so wc find the Romans (under
                    Leo VI.) and the IVIagyars co-operating against the tsar Simeon. But Simeon
                    played the same game more effectively by using the Petchenegs against the
                    Magyars, and the result was that the Magyars before the end of the 9th century
                    were forced to move westward into their present country, and their place was
                    taken by the Petchenegs. From their new seats the Magyars could invade the
                    Empire and threatened the coast towns of Dalmatia. The conquest of Bulgaria made
                    the Petchcnegs immediate neighbours of the Empire, and during the nth century
                    the depredations of these irreclaimable savages, who filtered into the Balkan
                    peninsula, constantly preoccupied the government. In 1064 they were driven from
                    the Dniester regions into Little Walachia by the Kumans (or PoIovtsi), a people
                    of the same ethnical group as themselves. They were crushingly defeated by
                    Alexius Comncnus in 1091, and exterminated by John Comncnus in 1123.</p>
               <p>In the Macedonian period a grave domestic question troubled the government. This
                    was the growth of the large estates of the rich nobles of Asia Minor, at the
                    expense of small properties, to an excess which was politically and economically
                    dangerous. The legislation against the evil began under Romanus I. and was
                    directed to the defence of the poor against the rich, and to protecting the
                    military organization which was based on holdings of land to which the
                    obligation of military service was attached. There was also danger in the
                    excessive influence of rich and powerful families, from which the great military
                    officers were drawn, and which were extensively related by alliances among
                    themselves. The danger was realized in the struggle which Basil II. had to
                    sustain with the families of Sclerus and Phocas. Various kinds of legislation
                    were attempted. Under Romanus I. alienation of property to the large landowners
                    was forbidden. Niccphorus Phocas, whose sympathies were with the aristocracy to
                    which he belonged, holding that there had been enough legislation in favour of
                    the poor, sought to meet the difficulty of maintaining a supply of military
                    lands in the future by forbidding further acquisitions of estates by the Church.
                    Basil II. returned to the policy of Romanus, but, with much greater severity,
                    resorting to confiscation of some of the immense private estates; and he
                    endeavoured to keep down the aristocrats of Asia Minor by very heavy taxation.
                    Through the recovery of the Balkan provinces he gained in Europe a certain
                    political counterpoise to the influence of Asia Minor, which had been
                    preponderant since the seventh century. Asia Minor meant the army, and
                    opposition to its influence expressed itself in the nth century in a fatal
                    anti-military policy, which is largely responsible for the conquests of a new
                    enemy, the Seljuk Turks, who now entered into the inheritance of the Caliphs
                    (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Caliphate</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">ad fin,</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Seljuks).</hi>
                    Constantinople was haunted by the dread of a military usurpation. An attempt of
                    the military hero George Maniaccs (who had made a remarkable effort to recover
                    Sicily) to wrest the crown f rom Constantine IX. had failed ; and when Isaac
                    Comnenus, who represented the military aristocrats of Asia Minor, ascended the
                    throne, he found himself soon compelled to abdicate, in face of the opposition.
                    The reign of Constantine X., of the rival family of Ducas, marked the
                    culmination of this antagonism. The senate was filled with men of the lower
                    classes, and the military budget was ruthlessly cut down. This policy reduced
                    the army and stopped the supply of officers, since there was no longer hope of a
                    profitable career. The emperor thought to meet dangers from external enemies by
                    diplomacy. The successes of the Seljuks (after the fall of the great Armenian
                    fortress of Ani in 1064) at length awoke the government from its dream of
                    security. The general Romanus Diogenes was proclaimed emperor. He had to create
                    an army and to train it; he did not spare himself, but it was too late. He was
                    defeated and captured by Alp Arslan on the decisive field of Manzikert (1071).
                    Released by the sultan, who honoured his bravery, he was deposed in favour of
                    Michael Ducas, and falling into the hands of his enemies, was blinded. The east
                    and centre of Asia Minor were thus lost; the Seljuk kingdom of Rum was founded;
                    Nicaea was captured by the Turks in 10S0. The provinces which escaped the Seljuk
                    occupation were thoroughly disorganized, a prey to foreign and native
                    adventurers and usurpers (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Seljuks).</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus in the ’seventies of the nth century the Empire seemed through incompetence
                    and frivolity to have been brought te the verge of dissolution. The disorder was
                    terminated by the accession of the extraordinarily able statesman Alexius
                    Com-nenus (io8:), who effected a reconciliation with the rival family of Ducas,
                    established a strong government and founded a dynasty. Hc had to deal with three
                    great dangers—the Scljuks, the Pctehcnegs (see above), and in the west the
                    Normans. The Normans had wrested from East Rome its possessions in South Italy
                    (1041-71 ; sec <hi rend="smallcaps">Normans)</hi> —succeeding where German
                    emperors had failed—and throughout the Comnenian period</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-23-r03-0516" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0557.jp2"/>
               <p>the Empire was threatened by their projects of conquest beyond the Adriatic,
                    projects which aimed at Constantinople itself.</p>
               <p>Four great attempts against the Empire were made by the Normans; they were
                    unsuccessful, but they heralded the Western conquest of 1204. (1) Expedition of
                    Robert Guiscard, 1081-85,</p>
               <p>repelled by Alexius with help of Venice (2) Bohemond's expedition, 1105-7.
                    foiled by the able strategy of Alexius; (3) the invasion of Greece by Roger of
                    Sicily, 1147; Venice supported Manuel Comnenus, and the Normans were driven from
                    Corfu, 1149 ; (4) the expedition of William II. of Sicily, 1185, who succeeded
                    in capturing Thessalonica; the invaders were defeated at Demetritsa, but they
                    gained the islands of Cephallenia and Zacynthus.</p>
               <p>The two most important events in the reign of Alexius were the prices which he
                    paid for help against his enemies. (1) He was obliged (1084) to grant to Venice
                    (which had become independent of the Empire in the 9th century; see Venice), in
                    return for her naval aid against the Normans, commercial privileges which
                    practically made the Empire commercially dependent on the Republic. (2) He
                    sought auxiliary forces in western Europe to help him against the Seljuks; the
                    answer of the pope and Latin Christendom was the First Crusade— a succour very
                    different from that which he desired. Through his tact and discretion, the state
                    was safely steered through the dangers with which the disorderly hosts of
                    barbarous allies menaced it, and the immediate results were salutary; large
                    parts of Asia Minor, including Nicaea, were restored to the Empire, which was
                    thus greatly strengthened in the East while the Turks were weakened (see
                    Crusades). But for this help Byzantium might not have recovered the transient
                    strength and brilliance which it displayed under Manuel. In Asia Minor the
                    crusaders kept the terms of their agreement to restore to the emperor what had
                    belonged to him; but on capturing Antioch (1098) they permitted the Norman
                    Bohemond to retain it, in flagrant violation of their oaths; for to Antioch if
                    to any place the emperor had a right, as it had been his a few years before.
                    This was in itself sufficient to cause a breach between Byzantium and the Latin
                    kingdom of Jerusalem (founded 1099). But otherwise the new political situation
                    created by the Crusade was dangerous, ultimately fatal, to the Empire. For its
                    lands and seas became a highway from western Europe to the Latin colonies in
                    Syria; the Byzantine government was forced to take precautions to protect itself
                    against the crusading expeditions which travelled to the Holy Land; and these
                    precautions were regarded by the western powers as a hindrance to the sacred
                    objects of the crusades. The bitter religious antagonism between the Greek and
                    Latin Christians increased the mutual distrust and the danger.</p>
               <p>The history of the new relations between East and West dating from the First
                    Crusade is closely connected with the history of the futile attempts at bringing
                    about a reunion between the Greek and Latin Churches, which had severed
                    communion in 1054 (see below). To heal the schism and bring the Greek
                    Churchunder the domination of Rome was a principal object of papal policy from
                    GregoryVII. forward. The popes alternated between two methods for attaining
                    this, as circumstances dictated: namely, a peaceful agreement—the policy of
                    union; or an armed occupation of the Empire by some western power (the
                    Normans)—the policy of conquest. Their views varied according to the
                    vicissitudes of their political situation and their struggles with the western
                    emperors. The eastern emperors were also constantly preoccupied with the idea of
                    reconciliation, constantly negotiating with a view to union; but they did not
                    care about it for its own sake, but only for political advantages which it might
                    bring, and their subjects were bitterly opposed to it. Manuel Comnenus during
                    the first part of his reign was the close friend and ally of the western emperor
                    Conrad III., but after Conrad’s death, he formed the ambitious plan of realizing
                    in Europe a sovereignty like that of Justinian, and hoped to compass it in
                    conjunction with Rome, the enemy of the Hohenstaufen. His forward policy carried
                    war into Italy; he seized Ancona. But his strength was unequal to such designs.
                    His Latin sympathies, no less than his financial extravagance, made him highly
                    unpopular at home; and the national lack of sympathy with his Western policy was
                    exhibited—after the revolution which overthrew his son Alexius and raised his
                    cousin Andronicus I. to the throne —by the awful massacre of the Latin residents
                    at Constantinople in 1182, for which the expedition of William of Sicily (see
                    above) and the massacre of the people of Thessalonica was the revenge. The short
                    reign of the wicked and brilliant Andronicus was in all respects a reaction,
                    prudent, economical and popular. His fall was due to the aristocracy against
                    whom his policy ’was directed, and the reign of Isaac Angelus undid his efforts
                    and completed the ruin of the state. Oppressive taxation caused a revolt of the
                    Bulgarian and Walachian population in the European provinces; the work of
                    Zimisces and Basil was undone, and a new Bulgarian kingdom was founded by John
                    Asen—a decisive blow to the Greek predominance which the Macedonian emperors
                    seemed to have established.</p>
               <p>In the fatal year 1204 the perils with which the eastward expansion of western
                    Christendom (the Crusades, and the commercial predominance and ambitions of
                    Venice) had long menaced the Empire, culminated in its conquest and partition.
                    It was due to a series of accidents that the cloud burst at this moment, but the
                    conditions of such a catastrophe had long been present. Isaac Angelus was
                    dethroned by his brother Alexius III., and his son escaped (1201) to the west,
                    where arrangements were being made for a new crusade, which Venice undertook to
                    transport to the HolyLand. The prince persuaded Philip of Swabia (who had
                    married his sister) and Boniface of 'Montferrat to divert the expedition to
                    Byzantium, in order to restore his father and himself to the throne, promising
                    to furnish help to the Crusade and to reconcile the Greek Church with Rome;
                    Venice agreed to the plan; but Pope Innocent III., the enemy of Philip, forbade
                    it. Isaac and his son, Alexius IV., were restored without difficulty in 1203,
                    and the crusading forces were prepared to proceed to Palestine, if Alexius had
                    performed his promises. But the manner of this restoration, under Latin
                    auspices, was intensely unpopular; lie was not unwilling, but he was unable, to
                    fulfil his pledges; and a few months later he was overthrown in favour of one
                    who, if an upstart, was a patriot, Alexius V. Then the Crusaders, who were
                    waiting encamped outside the city, resolved to carry out the design which the
                    Normans had repeatedly attempted, and put an end to the Greek Empire. The
                    leaders of the Fourth Crusade must be acquitted of having formed this plan
                    deliberately before they started; it was not conceived before 1204. They first
                    arranged how they would divide the Empire amongst themselves (March); then they
                    captured the city, which had to endure the worst barbarities of war. In
                    partitioning the Empire, which was now to become the spoil of the conquerors,
                    the guiding mind was the Venetian leader, the blind doge, Henry Dandolo. He
                    looked to the interests of Venice from the narrowest point of view, and in
                    founding the new Latin Empire, which was to replace the Greek, it was his aim
                    that it should be feeble, so as to present no obstacles to Venetian policy. The
                    Latin Empire of Romania was a feudal state like the kingdom of Jerusalem; the
                    emperor was suzerain of all the princes who established themselves on Greek
                    territory; under his own immediate rule were Constantinople, southern Thrace,
                    the Bithynian coast, and some islands in the Aegean. But he was hampered from
                    the beginning by dependence on Venice, want of financial resources, and want of
                    a fleet; the feudal princes, occupied with their separate interests, gave him
                    little support in his conflict with Greeks and Bulgarians; at the end of ten
                    years the worthless fabric began rapidly to decline, and the efforts of the
                    popes, for whom it was the means of realizing Roman supremacy in the East, were
                    unavailing to save it from the extinction to which it was doomed in its cradle.</p>
               <p>The original Act of Partition (which gave } of the Byzantine territory to the
                    future emperor, | to Venice, the remaining j to the Crusaders) could hardly be
                    carried out strictly, as the territory was still to be won. . The most important
                    vassal state was the kingdom of Ihessalonica, including Thessaly, which was
                    assigned to Boniface of Montferrat. But it was conquered by the Greeks of Epirus
                    Jn 1222. The chief of the territories taken by Venice</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-23-r03-0517" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0558.jp2"/>
               <p>was Crete. For the Latin states in Greece and the Aegean see <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Greece.</hi> The first Latin emperor, Baldwin of Flanders,
                    was captured and put to death by the Bulgarians in 1205. He was succeeded by his
                    brother Henry, an able statesman, after whose death (1216) the decline began.</p>
               <p>Three Greek states emerged from the ruin of the Roman Empire. A member of the
                    Comncnian house had founded an independent state at Trcbizond, and this empire
                    survived till 1461, when it was conquered by the Ottomans. A relation of the
                    Angeli maintained in Europe an independent Greek state known as the Dcspotatc of
                    Epirus. But the true representative of the imperial line was Theodore Lascaris,
                    who collected the Byzantine aristocracy at Nicaca and was elected emperor in
                    1206. IIe and his successors advanced surely and rapidly against the Latin
                    Empire, both in Europe and Asia. It was a question whether Constantinople would
                    fall to the Walacho-Bulgarians or to the Greeks. But an astute diplomat and
                    general, the emperor Michael Palaeologus, captured it in 1261. IBs object was to
                    recover all the lost territory from the Latins, but he was menaced by a great
                    danger through Charles of Anjou, who had overthrown the rule of the
                    Hohenstaufens in the two Sicilies, and determined to restore the Latin kingdom
                    of Romania. To avert this peril, Michael negotiated with Pope Gregory X.; he was
                    ready to make every concession, and a formal union of the Churches was actually
                    brought about at the council of Lyons in 1274. The emperor had the utmost
                    difficulty in carrying through this policy in face of clerical opposition; it
                    aroused disgust and bitterness among his subjects; and it was undone by his
                    successor. Meanwhile the pope had with difficulty bridled Charles of Anjou; but
                    in Martin IV. he found a more pliable instrument, and in 1282 he made vast
                    preparations for an expedition against the Greek Empire. It was saved by the
                    Sicilian Vespers (see Sicily), to be the prey of other powers.</p>
               <p>The end of the 13th century saw the rise of the Ottoman power in Asia and the
                    Servian in Europe. The Empire was assisted by a band of Spanish mercenaries (the
                    Catalan Grand Company; see Greece, <hi rend="italic">History,</hi> “Byzantine
                    Period”) against the advance of the Ottoman Turks in Asia Minor; they
                    distinguished themselves by saving Philadelphia (1304). In 1326 Brusa (Prusa)
                    became the Ottoman capital, while on the other side the Servians (crushing the
                    Bulgarians in 1330) were gradually closing in on Byzantium. Under Stephen DuSan
                    (1331-i35S) Servia attained the height of her power. .The enemies were
                    strengthened by the domestic struggles within the Empire, first between
                    Andronicus H. and his son, then between John VI. and the usurper Cantacuzenus.
                    But before the fate of Byzantium was settled the two enemies on its flanks came
                    face to face. In 1387 the Servian power was crushed on the field of Kossovo by
                    the Ottomans (who had crossed the Hellespont in 1360 and taken Philippopolis in
                    1363). Sultan Bayezid I. won Philadelphia, the last Asiatic possession of the
                    Empire, and conquered Trnovo, the Bulgarian capital, in 1393. Constantinople was
                    now surrounded. The Ottoman power was momentarily eclipsed, and the career of
                    conquest checked, by the Mongol invasion of Timur and the great defeat which it
                    sustained in the battle of Angora (1402). Mahommcd I. found it necessary to ally
                    himself with the emperor Manuel. But the pause was brief. Murad II. took
                    Adrianople, and tried (1422) to take Constantinople.</p>
               <p>It was small compensation that during this time the Palaeologi had been
                    successful against the Franks in Greece. The situation was desperate. The Turks
                    were in possession of the Balkan peninsula, threatening Hungary; there was no
                    chance of rescue, except, from western Europe. John VI. and Manuel had both
                    visited the West in search of help. The jeopardy of the Empire was the
                    opportunity of Rome, and the union of the Churches became the pressing question.
                    .It was taken up earnestly by Pope Eugenius IV., and the result was the Decree
                    of Union at the council of Florence in 1439. The emperor and the higher clergy
                    were really in earnest, but the people and the monks did not accept it, and the
                    last agony of Byzantium was marked by ecclesiastical quarrels. Eugenius IV.
                    preached a crusade for the rescue of the Empire, and in 1443 an army of
                    Hungarians and Poles, led by the Hungarian king, won a victory over Murad, which
                    was more than avenged in the next year on the memorable field of Varna. The end
                    came nine years later under Murad ’s successor, Mahommed II. An army of about
                    150,000 blockaded the city by land and sea, and Mahommcd began the siege on the
                    7th of April. The emperor Constantinc XL, Palaeologus, on whom the task of the
                    forlorn defence devolved (and whose position was all the more difficult because
                    he was alienated from his subjects, having embraced the Latin rite), can have
                    had little more than 8000 men at his disposal; he received no help from the
                    Western powers; but an experienced Genoese soldier of fortune, John Justiniani,
                    arrived with two vessels and 400 cuirassiers and aided the emperor with his
                    courage and advice. The resident foreigners, both Venetians and Genoese, loyally
                    shared in the labours of the defence. The final storm of the land walls took
                    place on the night of the 29th of May. All looked to Justiniani for salvation,
                    and when he, severely wounded, retired from the wall to have his wound looked
                    to, a panic ensued. The enemy seized the moment, and the Janissaries in a final
                    charge rushed the stockade which had been constructed to replace a portion of
                    the wall destroyed by the Turkish cannon. This decided the fate of the city.
                    Constantine fell fighting heroically. Soon after sunrise (May 30) the Mahommcdan
                    army entered Constantinople (Stambul = ’s <hi rend="italic">τήν</hi> πόλχρ, “
                    the city ”), which was in tbeir eyes the capital of Christendom.</p>
               <p>The ultimate responsibility for this disaster is generally imputed to the
                    political adventurers who dismembered the Empire in 1204. It may indeed be said
                    that at that time the Byzantine state seemed already stricken with paralysis and
                    verging to dissolution, and it was menaced by the re-arisen power of Bulgaria.
                    But more than once before (in the 7th century and in the nth) it had recovered
                    its strength when it was weak and in dire peril; and, considering what the
                    emperors of Nicaea and Michael VIIL accomplished, it seems probable that, if
                    there had been no Fourth Crusade, it might have so revived and consolidated its
                    forces in the course of the 13th century, as to be able to cope successfully
                    with the first advances of the Ottomans. The true statement is that the Fourth
                    Crusade was only an incident (not in itself decisive) in a world-movement which
                    doomed the Eastern Empire to extinction—namely, the eastward movement of western
                    Europe which began in the I ith century with the rise of the Normans and the
                    First Crusade. Henceforward the Empire was a middle state, pressed between
                    expanding forces on the east and on the west, and its ultimate disappearance was
                    inevitable.</p>
               <p>                    <hi rend="italic">Church and State.—</hi> In making tbc state Christian,
                    Constantine made the Church a state institution, and therefore under imperial
                    control. Caesaro-papism was the logical consequence. The Sacerdotium was united
                    with the imperium in the person of the monarch as in the pagan state. The Church
                    acquiesced,and yet did not acquiesce, in this theory. When a heretical emperor
                    sought to impose his views, champions of ecclesiastical freedom never failed to
                    come forward. At the very beginning Athanasius fought for the independence of
                    the Church against the emperor Constantius. But the political principle which
                    Constantine had taken for granted, and which was an indispensable condition of
                    his adoption of Christianity, w’as fully recognized under Theodosius I., and,
                    notwithstanding protests from time to time, was permanent. It is significant
                    that Constantinople, which had become a second Rome politically, with its senate
                    and capitol, became then a second Rome ecclesiastically, and that the elevation
                    of the sec of Constantinople to patriarchal rank next to the Roman see was due
                    to Theodosius (381), who gave a permanent form to the dualism of the Empire. The
                    patriarch became a state minister for religion. The character of the Church as a
                    state institution is expressed above all in the synods. The general councils arc
                    not only summoned by the emperor, but arc presided over by him or by his lay
                    deputies. The order of the proceedings is modelled on that of the senate. The
                    emperor or his representative not only keeps order but conducts the
                    deliberations and intervenes in the theological debates. It has been erroneously
                    thought that at the council of Chalccdon (451) the legate of Pope Lco presided;
                    but the</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-23-r03-0518" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0559.jp2"/>
               <p>acts of that assembly teach us otherwise; the privilege which the Roman legates
                    possessed was that of voting first (the right of the <hi rend="italic">princeps
                        senatus).</hi> The first gcncral council at which a churchman presided was
                    the scvcnth (at Nicaea, 787), at which the emperor (or empress) deputed, not a
                    layman, but the patriarch Tarasius to preside. The resolutions of thcsc
                    ccclesiastical state-councils did not become the law of the Empire till they
                    were confirmed by imperial edicts.</p>
               <p>The emperors, in their capacity as heads of the Church, did not confine
                    themselves to controlling it by controlling the councils. They soon began to
                    issue edicts dealing with theology, by virtue of their own authority. It has
                    been said that the council of Chalcedon closed an epoch of “ parliamentary
                    constitutionalism ”; a general council was not summoned again for more than one
                    hundred years, though the Empire during that period was seething with religious
                    disunion and unrest. The usurper Basiliscus in his short reign set an example
                    which his successors were not slow to follow. He issued an edict quashing the
                    decision of Chalcedon. Zeno <hi rend="sup">i</hi> S <hi rend="italic"
                        >Henotikon</hi> (see below) a few years later was the second and more famous
                    example of a method which Justinian largely used, and of which the <hi
                        rend="italic">Ecthesis</hi> of Heraclius, the <hi rend="italic">Type</hi> of
                    Constans II. and the iconoclastic edicts of Leo III. are well-known instances.
                    It was a question of political expediency (determined by the circumstances, the
                    intensity and nature of the opposition, &amp;c.) whether an emperor supported
                    his policy or not by an ccclesiastical council.</p>
               <p>The emperor was always able to control the election of the patriarch, and
                    through him he directed the Church. Sometimes emperor and patriarch collided;
                    but in general the patriarchs were docile instruments, and when they wcre
                    refractory they could be deposed. There were several means of resistance open to
                    a patriarch, though he rarely availcd himself of them. His participation in the
                    ceremony of coronation was indispensable, and he could refuse to crown a new
                    emperor except on certain conditions, and thus dictate a policy (instances in
                    812, Michael I.; 969, John Zimisces). There was the power of excommunication
                    (Leo VI. was excommunicated on account of his fourth marriage). Another mcans of
                    resistance for the Church was to invoke the support of the bishop of Romc, who
                    embodied the principle of ecclesiastical independence and whose see admittedly
                    enjoyed precedence and primacy over all the sces in Christendom. Up to the end
                    of the 8th century he was a subject of the emperor, and some emperors exerted
                    their ecclesiastical control over Rome by drastic measures (Justinian and
                    Constans II.). But after the conquest of Italy by Charles the Great, the pope
                    was outside the Byzantine domination; after the coronation of Charles in 800 he
                    was associated with a rival empire; and when ecclesiastical controversies arose
                    in the East, the party in opposition was always ready to appeal to him as the
                    highest authority in Christendom. Under the iconoclastic emperors the
                    image-worshippers lookcd to him as the guardian of orthodoxy.</p>
               <p>As to the ecclesiastical controversies which form a leading feature of Byzantine
                    history, their political significance alone concerns us. After the determination
                    of the Arian controversy in 381 new questions (as to the union of the divine and
                    human elements in the person of Christ: one or two natures?) arose, and it may
                    seem surprising that such points of abstruse theology should have awakened
                    universal interest and led to serious consequences. The secret was that they
                    masked national feelings; hence their political importance and the attention
                    which the government was forced to bestow on them. The reviving sense of
                    nationality (anti-Greek) in Syria and in Egypt found expression in the 5th
                    century in passionate monophysitism (the doctrine of one nature) : theology was
                    the only sphere in which such feelings could be uttered. The alienation and
                    dissension which thus began had fatal consequences, smoothing the way for the
                    Saracen conquests of those lands; the inhabitants were not unwilling to be
                    severed politically from the Empire. This ultimate danger was at first hardly
                    visible. What immediately troubled the emperors in the first half of the</p>
               <p>Sth century was the preponderant position which the sec of Alexandria occupied,
                    threatening the highcr authority of Constantinople. The council of Chalcedon,
                    called by Marcian, an able statcsman, was as much for the purpose of ending the
                    domination of Alexandria as of settling the theological question. The former
                    objcct was effected, but the theological decision of the council was fatal; it
                    only scaled and promoted the disunion. The rccalcitrant spirit of Syria and
                    Egypt forced Zeno, thirty ycars latcr, to issue his Henotikon, affirming the
                    decisions of previous councils but pointedly ignoring Chalcedon. This
                    statesman-like document secured peace in the East for a génération. Rome refused
                    to accept the Henötikon, and when Justinian resolved to restore impérial
                    supremacy in the Wcstern kingdoms, conciliation with Rome became a matter of
                    political importance. For the sake of this project, the unity of the East was
                    sacrificed. The doctrine of Chalccdon was reasserted, the IIenotikon set aside;
                    New Rome and Old Rome were again hand in hand. This meant the final alienation
                    of Egypt and Syria. The national instinct which had been alive in the 5th
                    century grew into strong national sentiment in the 6th. One of the chief
                    anxieties of Justinian <hi rend="sup">i</hi> S long and busy reign was to repair
                    the mischief. Deeply interested himself in matters of dogma, and prepared to
                    assert to its fullest extent his authority as head of the Church, he has been
                    called “ the passionate theologian on the throne ”; but in his ’chief
                    ecclesiastical measures political considerations were predominant. His wife
                    Theodora was a monophysite, and he permitted her to extend her protection to the
                    heretics. He sought new formulae for the purpose of reconciliation, but nothing
                    short of repudiation of the Chalcedon acts would have been enough. The last
                    great efforts for union were made when the Saracens invaded and conquered the
                    dissident provinces. A new formula of union was discovered (One Will and One
                    Energy). This doctrine of monothelism would never have been heard of but for
                    political exigencies. The Egyptians and Syrians would perhaps have accepted this
                    compromise; but it was repudiated by the fanatical adherents of Chalcedon.
                    Heraclius sought to impose the doctrine by an edict (Ecthcsis, 638), but the
                    storm, especially in Italy and Africa, was so great that ten years later an
                    edict known as the Type was issued by Constans forbidding all disputation about
                    the number of wills and energies. Constans was a strong ruler, and maintained
                    the Type in spite of orthodox opposition throughout his reign. But the
                    expediency of this policy passed when the Saracens were inexpugnably settled in
                    their conquests, and in his "successor’s reign it was more worth while to effect
                    a reconciliation with Rome and the West. This was the cause of the 6th
                    Ecumenical Council which condemned monothelism (680-681).</p>
               <p>In the Hellenic parts of the Empire devotion to orthodoxy scrved as a chrysalis
                    for the national sentiment which was to burst its shell in the 10th century. For
                    the Greeks Christianity had been in a certain way continuous with paganism. It
                    might be said that the old deities and heroes who had protected their cities
                    wcrc still their guardians, under the new form of saints (sometimes imaginary)
                    and archangels, and performed for them the same kind of miracles. Pagan idolatry
                    was replaced by Christian image-worship, which by the Christians of many parts
                    of Asia Minor, as well as by the Mahommedans, was regarded as simply polytheism.
                    Thus in the great iconoclastic controversy, which distracted the Empire for
                    nearly 120 years, was involved, as in the monophysitic, the antagonism between
                    different racial elements and geographical sections. Leo III., whose services as
                    a great deliverer and reformer were obscured in the memory of posterity by the
                    ill-fame which he won as an iconoclast, was a native of Commagcne. His first
                    edict against the veneration of pictures evoked riots in the capital and a
                    revolt in Greece. The opposition was everywhere voiced by the monks, and it is
                    not to be overlooked that for many monks the painting of sacred pictures was
                    their means of existence. Leo’s son Constantine V. pursued the same policy with
                    greater rigour, meeting the monastic resistance by systematic persecution, and
                    in his reign a general council condemned image-worship</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-23-r03-0519" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0560.jp2"/>
               <p>(753) Iconoclasm was supported by the army (t.e. Asia Minor), and a considerable
                    portion of the episcopate, but it was not destined to triumph. When the Athenian
                    Irene, wife of Leo IV., came to power after her husband’s death, as regent for
                    her son Copstantine VI., she secured the restoration of the worship of icons.
                    The Iconoclastic Council was reversed by the 7th Ecumenical Council of 787. The
                    iconoclastic party, however, was not yet defeated, and (after the neutral reign
                    of Nicephorus I.) came again to the helm in the reigns of the Armenian Leo V.
                    and the first two Phrygian emperors, Michael II. and Theophilus. But the Empire
                    was weary of the struggle, and on the death of Theophilus, who had been rigorous
                    in enforcing his policy, icon-worship was finally restored by his widow Theodora
                    (843), and the question was never reopened. This was a triumph for the Greek
                    element in the Empire; the “ Sunday of orthodoxy ” on which iconoclasm was
                    formally condemned is still a great day in the Greek Church.</p>
               <p>The ablest champions who wielded their pens for the cause of icons, defending by
                    theological arguments practices which really had their roots in polytheism, were
                    in the early stage John of Damascus and in the later Theodore (abbot of the
                    monastery of Studium at Constantinople). The writings of the iconoclasts were
                    destroyed by the triumphant party, so that we know their case only from the
                    works of their antagonists.</p>
               <p>In this struggle the Greeks and Latins were of one mind; the image-worshippers
                    had the support of the Roman see. When the pope resisted him, Leo III.
                    confiscated the papal estates in Sicily and Calabria; and the diocese of
                    Illyricum was withdrawn from the control of Rome and submitted to the patriarch
                    of Constantinople. But when iconoclasm was defeated, there was ’no question of
                    restoring Illyricum, nor could there be, for political reasons; since the
                    iconoclastic schism had, with other causes, led to the detachment of the papacy
                    from the Empire and its association with the Frankish power. By the foundation
                    of the rival Roman Empire in 800 the pope had definitely become a subject of
                    another state. No sooner had the iconoclastic struggle terminated than
                    differences and disputes arose between the Greek and Latin Churches which
                    finally led to an abiding schism, and helped to foster the national
                    self-consciousness of the Greeks. A strife over the patriarchal chair between
                    Ignatius (deposed by Michael III. and supported by Rome) and Photius the learned
                    statesman who succeeded him, strained the relations with Rome; but a graver
                    cause of discord was the papal attempt to win Bulgaria, whose sovereign Boris
                    had been baptized under the auspices of Michael III. (c. 865), and was inclined
                    to play Old Rome against New Rome. Photius stood out as the champion of the
                    Greeks against the claim of the Roman see, and his patriarchate, though it did
                    not lead to a final breach, marks the definite emancipation of the Greeks from
                    the spiritual headship of Rome. This is the significance of his encyclic letter
                    (867), which formulated a number of differences in rite and doctrine between the
                    Greek and Latin Churches, differences so small that they need never have proved
                    a barrier to union, if on one side there had been no question of papal
                    supremacy, and if the Greek attitude had not been the expression of a tenacious
                    nationality. There was a reconciliation about 900, but the Churches were really
                    estranged, and the open and ultimate breach which came in 1054, when the
                    influence of the Cluny movement was dominant at Rome (Leo IX. was pope and
                    Michael Cerularius patriarch), sealed a disunion which had long existed.
                    Subsequent plans of reunion were entertained by the emperors merely for
                    political reasons, to obtain Western support against their foes, or to avert
                    (through papal influence) the aggressive designs of Western princes. They were
                    doomed to futility because they were not seriously meant, and the Greek
                    population was entirely out of sympathy with these political machinations of
                    their emperors. The Union of Lyons (1274) was soon repudiated, and the last
                    attempt, the Union of Florence in 1439, was equally, hollow (though it
                    permanently secured the union of the Rumanians and of the Ruthcnians). Part of
                    the historical significance of the relations between the Greek and Latin</p>
               <p>Churches lies in the fact that they illustrate, and promoted by way of
                    challenge, the persistence of Greek national self-consciousness.</p>
               <p>The emperors legislated against paganism and ’against heresy, not merely under
                    ecclesiastical pressure, but because they thought religious uniformity
                    politically desirable. Theodosius the Great, a Spaniard, with no sympathy for
                    Hellenic culture, set himself the task of systematically eradicating pagan
                    institutions and customs. Though his persecution accomplished much, paganism was
                    far from being extinct either in the East or in the West in the 5th century. Not
                    only did heathen cults survive in many remote districts, but the old gods had
                    many worshippers among the higher classes at Rome, Constantinople, Antioch,
                    Alexandria and Athens. The most distinguished Greek literati of that period were
                    non-Christian. Justinian, who united theological enthusiasm with belief in the
                    ideal of uniformity and, like Theodosius, was cut of sympathy with Hellenism (“
                    IIelIen ” now came to mean “ pagan ”), persecuted polytheism more earnestly and
                    severely than his predecessors. His measures created a panic among the higher
                    classes at Byzantium, of whom many, as he suspected, were addicted to the
                    ancient religion. He instituted a regular inquisition, exacted oaths of
                    orthodoxy from all officials and teachers, and closed the philosophical schools
                    of Athens. Missionaries (and it is remarkable that he employed monophysite
                    heretics) were sent to abolish the old heathen worship which survived in many
                    parts of Asia Minor where Christianity had hardly penetrated. By the end of the
                    6th century formal paganism had practically disappeared.</p>
               <p>In Asia Minor, especially in the cast, there were many dissident communities
                    which asserted independence of the Church of Constantinople and of all
                    ecclesiastical traditions, founding their doctrines directly on the Bible. Most
                    important of these heretics were the Paulicians <hi rend="italic">(q.v.),</hi> a
                    dualistic sect whom the Church regarded as Manichaeans.</p>
               <p>                    <hi rend="italic">The Autocracy and its Constitutional Forms.—</hi> With
                    Diocletian the Principate of Augustus had become Undisguisedly an absolute
                    monarchy, and this constitution prevailed to the end. There is virtually no
                    constitutional history in the proper sense of the term in the later Roman
                    Empire, for there was neither evolution nor revolution. The monarchical system
                    remained in all its essential points unchanged, and presents a remarkable
                    example of an autocracy of immense duration which perfectly satisfied the ideas
                    of its subjects. No attempt was made to alter it,—to introduce, for instance, a
                    limited monarchy or a republican government; all revolts and conspiracies were
                    aimed at the policies of particular autocrats, not at autocracy itself;
                    generally they only represented sectional antagonisms and personal ambitions.
                    The emperors inherited a deeply rooted instinct of legality as a tradition from
                    Old Rome; and this respect for law which marked their acts, along with the
                    generally good administration of justice, was a palladium of the monarchy. They
                    were supreme in legislation, as well as in the administrative and judicial
                    spheres; but they were on the whole moderate in wielding legislation as an
                    instrument of policy.</p>
               <p>There were, however, recognized constitutional principles which it would have
                    been impossible for the emperor to override.</p>
               <p>(1) The elective principle, inherited from the Rcpubfic, was never changed. A
                    new emperor had to be elected by the senate and acclaimed by the people. The
                    succession never became automatic. But even Augustus had indirectly introduced
                    the dynastic principle. Theodosius the Great, by causing his two sons, Arcadius
                    and Honorius, to be elected Augusti in their infancy, practically elevated the
                    dynastic idea into a constitutional principle; henceforward it was regarded as
                    in the regular course that the son born to a reigning sovereign should in his
                    infancy be elected Augustus. Thus the election, though always an indispensable
                    form, was only a reality when a dynasty came to an end.</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-23-r03-0520" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0561.jp2"/>
               <p>(2) When the position of Christianity was assured by the failure of Julian <hi
                        rend="sup">i</hi> S reaction, it was evident that profession of that
                    religion would henceforward be a necessary qualification for election to the
                    throne. This was formally and constitutionally recognized when the coronation of
                    the emperor by the patriarch was introduced in 457, or perhaps in 450.</p>
               <p>(3) The sovereignty of the emperor was personal and <hi rend="italic">not
                        territorial.</hi> In this respect it always retained the character which it
                    had inherited as the offspring of a Roman magistracy. Hence no Roman territory
                    could be granted by the emperor to another power. For instance, the Western
                    emperor Conrad III. could promise to hand over Italy to Manuel Comnenus as the
                    dowry of his wife, but it would have been constitutionally illegal for Manuel to
                    have made such a promise to any foreign prince; an Eastern emperor had no right
                    to dispose of the territory of the state. Tendencies towards a territorial
                    conception begin indeed to appear (partly under Western influence) in the time
                    of the Palaeologi, especially in the custom of bestowing appanages on imperial
                    princes.</p>
               <p>(4) While the senate of Rome generally lost its importance and at last became a
                    mere municipal body, the new senate of Constantine preserved its position as an
                    organ of the state till the fall of Constantinople. For the imperial elections
                    it was constitutionally indispensable, and it was able sometimes to play a
                    decisive part when the throne was vacant—its only opportunity for independent
                    action. The abolition, under Diocletian’s system, of the senatorial provinces
                    deprived the senate of the chief administrative function which it exercised
                    under the Prindpate; it had no legislative powers; and it lost most of its
                    judicial functions. It was, however, still a judicial court; it tried, for
                    instance, political crimes. In composition it differed from the senate of the
                    Principate. The senators in the 4th century were chiefly functionaries in the
                    public service, divided into the three ascending ranks of <hi rend="italic"
                        >Claris simi, Spectabilcs. illustres.</hi> The majority of the members of
                    the senatorial order lived in the provinces, forming a provincial aristocracy,
                    and did not sit in the senate. Then the two lower ranks ceased to have a right
                    to sit in the senate, which was confined to the <hi rend="italic">illustres</hi>
                    and men of higher rank (Patricians). The senatorial order must therefore be
                    distinguished from the senate in a narrower sense; the latter finally consisted
                    mainly of high ministers of state and the chief officials of the palace. It
                    would be a grave mistake to underrate the importance of this body, through an
                    irrelevant contrast with the senate of the Republic or even of the Principate.
                    Its composition ensured to it great influence as a consultative assembly; and
                    its political weight was increased by the fact that the inner council of
                    imperial advisers was practically a committee of the senate. The importance of
                    the senate is illustrated by the fact that in the nth century Constantine X., in
                    order to carry out a revolutionary, anti-military policy, found it necessary to
                    alter the composition of the senate by introducing a number of new men from the
                    lower classes.</p>
               <p>(5) The memory of the power which had once belonged to the <hi rend="italic"
                        >populus Romanus</hi> lingered in the part which the inhabitants of New
                    Rome, and their representatives, played in acclaiming newly elected emperors,
                    and in such ceremonies as coronations. In the 6th century the factions (“ demes
                    ”) of the circus, Blues and Greens, appear as political parties, distract the
                    dty by their quarrels, and break out in serious riots. On one occasion they
                    shook the throne (“ Nika ” revolt, 532). The emperors finally quelled this
                    clement of disturbance by giving the factions a new organization, under “
                    de-marchs” and “ democrats/’ and assigning them a definite quasi-political <hi
                        rend="italic">locus standi</hi> in the public ceremonies in the palace and
                    the capital. The duty of providing <hi rend="italic">panem et cir-censes</hi>
                    was inherited from Old Rome; but the free distribution of bread cannot be traced
                    beyond the 6th century (had the loss of the Egyptian granary to do with its
                    cessation?), while the spectacles of the hippodrome lasted till the end. Outside
                    the capital the people took little interest in politics, except when theology
                    was concerned; and it may be said generally that it was mainly in the
                    ecclesiastical sphere that public opinion among the masses, voiced by the clergy
                    and monks, was an influence which made itself felt.</p>
               <p>The court ceremonial of Constantinople, which forms such a market contrast to
                    the ostentatiously simple establishments of Augustus and the Antonines,.had in
                    its origin a certain constitutional significance. It was introduced by Aurelian
                    and Diocletian, not, we must suppose, from any personal love of display, but
                    rather to dissociate the emperor from the army, at a time when the state had
                    been shaken to its foundations by the predominance of the military element and
                    the dependence of the emperor on the soldiers. It was the object of Diocletian
                    to make him independent of all, with no more particular relation to the army
                    than to any other element in the state; the royal court and the inaccessibility
                    of the ruler were calculated to promote this object. The etiquette and
                    ceremonies were greatly elaborated by Justinian, and were diligently maintained
                    and developed. The public functions, which included processions through the
                    streets to various sanctuaries of the dty on the great feast-days of the Church,
                    supplied entertainment of which the populace never wearied; and it did not
                    escape the wit of the rulers that the splendid functions and. solemn etiquette,
                    of the court were an effective means of impressing the imagination of
                    foreigners, who constantly resorted to Constantinople from neighbouring kingdoms
                    and dependencies, with the majesty and power of the Basileus.</p>
               <p>The imperial <hi rend="italic">dignity</hi> was collegial. There could be two or
                    more emperors <hi rend="italic">imperatores,</hi> βασιλεῑς). at the same time;
                    edicts were issued, public acts performed, in their joint names. Through the
                    period of dualism, in the 4th and 5th centuries, when the administration of the
                    Eastern provinces was generally separate from that of the Western, the imperial
                        <hi rend="italic">authority</hi> was also collegial. But after this period
                    the system of divided authority came to an end and was never renewed. There was
                    frequently more than one emperor, not only in the case of a father and his sons,
                    or of two brothers, but also in the case of a minority, when a regent is elected
                    emperor (Romanus I.; cf. Nicfephorus II. and John Zimisces). But one colleague
                    always exercised the sole authority, was the real monarch, the “great” or the
                    “first” Basileus; the other or others were only sleeping partners. Under the
                    Comneni a new nomenclature was introduced; a brother, <hi rend="italic"
                        >e.g.,</hi> who before could have become the formal colleague of the ruler,
                    received the title of <hi rend="italic">Sebastocrator</hi> (SebaStos was the
                    Greek equivalent of Augustus).</p>
               <p>                    <hi rend="italic">Legislation.—</hi> The history of the legislation of the
                    Eastern Empire is distinguished by three epochs associated with the names of (1)
                    Justinian, (2) LeoIII., (3) Basil I. and Leo VI.</p>
               <p>(1) The Justinianean legislation (see Justinian) is thoroughly Roman in spirit,
                    and inspired by pious adhesion to the traditions of the past; but it admitted
                    modifications of the older law in accordance with tendencies which had been long
                    since making themselves felt: consideration is accorded to principles of
                    humanity in the laws affecting persons, and to the principle of public interest
                    in the laws relating to things. Justinian not only sanctioned changes which time
                    had brought about, like the mitigation of the strict <hi rend="italic">patria
                        potestas</hi> and the greater independence of wives, but introduced a
                    revolutionary change in the law of succession to property, abolishing
                    inheritance by <hi rend="italic">agnatio</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps"> qt</hi></hi> relationship through males,
                    and substituting inheritance by blood relationship whether through males or
                    females.</p>
               <p>(2) Justinian’s reign was followed by a period in which Juristic studies
                    decayed. The seventh century, in which social order was profoundly disturbed, is
                    a blank in legal history, and it would seem that the law of Justinian, though it
                    had been rendered into Greek, almost ceased to be studied or understood.
                    Practice at least was modified by principles in accord with the public opinion
                    of Christian society and influenced by ecclesiastical canons. In a synod held at
                    Constantinople in the reign of Justinian II. numerous rules were enacted,
                    differing from the existing laws and based on ecclesiastical doctrine and
                    Alosaic principles, and these were sanctioned as laws of the realm by the
                    emperor. Thus Church influence and the decline of Roman tradition, in a state
                    which had become predominantly Greek, determined the character of the ensuing
                    legislative epoch under the auspices of Leo III., whose law book (a.d. 740),
                    written in Greek, marks a new era and Teflectsthechanged ideas of the community.
                    Entitled a “ Brief Selection of Laws ” and generally known as the <hi
                        rend="italic">Ecloga,</hi> it may be described as a Christian law book. In
                    regard to the <hi rend="italic">patria potestas</hi> increased facilities are
                    given for emancipation from paternal control when the son comes to years of
                    discretion, and the paternal is to a certain extent replaced by a <hi
                        rend="italic">parental</hi> control over minors. The. law of guardianship is
                    considerably modified. The laws of marriage are transformed under the influence
                    of the Christian, conception of matrimony; the institution of <hi rend="italic"
                        >Concubinatus</hi> is abolished. Impedi--ments to marriage on account of
                    consanguinity and of spiritual relationship are multiplied. While Justinian
                    regarded marriage as a contract, and therefore, like any other contract,
                    dissoluble at the pleasure of the parties, Leo III. accepted the Church view
                    that it was an indissoluble bond. Ecclesiastical influence is written</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-23-r04-0521" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0562.jp2"/>
                <p>large in the criminal law, of which a prominent feature is the substitution of
                    mutilation of various kinds for the capital penalty» Death is retained for some
                    crimes, such as murder and high treason; other offences were punished by
                    amputation (of hand, nose, &amp;c.). This system (justified by the passage
                    in the New Testament, “ If thine eye offend thee,” &amp;c.), though to
                    modern notions barbaric, seemed a step in the direction of leniency; and it may
                    be observed that the tendency to avoid capital punishment increased, and we are
                    told that in the.reign of John Comnenus it was never inflicted. (The same
                    spirit, it may be noted, is apparent in the usual, though by no means
                    invariable, practice of Byzantine emperors to render dethroned rivals or members
                    of a deposed dynasty innocuous by depriving them of eyesight or forcing them to
                    take monastic orders, instead of putting them to death.) The Church, which had
                    its own system of penalties, exercised a great influence on the actual operation
                    of criminal law, especially through the privilege of asylum (recognized by
                    Justinian, but with many reserves and.restrictions), which was granted to
                    Christian churches and is admitted without exceptions in the <hi rend="italic">Ecloga. </hi></p>
                <p>(3) The last period of legislative activity under Basil I. and Leo VI. represents
                    a reaction, in a certain measure, against the <hi rend="italic">Ecloga</hi> and a return to Justinian. The <hi rend="italic">Ecloga</hi> had met practical
                    needs, but the Isaurian and Phrygian emperors had done nothing to revive legal
                    study. To do so was the aim of Basil, and the revival could only be based on
                    Justinianean law books or their Greek representatives. These books were now
                    treated somewhat as Justinian and his lawyers had treated their own
                    predecessors. A handbook of extracts from the Institutes, Digest and Code was
                    issued in 879 <hi rend="italic">(6</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">p6/xos, **</hi> the law as it is ”), to</p>
                <p>fulfil somewhat the same function as the Institutes. Then a collection of all the
                    laws of the Empire was prepared by means of two commissions, and completed under
                    Leo VI. It was entitled the <hi rend="italic">Basilika.</hi> In many points
                    (in civil, but not in criminal, law) the principles of the <hi rend="italic">Ecloga</hi> are set aside in favour of the older jurisprudence. Thus the
                    Justinianean ordinances on the subject of divorce were revived, and there
                    remained henceforward a contradiction between the civil and the canon law.</p>
                <p>After this there was no legislation on a grand scale; but there was a great
                    revival of legal study under Constantine IX., who founded a new law-school, and
                    there were many learned specialists who wrote important commentaries, such as
                    John Xiphilin filth century), Theodore Balsamon (12th century), Harmenopulos
                    (14th century). The civil code of Moldavia (published 1816—17) is a codification
                    of Byzantine law; and modern Greece, although in framing its code it took the
                    Napoleonic for its model, professes theoretically to base its civil law on the
                    edicts of the emperors as contained in the <hi rend="italic">Hexabiblos</hi> of Harmenopulos.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic"> Administration.—</hi> Three principles underlay the
                    administrative reform of Diocletian: the separation of civil from military
                    functions; the formation of small provincial units; and the scalar structure
                    which deepened on the interposition of the vicar of a diocese and the praetorian
                    prefect between the provincial governor and the emperor. This system lasted
                    unchanged for three and a half centuries. The few unimportant alterations that
                    were made were in harmony with its spirit, until the reign of Justinian, who
                    introduced certain reforms that pointed in a new direction. We find him
                    combining some of the small provinces into large units, undermining the scalar
                    system by doing away with some of the dioceses and vicars, and placing in some
                    eases military and civil authority in the same hands. The chief aim of
                    Diocletian in his general reform had been to secure central control over the
                    provincial governments; the object of Justinian in these particular reforms was
                    to remedy corruption and oppression. These changes, some of which were soon
                    cancelled, would hardly in themselves have led to a radical change; but they
                    prepared the way for an administrative revolution, brought about by stress of
                    external necessities. In the 7th century all the energies of the Empire, girt
                    about by active enemies, were centred on war and defence; everything had to give
                    way to military exigencies; and a new system was gradually introduced which Jed
                    ultimately to the abolition of the old. The change began in Italy and Africa, at
                    the end of the 6th century, where operations against the Lombards and the
                    Berbers were impeded by the friction between the two co-ordinate military and
                    civil authorities (masters of soldiers, and praetorian prefects). The military
                    governors were made supreme with the title of <hi rend="italic">exarchs,</hi> “ viceroys”; the civil authority was subordinated to them in ease of collision,
                    otherwise remaining unaltered. The change is an index of the dangerous crisis
                    through which these provinces were passing. In the East similar circumstances
                    led to similar results. The Saracen danger hanging imminent over Asia Minor
                    imposed a policy of the same kind. And so before the end of the 7th century we
                    find the Empire divided into six great military provinces, three in Europe and
                    three in Asia: (1) Exarchate of <hi rend="italic">Africa,</hi> (2) Exarchate
                    of <hi rend="italic">Italy,</hi> (3) Strategia of <hi rend="italic">Thrace,</hi> (4) County of <hi rend="italic">Opsikion ( — obsequium),</hi> including
                    Bithynia, Honorias, Paphlagonia, parts of Helles-pontus and Phrygia, (5)
                    Strategia of the <hi rend="italic">Anatolikoi,</hi> most of west and central
                    Asia Minor, (6) Strategia of the <hi rend="italic">Armenia koi,</hi> eastern
                    Asia Minor. In addition to these there was a naval circumscription, (7) the
                    Strategia of the <hi rend="italic">Karabisianoi</hi> (from xapa/Jo?,a vessel),
                    including the southern coastland of Asia Minor, and the Aegean (see below under <hi rend="italic">Navy), </hi></p>
                <p>The lands of the old prefecture of Illyricum were not included in the system,
                    because this part of the Empire was then regarded as a lost position. On the
                    contrary, here military powers were committed to the Prefect of Illyricum, whose
                    actual sphere extended little beyond Thessalonica, which was surrounded by
                    Slavonic tribes.</p>
                <p>The Eastern changes, perhaps initiated by Heraclius, but probably due mainly to
                    Constans II., did not interfere with the civil administration, except in so far
                    as its heads were subordinated to the military commanders. But Leo III., who as
                    a gieat administrative reformer ranks with Augustus and Diocletian, did away
                    w'ith the old system altogether. ft) Reversing Diocletian’s principle, he
                    combined military and civil powers in the same hands. The strategos or military
                    commander became also a civil governor; his higher officers (tur-marchs) were
                    likewise dvil functionaries. *(2) The scalar principle disappeared, including
                    both the vicars and the praetorian prefect of the East (some of whose functions
                    were merged in those of the prefect of the dty); no authority interposed between
                    the strategoi and the emperor. (3) The new provinces, which were called <hi
                        rend="italic"> themes</hi> (the name marks their military origin: <hi
                        rend="italic"> thima —</hi> corps), resembled in size the provinces of
                    Augustus, each including several of the Diocletian divisions. This third and
                    last provindal reform has, like its predecessors, its own history. The list of
                    themes in the nth century is very different from that of the 8th. The changes
                    were in one direction—the reduction of large provinces by cutting off parts to
                    form smaller themes, a repetition of the process which reduced the provinces of
                    Augustus. Hence the themes came to vary greatly in size and importance. Leo
                    himself began the process by breaking up the Anatolic command into two themes
                    (Anatolic and Thraeesian). The principle of splitting up was carried out
                    systematically by Leo VI. (who was also responsible for a new ecclesiastical
                    division of the Empire).</p>
                <p>The development will be exhibited by a list of the themes in the middle of the
                    10th century. A. Asia: j(1) Opsikion, (2) Optimaton,</p>
                <p>(з) Paphlagonia, (4) Bukellarian) = old Opsikion; J(5) Anatolic, (6) Thraeesian,
                    (7) Samos (naval), (8) Cappadocia, (o) Scleucia) = old Anatolic; }(io) Armeniac,
                    (11) Colonea, (12) Scbastca, (13) Charsianon, (14) Chaldia, (15) Mesopotamia)
                    =old Armeniac; (16) Cibyrrhaeot, (17) Aegean (= Dodekanesos). B. Europe: (1)
                    Thrace, (2) Macedonia, (3) Strymon, <hi rend="smallcaps">(a)</hi> Thessalonica, (5) Hellas, (6) Peloponnesus, (7) Nicopolis, (8) Dyrrnachium, (9)
                    Longibardia, (10) Cephallenia, (11) Cherson.</p>
                <p>It is interesting to note that up to Leo VI. the district between Constantinople
                    and the wall of Anastasius formed a separate theme or government, entitled the
                    Wall (r&lt;5 Tet^io*) or the Ditch (1$ <hi rend="italic">T&amp;Qpcn)';</hi> Leo VI. united it with the theme of Thrace.</p>
                <p>In the central administration, the general principles seem to have remained
                    unchanged; the heads of the great administrative bureaux in Constantinople
                    retain the <hi rend="italic">palatine</hi> character which belonged to most of
                    them from the beginning. But there were many changes in these offices, in their
                    nomenclature and the delimitation of their functions. There are great
                    differences between the administrative corps in the $th, in the 10th and in the
                    15th centuries. We can hardly be wrong in conjecturing that, along with his
                    provincial reform, Leo III. made a rearrangement of the central bureaux; the
                    abolition of the Praetorian Prefecture of the East entailed, in itself,
                    modifications. But minor changes were continually being made, and we may note
                    the following tendencies: (1) Increase in the number of ministers directly
                    responsible to the emperor,</p>
                <p>(и) subordinate offices in the bureaux being raised to the rank</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-23-r04-0522" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0563.jp2"/>
                <p>of independent ministries; (6) new offices being created and old ones becoming
                    merely titular. (2) Changes in nomenclature; substitution of Greek for Latin
                    titles. (3) Changes in the relative importance and rank of the high officials,
                    both civil and military.</p>
                <p>The Prefect of the City (&amp;rapxo$) controlled the police organization and
                    administration of justice in the capital; he was vice-president of the imperial
                    court of justice, and, when the office of Prefect of the East was abolished, he
                    inherited the functions of that dignitary as judge of appeals from the
                    provinces. But the <hi rend="italic">pracfectus vigilum,</hi> commander of the
                    city guards, who was subordinate to him, became an independent officer, entitled
                    Drun-gary of the Watch, and in the 11 th century superseded him as
                    vice-president of the imperial court. We are told that in the last years of the
                    Empire the Prefect of the City had no functions at all; but his office survives
                    in the <hi rend="italic">Shchr-imancti, “</hi> city prefecture,” of the
                    Ottomans, in whose organization there are many traces of Byzantine
                    influence.</p>
                <p>Instead of the Quaestor of the Sacred Palace, whose duty was to draft the
                    imperial laws and rescripts, we find in the 9th century a quaestor who possesses
                    certain judicial and police functions and is far lower in the hierarchy of rank.
                    It has been supposed that the later quaestor really inherited the duties of
                    another officer, the <hi rend="italic">quaesitor,</hi> who was instituted by
                    Justinian. In the latest period the quaestor, if he still existed as a name, had
                    no functions.</p>
                <p>The Master of Offices, who supervised the bureaux in the palace and was master of
                    court ceremonies, also performed many functions of a minister of foreign
                    affairs, was head of the imperial post <hi rend="italic">(cursus),</hi> and of
                    the corps of <hi rend="italic">agentes in rebus</hi> or Imperial Messengers.
                    This ministry disappeared, probably in the 8th century, but the title was
                    retained as a dignity at all events till the end of the 9th. The most important
                    functions, pertaining to foreign affairs, were henceforward performed by the
                    Logothete of the Post <hi rend="italic">(\oyoQerr]$</hi> <hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps"> tov</hi></hi> <hi rend="italic">bpopov).</hi> In the 12th century this minister was
                    virtually the chancellor of the Empire; his title was changed to that of Great
                    Logothete by Andronicus II.</p>
                <p>The two financial ministers, <hi rend="italic">comes sacrarum largitionum</hi> and <hi rend="italic">comes rei privatae,</hi> continued to the end under the
                    titles X070- <hi rend="italic">Q’trqs</hi> <hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps"> too</hi></hi> <hi rend="italic">ytvixov</hi> (General Logothete) and <hi rend="italic">b
                        etrl</hi> <hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps"> tov ISlkov</hi></hi> (Anastasius added a third, the Count of the Sacred Patrimony, but he was
                    afterwards suppressed). But in the 9th century we find both these ministers
                    inferior in rank to the <hi rend="italic">Sacellarius,</hi> or private
                    pursekeeper of the emperor. Besides these there was a fourth important financial
                    department, that of the military treasury, under a Logothete.</p>
                <p>The employment of eunuchs as high ministers of state was a feature of the
                    Byzantine Empire from the end of the 4th century. Ibis laid down as a principle
                    (a.d. 900) that all offices are open to them, except the Prefecture of the City,
                    the quaestor-ship, and the military posts which were held by “ Domestics.” There
                    were then eight high posts which could only be held by eunuchs, of which the
                    chief were the parakoimomenos and the protovestiarios (master of the
                    wardrobe).</p>
                <p>An emperor who had not the brains or energy to direct the affairs of the state
                    himself, necessarily committed the task of guiding the helm to some particular
                    minister or court dignitary who had gained his confidence. Such a position of
                    power was outside the constitution, and was not associated with any particular
                    office; it might be held by an ecclesiastic or a eunuch; it had been held by the
                    eunuchs Eutropius and Chrysaphius in the reigns of Arcadius and Theodosius II.
                    respectively. In later times, such a first minister came to be denoted by a
                    technical term, <hi rend="italic">b TupabvvaoTtvwv.</hi> This was the
                    position, for instance, of Stylianus, the father-in-law of Leo VI. Most of the
                    emperors between Basil II. and Alexius Comnenus were under the influence of such
                    ministers.</p>
                <p>The orders of rank (which must be distinguished from titles of office) were
                    considerably increased in later times. In the 4th and 7th centuries there were
                    the three great classes of the <hi rend="italic">illustres, spectabiles</hi> and <hi rend="italic">clarissimi;</hi> and above the <hi rend="italic">illustres</hi> a small, higher class of patricians. In the 9th century we
                    find an entirely different system; the number of classes being largely
                    augmented, and the nomenclature different. Instead of epithets like <hi
                        rend="italic"> illustres,</hi> the names are titles which had designated
                    offices; '‘patrician” alone survives. The highest rank is now (1) the magistroi;
                    then come the patricians in two classes: (2) proconsular patricians, (3)
                    respectable patricians; below these (4) protospatharioi; (5) dishypatoi <hi
                        rend="italic"> ( = bis cónsules);</hi> (6) spatharokandidatoi; (7)
                    spatharioi; and other lower ranks. Particular ranks do not seem now to have been
                    inalienably attached to particular offices. The strategos of the Anatolic Theme, <hi rend="italic">e.g.,</hi> might be a patrician or only a protospathar.
                    Whoever was promoted to one of these ranks received its insignia from the
                    emperor’s hand, and had to pay fixed fees to various officials, especially to
                    the palace eunuchs</p>
                <p>In the provinces ordinary justice was administered by judges <hi rend="italic">(KpLTcá)</hi> who were distinct from the governors of the themes, and
                    inherited their functions from the old provincial governors of Diocletian’s
                    system. In Constantinople higher and lower courts of justice sat regularly and
                    frequently. The higher tribunals were those of the Prefect and the Quaestor,
                    before whom different kinds of cases came. Appeals reached the emperor through
                    the bureau of Petitions <hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps"> (tûv</hi></hi> <hi rend="italic">bcrjakcop)</hi> ; he might deal with the case immediately;
                    or might refer it to the imperial court of appeal, of which he was president;
                    ^or else to the special court of the Twelve Divine Judges (fotot ôuaarat), which
                    was instituted by Justinian.</p>
                <p>While the administration of justice was one of the best features of the Eastern
                    Empire, its fiscal system, likewise inherited from the early Empire, was one of
                    its worst. If the government had been acquainted with the principles of public
                    economy, which have not been studied till comparatively recent times, a larger
                    revenue might have been raised without injuring the prosperity of the
                    inhabitants. Taxes were injudiciously imposed and oppressively collected. The
                    commerce of the Empire was one of its great sources of strength, but the
                    government looked on the merchants as a class from which the utmost should be
                    extorted. The chief source of revenue was the land. The main burdens which fell
                    upon the landed proprietors throughout the whole period were the land tax proper
                    and the <hi rend="italic">annona.</hi> The land tax <hi rend="italic">(capitolio terrena—the</hi> old <hi rend="italic">Iributum</hi> of the
                    imperial, <hi rend="italic">stipendium</hi> of the senatorial, provinces) was
                    based, not on the yearly produce, but on the capital of the proprietor, the
                    character and value of the land being taken into account. In later times this
                    seems to have become the <hi rend="italic">Kairpticbp,</hi> or hearth tax. The <hi rend="italic">annona</hi> was an additional impost for supporting the
                    army and imperial officials; it was originally paid in produce. In later times,
                    we meet it under the name of crtrapxta or <hi rend="italic">Gvp&amp;vq.</hi> The province was divided into fiscal districts, and the total revenue to
                    be derived from each was entered in a book of assessment. The assessment was in
                    early times revised every fifteen years (the “ indiction ” period), but
                    subsequently such revisions seem to have been very irregular. The collection of
                    the taxes was managed through the curial system, while it lasted (till 7th
                    century?). The decurions, or municipal councillors, of the chief town in each
                    district were responsible for collecting and delivering the whole amount, and
                    had to make good the sums owed by defaulters. This system of collective
                    responsibility pressed very heavily on the decurions, and helped to cause their
                    decay in the Western provinces. After the abolition of the curial organization,
                    the principle óf collective responsibility remained in the form of the c7n/3oXi)
                    or additional charge; that is, if a property was left without an owner, the
                    taxes for which it was liable became an extra charge on the other members of the
                    district <hi rend="italic">(oc bpbKqpooL).</hi> The taxes were collected by <hi rend="italic">praktores,</hi> who were under the General Logothete.
                    The peasant proprietors were also liable to burdens of other kinds (corvées), of
                    which the most important was the furnishing of horses, vehicles, postboys,
                    &amp;c., for the state post (see Angaria).</p>
                <p>The history of landed property and agrarian conditions in the Eastern Empire
                    still awaits a thorough examination. It may be noted that individual hereditary
                    proprietorship was always the rule (on crown and monastic lands as well as in
                    other cases), and that the commonly supposed extensive existence of communities
                    possessing land in common is based on erroneous interpretation of documents.
                    When imperial lands were granted to monasteries or as fiefs (irpópotcu) to
                    individuals, the position and rights of the peasant proprietors on the estates
                    were not changed, but in many</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-23-r04-0523" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0564.jp2"/>
                <p>cases the imposts were paid to the new master instead of to the fisc. In the 4th,
                    5th and 6th centuries the cultivators were attached to the soil <hi
                        rend="italic"> (coloni, ascripticii;</hi> see <hi rend="smallcaps">Serfdom),</hi> in the interests of the fiscus; it has been supposed, on
                    insufficient grounds, that this serfdom was abolished for a time by Leo III.,
                    though it is probable that the condition of the peasants was largely changed by
                    the invasions of the 7th century. In any case the system of compulsory
                    attachment of peasants to their lands remained in force, and the class of
                    adscripticü (i»'a7rô7pa&lt;£oi) existed till the latest times. The chief
                    sources for agrarian conditions are, besides the imperial laws, monastic
                    records, among which may be mentioned as specially valuable those of the
                    Monastery of Lemboi near Smyrna.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic"> Army and Navy.—</hi> The general principle of the military
                    defence of the Empire in the 4th century consisted in large forces stationary on
                    the frontiers, and reserve forces, stationed in the interior provinces, which
                    could be moved to any point that was in danger. Thus the army was composed of
                    (1) the <hi rend="italic">limitanei,</hi> frontier-troops (under <hi
                        rend="italic"> duces)</hi> , and (2) reserve forces (under <hi
                        rend="italic"> magistri militum)</hi> of two denominations, (a) <hi
                        rend="italic"> palatini</hi> and (6) <hi rend="italic">comitatenses.</hi> The limitanei were the more numerous; it has been estimated that if they
                    numbered about 350,000, the comitatenses and palatini together amounted to less
                    than 200,000. It is to be noted that for the old legion of 6000 men a smaller
                    legion of 1000 had been substituted, and that the proportion of cavalry to
                    infantry was small. In the 6th century the fundamental principles of the system
                    were the same; but the cavalry had become a much more important branch of the
                    service, and in the wars of Belisarius the <hi rend="italic">foederati,</hi> barbarian mercenaries of various races, commanded by their own chiefs, played a
                    great rôle. The peasants of Illyria and Thrace, the mountaineers of southern
                    Asia Minor still supply an important part of the army, but the number of
                    barbarians (Heruli, Vandals, Goths, Slavs, Arabs, &amp;c.) is much larger.
                    Solidity and a corresponding want of mobility characterized at this time both
                    cavalry and infantry; their great merit was straight and rapid shooting:
                    Belisarius ascribed his. success in Italy to the excellence of the archery. It
                    is remarkable with what small forces (not more than 25,000) the first conquest
                    of Italy was achieved, though Belisarius was far from being a military genius
                    and the discipline in his army was flagrantly defective.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic"> Frontier Defence.—</hi> Justinian carried out on the
                    frontiers and in the exposed provinces a carefully devised and expensive system
                    of defensive works. Fortified towns along the <hi rend="italic">limes</hi> were connected by intervening forts, and at some distance behind was a second
                    line of more important fortresses more strongly garrisoned, which furnished both
                    a second barrier and places of refuge for the inhabitants of the open country.
                    There was an elaborate system of signals by which the garrisons of the front
                    stations eould announce not only the imminence of a hostile invasion, but the
                    number and character of the enemy. In North Africa there are abundant remains of
                    the forts of the 6th and 7th centuries, displaying the military architecture of
                    the period and the general frontier system. The typical fortress had three
                    defences: the wall flanked by square towers of three storeys; at a few yards’
                    distance a second wall of stone; and outside a deep foss about 20 yds. wide,
                    with vertical sides, filled with water, and along its edge a rampart of
                    earth.</p>
                <p>We have already seen how the disasters and losses of the 7th century led to a
                    radical change in the military organization, and how the Empire was divided into
                    themes. . The preponderant influence which Asia Minor won and retained till the
                    nth century is reflected in the military establishment, which mainly depended on
                    the Asiatic provinces. The <hi rend="italic">strategos</hi> of a large theme
                    commanded a corps of 10,000 and the scheme of the divisions and subordinate
                    commands has a remarkable resemblance to the organization of some of the armies
                    of modern Europe.</p>
                <p>The recorded scheme was probably not uniform in all the themes, and varied at
                    different periods. The <hi rend="italic">Thema</hi> (corps) consisted of <hi
                        rend="italic"> 2 turmai</hi> (brigades) under <hi rend="italic">turmarchai;</hi> the turma of 5 <hi rend="italic">banda</hi> (regiments),
                    each under a <hi rend="italic">drungarios</hi> (colonel); the banaon of 5 <hi
                        rend="italic"> Pent-arkhiai</hi> (companies) under a <hi rend="italic">kometes</hi> (captain). The pentarkhia, containing 200 men, had 5
                    subdivisions under <hi rend="italic">pentekontarkhai</hi> (lieutenants); and
                    there was a smaller unit of ten men under the <hi rend="italic">dekarkhes</hi> (corporal). The total strength in the 9th century was 120,000; in Justinian’s
                    time it was reckoned at 150,000.</p>
                <p>Distinct from the military forces <hi rend="italic">{pk^ara.)</hi> of the
                    provinces were the forces (rAy/xara) stationed in or near the capital. The most
                    important of these were the Scholae and the Excubitores. The Scnolarian troops
                    were in early times under the Master of Offices, but subsequently their chief
                    officer, the Domestic of the Schools, became the highest military commander in
                    the Empire next to the Strategos of the Anatolic Theme. In war, when the emperor
                    did not assume the chief command himself, he might entrust it to any commander,
                    and he often entrusted it to the Domestic. In the nth century, after the
                    conquest of Bulgaria, there were two Domestics, one for the east and one for the
                    west, and under Alexius Comnenus the Domestic of the west received the title
                    Great Domestic. Under the Palaeologi the Great Domestic was superior in rank to
                    all other ministers.</p>
                <p>Besides the Scholarians, and the Excubitores (who had been organized in the 5th
                    century), there were the regiments of the Hikanatoi, the Anthmos and the
                    Numeroi. The Numcroi were foot-soldiers. The Optimatoi, also infantry, properly
                    belonged »to the same category, though they were constituted as a theme. It is
                    to be observed that the demes or corporations of Constantinople were partly
                    organized as militia, and were available for purposes of defence.</p>
                <p>The great difference between this Byzantine army and that of the earlier Empire
                    is that its strength (like that of the feudal armies of the West) lay entirely
                    in cavalry, which the successors of Hera-clius and the 1 saurian emperors
                    developed to great perfection. The few contingents of foot were quite
                    subsidiary. The army was free from the want of discipline which was so notable
                    in the 6th century; it was maintained in Asia Minor, which was the great
                    recruiting ground, by a system of military holdings of land (an extension of the
                    old Roman system of assigning lands ¡n the frontier districts to federate
                    barbarians and to veterans). The conditions of the marauding expeditions and
                    guerilla warfare, continuously carried on against and by the Saracens in the
                    8th, 9th and iotn centuries, were carefully studied by generals and tacticians,
                    and we possess the theory of the Byzantine methods in a treatise composed by the
                    emperor Nicephorus. Phocas, and edited by one of his pupils. Every detail of an
                    inroad into Saracen territory is regulated.</p>
                <p>In the 8th and 9th centuries there was a system of signals by which an
                    approaching Saracen incursion was announced to Constantinople from the Cilician
                    frontier. The news was flashed across Asia Minor by eight beacon fires. The
                    first beacon was at Lulon (which commanded the pass between Tyana and the
                    Cilician gates), the last on Mt. Auxentius in Bithynia. When this fire appeared,
                    a light was kindled in the pharos of the imperial palace at Constantinople. The
                    system was discontinued in the reign of Michael III., probably after the capture
                    of Lulon by the enemy in 860, and was not renewed, though Lulon was recovered in
                    877. It should be noted that this famous telegraphic system was only an
                    application on a large scale of the frontier signalling referred to above.</p>
                <p>The loss of a great part of Asia Minor to the Seljuks, and the disorganization of
                    the provinces which they did not acquire, seriously weakened the army, and the
                    emperors had recourse more and more to foreign mercenaries and barbarian
                    auxiliaries. The employment of Scandinavians had begun in the 10th century, and
                    in 988 was formed the Varangian guard, consisting chiefly of English
                    adventurers. In the arsenal of Venice are two lions, which were transported from
                    the Peiraeus, inscribed with obscure Runic characters, carved perhaps by
                    Scandinavians in the army of Basil II. Under Michael IV. the famous Norwegian
                    prince Harald Hardrada (described by a Greek writer as “ Araltcs, son of the
                    king of Varangia ”) fought for the Empire in Sicily and in Bulgaria. But in the
                    latter part of the 1 rth century foreign mercenaries greatly increased in
                    numters and importance.</p>
                <p>The note of the Byzantine army was efficiency, and nowhere is the immeasurable
                    superiority of the civilization of the Eastern Empire to the contemporary states
                    of Europe more apparent. The theory’ of military science was always studied and
                    taught; constant practice, interpreting and correcting theories, safeguarded it
                    against pedantry”, and a class of magnificent staff officers were trained, wno
                    in the 10th century were the terror of the enemy. The particular tactics of the
                    various foes whom they had to face were critically studied. We have a series of
                    military text-books, from the time of Anastasius I. to that of Basil IL, in
                    which we can learn their principles and methods. In this army there was plenty
                    of courage, and distinct professional pride, but no love of fighting for
                    fighting’s sake, nor the spirit which in western Europe developed into chivalry.
                    . The Byzantines despised such ideas as characteristic of barbarians who had
                    physical strength and no brains. The object of a good general, as Leo VI. shows
                    in his important treatise on Tactics, was in their opinion not to win a great
                    battle, but to attain success without the risks and losses of a great battle.
                    The same author criticizes the military character of the Franks. Paying a
                    tribute to their fearlessness, he points out their want of discipline, the
                    haphazard nature of their array and order of battle, their eagerness to attack
                    before the word was given, their want of faculty for strategy or tactical
                    combinations, their incapacity for operations on difficult ground, the ease with
                    which they could be deceived by simple artifices, their carelessness in pitching
                    camps, and their lack of a proper intelligence department. These criticisms,
                    borne out by all we know of feudal warfare, illustrate the contrast betw’een a
                    western host, with its three great “ battles,” rushing headlong at the foe, and
                    the Byzantine army, with its large number of small units, co-operating in
                    perfect harmony, under a commander who had been trained in military’ science,
                    had a definite plan in his head, and could rely on all his subordinates for
                    strict and intelligent obedience.</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-23-r04-0524" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0565.jp2"/>
                <p>Under the early Empire, as Rome had no rival in the Mediterranean, it was natural
                    that the navy and naval theory should be neglected. When Constantine the Great
                    decided to besiege Byzantium by sea, both he and his opponent Licinius had to
                    create fleets for the struggle. Even when the Vandals in Africa made transmarine
                    conquests and became a naval power, the Romans did not seriously address
                    themselves to building an efficient navy and securing their own thalassocracy;
                    the Vandals harried their coasts; their expeditions against Africa failed. And
                    even when the Vandal power was in its decline and Belisarius set forth on his
                    successful expedition of conquest, his fears for the safety of his squadron in
                    case he should be attacked at sea allow us to suspect that the fleet of the
                    enemy was superior to the Roman. The conquest of Africa secured for Justinian
                    the undisputed command of the Mediterranean, but he did nothing for the naval
                    establishment. It was not till the Saracens, aspiring to conquer all the
                    Mediterranean coastlands, became a naval power that the Roman Empire was forced,
                    in a struggle for its being, to organize an efficient fleet. This, as we saw,
                    was the work of Constans II., and we saw what it achieved. In this first period
                    (c. 650-720) the naval forces, designated as the <hi rend="italic">Karabisianoi,</hi> were placed under the command of an admiral, with title
                    of <hi rend="italic">stratèges.</hi> They consisted of two geographical
                    divisions, each under a drudgarios: the province of the Cibyrrhaeots (probably
                    named from the smaller Cibyra in Pamphylia) which included the southern coast
                    districts of Asia Minor, and the Aegean province, which embraced the islands and
                    part of the west coast of Asia Minor. The former was the more important; the
                    marines of this province were the hardy descendants of the pirates, whose
                    subjugation had taxed the resources of the Roman government in the last years of
                    the Republic. It was a new principle to impose, the burden of naval defence on
                    the coast and island districts.. Distinct from these fleets, and probably
                    organized on a different principle, was the naval contingent stationed at
                    Constantinople. Leo III. changed the naval administration, abolishing the
                    supreme command, and making the Cibyrrhaeot and Aegean provinces separate
                    independent themes under <hi rend="italic">strategoi.</hi> The change was due
                    to two motives. There was a danger lest a commander of the whole navy should
                    become over powerful (indicated in the political rôle played by the navy before
                    Leo’s accession); but apart from this, the general reform of Leo, which united
                    civil and military powers in the same hands, naturally placed the commanders of
                    the two. branches of the navy on a new footing, by making them provincial
                    governors. In this and the following reigns, the tendency was to neglect the
                    fleet; the interest of the government was concentrated on the army. For a time
                    this policy was prosecuted with impunity, since the Omayyad dynasty was growing
                    weak, and then under the Abbasids, who transferred the capital from Damascus to
                    Bagdad, the sea-power of the caliphate declined. But the neglect of the fleet
                    was avenged in the 9th century, when Crete and Sicily were wrested from the
                    Empire, the loss of south Italy was imminent, and Moslem squadrons sailed in the
                    Adriatic,—losses and dangers which led to a reorganization of the navy under
                    Basil I. and Leo VI. After this reform we find the navy consisting of two main
                    contingents: the imperial fleet (stationed at Constantinople), and the
                    provincial fleets, three in number, of (a) Cibyrrhaeot theme, (Z&gt;) Aegean
                    theme, <hi rend="italic">(c)</hi> theme of Samos. A small distinct contingent
                    was supplied by the Mardaites who, natives of Mt. Lebanon, had been transplanted
                    (partly to Pamphylia, partly to Epirus, the Ionian Islands, and Peloponnesus)..
                    The imperial fleet seems to have consisted of about 100 warships manned by
                    23,000 marines (the same men fought and *rowed); the provincial fleets of 77
                    warships manned by 17,000. When the fleets acted together, the admiral in
                    supreme command for the time was called the “ drungarios of the naval forces.”
                    The warships (ÔpojLiœres, “dromonds”) were mainly biremes, but there were also
                    uniremes, built for speed, called “galleys” (yaXatat). Pyrotechnic was an
                    important department in the naval establishment; the manufacture of the terrible
                    explosive known as <hi rend="italic">liquid</hi> or <hi rend="italic">marine
                        fire</hi> (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Greek Fire)</hi> was carefully
                    guarded as a state secret.</p>
                <p>The navy, active and efficient in the 10th century, is described by a military
                    and therefore unprejudiced officer of the nth as the glory of Romania. But
                    towards the end of the. nth century it declined, the main cause being the
                    disorganization of the naval provinces of Asia Minor, which, as we saw, was a
                    result of the Seljuk conquest of the interior. This decline had important
                    indirect consequences; it led to the dependence of the Empire on the Venetian
                    navy , in the struggle with the Norman power, and for this help Venice exacted
                    commercial privileges which injured Byzantine commerce and opened the door to
                    the preponderant influences of .the Venetians in eastern trade. In the period of
                    the Palaeologi the imperial navy, though small, was active ; and the importance
                    which it possessed for the state is illustrated by the high rank at court which
                    the admiral (who in the nth century had received the title of Great Duke, <hi
                        rend="italic"> iieyas 5ob£)</hi> then occupied; the only minister who was
                    superior to him was the Great Domestic.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic"> Diplomacy.-—</hi> In protecting the state against the
                    barbarians who surrounded it, diplomacy was a weapon as important in the eyes of
                    the Byzantine government as soldiers or fortifications.</p>
                <p>The peace on the frontiers was maintained not only by strong military defences,
                    but by more or less skilful management of the frontier peoples. In the later
                    Empire this kind of diplomacy, which we may define as the <hi rend="italic">science of managing the barbarians,</hi> was practised as a fine art; its
                    full development was due to Justinian. Its methods fall under three general
                    heads. (1) One people was kept in check by means of another. The imperial
                    government fomented rivalry and hatred among them. Thus Justinian kept the
                    Gepidae in check by the Lombards, the Kuturgurs by the Utigurs, the Huns by the
                    Avars. (2) Subsidies were given to the peoples on the frontiers, in return for
                    which they undertook to defend the frontier adjacent to them, and to supply
                    fighting men when called upon to do so. The chiefs received honours and
                    decorations. Thus the Berber chiefs on the African border received a staff of
                    silver, encrusted with gold, a silver diadem, white cloak, embroidered tunic,
                    &amp;c. More important potentates were invested with a costlier dress. In
                    these investitures precedence was carefully observed. The chiefs thus received a
                    definite position in the Empire, and the rich robes, with the ceremony, appealed
                    to their vanity. In some cases they were admitted to posts in the official
                    hierarchy,—being created Patricians, Masters of soldiers, &amp;c. They were
                    extremely fond of such honours, and considered themselves half-Romans. Another
                    mode of winning influence was to marry barbarian princes to Roman wives, and
                    rear their sons in the luxury of the palace. Dissatisfied pretenders, defeated
                    candidates for kingship, were welcomed at Constantinople. Thus there were
                    generally some princes, thoroughly under Byzantine influence, who at a
                    favourable opportunity could be imposed on their compatriots. Throughout
                    Justinian’s reign there was a constant influx of foreign potentates to
                    Constantinople, and he overwhelmed them with attentions, pompous ceremonies and
                    valuable presents. (3) Both these methods were already familiar to the Roman
                    government, although Justinian employed them far more extensively and
                    systematically than any of his predecessors. The third method was new and
                    characteristic. The close connexion of religion and politics at Constantinople
                    prepares us to find that Christian propaganda should go hand-in-hand with
                    conquest, and that the missionary should co-operate with the soldier. The
                    missionary proved an excellent agent. The typical procedure is as follows. In
                    the land which he undertakes to convert, the missionary endeavours to gain the
                    confidence of the king and influential persons, and makes it a special object to
                    enlist the sympathies of the women. If the king hesitates, it is suggested that
                    he should visit New Rome. The attraction of this idea is irresistible, and when
                    he comes to the capital, the pomp of his reception, the honours shown him by the
                    emperor, and the splendour of the religious ceremonies overcome his last
                    scruples. Thenceforward imperial influence is predominant in his dominion;
                    priests become his advisers; a bishop is consecrated, dependent on the patriarch
                    of Constantinople; and the barbarians are transformed by the penetration of
                    Byzantine ideas. By the application of these various means, Justinian
                    established Roman influence in Nubia, Ethiopia and South Arabia, in the
                    Caucasian regions, and on the coast of the Euxine. The conversion of the Lazi
                    (of Colchis) was specially notable, and that of the Sabiri, who were politically
                    important because they commanded the eastern pass of the Caucasus known as the
                    Caspian Gates. It‘will be observed that the great prestige of the Empire was one
                    of the conditions of the success of this policy.</p>
                <p>The policy had, of course, its dangers, and was severely criticized by one of
                    Justinian’s contemporaries, the historian Procopius. Concessions encouraged
                    greater demands; the riches of the Empire were revealed. It was a system, of
                    course, which could not be permanently successful without military power behind
                    it, and of course it was not infallible; but in principle it was well-founded,
                    and proved, of immeasurable value. Less prejudiced writers than Procopius fully
                    admit the far-sightedness and dexterity of the emperor in his diplomatic
                    activity. A full account of it will be found in Diehl’s <hi rend="italic">Justinien. </hi></p>
                <p>In the 10th century we have again the means of observing how the government
                    conducted its foreign policy on carefully</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-23-r04-0525" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0566.jp2"/>
                <p>thought out principles. The Empire was then exposed to constant danger from
                    Bulgaria, to inroads of the Magyars, and to attacks of the Russians. The key to
                    the diplomatic system, designed to meet these dangers, was the cultivation of
                    friendly relations with the Petchenegs, who did not menace the provinces either
                    by land or sea and could be incited to act against Russians, Bulgarians or
                    Magyars. The system is explained in the treatise (known as <hi rend="italic">De
                        adminìstrando imperio)</hi> composed by the emperor Constantine
                    Porphyrogennetos <hi rend="italic">(c.</hi> 950). The series of these northern
                    states was completed by the kingdom of the Khazars (between the Caucasus and the
                    Don), with which the Empire had been in relation since the time of Heraelius,
                    who, to win its co-operation against Persia, promised his daughter in marriage
                    to the king. Afterwards the Khazars gave two empresses to New Rome (the wives of
                    Justinian II. and Constantine V.). Their almost civilized state steered
                    skilfully between the contending influences of Islam and Christianity, and its
                    kings adopted the curious means of avoiding suspicion of partiality for either
                    creed by embracing the neutral religion of the Jews. Commercial and political
                    relations with the Khazars were maintained through the important outpost of the
                    Empire at Cherson in the Crimea, which had been allowed to retain its republican
                    constitution under a president <hi rend="italic">(irparrevow)</hi> and
                    municipal board (ap%oms), though this freedom was limited by the appointment of
                    a <hi rend="italic">strategos</hi> in 833, a moment at which the Khazars were
                    seriously threatened by the Petchenegs. The danger to be feared from the Khazars
                    was an attack upon Cherson, and it seems probable that this was a leading
                    consideration with Leo III. when he wedded his son Constantine V. to a Khazar
                    princess. In the 9th century it was an object of the government to maintain the
                    Khazars (whose army consisted mainly of mercenaries) against the Petchenegs; and
                    hence, if it should become necessary to hold the Khazars in check, the principle
                    was to incite against them not the Petchenegs, but other less powerful
                    neighbours, the Alans of the Caucasus, and the people of “Black Bulgaria” on the
                    middle Volga (a state which survived till the Mongol conquest).</p>
                <p>For this systematic diplomacy it was necessary to collect information about the
                    peoples whom it concerned. The ambassadors sent to the homes of barbarous
                    peoples reported everything of interest they could discover. We owe to Priscus a
                    famous graphic account of the embassy which he accompanied to the court of
                    Attila. We possess an account of an embassy sent to the Turks in Central Asia in
                    the second half of the 6th century, derived from an official report. Peter the
                    Patrician in Justinian’s reign drew <hi rend="sup">T</hi> up careful reports
                    of his embassies to the Persian court. When foreign envoys came to
                    Constantinople, information was elicited from them as to the history and
                    domestic polities of their own countries. It can be shown that some of the
                    accounts of the history and customs of neighbouring peoples, stored in the
                    treatise of Constantine Porphyrogennetos referred to above (furnishing numerous
                    facts not to be found anywhere else), were derived from barbarian ambassadors
                    who visited Constantinople, and taken down by the imperial secretaries. We may
                    conjecture with some probability that the famous system of the <hi rend="italic"
                        > Relazioni,</hi> which the Venetian government required from its
                    ambassadors, goes back originally to Byzantine influence.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps"> Bibliography.</hi> —1. General works: Gibbon’s <hi
                        rend="italic"> Decline and Fall of the Roman Empire;</hi> Finlay’s <hi
                        rend="italic"> History of Greece</hi> (ed., Tozer; vols. i.-iv., 1877);
                    Hopf, <hi rend="italic">Geschichte Griechenlands</hi> (in Ersch and Gruber, <hi rend="italic">Enzyklopädie</hi> (1 Sekt., vols. Ixxxv., lxxxvi.,
                    1876-78)); Hertzberg, <hi rend="italic">Geschichte der Byzantiner und des
                        osmanischen Reiches bis gegen Ende desiò Jahrhunderts (188$);
                        PaparrhcgopulosJloTopla.</hi> tov <hi rend="italic">'KWrjvtKov</hi> SJwuj
                    (5 vols., 2nd ed., 1887-88); Oman, <hi rend="italic">The Byzantine Empire</hi> (1892) (a popular sketch); Geizer, <hi rend="italic">Abriss der byzantinischen
                        Kaiser geschickte,</hi> in Krumbacher’s <hi rend="italic">Geschichte der
                        byzantinischen Litteratur</hi> (ed. ii., 1897) (a summary but original
                    outline). 2. Works dealing with special periods, or branches of the subject:
                    Schiller, <hi rend="italic">Geschichte der römischen Kaiserzeit</hi> (voi.
                    ii., 1887) (Diocletian to Theodosius the Great); Hodgkin, <hi rend="italic">Italy and her Invaders</hi> (8 vols., 1879-99) (to <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.</hi> 800) ; Bury, <hi rend="italic">History of the Later Roman
                        Empire,</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.</hi> 395-800 (2 vols., 1889); Diehl, <hi
                        rend="italic"> Justinien</hi> (1901) ; Diehl, <hi rend="italic">VAfrique
                        byzantine</hi> (1896); Pernice, <hi rend="italic">L'lmperatore Eraclio</hi> (1905) ; Rambaud, <hi rend="italic">L'Empire grec au dixième siècle</hi> (1870); Schlumberger, <hi rend="italic">Nicéphore Phocas</hi> (1 vol.) and <hi
                        rend="italic"> L'Épopée byzantine</hi> (3 vols.. 1890-1905; 4 vols., finely
                    illustrated, covering the period 960-1057); Gay, <hi rend="italic">L'Italie
                        méridionale et l'empire byzantin, 867-1071</hi> (1904); Neumann, <hi
                        rend="italic"> Die Well-stellung des byzantinischen Reiches vor den
                        Kreuzzügen</hi> (1894); Meliarakes, <hi rend="italic">Aoropta</hi> tov <hi rend="italic">BaaiKdov</hi> tîjs <hi rend="italic">Ninalas Kai</hi> tou <hi rend="italic">beoiroT&amp;Tov rrjs</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">’Hitéîpou</hi> (1898) ; Gerland, <hi rend="italic">Geschichte des lateinischen Kaiserreiches von Rons tan tino pel</hi> (part
                    i., 1905); Fallmerayer, <hi rend="italic">Geschichte des Kaiser-turns Trapezunt</hi> (1827); Norden, <hi rend="italic">Das Papsttum und Byzanz</hi> (1903);
                    Pears, <hi rend="italic">The Fall of Constantinople, being the story of the
                        Fourth Crusade</hi> (1885), and <hi rend="italic">The Destruction of the
                        Greek Empire</hi> (1903).</p>
                <p>(J. B. B.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
