<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>translated from HTML to TEI</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-23-r03-0398-01"
                facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0421.jp2" type="entry">

                <p><label>ROBERT II.</label> (1316-1390), called “the Steward,” king of Scotland,
                    was a son of Walter, the steward of Scotland (d. 1326), and Marjorie (d. 1316),
                    daughter of King Robert the Bruce, and was born on the 2nd of March 1316. In
                    1318 the Scottish parliament decreed that if King Robert died without sons the
                    crown should pass to his grandson; but the birth of a son, afterwards King David
                    II., to Bruce in 1324 postponed the accession of Robert for nearly forty-two
                    years. Soon after the infant David became king in 1329, the Steward began to
                    take a prominent part in the affairs of Scotland. He was one of the leaders of
                    the Scottish army at the battle of Halidon Hill in July 1333; and after gaining
                    some successes over the adherents of Edward Baliol in the west of Scotland, he
                    and John Randolph, 3rd earl of Moray (d. 1346), were chosen as regents of the
                    kingdom, while David sought safety in France. The colleagues soon quarrelled;
                    then Randolph fell into the hands of the English and Robert became sole regent,
                    meeting with such success in his efforts to restore the royal authority that the
                    king was able to return to Scotland in 1341. Having handed over the duties of
                    government to David, the Steward escaped from the battle of Neville’s Cross in
                    1346, and was again chosen regent while the king was a captive in England. Soon
                    after this event some friction arose between Robert and his royal uncle.
                    Accused, probably without truth, of desertion at Neville’s Cross, the Steward as
                    heir-apparent was greatly chagrined by the king’s proposal to make Edward III.
                    of England, or one of his sons, the heir to the Scottish throne, and by David’s
                    marriage with Margaret Logie. In 1363 he rose in rebellion, and after having
                    made his submission was seized and imprisoned together with four of his sons,
                    being only released a short time before David’s death in February 1371. By the
                    terms of the decree of 1318 Robert now succeeded to the throne, and was crowned
                    at Scone in March. 1371. His reign in unimportant. Some steps were taken by the
                    nobles to control the royal authority. In 1378 a war broke out with England; but
                    the king took no part in the fighting, which included the burning of Edinburgh
                    and the Scottish victory at Otterbourne in 1388. As age and infirmity were
                    telling upon him, the estates in 1389 appointed his second surviving son Robert,
                    earl of Fife, afterwards duke of Albany, guardian of the kingdom. The king died
                    at Dundonald on the 13th of May 1390, and was buried at Scone. His first wife
                    was Elizabeth, daughter of Sir Robert Mure of Rowallan, a lady who had formerly
                    been his mistress. By her he had at least four sons, the eldest of whom was his
                    successor, King Robert III., and six daughters. By his second wife, Euphemia,
                    daughter of Hugh, earl of Ross, and widow of Moray, formerly his</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-23-r03-0399" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0422.jp2"/>
               <p>colleague as regent, he had two sons and several daughters; and he had also many
                    illegitimate children.</p>
               <p>See Andrew of Wyntoun <hi rend="italic">The Orygynale Cronykil of Scotland,</hi>
                    edited by. D. Laing (Edinburgh, 1872-1879); John of Fordun <hi rend="sub">1</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">Scotichronicon,</hi> continued by Walter Bower, edited by T.
                    Hearne (Oxford, 1722); John Major, <hi rend="italic">Historia majoris
                        Britanniae,</hi> translated by A. Constable (Edinburgh, 1892); and P. F.
                    Tytler, <hi rend="italic">History of Scotland</hi> (Edinburgh, 1841-1843).</p>



            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
