<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/>         </publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>translated from HTML to TEI</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-23-r03-0462-01" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0495.jp2" type="entry">

<p><label>ROJAS ZORRILLA, FRANCISCO DE</label>
(1607-c. 1660), Spanish dramatist, was born at Toledo; the only circumstance recorded of his life is that he became a knight of Santiago in 1644. The exact date of his death is unknown. His plays were published in 1640-45; the best of his dramatic compositions, <hi rend="italic">Del Rey abajo Ninguno,</hi> is not included in the collection and was printed separately under the title of <hi rend="italic">Garcia del Castanar <hi rend="sub">t</hi></hi> Of his other pieces, apart from their intrinsic merit, an international interest attaches to <hi rend="italic">No hay padre siendo rey,</hi> which was borrowed by Rotrou for his <hi rend="italic">Venceslas;</hi> to <hi rend="italic">Donde hay agravios no hay zelos</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Amo criado,</hi> which were imitated by Scarron in his <hi rend="italic">Jodelet Souffleté</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Maître Valet;</hi> to <hi rend="italic">Entre Bobos anda el juego,</hi> the source of Thomas Corneille’s <hi rend="italic">Don Bertrand de Cigarral, as</hi> well as of Scarron’s <hi rend="italic">Don Japhet JArmenie;</hi> to <hi rend="italic">Obligados y ofendidos,</hi> from which are derived <hi rend="italic">Les Généreux Ennemis</hi> by Boisrobert, <hi rend="italic">Les Illustres Ennemis</hi> by Thomas Corneille, and Scarron’s <hi rend="italic">Écolier de Salamanque;</hi> and to <hi rend="italic">La traiciän busca el castigo,</hi> upon which are based Vanbrugh’s <hi rend="italic">False Friend</hi> and Le Sage’s <hi rend="italic">Traître puni.</hi> Rojas Zorrilla’s power of conveying a tragic impression is manifest in <hi rend="italic">Garda del Castanar;</hi> his chief defect is his persistent preciosity of diction.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>