<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>translated from HTML to TEI</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-23-r03-0460-02"
                facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0493.jp2" type="entry">

                <p><label>ROHAN, LOUIS RENÉ ÉDOUARD</label>, <hi rend="smallcaps">Cardinal de</hi>
                    (1734-1803), prince de Rohan-Guéménée, archbishop of Strassburg, a cadet of the
                    great family of Rohan (which traced its origin to the kings of Brittany, and was
                    granted the precedence and rank of a foreign princely family by Louis XIV.), was
                    born at Paris on the 25th of September 1734. Members of the Rohan family had
                    filled the office of archbishop of Strassburg from 1704—an office which made
                    them princes of the empire and the compeers rather of the German prince-bishops
                    than of the French ecclesiastics. For this high office Louis de Rohan was
                    destined from his birth, and soon after taking orders, in 1760, he was nominated
                    coadjutor to his uncle, Constantine de Rohan-Rochefort, who then held the
                    archbishopric, and he was also consecrated bishop of Canopus. But he preferred
                    the elegant life and the gaiety of Paris to his clerical duties, and had also an
                    ambition to make a figure in politics. He joined the party opposed to the
                    Austrian alliance, which had been cemented by the marriage of the archduchess
                    Marie Antoinette to the dauphin. This party was headed by the duc d’Aiguillon,
                    who in 1771 sent Prince Louis on a special embassy to Vienna to find out what
                    was being done there with regard to the partition of Poland. Rohan arrived at
                    Vienna in January 1772, and made a great noise with his lavish fêtes. But the
                    empress Maria Theresa was implacably hostile to him ; not only did he attempt to
                    thwart her policy, but he spread scandals about her daughter Marie Antoinette,
                    laughed at herself, and shocked her ideas of propriety by his dissipation and
                    luxury. On the death of Louis XV. in 1774, Rohan Was recalled from Vienna, and
                    coldly, received at Paris; but the influence of his family was too great for him
                    to be neglected, and in 1777 he was made grand almoner, and in 1778 abbot of St
                    Vaast. In 1778 he was made a cardinal on the nomination of Stanislaus
                    Poniatowski, king of Poland, and in the following year succeeded his uncle as
                    archbishop of Strassburg and became abbot of Noirmoutiers and Chaise-Dieu. His
                    various preferments brought him in an income of two and a half millions of
                    livres; yet the cardinal was restless and unhappy until he should be reinstated
                    in favour at court and had appeased the animosity which Marie Antoinette felt
                    against him. In pursuit of this object he fell into the hands of a gang of
                    intriguers, the comtesse de Lamotte, the notorious Cagliostro and others, whose
                    actions</p>                <pb xml:id="eb11-23-r03-0461" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0494.jp2"/>
               <p>form part of the “ affair of the diamond necklace.” This story is disentangled
                    elsewhere (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Diamond Necklace),</hi> and diverging views
                    are still taken of it. Rohan certainly was led to believe that his attentions to
                    the queen were welcomed, and that his arrangement by which she received the
                    famous necklace was approved. He was the dupe of others, and at the trial in
                    1786 before the parlement his acquittal was received with universal enthusiasm,
                    and regarded as a victory over the court and the unpopular queen. He was
                    deprived, however, of his office as grand almoner and exiled to his abbey of
                    Chaise-Dieu. He was soon allowed to return to Strassburg, and his popularity was
                    shown by his election in 1789 to the states-general by the clergy of the
                    bailliages of Haguenau and Weissenburg. He at first declined to sit, but the
                    states-general, when it became the national assembly, insisted on validating his
                    election. But as a prince of the church in January 1791 he refused to take the
                    oath to the constitution, and went to Ettenheim, in the German part of his
                    diocese. In exile his character improved, and he spent what wealth remained to
                    him in providing for the poor clergy of his diocese who had been obliged to
                    leave France; and in 1801 he resigned his nominal rank as archbishop of
                    Strassburg. On the 17th of February 1803 he died at Ettenheim.</p>               <p>See the <hi rend="italic">Mémoires</hi> of his secretary, the abbé Georgel, of
                    the baroness d’Oberkirch, of Beugnot, and of Madame Campan; and works cited
                    under Diamond Necklace.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
