<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>translated from HTML to TEI</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-23-r03-0433-03"
                facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0466.jp2" type="entry">

               <p>                   <label>ROCKEFELLER, JOHN DAVISON</label> (1839- ), American</p>               <p>capitalist, was born in Richford, Tioga county, New York, on the 8th of July
                    1839. In 1853 his family removed to Ohio, living after 1857
                    in Cleveland, where Rockefeller had begun to work as a bookkeeper in 1855 and
                    where in 1858 he went into the produce commission business. His firm, Clark
                    &amp; Rockefeller, in 1862 invested in an oil refinery, planned by Samuel
                    Andrews, and in 1865 Rockefeller sold out his share to his partner Clark, bought
                    for $72,500 a larger share in another refinery, and formed the partnership of
                    Rockefeller &amp; Andrews. At about the same time another refinery was
                    started by Rockefeller’s brother William (b. 1841), but in 1867 Rockefeller
                    Andrews absorbed this business, and Henry M. Flagler was added to the
                    partnership, In 1870 the two Rockefellers, Flagler, Andrews and a refiner named
                    Stephen V. Harkness formed the Standard Oil Company, with a capital of
                    $1,000,000 (increased in 1872 to $2,500,000 and in 1874 to $3,500,000), of which
                    John D. Rockefeller was president. This great corporation gradually established
                    itself in practical control of the oil production in America, by means of
                    business methods and financial operations which have been severely criticized,
                    but which brought immense wealth to those concerned. Its capital was further
                    increased in 1882, when separate companies were organized in each state; and in
                    later years, as the first great American “ trust,” the Standard Oil Company was
                    hotly attacked during the anti-trust movement (see <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Inter-state Commerce).</hi> Into the merits of this question it is
                    impossible to enter here. Rockefeller himself retired from active business in
                    1895; he had for a time large iron interests (mines and ore-carrying vessels) on
                    Lake Superior, which he sold to the United States Steel Corporation, and his
                    personal wealth was probably greater than that of any other man in the country.
                    In private life he was a devoted member of the Baptist church, and his
                    benefactions were numerous. To “ the University of Chicago founded by John D.
                    Rockefeller ” (in 1892) he had given, up to 1910, $24,809,666, while to the
                    General Education Board he had given $43,000,000; he founded (1901) and
                    supported the Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research in New York City; he
                    gave large sums to Rush Medical College in Chicago, to Johns Hopkins Hospital in
                    Baltimore, to Barnard College in New York City and to the Baptist Missionary
                    Society; and in 1909 he gave $1,000,000 to endow a medical commission to
                    investigate the nature of the hook-worm and to suppress the hook-worm disease.</p>               <p>See Ida M. Tarbell's <hi rend="italic">History of the Standard Oil Company</hi>
                    (New York, 1903), a severe attack on the Trust; also his own <hi rend="italic"
                        >Random Reminiscences</hi> (1909).</p>            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
