<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>translated from HTML to TEI</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-23-r03-0423-05"
                facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0456.jp2" type="entry">

               <p>                   <label>ROBINSON, MARY</label> [“ Perdita ”] (1758-1800), English</p>               <p>actress and author, was born in Bristol on the 27th of November 1758, the
                    daughter of a captain of a whaler named Darby. In 1774 she was married to Thomas
                    Robinson, a clerk in London, where her remarkable beauty brought her many
                    attentions; and when, after two years of fashionable life, her husband was
                    arrested for debt, she shared his imprisonment. She had been a precocious child,
                    encouraged to write verses, and while in King’s Bench prison she completed the
                    collection published in two volumes in 1775. On her release, thanks to Garrick,
                    she secured an engagement at Drury Lane, making a successful first appearance as
                    Juliet in 1776. On the 3rd of December 1779 she was Perdita in Garrick’s version
                    of <hi rend="italic">The Winter's Tale,</hi> and her beauty so captivated
                    George, prince of Wales (afterwards</p>                <pb xml:id="eb11-23-r03-0424" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0457.jp2"/>
               <p>George IV.), then in his eighteenth year, that he began a correspondence with
                    her, signing himself “ Florizel.” She was for about two years his mistress, but
                    he then deserted her, even dishonouring his bond for £20,000, payable when he
                    came of age, and left her to obtain a pension of £500 in exchange for it from
                    Charles James Fox. Owing to the hostility of public opinion, she feared to
                    return to the stage, but she published some more volumes of her writings. There
                    are numerous charming portraits of “ Perdita ”; two in the Wallace Collection,
                    by Reynolds and by Gainsborough, reveal “ her grave, refined beauty.” Hoppner,
                    Cosway and Romney also painted her.</p>               <p>See <hi rend="italic">Memoirs of Mary Robinson, “ Perdita,”</hi> with
                    introduction and notes by J. F. Molloy (1894).</p>            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
