<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>translated from HTML to TEI</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-23-r03-0447-02"
                facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0480.jp2" type="entry">
               <p>                   <label>RODIN, AUGUSTE</label> (1840- ), French sculptor, was born</p>               <p>in 1840, in Paris, and at an early age displayed a taste for his art. He began
                    by attending Barye’s classes, but did not yield too completely to his influence.
                    From 1864 to 1870, under pressure of necessity, he was employed in the studio of
                    Carrier-Belleuse, where he learnt to deal with the mechanical difficulties of a
                    sculptor. Even so early as 1864 his individuality was manifested in his “ Man
                    with a Broken Nose.” After the war, finding nothing to do in Paris, Rodin went
                    to Brussels, where from 1871 to 1877 he worked, as the colleague of the Belgian
                    artist Van Rasbourg, on the sculpture for the outside and the caryatides for the
                    interior of the Bourse, besides exhibiting in 1875 a “ Portrait of Gamier.” In
                    1877 he contributed to the Salon “ The Bronze Age,” which was seen again, cast
                    in bronze, at the Salon of 1880, when it took a third-class medal, was purchased
                    by the State, and is now in the museum of the Luxembourg. Between 1882 and 1885
                    he sent to the Salons busts of “ Jean-Paul Laurens ” and “ Carrier-Belleuse ”
                    (1882), “ Victor Hugo ” and “ Dalou ” (1884), and “ Antonin Proust ” (1885).
                    From about this time he chiefly devoted himself to a great decorative
                    composition six metres high, which was not finished for twenty years. This is
                    the “ Portal of Hell,” the most elaborate perhaps of all Rodin’s works, executed
                    to order for the Musée des arts décoratifs. It is inspired mainly by Dante’s <hi
                        rend="italic">Inferno,</hi> the poet himself being seated at the top, while
                    at his feet, in under-cut relief, we sec the writhing crowd of the damned, torn
                    by the frenzy of passion and the anguish of despair. The lower part consists of
                    two bas-reliefs, in their midst two masks of tormented faces. Round these run
                    figures of women and centaurs. Above the door three men cling to each other in
                    an attitude of despair. After beginning this titanic undertaking, and while
                    continuing to work on it, Rodin executed for the town of Damvillers a statue of
                    “ Bastien-Lepage for Nancy a “ Monument to Claude le Lorrain,” representing the
                    Chariot of the Sun drawn by horses; and for Calais “ The Burgesses of Calais ”
                    surrendering the keys of the town and imploring mercy. In this, Rodin, throwing
                    over all school tradition, represents the citizens not as grouped on a square or
                    circular plinth, but walking in file. This work was exhibited at the Petit
                    Gallery in 1889. At the time of the secession of the National Society of Fine
                    Arts, or New Salon, in 1890, Rodin withdrew from the old Society of French
                    Artists, and exhibited in the New Salon the bust of his friend “ Puvis de
                    Chavannes ” (1892), “ Contemplation ” and a “ Caryatid,” both in marble, and the
                    “ Monument to Victor Hugo ” (1897), intended for the gardens of the Luxembourg.
                    In this the poet is represented nude, as a powerful old man extending his right
                    arm with a sovereign gesture, the Muses standing behind him. In 1898 Rodin
                    exhibited two very dissimilar works, “ The Kiss,” exhibited again in 1900, a
                    marble group representing Paolo Malatesta and Francesca da Rimini, and the
                    sketch in plaster for a “ Statue of Balzac.” This statue, a commission from the
                    Society of Men of Letters, had long been expected, and was received with
                    vehement dissensions. Some critics regarded this work, in which Balzac was
                    represented in his voluminous dressing-gown, as the first-fruits of a new phase
                    of sculpture; others, on the contrary, declared that it was incomprehensible, if
                    not ridiculous. This was the view taken by the society who had ordered it, and
                    who “ refused to recognize Rodin’s rough sketch as a statue of Balzac, ” and
                    withdrew the commission, giving it to the sculptor Falgui1ère. Falguière
                    exhibited his model in 1899. In the same Salon, Rodin, to prove that the conduct
                    of the society had made no change in his friendship with Falguière, exhibited a
                    bust in bronze of his rival, as well as one of “ Henri Rochefort.” In 1900, the
                    city of Paris, to do honour to Rodin, erected at its own expense a building
                    close to one of the entrances to the Great Exhibition, in which almost all of
                    the works of the artist were to be seen, more especially the great “ Portal of
                    Hell,” still quite incomplete, the “ Balzac,” and a host of other works, many of
                    them unfinished or mere rough sketches. Here, too, were to be seen some of
                    Rodin’s designs, studies and water-colour drawings. He has also executed a great
                    many etchings and <hi rend="italic">sgraffiti</hi> on porcelain for the
                    manufactory at Sèvres. His best-known etching is the portrait of Victor Hugo.
                    Many of Rodin’s works are in private collections, and at the Luxembourg he is
                    represented by a “ Danaïd ” (in marble), a “Saint John” (in bronze, 1880), “ She
                    who made the Helmet ” (bronze statuette), the busts of “ J. P. Laurens ” and of
                    “ A Lady ” and other works. In the Musée Galliera is a very fine bust of Victor
                    Hugo. Rodin’s “ Hand of God ” was exhibited in the New Gallery, London, in 1905.
                    In 1904 Mr Ernest Beckett (Lord Grimthorpe) presented the British nation with
                    the sculptor’s “ Le Penseur.” In the same year Rodin became president of the
                    International Society of Sculptors, Painters and Engravers, in succession to
                    James McNeill Whistler.</p>               <p>See Sculpture <hi rend="italic">(Modern French)</hi> ; also Geffroy, <hi
                        rend="italic">La Vieartisiique</hi> (Paris, 1892, 1893, 1899, 1900); L.
                    Maillard, <hi rend="italic">Rodin</hi> (Paris, 1899); <hi rend="italic">La
                        Plume, Rodin et son œuvre</hi> (Paris, 1900); Alexandre, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Le Batzac de Rodin</hi> (Paris, 1898); H. Boutet, <hi rend="italic">Dix
                        dessins choisis de Auguste Rodin</hi> (1904); R. Dircks <hi rend="sub"
                        >l</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">Auguste Rodin</hi> (1904); H. Duhem, /lwgwj/e <hi
                        rend="italic">Radin</hi> (1903); C. Black, <hi rend="italic">Auguste Rodin:
                        the Man, his Ideas and his Works</hi> (1905).</p>            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
