<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>translated from HTML to TEI</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-23-r03-0425-04"
                facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0458.jp2" type="entry">

               <p>                   <label>ROCHAMBEAU, JEAN BAPTISTE DONATIEN DE VIMEUR</label>,
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Comte de</hi> (1725-1807), French soldier, was born at
                    Vendôme (Loir-et-Cher) on the ist of July 1725. He was originally destined for
                    the church and was brought up at the Jesuit college at Blois, but after the
                    death of his elder brother he entered a cavalry regiment, served in Bohemia and
                    Bavaria and on the Rhine, and in 1747 had attained the rank of colonel He took
                    part in the siege of Maestricht in 1748, became governor of Vendôme in 1749, and
                    after distinguishing himself in 1756 in the Minorca expedition was promoted
                    brigadier of infantry. In 1757 and 1758 he fought in Germany, notably at
                    Crefeld, received several wounds in the battle of Clostercamp (1760), was
                    appointed <hi rend="italic">maréchal de camp</hi> in 1761 and inspector of
                    cavalry and was frequently consulted by the ministers on technical points. In
                    1780 he was sent, with the rank of lieutenant-general, in command of 6000 French
                    troops to help the American colonists under Washington against the English. He
                    landed at Newport, Rhode Island, on the 10th of July, but was held here inactive
                    for a year, owing to his reluctance to abandon the French fleet, which was
                    blockaded by the British in Narragansett Bay. At last, in July 1781,
                    Rochambeau’s force was able to leave Rhode Island and, marching across
                    Connecticut, joined Washington on the Hudson. Then followed the celebrated march
                    of the combined forces to Yorktown, where on the 22nd of September they formed a
                    junction with the troops of Lafayette; as the result Cornwallis was forced to
                    surrender on the 19th of October. Throughout, Rochambeau had displayed an
                    admirable spirit, placing himself entirely under Washington’s command and
                    handling his troops as part of the American army. In recognition of his
                    services, Congress voted him and his troops the thanks of the nation and
                    presented him with two cannon taken from the English. These guns, which
                    Rochambeau took back to Vendôme, were requisitioned in 1792. On his return to
                    France he was loaded with favours by Louis XVI. and was made governor of
                    Picardy. During the Revolution he commanded the Army of the North in 1790, but
                    resigned in 1792. He was arrested during the Terror, and narrowly escaped the
                    guillotine. He was subsequently pensioned by Bonaparte, and died at Thore
                    (Loir-et-Cher) on the 10th of May 1807.</p>               <p>A statue of Rochambeau by Ferdinand Hamar, the gift of France to the United
                    States, was unveiled in Lafayette Square, Washington, by President Roosevelt on
                    the 24th of May 1902. The ceremony was made the occasion of a great
                    demonstration of friendship between the two nations. France was represented by
                    her ambassador, M. Cambon, Admiral Fournier and General Brugère, a detachment of
                    sailors and marines from the warship “ Gaulois ” being present. Representatives
                    of the Lafayette and Rochambeau families also attended. Of the many speeches
                    perhaps the most striking was that of Senator Henry C. Lodge, who, curiously
                    enough in the circumstances, prefaced his eloquent appreciation of the services
                    rendered to the American cause by France by a brilliant sketch of the way in
                    which the French had been driven out of North America by England and her
                    colonists combined. General Brugère, in his speech, quoted Rochambeau’s words,
                    uttered in 1781: “ <hi rend="italic">Entre vous.</hi>
               </p>                <pb xml:id="eb11-23-r03-0426" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0459.jp2"/>
               <p>                   <hi rend="italic">entre nous, à la vie, à la mort.</hi> A “ Rochambeau fête ”
                    was held simultaneously in Paris.</p>               <p>The <hi rend="italic">Mémoires militaires, historiques et politiques, de
                        Rochambeau</hi> were published by Luce de Lancival in 1809. Of the first
                    volume a part, translated into English by M. W. E. Wright, was published in 1838
                    under the title of <hi rend="italic">Memoirs of the Marshal Count de R. relative
                        to the War of Independence in the United States.</hi> Rochambeau’s
                    correspondence during the American campaign is published in H. Doniol, <hi
                        rend="italic">Hist, de la participation de la France a l’etablissement des
                        États Unis d’Amérique,</hi> vol. v. (Paris, 1892). See Duchesne, “ Autour de
                    Rochambeau ’’ in the <hi rend="italic">Revue des Jacuttes catholiques de
                        l’ouest</hi> (1898-1900); E. Gachot, “ Rochambeau ” in the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Nouvelle Revue</hi> (1902); H. de Ganniers, “ La Dernière Campagne du
                    maréchal de Rochambeau ’’ in the <hi rend="italic">Revue des questions
                        historiques</hi> (1901).</p>            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
