<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>translated from HTML to TEI</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-23-r03-0464-01"
                facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0497.jp2" type="entry">

                <p><label>ROLAND, LEGEND OF</label>. The legend of the French epic hero Roland
                    (transferred to Italian romance as Orlando) is based on authentic history.
                    Charlemagne invaded Spain in 778, and had captured Pampeluna, but failed before
                    Saragossa, when the news of a Saxon revolt recalled him to the banks of the
                    Rhine. On his retreat to France through the defiles of the Pyrenees, part of his
                    army was cut off from the main body by the Basques, who had ambushed in a narrow
                    defile, and now drove the rearguard into a valley where it was surrounded and
                    entirely destroyed. The Basques, after plundering the baggage, made good their
                    escape, favoured by the darkness and by their knowledge of the ground. The
                    incident is related in the <hi rend="italic">Annales</hi> (Pertz i. 159)
                    commonly ascribed to Einhard, and with more detail in Einhard's <hi
                        rend="italic">Vita Karoli</hi> (cap. ix.; Pertz ii. 448), where the names of
                    the leaders are given. “ In this battle were slain Eggihard, <hi rend="italic"
                        >praepositus</hi> of the royal table; Anselm, count of the palace; and
                    Hruodland, praefect of the Breton march. . . The scene of the disaster is fixed
                    by tradition at Roncevaux, on the road from Pampeluna to Saint Jean Pied de
                    Port. There is no foundation in this story for the fiction of the twelve peers,
                    which may possibly arise from a still earlier tradition. In 636-37, according to
                    the <hi rend="italic">Chronicles</hi> of Fredegarius (ed. Krusch p. 159), twelve
                    chiefs, whose names are given, were sent by Dagobert against the Basques. The
                    expedition was successful, but in an engagement fought in the valley of Subola,
                    or Robola, identified with Mauleon, which is not far from Roncevaux, the Duke
                    Harembert, with other Frankish chiefs, was slain. Later fights in the same
                    neighbourhood and under similar circumstances are related in 813 <hi
                        rend="italic">{Vita Hludowici,</hi> Pertz ii. 616), and especially in 824
                    (Einhard's <hi rend="italic">Annales',</hi> Pertz i. 213). These incidents no
                    doubt served to strengthen the tradition of the disaster to Charlemagne's
                    rear-guard in 778, the importance of which was perhaps underrated by the
                    Frankish historians and was certainly magnified in popular story. The author of
                    the <hi rend="italic">Vita Hludowici,</hi> writing sixty years after the battle
                    of Roncevaux, thought it superfluous to give the names of the fallen chiefs, as
                    being matter of common report.</p>
               <p>                    <hi rend="italic">Growth of the Legend.—</hi> The choice of Roland or Hruodland
                    as the hero of the story probably points to the borders of French Brittany as
                    the home of the legend. The exaggeration of a rear-guard action into a national
                    defeat; the substitution of a vast army of Saracens, the enemies of the Frankish
                    nation and the Christian faith, for the border tribe mentioned by Einhard; <note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="1"> It is noteworthy,
                        however, that an Arab historian, Ibn-al-Athîr, states that Charles’s
                        assailants were the Arabs of Saragossa, by whom he had been originally
                        invited to interfere in Spain. </note> and the vengeance inflicted by
                    Charlemagne, where in fact the enemy escaped with complete impunity—all are in
                    keeping with the general laws of romance. Charlemagne himself appears as the
                    ancient epic monarch, not as the young man he really was in 778. The earliest
                    version of the legend which we possess dates no eariier than the nth century,
                    but there is abundant evidence of the existence of a continuous tradition dating
                    from the original event, although its methods of transmission remain a vexed
                    question. Roncevaux lay on the route to Compostella, and the many pilgrims who
                    must have passed the site from the middle of the 9th century onwards may have
                    helped to spread the story. Whether the actual <hi rend="italic">cantilena
                        Rollandi</hi> chanted by Taillefer at the battle of Hastings (William of
                    Malmesbury, <hi rend="italic">De gestis regum angl.</hi> iii. 242, and Wace, <hi
                        rend="italic">Brut.</hi> ii. <hi rend="smallcaps">ii,</hi>
                     8035 seq.) was any part of the existing <hi rend="italic">Chanson de
                        Roland</hi> cannot be stated, but the choice of the legend on this occasion
                    by the trouvère is proof of its popularity.</p>
               <p>The oldest extant forms of the legend are: <hi rend="italic">{a)</hi> chapters
                    xix.-xxx. of the Latin chronicle, known as the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Pseudo-Turpin,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>which purports to be the work of Turpin, archbishop of Reims, who died about
                    800, but probably dates from the 12th century; (ô) <hi rend="italic">Carmen de
                        proditione Guenonis, &amp;</hi> poem in Latin distichs; and <hi
                        rend="italic">(c)</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Chanson de Roland,</hi> a
                    French <hi rend="italic">chanson de geste</hi> of about 4000 Hnes, the oldest
                    recension of which is in the Bodleian Library, Oxford (MS. Digby 23). It is in
                    assonanced tirades, of unequal length, many of them terminated with the refrain
                        <hi rend="italic">Aoi.</hi> This MS. was written by an Anglo-Norman scribe
                    about the end of the 12th century, and is a corrupt copy of a text by a French
                    trouvère of the middle of the nth century. It concludes with the words: “ Ci
                    falt la geste, que Turoldus declinet.” There was a Turold (d. 1098) who was
                    abbot of Peterborough; another was tutor to William the Conqueror and died in
                    J035. Even if we could identify this personage, we cannot tell whether he was
                    the poet, the minstrel or the scribe of the MS., but it seems likely that he was
                    merely the scribe. The poem, which was first printed by Francisque Michel
                    (Oxford, 1837), is the finest monument of the heroic age of French epic. In its
                    fundamental features it evidently dates back to the reign of Charlemagne, who is
                    not represented as the capricious despot of the later <hi rend="italic">chansons
                        de geste,</hi> but as governing in accordance with Frankish custom,
                    accepting the counsel of his barons, and carrying out the curious procedure of
                    Frankish law. <hi rend="italic">Roland</hi> represents the monarchical idea, and
                    was evidently, in its primitive form, written before the feudal revolts which
                    weakened the power of Charlemagne’s successors. Its unity of conception, the
                    severity and conciseness of the language, the directness, vividness and sobriety
                    of the narrative, place it far above the chansons of later trouvères, with their
                    wordiness and their loose, episodic construction. With the exception of the
                    small place allotted to Aide, women have practically no place in the story, and
                    the romantic element is thus absent. Roland's master-passions are daring and an
                    exaggerated conception of honour, the extravagance of which is the cause of the
                    disaster. His address to Oliver before the battle is typical of the warlike
                    spirit of the poem:—</p>
               <p>“ Notre empereur qui ses Francs nous laissa,</p>
               <p>Tels vingt mille hommes a pour nous mis à part,</p>
               <p>Qu’il sait très bien que pas un n’est couard.</p>
               <p>Pour son seigneur grands maux on souffrira,</p>
               <p>Terribles froids, grands chauds endurera,</p>
               <p>Et de son sang, de sa chair on perdra!</p>
               <p>Brandis ta lance; et moi, ma Durendal,</p>
               <p>Ma bonne épée, que le Roi me donna.</p>
               <p>Et si je meurs, peut dire qui Vaura</p>
               <p>C’était l’épée d’un très noble vassal.”</p>
               <p>(tr. Petit de Julleville xi. 1114 seq.)</p>
               <p>                    <hi rend="italic">The Story as related in the Chanson de Roland.—</hi>
                    Charlemagne, after fighting for seven years in Spain, had conquered the whole
                    country with the exception of Saragossa, the seat of the Saracen king Marsile.
                    He was encamped before Cordova when he received envoys from the Saracen king,
                    sent to procure the evacuation of Spain by the Franks through false offers of
                    submission. Charlemagne held a council of his barons, Naimes of Bavaria, Roland,
                    Oliver, Turpin, Ogier, Ganelon and the rest. Roland, the emperor’s nephew, was
                    eager for war; the peace party was headed by Ganelon of Mayence. <note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="2"> Ganelon may perhaps
                        be identified with Wenilo, archbishop of Sens, whose treason against Charles
                        the Bald is related in the <hi rend="italic">Annales Bertiniani</hi> (anno
                        859). </note> The Franks were weary of campaigning, and Ganelon’s counsels
                    won the day. At the suggestion of Roland, Ganelon, who was his stepfather, was
                    entrusted with the embassy to Marsile—a sufficiently perilous errand, since two
                    former envoys had been beheaded by the Saracens. Ganelon, inspired by hatred of
                    Roland and Oliver, agreed with Marsile to betray Roland and his comrades for ten
                    mule-loads of gold. He then returned to Charlemagne bearing Marsile’s supposed
                    assent to the Frankish terms. The retreat began. Roland, at Ganelon's
                    instigation, was placed in command of the rear-guard. With him were the rest of
                    the famous twelve peers, <note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                        n="3"> The lists vary in different texts. </note> his companions-in-arms,
                    Oliver, Gerin, Gerier, Oton, Berengier, Samson, Anseis, Girard</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-23-r03-0465" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0498.jp2"/>
               <p>de Roussillon, Engelier the Gascon, Ivon and Ivoire, and the flower of the
                    Frankish army. They had nearly reached the summit of the pass when Oliver, who
                    had mounted a high rock, saw the advancing army of the Saracens, 400,000 strong.
                    In vain Oliver begged Roland to sound his horn and summon Charlemagne to his
                    aid. A description of the battle, a series of single combats, follows. Oliver,
                    with his sword Hauteclêre, rivalled Roland with Durendal. After the first fight,
                    a second division of the pagan army appears, then a third. Roland’s army was
                    reduced to sixty men before he consented to sound his horn. Presently all were
                    slain but Roland and Oliver, Turpin and another. Finally, when the Saracens,
                    warned of the return of Charlemagne, had retreated, Roland alone survived on the
                    field of battle. With a last effort he blew his horn once more, and heard before
                    he died the sound of Charlemagne’s battlecry of “ Montjoie.” Charlemagne pursued
                    the enemy, and destroyed their army. The raising of a second army by Baligant,
                    the emir of Babylon, and its defeat by the emperor, who slays Baligant in single
                    combat, is obviously an interpolation in the original narrative. The trouvère
                    then relates the return of the Franks, the burial of the heroes of Roncevaux,
                    and, at great length, the trial of Ganelon at Aix, his execution, and that of
                    his thirty kinsmen, and the death of Alde, Roland’s betrothed and Oliver’s
                    sister, when she heard the news of Roland’s death. The trial of Ganelon is one
                    of the most curious parts of the story, providing, as it does, a full account of
                    the Frankish criminal procedure.</p>
               <p>                    <hi rend="italic">Relations between the Earlier Forms of the Legend.—</hi> The
                        <hi rend="italic">Pseudo-Turpin</hi> represents a different recension of the
                    story, and is throughout clerical in tone. It was the trouvère of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Chanson de Roland</hi> who developed the characters into epic
                    types; he invented the heroic friendship of Roland and Oliver, the motives of
                    Ganelon’s treachery, and many other details. The famous fight between Roland and
                    the giant Ferragus appears in the <hi rend="italic">Pseudo-Turpin</hi> (chapter
                    xviii.), but not in the poem. The <hi rend="italic">Chanson de Roland</hi>
                    presupposes the existence of a whole cycle of epic poetry, probably in episodic
                    form; it contains allusions to many events outside the narrative, some of which
                    can be explained from other existing chansons, while others refer to narratives
                    which are lost. In lines 590-603 of the poem Roland gives a list of the
                    countries he has conquered for Charles, from Constantinople and Hungary on the
                    east to Scotland on the west. Of most of these exploits no trace remains in
                    extant poems, but his capture of Bordeaux, of Nobles, of Carcassonne, occur in
                    various compilations. Roland was variously represented by the romancers as the
                    son of Charlemagne’s sister Gilles or Berte and the knight Milon d’Anglers. The
                    romantic episode of the reconciliation of the pair with Charlemagne through
                    Roland’s childish prattle <hi rend="italic">{Berte et Milon)</hi> is probably
                    foreign to the original legend. In the Scandinavian versions Roland is the son
                    of Charlemagne and his sister, a recital probably borrowed from mythology. His
                        <hi rend="italic">enfances,</hi> or youthful exploits, were, according to
                        <hi rend="italic">Aspremont,</hi> performed in Italy against the giant
                    Eaumont, but in <hi rend="italic">Girais de Viane</hi> his first taste of battle
                    is under the walls of Vienne, where Oliver, at first his adversary, becomes his
                    brother-in-arms.</p>
               <p>                    <hi rend="italic">Other Versions.—</hi> Most closely allied to the Oxford <hi
                        rend="italic">Roland</hi> are (a) a version in Italianized French preserved
                    in a 13th or 14th century MS. in the library of St Mark, Venice (MS. Fr. iv.) ;
                    (δ) the <hi rend="italic">Ruolantes Liet</hi> (ed. W. Grimm, Göttingen, 1838) of
                    the Swabian priest Konrad (fl. 1130), who gave, however, a pious tone to the
                    whole; <note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="4"> A proof of
                        the popularity of the legend in Germany is supplied by the so-called Roland
                        statues, of which perhaps the most famous example is that of Bremen. Mention
                        of a <hi rend="italic">statua Rolandi</hi> is made in a <hi rend="italic"
                            >Privilegium</hi> granted by Henry V. to the town of Bremen in 1111. The
                            <hi rend="italic">Rolandssäule</hi> were probably symbolic of. the
                        judicial rights possessed by the towns where they are found, and it has been
                        suggested that the word arises from false etymology with <hi rend="italic"
                            >Rothlandsaide,</hi> red-land-pillar, the symbol of the possession of
                        the power of life and death.</note> (c) the 8th branch of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Karlamagnus-saga</hi> (ed. C. Unger, Christiania, 1860), and
                    the Danish version of that compilation.</p>
               <p>In the 12th century the <hi rend="italic">Chanson de Roland</hi> was modernized
                    by replacing the assonance by rhyme, and by amplifications and additions.
                    Several MSS. of this rhymed recension, sometimes known as <hi rend="italic"
                        >Roncevaux,</hi> are preserved. In the prose compilations of <hi
                        rend="italic">Galien</hi> and in David Aubert’s <hi rend="italic">Conquîtes
                        de Charlemagne</hi> (1158) the story kept its popularity for many centuries.
                    In England the story was understood in the original French, and the English
                    romances of Charlemagne <hi rend="italic">(q.v.)</hi> are mostly derived from
                    late and inferior sources. In Spain the legend underwent a curious
                    transformation. Spanish patriotism created a Spanish ally of Marsile, Bernard
                    del Carpio, to be the rival and victor of Roland. It was in Italy that the
                    Roland legend had its greatest fortune : Charlemagne and Roland appear in the
                        <hi rend="italic">Paradiso</hi> (canto xviii.) of Dante ; the statues of
                    Roland and Oliver appear on the doorway of the cathedral of Verona; and. the
                    French <hi rend="italic">chansons de geste</hi> regularly appeared in a corrupt
                    Italianized French. The Roland legend passed through a succession of revisions,
                    and, as the. <hi rend="italic">Spagna,</hi> forming the 8th book of the great
                    compilation of Carolingian romance, the <hi rend="italic">Reali di Francia,</hi>
                    kept its popularity down to the Renaissance. The story of Roland (Orlando) in a
                    greatly modified form is the subject of the poems of Luigi Pulci <hi
                        rend="italic">(Morgante Maggiore,</hi> 1481), of Matteo Boiardo <hi
                        rend="italic">(Orlando innamorato,</hi> i486), of Ariosto <hi rend="italic"
                        >(Orlando furioso,</hi> 1516), and of Francesco Berni <hi rend="italic"
                        >(Orlando,</hi> 1541).</p>
               <p>                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Authorities.—For a complete bibliography of the editions of
                        the various MSS. of the</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">Chanson de Roland,</hi> of the foreign versions, and of the
                    enormous literature of the subject, see Lcon Gautier, <hi rend="italic">Les
                        Épopées françaises</hi> (2nd ed., vol. iii., 1880), and the same author’s
                        <hi rend="italic">Bibliographic des chansons de geste</hi> (1897). Among
                    critical editions of the <hi rend="italic">Chanson</hi> are those by. Wendelin
                    Foerster in the <hi rend="italic">Altfranz. Bibliotek,</hi> vols, vi. and vii.
                    (Ikilbronn, 1883-86), and by E. Stengel, <hi rend="italic">Das altfranzösische
                        Rolandslied</hi> (Leipzig, 1900, &amp;c.). The most popular edition is
                        <hi rend="italic">La Chanson de Roland</hi> (Tours, 1872, and numerous
                    subsequent editions), by Léon Gautier, with.text, translation, introduction,
                    notes, variants and glossary. L. Petit de Julleville published in 1878 an
                    edition with the old French text, and a modern French translation in assonanced
                    verse. There are various other translations in French; in English prose by I.
                    Butler (Boston, Mass., 1904); and a partial English verse translation by A. Way
                    and F. Spencer (London, 1895). Consult further G. Paris, <hi rend="italic">Hist.
                        poét. de Charlemagne</hi> (reprint, 1905), and <hi rend="italic">De Pseudo
                        Turpino</hi> (Paris, 1865); P. Rajna <hi rend="sub">1</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">Le Origini dell’ epopea francese</hi> (Florence, 1884) and <hi
                        rend="italic">Le Fonti dell’ Orlando Furioso</hi> (2na ed., Florence, 1900);
                    F. Picco, <hi rend="italic">Rolando netla storia e nella poesia</hi> (Turin,
                    1901); G. Paris, “ Roncevaux,” in <hi rend="italic">Légendes du moyen âge</hi>
                    (1903), on the topography of the battlefield.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
