<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>translated from HTML to TEI</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-23-r03-0408-01"
                facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0431.jp2" type="entry">

                <p><label>ROBES</label> (Fr. <hi rend="italic">robe.</hi> Late Lat. <hi
                        rend="italic">roba, raupa,</hi> meaning (1) spoils, (2) robe, stuff, cf.
                    Mod. Ital. <hi rend="italic">roba,</hi> connected with a Teutonic root <hi
                        rend="italic">raup, raub,</hi> German <hi rend="italic">rauben</hi> and
                    English <hi rend="italic">rob),</hi> the name generally given to a class of
                    official costume, especially as worn by certain persons or classes on occasions
                    of particular solemnity. According to Du Cange, the word robe was earliest used,
                    in the sense of a garment, of those given by popes and princes to the members of
                    their household or their great officers. Thus Matthew Paris <hi rend="italic"
                        >(Chr on. Majora,</hi> Rolls Series, V. 38) tells how, in 1248, the pope
                    gave to some Tatar envoys “ vestes pretiosissimas quas Robas vulgaritcr
                    appellamus, de escarleto praeelecto, cum pellibus et furruris,” with which Du
                    Cange compares the “ festiva indumenta ” given, <hi rend="italic">e.g.,</hi> by
                    King John <hi rend="italic">magnatum suorum multitudini</hi> at Christmas time
                    (1214, Matt. Paris, Rolls Series, II. 520) and the <hi rend="italic">raubae
                        papales Scutiferorum,</hi> and the like, given by the popes to members of
                    their households, after the fashion of a livery. It would, however, be perhaps
                    going too far to assume that, <hi rend="italic">e.g.,</hi> peers’ robes were
                    originally the king’s livery, for there seems to be no proof that this was the
                    case; but it is curious that in most early cases where robes are mentioned, if
                    not of cloth of gold, &amp;c., they are of scarlet, furred. A robe is
                    properly a long garment, and the term “ robes ” is now applied only in those
                    cases where a long garment forms part of the official costume, though in
                    ordinary usage it is taken to include all the other articles of dress proper to
                    the costume in question. The term “ robes,” moreover, connotes a certain degree
                    of dignity or honour in the wearer. We speak of the king’s robes of state, of
                    peers’ robes, of the robes of the clergy, of academic robes, judicial robes,
                    municipal or civic robes; we should not speak of the robes of a cathedral
                    verger, though he too wears a long gown of ceremony, and it is even only by
                    somewhat stretching the term “ robes ” that we can include under it the ordinary
                    academical dress of the universities. In the case of the official costume of the
                    clergy, too, a distinction must be drawn. The <hi rend="italic">Vestimenta
                        sacra</hi> are not spoken of as “ robes a priest is not “ robed ” but “
                    vested ” for Mass; yet the rochet and chimere of an English bishop, even in
                    church, are more properly referred to as robes than as vestments, and while the
                    cope he wears in church is a vestment rather than a robe, the scarlet cope which
                    is part of his parliamentary full dress is a robe, not a vestment. For the sake
                    of convenience the official, non-liturgical costume of the clergy Es dealt with
                    under the general heading <hi rend="smallcaps">Vestments</hi> and the subsidiary
                    articles <hi rend="italic">(e.g.</hi>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Cope).</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The coronation robes of emperors and kings, representing as they do the
                    sacerdotal significance of Christian kingship, are Sssentially vestments rather
                    than robes (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Coronation).</hi> Apart from these,
                    however, are the royal robes of state; in the case of the king of England a
                    crimson velvet surcoat and long mantle, fastened in front of the neck, ermine
                    lined, with a deep cape or tippet of ermine. <note anchored="true"
                        place="bottom" type="authorial" n="1"> For the sovereign’s coronation robes,
                        see <hi rend="sup">U</hi> The King’s Coronation Ornaments,” by W. St John
                        Hope, in <hi rend="italic">The Ancestor,</hi> vols. i. and ii., also L.
                        Wickham Legg, <hi rend="italic">English Coronation Records,</hi> 1901. The “
                        parliamentary robes ” used to be of crimson or purple velvet, furred with
                        ermine. See the ahove, also the inventories of the , wardrobes of
                        sovereigns, &amp;c. </note>
               </p>
               <p>The subject of official robes is too vast for any attempt to be made to deal
                    with it comprehensively here. All countries, East and West, which boast an
                    ancient civilization have retained them in greater or less degree, and the
                    tendency in modern times has been to multiply rather than to diminish their
                    number. Even in republican France they survived the Revolution, at least in the
                    universities and the law courts. But nowhere has custom been so conservative in
                    this matter is in the United Kingdom, where in this as in other matters the wise
                    Machiavellian principle has been followed of changing</p>
               <p>the substance of institutions without altering their outward semblance. The
                    present article, then, does not attempt to deal with any but British robes,
                        <note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="2"> In the United
                        States few save Federal judges wear robes. The scarlet judicial robes were
                        discarded at the Revolution. Those of black silk now worn are slightly
                        modified academic gowns. John Jay, first Chief Justice of the Supreme Court
                        (1787), set the. fashion by sitting in the LL.D. gown granted him by
                        Columbia University.. </note> under the headings of (1) peers’ robes, (2)
                    robes in the House of Commons, (3) robes of the Orders of Knighthood, (4)
                    judicia! and forensic robes, (5) municipal and civic robes, (6) academic
                    costume.</p>
               <p>                    <hi rend="italic">PeerP Robes.—</hi> As early as the end of the 14th century
                    peers seem to have worn at their creation some kind of robe of honour; this we
                    may conclude from the description of the investiture of the earI of Somerset in
                    1397 <hi rend="italic">(Rot. Part.</hi> iii. 343), which says: “ le dit Monsieur
                    John fut amesnée devant le Roy en Parlement entre deux Contes, c’est assavoir
                    Huntyngdon et Mares-chall, vestuz en un pane (Du Cange; <hi rend="italic"
                        >pannus=$. habitus vesti-mentum)</hi> come vesture de honor ”; while in
                    accounts of various creations of about the same time <hi rend="italic">(Rot.
                        Part.</hi> iii. 205, 206) are used the words “ advenienteque . . . prefato
                    Duce honorifice . . . t ogato et orna to.” An early illustration of their use is
                    to be found in an illumination on the foundation charter of King’s College,
                    Cambridge (see fig. 1), which represents the peers as</p>
               <p>early as 1446 wearing gowns, mantles and hoods of scarlet, furred with miniver,
                    the mantle opening on the right shoulder and guarded with two, three or four
                    bars of miniver, in the form of short stripes high up on the shoulder. The
                    origin of these is as yet unknown, and it is not certain precisely when the
                    peers’ velvet rohe of estate was first used. At the coronation of Henry VI. the
                    king’s own parliament robe was of scarlet and miniver (Gregory’s <hi
                        rend="italic">Chronicle,</hi> ed. Gairdner, Camden Soc. pp. 165-70), so the
                    peers’ robes were certainly not yet of velvet; at that of Henry VII. (see <hi
                        rend="italic">Rutland Papers,</hi> 1842; “ Device for the Coronation of
                    Henry VII.”) the king had a robe of crimson velvet and ermine, but the “ lords
                    temporall ” are only said to have been “ in their robes ”; at that of Henry
                    VIII. (see Hall’s <hi rend="italic">Chronicle}</hi> the king in his progress
                    through the city wore a crimson velvet robe furred with ermine, “ his knights
                    and esquires for his body ” wore crimson velvet, and “ all the gentlemen,”
                    &amp;c., scarlet, while we hear of the “ lords spiritual and temporal, and
                    of their costly and rich apparel, of several devises and fashions,” and notably
                    of the duke of Bucking -ham’s robe of gold and needlework (Stow’s <hi
                        rend="italic">Annals,</hi> p. 813), which would show that the velvet robe of
                    estate was not yet worn at the king’s coronation. The duke of Richmond at his
                    creation in 1525 (17 Henry VIII., see Brewer, <hi rend="italic">State
                        Papers,</hi> iv. 639) is described as clad in robes of estate, and the
                    description of the investiture says that “ the patent was read, the <hi
                        rend="italic">robe,</hi> sword, cap and circlet put on,” and about this time
                    references are found to the “ parliament robes ” of peers, implying that there
                    were others.</p>
               <p>An account of the coronation of Anne Boleyn in 1533, in J. Nichols, <hi
                        rend="italic">Progresses of Queen Elizabeth,</hi> vol. i. p. r, says that in
                    her progress through the city “ all the Iordes for the most part were clothed in
                    crimson velvet,” while at</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-23-r03-0409" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0436.jp2"/>
               <p>Westminster the barons and viscounts wore their parliament robes, <note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="3"> These are well
                        described in the account of the opening of parliament by Henry VIlI. in 1537
                        given in Wriothesley’s <hi rend="italic">Chronicle of England</hi> (Camden
                        Soc., 1875, ed. W. Hamilton): “ all erles marques and lordes, all in their
                        Perliament robes of scarlett furred with white, and their hoodes about their
                        neckes, which were forty in number; everie duke having fower barres of white
                        fur alongest the right side of their robes, and everie earle having three
                        bars, . . and everie lord two barres in likewise.” </note> the earls,
                    marquesses and dukes wearing their robes of estate of crimson velvet “ furred
                    with ermins, poudred according to their degrees.” This was also the case at the
                    coronation of James I., and in Selden <hi rend="sup">i</hi> S <hi rend="italic"
                        >Titles of Honour</hi> (3rd ed., 1672) the illustrations show the baron and
                    viscount in parliamentary robes, the higher ranks in robes of estate. By the
                    time of James II.’s coronation, however, the baron and viscount had the velvet
                    robes of estate (see illustration on p. 188 of Perkins’s <hi rend="italic">The
                        Coronation Book,</hi> 1902, where the surcoat also appears to have a pointed
                    collar edged with white and to be sleeveless). The colour of these seems to have
                    been crimson at first, sometimes varying to purple. They consisted of a long
                    gown or surcoat with girdle, a mantle lined with ermine, a hood and a tippet of
                    ermine, the rows being as follows: for a duke 4, a marquess 3I, an earl 3, a
                    viscount 25, and a baron 2.</p>
               <p>Till late in the 18th century peers continued to attend the House of Lords in
                    parliamentary robes, with the stars and ribbons of their orders, but robes are
                    now only worn in the Hourse of Lords, <hi rend="italic">e.g.</hi> at the opening
                    of parliament, on occasions when the sovereign gives his assent to bills by “
                    royal commission ” (when five or six peers on the government side appear in
                    robes, and the lord chancellor also wears his peer’s robe of scarlet ermine),
                    and at the introduction of a newly created peer, when the new peer and his two
                    introducers wear their parliamentary robes (over morning dress) during the
                    ceremony of introduction only. The mover and seconder of the Address no longer
                    wear robes, but uniform. On all the above occasions, and when the peers as a
                    body attend church or some other ceremony, the parliamentary robe of scarlet
                    cloth is worn; in the present day it takes the form of a mantle opening on the
                    right shoulder, with a collar of “ ermine,” and guarded with rows of ermine and
                    gold lace round the right shoulder, varying in number according to the rank of
                    the wearer. The modern coronation robes consist of a crimson velvet surcoat and
                    a mantle with a tippet of ermine and with rows of ermine as in the parliamentary
                    robes. The surcoat is no longer a gown, but a short sleeveless garment.</p>
               <p>For Scotland, an order of James II. (1455) prescribed for earls “ mantles of
                    brown granick colour ” open before, lined and faced in front, as far as the
                    girdle, with white fur, and with hoods to match ; for the other lords of
                    parliament a red mantle lined with silk or fur, with a furred hood, while James
                    I. (and Vi.) in 1606 had to issue an order restraining the. Scotch peers from
                    wearing velvet robes in parliament, and confining them to those of scarlet cloth
                        <hi rend="italic">(Miscellany of the Maitland Club,</hi> vol. i. p. 147).
                    The robes of the Scottish peers are now, of course, similar to those of the
                    others.</p>
               <p>The peeresses’ robes at the coronation of Anne Boleyn are also described in the
                    account mentioned above. The duchess of Norfolk, the train-bearer, was followed
                    by “ ladies being lords’ wives ” in scarlet robes furred with ” lettice,” while
                    Wriothesley <hi rend="italic">(loc. cit.)</hi> adds that the duchess was also in
                    scarlet. <note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="4"> “ After
                        her followed ladies being lordes* wives, which had circotes of scarlet, with
                        narrow sleeves, the breast all lettice, with barres of pouders according to
                        their degrees, and over that they had mantles of scarlet furred, and every
                        mantle had lettice about the necke like a neckerchief, likewise poudered, so
                        that by the pouderings their degrees might be known. Then followed ladies
                        being knights’ wives in gownes of scarlet.” </note> The order of the
                    earl-marshal for the regulation of the peeresses’ robes at the coronation of
                    James II. (given in J. H. T. Perkins’s <hi rend="italic">The Coronation
                        Book,</hi> 1902, pp. 202-5) shows that by then all peeresses wore the robes
                    of state of crimson velvet, and minutely regulates all details, such as shape,
                    powderings, length of train and width of the fur edging of the mantle. They have
                    changed very little up to the present day.</p>
               <p>                    <hi rend="italic">Robes of the Orders of Knighthood.—</hi> The history of the
                    robes of the two oldest orders is given in great detail in Ashmole’s <hi
                        rend="italic">Order of the Garter</hi> (London, 1672) and Anstis’s <hi
                        rend="italic">Order of the Bath</hi> (London, 1725); see also G. F. Beltz,
                        <hi rend="italic">Memorials of lhe Order of the Garler</hi> (London, 1841),
                    p. l-lii. In each case the robes</p>
               <p>consisted of a mantle, surcoat and hood. The robes of the Garter were originally
                    of blue woollen stuff, the surcoat and hood being powdered with garters
                    embroidered in silk and gold. In the time of Henry VI. the mantle was first made
                    of velvet, and between the time of Elizabeth and of Charles I. it seems to have
                    been sometimes purple in colour. The surcoat varied in colour from year to year;
                    in the reign of the founder alone, <hi rend="italic">e.g.,</hi> it was first
                    blue, then black (possibly as a sign of mourning for the plague), then “
                    sanguine in grain.” The hood was made of the same material as the surcoat, and
                    when hats began to be worn, was carried hanging over the shouIder. The number of
                    garters embroidered on the surcoat and hood came to be fixed by rank, but after
                    Henry VI. the surcoat seems to have been made of plain velvet. Robes were
                    sometimes granted to ladies in the early days (see Beltz, p. ccxxi., for a list
                    of those ladies), in which case the robe and hood were of the colour of the
                    surcoat worn by the knights that year, and powdered with garters. The last lady
                    to receive the robes was Margaret, countess of Richmond, in 1488. At the present
                    day the mantle is of dark blue velvet, of the same colour as the rihbon, lined
                    with this taffeta, and with the star embroidered on the left shoulder, the hood
                    and surcoat of crimson velvet lined with white taffeta, and with these are worn
                    a doublet and trunk-hose of white satin and a plumed hat (see Lawrence-Archer,
                        <hi rend="italic">The Orders of Chivalry,</hi> p. 106).</p>
               <p>The robes worn by the knights of the Bath created at the coronation of Henry IV.
                    were green with furred hoods, and a white silk cord hanging from the left
                    shoulder. <note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="5"> “ Longues
                        cottes vertes a estroictes manches fourres de menever, et chapperons pareil
                        fourres de menever, en guise de prélats; et avoient les dits chevaliers sur
                        la senestre espaule un£ double cordeau de soye blanche a blanche houppettes
                        pendans ” (Froissart). </note> In the various accounts of later creations of
                    knights of the Bath quoted by Anstis, the costume worn before the ceremonial
                    bath seems to have been a priest-like garment of russet or grey, with a girdle
                    and hood; after the bath, was put on a red surcoat and mantle, the latter with a
                    lace of white silk, from which hung a pair of white gloves; and the final
                    costume was a blue (later a purple) velvet or satin gown, with hood furred with
                    miniver (later lined with sarcenet), and the white cord hanging from the
                    shoulder, until it should be removed by the sovereign or a lady for some deed of
                    valour. The mantle in the present day is of crimson velvet lined with white over
                    a white satin under-coat and trunk-hose, and a plumed hat and white boots with
                    red tops are worn. The mantle of the Thistle is of dark green velvet over
                    surcoat, &amp;c., of cloth of silver; that of St Patrick azure, with doublet
                    and trunk-hose of white satin; that of St Michael and St George of Saxon blue
                    satin lined with scarlet; and that of the Star of India of light blue satin
                    lined with white.</p>
               <p>                    <hi rend="italic">House of Commons.</hi> —The speaker of the House of Commons
                    wears on state occasions a black damask robe with gold lace and a full-bottomed
                    wig; in the House itself he wears a black silk robe with train and a
                    full-bottomed wig. The clerks at the table wear barristers’ gowns and wigs.</p>
               <p>                    <hi rend="italic">Judicial and Forensic Robes.—</hi> It is frequently stated
                    that judicial robes had their origin in the dress of ecclesiastics. But though
                    ecclesiastics in early days frequently acted as judges, and though, as Fortescue
                    says, the serjeant’s long robe was “ ad instar sacerdotis,” judicial robes more
                    probably arose from the ordinary civilian dress of the early 14th century. The
                    chief argument for the ecclesiastical origin has been found in the coif <hi
                        rend="italic">(lena, birretum album),</hi> a cap of white linen or silk,
                    tied under the chin, and described by Fortescue as “ the principal or chief
                    insignment and habit wherewith serjeants-at-law at their creation are decked,”
                    which is said to have been used by ecclesiastics to hide the tonsure when in
                    court. This view is disposed of by Pulling <hi rend="italic">(The Order of the
                        Coif,</hi> London, 1884). More probably the coif was a head-dress in common
                    use in the 13th century, which survived as the distinguishing mark of men of
                    law. <note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="6"> Mr Oswald
                        Barron, in <hi rend="italic">The Ancestor,</hi> vols. v. (p. 105) and vii.
                        (p. 108 seq., plate xii.), has given reproductions of figures from MSS.
                    </note> As such it is found in a wardrobe-roll of</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-23-r03-0410" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0437.jp2"/>
               <p>Richard II. (1391, see Fairholt, ii. 341) in an entry for “ twenty-one linen
                    coifs for counterfeiting men of the law in the king’s play at Christmas.” The
                    serjeant-at-law’s “ houve of silk ” is also mentioned in <hi rend="italic">Piers
                        the Plowman</hi> (latter half of the 14th century) <note anchored="true"
                        place="bottom" type="authorial" n="7">
                        <hi rend="italic">Prol.</hi> line 210 (ed. Skeat, Clarendon Press) : “ Jit
                        houed there an hondreth in houues of silke, seriauntz it seemed that
                        serveden atte barre”; and ni. 293: <hi rend="sup">u</hi> Shal no seriaunt
                        for here seruyse were a silk howue, Ne no pelure in his cloke, for pledîng
                        atte barre.” </note> together with his furred cloak. Chaucer, at the same
                    period, describes his serjeant-at-law as wearing a party-coloured gown and
                    girdle with bars. <note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="8">
                        <hi rend="italic">Prol..</hi> line 382 (ed. Morris, Clarendon Press) : “ He
                        rood but homely in a medlee cote Girt w ith a ceint of silk, with barres
                        smale; of his array telle I no longer tale.” </note>
               </p>
               <p>The earliest document quoted by Planché and others with reference to judges’
                    costume is a Close-roll of 20 Edw. III. (1347). See also a wardrobe-roll of 21
                    Edw. IIl., and wardrobe accounts of ii Richard II. and 22 Henry VI., all quoted
                    in Dugdale’s <hi rend="italic">Origines Juridiciales,</hi> from which we gather
                    that the robes of the judges varied in colour, in the 14th and 15th centuries,
                    from scarlet to green or <hi rend="sup">u</hi> violet in grain,” and that their
                    winter gowns were furred with budge or miniver.</p>
               <p>For the early 15th century there are more data. Firstly, there is the
                    illumination of the serjeant-at-law in the Ellesmere MS. of <hi rend="italic"
                        >The Canterbury Tales</hi> (reproduced in Fur-nivall’s 6-text edition for
                    the Chaucer Society), in which he is shown wearing a short,</p>
               <p>Îparty-coloured rayed gown of red and blue, ined with white fur, a hood and
                    tippet edged with white fur, and a white coif with two little bands showing
                    below the hood. Secondly, there are a certain number of effigies, or brasses of
                    judges and serjeants belonging to the first half of the 15th century. <note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="9"> The effigy <hi
                            rend="sup">u</hi> supposed to represent Sir Richard de Willoughby, chief
                        justice of the king’s bench ” <hi rend="italic">temp.</hi> Edw’ard III.,
                        illustrated by Fairholt, p. 201, wears a long gown with girdle and
                        skull-cap, no distinctively judicial dress. The figure of Robert Grymbald
                            <hi rend="italic">(temp.</hi> Henry 11.), engraved from his seal by
                        Dugdale, wears the ordinary dress of the time. </note> Of judges, an early
                    brass is that of SirJohn Cassy <hi rend="italic">(c.</hi> 1400) (see fig. 2)
                        <note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="10"> See also that
                        of Sir Hugh de Holes (1415; see Haines, <hi rend="italic">Brasses,</hi> i.
                        xc), and a stone effigy of Sir William Gascoigne in Harwood Church, Yorks
                        (d. 1419, see Planché, <hi rend="italic">Cyclopaedia,</hi> i. 427). Of
                        serjeants-at-law, an early example is the brass of Nichol Rolond at Copie,
                        Beds. <hi rend="italic">(c.</hi> 1410, see Druitt, <hi rend="italic">Costume
                            in Brasses,</hi> p. 221); also that of Thomas Rolf at Gosfield, Essex
                            <hi rend="italic">(c.</hi> 1440, see Haines, p. 85), who wears a gown,
                        tabard, tippet, hood and coif, with two bands showing below the hood, like
                        the Ellesmere MS. figure. The inscription calls Rolf “ Iegi professus,”
                        which Haines takes to mean <hi rend="sup">u</hi> professor of law,” Boutell
                        and Clark <hi rend="italic">(Archaeological Journal,</hi> vol. i. pp. 203-4)
                        consider that he. is a serjeant-at-law. Druitt (p. 224) remarks on the
                        likeness of his tabard to that of a Master of Arts, but compares a figure on
                        a 15th-century cope, who also appears to be a serjeant-at-law and wears a
                        tabard. That a tabard sometimes formed part of the dress of a serjeant, can
                        be seen in the extract from the <hi rend="italic">Liber famelicus</hi> of
                        Sir James Whitelocke, quoted by Druitt, p. 225, footnote. </note>
               </p>
               <p>for the second naif of the 15th century the authority is Chief-Justice
                    Fortescue, who, writing in the reign of Henry VI., describes the dress of the
                    serjeant-at-law as follows:— “ Roba longa ad instar sacerdotis cum capicio
                    penulato circa humeros ejus, et desuper collo-bium, cum duobus labellulis,
                    qualiter uti solent doctores legum in Universitatibus quibusdam, cum supra
                    descripto birreto vestiebatur.” “ Hq was clothed in a long robe, after the
                    fashion of a priest, with a furred cape about his shoulders, and above it a
                    hood, with two bands, such as are used by doctors of laws in some universities,
                    with the coif as described above ” <hi rend="italic">(De Laudibus Legum Angliae <hi rend="sub">f</hi></hi> cap. Ii.). Fortescuecontinues: “ But being once made a justice, instead of
                    his hood, he shall wear a cloak closed upon his right shoulder, all the other
                    ornaments of a serjeant still remaining; saving that a justice shall wear no
                    party-coloured vesture, as a serjeant may, and his cape is furred with miniver,
                    whereas</p>
               <p>the serjeant’s cape is furred with white lamb (budge).”</p>
               <p>This description of Fortescue’s is borne out by some illuminations from a
                    15th-century MS. representing sittings of the four superior courts in the time
                    of Henry VI. (reproduced <hi rend="italic">in Archaeologia <hi rend="sub">f</hi></hi> vol. xxxix. p. 358, &amp;c., with an article by G. R. Corner; see
                    plate), ln them we see the scarlet robes of the judges furred with mimver, and
                    the party-coloured rayed gowns, tippets and hoods of the serjeants, besides the
                    costume of the minor officials of the court. Both serjeants and judges wear the
                    coif, certain of the judges also wearing furred caps or turban-like
                    head-dresses. The colour of the serjeants’ party-coloured robes seems to have
                    varied; <note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="11"> They were
                        probably originally liveries; see G. R. Corner in <hi rend="italic"
                            >Archaeologia,</hi> also Pulling, <hi rend="italic">op. cit.</hi> pp.
                        211-12. </note> in these illuminations they are blue and green, but by the
                    17th century, to quote Dugdale, <hi rend="italic">Origines Juridiciales <hi
                            rend="sub"> f</hi></hi> cap. 38: “The.robes they now use do still somewhat resemble those of the
                    justices of either bench, and are of three distinct colours, viz. murrey, black,
                    furred with white, and scarlet ; but the robe which they usually wear at their
                    creation only is of two colours, viz. murrey and mouse colour; whereunto they
                    have a hood suitable, as also a coif of white silk or linen.” (See also Pulling,
                    p. 218, and Drujtt, p. 225.) Sir E. Brabrook <hi rend="italic">(Proceedings of
                        the Soc. of Antiquaries <hi rend="sub">f</hi></hi> 2nd series, vol. ui. p. 414) quotes descriptions of calls of serjeants
                    showing that as late as 1700 the serjeants wore party-coloured gowns at their
                    creation and during the year following, and stating on what occasions they wore
                    their black, scarlet or purple gowns (the last with scarlet or purple hoods). At
                    the last general call (1736), and at the creation of a serjeant in 1762,
                    party-coloured robes were still worn, but at a creation of 1809 they are no
                    longer found.. Until their final abolition the serjeants wore purple robes at
                    their creation, and on ordinary occasions a black cloth or silk gown, with a
                    scarlet robe for state occasions.</p>
               <p>of the 13th and 14th century, showing the coif worn by both clerks and laymen.</p>
               <p>Illustrations of judicial costumes in the 16th century are to be found in vol.
                    1. of <hi rend="italic">Vetusta Monumenta</hi> (Soc. of Antiquaries, 1747), in
                    which are reproduced, firstly, a *' painted table in the King’s Exchequer,” <hi
                        rend="italic">temp.</hi> Henry Vll., on which the officials of the Exchequer
                    are shown wearing long gowns, furred tippets and mantles, with coifs (see fig·
                    3)ï <hi rend="sup">an</hi> d secondly, a sitting of the Court of Wards and
                    Liveries, <hi rend="italic">temp.</hi> Elizabeth, in which are shown serjeants
                    wearing party-coloured gowns, tippets, hoods and coifs (see also Pulling, facing
                    pp. 86 and 214).</p>
               <p>About this time the square cap, otherwise known as the cornered, black or
                    sentence cap (the last from the fact of its being put on by. the judge when
                    pronouncing sentence of death), begins to be seen in monuments (cf. that of Sir
                    Richard Harpur, <hi rend="italic">temp.</hi> Mary; Fairhold, p. 223). Sometimes
                    this cap is worn over the coif only, sometimes over the coif and skull-cap (cf.
                    the portrait of Sir Edward Coke, in Pulling, facing p. 180). Theform also
                    varies; sometimes, as in the portrait of Coke, it has no ear-flaps, some times,
                    as in its present form, it, has. The form with ear-flaps is held by some to be a
                    combination of the square cap and skull-cap. The square cap was a mark of
                    dignity, worn or carried on solemn occasions, hence its use when pronouncing
                    sentence of death, to mark the solemnity of the moment.</p>
               <p>Among the State Papers of 1625 is a " Discourse on what robes and apparel the
                    judges are to wear, and how the serjeants-at-law are to wear their robes, and
                    when,” and on the 4th of July 1635 there was a “ solemn decree and rule made by
                    all the judges of the courts at Westminster,” which is quoted in Dugdale <hi
                        rend="italic">(loc. cit.)</hi> and Pulling (p. 215, footnote).</p>
               <p>This costume is illustrated in Hollar’s engraving of the coronation procession
                    of Charles II. Towards the end of the 17th century the judges took to wearing
                    wigs, and have continued to wear them ever since. The wearing of wigs naturally
                    concealed the coif and velvet skull-cap, so a device had to be invented by which
                    they could still be displayed. The expedient was hit upon of putting a round
                    patch of white stuff, with a black spot in the middle of it, on the crown of the
                    wig of certain of the judges, to represent the coif and skull-cap. The rank of
                    serjeant no longer existing, this round patch has now disappeared, the only
                    trace of it left being the circular depression on the crown of the wig.</p>
               <p>The costume of judges of the High Court at the present day differs very little
                    from that given in the order of 1635; but the cap is carried in the hand as a
                    part of the full dress, and only worn when a judge is
                    passing sentence of death. <note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                        n="12"> See an essay by Sir Herbert Stephen in <hi rend="italic">Unuiritten
                            Lauis and Ideals,</hi> ed. E. H. Pitcairn (Smith, Elder, 1899), from
                        which the following paragraph is largely condensed. </note> The</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-23-r03-0411" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0440.jp2"/>
               <p>dress worn when trying criminal cases, attending church officially, and on “ red
                    letter days ” in the courts, consists of a scarlet gown, with a broad black
                    belt, a tippet trimmed with white fur, known by courtesy as “ ermine ” (this is
                    worn only on state occasions), and a scarlet casting-hood, always worn with the
                    scarlet gown, the end of which is passed under the belt. For summer the robes
                    are of thinner stuff, faced with slate-coloured silk instead of ermine. The
                    full-bottomed wig is worn on state occasions; at other times a wig is worn
                    similar to that of barristers, except that it has one vertical curl just above
                    the tail of the wig instead of the three rows of horizontal curls going all the
                    way round.</p>
               <p>The judges of the King’s Bench Division have also a black gown, trimmed with
                    ermine, which may be worn with the scarlet casting-hood when they sit two or
                    more together. The summer equivalent of the black robes is in thin blue stuff,
                    faced with silk. A costume like that of King’s Counsel, namely, a black silk
                    gown, with black cloth court suit, is the dress of judges when sitting alone to
                    try civil actions, and of vice-chancellors and judges of the Chancery Division,
                    but Sir Herbert Stephen remarks that of late years certain of the judges have
                    preferred on grounds of comfort the black or blue gown with scarlet
                    casting-hood. The court dress of the judges of the High Court and of Indian and
                    colonial judges consists of a black damask tufted gown, without train, worn over
                    a black velvet court suit, with full-bottomed wig, lace bands and three-cornered
                    silk hat. <note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="13"> Minute
                        details of court and levée dress, judicial and legal, will be found in <hi
                            rend="italic">Dress worn at Court</hi> (pp. 60-61), issued with the
                        authority of the Lord Chamberlain, and ed. H. A. P. Trendell, of the Lord
                        ChamberlainSdepartmcnt (London, 1908),—also details of mourning costume.
                    </note>
               </p>
               <p>The Lord Chancellor, when in the House of Lords, and sitting on Appeals, wears a
                    black silk trained gown, over a black cloth court suit, with full-bottomed wig;
                    he has also his peer’s robe (see above), and his state robe of black damask with
                    gold lace, worn over a velvet court suit, with full-bottomed wig, lace bands,
                    &amp;c.; the purse is carried on state occasions when in the royal presence.
                    The state robe of the Master of the Rolls, the Lords Justices of the Court of
                    Appeal, and the President of the Probate, Divorce and Admiralty Divisions is the
                    same, except that they have not the purse, and similar to it is the full-dress
                    gown of the Speaker of the House of Commons, the Chancellor of the Exchequer,
                    &amp;c. The Lords Justices of the Court of Appeal sit in court in a costume
                    similar to that of King’s Counsel.</p>
               <p>The Lords of Appeal have no official robes, but sit in ordinary civilian dress.
                    On state occasions they wear their peers’ robes. The robes of state of the Lord
                    Chief Justice of England are the same as those of the judges of the High Court,
                    except that his are trained, and he wears the gold chain of office, the “ collar
                    of SS.”</p>
               <p>The Scottish judges have two sets of robes, one for Justiciary (f.e. the
                    criminal court), which is also their full dress, and one for civil causes (Court
                    of Session). The dress for the President and Ordinary Lords of Session was fixed
                    in 1610 by an order of James I., and was of purple cloth, faced with crimson
                    satin, with hood to match, the President’s gown having crimson velvet instead of
                    satin. The four “ extraordinary Sessionarics ” were to wear black velvet, satin,
                    or silk gowns, lined with black. The Lord Justice General wore a scarlet gown
                    lined with ermine and an ermine hood, the Lord Justice Deputy and Lord Justice
                    Clerk black gowns with crimson satin facings and hoods (see <hi rend="italic"
                        >Register of the Privy Council of Scotland,</hi> vol. viii. p. 612). At the
                    foundation of the High Court of Justiciary (1672) it was enacted “ that for the
                    splendour of that court, all the judges sit in red robes, faced with white, that
                    of the Justice Generalls being lined with ermine for distinction from the rest ”
                    (see <hi rend="italic">Acts of Parliament of Scotland,</hi> vol. viii. p. 88).
                    The present full dress of the Lord Justice General is a scarlet silk robe with
                    tippet and hood, the hood falling down the back; the collar is of ermine, with
                    which the tippet, sleeves and gown are edged and the hood lined. The Lord
                    Justice Clerk wears a scarlet cloth robe and hood, and a white silk tippet lined
                    with scarlet, the silk being perforated with small holes to imitate ermine, as
                    also on the sleeves and edges of the gown. In front of the tippet on each side
                    are two crosses in scarlet silk, and on each side of the gown six crosses. The
                    ordinary Lords Commissioners of Justiciary have robes the same as those of the
                    Lord Justice Clerk, except that the satin is not perforated. Instead of the
                    bands worn by English judges, the Scottish judges wear a long fall in front.</p>
               <p>                    <hi rend="italic">The Bar.—</hi> There appears to have been no official costume
                    for the bar until the end of the 17th century. Druitt <hi rend="italic">(Costume
                        in Brasses,</hi> pp. 232-33) gives a Ust of several brasses of <hi
                        rend="italic">in lege periti,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Qpprenticii ad
                        legem,</hi> most of whom wear ordinary civilian costume, occasionally with
                    the addition of a high cap. In the 16th and 17th centuries they wear the
                    false-sleeved gown worn by civilians. Before the 17th century the costume worn
                    by students at the Inns of Court and by “ Utter Barristers ” consisted of a
                    stuff gown, and sometimes, in term-time, a round cap, which was worn in hall and
                    in church (see Herbert, <hi rend="italic">History of the Inns of Court</hi>
                    (1804), p. 230). In Westminster Hall (see Pulling, p. 223) the same costume was
                    worn, Benchers and Readers having a more elaborate gown with facings of black
                    velvet and tufts of silk. Frequent laws were passed in the 16th century and
                    later, forbidding the wearing of swords, cloaks, boots and spurs, &amp;c.,
                    in hall, and insisting on the wearing of gowns by students of the Inns of Court
                    when walking in the city. In the 17th century, barristers, like the judges,
                    adopted wigs, the full-bottomed wigs being confined to judges, “ King’s
                    Counsellors,” &amp;c., and ordinary counsellors wearing small wigs. In
                    Hollar’s engraving of the coronation of Charles H. the King’s Counsel, the
                    King’s Attorney and Solicitor, and the Master of the Rolls wear a lacêd gown with
                    hanging sleeves. The silk gown, fuU-bottomed wig and black court dress now worn
                    by King’s Counsel is generally held to date from the funeral of Queen Mary II.,
                    being the mourning dress worn by the wish of King William for a considerable
                    period after the queen’s death, and adopted as a convenient costume ever since.
                    There is a well-known jest of Chief Baron Pollock to the effect that “ the Bar
                    went into mourning at the death of Queen Anne, and never came out again,” which
                    bears out this theory as to the origin of the costume. At the present time
                    barristers wear black stuff gowns, with small wigs having three rows of curls
                    round the head. King’s Counsel wear black silk gowns over a cloth court suit
                    (cp. the expression “ to take silk,” <hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi> to become a
                    K.C.); on fuU-dress occasions they wear a full-bottomed wig, and at court a
                    black damask tufted gown over a velvet court suit. This is also the dress for
                    state occasions of the Attorney-General, Solicitor-General, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>                    <hi rend="italic">Municipal and Civic Robes.—</hi> The word “ livery,” the use
                    of which is now practically confined to the costume of the “ livery companies,”
                    the dress of men-servants, &amp;c., originally meant an allowance of food or
                    clothing granted to certain persons <hi rend="italic">(LaXJiberata,</hi> Fr. <hi
                        rend="italic">livrée).</hi> It is still used of the allowances of food made
                    to the fellows of certain colleges. As early as the 13th century, according to
                    Matt. Paris <hi rend="italic">(Chron. Maj.,</hi> Rolls Series, III. 337), we
                    find the citizens of London assuming a uniform dress to do honour to some great
                    occasion, as, <hi rend="italic">e.g.,</hi> when in 1236 a body of them rode out
                    to meet Henry III. and Queen Eleanor, “ sericis Vestimentis ornati, cicladibus
                    auro textis circumdati, excogitatis mutatoriis amicti,” or when 600 citizens
                    rode out to meet Queen Marghrct, wife of Edward I., “ in one livery of red and
                    white, with the cognizances of their misteries embroidered upon their sleeves ”
                    (see Stow’s <hi rend="italic">Survey,</hi> ed. Morley, p. 444). By the 14th
                    century there is evidence of the adoption of liveries by the trades and
                    fraternities. At the celebrations of the birth of Edward III. (see Riley’s <hi
                        rend="italic">Memorials,</hi> p. 105) the mayor and aldermen were “ richly
                    arrayed in suits of robes,” while the drapers, mercers and vintners were also “
                    in costume.” This need not, howcver, refer to Uvcries. G. Unwin <hi
                        rend="italic">(The Gilds of London,</hi> 1908) quotes a chronicler who
                    records that by the year 1319 “ many of the people</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-23-r03-0412" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0441.jp2"/>
               <p>of'the trades of London were arrayed in livery,” and an ordinance of 1347 of the
                    fraternity of the Mercers commanding that “ all those of the said mistery shall
                    be clothed of one suit once a year at the feast of Easter,” and Riley <hi
                        rend="italic">(op. cit.</hi> p. 516) quotes an order of 1389 allowing the
                    sheriffs, on grounds of expense, to proceed to Westminster by boat instead of on
                    horseback, “ without there being any arraying of men of the trades in like suit
                    for that purpose; except that such men of the trades as should wish to accompany
                    them should walk in such suit of vestments of the livery of their respective
                    trade as they might then have. ” As to the liveries of the religious
                    fraternities, Chaucer <hi rend="italic">(Prol.</hi> 361) describes:—</p>
               <p>“ An Haberdasher and a Carpenter A Webbe <hi rend="sub">t</hi> a Dyere, and a
                    Tapicer, ”</p>
               <p>As, <hi rend="sup">u</hi> clothed alle in a Hveree</p>
               <p>Of a solempne and greet fraternitee.”</p>
               <p>In 1389 there was a petition against the giving of liveries by the fraternities,
                    on the ground that these gatherings were centres of political agitation, but in
                    the statutes of Edward III. and Richard II. against liveries members of guilds
                    were expressly excepted from these prohibitions. However, it was doubtless
                    deemed prudent to make sure of the privilege, and so, when the livery companies
                    were incorporated, they took care to have their Everies authorized by their
                    charters.</p>
               <p>These Everies consisted of a gown and hood, though the hood only was sometimes
                    given; thus the Grocers’ Company had in 1430 55 members in the fuU Every, 17 in
                    hoods and 42 not in Every. It was also customary for such of the companies as
                    wished it to present Everies to outsiders, for instance, to the mayor, should he
                    belong to another company. Thus in 1399 the Tailors gave liveries to the king,
                    the prince and the mayor, and hoods to the sheriffs., But in 1415 and 1423 the
                    mayor and aldermen were forbidden to receive any Every except that of their own
                    company. A similar custom was that by which a member of any company might send
                    to thé mayor a certain sum, receiving in return a suit of the livery of the
                    mayor’s company. The colours of the various Everies varied very much from time
                    to time. Thus in 1414 the Grocers wore liveries of scarlet and green, which were
                    changed in 1418 to scarlet and black, in 1428 to scarlet and blue and in 1450 to
                    “violet in grain,” with party-coloured hoods of violet and crimson. At first
                    both gowns and hoods were party-coloured, but later a party-coloured hood was
                    worn with a gown of one colour. The gowns were also lined and edged with fur. An
                    early illustration of the Everies is to be found on the first charter of the
                    Leathersellers’ Company, granted them in 1444 by Henry VI., where the members of
                    the company are depicted kneeling before the king in short party-coloured gowns
                    of red and blue, edged at the neck, wrists and round the bottom with fur and
                    with white girdles (see fig. 4, Jrom a coloured reproduction in W. H.</p>
               <p>Black’s <hi rend="italic">History</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Antiquities of the
                        Leathersellers' Cof.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the reign of Henry VIII., Holbein’s picture of the king giving a charter to
                    the Barber-Surgeons’ Company shows the members of the latter wearing gowns of
                    rich stuff, with red and black party-coloured hoods, three of the figures also
                    in coifs. The form of gown which has survived, practically unchanged, till the
                    present day, may be seen on the second charter of the Leathersellers’ Company,
                    granted them by James I. in 1604 (see fig. 5, and for coloured plate see W. H.
                    Black, <hi rend="italic">op. citf.</hi> Here we see them in flat caps, long
                    black furred gowns, with false sleeves, and having on the right shoulder
                    party-coloured hoods of scarlet and black, the end of which is cast over the
                    left shoulder and hangs down nearly to the edge of the gown.</p>
               <p>Besides the liveries of the city companies, and those of the mayor and sheriffs,
                    there was often a special livery adopted by all the citizens on some great</p>
               <p>occasion, such as a visit of</p>
               <p>the sovereign to the City.</p>
               <p>W. St John Hope (Cor-</p>
               <p>                    <hi rend="italic">poration Plate and in</hi>
               </p>
               <p>                    <hi rend="italic">signias</hi> ii. 141 ) quotes a</p>
               <p>number of such cases,</p>
               <p>showing that the city</p>
               <p>livery was sometimes</p>
               <p>green, sometimes blue,</p>
               <p>sometimes violet, some</p>
               <p>times red and white,</p>
               <p>the city colours <hi rend="italic">par excellence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As to the costume of the mayor, aldermen, sheriffs, &amp;c., we have seen
                    above the mayor “ richly costumed,” and the aldermen “ in like suits of robes,”
                    at the birth of Edward III., and Riley <hi rend="italic">(op. citf</hi> gives an
                    order of 1378, that the aldermen are to ride to Westminster in the mayor’s
                    procession, <hi rend="sup">u</hi> arrayed in a cloak and hood at least, that are
                    party-coloured with red, scarlet and white, the red on the right side <hi
                        rend="sup">6</hi> ; while he quotes (from Letter-book H. fol. cxlvi) the
                    amusing sentence passed by his fellow-aldermen in 1382 on one John Seley, for
                    disregarding the order to have his green cloak for the Whitsuntide procession
                    lined with green taffeta. Thus before the 15th century the aldermen apparently
                    had not yet their scarlet robes, but on state occasions wore the ordinary city
                    livery. For the early 15th century we have the <hi rend="italic">Liber
                        Albus</hi> (written <hi rend="italic">C.</hi> 1419; Rolls Scries, ed.
                    Riley), where we are told (p. 35) that “ The Mayor, Sheriff and Aldermen were
                    wont to array themselves in like suits of robes twice in the year, viz. when the
                    mayor rode to Westminster to take the oath, and on the day following the feast
                    of SS. Simon and Jude; and this raiment was trimmed with fur as befitting their
                    honourable rank; and they would also dress themselves in suits of robes against
                    the feast of Pentecost, these robes having a lining of silk.” The scarlet,
                    violet and black robes, still worn by the Lord Mayor, aldermen, &amp;c.,
                    were early in use. There is an order of 1421 (8
                    HenryV.)thatthealdermensnoulduse“ togiset armilausis de scarleto,” and in
                    numerous accounts of royal receptions and other solemn occasions in the City we
                    are told that the mayor and aldermen were jn scarlet (W. St John Hope, in <hi
                        rend="italic">Corporation Plate and Insignia,</hi> i., Introd. lxxxv seq.,
                    and ii. 138-147, quotes a number of these, and treats the whole subject of
                    mayors’, &amp;c., robes very fully). <hi rend="italic"><hi rend="sup">
                            r</hi> The Liber Albus</hi> (i. i,ch. vi.) also shows us the mayor and
                    aldermen assembled at the Guildhall on the day of the election of the new mayor
                        <hi rend="italic">induti togis de violet.</hi> As to the form of the dress
                    in the 14th and 15th century, we can see from brasses of lord mayors and
                    aldermen (see Haines, <hi rend="italic">Manual,</hi> pp. cc-cci ; and Cotman,
                        <hi rend="italic">Norfolk Brasses.</hi> There is a fine series of brasses of
                    mayors, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.,</hi> at Norwich) that it consisted of a
                    long gown, a mantle fastened on the right shoulder and a hood.</p>
               <p>As Jo the provincial mayors and aldermen there is evidence that at quite an
                    early date many of them followed the fashion of London ; <hi rend="italic"
                        >e.g.</hi> the Royal Charter of Nottingham, of 1448, contains the words: “
                    that the Aldermen of the same town forever . . . may use gowns, hoods and cloaks
                    of one suit and one livery together with furs and linings suitable to these
                    cloaks, in the same manner and form as the Mayor and Aldermen of our city of
                    London do use, the Statute of Liveries . . . notwithstanding ” (see <hi
                        rend="italic">Nottingham Records,</hi> ii. 205), while the charter granted
                    by Henry VI. to Kingston-on-Hull in 1440 contains practically the same words
                    (see St J. Hope, i. Ixxxvi). The costume of provincial mayors, &amp;c., is
                    shown by St John Hope <hi rend="italic">(loc. citf.</hi> to have generally
                    consisted of a scarlet furred gown and cloak, with tippet or scarf of black
                    velvet. The colour was not, however, invariably scarlet, but varied to violet,
                    blue and black, sometimes even for the mayor. An account of the robes of modern
                    provincial mayors,will be found in St J. Hope, p. Ixxxix seq. and under the
                    accounts of the various boroughs, <hi rend="italic">passim.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is some doubt as to when the Lord Mayor first began to wear his robe of
                    estate of crimson velvet. Stow <hi rend="italic">(Survey,</hi> ed. Strype, 1720,
                    ii. ι6β) says that at the reception of Henry VI. at Eltham the
                    InayorwasincrimsonvelvetZthealdermeninscarIetwith <hi rend="sup">u</hi> sanguine
                    ” hoods, but at the coronation of Edward V. (see St J. Hope) he wore scarlet. At
                    the coronation of Anne Boleyn (see Wriothesley's <hi rend="italic">Chronicle,
                        loc. cit. supr.,</hi> and Hall’s <hi rend="italic">Chronicle}</hi> the mayor
                    wore his crimson velvet robe of state, the aldermen and sheriffs scarlet; and at
                    the entry of Anne of Cleves into London the mayor was again in his crimson
                    velvet robe with his collar of gold, the aldermen and councilmen in robes of
                    black velvet with chains of gold (but see</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-23-r03-0413" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0444.jp2"/>
               <p>St J. Hope, ii. 144, who quotes the order for these same robes, from which it
                    would appear that the mayor also wore black velvet).</p>
               <p>About this period begin to occur notices of the wearing of official robes by the
                    wives of mayors and aldermen ; <hi rend="italic">eg.</hi> for Lincoln there is
                    an entry in the corporation records in 1544: “ Evciy alderman that hath not been
                    mayor to prepare for himself and his wife gowns of crimson, and every one that
                    hath been mayor to prepare for himself and his wife gowns of scarlet and tippets
                    of velvet to be worn at all principal feasts” (scciath report,Ήπ/. MSS. <hi
                        rend="italic">Commiss..</hi> App.VlII). St John Hope (p. lxxxix) quotes
                    numerous instances in the 16th century, in some of which the husband was liable
                    to a heavy fine in the event of his wife’s non-compliance with the rule.</p>
               <p>In 1568 (see Stow, and J. G. Nichols, <hi rend="italic">Account of 55 Royal
                        Processions and Entertainments,</hi> pt. ii. p. 94) first appeared an “
                    Order observed by my Lord Mayor, Aldermen and Sheriffs, for their meetings and
                    ,wearing the apparel throughout the whole year, according as formerly it hath
                    been used,” which has been altered and revised from time to time by order of the
                    Corporation, and is still issued under the name of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Handbook of Ceremonials</hi> to the officers of the City Corporation. In
                    1568 we find the aldermen and sheriffs going to Westminster in the Lord Mayor’s
                    procession in scarlet-furred gowms “ and their cloaks borne with them,” and in
                    1575 Nichols auotes a London citizen’s description of the same procession; “they
                    of the livery in their long gowns, with hood on the left shoulder, half black
                    and half red. . . . The Mayor in a long gown of scarlet, and on his left
                    shoulder a hood of black velvet, and a collar of SS. . ... The Aldermen in
                    scarlet gowns, those having been mayors with chains of gold, the others with
                    black velvet tippets.” The Order of 1629 gives particulars of the various gowns;
                    the cloaks are violet from Michaelmas to Whitsuntide, furred, for mayors and
                    ex-mayors, with “ amys,” for aldermen with “ calabre,” and scarlet in summer,
                    lined with “ changeable taffety ” andgreen taffety ” respectively.</p>
               <p>After the 16th Centun <hi rend="sup">r</hi> the costume of the Lord Mayor can be
                    studied in successive “ Orders ” or Ceremonial Books, accounts of coronations,
                    &amp;c., and in portraits and statues belonging to the various city
                    companies. Early in the 19th century (1806) the Lord Mayor began to wear on some
                    state occasions a black robe with gold lace, similar to that of the Lord
                    Chancellor. The Ceremonial Book was thoroughly revised in 1864, and the latest
                    edition is that issued in 1906 <hi rend="italic">(Handbook of Ceremonials,</hi>
                    &amp;c., “ issued under the direction and with the approval of the
                    Privileges Committee of the Court of Aldermen ”).</p>
               <p>At the present day the Lord Mayor has several sets of robes; a special
                    coronation robe (see illustration in Naylor, <hi rend="italic">Book of the
                        Coronation of George IV.,</hi> 1837), a crimson velvet robe of state like
                    that of an earl, worn with the chain and jewel, <hi rend="italic">e.g.</hi> in
                    the presence of the sovereign when in the city; <note anchored="true"
                        place="bottom" type="authorial" n="14"> Sir G. G. Young in a pamphlet called
                            <hi rend="italic">The Place of the Lord Mayor in proceeding through or
                            within the City of London</hi> (1852), quotes various royal visits to
                        the city which seem to show that the Lord Mayor did not always wear his
                        crimson velvet robe on these occasions. Thus in 1638 Charles I., on going to
                        meet Marie de Médicis, was met by the Lord Mayor in scarlet, which was also
                        worn at the entry of Charles II. in 1660. In 1702, when Queen Anne went to a
                        thanksgiving service at St Paul’s, -the Lord Mayor wore crimson velvet, with
                        the collar and jewel; but in 1705, at the thanksgiving after Blenheim, he
                        met the queen on horseback, dressed in scarlet. In 1714, at the reception of
                        George I., the Lord Mayor wore crimson velvet robes. </note> a black robe of
                    state trimmed with gold, which is worn with the chain and jewel, <hi
                        rend="italic">e.g,</hi> at the GuiIdhall on Lord Mayor’s Day; the scarlet
                    robes, which are worn, with or without the chain, on most public occasions, such
                    as the service at St Paul’s on the first day of the Easter Law Term, audiences
                    of the sovereign, the election of the Lord Mayor, the opening of the Central
                    Criminal Court, &amp;c.; a violet gown, which is worn, <hi rend="italic"
                        >e.g.,</hi> when the Lord Mayor elect is presented to the king, when he is
                    sworn in, at the election of sheriffs, &amp;c., and a black gown worn in
                    church on Good Friday, &amp;e. The aldermen wear scarlet on most occasions
                    of ceremony, ex-mayors “ having the Cap of Dignity attached to their gown, and
                    being entitled to introduce a sword and mace into their badges.” Violet robes
                    are also worn on certain occasions marked in the almanac of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Alder· man’s Pocket-Book',</hi> and black gowns when the Lord
                    Mayor wears his. The sheriffs and recorders <note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial" n="15"> The recorders had from an early date annual suits
                        of robes like ' the mayor, aldermen, &amp;c. See <hi rend="italic">Liber
                            Atbus,</hi> p. 43: “ Habet itaqueRecordator pro feodo de Camera totiens
                        et talem vesturam Hneatam sive penulatum, quotiens et gualcm Major et
                        Aldcrmanni capiunt annuatim.” The chamberlain,. common serjeant, &amp;c.,
                        had also gowns (see an order of 1523 in St J. Hope, ii. 146). For the
                        sword-bearer’s cap of maintenance see article Cap and St John Hope i.
                        lxxvi-lxxix. For mayor’s and sheriff’s chains see ibid, pp. Ixxix-Ixxxiv.
                    </note> have scarlet, violet and black gowns, and the members of the common
                    council bave deep mazarine blue gowns, which seem to have been first prescribed
                    in 1761.</p>
               <p>For Scotland an order of James I. and VI. of 1610 (sec <hi rend="italic"
                        >Register of Privy Council, Ioc. cit.)</hi> ordered that the provosts,
                    aldermen, &amp;c., of every borough should wear, for ordinary occasions,
                    black furred gowns, the officers of the chief boroughs having also scarlet
                    furred gowns for Sundays and other solemn occasions, when the provost of
                    Edinburgh was to wear a gold chain.</p>
               <p>                    <hi rend="italic">Academic Costume.</hi> —No thorough study has so far been made
                    of early English academic costume as compared with that of the continental
                    univcrsitics”-a study which ought to throw much light on the subject. <note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="16"> Practically the only
                        detailed study of early English academic costume is a paper on “ English
                        Academic Costume (Medieval),” by Dr E. C. Clark, in <hi rend="italic"
                            >Archaeolog. Journal,</hi> vol. 1. pp. 74 seq., 137 sea. and 183 seq.,
                        which contains a mass of information, and upon which the present article is
                        to a great extent based. Rashdall ( <hi rend="italic">Universities of Europe
                            in the Middle Ages,</hi> vol. ii. pt. Ü.) and Druitt <hi rend="italic"
                            >(Costume on Brasses,</hi> ch. ii.) each devote a chapter to the
                        subject; Rashdall treats of both the English and continental universities,
                        not very thoroughly, Druitt of English academic dress only, but thoroughly.
                        Clark gives many facts about foreign, as well as the English, costume.
                    </note> A vexed question is that of how far academic dress is derived from the
                    ecclesiastical. Anthony Wood’s view, that it was derived from the <hi
                        rend="italic">tunica talaris</hi> and <hi rend="italic">cucullus</hi> of the
                    Benedictines, would not now meet with much support; but many writers seem to be
                    unnecessarily anxious to trace each item of the academic robes to some definite
                    ecclesiastical garment. The medieval scholar was of course a clerk, and had to
                    wear the clerkly gown and the tonsure. But the fact that this was the case makes
                    it more difficult to distinguish between academical and ecclesiastical robes,
                    notably in the case of brasses and other monuments of university graduates and
                    dignitaries who were also priests. Another source of difficulty is the variety
                    of names by which the different parts of the academic costume are called in the
                    university statutes and elsewhere, resulting sometimes in inextricable
                    confusion.</p>
               <p>The earliest information as to English academic dress is found in the second
                    half of the 14th century. Certain early statutes show that “ excess in apparel ”
                    had already to be rebuked in scholars (cf. the Constitution of Archbishop
                    Stratford, 1342), while the statutes of certain colleges require of the scholars
                    the tonsure and a “ decent habit ” suitable to a clerk (cf. Statutes of
                    Peterhouse, 1344, and of Merton ColI., Oxford), <hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi> a
                    long gown <hi rend="italic">(toga</hi> or <hi rend="italic">tunica
                        talaris),</hi> which it is stipulated in some cases must be closed in front.
                    Some colleges had liveries, prescribed perhaps by the founder of the college and
                    laid down by the statutes. The differences of colour and shape in the
                    undergraduate gowns of most of the Cambridge colleges are supposed to be a
                    survival of this. There was also an ordinance of Richard II. for King’s Hall,
                    Cambridge (1379), which fixed the dress of a scholar as the <hi rend="italic"
                        >roba talaris,</hi> over which, if a bachelor, he should wear a tabard
                    suited to his degree. The undergraduates seem in the early days to have worn a
                    hood, the ordinary head-covering worn by all, but they gradually ceased to do
                    so, until nobody below the rank of a bachelor might wear one.</p>
               <p>It is proposed to give here (1) a list of the various parts of the academic
                    dress, with a few remarks on each; (2) a short account of the early costume of
                    the various degrees; (3) a sketch of any changes which have taken place since
                    the Reformation.</p>
               <p>The <hi rend="smallcaps">Gown</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">(toga, roba,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">tunica talaris)</hi>
                    was worn by all degrees, as befitting clerks. It is hard to determine whether
                    there was at first any difference between the gown of the higher degrees, which
                    some maintain was the <hi rend="italic">roba,</hi> and that of the lower
                    degrees, the <hi rend="italic">toga</hi> or <hi rend="italic">tunica
                        talaris,</hi> but it seems improbable. It was frequently fur-lined, but the
                    use of the more costly furs was forbidden to all below the degree of Master,
                    except sons of noblemen, or those possessing a certain income, bachelors using
                    budge (see in Anstey’s <hi rend="italic">Munirnenta Acadernica,</hi> p. 301, the</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-23-r03-0414" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0445.jp2"/>
               <p>Statute of 1432 <hi rend="italic">de Odmissione ad pelluram).</hi> Students, and
                    even doctors in theology <hi rend="italic">(Mun. Acad.</hi> ü. 393), were also
                    restricted to budge, and to sad-coloured habits. The robes of masters were to be
                    flowing and reach to the ankles (see <hi rend="italic">Mun. Acad.</hi> p. 212,
                    an order of 1358 to the tailors not to stint the robes, which should be “ <hi
                        rend="italic">largae et Ialaresf <hi rend="sup">i</hi></hi> because clerks should be distinguished from the laity).</p>
               <p>The Cope, worn as part of academic dress over the gown, probably originated in
                    the ordinary <hi rend="italic">cappa clericalis,</hi> or everyday mantle of the
                    clergy, which had been introduced into general use in England by synods of 1222,
                    1237 and 1268. <note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="17"> See
                        Rev. T. A. Lacey in <hi rend="italic">Transactions of the St Paul’s
                            Ecclesio-logical Society,</hi> vol. iv. (1900), p. 128, &amp;c. Also
                        Rev. N. F. Robinson in the same (1898), pp. 181-220. </note> This kind of
                    cope, closed in front, and originally black in colour, is generally known as the
                        <hi rend="italic">cappa clausa,</hi> and sometimes, for convenience’ sake,
                    had a slit in front to allow of the passage of the hands. It was worn by Regent
                    Masters when lecturing</p>
               <p>                    <hi rend="italic">{Mun. Acad.</hi> p. 421) and as a full dress by certain
                    doctors. By the second half of the 14th century differences of colour occur; <hi
                        rend="italic">e.g.</hi> the Chancellor represented in a 14th-century
                    miniature in the Oxford <hi rend="italic">Chancellors Book</hi> (reproduced by
                    J. W. Wells, <hi rend="italic">The Oxford Degree Ceremony</hi> (1906), facing p.
                    19) wears a scarlet cope closed in front, lined with miniver and with tippet and
                    hood of miniver, and there is also a mention in an ancient statute of Cambridge
                    of a red cope worn by Inceptors in Canon Law (Clark, p. 102). The Rev. N. F.
                    Robinson <hi rend="italic">(loc. cit.</hi> p. 195) quotes the will of R. Browne,
                    archdeacon of Rochester (d. 1452), to prove that the habit of a doctor of civil
                    law was violet; he also thinks that that of a doctor of theology was green, and
                    of a doctor of canon law scarlet. By the 16th century all copes were scarlet.
                    Clark (p. 138) gives as evidence “ Stokys <hi rend="sup">i</hi> picture ” in the
                    Cambridge Registrary. The scarlet <hi rend="italic">cappa clausa</hi> has
                    survived to the present day at Cambridge as the dress worn by the
                    Vice-Chancellor and by Regius Professors of Divinity, Law and Medicine when
                    presenting for degrees. It is now open down the front, but the fur edging only
                    reaches half-way down, marking the place where the slit used to be. At Oxford
                    the so-called “ cope ” which is the Convocation robe of certain doctors is not a
                    real cope, but is probably derived from the medieval tabard, the out-of-door
                    dress worn by the clergy and others, it having become customary by the beginning
                    of the 16th century for Regent Masters to wear the tabard at lectures as more
                    convenient than the cope (Rashdall, II. ii. 639, and <hi rend="italic">Mun.
                        Acad.</hi> p. 421, where the <hi rend="italic">pallium</hi> is spoken of as
                    an alternative to the <hi rend="italic">cappa clausa.</hi> The <hi rend="italic"
                        >pallium</hi> is most probably to be Identified with theta bard). <note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="18"> Clark (pp. 138-39)
                        treats of the <hi rend="italic">pallium</hi> and tabard as two separate
                        garments, deciding that the <hi rend="italic">pallium</hi> was a kind of
                        tippet. Robinson considers the <hi rend="italic">pallium</hi> to correspond
                        to the tabard, his <hi rend="italic">labordum talare,</hi> which the Rev. T.
                        A. Lacey (p. 128) also compares with the chimere of Anglican bishops. (See
                        article Chimere <hi rend="smallcaps"/> where the chimere is likewise traced
                        to the tabard.) Moroni, <hi rend="italic">Dizionario delF erudizione
                            storica-ecclesiastica,</hi> s.v. <hi rend="italic">zimarra,</hi> says
                        that professors of the university of Rome wear black <hi rend="italic"
                            >zimarrc</hi> while teaching. This recalls the <hi rend="italic"
                            >pallium</hi> of Regent Masters <hi rend="italic">(Mum Acad.</hi> p.
                        421) and Inceptors in arts and medicine <hi rend="italic">(id.</hi> p. 430).
                    </note> The <hi rend="italic">capa manicala</hi> mentioned in Anstey <hi
                        rend="italic">(Mun. Acad.</hi> p. 421, &amp;c.) seems to have been a
                    shorter gown with bell-shaped sleeves reaching to the elbow, and lined with fur,
                    worn by masters and bachelors of arts (see Druitt, p. 124), and a shorter tabard
                    is also occasionally found (Robinson’s <hi rend="italic">Tabcrdum ad medias
                        tibias).</hi> These are illustrated in fig. 6 from a MS. of the 15th century
                    at New College, Oxford. <note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                        n="19"> The Chandler MS. The drawings from which the illustration is taken
                        are reproduced in the <hi rend="italic">Transactions of the St Paul’s
                            Ecclesio-logical Society,</hi> p. 208, with an explanatory article by
                        the Rev. N. F. Robinson, and in <hi rend="italic">Archaeologia,</hi> vol.
                        liii. pl. i., with notes by T. F. Kirby. Robinson identifies the various
                        groups of the Society of New College on his plate i. (xv. in <hi
                            rend="italic">Arehaeol.)</hi> by the aid of a statute of the College
                        settling the order of standing in choir and at processions, and thus claims
                        to settle the question of the dress of the various kinds of Doctor and
                        Bachelor, M.A.’s, &amp;c., at the period. </note> The D.D.’s wear the <hi
                        rend="italic">cappa clausa,</hi> the other doctors tabards (see also pi.
                    iii., xvi. in <hi rend="italic">Archaeologia,</hi> where William of Wykeham and
                    all the doctors wear long sweeping tabards, as ample as copes), the Warden a
                    shorter tabard, reaching just below the knees, and the M.A.’s gowns or tabards
                    with false sleeves.</p>
               <p>The Hood was originally worn by all scholars, as by everybody, and had evidently
                    no academic significance. Sometimes a cap was also worn, the hood being thrown
                    back (Chaucer’s “ clerk of Oxenford ” in the Ellesmere MS. illumination wears a
                    red skull-cap, and a furred tippet and hood, with the hood falling rather back,
                    though not on his shoulders). The liripipe <note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial" n="20"> In the present article “ liripipe ” will be used of
                        the tail of the hood, “ tippet ” of the shoulder-cape, sometimes forming
                        part of the same garment as the hood, sometimes not, and “ scarf ” of the “
                        tippet ” or scarf, <hi rend="italic">e.g.</hi> of D.D.’s, Anglican clergy.
                    </note> became somewhat elongated, as is seen in the hoods of the so-called M.A.
                    group in the Chandler MS. An early mention of the undergraduate hood is the
                    much-discussed Oxford Statute of 1489 <hi rend="italic">(Mun. Acad.</hi> p.
                    360), which reads: “ ut nullus de cetero scholaris non-graduatus (nobili
                    sanguine insignitis &amp;c. exceptis) capitio quovis utatur pubhce. .. nisi
                    liripipium consutum habeat et non contextum, prout antiqua Universitatis
                    laudabilis consuetudo exposcit...” <note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial" n="21"> “that no non-graduate scholar (with the usual
                        exceptions of noblemen, &amp;c.) shall wear any kind of hood in public,
                        unless it have the liripipe sewn on, and not woven in one piece, as the
                        ancient and venerable custom of the university demands.” The meaning of this
                        is not clear; Anstey (marginal note<hi rend="italic">ad loc.)</hi> takes it
                        to mean that the tail of the hood should be sewn to the hood; others
                        that the tail of the hood should be sewn down to the gown; cf. Chaucer, <hi
                            rend="italic">Prol. to Canon’s, Yeoman’s Tale:</hi> “Till that I
                        understood How that his cloke was sowed to his hood, For which, whan I
                        hadde long avysed me, I demed him some Chanoun for to be,” which shows that
                        this method of sewing the hood, whatever it were, was used to define rank;
                        others again hold that “ <hi rend="italic">liripipium ’’</hi> here means a
                        tippet or shoulder-cape, and that for some reason the. hood was to be sewn
                        to the tippet and not made all in one piece with it. Rashdall reads <hi
                            rend="italic">“ Consuetum ’’</hi> instead of “ <hi rend="italic"
                            >consutum ”</hi> (footnote, ii. p. 641). The Constitution of Archbishop
                        Bourchier (1463) forbids undergraduates to use liripipes or “ tippets ”
                        round the neck in public (Clark, p. 85), so the sewing down of the liripipe
                        at the back may have been to prevent this improper use as a scarf. But in
                        this case, what is the force of “<hi rend="italic">et non
                        Contextum</hi>”?</note> but the undergraduate</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-23-r03-0415" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0448.jp2"/>
               <p>hood had gone out of use by the end of the 16th century. <note anchored="true"
                        place="bottom" type="authorial" n="22"> An interesting survival, which only
                        disappeared about the middle of the 19th century, was the little black hood
                        placed round the neck of candidates going in for <hi rend="italic">viva
                            voce</hi> in all examinations subsequent to responsions at Oxford. This
                        was a survival of the custom of conferring on <hi rend="italic">sophistae
                            generales, i.e.</hi> those who had passed the first stage of the
                        exercises for the B.Ä. degree, a hood of plain black cloth. See A. Clark’s
                            <hi rend="italic">Introduction to the Registers of Oxford
                            University,</hi> vol. ii. pt. i. p. 22 (Oxford Hist. Soc., 1887).
                    </note> Bachelors’ hoods were to be lined throughout with fur <hi rend="italic"
                        >{Mun. Acad.</hi> p. 361), which we learn from the statute <hi rend="italic"
                        >de admissione ad pelluram</hi> (1432) to have been budge. Masters and
                    noblemen might use miniver, or silk in summer <hi rend="italic">{Mun. Acad.</hi>
                    pp. 283, 301). There were evidently hoods of at least two kinds for masters,
                    sometimes called respectively <hi rend="italic">caputium</hi> and <hi
                        rend="italic">epomis,</hi> whether corresponding to the distinction between
                    regents and nonregents we do not know. (See <hi rend="italic">Mun. Acad.</hi> p.
                    638, will of Thomas Bray, M.A., and Robinson, <hi rend="italic">loc. cit.</hi>
                    In the Oxford <hi rend="italic">Corpus Statulorurn</hi> of 1768 the <hi
                        rend="italic">epomis</hi> is worn with the ordinary gown, the <hi
                        rend="italic">Capntiiim</hi> with the scarlet habit.) At a later date, at
                    Cambridge, a distinction was made between the hoods of non-regents, which were
                    lined with silk, and those of regents, which were lined with miniver. <note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="23"> See <hi
                            rend="italic">Caius’ Statutes</hi> (1557), also an account of the
                        entertainments at Cambridge on the visit of Queen Elizabeth, 1564, given in
                        Nichols, <hi rend="italic">Progresses,</hi> vol. iii., “ Theologjae
                        Baccalaureos ac non-Regentes primum, sericis caputiis induti, turn Regentes
                        Magistri suis pelliceis albescentibus decorati; tandem Juris Artiumque
                        Baccalaureos suis agninis bracceis conspicui.” </note> Later again the
                    regents wore their hoods in such a way as to show the white lining, while the
                    non-regents wore theirs“ squared,” so that the white did not show. Hence the
                    name “ White Hoods ” and “ Black Hoods ” given to the upper and lower houses of
                    the old Senate respectively. It is not settled when the modern colourings of
                    hoods arose; they probably followed those of·the gowns of the faculties, but
                    about these we are equally uncertain. The Oxford Proctor still wears a miniver
                    hood. The modern Cambridge hood has preserved .the original shape more closely
                    than the Oxford one, being a hood and tippet combined, the hood having square
                    corners. The tippet, which appears as part of the early costume of certain
                    doctors, was probably, like the judges’ tippet, originally the shoulder-cape
                    forming part of the same garment as the hood. Clark and others would derive it
                    from the almuce (ç.v.), but do not seem to show any definite grounds for so
                    doing. Its place seems to have been taken by the scarf worn by D.D.’s,
                    &amp;c., probably developed from the hood with long liripipe as worn
                    turban-wise on the head or as a scarf round the shoulders. It seems rather
                    far-fetched to derive the scarf from the two pendants of the almuce. <note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="24"> See Rev. E. Wickham
                        Legg in <hi rend="italic">Trans, of St Paul’s Eccles. Soc.</hi> vol. iii.
                        Also Lacey and Robinson <hi rend="italic">{loc. cit.}.</hi>
                    </note> (See article <hi rend="smallcaps">Vestments</hi> and cp. the mayor’s
                    scarf mentioned above.)</p>
               <p>There seem to have been at least three varieties of academic head-dress: <note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="25"> The subject is
                        discussed in detail by Clark, “ College Caps and Doctors’ Hats,” in <hi
                            rend="italic">Archaeol. Journal,</hi> vol. lxi.,and N. F. Robinson, “
                        PiIeus Quadratus,** in <hi rend="italic">Transact, of St Paul’s
                            Ecclesiological Socy.,</hi> vol. V. pt. i. (1901). There is also much
                        miscellaneous information in C. Wordsworth, <hi rend="italic">University
                            Life in the 18th Century,</hi> p. 499 seq. </note> firstly, the doctor’s
                    skull-cap with “ apex ” as illustrated in the <hi rend="italic">Chandler
                        MS.</hi> drawings; secondly, the square cap of cloth as prescribed by Laud’s
                    statutes of 1636 for graduates and foundation scholars (similarly for Cambridge
                    by Burleigh’s letter to the vice-chancellor in 1588), with its counterpart of
                    velvet worn by doctors; thirdly, a round cloth cap prescribed by the Laudian
                    statutes and Burleigh’s letter for undergraduates who were not foundation
                    scholars, with the round cap of velvet for doctors which survives as part of
                    their full dress to the present day. The square cap was adopted at the
                    universities, according to Robinson, after 1520, in imitation of the university
                    of Paris. For the development of Jhe modern “ college cap,” see Biretta. In this
                    connexion should be mentioned the term “ tuft-hunting,” <hi rend="italic"
                        >i.e.</hi> attempting to thrust oneself into the society of one’s social
                    superiors, derived from the gold tufts or tassel worn by noblemen and
                    fellow-commoners on their college caps.</p>
               <p>As to the dresses of the different degrees, the drawings from the <hi
                        rend="italic">Chandler MS.</hi> give a good idea of the early costume. It is
                    also</p>
               <p>well illustrated by brasses. <note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial" n="26"> See for doctors’ costume, J. G. and L. A. B.
                        Waller’s <hi rend="italic">Series of Monumental Brasses</hi> (London, 1864),
                        plate of ” Four Ecclesiastics/’ from New College, Oxford, who are also
                        illustrated in Druitt, pp. 131, 129, 119; and for M.A.’s and B.A.’s, Druitt,
                        p. 135 seq. and plate facing p. 136. On the brass of John Lowlhe, D.C.L.,
                        should be noticed the two curious long streamers or Iiripipes hanging from
                        the back of his tabard or hood, lt is hard to say w’hat they can be; but the
                        closest parallel is in the two streamers on the back of the old Oxford
                        commoners’ gown, which were probably survivals of sleeves. They are said to
                        have given rise to the term “ plucking,” <hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi> failing
                        in examination, the story being that a man’s creditors might assemble at the
                        conferring of degrees, and by ” plucking ” at his gown prevent him from
                        going up for his degree. </note> Doctors of theology seem to have w’orn a
                    tippet but no hood. Masters of Arts seem to have worn a gowm, over which was a
                    garment with bell-shaped sleeves reaching to the elbow, a tippet and a hood (see
                    Druitt, plate facing p. 136, and p. 135). The same dress was sometimes worn by
                    B.A.’s (see brass of John Palmer, B.A., d. 1479, New College, Oxford, in Druitt,
                    p. 141), and bachelors of law and divinity, the latter being generally already
                    M.A.’s (Druitt, p. 139). Haines’s theory is that alter the middle of the 15th
                    century the dress of the M.A.’a was changed, and they wore a sleeveless tabard
                    reaching to midway bctw'een ankle and knee. This costume certainly occurs on
                    brasses, chiefly of the 16th or late 15th centuries, but the change is hard to
                    explain. <note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="27"> It is
                        just possible that this sleeved garment may be the <hi rend="italic">capa
                            manicata</hi> mentioned in <hi rend="italic">Mun. Acad.</hi> p. 421, “
                        nullus regens in artibus ... in capa manicata Iectiones Iegat ordinarias,
                        sed in pallio vel capa clausa.” Clark (pp. 188,189, c.) identifies the <hi
                            rend="italic">cappa manicata</hi> with the tabard, but if, as suggested
                        above, the <hi rend="italic">pallium</hi> is the tabard, the <hi
                            rend="italic">cappa manicata</hi> cannot be the same. Braun, <hi
                            rend="italic">Liturgische Gewandung,</hi> p. 308, shows that a sleeved
                        cope, called <hi rend="italic">cappa 'manicata,</hi> did develop from the
                            <hi rend="italic">cappa Clericalis</hi> or everyday cope of the clergy,
                        at the end of the 12th century, its use being forbidden by various synods.
                        It is possible, then, that the <hi rend="italic">capa manicata</hi> may have
                        been w <hi rend="sup">r</hi> orn by non-regents, the tabard (which Haines
                        alleges to have been adopted generally by M.A.’s in the late 15th century),
                        or <hi rend="italic">pallium,</hi> by regents. </note></p>
               <p>Academic dress underwent much inquiry and some revision at the time of the
                    Reformation, chiefly in the direction of sobriety and
                    uniformity, “ excess of apparel ” being repressed as severely as ever, but not
                    with much more effect. <note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                        n="28"> The essential parts of Laud’s statutes, Burleigh’s letter, c., with
                        much other matter bearing on academic costume from the 16th century onwards,
                        will be found in C. Wordsworth’s UwtreriJZy <hi rend="italic">Life in the
                            18th Century</hi> (London and Cambridge, 1874, p. 485 seq.). To the
                        passages quoted by him may be added the following from <hi rend="italic"
                            >Johannis Berebloci Commentarii,</hi> an eye-wit ness’s account of Queen
                        Elizabeth’s visit to Oxford in 1566 (published in <hi rend="italic"
                            >Elizabethan Oxford</hi> ed. C. Plummer, Oxford Hist. Soc., 1887) ; at
                        one of the disputations Mr. Campion, M.A., vvas dressed as follows: “ Toga
                        illi turn Dalmatica talaris fuit, manicis remissis ac Iargitate sua
                        dittîuentibust. Huic pallium inductum est undique consutum, praeter quam qua
                        dextro patebant aditus. Postremo erant hu men superius pellibus albis,
                        Candoreque Iucentibus, redimiti. Atque hic tum habitus fuit omnium
                        magistrorum, praeterquam quod nqnnulli, loco palluda-menti illius pellicei,
                        serico utebantur, omni colore vanegato.” This points to the wide-sleeved
                        gow’n, tabard and hood as the dress of masters, but the colour of the hood
                        was evidently not fixed. For Doctor White, D.C.L., “ ei vestis Dalmatica
                        Iuerat talaris, ex electiori et clarissima purpura; lato clavo coccineo
                        superius induebatur, add it urn postremo humeris pal uda ment urn est
                        ejusdem coloris, cum serico subtegminc, similique turn vestiti habitu omncs
                        Doctores sedebant.” Here <hi rend="italic">vestis Dalmatica</hi> w'ould be
                        the ordinary gown, <hi rend="italic">clavus latus</hi> the scarlet gown, and
                            <hi rend="italic">paludamentum</hi> the hood, as before. For costume up
                        to the middle of the IOth century see Wall-Gunning, <hi rend="italic">Cere
                            mon ies observed in the Senate House at Cambridge</hi> (1828). </note>
                    Burleigh’s letter to the Vice-Chancellor of Cambridge University (1585), and the
                    statutes of Queen Elizabeth, strictly enforce the wearing of cap and gown by
                    all, and hoods and habits by those entitled to wear them, and similar
                    regulations were made for Oxford by Laud’s statutes of 1633, further details
                    being dealt with by a decree of 1770. Academic dress during the 17th century may
                    be further studied in Bedcl Buck’s book (1665, see Appendix B. to Peacock, <hi
                        rend="italic">Observations on the Statutes of the .University of
                        Cambridge},</hi> and Loggan’s plates of academic costume in <hi
                        rend="italic">Oxonia Illustrata</hi> (1675) <hi rend="sup">an</hi> ^ <hi
                        rend="italic">Cantabrigia Illustrata</hi> (1690, ed. J. W. Clark, 1905).</p>
               <p>There have been few far-reaching changes since Loggan’s day. Cambridge has of
                    late years inquired into and revised her regulations as to dress, and in the <hi
                        rend="italic">Ordinances</hi> (latest ed. 1908, Statute A, cap. VII. p. 303)
                    clear rules are laid down; the Oxford reguIations (see <hi rend="italic">Statuta
                        et Decreta Univ. Oxon.</hi>
               </p>

                <pb xml:id="eb11-23-r03-0416" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0449.jp2"/>
               <p>for 1909, Tit. xiv., <hi rend="italic">de Vestitu et habitu,</hi> pp. 327-328)
                    have not been revised lately, and some of them are a dead letter.</p>
               <p>Doctors of both universities have three sets of robes: firstly, the full-dress
                    gown of scarlet cloth; secondly, the congregation habit and hood of scarlet (now
                    at Cambridge a cope, at Oxford the so-called “cope”); thirdly, the black gown.
                    The. first is worn by all doctors except the doctor of music, and is accompanied
                    by the round cap of velvet. The Oxford D.D. also wears a cassock, sash and
                    scarf. The scarlet gown is of a different and older shape than the M.A. and B.A.
                    gowns. As now worn, it is faced with silk of the same colour as the hood of the
                    faculty. The second, or cope, has now gone almost out of use, but is still worn
                    when presenting for degrees, &amp;c. It is sometimes worn over the black
                    gown. There are several types of black gown, but the tufted gown of Loggan’s day
                    has now gone out of use. The M.D. and Mus.D. black gowns at Cambridge are now
                    made after the pattern of the LL.D. gown, with wing-like sleeve and flap collar,
                    trimmed with black lace, but the D.D., D.Sc. and Litt.D. wear the M.A. gown, the
                    former with the scarf, the two latter with lace on the sleeve, placed
                    horizontally for D.Sc. and vertically for Litt.D. Some doctors of divinity wear
                    the full-sleeved gown with scarf. The head-dress of a D.D. is the square cap,
                    that of the lay doctors the velvet bonnet with gold cord. At Oxford, too, some
                    doctors wear the M.A. gown, others the doctor’s laced gown. The M.A. and B.A.
                    gowns are two varieties of the civilian gown of the 15th and 16th century. The
                    B.A. loose-sleeved gown is no longer worn with the sleeve tucked up round the
                    elbow.</p>
               <p>The Oxford sleeveless commoner’s gown, though still by statute <hi rend="italic"
                        >talaris,</hi> now reaches little below the waist, the full-sleeved
                    scholar’s gown to the knees. The tufted silk gown of the gentleman-commoner and
                    the nobleman’s gold-laced gown are not yet abolished by statute, but have fallen
                    into disuse. Vice-Chancellors have no official costume, but wear the habit of
                    their degree. The Chancellors of the older universities wear a black damask robe
                    with gold lace, and a black velvet square cap with gold tassel or a doctor’s
                    velvet bonnet with gold cord; those of the newer universities have robes “
                    created ” by the robe-makers, who are nowadays to a large extent the arbiters of
                    academic dress.</p>
               <p>For the colours of the hoods of the various university degrees see <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Universities</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">ad fin.</hi>
                    (C. B. P.)
               </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
