<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>translated from HTML to TEI</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-23-r03-0416-01"
                facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0449.jp2" type="entry">

               <p>                   ROBESPIERRE, MAXIMILIEN FRANÇOIS MARIE ISIDORE DE
                    (1758-1794), French revolutionist, was born at Arras on the 6th of May 1758. His
                    family, according to tradition, was of Irish descent, having emigrated from
                    Ireland at the time of the Reformation on account of religion, and his direct
                    ancestors in the male line had been notaries at the little village of Carvin
                    near Arras from the beginning of the 17th century. His grandfather, being more
                    ambitious, established himself at Arras as an advocate; and his father followed
                    the same profession, marrying Jacqueline Marguerite Carraut, daughter of a
                    brewer in the same city, in 1757. Of this marriage four children were born, two
                    sons« and two daughters, of whom Maximilien was the eldest; but in 1767 Madame
                    Derobespierre, as the name was then spelt, died, and the disconsolate widower at
                    once left Arras and wandered about Europe until his death at Munich in 1769. The
                    children were taken charge of by their maternal grandfather and aunts, and
                    Maximilien was sent to the college of Arras, whence he was nominated in 1770
                    through the bishop of his native town to a bursarship at the college of
                    Louis-le-Grand at Paris. Here he had for fellow-pupils Camille Desmoulins and
                    Stanislas Fréron.</p>               <p>Completing his law studies with distinction, and having been admitted an
                    advocate in 1781, Robespierre returned to his native city to seek for practice,
                    and to struggle against poverty. His reputation had already preceded him, and
                    the bishop of Arras, M. de Conzié, appointed him criminal judge in the diocese
                    of Arras in March 1782. This appointment, which he soon resigned, to avoid
                    pronouncing a sentence of death, did not prevent his practising at the bar, and
                    he speedily became a successful advocate. He now turned to literature and
                    society, and came to be esteemed as one of the best writers and most popular
                    dandies of Arras. In December 1783 he was elected a member of the academy of
                    Arras, the meetings of which he attended regularly; and, like all other young
                    Frenchmen with literary proclivities, he began to compete for the prizes offered
                    by various provincial academies. In 1784 he obtained a medal from the academy of
                    Metz for his essay on the question whether the relatives of a condemned criminal
                    should share his disgrace, the prize being divided between him and Pierre Louis
                    Lacretelle, an advocate and journalist in Paris. An <hi rend="italic">éloge</hi>
                    on J. B. L. Gresset (1709-1777), the author of <hi rend="italic">Vert-Vert</hi>
                    and <hi rend="italic">Le Mechant,</hi> written for the academy of Amiens in
                    1785, was not more successful; but Robespierre was compensated for these
                    failures by his great popularity in the little literary and musical society at
                    Arras known as the “ Rosati,” of which Carnot was also a member. There the
                    sympathetic quality of Robespierre’s voice, W’hich afterwards did him such good
                    service in the Jacobin Club, always caused bis indifferent verses to be loudly
                    applauded by his friends.</p>               <p>In 1788 he took part in the discussion as to the way in which the states-general
                    should be elected, showing clearly and forcibly in his <hi rend="italic">Adresse
                        à la nation artésienne</hi> that, if the former mode of election by the
                    members of the provincial estates were again adopted, the new states-gemral
                    would not represent the people of France. Necker also perceived this, and
                    therefore determined to make the old royal <hi rend="italic">bailliages</hi> and
                        <hi rend="italic">sénéchaussées</hi> the units of election, which thus took
                    place on the basis of almost universal suffrage. Under this plan the city of
                    Arras was to return twenty-four members to the assembly of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >bailliage</hi> of Artois, which was to elect the deputies. The corporation
                    claimed the right to a preponderating influence in these city elections, and
                    Robespierre headed the opposition, making himself very conspicuous and drawing
                    up the <hi rend="italic">cahier,</hi> or table of complaints and grievances, for
                    the gild of the cobblers. Although the leading members of the corporation were
                    elected, their chief opponent succeeded in getting elected with them. In the
                    assembly of the <hi rend="italic">bailliage</hi> rivalry ran still higher, but
                    Robespierre had already made his mark in politics; by the <hi rend="italic">Avis
                        aux habitants de Campagne</hi> (Arras, 1789), which is almost certainly
                    by-him, he secured the support of the country electors, and, though but thirty
                    years of age, poor and without influence, he was elected fifth deputy of the <hi
                        rend="italic">tiers état</hi> of Artois to the states-general.</p>               <p>When the states-general met at Versailles on 5th May 1789, the young deputy of
                    Artois already possessed the one faculty which w <hi rend="sup">r</hi> as to
                    lead him to supremacy: he was a fanatic. As Mirabeau is reported to have said: “
                    That young man believes what he says: he will go far.” Without the courage and
                    wide tolerance which make a statesman, without the greatest qualities of an
                    orator, without the belief in himself which marks a great man, nervous, timid
                    and suspicious, Robespierre yet believed in the doctrines of Rousseau with all
                    his heart, and would have gone to death for them; and in the belief that they
                    would eventually succeed and regenerate France and mankind, he was ready to work
                    with unwearied patience. While the Constituent Assembly occupied itself in
                    drawing up a constitution, Robespierre turned from the assembly of provincial
                    lawyers and wealthy <hi rend="italic">bourgeois</hi> to the people of Paris.
                    However, he spoke frequently in the Constituent Assembly, and often with great
                    success, and was eventually recognized as second only to Petion de Villeneuve—if
                    second to him—as a leader of the small body of the extreme left,—the thirty
                    voices, as Mirabeau contemptuously called them. It is hardly necessary to
                    examine minutely Robespierre’s speeches and behaviour before 1791, when the
                    death of Mirabeau left the way clear for the influence of his party; but what is
                    noteworthy, as proving the religious cast of his mind and his belief in the
                    necessity of a religion, is· that he spoke several times in favour of the lower
                    clergy and laboured to get their pensions increased. When he instinctively felt
                    that his doctrines would have no success in the Assembly, he turned to the
                    Society of the Friends of the Constitution, known</p>                <pb xml:id="eb11-23-r03-0417" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0450.jp2"/>
               <p>later as the Jacobin Club, which had consisted originally of the Breton deputies
                    only, but which, after the Assembly moved to Paris, began to admit among its
                    members various'leaders of the Parisian <hi rend="italic">bourgeoisie,</hi> As
                    time went on, many of the more intelligent artisans and small shopkeepers became
                    members of the club, and among such men Robespierre found the hearers he sought.
                    They did more than listen to him: they idolized him; the fanatical leader had
                    found followers. As the wealthier <hi rend="italic">bourgeois</hi> of Paris and
                    deputies of a more moderate type seceded to the club of ’89, the influence of
                    the old leaders of the Jacobins (Barnave, Duport, Alexandre de Lameth)
                    diminished; and when they themselves, alarmed at the progress of the Revolution,
                    founded the club of the Feuillants in 1791, the followers of Robespierre
                    dominated the Jacobin Club. The death of Mirabeau strengthened Robespierre'S
                    influence in the Assembly; but on the 15th of May 1791 he proved his lack of
                    statesmanlike insight and his jealous suspicion of his colleagues by proposing
                    and carrying the motion that no deputies who sat in the Constituent could sit in
                    the succeeding Assembly. The flight of the king on the 20th of June and his
                    arrest at Varennes made Robespierre declare himself at the Jacobin Club to be
                        <hi rend="italic">ni monarchiste ni républicain.</hi> After the “ massacre ”
                    of the Champ de Mars (on the 17th of July 1791) he established himself, in order
                    to be nearer to the Assembly and the Jacobins, in the house of Duplay, a
                    cabinetmaker in the Rue St Honoré, and an ardent admirer of his, where he lived
                    (with but two short intervals) till his death. At last came his day of triumph,
                    when on the 30th of September, on the dissolution of the Constituent Assembly,
                    the people of Paris crowned Pétion and himself as the two incorruptible
                    patriots.</p>               <p>On the dissolution of the Assembly he returned for a short visit to Arras, where
                    he met with a triumphant reception. In November he returned to Paris, and on the
                    18th of December made a speech which marks a new epoch in his life. Brissot de
                    Warville, the <hi rend="italic">âme politique</hi> of the Girondin party which
                    had been formed in the Legislative Assembly, urged vehemently that war* should
                    be declared against Austria, and the queen was equally urgent, in the hope that
                    a victorious army might restore the old absolutism of the Bourbons. Two men
                    opposed the projects of the queen and the Girondins—Marat and Robespierre.
                    Robespierre feared a development of militarism, which might be turned to the
                    advantage of the reaction. This opposition from those whom they had expected to
                    aid them irritated the Girondins greatly, and from that moment began the
                    struggle which ended in the <hi rend="italic">coups Petal</hi> of the 31st of
                    May and the 2nd of June 1793. Robespierre persisted in his opposition to the
                    war; the Girondins, especially Brissot, attacked him violently; and in April
                    1792, he resigned the post of public prosecutor at the tribunal of Paris, which
                    he had held since February, and started a journal, <hi rend="italic">Le
                        Défenseur de la Constitution,</hi> in his own defence. It is noteworthy that
                    during the summer months of 1792 in which the fate of the Bourbon dynasty was
                    being sealed, neither the Girondins in the Legislative Assembly nor Robespierre
                    took any active part in overthrowing it. Stronger men with practical instincts
                    of statesmanship, like Danton and Billaud-Varenne, who dared to look facts in
                    the face and take the responsibility of doing while others were talking, were
                    the men who made the 10th of August and took the Tuileries. The Girondins,
                    however, were quite ready to take advantage of the accomplished fact; and
                    Robespierre, likewise, though shocked at the shedding of blood, was willing to
                    take his seat on the Commune of Paris, which had overthrown Louis XVI., and
                    might check the Girondins. The strong men of the Commune were glad to have
                    Robespierre’s assistance, not because they cared for him or believed in him, but
                    because of the help got from his popularity, his reputation
                    for virtue, which had won for him the surname of “ The Incorruptible,” and his
                    influence over the Jacobin Club and its branches, which spread all over France.
                    He it was who presented the petition of the Commune of Paris on 16th August to
                    the Legislative Assembly, demanding the establishment of a revolutionary
                    tribunal and the summoning of a Convention. The massacres of September in the
                    prisons, which Robespierre in vain attempted to stop, showed that the Commune
                    had more confidence in Billaud than in him. Yet, as a proof of his personal
                    popularity, he was a few days later elected first deputy for Paris to the
                    National Convention.</p>               <p>On the meeting of the Convention the Girondins immediately attacked Robespierre;
                    they were jealous of his influence in Paris, and knew that his single-hearted
                    fanaticism would never forgive their intrigues with the king at the end of July.
                    As early as the 26th of September the Girondin M. D. A. Lasource accused him of
                    aiming at the dictatorship; afterwards lie was informed that Marat, Danton and
                    himself were plotting to become triumvirs; and eventually on the 29th of October
                    Louvet de Couvrai attacked him in a studied and declamatory harangue, abounding
                    in ridiculous falsehoods and obviously concocted in Madame Roland’s boudoir. But
                    Robespierre had no difficulty in rebutting this attack (5th of November), while
                    he denounced the federalist plans of the Girondins. All personal disputes,
                    however, gave way by the month of December 1792 before the‘great question of the
                    king’s trial, and here Robespierre took up a position which is at least easily
                    understood. These are his words spoken on the 3rd of December: “ This is no
                    trial; Louis is not a prisoner at the bar; you arc not judges; you are—you
                    cannot but be—statesmen, and the representatives of the nation. You have not to
                    pass sentence for or against a single man, but you have to take a resolution on
                    a question of the public safety, arid to decide a question of national
                    foresight. It is with regret that I pronounce the fatal truth: Louis ought to
                    perish rather than a hundred thousand virtuous citizens; Louis must die, that
                    the country may live.” This great question settled by the king’s execution, the
                    struggle between Robespierre and the Girondins entered upon a more acute stage,
                    and the want of statesmanship among the latter threw upon the side of the
                    fanatical Robespierre Danton and all those strong practical men who cared little
                    for personal questions, and whose only desire was the victory of France in her
                    great struggle with Europe. Had it been at all possible to act with that group
                    of men of genius whom history calls the Girondins, Danton, Lazare Carnot, Robert
                    Lindet, and even Billaud-Varenne, would have sooner thrown in their lot with
                    them than with Robespierre, whom they thoroughly understood; but the Girondins,
                    spurred on by Madame Roland, refused to have anything to do with Danton.
                    Government became impossible; the federalist idea, which would have broken
                    France to pieces in the very face of the enemy, grew and flourished, and the men
                    of action had to take a decided part. In the month of May 1793 Camille
                    Desmoulins, acting under the inspiration of Robespierre and Danton, published
                    his <hi rend="italic">Histoire des Brissolins</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Brissot
                        démasqué}</hi> Maximin Isnard declared that Paris must be destroyed if it
                    pronounced itself against the provincial deputies; Robespierre preached
                    insurrection at the Jacobin Club; and on the 31st of May and the 2nd of June the
                    Commune of Paris destroyed the Girondin party. For a moment it seemed as if
                    France would avenge them; but patriotism was stronger than federalism. The
                    defence of Lyons exasperated the men who were working for France, and the armies
                    who were fighting for her, and on the 27th of July 1793, when the struggle was
                    practically decided, the Convention elected Robespierre to the new Committee of
                    Public Safety. Hc had not solicited, so it seems, nor even desired this
                    election, yet it marks an important epoch, not only in the life of Robespierre,
                    but in the history of the Revolution. Danton and the men of action had
                    throughout the last two years of the crisis, as Miraheau had in the first two
                    years, seen that the one great need of France, if she was to see the end of her
                    troubles without the interference of foreign armies, was the existence of a
                    strong executive government. The means for establishing the much-needed strong
                    executive were found in the Committee of Public Safety. The success of this
                    Committee in suppressing the Norman insurrection had confirmed the majority of
                    the Convention in the expediency of strengthening its powers, and the Committee
                    of General</p>                <pb xml:id="eb11-23-r03-0418" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0451.jp2"/>
               <p>Security which sat beside it was also strengthened and given the entire
                    management of the internal police of the country. It was not until Robespierre
                    was elected to the Committee that he became one of the actual rulers of France.
                    Indeed, the Committee was not finally constituted until the 13th of September,
                    when the last two of the “ great ” twelve who held office until July 1794 were
                    elected. Of these twelve at least seven —Lazare Carnot, Billaud-Varenne, Collot
                    d’Herbois, Prieur Duvernois (of the Marne), Prieur (of the Côte dOr), Jean Bon
                    Saint-André and Robert Lindet —were essentially men of action, and were entirely
                    free from the influence of Robespierre. Of the other four, Hérault de Séchelles
                    was a professed adherent of Danton, Barère de Vieuzac was an eloquent Provençal,
                    who was ready to be the spokesman to the Convention of any view which the
                    majority of the Committee might adopt; and only Georges Couthon and Saint-Just,
                    devoted to Robespierre, adroitly sustained his policy. It is necessary to dwell
                    upon the fact that Robespierre was always in a minority in the great Committee
                    in order to absolve him from the blame of being the inventor of the Terror, as
                    well as to deprive him of the glory of the gallant stand made against Europe in
                    arms.</p>               <p>After this examination of Robespierre’s position it is not necessary to
                    investigate closely every act of the great Committee during the year which was
                    pre-eminently the year of the Terror; the biographer is rather called upon to
                    examine his personal position with regard to the establishment of the Terror and
                    the fall of the Hébertists and Dantonists, and then to dwell upon the last three
                    months in which he stood almost alone trying to work up an effective
                    counterbalance to the power of the majority of the great Committee. The Terror
                    was the embodiment of the idea of Danton, that it was necessary to have resort
                    to extreme measures to keep France united and strong at home in order to meet
                    successfully her enemies upon the frontier. This idea was systematized by the
                    Committee of Public Safety. With the actual organization of the Terror
                    Robespierre had little or nothing to do; its two great engines, the
                    revolutionary tribunal and the almost absolute power in the provinces of the
                    representatives on mission, were in existence before he joined the Committee of
                    Public Safety, and the laws of the maximum and of the suspects were by no means
                    of his creation. The reason why he is almost universally regarded as its creator
                    and the dominant spirit in the Committee is not hard to discover. Men like
                    Lazare Carnot and Billaud-Varenne were not conspicuous speakers in the
                    Convention, nor were they the idols of any section of the populace; but
                    Robespierre had a fanatical following among the Jacobins and was one of the most
                    popular orators in the Convention, on which his carefully prepared addresses
                    often made a deep impression. His panegyrics on the system of revolutionary
                    government and his praise of virtue led his hearers to believe that the system
                    of the Terror, instead of being monstrous, was absolutely laudable; his pure
                    life and admitted incorruptibility threw a lustre on the Committee of which he
                    was a member; and his colleagues offered no opposition to his posing as their
                    representative and reflecting some of his personal popularity upon them so long
                    as he did not interfere with their work. Moreover, he alone never left Paris,
                    whilst all the others, except Barère, were constantly engaged on missions to the
                    armies, the navy and the provinces. It has been asserted that Robespierre,
                    Couthon and Saint-Just took upon themselves the direction of “ la haute
                    politique,” while the other members acted only in subordinate capacities;
                    undoubtedly it would have suited Robespierre to have had this believed, but as a
                    matter of fact he was in no way especially trusted in matters of supreme
                    importance.</p>               <p>After this explanation it may be said at once that Robespierre was not the sole
                    author of the overthrow of the Dantonists and the Hébertists, though he
                    thoroughly agreed with the majority and had no desire to save them, the
                    principles of both parties being obnoxious to him. The Hébertists were
                    communists in the true meaning of the word. They held that each commune should
                    be self-governing, and, while admitting the right of a central authority to levy
                    men and money for the puiposes of the state, they believed that in purely
                    internal matters; as well as in determining the mode in whicn men and money were
                    to be raised, the local government ought to be supreme. This position of the
                    Hébertists was of course obnoxious to the Committee, who believed that success
                    could only be won by their retention of absolute power; and in the winter of
                    1794-1795 it became obvious that the Hébertist party must perish, or its
                    opposition to the Committee would grow too formidable owing to its paramount
                    influence in the Commune of Paris. Robespierre shared his colleagues’ fear of
                    the Hébertist opinions, and he had a personal reason for disliking that party of
                    atheists and <hi rend="italic">Sansctdottes,</hi> since he believed in the
                    necessity of religious faith, and detested their imitation of the grossness that
                    belongs to the lowest class of the populace. In 1792 he had indignantly thrown
                    from him the cap of liberty which an ardent admirer had placed upon his head; he
                    had never pandered to the depraved tastes of the mob by using their language;
                    and to the last day of his life he wore knee-breeches and silk stockings and
                    wore his hair powdered. His position towards the Dantonist party was of a
                    different character. After having seen established the strong executive he had
                    laboured for, and having moved the resolutions which finally consolidated the
                    power of the Committee of Public Safety in September 1793, Danton retired to his
                    country house. But to his retreat came the news of the means the Committee used
                    to maintain their supremacy. Danton did not believe that this continuous series
                    of sacrifices under the guillotine was necessary, especially since the danger to
                    the country had passed away with the victories of the revolutionary army; hence
                    he inspired Camille Desmoulins to protest against the Terror in the <hi
                        rend="italic">Vieux Cordelier.</hi> Where is this system of terror to end?
                    What is the good of a tyranny comparable only to that of the Roman emperors as
                    described by Tacitus? Such were the questions which Camille Desmoulins asked
                    under Danton’s inspiration. This “ moder-antism,” as it was called, was as
                    objectionable to the members of the Committee as the doctrines of the
                    Hébertists. Both parties must be crushed. Before the blows at the leaders of
                    those two parties were struck, Robespierre retired for a month (from 13th
                    February to 13th March 1794) from active business in the Convention and the
                    Committee, apparently to consider his position; but he came to the conclusion
                    that the cessation of the Reign of Terror would mean the loss of that supremacy
                    by which he hoped to estabh’sh the ideal of Rousseau; for Danton, he knew, was
                    essentially a practical statesman and laughed at his ideas and especially his
                    politico-religious projects. 'He must have considered too that the result of his
                    siding with Danton would probably have been fatal to himself. The result of his
                    deliberations was that he abandoned Danton and co-operated in the attacks of the
                    Committee on the two parties. On the 15th of March he reappeared in the
                    Convention; on the 19th Hébert and his friends were arrested; and on the 24th
                    they were guillotined. On the 30th of March Danton, Camille Desmoulins and their
                    friends were arrested, and on the 5th of April they too were guillotined.</p>               <p>It was not until after the execution of Danton that Robespierre began to develop
                    a policy distinct from that of his colleagues in the Committee, an opposition
                    which ended in his downfall. He began by using his influence over the Jacobin
                    Club to dominate the Commune of Paris through his devoted adherents, two of
                    whom, Fleuriot-Lescot and C. F. de Payan, were elected respectively mayor and
                        <hi rend="italic">procureur</hi> of the Commune. He also attempted to usurp
                    the influence of the other members of the Committee qver the armies by getting
                    his young adherent, Saint-Just, sent on a mission to the frontier. In Paris
                    Robespierre determined to increase the pressure of the Terror: no one should
                    accuse him of moderantism; through the increased efficiency of the revolutionary
                    tribunal Paris should tremble before him as the chief member of the Committee;
                    and the Convention should pass whatever measures he might dictate. To secure his
                    aims, Couthon, his other ally in the Committee,</p>                <pb xml:id="eb11-23-r03-0419" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0452.jp2"/>
               <p>proposed and carried on the ioth of June the outrageous law of 22nd Prairial, by
                    which even the appearance of justice was taken from the tribunal, which, as no
                    witnesses were allowed, became a simple court of condemnation. The result of
                    this law was that between the 12th of June and the 28th of July, the day of
                    Robespierre’s death, no less than 1285 victims perished by the guillotine in
                    Paris. It was the bloodiest and the least justifiable period of the Terror. But
                    before this there had taken place in Robespierre’s life an episode of supreme
                    importance, as illustrating his character and his political aims: on the 7th of
                    May he secured a decree from the Convention recognizing the existence of the
                    Supreme Being. This worship of the Supreme Being was based upon the ideas of
                    Rousseau in the <hi rend="italic">Social Contract,</hi> and was opposed by
                    Robespierre to Catholicism on the one hand and the Hebertist atheism on the
                    other. In honour of the Supreme Being a great fête was held on the 8th of June;
                    Robespierre, as president of the Convention, walked first and delivered his
                    harangue, and as he looked around him he may well have believed that his
                    position was secured and that he was at last within reach of a supreme power
                    which should enable him to impose his belief on all France, and so ensure its
                    happiness. The majority of the Committee found his popularity—or rather his
                    ascendancy, for as that increased his personal popularity diminished— useful to
                    them, since by increasing the stringency of the Terror he strengthened the
                    position of the Committee, whilst attracting to himself, as occupying the most
                    prominent position in it, any latent feeling of dissatisfaction at such
                    stringency. Of the issue of a struggle between themselves and Robespierre they
                    had little fear: they controlled the Committee of General Security through their
                    alliance with its leaders, André Amar and Marc Guillaume Alexis Vadier; they
                    were hopeful of obtaining a majority in the Convention; for they knew that the
                    chief deputies on the left, or “ the Mountain,” were Dantonists, who burned to
                    avenge Danton’s death; while they felt sure also that the mass of the deputies
                    of the centre, or “ the Marsh,” could be hounded on against Robespierre if they
                    were to accuse him of aiming at the dictatorship and pour on him the obloquy of
                    having increased the Terror when victory on the frontier rendered it less
                    necessary; and they knew finally that his actual adherents, though devoted to
                    him, were few in number. The devotion of these admirers had been further excited
                    by the news that a half-witted girl, named Cécile Renault, had been found
                    wandering near his house, with a knife in her possession, intending to play the
                    part of Charlotte Corday. She was executed on the 17th of June, on the very day
                    that Vadier raised a laugh at Robespierre’s expense in the Convention by his
                    report on the conspiracy of Catherine Théot <hi rend="italic">(q.vf,</hi> a mad
                    woman, who had asserted that Robespierre was a divinity.</p>               <p>Robespierre felt that he must strike his blow now or never. Yet he was not
                    sufficiently audacious to strike at once, as Payan and Jean Baptiste Coffinhal,
                    the ablest of his adherents, would have had him do, but retired from the
                    Convention for some weeks, as he had done before the overthrow of the Hébertists
                    and the Dantonists, to prepare his plan of action. This retirement seemed
                    ominous to the majority of the Committee, and they too prepared for the struggle
                    by communicating with the deputies of the Mountain, who were either friends of
                    Danton or men of proved energy like Barras, Freron and Tallien. These weeks, the
                    last of his life, Robespierre passed very peacefully, according to his wont all
                    through the Revolution. He continued to live with the Duplays, with whose
                    daughter Éléonore he had fallen in love, and used to wander with her and his
                    favourite dog, a great Danish hound, named Bruant, in the Champs Élysées during
                    the long summer evenings. At last, on the 26th of July, Robespierre appeared,
                    for the first time for more than four weeks, in the Convention and delivered a
                    carefully studied harangue, which lasted for more than four hours, in which he
                    declared that the Terror ought to be ended, that certain deputies who had acted
                    unjustly and exceeded their powers ought to be punished, and that the Committees
                    of</p>               <p>Public Safety and General Security ought to be renewed. Great was the excitement
                    in the Convention: all wondered who were the deputies destined to be punished;
                    all were surprised that the Terror should be imputed as a fault to the very
                    Committee of which Robespierre had been a member. The majority of the Committee
                    of Public Safety determined to act promptly. The Convention, moved by
                    Robespierre’s eloquence, at first passed his motions; but he was replied to by
                    Joseph Cambon the financier, Billaud-Varcnne, Amar and Vadier, and the
                    Convention rescinded their decrees and referred Robespierre’s question to their
                    committees. On the following day, the 27th of July, or in the revolutionary
                    calendar the 9th Thermidor, Saint-Just began to speak on behalf of the motions
                    of Robespierre, when violent interruptions showed the temper of the Convention.
                    Jean Lambert, Tallien, Billaud-Varenne and Vadier again attacked Robespierre;
                    cries of “ Dowm with the tyrant!” were raised; and, when Robespierre hesitated
                    in his speech in answer to these attacks, the words “ C’est le sang de Danton
                    qui t’étouffe ” showed what was uppermost in the minds of the Mountain.
                    Robespierre tried in vain to gain a hearing, the excitement increased and at
                    five in the afternoon Robespierre, Couthon and Saint-Just, with two young
                    deputies, Augustin Robespierre (younger brother of Maximilien) and Philippe
                    François Joseph Lebas, the only men in all the Convention who supported them,
                    were ordered to be arrested. Yet all hope for Robespierre was not gone; he was
                    speedily rescued from his prison, with the other deputies, by the troops of the
                    Commune and brought to the Hôtel de Ville. There he was surrounded by his
                    faithful adherents, led by Payan and CoffinhaL But the day w <hi rend="sup"
                        >r</hi> as past when the Commune could overawe the Convention; for now the
                    men of action were hostile to the Commune, and its chief was not a master of <hi
                        rend="italic">coups d'état.</hi> On the news of the release of Robespierre,
                    the Convention had again met, and declared the members of the Commune and the
                    released deputies outlawed. The national guards under the command of Barras had
                    little difficulty in making their way to the Hôtel de Ville; Robespierre was
                    shot in the lower jaw by a young gendarme named Meda while signing an appeal to
                    one of the sections of Paris to take up arms for him, though the wound was
                    afterwards believed to have been inflicted by himself; and all the released
                    deputies were again arrested. After a night of agony, Robespierre w <hi
                        rend="sup">r</hi> as the next day taken before the tribunal, where his
                    identity as an outlaw was proved, and without further trial he was executed with
                    Couthon and Saint-Just and nineteen others of his adherents on the Place de la
                    Révolution on the ioth Thermidor (28th July) 1794.</p>               <p>The character of Robespierre, when looked upon simply in the light of his
                    actions and his authenticated speeches, and apart from the innumerable legends
                    which have grown up about it, is not a difficult cfne to understand. A
                    well-educated and accomplished young lawyer, he might have acquired a good
                    provincial practice and lived a happy provincial life had it not been for the
                    Revolution. Like thousands of other young Frenchmen, he had read the works of
                    Rousseau and taken them as gospel. Just at the very time in life when this
                    illusion had not been destroyed by the realities of life, and without the
                    experience which might have taught the futility of idle dreams and theories, he
                    was elected to the states-general. At Paris he was not understood till he met
                    with his audience of fellow-disciples of Rousseau at the Jacobin Club. His
                    fanaticism w’on him supporters; his singularly sweet and sympathetic voice
                    gained him hearers; and his upright life attracted the admiration of all. As
                    matters approached nearer and nearer to the terrible crisis, he failed, except
                    in the two instances of the question of war and of the king’s trial, to show
                    himself a statesman, for he had not the liberal views and practical instincts
                    which made Mirabeau and Danton great men. His admission to the Committee of
                    Public Safety gave him power, which he hoped to use for the establishment of his
                    favourite theories, and for the same purpose he acquiesced in and even
                    heightened the horrors of the Reign of Terror. It is here that the fatal mistake
                    of allowing a theorist to have poorer appeared:</p>                <pb xml:id="eb11-23-r03-0420" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0453.jp2"/>
               <p>Billaud-Varenne systematized the Terror because he believed it necessary for the
                    safety of the country; Robespierteintensified it in order to carry out his own
                    ideas and theories. Robespierre’s private life was always respectable: he was
                    always emphatically a gentleman and man of culture, and even a little bit of a
                    dandy, scrupulously honest, truthful and charitable. In his habits and manner of
                    life he was simple and laborious; he was not a man gifted with flashes of
                    genius, but one who had to think much before he could come to a decision, and he
                    worked hard all his life.</p>               <p>On the family of Robespierre see A. J. Paris in the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Mémoires</hi> (2nd series, vol. iii.) of tne Academy of Arras; the <hi
                        rend="italic">Œuvres de Maximitien Robespierre</hi> (3 vols., 1840),
                    published by Laponneraye with preface by Armand Carreb contain some of his
                    speeches and the memoirs of Charlotte Robespierre on her brothers. The standard
                    work on Robespierre’s career is Ernest Hamel, <hi rend="italic">Histoire de
                        Robespierre d’après des papiers de famille, les sources originales et des
                        documents entièrement inédits</hi> (3 vols., 1865-67). After the appearance
                    of the first volume, the publisher refused to proceed for fear of prosecution
                    until compelled to do so by the author. Another edition with a different title
                    appeared in 1878. See also Ch. d’Heri-cault, <hi rend="italic">La Révolution de
                        Thermidor</hi> (2nd ed., 1878) ; Karl Brunnemann, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Maximilian Robespierre</hi> (Leipzig, 1880); F. Ä. Aulard, <hi
                        rend="italic">Les Orateurs de l’Assemblée Constituante</hi> (1882); M. de
                    Lescure, “Le Roman dç Robespierre," in <hi rend="italic">La Société française
                        pendant</hi> /a <hi rend="italic">Terreur</hi> (1882); Ε. Hamel, <hi
                        rend="italic">La Maison de Robespierre</hi> (1895); Hilaire Belloc, <hi
                        rend="italic">Robespierre</hi> (1901); and C. F. Warwick, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Robespierre and the French Revolution</hi> (1909). Many of the books which
                    have been written about Robespierre are most untrustworthy, and the picture of
                    him given by Thomas Carlyle in his <hi rend="italic">French Revolution</hi> is
                    unjust.</p>            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
