<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>translated from HTML to TEI</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-23-r03-0433-02"
                facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0466.jp2" type="entry">

                <p><label>ROCK-CRYSTAL</label> a colourless and transparent variety of quartz <hi
                        rend="italic">(q.v.),</hi> used as an ornamental stone. It usually occurs as
                    crystals lining cavities in quartz-veins, which often run through granite,
                    gneiss and crystalline schists. The limpidity of the crystal, its coldness to
                    the touch and its common occurrence in rocks among Alpine glaciers, led to the
                    ancient belief that it was a kind of congealed water, whence the name crystal,
                    from Gr. <hi rend="italic">κῥνσταλλς</hi> (ice). In the Swiss Alps the <hi
                        rend="italic">“Strahler”</hi> or crystal -gatherer, searches the rocks at
                    much personal risk, and is often led to a drusy cavity by tracing narrow veins,
                    or strings, of quartz on the mountain-side. A remarkable druse, or <hi
                        rend="italic">Krystalkeller,</hi> discovered at Zinkenstock in the Bernese
                    Oberland, in 1719, yielded about 20 tons of crystal, a single specimen weighing
                    8 cwt. The famous discovery of the Galenstock, in 1867, furnished magnificent
                    crystals, but they were dark brown or smoky quartz. La Gardette, near Le Bourg
                    d'Oisans, in the Alps of Dauphiné, is a notable locality for fine specimens of
                    rock-crystal. The Alps and India probably furnished the ancients with their
                    supplies.</p>
               <p>Rock-crystal has been used for ornamental purposes since the Mycenean period. By
                    the Romans under the Empire it was highly valued, and carved into vases and
                    goblets, in some cases elaborately engraved. Lenses or globes were used for
                    kindling the sacred vestal fire and for cauterizing the flesh, whilst ladies
                    carried balls of crystal in order to cool their hands during the heat of summer.
                    The artists of the Early Renaissance greatly favoured the use of rock-crystal,
                    and executed beautiful carvings in this material. In modern times the use of
                    rock-crystal has been largely superseded by that of glass, and it is notable
                    that flint-glass is known in France as <hi rend="italic">“ cristal”</hi>
                    probably from its resemblance to limpid quartz, or perhaps from the fact that
                    powdered rock-crystal has been used as a source of silica in the manufacture of
                    the finest glass. Rock-crystal is still cut as a faceted stone for personal
                    decoration, but though not without brilliancy it lacks the “ fire ” of many
                    gemstones. It is often known locally by such names as Bristol diamond, Cornish
                    diamond, Isle of Wight diamond, Briançon diamond, Marmaros diamond, Lake George
                    diamond, &amp;c. Rock-crystal is also carved into seals, paper-weights and
                    other trivial objects, and into spheres for divination by crystal-gazing,
                    Japanese balls being specially noteworthy. In Japan the crystal has been
                    obtained for centuries from the granitic districts around Kimpū-san, in the
                    province of Kai. Probably the most valuable application of rock-crystal is for
                    spectacle lenses, which in consequence of their hardness are not readily abraded
                    by use. They should be cut at right angles to the optic axis, or axis of the
                    prism.</p>
               <p>The “ pebble ” for lenses is found loose in the soil in many parts of the
                    provinces of Goyaz, Sao Paulo and Minas Geraes in Brazil. Much of the material
                    for spectacles comes also from Madagascar, where large crystals of clear quartz
                    are found in the beds of certain streams, especially in the N.E. part of the
                    island, having probably</p>
               <p>been derived from quartz-veins in the gneiss and pegmatite. In India
                    rock-crystal has been worked at many localities, and the loot of the palace of
                    Delhi yielded marvellous ornaments carved in this material. At the present day
                    it is cut and polished at Vellum in the Tanjore district in Madras, and is known
                    as Vellum stone. Among the numerous localities in the United States which yield
                    rock-crystal mention may be made of those in Herkimcr Co., New York State,
                    whence the Lake George crystals are obtained; and it is notable that some of the
                    Herkimer quartz encloses bituminous matter. Mokelumne Hill, Calaveras Co.,
                    California, has Iurnisheil some remarkable rock-crystal. In Europe the
                    localities are very numerous, the most important being those in the Alps. Very
                    fine crystals remarkable for pellucidity though not of large size occur in
                    cavities in the statuary marble of Carrara; ancf remarkably hollowed crystals
                    arc known from Porretta near Bologna in ltaly. The finest rock-crystal in Great
                    Britain occurs at Tintagcl and the Delabolc slate quarry in N. Cornwall; and at
                    Snowdon in N. Wales. (F. W. R.*)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
