<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>translated from HTML to TEI</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-23-r03-0399-02"
                facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0422.jp2" type="entry">

               <p>                   <label>ROBERT I.</label> (<hi rend="italic">c.</hi> 865-923), king of
                    France, or king of the Franks, was the younger son of Robert the Strong, count
                    of Anjou, and the brother of Odo, or Eudes, who became king of the western
                    Franks in 888. Appointed by Odo ruler of several .counties, including the county
                    of Paris, and abbot <hi rend="italic">in commendam</hi> of many abbeys, Robert
                    also secured the office of duke of the Franks, a military dignity of high
                    importance. He did not claim the crown of France when his brother died in 898;
                    but recognizing the supremacy of the Carolingian king, Charles III., the Simple,
                    he was confirmed in his offices and possessions, after which he continued to
                    defend northern France from the attacks of the Normans. The peace between the
                    king and his powerful vassal was not seriously disturbed until about 921. The
                    rule of Charles, and especially his partiality for a certain IIagano, had
                    aroused some irritation; and, supported by many of the clergy and by some of the
                    most powerful of the Frankish nobles, Robert took up arms, drove Charles into
                    Lorraine, and was himself crowned king of the Franks at Reims on the 29th of
                    June 922. Collecting an army, Charles marched against the usurper, and on the
                    15th of June 923, in a stubborn and sanguinary battle near Soissons, Robert was
                    killed, according to one tradition in single combat with his rival. Robert left
                    a son. Hugh the Great, duke of the Franks, and his grandson was Hugh Capet, king
                    of France.</p>               <p>See F. Lot, <hi rend="italic">Les Derniers Carolingiens</hi> (Paris, 1891); and
                    E. Lavisse, <hi rend="italic">Histoire de France,</hi> tome ii. (Paris, 1903).
               </p>            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
