<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="chi.28490931-1526160593_Page_701.jpf" type="entry" xml:id="eb07-19-s01-0646-01" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SARAPILLY</label>,
a town of Hindustan, in the Carnatic, thirteen miles south from the town of Nelloor. Long. 79. 58. E. Lat. 14. 14. N.</p><p>. SARATOV, a large province or government, partly in the south-east of Europe, and partly in Asia. Its form is that of a triangle on both sides of the Volga, having on the one side the country of the Don Cossacks, and on the other that of Astracan. It is very thinly peopled, containing an area of 91,000 square miles, and the population not exceeding 1,000,000, in consequence of the barrenness of the soil and the unpropitious climate. Great part of the soil is of a saline quality, and unfit for the growth of vegetables. There are several salt lakes, the most productive of which is that of Elton or Ulton. The country lying to the west of the Volga is less level, but has no hills of any great height. The ground is partly arable and partly pastoral. German colonists have been settled in the country, but with little success. The capital is of the same name, and is situated on the Volga. It is neatly built, and has wide, straight streets ; but the houses are mostly of wood. The position of the place between Moscow and Astracan is favourable to trade, and it has, besides, the command of water-carriage on the Volga. The principal articles of its trade, which are not derived from the two cities already named, are fish, comar, and salt. The population is 5000. It is 374 miles north by west of Astracan, and 465 south-east of Moscow. Long. 46. 0. E. Lat. 51. 31. N.</p></div></body></text></TEI>