<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="chi.28490931-1526160593_Page_689.jpf" type="entry" xml:id="eb07-19-s01-0634-14" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SAN <hi rend="smallcaps">Lucar de Barrameda,</hi></label>
 a city of Spain, in the province of Andalusia. It is a good port, at the entrance of the river Guadalquivir, and the city is built on its eastern bank. The trade of Seville in a great degree centres here, as the larger vessels belonging to that city cannot ascend higher up the river. It is well fortified towards the sea. The country around it is cultivated quite to the shore, and produces rich crops of grapes, olives, and the other fruits of the climate, but little or no corn. It contains 15,200 inhabitants.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">San</hi> SEBASTIAN, a city of Spain, in the province of Gui- puscoa, at the mouth of the river Urumea, which runs from Navarre. Its harbour is excellent, and, as well as the city, is defended by the strong fortress La Mota, which overlooks both ; and it has other powerful fortifications towards the land as well as the sea. It has considerable trade by means of ships of great burden. The mole is a magnificent and well-executed work, as is the lighthouse, which is visible at sea at nine leagues distance. San Sebastian has always been considered, for its extent, the most commercial city of Spain, and its trade is as ancient, as its foundation. The city contains about seven hundred houses, mostly containing two or more families, and the population is 13,100 souls ; but the country around it is thickly studded with country residences, and is well peopled. The land in its neighbourhood is not fertile, but the hills which surround it abound with iron, and are a great source of wealth to the inhabitants. It is in latitude 43. 19. 39. north, and longitude 1. 30. 35. west from London.</p></div></body></text></TEI>