<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="gri_33125011196389_0635.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0629-03"
                xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                <p><label>SALTING <hi rend="smallcaps">meat for the use of the navy</hi></label> .
                    The following is the method recommended by the late admiral Sir Charles Knowles.
                    When the ox is killed, let it be ſkinned and cut up into pieces fit for uſe as
                    quick as poſſible, and ſalted while the meat is hot. For which purpoſe we muſt
                    have a ſufficient quantity of ſaltpetre and bay-ſalt pounded together and made
                    hot in an oven, of each equal parts; with this ſprinkle the meat at the rate of
                    about two ounces to the pound; then lay the pieces on ſhelving boards to drain
                    for 24 hours; which done, turn them and repeat the ſame operation, and let them
                    lie for 24 hours longer. By this time the ſalt will be all melted, and have
                    penetrated the meat, and the pieces be drained off; each piece muſt then be
                    wiped dry with clean coarſe cloths. A ſufficient quantity of common felt muſt
                    then be made hot like- wiſe in an oven, and mixed when taken out with about
                    one-third of brown ſugar: then the caſks being ready, rub each piece well with
                    this mixture, and pack them well down, allowing about half a pound of the ſalt
                    and ſugar to each pound of meat, and it will keep good ſeveral years.</p>
                <p>It is beſt to proportion the caſks to the quantity uſed at one time, as the leſs
                    it is expoſed to the air the better. The ſame proceſs does for pork, only a
                    larger quantity of ſalt and leſs ſugar muſt be uſed; but the preſervation of
                    both depends equally upon the meat being hot when firſt ſalted.</p>
                <p>One pound of beef requires two ounces of ſaltpetre and two ounces of bay-ſalt,
                    becauſe it is to be ſprinkled twice; an ounce of each to a pound of beef both
                    times. The ſaltpetre requiſite for 100 lb. of beef is I2 <hi rend="superscript">
                        1</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> lb. which at 12 d. per lb. is 12s.
                    6d.; and the ſame quantity of bay-ſalt (for 100 lb. of beef), at three
                    half-pence per lb. is 1s. 6d.; of brown ſugar and common ſalt mixed together
                    half a pound is required, the former in the proportion of one-third, the latter
                    of two- thirds, to a pound of beef. The brown ſugar at 8d. per pound. A hundred
                    pounds of beef will take 250 ounces of it, which coſts 10s. 5d. The quantity of
                    common ſalt requiſite for 100 lb. of beef is 533 ounces, which at 2d. per lb.
                    amounts to 5s. 6d. The expence therefore will ſtand thus.</p>
                <pb facs="gri_33125011196389_0636.tif" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0630"/>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell> Saltpetre, 12 <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> / <hi rend="subscript">
                                2</hi> lb. for 100 lb. of beef, is </cell>
                        <cell> L </cell>
                        <cell> 0 </cell>
                        <cell> 12 </cell>
                        <cell> 6 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> Bay-ſalt, 12 <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> / <hi rend="subscript">
                                2</hi> lb. for do. is </cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell> 0 </cell>
                        <cell> 10 </cell>
                        <cell> 6 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> Brown-ſugar, 230 oz. for do. is </cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell> 0 </cell>
                        <cell> 10 </cell>
                        <cell>
                            <hi rend="italic">5</hi>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> Beef, 100 lb. at 6d. per pound, is </cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell> 2 </cell>
                        <cell> 10 </cell>
                        <cell>
                            <hi rend="italic">0</hi>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> Three caſks for it at 1s. 6d each, </cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell> 0 </cell>
                        <cell> 4 </cell>
                        <cell>
                            <hi rend="italic">6</hi>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> Labour, and heating the oven twice, </cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell> 0 </cell>
                        <cell> 4 </cell>
                        <cell> 0 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> Common ſalt, 533 oz. for do. is </cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell> 0 </cell>
                        <cell> 5 </cell>
                        <cell>
                            <hi rend="italic">6</hi>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell> L </cell>
                        <cell> 4 </cell>
                        <cell> 8 </cell>
                        <cell> 5 </cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>Theſe articles are taken high; and if beef coſts 6d. per pound, meat cured thus
                    will coſt leſs than 1s. per pound; and therefore comes much cheaper than
                    live-ſtock in long ſea-voyages.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
