<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196389_0606.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0600-02" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SAGAPENUM</label>,
in pharmacy, &amp;c. a gum-reſin brought to us in two forms; the finer and purer is in looſe granules or ſingle drops; the coarſer kind is in maſſes compoſed oſ theſe drops of various ſizes, cemented together by a matter of the ſame kind. In either cafe, it is of a firm and compact ſubſtance, conſiderably heavy, and of a reddiſh colour on the outſide, browniſh<pb facs="gri_33125011196389_0607.tif" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0601"/>
within, and ſpotted in many places with ſmall yellowiſh or whitiſh ſpecks. Its ſmell is ſtrong and diſagreeable; its taſte acrid and unpleaſant.</p><p>It is brought to us from Perſia and the Eaſt Indies. The plant which produces it has never been deſcribed; but is ſuppoſed to be, as Dioſcorides ſays, of the ferula kind, from the ſeeds and fragments of the ſtalks ſometimes met with in the body of it.</p><p>Sagapenum is a very great attenuant, aperient, and diſcutient. It is good in all diſorders of the breaſt that owe their origin to a tough phlegm. It has alſo been found to diſcuſs tumors in the nervous parts in a remarkable manner; and to give relief in habitual headache, where almoſt all things elſe have failed. Its doſe is from ten grains to two ſcruples; but it is now ſeldom given alone. It has been found, however, to do great things in aſthmas; in obſtructions of the viſcera, particularly the ſpleen; in nervous complaints; and even in epilepſies. It alſo promotes the menſes, and expels the ſecundines; and is an ingredient in the theriaca, mithridate, and many other of the ſhop compoſitions.</p></div></body></text></TEI>