<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196389_0712.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0706-01" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SCILLY</label>,
or <hi rend="smallcaps">Sillev,</hi> a cluſter of ſmall iſlands and rocks, ſituated in the Atlantic Ocean, in W. Long 7⁰. N. Lat. 50⁰.</p><p>Theſe iſlands were firſt called <hi rend="italic">Caſſiterides,</hi> or the <hi rend="italic">Tin Isles,</hi> from their being rich in that metal. The common opinion is, that this is a Greek appellation; which in the moſt obvious ſenſe is true: But as the Phoenicians were familiar with the metal, and with the country that produced it, before the Greeks knew any thing of either, it is very likely they introduced the names of both from their own language. Strabo ſays theſe iſlands were ten in number, lying cloſe together, of which only one was uninhabited: the people led an erratic life, lived upon the produce of their cattle, wore an under garment which reached down to their ankles, and over that another, both of the ſame colour, which was black, girt round a little below the breaſt with a girdle, and walked with ſtaves in their hands. The riches of theſe iſlands were tin and lead, which, with thc ſkins of their cattle, they exchanged with foreign merchants, that is, the Phoenicians from Cadiz, for earthen-ware, ſalt, and utenſils made of braſs. An author of as great or greater antiquity, ſeems to include a part at leaſt of Cornwall amongſt theſe iſlands; or rather he ſuggeſts, that they were not perfect iſlands except at full ſea, but that at ebb the inhabitants paſſed from one to another upon the sands, and that they even tranſported their tin in large ſquare blocks upon carriages from one iſland to another. He farther takes notice, that such as inhabited about Belerium (the Land’s End) were in their converſation with ſtrangers remarkably civil and courteous. Other ancient writers ſtyle theſe iſlands <hi rend="italic">Hesperides,</hi> from their weſtern ſituation, and <hi rend="italic">Oestrymnides,</hi> aſſerting that the land was extremely fertile, as well as full of mines; and that the people, though very brave, were entirely addicted to commerce, and boldly paſſed the ſeas in their leather boats.</p><p>The Romans were exceedingly deſirous of having a ſhare in this commerce, which the Phoenicians as carefully laboured to prevent, by concealing their navigation to theſe iſlands as much as it was in their power. At length, however, the Romans prevailed; and Publius Craſſus coming thither, was ſo well pleaſed with the</p><p>induſtry and manners of the people, that he taught them various improvements, as well in working their mines, which till that time were but ſhallow, as in carrying their own merehandiſe to different markets. There is no room to doubt that they followed the fate of the reſt of Britain, and particularly of Cornwall, in becoming ſubject to the Roman empire. We find them called in the Itinerary of Antoninus, <hi rend="italic">Sigdeles;</hi> bv Sulpitius, Sillenae <hi rend="italic">;</hi> and by Solinus they are termed- <hi rend="italic">Silures.</hi> All we know of them during this period is, that their tin trade continued, and that ſometimes ſtate- priſoners were exiled, or, to uſe the Roman phraſe, relegated hither as well as to other iſlands.</p><p>When the legions were withdrawn, and Britain with its dependencies left in the power of the natives, there is no reaſon to queſtion that theſe iſlands ſhared the ſame lot with the reſt. As to the appellation which from this period prevailed, the ordinary way of writing it is <hi rend="italic">Sally;</hi> in records we commonly ſind it ſpelt <hi rend="italic">Silly, Silley,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Sulley;</hi> but we are told the old Britiſh appellation was <hi rend="italic">Sulleb,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Sylleb,</hi> which ſignifies rocks conſecrated to the ſun. We have not the leaſt notice of any thing that regards them from the fifth to the tenth century. It is, however, with much appearance of truth conjectured, that ſome time within, this ſpace they were in a great meaſure deſtroyed by an earthquake, attended with a ſinking of the earth, by which moſt of their lowlands, and of courſe the greateſt part of their improvements, were covered by the ſea, and thoſe rich mines of tin which had rendered them ſo famous ſwallowed up in the deep. They have a tradition in Cornwall, that a very externſive tract of country called the <hi rend="italic">Lione</hi> ſs <hi rend="italic">,</hi> in the old Corniſh <hi rend="italic">Lethousow,</hi> ſuppoſed to lie between that country and Scilly, was loſt in that manner; and there are many concurrent circumſtances which render this probable. In reference to theſe iſlands, the caſe is ſtill ſtronger; for at low ebbs their ſtone-incloſures are ſtill viſible from almoſt all the iſles, and thereby afford an ocular demonſtration that they were formerly of far greater extent, and that in remoter ages their inhabitants muſt have been very numerous, and at the ſame time very induſtrious. This ſufficiently proves the fact, that by ſuch an earthquake they were deſtroyed; and that it happened at ſome period of time within thoſe limits that have been aſſigned, appears from our hearing nothing more of their tin trade, and from our having no notice of it at all in any of our ancient chronicles, which, if it had fallen out later, from their known attention to extraordinary events, muſt certainly have happened.</p><p>It is generally ſuppoſed, and with great appearance of truth, that king Athelitan, after having overcome a very powerful confederacy formed againſt him, and having reduced Exeter, and driven the Britons beyond the river Tamar, which he made the boundary of their Corniſh dominions, paſſed over into theſe iſlands, (then ſurely in a better ſtate than now, or they would not have been objects of his vengeance), and reduced them likewiſe. Hiltory does not inform us, that the Danes ever fixed themſelves in theſe illands; but as their method of fortifying is very well known, it has been conjectured that the Giant’s Caſtle in the iſle of St Mary was erected by them; and indeed, if we conſider the convenient ſituation of theſe iſlands, and the<pb facs="gri_33125011196389_0713.tif" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0707"/>
trade of piracy which that nation carried on, there ſeems to be nothing improbable in that conjecture. It is more certain that there were churches erected in theſe iſles, and that there were in them alſo many monks and hermits, before the conqueſt.</p><p>The fertility of the iſlands is much inſiſted upon in all the accounts; and it is expreſsly ſaid of St Mary’s, that it bears exceeding good corn, inſomuch that if men did but caſt corn where ſwine had rooted, it would come up. There is mention made of a breed of wild ſwine, and the inhabitants had great plenty of fowl and fiſh. But notwithſtanding the fertility of the country, and the many commodities that men had or might have there, it was nevertheleſs but thinly peopled; and the reaſon aſſigned is, becauſe they were liable to be frequently ſpoiled by French or Spaniſh pirates. In Leland’s time, one Mr Havers of Wiltſhire, and Mr Whittington of Glouceſterſhire, were proprietors of Scilly, and drew from thence, in rents and commodities, about 40 merks a-year.</p><p>The inhabitants at that juncture, and long before, appear to have carried on a ſmall trade in dried ſkate and other fiſh to Bretagne, with which they purchaſed ſalt, canvas, and other neceſſaries. This ſeems to be the remains of a very old kind of commerce, ſince, for many ages, the people of that country, thoſe of the Scilly iſles, and the people of Cornwall, looked upon themſelves as countrymen, being in truth no other than remnants of the ancient Britons, who, when driven out by the Saxons, took refuge in thoſe iſlands, and in that part of France which had before been called <hi rend="italic">Armorica,</hi> and from hence ſtyled <hi rend="italic">Bretagne, Brittany,</hi> or Li <hi rend="italic">ttle Britain,</hi> and the people <hi rend="italic">Bretons.</hi> This, in all probability, was a great relief to thoſe who dwelt in thoſe iſles; who, during the long civil war between the houſes of York and Lancaſter, had their intercourſe with England ſo much interrupted, that if it had not been for this commerce with their neighbours on the French coaſt, they might have been driven to the laſt diſtreſs.</p><p>The Scilly, or Silley iſlands, lie due weſt from the Lizard about 17 leagues; weſt and by ſouth from the old Land’s End, next Mount’s Bay, at the diſtance of 10 leagues; and from the weſtern Land’s End, they lie weſt-ſouth-weſt, at the diſtance of ſomething more than nine leagues. There are five of them inhabited; and that called <hi rend="italic">Sam</hi> ſ <hi rend="italic">on</hi> has one family in it. The largeſt of theſe is St Mary’s, which lies in the north latitude of 49 degrees 55 minutes, and in the longitude of 6 degrees 40 minutes weſt from Greenwich. It is two miles and a half in length, about one and a half in breadth, and between nine and ten miles in compaſs. On the weſt ſide there projects an iſthmus. Beyond this there is a peninſula, which is very high; and upon which ſtands Star Caſtle, built in 1593, with ſome outworks and batteries. On theſe there are upwards of threeſcore pieces of cannon mounted; and for the defence of which there is a garriſon of an entire company, with a maſter-gunner and ſix other gunners. In the magazine there are arms for 300 iſlanders, who, when ſummoned, are bound to march into the fortreſs. Underneath the caſtle barracks and lines ſtands Hugh Town, very improperly built, as lying ſo low as to be ſubject to inundations. A mile within land ſtands Church Town, ſo denominated from their place of worſhip; it conſiſts of a few houſes only, with a court-house. About two furlongs eaſt of this lies the Old Town, where there are more houſes, and ſome of them very convenient dwellings. The number of inhabitants in this iſland is about 600 or 700; and it produces to the lord proprietor 300 1. <hi rend="italic">per annum.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Treſcow</hi> lies directly north from St Mary’s, at the diſtance of two miles. It was formerly ſtyled <hi rend="italic">St Nicholas’s island;</hi> and was at leaſt as large as St Mary’s, though at preſent about half the ſize. The remains of the abbey are yet viſible, the ſituation well choſen, with a fine baſon of freſh water before it, half a mile long and a furlong wide, with an ever-green bank high enough to keep out the ſea, and ſerving at once to preſerve the pond, and ſhelter the abbey. In this pond there are moſt excellent eels, and the lands lying round it are by far the beſt in thoſe iſlands. There are about half a ſcore ſtone houſes, with a church, which are called <hi rend="italic">Dolphin Town;</hi> an old caſtle built in the reign of Henry VIII. called Oliver’s Caſtle; and a new block-houſe, railed out of the ruins of that caſtle, which is of far greater uſe. This iſland is particularly noted for producing plenty of the fineſt ſamphire, and the only tin works that are now viſible are found here. There are upon it at preſent about 40 families, who are very induſtrious, and ſpin more wool than in St Mary’s. Its annual value is computed at 80 l. a-year.</p><p>A mile to the eaſt of Treſcaw, and about two miles from the moſt northern part of St Mary’s, lies the iſle of <hi rend="italic">St Martin’s,</hi> not much inferior in ſize to that of Treſcaw. It very plainly appears to have been formerly extremely well cultivated; notwithſtanding which it was entirely deſerted, till within ſomewhat leſs than a century ago, that Mr Thomas Ekines, a conſiderable merchant, engaged ſome people to ſettle there. He likewiſe cauſed to be erected a hollow tower twenty feet in height, with a ſpire of as many feet more; which being neatly covered with lime, ſerves as a day- mark for directing ſhips croſſingthe channel or coming into Scilly. St Martin’s produces ſome corn, affords the beſt paſture in theſe iſlands, nouriſhes a great number of ſheep, and has upon it 17 families, who pretend to have the ſecret of burning the beſt kelp, and are extremely attached to their own iſland. As a proof of this, it is obſervable, that though ſome of the inhabitants rent lands in St Mary’s, yet they continue to reſide here, going thither only occaſionally.</p><p><hi rend="italic">St Agnes,</hi> which is alſo called the <hi rend="italic">Light-houſe Iſland,</hi> lies near three miles ſouth-Weſt of St Mary’s; and is, though a very little, a very well cultivated iſland, fruitful in corn and graſs. The only inconvenience to which the people who live in it are ſubject, is the want of good water, as their capital advantage conſiſts in having ſeveral good coves or ſmall ports, where boats may lie with ſafety; which, however, are not much uſed. The light-houſe is the principal ornament and great ſupport of the iſland, which ſtands on the moſt elevated ground, built with ſtone from the foundation to the lanthorn, which is fifty-one feet high, the gallery four, the ſaſh-lights eleven teet and a half high, three feet two inches wide, and ſixteen in number. The floor of the lanthorn is of brick, upon which ſtands a ſubſtantial iron grate, ſquare, barred on every ſide, with one great chimney in the canopy-roof, and ſeveral leſſer ones to let out the ſmoke, and a large pair of ſmith’s bellows<pb facs="gri_33125011196389_0714.tif" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0708"/>
are ſo fixed as to be eaſily uſed whenever there is occaſion. Upon the whole, it is a noble and commodious ſtructure; and being plaſtered white, is a uſeful day- mark to all ſhips coming from the ſouthward. The keeper of this light-houſe has a ſalary from the Trinity- houſe at Deptford of 40 1. a-year, with a dwelling-houſe and ground for a garden. His aſſiſtant has 20 1. a-year. It is ſupplied with coals by an annual ſhip; and the carriage of theſe coals from the ſea-ſide to the light-houſe is looked on as a conſiderable benefit to the poor inhabitants. They have a neat little church, built by the Godolphin family. There are at preſent 50 houſeholds in the iſland, which yield the proprietor 40 1. a-year.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Brehar,</hi> or, as pronounced, <hi rend="italic">Bryer iſland,</hi> lies north- weſt of St Mary’s, and to the weſt of Treſcaw, to which, when the ſea is very low, they ſometimes paſs over the ſand. It is very mountainous, abounds with ſea and land fowls, excellent ſamphire, and a great variety of medical herbs. There are at preſent thirteen families, who have a pretty church, and pay 301. a-year to the proprietor.</p><p>South from hence, and weſt from Treſcaw, ſtands the iſland of <hi rend="italic">Samſon,</hi> in which there is not above one family, who ſubſiſt chiefly by the making of kelp. To the weſtward of theſe there lie four iſlands, which contain in the whole 360 acres of meadow and arable land. The <hi rend="italic">eastern isles,</hi> ſo denominated from their poſition in reſpect to St Mary’s, contain 123 acres; and there are alſo ſeven other rocky and ſcattered ſlands, that have each a little land of ſome uſe; and beſides theſe, innumerable rocks on every ſide, among which we muſt reckon <hi rend="italic">Sally,</hi> now nothing more than a large, ill-ſhaped, craggy, inacceſſible iſland, lying the fartheſt north-weſt of any of them, and consequently the neareſt to the continent.</p><p>The air of theſe iſlands is equally mild and pure; their winters are ſeldom ſubject to froſt or ſnow. When the former happens, it laſts not long; and the latter never lies upon the ground. The heat of their ſummers is much abated by ſea-breezes. They are indeed frequently incommoded by ſea fogs, but theſe are not unwholeſome. Agues are rare, and fevers more ſo. The moſt fatal diſtemper is the ſmall-pox; yet thoſe who live temperately ſurvive commonly to a great age, and are remarkably free from diſeaſes. The ſoil is very good, and produces grain of all ſorts (except wheat, of which they had anciently plenty) in large quantities. They ſtill grow a little wheat, but the bread made of it is unpleaſant. They eat, for this reaſon, chiefly what is made of barley; and of this they have ſuch abundance, that though they uſe it both for bread and beer, they have more than ſuffices for their own conſumption. The uſe of potatoes is a new improvement; and they proſper to ſuch a degree, that in ſome places there are two crops in a-year. Roots of all ſorts, pulſe, and ſalads, grow well; dwarf fruit-trees, gooſe- berries, currants, raſpberries, and every thing of that kind, under proper ſhelter, thrive exceedingly; but they have no trees, though formerly they had elder; and porthelik, i. e. the harbour of willows, proves they had theſe likewiſe; and with a little care, no doubt, great improvements might be made. The ranunculus, anemone, and moſt kinds of flowers, are ſucceſsfully cultivated in their gardens. They have wild fowl of all</p><p>ſorts, from the ſwan to the ſnipe; and a particular kind called the <hi rend="italic">hedge chicken,</hi> which is not inferior to the ortolan: alſo tame fowl, puffins, and rabbits, in great numbers. Their black cattle are generally ſmall, but very well taſtled, though they feed upon ore-weed. Their horſes are little, but ſtrong and lively. They have alſo large flocks of fine ſheep, whoſe fleeces are tolerably good and their fleſh excellent. There are no venomous creatures in theſe iſlands.</p><p>We muſt now paſs to the ſea, which is of more conſequence to theſe isles than that ſmall portion of land which is diſtributed amongſt them. St Mary’s harbour is very ſafe and capacious, having that iſland on the ſouth; the eaſtern iſlands, with that of St Martin, on the eaſt; Treſcaw, Brehar, and Samſon, to the north; St Agnes and ſeveral ſmall iſlands to the weſt. Ships ride here in three to five fathom water, with good anchorage. Into this harbour there are four inlets, viz. Broad Sound, Smith’s Sound, St Mary’s Sound, and Crow Sound: ſo that hardly any wind can blow with which a ſhip of 150 tons cannot ſafely ſail through one or other of them, Crow Sound only excepted, where they cannot paſs at low water, but at high there is from 16 to 24 feet in this paſſage. Beſides theſe there are two other harbours; one called <hi rend="italic">New Grynſey,</hi> which lies between Brehar and Treſcaw, where ſhips of 300 tons may ride ſecurely. The other is called <hi rend="italic">Old Grynſey,</hi> and lies between Treſcaw, St Helen’s, and Theon, for ſmaller ſhips. The former is guarded by the batteries at Oliver’s Caſtle; the latter by the Blockhouſe, on the eaſtern ſide of Treſcaw, called <hi rend="italic">Dover.</hi> Small coaſters bound to the northward have more convenient outlets from theſe little harbours than from St Mary’s, where, at the weſt end of Hugh Town, there is a fine pier built by the preſent earl of Godolphin, 430 feet long, 20 feet wide in the narroweſt part, and 23 feet in height, with 16 feet of water at a ſpring, and 10 at a neap tide; ſo that under the ſhelter of this pier, veſſels of 150 tons may lie ſecurely, not only cloſe to the quay, but all along the ſtrand of the town.</p><p>In this harbour, and in all the little coves of the ſeveral iſles, prodigious quantities of mackerel may be caught in their ſeaſon; alſo ſoal, turbot, and plaiſe, remarkably good in their kind; and ling, which from its being a thicker fiſh, mellower, and better fed, is very juſtly preferred to any caught nearer our own coaſts. Salmon, cod, pollock, are in great plenty, and pilchards in vaſt abundance. To theſe we may add the alga marina, fucus, or ore-weed, which ſerves to feed both their ſmall and great cattle, manures their lands, is burned into kelp, is of uſe in phyſic, is ſometimes preſerved, ſometimes pickled, and is in many other reſpects very beneficial to the inhabitants, of whom we are next to ſpeak.</p><p>The people of Scilly in general are robuſt, handſome, active, hardy, induſtimus, generous, and good- natured; ſpeak the Engliſh language with great propriety; have ſtrong natural parts (though for want of a good ſchool they have little education), as appears by their dexterity in the ſeveral employments to which they are bred. They cultivate moſt of their lands as well as can be expected under their preſent circumſtances. They are bred from their infancy to the management of their boats, in which they excel; are good<pb facs="gri_33125011196389_0715.tif" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0709"/>
fiſhermen, and excellent pilots. Their women are admirable houſewives, ſpin their own wool, weave it into coarſe cloth, and knit ſtockings. They have no timber of their own growth, and not much from England; yet they have many joiners and cabinet-makers, who, out of the fine woods which they obtain from captains of ſhips who put in here, make all kinds of domeſtic furniture in a very neat manner. They are free from the land-tax, malt-tax, and exciſe; and being furniſhed with plenty of liquors from the veſſels which are driven into their roads for refreſhment, for neceſſary repairs, or to wait for a fair wind, in return for proviſions and other conveniences; this, with what little fiſh they can cure, makes the beſt part of their trade, if we except their kelp, which has been a growing manufacture for theſe fourſcore years, and produces at preſent about 500 1. per annum.</p><p>The right honourable the carl of Godolphin is ſtyled proprietor of Scilly, in virtue of letters-patent granted to the late earl, then lord Godolphin, dated the 25th of July 1698, for the term of 89 years, to be computed from the end and expiration of a term of 50 years, granted to Francis Godolphin, Eſq; by king Charles I.; that is, from the year 1709 to 1798, when his leaſe determines. In virtue of this royal grant, his lordſhip is the ſole owner of all lands, houſes, and tenements; claims all the tithes, not only of the fruits of the earth, but of fiſh taken at ſea and landed upon thoſe premiſes; harbour-duties paid by ſhips; and one moiety of the wrecks, the other belonging to the admiralty. There is only one eccleſiaſtical perſon upon the iſlands, who reſides at St Miry’s, and viſits the other inhabited iſlands once a-year. But divine ſervice is peformed, and ſermons read, every Sunday in the churches of thoſe iſlands, by an honeſt layman appointed for that purpoſe; and there are likewiſe church-wardens and overſeers, regularly cholen in every pariſh. As to the civil government, it is adminiſtered by what is called the <hi rend="italic">Court oſ Twelve;</hi> in which the commander in chief, the proprietor’s agent, and the chaplain, have their ſeats in virtue of their offices: the other nine are choſen by the people. Theſe decide, or rather compromiſe, all differences; and puniſh ſmall offences by fines, whippings, and the ducking-ſtool: as to greater enormities, we many conclude they have not been hitherto known; ſince, except for the ſoldiers, there is no priſon in the iſlands. But in cafe of capital offences, the criminals may be tranſported to the county of Cornwall, and there brought to juſtice.</p><p>The great importance of theſe iſlands ariſes from their advantageous ſituation, as looking equally into St George’s Channel, which divides Great Britain from Ireland, and the Engliſh Channel, which ſeparates Britain from France. For this reaſon, moſt ſhips bound from the ſouthward ſtrive to make the Scilly iſlands, in order to ſteer their courſe with greater certainty. It is very convenient alſo for veſſels to take ſhelter amongſt them; which, prevents their being driven to Milford Haven, nay ſometimes into ſome port in Ireland, if the wind is ſtrong at eaſt; or, if it blows hard at north- weſt, from being forced back into ſome of the Corniſh harbours, or even on the French coaſts. If the wind ſhould not be very high, yet if unfavourable or unſteady, as between the channels often happens, it is better to put into Scilly, than to beat about at ſea in bad weather.</p><p>The intercourſe between theſe two channels is another motive why ſhips come in here, as chooſing rather to wait in ſafety for a wind, than to run the hazard of being blown out of their courſe; and therefore a ſtrong gale at eaſt ſeldom fails of bringing tlrirty or forty veſſels, and frequently a larger number, into Scilly; not more to their own ſatisfaction than to that of the inhabitants. Ships homeward-bound from America often touch there, from the deſire of making the firſt land in their power, and for the ſake of refreſhment. Theſe reaſons have an influence on foreign ſhips, as well as our own; and afford the natives an opportunity of ſhowing their wonderful dexterity in conducting them ſafely into St Mary’s harbour, and, when the wind ſerves, through their founds. Upon firing a gun and making a waft, a boat immediately puts off from the neareſt iſland, with ſeveral pilots on board; and having with amazing activity dropped one of them into every ſhip, till only two men are left in the boat, theſe return again to land, as the wind and other circumſtances direct, in one of their little coves.</p><p>Reſpecting a current which often prevails to the weſt-ward of Scilly, Mr Rennel has publiſhed ſome obſervations of much importance. “It is a circumſtance (ſays he) well known to ſeamen, "that ſhips, in coming from the Atlantic, and fleering a courſe for the Britiſh channel, in a parallel ſomewhat to the ſouth of the Scilly iſlands, do notwithſtanding often find themſelves to the north of thoſe iſlands; or, in other words, in the mouth of St George’s or of the Briſtol channel. This extraordinary error has paſſed for the effects either of bad ſteerage, bad obſervations of latitude, or the indraught of the Briſtol channel: but none of theſe account for it ſatisfactorily; becauſe, admitting that at times there may be an indraught, it cannot be ſuppoſed to extend to Scilly; and the cafe has happened in weather the moſt favourable for navigating and for taking observations. The conſequences of this deviation from the intended tract have very often been fatal; particularly in the loſs of the Nancy packet in our own times, and that of Sir Cloudeſley Shovel and others of his fleet at the beginning of the preſent century. Numbers of cafes, equally melancholy, but of leſs celebrity, have occurred; and many others, in which the danger has been imminent, but not fatal, have ſcarcely reached the public ear. All of theſe have been referred to accident; and therefore no attempt ſeems to have been made to inveſtigate the cauſe of them.</p><p>“I am, however, of opinion, that, they may be imputed to a ſpeciſic cauſe; namely, a current: and I ſhall therefore endeavour to inveſtigate both that and its effects, that ſeamen may be apprized of the times when they are particularly to expect, it in any conſiderable degree of ſtrehgth; for then only it is likely to occaſion miſchief, the current that prevails at ordinary times being probably too weak to produce an error in the reckoning, equal to the difference of parallel between the ſouth part, of Scilly and the tract in which a commander, prudent in his meaſures, but unſuſpicious of a current, would chooſe to ſail.”</p><p>The original cauſe of this current is the prevalence of weſterly winds in the Atlantic, which impel the waters along the north coaſt of Spain, and accumulate them in the Bay of Biſcay; whence they are projected along the coaſt of France, in a direction north-weſt by<pb facs="gri_33125011196389_0716.tif" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0710"/>
weſt to the weſt of Scilly and Ireland. The major aſſigns ſtrong reaſons for the exiſtence of this current between Uſhant and Ireland, in a chart of the tracts of the Hector and Atlas, Eaſt India ſhips, in 1778 and 1787. The following remarks on the effect of this current are abridged ſrom the author’s work, which is well worthy the peruſal of all ſailors and ſhipmaſters.</p><p>1 ft, If a ſhip croſſes it obliquely, that is, in an eaſt by ſouth or more ſoutherly direction, ſhe will continue much longer in it, and of courſe be more affected by it, than if ſhe croſſed it more directly. The ſame conſequence will happen if ſhe croſſes it with light winds. 2dly, A good obſervation of latitude at noon would be thought a ſufficient warrant for running eaſtward during a long night; yet as it may be poſſible to remain in the current long enough to be carried from a parallel, which may be deemed a very ſafe one, to that of the rocks of Scilly, it would appear prudent, after experiencing a continuance of ſtrong weſterly winds in the Atlantic, and approaching the Channel with light ſoutherly winds, either to make Uſhant in time of peace, or at all events to keep in the parallel of 48⁰ 45' at the higheſt. 3dly, Ships bound to the weſtward, from the mouth of the Channel, with the wind in the ſouth-weſt quarter, ſhould prefer the larboard tack. 4thly, Major Rennel approves the deſign of removing the light- houſe of Scilly (if it be not already removed) to the ſouth-weſt part of the high rocks. 5thly, He recommends the fending a veſſel, with time-keepers on board, to examine the foundings between the parallels of Scilly and Uſhant; from the meridian of the Lizard Point as far weſt as the moderate depths extend. A ſet of timekeepers, he obſerves, will effect more in one ſummer, in ſkilful hands, than all the ſcience of Dr Halley could do in the courſe of a long life.</p><p>In time of war, the importance of theſe iſlands is ſtill more conſpicuous; and it is highly probable, that they afforded the allies a place for aſſembling their fleet, when the Britons, Danes, Scots, and Iriſh, ſailed under the command of Anlaff, to attack King Athelſtan; which convinced him of the neceſſity of adding them to his dominions. Upon the like principle, Henry VIII. when upon bad terms with his neighbours, cauſed an old fortreſs to be repaired; and Queen Elizabeth, who had more to fear, directed the conſtruction of a caſtle, which, in part at leaſt, ſtill remains. But the moſt ſingular inſtance ot the detriment that might ariſe ſrom theſe iſlands falling into other hands than our own happened in 1651, when Sir John Grenville took ſhelter in them with the remains of the Corniſh cavaliers. For the depredations committed by his frigates ſoon made it evident that Scilly was the key of the Engliſh commerce; and the clamours of the merchants thereupon roſe ſo high, that the parliament were forced to ſend a fleet of fifty ſail, with a great body of land-forces on board, under Sir George Avſcue and admiral Blake, who with great difficulty, and no inconſiderable loſs, made themſelves matters of Treſcaw and Brehar; where they erected thoſe lines and fortifications near the remains of the old fortreſs that are called <hi rend="italic">Oliver's Caſtle.</hi> But at length, finding that little was to be done in that way, they choſe to grant Sir John Grenville a moſt honourable capitulation, as the ſureſt means to recover places of ſuch conſequence: with which the parliament were very little</p><p>ſatisſied, till Mr Blake gave them his reaſons; which appeared to be ſo well founded, that they directed the articles he had concluded to be punctually carried into execution.</p></div></body></text></TEI>