<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196389_0617.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0611-05" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SALICORNIA, <hi rend="smallcaps">jointed glass-wort,</hi></label>
 or <hi rend="italic">Saltwort</hi>: A genus of the monogynia order, belonging to the monandria claſs of plants; and in the natural method ranking under the 12th order, <hi rend="italic">Holoraceae.</hi> The calyx is ventricoſe, or a little ſwelling out and entire; there are no petals, and but one ſeed. There are four ſpecies, of which the rtroſt remarkable are, I. The fruticoſa, with obtuſe points, grows plentifully in moſt of the ſalt marſhes which are overflowed by the tides in many parts of England. It is an annual plant, with thick, ſucculent, jointed ſtalks, which trail upon the ground. The flowers are produced at the ends of the joints toward the extremity of the branches, which are ſmall, and ſcarce diſcernible by the naked eye. 2. The</p><p>perennis, with a ſhrubby branching ſtalk, grows naturally in Sheppey iſland. This hath a ſhrubby branching ſtalk about ſix inches long 5 the points of the articulations are acute; the ſtalks branch from the bottom, and form a kind of pyramid. They are perennial, and produce their flowers in the ſame manner as the former.</p><p>The inhabitants near the ſea-coaſts where theſe plants grow, cut them up toward the latter end of ſummer, when they are fully grown; and, after having dried them in the fun, they burn them for their aſhes, which are uſed in making of glaſs and ſoap. Theſe herbs are by the country people called <hi rend="italic">kelp,</hi> and promiſcuouſly gathered for uſe. See the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Salsola;</hi> alſo <hi rend="italic">Dyeing of LEATHER,</hi> p. 750, note A.</p></div></body></text></TEI>