<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196389_0666.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0660-01" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SARDIS</label>,
or <hi rend="smallcaps">Sardes,</hi> now called <hi rend="italic">Sardo</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Sart,</hi> is an ancient town of Natolia in Aſia, about 40 miles eaſt of Smyrna. It was much celebrated in early antiquity, was enriched by the fertility of the ſoil, and had been the capital of the Lydian kings. It was ſeated on the ſide of mount Tmolus; and the citadel, placed on a lofty hill, was remarkable for its great ſtrength. It was the ſeat of King Croeſus, and was in his time taken by Cyrus; after which the Perſian Satrapas or commandant reſided at Sardis as the emperor did at Suſa. The city was alſo taken, burnt, and then evacuated by the Mileſians in the time of Darius, and the city and for- treſs ſurrendered on the approach of Alexander alter the battle of Granicus. Under the Romans Sardis was a very conſiderable place till the time of Tiberius Caeſar, when it buffered prodigiouſly by an earthquake. The munificence of the emperor, however, was nobly exerted to repair the various damages it then ſuſtained. Julian attempted to reſtore the heathen worſhip in the place. He erected temporary altars where none had been left, and repaired the temples if any veſtiges remained. In the year 400 it was plundered by the Goths, and ſt ſuffered conſiderably in the ſubſequent troubles</p><p>of Aſia. On the incurſion of the Tartars in 1304, the Turks were permitted to occupy a portion of the citadel, ſeparated by a ſtrong wall with a gate, and were afterwards murdered in their ſleep. The ſite of this once noble city is now green and flowery, the whole being reduced to a poor village, containing nothing but wretched huts. There are, however, ſome curious remains of antiquity about it, and ſome ruins which diſplay its ancient grandeur. See <hi rend="italic">Chandler's Travels in A</hi> ſ <hi rend="italic">ia Minor,</hi> p. 251, &amp;c <hi rend="italic">.</hi></p><p>There is in the place a large caravanſary, where travellers may commodiouſly lodge. The inhabitants are generally ſhepherds, who lead their ſheep into the fine paſtures of the neighbouring plain. The Turks have a moſque here, which was a Chriſtian church, at the gate of which there are ſeveral columns of poliſhed marble. There are a few Chriſtians, who are employed in gardening. E. Long. 28. 5. N. Lat. 37. 51.</p></div></body></text></TEI>