<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196389_0721.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0715-03" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SCOMBER</label>,
the <hi rend="smallcaps">Mackerel,</hi> in ichthyology, a genus belonging to the order of thoracici. The head is ſmooth and compreſſed, and there are ſeven rays in the gill membrane. There are ten ſpecies; — of which the moſt remarkable are the following.</p><p>1. The ſcomber, or common mackerel, a ſummer-fiſh of paſſage that viſits our ſhores in vaſt ſhoals. It is leſs uſeful than other ſpecies of gregarious fiſh, being very tender, and unfit for carriage; not but that it may be preierved by pickling and ſalting, a method, we believe, practiſed only in Cornwall, where it proves a great relief to the poor during winter. It was a ſiſh greatly eſteemed by the Romans, becauſe it furniſhed the precious garum, a ſort of pickle that gave a high reliſh to their fauces; and was beſides uſed medicinally. It was drawn from different kinds of fiſh, but that made from the mackerel had the preference: the beſt was made at<pb facs="gri_33125011196389_0722.tif" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0716"/>
Carthagena, vaſt quantities of mackerel being taken near an adjacent iſle, called from that circumſtance <hi rend="italic">Scombraria,</hi> and the garum, prepared by a certain company in that city, bore a high price, and was diſtinguiſhed by the title of <hi rend="italic">garum ſociorum.</hi> This fiſh is eaſily taken by a bait; but the beſt time is during a freſh gale of wind, which is thence called a <hi rend="italic">mackerel gale.</hi> In the ſpring the eyes of mackerel are almoſt covered with a white film; during which period they are half blind. This film grows in winter, and is caſt the beginning of ſummer. It is not often that it exceeds two pounds in weight, yet there have been inſtances of ſome that weighed upwards of five. The noſe is taper and ſharp pointed; the eyes large; the jaws of an equal length; the teeth ſmall, but numerous. The form of this fiſh is very elegant. The body is a little compreſſed on the ſides: towards the tail it grows very ſlender, and a little angular. It is a moſt beautiful fiſh when alive; for nothing can equal the brilliancy of its colour, which death impairs, but does not wholly obliterate.</p><p>2. The thunnus, or tunny, was a fiſh well known to the ancients: it made a conſiderable branch of commerce: the time of its arrival in the Mediterranean from the ocean was obſerved, and ſtations for taking them were eſtabliſhed in places it moſt frequented.</p><p>There are ſtill very conſiderable tunny fiſheries on the coaſt of Sicily, as well as ſeveral other parts of the Mediterranean; where they are cured, and make a great article of proviſion in the adjacent kingdoms. — They are caught in nets, and amazing quantities are taken; for they come in vaſt ſhoals, keeping along the ſhores. See <hi rend="italic">Tunny-FISHERY.</hi></p><p>They frequent our coaſts, but not in ſhoals like the tunnies of the Mediterranean. They are not uncommon in the lochs on the weſtern coaſt of Scotland; where they come in purſuit of herrings; and often during night ſtrike into the nets, and do conſiderable damage. When the fiſhermen draw them up in the morning, the tunny riſes at the ſame time towards the ſurface, ready to catch the fiſh that drop out. On perceiving it, a ſtrong hook baited with a herring, and faſtened to a rope, is inſtantly flung out, which the tunny ſeldom fails to take. As ſoon as hooked, it loſes all ſpirit; and after a very little reſiſtance ſubmits to its fate. It is dragged to the ſhore and cut up, either to be ſold freſh to people who carry it to the country markets, or is preſerved ſalted in large caſks. The pieces, when freſh, look exactly like raw beef; but when boiled turn pale, and have ſomething of the flavour of ſalmon.</p><p>One that was taken when Mr Pennant was at Inverary in 1769, weighed 460 pounds. The fiſh was ſeven feet ten inches long: the greateſt circumference five feet ſeven; the leaſt near the tail one foot fix. The body was round and thick, and grew ſuddenly very ſlender towards the tail, and near that part was angular. The irides were of a plain green: the teeth very minute. The tail was in form of a creſcent; and two feet ſeven inches between tip and tip. The ſkin on the back was ſmooth, very thick, and black. On the belly the ſcales were viſible. The colour of the ſides and belly was ſilvery, tinged with caerulean and pale purple: near the tail marbled with grey.</p><p>They are known on the coaſt of Scotland by the</p><p>name of <hi rend="italic">mackrelſture: Mackrel,</hi> from being of that genus; and <hi rend="italic">ſture,</hi> from the Daniſh, <hi rend="italic">stor</hi> “great. ”</p></div></body></text></TEI>