<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196389_0587.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0581-01" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SABBATH</label>,
in the Hebrew language, ſignifies <hi rend="italic">rest.</hi> The ſeventh day was denominated the <hi rend="italic">Sabbath, or day of rest,</hi> becauſe that in it God had reſted from all his works which he created and made. From that time the ſeventh day ſeems to have been ſet apart for religious services; and, in conſequence of a particular injunction, was afterwards obſerved. by the Hebrews as an holyday. They were commanded to ſet it apart for ſacred purpoſes in honour or the creation, and likewiſe in memorial of their own redemption from Egyptian bondage.</p><p>The importance of the inſtitution may be gathered from the different laws reſpecting it. When the ten commandments were publiſhed from Mount Sinai in tremendous pomp, the law of the Sabbath held a place in what is commonly called the firſt table, and by ſubsequent ſtatutes the violation of it was to be puniſhed with death. Six days were allowed for the use and ſervice of man; but the ſeventh day God reſerved to himſelf, and appointed it to be obſerved as a ſtated time for holy offices, and to be ſpent in the duties of piety and devotion. On this day the miniſters of the temple entered upon their week; and thoſe who had attended on the temple ſervice the preceding week went out at the fame time. New loaves of ſhew-bread were placed upon the golden table, and the old ones taken away. Two lambs for a burnt-offering, with a certain proportion of fine flour, mingled with oil, for a bread-offering, and wine for a libation, were offered. The Sabbath, as all other feſtivals, was celebrated from evening to evening. It began at six in the evening on Friday, and ended at the ſame time the next day.</p><p>Concerning the time at which the Sabbath was firſt inſtituted, different opinions have been held. Some have maintained, that the ſanctification of the ſeventh day, mentioned in Gen. ii. is only there ſpoken of δια <hi rend="italic">τςολϵψιt</hi> or by anticipation; and is to be underſtood of the Sabbath afterwards injoined the children of Israel at the commencement of the Moſaic diſpenſation. But without entering into a particular examination of all the arguments adduced to ſupport this opinion, a few obſervations, it is preſumed, will be ſufficient to ſhow that it reſts on no ſolid foundation.</p><p>It cannot eaſily be ſuppoſed that the inſpired penman would have mentioned the ſanctification of the ſeventh day amongſt the primeval tranſactions, if ſuch ſanctification had not taken place until 2500 years afterwards. Writers, ambitious of that artificial elegance which the rules of criticiſm have eſtabliſhed, often bring together in their narratives events which were themſelves far diſtant, for the fake of giving form to their diſcourſe; but Moſes appears to have deſpiſed all ſuch flimſy refinements, and to have conſtructed his narrative in great conformity to the series of events.</p><p>From the accounts we have of the religious ſervice practiſed in the patriarchal age, it appears that, immediately after the fall, when Adam was reſtored to favour through a Mediator, a ſtated form of public wor- ship was inſtituted, which man was required to obſerve in teſtimony, not only of his dependence on the Creator, but alſo of his <hi rend="italic">faith</hi> and <hi rend="italic">hope</hi> in the promiſe made to our firſt parents, and ſeen afar of. Of an inſtitution then ſo grand and important, no circumſtance would be omitted that is necessary to preſerve it, or that contributes to render the obſervance of it regular and ſolemn.</p><p>That determined times are neceſſary for the due celebration of divine ſervice, cannot be denied. Such is the conſtitution of man, that he muſt have particular times ſet apart for particular services. He is doomed to toil and labour; to earn his bread in the ſweat of his face; and is capable of performing religious duties only in ſuch a manner as is confident with his situation in the world. If ſtated times for religious solemnities had not been enjoined, the conſequence would have been, that ſuch iolemnities would have been altogether neglected; for experience ſhows, that if mankind were left at liberty when and how often they ſhould perform religious offices, theſe offices would not be performed at all. It is the obſervation of holy times that preſerves the practice of holy services; and without the frequent and regular returns of hallowed days, man would quickly forget the duty which he owes to God, and in a ſhort time no veſtige of religion would be found in the world.</p><p>Among the ordinances which God vouchsafed his ancient people, we find that the pious obſervation of holydays was particularly infiſted upon; and the Sabbath was enjoined to be kept holy, in the moſt ſolemn manner, and under the ſevereſt penalties. Can it then be ſuppoſed that He would ſuffer mankind, from the creation of the world to the Moſaic era, to remain without an inſtitution ſo expedient in itſelf, and as well fitted to anſwer the end proposed by it, under the one diſpenſation, as ever it could be under the other? No; we have every imaginable reaſon to conclude, that when religious services were enjoined, religious times were appointed alſo; for the one neceffarily implies the other.</p><p>It is no objection to the early inſtitution of the Sabbath, that there is no mention of it in the hiſtory of the patriarchal age. It would have ſwelled the Bible to a moſt enormous ſize, had the ſacred hiſtorian given a particular account of all the tranſactions of thoſe times; besidcs, it would have anſwered no end. When Moſes wrote the book of Genesis, it was unnecessary to relate minutely tranſactions and inſtitutions already well known by tradition: accordingly we ſee, that his narrative is everywhere very concise, and calculated only to preſerve the memory of the moſt important facts. However, if we take a view of the church-ſervice of the patriarchal age, we ſhall find that what is called the <hi rend="italic">legal</hi> diſpenſation, at leaſt the liturgie part of it, was no new ſyſtem, but a collection of inſtitutions obſerved from the beginning, and republiſhed in form by Moſes. The Scriptures inform us that Cain and Abel offered ſacrifices; and the account which is given of the acceptance of the one, and the rejection of the other, evidently ſhows that ſtated laws reſpecting the ſervice had then taken place. “ In proceſs of time,” <hi rend="italic">at the end of the days,</hi> “Abel brought an offering.” Here was <hi rend="italic">prieft, altar, matter oſ ſacrifice, appointed time, motive to ſacrifice, atonement made,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">accepted.</hi> The diſtinction of animals into clean and unclean before the flood, and</p><p>Noah’s ſacrifice immediately after his deliverance, without any new direction, is an unanſwerable proof of the ſame truth. It is teſtiſied of Abraham, by God himſelf, that he kept his <hi rend="italic">charge,</hi> his <hi rend="italic">commandments,</hi> his <hi rend="italic">statutes,</hi> and his <hi rend="italic">laws.</hi> Theſe expressions comprehend the various branches, into which the law given at Sinai was divided. They contain the moral precepts, affirmative and negative, the matter of religious ſervice, a body of<pb facs="gri_33125011196389_0588.tif" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0582"/>
laws to direct obedience, and to which man was to conform his conduct in every part oſ duty. Agreeably to this, we find that ſacrifices were offered, altars and places of worſhip conſecrated, and the <hi rend="italic">Sabbath</hi> alſo mentioned as a well known ſolemnity, before the promulgation of the law. It is expreſsly taken notice of at the fall of manna; and the incidental manner in which it is then mentioned, is a convincing proof that the lſraelites were no ſtrangers to the inſtitution: for had it been a <hi rend="italic">new</hi> one, it must have been enjoined in a poſitive and particular manner, and the nature of it must have been laid open and explained, othferwiſe the term would have conveyed no meaning.</p><p>The diviſion of time into <hi rend="italic">weeks,</hi> or periods of ſeven days, which obtained ſo early and almoſt universally, is a ſtrong indication that <hi rend="italic">one</hi> day in ſeven was always diſtinguiſhed in a particular manner.<note anchored="true" n="1" place="margin" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">* שבע</hi> Seven.</p></note> <hi rend="italic">Week</hi> *, and <hi rend="italic">ſeven days,</hi> are in ſcripture language ſynonymous terms. God commanded Noah, <hi rend="italic">ſeven days</hi> before he entered the ark, to introduce into it all forts of living creatures. When the waters of the flood began to abate, Noah ſent forth a dove, which, finding no reft for the ſole of her foot, returned to him. After <hi rend="italic">ſeven days</hi> he ſent forth the dove a ſecond time, and again ſhe returned to the ark. At the expiration of other <hi rend="italic">ſeven dαys</hi> he let go the dove a third time: and a <hi rend="italic">week</hi> is ſpoken of (Gen. xxix.) as a well known ſpace of time.</p><p>This ſeptenary diviſion of time has been, from the earlieſt ages, uniformly obſerved over all the eaſtern world. The Iſraelſtes, Aſſyrians, Lgyptians, Indians, Arabians, and Perſians, have always made uſe of a week, conſiſting of ſeven days. Many vain attempts have been made to account for this uniformity; but a practice ſo general and prevalent could never have taken place, had not the ſeptenary diſtribution of time been inſtituted from the beginning, and handed down by tradition.</p><p>From the same ſource alſo muſt the ancient heathens have derived their notions of the ſacredneſs of the seventh day. That they had ſuch notions of it is evident from ſeveral paſſages of the Greek poets quoted by Ariſtobulus, a learned Jew, by Clement of Alexandria, and Euſebius.</p><p><hi rend="italic">ὲϐϛομη ίερον ήμαρ.</hi> Hefiod.</p><p>The ſeventh, the <hi rend="italic">ſacred</hi> day.</p><p><hi rend="italic">F. ϐϛοματη</hi> δ'ηπειτ χατηλυθεν, ίηετγ ήμαρ. Homer.</p><p>Afterwards came the ſeventh, the <hi rend="italic">facred</hi> day. Again:</p><p>Εϐϛομον ήμαρ εην, χαι τω τετλεςο παντα.</p><p>On the <hi rend="italic">seventh</hi> day all things were <hi rend="italic">completed.</hi></p><p>F <hi rend="italic">.</hi> ϐδοματη δηοι τετλησμενα παντα τετυχται. Linus.</p><p>All things were made <hi rend="italic">perfect</hi> on the <hi rend="italic">ſeventh</hi> day.</p><p>That they likewiſe held the number <hi rend="italic">ſeven</hi> in high eſtimation has been ſhown by a learned, though ſometimes fanciful, author<note anchored="true" n="2" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>* Holloway's Originals, <hi rend="italic">vol. ii.</hi> p. 60.</p></note> *, with ſuch evidence as to enforce conviction. The Pythagoreans call it the <hi rend="italic">venerable</hi> number, <hi rend="italic">σεϐαμ αϗιος</hi>, <hi rend="italic">worthy of veneration,</hi> and held it to be <hi rend="italic">perfect</hi> and <hi rend="italic">mοft proper</hi> to religion. They denominated it <hi rend="italic">fortune,</hi> and alſo ſtyled it <hi rend="italic">voice, ſound, muſe,</hi> becauſe, no doubt, <hi rend="italic">ſeven</hi> diſtinct notes comprehend the whole ſcaleof muſic, beyond which neither voice nor inſtrument can go, but muſt return from the ſeventh, and begin again anew. They likewiſe deſigned it τελεσϙορος, <hi rend="italic">leading to the end.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Seven,</hi> in the Hebrew language, is expreſſed by a word that primarily ſignifies <hi rend="italic">fulneſs, completion, ſufficiency,</hi> and is applied to a <hi rend="italic">week,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">ſeven days,</hi> because that was the <hi rend="italic">full</hi> time employed in the work, of creation; to the <hi rend="italic">Sabbath,</hi> becauſe on it all things were <hi rend="italic">completed;</hi> and to an <hi rend="italic">οath,</hi> becauſe it is <hi rend="italic">ſufficient</hi> to put an end to all ſtrife. This opening oſ the Hebrew root will enable us to come at the meaning of thoſe expreſſions of the heathens, and alſo let us see whence theyderived their ideas and modes of speaking, and that the knowledge of the tranſactions at the creation, though much perverted, was never entirely loſt by them.</p><p>It has been ſuppoſed by ſome, that the heathens borrowed the notion of the <hi rend="italic">ſacredneſs</hi> of the ſeventh day from the Jews. But this opinion will not readily be admitted, when it is conſidered that the Jews were held in the greateſt contempt by the ſurrounding nations, who derided them no leſs for their ſabbaths than for their circumciſion. All forts of writers ridiculed them on this account. Seneca charged them with ſpending the ſeventh part of their time in ſloth. Tacitus ſaid, that not only the ſeventh day, but alſo the ſeventh year, was unprofitably waited. Juvenal brings forward the same charge; and Perſius upbraided them with their <hi rend="italic">recutita ſabbata.</hi> Plutarch ſaid that they kept it in honour of Bacchus. Tacitus affirmed, that it was in honour of Saturn; but the moſt abominable aſſertion of all is that of Apion, who ſaid that they obſerved the Sabbath in memory of their being cured on that day of a</p><p>ſhameful diſeaſe, called by the Egyptians s <hi rend="italic">abbo.</hi></p><p>Some perceiving the force of this objection have contended, that time was divided into weeks of ſeven days, that each of the planetary gods, the Sun, Moon, Mercury, Venus, Mars, Jupiter, and Saturn, who were the <hi rend="italic">Dii majorum gentium,</hi> might have a day appropriated to his ſervice. But if ſuch was the origin of weeks, how came the great and ancient goddeſs <hi rend="italic">Tellus</hi> to be omitted ? She was worſhipped by the early idolaters as well as the other planets, and muſt ſurely have been deemed by them as worthy of a particular day ſet apart to her honour as the planet Saturn, who was long undiſcovered, afterwards ſeen but occaſionally, and at all times conſidered as of malign aſpect. (See <hi rend="smallcaps">Rem</hi> PHAN )</p><p>Others have ſuppoſed, that as the year was divided into lunar months of ſomething more than 28 days, it was natural to divide the month into quarters from the different phaſes of the moon, which would produce as many weeks of ſeven days. But this ſuppoſition is leſs tenable than the former. The phaſes of the moon are not ſo precilely marked at the quarters as to attract to them any particular notice, nor are the quarterly appearances of one month commonly like thoſe of another. We cannot, therefore, conceive what ſhould have induced the earlieſt obſervers of the phaſes of the moon to divide the month into four parts rather than into three, or five, or ſeven. Had the ancient week conſiſted of 14 days, it might have been inferred, with ſome degree of plauſibility, that its length was regulated by the phaſes of the moon, becauſe the ſhape of that luminary, at the end of the ſecond quarter, is very preciſely marked 5 but there is nothing which, in the preſent hypotheſis, could have everywhere led mankind to make their weeks conſiſt of ſeven days. This diviſion of time, therefore, can be accounted for only by admitting the primeval institution<pb facs="gri_33125011196389_0589.tif" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0583"/>
ſtitution of the Sabbath, as related by Moſes in the book of Geneſis. That inſtitution was abſolutely neceſſary to preſerve among men a ſenſe of religion; and it was renewed to the. Jews at the giving of the law, and its obſervance enforced by the ſevereſt penalties. It was accordingly obſerved by them with more or leſs ſtrictneſs in every period of their commonwealth, and there is none of the inſtitutions of their divine lawgiver which, in their preſent ſtate of diſperſion, they more highly honour. They regard it, indeed, with a ſuperſtitious reverence, call it their spous <hi rend="italic">e,</hi> their <hi rend="italic">delight,</hi> and ſpeak of it in the moſt magnificent terms. They have often varied in their opinions of the manner in which it ought to be kept. In the time of the Maccabees, they carried their reſpect for the ſabbath ſo very high, that they would not on that day defend themſelves from the attacks of their enemies. But afterwards they did not ſcruple to ſtand upon their neceſſary defence, although they would do nothing to prevent the enemy from carrying on their operations. When our Saviour was on earth, it was no ſin to looſe a beaſt from the ftall, and lead him to water; and if he had chanced to fall into a ditch, they pulled him out: but now it is abſolutely unlawful to give a creature in that ſituation any other aſſiſtance than that of food; and if they lead an animal to water, they muſt take care not to let the bridle or halter hang looſe, otherwiſe they are tranſgreſſors.</p><p>As the law enjoins reſt on that day from all ſervile employments, in order to comply with the injunction, they undertake no kind of work on Friday but ſuch as can eafily be accompliſhed before evening. In the afternoon they put into proper places the meat that they have prepared to eat the day following. They afterwards ſet out a table covered with a clean cloth, and place bread upon it, which they alſo cover with another cloth; and during the ſabbath the table is never moved out of its place. About an hour before ſunſet, the women light the ſabbath lamps, which hang in the places where they eat. They then ſtretch forth their hands to the light, and pronounce the following benediction. “Bleſſed be thou, O God, king of the world, who haſt enjoined us, that are ſanctified by thy commandments, to light the ſabbath lamp.” Theſe lamps are two or more in number, according to the ſize of the chamber in which they are ſuſpended, and continue to burn during the greateſt part of the night. In order to begin the ſabbath well, they waſh their hands and faces, trim their hair, and pare their nails, beginning at the fourth finger, then going to the second, then the fifth, then the third, and ending with the thumb. If a Jew caſts the parings of his nails to the ground, he is <hi rend="italic">raſcah,</hi> that is, a <hi rend="italic">wicked</hi> man; for Satan has great power over thoſe parings of nails; and it ſeems they are of great uſe to the wizzards, who know how to employ them in their enchantments. If he buries them in the earth, he is <hi rend="italic">tzedic,</hi> that is, a <hi rend="italic">just</hi> man: if he burns them in the fire, he is <hi rend="italic">chesιd,</hi> that is, worthy of honour, an holy man. When they have performed theſe preparatory ceremonies, they repair to the ſynagogue, and enter upon their devotions. As ſoon as prayers begin, the departed fouls ſpring out of the purgatorial flames, and have liberty to cool themſelves in water while the ſabbath lasts; for which reason the Jews prolong the continuance of it as much as they can; and the Rabbins have ſtrictly commanded them not to exhauſt all the water on tire ſabbath day, left thoſe miſerable ſouls ſhould by that means be deprived of the refreſhing element. When they have ended their prayers, they return home, and ſalute one another, by wiſhing a good ſabbath. They then sit down to table. The maſter of the family takes a cup full of wine, and lifting up his hand, says, “Bleſſed be thou, O God our Lord, king of the world, who haſt created the fruit of the vine.— Bleſſed be thou, O God our Lord, king of the world, who haſt ſanctified us by thy commandments, and given us thy holy ſabbath; and of thy good will and pleaſure haſt left it to us an inheritance, the memorial of thy works of creation. For it is the beginning of the congregation of faints, and the memorial of the coming out of Egypt. And thou haſt alſo chosen us from all other people, and ſanctified us, and with love and pleaſure haſt left thy holy ſabbath an inheritance. Bleſſed be thou, O God, who ſanctifieſt the ſabbath.” After this benediction is ended, he drinks, and gives the cup to all that are preſent. He then removes the cloth, and taking bread, ſays, “Bleſſed be thou, O God our Lord, king of the world, who bringeſt bread out of the earth." Then he breaks off a bit, and eats, and alſo gives a piece of it to every one of the company.</p><p>On the morning of the ſabbath, the Jews do not riſe ſo early as they do at other times. Thinking, the greater pleaſure they take on that day, the more devoutly they keep it. When they come into the ſynagogue, they pray as uſual, only the devotions are ſome what longer, being intermingled with pſalmody, in honour of the ſabbath. The Pentateuch is then produced, and ſeven ſections of it are read in order by ſeven perſons choſen for the purpoſe. Several leſſons are likewiſe read out of the prophets, which have ſome relation to what was read out of the law. After morning prayers they return to their houſes, and eat the ſecond ſabbath- meal, ſhewing every token of joy, in honour of the feſtival. But if one has ſeen any thing ominous in his ſleep; if he has dreamed that he burnt the book of the law; that a beam has come out of the walls of his houſe; that his teeth have fallen out; then he faſts until very late at night, for all ſuch dreams are bad ones. In the afternoon they go again to the ſynagogue, and. perform the evening ſervice, adding to the ordinary prayers ſome leſſons that reſpect the ſabbath. When the devotional duties are ended, they return home, and light a candle reſembling a torch, and again sit down to eat. They remain eating until near six, and then the maſter of the family takes a cup, and pouring wine into it rehearses ſome bcnedictions; after which he pours a little of the wine upon the ground, and ſays, “Bleſſed be thou, O Lord, King of the world, who haſt created the fruit of the vine.” Then holding the cup in his left hand, with the right he takes a box of ſweet ſpices, and ſays, “Bleſſed be thou, O Lord God, who haſt created various kinds of ſweet ſpices.” He ſmells the ſpices, and holds them out to the reit, that they may do the fame. He then takes the cup in his right hand, and going to the candle views the left very narrowly, and pronounces a bleſſing. With the cup in the left hand, he examines the right in the ſame manner. Again, holding the cup in his right hand, he rehearſes another benediction, and at the ſame time pours ſome of the wine on the ground. After this he drinks a little of it, and then hands it about to the reſt of the family, who finiſh<pb facs="gri_33125011196389_0590.tif" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0584"/>
what remains. In this manner the ſabbath is ended by the Jews, and they may return to their ordinary employments. Thoſe who meet pay their compliments, by wiſhing one another a happy week.</p><p>The Rabbins have reckoned up nine and thirty primary prohibitions, which ought to be obſerved on the ſabbatic feſtival; but their circumſtances and dependents, which are alſo obligatory, are almoſt innumerable, The 39 articles are, Not to till the ground; to ſow; to reap; to make hay; to bind up ſheaves of corn; to threſh; to winnow; to grind; to ſift meal; to knead the dough; to bake; to ſhear; to whiten; to comb or card wool; to ſpin; to twine or twiſt; to warp; to dye; to tie; to untie; to ſew; to tear or pull in pieces; to build; to pull down; to beat with a hammer; to hunt or fiſh; to kill a beaſt; to flay it; to dreſs it; to ſcrape the ſkin; to tan it; to cut leather; to write; to ſcratch out; to rule paper for writing; to kindle a fire; to extinguish it; to carry a thing from place to place; to expoſe any thing to ſale. Theſe are the primary prohibitions, and each of theſe has its proper conſequences, which amount to an incredible number; and the Jews themſelves ſay, that if they could keep but two ſabbaths as they ought, they would ſoon be delivered out of all their troubles.</p><p>If a Jew on a journey is overtaken by the ſabbath in a wood, or on the highway, no matter where, nor under what circumſtances, he sits down; he will not ſtir out of the ſpot. If he falls down in the dirt, he lies there; he will not rise up. If he ſhould tumble into a privy, he would rest there: he would not be taken out<note anchored="true" n="3" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="smallcaps">(A)</hi> This, it ſeems, was once really the caſe. A Jew of Magdeburg fell into a privy on a Saturday. He might have been taken out; but he told thoſe who offered him their aſſiſtance to give themſelves no trouble, for there he was determined to keep holy the ſabbath day. The biſhop, when he heard of it, reſolved that he ſhould ſanctify the next day alſo in the same place; and ſo, betwixt them, the poor Jew loſt his life.</p></note> <hi rend="smallcaps">(a).</hi> If he sees a flea ſkipping upon his clothes, he muſt not catch it. If it bites him, he may only remove it with his hand; he muſt not kill it; but a louſe meets with no ſuch indulgence, for it may be deſtroyed. He muſt not wipe his hands with a towel or cloth, but he may do it very lawfully with a cowl’s tail. A freſh wound muſt not be bound up on the ſabbath-day; a plaſter that had been formerly applied to a fore may remain on it; but if it falls off, it muſt not be put on anew. The lame may uſe a ſtaff, but the blind muſt not. Theſe particulars, and a great many more of the ſame nature, are obſerved by the Jews in the ſtricteſt manner. But if any one wishes to know more of the practice of that devoted race, he may conſult Buxtorf’s <hi rend="italic">Judaica Synagoga,</hi> chap. x. xi. where he will find a complete detail of their cuſtoms and ceremonies on the ſabbath; and likewise see the primary prohibitions branched out into their reſpective circumſtances.</p><p>As the ſeventh day was obſerved by the Jewiſh church, in memory of the rest of God after the works of creation, and their own deliverance from Pharaoh’s tyranny; ſo the firſt day of the week has always been obſerved by the Chriſtian church, in memory of the reſurrection of Jeſus Chriſt, by which he completed the work of man’s redemption on earth, and reſcued him from the dominion of him who has the power of death.</p><p>This day was denominated by the primitive Chriſtians the <hi rend="italic">Lord’s day.</hi> It was alſo ſometimes called <hi rend="italic">Sunday;</hi> which was the name given to it by the heathens, who dedicated it to the sun. And indeed, although it was originally called <hi rend="italic">Sunday</hi> by the heathens, yet it may very properly retain that name among Chriſtians, becauſe it is dedicated to the honour of “The true light,” which lighteth every man that cometh into the world, of Him who is ſtyled by the prophet “The Sun of righteouſneſs,” and who on this day aroſe from the dead. But although it was, in the primitive times, indifferently called the <hi rend="italic">Lord’s day</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Sunday,</hi> yet it was never denominated the <hi rend="italic">ſabbath;</hi> a name conſtantly appropriated to Saturday, or the <hi rend="italic">ſeventh</hi> day, both by ſacred and eccleſiaſtical writers.</p><p>Of the change from the <hi rend="italic">ſeventh</hi> to the <hi rend="italic">firſt</hi> day of the week, or even of the inſtitution of the <hi rend="italic">Lord’s day</hi> feſtival, there is no account in the New Teſtament. However, it may be fairly inferred from it, that the firſt day of the week was, in the apoſtolic age, a ſtated time for public worſhip. On this day the apoſtles were aſſembled, when the Holy Ghoſt came down ſo viſibly upon them to qualify them for the conversion of the world. On this day we find St Paul preaching at Troas, when the diſciples came to break bread: and the directions which the ſame apoſtle gives to the Corinthians concerning their contributions for the relief of their ſuffering brethren, plainly allude to their religious aſſemblies on the firſt day of the week.</p><p>Thus it would appear from ſeveral paſſages in the New Teſtament, that the religious obſervation of the firſt day of the week is of apoſtolical appointment; and may indeed be very reaſonably ſuppoſed to be among thoſe directions and inſtructions which our bleſſed Lord himſelf gave to his diſciples, during the 40 days between his reſurrection and aſcenſion, wherein he converſed with them, and ſpoke of the things pertaining to the kingdom of God. Still, however, it muſt be owned that thoſe paſſages, although the plainest that occur, are not ſuſſieient to prove the apoſtolical inſtitution of the Lord’s day, or even the actual obſervation of it. In order, therefore, to place the matter beyond all controverſy, recourſe muſt be had to eccleſiaſtical teſtimony.</p><p>From the conſentient evidence and uniform practice of the primitive church, and alto from the atteflation of Pliny, an heathen of no mean figure both in learning and power, we find that the firſt day of the week was obſerved in the earlieſt ages as an holyday or feſtival, in honour of the reſurrection of Chriſt. Now there are but two ſources whence the cuſtom could poſſibly have ariſen. It muſt have been inſtituted either by <hi rend="italic">human</hi> or <hi rend="italic">divine</hi> authority: by human authority it was not inſtituted; for there was no general council in thoſe early times, and without the decree of a general council it was impoſſible that any eccleſiaſtical inſtitution could have been univerſally eſtabliſhed at once. It remains, therefore, that it muſt have been inſtituted by<pb facs="gri_33125011196389_0591.tif" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0585"/>
divine authority: and that it really was ſo, will farther appear from the following conſiderations. It is certain that the apoſtles travelled over the greateſt part of the world, and planted churches in the remoteſt parts of it. It is certain alſo that they were all led by the ſame <hi rend="italic">Spirit;</hi> and their deſire was, that unity and uniformity ſhould be obſerved in all the churches which they had founded. It is not therefore ſurpriſing that, in the primitive times, the ſame doctrine, the ſame worſhip, the ſame rites and cuſtoms, ſhould prevail all over the Chriſtian world; nay, it would have been unaccountable had the caſe been otherwiſe. For this reaſon we may conclude that every cuſtom, univerſally obſerved in the early ages of the Chriſtian church, and not inſtituted by a general council, was of original appointment.</p><p>As the <hi rend="italic">Lord's day</hi> is ſanctiſied, that is, <hi rend="italic">ſet apart</hi> to Chriſtians for the worſhip and ſervice of God, their Creator, Redeemer, and Sanctifier, a little conſideration will eaſily diſcover how it ought to be obſerved. Although a day ſeparated from worldly buſineſs, yet it is in no ſenſe a day of idleneſs, but a ſeaſon appropriated to the works of ſalvation and labours of charity.</p><p>In the primitive times this holy day was obſerved in the moſt ſolemn manner. From the monuments of thoſe early ages we learn, that it was ſpent in a due and confiant attendance on all the offices of divine worſhip. On it they held their religious aſſemblies, in which the writings of the apoſtles and prophets were read to the people, and the doctrines of Chriſtianity further preſſed upon them by the exhortations of the clergy. Solemn prayers and praiſes were offered up to God, and hymns ſung in honour of Chriſt; the Lord’s ſupper was conſtantly celebrated; and collections were made for the maintenance of the clergy and the relief of the poor. On this day they abſtained, as much as they could, from bodily labour. They looked upon it as a day of joy and gladneſs; and therefore all faſting on it was prohibited, even during the ſeaſon of lent, their great annual faſt.— Such was the zeal of thoſe times, that nothing, no not the ſevereſt perſecutions, hindered them from celebrating holy offices on this day. They were often beset and betrayed, and as often ſlaughtered in conſequence of cruel edicts from emperors, thoſe very emperors for whoſe happineſs and proſperity they always offered up their fervent prayers. For this cause, when they could not meet in the daytime, they aſſembled in the morning before it was light; and when ſick, in exile, or in priſon, nothing troubled them more than that they could not attend the ſervice of the church. No trivial pretences were then admitted for any one’s abſence from public worſhip; for ſe- vere cenſures were paſſed upon all who were abſent without ſome urgent neceſſity. When the empire became Chriſtian, Conſtantine and his ſucceſſors made laws for the more ſolemn obſervation of the Lord’s day. They prohibited all proſecutions and pleadings and other juridical matters to be tranſacted on it, and alſo all unneceſſary labour; not that it was looked upon as a Jewiſh ſabbath, but becauſe theſe things were conſidered as inconſiſtent with the duties of the feſtival.</p><p>But although the primitive Chriſtians did not indulge themſelves in the practice of unneceſſary labour or trifling amuſements, yet they did not wholly abſtain from working, if great neceſſity required it. The council of <hi rend="italic">Laodicea</hi> enjoined that men ſhould abſtain from work on the Lord’s day <hi rend="italic">iſ possible</hi>; but if any were found to <hi rend="italic">judaize,</hi> they were to be cenſured as great tranſgreſſors. So circumſpect were the primitive Chriſtians about their conduct on this feſtival, that on the one hand they avoided all things which tended to profane it, whilſt on the other they cenſured all thoſe who inſiſted it ſhould be obſerved with Phariſaical rigour.</p><p>The primary duty of the Lord’s day is <hi rend="italic">public worship.</hi> The nature and deſign of the Chriſtian religion ſufficiently shows the neceſſity and importance of aſſembling for the duties of devotion. The whole ſcope of Chriſtianity is to bring us to an union with God, which cannot be obtained or preſerved without frequent communications with him; and the reaſons which ſhow religious intercourſe to be the indiſpenſable duty of Chriſtians in a private capacity, will bind it with equal or more force on them confidered as a community.</p><p>The advantages of public worſhip, when duly performed, are many and great. There are two, however, which deserve to be conſidered in a particular manner. It gives Chriſtians an opportunity of openly profeſſing their faith, and teſtifying their obedience to their Redeemer in the wiſeſt and beſt manner; and in an age when atheiſm has ariſen to an alarming height, when the Son of God is crucified afreſh, and put to open ſhame, every man, who has any regard for religion, will cheerfully embrace all opportunities of declaring his abhorrence of the vicious courſes purſucd by thoſe degenerate apoſtates. He will with pleaſure lay hold on every occaſion to teſtiſy that he is neither afraid nor aſhamed to confeſs the truth; and will think it his indiſpenſable duty openly to diſavow the fins of others, that he may not incur the guilt of partaking of them.</p><p>Public worſhip preſerves in the minds of men a ſenſe of religion, without which ſociety could not exiſt. Nothing can keep a body of men together and unite them in promoting the public good, but ſuch principles of action as may reach and govern the heart. But theſe can be derived only from a ſenſe of religious duties, which can never be ſo ſtrongly impreſſed upon the mind as by a constant attendance upon public worſhip. Nothing can be more weak than to neglect the public worſhip of God, under the pretence that we can employ ourſelves as acceptably to our Maker at home in our cloſets. Both kinds of worſhip are indeed necessary; but one debt cannot be paid by the diſcharge of another. By public worſhip every man profeſſes his belief in that God whom he adores, and appeals to Him for his ſincerity, of which his neighbour cannot judge. By this appeal he endears himſelf more or leſs to others. It creates confidence; it roots in the heart benevolence, and all other Chriſtian virtues, which produce, in common life, the fruits of mutual love and general peace.</p><p>People in general are of opinion that the duties of the Lord’s day are over when public worſhip is ended. But they ſeem to forget for what purpoſes the day was ſet apart. It is not only appropriated to the duties of public worſhip, but alſo ſanctiſied to our improvement in the knowledge of the doctrines of Chriſtianity. It is an inſtitution calculated to alleviate the condition of the laborious claſſes of mankind, and, in<pb facs="gri_33125011196389_0592.tif" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0586"/>
consequence of that, to afford reſt to <hi rend="italic">beaſts</hi> alſo. It is proper, it is neceſſary, that man ſhould reflect on his condition in the world, that he ſhould examine the ſtate of his ſoul, and inquire what progreſs he has made in that work which was given him to do. Those that have children or ſervants are obliged to look after <hi rend="italic">their</hi> inſtruction as well as their own. Theſe are the ends which the inſtitution of Sunday was deſigned to anſwer. Every man must allow that theſe things muſt be done at ſome time or other; but unleſs there be <hi rend="italic">set</hi> times for doing them, the generality of mankind would wholly neglect them.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Visiting</hi> and <hi rend="italic">travelling</hi> (though very common) are enormous profanations of this holy day. Families are thereby robbed of their <hi rend="italic">time;</hi> a loss for which no amends can ever be made them: Servants, inſtead of having leisure to improve themſelves in ſpiritual knowledge, are burdened with additional labour: And in a man of any humanity, it muſt excite many painful ſenſations, when he reflects how often the uſeful horſe on that day experiences all the anguiſh of hunger, torn ſides, and battered knees. Every kind of <hi rend="italic">amuſement,</hi> every kind of <hi rend="italic">common</hi> labour, is an encroachment on the particular duties of the Lord’s day; and conſequently men profane the day by ſpending it in any amuſements, or undertaking upon it any ordinary employment unleſs it be a work of abſolute neceſſity.</p><p><hi rend="italic">SABBATH-Breaking,</hi> or profanation of the Lord’s day, is puniſhed by the municipal laws of England. For, besides the notorious indecency and ſcandal of permitting any ſecular buſineſs to be publicly tranſacted on that day in a country profeſſing Chriſtianity, and the corruption of morals which uſually follows its profanation, the keeping one day in ſeven holy, as a time of relaxation and refreſhment, as well as for public worſhip, is of admirable ſervice to a ſtate, conſidered merely as a civil inſtitution. It humanizes, by the help of converſation and ſociety, the manners of the lower claſſes; which would otherwiſe degenerate into a ſordid ferocity and ſavage ſelfiſhneſs of ſpirſt: it enables the induſtrious workman to purſue his occupation in the enſuing week with health and cheerfulneſs: it imprints on the minds of the people that ſenſe of their duty to God ſo neceſſary to make them good citizens; but which yet would be worn out and defaced by an unremitted continuance of labour, without any ſtated times of recalling them to the worſhip of their Maker. And therefore the laws of King Athelſtan forbad all merchandizing on the Lord’s day, under very ſevere penalties. And by the ſtatute 27 Hen. VI. c. 5. no fair or market ſhall be held on the principal feſtivals, Good- friday, or any Sunday (except the four Sundays in harveſt), on pain of forfeiting the goods expoſed to ſale. And, ſince, by the ſtatute 1 Car. I. c. 1. no perſons shall assemble, out of their own pariſhes, for any ſport whatſoever, upon this day; nor, in their pariſhes, ſhall uſe any bull or bear beating, interludes, plays, or other unlawful exerciſes or paſtimes; on pain that every offender ſhall pay 3s. 4d. to the poor. This ſtatute does not prohibit, but rather impliedly allows, any innocent recreation or amuſement, within their reſpective pariſhes, even on the Lord’s day, after divine ſervice is over. But by ſtatute 29 Car. II. c. 7. no perſon is allowed to work on the Lord’s day, or uſe any boat or barge, or expoſe any goods to ſale, except meat in</p><p>public houſes, milk at certain hours, and works of neceſſity or charity, on forfeiture of 5 s. Nor ſhall any drover, carrier, or the like, travel upon that day, under pain of 20 s.</p></div></body></text></TEI>