<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196389_0693.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0687-05" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SCALD</label>
- <hi rend="smallcaps">cream,</hi> ſometimes alſo called <hi rend="italic">Clouted-cream;</hi> a curious method of preparing cream for butter, almoſt peculiar to Devonſhire. Dr Hales, in Philoſophical Tranſactions, volume 49, page 342, 1755, part 1ft, gives ſome account of the method of preparing this delicate and luxurious article: other writers alſo ſpeak of it. With an elucidation or two, we ſhall nearly quote Mr Feltham’s account from the Gentleman’s Magazine, volume 61. part 2. It is there obſerved, that the purpoſe of making scald-cream is far ſuperior butter than can be procured from the uſual raw cream, being preserable for flavour and keeping; to which thoſe accuſtomed are ſo partial, as ſeldom to eat any other. As leaden ciſterns would not anſwer for ſcalding cream, the dairies moſtly adopt braſs pans, which hold from three to five gallons for the milk; and that which is put into thoſe pans one morning, stands till the next, when, without diſturbing it, it is ſet over (on a trivet) a steady briſk wood fire, devoid of ſmoke, where it is to remain from ſeven to fifteen minutes, according to the ſize of the pan, or the quantity in it: the preciſe time of removing it from the fire muſt be particularly attended to, and is, when the ſurface begins to wrinkle or to gather in a little, ſhowing ſigns of being near the agitation of boiling, which it muſt by no means do; it is then inſtantly to be taken off, and placed in the dairy until the next morning, when the fine cream is thrown up, and may be taken for the table, or for butter, inter which it is now ſoon converted by ſtirring it with the hand. Some know when to remove it from the fire by founding the pan with the finger, it being then leſs ſonorous; but this is only acquired by experience. Dr Hales obſerves, that this method of preparing milk will take off the ill taſte it ſometimes acquires from the cows feeding on turnips, cabbage, &amp;c.</p></div></body></text></TEI>