<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196389_0663.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0657-02" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SAPPHO</label>,
a famous poeteſs of antiquity, who for her excellence in her art has been called the <hi rend="italic">Tenth Muſe,</hi> was born at Mitylene in the iſle of Leſhos, about 610 years before Chriſt. She was contemporary with Steſichorus and Alcaeus; which laſt was her countryman, and as ſome think her ſuitor. A verſe of this poet, in which he inſinuates to her his paſſion, is preſerved in Ariſtotle, <hi rend="italic">Rhet. lib.</hi> i. <hi rend="italic">cap.</hi> 9. together with the fair damſel’s anſwer.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Alc.</hi> I fain to Sappho would a wiſh impart,</p><p>But fear locks up the ſecret in my heart.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sap.</hi> Thy downcaſt looks, reſpect, and timid air. Too plain the nature of thy wiſh declare.</p><p>If lawlefs, wild, inordinate deſire,</p><p>Did not with thoughts impure thy boſom fire. Thy tongue and eyes, by innocence made bold, Ere now the ſecret of thy ſoul had told.</p><p>M. la Fevre obſerves, that Sappho was not in her uſual good-humour when ſhe gave ſo cold an anſwer to a requeſt, for which, at another time, perhaps ſhe would not have waited. — It has been thought, too, that Anacreon was one of her lovers, and his editor Barnes has taken ſome pains to prove it: but chronology will not admit this; ſince, upon inquiry, it will be found that Sappho was probably dead before Anacreon was born. Of the numerous poems this lady wrote, there is nothing remaining but ſome ſmall fragments, which the ancient ſcholiaſts have cited; a hymn to Venus, preſerved by Dionyſius of Halicarnaſſus; and an ode to one of her miſtreſſes<note anchored="true" n="1" place="margin" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">† See</hi> Poetry, <hi rend="italic">n8. 122.</hi></p></note> <hi rend="italic">†</hi>: which laſt piece confirms a tradition delivered down from antiquity, that her amorous paſſion extended even to perſons of her own ſex, and that ſhe was willing to have her miſtreſſes as well as her gallants.</p><p>Ovid introduces her making a ſacrifice to Phaon, one of her male paramours; from which we learn, that Sappho’s love for her own ſex did not keep her from loving ours. She fell deſperately in love with Phaon, and did all ſhe could to win him; but in vain: upon which ſhe threw herſelf headlong from a rock, and died. It is ſaid that Sappho could not forbear following Phaon into Sicily, whither he retired that he might not ſee her; and that during her ſtay in that iſland ſhe probably compoſed the hymn to Venus, ſtill extant, in which ſhe begs ſo ardently the aſſiſtance of that goddeſs. Her prayers, however, proved ineffectual: Phaon was cruel to the laſt degree. Tire unfortunate Sappho was forced to take the dreadful leap; ſhe went to the promontory Leucas, and threw herſelf into the ſea. The cruelty of Phaon will not ſurpriſe us ſo much, if we reflect, that ſhe was a widow (for ſhe had been married to a rich man in the iſle of Andros, by whom ſhe had. a daughter, named <hi rend="italic">Cleis</hi>); that ſhe had never been hand-<pb facs="gri_33125011196389_0664.tif" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0658"/>
ſome; that ſhe had obſerved no meaſure in her paſſion to both ſexes; and that Phaon had long known all her charms. She was, however, a very great wit, and for that alone deferves to be remembered. The Mitylenians held her merit in ſuch high eſteem, that they paid her ſovereign honours after her death, and ſtamped their money with her image. The Romans afterwards erected a noble ſtatue of porphyry to her; and in ſhort, ancients as well as moderns have done honour to her memory. Voſſius ſays, that none of the Greek poets excelled Sappho for ſweetneſs of verſe; and that ſhe made Archilochus the model of her ſtyle, but at the ſame time took care to ſoſten the ſeverity of his expreſſion. It muſt be granted, ſays Rapin, from what is left us of Sappho, that Longinus had great reaſon to extol the admirable genius of this woman; for there is in what remains of her ſomething delicate, harmonious, and impaſſioned to the laſt degree.</p></div></body></text></TEI>