<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196389_0586.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0580-01" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SABA</label>,
a Hutch iſland near St Euſtatia in the West Indies.<note anchored="false" n="1" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>Raynal's History, vol. iv.</p></note> It is a ſteep rock, on the ſummit of which is a little ground, very proper for gardening. Frequent rains, which do not lie any time on the foil, give growth to plants of an exquiſite flavour, and cabbages of an extraordinary ſize. Fifty European families, with about one hundred and fifty ſlaves, here raiſe cotton, ſpin it, make ſtockings of it, and fell them to other colonies for as much as ten crowns<note anchored="true" n="2" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>*L. 1: 5: 0.</p></note> * a pair. Throughout America there is no blood ſo pure as that of Saba; the women there preſerve a freſhneſs of complexion, which is not to be found in any other of the Caribbee iſlands. Happy colony! elevated on the top of a rock between the sky and lea, it enjoys the benefit of both elements without dreading their ſtorms; it breathes a pure air, lives upon vegetables, cultivates a ſimple commodity, from which it derives eaſe without the temptation of riches: is employed in labours leſs troubleſorne than uſeful, and poſſeſſes in peace all the bleſſings of moderation, health, beauty, and liberty. This is the temple of peace from whence the philosopher may contemplate at leiſure the errors and pallions of men, who come, like the waves of the ſea, to ſtrike and daſlr themſelvcs on the rich coaſts of America, the ſpoils and poſſeſſion of which they are perpetually contending for, and wreſting from each other: hence may he view at a diſtance the nations of Europe bearing thunder in the midſt. of the ocean, and burning with the flames of ambition and avarice under the beats of the tropics; devouring gold without ever being ſatisſied; wading through ſeas of blood to amaſs thoſe metals, thoſe pearls, thoſe diamonds, which are uſed to adorn the oppreſſors of mankind; loading innumerable ſhips with thoſe precious calks, which furniſh luxury with purple, and ſrom which flow pleaſures, effeminacy, cruelty, and debauchery. The tranquil inhabitant of Saba views this maſs of follies, and ſpins his cotton in peace.</p></div></body></text></TEI>