<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196389_0710.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0704-05" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SCHURMAN</label>
(Anna-Maria), a moſt extraordinary German lady. Her natural genius diſcovered itſelf at ſix years of age, when ſhe cut all ſorts of figures in</p><p>paper with her ſciſſars without a pattern. At eight, ſhe learned, in a few days, to draw flowers in a very agreeable manner. At ten, ſhe took but three hours to learn embroidery. Afterwards ſhe was taught muſic, vocal and inſtrumental; painting, ſculpture, and engraving; in all of which ſhe ſucceeded admirably. She excelled in miniature-painting, and in cutting portraits upon glaſs with a diamond. Hebrew, Greek, and Latin, were ſo familiar to her, that the moſt learned men were aſtoniſhed at it. She ſpoke French, Italian, and Engliſh, fluently. Her hand-writing, in almoſt all languages, was ſo inimitable, that the curious preſerved ſpecimens of it in their cabinets. But all this extent of learning and uncommon penetration could not protect her from falling into the errors of Labadie, the famous French enthuſiaſt, who had been baniſhed France for his extravagant tenets and conduct. To this man ſhe entirely attached herſelf, and accompanied him wherever he went; and even attended him in his laſt illneſs at Altena in Holſtein. Her works, conſiſting of <hi rend="italic">De vitae humanae termino,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Dissertatio de ingenii muliebris ad doctrinam et meliores literas aptitudine,</hi> and her Letters to her learned correſpondents, were printed at Leyden in 1648; but enlarged in the edition of Utrecht, 1662, in 12mo, under the following title: <hi rend="italic">A. M. Schurman Opuſcula Hebraea, Graeca, Latina, Gallica, Proſaica, et Metrica.</hi> She publiſhed likewiſe at Altena, in Latin, A Defence of her attachment to Labadie, while ſhe was with him in 1673; not worth reading. She was born at Cologne in 1607, but reſided chiefly in Holland, and died in Frieſland in 1678.</p></div></body></text></TEI>