<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-03-25T20:16:08Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>and glen, thrown promiscuously together, present the grandest of savage landscapes,
                which, as the field of wild adventure, cast into shade what Mr. Scrope calls “ the
                tame and hedge-bound country of the south.”</p>
            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Τηε Fowling-piece.</hi> Before making choice of a gun, the
                shooter should determine what weight he can conveniently carry. The heaviest gun, as
                regards shooting, will be most effective, but he should recollect that unless he be
                a very robust person, a light gun will, on the whole, bring him more game, as a few
                additional pounds in the weight of a gun makes a deal of difference in the distance
                a person can travel in a day. and, moreover, he cannot shoot as well when
                fatigued.</p>
            <p>The most approved guns under the system which prescribes a heavy charge of powder,
                and a light one of very small shot, are double barrels, weighing, according to the
                fancy of the shooter, from six to nine pounds, and bearing the following relative
                proportions of length to guage : fourteen guage, thirty-four inches long; seventeen
                guage, thirty-two inches long ; twenty guage, thirty inches long. Taking the season
                throughout, we are convinced, that the most effective gun is a short, wide-bored
                one, each barrel being charged with rather less than 1<hi rend="superscript"
                    >1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">2</hi> drams avoirdupois weight of powder, and full
                2 oz. of No. 2 shot, containing 220 pellets. This is the general charge, but it may
                be varied according to circumstances. When game is wild, we would charge the reserve
                barrel, and, on some occasions, both barrels, with 2<hi rend="superscript"
                    >1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">2</hi> drams of powder, and a No. 5 blue cartridge
                for partridges, and with a No. 4 or 5 red cartridge for grouse shooting. No. 7 shot
                is best for snipe shooting. Small shot may be used for partridge sh∞ting in
                September, though we do not see any reason for not adhering to No. 2, except that
                birds very near the gun are liable to be more disfigured by it.</p>
            <p>Barrels twenty-six or twenty-eight inches long, and fourteen or sixteen guage, are of
                convenient size. We think it will not be questioned that these barrels are as
                efficient as long narrow-bored ones for short distances, viz. under thirty-five
                yards, and nine-tenths of game brought to the bag is killed within that distance.
                And for making long shots, the wire-cartridge has obviated the necessity of using
                long guns. A most material advantage attending the use of a short gun is, the
                comparative ease with which it may be carried. A pound additional weight at the
                breech is not so fatiguing to the arm as half that weight added to the end of the
                barrel ; it is the top-heavy gun that distresses the shooter.</p>
            <p>Different proportions of powder and shot are required for different sizes of shot.
                The following may be the proper proportions for a gun not exceeding eight pounds
                :</p>
            <p>Size of shot. Weight of shot. Weight of powder.</p>
            <p>No. oz. drams.</p>
            <list type="ordered">
                <item>2 1<hi rend="superscript">4</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">10</hi></item>
            </list>
            <p><hi rend="superscript">3</hi> 1<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript"
                    >2</hi></p>
            <list type="ordered">
                <item>1<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">2</hi> 1<hi
                        rend="superscript">3</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">4</hi></item>
                <item>1<hi rend="superscript">3</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">8 </hi> 2</item>
                <item>1<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">4</hi> 2<hi
                        rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">4</hi></item>
                <item>1<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">8</hi> 2<hi
                        rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">2</hi></item>
            </list>
            <p>These proportions cannot be materially deviated from without destroying the effect.
                If the powder is decreased, the discharge is weakened ; if the powder is increased,
                the shot spreads ; if the weight of shot is decreased, there will not be a
                sufficient number of pellets for effective shooting; if the weight of shot is
                increased, the discharge is weakened.</p>
            <p>The usual objection to large shot is, that after it has travelled thirty yards it
                becomes dispersed ; but let the powder be reduced to less than 1<hi
                    rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">2</hi> dram, and that objection
                fails. If</p>
            <p>it is not overcharged with powder, a gun will shoot No. 2 shot close enough to kill
                at from thirty-five to fifty yards, with more certainty than if charged with small
                shot, and two or three drams of powder.</p>
            <p>It is not so much the velocity as the momentum of a shot that renders it effective.
                The momentum of a shot increases in a direct ratio with its weight. The momentum of
                a No. 2 shot much more than compensates for the diminished weight of powder and
                additional weight of lead that we have recommended. Large shot droops more than
                small, and sooner comes to the ground, as it is not carried with the same velocity.
                It is the momentum, and not the velocity, that the shooter must look to.</p>
            <p>We do not suppose that feathers or fur of game present any serious obstacle to either
                large or small shot ; but if they did, the fact that large shot is most effective
                for shooting wild fowl armed with down, at once tells that it must be so for
                shooting game which is not so protected. Another advantage of large shot is, that
                when the aim taken is not quite correct, a single outside pellet will often bring
                down a bird, when it would require many small shots to do so.</p>
            <p>The shooting of barrels depends mainly on three things, viz., the metal of which they
                are made, the boring, and the breeching. The quality of the metal is of much
                importance. All barrels expand when fired ; and those made of inferiormetal expand
                more than those made of stub-twist. Mr. Greener, in his excellent treatise on the “
                    Gun,”@@<hi rend="superscript">1</hi> says, “ that a barrel is a spring on an
                extended scale, and the more we can make it partake of the nature of a spring, the
                better. If we must have expansion, let us have it in its most beneficial form ; an
                expansion that will aid the powder in expelling the lead. This cannot be entirely
                obtained, nor can the quantity of expansion be entirely destroyed, though you were
                to make your barrels of the weight of a twenty-four pounder. We must, therefore,
                decrease it, by making our iron as elastic and tenacious as possible. The qualities
                of elasticity and tenacity can only be obtained by hammer-hardening the iron.
                Barrels hammer-hardened will shoot as well without any artificial friction, as those
                whose friction is extreme, yet have not yet been benefited by the process.”</p>
            <p>The term friction implies a gradual contraction of the barrel towards the muzzle,
                which retards the progress of th∣ shot, that more time may be allowed to the powder
                to burn. “The shooting of all barrels,” says Mr. Greener, “ depends on a certain
                degree of friction. The degree of friction necessary varies according to the nature
                and substance of the metal. Those metals that requiro least shoot best. The object
                of the friction is to create a greater force, by detaining the charge longer in the
                barrel. If, then, there should not be an extra quantity of powder to consume, the
                friction would be a decided evil." A greater degree of friction is generally allowed
                to a short barrel than to a long one. A gradual expansion of the barrel towards the
                muzzle is termed relief. Relief accelerates the progress of shot through the
                barrels. What is the proper degree of relief or friction for different descriptions
                of barrels, is a subject fruitful of much controversy ; as is also the form of the
                breech. The best breech is that which will cause the greatest quantity of powder to
                consume in the barrel.</p>
            <p>Mr. Greener would not prevent the barrel expanding when fired, by increasing its
                thickness, but by improving the quality of the metal. When the barrel expands much,
                or is held loosely when fired, a loss of strength is induced, as that power which,
                if possible, should be exerted on the shot, is uselessly expended in a contrary
                direction, whereas, when the barrel is firmly fixed, and made of metal that only</p>
            <p><hi rend="superscript">@@@,</hi> The Gun, by William Greener. London. 1835</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
