<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-25T20:16:31Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>is surrounded by rich pastures, on which are reared numerous horses.</p><p>SHUMSABAD, a small town of the Sikh territorial province of Lahore, situated on the east side of the Jhylum river, 100 miles N.W. by W. from Lahore. Long. 72.15. E. Lat. 32. 16. N.</p><p>SHUNDRABANDY, a town of Southern India, in the district of Tinnevelly, 40 miles S.W. from Madura. Long. 77. 45. E. Lat 3. 35. N.</p><p>SHUS, a large mass of ruins in the province of Khuzis- tan, in Persia, extending twelve miles from the Kerah to the Ahzal. They occupy an immense extent of ground, and are supposed, by Major Rennel and Colonel Kinneir, to be the ancient capital of Susa.</p><p>SHUSTER, the principal district of the province of Khuzistan, in Persia, and composing a separate government. It constitutes the finest portion of Susiana, being watered by four noble rivers, and a multitude of smaller streams, by which means the land is fertilised, and rendered productive. But the bounties of nature are here blasted by the oppression and malignity of man, and the ignorant and rapacious rulers of Persia, causing devastation and ruin over all the territories subject to their sway. This wealthy province, accordingly, which was formerly rich in its productions of cotton, sugar, rice, and grain, is now a forsaken waste ; from the Abzal to the Tigris, and the river which Colonel Kinneir considers the Gyndes, on the western side, and from the banks of the Karoon to those of the Shat-ul-Arab, all is dreary and desolate ; and upon the east side of Shuster, a lonely wild, upwards of sixty miles in length, extends from that city to the entrance of the valley of Ram Hormuz. Even in the most flourishing parts of the country, namely, between Bundekeel and Dezphoul, the corn is reared by the officers of the government, and the richer citizens of Shuster and Dezphoul, the original cultivators of the soil being all ruined by the heavy contributions imposed upon them, and which had been exacted with such severity, as to drive them from their habitations. Ram Hormuz, which forms part of this district, is one of the most romantic valleys in Persia. It is ruled by five hostile chiefs, four of whom are brothers, and have each a castle, from which they make frequent sallies, and carry off the corn and cattle of their rivals.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Shuster,</hi> a city of Persia, the capital of the province of Khuzistan, and the residence of a Beglerbeg, is situated at the foot of the mountains of Bucktiari, on an eminence overlooking the rapid course of the Karoon, across which is a bridge of one arch, upwards of eighty feet in height; from the summit of which the Persians frequently throw themselves into the water without sustaining the slightest injury. The streets, as in roost eastern towns, are narrow and dirty, though the houses are good, being principally built of stone ; it is defended on the western side by the river, and on the other sides by the old stone wall, which is now fallen into decay. The ruins which still remain attest the former magnificence and extent of this city. Those most worthy of attention, are the castle, the dike, and a bridge. Part of the walls of the former, said to have been the abode of Valerian, are still standing on a small hill at the western extremity of the town. It is on two sides defended by a ditch, and on the other two by a branch of the Karoon. It has but one gateway, built in the Roman fashion, and formerly entered by a chain-bridge. Not far from the castle is the dike, built by Sapor, across the Karoon, twenty feet in breadth, and four hundred yards in length, with two small arches in the middle. It is built of culstone, bound together by clumps of iron ; and having, from want of care, given way to the torrent, Prince Mahomed Ali Meerza, governor of Kermanshaw, has rebuilt it. Over the artificial canal, formed by the building of this dike, is a bridge built of hewn stone, consisting of thirty-two arches, twenty-eight of which are yet entire. This city is generallly believed to have been the ancient Susa, though Colonel Kinneir, and Major Rennel, both good authorities, rather assign the ruins of Shus as the site of this renowned capita). Long. 48.59. E. Lat. 32. N.</p><p>SHROPSHIRE, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Salop,</hi> a county of England. (See <hi rend="smallcaps">Salop.)</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">SHROVE-Tuesday,</hi> is the Tuesday after Quinquagesima Sunday, or the day immediately preceding the first of Lent, being so called from the Saxon word to <hi rend="italic">shrive,</hi> which signifies to confess. Hence Shrove-Tuesday signifies Con- fession-Tuesday, on which day all the people in every parish throughout England, during the Catholic times, were obliged to confess their sins, one by one, to their own parish priest, in their own parish-churches ; and, that this might be done the more regularly, the great bell in every parish was rung at ten o’clock, or perhaps sooner, that it might be heard by all, and that they might attend, according to the custom then in use.</p><p>SHROUDS, a range of large ropes extending from the mast-heads to the right and left side of the ship, to support the masts, and enable them to carry sail.</p><p>The shrouds as well as the sails are denominated from the masts to which they belong. Thus there are the main, fore, and mizen shrouds ; the main-top-mast, fore-top-mast, and mizen-top-mast shrouds ; and the main-top-gallant, fore- top-gallant, and mizen-top-gallant shrouds. The number of shrouds by which a mast is sustained, as well as the size of the rope of which they are formed, is always in proportion to the size of the mast and the weight of the sail it is intended to carry.</p><p>Bowsprit shrouds are those which support the bowsprit. Bumpkin shrouds are those which support the bumpkins. Futtuck shrouds are shrouds which connect the efforts of the topmast shrouds to the lower shrouds. Bentick shrouds are additional shrouds to support the masts in heavy gales. Preventer shrouds are similar to bentick shrouds, and are used in bad weather to ease the lower rigging.</p><p>SHRUB, <hi rend="italic">frutex,</hi> a little, low, dwarfish tree, or a woody vegetable, of' a size less than a tree, and which, instead of one single stem, frequently puts forth from the same root several sets or stems.</p><p>SHUTTLE, in the manufactures, an instrument used by weavers, which guides the thread it contains, either of woollen, silk, flax, or other matter, so as to make it form the woofs of stuffs, cloths, linens, ribands, and other fabrics, by throwing the shuttle alternately from left to right, and from right to left, across between the threads of the warp, which are stretched out lengthwise on the loom.</p><p>In the middle of the shuttle is a kind of cavity, called the eye or chamber of the shuttle, in which is inclosed the spoul, which is a part of the thread destined for the woof ; and this is wound on a little tube of paper, rush, or other matter.</p><p>SIAK, is a river and a large district of Sumatra. The district extends about 450 miles along the north-east coast. This district has a considerable trade, which is carried on by vessels from the coast of Coromandel, which supply cargoes of piece goods, and also raw silk, opium, and other articles, which they provide at Prince of Wales’ island or Malacca, receiving in return gold, wax, sago, salted fish and fish roes, elephants’ teeth, camphire, rattans, and other canes. Spars and masts, and large supplies of frame timber used to be imported by the Dutch East India Company for the use of Batavia. The maritime power of the kingdom of Siak has always been considerable.</p><p>The river Siak is one of the largest in the island, and discharges itself into the sea opposite Malacca in N. lat. 1.40. From a survey ordered by the British government of Prince of Wales’ island, it appears that from its mouth to the town of Siak, is sixty-five miles. The width of the river is in general from about a half to three quarters of a mile, and its depth from seven to fifteen fathoms ; but on the bar at low water, there is only fifteen feet of depth, and there are several shoals near its mouth.</p></body></text></TEI>