<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-25T20:16:21Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>the ground. At such times he should look well after the young dogs, as, when they see the birds running, they are apt to snap up such of them as cannot get out of the way. The very young birds are called cheepers, from their uttering a scream as they rise. Full grown birds never scream as they rise, except when the young ones are helpless, nor do young birds after they are large enough for the table.</p><p>The cock partridge is distinguished from the hen by the brown feathers which form a crescent, or horse-shoe, as it is sometimes called, on the breast.</p><p>The pointer is decidedly the best dog for partridge shooting. Markers and retrievers will be of much service to the shooter whose object is to kill a great quantity of birds, rather than to enjoy the sport.</p><p><hi rend="italic">The Pheasant.</hi> The pheasant is the most splendidly arrayed of undomesticated British birds. It is deservedly in high request amongst sportsmen, and it claims the first attention of the game-preserver. The numberless plantations and coppices which are everywhere springing up, afford yearly additional shelter. The pheasant prefers woods of oak and beech, that it may feed on the acorns and mast. The fine old woods consisting of these trees may perhaps be diminishing, but they are more than replaced by plantations of larch or other quick-growing trees. Pheasants generally choose the larch or sprucefir to roost in, and plantations of this description, if near corn, turnip, or potato fields, afford sufficient cover for them. They are, in many counties, allowed to become so numerous, as to do serious mischief to the labours of husbandry’. ,</p><p>During August and the early part of September, pheasants will remain nearly all day in potato and corn fields. Pheasant shooting commences on the first of October, and ends on the first of February. In October, the shooter usually meets with them in potato and turnip fields, deep stubbles and rushy fields near covers, but especially under hedges, holly trees, or in coppices near to covers. In such situations they will suffer the shooter to approach very near to them ; they are generally pointed by the dogs, and, a large majority of them being young birds, are easily killed ; but in that month the trees are so full of foliage, and the briars and brushwood are so annoying, that it is seldom possible to beat the woods with any degree of pleasure, for not only are they almost impervious, but the pheasants are seldom seen when they rise, or if seen and shot, are very frequently lost, or not found without considerable loss of time. It is in November, when the birds have moulted, and when the leaves have fallen, and the brambles are decaying, and the paths in the woods are beginning to be worn, that pheasant shooting is in perfection. The birds are then full grown, and also better fed than later in the season.</p><p>It is not usual to kill the hens wherever pheasants are strictly preserved ; but it is necessary to kill the cocks where they are too numerous. Pheasants do not pair, and as it is better that there should be but few cocks, the shooter’s being able to single them out and kill them, tends ultimately to the increase, and not to the diminution of the number of birds in cover. At the commencement of the season the shooter will frequently flush a nide of pheasants, but in the after part of the season he will oftener find solitary birds. Pheasants will occasionally wander a considerable distance from the wood to which they belong, especially during winter, in search of food, and in wet and foggy weather. The pheasant basks at the root of a tree, or under a hedge, in the same manner as the partridge, but each bird nestles itself separately. Pheasants approach nearer to domesticated poultry than any other kind of game. Pheasant shooting is most destructive where the plantations are not more than forty yards wide; when the shooters remain on the outside, while the beaters and dogs rouse the game within. The pheasant shooter does not expect set shots; his object is to cause the birds to rise as near to him as he can. Having no notice of them, he should ever be on the alert for snap shots.</p><p>A short double-barrelled fowling-piece, of wide bore, is preferable to a long one. The shot should be large, and it is well to use plenty of it. A close-shooting gun is not to be recommended to the pheasant shooter. The birds should rarely be fired at in cover when more than thirty yards from the gun, or they will escape wounded in the underwood. They are generally brought down within twenty yards from the gun. Pheasants are most plentiful in Norfolk, Suffolk, and some of the adjoining counties. There are some in every county in England, and in most of the counties in Scotland. A perfect bird has a white annular space on the neck, but this mark is often wanting.</p><p>The pheasant makes a considerable noise when rising, sufficiently so to unnerve the young and over-anxious shooter. The bird should be allowed to rise clear of the bushes, and to its full height, before the shooter fires at it, or it is probable he will fire too low; and again, the short fan-like feathers on either side of the tail appear, as the bird is rising, to be part of the bird, making the body seem longer and larger than it really is ; and this circumstance, together with the rapidity of the movement of the bird when rising, is the cause of the shooter firing too low. The aim should always be at the head, unless the bird is crossing, and then well forward. Firing too soon, lest the bird should be out of reach, is a very common error, particularly with young sportsmen.</p><p>For reasons which we have before adverted to, the setter, or cock-dog, is to be preferred to the pointer for pheasant shooting. Pheasants will sometimes lie very close, so that it is with great difficulty they can be made to rise ; therefore dogs that will dash into the thicket are most useful. Beaters and retrievers are indispensable to the pheasant shooter.</p><p><hi rend="italic">The Hare.</hi> The shooter seldom beats purposely for hares. Birds are mainly the object of his pursuit. He chooses his ground, and regulates the charge of his fowling-piece with reference to the birds he expects to meet with. Hares are started casually, as it were, while he is in quest of birds. Leveret shooting often commences with grouse shooting, on the 12th of August, though it is not uncommon, nor is it considered unfair, to kill leverets during the summer months. Hares are not in season until September. The shooter should desist from killing them in February, but he is not prevented from killing them at any season, by any legislative enactment, if he have taken out a game certificate. It is the prescriptive law of the chase, held sacred by sportsmen, that prevents him.</p><p>In September, hares lie close, in hedges, in woods, or in growing com, and are somewhat difficult to be found. They are scared from the woods by the leaves falling in autumn, and they are then found, particularly after stormy weather, in pasture and stubble fields. Dogs will frequently point them. In November and December, they are often seen on their seats, or forms, as they are sometimes called, by the shooter keeping his eyes on the ground about eight or ten</p></body></text></TEI>