<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-03-25T20:16:41Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>thick woods, torrents and precipices, without a human habitation, except a few sheds
                erected by hunters when they are in pursuit of game. In approaching the eastern
                ocean, these mountains decline in elevation, and turning to the north, run parallel
                to the sea, leaving a narrow space between them. The mountains of Okhotsk run
                northward down the Lena to Yakutsk ; one runs eastward to the sea of Okhotsk, whilst
                another continues its course with the peninsula of Kamtschatka, which consists of a
                rocky chain of mountains, about which little information has ever been acquired.</p>
            <p>The surface of Siberia comprises every variety of soil. The tracts which are called
                steppes are dry, elevated, and extensive plains, which are not inhabited, and some
                of them, which are uninhabitable, are destitute both of food and water. Others have
                shrubs growing on them or a stunted herbage, and are watered by streams or wells,
                though without inhabitants, and thus afford pasture to the herds and flocks of the
                shepherds who range over these desolate plains, ln regard to the soil on these
                steppes, great variety prevails, none being fruitful and proper for meadow or arable
                land, or indiscriminately for both ; in others the soil is unfruitful, whether it be
                sand or salt, or in some cases of a rocky formation.</p>
            <p>Siberia is well watered by numerous and large rivers, an account of which may be
                found in the articde <hi rend="smallcaps">Russia.</hi> It may merely be mentioned
                here, that those great rivers are the Ir- tysch, the Obi, the Jenesei, and the Lena,
                which have all their sources in the frontier range of mountains, and roll onwards to
                the Frozen Ocean. All the other numerous rivers which rise in Siberia, are
                tributaries of those main rivers.</p>
            <p>The cold and mountainous regions of Siberia are great depositories of those vast
                stores of mineral wealth by which the Russian empire is encircled. The elevated
                districts of this vast country abound in the most precious ores of all the different
                metals.</p>
            <p>An official account of the produce of the mines of gold, silver, and platina, in
                Russia, has been published at St. Petersburg ; it embraces a period of sixteen
                years, from 1823 to 1838 inclusive, and shews the following results :—</p>
            <table cols="4"> <row><cell/><cell>Gold. Poods.</cell> <cell>Silver. Poods.</cell> <cell>Platina. Poods.</cell></row>
            <row><cell>Produce of the Imperial mines—</cell><cell cols="3"/></row>
            <row><cell>   In Ural,</cell> <cell>1,592</cell><cell>...</cell><cell>29</cell></row>
            <row><cell>   In Altai,</cell> <cell>538½</cell> <cell>14,704¼</cell><cell>...</cell></row>
            <row><cell>   In Nertshinskoi,</cell><cell> 9¾</cell> <cell>3,301¾</cell><cell>...</cell></row>
            <row><cell>Produce of mines belonging to individuals,</cell>
             <cell>3,009¾</cell> <cell>...</cell>
                <cell>1,230</cell></row>
            <row><cell/><cell>5,150½</cell> <cell>18,006</cell> <cell>1,259</cell></row></table>
            <p>Value in Sterling about L.12,000,000 and L.6,000,000.</p>
            <p>During the same period, the value of money coined at the Imperial Mint at St.
                Petersburg, from Russian and foreign bullion, was about L.14,000,000 in gold,
                L.8,000,000 in silver, and L.400,000 in platina.</p>
            <p>The population of Siberia consists of numerous tribes, who differ in their origin and
                their manners, and have been gradually subjected to the Russian authority, paying a
                stated tribute, which is not oppressive, and following their own pursuits
                unmolested. The Mongols, who withdrew from the Chinese dominion during the last
                century, and voluntarily placed themselves under the dominion of Russia, inhabit the
                regions about the Selenga, in the government of Irkutsk, from the 122d to the l25th
                degree of longitude, and between the 50th and 53d degree of north latitude They
                consist of seven stems, or twenty families, which were estimated to compose 6918
                males in 1766. The Burats inhabit Daouria, the banks of the Selenga, of the lake
                Baikal, and of the Upper Jenesei. They are remarkably industrious, and are chiefly
                employed in pastoral pursuits. The Tartars form a very numerous race, and are found
                scattered over Siberia, under the different appellations of Tobolskian Tartars, from
                the river Tobol, on which they dwell ; the Tom- skian Tartars, who inhabit both
                sides of the river Tom, above and below the city of Tomsk ; the Krasnayarskian and
                the Kusneretskian Tartars, who greatly resemble the Mongolian tribes; the Tartars of
                the Obi, who are partly agricultural and partly pastoral in their habits ; the
                Tartar tribe, which dwelt formerly between the Obi and the Jenesei, but which now
                inhabit the whole country along the river Tschulym ; other tribes, of which it would
                serve little purpose to give the barbarous appellatious, inhabit the country between
                the Obi and the Irtysch, which is called the steppe of Baraba. There are others on
                the left shore of the Jenesei, upon which they follow their pastoral occupations
                amongst the Sayome mountains. Certain districts in the governments of Tobolsk and
                Kolhyvan, and partly in the eastern half of that of Perm, beyond the Ural mountains,
                are to be regarded as the peculiar home and seat of the Siberian Tartars. The
                northern districts of Siberia are possessed by twenty tribes, peculiar to itself.
                The principal are the Tungouses on the Jenesei, the Ostiaks, the Yakantes, the
                Samoiedes, and the Tchantchis. The extensive deserts on which roam the pastoral
                tribe of the Tungouses, extend eastward across the Lena, as far as the Amoor and the
                Eastern Ocean. They extend northward from the 53d to the 65th degree. The history of
                the Samoiedes is little known. Their present abodes are on the coasts of the Frozen
                Ocean, from about the 65th degree of north latitude, quite to the sea shore. They
                swarm up to the 75th degree of north latitude, dwelling on the coldest and most
                desolate regions of the earth, from the White Sea to the other side of the Jenesei,
                and almost up to the Lena, and, therefore, being both in Europe and in Siberia.
                There are the Ostiaks of the Obi, of the Narym, and of the Jenesei. The Ostiaks are
                not numerous ; but they include many subordinate tribes, which it is unnecessary to
                specify by name, as they all resemble each other in manners. Giorgi gives the
                following statement of the population in 1801. In the government of Tobolsk, 622,422
                ; in the government of Irkutsk, 451,937.</p>
            <p>The religion generally diffused amongst these wild tribes, if it deserve the name, is
                a rude superstition, or idolatry, congenial to the state of barbarism which
                generally prevails. The system of Boodh, or of the Lamas, is the creed of the
                Mongols and Tartars ; and the residence of the Lama, the chief of that religion, is
                on the Upper Selenga, to the south of Baikal. The great temple was entered by a late
                traveller, who found there about a hundred priests, clothed in red, and seated in
                successive rows. The high-priest was seated upon a lofty and splendid throne, behind
                which was an altar, upon which were placed the images of their gods, the inferior
                ones being arranged in rows along the wall. Offerings were presented to them of
                rice, brandy, and sometimes a hen or sheep roasted whole. Their worship consists in
                a great measure of noise, the most formidable sounds being produced by a combination
                of the most noisy instruments, such as bells, kettle-drums, trumpets, shells, and
                other instruments. Those superstitious rites are, however, denounced by the pure
                followers of the genuine Lamas. They practise other vile and bloody rites, by way of
                expiating the anger of their gods ; such as leaping, and howling in a frightful
                mannner, and pretending to wound their backs with knives. Amongst the rude wanderers
                in the northern regions of Siberia complete paganism prevails, consisting of the
                ignorant arts of sorcery, and the worship of deformed stone images. The light of
                Christianity has hardly yet penetrated into these benighted regions. By the recent
                enterprising and active efforts, however, of the missionary societies of Britain,
                aided by the countenance of the Russian government, a beginning has been made in the
                great work of civilizing and of converting these barbarous tribes.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
