<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-25T20:17:43Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sinus</hi>, in <hi rend="italic">Surgery,</hi> a little cavity or sacculus, frequently formed by a wound or ulcer, in which pus is collected.</p><p>SION, a small town and port in the island of Bombay, situated about nine miles from the presidency, at the oppo- site extremity of the island, on the top of a small conical hill, where it commands the passage from Bombay to the neighbouring island of Salsette. A causeway was built by Mr. Duncan across a small arm of the sea, which separated the two islands. It has a draw-bridge in the centre.</p><p>SIPHANTO, an island in the Ægeian sea subject to Turkey, south-west from Paros, and north-east from Komili. It is forty-five square miles in extent, and generally moun- tainous. Its inhabitants are about 5000, chiefly Greek by religion, and wholly so by origin, who grow corn, capers, figs, oil, cotton, and vines. They have some small ma- nufactures of silk, linen, sail-cloth, and straw hats. This island had in ancient times mines of gold and silver, but no traces of them now exist. There is one town and five villages. The town has the same name as the island. Lat. 37. 1. Long. 24. 33. E.</p><p>SI-PORAH, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Good Fortune Island</hi>, a woody island in the Eastern seas, inhabited by the same race of people as the Poggy or Napan islands, from which it lies north-west.</p><p>SIR, the title of a knight or baronet, which, for distinction’s sake, as it is now given indiscriminately to all men, is always prefixed to the knight’s Christian name, either in speaking or in writing to him.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir Charles Hardy’s</hi> island, in the Southern Pacific Ocean, discovered by Captain Carteret in the year 1767. Long. 154. 6. E. Lat-4. 38. S.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir Charles</hi> H<hi rend="smallcaps">ardy’s Islands,</hi> a cluster of small islands in the South Pacific Ocean, discovered by Captain Cook in 1770. Long. 217. W. Lat. 11. 55. S.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir Charles Saunders’ Island,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Tapooamanhoo,</hi> in the Southern Pacific Ocean, discovered by Captain Wallis in 1765. It is about six miles in length. Long. 150. 40. W. Lat. 17. 28. S.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir Ηενrυ Martin's Island,</hi> in the Pacific Ocean, discovered by Lieutenant Hergest in 1792, and the most fertile and considerable of the group to which it belongs. Long. 220. 19. E. Lat. 80. 51. S.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir Isaac Ροιντ,</hi> a cape on the south coast of New Hol- land. Long. 135. 10. E. Lat. 34. 27. S.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir Joseph Banks’ Group,</hi> a cluster of small islands in Spencer’s Gulf, on the south coast of New Holland.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir Roger Curtis' Isles,</hi> an island, with two smaller ones near it, on the south coast of New Holland, twenty-two miles south-east of Wilson’s promontory.</p><p>SIRAF, a small sea-port of Persia, in Laristan, chiefly inhabited by Arabians. Thirty-eight miles south-west of Lar.</p><p>SIRCAR, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Circar</hi>, any office under the government in Hindustan. It is sometimes used for the state of govem- ment itself; likewise a province, or any number of pergun- nahs placed under one head in the government books, for convenience in keeping accounts. In common usage, the under banyans of European gentlemen are, in Bengal, call- ed <hi rend="italic">sircars.</hi></p><p>SIRE, a title of honour formerly given to the king of France as a mark of sovereignty.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sire,</hi> was also anciently used in the same sense with <hi rend="italic">sieur </hi>and <hi rend="italic">seigneur,</hi> and applied to barons, gentlemen, and citizens.</p><p>SIRENS, in fabulous history, certain celebrated song- stresses who were ranked amongst the demigods of antiquity. Hyginus places their birth amongst the consequences of the rape of Prosperine. Others make them daughters of the river Acheleüs and one of the muses. The number of the Sirens was three, and their names were Parthenope, Lygea, and Leucosia. Some make them half women and half fish; others half women and half birds; there are antique representations of them still subsisting under both these</p><p>forms. Pausanias tells us, that the Sirens, by the persuasion of Juno, challenged the Muses to a trial of skill in singing; and these having vanquished them, plucked the golden feathers from the wings of the Sirens, and formed them into crowns, with which they adorned their own heads. The Argonauts are said to have been diverted from the enchantment of their songs by the superior strains of Orpheus, Ulysses, however, had great difficulty in securing himself from seduction.</p><p>Pope, in his notes to the twelfth book of the Odyssey, observes, that the critics have greatly laboured to explain what was the foundation of this fiction of the Sirens. We are told by some, that the Sirens were queens of certain small islands named <hi rend="italic">Sirenusæ,</hi> that lie near Capræa in Italy, and chiefly inhabited the promontory of Minerva, upon the top of which that goddess had a temple built by Ulysses.</p><p>Mr. Bryant says, however, that the Sirens were Cuthite and Canaanitish priests, who had founded temples in Sicily, which were rendered infamous on account of the women who officiated. They were much addicted to cruel rites, so that the shores upon which they resided are described as covered with the bones of men destroyed by their artifice.</p><p>All ancient authors agree in telling us, that Sirens inha- bited the coast of Sicily. The name, according to Bochart, who derives it from the Phoenician language, implies a songstress. Hence it is probable, says Dr. Burney, that in ancient times there may have been excellent singers, but of corrupt morals, on the coast of Sicily, who, by seducing voyagers, gave rise to this fable. And if this conjecture be well founded, he observes, the Muses are not the only pagan divinities who preserved their influence over mankind in modern times; for every age has its Sirens, and every Siren her votaries. When beauty and talents, both powerful in themselves, are united, they become still more attractive.</p><p>SIRGOOJAH, a town and district of Hindustan, in the province of Gundwana, the latter situated about the 23d de- gree of north latitude. The town is situated about twelve miles from the northern frontier of Palamow. Long. 83.50. E. Lat. 23. 5. N.</p><p>SIRHIND, a town and district in the province of Delhi, of which the latter occupies the north-western quarter, be- ing situated between the 30th and 31st degrees of north 1a- titude. It is not fertile, being barren and sandy, and in many places destitute of water. Its vicinity to the capital was, however, in its favour, as the Afghan emperor, Feroze III. caused several canals to be cut from the rivers Jumna and Suttubje, in order to fertilize it. The country is at present possessed by the Seiks. Its principal towns are Pati- cola, which is large and flourishing, and Tahnesir. The town was built or repaired by Sultan Feroze about the year 1351. It is now a scene of desolation, and has never reco- vered the dreadful ravages to which it was exposed by the Seiks in 1707. It is 155 miles north north-west from Delhi. Long. 75. 55. E. Lat. 30. 40. N.</p><p>SIRINAGAR, a town of Hindustan, in the province of Allahabad, district of Bundelama, twelve miles north north- east from Chatterpoor. Long. 79. 55. E. Lat. 25. 6. N.</p><p>SIROCCO, a periodical wind which generally blows in Italy and Dalmatia every year about Easter. It blows from the south-east by south. It is attended with heat, but not rain. Its ordinary period is twenty days, and it usually ceases at sunset.</p><p>SIRSEY, a small town of Hindustan, in the province of Bahar, twenty-five miles east south-east from Patna. Long.· 85. 35. E. Long. 25. 22. N.</p><p>SIRVATON, a rock in the Eastern seas, near the north coast of Java. Long. 110. 49. E. Lat. 6. 36. S.</p><p>SISTRUM, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Cistrum</hi>, a kind of ancient musical instrument used by the priests of Isis and Osiris. It is de- scribed by Spon as of an oval form ; in manner of a racket, with three sticks traversing it breadthwise, which playing</p></body></text></TEI>