<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-03-25T20:16:52Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>neral, that he has observed it. And if he does not thoroughly understand its meaning,
                he intimates this by another general signal. And here it is to be observed, that as
                soon as the signal is answered by the ships to which it is addressed, it is usual to
                haul it down, to avoid the confusion which might arise from others being hoisted in
                the same place. The order remains till executed, notwithstanding that the signal is
                hauled down.</p>
            <p>It may happen that the commander who throws out the signal for any piece of service,
                sees reasons for altering his plan. He intimates this by a general annulling signal,
                accompanying the signal already given. This will frequently be more simple than to
                make the signals for the movements which would be required for re-establishing the
                ships in their former situation.</p>
            <p>All these things are of very easy comprehension, and require little thought for their
                contrivance. But when we come to the particular evolutions and movements, and to
                combine these with the circumstances of situation in which the fleet may be at the
                time, it is evident that much reflection is necessary for framing a body of signals
                which may be easily exhibited, distinctly perceived and well understood, with little
                risk of being mistaken one for another. We shall take notice of the circumstances
                which chiefly contribute to give them these qualities as we proceed in describing
                their different classes.</p>
            <list type="ordered">
                <item><hi rend="italic">Of Day Signals.</hi></item>
            </list>
            <p>These are made by means of signals of different colours ; but before we proceed to
                the description of the signals by means of colours, such as flags, banners, or
                triangular flags, pendants, or vanes, we must take notice of the ostensible
                distinctions of the various divisions and subdivisions of a fleet, so that we may
                understand how the same signal may be addressed to a squadron, division, or single
                ship or ships. We suppose it known that a fleet of ships of war is distributed into
                three grand divisions, which we shall term squadrons, called the van, centre, and
                rear. These denominations have not always a relation to the one being more advanced
                than the other, either towards the enemy or in the direction of their course.</p>
            <p>In a land army, the position of every part is conceived from its reference to the
                enemy ; and the reader, conceiving himself as facing the enemy, easily understands
                the terms van, centre, and rear, the right and left wing, and so forth. But the
                movements of a sea army having a necessary dependence on the wind, they cannot be
                comprehended unless expressed in a language which keeps this circumstance
                continually in view. The simplest and most easily conceived disposition of a fleet,
                is that in which it is almost indispensably obliged to form in order to engage an
                enemy. This is a straight line, each ship directly ahead of its neighbour, and
                close-hauled. This is therefore called the line of battle. In this position, the two
                extremities of the fleet correspond to the right and left wings of an army. Suppose
                this line to be in the direction east and west, the wind blowing from the
                north-north-west, and therefore the fleet on the starboard tack ; the ships’ heads
                are to the west, and the westermost division is undoubtedly the van of the fleet,
                and the eastermost division is the rear. And it is in conformity to this arrangement
                and situation that the list of the fleet is drawn up. But the ships may be on the
                same east and west line, close-hauled, with their heads to the west, but the wind
                blowing from the south-south-west. They must therefore be on the larboard tack. The
                same ships, and the same division, are still, in fact, the van of the fleet. But
                suppose the ships’ heads to be to the eastward, and that they are close-hauled,
                having the wind from the south-south- east or the north-north-east, the ships which
                were the real van on both tacks in the former situation, are now, in fact, the rear
                on both tacks ; yet they retain the denomination of the van squadron of this fleet,
                and are under the immediate direction of the officer of the second rank, while the
                other extremity is under the direction of the third officer. This subordination
                therefore is rather an arrangement of rank and precedence than of evolution. It is,
                however, considered as the natural order to which the general signals must be
                accommodated. For this reason, the division which is denominated van in the list of
                this fleet, is generally made to lead the fleet when in the line of battle on the
                starboard tack, and to form the weathermost column in the order of sailing in
                columns ; and, in general, it occupies that station from which it can most easily
                pass into the place of the leading division on the starboard line of battle ahead.
                Although this is a technical nicety of language, and may frequently puzzle a
                landsman in reading an account of naval operations, the reflecting and intelligent
                reader will see the propriety of retaining this mode of conceiving the subordinate
                arrangement of a fleet, and will comprehend the employment of the signals which are
                necessary for re-establishing this arrangement, or directing the movements while
                another arrangement is retained.</p>
            <p>This being understood, it is easy to contrive various methods of distinguishing every
                ship by the place which she occupies in the fleet, both with respect to the whole
                line, with respect to the particular squadron, the particular division of that
                squadron, and the particular place in that division. This may be done by a
                combination of the position and colour of the pendants and vanes of each ship. Thus
                the colour of the pendants may indicate the squadron, their position or mast on
                which they are hoisted may mark the division of that squadron, and a distinguishing
                vane may mark the place of the private ship in her own division. The advantages
                attending this method are many. In a large fleet it would hardly be possible for the
                commander-in-chief to find a sufficient variety of single signals to mark the ship
                to which an order is addressed, by hoisting it along with the signal appropriated to
                the intended movement. But by this contrivance one-third part of these signals of
                address is sufficient. It also enables the commander-in-chief to order a general
                change of position by a single signal, which otherwise would require several. Thus,
                suppose that the fore, main, and mizen masts, are appropriated, with the proper
                modifications, for exhibiting the signals addressed to the van, the centre, and the
                rear squadrons of the fleet, and that a red, a white, and a blue flag, are chosen
                for the distinguishing flags of the officers commanding these squadrons ; then, if
                the commander-in-chief shall hoist a red flag at his mizen topgallant mast-head, it
                must direct the van squadron to take the position then occupied by the rear
                squadron, the evolution necessary for accomplishing this end being supposed known by
                the commander of the squadron, who will immediately make the necessary signals to
                the squadron under his particular direction. In the same manner, the distinguishing
                signal for the leading ship of a squadron being hoisted along with the signal of
                address to the whole fleet, and the signal for any particular service, will cause
                the three or the nine leading ships to execute that order.</p>
            <p>All that has been said hitherto may be considered as so many preparations for the
                real issuing of orders by the commander-in-chief. The most difficult part of the
                language remains, viz. to invent a number of signals which shall correspond to that
                almost infinite variety of movements and services which must be performed.</p>
            <p>Distinctness, simplicity, and propriety, are the three essential qualities of all
                signals. A signal must be some object easily seen, strongly marked, so that it may
                be readily understood, with little risk of its being mistaken for another. When made
                by flags, banners, or pendants, they must be of the fullest colours, and strongest
                contrasts. The ships are frequently at a very great distance, so that the inter</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
