<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-25T20:18:19Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>purposes, without any regard to the formation of a fresh supply. That the land is capable of furnishing plenty of this valuable article, is evident from the manner in which young forest trees of various kinds shoot up in the mountainous districts, and in the escars which traverse the county in various directions, checked in their growth only by want of due care to protect the young shoots from the depredations of cattle. But this defect in the picturesque and agricultural character of the surface is daily diminishing. The attention of the principal landholders is now particularly directed to the increase of forest timber, and numerous plantations are to be seen round the mansions and villas of the gentry, particularly on the borders of the beautiful lakes which grace the landscape. The prevalence of western gales from the Atlantic forbids the full growth of any trees near the shore, except the willow and sycamore, which are observed to incline in the direction of the prevailing blast. Arbutus of small size grows freely in most parts, as does the myrtle in more favoured aspects. Many parts of the beach along the sea-shore is covered with a coraline sand, interspersed with numerous beds of oyster-shells of considerable extent. These beds are also found in some parts of the interior, at elevations of more than fifty feet above high water mark.</p><p>The population, like that of every other county in Ireland, has been steadily on the increase, ever since the observations of statistical writers have been directed to this subject. The numbers of inhabitants at several periods, are as follows :</p><p>Year.	Authority.	No.</p><p>1760	.....De Burgo	38,736</p><p>1792	Beaufort	60,000</p><p>1812	Parliamentary census..119,265</p><p>1821	ditto	146,229</p><p>1831	ditto	171,508</p><p>According to the last of these results, the population is to the acreable extent of the cultivated land, as one to 1.585 acres, and to that of the total landed surface, as one to 2.693 ; or, in other words, there is one; inhabitant to every acre and a-half in the first ease, and to every two acres and a-half in the second. The census taken by the commissioners of Public Instruction in 1834, being arranged in dioceses instead of counties, cannot be depended on as strictly accurate. According to it, the population may be estimated at 174,400, of which number 17,900 were Protestants, and 156,500 Roman Catholics; the former being to the latter as one to nine nearly. The number of presbyterians and other dissenters, who are included in the preceding statement of numbers among the protestants, amounts only to 560. The number of children receiving instruction in public schools, was as follows, ac- cording to the returns made under the Population act in 1821, the Commission of Education in 1824-6, the Commission of Public Instruction in 1834, and the Report of the Commissioners of National Education in 1839:</p><p>Sex not</p><p>Males. Females. ascertained. Total.</p><p>1821	5849	3010	—	8,859</p><p>1824—6	6516	 3686	 221	10,432</p><p>1834	8562	5259	—	13,821</p><p>1838	1551	1102	—	2,653</p><p>In the return of 1824—6, the only one in which the difference of religious persuasion is noted, the numbers of each of these are, of the Established Church, 2558; Protestant dissenters, 200; and Roman Catholics, 7495; the religion of the remaining one hundred and eighty not having been ascertained. Of the total number of schools, two hundred and twenty-six, included in the same return, one hundred and thirty were pay-schools, in which the teachers were</p><p>remunerated by the pupils’ fees, seventy-four were supported, either wholly or partially, by voluntary subscriptions, and but twenty-two by grants of public money.</p><p>The county is divided into the six baronies of Carbery, Coolavin, Corran, Leney, Tiraghrill, and Tyreragh, which are subdivided into thirty-nine parishes: of these, twenty- three are in the diocese of Tuam, and sixteen in that of Elphin. The county was represented in the Irish Parliament by four members; two for the county and two for the borough of Sligo. By the act of Union, the number was reduced to three, one being deducted from the borough. The Reform act made no change in this respect. The constituency of the county, as registered under the same act at different periods, together with the numbers under the previous act of 1829, by which the forty-shilling constituency had been abolished, was as follows :</p><p>£50.	4'20.	£10. Total.</p><list type="ordered"><item>	 399	315	299	1013</item><item>	 168	151	370	695</item></list><p>1834 	 _	_	_	804</p><p>1837 	 273	220	546	1039</p><p>According to the last specified return, the number of electors is to the total population as one to one hundred and fifty, and to the number of heads of families as one to twenty- five. The county is in the Connaught circuit ; the assizes, and some of the sessions of the peace, are held in the town of Sligo, which contains the county court-house and prison. Sessions of the peace are also held at Ballymote and Easkey, where there are likewise court-houses and bridewells. The county infirmary, and four hospitals are in the first- named town. The lunatic asylum is in Ballynasloe, but several of the unhappy creatures, for whose protection and recovery it was designed, are still kept in the county jail. There are nine dispensaries in various places.</p><p>Most parts of the county afford ample scope for agricultural improvements, either in tillage or pasturage. Oats and potatoes are the principal crops on the tillage land. The culture of wheat was long unknown, the coldness and humidity of the climate having been deemed insuperable bars to its successful treatment, but it is now raised in considerable quantities on the rich lowlands. Green crops, under the rotation system, are also more and more attended to every year. Ploughing is usually effected by two horses, and, in some light soils, two asses are substituted for them ; oxen are never used for this purpose. The spade, in many of the mountain districts, still supplies the place of the plough. Fences of every kind are usually constructed ; those of dry stones being most common, particularly in the more elevated districts, where the farmers adopt this mode of structure as well to clear their fields of surface stones, as to secure them from trespass. Sea-weed, collected on the shore, which, some years ago, had been manufactured into kclp, is now used as manure, and is in such repute, that it is carried twenty miles up the country. The beds of oys- ter shells and the coraline sand on some stretches of the beach, arc applied to the same purpose. Tillage farms are from five acres, and even lower, to two hundred or three hundred in size. Those used chiefly for pasturage are often of much greater extent, and, until lately, were mostly held by a number of tenants in a species of partnership, according to which, each had an exclusive portion of tillage ground, while a large tract of mountain or coarse bottom- land was depasturced in common ; but this system has been for several years so much discouraged as to be nearly if not altogether obsolete. The average rent of land is ten shillings and eightpence per acre. Though the tillage sys- tem, as stated, is much encouraged and rapidly extending, it is still subordinate to that of pasturage, which is adopted in all parts of the county, and on every description of soil. Horned cattle of the largest size are fattened in the rich lowland plains; young cattle are reared in the hilly and</p></body></text></TEI>