<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-25T20:16:14Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>vers, and are only to be approached by having recourse to some stratagem, as waiting in a shed, or on an island, or on the banks of a pool, or stalking behind a horse trained to the purpose. The largest shoulder gun that is at hand may be used charged with the red or green wire-cartridges, the size of shot being regulated by the bore of the piece.</p><p>During a severe frost, wild-fowl are compelled to leave the pools, and are then found in small rivers., brooks, or in drains where there are springs of fresh water. The flights being broken, ducks are found singly or only few in number, and are consequently easy of access, and may be shot with a common fowling-piece. The size of shot should be No. 2, or. 3. Wild-fowl are so fortified with down on some parts as to resist any but hard-stricken shot. Their back is the most vulnerable part, and all kinds of wild-fowl present it to the shooter as they rise. They are also easily brought down when they present a cross shot ; but when approaching it is not advisable to fire at them. If a dog accompany the shooter, it should follow at heel. As the shooter pursues the course of a river or brook, he should keep out of sight as much as possible, and come suddenly on every turn or winding. When there is a mist during a frost, wild ducks will remain in the brooks and gutters all day. The earlier in the morning the better for this sport. Ducks may also be killed on the wing, on the verge of night, by the shooter lying hid near to fresh water springs. If it be a dark evening, he need only wait about a quarter of an hour, but if moonlight he may wait about an hour. They may also be walked up on a moonlight night, when, if they rise above the horizon, they may be killed almost as easily as in the day time. The objection to night shooting is, that birds knocked down are often lost. These are the principal methods by which ducks are killed by any but professed wild-fowl shooters.</p><p>The larger kinds of wild-fowl, such as hoopers <hi rend="italic">(wild swans)</hi> and geese, can rarely be brought down by the common fowling-piece, unless, struck on the head or back. Wild-fowl shooting, in creeks and harbours on the sea-coast, is conducted in a very different manner, and on a larger scale-of operations. There are two kinds of guns used for the purpose, the shoulder-gun and the punt-gun ; the latter being fired from a rest, or frame, or carriage, either in a boat or some other floating craft. Mr. Greener, to whose work we have already referred, says, “ Never make duck guns (shoulder-guns) above seven-eighths in the. bore, if you wish them to kill at a great distance, and not less than fifteen or sixteen pounds weight, and full four feet long.” Colonel Hawker,@@<hi rend="superscript">,</hi> who has devoted nearly one hundred and fifty pages to the subject of wild-fowl shooting, says, “ The barrel of a punt-gun, to be in good proportion, should, I conceive, (including the patent plug, of about six pounds weight, and from two to three inches in length), be about seventy or eighty pounds weight, from seven to nine feet long, and from an inch and a quarter, to an inch and a half bore, according to the one length and weight, or the other. The smaller the bore is, in reason, the further you can kill at a small number of birds; but the larger size of thesetwo shoots the best, and is the most regular pattern. Any thing beyond that size seldom answers.” Both these writers seem to agree that the common punt-gun, though it weigh eighty or one hundred pounds, cannot be charged to the extent of its shooting powers, by reason of the tremendous recoil that would result; but each advises that the additional weight should be gained by using the barrels double. Thus more than a double advantage would be secured, for not only would there be two barrels at command, but the discharge from each barrel would be more effective. The charge of shot for a punt-gun averages from ten to twenty ounces ; the shot is much larger than any used for shooting game.</p><p>The Colonel, and we apprehend he is the only practical writer on this department of the subject, describes the various kinds of punts (which are flat-bottomed boats or canoes, so constructed as to be manageable either on sands, or in mud, or water,) used in several different counties, and gives the following directions for shooting wild-fowl, from a punt, with a large shoulder-gun. “ Sit down on some straw or rushes, with your gun by your side, and take with you a small Newfoundland dog. Row about, till you can see or hear a flock of wild-fowl on the mud. To find them sitting, if by night, look at first Very low, so as to bring the surface of the mud in contrast with the horizon, by which means you will overlook the black edges of the creeks and holes, instead of seeing, and perhaps mistaking them for birds. :</p><p>“ When you have rowed within two or three gun-shots of the fowl, take in your oars, and reconnoitre the creeks. Having ascertained which is likely to be the best, lie down, and push along with the <hi rend="italic">setting pole</hi> or <hi rend="italic">gunning spread, </hi>and while the mud banks stand above the little channels, you are so completely hid, that you will seldom fail to get a shot, provided there is a creek within reach of the birds, and you do not go directly to windward of them.</p><p>“ On arriving sufficiently near, should the water be so low that you cannot present your gun at the birds without kneeling or standing up, you must get aground at the side of the creek, or steady your canoe by means of forcing each oar from between the <hi rend="italic">thowls</hi> into the mud, otherwise the recoil of the gun will set her rocking, and thus you might probably be tipped out. Having made all fast, rise up and fire. Take care, however, to rise high enough to be well clear of the mud, or not a feather will you touch ; and present as follows : By day, or moonlight, if the birds are close, directly at them ; or if beyond forty yards, shoot at their heads; unless they are feeding in a concave place, where the tide has left a kind of plash, in which case you must level rather under them, or you will only graze their back feathers. In star-light, take your aim just at the top of the narrow black line, in which birds always appear to one who is low down ; and when so dark that you cannot see your gun, present, as you think, about a foot over, or you will most likely shoot above a foot under them.</p><p>Should you have been successful, you will, if at night, generally hear your cripples (wounded fowl) beating On the mnd, before you can sufficiently recover your eyes, from being dazzled by the fire, to see them. Your man then puts on his mud-boards, (which are flat square pieces of wood fastened to. the feet, to enable the party to walk Or wade through mud), taking the setting pole to support him, and assist the dog in collecting the killed and wounded; taking care to secure first the outside birds, lest they should escape to a creek. During this time you are left in charge of the punt ; and should, if possible, keep a look out, in order to see if any more birds fall dead or wounded from the company, before they have flown out of sight.</p><p>“ The gunner generally calculates on bringing home the half only of what he shoots, from the difficulty of catching the whole of his winged birds, which he calls <hi rend="italic">cripples,</hi> and those that (to use the pigeon phrase) fall out of bounds, which he calls <hi rend="italic">droppers.</hi> If the birds fly up, he generally declines firing, knowing that the moment they are on the wing, they become so much more spread·, that he could seldom get more than three or four, for which it would be hardly worth while to disturb the mud; particularly as</p><p><hi rend="superscript">@@@1</hi> Instructions to Young Sportsmen. Eighth edition. London, 1838.</p></body></text></TEI>