<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-25T20:18:25Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>lumes which appeared during that period are monuments of his industry and ingenuity, many of the pieces contained in them being written by himself.</p><p>In the mean time he published <hi rend="italic">catalogus Plantarum gua in Insula Jamaica sponte proveniunt ; seu Prodromi Historice Naturalis pars prima ;</hi> which he dedicated to the Royal Society and the College of Physicians. About the same time he formed the plan of a dispensary, where the poor might be furnished at prime cost with such medicines as their several maladies might require; and this he afterwards carried into execution, with the assistance of the president and other members of the College of Physicians.</p><p>His eager thirst for natural knowledge seems to have been bom with him, so that his cabinet of curiosities may be said to have commenced with his being. He was continually enriching and enlarging it; and the fame which, in the course of a few years, it had acquired, brought every thing that was curious in art or nature to be first offered to him for purchase. These acquisitions however increased it but very slowly in comparison of the augmentation which it received in 1701 by the death of Mr. William Courten, a gentleman who had employed all his time, and the greater part of his fortune, in collecting rarities, and who bequeathed the whole to Dr. Sloane, on condition of his paying certain debts and legacies with which he had charged it. These terms our author accepted, and he executed the will of the donor with the most scrupulous exactness; on which account some people have said, that he purchased Mr. Courten’s curiosities at a dear rate.</p><p>In 1707 the first volume of Dr. Sloane’s Natural History of Jamaica appeared in folio, though the publication of the second was delayed till 1725. By this very useful as well as magnificent work, the materia medica was enriched with a great number of excellent drugs not before known. In 1708 the author was elected a foreign member of the Royal Academy of Sciences at Paris, in the room of Mr. Tschir- naus; an honour so much the greater, as we were then at war with France, and the queen’s express consent was necessary before he could accept it. In proportion as his credit rose among the learned, his practice increased among the people of rank. Queen Anne herself frequently consulted him, and in her last illness was blooded by him.</p><p>On the advancement of George I. to the throne, that prince, on the 3d of April 1716, created Sloane a baronet, an hereditary title of honour to which no English physician had before attained; and at the same time made him physician-general to the army, in which station he continued till 1727, when he was appointed physician in ordinary to George II. He attended the royal family till his death ; and was particularly favoured by Queen Caroline, who placed the greatest confidence in his prescriptions. In the mean time he had been unanimously chosen one of the elects of the College of Physicians on the 1st of June 1716, and he was elected president of the same body on the 30th of September 1719, an office which he held for sixteen years. During that period he not only gave the highest proofs of his zeal and assiduity in the discharge of his duty, but in 1721 made a present to that society of L.100, and so far remitted a very considerable debt, which the corporation owed him, as to accept it in such small sums as were least inconvenient to the state of their affaire. Sir Hans was no less liberal to other learned bodies. He had no sooner purchased the manor of Chelsea, than he gave the company of apothecaries the entire freehold of their botanical garden there, upon condition only that they should present yearly to the Royal Society fifty new plants, till the number should amount to two thousand.@@<hi rend="superscript">,</hi> He gave besides several other considerable donations for the improvement of this garden, the situation of which, on the banks of the Thames, and in the neighbourhood of the capital, was such as to render it useful in two respects ; first, by producing the most rare medicinal plants ; and, secondly, by serving as an excellent school for young botanists, an advantage which he himself had derived from it in the early part of his life.</p><p>The death of Sir Isaac Newton, which happened in 1727, made way for the advancement of Sir Hans to the presidency of the Royal Society. He had been vice-president, and frequently sat in the chair for that great man; and by his long connection with this learned body he had contracted so strong an affection for it, that he made them a present of an hundred guineas, caused a curious bust of Charles II. its founder, to he erected in the great hall where it met, and, as is said, was very instrumental in procuring Sir Godfrey Copley’s benefaction of a medal of the value of five guineas, to be annually given as an honorary mark of distinction to the person who communicates the best experiments to the Society.</p><p>On his being raised to the chair, Sir Hans laid aside all thoughts of further promotion, and applied himself wholly to the faithful discharge of the duties of the offices which he enjoyed. In these laudable occupations he employed his time, from 1727 to 1740, when, at the age of fourscore, he formed a resolution of quitting the service of the public, and of living for himself. With this view he resigned the presidency of the Royal Society much against the inclination of that respectable body, who chose Mr. Martin Folkes to succeed him, and in a public assembly thanked him for the great and eminent services which he had rendered them. In the month of January 1741, he began to remove his library, and his cabinet of rarities, from his house in Bloomsbury to that at Chelsea; and on the 12th of March following, having settled all his affairs, he retired thither himself, to enjoy in peaceful tranquillity the remains of a well-spent life. He did not however bury himself in that solitude which excludes men from society. He received in Chelsea, as he had done in London, the visits of people of distinction, of learned foreigners, and of the royal family, who sometimes did him the honour to wait on him; hut, what was still more to his praise, he never refused admittance or advice to rich or poor who came to consult him concerning their health. Not contented with this contracted method of doing good, he now, during his retreat, presented to the public such useful remedies as success had warranted, during the course of a long-continued practice. Among these, is the efficacious receipt for distempers in the eyes, and his remedy for the bite of a mad dog.</p><p>During the whole course of his life, Sir Hans had lived with so much temperance, as had preserved him from feeling the infirmities of old age; but in his ninetieth year he began to complain of pains, and to be sensible of a universal decay. He was often heard to say, that the approach of death brought no terrors along with it; that he had long expected the stroke ; and that he was prepared to receive it whenever the great Author of his being should think fit. After a short illness of three days, he died on the 11th o. January 1752, and was interred on the 18th at Chelsea, in</p><p><hi rend="superscript">@@@,</hi> This garden was first established by the company in 1673; and having, after that period, been stocked by them with a great variety of plants, for the improvement of botany. Sir Hnns, in order to encourage so serviceable an undertaking, granted to the company the inheritance of it, being part of his estate and manor of Chelsea, on condition that it should be for ever preserved as a physic garden. As n proof of its being so maintained, he obliged the company, in consideration of the said grant, to present yearly to the Royal Society, in one of their weekly meetings, fifty specimens of plants that had been grown in the garden the preceding year, and which were all to be specifically distinct from each other, until the number of two thousand should be completed. This number was completed in the year 1761. In 1733 the company erected a marble statue of Sir Hans, executed by Rysbrac, which is placed upon a pedestal in the centre of the garden, with a Latin inscription, expression bis donation, and the design and advantages of it.</p></body></text></TEI>