<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-03-25T20:16:58Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>This method requires the signal of advertisement, the annulling signal, the signal of
                address to the particular ship or division, the signa) of acknowledgment, the signal
                of indistinctness, of distress, of danger, and one or two more, which in every
                method must be employed.</p>
            <p>Another method of expressing numbers with fewer colours is as follows : Let the flags
                be A, B, C, D, E, F, and arrange them as follows :</p>
            <table>
                <row>
                    <cell/>
                    <cell><p>A</p><p>1</p></cell>
                    <cell><p>B</p><p>2</p></cell>
                    <cell><p>C</p><p>3</p></cell>
                    <cell><p>D</p><p>4</p></cell>
                    <cell><p>E</p><p>5</p></cell>
                    <cell><p>F</p><p>6</p></cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>A</cell>
                    <cell>7</cell>
                    <cell>8</cell>
                    <cell>9</cell>
                    <cell>10</cell>
                    <cell>11</cell>
                    <cell>12</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>B</cell>
                    <cell>13</cell>
                    <cell>14</cell>
                    <cell>15</cell>
                    <cell>16</cell>
                    <cell>17</cell>
                    <cell>18</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>C</cell>
                    <cell>19</cell>
                    <cell>20</cell>
                    <cell>21</cell>
                    <cell>22</cell>
                    <cell>23</cell>
                    <cell>24</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>D</cell>
                    <cell>25</cell>
                    <cell>26</cell>
                    <cell>27</cell>
                    <cell>28</cell>
                    <cell>29</cell>
                    <cell>30</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>E</cell>
                    <cell>31</cell>
                    <cell>32</cell>
                    <cell>33</cell>
                    <cell>34</cell>
                    <cell>35</cell>
                    <cell>36</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>F</cell>
                    <cell>37</cell>
                    <cell>38</cell>
                    <cell>39</cell>
                    <cell>40</cell>
                    <cell>41</cell>
                    <cell>42</cell>
                </row>
            </table>
            <p>The number expressed by any pair of flags is found in the intersection of the
                horizontal and perpendicular columns. Thus the flag D, hoisted along with and above
                the flag F, expresses the number 40, &amp;c. In order to express a greater number,
                (but not exceeding 84), suppose 75, hoist the flag C</p>
            <p>E, which expresses 33, or 75 wanting 42, and above them a flag or signal G, which
                alone expresses 42.</p>
            <p>This method may be still farther improved by arranging the flags thus :</p>
            <table>
                <row>
                    <cell/>
                    <cell><p>A</p><p>1</p></cell>
                    <cell><p>B</p><p>2</p></cell>
                    <cell><p>c</p><p>3</p></cell>
                    <cell><p>D</p><p>4</p></cell>
                    <cell><p>E</p><p>5</p></cell>
                    <cell><p>F</p><p>6</p></cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>A</cell>
                    <cell>7</cell>
                    <cell>8</cell>
                    <cell>9</cell>
                    <cell>10</cell>
                    <cell>11</cell>
                    <cell>12</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>B</cell>
                    <cell>—</cell>
                    <cell>13</cell>
                    <cell>14</cell>
                    <cell>15</cell>
                    <cell>16</cell>
                    <cell>17</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>C</cell>
                    <cell>—</cell>
                    <cell>—</cell>
                    <cell>18</cell>
                    <cell>19</cell>
                    <cell>20</cell>
                    <cell>21</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>D</cell>
                    <cell/>
                    <cell>—</cell>
                    <cell>—</cell>
                    <cell>22</cell>
                    <cell>23</cell>
                    <cell>24</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>E</cell>
                    <cell/>
                    <cell/>
                    <cell/>
                    <cell/>
                    <cell>25</cell>
                    <cell>26</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>F</cell>
                    <cell/>
                    <cell/>
                    <cell/>
                    <cell/>
                    <cell/>
                    <cell>27</cell>
                </row>
            </table>
            <p>In this last method the signification of the signal is totally independent of the
                position of the flags. In whatever parts of the ship the flags D and E are seen,
                they express the number 23. This would suit battle signals.</p>
            <p>Another method still may be taken. Flags hoisted anywhere on the foremast may be
                accounted units, those on the mainmast tens, and those on the mizenmast hundreds.
                Thus numeral signals may be made by a ship dismasted, or having only poles in their
                place. Many other ways may be contrived for expressing numbers by colours, and there
                is great room for exercising the judgment of the contriver. For it must always be
                remembered, that these signals must be accompanied with a signal by which it is
                addressed to some particular ship or division of the fleet, and it may be difficult
                to connect the one with the other, which is perhaps shewn in another place, and
                along with other executive signals.</p>
            <p>One great advantage of these numeral signals is, that they may be changed in their
                signification at pleasure. Thus, in the first method, it can be settled, that on
                Sundays the colours A, B, C, D, &amp;c., express the cyphers</p>
            <list type="ordered">
                <item>2, 3, 4, &amp;c., but that on Mondays they express the cyphers 0, 1,2, 3,
                    &amp;c., and on Tuesdays the cyphers 9, 0, 1,</item>
                <item>&amp;c., and so on through all the days of the week. This mean of secrecy is
                    mentioned by Dr. Hooke for the coast and alarm signals, where, by the bye, he
                    shews a method for conveying intelligence over land very similar to what is now
                    practised by the French with their telegraph.</item>
            </list>
            <p>It is equally easy to express numbers by night signals. Thus M. de la Bourdonnais
                proposes that one discharge of a great gun shall express 7, and that 1, 2, 3, 4, 5.
                6, shall be expressed by lights. Therefore to express 24, we must fire three guns,
                and shew three lights. This iβ the most perfect of all forms of night and fog
                signals. For both the manner of firing guns and of exhibiting lights may be va ried
                to a sufficient extent with very few guns or lights, and with great
                distinctness.</p>
            <p>Thus, for guns. Let F mark the firing of a single gun at moderate intervals, and <hi
                    rend="italic">ff</hi> a double gun, that is, two discharged at the interval of a
                second. We may express numbers thus :</p>
            <list type="ordered">
                <item>F.</item>
                <item>F, F.</item>
                <item>F, F, F.</item>
                <item>F, F, F, F.</item>
                <item><hi rend="superscript">F,</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">f,f.</hi></item>
                <item>F, F, <hi rend="italic">ff.</hi></item>
                <item>F,<hi rend="italic">ff,</hi> F.</item>
                <item>F,<hi rend="italic">ff,</hi> FF.</item>
                <item>F,<hi rend="italic">ff, F,ff.</hi></item>
            </list>
            <p>10<hi rend="italic"> ff.</hi></p>
            <p>100, &amp;c.,<hi rend="italic"> ff,ff,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">fff.</hi></p>
            <p>It might be done with fewer guns if the <hi rend="italic">ff</hi> were admitted as
                the first firing. But it seems better to begin always with the single gun, and thus
                the double gun beginning a signal distinguishes the tens, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>In like manner, a small number of lights will admit of a great variety of very
                distinct positions, which may serve for all signals to ships not very remote from
                the commander-in- chief. For orders to be understood at a very great distance, it
                will be proper to appropriate the numbers which are indicated by signals made with
                rockets. These can be varied in number and kind to a sufficient extent, so as to be
                very easily distinguished and understood. It is sufficient to have shewn how the
                whole, or nearly the whole notation of signals, may be limited to the expression of
                numbers.</p>
            <p>We have taken little notice of the signals made by private ships to the
                commander-in-chief. This is a very easy business, because there is little risk of
                confounding them with other signals. Nor have we spoken of signals from the flag
                ships whose ultimate interpretation is number, as when ships are directed to change
                their course so many points. Those also are easily contrived in any of the methods
                already described ; also when a private ship wishes to inform the commander-in-chief
                that soundings are found at so many fathoms. In like manner, by numbering the points
                of the compass, the admiral can direct to chace to any one of them, or may be
                informed of strange ships being seen in any quarter, and what is their number. <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">(b. b. b.)</hi></p>
            <p>Of late years, that is, within this century, a great improvement has taken place in
                the signal department of the Royal Navy. The following brief memorandum on the
                subject will give as general an idea on the subject as could be given without the
                introduction of coloured plates, and more copious explanations than are consistent
                with the plan of this work.</p>
            <p>There are three volumes of signals in use in the navy ; one is called “ General
                Signals,” the other “ Night and Fog Signals,” the other “Vocabulary Signals, for the
                use of her Majesty’s fleet.” The <hi rend="italic">General Signals</hi> consist of a
                set of numerical references, from 1 to 999, and contain all the most general orders
                relating to action, sailing, manœuvring, and every other evolution in use, either at
                sea or at anchor. All these signals are made by means of a set of numeral flags,
                from 1 to 9, with the addition of zero ; a set of divisional flags, to distinguish
                the different parts of a fleet ; flags to affirm signals, to annul them, and to
                prepare measures; interrogative, answering, compass, geographical, and horary
                pendants. These, with the union jack, compose the flags in use when the general
                signal-book is employed. All these flags and pendants depend upon their form and
                colour for their distinction, and are hoisted at the most conspicuous places for
                being seen, but seldom more than three at a time. Besides these, distant signals are
                made with square and tri-</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
