<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-03-25T20:14:29Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>the centre of gravity of the displacement when the ship is inclined. Draw OM
                perpendicular to <hi rend="italic">ac.</hi> Then, after the inclination, the line OM
                will be vertical. From F and G draw FT and GV, perpendicular to OM, and from G draw
                GZ parallel to MO, cutting FT in Z.</p>
            <p>Now, when the ship has inclined so that the point O becomes the centre of gravity of
                the displacement, the upward pressure of the water acts on the then vertical line
                OM, with a force equal to the weight of the ship, because it supports that weight ;
                that is to say, with a force equal to the displacement, which we will represent by
                D. But the axis of revolution is the point G the centre of gravity, and GV being
                drawn from this point perpendicular to the direction OM in which the force acts, D
                the displacement multiplied by GV, its perpendicular distance from the axis of
                rotation, will be the force exerted to right the ship, or make it resume its upright
                position. But, by the construction, D × GV = D × FT — D × FZ.</p>
            <p>Now D × FT is the horizontal moment of the displacement produced by the transfer of
                the solid from the weather to the lee side of the middle line ; it is therefore
                equal to the horizontal moment <hi rend="italic">bl,</hi> and consequently we have
                the effort to right the ship, or the moment of stability, as it is called, <hi
                    rend="italic">= b</hi>I — D × FZ.</p>
            <p>But if <hi rend="italic">s</hi> be taken = sin. of inclination,</p>
            <p>FZ = s × rad. FG, or if FG = d, then moment of stability = <hi rend="italic">bl —
                    D∙d∙s.</hi></p>
            <p>Hence, in order to calculate the actual moment of stability of a vessel at a given
                angle of inclination,</p>
            <list type="instructions" rend="numbered">
                <item>Assume an inclined load water-section, cutting the horizontal load
                    water-section at an angle of which <hi rend="italic">s</hi> is the sine ; and
                    suppose the assumed inclined and the horizontal load water-sections to intersect
                    each other in their common intersection with the longitudinal vertical section
                    of the ship.</item>
                <item>Find, by the methods of approximation, the solid contents of the two prismatic
                    solids of immersion and emersion, intercepted between the segments of the
                    inclined and the horizontal load water-sections.</item>
                <item>Find, by the method of approximating to the area of plane surfaces, the area
                    of the above-mentioned assumed inclined section.</item>
                <item>Find the value of DS (fig. 1), which has been shown to l&gt;e equal to the
                    difference between the contents of the prismatic solids of immersion and
                    emersion, already found, divided by the product of the area of the assumed
                    inclined section, into <hi rend="italic">s,</hi> the sine of the angle of
                    inclination.</item>
                <item>Through the point S draw a section parallel to the assumed inclined section;
                    find in each vertical transverse section the areas of each of the sections of
                    the true prismatic solids of immersion and emersion ; and also find the
                    horizontal moments of these areas from the point S.</item>
                <item>Find the horizontal distance of the centre of gravity of the whole emerged
                    solid from S, assuming the emerged solid to be equal to half the sum of the two
                    solids of immersion and emersion, which are intercepted between the segments of
                    the assumed inclined load water-section and the horizontal load
                    water-section.</item>
                <item>Find also the horizontal distance of the centre of gravity of the whole
                    immersed solid from S, assuming the immersed solid to be equal to half the sum
                    of the same two solids of immersion and emersion.</item>
                <item>Add these two distances together ; their sum will be the horizontal distance
                    between the centres of gravity of the solids of immersion and emersion. Take the
                    product of this distance multiplied into half the sum of the solids of immersion
                    and emersion, and we shall have the value of the positive part of the expression
                    for the moment of stability, or the value of <hi rend="italic">bl.</hi></item>
                <item>The product of three quantities, the displacement, the distance between the
                    centres of gravity of the ship and of the displacement, and the sine of the
                    angle of inclination, will give the value of the negative part of the
                    expression.</item>
                <item>10. Subtract the value of the negative part of the expression from that of the
                    positive part, and the remainder will be the value of the expression for the
                    moment of stability of the ship at the given angle of inclination.</item>
            </list>
            <p>It will be seen that the calculation of the moment of stability of a ship is very
                laborious. Several of the steps above enumerated in order, will, however, have been
                already taken for other purposes. The calculations may be considerably shortened by
                assuming a value for the distance DS, or the distance that the point S is from the
                middle line of the ship. We have already described the method of ascertaining this
                distance correctly, but generally it may be assumed to be about two or three tenths
                of a foot at first ; and if the solids of immersion and emersion arc not found to he
                equal, or very nearly so, with that assumption, another point must be taken, either
                within or without the former, according as the solid of immersion or emersion is the
                lesser. If <hi rend="italic">e</hi> be the difference between the two solids, and
                    <hi rend="italic">a</hi> the area of the first assumed inclined section, if <hi
                    rend="italic">x</hi> be the perpendicular distance between the true inclined
                section and the section we have assumed, <hi rend="italic">ax</hi> will cqual <hi
                    rend="italic">c</hi> nearly, or <hi rend="italic">x = </hi>which distance must
                be set off perpendicularly to the assumed section, and we obtain the correct
                position of the point S.</p>
            <p>In order to determine the distance <hi rend="italic">d</hi> between the centre of
                gravity of the ship and the centre of gravity of the displacement, the distance of
                the centre of gravity of the ship above or below the load water-line must be
                ascertained. To avoid the labour attendant on obtaining the position of this point
                by calculation, it may be determined experimentally in each class of ships of war
                when fully stowed and equipped.</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Method of ascertaining the centre of Gravity of a Ship by
                    Experiment.</hi></p>
            <p>We shall describe two methods of performing this experiment. The first of these was
                proposed by Chapman, and he strongly recommended that it should be made on ships of
                all classes. The principle on which it is founded is as follows. Various weights on
                board are removed in a transverse direction, so as to cause the ship to incline ;
                and the momentum of the total weight so removed will necessarily be equal to the
                moment of stability. Now the momentum of the weight removed will be equal to the
                product of the weights, the distance they are removed in a transverse direction, and
                the cosine of the angle of inclination ; which quantity, therefore, is equal to the
                moment of stability. If W represent the weights, <hi rend="italic">a</hi> the
                distance they are removed, and <hi rend="italic">c</hi> the cosine of the angle of
                inclination ; then, <hi rend="italic">bl — Dds </hi>being the expression for the
                moment of stability, we have this equation,</p>
            <p>W∙<hi rend="italic">a· c = b</hi>I<hi rend="italic"> —</hi> Dds,</p>
            <p>therefore<hi rend="italic"> d = </hi><hi rend="italic superscript">b</hi><hi
                    rend="superscript">I - W ∙ </hi><hi rend="italic superscript">a ∙ e</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> / </hi><hi rend="italic subscript">Ds</hi></p>
            <p>in which <hi rend="italic">d,</hi> the distance between the centre of gravity of the
                ship and the centre of gravity of the displacement, is the only unknown quantity,
                and may therefore easily be found.</p>
            <p>We shall now describe the method by which this experiment was applied to determine
                the centre of gravity of her majesty’s ship sl∞p Scylla, of eighteen guns, and which
                was originally an eighteen-gun brig. She was lying in Portsmouth harbour in May
                1830, under the command of Captain Hindmarsh, at whose request the experiment was
                performed, by the late Mr Morgan of the School of Naval Architecture, then a foreman
                of her majesty’s dock-yard at Portsmouth, assisted by the writer of the present
                article.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
