<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-25T20:16:01Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>tends along the Caspian, 200 miles from the mouth of the Cyrus, to the little river Rubas ; and forms a large triangular peninsula, the point of which stretches into the Cas- pian. From its form it varies extremely in breadth, which, at the extremity of the peninsula on the Rubas, is scarcely sixteen miles ; near Kuba it amounts to forty ; from the mouth of the Ata it is above fifty ; while in the in- terior part it amounts to 160. It has the Caspian to the east ; Daghestan to the north ; the Kur and the plains of Mogam to the south and south-west, being separated by the river Kur from the provinces of Ghilan and Azerbijan ; and the kingdom of Georgia to the north-west. The north- ern part of this province consists of a plain, which is formed by the mountains that extend toward the sea near Derbend, and which, gradually receding behind that city, approach again in a circular form near the sea at the mouth of the river Ata. Numerous streams, issuing from the mountains, greatly contribute to fertilize this plain, and, at the same time, to secure it against the access of an invading army. They branch off in various directions, and being generally mountain-streams, are uncommonly rapid, though they are shallow, with a wide channel, and a rough and sandy bed. The plain is interspersed with small woods and clumps of bushes, and the villages are surrounded with orchards, vineyards, and plantations of mulberries. The second division of Schirvan extends on one side along the coast from the Ata to the plains watered by the Kur; and on the other it is bounded by the higher range of mountains, which run in a south-east course through the province. The length of this district is about eighty miles ; but as the coast projects considerably, the breadth varies. The higher portions of the country are here the most fertile ; the part towards the sea is barren, being devoid of water ; and to the north of Baku is a desert tract of about fifty miles. The plain along the left of the Kur is about 140 miles in length, and from forty to fifty in breadth. The district is in a great degree surrounded with mountains, and, being exposed to frequent inundations, is overgrown with rushes to a considerable distance. The most elevated division of Schirvan is that which extends from the Rubas to Lesges- tan. This tract varies much in breadth, and is intersected by narrow valleys, in many of which are small lakes, which continue filled even in the greatest heat of summer. This province is abundantly watered by streams, which fall, some into the Caspian, and others into the Kur. The most considerable are the Samur, Deli, Sagaite, and Persagat. This province was annexed to Persia in the year 1500, and con- tinued subject to that empire till the decline of the Sefi dynasty, when the native princes, taking advantage of the weakness of Persia, re-established their independence. Of late, however, the Russians have obtained possession of the sea-coast, though the interior is still in the hands of the native chiefs. The principal towns are Schamachi, the ca- pital, and Baku.</p><p>SHOAD, among miners, denotes a train of metallic stones, serving to direct them in the discovery of mines.</p><p><hi rend="italic">SHOAD-Stones,</hi> a term used by the miners of Cornwall and other parts of this kingdom, to express such loose masses of stone as are usually found about the entrances into mines, sometimes running in a straight course from the load or vein of ore to the surface of the earth.</p><p>SHOAL, in the sea-language, denotes a place where the water is shallow ; and likewise a great quantity of fishes, such as a <hi rend="italic">shoal of herrings.</hi></p><p>SHOAL-WATER BAY, on the east coast of New Hoi- land, visited by Captain Flinders in 1802. Long. of Aken’s island at its entrance, 150. 15. E. Lat. 22. 21. S.</p><p>SHOE, a small island in the Pacific Ocean, near the coast of Waygoo. Long. 130. 53. E. Lat. 0. 1. S.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Shoe,</hi> a covering for the foot, usually of leather. Shoes among the Jews were made of leather, linen, rush, or wood ;</p><p>those of soldiers were sometimes of brass or iron. They were tied with thongs, which passed under the soles of the feet. To put off their shoes was an act of veneration ; it was also a sign of mourning and humiliation. To bear one’s shoes, or to untie the latchets of them, was considered as the meanest kind of service.</p><p>Among the Greeks, shoes of various kinds were used. Sandals were worn by women of distinction. The Lacedæmonians wore red shoes. The Grecian shoes generally reached to the middle of the leg. The Romans used two kinds of shoes ; the <hi rend="italic">calceus,</hi> which covered the whole foot, somewhat like our shoes, and was tied above with latchets or strings; and the <hi rend="italic">solea</hi> or slipper, which covered only the sole of the foot, and was fastened with leathern thongs. The calceus was always worn along with the toga when a person went abroad; slippers were put on during a journey and at feasts, but it was reckoned effeminate to appear in public with them. Black shoes were worn by the citizens of ordinary rank, and white ones by the women. Red shoes were sometimes worn by the ladies, and purple ones by the coxcombs of the other sex. Red shoes were put on by the chief magistrates of Rome on days of ceremony and tri- umphs. The shoes of senators, patricians, and their chil- dren, had a crescent upon them, which served for a buckle ; and these were called <hi rend="italic">caleei lunati.</hi> Slaves wore no shoes; and hence they were called <hi rend="italic">cretati,</hi> from their dusty feet. Phocion also and Cato of Utica went without shoes. The toes of the Roman shoes were turned up in the point; and hence they were called <hi rend="italic">calcei rostroti.</hi></p><p>In the ninth and tenth centuries the greatest princes of Europe wore wooden shoes, or the upper part of leather and the sole of wood. In the reign of William Rufus, a great beau, Robert, surnamed the horned, used shoes with long sharp points, stuffed with tow, and twisted like a rain’s horn. It is said that the clergy, being highly offended, declaimed with great vehemence against the long-pointed shoes. The points, however, continued to increase till, in the reign of Richard IL, they were of so enormous a length that they were tied to the knees with chains, sometimes of gold, sometimes of silver. The upper parts of these shoes were in Chaucer’s time cut in imitation of a church window. The long-pointed shoes were called crackowes, and con- tinued in fashion for three centuries, in spite of the bulls of popes, the decrees of councils, and the declamations of the clergy. At length the parliament of England interposed by an act passed in the year 1463, prohibited the use of shoes or boots with pikes exceeding two inches in length, and forbade all shoemakers from making shoes or boots with longer pikes, under severe penalties. But even this was not sufficient. It was necessary to denounce the dreadful sentence of excommunication against all who wore shoes or boots with points longer than two inches. The present fashion of shoes was introduced in 1633, but the buckle was not used till 1670.</p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Shoe </hi><hi rend="italic">of an Anchor,</hi> a small block of wood, convex on the back, and having a small hole, sufficient to contain the point of the anchor-fluke, on the fore-side. It is used to prevent the anchor from tearing or wounding the planks on the ship’s bow, when ascending or descending; and for this purpose the shoe slides up and down along the bow, between the fluke of the anchor and the planks, as being pressed close to the latter by the weight of the former.</p><p>SHOKET, a village of Syria, in the pachalic of Damascus, on the Orontes, 140 miles north of Damascus.</p><p>SHOLAPOOR, a town and district of Hindustan, province of Bejapoor, situated in about the l8th degree of latitude. The town is 125 miles south-east from Poorat. Long. 75. 40. E. Lat. 17. 43. N.</p><p>SHOLAVANDEN, a town of Southern India, district of Madura, ten miles north-west from the town of Madura. Long. 78. 10. E. Lat. 9. 50. N.</p></body></text></TEI>