<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-25T20:16:15Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>widgeon, by night, if not fired at, will, in cold weather, pro- 'bably settle again at no great distance.</p><p>“ In following wild-fowl, it is easier to get within twenty yards of them by going to leeward, than a hundred and fifty if directly to windward, so very acute is their sense of smelling.</p><p>“ The best time, therefore, to have sport with a canoe and a shoulder-gun, (provided it be low water, or half ebb, while you are hid in the creeks), is in clear, frosty, moonlight nights, when the wind happens to blow towards you as you face the moon. It is' then impossible for the wildfowl to smell you; and you may, by getting them directly under the light, have tne most accurate outline of every bird, and even distinctly see them walking about, at a much greater distance than a gun would do execution. From thus being on the shining mud-banks, they appear quite black, except some of the old cock widgeons, on the wings of which the white is often plainly to be seen.</p><p>“ It does not follow, however, that nothing can be done without a bright moon. So far from it, that some of the best shoulder-gunners in the kingdom prefer but very little moon even for the mud. Here, by constant habit, they can easily distinguish the black phalanxes of widgeons from the shades on the places they frequent, and particularly if they are feeding among the puddles which have been left by the tide. In this pursuit, and when not favoured by the best of light, there are a few cautions to be given to an inexperienced shooter. First, to ascertain that the black patch to be seen <hi rend="italic">is a</hi> flock of birds, which he will do, by observing the occasional change of feature in the outside of it. Secondly, on approaching them, to be careful that their enormous masses and tremendous noise do not deceive him in the distance, and tempt him to fire out of shot. And, thirdly, not to be too eager in getting his dead birds, as it sometimes happens, in hard weather, that the remainder of the flock will again pitch down among them, particularly if he has winged some of the younger birds, which have not the cunning to make off for a creek, like the old ones. In this case, a reserved gun would, probably, more than double the produce of his first shot. It should be understood, that this night shooting is chiefly at the widgeon, as the geese, of late years, (since there have been so many shooters), have seldom ventured much in harbour by night, except sometimes at high spring tides, with a full moon ; and the greater part of the ducks, teal, dunbirds, and such like, repair inland to the ponds and fresh springs, unless driven to the salt feeding ground by severe frost.</p><p>“ A company of widgeons, when first collecting, may be heard at an immense distance, by the whistling of the cocks and purring noise of the hens ; but when they are quietly settled, and busy at feed, you sometimes can only hear the motion of their bills, which is similar to that of tame ducks.”,</p><p>Geese, ducks, widgeons, hoopers, curlews, and other wildfowl, are killed in this manner ; but the most destructive method of killing them is with the heavy stanchion or swivel punt-gun, used by the persons on the coast who make a trade of wild-fowl shooting. When a fair shot can be obtained by this method, from twenty to fifty birds may be killed at one discharge ; but it is laborious, wearisome work, and, except for a single occasion, can scarcely be called sport. This kind of shooting is carried on in the night, usually in frosty weather, at which time sailing about on water, or working the canoe through mud, cannot be accompanied with very agreeable sensations.</p><p>The size of shot for punt-shooting should, in some measure, be regulated by the size of the birds expected to be met with, and their degree of tameness; yet it is well to be prepared With shot of sufficient size, as hoopers, geese, and other large birds, are sometimes found when least expected</p><p><hi rend="italic">The Water-hen,. &amp;c.—</hi>There are various kinds of wildfowl, which will dive rather than fly away when disturbed. They are, for the most part, clumsy birds on the wing, and are killed without difficulty when they can be made to rise. When shot at swimming, the shooter takes aim, and fires instantaneously, or they will be under water whilst he is drawing the trigger.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sporting Dogs.</hi> Before noticing the different kinds of game which, are the object pf the shooter’s pursuit, a few observations on sporting dogs may not be irrelevant. The shooter’s dogs are pf four kinds ; the pointer, setter, spaniel, and. retriever.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Pointers and Setters.</hi> If flogs were, unknown in Europe, and some traveller from a distant part of the southern hemisphere were to. relate that he had seen a new species of quadruped with wonderfully fine olfactory nerves, by the aid of which it was enabled to hunt to death the bare, stag, fox, or jackal, the tale would readily be credited ; for the instinct of the hound, as compared with that of other animals, is. not such as to excite surprise. But were the traveller to relate that he had seen a quadruped which, untaught, would stand motionless, as if converted into a statue, on coming in contact with the slightest scent of game, he would not be believed ; it would appear incredible, such is the extraordinary instinct of the pointer and setter. We use the term <hi rend="italic">extraordinary</hi> advisedly. There are other animals, and indeed other dogs, which possess a degree of instinct more nearly approaching to reason, but none possessing so extraordinary an instinct, an instinct not analogous to that of any other living creature that we are aware of. The pointer seems to be endued with it for the exclusive service of man ; whereas the instincts of all other animals are conducive to the supply of their individual wants, and their usefulness to man is secondary thereto. It would be difficult to controvert the argument that this instinct was given to the pointer for the purpose of aiding men to capture or kill game, by means of such engines as nets or guns.. This, we are aware, may be a doubtful position to maintain ; but who can say for what other apparent purpose this peculiar faculty was given ? It may, indeed, be urged, that the propensity to point, in the pointer, is a means ordained by providence for his subsistence in a wild state, by enabling him to approach within reach of. his prey, and thus to accomplish, by another species of stealth, what the tiger and other animals of the cat tribe effect by ambuscade. Such, an argument, however, is presumptively rebutted by the fact, that all existing races of wild dogs are gregarious, and resort to the chase for food ; nor is there any record of the existence of dogs in a state of nature, except those calculated for the chase. It is therefore gratuitous to assert, that the instinct or faculty of pointing was bestowed upon the pointer as a means of subsistence, since he has ever been dependant on man for food.</p><p>It is strongly argued, that all dogs have descended from one common stock, and that by difference in food, climate, and training,, they have become what they are at present; nor is. it more improbable that such is the fact, than that the human race are descended from one common parent ; for dogs are not more dissimilar than the various tribes of men. who differ not only ip outward form, but morally and intellectually, as much as dogs vary in size, shape, temper, and sagacity. Those animals which can be domesitcated improve by acquaintance with man, as the wild fruits by cultivation. All wild dogs have some qualities in common ; but their instincts are somewhat limited, or not called forth. It is only in its domesticated state that we find the various qualities which render the dog so useful a servant to man. Wild dogs are, in comparison with domesticated dogs, w hat savages (for wherever they have been found, savages bear some resemblance to each other, and are engaged in similar pursuits) are to civilized society. It</p></body></text></TEI>