<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-25T20:16:20Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>have been running about. A good retriever will follow the ’bird on whose track he is first put, as a blood-hound will that of a human being or deer. They should be taught to bring their game, or in many instances their finding a wounded bird would be of no advantage to the shooter.</p><p>We proceed next to give some description of the art of shooting game, in the course of which we shall endeavour to confine our obseravtions to such of the habits and peculiarities of the birds and quadrupeds under notice, as it is essential the shooter should be made acquainted with, and at the same time to detail the means of proceeding most likely to ensure success in the pursuit of them.</p><p><hi rend="italic">The Partridge.</hi> We commence with the partridge, as shooting that bird is generally the young shooter's first lesson at game, although in the order of the season grouse shooting takes precedence. Partridge shooting commences on the first of September, and ends on the first of February.</p><p>The habits of the partridge at different seasons should be closely understood and studied by the shooter, that he may be able, with a tolerable degree of certainty, to find them at any given time. In the early part of the season, they will be found, just before sunrise, running to a brook, a spring, or marsh, to drink ; from which place they almost immediately fly to some field where they can find abund- ance of insects, or else to the nearest corn-field or stubble- field, where they w ill remain, according to the state of the weather, or other circumstances, until nine or ten o’clock, when they go to bask. The basking place is commonly on a sandy bank-side facing the sun, where the whole covey sits huddled together for several hours. About four or five o’clock, they return to the stubbles to feed, and about six or seven they go to their jucking-place, a place of rest for the night, which is mostly in aftermath, or in a rough pas- ture field, where they remain huddled together until morn- ing. Such are their habits during the early part of the season ; but their times of feeding and basking varies much with the length of the days. While the corn is standing, unless the weather be very fine or very wet, partridges will often remain in it all day ; when fine, they bask on the outskirts ; when wet, they run to some bare place in a sheltered situation, where they will be found crowded together as if basking, for they seldom remain long in com or grass when It is wet. Birds lie best on a hot day. They are wildest on a damp or boisterous day.</p><p>The usual way of proceeding in search of partridges in September is, to try the stubbles first, and next the potato and turnip field. Birds frequently bask amongst potatoes or turnips, especially when those fields are contiguous to a stubble-field. The best partridge shooting is obtained in potato and turnip fields. It not unfrequently happens that' potatoes or turnips are grown on a headland in a corn field; in that case the headland will be a favourite resort of birds.</p><p>After the middle of October it is ever uncertain where birds will be found; the stubbles having been pretty well gleaned, birds do not remain in them so long as in the early part of the season. When disturbed at this time they will sometimes take shelter in woods, when they are flushed one by one. The best shots that can be obtained at partridges in winter, are when the birds are driven into woods.</p><p>When a covey separates, the shooter will generally be able to kill many bfrds, but late in the season it is seldom that the covey can be broken. In November and December the shooter must not expect to hate his birds pointed, but must remain content with firing at long distances. We transcribe the following observations on dispersing coveys : “ In the early part of the season, when the shooter <hi rend="italic">breaks </hi>a covey, he should proceed without loss of time in search of the dispersed birds, for the parent birds begin to call ' almost immediately on their alighting, the young ones answer, and in less than half an hour, if not prevented by the presence of the shooter and his dogs, the whole covey will be re-assembled, probably in security in some snug corner, where the shooter least thinks of looking for them. As the season advances birds are longer in re-assembling after being dispersed. It is necessary to beat very closely for dispersed birds, as they do not stir for some time after alighting, on which account dogs cannot wind them until nearly upon them, especially as they resort to the roughest places when dispersed. Birds dispersed afford the primest sport. The pointing is often beautiful, the bird being generally in a patch of rushes, or tuft of grass or fern, and close to the dog. When a bird has been running about some time, dogs easily come upon the scent of it; but when it has not stirred since alighting, and has perhaps crept into a drain, or run into a hedge-bottom, or the sedgy side of a ditch, no dog can wind it until close upon it, and the very best dogs will sometimes flush a single bird. In the month of October, and afterwords, the shooter will find it difficult to approach within gun-shot of a covey, nor can he disperse them, except by firing at them when he chances to come close upon them. Should he then be so fortunate as to disperse a covey, he may follow them leisurly, for they will then lie several hours in their lurking place, which is chosen with much tact, as a patch of rushes, a gorse bush, a holly bush, the bottom of a double bank fence, or a coppice or wood. The length of time that will transpire before a dispersed covey will re-assemble, depends, too, on the time of the day, and state of the weather. In hot weather, they will lie still for several hours. A covey dis- persed early in the morning, or late at night, will soon re- assemble. A covey dispersed between the hours of ten and two, will be some time in re-assembling. A covey found in the morning in a stubble field, and dispersed, will next assemble near the basking place. A covey dispersed after two o’clock, will next assemble in the stubble field at feeding time. A covey disturbed and dispersed late in the afternoon, or evening, will next re-assemble near the jucking- place. A covey being disturbed on or near to their jucking- place, will seek a fresh one, perhaps about two fields dis- tant; and if often disturbed at night on their jucking-place, they will seek another stubble field to feed in, and change their quarters altogether. The most certain method of driving partridges from a farm, is to disturb them night after night at their jucking-place, which is usually in a mea- dow, adjoining to a corn field, where the aftermath is suffered to grow, or in a field rough with rushes, fern, thistles, or heather. When a covey is dispersed on a dry hot day, it is necessary to search much longer, and beat closer, for the dispersed birds, than when the day is cool, and the ground moist. A dog should be only slightly rated for flushing a bird on a hot day.”@@<hi rend="superscript">1</hi></p><p>The number of birds in a covey varies much, perhaps the average may be from ten to fifteen. In some years, when the coveys are large after a fine hatching season, it is not uncommon to see upwards of twenty birds in a co- vey ; and sometimes after a wet season, ten birds may be deemed a fair covey. Birds are always most numerous after a dry summer. When there are thunder-storms about midsummer, great numbers of young birds are drowned. The young birds have many enemies besides the elements, such as cats, young dogs, hawks, foxes, and vermin of different descriptions. When the eggs are taken, or the young birds destroyed soon after leaving the shell, there will be a second hatch. Sportsmen often meet with second hatches in September, when the old birds rise screaming, and generally alight within fifty yards, as if to induce the young birds to follow. In that case the fair sportsman will not fire at the old birds, but will coll in his dogs and leave</p><p>@@@‘ The Oakleigh Shooting Code.</p></body></text></TEI>