<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-25T20:18:50Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p><hi rend="italic">Republica,</hi> in Greek. At first he dropped a word or two at intervals in the new pronunciation, and sometimes he would stop as if he had committed a mistake, and correct himself. No notice was taken of this for two or three days ; but as he repeated it more frequently, his audience began to wonder at the unusual sounds, and at last some of his friends mentioned to him what they had remarked. He owned that something was in agitation, but that it was not yet sufficiently digested to be made public. They entreated him earnestly to discover his project, He did so, and in a short time great numbers resorted to him for information. The new pronunciation was adopted with enthusiasm, and soon became universal at Cambridge. It was afterwards opposed by Bishop Gardiner the chancellor ; but its superiority to the old mode was so visible, that in a few years it spread over all England.</p><p>In 1539 he travelled into foreign countries, and studied for some time in the universities of France and Italy. At Padua he took the degree of LL.D. On his return, he was admitted <hi rend="italic">ad eundem</hi> at Cambridge, and was appointed regius professor of the civil law. He was useful in promoting the reformation of religion as well as of learning. Having gone into the family of the duke of Somerset the protector, during the minority of Edward the Sixth, he was employed by that nobleman in public affairs ; and in 1548 he was made secretary of state, and received the honour of knighthood. While Somerset continued in office, he was sent as ambassador, first to Brussels, and afterwards to France. Upon the accession of Mary, he lost all his places, but was fortunate enough to preserve the friendship of Gardiner and Bonner. He was exempted from persecution, and was allowed, probably by their influence, a pension of L. 100. During Elizabeth’s reign he was employed in public affairs, and was thrice sent to France in the capacity of an ambassador. He died in the year 1577.</p><p>Sir Thomas Smith was a man of excellent talents, united with solid and variegated learning. He obtained a respectable place among the scholars of the age, by the publication of his epistle to the bishop of Winchester, “De recta et emendata Linguae Graecae Pronuntiatione.” Lutetiae, 1568, 4to. The same volume includes his dialogue, “ De recta et emendata Linguae Anglicanae Scriptione.” But the work by which he is best known in modern times, is entitled <hi rend="italic">“De Republica Anglorum:</hi> the Maner of Gouern- ment or Policie of the Realme of England.” Lond. 1583, 4to. Of this treatise, which was translated into Latin, there are many editions.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Smith, Edmund</hi>, an English poet, the only son of Mr. Neale, an eminent merchant, by a daughter of Baron Lechmere, was born in 1668. By his father’s death, he was left young to the care of Mr. Smith, who had married his father’s sister, and who treated him with so much tenderness, that at the death of his generous guardian, he assumed his name. His writings are not many, and these are scattered in miscellanies and collections. His celebrated tragedy of Phædra and Hippolytus was acted in 1707; and being introduced at a time when the Italian opera so much engrossed the attention of the polite world, gave Mr. Addison, who wrote the prologue, an opportunity to rally the vitiated taste of the public. Notwithstanding the esteem in which it has always been held, it is perhaps rather to be considered as a fine poem than as a good play. This tragedy, with a poem to the memory of Mr. John Philips, three or four odes, with a Latin oration spoken at Oxford, <hi rend="italic">In lαudem Thomæ Bodleii,</hi> were published as his works by his friend Mr. Oldisworth. Mr. Smith died in 1710.</p><p>SMITH, <hi rend="smallcaps">Adam</hi> was bom at Kirkcaldy, on the 5th of June 1723. His father, who held the situation of comptroller of customs in that town, died a few months before his birth ; so that the charge of his early education devolved wholly on his mother, the daughter of Mr. Douglas of Strathenry, in the county of Fife. His constitution during infancy is said to have been extremely infirm and delicate, and required all the anxious attention of his mother, who treated him with the greatest indulgence. This did not, however, produce any unfavourable effect on his temper or dispositions; and he repaid the fond solicitude of his parent by every attention that filial gratitude and affection could dictate, during the long period of sixty years. When only three years of age, he was stolen from Strathenry, to which place he had been carried by his mother, by a party of gipsys. Fortunately, however, for the best interests of mankind, he was speedily recovered by the exertions of his uncle.</p><p>He received the first rudiments of his education in the grammar school of Kirkcaldy. The weakness of his constitution prevented him from indulging in the amusements common to boys of his age. But Mr. Stewart states, that he was even then distinguished by his passion for books, and by the extraordinary powers of his memory ; that he was much beloved by his school-fellows, many of whom subsequently attained to great eminence, for his friendly and generous disposition ; and that even then he was remarkable for those habits which remained with him through life, of speaking to himself when alone, and of mental absence in company. He continued at Kirkcaldy until 1737, when he was sent to the University of Glasgow, where he remained for three years. He then entered Balliol College, Oxford, as an exhibitor on Snell’s foundation ; and he continued for seven years to prosecute his studies at that celebrated seminary.</p><p>Mr. Stewart mentions, on the authority of Dr. Maclaine of the Hague, that mathematics and natural philosophy formed young Smith’s favourite pursuits while at Glasgow. But subsequently to his removal to Oxford he seems to have entirely abandoned them, and to have principally devoted the time not consumed in the routine duty of the University to the study of polite literature, and of those moral and political sciences of which he was destined afterwards to become so great a master. Smith does not seem to have felt any very peculiar respect for his English <hi rend="italic">alma mater. </hi>The severe remarks in the <hi rend="italic">Wealth of Nations</hi> on the system of education followed in Oxford and Cambridge, had evidently been suggested by his own observation.</p><p>While he resided at Oxford, something had occurred to excite the suspicions of his superiors with respect to the nature of his private pursuits ; and the heads of his college, having entered his apartment without his being aware, unluckily found him engaged reading Hume’s <hi rend="italic">Treatise of Human Nature.</hi> The objectionable work was, of course, seized ; the young philosopher being at the same time severely reprimanded.</p><p>Subsequently to his return from Oxford in 1747, he continued to reside for nearly two years at Kirkcaldy with his mother. He had been sent to Oxford that he might be qualified for entering the church of England. The ecclesiastical profession was not, however, agreeable to his taste; and in opposition to the advice of his friends, he returned to Scotland, resolved to devote himself exclusively to literary pursuits. In the latter part of the year 1748, he fixed his residence in Edinburgh, where, in consequence of the encouragement and persuasion of Lord Kames, and some of his other friends, he was prevailed upon to deliver, during that and the two following years, a course of lectures on rhetoric and polite literature. The lectures were attended by a respectable auditory, composed chiefly of students of law and theology ; and he had the honour to reckon among his pupils Mr. Wedderburne, afterwards Lord Loughborough, Mr. William Johnstone, afterwards Sir William Pulteney, and Dr. Blair ; with all of whom he subsequently continued on the most intimate terms. It was also at this period that he laid the foundation of that friendship with David Hume, which</p></body></text></TEI>