<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-25T20:16:24Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>his own distance, a snipe would have the least chance for its life at twenty yards. But there are two points to be attended to in determining the proper distance—the flight of the bird, and the manner in which the shot is thrown. In snipe-shooting the latter is subservient to the former. The few full snipes occasionally found on heathery and rush-clad hills, as well as in the enclosed grounds, he much more dispersed than the gregarious birds of the marsh. Hence those found on the uplands are easy, and those on the fens difficult of approach. It is, however, the same description of bird that is found in both situations.” When the shooter uses wire cartridges, which, by the bye, are not precisely calculated for snipe-shooting, it would be prudent to allow the bird to move to a considerable distance before firing. It is scarcely necessary to add, that the shot used for snipeshooting should be very small. When several snipes rise together, they are styled a wisp.</p><p><hi rend="italic">The Woodcock.</hi> There is a proverb current among sports- ■ men, that to kill a woodcock is to perform a day’s work, which doubtlessly originated in the circumstance of a woodcock being seldom found until a very large extent of wood has been closely beaten by both men and dogs. In the month of November, however, when woodcocks are most abundant, it would not be a difficult task, according to that standard of labour, to do the work of a week in a day, in any noted cover, for every cover frequented by woodcocks, (or cocks as they are called in the sportsman’s nomenclature), acquires a notoriety which it seldom loses, since any wood well frequented with cocks one year, has generally a fair supply the next. But whether the same cocks that frequent a wood this year, return the next, with their offspring, or whether an entirely new set of occupants take possession, we leave the ornithologist to decide. A certain description of woods are seldom known to fail of woodcocks during the winter months ; these woods or plantations are such as are swampy, or have a stream of water running through them, or woods abounding in springs, or where, from the nature of the ground, or want of draining, the top water encourages the growth of moss. The woodcock is rarely found where moss is not abundant. During a frost, cocks are found near fresh water springs ; at other times, they are most commonly flushed in the open glades of the densest woods, or rather in those parts of the woods not choked up at the bottom with fern, rushes, or brambles, but where they can freely run about, and in those parts where willows, osiers, hazel-trees, or crate-wood is plentiful. In such places it will readily be ascertained whether there are cocks or not, by the borings in the moss or dead leaves, and by the droppings. Should the cock not be brought down, it will not fly far after being fired at; it should, when practicable, be marked down, as by this means several successive shots may be obtained at it when the gun is unsuccessful. It is seldom that the skilful shooter springs a cock which he does not eventually kill. The difficulty of woodcock shooting arises, for the most part, from the birds springing in the thickest part of woods, and contriving to wing their flight through the trees, in such a manner as to baffle the sportsman’s aim. After being fired at in a wood, cocks will frequently alight amongst hedge-rows on the outskirts, especially under a hedge running close to and parallel with a water-course, when they are easily killed, as they will not rise until the shooter is close upon them ; and their flight is not difficult to master when there are no trees to obstruct the aim. Woodcocks are found in October on moors, and in covers near the sea. About the last week in October they find their way to the inland covers, where they remain during the early part of the winter, and they are sometimes found there again in March. A sharp frost, or a dense fog, at the end of October or beginning of November, is usually the shooter’s first intimation of the arrival of cocks ; and if he is ambitious of the fame of killing them, he must fag hard during the month of November, or it is probable that his return for the season of the numbers bagged will not be satisfactory. November is unquestionably the best month for cock shooting.</p><p><hi rend="italic">The Red Grouse.</hi> Grouse shooting commences on the l2th of August. We have already alluded to the vast extent of the northern moors. The number of birds killed on the opening day, on some parts, is very great. It is not uncommon for an experienced and skilful shooter, on the best moors, to bag fifty brace on the 12th of August. What may be termed a good day's sport, differs much on different moors. On well-preserved moors, the average may be from ten to twenty brace. On subscription moors, the shooter should not be dissatisfied if he has the opportunity of killing from three to five brace per day, during the first week of the season, though this would be deemed a low average for the Scottish moors. After the first week, few sportsmen, except those residing in the immediate neighbourhood of the hills, ever trouble the moor game.</p><p>Many causes contribute to the popularity of grouse shooting, amongst which may be enumerated the following. It oommences during the parliamentary recess, and long vacation—the legislator’s, lawyer’s, and collegian’s holiday ; and it is no wonder that after being cooped up all summer, these, or any other classes of society, should seek relaxation in the sports of the field. August is the season when every one, from the peer to the shopkeeper, who can afford the indulgence, either rusticates or travels. In that month the casual tourist, the laker, and the angler, are often in the North, when the temptation to draw a trigger is irresistible. Grouse shooting fascinates the young shooter more than any other kind of sport, inasmuch as the season commences with it. The opening day is looked forward to with pleasing anticipation all summer. To the more practised sportsman, grouse shooting recommends itself by reason of the superiority of the sport over every other kind of shooting. Partridge shooting is a comparatively tame and uninteresting amusement. Partridge sh∞ting, as compared with grouse shooting, may be termed domestic sporting. To the majority of sportsmen, a grouse shooting excursion only occurs once a year, and then lasts only a few days. The sport therefore seldom palls ; but during the long interval of time that elapses between each, the coming season is ever looked forward to with additional interest.<hi rend="superscript">1 </hi>Grouse shooting is, in many respects, a source of greater expenditure to the sportsman : it requires more preparation, and is attended with more difficulties than any other kind of shooting ; but these circumstances, whatever some people may imagine to the contrary, so far from detracting from, serve to enhance the enjoyment of the sport ; for we are apt to estimate whatever is obtained with difficulty and expense at a higher rate than what is gratuitously afforded us. To the lover of the romantic and the picturesque, grouse shooting has attractions of the highest order. It is the sport of all others peculiarly British : the partridge, the pheasant, the black-cock, are widely dispersed over other countries ; but the red grouse is only found in the British Islands.</p></body></text></TEI>