<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-25T20:16:28Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>SHORE, a place which is washed by the sea, or by some large river.</p><p>Count Marsigli divides the sea-shore into three portions ; the first of which is that tract of land which the sea just reaches in storms and high tides, but which it never covers ; the second part of the shore is that which is covered in high tides and storms, but is dry at other times ; and the third is the descent from this, which is always covered with water.</p><p>The first part is only a continuation of the continent, and suffers no alteration from the neighbourhood of the sea, except that it is rendered fit for the growth of some plants, and wholly unfit for that of others, by the saline steams and impregnations ; and it is scarcely to be conceived by any but those who have observed it, how far on land the effects of the sea can reach, so as to make the earth proper for plants which will not grow without this influence ; there being several plants frequently found upon high hills and dry places, at three, four, and more miles from the sea, which yet would not grow unless in the neighbourhood of it, nor will they ever be found elsewhere.</p><p>The second part or portion of the shore is much more affected by the sea than the former, being frequently washed and beaten by it. Its productions are rendered salt by the water, and it is covered with sand, or with the fragments of shells in the form of sand, and in some places with a tar- tarous matter deposited from the water. The colour of this whole extent of ground is usually dusky and dull, especially where there are rocks and stones covered with a slimy matter.</p><p>The third part of the shore is more affected by the sea than either of the others ; and it is covered with an uniform crust of the true nature of the bottom of the sea, except that plants and animals have their residence in it, and the decayed parts of these alter it a little.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Shore, </hi><hi rend="italic">Jane,</hi> the celebrated mistress of Edward IV., was the wife of Matthew Shore, a goldsmith in Lombard-street, London. Historians represent her as extremely beautiful, remarkably cheerful, and of most uncommon generosity. The king, it is said, was no less captivated with her temper than with her person. She never made use of her influence to prejudice any person ; and if ever she importuned him, it was in favour of the unfortunate. After the death of Edward, she attached herself to Lord Hastings; and when Richard III. cut off that nobleman as an obstacle to his ambitious schemes, Jane Shore was arrested as an accomplice, on the ridiculous accusation of witchcraft. This, however, terminated only in a public penance, excepting that Richard rifled her of all her little property ; but whatever severity might have been exercised towards her, it appears that she was alive, though sufficiently wretched, under the reign of Henry VIII., when Sir Thomas More saw her, poor, old, and shrivelled, without the least trace of her former beauty. Mr. Rowe, in his tragedy of Jane Shore, has adopted the popular story related in the old historical ballad, of her perishing by hunger in a place where Shoreditch now stands. But Stow assures us, that that street was so named before her time.</p><p>SHOREHAM, a town of the county of Sussex, in the rape of Brember and hundred of Fishergate, fifty-six miles from London. It stands on the river Adar, about a mile from the sea, and has a bridge over that river, It has a custom-house, which presides over that at Brighton. The harbour is not deep, but useful as shelter, when the wind is high, for vessels unloading on the beach at Brighton, although there is scarcely any water when the tide is out. It is an ancient place, ill built, with few good houses. The church is old, and was originally monastic. It is a borough, which, on account of bribery in 1771, was extended, to comprehend all the forty shilling freeholders of the rape on which it stands, and still continues to elect two members to the House of Commons. There is some trade in building ships, and a considerable oyster fishery. A market, well supplied, is also held on Saturday. The population was, in 1801, 987 ; in 1811, 980; in 1821, 1282; and in 1831, 1734.</p><p>SHORT, <hi rend="smallcaps">James,</hi> an eminent optician, was born in Edinburgh, on the 22d of June in the year 1710. At ten years of age, having lost his father and mother, and being left in a state of indigence, he was received into Heriot’s Hospital, where he soon displayed his mechanical genius, in constructing for himself little chests, book-cases, and other conveniences, with such tools as fell in his way. At the age of twelve he was removed from the Hospital to the High School, where he shewed a considerable taste for classical literature, and generally kept at the head of his forms. In the year 1726 he entered the university, where he passed through the usual course of education, and took his master’s degree with great applause.</p><p>By his friends he was intended for the church ; but after attending a course of theological lectures, his mind revolted from a profession which be thought little suited to his talents, and he devoted his whole time to mathematical and mechanical pursuits. He had been fortunate enough to have the celebrated Maclaurin for his preceptor, who having soon discovered the bent of his genius, and made a proper estimate of the extent of his capacity, encouraged him to prosecute those studies in which nature had qualified him to make the greatest figure. Under the eye of that eminent master, he began in 1732 to construct Gregorian telescopes ; and, as the professor observed in a letter to Dr. Jurin, “ by taking care of the figure of his specula, he was enabled to give them larger apertures, and to carry them to greater perfection than had ever been done before him.”</p><p>In the year 1736 Mr. Short was called to London, at the desire of Queen Caroline, to give instructions in mathematics to the Duke of Cumberland ; and immediately on his appointment to that honourable office, he was elected a fellow of the Royal Society, and patronized by the Earls of Morton and Macclesfield. In the year 1739 he accompanied the former of these noblemen to the Orkney Isles, where he was employed in adjusting the geography of that part of Scotland ; and happy it was for him that he was so employed, as he might otherwise have been involved in a scuffle which took place between the retainers of Sir James Stewart of Barra and the attendants of the earl, in which some of the latter were dangerously wounded.</p><p>Mr. Short having returned to London, and finally established himself there in the line of his profession, was, in 1742, employed by Lord Thomas Spencer to make for him a reflector of twelve feet focus, for which he received six hundred guineas. He made several other telescopes of the same focal distance with greater improvements and higher magnifiers ; and in 1752 finished one for the king of Spain, for which, with its whole apparatus, he received twelve hundred pounds. This was the noblest instrument of the kind that had then been constructed, and perhaps it has never yet been surpassed, except by the astonishing reflectors of Herschel.</p><p>Mr. Short used to visit the place of his nativity once every two or three years during his residence in London, and in 1766 he visited it for the last time. On the 15th of June 1768 he died, after a very short illness, at Newington Butts, near London, of a mortification in his bowels, and was buried on the 22d of the same month, having completed his fifty- eighth year.</p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Short</hi><hi rend="italic">-Hand Writing.</hi> (See STENOGRAPHY.)</p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Short</hi><hi rend="italic">-Sightedness,</hi> a certain defect in vision, by which objects cannot be distinctly seen unless they are very near to the eye. (See <hi rend="smallcaps">Optics).</hi></p><p>SHOT, a denomination given to all sorts of balls for firearms; those for cannon being of iron, and those for guns and pistols of lead.</p></body></text></TEI>