<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-25T20:18:16Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>1525 entered into the service of the cardinal and archbishop John du Bellay. He retired to Strasburg in 1542, where he acquired the esteem and friendship of the most considerable persons, particularly of James Sturmius, by whose advice and assistance he was enabled to write the history of his own time. He was employed in some public negociations; but the death of his wife, in 1555, plunged him into so deep a melancholy, that he entirely lost his memory, and died the year following. In 1555 came out, in folio, <hi rend="italic">De Statu Religionis et Reipublicæ sub Carolo Quinto,</hi> in fifteen books, from the year 1517, when Luther began to preach, to the year of its publication, and this history was ]&gt;resently translated into most of the languages of Europe. Besides this great work, he wrote, <hi rend="italic">De quatuor summis Imperiis, libri tres ;</hi> with some other historical and political pieces.</p><p>SLESWICK, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Schleswig,</hi> a province in the kingdom of Denmark, in that division usually denominated the Duchies, including, with this province, Holstein and Lauenberg, all of which are inhabited by people of German origin, who speak that language, and are regulated by different laws from the rest of Denmark. This province is bounded on the north by Jutland; on the north-east by the Little Belt, wherein the Island of Aroe, which is a part of it, lies ; on the east by the Baltic sea, wherein are the Islands Alsen and Fernem ; on the south by Holstein, from which it is divided by the river Eyder and the Sleswick canal ; and on the west by the German Ocean, in which are the islands of Nordstrand, Pellworm, and some other smaller ones. The whole extent is 3515 square miles. It comprehends thirteen cities, fourteen market-towns, and 1500 hamlets or villages, divided into 257 parishes, which contained 36,000 inhabitants in 1832. it is in general a level district, having on the western side many tracts of rich meadow land; while, on the eastern side, its agricultural produce are corn, butter, cheese, and meal; but through the middle of the province runs a ridge of sandy hills, which scarcely repay the cost of cultivation. There are many lakes and marshes, and on the eastern side, fiorden or bays, formed by projecting woody headlands, which have a picturesque appearance. The climate is cold in winter, but remarkably variable. There are few manufactures, and the trade chiefly consists of the export of the products of the soil, or of the fisheries; which last forms an important part of the occupation of a great number of the inhabitants. The principal towns, besides the capital, are Hadersleben, Apenrade, Tondern, Bredsted, Husum, Nordstrand, Toning, Fred- richstadt, Flensburg, and Eckenfiorde.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sleswick,</hi> a city, the capital of the province of that name in the continental dominions of Denmark. It stands on an arm of the sea on the German Ocean, and the buildings are erected in the form of a crescent. It is an open town, most irregularly built, and is divided into four distinct parts. It is the seat of a Lutheran bishop, has a domkirche or cathedral, and four other churches, and several collegiate institutions for education. The harbour has only nine feet water, and is of small extent. The trade is inconsiderable. There are sugar refineries, tanneries, distilleries, and breweries, all for the home consumption. It contains 1320 houses, with 10,640 inhabitants. Lat. 54. 31. 15. Long. 9. 29. 25. E.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">SLEUT-Hound,</hi> the ancient Scots name of the bloodhound. The word is derived from the Saxon <hi rend="italic">slot,</hi> the impression that a deer leaves of its foot in the mire, and <hi rend="italic">hound, </hi>a dog ; so they derive their name from following the track.</p><p>SUCH, in <hi rend="italic">Metallurgy,</hi> the ore of any metal, particularly of gold, when it has been pounded and prepared for further working.</p><p>The manner of preparing the slich at Chremnitz in Hungary, is this. They lay a foundation of wood three yards deep; upon this they place the ore, and over this there are</p><p>twenty-four beams, armed at their bottoms with iron ; these, by a continual motion, beat and grind the ore, till it is reduced to powder. During this operation, the ore is covered with water. There are four wheels used to move these beams, each wheel moving six ; and the water, as it runs off, carrying some of the metalline particles with it, is received into several basons, one placed behind another; and finally, after having passed through them all, and deposited some sediment in each, it is let off into a very large pit, almost half an acre in extent ; in which it is suffered to stand as long as to deposit all its sediment, of whatever kind, and after this is let out. This work is carried on day and night, and the ore is taken away and replaced by more as often as occasion requires. That ore which lies next the beams, by which it was pounded, is always the cleanest or richest.</p><p>When the slich is washed as much as they can, a hundred weight of it usually contains about an ounce, or perhaps but half an ounce of metal, which is not all gold ; for there is always a mixture of gold and silver, but the gold is in a larger quantity, and is usually two-thirds of the mixture. They then put the slich into a furnace with some limestone, and slacken, or the scoria of former meltings, and run them together. The first melting produces a substance called <hi rend="italic">lech,</hi> which they bum with charcoal, to make it lighter, to open its body, and render it porous, after which it is called <hi rend="italic">rost ;</hi> to this they add sand in such quantity as they find necessary, and then melt it over again.</p><p>At Chremnitz many other methodsare practised of reducing gold from its ore, but particularly one, in which they employ no lead during the whole operation : whereas, in general, lead is always necessary, after the before-mentioned processes.</p><p>SLICKENBURG, a small island near the north-west coast of Borneo. Long. 112. 31. E. Lat. 3. 59. N.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">SLIDING-rule,</hi> a mathematical instrument, serving to work questions in gauging, measuring, and the like, without the use of compasses ; merely by the sliding of the parts of the instrument one by another, the lines and divisions of which give the answer by inspection. This instrument is variously contrived and applied by various authors, particularly Everard, Coggeshall, Gunter, Hunt, and Partridge ; but the most common and useful are those of Everard and Coggeshall.</p><p>SLIGO, a maritime county in the province of Connaught in Ireland, is bounded on the north by the Atlantic Ocean, on the east by Leitrim, on the south-east by Roscommon, and on the south and west by Mayo. It extends from 53º 54' to 54º 28' north latitude, and from 8° 10' to 9° 10' west longitude ; being thirty-eight miles in its greatest length from north to south, between Mullaghmore Head and Lough Gara, and forty-one in breadth from west to east, between Ardmaree and the junction of the three counties of Sligo, Roscommon, and Leitrim, and comprehending an area of 461,753 acres, or 721 square miles.</p><p>According to Ptolemy the geographer, this district was inhabited by the tribe of the Nagnatae, whose chief city, Nagnata, is supposcd to have been situated somewhere in the vicinity of the town of Sligo. It afterwards formed part of the kingdom of Connaught, one of the five into which the island was divided previously to the arrival of the English, in the reign of Henry II. It was afterwards possessed by one of the family of the O’Conors, kings of Connaught, who was called O’Conor Sligo, to distinguish him from the other chieftains of the same family ; and under him the heads of the septs of O’Bean, O’Doud, O’Gara, O’Hara, M'Donogh, and M’Firbis, were subordinate chieftains in their respective districts. After a protracted struggle between the natives and the English, it fell into the hands of the De Burgos, who, either by force or treaties, had made themselves masters of the greater</p></body></text></TEI>