<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-25T20:16:40Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>found the rare and precious yellow, and still more rarely, the white sable. In Kamtschatka, these precious furs are to be found in the greatest abundance, but not of so fine a quality; the skin being thick, and the hair long, but not very black. When this country was first invaded by Europeans, these animals were in such abundance, that for iron wire to the amount of ten rubles, sables might have been obtained to the amount of five or six hundred. But the animal has been so diligently hunted, that it has become scarce, so that one skin may be exchanged on the spot for ten pounds. The great art is, to catch the animal without injuring the skin, for which purpose various contrivances are resorted to. The hunter, following the track of the animal, discovers his covert, which is usually a burrow in the earth ; the animal, to escape him, ascends a hollow tree, which the hunter immediately surrounds with a net; and kindling a fire under it, forces the little creature to descend, when it falls into the net and is caught. Various other animals are hunted for their skins, which form a considerable article of commerce. Wild-fowl abound every where in siberia, namely, wild ducks and geese, swans, woodcocks, snipes, bustards, snow-birds, pheasants, partridges. &amp;c. ; these are so plentiful, that even in the governments which are the poorest in wild animals, they form an ordinary and not very costly dish. The eider fowl, which supplies the fine and soft down that is so much esteemed in all countries, harbours about the coasts of the White Sea and the Northern Ocean. In siberia are found the prodigious remains of animals, none of which are now found to exist ; the bones and entire carcase of the mammoth, that extraordinary animal, which surpasses in bulk every known species, is found preserved in the ice on the shores of rivers in the north, and on the coasts of the Frozen Ocean. The bones of the elephant and rhinoceros occur also in vast quantities. The seas that wash the coasts of Siberia, and the rivers, teem with a great variety of marine animals and with fish. The Frozen Ocean and the Eastern Seas abound in whales, seals, otters, also the narhwal, the pott-fish, from whose brain spermaceti is prepared, the sea dog, the dolphin, the sea lion, the sea cow, the sea bear, and various other species, which are sought after for their skin or their blubber. The Obi abounds beyond all the others in vast quantities of migrating fish which pass from the sea ; not only those which are found in other rivers, but a variety of fish which are caught no where else, namely, sturgeons, starlet, white salmon, pikes, muroena, or white salmon of Pallas, quobbe, and a multitude of other fish, of which the Russian names would convey no information to the reader. The migrating fish proceed up the rivers in June, and the fishing in the Obi is carried on by the Ostiacks and Samoiedes. The Irtysch, the Jenisei, and the Lena, as well as their numerous tributaries, contain abundance of excellent fish, mostly resembling those already named. The fishing on the coasts and islands of the Eastern ocean is remarkable for the variety and quality of its objects ; and as agriculture is here impracticable from the soil and the climate, the inhabitants depend for their subsistence on the fishing, and the chase. All the large cetacea of the Arctic seas are here pursued with avidity, and the oil which they afford forms an article of commerce. Of all the lesser animals which are objects of the chase on the Eastern ocean, the sea otter is the most important. Its beautiful fur is everywhere highly esteemed, and sells in China for a very high price. The rivers in Kamtschatka abound more especially with fish, which supply the inhabitants with subsistence, which no labour could extract from the barren soil. These fish, which are mostly of the salmon kind, proceed up the rivers in such vast multitudes, that the shores are often found covered with the dead.</p><p>The surface of siberia is diversified by alternate ranges of mountains and by widely extended plains. The Ural mountains, so called from the Tartar word signifying a belt or girdle, which form the natural boundary between Asia and Europe, extend almost in a direct line above 1500 English miles. The mountains between the Caspian and the Aral may be considered as the commencement of the Ural mountains ; which, after being divided by the straits of Weygat, terminate in the mountain chain of Nova Zembla, several subordinate ridges branching off in a western, as well as in an eastern direction, from the same chain. These mountains are rich in minerals, and they are in many parts also clothed with tall firs, larches, birch, and other woods. They are well watered by rivers, and at different degrees of elevation are found beautiful pellucid lakes, ponds, and numerous streams, all teeming with fish. The breadth of the Ural mountains at Sollkamskoi and Verchoturia, the high road out of European Russia, is about forty miles, and their height from four to five thousand feet. At their northern extremity, along the lower Obi, their elevation is not so great. The Ural mountains, at their northern extremity, lock in by several ridges with the great Altaic chain, which traverses northern Asia from west to east through its whole extent, and fix the respective limits of the Chinese empire from the Irtysch to the Amour. The great Altai stretches northward beyond Siberia, into the regions of Tartary ; and proceeding with various windings toward the N.N.E., throws out considerable masses, between which the head waters of the Jenesei, the Obi, and the Irtysch, take their rise ; and the lesser Altai separates the Chinese territories from the Russian government of Kolivane, through which the streams mentioned above pursue their course. Near its summit a Chinese patrol was found guarding the limits of the empire by the traveller Shcangin. The highest mountains consist of granite, and are covered with perpetual snow. The lower mountains consist of porphyry, jasper, and serpentine, and exhibit many beautiful varieties of these rocks. The highest summit of these mountains, in the government of Kolivane, does not rise more than 3000 feet above the level of thesea. One summit, however, to the north of the river Ouba, has an elevation of 5691 feet. Although the Altai mountains bear different names, they range eastward as far as the ocean. The higher parts are generally bare, and the shores of the rivers which run through them are generally clothed with forests. As they extend east from the Jenesei to the Baikal sea, they assume a grander character, and are called the Sayanskoi mountains. They are chiefly naked granite rocks, sharp and abrupt, and frequented chiefly by hunters; and they determine the boundaries between siberia and Mongolia. The mountains of Baikal have nearly the same direction as that sea, and run down to the west on the right of the Angora, where it flattens in a morasse steppe of prodigious extent. To the east, it advances from the origin of the Lena on both sides of that river, and here it is lost in a wide extended floetz ridge. In the inferior regions of the Angora and the Lena, coal is frequently produced. Several of these mountain ranges in the neighbourhood of the Baikal are so high, that they are covered with perpetual snow. The Nertsh- inskoi mountains, otherwise called the mountains of Daouria, extend from the lake Baikal and the sources of the Selenga and the Amour, down the two sides of these rivers; on the one side, as far as where the Argoon falls into the Amour; and on the other, or northern side, up to the sources of the Niusa and the Oldekon, where it joins the spacious range of Okhotsk. The portion of this range enclosed by the Amoor and Argoon, which is properly called the Nertshinskoi chain of mountains, is found to be the richest in minerals of any of the mountains hitherto explored in these regions ; producing, amongst other sorts, zinc, iron, copper, and lead ores containing silver and gold. These mountains present, according to the descriptions of a traveller who visited them in search of the rhubarb plant, a wild scene of desolation ;</p></body></text></TEI>