<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-25T20:16:18Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Courage@@<hi rend="superscript">1</hi> is another attribute of the pointer ; a high-couraged pointer will continue ranging till he has not, as the saying is, a leg to stand upon, even though he should not meet with game.</p><p>The usual price paid for breaking a dog is from two to five guineas. The breaker runs the dogs in spring, and again in August, but without the gun ; this, followed by a week’s shooting in September, renders their education complete, but unless they have sufficient practice afterwards, the initiatory lessons will soon be forgotten. Young dogs will learn more in six successive days, than in six weeks, if taken out only at the rate of one day per week. The dog-breaker should be a person of discriminating judgment, and possessed of a good temper ; and the art of winning, not by brute force, but by judicious management, an ascendancy over the dogs entrusted to his care. Breaking dogs, when many young ones are taken out together, is a very difficult and tiresome task. One or more old staunch dogs are usually allowed to accompany the young ones, to induce them to back. A dog pointing is conscious of the presence of game. A dog which backs another is not aware of the proximity of game at the time, otherwise than by inference. Whenever the dog in advance points, it is the breaker’s duty to make all the rest that acknowledge the scent to point, and all that do not acknowledge the scent should be shewn the dog pointing, and be made to back, which is done by the breaker holding up his hand, and crying, in an un- der tone, “ to-ho.” The dogs are taught to fall the moment the game rises, or on the report of a gun. They should come in on hearing their names or the whistle, and should never be allowed to pass a fence before their master. The efficiency of the training which a dog has received may be conjectured from his manner of quartering his ground. He should range at a short distance in advance of the shooter, alternately to the right and left ; and this should be taught rather by the motion of the hand than by the voice. An offence should never be overlooked if the dog seems conscious of it ; but the breaker’s knowledge of the disposition of the dog should be his guide in regulating the punishment. Some dogs will not bear the whip, or even rating, but require encouragment and good words on all occasions. When it is necessary to flog a headstrong dog, it should be done severely, the blows falling on the side, from the shoulder to the flank. The lash or switch with which the dog is punished, should not be made to lap round the body, nor should the dog be kicked. When the dog is in fault, and is very eager in pursuing the sport, no punish- ment that will be longer remembered, can he administered, than making him crouch five or ten minutes. In common with other sports, shooting has a vocabulary of its own. We have elsewhere given a list of some of the words made use of by the breakers and sportsmen to the dogs, which we transcribe, many of them being anything but euphonious to the unaccustomed ear. <hi rend="italic">“ To-ho</hi> spoken in an under tone, when the dog is ranging, is a warning to him that he is close upon game, and is a direction to him to stand. There is no necessity for using it to a dog that knows his business. Spoken in a peremptory manner, it is used to make the dog crouch when he has flushed game, or been otherwise in fault. <hi rend="italic">Down-charge,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">down-to-charge,</hi> is used to make the dog, whether it be near or at a distance, to crouch when the shooter charges, that the dog may not flush game when the shooter is unprepared. When the dog will not crouch, but continues beating, the leg-strap may be put on. <hi rend="italic">Take-heed,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">be-careful,</hi> are used when the dog ranges over ground where it is customary to find birds. <hi rend="italic">Take-heed,</hi> is a word of correction ; <hi rend="italic">be-careful,</hi> of encouragement. The former is used by way of cau- tion or notice to prevent the dog flushing birds by running over the ground too fast ; the latter is likewise a caution, but used when the dog beats slowly or carelessly. <hi rend="italic">’ Ware fence</hi> is used to prevent dogs passing a fence before the gun. The dog should never, on any account, leave an enclosure until its master has left it. <hi rend="italic">’Ware,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">beware, </hi>is used to rate a dog for giving chase to a hare, birds, or cat- tle, pointing larks, or approaching too near the heels of a horse. <hi rend="italic">Seek,</hi> is a direction to the dog to look for a dead or wounded bird, hare, or rabbit. <hi rend="italic">Dead</hi> is used to make a dog relinquish his hold of dead or wounded game. The dog should retain possession of wounded game until it is taken from him ; for should he suffer a bird that is only slightly wounded to disengage itself from his grasp, another <hi rend="italic">seek </hi>becomes necessary, and the bird is either lost, or despoiled of its plumage by the catching and re-catching. Some dogs are taught to bring the game to their master. The breaker should teach the dog, in all cases, to retain game until it is taken from him, or until he hear the word <hi rend="italic">dead,</hi> when he should instantly drop it. The dog should be punished if he break the skin with his teeth.”@@<hi rend="superscript">3</hi></p><p>The most useful dogs are those which are best broken. As much depends on the breaking as the breed of a dog. Dogs should be constantly shot over during the season by a successful shot, and exercised during the shooting recess, by some person who understands well the management of them, otherwise they will fall off in value. The half-bred ones will become unmanageable, and even the thorough- bred ones will acquire disorderly habits.</p><p>We look upon the setter to be an inferior kind of point- er, perhaps originally a cross between the pointer and the spaniel, or some such dog as the Newfoundland, for it has some qualities in common with each. The pointer has the finer nose, and is more staunch than the setter. Pointers are averse to water ; setters delight in it ; hence the advantage of the latter on marshes to the snipe shooter. The setter will face briars and gorse bushes better than the pointer, which is in this respect a tender dog ; and for this reason the setter is preferred to the pointer for cover shoot- ing. Besides, his being not so staunch as the pointer is an additional advantage in heavy covers. The sportsman who shoots over well-broken pointers, frequently passes game in the woods, while the pointers, which are not seen by him, are at their point ; the setter, being more impatient to run in, affords the shooter many shots in cover, which the overstaunch pointer would not. The pointer is always to be preferred on open grounds. In hot weather the pointer will endure more fatigue than the setter.</p><p><hi rend="italic">The Spaniel or Cock Dog.</hi> The spaniel is the best dog for beating covers, provided he can be kept near the gun. He is generally expected to give tongue when game is flushed ; some spaniels will give notice of game before it springs, which may be very well where wood-cocks only are expected to be found. Wood-cock and pheasant sh∞ting are usually combined ; where covers are limited, pheasant shooting cannot be conducted too quietly. Wherever the underwood is so thick that the shooter cannot keep his eye on the dogs, spaniels are to be preferred to pointers or set- ters, whatever species of game the shooter may be in pursuit of. If spaniels cannot be kept near the shooter, they are the worst dogs he can employ.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Retrievers.</hi> The business of the retriever is to find lost birds. Newfoundland dogs are the best for the purpose. They should have a remarkably fine sense of smelling, or they will be of little use in tracing a wounded pheasant, or other game, through a thick cover, where many birds</p><p><hi rend="superscript">@@@1</hi> Courage, as applied to the pointer, signifies a willingness and determination to range ; it is an union of the qualities known by the terms mettle and bottom, as applied to horses.</p><p><hi rend="superscript">@@@,</hi> The Oakleigh Shooting Code. London, Ridgways. Third Edition.</p></body></text></TEI>