<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-25T20:18:29Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>joint efforts the public is chiefly indebted for the improvements which have been made there, as fully appears in a report that Mr. Smeaton presented to the board of trustees in 1791, which they immediately published.</p><p>Mr. Smeaton being at Austhorpe, walking in bis garden on the 16th of September 1792, was struck with palsy, and died the 28th of October.</p><p>SMELL, a word which in most languages has two meanings, signifying cither that sensation of mind of which we are conscious, in consequence of certain impressions made on the nostrils, and conveyed to the brain by the olfactory nerves; or that unknown virtue, or quality in bodies, which is the cause of our sensations of smell.</p><p>SMELLIE, <hi rend="smallcaps">William,</hi> a learned and ingenious printer, was born at Edinburgh in the year 1740. His father, Alexander Smellie, who followed the occupation of a master- builder, is said to have been a classical scholar, and a writer of Latin verses. He belonged to the sect of reformed Presbyterians, more commonly described as Cameronians. He left two sons and three daughters. John, the elder son, followed his father’s employment, and married a sister of the late James Ferrier, Esq. clerk of session. Two of his daughters were likewise married. Residing in the suburban street called the Pleasance, he sent his younger son to Duddingstone school, which is scarcely a mile distant. William Smellie was there initiated in the ordinary branches of education, including the Latin language ; but he left school at the early age of twelve, and was destined to follow some mechanical employment. It was his father’s original intention to bind him an apprentice to a staymaker, but some difference occurred as to the terms of the indenture ; “ and the young scholar was preserved from the mortifying drudgery of scraping whalebone, and stitching coats of armour to force the female form into every shape save that of natural elegance.” On the first of October 1752, he was bound an apprentice, for six years and a half, to Hamilton, Balfour, and Neill, printers to the university.</p><p>To this occupation he applied himself with great assiduity, and he soon became conspicuous for the rapidity, as well as the correctness, with which he dispatched his work. With equal assiduity he devoted his evenings to the acquisition of knowledge. Two years before the expiration of his apprenticeship, his masters appointed him a corrector of the press, with a weekly allowance of ten shillings, which at that period was no despicable remuneration. His father was now dead, and two of his sisters were materially indebted to him for their support. During his apprenticeship, he was permitted to attend some of the academical lectures. The printing-office was within the precincts of the university buildings; “and he generally continued at work till he heard the bell ring for lecture, when he immediately laid down his composing-stick, shifted his coat, ran off with his note-book under his arm, and returned to his work immediately after lecture.” The Edinburgh Philosophical Society having offered a silver medal for the most accurate edition of a Latin classic, Smellie set and corrected an edition of Terence, which obtained this prize for his employers. His edition, which bears the date of 1758, but was actually printed during the preceding year, has been described as immaculate ; but of the literal accuracy of this description, we entertain some doubt. It is very elegantly printed, and is in all respects creditable to the Edinburgh press of that period. His apprenticeship was completed on the first of April 1759; and in the ensuing month of September, he agreed to transfer his services to the office of Murray and Cochrane. Here he was not only to perform the ordinary work of a corrector, but was likewise to collect articles for the Scots Magazine, and to make abstracts, extracts, or transcripts of such pieces as his employers should direct. He was moreover to lend his aid “ in writing accounts, and, in cases of hurry in printing, in composing or case-work</p><p>and in return for these various services, he was to receive a weekly salary of sixteen shillings.</p><p>It was one advantage of his new situation, that his employers allowed him three hours a-day for the prosecution of his academical studies ; and thus, under peculiar circumstances, he was enabled to obtain a regular education. He not only studied the Latin, Greek, and Hebrew languages, but likewise mathematics, logic, rhetoric, moral, and natural philosophy. He besides attended all the medical courses, including the lectures on chemistry and botany. The Hebrew class he attended in the year 1758, with the immediate view of preparing himself to superintend the printing of Dr. Robertson’s Hebrew Grammar. His course of study had thus been so regular and complete, that he was in a state of mature preparation for more than one of the learned professions. Some of his friends recommended the study of divinity ; Dr. Buchan urged him to betake himself to the practice of physic ; but the hazard of relinquishing a certain though small income for a very uncertain experiment, must have served to mancipate him to his original avocation. An early marriage fixed him more completely in the printing-office. His wife, Jane Robertson, was the daughter of an army-agent in London, who had once been opulent, but who finally left his family in indigent circumstances. Her mother was the cousin of Mrs. Oswald of Dunikier, and there were other family connexions described as genteel, but they do not appear to have rendered any service to Smellie or his children. The marriage took place in 1763, when he had only attained the twenty-third year of his age.</p><p>In the mean time, his love of learning suffered no abatement. In the year 1760 he had become a member of the Newtonian Society, a literary association chiefly composed of young men educated in the university. They held their weekly meetings in one of the class-rooms. At each meeting an essay was read by one of the members ; and a subject, previously assigned, was discussed in due form. The essays were restricted to subjects of natural science, but the debates extended to a wider range. The list of members included various names which were afterwards conspicuously known ; and among others, we find that of Robert Blair, the late president of the court of session. To this association likewise belonged Thomas Blacklock, Robert Hamilton, Alexander Adam, Henry Hunter, Samuel Charters, and William Buchan. After the interruption of their regular meetings as a society, some of the members continued for several years to hold a weekly meeting in a tavern, where they partook of a sober repast, and spent their evenings in literary and social conversation. With two very estimable members of this club, Dr. Hamilton of Aberdeen, and Dr. Charters of Wilton, Smellie always retained a friendly connexion. A new association, of which he acted as secretary, was formed in the year 1778, under the denomination of the Newtonian Club. Most of the other members were connected with the medical profession, and five of them either then were or afterwards became medical professors in the university. In the list of these associates we find the names of Dugald Stewart and James Gregory. No person was eligible unless he was a member of the Philosophical Society ; and the meetings of the club were appointed to take place immediately after the close of each meeting of the society. The number of members was not to exceed twenty ; and a single black ball was to exclude any candidate. The last of their regulations stands thus : “ As this club consists entirely of philosophers, it would therefore be ridiculous to make any laws for its internal police.”</p><p>For the different branches of natural history Smellie had evinced an early predilection. To the study of botany he devoted so much attention, that in 1765 his Dissertation on the Sexes of Plants gained the gold medal given by Dr. Hope. In this dissertation, which was inserted in the first edition of the Encyclopædia, he strenuously opposed the</p></body></text></TEI>