<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-25T20:17:42Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>350 to 400 tons burdens; they carry from eighty to a hundred seamen ; and such is their ignorance of navigation, that great numbers, notwithstanding their being so fully manned, perish in the stormy seas that wash the Chinese shores. They bring annually about 2000 Chinese ; and for several days after their arrival, the Sampan proas which trade to Rhio, Malacca, Penang, &amp;c., are literally crowded with emigrants proceeding to the various neighbouring ports, with a view of getting employment in the pepper, coffee, and gambier plantations, and in the tin mines. Great numbers go to Java to the sugar and coffee plantations, and many to Borneo to collect gold dust. Those various imports, however, are not consumed in Singapore, which is rather a mercantile depot of goods, from which they are dispersed all over the Eastern seas. The goods which are adapted for a European remittance, such as raw silk, nan- kccns, and camphor, are chiefly purchased by the Europeans from the Chinese merchants, through whose hands the trade chiefly passes. The other articles are taken by the proas which frequent the harbour, and are by these spread over the whole Archipelago. The exports of the Chinese from Singapore, are birds’ nests, camphor, beche de mer, sandal wood, ebony, tortoise shell, rattans, flint stones, buffaloes’ hides, sharks’ fins, tripang, European camlets, woollens, and long ells, and a few pieces of chintzes, long cloths, Bengal piece goods, tin, pepper, gambier, and from eight to ten chests of opium, a contraband article, the importation of which into Canton is now effectually proscribed. The exports of Singapore to Calcutta, Madras, and Bombay, amount in value to about 2,600,000, and the imports to 2,748,026 sicca rupees.</p><p>Exports.	Imports.</p><p>1831-2.. 7,825,786 dollars. 8,904,774 dollars.</p><list type="ordered"><item>7... 7,806,965	„	8,243,629	„</item><item>8...8.024,123	„	8,881,195	„</item></list><p>No export or import duties are levied at this port, nor any anchorage, harbour, or lighthouse dues, or any fees ; but a register is kept of all exports and imports. A newspaper is published once a-week, the <hi rend="italic">Singapore chronicle. </hi>The population of Singapore, as already stated, rapidly increased after the settlement was established. Population in 1823, 10,683. In 1828, the inhabitants, consisting of Europeans, Malays, Chinese, natives of Bengal, of Coromandel, Arabs, Buggis, and others, amounted to 17,664 ; in 1833, to 20,978. In 1838 a handsome new church was opened for worship. <hi rend="italic">(Asiatic Journal,</hi> new series ; <hi rend="italic">Singapore chronicle;</hi> Macculloch’s <hi rend="italic">commercial Dictionary.)</hi></p><p>SINGBOOM, a district and town in the province of Orissa. The province is situated between the 22d and 23d degrees of north latitude, and bounded on three sidesby the districts of Chuta, Nagpoor, Michnapoor, and Mohurbunge ; and on the south by that of Kunjeur. The town is possessed by Zemindars. Long. 85. 55. E. Lat. 22. 37. N.</p><p>SINGHEA, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Singee,</hi> a town of Hindustan, province of Bahar, situated on the river Gunduck. Long. 85. 15. E. Lat. 25. 52. N.</p><p>SINGHERICONDA, a town of the Northern Carnatic, twenty miles south from Ongole. Lat. 80. 2. E. Lat. 15. 14. N.</p><p>SINGING, in a general sense, means the production of appreciable and varied sounds by the voice. In a more limited sense, it means different inflexions of the voice through intervals admittcd in music, and consistent with the rules of melodic modulation. It is well known that these inflexions differ from those of the voice in speaking. In singing, harshness of vocal <hi rend="italic">timbre</hi>, (see Music,) and falseness of intonation are much more frequently met with than the opposite qualitics, especially among persons not trained to sing. Musical training, when applied to a person possessed of a naturally good quality of voice, and a good ear, produces effects that can hardly be imagined by those who have not watched them attentively. Upon the subject of vocal-training, the reader may consult any of the best treatises on singing. For some remarks on the mechanism of the human voice in singing, and the compasses of voices, see Music.</p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Singing</hi><hi rend="italic"> of Birds.</hi> Birds may more correctly be said to <hi rend="italic">whistle</hi> than to <hi rend="italic">sing.</hi> This is shown by the structure of their vocal organs, as well as by the mechanism of the automaton singing-bird of Maillardet. The power of <hi rend="italic">singing</hi> is confined to the human race. In the notes of but few birds can distinct melodic intervals be perceived. The notes of the quail, the cuckoo, &amp;c. as well as many of the notes of the blackbird, &amp;c. constitute distinct melodic intervals, and are therefore susceptible of musical notation. Captive singing-birds may be taught tunes, as in the case of piping-bullfinches, &amp;c. These last have even been taught to perform in concert. We have observed, among a number of piping-bullfinches, marked differences of musical ear. Some piped well in tune ; others more or less out of tune.</p><p>SINGROWLA, a district of Hindustan, in the province of Gundwana, situated about the 24th degree of north latitude, and bounded on the east by the district of Palamow in Bahar. The country is in general very desolate.</p><p>SINGUMNERE, a district of Hindustan, belonging to the Mahratta Peshwa, in the province of Aurungabad, situated about the 20th degree of north latitude. It is a hilly, but a fertile district. The chief towns are Singumnere, Bat- towal, and Bejapoor. The capital is of the same name. Long. 74. 40. E. Lat. 19. 46. N.</p><p>SINKEL, a town situated near the mouth of the Sinkel river, on the west coast of Sumatra. Long. 98.26. E. Lat. 2. 15. N. Camphor, benzoin, wax, and gold, are exported from this place. Vessels that frequent this port are exposed to great danger from piratical attacks. The river Sinkel is the longest on the western coast, which rises in the mountains of Dalholi, and after a long course, empties itself into the sea by a mouth three quarters of a mile wide.</p><p>SINISTER, something on or towards the left hand. Hence some derive the word <hi rend="italic">sinister a sinendo,</hi> because the gods, by such auguries, permit us to proceed in our designs.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sinister,</hi> is ordinarily used amongst us for unlucky; though, in the sacred rights of divination, the Romans used it in an opposite sense. Thus <hi rend="italic">avis sinistra,</hi> or a bird on the left hand, was esteemed a happy omen ; and hence in the law of the twelve tables, <hi rend="italic">Aνa sinistra populi magister esta.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sinister</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Heraldry.</hi> The sinister side of an escutcheon is the left-hand side; the sinister chief, the left angle of the chief ; the sinister base, the left-hand part of the base.</p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Sinister</hi><hi rend="italic"> Aspect,</hi> amongst astrologers, is an appearance of two planets happening according to the succession of the signs, as Saturn in Aries, and Mars in the same degree of Gemini.</p><p>SINISTRI, a set of ancient heretics, so called because they held the left hand in abhorrence, and made it a point of religion not to receive any thing therewith.</p><p>SINKING <hi rend="smallcaps">Fund</hi>, a provision made by parliament, consisting of the surplusage of other funds, intended to be appropriated to the payment of the national debt ; on the credit of which very large sums have been borrowed for public uses. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Funding System.</hi></p><p>SINOPLE, in <hi rend="italic">Heraldry,</hi> denotes vert, or green colour in armories. Sinople is used to signify love, youth, beauty, rejoicing, and liberty ; and hence it is that letters of grace, ambition, and legitimation, are always sealed with green wax.</p><p>SINTCHEI, one of the remote Kurile islands in the Eastern ocean. Long. 155. 14. E. Lat. 50. 15. N.</p><p>SINUOSITY, a series of bends and turns in arches or other irregular figures, sometimes jutting out and sometimes falling in.</p><p>SINUS, in <hi rend="italic">Anatomy,</hi> denotes a cavity in certain bones and other parts, the entrance of which is very narrow, and the bottom wider and more spacious.</p></body></text></TEI>