<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-05-20T16:31:30Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>forms the Christian, ennobles man, and is the only source of that heart-felt serenity and sedate fortitude which support humanity, when every other object of confidence fails. He died at Berlin on the 27th of February 1779.</p><p>SUMATRA, a large island in the Eastern Seas, the most western of that great chain of islands which extends in the eastern ocean from the coasts of New Holland and New Guinea to the coast of China on the east, and westward to the Malayan peninsula. The equator divides it into two parts almost equal. It may be estimated at 1050 miles in ength by 165 miles in average breadth, and its general direction is north-west and south-east : the one extremity is in 5° 56' N. and the other in 5° 56' S. This island lies exposed on the south-west to the great Indian Ocean ; the north point stretches into the Bay of Bengal, to the north-east it is divided from the peninsula of Malaya by the Straits of Malacca, to the east by the Straits of Banca from the island of that name, to the south-east by the commencement of the Chinese Seas, and on the south it is separated from the island of Java by the Straits of Sunda. The origin of the name is unknown. In the east it is generally known by the name of Pulo Purichu and Indalas. It is one of the largest islands in the world, and is broadest at its southern extremity, narrowing gradually towards the north. It is of a very unequal surface. A chain of mountains runs through its whole extent : the ranges are from 3000 to 5000 feet high, and in some places much higher, being in many parts double and treble ; and they run nearer to the western than the eastern shore, being seldom more than twenty miles from the sea. These mountains, though high, do not rise above the level of perpetual snow. Mount Ophir, situated immediately under the equinoctial line, is 13,800 feet above the level of the sea. Between these ridges of mountains are extensive plains, considerably elevated above the surface of the maritime lands, where the air is cool, and they are esteemed in consequence the most eligible portion of the country ; and being cleared from woods, which in all other parts cover both the hills and valleys in Sumatra with an eternal shade, they are the best inhabited parts of the country. The most satisfactory account of the country is derived from the journeys into the interior by Sir Stamford Raffles, who was appointed governor of the British settlements at Sumatra, and arrived in Bencoolen in 1818; and who made excursions inland and along the coast, and also crossed the island from Bencoolen to Palembang. He afterwards proceeded from Padang, on the south coast, and, traversing the first range of mountains, penetrated to the ulterior plains; and he describes the country as populous, well cultivated, and fertile. The hills which he passed rose to the height of 5200 feet, as estimated by the barometer, and the slopes were covered with plantations of coffee, indigo, maize, sugar-cane, and all the oil-giving plants, and the lower plains were almost exclusively occupied with rice. The rice-fields are managed in the same manner as those of Java, and were equal in fertility. After arriving at the summit of the steep ascent, he observes, “ our view opened on one of the finest countries we ever beheld ;” “ as we descended,” be continues, “ the scene improved ; we found ourselves in an immense amphitheatre, surrounded by mountains 10,000 and 12,000 feet high ; the soil on which we stood rich beyond description, and vegetation luxuriant and brilliant in every direction ; the people superior to those on the coast, in general about six feet high, and proportionably stout, with clear and clean skins, and an open ingenuous countenance. They seemed to have abundance of every thing ; rice, the staple food of the country, being five times as cheap as at Bencoolen, and every other article of produce in proportion. The children were deco</p><p>rated with a profusion of silver ornaments, and particularly with strings of dollars and other coins hanging round their neck, to the value sometimes of 100 dollars. A fine breed of cattle,” he continues, “ which seems peculiar, abounds here, and throughout the Menangcabow country ; oxen seem to be used in agriculture in preference to buffaloes ; they are generally about three feet four inches high, beautifully made, and mostly of a light-brown colour, with black eyes and lashes, and are sold at from three to four dollars a head.”@@<hi rend="superscript">1</hi> Here are also found many large and beautiful lakes, which extend at intervals through the interior of the country, and tend to facilitate the intercourse between its different districts. But little is known respecting the interior of this large and fertile island, or the dimensions, direction, and situation of the lakes. The most remarkable is one of great extent in the Batta country. There is a second in the country of Menangcabow, which is used by the inhabitants for transporting goods to and from Palembang ; there is another in the Corinchia country ; one in the Lampoon country, extending to Passumah, which is very large, and in which there are boats of a large size, which carry sails, and require a day and a night to cross it. This lake is stated by Mr Anderson, who visited the east coast of Sumatra in 1822, under the orders of the East India Company, to be very large, the shore not being visible from the opposite side. The borders of the lake are reported to be in a high state of cultivation, containing numerous villages, and a dense population. The lake has an island in the centre, where edible bird-nests, so highly prized as a luxury in China, are procured. Those who navigate this lake are mostly pirates, who plunder each other, and carry off their children, selling them for slaves.@@* The lake of Sincara, in one of the interior valleys of the island, is described by Sir Stamford Raffles as a beautiful sheet of water, about fourteen miles long by seven broad, surrounded by mountains and hills, except on one side, where it is bounded by a plain of its own width. On the margin of this lake for two or three miles are rice-fields, plantations, and villages, rising successively above each other, and advancing up the hill nearly to the summit of the first ridge, where the forest has been cleared, and cultivation extended. On the banks of this lake are situated seven principal towns, with their numerous villages and hamlets ; which being shaded by trees, form so many groves, the dark foliage of which pleasingly contrasts with the bright tints of the rice-plantations in the middle of which they are placed. At each of these towns a weekly market is held, to which the traders from the other towns and adjacent countries repair by water. There are numerous canals, and each town has one or two large boats capable of carrying six tons with one hundred men. Sir Stamford sounded at a short distance from the shore, and found bottom at 68 fathoms ; but in the centre no bottom was found at 180 fathoms. The lake abounds in fish.</p><p>From the direction of the mountains, which, as has been mentioned, approach near to the western coast, being only twenty miles from the sea, while on the eastern side there is an intervening country not less than 150 miles in breadth, all the largest rivers are found on that coast. The rivers on the western coast are numerous, but they are in general too small and rapid for the purpose of navigation. And it is the vicinity of the mountains on this side that occasions the profusion of springs, as well as their rapidity and diminutive size. They have not space to accumulate in so limited a range ; while the extended declivity of the eastern coast not only presents a larger surface for the formation of rivers, by the reception of rain, and by the union of subsidiary</p><p><hi rend="superscript">@@@,</hi> Memoir of the Life and Public Services of Sir Thomas Stamford Rattles, p. 349.</p><p>@@@• Mission to the East Coast of Sumatra, by <hi rend="italic">J.</hi> Anderson, Esq., p. 252</p></body></text></TEI>