<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-05-20T16:29:41Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>for no one could take from him his learning and eloquence. So great was the fame of Stilpo, that the most eminent philosophers of Athens took pleasure in attending upon his discourses. His peculiar doctrines were, that species or universals have no real existence, and that one thing cannot be predicated of another. With respect to the former of these opinions, he seems to have taught the same doctrine with the sect afterwards known by the appellation of <hi rend="italic">Nominalists.</hi> To prove that one thing cannot be predicated of another, he said, that <hi rend="italic">goodness</hi> and <hi rend="italic">man,</hi> for instance, are different things, which cannot be confounded by asserting the one to be the other. He argued further, that goodness is a universal, and universals have no real existence; consequently, since nothing cannot be predicated of any thing, goodness cannot be predicated of man. Thus, while the subtile logician was, through his whole argument, predicating one thing of another, he denied that any one thing could be the accident or predicate of another. If Stilpo was serious in this reasoning, if he meant any thing more than to expose the sophistry of the schools, he must be confessed to have been an eminent master of the art of wrangling ; and it was not wholly without reason that Glycera, a celebrated courtezan, when she was reproved by him as a corrupter of youth, replied, that the charge might be justly retorted upon himself, who spent his time in filling their heads with sophistical quibbles and useless subtleties. In ethics he seems to have been a Stoic, and in religion he had a public and a private doctrine, the former for the multitude, and the latter for his friends. He admitted the existence of a Supreme Divinity, but had no reverence for the Grecian superstitions.</p><p>STILOBATUM, in <hi rend="italic">Architecture,</hi> denotes the body of the pedestal of any column.</p><p>STILTON, a town of the hundred of Normancross, in the county of Huntingdon, seventy-four miles from London. It stands on the great north road, and has many good inns, with post-horses. It has long been celebrated for the excellence of its cheese. The inhabitants amounted in 1801 to 509, in 1811 to 663, in 1821 to 710, and in 1831 to 793.</p><p>STIMULANTS, in <hi rend="italic">Medicine</hi>, substances which increase the action of certain parts of the body. In particular, they quicken the motion of the blood, increase the action of the muscular fibres, and affect the nervous system.</p><p>STING, an apparatus in the bodies of certain insects, in the form of a little spear, serving them as a weapon of offence.</p><p>STIPULATION, in the civil law, the act of stipulating, that is, of treating and concluding terms and conditions to be inserted in a contract. Stipulations were anciently performed at Rome, with abundance of ceremonies; the first of which was, that one party should interrogate, and the other answer, to give his consent, and oblige himself. By the ancient Roman law, nobody could stipulate but for himself; but as the tabelliones were public servants, they were allowed to stipulate for their masters ; and the notaries succeeding the tabelliones, have inherited the same privilege.</p><p>STIRLING, one of the most ancient towns in Scotland, and capital of the county of the same name, is situated in 5<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> 40' west longitude, and 56° 6' north latitude, in a plain called the Carse, watered by the river Forth, and on the sloping ridge of a rock, at the western and precipitous extremity of which the castle is built. The town is very irregular, the street upon the crest of the hill being broad and spacious, but the other streets narrow and inconvenient. Within the last few years great improvements have been undertaken. The pavement of the streets, which was of the worst description, has been rendered equal to that of almost any other place in the kingdom ; and the opening of the town at its lower extremity is affording scope for the most marked improvements. Many elegant houses and fine shops have been erected. In the suburbs there are many handsome villas; in Southfield, Melville Terrace, Allan Park, Wellington Place, and Dunbarton Road. Stirling is a most convenient place for the residence of people of small but easy fortune. House-rents are low; and ground for gardens may be procured upon easy terms. There arc no local public burdens of any kind ; the streets being lighted and cleaned, and water brought to the town, at the expense of the corporation. The situation of Stirling is very convenient in other respects. The steam-boats supply an easy and cheap conveyance to and from Edinburgh ; and many coaches pass through the town in different directions. “ In point of extent, variety, and magnificence, the view from Stirling Castle is perhaps unequalled by any other in Britain.”@@<hi rend="superscript">1</hi></p><p>The public buildings are the two parish churches, both in the Gothicstyle, with a modern erection between them, which adds nothing to their beauty : they are called the East and West Churches. The former is a fine building, erected in the year 1494. In the two churches there are three clergymen, and in one of the United Secession churches two. The town council has the patronage of the churches, and two of the ministers are entirely supported by the corporation. It also bears the whole expenses of the jail for the counties of Stirling, Clackmannan, and Kinross, except a part of the jailer’s salary, paid by the counties. Besides two chapels belonging to the United Associate Synod, there is an Old Light church, the minister of which, and a majority of the congregation, have within a few weeks joined the established church. There are likewise an Episcopal and a Roman Catholic chapel, the latter a neat building, erected within the last two years ; a Cameronian, a Congregational, and several Baptist places of worship. The townhouse, with a spire, in which there is a set of music-bells, which play a tune before the striking of each hour, and the jail behind, which is very insecure, form two sides of a quadrangle, the third side of which is finely fitted up as a courtroom, in which the circuit court sits twice a year, and also frequently the sheriff court. The fourth side of the quadrangle is private property, which is very inconvenient. In the town-house are still kept the pint jug, the ancient legal standard for liquid measure in Scotland, and two silver keys, representative of the keys of the two ancient gates of the town ; and in the circuit court-room about a dozen of the fine ancient carvings known by the name of the Stirling heads. In the narrow lane leading to the castle, there is a military hospital. The building was once the property of the Argyle family, and is still called Argyle House. Near it, and close beside the two churches, is situated a ruin, called Mar’s Work. It is an unfinished house, begun, but never completed, by the regent Mar. The Athenaeum is a handsome house in King Street, with a spire 120 feet high. In the ground-floor there are shops, but the two upper stories contain, the first a public reading-room, to which respectable strangers have access at all times, and the second a subscription library, containing about 5000 volumes. Close beside the Athenæum is the corn-market, for the accommodation of which a splendid hall has been erected within the last twelvemonths. There are three public school-houses in the town. The parish school has four departments, viz. a grammar-school, a mathematical, and two English schools. In addition to their fees, the teachers have each a salary of fifty pounds from the town council ; and the master of the grammar-school has twenty pounds more for an assistant. Education is cheap and good. In the town there are four charitable endowments, commonly called hospitals, in full</p><p>@@@* M‘Culloch's Statistical Account of the British Empire, vol. i. p. 299.</p></body></text></TEI>