<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T17:43:49Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>of his plans, both in Sumatra and in other places, attest the judgment with which they were formed. During his short administration the cultivation of rice was extended, the spice plantations were established, the population increased, and the people were conciliated ; so that this wise and beneficent ruler had good reason to boast that he was making a country and a garden out of a wilderness, and laying the foundation of the future civilization of Sumatra. We have no data for estimating the population of this island. Sir Stamford reckoned the inhabitants of the Batta country, the valley beyond the first range of mountains, to be between one and two millions. But this is merely a conjecture, and there are many districts still unexplored. The British establishment at Bencoolen was withdrawn in 1824, when Sumatra was relinquished to the Dutch.	<hi rend="smallcaps">(f.)</hi></p><p>SUMAUN, a town of Hindustan, province of Agra. It is twenty-eight miles north-north-east from the town of Etaweh. Long. 79. 5. E. Lat. 27. 6. N.</p><p>SUMBAWA, a large island in the Eastern Seas, about 180 miles in length by forty in average breadth. It is situated between the eighth and ninth degrees of south latitude, and is separated from Lombhook by the Straits of Allass. It is almost divided into two equal parts by a deep bay, which indents it in the middle. This island is divided into the different states of Beema, Dompoo, Tambora, San- gur, Pekat, and Sumbawa, all governed by their respective chiefs, who were formerly either allies or under the protection of the Dutch East India Company, and were all sufficiently obedient, with the exception of the chief of Sumbawa, who rebelled. Near the north-east end of the island, on a fine bay which stretches seven or eight leagues south, is situated the town of Beema, remarkable for its excellent harbour, the sides of which are bold and high, and the approach safe; but the passage through is sometimes dangerous, from the strong current which generally prevails, and the great depth of water, as 100 fathoms of line, though close in shore, will hardly reach the bottom. The channel in some places is only 150 or 200 yards across ; but the depth is so great that a ship of the line may sail on either side within thirty yards of the rocky mountains. These give a grand and picturesque appearance to the channel, which terminates in a safe and commodious basin, presenting one of the finest harbours in the world. On the east side of the bay stands the town of Beema, which comprehends under its jurisdiction the Straits of Sapy, the whole of Manzeray, and the island of Gonong Api. The island produces sappan wood, rice, horses, saltpetre, sulphur, wax, birds’ nests, tobacco, &amp;c., though there is but little trade carried on at this place. The number of horses exported under the appellation of Beema horses is very considerable. There are two volcanic mountains in the island, Gonong Api and another, which are looked upon with superstitious veneration by the inhabitants. Gold-dust is found in Sumbawa, particularly in the district of Dompoo, which also supplies teak-timber. Pearls are fished for in the large bay to the westward of Beema Bay, as also at Pekat.</p><p>SUMBHULPORE, a district of Hindustan, in the province of Gundwana, situated between the twenty-first and twenty-second degrees of north latitude. It is of an unwholesome atmosphere, especially to foreigners, owing to the mountainous and woody nature of the country, to the sudden vicissitudes of heat and cold, and to the quantity of jungle which it contains. The soil in the valleys is a rich loam, which produces sugar, cotton, and all kinds of grain ; and in the mountains gold and diamonds are found. This district constituted the ancient kingdom of Gurrah, and was overrun by the armies of Aurungzebe. On the decline of the Mogul empire it became independent ; and in the war between the British and the Mahrattas in 1803 several of the pergunnahs or parishes were taken possession of by the former. The capital, which is of the same name, is situated on the east side of the Mahanuddy river. Long. 83. 47. E. Lat. 21. 33. N.</p><p>SUMBOONHAUT, a town and temple in the Ghoorkha country, in Nepaul. It is celebrated for a temple containing. from time immemorial the sacred fire, and is annually resorted to by innumerable pilgrims from Bootan and Thibet, and is a source of considerable revenue to the Nepaul government. Long. 85. 38. E. Lat. 27. 33. N.</p><p>SUMBUL, a town of Hindustan, province of Delhi, and district of Bareilly, situated on the Yarvufadur river. It is fifty-two miles west-north-west from Bareilly.</p><p>SUMISHORE, a town of Hindustan, in the province of Bahar. It is forty-six miles west-north-west from Bettiah. Long. 84.15. E. Lat. 27. 15. N.</p><p>SUMMER, the name of one of the seasons of the year, being one of the quarters when the year is divided into four quarters, or one half when the year is divided only into two, summer and winter. In the former case, summer is the quarter during which, in northern climates, the sun is passing through the three signs Cancer, Leo, Virgo, or from the time of the greatest declination, till the sun again comes to the equinoctial, or has no declination ; which is from about the 21st of June till about the 22d of September. In the latter case, summer contains the six warmer months, while the sun is on one side of the equinoctial ; and winter the other six months, when the sun is on the other side.</p><p>SUMNUM, a small town of Persia, in the province of Khorassan. It is the capital of a rich district containing filly villages, and bounded on the north by Mount Elburz, and on the south by the Great Salt Desert.</p><p>SUMY, a city of Russia, the capital of a circle of the same name, in the province Slobod-Ukraine, 911 miles from St Petersburg. It stands on the river Psiol, where the Sumy falls into it. It is surrounded with walls and ditches, contains two stone and eight wooden churches, 1230 houses, with 13,600 inhabitants, who distil much brandy, and are celebrated for the horses which they breed. Long. 28.1. E. Lat. 50. 50. N.</p><p>SUMPTUARY <hi rend="smallcaps">Laws (</hi><hi rend="italic">Leges Sumptuaria),</hi> are laws made to restrain luxury. Most ages and nations have had some such laws. Political writers have been much divided in opinion with respect to their utility. Montesquieu observes that luxury is necessary in monarchies, as in France, but ruinous to democracies, as in Holland. With regard to England, whose government is compounded of both species, it may still be a dubious question, says Blackstone, how far private luxury is a public evil, and as such cognizable by public laws.</p><p>SUN, <hi rend="smallcaps">Sol,</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Astronomy,</hi> the great luminary which enlightens the world, and by its presence constitutes day.</p><p>SUNBURY, a town of the county of Middlesex, in the hundred of Spelthorne, eighteen miles from London. It is finely situated on the left bank of the Thames, between Hampton Court and Shepperton, and is much resorted to by the lovers of angling in the summer season. The population amounted in 1811 to 1655, in 1821 to 1777, and in 1831 to 1863.</p><p>SUNDA, <hi rend="smallcaps">Straits of.</hi> The arm of the sea which separates the large islands of Sumatra and Java is so called by the Europeans, and by the Malays Sunda Kalapa. The length of this channel, taken from the flat point to Varkens or Hog Point, is about seventy miles ; and on the opposite coast, from Java Head to Bantam Point, about ninety. The passage, though wide, is occasionally dangerous, from the currents. There are two passages formed by Prince’s Island, which lies in the mouth of the straits ; one between it and Java, which is generally made use of during the south-west monsoon, in order that they may approach as close as possible to the shore, so as to anchor to escape the danger of being driven to sea by the currents which set strongly out of the straits to the westward. The other pas</p></body></text></TEI>