<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T17:43:52Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>place of considerable antiquity. At the latter end of the twelfth century it received a charter from Bishop Pudsey, which gave it equal privileges with those enjoyed by Newcastle, and from that time it has risen into importance. The town consists of one long street, under the names of Sunderland High Street and Bishopwearmouth High Street, and the two together extend to nearly a mile in length. This continued street is broad, well built, having many respectable shops, and in it are the principal buildings. With this exception, Sunderland presents the appearance of one mass of small houses, of considerable age, crowded together, with interstices of narrow streets and lanes ; and here the population is extremely dense. To this crowded state of the population, together with the want of cleanliness, may be traced the fearfid ravages of the cholera in 1832, which first broke out in England at this port. On the outskirts of the town there are some good streets, which are rapidly extending, with excellent houses, and in them the higher class of the inhabitants reside. There are various well frequented literary institutions in the town, to most of which libraries are attached. It contains numerous charitable institutions, which are liberally supported. The great object of interest is the magnificent iron bridge which crosses the Wear, and connects Sunderland with Monkwearmouth. It consists of a single arch of 236 feet in span, formed by small segments of iron, having a height of upwards of 100 feet from the centre of the arch to the surface of the river at low water, which enables vessels of above 300 tons burden to pass under by merely lowering their top-gallants. The projector of the bridge was Rowland Burdon, Esq. of this neighbourhood, who subscribed L.23,000 out of the L.27,000 which it cost. The harbour is constructed at the mouth of the river, by means of two piers of more than 200 yards in length, which form a beautiful promenade. It is defended by a battery, near to which are extensive brick barracks, capable of holding 2000 men. At the end of the north pier there is a lighthouse. The w<hi rend="superscript">,</hi>ater in the harbour is too shallow to admit large vessels, and they are loaded and discharged by means of large boats locally called keels. Great advantages have been gained by the formation of a railway, running through the eastern part of the town, in the direction of the low quay ; by which means the coals and other products of the interior are more easily and expeditiously shipped than higher up the river, where great inconvenience was frequently experienced from its crowded state above the existing staiths where the coals are kept. The trade, which is principally in the building of vessels and shipment of coals, is on the increase. Of the former, a hundred can be laid on the stocks at the same time; and when it is mentioned that there are upwards of thirty yards for building ships, five for small craft, and four dry and floating docks, besides a large basin or dock, which is constructed on the left bank, near the mouth of the river, the shipping interest of the port must appear to be of great value. In the year 1836 the number of ships which left the port was 994, with a tonnage of 153,415 ; and in 1837 they had increased to 1338, with a tonnage of 193,133. The coal-trade employs many vessels and hands. It is calculated that upwards of 2000 seamen belonging to the town are occupied in the trade, besides those employed in the keels. The quantity of coals shipped for home consumption in 1836 was 971,190 tons; for foreign consumption, 170,367 tons. In 1837 the quantity for home use was 931,944 tons; for foreign, 242,252 tons. In addition to those important branches of industry, there are several extensive manufactories for chain-cables, ropes, sail-cloths, salt, glass, and pottery. Lime also forms a considerable part of the trade, upwards of 40,000 tons being annually shipped. The value of the custom-duty received at this port for the year 1836, after deducting all expenses, amounted to L.71,637, and lor the year 1837 L.80,072. The municipal govemment of the borough is vested in a mayor, fourteen aldermen, and forty-one councillors, and it is divided into seven wards. The borough returns two members to parliament. In 1821 the population of Sunderland alone amounted to 14,725, and in 1831 to 17,060. In 1821 the conjoined population amounted to 31,891, and in 1831 to 40,735.</p><p>SUNDRABORN, a small state and town on the island of Celebes.</p><p>SLJNERAMPORE, a town of Bengal, district of Dacca, situated on the Megna river. Long. 91. E. Lat. 24. 5. N.</p><p>SUNGEI <hi rend="smallcaps">Tenang,</hi> a country in the interior of Sumatra, between the second and third degrees of south latitude. It is mountainous, and the access to it is extremely difficult, from high ranges of mountains, and thick forests which intervene.</p><p>SUNNINGHILL, a parish in Berkshire, in the hundred of Cookham, twenty-two miles from London, and five miles from Staines. It is finely situated in the most delightful part of Windsor forest. It chiefly consists of elegant villas, and was once much visited on account of some mineral springs, which had great reputation in removing paralytic complaints. Besides the hill, the parish contains the liberty of Early, and the townships of Sandford and Woodley. The whole population amounted in 1811 to 1534, in 1821 to 1648, and in 1831 to 1701. A small portion of this parish is on the opposite side of the Thames, and in the county of Oxford.</p><p>SUPEREROGATION, in <hi rend="italic">Theology,</hi> what a man does beyond his duty, or more than he is commanded to do. The Romanists strenuously contend for works of supererogation, and maintain that a stock of merit is accumulated, of which the church has the disposal, and which she distributes in indulgences according to her own pleasure. This absurd doctrine was first invented towards the close of the twelfth century, and modified and embellished by St Thomas in the thirteenth. Men were then taught to believe that there actually existed an immense treasure of merit, composed of the pious deeds and virtuous actions which the saints had performed beyond what was necessary for their own salvation, and which were therefore applicable to the benefit of others ; and the guardian and dispenser of this precious treasure was the Roman pontiff ; and that of consequence he was empowered to assign to such as he thought proper a portion of this inexhaustible source of merit, suitable to their respective guilt, and sufficient to deliver them from the punishment due to their crimes. The reformed churches do not allow of any work of supererogation ; but hold, with the apostles, that when we have done our best, we are but unprofitable servants.</p><p>SUPERFICIES, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Surface,</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Geometry,</hi> the outside or exterior face of any body. This is considered as having the two dimensions of length and breadth only, but no thickness ; and therefore it makes no part of the substance, or solid content, or matter, of the body. The terms, or bounds, or extremities, of a superficies, are lines ; and superficies may be considered as generated by the motions of lines. Superficies are either rectilinear, curvilinear, plane, concave, or convex. A rectilinear superficies is that which is bounded by right lines ; curvilinear superficies is bounded by curve lines ; plane superficies is that which has no inequality in it, or risings, or sinkings, but lies evenly and straight throughout, so that a right line may wholly coincide with it in all parts and directions ; convex superficies is that which is curved and rises outwards ; concave superficies is curved and sinks inwards.</p><p>SUPERFLUOUS <hi rend="smallcaps">Interval.</hi> See Music.</p><p>SUPERINTENDENT, which is equivalent to bishop, denotes an ecclesiastical superior in several reformed churches, particularly among the Lutherans of Germany.</p><p>SUPERLATIVE, in <hi rend="italic">Grammar,</hi> one of the degrees of</p></body></text></TEI>