<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-05-20T16:32:13Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Garengeot, Louis, La Motte, Frère St Cosme,@@<hi rend="superscript">1</hi> Portal, Pou- teau, Lecat, Chopart, Morand, Moreau, &amp;c.</p><p>It is about the middle of the eighteenth century that our attention is first attracted to our transatlantic brethren. In 1763, lectures on anatomy and surgery were delivered in Philadelphia by Dr Shippen; and in 1791 the medical school of that city was completely established, under Benjamin Rush, the Hippocrates of Colombia ; a school which has since lent invaluable aid to the progress of both medicine and surgery.</p><p>Our own country was at this time by no means barren in surgery. Percival Pott and John Hunter are names which occur, the one in the middle, the other in the end, of the eighteenth century, and are fully equivalent to Petit and Desault ; indeed Hunter may be justly ranked as the greatest man that ever graced the profession. Pott, the best author, operator, and practical surgeon of his time, greatly improved the practice of surgery in England, both by his writings and by personal example. Like Desault, his attention was particularly directed to the treatment of fractures, of which he had some painful experience in his own person, having sustained a severe compound fracture of the leg. He has left a justly celebrated treatise on the subject. On amputation his observations are most important, clearly discriminating between those cases, of injury more particularly, which demand the operation, and those which do not ; at the same time marking the period most advantageous to its performance. Regarding injuries of the head, he wrote with more precision, and at the same time with more originality, than any previous author, and will ever remain a valued authority upon that subject. The same may be said of his description of vertebral disease, he having been the first who clearly distinguished between those curvatures of the spine depending on mere change of form in the bones, and those occasioned by caries or abscess : the latter formidable affection is still known as “ Pott’s disease” of the vertebras. He greatly improved the treatment of fistula in ano, and abscesses in general ; and by simplifying the whole art of surgery, discarding the cautery and escharotic unguents, or rather limiting them to their proper place and use, employing also the cutting instruments with caution and reserve, and placing more implicit trust in, and showing more respect for, the powers of nature than had hitherto been the custom, he achieved a most important and beneficial reform in surgery. Until his time, the maxim “ Dolor medicina doloris” remained unrefuted. The actual cautery, for example, was in such general use, that “ at the time when surgeons visited the hospital, it was regularly heated and prepared in the wards, and in the presence of the patients, as a part of the necessary apparatus. Mr Pott lived to see these remains of barbarism set aside, and a more humane and rational plan, of which he was the originator, universally adopted.” John Hunter, a native of Scotland, the pupil, first of Cheselden, and afterwards of Pott, though not remarkably distinguished as an operator, was the most gifted surgeon of which the medical profession can boast, and no less eminent as an anatomist, physiologist, and general philosopher. His researches comprehended a wider range than those of Pott, but arrived at the same end, the improvement of surgery. The knowledge obtained by his vast inquiries into physiology, pathology, and human and comparative anatomy, was, with all the power of his genius, brought to bear upon the practice of the profession, and with the happiest success. The doctrines of adhesion, granulation, ulceration, and inflammation with its various results, were, until detected and explained by him, comparatively obscure and uncertain ; and no one is ignorant how much the successful treatment of disease, either by surgery or medicine, must ever depend on an accurate and familiar knowledge of these rudiments. To him we are indebted for the simplification of more than one operation, the discovery of the vitality of the blood, important advice as to the treatment of gunshot wounds, the enforcement of excision of bitten or poisoned parts, many new facts as to the physiology and pathology of teeth, and other valuable additions to practical surgery. But these assume an unimportant place among his deeds, when placed beside the two with which his name is indelibly associated— the cure of popliteal aneurism by ligature of the femoral artery, and the elucidation of the venereal disease ; his work on the latter subject still remaining standard, and in many respects unsurpassed. His improvement of the operation for aneurism marks an era in the history of surgery, being one of the most important of its advances. Dissatisfied with the cruel, formidable, and unsatisfactory operation for popliteal aneurism, by incision of the tumour and ligature of the vessel at its diseased part, he made himself aware of the causes of failure by the old system, contemplated the plan of cure which bears his name, satisfied himself of its practicability by diligent study and experiment, successfully brought it to the test of actual practice ; and tben, extending the principle to all aneurisms, effected for surgery a great triumph over that formidable disease.@@<hi rend="superscript">2</hi> His first operation was performed in 1785, and was successful; proving that permanent removal of the force of the circulation in the aneurism is sufficient for its cure, by permitting consolidation and ultimate obliteration of the tumour. Since his time the method of applying the ligature has been considerably improved, and the certainty of success consequently increased. But “the more brilliant a discovery, and the more beneficial its results, the more certain is its author of becoming the butt of envy and the object of detraction.” And accordingly we find that Hunter has not been permitted to remain in undisturbed possession of bis discovery. Its merit has by some been claimed as due to Aëtius ; others, with better hopes of success, support the pretensions of Guillemeau (a pupil of Ambrose Paré), Anel@@<hi rend="superscript">5</hi> and Desault; but a candid inquiry into facts and dates will ever result in ascribing the honour to our illustrious countryman. Had he even been deprived of this, his name must still have been immortalized by other and more palpable labour of his mind and hand—his books and museum.</p><p>In the same century with Pott and Hunter, Britain also produced White, an excellent practical surgeon and lucid writer ; Cheselden and Douglas, two eminent lithotomists, the former peculiarly successful ; Sharp, famed for his Critical Inquiry into the State of Surgery ; and Monro, a name indissolubly united with the birth and fame of the Edinburgh medical school.@@<hi rend="superscript">4</hi></p><p>In Italy, where, during the times of Pott and Hunter, several eminent surgeons lived, Lancisi, Morgagni, Bertrandi, Troja, &amp;c.,—the labours of Hunter in aneurism were ably followed up by Scarpa, who still further elucidated the doctrines regarding the new treatment of that disease, and established the success of the operation. He was also eminently successful in his researches as to the anatomy and patho-</p><p><hi rend="superscript">@@@,</hi> Frire Jean de St Cosme, although a monk, had been educated as a surgeon. He was the inventor of the Lithotome Caché, and with it obtained wonderful success and celebrity as a lithotomist.</p><p><hi rend="superscript">@@@,</hi> “ So discouraging were the results of the old operation, that many surgeons preferred performing amputation of the aneurismal limb."</p><p>@@@*	Guillemeau and Λnel placed their incisions and ligatures in the immediate neighbourhood of the tumour.</p><p>@@@*	Dr Monro was appointed professor of anatomy to the company of surgeons in 1719, and during the ensuing year be was appointed to a similar chair in the university. Several other professors in the same faculty had previously been nominated ; Sir Robert Sibbald, Dr Halket, and Dr Pitcairne, so early as the year 1685. But Dr Monro was the first who regularly delivered public courses of lectures, and be may in a great measure be regarded as the founder of the medical school of Edinburgh.</p></body></text></TEI>