<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T17:43:16Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Cirencester. Lond. 1757, 4-to. The Medallic History of Marcus Aurelius Valerius Carausius, Emperor in Britain. Loud. 1757-9, 2 vols. 4to.</p><p>STUPOR, a numbness in any part of the body, whether occasioned by ligatures obstructing the blood’s motion, by the palsy, or the like.</p><p>STURM, <hi rend="smallcaps">John,</hi> better known by the name of Sturmius, a learned philologer and rhetorician, was born at Schleiden in Eissel, near Cologne, on the 1st of October 1507. He studied at first in his native country with the sons of Count von Manderscheid, whose receiver his father was. He afterwards pursued his study at Liege, in the college of St Jerome, and then went to Louvain in 1524. He there spent five years, three in learning and two in teaching. He set up a printing-press with Rudger Rescius, professor of the Greek tongue, and printed several Greek authors. In 1529 he went to Paris, where he was highly esteemed, and read public lectures on the Greek and Latin writers, and on logic. There he married, and kept a great number of boarders : but as he was inclined to what were called the new opinions, he was more than once in danger ; and this undoubtedly was the reason why he removed to Strasburg in 1537, in order to take possession of the place offered him by the magistrates. The year following he opened a school, which became famous, and by his means obtained of Maximilian II. the privileges of a university in the year 1566. He was very well skilled in polite literature, wrote Latin with great purity, and was an able teacher. His talents were not confined to the school ; for he was frequently intrusted with deputations in Germany and foreign countries, and discharged these employments with great honour and diligence. He showed extreme charity to the refugees on account of religion : he not only laboured to assist them by his advice and recommendations, but he even impoverished himself for them. He died on the 3d of March 1589, in the eighty-second year of his age, after he had been for some time blind. Although he was thrice married, he left no children. He was a learned writer, and published various works, which were found to be useful and important by his contemporaries. One of these was an edition of Cicero in nine vols. 8vo. He bestowed much labour in elucidating the rhetorical works of Aristotle, Hermogenes, and Cicero. With the view of improving the system of education, he published several treatises ; one of which was frequently reprinted. It is entitled “ De Literarum Ludis recte aperiendis liber.” Argent. 1538, 4to. F. A. Hallbauer edited a collection of his tracts, under the title “ De Institutione Scholastica Opuscula omnia.” Jenæ, 1730, 8vo. The name of Sturmius is familiar to the reader of Ascham’s epistles. He must not be confounded with John Sturm, a native of Mechlin, and physician and professor of mathematics at Louvain, who also wrote several works.</p><p>STURMINSTER-MARSHAL, a town of the hundred of Cogdean and county of Dorset, 104 miles from London. It has a large church, and had formerly a market, which has of late years been disused. It stands on the river Stour. The number of inhabitants amounted in 1801 to 604, in 1811 to 662, in 1821 to 715, and in 1831 to 803.</p><p>STURMINSTER-NEWTON, a town in the hundred of the same name in the county of Dorset, 111 miles from London. It stands on the river Stour, and had once a considerable trade in making flannels, baize, and blankets; but of late it has declined. The buildings are indifferent, but it has a fine church, lately repaired. The market is held on Thursday. The inhabitants amounted in 1801 to 1406, in 1811 to 1461, in 1821 to 1612, and in 1831 to 1831.</p><p>STUTTGART, the capital of the kingdom of Wirtem- berg, stands in a beautiful valley, and is surrounded on every side with hills of very moderate elevation, which are clothed to the tops with vineyards. The valley is watered by a clear and rapid but not copious river, which meanders through the walks at the extremity of the city. A great part of the city is composed of fine and modern buildings, and those streets are clean, well paved, and light. The royal palace is an extensive and magnificent pile of building ; and the theatre, opera-house, the gymnasium, and the Catholic church, are fine specimens of architecture. Though there are no fortifications, the entrance to the city is through handsome gates, and one of them of most imposing beauty. Besides the gymnasium, there are other institutions for instruction ; and the collection of ancient paintings, and the workshop of the sculptor Daneker, will be a treat to an amateur of the fine arts. The inhabitants amounted in 1817 to 26,016, and in 1831 had increased to 31,500. It is a place of little trade beyond what arises from supplying the court and tile nobility that resort to it. Long. 9. 5.33. E. Lat. 46. 48. 32. N.</p><p>STYLE, a word of various significations, originally deduced from <hi rend="italic">stylos,</hi> a kind of bodkin wherewith the ancients wrote on plates of lead, or on wax, &amp;c. and which is still used to write on ivory leaves and paper prepared for that purpose.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Style,</hi> in language, is the peculiar manner in which a man expresses his conceptions. It is a picture of the ideas which rise in his mind, and of the order in which they are there produced. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Rhetoric.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Old </hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Style,</hi> the Julian method of computing time, as the</p><p><hi rend="italic">New </hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Style</hi> is the Gregorian method of computation. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Chronology.</hi></p><p>STYLITES, <hi rend="smallcaps">Pillar Saints,</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Ecclesiastical History,</hi> an appellation given to a kind of solitaries, who stood motionless upon the tops of pillars raised for this exercise of their patience, and remained there for several years, amidst the admiration and applause of the stupid populace. Of these we find several mentioned in ancient writers, and even as low as the twelfth century, when they were totally suppressed. The founder of the order was Simeon Stylites, a famous anchoret in the fifth century, who first took up his abode on a column six cubits high, then on a second of twelve cubits, a third of twenty-two, a fourth of thirty- six, and on another of fi&gt;rty cubits, where he thus passed thirty-seven years of his life. The tops of these columns were only three feet in diameter, and were defended by a rail that reached almost to the girdle, but did not permit the votary to lie down. The faquirs, or devout people of the east, imitate this insane mode of life to the present day.</p><p>STYX, in <hi rend="italic">Fabulous History,</hi> a river of hell, round which it flows nine times. The gods held the waters of the Styx in such veneration, that to swear by them was reckoned an oath altogether inviolable. If any of the gods had perjured themselves, Jupiter obliged them to drink the waters of the Styx, which lulled them for one whole year into a sens∣ less stupidity; for the nine following years they were deprived of the ambrosia and the nectar of the gods ; and after the expiration of the years of their punishment, they were restored to the assembly of the deities, and to all their original privileges. It is said that this veneration was shown to the Styx, because it received its name from the nymph Styx, who with her three daughters assisted Jupiter in his war against the Titans.</p><p>Styx was a river which it was necessary for departed shades to pass before they could enter the infernal regions ; and it was the office of Charon to ferry them over. Mythological writers have said that the Egyptians framed both this and some other fables relating to the dead, from certain customs peculiar to their country ; that in particular there was, not far from Memphis, a famous burying-place, to which the dead bodies were conveyed in a boat across the lake Acherusia; and that Charon was a boatman who had long officiated in that service. The learned Dr Blackwell, in his Life of Homer, has observed, that, in the old Egyptian language<hi rend="subscript">t </hi><hi rend="italic">Charoni</hi> signified "ferryman.”</p></body></text></TEI>