<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-05-20T16:29:38Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>beautiful structures of Athens, forms a prominent object on the Calton Hill.@@<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>	(n. <hi rend="smallcaps">l.)</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Stewart’s </hi><hi rend="italic">Islands,</hi> a cluster of small, low islands, in the South Pacific Ocean, discovered by Captain Hunter in 1791. They are five in number. Long. 163. 18. E. Lat. 8. 26. S.</p><p>STEYER, a city of Austria, in the province of the Upper Ens, the capital of the circle of Traun. It stands at the junction of the two rivers Steyer and Traun, which, when united, flow into the Danube. It is a place of great industry, and contains various manufactories. There are some of cotton and of linen goods ; but the chief occupation is that of preparing cutlery and arms of various kinds, the latter chiefly for the imperial armies. The other necessaries for the equipment of armies are also extensively fabricated. The city contains 10,640 inhabitants, having of late years greatly increased. Long. 14. 14. 45. E. Lat 48. 4.45. N.</p><p>STEYERM ARK, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Steiermark,</hi> one of the provinces of the Austrian empire. Its name is derived from an ancient palace at the junction of the Steyer with the Ens, which in the twelfth century was inhabited by a Count Trungau, who was ruler over a part of Carinthia, then an independent duchy. It extends in north latitude from 45° 54' to 47° 50', and in east longitude from 13° 26' to 16° 19', being an extent of 8600 square miles. It comprehends twenty cities, ninety-six market-towns, and 3540 villages, with a population, according to the last census, of 869,000 persons, all adhering to the Catholic church, with the exception of four Lutheran congregations and a few Jews. It is bounded on the north by the province of Lower Ens, on the east by Hungary, on the south by the Illyrian province of Laybach, and on the west by that province and the Upper Ens. The northern and western divisions of the province are covered with the lofty mountains of the Julian Alps, divided into two branches. These mountains in no case reach the line of perpetual snow, the highest of them, called the Grossenberg, being but 8380 feet, and the others from 3250 to 7600 feet. The southern and eastern parts of the province are less elevated, consisting of plains and undulating bills. The mountains give rise to numerous rivulets, which form within it large rivers, all of which terminate in the Danube. The principal of these are the Mur, the Drave, the Ens, and the Raab. There are no extensive lakes, but many of small extent, and some of them in very elevated situations. It abounds in mineral springs, both warm and cold, and containing various combinations of iron, salt, and sulphur ; but they are not much repaired to by invalids. One half of the province is covered with woods, which yield fuel and timber for building, and contain abundance of game both of the larger and smaller kind. Of the former kind are roebucks, wild swine, gemsen, and bears, as well as beasts of prey, especially wolves and lynxes. The land in the valleys is fertile and well cultivated, and produces good corn, a great proportion of which is maize, forming the chief food of the labouring classes. More than 60,000 acres are cultivated with vines, which produce tolerable wine. Hemp and flax are sufficiently raised to provide clothing, with the aid of the wool of about 150,000 sheep. The mineral productions are various. Salt is the most considerable in quantity. Iron is produced, and is converted into utensils for internal use, but not for exportation. Silver is raised to the extent of about 60,000 ounces yearly, and likewise some copper, cobalt, alum, vitriol, and sulphur. The commerce is not extensive, except between the upper and lower parts of the province, though some is carried on both with other parts of Germany and with Austrian Italy. One of tile great roads to Lombardy passes through this province. It still retains some privileges respecting the assembling of the states, but they are of little practical efficacy. The capital is Gratz, a city of 40,900 inhabitants.</p><p>STEYNING, a town of the hundred of that name, in the rape of Bramber and county of Sussex, fifty-one miles from London. It is ill built, but has a curious church, of Norman architecture, and was the burial-place of some of the Saxon kings. It returned two members to the House of Commons, but was disfranchised by the act of 1832. It has a market on Wednesday, and several fairs at which great numbers of sheep are sold. The inhabitants amounted in 1801 to 1174, in 1811 to 1210, in 1821 to 1324, and in 1831 to 1436.</p><p>STIBADIUM, among the Romans, a low kind of table, couch, or bed, of a circular form, which succeeded to the triclinia, and was of different sizes according to the number of guests for which it was designed. Tables of this kind were called <hi rend="italic">hexaclina, octaclina,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">enneaclina,</hi> according as they held six, eight, or nine guests, and so of any oilier number.</p><p>STICCATO <hi rend="italic">(Ital.),</hi> a rude musical instrument, formed of a number of sticks of hard wood of different lengths, generally attached to each other by strings at the ends, but so as to hang separate from one another when suspended by the top. It is played upon by striking the sticks with rods of cane or whalebone tipped with ivory balls. Mersenne, in his <hi rend="italic">Harmonia Universalis,</hi> calls this instrument <hi rend="italic">ligneum psalterium.</hi></p><p>STICHOS, a name given by the old wτiters to a pectoral confection, the principal ingredient of which was tile herb <hi rend="italic">marrubium</hi> or horehound.</p><p>STIGMATA, in <hi rend="italic">Natural History,</hi> the apertures in different parts of tile bodies of insects, communicating with the tracheæ or air-vessels, and serving for the office of respiration.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Stigmata,</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Antiquity,</hi> certain marks impressed on the left shoulder of the soldiers when listed.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Stigmata</hi> were also a kind of notes or abbreviations, consisting only of points disposed various ways ; as in triangles, squares, crosses, &amp;c.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Stigmata</hi> is likewise a term used among the Franciscans, to express the marks or prints of our Saviour’s wounds, said to have been miraculously impressed by him on the body of their seraphic father St Francis.</p><p>STIGMATIZING, among the ancients, was inflicted upon slaves as a punishment, but more frequently as a mark to distinguish them : in which case it was done by applying a red-hot iron marked with certain letters to their foreheads, till a fair impression was made ; and then pouring ink into their furrows, that the inscription might be the more conspicuous. It was customary to stigmatize the worshippers and votaries of some of the gods. The marks used on these occasions were various ; sometimes they contained the name of the god, sometimes his particular ensign, as the thunderbolt of Jupiter, the trident of Neptune, the ivy of Bacchus ; or they marked themselves with some mystical number, by which the god’s name was described. To these three ways of stigmatizing St John is supposed to refer (Rev. chap, xiii. ver. 16, 17). Theodoret is of opinion that the Jews were forbidden to brand themselves with stigmata, because the idolaters, by that ceremony, used to consecrate themselves to their false gods. Among some nations, stigmatizing was considered as a distinguishing mark of honour and nobility. In Thrace, as Herodotus informs us, it was practised by none but persons of credit, nor omitted by any but persons of the meanest rank. The ancient Britons are also said to have</p><p><hi rend="superscript">@@@,</hi> The Editor had hoped to have the gratification of introducing into this work, so deeply indebted to this great and good man, a more detailed account of his life and writings ; but circumstances induced him to abandon the design, and to give a place only to the above brief notice, contributed by one of his literary assistants.</p></body></text></TEI>