<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-05-20T16:31:42Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>sage, called the Great Channel, is sometimes resorted to during the south-east monsoon ; but it is navigated with the greatest difficulty, in consequence of the opposition from the south-easterly gales. In the narrowest part of the straits is an island, which, from its situation, is called Thwart the Way, or Middle Isle ; on both sides of which a strong current runs during the whole year, setting with the prevailing easterly or westerly winds either to the north-east or southwest. The other chief islands in the straits are Prince’s Isle, Krakatau, and Pulo Baby. The rest are small and insignificant, mostly level, founded on beds of coral, and covered with trees.</p><p>SUNDAY, or the <hi rend="smallcaps">Lord’s Day,</hi> a solemn festival observed by Christians on the first day of every week, in memory of our Saviour’s resurrection. In the Breviary and other offices, we meet with Sundays of the first and second class. Those of the first class are, Palm, Easter, Advent, and Whitsunday, those of <hi rend="italic">Quasimodo </hi>and <hi rend="italic">Quadragesima.</hi> Those of the second class are the common Sundays. Anciently each Sunday in the year had its particular name, which was taken from the introit of the day ; which custom has only been continued to some few in lent ; as <hi rend="italic">Reminiscere, Oculi, Lætare, Judica.</hi> Some are of opinion that the Lord's Day mentioned in the Apocalypse is our Sunday, which they believe was so early instituted by the apostles. Be this as it may, it is certain a regard was paid to this day even in the earliest ages of the church, as appears from the first Apology of Justin Martyr, where he describes the exercise of the day as not much unlike to ours. But it was Constantine the Great who first made a law for the proper observance of Sunday ; and who, according to Eusebius, appointed it should be regularly celebrated throughout the Roman empire. Before him, and even in his time, they observed the Jewish Sabbath as well as Sunday ; both to satisfy the law of Moses, and to imitate the apostles, who used to meet together on the first day. By Constantine’s law, promulgated in 321, it was decreed, that for the future the Sunday should be kept as a day of rest in all cities and towns ; but he allowed the country people to follow their work. In 538, the council of Orleans prohibited country labour ; but because there were still many Jews in Gaul, and the people fell into many superstitious uses in the celebration of the new Sabbath, like those of the Jews in that of the old, the council declares, that to hold it unlawful to travel with horses, cattle, and carriages, to prepare food, or to do any thing necessary to the cleanliness and decency of houses or persons, savours more of Judaism than of Christianity.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sunday Island,</hi> a small island on the east coast of New Holland, discovered by Captain Bligh in 1788. Lat. 11. 58. S.</p><p>SUNDEEP <hi rend="smallcaps">Isle,</hi> an island of Bengal, in the district of Chittagong, about twenty miles in length by ten in breadth. It is the seat of a salt manufacture by the government, subordinate to the Bulwa and Chittagong agency. The soil is fertile and affords excellent pasture for cattle, and might be easily rendered of much more value than it is at present ; but its station for the manufacture of salt supersedes every other use. Ships may safely approach it on all sides except the north. The entrance of the river is safe, and it possesses good anchorage, where ships may remain safe during the adverse monsoon ; but the climate is dangerous to Europeans. The town is situated about a mile from the western shore, on the north bank of a creek called Sittal. Towards the end of the sixteenth century a number of Portuguese had settled on the coasts of Arracan and Chittagong ; and, having recommended themselves by their bravery and maritime skill, had risen to considerable commands in the service of the native princes. But in consequence of their turbulent conduct, they were expelled by the rajah of Arracan from his dominions, and many of them put to death. A remnant however joining together, elected Sebastian Gonzales for their chief, who took possession of this island, and having collected about 3000 men, extended his conquests. He was at last subdued by the rajah of Arracan, who retained possession of the island till 1666, when it was conquered by the Mogul armies, and came into the possession of the British along with the province of Bengal. Long, of the town 91. 36. E. Lat. 22. 25. N.</p><p>SUNDELLA, a town of Hindustan, in the nabob of Oude's territories. It is thirty miles north-west from Lucknow. Long. 80. 30. E. Lat. 27. 5. N.</p><p>SUNDERBUNDS, an extensive and woody district of Bengal, situated at the mouth of the eastern or great branch of the river Ganges. It is a dreary region, consisting of a labyrinth of rivers and creeks, all of salt, except those that communicate immediately with the principal arm of the Ganges, these numerous natural canals being so disposed as to form a complete inland navigation. Bishop Heber describes the prospect on the banks of the river as a dismal unbroken line of black wood and thicket, apparently impenetrable and interminable, which, he adds, “ one might easily imagine to be the habitation of every thing monstrous, disgusting, and dangerous, from the tiger and the cobra de capello down to the scorpion and mosquito. The seamen,” he continues, “ spoke of the shore with horror, as the grave of all who were so unfortunate as to remain many days in its neighbourhood.” On a nearer approach, the appearance of the Sunderbunds improved ; the woods assumed a greater variety of green and shade ; several round-topped trees and some low palms were seen among them, and a fresh vegetable fragrance was wafted from the shore.</p><p>In tracing the coast of this delta, eight openings are found, each of which appears to be the principal mouth of the Ganges. The navigation through the Sunderbunds is effected chiefly by means of the tides, there being two distinct passages ; the one named the Southern or Sunderland Passage, and the other the Balliaghaut Passage. The first is the longer of the two, and opens into the river about sixty-five miles below Calcutta. The latter opens into a lake on the east side of Calcutta ; the navigation is intricate, extending more than 200 miles through a forest, divided into numberless islands by various channels, and the prospects are romantic. At one time the masts of vessels are entangled among the branches of trees, and at other times they sail on a broadly-expanded river skirted with beautiful woods. The water is everywhere salt ; and the whole tract is uninhabited except by tigers, and wild deer, their natural prey. During the dry season, the lower shores of these rivers are visited by salt-makers and woodcutters, who supply Calcutta with wood for fuel from these desolate tracts, and many of whom every year are devoured by tigers ; these animals growing here to an enormous size, and so ferocious that they have been sometimes known to swim off and attack boats. In addition to these, the waters swarm with alligators. Some attempts have been made to bring parts of the Sunderbunds into cultivation, but with little success, as the want of fresh water must always prove a great obstacle to improvement ; nor is it desirable to settle such an unhealthy tract while so many healthy stations remain unoccupied. The Sunderbunds are deemed of importance as a political barrier to Bengal on the south.</p><p>SUNDERLAND, a large and important seaport town on the east coast of England, in the county of Durham, 268 miles from London by way of Stockton. The municipal boundary includes the townships of Monkwearmouth, Bishopwearmouth, and Southwick, which form an area of 5095 acres. The river Wear, after running through the centre of the borough, falls into the sea. Sunderland proper is situated on the south or right side of the river, and is a</p></body></text></TEI>