<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-05-20T16:30:04Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>the metal ; for in these instances the stove is much larger than that described, and consequently the fire more powerful. Its size must depend on the size and number of the apartments. In its general construction it resembles the other, consisting of the inner part for the fuel, with its grating, ash-pit, and vent, and of the outer casing, with the aperture for the supply of air to the chamber, and the tube or tubes for its transmission to the apartments.</p><p>The great advantage attending the use of stoves of this kind is, that they do not become so warm as to decompose the impurities in the air flowing into the hot chamber, and consequently there are no offensive effluvia generated. As the temperature is not so high as that of metal stoves, more of the warm air is requisite, by which there is a frequent renewal of that in the apartment, and the temperature throughout is more uniform than when a smaller quantity of hotter air is admitted. It has already been mentioned that the temperature of the air from the hot chamber of the stove described is from 120° to 180°. Perhaps this is higher than it ought to be. Many prefer having the stove so constructed that the temperature of the air which it throws into the apartment shall not exceed 70°. Of course, in this case, a much larger quantity of it is necessary. By throwing in a sufficient supply, that of the apartments may be maintained at about 60°. The mouths of the hot air-tubes are made to terminate as near the floor as possible, that the air may rise, and gradually mix with the atmosphere of the apartment.</p><p>In erecting stoves for the supply of hot air in this way, there are many circumstances to be considered, to which it would here be useless to allude. Much must depend on local situation, the size and number of the apartments, and the draught through them. These considerations must be left to the skill and ingenuity of the workman, who must be guided by keeping in view the general principles which determine the supply of air to the furnace, the ascensional force of the column of warm air to be conveyed through the tubes, the manner in which the apartments to be warmed are disposed, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi></p><p>In heating buildings by these stoves when they are not in constant use, as is the case in churches, the time for keeping them going must also depend on circumstances. If the object is merely to throw in a supply of warm air, then the stove must be kindled a few hours before the apartment is to be occupied, especially if it is not expected that there shall be much change in its atmosphere; but if the object is to keep the place warm, then the stove might to be kept in constant use, so as to be constantly throwing in warm air. During night the fire can be damped, and it is again made brisk when required. This is much better than allowing the fire to go out, because in again heating the stove to the requisite temperature, there must be a considerable waste of fuel. After the fire is in good condition, and the stove well heated, the combustion should be allowed to proceed slowly, which is accomplished by the proper regulation of the draught.</p><p>STOW, <hi rend="smallcaps">John,</hi> an industrious historian, son of Thomas Stow', merchant-tailor, of St Michael’s, Cornhill, in London, was born about the year 1525. Of the early part of his life we know very little, except that he was bred to his father’s business, which in the year 1560 he relinquished, devoting himself entirely to the study of our ancient historians, chronicles, annals, charters, registers, and records. Of these he made a considerable collection, travelling for that purpose to different parts of the kingdom, and transcribing such manuscripts as he could not purchase. But this profession of an antiquary being attended with no present emolument, he was obliged for subsistence to return to his trade. It happened, however, that his talents and necessities were made known to Dr Parker, archbishop of Canterbury ; who being himself an antiquary, encouraged and enabled Stow to prosecute his darling study. In those times of persecution, though Elizabeth was then upon the throne, honest John Stow did not escape danger. His collection of popish records was deemed a cause of suspicion. His younger brother Thomas preferred no less than 140 articles against him before the ecclesiastical commission ; but the proof being insufficient, he was acquitted. In 1565 he first published his Summary of the Chronicles of England. About the year 1584 he began his Survey of London. In 1585 he was one of the two collectors for a great muster of Limestreet ward. During the same year he petitioned the corporation of London to bestow on him the benefit of two freemen, to enable him to publish his Survey; and in 1589 he again petitioned for a pension. Whether he succeeded is not known. He was principally concerned in the second edition of Holinshed’s Chronicle, published in 1587. He also corrected and twice augmented Chaucer’s Works, published in 1561 and in 1597. His Survey of London was first published in 1598. To these laborious works he would have added his large Chronicle, or History of England ; but he lived only to publish an abstract of it, under the title of “ <hi rend="italic">Flores Historiarum, </hi>or Annals of this Kingdom, from the time of the Ancient Britons to his own.” This work was printed in 1600. The folio volume which was printed after his death, with the title of Stow’s Chronicle, was taken from his papers by Edmund Howes. Having thus spent his life and fortune in these laborious pursuits, he was at last obliged to solicit the charitable and well-disposed for relief. For this purpose, King James I. granted him in 1603 a brief, which was renewed in 1604, authorizing him to collect in churches the benefactions of his fellow-citizens. He died in April 1605, aged eighty ; and was buried in his parish church of St Andrew’s Undershaft, where his widow erected a decent monument to his memory. John Stow was a most indefatigable antiquary, a faithful historian, and an honest man.</p><p>STOW ON THE WOLD, a town of the hundred of Haughton, in the county of Gloucester, eighty-two miles from London. It stands on a hill in a wild district near the river Windrash. It is irregularly and not well built. The parish is very extensive, though not densely peopled. The town has a market on Thursday, and several fairs at which sales are made of hops, sheep, and cheese. The inhabitants amounted in 1801 to 1471, in 1811 to 1544, in 1821 to 1731, and in 1831 to 1810.</p><p>STOWEY-NETHER, a town of the county of Somerset, in the hundred of Willerton and Freemanners, six miles from Bridgewater, and 149 miles from London. It is in a fertile district at the foot of the Quanloch Hills. It formerly contained a castle, of which no vestige now appears, though the ditch that surrounded it may be traced. The parish church is a handsome building ; and near to it is a spring, which has the property of incrusting, with the appearance of stone, pieces of wood, or other substances that may be thrown into it. There is a small market held on Thursday. The population amounted in 1801 to 586, in 1811 to 620, in 1821 to 773, and in 1831 to 778.</p><p>STOWMARKET, a town in the hundred of Stow and county of Suffolk, seventy-six miles from London. It stands on the river Orwell, and has also a canal. It is a place of small trade, with a market on Thursday. The inhabitants amounted in 1801 to 1761, in 1811 to 2006, in 1821 to 2252, and in 1831 to 2672.</p><p>STOWAGE, the general disposition of the several materials contained in a ship’s hold, with regard to their figure, magnitude, or solidity.</p><p>STRABO, an illustrious geographer, was born at Λma- sia, a city of Cappadocia. The time of his birth cannot be ascertained, but he is known to have flourished during the age of Augustus and Tiberius. He studied under</p></body></text></TEI>