<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-05-20T16:32:07Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>capital of Chorassan, established by Sapores the First as early as the end of the third century, had by this time risen to great celebrity ; and from it Rhazes, Hally Abbas, and Avicenna derived their medical education. Mesue lived during the caliphate of Haroun al Raschid, in the end of the eighth century, and Serapion during that of Almamon, about a century later ; both eminent medical men in their time, but both pure physicians. The first Arabian worthy in the surgical department was the celebrated Rhazes, who presided over an hospital at Bagdat in the end of the ninth and beginning of the tenth centuries. His works are not remarkable for anatomical knowledge, which is not surprising, since the study of anatomy was strictly forbidden by the Mahommedan religion, and consequently the Arabians had to rest contented with the writings of the Greeks on that subject. “ One of their religious prejudices against dissection was, that the soul did not instantly forsake the body, but lingered in some particιdar portion of it for some time after apparent dissolution, so that the dismemberment of it might be a species of hideous martyrdom a very sufficient reason why a professor of such a belief should strenuously object to the anatomization of himself and his friends. Rhazes is the first who has described spina ventosa and spina bifida. Of the real nature of the latter, however, he does not seem to have had any clear idea. Regarding cancer, he advised that the knife should never be used except when the disease was limited, and the whole tumour could be completely removed ; condemning the opposite procedure as cruel and unavailing ; an opinion which after-experience has shown to be most just and true. In bites from rabid animals, he first cauterized the wotmds, and then prescribed emetics to expel the “ black bile ;” an evacuation considered most essential to the cure. His account of hernia is better than any to be found in the Greek writers. His works on surgery, however, are little more than compilations from Hippocrates, Oribasius, Aëtius, and Paulus. His confidence in oculism does not seem to have been great; for, having in his old age become blind from cataract, he could not, though urged, be prevailed upon to undergo an operation for its removal. In his time lithotomy, and some other operations, seem to have been entirely in the hands of juggling impostors. Hally Abbas, surnamed the Magician, on account of the extent of his knowledge and acquirements, lived in the end of the tenth century. His great work, the Al-meleky, written about the year 980, is, in its anatomical and physiological department, a mere transcript from the Greeks ; and his surgery possesses but few peculiarities. “ From the idea that caustics were efficacious when a redundancy of the humours flowed to a particular part, he recommended their application for the cure of hydrocele. In the management of dropsical affections his attention was always directed to the remote causes; and he preferred puncturing in the linea alba, a little below the umbilicus, for the relief of ascites.” Avicenna, who divides with Rhazes the honour of having first introduced chemistry into physic, flourished later than the two preceding Arabians. He was termed, in his day, the Prince of Physicians, and seems to have been regarded as almost miraculous for the extent and variety of his knowledge. He was born in 980, and died in 1036, without a rival, either in the medical profession, or in general science. In his great medical work, the Canon, the surgical department is not altogether forgotten, but holds a second place to physic; indeed, before the appearance of Albucasis, surgery seems to have been all but extinct amongst the Arabians. He has distinguished between closure of the pupil and cataract, and in operating for the latter recommends depression ; extraction he considers a very dangerous experiment. It is probable that to him we owe the first use of the flexible catheter. His works are said to have remained the oracles of medical knowledge for nearly six hundred years. Albucasis, who died in 1122, exerted himself more than his predecessors in behalf of surgery, which, by his own account, he found in a most deplorable condition ; and he is chiefly distinguished as a surgical writer. Cauteries and caustics seem to have been his favourite remedies; and he becomes enraptured when speaking of the “divine and secret virtues” of fire surgically employed. The actual cautery he looked upon with veneration, and describes more than fifty affections in which his experience had found it beneficial. He is minute in his directions for its application, and forbids its use, “except by persons acquainted with the anatomy of the frame, and the position of the <hi rend="italic">nerves, tendons, veins, and arteries</hi> from which latter circumstance some idea may be formed of the extent to which he himself was in the habit of roasting his unfortunate patients. He checked arterial hæmorrhage by his favourite method of cauterization, but also employed styptics, as well as complete division of the vessel, and ligature. He is supposed to have been the first to remark, that it is by the formation of a coagulum in the orifice of an artery that its calibre is closed and hæmorrhage arrested. He has described a particular instrument of his own for the cure of fistula lachrymalis, and the needle used by the surgeons of Irak for cataract. He speaks of operating for the relief of hydrocephalus, but the success of the practice does not seem to have been greater then than in its revival in our own time ; for he confesses that he knew of but one successful case, and therefore does not recommend the operation. He seems to have been conversant with the mode of removing tumours by ligature when the knife is inexpedient ; he advises amputation in gangrene of the extremities ; and is the first who has described the mode of extracting calculus by incision in the female. His method of lithotomy resembled that practised by Paulus Ægineta; and, like him, he seems to have been bold in puncturing and excising the tonsils, removing the uvula when obstinately relaxed, and extracting polypous tumours from the fauces. He mentions bronchocele as occurring most frequently among women ; but, fond of the knife and cautery as he was, he does not seem to have employed either for the removal of that tumour ; indeed he telle us of “ an ignorant operator who,” in attempting extirpation of a bronchocele, “ by wounding the arteries of the neck, killed the patient upon the spot." He invented the probang, for dislodging foreign bodies from the gullet ; and in wounds of the intestines practised union of the divided parts by suture more than once with success. Though thus bold in his operations, and, like all the Arabians, too fond of the employment of instruments, he was not however without judgment and caution. For example, he condemns tracheotomy as worse than useless when the inflammatory affection of the windpipe is acute, and has extended to the bronchi ; an opinion which is acknowledged as true, though unfortunately not always followed in the present day. And he exceeds even Rhazes in his dislike to operative interference with cancerous tumours, declaring that he never either cured, or saw cured, a single instance of that disease ; a conclusion too nearly consistent with the history of that most implacable malady in all succeeding ages. His remarks on abscesses are most judicious ; directing particular attention to their situation, and recommending their being early opened, whether “matured” or not, when in the neighbourhood of joints or other important parts, which would be injured by their continuance; a rule of practice which, if more faithfully followed, would materially diminish the number of diseased joints and bones. He also advised what has since been so much insisted on by Mr Abernethy, that when the abscess is very large, its contents should be evacuated by degrees. He is the only one among the ancient writers on surgery who has described the instruments used in each particular operation. Avenzoar, a Spanish Arab, practised physic with distinction, about the beginning</p></body></text></TEI>