<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-05-20T16:32:10Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>tioner. About the middle of the fourteenth century, Guy de Chauliac practised with renown at Avignon, and is “ accounted one of the revivers of the languishing art.” In his <hi rend="italic">chirurgia,</hi> a history of the state of surgery in bis day,@@<hi rend="superscript">1</hi> we find the first mention of the Cæsarean operation. Contemporary with him was John of Ardern, an English surgeon. He wrote with simplicity and honesty, and may be regarded as a reviver of surgery in that country. In his practice he was peculiarly successful in the treatment of fistula in ano, and thereby acquired a great reputation. Valesco de Taranta, a Portuguese, practised at Montpellier, and wrote on surgery in the beginning of the fifteenth century. He was the first who proposed the cure of cancer by the application of arsenic. About the middle of the same century, lithotomy, the practice of which had hitherto been confined to itinerant and ill-informed operators, was restored to the regular profession by Germain Colot, a French surgeon, high in favour with Louis the Eleventh. He first contrived to witness the operation by the itinerants, then practised it on the dead body, and at last performed it successfully on a condemned criminal who happened to be afflicted with stone, and who con- scnted to undergo the operation on condition of being pardoned if he survived. His success, in having thus doubly saved life, obtained for Colot much renown ; and lithotomy ever after continued a regular part of surgical practice.@@<hi rend="superscript">5</hi> The fifteenth century contains other two events important to surgery ; the discovery of the art of printing, about the year 1450, which gave a new impulse to science and literature, by rendering the accumulated stores of knowledge more accessible ; and the importation of the venereal disease from America, by the first discoverers of that continent, giving the <hi rend="italic">small</hi> pox as if in exchange, about the year 1492.@@<hi rend="superscript">3</hi> In this century also the Turks captured Constantinople, thus overthrowing the last remains of the eastern empire ; and by the multitude of Christians who fled from that city many manuscripts of the Greek medical writers were brought to Italy, and their contents thence slowly disseminated over Europe.</p><p>Hitherto surgery can scarcely lay claim to an actual revival. Occasional attempts had been made to raise it from its low position, but all proved abortive. At length, however, in the beginning of the sixteenth century, the practitioners of the healing art were happily convinced that the observation of nature was superior to compilation from the ancients, whether Arabian, Roman, or Greek ; they consequently ceased to tread blindly and servilely in the footsteps of their predecessors, and a new era arose to the profession. About the same time Vesalius gave birth to anatomy, properly so called ;@@<hi rend="superscript">4</hi> illuminated by which science, surgery became a worthy object of pursuit to men of talents and education, and under their cultivation it was gradually raised to an enlightened and liberal profession.</p><p>The most conspicuous name in this new era of surgery is that of Ambrose Paré, a Frenchman. In this country surgery was then sadly depressed, having retrograded since tbe time of John of Ardern. Its list of practitioners comprised barbers, farriers, sow-gelders, cobblers, and tinkers; and it is not matter of surprise that from among these no name has been banded down as worthy of remembrance. The combination of the practice of surgery with the more harmless manipulations of the barber, was not confined however to this island, but existed also in France, and continued in both countries for upwards of 200 years. The great Paré does not reject the appellation of barber-surgeon, as applied to himself ; nor does he seem to think that there is any thing derogatory in the title. He was surgeon successively to Henry the Second, Francis the Second, Charles the Ninth, and Henry the Third, of France ; and followed the French armies in all their campaigns down to the battle of Moncontour in 1569. His consequent experience of gunshot and other wounds, on the field of battle, naturally directed his attention to the subject of haemorrhage ; and it is to him that we owe the revival and improvement of the method of arresting bleeding from arteries by ligature, and discontinuance of the cauteries and styptics, which, to the disgrace of surgery, had hitherto been in exclusive use for this purpose. Yet so averse are mankind to abandon their ancient customs, that the improvement of Paré was not sanctioned till after much abuse and persecution, directed both against himself and his discovery ; indeed so bitter and unrelenting were his jealous brethren, that he was compelled for his own safety to adduce garbled and incorrect extracts from Galen and other ancients, in proof that to them, and not to him, the invention was to be referred. So far he was less in error than he himself supposed, for we have already stated that he has merely the merit of reviving the use of the ligature.@@<hi rend="superscript">4</hi> Celsus distinctly advises its employment when pressure fails to stop arterial hæmorrhage ; and Albucasis sometimes condescended to use it instead of his favourite cautery and cruel styptics. Paré, however, was amply repaid by future fame for the opposition which he had at first sustained. He rose to an unparalleled height of popularity with the army, by whom he was absolutely adored. On one occasion, his mere presence among the garrison of a beleagured city about to capitulate, re-animated the troops to such an extent, that their resistance became more energetic than before, and the besieging army perished beneath the walls. By bis sovereigns he was also highly esteemed. From the general massacre on the fearful night of St Bartholomew he was rescued by the personal exertions of Charles the Ninth, his great merits being appreciated even by that weak and cruel monarch. But he was not content with the respect and praise of his contemporaries ; his writings, the result of great experience and accurate observation, freed from the</p><p>@@@*	Some idea may be formed of the languishing state of surgery at this time, from his division of the surgeons into the following five sects. The first applied cataplasms indiscriminately to every description of ulcer and wound. The second in similar cases employed wine only. The third used emollient ointments and plasters. The fourth, chiefly military surgeons, promiscuously employed oils, wool, potions, and charms. The fifth, “ consisting of ignorant practitioners and silly women, had recourse upon all occasions to the saints, praised each other’s writings perpetually, and followed each other in one undeviating track, like cranes.”</p><p><hi rend="superscript">@@@,</hi> In the beginning of the sixteenth century, cutting upon the staff was introduced by Johannes de Romanis and Marianus Sanctus, and very successfully followed by Laurence Colot. a descendant of Germain.</p><p>@@@*	The first author who clearly describes the venereal disease is Marcellus Cuman as, who wrote in 1495. It was not till 1530 that Fracastorius wrote his celebrated poem <hi rend="italic">De Morbo Galilco,</hi> in reference to which it has been said that the chaste and classic elegance of its language was worthy of the best days of imperial Rome, and the mellifluence of its versification hardly surpassed by the bard of Mantua himself. By G, Torella, physician to Pope Alexander the Sixth, we are informed that the insane abuse of mercury as a means of cure was not quite a universal practice on the outbreak of the disease ; for, in describing some particular forms of mercurial ointment, he himself states that “ they destroyed on infinite number of people, who in this case did not die, but were downright killed ; and these bold empirics must give an account, if not in this, in the next world, of their practice, and be drowned in the pit of repentance.” It is but very lately that the “ pit of repentance" ceased to be useful under very similar circumstances.</p><p><hi rend="superscript">@@@4</hi> A little later in the century, Fallopius taught anatomy at Pisa, and Eustachius at Rome, and to their efforts, as well as to those of Vesalius, the advancement of that science is much indebted. Fallopius died in 1563 ; Eustachius in 1574.</p><p><hi rend="superscript">@@@i</hi> Ason example of how little the hint of Celsus was attended to, we may mention, that Procopius relates how Artabazes perished of a wound in the neck, “ the artery of the neck having been cut through, so that the blood <hi rend="italic">could not be stopped."</hi> Their cauteries and styptic* had no effect on the carotid, or its larger trunks.</p></body></text></TEI>