<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T17:41:59Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>add, that the landlords and farmers of the adjoining counties of Perth and Clackmannan, which, although politically separated, form only one district, the basin of the Forth, have as promptly availed themselves of these improvements as those of Stirlingshire.</p><p>The land on the banks of the Forth is exceedingly well adapted for orchards, of which there are a few, but of no great extent. The island of Inchmurrin, in Lochlomond, the property of the duke of Montrose, has been stocked with fellow deer for more than a century, the number being about 240, which are properly attended to, and kept always in a thriving condition.</p><p>The manufactures are carpets, tartans, plaid-shawls, trouser-stuffs, and other woollens, in the town of Stirling, but more in the neighbourhood. These within the last ten years have increased in nearly a tenfold degree, so that this district has now become one of the principal seats of the woollen manufacture in Scotland, and promises soon to take the lead. Paper, cottons, alum, copperas, soda, Prussian blue, &amp;c. are produced on an extensive scale ; spirits at several large distilleries, the amount of duty from home-made spirits being greater than in any other district in Scotland ; and iron goods at Carron. The Carron Works, celebrated over all Europe, were established upon the banks of the river of that name about eighty years ago, by Dr Roebuck and Messrs Cadell and Garbet, who were joined in the undertaking by several other gentlemen. By the charter of the company, they are authorized to employ a capital of L.150,000, which is divided into 600 shares; and ten of these are required to give a vote in the management. During the late war they employed upwards of 2000 able-bodied men, and paid in wages above L.120,000 yearly ; and this is nearly true at the present day. At these works all sorts of cast-iron goods are made, and also bar-iron, said to be equal to the Russian, but particularly cannon, and that kind called carronades, which having been invented here, take their name from the works. The boring of the cannon is a very interesting operation, which is performed in about forty-eight hours, by machinery moved by water. One of their engines raises upwards of thirty tons of water in a minute ; and so extensive are the works, that they are said to consume every day about 200 tons of coals. They have water-carriage from the Firth of Forth by means of the Carron, and to the Firth of Clyde by the Forth and Clyde Canal, which passes through the district a little to the south of the Carron. The number of vessels in the London trade alone is seven, and about as many more are constantly trading to other places.</p><p>Some years ago another extensive foundery was projected, and it is at present in operation upon a respectable footing, manufacturing goods equal to those of Carron.</p><p>Notwithstanding the favourable situation of Stirlingshire, on a navigable river, and between the east and west seas, which for many years have been connected by a canal, it has but a small town-population, and till lately its commerce was inconsiderable. Even now, half its exports, not including its agricultural produce, is supposed to be furnished by the Carron Works. In consequence of the increase of the woollen manufacture, commerce must necessarily be increased also. The principal town is Stirling, containing, in 1831,8556 inhabitants ; a place of great antiquity, which, though situated on the navigable part of the Forth, has little trade by water, and is chiefly indebted for its importance to its situation on the confines of the Highlands. Falkirk, on the eastern side of the county, a little to the south of the Forth and Clyde Canal, had a population, including a large and populous parish, in 1831, of 12,743, and is distinguished for its great fairs or trysts, which are held on the second Tuesday in August, September, and October, where cattle, sheep, and horses are brought for sale to the annual value of L.650,000. Grangemouth, founded by Sir Laurence Dundas in 1777, on the angle formed by the junction of the Carron and the Forth and Clyde Canal, is now a considerable town, and the principal seaport of the county. Its trade is chiefly with the north of Europe and along the east coast. It has a custom-house, a dry dock, and other necessary works. The depth of water in the harbour is generally, in spring tides from sixteen to eighteen feet, and in neap tides from ten to twelve. The only other towns are Kilsyth, Bannockburn, Denny, Campsie, and Balfron. On the east side there is a number of small villages, occupied partly by agricultural labourers and mechanics, and partly by weavers employed by the Glasgow manufacturers.</p><p>Besides the Forth and Clyde and Union Canals, the Edinburgh and Glasgow Railway, now constructing, passes through this county, in a direction nearly parallel to the canals, and must be productive of great benefit to its population.</p><p>The county, which in 1831 had only 118 freeholders, has now a constituency of 2332, who send one member to parliament. Stirling, its only royal borough, is associated with Culross, Dunfermline, Inverkeithing, and Queensferry, in the elections for the Scotish burghs ; and Falkirk, a parliamentary borough, with Airdrie, Hamilton, Lanark, and Linlithgow; Stirling and Falkirk being both the returning burghs. A poor-rate is only levied in a few parishes, the poor being chiefly supported, as in most parts of Scotland, by voluntary contributions.</p><p>Stirlingshire exhibits remains highly interesting to the antiquary, and has been the scene of some of the most remarkable events in Scotish history. The Roman wall, called the Wall of Antoninus, and vulgarly Græme’s Dyke, which traversed this county, may still be traced in several places. The battles of Stirling, in which Wallace defeated the English under Warren carl of Surrey ; of Falkirk, in which he in his turn was defeated ; of Bannockburn, which secured the independence of Scotland ; of Sauchie-burn, between James III. and his rebellious subjects, in which the former was defeated, and was afterwards treacherously slain at Milton; were fought in this county. Stirlingshire was in former days the battle-ground of Scotland. Here we may refer to Nimmo’s History of Stirlingshire, Ray’s Military Antiquities, and Chalmers’s Caledonia.</p><p>The population of Stirlingshire, according to the census of 1801, was 50,825, in 1811 it amounted to 58,174, in 1821 to 65,376, and in 1831 to 72,600. The increase of population from 1811 to 1831 was 21,775.	<hi rend="smallcaps">(d. d.)</hi></p><p>STIRRUP, in the manège, a rest or support for the horseman’s foot, for enabling him to mount, and for keeping him firm in his seat. Stirrups were unknown to the ancients. The want of them in getting upon horseback was supplied by agility or art. Some horses were taught to stoop to take up their riders ; but the riders often leapt up by the help of their spears, or were assisted by their slaves, or made use of ladders for the purpose. Gracchus furnished the highways with stones, which were intended to answer the same end. The same was also required of the surveyors of the roads in Greece, as part of their duty. Menage observes that St. Jerom is the first author who mentions stirrups. But the passage alluded to is not to be found in his epistles ; and if it were there, it would prove nothing, because St Jerom lived at a time when stirrups are supposed to have been invented, and after the use of saddles. Mont- faucon denies the genuineness of this passage ; and, in order to account for the ignorance of the ancients with regard to an instrument so useful and so easy of invention, he observes, that while cloths and housings only were laid upon the horses’ backs, on which the riders were to sit, stirrups could not have been used, because they could not have been fastened with the same security as upon a saddle. But it is more probable, that in this instance, as in many others, the</p></body></text></TEI>