<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-05-20T16:29:34Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>train Shandy, which procured him both money and reputation. In these volumes there was abundance of matter which every one could relish ; and what was unintelligible was thought profound. Much ingenious speculation was squandered upon the black leaves and marbled pages, which were long contemplated with wonder, before they were discovered to mean nothing. “ The republic of dark authors,” says Swift, “ have been peculiarly happy in the variety, as well as extent, of their reputation.”</p><p>Before this period, Sterne had only printed two sermons. The two volumes of Tristram Shandy were succeeded by two volumes of Sermons. In 1761 appeared the third and fourth volumes of the novel, and the fifth and sixth in the year following. The seventh and eighth volumes were published in 1765; but these monstrous births had by that time ceased to please. Four volumes of Sermons were produced in 1766 ; and in 1767, these were followed by the ninth and last volume of Tristram Shandy. In 1768 Sterne returned from Italy, whither he had repaired in the hopes of finding relief for a consumptive complaint with which he had long been afflicted. He only survived to prepare for the press the first part of his Sentimental Journey, which was published in 1768. In the month of March of that year he expired at his lodgings in Bond Street, surrounded by strangers ; a mode of death which he considered as most desirable.</p><p>The English writer to whom the author of Tristram Shandy is most indebted for his matter is Burton ; and his manner bears some resemblance to the capricious, whimsical, and digressive Tale of a Tub. He even mimics Swift in sneering at “ the great Dryden ;” but in the writings of his prototype he might have found many tilings infinitely more worthy of imitation. In order to make room for his pathos, however, he eschewed the misanthropy of the dean of St Patrick’s, and set up for a lover of his species, to which character his claims were less than equivocal, for his philanthropy did not extend so far as to his own mother. That sensibility is worthy only of ridicule that bestows a tear with greater promptitude than a shilling. For the irony of Swift, Sterne substituted buffoonery, which, in conformity with the opinion of Aristotle, the dean regarded as the less liberal species of pleasantry But the strongest objection to much of the satire in Tristram Shandy is, that the author threw away his ridicule upon pedantry that had become altogether obsolete.</p><p>It would be harsh justice to conclude, that the beauties of Sterne’s writings are drawn from some yet undiscovered source, because he is known to have had confused notions on the subject of literary honesty, and to tear the laurel from his brows, because some of its leaves are purloined from the tombs of the dead. “ Every man’s wit,” he says, “ must come from every man’s own soul, and no other body's.” That he had much wit of his own, there is reason as well as charity in supposing, although his propensity to make free with the wit of others may justify some suspicion on the subject, upon the principle that a rich man, who retains the use of his reason, is seldom guilty of theft. And it cannot be denied, that the world would be indebted to the writer who could produce such another tissue of reproductions, if such it is, as “ The Life and Opinions of Tristram Shandy, Gent.”</p><p>STERNOMANTIS, in <hi rend="italic">Antiquity,</hi> a designation given to the Delphian priestess, more usually called <hi rend="smallcaps">Pythia. </hi>Sternomantis is also used for any one that had a prophesying demon within him.</p><p>STERNUTATIVE, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Sternutatory,</hi> a medicine proper to produce sneezing.</p><p>STETTIN, one of the governments into which the Prussian province of Pomerania is divided. It extends over 4895 square miles, comprises forty cities and market-towns, and 1510 villages. It is divided into eleven circles. The inhabitants amounted in 1817 to 327,002, and in 1831 to 432,570 ; the whole of them adhering to the Lutheran church, with the exception of about 3000 Catholics and 1500 Jews. It has been formed out of the whole of the former province of Pomerania and the western part of Hither Pomerania. The capital is the city of the same name, situated on the left bank of the river Oder, from which it has a gradual ascent. It is a well-built city, but some of its streets are steep. It is strongly fortified, has a citadel, and a fine place of arms, and storehouses for munitions of war. From its position near the mouth of such a river, it has facilities for carrying on a very extensive commerce. The productions of foreign countries are conveyed from it to the cities of Kustrin, Frankfurt, Breslau, and even to Cracow ; and it is the best shipping port for the productions of the districts which surround those cities. The larger classes of vessels cannot ascend to Stettin, but are loaded or discharged by means of barges at the port of Swinemunde, near the discharge of the Fresh Haff into the Balric. It contains a fine old royal palace, a Gothic cathedral with two lofty towers, a gymnasium, to which belong an astronomical observatory, a library, and museums. It has considerable manufactories of linen and woollen goods, tobacco and snuff, several sugar refineries, tanneries, soapboilers’ works, and extensive breweries and distilleries. Many vessels are built at Stettin, and more than 200 are owned by the merchants of the city. About 800 ships yearly enter and clear out. The city, with the suburbs, contains 32,191 inhabitants, and the markets are well and cheaply supplied. Long. 14. 50. 25. E. Lat. 52. 25. 36. N.</p><p>STEVENAGE, a town of the hundred of Broadwater, in the county of Hertford, thirty-one miles from London. It formerly belonged to the abbot of Westminster. The church, which stands on a hill, is an ancient building, with a large square tower. There is a free grammar-school, and an endowed alms-house. This town has a market on Wednesday. The inhabitants amounted in 1801 to 1254, in 1811 to 1302, in 1821 to 1664, and in 1831 to 1859.</p><p>STEWARD <hi rend="italic">(senescallus,</hi> compounded of the Saxon <hi rend="italic">steda, i. e. “ room” or </hi>“ stead,” and <hi rend="italic">weard,</hi> “ a ward” or “ keeper”), an officer appointed in another’s stead or place, and always taken for a principal officer within his jurisdiction. Of these there are various kinds. The greatest officer under the crown is the lord high steward of England, whose office was anciently the inheritance of the earls of Leicester, till forfeited by Simon de Montfort to King Henry III. But the power of this officer is so very great, that it has not been judged safe to trust it any longer in the hands of a subject, excepting only for a particular occasion ; as to officiate at a coronation, or at the arraignment of a nobleman for high treason or felony. During his office, the steward bears a white staff in his hand ; and when the trial is ended, he breaks the staff, and with it his commission expires. There is likewise a lord steward of the king’s household, who is the chief officer of the king’s court, has the care of the king’s house, and authority over all the officers and servants of the household, except such as belong to the chapel, chamber, and stable.</p><p>The court of the lord high steward of Great Britain, is a court instituted for the trial of peers indicted for treason or felony, or for misprision of either. When such an indictment is found by a grand jury of freeholders in the king's bench, or at the assizes before the justices <hi rend="italic">of oyer</hi> and <hi rend="italic">terminer,</hi> it is to be removed by a writ of <hi rend="italic">certiorari</hi> into the court of the lord high steward, which has the only power to determine it. A peer may plead a pardon before the court of king’s bench, and the judges have power to allow it, in order to prevent the trouble of appointing a high steward merely for the purpose of receiving such plea; but he may not plead in that inferior court any other plea, as guilty or not guilty of the indictment, but only in this court ;</p></body></text></TEI>