<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-05-20T16:29:32Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>horseback, and even to write them, though he generally rode a very mettlesome steed. His Thesaurus was his great work, but he was also the author of many other treatises in the French and Latin languages. His poems are numerous. His “ Apologie pour Herodote” is a very singular performance. It has been illustrated by the annotations of Duchat. The number of books which he published, though fewer than his father, was great, and they were superior in elegance to any thing which the world had then seen. A great proportion of them were Greek. He was the editor, however, of many Latin and even of some oriental writings. His Greek classics are remarkably correct ; and many of his editions are accompanied by most learned notes. His Thesaurus still maintains an unrivalled reputation. An edition, with very ample additions, was recently published by Barker and Valpy ; and another elaborate edition is now in progress at Paris.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Paul Stephanus,</hi> the son of Henry, continued his father’s profession at Geneva. He was a man of learning, executed translations of several books, and published a considerable number of the ancient classics ; but his editions possess little of his father’s elegance. He died in 1627, at the age of sixty, after selling his types to one Chouet, a printer. His son Antony, the last printer of the family, abandoned the Protestant religion, and returned to France, the country of his ancestors. He received letters of naturalization in 1612, and was made printer to the king ; but managing his affairs ill, he was reduced to poverty, and obliged to retire into an hospital, where he died in 1674, miserable and blind, at the age of eighty.@@<hi rend="superscript">1</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Stephen’s Island,</hi> in Torres Strait, north of Darnley’s Island. Long. 143. E. Lat. 9. 0. S.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Stephen’s Islands,</hi> two small islands in the Eastern Seas, the one about three miles long, and the other about six. The passage between them is three miles broad. Long. 138. 39. E. Lat. 0. 22. S.</p><p>STEPNEY, a parish of the county of Middlesex, in the hundred of Ossulton, adjoining to London, and forming one of the suburbs, or rather a part of the metropolis. It was very extensive, and comprehended the districts on the side of the Thames, and extending till it united with Hackney, but has been divided into the distinct parishes of Stratford, Whitechapel, Limehouse, Wapping, Shadwell, Ratcliff Highway, Spitalfields, and Bethnal Green. It is commonly said by seamen, that all children born at sea are parishioners of Stepney, and that all the colonies of England are part and parcel of this parish, so as to make it the largest in the world. The population of the present division, containing four hamlets, Mile End Old Town, Mile End New Town, Poplar with Blackwall, and Ratcliff, amounted in 1801 to 25,260, in 1811 to 37,199, in 1821 to 49,163, and in 1831 to 67,872.</p><p>STERCORARIANS, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Stercoranistæ,</hi> formed from <hi rend="italic">stercus,</hi> “ dung,” a name which those of the Romish church anciently gave to such as held that the host was liable to digestion, and all its consequences, like other food.</p><p>STEREOGRAPHIC <hi rend="smallcaps">Projection,</hi> is the projection of the circles of the sphere on the plane of some one great circle, the eye being placed in the pole of that circle.</p><p>STEREOMETER, an instrument invented in France for measuring the volume of a body, however irregular, without plunging it in any liquid.</p><p>STEREOMETRY, Σ<hi rend="italic">τεϑεομετϑια</hi>, formed of <hi rend="italic">οτεϑος, solid, </hi>and <hi rend="italic">μετϑοv, measure,</hi> that part of geometry which teaches how to measure solid bodies, s. <hi rend="italic">e.</hi> to find the solidity or solid contents of bodies ; as globes, cylinders, cubes, vessels, ships, &amp;c.</p><p>STEREOTOMY, formed from <hi rend="italic">σετϑεος</hi> and <hi rend="italic">τομη, section, </hi>the art or act of cutting solids, or making sections thereof; as walls and other membranes in the profiles of architecture.</p><p>STEREOTYPE <hi rend="smallcaps">Printing,</hi> a method of printing, which was introduced into this country by William Ged of Edinburgh, before the middle of the eighteenth century. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Printing.</hi></p><p>STERLING, an epithet by which genuine English money is distinguished. It is unnecessary to mention the various conjectures of antiquaries about the origin and meaning of this appellation. The most probable opinion seems to be this, that some artists from Germany, who were called <hi rend="italic">Esterlings,</hi> from the situation of their country, had been employed in fabricating our money, which consisted chiefly of silver pennies ; and that from them the penny was called an <hi rend="italic">esterling,</hi> and our money <hi rend="italic">esterling</hi> or <hi rend="italic">sterling</hi> money.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Stern</hi>, the posterior part of a ship. The stern is terminated above by the taffarel, and below by the counters ; it is limited on the sides by the quarter-pieces, and the intermediate space comprehends the galleries and windows of the different cabins.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Stern-East,</hi> a rope used to confine the stern of a ship or boat to any wharf or jetty head, &amp;c.</p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Stern</hi><hi rend="italic">-Most,</hi> in sea language, usually denotes that part of a fleet of ships which is in the rear, or farthest a-stern, as opposed to headmost.</p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Stern-</hi><hi rend="italic">Post, </hi>a long straight piece of timber erected on the extremity of the keel, to sustain the rudder and terminate the ship behind.</p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Stern-</hi><hi rend="italic">Sheets,</hi> that part of a boat which is contained between the stern and the aftmost or hindmost seat of the rowers. It is generally furnished with benches to accommodate the passengers.</p><p>STERNE, <hi rend="smallcaps">Laurence,</hi> an eccentric writer of fiction, has left behind him a sketch of the principal events of his life, and some particulars of his family history. From that outline it appears that he was born at Clonmell, in the south of Ireland, on the 24th November 1713. His father was a lieutenant in the army, and grandson of Dr Richard Sterne, archbishop of York. When his son was about eight years of age, Lieutenant Sterne placed him at a school in Halifax, to which town he had been conducted by his professional duties. That officer died in 1731, and in the following year, young Sterne, by the bounty of a relation and namesake of his own, was transferred from the school of Halifax to Jesus College, Cambridge.</p><p>Having completed his studies at the university, he proceeded to York ; and his uncle, Dr Jacques Sterne, prebendary of Durham, and canon residentiary and precentor of York, procured him the living of Sutton, and afterwards a prebend at York. At York he formed an acquaintance with the lady who afterwards became his wife, under circumstances sufficiently romantic. From a friend of hers he obtained the living of Stillington, but continued for twenty years to reside at Sutton, relieving the burden of his double charge, as he informs us, “ by books, painting, fiddling, and shooting.” In the library of Shelton Castle, the residence of his friend and relation, John Hall Stevenson, author of a licentious production, entitled Crazy Tales, Sterne found among the dross of antiquity many a brilliant gem, which he transferred without scruple to his own pages. In this stolen garb he cut a most imposing figure, until Dr Ferriar of Manchester, twenty years after the death of the celebrated plagiary, restored the pilfered trappings to the rightful owners.@@’</p><p>In 1759, Sterne produced tbe first two volumes of Tris-</p><p><hi rend="superscript">@@@1</hi> Almeloveen de Vitis Stephanorum Amst. 1683, 8vo. Maktaire, Historia Stephanorum. Loud. 1709, 8vo. Biographie Universelle, tom. xiii. p. 380.</p><p>@@@s See Dr Ferriar's Illustrations of Sterne. Lond. 1798, 8vo.</p></body></text></TEI>