<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-05-20T16:31:29Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>twelve in breadth. Long. 125. 27. to 128. 30. E. Lat. 9. 24. to 10. 32. N. The largest, from which the others derive their name, is twenty miles in circumference, and is twenty miles north-north-east from the coast of Mindanao. Long. 126. 27. E. Lat. 9. 27. N. There is a town of the same name on the north coast of the island of Mindanao. Long. 125. 31. E. Lat. 9. 45. N.</p><p>SULLY, <hi rend="smallcaps">Maximilien de Bethune,</hi> Duke of, was born at Rosny on the 13th of December 1560, and died at Villebon on the 22d of December 1640. His name is so conspicuous in the public annals of France, that a mere outline of his personal history would require an ample allotment of space. He participated in the fortunes of Henry IV. and rendered him the most important services in the cabinet as well as the field. He was grand master of the artillery, and superintendent of the finances. Rigidly attentive to the interest of the king, he had no disposition to neglect his own ; and in the course of a long life he accumulated an immense fortune, of which he laid the foundation by his marriage with Anne de Courtenay, a rich heiress. He was remarkable for his decision of character and bluntness of manners ; and in spite of all the allurements presented to him, he steadily adhered to the protestant faith. The Memoirs of Sully furnish some of the most curious and valuable materials for the history of that eventful era.</p><p>SULPHUR <hi rend="smallcaps">Island,</hi> an island in the North Pacific Ocean, discovered by Captain Gore in 1779, about five miles long. Long. 141. 12. E. Lat. 24. 48. N.</p><p>SULPICIA, a Roman poetess, who lived under the reign of Domitian, and has been so much admired as to be termed the Roman Sappho. We have nothing, however, left of her writings but a satire, or rather the fragment of one, against Domitian, who published a decree for the banishment of philosophers from Rome. This satire is to be found in Scaliger’s <hi rend="italic">Appendix Virgiliana,</hi> and in other collections. It was separately published, with elaborate annotations by C. G. Schwartz. Altorf. 1721, 8vo. Harab. 1819, 4to. She is mentioned by Martial and Sidonius Apollinaris; and is said to have addressed a poem on conjugal love to her husband Calenus, a Roman knight.</p><p>SULPITIUS <hi rend="smallcaps">Severus,</hi> an ecclesiastical writer, was born in Aquitania about the year 363. His father was a man of superior rank. Having received a suitable education, the son applied himself to the practice of the law, and distinguished himself by his learning and eloquence. He married a rich wife, and was thus placed in a state of greater independence. He chiefly resided at Toulouse, and at <hi rend="italic">Eluso</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Elusio,</hi> near Carcassonne. The death of his beloved wife weaned his affections from the world, and he is supposed to have devoted himself to an ecclesiastical, if not a monastic life. He had recourse to the instructions of Martin bishop of Tours, whose life he has written ; and he likewise contracted a friendship with Paulinus bishop of Nola. The invasion of the Vandals impelled him to seek a place of refuge at Marseille, where he entered a monastery, and is supposed to have died about the year 410. His principal work is his <hi rend="italic">Historia Sacra,</hi> deduced from the creation of the world to his own time, and written in a style superior to the standard of that declining age of Lati- nity. The first edition was published by Flacius Illyricus. Basil. [1556] 8vo. Various editions of his works subsequently appeared ; some of which were illustrated by the notes of Sigonius, Vorstius, Horn, and Le Clerc. A more elaborate edition was undertaken by De Prato, Ve- ronæ, 1741—54, 2 tom. 4to. He promised a third volume, which however did not make its appearance.</p><p>SULTAN, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Soldan,</hi> a title or appellation given to the emperor of the Turks.</p><p>SULTANHISSAR, a village of Anatolia, in Asiatic Turkey, situated near the remains of the ancient Greek city of Tralles, and twenty-three miles east of Scalanova. On</p><p>the top of an adjacent hill are found traces of some ancient buildings, particularly a temple and a theatre, with fifty rows of seats. Some remains of a magnificent portico are also seen, with two rows of pillars.</p><p>SULTANPORE, a town of Hindustan, province of Lahore, belonging to the Sikhs. Long. 74. 45. E. Lat. 31. 18. N. 2. A town in the province of Oude, pleasantly situated on the eastern bank of the Goompty river, seventy-eight miles south east from Lucknow. Long. 82. 3. E. Lat. 26. 18. N. 3. A town in the Afghan territories, province of Mooltan, twenty miles east from the city of Mool- tan. Long. 71. 40. E. Lat. 30. 38. N. 4. A town in the Mahratta territories, province of Khandesh, on the north side of the Tuptee river, ninety miles east by north from Surat. Long. 74. 22. E. Lat. 21. 35. N.</p><p>SULZER, <hi rend="smallcaps">John George,</hi> a philosophical writer of distinction, was born at Winterthur, in the canton of Zurich, on the 16th of October 1720. He was the youngest of twenty-five children. At the age of sixteen, when he went to the university of Zürich, he had not the smallest notion of the sciences or of elegant literature, and consequently no taste for study. The first incident that developed a hidden germ of philosophical genius, was his meeting with Wolf’s Metaphysics. This was the birth of his taste for science ; but he wanted a guide. The clergyman with whom he lodged was an ignorant man ; and the academical prelections were, as yet, above the reach of his comprehension. On the other hand, a sedentary life was not suitable to his taste ; and a sociable turn of mind often led him into company, where he lost much time in frivolous amusements, yet without corrupting his morals. Who, that observed him at this period, says Mr Formey in his Eloge, would have thought that Sulzer would one day be numbered among the most knowing and wise men of his time? John Gessner, who became an eminent naturalist, was the instrument of Providence that rendered Sulzer’s inclination to study triumphant over his passion for amusement and company. Animated by the counsels and example of this fellow-student, he applied himself to philosophy and mathematics with great ardour, and resumed the pursuit of Greek literature and the oriental languages. He was settled as a pastor in a rural district. In 1741 he published Moral Contemplations on the Works of Nature ; and in the following year an Account of a Journey through the Alps, which showed at the same time his knowledge of natural history, and the taste and sensibility with which he surveyed the beauties of nature, and the grandeur and goodness of its Author. He afterwards became private tutor to a young gentleman at Magdeburg. This procured him the acquaintance of Euler, Maupertuis, and Sack, which opened to his merit the path of preferment, and advanced him successively to the place of mathematical professor in the Gymnasium of Berlin in 1747, and to that of member of the Royal Academy in 1750. In this last quality he distinguished himself in a very eminent manner, enriched the class of speculative philosophy with a great number of excellent memoirs, and was justly considered as one of the first-rate metaphysicians in Germany. But his genius was not confined to th is branch of science. His universal Theory of the Fine Arts is a valuable production. A profound knowledge of the arts and sciences, and a perfect acquaintance with true taste, are eminently displayed in this work, and will secure to its author a permanent and distinguished rank in the re public of letters. The first volume of this excellent work was published in 1771, and the second in 1774. His Remarks on the Philosophical Essays of Hume is a work of real merit, which does justice to the acuteness, while it often detects the sophistry, of the Scotish philosopher. The moral character of Sulzer was amiable and virtuous : sociability and beneficence were its characteristical lines; and his virtues were animated by that sacred philosophy which</p></body></text></TEI>