<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T17:43:17Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>SUAKIN. a seaport town of Nubia, situated on the western coast of the Red Sea, was formerly a place of great wealth and importance, but has long been in a declining state, and is now almost in ruins. Snakin looks better when seen at a distance than on a nearer view ; the buildings all white-washed and on an elevated site, and two minarets, giving the town a handsome appearance. Like all the towns in the east, it has narrow and dirty streets. All that remains of its former grandeur is its capacious port, which is capable of containing 200 large vessels, that can anchor close to the island in seven fathoms water ; but is so narrow at the mouth as to render an entrance impracticable, except with the most favourable wind. It is rather remarkable that this narrow passage should have so long remained open, considering the clouds of sand which are borne toward it at one season, and the action of the sea continually breaking over it, after having passed over sandbanks. The Turks obtained possession of Suakin at the same time that they occupied the opposite coast of Arabia. In the fifteenth century Suakin was a place of great importance and wealth, the emporium of the Red Sea, and one of the richest cities in the east. It derived its importance from its being in the middle ages the maritime capital of the Turks in the Red Sen, when that empire maintained there a powerful navy. Suakin has declined along with the Turkish power ; and its only support is now derived from its being the channel of communication between Arabia and the interior of Africa. Pilgrims and slave-dealers, or persons who combine these two vocations, quit the Nile at Shendi, and proceed through Taka and other districts of Nubia to this port, where they embark for Jidda. They carry with them slaves, with a little ivory and gold, and take Indian goods in return. The surrounding country is arid and barren, and produces no grain except that coarse species called dhonrra nr juwarry. There is abundance of good water, which is preserved in wells and tanks. Fish are cheap and plentiful, and the mullets are particularly fine. Sheep are cheap, and do not cost above a dollar each. But fowls are scarce and dear. The country around, and the coast to a considerable extent, is occupied by a hardy race of Bedouin Arabs, called Suakini. Suakin is supposed to be the Soter Limen of Diodorus, the Theon Scter of Ptolemy ; though it is not easy to conceive how these terms, signifying “ the safe harbour,” could apply to one of such difficult entrance. Long. 37. 33. E. Lat. 19. 48. N.</p><p>SUΛN, a small town of Hindustan, in the province of Bahar, district of Rotas. It is twenty-five miles south-east from Patna. Long. 86. 25. E. Lat. 25. 16. N.</p><p>SUAREZ, <hi rend="smallcaps">Francis,</hi> a renowned Jesuit, was born at Grenada on the 5th of January 1548. He belonged to a noble family, and was sent to prosecute the study of law in the university of Salamanca ; but when he had finished his course, he was induced to change his destination, and assume the habit of St Ignatius. He at first experienced much difficulty in comprehending the principles of the philosophy which was then taught ; but having been placed under the guidance of Rodriguez, he soon began to be distinguished by the uncommon rapidity of his progress, and became one of the most distinguished members of the society. Having taught philosophy at Segovia, he was afterwards employed in teaching theology at Valladolid, Rome, Alcala, and Salamanca. Wherever he taught, his lectures attracted a numerous auditory. He was at length appointed to the first chair of divinity in the university of Coimbra; but before entering upon his office, he went to Evora, and took his doctor’s degree. Here his reputation continued to increase. At the instigation of the pope, he prepared an elaborate work, entitled “ Defensio Catholics Fidei contra Anglicanæ Sectæ Errores.” Conimbricæ, 1613, fol. This work gave much offence to King James, and was burnt at St Paul’s by the hands of the hangman. Nor did it receive better treatment from the parliament of Paris ; who, by an <hi rend="italic">arrêt</hi> pronounced on the 26th of June 1614, condemned it to the flames, as containing maxims contrary to the rights of sovereigns. It was ably refuted by Robert Abbot, afterwards bishop of Salisbury. Suarez, having been called to Lisbon for some weighty conference, died there on the 25th of September 1617. An instant before he expired, he said to those who surrounded his bed, “ I never knew it was so pleasant to die.”</p><p>Suarez was a great master of the scholastic philosophy and theology of his age, nor was he a mean or ordinary proficient in jurisprudence. Grotius has described him as the most acute of philosophers and divines. His treatise “ De Legibus et Deo Legislatore,” is commended by Sir James Mackintosh, “ as exhibiting the most accessible and perspicuous abridgment of the theological philosophy in its latest form.” According to the same competent authority, “ he first saw that international law was composed, not only of the simple principles of justice applied to the intercourse between states, but of those usages, long observed in that intercourse by the European race, which have since been more exactly distinguished as the consuetudinary law acknowledged by the Christian nations of Europe and America.” Of this learned Jesuit, the works are very numerous. An edition of them in twenty-three vols. fol. began to be published at Maintz and Lyon in the year 1630. An edition was published at Venice in the year 1740.	(x.)</p><p>SUBAH, the general name of the viceroyships, or greater governments, into which the Mogul empire was divided, consisting of several provinces : the jurisdiction of a sub- ahdar, the same as subahship, subaedaree, or nizamut.</p><p>SUBAHDAR, the viceroy, lord-lieutenant, or governor, holding a subah ; the same as nabob or nazim. Also the black commander of a company of sepoys.</p><p>SUBALTERN, a subordinate officer, or one who discharges his post under the command and subject to the direction of another; stich are lieutenants, sub-lieutenants, cornets, and ensigns, who serve under the captain.</p><p>SUBARKAN, a village of Diarbekir, in Asiatic Turkey, on the Euphrates, seventy-five miles east-south-east of Ker- kesieh.</p><p>SUBBULGUR, a town of Hindustan, in the province of Agra. It is surrounded by a high stone wall in good repair, with a number of bastions ; but has few cannon mounted. On one side of the fort is a deep precipice. The country in the vicinity is well cultivated. It is sixty-five miles south-west from the city of Agra. Long. 75. 25. E. Lat. 26. 22. N. There is another town of the same name in the province of Delhi, situated on the east side of the Ganges. The town is surrounded by a very extensive line of fortification, though it exhibits as well as the walls, little more than falling ruins. The town is improving since it came under British authority. It is twelve miles south from Hurdwar. Long. 78. 10. E. Lat. 29. 48. N.</p><p>SUBDEACON, an inferior minister, who anciently attended at the altar, prepared the sacred vessels, delivered them to the deacons in time of divine service, attended the doors of the church during communion service, and went on the bishop’s embassies with his letters or messages to foreign churches. They were so subordinate to the superior rulers of the church, that, by a canon of the council of Laodicea, they were forbidden to sit in the presence of a deacon without his leave. According to the canon law, a person must be twenty-two years of age to be promoted to the order of sub-deacon.</p><p>SUBDOMINANT, in <hi rend="italic">Music.</hi> See Music.</p><p>SUBDUPLE <hi rend="smallcaps">Ratio</hi> is when any number or quantity is contained in another twice. Thus 3 is said to be subduple of 6 as 6 is duple of 3.</p><p>SUBDUPLICATE <hi rend="smallcaps">Ratio</hi> of any two quantities, is the ratio of their square roots.</p></body></text></TEI>