<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-05-20T16:30:58Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>experiments encouraged us to extend them much farther. We hoped by these means to discover the absolute cohesion of many substances, which would have required an enormous apparatus and a most unmanageable force to tear them asunder directly. But we could reason with confidence from the resistance to twist (which we could easily measure), provided that we could ascertain the proportion of the direct and the lateral strengths. Our experiments on chalk, finely prepared clay, and white bee’s wax (of one melting and one temperature), were very consistent and satisfactory. But we have hitherto found great irregularities in this proportion in bodies of a fibrous texture like timber. These are the most important cases, and we still hope to be able to accomplish our project, and to give the public some valuable information. This being our sole object, it was our duty to mention the method which promises success, and thus excite others to the task ; and it will be no mortification to us to be deprived of the honour of being the first who thus adds to the stock of experimental knowledge.</p><p>When the matter of the axle is of the most simple texture, such as that of metals, we do not conceive that the length of the axle has any influence on the fracture. It is otherwise if it be of a fibrous texture like timber; the fibres are bent before breaking, being twisted into spirals like a cork-screw. The length of the axle has somewhat of the influence of a lever in this case, and it is easier wrenched asunder if long. Accordingly we have found it so ; but we have not been able to reduce this influence to calculation.</p><p>Many useful deductions might be made from these premises respecting the manner of disposing and combining the strength of materials in our structures. The best form of joints, mortises, tenons, scarphs, the rules for joggling, tabling, faying, fishing, &amp;c. practised in the delicate art of mast-making, arc all founded on this doctrine; but the discussion of these would be equivalent to writing a complete treatise of carpentry.	<hi rend="smallcaps">(b. b. b.)</hi></p><p>The most recent experiments on the strength and elasticity of material give the results entered in the following tables.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Table</hi> I.—<hi rend="italic">Distensions of Pods for a Strain of one Pound per Square Inch ; computed from the results given in Tredgold, edition of</hi> 1840, <hi rend="italic">as deduced from observations on transverse strain.</hi></p><p>British timber......{Oak		........<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">22000</hi></p><p>Larch............................<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">36000</hi></p><p>Scotch fir	<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">80000</hi></p><p>Ash	<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">120000</hi></p><p>Memel fir	<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">75000</hi></p><p>Norway fir	<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">109000</hi></p><p>American pine.............<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">50000</hi></p><p>White spruce................<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">92000</hi></p><p>Riga oak	<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">100000</hi></p><p>American oak	<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">100000</hi></p><p>English malleable iron	<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">24200000</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Table</hi> II.—<hi rend="italic">Cohesive Strengths of Bars per Square Inch.</hi></p><p>lbs.	lbs.</p><p>Oak	from	14,000	to	 19,000</p><p>Beech	from	11,000	to	 22,000</p><p>Ash	from	12,000	to	 17,000</p><p>Elm	from	13,000	to	14,000</p><p>Mahogany	from	8,000	to	 21,000</p><p>Teak	from	8,000	to	 15,000</p><p>Pine (Norway)	from	7,000	to	 14,000</p><p>Larch	  from	9,000	to	 10,000</p><p>Iron wire	from	94,000	to	 113,000</p><p>Swedish iron	from	53,000	to	 78,000</p><p>English iron	from	55,000	to	 66,000</p><p>Cast iron	from	16,000	to	 33,000</p><p>STRETCHING, in <hi rend="italic">Navigation,</hi> is generally understood to imply the progression of a ship under a great surface of sail, when close-hauled.</p><p>STRETTA (Ital.), a musical term, often applied to the last allegro of a finale, &amp;c. in an opera. It signifies also a kind of peroration or winding up of a piece of music, particularly of a fugue. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Music</hi>.</p><p>STRETTO, or <hi rend="italic">più Stretto</hi> (Ital.), indicates an acceleration of the time of a piece of music.</p><p>STRIATED <hi rend="smallcaps">Leaf, </hi>among botanists, one that has a number of longitudinal furrows on its surface.</p><p>STRIKE, a measure of capacity, containing four bushels. Also an instrument used in measuring corn.</p><p>STROMBOLI, the most northern island of the Lipari group, in the Mediterranean, being a part of the kingdom of Naples. It was known to the ancients by the name of Strongyle ; a name implying a conical mountain with an irregular base. The mountain is bifurcated, upwards of 2000 feet in height, and about nine miles in circumference, and is evidently a monstrous product of subterraneous fires. The crater of this mountain is on the north-west side, about two thirds of the whole height from the base ; it is of a circular form, and about one hundred and seventy yards in diameter, and has a yellow efflorescence adhering to its sides, as to those of Mount Ætna. This crater has burnt without intermission from the earliest periods, and is supposed to be supported by oxygen, pyrites, and sulphur ; but there are not any traces of the aid of bitumen. It appears to be not only the vent of all these islands, but likewise to have subterraneous communication with Sicily and Italy ; for, previously to a severe earthquake taking place in those parts, Stromboli has been observed to be covered with dense clouds of smoke, and to emit with increased activity unusually ardent</p><p>flames. The access to the summit, though fatiguing, is not dangerous. When a person approaches the crater, and the smoke clears away, as it does at intervals, he can observe an undulating igneous substance, which at short periods rises and falls with great agitation, and when swollen to the utmost height bursts with a violent explosion and a discharge of red-hot stones in a semi-fluid state, accompanied with showers of ashes, and a strong sulphureous smell. These masses are thrown up to the height of from sixty or seventy to three hundred feet, and some few even to a thousand. In the moderate ejections the stones in their ascent gradually diverge like a grand pyrotechnical exhibition, and fall again into the abyss, except on the side next the sea, where they roll down in quick succession to the water.</p><p>The island contains about 1200 inhabitants. The principal places are St Bartolo and St Vincenzo. The soil is a black mold, very fertile, consisting of argilaceous tufa, scoriæ, puzzolana, and sand. Stromboli produces some good wine, with excellent wheat, barley, cotton, rasins, currants, and figs. The church of St Bartolo is in long. 15. 13. 10. E., and lat. 38. 48. 12. N.</p><p>STROMNESS, a town in the parish of the same name in the island of Pomona, Orkney, in long. 3. 38. W. and lat. 58. 58. N. The town is situated on the western side of the island, and was formerly an insignificant village, dependent on the borough of Kirkwall, which kept it completely under; but by a decision of the House of Lords, Stromness and all other villages were declared free from being assessed, and otherwise independent of royal boroughs. The present town consists of one long rambling street, built round the bay on which it is placed. The greater portion of the houses are built so close on the water that they require to be defended by bulwarks, jetties, and quays, to keep them from being overwhelmed by</p></body></text></TEI>