<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T17:41:39Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>be followed ; as Mr for Master, Μ. D. for Doctor of Physic, and Abp. for Archbishop, &amp;c.</p><p>2.	Substantives, adjectives, verbs, and participles are to be expressed by their initial consonant with distinguishing marks, viz. a substantive must have a dot exactly over its initial consonant ; an adjective must have a dot under it ; a verb is to be expressed by a comma over its initial consonant ; and a participle by a comma under.@@<hi rend="superscript">1</hi> These, being the four principal parts of speech, will be sufficient ; and an adept will never be at a loss to know when he can with safety apply this rule to them.</p><p>3.	To render the writing more legible, the last letter of the word may be joined to the first, and the proper mark applied.</p><p>4.	The constituent or radical part of words, especially if they are long, will often serve for the whole or sometimes the first syllable : as we ought to moderate our <hi rend="italic">ex.</hi> by our <hi rend="italic">circum.;</hi> a man’s <hi rend="italic">man.</hi> commonly shape his <hi rend="italic">for.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">5.</hi>	All long words without exception may have their prepositions or terminations expressed by the incipient consonant of such preposition or termination.</p><p>6.	When there is a great dependence between the parts of a sentence, the initial letter will often suffice ; as <hi rend="italic">L.</hi> is the capital of Great <hi rend="italic">B. ;</hi> the eldest <hi rend="italic">S.</hi> of the king of Great <hi rend="italic">B.</hi> is styled prince of <hi rend="italic">W.</hi> Every one, it is presumed, will allow this to be perfectly legible in long-hand ; then why may it not in stenography ?</p><p>7.	The terminations <hi rend="italic">ness</hi> and <hi rend="italic">less</hi> may be omitted ; as <hi rend="italic">faithfulness</hi> is only to be written <hi rend="italic">faithful; forwardness, forward; heedless, heed; stubbornness, stubborn, &amp;c.</hi></p><p>8.	The second and third persons of verbs, ending in <hi rend="italic">eth </hi>and <hi rend="italic">est,</hi> may be expressed by <hi rend="italic">s ;</hi> as, he <hi rend="italic">loves,</hi> thou <hi rend="italic">teaches ; </hi>instead of he <hi rend="italic">loveth,</hi> thou <hi rend="italic">teachest:</hi> or even without <hi rend="italic">s;</hi> as, he <hi rend="italic">love,</hi> &amp;c.</p><p>9.	Words may often be entirely omitted, and yet no ambiguity ensue ; as, <hi rend="italic">In beginning God created heaven and earth,</hi> fo? In <hi rend="italic">the</hi> beginning God created <hi rend="italic">the</hi> heaven and <hi rend="italic">the </hi>earth.</p><p>10.	When there is an immediate repetition of a sentence or word, a line is to be drawn under the sentence or word to be repeated ; as, Λmen, Amen, is to be written <hi rend="italic">Amen; </hi>but if any words intervene before a word or sentence is to be repeated, the line must be drawn as before, and a Λ or mark of omission placed where the repetition should begin ; as, <hi rend="italic">Is it just the innocent should be</hi> condemned Λ reviled ?</p><p>STENTOROPHONIC <hi rend="smallcaps">Tube,</hi> a speaking trumpet; thus called from Stentor, a person mentioned by Homer.</p><p>STEP, in a ship, a block of wood fixed on the decks or bottom of a ship, and having a hole in its upper side, fitted to receive the heel of a mast or capstern. The steps of the main and fore masts of every ship rest upon the kelson, to which they are firmly secured by knees, bolts, or spikenails. The step of the mizen-mast usually rests upon the lower deck.</p><p>STEPHANO, <hi rend="smallcaps">St,</hi> a city of the province of Mazzara, in the island of Sicily. It stands on the sea-shore, in a situation rather unhealthy, on the declivity of Mount Quisquina, and at the distance of forty-eight miles from Palermo. It contains about 6000 inhabitants.</p><p>STEPHANOPHORUS, in <hi rend="italic">Antiquity,</hi> the chief priest of Pallas, who presided over the rest It was usual for every god to have a chief priest ; that of Pallas was the Stephanophorus, and that of Hercules was called Dadouchus. Stephanophorus was also a priest who assisted the women in the celebration of the festival Thesmophoria.</p><p>STEPHANUS <hi rend="smallcaps">Byzantinus,</hi> a learned grammarian, who flourished about the close of the fifth century. He wrote a large work, in which he made a great number of observations, borrowed from mythology and history, which showed the origin of cities and colonies ; of which we have little remaining but an abridgement by Hermolaus the grammarian. Even in this state, it has been found a work of no inconsiderable value. It is alphabetically arranged, and bears the inscription <hi rend="italic">∏εϑl ∏0όλεωv, or</hi> “ Concerning Cities.” The first edition was printed by Aldus, Venet. 1502, fol. This was followed by an edition printed by the heirs of P. Junta, Florent. 1521, fol. The text received many emendations in the edition of Xylander, Basil. 1568, fol. All these editions contain the Greek text, without any Latin version. An edition, with a translation, and copious annotations, was published by Thomas de Pinedo, Amst. 1678, fol. Another edition, with a translation and a commentary, was prepared by Berkelius, and after his death was completed by J. Gronovius, Lugd. Bat. 1688, fol. Nor must we here omit the posthumous “ Notæ et Castigationes” of Holstenius, Lugd. Bat. 1684, fol.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Stephanus, </hi><hi rend="italic">Henry,</hi> the founder of a most remarkable and meritorious family of printers, was born at Paris in the year 1470. The French name is Estienne, which is frequently transformed into the English <hi rend="italic">Stephens,</hi> although the correct translation would be <hi rend="italic">Stephen.</hi> He began the business of a printer about the year 1503. This is the date of Boethius’s treatise on arithmetic, the first book that is known to have issued from his press. A great proportion of the books which he published were Latin. They are printed in the Roman letter, and are not inelegant, though some of them abound rather too much in contractions. He died about the year 1520, and left behind him three sons, Francis, Robert, and Charles. His widow married Simeon de Colines <hi rend="italic">(Colinceus</hi> in Latin), who thus got possession of Henry’s printing-office, and continued the business till his death.</p><p>Of Francis, the eldest son, little more is known than that he carried on business along with Colinæus, and that he died at Paris in 1550.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Robert Stephanus,</hi> the second son, was born at Paris in 1503. In his youth he made great proficiency in the Latin, Greek, and Hebrew languages, and at the age of nineteen had acquired so much knowledge that his step-father intrusted him with the management of his press. He soon afterwards began business himself, and married Perrete, the daughter of Jodocus Badius, a printer and an author. She was a woman of learning, and understood Latin, which indeed was the necessary consequence of her situation. Her husband always entertained a number of learned men as correctors of the press. Being foreigners, and of different nations, they made use of no other language but Latin ; which Perrete being accustomed to hear, was able in a short time not only to understand, but even to speak with tolerable ease.</p><p>In 1531 he published his “ Thesaurus Linguæ Latins ;” a work of great labour, and of great value. The device which he exhibited in all his books was a tree branched, with a man looking upon it, and these words <hi rend="italic">Noli altum sapere,</hi> to which he sometimes added <hi rend="italic">sed time.</hi> In 1539, Francis I. made him his printer, and ordered a new set of elegant types to be founded for him. His frequent editions of the New Testament gave great offence to the doctors of the Sorbonne, who accused him of heresy for his annotations, and insisted upon the suppression of some of his books. Although Henry, the French king, in some measure protected him, the persecution of these divines rendered him so unhappy, not to mention the expense and loss of time which an almost constant attendance at court unavoidably occasioned, that in 1552 he abandoned his country and settled</p><p><hi rend="superscript">@@@1</hi> The dot or comma being placed thus will never occasion them to be mistaken for vowels, because they should always be on one side or other ; whereas the mark for parts of speech may constantly be placed exactly over or under.</p></body></text></TEI>