<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T17:44:20Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>yoke of authority, and digested by genius of a high order, have rendered him immortal. His works, first published in 1535, and afterwards more fully in 1682, exerted a most powerful and beneficial influence upon his profession. The influence was not however immediate ; for at his death the light he had shed was for a time obscured, surgery reverting to the state of degradation in which he found it, in consequence of its baneful association with barberism. Pigrai was his successor, but an unworthy one : endeavouring to follow the footsteps of his master, he obscured and almost effaced them. The most interesting of Pare’s surgical treatises is that on gunshot wounds, a class of injuries then of recent introduction, and little understood : the murderous cannon and firelock had not long been in use.</p><p>In the seventeenth century surgery again revived, resuming the impulse which the genius of Paré had imparted. Italy produced Cæsar Magatus, who simplified, and consequently must have improved, the treatment of wounds ; the never-to-be-forgotten Tagliacotius, with his rude repairs of the human face ; and Marcus Aurelius Severinus, a skilful and intrepid operator. At the end of the sixteenth and beginning of the seventeenth centuries, Padua was favoured with Fabricius ab Aquapendente, the preceptor of Harvey, a most distinguished physiologist, and the most eminent surgeon of his time. His <hi rend="italic">Opera Chirurgica</hi> passed through no less than seventeen editions, and contain not only an excellent digest of surgery as it then was, but also many improvements of his own. About the middle of the seventeenth century arose the true father of British surgery, our own Wiseman, the Paré of England. One or two English names are to be found before him : William Clowes, a military surgeon of some eminence, attended the Earl of Leicester’s army in the Low Countries, and wrote on gunshot wounds ; and Lowe, a Scotchman, gave to the world a Discourse on the whole Art of Chirurgery, dated 1612: but Wiseman doubtless is the first Briton worthy of note in surgery. He was serjeant-surgeon to Charles II., and amidst the horrors of the civil wars had ample scope for the study of his profession. His surgical works, consisting of eight treatises, dated 1676, contain much information, at that time most valuable, and still amply rewarding an attentive perusal. In military practice he strongly advocated immediate amputation, “ while the patient is free of fever,” in the case of such injuries as rendered preservation of the member improbable, of course allowing the primary shock of the accident to be past ; a point of practice which long discussion in after years served to confirm. It was not till his time that surgeons ceased to believe that gunshot wounds were necessarily envenomed by the powder and ball, and had to be treated accordingly with potent and cruel dressings. The immortal Harvey, contemporary with Wiseman, cannot perhaps be classed among the eminent surgeons, having principally confined himself to anatomy and physiology, yet he is inseparably connected with that science by his discovery of the circulation of the blood ; a discovery which has done so much for the advancement of all medical knowledge, but of surgery in particular. James Young, a surgeon in Plymouth, may be said to have been also contemporary with Wiseman, having written in 1679. He is the first who proposed amputation by a flap, an improvement to which two French surgeons, Verduin and Sabaurin, lay claim ; and he is also the first who recommends limited compression of the main artery in amputation.</p><p>Germany boasts of several eminent surgeons of this time ; Fabricius Hildanus, a most successful practitioner, and author of a surgical treatise dated 1641 ; Scultetus, author of the work, celebrated for its horrid array of lethal weapons, called <hi rend="italic">Armamentarium chirurgicum,</hi> 1653 ; and Purmann, who displayed too great an attachment to the dangerous representations of Scultetus. Heister, a professor in the university of Helmstadt, wrote a system of surgery, which has been translated into most of the European languages, and is still in high repute.</p><p>Holland likewise possessed successful practitioners of surgery, but tainted with an unworthy concealment of their methods of cure. Rau, a native of Germany, though a professor at Leyden, was perhaps the most successful litho- tomist that ever lived, but he kept his method of operating a profound secret, and made it a mystery even to his own pupils; as appears from the circumstance that his two favourites, Heister and Albinus, of a more liberal spirit than their master, in attempting to divulge his secret for the benefit of the profession at large, have varied most materially in their statements. This illiberal spirit pervaded the other branches of medicine as well as the surgical. The famous anatomist Ruysch preserved inviolate the secret of his wonderfully minute injections, although really the discovery of his friend De Graaf ; and Roonhuysen the accoucheur worked stealthily with his invented lever. The succeeding generation however removed this stigma from the Dutch ; and their great Camper was equally celebrated for the number of his discoveries and the zeal with which he made them known.</p><p>From the time of Paré, France produced no surgeons of great eminence until the eighteenth century. In the seventeenth, we find the names of Dionis, Belloste, Saviard, and a few others of some renown, but not at all equal to their contemporaries in other nations. Some idea may be formed of the then feeble condition of surgery in France, from the fact, that Louis XIV. was not cured of a simple fistula in ano, until after his life had been in no small degree endangered by repeated abortive operations. That the French can boast of surgeons of the first class in the next century, however, is indisputably shown by the simple mention of Petit and Desault ; names that must ever occupy a proud place in the annals of surgery. The former, adding to the most powerful talents great industry, and an innate love of his pursuits, rose rapidly to eminence, though not without much envious opposition, which seems to be the portion of nearly all those who occupy a pre-eminent place in the profession. On general surgery, he has left a work of much value ; and his treatise on diseases of the bones, though produced at an early age, entitles him to be called tbe father of that branch of pathology. For many years it remained the best work on the subject. He was the inventor of the screw-tourniquet, and the first who operated for fistula lachrymalis by transfixion of the sac. He contributed largely to the Memoirs of the Royal Academy of Surgery ; an institution which has done much for the advancement of surgery, not only in France, but throughout the world. Its Memoirs, containing the result of the labours of many eminent men, constitute a work of the greatest value. Desault, also of high reputation, both as an anatomist and as a surgeon, was the first who taught surgical anatomy, and gave clinical lectures on surgery. His improvements on the apparatus for fractures were most important ; and a splint invented by him is still in use for fractures high in the femur. His modifications of cutting instruments were also good ; among others, changing the amputating instrument to a straight knife, instead of the old curved weapon. He was the first who contemplated the cure of artificial anus, resulting from strangulated hernia ; and he further improved Pare’s revival of ligature of the arteries. The proposal of curing aneurism by ligature of the vessel on the distal side of the tumour originated with him ; a proceeding, however, of which the merit is still dubious. His writings are both valuable and extensive. After the great names of Petit and Desault, not a few French surgeons of the same century, though less eminent, yet deserve mention ; Le Dran, a copious and excellent author ; Sabatier, famous in the department of operative surgery j</p></body></text></TEI>