<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T17:44:46Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>fellows, being graduates, may use in the choir, besides their surplices, such hoods as pertain to their several degrees; but in all other places every minister shall be at liberty to use a surplice or not. And hence, in marrying, churching of women, and other offices not specified in this rubric, and even in the administration of the holy communion, it seems that a surplice is not necessary. Indeed for the holy communion the rubric appoints a white alb plain, which differs from the surplice in being close-sleeved, with a vestment or cope.</p><p><hi rend="superscript">1</hi> SURREY, an inland English county, on the banks of the Thames, by which, on its northern side, it is separated from Middlesex. On the west it is bounded by Berkshire and Hampshire, on the south by Sussex, and on the east by Kent. Its shape is an oblong, of moderate regularity, except on its northern side, where considerable indentations are formed by the curvatures of the Thames. Its length from east to west is about thirty-seven miles, and its breadth from north to south about twenty-five. The area is 758 square miles, or 485,120 statute acres.</p><p>The population of this county at the four decennial periods of enumeration was found to be as follows ; viz. in 1801 it amounted to 269,043, in 1811 to 323,851, in 1821 to 398,658, and in 1831 to 485,700.</p><p>At the last date the occupiers of land employing labourers were	 1,873</p><p>Occupiers of land not employing labourers	 727</p><p>Labourers employed in agriculture	 16,761</p><p>Labourers employed in manufactures	 2,065</p><p>Labourers in retail trade and handicraft	44,139</p><p>Capitalists, bankers, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c...................................</hi> 14,235 Labourers not agricultural	 24,878</p><p>Males at and above twenty years	 10,756</p><p>Male servants	'.	 6,232</p><p>Female servants	 24,540</p><p>In the same year the number of families chiefly employed in agriculture was found to be 14,647 ; of those chiefly employed in trade, manufactures, and handicraft, 49,616 ; and of those not comprised in either of the preceding classes, 44,814. The number of inhabited houses was 80,070, occupied by 109,077 families; of uninhabited, 6102; and of those building, 1073.</p><p>The amount of the annual value of the real property of the county, as assessed for the purposes of the property-tax in 1813, was L. 1,579,173.</p><p>The towns and villages within this county, whose inhabitants exceed 3000, are, with their population in 1831, as follows. Such of them which are so in contact with the metropolis as to form suburbs to it, are here distinguished by an asterisk.</p><p>*Southwark	91,501 Farnham	5,858</p><p>*Lambeth		87,856	Battersea	5,540</p><p>*Newington	44,526	Streatham	5,068</p><p>*Bermondsey	29,741	Chertsey	4,795</p><p>Camberwell	28,231	Dorking	4,711</p><p>*Rotherhithe	12,875	Godaiming	4,529</p><p>Croydon	12,447	Mitcham	4,387</p><p>Clapham	9,958	Egham	4,203</p><p>Kingston	7,257	Guildford	3,813</p><p>Richmond	7,243	Putney	3,811</p><p>Wandsworth	6,879	Ryegate	3,397</p><p>The face of the country	exhibits great varieties. On</p><p>the north, by the banks of the Thames, from Lambeth to Egham, the richness of the highly improved country, the abundance of trees, the verdure of the meadows, the undulation of the hills, with the numerous elegant private houses, all display the most pleasing marks of taste, wealth, and comfort. The centre of the county is a range of chalk hills, much covered with thick underwood, intermixed with arable fields badly cultivated, and utterly destitute of water. The south part, at the foot of this range of hills, is a flat clayey country, nearly impassable in the winter, but covered with some of the best and largest oak trees that are to be found in the island. The north-western part exhibits a considerable tract of the most sterile black heaths, while on the south-west, near Farnham, is some of the most productive land in England.</p><p>The productions of agriculture are various, and, at a distance from the capital, scarcely differ from those of other districts in similar circumstances. A greater proportion of clover and of sanfoin is cultivated on the hills, where there arc no natural meadows, than in most other parts of the kingdom. Woad is also very extensively raised in the same districts. It is commonly sown along with turnips intended for feeding sheep, which will not touch woad. It is generally harvested before the corn-crops are ready for the sickle. Near London, the garden-ground extends over several thousand acres. The growing of plants, for the use of the druggists and perfumers, engages much attention ; and those gardens supply peppermint, lavender, wormwood, chamomile, aniseed, liquorice, poppy, and other similar articles. Hops are extensively cultivated near Farnham, and are sold for higher prices than those of any other districts.</p><p>No minerals are now raised in the county ; for though iron is known to exist, and was formerly worked with charcoal, the improvements in chemistry have fixed that operation to the coal-districts. The fossil riches are valuable, especially fullers’ earth, which is of the best quality, and in abundance, and supplies the cloth manufacturers both in the west and north of England. Limestone is plentiful ; and that, as well as chalk, is converted into lime, upon a great scale, for the use of the builders of the metropolis. The quarries of Merstham produce an excellent fire-stone ; and the sand near Dorking and Ryegate is in great request for making glass, hour-glasses, and other purposes.</p><p>The manufactures are various and extensive ; but, being almost exclusively near the metropolis, may more properly be considered as belonging to London than to the county of Surrey. The principal of these are breweries and distilleries on a magnificent scale. The tanners, rope and sail-makers, glass-makers, starch and hair-powder makers, and the preparers of vinegar and raisin wines, carry on large trades. A few miles farther from London, chiefly on the banks of the river Wandle, the calico-printers and bleachers have large establishments.</p><p>All the rivers of this county empty themselves into the Thames. The only navigable river, besides that fine stream which bounds it, is the Wey, on which barges pass above Guildford into the Basingstoke Canal. The Mole is a beautiful small stream, celebrated for sinking into the ground, and at some few miles lower again emerging. The Wandle runs a short course, but is of great value, from the vast quantity of mill-machinery which it keeps in motion, and the employment which it thus affords to several thousand persons. It rises in one spring near Croydon, turns a large mill within a few yards of its source, and runs nine miles before it joins the Thames. The Medway rises in Surrey, but is a very small stream till it enters the county of Kent. The Loddon, a small river on the western border, is chiefly valuable for the supply of water which it affords to the Basingstoke Canal. That canal was one of the first executed in this part of the kingdom, having been finished in 1796. The Croydon Canal only reaches that town from the Thames ; and the little success attending it has prevented its being carried farther, as was originally intended. The Surrey Canal runs parallel to the Thames ; but, by avoiding the sinuosities of that river, and the whole of the metropolis, is expected to be beneficial to the inhabitants on the upper banks, by conveying coals and other heavy commodities to them, from ships, at a cheap rate. Its entrance, from the Thames below London Bridge, has a fine basin, capable of containing 100 sail of square-rigged ves-</p></body></text></TEI>