<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-05-20T16:32:01Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>mately evacuated. He seems to have been perfectly acquainted with tetanus and spontaneous gangrene ; observing, that even minute wounds of tendinous parts, as the fingers and toes, sometimes produce convulsions which terminate fatally ; and that black spots on the feet frequently increase to extensive gangrene and incurable mortifications. Some of his practices have been long and justly exploded, some have been successfully continued, and others have, after disuse, been revived as modern inventions. For example, his method of ascertaining the presence or absence of fluid in the chest was by percussion, and applying the ear to the part, thus anticipating the use of the modern stethoscope. One of his modes of counter-irritation, we have seen, was by burning flax on the part, as in the modern moxa; and he strongly recommends the production of eschars on the back and breast in the earlier stages of pulmonary disease, thus anticipating the supposed valuable discoveries of a celebrated modern charlatan. His writings are elegant, and well repay a careful perusal. By them he made posterity his debtor ; his contemporaries were not insensible to his merits, and endeavoured to reward them during his life. The inhabitants of Argos voted him a statue of gold ; he was more than once crowned by the Athenians, and, though a stranger, was initiated into the most sacred mysteries of their religion, the highest distinction which they could confer ; alter his death, universal and almost divine honours were paid to his memory ; temples were erected to him, and his altars covered with offerings.</p><p>We have already seen that surgery had long been stationary before the time of Hippocrates ; and it made but little advancement during many succeeding generations. The Asclepiades had confined the knowledge of medicine among themselves; Hippocrates, however, gave oral instructions in anatomy and the art of healing, and thus disclosed its mysteries to the world. But few of his disciples seem to have profited much by his liberality. One of them, his kinsman Ctesias, we are told, acquired considerable renown for his skill ; and having been taken prisoner by Artaxerxes Mnemon, in a battle fought against his brother Cyrus, was successful in curing him of a severe wound, and thus obtained favour with his captor. Plato began to flourish about this time; but though he was connected with medicine, we cannot lay claim to him as eminent in surgery ; and he was more famous for his philosophy than his physic. Perhaps the most distinguished in surgery, among the more immediate successors of Hippocrates, was Diodes Carystus. He devoted more attention to anatomy than any of his predecessors, was curious in bandaging wounds of the head, and invented the bellulon, an instrument for extracting darts. Carrying his surgery into the practice of medicine, he was not very happy in the result; from observing that external wounds, abscesses, and inflammations were attended with fever, he supposed that general fever was uniformly occasioned by one or more of these causes operating internally. He followed Hippocrates in practice, and, like him, cultivated his profession, “ not for lucre or vain-glory, but from real love of the medical art, and a pure spirit of humanity.” Praxagoras of Cos was the last of the Asclepiades who succeeded in leaving a name behind him. As a surgeon he is reported to have been bold in the extreme, incising the fauces freely, and excising portions of the soft palate, in bad cases of cynanche ; and making incisions into the bowels to remove obstructions, when milder measures failed. Aristotle, the celebrated preceptor of Alexander the Great, although not strictly in the medical profession, was the promulgator of doctrines which for a long time had a powerful effect on medicine. While he followed out the general principles of the healing art, and</p><p>was curious in anatomical research, he seems to have disdained to meddle with the practical details, and among the rest those of surgery.</p><p>On the dismemberment of the vast empire of Macedonia after the death of Alexander the Great, learning took up its chief abode at Alexandria, under the protection of Ptolemy Soter. And here it was that popular prejudice first gave way, and permitted the examination of dead bodies, the greatest possible boon to the medical profession, inasmuch as it removed what had hitherto been the most serious obstacle to its advancement, ignorance of human anatomy. Heropbilus and Erasistratus, the two great heads of the Egyptian medical school, were the first who had an opportunity of practising human dissection, the bodies of criminals having been given to them for that purpose; and they consequently not only corrected many errors, but made numerous and important discoveries, in anatomy ; thus imparting a fresh stimulus, and affording a new and more solid basis to both medicine and surgery. By some they have been accused of carrying their enthusiasm in this inquiry to such an extent as to "open the bodies of living criminals for the furtherance of their physiological views ;" but this is probably a mere exaggeration, originating in the horror with which human dissection was at first regarded ; a horror which unfortunately is not even in our day altogether extinguished, notwithstanding the recent legislative enactments in favour of anatomical research. But we find even these privileged men falling into most palpable mistakes ; for example, Heropbilus plainly confounds the tendons and ligaments with the nerves. Yet the fact that the names which he gave to many parts still remain in use, will of itself remind posterity how much they are indebted to him for his anatomical labours. He was likewise one of the greatest surgeons of ancient times, and, as well as Erasistratus, acquired as much fame for brilliant cures as for anatomical knowledge. The surgical practice of the latter was characterized by peculiar boldness and decision, and strongly marked with the failing of his time and school, a love of multiplying and inventing murderous implements, mid the relentless use of them. “ In schirrosities and tumours of the liver, he did not scruple to make an ample division of the integuments, and try applications to that viscus itself. He followed the same practice in diseases of the spleen, which he regarded as of little consequence in the animal economy.” And perhaps he was right in his supposition, though not in his practice. In cases of retention of urine, he made use of the particular catheter which hing bore his name. Xenophon of Cos, said to have been a follower of Erasistratus, seems to have been among the first who arrested hæmorrhage from a member, by encircling it tightly with a ligature. Mantius, a pupil of Heropbilus, wrote a treatise on surgical dressings, which he rendered complicated in the extreme. Another, Andreas of Carystus, wrote on the union of fractured bones, and invented several ponderous machines for reducing luxations of the femur. Indeed the surgeons of the Alexandrian school were all distinguished by the nicety and complexity of their dressings and bandagings, of which they invented a great variety. Among them, as in the time of Hippocrates. lithotomy was practised by particular individuals, who devoted themselves exclusively to that operation ; and we are told that one of them, Ammonius, employed an instrument. by means of which he broke down stones in the bladder, plainly anticipating Civiale, and furnishing a marked example to the present age of the truth of Solomon’s apophthegm, that “ there is nothing new under the sun.”@@* It is not improbable that some of their other practices might have afforded equally</p><p><hi rend="superscript">@@@,</hi> A curious illustration of this is given by Dr James Johnson, in the narrative of his visit to Pompeii. “ The Dillator or Speculum, for which Mr Weiss of the Strand obtained so much repute a few years ages, has its exact prototype in the Bourbon Museum at Naples. The coincidence in such an ingenious contrivance would be absolutely miraculous ; but unfortunately there is a key to the similitude, which de-</p></body></text></TEI>