<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-05-20T16:32:39Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>sels. Railroads have been constructed from Merstham to the Thames ; but the project has not repaid those who have advanced the capital a sufficient interest to recommend any further attempts. Several railroads which will pass through the county have been projected, and acts of the legislature for some of them have been obtained : only one of them has yet made much progress, namely, the London and Southampton. Some obstacles long delayed that intended to proceed to Brighton, and the same is the case with the one projected from London to Dover.</p><p>Among the Roman antiquities of this county are the Ermine Way, which traversed it, and the remains of which may still be traced near Dorking. The piles are still standing in the river Thames at Walton, which were placed there by the ancient Britons, to impede the passage of Julius Cæsar. The vestiges of the encampments of the Romans may be distinctly traced at Bottlehill, at Waltonhill, and some other spots. Among the antiquities of later date, are the Palace of Lambeth, belonging to the see of Canterbury ; that of Farnham, belonging to the see of Winchester; the remains <hi rend="italic">of</hi> the Abbey at Croydon, the Castle of Guildford, Waverley Abbey, and some other Saxon edifices. The meadow of Runnymead, St Anne’s Hill, the seat of the late Mr Fox, the park of Richmond, and the terrace there, with the palace and gardens of Kew, are all objects that excite a high degree of interest. It is difficult to determine which of the towns is the capital of the county. The principal prison is in the borough of Southwark, and the quarter-sessions are held there ; but the lent assizes are held at Kingston-on-Thames, and the summer assizes alternately at Croydon and at Guildford.</p><p>The titles derived from this county are those of the Duke of Richmond, the Earls of Surrey, Guildford, and Onslow, and Baron Abinger. The county is formed into the eastern and western division to elect two members for each. The election for the east division is held at Croydon ; and the other</p><p>polling places are Ryegate, Camberwell, and Kingston. The western election is held at Guildford ; and the other polling places are Dorking and Chertsey. The boroughs of Gatton and Haselmere, which formerly returned two members each, have been disfranchised ; and Ryegate, which chose two, now elects but one member. Lambeth has been erected into a borough, and returns two members; as do the ancient boroughs of Southwark and Guildford.</p><p>The number of seats belonging to noblemen and gentlemen in this county is so great as to forbid the noticing of even all those which in any other county would be deemed highly worthy of notice. The most remarkable are, her majesty’s palace of Kew ; Claremont, king of Belgium ; Clandon Place, earl of Onslow ; Pepper Harrow, Lord Middleton ; Oatlands, Lord Francis Egerton ; Painshill, Lord Carhampton ; Ockham Park, earl of Lovelace; Addington Palace, archbishop of Canterbury ; Rooksnist, C. H. Turner, Esq. ; Nonsuch Park, S. Farmer, Esq. ; Gatton, Lord Monson ; Nork House, Lord Arden ; Betchworth, Right Honourable H. Goulbourne ; Norbury Park, Joseph Dennison, Esq.</p><p>See Manning and Bray’s History of Surrey ; Salmon’s Antiquities of Surrey ; Stevenson’s View of the Agriculture of Surrey : Lyson’s Environs of London.</p><p>SURROOL, a town of Bengal, district of Birbhoom, where the East India Company have a factory for white cottons. Long. 87. 42. E. Lat. 23. 39. N.</p><p>SURSOLID, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Surdesolid,</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Arithmetic,</hi> the fifth power of a number, or the fourth multiplication of any number, considered as a root.</p><p>SURSUTTY, a river of Hindustan, which rises in the mountains on the north-east boundary of the province of Delhi, and running south-west, is lost in the sands of Ajmeer. A town and fortress of the same name is situated on the western bank of this river, and now belongs to an independent chief. Long. 75. 27. E. Lat. 29. 13. N.</p></body></text></TEI>