<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T17:43:22Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>again by order of the Caliph Omar, and was used for navigation from the year 644 to 767 ; at which time another caliph caused it to be shut up. in order to deprive a rebel chief of his supplies of provisions. While the French army was in Egypt, some learned discussions were maintained on the practicability and advantages of its restitution. But however useful its re-establishment might be to the country through which it passes, it is very problematical if it could ever be rendered a medium of commercial communication on a large scale.</p><p>SUFFOLK, an English maritime county, on the borders of the German Ocean. It is bounded on the east by the sea; on the south by Essex, from which it is divided by the river Stour ; on the west by Cambridgeshire ; and on the north by Norfolk. Its medium length from east to west is forty-seven miles, and its breadth from north to south twenty-seven. The square contents are 1512 miles, or 967,680 statute acres. It consists of two grand divisions, one called the Liberty of Bury, the other the Guildable Land, each of which furnishes a distinct grand jury at the assizes. The next division is into twenty-one hundreds, and these are subdivided into five hundred and twenty-three parishes. The entire country forms a part of the diocese of Norwich.</p><p>The population of this county at the four decennial periods of enumeration was found to amount in 1801 to 210,431, in 1811 to 234,211, in 1821 to 270,542, and in 1831 to 296,000.</p><p>At the last period the occupiers of land employing labourers were	 4,526</p><p>Occupiers not employing labourers	 1,121</p><p>Labourers employed in agriculture	33,040</p><p>Labourers employed in manufactures	 676</p><p>Labourers employed in retail trade or handicraft... 18,167 Capitalists, bankers, &amp;c	 2,228</p><p>Labourers not agricultural	 5,336</p><p>Other labourers under	twenty years of age	 4,940</p><p>Males at and above twenty	years	71,376</p><p>Male servants.	 2,032</p><p>Female servants	11,483</p><p>In the same year the number of families chiefly employed in agriculture was found to be 31,491 ; those chiefly employed in trade, manufactures, and handicraft, were 18,116; and those comprised in neither of the preceding classes were 11,926. The number of inhabited houses was 50,139, occupied by 61,533 families; the uninhabited houses were 1141, and those building 259.</p><p>The annual value of the real property of the county, as assessed for the purposes of the property-tax in the year 1813, was L. 1,127,404.</p><p>The towns of this county containing more than 2000 inhabitants, with their population in 1831, were the following: Ipswich	20,454</p><p>Bury St Edmund’s			11,436</p><p>Woodbridge	 4,769</p><p>Sudbury	 4,677</p><p>Lowestolfe	 4,238</p><p>Beedes	 3,862</p><p>Bungay	 3,734</p><p>Hadleigh	 3,425</p><p>Mildenhall	 3,267</p><p>Long Melford	 2,514</p><p>Halesworth	      2,473</p><p>Framlingham	 2,445</p><p>Eye	 2,313</p><p>Newmarket, but a part of this town, with 714, is in</p><p>Cambridgeshire.	 2,134</p><p>Gorlestone, a suburb to Yarmouth in Norfolk, and</p><p>by the reform bill a part of that borough	 2,111</p><p>Lavenham	   2,107</p><p>Brandon		 2,065</p><p>Suffolk is generally a level tract of country, in which, as there are few elevations, there are scarcely any extensive prospects. It is, however, tolerably well clothed with trees, but wants running water ; most of the streams being very sluggish in their course, and by no means copious. The soil is as various as in other districts of the same extent. On the sea-coast it is in general sandy, but rendered productive by the application of shell-marl, which is found in abundance. In the middle of the county, from north to south, called usually High Suffolk, which is the larger part, the soil is a tenacious, loamy clay, affording good pasturage for cows, whose butter is chiefly used to supply the London markets.</p><p>The north-western division is a poor sandy soil, in many places covered with heath, and scarcely fit for any other purpose than that of feeding sheep or breeding rabbits, of which latter animals, it is said, the skins of more than 40,006 annually supply fur to the hatters. The corn furnished by the eastern division of the county, besides supplying its vicinity, is sent to London from the ports of Ipswich and Woodbridge. The cultivation is commonly conducted on the Norfolk system of turnips, barley, clover, and wheat ; and the husbandry being well executed, the crops are generally very good. The beans are peculiarly productive. Turnips, and in some districts carrots, are extensively cultivated. Hemp is grown in the garden of almost every peasant, and spun into linen for their domestic uses. Some few hops are grown in the vicinity of Stow- market.</p><p>They have an excellent breed of draught-horses, well known by the name of Suffolk punches. The cows have been long celebrated for the abundance of their milk, which, in proportion to their size and the quantity of food they consume, exceeds the produce of any other race in the kingdom. They are all without horns. The sheep, of which large flocks are kept, are mostly of the Norfolk breed ; but of late years they have been changed for those of the South Downs.</p><p>There are few manufactures in this county, though it was the first in which the Flemings introduced the clothing trade. Before the extension of machinery in the northern counties, the females found constant winter employment in spinning worsted, but that has ceased. A small portion of the manufacture of mixed silk and worsted stuffs is retained, in which 269 males above twenty years of age are employed at Sudbury, forty-two are so employed at Glemsford, and a few at Lavenham and at Hadleigh. At Brandon no less that sixty men are employed in making gun-flints. There is some coarse linen made from hemp at Haverhill, and a little bone-lace at Eye.</p><p>The branch of industry which, next to agriculture, gives employment to the greatest number of inhabitants, is the fishery. Many vessels are equipped at Lowestoffe and Southwold to take herrings, which are cured in houses appropriated for that purpose in these towns. The taking of mackerel is beneficial before the season when the shoals of herrings arrive on the coast. There is little other commerce in the county than that which arises from the transmission of the agricultural products to the metropolis.</p><p>The navigable rivers are the Sark, which passes by Thetford, and runs to the Ouse ; the Deben, of short course, which runs by Woodbridge to the sea ; the Orwell, a beautiful river, navigable to Ipswich ; and the Blythe, navigable to Framlingham. To these may be added the Wave- nay, which forms the northern boundary of the county ; and the Stour, which is its southern. The only navigable canal is one between Ipswich and Stowmarket ; but the river Yare having been rendered navigable to Norwich, has a canal at its mouth at Lowestoffe in this county : the admission is by gates, which exhibit one of the most complete specimens of hydraulic architecture in the kingdom.</p></body></text></TEI>