<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T17:44:17Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>of the twelfth century, at Seville in Andalusia. He describes inflammation and abscess of the mediastinum, from which he had himself suffered ; and mentions a case of abscess of the kidney, from which fourteen pints of matter were evacuated. He speaks of bronchotomy as expedient in dangerous cases of inflammation of the tonsils : and in stricture of the gullet proposes three modes of treatment ; the occasional passage of a tin or silver tube ; the use of a milk bath, that nutritious particles may be taken up by the pores on the skin ; and the injection of nutritious fluids by the rectum. He also details cases of “ rupture, fracture of the hipbone, wounds of the arteries and veins, tumours, and other varieties of surgical disease, which he appears to have understood well, and treated with discretion.” He does not complain, like Rhazes, that lithotomy was in the hands of mountebanks, but tells us that the Arabians then reckoned such operations “ filthy and abominable, and unfit for any man of character to perform and held that “ no religious man, according to the law, ought so much as to view the genitals.” The brightest name in the history of Arabian philosophy is that of Averrhoes, the pupil of Avenzoar, born at Cordova about the middle of the twelfth century, and said to have died in the year 1206. But be cultivated the study of medicine only as a branch of general philosophy, and surgery he seems to have altogether neglected.</p><p>Such were the Arabians. Of these, Albucasis was the most famous in surgery, as Celsus had been among the Romans, and Paulus Ægineta among the Greeks. But even he could not escape the unfortunate failing of the Saracenic school ; endless invention of manifold and complicated instruments, attaching far too much importance to the mechanical part of their profession, and mistaking the inspiration of terror and infliction of cruelty for energetic and judicious surgery. In order, for example, to arrest haemorrhage from a wounded surface, if time pressed and assistants were scarce, it was not uncommon to dip the part into boiling pitch, a liquid which was then dignified with the appellation of a styptic. They however systematically divided physic, surgery, and pharmacy into three distinct professions ; and so, by commencing the division of labour, may be considered as having done something not unimportant towards the ultimate advancement of medical knowledge. “ The last traces of their intellectual illumination appeared among the Spanish Moors in the thirteenth century, when the Christian arms having become more and more powerful, they were compelled to substitute the field for the study—the sword for the pen— and, before an overwhelming opposition, were at length driven from a region whose fields they had tilled, and whose olives they had gathered, for a thousand years. With the decline of the Saracenic school, the daylight of science went down over the nations ; and an intellectual darkness, which endured for three hundred years, enveloped the general face of society. All the fountains of science were dried up, and the world seemed retrograding into the unillumined chaos of ignorance.”@@<hi rend="superscript">1</hi></p><p>A knowledge of the Greek and Arabian systems of medicine was introduced into Italy, at Salerno, in the beginning of the eleventh century ; and this school soon rose to celebrity as a seat of medical learning. In the time of the Crusades, Salerno was a place of great resort for warriors of all nations passing between Europe and Palestine; and by these wanderers, on their return, the light of medical science was thence slowly conveyed over Europe. It obtained the privileges of a university ; but the medical school of Salerno did not long retain its high reputation. In modern times, it is chiefly remembered on account of the <hi rend="italic">Regimen Sanitatis Salernitanum,</hi> a singular production, of which more than one hundred and sixty editions are known to have been published. Though written in the name of the <hi rend="italic">Schola Salernitana,</hi> it has generally been ascribed to Joannes de Milano. The English king to whom it is addressed is supposed to have been Robert of Normandy, whose claims to the English crown were recognised by some of his contemporaries. The poem opens with these lines :</p><p>Anglorum Regi scripsit Schola tota Salerni. Si vis incolumem, si vis te reddere sanum, Curas toile graves, irasci crede profanum, Parce mero, conato parum, non sit tibi vanum Surgere post epulas, somnum fuge meridianum, Non mictum retine, nec comprime fortiter anum.@@*</p><p>In the twelfth century, the Jews practised medicine, not only among their own tribes, but also among the Moors and Christians ; and though, like all others of this age, merely treading in the beaten track of the Greeks and Arabians, yet, from their superiority in such learning, they came to be reputed the most skilful practitioners. About the middle of that century, as bus already been stated, surgery was completely separated from physic, by the edict of the Council of Tours prohibiting the clergy,@@<hi rend="superscript">3</hi> who then shared with the Jews the practice of the healing art in Christian Europe, from in any way causing the effusion of blood, at least as a means of curing bodily ailment. Surgery was in consequence abandoned to the uneducated laity, and sunk to a deplorable state of prostration ; it became a mere matter of plasters and unguents ; and if any thing happened to be written on the subject, it was but a bad compilation from the Arabians.@@<hi rend="superscript">4</hi> We shall however notice some of the more remarkable events in connection with it during its temporary abasement. In the year 1271, the foundation of the College of Surgeons at Paris was laid by Pitard, a surgeon of eminence in those days, and whose enthusiasm effected something towards raising his humbled profession. About the same time lived Gulielmus de Sa- liceto, <hi rend="italic">a</hi> professor at Verona, said to have been “ a powerful man” in both surgery and medicine. He seems to have earnestly dissuaded men from the copying and study of books in preference to practical experience, and he himself set a better example. In our own country Gilbertus Anglicanus is the first name connected with surgery ; but he seems to have been little more than a compiler from the Arabians. He lived about the beginning of the fourteenth century ; and shortly after him appeared John of Gaddes- den, author of the <hi rend="italic">Rosa Λnglica,</hi> and said to have been an erudite and ingenious man, as well as a skilful practi-</p><p><hi rend="superscript">@@@,</hi> Moir's Outlines of the Ancient History of Medicine. Edinb. 1831, 16to. Of this work we have not scrupled to make free use in the course of the preceding observations.</p><p><hi rend="italic">@@@•	Regimen Sanitatis Salernitanum :</hi> a Poem on the Preservation of Health, in rhyming Latin verse, addressed by the School of Salerno to Robert of Normandy, son of William the Conqueror, with an ancient translation ; and an introduction and notes by Sir Alexander Croke, D.C.L. and F.A.S. Oxford, 1830, 12mo.</p><p><hi rend="superscript">@@@3</hi> The early clergy claimed the practice of medicine as their peculiar privilege, and, using it chiefly as a means of personal power and gain, disgraced it by ignorance, charlatanry, and imposture. It was to check this that the Roman council assembled by Pope Innocent II. In 1139, threatened with the severest penalties those monks and canons who applied to the practice of medicine, "neglecting the sacred objects of their own profession, and holding out the delusive hope of health in exchange for ungodly lucre.” But even this, though followed by the more peremptory edict at Tours in 1163, where Alexander III. presided, did not make them altogether forego what they found so convenient and profitable. It was necessary to repeat the edict in 1179 and 1216; but notwithstanding, the monks continued stiil to practise physic, and it was chiefly by their evil influence that the school of Salerno was brought to decay.</p><p>@@@*	The writers of that age were aptly termed by Severinus, Arabistæ.</p></body></text></TEI>