<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-05-20T16:31:23Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>moulds, and the syrup, or that part which did not crystallize, descends into the pots in which the moulds are placed. After this purgation the moulds are removed and fixed in other pots, and a stratum of fine white clay diluted with water is laid on the upper part of the loaf. The water descending through the sugar by its own weight, mixes with the syrup which still remains in the body of the loaf, and washes it away. When the clay dries, it is taken off, and another covering of moist clay put in its place ; and if it be not then sufficiently washed, a third covering of clay is applied. After the loaves have stood some days in the moulds, and have acquired a considerable degree of firmness and solidity, they are taken out and carried to a stove, where they are gradually heated to the 50° of Reaumur (64° of Fahrenheit), in order to dissipate any moisture which may be still confined in them. After remaining in the stove eight days, they are taken out ; and after cutting off all discolouring specks, and the head if still wet, they are wrapped in blue paper, and are ready for sale. The several syrups collected during the different parts of the process, treated in the same manner which we have just described, afford sugars of inferior quality; and the last portion, which no longer affords any sugar, is sold by the name of <hi rend="italic">molasses.</hi></p><p>The beauty of refined sugar, when formed into loaves, consists in whiteness, joined to a smallness of grain ; in being dry, hard, and somewhat transparent. The process which we have described above refers to sugar once refined; but some more labour is necessary to produce double-refined sugar. The principal difference in the operation is this ; the latter is clarified by white of eggs instead of blood, and fresh water in place of lime-water.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Sugar-candy</hi> is the true essence of the cane formed into large crystals by a slow process. When the syrup is well clarified, it is boiled a little, but not so much as is done in the process for making common sugar. It is then placed in old moulds, having their lower ends stopped with linen, and crossed at little distances with small twigs to retain the sugar as it crystallizes. The moulds are then laid in a cool place. In proportion as the syrup cools, crystals are formed. In about nine or ten days the moulds are carried to the stove, and placed in a pot; but the linen is not removed entirely, so that the syrup falls down slowly in drops. When the syrup has dropped away, and the crystals of the sugar∙candy are become dry, the moulds are taken from the stove, and broken in pieces to disengage the sugar, which adheres strongly to the sides of the mould. If the syrup has been coloured with cochineal, the crystals take a slight taint of red ; if indigo has been mixed, they assume a bluish colour. If it be desired to have the candy perfumed, the essence of flowers or amber may be dropped into the moulds along with the syrup.</p><p>The average quantity of sugar imported into Great Britain and Ireland during the last twenty years ending with 1837 is 4,486,014 cwts. ; the quantity imported in 1837 was 4,482,578 cwts., which is somewhat under the average of the preceding nineteen years, while the population may be assumed to have increased at least twenty per cent. during the same period. From these facts we may fairly assume, that if the duty on sugar were reduced so as to bring the price within the reach of the poorer classes, the demand would greatly increase.</p><p>Sugar was imported into England in the fourteenth century, but in small quantities. The demand, however, increased very rapidly, and the consumption of this important necessary of life is now about twenty times greater than it was in the beginning of last century.</p><p>In 1700 it was 22,000,000	lbs.</p><p>... 1754 	 119,320,000	...</p><p>... 1790 	 181,500,000	...</p><p>... 1807 	 255,098,450	...</p><p>... 1837	432,938,608	...</p><p>Taking the aggregate population of the united kingdom in 1837 at twenty four millions and a half, this gives to each individual just sixteen pounds per annum; a proportion very far below what might be expected were the price reduced.</p><p>An Account of the Quantity of Sugar imported into the United Kingdom, distinguishing Great Britain from Ireland, and specifying the Countries whence the Imports were received ; together with a Statement of the Quantities and Descriptions cleared from the Warehouses and retained for Consumption, the Rates of Duty and Drawback, the Gross Amount of Duty, the Sum paid for Drawback, &amp;c., and the Net Amount of Revenue, with the Gazette Average Prices, at the end of each Quarter of the Year 1837.</p><table><row><cell>Places whence imported.</cell><cell cols="4">Quantities Imported into</cell></row><row><cell/><cell>Great Britain.</cell><cell cols="2">Ireland.</cell><cell>United Kingdom.</cell></row><row><cell>British Colonies</cell><cell/><cell/><cell/><cell/></row><row><cell>and Plantations in America, viz	</cell><cell>Cwts. qrs. lbs.</cell><cell cols="2">Cwts. qrs. lbs.</cell><cell>Cwts. qrs. lbs.</cell></row><row><cell>Antigua	</cell><cell>56,360 0 2</cell><cell>5,810</cell><cell>1 2</cell><cell>62,170 1 4</cell></row><row><cell>Barbadoes	</cell><cell>413,287 2 21</cell><cell>32,425</cell><cell>1 23</cell><cell>445,713 0 16</cell></row><row><cell>Dominica 	</cell><cell>33,723 2 10</cell><cell/><cell/><cell>33.723 2 10</cell></row><row><cell>Grenada	</cell><cell>101,921 2 20</cell><cell>...</cell><cell/><cell>161,921 2 10</cell></row><row><cell>Jamaica	</cell><cell>901,078 2 15</cell><cell>3,221</cell><cell>0 3</cell><cell>904,299 2 18</cell></row><row><cell><p>Montserrat	</p><p>Nevis	</p></cell><cell><p>5,694 3 24</p><p>24,269 0 0</p></cell><cell/><cell/><cell><p>5,694 3 24</p><p>24,269	0 0</p><p>73,269	2 18</p></cell></row><row><cell>St Christopher.</cell><cell>72,200 2 16</cell><cell>1,003</cell><cell>0 2</cell><cell/></row><row><cell>St Lucia	</cell><cell>31,235 3 9</cell><cell>20,194</cell><cell>2 0</cell><cell>51,430 1 9</cell></row><row><cell>St Vincent	</cell><cell>201,191 1 21</cell><cell/><cell/><cell>201,191 1 21</cell></row><row><cell>Tobago	</cell><cell>90,803 0 25</cell><cell>...</cell><cell/><cell>90,803 0 25</cell></row><row><cell>Tortola	</cell><cell><p>13,034 0 5</p><p>224,873 1 2</p></cell><cell/><cell/><cell>13,534 0 5</cell></row><row><cell>Trinidad	</cell><cell/><cell>70,493</cell><cell>3 1</cell><cell>295,367 0 3</cell></row><row><cell>Demerara	</cell><cell>705,637 3 18</cell><cell>87,214</cell><cell>0 4</cell><cell>792,851 3 22</cell></row><row><cell>Berbice	...</cell><cell>148,836 0 5</cell><cell>1,699</cell><cell>3 14</cell><cell>150,535 3 19</cell></row><row><cell><p>Honduras	</p><p>British North</p><p>American Co-</p></cell><cell>0 3 21</cell><cell/><cell/><cell>0 3 21</cell></row><row><cell><p>lonies	</p><p>West Coast of</p></cell><cell>2,304 0 17</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>1 18</cell><cell>2,365 2 7</cell></row><row><cell>Africa	</cell><cell>1 311</cell><cell/><cell/><cell>1 3 11</cell></row><row><cell><p>Mauritius	</p><p>British Possessions in the East Indies, viz.—</p><p>East	India</p><p>Company’s Territories, exclusive of</p></cell><cell>537,454 3 17</cell><cell/><cell/><cell>537,454 3 17</cell></row><row><cell>Singapore	</cell><cell>297,923 3 10</cell><cell>...</cell><cell/><cell>297,923 3 10</cell></row><row><cell>Singapore	</cell><cell>5,019 0 26</cell><cell>...</cell><cell/><cell>5,019 0 26</cell></row><row><cell>Ceylon	</cell><cell>2 0 0</cell><cell/><cell/><cell>2 0 0</cell></row><row><cell>Siam	</cell><cell>18,805 3 6</cell><cell/><cell/><cell>18,805 3 6</cell></row><row><cell><p>Java	</p><p>Philippine</p></cell><cell>2,877 3 13</cell><cell/><cell/><cell>2,877 3 13</cell></row><row><cell>Islands	</cell><cell>49,118 1 12</cell><cell/><cell/><cell>49.118 1 12</cell></row><row><cell><p>China	</p><p>New	South</p></cell><cell>0 0 2</cell><cell>...</cell><cell/><cell>0 0 2</cell></row><row><cell><p>Wales	</p><p>Foreign	Co</p><p>lonies in the West Indies, viz—</p></cell><cell>1,042 2 5</cell><cell/><cell/><cell>1,042 2 5</cell></row><row><cell>Cuba	</cell><cell>125,985 0 26</cell><cell/><cell/><cell>125,985 0 26</cell></row><row><cell><p>St Thomas.....</p><p>United States of</p></cell><cell>308 3 0</cell><cell>...</cell><cell/><cell>308 3 0</cell></row><row><cell>America	</cell><cell><p>1,667 0 12</p><p>0 0 4</p></cell><cell>...</cell><cell/><cell><p>1,667 0 12</p><p>0 0 4</p></cell></row><row><cell><p>Columbia	</p><p>Brazil	</p><p>States of the</p></cell><cell><p>533 1 5</p><p>110,216 1 26</p></cell><cell>...</cell><cell/><cell><p>533 1 5</p><p>110,216 126</p></cell></row><row><cell>Rio de la Plata</cell><cell>0 0 11</cell><cell>...</cell><cell/><cell>0 0 11</cell></row><row><cell><p>Chili	</p><p>Peru	</p><p>Europe	</p></cell><cell><p>0 0 10</p><p>7,993 0 24</p><p>14,485 0 21</p></cell><cell>...</cell><cell/><cell><p>0 0 10</p><p>7,993 0 24</p><p>14,485 0 21</p></cell></row><row><cell>Total	</cell><cell>4,260,514 3 24</cell><cell>222,063</cell><cell>1 11</cell><cell>4,482,578 1 7</cell></row><row><cell>Total in 1836 .</cell><cell>4,411,527 0 8</cell><cell>237,633</cell><cell>3 27</cell><cell>4,640,161 0 7</cell></row></table></body></text></TEI>