<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T17:43:42Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>which is an article of trade, and sells at a high price. The benzoin is produced from a tree which grows in the northern parts of the island. Cassia and cotton are also produced, and form articles of export. Various other shrubs and plants are cultivated, and are converted by the natives to many useful purposes. Hemp is extensively cultivated, not however for the useful purpose of making ropes, but to procure an intoxicating liquor called <hi rend="italic">bang,</hi> which they smoke in pipes along with tobacco. Plantations of the latter plant are met with in almost every district ; and there is a variety of other creeping plants, which are manufactured into twine, thread, and other articles of the same nature.</p><p>No country in the world is more distinguished than Sumatra for the variety of fine fruits with which it abounds, and which are the spontaneous produce of the earth; for the natives bestow no more care on this than on any other production. The most remarkable are the mangustin, which is produced in abundance, and which for delicacy and flavour holds pre-eminence over all the Indian fruits ; the pineapple, which, though not indigenous, grows in great plenty with ordinary culture ; the orange, which is in great perfection and variety ; the shadock of the West Indies, which is here very fine, and is distinguished into the white and the red. Limes and lemons abound ; as also the breadfruit; the jack-fruit; the mango, a rich high-flavoured fruit of the plum kind ; the papaw, a fruit substantial and wholesome, like a smooth sort of melon, but not very highly flavoured ; the pomegranate, the tamarind, nuts and almonds of different kinds, besides various other fruits of which the names are scarcely known in Europe. Owing to the equable temperature that prevails throughout the year, there is a perpetual succession of shrubs and flowers, which diffuse a pleasant fragrance, and are many of them used in medicine, or in affording useful dyes. The castoroil plant is found in abundance, especially near the seashore ; also the caoutchouc or Indian rubber plant ; the indigo plant ; a red wood called ubar, resembling logwood in its properties ; and the uphas, or poison-tree, whose deleterious qualities have been so much exaggerated.</p><p>The zoology of Sumatra is distinguished by some of the most remarkable animals in nature. The shelter afforded by its vast forests or tracts of jungle is most favourable to the breed of wild animals, which abound throughout the island. Numerous herds of elephants range over the forests, and are pursued and killed for their teeth ; they are extremely destructive to the plantations of the natives, which they trample down by merely walking through the grounds, and thus obliterating all traces of cultivation. The rhinoceros, both the single and the double horned, is also a native of the woods. Of the ferocious animals, the tiger is the most remarkable. Here he grows to an enormous size, and his strength is so prodigious that he is enabled to drag into the woods the largest prey, and by a stroke of the fore-paw will break the leg of a horse or buffalo. Whole villages are sometimes depopulated by these animals, and great numbers of inhabitants lose their lives. Sir Stamford Raffles, who fixed his residence in the interior, east of Bencoolen, among the hills, states, among its conveniences, that the temperature was six degrees lower than on the coast ; and that the only inconvenience he could suffer would be from tigers and elephants abounding in the vicinity. One of the villagers mentioned to him, that both his father and grandfather had been carried off by these animals ; and he adds, that there is scarcely a family that has not lost some of its members by them, and that on the banks of one of the rivers upwards of a hundred persons had been carried off by tigers the year before ; yet the inhabitants are so superstitious that they will not use any means for their extirpation. When a tiger enters a village, these ignorant people prepare rice and fruits as an offering to the animal, conceiving that he will be pleased with these</p><p>hospitable attentions, and pass on without doing them any harm. They are occasionally caught in traps, which are ingeniously contrived in the form of a cage with falling doors, into which the beast is enticed, and is then enclosed ; or a large beam of timber is so placed as to fall on his back and crush him. Another expedient is to entice him to ascend a plank, which being nearly balanced, is weighed down by him when he is past the centre, and he falls upon sharp stakes prepared below. The natives sometimes contrive to poison tigers. The bear is common : he is small and black, and climbs the cocoa-trees, feeding upon the tender part or cabbage. The deer abounds in every variety of species ; and the monkey tribes are innumerable. Here arc also sloths, squirrels, teleggos or stinkards, civet- cats, tiger-cats, porcupines, hedgehogs, armadillos, bats of all kinds, alligators in the rivers, which are also haunted by the hippopotamus, guanos, cameleons, flying lizards, tortoises, and turtle. The alligators are very voracious, frequently destroying the people as they bathe in the river, according to their invariable custom, from which no dangers deter them. The house-lizards are four inches in length, and are the largest reptiles that can walk in an inverted position. Among the animals which are domesticated is the buffalo, which, however, exists in a wild state, and is a remarkably strong and active animal, keeping pace with the swiftest horse ; and is even said by Marsden to fight an equal battle with the tiger, the females and weaker sort only being his sure prey. This animal supplies the inhabitants with milk, butter, and beef. The cow is a stranger to the country, and does not appear to be naturalized. The breed of horses is small, but they are well made and hardy. The sheep arc also a small breed ; the other animals are the goat and the hog, both domestic and wild ; the otter, the cat, the rat, and the dog.</p><p>Frogs, toads, and reptiles of every kind, abound in the swamps ; and the noise which they make on the approach of rain is tremendous. They fall a prey to the snakes, which are common in this island, and are of all sizes, some thirty feet in length, though Marsden states, that the largest he ever saw was only twelve feet long, which was killed in a hen-house, where it was devouring the poultry. He also mentions his opinion, that the bite of very few of these serpents is mortal, as he never saw a well-authenticated instance of a person suffering from them. Among the poisonous serpents is the viper ; and the hooded snake is sometimes found in the country. The boa constrictor is the largest, and sometimes grows to the length of thirty feet, and is of proportionate bulk and strength.</p><p>The surrounding seas abound in fish. Among these are the duyong, a large sea-animal of the mammalia order, with two strong pectoral fins serving for the purpose of feet; the grampus-whale, a fish which derives its name from the peculiarity of its dorsal fin resembling a sail. There are, besides, sharks, skates, the muræna gymnotus, rock cod, pom- fret, mullet, the flying fish, and many others.</p><p>Of birds there is a much greater variety than of other animals ; and so numerous are the curious species, that Marsden cannot even give a list of them. They consist of peacocks, eagles, vultures, kites, and crows, jackdaws, kingfishers ; the rhinoceros bird, remarkable for its horn ; the stork, the snipe, coot, plover, pigeons, quails, starlings, swallows, minas, parrots and parroquets, geese, ducks, teal, &amp;c. The Sumatran pheasant is a bird of great magnificence and beauty ; the plumage being perhaps the most rich, without any degree of gaudiness, of all the feathered race.</p><p>The island may be said literally to swarm with insects, which are extremely annoying and destructive. These consist of cochroaches, crickets, bees, flies of all sorts, mosquitoes, scorpions, centipedes, and water and land leeches. These leeches are extremely annoying to those who travel in the woods ; and Sir Stamford Raffles mentions, that in</p></body></text></TEI>