<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-05-20T16:31:10Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>SUBJECT, in <hi rend="italic">Music.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Music</hi>.</p><p>SUBITO, in the Italian music, is used to signify that a tiling is to be performed quickly and hastily ; thus we meet with <hi rend="italic">volti subito,</hi> turn over the leaf quickly.</p><p>SUBLIMATE, a chemical preparation, consisting of quicksilver united with muriatic acid.</p><p>SUBLIMATION, in <hi rend="italic">Chemistry,</hi> the condensing and collecting, in a solid form, by means of vessels aptly constructed, the fumes of bodies raised from them by the application of a proper heat.</p><p>SUBMULTIPLE, in <hi rend="italic">Geometry,</hi> &amp;c. A submultiple number or quantity is that which is contained a certain number of times in another, and which, therefore, repeated a certain number of times, becomes exactly equal thereto. Thus 3 is a submultiple of 21. In this sense a submultiple coincides with an aliquot part.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Submultiple Ratio,</hi> is that between the quantity contained and the quantity containing. Thus the ratio of 3 to 21 is submultiple. In both cases submultiple is the reverse of multiple : 21, <hi rend="italic">e. gr.</hi> being a multiple of 3, and the ratio of 21 to 3 a multiple ratio.</p><p>SUBPŒNA, in <hi rend="italic">Law,</hi> a writ by which persons are called into chancery, in cases where the common law has provided an ordinary remedy ; and the name of it proceeds from the words therein, which charge the party called to appear at the day and place affirmed, “ sub pcεna centum librarum,” &amp;c.</p><p>SUBREPTITIOUS, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Surreptitious,</hi> a term applied to a letter, license, patent, or other act, fraudulently obtained of a superior, by concealing some truth which, had it been known, would have prevented the concession or grant.</p><p>SUBROGATION, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Subrogation,</hi> in the civil law, the act of substituting a person in the place, and entitling him to the rights, of another. In its general sense, subrogation implies a succession of any kind, whether of a person to a person, or of a person to a thing.</p><p>SUBROY, a small town of Hindustan, province of Cutch, on the Gulf of Cutch, from which place it is distant twenty- three miles to the north. This town stands on a rising ground on the road from Luckput Bunder to Mundavie, and is defended by a castle. It is populous and flourishing, and the surrounding country is tolerably well cultivated.</p><p>SUBSTRACTION, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Subtraction,</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Arithmetic,</hi> the second rule, or rather operation, in arithmetic, whereby we deduct a less number from a greater, to learn their precise difference.</p><p>SUBTANGENT <hi rend="smallcaps">of λ Curve,</hi> the line that determines the intersection of a tangent with the axis, or that determines the point wherein the tangent cuts the axis prolonged.</p><p>SUBTENSE, formed from <hi rend="italic">sυb,</hi> under, and <hi rend="italic">tendo,</hi> I stretch, in <hi rend="italic">Geometry,</hi> a right line which is opposite to an angle, and drawn between the two extremities of the arc which measures that angle.</p><p>SUBUNREEKA, a river of Hindustan, which has its source in the province of Bahar, district of Chuta Nagpeor, whence it flows in a south-easterly direction, and after a winding course of 250 miles falls into the Bay of Bengal. It is fordable except in the rainy season. It was the first river of Bengal into which Europeans were allowed to Alter. The channel is now choked up with sand.</p><p>SUCCADANA, a town on the west coast of the island of Borneo. It is situated on the principal or southern outlet of a large river, which is navigable 150 miles for prows. It is celebrated for very large diamonds, and also for the best camphire ; and is a considerable mart for opium, the sale of which is monopolized by the rajah and his family. It is the custom here, as at all the eastern ports, to give a present at the first audience, in proportion to the rank of the person visited ; to the king about fifty dollars, to the rajah thirty, and the shahbunder and agent about twenty each. Gold dust, tin, and pepper, are also to be procured here. Lat. 1. 30. S.</p><p>SUCCULA, in <hi rend="italic">Mechanics,</hi> an axis or cylinder with staves in it to move it round, but without any tympanum or pc- ritrochium.</p><p>SUCKLING, <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir John,</hi> an English poet and dramatist, was the son of Sir John Suckling, comptroller of the household to King Charles I. anti was born in the year 1608-9. He is supposed to have been born at Twickenham, as it appears from the parish-register that he was baptized there on the 10th of February. He discovered an uncommon aptitude for the acquiring of languages, insomuch that he is reported to have spoken Latin at five years of age, and to have written it at nine. When he grew up, he travelled ; but seems to have affected nothing more than the character of a courtier and fine gentleman ; which he so far attained that he was allowed io have the peculiar happiness of making every thing he did become him. In his travels he made a campaign under the great Gustavus Adolphus ; and his loyalty, if not his valour, appeared in the beginning of our civil wars ; for, after his return to England, he raised a troop of horse for the king’s service, entirely at his own charge, and mounted them so completely and richly that they are said to have cost him L.12.000. This troop, with Sir John at its head, behaved so ill in the engagement with the Scots, upon the English borders, in 1639, as to occasion a famous lampoon, composed by Sir John Mennig, which was set to a brisk tune, and much sung by the parliamentarians. This disastrous expedition, and the ridicule that attended it, were supposed to have hastened his death ; but he survived till the 7th of May 1741. He was a sprightly wit and an easy versifier, but no great poet. His poems, plays, speeches, tracts, and letters, were collected into an octavo volume in the year 1709.</p><p>SUCKUT, a small town and district of Hindustan, province of Lahore, intersected by the Beyah river, belonging to the Sikhs. Long. 75. 45. E. Lot. 32. 41. N.</p><p>SUCTASGUR, a town and fortress of Hindustan, province of Allahabad. The fortifications were formerly more considerable, and defended the passes of the western hills. They are now neglected. It is the capital of a small district, which was included in the collectorship of Benares. It is fourteen miles south of the fortress of Chunar.</p><p>SUDASHYGUR, a fortress of Hindustan, on the western shore of the province of Canara. It is situated on a high point of land, and being remarkably white, is a conspicuous point from the sea. It commands the entrance of the Aliga river.</p><p>SUDATORY, a name given by the ancient Romans to their hot or sweating-rooms ; sometimes also called <hi rend="italic">Laconica.</hi></p><p>SUDBURY, a town in the hundred of Babergh and county of Suffolk, fifty-six miles from London. It stands on the river Stour, which divides it from Essex, and is navigable to the sea by Manningtree. The town comprises three parishes, with each a church, and is tolerably well built. It was one of the earliest seats of the woollen manufacture, some share of which it still retains ; and it has likewise some silk trade. It is a borough, governed by a mayor, six aldermen, and twenty-three common-council men, and returns two members to the House of Commons. It has a good market on Saturdays. The inhabitants in 1801 amounted to 3263, in 1811 to 8471, in 1821 to 3950, and in 1881 to 4677.</p><p>SUECA, a city of Spain, in the province of Valencia, and government of Alcira. It stands on the banks of the river Xucar, in a marshy soil, which, though not very favourable to health, is well adapted for the growth of rice, which is here cultivated to a great extent. In the town there is a church, with a monastery and a chapel ; and it contains 700 dwellings, with 4800 inhabitants.</p></body></text></TEI>