<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196389_0609.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0603-10" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SAIL</label>,
in navigation, an aſſemblage of ſeveral breadths of canvas ſewed together by the lifts, and edged round with cord, faſtened to the yards of a ſhip, to make it drive before the wind. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Ship.</hi></p><p>The edges of the cloths, or pieces, of which a ſail is compoſed, are generally ſewed together with a double ſeam; and the whole is ſkirted round at the edges with a cord, called the <hi rend="italic">bolt-rope.</hi></p><p>Although the form of ſails is extremely different, they are all nevertheleſs triangular or quadrilateral figures; or, in other words, their ſurfaces are contained either between three or four ſides.</p><p>The former of theſe are ſometimes ſpread by a yard, as lateen-ſails; and otherwiſe by a ſtay, as ſtay-ſails; or by a maſt, as ſhoulder of-mutton ſails; in all which caſes the foremoſt leech or edge is attached to the ſaid yard, maſt, or ſtay, throughout its whole length. The latter, or thoſe which are four-ſided, are either extended by yards, as the principal ſails of a ſhip; or by yards and booms, as the ſtudding-ſails, drivers, ringtails, and all thoſe ſails which are ſet occaſionally; or by gaffs and booms, as the main-ſails of ſloops and brigantines.</p><p>The principal ſails of a ſhip(PlateCCCCXLIV. fig. 2.) are the courſes or lower fails a; the top-ſails <hi rend="italic">b,</hi> which are next in order above the courſes; and the top-gallant ſails <hi rend="italic">c</hi>, which are expanded above the top-ſails.</p><p>The courſes are the main-ſail, fore-ſail, and mizen, main ſtay-ſail, fore ſtay-ſail, and mizen ſtay-ſail: but more particularly the three firſt. The main-ſtay ſail is rarely uſed except in ſmall veſſels.</p><p>In all quadrangular ſails the upper edge is called the <hi rend="italic">head</hi>; the ſides or ſkirts are called <hi rend="italic">leeches</hi>; and the bottom or lower edge is termed the <hi rend="italic">foot.</hi> If the head is parallel to the foot, the two lower corners are denominated <hi rend="italic">clues,</hi> and the upper corners earings.</p><p>In all triangular ſails, and in thoſe four-ſided ſails wherein the head is not parallel to the foot, the foremoſt corner at the foot is called the <hi rend="italic">tack,</hi> and the after lower-corner the <hi rend="italic">clue</hi>; the foremoſt perpendicular or sſoping edge is called the <hi rend="italic">fore-leech,</hi> and the hindmoſt the <hi rend="italic">after-leech.</hi><pb facs="gri_33125011196389_0610.tif" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0604"/>
The heads of all four-ſided ſails, and the fore-leeches of lateen-ſails, are attached to their reſpective yard or gaff by a number of ſmall cords called <hi rend="italic">ro-bands</hi>; and the extremities are tied to the yard-arms, or to the peek of the gaff, by earings.</p><p>The ſtay-ſails are extended upon ſtays between the maſts, whereon they are drawn up of down occaſionally, as a curtain Aides upon its rod, and their lower parts are ſtretched out by a tack and ſheet. The clues of a top- ſail are drawn cut to the extremities of the lower yard, by two large ropes called the <hi rend="italic">top-ſail ſheets</hi>; and the clues of the top-gallant ſails are in like manner extended upon the top-ſail yard-arms, as exhibited by fig. 2.</p><p>The ſtudding-ſails are ſet beyond the leeches or ſkirts of the main-ſail and fore-ſail, or of the top-ſails or top-gallant ſails of a ſhip. Their upper and lower edges are accordingly extended by poles run out beyond the extremities of the yards for this purpoſe. Thoſe ſails, however, are only ſet in favourable winds and moderate weather.</p><p>All ſails derive their name from the maſt, yard, or flay, upon which they are extended. Thus the principal ſail extended upon the main-maſt is called the <hi rend="italic">main- ſail, d</hi>; the next above, which ſtands upon the main-top malt, is termed the <hi rend="italic">main-top ſail, e</hi>; and the higheſt, which is ſpread acroſs the main-top-gallant maſt, is named the <hi rend="italic">main-top-gallant ſail, f.</hi></p><p>In the ſame manner there is the fore-ſail, <hi rend="italic">g</hi>; the fore top-ſail, <hi rend="italic">h</hi>; and the fore-top-gallant-ſail, i; the mizen, <hi rend="italic">k</hi>; the mizen top-ſail, l; and mizen top-gallant-ſail, <hi rend="italic">m.</hi> Thus alſo there is the main-ſtay-ſail, <hi rend="italic">o;</hi> main-top-maſt ſtay-ſail, <hi rend="italic">p</hi>; and main-top-gallant ſtay- fail, <hi rend="italic">q</hi>; with a middle ſtay-ſail which ſtands between the two laſt.</p><p><hi rend="italic">N. B.</hi> All theſe ſtay-ſails are between the main and fore-maſts.</p><p>The ſtay-ſails between the main-maſt and mizen-maſt are the mizen ſtay-ſail, <hi rend="italic">r;</hi> and the mizen top-maſt ſtay-ſail, s; and ſometimes a mizen top-gallant ſtay-ſail above the latter.</p><p>The ſtay-ſails between the foremaſt and the bow- ſprit are the fore ſtay-ſail, <hi rend="italic">t</hi>; the fore top-maſt ſtay-ſail u; and the jib, <hi rend="italic">x.</hi> There is beſides two ſquare ſails extended by yards under the bow-ſprit, one of which is called the <hi rend="italic">ſprit-ſail, y;</hi> and the other the <hi rend="italic">ſprit-ſail top-ſail, z.</hi></p><p>The ſtudding-ſails being extended upon the different yards of the main-maſt and fore-maſt, are likewiſe named according to their ſtations, the <hi rend="italic">lower, top-maſt,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">top-gallant ſtudding ſails.</hi></p><p>The ropes by which the lower yards of a ſhip are hoiſted up to their proper height on the malts, are called the <hi rend="italic">jears.</hi> In all other ſails the ropes employed for this purpoſe are called <hi rend="italic">hαliαrds.</hi></p><p>The principal ſails are then expanded by haliards, ſheets, and bowlines; except the courſes, which are always ſtretched out below by a tack and ſheet. They are drawn up together, or truſſed up, by bunt-lines, clue-lines, <hi rend="italic">d d</hi>; leech-lines, <hi rend="italic">e e</hi>; reef-tackles, <hi rend="italic">ſſ</hi>; ffab- line, <hi rend="italic">g</hi>; and ſpiling-lines. As the bunt-lines and leech-lines paſs on the other fide of the ſail, they are expreſſed by the dotted lines in the figure.</p><p>The courſes, top-ſails, and top-gallant ſails, are wheeled about the maſt, ſo as to fuit the various directions of the wind by braces. The higher ſtud- ding ſails, and in general all the ſtay-ſails, are drawn down, ſo as to be furled, or taken in, by down-hauls.</p><p>Some experienced ſail-makers contend, that it would be of much advantage if many of the ſails of ſhips were made of equal magnitude; in which cafe, when neceſſity required it, they could be interchangeably uſed. For example, as the mizen top-ſail is now made nearly as large as the main top-gallant ſail, it would be eaſy to make the yards, maſts, and ſails, ſo as mutually to ſuit each other. The main and fore-top ſails differ about two feet at head and foot, and from one to three feet in depth. Theſe likewiſe could be eaſily made alike, and in ſome caſes they are ſo. The ſame may be ſaid of the main and fore top-gallant ſails, and of the mizen top-gallant ſail, and main fore-royal. The main-ſail and fore-ſail might alſo, with reſpect to their head, be made alike; but as the former has a gore at the leech, and a larger gore at the foot for clearing it of the gallows, boats, &amp;c. which the latter has not, there might be more difficulty in arranging them. The difficulty, however, appears not to be inſurmountable. Theſe alterations, it is thought, would be extremely uſeful in the event of loſing ſails by ſtreſs of weather. Fewer ſails would be thus neceſſary, leſs room would be required to ſtow them, and there would be leſs danger of con- fuſion in taking them out. But perhaps the utility of theſe alterations will be more felt in the merchant-ſervice than in the navy, which latter has always a large ſtore of ſpare ſails, and ſufficient room to ſtow them in order. Thus, too, ſpare yards and maſts might be con- ſiderably reduced in number, and yet any caſual damages more eaſily repaired at ſea. Top-maſt ſtudding ſails are occaſionally ſubſtituted for awnings, and might, by a very little attention in planning the rigging of a ſhip, be ſo contrived as to anſwer both purpoſes. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Ship-building.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sail</hi> is alſo a name applied to any veſſel beheld at a diſtance under ſail.</p><p><hi rend="italic">To ſet</hi> <hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Sail,</hi> is to unfurl and expand the ſails upon their reſpective yards and ſtays, in order to begin the action of ſailing.</p><p><hi rend="italic">To Make</hi> <hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Sail,</hi> is to ſpread an additional quantity of ſail, ſo as to increaſe the ſhip’s velocity.</p><p><hi rend="italic">To /horten</hi> <hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Sail,</hi> is to reduce or take in part of the ſails, with an intention to diminiſh the ſhip’s velocity.</p><p><hi rend="italic">To Strike</hi> <hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Sail,</hi> is to lower it ſuddenly. This is particularly uſed in ſaluting or doing homage to a ſuperior force, or to one whom the law of nations acknowledges as ſuperior in certain regions. Thus all foreign veſſels ſtrike to a Britiſh man of war in the Britiſh ſeas.</p></div></body></text></TEI>