<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196389_0707.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0701-01" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SCHISTUS</label>,
in mineralogy, a name given to ſeveral different kinds of ſtones, but more eſpecially to ſome of the argillaceous kind; as,</p><p>1. The bluiſh purple ſchiſtus, ſchiſtus tegularis, or common roof ſlate. This is ſo ſoft that it may be ſlightly ſcraped with the nail, and is of a very brittle lamellated texture, of the ſpeciſic gravity of 2,876. It is fuſible <hi rend="italic">per se</hi> in a ſtrong heat, and runs into a black ſcoria. By a chemical analyſis it is found to conſiſt of 26 parts of argillaceous earth, 46 of ſiliceous earth, 8 of magneſia, 4 of calcareous earth, and 14 of iron. The dark-blue ſlate, or ſchiſtus ſcriptorius, contains more magneſia and leſs iron than the common purple ſchiſtus, and efferveſces more briſkly with acids. Its ſpeciſic gravity is 2,701.</p><p>2. The pyritaceous ſchiſtus is of a grey colour, brown, blue, or black; and capable of more or leſs decompoſition by expoſure to the air, according to the quantity of pyritous matter it contains and the ſtate of the iron in it. When this laſt is in a ſemi-phlogiſticattd ſtate it is eaſily decompoſed; but very ſlowly, or not at all, if the calx is much dephlogiſticated. The aluminous ſchiſtus belongs to this ſpecies.</p><p>3. The bituminous ſchiſtus is generally black, and of a lamellated texture, of various degrees of hardneſs, not giving fire with ſteel, but emitting a ſtrong ſmell when heated, and ſometimes without being heated. M. Magellan mentions a ſpecimen which burns like coal, with a ſtrong ſmell of mineral bitumen, but of a yellowiſh brown, or rather dark aſh-colour, found in Yorkſhire. — This kind of ſchiſtus does not ſhow any white mark when ſcratched like the other ſchiſtus.</p></div></body></text></TEI>