<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196389_0643.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0637-01" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SAMBUCUS, <hi rend="smallcaps">elder,</hi></label>
 in botany: A genus of the trigynia order, belonging to the pentandria claſs of plants; and in the natural method ranking under the<pb facs="gri_33125011196389_0644.tif" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0638"/>
43d order, <hi rend="italic">Dumofae.</hi> The calyx is quinquepartite; the corolla quinqueſid; the berry triſpermous.</p><p>The moſt remarkable ſpecies are, I. The nigra, or common black elder-tree, riſes with a tree-ſtem, branching numerouſly into a large ſpreading head, twenty or thirty feet high; pinnated leaves, of two or three pair of oval lobes and an odd one; and large five parted umbels of white flowers towards the ends of the branches, ſucceeded by bunches of black and other different coloured berries, in the varieties; which are. —Common black-berried elder-tree—White-berried elder—Green- berried elder—Laciniated, or parſley-leaved elder, having the folioles much laciniated, ſo as to reſemble parſley leaves—Gold-ſtriped-leaved elder—Silver-ſtriped elder—Silver-duſted elder. 2. The racemoſa, race-moſe red-berried elder, riſes with a tree-like ſtem, branching ten or twelve feet high, having reddiſh-brown branches and buds; pinnated leaves of ſix or ſeven oval deeply-ſawed lobes; and compound, oval, racemous, cluſters of wſhitiſh-green flowers, ſucceeded by oval cluſters of red berries. This is a reſident of the mountainous parts of the ſouth of Europe, and is retained in our gardens as a flowering ſhrub, having a peculiar Angularity in its oval-cluſtered flowers and berries. 3. The Canadenſis, or Canada ſhrubby elder, riſes with a ſhrub- by ſtem, branching eight or ten feet high, having reddiſh ſhoots; ſomewhat bipinnated leaves, often ternate below, the other compoſed of five, ſeven, or nine oval lobes; and towards the ends of the branches, cymoſe. quinquepartite umbels of flowers, ſucceeded by blackiſh red berries. All the forts of elder are of the deciduous tribe, very hardy, and grow freely anywhere; are generally free ſhooters, but particularly the common elder and varieties, which make remarkably ſtrong, jointed ſhoots, of ſeveral feet in length, in one ſeaſon; and they flower moſtly in ſummer, except the racemoſe elder, which generally begins flowering in April; and the branches being large, ſpreading, and very abundant, are exceedingly conſpicuous; but they emit a moſt diſagreeable odour. The flowers are ſucceeded in the moſt of the forts by large bunches of ripe berries in autumn, which, although very unpalateable to eat, are in high eſtimation for making that well known cordial liquor called <hi rend="italic">elder wine,</hi> particularly the common black- berried elder. The merit of the elder in gardening may be both for uſe and ornament, eſpecially in large grounds.</p></div></body></text></TEI>