<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196389_0655.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0649-01" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SANDYS</label>
(Sir Edwin), ſecond ſon of Dr Edwin Sandys archbiſhop of York, was born about 1561, and educated at Oxford under Mr Richard Hooker, author of the Eccleſiaſtical Polity. In 1581 he was collated to a prebend in the cathedral of York. He travelled into foreign countries; and, upon his return, grew famous for learning, prudence, and virtue. While he was at Paris, he drew up a tract, publiſhed under the title of <hi rend="italic">Europae Speculum.</hi> In 1602, he reſigned his prebend; and, the year following, was knighted by king James I. who employed him in ſeveral important affairs. He was dexterous in any great employment, and a good patriot. However, oppoſing the court with vigour in the parliament held in 1621, he, with Mr Selden, was committed to cuſtody for a month. He died in 1629, having bequeathed 15001. to the univerſity of Oxford, for the endowment of a metaphyſical lecture.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sandys</hi> (George), brother of the foregoing Sir Edwin, and youngeſt ſon of archbiſhop Sandys, was bora in 1577. He was a moſt accompliſhed gentleman; travelled over ſeveral parts of Europe and the Eaſt; and publiſhed a relation of his journey in folio, in 1615. He made an elegant tranſlation of Ovid’s Metamorphoſes; and compoſed ſome poetical pieces of his own, that were greatly admired in the times of their being written. He alſo paraphraſed the Pſalms; and has left behind him a Tranſlation, with Notes, of one Sacred Drama written originally by Grotius, under the title of <hi rend="italic">Christus Patiens;</hi> on which, and A <hi rend="italic">damus Exul,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Masenιus,</hi> is founded Lauder’s impudent charge of plagiariſm againſt our immortal Milton. Our author became one of the privy chamber to Charles I. and died in 1643.</p></div></body></text></TEI>