<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196389_0711.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0705-11" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SCILLA</label>,
the <hi rend="smallcaps">squill,</hi> in botany: A genus of the monogynia order, belonging to the hexandria claſs of plants; and in the natural method ranking under the 10th order, <hi rend="italic">Coronaria.</hi> The corolla is hexapetalous and deciduous; the filaments filiform.</p><p>The moſt remarkable ſpecies is the maritima, or ſea- onion, whoſe roots are uſed in medicine. Of this there are two forts, one with a red, and the other with a white root; which are suppoſed to be accidental varieties, but the white are generally preferred for medicinal uſe. The roots are large, ſomewſhat oval-ſhaped, compoſed of many coats dying over each other like onions; and at the bottom come out ſeveral fibres. From the middle of the root ariſe ſeveral ſhining leaves, which continue green all the winter, and decay in the ſpring. Then the flower-ſtalk comes out, which riſes two feet high, and is naked half-way, terminating in a pyramidal thyrſe of flowers, which are white, compoſed of ſix petals, which ſpread open like the points of a ſtar. This grows naturally on the ſea-ſhores, and in the ditches, where the ſalt-water naturally flows with the tide, in moſt of the warm parts of Europe, ſo cannot be propagated in gardens; the froſt in winter al-<pb facs="gri_33125011196389_0712.tif" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0706"/>
ways deſtroying the roots, and for want of ſalt-water they do not thrive in ſummer. Sometimes the roots which are bought for uſe put forth their stems and produce flowers, as they lie in the druggiſts ſhops. — This root is very nauſeous to the taſte, intenſely bitter, and ſo acrimonious, that it ulcerates the ſkin if much handled. Taken internally, it powerfully ſtimulates the ſolids, and promotes urine, ſweat, and expectoration. If the doſe is conſiderable, it proves emetic, and ſometimes purgative. The principal uſe of this medicine is where the primae viae abound with mucous matter, and the lungs are oppreſſed by tenacious phlegm. It has been recommended in hydropic caſts, taken in powder, from four to ten grains in a dole, mixed with a double quantity of nitre. The moſt commodious mode of exhibiting this root is as a bolus or pill. Liquid forms are too diſagreeable to moſt people; though this may be remedied in ſome degree by the addition of ſome aromatic diſtiſted waters. It yields the whole of its virtues to aqueous and vinous menſtrua, and likewiſe to vegetable acids.</p></div></body></text></TEI>