<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196389_0665.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0659-02" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SARDANAPALUS</label>,
the laſt king of Aſſyria, whoſe character is one of the moſt infamous in hiſtory. He is ſaid to have ſunk ſo far in depravity, that, as far as he could, he changed his very ſex and nature. He clothed himſelf as a woman, and ſpun amidſt companies of his concubines. He painted his face, and behaved in a more lewd manner than the moſt laſcivious harlot. In ſhort, he buried himſelf in the moſt unbounded ſenſuality, quite regardleſs of ſex and the dictates of nature. Having grown odious to all his ſubjects, a rebellion was formed againſt him. by Arbaces the Mede and Belefis the Babylonian. They were attended, however, with very bad ſucceſs at firſt, being defeated with great Slaughter in three pitched battles. With great difficulty' Belefis prevailed upon his men to keep the field only five days longer; when they were joined by the Bactrinus, who had come to the aſſiſtance of Sardanapalus, but</p><p>had been prevailed upon to renounce their allegiance to him. With this reinforcement they twice defeated the troops of Sardanapalus, who ſhut himſelf up in Nineveh the capital of his empire. The city held out for three years; at the end of which, Sardanapalus finding himſelf unable to hold out any longer, and dreading to fall into the hands of an enraged enemy, retired into his palace, in a court of which be cauſed a vaſt pile of wood to be railed; and heaping upon it all his gold and filler, and royal apparel, and at the ſame time incloſing his eunuchs and concubines in an apartment within the pile, he ſet fire to it, and ſo deſtroyed himſelf and all together.</p></div></body></text></TEI>