<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196389_0671.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0665-04" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SATYAVRATA</label>,
or <hi rend="smallcaps">Menu,</hi> in Indian mythology, is believed by the Hindoos to have reigned over the whole world in the earlieſt age of their chronology, and to have reſided in the country of Dravira on the coaſt of the eaſtern Indian peninſula. His patronymic name was <hi rend="italic">Vaivaſwata</hi>, or <hi rend="italic">child oſ the ſun.</hi> In the <hi rend="italic">Bhagavat</hi> we are informed, that the Lord of the Univerſe, intending to preſerve him from the ſea of deſtruction, cauſed by the depravity of the age, thus told him how he was to act. “In ſeven days from the preſent time, O thou tamer of enemies, the three worlds will be plunged in an ocean of death; but, in the midſt of the deſtroying waves, a large veffel, ſent by me for thy uſe, ſhall ſtand before thee. Then ſhalt thou take all medicinal herbs, all the variety of ſeeds; and, accompanied by ſeven ſaints, encircled by pairs of all brute animals, thou ſhalt enter the ſpacious ark and continue in it, ſecure from the flood on one immenſe ocean without light, except the radiance of thy holy companions. When the ſhip ſhall be agitated by an impetuous wind, thou</p><p>ſhalt faſten it with a large ſea-ſerpent on my horn; for I will be near thee: drawing the veffel, with thee and thy attendants, I will remain on the ocean, O chief of men, until a night of Brahma ſhall be completely ended. Thou ſhalt then know my true greatneſs, rightly named the ſupreme Godhead; by my favour, all thy queſtions ſhall be anſwered, and thy mind abundantly in- ſtructed. ” All this is ſaid to have been accompliſhed; and the ſtory is evidently that of Noah diſguiſed by A- ſiatic fiction and allegory. It proves, as Sir William Jones has rightly obſerved, an ancient Indian tradition of the univerſal deluge deſcribed by Moſes; and enables us to trace the connection between the eaſtern and weſtern traditions relating to that event. The ſame learned author has ſhown it to be in the higheſt degree probable, that the <hi rend="italic">Satyavrata</hi> of India is the <hi rend="italic">Cronus</hi> of Greece and the <hi rend="italic">Saturn</hi> of Italy. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Saturn</hi>; and <hi rend="italic">Aſiatic Reſearches,</hi> Vol. I. p. 230, &amp;c.</p></div></body></text></TEI>