<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196389_0667.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0661-15" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SATURN</label>,
in aſtronomy, one of the planets of our ſolar ſyſtem, revolving at the diſtance of more than 900 millions of miles from the fun. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Astronomy,</hi> n⁰ 31, 104—109, 191, and 269.</p><p>Dr Herſchel, who has ſo much ſignalized himſelf by his diſcoveries in the celeſtial regions, has not omitted to make his obſervarions on this planet, which he conſi ders as one of the moſt engaging objects that aſtronomy offers to our view. His attention was firſt drawn to it in the year 1774, when he ſaw its ring reſembling in appearance a narrow line, extending on both ſides not much leſs than the diameter oſ the planet’s diſk. The obſervation was taken with a five and an half feet re-<pb facs="gri_33125011196389_0668.tif" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0662"/>
flector on the 17th of March; and on the 3d of April, the ſame year, when the planet appeared totally deprived of this noble appendage, by reaſon of the edge of the ring being then turned directly towards the earth, and inviſible on account of its thinneſs or incapacity to reflect the light to ſuch a diſtance. During the ſuccecding year, the ring appeared gradually opened, and at laſt aſſumed the ſhape of an ellipſe. “It ſhould be noticed (ſays he), that the black diſk or belt upon the ring of Saturn is not in the middle of its breadth. Nor is the ring ſubdivided by many ſuch lines, as has been repreſented in ſeveral treatiſes of aſtronomy; but that there is one Angle, dark, conſiderably broad line, belt, or zone, upon the ring, which I have always permanently found in the place where my figure repreſents it. ”</p><p>This zone, which is on the northern part of the ring, does not change its ſhape or colour like the belts of Jupiter, ſo that it is probably owing to ſome permanent projection. It cannot, however, be the ſhadow of a chain of mountains, as it is viſible all round the ring; and there could be no ſhades viſible at the ends of the anſae, on account of the direction of the ſun’s illumination, which would be in the line of the chain; and the ſuppoſed argument will hold good againſt the ſuppoſition of caverns or concavities. It is likewiſe evident, that this dark zone is contained between two concentric circles, as all the phenomena anſwer to the projection of ſuch a zone. The Doctor gives a figure, repreſenting the planetas it appeared to him on the 10th of May 1780; whence we ſee that the zone is continued all the way round, with a gradual decreaſe towards the middle, anſwering to the appearance of a narrow circular plane projected into an ellipſis. See Philoſoph. Tranf. for 1790, p. 3, &amp;c.</p><p>It hath been conjectured, that this appearance is owing to a diviſion of the ring, or rather that there are two rings about the planet; “but (lays Dr Herſchel) if one ring, of a breadth ſo conſiderable as that of Saturn, is juſtlv to be eſteemed the moſt wonderful arch that by the laws of gravity can be held together, how improbable muſt it appear to ſuppoſe it ſubdivided into narrow flips of rings, which by this ſeparation will be deprived of a ſufficient depth, and thus loſe the only dimenſion which can keep them from falling upon the planet? It is true, indeed, that it may revolve with ſuch velocity as greatly to aſſiſt its ſtrength, and that in the ſubdiviſions, of courſe, the different velocities for each diviſion may be equally ſuppoſed to keep them up. ”</p><p>As to the ſubſtance of the ting, the Doctor ſuppoſes it to be no leſs ſolid than that of Saturn himſelf. Thus in the two figures given with the Doctor’s Diſſertation in the Philoſophical Tranſactions above referred to, the ſhadow of the planet is delineated upon the ring as it actually appeared, according to the ſituation of the ſun; and in like manner we will ſee the ſhadow of the ring upon the planet: and if we deduce the quantity of matter contained in the planet from the power by which the ſatellites are preſerved in their orbits, the ring muſt alſo be taken into account. It is indeed evident that the ring exerts a very conſiderable force upon theſe bodies, ſince we find them affected with many irregularities in their motions, which we cannot properly aſcribe to any other cauſe than the quantity of matter contained in the ring; or, at leaſt, it ought to be allowed to have a proper ſhare in producing them.</p><p>The ring ſeems to be endowed with a greater reflective power than the body of the planet; and the Doctor gives inſtances of his feeing part of the ring brighter than Saturn himſelf, as well as of his feeing it plainly through a teleſcope which could ſcarcely afford light enough for the planet. The moſt remarkable property of this wonderful ring, however, is its extreme thinneſs. “When we were nearly in the plane of the ring (ſays our author), I have repeatedly ſeen the ſirſt, ſecond, and third ſatellites, nay even the ſixth and ſeventh. paſs before and behind the ring in ſuch a manner that they ſerved as excellent micrometers to eſtimate its thickneſs. It may be proper to mention a few inſtances, eſpecially as they will ſerve to ſolve ſome phenomena that have been remarked by other aſtronomers, though they have not been accounted for in a manner conſiſtently with other known facts. July 18th 1789, at 19 <hi rend="superscript"> h</hi> 41' 9 <hi rend="italic">",</hi> ſidereal time, the firſt ſatellite ſeemed to hang upon the following arm, declining à little towards the north, and I ſaw it gradually advance upon it towards the body of Saturn; but the ring was not ſo thick as the lucid point. July 23d, at 19 <hi rend="superscript"> h</hi> 41' 8''; the ſecond ſatellite was a very little preceding the ring; but the ring appeared to be leſs than half the thickneſs of the ſatellite. July 27th, at 20 <hi rend="superscript"> h</hi> 15' 12", the ſecond ſatellite was about the middle, upon the following arm of the ring, and towards the ſouth; and the ſixth ſatellite on the farther end towards the north; but the arm was thinner than either of them, Aug. 29th, at 22 <hi rend="superscript"> h</hi> 12' 55", the third ſatellite was upon the ring, near the end of the preceding arm, when the latter ſeemed not to be the fourth, or at moſt the third part of the diameter of the ſatellite; which, in the ſituation it was, I took to be leſs than one ſingle ſecond in diameter. At the ſame time, I alſo ſaw the ſeventh ſatellite following the third, at a little diſtance, in the ſhape of a bead upon a thread, projecting on both ſides of the ſame arm. Hence alſo we are ſure that the arm appeared thinner than the ſeventh ſatellite, which is conſiderably ſmaller than the ſixth, which again is leſs than the ſirſt Auguſt 31 ft, at 20 <hi rend="superscript"> h</hi> 48' 26", the preceding arm was loaded about the middle with the third ſatellite. October 15th, at 0 <hi rend="superscript"> h</hi> 43' 44", I ſaw the ſixth ſatellite, without obſtruction, about the middle of the preceding arm, though the ring was but barely viſible with my 40 feet reflector, even while the planet was in the meridian. However, we were then a little inclined to the plane of the ring, and the third ſatellite, when it came near its conjunction with the ſirſt, was ſo ſituated, that it muſt have partly covered it a few minutesafter I loſt it behind my houſe. In all theſe obſervatiυns, the ring did not in the leaſt interfere with my view of the ſatellites. October 16th, I followed the ſixth and ſeventh ſatellites up to the very diſk of the planet; and the ring, which was extremely faint, did</p><p>not in the leaſt obſtruct my ſeeing them gradually approach the diſk, wſhere the ſeventh vaniſhed at 21 <hi rend="superscript"> h</hi> 46⁰ 44", and the ſixth at 22 <hi rend="superscript"> h</hi> 36' 44". There is, however, ſome ſuſpicion, that by a refraction through ſome very rare atmoſphere on the two planes of the ring, the ſatellites might be lifted up and depreſſed ſo as to become viſible on both ſides of the ring, even though the latter ſhould be equal in thickneſs to the diameter of the ſmalleſt ſatellite, which may amount to 1000 miles. — As for the arguments of its incredible thinneſs. which<pb facs="gri_33125011196389_0669.tif" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0663"/>
ſome aſtronomers have brought from the ſhort time of its being invifible when the earth paſſes through its plane, we cannot ſet much value upon them; for they mult have ſuppoſed the edge of the ring, as they have alſo repreſented it in their figures, to be ſquare; but there is the greateſt reaſon to ſuppoſe it either ſpherical or ſpheroidal; in which caſe evidently the ring cannot diſappear for any long time. Nay, I may venture to ſay, that the ring cannot poſſibly diſappear, on account of its thinneſs; ſince, either from the edge or the ſides, even if it were ſquare on the corners, it muſt always expoſe to our ſight ſome part which is illuminated by the rays of the ſun; and that this is plainly the caſe we may conclude from its being viſible in my teleſcopes during the time when others of leſs light had loſt it; and when evidently we were turned towards the unenlightened ſide, ſo that we muſt either ſee the rounding ſide of the unenlightened edge, or elſe the reflection of the light of Saturn upon the ſide of the darkened ring, as we ſee the reflected light of the earth on the darkened part of the new moon. I will not, however, take upon me to decide which of the two maybe the caſe, eſpecially as there are other very ſtrong reaſons which induce us to think that the edge of the ring is oſ ſuch a nature as not to reflect much light. ”</p><p>Several aſtronomers have ſuppoſed that the ring of Saturn is full of mountains and inequalities, like the moon; and of this opinion Dr Herſchel himſelf was for a conſiderable time, till happening to obſerve one of theſe lucid points with attention for a conſiderable time, he ſaw it leave the ring altogether, and ſhow itſelf as a ſatellite never before obſerved. With regard to the ring itſelf, he concludes his obſervations in theſe words: “Upon the whole, therefore, I cannot ſay that I had any one inſtance that could induce me to believe that the ring was not of one uniform thickneſs; that is, equally thick at equal diſtances from the centre, and of an equal diameter throughout the whole of its conſtruction. The idea of protuberant points upon the ring of Saturn, indeed, is of itſelf ſufficient to render their exiſtence inadmiſſible, when we conſider the enormous ſize which ſuch points ought to be of to render them viſible at the diſtance we are from that planet.</p><p>With regard to the ſatellites, the Doctor informs us, that he was long convinced of the exiſtence of a ſixth; and had he been more at leiſure at the time of his diſcovering thoſe of the Georgium Sidus, he would probably have completed the diſcovery of the ſatellites of Saturn alſo. The ſixth was firſt obſerved diſtinctly on the 28th of Auguſt 1789, and the ſeventh on the 17th of September the fame year. Theſe ſatellites, however, do not occupy the place which we ſhould have previouſly ſuppoſed them, being, in fact, the innermoſt of the whole. The ſeventh is next the body of the planet itſelf, and is very ſmall. It revolves at the diſtance of 27. ''366 from the centre of Saturn, and ſeems to move exactly in the plane of the ring; but the Doctor ob- ſerves, that it is exceedingly difficult to make a ſufficient number of obſervations on it to determine the revolution exactly. He computes its periodical time at 22 <hi rend="superscript"> h</hi> 40' 46''. The ſixth ſatellite is next to the ſeventh, and revolves at the diſtance of 35". 058 from the centre of its primary in 1d 8 <hi rend="superscript"> h</hi> 53'9 <hi rend="superscript"> 7</hi>. Its light is conſiderably ſtrong, but not equal to that oſ the firſt ſatellite of former aſtronomers, which Lies immediately beyond it.</p><p>The planet Saturn is now obſerved to have belts or faſciae upon its diſk as diſtinctly as Jupiter. Dr Herſchel, on the 9th of April 1775, obſerved a northern belt on his body, inclined a little to the line of the ring. On the 1st of May 1776, there was another belt obſerved, inclined about 15 <hi rend="superscript"> 0</hi> to the ſame line, but more to the ſouth; and on the following ſide came up to the place where the ring croſſes the body of the planet. — On the 8th of April two belts were obſerved, and theſe continued with variations, and ſometimes the appearance of a third belt, till the 8th of September, when the account of the obſervations was diſcontinued. The Doctor remarks, that he generally obſerved theſe belts in equatorial ſituations, though ſometimes it was other- wiſe. Two concluſions, he ſays, may be drawn from the obſervations he made this year. “The firſt, which relates to the changes in the appearance oſ the belts, is, that Saturn has probably a very conſiderable atmoſphere, in which theſe changes take place, juſt as the alterations in the belts of Jupiter have been ſhewn with great probability to be in his atmoſphere. This has alſo been confirmed by other obſervations. Thus, in occultations of Saturn’s ſatellites, I have found them to hang to the diſk for a long while before they would vaniſh. And though we ought to make ſome allowance for the encroachment of light, whereby a ſatellite is ſeen to reach up to the diſk ſooner than it actually does, yet without a conſiderable refraction it could hardly be kept ſo long in view after the apparent contact. The time of hanging upon the disk in the seventh ſatellite has actually amounted to 20 minutes. Now, as its quick motion during that interval carries it through an arch of near six degrees, we find that this would denote a refraction of about two ſeconds, provided the encroaching of light had no ſhare in producing the effect. By an obſervation of the ſixth ſatellite, the refraction oſ Saturn’s atmoſphere amounts to nearly the ſame quantity; for this ſatellite remained about 14 or 15 minutes longer in view than it ſhould have done; and as it moves about 2 <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi> degrees in that time, and its orbit is larger than that of the ſeventh, the difference is inconſiderable. The next inference we may draw from the appearance of the belts on Saturn is, that this planet turns upon an axis which is perpendicular to his ring. The arrangement of the belts, during the courſe of 14 years that I have obſerved them, has always followed the direction of the ring, which is what I have called <hi rend="italic">being equatorial.</hi> Thus, as the ring opened, the belts began to advance towards the ſouth, and to ſhow an incurvature anſwering to the projection of an equatorial line, or to a parallel of the ſame. When the ring cloſed up, they returned towards the north, and are now, while the ring paſſes over the centre, exactly ranging with the ſhadow of it, on the body, generallv one on each ſide, with a white belt cloſe to it. When I ſay that the belts have always been equatorial, I paſs over trifling exceptions, which certainly were owing to local cauſes. The ſtep from equatorial belts to a rotation on an axis is ſo eaſy, and, in the caſe of Jupiter, ſo well aſcertained, that I ſhall not heſitate to take the ſame conſequence for granted here. But if there could remain a doubt, the obſervations of June 19th, 20th, and 21ft, 1780, where the ſame ſpot upon one of the belts was ſeen in three different ſituations, would remove it completely, ”<pb facs="gri_33125011196389_0670.tif" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0664"/>
Another evidence that Saturn, as well as the other planets, revolves upon its axis, is drawn from its flattened ſhape, like that of Mars, Jupiter, and Saturn. On the 31ftof May 1781, the diſk ſeemed to deviate as much from a true circle as that of Jupiter, though by the interference of the ring this could not be ſo well determined as after an interval of eight years. On the 18th of Auguſt 1787, the difference between the equatorial and polar diameters was meaſured, the mean of three obſervations of the former being 22". 81, of the latter 20". 61. From theſe obſervations, it appears that the polar diameter of Saturn is to his equatorial diameter nearly as 10 to 11; and that his axis is perpendicular to the plane of the ring.</p><p>In a ſubſequent paper, the Doctor gives up his reaſoning againſt fixed lucid points in the ring, in conſequence of having frequently obſerved them in ſuch ſituations as could not by any means be accounted for by the ſatellites. He even attempts to invalidate his own arguments above-mentioned concerning the vaſt magnitude of the mountains neceſſary to make them viſible at this diſtance. “As obſervations (ſays he) carefully made ſhould always take the lead of theories, I ſhall not be concerned if ſuch lucid ſpots as I am now going to admit, ſhould ſeem to contradict what has been ſaid in my laſt paper concerning the idea of inequalities or protuberant points. We may, however, remark, that a lucid and apparently protuberant point may exiſt without any great inequality in the ring. A vivid light, for inſtance, will ſeem to project greatly beyond the limits of the body on which it is placed. If, therefore, the Luminous places on the ring ſhould be ſuch as proceed from very bright reflecting regions, or, which is more probable, owe their exiſtence to the more fluctuating cauſes of inherent fires acting with great violence, we need not imagine the ring of Saturn to be very uneven or diſtorted, in order to preſent us with ſuch appearances. In this ſenſe of the word, then, we may ſtill oppoſe the idea of protuberant points, ſuch as would denote immenſe mountains of elevated ſurface.</p><p>"On comparing together ſeveral obſervations, a few</p><p>trials ſhew that the brighteſt and beſt obſerved ſpot agrees to a revolution of 10 <hi rend="superscript"> h</hi> 32' 15". 4; and calculating its diſtance from the centre of Saturn, on a ſuppoſition of its being a ſatellite, we find it 17". 227, which brings it upon the ring. It is therefore certain, that unleſs we ſhould imagine the ring t® be ſuſſiciently fluid to allow a ſatellite to revolve in it, or ſuppoſe a notch, groove, or diviſion in thc ring, to ſuffer the ſatellite to paſs along, we ought to admit a revolution of the ring itſelf. The denſity of the ring, indeed, may be ſuppoſed to be very inconſiderable by thoſe who imagine its light to be rather the effect of ſome ſhining fluid, like an aurora borealis, than a reflection from ſome permanent ſubſtance; but its diſapparition, in general, and in my teleſcopes its faintneſs, when turned edgewiſe, are in no manner favourable to this idea. —When we add alſo, that this ring caſts a deep ſhadow upon the planet, is very ſharply defined both in its outer and inner edge, and in brightneſs exceeds the planet itſelf, it ſeems to be almoſt proved that its conſiſtence cannot be leſs than the body of Saturn, and that conſequently no degree of fluidity can be admitted ſufficient to permit a revolving body to keep in motion for any length of time. A groove might afford a paſ</p><p>ſage, eſpecially as on a former occaſion we have already conſidered the idea of a divided ring. A circum- ſtance alſo which ſeems rather to favour this idea, is, that in ſome obſervations a bright ſpot has been ſeen to project equally on both ſides, as the ſatellites have been obſerved to do when they paſſed the ring. But, on the other hand, we ought to conſider, that the ſpot has often been obſerved very near the end of the arms of Saturn’s ring, and that the calculated diſtance is conſequetltly a little too ſmall for ſuch appearances, and ought to be 19 or 20 ſeconds at leaſt. We ſhould alſo attend to the ſize of the ſpot, which ſeems to be variable: for it is hardly to be imagined that a ſatellite, brighter than the ſixth, and which could be ſeen with the moon nearly at full, ſhould ſo often eſcape our notice in its frequent revolutions, unleſs it varied much in its apparent brightneſs. To this we muſt add another argument drawn from the number of lucid ſpots, which will not agree with the motion of one ſatellite only; whereas, by admitting a revolution of the ring itſelf in 10 <hi rend="superscript"> h</hi> 32' 15". 4, and ſuppoſing all the ſpots to adhere to the ring, and to ſhare in the fame periodical return, provided they laſt long enough to be ſeen many times, we ſhall be able to give an eaſy ſolution of all the remaining phenomena. See Phil. Tranſi 1790, p. 427.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Saturn,</hi> in chemiſtry, an appellation given to lead.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Saturn,</hi> in heraldry, denotes the black colour in blazoning the arms of ſovereign princes.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Saturn,</hi> one of the principal of the Pagan deities, was the the ſon of Coelus and Terra, and the father of Jupiter. He depoſed and caſtrated his father; and obliged his brother Titan to reſign his crown to him, on condition of his bringing up none of his male iſſue, that the ſucceſſion might at length devolve on him. For this purpoſe he devoured all the ſons he had by his wife Rhea or Cybele: but ſhe bringing forth at one time Jupiter and Juno, ſhe preſented the latter to her huſhand, and ſent the boy to be nurſed on mount Ida; when Saturn being informed of her having a ſon, demanded the child; but in his ſtead his wife gave him a ſtone ſwaddled up like an infant, which he inſtantly ſwallowed. Titan finding that Saturn had violated the contract he had made with him, put himſelf at the head of his children, and made war on his brother, and having made him and Cybele priſoners, confined them in Tartarus; but Jupiter being in the mean time grown up, raiſed an army in Crete, went to his father’s aſſiſt- ance, defeated Titan, and reſtored Saturn to the throne. Some time after, Saturn being told that Jupiter intended to dethrone him, endeavoured to prevent it; but the latter being informed of his intention, depoſed his father, and threw him into Tartarus. But Saturn eſcaping from thence fled into Italy, where he was kindly received by Janus king of the country, who aſſociated him to the government: whence Italy obtained the name of <hi rend="italic">Saturnia Tellus;</hi> as alſo that of <hi rend="italic">Latium,</hi> from <hi rend="italic">latio,</hi> “to lie hid.” There Saturn, by the wiſdom and mildneſs of his government, is ſaid to have produced the golden age.</p><p>Saturn is repreſented as an old man with four wings, armed with a ſcythe; ſometimes he is delineated under the figure of a ſerpent with its tail in its mouth. This is emblematic of the ſeaſons, which roll perpetually in the ſame circle. Sometimes alſo Saturn is painted<pb facs="gri_33125011196389_0671.tif" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0665"/>
with a ſand glaſs in his hand. The Greeks ſay, that the ſtory of his mutilating his father and deſtroying his children is an allegory, which ſignifies, that Time devours the part and preſent, and will alſo devour the future. The Romans, in honour of him, built a temple and celebrated a feſtival, which they called <hi rend="italic">Saturnalia.</hi> During this feſtival no buſineſſs or profeſſion was allowed to be carried on except cookery; all diſtinctions of rank ceaſed; ſlaves could ſay what they pleaſed to their maſters with impunity; they could even rally them with their faults before their faces.</p></div></body></text></TEI>