<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:02:16Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>The language itſelf is a mixture of Perſian, Arabic, and Shanſcrit, grafted upon the provincial dialect of Punjab, which is a kind of Hindowee, or, as we commonly call it, <hi rend="italic">Moors.</hi></p><p>SEGEBERG, a town of Germany, in the duchy of Holſtein, and in Wagria; with a caſtle ſtanding on a high mountain, conſiſting of limeſtone, large quantities of which are carried to Hamburg and Lubeck. It belongs to Denmark, and is ſeated on the river Treve, in E. Long. 10. 9. N. Lat. 54. 0.</p><p>SEGEDIN, a ſtrong town of Lower Hungary, in the county of Czongrad, with a caſtle. The Imperialiſts took it from the Turks in 1686. It is ſeated at the confluence of the rivers Teſſe asd’Maſroch, in E. Long. 20. 35. N. Lat. 46. 28.</p><p>SEGMENT of <hi rend="italic">a </hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Circle,</hi> in geometry, is that part of the circle contained between a chord and an arch of the ſame circle.</p><p>SEGNA, a city of Croatia, belonging to the houſe of Auſtria, and ſeated on the coaſt of the Gulph of Venice. It was formerly a place of ſtrength and great importance; but it has ſuffered many calamities, and its inhabitants at preſent do not amount to 7000. In the beginning of this century it ſent 50 merchant ſhips to ſea; but the inconveniency of its ſituation and badneſs of its harbour, in which the ſea is never calm, diſcouraged navigation, and Segna has now very few ſhips belonging to it. Among the cuſtoms of the Segnans, Mr Fortis mentions one relative to the dead, which for its Angularity may be worthy of notice.</p><p>@@“All the relations and friends of the family go to kiſs the corpſe, by way of taking leave, before burial. Each of them uncovers the face, over which a handkerchief is ſpread, more or leſs rich according to the family; having kiſſed the dead perſon, every one throws another handkerchief over the face; all which remain to the heirs, and sometimes there are 20, 30, and more at this ceremony. Some throw all theſe handkerchiefs into the grave with the corpſe; and this, in former times, was the general cuſtom; but then they were rich. This ſeems to have been brought into uſe as a ſubſtitute for the ancient <hi rend="italic">vaſi lachrimatorii.”</hi> E. Long. 15. 21. N. Lat. 45. 22.</p><p>SEGNI, an ancient town of Italy, in the Campagma of Rome, with a biſhop’s ſee, and the title of duchy. It is ſaid that organs were firſt invented here. It is ſeated on a mountain. E. Long. 13. 15. N. Lat. 41. 50.</p><p>SEGORBE, a town of Spain, in the kingdom of  Valencia, with the title of a duchy, and a biſhop’s ſee. It is ſeated on the ſide of a hill, between the mountains, in a ſoil very fertile in corn and wine, and where there are quarries of fine marble. It was taken from the Moors in 1245; and the Romans thought it worth their while to carry ſome of the marble to Rome. W.</p><p>Long. 0. 3. N. Lat. 39. 48.</p><p>SEGOVIA, an ancient city of Spain, of great power in the time of the Cæſars, is built upon two hills near the banks of the Arayda in Old Caſtile. W. Long. 3. 48. N. Lat. 41.0. It is ſtill a biſhop’s ſee, and is diſtinguiſhed for ſome venerable remains of antiquity. In the year 1525 the city contained 5000 families, but now they do not ſurpaſs 2000, a ſcanty population for 25 pariſhes; yet, beſides 21 churches and a cathedral, there are 21 convents.</p><p>The firſt object in Segovia that attracts the eye is the aqueduct, which the singular ſituation of the citv renders neceſſary. As it is built upon two hills, and the valley by which they are ſeparated, and extends conſiderably in every direction, it was difficult for a part of the citizens to be ſupplied with water. The difficulty was removed, according to the opinion of the learned, in the reign of Trajan, by this aqueduct, which is one of the moſt aſtoniſhing and the beſt preſerved of the Roman works.@@ In the opinion of Mr Swinburne, who ſurveyed it in 1776, and who ſeems to have given a very accurate account of the curioſities of Segovia, it is ſuperior in elegance of proportion to the Pont du Gard at Niſmes. It is ſo perfectly well preſerved, that it does not ſeem leaky in any part. From the firſt low arches to the reſervoir in the town, its length is 2400 Spaniſh feet; its greateſt height (in the Plaza del Azobejo at the foot of the walls) is 104; it is there compoſed of a double row of arches, built of large ſquare ſtones without mortar, and over them a hollow wall of coarſer materials for the channel of the water, covered with large oblong flags. Of the lower range of arcades, which are 15 feet wide by 65 high, there are 42. The upper arches are 119 in number, their height 27 Spaniſh feet, their breadth ſeventeen, the tranſverſal thickneſs, or depth of the piers, eight feet.</p><p>@@The cathedral is a mixture of the Gothic and Mooriſh architecture. The inſide is very ſpacious and of majeſtic ſimplicity. The windows are well diſpoſed, and the great altar has been lately decorated with the fineſt Grenadian marble. But it is to be regretted, that in this cathedral, as well as in moſt others of Spain, the choir is placed in the middle of the nave. The church is nearly upon the model of the great church of Salamanca, but it is not ſo highly finiſhed.</p><p>The alcazar, or ancient palace of the Moors, ſtands in one of the fineſt poſitions poſſible, on a rock riſing above the open country. A very pretty river waſhes the foot of the precipice, and the city lies admirably well on each ſide on the brow of the hill; the declivity is woody, and the banks charmingly rural; the ſnowy mountains and dark foreſts of Saint Ildefonzo compoſe an awful back-ground to the picture. Towards the town there is a large court before the great outward tower, which, as the priſon of Gil Blas, is ſo well deſcribed by Le Sage, that the ſubject requires no farther explanation. The reſt of the buildings form an antique palace, which has ſeldom been inhabited by any but priſoners ſince the reign of Ferdinand and Iſabella, who were much attached to this ſituation. There are ſome magnificent halls in it, with much gilding in the ceilings, in a ſemi-barbarous taſte. All the kings of Spain are ſeated in ſtate along the cornice of the great ſaloon; but it is doubtful whether they are like the princes whoſe names they bear; if that reſemblance, however, be wanting, they have no other merit to claim. The royal apartments are now occupied by a college of young gentlemen cadets, educated at the king’s expence in all the ſciences requiſite for forming an engineer. The grand-maſter of the ordnance reſides at Segovia, which is the head eſtabliſhment of the Spaniſh artillery.</p><p>The mint is below the alcazar, a large building, the moſt ancient place of coinage in the kingdom. The machines for melting, ſtamping, and milling the coin, are worked by water: but there is reaſon to believe</p><p>@@@ [mu] Fortis's Travels into Dalmatia.</p><p>@@@ [mu] Swineburn's Travels through Spain.</p><p>@@@ [mu] Travels in Spain by the Chev. Bourgeanne.</p></body></text></TEI>