<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:02:37Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>contained in ſome veſſel, whether of the capſule, pod, berry, apple, or cherry kind.</p><p>A simple seed is ſuch as bears neither crown, wing, nor downy <hi rend="italic">pappus ;</hi> the varieties in seeds, arising from theſe circumſtances, are particularly enumerated, under their respective heads.</p><p>In aſſimilating the animal and vegetable kingdoms, Linnaeus denominates ſeeds the eggs of plants. The fecundity of plants is frequently marvellous ; from a ſingle plant or ſtalk of Indian Turkey wheat, are produced, in one ſummer, 2000 ſeeds ; of elecampane, 3000; of ſun-flower, 4000; of poppy, 32,000; of a ſpike of cat’s tail, 10,000 and upwards : a ſingle fruit, or ſeed-veſſel, of tobacco, contains 1000 ſeeds ; that of white poppy, 8000. Mr Ray relates, from experiments made by himſelf, that 1012 tobacco-seeds are equal in weight to one grain ; and that the weight of the whole quantum of ſeeds in a ſingle tobacco-plant, is ſuch as muſt, according to the above proportion, determine their number to be 360,000. The ſame author eſtimates the annual produce of a ſingle ſtalk of ſpleen-wort to be upwards of one million of ſeeds.</p><p>The diſſemination of plants respects the different methods or vehicles by which nature has contrived to disperse their seeds for the purpoſe of increaſe. Theſe by naturaliſts are generally reckoned four.</p><p>1. Rivers and running waters. 2. The wind. 3. Animals. 4. An elaſtic spring, peculiar to the ſeeds themſelves.</p><p>1. The ſeeds which are carried along by rivers and torrents are frequently conveyed many hundreds of leagues from their native foil, and caſt upon a very different climate, to which, however, by degrees they render themselves familiar.</p><p>2. Thoſe which are carried by the wind, are either  <hi rend="italic">winged,</hi> as in fir-tree, trumpet-flower, tulip-tree, birch, arbor-vitae, meadow rue, and Jeſſamine, and ſome umbelliferous plants ; furniſhed with a <hi rend="italic">pappus,</hi> or downy crown, as in valerian, poplar, reed, ſucculent ſwallow- wort, cotton-tree, and many of the compound flowers ; placed within a winged <hi rend="italic">calyx</hi> or ſeed-vessel, as in ſcabious, ſea-pink, dock, dioſcorea, aſh, maple, and elm- trees, logwood and woad ; or laſtly, contained within a swelled <hi rend="italic">calyx</hi> or ſeed-veffel, as in winter-cherry, cucubalus, melilot, bladder-nut, fumatory, bladder-ſena, heart- ſeed, and chick-peaſe.</p><p>3. Many birds fwallow the ſeeds of vanelloe, juniper, miſletoe, oats, millet, and other graſſes, and void them entire. Squirrels, rats, parrots, and other animals, ſuffer many of the ſeeds which they devour to eſcape, and thus in effect diſſeminate them. Moles, ants, earthworms, and other infects, by ploughing up the earth, admit a free paſſage to thoſe ſeeds which have been ſeattered upon its ſurface. Again, ſome ſeeds attach themſelves to animals, by means of hooks, crotchets, or hairs, which are either affixed to the ſeeds themſelves, as in hound’s tongue, mouſe-ear, vervain, carrot, baſtard-parsley, ſanicle, water hemp-agrimony, <hi rend="italic">arctopus</hi> and <hi rend="italic">verbeſina;</hi> to their calyx, as in burdock, agrimony, <hi rend="italic">rhexia, </hi>ſmall wild bugloſs, dock, nettle, pellitory, and lead wort; or to their fruit or ſeed-veſſel, as in liquorice, enchanter’s night ſhade, croſs-wort, clivers, French honey- ſuckle, and arrow-headed graſs.</p><p>4. The ſeeds which diſperſe themſelves by an elaſticn force, have that force reſident either in their <hi rend="italic">calyx,</hi> as in oats and the greater number of ferns ; in their <hi rend="italic">pappus,</hi> as in centaurea crupina ; or in their c<hi rend="italic">apſule,</hi> as in gerannium, herb-bennet, African spirae, fraxinella, horſe-tail, balſam, Malabar nut, cucumber, elaterium, and male balſam apple.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Semen,</hi> in the animal economy. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Physiology, </hi>ſect. xii. and <hi rend="smallcaps">Anatomy,</hi> n<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> 109.</p><p><hi rend="italic">SEMEN Sanctum,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Santonicum,</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Artemisia.</hi></p><p>SEMENDRIAH, a town of Turkey in Europe, in the province of Servia, with a good citadel. It is the capital of a ſangiacate, was taken by the Turks in 1690, and is ſeated on the Danube, in E. Long. 21.45. N. Lat. 45. 0.</p><p>SEMENTINÆ <hi rend="smallcaps">FeriAE,</hi> in antiquity, feaſts held annually among the Romans, to obtain of the gods a plentiful harveſt. They were celebrated in the temple of Tellus, where ſolemn ſacrifices were offered to Tellus and Ceres. Theſe feaſts were held about ſeed-time, uſually in the month of January ; for, as Macrobius observes, they were moveable feaſts.</p><p>SEMI, a word borrowed from the Latin, ſignifying <hi rend="italic">half ;</hi> but only uſed in composition with other words, as in the following articles.</p><p><hi rend="italic">SEMI_Arians,</hi> in eccleſiaſtieal hiſtory, a branch of the ancient Arians, conſiſting, according to Epiphanius, of ſuch as, in appearance, condemned the errors of that hereſiarch, but yet acquieſced in ſome of the principles thereof, only palliating and hiding them under softer and more moderate terms. Though they ſeparated from the Arian faction (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Arians),</hi> they could never be brought to acknowledge that the Son was homoouſios, that is, conſubſtantial, or of the ſame ſubſtance with the Father ; they would only allow him to be homoiouſios, that is, of a like ſubſtance with the Father, or ſimilar to the Father in his eſſence, not by nature, but by a peculiar privilege.</p><p>The ſemi-arianiſm of the moderns conſists in their maintaining that the Son was from all eternity begotten by the <hi rend="italic">will</hi> of the Father, contrary to the doctrine of the orthodox, who ſeem to teach that the eternal generation is <hi rend="italic">neceſſary.</hi> Such at leaſt are the respective opinions of Dr Clarke and Bishop Bull. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Theology.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Semicircle,</hi> in geometry, half a circle, or that figure comprehended between the diameter of the circle and half its circumference.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Semicolon,</hi> in grammar, one of the points or ſtons uſed to diſtinguiſh the several members of a ſentence from each other.</p><p>The mark or character of the ſemicolon is (;), and has its name as, being of somewhat leſs effect than a colon ; or as demanding a ſhorter pauſe.</p><p>The proper uſe of the ſemicolon is to diſtinguiſh the conjunct members of a ſentence. Now, by a conjunct member of a ſentence is meant ſuch a one as contains at leaſt two simple members.—Whenever, then, a ſentence can be divided into ſeveral members of the ſame degree, which are again diviſible into other ſimple members, the former are to be ſeparated by a ſemicolon. For inſtancc : “ If fortune bear a great ſway over him, who has nicely ſtated and concerted every circumſtance of an affair ; we muſt not commit every thing, without reſerve, to fortune, left ſhe have too great a hold of us." Again : <hi rend="italic">Si quantum in agro lociſque deſertis audacia poteſt, tantum in foro atque judiciis impudentia valeret ; non minus in causa cederet Aulus Caecinna Sexta Æbutii impu∙</hi></p></body></text></TEI>