<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:05:14Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>111, The bread-room ſcuttle, out of the gun-room; 112, The main capſtan ; 111, The pall of the capſtan ; 114, The partner ; 115. The bulkhead of the bread room.</p><p>X,	The bread-room.</p><p>Y,	The ſteward’s room, where all proviſions are weighed and ſerved out.</p><p>Z,	The cockpit, where are ſubdiviſions for the purſer, the ſurgeon, and his mates.</p><p>A A, The platform or orlop, where proviſion is made for the wounded in the time of ſervice ; 116, The hold abaft the main-maſt ; 117, The ſtep of the mizen-maſt ; 118, The kelſon, or falſe keel ; 119, The dead wood, or riſing.</p><p>Ships βf war are fitted out either at the expence of the ſtate or by individuals. Thoſe fitted out at the public expence are called <hi rend="italic">King’s ships,</hi> and are divided into sh<hi rend="italic">ips oſ the line, frigates, floοps,</hi> &amp;c. For an account of each of theſe, ſee the reſpective articles. Ships of war fitted out by individuals are called <hi rend="italic">privateers.</hi> See the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Privateer.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Armed-SHip.</hi> See  Armed-<hi rend="italic">Ship.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Bomb-SHIP.</hi> See <hi rend="italic">BoMB-Vessels.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Double-SH</hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps">ip.</hi> See <hi rend="italic smallcaps">Ship-</hi><hi rend="italic">Building.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Fire-SHiP.</hi> See <hi rend="italic">FIRE-Ship.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Hoſpital-SHip,</hi> a veſſel fitted up to attend on a fleet of men of war, and receive their ſick or wounded ; for which purpoſe her decks ſhould be high, and her ports ſufficiently large. Her cables ought also to run upon the upper deck, to the end that the beds or cradles may be more commodiouſly placed between decks, and admit a free paſſage of the air to disperſe that which is offensive or corrupted.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Merchant-SHIP,</hi> a veſſel employed in commerce to carry commodities of various forts from one port to another.</p><p>The largeſt merchant ſhips are thoſe employed by the different companies of merchants who trade to the Eaſt Indies. They are in general larger than our 40 gun ſhips ; and are commonly mounted with 20 guns on their upper-deck, which are nine pounders ; and six on their quarter-deck, which are six pounders.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Register-SHIP.</hi> See <hi rend="italic">REGISTER-Ship.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Store-</hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Ship,</hi> a veſſel employed to carry artillery or naval ſtores for the uſe of a fleet, fortreſs, or garriſon.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Tranſport-SHIP,</hi> is generally uſed to conduct troops from one place to another.</p><p>Beſides the different kinds of ſhips abovementioned, which are denominated from the purpoſe for which they are employed, veſſels have alſo, in general, been named according to the different manner of rigging them. It would be an endleſs, and at the same time an unneceſſary task, to enumerate all the different kinds of veſſels with reſpect to their rigging ; and therefore a few only are here taken notice of. Fig. 3. Plate CCCCLI. is a shi<hi rend="italic">p</hi> which would be converted into a <hi rend="italic">bark</hi> by ſtripping the mizen maſt of its yards and the ſails belonging to them. If each maſt, its correſponding topmaſt and topgallant-maſt, inſtead of being compoſed of ſeparate pieces of wood, were all of one continued piece, then this veſſel with very little alteration would be a <hi rend="italic">polacre.</hi> Fig. 4. repreſents a sno<hi rend="italic">w ;</hi> fig. 5. a <hi rend="italic">bilander ;</hi> fig. 6. a <hi rend="italic">brig ;</hi> fig. 7. a <hi rend="italic">ketch ;</hi> fig. 8. a <hi rend="italic">ſchooner ;</hi> fig. 9. a <hi rend="italic">ſloοp ;</hi> fig. 10. a z<hi rend="italic">ebec ;</hi> fig. 11. a <hi rend="italic">galliot ; </hi>fig. 12. a <hi rend="italic">dogger ; fig.</hi> 13. a <hi rend="italic">galley</hi> under ſail; fig. 14. ditto rowing.</p><p>Ships are also ſometimes named according to the different modes of their conſtruction, Thus we say, a <hi rend="italic">cat- </hi>built ſhip, &amp;c.</p><p><hi rend="italic">To </hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Ship,</hi> is either uſed actively, as to embark any perſon or put any thing aboard ſhip : or paſſively, to receive any thing into a ſhip ; as, “ we ſhipped a heavy ſea at three o’clock in the morning,”</p><p><hi rend="italic">To SHIP,</hi> alſo implies to fix any thing in its place ; as, to ſhip the oars, that is, to put them in their row- locks ; to ſhip the ſwivel guns, is to fix them in their ſockets ; to ſhip the handspokes, &amp;c.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Machine for drawing Bolts out of </hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Ships,</hi> an infiniment invented by Mr William Hill for this purpoſe. His account of which is as follows@@*.</p><p>“ Firſt, The uſe of this machine is to draw the kelſon and dead wood bolts out, and to draw the knee of the head bolts.—Secondly, The heads of the kelſon bolts heretofore were all obliged to be driven thro’ the kelſon, floor-timbers, and keel, to get them out: by this means the kelſon is often entirely deſtroyed, and the large hole the head makes materially wounds the floors ; and frequently, when the bolt is much corroded, it scarfs, and the bolt comes out of the side of the keel. —Thirdly, The dead-wood bolts that are driven with two or three drifts, are ſeldom or never got out, by which means the dead-wood is condemned, when ſome of it is really ſerviceable. — Fourthly, In drawing the knee of the head- bolts, ſometimes the knee ſtarts off, and cannot be got to again, but furs up, and with this machine may be drawn in ; for it has been proved to have more power in ſtarting a bolt than the maul.”</p><p>In fig. I@@. “A, A, repreſent two ſtrong male ſcrews, working in female ſcrews near the extremities of the cheeks, againſt plates of iron E, E. C C is the bolt to be drawn ; which, being held between the chaps of the machine at DD, is, by turning the ſcrews by the lever B, forced upwards out of the wood or plank of the ſhip. F, F, are two dogs, with hooks at their lower extremities ; which, being driven into the plank, ſerve to ſupport the machine till the chaps have got fast hold oſ the bolt. At the upper part of theſe dogs are rings paſſing thro’ holes in a collar, moveable near the heads ot the ſcrews. Fig. 2. is a view of the upper side of the cheeks when joined together; <hi rend="italic">a, a,</hi> the holes in which the ſcrews work ; <hi rend="italic">b,</hi> the chaps by which the bolts are drawn. Fig. 3. The under side of the cheek: <hi rend="italic">a, a, </hi>the holes in which the ſcrews work ; <hi rend="italic">b,</hi> the chaps by which the bolts are drawn, and where the teeth that gripe the bolt are more diſtinctly ſhown. Fig. 4. One of the cheeks ſeparated from the other, the letters referring as in fig. 2. and 3.</p><p>This machine was tried in his majeſty’s yard at Deptford, and was found of the greateſt utility. — “ Firſt, it drew a bolt that was driven down ſo tight as only to go one inch in sixteen blows with a double-headed maul, and was well clenched below : the bolt drew the ring a conſiderable way into the wood, and wire drew itſelf through, and left the ring behind. Secondly, it drew a bolt out of the Venus’s dead-wood that could not be got out by the maul. That part of it which went through the keel was bent cloſe up to the lower part of the dead-wood, and the machine drew the bolt ſtraight, and drew it out with eaſe. It alſo drew a kelſon bolt out of the Stanley West Indiaman, in Meſſrs Wells’s yard, Deptford ; which being a bolt of two drifts, could not be driven out.</p><p>@@@[m]* Transactions of the Society for the Encouragement of Arts, &amp;c. vol. x.</p><p>@@@[mu] Plate CCCCLIII.</p></body></text></TEI>