<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:01:58Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>him to think of trying the Bath waters; but that deſign was ſtopped by the fatal accident which put an end to his life.</p><p>His Grace had been for many years ſubject to the gout, which, in the latter part of his life, returned with more frequency and violence, and did not go off in a regular manner, but left the parts affected for a long time very weak, and was ſucceeded by pains in different parts of the body. About a year and a half before he died, after a fit of the gout, he was attacked with a pain in the arm, near the ſhoulder, which having continued about <hi rend="italic">12</hi> months, a ſimilar pain ſeized the upper and outer part of the oppoſite thigh, and the arm ſoon became eaſier. This was much more grievous than the former, as it quickly diſabled him from walking, and kept him in almoſt continual torment, except when he was in a reclining poſition. During this time he had two or three fits of the gout; but neither the gout nor the medicines alleviated theſe pains, which, with the want of exerciſe, brought him into a general bad habit of body.</p><p>On Saturday July 30. 1768, he was ſeized, as he ſat at dinner, with a ſickneſs at his ſtomach. He recovered before night; but the next evening, while his phyſicians were attending, and his ſervants raiſing him on his couch, he ſuddenly cried out that his thigh-bone was broken. The ſhock was ſo violent, that the ſervants perceived the couch to ſhake under him, and the pain fo acute and unexpected, that it overcame the firmneſs he ſo remarkably poſſeſſed. He lay for ſome time in great agonies; but when the ſurgeons arrived, and diſcovered with certainty that the bone was broken, he was perfectly reſigned, and never afterwards aſked a queſtion about the event. A fever ſoon enſued. On Tueſday he became lethargic, and continued ſo till about five o’clock on Wedneſday afternoon, when he expired with great calmneſs, in the 75th year of his age.</p><p>On examination, the thigh-bone was found to be carious about four inches in length, and at nearly the  ſame diſtance from its head. The diſeaſe took its riſe from the internal part of the bone, and had ſo entirely deſtroyed its ſubſtance, that nothing remained at the part where it was broken but a portion of its outward integument; and even this had many perforations, one of which was large enough to admit two fingers, and was filled with a fungous ſubſtance ariſing from within the bone. There was no appearance of matter about the caries, and the ſurrounding parts were in a ſound  ſtate. It was apparent that the torture which he underwent during the gradual corroſion of this bone muſt have been inexpreſſibly great. Out of tenderneſs to his family he ſeldom made any complaints to them, but to his phyſicians he frequently declared his pains were ſo excruciating, that unleſs ſome relief could be procured he thought it would be impoſſible for human, nature to ſupport them long. Yet he bore them for upwards of  ſix months with aſtoniſhing patience and fortitude; ſat up generally the greater part of the day, admitted his particular friends to ſee him, mixed with his family at the uſual hours, ſometimes with his uſual cheerfulneſs; and, except ſome very ſlight defects of memory, retained all his faculties and ſenſes in their full vigour till within a few days of his death. He was buried, purſuant to his own directions, in a covered paſſage, leading from a private door of the palace to the north door of Lambeth church; and he forbade any monument or epitaph to be placed over him.</p><p>By his will he appointed the Rev. Dr Daniel Burton, canon of Chriſt-church, and Mrs Catherine Talbot, already mentioned in the courſe of theſe memoirs, his executors; and left 13,000 1. in truſt to the Dr Porteous and Stinton, his chaplains; to pay the intereſt thereof to Mrs Talbot and her daughter during their joint lives, or the life of the ſurvivor; and after the deceaſe of both thoſe ladies, 11,000 l. of the ſaid 13,000 l. are to be transferred to charitable purpoſes; amongſt which are 1000 1. to the Society for the Propagation of the Goſpel, and 1000 1. to the ſame ſociety for a biſhop or biſhops in the king’s dominions in America.</p><p>The following deſcription is given of his perſon: He was tall and comely; in the early part of his life ſlender, and rather conſumptive; but as he advanced in years his conſtitution gained ſtrength, and his ſize increaſed, yet never to a degree of corpulency that was diſproportionate or troubleſome.</p><p>The dignity of his form correſponded with the greatneſs of his mind, and inſpired at all times reſpect and awe; but peculiarly ſo when he was engaged in any of the more ſolemn functions of religion, into which he entered with ſuch devout earneſtneſs and warmth, with ſo juſt a conſciouſneſs of the place he was in, and the buſineſs he was about, as ſeemed to raiſe him above himſelf, and added new life and ſpirit to the natural gracefulneſs of his appearance.</p><p>His countenance was open, ingenuous, and expreſſive of every thing right. It varied eaſily with his ſpirits and his feelings, ſo as to be a faithful interpreter of his mind, which was incapable of the leaſt diſſimulation. It could ſpeak dejection, and, on occaſion, anger, very ſtrongly; but when it meant to ſhow pleaſure or approbation, it ſoftened into a moſt gracious ſmile, and diffuſed over all his features the moſt benevolent and reviving complacency that can be imagined.</p><p>SECOMIÆ, in natural hiſtory, the name of a genus of foſſils of the claſs of ſeptariæ; the characters of which are, That they are bodies of a duſky hue; divided, by ſepta or partitions of a ſparry matter, into ſeveral more or leſs regular portions; of a moderately firm texture; not giving fire with ſteel; but fermenting with acid menſtrua, and eaſily calcining. The ſeptariæ of this genus are of all others the moſt common, and are what have been known by the little expreſſive or miſtaken names of the waxen vein, or ludus Helmontii. We have many ſpecies of theſe bodies common among us. Of the whitiſh or browniſli, we have thirteen; of the yellowiſh five; and of the ferruginous ones four.</p><p>SECOND, in geometry, chronology, &amp;c. the 60th part of a prime or minute, whether of a degree or of an hour.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Second,</hi> in muſic, one of the muſical intervals; being only the difference between any found and the next neareſt found, whether above or below it.</p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Second</hi><hi rend="italic"> Major,</hi> in muſic. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Interval.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Second</hi><hi rend="italic"> Minor,</hi> in muſic. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Interval.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Second</hi><hi rend="italic"> Sight,</hi> in Erſe called <hi rend="italic">Taiſch,</hi> is a mode of feeing ſuperadded to that which nature generally her flows. This gift or faculty, which is neither voluntary</p></body></text></TEI>