<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:03:34Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>(ſays Major Dirçm) muſt have been the richeſt, most convenient, and beautiful ſpot poſſeſſed in the preſent age by any native prince in India ; but when the allies left it, the Sultan’s fort and city only remained in repair amidſt all the wrecks of his former grandeur, the iſland preſenting nothing but the appearance of wretched barrenneis. Tippoo is a man of talents, enterpriſe, and great wealth ; but, in the opinion of our author, the remaining years of his ill-fated life will be unequal to renew the beauties of his terreſtrial paradiſe. N. Lat. 12⁰ 31' 45". E. Long. 96⁰ 46' 45".</p><p>SERINGHAM, an iſland of Indoſtan, formed about six miles north-weſt of Trinchinopoly by the river Cavery, which divides itſelf into two branches : that to the northward takes the name of <hi rend="italic">Coleroon,</hi> but the ſouthern branch preſerves its old name the <hi rend="italic">Cavery. </hi>Each of theſe rivers, after a courſe of about 90 miles, empty themſelves into the ſea ; the Coleroon at Devicottah, and the Cavery near Tranquebar, at about 20 miles diſtance from one another. In this iſland, facing Trinchinopoly, ſtood a famous pagoda ſurrounded by ſeven ſquare walls of ſtone, 25 feet high and four feet thick. The ſpace between the outward and ſecond walls meaſured 310 ſeet, and ſo proportionably of the rest. Each incloſure had four large gates, with a high tower; which were placed, one in the middle of each side of the incloſure, and oppoſite to the four cardinal points. The outward wall was about four miles in circumference, and its gateway to the ſouth was ornamented with pillars, ſome of which were ſingle ſtones 33 feet in length and five in diameter ; while thoſe that formed the roof were ſtill larger ; and in the inmoſt incloſure were the chapels.—About half a mile to the eaſt was another large pagoda called J<hi rend="italic">umbikistna,</hi> which had but one incloſure.</p><p>The pagoda of Seringham was held in great veneration, from a belief that it contained the identical image of the god Wiſtnou worſhipped by Brama; and pilgrims came here from all parts of India with offerings of money to procure absolution. A large part of the revenue of the iſland was allotted for the maintenance of the Bramins who inhabited the pagoda; and theſe, with their families, formerly amounted to no fewer than 40,000 perſons, all maintained by the ſuperſtitious liberality of the adjacent country.</p><p>SERIOLA, in botany: A genus of plants belonging to the order of polygamia æqualis, and to the claſs of ſyngeneſia; and in the natural ſyſtem ranged under the 49th order, <hi rend="italic">Compositae.</hi> The receptacle is paleaceous ; the calyx simple ; and the pappus is ſomewhat plumoſe. There are four ſpecies ; 1. The Levigata. 2. Æthnenfis. 3. Cretenſis. 4. Urens. The firſt is a native of the iſland of Candia, and flowers in July and Auguſt; the second is a native of Italy ; and the fourth is a native of the ſouth of Europe.</p><p>SERIPHIUM, in botany ; a genus of plants belonging to the order of monogamia, and to the claſs of ſyngeneſia. The calyx is imbricated ; the corolla is manopetalous and regular, with one oblong ſeed under it. There is only one ſpecies, the <hi rend="italic">cinereum,</hi> which is a native of the Cape of Good Hope.</p><p>SERIPHUS (anc. geog.), one of the Cyclades or iſlands in the Ægean ſea, called <hi rend="italic">Saxum Seriphium</hi> by Tacitus, as if all a rock ; one of the usual places of baniſhment among the Romans. The people, <hi rend="italic">Seriphii ; w</hi>ho, together with the Siphnii, joined Greece againſt Xerxes, were almoſt the only iſlanders who refuſed to give him earth and water in token of ſubmiſſion, (Herodotus). <hi rend="italic">Seriphia Rana,</hi> a proverbial saying concerning a perſon who can neither sing nor ſay; frogs in this iſland being ſaid to be dumb, (Pliny).</p><p>SERMON, a diſcourſe delivered in public, for the purpose of religious inſtruction and improvement.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Funeral </hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Sermon.</hi> See <hi rend="italic smallcaps">Funeral</hi><hi rend="italic"> Orations.</hi></p><p>SERON <hi rend="smallcaps">of a</hi>LMONDs, is the quantity of two hundred weight; of aniſe ſeed, it is from three to four hundred; of Caſtile ſoap, from two hundred and an half to three hundred and three quarters.</p><p>SEROSITY, in medicine, the watery part of the blood.</p><p>SERPENS, in aſtronomy, a conſtellation in the northern hemiſphere, called more particularly <hi rend="italic">Serpent Ophiuchi.</hi> The ſtars in the conſtellation Serpens, in Ptolemy’s catalogue, are 18 ; in Tycho’s, 13 ; in Hevelius’s, 22 ; and in the Britannic catalogue, 64.</p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Serpens.</hi><hi rend="italic"> Biceps,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Double-headed Snake;</hi> a monſter  of the ſerpent kind, there being no permanent ſpecies of this conformation. That represented on Plate CCCCXLIX. and copied from Edwards, came from the iſland of Barbadoes ; and was ſaid to have been taken out of an egg of the ſize of a ſmall pullet’s egg by a man who found it under-ground as he was digging. The heads were not in an horizontal poſition when the ſnake lay on its belly, but inclined to each other on their under-ſides, leaving an opening for the throat to come in between the two heads underneath, as is expreſſed at A. The upper-ſide, for the whole length, was covered with ſmall scales, falling one over another ; the, belly was covered with ſingle scales running acroſs it, in the form of half rings. Tt was all over of a yellowiſh colour, without any ſpots or variation. Mr Edwards alſo informs us, that a perſon brought to him a common Engliſh ſnake, which had two heads quite ſeparate from each other, the necks parting about an inch from the head.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Serpens, </hi><hi rend="italic">Serpent,</hi> in the Linnæan ſyſtem of zoology, an order of animals belonging to the claſs of <hi rend="italic">amphibia,</hi> and comprehending six genera, viz. the <hi rend="italic">crotalus, </hi>or rattle-ſnake ; the <hi rend="italic">boa,</hi> including ten ſpecies ; the <hi rend="italic">coluber,</hi> or viper; the <hi rend="italic">anguis,</hi> or ſnake : the amphisbaena<hi rend="italic">,</hi> or annulated ſnake, the body and tail of which are compoſed of annular ſegments ; and the <hi rend="italic">caecilia,</hi> or tentaculated snake, the body and tail of which are wrinkled, without scales, and the upper part furniſhed with two feelers ; and including two ſpecies. See an account of theſe genera under their reſpective names.</p><p>The characters of ſerpents, according to Linnæus, are theſe : They are amphibious animals, breathing through the mouth by means of kings only ; having a tapering body, no diſtinct neck ; the jaws not articulated, but dilatable, and deſtitute of feet, fins, and ears.</p><p>The ſerpent has from the beginning been the enemy of man; and it has hitherto continued to terrify and annoy him, notwithſtanding all the arts which have been practiſed to deſtroy it. Formidable in itſelf, it deters the invader from the purſuit ; and from its figure, capable of finding ſhelter in a little ſpace, it is not easily diſcovered by thoſe who would venture to encounter it. Thus poſſeſſed at once of potent arms, and inacceſſible or ſecure retreats, it baffles all the</p></body></text></TEI>