<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:04:51Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>America affords many very elegant shells, but neither in ſo great abundance nor beauty as the ſhores of Aſia. Panama is famous for the cylinders or rhombi, and we have beſide, from the ſame place, ſome good porcelains, and a very fine ſpecies of dolium, or concha globoſa, called from this place the Panama purple ſhell, One of the most beautiful of the cylinders is alſo known among our naturalists under the name of the Panama ſhell. About Braſil, and in the gulf of Mexico, there are found murices and dolia of extreme beauty ; and alſo a great variety of porcelains, purpuras, pectens, neritæ, bucardiae or heart-ſhells, and elegant limpets. The file of Cayenne affords one of the moſt beautiful of the buccinum kind, and the Midas ear is found principally about this place. Jamaica and the iſland of Barbadoes have their ſhores covered with porcelains, chamæ, and buccina ; and at St Domingo there are found almoſt all the ſame ſpecies of shells that we have from the Eaſt Indies; only they are leſs beautiful, and the colours more pale and dead. The pearl-oyſter is found alſo on this coaſt, but ſmaller than in the Perſian gulf. At Martinico there are found in general the ſame ſhells as at St Domingo, but yet leſs beautiful. About Canada are found the violet chamæ, and the lakes of that country abound with muſcles of a very elegant pale blue and pale red colours. Some ſpecies of theſe are remarkably light and thin ; others are very thick and heavy. The Great Bank of Newfoundland is very barren in ſhells :the principal kind found there are muſeles of ſeveral ſpecies, ſome of which are of considerable beauty. About Carthagena there are many mother-of-pearl ſhells, but they are not of ſo brilliant colours as thoſe of the Perſian gulf. The iſland of Magellan, at the ſouthern point of America, furnishes us with a very remarkable ſpecies of muſcle called by its name ; and ſeveral very elegant ſpecies of limpets are found there, particularly the pyramidal.</p><p>In Africa, on the coaſt of Guinea, there is a prodigious quantity of that ſmall ſpecies of porcelain which is uſed there as money ; and there is another ſpecies of porcelain on the ſame coaſt which is all over white ; the women make bracelets of theſe, and the people of the Levant adorn their hair with them. The coaſt of Zanguebar is very rich in ſhells : we find there a vaſt variety of the large porcelains, many of them of great Beauty ; and the nux marts or ſea-nut is very frequent there. Beſide theſe, and many other shells, there are found on this coaſt all the ſpecies of nautili, many of which are very beautiful. The Canary iſles abound with a vaſt variety of the murices, and ſome other good ſhells ; and we have from Madeira great variety of the echini or ſea-eggs different from thoſe of the European ſeas. Several ſpecies of muſcles are alſo common there, and the auris marina is nowhere more abundant. The Red ſea is beyond all other parts of the world abundant in ſhells, ſcarce any kind is wanting there ; but what we principally have from thence are the purpuras, porcelains, and echini marini.</p><p>The Mediterranean and Northern ocean contain a great variety of shells, and many of very remarkable elegance and beauty ; they are upon the whole, however, greatly inferior to thoſe of the Eaſt Indies. The Mediterranean abounds much more in ſhells than the Ocean. The gulf of Tarentum affords great variety of purpurae, of porcelains, nautili, and elegant oyſters; the coaſts of Naples and Sardinia afford alſo the ſame, and</p><p>with them a vaſt number of the ſolens of all the known ſpecies. The iſland of Sicily is famous for a very elegant kind of oyſter which is white all over ; pinnæ marinæ and porcelains are alſo found in great plenty there, with tellinæ and chamæ of many ſpecies, and a great variety of other beautiful ſhells. Corſica is famous, beyond all other places, for vaſt quantities of the pinnæ marinæ ; and many other very beautiful ſhells are found there. (Lister, Hiſt Conchyl.) About Syracuſe are found the gondola ſhell, the alated murex, and a great variety of elegant ſnails, with ſome of the dolia and neritæ. The Adriatic ſea, or gulf of Venice, is leſs furniſhed with ſhells than almoſt any of the ſeas thereabout, Muſeles and oyſters of ſeveral ſpecies are however found there, and ſome of the cordiſorm or heart- ſhells; there are alſo ſome tellinæ. About Ancona there are found vaſt numbers of the pholades buried in ſtone ; and the aures marinæ are particularly frequent about Puzzoli. (Bοnani, Recreat. Ment. et Ocul).</p><p>The ports of Marſeilles, Toulon, and Antibes, are full of pinnæ marinæ, muſeles, tellinæ, and chamæ. The coaſts of Bretagne afford great numbers of the conchæ anatiferæ and pouccepieds ; they are found on old rotten boards, on ſea ſubſtances, and among cluſters of sponges. The other ports of France, as Rochelle, Dunkirk, Breſt, St Maloes, and others, furnish oyſters excellent for the table, but of the common kind, and of no beauty in their ſhells ; great numbers of muſeles are alſo found there ; and the common tellinæ, the onion-peel oyſters, the ſolens, and conchæ anatiferæ, are alſo frequent there. At Granville, in Lower Normandy, there are found very beautiful pectens, and ſome of the cordiform or heart- ſheils.</p><p>Our own Engliſh coaſts are not the leaſt fruitful in ſhells, tho’ they do not produce ſuch elegantly painted ones as the Indies. About Plymouth are found oyſters, muſeles, and ſolens, in great abundance; and there, and on moſt of our other ſhores, are numbers of the aures marinæ and dentalia, with pectens, which are excellent food; and many elegant ſpecies of the chamæ and tellinæ are fiſhed up in the ſea about Scarborough and other places. Ireland affords us great numbers of muſeles, and some very elegant ſcallop-ſhells in great abundance, and the pholades are frequent on most of our ſhores. We have alſo great variety of the buccina and cochleæ, ſome volutæ; and, on the Guernſey coaſt, a peculiarly beautiful ſnail, called thence the Guernſey-ſnail.</p><p>The coaſts of Spain and Portugal afford much the ſame ſpecies of ſhells with the Eaſt Indies, but they are of much fainter colours, and greatly inferior in beauty. There are, according to Tavernier and others, ſome rivers in Bavaria in which there are found pearls of a fine water. About Cadiz there are found very large pinnæ marinæ, and ſome fine bucciua. The iſles of Majorca and Minorca afford a great variety of extremely elegant ſhells. The pinnæ marinæ are alſo very numerous there, and their silk is wrought into gloves, ſtockings, and other things. The Baltic affords a great many beautiful ſpecies, but particularly an orange-coloured pecten, or ſcallop-ſhell, which is not found in any other part of the world.</p><p>The freſh water ſhells are found much more frequently, and in much greater plenty than the ſea kinds ; there is ſcarce a pond, a ditch, or a river of freſh water in any part of the world in which there</p></body></text></TEI>