<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-18T21:03:49Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>From theſe noxious qualities in the ſerpent kind, it is no wonder that not only man,
                but beaſts and birds, carry on an unceasing war againſt them. The ichneumon of the
                Indians, and the peccary@@* of America, deſtroy them in great numbers. Theſe
                animals have the art of ſeizing them near the head ; and it is ſaid that they can
                skin them with great dexterity. The vulture and the eagle alſo prey upon them in
                great abundance ; and often, ſouſing down from the clouds, drop upon a long ſerpent,
                which they snatch up ſtruggling and writhing in the air. Dogs alſo are bred up to
                oppoſe them. Father Feuillce tells us, that being in the woods of Martinico, he was
                attacked by a large ſerpent, which he could not eaſily avoid, when his dog
                immediately came to his relief, and ſeized the aſſailant with great courage. The
                ſerpent entwined him, and presſed him ſo violently, that the blood came out ol his
                mouth, and yet the dog never ceaſed till he had torn it to pieces. The dog was not
                ſenſible of his wounds during the ſight ; but ſoon after his head ſwelled
                prodigiouſly, and he lay on the ground as dead. But his maſter having found a banana
                tree hard by, he applied its juice mixed with treacle to the wounds, which recovered
                the dog, and quickly healed his sores.</p>
            <p>The Pſylli of old were famous for charming and deſtroying ſerpents@@*. Some moderns
                pretend to the ſame art. Caſaubon ſays that he knew a man who could at any time
                ſummon 100 ſerpents together, and draw them into the fire. Upon a certain occaſion,
                when one of them, bigger than the reft, would not be brought in, he only repeated
                his charm, and it came forward, like the reſt, to ſubmit to the flames. Philoſtratus
                deſcribes particularly how the Indians charm ſerpents, “ They take a ſcarlet robe,
                embroidered with golden letters, and ſpread it before a ſerpent’s hole.— The golden
                letters have a fascinating power ; and by looking ſtedfaſtly, the ſerpent’s eyes are
                overcome and laid aſleep.” Theſe and many other feats have been often practiſed upon
                theſe animals by artful men, who had firſt prepared the ſerpents for their exerciſe,
                and then exhibited them as adventitiouſly aſſembled at their call. In India there is
                nothing ſo common as dancing ſerpents, which are carried about in a broad flat
                veſſel, ſomewhat reſembling a sieve. Theſe erect and put themſelves in motion at the
                word of command. When their keeper ſings a slow tune, they ſeem by their heads to
                keep time ; when he ſings a quicker meaſure, they appear to move more brisk and
                lively. All animals have a certain degree of docility ; and we find that ſerpents
                themſelves can be brought to move and approach at the voice of their maſter. From
                this trick, ſucceſsfully practiſed before the ignorant, it is moſt probable has
                ariſen moſt of the boaſted pretenſions which ſome have made to charming of ſerpents
                ; an art to which the native Americans pretend at this very day, but the exiſtence
                of which we are aſſured of by Mr Haſſelquiſt amongſt the native Egyptians.</p>
            <p>Though the generality of mankind regard this formidable race with horror, yet there
                have been ſome nations, and there are ſome at this day, that consider them with
                veneration and regard. The adoration paid by the ancient Egyptians to a ſerpent is
                well known : many of the nations at preſent along the weſtern coaſt of Africa retain
                the ſame unaccountable veneration. Up</p>
            <p>on the gold and slave coaſts, a ſtranger, upon entering the cottages of the natives,
                is often ſurpriſed to fee the roof ſwarming with ſerpents, that cling there without
                moleſting and unmoleſted by the natives. But his surpriſe will increate upon going
                farther ſouthward to the kingdom of Widah, when he finds that a ſerpent is the god
                of the country. This animal, which travellers deſcribe as a huge overgrown creature,
                has its habitation, its temple, and its prieſts. Theſe impreſs the vulgar with an
                opinion of its virtues ; and numbers are daily ſeen to offer not only their goods,
                their proviſions, and their prayers, at the ſhrine of their hideous deity, but alſo
                their wives and daughters. These the prieſts readily accept of, and after ſome days
                of penance return them to their ſuppliants, much benefited by the ſerpent’s ſuppoſed
                embraces.</p>
            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Serpent,</hi> a muſical inſtrument, ſerving as a baſs to the
                cornet, or small shawm<hi rend="italic">,</hi> to ſuſtain a chorus of fingers in a
                large edifice. It has its name <hi rend="italic">ſerpent </hi>from its figure, as
                consiſting of ſeveral folds or wreaths, which serve to reduce its length, wſhich
                would other- wise be six or ſeven feet.</p>
            <p>It is uſually covered with leather, and conſiſts of three parts, a mouth-piece, a
                neck, and a tail. It has six holes, by means whereof it takes in the compaſs of two
                octaves.</p>
            <p>Merſennus, who has particularly described this inſtrument, mentions ſome peculiar
                properties of it, e<hi rend="italic">. gr.</hi> that the found of it is ſtrong
                enough to drown 20 robuſt voices, being animated merely by the breath of a boy, and
                yet the found of it may be attempered to the ſoftneſs of the ſweeteſt voice. Another
                peculiarity to this inſtrument is, that great as the distance between the third and
                fourth hole appears, yet whether the third hole be open or ſhut, the difference is
                but a tone.</p>
            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Serpent,</hi> in mythology, was a very common ſymbol of the sun,
                and he is repreſented biting his tail, and with his body formed into a circle, in
                order to indicate the ordinary courſe of this luminary, and under this form it was
                an emblem of time and eternity. The ſerpent was alſo the ſymbol of medicinc, and of
                the gods which presided over it, as of Apollo and Æsculapius : and this animal was
                the object of very ancient and general worſhip, under various appellations and
                characters. In moſt of the ancient rites we find ſome allusion to the ſerpent, under
                the ſeveral titles of Ob, Ops, Python, &amp;c. This idolatry is alluded to by Moſes,
                (Æev. XX. 27.) The woman at Endor who had a familiar ſpirit is called Oub, or Ob,
                and it is interpreted Pythonisſa. The place where ſhe resided, ſays the learned Mr
                Bryant, ſeems to have been named from the worſhip then inſtituted ; for Endor is
                compounded of Enador, and signifies s<hi rend="italic">ons Pythonis, "</hi>the
                fountain of light, the oracle of the god Ador, which oracle was probably founded by
                the Canaanites, and had never been totally ſuppressed. His pillar was alſo called
                    Abbadi<hi rend="italic">ir,</hi> or A<hi rend="italic">badir,</hi> compounded of
                    <hi rend="italic">ab</hi> and <hi rend="italic">adir,</hi> and meaning the
                ſerpent deity Addir, the ſame as Adorus.</p>
            <p>In the orgies of Bacchus, the perlons who partook of the ceremony uſed to carry
                ſerpents in them hands, and with horrid ſcreams call upon Eva ! Eva! Eva being,
                according to the writer just mentioned, the same as epha, or opha, which the Greeks
                rendered <hi rend="italic">ophis, </hi>and by it denoted a ſerpent. Theſe ceremonies
                and</p>
            <p>@@@[m] See Viverra and Gus.</p>
            <p>@@@[m] See PSYLLI.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
