<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:06:56Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>velocity ; to diſcover which, a little experience and attention will lead the ſkilful mariner @@<hi rend="smallcaps">(a),</hi></p><p>SHIRAUZ. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Schiras.</hi></p><p>SHIRE, is a Saxon word ſignifying a diviſion ; but a county, <hi rend="italic">comitatus,</hi> of the ſame import, is plainly derived from comes, " the count of the Franks ;” that is, the earl or alderman (as the Saxons called him) of the ſhire, to whom the government of it was entruſted. This he uſually exerciſed by his deputy, ſtill called in Latin <hi rend="italic">vice-comes, </hi>and in Engliſh the <hi rend="italic">ſheriff, shrieve, or shire reeve,</hi> ſignifying the “ officer of the ſhire ;” upon whom, in proceſs of time, the civil adminiſtration of it totally devolved. In ſome counties there is an intermediate diviſion between the ſhire and the hundred ; as lathes in Kent and rapes in Suſſex, each of them containing about three or four hundreds apiece. Theſe had formerly their lathe-reeves and rape-rceves, acting in ſubordination to the ſhire-reeve. Where a county is divided into three of theſe intermediate juriſdictions, they are called <hi rend="italic">trithings,</hi> which were anciently governed by a trithing reeve. Theſe trithings ſtill ſubſiſt in the large county of York, where, by an eaſy corruption, they are denominated <hi rend="italic">ridings ;</hi> the north, the eaſt, and the west riding.</p><p>SHIRL, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Cockle,</hi> in mineralogy. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Cockle. </hi>SHIRT, a looſe garment, commonly of linen, worn next the body.— Some doubt the propriety of changing the linen when a perſon is ſick. Clean linen promotes perſpiration; and it may be renewed as often as the patient pleaſes, whether the diſorder be of the acute or the chronical kind. Except during a criſis in fevers, whilſt the patient is in a ſweat, a change of linen, if well dried and warmed, may be daily uſed.</p><p>Shirts were not worn by Jews, Greeks, or Romans, but their place was ſupplied by thin <hi rend="italic">tunica</hi> of wool. The want of linen among the ancients made frequent waſhings and ablutions neceſſary.</p><p>SHIVER. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Schistus</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Shale.</hi></p><p>SHIVERS, in the ſea language, names given to the little rollers, or round wheels of pulleys.</p><p>SHOAD, among miners, denotes a train of metalline ſtones, ſerving to direct them in the diſcovery of mines.</p><p><hi rend="italic">SHOAD-Stones,</hi> a term uſed by the miners of Cornwall and other parts of this kingdom, to expreſs ſuch looſe maſſes of ſtone as are uſually found about the entrances into mines, ſometimes running in a ſtraight course from the load or vein of ore to the ſurface of the earth.</p><p>Theſe are ſtones of the common kinds, appearing to have been pieces broken from the ſtrata or larger maſſes; but they uſually contain mundic, or marcaſitic matter, and more or leſs of the ore to be found in the mine, They appear to have been at ſome time rolled about in water, their corners being broken off, and their ſurface ſmoothed and rounded.</p><p>The antimony mines in Cornwall are always eaſily diſcovered by the ſhoad-ſtones, theſe uſually lying up to</p><p>the surface, or very nearly ſo ; and the matter of the ſtone being a white ſpar, or debated cryſtal, in which the native colour of the ore, which is a ſhining bluiſh black, eaſily diſcovers itſelf in ſtreaks and threads.</p><p>Shoad-ſtones are of ſo many kinds, and of ſuch various appearances, that it is not eaſy to deſcribe or know them : but the miners, to whom they are of greateſt uſe in the tracing or ſearching after new mines, distinguiſh them from other ſtones by their weight ; for if very ponderous, though they look ever ſo much like common ſtones, there is great reaſon to ſuſpect that they contain ſome metal. Another mark ot them is their being ſpongy and porous; this is a ſign of eſpecial uſe in the tin countries ; for the tin ſhoad-ſtones are often ſo porous and ſpongy, that they reſemble large bodies thoroughly calcined. There are many- other appearances or tin ſhoads, the very hardeſt and ſirmeſt ſtones often containing this metal.</p><p>When the miners, in tracing a ſhoad up bill, meet with ſuch odd ſtones and earths that they know not well what to make of them, they have recourſe to vanning, that is, they calcine and powder the ſtone, clay, or whatever elſe is suppoſed to contain the metal ; and then waſhing it in an inſtrument, prepared for that purpose, and called a <hi rend="italic">vanning ſhovel,</hi> they find the earthy matter waſhed away, and of the remainder, the ſtony or gravelly matter lies behind, and the metalline matter at the point of the ſhovel. If the perſon who performs this operation has any judgment, he eaſily diſcovers not only what the metal is that is contained in the ſhoad, but alſo will make a very probable gueſs at what quantity the mine is likely to yield of it in proportion to the ore.</p><p>SHOAL, in the ſea-language, denotes a place where the water is ſhallow ; and likewiſe a great quantity of fiſhes, ſuch as <hi rend="italic">a shoal of herrings,</hi></p><p>SHOCK, in electricity. The effect of the exploſion of a charged body, that is, the diſcharge of its electricity on any other body, is called the electric shock<hi rend="italic">.</hi></p><p>SHOE, a covering for the foot, uſually of leather.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Shoes,</hi> among the Jews, were made of leather, linen, ruſh, or wood ; thoſe of ſoldiers were ſometimes of braſs or iron. They were tied with thongs which paſſed under the ſoles of the feet. To put off their ſhoes was an act of veneration ; it was alſo a ſign of mourning and humiliation : to bear one’s ſhoes, or to untie the latchets of them, was considered as the meaneſt ſervice.</p><p>Among the Greeks ſhoes of various kinds were uſed. Sandals were worn by women of diſtinction. The Lacedemonians wore red ſhoes. The Grecian ſhoes generally reached to the middle of the leg. The Romans uſed two kinds of ſhoes ; the <hi rend="italic">calceus,</hi> which covered the whole foot ſomewhat like our ſhoes, and was tied above with latchets or ſtrings ; and the <hi rend="italic">ſolea</hi> or flipper, which covered only the ſole of the foot, and was faſtened with leathern thongs. The calceus was always worn</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">@@@(a)</hi> An ingenious mechanic would probably conſtruct this machine to better advantage in many respects. The author only meant to ſuggeſt the principle ; experiment alone can point out the best method of applying it, He is ſenſible of at leaſt of one deficiency, viz. that the little index R, fig. 4. will not be ſtrong enough to retain the palate D in an oblique poſition when the ſhip is sailing by the wind ; more eſpecially as the compass plate S, in whoſe notched rim the index R is to fall, is not fixed to, but only fitted tight on the ſocket N. Many means, however, might be contrived to remedy this inconveniences</p></body></text></TEI>