<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-18T21:04:15Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>thunder, views the deſtructive bolt with ſerene aſpect, and stands erect amidſt the
                fearful majeſty of the dreaming clouds. Woman trembles at the lightning, and the
                voice of diſtant thunder ; and ſhrinks into herſelf or sinks into the arms of man.
                Man receives a ray of light ſingle, woman delights to view it through a priſm in all
                its dazzling colours. She contemplates the rainbow as the promiſe of peace ; he
                extends his inquiring eye over the whole horizon. Woman laughs, man ſmiles ; woman
                weeps, man remains silent. Woman is in anguiſh when man weeps, and in deſpair when
                man is in anguiſh ; yet has ſhe often more faith than man. Man without religion, is
                a diſeaſed creature, who would perſuade himſelf he is well, and needs not a
                phyſician ; but woman without religion, is raging and monſtrous. A woman with a
                beard is not ſo diſguſting as a woman who acts the freethinker ; her ſex is formed
                to piety and religion ; to them Chriſt firſt appeared ; but he was obliged to
                prevent them from too ardently, and too haſtily, embracing him : ‘ Touch me not.’
                They are prompt to receive and ſeize novelty, and become its enthuſiaſts. The whole
                world is forgotten in the emotion cauſed by the preſence and proximity of him they
                love. They sink into the moſt incurable melancholy, as they alſo riſe to the moſt
                enraptured heights.</p>
            <p>“ Male ſenſation is more imagination, female more heart. When communicative, they are
                more communicative than man ; when ſecret, more ſecret. In general they are more
                patient, long-ſuffering, credulous, benevolent, and modeſt. Woman is not a
                foundation on which to build. She is the gold, ſilver, precious ſtones, wood, hay,
                ſtubble ( I Cor. iii. 12. ) ; the materials for building on the male foundation. She
                is the leaven, or more expreſſively the oil to the vinegar of man : the ſecond part
                of the book of man.</p>
            <p>“ Man ſingly is but half man ; at leaſt but half human ; a king without a kingdom.
                Woman, who feels properly what ſhe is, whether ſtill or in motion, reſts upon the
                man ; nor is man what he may and ought to be, but in conjunction with woman :
                therefore, ‘ it is not good that man ſhould be alone, but that he ſhould leave
                father and mother, and cleave to his wife, and they two ſhall be one fleſh.”</p>
            <p>They differ alſo in their exterior form and appearance.</p>
            <p>“ Man is the moſt firm ; woman the moſt flexible. Man is the ſtraighteſt ; woman the
                moſt bending. Man ſtands ſtedfaſt ; woman gently retreats. Man ſurveys and obſerves
                ; woman glances and feels. Man is ſerious ; woman is gay. Man is the talleſt and
                broadeſt ; woman the ſmalleſt and weakeſt. Man is rough and hard ; woman ſmooth and
                ſoft. Man is brown ; woman is fair. Man is wrinkly ; woman is not. The hair of man
                is more ſtrong and ſhort ; of woman more long and pliant. The eyebrows of man are
                compreſſed; of woman lets frowning. Man has moſt convex lines ; woman moſt concave.
                Man has moſt ſtraight lines ; woman moſt curved. The countenance of man taken in
                profile is more ſeldom perpendicular than that of the woman. Man is moſt angular;
                woman moſt round.”</p>
            <p>In determining the comparative merit of the two ſexes,@@ it is no derogation from
                female excellency that it differs in kind from that which diſtinguiſhes the male
                part of our ſpecies : and if, in general, it ſhould be found (what upon an impartial
                inquiry will moſt certainly be found) that women fill up their appointed circle of
                action with greater regularity than men, the claim of preference cannot juſtly be
                decided in our favour. In the prudential and economical parts of life, it is
                undeniable that they riſe far above us : and if true fortitude of mind is beſt
                discovered by a cheerful reſignation to the meaſures of Providence, we ſhall not
                find reaſon, perhaps, to claim that moſt lingular of the human virtues as our
                peculiar privilege. I here are numbers of the other sex who, from the natural
                delicacy of their conſtſtution, paſs through one continued ſcene of suffering from
                their cradles to their graves, with a firmneſs of reſolution that would deserve so
                many ſtatues to be erected to their memories, if heroism were not esteemed more by
                the ſplendor than the merit of actions.</p>
            <p>But whatever real difference there may be between the moral or intellectual powers of
                the male and female mind, Nature does not ſeem to have marked the diſtinction ſo
                ſtrongly as our vanity is willing to imagine ; and after all, perhaps, education
                will be found to conſtitute the principal ſuperiority. It muſt be acknowledged, at
                leaſt, that in this article we have every advantage over the ſofter ſex that art and
                induſtry can poſſibly ſecure to us. The moſt animating examples of Greece and Rome
                are ſet before us, as early as we are capable of any obſervation ; and the nobleſt
                compoſitions of the ancients are given into our hands almoſt as ſoon as we have
                ſtrength to hold them ; while the employments of the other ſex, at the ſame period
                of life, are generally the reverſe of every thing that can open and enlarge their
                minds, or fill them with juſt and rational notions. I he truth of it is, female
                education is ſo much worſe than none, as it is better to leave the mind to its
                natural and uninſtructed ſuggeſtions, than to lead it into falle purſuits, and
                contract its views, by turning them upon the loweſt and moſt trifling objects. We
                ſeem, indeed, by the manner in which we ſuffer the youth of that ſex to be trained,
                to conſider women agreeably to the opinion of certain Mahometan doctors, and treat
                them as if we believed they had no fouls : why elſe are they</p>
            <p>Bred only, and completed to the taſte</p>
            <p>Of luſtful appetence, to fing, to dance,</p>
            <p>To dreſs, and troul the tongue, and roll the eye.</p>
            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Milton.</hi></p>
            <p>This ſtrange neglect of cultivating the female mind can hardly be allowed as good
                policy, when it is considered how much the intereſt of society is concerned in the
                rectitude of their underſtandings. That ſeason of every man’s life which is moſt
                ſuſceptible of the strongeſt impreſſions, is neceſſarily under female direction ; as
                there are few inſtances, perhaps, in which that ſex in not one of the ſecret ſprings
                which regulates the moſt important movements of private or public tranſactions. What
                Cato obſerves of his countrymen is in one reſpect true of every nation under the fun
                : “ The Romans (said he) govern the world, but it is the women that govern the
                Romans.”</p>
            <p>If it be true then ( as true beyond all peradventure it is) that female influence is
                thus extenſive, nothing certainly can be of more importance than to give it a proper
                tendency, by the aſſiſtance of a well-directed education. Far are we from
                recommending any attempts</p>
            <p>@@@[mu] <hi rend="italic">Fitzosborne's Letters.</hi></p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
