<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:03:23Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ſpun upon them) fit for the cavity or eye of the ſhuttle; and that for the warp is wound on a kind of wooden bobbins to fit it for warping. When warped, it is ſtiffened with a kind of ſize, whereof that made of the ſhreds of parchment is held the best; and when dry is put on the loom.</p><p>When mounted on the loom, the workman raising and lowering the threads (which are passed through a reed), by means of four treddles placed underneath the loom, which he makes to act tranſverſely, equally, and alternately, one after another, with his feet, in proportion as the threads are raiſed and lowered, throws the ſhuttle acroſs from one side to the other ; and each time that the ſhuttle is thrown, and the thread of the woof is croſſed between thoſe of the warp, ſtrikes it with the frame to which the reed is faſtened, through thoſe teeth the threads of the warp paſs ; and this ſtroke he repeats twice or thrice, or even more, till he judges the croſſing of the ſerge ſufficiently cloſe : thus he proceeds till the warp is all filled with woof.</p><p>The ſerge now taken off the loom is carried to the fuller, who ſcours it in the trough of his mill with a kind of fat earth, called <hi rend="italic">fuller’s earth,</hi> firſt purged of all ſtones and filth. After three or four hours ſcouring, the fuller’s earth is waſhed out in fair water, brought by little and little into the trough, out of which it is taken when all the earth is cleared ; then, with a kind of iron pincers or plyers, they pull off all the knots, ends, ſtraws, &amp;c. flicking out on the ſurface on either side ; and then returning it into the fulling trough, where it is worked with water ſomewhat more than lukewarm, with ſoap diſſolved therein for near two hours : it is then waſhed out till ſuch time as the water becomes quite clear, and there be no ſigns of ſoap left ; then it is taken out of the trough, the knots, &amp;c. again pulled off, and then put on the tenter to dry, taking care as fast as it dries to ſtretch it out both in length and breadth till it be brought to its juſt dimenſions. When well dried, it is taken off the tenter, and dyed, ſhorn, and preſſed.</p><p>SERGEANT, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Serjeant </hi><hi rend="italic">at Law,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">of the Coif, </hi>is the higheſt degree taken at the common law, as that of Doctor is of the civil law ; and as these are ſuppoſed to be the moſt learned and experienced in the practice of the courts, there is one court appointed for them to plead in by themſelves, which is the common pleas, where the common law of England is moſt ſtrictly obſerved : but they are not reſtricted from pleading in any other court, where the judges, who cannot have that honour till they have taken the degree of ſerjeant at law, call them <hi rend="italic">brothers.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Sergeant</hi><hi rend="italic"> at Arms,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Mace,</hi> an officer appointed to attend the perſon of the king ; to arreſt traitors, and inch perſons of quality as offend ; and to attend the lord high ſteward, when fitting in judgment on a traitor.</p><p>Of theſe, by ſtatute 13 Rich. IL cap. 6. there are not to be above 30 in the realm. There are now nine at court at L. 100 <hi rend="italic">per annum</hi> ſalary each ; they are called the <hi rend="italic">king’s ſergeants at arms,</hi> to diſtinguiſh them from others : they are created with great ceremony, the perſon kneeling before the king, his majeſty lays the mace on his right ſhoulder, and ſays, <hi rend="italic">Riſe up, ſergeant at arms, and eſquire for ever.</hi> They have, beſides, a patent for the office, which they hold for life.</p><p>They have their attendance in the preſence-chamber, where the band of gentlemen-penſioners wait ; and, receiving the king at the door, they carry the maces before him to the chapel door, whilſt the band of penſioners ſtand foremoſt, and make a lane for the king, as they alſo do when the king goes to the houſe of lords.</p><p>There are four other ſergeants at arms, created in the ſame manner ; one, who attends the lord chancellor ; a ſecond, the lord treaſurer ; a third, the ſpeaker of the houſe of commons ; and a fourth, the lord mayor of London on ſolemn occaſions.</p><p>They have a conſiderable ſhare of the fees of honour, and travelling charges allowed them when in waiting, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> five ſhillings per day when the court is within ten miles of London, and ten ſhillings when twenty miles from London. The places are in the lord chamberlain’s gift.</p><p>There are also ſergeants of the mace of an inferior kind, who attend the mayor or other head officer of a corporation.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Common </hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Sergeant,</hi> an officer in the city of London, who attends the lord, mayor and court of aldermen on court days, and is in council with them on all occaſions, within and without the precincts or liberties of the city. He is to take care of orphans eſtates, either by taking account of them, or to ſign their indentures, before their paſſing the lord mayor and court of aldermen : and he was likewiſe to let and manage the orphans eſtates, according to his judgnaent to their beſt advantage. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Recorder.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sergeant,</hi> in war, is an uncommiſſioned officer in a company of foot or troop of dragoons, armed with an halbert, and appointed to see discipline obſerved, to teach the ſoldiers the exerciſe of their arms, to order, ſtraiten, and form their ranks, files, &amp;e. He receives the orders from the adjutant, which he communicates to his officers. Each company generally has two ſergeants.</p><p>SERGEANTY <hi rend="italic">(Serjeantia),</hi> ſignifies, in law, a ſervice that cannot be due by a tenant to any lord but the king ; and this is either <hi rend="italic">grand ſergeanty,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">petit.</hi> The firſt is a tenure by which the one holds his lands of the king by ſuch ſervices as he ought to do in perſon to the king at his coronation ; and may alſo concern matters military, or ſervices of honour in peace ; as to be the king’s butler, carver, See. <hi rend="italic">Petit ſergeanty</hi> is where a man holds lands of the king to furniſh him yearly with ſome small thing towards his wars ; and in effect payable as rent. Though all tenures are turned into soccage by the 12 Car. II. cap. 24. yet the honorary ſervices of grand ſergeanty ſtill remain, being therein excepted. See <hi rend="italic smallcaps">Knight-</hi><hi rend="italic">Service.</hi></p><p>SERIES, in general, denotes a continual ſucceſſion of things in the ſame order, and having the ſame relation or connection with each other : in this ſenſe we ſay, a ſeries of emperors, kings, biſhops, &amp;c.</p><p>In natural hiſtory, a ſeries is uſed for an order or ſubdiviſion of ſome claſs of natural bodies ; comprehending all ſuch as are diſtinguiſhed from the other bodies of that claſs, by certain characters which they poſſeſs in common, and which the rest of the bodies of that caſt have not.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Series,</hi> in arithmetic and algebra, a rank or number of terms in ſucceſſion, increaſing or diminiſhing in ſome certain ratio or proportion. There are ſeveral kinds of ſeries ; as <hi rend="italic">arithmetical, geometrical, infinite,</hi> &amp;c.</p></body></text></TEI>