<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-18T21:03:01Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>The following paſſage expreſſes finely the progreſs of conviction.</p>
            <sp>
                <l>Let me not ſtir, nor breathe, lest I diſſolve</l>
                <l>That tender, lovely form, of painted air,</l>
                <l>So like Almeria. Ha ! it sinks, it falls ;</l>
                <l>I’ll catch it e’er it goes, and graſp her ſhade.</l>
                <l>’Tis life ! ’tis warm ! ’tis ſhe ! ’tis ſhe herſelf !</l>
                <l>It is Almeria ! ’tis, it is my wife !</l>
            </sp>
            <bibl><title>Mourning Bride</title>, act 2. ſc. 6.</bibl>
            <p>In the progreſs of thought our reſolutions become more vigorous as well as our
                paſſions.</p>
            <sp>
                <l>If ever I do yield or give conſent,</l>
                <l>By any action, word, or thought, to wed</l>
                <l>Another lord; may then just heav’n ſhow’r down, &amp;c.</l>
            </sp>
            <bibl><title>Mourning Bride</title>, act 1. ſc. 1.</bibl>
            <p>And this leads to a ſecond obſervation, That the different ſtages of a paſſion, and
                its different directions, from birth to extinction, muſt be carefully repreſented in
                their order ; becauſe otherwise the ſentiments, by being misplaced, will appear
                forced and unnatural. — Reſentment, for example, when provoked by an atrocious
                injury, diſcharges itſelf ſirſt upon the author : ſentiments therefore of revenge
                come always ſirſt, and muſt in ſome meaſure be exhauſted before the perſon injured
                think of grieving for himſelf. In the Cid of Corneille, Don Diegue having been
                affronted in a cruel manner, expreſſes ſcarce any ſentiment of revenge, but is
                totally occupied in contemplating the low ſituation to which he is reduced by the
                affront :</p>
            <sp>
                <l>O rage ! ô deſeſpoir ! ô vieilleſſe ennemie !</l>
                <l>N’ai-je donc tant vecu que pour cette infamie?</l>
                <l>Et ne suis-je blanchi dans les travaux guerriers,</l>
                <l>Que pour voir en un jour fletrir tant de lauriers ?</l>
                <l>Mon bras, qu’avec respect tout l’Espagne admire,</l>
                <l>Mon bras qui tant de fois a fauve cet empire,</l>
                <l>Tant de fois affermi le trône de son roi,</l>
                <l>Trahit donc ma querelle, et ne fait rien pour moi !</l>
                <l>O cruel souvenir de ma gloire passé !</l>
                <l>Oeuvre de tant de jours en un jour effacée !</l>
                <l>Nouvelle dignité fatale a mon bonheur !</l>
                <l>Precipice élevé d’où tombe mon honneur !</l>
                <l>Faut-il de votre éclat voir triompher le comte,</l>
                <l>Et mourir fans vengeance, ou vivre dans la honte ? Comte, fois de mon prince à
                    present gouverneur,</l>
                <l>Ce haut rang n’admet point un homme fans honneur ; Et ton jaloux orgueil par cet
                    affront insigne,</l>
                <l>Malgré le choix du roi, m’en a sû rendre indigne.</l>
                <l>Et toi, de mes exploits glorieux instrument,</l>
                <l>Mais d’un corps tout de glace inutile ornement,</l>
                <l>Fer jadis tant à craindre, et qui dans cette offense,</l>
                <l>M ’as fervi de parade, et non pas de defense,</l>
                <l>Va, quitte déformais le dernier des humains,</l>
                <l>Paffe pour me venger en de meilleures mains.</l>
            </sp>
            <bibl><title>Le Cid</title>, act 1. ſc. 7.</bibl>
            <p>Theſe ſentiments are certainly not the firſt that are ſuggeſted by the paſſion of
                reſentment. As the firſt movements of reſentment are always directed to its object,
                the very ſame is the caſe of grief. Yet with relation to the hidden and ſevere
                diſtemper that ſeized Alexander bathing in the river Cydnus, Quintus Curtius
                deſcribes the firſt emotions of the army as directed to themſelves, lamenting that
                they were left without a leader, far. from home, and had ſcarce any hopes of
                returning in ſafety : their king’s diſtreſs, which muſt naturally have been their
                firſt concern, occupies them but in the ſecond place according to that author. In
                the Aminta of Taſſo, Sylvia, upon a report of her lover’s death, which ſhe believed
                certain, inſtead of bemoaning the loss of her beloved, turns her thoughts upon
                herself, and wonders her heart does not break :</p>
            <sp>
                <l>Ohime, ben ſon di ſaſſo,</l>
                <l>Poi che queſta novella non m’uccide.</l>
            </sp>
            <bibl>Act. 4. ſc. 2.</bibl>
            <p>In the tragedy of Jane Shore, Alicia, in the full purpoſe of deſtroying her rival,
                has the following reflection:</p>
            <sp>
                <l>Oh Jealouſy ! thou bane of pleaſing friendſhip,</l>
                <l>Thou worſt invader of our tender boſoms ;</l>
                <l>How does thy rancour poiſon all our ſoftneſs,</l>
                <l>And turn our gentle nature into bitterneſs !</l>
                <l>See where ſhe comes ! Once my heart’s deareſt bleſſing,</l>
                <l>Now my chang’d eyes are blaſted with her beauty,</l>
                <l>Loathe that known face, and sicken to behold her.</l>
            </sp>
            <bibl>Act 3. sc. 1.</bibl>
            <p>Theſe are the reflections of a cool ſpectator. A paſſion, while it has the aſcendant,
                and is freely indulged, suggeſts not to the person who feels it any ſentiment to its
                own prejudice : reflections like the foregoing occur not readily till the paſſion
                has ſpent its vigour.</p>
            <p>A perſon ſometimes is agitated at once by different paſſions ; and the mind in that
                caſe, vibrating like a pendulum, vents itſelf in ſentiments that partake of the ſame
                vibration. This we give as a third obſervation:</p>
            <sp>
                <speaker>Queen.</speaker>
                <l>Would I had never trod this Engliſh earth,</l>
                <l>Or felt the flatteries that grow upon it !</l>
                <l>Ye’ve angels faces, but heav’n knows your hearts.</l>
                <l>What ſhall become of me now ? wretched lady !</l>
                <l>I am the moſt unhappy woman living.</l>
                <l>Alas ! poor wenches, where are now your fortunes ?</l>
                <stage>[To her women.</stage>
                <l>Shipwreck’d upon a kingdom, where no pity,</l>
                <l>No friends, no hope, no kindred, weep for me ?.</l>
                <l>Almoſt no grave allow’d me.</l>
            </sp>
            <bibl><title>Henry VIII</title>. act 3. sc. 1.</bibl>
            <sp>
                <speaker>Othello.</speaker>
                <l>Oh devil, devil !</l>
                <l>If that the earth could teem with woman’s tears,</l>
                <l>Each drop ſhe falls would prove a crocodile.</l>
                <l>Out of my ſight !</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker>Desdemona.</speaker>
                <l>I will not ſtay t’offend you. <stage>[Going.</stage></l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker>Lodovico.</speaker>
                <l>Truly, an obedient lady:</l>
                <l>I do beseech your lordſhip, call her back.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker>Oth.</speaker>
                <l>Miſtress- </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker>Des.</speaker>
                <l>My lord.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker>Oth.</speaker>
                <l>What would you with her, Sir ?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker>Lod.</speaker>
                <l>Who, I, my lord ?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker>Oth.</speaker>
                <l>Ay; you did wiſh that I would make her turn.</l>
                <l>Sir, ſhe can turn and turn, and yet go on ;</l>
                <l>And turn again. And ſhe can weep, Sir, weep ;</l>
                <l>And ſhe’s obedient : as you ſay, obedient :</l>
                <l>Very obedient—proceed you in your tears— </l>
                <l>Concerning this, Sir,— oh well painted paſſion !—</l>
                <l>I am commanded home—get you away,</l>
                <l>I’ll ſend for you anon—Sir, I obey the mandate,</l>
                <l>And will return to Venice. Hence, avaunt !</l>
            </sp>
            <p><stage>[Exit Deſdemona</stage></p>
            <bibl><title>Othello</title>, act 4. ſc. 6.</bibl>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
