<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-18T21:03:02Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <sp>
                <speaker>AEmilia.</speaker>
                <l>Oh ! my good lord, I would ſpeak a word with you.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker>Othello.</speaker>
                <l>Yes, ’tis Æmilia—By and by.—She’s dead.</l>
                <l>’Tis like ſhe comes to ſpeak of Caſſio’s death ;</l>
                <l>The noiſe was high.— Ha ! no more moving ?</l>
                <l>Still as the grave. Shall ſhe come in ? wer’t good ?</l>
                <l>I think ſhe ſtirs again — No—what’s the beſt ?</l>
                <l>If ſhe come in, ſhe'll, ſure, ſpeak to my wife :</l>
                <l>My wife ! my wife ! what wife ? I have no wife ;</l>
                <l>Oh inſupportable ? oh heavy hour !</l>
            </sp>
            <bibl><title>Othello</title>, act 5. ſc. 7.</bibl>
            <p>A fourth obſervation is, That nature, which gave us paſſions, and made them extremely
                beneficial when moderate, intended undoubtedly that they ſhould be ſubjected to the
                government of reaſon and conſcience. It is therefore againſt the order of nature,
                that paſſion in any case ſhould take the lead in contradiction to reaſon and
                conſcience : ſuctr a ſtate of mind is a fort of anarchy which every one is aſhamed
                of and endeavours to hide or diſſemble. Even love, however laudable, is attended
                with a conſcious ſhame when it becomes immoderate : it is covered from the world,
                and diſcloſed only to the beloved object :</p>
            <sp>
                <l>Et que l’amour ſouvent de remors combattu</l>
                <l>Paroisse une foiblesse, et non une vertu.</l>
            </sp>
            <p><hi rend="italic"><bibl><author>Boileau</author>, <title>l’Art Poet.</title> chant.
                        3. l. 101.</bibl></hi></p>
            <sp>
                <l>O, they love leaſt that let men know they love.</l>
            </sp>
            <bibl><title>Two Gentlemen of Verona</title>, act 1.sc. 3.</bibl>
            <p>Hence a capital rule in the repreſentation of immoderate paſſions, that they ought to
                be hid or diſſembled as much as poſſible. And this holds in an eſpecial manner with
                reſpect to criminal paſſions : one never counſels the commiſſion of a crime in plain
                terms ; guilt muſt not appear in its native colours, even in thought ; the propoſal
                muſt be made by hints, and by repreſenting the action in ſome favourable light. Of
                the propriety of ſentiment upon ſuch an occaſion, Shakespeare, in the <hi
                    rend="italic"><bibl><title>Tempest</title></bibl>,</hi> has given us a beautiful
                example, in a ſpeech by the uſurping duke of Milan, adviſing Sebaſtian to murder his
                brother the king of Naples :</p>
            <sp>
                <speaker>Antonio.</speaker>
                <l>—What might,</l>
                <l>Worthy Sebaſtian,—O, what might—no more.</l>
                <l>And yet, methinks, I ſee it in thy face</l>
                <l>What thou ſhouldſt be : the occaſion ſpeaks thee, and</l>
                <l>My ſtrong imagination ſees a crown</l>
                <l>Dropping upon thy head.</l>
            </sp>
            <bibl>Act 2. ſc. 2.</bibl>
            <p>A picture of this kind, perhaps ſtill finer, is exhibited in <bibl><hi rend="italic"
                            ><title>King John</title>,</hi> where that tyrant ſolicits <hi
                        rend="italic">(act 3. ſc. 5.)</hi></bibl> Hubert to murder the young prince
                Arthur ; but it is too long to be inſerted here.</p>
            <p>II. As things are beſt illuſtrated by their contraries, we proceed to faulty
                ſentiments, diſdaining to be indebted for examples to any but the moſt approved
                authors. The firſt claſs ſhall conſiſt of ſentiments that accord not with the
                paſſion ; or, in other words, ſentiments that the paſſion does not naturally
                ſuggeſt. In the ſecond claſs ſhall be ranged ſentiments that may belong to an
                ordinary paſſion, but unſuitable to it as tinctured by a ſingular character.
                Thoughts that properly are not ſentiments, but rather deſcriptions, make a third.
                Sentiments that belong to the paſſion represented, but are faulty as being
                introduced too early or too late, make a fourth, Vicious ſentiments expoſed in their
                native dreſs, inſtead of being concealed or diſguiſed, make a fifth. And in the laſt
                claſs shall be collected ſentiments ſuited to no character nor paſſion, and
                therefore unnatural.</p>
            <p>The <hi rend="italic">first</hi> claſs contains faulty ſentiments of various kinds,
                which we ſhall endeavour to diſtinguiſh from each other.</p>
            <p>1. Of ſentiments that are faulty by being above the tone of the paſſion, the
                following may ſerve as an example :</p>
            <sp>
                <speaker>Othello.</speaker>
                <l> —O my soul’s joy !</l>
                <l>If after every tempeſt come ſuch calms,</l>
                <l>May the winds blow till they have waken’d death :</l>
                <l>And let the labouring bark climb hills of ſeas</l>
                <l>Olympus high, and duck again as low</l>
                <l>As hell’s from heaven ?</l>
            </sp>
            <bibl><title>Othello</title>, act 2. sc. 6.</bibl>
            <p>This ſentiment may be ſuggeſted by violent and inflamed paſſion ; but is not ſuited
                to the ſatisfaction, however great, that one feels upon eſcaping danger.</p>
            <p>2. Inſtance of ſentiments below the tone of the paſſion. Ptolemy, by putting Pompey
                to death, having incurred the diſpleaſure of Cæsar, was in the utmoſt dread of being
                dethroned : in that agitating ſituation, Corneille makes him utter a ſpeech full of
                cool reflection, that is in no degree expreſſive of the paſſion.</p>
            <sp>
                <l>Ah ! ſi je t’avois crû, je n’aurois pas de maître,</l>
                <l>Je serois dans le trône où le ciel m’a fait naître ;</l>
                <l>Mais c’est une imprudence aſſez commune aux rois,</l>
                <l>D’écouter trop d’avis, et se tromper au choix.</l>
                <l>Le Destin les aveugle au bord du précipice,</l>
                <l>Ou ſi quelque lumiere en leur ame se glisse, </l>
                <l>Cette fausse clarté dont il les eblouit,</l>
                <l>Le plonge dans une gouffre, et puis s’evanouit.</l>
            </sp>
            <bibl><title>La Mort de Pompé</title>, act 4. sc. 4.</bibl>
            <p>3. Sentiments that agree not with the tone of the paſſion ; as where a pleaſant
                ſentiment is grafted upon a painful paſſion, or the contrary. In the following
                inſtances, the ſentiments are too gay for a ſerious paſſion :</p>
            <sp>
                <l>No happier taſk theſe faded eyes purſue ;</l>
                <l>To read and weep is all they now can do.</l>
            </sp>
            <bibl><title>Eloiſa to Abelard</title>, l.47.</bibl>
            <p>Again ;</p>
            <sp>
                <l>Heav’n firſt taught letters for ſome wretch’s aid,</l>
                <l>Some baniſh’d lover, or ſome captive maid :</l>
                <l>They live, they ſpeak, they breathe what love inſpires,</l>
                <l>Warm from the soul, and faithful to its fires ;</l>
                <l>The virgin’s wiſh without her fears impart,</l>
                <l>Excuſe the bluſh, and pour out all the heart ;</l>
                <l>Speed the ſoft intercourſe from soul to foul,</l>
                <l>And waft a ſigh from Indus to the pole.</l>
            </sp>
            <bibl><title>Eloiſa to Abelard</title>, l.51.</bibl>

            <p>Theſe thoughts are pretty : they suit <bibl><title>Pope</title></bibl>, but not
                Eloiſa.</p>
            <sp>
                <l>Satan, enraged by a threatening of the angel Gabriel, anſwers thus :</l>
                <l>Then when I am thy captive, talk of chains,</l>
                <l>Proud limitary cherub ; but ere then Far heavier load thyſelf expect to feel</l>
                <l>From my prevailing arm, though heaven’s King</l>
            </sp>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
