<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:03:32Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p><hi rend="italic">Summation of SERIES</hi> is the method of finding the sum of the terms of an infinite ſeries produced to infinity, or the ſum of any number of terms of ſuch a</p><p>Teries.</p><p>The value of any arithmetical ſeries, as 1<hi rend="superscript">2</hi> + 2<hi rend="superscript">2</hi> + 3<hi rend="superscript">2</hi> + 4<hi rend="superscript">2</hi>.... n<hi rend="superscript">2</hi>, varies according as (n) the number  of its terms varies ; and therefore, if it can be expressed in a general manner, it muſt be explicable by n and its powers with determinate coefficients ; and thoſe powers, in this caſe, muſt be rational, or ſuch whoſe indices are whole poſitive numbers ; becauſe the progreſsion, being a whole number, cannot admit of ſurd quantities. Laſtly, it will appear that the greateſt of the  said indices cannot exceed the common index of the ſeries by more than unity : for, otherwiſe, when <hi rend="italic">n</hi> is taken indefinitely great, the higheſt power of n would be indefinitely greater than the ſum of all the reſt of the terms.</p><p>Thus the higheſt power of n, in an expreſſion exhibiting the value of 1<hi rend="superscript">2</hi> + 2<hi rend="superscript">2</hi> + 3<hi rend="superscript">2</hi> + 4<hi rend="superscript">2</hi>.... n<hi rend="superscript">2</hi>, cannot be greater than n<hi rend="superscript">3</hi> ; 1<hi rend="superscript">2</hi> + 2<hi rend="superscript">2</hi> + 3<hi rend="superscript">2</hi> + 4<hi rend="superscript">2</hi>.... n<hi rend="superscript">2</hi>, manifeſtly leſs than n<hi rend="superscript">3</hi>, or n<hi rend="superscript">2 </hi>+ n<hi rend="superscript">2 </hi>+ n<hi rend="superscript">2 </hi>+, &amp;c. continued to n terms ; but n<hi rend="superscript">4</hi>, when <hi rend="italic">n</hi> is indefinitely great, is indefinitely greater than n<hi rend="superscript">3</hi>, or any other inferior power of  n, and therefore cannot enter into the equation. This being premiſed, the method of inveſtigation may be as follows :</p></body></text></TEI>