<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-18T21:03:05Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>Corneille, in his <bibl><title>Examen of the Cid,</title></bibl> anſwering an
                objection, That his ſentiments are ſometimes too much refined for perſons in deep
                diſtreſs, obſerves, that if poets did not indulge ſentiments more ingenious or
                refined than are prompted by paſſion, their performances would often be low, and
                extreme grief would never ſuggeſt but exclamations merely. This is in plain language
                to assert, that forced thoughts are more agreeable than thoſe that are natural, and
                ought to be preferred.</p>
            <p>The <hi rend="italic">Second</hi> claſs is of ſentiments that may belong to an
                ordinary paſſion, but are not perfectly concordant with it, as tinctured by a
                Angular character.</p>
            <p>In the laſt act of that excellent comedy <bibl><title>The Careless
                    Husband,</title></bibl> Lady Eaſy, upon Sir Charles’s reformation, is made to
                expreſs more violent and turbulent ſentiments of joy than are conſiſtent with the
                mildneſs of her character.</p>
            <sp>
                <speaker>Lady Eaſy.</speaker>
                <p>O the soft treaſure! O the dear reward of long-deſiring love. Thus! thus to have
                    you mine, is ſomething more than happineſs ; 'tis double life, and madneſs of
                    abounding joy.</p>
            </sp>
            <p>The following inſtances are deſcriptions rather than ſentiments, which compoſe a <hi
                    rend="italic">third</hi> claſs.</p>
            <p>Of this deſcriptive manner of painting the paſſions, there is in the
                        <bibl><title>Hippolytus</title> of <author>Euripides</author>, act v.</bibl>
                an illuſtrious inſtance, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> the ſpeech of Theſeus, upon
                hearing of his ſon’s diſmal exit. In <bibl><author>Racine</author>’s tragedy of
                        <title>Esther</title></bibl>, the queen hearing of the decree iſſued againſt
                her people, inſtead of expreſſing ſentiments ſuitable to the occaſion, turns her
                attention upon herſelf, and deſcribes with accuracy her own ſituation.</p>
            <sp>
                <p>Juſte ciel ! tout mon fang dans mes veines se glace.</p>
            </sp>

            <bibl>Act 1. sc. 3.</bibl>
            <p>Again,</p>
            <sp>
                <speaker>Aman.</speaker>
                <p>C’en eſt fait. Mon orgueil eſt forcé de plier. L’inexorable Aman eſt reduit à
                    prier.</p>
            </sp>
            <bibl><title>Esther</title>, act 3. sc. 5.</bibl>
            <sp>
                <speaker>Athalie.</speaker>
                <l> Quel prodige nouveau me trouble et m’embarraſſe ?</l>
                <l>La douceur de sa voix, son ensance, ſa grace,</l>
                <l>Font insensiblement à mon inimitié</l>
                <l>Succeder Je serois senlible à la pitié ?</l>
            </sp>
            <bibl><title>Athalie</title>, act 2. sc. 7.</bibl>
            <sp>
                <speaker>Titus.</speaker>
                <l>O de ma paſſion fureur desesperée !</l>
            </sp>
            <bibl><title>Brutus oſ Voltaire</title>, act 3. ſc. 6.</bibl>
            <p>What other are the foregoing inſtances but deſcribing the paſſion another feels ?</p>
            <p>The <hi rend="italic">fourth</hi> claſs is of ſentiments expreſſed too early or too
                late.</p>
            <p>Some examples mentioned above belong to this claſs. Add the following from
                        <bibl><title>Venice Preserved</title>, act 5</bibl>. at the dole of the
                ſcene between Bélvidera and her father Priuli. The account given by Belvidera of the
                danger ſhe was in, and of her huſband’s threatening to murder her, ought naturally
                to have alarmed her relenting father, and to have made him expreſs the moſt
                perturbed ſentiments. Inſtead of which, he diſſolves into tenderneſs and love for
                his daughter, as if he had already delivered her from danger, and as if there were a
                perfect tranquillity :</p>
            <sp>
                <l>Canſt thou forgive me all my follies paſt !</l>
                <l>I’ll henceforth be indeed a father ; never,</l>
                <l>Never more thus expoſe, but cheriſh thee,</l>
                <l>Dear as the vital warmth that feeds my life,</l>
                <l>Dear as thoſe eyes that weep in fondneſs o’er thee :</l>
                <l>Peace to thy heart.</l>
            </sp>
            <p>Immoral ſentiments expoſed in their native colours, inſtead of being concealed or
                diſguised, compoſe the <hi rend="italic">fifth </hi>claſs.</p>
            <p>The Lady Macbeth, projecting the death of the king, has the following ſoliloquy :</p>
            <sp>
                <l>—The raven himſelf’s not hoarse</l>
                <l>That croaks the fatal entrance of Duncan</l>
                <l>Under my battlements. Come, all you ſpirits</l>
                <l>That tend on mortal thoughts, unſex me here,</l>
                <l>And fill me from the crown to the toe, top full</l>
                <l>Of direct cruelty ; make thick my blood,</l>
                <l>Stop up th’ acceſs and paſſage to remorſe,</l>
                <l>That no compunctious viſitings of nature</l>
                <l>Shake my fell purpoſe.</l>
            </sp>
            <bibl><title>Macbeth</title>, act 1. ſc. 7.</bibl>
            <p>This ſpeech is not natural. A treacherous murder was never perpetrated even by the
                moſt hardened miſcreant without compunction : and that the lady here muſt have been
                in horrible agitation, appears from her invoking the infernal ſpirits to fill her
                with cruelty, and to stop up all avenues to remorſe. But in that ſtate of mind it is
                a never-failing artifice off ſelf-deceit to draw the thickeſt veil over the wicked
                action, and to extenuate it by all the circumſtances that imagination can ſuggeſt :
                and if the crime cannot bear diſguiſe, the next attempt is to thruſt it out of mind
                altogether, and to ruſh on to action without thought. This laſt was the huſhand’s
                method.</p>
            <sp>
                <l>Strange things I have in head, that will to hand ;</l>
                <l>Which muſt be acted ere they muſt be ſcann’d.</l>
            </sp>
            <bibl>Act 3. sc. 5.</bibl>
            <p>The lady follows neither of theſe courſes, but in a deliberate manner endeavours to
                fortify her heart in the commiſſion of an execrable crime, without even attempting
                to colour it. This, we think, is not natural ; we hope there is no ſuch wretch to be
                found as is here repreſented.</p>
            <p>The <hi rend="italic">last</hi> claſs comprehends ſentiments that are unnatural, as
                being ſuited to no character nor paſſion. Theſe may be ſubdivided into three
                branches : firſt, ſentiments unſuitable to the conſtitution of man, and to the laws
                of his nature ; second, inconsiſtent ſentiments ; third, ſentiments that are pure
                rant and extravagance.</p>
            <p>When the fable is of human affairs, every event, every incident, and every
                circumſtance, ought to be natural, otherwiſe the imitation is imperfect. But an
                imperfect imitation is a venial fault, compared with that of running croſs to
                nature. In the <bibl><title>Hippolytus</title> of <author>Euripides</author> (act
                    iv. ſc. 5.)</bibl>, Hippolytus, wiſhing for another ſelf in his own ſituation, “
                How much (ſays he) ſhould I be touched with his misfortune !” as if it were natural
                to grieve more for the misfortune of another than for one’s own.</p>
            <sp>
                <speaker>Oſmyn.</speaker>
                <p> Yet I behold her—yet—and now no more. Turn your lights inward, eyes, and view my
                    thought ; So ſhall you ſtill behold her—’Twill not be.</p>
            </sp>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
