<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:03:33Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>To proceed farther would lead us far beyond the limits aſſigned for this article ; we muſt therefore refer thoſe who require more information on this ſubject to the following authors. Bertrand’s <hi rend="italic">Diveloppement,</hi> &amp;c. vol. I ; Dodson’s Mathematical Repoſitory, vol. I ; Emerſon’s Algebra ; Appendix to Graveſend’s Algebra; Hutton’s Paper on Cubic Equations and Infinite Series, in the Philoſophical Tranſactions for 1780, Maclaurin’s Fluxions; Malcolm’s Arithmetic ; Maſere’s Annuities ; and <hi rend="italic">Scriptores Logarithmici, &amp;c.</hi> ; De Moivre’s Doctrine of Chances, and a Paper by the ſame author in the Philoſophical Tranſactions, n⁰ 240; Simpſon’s Algebra, Essays, Fluxions, and Miſcellanies ; Sterling’s <hi rend="italic">Summatio et Interpolatio Serierum ; Syntagma Mathesios, &amp;c.</hi></p><p>SERINGAPATAM, the capital of Mysore, the dominions of Tippoo Sultan, is situated in an iſland of the Cavery river, about 290 or 390 miles from Madras. The iſland, upon ſurvey, appeared to be about four miles in length by one and a half in breadth, acroſs the middle, where it is likewiſe higheſt, whence it gradually falls and narrows towards the extremities. The west end of the iſland, on which there is a fort of conſiderable ſtrength, ſlopes more, eſpecially towards the north ; and the ground rising on the oppoſite side of the river commands a diſtinct view of every part of the fort. The fort and outworks occupy about a mile of the weſt end of the iſland, and are diſtinguiſhed by magnificent buildings, and ancient Hindoo pagodas, contraſted with the more lofty and ſplendid monuments lately raiſed in honour of the Mahometan faith. Thc great garden, called the <hi rend="italic">Laul Baug,</hi> covers about as much of the eaſt end of the iſland as the fort and outworks do of the weſt ; and the whole intermediate ſpace, except a ſmall incloſure on the north bank near the fort, was, before the laſt war, filled with houſes, and formed an extenſive ſuburb, of which the greateſt part was deſtroyed by Tippoo to make room for batteries to defend the iſland when attacked by the combined forces of Earl Cornwallis and the Mahratta chiefs in February 1792. This ſuburb, or town of modern ſtructure, is about half a mile ſquare, divided into regular croſs ſtreets, all wide, and ſhaded on each side by trees. It is surrounded by a strong mud wall, contains many good houſes, and seems to have been preserved by the Sultan for the accommodation of merchants, and for the convenience of troops ſtationed on that part of the iſland for its defence. A little to the eaſtward of the town is the entrance to the great garden, which was laid out in regular ſhady walks of large cypreſs trees, and abounding with fruit-trees, flowers, and vegetables of every deſcription. It poſſessed all the beauty and elegance of a country retirement, and was dignified by the mauſoleum of Hyder the late ſultan, and a ſuperb new palace built by his ſon. This noble garden was devoted to deſtruction ; and the trees which had ſhaded their proud master, and contributed to his pleaſures, were formed into the means of protecting his enemies in ſubverting his empire. Before that event, ſo glorious to the arms of England, this inſulated metropolis</p></body></text></TEI>