<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:02:23Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>had been removed to the Gate-houſe, an order was made for conveying him back to the King’s Bench, whence he was releaſed in the latter end of the ſame year ; but fifteen years after, the parliament ordered him 5000 l. for the loſſes he had ſuſtained on this occaſion. He was afterwards committed, with ſeveral other gentlemen, for diſperſing a libel ; but the author, who was abroad, being discovered, they were at length ſet at liberty. In 1634, a diſpute ariſing between the Engliſh and Dutch concerning the herring-fiſhery on the Britiſh coaſt, he was prevailed upon by archbiſhop Laud to draw up his M<hi rend="italic">are Clauſum,</hi> in anſwer to Grotius’s <hi rend="italic">Mare Liberum : </hi>which greatly recommended him to the favour of the court. In 1640, he was choſen member for the univerſity of Oxford ; when he again opposed the court, though he might, by complying, have raised himſelſ to very conſiderable posts. In 1643, he was appointed one of the lay-members to sit in the aſſembly of divines at Weſtminſter, and was the ſame year appointed keeper of the records in the Tower. Whilſt he attended his duty in the aſſembly, a warm debate aroſe reſpecting the diſtance of Jericho from Jeruſalem. The party which contended for the ſhorteſt diſtance, urged, as a proof of their opinion being well founded, that fiſhes were carried from the one city to the other, and sold in the market. Their adverſaries were ready to yield to the force of this concluſive argument, when Selden, who deſpiſed both parties, as well as the frivoloulneſs of their diſpute, exclaimed, “ Perhaps the fiſhes were ſalted !” This unexpected remark left the victory doubtful, and renewed the debate ; and our author, who was ſick of ſuch trifling, soon found employment more ſuited to his genius ; for, in 1645, he was made one of the commiſſioners of the admiralty. The ſame year he was unanimouſly elected maſter of Trinity-college, Cambridge ; but declined accepting. He died in 1654; and was interred in the Temple-church, where a monument is erected to his memory. Dr Wilkes obſerves, that he was a man of uncommon gravity and greatneſs of foul, averſe to flattery, liberal to ſcholars, charitable to the poor; and though he had great latitude in his principles with regard to ecclefiaſtical power, yet he had a ſincere regard for the church of England. He wrote many learned works beſides thoſe already mentioned ; the principal of which are, 1. <hi rend="italic">De Jure Naturali</hi> &amp; <hi rend="italic">Gentium juxta Disciplinam Hebraeorum.</hi> 2. <hi rend="italic">De Nuptiis &amp; Divοrciis. 3. De Anno Civili veterum Hebraeorum.</hi> 4. <hi rend="italic">De Nummis.</hi> 5. <hi rend="italic">De Diis Syris. 6. Uxor Hebraica. 7. Jani Anglorum Facies altera,</hi> &amp;c. All his works were printed together in 1726, in 3 vols folio.</p><p>SERENITES, in natural hiſtory, the name of a large claſs of foſſils, the characters of which are theſe : they are bodies compoſed of ſlender and ſcarce viſible filaments, arranged into fine, even, and thin flakes ; and thoſe diſpoſed into regular figures, in the ſeveral different genera, approaching to a rhomboïde, or hexangular column, or a rectangled parallelogram ; fiſſile, like the talcs, but they not only lie in a horizontal, but also in a perpendicular direction : they are flexile in a ſmall degree, but not at all elaſtic ; they do not ferment with acid menstrua, but readily calcine in the fire. Of this clals there are ſeven orders of bodies, and under thoſe ten genera. The selenitæ of the firſt order are thoſe compoſed of horizontal plates, and approaching to a rhomboidal form: of the second are thoſe compoſed of horizontal plates, arranged into a columnar and angular</p><p>form: of the third are thoſe whoſe filaments are ſcarce visibly arranged into plates, but which, in the whole maſſes, appear rather of a ſtriated than of a tubulated ſtructure: of the fourth are thoſe which are flat, but of no determinately angular figure : of the fifth are thoſe formed of plates, perpendicularly arranged : of the sixth are thoſe formed of congeries of plates, arranged into the figure of a ſtar ; and of the ſeventh are thoſe of a complex and indeterminate figure.</p><p>Of the firſt of theſe orders there are three genera.</p><p>1. The <hi rend="italic">leptodecarbombes. 2.</hi> The <hi rend="italic">pachodecarbombes.</hi> 3.The <hi rend="italic">tetradecarbοmbes.</hi> Of the second order there are also three genera. 1. The <hi rend="italic">iſchnamb luces. 2. The iſambluces.</hi> 3. The <hi rend="italic">οxuciae.</hi> Of the third order there is only one known genus, the <hi rend="italic">inamblucia.</hi> Of the fourth order there is also only one known genus, the <hi rend="italic">ſanidia.</hi> Of the fifth order there is also only one known genus, the <hi rend="italic">cathetοlipes.</hi> Of the sixth order, there are two genera. 1. The <hi rend="italic">lepaſlra.—</hi></p><p>2.	The <hi rend="italic">trichestra.</hi> Of the ſeventh order there is only one genus, the <hi rend="italic">ſymplexia.</hi></p><p>The ſtructure of the ſelenitas of all the genera of the firſt order is exactly alike ; they are all compoſed of a great number of broad flakes or plates, in a great meaſure externally reſembling the flakes of the soliaceous talcs : theſe are of the length and breadth of the whole maſs ; the top and bottom being each only one ſuch plate, and thoſe between them, in like manner, each complete and ſingle; and the body may always be easily and evenly ſplit, according to the direction of theſe flakes. Theſe differ, however, extremely from the talcs, for they are each compoſed of a number of parallel threads or filaments, which are uſually diſpoſed parallelly to the ſides of the body, though sometimes parallelly to its ends. In many of the ſpecies they are also divided by parallel lines, placed at a conſiderable diſtance from each other, and the plates in ſplitting often break at theſe lines ; add to this, that they are not elaſtic, and that they readily calcine. The ſtructure of thoſe of the second order is the ſame with that of the firſt ; but that in many of the ſpecimens of them the filaments of which the plates are compoſed ran in two directions, and meet in an obtuſe angle ; and in the middle there is generally ſeen in this cafe a ſtraight line running the whole length of the column and ſmall parcels of clay inſinuating themſelves into this crack, repreſent in it the figure of an ear of graſs so naturally, as to have deceived many into a belief that there was really an ear of graſs there. The other orders conſiſting only of ſingle genera, the ſtructure of each is explained under the generical name.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">SelenItes,</hi> in chemiſtry, called <hi rend="italic">also gypſum spatosum, </hi>a species of gypſum or platter of Paris. See <hi rend="smallcaps">GYP</hi>SUM.</p><p>SELENOGRAPHY, a branch of coſmography, which describes the moon and all the parts and appearances thereof, as geography does thoſe of the earth. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Moon.</hi></p><p>SELEUCIA, (anc. geogr.), ſurnamed <hi rend="italic">Babylonia, </hi>becauſe ſituated on its confines, at the confluence of the Euphrates and Tigris. Ptolemy places it in Mesopotamia. It is called also <hi rend="italic">Seleucia ad Tigrim,</hi> (Polybius, Strabo, Iſidorus, Characenus) ; waſhed on the south by the Euphrates, on the eaſt by the Tigris, (Theophy∙ lactus) ; generally agreed to have been built or enlarged by Seleucus Nicanor, maſter of the eaſt after Alexander ; by means of which Babylon came to be deſerted.</p></body></text></TEI>