<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-18T21:04:36Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>he is expenſive while living, in eating up our graſs, &amp;c. it may be anſwered that
                it is quite the contrary ; for he can feed where every other animal has been before
                him and grazed all they could find ; and that if he takes a little graſs on our
                downs or in our fields, he amply repays us for every blade of graſs in the richneſs
                of the manure which he leaves behind him. He protects the hands from the cold wintry
                blaſt, by providing them with the ſofteſt leather gloves. Every gentleman’s library
                is alſo indebted to him for the neat binding of his books, for the ſheath of his
                ſword, and for cases for his inſtruments ; in ſhort, not to be tedious in mentioning
                the various uſes of leather, there is hardly any furniture or utenſil of life but
                the ſheep contributes to render either more uſeful, convenient, or ornamental.</p>
            <p>As the ſheep is ſo valuable an animal, every piece of information concerning the
                proper method of managing it muſt be of importance. It will not therefore be uſeleſs
                nor unentertaining to give ſome account of the manner of managing ſheep in Spain, a
                country famous for producing the beſt wool in the world.</p>
            <p>In Spain there are two kinds of ſheep : the coarſe- woolled ſheep, which always
                remain in their native country, and are houſed every night in winter ; and the
                fine-wooled ſheep, which are always in the open air, and travel every ſummer from
                the cool mountains of the northern parts of Spain, to feed in winter on the ſouthern
                warm plains of Andalusia, Mancha, and Eſtramadura. Of theſe latter, it appears from
                accurate computations, that there are about five millions @@( <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >b</hi> ) ; and that the wool and fleſh of a flock of 10,000 ſheep produce
                yearly about 24 reals a head, or about the value of 12 Engliſh ſixpences, one of
                which belongs to the owner, three to the king, and the other eight are allowed for
                the expences of paſture, tythes, ſhepherds, dogs, ſalt, ſhearing, &amp;c. Ten
                thouſand ſheep form a flock, which is divided into ten tribes, under the management
                of one perſon, who has abſolute dominion over fifty ſhepherds and fifty dogs.</p>
            <p>M. Bourgoanne, a French gentleman, who reſided many years in Spain, and directed his
                inquiries chiefly to the civil government, trade, and manufactures, of that country,
                gives the following account of the wandering ſheep of Segovia. “ It is (says he) in
                the neighbouring mountains that a part of the wandering ſheep feed during the fine
                ſeaſon.@@ They leave them in the month of October, paſs over thoſe which ſeparate
                the two Caſtiles, croſs New Caſtile, and diſperſe themſelves in the plains of
                Eſtramadura and Andaluſia. For ſome years paſt thoſe of the two Caſtiles, which are
                within reach of the Sierra-Morena, go thither to paſs the win</p>
            <p>ter ; which, in that part of Spain, is more mild : the length of their day’s journey
                is in proportion to the paſture they meet with. They travel in flocks from 1000 to
                1200 in number, under the conduct of two ſhepherds ; one of whom is called the <hi
                    rend="italic">Mayoral,</hi> the other the <hi rend="italic">Zagal.</hi> When
                arrived at the place of their deſtination, they are diſtributed in the paſtures
                previouſly aſſigned them. They return in the month of April ; and whether it be
                habit or natural inſtinct that draws them towards the climate, which at this ſeaſon
                becomes moſt proper for them, the inquietude which they manifeſt might, in case of
                need, ſerve as an almanac to their conductors.”</p>
            <p>Mr Arthur Young, in that patriotic work which he conducted with great induſtry and
                judgment, the Annals of Agriculture, gives us a very accurate and intereſting
                account of the Pyrenean or Catalonian ſheep.</p>
            <p>“ On the northern ridge, bearing to the west, are the paſtures of the Spaniſh flocks.
                This ridge is not, however, the whole ; there are two other mountains, quite in a
                different ſituation, and the ſheep travel from one to another as the paſturage is
                ſhort or plentiful. I examined the ſoil of theſe mountain paſtures, and found it in
                general ſtony ; what in the west of England would be called a st<hi rend="italic"
                    >one brash,</hi> with ſome mixture of loam, and in a few places a little peaty.
                The plants are many of them untouched by the ſheep ; many ferns, narciſſus, violets,
                &amp;c. but burnet <hi rend="italic">(poterium ſanguisorba}</hi> and the
                narrow-leaved plantain <hi rend="italic">(plantago lanceοlata)</hi> were eaten, as
                may be ſuppoſed, cloſe. I looked for trefoils, but found ſcarcely any : it was very
                apparent that ſoil and peculiarity of herbage had little to do in rendering theſe
                heights proper for ſheep. In the northern parts of Europe, the tops of mountains
                half the height of theſe (for we were above ſnow in July) are bogs, all are ſo which
                I have ſeen in our iſlands, or at leaſt the proportion of dry land is very trifling
                to that which is extremely wet : Here they are in general very dry. Now a great
                range of dry land, let the plants be what they may, will in every country suit
                ſheep. The flock is brought every night to one ſpot, which is ſituated at the end of
                the valley on the river I have mentioned, and near the port or paſſage of Picada :
                it is a level ſpot ſheltered from all winds. The ſoil is 8 or 9 inches deep of old
                dung, not at all incloſed : from the freedom from wood all around, it ſeems to be
                choſen partly for ſafety againſt wolves and bears. Near it is a very large ſtone, or
                rather rock, fallen from the mountain. This the ſhepherds have taken for a ſhelter,
                and have built a hut againſt it ; their beds are ſheep-ſkins, and their door ſa
                ſmall that they crawl in. I faw no place for fire ; but they have it, ſince they
                dress here the fleſh of their ſheep,</p>
            <p>@@@[mu] Bourgoanne's Travels, vol. i. p. 53.</p>
            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">@@@(b)</hi> In the 16th century the travelling ſheep were
                eſtimated at ſeven millions : under Philip III. the number was diminiſhed to two
                millions and a half. Uſtariz, who wrote at the beginning of this century, made it
                amount to four millions. .The general opinion is, that at preſent it does not exceed
                five millions. If to this number the eight millions of ſtationary ſheep be added, it
                will make nearly thirteen millions of animals, all managed contrary to the true
                intereſts of Spain, for the advantage of a few individuals. For the proprietors of
                ſtationary flocks alſo have privileges which greatly reſemble thoſe of the members
                of the Meſta. According to Arriquebar, Spain contains eight millions of fine-wooled
                ſheep, ten millions of coarſe-wooled, and five hundred thouſand bulls, oxen, and
                cows.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
