<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:04:06Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Framiload and the Thames near Lechlade, and will be continued over the Thames near Ingleſham, into deep water in the Thames below St John-Bridge, and ſo to Oxford, &amp;c. and London, for conveyance of coals, goods, &amp;c. It is now navigable from the Severn to Themsford, by way of Stroud, Cirenceſter, Cricklade, &amp;c. being filled with water for that purpoſe near 40 miles.</p><p>SEVERUS (Cornelius), an ancient Latin poet of the Auguſtan age ; whoſe <hi rend="italic">Ætna,</hi> together with a fragment <hi rend="italic">De morte Ciceronis,</hi> were publiſhed, with notes and a proſe interpretation, by Le Clerc, 12mo, Amsterdam, 1703. They were before inſerted among the <hi rend="italic">Catalecta Virgilii</hi> publiſhed by Scaliger ; whoſe notes, with others, Le Clerc has received among his own.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Severus</hi> (Septimus), a Roman emperor, who has been ſo much admired for his military talents, that some have called him the moſt warlike of the Roman emperors. As a monarch he was cruel, and <hi rend="italic">it</hi> has been obſerved that he never did an act of humanity or forgave a fault. In his diet he was temperate, and he always ſhowed himſelf an open enemy to pomp and ſplendor. He loved the appellation of a man of letters, and he even compoſed an hiſtory of his own reign, which ſome have praiſed for its correctneſs and veracity. However cruel Severus may appear in his puniſhments and in his revenge, many have endeavoured to exculpate him, and obſerved that there was need of ſeverity in an empire where the morals were ſo corrupted, and where no leſs than 3000 perlons were accuſed of adultery during the ſpace of 17 years. Of him, as of Augustus, ſome were fond to say, that it would have been better for the world if he had never been born, or had never died. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Rome,</hi> n<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> 372.</p><p><hi rend="italic">SEVERUS' Wall,</hi> in Britiſh topography, the fourth and laſt barrier erected by the Romans againſt the incurſions of the North Britons. See the articles <hi rend="smallcaps">Adrian,</hi> and A<hi rend="italic smallcaps">ntoninUS'</hi><hi rend="italic">s Wall.</hi></p><p>We learn from ſeveral hints in the Roman hiſtorians, that the country between the walls of Hadrian and Antoninus continued to be a ſcene of perpetual war and ſubject of contention between the Romans and Britons, from the beginning of the reign of Commodus to the arrival of the emperor Septimius Severus in Britain, A. D. 206. This laſt emperor having ſubdued the Mæatæ, and repulſed the Caledonians, determined to erect a ſtronger and more impenetrable barrier than any of the former, againſt their future incurſions.</p><p>Though neither Dio nor Herodian make any mention of a wall built by Severus in Britain for the protection of the Roman province, yet we have abundant evidence from other writers of equal authority, that he really built ſuch a wall. “ He fortified Britain (says Spartian) with a wall drawn croſs the iſland from sea to sea ; which is the greateſt glory of his reign. After the wall was finiſhed, he retired to the next ſtation (York), not only a conqueror, but the founder of an eternal peace.” To the same purpoſe, Aurelius Victor and Oroſius, to ſay nothing of Eutropius and Caſſiodorus : “ Having repelled the enemy in Britain, he fortified the country, which was ſuited to that purpoſe, with a wall drawn croſs the iſland from ſea to sea.</p><p>Severus drew a great ditch, and built a ſtrong wall, fortified with ſeveral turrets, from ſea to ſea, to protect that part of the iſland which he had recovered from</p><p>the yet unconquered nations.” As the reſidence of the emperor Severus in Britain was not quite four years, it is probable that the two laſt of them were employed in building this wall ; according to which account, it was begun A. D. 209, and finiſhed A. D. 210.</p><p>This wall of Severus was built nearly on the ſame tract with Hadrian’s rampart, at the diſtance only of a few paces north. The length of this wall, from Cousins’ houſe near the mouth of the river Tyne on the eaſt, to Boulneſs on the Solway frith on the west, hath been found, from two actual menſurations, to be a little more than 68 English miles, and a little leſs than 74 Roman miles. To the north of the wall was a broad and deep ditch, the original dimenſions of which cannot now be aſcertained, only it ſeems to have been larger than that of Hadrian. The wall itſelf, which ſtood on the ſouth brink of the ditch, was built of free-stone, and where the foundation was not good, it is built on piles of oak ; the interſtices between the two faces of this wall is filled with broad thin ſtones, placed not perpendicularly, but obliquely on their edges ; the running mortar or cement was then poured upon them, which, by its great ſtrength and tenacity, bound the whole together, and made it firm as a rock. But though theſe materials are ſufficiently known, it is not eaſy to gueſs where they were procured, for many parts of the wall are at a great diſtance from any quarry of free ſtone ; and, though ſtone of another kind was within reach, yet it does not appear to have been anywhere uſed. The height of this wall was 12 feet beſides the parapet, and its breadth 8 feet, according to Bede, who lived only at a ſmall diſtance from the eaſt end of it, and in whoſe time it was almoſt quite entire in many places. Such was the wall erected by the command and under the direction of the emperor Severus in the north of England ; and, conſidering the length, breadth, height, and ſolidity, it was certainly a work of great magnificence and prodigious labour. But the wall itſelf was but a part, and not the moſt extraordinary part, of this work. The great number and different kinds of fortreſſes which were built along the line of it for its defence, and the military ways with which it was attended, are ſtill more worthy of our admiration, and come now to be deſcribed.</p><p>The fortreſſes which were erected along the line of Severus’s wall for its defence, were of three different kinds, and three different degrees of ſtrength ; and were called by three different Latin words, which may be tranſlated statio<hi rend="italic">ns, castles,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">turrets.</hi> Of each of theſe in their order.</p><p>The st<hi rend="italic">ationes,</hi> ſtations, were ſo called from their ſtability and the ſtated reſidence of garriſons. They were alſo called <hi rend="italic">callra,</hi> which hath been converted into <hi rend="italic">chestres,</hi> a name which many of them ſtill bear. Theſe were by far the largeſt, ſtrongeſt, and moſt magnificent of the fortreſſes which were built upon the wall, and were deſigned for the head-quarters of the cohorts of troops which were placed there in garriſon, and from whence detachments were ſent into the adjoining caſtles and turrets. Theſe ſtations, as appears from the veſtiges of them which are ſtill visible, were not all exactly of the ſame figure nor of the ſame dimenſions ; ſome of them being exactly ſquares, and others oblong, and ſome of them a little larger than others. Theſe variations were no doubt occasioned by the difference of si-</p></body></text></TEI>