<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:03:47Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>The <hi rend="italic">coluber stolatus</hi> and myct<hi rend="italic">erizαns,</hi> though marked by Linnæus, we are aſſured by Dr Gray are not poiſonous: he thinks the ſame may be ſaid of the <hi rend="italic">leberis </hi>and <hi rend="italic">dypsas.</hi> On the other hand, he obſerves, that the <hi rend="italic">boa contortrix, coluber cerastes, laticaudatus,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">coluber ſulvus,</hi> none of which are marked in the <hi rend="italic">Systema Nature,</hi> are all poiſonous.</p><p>In addition to the method of cure mentioned in the articles referred to above, we ſhall ſubjoin the preſcription of a new author, Dr Moseley@@*, who ſpent 12 years in the West Indies, and whoſe abilities and extensive practice very juſtly intitle his opinion to a place in this work, to the attention of the public, and to all medical gentlemen going to the West Indies.</p><p>“ The bites and ſtings of all venomous animals are cured by the ſame local means ; which are very ſimple, if they were always at hand. The injured part muſt be inſtantly deſtroyed or be cut out. Deſtroying it is the molt ſafe, and equally certain : and the beſt application for that purpoſe is the lapis infernalis or the butter of antimony.—Theſe are preferable to an hot iron, which the ancients uſed, becauſe an hot iron forms a crust, which acts as a defence to the under parts, inſtead of deſtroying them. The lapis infernalis is much better than any other cauſtic, as it melts and penetrates during its application. The bitten part muſt be destroyed to the bottom, and where there is any doubt that the bottom of the wound is not ſufficſently expoſed, butter of antimony ſhould be introduced into it on the following day, as deep as poſſible ; and inciſions ſhould be made to lay every part open to the action of theſe applications. Beſides deſtroying, burning, or cutting out the part, inciſions ſhould be made round the wound, to prevent the communication of the virus. The wound is to be dreſſed for ſome time with poultices, to aſſuage the inflammation cauſed by the cauſtics ; and afterwards with acrid dreſſings and hot digeſtives to drain the injured parts.</p><p>“ Where the above-mentioned cauſtics cannot be procured, corroſive ſublimate, oil of vitriol, aquafortis, ſpirit of ſalt, common cauſtic, or a plaſter made of quicklime and ſoap, may be applied to the wound. Gunpowder laid on the part, and fired, has been uſed with ſucceſs. When a perſon is bitten remote from any aſſiſtance, he ſhould make a tight ligature above the part, until proper application can be made. The Spaniſh writers ſay, that the <hi rend="italic">habilla de Carthagena,</hi> or Carthagena bean, is a ſpecific for poiſonous bites, taken inwardly.</p><p>“ Ulloa ſays, it is ‘ one of the moſt effectual antidotes known in that country (Carthagena) againſt the bites of vipers and ſerpents : for a little of it being eaten immediately after the bite, it preſently flops the effects of the poiſon ; and accordingly all who frequent the woods, either for felling trees or hunting, never fail to eat a little of this habilla fasting, and repair to their work without any apprehenſion.</p><p>‘ The natives tell you, that this habilla being hot in the higheſt degree, much of it cannot be eaten ; that</p><p>the common doſe of ſe is leſs than the fourth part of a kernel ; and that no hot liquor, as wine, brandy, &amp;c. muſt be drunk immediately after taking it.’</p><p>“ The Carthagena bean, or habilla, is found in great abundance in the West Indian iſlands, where it is generally known by the name of <hi rend="italic">Antidote</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Cocoon,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Antidote Cocoon.</hi> In ſmall doſes it is ſtomachic and diaphoretic ; and in large doſes emetic and purgative. In ſeveral diſorders it is a powerful remedy ; but its virtues are not ſufficiently known, except among the Indians and negroes, who chiefly uſe an infuſion or tincture of it made in rum. This is externally as well as internally uſed for many complaints @@<hi rend="smallcaps">(a).</hi></p><p>“ I have been informed by ſome intelligent Indians, that any of the red peppers, ſuch as bird pepper, or bell pepper, or what is called <hi rend="italic">Cayenne pepper,</hi> powdered and taken in a glaſs of rum as much as the ſtomach can poſſibly bear, ſo as to cauſe, and keep up for ſome time, great heat and inflammation in the body arid a vigorous circulation, will ſtop the progreſs of the poiſon oſ ſerpents, even after its effects are viſible ; and that the bitten part only afterwards mortifies and separates, and that the patient, with bark, wine, and cordials, ſoon recovers.</p><p>“ This fiery practice is certainly agreeable to that of the ancients, and probably the only internal treatment that can have any good effect ; as in theſe caſes the powers of life, and the action of the heart, are ſuddenly enfeebled, and the pulſe in ſtrength and frequency obſerves almoſt a regular declension from the time of the bite until it entirely ceaſes in death.”</p><p><hi rend="italic">Polygala fenega,</hi> or rattleſnake-root, was formerly considered as a ſovereign remedy for the bite of the rattleſnake ; but this opinion is now exploded. </p><p>If it be aſked for what purpoſe were ſerpents created with ſuch deſtructive weapons ? we anſwer, that they were given for ſelf-defence. Without theſe, ſerpents, of all other animals, would be the moſt expoſed and defenceleſs ; without feet for eſcaping a purſuit, without teeth capable of inflicting a dangerous wound, or without ſtrength for reſiſtance ; incapable, from their ſize, of finding ſecurity in very ſmall retreats like the earthworm, and diſguſting all from their deformity, nothing was left for them but a speedy extirpation. But furniſhed as they are with powerful poiſon, every rank of animals approach them with dread, and never ſeize them but at an advantage. Nor is this all the benefit they derive from it. The malignity of a few ſerves for the protection of all. Though not above a tenth of their number are actually venomous, yet the ſimilitude they all bear to each other excites a general terror of the whole tribe ; and the uncertainty of their enemies about what ſerpents are poiſonous, makes even the moſt , harmleſs formidable. Thus Providence ſeems to have acted with double precaution : it has given ſome of them poiſon for the general defence of a tribe naturally feeble ; but it has thinned the numbers of thoſe which are venomous, left they ſhould become too powerful for the rest of animated nature.</p><p>@@@[m]* P. 32.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">@@@(a) "</hi> This bean is the ſeed of the <hi rend="italic">Fevillea</hi> foliis cordatis of Plumier, Ed. Burmanni, p. 203. tab. 209, <hi rend="italic">Fevillea</hi> foliis cordatis, angulatis, of Linnæus, Spec. P. <hi rend="italic">Fevillea</hi> foliis craſſioribus, glabris, quandoque cordatis, quandoque trilobis, or <hi rend="italic">Antidote Cocoon,</hi> of Brown, p. 374.”</p></body></text></TEI>