<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:04:46Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>them ſafe for some time from either giving or receiving infection. There are people who employ themſelves in the buſiness, and contract to anoint our large ſheep at five ſhillings a ſcore, inſuring for that price the ſucceſs of the operation ; that is, agreeing, in caſe many of the ſheep break out afreſh, to repeat the operation gratis even ſome months afterwards.”</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">dunt</hi> is a diſtemper cauſed by a bladder of water gathering in the head. No cure for this has yet been diſcovered.</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">rickets</hi> is a hereditary diſeaſe for which no antidote is known. The firſt ſymptom is a kind of light- headedneſs, which makes the affected ſheep appear wilder than uſual when the ſhepherd or any perſon approaches him. He bounces up ſuddenly from his lare, and runs to a diſtance, as though he were purſued by dogs. In the second ſtage the principal ſymptom is the ſheep’s rubbing himſelf againſt trees, &amp;c. with ſuch fury as to pull off his wool and tear away his fleſh. “ The diſtreſſed animal has now a violent itching in his skin, the effect of an highly inflamed blood ; but it does not appear that there is ever any cutaneous eruption or ſalutary critical diſcharge. In ſhort, from all circumstances, the fever appears now to be at its height.”— The laſt ſtage of this diſeaſe “ ſeems only to be the progreſs of diſſolution, after an unfavourable crisis. The poor animal, as condemned by Nature, appears ſtupid, walks irregularly (whence probably the name <hi rend="italic">rickets), </hi>generally lies, and eats little: theſe ſymptoms increaſe in degree till death, which follows a general conſumption, as appears upon dissection of the carcaſe ; the juices and even ſolids having ſuffered a general diſſolution.”</p><p>In order to diſcover the ſeatand nature of this diseaſe, ſheep that die of it ought to be diſſected. This is ſaid to have been done by one gentleman, Mr Beal and he found in the brain or membranes adjoining a maggot about a quarter of an inch long, and of a browniſh colour. A few experiments might eaſily determine this fact.</p><p>The fly-struck is cured by clipping the wool off as far as infected, and rubbing the parts dry with lime or wood-aſhes ; curriers oil will heal the wounds, and prevent their being ſtruck any more ; or they may be cured with care, without clipping, with oil of turpentine, which will kill all the vermin where it goes ; but the former is the sureſt way.</p><p>The flu<hi rend="italic">x</hi> is another diſeaſe to which ſheep are ſubject. The beſt remedy is ſaid to be, to houſe the ſheep immediately when this diſtemper appears, to keep them very warm, and feed them on dry hay, giving them frequent gliſters of warm milk and water. The cauſe of that diſtemper is either their feeding on wet lands, or on graſs that is become moſſy by the lands having been fed many years without being ploughed. When the farmer perceives his ſheep-walks to become moſſy, or to produce bad graſs, he ſhould either plough or manure with hot lime, making kilns either very near or in the ſheep walks, becauſe the hotter the lime is out on, the ſweeter the graſs comes up, and that early in the year.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Bursting,</hi> or as it is called in ſome places the <hi rend="italic">blast,</hi> attacks ſheep when driven into freſh graſs or young clover. They overeat themſelves, foam at the mouth, ſwell exceedingly, breathe very quick and ſhort, then jump up, and inſtantly fall down dead. In this caſe, the only chance of having their life is by ſtabbing them in the maw with an instrument made for the purpoſe. The infiniment is a hollow tube, with a pointed weapon paſſing through it. A hole is made with the pointed weapon ; which is immediately withdrawn, and the hole is kept open by inſerting the tube till the wind is diſcharged.</p><p>Sheep are infeſted with worms in their noſe called aestru<hi rend="italic">s oves,</hi> and produced from the egg of a large twowinged fly. The frontal ſinuſes above the noſe in ſheep and other animals are the places where theſe worms live and attain their full growth. Theſe ſinuſes are always full of a ſoft white matter, which furniſhes theſe worms with a proper nouriſhment, and are ſufficiently large for their habitation; and when they have here acquired their deſtined growth, in which they are fit to undergo their changes for the fly-ſtate, they leave their old habitation, and, falling to the earth, bury themſelves there ; and when theſe are hatched into flies, the female, when ſhe has been impregnated by the male, knows that the noſe of a ſheep or other animal is the only place for her to depoſit her eggs, in older to their coming to maturity. Mr Vallisnieri, to whom the world owes ſo many diſcoveries in the infect claſs, is the firſt who has given any true account of the origin of theſe worms. But though their true hiſtory had been till that time unknown, the creatures themſelves were very early diſcovered, and many ages since were eſteemed great medicines in epilepsies.</p><p>The fly produced from this worm has all the time of its life a very lazy diſpoſition, and does not like to make any uſe either of its legs or wings. Its head and corſelet together are about as long as its body, which is composed of five rings, ſtreaked on the back ; a pale yellow and brown are there diſpoſed in irregular ſpots ; the belly is of the same colours, but they are there more regularly diſpoſed, for the brown here makes three lines, one in the middle, and one on each side, and all the intermediate ſpaces are yellow. The wings are nearly of the ſame length with the body, and are a little inclined in their position, ſo as to lie upon the body : they do not, however, cover it ; but a naked ſpace is left between  them. The ailerons or petty wings which arc found under each of the wings are of a whitiſh colour, and perfectly cover the balancers, so that they are not to be ſeen without lifting up theſe.</p><p>The fly will live two months after it is firſt produced, but will take no nouriſhment of any kind ; and possibly it may be of the same nature with the butterflies, which never take any food during the whole time of their living in that ſtate. Reaumur, Hiſt. Inſi vol iv. p. 552, &amp;c.</p><p>To find a proper compoſition for marking ſheep is a matter of great importance, as great quantities of wool are every year rendered uſeleſs by the pitch and tar with which they are uſually marked. The requiſite qualities for ſuch a compoſition are, that it be cheap, that the colour be ſtrong and laſting, ſo as to bear the changes of weather, and not to injure the wool. Dr Lewis recommends for this purpoſe melted tallow, with ſo much charcoal in fine powder ſtirred into it as is ſufficient to make it of a full black colour, and of a thick confidence. This mixture, being applied warm with a marking iron, on pieces of flannel, quickly fixed or hardened, bore moderate rubbing, reſiſted the ſun and rain.</p></body></text></TEI>