<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:04:20Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>parance of the ſhadow, according to the laws of perspective, The method <hi rend="italic">is</hi> this: From the luminous body, which is here considered as a point, let fall a perpendicular to the perſpective plane or table ; <hi rend="italic">i. e.</hi> find the appearance of a point upon which a perpendicular, drawn from the middle of the luminary, falls on the perſpective plane ; and from the ſeveral angles, or raiſed points of the body, let fall perpendiculars to the plane. Theſe points, whereon the perpendiculars fall, connect by right lines, with the point upon which the perpendicular let fall from the luminary falls ; and continue the lines to the side oppoſite to the luminary. Lastly, through the raiſed points draw lines through the centre of the luminary, intersecting the former ; the points of intersection are the terms or bounds of the ſhadow.</p><p>SHADWELL (Thomas), deſcended of an ancient family in Staffordſhire, was born in 1640, and educated at Caius college, Cambridge, He then was placed in the Middle Temple to ſtudy the laws ; where having ſpent ſome time, he travelled abroad. Upon his return home, he became acquainted with the moſt celebrated perlons of wit in that age, He applied himſelf chiefly to dramatic writing, in which he had great ſucceſs ; and upon the Revolution was made poet-laureat and hiſtoriographer to king William and queen Mary, in the room of Mr. Dryden. Theſe employments he enjoyed till his death, which happened in 1692. Beſide his dramatic writings, he compoſed ſeveral other pieces of poetry; the chief of which are his congratulatory poem on the prince of Orange’s coming to England ; another on queen Mary; his tranſlation of Juvenal’s 10th ſatire, &amp;c. Mr Dryden treats him with great contempt, in his ſatire called <hi rend="italic">Mac-Fleckno.</hi> The beſt judges of that age, however, gave their teſtimony in favour of his comedies ; which have in them fine ſtrokes of humour ; the characters are often original, ſtrongly marked, and well ſuſtained, An edition of his works, with ſome account of his life and writings prefixed, was publiſhed in 1720, in 4 vols 8vo,</p><p>SHAFT <hi rend="italic">of a </hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Column,</hi> in building, is the body thereof between the baſe and capital ; ſo called from its straightneſs, See <hi rend="smallcaps">Architecture.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Shaft,</hi> in mining, is the pit or hollow entrance into the mine. In the tin-mines, after this is ſunk about a fathom, they leave a little, long, ſquare place, which is called a shamble.</p><p>Shafts are ſunk ſome ten, ſome twenty fathoms deep into the earth, more or leſs. Of theſe ſhafts, there is the landing or working ſhaft, where they bring up the work or ore to the ſurface ; but if it be worked by a horſe engine or whim, it is called a <hi rend="italic">whim-shaft ;</hi> and where the water is drawn out of the mine, it is indifferently named an eng<hi rend="italic">ine-shaft,</hi> or the <hi rend="italic">rod-shaft.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Mine.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Shaft,</hi> in ornithology, See <hi rend="smallcaps">Trochilus.</hi></p><p>SHAFTESBURY, a town of Dorſetſhire in England, in W. Long. 3. 20, N. Lat, 51. 0. It ſtands on a high hill, and is built in the form of a bow. It enjoys a ſerene wholeſome air, and has a fine proſpect. It is a good thoroughfare, is governed by a mayor, and lends two members to parliament. This town is ſuppoſed to have been built in the 8th century, and to have been enlarged by king Alfred, and had 12 churches, beſides a Benedictine monaſtery, in the time of the Saxons, but has now only three. St Edward the martyr was</p><p>buried here. It had three mints before the conqueſt, and, in the reign of Henry VIII. was the ſee of a ſuffragan biſhop. It was incorporated by queen Elizabeth and Charles II and is governed by a mayor, recorder, twelve aldermen, bailiffs, and a common-council. It contains about 320 houfes, many of which are of free-ſtone. Water is ſo scarce, that it uſed to be ſupplied from Motcomb ; but it was obtained more commodiouſly in 1718, by means of engines, which raiſed the water above 300 feet perpendicular, and conveyed it to a large ciſtern in the middle of the town, from the diſtance of two miles. Yet even this is laid aſide, and they have dug ſeveral pits, in which they preſerve the rain-water; and the poor get their living to this day by fetching it in pails or on horſes. It gives the title of earl to the noble family of Cooper.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">ShaFtesburY</hi> (earl of). See <hi rend="smallcaps">Cooper.</hi></p><p>SHAG, in ornithology. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Pelicanus.</hi></p><p>SHAGREEN, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Chagreen,</hi> in commerce, a kind of grained leather prepared of the ſkin of a ſpecies of <hi rend="smallcaps">Squalus,</hi> much uſed in covering cafes, books, &amp;c.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Manner oſ preparing SHAGREEN.</hi> The ſkin, being flayed off, is ſtretched out, covered over with muſtard- ſeed, and the ſeed bruiſed on it ; and thus it is expoſed to the weather for ſome days, and then tanned.</p><p>The beſt is that brought from Conſtantinople, of a browniſh colour ; the white is the worſt. It is extremely hard ; yet, when ſteeped in water, it becomes very ſoft and pliable ; whence it is of great uſe among caſe-makers. It takes any colour that is given it, red, green, yellow, or black. It is frequently counterfeited by morocco, formed like ſhagreen ; but this laſt is diſtinguiſhed by its peeling off, which the firſt does not.</p><p>SHAIK properly ſignifies an old man. In the east it is uſed to denote a lord or chief, a man of eminence and property. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Schiechs.</hi></p><p>SHAKE, in singing. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Trill.</hi></p><p>SHAKESPEARE or <hi rend="smallcaps">Shakspeare</hi> (William), the prince of dramatic writers, was born at Stratford upon Avon in Warwickshire, on the 23d of April 1564. From the regiſter of that town, it appears that a plague broke out there on the 30th of June following, which raged with great violence ; but fortunately it did not reach the houſe in which this infant prodigy lay. His father, John Shakeſpeare, enjoyed a ſmall patrimonial eſtate, and was a considerable dealer in wool ; his mother was the daughter and heir of Robert Arden of Wellingcote. Our illuſtrious poet being designed for the busineſs of his father, received no better education than the inductions which the free-school of Stratford could afford. After applying ſome time to the ſtudy of Latin, he was called home to aſſiſt his father, who ſeems by ſome accident to have been reduced in his circumſtances. Before arriving at the age of 19, he married the daughter of Mr Hathaway, a ſubſtantial yeoman in the neighbourhood of Stratford. This lady was eight years older than her huſband, Having the misfortune to fall into bad company, he was seduced into ſome profligate actions, which drew on him a criminal proſecution, and at length forced him to take refuge in the capital. In concert with his associates, he broke into a park belonging to Sir Thomas Lucy of Charlecote, and carried off ſome of his deer, Every admirer of Shakeſpeare will regret that ſuch a blemiſh ſhould have ſtained his character ;</p></body></text></TEI>