<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-18T21:02:59Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>writer into a ſpectator, ſo as to figure, in some obſcure manner, an action as
                paſſing in his sight and hearing. In that figured ſituation, being led naturally to
                write like a ſpectator, he entertains his readers with his own reflections, with
                cool deſcription, and florid declamation ; inſtead of making them eye-witneſſes, as
                it were, to a real event, and to every movement of genuine paſſion. Thus moſt of our
                plays appear to be cast in the same mould ; perſonages without character, the mere
                outlines of paſſion, a tireſome monotony, and a pompous declamatory ſtyle.</p>
            <p>This deſcriptive manner of repreſenting paſſion is a very cold entertainment ; our
                ſympathy is not raiſed by deſcription ;. we muſt firſt be lulled into a dream of
                reality, and every thing muſt appear as paſſing in our light. Unhappy is the player
                of genius who acts a part in what may be termed a <hi rend="italic">deſcriptive
                    tragedy ;</hi> after aſſuming the very paſſion that is to be repreſented, how is
                he cramped in action, when he muſt utter, not the ſentiments of the paſſion he
                feels, but a cold deſcription in the language of a byſtander ? It is that
                imperfection, undoubtedly, in the bulk of our plays, which confines our ſtage almoſt
                entirely to Shakeſpeare, notwithſtanding his many irregularities. In our late
                Engliſh tragedies, we ſometimes find ſentiments tolerably well adapted to a plain
                paſſion : but we muſt not in any of them expect a ſentiment expreſſive of character
                ; and, upon that very account, our late performances of the dramatic kind are for
                the moſt part intolerably inſipid.</p>
            <p>But it may be proper to illuſtrate this ſubject by examples. The firſt examples ſhall
                be of ſentiments that appear the legitimate offspring of paſſion ; to which ſhall be
                oppoſed what are deſcriptive only, and illegitimate : and in making this compariſon,
                the inſtances ſhall be borrowed from <bibl><author>Shakeſpeare</author></bibl> and
                        <bibl><author>Corneille</author></bibl>, who for genius in dramatic
                compoſition ſtand uppermoſt in the rolls of fame.</p>
            <p>I. <bibl><author>Shakeſpeare</author></bibl> ſhall furniſh the firſt example, being
                of ſentiments dictated by a violent and perturbed paſſion :</p>
            <sp>
                <speaker>Lear.</speaker>
                <l>—Filial ingratitude!</l>
                <l>Is it not as if this mouth ſhould tear this hand</l>
                <l>For lifting food toſt ?—But I’ll puniſh home ;</l>
                <l>No, I will weep no more.—In ſuch a night,</l>
                <l>To ſhut me out !—Pour on, I will endure.</l>
                <l>In ſuch a night as this ! O Regan, Gonerill,</l>
                <l>Your old kind father, whoſe frank heart gave all—</l>
                <l>O ! that way madneſs lies ; let me ſhun that ;</l>
                <l>No more of that.—</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker>Kent.</speaker>
                <l>Good, my lord, enter here.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker>Lear.</speaker>
                <l>Prithee, go in thyſelf, ſeek thine own eaſe,</l>
                <l>This tempeſt will not give me leave to ponder</l>
                <l>On things would hurt me more : —but I’ll go in ;</l>
                <l>In, boy, go firſt. You houſeleſs poverty— </l>
                <l>Nay, get thee in ; I’ll pray, and then I’ll ſleep—</l>
                <l>Poor naked wretches, whereſoe’er you are,</l>
                <l>That bide the pelting of this pitileſs ſtorm !</l>
                <l>How ſhall your houſeleſs heads, and unfed ſides,</l>
                <l>Your loop’d and window’d raggedneſs defend you</l>
                <l>From ſeaſons ſuch as theſe !—Ο I have ta’en</l>
                <l>Too little care of this ! take phyſic, Pomp ;</l>
                <l>Expoſe thyſelf to feel what wretches feel,</l>
                <l>That thou may’ſt ſhake the ſuperflux to them,</l>
                <l>And ſhow the heav’ns more juft.</l>
            </sp>
            <bibl><title>King Lear</title>, act 3. sc. 5.</bibl>
            <p>With regard to the French author, truth obliges us to acknowledge, that he deſcribes
                in the ſtyle of a ſpectator, inſtead of expreſſing paſſion like one who feels it ;
                which naturally betrays him into a tireſome monotony, and a pompous declamatory
                ſtyle. It is ſcarce neceſſary to give examples, for he never varies from that tone.
                We ſhall, however, take two paſſages at a venture, in order to be confronted with
                thoſe tranſcribed above. In the tragedy of <bibl><title>Cinna</title></bibl>, alter
                the conspiracy was diſcovered, Æmilia, having nothing in view but racks and death to
                herſelf and her lover, receives a pardon from Auguſtus, attended with the brighteſt
                circumſtances of magnanimity and tenderneſs. This is a lucky ſituation for
                repreſenting the paſſions of surpriſe and gratitude in their different ſtages, which
                ſeem naturally to be what follow. Theſe paſſions, raiſed at once to the utmoſt
                pitch, and being at firſt too big for utterance, muſt, for ſome moments, be
                expreſſed by violent geſtures only : ſo ſoon as there is vent for words, the firſt
                expreſſions are broken and interrupted : at laſt, we ought to expect a tide of
                intermingled ſentiments, occaſioned by the fluctuation of the mind between the two
                paſſions. Æmilia is made to behave in a very different manner : with extreme
                coolness ſhe deſcribes her own ſituation, as if ſhe were merely a ſpectator ; or
                rather the poet takes the taſk off her hands:</p>
            <sp>
                <l>Et je me rends, Seigneur, à ces hautes bontés :</l>
                <l>Je recouvre la vûe auprès de leurs clartés.</l>
                <l>Je connois mon forfait qui me sembloit juſtice ;</l>
                <l>Et ce que n’avoit pû la terreur du supplice,</l>
                <l>Je fens naître en mon ame un repentir puissant,</l>
                <l>Et mon cœur en secret me dit, qu’il y consent.</l>
                <l>Le ciel a resolu votre grandeur suprême ;</l>
                <l>Et pour preuve, Seigneur, je n’en veux que moi-même.</l>
                <l>J’ose avec vanité me donner cet éclat,</l>
                <l>Puisqu’il change mon cœur, qu’il veut changer l’état.</l>
                <l>Ma haine va mourir, que j’ai crue immortelle;</l>
                <l>Elle est morte, et ce cœur devient sujet fidele ;</l>
                <l>Et prenant déformais cette haine en horreur,</l>
                <l>L’ardeur de vous servir succede à sa fureur.</l>
            </sp>
            <bibl>Act 5. sc. 3</bibl>
            <p>So much in general upon the genuine ſentiments of paſſion. We proceed to particular
                obſervations. And, firſt, paſſions ſeldom continue uniform any conſiderable time :
                they generally fluctuate, ſwelling and ſubſiding by turns, often in a quick
                ſucceſſion ; and the ſentiments cannot be juſt unleſs they correſpond to ſuch
                fluctuation. Accordingly, a climax never ſhows better than in expreſſing a ſwelling
                paſſion : the following paſſages may ſuffice for an illuſtration.</p>
            <sp>
                <speaker>Almeria.</speaker>
                <l>—How haſt thou charm’d</l>
                <l>The wildneſs of the waves and rocks to this ;</l>
                <l>That thus relenting they have giv’n thee back</l>
                <l>To earth, to light and life, to love and me ?</l>
            </sp>
            <bibl><title>Mourning Bride</title>, act 1. ſc. 7.</bibl>
            <sp>
                <l>I would not be the villain that thou think’ſt</l>
                <l>For the whole ſpace that’s in the tyrant’s graſp,</l>
                <l>And the rich earth to boot.</l>
            </sp>
            <bibl><title>Macbeth</title>, act 4. ſc. 4.</bibl>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
