<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:06:51Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Main and fore courſes are lined on the leeches, from clue to earing, with one cloth ſeamed on and ſtuck or ſtitched in the middle, and have a middle band half way between the lower reef band and the foot, alſo four buntline cloths, at equal diſtances between the leeches, the upper end of which are carried under the middle band, that the lower side of the band may be tabled upon or ſewed over the end of the buntline pieces. They have likewiſe two reef bands ; each in breadth one third of the breadth of the canvas ; the upper one is one ſixth of the depth of the ſail from the head, and the lower band is at the ſame diſtance from the upper one ; the ends go four inches under the leech linings, which are ſeamed over the reef bands. All linings are ſeamed on, and are ſtuck with 68 to 72 ſtitches in a yard.</p><p>“ Main, fore, and mizen, topſails have leech linings, mast and top linings, buntline cloths, middle bands and reef bands. The leech linings are made of one breadth of cloth, ſo cut and ſewed as to be half a cloth broad at the head, and a cloth and a half broad at the foot ; the piece cut out being half the breadth of the cloth at one end, and tapering to a point at the other. The middle bands are put on half way between the lower reef and foot, the buntline cloths join the top-linings, and the buntline cloths and top-linings are carried up to the lower side of the middle band, which is tabled on them. The maſt lining is of two cloths, and extends from the foot of the ſail to the lower reef, to receive the beat or chafe of the maſt. The middle band is made of one breadth of canvas, of the fame number as the top-lining. It is firſt folded and rubbed down, to make a creaſe at one third of the breadth ; then tabled on the ſelvage, and ſtuck along the creaſe ; then turned down, and tabled and ſtuck through both the double and ſingle parts, with 68 to 7 2 ſtitches in a yard. It is the opinion of many, that middle bands ſhould not be put on until the ſail is half worn.</p><p>“ Main and fore topsails have three and ſometimes four reef bands from leech to leech, over the leech linings ; the upper one is one eighth of the depth of the ſail from the head, and they are the ſame diſtance aſunder in the royal navy, but more in the merchant ſervice. The reef bands are each of half a breadth of canvas put on double ; the firſt ſide is ſtuck twice, and the laſt turned over, ſo that the reef holes may be worked upon the double part of the band, which is alſo ſtuck with 68 to 72 ſtitches in a yard.</p><p>“ The top-lining of topſails is of canvas n<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> 6 or 7. The other linings of this, and all the linings of other ſails, ſhould be of the ſame quality as the sails to which they belong.</p><p>“ Top-linings and maſt cloths are put on the aft ſide, and all ocher linings on the fore ſide, of ſails. Mizens are lined with one breadth of cloth from the clue five yards up the leech, and have a reef band ſewed on, in the ſame manner as on other ſails, at one fifth the depth of the ſail from the foot ; they have alſo a nock-piece and a peek-piece, one cut out of the other, ſo that each contains one yard. Mizen topſails of 50 gun ſhips and upwards have three reefs, the upper one is one eighth of the depth of the ſail from the head, and the reefs are at the ſame diſtance aſunder. Mizen topſails of ſhips of 44 guns and under have two reefs one ſeventh part of the depth of the ſail aſunder, the upper one being at the ſame diſtance from the head. Main and main top</p><p>ſtudding ſails have each one reef, at one eighth of the depth of the ſail ſrom the head. Reef bands ſhould not be put on until the ſail is ſewed up, a contrary practice being very erroneous. Lower ſtayſails, fore top and main top ſtayſails, and flying jibs, have clue-pieces two yards long. Square tack ſtayſails have half a breadth of cloth at the fore part, with a clue-piece containing two yards, and a peek-piece, containing one yard.</p><p>“ Sails have two holes in each cloth, at the heads and reefs of courſes, topſails, and other ſquare ſails ; one hole in every yard in the ſtay of flying jibs, and one in every three quarters of a yard in the ſtays of ſquare tack and other ſtayſails. Theſe are made by an inſtrument called a <hi rend="italic">pegging awl, or</hi> a ſtabber, and are fenced round by ſtitching the edge to a ſmall grommet, made with log or other line ; when finiſhed, they ſhould be well ſtretched or rounded up by a pricker or a marline-ſpike. Reef and head holes of large ſails have grommets of twelve-thread line, worked round with 18 to 21 ſtitches ; ſmaller ſails have grommets of nine-thread line, with 16 to 18 ſtitches, or as many as ſhall cover the line, and ſmaller holes in proportion. The holes for marling the clues of ſails and the top-brims of topſails have grommets of log-line, and ſhould have from 9 to 11 ſtitches ; twelve holes are worked in each cloth. Main courſes have marling holes from the clue to the lower bow line cringle up the leech, and from the clue to the firſt buntline cringle on the foot. Fore courſes have marling holes one eighth of the depth of the ſail up the leech, and from the clue to the firſt buntline cringle at the foot. Main and fore topſails have marling holes three feet each way from the clue and at the top-brims. Spritſails, mizen topſails, lower ſtayſails, main and fore top ſtayſails, and jibs, have marling holes two feet each way from the clues. All other ſails are ſewed home to the clues. Marling holes of courſes are at three fourths of the depth of the tablings at the clues from the rope, and thoſe of topsails are at half the depth of the tablings at the clues and top-brim from the rope.”</p><p>The rope, which is ſewed on the edges of ſails to prevent their rending, and which is called <hi rend="italic">bolt-rope, </hi>ſhould be well made of fine yarn, ſpun from the bell Riga rhine hemp well topt, and ſewed on with good Engliſh-made twine of three threads, ſpun 200 fathom to the pound ; the twine in the royal navy is dipped in a compoſition made with bees-wax, 4 lbs ; hogs lard 5 lbs ; and clear turpentine one pound ; and in the merchant ſervice, in tar ſoftened with oil. They ſhould be ſtoved in a ſtove by the heat of a flue, and not in a baker’s oven or a ſtove tub ; and tarred in the beſt Stockholm tar. The flexibility of them ſhould be always conſidered, in taking in the slack, which mull rest on the judgment of the ſailmaker.</p><p>" Bolt-ropes of courſes, topſails, and all other ſails, ſhould be neatly ſewed on through every buntline of the rope ; and, to avoid ſtretching, the rope muſt be kept tightly twiſted while ſewing on, and care taken that neither too much nor too little slack is taken in ; they are to be croſs-ſtitched at the leeches every twelve inches in length ; at every ſeam, and in the middle of every cloth at the foot, with three croſs-ſtitches : four croſs-ſtitches ſhould be taken at all beginnings and fastenings off ; the firſt ſtitch given twice, and the last three times. Small ſails have two croſs ſtitches at every ſeam, and three at every faſtening off.</p></body></text></TEI>