<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:01:52Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>could, by reading the uſual preparatory books, and attending the beſt lectures during that and the following winter in London, in order to improve himſelf farther, in January 1718-19 he went to Paris. There he lodged in the ſame houſe with the famous anatomiſt Mr Winſlow, whoſe lectures he attended, as he did thoſe of the materia medica, chemiſtry, and botany, at the king’s gardens. The operations of ſurgery he ſaw at the <hi rend="italic">Hotel Dieu,</hi> and attended alſo for ſome time M. Gregoire, the accoucheur, but without any deſign of ever practiſing that or any other branch of ſurgery. Here he became acquainted with Mr Martin Benſon, afterwards biſhop of Glouceſter, one of the moſt agreeable and virtuous men of his time; with whom he quickly became much connected, and not many years after was united to him by the ſtricteſt bonds of affinity as well as affection.</p><p>During the whole of Mr Secker's continuance at Paris, he kept up a conſtant correſpondence with Mr Joſeph Butler, afterwards biſhop of Durham, with whom he became acquainted at the academy of one Mr Tones, kept firſt at Glouceſter, and afterward at Tewkſhury. Mr Butler having been appointed preacher at the Rolls on the recommendation of Dr Clarke and Mr Edward Talbot, ſon to biſhop Talbot, he now took occaſion to mention his friend Mr Secker, without Secker’s knowledge, to Mr Talbot, who promiſed, in caſe he choſe to take orders in the church of England, to engage the biſhop his father to provide for him. This was communicated to Mr Secker in a letter from Mr Butler about the beginning of May 1720. He had not at that time come to any reſolution of quitting the ſtudy of phyſic; but he began to foreſee many obſtacles to his purſuing that profeſſion; and having never diſcontinued his application to theology, his former difficulties both with regard to conformity and ſome other doubtful points had gradually leſſened, as his judgment became ſtronger, and his reading and knowledge more extenſive. It appears alſo from two of his letters ſtill in being, written from Paris to a friend in England, (both of them prior to the date of Mr Butler’s above- mentioned), that he was greatly diſſatisfied with the diviſions and diſturbances which at that particular period prevailed among the Diſſenters.</p><p>In this ſtate of mind Mr Butler’s unexpected propoſal found him; which he was therefore very well diſpoſed to take into conſideration; and after deliberating on the ſubject of ſuch a change for upwards of two months, he reſolved at length to embrace the offer, and for that purpoſe quitted France about the beginning of Auguſt 1720.</p><p>On his arrival in England, he was introduced to Mr Talbot, with whom he cultivated a cloſe acquaintance; but it was unfortunately of very fhort duration; for in the month of December that gentleman died of the ſmall-pox. This was a great ſhock to all his friends, who had juſtly conceived the higheſt expectations of him; but eſpecially to an amiable lady whom he had lately married, and who was very near linking under ſo ſudden and grievous a ſtroke. Mr Secker, beſide ſharing largely in the common grief, had peculiar reaſon to lament an accident that ſeemed to put an end to all his hopes; but he had taken his reſolution, and he determined to perſevere. It was ſome encouragement to him to find that Mr Talbot had, on his death-bed, recommended him, together with Mr Benſon and Mr Butler, to his father’s notice. Thus did that excellent young man (for he was but 29 when he died), by his nice diſcernment of characters, and his conſiderate good nature, provide moſt effectually, in a few ſolemn moments, for the welfare of that church from which he himſelf was ſo prematurely ſnatched away; and at the ſame time raiſed up, when he leaſt thought of it, the trueſt friend and protector to his wife and unborn daughter; who afterwards found in Mr Secker all that tender care and aſſiſtance which they could have hoped for from the neareſt relation.</p><p>It being judged neceſſary by Mr Secker’s friends that he ſhould have a degree at Oxford; and having been informed, that if he ſhould previouſly take the degree of Doctor in Phyſic at Leyden, it would probably help him in-obtaining the other, he went over and took his degree there in March 1721: and, as part of his exerciſe for it, he compoſed and printed a diſſertation <hi rend="italic">de Medicina Statica.</hi> which is ſtill extant, and is thought by the gentlemen of that proſeſſion to be a ſenfible and learned performance.</p><p>In April the ſame year, he entered himſelf a gentleman commoner of Exeter college, Oxford; after which he obtained the degree of Bachelor of Arts, in consequence of the chancellor’s recommendatory letter to the convocation.</p><p>He now ſpent a conſiderable part of his time in London, where he quickly gained the eſteem of ſome of the moſt learned and ingenious men of thoſe days, particularly of Dr Clarke, rector of St James’s, and the celebrated dean Berkeley, afterwards biſhop of Cloyne, with whom he every day became more delighted, and more cloſely connected. He paid frequent viſits of gratitude and friendſhip to Mrs Talbot, widow of Mr Edward Talbot, by whom ſhe had a daughter five months after his deceaſe. With her lived Mrs Catharine Benſon, ſiſter to biſhop Benſon, whom in many reſpects ſhe greatly reſembled. She had been for ſeveral years Mrs Talbot’s inſeparable companion, and was of unſpeakable ſervice to her at the time of her huſband’s death, by exerting all her courage, activity, and good ſenſe (of which ſhe poſſeſſed a large ſhare), to ſupport her friend under ſo great an affliction, and by afterwards attending her ſickly infant with the utmoſt care and tenderneſs, to which, under Providence, was owing the preſervation of a very valuable life.</p><p>Biſhop Talbot being in 1721 appointed to the ſee of Durham, Mr Secker was in 1722 ordained deacon by him in St James’s church, and prieſt not long after in the ſame place, where he preached his firſt ſermon March 28. 1723. The biſhop’s domeſtic chaplain at that time was Dr Rundle, a man of warm fancy and very brilliant converſation, but apt ſometimes to be carried by the vivacity of his wit into indiſcreet and ludicrous expreſſions, which created him enemies, and, on one occaſion, produced diſagreeable conſequences.—. With him Mr Secker was ſoon after aſſociated in the biſhop’s family, and both taken down by his lordſhip to Durham in July 1723.</p><p>In the following year the biſhop gave Mr Secker the rectory of Houghton-le-Spring. This preferment putting it in his power to fix himſelf in the world, in a manner agreeable to his inclinations, he ſoon after made a propoſal of marriage to Mrs Benſon; which being ac-</p></body></text></TEI>