<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:07:07Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>The ſecond part or portion of the ſhore is much more affected by the ſea than the former, being frequently waſhed and beaten by it. Its productions are rendered ſalt by the water, audit is covered with sand, or with the fragments of ſhells in form of fand, and in ſome places with a tartarous matter depoſited from the water ; the colour of this whole extent of ground is uſually duſky and dull, eſpecially where there are rocks and ftones, and theſe covered with a ſlimy matter.</p><p>The third part of the ſhore is more affected by the ſea than either of the others ; and is covered with an uniform crust of the true nature of the bottom of the ſea, except that plants and animals have their reſidence in it, and the decayed parts of theſe alter it a little.</p><p>SHORE (Jane), the celebrated concubine of the licentious king Edward IV. was the wife of Mr Matthew Shore, a goldſmith in Lombard ftreet, London. Kings are ſeldom unſucceſsful in their amorous purſuits; therefore there was nothing wonderful in Mrs Shore’s removing from Lombard-ſtreet to ſhine at court as the royal favourite. Historians repreſent her as extremely beautiful, remarkably cheerful, and of moſt uncommon generoſity. The king, it is ſaid, was no leſs captivated with her temper than with her perſon : ſhe never made uſe of her influence over him to the prejudice of any perſon ; and if ever ſhe importuned him, it was in favour of the unfortunate. After the death of Edward, ſhe attached herſelf to the lord Haſtings ; and when Richard III. cut off that nobleman as an obſtacle to his ambitious ſchemes, Jane Shore was arreſted as an accomplice, on the ridiculous accuſation of witchcraft. This, however, terminated only in a public penance ; excepting that Richard rifled her of all her little property : but whatever ſeverity might have been exerciſed towards her, it appears that ſhe was alive, though ſufficiently wretched, under the reign of Henry VIII. when Sir Thomas More ſaw her poor, old, and ſhrivelled, without the leaſt trace of her former beauty. Mr Rowe, in his tragedy of Jane Shore, has adopted the popular ſtory related in the old hiſtorical ballad, of her periſhing by hunger in a ditch where Shoreditch now ſtands. But Stow aſſures us that street was ſo named before her time.</p><p>SHORL. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Schorl.</hi></p><p>SHORLING and <hi rend="smallcaps">Morling,</hi> are words to diſtinguiſh fells of ſheep ; sho<hi rend="italic">rling</hi> being the fells after the fleeces are ſhorn off the ſheep’s back ; and <hi rend="italic">morling,</hi> the fells flead off after they die or are killed. In ſome parts of England they understand by a sh<hi rend="italic">orling,</hi> a ſheep whoſe face is ſhorn off ; and by a <hi rend="italic">marling,</hi> a ſheep that dies.</p><p>SHORT (James), an eminent optician, was born in Edinburgh on the 10th of June, O. S. în the year 1710. At ten years of age, having lost his father and mother, and being left in a state of indigence, he was received into Heriots' Hoſpital, (see <hi rend="italic">EDINBURGH Public Buildings,</hi> n⁰ 16. ), where he ſoon diſplayed his mechanical genius in conſtructing, for himſelf, little cheſts, book- cases, and other conveniences, with ſuch tools as fell in his way. At the age of twelve he was removed from the Hoſpital to the High School, where he ſhowed a conſiderable taſte for claſſical literature, and generally kept at the head of his forms. In the year 1726 he was entered into the univerſity, where he paſſed through</p><p>the usual courſe of education, and took his maſter’s degree with great applauſe.</p><p>By his friends he was intended for the church ; but after attending a courſe of theological lectures, his mind revolted from a profeſſion which he thought little suited to his talents ; and he devoted his whole time to mathematical and mechanical purſuits. He had been fortunate enough to have the celebrated M'Laurin for his preceptor ; who having ſoon diſcovered the bent of his genius, and made a proper eſtimate of the extent of his capacity, encouraged him to proſecute thoſe ſtudies in which nature had qualified him to make the greateſt figure. Under the eye of that eminent maſter, he began in 1732 to conſtruct Gregorian teleſcopes; and, as the profeſſor obſerved in a letter to Dr Jurin, “by taking care of the figure of his ſpecula, he was enabled to give them larger apertures, and to carry them to greater perfection, than had ever been done before him.” See <hi rend="smallcaps">Optics,</hi> n⁰ 97.)</p><p>In the year 1736 Mr Short was called to London, at the deſire of Queen Caroline, to give inſtructions in mathematics to William duke of Cumberland; and immediately on his appointment to that very honourable office he was elected a fellow of the royal ſociety, and patroniſed by the earls of Morton and Macclesfield. In the year 1739 he accompanied the former of thoſe noble lords to the Orkney Iſles, where he was employed in adjuſting the geography of that part of Scotland : and happy it was for him that he was ſo employed, as he might otherwiſe have been involved in a ſcuffle which took place between the retainers of Sir James Stewart of Barra and the attendants of the earl, in which ſome of the latter were dangerouſly wounded.</p><p>Mr Short having returned to London, and finally establiſhed himſelf there in the line of his profeſſion, was in 1743 employed by lord Thomas Spencer to make for him a reflector of twelve feet focus, for which he received 600 guineas. He made ſeveral other teleſcopes of the ſame focal diſtance with greater improvements and higher magnifiers ; and in 1752 finiſhed one for the king of Spain, for which, with its whole apparatus, he received 1200 l. I his was the nobleſt inſtrument of the kind that had then been conſtructed, and perhaps it has never yet been ſurpaſſed except by the aſtoniſhing reflectors of Herſchel. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Telescope.</hi></p><p>Mr Short was wont to viſit the place of his nativity once every two or three years during his reſidence in London, and in 1766 he viſited it for the laſt time. On. the 15th of June 1768 he died, after a very ſhort illness, at Newington Butts, near London, of a mortification in his bowels, and was buried on the 22d of the ſame month, having completed, within a few days, his fifty-eighth year. He left a fortune of about 20,00cl. of which 15,000 l. was bequeathed to two nephews, and the rest in legacies to his friends. In gratitude for the ſteady patronage of the earl of Morton, he left to his daughter the Lady Mary Douglas, afterwards counted of Aboyne, 1000 l. and the reverſion of his fortune, ſhould his nephews die without iſſue ; but this reverſionary legacy the lady, at the deſire of her father, generouſly relinquished by a deed in favour of Mr Short’s brother Mr Thomas Short and his children. Mr Short's eminence as an artiſt is univerſally known, and we have often heard him ſpoken of by thoſe who had</p></body></text></TEI>