<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:02:43Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ably pale and wan all her life after, that it was eaſy to read the loss of her blood and ſpirits in her countenance. In the mean time, Seneca, finding his death flow and lingering, deſired Statius Annæus his phyſician to give him a dose of poison, which had been prepared ſome time before in case it ſhould be wanted ; but this not having its uſual effect, he was carried to a hot bath, where he was at length ſtiſted with the ſteams. He died, as Lipſius conjectures, in the 63d or 64th year of his age, and in about the 10th or 11th of Nero’s reign. Tacitus, on mentioning his death, obſerves, that, as he entered the bath, he took of the water, and with it ſprinkled ſome of his neareſt domeſtics, saying, “ That he offered thoſe libations to Jupiter the Deliverer.” Theſe words are an evident proof that Seneca was not a Chriſtian, as ſome have imagined him to have been ; and that the 13 epiſtles from Seneca to St Raul, and from St Paul to Seneca, are ſuppoſititious pieces. His philosophical works are well known.— They conſiſt of 124 <hi rend="italic">epistles</hi> and diſtinct treatiſes ; and, except his books of phyſical queſtions, are chiefly of the moral kind, treating of anger, conſolation, providence, tranquillity of mind, conſtancy, clemency, the ſhortneſs of life, a happy life, retirement, benefits. He has been juſtly cenſured by Quintilian and other critics, as one of the firſt corrupters of the Roman ſtyle ; but his works are highly valuable, on account of the vaſt erudition which they diſcover, and the beautiful moral ſentiments which they contain.</p><p>SENECIO, <hi rend="smallcaps">Groundsel,</hi> in botany: A genus belonging to the claſs of ſyngeneſia, and to the order of polygamia ſuperflua ; and in the natural claſſiſication ranked under the 49th order, <hi rend="italic">Compositae.</hi> The receptacle is naked ; the pappus ſimple ; the calyx cylindrical and calyculated. The ſcales are equal and contiguous, ſo as to ſeem entire ; thoſe at the baſe are few, and have their apices or points decayed. There are 57 ſpecies. Of theſe, ſeven are Britiſh, the vulgaris, viſeoſus, ſylvaticus, erucifolius, jacobæa, paludoſus, and ſaracenicus.</p><p>1. The <hi rend="italic">vulgaris,</hi> or common groundſel, has its corollæ naked, its leaves ſeſſile, ſmooth, and ſinuated, their ſegments ſhort, broad, and minutely ſerrated; the flowers are yellow, and without radii. This weed grows in cultivated ground everywhere, and flowers in May. Its leaves have been uſed in medicine externally as a vulnerary and refrigerant, and internally as a mild emetic ; but they have little or no efficacy. 2. The <hi rend="italic">viſeoſus, or </hi>cotton groundſel, has its corollas revolute, its leaves pin- natiſid, viſcid, and downy. The ſcales of the calyx are lax and hairy, and are of the same length with the perianthium. 3. The <hi rend="italic">ſylvaticus,</hi> or mountain groundſel, has its corollæ revolute, its leaves pinnatifid and dentated, the ſtem comrybous and erect. It flowers in July, and is frequent in woods and heaths. 4. The <hi rend="italic">eruciſolius,</hi> hoary perennial ragwort ; the corollæ are radiant ; the leaves are pinnatifid, dentated, and downy beneath ; the ſtem is erect, and two feet high ; the flowers are yellow, and grow in cluſters. This plant is frequent in woods and hedges. 5. The <hi rend="italic">jacobaea,</hi> common ragwort ; the corollæ are radiant ; the leaves pinnated and lyre-ſhaped, and of a dark-green colour ; the ſtalk is erect, round, and generally purpliſh ; the flowers grow in cluſters on the tops of the ſtalks. The leaves have a bitteriſh ſubacrid taſte, and extremely nauſeous. Si</p><p>mon Paulli says, that a decoction of them cured many ſoldiers of an epidemic dyſentery. 6. The <hi rend="italic">paludoſus, </hi>marſh ragwort ; the corollæ are radiant ; the leaves ſword-ſhaped, acutely ſerrated, and ſomewhat downy underneath ; the ſtem is erect, branched towards the top, and four or five feet high ; the flowers are large and yellow. This plant is frequent in fens and ditches in England. 7. The <hi rend="italic">ſaracenicus,</hi> broad-leaved ragwort; the corollæ are radiant ; the leaves are lanceolated, ſerrated, and ſomewhat ſmooth ; the ſtem is erect, ſimple, and four or five feet high ; there are ſeveral flowers on each footſtalk, which are yellow, and grow in cluſters on the top. The plant grows in moiſt paſtures in England ; and flowers in July or Auguſt.</p><p>SENEGAL, a part of Negroland in Africa, the boundaries of which are not known. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Guinea.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Isle of S</hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps">enegal,</hi> ſometimes called <hi rend="italic">Saint Louis,</hi> is a small iſland in the mouth of the river Senegal, and according to Maſkelyne’s tables is ſituated in N. Lat 15. 53. W. Long. 16. 31. The Dutch were the firſt Europeans who fettled at Senegal ; but their colony was expelled by the French in 1687. It was taken by the Engliſh in 1692 ; and retaken by the French the year following. It was a second time taken poſſeſſion of by the Engliſh in 1758; but in 1779 the French recovered it, and it was ceded by the Britiſh crown by the treaty of 1783.</p><p>The best account of this iſland which we have ſeen, is given in the interesting voyage of M. Saugnier to the coaſt of Africa. This adventurer viſited Senegal in June 1785.</p><p>“The iſland (says he), properly ſpeaking, is only a bank of sand in the middle of the river. It is 1000 geometrical paces long, and about 60 in its greateſt width ; is almoſt on a level with the river and with the ſea, being defended from the latter by Barbary point, which is of greater elevation than the colony. The eaſtern branch of the river is the more conſiderable of the two, being about 400 toiſes acroſs ; the weſtern branch is only from 50 to 200 toiſes wide. The iſle conſiſts entirely of burning ſands, on the barren ſurface of which you ſometimes meet with ſcactered flints, thrown out among their ballaſt by veſſels coming from Goree, or with the ruins of buildings formerly erected by Europeans. There is ſcarcely ſuch a thing as a garden upon the iſland ; European ſeeds in general not thriving here. It is not ſurpriſing that the soil is ſo unproductive ; for the air is ſtrongly impregnated with ſea salt, which pervades every thing, and conſumes even iron in a very ſhort ſpace of time. The heats are  exceſſive, and rendered ſtill more inſupportable by the reflection of the fand ; ſo that from ten in the morning until four in the afternoon it is almoſt impoſſible to do any work. During the months of January, February, March, and April, the heats are moderated ; but in Auguſt and the following months they become ſo oppreſſive as even to affect the natives themſelves. What effect then muſt they have upon the Europeans, ſuddenly tranſported into this burning climate ? The nights are a little leſs ſultry ; not always, however, but only when the ſea-breeze ſets in. It is then that the inhabitants of the colony breathe a freſher air, for which they have been longing the whole of the day ; but this air in our climate would ſeem aburning vapour. The nights are nevertheleſs troublesome, notwithſtanding the comforts of the</p></body></text></TEI>