<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:03:16Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>judge, of his own authority, whether the patties will or not.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sequestration,</hi> in the civil law, is the act of the ordinary, dispoſing of the goods and chattels of one deceaſed, whoſe eſtate no man will meddle with.</p><p>A widow is alſo ſaid to ſequeſter, when ſhe diſclaims having any thing to do with the eſtate of her deceaſed huſhand.</p><p>Among the Romaniſts, in queſtions of marriage, where the wife complains of impotency in the huſband, ſhe is to be ſequeſtered into a convent, or into the hands of matrons, till the proceſs be determined.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sequestration</hi> is alſo uſed for the act of gathering the fruits of a benefice void, to the uſe of the next incumbent.</p><p>Sometimes a benefice is kept under ſequeſtration for many years, when it is of ſo ſmall value, that no clergyman fit to ſerve thc cure will be at the charge of taking it by inſtitution ; in which caſe the ſequeſtration is committed either to the curate alone, or to the curate and church-wardens jointly. Sometimes the profits of a living in controversy, either by the conſent of the parties, or the judge’s authority, are ſequeſtered and placed for ſafety in a third hand, till the suit is determined, a miniſter being appointed by the judge to ſerve the cure, and allowed a certain ſalary out of the profits. Sometimes the profits of a living are ſequeſtered ſor neglect of duty, for dilapidations, or for ſatisfying the debts of the incumbent.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sequestration,</hi> in chancery, is a commiſſion uſually directed to ſeven perſons therein named, empowering them to ſeize the defendant’s perſonal eſtate, and the profits of his real, and to detain them, ſubject to the order of the court. It iſſues on the return of the ſerjeant at arms, wherein it is certified, that the defendant had ſecreted himſelf.</p><p>Sequeſtrations were firſt introduced by Sir Nicholas Bacon, lord keeper in the reign of Queen Elizabeth ; before which the court found ſome difficulty in enforcing its proceſs and decrees ; and they do not ſeem to be in the nature of proceſs to bring in the defendant, but only intended to enforce the performance of the court’s decree.</p><p>A ſequeſtration is alſo made, in London, upon an action of debt ; the courſe of proceeding in which caſe is this : The action being entered, the officer goes to the defendant’s ſhop or warehouſe, when no perſon is there, and takes a padlock, and hangs it on the door, uttering theſe words : “ I do ſequeſter this warehouſe, and the goods and merchandize therein, of the defendant in this action, to the uſe of the plaintiff,” &amp;c. after which he ſets on his ſeal, and makes a return of the ſequeſtration in the compter ; and four days being paſſed after the return made, the plaintiff may, at the next court, have judgment to open the ſhop or warehouſe, and to have the goods appraiſed by two freemen, who are to be ſworn at the next court held for that compter ; and then the ſerjeant puts his hand to the bill of appraiſement, and the court grants judgment thereon ; but yet the defendant may put in bail before ſatisfaction, and by that means diſſolve the ſequeſtration ; and after ſatisfaction, may put in bail to diſprove the debt, &amp;c.</p><p>In the time of the civil wars, ſequeſtration was uſed for a ſeizing oſ the eſtates of delinquents for the uſe of the commonwealth.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sequestration,</hi> in Scots law. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Law,</hi> p. 683.</p><p>SEQUIN, a gold coin, ſtruck at Venice, and in ſeveral parts of the Grand Signior’s dominions. In Turkey it is called <hi rend="italic">dahab,</hi> or piece of gold, and according to Volney is in value about 6s. 3d. Sterling. It varies, however, conſiderably in its value in different countries. At Venice it is equal to about 9s. 2d. Sterling.</p><p>The Venetian ſequms are in great requeſt in Syria, from the fineneſs of their ſtandard, and the practice they have of employing them for womens trinkets. The faſhion of theſe trinkets does not require much art ; the piece of gold is ſimply pierced, in order to ſuſpend it by a chain, likewiſe of gold, which flows upon the breaſt. The more ſequins that are attached to this chain, and the greater the number of theſe chains, the more is a woman thought to be ornamented. This is the favourite luxury, and the emulation of all ranks. Even the female peasants, for want of gold, wear piaſtres or ſmaller pieces ; but the women of a certain rank diſdain ſilver ; they will accept of nothing but ſequins of Venice, or large Spaniſh pieces, and cruſadoes. Some of them wear 200 or 300, as well lying flat, as ſtrung one on another, and hung near the forehead, at the edge of the head-dreſs. It is a real load : but they do not think they can pay too dearly for the ſatisfaction of exhibiting this treaſure at the public bath, before a crowd of rivals, to awaken whoſe jealouſy conſtitutes their chief pleasure. The effect of this luxury on commerce, is the withdrawing conſiderable ſums from circulation, which remain dead ; besides, that when any of theſe pieces return into common uſe, having loſt their weight by being pierced, it becomes necessary to weigh them. The practice of weighing money is general in Syria, Egypt, and all Turkey. No piece, however effaced, is refuſed there ; the merchant draws out his ſcales and weighs it, as in the days of Abraham, when he purchaſed his ſepulchre. In conſiderable payments, an agent of exchange is ſent for, who counts paras by thousands, rejects a great many pieces of falſe money, and weighs all the ſequins, either ſeparately or together.</p><p>SERAGLIO, formed from the Perſian word seraw,  or Turkiſh word <hi rend="italic">ſarai,</hi> which ſignifies a houſe, and is commonly uſed to expreſs the houſe or palace of a prince. In this ſenſe it is frequently uſed at Conſtantinople ; the houſes of foreign ambaſſadors are called s<hi rend="italic">eraglios.</hi> But it is commonly uſed by way of eminence for the palace of the grand ſignior at Conſtantinople, where he keeps his court, and where his concubines are lodged, and where the youth are trained up for the chief polls of the empire.</p><p>It is a triangle about three Italian miles round, wholly within the city, at the end of the promontory Chryſoceras, now called the <hi rend="italic">Seraglio Point.</hi> The buildings run back to the top of the hill, and from thence are gardens that reach to the edge of the ſea. It is inclosed with a very high and ſtrong wall, upon which there are ſeveral watch towers : and it has many gates, ſome of which open towards the ſea-ſide, and the rest into the city ; but the chief gate is one of the latter, which is conſtantly guarded by a company oſ capoochees, or porters ; and in the night it is well guarded towards</p></body></text></TEI>