<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:03:10Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Method, conſiſting of a beautiful collection of woody plants, some of which, from their ſize and elegance, are very proper furniture for hedges. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Botany,</hi> p. 467.</p><p>SEPS, in zoology, a ſpecies of <hi rend="smallcaps">Lacerta.</hi></p><p>SEPTARIÆ, in natural hiſtory, a large claſs of foſſils, commonly known by the names of <hi rend="italic">ludus Helmontii</hi> and wa<hi rend="italic">xen veins.</hi></p><p>They are defined to be foſſils not inflammable, nor soluble in water ; of a moderately firm texture and duſky hue, divided by ſeveral ſepta or thin partitions, and compoſed of a ſparry matter greatly debaſed by earth ; not giving fire with ſteel ; fermenting with acids, and in great part diſſolved by them ; and calcining in a moderate fire.</p><p>Of this claſs there are two diſtinct orders of bodies, and under thoſe six genera. The septariæ of the first order are thoſe which are uſually found in large maſſes, of a simple uniform conſtruction, but divided by large ſepta either into larger and more irregular portions, or into ſmaller and more equal ones, called <hi rend="italic">talc. </hi>The genera of this order are four. 1. Thoſe divided by ſepta of ſpar, called se<hi rend="italic">comiœ .</hi> 2. Thoſe divided by ſepta of earthy matter, <hi rend="italic">called gaiophragmia ;</hi> 3. Thoſe divided by ſepta of the matter of the pyrites, called <hi rend="italic">pyritercia</hi> : And, 4. Thoſe divided by ſepta of ſpar, with an admixture of cryſtal, called <hi rend="italic">diaugophragmia.</hi></p><p>Thoſe of the ſecond order are ſuch as are uſually found in ſmaller maſſes, of a cruſtated ſtructure, formed by various incruſtations round a central nucleus, and divided by very thin ſepta. Of this order are only two genera. 1. Thoſe with a ſhort roundiſh nucleus, inclosed within the body of the maſs ; and, 2. Thoſe with a long nucleus, ſtanding out beyond the ends of the maſs.</p><p>SEPTAS, in botany : A genus of plants belonging to the order of <hi rend="italic">Heρtagynia,</hi> and the claſs of <hi rend="italic">Heptandria ; </hi>and in the natural ſyſtem ranged under the 13th order, <hi rend="italic">Succulenta.</hi> The calyx is divided into ſeven parts ; the petals are ſeven ; the germens ſeven : the capſules are alſo ſeven, and contain many ſeeds. There is only one ſpecies, the <hi rend="italic">Capensis,</hi> which is a native of the Cape of Good Hope, is round-leaved, and flowers in Auguſt or September.</p><p>SEPTEMBER, the ninth month of the year, conſiſting of only thirty days ; it took its name as being the ſeventh month, reckoning from March, with which the Romans began their year.</p><p>SEPTENNIAL, any thing laſting ſeven years.</p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Septennial</hi><hi rend="italic"> Elections.</hi> Blackſtone, in his Commentaries, Vol. I. p. 189. ſays, (after obſerving that the utmoſt extent of time allowed the ſame parliament to  sit by the ſtat. 6 W. and M. c. 2. was three years), “ But, by the ſtatute 1 Geo. I. ft. 2. c. 38. (in order <hi rend="italic">profeſſedly</hi> to prevent the great and continued expences of frequent elections, and the violent heats and animoſities conſequent thereupon, and for the peace and ſecurity of the government, juſt then recovering from the late rebellion), this term was prolonged to ſeven years ; and what alone is an inſtance of the vaſt authority of parliament, the very ſame houſe that was choſen for three years enacted its own continuance for ſeven.”</p><p>SEPTENTRIO, in aſtronomy, a conſtellation, more uſually called <hi rend="italic">urſa minor.</hi></p><p>In coſmography, the term s<hi rend="italic">eptentrio</hi> denotes the ſame with <hi rend="italic">north:</hi> and hence ſeptentrional is applied to any thing belonging to the north ; as <hi rend="italic">ſeptentrional ſigns, parallels,</hi> &amp;c.</p><p>SEPTICS, are thoſe ſubſtances which promote putrefaction, chiefly the calcareous earths, magneſia, and teſtaceous powders. From the many curious experiments made by Sir John Pringle to aſcertain the <hi rend="italic">ſeptic </hi>and <hi rend="italic">antiſeptic</hi> virtues of natural bodies, it appears that there are very few ſubſtances of a truly <hi rend="italic">ſeptic</hi> nature. Thoſe commonly reputed ſuch by authors, as the alcaline and volatile ſalts, he found to be no wife <hi rend="italic">ſeptic. </hi>However, he diſcovered ſome, where it ſeemed leaſt likely to find any ſuch quality ; theſe were chalk, common ſalt, and teſtaceous powders. He mixed twenty grains of crabs eyes, prepared with six drams of ox’s gall, and an equal quantity of water. Into another phial he put an equal quantity of gall and water, but no crabs-eyes. Both theſe mixtures being placed in the furnace, the putrefaction began much ſooner, where the powder was, than in the other phial. On making a like experiment with chalk, its <hi rend="italic">ſeptic</hi> virtue was found to be much greater than that of the crabs-eyes : nay, what the doctor had never met with before, in a mixture of two drams of fleſh, with two ounces of water and thirty grains of prepared chalk, the fleſh was reſolved into a perfect mucus in a few days.</p><p>To try whether the teſtaceous powders would alſo diſſolve vegetable ſubſtances, the doctor mixed them with barley and water, and compared this mixture with another of barley and water alone. After a long maceration by a fire, the plain water was found to ſwell the barley, and turn mucilaginous and four ; but that with the powder kept the grain to its natural ſize, and though it ſoftened it, yet made no mucilage, and remained ſweet.</p><p>Nothing could be more unexpected, than to find ſea ſalt a haſtener of putrefaction ; but the fact is thus ; one dram of ſalt preſerves two drams of freſh beef in two ounces of water, above thirty hours uncorrupted, in a heat equal to that of the human body ; or, which is the ſame thing, this quantity of ſalt keeps fleſh ſweet twenty hours longer than pure water ; but then half a dram of ſalt does not preſerve it above two hours longer. Twenty-five grains have little or no antiſeptic virtue, and ten, fifteen, or even twenty grains, manifeſtly both hasten and heighten the corruption. The quantity which had the moſt putrefying quality, was found to be about ten grains to the above proportion of fleſh and water.</p><p>Many inferences might be drawn from this experiment : one is, that ſince ſalt is never taken in aliment beyond the proportion oſ the corrupting quantities, it would appear that it is ſubſervient to digeſtion chiefly by its sep<hi rend="italic">tic</hi> virtue, that is, by softening and resolving meats ; an action very different from what is commonly- believed.</p><p>It is to be obſerved, that the above experiments were made with the ſalt kept for domeſtic uses. Sec Pringle’s Obſerv. on the Dheaſes of the army, p. 348, et ſeq.</p><p>SEPTIZON, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Septizonium,</hi> in Roman antiquity, a celebrated mauſoleum, built by Septimus Severus, in the tenth region of the city of Rome : it was ſo</p></body></text></TEI>