<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:04:02Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>rolina, there were upwards of two quarts of oil drawn, which is as great a quantity as hath been obtained from any vegetable whatever. This might occaſion its being called the <hi rend="italic">oily grain.</hi></p><p>SESELI, <hi rend="smallcaps">meadow saxifrage,</hi> in botany: A genus of plants belonging to the claſs of pentandria, and to the order of digynia ; and in the natural ſyſtem ranging under the 45th order, <hi rend="italic">Umbellatae.</hi> The umbels are globular ; the involucrum conſiſts of one or two leaflets ; the fruit is egg-ſhaped and ſtreaked. There are 11 ſpecies, the <hi rend="italic">pimpinelloides. montanum, glaucum, annuum, ammoides, tortuoſum, turbith, hyppomarathrum, pyrenaeum, ſaxiſragum,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">elatum.</hi> The montanum grows naturally in France and Italy ; the glaucum is a native of France ; the ammoides and tortuoſum grow in the ſouth of Europe ; and the hyppomarathrum is a native of Auſtria;</p><p>SESOSTRIS, king of Egypt. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Egypt,</hi> p. 368.</p><p>SESQUI, a Latin particle, ſignifying a whole and a half ; which, joined with <hi rend="italic">altera, terza, quarta,</hi> &amp;c. is much uſed in the Italian music to expreſs a kind of ratios, particularly ſeveral ſpecies of triples.</p><p><hi rend="italic">SESQUI-Alterate,</hi> in geometry and arithmetic, is a ratio between two lines, two numbers, or the like, where one of them contains the other once, with the addition of a half.</p><p>Thus 6 and 9 are in a ſeſquialterate ratio ; ſince 9 contains 6 once, and 3, which is half of 6, over; and 20 and 30 are in the ſame ; as 30 contains 20, and half 20 or 10.</p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps">SesQUI</hi><hi rend="italic">-Duplicate</hi> ratio, is when of two terms the greater contains the leſs twice, and half the lei's remains ; as 15 and 6 ; 50 and 20.</p><p>SESQUI-Tertional proportion, is when any number or quantity contains another once and one third.</p><p>SESSILE, among botaniſts. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Botany.</hi></p><p>SESSION, in general, denotes each fitting or aſſembly of a council, &amp;c.</p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Session</hi><hi rend="italic"> oſ Parliament,</hi> is the ſeaſon or ſpace from its meeting to its prorogation. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Parliament.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Kirk-SESS</hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps">ion,</hi> the name of a petty ecclesiaſtical court in Scotland. See <hi rend="italic">KIRK-Session.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sessions</hi> for weights and meaſures. In London, four juſtices from among the mayor, recorder, and aldermen (of whom the mayor or recorder is to be one), may hold a ſeſſion to inquire into the offences of felling by falſe weights and meaſures, contrary to the ſtatutes ; and to receive indictments, puniſh offenders, &amp;c. Char.  king Charles I.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Court of </hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Session.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Law,</hi> Part III. Sect. ii.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Court of Quarter-SEssi0NS,</hi> an Engliſh court that must be held in every county once in every quarter of a year; which, by ſtatute 2 Hen. V. c. 4. is appointed to be in the firſt week after Michaelmas-day, the firſt week after the epiphany, the firſt week after the cloſe of Eaſter, and in the week after the tranſlation of St Thomas the martyr, or the 7th of July. It is held before two or more juſtices of the peace, one of which muſt be of the quorum. The juriſdiction of this court, by 34 Edw. III. c. I. extends to the trying and determining all felonies and treſpaſſes whatſoever : though they ſeldom, if ever, try any greater offence than ſmall felonies within the benefit of clergy ; their commiſſion providing, that if any caſe of difficulty ariſes, they ſhall not pro</p><p>ceed to judgment, but in the preſence oſ one of the juſtices of the courts of king’s-bench or common-pleas,  or one of the judges of aſſize : and therefore murders, and other capital felonies, are uſually remitted for a more ſolemn trial to the aſſizes. They cannot alſo try any new-created offence, without expreſs power given them by the ſtatute which creates it. But there are many offences and particular matters which, by particular ſtatutes, belong properly to this juriſdiction, and ought to be proſecuted in this court ; as, the ſmaller miſdemeanors against the public or commonwealth, not amounting to felony ; and eſpecially offences relating to the game, highways, alehouſes, baſtard children, the ſettlement and proviſion for the poor, vagrants, ſervants wages, and Popiſh recuſants. Some of theſe are proceeded upon by indictment : others in a ſummary way, by motion, and order thereupon; which order may for the mod part, unleſs guarded againſt by particular ſtatutes, be removed into the court of king’s-bench by writ of <hi rend="italic">certiorari facias,</hi> and be there either quaſhed or confirmed. The records or rolls of the ſeſſions are committed to the cuſtody of a ſpecial officer, denominated <hi rend="italic">custos rotulorum,</hi> who is always a juſtice of the quorum ; and among them oſ the quorum (saith Lambard) a man for the moſt part eſpecially picked out, either for wiſdom, countenance, or credit. The nomination of the <hi rend="italic">custos rotulorum</hi> (who is the principal officer in the county, as the lord-lieutenant is chief in military command) is by the king’s ſign-manual : and to him the nomination of the clerk of the peace belongs ; which office he is expreſsly forbidden to sell ſor money.</p><p>In moſt corporation-towns there are quarter-ſeſſions kept before juſtices of their own, within their reſpective limits ; which have exactly the ſame authority as the general quarter-ſeſſions of the county, except in a very few inſtances ; one of the moſt considerable of which is the matter of appeals from orders of removal of the poor, which, though they be from the orders of corporation-juſtices, muſt be to the ſeſſions of the county, by ſtatute 8 and 9 W. III. c. 30. In both corporations and counties at large, there is ſometimes kept a ſpecial or petty ſeſſion, by a few juſtices, for diſpatching ſmaller bulineſs in the neighbourhood between the times of the general ſeſſions ; as for licenſing alehouſes, paſſing the account of pariſh-officers, and the like.</p><p>SESTERCE, <hi rend="smallcaps">Sestertius,</hi> a ſilver coin, in uſe among the ancient Romans, called alſo limply <hi rend="italic">nummus, </hi>and ſometimes nummus <hi rend="italic">ſestertius.</hi> The ſeſtertius was the fourth part of the denarius, and originally contained two aſſes and a half. It was at firſt denoted by LLS ; the two L’s ſignifying two libræ, and the S half. But the librarii, afterwards converting the two L’s into an H, expreſſed the ſeſtertius by HS. The word <hi rend="italic">ſestertius</hi> was firſt introduced by way of abbreviation for <hi rend="italic">ſemijlcrtius, </hi>which ſignifies two, and a half of a third, or, literally, only half a third ; for in expreſſing half a third, it was underſtood that there were two before.</p><p>Some authors make two kinds of ſeſterces ; the leſs called <hi rend="italic">ſeslertius,</hi> in the maſculine gender; and the great one, called <hi rend="italic">ſestertium,</hi> in the neuter : the firſt, that we have already deſcribed ; the latter containing a thouſand of the other. Others will have any ſuch diſtinction of great and little ſeſterces unknown to the Romans : <hi rend="italic">ſestertius,</hi> ſay they, was an adjective, and ſignified <hi rend="italic">as ſester-</hi></p></body></text></TEI>