<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:06:52Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>" On main and fore courſes two inches ſlack cloth ſhould be allowed in the head and foot, and one inch and a half in the leeches, in every yard in length. Topſails are allowed 3 inches ſlack in every cloth in the foot, one inch and a half in every yard in the leech, and two inches in every cloth left open in the top-brim. Mizen courſes have two inches ſlack in every yard in the foremoſt leech, but none in the after leech or foot. Spritſail courſes have no ſlack cloth. Jibs have four inches ſlack in every yard in the flay, one inch in every cloth in the foot, and none in the leech. Stayſails have three, inches ſlack in every yard in the ſtay, one inch in</p><p>every cloth in the foot, but none in the leech. Topgallant  sails have two inches ſlack in every cloth in the foot, and one inch in every yard in the leech. Studding ſails have an inch and a half ſlack in every yard in goring leeches, but no ſlack in ſquare leeches, and one inch in every cloth in the head and foot.”</p><p>Theſe directions for ſailmaking, we truſt may be uſeful. They are indeed very general, but the limits preſcribed us will not permit of a more minute detail. The ſailmaker will find every inſtruction that he can want in the <hi rend="italic">Elements oſ Rigging and Seamanship,</hi> a work which we therefore recommend to his attention.</p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Ship’s</hi><hi rend="italic"> Form Gauge,</hi> an inſtrument recommended by Mr Hutchinſon as fit to aſcertain any alteration in the bottom of a ſhip, by its hogging or sagging ; and alſo to regulate the ſtowage of a ſhip.</p><p>“ All ſhips (ſays he) of any conſequence are built with ſtaunchions fixed from the kelſon to the middle of all the lower-deck beams fore and aft, in order to ſupport them in their exact, regular height, as well as the whole frame of the ſhip in the regular form in which ſhe was built upon the ſtocks ; yet notwith- ſtanding theſe ſtaunchions, it is proved from experience that our ſhips bottoms, hitherto, by the preſſure of water, and improper ſtowage, have generally been hogged upwards, or sagged downwards, and moſt about the midſhip frame or main body of the ſhip, which is commonly about the fore part of the main hatchway ; which naturally makes it the beſt place at which to fix the ſhip’s form gauge, where either the hogging or fagging of her bottom may be obſerved and ſeen ſooneſt and beſt, to regulate the ſtowage of heavy materials to the greateſt advantage, ſo as to keep her bottom nearly in the same form in which ſhe was built.</p><p>“ The gauge I recommend is nothing more than a narrow plate of iron divided into inches and quarters like the ſlide of a carpenter’s rule. Let this be fixed to the after side of the ſtaunchion now mentioned, with its upper end projecting two or three inches above the ſtaunchion ; a groove being cut out for it in the after  side of the lower-deck beam, and a mark being made (when the ſhip is on the ſtocks) at the part of the beam which correſponds to the o on the gauge. When the ſhip alters in her ſhape, the gauge will ſlide up and down in this groove, and the quantity of hogging or lagging will be pointed out on the gauge by the mark on the beam. The ſtowage may then be ſo managed as to bring this mark to coincide again with the o, or to approach it as near as we ſee neceſſary.”</p><p><hi rend="italic">SHIP-Money,</hi> was an impoſition charged upon the ports, towns, cities, boroughs, and counties of this realm, in the reign of king Charles I. by writs, commonly called s<hi rend="italic">hip-writs,</hi> under the great seal of England, in the years 1635 and 1636, for the providing and furniſhing of certain ſhips for the king’s ſervice, &amp;c. which was declared to be contrary to the laws and ſtatutes of this realm, the <hi rend="italic">petition of right</hi> and liberty of the ſubject, by ſtat. 17 Car. I. c. 14. See <hi rend="italic">Blαckstοne's Commentaries,</hi> vol. iv. p. 30.</p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps">ShiP-</hi><hi rend="italic">Shape,</hi> according to the faſhion of a ſhip, or in the manner of an expert ſailor ; as, The mail is not rigged ſhip ſhape ; Trim your ſails ſhip-ſhape.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Stowing and Trimming oſ </hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Ships,</hi> the method of diſpoſing of the cargo in a proper and judicious manner in the hold of a ſhip.</p><p>A ſhip’s sailing, fleering, fraying, and wearing, and being lively and comparatively easy at ſea in a ſtorm, depends greatly on the cargo, ballaſt, or other materials, being properly ſtowed, according to their weight and bulk, and the proportional dimensions of the built of the ſhip, which may be made too crank or too ſtiff to paſs on the ocean with ſafety. Theſe things render this branch of knowledge of ſuch conſequence, that rules for it ought to be endeavoured after, if but to prevent, as much as poſſible, the danger of a ſhip oversetting at ſea, or being ſo labourſome as to roll away her maſts, &amp;c. by being improperly ſtowed, which is often the case.</p><p>When a ſhip is new, it is prudent to consult the builder, who may be ſuppoſed beſt acquainted with a ſhip of his own planning, and moſt likely to judge what her properties will be, to adviſe how the cargo or materials, according to the nature of them, ought to be diſpoſed of to advantage, ſo as to put her in the beſt sailing trim ; and at every favourable opportunity afterwards it will be proper to endeavour to find out her beſt trim by experiment.</p><p>Ships muſt differ in their form and proportional dimenſions ; and to make them anſwer their different purpoſes, they will require different management in the ſtowage, which ought not to be left to mere chance, or done at random, as goods or materials happen to come to hand, which is too often the cauſe that ſuch improper ſtowage makes ſhips unfit for ſea : therefore the ſtowage ſhould be conſidered, planned, and contrived, according to the built and properties of the ſhip, which if they are not known ſhould be inquired after. If ſhe is narrow and high-built in proportion, ſo that ſhe will not ſhift herſelf without a great weight in the hold, it is a certain ſign ſuch a ſhip will require a great part of heavy goods, ballaſt, or materials, laid low in the hold, to make her ſtiff enough to bear ſufficient ſail without being in danger of overſetting. But if a ſhip be built broad and low in proportion, ſo that ſhe is ſtiff and will ſupport herſelf without any weight in the hold, ſuch a ſhip will require heavy goods, ballaſt, or materials, ſtowed higher up, to prevent her from being too ſtiff and labourſome at ſea, ſo as to endanger her maſts being rolled away, and the hull worked looſe and made leaky.</p><p>In order to help a ſhip’s ſailing, that ſhe ſhould be lively and eaſy in her pitching and aſcending motions,</p></body></text></TEI>