<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:04:47Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>and yet could be waſhed out freely with soap, or ley, or ſtale urine. In order to render it ſtill more durable, and prevent its being rubbed off, with the tallow may be melted an eighth, ſixth, or fourth, of its weight of tar, which will readily waſh out along with it from the wool. Lewis’s Com. Phil. Techn. p. 361.</p><p><hi rend="italic">SHEEP-Stealing.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Theft.</hi></p><p>SHEERING, in the ſea-language. When a ſhip is not ſteered ſteadily, they ſay ſhe sheers, or goes ſheering ; or when, at anchor, ſhe goes in and out by means of the current of the tide, they alſo ſay ſhe ſheers.</p><p>SHEERNESS, a fort in Kent, ſeated on the point where the river Medway falls into the Thames. It was built by king Charles II. after the inſult of the Dutch, who burnt the men of war at Chatham. The buildings belonging to it, in which the officers lodge, make a pretty little neat town ; and there is alſo a yard and a dock, a chapel and a chaplain. Mr Lyons, who ſailed with the Honourable Captain Phipps in his voyage towards the pole, fixed the longitude of Sheerueſs to 0. 48'. E. its latitude 51⁰ 25'.</p><p>SHEERS, a name given to an engine uſed to hoiſt or diſplace the lower maſts of a ſhip. The ſheers employed for this purpoſe in the royal navy are compoſed of ſeveral long maſts, whoſe heels reſt upon the side of the hulk, and having their heads declining outward from the perpendicular, ſo as to hang over the veſſel whoſe maſts are to be fixed or diſplaced. The tackles, which extend from the head of the maſt to the ſheer- heads, are intended to pull in the latter toward the maſt- head, particularly when they are charged with the weight of a maſt after it is raiſed out of any ſhip, which is performed by ſtrong tackles depending from the ſheer-heads. The effort of theſe tackles is produced by two capſterns, fixed on the deck for this purpoſe.</p><p>In merchant ſhips this machine is compoſed of two maſts or props, erected in the ſame veſſel wherein the maſt is to be planted, or from whence it is to be removed. The lower ends of theſe props reſt on the oppoſite ſides of the deck, and their upper parts are faſtened acroſs, ſo as that a tackle which hangs from the intersection may be almoſt perpendicularly above the station of the maſt to which the mechanical powers are applied. Theſe ſheers are ſecured by stays, which extend for ward and aft to the oppoſite extremities of the veſſel.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">SHEET-Lead.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Plumbery.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sheet,</hi> in ſea-language, a rope faſtened to one or both the lower corners of a ſail, to extend and retain it in a particular ſtation. When a ſhip ſails with a lateral wind, the lower corner of the main and fore-ſail are fastened by a tack and a ſheet ; the former being to windward, and the latter to leeward ; the tack, however, is entirely diffuſed with a ſtern wind, whereas the ſail is never ſpread without the aſſiſtance of one or both of the ſheets. The ſtay-ſails and ſtudding-ſails have only one tack and one ſheet each : the ſtay-ſail tacks are always faſtened forward, and the ſheet drawn aft; but the ſtudding-ſail tack draws the under clue of the ſail to the extremity of the boom, whereas the ſheet is employed to extend the inmoſt.</p><p>SHEFFIELD, a town in the west riding of Yorkſhire, about 162 miles from London, is a large, thriving, populous town on the borders of Derbyſhire; has a fine ſtone bridge over the Don, and another over the Sheaf, and a church built in the reign of Henry I.</p><p>It had a caſtle built in the reign of Henry III. in which, or elſe in the manor-houſe of the Park, Mary Queen of Scots was priſoner 16 or 17 years ; but after the death of Charles I. it was, with ſeveral others, by order of parliament demoliſhed. In 1673 an hoſpital was erected here, and endowed with 2001. a-year. There is a charity-ſchool for 30 boys, and another for 30 girls. This town has been noted ſeveral hundred years for cutlers and ſmiths manufactures, which were encouraged and advanced by the neighbouring mines of iron, particularly for files and knives, or whittles ; for the laſt of which eſpecially it has been a ſtaple for above 300 years ; and it is reputed to excel Birmingham in theſe wares, as much as it is ſurpaſſed by it in locks, hinges, nails, and poliſhed ſteel. The firſt mills in England for turning grindſtones were also ſet up here. The houſes look black from the continual ſmoke of the forges. Here are 600 maſter cutlers, incorporated by the ſtyle of the <hi rend="italic">Cutlers of Hallamſhire</hi> (of which this is reckoned the chief town), who employ not leſs than 40,000 perſons in the iron manufactures ; and each of the maſters gives a particular ſtamp to his wares. There is a large market on Tueſday for many commodities, but eſpecially for corn, which is bought up here for the whole West Riding, Derbyſhire, and Nottinghamſhire. It has fairs on Tueſday after Trinity-Sunday, and November 28. In the new market-place, erected by the Duke of Norfolk, the ſhambles are built upon a moſt excellent plan, and ſtrongly incloſed. There are ſeveral other new good buildings, ſuch as a large and elegant octagon chapel belonging to the hoſpital or almshouſes ; likewise a good aſſembly-room and theatre. We muſt not omit the large ſteam-engine, lately finiſhed, for the purpoſe of poliſhing and grinding the various forts of hardware. The pariſh being very large, as well as populous, Mary I. incorporated 12 of the chief inhabitants, and their ſucceſſors for ever, by the ſtyle of the <hi rend="italic">Twelve Capital Burgesses of Sheffield,</hi> empowering them to elect and ordain three priests to aſſiſt the vicar, who were to be paid out of certain lands and rents which ſhe gave out of the crown ; and ſince this ſettlement two more chapels have been built in two hamlets of this pariſh, which are ſerved by two of the aſſiſtants, while the third, in his turn, helps the vicar in his pariſh-church. James I. founded a free grammar-ſchool here, and appointed 13 ſchool burgeſſes to manage the revenue, and appoint the maſter and uſher. A new chapel was built lately by the contributions of the people of the town and of the neighbouring nobility and gentry. Water is conveyed by pipes into Sheffield, whoſe inhabitants pay but a moderate rent for it. In the neighbourhood there are ſome mines of alum. The remains of the Roman fortification between this town and Rotheram, which is six miles lower down the river, are ſtill visible ; and here is alſo the famous trench of five miles long, by ſome called <hi rend="italic">Devil’s</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Dane’s Bank,</hi> and by others <hi rend="italic">Kemp Bank</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Temple’s Bank.</hi> W. Long. 1. 29. N, Lat. 53. 20.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sheffield</hi> (John), duke of Buckinghamſhire, an eminent writer of the laſt and preſent century, of great perſonal bravery, and an able miniſter of ſtate, was born about 1650. He loſt his father at nine years of age ; and his mother marrying lord Oſſulſton, the care of his education was left entirely to a governor, who did not greatly improve him in his studies. Finding that he was deficient in many parts</p></body></text></TEI>