<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196389_0647.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0641-01" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SANBALLAT</label>,
the chief or governor of the Cuthites or Samaritans, was always a great enemy to the Jews. He was a native of Horon, or Horonaim, a city beyond Jordan, in the country of the Moabites. He lived in the time of Nehemiah, who was his great opponent, and from whoſe book we learn his hiſtory. There is one circumſtance related of him which has occaſioned ſome diſpute among the learned; and the ſtate of the queſtion is as follows: When Alexander the Great came into Phoenicia, and ſat down before the city of Tyre, Sanballat quitted the intereſts of Darius king of Perſia, and went at the head of 8000 men to offer his ſervice to Alexander. This prince readily entertained him, and being much ſolicited by him, gave him leave to erect a temple upon mount Gerizim, where he conſtituted his ſon-in-law Manaſſeh the high-prieſt. But this ſtory carries a flagrant anachroniſm: for 120 years before this, that is, in the year of the world 3550, Sanballat was governor of Samaria; wherefore the learned Dr Prideaux (in his Connection of the Hi- ſtories of the Old and New Teſtament) ſuppoſes two Sanballats, and endeavours to reconcile it to truth and probability, by ſhowing it to be a miſtake of Joſephus. This author makes Sanballat to flouriſh in the time of Dari us Codomannus, and to build his temple upon mount Gerizim by licence from Alexander the Great; whereas it was performed by leave from Darius Nothus, in the 15th year of his reign. This takes away the difficulty ariſing from the great age of Sanballat, and brings him to be contemporary with Nehemiah, as the Scripture hiſtory requires.</p></div></body></text></TEI>