<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="gri_33125011196389_0585.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0579-01"
                xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                <p><label>S</label>, ſ, or s, the 18th letter and 14th conſonant of our alphabet;
                    the found of which is formed by driving the breath through a narrow paſſage
                    between the palate and the tongue elevated near it, together with a motion of
                    the lower jaw and teeth towards the upper, the lips being a little way open;
                    with ſuch a configuration of every part of the mouth and larynx, as renders the
                    voice ſomewhat ſibilous and hiſſing. Its found, however, varies; being ſtrong in
                    ſome words, as this, thus, &amp;c. and ſoft in words which have a final e,
                    as muſe, wiſe, &amp;c. It is generally doubled at the end of words, whereby
                    they become hard and harſh, as in kiſs, loss, &amp;c. In ſome words it is
                    ſilent, as iſle, iſland, viſcount, &amp;c. In writing or printing, the long
                    character ſ is generally uſed at the beginning and middle of words, but the
                    ſhort s at the end.</p>
                <p>In abbreviations, S ſtands for <hi rend="italic">ſocietas</hi> or <hi
                        rend="italic">ſocius;</hi> as,</p>
                <p>R. S. S. for <hi rend="italic">regiae ſoc'etatis ſocius, i. e.</hi> fellow of the
                    royal ſociety. In medicinal preſcriptions, S. A. ſignifies <hi rend="italic"
                        >ſecundum artem,</hi> i. e. according to the rules of art: And in the notes
                    of the ancients, S ſtands for <hi rend="italic">Sextus;</hi></p>
                <p>S. P. for <hi rend="italic">Spurius;</hi> S. C. <hi rend="italic">for ſenatus
                        conſultum;</hi> S. P. Q. R. <hi rend="italic">for ſenatus populuſque
                        Romanus;</hi> S. S. S. <hi rend="italic">for ſtratum ſu- per ſtratum,</hi>
                    i. e. one layer above another alternately; S. V. B. E. E. Q. V. for <hi
                        rend="italic">ſi vales bene eſt, ego quoque valeo,</hi> a form uſed in
                    Cicero’s time, in the beginning of letters. Uſed as a numeral, S anciently
                    denoted ſeven; in the Italian inuſic, S ſignifies <hi rend="italic">ſolo:</hi>
                    And in books of navigation, S. ſtands for ſouth; S. E. for ſouth-eaſt; S. W. for
                    ſouth-weſt; S. S. E. for ſouth ſouth-eaſt; S. S. W for ſouth ſouth-weſt
                    &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
