<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196389_0585.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0579-02" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SAAVEDRA</label>
(Michael de Cervantes), a celebrated Spaniſh writer, and the inimitable author of Don. Quixote, was born at Madrid in the year 1549. From<pb facs="gri_33125011196389_0586.tif" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0580"/>
his infancy he was fond of books; but he applied himſelf wholly to books of entertainment, ſuch as novels and poetry of all kinds, eſpecially Spaniſh and Italian authors. From Spain he went to Italy, either to ſerve Cardinal Aquaviva, to whom he was chamberlain at Rome; or elſe to follow the proſeſſion of a ſoldier, as he did ſome years under the victorious banners of Marco Antonio Colonna. He was preſent at the battle of Lepanto, fought in the year 1571; in which he either loſt his left hand by the ſhot of an harquebus, or had it ſo maimed that he loſt the uſc of it. After this he was taken by the Moors, and carried to Algiers, where he continued a captive five years and a half. Then he returned to Spain, and applied himſelf to the writing of comedies and tragedies; and he compoſed ſeveral, all of which were well received by the public, and acted with great applauſe. In the year 1584 he publiſhed his Galatea, a novel in fix books; which he presented to Aſcanio Colonna, a man of high rank in the church, as the firſt fruits of his wit. But the work which has done him the greateſt honour, and will immortalize his name, is the hiſtory of Don Quixote; the firſt part of which was printed at Madrid in the year 1605. This is a satire upon books of knight-errantry; and the principal, if not the ſole, end of it was to deſtroy the reputation of theſe books, which had ſo infatuated the greater part of mankind, eſpecially thoſe of the Spaniſh nation. This work was univerſally read; and the moſt eminent painters, tapeſtry-workers, engravers, and ſculptors, have been employed in repreſenting the hiſtory of Don Quixote. Cervantes, even in his lifetime, obtained the glory of having his work receive a royal approbation. As King Philip III. was Handing in a balcony of his palace at Madrid, and viewing the country, he obſerved a ſtudent on the banks of the river Manzanares reading in a book, and from time to time breaking off and beating his forehead with extraordinary tokens of pleaſure and delight: upon which the king laid to thoſe about him, “ That ſcholar is either mad, or reading Hon Quixote: ” the latter of which proved to be the cafe. But <hi rend="italic">virtus laudatur et alget:</hi> notwithstanding the vaſt applauſe his book every where met with, he had not intereſt enough to procure a ſmall pension, but had much ado to keep himſelf from ſtarving. In the year 1615, he publiſhed a ſecond part; to which he was partly moved by the preſumption of ſome ſcribbler, who had publiſhed a continuation of this work the year before. He wrote alſo ſeveral novels; and among the rest, “ The Troubles of Perſiles and Sigiſmunda. ” He had employed many years in writing this novel, and ſiniſhed it but juſt before his death; for he did not live to fee it publiſhed. His fickneſs was of ſuch a nature, that he himſelf was able to be, and actually was, his own hiſtorian. At the end of the pieſace to the Troubles of Perſiles and Sigiſmunda, he repreſents himſelf on horſeback upon the road, and a ſtudent,. who had overtaken him, engaged in converſation with him: “ And happening to talk of my illneſs (ſays he), the ſtudent soon let me know my doom, by laying it was a dropſy I had got; the thirst attending which all the water of the ocean, though it were not ſalt, would not ſuſſice to quench. Therefore Senor Cervantes, ſays he, you muſt drink nothing at all, but do not forget to eat; for this alone will recover you without any other physic. I have been told the fame by others, anſwered I;</p><p>but I can no more forbear tippling, than if I were born to do nothing elſe. My life is drawing to an end; and from the daily journal of my pulſe, I ſhall have ſiniſhed my courſe by next Sunday at the fartheſt. —But adieu, my merry friends all, for I am going to die; and I hope to ſee you ere long in the other world, as happy as heart can wiſh. ” His dropſy increaſed, and at laſt proved fatal to him; yet lie continued to fay and to write bon mots. He received the laſt ſacrament on the 18th of April 1616; yet the day after wrote a He- dication of the Troubles of Perſiles and Sigiſmunda to the Condé de Lemos. The particular day of his death is not known.</p></div></body></text></TEI>