<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196389_0612.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0606-02" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SAINT</label>,
means a perſon eminent for piety and virtue, and is generally applied by us to the apoſtles and other holy perſons mentioned in Scripture. But the Romaniſts make its application much more extenſive. Under the word <hi rend="smallcaps">Canonization</hi> we have already ſaid ſomething on their practice of creating ſaints. Our readers, however, will not, we truſt, be diſpleaſed with the following more enlarged account, which they themſelves give of the matter. The canonization of ſaints, then, they tell us, is the enrolment of any perſon in the <hi rend="italic">canon</hi> or catalogue of thoſe who are called <hi rend="italic">ſaints;</hi> or, it is a judgment and ſentence of the church, by which it is declared, that a deceaſed perſon was eminent for ſanctſty during his lifetime, and eſpecially towards the end of it; and that conſequently he muſt now be in glory with God, and deferves to be honoured by the church on earth with that veneration which ſhe is wont to pay to the bleſſed in heaven.</p><p>The diſcipline with regard to this matter has varied. It would ſeem that in the firſt ages every biſhop in his own dioceſe was wont to declare what perſons were to be honoured as ſaints by his people. Hence St Cyprian, about the middle of the third century, B. 3. <hi rend="italic">ep.</hi> 6. requires that he be informed of thoſe who ſhould die in priſon for the faith, that ſo he might make mention of them in the holy ſacrifice with the martyrs, and might honour them afterwards on the anniverſary day of their happy death. This veneration continued ſometimes to be confined to one country; but ſometimes it extended to diſtant provinces, and even became univerſal all over the church. It was thus that St Laurence, St Ambroſe, St Auguſtine, St Baſil, and many others, appear to have been canonized by cuſtom and univerſal perſuaſion. In thoſe ages none were reckoned ſaints but the apoſtles, the martyrs, and very eminent confeſſors, whoſe ſanctity was notorious everywhere.</p><p>Afterwards it appears that canonizations were wont to be performed in provincial ſynods under the direction of the metropolitan. It was thus that St Iſidore of Seville was canonized in the 7th century, by the 8th council of Toledo, 14 years after his death. This manner of canonization continued occaſionially down to the 12th century. The laſt inſtance of a ſaint canonized in that way, is that of St Walter abbot of Pontoiſe, who was declared a ſaint by the archbiſhop of Rouen in the year 1153.</p><p>In the 12th century, in order to prevent miſtakes in ſo delicate a matter, Pope Alexander III. judged it proper to reſerve this declaration to the holy ſee of Rome excluſively; and decreed that no one ſhould for the future be honoured by the church as a ſaint without the expreſs approbation of the pope.</p><p>Since that time, the canonization of ſaints has been carried on in the form of a proceſs; and there is at Rome a congregation of cardinals, called the <hi rend="italic">congregation of holy rites,</hi> who are aſſiſted by ſeveral divines under the name of <hi rend="italic">conſultors,</hi> who examine ſuch matters, and prepare them for the deciſion of his holineſs. When therefore any potentate, province, city, or religious body, think fit, they apply to the pope tor the canonization of any perſon.</p><p>The firſt juridical ſtep in this buſineſs muſt be taken by the biſhop in whoſe dioceſe the perſon for whom the application is made had lived and died, who by his own authority calls witneſſes to atteſt the opinion of the holineſs, the virtues, and miracles, of the perſon in queſtion. When the deceaſed has reſided in different dioceſes, it may be neceſſary that different biſhops take ſuch depoſitions; the originals of which are preſerved in the archives of their reſpective churches, and authentic copies ſealed up are ſent to Rome by a ſpecial meſſenger, where they are depoſited with the congregation of rites, and where they muſt remain for the ſpace of ten years without being opened. They are then opened, and maturely examined by the congregation, and with their advice the pope allows the cauſe to go on or not as he thinks proper. The ſolicitors for the canonization are then referred by his holineſs to the ſaid congregation, which, with his authority, gives a commiſſion to one or more biſhops, or other reſpectable perſons, to examine, on the ſpot and in the places where the perſon in queſtion has lived and died, into his character and whole behaviour. Theſe commiſſioners ſummon witneſſes, take depoſitions, and collect letters and other writings of the venerable man, and get all the intelligence they can concerning him, and the opinion generally entertained of him. The report of theſe commiſſioners is conſidered attentively and at length by the congregation, and every part of it diſcuſſed by the conſultors, when the congregation determines whether or not they can permit the proceſs to go on. If it be allowed to proceed, a cardinal, who is called <hi rend="italic">ponent,</hi> undertakes to be the principal agent in that affair. The firſt queſtion then that comes to be examined is, whether or not the perſon propoſed for canonization can be proved to have been in an eminent degree endued with the moral virtues of prudence, juſtice, fortitude, and temperance; and with the theological virtues of faith, hope, and charity? All this is canvaſſed with great deliberation; and there is a diſtinguiſhed eccleſiaſtic called the <hi rend="italic">promoter oſ the holy faith,</hi> who is ſworn to make all reaſonable objections to the proofs that are adduced in favour of the canonization. If the deciſion be favourable, then the proofs of miracles done to ſhow the ſanctity of the perſon in queſtion are permitted to be brought forward; when two miracles muſt be verified to the ſatisfaction of the congregation, both as to the reality of the facts, and as to their having been truly above the power of nature. If the deciſion on this comes out likewiſe favourable, then the whole is laid<pb facs="gri_33125011196389_0613.tif" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0607"/>
before the pope and what divines he chooſes<note anchored="true" n="1" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="smallcaps">a) [</hi> m <hi rend="smallcaps">]</hi> His holineſs generally appoints three conſiſtories; in the firſt of which the cardinals only aſſiſt, and give their opinion; in the ſecond, a preacher pronounces a ſpeech in praiſe of the candidate before a numerous audience; to the third, not only the cardinals, but all the biſhops who are at Rome, are invited, and all of them. give their vote by word of mouth.</p></note> <hi rend="smallcaps">(a).</hi> Public prayer and faſting are likewiſe preſcribed, in order to obtain light and direction from heaven. After all this long procedure, when the pope is reſolved to give his approbation, he iſſues a bull, firſt of <hi rend="italic">beatification,</hi> by which the perſon is declared <hi rend="italic">bleſſed,</hi> and afterwards another of <hi rend="italic">ſanctification,</hi> by which the name of <hi rend="italic">ſaint</hi> is given him. Theſe bulls are publiſhed in St Peter’s church with very great ſolemnity.</p><p>A perſon remarkable for holineſs of life, even before he is canonized, may be venerated as ſuch by thoſe who are perſuaded of his eminent virtue, and his prayers may be implored; but all this muſt reſt on private opinion. After his canonization, his name is inſerted in the Martyrology, or catalogue of ſaints, of which the reſpective portion is read every day in the choir at the divine office. A day is alſo appointed for an yearly commemoration of him. His name may be mentioned in the public church ſervice, and his interceſſion with God beſought. His relics may be enſhrined: he may be painted with rays of glory, and altars and churches may be dedicated to God in honour of him, and in thankſgiving to the divine goodneſs for the bleſſings beſtowed on him in life, and for the glory to which he is raiſed in heaven.</p><p>The affair of a canonization is neceſſarily very expenſive, becauſe ſo many perſons muſt be employed about it; ſo many journeys muſt be made; ſo many writings for and againſt it muſt be drawn out. The expence altogether amounts to about 25,000 Roman crowns, or L. 6000 Sterling. But it is generally contrived to canonize two or three at a time, by which means the particular expence of each is very much leſſened, the ſolemnity being common.</p><p>It often happens that the ſolicitors for a canonization are unſucceſsful. Thus the Jeſuits, even when their intereſt at Rome was greateſt, could not obtain the canonization of Bellarmine; and it is remarkable, that the objection is ſaid to have been, his having defended the indirect power of the pope over Chriſtian princes even in temporals.</p><p>Several authors have written on canonization, and particularly Proſper Lambertini, afterwards pope under the name of Benedict XIV. who had held the office of <hi rend="italic">promoter of the faith</hi> for many years. He publiſhed on it a large work in ſeveral volumes, in folio, of which there is an abridgment in French. In this learned performance there is a full hiſtory of the canonization of ſaints in general, and of all the particular proceſſes of that kind that are on record: an account is given of the manner of proceeding in theſe extraordinary trials; and it is ſhiown, that, beſides the aſſiſtance of providence, which is implored and expected in what is ſo much connected with religion, all prudent human means are made uſe of, in order to avoid miſtakes, and to obtain all the evidence of which the matter is ſuſceptible, and which muſt appear more than ſufficent to every impartial judge. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Pope, Popery, &amp;c.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Saint-Foin,</hi> in botany, a ſpecies of the hedyſarum. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Hedysarum</hi>; and <hi rend="smallcaps">Agriculture,</hi> n <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> 180,</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Saint</hi> Januarius's Blood. <hi rend="italic">See</hi> <hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Chemistry,</hi> <hi rend="italic">n° 800.</hi></p></div></body></text></TEI>