<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196389_0716.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0710-02" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SCIOPPIUS</label>
(Gaſpar), a learned German writer of the 17th century, was born at Neumark in the Upper Palatinate on the 27th of May 1576. He ſtudied at the univerſity with ſo much ſucceſs, that at the age of 16 he became an author; and publiſhed books, ſays Ferrari, which deſerved to be admired by old men. His diſpoſitions did not correſpond with his genius. Naturally paſſionate and malevolent, he aſſaulted without<pb facs="gri_33125011196389_0717.tif" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0711"/>
mercy the character of eminent men. He abjured the ſyſtem of the Proteſtants, and became a Roman catholic about the year 1599; but his character remained the ſame. He poſſeſſed all thoſe qualities which fitted him for making a diſtinguiſhed figure in the literary world; imagination, memory, profound learning, and invincible impudence. He was familiar with the terms of reproach in moſt of the languages. He was entirely ignorant of the manners of the world. He neither ſhowed reſpect to his ſuperiors, nor did he behave with decency to his equals. He was poſſeſſed with a frenzy of an uncommon kind: he was indeed a perfect firebrand, ſcattering around him, as if for his amuſement, the moſt atrocious calumnies. Joſeph Scaliger, above all others, was the object of his ſatire. That learned man, having drawn up the hiſtory of his own family, and deduced its genealogy from princes, was ſeverely attacked-by Scioppius, who ridiculed his high pretentions. Scaliger in his turn wrote a book intitled The Life and Parentage of Gaſpar Scioppius, in which he informs us, that the father of Scioppius had been ſucceſſively a grave-digger, a journeyman ſtationer, a hawker, a ſoldier, a miller, and a brewer of beer. We are told that his wife was long kept as a miſtreſs, and at length forſaken by a debauched man whom ſhe followed to Hungary, and obliged to return to her huſband; that then he treated her harſhly, and condemned her to the loweſt offices of ſervitude. His daughter, too, it is tard, was as diſorderly as her mother: that after the flight of her huſhand, who was going to be burned for ſome infamous crimes, ſhe became a common proſtitute; and at length grew ſo ſcandalous, that ſhe was committed to priſon. Theſe ſevere accuſations againſt the family of Scioppius inflamed him with more eagerneſs to attack his antagoniſt anew. He collected all the calumnies that had been thrown out againſt Scaliger, and formed them into a huge volume as if he had intended to cruſh him at once. He treated with great contempt the King of England, James I. in his <hi rend="italic">Eccleſiaſticus, &amp;c.</hi> and in his <hi rend="italic">Collyrium Regium Britanniae Regi graviter ex oculis laboranti munere mi</hi> ſſ <hi rend="italic">um;</hi> that is, “An Eve ſalve for his Britannic Majeſty. ” In one of his works he had the audacity to abuſe Henry IV. of France in a moſt ſcurrilous manner, on which account his book was burned at Paris. He was hung in effigy in a farce which was reprefented before the king of England, but he gloried in his diſhonour. Provoked with his inſolence to their Sovereign, the ſervants of the Engliſh ambaſſador aſſaulted him at Madrid, and corrected him ſeverely; but he boaſted of the wounds he had received. He publiſhed more than thirty defamatory libels againſt the Jeſuits; and, what is very ſurpriſing, in the very place where he declaims with moſt virulence againſt that ſociety, he ſubſcribes his own name with expreſſions of piety. 7 <hi rend="italic">Gaſpar Scioppius, already on the brink oſ the grave, and ready to appear before the tribunal of Jeſus Chriſt to give an account of my works.</hi> Towards the end of his life he employed himſelf in ſtudying the Apocalypſe, and affirmed that he had found the key to that myſterious book. He ſent ſome of his expoſitions to Cardinal Mazarine, but the cardinal did not find it convenient to read them.</p><p>Ferrari tells us, that during the laſt fourteen years of his life he ſhut himſelſ up in a ſmall apartment, where he devoted himſelf ſolely to ſtudy. The fame writer</p><p>acquaints us, that he could repeat the Scriptures almoſt entirely by heart; but his good qualities were eclipſed by his vices. For his love of ſlander, and the furious aſſaults which he made upon the moſt eminent men, he was called the <hi rend="italic">Cerberus oſ literature.</hi> He accuſes even Cicero of barbariſms and improprieties. He died on the 19th November 1649, at the age oſ 74, at Padua, the only retreat which remained to him from the multitude of enemies whom he had created. Four hundred books are aſcribed to him, which are ſaid to diſcover great genius and learning. The chief of theſe are, l. <hi rend="italic">Vereſimilium Libri</hi> IV <hi rend="italic">,</hi> 1596, in 8vo. 2. <hi rend="italic">Commentarius de arte critica,</hi> 1661, in 8vo. 3. <hi rend="italic">De ſua ad Catholicos migratione,</hi> 1660, in 8vo. 4. <hi rend="italic">Notationes Criticae in Phaedrum, in Priapeia, Patavii,</hi> 1664, in 8vo. 5. <hi rend="italic">Suſpectarum lectionum Libri</hi> V. 1664, in 8vo. 6. <hi rend="italic">Classicum belli ſacri,</hi> 1619, in 4to. 7 <hi rend="italic">Collyrium regium,</hi> 16ll, in 8vo. 8. <hi rend="italic">Grammatica Philosophica,</hi> 1644, in 8vo. 9. <hi rend="italic">Relatio ad Reges et Principes de Stratagematibus et Societatis Jesu,1641</hi>, in 12mo. This laſt mentioned book was publiſhed under the name of <hi rend="italic">Alphοn</hi> ſ <hi rend="italic">ο de Vargas.</hi> He was at firſt well diſpoſed to the Jeſuits; but theſe fathers on one occaſion oppoſed him. He preſented a petition to the diet of Ratiſhonne in 1630, in order to obtain a penſion; but the Jeſuits, who were the confeſſors both of the emperor and the electors, had influence to prevent the petition from being granted. From that moment Scioppius turned his whole artillery againſt the Jeſuits.</p></div></body></text></TEI>