<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196389_0719.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0713-06" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SCOLOPAX</label>,
in ornithology, a genus belonging to the order of grallae. The back is cylindrical, obtuſe, and longer than the head; the noſtrils are linear; the face is covered; and the feet have four toes. There are 18 ſpecies; of which the following are the principal.<pb facs="gri_33125011196389_0720.tif" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0714"/>
1. The <hi rend="italic">arquata,</hi> or curlew, frequents our ſea-coaſts and marſhes in the winter time in large flocks, walking on the open ſands; feeding on ſhells, frogs, crabs, and other marine infects.<note anchored="false" n="1" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>Plate CCCCXLV.</p></note> In summer they retire to the mountainous and unfrequented parts of the country, where they pair and breed. Their eggs are of a pale olive colour, marked with irregular but diſtinct ſpots of pale brown. Their fleſh is very rank and fiſhy, not- withſtanding an old Engliſh proverb in its favour. Curlews differ much in weight and ſize; ſome weighing 37 ounces, others not 22: the length of the largeſt to the tip of the tail, 25 inches; the breadth, three feet five inches; the bill is ſeven inches long: the head, neck, and coverts of the wings are of a pale brown; the middle of each feather, black; the breaſt and belly white, marked with narrow oblong black lines: the back is white, ſpotted with a few black ſtrokes: the quill feathers are black, but the inner webs ſpotted with white; the tail is white, tinged with red, and beautifully barred with black; the legs are long, ſtrong, and of a bluiſh grey colour; the bottoms of the toes flat and broad, to enable it to walk on the ſoft mud, in ſearch of food.</p><p>2 The <hi rend="italic">phaeopus,</hi> or whimbrel, is much leſs frequent on our ſhores than the curlew; but its haunts, food, and general appearance, are much the ſame. It is obſerved to viſit the neighbourhood of Spalding (where it is called the <hi rend="italic">curlew knot</hi>) in vaſt flocks in April, but continues there no longer than May; nor is it ſeen there any other time of the year: it ſeems at that ſeaſon to be on its paſſage to its breeding place, which Mr Pennant ſuſpects to be among the Highlands of Scotland. The ſpecific difference is the ſize; this never exceeding the weight of 12 ounces.</p><p>3. The <hi rend="italic">rusticola,</hi> or woodcock, during ſummer inhabits the Alps of Norway, Sweden, Poliſh Pruſſia, the march of Brandenburg, and the northern parts of Europe: they all retire from thoſe countries the beginning of winter, as ſoon as the froſts commence; which force them into milder climates, where the ground is open, and adapted to their manner of feeding. They live on worms and inſects, which they ſearch for with their long bills in ſoft grounds and moiſt woods. — Woodcocks generally arrive here in flocks, taking advantage of the night or a miſt: they ſoon ſeparate; but before they return to their native haunts, pair. They feed and fly by night; beginning their flight in the evening, and return the ſame way or through the ſame glades to their day retreat. They leave England the latter end of February, or beginning of March; not but they have been known to continue here accidentally. Theſe birds appear in Scotland firſt on the eaſtern coaſts, and make their progreſs from eaſt to weſt. They do not arrive in Breadalbane, a central part of the kingdom, till the beginning or middle of November; nor the coaſts of Nether Lorn, or of Roſsſhire, till December or January: they are very rare in the remote Hebrides, and in the Orkneys. A few ſtragglers now and then arrive there. They are equally ſcarce in Caithneſs. Our ſpecies of woodcock is unknown in North America: but a kind is found that has the general appearance of it; but is ſcarce half the ſize, and wants the bars on the breaſt and belly. The weight of the woodcock is uſually about 12 ounces; the length near 14 inches; and the breadth, 26; the bill is three inches long, duſky towards the end, reddiſh at the baſe; tongue ſlender, long, ſharp, and hard at the point; the eyes large, and placed near the top of the head, that they may not be injured when the bird thruſts its bill into the ground; from the bill to the eyes is a black line; the fore-head is a reddiſh aſh colour; the crown of the head, the hind part of the neck, the back, the coverts of the wings, and the ſcapulars, are prettily barred with a ferruginous red, black, and grey; but on the head the black predominates: the quill-feathers are duſky, indented with red marks. The chin is of a pale yellow; the whole under ſide of the body is of a dirty white, marked with numerous tranſverſe lines of a duſky colour. The tail conſiſts of 12 feathers, duſky or black on the one web, and marked with red on the other; the tips above, are aſh coloured, below white; which, when ſhooting on the ground was in vogue, was the ſign the fowler diſcovered the birds by. The legs and toes are livid; the latter divided almoſt to their very origin, having only a very ſmall web between the middle and interior toes; as thoſe of the two ſpecies of ſnipes found in England.</p><p>4. The <hi rend="italic">oegocephala,</hi> or godwit, weighs 12 ounces and a half; the length is 16 inches; the breadth 27; the bill is four inches long, turns up a little, black at the end, the reſt a pale purple; from the bill to the eye is a broad white ſtroke; the feathers of the head, neck, and back, are of a light reddiſh brown, marked in the middle with a duſky ſpot; the belly and vent feathers white, the tail regularly barred with black and white. The ſix firſt quill-feathers are black; their interior edges of a reddiſh brown; the legs in ſome are duſky, in others of a greyiſh blue, which perhaps may be owing to different ages; the exterior toe is connected as far as the firſt joint of the middle toe with a ſtrong ſerrated membrane. The male is diſtinguiſhed from the female by ſome black lines on the breaſt and throat; which in the female are wanting. Theſe birds are taken in the fens, in the ſame ſeaſon and in the ſame manner with the ruffs and reeves<note anchored="true" n="2" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>*See <hi rend="italic">Tringo</hi>.</p></note> *; and when fattened are eſteemed a great delicacy, and ſell for half a crown or five ſhillings a piece. A ſtale of the ſame ſpecies is placed in the net. They appear in ſmall flocks on our coaſts in September, and continue with us the whole winter; they walk on the open ſands like the curlew, and feed on insects.</p><p>5. The <hi rend="italic">glottis,</hi> or greenſhank, is in length to the end of the tail, 14 inches; to that of the toes, 20; its breadth, 25. The bill is two inches and a half long; the upper mandible black, ſtraight, and very ſlender; the lower reflects a little upwards; the head and upper part of the neck are aſh-coloured, marked with ſmall duſky lines pointing down; over each paſſes a white line; the coverts, the ſcapulars, and upper part of the back, are of a browniſh aſh-colour; the quill-feathers duſky, but the inner webs ſpeckled with white; the breaſt, belly, thighs, and lower part of the back, are white; the tail is white, marked with undulated duſky bars: the inner coverts of the wings finely croſſed with double and treble rows of a duſky colour. It is a bird of an elegant ſhape, and ſmall weight in proportion to its dimenſions, weighing only ſix ounces. The legs are very long and ſlender, and bare above two inches higher than the knees he exterior toe is united to the middle toe, as far as the ſecond joint, by a ſtrong<pb facs="gri_33125011196389_0721.tif" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0715"/>
membrane which borders their ſides to the very end. — Theſe birds appear on the Engliſh coaſts and wet grounds in the winter-time in but ſmall numbers.</p><p>6. The <hi rend="italic">calidris,</hi> or red-ſhank, is found on moſt of our ſhores; in the winter time it conceals itſelf in the gutters, and is generally found ſingle or at moſt in pairs. It breeds in the fens and marſhes; and flies round its neſt when diſturbed, making a noiſe like a lapwing. It lays four eggs, whitiſh tinged with olive, marked with irregular ſpots of black chiefly on the thicker end. It weighs five ounces and a half: the length is 12 inches, the breadth 21; the bill near two inches long, red at the baſe, black towards the point. The head, hind part of the neck, and ſcapulars, are of a duſky aſh-colour, obſcurely ſpotted with black; the back is white, ſprinkled with black ſpots; the tail elegantly barred with black and white; the cheeks, under ſide of the neck, and upper part of the breaſt, are white, ſtreaked downward with duſky lines; the belly white; the exterior webs of the quill-feathers are duſky; the legs long, and of a fine bright orange colour; the utmoſt toe connected to the middle toe by a ſmall membrane; the inmoſt by another ſtill ſmaller.</p><p>7. The <hi rend="italic">gallinago,</hi> or common ſnipe, weighs four ounces; the length, to the end of the tail, is near 12 inches; the breadth about 14; the bill is three inches long, of a duſky colour, flat at the end, and often rough like ſhagrin above and below. The head is divided lengthwiſe with two black lines, and three of red, one of the laſt paſſing over the middle of the head, and one above each eye: between the bill and the eyes is a duſky line; the chin is white; the neck is varied with brown and red. The ſcapulars are beautifully ſtriped lengthwiſe with black and yellow; the quill-feathers are duſky; but the edge of the firſt is white, as are the tips of the ſecondary feathers: the quill-feathers next the back are barred with black and pale red; the breaſt and belly are white; the coverts of the tail are long, and almost cover it; they are of a reddiſh brown colour. The tail conſiſts of 14 feathers, black on their lower part, then croſſed with a broad bar of deep orange, another trarrow one of black; and the ends white, or pale orange. The vent feathers are of a dull yellow; the legs pale green; the toes divided to their origin. In the winter-time ſnipes are very frequent in all our marſhy and wet grounds, where they lie concealed in the ruſhes, &amp;c. In ſummer they diſperſe to different parts, and are found in the midſt of our higheſt mountains as well as of our low moors; their neſt is made of dried graſs; they lay four eggs of a dirty olive colour, marked with duſky ſpots; their young are ſo often found in England, that we doubt whether they ever entirely leave this iſland. When they are diſturbed much, particularly in the breeding ſeaſon, they ſoar to a vaſt height, making a ſingular bleating noiſe; and when they deſcend, dart down with vaſt rapidity: it is alſo amuſing to obſerve the cock, while his mate fits on her eggs, poiſe himſelf on her wings, making ſometimes a whittling and ſometimes a drumming noiſe. Their food is the ſame with that of the woodcock; their flight very irregular apd ſwift, and attended with a ſhrill ſcream. They are moſt univerſal birds, found in every quarter of the globe, and in all climates.</p></div></body></text></TEI>