<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196389_0725.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0719-02" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SCORZONERA, <hi rend="smallcaps">Viper-grass,</hi></label>
 in botany: A genus of the polygamia æqualis order, belonging to the ſyngeneſia claſs of plants; and in the natural method ranking under the 49th order, <hi rend="italic">Compositœ.</hi> The receptacle is naked; the pappus plumy; the calyx imbricated, with ſcales membranaceous on their margins.</p><p>The moſt remarkable ſpecies is the hiſpanica, or common ſcorzonera, which is cultivated in the gardens of this country, both for culinary and medicinal purpoſes. The root is carrot-ſhaped, about the thickneſs of a finger, covered with a dark brown ſkin, is white within, and has a milky juice. The ſtalk riſes three feet high, is ſmooth, branching at the top, and garniſhed with a few narrow leaves, whoſe baſe half embrace the ſtalk The flowers are of a bright yellow colour, and terminate the ſtalks in ſcaly empalements compoſed of many narrow tongue-ſhaped hermaphrodite florets lying imbricatim over each other like the ſcales of fiſh, and are of a bright yellow colour. After theſe are decayed, the germen, which fits in the common empalements, turns to oblong cornered ſeeds, having a roundiſh ball of feathered down at the top This plant is propagated by ſeeds; and muſt be carefully thinned and kept free from weeds, otherwiſe the plants will be weak.</p><p>The roots of ſcorzonera were formerly much celebrated for their alexipharmic virtues, and for throwing out the ſmall-pox; but have now almoſt entirely loſt their character: however, as they abound with an acrid juice, they may ſometimes be of uſe for ſtrengthening the viſcera, and promoting the fluid ſecretions.</p></div></body></text></TEI>