<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196389_0652.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0646-02" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SANDARACH</label>,
in natural hiſtory, a very beautiful native foſſil, though too often confounded with the common factitious red arſenic, and with the red matter formed by melting the common yellow orpiment.</p><p>It is a pure ſubſtance, of a very even and regular ſtructure, is throughout of that colour which our dyers term an <hi rend="italic">orange ſcarlet,</hi> and is conſiderably transparent even in the thickeſt pieces. But though, with reſpect to colour, it has the advantage of cinnabar while in the maſs, it is vaſtly inferior to it when both are reduced to powder. It is moderately hard, and remarkably heavy; and, when expoſed to a moderate heat, melts and flows like oil: if ſet on fire, it burns very briſkly.</p><p>It is found in Saxony and Bohemia, in the copper and ſilver mines; and is ſold to the painters, who find it a very fine and valuable red: but its virtues or qualities in medicine are no more aſcertained at this time than thoſe of the yellow orpiment.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Gum-SANDARACH</hi> <hi rend="italic subscript"> y</hi> is a dry and hard reſin, uſually met with in looſe granules, of the bigneſs of a pea, a horſe-bean, or larger; of a pale whitiſh yellow colour, tranſparent, and of a reſinous ſmell, brittle, very inflammable, of an acrid and aromatic taſte, and diffuſing a very pleaſant ſmell when burning. It is produced from<pb facs="gri_33125011196389_0653.tif" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0647"/>
a ſpecies of the juniper; (ſee <hi rend="smallcaps">Juniperus. )</hi> It flows only from theſe trees in hot countries: but the natives promote its diſcharge by making inciſions in the bark.</p><p>Sandarach is eſteemed good in diarrhoeas and in haemorrhagies.</p><p>The varniſh-makers make a kind of varniſh of it, by diſſolving it in oil of turpentine or linſeed, or in ſpirit of wine.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Pounded</hi> <hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Sandarach.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Pounce.</hi></p></div></body></text></TEI>