<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196389_0637.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0631-04" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SALVIA, <hi rend="smallcaps">sage:</hi></label>
 A genus of the monogynia order; belonging to the digynia claſs of plants; and in the natural method ranking under the 42d order, <hi rend="italic">Verticillatae.</hi> The corolla is unequal; and the filaments placed croſswiſe on a pedicle. The moſt remarkable ſpecies are,</p><p>1. The officinalis, or common large ſage, which is cultivated in gardens; of which there are the following varieties: 1. The common green ſage; 2. The wormwood ſage. 3. The green ſage, with a variegated leaf. 4. The red ſage. 5. The red ſage with a variegated leaf. Theſe are accidental variations, and therefore are not enumerated as ſpecies. The common ſage grows naturally in the ſouthern parts of Europe, but is here cultivated in gardens for uſe; but that variety with red or blackiſh leaves is the moſt common in the Britiſh gardens; and the wormwood ſage is in greater plenty here than the common green-leaved ſage, which is but in few gardens.</p><p>2. The tomentoſa, generally titled <hi rend="italic">balſamic ſage</hi> by the gardeners. The ſtalks of this do not grow ſo upright as, thoſe of the common ſage; they are very hairy, and divide into ſeveral branches, which are garniſhed with broad heart-ſhaped woolly leaves ſtanding upon long foot-ſtalks; they are ſawed on their edges, and their upper ſurfaces are rough: the leaves, which are upon the flower-ſtalks, are oblong and oval, ſtanding upon ſhorter foot ſtalks, and are very ſlightly ſawed on their edges; they grow in whorled ſpikes toward the top of the branches; the whorls are pretty far diſtant, but few flowers in each; they are of a pale blue, about the ſize of thoſe of the common fort. This ſage is preferred to all the others for making tea.</p><p>3. The auriculata, common ſage of virtue, which is alſo well known in the gardens and markets. The leaves of this is narrower than thoſe of the common fort; they are hoary, and ſome of them are indented on their edges towards the baſe, which indentures have the appearance of ears. The ſpikes of flowers are longer than thoſe of the two former ſorts, and the whorls are generally naked, having no leaves between them. The flowers are ſmaller, and of a deeper blue than thoſe of common red ſage.</p><p>4. The pomifera, with ſpear-ſhaped oval entire leaves, grow naturally in Crete. This hath a ſhrubby ſtalk, which riſes four or five feet high, dividing into ſeveral branches. The flowers grow in ſpikes at the end of the branches; they are of a pale blue colour, and have obtuſe empalements. The branches of this ſage have often punctures made in them by infects, at which places grow large protuberances as big as apples, in the ſame manner as the galls upon an oak, and the rough balls on the briar.</p><p>All the ſorts of ſage may be propagated by ſeeds, if they can be procured; but, as ſome of them do not perfect their ſeeds in this country, and moſt of the ſorts, but eſpecially the common kinds for uſe, are eaſily propagated by flips, it is not worth while to raiſe them from ſeeds.</p></div></body></text></TEI>