<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196389_0640.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0634-03" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SAMANEANS</label>,
in antiquity, a kind of magi or philoſophers, have been confounded by ſome with the Bramins. They proceeded from Ariana, a province of Perſia, and the neighbouring countries, ſpread themſelves in India, and taught new doctrines.</p><p>The Bramins, before their arrival, it is ſaid, were in the higheſt period of their glory, were the only oracles of India, and their principal reſidence was on the banks of the Ganges, and in the adjacent mountains; while the Samaneans were fettled towards the Indus. Others ſay, that the Bramins acquired all their knowledge from the Samaneans, beſore whoſe arrival it would be difficult to prove that the Bramins were the religious teachers of the Indians. The moſt celebrated and ancient of the Samanean doctors was Boutta, or Budda, who was born 683 years before Chriſt. His ſcholars paid him divine honours; and his doctrine, which conſiſted chiefly in the tranſmigration of fouls, and in the wor- ſhip of cows, was adopted not only in India, but alſo in Japan, China, Siam, and Tartary. It was propagated, according to M. de Sainte Croix, in Thibet, in the 8th century, and ſucceeded there the ancient religion of Zamolxis. The Samaneans, or Buddiſts, were entirely deſtroyed in India by the jealous rage of the Bramins, whoſe abſurd practices and fables they affected to treat with contempt; but ſeveral of their books are ſtill preſerved and reſpected on the coaſts of Malabar.</p><p>We are told, too, that ſeveral of the Bramin orders have adopted their manner of living, and openly profeſs the greateſt part of their doctrines. <hi rend="italic">L''Ezour Vedam, ou Ancien Comment du Vedam,</hi> publiſhed by M. de S. Croix, Paris 1779. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Bramins.</hi></p><p><note anchored="false" n="1" place="margin" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">Modern Univ. H.</hi> vol. viii. p. 157.</p></note> SAMAR, a Spaniſh iſland not far from Manilla in the Eaſt Indies, is called <hi rend="italic">Samar</hi> on the ſide which looks towards the other iſles, and <hi rend="italic">Ibabao</hi> on that next the ocean. It is like the trunk of a man’s body, without head or legs. Its greateſt length, from Cape Baliquaton, which, with the point of Manilla, makes the ſtrait of St Bernardino, in 13 degrees 30 minutes north latitude, extends to that of Guignan in 11 degrees towards the ſouth. The other two points, making the greateſt breadth of the iſland, are Cabo de Spirito Santo, or <hi rend="italic">Cape oſ the Holy Ghost,</hi> the high mountains of which are the firſt diſcovered by ſhips from New Spain; and that which lying oppoſite to Leyte weſtward, makes another ſtrait, ſcarce a ſtone’s throw over. The whole compaſs of the iſland is about 130 leagues. Between Guignan and Cape Spirito Santo is the port of Borognon, and not far from thence thoſe of Palapa and Catubig, and the little iſland of Bin, and the coaſt of Catarman. Veſſels from countries not yet diſcovered are very frequently caſt away on the before-mentioned coaſt of Palapa. Within the ſtraits of St Bernardino, and beyond Baliquaton, is the coaſt of Samar, on which are the villages of Ibatan, Bangahon, Cathalogan, Paranos, and Calviga. Then follows the ſtrait of St Juanillo, without which, ſtanding eaſtward, appears the point and little iſland of Guignan, where the compaſs of the iſland ends. It is mountainous and craggy, but fruitful in the few plains there are. The fruits there are much the ſame as that of <hi rend="smallcaps">Leyte</hi>; but there is one particular fort, called by the Spaniards <hi rend="italic">chicoy,</hi> and by the Chineſe, who put a great value on it, <hi rend="italic">ſeyzu</hi>, without kernels.</p></div></body></text></TEI>