<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196389_0624.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0618-03" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SALSETTE</label>,
an iſland of the Eaſt Indies, adjacent to Bombay, from which it is in one place divided only by a narrow paſs fordable at low water. It is about 26 miles long, and eight or nine broad. The ſoil is rich, and by proper cultivation capable of producing any thing that will grow in tropical climates. It is everywhere well watered, and when in the poſſeſſion of the Portugueſe furniſhed ſuch quantities of rice, that it was called the <hi rend="italic">Granary of Gοa.</hi> It abounds alſo in all kinds of proviſions, and has great plenty of game, both of the four-footed and feathered kind. It has pretty high mountains; and there is a tradition that the whole was thrown up from the bottom of the ſea: in confirmation of which it is ſaid, that on the top of the higheſt hill there was found, ſome years ago, a ſtone anchor, ſuch as was anciently uſed by the inhabitants of that country. Here we meet with the ruins of a place called <hi rend="italic">Canara,</hi> where there are excavations of rocks, ſuppoſed to be contemporary with thoſe of <hi rend="smallcaps">Elephanγa.</hi> They are much more numerous, but not comparable to the former either in bigneſs or workmanſhip.</p><p>The iſland of Salſette lately formed part of the Portugueſe dominions in India. It ought to have been ceded to the Engliſh along with Bombay, as part of the dower of Catharine of Liſhon, eſpouſed to Charles II. The fulfilment of this article, however, being evaded, the iſland remained in poſſeſſion of the Portugueſe; and notwithſtanding the little care they took of it, the revenue of it was valued at 60,0001. Such was the negligence of the Portugueſe government, that they took no care to fortify it againſt the attacks of the Marattas, from whoſe dominions Salſette was only feparated by a very narrow paſs fordable at low water. Here they had only a miſerable redoubt of no conſequence, till, on the appearance of an approaching war with the Marattas, they began to build another, which indeed would have anſwered the purpoſe of protecting the iſland, provided the Marattas had allowed them to finiſh it. This, however, was not their intention. They allowed them indeed to go quietly on with their works, till they ſaw them almoſt completed, when they came and took poſſeſſion of them. The Marattas thus became dangerous neighbours to the Engliſh at Bombay, until it was ceded to the latter by the treaty concluded with theſe people in 1780. E. Long. 72. 15. N. Lat. 19. 0.</p></div></body></text></TEI>