<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196389_0650.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0644-01" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SANCROFT</label>
(William) archbiſhop of Canterbury, was born at Freſingfield in Suffolk in 1616; and admitted into Emanuel college, Cambridge, in 1633. In 1642 he was elected a fellow; and, for refuſing to take the covenant, was ejected from his fellowſhip. In 1660 he was choſen one of the univerſity preachers; and in 1663 was nominated to the deanry of York. In 1664 he was inſtalled dean of St Paul's. In this ſtation he ſet himſelf with unwearied diligence to repair the cathedral, till the fire of London in 1666 employed his thoughts on the more noble undertaking of rebuilding it, toward which he gave 14001. He alſo rebuilt the deanry, and improved the revenue of it. In 1668 he was admitted archdeacon of Canterbury, on the king’s preſentation. In 1677, being now prolocutor of the convocation, he was unexpectedly advanced to the arch- biſhopric of Canterbury. In 1678 he was committed to the tower, with fix other biſhops, for preſenting a petition to the king againſt reading the declaration of indulgence. Upon king James II.’s withdrawing himfelf, he concurred with the lords in a declaration to the prince of Orange for a free parliament, and due indulgence to the Proteſant diſſenters. But when that prince and his confort were declared king and queen, his grace refuſing to take the oaths to their majeſties, he was ſuſpended and deprived. He lived in a very private manner, till he died in 1693. His learning, integrity, and piety, made him an exalted ornament of the church.</p><p>He publiſhed a volume in 12mo, intitled <hi rend="italic">Modern Politics,</hi> taken from Machiavel, Borgia, and other choice authors; Familiar Letters to Mr North, an 8vo pamphlet; and three of his ſermons were printed together after his death.</p></div></body></text></TEI>