<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196389_0615.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0609-03" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SALE</label>,
is the exchange of a commodity for money; barter, or permutation, is the exchange of one commodity for another. When the bargain is concluded, an obligation is contracted by the buyer to pay the value, and by the feller to deliver the commodity, at the time and place agreed on, or immediately, if no time be ſpeciſied.</p><p>In this, as well as other mercantile contracts, the ſafety of commerce requires the utmoſt good faith and veracity. Therefore, although, by the laws of England, a fale, above the value of 101. be not binding, unleſs earneſt be paid, or the bargain confirmed by writing, a merchant would loſe all credit who refuſed to perform his agreement, although theſe legal requiſιtes were omitted.</p><p>When a ſpecific thing is fold, the property, even before delivery, is in ſome reſpect veſted in the buyer; and if the thing periſhes, the buyer muſt bear the loſs. For example, if a horſe dies before delivery, he muſt pay the value: but if the bargain only determines the quantity and quality of the goods, without ſpecifying the identical articles, and the ſeller’s warehouſe, with all his goods, be burned, he is intitled to no payment. He muſt alſo bear the loſs if the thing periſh through his fault; or when a particular time and place of delivery is agreed on, if it periſh before it be tendered, in terms of the bargain.</p><p>If a perſon purchaſe goods at a ſhop without agreeing for the price, he is liable for the ordinary market- price at the time of purchaſe.</p><p>If the buyer proves inſolvent before delivery, the feller is not bound to deliver the goods without payment or ſecurity.</p><p>If the importation, or uſe of the commodities fold, be prohibited by law, or if the buyer knows that they were ſmuggled, no action lies for delivery.</p><p>The property of goods is generally preſumed, in favour of commerce, to belong to the poſſeſſor, and cannot be challenged in the hands of an onerous purchaſer. But to this there are ſome exceptions. By the Scots law, ſtolen goods may in all caſes be reclaimed by the proprietor, and alſo by the Engliſh law, unleſs they were bought <hi rend="italic">bona fide</hi> in open market; that is, in the accuſtomed public places, on ſtated days in the country, or in a ſhop in London; and horſes may be reclaimed, unleſs the ſale be regularly entered by the book-keeper of the market. In all caſes, if the goods be evicted by the lawful proprietor, the ſeller is liable to the purchaſer for the value.</p><p>Actions for payment of ſhop-accounts, as well as other debts not conſtituted by writing, are limited in England to fix years. The teſtimony of one witneſs is admitted; and the ſeller’s books, although the perſian that kept them be dead, are good evidence for one year. In Scotland, merchants books may be proved within three years of the date of the laſt article, by one witneſs, and the creditor’s books and oath in ſupplement. After three years, they can only be proved by the oath or writ of the debtor. A merchant’s books are in all caſes good evidence againſt him.</p></div></body></text></TEI>