<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196389_0641.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0635-01" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SAMARITANS</label>
. We have already ſpoken of the Samaritans under the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Cuth.</hi> The Samaritans<pb facs="gri_33125011196389_0642.tif" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0636"/>
are the people, of the city of Samaria, and the inhabitants of the province of which Samaria was the capital city. In this ſenſe, it ſhould ſeem that we might give the name of Samaritans to the Iſraelites of the ten tribes, who lived in the city and territory of Samaria. However, the ſacred authors commonly give the name of Samaritans only to thoſe ſtrange people whom the kings of Aſſyria ſent from beyond the Euphrates to inhabit the kingdom of Samaria, when they took away captive the Iſraelites that were there before. Thus we may fix the epoch of the Samaritans at the taking of Samaria by Salmaneſer, in the year of the world 3283. This prince carried away captive the Iſraelites that he found in the country, and aſſigned them dwellings beyond the Euphrates, and in Aſſyria, (2 Kings xvii. 24.) He ſent other inhabitants in their ſtead, of which the moſt conſiderable were the Cuthites, a people deſcended from Culh, and who are probably of the number of thoſe whom the ancients knew by the name of Scythians.</p><p>After Salmaneſer, his ſucceſſor Eſar-haddon was informed, that the people which had been ſent to Samaria were infeſted by lions that devoured them, (2 Kings xvii. 25.); this he imputed to the ignorance of the people in the manner of worſhipping the god of the country. Wherefore Eſar-haddon ſent a prieſt of the God of Iſrael that he might teach them the religion of the Hebrews. But they thought they might blend this religion with that which they profeſſed before; ſo they continued to worſhip their idols as before, in conjunction with the God of Iſrael, not perceiving how abſurd and incompatible theſe two religions were.</p><p>It is not known how long they continued in this ſtate; but at the return from the captivity of Babylon, it appears they had entirely quitted the worſhip of their idols; and when they aſked permiſſion of the Iſraelites that they might labour with them at the rebuilding of the temple of Jeruſalem, they affirmed, that from the time that Eſar-haddon had brought them into this country they had always worſhipped the Lord, (Ezrah iv. 1, 2, 3.) And indeed, after the return from the captivity, the ſcripture does not any where reproach them with idolatrous worſhip, though it does not diſſemble either their jealouſy againſt the Jews, nor the ill offices they had done them at the court of Perſia, by their ſlanders and calumnies, or the ſtratagems they contrived to hinder the repairing of the walls of Jeruſalem. — (Nehem. ii. 10 <hi rend="italic">,</hi> 19. iv. 2, &amp;c. vi. 1, <hi rend="italic">2,</hi> &amp;c.)</p><p>It does not appear that there was any temple in Samaria, in common to all theſe people who came thither from beyond the Euphrates, before the coming of Alexander the Great into Judea. Before that time, every one was left to his own diſcretion, and worſhipped the Lord where he thought fit. But they preſently comprehended, from the books of Moſes which they had in their hands, and from the example of the Jews their neighbours, that God was to be worſhipped in that place only which he had choſen. So that ſince they could not go to the temple of Jeruſalem, which the Jews would not allow of, they bethought themſelves of building a temple of their own upon mount Gerizim, near the city of Shechem, which was then their capital. Therefore Sanballat, the governor of the Samaritans, applied himſelf to Alexander, and told him he had a son-in-law <hi rend="subscript"> i</hi> called Manaſſes, ſon to Jaddus,</p><p>the high-prieſt of the Jews, who had retired to Samaria with a great number of other perſons of his own nation; that he deſired to build a temple in this province, where he might exerciſe the high-prieſthood; that this undertaking would be to the advantage of the king’s affairs, becauſe in building a temple in the province of Samaria, the nation of the Jews would be divided, who are a turbuſent and ſeditious people, and by ſuch a diviſion would be made weaker, and leſs in a condition to undertake new enterprizes.</p><p>Alexander readily conſented to what Sanballat deſired, and the Samaritans preſently began their building of the temple of Gerizim, which from that time they have always frequented, and ſtill frequent to this day, as the place where the Lord intended to receive the adoration of his people. It is of this mountain, and of this temple, that the Samaritan woman of Sychar ſpoke to our Saviour, (John iv. 20.) See <hi rend="smallcaps">GARIZIM</hi>.</p><p>The Samaritans did not long continue under the obedience of Alexander. They revolted from him the very next year, and Alexander drove them out of Samaria, put Macedonians in their room, and gave the province of Samaria to the Jews. This preference that Alexander gave to the Iſraelites contributed not a little to increaſe that hatred and animoſity that had already obtained between theſe two people. When any Iſraelite had deſerved puniſhment for the violation of ſome important point of the law, he preſently took refuge in Samaria or Shechem, and embraced the way of worſhip according to the temple of Garizim. When the Jews were in a proſperous condition, and affairs were favourable to them, the Samaritans did not fail to call themſelves Hebrews, and pretended to be of the race of Abraham. But no ſooner were the Jews fallen into diſcredit or perſecution, but the Samaritans immediately diſowned them, would have nothing in common with, them, acknowledged themſelves to be Phoenicians originally, or that they were deſcended from Joſeph and Manaſſeh his ſon. This uſed to be their practice in the time of Antiochus Epiphanes.</p><p>The Samaritans, having received the Pentateuch, or the five books of Moſes, from the prieſt that was lent by Eſar-haddon, have preſerved it to this day, in the ſame language and character it was then, that is, in the old Hebrew or Phoenician character, which we now call the Samaritan, to diſtinguiſh it from the modern Hebrew character, which at preſent we find in the books of the Jews. Theſe laſt, after their captivity, changed their old characters, and took up thoſe of the Chaldee, which they had been uſed to at Babylon, and which they continue ſtill to uſe. It is wrong, ſays F. Calmet, to give this the name of the Hebrew character, for that can be ſaid properly only of the Samaritan text. The critics have taken notice of ſome variations between the Pentateuch of the Jews and that of the Samaritans; but theſe varieties of reading chiefly regard the word Gerizim, which the Samaritans ſeem to have purpoſely introduced to favour their pretenſions, that mount Gerizim was the place in which the Lord was to be adored. The other various readings are of ſmall importance.</p><p>The religion of this people was at firſt the Pagan. Every one worſhipped the deity they had been uſed to in their own country (2 Kings xvii. 25, 30, 31.)<pb facs="gri_33125011196389_0643.tif" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0637"/>
The Babylonians worſhipped Succoth-benoth; the Cuthites, Nergal; the Hamathites, Aſhima; the Avites, Nibhaz and Tartak; the Sepharvites, Adrammelech and Anammelech. If we would enumerate all the names of falſe gods to whom the Samaritans have paid a ſacrilegious worſhip, we ſhould have enough to do. This matter is ſufficiently perplexed, by reaſon of the different names by which they were adored by different nations, inſomuch that it would be almoſt impoſſible to clear up this affair. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Succoth-Benoth, &amp;c.</hi> Afterwards, to this profane worſhip the Samaritans added that of the Lord, the God of Iſrael, (2 Kings xvii. 29, 30, 31, 32. ) They gave a proof of their little regard to this worſhip of the true God, when under Antiochus Epiphanes they conſecrated their temple at Gerizim to Jupiter Argivus. In the time of Alexander the Great, they celebrated the ſabbatical year, and conſequently the year of jubilee alſo. We do not know whether they did it exactly at the fame time with the Jews, or whether they obſerved any other epoch; and it is to little purpoſe that ſome critics have attempted to aſcertain the firſt beginning of it. Under the kings of Syria they followed the epoch of the Greeks, or that of the Seleucidae, as other people did that were under the government of the Seleucidae. After that Herod had re-eſtabliſhed Samaria, and had given it the name of Sebaſte, the inhabitants of this city, in their medals, and all public acts, took the date of this new eſtabliſhment. But the inhabitants of Samaria, of which the greater part were Pagans or Jews, were no rule to the other Samaritans, who probably reckoned their years according to the reigns of the emperors they were ſubject to, till the time they fell under the juriſdiction of the Mahometans, under which they live at this day; and they reckon their year by the Hegira, or, as they ſpeak, according to the reign of Iſhmael, or the Iſhmaelites. Such of our readers as deſire to be further acquainted with the hiſtory of the ancient Samaritans, we refer to the works of Joſephus, where they will find that ſubject largely treated of.</p><p>As to their belief, it is objected to them, that they receive only the Pentateuch, and reject all the other books of ſcripture, chiefly the prophets, who have more expreſsly declared the coming of the Meſſiah. — They have alſo been accuſed of believing God to be corporeal, of denying the Holy Ghoſt, and the reſurrection of the dead. Jeſus Chriſt reproaches them (John iv. 22.) with worſhipping they know not what; and in the place already referred to he ſeems to exclude them from ſalvation, when he fays, that “Salvation is of the Jews.” True it is, that theſe words might only ſignify, that the Meſſiah was to proceed from the Jews; but the crime of ſchiſm alone, and a ſeparation from the true church, was ſufficient to exclude them from ſalvation. The Samaritan woman is a ſufficient teſtimony that the Samaritans expected a Meſſiah, who they hoped would clear up all their doubts (John iv. 25.) Several of the inhabitants of Shechem believed at the preaching of Jeſus Chriſt, and ſeveral of Samaria believed at that of St Philip; but it is ſaid, they ſoon fell back to their former errors, being perverted by Simon Magus.</p><p>The Samaritans at prefect are very few in number. Joſeph Scaliger) being curious to know their uſages,</p><p>wrote to the Samaritans of Egypt, and to the high- prieſt of the whole ſect who reſided at Neapolis in Syria. They returned two anſwers to Scaliger, dated in the year of the Hegira 998. Theſe were preſerved in the French king’s library, and were tranſlated into Latin by father Morin, and printed in England in the collection of that father’s letters, in 1682, under the title of <hi rend="italic">Antiquitates Eccleſiae Orientalis.</hi> By theſe letters it appears, that they believe in God, in his ſervant Moſes, the holy law, the mountain Gerizim, the houſe of God, the day of vengeance and of peace; that they value themſelves upon obſerving the law of Moſes in many points more rigidly than the Jews themſelves. — They keep the ſabbath with the utmoſt ſtrictneſs required by the law, without ſtirring from the place they are in, but only to the ſynagogue. They go not out of the city, and abſtain from their wives on that day. They never delay circumciſion beyond the eighth day. They ſtill ſacrifiee to this day in the temple on mount Gerizim, and give to the prieſt what is enjoined by the law. They do not marry their own nieces, as the Jews do, nor do they allow themſelves a plurality of wives. Their hatred for the Jews may be ſeen through all the hiſtory of Joſephus, and in ſeveral places of the New Teſtament. The Jewiſh hiſtorian informs us, that under the government of Coponius, one paſſover night, when they opened the gates of the temple, ſome Samaritans had ſcattered the bones of dead men there, to inſult the Jews, and to interrupt the devotion of the feſtival. The evangeliſts ſhew us, that the Jews and Samaritans held no correſpondence together (John iv. 9. ) “The Jews have no dealings with the Samaritans. ” And the Samaritan woman of Sychar was much ſurpriſed that Jeſus talked with her, and aſked drink of her, being a Samaritan. When our Saviour ſent his apoſtles to preach in Judea, he forbad them to enter into the Samaritan cities, (Matt. x. 5); becauſe he looked upon them as ſchiſmatics, and as ſtrangers to the covenant of Iſrael. One day when he ſent his diſciples to provide him a lodging in one of the cities of the Samaritans, they would not entertain him, becauſe they perceived he was going to Jeruſalem. (Luke ix. 52. 53. ) “Becauſe his face was as though he would go to Jeruſalem. ” And when the Jews were provoked at the reproaches of Jeſus Chriſt, they told him he was a Samaritan (John viii. 48. ), thinking they could ſay nothing more ſevere againſt him. Joſephus relates, that ſome Samaritans having killed ſeveral Jews as they were going to the feaſt at Jeruſalem, this occaſioned a kind of a war between them. The Samaritans continued their fealty to the Romans, when the Jews revolted from them; yet they did not eſcape from being involved in ſome of the calamities of their neighbours.</p><p>There are ſtill at this day ſome Samaritans at Shechem, Otherwiſe called Naplouſe. They have prieſts there, who ſay they are of the family of Aaron. They have a high-prieſt, who reſides at Shechem, or at Gerizim, who offers ſacrifices there, and who declares the feaſt of the paſſover, and all the other feaſts, to all the diſperſed Samaritans. Some of them are to be found at Gaza, ſome at Damaſcus, and ſome at Grand Cairo.</p></div></body></text></TEI>