<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196389_0619.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0613-02" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SALLET</label>,
or SALLAD <hi rend="smallcaps">,</hi> a diſh of eatable herbs, ordinarily accompanying roaſt meat; compoſed chiefly of crude, ſreſh herbage, ſeaſoned with ſalt, oil, and vinegar.</p><p>Menage derives the word from the Latin <hi rend="italic">balata;</hi> of <hi rend="italic">ſal,</hi> “ſalt; ” others from <hi rend="italic">ſalcedo;</hi> Du-Cange from <hi rend="italic">ſalgama,</hi> which is uſed in Auſonius and Columella in the ſame ſenſe.</p><p>Some add muſtard, hard eggs, and ſugar; others, pepper, and other ſpices, with orange-peel, ſaffron, &amp;c.</p><p>The principal ſallet-herbs, and thoſe which ordinarily make the baſis of our Engliſh ſallets, are lettuce, celery, endive, creſſes, radiſh, and rape; along with which, by way of furniture, or additionals, are uſed purſlane, ſpenach, ſorrel, tarragon, burnet, corn-ſallet, and chervil.</p><p>The gardeners call ſome plants <hi rend="italic">ſmall herbs</hi> in ſallets; theſe ſhould always be cut while in the ſeed-leaf: as creſſes, muſtard, radiſh, turnep, ſpinach, and lettuce; all which are raiſed from ſeeds ſown in drills, or lines, from the middle of February to the end of March, under glaſſes or frames; and thence to the middle of May, upon natural beds, warmly expoſed; and during the ſummer heats in more ſhady places; and afterwards in September, as in March, &amp;c.; and laſtly, in the rigour of the winter, in hot-beds. If they chance to be frozen in very froſty weather, putting them in ſpring-water two hours before they be uſed recovers them.</p></div></body></text></TEI>