<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196389_0623.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0617-03" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SALONA</label>,
a ſea-port town of Dalmatia, ſeated on a bay of the gulph of Venice. It was formerly a very conſiderable place, and its ruins ſhow that it was 10 miles in circumference. It is 18 miles north of Spalatto, and ſubject to Venice.<note anchored="false" n="1" place="margin" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">Fortis's Travels into Dalmatia</hi></p></note> It is now a wretched village, preſerving few diſtinguiſhable remains of its ancient ſplendor. Doubtleſs the two laſt ages have deſtroyed all that had eſcaped the barbarity of the northern nations that demoliſhed it. In a valuable MS. relation of Dalmatia, written by the ſenator Giam- battiſta Guiſtiniani, about the middle of the 16th century, there is a hint of what exiſted at that time. “The nobility, grandeur, and magnificence of the city of Salona, may be imagined from the vaults and arches of the wonderful theatre, which are ſeen at this day; from the vaſt ſtones of the fineſt marble, which lies ſcattered on, and buried in the fields; from the beautiful column of three pieces of marble, which is ſtill ſtanding in the place where they ſay the arſenal was, towards the ſea- ſhore; and from the many arches of ſurpriſing beauty.<pb facs="gri_33125011196389_0624.tif" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0618"/>
ſupported by very high marble columns; the height of the arches is a ſtone-throw, and above them there was an aqueduct, which reached from Salona to Spalatro. There are to be ſeen many ruins and veſtiges of large palaces, and many ancient epitaphs may be read on fine marble ſtones; but the earth, which is increaſed, has buried the moſt ancient ſtones, and the moſt valuable things. ” E. Long. 17. 29. N. Lat. 44. 10.</p></div></body></text></TEI>