<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196389_0707.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0701-08" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SCHOMBERG</label>
(Frederick-Armand duke of), a diſtinguiſhed officer, ſprung from an illuſtrious family in Germany, and the ſon of count Schomberg, by an Engliſh lady, daughter of lord Dudley, was born in 1608. He was initiated into the military fife under Frederick- Henry prince of Orange, and afterwards ſerved under his ſon William II. of Orange, who highly eſteemed him He then repaired to the court of France, where his reputation was ſo well known, that he obtained the government of Gravelines, of Furnes, and the ſurrounding countries. He was reckoned inferior to no general in that kingdom except mareſchal Turenne and the prince of Condé; men of such exalted eminence that it was no diſgrace to acknowledge their ſuperiority. The French court thinking it neceſſary to diminiſh the power of Spain, lent Schomberg to. the aſſiſtance of the Portugueſe, who were engaged in a war with that country respecting the ſucceſſion to their throne. — Schomberg’s military talents gave a turn to the war in favour of his allies. The court of Spain was obliged to ſolicit for peace in 1668, and to acknowledge the houſe of Braganza as the juſt heirs to the throne of Portugal. For his great ſervices he was created count Mentola in Portugal; and a penſion of 5000 <hi rend="italic">l.</hi> was beſtowed upon him, with the reverſion to his heirs.</p><p>In 1673 he came over to England to command the army; but the Engliſh at that time being, diſguſted with the French nation, Schomberg was luſpected of coining over with a deſign to corrupt, the army, and bring it under French diſcipline. He therefore found it neceſſary to return to France, which he ſoon left, and went to the Netherlands. In the month of June 1676, he forced the prince of Orange to raiſe the ſiege of Maeſtricht; and it is ſaid he was then railed to the rank of marelchal of France. But the French <hi rend="italic">Dictionaire Historique,</hi> whole information on a point of this nature ought to be authentic, ſays that he was inveſted with this honour the ſame year in which he took the<pb facs="gri_33125011196389_0708.tif" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0702"/>
fortreſs of Bellegarde from the Spaniards while ſerving in Portugal.</p><p>Upon the revocation of the edict of Nantes, when the perſecution commenced againſt the Proteſtants, Schomberg, who was of that perſuaſion, requeſted leave to retire into his own country. This requeſt was refuſed; but he was permitted to take refuge in Portugal, where he had reaſon to expect he would be kindly received on account of paſt ſervices. But the religious zeal of the Portugueſe, though it did not prevent them from accepting aſſiſtance from a heretic when their kingdom was threatened with ſubverſion, could not permit them to give him ſhelter when he came for protection. The inquiſition interfered, and obliged the king to ſend him away. He then went to Holland by the way of England. Having accepted an invitation from the elector of Brandenburg, he was inveſted with the government of Ducal Pruſſia, and appointed commander in chief of the elector’s forces. When the prince of Orange ſailed to England to take poſſeſſion of the Crown which his father-in law James II. had abdicated, Schomberg obtained permiſſion from the elector of Brandenburg to accompany him. He is ſuppoſed to have been the author of an ingenious ſtratagem which the prince employed alter his arrival in London to diſcover the ſentiments of the people reſpecting the revolution. The ſtratagem was, to ſpread an alarm over the country that the Iriſh were approaching with fire and ſword. When the prince was eſtabliſhed on the throne of England, Schomberg was appointed commander in chief of the forces and maſter of the ordnance. In April 1689 he was made knight of the garter, and naturalized by act of Parliament 5 and in May following was created a baron, earl, marquis, and duke of the kingdom of England, by the name and title of baron Teys, earl of Brentford, marquis of Harwich, and duke of Schomberg. The Houſe of Commons voted to him L. l00, 000 as a reward for his ſervices. Of this he only received a ſmall part; but after his death a penſion of L. 5000 a-year was beſtowed upon his ſon.</p><p>In Auguſt 1689 he was ſent to Ireland to reduce that kingdom to obedience. When he arrived, he found himſelf at the head of an army con filling only of 12, 000 foot and 2000 horſe, while king James commanded an army three times more numerous. Schomberg thought it dangerous to engage with ſo ſuperior a force, and being diſappointed in his promiſed ſupplies from England, judged it prudent to remain on the defenſive. He therefore polled himſelf at Dundalk, about five or fix miles diſtance from James, who was encamped at Ardee. For ſix weeks he remained in this poſition, without attempting to give battle, while from the wetneſs of the ſeaſon he loſt nearly the half of his army. Schomberg was much blamed for not coming to action; but ſome excellent judges admired his conduct as a diſplay of great military talents. Had he riſked an engagement, and been defeated, Ireland would have been loſt. At the famous battle of the Boyne, fought on the 1st July 1690, which decided the late of James, Schomberg paſſed the river at the head of his cavalry, defeated eight ſquadrons of the enemy, and broke the Iriſh inſantry. When the French Proteſtants loſt their commander, Schomberg went to rally and lead them on to charge. While thus engaged, a party of king James’s guards, which had been ſeparated from the reſt, paſſed Schom</p><p>berg, in attempting to rejoin their own army. They attacked him with great fury, and gave him two wounds in the head. As the wounds were not dangerous, he might ſoon have recovered from them; but the French Proteſtants, perhaps thinking their general was killed, immediately fired upon the guards, and ſhot him dead on the ſpot. He was buried in St Patrick’s cathedral.</p><p>Biſhop Burnet lays, Schomberg was “a calm man, of great application and conduct, and thought much better than he ſpoke; of true judgment, of exact probity, and of a humble and obliging temper. ”</p></div></body></text></TEI>