<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196389_0718.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0712-05" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SCIURUS</label>,
the <hi rend="smallcaps">squirrel</hi>; a genus of quadrupeds belonging to the order of glires. It has two fore-teeth in each jaw, the ſuperior ones ſhaped like wedges, and the inferior ones compreſſed. There are 11 ſpecies; of which the moſt remarkable are,</p><p>1. The <hi rend="italic">vulgaris,</hi> or common ſquirrel, with ears terminated with long tufts of hair; large, lively, black eyes; head, body, legs, and tail, of a bright reddiſh brown; breaſt and belly white; hair on each ſide the tail lies flat. In Sweden and Lapland, it changes in winter into grey. In Ruſſia it is ſometimes found black. In many parts of England there is a beautiful variety, with milk white tails. —This ſpecies inhabits Europe and North America, the northern and the temperate parts of Aſia: and a variety is even found as far ſouth as the iſle of Ceylon. It is a neat, lively, active animal; lives always in woods: in the ſpring, the female is ſeen purſued from tree to tree by the males, feigning an eſcape from their embraces; makes its neſt of moſs and dried leaves between the fork of two branches; brings three or four young at a time; has two holes to its neſt; ſtops up that on the ſide the wind blows, as Pliny juſtly remarks; lays in a hoard of winter proviſion, Rich as nuts, acorns, &amp;c.; in ſummer, feeds on buds and young ſhoots; is particularly fond of thoſe of fir, and the young cones; ſits up to eat, and uſes its forefeet as hands; covers itſelf with its tail; leaps to a ſurpriſing diſtance; when diſpoſed to croſs a river, a piece of bark is its boat, its tail the ſail; is in great plenty in Dunmallet, and there called <hi rend="italic">Conn.</hi> Boys frequently nurſe this beautiful and active animal under cats.</p><p>There are three creatures, the ſquirrel, the field- mouſe, and the bird called the <hi rend="italic">nuthatch,</hi> which live much on hazel nuts; and yet they open them each in a different way. The firſt, after raſping off the ſmall end, ſplits the ſhell in two with his long fore-teeth, as a man does with his knife; the ſecond nibbles a hole with his teeth, ſo regular as if drilled with a wimble, and yet ſo ſmall, that one would wonder how the kernel can be extracted through it; while the laſt pecks an irregular ragged hole with its bill; but as this artiſt has no paws to hold the nut firm while he pierces it, like an adroit workman, he fixes it, as it were in a vice, in ſome cleft of a tree, or in ſome crevice; when, ſtanding over it, he perforates the ſtubborn ſhell. While at work, they make a rapping noiſe, that may be heard at <hi rend="italic">a</hi> conſiderable diſtance.” <hi rend="italic">White’s Seibοrne.</hi></p><p>2. The <hi rend="italic">cinereus,</hi><note anchored="false" n="1" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>Plate CCCCXLY. Fig 1.</p></note> or grey ſquirrel, with plain ears; hair of a dull grey colour, mixed with black, and often tinged with dirty yellow; belly and inſides of the legs white; tail long, buſhy, grey, and ſtriped with black: ſize of a half-grown rabbit. —Inhabits the woods of Northern Aſia, North America, Peru, and Chili. They are very numerous in North America, do incredible damage to the plantations of maize, run up the ſtalks and eat the young ears. Deſcend in vaſt flocks from the mountains, and join thoſe that inhabit the lower parts; are proſcribed by the provinces, and a reward of three-pence per head given for every one that is killed. Such a number was deſtroyed one year, that Pennſylvania alone paid in rewards L. 8000 of its currency. Make their neſts in hollow trees, with moſs, ſtraw, wool, &amp;c. Feed on maize in the ſeaſon, and on pine cones, acorns, and maſts of all kinds: form holes under-ground, and there depoſit a large ſtock of winter proviſion. Deſcend from the trees, and viſit their magazines when in want of meat; are particularly buſy at the approach of bad weather; during the cold ſeaſon keep in their neſt for ſeveral days together; ſeldom leap from tree to tree, only run up and down the bodies; their hoards often deſtroyed by ſwine; when their magazines are covered with deep ſnow, the ſquirrels often periſh for want of food; are not eaſily ſhot, nimbly changing their place when they ſee the gun levelled; have the actions of the common ſquirrel; are eaſily tamed; and their fleſh is eſteemed very delicate. Their furs, which are imported under the name of <hi rend="italic">petit-gris</hi>, are valuable, and uſed as linings to cloaks.</p><p>3. The <hi rend="italic">niger,</hi> or black ſquirrel, with plain ears; ſometimes wholly black, but often marked with white on the noſe, the neck, or end of the tail; the tail ſhorter than that of the former; the body equal. It inhabits the north of Aſia, North America, and Mexico; breeds and aſſociates in ſeparate troops; is equally numerous with the former; commits as great ravages among the maize; makes its neſt in the ſame manner, and forms, like them, magazines for winter food. The fineſt are taken near the lake Baikal, and about Barguzinſkoi-oſtrog, upon the Upper Angara, in the diſtrict of Nertſchinſk, which are the beſt in all Siberia; theſe continue black the whole year, the others grow ruſty in ſummer. — There is a variety with plain ears; coarſe fur mixed with dirty white and black; throat and inſide of the legs and thighs black; tail much ſhorter than thoſe of ſquirrels uſually are; of a dull yellow colour, mixed with black; body of the ſize of the grey ſquirrel. It inhabits Virginia; the planters call it the <hi rend="italic">cat ſquirrel.</hi></p><p>4. The <hi rend="italic">flavus,</hi> or fair ſquirrel, with the body and tail of a flaxen colour; of a very ſmall ſize, with plain round ears, and rounded tail. Inhabits the woods near Amadabad, the capital of Guzurat, in great abundance, leap, ing from tree to tree. Linnaeus ſays it is an inhabitant of South America.</p><p>5. The <hi rend="italic">ſtriatus,</hi> or ground ſquirrel, with plain ears;<pb facs="gri_33125011196389_0719.tif" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0713"/>
ridge of the back marked with a black ſtreak; each ſide with a pale yellow ſtripe, bounded above and below with a line of black; head, body, and tail, of a reddiſh brown; the tail the darkeſt: breaſt and belly white; noſe and feet pale-red; eyes full. —Inhabits the north of Aſia, but found in the greateſt abundance in the foreſts of North America. They never run up trees except they are purſued, and find no other means of eſcaping: they burrow, and form their habitations under ground, with two entrances, that they may get acceſs to the one in caſe the other is ſtopped up. Their retreats are formed with great ſkill, in form of a long gallery, with branches on each ſide, each of which terminates in an enlarged chamber, as a magazine to ſtore their winter proviſion in; in one they lodge the acorns, in another the maize, in a third the hickery nuts, and in the laſt their favourite food the chinquapin cheſnut. They very ſeldom ſtir out during winter, at leaſt as long as their proviſions laſt; but if that fails, they will dig into cellars where apples are kept, or barns where maize is ſtored, and do a great deal of miſchief; but at that time the cat deſtroys great numbers, and is as great an enemy to them as to mice. During the maize harveſt theſe ſquirrels are very buſy in biting off the ears, and filling their mouths ſo full with the corn, that their cheeks are quite diſtended. It is obſervable that they give great preference to certain food; for if, after filling their mouths with rye, they happen to meet with wheat, they fling away the firſt, that they may indulge in the laſt. They are very wild, bite ſeverely, and are ſcarcely ever tamed; the ſkins are of little uſe, but are ſometimes brought over to line cloaks.</p><p>6. The <hi rend="italic">glis</hi>, or fat ſquirrel, with thin naked ears; body covered with ſoft aſh-coloured hair; belly whitiſh; tail full of long hair: from noſe to tail, near fix inches; tail, four and a half: thicker in the body than the common ſquirrel. —Inhabits France and the ſouth of Europe; lives in trees, and leaps from bough to bough; feeds on fruits and acorns; lodges in the hollows of trees; remains in a torpid ſtate during winter, and grows very fat. It was eſteemed a great delicacy by the Romans, who had their gliraria, places conſtructed to keep and feed them in.</p><p>7. The <hi rend="italic">ſagitta,</hi> or arrow ſquirrel, with a ſmall round head, cloven upper lip: ſmall blunt ears, two ſmall warts at the utmoſt corner of each eye, with hairs growing out of them: neck ſhort: four toes on the fore feet; and inſtead of a thumb, a ſlender bone two inches and a half long, lodged under the lateral membrane, ſerving to ſtretch it out: from thence to the hind legs extends the membrane, which is broad, and a continuation of the ſkin of the ſides and belly: there are five toes on the hind feet; and on all the toes, ſharp compreſſed bent claws: the tail is covered with long hairs diſpoſed horizontally: colour of the head, body, and tail, a bright bay; in ſome parts inclining to orange: breaſt and belly of a yellowiſh white: length from noſe to tail, eighteen inches; tail, fifteen. —Inhabits Java, and others of the Indian iſlands: leaps from tree to tree as if it flew: will catch hold of the boughs with its tail. Niewhoff, p. 354. deſcribes this under the name of the flying cat, and ſays the back is black.</p><p>8. The <hi rend="italic">volans,</hi> or flying ſquirrel, with round naked ears, full black eyes, and a lateral membrane from the fore to the hind legs: tail with long hairs diſpoſed horizontally, longeſt in the middle: its colour above, a browniſh aſh; beneath, white tinged with yellow: much leſs than the common ſquirrel. Inhabits Finland, Lapland, Poland, Ruſſia, North America, and New Spain: lives in hollow trees: ſleeps in the day: during the night is very lively: is gregarious, numbers being found in one tree: leaps from bough to bough ſometimes at the diſtance of ten yards: this action has improperly been called flying, for the animal cannot go in any other direction than forward; and even then cannot keep an even line, but ſinks conſiderably before it can reach the place it aims at: ſenſible of this, the ſquirrel mounts the higher in proportion to the diſtance it wiſhes to reach: when it would leap, it ſtretches out the forelegs, and extending the membranes becomes ſpecifically lighter than it would otherwiſe be, and thus is enabled to ſpring further than other ſquirrels that have not this apparatus. When numbers leap at a time, they ſeem like leaves blown off by the wind. Their food the ſame as the other ſquirrels. They are eaſily tamed: bring three or four young at a time. See fig. 3 &amp; 4, the one repreſenting the animal in what is called a <hi rend="italic">fifing,</hi> the other in a <hi rend="italic">fitting,</hi> poſture.</p></div></body></text></TEI>