<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196389_0695.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0689-04" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SCANDINAVIA</label>,
a general name for the countries of Norway, Sweden, and Denmark, anciently under the dominion of one prince. The inhabitants of theſe countries, in former times, were exceſſively addicted to war. From their earlieſt years they applied themſelves to the military art, and accuſtomed themſelves to cold, fatigue, and hunger. Even the very ſports of youth and childhood were dangerous.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Vol.</hi> XVI. Part II.</p><p>They conſiſted in taking frightful leaps, climbing up the ſteepeſt rocks, fighting naked with offenſive weapons, wreſtling with the utmoſt fury; ſo that it was uſual to fee them grown up to be robuſt men, and terrible in the combat, at the age of 15. At this early age the young men became their own maſters; which they did by receiving a ſword, a buckler, and a lance. This ceremony was performed at ſome public meeting. One of the principal men of the aſſembly named the youth in public; after which he was obliged to provide for his own ſubſiſtence, and was either now to live by hunting, or by joining in ſome incurſion againſt the enemy. Great care was taken to prevent the young men from too early connections with the female ſex; and indeed they could have no hope to gain the affection of the fair, but in proportion to the courage and addreſs they had ſhown in their military exerciſes. Accordingly, in an ancient ſong, we find Bartholin, king of Norway, extremely ſurpriſed that his miſtreſs ſhould prove unkind, as he could perform eight different exerciſes. The children were generally born in camps; and being inured from their infancy to behold nothing but arms, effuſion of blood, and ſlaughter, they imbibed the cruel diſpoſition of their fathers, and when they broke forth upon other nations, behaved rather like furies than like human creatures.</p><p>The laws of this people, in ſome meaſure, reſembled thoſe of the ancient Lacedemonians. They knew no virtue but bravery, and no vice but cowardice. The greateſt penalties were inflicted on ſuch as fled from battle. The laws of the ancient Danes declared ſuch perlons infamous, and excluded them from ſociety. Among the Germans, cowards were ſometimes ſuffocated in mud; after which they were covered over with hurdles, to ſhow, ſays Tacitus, that though the puniſhment of crimes ſhould be public, there are certain degrees of cowardice and infamy which ought to be buried in oblivion. Frotho king of Denmark enacted, by law, that whoever ſolicited an eminent poſt ought upon all occaſions to attack one enemy, to face two, to retire only one ſtep back from three, and never to make an actual retreat till affaulted by four. The rules of juſtice themſelves were adapted and warped to theſe prejudices. War was looked upon as a real act of juſtice, and force was thought to be an inconteſtable title over the weak, and a viſible mark that God had intended them to be ſubject to the ſtrong. They had no doubt but that the intentions of the Deity had been to eſtabliſh the ſame dependence among men that takes place among inferior creatures; and, ſetting out from this principle of the natural <hi rend="italic">inequality</hi> among men, they had from thence inferred that the weak had no right to what they could not defend. This maxim was adopted; with ſuch rigour, that the name of divine judgement was given not only to the judicatory combat, but to conflicts and battles of all ſorts; victory being, in their opinion, the only certain mark by which providence enables us to diſtinguiſh thoſe whom it has appointed to command others. —Laſtly, their religion, by annexing eternal happineſs to the military virtues, gave the utmoſt poſſible degree of vigour to that propenſity which thele people had for war, and to their contempt of death, of which we ſhall now give ſome inſtances. We are informed that Harold, ſurnamed <hi rend="italic">Blaatand,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Blue-tooth,</hi> a king of Denmark, who lived in the be-<pb facs="gri_33125011196389_0696.tif" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0690"/>
ginning of the ninth century, had founded on the coaſts of Pomerania a city named <hi rend="italic">Julin</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Jomſburg.</hi> To this place he ſent a colony of young Danes, beſtowing the government on a celebrated warrior called <hi rend="italic">Palnatοkο.</hi> In this colony it was forbidden to mention the word <hi rend="italic">fear,</hi> even in the moſt imminent dangers. No citizen of Jomſburg was to yield to ∙ny number of enemies however great. The fight of inevitable death was not to be taken as an excuſe for ſhowing the ſmalleſt apprehenſion. And this legiſlator really appears to have eradicated from the minds of moſt of the youths bred up under him, all traces of that ſentiment ſo natural and ſo univerſal, which makes men think on their deſtruction with horror. Nothing can ſhow this better than a ſingle fact in their hiſtory, which deferves to have place here for its Angularity. Some of them having made an irruption into the territories of a powerful Norwegian lord, named <hi rend="italic">Haquin,</hi> were overcome in ſpite of the obſtinacy of their reſiſtance; and the moſt diſtinguiſhed among them being made priſoners, were, according to the cuſtom of thoſe times, condemned to death. The news of this, far from afflicting them, was on the contrary received with joy. The firſt who was led to puniſhment was content to fay, without changing countenance, and without expreſſing the leaſt ſign of fear, “Why ſhould not the fame happen to me as did to my father? He died, and ſo muſt I.” A warrior, named <hi rend="italic">Thorchill,</hi> who was to cut off the head of the second, having aſked him what he felt at the fight of death, he anſwered, “that he remembered too well the laws of Jomſhurg to utter any words that denoted fear.” The third, in reply to the ſame queſtion, ſaid, “he rejoiced to die with glory; and that he preferred ſuch a death to an infamous life like that of Thorchill’s.” The fourth made an anſwer much longer and more extraordinary. ‘I ſuffer with a good heart; and the preſent hour is to me very agreeable. I only beg of you (added he, addreſſing himſelf to Thorchill) to be very quick in cutting off my head; for it is a queſtion often debated by us at Jomſhurg, whether one retains any ſenſe after being beheaded. I will therefore graſp this knife in my hand; if, after my head is cut off, I ſtrike it towards you, it will ſhow I have not loſt all ſenſe; if I let it drop, it will be a proof of the contrary. Make haſte therefore, and decide the diſpute.” Thorchill, adds the hiſtorian, cut off his head in a moſt expeditious manner; but the knife, as might be expected, dropt from his hand. The fifth ſhowed the ſame tranquillity, and died rallying and jeering his enemies. The ſixth begged of Thorchill, that he might not be led to puniſhment like a ſheep: “Strike the blow in my face (ſaid he), I will fit ſtill without ſhrinking; and take notice whether I once wink my eyes, or betray one ſign of fear in my countenance; for we inhabitants of Jomſburg are uſed to exerciſe ourſelves in trials of this ſort, ſo as to meet the ſtroke of death without once moving.” He kept his promiſe before all the ſpectators, and received the blow without betraying the leaſt ſign of fear, or ſo much as winking with his eyes. The ſeventh, ſays the hiſtorian, was a very beautiful young man, in the flower of his age. His long hair, as fine as ſilk, floated in curls and ringlets on his ſhoulders. Thorchill aſked him, what he thought of death? “I receive it willingly (ſaid he), ſince I have fulfilled the greateſt duty of life, and have ſeen all thoſe put to death whom I would not ſurvive. I only beg of you one favour, not to let my hair be touched by a ſlave, or ſtained with my blood.”</p><p>Neither was this intrepidity peculiar to the inhabitants of Jomſhurg; it was the general character of all the Scandinavians, of which we ſhall only give his further inſtance. A warrior, having been thrown upon his back in wreſtling with his enemy, and the latter finding himſelf without his arms, the vanquiſhed perſon promiſed to wait, without changing his poſture, till his antagoniſt fetched a ſword to kill him; and he faithfully kept his word. —To die with his arms in his hand was the ardent wiſh of every free man; and the pleaſing idea which they had of this kind of death led them to dread ſuch as proceeded from old age and diſeaſe. The hiſtory of ancient Scandinavia is full of inſtances of this way of thinking. The warriors who found themſelves lingering in diſeaſe, often availed themſelves of their few remaining moments to ſhake off life, by a way that they ſuppoſed to be more glorious. Some of them would be carried into a field of battle, that they might die in the engagement. Others ſlew themſelves: many procured this melancholy ſervice to be performed by their friends, who conſidered it as a moſt ſacred duty. “There is, on a mountain of Iceland, (ſays the author of an old Iceland romance), a rock ſo high, that no animal can fall from the top and live. Here men betake themſelves when they are afflicted and unhappy. From this place all our anceſtors, even without waiting for ſickneſs, have departed into Eden. It is uſeleſs, therefore, to give ourſelves up to groans and complaints, or to put our relations to needleſs expences, ſince we can eaſily follow the example of our fathers, who have all gone by the way of this rock.” — When all theſe methods failed, and at laſt when Chriſtianity had baniſhed ſuch barbarous practices, the diſconſolate heroes conſoled themſelves by putting on complete armour as ſoon as they found their end approaching.</p></div></body></text></TEI>