<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196389_0619.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0613-04" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SALLUSTIUS</label>
(Caius Criſpus), a celebrated Roman hiſtorian, was born at Amiternum, a city of Italy, in the year of Rome 669, and before Chriſt 85. His education was liberal, and he made the beſt uſe of it. His Roman Hiſtory in fix books, from the death of Sylla to the conſpiracy of Catiline, the great work from which he chiefly derived his glory among the antients, is unfortunately loſt excepting a few fragments; but his two detached pieces of Hiſtory which happily remain entire, are ſufficient to juſtify the great encomiums he has received as a writer. —He has had the ſingular honour to be twice tranſlated by a royal hand: firſt by our Elizabeth, according to Camden;<pb facs="gri_33125011196389_0620.tif" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0614"/>
and ſecondly, by the preſent Infant of Spain, whoſe verſion of this elegant hiſtorian, lately printed in folio, is one of the moſt beautiful books that any country has produced ſince the invention of printing. No man has inveighed more ſharply againſt the vices of his age than this hiſtorian; yet no man had leſs pretenſions to virtue than he. His youth was ſpent in a moſt lewd and profligate manner; and his patrimony almoſt ſquandered away when he had ſcarcely taken poſſeſſion of it. Marcus Varro, a writer of undoubted credit, relates, in a fragment preſerved by Aulus Gellius, that Salluſt was actually caught in bed with Fauſta the daughter of Sylla, by Milo her huſhand; who ſcourged him very ſeverely, and did not ſuffer him to depart till he had redeemed his liberty with a conliderable ſum. A. U. C. 694, he was made queſtor, and in 702 tribune of the people; in neither of which places is he allowed to have acquitted himſelf at all to his honour. By virtue of his queſtorſhip, he obtained an admiſſion into the ſenate; but was expelled thence by the cenſors in 704, on account of his immoral and debauched way of life. In the year 705 Caeſar reſtored him to the dignity of a ſenator; and to introduce him into the houſe with a better grace, made him queſtor a ſecond time. In the adminiſtration of this office he behaved himſelf very ſcandalouſly; expoſed every thing to ſale that he could find a purchaſer for; and if we may believe the author of the invective, thought nothing wrong which he had a mind to do: <hi rend="italic">Nihil non venale habuerit, cujus aliquis emptor ſuit, nihil non aquum et verum duxit, quοd ipſi facere collibuiſſet.</hi> In the year 707, when the African war was at an end, he was made praetor for his ſervices to Caeſar, and ſent to Numidia. Here he acted the ſame part as Verres had done in Sicily; out- rageouſly plundered the province; and returned with ſuch immenſe riches to Rome, that he purchaſed a moſt magnificent building upon mount Quirinal, with thoſe gardens which to this day retain the name of <hi rend="italic">Salluſtian gardens,</hi> beſides his country houſe at Tivoli. How he ſpent the remaining part of his life, we have no account ſrom ancient writers. Euſebius tells us, that he married Terentia, the divorced wife of Cicero; and that he died at the age of 50, in the year 710, which was about four years before the battle of Actium. Of the many things which he wrote, beſide his Hiſtories of the Catilinarian and Jugurthine wars, we have fume orations or ſpeeches, printed with his fragments.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">SALLY-ports,</hi> in fortification, or <hi rend="italic">Poſtern-Gates, as</hi> they are ſometimes called, are thoſe under-ground paſſages which lead from the inner works to the outward ones; ſuch as from the higher flank to the lower, or to the tenailles, or the communication from the middle of the curtain to the ravelin. When they are made for men to go through only, they are made with ſteps at the entrance and going out. They are about 6 feet wide and 8 <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> feet high. There is alſo a gutter or ſhore made under the ſally-ports, which are in the middle of the curtains, for the water which runs down the ſtreets to paſs into the ditch; but this can only be done when they are wet ditches. When ſally-ports ſerve to carry guns through them for the out-works, inſtead of making them with ſteps, they muſt have a gradual ſlope, and be 8 feet wide.</p></div></body></text></TEI>