<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196389_0680.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0674-04" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SAVILE</label>
(Sir George), afterwards marquis of Halifax, and one of the greateſt ſtateſmen of his time, was born about the year 1630; and ſome time after his return from his travels was created a peer, in conſideration of his own and his father’s merits. He was a ſtrenuous oppoſer of the bill of excluſion; but propoſed ſuch limitations of the duke of York’s authority, as ſhould diſable him from doing any harm either in church or ſtate, as the taking out of his hands all power in eccleſiaſtical matters, the diſpoſal of the public money, and the power of making peace and war; and lodging theſe in the two houſes of parliament. After that bill was rejected in the houſe of lords, he preſſed them, though without ſucceſs, to proceed to the limitation of the duke’s power; and began with moving, that during the king’s life he might be obliged to live five hundred miles out of England. In Auguſt 1682 he was created a marquis, and ſoon after made privy-ſeal. Upon King James’s acceffion, he was made preſident of the council; but on his refuſal to conſent to the repeal of the teſt, he was diſmiſſed from all public employments. In that aſſembly of the lords which met after king James’s withdrawing himſelf the firſt time from Whitehall, the marquis was choſen their preſident; and upon the king’s return from Feverſham, he was ſent, together with the earl of Shrewſhury and lord Delamere, front the Prince of Orange, to order his majeſty to quit the palace at Whitehall. In the convention of parliament he was choſen ſpeaker of the houſe of lords, and ſtrenuouſly ſupported the motion for the vacancy of the throne, and the conjunctive ſovereignty of the prince and princeſs; upon whoſe acceſſion he was again made privy- ſeal. Yet, in 1689, he quitted the court, and became a zealous oppoſer of the meaſures of government till his death, which happened in April 1695. The rev. Mr Grainger obſerves, that “he was a perſon of unſettled principles, and of a lively imagination, which ſometimes got the better of his judgment. He would never loſe<pb facs="gri_33125011196389_0681.tif" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0675"/>
his jeſt, though it ſpoiled his argument, or brought his ſincerity or even his religion in queſtion. He was deſervedly celebrated for his parliamentary talents; and in the famous conteſt relating to the bill of excluſion was thought to be a match for his uncle Shaftſbury. The pieces he has left us ſhow him to have been an ingenious, if not a maſterly writer; and his <hi rend="italic">Advice to a Daughter</hi> contains more good ſenſe in fewer words than is, perhaps, to be found in any of his contemporary authors.” His lordſhip alſo wrote, The Anatomy of an Equivalent: a Letter to a Diſſenter; a Rough Draught of a New Model at Sea; and Maxims of State; all which were printed together in one volume 8vo. — Since theſe were alſo publiſhed under his name the Character of king Charles II. 8vo; the Character of Biſhop Burnet, and Hiſtorical Obſervations upon the reigns of Edward I. II. III. and Richard II. with Remarks upon their faithful Counſellors and falſe Favourites.</p></div></body></text></TEI>