<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196389_0699.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0693-01" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SCARBOROUGH</label>,
a town of the North Riding of Yorkſhire, ſeated on a ſteep rock, near which are ſuch craggy cliffs that it is almoſt inacceſſible on every fide. On the top of this rock is a large green plain, with two wells of freſh water ſpringing out of the rock. It has of late been greatly frequented on account of its mineral waters called the <hi rend="italic">Scarborough-Spa;</hi> on which account it is much mended in the number and beauty of the buildings. The ſpring was under the cliff, part of<pb facs="gri_33125011196389_0700.tif" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0694"/>
which fell down in 1737, and the water was loſt; but in clearing away the ruins in order to rebuild the wharf, it was recovered, to the great joy of the town. The waters of Scarborough are chalybeate and purging. The two wells are both impregnated with the ſame principles, in different proportions; though the purging well is the moſt celebrated, and the water of this is uſually called the <hi rend="italic">Scarborough water.</hi> When theſe waters are poured out of one glaſs into another, they throw up a number of air-bubbles; and if they are ſhaken for ſome time in a phial cloſe flopped, and the phial be ſuddenly opened before the commotion ceaſes, they diſplode an elaſtic vapour, with an audible noiſe, which ſhows that they abound in fixed air At the fountain they have a briſk, pungent, chalybeate taſte; but the purging water taſtes bitteriſh, which is not uſually the caſe with the chalybeate one. They loſe their chalybeate virtues by expoſure and by keeping; but the purging water the ſooneſt. They both putrefy by keeping; but in time recover their ſweetneſs. Four or five half pints of the purging water drank within an hour, give two or three eaſy motions, and raiſe the ſpirits. The like quantity of the chalybeate purges leſs, but exhilarates more, and paſſes off chiefly by urine. Theſe waters have been found beneficial in hectic fevers, weakneſſes of the ſtomach, and indigeſtion; in relaxations of the ſyſtem; in nervous, hyſteric, and hypochondriacal diſorders; in the green ſickneſs, ſcurvy, rheumatiſm, and aſthmatic complaints; in gleets, the fluor albus, and other preternatural evacuations; and in habitual coſtiveneſs. Here are aſſemblies and balls in the ſame manner as at Tunbridge. It is a place of ſome trade, has a very good harbour, and fends two members to parliament. E. Long. 54. 18 N. Lat. O 3.</p></div></body></text></TEI>