<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196389_0617.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0611-07" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SALINO</label>,
one of the Lipari iſlanda, ſituated between Sicily and Italy, conſiſts of two mountains both in an high ſtate of cultivation. The one lying more towards the north than the other is rather the higheſt of the two, and is called <hi rend="italic">del Capo,</hi> “the head.” The other is called <hi rend="italic">della Foſſa felice,</hi> or “the happy valley.” One third of the extent of theſe hills from the bottom to the ſummit is one continued orchard, conſiſting of vines, olive, fig, plum, apricot, and a vaſt diverſity of other trees. The white roofs of the houſes, which are everywhere interſperſed amid this diverſity of verdure and foliage, contribute to variegate the proſpect in a very agreeable manner. The back part of almoſt all the houſes is ſhaded by an arbour of vines, ſupported, by pillars of brick, with croſs poles to ſuſtain the branches and foliage of the vines. Thoſe arbours ſhelter the houſes from the rays of the ſun, the heat of which is quite ſcorching in theſe ſouthern regions. The vines are extremely fruitful; the poles bending under the weight of the grapes.</p><p>The ſcenes in this iſland are more intereſting to the lover of natural hiſtory than to the antiquarian. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Reticulum.</hi></p><p>On the ſouth fide of the iſland, however, there are ſtill to be ſeen ſome fine ruins of an ancient bath, a Roman work. They conſiſt of a wall 10 or 11 fathoms in extent, and terminating in an arch of no great height, of which only a ſmall part now remains. The building ſeems to have been reduced to its preſent ſtate rather by the ravages of men than the injuries of time. Almoſt all the houſes in the iſland are built of materials which have belonged to ancient monuments. The ancients had, in all probability, baths of freſh as well as of ſalt water in this iſland; for whenever the preſent inhabitants have occaſion for a ſpring of freſh water, they have only to dig a pit on the ſhore, and pure ſweet water flows in great abundance.</p><p>There were formerly mines of alum here, from which the inhabitants drew a very conſiderable yearly revenue. But whether they are exhauſted, or whatever circumſtance may have cauſed them to be given up, they are<pb facs="gri_33125011196389_0618.tif" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0612"/>
now no longer known. The iſland abounds in a variety of fruits.</p><p>On the eaſt-ſide it is very populous. There are two places which are both called <hi rend="italic">Lingua, "</hi> the tongue,” and which contain a good number of inhabitants; the one is near Salino, the other is diſtinguiſhed by the name of <hi rend="italic">St Marina</hi>: there are beſides theſe two other villages. All theſe places together may contain about 4000 inhabitants: the circumference of the iſland may be about 14 miles.</p></div></body></text></TEI>