<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196389_0605.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0599-04" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SAFFRON</label>,
in the materia medica, is formed of the ſtigmata of the crocus officinalis<note anchored="true" n="1" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>*See Crocus</p></note> *, dried on a kiln, and preſſed together into cakes. Of this there are two kinds, the Engliſh and Spaniſh; of which the latter is by far the most eſteemed. Saffron is principally cultivated in Cambridgeſhire, in a circle of about ten miles diameter. The greateſt part of this tract is an open level country, with few incloſures; and the cuſtom there is, as in moſt other places, to crop two years, and let the land be fallow the third. Saffron is generally planted upon fallow-ground, and, all other things being alike, they prefer that which has borne barley the year before.</p><p>The ſaſſron ground is ſeldom above three acres, or leſs than one; and in chooſing, the principal thing they have regard to is, that they be well expoſed, the ſoil not poor, nor a very ſtiff clay, but a temperate dry-mould, ſuch as commonly lies upon chalk, and is of an hazel colour; though, if every thing elſe anſwers, the colour of the mould is pretty much neglected.</p><p>The ground being made choice of, about Lady-day or the beginning of April, it muſt be carefully ploughed, the furrows being drawn much cloſer together, and deeper if the ſoil will allow it, than is done for any kind of corn; and accordingly the charge is greater.</p><p>About five weeks after, during any time in the month of May, they lay between 20 and 30 loads of dung upon each acre, and having ſpread it with great care, they plough it in as before. The ſhorteſt rotten dung is the beſt; and the farmers, who have the conveniency of making it, ſpare no pains to make it good, being ſure of a proportionable price for it. About midſummer they plough a third time, and between every 16 feet and an half they leave a broad furrow or trench, which ſerves both as a boundary to the ſeveral parcels, and for throwing the weeds into at the proper ſeaſon. The time of planting is commonly in the month of July. The only inſtrument uſed at this time is a ſmall narrow ſpade, commonly called a <hi rend="italic">ſpit-ſhovel.</hi> The method is this: One man with his ſhovel raiſes about three or four inches of earth, and throws it before him about ſix or more inches. Two perſons, generally women, follow with roots, which they place in the fartheſt edge of the trench made by the digger, at about three inches from each other. As ſoon as the digger has gone once the breadth of the ridge, he begins again at the other ſide; and, digging as before, covers the roots laſt ſet, which makes room for another row of roots at the ſame diſtance from the firſt that they are from one another. The only dexterity neceſſary in digging is, to leave ſome part of the. firſt ſtratum of earth untouched, to lie under the roots; and, in ſetting, to place the roots directly upon their bottom. The quantity of roots planted on an acre is generally about 16 quarters, or 128 buſhels. From the time of planting till the beginning of September, or ſometimes later, there is no more labour required; but at that time they begin to vegetate, and are ready to ſhow themſelves above ground, which may be known by digging up a few of the roots. The ground is then to be pared with a ſharp hoe, and the weeds raked into the furrows, otherwiſe they would hinder the growth of the ſaffron. In ſome time after, the flowers appear.</p><p>They are gathered before they are full blown, as well as after, and the proper time for it is early in the morning. The owners of the ſaffron-fields get together a ſuſſicient number of hands, who pull off the whole flowers, and throw them by handfuls into a baſket, and ſo continue. till about. 11 o’clock. Having then carried home the flowers, they immediately fall to picking out the ſtigmata or chives, and together with them a pretty large proportion of the ſtylus itfelf, or firing to which they are attached: the reſt of the flower they throw away as uſeleſs. Next morning they return to the field, without regarding whether the weather be wet or dry; and ſo on daily, even on Sundays, till the whole crop is gathered. — The next labour is to dry the chives on the kiln.. The kiln is built upon a thick<pb facs="gri_33125011196389_0606.tif" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0600"/>
plank, that it may be moved from place to place. It is ſupported by four ſhort legs: the outſide conſiſts of eight pieces of wood of three inches thick, in form of a quadrangular frame, about 12 inches ſquare at the bottom on the inſide, and 22 on the upper part; which laſt is likewiſe the perpendicular height of it. On the foreſide is left a hole of about eight inches ſquare, and four inches above the plank, through which the fire is put in; over all the reſt laths are laid pretty thick, cloſe to one another, and nailed to the frame already mentioned. They are then plaſtered over on both ſides, as are alfo the planks at bottom, very thick, to ſerve for an hearth. Over the mouth is laid a haircloth, fixed to the edges of the kiln, and likewiſe to two rollers or moveable pieces of wood, which are turned by wedges or ſcrews, in order to ſtretch the cloth. Inſtead of the hair-cloth, ſome people uſe a net-work or iron-wire, by which the ſaffron is ſooner dried, and with leſs fuel; but the difficulty of preſerving it from burning makes the hair-cloth preferred by the beſt judges. The kiln is placed in a light part of the houſe; and they begin with putting five or ſix ſheets of white paper on the hair-cloth, and upon theſe they lay out the wet ſaffron two or three inches thick. It is then covered with ſome other ſheets of paper, and over theſe they lay a Coarſe blanket five or fix times doubled, or inſtead of this, a canvas pillow filled with ſtraw; and after the fire has been lighted for ſome time, the whole is covered with a board having a conſiderable weight upon it. At firſt they apply a pretty ſtrong heat, to make the chives <hi rend="italic">ſweat</hi> as they call it; and at this time a great deal of care is neceſſary to prevent burning. When it has been thus dried about an hour, they turn the cakes of ſaffron upſide down, putting on the coverings and weight as before. If no ſiniſter accident happens during theſe firſt two hours, the danger is thought to be over; and nothing more is requiſite than to keep up a very gentle fire for 24 hours, turning the cake every half hour. That fuel is beſt which yields the leaſt ſmoke; and for this reaſon charcoal is preferable to all others.</p><p>The quantity of ſaffron produced at a crop is uncertain. Sometimes five or fix pounds of wet chives are got from one rood, ſometimes not above one or two; and ſometimes not ſo much as is ſufficient to defray the expence of gathering and drying. But it is always ob- ſerved, that about five pounds of wet ſaffron go to make one pound of dry for the firſt three weeks of the crop, and fix pounds during the laſt week. When the heads are planted very thick, two pounds of dry ſaffron may at a medium be allowed to an acre for the firſt crop, and 24 pounds for the two remaining ones, the third being conſiderably larger than the ſecond.</p><p>To obtain the ſecond and third crops, the labour of hoeing, gathering, picking, &amp;c. already mentioned, muſt be repeated; and about midſummer, after the third crop is gathered, the roots muſt all be taken up and tranſplanted. For taking up the roots, ſometimes the plough is made uſe of, and ſometimes a forked hoe; and then the ground is harrowed once or twice over. During all the time of ploughing, harrowing, &amp;c. 15 or more people will find work enough to follow and gather the heads as they are turned up. The roots are next to be carried to the houſe in facks, where they are cleaned and raſed. This labour conſiſts in cleaning the roots</p><p>thoroughly from earth, decayed old pieces, involucra, or excrescences; after which they become fit to be planted in new ground immediately, or they may be kept for ſome time, without danger of ſpoiling. The quantity of roots taken up in proportion to thoſe planted is uncertain; but, at a medium, 24 quarters of clean roots, fit to be planted, may be had front each acre. — There ſometimes happens a remarkable change in the roots of ſaffron and ſome other plants. As ſoon as they begin to ſhoot upwards, there are commonly two or three large tap-roots ſent forth from the fide of the old one, which will run two or three inches deep into the ground. At the place where theſe bulbs firſt come out from, the old one will be formed ſometimes, though not always, and the tap-root then decays. The bulb increaſes in bigneſs, and at laſt falls quite off; which commonly happens in April. But many times theſe tap-roots never produce any bulbs, and remain barren for ever after. All ſuch roots therefore ſhould be thrown away in the making a new plantation. This degeneracy of the roots is a diſeaſe for which no cure is as yet known.</p><p>When ſaffron is offered to ſale, that kind ought to be choſen which has the broadeſt blades; this being the mark by which Engliſh ſaffron is diſtinguiſhed from the foreign. It ought to be of an orange or fiery-red colour, and to yield a dark yellow tincture. It ſhould be choſen freſh, not above a year old, in cloſe cakes, neither dry nor yet very moiſt, tough and firm in tearing, of the ſame coloιfr within as without, and of a ſtrong, acrid, diffuſive ſmell.</p><p>This drug has been reckoned a very elegant and uſeful aromatic. Beſides the virtues it has in common with other ſubſtances of that claſs, it has been accounted one of the higheſt cordials, and is ſaid to exhilarate the ſpirits to ſuch a degree as, when taken in large doſes, to occaſion immoderate mirth, involuntary laughter, and the ill effects which follow from the abuſe of ſpirituous liquors. This medicine is particularly ſerviceable in hyſteric depreſſions proceeding from a cold cauſe or obſtnuction of the uterine ſecretions, where other aromatics, even thoſe of the more generous kind, have little effect. Saffron imparts the whole of its virtue and colour to rectified ſpirit, proof-ſpirit, wine, vinegar, and water. A tincture drawn with vinegar loſes greatly of its colour in keeping: the watery and vinous tinctures are apt to grow ſour, and then loſe their colour alſo: that made in pure ſpirit keeps in perfection for many years.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Meadow-SAFFRON.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Colchicum.</hi></p></div></body></text></TEI>