<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196389_0679.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0673-02" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SAVARY</label>
(James), an eminent French writer on the ſubject of trade, was born at Done, in Anjou, in 1622. Being bred to merchandize, he continued in trade until 1658; when he left off the practice, to cultivate the theory. He had married in 1650; and in 1660, when the king declared a purpoſe of aſſigning privileges and penſions to ſuch of his ſubjects as had twelve children alive, Mr Savary was not too rich to put in his claim to the royal bounty. He was afterwards admitted of the council for the reformation of commerce; and the orders which paſſed in 1670 were drawn up by his inſtructions and advice. He wrote <hi rend="italic">Le Parfait Negociant,</hi> 4to; and, <hi rend="italic">Avis et conſeils ſur les plus importantes matieres du Commerce,</hi> in 4t0. He died in 1690; and out of 17 children whom he had by one wife, left 11. Two of his ſons, James and Philemon Lewis, laboured jointly on a great work, <hi rend="italic">Dictionnaire Uηiverſelle du Commerce,</hi> 2 vols folio. This work was begun by James, who was inſpector-general of the manufactures at the cuſtomhouſe, Paris; who called in the aſſiſtance of his brother Philemon Lewis, although a canon of the royal church of St Maur; and by his death left him to finiſh it. This work appeared in 1723, and Philemon afterwards added a third ſupplemental volume to the former. Poſtlethwayte’s Engliſh Dictionary of Trade and Commerce is a tranſlation, with conſiderable improvements, from Savary.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Savary,</hi> an eminent French traveller and writer, was born at Vitre, in Brittany, about the year 1748. He ſtudied with applauſe at Rennes, and in 1776 travelled into Egypt, where he remained almoſt three years. During this period he was wholly engaged in the ſtudy of the Arabian language, in ſearching out ancient monuments, and in examining the national manners. After making himſelf acquainted with the knowledge and philoſophy of Egypt, he viſited the iſlands in the Archipelago, where be ſpent 18 months. On his return to France, in 1780, he publiſhed, 1. A Tranſlation of the Koran, with a ſhort Life of Mahomet, in 1783, 2 vols 8vo. 2. The Morality of the Koran, or a collection of the moſt excellent maxims in the Koran; a work extracted from his tranſlation, which is eſteemed both elegant and faithful. 3. Letters on Egypt, in 3 vols 8vo, in 1785. In theſe the author makes his obſervations with accuracy, paints with vivacity, and renders intereſting every thing he relates. His deſcriptions are in general faithful, but are perhaps in ſome inſtances too much ornamented. He has been juſtly cenſured for painting modern Egypt and its inhabitants in too high colours. Theſe letters, however, were bought up by the curious public, and read with pleaſure and advantage. Encouraged by this flattering reception, he prepared his letters upon Greece, He died<pb facs="gri_33125011196389_0680.tif" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0674"/>
ſoon after at Paris of a malady contracted from too intenſe application. A ſenſible obſtruction <hi rend="italic">in</hi> the right lobe of the liver had made a deciſive progreſs, which the return of ſummer, ſome ſimple medicines, a ſtrict regimen, and travelling, ſeemed to remove.</p><p>On his return into the country adjacent to Paris, his health however was ſtill doubtful; for it is well known that when the organization of one of the viſcera has been much deranged, deep traces of it will ever remain. His active mind, however, made him regardleſs of his health, and he conceived it his duty to profit by thoſe appearances of recovery which he experienced at the cloſe of the ſummer and the beginning of autumn, to put into order his travels into the iſlands of the Archipelago, intended as a continuation of his letters on Egypt. His warmth of temper was exaſperated by ſome lively criticiſms which had been made on his former productions, and he gave himſelf up to ſtudy with a degree of activity of which the conſequences were ſufficiently obvious. An obſtruction in the liver again took place, and made a new progreſs; his digeſtion became extremely languid; ſleep quite forſook him, both by night and by day; a dry and troubleſome cough came on; his face appeared bloated, and his legs more and more inflamed. The uſe of barley water and cream of tartar ſtill however promoted, in ſome degree, the urinary ſecretions, and afforded ſome little glimmering of hope. In this ſituation he returned to Paris in the beginning of the year 1788, to attend to the publication of his new work concerning the iſlands of the Archipelago, particularly the iſle of Candia. He had then all the ſymptoms of a dangerous dropſy, which became ſtill more alarming from the very exhauſted ſtate of the viſcera. The right lobe of the liver was extremely hard and ſenſible. The patient had ſhiverings without any regular returns, and his ſtrength was undermined by a hectic fever. At the ſame time ſtill more uneaſy ſymptoms took place, thoſe of a dropſy in the cheſt; but the circumſtances which deſtroyed all hope, and announced his approaching diſſolution, were a ſevere pain in the left ſide, with a very troubleſome cough, and a copious and bloody expectoration <hi rend="italic">(in hepaticis,</hi> ſays Hippocrates, <hi rend="italic">ſputum cruentum mortiferum};</hi> his reſpiration became more and more difficult; his ſtrength was exhauſted, and his death took place on the 4th of February 788, attended with every indication of the moſt copious overflowing in the cheſt, and of an abſceſs in the liver. — Thus was deſtroyed, in the vigour of his age, an author whoſe character and talents rendered him worthy of the happieſt lot.</p><p>Mr Savary’s genius was lively and well cultivated; his heart warm and benevolent; his imagination vigorous; his memory retentive. He was cheerful and open; and had ſo great a talent for telling a ſtory, that his company was not leſs agreeable than inſtructive. He did not mingle much with the world, but was ſatisfied with performing well the duties of a ſon, of a brother, and of a friend.</p></div></body></text></TEI>