<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196389_0697.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0691-02" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SCAPULA</label>,
in anatomy, the ſhoulder, or ſhoulder- bone.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Scapula</hi> (John), the reputed author of a Greek lexicon, ſtudied at Lauſanne. His name is recorded in the annals of literature, neither on account of his talents nor learning, nor virtuous induſtry, but for a groſs act of diſingenuity and fraud which he committed againſt an eminent literary character of the 16th century. Being employed by Henry Stephens as a corrector to his preſs while he was publiſhing his <hi rend="italic">Theſaurus linguae Graecae,</hi> Scapula extracted thoſe words and explications which he reckoned moſt uſeful, compriſed them in one volume, and publiſhed them as an original work, with his own name.</p><p>The compilation and printing of the Theſaurus had coſt Stephens immenſe labour and expence; but it was ſo much admired by thoſe learned men to whom he had</p><p>ſhown it, and ſeemed to be of ſuch eſſential importance to the acquiſition of the Greek language, that he reaſonably hoped his labour would be crowned with honour, and the money he had expended would be repaid by a rapid and extenſive ſale. But before his work came abroad, Scapula’s abridgment appeared; which, from its ſize and price, was quickly purchaſed, while the Theſaurus itſelf lay neglected in the author’s hands. The conſequence was, a bankruptcy on the part of Stephens, while he who had occaſioned it was enjoying the fruits of his treachery. Scapula’s Lexicon was tirſt printed in 1570, in 4to. It was afterwards enlarged, and publiſhed in folio. It has gone through ſeveral editions, while the valuable work of Stephens has never been reprinted. Its ſucceſs is, however, not owing to its ſuperior merit, but to its price and more commodious ſize. Stephens charges the author with omitting a great many important articles. He accuſes him of miſunderſtanding and perverting his meaning; and of tracing out abſurd and trifling etymologies, which he himſelf had been careful to avoid. He compoſed the following epigram on Scapula:</p><p><hi rend="italic">Quidam επιτεμνων me</hi> capulo <hi rend="italic">tenus abdidit enſem AEger eram a</hi> Scapulis, <hi rend="italic">ſanus et huc redeo.</hi></p><p>Doctor Buſby, ſo much celebrated for his knowledge of the Greek language, and his ſucceſs in teaching it, would never permit his ſcholars at Weſtminſter ſchool to make uſe of Scapula.</p></div></body></text></TEI>