<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196389_0709.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0703-02" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SCHORL</label>,
a precious ſtone of the ſecond order, of which the varieties are, <hi rend="italic">Siberian,</hi> ruby-coloured, reddiſh, green, brown, blue and black; <hi rend="italic">mother of emerald,</hi> dark green; <hi rend="italic">lapis crucifer,</hi> or the <hi rend="italic">croſs ftone;</hi> bar ſchorl; horn blend, black, green, or blue; <hi rend="italic">Cianite,</hi> blue ſchorl; <hi rend="italic">Thumstein; Laxman's quadrangular ſchorl.</hi></p><p>Tranſparent ſchorl is chryſtallized in polygonal prisms, generally with four, fix, or nine ſides; ſome of them are ſo fine as to paſs for gems of the firſt order, especially for the emerald. In the ſemitranſparent ſchorls there are likewiſe ſome of great beauty, as the ruby-coloured, lately diſcovered in Siberia by counſellor Her. man, in a bed of reddiſh argilla, mixed with fragments of felt ſpath, quartz, and mica, on a low granite mountain. The bed of argilla is evidently produced by the decompoſition of granite; which operation Herman ſuppoſes muſt have ſet at liberty the ruby ſchorl formerly pent up in the chinks or fiſſures of the decompoſed part of the mountain. The diſcovery is quite new, no ſuch ſpecies being before known, as it is as hard as the firſt order of precious ſtones, the diamond excepted, takeſ a fine poliſh, and equals in colour the oriental ruby, though not in tranſparency.</p><p>Its ſtructure is made up of fine cylindric columns, like needles collected into bundles or treſſes, lying one on another in different directions, whilſt each individual column is made up of fine plates or laminæ, like the gems. It is fuſible <hi rend="italic">per ſe</hi> into a white tranſparent glaſs, and melts imperfectly with borax when calcined, as it does with microcoſmic ſalt and mineral alkali, into a ſmall vitreous globe, with little ſpots of a white enamel colour. Acids have no effect upon it, even when calcined. Laſtly, it loſes its colour in the fire, after having firſt turned blue. The mother of emeralds is likewiſe a ſemitranſparent ſchorl, in the opinion of ſome able naturaliſts, although Mr Born aſſerts it to be a jade, we know not upon what authority.</p><p>The ſtructure of the ſemitranſparent ſchorls, and ſome of the tranſparent that are not ſo perfectly diaphanous as to conceal their texture, is obſcurely ſparry; but that of the opaque is either filamentous, like aſbeſtos, or hard and brittle like threads of glaſs, or it is compoſed of ſcales. Of this laſt kind is that called <hi rend="italic">horn blend,</hi> which is generally green or black; but there is a beautiful variety of it found on the mount St Gothard, in Switzerland, of a fine ſky-blue colour covered with ſilver talk. Bar ſchorl has been found on the Carpathian mountains chryſtallized in priſms. Lapis crucifer, or the croſs ſtone, is found ſometimes near Brazil in Switzerland, and there named Tauffstein, or chriſtening ſtone; but oftener at Thum in Saxony, and therefore named there Thurnſtein. It is a ſchorl in form of a croſs: that of Brazil conſiſts of two hexagonal chryſtals. The exact cryſtallization of the other is unknown to us.</p><p>Moſt countries produce ſchorls. Ruſſia is particularly rich in ſchorls. It is even difficult to point out all the different places of the empire which produce them; but we ſhall take notice of thoſe moſt remarkable, particularly new diſcoveries. The ruby-coloured ſchorl mentioned above was found by Mr Herman at Sara- poulſky, a village in the government of Perm, ten verſts from Mourſinſky Slabode, in Siberia. The Siberian inſpector, Mr Laxman, has lately diſcovered in the mountain Alpeſtria, on the river Sleudenka near the lake Baikal, the following new ſchorls. Firſt, a green tranſparent ſchorl, of ſo brittle a nature as not to bear carriage without breaking into ſmall pieces truncated. Pallas is poſitive in declaring this dark green ſchorl a hyacinth. This laſt has often ſome of the ſmall yellowiſh white garnets flicking in it, deſcribed in the arti-<pb facs="gri_33125011196389_0710.tif" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0704"/>
cle <hi rend="smallcaps">Garnet,</hi> where an account will be found of the ſpecies of matrix that contains them all. Schorls are likewiſe found in the mountains and mines of Niſelga, Kraſnavolok, and Sondala, as likewiſe between the Onega Lake and White Sea. Black ſchorl is likewiſe found near the White Sea, and in the Altai, Ural, and Daurian mountains.</p><p>None of the tranſparent ſchorls have been found in Scotland as far as we have heard; but many varieties of the opake kinds have been found in various places, particularly in the iſland of Arran, where there is a bed of greeniſh horn-like ſchorl of immenſe extent near the harbour of Lamlaſh.</p><p>Fine ſpecimens of ſchorl are dear; the ruby ſchorl from Siberia, 25 to 50 rubles a ring ſtone; the green, when fine, from 15 to 30. The high price of the ruby ſchorl is owing to its novelty and rarity; and of the green, is owing to its paſſing for an emerald. The ſpeciſic gravity of ſchorl is 3,6.</p></div></body></text></TEI>