<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196389_0681.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0675-06" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SAUNDERSON</label>
(Dr Robert), an eminent caſuiſt, was born at Rotherham in Yorkſhire on the 19th September 1587, and was deſcended oſ an ancient fa-</p><p>mily. He attended the grammar-ſchool at Rotherham, where he made ſuch wonderful proficiency in the languages, that at 13 it was judged proper to ſend him to Lincoln college, Oxford. In 1608 he was appointed logic reader in the ſame college. He took orders in 1611, and was promoted ſucceſſively to ſeveral benefices. Archbiſhop Laud recommended him to king Charles I. as a profound caſuiſt; and that monarch, who ſeems to have been a great admirer of caſuiſtical learning, appointed him one of his chaplains in 1631. Charles propoſed ſeveral cafes of confidence to him, and received ſo great ſatisfaction from his anſwers, that at the end of his month’s attendance he told him, that he would wait with impatience during the intervening 11 months, as he was reſolved to be more intimately acquainted with him, when it would again be his turn to officiate. The king regularly attended his ſermons, and was wont to fay, that “he carried his ears to hear other preachers, but his conſcience to hear Mr Saunderſon.”</p><p>In 1642 Charles created him regius profeſſor of divinity at Oxford, with the canonry of Chriſt church annexed: but the civil wars prevented him till 1646 from entering on the office; and in 1648 he was ejected by the viſitors which the parliament had commiſſioned. He muſt have flood high in the public opinion; for in the ſame year in which he was appointed profeſſor of divinity, both houſes of parliament recommended him to the king as one of their truſtees for ſettling the affairs of the church. The king, too, repoſed great confidence in his judgment, and frequently conſulted him about the ſtate of his affairs. When the parliament propoſed the abolition of the epiſcopal form of church-government as incompatible with monarchy, Charles deſired him to take the ſubject under his conſideration and deliver his opinion. He accordingly wrote a treatiſe entitled, Epiſcopacy as eſtabliſhed by law in England not prejudicial to regal power. At taking leave, the king adviſed him to publiſh Cafes of Conſcience: he replied, that “he was now grown old and unfit to write caſes of conſcience.” The king ſaid, “it was the ſimpleſt thing he ever had heard from him; for no young man was fit to be a judge, or write caſes oſ conſcience.” Walton, who wrote the life of Dr Saunderſon, informs us, that in one of theſe conferences the king told him (Dr Saunderſon), or one of the reſt who was then in company, that “the remembrance of two errors did much affect him; which were his aſſent to the earl of Strafford’s death, and the aboliſhing of epiſcopacy in Scotland; and that if God ever reſtored him to the peaceable poſſeſſion of his crown, he would prove his repentance by a public confeſſion and a voluntary penance, by walking barefoot from the Tower of London, or Whitehall, to St Paul’s church, and would deſire the people to intercede with God for his pardon.”</p><p>Dr Saunderſon was taken priſoner by the parliament’s troops and conveyed to Lincoln, in order to procure in exchange a Puritan divine named <hi rend="italic">Clark,</hi> whom the king’s army had taken. The exchange was agreed to, on condition that Dr Saunderſon’s living ſhould be reſtored, and his perſon and property remain unmoleſted. The firſt of theſe demands was readily complied with: and a ſtipulation was made, that the ſecond ſhould be obſerved; but it was impoſſible to reſtrain the licentiouſneſs of the ſoldiers. They entered<pb facs="gri_33125011196389_0682.tif" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0676"/>
his church in the time of divine ſervice, interrupted him when reading prayers, and even had the audacity to take the common prayer book from him, and to tear it to pieces.</p><p>The Honourable Mr Boyle, having read a work of Dr Saunderſon’s entitled <hi rend="italic">De juramenti obligatione,</hi> was ſo much pleaſed, that he inquired at Biſhop Barlow, whether he thought it was poſſible to prevail on the author to write Caſes of Confidence, if an honorary penſion was aſſigned him to enable him to purchaſe books, and pay an amanuenſis. Saunderſon told Barlow, “that if any future tract of his could be of any uſe to mankind, he would cheerfully fit about it without a penſion.” Boyle, however, ſent him a preſent of 50l, ſenſible no doubt, that, like the other royaliſts, his finances could not be great. Upon this Saunderſon publiſhed his book <hi rend="italic">De Conſcientia.</hi></p><p>When Charles II. was reinſtated in the throne, he recovered his profeſſorſhip and canonry, and ſoon after was promoted to the biſhopric of Lincoln. During the two years and a half in which he poſſeſſed this new office, he ſpent a conſiderable ſum in augmenting poor vicarages, in repairing the palace at Bugden, &amp;c. He died January 29. 1662-3, in his 76th year.</p><p>He was a man of great acuteneſs and ſolid judgment. “That ſtaid and well-weighed man Dr Saunderſon (ſays Dr Hammond) conceives all things deliberately, dwells upon them diſcreetly, diſcerns things that differ exactly, paſſeth his judgment rationally, and expreſſes it aptly, clearly, and honeſtly.” Being aſked, what books he had read moſt? he replied, that "he did not read many books, but thoſe which he did read were well choſen and frequently peruſed.” Theſe, he ſaid, were chiefly three, Ariſtotle’s Rhetoric, Aquinas’s <hi rend="italic">Secunda Secunda,</hi> and Tully’s Works; eſpecially his Offices, which he had not read over leſs than 20 times, and could even, in his old age, recite without book.” He added, that “the learned civilian Dr Zouch had written <hi rend="italic">Elementa juris prudentia,</hi> which he thought he could alſo ſay without book, and that no wife man could read it too often.” He was not only converſant with the fathers and ſchoolmen, with caſuiſtical and controverſial divinity; but he was well acquainted with all the hiſtories of the Engliſh nation, was a great antiquary, had ſearched minutely into records, and was well ſkilled in heraldry and genealogy.</p><p>It will now be proper to give a ſhort account of his works. 1. In 1615 he publiſhed <hi rend="italic">Logica Artis Compendium,</hi> which was the ſyſtem of lectures he had delivered in the Univerſity when he was logic-reader. 2. Sermons, amounting in number to 36, printed in 1681, folio, with the author’s life by Walton. 3. Nine Cafes of Conſcience reſolved; firſt collected in one volume, in 1678, 8vo. 4. <hi rend="italic">De juramenti obligatione.</hi> This book was tranſlated into Engliſh by Charles I. while a priſoner in the Iſle of Wight, and printed at London in 1665, 8vo. 5. <hi rend="italic">De Obligatione conſcientiae.</hi> 6. Cenſure of Mr Antony Aſcham his book of the confuſions and revolutions of government. 7. <hi rend="italic">Pax Eccleſiae</hi> concerning Predeſtination, or the five points. 8. Epiſcopacy, as eſtabliſhed by law in England, not prejudicial to the regal power, in 1661. Besides theſe, he wrote two Diſcourſes in defence of Uſher’s writings.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Saunderson</hi> (Dr Nicolas), was born at Thurlſtone in Yorkſhire in 1682, and may be conſidered as a prodigy for his application and ſucceſs in mathematical literature in circumſtances apparently the moſt unfavourable. He loſt his ſight by the ſmall-pox before he was a year old. But this diſaſter did not prevent him from ſearching after that knowledge for which nature had given him ſo ardent a deſire. He was initiated into the Greek and Roman authors at a free-ſchool at Pennifton. After ſpending ſome years in the ſtudy of the languages, his father (who had a place in the exciſe) began to teach him the common rules of arithmetic. He ſoon ſurpaſſed his father; and could make long and difficult calculations, without having any ſenſible marks to aſſiſt his memory. At 18 he was taught the principles of algebra and geometry by Richard West of Undoorbank, Eſq; who, though a gentleman of fortune, yet, being ſtrongly attached to mathematical learning, readily undertook the education of ſo uncommon a genius. Saunderſon was alſo aſſiſted in his mathematical ſtudies by Dr Nettleton. Theſe two gentlemen read books to him and explained them. He was next ſent to a private academy at Attercliff near Sheffield, where logic and metaphyſics were chiefly taught. But theſe ſciences not ſuiting his turn of mind, he ſoon left the academy. He lived ſor ſome time in the country without any inſtructor; but ſuch was the vigour of his own mind, that few inſtructions were neceſſary: he only required books and a reader.</p><p>His father, beſides the place he had in the exciſe, poſſeſſed alſo a ſmall eſtate; but having a numerous family to ſupport, he was unable to give him a liberal education at one of the univerſities. Some of his friends, who had remarked his perſpicuous and intereſting manner of communicating his ideas, propoſed that he ſhould attend the univerſity of Cambridge as a teacher of mathematics. This propoſal was immediately put in execution; and he was accordingly conducted to Cambridge in his 25th year by Mr Joſhua Dunn, a fellow- commoner of Chriſt’s college. Though he was not received as a member of the college, he was treated with great attention and reſpect. He was allowed a chamber, and had free acceſs to the library. Mr Whiſton was at that time profeſſor of mathematics; and as he read lectures in the way that Saunderſon intended, it was naturally to be ſuppoſed he would view his project as an invaſion of his office. But, inſtead of meditating any oppoſition, the plan was no ſooner mentioned to him than he gave his conſent. Saunderſon’s reputation was ſoon ſpread through the univerſity. When his lectures were announced, a general curioſity was excited to hear ſuch intricate mathematical ſubjects explained by a man who had been blind from his infancy. The ſubject of his lectures was the <hi rend="italic">Principia Mathematica,</hi> the Optics, and <hi rend="italic">Arithmetica Univerſalis</hi> of Sir Iſaac. Newton. He was accordingly attended by a very numerous audience. It will appear at firſt incredible to many that a blind man ſhould be capable of explaining optics, which requires an accurate knowledge of the nature of light and colours; but we muſt recollect, that the theory of viſion is taught entirely by lines, and. is ſubject to the rules of geometry.</p><p>While thus employed in explaining the principles of the Newtonian philoſophy, he became known to its illuſtrious author. He was alſo intimately acquainted with Halley, Cotes, De Moivre, and other eminent mathematicians. When Whiſton was removed from his<pb facs="gri_33125011196389_0683.tif" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0677"/>
profeſſorſhip, Saunderſon was univerſally allowed to be the man beſt qualified for the ſucceſſion. But to enjoy this office, it was neceſſary, as the ſtatutes direct, that he ſhould be promoted to a degree. To obtain this privilege the heads of the univerſity applied to their chancellor the duke of Somerſet, who procured the royal mandate to confer upon him the degree of maſter of arts. He was then elected Lucaſian profeſſor of mathematics in November 1711. His inauguration ſpeech was compoſed in claſſical Latin, and in the ſtyle of Cicero, with whoſe works he had been much converſant. He now devoted his whole time to his lectures, and the inſtruction of his pupils. When George II. in 1728, viſited the Univerſity of Cambridge, he expreſſed a deſire to fee Profeſſor Saunderſon. In compliance with this deſire, he waited upon his majeſty in the ſenate-houſe, and was there, by the king’s command, created doctor of laws. He was admitted a member of the Royal Society in 1736.</p><p>Saunderſon was naturally of a vigorous conſtitution; but having confined himſelf to a ſedentary life, he at length became ſcorbutic. For ſeveral years he felt a numbneſs in his limbs, which, in the ſpring of 1739, brought on a mortification in his foot; and, unfortunately, his blood was ſo vitiated by the ſcurvy, that aſſiſtance from medicine was not to be expected. When he was informed that his death was near, he remained for a little ſpace calm and ſilent; but he ſoon recovered his former vivacity, and converted with his uſual eaſe. He died on the 19th of April 1739, in the 57th year of his age, and was buried at his own requeſt in the chancel at Boxworth.</p><p>He married the daughter of the reverend Mr Dickens, rector of Boxworth, in Cambridgeſhire, and by her had a ſon and daughter.</p><p>Dr Saunderſon was rather to be admired as a man of wonderful genius and aſſiduity, than to be loved for amiable qualities. He ſpoke his ſentiments freely of characters, and praiſed or condemned his friends as well as his enemies without reſerve. This has been aſcribed by ſome to a love of defamation; but perhaps with more propriety it has been attributed by others to an inflexible love of truth, which urged him upon all occaſions to ſpeak the ſentiments of his mind without diſguiſe, and without conſidering whether this conduct would pleaſe or give offence. His ſentiments were ſuppoſed unfavourable to revealed religion. It is ſaid, that he alleged he could not know God, becauſe he was blind, and could not ſee his works; and that, upon this, Dr Holmes replied, “Lay your hand upon yourſelf, and the organization which you will feel in your own body will diſſipate ſo groſs an error.” On the other hand, we are informed, that he had deſired the ſacrament to be given him on the evening before his death. He was, however, ſeized with a delirium, which rendered this impoſſible.</p><p>He wrote a ſyſtem of algebra, which was publiſhed, in 2 volumes 4t0, at London, after his death, in the year 1740, at the expence of the Univerſity of Cambridge.</p><p>Dr Saunderſon invented for his own uſe a Palpable Arithmetic; that is, a method of performing operations in arithmetic ſolely by the ſenſe of touch. It conſiſted of a table railed upon a ſmall frame, ſo that he could apply his hands with equal eaſe above and below. On this table were drawn a great number of parallel lines which were croſſed by others at right angles; the edges of the table were divided by notches half an inch diſtant from one another, and between each notch there were five parallels; ſo that every ſquare inch was divided into a hundred little ſquares. At each angle of the ſquares where the parallels interſected one another, a hole was made quite through the table. In each hole he placed two pins, a big and a ſmall one. It was by the various arrangements of the pins that Saunderſon performed his operations. A deſcription of this method of making calculations by his table is given under the article <hi rend="smallcaps">BLIND,</hi> n⁰ 38, though it is there by miſtake ſaid that it was not of his own invention.</p><p>His ſenſe of touch was ſo perfect, that he could diſcover with the greateſt exactneſs the ſlighteſt inequality of ſurface, and could diſtinguiſh in the moſt finiſhed works the ſmalleſt overſight in the poliſh. In the cabinet of medals at Cambridge he could ſingle out the Roman medals with the utmoſt correctneſs; he could alſo perceive the ſlighteſt variation in the atmoſphere. One day, while ſome gentlemen were making obſervations on the ſun, he took notice of every little cloud that paſſed over the ſun which could interrupt their labours. When any object paſſed before his face, even though at ſome diſtance, he diſcovered it, and could gueſs its ſize with conſiderable accuracy. When he walked, he knew when he paſſed by a tree, a wall, or a houſe. He made theſe diſtinctions from the different ways his face was affected by the motion of the air.</p><p>His muſical ear was remarkably acute; he could diſtinguiſh accurately to the fifth of a note. In his youth he had been a performer on the flute; and he had made ſuch proficiency, that if he had cultivated his talents in this way, he would probably have been as eminent in muſic as he was in mathematics. He recognized not only his friends, but even thoſe with whom he was ſlightly acquainted, by the tone of their voice; and he could judge with wonderful exactneſs of the ſize of any apartment into which he was conducted.</p></div></body></text></TEI>