<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196389_0665.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0659-03" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SARDINIA</label>,
an iſland of the Mediterranean, bounded by the ſtrait which divides it from Corſica on the north; by the Tulcan ſea, which flows between this iſland and Italy, on the eaſt; and by other parts of the Mediterranean ſea on the ſouth and weft.<note anchored="false" n="1" place="margin" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">Sutherland's Tour up the Straits.</hi></p></note> It is about 140 miles in length and 70 in breadth, and contains 420, 000 inhabitants. The revenue ariſes chiefly from a duty upon ſalt, and is barely ſufficient to defray the expences of government; but it certainly might be conſiderably augmented, as the foil produces wine, corn, and oil, in abundance. Moſt of the ſalt that is exported is taken by the Danes and Swedes; the Engliſh formerly took great quantities for Newfoundland, but having found it more convenient to procure it from Spain and Portugal, they now take little or none. A profitable tunny fiſhery is carried on at the ſouth-weſt part of the iſland, but it is monopolized by the Duke de St Pierre, and a few more people, who happen to be proprietors of the adjoining land. Wild boars abound in the hilly parts of the iſland, and here are ſome few deer, not ſo large as thoſe in Britain, but in colour and make exactly the ſame. Beeves and ſheep are alſo common, as well as horſes.</p><p>The feudal ſyſtem ſtill ſubſiſts in a limited degree, and titles go with their eſtates, ſo that the purchaſer of the latter inherits the former. The regular troops ſeldom exceed 2000 men; but the militia amount to near 26, 000, of whom 11, 000 are cavalry. Their horſes are ſmall, but uncommonly active. In a charge, we ſhould beat them: but, on a march, they would be ſuperior to us. The country people are generally armed; but notwithſtanding their having been ſo long under the Spaniſh and Italian government, aſſaſſinations are by no means frequent; and yet by the laws of the country, if a man ſtabs another without premeditated malice, with in four hours after quarrelling with him, he is not liable to be hanged. On the other hand, the church affords no protection to the guilty. The Sardinians are not at all bigoted; and, next to the Spaniards, the Engliſh are their favourites. The whole iſland is ſubject to the Duke of Savoy, who enjoys the title of king of Sardinia. See <hi rend="smallcaps">CAGLIARI</hi></p><p>There is in this iſland a pleaſing variety of hills and valleys, and the foil is generally fruitful; but the inhabitants are a ſlothful generation, and cultivate but a little part of it. On the coaſt there is a fiſhery of anchovies and coral, of which they ſend large quantities to Genoa and Leghorn. This iſland is divided into two parts; the one, called <hi rend="italic">Capo-di-Cagliari</hi> lies to the ſouth; and the other <hi rend="italic">Capο-di Lugary,</hi> which is leated to the north. The principal towns are Cagliari the capital, Oriſtagno, and Saſſari.</p> </div> </body>
</text></TEI>