<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:19:11Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>raccioli, in the year 1784. The government of this nobleman was very beneficial to Sicily, as he, in a great meaſure, cleared the island of the banditti that uſed to infeſt it, and made ſeveral excellent regulations for the eſtabliſhment of ſocial order and perſonal ſecurity. He deserves the thanks of every well-wiſher to mankind for Waving aboliſhed the court of inquiſition, which had been eſtabliſhed in this country by Ferdinand the Catholic, and made dependent on the authority of the grand inquiſitor of Spain. Its laſt <hi rend="italic">auto da fe</hi> was held in the year 1724, when two perſons were burned. At length Charles III. rendered it independent of the Spaniſh inquiſitor, and abridged its power, by forbidding it to make uſe of the torture, and to inflict public punishments. The Marcheſe Squillace, and his ſucceſſor the Marcheſe Tanucci, were both enemies to the hierarchy; and, during their viceroyalties, took care to appoint ſenſible and liberal men to the office of inquiſitor : the laſt of whom was Ventimiglia, a man of a moſt humane and amiable character, who heartily wiſhed for the abolition of this diabolical court, and readily contributed toward it. While he held the office of inquiſitor, he always endeavoured to procure the acquittal of the accuſed; and when he could ſuceed no other way, would pretend ſome informality in the trial. The total annihilation of this  inſtrument of the worſt of tyranny was reſerved for Caraccioli. A prieſt being accuſed to the inquiſition, was dragged out of his houſe and thrown into the dungeon. He was condemned; but, on account of informality, and a violation of juſtice in the trial, he appealed to the viceroy, who appointed a committee of juriſts to examine the proceſs. The inquiſitor refuſed to acknowledge the authority of this commiſſion ; pretending that to expoſe the ſecrets of the holy office, and to ſubmit its deciſions to the examination of lay judges, would be ſo inconsiſtent with his duty, that he would see the inquiſition aboliſhed rather than consent to it. Caraccioli took him at his word, and procured a royal mandate by which the holy office was at once annihilated. He aſſembled all the nobility, judges, and biſhops, on the 27th of March 1782, in the palace of the inquiſition, and commanded the king’s order to be read ; after which he took poſſession of the archives, and cauſed all the prisons to be ſet open : in theſe were at that time only two priſoners, who had been condemned to perpetual confinement for witchcraft. The papers relating to the finances were preſerved ; but all the rest were publicly burned. The poſſeſſions of the holy office were aſſigned to the uſe of churches and charitable inſtitutions : but the officers then belonging to it retained their ſalaries during their lives. The palace itſelf is converted into a cuſtomhouſe, and the place where heretics were formerly roaſted alive for the honour of the Catholic faith, is now changed into a public garden. The cognizance of offences against orthodoxy is committed to the biſhops : but they cannot cite any one to appear before them without permiſſion from the viceroy ; neither can they confine any perſon to a ſolſtary priſon, nor deny him the privilege of writing to his friends, and converſing freely with his advocate. The nobility are ſo numerous in this iſland, that Labat ſays it is paved with noblemen. The general aſſembly of parliament is compoſed of 66 archbiſhops, biſhops, abbots, and priors, which form the Bracchio eccleſiaſtico.</p><p>Fifty-eight princes, 27 dukes, 37 marquisses, 27 counts, 1 viſcount, and 79 barons, form the militaire ; and the demaniale conſiſts of 43 repreſentatives of free towns. Out of each bracchio four deputies are choſen to conduct public buſineſs. But the viceroy, the prince of Butera, and the prætor of Palermo, are always the three firſt. <hi rend="italic">N. B.</hi> There are many titled perſons that have no ſeat in the aſſembly, viz. 62 princes, 55 dukes, 87 marquiſſes, 1 count, and 282 other feudatories. There are three archbiſhoprics and ſeven bishoprics ; and the iſland, ever ſince it was conquered by the Saracens, has been divided into three parts or valleys ; namely, the V<hi rend="italic">al di Demons, Pal di Noto,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Pal di Mazzara.</hi></p><p>SICINNIUS (Dentatus), a tribune of the people, lived a little after the expulsion of the kings from Rome. He was in 120 battles and skirmiſhes, beſides ſingle combats, in all of which he came off conqueror. He ſerved under nine generals, all of whom triumphed by his means. In theſe battles he received 45 wounds in the fore-part of his body, and not one in his back. The ſenate made him great preſents, and he was honoured with the name of the Roman Achilles.</p><p>SICYOS, in botany : A genus of plants belonging to the claſs of moncecia, and to the order of ſyngeneſia ; and in the natural ſyſtem arranged under the 34th order, <hi rend="italic">Cucurbitaceœ.</hi> The male flowers have their calyx quinquedentated, their corolla quinquepartite, and there are three filaments. The female flowers have their calyx and corolla ſimilar ; but their ſtyle is trifid, and their drupa monoſpermous. There are three ſpecies, the <hi rend="italic">angulata, laciniata, and garcini,</hi> which are all foreign plants.</p><p>SIDA, Y<hi rend="italic">ellow</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Indian </hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Mallow,</hi> in botany : A genus of plants belonging to the claſs of monadelphia, and to the order of polyandria ; and in the natural ſyſtem ranging under the 37th order, <hi rend="italic">Columniferae.</hi> The calyx is simple and angulated ; the ſtyle is divided into many parts ; there are ſeveral capſules, each containing one feed. T here are 27 ſpecies. 1. The Spinoſa ; 2. Anguſtifolia; 3. Alba; 4. Rhombiſolia ; 5. Alnifolia ; 6. Ciliaris ; 7. Retuſa ; 8. Triquetra ; 9. Jamaicenſis ; 10. Carpinifolia ; 11.Viſcoſa; 12. Cordifolia; 13. Umbellatæ; 14. Paniculata ; 15. Atroſanguinea ; 16. Periplocifolia; 17. Urens; 18. Arborea; 19. Occidentalis ; 20. Americana; 21. Abutilon ; 22. Mauritiana ; 23. Asiatica ; 24. Indica ; 25. Criſpa ; 26. Criſtata; 27. Ternata. The firſt 18 ſpecies have 17 capſules ; the rest are multicapſular. They are all natives of warm climates ; and moſt of them are found in the Eaſt or West Indies.</p><p>The Chineſe make cords of the ſida abutilon. This plant loves water, and may be advantageouſly planted in marſhes and ditches, where nothing elſe will grow. From experiments made by the Abbé Cavanilles, a Spaniard, which are inſerted in the <hi rend="italic">Mem. de l'Acad. Royale, </hi>it appears that the plants ſucceed beſt when ſown in May, and they arrive at perfection in three months and a half. The maceration of the ſmaller ſtalks is finiſhed in about 15 days; of the larger in a month. The ſtrength and goodneſs of the thread appeared to be in proportion to the perfection of the vegetation, and to the diſtance the plant was kept at from other plants. The fibres lie in ſtrata, of which there are sometimes ſix : they are not quite ſtraight, but preſerve an undulating direction, ſo as to form a network in their natu-</p></body></text></TEI>