<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:21:45Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>which we do not underſtand, is heated uniformly to the 48th degree of Fahrenheit’s thermometer. This degree of heat is greater than that in which the watery juices of vegetables freeze, and it is propagated from the inward parts of the earth to the ſurface, on which the vegetables grow. The atmoſphere being variably heated by the action of the fun in different climates, and in the ſame climate at different ſeaſons, communicates to the ſurface of the earth and to ſome diſtance below it the degree of heat or cold which prevails in itſelf. Different vegetables are able to preſerve life under different degrees of cold, but all of them periſh when the cold which reaches their roots is extreme. Providence has therefore, in the coldeſt climates, provided a covering of ſnow for the roots of vegetables, by which they are protected from the influence of the atmoſpherical cold. The ſnow keeps in the internal heat of the earth, which ſurrounds the roots of vegetables, and defends them from the cold of the atmoſphere.</p><p>Snow or ice water is always deprived oſ its fixed air, which eſcapes during the proceſs of congelation. Accordingly, as ſome of the inhabitants of the Alps who uſe it for their conſtant drink have enormous wens upon their throats, it has been aſcribed to this circumſtance. If this were the cauſe of theſe wens, it would be eaſy to remove it by exposing the ſnow-water to the air for ſome time. But ſeveral eminent phyſicians have rejected the notion that ſnow-water is the cauſe of theſe wens ; for in Greenland, where ſnow-water is commonly uſed, the inhabitants are not affected with ſuch ſwellings : on the other hand, they are common in Sumatra where ſnow is never ſeen.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Snow,</hi> in ſea-affairs, is generally the largeſt of all two- maſted vessels employed by Europeans, and the moſt convenient for navigation.</p><p>The ſails and rigging on the mainmaſt and fqremaſt of a ſnow are exactly ſimilar to thoſe on the ſame marts in a ſhip ; only that there is a ſmall maſt behind the mainmaſt of the former, which carries a ſail nearly reſembling the mizen of a ſhip. The foot of this maſt is fixed on a block of wood on the quarter-deck abaft the mainmaſt ; and the head of it is attached to the aftertop of the maintop. The ſail which is called the <hi rend="italic">try- ſail</hi> is extended from its maſt towards the ſtern of the veſſel.</p><p>When the sloops of war are rigged as ſnows, they are furniſhed with a horſe, which anſwers the purpoſe of the tryſail-maſt, the fore-part of the sail being attached by rings to the ſaid horſe, in different places of its height.</p><p><hi rend="italic">SNOW-Grotto,</hi> an excavation made by the waters on the ſide of Mount Etna, by making their way under the layers of lava, and by carrying away the bed of pozzolana below them. It occurred to the proprietor, that this place was very ſuitable for a magazine of ſnow : for in Sicily, at Naples, and particularly at Malta, they are obliged for want of ice to make uſe of ſnow for cooling their wine, ſherbet, and other liquors, and for making ſweetmeats.</p><p>This grotto was hired or bought by the knights of Malta, who having neither ice nor ſnow on the burning rock which they inhabit, have hired ſeveral caverns on Etna, into which people whom they employ collect and preſerve quantities of ſnow to be ſent to Malta when needed. This grotto has therefore been repaired with</p><p>in at the expence oſ that order ; flights of ſteps are cut into it, as well as two openings from above, by which they throw in the ſnow, and through which the grotto is enlightened. Above the grotto they have alſo levelled a piece oſ ground of conſiderable extent : this they have incloſed with thick and lofty walls, ſo that when the winds, which at this elevation blow with great violence, carry the ſnow from the higher parts of the mountain, and depoſite it in this incloſure, it is retained and amassed by the walls. The people then remove it into the grotto through the two openings ; and it is there laid up, and preſerved in ſuch a manner as to refill the force of the ſummer heats ; as the layers of lava with which the grotto is arched above prevent them from making any impreſſion.</p><p>When the ſeaſon for exporting the ſnow comes on, it is put into large bags, into which it is preſſed as cloſely as poſſible ; it is then carried by men out of the grotto, and laid upon mules, which convey it to the ſhore, where ſmall vessels are waiting to carry it away.</p><p>But before thoſe lumps of ſnow are put into bags, they are wrapped in freſh leaves ; ſo that while they are conveyed from the grotto to the ſhore, the leaves may prevent the rays of the ſun from making any impreſſion upon them.</p><p>The Sicilians carry on a conſiderable trade in ſnow, which affords employment to ſome thouſands of mules, horſes, and men. They have magazines of it on the ſummits of their loftiest mountains, from which they diſtribute it through all their cities, towns, and houſes ; for every perſon in the iſland makes uſe of ſnow. They conſider the practice of cooling their liquors as abſolutely neceſſary for the preſervation of health ; and in a climate the heat of which is conſtantly relaxing the fibres, cooling liquors, by communicating a proper tone to the fibres of the ſtomach, muſt greatly ſtrengthen them for the performance of their functions.</p><p>In this climate a ſcarcity of ſnow is no leſs dreaded than a ſcarcity of corn, wine, or oil. We are informed by a gentleman who was at Syracuſe in the year 177<hi rend="smallcaps">7,</hi> when there was a ſcarcity of ſnow, the people of the town learned that a ſmall veſſel loaded with that article was paſſing the coaſt : without a moment’s deliberation they ran in a body to the ſhore and demanded her cargo ; which when the crew refuſed to deliver up, the Syracuſans attacked and took, though with the loſs of ſeveral men.</p><p><hi rend="italic">SNOW-Drοp,</hi> in botany. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Chionanthus.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">SNOWDON-hill,</hi> the name of a mountain in Caernarvonſhire in Wales, generally thought to be the higheſt in Britain ; though ſome have been of opinion that its height is equalled, or even exceeded, by mountains in the Highlands of Scotland. The mountain is ſurrounded by many others, called in the Welſh language <hi rend="italic">Crib Coch, Crib y Distill, Lliweddy yr Arran,</hi> &amp;c.</p><p>According to Mr Pennant@@*, this mountainous tract yields ſcarcely any corn. Its produce is cattle and ſheep; which, during ſummer, keep very high in the mountains, followed by their owners with their families, who reside during that ſeaſon in <hi rend="italic">havοdtys,</hi> or “ ſummer dairy- houſes,” as the ſarmers in the Swiſs Alps do in their <hi rend="italic">ſennes.</hi> Theſe houſes conſiſt of a long low room, with a hole at one end to let out the ſmoke from the fire which is made beneath. Their furniture is very ſimpſe; ſtones are ſubſtituted for stools, and their beds are of</p><p>@@@[m]* Journey to Snowden.</p></body></text></TEI>