<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-18T21:20:00Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>when loaded with their young, which cling to them. They are the prey of leopards and
                others of the feline race ; and of ſerpents, which purſue them to the ſummits of the
                trees, and ſwallow them entire. They are not carnivorous, but for miſchief’s ſake
                will rob the neſts of birds of the eggs and young. In the countries where they moſt
                abound, the ſagacity of the feathered tribe is more marvelouſly shown in their
                contrivances to fix the neſt beyond the reach of theſe invaders.</p>
            <p>The simiæ being more numerous in their ſpecies than any other animals, and differing
                greatly in their appearances, it ſeemed neceſſary to methodize and ſubdivide the
                genus. Accordingly Mr Ray firſt diſtributed them into three claſſes.</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Simiae,</hi> Apes, ſuch as wanted tails.</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Cercopitheci,</hi> Monkeys, ſuch as had tails.</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Papiones,</hi> Baboons, thoſe with ſhort tails ; to distinguiſh
                them from the common monkeys, which have very long ones.</p>
            <p>The principal marks by which the ſpecies of this genus are diſtinguiſhable from each
                other, are derived, 1st, from the tail, which is either long, ſhort, or altogether
                wanting, or is ſtraight, or prehenſile ; 2dly, from the buttocks, which are naked,
                and furniſhed with callosities, or are covered with hair ; 3dly, from the nails,
                which are flat and rounded like those of man, or ſharp pointed like the claws of
                beaſts in general ; 4thly, from the preſence or abſence of a beard on the chin ;
                and, 5thly, from the cheeks being provided with, or wanting, pouches in their under
                parts. For greater convenience, the ſpecies of this genus, which are very numerous,
                are arranged under five ſubordinate divisions, conſidered as distinct genera by ſome
                authors, and not without reason. Three of theſe ſubdiviſions were adopted by
                Linnaeus ; but Dr Gmelin, following Buffon, has added other two taken from the third
                diviſion of his great precursor. Theſe ſubdiviſions are the simi<hi rend="italic"
                    >ae, papiones, cercopitheci, ſapaji,</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                >ſagoini.</hi></p>
            <p>I. The <hi rend="smallcaps">Simiæ,</hi> or <hi rend="smallcaps">Apes.</hi> They have
                no tails. The viſage is flat ; the teeth, hands, fingers, feet, toes, and nails,
                reſemble thoſe of man, and they walk naturally erect. This diviſion includes the
                simiæ, or apes properly ſo called, which are not found in America.</p>
            <p>1. The chimpanzee, the ſimia troglodytes of Linnaeus, common in the mountains of
                Sierra Leona, reſembles man more than the orang-outang. This animal was firſt
                brought to Europe in 1738, when it was exhibited as a snow in London. The following
                deſcription of one that was kept ſome months at the colony of Sierra Leona is given
                by Wadſtrom, in his Eſſay on Colonization @@*. He was nearly two feet high ; but the
                full ſtature is nearly five feet. He was covered with black hair, long and thick on
                the back, but ſhort and thin on the breaſt and belly. His face was bare ; his hands
                and his head reſembled those of an old black man, except that the hair on his head
                was ſtraight. He ate, drank, slept, and sat at table, like a human being. At firſt
                he crept on all fours, on the outside of his hands ; but, when grown larger, he
                endeavoured to go erect, ſupporting himſelf by a ſtick. He was melancholy, but
                always good natured.</p>
            <p>2. The ſatyrus, orang-outang, or great ape, has a flat face, and a deformed
                reſemblance of the human ;</p>
            <p>ears like thoſe of a man ; the hair on the head longer than on the body. The body and
                limbs are</p>
            <p>covered with reddiſh and ſhaggy hair ; longeſt on the back, thinneſt on the
                fore-parts. The face and paws are swarthy ; the buttocks covered with hair. They
                inhabit the interior parts of Africa, the iſles of Sumatra, Borneo, and Java. Are
                ſolitary, and live in the moſt desert places. They grow to the height of six feet ;
                have prodigious ſtrength, and will overpower the ſtrongeſt man. The old ones are
                ſhot with arrows, the young alone can be taken alive. They live entirely on fruits
                and nuts. They will attack and kill the negroes who wander in the woods ; will drive
                away the elephants, and beat them with their fills or pieces of wood ; and will
                throw ſtones at people that offend them. They ſleep in trees ; and make a fort oſ
                ſhelter from the inclemency of the weather. They are of a grave appearance and
                melancholy diſposition, and even when young not inclined to frolic. They go erect,
                and are vaſtly ſwift and agile. Theſe accounts are chiefly taken from Andrew Battel,
                an Engliſh ſailor, who was taken priſoner 1589, and lived many years in the inner
                parts of Congo ; his narrative is plain, and ſeems very authentic. It is preſerved
                in Purchas’s collection. Froger @@* informs us, “ that thoſe along the banks of the
                river Ganges are larger and more miſchievous than in any part of Africa : the
                negroes dread them, and cannot travel alone in the country without running the
                hazard of being attacked by theſe animals, who often preſent them with a ſtick, and
                force them to fight. I have heard the Portugueſe ſay, that they have often ſeen them
                hoiſt up young girls, about ſeven or eight years old, into trees, and that they
                could not be wreſted from them without a great deal of difficulty. The moſt part of
                the negroes imagine them to be a foreign nation come to inhabit their country, and
                that they do not speak for fear of being compelled to work.” When taken young, they
                are capable of being tamed, and taught to perform many menial offices. Francis
                Pyrard @@* relates, “ that in the province of Sierra Leona, there is a ſpecies ſo
                ſtrong limbed, and ſo induſtrious, that, when properly trained and fed, they work
                like ſervants ; that they generally walk on the two hind feet ; that they pound any
                ſubſtances in a mortar ; that they go to bring water from the river in ſmall
                pitchers, which they carry full on their heads. But when they arrive at the door, if
                the pitchers are not ſoon taken off, they allow them to fall ; and when they
                perceive the pitchers overturned and broken, they weep and lament.” Father Jarric
                @@*, quoted by Nieremberg, ſays the ſame thing, nearly in the same terms. With
                regard to the education of theſe animals, the teſtimony of Shoutten @@* accords with
                that of Pyrard. “ They are taken (he remarks) with ſnares, taught to walk on their
                hind feet, and to uſe their fore feet as hands in performing different operations,
                as rinsing glaſſes, carrying drink round the company, turning a ſpit, &amp;c.” “ I
                saw at Java</p>
            <p>(ſays Guat @@*) a very extraordinary ape. It was a female. She was very tall, and
                often walked erect on her hind feet. On theſe oceasions, ſhe concealed with her
                hands the parts which diſtinguiſh the ſex. Except the eye-brows, there was no hair
                on her face, which pretty much reſembled the groteſque ſemale faces I ſaw among the
                Hottentots at the Cape. She made her bed very neatly every day, lay upon her side,
                and covered herſelf with the bed cloaths. When her head ached, ſhe bound it up with
                a handkerchieſ ; and it was amusing to ſee</p>
            <p>@@@*[m] Part ii. p. 273.</p>
            <p>@@@*[m] Descript. Historique du Royaume de Macacar, p. 51.</p>
            <p>@@@*[m] Voyages de Francois Pyrard, tom. ii. p. 331.</p>
            <p>@@@*[m] Eus. Nieremberg, Hist. Nat. Peregrin. lib. ix. cap. 45.</p>
            <p>@@@*[m] Voyages de Guat. Shout ten aux Indes Orientales.</p>
            <p>@@@*[m] Voyage de Fr. le Guat, tom. ii. p. 96.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
