<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:23:30Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>which he could immediately have procured by a letter to his generals.</p><p>The concern expreſſed by Henry and Francis for the calamity of their ally was more sincere. Alarmed at the progreſs of the imperial arms, they had, even before the taking of Rome, entered into a cloſer alliance, and agreed to invade the Low Countries with a powerful army ; but no ſooner did they hear of the Pope’s captivity, than they changed, by a new treaty, the ſcene of the projected war ſrom the Netherlands to Italy, and reſolved to take the moſt vigorous meaſures for reſtoring him to liberty. Henry, however, contributed only money. A French army entered Italy, under the command of Marſhal Lautrec ; Clement obtained his freedom ; and war was for a time carried on by the confederates with ſucceſs ; but the death of Lautrec, and the revolt of Andrew Doria, a Genoeſe admiral in the ſervice of France, entirely changed the face oſ affairs. The French army was utterly ruined ; and Francis, diſcouraged and almoſt exhauſted by so many unſucceſsful enterpriſes, began to think of peace, and of obtaining the releaſe of his ſons by conceſſions, not by the terror of his arms.</p><p>At the ſame time Charles, notwithſtanding the advantages he had gained, had many reaſons to wiſh for an accommodation. Sultan Solyman having over-run Hungary, was ready to break in upon the Auſtrian territories with the whole force of the Eaſt ; and the progreſs of the Reformation in Germany threatened the tranquillity of the empire. In conſequence of this situation of affairs, though pride made both parties conceal or diſſemble their real ſentiments, two ladies were permitted to reſtore peace to Europe. Margaret of Auſtria, Charles’s aunt, and Louiſa, Francis’s mother, met in 1529 at Cambray, and ſettled the terms of accommodation between the French king and the emperor. Francis agreed to pay two millions of crowns as the ranſom of his two ſons, to resign the ſovereignty oſ Flanders and Artois, and to forego all his Italian claims; and Charles ceaſed to demand the reſtitution of Burgundy.</p><p>All the ſteps of this negociation had been communicated to the king of England ; and Henry was, on that  occaſion, ſo generous to his friend and ally Francis, that he ſent him an acquittal of near six hundred thouſand crowns, in order to enable him to fulfil his agreement  with Charles. But Francis’s Italian confederates were leſs ſatisfied with the treaty of Cambray, They were almoſt wholly abandoned to the will of the emperor ; and ſeemed to have no other means of ſecurity leſt but his equity and moderation. Of theſe, from his paſt conduct, they had not formed the moſt advantageous idea. But Charles’s preſent circumſtances, more eſpecially in regard to the Turks, obliged him to behave with a generoſity inconſiſtent with his character. The Florentines alone, whom he reduced under the dominion of the family of Medici, had reaſon to complain of his ſeverity. Sforza obtained the inveſtiture of Milan and his pardon ; and every other power experienced the lenity of the conqueror.</p><p>After having received the imperial crown from the hands of the Pope at Bologna, Charles proceeded on his journey to Germany, where his preſence was become highly neceſſary ; for although the conduct and valour of his brother Ferdinand, on whom he had conferred</p><p>the hereditary dominions of the houſe of Auſtria, and who had been elected king of Hungary, had obliged Solyman to retire with infamy and loss, his return was to be feared, and the diſorders of religion were daily increasing ; an account of which, and of the emperor’s tranſactions with the Proteſtants. is given under the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Reformation.</hi></p><p>Charles having exerted himſelf as much as he could againſt the reformers, undertook his firſt expedition againſt the piratical ſtates of Africa. Barbary, or that part of the African continent lying along the coaſt of the Mediterranean ſea, was then nearly in the ſame condition which it is at preſent. Morocco, Algiers, and Tunis, were its principal ſtates ; and the two laſt were neſts oſ pirates. Barbaroſſa, a famous Corſair, had ſucceeded his brother in the kingdom of Algiers, which he had formerly aſſiſted him to uſurp. He regulated with much prudence the interior police of his kingdom, carried on his piracies with great vigour, and extended his conqueſts on the continent of Africa ; but perceiving that the natives ſubmitted to his government with impatience, and fearing that his continual depredations would one day draw upon him a general combination of the Chriſtian powers, he put his dominions under the protection of the grand ſeignior. Solyman, flattered by ſuch an act of ſubmiſſion, and charmed with the boldness of the man, offered him the command of the Turkiſh fleet. Proud of this diſtinction, Barbaroſſa repaired to Conſtantinople, and made uſe of his influence with the ſultan to extend his own dominion. Partly by force, partly by treachery, he uſurped the kingdom of Tunis; and being now poſſeſſed of greater power, he carried on his depredations againſt the Chriſtian ſtates with more deſtructive violence than ever.</p><p>Daily complaints of the piracies and ravages committed by the galleys of Barbaroſſa were brought to the emperor by his ſubjects, both in Spain and Italy ; and all Chriſtendom ſeemed to look up to him, as its greateſt and moſt fortunate prince, for relief from this new and odious ſpecies of oppreſſion. At the ſame time Muley-Haſcen, the exiled king of Tunis, finding none of the African princes able or willing to ſupport him in recovering his throne, applied to Charles for aſsiſtance againſt the uſurper. Equally desirous of delivering his dominions from the dangerous neighbourhood of Barbaroſſa, of appearing as the protector of an unfortunate prince, and of acquiring the glory annexed in that age to every expedition againſt the Mahometans, the emperor readily concluded a treaty with Muley Haſcen, and ſet ſail for Tunis with a formidable armament. The Goletta, a ſea port town, fortified with 300 pieces of cannon, was taken, together with all Barbaroſſa’s fleet : he was defeated in a pitched battle, and 10,000 Chriſtian ſlaves, having knocked off their fetters, and made themſelves maſters of the citadel, Tunis was preparing to ſurrender. But while Charles was deliberating on the conditions, his troops fearing that they would be deprived of the booty which they had expected, broke ſuddenly into the town, and pillaged and maſſacred without diſtinction. Thirty thouſand perſons periſhed by the ſword, and 10,000 were made priſoners. The ſceptre was reſtored to Muley Haſcen, on condition that he ſhould acknowledge himſelf a vaſſal of the crown of Spain, put into the emperor’s hands all the fortified sea-ports in the kingdom of  Tunis, and</p></body></text></TEI>