<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:21:17Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Theſe roots have ſcarce any ſmell or particular taſte: when freſh, they are ſaid to be ſomewhat acrid, but as brought to us they diſcover, even when long-chewed, no other than a flight unctuosity in the mouth. Boiled in water, they impart a reddiſh colour, and a kind of vapid ſoftneſs : the decoction when inſpiſſated yields an unctuous, farinaceous, almoſt inſipid maſs, amounting to upwards of half the weight of the root. They give a gold yellow tincture to rectified ſpirit, but make no ſenſible alteration in its taſte : on drawing off the ſpirit from the filtered liquor, there remains an orange-coloured extract, nearly as inſipid as that obtained by water, but ſcarcely in half its quantity.</p><p>China root is generally ſuppoſed to promote perſpiration and urine, and by its ſoft unctuous quality to blunt acrimonious humours. It was firſt introduced into Europe about the year 1535, with the character of a ſpecific againſt venereal diſorders : the patient was kept warm, a weak decoction of china root was uſed for common drink, and a stronger decoction taken twice a day in bed to promote a ſweat. Such a regimen is doubtleſs a good auxiliary to mercurial alteratives : but whatever may be its effects in the warmer climates, it is found in this to be of itſelf greatly inſufficient. At preſent the china root is very rarely made uſe of, having for ſome time given place to ſarſaparilla, which is ſuppoſed to be more effectual. Proſper Alpinus informs us, that this root is in great eſteem among the Egyptian women for procuring fatneſs and plumpness.</p><p>SMITH (Sir Thomas), was born at Walden in Eſſex in 1512. At 14 he was ſent to Queen’s college Cambridge, where he diſtinguiſhed himſelf ſo much, that he was made Henry VIII.’s ſcholar together with John Cheke. He was choſen a fellow of his college in 1531, and appointed two years after to read the public Greek lecture. The common mode of reading Greek at that time was very faulty ; the ſame found being given to the letters and diphthongs ι, η, υ, ει, οι, υι. Mr Smith and Mr Cheke had been for ſome time ſenſible that this pronunciation was wrong : and after a good deal of conſultation and reſearch, they agreed to introduce that mode of reading which prevails at preſent. Mr Smith was lecturing on Arist<hi rend="italic">otle de Republica</hi> in Greek. At firſt he dropped a word or two at intervals in the new pronunciation, and ſometimes he would stop as if he had committed a miſtake and correct himſelf. No notice was taken of this ſor two or three days ; but as he repeated more frequently, his audience began to wonder at the unuſual founds, and at laſt ſome oſ his friends mentioned to him what they had remarked. He owned that ſomething was in agitation, but that it was not yet ſufficiently digeſted to be made public. They entreated him earneſtly to diſcover his protect : he did ſo ; and in a ſhort time great numbers reſorted to him for information. The new pronunciation was adopted with enthuſiaſm, and ſoon became universal at Cambridge. It was afterwards oppoſed by biſhop Gardiner the chancellor ; but its superiority to the old mode was ſo viſible, that in a few years it spread over all England.</p><p>In 1539 he travelled into foreign countries, and ſtudied ſor ſome time in the univerſities of France and Italy. On his return he was made regius profeſſor of civil law at Cambridge. About this time he publiſhed a</p><p>treatiſe on the mode of pronouncing Engliſh. He was uſeful likewiſe in promoting the reformation. Having gone into the family of the duke of Somerſet, the protector during the minority of Edward VI. he was employed by that nobleman in public affairs ; and in 1548 was made ſecretary of ſtate, and received the honour of knighthood. While that nobleman continued in office, he was ſent ambaſſador, firſt to Brussels and afterwards to France.</p><p>Upon Mary’s acceſſion he loſt all his places, but was fortunate enough to preſerve the friendſhip of Gardiner and Bonner. He was exempted from perſecution, and was allowed, probably by their influence, a penſion of L. 100. During Elizabeth’s reign he was employed in public affairs, and was ſent three times by that princeſs as her ambaſſador to France. He died in 1577. His abilities were excellent, and his attainments uncommonly great : He was a ρhilosopher, a phyſician, a chemiſt, mathematician, linguiſt, hiſtorian, and architect. He wrote, 1. A treatiſe called the <hi rend="italic">Engliſh Commonwealth.</hi> 2. A letter <hi rend="italic">De Recta et Emendata Linguæ Graecae Pronunciatiοne.</hi> 3. <hi rend="italic">De Moribus Turcarum.</hi> 4. <hi rend="italic">De Druidum Moribus.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Smith</hi> (Edmund), a diſtinguiſhed Engliſh poet, the only ſon of Mr Neale an eminent merchant, by a daughter of baron Lechmere, was born in 1668. By his father’s death he was left young to the care of Mr Smith, who had married his father’s sister, and who treated him with ſo much tenderneſs, that at the death of his generous guardian he aſſumed his name. His writings are not many, and thoſe are ſcattered about in miſcellanies and collections : his celebrated tragedy of Phædra and Hippolitus was acted in 1707 ; and being introduced at a time when the Italian opera ſo much engroſſed the polite world, gave Mr Addiſon, who wrote the prologue, an opportunity to rally the vitiated taſte of the public. However, notwithſtanding the eſteem it has always been hdd in, it is perhaps rather to be conſidered as a fine poem than as a good play. This tragedy, with a Poem to the memory of Mr John Philips, three or four Odes, with a Latin oration ſpoken at Oxford <hi rend="italic">in laudem Thomae Bodleii,</hi> were publiſhed as his works by his friend Mr Oldiſworth. Mr Smith died in 1710, sunk into indolence and intemperance by poverty and diſappointments ; the hard fate of many a man of genius.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Smith</hi> (John), an excellent mezzotinter, flouriſhed about 1700; but neither the time of his birth nor death are accurately known. He united ſoftneſs with ſtrength, and finiſhed with freedom. He ſerved his time with one Tillet a painter in Moorſields; and as ſoon as he became his own maſter, learned from Becket the ſecret of mezzotinto, and being farther inſtructed by Van der Vaart, was taken to work in Sir Godfrey Kneller’s houſe ; and as he was to be the publisher of that maſter’s works, doubtleſs received conſiderable hints from him, which he amply repaid. “ To poſterity perhaps his prints (ſays Mr Walpole) will carry an idea of ſomething burleſque ; perukes of an enormous length flowing over suits of armour, compoſe wonderful habits. It is equally ſtrange that faſhion could introduce the one, and eſtabliſh the practice of repreſenting the other, when it was out of faſhion. Smith excelled in exhibiting both, as he found them in the portraits of Knel-</p></body></text></TEI>