<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:23:09Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>left he had along with him the 10,000 men whom they had relieved as above related. At laſt, after the conſul had remained a whole day before the city, his ſucceſſor Furius, thinking this a sufficient recompenſe to the Numantines for breaking the treaty, ordered him to be received again into the camp. However, Furius did not chooſe to engage with ſuch a deſperate and reſolute enemy as the Numantines had ſhowed themſelves; and the war with them was diſcontinued till the year 133 B. C. when Scipio Æmilianus, the deſtroyer of Carthage, was ſent againſt them. Againſt this renowned commander the Numantines with all their valour were not able to cope. Scipio, having with the utmoſt care introduced ſtrict diſcipline among his troops, and reformed the abuſes which his predeceſſors had suffered in their armies, by degrees brought the Romans to face their enemies, which at his arrival they had abſolutely refuſed to do. Having then ravaged all the country round about the town, it was ſoon blocked up on all ſides, and the inhabitants began to feel the want of provisions. At laſt they reſolved to make one deſperate attempt for their liberty, and either to break through their enemies, or periſh in the attempt. With this view they marched out in good order by two gates, and fell upon the works of the Romans with the utmoſt fury. The Romans, unable to ſtand this deſperate ſhock, were on the point of yielding ; but Scipio, haſtening to the places attacked, with no fewer than 20,000 men, the unhappy Numantines were at laſt driven into the city, where they ſuſtained for a little longer the miſeries of famine. Finding at laſt, however, that it was altogether impoſſible to hold out, it was reſolved by the majority to ſubmit to the pleaſure of the Roman commander. But this reſolution was not univerſally approved. Many ſhut themſelves up in their houſes, and died of hunger, while even thoſe who had agreed to surrender repented their offer, and ſetting fire to their houſes, periſhed in the flames with their wives and children, ſo that not a ſingle Numantine was left alive to grace the triumph of the conqueror of Carthage.</p><p>After the deſtruction of Numantia the whole of Spain ſubmitted to the Roman yoke; and nothing remarkable happened till the times of the Cimbri, when a prætorian army was cut off in Spain by the Luſitanians. From this time nothing remarkable occurs in the hiſtory of Spain till the civil war between Marius and Sylla. The latter having cruſhed the Marian faction, as related under the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Rome,</hi> proſcribed all thoſe that had ſided againſt him whom he could not immediately deſtroy. Among theſe was Sertorius, a man of conſummate valour and experience in war. He had by Marius been appointed praetor of Spain ; and upon the overthrow of Marius, retired to that province. Sylla no ſooner heard of his arrival in that country, than he ſent thither one Caius Annius with a powerful army to drive him out. As Sertorius had but few troops along with him, he diſpatched one Julius Salinator with a body of 6000 men to guard the paſſes of the Pyrenees, and to prevent Annius from entering the country. But Salinator having been treacherouſly murdered by aſſaſſins hired by Annius for that purpoſe, he no longer met with any obſtacle ; and Sertorius was obliged to embark for the coaſt of Africa with 3000 men, being all he had now remaining. With theſe he landed in Mauritania ; but as his men were ſtraggling careleſsly about,</p><p>great numbers oſ them were cut off by the Barbarians. This new misfortune obliged Sertorius to re-embark for Spain ; but finding the whole coaſt lined with the troops of Annius, he put to ſea again, not knowing what courſe to steer. In this new voyage he met with a ſmall fleet of Cilician pirates ; and having prevailed with them to join him, he made a deſcent on the coaſt of Yvica, overpowered the garriſon left there by Annius, and gained a conſiderable booty. On the news of this victory Annius ſet ſail for Yvica, with a conſiderable ſquadron, having 5000 land forces on board. Sertorius, not intimidated by the ſuperiority of the enemy, prepared to give them battle. But a violent ſtorm ariſing, moſt of the ſhips were driven on ſhore and daſhed to pieces, Sertorius himſelf with great difficulty eſcaping with the small remains of his fleet. For ſome time he continued in great danger, being prevented from putting to ſea by the fury of the waves, and from landing by the enemy ; at laſt, the ſtorm abating, he passed the ſtraits of Gades, now Gibraltar, and landed near the mouth of the liver Bæotis. Here he met with ſome ſeamen newly arrived from the Atlantic or Fortunate Iſlands; and was ſo taken with the account which they gave him of thoſe happy regions, that he reſolved to retire thither to ſpend the reſt of his life in quiet and happineſs. But having communicated this design to the Cilician pirates, they immediately abandoned him, and ſet ſail for Africa, with an intention to aſſiſt one of the barbarous kings againſt his ſubjects who had rebelled. Upon this Sertorius ſailed thither alſo, but took the oppoſite ſide ; and having defeated the king named <hi rend="italic">Aſcalis,</hi> obliged him to ſhut himſelf up in the city of Tingis, now Tangier, which he cloſely beſieged. But in the mean time Pacianus; who had been ſent by Sylla to aſſiſt the king, advanced with a conſiderable army againſt Sertorius. Upon this the latter, leaving part of his forces before the city, marched with the reſt to meet Pacianus, whoſe army, though greatly ſuperior to his own in number, he entirely defeated; killed the general, and took all his forces priſoners.—The fame of this victory ſoon reached Spain ; and the Luſitanians, being threatened with a new war from Annius, invited Sertorius to head their armies. With this requeſt he very readily complied, and ſoon became very formidable to the Romans. Titus Didius, governor oſ that part of Spain called <hi rend="italic">Baetica,</hi> firſt entered the lists with him ; but he being defeated, Sylla next diſpatched Metellus, reckoned one of the beſt commanders in Rome, to flop the progreſs of this new enemy. But Metellus, notwithſtanding all his experience, knew not how to act againſt Sertorius, who was continually changing his ſtation, putting his army into new forms, and contriving new ſtratagems. On his first arrival he ſent for L. Domitius, then praetor of Hither Spain, to, his aſſiſtance ; but Sertorius being informed of his march, detached Hirtuleius, or Herculeius, his quæstor, againſt him, who gave him a total overthrow. Metellus then diſpatched Lucius Lollius prætor of Narbonne Gaul againſt Hirtuleius ; but he met with no better ſucceſs, being utterly defeated, and his lieutenant-general killed.</p><p>The fame of theſe victories brought to the camp of Sertorius ſuch a number of illuſtrious Roman citizens of the Marian faction, that he formed a design of erecting Luſitania into a republic in oppoſition to that of Rome. Sylla was continually sending freſh ſupplies to</p></body></text></TEI>