<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:23:03Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>cline ſeveral years before his death, which happened in 1716. He was interred in Weſtminſter Abbey, where a monument is erected to his memory. He publiſhed, I. Animadverſions on Dr Sherlock’s Vindication of the Holy and Ever Bleſſed Trinity. 2. A Defence of his Animadverſions. 3. Sermons, 8 vols 8vo. And after his deceaſe were publiſhed his <hi rend="italic">Opera Posthuma Latina, </hi>and his poſthumous Engliſh works. Dr South was remarkable for his wit, which abounds in all his writings, and particularly in his sermons ; but at the ſame time they equally abound in ill-humour, ſpleen, and ſatire. He was remarkable for being a time-ſerver. During the life of Cromwell he was a ſtaunch Preſbyterian, and then railed againſt the Independents : at the Reſtoration he exerted his pulpit-eloquence againſt the Preſbyterians ; and in the reign of Queen Anne, was a warm advocate for Sacheverel.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">South,</hi> one of the four cardinal points from which the winds blow.</p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps">South</hi><hi rend="italic"> Sea,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Pacific Ocean,</hi> is that vaſt body of water interpoſed between Aſia and America. It does not however, ſtrictly ſpeaking, reach quite to the continent of Aſia, excepting to the northward of the peninſula of Malacca : for the water interpoſed between the eaſtern coaſt of Africa and the peninſula just mentioned has the name of the <hi rend="italic">Indian Ocean.</hi> The South Sea then is bounded on one ſide by the weſtern coaſt of America, through its whole extent, from the unknown regions in the north to the ſtraits of Magellan and Terra del Fuego, where it communicates with the ſouthern part of the Atlantic. On the other ſide, it is hounded by the coaſt of Aſia, from the northern promontory of Tſchukotſkoi Noss, to the peninſula of Malacca already mentioned. Thence it is bounded to the ſouth- ward by the northern coaſts of Borneo, Celebes, Macassar, New Guinea, New Holland, and the other iſlands in that quarter, which divide it from the Indian Ocean. Then, waſhing the eaſtern coaſt of the great iſland of New Holland, it communicates with that vaſt body of water encompaſſing the whole ſouthern part of the globe, and which has the general name of the <hi rend="italic">Southern Ocean</hi> all round. Thus does this vaſt ocean occupy almoſt the ſemicircumference of the globe, extending almoſt from one pole to the other, and about the equatorial parts extending almoſt 180⁰ in longitude, or 12,500 of our miles.</p><p>The northern parts of the Pacific Ocean are entirely deſtitute of land ; not a ſingle iſland having yet been diſcovered in it from the latitude of 40⁰ north and upwards, excepting ſuch as are very near the coaſt either of Aſia or America ; but in the ſouthern part there arc a great number.</p><p>Till very lately the South Sea was in a great meaſure unknown. From the great extent of ice which covers the ſouthern part of the globe, it was imagined that much more land exiſted there than in the northern regions : but that this could not be juſtly inferred merely from that circumſtance, is plain from what has been advanced under the article <hi rend="smallcaps">America,</hi> n⁰ 3—24; and the ſouthern continent, long known by the name of <hi rend="italic">Terra Australis,</hi> has eluded the ſearch of the moſt expert navigators ſent out from Britain and France by royal authority. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Terra Australis.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps">South</hi><hi rend="italic"> Sea Company.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Company.</hi></p><p>SOUTHAMPTON, a ſea-port town of Hampſhire in England. It is commodiouſly ſeated on an arm of the ſea ; is a place of good trade, and well inhabited. It is ſurrounded by walls and ſeveral watch-towers, and had a ſtrong caſtle to defend the harbour, now in ruins. It is a corporation and a county of itſelf, with the title of an earldom, and sends two members to parliament. W. Long. i. 26. N. Lat. 50. 55.</p><p>SOUTHERN (Thomas), an eminent dramatic writer, was born at Dublin in 1660, and received his education in the univerſity there. He came young to London to ſtudy law; but inſtead of that devoted himſelf to poetry and the writing of plays. His Perſian Prince, or Loyal Brother, was introduced in 1682, wſhen the Tory intereſt was triumphant in England ; and the character of the loyal brother being intended to compliment James duke of York, he rewarded the author when he came to the throne with a commiſſion in the army. On the Revolution taking place, he retired to his ſtudies, and wrote ſeveral plays, from which he is ſuppoſed to have derived a very handſome ſubſiſtence, being the firſt who raiſed the advantage of play-writing to a ſecond and third night. The moſt finiſhed of all his plays is Oroonoko, or the Royal Slave, which is built on a true ſtory related in one of Mrs Behn’s novels. Mr Southern died in 1746, in the 86th year of his age; the latter part of which he ſpent in a peaceful ſerenity, having, by his commiſſion as a ſoldier, and the profits of his dramatic works, acquired a handſome fortune ; and being an exact economiſt, he improved what fortune he gained to the beſt advantage. He enjoyed the longeſt life of all our poets ; and died the richeſt of them, a very few excepted. His plays are printed in two vols 12mo.</p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Southern</hi><hi rend="italic"> Continent.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">America,</hi> n⁰3—24. and <hi rend="italic smallcaps">Terra</hi><hi rend="italic"> Australis.</hi></p><p>SOUTHERNWOOD, in botany. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Artemisia.</hi></p><p>SOUTHWARK, a town of Surry, and a ſuburb of the city of London, being ſeparated from that metropolis only by the Thames. See <hi rend="smallcaps">London,</hi> n⁰ 96.</p><p>SOW, in zoology. See Bus.</p><p>Sow, in the iron works, the name oſ the block or lump of metal they work at once in the iron furnace.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Sow-Thistle.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Sonchus.</hi></p><p>SOWING, in agriculture and gardening, the depoſiting any kind of ſeed in the earth for a future crop. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Agriculture.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Drill-</hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Sowing.</hi> See <hi rend="italic">DRILL-Sowing.</hi></p><p>SOY. -See <hi rend="smallcaps">Dolichos.</hi></p><p>SOZOMENUS (Hermias), an eccleſiaſtical hiſtorian of the 5th century, was bom in Bethelia, a town of Paleſtine. He was educated for the law, and became a pleader at Conſtantinople. He wrote an A- bridgment of Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtory, in two books, from the aſcenſion of our Saviour to the year 323. This compendium is loſt ; but a continuation of it in nine books, written at greater length, down to the year 440, is ſtill extant. He ſeems to have copied Socrates, who wrote a hiſtory of the ſame period. The ſtyle of Sozomenus is perhaps more elegant ; but in other reſpects he falls far ſhort of that writer, diſplaying throughout his whole book an amazing credulity and a ſuperſtitious attachment to monks and the monaſtic life. The</p></body></text></TEI>