<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-18T21:24:20Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>be wanting : for a liquor which answers to N⁰ 4 will sink N<hi rend="superscript"
                    >o</hi> 2 by heating it a few degrees, and therefore N⁰ 3 may be ſpared. This is
                a great advantage in ordinary buſineſs. A nice hydrometer is not only an expenſive
                inſtrument, but exceedingly delicate, being ſo very thin. If broken or even bruiſed,
                it is uſeleſs, and can hardly be repaired except by the very maker.</p>
            <p>As the only queſtion here is, to determine how many gallons of exciſe proof ſpirits
                is contained in a quantity of liquor, the artiſt has conſtructed this ſeries of
                bubbles in the ſimpleſt manner poſſible, by previouſly making 40 or 50 mixtures of
                ſpirits and water, and then adjuſting the bubbles to theſe mixtures. In ſome ſets
                the number on each bubble is the number of gallons of proof ſpirits contained in 100
                gallons of the liquor. In other ſets the number on each bubble expreſſes the gallons
                of water which will make a liquor of this ſtrength, if added to 14 gallons of
                alcohol. Thus, if a liquor anſwers to N⁰ 4, then 4 gallons of water added to 14
                gallons of alcohol will make a liquor of this ſtrength. The firſt is the beſt method
                ; for we ſhould be miſtaken in ſuppoſing that 18 gallons, which anſwer to N⁰ 4,
                contains exactly 14 gallons of alcohol : it contains more than 14, for a reaſon to
                be given by and by.</p>
            <p>By examining the ſpecific gravity of bodies, the philoſopher has made ſome very
                curious diſcoveries. The moſt remarkable of theſe is the change which the denſity of
                bodies suffers by mixture. It is a moſt reaſonable expectation, that when a cubic
                foot of one ſubſtance is mixed <hi rend="italic">any how</hi> with a cubic foot of
                another, the bulk of the mixture will be two cubic feet ; and that 8 gallons of
                water joined to 18 gallons of oil will fill a veſſel of 36 gallons. Accordingly this
                was never doubted ; and even Archimedes, the moſt ſcrupulous of mathematicians,
                proceeded on this ſupposition in the ſolution of his famous problem, the diſcovery
                of the proportion of ſilver and gold in a mixture of both. He does not even mention
                it as a poſtulate that <hi rend="italic">may</hi> be granted him, ſo much did he
                conceive it to be an axiom. Yet a little reflection ſeems sufficient to make it
                doubtful and to require examination. A box filled with muſket-balls will receive a
                conſiderable quantity of ſmall ſhot, and after this a conſiderable quantity of fine
                sand, and after this a conſiderable quantity of water. Something like this might
                happen in the admixture of bodies of porous texture. But ſuch ſubſtances as metals,
                glaſs, and fluids, where no diſcontinuity of parts can be perceived, or was
                suſpected, ſeem free ſrom every chance oſ this kind oſ introſuſception. Lord Bacon,
                however, without being a naturaliſt or mathematician <hi rend="italic">ex
                    professo,</hi> interred from the mobility of fluids that they consiſted of
                diſcrete particles, which muſt have pores interpoſed, whatever be their figure. And
                if we aſcribe the different denſities, or other ſenſible qualities, to difference in
                ſize or figure of thoſe particles, it muſt frequently happen that the ſmaller
                particles will be lodged in the interſtices between the larger, and thus contribute
                to the weight of the ſenſible maſs without increaſing its bulk. He therefore
                ſuspects that mixtures will be in general leſs bulky than the ſum of their
                ingredients.</p>
            <p>Accordingly, the examination of this queſtion was one of the firſt employments of the
                Royal Socſety of London, and long before its inſtitution had occupied the attention
                of the gentlemen who afterwards composed it. The regiſter of the Society’s early
                meetings</p>
            <p>contains many experiments on this ſubject, with mixtures of gold and ſilver, of other
                metals, and of various fluids, examined by the hydroſtatical balance of Mr Boyle. Dr
                Hooke made a prodigious number, chiefly on articles of commerce, which were
                unfortunately loſt in the fire of London.</p>
            <p>It was ſoon found, however, that Lord Bacon’s conjecture had been well founded, and
                that bodies changed their density very ſenſibly in many caſes. In general, it was
                found that bodies which had a ſtrong chemical affinity increaſed in denſity, and
                that their admixture was accompanied with heat.</p>
            <p>By this dilcovery it is manifeſt that Archimedes had not ſolved the problem of
                detecting the quantity of silver mixed with the gold in King Hiero’s crown, and that
                the phyſical ſolution of it requires experiments made on all the kinds of matter
                that are mixed together. We do not find that this has been done to this day,
                although we may affirm that there are few queſtions of more importance. It is a very
                curious fact in chemiſtry, and it would be moſt deſirable to be able to reduce it to
                ſome general laws ; For inſtance, to aſcertain what is the proportion of two
                ingredients which produces the greateſt change of denſity. This is important in the
                ſcience of phyſics, becauſe it gives us considerable information as to the mode of
                action of thoſe natural powers or forces by which the particles of tangible matter
                are united. If this introſuſception, concentration, compenetration, or by whatever
                name it be called, were a mere reception of the particles of one ſubſtance into the
                interſtices of thoſe of another, it is evident that the greateſt concentration would
                be obſerved when a ſmall quantity of the recipiend is mixed with, or diſſeminated
                through, a great quantity of the other. It is thus that a ſmall quantity of fine
                fand will be received into the interſtices of a quantity of ſmall ſhot, and will
                increaſe the weight of the bagful, without increaſing its bulk. The caſe is nowiſe
                different when a piece of freeſtone has grown heavier by imbibing or abſorbing a
                quantity of water. If more than a certain quantity of fand has been added to the
                ſmall ſhot, it is no longer concealed. In like manner, various quantities of water
                may combine with a maſs of clay, and increaſe its ſize and weight alike. All this is
                very conceivable, occaſioning no difficulty,</p>
            <p>But this is not the caſe in any of the mixtures we are now conſidering. In all theſe,
                the firſt additions of either of the two ſubſtances produce but an inconſiderable
                change of general denſity ; and it is in general moſt remarkable, whether it be
                condensation or rarefaction, when the two ingredients are nearly of equabulks. We
                can illuſtrate even this difference, by reflecting on the imbibition of water by
                vegetable ſolids, ſuch as timber. Some kinds of wood, have their weight much more
                increaſed than their bulks ; other kinds of wood are more enlarged in bulk than in
                weight. The like happens in grains. This is curious, and ſhows in the moſt
                unqueſtionable manner that the particles of bodies are not in contact, but are kept
                together by forces which act at a diſtance. For this diſtance between the centres of
                the particles is moſt evidently ſuſceptible of variation ; and this variation is
                occaſioned. by the introduction of another ſubſtance, which, by acting on the
                particles by attraction or repulſion, diminiſhes or increaſes their mutual actions,
                and makes new diſtances</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
