<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:22:31Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>that wickedneſs. The place where it ſtood is now covered by the waters of the Dead Sea, or the Lake Asphaltites. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Asphaltites.</hi></p><p>SODOMY, an unnatural crime, ſo called from the city of Sodom, which was deſtroyed by fire for the ſame. The Levitical law adjudged thoſe guilty of this execrable crime to death ; and the civil law aſſigns the same puniſhment to it. The law of England makes it felony. There is no ſtatute in Scotland againſt Sodomy ; the libel of the crime is therefore founded on the divine law, and practice makes its puniſhment to be burned alive.</p><p>SODOR, a name always conjoined with Man, in mentioning the biſhop of Man’s dioceſe. Concerning the origin and application of this word, very different opinions have been formed by the learned. Buchanan (lib. i. cap. 34 ) ſays, that before his time the name of <hi rend="italic">Sodor</hi> was given to a town in the isle of Man. In Gough’s edition of Camden’s <hi rend="italic">Britannia</hi> (vol. iii. p. 701.) it is ſaid, that after the isle of Man was annexed to the crown of England, this appellation was given to a ſmall iſland within muſket-ſhot of Man, in which the cathedral ſtands, called by the Norwegians the <hi rend="italic">Holm,</hi> and by the inhabitants the <hi rend="italic">Peel.</hi> In ſupport of this opinion a charter is quoted A. D. 1505, in which Thomas earl of Derby and lord of Man confirms to Huan Heſketh biſhop of Sodor all the lands, &amp;c. anciently belonging to the biſhops of Man. “ Ecclesiam cathedralem ſancti Germani in <hi rend="italic">Holm Sodor vel Pels</hi> vocatam, ecclesiam ſancti Patricii ibidem, et locum præfatum in quo ecclesiæ præsatæ sitæ ſunt.” The truth of either, or perhaps of both, theſe accounts might be allowed; but neither of them are sufficient to account for the conſtant conjunction of Sodor and Man, in charters, regiſters, and hiſtories. If Sodor was a ſmall town or iſland belonging to Man, it cannot be conceived why it is always mentioned before it, or rather why it ſhould be mentioned at all in ſpeaking of a biſhop’s dioceſe. To ſpeak oſ the biſhopric of Sodor and Man in this cafe would be as improper as it would be to call the biſhopric of Durham the biſhopric of Holy Island and Durham, or the biſhopric of Darlington and Durham ; the former being a ſmall island and the latter a town belonging to the county and dioceſe of Durham. Neither of theſe accounts, therefore, give a ſatisfactory account of the original conjunction of Sodor and Man.</p><p>The island of Iona was the place where the biſhop of the isles resided, the cathedral church of which, it is ſaid, was dedicated to our Saviour, in Greek <hi rend="italic">Soter, </hi>hence <hi rend="italic">Sotorenſes,</hi> which might be corrupted into <hi rend="italic">Sodorenſes,</hi> a name frequently given by Daniſh writers to the weſtern isles of Scotland. That we may be the more diſpoſed to accede to this Grecian etymology, the advocates for this opinion tell us, that the name I<hi rend="italic">columkill,</hi> which is often applied to this iſland, is alſo of Greek extraction, being derived from c<hi rend="italic">olumba,</hi> “ a pigeon ;” a meaning that exactly correſponds to the Celtic word O<hi rend="italic">olum</hi> and the Hebrew word <hi rend="italic">Iona.</hi> We muſt confeſs, however, that we have very little faith in the conjectures of etymologiſts, and think that upon no occaſion they alone can eſtablifh any tact, though when concurring with facts they certainly tend to confirm and explain them. It is only from hiſtorical facts that we can know to what Sodor was applied.</p><p>It appears from the hiſtory of the Orkneys, compiled</p><p>by an old Iſlandſe writer, translated and enlarged by Torfæus, that the Æbudæ or Weſtern isles of Scotland were divided into two cluſters, Nordureys and Sudereys. The Nordureys, which were ſeparated from the Sudereys by the point of Ardnamurchan, a promontory in Argyleſhire, consiſted of Muck, Egg, Rum, Canna, Sky, Rafay, Barra, South Uiſt, North Uiſt, Benbecula, and Lewis, including Harris, with a great number of ſmall isles. The Sudereys were, Man, Arran, Bute, Cumra, Avon, Gid, Ila, Colonſay, Jura, Scarba, Mull, Iona, Tiree, Coll, Ulva, and other ſmall iſlands. All theſe, when joined together, and ſubject to the same prince, made up the kingdom of Man and the isles. In the Norwegian language <hi rend="italic">Suder</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Norder,</hi> signifying ſouthern and northern, and ey or <hi rend="italic">ay</hi> an island. When the Æbudæ were under one monarch, the seat of empire was fixed in the Sudereys, and the Nordureys were governed by deputies ; hence the former are much oftener mentioned in hiſtory than the latter ; hence, too, the Sudereys often comprehend the Nordureys, as in our days Scotland is ſometimes comprehended under England. Sudereys, or Suder, when angliciſed, became Sodor ; and all the weſtern iſles of Scotland being included in one dioceſe under the Norwegian princes, the biſhop appointed to ſuperintend them was called the biſhop of Man and the isles, or the. biſhop of Sodor and Man. Since Man was conquered by Edward III. it has been ſeparated from the other isles, and its biſhops have exerciſed no juriſdiction over them. Should it now be aſked, why then is the biſhop of Man ſtill called the biſhop of Sodor and Man ? we reply, that we have been able to diſcover no reaſon ; but ſuppoſe the appellation to be continued in the ſame way, as the title king of France, has been kept up by the kings of Great Britain, for ſeveral centuries after the Engliſh were entirely expelled from France.</p><p>SOFA, in the eaſt, a kind of alcove raiſed half a foot above the floor oſ a chamber or other apartment ; and uſed as the place of ſtate, where visitors of diſtinction are received. Among the Turks the whole floor of their ſtate-rooms is covered with a kind of tapestry, and on the window-side is raiſed a ſofa or ſopha, laid with a kind of matraſs, covered with a carpet much richer than the other. On this carpet the Turks are ſeated, both men and women, like the taylors in England, croſs-legged, leaning againſt the wall, which is bolſtered with velvet, ſattin, or other ſtuff ſuitable to the ſeaſon. Here they eat their meals ; only laying a skin over the carpet to ſerve as a table-cloth, and a round wooden board over all, covered with plates, &amp;c.</p><p>SOFALA, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Cefala,</hi> a kingdom of Africa, lying on the coaſt of Moſambique, near Zanguebar. It is bounded on the north by Monomotapa ; on the eaſt by the Moſambique Sea ; on the ſouth by the kingdom of Sabia ; and on the weſt by that of Manica. It contains mines of gold and iron, and a great number of elephants. It is governed by a king, tributary to the Portugueſe, who built a fort at the principal town, which is of the ſame name, and of great importance for their trade to the Eaſt Indies. It is ſeated in a ſmall island, near the mouth of a river. E. Long. 35. 40.</p><p>S.	Lat. 20. 20.</p><p>SOFFITA, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Soffit,</hi> in architecture, any timber ceiling formed of croſs beams of flying cornices, the ſquare compartiments or pannels of which are enriched</p></body></text></TEI>