<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:21:33Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>cannes the oil-cup and the pivot of the horizontal axis BC be ſcrewed to one ſide of this croſs bar, ſo that the centre of the cup may be exactly under the upper pivot hole. By this conſtruction we have only to unſcrew this cock, and then both axles come out of their places at once, and may be replaced without any trouble. We have ſketched in fig. 8. the manner in which this may be done, where M repreſents a ſection of the lower croſs bar. BCDE is the cock, fixed to the bar by the pins which go through both with finger nuts, a and <hi rend="italic">b </hi>on the oppoſite ſide. F i is the hard steel pin with the conical top <hi rend="italic">i,</hi> on which the lower end I of the upright ſpindle AG refis, in the manner recommended as the best and the moſt durable. The pivot of the horizontal axis turns in a hole at E the top of the cock.</p><p>After all, we muſt acknowledge that the ſmoke jack is inferior to the common jack that is moved by a weight. It is more expensive at firſt, and requires more frequent repairs ; its motion is not ſo much under command ; it occaſions foot to be thrown about the fire, to the great annoyance of the cook ; and it is a great encumbrance when we would clean the vent.</p><p><hi rend="italic">SMOKE-Farthings.</hi> The pentecoſtals or cuſtomary oblations offered by the diſperſed inhabitants within a dioceſe when they made their proceſſion to the mother or cathedral church, came by degrees into a ſtanding annual rent called <hi rend="italic">ſmoke-farthings.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">SMOKE-Silver.</hi> Lands were holden in ſome places by the payment oſ the ſum of 6 d. yearly to the ſheriff, called <hi rend="italic">ſmoke-ſilver</hi> (Par. 4. Edw. VI.) Smoke-ſilver and ſmoke-penny are to be paid to the miniſters of divers pariſhes as a <hi rend="italic">modus</hi> in lieu of tithe-wood : and in ſome manors formerly belonging to religious houſes, there is ſtill paid, as appendant to the laid manors, the ancient Peter-pence, by the name of <hi rend="italic">ſmoke-money (Twisd. Hist. Vindicat. 77.)—</hi>The bishop of London <hi rend="italic">anno</hi> 1444 issued out his commiſſion, Ad <hi rend="italic">levandum le</hi> ſmoke-far- things, &amp;c.</p><p>SMOLENSKO, a large and ſtrong city of Ruſſia, and capital of a palatinate of the ſame name, with a caſtle ſeated on a mountain, and a bishop’s ſee. It is ſtrong by its ſituation, being in the middle of a wood, and ſurrounded by almoſt inacceſſible mountains. It has been taken and retaken ſeveral times by the Poles and Russians ; but theſe laſt have had poſſeſſion of it ever ſince the year 1687. It is ſeated on the river Nieper, near the frontiers of Lithuania, 188 miles ſouth-weſt of Moſcow. E. Long. 31. 22. N. Lat. 54. 50.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Smolensko,</hi> a duchy and palatinate of Ruſſia, bound ed on the north by Biela, on the eaſt by the duchy of Moſcow, on the ſouth by that of Severia and the palatinate of Meiſlaw, and on the west by the ſame palatinate and by that of Witeplk. It is full of foreſts and mountains : and the capital is of the ſame name.</p><p>SMOLLET (Dr Tobias), an author whoſe writings will transmit his name with honour to poſterity, was born in the year 1720 at a ſmall village within two miles of Cameron, on the banks of the river Leven. He appears to have received a claſſical education, and was bred to the practice of phyſic and ſurgery ; and in the early part of his life ſerved as a ſurgeon’s mate in the navy.</p><p>The incidents that beſel him during his continuance in this capacity ſerved as a foundation for Roderic Random, one of the moſt entertaining novels in the Engliſh tongue. He was preſent at the siege of Carthagena ; and in the before-mentioned novel he has given a faithful, though not very pleaſing, account of the management of that ill-conducted expedition, which he cenſures in the warmeſt terms, and from circumſtances which fell under his own particular obſervation.</p><p>His connection with the ſea ſeems not to have been of long continuance ; and it is probable that he wrote ſeveral pieces before he became known to the public by his capital productions. The firſt piece we know of with certainty is a Satire in two parts, printed firſt in the years 1746 and 1747, and reprinted in a Collection of his Plays and Poems in 1777. About this period, or ſome time before, he wrote for Mr Rich an opera intitled Alceſte, which has never been performed nor printed.</p><p>At the age of 18 he wrote a tragedy intitled The Regicide, founded on the ſtory of the aſſaſſination of James I. of Scotland. In the preface to this piece, publiſhed by ſubſcription in the year 1749, he bitterly exclaimed againſt falſe patrons, and the duplicity of theatrical managers. The warmth and impetuoſity of his temper hurried him, on this occaſion, into unjuſt reflections againſt the late George Lord Lyttleon and Mr Garrick ; the character of the former he characteriſed in the novel of Peregrine Pickle, and he added a burleſque of the Monody written by that nobleman on the death of his lady. Againſt Mr Garrick he made illiberal ill-founded criticiſms ; and in his novel of Roderic Random gave a very unfair representation of his treatment of him reſpecting this tragedy. Of this conduct he afterwards repented, and acknowledged his errors ; though in the ſubſequent editions of the novel the paſſages which were the haſty effuſions of disappointment are not omitted.</p><p>However, in giving a sketch of the liberal arts in his Hiſtory of England, he afterwards remarked, “ the exhibitions of the ſtage were improved to the moſt exquiſite entertainment by the talents and management of Garrick, who greatly ſurpaſſed all his predeceſſors of this and perhaps every other nation, in his genius for acting, in the ſweetneſs and variety of his tones, the irreſiſtible magic of his eye, the fire and vivacity of his action, the eloquence of attitude, and the whole pathos of expreſſion.</p><p>“ Candidates for literary fame appeared even in the higher ſphere of life, embelliſhed by the nervous ſenſe and extenſive erudition of a Corke; by the delicate taſte, the poliſhed muſe, and the tender feelings, of a Lyttleton.”</p><p>Not ſatisfied with this public declaration, he wrote an apology to Mr Garrick in ſtill ſtronger terms. With theſe simple conceſſions, Mr Garrick was completely ſatisfied ; ſo that in 1757, when Dr Smollet’s comedy of the Reprisals, an afterpiece of two acts, was performed at Drury Lane theatre, the latter acknowledged himſelf highly obliged for the friendly care of Mr Garrick exerted in preparing it for the ſtage ; and ſtill more for his acting the part of Luſignan in Zara for his benefit, on the ſixth inſtead of the ninth night, to which he was only intitled by the cuſtom of the theatre.</p><p>The Adventuresof Roderic Random, publiſhed in 1748, </p><p>2 vols 12mo, a book which ſtill continues to have a moſt</p></body></text></TEI>