<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:23:24Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>bands the balance of power among the potentates of Europe. Feats of chivalry however, parties of gallantry, and ſuch exerciſes as were in that age reckoned manly or elegant, rather than ſerious buſineſs, occupied the two courts during the time that they continued together, which was 18 days.</p><p>After taking leave of this ſcene of diſſipation, the king of England paid a viſit to the emperor and Margaret of Savoy at Gravelines, and engaged them to go along with him to Calais; where the artful and politic Charles completed the impreſſion which he had begun to make on Henry and his favourite, and effaced all the friendſhip to which the frank and generous nature of Francis had given birth. He renewed his aſſurances of aſſiſting Wolſey in obtaining the papacy ; and he put him in preſent poſſeſſion of the revenues belonging to the ſees oſ Badajox and Palencia in Spain. He flattered Henry’s pride, by convincing him of his own importance, and oſ the juſtneſs of the motto which he had choſen ; offering to ſubmit to his ſole arbitration any difference that might ariſe between him and Francis.</p><p>This important point being ſecured, Charles repaired  to Aix-la-Chapelle, where he was ſolemnly inveſted with the crown and ſceptre of Charlemagne, in preſence of a more ſplendid and numerous aſſembly than had appeared on any former inauguration.  About the ſame time Solyman the Magnificent, one of the moſt accompliſhed, enterpriſing, and victorious of the Turkiſh princes, and a conſtant and formidable rival to the emperor, aſcended the Ottoman throne.</p><p>The firſt act oſ Charles’s adminiſtration was to appoint a diet of the empire, to be held at Worms, in order to concert with the princes proper meaſures for checking the progreſs of “ thoſe new and dangerous opinions which threatened to diſturb the peace of Germany, and to overturn the religion of their anceſtors.” The opinions propagated by Luther and his followers were here meant. But all his efforts for that purpoſe were insufficient, as is related under the articles <hi rend="smallcaps">Luther</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Reformation,</hi></p><p>In 1521, the Spaniards, diſſatisſied with the departure of their ſovereign, whoſe election to the empire they foreſaw would interfere with the adminiſtration of his own kingdom, and incenſed at the avarice of the Flemings, to whom the direction of public affairs had been committed ſince the death of cardinal Ximenes, ſeveral grandees, in order to ſhake off this oppreſſion, entered into an aſſociation, to which they gave the name oſ the <hi rend="italic">Sancta Juncta ;</hi> and the ſword was appealed to as the means of redreſs. This ſeemed to Francis a favourable juncture for reinſtating the family of John d’Albert in the kingdom of Navarre. Charles was at a diſtance ſrom that part of his dominions, and the troops uſually ſtationed there had been called away to quell the commotions in Spain. A French army, under Andrew de Foix, ſpeedily conquered Navarre ; but that young and inexperienced nobleman, puſhed on by military ardour, ventured to enter Caſtile. The Spaniards, though divided among themſelves, united againſt a foreign enemy, routed his forces, took him prisoner, and recovered Navarre in a ſhorter time than he had ſpent in ſubduing it.</p><p>Hoſtilities thus begun in one quarter, between the rival monarchs, ſoon ſpread to another. The king of France encouraged the duke of Bouillon to make war</p><p>againſt the emperor, and to invade Luxembourg. Charles, after humbling the duke, attempted to enter France ; but was repelled and worſted before Mezieres by the famous chevalier Bayard, diſtinguifhed among his cotemporaries by the appellation of <hi rend="italic">The Knight without fear and without reproach ;</hi> and who united the talents of a great general to the punctilious honour and romantic gallantry of the heroes of chivalry. Francis broke into the Low Countries, where, by an exceſs of caution, an error not natural to him, he loſt an opportunity of cutting off the whole imperial army; and, what was of still more conſequence, he diſguſted the conſtable Bourbon,· by giving the command of the van to the duke of Alençon.</p><p>During theſe operations in the field, an unſucceſsful congreſs was held at Calais, under the mediation of Henry VIII. It ſerved only to exaſperate the parties which it was intended to reconcile. A league was ſoon after concluded, by the intrigues of Wolſey, between the pope, Henry, and Charles, againſt France. Leo had already entered into a ſeparate league with the emperor, and the French were faſt loſing ground in Italy.</p><p>The inſolence and exactions of Mareſhal de Lautrec, governor of Milan, had totally alienated the affections of the Milaneſe from France. They reſolved to expel the troops of that nation, and put themſelves under the government of Francis Sforza, brother to Maximilian their late duke. In this reſolution, they were encouraged by the pope, who excommunicated Lautrec, and took into his pay a conſiderable body of Swiſs. The papal army, commanded by Proſper Colonna, an experienced general, was joined by ſupplies from Germany and Naples ; while Lautrec, neglected by his court, and deſerted by the Swiſs in its pay, was unable to make head againſt the enemy. The city of Milan was betrayed by the inhabitants to the confederates ; Parma and Placentia were united to the eccleſiaſtieal ſtate ; and of their conqueſts in Lombardy, only the town of Cremona, the caſtle of Milan, and a few inconſiderable forts, remained in the hands of the French.</p><p>Leo X. received the accounts of this rapid ſucceſs with ſuch tranſports of joy, as are ſaid to have brought on a fever, which occaſioned his death. The ſpirit of the confederacy was broken, and its operations ſuſpended by this accident. The Swiſs were recalled ; ſome other mercenaries diſhanded for want of pay ; and only the Spaniards, and a few Germans in the emperor’s ſervice, remained to defend the duchy of Milan. Bub Lautrec, who with the remnant of his army had taken ſhelter in the Venetian territories, deſtitute both of men and money, was unable to improve this favourable opportunity as he wiſhed. All his efforts were rendered ineffectual by the vigilance and ability of Colonna and his aſſociates.</p><p>Meantime much diſcord prevailed in the conclave, Wolſey’s name, notwithſtanding all the emperor’s magnificent promiſes, was ſcarcely mentioned there. Julio de Medici, Leo’s nephew, thought himſelf ſure of the election ; when, by an unexpected turn of fortune, cardinal Adrian of Utrecht, Charles’s preceptor, who at that time governed Spain in the emperor’s name, was unanimouſly raiſed to the papacy, to the aſtoniſhment of all Europe and the great diſguſt of the Italians.</p></body></text></TEI>