<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:23:37Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Happily for the Proteſtants, Charles received intelligence of this revolution ſoon after the diet at Ratiſbon; and by the conceſſions which he made them, he obtained ſuch liberal ſupplies, both oſ men and money, as left him under little anxiety about the ſecurity of Germany.</p><p> He therefore haſtened to join his fleet and army in Italy, in order to carry into execution a great and favourite enterprize which he had concerted againſt Algiers : though it would certainly have been more conſiſtent with his dignity to have conducted the whole force of the empire againſt Solyman, the common enemy of Chriſtendom, who was ready to enter his Auſtrian dominions. But many reaſons induced Charles to prefer the African expedition : he wanted ſtrength, or at leaſt money, to combat the Turks in ſo diſtant a country as Hungary; and the glory which he had formerly acquired in Barbary led him to hope for the like ſucceſs, while the cries of his Spaniſh ſubjects rouſed him to take vengeance on their ravagers. But the unfortunate event of this expedition has already been related under the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Algiers,</hi> n⁰ 14—20.</p><p>The loſs which the emperor ſuffered in this calamitous expedition encouraged the king of France to begin hoſtilities, on which he had been for ſome time reſolved; and an action diſhonourable to civil ſociety furniſhed him with too good a pretext for taking arms. The marquis del Guaſto, governor oſ the Milaneſe, having got intelligence of the motions and deſtination of two ambaſſadors, Rincon and Fergoſo, whom Francis had diſpatched, the one to the Ottoman Porte, the other to the republic of Venice ; knowing how much his master wiſhed to diſcover the intentions of the French monarch, and of what conſequence it was to retard the execution of his meaſures, he employed ſome ſoldiers belonging to the garriſon oſ Pavia to lie in wait for theſe ambaſſadors as they ſailed down the Po, who murdered them and moſt of their attendants, and ſeized their papers. Francis immediately demanded reparation for this barbarous outrage ; and as Charles endeavoured to put him off with an evaſive anſwer, he appealed to all the courts of Europe, ſetting forth the heinouſneſs of the injury, the iniquity of the emperor in diſregarding his juſt requeſt, and the neceſſity of vengeance. But Charles, who was a more profound negotiator, defeated in a great meaſure the effects of theſe repreſentations : he ſecured the fidelity of the Proteſtant princes in Germany, by granting them new conceſſions ; and he engaged the king of England to eſpouſe his cauſe, under pretence of defending Europe againſt the Infidels ; while Francis was only able to form an alliance with the kings of Denmark and Sweden (who for the firſt time intereſted themſelves in the quarrels of the more potent monarchs of the ſouth), and to renew his treaty with Solyman, which drew on him the indignation of Chriſtendom.</p><p>But the activity oſ Francis ſupplied all the defects of his negotiation. Five armies were ſoon ready to take the field, under different generals, and with different deſtinations. Nor was Charles wanting in his preparations. He and Henry a ſecond time made an ideal diviſion of the kingdom of France. But as the hoſtilities which followed terminated in nothing deciſive, and were diſtinguiſhed by no remarkable event, except the battle of Ceriſoles (gained by count d’Enguien over the imperialiſts, and in which 10,000 of the emperor’s beſt</p><p>troops ſell), at laſt Francis and Charles, mutually tired of haraſſing each other, concluded at Creſpy a treaty of peace, in which the king of England was not mentioned ; and from being implacable enemies, became once more, to appearance, cordial friends, and even allies by the ties of blood.</p><p>The chief articles of this treaty were, that all the conqueſts which either party had made ſince the truce of Nice ſhould be reſtored ; that the emperor ſhould give in marriage to the duke of Orleans, either his own eldest daughter, with the Low Countries, or the ſecond daughter of his brother Ferdinand, with the inveſtiture of the Milaneſe ; that Francis should renounce all pretenſions to the kingdom of Naples, as well as to the ſovereignty of Flanders and Artois, and Charles give up his claim to the duchy of Burgundy ; and that both ſhould unite in making war againſt the Turks.</p><p>The emperor was chiefly induced to grant conditions ſo advantageous to France, by a desire of humbling the Proteſtant princes in Germany. With the papal juriſdiction, he foreſaw they would endeavour to throw off the imperial authority ; and he determined to make his zeal for the former a pretence for enforcing and extending the latter. However, the death of the duke of Orleans before the conſummation of his marriage, diſentangled the emperor from the moſt troubleſome ſtipulation in the treaty of Creſpy ; and the French monarch, being ſtill engaged in hoſtilities with England, was unable to obtain any reparation for the loſs which he ſuffered by this unforeſeen event. Theſe hoſtilities, like thoſe between Charles and Francis, terminated in nothing deciſive. Equally tired of a ſtruggle attended with no glory or advantage to either, the contending princes concluded, at Campe, near Ardies, a treaty of peace; in which it was ſtipulated, that France ſhould pay the arrears due by former treaties to England. But theſe arrears did not exceed one-third of the ſums expended by Henry on his military operations ; and Francis being in no condition to diſcharge them, Boulogne (a chargeable pledge) was left in the hands of the Engliſh as a ſecurity for the debt.</p><p>In conſequence of the emperor’s reſolution to humble the Proteſtant princes, he concluded a diſhonourable peace with the Porte, ſtipulating that his brother Ferdinand ſhould pay tribute for that part of Hungary which he ſtill possessed ; while the ſultan enjoyed the imperial and undiſturbed poſſeſſion of all the reſt. At the ſame time he entered into a league with pope Paul III. for the extirpation of hereſy ; but in reality with a view to oppreſs the liberties of Germany. Here, however, his ambition met with a ſevere check ; for though he was ſucceſsful at firſt, he was obliged in 1552 to conclude a peace with the Proteſtants on their own terms ; as has been related under the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Reformation,</hi> n⁰ 26—32.</p><p>By the peace concluded on this occaſion the emperor loſt Metz, Toul, and Verdun, which had formed the barrier of the empire on that quarter; and therefore ſoon after put himſelf at the head of an army, in order to recover theſe three biſhoprics. In order to conceal the deſtination of his army, he gave out, that he intended to lead it into Hungary, to ſecond Maurice in his operations againſt the Infidels ; and as that pretext failed him, when he began to advance towards the Rhine, he propagated a report that he was marching</p></body></text></TEI>