<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:19:10Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>which show their heads near the baſe of the large ones. Theſe are probably the dogs deſcribed by the ancient poets as howling round Scylla. The rock is near 200 feet high, and has a kind of caſtle or fort built on its ſummit with a town called <hi rend="italic">Scylla</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Sciglio,</hi> containing 300 or 4c0 inhabitants on its ſouth side, which gives the title of prince to a Calabreſe family.</p><p>Charybdis is now ſo much diminiſhed, that it ſeems almoſt reduced to nothing in compariſon of what it was, though even yet it is not to be paſſed without danger. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Charybdis.</hi></p><p>In the ſtraits, Mr Brydone informs us, a moſt ſurpriſing phenomenon is to be obſerved. In the heat of ſummer, after the ſea and air have been much agitated, there appears in the heavens over the ſtraits a great variety of singular forms, ſome at rest and others moving with great velocity. Theſe forms, in proportion as the light increaſes, ſeem to become more aerial, till at laſt, ſome time before ſun-riſe, they totally diſappear. The Sicilians repreſent this as the moſt beautiful ſight in nature. Leonti, one of their beſt and lateſt writers, ſays, that the heavens appear crowded with a variety of objects, ſuch as palaces, woods, gardens, &amp;c. beſides the figures of men and other animals that appear in motion among them. Some treatiſes have been written concerning this phenomenon ; but nothing ſatisfactory has been delivered concerning its cauſe.</p><p>Though Sicily lies in a warm climate, the air is healthful, being refreſhed with ſea-breezes on every ſide. It has at all times been remarkably fertile ; but the era of its greateſt proſperity was from the ſiege of Syracuſe by the Athenians to the Carthaginian conqueſts. Then and long after it supplied with grain in years of ſcarcity all the countries upon the Mediterranean except Egypt and the coaſts of Alia, and Rome and Carthage continually. Even now, under all the impediments of ſuperſtition and bad government, its productions are, in quantity and quality, the beſt in Europe. Of the vegetable are grain, wines, oil, fruits, tobacco, mulberry trees for the ſilkworm, cotton, medicinal roots, and ſugar canes. The laſt of theſe flouriſh near Avola and Merilli. They are of an inferior quality to thoſe of the West Indies, but their ſugar is ſweeter than any other. The animal production is similar to that of Italy, but the horned cattle are a ſmaller breed. The coaſts abound with fiſh, particularly with tunney and anchovies ; the export of which forms a very lucrative branch of commerce. There are mines of ſilver, copper, and lead, but none are worked. Near Palma are beds of the beſt ſulphur : at the mouth of the river Giaretta is found a yellow amber, preferable to that of the Baltic ; and in every part of the iſland quarries of marbles, that have furniſhed materials for all the noble edifices of Sicily. The moſt beautiful are in the neighbourhood of Palermo, particularly the yellow, and thoſe that reſemble the verde antique, porphyry, and lapis lazuli. The population of the iſland amounts to 1,300,000 fouls ; not as much again as the ſingle city of Syracuſe formerly contained.</p><p>Here are ſeveral rivers and good ſprings ; but few of the rivers are navigable, having but a ſhort courſe, and descending precipitately from the mountains. The chief are the Cantera, the Janetta, and the Salso ; of which, the two former run from west to eaſt, and the third from north to ſouth.</p><p>Of the mountains in this iſland the moſt noted is Mount Etna, now called <hi rend="italic">Monte Gibellο,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Mοngibellο,</hi> a volcano whoſe eruptions have often proved fatal to the neighbouring country. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Etna.</hi></p><p>Were the Sicilians a cultivated people, among whom thoſe arts were encouraged which not only promote the wealth and comfort of a nation, but also exerciſe the nobler faculties and extend the views of mankind, the circumſtances of their government are ſuch, that it might gradually be improved into a free conſtitution : but to this, the ignorance, ſuperſtition, and poverty, of the people ſeem to be invincible obſtacles. The monarchical power in Sicily is far from being absolute ; and the parliament claims a ſhare of public authority independently of the will of the king, deduced from a compact made between Roger and the Norman barons after the expulſion of the Saracens, This claim is denied by the king, who wiſhes the nobles to conſider their privileges as derived solely from his favour. Hence the government is in a ſituation which greatly reſembles that of our own and the other kingdoms of Europe in the feudal times ; there are continual jealouſies and oppoſitions between the king and the barons, of which an enlightened people might eaſily take advantage, and obtain that ſhare in the conſtitution which might ſecure them from future oppreſſion. In theſe diſputes, the king has the advantage at leaſt of power if not of right; and ſeveral works, in which the claims of the Sicilian barons have been aſſerted, were publicly burned a few years ago.</p><p>As the sovereign holds his court at Naples, Sicily is governed by a viceroy, who is appointed only for three years, though at the end of that term his commiſſion is sometimes renewed. He lives in great ſtate, and, as the repreſentative of the king, his power is very conſiderable. He preſides in all the courts and departments of government, and is commander in chief of all the forces : he calls or diſſolves the parliament when he pleaſes ; and by him all orders, laws, and ſentences, muſt be ſigned : but his office is far from being deſirable, as it generally renders him the object either of the jealouſy of the court of Naples, or of the hatred of the Sicilians.</p><p>The parliament conſiſts of the nobles, the biſhops, and abbots, and the repreſentatives of 43 cities, which are immediately ſubject to the crown. Thoſe cities which are ſubject to any of the nobles ſend no members to the parliament ; in theſe the king has not much authority, and derives little advantage from them. According to the laws, the parliament ought to be aſſembled at the end of every three years : but the government pays little attention to this rule. The common people are in general very much attached to the nobles, and are inclined to take their part in all their differences with the court : but the magiſtrates and principal inhabitants of the cities which belong to theſe feudal lords, wiſh to get rid of their authority, and imagine that they ſhould be leſs oppreſſed, if immediately ſubject to the king : theſe inclinations are not diſagreeable to the court, and are encouraged by moſt of the lawyers, who are of great ſervice to government in conteſt- ing the privileges of the nobles. Many of theſe privileges are now abridged ; and the power of the barons, with reſpect to the adminiſtration of juſtice in their domains, was very properly limited by the viceroy Ca-</p></body></text></TEI>