<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-18T21:24:31Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>curve will be found to be extremely regular, reſembling a hyperbolic arch whoſe
                aſſymptote makes an angle of 30⁰ with the axis. Ordinates were then interpolated
                analytically for every 10 ounces of contained ſalt, and thus the table was
                conſtructed. We did not, however, rest it on one ſeries alone ; but made others, in
                which <hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">4</hi>th of the ſalt was
                repeatedly abſtracted. They agreed, in the caſe of common ſalt, with great
                exactneſs, and in ſome others there were ſome very inconsiderable
                irregularities.</p>
            <p>To ſhow the authority of the tables of ſtrength was by no means our only motive for
                giving an example of the proceſs. It may be of uſe as a pattern for ſimilar
                experiments. But, beſides, it is very inſtructive. We see, in the firſt place, that
                there is a very ſenſible change of density in one or both of the ingredients. For
                the ſeries is of that nature (as we have formerly explained), that if the
                ingredients retained their denſities in every proportion of commixture, the ſpecific
                gravities would have been in arithmetical progreſſion ; whereas we ſee that their
                differences continually diminiſh as the brines grow more dense. We can form ſome
                notion of this by comparing the different brines. Thus in the firſt brine, weighing
                5027 grains, there are 3770 grains of water in a veſſel holding 4200. If the density
                of the water remains the ſame, there is left for the ſalt only as much ſpace as
                would hold 430 grains of water. In this ſpace are lodged 1257 grains of ſalt, and
                its ſpecific</p>
            <p>gravity, in its liquid form, is <hi rend="superscript">1257</hi>/<hi rend="subscript"
                    >430</hi> = 2,8907 very nearly. But in the 8th brine the quantity of water is
                4156, the ſpace left for 157 grains of ſalt is only the bulk oſ 44 grains of water,
                and the density of the ſalt is</p>
            <p><hi rend="superscript">157</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">44 </hi>= 3,568, conſiderably
                greater than before. This</p>
            <p>induced us to continue the dilution of the brine as follows, beginning with the 8th
                brine.</p>
            <table>
                <row>
                    <cell><p>157</p><p>78,5</p></cell>
                    <cell>2)4313 8th brine 2156,5</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>78,5</cell>
                    <cell><p>2156,5</p><p>2105,5</p><p>2)4262,0 9th brine</p></cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>39,7</cell>
                    <cell>2131</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>39,7</cell>
                    <cell><p>2131</p><p>2102</p><p>2)4233 10th brine</p></cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>19,8</cell>
                    <cell><p>2116,5</p><p>2116, 5</p><p>2102</p><p>4218 11th brine.</p></cell>
                </row>
            </table>
            <p>This laſt brine contains 4198,2 grains of water, leaving only the bulk of 1,8 grains
                of water to contain 19,8 of ſalt, ſo that the ſalt is ten times denſer than water.
                This will make the ſtrength 243 inſtead of 210 indicated by the ſpeciſic gravity.
                But we do not pretend to meaſure the denſities with accuracy in theſe diluted
                brines. It is evident from the proceſs that a ſingle grain of exceſs or defect in
                taking out the brine</p>
            <p>and replacing it with water has a ſenſible proportion to the whole variation. But we
                ſee with sufficient evidence, that from the ſtrong to the weak brines the ſpace left
                for the portion oſ ſalt is continually diminiſhing. In the firſt dilution 527<hi
                    rend="superscript">l</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">2</hi> grains of water were added
                to fill up the veſſel ; but <hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript"
                    >8</hi>th of its contents of pure water is only 525 ; ſo that here is a
                diminution of 2<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">2 </hi>grains in
                the ſpace occupied by the remaining ſalt. The ſubſequent additions are 604,7 ; 706,5
                ; 847 ; 1054,5 ; 1405 ; 2102 ; 2105,5 ; 2102; 2102; inſtead of 600; 700; 840; 1050;
                1400 ; 2100; 2100; 2100; 2100. Nothing can more plainly ſhow the condenſation in
                general, though we do not learn whether it happens in one or both of the ingredients
                ;nor do the experiments ſhow with sufficient accuracy the progreſſion of this
                diminution. The exceſſes of the added water being only six or ſeven grains, we
                cannot expect a nice repartition. When the brine is taken out, the upper part of the
                veſſel remains lined with a briny film containing a portion of ſalt and water,
                perhaps equal or ſuperior to the differences. Had our time permitted, we ſhould have
                examined this matter with ſcrupulous attention, uſing a veſſel with a ſtill narrower
                neck, and in each dilution abſtracting one half of the brine. The curve whoſe
                abſciſſae and ordinates repreſent the weight of the contained ſalt and the weight of
                a conſtant bulk of the brine, exhibits the beſt and moſt ſynoptical view of the law
                of condenſation, becauſe the poſition of the tangent in any point, or the</p>
            <p>value of the ſymbol <hi rend="superscript">x</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">y</hi>, always
                ſhows the rate at which</p>
            <p>the ſpecific gravity increaſes or diminiſhes. We are inclined to think that the curve
                in all caſes is of the hyperbolic kind, and complete ; that is, having the tangent
                perpendicular to the axis at the beginning of the curve. The mathematical reader
                will eaſily gueſs the phyſical notions which incline us to this opinion ; and will
                alſo ſee that it is hardly poſſible to diſcover this experimentally, becauſe the
                miſtake of a ſingle grain in the very ſmall ordinates will change the poſition of
                the tangent many degrees. It was for this reaſon that we thought it uſeleſs to
                proſecute the dilution any farther. But we think that it may be proſecuted much
                farther in Dr Watſon's or Mr Achard’s method, viz. by diſſolving equal weights of
                ſalt in two veſſels, of very different capacities, having tubular necks, in which
                the change of bulk may be very accurately obſerved. We can only conclude, that the
                condenſation is greateſt in the ſtrongeſt brines, and probably attains its maximum
                when the quantities of true ſaline matter and water are nearly equal, as in the,
                caſe of vitriolic acid, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>We conſider theſe experiments as abundantly ſufficient for deciding the queſtion “
                Whether the ſalt can be received into the pores of the water, or the water into the
                pores of the ſalt, ſo as to increaſe its weight without increaſing its bulk?" and we
                muſt grant that it may. We do not mean that it is simply lodged in the pores as sand
                is lodged in the interſtices of ſmall ſhot ; but the two together occupy leſs room
                than when ſeparate. The experiments of Mr Achard were insufficient for a decision,
                becauſe made on ſo ſmall a quantity as 600 grains of water. Dr Watſon’s experiments
                have, for the moſt part, the ſame defect. Some of them, however, are of great value
                in this queſtion, and are very fit for aſcer-</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
