<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:22:50Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>thor of ſuch a performance could be taxed with inſanity ? The father upon this was acquitted, and the children returned home covered with ſhame and confuſion. The ſeven tragedies of Sophocles which ſtill remain, together with the Greek Scholia which accompany them, have been tranſlated into Latin by Johnſon, and into Engliſh by Dr Franklin and Mr Potter.</p><p>SOPHOR A, in botany : A genus of plants belonging to the claſs of <hi rend="italic">decandria,</hi> and to the order of <hi rend="italic">monogenia ;</hi> and in the natural ſyſtem arranged under the 32d order, <hi rend="italic">Papilionaceœ.</hi> The calyx is quinquedentate and gibbous above : the corolla is papilionaceous ; the wings being of the ſame length with the vexillum: the ſeed is contained in a legumen. There are 16 ſpecies ; the tetraptera, microphylla, flaveſcens, alopecuroides, tomentoſa, occidentalis, capenſis, aurea, japonica, geniſtoides, auſtralis, tinctoria, alba, lupinoides, biflora, and hirsuta.</p><p>SOPORIFIC, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Soporiferous,</hi> a medicine that produces ſleep. Such are opium, laudanum, the ſeed of poppies, &amp;c. The word is formed from the Latin <hi rend="italic">ſopor</hi> “ ſleep.” The Greeks in place of it uſe the word <hi rend="italic">hypnotic.</hi></p><p>SORBONNE, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Sorbon,</hi> the houſe or college of the faculty of theology eſtabliſhed in the univerſity of Paris. It was founded in 1252 by St Louis, or rather by Robert de Sorben his confeſſor and almoner, firſt canon of Cambray, and afterwards of the church of Paris; who gave his own name to it, which he himſelf took from the village of Sorbon or Serbon, near Sens, where he was born. The foundation was laid in 1250 ; queen Blanche, in the abſence of her husband, furniſhing him with a houſe which had formerly been the palace of Julian the apoſtate, of which ſome remains are ſtill ſeen. Afterwards the king gave him ail the houſes he had in the ſame place, in exchange for ſome others. The college has been ſince magnificently rebuilt by the cardinal de Richelieu. The deſign of its inſtitution was for the uſe of poor ſtudents in divinity. There are lodgings in it for 36 doctors, who are ſaid to be of the <hi rend="italic">ſociety of the Sorbonne ;</hi> thoſe admitted into it without being doctors, are ſaid to be of the <hi rend="italic">hoſpitality of the Sorbonne.</hi> Six regent doctors formerly held lectures every day for an hour and a half each ; three in the morning, and three in the afternoon.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sorbonne,</hi> is alſo uſed in general for the whole faculty of theology at Paris ; as the aſſemblies of the whole body are held in the houſe of the Sorbonne ; and the bachelors of the other houſes of the faculty, as the houſe of Navarre, &amp;c. come hither to hold their <hi rend="italic">ſorbonnique,</hi> or act for being admitted doctor in divinity.</p><p>SORBUS, <hi rend="smallcaps">service-tree,</hi> in botany; a genus of plants belonging to the claſs of <hi rend="italic">icoſandria,</hi> and to the order of <hi rend="italic">trigynia.</hi> The calyx is quinqueſid ; the petals are five ; the berry is below the flower, ſoft and containing three ſeeds. There are three ſpecies ; the aucuparia, domeſtica, and hebrida.</p><p>1.	The <hi rend="italic">aucuparia,</hi> mountain-aſh, quicken-tree, quick- beam, or roan-tree, riſes with a ſtraight upright ſtem and regular branching head, twenty or thirty feet high or more, covered with a ſmooth greyiſh brown bark; pinnated leaves of eight or ten pair of long, narrow, ſerrated folioles, and an odd one, ſmooth on both ſides ; and large umbellate cluſters of white flowers at the ſides</p><p>and ends of the branches, ſucceeded by cluſters of fine red berries, ripe in autumn and winter. There is a variety with yellow ſtriped leaves. This ſpecies grows wild in many parts of this iſland in mountainous places, woods, and hedge-rows, often growing to the ſize of timber; and is admitted into moſt ornamental plantations, for the beauty of its growth, foliage, flowers, and fruit ; the latter, in particular, being produced in numerous red large bunches all over the tree, exhibit a fine appearance in autumn and winter, till devoured by the birds, eſpecially the blackbird and thruſh, which are ſo allured by this fruit as to flock from all parts and feed on it voraciouſly.—In the iſland of Jura the juice of the berries is employed as an acid for punch. It is probable that this tree was in high eſteem with the Druids; for it is more abundant than any other tree in the neighbourhood of thoſe Druidical circles of ſtones, ſo common in North Britain. It is ſtill believed by ſome perſons, that a branch of this tree can defend them from enchantment or witchcraft. Even the cattle are ſuppoſed to be preſerved by it from danger. The dairy-maid drives them to the ſummer paſtures with a rod of the roan-tree, and drives them home again with the ſame. In Strathſpey, we are told, a hoop is made of the wood of this tree on the 1st of May, and all the ſheep and lambs are made to paſs through it.</p><p>2.	The <hi rend="italic">domestica,</hi> or cultivated ſervice-tree, with eatable fruit, grows with an upright ſtem, branching 30 or 40 feet high or more, having a browniſh bark, and the young ſhoots in ſummer covered with a mealy down ; pinnated leaves of eight or ten pair of broadiſh deeply ſerrated lobes and an odd one, downy underneath, and large umbellate cluſters of white flowers at the ſides and ends of the branches, ſucceeded by bunches of large, fleſhy, edible red fruit, of various ſhapes and ſizes. This tree is a native of the ſouthern warm parts of Europe, where its fruit is uſed at table as a deſert, and it is cultivated here in many of our gardens, both as a fruit-tree and as an ornament to diverſify hardy plantations.</p><p>3.	The <hi rend="italic">hebrida,</hi> or mongrel ſervice tree oſ Gothland, grows twenty or thirty feet high ; it has half-pinnated leaves, very downy underneath ; and cluſters of white flowers, ſucceeded by bunches of round reddiſh berries in autumn.</p><p>SORCERY, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Magic</hi> ; the power which ſome perſons were formerly ſuppoſed to poſſeſs of commanding the devil and the infernal ſpirits by ſkill in charms and invocations, and of ſoothing them by fumigations. Sorcery is therefore to be diſtinguiſhed from witchcraft ; an art which was ſuppoſed to be practiſed, not by commanding evil ſpirits, but by compact with the devil. As an inſtance of the power of bad ſmells over demons or evil ſpirits, we may mention the flight of the evil ſpirit mentioned in Tobit into the remote parts of Egypt, produced, it is ſaid, by the ſmell of the burnt liver of a fiſh. Lilly informs us, that one Evans having raiſed a ſpirit at the requeſt of Lord Bothwell and Sir Kenelm Digby, and forgetting a fumigation, the ſpirit, vexed at the diſappointment, pulled him without the circle, and carried him from his houſe in the Minories into a field near Batterſea Cauſeway.</p><p>King James, in his <hi rend="italic">Damonologia,</hi> has given a very full account of the art of ſorcery. “ Two principal things (says he) cannot well in that errand be wanted:</p></body></text></TEI>