<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:23:33Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>plan for defeating the invaſion of a powerful enemy ; and he prudently perſevered in following it, though contrary to his own natural temper and to the genius of his people. He determined to remain altogether upon the defenſive, and to deprive the enemy of ſubſiſtence by laying waste the country before them. The execution of this plan was committed to the mareſchal Montmorency its author, a man happily fitted for ſuch a truſt by the inflexible ſeverity of his diſpoſition. He made choice of a ſtrong camp, under the walls of Avignon, at the confluence of the Rhone and Durance, where he aſſembled a conſiderable army ; while the king, with another body of troops, encamped at Valence, higher up the Rhone. Marſeilles and Arles were the only towns he thought it neceſſary to defend ; and each of theſe he furniſhed with a numerous garriſon of his beſt troops. The inhabitants of the other towns were compelled to abandon their habitations : the fortifications of ſuch places as might have afforded ſhelter to the enemy were thrown down ; corn, forage, and proviſions of every kind, were carried off or deſtroyed ; the mills and ovens were ruined, and the wells filled up or rendered uſeleſs.</p><p>This devaſtation extended from the Alps to Marſeilles, and from the ſea to the confines of Dauphiny ; ſo that the emperor, when he arrived with the van of his army on the confines of Provence, inſtead of that rich and populous country which he expected to enter, beheld nothing but one vaſt and deſert solitude. He did not, however, deſpair of ſucceſs, though he ſaw that he would have many difficulties to encounter; and as an encouragement to his officers, he made them liberal promiſes of lands and honours in France. But all the land which any of them obtained was a grave, and their maſter loſt much honour by this raſh and presumptuous enterprize. After unsucceſsfully inveſting Marſeilles and Arles, after attempting in vain to draw Montmorency from his camp at Avignon, and not daring to attack it, Charles having ſpent two inglorious months in Provence, and loſt one half of his troops by diſeaſe or by famine, was under the neceſſity of ordering a retreat ; and though he was ſome time in motion before the enemy ſuſpected his intention, it was conducted with ſo much precipitation and diſorder, as to deserve the name of a flight, ſince the light troops of France turned it into a perfect rout. The invaſion of Picardy was not more ſucceſsful: the imperial forces were obliged to retire without effecting any conqueſt oſ importance.</p><p>Charles had no ſooner conducted the ſhattered remains of his army to the frontiers of Milan, than he ſet out ſor Genoa ; and unwilling to expoſe himſelf to the ſcorn of the Italians after ſuch a reverſe of fortune, he embarked directly for Spain.</p><p>Meanwhile Francis gave himſelf up to that vain reſentment which had formerly diſgraced the proſperity of his rival. They had frequently, in the courſe of their quarrels, given each other the lie, and mutual challenges had been ſent ; which, though productive of no ſerious conſequences between the parties, had a powerful tendency to encourage the pernicious practice of duelling. Charles, in his invective pronounced at Rome, had publicly accuſed Francis of perfidy and breach of faith ; Francis now exceeded Charles in the indecency of his accuſations. The Dauphin dying ſuddenly, his death</p><p>was imputed to poiſon: Montecuculi his cup-bearer was put to the rack ; and that unhappy nobleman, in the agonies of torture, accuſed the emperor’s generals Gonzaga and de Leyva, of inſtigating him to the deteſtable act. The emperor himſelf was ſuſpected; nay, this extorted confeſſion, and ſome obſcure hints, were conſidered as inconteſtable proofs of his guilt ; though it was evident to all mankind, that neither Charles nor his generals could have any inducement to perpetrate ſuch a crime, as Francis was ſtill in the vigour of life himſelf, and had two ſons beſides the dauphin, grown up to a good age.</p><p>But the incenſed monarch’s reſentment did not ſtop here. Francis was not ſatisfied with endeavouring to blacken the character of his rival by an ambiguous teſtimony which led to the moſt injurious ſuſpicions, and upon which the moſt cruel conductions had been put; he was willing to add rebellion to murder. For this purpoſe he went to the parliament of Paris ; where being ſeated with the uſual ſolemnities, the advocate-general appeared, and accuſed Charles of Auſtria (ſo he affected to call the emperor) of having violated the treaty of Cambray, by which he was freed from the homage due to the crown of France for the counties of Artois and Flanders ; adding, that this treaty being now void, he was ſtill to be conſidered as a vaſſal of France, and conſequently had been guilty of rebellion in taking arms againſt his sovereign. The charge was ſuſtained, and Charles was ſummoned to appear before the parliament of Paris at a day fixed. The term expired ; and no perſon appearing in the emperor’s name, the parliament gave judgment, that Charles of Auſtria had forfeited, by rebellion and contumacy, the counties of Flanders and Artois, and declared theſe fiefs reunited to the crown of France.</p><p>Francis, ſoon after this vain diſplay of his animoſity, marched into the Low Countries, as if he had intended to execute the sentence pronounced by his parliament ; but a ſuſpenſion of arms took place, through the interpoſition of the queens of France and Hungary, before any thing of conſequence was effected : and this cesſation of hoſtilities was followed by a truce, concluded at Nice, through the mediation of the reigning pontiff Paul III. of the family of Farneſe, a man of a venerable character and pacific diſpoſition.</p><p>Each of theſe rival princes had ſtrong reaſons to incline them to peace. The finances of both were exhausted ; and the emperor, the moſt powerful of the two, was deeply impreſſed with the dread of the Turkiſh arms, which Francis had drawn upon him by a league with Solyman. In conſequence of this league, Barbaroſſa with a great fleet appeared on the coaſt of Naples; filled that kingdom with conſternation; landed without reſiſtance near Taranto ; obliged Caſtro, a place of ſome ſtrength, to ſurrender ; plundered the adjacent country ; and was taking meaſures for ſecuring and extending his conqueſts, when the unexpected arrival of Doria, the famous Genoele admiral, together with the pope’s galleys and a ſquadron of the Venetian fleet, made it prudent for him to retire. The ſultan’s forces alſo invaded Hungary, where Mahmet the Turkiſh general, after gaining ſeveral inferior advantages, defeated the Germans in a great battle at Eſſek on the Drave. Happily for Charles and Europe it was not in Francis’s power at this juncture either to join the Turks or aſ-</p></body></text></TEI>