<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:20:07Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>gambols ; in which they are very agile and silent : even when ſhot at, do not make the leaſt noiſe : but will unite in company, knit their brows, and gnaſh their teeth, as if they meant to attack the enemy : are very common in the Cape de Verd islands.</p><p>24.	The muſtache, or cercopithecus cephus, has a beard on the cheeks ; the crown of the head is yellowiſh : the feet are black, and the tip of the tail is of an aſh colour. Its tail is much longer than the body and head, being 19 or 20 inches in length. The female menſtruates.</p><p>25.	The mangabey, cercopithecus æthiops, or whiteeyed monkey, has a long, black, naked, and dog-like face : the upper eye-lids of a pure white : ears black, and like the human : no canine teeth : hairs on the ſides of the face beneath the cheeks, longer than the rest : tail long : colour of the whole body tawny and black : flat nails on the thumbs and fore-fingers ; blunt claws on the others : hands and feet black —Shown in London ſome years ago ; place uncertain : that deſcribed by M. de Buffon came from Madagaſcar ; was very good- natured ; went on all-fours.</p><p>26.	The egret, or cercopithecus aygula, has a long face, and an upright fharp-pointed tuft of hair on the top of the head. The hair on the forehead is black : the tuft, and the upper part of the body light-grey ; the belly white : the eye-brows are large ; the beard very ſmall. Size of a ſmall cat. They inhabit Java. They fawn on men, on their own ſpecies, and embrace each other. They play with dogs, if they have none of their own ſpecies with them. If they ſee a monkey of another kind, they greet him with a thouſand grimaces. When a number of them sleep, they put their heads together. They make a continual noiſe during night.</p><p>27.	The rillow, cercopithecus ſinicus, or Chineſe bonnet, has a long ſmooth noſe, of a whitiſh colour ; hair on the crown of the head long, lying flat, and parted like that of a man ; colour, a pale cinereous brown, Inhabit Ceylon. They keep in great troops ; and rob gardens of their fruit, and fields of their corn ; to prevent which, the natives are obliged to watch the whole day : yet theſe animals are ſo bold, that, when driven from one end of the field, they will immediately enter at the other, and carry off with them as much as their mouth and arms can hold. Boſman, ſpeaking of the thefts of the monkeys of Guinea, ſays, that they will take in each paw one or two ſtalks of millet, as many under their arms, and two or three in their mouth ; and thus laden, hop away on their hind-legs : but, if purſued, they fling away all, except what is in their mouths, that it may not impede their flight. They are very nice in the choice of the millet ; examine every ſtalk : and if they do not like it, fling it away : ſo that this delicacy does more harm to the fields than their thievery.</p><p>28.	The tawny monkey, or cercopithecus fulvus, has long tuſks in the lower jaw : the viſage is long and fleſh coloured, with fleſh coloured ears, and a flattiſh noſe. Inhabits India. This is a very ill natured animal,</p><p>about the ſize of a cat ; it was lately in the poſſeſſion of Mr Brook, an animal merchant and exhibitor in London : The upper parts of the body are covered with a pale tawny coloured fur, which is aſh coloured at the roots ; the hinder part of the back is orange coloured, the legs aſh coloured, the belly white, and the tail ſhorter than the body.</p><p>29.	King monkey, full-bottom monkey, or cercopi- thecus regalis, has no thumb on the hands ; the head, cheeks, throat, and shoulders, are covered with long, flowing, coarſe hairs. Inhabits the foreſts of Sierra Leona in Guinea, where it is called <hi rend="italic">bey,</hi> or king <hi rend="italic">monkey. </hi>It is above three feet high when erect ; The head is ſmall, with a ſhort, black, naked face ; and the head, cheeks, throat, neck, and ſhoulders, are covered with long, coarſe, flowing hairs, of a dirty yellowiſh colour, mixed with black, and reſembling a full-bottomed wig ; the body, arms, and legs, are covered with ſhort hairs of a fine gloſſy black colour ; the hands are naked, and have no thumbs ; the feet have five very long ſlender toes, which are armed with narrow pointed claws ; the tail is very long, and is covered with ſnow white hairs, having a tuft at the end ; the body and limbs are very ſlender ; Its ſkin is held in high eſtimation by the negroes for making pouches and gun cafes.</p><p>IV.	<hi rend="smallcaps">Sapajous, Sapaji,</hi> have prehenſile tails, and no cheek-pouches. Theſe animals have long tails, which, at the extremity, is generally deprived of hair on the under side, and covered with a ſmooth ſkin ; this part they can fold, extend, curl up, and unfold at pleaſure ; by which they are enabled to hang upon branches, or to lay hold of any thing which is beyond the reach of their hands, uſing the extremity of the tail like a finger or hand ; the partition between the noſtrils is very thick, and the apertures are ſituated on the ſides of the noſe ; the buttocks are clothed with hair, and have no calloſities ; the females of this ſubgenus do not menſtruate ; and this race of animals is only to be found in America : This ſubdiviſion of the genus is made with great propriety by Dr Gmelin, in imitation of the Count de Buffon.</p><p>30.	The guariba, ſapajus Beelzebub, or the preacher monkey, has black ſhining eyes ; ſhort round ears ; and a round beard under the chin and throat. The hairs on the body are of a ſhining black, long, yet lie ſo cloſe on each other that the animal appears quite ſmooth : the feet and end of the tail are brown ; the tail very long, and always twilled at the end. Size of a fox. Inhabit the woods of Brazil and Guiana in vaſt numbers, and make a moſt dreadful howling. Sometimes one mounts on a higher branch, the rest ſeat themſelves beneath : the firſt begins as if it was to harangue, and ſets up ſo loud and ſharp a howl as may be heard a vaſt way, and a perſon at a diſtance would think that a hundred joined in the cry : after a certain ſpace, he gives a ſignal with his hand, when the whole aſſembly joins in chorus ; but on another ſignal is silent, and the orator finiſhes his addreſs @@<hi rend="smallcaps">(b).</hi> Their clamour is the moſt diſagreeable and tremendous that can be conceived ; owing to a hollow and hard bone placed in the throat.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">@@@(b)</hi> A singular account, yet related by Marcgrave and ſeveral other writers. Marcgrave is a writer of the firſt authority, and a moſt able naturaliſt, long resident in the Brasils, and ſpeaks from his own knowledge.</p></body></text></TEI>