<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-18T21:21:51Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>ven in the evening, and the penalty of obſtructing is 100 l. Every maker of ſoap
                before he begins any making, if within the bills of mortality, ſhall give 12 hours,
                if elſewhere 24 hours, notice in writing to the officer, of the time when he intends
                to begin, on pain of 50 l. No maker ſhall remove any ſoap unſiirveyed on pain of 20
                l. without giving proper notice of his intention. And if any maker ſhall conceal any
                ſoap or materials, he ſhall forfeit the ſame, and alſo 500l. Every barrel of ſoap
                ſhall contain 256 lb. avoirdupois, half barrel 128 lb. firkin 64lb. half-firkin
                32lb. beſides the weight or tare of each caſk : and all ſoap, excepting hard cake
                ſoap and ball ſoap, ſhall be put into ſuch caſks and no other, on pain of
                forfeiture, and 5 l. The maker ſhall weekly enter in writing at the next office the
                ſoap made by him in each week, with the weight and quantity at each boiling, on pain
                of 50 l ; and within one week after entry clear off the duties, on pain of double
                duty. See, beſides the ſtatutes above cited, 5 Geo. III. cap. 43. 12 Geo. III. cap.
                46. 11 Geo. cap. 30. 1 Geo. ſtat. 2. cap. 36.</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Starkey's </hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Soap.</hi> See <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Chemistry,</hi> n⁰ 1027.</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Acid </hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Soap.</hi> This is formed by
                the addition of concentrated acids to the expreſſed oils. Thus the oil is rendered
                partially soluble in water ; but the union is not ſufficiently complete to anſwer
                any valuable purpoſe,</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Soap-Berry Tree.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Sapindus.</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Soap-Earth.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Steatites.</hi></p>
            <p>SOAPWORT. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Saponaria.</hi></p>
            <p>SOC (Sax.), ſignifies power or liberty to miniſter juſtice or execute laws : alſo the
                circuit or territory wherein ſuch power is exerciſed. ‘ Whence our law-Latin word
                    <hi rend="italic">ſocca</hi> is uſed for a ſeigniory or lordſhip enfranchiſed by
                the king, with the liberty oſ holding or keeping a court of his s<hi rend="italic"
                    >ockmen :</hi> And this kind of liberty continues in divers parts oſ England to
                this day, and is known by the names of <hi rend="italic">ſoke</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">ſoken.</hi></p>
            <p>SOCAGE, in its moſt general and extenſive ſignification, ſeems to denote a tenure by
                any certain and determinate ſervice.@@ And in this ſenſe it is by our ancient writer
                s conſtantly put in oppoſition to chivalry or knight-ſervice, where the render was
                precarious and uncertain. The ſervice muſt therefore be certain, in order to
                denominate it ſocage ; as to hold by fealty and 20 s. rent ; or, by homage, fealty,
                and 20 s. rent ; or, by homage and fealty without rent ; or, by fealty and certain
                corporal ſervice, as ploughing the lord’s land for three days ; or, by fealty only
                without any other ſervice : for all theſe are tenures in ſocage.</p>
            <p>Socage is of two sorts : free-socage, where the ſervices are not only certain but
                honourable ; and <hi rend="italic">villein-</hi>ſoeage, where the ſervices, though
                certain, are of a baſer nature (ſee <hi rend="smallcaps">Villenage).</hi> Such as
                hold by the former tenure are called, in Glanvil and other ſubſequent authors, by
                the name of <hi rend="italic">liberi sοkemanni,</hi> or tenants in free- ſocage. The
                word is derived from the Saxon appellation soc<hi rend="italic">,</hi> which
                ſignifies liberty or privilege ; and, being joined to an uſual termination, is
                called <hi rend="italic">ſocage,</hi> in Latin socagium<hi rend="italic"> ;</hi>
                ſignifying thereby a free or privileged tenure.</p>
            <p>It ſeems probable that the ſocage-tenures were the relics of Saxon liberty; retained
                by ſuch perſons as had neither,forfeited them to the king, nor been obliged to
                exchange their tenure for the more honourable, as it was called, but at the ſame
                time more burthenſome, te</p>
            <p>nure of knight-ſervice. This is peculiarly remarkable in the tenure which prevails in
                Kent, called <hi rend="italic">gavelkind, </hi>which is generally acknowledged to be
                a ſpecies of focage-tenure ; the preſervation whereof inviolate from the innovations
                of the Norman conqueror is a fact univerſally known. And thoſe who thus preſerved
                their liberties were ſaid to hold in free and common ſocage.</p>
            <p>As therefore the grand criterion and distinguiſhing mark of this ſpecies of tenure
                are the having its renders or ſervices aſcertained, it will include under it all
                other methods of holding free lands by certain and invariable rents and duties ; and
                in particular, <hi rend="italic">Petit </hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Serjeanty,
                    </hi><hi rend="italic">Tenure in </hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Burgage,</hi>
                and <hi rend="smallcaps">Gavelkind.</hi> See theſe articles.</p>
            <p>SOCIETY, a number of rational and moral beings, united for their common preſervation
                and happineſs.</p>
            <p>There are ſhoals of fiſhes, herds of quadrupeds, and flocks of birds. But till
                obſervation enable us to determine with greater certainty, how far the inferior
                animals are able to look through a ſeries of means to the end which theſe are
                calculated to produce, how far their conduct may be influenced by the hope of reward
                and the fear of punishment, and whether they are at all capable of moral
                diſtinctions—we cannot with propriety apply to them the term <hi rend="italic"
                    >Society.</hi> We call crows, and beavers, and ſeveral other ſpecies oſ animals,
                    <hi rend="italic">gregarious ;</hi> but it is hardly good Engliſh to ſay that
                they are <hi rend="italic">ſocial.</hi></p>
            <p>It is only human ſociety, then, that can become the ſubject of our preſent
                inveſtigation. The phenomena which it preſents are highly worthy of our notice.</p>
            <p>Such are the advantages which each individual evidently derives from living in a
                ſocial ſtate ; and ſo helpleſs does any human being appear in a solitary ſtate, that
                we are naturally led to conclude, that if there ever was a period at which mankind
                were ſolitary beings, that period could not be of long duration ; for their aversion
                to ſolitude and love of society would ſoon induce them to enter into ſocial union.
                Such is the opinion which we are led to conceive, when we compare our own condition
                as members of civilized and enlightened society with that of the brutes around us,
                or with that of ſavages in the earlier and ruder periods of ſocial life. When we
                hear of Indians wandering naked through the woods, deſtitute of arts, unskilled in
                agriculture, ſcarce capable oſ moral diſtinctions, void of all religious ſentiments,
                or poſſeſſed with the moſt abſurd notions concerning ſuperior powers, and procuring
                means of ſubſiſtence in a manner equally precarious with that of the beaſts of
                prey—we look down with pity on their condition, or turn from it with horror. When we
                view the order of cultivated ſociety, and conſider our inſtitutions, arts, and
                manners—we rejoice over our ſuperior wiſdom and happineſs.</p>
            <p>Man in a civilized ſtate appears a being of a ſuperior order to man in a ſavage ſtate
                ; yet ſome philoſophers tell us, that it is only he who, having been educated in
                ſociety. has been taught to depend upon others, that can be helpleſs or miſerable
                when placed in a ſolitarv ſtate. They view the ſavage who exerts himſelf with
                intrepidity to ſupply his wants, or bears them with fortitude, as the greateſt hero,
                and poſſeſſing the greateſt happineſs. And therefore if we agree with them, that the
                propenſities of nature may have prompted men to</p>
            <p>@@@[mu] <hi rend="italic">Blackft. Comment. </hi>vol. ii.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
