<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:23:14Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>reſt, and rolling down huge ſtones from the mountains upon the Moors (the name by which the Saracens were known in Spain), no fewer than 124,000 of theſe unhappy people periſhed in one day. The remainder fled till they were ſtopped by a river, and beginning to coaſt it, part of a mountain ſuddenly fell down, ſtopped up the channel of the river, and either cruſhed or drowned, by the sudden riſing of the water, almoſt every one of that vaſt army.</p><p>The Moors were not ſo much diſheartened by this diſaſter, but that they made a ſecond attempt againſt Don Pelagio. Their ſucceſs was as bad as ever, the greateſt part of their army being cut in pieces or taken ; in conſequence of which, they loſt all the Aſturias, and never dared to enter the lifts with Pelagio afterwards. Indeed, their bad ſucceſs had in a great meaſure taken from them the desire of conquering a country where little or nothing was to be got ; and therefore they rather directed their force againſt France, where they hoped for more plunder. Into this country they poured in prodigious multitudes ; but were utterly defeated, in 732, by Charles Martel, with the loſs of 300,000 men, as the hiſtorians of thoſe times pretend.</p><p>Don Pelagio died in 737, and ſoon after his death ſuch inteſtine diviſions broke out among the Moors, as greatly favoured the increaſe of the Chriſtian power. In 745 Don Alonſo the Catholic, ſon-in-Iaw to Pelagio, in conjunction with his brother Froila, paſſed the mountains, and fell upon the northern part of Galicia ; and meeting with little reſiſtance, he recovered almoſt the whole of that province in a ſingle campaign. Next year he invaded the plains of Leon and Caſtile ; and before the Moors could aſſemble any force to oppose him, he reduced Aſtorgas, Leon, Saldagna, Montes de Oca, Amaya, Alava, and all the country at the foot of the mountains. The year following he puſhed his conqueſts as far as the borders of Portugal, and the next campaign ravaged the country as far as Caſtile. Being ſensible, however, that he was yet unable to defend the flat country which he had conquered, he laid the whole of it waste, obliged the Chriſtians to retire to the mountains, and carried off all the Moors for Haves. Thus ſecured by a deſert frontier, he met with no interruption for ſome years ; during which time, as his kingdom advanced in ſtrength, he allowed his ſubjects gradually to occupy part of the flat country, and to rebuild Leon and Aſtorgas, which he had demoliſhed. He died in 757, and was ſucceeded by his ſon Don Frυila. In his time Abdelrahman, the khaliff’s viceroy in Spain, threw off the yoke, and rendered himſelf independent, fixing the ſeat of his government at Cordova. Thus the inteſtine diviſions among the Moors were compoſed; yet their ſucceſs ſeems to have been little better than before ; for, ſoon after, Froila encountered the Moors with ſuch ſucceſs, that 54,000 of them were killed on the ſpot, and their general taken priſoner. Soon after he built the city of Oviedo, which he made the capital of his dominions, in order to be in a better condition to defend the flat country, which he now determined to people.</p><p>In the year 758 the power of the Saracens received another blow by the riſe of the kingdom of Navarre. This kingdom, we are told, took its origin from an accidental meeting of gentlemen, to the number of 600,</p><p>at the tomb oſ an hermit named <hi rend="italic">John,</hi> who had died among the Pyrenees. At this place, where they had met on account of the ſuppoſed ſanctity of the deceaſed, they took occaſion to converſe on the cruelty of the Moors, the miſeries to which the country was expoſed, and the glory that would reſult from throwing off their yoke ; which, they ſuppoſed, might eaſily be done, by reaſon of the ſtrength of their country. On mature deliberation, the project was approved; one Don Garcia Ximenes was appointed king, as being of illuſtrious birth, and looked upon as a perſon of great abilities. He recovered Ainſa, one of the principal towns oſ the country, out of the hands of the infidels, and his ſucceſſor Don Garcia Inigas extended his territories as far as Biſcay ; however, the Moors ſtill poſſeſſed Portugal, Murcia, Andaluſia, Valentia, Granada, Tortoſa, with the interior part of the country as far as the mountains of Caſtile and Saragoſſa. Their internal diſſenſions, which revived after the death of Abdelrahman, contributed greatly to reduce the power of the infidels in general. In 778, Charles the Great being invited by ſome diſcontented Mooriſh governors, entered Spain with two great armies ; one paſſing through Catalonia, and the other through Navarre, where he puſhed his conqueſts as far as the Ebro. On his return he was attacked and defeated by the Moors ; though this did not hinder him from keeping poſſeſſion of all thoſe places he had already reduced. At this time he ſeems to have been maſter of Navarre: however, in 831 count Azner, revolting from Pepin ſon to the emperor Louis, again revived the independency of Navarre ; but the</p><p>ſovereigns did not assume the title of kings till the time oſ Don Garcia, who began to reign in 857.</p><p>In the mean time, the kingdom founded by Don Pelagio, now called the kingdom of <hi rend="italic">Leon</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Oviedo,</hi> continued to increaſe rapidly in ſtrength, and many advantages were gained over the Moors, who having two enemies to contend with, loſt ground every day. In 921, however, they gained a great victory over the united forces of Navarre and Leon, by which the whole force of the Chriſtians in Spain muſt have been entirely broken, had not the victors conducted their affairs ſo wretchedly, that they ſuſſered themſelves to be almoſt entirely cut in pieces by the remains of the Chriſtian army. In ſhort, the Chriſtians became at length ſo terrible to the Moors, that it is probable they could not long have kept their footing in Spain, had not a great general, named <hi rend="italic">Mohammed Ebn Amir Almanzor,</hi> appeared, in 979, to ſupport their sinking cauſe. This man was visir to the king of Cordova, and being exceedingly provoked againſt the Chriſtians on account of what his countrymen had ſuffered from them, made war with the moſt implacable fury. He took the city  of Leon, murdered the inhabitants, and reduced the houses to aſhes. Barcelona ſhared the ſame fate ; Caſtile was reduced to a deſert ; Galicia and Portugal ravaged ; and he is ſaid to have overcome the Chriſtians in fifty different engagements. At laſt, having taken and demoliſhed the city of Compoſtella, and carried off in triumph the gates of the church of St James, a flux happened to break out among his troops, which the ſuperſtitious Chriſtians ſuppoſed to be a divine judgement on account of his ſacrilege. Taking it for granted, therefore, that the Moors were now entirely deſtitute of all heavenly aid, they fell upon them with</p></body></text></TEI>