<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:19:48Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ſufficient for three), round my fore-finger, and to give it a twiſt at the bottom ; which is done with the utmoſt expedition, and gives no occaſion for the uſe of pins. Theſe rolled paper-cases being likewiſe of a form more nearly reſembling that of a cocoon, with a much narrower opening on the top than the others, takes away the seceſſity of wasting much silk in the outer web, and conſequently leaves more to be employed in forming the ball. The ſilk is readily taken out of theſe cases by untwiſting the bottom ; and if this be done with moderate care, and the papers are preſerved, they will ſerve ſeveral times for the like purpoſe.”</p><p>Others adviſe, that when the ſilk worms are preparing to ſpin, little buſhes of heath, broom, or twigs, ſhould be ſtuck upright near the ſhelf or box in which they are incloſed : the worms mount theſe, and attach their web to them.</p><p>When the worms are ready to mount, in order to ſpin, if the weather be hot, attended with thunder, you will see them in a languiſhing condition ; your care muſt then be to revive them, which is effected thus : Take a few eggs and onions, and fry them in a pan with ſome ſtale hog’s lard, the ranker the better, and make pancake ; which done, carry it ſmoaking hot into the room where they are kept, and go round the chamber with it. You will be ſurpriſed to see how the ſmell revives them, excites thoſe to eat who have not done feeding, and makes the others that are ready to ſpin climb up the twigs.</p><p>In about ten or twelve days, according to the accounts which we have received from Mr Andrew Wright of Paiſley, it may be saſely concluded, that if the worms have finiſhed their work, the cocoons may be collected.</p><p>We ſhall now diſtinguiſh the cocoons from one another according to their value or their uſe, and conſider the method of managing each. They may be diſtinguiſhed into the good and bad. The good cocoons maybe known by theſe marks : they are little, ſtrong, and firm ; have a fine grain, both ends are round, and they are free from ſpots. Among the good cocoons alſo may be arranged thoſe which are called <hi rend="italic">calcined</hi> cocoons, in which</p><p>the worm, in conſequence of ſickneſs, is petrified or reduced to a fine powder. Theſe cocoons produce more ſilk than others, and are ſold in Piedmont at half as much again. They may be diſtinguiſhed by the noiſe which, the worm makes when the cocoon is ſhaken. Of the bad cocoons there are six ſpecies : 1. The <hi rend="italic">pointed cocoons, </hi>one extremity of which ends in a point ; the ſilk which covers the point is weak, and ſoon breaks or tears. 2. The <hi rend="italic">cocalons,</hi> which are bigger, but the contexture is weak. 3. The <hi rend="italic">dupions,</hi> or double cocoons, which have been formed by the joint labour of two and ſometimes of three worms. 4. The souff<hi rend="italic">lons,</hi> which have a looſe contexture, ſometimes ſo loose that they are transparent.</p><p>5.	The <hi rend="italic">perforated cocoons,</hi> which have a hole at one end.</p><p>6.	The <hi rend="italic">bad choquette,</hi> which is compoſed of defective cocoons, ſpotted or rotten. Beſides theſe there is the <hi rend="italic">good choquette,</hi> which does not properly belong to either of theſe two classes : it is formed of thoſe cocoons in which the worm dies before the ſilk is brought to perfection. The worms adhere to one side of the cocoon, and therefore when the cocoon is ſhaken will not rattle : the ſilk is as fine, but is not of ſo bright a colour, nor is ſo ſtrong and nervous, as that which is obtained from good cocoons.</p><p>The cocoons which are kept for breeding are called <hi rend="italic">royal</hi> cocoons. For ſelecting and preſerving theſe, we have been favoured with some valuable inſtructions by Mr Wright of Paiſley, which we ſhall preſent to our readers—The largeſt and beſt cocoons ought to be kept for breed, about an equal number of males and females; the cocoons that contain the former are ſharper pointed at the ends than thoſe that contain the latter. Although it ſhould happen that there are more females than males, little inconvenience or ill conſequences can ariſe from it, as one male will ſerve two or three females, if the time of their coming out of the cocoons anfwer. About 12 or 15 days after they begin to ſpin, the cocoons for breed may be laid on ſheets of white paper ; about this time the moth opens for itſelf a paſſage through the end of its cocoon, and iſſues out. When the female has laid her eggs, which on an average may amount to 250, they are ſpread upon ſheets of paper and hung up to dry in ſome place where they may not be expoſed to the heat of the ſun : after being dried they muſt be kept in a cool: well-aired place, where neither vapours nor moiſture can reach them. That they may be preſerved ſrom external accidents, as insects of different kinds will deſtroy them, and mice is their enemy in all the ſtages of their exiſtence, they ſhould be kept in ſtone pots or glaſs bottles with their mouths stopped, and there remain until brought out next ſeaſon to be hatched.</p><p>The cocoons from which the silk is to be immediately wound muſt be expoſed to the heat of an oven, in order to kill the chryſalis or aurelia, which would otherwiſe eat its way through the cocoon, and render it uſeleſs. The following directions are given for managing this proceſs. by one of the firſt silk manufacturers in Italy.</p><p>Put your cocoons in long fhallow baſkets, and fill them up within an inch of the top. You then cover them with paper, and put a wrapper over that. Theſe baſkets are to be diſpoſed in an oven, whoſe heat is as near as can be that of an oven from which the. bread is juſt drawn after being baked. When your cocoons have remained therein near an hour, you muſt draw them out; and to ſee whether all tire worms are dead, draw out a dupion from the middle of your baſket and open it : if the worm be dead, you may conclude all the reſt are ſo; becauſe the contexture of the dupion being ſtronger than that of the other cocoons, it is conſequently leſs eaſy to be penetrated by the heat. You muſt obſerve to take it from the middle of the baſket, becauſe in that part the heat is least perceptible. After you have drawn your baſkets from the oven, you muſt firſt cover each of them with a woollen, blanket or rug, leaving the wrapper besides, and then you pile them above one another. If your baking has ſucceeded, your woollen cover will be all over wet with a kind of dew, the thickness of your little finger. If there be leſs, it is a sign your coceons have been too much or too little baked. If too much baked, the worm, being over-dried, cannot transpire a humour he no longer contains, and your cocoon is then burnt. It not enough baked, the worm has not been ſufficiently penetrated by the heat to diſtil the liquor he contains, and in that case is not dead.</p><p>You muſt let your baſkets ſtand thus covered five or  six hours if poſſible, in order to keep in the heat, as this makes an end of ſtifling thoſe worms which might have avoided the firſt impreſſion of the fire. You are like-</p></body></text></TEI>