<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:19:14Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>lour, and elegant erudition, all concurred to render him the ornament and delight of the Engliſh court : and as the credit which he enjoyed with the queen and the earl of Leiceſter was wholly employed in the encouragement of genius and literature, his praiſes have been tranſmitted with advantage to poſterity. No perſon was ſo low as not to become an object of his humanity. After the battle of Zutphen, while he was lying on the field mangled with wounds, a bottle of water was brought him to relieve his thirſt ; but obſerving a ſoldier near him in a like miſerable condition, he ſaid, <hi rend="italic">This man's necessity is ſtill greater than mine ;</hi> and reſigned to him the bottle of water. Beſides his <hi rend="italic">Arcadia, </hi>he wrote ſeveral ſmaller pieces both in proſe and verſe, which have been publiſhed.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sidney</hi> (Algernon), was the ſecond ſon of Robert earl of Leiceſter, and of Dorothy eldest daughter of the earl of Northumberland. He was born about the year 1617. During the civil wars he took part againſt the king, and diſtinguished himſelf as a colonel in the army of the parliament. He was afterwards appointed one of king Charles’s judges, but declined appearing in that court. During the uſurpation of Cromwel, Sidney, who was a violent republican, retired to the country, and ſpent his time in writing thoſe diſcourſes on government which have been ſo deſervedly celebrated. After the death of the Protector, he again took part in the public tranſactions of his country, and was abroad on an embaſſy to Denmark when king Charles was reſtored. Upon this he retired to Hamburgh, and afterwards to Francfort, where he reſided till 1677, when he returned to England and obtained from the king a pardon. It has been affirmed, but the ſtory deserves no credit, that during his residence abroad king Charles hired ruffians to asſaſſinate him. After his return he made repeated attempts to procure a seat in parliament, but all of them proved unſucceſsful. After the intention of the commons to ſeclude the duke of York from the throne had been defeated by the ſudden diſſolution of parliament, Sidney joined with eagerneſs the councils of Russel, Eſſex, and Monmouth, who had reſolved to oppoſe the duke’s ſucceſſion by force of arms. Frequent-meetings were held at London; while, at the same time, a let of ſubordinate conſpirators, who were not, however, admitted into their confidence, met and embraced the moſt deſperate reſolutions. Keiling, one of theſe men, diſcovered the whole conſpiracy ; and Algernon Sidney, together with his noble aſſociates, was immediately thrown into priſon, and no art was left unattempted in order to involve them in the guilt of the meaner conſpirators.</p><p>Howard, an abandoned nobleman, without a ſingle ſpark of virtue or honour, was the only witneſs againſt Sidney ; but as the law required two, his diſcourſes on government, found unpubliſhed in his cloſet, were conſtrued into treaſon, and declared equivalent to another witneſs. It was in vain for Sidney to plead that papers were no legal evidence ; that it could not be proved they were written by him ; and that if they were, they contained nothing treaſonable. The defence was over ruled ; he was declared guilty, condemned, and executed ! His attainder was reverſed in the firſt year of king William.</p><p>He was a man of extraordinary courage ; ſteady even to obſtinacy ; of a ſincere but rough and boiſterous</p><p>temper. Though he proſeſſed his belief in the Christian religion, he was an enemy to an eſtabliſhed church, and even, according to Burnet, to every kind of public worſhip. In his principles he was a zealous republican: government was always his favourite ſtudy ; and his eſsays on that ſubject are a proof of the progreſs which he made.</p><p>SIDON (anc. geog.), a city of Phoenicia in Asia, famous in Scripture for its riches, arising from the extenſive commerce carried on by its inhabitants. Heavy judgments were denounced againſt the Sidonians on account of their wickedneſs, which were accompliſhed in the time of Ochus king of Perſia : for that monarch having come againſt them with an army on account of their rebellion, the city was betrayed by its king ; upon which the wretched inhabitants were ſeized with deſpair ; they ſet fire to their houſes, and 40,000, with their wives and children, periſhed in the flames.</p><p>This city is now called <hi rend="italic">Saide,</hi> and, according to Mr Bruce’s account, not only its harbour is filled up with  sand, but the pavement of the ancient city ſtood 7½ feet lower than the ground on which the preſent city ſtands. Volney defcribes it as an ill-built dirty city. Its length along the ſea-ſhore is about 600 paces, and its breadth 150. At the north-west side of the town is the caſtle, which is built in the ſea itſelf, 80 paces from the main land, to which it is joined by arches. To the west of this caſtle is a ſhoal 15 feet high above the ſea, and about 2c0 paces long. The ſpace between this ſhoal and the caſtle forms the road, but veſſels are not ſafe there in bad weather. The ſhoal, which extends along the town, has a baſon incloſed by a decayed pier. This was the ancient port ; but it is ſo choaked up by fand, that boats alone can enter its mouth near the caſtle. Fakr-el-din, emir of the Druſes, deſtroyed all theſe little ports from Bairout to Acre, by sinking boats and ſtones to prevent the Turkiſh ſhips from entering them. The baſon of Saide, if it were emptied, might contain 20 or 25 ſmall veſſels. On the ſide of the ſea, the town is abſolutely without any wall; and that which encloſes it on the land ſide is no better than a priſon- wall. The whole artillery does not exceed six cannons, and theſe are without carriages and gunners. The garriſon ſcarcely amounts to 100 men. The water comes from the river <hi rend="italic">A</hi>oula, through open canals, from which it is fetched by the women. Theſe canals ſerve alſo to water the orchards of mulberry and lemon trees.</p><p>Saide is a conſiderable trading town, and is the chief emporium of Damaſcus and the interior country. The French, who are the only Europeans to be found there, have a conſul, and ſive or ſix commercial houſes. Their exports conſiſt in silks, and particularly in raw and ſpun cottons. The manufacture of this cotton is the principal art of the inhabitants, the number of whom may be eſtimated at about 5000. It is 45 miles west from Damaſcus. E. Long. 36. 5. N. Lat. 37.</p><p>SIDUS <hi rend="smallcaps">GeORgium,</hi> in aſtronomy, a new primary planet, diſcovered by Dr Herſchell in the year 1781, By moſt foreign, and even by ſome Britiſh philoſophers, it is known by the name of <hi rend="italic">Herſchell,</hi> an honour which is due to the diſcoverer. As the other planets are diſtinguiſhed by marks or characters, the planet Herſchell is diſtinguiſhed by an H, the initial letter of the diſcoverer’s name, and a cross to ſhow that it is a Chriſtian planet. From many calculations of our beſt aſtrono-</p></body></text></TEI>