<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-18T21:23:07Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>The Pouhon ſpring riſes from the hill to the north oſ Spa, which conſiſts of
                argillaceous ſchiſtus and serrugineous ſlate. The other fountains riſe from the
                ſurrounding hills to the ſouth-eaſt, ſouth, west, and north-west of the town; and
                this ridge of mountains is formed of calcareous earths mixed with ſiliceous
                ſubſtances. The ſurface of the mountains is covered with woods, interſperſed with
                large boggy ſwamps filled with mud and water. The Pouhon is conſidered as the
                principal ſpring at Spa, being impregnated with a greater quantity of iron than any
                of the reſt, and containing more fixed air than any except the Tonnelet. It is from
                this ſpring that the Spa water for exportation is bottled ; for which the demand is
                ſo great, that, according to the beſt information which Mr Thickneſſe could obtain,
                the quantity exported amounts to 200,000 or 250,000 bottles annually.@@ This exported
                water is inferior in its virtue to that which is drunk on the ſpot ; for the veſſels
                into which it is collected are injudiciouſly expoſed to the ſun, rain, wind, and
                duſt, for ſeveral hours before they are corked, by which means a considerable part
                of its volatile ingredients muſt be evaporated ; for it has been found by
                experiment, that by expoſing it to a gentle heat, air-bubbles aſcend in great
                numbers. It is in its greateſt perfection when collected in cold dry weather ; it is
                then pellucid, colourleſs, and without ſmell, and almoſt as light as diſtilled
                water. It varies in its heat from 52⁰ or 53⁰ to 67⁰ of Fahrenheit’s thermometer.</p>
            <p>The Geronſtere is a much weaker chalybeate water than the Pouhon ; and as it is
                exceedingly nauſeous, and taſtes and ſmells like rotten eggs, it certainly contains
                ſome hepatic gas. This is a circumſtance which Dr Aſh ſeems not to have attended to
                ſufficiently. The Sauveniere water alſo, when newly taken from the well, ſmells a
                little of ſulphur. The Groiſheck contains more alkali, and almoſt as much gas as the
                Pouhon, and has been celebrated for its good effects in the caſe of calculous
                concretions. The Tonnelet contains more gas than any of the reſt. So ſmall is the
                quantity of any fossil body held in ſuſpenſion by the aerial acid in it, and ſo
                volatile is the gas, that it begins to paſs off very rapidly the moment it is taken
                out of the well, and in a ſhort time is entirely gone. Dr Aſh informs us, that in
                the neighbourhood of this well, the cellars, on any approaching change of weather,
                are found to contain much fixed air ; and the beſt prognoſtic which they have of
                rain is the aversion which cats ſhow to be carried into theſe cellars.</p>
            <p>The Spa waters are diuretic, and ſometimes purgative. They exhilarate the ſpirits
                with an influence much more benign than wine or ſpirituous liquors, and they are
                more cooling, and allay thirſt more effectually than common water. They are found
                beneficial in caſes of weakneſs and relaxation, either partial or univerſal ; in
                nervous diſorders ; in obſtructions of the liver and ſpleen ; in caſes where the
                blood is too thin and putreſcent ; in caſes of exceſſive diſcharges proceeding from
                weakneſs ; in the gravel and ſtone ; and in moſt caſes where a ſtrengthening remedy
                is wanted. But they are hurtful in confirmed obſtructions attended with fever, where
                there is no free outlet to the matter, as in ulcerations of the lungs. They are alſo
                injurious to bilious and plethoric conſtitutions, when uſed before the body is
                cooled by proper evacuations.</p>
            <p>SPACE. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Metaphysics,</hi> Part II. Chap. iv.</p>
            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Space,</hi> in geometry, denotes the area of any figure, or that
                which fills the interval or diſtance between the lines that terminate it.</p>
            <p>SPADIX, in botany, anciently ſignified the receptacle of the palms. It is now uſed to
                expreſs every flower-ſtalk that is protruded out of a ſpatha or ſheath.</p>
            <p>The ſpadix of the palms is branched ; that of all other plants ſimple. This last caſe
                admits of ſome variety : in calla, dracontium, and pothos, the florets cover it on
                all ſides ; in arum, they are diſpoſed on the lower part only ; and in zoſtera on
                one ſide.</p>
            <p>SPAGIRIC <hi rend="smallcaps">art,</hi> a name given by authors to that ſpecies of
                chemiſtry which works on metals, and is employed in the ſearch of the philoſopher’s
                ſtone.</p>
            <p>SPAHIS, horsemen in the Ottoman army, chiefly raiſed in Aſia. The great ſtrength of
                the grand ſeignior’s army conſiſts in the janiſaries, who are the foot ; and the
                ſpahis, who are the horſe.</p>
            <p>SPAIN, a country of Europe, famous both in ancient and modern hiſtory, ſituated in
                that large peninſula which forms the ſouth-weſtern part of Europe. It is bounded on
                the ſouth and eaſt by the Mediterranean ſea and ſtraits of Gibraltar, on the north
                and west by the Bay of Biſcay and Atlantic Ocean, on the ſouth- west by Portugal,
                and on the north-eaſt by the Pyrenees.</p>
            <p>The moſt ancient name of Spain was <hi rend="italic">Iberia,</hi> ſuppoſed by ſome to
                be derived from the <hi rend="italic">Iberians,</hi> a people inhabiting Mount
                Caucaſus, a colony of whom ſettled in this country. Others derive it from the
                Phenician word <hi rend="italic">Ebra</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Ibra,</hi>
                ſignifying a paſſage or limit. By the Romans it was called <hi rend="italic"
                    >Spania</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Lliſpania,</hi> from the Phenician name <hi
                    rend="italic">Sphanija ;</hi> and this again from <hi rend="italic"
                    >ſhaphan,</hi> a Phenician word ſignifying a rabbit, becauſe the weſtern part of
                Spain abounded with thoſe animals.</p>
            <p>Spain, as well as the reſt of Europe, was probably peopled by the Celtes ; but the
                Spaniſh hiſtorians derive the origin of their nation from Tubal the fifth ſon of
                Japhet, asserting that Spain had been a monarchy for 2226 years before the coming of
                the Celtes into it. Till the coming of the Carthaginians into Spain, however,
                nothing certain can be affirmed of the Spaniards ; and this happened not long before
                the commencement of the firſt Punic war. Their ſucceſs in reducing the country, and
                their final expulſion by the Romans, has already been rclated under the articles <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Rome</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Carthage ; </hi>we have here
                therefore only to take notice of the ſtate oſ Spain under the Roman government,
                until the Romans were in their turn expelled by the northern barbarians.</p>
            <p>At the time oſ the Roman conqueſt, Spain, though prodigious quantities of ſilver had
                been carried out of it by the Carthaginians and Tyrians, was yet a very rich
                country. In the most ancicnt times, indeed, its riches are ſaid to have exceeded
                what is related of the moſt wealthy country in America. Ariſtotle aſſures us, that
                when the Phenicians firſt arrived in Spain, they exchanged their naval commodities
                for ſuch immenſe quantities of ſilver, that their ſhips could neither contain nor
                ſuſtain its load, though they uſed it for ballaſt, and made their anchois and other
                implements oſ ſilver. When the Carthaginians firſt came to Spain, they found the
                quantity of ſilver nothing leſſened, ſince the inhabitants at that time made all
                their utensils, and even</p>
            <p>@@@[mu] Thicknesses Journey through the Pais Bas.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
