<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:21:20Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>which he wins the attention and commands the paſſions of his readers, leave him among our Britiſh moraliſis without a rival.</p><p>Towards the end of 1763 Dr Smith received an invitation from Mr Charles Townſend to accompany the Duke of Buccleugh on his travels ; and the liberal terms in which this propoſal was made induced him to reſign his office at Glaſgow. He joined the Duke of Buccleugh at London early in the year 1704, and ſet out with him for the continent in the month of March following. After a stay of about ten days at Paris, they proceeded to Thoulouſe, where they fixed their residence for about 18 months; thence they went by a pretty extenſive route through the ſouth of France to Geneva, where they paſſed two months. About Christmas 1765 they returned to Paris, and remained there till October following. The ſociety in which Dr Smith paſſed theſe ten months may be conceived in conſequence of the recommendation of Mr Hume. Turgot, Queſnai, Necker, D’Alembert, Helvetius, Marmontel, Madame Riccoboni, were among the number of his acquaintances ; and ſome of them he continued ever after to reckon among the number of his friends. In October 1766 the duke of Buccleugh returned to England.</p><p>Dr Smith ſpent the next ten years of his life with his mother at Kirkaldy, occupied habitually in intenſe study, but unbending his mind at times in the company of ſome of his old ſchoolfellows, who still continued to reſide near the place of their birth. In 1776 he publiſhed his <hi rend="italic">Inquiry into the Nature and Cauſes of the Wealth of Nations ;</hi> a book ſo univerſally known, that any panegyric on it would be uſeleſs. The variety, importance, and (may we not add) novelty, of the information which it contains ; the skill and comprehenſiveneſs of mind displayed in the arrangement ; the admirable illuſtrations with which it abounds ; together with a plainneſs and perſpicuity which makes it intelligible to all—render it unquestionably the moſt perfect work which has yet appeared on the general principles of any branch of legiſiation.</p><p>He ſpent the next two years of his life in London, where he enjoyed the ſociety of ſome of the most eminent men of the age : but he removed to Edinburgh in 1778, in conſequence oſ having been appointed, at the request of the duke of Buccleugh, one of the commiſſioners of the customs in Scotland. Here he ſpent the last twelve years of his life in an affluence which was more than equal to all his wants. But his studies ſeemed entirely ſuſpended till the infirmities of old age reminded him, when it was too late, of what he yet owed to the public and to his own fame. The principal materials of the works which he had announced had long ago been collected, and little probably was wanting but a few years of health and retirement to complete them. The death of his mother, who had accompanied him to Edinburgh in 1784, together with that of his couſin Miſs Douglas in 1788, contributed to fruſtrate theſe projects. They had been the objects of his affection for more than 60 years, and in their Society he had enjoyed from his infancy all that he ever knew of the endearments of a family. He was now alone and helpleſs ; and though he bore his loſs with equanimity, and regained apparently his former cheerfulneſs, yet his health and ſtrength gradually declined till the period of</p><p>his death, which happened in July 1790. Some days before his death he ordered all his papers to be burnt except a few eſſays, which have ſince been publiſhed.</p><p>Of the originality and comprehenſiveneſs oſ his views; the extent, the variety, and the correctneſs of his information ; the inexhaustible fertility of his invention—he has left behind him laſting monuments. To his private worth, the most certain of all teſtimonies may be found in that confidence, reſpect, and attachment, which followed him through all the various relations oſ life. He was habitually abſent in converſation, and was apt when he ſpoke to deliver his ideas in the form of a lecture. He was rarely known to start a new topic himſelf, or to appear unprepared upon thoſe topics that were introduced by others. In his external form and appearance there was nothing uncommon. When perfectly at eaſe, and when warmed with converſation, his gestures were animated and not ungraceful ; and in the ſociety oſ thoſe he loved, his features were often brightened by a ſmile of inexpreſſible benignity. In the company of strangers, his tendency to abſence, and perhaps still more his conſciouſneſs of that tendency, rendered his manners ſomewhat embarraſſed ; an effect which was probably not a little heightened by thoſe ſpeculative ideas of propriety which his recluſe habits tended at once to perfect in his conception, and to diminiſh his power of realizing.</p><p>SMITHIA, in botany : A genus of the <hi rend="italic">decandria </hi>order, belonging to the <hi rend="italic">diadelphia</hi> claſs of plants ; and in the natural method ranking under the 32d order, <hi rend="italic">Papilionaceœ.</hi> The calyx is monophyllous and belabiated ; the corolla winged ; the legumen inclosed in the calyx, with three or four joints, and contain as many ſeeds, which are ſmooth, compreſſed, and kidney-ſhaped. There is only one species, viz. the <hi rend="italic">thοnina.</hi></p><p>SMITZ (Gaſpar), who, from painting a great number of Magdalens, was called <hi rend="italic">Magdalen Smith,</hi> was a Dutch painter, who came to England ſoon after the Reſtoration. For theſe portraits sat a woman that he kept, and called his wife. A lady, whom he had taught to draw, took him with her to Ireland, where he painted ſmall portraits in oil, had great buſineſs, and high prices. His flowers and fruit were ſo much admired, that one bunch of grapes ſold there for L. 40. In his Magdalens he generally introduced a thiſtle on the fore ground. He had ſeveral ſcholars, particularly Maubert, and one Gawdy of Exeter. Yet, notwithſtanding his success, he died poor in Ireland in 1707.</p><p>SMITHERY, a ſmith’s ſhop; alſo the art of a ſmith, by which iron is wrought into any ſhape by means of fire, hammering, filing, &amp;c.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">SMITING-line,</hi> in a ſhip, is a ſmall rope faſtened to the mizen-yard-arm, below at the deck, and is always furled up with the mizen-ſail, even to the upper end of the yard, and thence it comes down to the poop. Its uſe is to looſe the mizen-ſail without striking down the yard, which is eaſily done, becauſe the mizen-ſail is furled up only with rope-yarns ; and therefore when this rope is pulled hard, it breaks all the rope-yarns, and ſo the ſail falls down of itſelf. The ſailor’s phraſe is, <hi rend="italic">ſmite the mizen</hi> (whence this rope takes its name), that is, hale by this rope that the ſail may fall down.</p><p>SMOKE, a dense elaſſic vapour, arising from burning bodies. As this vapour is extremely diſagreeable to the ſenſes, and often prejudicial to the health, man</p></body></text></TEI>