<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:19:45Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ment would not be much reliſhed by theſe infects ; but repeated experiments made by our author, prove that they prefer it to any other, and eat it with the greateſt avidity. The mulberry leaves muſt be gathered about the end of autumn, before the froſts commence, in dry weather, and at times when the heat is greateſt. They muſt be dried afterwards in the sun, by ſpreading them upon large cloths, and laid up in a dry place after they have been reduced to powder. When it is neceſſary to give this powder to the worms, it ſhould be gently moiſtened with a little water, and a thin coat of it muſt be placed around the young worms, which will immediately begin to feed upon it.</p><p>We have mentioned all the different kinds of food, which, as far as we have heard, have been tried with any ſucceſs to nouriſh the ſilk worm ; not, however, with great confidence, but as experiments which it might be worth while carefully to conſider and perform. We muſt not omit to mention that one perſon, who has had much experience in the managing of ſilk worms, aſſures us, that the ſilk produced from any other food than mulberry leaves is of an inferior quality, and that the worms are ſickly. We think, however, that there is reason to suſpect that the experiment has not been ſkilfully performed ; and therefore, before every other food except mulberry leaves is diſcarded, the experiment ought to be performed with more attention and care. We know that many animals in a domeſtic ſtate can live upon food very different from that which ſupported them when running wild in the fields. Certain it is, however, that every animal, in its ſtate of nature, partakes of a food peculiar to itſelf, which is rejected by other animals as if it were of a poiſonous quality ; and it may be mentioned as a curious fact, as well as an admirable instance of the care of that Being who feeds the fowls of heaven, that notwithſtanding the numberleſs infects that prey upon animals and vegetables, the mulberry tree is left untouched by them all, as the excluſive property of the ſilk worm, the chief of the infect tribe, which toils and ſpins for the uſe of man.</p><p>Having now considered the food proper for the ſilk worm, we ſhall next conſider what ſituation is moſt favourable to them. In the opinion of ſome perſons in this country who have been in the practice of rearing ſilk worms, they ought always to be kept in a dry place, well ſheltered, and posſeſſing a conſiderable degree of warmth, and which is not expoſed to ſudden traditions from heat to cold. If the weather be too cold, a ſmall fire muſt be made : this is of moſt importance when the worms are ready for ſpinning. A ſouthern expoſure is therefore preferable. Some think light is of great utility to ſilk worms, others think that they thrive better in the dark. As to what apartments are beſt accommodated for promoting the health of ſilk worms, and moſt convenient for thoſe who have the care of them, they may be various according to the extent of the manufacture or the wealth of the proprietors. Silk worms may be kept in boxes or in ſhelves. When ſhelves are to be uſed,they maybe conſtructed in the following manner: The ſhelves may be of wicker, ranged at the diſtance of a foot and a half, and fixed in the middle of the room : their breadth ought to be ſuch, that any perſon can eaſily reach to the middle from either ſide. This is perhaps the simpleſt and cheapeſt apparatus for rearing ſilk worms ; but there is another apparatus which</p><p>may be recommended to those who are anxious to unite ſome degree of elegance with convenience. This apparatus is the invention of the Rev. George Swayne of Ruckle-church, a gentleman who, greatly to his honour, has ſtudied this ſubject much, in order to find out the way for promoting the culture of ſilk among the poor.This apparatus, with the description of it, we have borrowed from that valuable and patriotic work, the Tranſactions of the Society for encouraging Arts, Manufactures, and Commerce, Vol. VII. p. 148. The apparatus consiſts of a wooden frame four feet two inches high, each ſide 16 inches and a half wide, divided into eight partitions by ſmall pieces of wood which form grooves, into which the slides run,andare thus eaſily thruſt into or drawn out of the frame. The upper slide (a) in the model sent to the society by Mr Swayne is of paper only, and deſigned to receive the worms as soon as hatched ; the two next <hi rend="italic">(b, b)</hi> are of catgut, the threads about one-tenth of an inch diſtant from each other : theſe are for the infects when a little advanced in ſize : the five lower ones, marked <hi rend="italic">c, c, c, c, c,</hi> are of wickerwork; but, as Mr Swayne afterwards found, netting may be ſubſtituted with advantage inſtead of wicker bottoms. Under each of theſe, as well as under thoſe of catgut, are Aiders made of paper, to prevent the dung of the worms from falling on thoſe feeding below them.</p><p>The management of ſilk worms is next to be attended to. The proper time for hatching them is when the leaves of the mulberry are full grown, or nearly ſo ; that as ſoon as theſe infects are capable of receiving food they may obtain it in abundance. To attempt to hatch them sooner would be hurtful, as the weather would not be ſufficiently warm. Besides, as leaves are neceſſary to the life of a vegetable, if the young leaves of the mulberry-tree are cropped as ſoon as they are unfolded, the tree will be so much weakened as to be incapable of producing ſo many leaves as it would otherwiſe have done ; and if this practice be frequently repeated, will inevitably be deſtroyed.</p><p>When the proper ſeaſon is arrived, the eggs may be hatched either by the heat of the fun, when it happens to be ſtrong enough, or by placing them in a ſmall room moderately heated by a stove or fire; and after being expoſed for fix or ſeven days to a gentle heat, the ſilk worm issues from the egg in the form of a ſmall black hairy caterpillar. When Mr Swayne’s apparatus is used, the worms are to be kept on the drawers wfith, paper bottoms till they are grown ſo large as not readily to creep through the gauze-bottomed drawers : they are then to be placed on thoſe drawers, where they are to remain till their excrements are so large as not readily to fall through ; when this is the case, they muſt be removed to the drawers with the wicker or netting bottoms, and fed thereon till they ſhow ſymptoms of being about to ſpin. It is ſcarcely neceſſary to mention, that the paper hides beneath the gauze and wicker drawers are intended to receive the dung, which ſhould be emptied as often as the worms are fed, at leaſt once a-day ; or to direct, that when the worms are fed, the Aides are to be firſt drawn out a conſiderable way, and the drawers to rest upon them.</p><p>It has been already mentioned, that wet or damp food is exceedingly prejudicial to theſe infects. It produces contagious and fatal diſeaſes. To prevent the necessity of giving them wet or damp food, attention</p></body></text></TEI>