<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:21:04Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>for explaining one of the moſt ſingular facts that occurred to their obſervation, to wit, how the young Devaud can write, although he has his eyes ſhut, and an obſtacle before them. His paper is imprinted on his imagination, and every letter which he means to write is alſo painted there, at the place in which it ought to ſtand on the paper, and without being confounded with the other letters ; now it is clear that his hand, which is obedient to the will of his imagination, will trace them on the real paper, in the same order in which they are repreſented on that which is pictured in his head. It is thus that he is able to write ſeveral letters, ſeveral ſentences, and entire pieces of writing ; and what ſeems to confirm the idea, that the young Devaud writes according to the paper painted on his imagination is, that a certain ſleep-walker, who is deſcribed in the French Encyclopedie (article <hi rend="italic">Somnambulism),</hi> having written ſomething on a paper, another piece of paper of the ſame ſize was ſubſtituted in its ſtead, which he took for his own, and made upon this blank paper the corrections he meant to have made on the other which had been taken away, preciſely in the places where they would have been.</p><p>“ It appears from the recital of another fact, that Devaud, intending to write at the top of the firſt leaf of a white paper book, <hi rend="italic">Vevey, le—</hi> flopped a moment as if to recollect the day of the month, left a blank ſpace, and then proceeded to <hi rend="italic">Decembre</hi> 1787 ; after which he aſked ſor an almanac : a little book, ſuch as is given to children for a new year’s gift, was offered to him; he took it, opened it, brought it near his eyes, then threw it down on the table. An almanac which he knew was then preſented to him ; this was in German, and of a form ſimilar to the almanac of Vevey : he took it, and then ſaid, ‘ What is this they have given me ; here, there is your German almanac.’ At laſt they gave him the almanac of Berne ; he took this likewiſe, and went to examine it at the bottom of an alcove that was perfectly dark. He was heard turning over the leaves, and saying 24, then a moment afterwards 34. Returning to his place, with the almanac open at the month of December, he laid it on the table and wrote in the ſpace which he had left blank the 24th. This ſcene happened on the 23d ; but as he imagined it to be the 24th, he did not miſtake. The following is the explication given of this fact by the authors of the report.</p><p>“ The dates 23d, 24th, and 25th, of the month of December, had long occupied the mind of the young Devaud. The 23d and 25th were holidays, which he expected with the impatience natural to perſons of his age, for the arrival of thoſe moments when their little daily labours are to be ſuſpended. The 25th eſpecially was the object of his hopes ; there was to be an illumination in the church, which had been deſcribed to him in a manner that quite tranſported him. The 24th was a day of labour, which came very diſagreeably between the two happy days. It may eaſily be conceived, how an imagination ſo irritable as that of the young Devaud would be ſtruck with thoſe pleaſing  epochs. Accordingly, from the beginning of the month he had been perpetually turning over the almanac of Vevey. He calculated the days and the hours that were to elapſe before the arrival of his wished-for holidays ; he ſhowed to his friends and acquaintance the dates of thoſe days which he expected with ſo much impatience ; every time he took up the almanac, it was only to conſult the month of December. We now ſee why that date preſented itſelf to his mind. He was performing a taſk, becauſe he imagined the day to be the Monday which had ſo long engrossed him. It is not ſurpriſing, that it ſhould have occurred to his imagination, and that on opening the almanac in the dark he might have thought he ſaw this date which he was ſeeking, and that his imagination might have repreſented it to him in as lively a manner as if he had actually ſeen it. Neither is it ſurpriſing that he ſhould have opened the almanac at the month of December ; the cuſtom of peruſing this month muſt have made him find it in the dark by a mere mechanical operation. Man never ſeems to be a machine ſo much as in the ſtate of ſomnambuliſm ; it is then that habit comes to ſupply thoſe of the ſenſes that cannot be ſerviceable, and that it makes the person act with as much preciſion as if all his ſenſes were in the utmoſt activity. Theſe circumſtances deſtroy the idea of there being any thing miraculous in the behaviour of young Devaud with reſpect to the date and the month that he was in queſt of ; and the reader, who has entered into our explanations, will not be ſurpriſed at his knowing the German almanac ; the touch alone was ſufficient to point it out to him ; and the proof of this is the ſhortneſs of the time that it remained in his hands.</p><p>“ An experiment was made by changing the place of the ink-ſtandiſh during the time that Devaud was writing. He had a light beſide him, and had certified himſelf of the place where his ink-holder was ſtanding by means of sight. From that time he continued to take ink with preciſion, without being obliged to open his eyes again : but the ink-ſtandiſh being removed, he returned as uſual to the place where he thought it was: It muſt be obſerved, that the motion of his hand was rapid till it reached the height of the ſtandiſh, and then he moved it ſlowly, till the pen gently touched the table as he was ſeeking for the ink : he then perceived that a trick had been put on him, and complained of it ; he went in ſearch of his ink-ſtandiſh and put it in its place. This experiment was ſeveral times repeated, and always attended with the ſame circumſtances. Does not what we have here ſtated prove, that the ſtandiſh, the paper, the table, &amp;c. are painted on his imagination in as lively a manner as if he really ſaw them, as he fought the real ſtandiſh in the place where his imagination told him it ought to have been ? Does it not prove that the ſame lively imagination is the cauſe of the moſt ſingular actions of this sleep-walker ? And laſtly, does it not prove, that a mere glance of his eye is ſufficient to make his impreſſions as lively as durable?</p><p>“ The committee, upon the whole, recommend to ſuch as wiſh to repcat the ſame experiments, 1. To make their obſervations on different ſleep walkers. 2. To examine often whether they can read books that are unknown to them in perfect darkneſs. 3. To obſerve whether they can tell the hours on a watch in the dark. 4. To remove when they write the ink-ſtandiſh from its place, to ſee whether they will return to the ſame place in order to take ink, 5. And, laſtly, to take notice whether they walk with the ſame confidence in a dark</p></body></text></TEI>