<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:23:23Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>cis were leſs extenſive, but more united than thoſe of Charles. His ſubjects were numerous, active, brave, lovers of glory, and lovers of their king. Theſe were ſtrong arguments in favour of his power, ſo neceſſary at this juncture : but he had no natural intereſt in the Germanic body; and the electors, hearing ſo much of military force on each side, became more alarmed for their own privileges than the common ſafety. They determined to reject both candidates, and offered the imperial crown to Frederic, ſurnamed the <hi rend="italic">Wife,</hi> duke of Saxony. Rut he, undazzled by the ſplendour of an object courted with ſo much eagerneſs by two mighty monarchs, rejected it with a magnanimity no leſs lingular than great.</p><p>“ In times of tranquillity (ſaid Frederic), we wiſh for an emperor who has no power to invade our liberties ; times of danger demand one who is able to ſecure our ſafety. The Turkiſh armies, led by a warlike and victorious monarch, are now aſſembling: they are ready to pour in upon Germany with a violence unknown in former ages. New conjunctures call for new expedients. The imperial ſceptre muſt be committed to ſome hand more powerful than mine or that of any other German prince. We poſſeſs neither dominions, nor revenues, nor authority, which enable us to encounter ſuch a formidable enemy. Recourſe muſt be had, in this exigency, to one of the rival monarchs. Each of them can bring into the field forces sufficient for our defence. But as the king of Spain is of German extraction, as he is a member and prince of the empire by the territories which deſcend to him from his grandfather, and as his dominions ſtretch along that frontier which lies moſt exposed to the enemy, his claim, in my opinion, is preferable to that of a ſtranger to our language, to our blood, and to our country.” Charles was elected in conſequence of this ſpeech in the year 1520.</p><p>The two candidates had hitherto conducted their rivalſhip with emulation, but without enmity. They had even mingled in their competition many expreſſions of friendſhip and regard. Francis in particular declared with his uſual vivacity, that his brother Charles and he were fairly and openly ſuitors to the ſame miſtreſs : “ The moſt aſſiduous and fortunate (added he) will win her; and the other muſt reſt contented.” But the preference was no ſooner given to his rival, than Francis diſcovered all the paſſions natural to diſappointed ambition. He could not ſuppreſs his chagrin and indignation at being baulked in his favourite purſuit, and rejected, in the face of all Europe, for a youth yet unknown to fame. The ſpirit of Charles reſented ſuch contempt ; and from this jealouſy, as much as from oppoſition of intereſts, aroſe that emulation between thoſe two great monarchs which involved them in almoſt perpetual hostilities, and kept their whole age in movement.</p><p>Charles and Francis had many interfering claims in Italy ; and the latter thought himſelf bound in honour to reſtore the king of Navarre to his dominions, unjuſtly ſeized by the crown of Spain. They immediately began to negotiate ; and as Henry VIII. of England was the third prince of the age in power and in dignity, his friendſhip was eagerly courted by each of the rivals. He was the natural guardian of the liberties of Europe. Senſible of the conſequence which his ſituation gave him, and proud of his pre-eminence, Henry knew it to</p><p>be his intereſt to keep the balance even between the contending powers, and to reſtrain both, by not joining entirely with either ; but he was ſeldom able to reduce his ideas to practice. Vanity and reſentment were the great ſprings of all his undertakings ; and his neighbours, by touching theſe, found an eaſy way to draw him into their meaſures, and force him upon many raſh and inconſiderate enterpriſes.</p><p>All the impolitic ſteps in Henry’s government muſt not, however, be imputed to himſelf ; many of them were occaſioned by the ambition and avarice of his prime miniſter and favourite cardinal Wolſey. This man, who, by his talents and accompliſhments, had riſen from one of the loweſt conditions in life to the higheſt employments both in church and ſtate, enjoyed a greater degree of power and dignity than any Engliſh ſubject ever poſſeſſed, and governed the haughty, preſumptuous, and untractable ſpirit of Henry, with abſolute authority. Francis was equally well acquainted with the character of Henry and of his miniſter. He had ſucceſsfully flattered Wolſey’s pride, by honouring him with particular marks of his confidence, and beſtowing upon him the appellation of <hi rend="italic">Father, Tutor,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Governor ; </hi>and he had obtained the reſtitution of Tournay, by adding a penſion to thoſe reſpectful titles. He now ſolicited an interview with the king of England near: Calais; in hopes of being able, by familiar converſation, to attach him to his friendſhip and intereſt, while he gratified the cardinal’s vanity, by affording him an opportunity of diſplaying his magnificence in the preſence of two courts, and of diſcovering to the two nations his influence over their monarchs. Charles dreaded the effects of this projected interview between two gallant princes, whoſe hearts were no leſs ſuſceptible of friendſhip than their manners were of inſpiring it. Finding it impoſſible, however, to prevent a viſit, in which the vanity of all parties was ſo much concerned, he endeavoured to defeat its purpoſe, and to pre-occupy the favour of the Engliſh monarch, and of his miniſter, by an act of complaiſance ſtill more flattering and more uncommon. Relying wholly upon Henry’s generoſity for his ſafety, he landed at Dover, in his way from Spain to the Low Countries. The king of England, who was on his way to France, charmed with ſuch an inſtance of confidence, haſtened to receive his royal gueſt; and Charles, during his ſhort stay, had the addreſs not only to give Henry favourable impreſſions of his Character and intentions, but to detach Wolſey entirely from the intereſt of Francis. The tiara had attracted the eye of that ambitious prelate ; and as the emperor knew that the papacy was the ſole point of elevation, beyond his preſent greatneſs, at which he could aſpire, he made him an offer of his intereſt on the firſt vacancy.</p><p>The,day of Charles’s departure, Henry went over to Calais with his whole court, in order to meet Francis. Their interview was in an open plain between Guiſnes and Ardres ; where the two kings and their attendants diſplayed their magnificence with ſuch emulation and profuſe expence, as procured it the name of the <hi rend="italic">Field of the Cloth of Gold.</hi> Here Henry erected a ſpacious houſe of wood and canvas, framed in London, on which, under the figure of an Engliſh archer, was the following motto : “ He prevails whom I favour ;” alluding to his own political ſituation, as holding in his</p></body></text></TEI>