<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-18T21:20:52Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>ken in war, but alſo 127 priſoners of different kinds, that he might have a
                ſufficiency of ſkulls to adorn the walls of his palace ; though at the very time of
                that massacre he <hi rend="italic">knew</hi> that there were six ſlave-ſhips in the
                road of Whidah from which he could have got for every prime ſlave a price little
                ſhort of thirty pounds Sterling @@*.</p>
            <p>Theſe facts, and numberleſs others which the reader will find detailed in the 13th
                volume of the Modern Univerſal Hiſtory, by writers who were at the greateſt pains to
                procure authentic information ; who were neither biaſſed by intereſt nor blinded by
                enthuſiasm ; and who appear to have held the infamous traffic in utter
                abhorrence—prove beyond the poſſibility of doubt, that ſlavery of the worſt kind
                muſt have prevailed among all the negro nations before they were viſited either by
                the Portugueſe or by the Arabs @@(I). Theſe two nations may indeed have been the
                firſt who dragged the unhappy negro from his native continent, and made his ſlavery
                doubly ſevere, by compelling him to labour, without his own conſent, for masters
                whom he hardly conſidered as human beings.</p>
            <p>On the beginning of this commerce, or the dreadful cruelty with which it has been
                carried on to the preſent day, it is impoſſible to reflect without horror : but
                there is ſome conſolation, however ſmall, in knowing that its original authors were
                not Europeans. The purchaſe of Guinea blacks for ſlaves by foreign nations commenced
                ages before the Portugueſe had laid that country open to the intercourſe of Europe.
                Even after they had made many incurſions into it, the inhabitants were as regularly
                purchaſed for ſlaves by ſome of the adjoining ſtates as they are now by the maritime
                Europeans.</p>
            <p>“ The Arabs of Egypt having reduced all the north of Africa, and carrying with them
                their love of black ſervants, would be ſure to open a ready communication for
                themſelves to their country. They certainly had one ſo early as 1512, and before the
                Europeans had any for that purpoſe @@(K). @@They went from Barbary by a route that
                was ſo much practiſed, as to be denominated expreſsly ‘ the way of the camels.’
                Meeting together at the town of Cape Cantin, that of Valadie near it, the commercial
                caravan traverſed the vaſt deſerts,</p>
            <p>thoſe of Sarra, which run like the tropic of Cancer over them in a long line acroſs
                the country ; to a place of great population called Hoden, the W<hi rend="italic"
                    >aden</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Hoden</hi> of our maps, and a little to the
                ſouth-weſt of Cape Blanco. From Hoden they turned to the left, and puſhed directly
                into the interior of the continent, to reach Tegazza, the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Tagazel</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Tagaza</hi> of our maps, and lying nearly
                eaſt of Hoden. Here affuredly they did, as the caravan does certainly at this day ;
                and added to the other wares upon their camels a quantity of ſalt from thoſe mines
                of rock-ſalt, which are extraordinary enough to be noticed as rocks in our maps.
                This they carried, as they ſtill carry it, toTanbut, the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Tombut</hi> or the maps, and a town in the heart of the African continent. And
                from this town they turned on the right for the ſea-coaſt again, and reached it in
                the great kingdom of Mele, the <hi rend="italic">Melli</hi> of our maps, to the
                ſouth of the Gambia, and just at the ſpringing as it were of that grand arch of ſea
                which curves ſo deeply into the body of the land, and conſtitutes the extenſive
                gulph of Guinea. At Melli and at Tombut they received a meaſure of gold for a
                meaſure of ſalt. The caravan collects gold at Tombut to the preſent time ; but at
                Melli they purchaſed gold, and alſo ſilver, in pieces as large as pebbles. And at
                Hoden they had <hi rend="italic">a great mart for βαves ; </hi>the blacks being
                brought thither from the countries adjoining, and bartered away to the traders. Such
                was the Slave Coaſt and the Gold Coaſt of former days. The ſtaple commodity of Hoden
                is only transferred now to Whidah ; and diverted from the Arabs of Barbary to the
                Chriſtians of Europe,” by whom the negroes are carried to the continent of America
                or to the Sugar Iſlands in the West Indies. In theſe countries they are all ſold
                like beaſts in a market; but they experience very different degrees of ſervitude
                from the different maſters who hold them as property. Such of them as are reconciled
                to the appearance of white men, or have been born in the European colonies, feel
                themſelves as happy under a humane maſter as they could be in their native continent
                    @@<hi rend="smallcaps">(l)</hi> ; and we believe that few of them in ſuch
                circumſtances have expreſſed a deſire to return.”</p>
            <p>In the French Well India iſlands, before the late re-</p>
            <p>@@@[m*] Dalzel's History of the Kingdom of Dabomy.</p>
            <p>@@@[m] Whitaker's review, p. 185.</p>
            <p>@@@(I) The ſame thing appears from the voyages of M. Saugnier, who had an opportunity
                of converſing with many tribes of negroes, and who always ſpeaks of ſlavery as an
                eſtabliſhed practice among them ; adding, that ſuch as are ſold for crimes are put
                to death by their own countrymen if they fly from their maſter. It appears likewiſe
                in a ſtill more ſtriking light from Dalzel’s Hiſtory of Dahomy, where we are told
                that all the Dahomans, from the loweſt to the higheſt, acknowledge the right of the
                ſovereign to diſpoſe of their perſons and properties at pleaſure ; and where we
                learn, that the ſovereign himſelf aſſured Mr Abſon the Engliſh governor at Whidah,
                that all his anceſtors had from time immemorial put to death every priſoner of war
                whom they could not sell as a ſlave.</p>
            <p>@@@(K) In the year 1442, Anthony Gonſalez, a Portugueſe adventurer, reſtored to their
                native country ſome Mooriſh priſoners whom he had two years before forcibly carried
                off from the coaſt of Africa. He landed them at <hi rend="italic">Rio del-Oro,</hi>
                and received from the Moors in exchange ten blacks and a quantity of gold duſt. This
                transaction proves, that a commerce in black ſervants was then regularly carried on
                by the Moors and not by the Portugueſe. So early as the year 1502, the Spaniards
                began to employ a few negroes in the mines of Hiſpaniola ; but in the year
                following, Ovando, the governor of that iſland, forbade the further importation of
                them, alleging that they taught the Indians all manner of wickedneſs, and rendered
                them leſs tractable than formerly : and it was not till the year 1517 that the
                ſupply of negroes to the Spaniſh American plantations became an eſtabliſhed and
                regular branch of commerce. <hi rend="italic">Edward's History of the Weft
                    Indies,</hi> Book IV. Chap. ii.</p>
            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">@@@(l)</hi> “ I have obſerved many of my ſlaves go on board the
                vesſel with joy, on my aſſurance that they would be well treated and happy on the
                plantation where I was going to send them. When the Banbarans find that they are
                truſted by the whites, they never think of making their eſcape, chooſing to be the
                ſlaves of <hi rend="italic">Europeans</hi> rather <pb n="529"> </pb>than of a <hi
                    rend="italic">black man</hi> who would treat them with the greateſt cruelty.
                    Voyages<hi rend="italic"> to the Coast of Africa by Messrs Saugnier and
                    Brisſon,</hi> p. 332. 335. Engliſh Tranſlation.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
