<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:20:22Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>pers. He ſpoke in high terms oſ the Analytical Works of Mr Cotes, and oſ the two Bernoullis. He was conſulted by Mr M'Laurin during the progreſs of his ineſtimable Treatiſe of Fluxions, and contributed not a little to the reputation of that work. The ſpirit of that moſt ingenious algebraic demonſtration of the fluxions of a rectangle, and the very proceſs of the argument, is the ſame with Dr Simſon’s in his diſſertation on the limits of quantities. It was therefore from a thorough acquaintance with the ſubject, and by a juſt taſte, that he was induced to prefer his favourite analyſis, or, to ſpeak more properly, to exhort mathematicians to employ it in its own ſphere, and not to become ignorant of geometry, while they ſucceſsfully employed the ſymbolical analyſis in cases which did not require it, and which ſuffered by its admiſſion. It muſt be acknowledged, however, that in his later years, the diſguſt which he felt at the artificial and ſlovenly employment on ſubjects of pure geometry, ſometimes hindered him from even looking at the moſt refined and ingenious improvements of the algebraic analyſis which occur in the writings of Euler, D’Alembert, and other eminent maſters. But, when properly informed of them, he never failed to give them their due praiſe ; and we remember him ſpeaking, in terms of great ſatisfaction, of an improvement of the infiniteſimal calculus, by D’Alembert and De la Grange, in their reſearches concerning the propagation of sound, and the vibrations of muſical cords.</p><p>And that Dr Simſon not only was maſter of this calculus and the ſymbolical calculus in general, but held them in proper eſteem, appears from two valuable diſſertations to be found in his poſthumous works; the one on logarithms, and the other on the limits of ratios. The laſt, in particular, ſhows how completely he was ſatisfied with reſpect to the ſolid foundation of the method of fluxions ; and it contains an elegant and ſtrict demonſtration of all the applications which have been made of the method by its illuſtrious author to the objects of pure geometry.</p><p>We hoped to have given a much more complete and inſtructive account of this eminent geometer and his works, by the aid of a perſon fully acquainted with both, and able to appreciate their value ; but an accident has deprived us of this aſſiſtance, when it was too late to procure an equivalent : and we muſt requeſt our readers to accept of this very imperfect account, ſince we cannot do juſtice to Dr Simſon’s merit, unleſs almoſt equally converſant in all the geometry of the ancient Greeks.</p><p>The life of a literary man rarely teems with anecdote; and a mathematician, devoted to his ſtudies, is perhaps more abſtracted than any other perſon from the ordinary occurrences of life, and even the ordinary topics of converſation. Dr Simſon was of this claſs ; and, having never married, lived entirely a college life. Having no occaſion for the commodious houſe to which his place in the univerſity intitled him, he contented himſelf with chambers, good indeed, and ſpacious enough for his ſober accommodation, and for receiving his choice collection of mathematical writers, but without any decoration or commodious furniture. His official fervant sufficed for valet, footman, and chambermaid.  As this retirement, was entirely devoted to ſtudy, he entertained no company in his chambers, but in a neighbouring</p><p>houſe, where his apartment was ſacred to him and his gueſts.</p><p>Having in early life devoted himſelf to the reſtoration of the works of the ancient geometers, he ſtudied them with unremitting attention ; and, retiring from the promiſcuous intercourſe of the world, he contented himſelf with a ſmall ſociety of intimate friends, with whom he could lay aſide every reſtraint of ceremony or reſerve, and indulge in all the innocent frivolities of life. Every Friday evening was ſpent in a party at whiſt, in which he excelled, and took delight in inſtructing others, till increaſing years made him leſs patient with the dulneſs of a lcholar. The card-party was followed by an hour or two dedicated ſolely to playful converſation. In like manner, every Saturday he had a leſs ſelect party to dinner at a houſe about a mile from town. Tire Doctor’s long life gave him occaſion to ſee the <hi rend="italic">dramatis perſonae</hi> of this little theatre ſeveral times completely changed, while he continued to give it a perſonal identity ; ſo that, without any deſign or wiſh of his own, it became, as it were, his own houſe and his own family, and went by his name In this ſtate did the preſent writer firſt ſee it, with Dr Simſon as its father and head, reſpected and beloved by every branch ; for, as it was for relaxation, and not for the enjoyment of his acknowledged ſuperiority, that he continued this habit of his early youth ; and as his notions “ of a fine talk” did not conſiſt in the pleaſure of having “ toſſed and gored a good many to-day,” his companions were as much at their eaſe as he wiſhed to be himſelf ; and it was no ſmall part of their entertainment (and of his too), to ſmile at thoſe innocent deviations from common forms, and thoſe miſtakes with reſpect to life and manners, which an almoſt total retirement from the world, and inceſſant occupation in an abſtract ſcience, cauſed this venerable preſident frequently to exhibit. Theſe are remembered with a more affecting regret, that they are now “ with the days that are paſt,” than the moſt pithy apophthegms, ushered in with an emphatical, “ Why, Sir!” or “ No, Sir!” which precludes all reply. Dr Simſon never exerted his preſidial authority, unleſs it were to check ſome infringement of good breeding, or any thing that appeared unfriendly to religion or purity of manners ; for theſe he had the higheſt reverence. We have twice heard him sing (he had a fine voice and moſt accurate ear) ſome lines of a Latin hymn to the divine geometer, and each time the rapturous tear ſtood in his eye.</p><p>But we ask the reader’s pardon for this digreſſion ; it is not however uſeleſs, ſince it paints the man as much as any recital of his ſtudies ; and to his acquaintances we are certain that it will be an acceptable memorandum. To them it was often matter of regret, that a perſon of ſuch eminent talents, which would have made him ſhine equally in any line oſ life, ſhould have allowed himſelf to be so completely devoted to a ſtudy which abſtracted lum from the ordinary purſuits of men, unfitted him for the active enjoyment of life, and kept him out of thoſe walks which they frequented, and where they would have rejoiced to meet him.</p><p>Dr Simſon was of an advantageous stature, with a fine countenance; and even in his old age had a graceful carriage and manner, and always, except when in mourning, dreſſed in white cloth. He was of a cheerful diſpoſition: and though he did not make the firſt.</p></body></text></TEI>