<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-18T21:24:30Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>ledge already diffused is judſicously compiled. But a due reſpect for the public, and
                gratitude for the very honourable reception hitherto given to our labours, induce us
                to exert ourſelves with honeſt zeal to merit the continuance of public favour. We
                aſſure our readers that the experiments were made with care, and on quantities
                sufficiently large to make the unavoidable irregularities in ſuch caſes quite
                inſignificant. The law of denſity was aſcertained in each ſubſtance in two ways. We
                diſſolved different portions of ſalt in the ſame quantity of water, and examined the
                ſpecific gravity of the brine by weighing it in a vessel with a narrow neck. The
                portions of ſalt were each of them one- eighth of what would make a nearly ſaturated
                solution of the temperature 55. We did not make the brine ſtronger, that there might
                be no riſk of a precipitation in form of cryſtals. We conſidered the ſpecific
                gravities as the ordinates of a curve, of which the abscissæ were the numbers of
                ounces of dry ſalt contained in a cubic foot of the brine. Having thus obtained
                eight ordinates correſponding to 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, and 8 portions of ſalt, the
                ordinates or ſpecific gravities for every other proportion of ſalt were had by the
                uſual methods of interpoſition.</p>
            <p>The other method was, by firſt making a brine nearly ſaturated, in which the
                proportion of salt and water was exactly determined. We then took out one-eighth of
                the brine, and filled up the veſſel with water, taking care that the mixture ſhould
                be complete ; for which purpoſe, beſides agitation, the diluted brine was allowed to
                remain 24 hours before weighing. Taking out one-eighth of the brine alſo takes out
                one eighth of the ſalt ; ſo that the proportion of ſalt and water in the diluted
                brine was known. It was now weighed, and thus we determined the ſpecific gravity for
                a new proportion of ſalt and water.</p>
            <p>We then took out one-ſeventh of the brine. It is evident that this takes out
                one-eighth of the original quantity of ſalt ; an abſtraction equal to the former. We
                filled the veſſel with water with the ſame precautions ; and in the ſame manner we
                proceeded till there remained only one-eighth of the original quantity of ſalt.</p>
            <p>The ſpecific gravities by theſe two methods agreed extremely well. In the very
                deliqueſcent ſalts the firſt method exhibited ſome ſmall irregularities, ariſing
                from the unequal quantities of water which they had imbibed from the atmoſphere. We
                therefore confided moſt in the experiments made with diluted brines.</p>
            <p>That the reader may judge of the authority of the tables which we ſhall insert, we
                ſubmit to his inſpection one ſeries of experiments.</p>
            <p>Two thouſand one hundred and eighty-eight grains of very pure and dry (but not
                decrepitated) common ſalt, prepared in large cryſtals, were diſſolved in 6562 grains
                of diſtilled water of the temperature 55⁰. A ſmall matraſs with a narrow neck, which
                held 4200 grains of diſtilled water, was filled with this brine. Its contents
                weighed 5027 grains. Now 6562 + 2188 : 2188 = 5027 : 1256,75. Therefore the bottle
                of brine contained 1256,75 grains of ſalt diſſolved in 3770,25 grains of water. Its
                ſpecific gravity is -= 5027</p>
            <p>or 1,196905 ; and a cubic foot of brine weighs 1196,9 ounces avoirdupois. Alſo 5027 :
                1256,75 =</p>
            <p>1196,9 : 299,28. Therefore a cubic foot of this brine contains 299,28 ounces of
                perfectly dry ſalt.</p>
            <p>The ſubſequent ſteps of the proceſs are repreſented as follows.</p>
            <table>
                <row>
                    <cell>Salt.</cell>
                    <cell>Brine.</cell>
                    <cell>Water.</cell>
                    <cell>Wt. of Cub. Ft.</cell>
                    <cell>Salt in Cub. Ft.</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell><p>8)1256,75</p><p>157,1</p></cell>
                    <cell><p>8)5027</p><p>628,4</p></cell>
                    <cell>3770,25 = <hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">8 </hi>of
                        brine.</cell>
                    <cell>1196,5</cell>
                    <cell><p>299,28</p><p>37,41 <hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript"
                        >8</hi></p></cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell><p>4398,6</p><p>527,4</p></cell>
                    <cell><p>Remains. Water to fill it</p><p>again.</p><p>2d Brine.</p><p><hi
                        rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">7 </hi>taken
                        out.</p></cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell><p>7) 1099,6</p><p>157,1</p></cell>
                    <cell><p>7)4926,0</p><p>703,7</p></cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell>1172,7</cell>
                    <cell><p>261,87</p><p>37,41</p></cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell><p>4222,3</p><p>604,7</p></cell>
                    <cell>Water added.</cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell><p>942,5</p><p>157,1</p></cell>
                    <cell><p>6)4827,0</p><p>804,5</p></cell>
                    <cell>3d Brine. Taken out.</cell>
                    <cell>1149,3</cell>
                    <cell>224,46</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell><p>4022,5</p><p>706,5</p></cell>
                    <cell>Remains. Water added.</cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>785,4 157,1</cell>
                    <cell><p>5)4729,0</p><p>946</p></cell>
                    <cell>4th Brine. Taken out.</cell>
                    <cell>1125,9</cell>
                    <cell>187,05</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell><p>3783</p><p>847</p></cell>
                    <cell><p>Remains.</p><p>Water added.</p></cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell><p>628,3</p><p>157,1</p></cell>
                    <cell><p>4) 4630</p><p>1157,5</p></cell>
                    <cell>5th Brine. Taken out.</cell>
                    <cell>1102,3</cell>
                    <cell>149,64</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell><p>3472,5</p><p>1054,5</p></cell>
                    <cell><p>Remains.</p><p>Water added.</p></cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>471,2</cell>
                    <cell><p>3)4527</p><p>1509</p></cell>
                    <cell>6th Brine. Taken out.</cell>
                    <cell>1077,9</cell>
                    <cell>112,23</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell><p>3018</p><p>1405</p></cell>
                    <cell><p>Remains.</p><p>Water added.</p></cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>314,1</cell>
                    <cell><p>2)4423</p><p>2212</p></cell>
                    <cell>7th Brine. Taken out.</cell>
                    <cell>10533</cell>
                    <cell>74,82</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell><p>2211</p><p>2102</p></cell>
                    <cell><p>Remains.</p><p>Water added.</p></cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>157,0</cell>
                    <cell>4313</cell>
                    <cell>8th Brine.</cell>
                    <cell>1027,9</cell>
                    <cell>37,41</cell>
                </row>
            </table>
            <p>Thus, by repeated abſtraction of brine, ſo as always to take out <hi
                    rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">8</hi>th of the ſalt contained in
                one conſtant bulk, we have obtained a brine conſiſting of 157 grains of ſalt united
                with 4313— 157, or 4156 grains of water. 4313</p>
            <p>Its ſpecific gravity is 1,0279, and a cubic foot</p>
            <p>of it weighs 1028 ounces, and contains 37<hi rend="superscript">4</hi>/<hi
                    rend="subscript">10</hi> ounces of dry ſalt. In like manner may the ſpecific
                gravity, the weight of a cubic foot, and the ſalt it contains, be eſtimated for the
                intermediate brines.</p>
            <p>When theſe eight quantities of ſalt contained in a cubic foot are made the abſciſſae,
                and the weights of the cubic foot of brine are the correſponding ordinates, the</p>

        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
