<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:21:11Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>perforated ; the berry is corticoſe, echinated, polyſpermous, and gaping. There are two species, the <hi rend="italic">dentata </hi>and <hi rend="italic">emarginata.</hi></p><p>SLOE. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Prunus.</hi></p><p>SLOOP, a ſmall veſſel furniſhed with one mail, the mainſail of which is attached to a gaff above, or to the mast on its foremoſt edge, and to a long boom below, by which it is occasionally ſhifted to either quarter. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Ship.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Stoop of War,</hi> a name given to the ſmalleſt veſſels of war except cutters. They are either rigged as ſhips or ſnows.</p><p>SLOT, in the ſportſman’s language, a term uſed to expreſs the mark of the foot of a ſtag or other animal proper for the chace in the clay or earth, by which they are able to gueſs when the animal paſſed, and which way he went. The ſlot, or treading of the  stag, is very nicely ſtudied on this occasion ; if the slot be large, deep printed in the ground, and with an open cleft, and, added to theſe marks, there is a large ſpace between mark and mark, it is certain that the ſtag is an old one. If there be obſerved the ſlots or treadings of two, the one long and the other round, and both of one ſize, the long ſlot is always that of the larger animal. There is alſo another way of knowing the old ones ſrom the young ones by the treading ; which is, that the hinder feet of the old ones never reach to their fore feet, whereas thoſe of the young ones do.</p><p>SLOTH, in zoology. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Bradypus.</hi></p><p>SLOUGH, a deep muddy place. The caſt ſkin of a ſnake, the damp of a coal pit, and the ſcar of a wound, are alſo called by the ſame appellation. The ſlough of a wild boar is the bed, soil, or mire, wherein he wallows, or in which he lies in the day-time.</p><p>SLUCZK, a large and populous town in Poland, in Lithuania, and capital of a duchy of the ſame name ; famous for three battles gained here by Conſtantine duke of Oſtrog over the Tartars, in the reign of Sigiſmund I. It is ſeated on the river Sluczk, 72 miles ſouth-eaſt of Minſki, and 70 ſouth of Novogrodeck. E. Long. 27. 44. N. Lat. 53. 2.</p><p>SLUG, in zoology. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Limax.</hi></p><p>SLUICE, a frame of timber, ſtone, or other matter, ſerving to retain and raiſe the water of a river, &amp;c. and  on occaſion to let it paſs.</p><p>Such is the ſluice of a mill, which ſtops and collects the water of a rivulet, &amp;c. to let it fall at length in the greater plenty upon the mill-wheel : ſuch alſo are thoſe uſed as vents or drains to diſcharge water off land. And ſuch are the ſluices of Flanders, Sec. which ſerve to prevent the waters of the ſea from overflowing the lower lands.</p><p>Sometimes there is a kind of canal incloſed between two gates or ſluices, in artificial navigations, to save the water, and render the paſſage of boats equally eaſy and ſafe, upwards and downwards ; as in the ſluices of Briare in France, which are a kind of maſſive walls built parallel to each other, at the diſtance of 20 or 24 feet, cloſed with ſtrong gates at each end, between which is a kind of canal or chamber, conſiderably longer than broad ; wherein a veſſel being incloſed, the water is let out at the firſt gate, by which the veſſel is raiſed 15 or 16 feet, and paſſed out of this canal into another much higher. By ſuch means a boat is conveyed out of the</p><p>Loire into the Seine, though the ground between them riſe above 150 feet higher than either of thoſe rivers @@*.</p><p>Sluices are made different ways, according to the uſe for which they are intended : when they ſerve for navigation, they are ſhut with two gates, preſenting an angle towards the ſſream ; when they are made near the ſea, two pair of gates are made, the one to keep the water out and the other in, as occaſion requires : in this caſe, the gates towards the ſea preſent an angle that way, and the others the contrary way ; and the ſpace incloſed by thoſe gates is called the <hi rend="italic">chamber.</hi> When ſluices are made in the ditches of a fortreſs, to keep up the water in ſome parts, inſtead of gates, ſhutters are made ſo as to slide up and down in grooves ; and when they are made to raiſe an inundation, they are then ſhut by means of ſquare timbers let down in culliſes, ſo as to lie cloſe and firm,</p><p>The word <hi rend="italic">ſluice</hi> is formed of the French <hi rend="italic">eſcluse,</hi> which Menage derives from the Latin <hi rend="italic">excluſa,</hi> found in the Salic law in the ſame ſenſe. But this is to be reſtrained to the ſluices of mills, &amp;c. ſor as to thoſe ſerving to raiſe veſſels, they were wholly unknown to the ancients.</p><p>SLUR, in muſic, a mark like the arch of a circle, drawn from one note to another, comprehending two or more notes in the ſame or different degrees. If the notes are in different degrees, it ſignifies that they are all to be ſung to one ſyllable ; for wind inſtruments, that they are to be made in one continued breath ; and for ſtringed inſtruments that are ſtruck with a bow, as a violin, &amp;c. that they are made with one ſtroke. If the notes are in the ſame degree, it ſignifies that it is all one note, to be made as long as the whole notes ſo connected ; and this happens moſt frequently betwixt the laſt note of one line and the firſt of the next ; which is particularly called s<hi rend="italic">yncopation.</hi></p><p>SLUYS, a town of Dutch Flanders, oppoſite the iſland of Cadſand, with a good harbour, 10 miles north of Bruges. E. Long. 3. 25. N. Lat. 51. 19.</p><p>SMACK, a ſmall veſſel, commonly rigged as a ſloop or hoy, uſed in the coasting or fiſhing trade, or as a tender in the king’s ſervice.</p><p>SMALAND, or <hi rend="smallcaps">East Gothland,</hi> a province of Sweden, which makes part of Gothland ; and is bounded on the north by Oſtrogothia or Eaſt Gothland, on the eaſt by the Baltic Sea, on the ſouth by Schonen and Bleckingia, and on the west by Weſtrogothia or Weft Gothland. It is about 112 miles in length, and 62 in breadth. Calmar is the capital town.</p><p>SMALKAIlD, a town of Germany, in Franconia, and in the county of Henneberg : famous for the confederacy entered into by the German Proteſtants againſt the emperor, commonly called the <hi rend="italic">league oſ Smalkald. </hi>The deſign of it was to defend their religion and liberties. It is ſeated on the river Werra, 25 miles ſouth- weſt of Erford, and 50 north-weſt of Bamberg. E. Long, 10. 53. N. Lat. 50. 49. It is ſubject to the prince of Heſſe-Caſſel.</p><p>SMALLAGE, in botany. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Apium.</hi></p><p>SMALT, a kind of glaſs of a dark blue colour, which when levigated appears of a moſt beautiful colour ; and if it could be made ſufficiently fine, would be an excellent ſuccedaneum for ultramarine, as not only reſiſting all kinds of weathcr, but even the moſt violent fires. It is prepared by melting one part of calcined cobalt with two of flint powder, and one of pot-aſh.</p><p>@@@[m]* See Canal.</p></body></text></TEI>