<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-18T21:22:10Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>The following table will exhibit at a glance the funds, eſtabliſhment, and
                expenditure, of the ſociety, from a few years after its commencement to the preſent
                time. Where the number of ſcholars is not mentioned, the defect may be ſupplied by
                taking an average from thoſe years where a computation has been made. Where the
                capital is not mentioned, it may eaſily be made out by conſidering the ſalaries as
                the intereſt.</p>
            <table>
                <row>
                    <cell>A. D.</cell>
                    <cell>Capital.</cell>
                    <cell>Schools.</cell>
                    <cell>Scholars.</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>1713</cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell>12</cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>1715</cell>
                    <cell>L.6,177</cell>
                    <cell>25</cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>1719</cell>
                    <cell>8,168</cell>
                    <cell>48</cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>1727</cell>
                    <cell>9,131</cell>
                    <cell>78</cell>
                    <cell>2757</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>1732</cell>
                    <cell>13,318</cell>
                    <cell>109</cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>1742</cell>
                    <cell>19,287</cell>
                    <cell>128</cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>1753</cell>
                    <cell>24,308</cell>
                    <cell>152</cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>1758</cell>
                    <cell>28,413</cell>
                    <cell>176</cell>
                    <cell>6409</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>1781</cell>
                    <cell>34,000 Salaries</cell>
                    <cell>180</cell>
                    <cell>7000</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>1793</cell>
                    <cell>3,080</cell>
                    <cell>307</cell>
                    <cell>12,913</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>1794</cell>
                    <cell>3214</cell>
                    <cell>323</cell>
                    <cell>14,370</cell>
                </row>
            </table>
            <p>Hitherto we have taken no notice of the correſponding board which was eſtabliſhed at
                London ſo early as the year 1729, to receive ſubſcriptions and lay out firms. That
                board indeed remained long inactive ; but in 1773 its members began to co-operate
                more cordially with their brethren in Scotland. Since that period an annual ſermon
                has been preached in recommendation of the charity ; and the preacher is now
                ſelected without any regard to the religious denomination to which he belongs ;
                ſometimes from the church of England, ſometimes from the church of Scotland, and
                ſometimes from ſectaries of different perſuaſions. The meetings of the correſpondent
                board have been attended by many of the nobility and gentry, who have made great
                exertions to promote the views of the ſociety. From its preſent flouriſhing ſtate
                therefore, from the indefatigable exertion and laudable zeal of the managers, and
                from the countenance and ſupport which they have received from perſons of the firſt
                rank and reſpectability in the nation, the benevolent mind may look forward with
                much confidence and ſatisfaction to a period not very diſtant, when its beneficial
                effects ſhall be felt not only in the Highlands, but ſhall be communicated to the
                reſt of the nation. We have been thus particular in our account of the Society for
                Propagating Chriſtian Knowledge, becauſe we have had acceſs to the moſt authentic
                ſources of information, and becauſe we know it to be an inſtitution calculated to
                enlighten and improve a conſiderable part of the Britiſh nation.</p>
            <p>3. <hi rend="italic">Society of the Sons of the Clergy,</hi> was incorporated by King
                Charles II. in 1678, by the name of <hi rend="italic">The Governors of the Charity
                    for Relief of the Poor Widows and Children of Clergymen.</hi> This ſociety is
                under the direction and management of a preſident and vice-preſident, three
                treaſurers, and a court of aſſiſtants compoſed of forty members. Several hundreds of
                widows and chil</p>
            <p>dren of the clergy have annually received conſiderable relief from this uſeful
                charity.</p>
            <p>4. <hi rend="italic">Society for the Sons of the Clergy of the Establiſhed Church of
                    Scotland,</hi> was inſtituted at Edinburgh in February 1790, and was conſtituted
                a body corporate by his majesty’s royal charter in 1792. The ſociety, after ſeveral
                meetings, are of opinion, that the period in which the families of clergymen feel
                moſt urgently the need both of friends and of pecuniary aid, is that which commences
                with the introduction of the ſons either to an univerſity or to buſineſs, and
                terminates with their eſtabliſhment in their reſpective profeſſions ; that many of
                the miniſters of this church, living at great diſtances from the ſeats either of
                univerſities or of buſineſs, posseſs incomes which, in the preſent ſtate of the
                country, are inadequate to the purpoſes of procuring for their ſons either the
                literary or profeſſional education which might enable them to come forward' with
                credit end ſucceſs in the world ; that the ſons of clergymen, from domeſtic tuition
                and example, have in genetal very advantageous means of receiving in their early
                years the impreſſions of virtue and honour, together with the rudiments of liberal
                knowledge ; and that of courſe the public intereſt may be promoted, by enabling this
                class of young men to obtain their ſhare in the reſpectable ſituations of life. The
                views of the ſociety have been limited to the ſons only of clergymen ; as they are
                of opinion, that within the limits which they have fixed, the field of beneficence
                will be ſtill very extenſive, and the claims for aid as many and as great as their
                funds can be ſuppoſed able to anſwer, at leaſt for many years to come. If the
                ſociety ſhall ever be in a ſituation to undertake more than the aids which will·be
                necessary in bringing forward the ſons of the clergy, it may then be conſidered in
                what manner the daughters alſo may become ſharers in its bounty.</p>
            <p>5. <hi rend="italic">Royal Humane Society,</hi> was inſtituted in London in 1774, for
                the recovery of perſons drowned or otherwiſe ſuffocated. We have already given ſome
                account of societies inſtituted in other countries with the ſame views, and have
                alſo copied the directions of this ſociety for the recovery of life, for which ſee
                the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Drowning.</hi> We have therefore only to ſtate,
                that the plan of this ſociety is ſo adverſe to any private intereſted views, that it
                acquits its founders of all ſordid motives. For the medical practitioners accept no
                pecuniary recompenſe for the time which they devote to a difficult and tedious
                proceſs ; for the anxiety which they feel while the event is doubtful ; for the
                mortification which they too often undergo, when death, in ſpite of all their
                efforts, at laſt carries off his prey ; nor for the inſults to which they willingly
                expoſe themſelves from vulgar incredulity. Their ſole reward is in the holy joy of
                doing good. Of an inſtitution thus free in its origin from the ſuſpicion of
                ambitious views, and in its plan renouncing ſelf-intereſt in every ſhape,
                philanthropy muſt be the only baſis. The good intention therefore of the ſociety is
                proved by its conſtitution ;</p>
 
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
