<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:22:22Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>exceeding L. 1000 a year. The directors of this ſociety, annually elected, are to conſiſt of 24 perſons, including the preſident, vice-preſident, treaſurer, and ſecretary ; and it is required that they be either painters, ſculptors, architects, or engravers by profeſſion.</p><p>6.	<hi rend="italic">Britiſh Society for Extending the Fiſheries and Improving the Sea-Coasts of this Kingdom,</hi> was inſtituted in 1786. The end and deſign of this ſociety will beſt appear from their chatter, of which we preſent an abstract.</p><p>The preamble ſtates, “ the great want oſ improvement in fiſheries, agriculture, and manufactures, in the Highlands and iſlands of North Britain ; the prevalence of emigration from the want of employment in thoſe parts ; the proſpect of a new nurſery of ſeamen, by the eſtabliſhment oſ fiſhing towns and villages in that quarter. The act therefore declares, that the perſons therein named, and every other perſon or perſons who ſhall thereafter become proprietors of the joint ſtock mentioned therein, ſhall be a diſtinct and ſeparate body politic and corporate, by the name of <hi rend="italic">The Britiſh Society  for Extending the Fiſheries and Improving the Sea-coasts  of this Kingdom :</hi> That the ſaid ſociety may raiſe a capital joint ſtock not exceeding L. 150,000, to be applied to purchasing or otherwiſe acquiring lands and tenements in perpetuity, for the building thereon, and on no other land whatever, free towns, villages, and fiſhing stations : That the joint ſtock ſhall be divided into ſhares of L. 50 each : That no one perſon ſhall in his or her name poſſess more than ten ſhares, or L. 500 : That the ſociety ſhall not borrow any ſum or ſums of money whatſoever : That the ſums to be advanced for this undertaking, and the profits ariſing therefrom, ſhall be divided proportionably to the ſum ſubſcribed ; and that no perſon ſhall be liable for a larger ſum than he or ſhe ſhall have reſpectively subscribed : That one or two ſhares shall intitle to one vote and no more, in perſon or by proxy, at all meetings of proprietors ; three or four ſhares to two votes ; five, six, or ſeven ſhares, to three votes ; eight or nine ſhares to four votes ; and ten ſhares to five votes and no more ; That more perſons than one inclining to hold in their joint names one or more ſhares ſhall be intitled to vote, by one of ſuch perſons, according to the priority of their names, or by proxy : That bodies corporate ſhall vote by proxy under their ſeal : That all perſons holding proxies ſhall be proprietors, and that no one perſon ſhall hold more than five votes by proxy : That the affairs of the ſociety ſhall be managed by a governor, deputy governor, and 13 other directors, to be elected annually on the 25th of March, from among the proprietors of the ſociety, holding at leaſt one full ſhare, by signed lists of their names to be tranſmitted by the proprietors to the ſecretary of the ſociety : that five proprietors, not being governor, director, or other officer, ſhall be in like manner annually elected to audit the accounts of the ſociety ; That there ſhall be one general meeting of the proprietors annually on the 25th oſ March : That occasional general meetings ſhall be called on the requeſt of nine or more proprietors : That the general meetings of the proprietors ſhall make all bye laws and conſtitutions for the government of the ſociety, and for the good and orderly carrying on of the buſineſs of the ſame : That no transfer shall be made of the ſtock of the ſociety for three years from the 10th of Auguſt 1786 : That</p><p>the caſh of the ſociety ſhall be lodged in the hank of England, bank of Scotland, or the royal bank of Scotland : That no director, proprietor, agent, or officer of the ſociety, ſhall retain any firm or ſums of money in his hands beyond the ſpace of 30 days, on any account whatſoever : That all payments by the ſociety ſhall be made by drafts on the ſaid banks, under the bands of the governor or deputy-governor, countersigned by the ſecretary or his deputy, and two or more directors ; And that the books in which the accounts of the ſociety ſhall be kept ſhall be open to all the proprietors.”</p><p>The inſtitution of this public-ſpirited ſociety was in a great meaſure owing to the exertions of the patriotic John Knox ; who, in the courſe of 23 years, traverſed and explored the Highlands of Scotland no leſs than 16 times, and expended ſeveral thouſand pounds of his own fortune in purſuing his patriotic designs.</p><p>7. <hi rend="italic">Britiſh Wool Society.</hi> See <hi rend="italic">Britiſh W</hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps">ool</hi><hi rend="italic"> Society.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Society</hi><hi rend="italic"> Isles,</hi> a cluſter oſ iſles, ſo named by Captain Cook in 1769. They are ſituated between the latitudes of 16. 10. and 16. 55. ſouth, and between the longitudes of 150. 57. and 152, west. They are eight in number ; namely, Otaheite, Huahine, Ulietea, Otaha, Bolabola, Maurua, Toobouai, and Tabooyamanoo or Saunders’s Iſland. The ſoil, productions, people, their language, religion, cuſtoms, and manners, are ſo nearly the ſame as at OTASHEITE, that little need be added here on that ſubject. Nature has been equally bountiful in uncultivated plenty, and the inhabitants are as luxurious and as indolent. A plantain branch is the emblem of peace, and exchanging names the greateſt token of friendlhip. Their dances are more elegant, their dramatic entertainments have ſomething of plot and conſiſtency, and they exhibit temporary occurrences as the objects of praiſe or ſatire ; ſo that the origin of ancient comedy may be already diſcerned among them. The people of Huahine are in general ſtouter and fairer than thoſe of Otaheite, and this iſland is remarkable for  its populouſneſs and fertility. Thoſe of Ulietea, on the contrary, are ſmaller and bladker, and much leſs orderly. Captain Cook put on ſhore a Cape ewe at Bolabola, where a ram had been left by the Spaniards ; and alſo an Engliſh boar and ſow, with two goats, at Ulietea, If the valuable animals which have been tranſported thither from Europe ſhould be ſuffered to multiply, no part of the world will equal theſe illands in variety and abundance of refreſhments fot future navigators.</p><p>SOCINIANS, in church-hiſtory, a ſect of Chriſtian heretics, ſo called from their founder Fauſtus Socinus (ſee SociNus). They maintain, “ That Jesus Christ was a mere man, who had no exiſtence before he was conceived by the Virgin Mary ; that the Holy Ghost is no diſtinct perſon, but that the Father is truly and properly God. They own, that the name of God is given in the Holy Scriptures to Jeſus Chriſt ; but contend, that it is only a deputed title, which, however, inveſts him with an abſolute ſovereignty over all created beings, and renders him an object of worship to men and angels. They deny the doctrines of ſatisfaction and imputed righteouſneſs ; and lay that Chriſt only preached the truth to mankind, ſet before them in himſelf an example of heroic virtue, and ſealed his doctrines with his blood. Original sin and absolute pre-deſtination they eſteem ſcholaſtic chimeras. They lika-</p></body></text></TEI>