<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:20:01Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>her thus hooded in bed. I could relate many other little articles which appeared to me extremely singular. But I admired them not ſo much as the multitude ; becauſe, as I knew the deſign of bringing her to Europe to be exhibited as a ſhow, I was inclined to think that ſhe had been taught many of theſe monkey tricks, which the people conſidered as being natural to the animal. She died in our ſhip, about the latitude of the Cape of Good Hope. The figure of this ape had a very great reſemblance to that of man, &amp;c.” Gmelli Carreri tells us, that he ſaw one of theſe apes, which cried like an infant, walked upon its hind-feet, and carried a matt under its arm to lie down and ſleep upon.</p><p>An orang-outang which Buffon ſaw, is deſcribed by him as mild, affectionate, and good-natured. His air was melancholy, his gait grave, his movements meaſured, his diſpoſitions gentle, and very different from thoſe of other apes. He had neither the impatience of the Barbary ape, the maliciouſneſs of the baboon, nor the extravagance of the monkeys. “ It may be alleged, (says our author), that he had the benefit of inſtruction ; but the other apes which I ſhall compare with him, were educated in the ſame manner. Signs and words were alone ſufficient to make our orang-outang act ; but the baboon required a cudgel, and the other apes a whip ; for none of them would obey without blows. I have ſeen this animal preſent his hand to conduct the people who came to viſit him, and walk as gravely along with them as if he had formed a part oſ the company. I have ſeen him sit down at table, unfold his towel, wipe his lips, uſe a ſpoon or a fork to carry the victuals to his mouth, pour his liquor into a glaſs, and make it touch that of the perſon who drank along with him. When invited to take tea, he brought a cup and a ſaucer, placed them on the table, put in ſugar, poured out the tea, and allowed it to cool before he drank it. All theſe actions he performed without any other inſtigation than the ſigns or verbal orders of his maſter, and often of his own accord. He did no injury to any perſon : he even approached company with circumspection, and preſented himſelf as if he wanted to be careſſed. He was very fond oſ dainties, which every body gave him : And as his breaſt was diſeaſed, and he was afflicted with a teazing cough, this quantity of ſweetmeats undoubtedly contributed to ſhorten his life. He lived one ſummer in Paris, and died in London the following winter. He eat almoſt every thing ; but preferred ripe and dried fruits to all other kinds of food. He drank a little wane ; but ſpontaneouſly left it for milk, tea, or other mild liquors.” This was only two feet four inches high, and was a young one. There is great poſſibilſty that theſe animals may vary in ſize and in colour, ſome being covered with black, others with reddiſh hairs.— They are not the ſatyrs of the ancients ; which had tails @@<hi rend="smallcaps">(a),</hi> and were a ſpecies of monkey. Linnaeus’s</p><p><hi rend="italic">homo nocturnus,</hi> an animal of this kind, is unneceſſarily ſeparated from his s<hi rend="italic">imia ſatyrus.</hi></p><p>To enable the reader to form a judgment of this animal, which has ſo great a reſemblance to man, it may not be unacceptable to quote from Buffon the differences and conformities which make him approach or recede from the human ſpecies. “ He differs from man externally by the flatneſs of his noſe, by the ſhortneſs of his front, and by his chin, which is not elevated at the baſe. His ears are proportionally too large, his eyes too near each other, and the diſtance between his noſe and mouth is too great. Theſe are the only differences between the face of an orang-outang and that of a man. With regard to the body and members, the thighs are proportionally too ſhort, the arms too long, the fingers too ſmall, the palm of the hands too long and narrow, and the feet rather reſemble hands than the human foot. The male organs of generation differ not from thoſe of man, except that the prepuce has no frænum. The female organs are extremely ſimilar to thoſe of a woman.</p><p>“ The orang-outang differs internally from the human ſpecies in the number of ribs : man has only 12, but the orang-outang has 13. The vertebræ of the neck are alſo ſhorter, the bones of the pelvis narrow, the buttocks flatter, and the orbits of the eyes sunk deeper. He has no ſpinal proceſs on the firſt vertebra of the neck. The kidneys are rounder than thoſe of man, and the ureters have a different figure, as well as the bladder and gall bladder, which are narrower and longer than in the human ſpecies. All the other parts of the body, head, and members, both external and internal, ſo perfectly reſemble thoſe of man, that we cannot make the compariſon without being aſtoniſhed that ſuch a ſimilarity in ſtructure and organization ſhould not produce the ſame effects. The tongue, and all the organs of ſpeech, for example, are the ſame as in man ; and yet the orang-outang enjoys not the faculty of ſpeaking ; the brain has the ſame figure and proportions ; and yet he poſſesses not the power of thinking. Can there be a more evident proof than is exhibited in the orang-outang, that matter alone, though perfectly organized, can produce neither language nor thought, unleſs it be animated by a ſuperior principle ? Man and the orang-outang are the only animals who have buttocks and the calf of the legs, and who, of courſe, are formed for walking erect ; the only animals who have a broad cheſt, flat ſhoulders, and vertebræ of the ſame ſtructure ; and the only animals whoſe brain, heart, lungs, liver, ſpleen, ſtomach, and inteſtines, are perfectly ſimilar, and who have an appendix vermiformis, or blind-gut. In fine, the orang-outang has a greater reſemblance to man than even to the baboons or monkeys, not only in all the parts we have mentioned, but in the largeneſs of the face, the figure of the cranium, of the jaws, of the teeth, and of the other bones of the head</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">@@@(a)</hi> Ælian gives them tails, <hi rend="italic">lib.</hi> xvi. c. 21. Pliny says they have teeth like dogs, <hi rend="italic">lib.</hi> vii. <hi rend="italic">c.</hi> 2. circumſtances common to many monkeys. <hi rend="italic">Ptolemy, lib.</hi> 7. <hi rend="italic">c.</hi> 2. ſpeaks of certain iſlands in the Indian ocean inhabited by people with tails like thoſe with which ſatyrs are painted, whence called the <hi rend="italic">iſles of ſatyrs.</hi> Keeping, a Swede, pretended to have diſcovered theſe <hi rend="italic">homines caudati</hi> ; that they would have trafficked with him, offering him live parrots ; that afterwards they killed ſome of the crew that went on ſhore, and eat them, &amp;c. &amp;c. Amaen<hi rend="italic">. Acad. v</hi>i. 71.</p></body></text></TEI>