<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:23:34Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ſemble an army ſtrong enough to penetrate into the Milaneſe. The emperor, however, was ſenſible that he could not long reſiſt the efforts of two ſuch powerful confederates, nor expect that the ſame fortunate circumſtances would concur a ſecond time in his favour ; he therefore thought it neceſſary, both for his ſafety and reputation, to give his conſent to a truce : and Francis choſe rather to run the riſk of diſobliging his new ally the ſultan, than to draw on his head the indignation, and perhaps the arms, of all Chriſtendom, by obſtinately obſtructing the re-eſtabliſhment of tranquillity, and contributing to the aggrandizement of the Infidels.</p><p>Theſe conſiderations inclined the contending monarchs to liſten to the arguments of the holy father ; but he found it impoſſible to bring about a final accommodation between them, each inflexibly perſiſting in aſſerting his own claims. Nor could he prevail on them to ſee one another, though both came to the place of rendezvous : ſo great was the remains of diſtruſt and rancour, or ſuch the difficulty of adjuſting the ceremonial ! Yet, improbable as it may ſeem, a few days after ſigning the truce, the emperor, in his paſſage to Barcelona, being driven on the coaſt of Provence, Francis invited him to come aſhore ; frankly viſited him on board his galley, and was received and entertained with the warmeſt demonſtrations of eſteem and affection. Charles, with an equal degree of confidence, paid the king next day a viſit at Aigues-mortes ; where theſe two hoſtile rivals and vindictive enemies, who had accuſed each other of every kind of baſeneſs, converſing together with all the cordiality of brothers, ſeemed to vie with each other in expreſſions of reſpect and friendſhip.</p><p>Beſides the glory of having reſtored tranquillity to Europe, the pope gained a point of much conſequence to his family. He obtained for his grandſon, Margaret of Auſtria, the emperor’s natural daughter, formerly wife of Alexander de Medici, whom Charles had raiſed to the ſupreme power in Florence. Lorenzo de Medici, the kinſman and intimate companion of Alexander, had aſſaſſinated him by one of the blackeſt treaſons recorded in hiſtory. Under pretence of having ſecured him an aſſignation with a lady of the higheſt rank and great beauty, he drew him into a ſecret apartment of his houſe, and there ſtabbed him as he lay careleſsly on a couch, expecting the embrace of the lovely fair, whom he had often ſolicited in vain. Lorenzo, however, did not reap the fruits of his crime ; for though ſome of his countrymen extolled him as a third Brutus, and endeavoured to ſeize this occaſion for recovering their liberties, the government of Florence paſſed into the hands of Coſmo II. another kinſman of Alexander. Coſmo was deſirous of marrying the widow of his predeceſſor ; but the emperor choſe rather to oblige the pope, by bellowing his daughter upon Octavio Farneſe, ſon of the duke of Parma.</p><p>Charles had ſoon farther cauſe to be ſenſible of his obligations to the holy father for bringing about the treaty of Nice. His troops everywhere mutinied for want of pay, and the ability of his generals only could have prevented a total revolt. He had depended, as his chief reſource for diſcharging the arrears due to his ſoldiers, upon the ſubſidies which he expected from his Caſtilian ſubiects. For this purpoſe he aſſembled the</p><p>Cortes of Caſtile at Toledo ; and having represented to them the great expence of his military operations, he propoſed to levy ſuch ſupplies as the preſent exigency of affairs demanded, by a general exciſe on commodities ; but the Spaniards, who already felt themſelves oppreſſed by a load of taxes unknown to their anceſtors, and who had often complained that their country was drained of its wealth and inhabitants, in order to proſecute quarrels in which they had no intereſt, determined not to add voluntarily to their own burdens. The nobles, in particular, inveighed with great vehemence againſt the imposition propoſed, as an encroachment on the valuable and diſtinguiſhing privilege of their order, that of being exempted from the payment of any tax. After employing arguments and promiſes in vain, Charles diſmiſſed the aſſembly with indignation ; and from that period neither the nobles nor the prelates have been called to the Cortes, on pretence that ſuch as pay no part of the public taxes ſhould not claim a vote in laying them on. Theſe aſſemblies have ſince conſiſted merely of the procurators or repreſentatives of 18 cities, two from each ; in all 36 members, who are abſolutely at the devotion of the crown.</p><p>The citizens of Ghent, ſtill more bold, broke out not long after into open rebellion againſt the emperor’s government, on account of a tax which they judged contrary to their ancient privileges, and a deciſion of the council of Mechlin in favour of the imperial authority. Enraged at an unjuſt impoſition, and rendered deſperate on ſeeing their rights betrayed by that very court which was bound to protect them, they flew to arms, ſeized ſeveral of the emperor’s officers, and drove ſuch of the nobility as reſided among them out of the city. Senſible, however, of their inability to ſupport what their zeal had prompted them to undertake, and deſirous of ſecuring a protector againſt the formidable forces with which they might expect ſoon to be attacked, they offered to acknowledge the king of France as their ſovereign, to put him into immediate poſſeſſion of their city, and to aſſiſt him in recovering thoſe provinces in the Netherlands which had anciently belonged to his crown. True policy directed Francis to comply with this propoſal. The counties of Flanders and Artois were more valuable than the duchy of Milan, for which he had ſo long contended ; and their ſituation in regard to France made it more eaſy to conquer or to defend them. But Francis overrated the Milaneſe. He had lived in friendſhip with the emperor ever ſince their interview at Aigues-mortes, and Charles had promiſed him the inveſtiture of that duchy. Forgetting, therefore, all his paſt injuries, and the deceitful promiſes by which he had been ſo often duped, the credulous, generous Francis, not only rejected the propoſitions of the citizens of Ghent, but communicated to the emperor his whole negociation with the malecontents.</p><p>Judging of Charles’s heart by his own, Francis hoped by this ſeemingly diſintereſted proceeding to obtain at once the inveſtiture of Milan ; and the emperor, well acquainted with the weakneſs of his rival, flattered him in this apprehenſion, for his own ſelfiſh purpoſes. His preſence being neceſſary in the Netherlands, he demanded a paſſage through France. It was immediately granted him ; and Charles, to whom every moment was precious, ſet out, notwithſtanding the remonſtrances of his council and the fears of his Spaniſh ſubjects, with a</p></body></text></TEI>