<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:23:32Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>pay annually 12,000 crowns for the ſubsiſtence of the Spaniſh garrison in the Goletta. Theſe points being  settled, and 20,000 Chriſtian ſlaves freed from bondage either by arms or by treaty, Charles returned to Europe, where his preſence was become necessary ; while Barbarossa, who had retired to Bona, recovered new ſtrength, and again became the tyrant of the ocean.</p><p>The king of France took advantage oſ the emperor’s abſence to revive his pretensions in Italy. The treaty of Cambray had covered up but not extinguiſhed the flames oſ diſcord. Francis in particular, who waited only for a favourable opportunity of recovering the territories and reputation which he had lost, continued to negotiate againſt his rival with different courts. But all his negotiations were disconcerted by unforeſeen accidents. The death of Clement VII. (whom he had gained by marrying his ſon the duke of Orleans, afterwards Henry II. to Catharine of Medici, the niece of that pontiff), deprived him of all the ſupport which he hoped to receive from the court of Rome. The king of England, occupied with domeſtic cares and projects, declined engaging in the affairs of the continent ; and the Proteſtant princes, associated by the league of Smalkalde, to whom Francis had alſo applied, and who ſeemed diſpoſed at firſt to liſten to him, filled with indignation and reſentment at the cruelty with which some of their reformed brethren had been treated in France, refuſed to have any connection with the enemy of their religion.</p><p>Francis was neither cruel nor bigotted : he was too indolent to concern himſelf about religious diſputes ; but his principles becoming ſuſpected, at a time when the emperor was gaining immortal glory by his expedition againſt the Infidels, he found it necessary to vindicate himſelf by ſome extraordinary demonstration of reverence for the eſtabliſhed faith. The indiſcreet zeal of ſome Proteſtant converts furniſhed him. with the occaſion. They had affixed to the gates of the Louvre and other public places papers containing indecent reflections on the rites of the Romiſh church. Six of the perſons concerned in this talk action were ſeized ; and the king, pretending to be struck with horror at their blasphemies, appointed a ſolemn proceſſion, in order to avert the wrath of heaven. The holy ſacrament was carried through the city of Paris in great pomp: Francis walked uncovered before it, bearing a torch in his hand ; the princes of the blood ſupported the canopy over it ; the nobles walked behind. In preſence of this numerous assembly, the king declared, that if one of his hands were infected with hereſy, he would cut it off with the other ; “ and I would ſacriſice (added he) even my own children, if found guilty of that crime.” As an awful proof of his ſincerity, the six unhappy perſons who had been ſeized were publicly burnt, before the proceſſion was finiſhed, and in the moſt cruel manner. They were fixed upon a machine which deſcended into the flames, and retired alternately, until they expired.—No wonder that the Proteſtant princes were incenſed at ſuch barbarity !</p><p>But Francis, though unſupported by any ally, commanded his army to advance towards the frontiers of Italy, under pretence of chaſtiſing the duke of Milan for a breach of the law oſ nations, in putting to death his ambassador. The operations oſ war, however, ſoon took a new direction. Inſtead of marching directly to</p><p>the Milaneſe, Francis commenced hoſtilitieg againſt the duke of Savoy, with whom he had cauſe to be dissatisfied, and on whom he had ſome claims ; and before the end of the campaign, that feeble prince ſaw himſelf ſtripped of all his dominions, except the province of Piedmont. To complete his misfortunes, the city of Geneva, the ſovereignty of which he claimed, and where the reformed opinions had already got footing, threw off his yoke ; and its revolt drew along with it the loſs of the adjacent territory. Geneva was then an imperial city, and has ever since remained entirely free.</p><p>In this extremity the duke of Savoy ſaw no reſource but in the emperor’s protection ; and as his misfortunes were chiefly occaſioned by his attachment to the imperial intereſt, he had a title to immediate aſſiſtance. But Charles, who was juſt returned from his African expedition, was not able to lend him the necessary ſupport. His treaſury was entirely drained, and he was obliged to diſhand his army till he could raiſe new ſupplies. Mean time the death of Sforza duke of Milan entirely changed the nature of the war, and afforded the emperor full leiſure to prepare ſor action. The French monarch’s pretext for taking up arms was at once cut off; but as the duke died without iſſue, all Francis’s rights to the duchy of Milan, which he had yielded only to Sforza and his deſcendants, returned to him in full force. He inſtantly renewed his claim to it ; and if he had ordered his army immediately to advance, he might have made himſelf maſter of it. But he unfortunately waited his time in fruitleſs negotiations, while his more politic rival took poſſeſſion of the duchy as a vacant fief of the empire ; and though Charles ſeemed ſtill to admit the equity of Francis’s claim, he delayed granting the inveſtiture under various pretences, and was ſecretly taking every poſſible meaſure to prevent him from regaining footing in Italy.</p><p>During the time gained in this manner Charles had recruited his finances, and of courſe his armies ; and finding himſelf in a condition for war, he at laſt threw off the maſk under which he had ſo long concealed his deſigns from the court of France. Entering Rome with great pomp, he pronounced before the pope and cardinals, assembled in full conſiſtory, a violent invective againſt Francis, by way of reply to his proposions concerning the inveſtiture of Milan. Yet Francis, by an unaccountable fatality, continued to negotiate, as if it had been ſtill poſſible to terminate their differences in an amicable manner; and Charles, finding him ſo eager to run into the ſnare, favoured the deception, and, by ſeeming to liſten to his propoſals, gained yet more time for the execution of his ambitious projects.</p><p>If misfortunes had rendered Francis too diffident, ſucceſs had made Charles too ſanguine. He preſumed on nothirg leſs than the ſubverſion of the French monarchy ; nay, he conſidered it as an infallible event. Having chafed the forces of his rival out of Piedmont and Savoy, he puſhed forward at the head of 50,000 men, contrary to the advice of his moſt experienced miniſters and generals, to invade the ſouthern provinces of France ; while other two armies were ordered to enter it, the one on the ſide of Picardy, the other on the  side of Champagne. He thought it impoſſible that Francis could resiſt ſo many unexpected attacks on ſuch different quarters ; but he found himſelf miſtaken.</p><p>The French monarch fixed upon the moſt effectual</p></body></text></TEI>