<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:23:50Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>the principal ; which was inſtituted in 1430 by Philip the good duke of Burgundy, and is common now to the kings of Spain and the houſe of Auſtria. The order of St Jago de Compoſtella was inſtituted in the year 1175 by Ferdinand IL king of Leon. The order of Calatrava was founded by Sancho III. of Caſtile. The order of Alcantara owes its inſtitution to Ferdinand II, king of Leon. The three laſt orders have large commanderies or eſtates annexed to them. The maſters of them were once ſo powerful, that they diſputed the king’s authority over them ; whereupon the king procured thoſe maſterſhips to be conferred on himſelf by the Pope, that they might no longer aſſume an independency of the ſtate. The knights of theſe three orders are eſteemed noblemen.</p><p>In the laſt century, the revenues of Spain amounted to 32 or 33 millions of livres ; but afterwards they were so reduced, that they did not exceed ſeven or eight millions. At preſent, the revenues of the crown arising in Spain are computed at five millions Sterling <hi rend="italic">per annum, b</hi>eſides what ariſes from America. The ſilver mines there are inexhauſtible ; and of the produce of theſe a fifth belongs to the king. The taxes in Spain are numerous and heavy. The land forces, in time of peace, are computed at about 80,000 ; and in time of war, muſt be much more numerous. Their navy at preſent  cannot be aſcertained.</p><p>The language of this country, eſpecially that ſpoken in Caſtile, which is by far the pureſt, approaches the neareſt to the Latin of any language in Europe, mixed with Arabic words and terminations introduced by the Moors. In ſome provinces, the vulgar tongue is a dialect of the old French, or rather Gaſcon, which is little underſtood in the others. In Biſcay, the language is ſaid to be a dialect of the Gothic or Celtic, and to have ſome analogy with the Welch and Iriſh. As to what regards the character of the Spaniards, they do not want either an inclination or capacity for the ſciences ; but have hardly an opportunity of acquiring any true learning or knowledge, at leaſt in their ſcirools and univerſities. They are admired for their ſecrecy, conſtancy, ravity, patience in adversity, and loyalty. They are alſo ſaid to be true to their word, great enemies to lying, and ſo nice and jealous in point of honour, that they will ſtick at nothing to wipe off any stain that is caſt upon it. Among their vices and defects are reckoned their pride and contempt of foreigners, their indolence, lazineſs, luſt, bigotry, and credulity in believing the feigned miracles and legends of their monks. They are alſo ſaid to be extremely paſſionate, jealous, and vindictive ; and are noted, above any other European nation, for deſpiſtng and neglecting agriculture, arts, and  manufactures.</p><p>We will here ſubjoin ſome directions for travelling in Spain by Mr Townſend, a late reſpectable traveller; as they will enable the reader to form a more diſtinct notion of the ſtate of that country than he could obtain from general description.</p><p>“ To travel commodiouſly in Spain, a man ſhould have a good conſtitution, two good ſervants, letters of credit for the principal cities, and a proper introduction to the beſt families, both of the native inhabitants and of ſtrangers settled in the country.</p><p>“ The language will be eaſily acquired.</p><p>" His ſervants ſhould be a Spaniard and a Swiſs ; of</p><p>which one ſhould be sufficiently acquainted with the art of cooking, and with the ſuperior art of providing for the journey ; which implies a perfect knowledge of the country though which he is to paſs, that he may ſecure a ſtock of wine, bread, and meat, in places where theſe excel, and ſuch a ſtock as may be sufficient to carry him through the diſtricts in which theſe are not to be obtained, For himſelf, his ſervants, and his baggage, he ſhould purchaſe three ſtrong mules, able to ſupport the load which is to be put upon them. In his baggage he ſhould have ſheets, a matraſs, a blanket, and a quilt, a table-cloth, knives, forks, and ſpoons, with a copper vesſel sufficiently capacious to boil his meat. This ſhould be furniſhed with a cover and lock. Each of the ſervants ſhould have a gun slung by the ſide of his mule.</p><p>“ To travel as an economiſt in Spain, a man muſt be contented to take his chance for conveyance, and either go by the poſt, wherever it is eſtabliſhed ; or join with officers, going to their various dations; to hire a coach, or quietly reſign himſelf to a calaſh, a calaſine, a horſe, a mule, or a borrico. This laſt is the moſt convenient for the purpoſe of croſſing the country, or of wandering among the mountains. If he is to traverse any diſtrict infeſted by banditti, it will be ſafe for him to go by the common carriers, in which caſe he will be mounted on a good mule, and take the place which would have been occupied by ſome bale of goods. Any one, who is fond of botany, for ſhort excurſions, will make choice of a borrico. This is always to be had when, as in ſome villages, neither horse nor mule are to be obtained. I have uſed this honourable appellation for the moſt patient of all animals, becauſe I would not shock the delicacy of a young traveller, by telling him, at his firſt ſetting out, that he may ſometimes find himſelf under the neceſſity of riding upon an aſs. He muſt, however, know, for his conſolation, that an aſs does not appear ſo contemptible in Spain as in the colder regions of the north.</p><p>“ The beſt time ſor him to begin this expedition is in autumn, when he may go by Bayonne, Burgos, Valladolid, and Segovia, battening to the court at St Ildesonſo. Here he is to procure letters for the chief cities in Spain. On theſe will depend the whole plealure of his excurſion. During the winter he may see all the ſouth of Spain, Toledo, Cordova, Seville, Cadiz, Gibraltar, Malaga, Granada, Carthagena, Murcia, Alicant, Valencia, and Barcelona. Returning by Zaragoza to Aranjuez in the ſpring, he may follow the Merino flock to the mountains of the north, whilſt the country, on which he has turned his back, is rendered unfit for travelling, by the dissolving heats, by want of proviſions, and by malignant fevers. This ſeaſon will be beſt employed in Galicia, the Aſturias, and the provinces of Biſcay, taking Salamanca and Leon in the way.”</p><p><hi rend="italic">New </hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Spain.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Mexico.	</hi></p><p>SPALATRO, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Spalatto,</hi> a rich, populous, and ſtrong town of the republic of Venice, capital of Venetian Dalmatia, with a good harbour and an archbiſhop’s ſee. Here are the ruins oſ the palace of Diodeſian, of which the late Mr Robert Adam publiſhed in 1764 a ſplendid account, enriched with 71 folio plates. In 1784, Spalatro was nearly depopulated by the plague. It is ſtrong by ſituation, being built on a peninſula, which is joined to Terra Firma by a neck of land half a mile over. It is ſeated on the Gulf of Venice, 35 miles</p></body></text></TEI>