<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:20:25Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>of almonds. They are applied as an external ſtimulant to benumbed or paralytic limbs; to parts affected with fixed rheumatic pains ; and to the ſoles of the feet, in the low ſtage of acute diſeaſes, for raiſing the pulſe : in this intention, a mixture of equal parts of the powdered ſeeds and crumb of bread, with the addition ſometimes of a little bruiſed garlic, are made into a cataplaſm with a ſufficient quantity of vinegar.</p><p>SINAPISM, in pharmacy, an external medicine, in form of a cataplaſm, compoſed chiefly of muſtard-ſeed  pulverized, and other ingredients mentioned in the preceding article.</p><p>SINCERITY, honeſty of intention, freedom from hypocriſy. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Moral Philosoγhy,</hi> n⁰ 157.</p><p>SINCIPUT, in anatomy, the forepart of the head, reaching from the forehead to the coronal future.</p><p>SINDY, a province of Hindoſtan Proper, bounded on the west by Makran, a province of Perſia ; on the north by the territories of the king of Candahar ; on the north-eaſt by thoſe of the Seiks ; on the eaſt by a ſandy deſert ; and on the ſouth-eaſt by Cutch. It extends along the courſe of the river Sinde or Indus from its mouth to Behker or Bhakor, on the frontiers of Moultan. Reckoned that way, it is 300 miles long ; and its breadth, in its wideſt part, is about 160. In many particulars of soil and climate, and in the general appearance oſ the ſurface, Sindy reſembles Egypt ; the lower part of it being compoſed of rich vegetable mould, and extended into a wide dell ; while the upper part of it is a narrow slip of country, confined on one side by a ridge of mountains, and on the other by a ſandy deſert, the river Indus, equal at leaſt to the Nile, winding through the midſt of this level valley, and annually overflowing it. During great part of the ſouth-weſt monſoon, or at leaſt in the months of July, Auguſt, and part of September, which is the rainy ſeaſon in moſt other parts of India, the atmoſphere is here generally clouded ; but no rain falls except very near the ſea. Indeed, very few ſhowers fall during the whole year ; owing to which, and the neighbourhood of the ſandy deſerts, which bound it on the eaſt and on the north- west, the heats are ſo violent, and the winds from thoſe quarters ſo pernicious, that the houſes are contrived ſo as to be occaſionally ventilated by means of apertures on the tops of them, reſembling the funnels of ſmall chimneys. When the hot winds prevail, the windows are cloſely shut ; and the loweſt part oſ the current of air, which is always the hotteſt, being thus excluded, a cooler, becauſe more elevated, part deſcends into the houſe through the funnels. By this contrivance alſo vaſt clouds of dust are excluded ; the entrance of which would alone be ſufficient to render the houſes uninhabitable. The roofs are compoſed of thick layers of earth inſtead of terraces. Few countries are more unwholeſome to European conſtitutions, particularly the lower part of the Delta. The prince of this province is a Mahometan, tributary to the king of Candahar. He reſides at Hydrabad, although Tatta is the capital. The Hindoos, who were the original inhabitants of Sindy, are by their Mahometan governors treated with great rigour, and denied the public exerciſe of their religion ; and this ſeverity drives vaſt numbers of them into other countries. The inland parts of Sindy produce ſaltpetre, ſal-ammoniac, borax, bezoar, lapis la</p><p>zuli, and raw ſilk. They have alſo manufactories of cotton and ſilk of various kinds ; and they make fine cabinets, inlaid with ivory, and finely lackered. They alſo export great quantities of butter, clarified and wrapt up in duppas, made of the hides of cattle. The ladies wear hoops of ivory on both their arms and legs, which when they die are burnt with them. They have large black cattle, excellent mutton, and ſmall hardy horses. Their wild game are deer, hares, antelopes, and foxes, which they hunt with dogs, leopards, and a ſmall fierce creature called a ſhiahguſh.</p><p>SINE, or <hi rend="italic">Right </hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Sine</hi><hi rend="italic"> of an Arch,</hi> in trigonometry, is a right line drawn from one end of that arch, perpendicular to the radius drawn to the other end of the arch ; being always equal to half the cord of twice the arch. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Trigonometry</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Geometry.</hi></p><p>SINECURE, a nominal office, which has a revenue without any employment.</p><p>SINEW, a tendon, that which unites the muſcles to the bones.</p><p>SINGING, the action of making divers inflections of the voice, agreeable to the ear, and correſpondent to the notes of a long or piece of melody. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Melody.</hi></p><p>The firſt thing to be done in learning to sing, is to raiſe a ſcale of notes by tones and ſemitones to an octave, and deſcend by the ſame notes ; and then to rise and fall by greater intervals, as a third, fourth, fifth, &amp;c. and to do all this by notes of different pitch. Then theſe notes are repreſented by lines and ſpaces, to which the syllables <hi rend="italic">fa, ſol, la, mi,</hi> are applied, and the pupil taught to name each line and ſpace thereby ; whence this practice is called <hi rend="italic">ſol-faing,</hi> the nature, reaſon, effects, &amp;c. whereof, ſee under the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Solfaing.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Singing</hi><hi rend="italic"> of Birds.</hi> It is worthy of obſervation, that the female of no ſpecies of birds ever sings : with birds it is the reverſe of what occurs in human kind. Among the feathered tribe, all the cares of life fall to the lot of the tender ſex ; theirs is the fatigue of incubation ; and the principal ſhare in nurſing the helpleſs brool: to alleviate theſe fatigues, and to ſupport her under them, nature hath given to the male the ſong, with all the little blandiſhments and ſoothing arts ; theſe he fondly exerts (even after courtſhip) on ſome ſpray contiguous to the neſt, during the time his mate is performing her parental duties. But that ſhe ſhould be silent is alſo another wiſe proviſion of nature, for her ſong would diſcover her neſt ; as would a gaudineſs of plumage, which, for the same reaſon, ſeems to have been denied her.</p><p>On the ſong of birds ſeveral curious experiments and obſervations have been made by the Hon. Dairies Barrington. See <hi rend="italic">Phil. Tranſ.</hi> vol. lxiii.</p><p>SINGULAR N<hi rend="smallcaps">umber,</hi> in grammar, that number of nouns and verbs which ſtands oppoſed to plural. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Grammar,</hi> n⁰ 14.</p><p>SINISTER, ſomething on or towards the left hand. Hence ſome derive the word sinist<hi rend="italic">er, a sinendo ;</hi> becauſe the gods, by ſuch auguries, permit us to proceed in our deſigns.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sinister,</hi> is ordinarily uſed among us for unlucky ; though, in the ſacred rites of divination, the Romans uſed it in an oppoſite ſenſe. Thus <hi rend="italic">avis sinistra,</hi> or a bird on the left hand, was eſteemed a happy omen : whence,</p></body></text></TEI>