<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:19:20Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>property as they conveniently could in ſuch a hurry. I was with the governor, together with a number of others ; but as ſoon as I was certain they were enemies, I went towards my own houſe with a view to ſave as much as poſſible of my property and natural collections; but was received in ſuch manner, that I could not venture to proceed. My houſe was situated near the ſhore, and unfortunately just oppoſite the frigate which fired.</p><p>I ſaw the balls paſſing through the houſe, and heard them whizzing about my ears. I ſaw that I ſhould loſe all my property ; but life was dearer to me, and I haſtened to the woods.</p><p>“In the afternoon the enemy landed, finding the town almoſt deſtitute of people, but rich in provisions, clothing, and other ſtores. They began immediately to break open the houſes and to plunder. What they did not want, they deſtroyed, burnt, or threw into the river. They killed all the cattle and animals they found in the fields or ſtreets, yards, or elſewhere, not sparing even aſſes, dogs, and cats. Theſe proceedings they continued the whole ſucceeding week, till they had entirely ruined our beautiful and proſpering colony ; and when they found nothing more worth plundering, they ſet fire to the public buildings and all the houſes belonging to the Europeans ; and burnt, as they ſaid, by mistake nine or ten houſes of the coloniſts. In the mean time, they were not leſs active on the water. They ſent three of their veſſels to Bance iſland, an Engliſh ſlave factory higher up the river, which they plundered and burnt, together with ſome ſlave ſhips lying there. They took besides about 10 or 12 prizes, including the company’s veſſels. Moſt of theſe they unloaded and burnt. They took along with them alſo two of our armed veſſels, one of which was a large ſhip, laden with provisions, and which had been long expected ; but ſhe unfortunately arrived a few days too ſoon, and was taken with her whole cargo. We expected at leaſt to receive our private letters, but even this was refuſed, and they were thrown overboard. At laſt, after inflicting on us every hardship we could ſuffer, only ſparing our lives and the houſes of the coloniſts, they ſailed on the 13th of October laſt, at noon, proceeding downwards to the Gold Coaſt, and left us in the moſt dreadful situation, without provisions, medicines, clothes, houſes, or furniture, &amp;c. &amp;c. and I fear much, that moſt of us ſhould have periſhed, had not our friends in the neighbourhood, both natives and Europeans, who were so happy as to eſcape the enemy, been so kind as to  send us what they could ſpare. In the mean time, moſt of us have either been, or ſtill are, very sick, and many have died for want of proper food and medicine. The worſt, however, is now past. At leaſt we are not in any want of proviſion, although of the coarſeſt kind, but are deſtitute of the moſt necessary articles and utenſils for the houſe, the table, and the kitchen.”</p><p>It was thus that the Convention executed their purpoſe of s<hi rend="italic">preading light and liberty through the world.</hi> The Sierra Leona colony was eſtabliſhed for no other end than to aboliſh the slave-trade, to enlighten the Africans, and to render them virtuous, rational, free, and happy ; and thoſe powerful patrons of the rights of man deſtroyed that colony with many circumſtances of the moſt wanton cruelty. Though Mr Afzelius is a Swede, and ought therefore to have been protected by the laws of neutrality, they burnt his houſe with the</p><p>reſt ; deprived him of his trunks, his clothes, and his bed ; deſtroyed the natural curiosities which he had collected at the hazard of his life ; and carried away the inſtruments by means of which only he could collect more. It is with pleaſure, however, that we learn from the proceedings oſ the general court held on the 25th of February 1795, that the directors do not yet deſpair of the colony ; and that they have adopted the moſt prudent meaſures to avert all ſuch calamities in future. That their benevolent labours may be finally crowned with ſucceſs is our earneſt prayer, in which we ſhall, doubtleſs, be joined by every good Chriſtian.</p><p>SIERRA <hi rend="smallcaps">morena,</hi> mountains of Andalusia in Spain.</p><p>SIEUR, a title of reſpect among the French, like that of <hi rend="italic">maſler</hi> among us. It is much used by lawyers, as alſo by superiors in their letters to inferiors.</p><p>SIFANTO, or SIPHANTO, an iſland of the Archipelago, to the west of Paros, to the north-eaſt of Milo, and to the ſouth-west of Serphanto. The air is ſo good here, that many of the inhabitants live to the age of 120; and their water, fruits, wild fowl, and poultry, are excellent, but more eſpecially the grapes. It abounds with marble and granite, and is one of the moſt fertile and beſt cultivated of theſe iſlands. The inhabitants employ themſelves in cultivating olive-trees and capers ; and they have very good silk. They trade in figs, onions, wax, honey, and ſtraw-hats ; and may be about 8000 in all. E. Long. 25. 15. N. Lat. 37. 9.</p><p>SI-FANS, or <hi rend="smallcaps">tou-fans,</hi> a people inhabiting the country on the west of China. Their country is only a continued ridge of mountains, incloſed by the rivers Hoang-ho on the north, Ya-long on the weft, and Yang-tfe kiang on the eaſt, between the 30th and 35th degrees of north latitude.</p><p>The Si-fans are divided into two kinds of people ; the one are called by the Chineſe <hi rend="italic">Black Siſans,</hi> the other <hi rend="italic">Tellow ;</hi> names which are given them from the different colours of their tents. The black are the moſt clowniſh and wretched ; they live in ſmall bodies, and are governed by petty chiefs, who all depend upon a greater.</p><p>The yellow Si-fans are ſubject to families, the oldeſt of which becomes a lama, and aſſumes the yellow dreſs. Theſe lama princes, who command in their respective districts, have the power of trying cauſes, and puniſhing criminals ; but their government is by no means burdenſome ; provided certain honours are paid them, and they receive punctually the dues of the god Fo, which amount to very little, they moleſt none of their ſubjects. The greater part of the Si-fans live in tents; but ſome oſ them have houſes built of earth, and even brick. Their habitations are not contiguous ; they form at moſt but ſome ſmall hamlets, consisting of five or six ſamilies. They feed a great number of flocks, and are in no want of any of the neceſſaries of life. The principal article of their trade is rhubarb, which their country produces in great abundance. Their horſes are ſmall ; but they are well ſhaped, lively, and robuſt.</p><p>Theſe people are of a proud and independent ſpirit, and acknowledge with reluctance the ſuperiority of the Chineſe government, to which they have been ſubjected : when they are ſummoned by the mandarins, they rarely appear ; but the government, for political reaſons,</p></body></text></TEI>