<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:19:42Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>to he adverted to at the time of beginning to breed theſe creatures in any place ; for it will make a great difference in the profit on the whole to the undertaker if he rears a good or a bad sort @@( A ). This is a department in reſpect to the economy of animals that has been in every caſe much leſs adverted to than it deserves ; and in particular with regard to the silk worm it has been almoſt entirely overlooked. A few eggs of the silk worm can be eaſily tranſported by post in a letter from any part of Europe to another, eſpecially during the winter ſeaſon. It would therefore be an easy matter for any patriotic ſociety, ſuch as the Society of Arts in London, to obtain a ſpecimen of the eggs from every country in which silk is now reared, to put theſe under the care of a perſon who could be depended upon, and who underſtood the management of them, with orders to keep each kind diſtinct from another, and advert to every particular that occurred in their management, ſo as to make a fair eſtimate of their reſpective merits. By theſe means the beſt might be (elected, and thoſe of inferior value rejected. Forty or fifty of each sort might be enough for the experiment ; but <hi rend="italic">it</hi> ought to be repeated ſeveral times before conduirons could be drawn from it that might be altogether relied upon ; for it is well known that a variation of circumſtances will make a change in the reſult ; and it is by no means certain that the ſame particular would affect thoſe of one breed exactly in the same manner as it would do thoſe of a different breed. One may be more hardy with regard to cold, another more delicate in reſpect to food, and ſo on. It is experience alone that can aſcertain the circumſtances here inquired for.</p><p>From the above mentioned particulars, it is evident, that the management of silk worms muſt be very different in hot climates from what is required in thoſe that are colder. At Madras, it appears from Dr Anderſon’s experiments that it is very difficult to prevent the eggs from hatching for a very few days, ſo that many generations of them muſt be propagated in one year. In this hotteſt ſeaſon,” ſays he, in a letter to Sir Joſeph Banks, dated July 6. 1791, “ the ſhorteſt time I have been able to remark for the whole evolutions of the silk worm is 40 days ; that is to ſay, six days an egg, 22 a worm, 11 a grub in the cocoon, and one a moth or butterfly.” Fortunately, where the climate forces forward their production ſo rapidly, nature hath been equally provident of food for their ſubſiſtence ; for in theſe regions the mulberry continues to grow and puſh out leaves throughout the whole year.</p><p>Though the silk worm be a native of China, there is no doubt but it might eaſily be propagated perhaps in moſt parts of the temperate zones. The eggs</p><p>of this infect, indeed, require a conſiderable degree of warmth to hatch them, but they can alſo endure a ſevere froſt. No leſs than 5400 lbs of ſilk was raiſed in 1789 in the cold, ſandy territories of Pruſſia. In the province of Pekin, in China, where great quantities of ſilk are fabricated, the winter is much colder than even in Scotland. From the information of ſome Ruffians who were ſent thither to learn the Chineſe language, we find that Reaumur’s thermometer was obſerved from 10 to 15, and even 20 degrees below the freezing point. Nor is it difficult to rear the food of the ſilk worm in a temperate clime. The mulberry-tree is a hardy vegetable, which bears, without injury, the winters of Sweden, and cven of Siberia. Of the ſeven species oſ the mulberry (ſee Mows) enumerated by Linnæus, four of theſe (viz. the white, red, black, and Tartarian), there is every reaſon to believe could be reared both in Britain and Ireland. The <hi rend="italic">white</hi> grows in Sweden ; the <hi rend="italic">red</hi> is abundant round Quebec ; the <hi rend="italic">black</hi> delights in bleak fixations, expoſed to wind on the ſea ſhore ; and the <hi rend="italic">Tartarian</hi> mulberry is repreſented as growing in the chilly regions of Siberia.</p><p>As to the ſuperior qualities of the different ſpecies, probably there is very little to be pointed out amongſt the four juſt mentioned with regard to nouriſhment, except what may be drawn from the following fact : that if the firſt three are laid down together, the ſilk worm will firſt eat the white, then the red, and next the black, in the order of the tenderneſs of the leaves. The Tartarian ſeems to hold as high a place in its eſteem as either the red or black ; but all muſt yield to the white, which ſeems to be its natural food.</p><p>In Calabria the red mulberry is uſed ; in Valencia the white; and in Granada, where excellent ſilk is produced, the mulberries are all black. The white ſeems to prosper very well in a moiſt ſtiff soil : the black agrees well with a dry, ſandy, or gravelly ſoil ; and the white is moſt luxuriant in a moiſt rich loam.</p><p>It may juſtly be aſſerted, that Britain poſſeſſes ſome advantages in the raiſing of raw ſilk which are not enjoyed by warmer countries. Even in the ſouth of France, Mr Arthur Young informs us, the mulberry leaves are often nipped by froſt in the bud ; but this is ſcarcely ever the caſe with us. It is well known that thunder and lightning are hurtful to the ſilk worm. Now our climate can boaſt that it is almoſt wholly exempted from thoſe dreadful ſtorrns of thunder and lightning which prevail ſo much in hot climates. Nature has then furniſhed us with every thing requiſite for the ſilk manufacture ; it remains only for us to improve the advantages which we poſſeſs. Let mulberry trees be planted by proprietors of lands, and let a few perſons</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">@@@(a) As</hi> the ſucceſs <hi rend="italic">of</hi> the ſilk manufacture muſt depend on the breed of worms, it is of great conſequence to bring them from thoſe countries where they are reckoned beſt.</p><p>Mr Andrew Wright, an ingenious ſilk manufacturer of Paiſley, has given the following directions for conveying the eggs of the ſilk worm from diſtant countries by ſea : As ſoon as the moth has laid her eggs, dry them immediately, and put them into glaſs vials ; ſeal them ſo cloſe that damp air or water will not penetrate into them. Put theſe phials that contain the eggs into earthen pots filled with cold water ; and as often as the water becomes warm renew it. Place the earthen veſſels in the coldeſt place of the ſhip, and let them remain until the end of the voyage. It muſt be ebſerved, that the ſhip choſen for this purpoſe ought to be one that would arrive in Britain in the months of June or July.</p></body></text></TEI>