<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>translated from HTML to TEI</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-23-r05-0850-01"
                facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0907.jp2" type="entry">

                <p><label>RŪMĪ</label> (1207-1273). Mahommed b. Mahommed b. Husain albalkbī, better
                    known as Maulānā Jalāl-uddīn Rūmī (or simply Jalāl-uddin, or Jelāl-eddīn), the
                    greatest Sūfic poet of Persia, was born on the 30th of September 1207 (604 a.h.
                    6th of Rabī' I.) at Balkh, in Khorāsān, where his family had resided from time
                    immemorial. He claimed descent from the caliph Abūbekr, and from the
                    Khwárizm-Sháh Sultan 'Alā-uddīn b. Tukush (1199-1220), whose only daughter,
                    Malika-i-Jahán, had been married to Jalāl-uddīn’s grandfather. Her son,
                    Mahommed, commonly called Bahá-uddln Walad, was famous for his learning and
                    piety, but being afraid of the sultan’s jealousy, he emigrated to Asia Minor in
                    1212. After residing for some time at Malatia and afterwards at Erzingán in
                    Armenia, Bahā-uddīn was called to Láranda in Asia Minor, as principal of the
                    local college. Here young Jalāl-uddīn grew up, and in 1226 married Jauhar
                    Khátfin, the daughter of Lálá Sharaf-uddín of Samarkand. Finally, Baha-uddīn was
                    invited to Iconium by 'Alā-uddīn Kaikubād (1219-1236), the sultan of Asia Minor,
                    or, as it is commonly called in the East, Rum—whence Jalāl-uddīn’s surname <hi
                        rend="italic">(takhallus)</hi> Rumi.</p>
               <p>After Baha-uddīn’s death in 1231, Jalāl-uddīn went to Aleppo and Damascus for a
                    short time to study, but, dissatisfied with the exact sciences, he returned to
                    Iconium, where he became by and by professor of four separate colleges, and
                    devoted himself to the study of mystic theosophy. His first spiritual instructor
                    was Sayyid Burhán-uddīn Husaini of Tirmidh, one of his father’s disciples, and,
                    later on, the wandering Sūfi Shams-uddīn of Tabriz, who soon acquired a most
                    powerful influence over Jalāl-uddín. Shams-uddīn’s aggressive character roused
                    the people of Iconium against him, and during a riot in which Jalāl-uddīn’s
                    eldest son, 'Alā-uddīn, was killed, he was arrested and probably executed; at
                    least he was no more seen. In remembrance of these victims of popular wrath
                    Jalāl-uddīn founded the order of the Maulawi (in Turkish Mevlevi) dervishes,
                    famous for their piety as well as for their peculiar garb of mourning, their
                    music and their mystic dance (sama), which is the outward representation of the
                    circling movement of the spheres, and the inward symbol of the circling movement
                    of the soul caused by the vibrations of a Sufi’s fervent love to God. The
                    establishment of this order, which still possesses numerous cloisters throughout
                    the Turkish empire, and the leadership of which has been kept in Jalāl-uddīn’s
                    family in Iconium uninterruptedly for the last six hundred years, gave a new
                    stimulus to his zeal and poetical inspiration. Most of his matchless odes were
                    composed in honour of the Maulawi dervishes, and even his <hi rend="italic">opus
                        magnum,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Mathnawi (Mesnevi),</hi> or, as it is
                    usually called, <hi rend="italic">The Spiritual Mathnawi
                        (mathnawī-i-ma'nawī),</hi> in six books or daftars, with 30,000 to 40,000
                    double-rhymed verses, can be traced to the same source. The idea of this immense
                    collection of ethical and moral precepts was first suggested to the poet by his
                    favourite disciple Hasan, better known as Husám-uddín, who in 1258 became
                    Jalāl-uddīn’s chief assistant. Jalāl-uddīn dictated to him, with a short
                    interruption, the whole work during the remaining years of his life. Soon after
                    its completion Jalāl-uddīn died, on the 17th of December 1273 (672 a.h. 5th of
                    Jomádá II.). His first successor in the rectorship of the Maulawi fraternity was
                    Husám-uddīn himself, after whose death in 1284 Jalāl-uddīn’s younger and only
                    surviving son, Shaikh Baháudddh Ahmed, commonly called Sultán Walad, and
                    favourably known as author of the mystical mathnawi <hi rend="italic"
                        >Rababnama,</hi> or the Book of the Guitar (died 1312), was duly installed
                    as grand-master of the order.</p>
               <p>Jalāl-uddīn’s life is fully described in Shams-uddīn Ahmed Aflaki’s <hi
                        rend="italic">Manákib-ul 'árifin</hi> (written between a.d. 1318 and 1353),
                    the most important portions of which have been translated by J. W. Redhouse in
                    the preface to his English metrical version of <hi rend="italic">The Mesnevi,
                        Book the First</hi> (London, 1881); there is also an abridged translation of
                    the <hi rend="italic">Mathnawi,</hi> with introduction on Sufism, by E. H.
                    Whinfield (2nd ed., 1898). Complete editions have been printed in Bombay,
                    Lucknow, Tabriz, Constantinople and in Bulaq (with a Turkish translation, 1268
                        A. H.), at the end of which a seventh daftar is added,
                    the genuineness of which is refuted by a remark of Jalāl-uddīn himself in one of
                    the Bodleian copies of the poem, Ouseley, 294 (f. 328a seq.). A revised edition
                    was made by ’Abd-ullatif between 1O24 and 1032 a.h., and the same author’s
                    commentary on the <hi rend="italic">Mathnawi, Latā'if-ulma'nawī,</hi> and his
                    glossary, <hi rend="italic">Latā'if-altughāt,</hi> have been lithographed in
                    Cawnpore (1876) and Lucknow (1877) respectively, the latter under the title <hi
                        rend="italic">Farhang-i-mathnawī.</hi> For the other numerous commentaries
                    and for further biographical and literary particulars of Jalāl-uddīn, see Rieu’s
                        <hi rend="italic">Cat. of the Persian MSS</hi>
               </p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-23-r05-0851" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0908.jp2"/>
               <p>                    <hi rend="italic">of the Brit. Mus.,</hi> vol. ii. p. 584 seq.; A. Sprenger's
                        <hi rend="italic">Oudh Cat.,</hi> p. 485; Sir Gore Ouseley, <hi
                        rend="italic">Notices of Persian Poets,</hi> p. 112 seq.; H. Ethé, in <hi
                        rend="italic">Morgenlandische Studien</hi> (Leipzig, 1870), p. 95 seq., and
                    in Geiger and Kuhn’s <hi rend="italic">Grundriss der iramscken Philologie</hi>
                    (Stuttgart, 1896-1904), vol. ii. pp. 287-292. Selections from Jalāl-uddīn's
                    diwan (often styled <hi rend="italic">Dīwān-i-Shams-i-Tabrīz)</hi> are
                    translated in German verse by V. von Rosenzweig (Vienna, 1838); into English by
                    R. A. Nicholson (2nd ed., 1898) and W. Hastic (1903). (H. E.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
