<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/>         </publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>translated from HTML to TEI</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-23-r05-0795-03" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0850.jp2" type="entry">

<p><label>ROZAS, JUAN MARTINEZ DE</label>
(1759-1813), the earliest leader in the Chilean struggle for independence, was born at Mendoza in 1759. In early life he was a professor of law, and of theology and philosophy at Santiago. He held the post of acting governor of Concepcion at one time, and was also colonel in a militia regiment. In 1808 he became secretary to the last Spanish governor, Francisco Antonio Carrasco, and used his position to prepare the nationalist movement that began in</p><p>1809. After resigning his position as secretary, Rozas was mainly responsible for the resignation of the Spanish governor, and the formation of a national Junta on the 18th of September</p><p>1810, of which he was the real leader. Under his influence many reforms were initiated, freedom of trade was established, an army was organized and a national congress was called together in July 1811. But at the end of that year divisions began to arise between Rozas’ followers from Concepción and the men of Santiago; and a feud broke out between Rozas and José Miguel Carrera <hi rend="italic">(q.v.)</hi> who had secured control of Santiago. In 1812 Carrera succeeded in securing the banishment of his rival, who retired to Mendoza, where he died on the 3rd of March 1813.</p><p>See P. B. Figueroa, <hi rend="italic">Diccionario biográfico de Chile, 1550-1887</hi> (Santiago, i888j, and J. B. Suarez, <hi rend="italic">Rasgos biográficos de hombres notables de Chile</hi> (Valparaiso, 1 <hi rend="italic">886) ;</hi> both giving biographical sketches of prominent characters in Chilean history.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>