<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>translated from HTML to TEI</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-23-r05-0773-01"
                facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0826.jp2" type="entry">

                <p><label>ROUND TOWERS</label> » A peculiar class of round tower exists throughout
                    Ireland; about one hundred and twenty examples once existed; most of these are
                    ruined, but eighteen or twenty are almost perfect. These towers were built
                    either near or adjoining a church; they are of various dates, from perhaps the
                    8th to the 13th century; though varying in size and detail, they have many
                    characteristics common to all. They are built with walls slightly battering
                    inwards, so that the tower tapers towards the top. The lower part is formed of
                    solid masonry, the one doorway being raised from 6 to 20 ft. above the ground,
                    and so only accessible by means of a ladder. The towers within are divided into
                    several storeys by two or more floors, usually of wood, but in some cases, as at
                    Keneith, of stone slightly arched. The access from floor to floor was by
                    ladders. The windows, which are always high up, are single lights, mostly arched
                    or with a flat stone'lintel. In some of the oldest towers they have triangular
                    tops, formed by two stones leaning together. One peculiarity of the door and
                    window openings in the Irish round towers is that the jambs are frequently set
                    sloping, so that the opening grows narrower towards the top, as in the temples
                    of ancient Egypt. The later examples of these towers, dating from the 12th and
                    13th centuries, are often decorated with chevron, billet and other Norman
                    enrichments round the jambs and arches. The roof is of stone, usually conical in
                    shape, and some of the later towers are crowned by a circle of battlements. The
                    height of the round towers varies from about 60 to 132 ft.; that at Kilcullen
                    was the highest. The masonry differs according to its date,—the oldest examples
                    being built of almost uncut rubble work, and the later ones of neatly jointed
                    ashlar.</p>
               <p>Much has been written as to the use of these towers, and the most conflicting
                    theories as to their origin have been propounded. It is fairly certain, however,
                    that they were constructed by Christian builders, both from the fact that they
                    always are. or once were near a church, and also because crosses and other
                    Christian emblems frequently occur among, the sculptured decorations of their
                    doors and windows. Their original purpose was probably for places of refuge, for
                    which the solid base and the door high above the ground seem specially adapted.
                    They may also have been watch-towers, and in later times often contained bells.
                    Their circular form was</p>
               <p>Crobably for the sake.of strength, angles which could be attacked y a battering
                    ram being thus avoided, and also because no quoins ordressed stones were
                    needed,except for the openings—an important point at a time when tools for
                    working stone were scarce and imperfect. Both these reasons may also account for
                    the Norman round towers which are so common at the west end of churches in
                    Norfolk, Suffolk and Essex, though these have little resemblance to those of
                    Ireland except in the use of a circular plan. One example exactly like those of
                    Ireland exists in the Isle of Man, within the precincts of Peel Castle adjacent
                    to the cathedral of St German; it was probably the work of Irish builders. There
                    are also three in Scotland, viz. at Egilshay in Orkney, and at Abemethy and
                    Brechin.</p>
               <p>Round towers wider and lower in proportion than those of Ireland appear to have
                    been built by many prehistoric races in different parts of Europe. The towers of
                    this class in Scotland are called “ brochs they average about 50 ft. high and 30
                    ft. in internal diameter. Their walls, which are usually about 15 ft. thick at
                    the bottom, are built hollow, of rubble masonry, with series of passages one
                    over the other running all round the tower. As in the Irish towers, the entrance
                    is placed at some distance from the ground; and the whole structure is designed
                    as a stronghold. The brochs</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-23-r05-0774" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0827.jp2"/>
               <p>appear to have been the work of a pre-Christian Celtic race. Many objects in
                    bronze and iron and fragments of hand-made pottery have been found in and near
                    these towers, all bearing witness of a very early date. (See Anderson, <hi
                        rend="italic">Scotland in Pagan Times,</hi> 1883, and <hi rend="italic"
                        >Scotland in Early Christian Times,</hi> 1881.) The <hi rend="italic"
                        >nuraghi</hi> of Sardinia are described in the article on that island.
                    During the 6th century church towers at and near Ravenna were usually built
                    round in plan, and not unlike those of Ireland in their proportions. The finest
                    existing example is that which stands by the church of S. Apollinarc in Classe,
                    the old port of the city of Ravenna (see Basilica, fig. 8). It is of brick,
                    divided into nine storeys, with singlelight windows below, three-light windows
                    in the upper storeys, and two-lights in the intermediate ones. The.most
                    magnificent example of a round tower is the well-known leaning tower of Pisa,
                    begun in the year 1174. It is richly decorated with tiers of open marble
                    arcades, supported on free columns. The circular plan was much used by Moslem
                    races for their minarets. The finest of these is the 13th-century minar of Kutb
                    at Old Delhi, built of limestone with bands of marble. It is richly fluted on
                    plan, and when complete was at least 250 ft. high.</p>
               <p>The best account of the Irish round towers is that given by Petrie in his <hi
                        rend="italic">Ecclesiastical Architecture of Ireland</hi> (Dublin, 1845).
                    See also Keane, <hi rend="italic">Towers and Temples of Ancient Ireland</hi>
                    (Dublin, 1850); Brash, <hi rend="italic">Ecclesiastical Architecture of
                        Ireland</hi> (Dublin, 1875); and Stokes, <hi rend="italic">Early
                        Architecture in Ireland</hi> (Dublin, 1878). (J. H. M.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
