<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/>         </publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>translated from HTML to TEI</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-23-r05-0787-02" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0842.jp2" type="entry">

<p><label>ROWLANDS, SAMUEL</label>
(c. 1573-1630), English author of pamphlets in prose and verse, which reflect the follies and humours of the lower middle-class life of his time, seems to have had no contemporary literary reputation; but his work throws considerable light on the social London of his day. Among his works, which include some poems on sacred subjects, are: <hi rend="italic">The Betraying of Christ</hi> (1598); <hi rend="italic">The Letting of Humours Blood in the Head-vaine</hi> (epigrams and satires) and <hi rend="italic">A Mery Meetinge, or ’tis Mery when Knaves mete</hi> (1600)—the two latter being publicly burnt by order, but republished later under other names— <hi rend="italic">{Humors Ordinarie</hi> and <hi rend="italic">The Knave of Clubbes); Greenes Ghost haunting Conie-Catchers</hi> (1602), which he pretended to have edited from Greene’s papers, but which is largely borrowed from his printed works; <hi rend="italic">Tis Merrie when Gossips meete</hi> (1602), a dialogue between a Widow, a Wife, a Maid and a Vintner; <hi rend="italic">Looke to it; for lie stabbe ye</hi> (1604), in which Death describes the tyrants, careless divines and other evil-doers whom he will destroy; <hi rend="italic">Hells broke loose</hi> (1605), an account of John of Leyden, and in the same year a <hi rend="italic">Theatre of Divine Recreation</hi> (not extant), poems founded on the Old Testament; <hi rend="italic">A Terrible Battell betwene . . . Time and Death</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Democritus, or Doctor Merry-man his Medicines against Melancholy humors,</hi> reprinted, with alterations, as <hi rend="italic">Doctor Merrie-man,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Diogenes Lanthorne</hi> (1607), in which “ Athens ” is London; <hi rend="italic">The Famous History of Guy, Earl of Warwick</hi> (1607), a long romance in Rowlands’s favourite six-lined stanza, and one of his hastiest, least successful efforts; <hi rend="italic">Humors Looking Glasse</hi> (1608); and <hi rend="italic">Martin Mark-all, Beadle of Bridewell</hi> (1610), a history of roguery containing much information about notable highwaymen and the completest vocabulary of thieves’ slang up to that time. Of his later works may be mentioned <hi rend="italic">Sir Thomas Over bury; or the Poysoned Knights Complaint,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">The Melancholic Knight</hi> (1615), which suggests a hearing of Beaumont and Fletcher’s <hi rend="italic">Knight of the Burning Pestle.</hi> The last of his humorous studies, <hi rend="italic">Good Newes and Bad Newes,</hi> appeared in 1622, and in 1628 he published a pious volume of prose and verse, entitled <hi rend="italic">Heavens Glory, Seeke it: Earts vanitie, Flye it: Hells Horror, Fere it.</hi> After this nothing is known of him. Mr Gosse, in his introduction to Rowlands’s complete works, edited (1872-80) for the Hunterian Club in Glasgow by Air S. J. H. Herrtage, sums him up as a “ kind of small non-political Defoe, a pamphleteer in verse whose talents were never put into exercise except when their possessor was pressed for means, and a poet of considerable talent without one spark or glimmer of genius.”</p><p>Mr Gosse’s notice is reprinted in his <hi rend="italic">Seventeenth Century Studies</hi> (1883). A recently discovered poem by Rowlands, <hi rend="italic">The Bride</hi> (1617), was reprinted at Boston, U.S.A., in 1905 by Mr A. C. Potter.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>