<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/>         </publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>translated from HTML to TEI</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-23-r05-0945-03" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_1008.jp2" type="entry">

<p><label>RUTLEY, FRANK</label>
(1842-1904), English geologist and petrog-rapher, was born at Dover on the 14th of May 1842. He was educated partly at Bonn, but his interest in geology was kindled at the Royal School of Mines, where he studied from 1862-64; he then joined the army, and served as lieutenant until 1867,</p>
<pb xml:id="eb11-23-r05-0946" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_1009.jp2"/><p>when he became an Assistant Geologist on the Geological Survey. Working then in the Lake district, he began to make a special study of rocks and rock-forming minerals, and soon qualified as acting petrographer on the Geological Survey. For several years he worked in this capacity at the Museum in Jermyn Street: he described the volcanic rocks of E. Somerset and the Bristol district in 1876, and wrote special memoirs on <hi rend="italic">The Eruptive Rocks of Brent Tor</hi> (1878), and on <hi rend="italic">The Felsiiic Lavas of England and Wales</hi> (1885). He was the author of an exceedingly useful little book on <hi rend="italic">Mineralogy</hi> (1874; 12th cd., 1900); also of <hi rend="italic">The Study of Rocks</hi> (1879; 2nd cd., 1881), <hi rend="italic">Rock-forming Minerals</hi> (1888), and <hi rend="italic">Granites and Greenstones</hi> (1894); and of a number of petrographical papers, dealing with perlitic and sphcrulitic structures, with the rocks of the Malvern Hills, &amp;c. In 1882 he was appointed lecturer on Mineralogy in the Royal College of Science, and held this post until ill-health compelled him to retire in 1898. He died in London on the 16th of May 1904.</p><p>Obituary (by H. B. Woodward), with bibliography, in <hi rend="italic">GeoL Mag.</hi> (July 1904).</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>