<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2018-12-30T23:25:55Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p><hi rend="italic">Lehrbuch für den Geschichtsunterricht in der Sekundärschule</hi> (Zürich, 1885), is very accurate and handy. Far more popular in style than any yet mentioned are J. Sutz's <hi rend="italic">Schweizer-Geschichte für das Volk erzählt</hi> (La Chaux de Fonds, 1899), and A. Gobat, <hi rend="italic">Histoire de la Suisse racontée au peuple</hi> (Neuchâtel, 1900). A very attractive summary (including social and economical history) is given in H. Vulliéty's <hi rend="italic">La Suisse à travers les âges</hi> (Basel and Geneva, 1901).</p><p>J. Heierli’s <hi rend="italic">Urgeschichte der Schweiz</hi> (Zürich, 1901), has superseded all earlier works (such as Heer) on prehistoric Switzerland. The authentic early history of the Confederation (see also <hi rend="smallcaps">Tell, Tschudi,</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Winkelried</hi>) is admirably told in W. Oechsli’s <hi rend="italic">Die Anfänge der schweizerischen Eidgenossenschaft</hi> (Zürich, 1891, also in French), as well as in the older work by A. Rilliet, <hi rend="italic">Les Origines de la confédération suisse</hi> (2nd cd., Geneva and Basel, 1869). For the earlier medieval history (1273-1334) J. E. Kopp’s <hi rend="italic">Geschichte der eidgenössischen Bünde</hi> (5 vols., Leipzig, Lucerne and Basel, 1845-1882) is a perfect storehouse of information, while the medieval political Swiss system in relation to the empire has been very clearly described by W. Oechsli in his article (published in vol. v., 1890, of Hilty’s <hi rend="italic">Politisches Jahrbuch)</hi> “ Die Bezieh- ιιngen der Schweiz. Eidgenossenschaft zum Reiche bis zum Schwabenkrieg, 1499,” while the same writer’s article (pub- lished in vol. xiii., 1888, of the <hi rend="italic">Jahrbuch für schweizerische Geschichte)</hi> “ Orte und Zugewandte,” gives an admirable account of the relations of many small districts and towns to the Swiss Confederation, as “allies, from the earliest times to 1798. The two following works trace certain phenomena throughout Swiss history —P. Schweizer, <hi rend="italic">Geschichte der schweizerischen Neutralität</hi> (Frauenfeld, 1895), and J. Schollenberger, <hi rend="italic">Geschichte der schweizer. Politik </hi>(2 vols., Frauenfeld, 1906 and 1908). As to the more recent history of Switzerland (since 1798) see, besides various articles in Hilty’s <hi rend="italic">Jahrbuch,</hi> C. Hilty, <hi rend="italic">Öffentliche Vorlesungen über die Helυetik</hi> (Bern,</p><p>1878)	; W. Oechsli, <hi rend="italic">Geschichte der Schweiz im xix. Jahrhundert </hi>(vol. i., Leipzig, 1903, extends from 1798 to 1813); F. Burckhardt, <hi rend="italic">Die schweizerische Emigration, 1798-1901</hi> (Basel, 1908); B. van Muyden, <hi rend="italic">La Suisse sous le pacte de 1815</hi> (2 vols., 1815-1838, Lausanne, 1890-1891) ; G. H. Dufour, <hi rend="italic">Der Sonderbunds-Krieg und die Ereignisse von 1856 in Neuenburg</hi> (Basel, 1876; also in French, Paris, 1876); G. Grote, <hi rend="italic">Seven Letters concerning the Politics of Switzerland </hi>(1847, enlarged ed., London, 1876); T. Curti, <hi rend="italic">Die schweizerischen Volksrechte, 1848-1900</hi> (Bern, 1900); J. Schollenberger, <hi rend="italic">Die Schweiz seit 1848</hi> (Berlin, 1908); and the blue-book (London, 1848) entitled <hi rend="italic">Correspondence Relative to the Affairs of Switzerland,</hi> with the following volumes of memoirs by Swiss statesmen : A. P. Segesser, <hi rend="italic">Fünf und vierzig Jahre im luzernischen Staatsdienst, 1841-1887 </hi>(Bern, 1887) ; J. C. Kern, <hi rend="italic">Souvenirs politiques, 1838-1883</hi> (Bern, 1887) ; and Nu ma Droz, <hi rend="italic">Études et portraits politiques</hi> (Geneva, 1895), as well as lives of others. For the history of Switzerland in the 19th century see T. Curti, <hi rend="italic">Geschichte der Schweiz im xix. Jahrhundert</hi> (Neuchâtel, 1902), and the work entitled <hi rend="italic">La Suisse αu xix</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">me</hi> <hi rend="italic">siècle (3</hi> vols., Lausanne, 1899-1900; also issued in German).</p><p>The following works are very useful for various departments of Swiss history: <hi rend="italic">Genealogisches Handbuch zur schweizer Geschichte </hi>(in course of publication since 1900 at Zürich); P. Ganz, <hi rend="italic">Geschichte der heraldischen Kunst in der Schweiz im xii. and xiii. Jahrhundert </hi>(Frauenfeld, 1899); E. Schulthess, <hi rend="italic">Die Städte- und Landes-Siegel der Schweiz</hi> (Zurich, 1853); P. Küpfer’s <hi rend="italic">Armorial des villes suisses </hi>(12o shields, Basel, 1885) ; A. Gautier, <hi rend="italic">Les Armoiries et les couleurs de la confédération et des cantons suisses</hi> (2nd ed., Geneva and Basel,</p><p>1879)	; and L. Tobler’s <hi rend="italic">Schweizerische Volkslieder</hi> (2 vols., Frauenfeld, 1882-1884; many historical ballads, texts with introductions). The best historical atlas is the <hi rend="italic">Historisch-geographischer Atlas der Schweiz</hi> by J. C. Vögelin, G. Meyer von Knonau and G. von Wyss (new ed., Zürich, 1870), while L. Poirier-Delay and F. Müllhaupt’s <hi rend="italic">Historischer Atlas der Schweiz</hi> (Bern, 1898), and J. S. Gerster’s small maps (Zürich, 1886) are also useful. There is a set of small Swiss historical maps in one sheet (No. 25) in Droysen’s <hi rend="italic">Allgemeiner historischer Atlas</hi> (Bielefeld, 1886), and a single general one (No. 44) in R. L. Poole’s <hi rend="italic">Historical Atlas of Modern Europe</hi> (Oxford, 1902).</p><p>For the pre-1798 constitution of Switzerland see J. Simler, <hi rend="italic">De Helvetiae republicâ</hi> (Zürich 1576; also in German and French), and Abraham Stanyan’s <hi rend="italic">An Account of Switzerland</hi> (London, 1714).</p><p>The best and most recent works on the existing Swiss constitution of 1874 and its history are the large volume by W. Burckhardt, <hi rend="italic">Kommentar der Schweiz. Bundesverfassung von 1874</hi> (Bern, 1905), and the smaller one by J. Schollenberger, <hi rend="italic">Bundesverfassung der Schweiz. Eidgenossenschaft. Kommentar mit Einleitung</hi> (Berlin, 1905), while the same author’s <hi rend="italic">Das Bundesstaatsrecht der Schweiz. Geschichte und System</hi> (Berlin, 19o2) and his <hi rend="italic">Grundriss der Staatsund Verwaltungsrechts der Schweiz. Kantone</hi> (2 vols., Zürich, 1898- 1899) are clear, and, especially the last-named, very useful as to cantonal matters. In English there is nothing better than J. M. Vincent’s <hi rend="italic">Government in Switzerland</hi> (New York and London, 1900), for the work by F. O. Adams and C. D. Cunningham is not very satisfactory, though better in its French edition (Basel and Geneva, 1890) than in its original English shape (London, 1889). The decisions of the Swiss Federal Tribunal as to Swiss constitutional law are collected (up to the end of 1902) in L. R. von Salis’s <hi rend="italic">Schweizerisches Bundesrecht</hi> (2nd ed., 5 vois., Bern, 1903-1904), while H. Ryffel's <hi rend="italic">Die schweizer. Landsgemeinden</hi> (Zürich, 1904) and T. Curti's <hi rend="italic">Die schweizer. Volksrechte</hi> (Bern, 1900) touch on special sides of the subject. See, too, <hi rend="smallcaps">Commune</hi> (Swiss) and <hi rend="smallcaps">Referendum and Initiative.</hi> Many of the older works are still worth consulting, such as those by Snell (1839-1844), Stettler (1847), Ullmer (1862- 1866), Pfaff (1870), Bluntschli (2nd ed., 1875), Meyer (1875-1878), Dubs (1878), Orelli (1885), and Blumer (latest ed., vol. i., 1891; vols. ii. and iii., 1880-1887). There are also useful articles in Furrer’s and Reichcsberg’s dictionaries. J. J. Blumer’s <hi rend="italic">Staats- und Rechts geschickte der Schweiz. Demokratieen</hi> (2 vols., St Gall, 1850- 1858) deals collectively with the old democratic cantons—Uri, Schwyz, Unterwalden, Glarus, Zug and Appenzell—and is still very useful for local history ; the special works as to the constitutional history of other cantons are mentioned in the articles relating to them. A general theoretical work on federal constitutions in general is L. le Fur’s <hi rend="italic">État Fédéral et Confédération d'états</hi> (Paris, 1896), vol. i. of a new German edition of which (prepared by the author with the help of P. Posener) appeared at Breslau in 1902; this is more up to date than E. A. Freeman’s <hi rend="italic">Federal Government </hi>(new ed. of vol. i., London, 1893), or than J. B. Westerkamp’s <hi rend="italic">Staatenbund und Bundesstaat</hi> (Leipzig, 1900).</p><p>There is no really satisfactory general ecclesiastical history of Switzerland before the Reformation, though monographs abound, and much material has been collected in the <hi rend="italic">Zeitschrift für Schweizerische Kirchengeschichte</hi> (Stans, from 1907). E. E. Gelpke’s <hi rend="italic">Kirchengeschichte der Schweiz</hi> (2 vols., Bern, 1856-1861) is now out of date, and only includes the early portion of the period (it is written from a Protestant standpoint), while vol. ii. of B. Fleischlin’s <hi rend="italic">Studien und Beiträge zur schweizer. Kirchengeschichte</hi> (Lucerne, 1902-1903) includes the period 800 to 1520, but is written from a strong Romanist point of view. As to the early history consult E. Egli<hi rend="superscript">,</hi>s <hi rend="italic">Die christlichen Inschriften der Schweiz von iv-ix. Jahrhundert</hi> (Zürich, 1895), and his <hi rend="italic">Kirchengeschichte der Schweiz bis auf Karl den Grossen</hi> (Zürich, 1893); S. Guyer, <hi rend="italic">Die christlichen Denkmäler des ersten Jahrtausends in der Schweiz </hi>(Leipzig, 1907); A. Lütolf, <hi rend="italic">Die Glaubensboten der Schweiz vor St Gallus</hi> (Lucerne, 1871); and E. F. Gelpke, <hi rend="italic">Die christliche Sagengeschichte der Schweiz</hi> (Bern, 1862). As to the medieval saints in Switzerland see E. A. Stückelberg, <hi rend="italic">Geschichte der Reliquien in der Schweiz</hi> (2 vols., Zurich and Basel, 19o2 and 1908), and his <hi rend="italic">Die Schweiz. Heiligen des Mittelalters</hi> (Zürich, 1903), and J. Genoud’s <hi rend="italic">Les Saints de la Suisse française</hi> (new ed., <hi rend="italic">2</hi> vοls., Fribourg, 1897). For the documentary history of some of the medieval Swiss dioceses see <hi rend="italic">Regesta episcoporum constantiensium,</hi> edited by P. Lade wig and T. Müller (2 vols., from 596 to 1383, as yet published, Innsbruck, 1895 and 1905); M. Besson, <hi rend="italic">Recherches sur les origines des évêchés de Genève, Lausanne, et Sion</hi> (Fribourg, 1906), and L. Stouff, <hi rend="italic">Le Pouvoir temporal des évêques de Bâle</hi> (2 vols., Paris, 1891). E. E. von Mülinen’s <hi rend="italic">Helvetia sacra (2</hi> vols., Bern, 1858 and 1861) gives the succession of the various bishops, abbots, provosts, &amp;c., but requires bringing up to date. For the medieval Swiss monasteries we have <hi rend="italic">Die Regesten der Archive in der Schweiz. Eidgenossenschaft </hi>(edited by T. von Mohr; <hi rend="italic">2</hi> vols., Coire, 1851-1854), though it refers only to a few monasteries, for which it is indispensable, while Arnold Nüscheler’s <hi rend="italic">Die Gotteshäuser der Schweiz</hi> (3 pts., Zurich, 1864-1873, continued by the author and others in the <hi rend="italic">Geschichtsfreund</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Argovia,</hi> complete index issued as an appendix to the <hi rend="italic">Anzeiger für schweizerische Geschichte,</hi> 1900) is most valuable and useful. Some of the great monasteries have histories of their own, such as Einsie- deln (<hi rend="italic">q</hi>.v.), Engelberg <hi rend="italic">(q.v.),</hi> and Muri, the last by Pater M. Kiem, <hi rend="italic">Geschichte der Benedictiner-Abtei Muri</hi> (2 vols., Stans, 1888 and 1891). Two monographs may be mentioned: R. G. Bindschedler, <hi rend="italic">Kirchliches Asylrecht und Freistätten in der Schweiz</hi> (Stuttgart, 1906), and Augusta Steinberg, <hi rend="italic">Studien zur Geschichte der Juden in der Schweiz während des Mittelalters</hi> (Zürich, 1903). For the Reformation and later times consult (on the Protestant side), besides biographies, &amp;c., of Calvin and Zwingli (<hi rend="italic">qq. v.),</hi> E. Bloesch, <hi rend="italic">Geschichte der schweizerischreformierten Kirchen</hi> (2 vols., Bern, 1898—1899); and W. Hadorn, <hi rend="italic">Geschichte des Pietismus in der Schweiz, reform. Kirchen</hi> (Constance, 1901), and the same author’s <hi rend="italic">Kirchengeschichte der reformierten Schweiz</hi> (since 1906). F. Meyer’s work, <hi rend="italic">Die evangelische Gemeinde in Locarno</hi> (2 vols., Zurich, 1836), treats of an important event of that period. The Romanist standpoint is presented in vols. iii. and iv. (1904 sqq.) of Fleischlin’s work mentioned above, and also in J. G. Mayers <hi rend="italic">Das Conzil von Trient und die Gegenreformation in der Schweiz</hi> (2 vols., Stans, 1901 and 1903).</p><p>For more modern days the best book, especially from the consti- tutional side, is C. Gareis and P. Zorn, <hi rend="italic">Staat und Kirche in der Schweiz </hi>(2 vols., Zürich, 1877-1878), which tells the story down to the date of publication. Special subjects are treated of in M. Kothing, <hi rend="italic">Die Bisthumsverhandlungen der schweiζerisch-konstanzischeη Diäzesan- stände von 1803-1802</hi> (Schwyz, 1863); F. Troxler, <hi rend="italic">Der Kulturkampf von 1863-1888</hi> (Bienne, 1889); Ch. Woeste, <hi rend="italic">Histoire du Culturkampf en Suisse, 1871-1886</hi> (Brussels, 1887, Romanist work); and P. Gschwind, <hi rend="italic">Geschichte der Entstehung der christkatholischen Kirche der Schweiz</hi> (vol. i. appeared at Basel in 1904). The work by A. Büchi entitled <hi rend="italic">Die katholische Kirche in der Schweiz</hi> (Munich, 1902) gives a full and authorized account of the present state of the Roman Catholic Church in Switzerland.</p></body></text></TEI>