<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-19T20:11:40Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>and Myten Mountains, and has a fine council-house, a church, and a monastery, and contains 4790 inhabitants, who have very little commerce of any kind except, what is created by the visits of tourists. Long. 8. 33. E. Lat. 47. 1. N.</p><p>SCIAGRAPHY, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Sciography,</hi> the profile or vertical section of a building, used for showing the inside of it.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sciagraphy</hi>, in <hi rend="italic">Astronomy,</hi> is a term made use of by some authors to signify the art of finding the hour of the day or night by the shadow of the sun, moon, or stars.</p><p>SCICLI, a city of the island of Sicily, in the province of Noto. It stands on a river of the same name, in a hollow way between two lofty rocks which terminate in the sea near the small harbour of Petershaven. It is in a humid atmosphere, but contains 10,500 inhabitants, who are industriously employed in various manufactures of cloth, pottery-ware, and leather.</p><p>SCIENCE, in <hi rend="italic">Philosophy,</hi> denotes any body of doctrines deduced from self-evident principles.</p><p>SCIGLIANO, a city of Italy, in the Neapolitan province of Calabria Citeriore. It is situated in a valley on the great road, is defended by a castle, and contains 5620 inhabitants, who are employed in making mattresses and blankets.</p><p>SC ILLY, a group of islands off the coast of Cornwall, from which they are distant about thirty miles. These islands are supposed by some to have been the Cassiterides or Ten Islands with which the Phoenicians traded ; but that is a disputable point. There are six islands of this group that are inhabited, but they are all in one parish, that of St Mary, in which is the parish church. There are a few small islands, or rather bare rocks, with no inhabitants, among which is that which gives its name to the whole group. The island of St Mary contains more inhabitants than all the others, and the town on it is the only one. In 1831 it contained 1311 inhabitants. It has a harbour, a church, and strong fortifications. On the island of St Agnes is the important lighthouse, which is of the highest value to ships approaching the channel in wintry or foggy weather. There is likewise on it a small church. The cultivation of these islands is imperfect, and does not, in common years, produce more than a bare sufficiency of food for the population, which is consequently on the decline ; appearing by the census of 1821 to have amounted to 2614, and by that of 1831 to 2465. In unfruitful seasons the greatest distress for food has been experienced, though in all seasons fish is the common aliment. These islands are dangerous to approach, and have been fatal to many ships, as well as to Admiral Shovel and a part of his fleet in the beginning of the last century. There are establishments of pilots ready to assist vessels, and they often conduct vessels into the harbour of St Mary, through intricate and hazardous passages. There are said to be several Druidical remains on these islands. The population in 1831 was, St Mary, 1311 ; Tresco, 470; St Agnes, 289 ; St Martins, 230 ; Bryher, 128 ; and Sampson Isle, 37.</p><p>SCINDAPSOS, <hi rend="italic">σχιvδαψος</hi>, a four-stringed musical instrument, according to Athenæus (lib. iv. c. 25).</p><p>SCIO, an island of the Mediterranean, not far from the coast of Smyrna, and one of those classed as the Sporades. It was known to the ancients by the name of Chios, and by the Turks is now called Sakez-Adassi. It is situated between the parallels of 38° 8' and 38° 30', and between the meridians 25° 50' and 26° 11', thus being in length twenty-two and in breadth twenty-one geographical miles. It is separated from the shore of Anatolia by a strait, called sometimes the Strait of Bianca, and sometimes that of Scio, which is seven leagues long, and has a depth of water of twenty fathoms. The road, or, as it is called, the Great Port, has depth for ships of the greatest draught of water ; and near to it is the harbour of Fin or Delfyn. To the south of this last port, at about two leagues distance, is the capital of the island, the city of Scio, which, in spite of the dreadful disasters which it has endured, still exists. It was</p><p>built by the Genoese when they possessed the island. It is wholly constructed of stone or brick, and was till recently much cleaner in its appearance than most towns in this part of the world. Mr Galt, who visited it in 1810, says, that “ the houses are built in the Italian style, with lofty pyramidal roofs. Except in the particular of dress, and with the exception of the streets where the shops are situated, every thing about Scio has the appearance of a town in Christendom. The shops are well filled, many of them with those gorgeous stuffs of woven gold and silver which are but rarely to be seen even in London. This was one of the principal manufacturing seats of the Turkish empire ; and silks, which rival in beauty and elegance the richest of France and ltaly, are produced in the looms of Scio. In the town are about ninety places of worship belonging to the Greek and Roman persuasions. There is a cathedral, a respectable building, adorned with modern paintings. Almost the whole of the lower class are silk weavers and embroiderers. Many of the villas in the neighbourhood of the town are large buildings, with attached pleasure-grounds and beautiful gardens.”</p><p>At a later period the city contained about 5000 houses, and the inhabitants were estimated at 25,000 persons. Besides the city, there were on the island seventy-six large villages, containing Armenians, Turks, and Greeks. The latter were calculated by none below eighty, but by some at a hundred thousand.</p><p>A traveller, Mr Laurent, who visited the island in 1818, says, “ All the ideas which fancy can form of an earthly paradise seem realized here ; the face of the country, itself most fruitful, is cultivated with the greatest assiduity, and every part presents rich vineyards intermingled with fruitful trees. The valleys are intersected with paths shaded by trees, spreading over the traveller’s head their luxuriant branches, bending in the seasons under the weight of lemons, oranges, and pomegranates. The inhabitants seem willing to join their efforts to add to the charms of their island ; by all the foreigner is welcomed, and the traveller hears the salute of the peasant, <hi rend="italic">kale emera, kalé espera,</hi> good day, or good evening, as he passes along.”</p><p>Among the productions of the island, wine is one of much celebrity when drank on the spot ; but, from the delicacy of its flavour, it suffers by removal. The corn produced is not equal to more than two months’consumption ; the fruits, which are the chief means of subsistence, are the finest in the Levant ; the figs are of an incredible size, and the lemons and oranges exported are said to have risen to the value of L.25,000. Mastic gum is an article of great importance, and the shrub from which it exudes was very extensively cultivated. The other articles of export were cotton wool, silk, terebinth, wrought silks, and tanned hides.</p><p>Literature was more cultivated in Scio than in any other of the Greek islands ; and no priest officiated there who had not been a member of the college.</p><p>The richest of the inhabitants were merchants at the head of considerable houses, with commercial establishments under the management of partners in Odessa, Venice, Fiume, Trieste, Leghorn, Genoa, Marseilles, Vienna, and London. They lived here in elegantly-furnished houses, were hospitable to strangers, and in the enjoyment of a degree of ease and freedom which was nowhere else to be witnessed within the other territories under the dominion of the Turks.</p><p>The favourable circumstances in which the people lived was in a great part owing to the power over the island having been granted to a sultana, a sister of the sultan, who, satisfied with a sum of money annually collected by the people among themselves, left them almost to their own religion, laws, manners, and occupations; but she is said to have prided herself on the superiority of those under her sway to any other Turkish subjects.</p></body></text></TEI>