<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-19T20:09:24Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>many, and procured him the patronage of all the princes who had any regard for polite
                literature. He was made professor of the belles lettres at Frankfort on the Oder,
                rector of the new academy of Königsberg, and counsellor to the elector of
                Brandenburg. He married two wives, the first of whom was the eldest daughter of
                Melancthon, and died in 1560. His poems are well known, and have often been
                printed.</p>
            <p>SABIONETTA, a city of the province of Mantua, in Austrian Lombardy, with a citadel,
                four churches, and 6320 inhabitants. Long. 10. 24. 45. E. Lat. 44. 59. 47. N.</p>
            <p>SABLE, or <hi rend="italic smallcaps">Sable</hi><hi rend="italic"> Animal,</hi> in
                    <hi rend="italic">Zoology,</hi> a creature of the weasel-kind, called by authors
                    <hi rend="italic">mustela zihellina.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Mammalia.</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sable, </hi><hi rend="italic">Cape,</hi> the most southerly
                province of Nova Scotia, in North America. Long. 65. 34. W. Lat. 43. 24. N.</p>
            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sable,</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Heraldry,</hi> signifies black,
                and is borrowed from the French, as are most terms in this science. In engraving it
                is expressed by both horizontal and perpendicular lines crossing each other. Sable
                of itself signifies constancy, learning, and grief ; and ancient heralds will have
                it, that when it is compounded with</p>
            <table cols="3">
                <row>
                    <cell>Or,</cell>
                    <cell rows="6">it signifies</cell>
                    <cell>Honour.</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Arg.</cell>
                    <cell>Fame.</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Gul.</cell>
                    <cell>Respect.</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Azu.</cell>
                    <cell>Application.</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Ver.</cell>
                    <cell>Comfort.</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Pur.</cell>
                    <cell>Austerity.</cell>
                </row>
            </table>
            <p>SABLES D’OLONNE, <hi rend="smallcaps">Les,</hi> an arrondissement of the department
                of Vendée, in France. It extends over seven hundred and thirty-two and a half square
                miles, and comprehends eleven cantons, divided into seventy-nine communes, with
                98,508 inhabitants in 1836. The capital is the city of the same name, situated at
                the termination of a sandy plain on the sea-shore, and only connected by a strip of
                land with the continent. It has a small harbour fit for vessels of not more than a
                hundred and fifty tons. It consists of four long parallel streets, with 4778
                inhabitants, who carry on the fisheries, and deal in corn, cattle, and salt, which
                last is made by the sun on the marshes. Long. 1. 53.3. W. Lat. 46. 29. 50. N.</p>
            <p>SABON, an island in the Eastern Seas, at the southern entrance of the Straits of
                Malacca, of a triangular form. It is separated from Sumatra by a navigable channel,
                the Straits of Sabon, and is twenty-four miles in circumference. Long. 103. 21. E.
                Lat. 0. 24. N.</p>
            <p>SABOU, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Saivu,</hi> probably the same island as Savo, near
                Timor, to which the reader is referred.</p>
            <p>SABRAO, an island in the Eastern Seas, separated from the island of Flores by the
                Straits of Flores. It is forty miles in length by eighteen in average breadth.</p>
            <p>SABRE, a kind of sword or scimitar, with a very broad and heavy blade, thick at the
                back, and a little falcated or crooked towards the point. It is the ordinary weapon
                worn by the Turks, who are very expert in the: use of it.</p>
            <p>SA BULAGH, a town and district of Persia, in Azer- bijan, situated on the lake
                Urumea, thirty miles from Ma- raga.</p>
            <p>SACÆA, a feast which the ancient Babylonians and other orientals held annually in
                honour of the deity Anaitis. The Sacæa were in the East what the Saturnalia were at
                Rome, namely, a feast for the slaves. One of the ceremonies was to choose a prisoner
                condemned to death, and to allow him all the pleasures and gratifications he could
                wish, before he was carried to execution.</p>
            <p>SACCHARUM, <hi rend="smallcaps">Sugar,</hi> or the <hi rend="italic">Sugar-cane.</hi>
                This plant is a native of Africa, the East Indies, and Brazil ; whence it was
                introduced into our West India islands soon after they were settled. The sugar-cane
                is the glory and the pride of those islands. It amply rewards the industrious
                planter, enriches the British merchant, gives bread to thousands of ma</p>
            <p>nufacturers and seamen, and brings an immense revenue to the crown. See <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Sugar.</hi></p>
            <p>SACCHAROMETER, an instrument for ascertaining the value of worts, and the strength of
                different kinds of malt liquor. The name signifies a measure of sweetness.</p>
            <p>SACHEVEREL, <hi rend="smallcaps">Dr Henry,</hi> a famous Tory clergyman in the reign
                of Queen Anne, who distinguished himself by indecent and scurrilous sermons and
                writings against the dissenters and revolution principles. He owed his consequence,
                however, to being indiscreetly prosecuted by the House of Lords for his
                assize-sermon at Derby, and his fifth of November sermon at St Paul’s in 1709, in
                which he asserted the doctrine of non-resistance to government in its utmost extent,
                and reflected severely on the act of toleration. The high and low church parties
                were very violent at that time ; and the trial of Sacheverel inflamed the high-
                church party to dangerous riots and excesses. He was, however, suspended for three
                years, and his sermons were burned by the common hangman. The Tories being in
                administration when Sacheverel’s suspension expired, he was freed with every
                circumstance of honour and public rejoicing ; was ordered to preach before the
                Commons on the 29th of May ; had the thanks of the house for his discourse; and
                obtained the valuable rectory of St Andrews, Holbom. He died in 1724.</p>
            <p>SACK, a wine used by our ancestors, which some have taken to be Rhenish and some
                Canary wine. Venner, in his <hi rend="italic">Via Recta ad Vitam Longam,</hi>
                printed in 1628, says that sack is “ completely not in the third degree, and that
                some affect to drink sack with sugar and some without ; and upon no other ground, as
                I think, but as it is best pleasing to their palate.” He goes on to say, “ that
                sack, taken by itself, is very hot and very penetrative ; being taken with sugar,
                the heat is both somewhat allayed, and the penetrative quality thereof also
                retarded.” He adds further, that Rhenish declines after a twelvemonth, but sack and
                the other stronger wines are best after they are two or three years old. It appears
                to be highly probable that sack was not a sweet wine, from its being taken with
                sugar ; and that it did not receive its name from having a saccharine flavour, but
                from its being originally stored in sacks or bo- rachios. It does not appear to have
                been a French wine, but a strong wine, the production of a hot climate. Probably it
                was what is called dry mountain, or some Spanish wine of that kind. This conjecture
                is the more plausible, as Howell, in his French and English Dictionary, printed in
                the year 1650, translates sack by the words “ vin d’Espagne, vin sec.”</p>
            <p>SACKBUT, a musical instrument of the wind kind, being a sort of trumpet, though
                different from the common trumpet both in form and size. It is fit to play a bass,
                and is contrived to be drawn out or shortened, according to the tone required,
                whether grave or acute. The Italians call it <hi rend="italic">trombone,</hi> and
                the Latins <hi rend="italic">tuba ductilis.</hi></p>
            <p>SACKVILLE, THOMAS, Lord Buckhurst and Earl of Dorset, a statesman and poet, the son
                of Richard Sackville of Buckhurst, in the parish of Withian, in Sussex, was born in
                the year 1536. He was sent to Hart Hall, in Oxford, in the latter end of the reign
                of Edward VI. whence he removed to Cambridge, where he took a degree of master of
                arts, and thence to the Inner Temple. He now applied himself to the study of the
                law, and was called to the bar. We are told that he commenced poet whilst at the
                universities, and that these his juvenile productions were much admired, though none
                of them have been preserved. In the fourth and fifth years of Queen Mary we find him
                a member of the House of Commons, about which time, in 1557, he wrote a poetical
                piece, entitled the Induction, or the Mirror of Magistrates. This last was meant to
                comprehend all the unfortunate great from the beginning of our history ; but the
                design being dropped, it was inserted in</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
