<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-19T20:13:30Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>management of the kirk-session, were in general found sufficient for the management of the poor. In some years of peculiar hardship or scarcity, such as the four last years of the seventeenth century, or the year 1740, voluntary assistance was no doubt given ; and in some instances temporary assessments were resorted to, to enable the kirk-sessions to meet the usual emergencies. But on all ordinary occasions the resources of the kirk-sessions were considered as sufficient, and continued to be so at least as late as 1755.”@@<hi rend="superscript">1 </hi>And as legal assessments were reluctantly introduced, notwithstanding the existence of a law in their favour, so they</p><p>have spread tardily. At this moment they embrace only 236 parishes, being little more than a fourth of the total parishes of Scotland. These assessments have not only been introduced, but are the heaviest, in the parishes bordering on England ; and with the exception of our larger towns, they decrease or disappear as we recede from the infectious example of the sister kingdom. Thus every parish in the synod of Merse and Teviotdale is burdened with assessment. In the midland synods, less than the half of the parishes are assessed ; whilst in the northern synods, embracing 157 parishes, only three are exposed to that burden.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Table, shewing the proportion of parishes assessed or not assessed, the number of permanent or occasional poor, the average relief given to each, &amp;c.@@</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">i</hi></p><table><row><cell cols="2"/><cell><p>Not</p><p>Assessed.</p></cell><cell><p>Voluntarily</p><p>Assessed.</p></cell><cell><p>Legally</p><p>Assessed.</p></cell><cell>Total.@@»</cell><cell>Rate per cent. to the population.</cell><cell>Average relief given to each.</cell></row><row><cell/><cell/><cell><p>517</p><p>24,379</p><p>6,209</p><p>211<hi rend="superscript">2</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">3</hi> 30,800</p></cell><cell>126</cell><cell>236</cell><cell><p>879</p><p>57,969</p><p>20,348</p><p>1111</p></cell><cell/><cell/></row><row><cell cols="2"><p>Parishes. . .	........			...</p><p>Poor on permanent roll,	</p></cell><cell/><cell><p>6592</p><p>2494</p></cell><cell><p>26,998</p><p>11,645</p><p>712<hi rend="superscript">2</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">3</hi></p><p>39,358</p></cell><cell/><cell>2.50</cell><cell>£1 18 6</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Occasional poor,	</cell><cell/><cell/><cell/><cell/><cell>.87</cell><cell>0 14 8</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Lunatics,	.	</cell><cell/><cell><p>186<hi rend="superscript">2</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">3</hi></p><p>9273</p></cell><cell/><cell/><cell>.048</cell><cell>10 12 4</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Total poor				</cell><cell/><cell/><cell/><cell>79,429</cell><cell>3.42</cell><cell/></row><row><cell>Total funds, including assessment,</cell><cell/><cell/><cell/><cell/><cell/><cell/><cell/></row><row><cell>church-door collections, other voluntary contributions, and session ∣ funds,	</cell><cell/><cell>£34,991</cell><cell>£19,824</cell><cell>£100,305</cell><cell>£155,121</cell><cell>∙∙</cell><cell>...</cell></row><row><cell>Total annual expense for levying assessment, litigation as to claims, &amp;c.,</cell><cell/><cell>£334</cell><cell>£332</cell><cell>£7344</cell><cell>£8009</cell><cell>...</cell><cell>...</cell></row></table><p>Both these institutions have long existed in Scotland, but were based till recently on an insecure foundation. With the view of putting them on a sound footing, the act of 10 Geo. IV., c. 56, and of 4 and 5 Will. IV., c. 40, were passed. All friendly societies, claiming the benefits of these acts, are obliged to submit a statement of their rules and regulations for the approval of the officer appointed by government for the purpose ; and these must receive his sanction ere the parties become entitled to the privileges conferred by the act in question, namely, the being allowed to invest the funds of the society in government securities at a minimum rate of interest (2<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">2</hi>d. per cent. per day), and in the funds of savings banks. Upwards of five hundred friendly societies have been instituted on the principle of these acts. The act as to savings banks, which has been in operation in all other parts of the empire since 1819, was extended to Scotland in 1835. According to the provisions of this act, the money of savings banks can be invested in government securities at the rate of L.3, 16s. 0<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">2</hi>d. per cent.; but the interest paid to depositors is not to exceed 2<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">2</hi>d. per cent. per day, or L.3, 8s. 5<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">4</hi>d. per cent. per annum. No individual can deposit more than L.30 in any one year, exclusive of interest, nor more than L.200 in all. Savings banks have been established under the law in Edinburgh, Glasgow, Cupar, Kirkaldy, Dunfermline, Dalkeith, and other towns. The deposits in the Edinburgh institution amount to about L.170,000, in rather less than 3<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">2</hi> years; and the other savings banks in Scotland have been equally successful.</p><p>The peers of Scotland, by the treaty of union, elect sixteen of their number to be their representatives in the House of Lords. This election takes place in the palace of Holyrood on the dissolution of parliament. These sixteen peers, who are not elected for life, as is the case with the Irish representative peers, but for the continuance of the parliament for which they are chosen, enjoy all the privileges of the peers of</p><p>England. The other peers of Scotland have all the privileges of the House of Lords, except the legislative and judicial powers, and the privileges thence arising. The number of Scottish peers at the union was one hundred and fifty-four; and there has been since restored five, making one hundred and fifty-nine ; but the present number is eighty-three, namely, seven dukes, four marquises, thirty- nine earls, three countesses, six viscounts, twenty-three barons, and one baroness. Thirty-six of these are also British peers ; and two are likewise peers of Ireland.</p><p>Scotland, before the passing of the reform bill in the year 1832, was represented in the House of Commons by forty-five members, thirty being returned by the counties, and fifteen by the royal burghs, sixty-six in number. The number of the Scottish representatives since the passing of the reform bill, is fifty-three, thirty being, as before, chosen by the counties, whilst the burghs and towns, seventy-six in number, of which ten are not royal burghs, send twenty- three. The counties, thirty-three in number, return only thirty members, because, for parliamentary objects, Kinross and Clackmannan, Elgin and Nairn, and Ross and Cromarty, are respectively united. The aggregate number of the county freeholders or voters, at the passing of the reform act, was 3211. The burgh constituencies were still more limited. With the exception of Edinburgh, which sent a member of itself, the other burghs were parcelled out in groups, and each burgh in the group voted by a delegate chosen by the magistrates and town- council., amounting, upon an average, to twenty in each, or 1320 in all. The aggregate number of the county constituencies, in 1838-39, was 46,480, or nearly fifteen limes the former amount ; and of the burgh constituencies, 36,373, or fully twenty-seven times its former extent. The total constituency of Scotland is 82,853.@@<hi rend="superscript">4</hi></p><p>The population of Scotland was supposed to be 1,050,000</p><p><hi rend="superscript">@@@1</hi> Sir Henry Monereiff's Life of Dr. Erskine, p. 468.</p><p><hi rend="superscript">@@@,</hi> Report of a Committee of the General Assembly on the management of the poor in Scotland, 1839.</p><p><hi rend="superscript">@@@5</hi> This is not the correct total, inasmuch us Edinburgh is in fact divided into thirteen parishes, although it is sometimes reckoned but one parish, and is here accounted only one, as far as poor-rates are concerned.</p><p>@@@* Burton's Manual, <hi rend="italic">ut supra,</hi> p. 29, <hi rend="italic">et seq.</hi></p></body></text></TEI>