<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-19T20:11:24Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>tage of being benefited by the early intelligence of discoveries made by foreigners, but was forced to wait till the intelligence was conveyed to him in the slow and uncertain channel of translation.</p><p>It was often wished that he would quit his retirement at Koping, and move in a larger sphere. It was suggested to him that a place might be procured in England, which might afford him a good income and more leisure ; and indeed latterly an offer was made to him of an annuity of L.300 if he would settle in this country. But death put an end to this project. For half a year before this melancholy event his health had been declining, and he himself was sensible that he would not recover. On the l9th of May 1786 he was confined to his bed ; on the 21st he bequeathed all of which he was possessed to his wife, who was the widow of his predecessor at Koping, and whom he had lately married ; and on the same day he departed this life. Thus, in less than two years, the world lost Bergman and Scheele, of whom Sweden may justly boast, as philosophers who were beloved and lamented by all their contemporaries, and whose memory posterity will never cease to revere.</p><p>SCHEINER, <hi rend="smallcaps">Christopher</hi>, a German mathematician and astronomer, eminent for being the first who discovered spots on the sun, was born at Schwaben, in the territory of Middleheim, in 1575. He first discovered spots on the sun’s disk in 1611, and made observations on these phenomena at Rome, until at length reducing them to order, he published them in one volume folio in 1630. He wrote also some smaller things relating to mathematics and philosophy, and died in 1660.</p><p>SCHELDT, a river which rises on the confines of Picardy, and runs north-east by Cambray, Valenciennes, Tournay, and Oudenarde, and receiving the Lis at Ghent, runs east by Dendermond, and then north to Antwerp. Below this city it divides into two branches, one called the Wester Scheldt, which separates Flanders from Zealand, and discharges itself into the sea near Flushing ; and the other called the Oster-Scheldt, which runs by Bergen- op-Zoom, and afterwards between the islands Beveland and Schowen, and a little below falls into the sea.</p><p>SCHELESTADT, an arrondissement of the department of the Lower Rhine, in France, extending over 257,945 acres, equal to 403 square miles. It is divided into eight cantons, and these into 114 communes, with a population, in 1836, of 134,887 persons. The capital is the city of the same name, situated on a canal connected with the river Ill. It is well built and strongly fortified, and contained in the same year 9700 inhabitants, who make hats, hosiery, clocks, wax-lights, and much potash. Long. 7. 26. E. Lat. 48. 17. N.</p><p>SCHEME, a draught or representation of any geometrical or astronomical figure or problem, by lines sensible to the eye, or of the celestial bodies in their proper places for any moment. It is otherwise called a diagram.</p><p>SCHEMNITZ, a city of the kingdom of Hungary, in the province of the Hither Danube, and the capital of a circle to which it gives the name. It stands on a lofty situation, 2170 feet above the level of the sea, in a district abounding in mines, and at the source of the river Schemnitz. It is wildly built, some of the streets being separated from others by rocks, woods, and gardens, especially in the extensive suburbs, the population of which equals that within the walls. It contains one Lutheran and four Roman Catholic churches, 1720 houses, with 20,450 inhabitants. It has establishments for education, of both religions; and also a mining academy, with five professors and 150 students. It is the great seat of the operations of mining ; and gold, silver, copper, iron, arsenic, and sulphur are procured and prepared for sale, the value of which is said to exceed L.200,000 annually. Long. 18. 48. 45. E. Lat. 48. 47. 45. N.</p><p>3</p><p>SCHERZO, a short musical composition, generally intime, of a light and playful style. In more modem symphonies, quartets, trios, sonatas, &amp;c. the scherzo takes the place of the older minuet, but is of a much more rapid movement. Some excellent examples of the scherzo are to be found in Beethoven’s works ; among others, one in his second Symphony, op. 36, in D major.</p><p>SCHIECHS, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Scheichs</hi>, is a name which is applied by the Arabs to their nobles. “ Among the Bedouins,” says Niebuhr, “ it belongs to every noble, whether of the highest or the lowest order. Their nobles are very numerous, and compose in a manner the whole nation ; the plebeians are invariably actuated and guided by the schiechs, who superintend and direct in every transaction. The schiechs and their subjects are bom to the life of shepherds and soldiers. The greater tribes rear many camels, which they either sell to their neighbours, or employ them in the carriage of goods, or in military expeditions. The petty tribes keep flocks of sheep. Among those tribes which apply to agriculture, the schiechs live always in tents, and leave the culture of their grounds to their subjects, whose dwellings are wretched huts. Schiechs always ride on horses or dromedaries, inspecting the conduct of their subjects, visiting their friends, or hunting. Traversing the desert, where the horizon is wide as on the ocean, they perceive travellers at a distance. As travellers are seldom to be met with on those wild tracts, they easily discover such as pass that way, and are tempted to pillage them when they find their own party the strongest.”	«</p><p>SCHIEDAM, a city of the Netherlands, in the province of South Holland. It stands on the river Schie, near to its junction with the Maas; is well built, and contains five churches, a good exchange and town-house, and 1520 dwellings, with (in 1832) 11,588 inhabitants. The chief trade is distillation. It has 200 distilleries employed in making gin, in which are consumed annually 300,000 quarters of corn. A great number of pigs are fattened, and their flesh converted into bacon. Long. 4. 18. E. Lat. 51. 55. N.</p><p>SCHILLER, <hi rend="smallcaps">John Christopher Frederick von,</hi> was born at Marbach, a small town in the duchy of Wurtemberg, on the 10th day of November 1759. It will aid the reader in synchronizing the periods of this great man’s life with the corresponding events throughout Christendom, if we direct his attention to the fact, that Schiller’s birth nearly coincided in point of time with that of Robert Burns, and that it preceded that of Napoleon by about ten years.</p><p>The position of Schiller is remarkable. In the land of his birth, by those who undervalue him the most, he is ranked as the second name in German literature ; everywhere else he is ranked, as the first. For us, who are aliens to Germany, Schiller is the representative of the German intellect in its highest form ; and to him, at all events, whether first or second, it is certainly due, that the German intellect has become a known power, and a power of growing magnitude, for the great commonwealth of Christendom. Luther and Kepler, potent intellects as they were, did not make themselves known as Germans : the rcvolutionary vigour of the one, the starry lustre of the other, blended with the convulsions of reformation, or with the aurora of ascending science, in too kindly and genial a tone to call off the attention from the work which they performed, from the service which they promoted, to the circumstances of their personal position. Their country, their birth, their abode, even their separate existence, was merged in the mighty cause to which they lent their co-operation. And thus at the beginning of the sixteenth century, thus at the beginning of the seventeenth, did the Titan sons of Germany defeat their own private pretensions by the very grandeur of their merits. Their interest as patriots was lost and confounded in their paramount interest as cosmopolites. What</p></body></text></TEI>