<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-19T20:09:21Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>sleep ; if he has dreamed that he burned the book of the law, that a beam has come
                out of the walls of his house, or that his teeth have fallen out ; then he fasts
                until very late at night, for all such dreams are bad ones. In the afternoon they go
                again to the synagogue, and perform the evening service, adding to the ordinary
                prayers some lessons that respect the sabbath. When the devotional duties are ended,
                they return home, and light a candle resembling a torch, and again sit down to eat.
                They remain eating until near six, and then the master of the family takes a cup,
                and pouring wine into it, rehearses some benedictions ; after which he pours a
                little of the wine upon the ground, and says, “ Blessed be thou, O Lord, King of the
                world, who hast created the fruit of the vine.” Then holding the cup in his left
                hand, with the right he takes a box of sweet spices, and says, “ Blessed be thou, O
                Lord God, who hast created various kinds of sweet spices.” He smells the spices, and
                holds them out to the rest, that they may do the same. He then takes the cup in his
                right hand, and going to the candle views the left very narrowly, and pronounces a
                blessing. With the cup in the left hand, he examines the right in the same manner.
                Again, holding the cup in his right hand, he rehearses another benediction, and at
                the same time pours some of the wine on the ground. After this he drinks a little of
                it, and then hands it about to the rest of the family, who finish what remains. In
                this manner the sabbath is ended by the Jews, and they may return to their ordinary
                employments. Those who meet pay their compliments, by wishing one another a happy
                week.</p>
            <p>The rabbin have reckoned up thirty-nine primary prohibitions, which ought to be
                observed on the sabbatical festival ; but their circumstances and dependents, which
                are also obligatory, are almost innumerable. The thirty-nine articles are, not to
                till the ground, to sow, to reap, to make hay, to bind up sheaves of corn, to
                thrash, to winnow, to grind, to sift meal, to knead the dough, to bake, to shear, to
                whiten, to comb or card wool, to spin, to twine or twist, to warp, to dye, to tie,
                to untie, to sew, to tear or pull in pieces, to build, to pull down, to beat with a
                hammer, to hunt or fish, to kill a beast, to flay it, to dress it, to scrape the
                skin, to tan it, to cut leather, to write, to scratch out, to rule paper for
                writing, to kindle a fire, to extinguish it, to carry a thing from place to place,
                and to expose any thing to sale. These are the primary prohibitions, and each of
                them has its proper consequences, which amount to an incredible number ; and the
                Jews themselves say, that if they could keep but two sabbaths as they ought, they
                would soon be belivered out of all their troubles.</p>
            <p>If a Jew on a journey is overtaken by the sabbath in a wood or on the highway, no
                matter where, nor under what circumstances, he sits down, he will not stir out of
                the spot. If he falls down in the dirt, he lies there ; he will not rise up. A fresh
                wound must not be bound up on the sabbath day. A plaster that had been formerly
                applied to a sore may remain on it ; but if it falls off, it must not be put on
                anew. The lame may use a staff, but the blind must not. These particulars, and a
                great many more of the same nature, are observed by the Jews in the strictest
                manner. But if any one wishes to know more of the practice of that race, he may
                consult Buxtorf’s <hi rend="italic">Judaica Synagoga</hi> (chap. X. xi.), where he
                will find a complete detail of their customs and ceremonies on the sabbath, and
                likewise see the primary prohibitions branched out into their respective
                circumstances.</p>
            <p>As the seventh day was observed by the Jewish church, in memory of the rest of God
                after the works of creation, and their own deliverance from Pharaoh’s tyranny ; so
                the first day of the week has always been observed by the Christian church, in
                memory of the resurrection of Jesus Christ, by which he completed the work of man’s
                redemp</p>
            <p>tion upon earth, and rescued him from the dominion of him who has the power of
                death.</p>
            <p>This day was denominated by the primitive Christians the Lord’s day. It was also
                sometimes called Sunday, which was the name given to it by the heathens, who
                dedicated it to the sun. And, indeed, although it was originally called Sunday by
                the heathens, yet it may very properly retain that name among the Christians,
                because it is dedicated to the honour of the true light, which lighteth every man
                that cometh into the world ; of Him who is styled by the prophet the Sun of
                righteousness, and who on this day arose from the dead. But although it was, in the
                primitive times, indifferently called the Lord’s day or Sunday, yet it was never
                denominated the sabbath ; a name constantly appropriated to Saturday, or the seventh
                day, both by sacred and ecclesiastical writers.</p>
            <p>Of the change from the seventh to the first day of the week, or even of the
                institution of the Lord’s day festival, there is no account in the New Testament.
                However, it may be fairly inferred from it, that the first day of the week was, in
                the apostolic age, a stated time for public worship. On this day the apostles were
                assembled, when the Holy Ghost came down so visibly upon them to qualify them for
                the conversion of the world. On this day we find St Paul preaching at Troas, when
                the disciples came to break bread ; and the directions which the same apostle gives
                to the Corinthians concerning their contributions for the relief of their suffering
                brethren, plainly allude to their religious assemblies on the first day of the
                week.</p>
            <p>Thus it would appear from several passages in the New Testament, that the religious
                observation of the first day of the week is of apostolical appointment ; and may
                indeed be very reasonably supposed to be amongst those directions and instructions
                which our blessed Lord himself gave to his disciples during the forty days between
                his resurrection and ascension, in which he conversed with them, and spoke of the
                things pertaining to the kingdom of God. Still, however, it must be owned that those
                passages, although the plainest that occur, are not sufficient to prove the
                apostolical institution of the Lord’s day, or even the actual observation of it. In
                order, therefore, to place the matter beyond all controversy, recourse must be had
                to ecclesiastical testimony.</p>
            <p>From the consentient evidence and uniform practice of the primitive church, and also
                from the attestation of Pliny, we find that the first day of the week was observed
                in the earliest ages as a holiday or festival, in honour of the resurrection of
                Christ. Now there are but two sources whence the custom could possibly have arisen.
                It must have been instituted either by human or divine authority. But by human
                authority it was not instituted ; for there was no general council in those early
                times, and without the decree of a general council it was impossible that any
                ecclesiastical institution could have been universally established at once. It
                remains, therefore, that it must have been instituted by divine authority ; and that
                it really was so, will further appear from the following considerations. It is
                certain that the apostles travelled over the greatest part of the world, and planted
                churches in the remotest parts of it. It is certain also that they were all led by
                the same spirit ; and their desire was, that unity and uniformity should be observed
                in all the churches which they had founded. It is not therefore surprising that, in
                the primitive times, the same doctrine, the same worship, the same rites and
                customs, should prevail all over the Christian world ; nay, it would have been
                unaccountable had the case been otherwise. For this reason we may conclude that
                every custom, universally observed in the early ages of the Christian church, and
                not instituted by a general council, was of original appointment.</p>
            <p>As the Lord’s day is sanctified, that is, set apart, to Chris-</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
