<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-19T20:09:39Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>wall there is a stockade of a paltry description. Inland it is quite defenceless. The town extends along the Irrawaddy about a mile and a half, but its breadth is inconsiderable. Over the site of the town and its environs arc innumerable temples, many of them ruinous and old, and also modern.</p><p>SAGAN, in scripture history, the suffragan or deputy of the Jewish high priest. According to some writers, he was only employed to officiate for him when he was rendered incapable of attending the service through sickness or legal uncleanness on the day of expiation ; or, according to others, he was destined to assist the high priest in the care of the affairs of the temple and the service of the priests.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sagan,</hi> a city of Prussian Silesia, in the government of Liegnitz, the capital of a circle of its own name, which extends over 484 square miles, and contains 41,600 inhabitants. It stands on the river Bober, and is strongly fortified. It was a principality, but has been mediatized ; and it still retains a fine palace of the prince, besides 540 houses, with 4920 inhabitants. It contains manufactures of linen, lace, paper, glass-ware, and hosiery, and carries on a considerable trade in corn and in corn-spirits.</p><p>SAGANAK, a town of Independent Tartary, situated on the Sihon or Jaxartes. It was taken by Ghengis Khan, and the greater part of the inhabitants put to death.</p><p>SAGANEER, a Rajpoot town of Hindustan, in the province of Ajmeer, and district of Jyenagur, eight miles southeast from the city of Jyenagur. Long. 75. 50. E. Lat. 26. 49. N. This is also the name of a town of the province of Gundwana, belonging to the rajah of Nagpoor. Long. 79. 18. E. Lat. 21. 34. N.</p><p>SAGARA <hi rend="smallcaps">Nacken Bay,</hi> a bay on the east coast of the island of Java. Long. 109. 21. E. Lat. 8. 15. S.</p><p>SAGARAWIDA <hi rend="smallcaps">Bay,</hi> on the south coast of the island of Java. Long. 113. E. Lat. 8. 15. S.</p><p>SAGE, <hi rend="smallcaps">Alain Rene,</hi> an ingenious French romance- writer, was born at Ruys, in Bretagne, in the year 1667. He had a fine flow of imagination, was a complete master of the French and Spanish languages, and wrote several admired romances in imitation of the Spanish authors. These were, 1. The Bachelor of Salamanca, two vols. 12mo; 2. New Adventures of Don Quixote, two vols. 12mo ; 3. The Devil on Two Sticks, two vols. 12mo ; and, 4. Gil Blas, four vols, 12mo. He produced also some comedies, and other humorous pieces. This ingenious author died in the year 1747, in the vicinity of Paris.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sage, </hi><hi rend="italic">John,</hi> so justly admired by all who knew him for his classical learning and reasoning powers, was born in 1652, in the parish of Creich and county of Fife, where his ancestors had lived for seven generations with great respect, though with little property. His father was a captain in Lord Duffus’s regiment, and fought for his king and country when Monk stormed Dundee on the 30th of August 1651.</p><p>The issue of the civil wars, and the loyalty of Captain Sage, left him nothing to bestow upon his son but a liberal education and his own principles of piety and virtue. In those days the Latin language was taught in the parochial schools of Scotland with great ability and at a trifling expense ; and after young Sage had acquired a competent knowledge of that language at one of those useful seminaries, his father, without receiving from an ungrateful court any recompense for what he had lost in the cause of royalty, was still able to send him to the university of St Andrews. Having remained in college the usual number of terms or sessions, and performed the exercises required by the statutes, he was admittcd to the degree of master of arts, the highest honour which it appears he ever received from any university.</p><p>During his rcsidcnce in St Andrews he studied the Greek and Roman authors with great diligence, and was likewise instructed in logic, metaphysics, and such other branches</p><p>of philosophy as then obtained in the schools. When Mr Sage had taken his master’s degree, the narrowness of his fortune compelled him to accept of the first literary employment which was offered to him ; and that happened to be nothing better than the office of schoolmaster in the parish of Bingry in Fifeshire, whence he was soon removed to Tippermuir, in the county of Perth. In these humble stations, though he wanted many of the necessaries and almost all the comforts of life, he prosecuted his studies with great success ; but in doing so, he unhappily imbibed the seeds of several diseases, which afflicted him through life, and, notwithstanding the native vigour of his constitution, impaired his health and shortened his days. From the miserable drudgery of a parish-schoolmaster he was relieved by Mr Drummond of Cultmalundie, who invited him to superintend the education of his sons, whom he accompanied first to the public school at Perth, and afterwards to the university of St Andrews. This was still an employment by no means adequate to his merit, but it was not wholly without advantages. At Perth, he gained the friendship and esteem of Dr Rose, afterwards bishop of Edinburgh, and at St Andrews that of every man capable of properly estimating genius and learning.</p><p>The education of his pupils terminated in 1684, when he was left with no determinate object of pursuit. In this moment of indecision, his friend Dr Rose, who had been promoted from the parsonage of Perth to the professorship of divinity in the university which he was leaving, recommended him so effectually to his uncle, then archbishop of Glasgow, that he was by that prelate admitted into orders, and presented to one of the churches in the city. He was then about thirty-four years of age, and had studied the Scriptures with great assiduity ; he was no stranger to ecclesiastical history, or the apologies and other writings of the ancient fathers, and had examined with great accuracy the modern controversies, especially those between the Romish and Reformed churches. A man so far advanced in life, and so thoroughly accomplished as a scholar, would naturally be looked up to by the greater part of the clergy as soon as he became one of their body. This was in fact the case. Mr Sage was, immediately on his admission into orders, appointed clerk to the synod or presbytery of Glasgow' ; an office of great trust and respectability, to which we know nothing similar in the church of England. During the establishment of episcopacy in Scotland, the authority of the bishops, though they possessed the sole power of ordination, was very limited in the government of the church. They did every thing with the consent of the presbyters over whom they presided. Diocesan synods were held at stated times for purposes of the same kind" with those which employ the meetings of presbyteries at present ; and the only prerogative which the bishop seems to have enjoyed was to be permanent president, with a negative voice over the deliberations of the assembly. The acts of each synod, and sometimes the charge delivered by the bishop at the opening of it, were registered in a book kept by the clerk, who was always one of the most eminent of the diocesan clergy.</p><p>Mr Sage continued in this office, discharging in Glasgow all the duties of a clergyman, in such a manner as endeared him to his flock, and gained him the esteem even of those who were dissenters from the establishment. Many of his brethren were trimmers in ecclesiastical as well as in civil politics. They had been republicans and presbyteri- ans in the days of the covenant; and, with that ferocious zeal which too often characterizes interested converts, had concurred in the severities which, during the reign of Charles II. were exercised against the party whom they had forsaken at the Restoration. When that party again raised its head during the reign of James, and every thing indicated an approaching change of the establishment, those</p></body></text></TEI>