<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-19T20:10:05Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>importance, although the mines have ceased to be productive, and its smelting-house is broken up. It is situated near the left bank of the southern branch of the Ilapicuru, three miles below a lake which communicates with the river. Its inhabitants cultivate wheat, which is not found farther north, and the fruits as well as the pulse and grain of Portugal flourish in this elevated district. They export in particular large quantities of quince marmalade. There are some other towns in the comarca, but few of any material importance. Rio de Contas, a town situated about a hundred and thirty miles south of Jacobina, lies on the high road from Bahia to Goyaz. It owed its origin to its gold mines, which were discovered in 1718. But these have failed, and the inhabitants have betaken themselves to the more advantageous occupation of agriculture. Fifty miles west-south-west of Contas is Villa Nova do Principe, formerly called Caytete, the inhabitants of which are employed in raising cotton and breeding cattle.</p><p>The comarca of the Ilheos begins at Belmonte, and extends northward to the river Jiquirica. The Rio Pardo, which, according to Prince Maximilian, is the limit between the province of Porto Seguro and this comarca, rises in Serro Frio, and falls into the sea by three branches.</p><p>The Bay of Bahia, or All-Saints, has been pronounced one of the finest harbours in the world. The entrance, which is nearly three leagues wide, is from the south, having the continent on the right hand, and the long island of Itaparica on the left. According to Mr Henderson, this island forms two entrances, the eastern or proper entrance being eight miles in width, and the western or false bar being less than two miles across. The bay is twelve leagues in diameter, and thirty-six leagues in circumference, without including the islands or remote parts. The anchorage is secure. Vessels are here sheltered from every wind, and there is accommodation for the united navies of the world. This little Mediterranean is spotted with above a hundred islands, many of which are cultivated and inhabited. The city of St Salvador, better known by the name of Bahia, is, with the exception of Rio, the largest and most flourishing city in Brazil. In ecclesiastical dignity it claims the precedency, being an archiepiscopal see. It has also a higher antiquity, and was long the capital of the empire. Notwithstanding the removal of the seat of government to Rio, the natural advantages of Bahia will enable it, under all changes, to preserve its rank as the second city in Brazil. It is situated on the right side of the bay, where the land, at a small distance from the shore, rises steeply to a high ridgy hill, on the summit of which the city is chiefly erected. From the inequality of the ground, and the plantations interspersed, it occupies a considerable space, its length from north to south being four miles. The buildings are chiefly of the seventeenth century, the churches being of course the most conspicuous edifices. The town has a magnificent appearance from the water, but when entered, its interior is found not to correspond with its imposing aspect at a distance. In the lower town, where the port is situated, the houses are high, and the streets confined and narrow, wretchedly paved, and kept in a very filthy state. The upper town, from its height, and from the slope of the streets, is much cleaner than the port, and although far from being well built, has a number of handsome private houses and public buildings. Here are the cathedral, the archiepiscopal palace, the governor’s palace, the ex-Jesuits’ church (built entirely of marble brought from Europe, but now degraded into barracks for soldiers), the misericordia with its hospital, and various other edifices. The cathedral, and several other churches, are handsome, and richly ornamented. The city is protected by a number of forts and batteries, some of which are garrisoned. Society is not considered so polished here as at Rio. Gaming, the resource of vacant minds, is eagerly followed by both sexes.</p><p>Intellectual pursuits seem to be little cultivated ; and a large library, containing some valuable manuscripts respecting the interior of America, is allowed to remain in a neglected state. Bahia contains thirty-six churches, a number of monasteries, has a university, a number of schools of instruction, a foundling hospital, the library already mentioned, a few printing-presses, and is the centre of a very considerable trade. There are about a hundred and twenty wholesale merchants, and amongst other manufactures carried on are those of cotton, glass, rum, and sugar. There are companies engaged in the whale-fishery, and in ship-building.</p><p>The best idea of the great importance of the trade of Bahia will be formed from the following statements of the exports and imports. A statement of the quantities of Brazilian produce exported from the port of Salvador or Bahia in the year ending the 1st of October 1835 : Sugar, 47,428 cases of thirteen hundredweights, 474 half cases, and 3071 barrels ; cotton, 40,320 bags of about 160 pounds ; 148,752 hides ; coffee, 12,601 sacks and 131 barrels ; tobacco, 54,419 bales, 172 sacks, and 5739 barrels; rum, 6129 pipes; molasses, 315 pipes ; besides many other smaller articles. The number of vessels which cleared from the port was 244.</p><p>A statement of the value of merchandise imported into the port of Bahia or Salvador in the year ending the 1st of July 1835 : Cotton manufactures to the value of L.664,104, of which Great Britain furnished L.573,097 ; woollen goods to the value of L.67,517, of which Great Britain supplied L.64,740 worth; linen manufactures to the value of L.77,863, Great Britain supplying L.57,497 worth ; silk L.42,086, of which Great Britain supplied L.5657 worth, and France L.25,053 ; and numerous other articles, of which a large proportion is furnished by Great Britain ; the total value of the imports being L.1,412,521.</p><p>The population of this city is estimated at 150,000. The environs of Bahia arc very beautiful; and being constantly refreshed by land and sea breezes, the climate is deemed very healthy. The Reconcave, as the country which extends round the whole sweep of this beautiful bay is denominated, is one of the richest and most populous parts of Brazil. It varies in breadth from twelve to forty miles. Upon the rivers which intersect it, and fall into the bay, are situated many flourishing towns, which carry on a considerable trade with the capital. One of the largest is Cachoeira, situated on the river Paraguassu, which divides it into two parts. Near this town was found a mass of native copper, weighing a ton and a half. Fifteen miles below Cachoeira, on the same river, is Maragogype, also a considerable town. The other chief towns are St Amaro, on the right bank of the Serigy or Serzipe, twelve miles from its mouth, and forty north-west of Bahia ; and Jaguaripe, on the right bank of the river of the same name, seven miles from its mouth, the inhabitants of which are chiefly manufacturers of earthenware. On the island of Itaparica, which is twenty-three miles in length from north to south, and ten in breadth, is a considerable town, with 16,000 inhabitants, who engage in the whale-fishery. The population of the whole province of St Salvador is estimated at 600,000.	<hi rend="smallcaps">( r. r. r.)</hi></p><p>SALVATION means the safety or preservation of any thing which is or has been in danger, and is generally used in a religious sense, when it means preservation from eternal death, or reception to the happiness of heaven, which is now offered to all men by the Christian religion upon certain conditions. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Theology.</hi></p><p>SALVIANUS, an ancient father of the Christian church, who flourished in the fifth century, and was well skilled in the sciences. He acquired such reputation for his piety and learning, that he was named the Master of the Bishops. He wrote a Treatise on Providence ; another on Avarice ; and some epistles, of which Baluze has given an excellent edition. That of Conrad Rittershusius, in two volumes 8vo, is also esteemed.</p></body></text></TEI>