<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-19T20:09:54Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>he accompanied Cæsar to Africa; and after the battle of Thepsa, he was appointed to the province of Numidia, where he enriched himself by the most nefarious means. He returned to Rome with immense wealth ; and after the murder of Cæsar abstained from taking any part in public affairs. He again devoted himself to a life of pleasure, and constructed a magnificent palace on the Quirina), in the midst of gardens which were afterwards known as the Horti Sallustiani. This palace was subsequently occupied by Vespasian, Nerva, and many other emperors, and was destroyed by fire when Rome was plundered by Alaric. According to Eusebius, Sallust was married to Terentia, wife of Cicero, and died <hi rend="smallcaps">b. c.</hi> 35, in the fifty-first year of his age, being not less distinguished for his talents than for his profligacy. Of his historical works the following remain : 1. Bellum Catilinarium, a history of the conspiracy of Catiline, B. c. 63, with a very beautiful introduction, in which he laments, with much apparent feeling, the corruption of the age, and the profligacy of his contemporaries ; 2. Bellum Jugurthinum, a history of the wars carried on against Jugurtha, king of Numidia, which he was probably induced to write from his residence in that country ; 3. Historiarum Libri Quinque, a work on the history of Rome, from the consulship of M. Æmilius Lepidus and Q. Lutatius Catulus, <hi rend="smallcaps">b. c.</hi> 78, to that of M. Æmilius Lepidus and L. Volcatius Tullus, <hi rend="smallcaps">b. c.</hi> 66, with an introduction on the manners and government of Rome, and a short summary of the wars of Marius and Sulla. Of this work only a few fragments have been preserved. Some other works, however, have come down to us, which are ascribed to Sallust, though without sufficient reason : 1. Duæ Orationes de Republica Ordinanda, addressed to Julius Cæsar when he was proceeding against Petreius and Afranius, in Spain ; and, 2. Declamatio in Ciceronem, which is alluded to by Quintilian. The character of Sallust as a historian stood high among the ancients, who regarded him as the rival of Thucydides, and in many points he was certainly the imitator of that writer. Like Thucydides, he endeavours to give the causes of the various events which he is narrating ; and if he more frequently ascribes them to unworthy motives, we may readily discover the reason of this in the corruption of the age in which he lived. But they both show themselves profound thinkers, and intimately acquainted with the springs of human action. The first edition of the works of Sallust was published in Rome in 1470, and in Venice the same year; but since that time a variety of editions have appeared. The best is that of C. H. Frotscher, giving the notes and emendations of Cortius, three vols. Lips. 1380, 8vo. C. Sallustii Histor. iii. fragmenta e cod. Vatic, edita ab. Angelo Maio, editio auctior et emendatior, curante J. Th. Kreissig, Misen. 1830.</p><p>SALLUZZO, a city of the kingdom of Sardinia, in the province of Turin, and the capital of the division of that name. It stands on an elevation not far from the river Po. It is surrounded with walls, is the see of a bishop, and has a cathedral, several churches and monasteries, and 10,150 inhabitants, who carry on much trade in wine and in corn, and make silk goods and ironmongery. Long. 16. 55. E. Lat. 25. 3. N.</p><p>SALLY-PORTS, in <hi rend="italic">Fortification,</hi> are those underground passages which lead from the inner to the outward works ; such as from the higher flank to the lower, or to the tenailles, or the communication from the middle of the curtain to the ravelin.</p><p>SALMASIUS, <hi rend="smallcaps">ClauDIus,</hi> a French writer of uncommon abilities and erudition, descended from an ancient and noble family, and born at or near Samur in the year 1596. His mother, who was a Protestant, infused her notions of religion into him, and he at length converted his father. He settled at Leyden ; and in 1650 he paid a visit to Christina queen of Sweden, who is reported to have shown him ex</p><p>traordinary marks of regard. Upon the violent death of Charles I. of England, he was prevailed on by the royal family, then in exile, to write a defence of that king ; which was answered by our Milton in 1651, in a work entitled <hi rend="italic">Defensio pro Populo Anglicano contra Claudii Salmasii Defensionem Pegiam.</hi> This book was read over all Europe, and conveyed such a proof of the writer’s abilities, that he was respected even by those who hated his principles. Salmasius died in 1653 ; and some did not scruple to say that Milton killed him by the acuteness of his reply. His works are numerous, and of various kinds; but the greatest monuments of his learning are, his <hi rend="italic">Notœ in Historice Augustae Scriptores,</hi> and his <hi rend="italic">Exercitationes Pliniana: in Salinum.</hi></p><p>SALMO, the <hi rend="smallcaps">Salmon.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Ichthyology.</hi></p><p>SALMON FISHERY. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Fishery.</hi></p><p>SALO, a market-town of Italy, in the Austrian kingdom of Venetian Lombardy, and in the delegation of Brescia. It is most delightfully situated on a bay in the lake of Garda, and behind it rises the Alpine mountain Pennino. It is the seat of a judicial tribunal, has three churches, an orphan-house, a hospital, and many well-built houses, and about 6500 inhabitants. The finest silk in Italy is produced in the vicinity ; and within the town there are manufactories of hats, leather, glass, and linen threads.</p><p>SALO <hi rend="smallcaps">Bay,</hi> on the north coast of the island of Java. Long. 112. 36. E. Lat. 6. 58. S.</p><p>SALOMBO, a cluster of small islands in the Eastern Seas. Long. 113. 13. E. Lat. 5. 30. S.</p><p>SALON, a city of France, in the department of the Mouths of the Rhone, and the arrondissement of Aix. It stands partly on the side of a hill and partly on the plain below, through which the canal of Craponne connects it with the river Crau. In 1836 it contained 5987 inhabitants, who cultivate great numbers of olive trees, in extracting the oil from which consists the chief occupation. Salon was the birthplace of the celebrated astrologer Nostradamus. Long. 5. 5. E. Lat. 43. 40. N.</p><p>SALONA, a seaport town of Dalmatia, situated on a bay of the Gulf of Venice. It was formerly a very considerable place, and its ruins show that it was twelve miles in circumference. In a valuable manuscript relation of Dalmatia, written by the senator Giambattista Giustiniani, about the middle of the sixteenth century, there is a sketch of what existed at the time. “ The nobility, grandeur, and magnificence of the city of Salona, may be imagined from the vaults and arches of the wonderful theatre, which are seen at this day ; from the vast stones of the finest marble, which lie scattered on and buried in the fields ; from the beautiful column of three pieces of marble, which is still standing in the place where they say the arsenal was, towards the sea-shore ; and from the many arches of surprising beauty, supported by very high marble columns. The height of the arches is a stone-throw, and above them there was an aqueduct, which reached from Salona to Spalatro. There are to be seen many ruins and vestiges of large palaces, and many ancient epitaphs may be read on fine marble stones ; but the earth, which is increased, has buried the most ancient stones and the most valuable things.” Long. 17. 29. E. Lat. 24. 10. N.</p><p>SALONICA, a large city of Turkey in Europe, the capital of a province of the same name, and anciently Thessalonica. It is situated on a bay formed by the two capes of the Great and Little Burnu. It is of a triangular shape, the base of which is on the sea-shore. The walls of brick, on a stone foundation, are of an unusual thickness, and defended by bastions at the appropriate points. The appearance of the city from without is magnificent, from the number of minarets, cupolas, and lofty buildings ; but the interior is found with narrow and crooked streets, disgusting public squares, and low, ill-built houses, resembling barracks ; but</p></body></text></TEI>