<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-19T20:10:53Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>of Forli. It contains 5100 inhabitants, mostly very poor, who are chiefly occupied in
                winding silk.</p>
            <p>SAVILE, <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir George,</hi> afterwards Marquis of Halifax, and one
                of the greatest statesmen of his time, was born about the year 1630 ; and some time
                after his return from his travels was created a peer, in consideration of his own
                and his father’s merits. He was a strenuous opposer of the bill of exclusion, but
                proposed such limitations of the Duke of York’s authority as should disable him from
                doing any harm either to church or state ; as the taking out of his hands all power
                in ecclesiastical matters, the disposal of the public money, and the power of making
                peace and war, and lodging these in the two houses of parliament. After that bill
                was rejected in the House of Lords, he pressed them, though without success, to
                proceed to the limitation of the duke’s power; and began with moving, that during
                the king’s life he might be obliged to live five hundred miles out of England. In
                August 1682 he was created a marquis, and soon after made privy-seal. Upon King
                James’s accession, he was made president of the council ; but on his refusal to
                consent to the repeal of the test act, he was dismissed from all public employments.
                In that assembly of the Lords which met after King James’s withdrawing himself the
                first time from Whitehall, the marquis was chosen their president; and upon the
                king’s return from Feversham, he was sent, together with the Earl of Shrewsbury and
                Lord Delamere, from the Prince of Orange, to order his majesty to quit the palace at
                Whitehall. In the convention of parliament he was chosen speaker of the House of
                Lords, and strenuously supported the motion for the vacancy of the throne, and the
                conjunctive sovereignty of the prince and princess, upon whose accession he was
                again made privy-seal. Yet, in 1689, he quitted the court, and became a zealous
                opponent of the measures of government till his dcath, which happened in April 1695.
                Mr Grainger observes, that “ he was a person of unsettled principles, and of a
                lively imagination, which sometimes got the better of his judgment. He would never
                lose his jest, though it spoiled his argument, or brought his sincerity or even his
                religion in question. He was deservedly celebrated for his parliamentary talents ;
                and in the famous contest relating to the bill of exclusion was thought to be a
                match for his uncle Shaftesbury. The pieces he has left us show him to have been an
                ingenious, if not a masterly writer ; and his Advice to a Daughter contains more
                good sense in fewer words than is, perhaps, to be found in any of his contemporary
                authors.” His lordship also wrote, the Anatomy of an Equivalent ; a Letter to a
                Dissenter ; a Rough Draught of a New Model at Sea ; and Maxims of State ; all which
                were printed together in one volume 8vo. Since these there were also published under
                his name, the Character of King Charles II. 8vo ; the Character of Bishop Burnet,
                and Historical Observations upon the Reigns of Edward I. Edward II. Edward III. and
                Richard II. with Remarks upon their faithful Counsellors and false Favourites.</p>
            <p>SAVILLE, <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir Henry,</hi> a learned Englishman, was the second
                son of Henry Saville, and was born at Bradley, near Halifax, in Yorkshire, on the
                30th of November 1549. He entered of Merton College, Oxford, in 1561, where he took
                the degrees in arts, and was chosen fellow. When he proceeded master of arts in
                1570, he read for that degree in the Almagest of Ptolemy, which procured him the
                reputation of a man eminently skilled in the mathematics and the Greek language ; in
                the former of which he voluntarily read a public lecture in the university for some
                time.</p>
            <p>In 1578 he travelled into France and other countries, where, diligently improving
                himself in all useful learning, in languages, and in the knowledge of the world, he
                became a most accomplished gentleman. At his return he was made tutor in the Greek
                tongue to Queen Elizabeth, who had a great esteem for him.</p>
            <p>In 1585 he was made warden of Merton College, which he governed thirty-six years with
                great honour, and improved it by all the means in his power. In 1596 he was chosen
                provost of Eton College, which he filled with many learned men. James I. upon his
                accession to the crown of England, expressed a great regard for him, and would have
                preferred him either in church or state ; but Saville declined it, and only accepted
                the ceremony of knighthood from the king, at Windsor, in 1604. His only son Henry
                dying about that time, he thenceforth devoted his fortune to the promoting of
                learning. Among other things, in 1619, he founded, in the university of Oxford, two
                lectures or professorships, one in geometry, and the other in astronomy, which he
                endowed with a salary of L.160 a year each, besides a legacy of L.600 to purchase
                more lands for the same use. He also furnished a library with mathematical books,
                near the mathematical school, for the use of his professors, and gave L.100 to the
                mathematical chest of his own appointing ; adding afterwards a legacy of L.40 a year
                to the same chest, to the university, and to his professors jointly. He likewise
                gave L.120 towards the new building of the schools, besides several rare manuscripts
                and printed books to the Bodleian Library, and a g∞d quantity of Greek types to the
                printing press at Oxford.</p>
            <p>After a life thus spent in the encouragement and promotion of science and literature
                in general, he died at Eton College on the 19th of February 1622, in the
                seventy-third year of his age, and was buried in the chapel there. On this occasion,
                the university of Oxford paid him the greatest honours, by having a public speech
                and verses made in his praise ; which were soon afterwards published in quarto,
                under the title of <hi rend="italic">Ultima Linea Savilii.</hi></p>
            <p>The highest encomiums were bestowed on Saville by all the learned of his time; by
                Casaubon, Mercerus, Meibomius, Joseph Scaliger, and especially the learned Bishop
                Montague, who, in his <hi rend="italic">Diatribæ</hi> upon Selden’s History of
                Tythes, styles him, “ that magazine of learning, whose memory shall be honourable
                amongst not only the learned, but the righteous, for ever.” His works are, 1. Four
                Books of the Histories of Cornelius Tacitus, and the Life of Agricola, with Notes
                upon them, in folio, dedicated to Queen Elizabeth, 1581. 2. A View of certain
                Military Matters, or Commentaries concerning Roman Warfare, 1598. 3. Rerum
                Anglicarum Scriptores post Bedam, 1596, a collection of the best writers of our
                English history. 4. The Works of St Chrysostom, in Greek, in eight vols, folio,
                1613. This is a very- fine edition, and composed with great cost and labour. In the
                preface he says, “ that having himself visited, about twelve years before, all the
                public and private libraries in Britain, and copied out thence whatever he thought
                useful to his design, he then sent some learned men into France, Germany, Italy, and
                the East, to transcribe such parts as he had not already, and to collate the others
                with the best manuscripts.” The whole charge of this edition, including the several
                sums paid to learned men, at home and abroad, employed in finding out, transcribing,
                and collating the best manuscripts, is said to have amounted to no less than L.8000.
                5. In 1618 he published a Latin work, written by Thomas Bradwardin, archbishop of
                Canterbury, against Pelagius, entitled De Causa Dei contra Pelagium, et de virtute
                Causarum, to which he prefixed the life of Bradwardin. 6. In 1621 he published a
                collection of his own Mathematical Lectures on Euclid’s Elemcnts, in 4to. 7. Oratio
                coram Elizabetha Regina Oxoniæ habita, anno 1592, printed at Oxford in 1658, in 4to.
                8. He translated into Latin King James’s Apology for the Oath of Allegiance. He also
                left several manuscripts, written by order of King James, all which are in the
                Bodleian Library. He wrote notes likewise upon the margin of many books in his
                library, particularly Eusebius’s Ecclesiastical History ; which were afterwards used
                by Valesius in his edition of that work in 1659.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
