<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-19T20:14:09Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>SCRUTINY <hi rend="italic">(Scrutinium),</hi> in the primitive church, was an
                examination or probation practised in the last week of Lent, upon the catechumens,
                who were to receive baptism on Easter-day. The scrutiny was performed with a great
                many ceremonies. Exorcisms and prayers were made over the heads of the catechumens ;
                and upon Palm Sunday the Lord’s Prayer and Creed were given them, which they were
                afterwards made to rehearse. This custom was more in use in the Church of Rome than
                anywhere else, though it appears, by some missals, to have been likewise used, at a
                much later period, in the Gallican church. It is supposed to have ceased about the
                year 860.</p>
            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Scrutiny</hi> is also used, in the <hi rend="italic">canon
                    Law,</hi> for a ticket or a little paper billet, in which, at elections, the
                electors write their votes privately, so that it may not be known for whom they
                vote. Among us the term <hi rend="italic">scrutiny</hi> is chiefly used for a strict
                perusal and examination of the several votes hastily taken at an election, in order
                to find out any irregularities committed therein by unqualified voters.</p>
            <p>SCRUTORE, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Scrutoir</hi> (from the French <hi rend="italic"
                    >escritoire),</hi> a kind of cabinet, with a door or lid opening downwards.</p>
            <p>SCRY, in falconry, denotes a large flock of fowl.</p>
            <p>SCUDDING, the movement by which a ship is carried precipitately before a tempest. As
                a ship flies with amazing rapidity through the water whenever this expedient is put
                in practice, it is never attempted in a contrary wind,</p>
            <p>unless when her condition renders her incapable of sustaining the mutual effort of
                the wind and waves any longer on her side, without being exposed to the most
                imminent danger of being overset.</p>
            <p>A ship either scuds with a sail extended on her foremast, or, if the storm is
                excessive, without any sail at all ; which, in the sea-phrase, is called <hi
                    rend="italic">scudding under bare poles.</hi> In sloops and schooners, and other
                small vessels, the sail employed for this purpose is called the <hi rend="italic"
                    >square sail.</hi> In large ships, it is either the foresail at large, reefed,
                or with its goose-wings extended, according to the degree of the tempest ; or it is
                the fore-top sail., close reefed, and lowered on the cap ; which last is
                particularly used when the sea runs so high as to becalm the foresail occasionally,
                a circumstance which exposes the ship to the danger of broaching to. The principal
                hazards incident to scudding are generally a pooping sea ; the difficulty of
                steering, which exposes the vessel perpetually to the risk of broaching to ; and the
                want of sufficient sea-room. A sea striking the ship violently on the stern may dash
                it inwards, by which she must inevitably founder. In broaching to, that is,
                inclining suddenly to windward, she is threatened with being immediately overturned,
                and, for want of sea-room, she is endangered by shipwreck on a lee-shore.</p>
            <p>SCULPONEÆ, among the Romans, a kind of shoes worn by slaves of both sexes. These
                shoes consisted only of blocks of wood made hollow, like the French sabots.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
