<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-19T20:09:18Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>tion of divine service, cannot be denied. Such is the constitution of man, that he
                must have particular times set apart for particular services. He is doomed to toil
                and labour, to earn his bread with the sweat of his brow ; and is capable of
                performing religious duties only in such a manner as is consistent with his
                situation in the world. If stated times for religious solemnities had not been
                enjoined, the consequence would have been, that such solemnities would have been
                altogether neglected ; for experience shows, that if mankind were left at liberty
                when and how often they should perform religious offices, these offices would not be
                performed at all. It is the observation of holy times that preserves the practice of
                holy services ; and without the frequent and regular returns of hallowed days, man
                would quickly forget the duty which he owes to God, and in a short time no vestige
                of religion would be found in the world.</p>
            <p>Among the ordinances which God vouchsafed his ancient people, we find that the pious
                observation of holidays was particularly insisted upon ; and the Sabbath was
                enjoined to be kept holy, in the most solemn manner, and under the severest
                penalties. Can it then be supposed that He would suffer mankind, from the creation
                of the world to the era of Moses, to remain without an institution so expedient in
                itself, and as well fitted to answer the end proposed by it under the one
                dispensation, as ever it could be under the other ? No. We have every imaginable
                reason to conclude, that when religious services were enjoined, religious times were
                appointed also ; for the one necessarily implies the other.</p>
            <p>It is not an objection to the early institution of the Sabbath that there is no
                mention of it in the patriarchal age. It would have swelled the Bible to a most
                enormous size had the sacred historian given a particular account of all the
                transactions of those times ; and, besides, it would have answered no end. When
                Moses wrote the book of Genesis, it was unnecessary to relate minutely transactions
                and institutions already well known by tradition. Accordingly we see that his
                narrative is everywhere very concise, and calculated only to preserve the memory of
                the most important facts. However, if we take a view of the church- service of the
                patriarchal age, we shall find that what is called the legal dispensation, at least
                the liturgie part of it, was no new system, but a collection of institutions
                observed from the beginning, and republished in form by Moses. The Scriptures inform
                us that Cain and Abel offered sacrifices ; and the account which is given of the
                acceptance of the one, and the rejection of the other, evidently shows that stated
                laws respecting the service had then taken place. “ In process of time,” at the end
                of the days, “ Abel brought an offering.” Here was priest, altar, matter of
                sacrifice, appointed time, motive to sacrifice, and atonement made, and accepted.
                The distinction of animals into clean and unclean before the Flood, and Noah’s
                sacrifice immediately after his deliverance, without any new direction, is an
                unanswerable proof of the same truth. It is testified of Abraham, by God himself,
                that he kept his charge, his commandments, his statutes, and his laws. These
                expressions comprehend the various branches into which the law given at Sinai was
                divided. They contain the moral precepts, affirmative and negative, the matter of
                religious service, a body of laws to direct obedience, and to which man was to
                conform his conduct in every part of duty. Agreeably to this, we find that
                sacrifices were offered, altars and places of worship consecrated, and the Sabbath
                also mentioned as a well-known solemnity, before the promulgation of the law. It is
                expressly taken notice of at the fall of manna ; and the incidental manner in which
                it is then mentioned is a convincing proof that the Israelites were no strangers to
                the insti</p>
            <p>tution. For had it been a new one, it must have been enjoined in a positive and
                particular manner, and the nature of it must have been laid open and explained,
                otherwise the term would have conveyed no meaning.</p>
            <p>The division of time into weeks, or periods of seven days, which obtained so early
                and almost universally, is a strong indication that one day in seven was always
                distinguished in a particular manner. <hi rend="italic">Week,@@'</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">seven days,</hi> are in scripture language synonymous terms. God
                commanded Noah, seven days before he entered the ark, to introduce into it all sorts
                of living creatures. When the waters of the Flood began to abate, Noah sent forth a
                dove, which, finding no rest for the sole of her foot, returned to him. After seven
                days he sent forth the dove a second time, and again she returned to the ark. At the
                expiration of other seven days he let go the dove a third time ; and a week is
                spoken of (Gen. xxix.) as a well-known period of time.</p>
            <p>This septenary division of time has, from the earliest ages, been uniformly observed
                over all the eastern world. The Israelites, Assyrians, Egyptians, Indians, Arabians,
                and Persians, have always made use of a week, consisting of seven days. Many vain
                attempts have been made to account for this uniformity ; but a practice so general
                and prevalent could never have taken place had not the septenary distribution of
                time been instituted from the beginning, and handed down by tradition.</p>
            <p>From the same source also must the ancient heathens have derived their notions of the
                sacredness of the seventh day. That they had such notions of it is evident from
                several passages of the Greek poets quoted by Aristobulus, a learned Jew’, by
                Clement of Alexandria, and Eusebius.</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic"> iζi.μr∣, itς.. hμxζ,</hi></p>
            <p>The seventh, the <hi rend="italic">sacred</hi> day.</p>
            <p>'EC‰<hi rend="subscript">l</hi>usra 5' l&lt;ι,ra <hi rend="italic">κxrtιλυrt., lιςt.
                    t∣μx^,</hi></p>
            <p>Afterwords came the seventh, the <hi rend="italic">sacred</hi> day.</p>
            <p>Again :</p>
            <p>E*3fl<hi rend="subscript">i</hi>uo, <hi rend="italic">hμxζ</hi> lav, x«u <hi
                    rend="italic">&lt;ru rιrιλιr.</hi> xa,r&lt;- On the <hi rend="italic"
                    >seventh</hi> day all things were <hi rend="italic">completed,</hi></p>
            <p>'Eζi.μaτn<hi rend="italic"> S,oj </hi>esτlλneμtrx rx.ra &lt;rteυnτaι,</p>
            <p>AU things were made <hi rend="italic">perfect</hi> on the <hi rend="italic"
                    >seventh</hi> day.</p>
            <p>That they likewise held the number <hi rend="italic">seven</hi> in very high
                estimation, has been showm by a learned, though sometimes fanciful author,@@<hi
                    rend="superscript">2</hi> with such evidence as to enforce conviction. The
                Pythagoreans call it the venerable number, &lt;rsCαcχκ)u <hi rend="italic"
                    >άξιο;,</hi> worthy of veneration, and held it to be perfect and most proper to
                religion. They denominated it fortune, and also styled it voice, sound, muse,
                because, no doubt, seven distinct notes comprehend the whole scale of music, beyond
                which neither voice nor instrument can go, but must return from the seventh, and
                begin again anew. They likewise designed it reλt&lt;rpojoς, leading to the end.
                Seven, in the Hebrew language, is expressed by a word that primarily signifies
                fulness, completion, sufficiency, and is applied to a week, or seven days, because
                that was the full time employed in the work of creation ; to the Sabbath, because on
                it all things were completed ; and to an oath, because it is sufficient to put an
                end to all strife. This opening of the Hebrew root will enable us to come at the
                meaning of those expressions of the heathens, and also let us see whence they
                derived their ideas and modes of speaking, and that the knowledge of the
                transactions at the creation, though much perverted, was never entirely lost by
                them.</p>
            <p>It has been supposed by some, that the heathens borrowed the notion of the sacredness
                of the seventh day from the Jews. But this opinion will not readily be admitted,
                when it is considered that the Jews were held in the greatest con-</p>
            <p><hi rend="superscript">@@@1</hi> שכע, <hi rend="italic">seven.</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="superscript">@@@,</hi> Holloway’s Originals, vol. ii. p. 60.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
