<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-19T20:13:00Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ent in different districts; but the average is about 31 inches. The quantity which falls on the east coast of Scotland ranges from 22 to 26 inches ; whilst, on the west coast and in the Hebrides, it is nearly double, varying, according to situation, from 35 to 46 inches. The number of fair days throughout the year is, on the west coast, only 160; whilst on the east it is 230. The mean annual fall of rain at Edinburgh for the years 1824 and 1825, was 23<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">2</hi> inches ; at Glasgow, for an average of thirty years, it was 30 inches ; whilst, still farther west, at Mount Stewart, in the Isle ofBute, it was, on an average of seven years, 46∙6 inches, the mean average of the whole country being, as just stated, 31 inches. The prevailing winds throughout Scotland are from the westerly points ; but on the east coast it blows from the easterly points about a third of the year. Easterly winds generally prevail in March and April., and often in May and part of June, and not only check vegetation, but are attended with slightly unfavourable effects on the health of the inhabitants, particularly such of them as are nervous, dyspeptic, consumptive, or rheumatic. But the climate of Scotland is eminently salubrious. There are, properly speaking, no fens or marshes. The low grounds are, in general, highly cultivated. From whatever point the wind may blow, except the east, a wide expanse of sea is passed ever ; and the air, though moist, is purified from injurious emanations, which are readily absorbed by the ocean. Hence it has been affirmed, that the mean duration of life is greater in Scotland than in almost any other country.@@<hi rend="superscript">1 </hi>“ We are pretty confident, from extensive observation in different countries, that the proportion of the population that reaches seventy or eighty years of age, and the vigour then remaining, are greater in Scotland than almost any where else.”</p><p>The mountains of Scotland consist either of detached groups, more or less closely wedged together, or of ridges or chains. These latter may be characterized as running in a north-east and south-west direction. The most celebrated chain, the Grampians, mentioned by Tacitus,@@<hi rend="superscript">3</hi> extend from the south-eastern boundaries of Argyleshire, with a more or less defined line, to the heart of Aberdeenshire. This chain may be regarded as a natural rampart, forming the south-eastern boundary of the Highlands. With the exception of Ben Nevis, the highest mountains in Scotland arc comprehended in the Grampian range. Another chain, to the south of the Grampians, and nearly parallel to them, stretches from Montrose to the Clyde, in Dunbartonshire ; but being intersected by the Tay and the Forth, it is divided into three distinct portions, which bear different names. From Montrose to the Tay, this chain is called the Siedlaw hills ; from the Tay to the Forth, it is known by the name of the Ochills; and the remainder passes under the names of the Dundaff, Fintry, and Campsie hills. The low- country, or strath, which separates this range of hills from the Grampians, is called Strathmore, or the great valley. There is also a chain of mountains in the south of Scotland, stretching from the Cheviot hills, on the borders of Northumberland, to Loch Ryan, in Wigtonshire. There are other smaller ranges, such as the Monagh Lea mountains, which run parallel to and along the western side of the Spey; the Lomond hills in Fifeshire ; the Pentland hills in Mid-Lothian, and others. The altitude and situation of the principal hills and mountains in Scotland having already been given under the head of Physical Geography, it is unnecessary to repeat the information here.</p><p>In the neighbourhood of the village of Leadhills, in Lanarkshire, 1564 feet above the level of the sea, is the highest cultivated land in Scotland. In Aberdeenshire, the plough sometimes reaches the height of about 1300 feet; but, with few exceptions, an elevation of 600 feet seems</p><p>to be the limit of the tillage lands of Scotland. None of the Scottish mountains ascends to the line of perpetual congelation ; yet snow may be found all the year round in some of the dark recesses, on which the sun never shines.</p><p>From the rugged and mountainous character of the surface of Scotland, the vales or level tracts cannot be expected to be extensive or numerous. They are, indeed, when compared with England, very much the reverse. Of these vales, called sometimes <hi rend="italic">straths</hi> or <hi rend="italic">carses,</hi> the following are the most important The vale or <hi rend="italic">carse</hi> of Stirling and Falkirk is a tract of low alluvial land, which extends on both sides of the Forth, with little interruption, and to a greater or less width, from Borrowstonness to about twenty miles north of Stirling, including the vales of the Teith and the Allan, two tributaries of the Forth. These lands are peculiarly fertile, and produce the richest crops of wheat and other grain. The vale of the Earn, a tributary of the Tay, known by the name of Strathearn, is of a similar character, but of comparatively limited extent. The carse of Gowrie, which lies on the north of the Tay, from Dundee to Perth, is incomparably the most fertile and productive district in Scotland, and is thought not to be surpassed in these respects by any other district of equal extent in the united kingdom. Strathmore stretches from Lawrencekirk in Angusshire to the neighbourhood of Perth, lying between the bases of the Siedlaw hills and the Grampians. This valley is not entirely flat, but is characterised by occasional gentle eminences. The <hi rend="italic">Merse,</hi> or level lands of Berwick shire, stretch from the confluence of the Leader and the Tweed to the town of Berwick, occupying most of the low and generally level part of the country, or nearly the half of its surface. The carse of Baldoon, lying south of the river Bladenoch, and on the east shore of the bay of Wigton, is of limited extent, but of nearly equal fertility to the carse of Gowrie. There are other less important straths or carses, such as those along the Teviot in Roxburghshire ; Tynedale, or the vale of Tyne, in East Lothian ; and the Howe, or vale of Eden, in Fifeshire. These lands are either loamy or alluvial.</p><p>By this term we mean tracts of land composed of morasses, intermixed with rocks, lakes, and peat-moss. The moor of Rannoch, lying between Schehallion, Ben Cru- achan, and Ben Nevis, is one of the most lonely, wild, and dreary districts in Scotland. It may be said to be entirely devoid of value, and would not of itself bring any rent. It is not inhabited, and very seldom visited. There is a tract about ten miles inland on the west coast of Sutherlandshire, not very dissimilar, but, though more rugged, it is not quite so dreary as that of the moor of Rannoch. The <hi rend="italic">flow</hi> of Glenluce lies between Newtonstewart and Luce Bay, stretching along the public road for about ten miles, composed chiefly of peat and morasses, and forming one of the bleakest and most dreary rides in Scotland.</p><p>From the rugged and mountainous nature of the country, the rivers of Scotland are characterised by a more rapid course, are more diversified by rocks and cataracts, and are more limpid than those of England. Their course is also necessarily shorter, and few of them are navigable, at least to any great extent. Being generally mountain streams, they are peculiarly liable to sudden overflowings, their rise and fall being equally sudden. From a very tedious and elaborate set of experiments, it is computed that they carry out to the sea, on an average, about <hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">2000</hi> the weight of their waters in mud ; that is, a film of about <hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">50</hi> of an inch annually, or one inch in fifty years over the whole surface from which they draw their waters.</p><p>The principal rivers of Scotland, with the single exception of the Clyde, are exclusively confined to the east. Three inconsiderable rivers flow in a south-easterly direction, the</p><p><hi rend="superscript">@@@,</hi> Malthus, i. cap. x.	</p><p><hi rend="superscript">@@@1</hi> Agricolæ Vita, c. 29.</p></body></text></TEI>