<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-19T20:09:48Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>derable distilleries of brandy and spirits of wine. Near to it are some Roman antiquities, especially the remains of an amphitheatre, an aqueduct, and a triumphal arch. Long. 0. 43. 58. W. Lat. 45. 44. 43. N.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Saintes, </hi><hi rend="italic">Des,</hi> a group of small islands in the West Indies, adjacent to Guadaloupe, of which government they form a part.</p><p>SAIPOOR, a town of Hindustan, in the province of Gundwana, possessed by independent zemindars. It is situated on the north-west side of the Rhair river, fifteen miles from the southern frontier of the Rhotas district, in Bahar. Long. 82. 50. E. Lat. 24. 2. N.</p><p>SAJENE, a Russian measure of length, equal to about seven English feet.</p><p>SAKERTOL, a town and fortress of Hindustan, in the province of Delhi, and district of Saharunpore. It was taken by the Mahrattas in 1772. It is situated on the western bank of the Ganges. Long. 77. 0. E. Lat. 29. 25. N.</p><p>SAKKAR, a district of Hindustan, in the province of Bejapoor, belonging to the nizam, and situated about the seventeenth degree of north latitude. It is well watered, being situated between the rivers Beemah and Krishna, and is extremely fertile. To the north of the Beemah it is somewhat hilly. The principal towns are Nusseritabad and Sakkar ; and the latter is the capital. It is situated on the north side of the Beemah river, sixty-five miles east from the city of Bejapoor. Long. 76. 38. E. Lat. 17. 4. N.</p><p>SAL SI <hi rend="smallcaps">Puedes,</hi> is the name of some islands in the Gulf of California. They lie in the interior of the gulf, and form a chain, leaving only some very narrow channels, of difficult entrance for vessels. They are of various sizes, the largest bearing the names of Las Animas, San Lorenzo, San Estevan, and San Augustin.</p><p>SALA, a city of Italy, in the province of Principato Citra, of the kingdom of Naples, situated on <hi rend="italic">a</hi> small river of the same name. It is an inland place, situated on an elevated spot, and has a castle, five parish churches, and 6100 inhabitants. Another place of the same name in Italy is in the duchy of Parma, being situated on the river Baganza. It was the favourite residence of the last duchess, and now belongs to her successor, who keeps on the land belonging to it a large flock of merino sheep, with the view of extending that race throughout the country. There is another place in Sicily of the name, in the intendancy of Trapani, which is described as containing 9800 inhabitants, but ill built and disgustingly filthy.</p><p>SALAD, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Sallad,</hi> a dish of eatable herbs, seasoned with salt, oil, and vinegar. Ménage derives the word from the Latin <hi rend="italic">salata,</hi> from <hi rend="italic">sal,</hi> salt ; but others from <hi rend="italic">salcedo. </hi>Ducange derives it from <hi rend="italic">salgama,</hi> which is used in Ausonius and Columella in the same sense. Some add mustard, hard eggs, and sugar. The principal salad herbs, and those which ordinarily make the basis of our English salads, are lettuce, celery, endive, cresses, radish, and rape.</p><p>SALADIN, a famous sultan of Egypt, equally renowned as a warrior and a legislator. He supported himself by his valour, and the influence of his amiable character, against the united efforts of the chief Christian potentates of Europe, who carried on wars against him, under the appellation of <hi rend="italic">Holg Wars.</hi></p><p>SALAIBSKOIE, a fortress of Asiatic Russia, situated at the confluence of the small river Salaiba with the Bia, and surrounded with immense forests.</p><p>SALAMANCA, one of the departments into which the kingdom or province of Leon, in Spain, is divided. It is situated between lat. 40° and 41° 38' north. The river Duero forms its limit to the north and north-west, except where it comes in contact with Portugal. Estremadura is on its southern side, and the province of Segovia to the eastward. It extends over 471 square leagues, and its population amounts to 272,982 souls. It generally consists of an open country</p><p>with extensive plains, and for the most part destitute of trees. The soil is more fruitful than its appearance would suggest. It yields excellent corn, and in moist summers the harvests are abundant ; but it is subject to that want which the greater part of Spain feels from the scarcity of water ; for although there are several rivers in the department, the influence of their moisture extends but a small distance from their banks. The principal of these rivers is the Duero, into which the Alba, the Tormes, and the Agueda run, whilst the Alagon, taking a southern course, runs into the Tagus. From the nature of the soil through which these rivers pass, they have worn very deep channels, and therefore cannot be used for the purposes of irrigation, without a portion of labour and expenditure which the inhabitants are neither willing nor able to bestow upon them. Though generally the department is destitute of wood, yet in some parts there are extensive forests of evergreen oak trees, without any brushwood under them ; and the oaks themselves are without those spreading branches and lofty tops with which our forests exhibit these trees. They are, however, of considerable benefit to the inhabitants by their copious produce of acorns, on which large droves of pigs are fed. The peasants who attend to these animals precede the drove, and proceeding from tree to tree, beat them with a kind of flail, causing the acorns to fall, which the swine most greedily devour. They thus proceed daily from tree to tree till the food they supply is exhausted. The hams of the pigs fattened in this way are most highly esteemed. In this department large flocks of the merino kind of sheep are fed ; and many of the stationary kind are bred here, whose wool is of a very inferior degree of fineness. In the early part of the late war the plains of Salamanca were very favourable to the operations of the French armies, who being superior in cavalry, could act on them with the most powerful effect. The cattle of this province are reckoned to be 9363 horses, 6163 mules, 22,002 asses, 107,800 oxen, 103,401 goats, and 107,200 pigs. Of fruits it yields 9500 fanegas of chestnuts, 502,000 of nuts, and 12,000 of raisins.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Salamanca,</hi> a city of Spain, head of the department of the same name, in the province or kingdom of Leon. It is situated on the river Tormes, over which there is a bridge standing, the piers of which were built by the Romans, and there remain twelve of the arches constructed by them, and thirteen of more recent date, probably erected since the expulsion of the Moors. At a short distance Salamanca has a most imposing effect. Its lofty towers and cupolas, the magnificent Gothic cathcdral, the numerous convents and colleges, and the lengthened bridge which leads to them, present a landscape of the first order.</p><p>The immediate vicinity of the city is fruitful, being on a plain surrounded by mountains of no great elevation, though the Sierra de Guadarrama is visible in the distance, towering above them. It is well supplied from its fields with wine, corn, fruits, and edible vegetables. It grows some flax and oil, but procures a part of the latter from Estremadura and Andalusia.</p><p>The principal fame of Salamanca has arisen from its university, which is one of the largest establishments for education in Spain, if not in Europe. The professors are not generally distinguished for their learning or activity, and principally exercise their faculties in keeping the minds of the pupils down to that level of inquiry and pursuit which is best calculated to secure their attachment to the existing civil and religious institutions of their country. Every inquiry which may have a tendency to lead them from this beaten track is most carefully checked ; and even books of science, if composed by foreigners, are viewed with a suspicion that there may be in them some latent heretical tenets. Under such restraints, it is not wonderful that the orthodoxy of the university of Salamanca is unimpeached. The spirit of loyalty was, in fact, so great, that at the com-</p></body></text></TEI>