<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-19T20:10:04Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>house, and delivered into the custody of his majesty’s officers. And in this manner the whole process is performed in twenty-four hours, the salt being usually drawn every morning.</p><p>In the storehouse the salt is put hot into drabs, which are partitions like stalls for horses, lined on three sides and at the bottom with boards, and having a sliding-board on the foreside to put in or draw out as occasion requires. The bottoms are made shelving, being highest behind, and gradually inclining forwards, by which means the saline liquor, which remains mixed with the salt, easily drains from it ; and the salt, in three or four days, becomes sufficiently dry, and is then taken out of the drabs, and laid up in large heaps, where it is ready for sale.</p><p>The saline liquor which drains from the salt is not a pure brine of common salt, but has a sharp and bitter taste, and is therefore called bittern. This liquor, at some works, is saved for particular uses, and at others is thrown away. A considerable quantity of this bittern is left at the bottom of the pan after the process is finished ; and as it contains much salt, it is suffered to remain in the pan when it is filled up with sea-water. But at each process this liquor becomes sharper and more bitter, and also increases in quantity. Thus, after the third or fourth process is finished, they are obliged to take it out of the pan, otherwise it mixes in such quantities with the salt as to give it a bitter taste, disposes it to grow soft and run in the open air, and renders it unfit for domestic uses.</p><p>After each process there also adheres to the bottom and sides of the pan a white stony crust, of the same calcareous substance with that before collected from the boiling liquor. This the operators call stone-scratch, distinguishing the other found in the lead pans by the name of powder- scratch. Once in eight or ten days they separate the stone- scratch from their pans with iron picks, and in several places find it a quarter of an inch in thickness. If this stony crust be suffered to adhere to the pan much longer, it grows so thick that the pan is burned by the fire, and quickly wears away.</p><p>The consumption of salt in this country is immense. Neckar estimated the consumption, in those provinces of France which had purchased an exemption from the <hi rend="italic">gabelle,</hi> at 19<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">2</hi> lbs. English for each individual. But we believe that tne people in this country may be estimated a little higher, or at <hi rend="italic">22</hi> lbs. ; and, on this supposition, taking the population at 16,500,000, the entire consumption will amount to 363,000,000 lbs. or 161,000 tons. Exclusively of this immense home consumption, we annually export about 10,000,000 bushels, which, at 56 lbs. a bushel, are equivalent to 250,000 tons. The cheapness of this important necessary of life is therefore not less remarkable than its diffusion.</p><p>In this country duties upon salt were imposed in the reign of William III. In the year 1798, they amounted to five shillings a bushel, but were subsequently increased to fifteen shillings, or about forty times the cost of the salt. So exorbitant a duty was productive of the worst effects, and by its magnitude, as well as by the regulations allowing salt duty-free to the fisheries, occasioned a great deal of smuggling. For this reason, the opinion of the public and the House of Commons having been strongly expressed against the tax, it was finally repealed in the year 1823. (M'Culloch’s Commercial Dictionary, art. <hi rend="italic">Salt.)</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Salt </hi><hi rend="italic">Springs. Of</hi> these there are great numbers in different parts of the world, which undoubtedly have their origin from some of the large collections of fossil salt mentioned under the article <hi rend="italic">common </hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Salt.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Salt, </hi><hi rend="italic">Valley of,</hi> in Syria. It is a lake in winter ; but in summer the moisture is evaporated by the heat of the sun, when the salt is left in beds of about half an inch thick, and is afterwards purified for use. It is about eighteen miles to the east of Aleppo.</p><p>SALTASH, a market-town of the county of Cornwall, in the hundred of East, and a part of the parish of St Stephen. It is 220 miles from London, on the banks of the river Tamar, three miles above Plymouth, with which place it is connected by the Crimble Ferry. It is a corporate town, with a charter granting jurisdiction on the river Tamar. It returned two members to parliament before 1832. It has a market, which is held on Saturday. The population amounted in 1801 to 1150, in 1811 to 1478, in 1821 to 1548, and in 1831 to 1637.</p><p>SALTCOATS, a seaport town in Ayrshire, on the Frith of Clyde, tlιirty miles distant from Glasgow. At the end of the seventeenth century it consisted only of four houses ; but it is now a place of considerable trade, and exports large quantities of coals, which are procured from the extensive coal-fields in the neighbourhood. There are some hundreds of looms in the town employed in weaving for the Glasgow and Paisley manufacturers ; and ship-building has been carried on successfully for some years. In 1821 the population of the town and parish was 3413, and in 1831 it was 3544.</p><p>SALTPETRE, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Νιγrε </hi><hi rend="italic">(nitrate of potash),</hi> a compound of nitric acid and potash. It is generally obtained in the form of six-sided prismatic crystals, terminated by six-sided pyramids, joined by their bases. Its specific gravity is 1∙933. See CHEMISTRY.</p><p>it is used in the various arts, and is the principal ingredient in the manufacture of gunpowder. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Gunpowder.</hi></p><p>SALTSKAMMER, a circle in the Austrian province of the Upper Ens, extending over 330 square miles, and containing three market-towns and seventy-two villages, with 15,600 inhabitants. It is a most picturesque district, five sixths of the surface being covered with Alpine mountains, and watered by the romantic river Traun, issuing from the beautiful lake of that name, which was a favourite retreat of the late Sir Humphry Davy to enjoy fishing. The capital is the town of Ischl, where a large quantity of salt is refined.</p><p>SALVADOR, Sτ, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Βahια,</hi> a large and important province of Brazil, extending from the Belmonte, in latitude 15° 25' south, to the Rio Real, which divides it from Seregipe d’el Rey, in latitude 11° 38' south. The river St Francisco separates it from Pernambuco on the west and north-west, while on the south-west it touches on Minas Geraes. It is divided into three comarcas, Bahia, Ilheos, and Jacobina ; the former two comprising the coast, and the latter the western part of the province. The eastern is divided from the western portion by a chain of mountains of considcrable elevation, from the eastern side of which proceed the numerous streams flowing into the prolific district of Reconcave, or forming the rivers of Ilheos. A considerable portion of Jacobina is occupied with cattle-plains, which are not susceptible of cultivation. It was formerly rich in gold, and, according to Cazal, it still produces that metal, and also silver, copper, iron, saltpetre, and crystals. This comarca comprehends the country on which the Rio St Francisco enters when it leaves the province in which it originates. The inhabitants are scattered everywhere over its surface, and occupy themselves chiefly in breeding cattle. “ The regular winter or wet season,” says Southey, “ extends only some thirty leagues from the coast ; and what rain falls in the interior comes only in thunder-showers, which are of course irregular, in no part frequent, and occur seldomer in the northern part of the province than in the south. After rain, the ground is presently covered with rich verdure, and the cattle fatten ; but when drought succeeds to this season of abundance, they are reduced to browse upon such shrubs as resist the burning sun. The streams fail, and if the tanks which the thunder-showers had filled are also dried, a dreadful mortality ensues. Because of the frequency of this evil, the province cannot depend upon its own pastures, but looks to Goyaz and Piauhy for a regular supply.” Jacobina, the capital of the comarca, is still a town of some</p></body></text></TEI>