<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-19T20:11:43Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Catholicos Migratione, 1660, in 8vo ; 4. Notationes Criticæ in Phædrum, in Priapeia, Patavii, 1664, in 8vo ; 5. Suspectarum Sectionum Libri v. 1664, in 8vo ; 6. Classicum Belli Sacri, 1619, in 4to ; 7. Collyrium Regium, 1611, in 8vo ; 8. Grammatica Philosophica, 1644, in 8vo ; 9. Relatio ad Reges et Principes de Stratagematibus Societatis Jesu, 1641, in 12mo. This last-mentioned work was published under the name of <hi rend="italic">Alphonse de Vargas.</hi></p><p>SCIOPTIC, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Scioptric Ball,</hi> a sphere or globe of wood, with a circular perforation, where a lens is placcd. It is so fitted that, like the eye of an animal, it may be turned round every way, and is used in making experiments in a darkened room.</p><p>SCIPIO, <hi rend="smallcaps">Publius Cornelius,</hi> a renowned Roman general, surnamed <hi rend="italic">Africanus</hi> for his conquests in that country. His other signal military exploits were, his taking the city of New Carthage in a single day ; his complete victory over Hannibal, the Carthaginian general ; and the defeat of Syphax king of Numidia, and of Antiochus in Asia. He was as eminent for his generous behaviour to his prisoners as for his valour. He died 180 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c</hi>. aged about fifty-one.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Scipio</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Lucius Cornelius,</hi> his brother, surnamed <hi rend="italic">Asiaticus</hi> for his complete victory over Antiochus at the battle of Magnesia, in which Antiochus lost fifty thousand infantry and four thousand cavalry. A triumph, and the surname of <hi rend="italic">Asiaticus,</hi> were the rewards of his valour. Yet his ungrateful countrymen accused him, as well as his brother, of peculation, for which he was fined ; but the public sale of his effects proved the falsehood of the charge, for they did not produce the amount of the fine. He flourished about 190 B. c.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Scipio</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Publius Æmilianus,</hi> was the son of Paulus Æmilius, but being adopted by Scipio Africanus, he was called <hi rend="italic">Scipio Africanus junior.</hi> He showed himself worthy of adoption, following the footsteps of Scipio Africanus, whom he equalled in military fame and public virtues. His chief victories were the conquest of Carthage and Numantia ; yet these signal services to his country could not protect him from an untimely fate. He was strangled in his bed by order of the Decemviri, who dreaded his popularity, 129 <hi rend="smallcaps">b. c. </hi>aged fifty-six.</p><p>SCIRO, an island of the Archipelago, to the west of My- tilene, to the north-east of Negropont, and to the southeast of Sciati. It is fifteen miles in length and eight in breadth. The vines form the beauty of the island, and the wine is excellent ; nor do the natives want wood. There is but one village, and that is built on a rock, which runs up like a sugar-loaf, and is ten miles from the harbour of St George. The inhabitants are Greeks.</p><p>SCIROCHO, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Sirocco,</hi> a name generally given in Italy to every unfavourable wind. In the south-west it is applied to the hot suffocating blasts from Africa ; and in the north-east it means the cold bleak winds from the Alps.</p><p>SCLAVONIA, a province of the Austrian empire, still occasionally dignified with the name of kingdom. It is bounded on the west by Croatia, on the north and east by Hungary, from which it is separated by the river Drave, and partly by the Danube, and on the south by Turkey, the river Save separating it from the territories of the sultan. The shape of this province is long and narrow, and it contains a superficies of about 5000 square miles. A chain of lofty mountains, which rises in Croatia, intersects it in its whole length from east to west. This elevated ridge is covered with forests, containing the finest oak and other valuable trees; but a proper water conveyance is wanting to render this natural product of the soil a valuable article of export. The rest of the country consists of fine plains, with a fertile soil, and a climate which, although mild, is cooler than might be expected under the parallels of forty-five and forty-six. This is to be attributed to the presence of the forest-covered mountain chain just mention</p><p>ed. During dry years the open parts of the mountainous tracts are barren ; in favourable years they produce excellent crops of wheat, barley, flax, hemp, and madder. The climate of the plains is sufficiently genial for the cultivation of maize, silk, and the fruits of the south of Europe. Limestone, sulphur, coal, salt, and some ferruginous substances, are amongst the most abundant mineral treasures of Sclavonia ; but these have not yet been thoroughly investigated. Much of the mountain chain yet remains unexplored. The manufactures are too insignificant to require specific notice ; those of glass and potash appear to be the most important. The exports consist of corn, tobacco, nuts, plums, hides, wax, honey, and madder ; the imports are chiefly iron, salt, and oil. Domestic weaving and knitting is universally practised, so that few of the finer fabrics of Great Britain or France are required, especially amongst a people the bulk of whom live in mud-huts. The transit trade is of more importance, in consequence of the three great rivers, the Danube, the Drave, and the Save, which directly or indirectly communicate with a large tract of country.</p><p>Under the Romans, Sclavonia formed a part of Pannonia, and derived its present name from a tribe of Sclavi or Slavi, who settled here in the sixth or seventh century. Subsequently, the Venetians, having acquired an ascendency over Dalmatia, extended their acquisitions to this country. In the tenth century it came under the dominion of Hungary, to which it remained subject, until, in the year 1526, it was overrun and subdued by the Turks. It was finally subjected to the house of Austria by the peace of Carlowitz, which was ratified in 1699. The country remained divided into military districts until 1745, but since that time a beginning has been made towards giving some of them a civil constitution. These form three counties. The military district, or generalate, consists of Brod, Peterwardin, and Gradisca. It is under a military government, at the head of which is the commanding general in Sclavonia, who resides at Peterwardin. The counties are subject to the kingdom of Hungary, each having its governor and vice-governor. Although Sclavonia has undergone a material improvement since its annexation to Austria, yet the population is not characterized either by industry, or by that degree of intelligence necessary to turn the natural advantages of the country to good account. The Sclavonians proper, or aborigines, do not now form the majority of the inhabitants ; they are largely intermixed with Magyars, Wallachians, Gypsies, Germans, Greeks, Jews, and Armenians. There are but few Protestants in the country. The most numerous religious denominations are the Roman Catholic, the Greek Catholic, and the Greek non-united Church. The population in 1831 amounted to 370,000, which is about eighty-five inhabitants to every square mile.</p><p>SCONE, a village of Scotland, now chiefly remarkable for being the place where the kings were anciently crowned. Kenneth II. upon his conquest of the Picts in the ninth century, having made Scone his principal residence, delivered his laws, called the Macalpine laws, from a tumulus, named the <hi rend="italic">Mote Hill of Scone.</hi> The old palace was begun by the Earl of Gowrie, but was completed by Sir David Murray of Gospatrick, the favourite of King James VI. to whom that monarch had granted it ; and the new possessor, in gratitude to his benefactor, put up the king’s arms in several parts of the house. During the middle ages of the Scottish monarchy Scone was the occasional residence of the kings ; and it was here that they were crowned, sitting on the famous stone called the stone of Dunstaffnage or stone of Scone, which, if the ancient chronicles may be believed, was the pillow on which Jacob slept when journeying through the plains of Luz. Edward <hi rend="italic">I.</hi> carried it off, to the great mortification of the Scotch, who looked upon it as a kind of palladium. The abbey and palace were demolished by a mob from Dundee at the Reformation. Charles II., before the battle of Worcester, was crowned in the chapel at Scone.</p></body></text></TEI>