<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-19T20:11:21Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>of cultivation is wine, which, though not of the best quality, finds a ready sale in the other cantons, and hence the hills are mostly covered with vineyards. Corn is raised about equal in amount to the consumption, and the meadows feed many cows, which produce much good butter. The river Rhine receives all the streams of the canton. The capital is the city of the same name, about one mile above the natural cascade of the Rhine. It is an antique-looking town, with a narrow street and large houses ; it is also walled, and has a citadel. There are three churches, a council-house, and several hospitals ; and it contains 7000 inhabitants, who carry on cotton-weaving, calico-printing, and make caps, hats, and hosiery. Long. 8. 32. E. Lat. 47. 42. N.</p><p>SCHAMACHI, the capital of the province of Shirvan, in Persia, once large, populous, and commercial, but now ruined, and its remains entirely covered with thick brushwood. The modern city is called New Schamachi, and is situated in a plain on the river Aksisi, about thirty miles from the Kur, and nearly the same distance from the Caspian. It is built in a square form, each side of which is eight hundred paces long ; and the walls are in tolerable repair, built of unburned brick, and surrounded with a very broad and deep ditch. It is supposed to have contained 6000 inhabitants previous to its capture during the late war by Aga Mahommed. It was desolated by this tyrant, and has not recovered from its fallen state. Long. 48. 45. E. Lat. 40. 27. N.</p><p>SCHANCK, <hi rend="smallcaps">Cape,</hi> a rocky point, with three rocky islets lying off it, on the south coast of New Holland. It is the west point of the principal entrance into Western Port. Long. 144. 53. E. Lat. 38. 30. S.</p><p>SCHANTARSKIJA, three islands off the eastern coast of Asiatic Russia, in the Sea of Okhotzk. Long. 138. to 139. E. Lat. 55. 15. to 55. 30. N.</p><p>SCHAREDSJE, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Ζακα,</hi> an island in the Persian Gulf, near the coast of Arabia, about thirty miles in circumference. Long. 54. 15. E. Lat. 25. N.</p><p>SCHASBURG, a city in the Austrian duchy of Sieven- burgen, the capital of a circle of its own name. It is situated on a hill near the river Kokel, consisting of two towns, one of which is surrounded with walls, and the other a kind of suburb. It contains four Lutheran churches, with a Catholic and a Greek one, 1230 houses, and 7100 inhabitants, chiefly of the Saxon race. There is a Lutheran college, and considerable manufacturing industry employed in making cotton and linen goods. Long. 23. 43. E. Lat. 46. 10. 9. N.</p><p>SCHAUENBURG, a province of the principality of Hesse-Casel, in Germany, adjoining to Hanover, Lippe-Detmold, and Lippe-Schauenburg. It is 193 square miles in extent, a poor sandy district, except on such parts as are near the river Weser, which are of moderate fertility. It comprehends five towns and 130 villages and hamlets, with 28,600 inhabitants, whose chief occupation, besides that of agriculture, is the spinning of flax. It produces some good coal, and abundance of wood. It is divided into three bailiwicks, and the capital is the city of Rentelen, on the Weser, containing 2850 inhabitants.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Schauenburg-Lippe,</hi> a small independent principality in the north of Germany, between Hanover on the north and north-east, Hesse-Casel on the east and south-east, and the Prussian Westphalian province on the south-west and the west. It extends over 210 square miles, and comprehends two small cities, three market-towns, and 108 villages, with a population of 23,128 persons, who all adhere to the Lutheran church, except 3600 Calvinists and about 100 Roman Catholics. The revenues of the prince amount to about L.2l,500, wholly drawn from his domains, no taxes of any kind being demanded ; and as the reigning prince was in his minority during the time of the greatest suffering in this part of Germany, his guardian managed so prudently as to leave him without any debt. The principality is bound</p><p>to provide a force of 240 men to the German confederation. The face of the country is undulating, but there are no hills of great height, and all are capable of cultivation. It rises gradually from the right bank of the Weser, into which run all the streams of the principality. It has one large lake, the Steinhuder, nearly fifty miles in compass, on which is a strong fortress used as an arsenal, and it is most abundantly stocked with fish. It has some valuable mineral springs ; one near Stadthagen is resorted to for curative purposes. There are some valuable coal-mines worked, which belong to the prince, and are said to form one quarter of his revenue. There are many flocks of sheep, some yielding fine wool from the native races having been crossed by merinos. The soil produces more corn than is consumed ; and it, with wool, flax, wood, and coal, are the chief objects of trade. The capital is Buckeberg, a city of 4220 inhabitants, on a gradual ascent from the Weser, and six miles from Minden.</p><p>SCHAZK, a city of Russia, the capital of a circle of the same name, within the province of Tambov. It is 737 miles from St Petersburg, on the river Schazk. It is old and ill built, and contains eight churches, only three of stone, 1011 houses, with 6800 inhabitants, chiefly making hempen goods, and cultivating that plant. Long. 4L 49. E. Lat. 54. 26. N.</p><p>SCHECHE SURE, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Surde,</hi> a small island in the Persian Gulf, with a village on the southern coast, where water and provisions may be obtained. Long. 54. 30. E. Lat. 26. 8. N.</p><p>SCHEDUAN, an immense naked rock in the Red Sea, eight miles long and five broad, at nearly an equal distance from the coasts of Asia and Africa. Lat. 27. 35. N.</p><p>SCHEDULE, a scroll of paper or parchment, annexed to a will, lease, or other deed, containing an inventory of goods, or some other matter omitted in the body of the deed. The word is a diminutive of the Latin <hi rend="italic">scheda,</hi> or Greek <hi rend="italic">σχεδη</hi>, a leaf or piece of paper.</p><p>SCHEELE, <hi rend="smallcaps">Charles William</hi>, was bom on the 19th of December 1742, at Stralsund, where his father had kept a shop. When he was very young, he received the usual instructions of a private school ; and was afterwards advanced to an academy. At a very early age he showed a strong desire to follow the profession of an apothecary, and his father suffered him to gratify his inclinations. With Mr Bauch, an apothecary at Gottenburg, he served his apprenticeship, which was completed in six years. He remained, however, some time longer at that place, and it was there that he so excellently laid the foundations of his knowledge. Among the various books which he read that treated of chemical subjects, Kunckell’s Laboratory seems to have been his favourite. He used to repeat many of the experiments contained in that work privately in the night, when the rest of the family had retired to rest. A friend of Scheele’s had remarked the progress which he had made in chemistry, and had asked him by what inducements he had at first been led to study a science in which he had gained such knowledge. Scheele replied, “ The first cause, my friend, arose from yourself. Nearly at the beginning of my apprenticeship you advised me to read Neuman’s Chemistry, from the perusal of which I became eager to make experiments myself ; and I remember very well how I mixed together, in a conserve-glass, oil of cloves and fuming acid of nitre, which immediately took fire. I see also still before my eyes an unlucky experiment which I made with pyrophorus. Circumstances of this kind did but the more inflame my desire to repeat experiments.” After Scheele’s departure from Gottenburg in the year 1765, he obtained a place with Kalstrom, an apothecary at Malmo Two years afterwards he went from thence to Stockholm, and managed the shop of Mr Scharenberg. In 1773, he changed this appointment for another at Upsal, under Mr</p></body></text></TEI>