<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-19T20:09:58Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>number of consumers than could formerly afford it. Manufactures of a coarser kind of earthenware, and of tobacco- pipes, are carried on at Broseley and other places. The raw materials of which these articles are formed are almost all found near the spots where they are converted to these useful and profitable purposes. The preparation of iron for the forge is in fact the principal manufacture of Shropshire; at Hales Owen, nearly five hundred males of twenty years of age and upwards are so employed ; and at Madeley half as many. At Dowley and other places in its vicinity, many men are employed in the blast-furnaces ; and at and near Shrewsbury seventy-four men are employed in iron-castings and at forges, in preparing the weighty apparatus of powerful machinery. Nails are largely made at Wellington. The finer kinds of earthenware employ two hundred men at Broseley and Madeley; carpeting employs ninety men at Bridgenorth ; glass is made at Wrockwordine ; flannels are made at Oswestry, Church Stretton, and Worthen. There is a small manufacture of hair-seating carried on at Drayton. The trade in Welsh flannels centres in a great degree in Shrewsbury. The merchants of that town repair to the markets of Welshpool and Oswestry, and make their purchases of the small country weavers, who bring their goods in an unfinished state ; and the pieces are rendered fit for the markets to which they are destined by the Shrewsbury traders.</p><p>Shrewsbury, the county town of Shropshire, from its vicinity to Wales, in which the towns are few, and from its distance from any other large town, has ever been considered as a kind of provincial capital. It is situatcd on a circular peninsula of considerable elevation, formed by the curvatures of the Severn. It presents at every approach a pleasing variety of views ; and the noble sweep of the river, which seems to embrace it, heightens at every turn the charm of the scenery. The exterior ranges of houses command the rich and beautiful landscapes of the surrounding country. The stately spires of two venerable churches, and the massive towers of the castle, give that imposing grandeur to the whole which is commonly felt in contemplating the works of antiquity. The walks between the river and the town are finely shaded by an avenue of lofty trees, and furnish an agreeable promenade to the inhabitants. The interior of the town by no means corresponds with its external beauty. The streets are intricately dispersed, many of them steep and narrow, and all badly paved. They exhibit a strange contrast of ancient and modern buildings, and are as uncouth in their names as in their appearance. This town, as well as many other parts of the county, exhibits many interesting remains of antiquity. Among these is the castle, placed on the narrow neck of land by which the only entrance to the town can be gained without passing a bridge. The remains consist of the keep, a square building of a hundred feet, connected with two towers ; the walls of the inner court ; and the great arch of the interior gate. The keep is the most perfect of the whole mass of building. The walls of this building are ten feet in thickness, and its beams of very large dimensions. It is stated to have been built by Roger de Montgomery the Norman, as a feudal hold ; but being forfeited to the crown in the reign of Henry I., was used as a royal fortress in subsequent periods, to check the incursions of the less civilized Welsh. The remains of the abbey, erected by the same founder as the castle, rewards the lover of antiquities for the inspection of them. The most perfect remains of this edifice is an octagonal structure six feet in diameter, usually called the Stone Pulpit, standing upon a portion of the ruined wall. It is crowned by an obtuse dome of stone-work at about eight feet from the base, supported on six narrow-pointed arches rising on pillars. The ancient church of St Chad, which fell down in 1788, presents an interesting group of ruins. That of St Mary, founded by Edgar, as well as St Alkmunds, founded by Queen Elfleda,</p><p>daughter of Offa king of Mercia, have received such alterations in more recent periods that they exhibit the architectural taste of several successive ages. The charitable institutions of Shrewsbury, consisting of hospitals, infirmary, schools, and other establishments, rather exceed the proportion to be found in other places of equal population, anil do much credit to the liberality of the natives.</p><p>Our limits do not admit of lengthened descriptions of the numerous remains of ancient architecture which are still existing in this county. The most remarkable are Haugmond Abbey, about four miles from Shrewsbury ; the walls of Wroxeter, of British and Roman construction; the Abbey of Buildwas, founded in 1135 by Roger bishop of Chester, for monks of the Cistercian order ; the Monastery of Wenlock, founded in 680, destroyed by the Danes, and afterwards re-established ; the Roman camp, called the Walls, at Quatford ; the castle of Ludlow, celebrated for its splendour in the reigns of Henry VIII. and of Elizabeth, during the latter period the residence of the Sidneys, and in the reign of Charles I. immortalized as the place where Milton composed some of his works; Wannington Castle, near Oswestry, a house of strength before the Norman conquest; Lilleshall Abbey, near Newport, with one of the most highly adorned Norman arches in the kingdom ; and Boscobel House, with the oak in the grounds near it which served as a shelter to Charles II. when, after the battle of Worcester, he was closely pursued by the victorious party.</p><p>By the parliamentary reform bill, this county has been formed into two separate divisions, distinguished as the northern and southern, each of which is empowered to elect two members to the House of Commons. The polling places for the northern division are Shrewsbury, Oswestry, Whitchurch, and Wellington ; and for the southern division, Church Stretton, Bridgenorth, Ludlow, Bishop’s Castle, and Wenlock. By the same law, the borough of Bishop’s Castle has been disfranchised. The borough of Shrewsbury, as before, returns two members, as well as Ludlow, Bridgenorth, and Wenlock.</p><p>The titles of peers derived from the county are, Earl of Shrewsbury, and Barons Hill and Forrester, and the Irish title of Earl of Ludlow. As there are fewer titles derived from this county, so the seats of peers are much fewer than in any other of the same extent. The most remarkable residences of noblemen and gentlemen are the following : Walcot Hall, Earl Powis ; Hardwicke, Lord Hill ; Ross Hall and Willey Park, Lord Forrester; Apley Park, Thomas Whitmore, M. P. ; Dudmaston, William Whitmore ; Pitchford, Honourable C. C. C. Jenkinson, M. P. ; Hod- nett, the late Mr Heber ; Hawkstone, Sir Richard Hill, Bart., M. P. ; Kinlet Hall, W. C. Childe, Esq. M. P. ; Stanley Hall, Sir T. Tyrwhit Jones, Bart ; Altingham, Lord Berwick ; Manor House, Lord Stafford ; Pradoe, Honourable Thomas Kenyon ; Pentrepant Hall, Honourable F. West; Orlaton Hall, William Cludde, Esq. ; Downton Castle, Richard Payne Knight, Esq.; Oakley Park, Honourable Robert Clive ; Plowden Hall, Edward Plowden, Esq. ; Aud- lim, Lady Cotton.	<hi rend="italic smallcaps">(g.)</hi></p><p>SALOPAR, a town of the island of Ceylon, belonging to the British, eighteen miles north-north-west of Trinco- malee.</p><p>SALPINX, <hi rend="italic">σαλπιγξ,</hi> the name of an ancient Greek trumpet.</p><p>SALSETTE, an island on the western coast of Hindustan, in the province of Aurungabad, about eighteen miles in length by fourteen in average breadth. It was formerly separated from Bombay by a narrow strait about two hundred yards across, opposite to the fort of Tannah, across which, in 1805, a causeway was carried, which, although it is said to have had a prejudicial effect on the harbour, has been of much advantage to the island. The soil is well adapted for the cultivation of sugar, cotton, hemp, indigo, and the</p></body></text></TEI>