<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-19T20:09:55Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>still a considerable degree of cleanliness is observable everywhere. The quays are covered with sheds ; and the nume- , rous buyers and sellers who are congregated near them, and near the ships, present a striking picture of animation and bustle, and seem to confirm what is asserted by the natives, that Salonica is the first trading city of the Levant. The inhabitants are calculated, for they are not ascertained, to be between sixty and seventy thousand, of whom one half are Turks, one quarter Greeks, one fifth Jews, and the remainder Franks of all the several European nations, each of which have resident consuls. The manufactures are extensive, yielding cotton and silk goods, turkey leather, carpets, tobacco, and snuff, and the small articles of gold, silver, copper, steel, and iron ; these, and many raw materials, such as raw silk, cotton, wool, corn, oil, honey, wax, with opium and other drugs, form the exports. Although the excellence and security of the haven naturally creates great maritime commerce, yet that by land with Austria and Germany is very extensive, and at one period conveyed vast quantities of colonial wares to great distances in the interior of Europe, as long as Bonaparte’s continental system was in force, and is still a valuable branch of the trade of this city. This place has institutions for education, and especially the Jews have an institution in which it is said there are more than a hundred tutors and a thousand pupils. The Greeks have several elementary schools, but none for the higher branches of learning. There are few remains of antiquity except the Hippodrome, which is of marble, and highly ornamented with most valuable sculpture. There is also a rotunda built in resemblance of that in Rome, and the remains of two triumphal arches built by Augustus and Constantine. In 1313 this city was ceded for a valuable consideration by the Greek emperors to the Venetians, who retained it ten years, and it fell under the Turks with Constantinople. Long. 22. 25. 25. E. Lat. 40. 40. N.</p><p>SALOON, a town of Hindustan, in the nabob’s territories, in the province of Oude, sixty-five miles south- south-east from Lucknow. Long. 81. 24. E. Lat. 26. 2. N.</p><p>SALOOR, a town of Hindustan, in the Northern Cir- care, fifty-three miles north-west from Vizagapatam. Long. 83. 19. E. Lat. 18. 26. N.</p><p>SALOP, or <hi rend="smallcaps">ShropsHIBE,</hi> an inland county of England. It is bounded on the north by Cheshire and the Welsh counties of Flint and Denbigh ; on the west by the Welsh counties of Denbigh, Montgomery, and Radnor ; on the south by Herefordshire and Worcestershire ; and on the east by Staffordshire. It is of an oblong figure, extending from north to south, and contains a variety of projections and indentations. Its greatest length is about forty-six, and its greatest breadth thirty-seven miles. Its superficial contents are 1341 square miles, or 854,240 statute acres.</p><p>This county is divided into fifteen districts or hundreds, of which five are on the north-east side of the river Severn, three extend to both banks of that river, and the remainder are on its south-west side. The ecclesiastical di- visions of the county are into the diocese of Lichfield and Coventry, extending over 114 churches ; of Hereford, over 127; of Worcester, over three; and of St Asaph, over twelve; besides which there are six in the peculiar jurisdiction of Bridgenorth, making in the whole 262 churches, of which 229 are parochial.</p><p>The population of this county at the four deccnnial periods of enumeration has been found to be as follows : In 1801, 167,639 ; in 1811, 194,298; in 1821, 206,153 ; and in 1831, 222,800.</p><p>The occupiers of land employing labourers, were.... 3,832</p><p>Occupiers of land not employing labourers	 2,139</p><p>Labourers employed in agriculture	17,296</p><p>Ditto employed in manufactures	 1,353</p><p>Ditto employed in retail trade or handicraft	14,461</p><p>Capitalists, bankers, &amp;c	   1,918</p><p>Labourers not agricultural	11,585</p><p>Other males under twenty years of age	 2,800</p><p>Males above twenty years of age	56,474</p><p>Male servants	 1,560</p><p>Female servants	  11,371</p><p>In the year 1831, the number of families chiefly employed in agriculture was found to be 17,096 ; of those chiefly employed in trade, manufactures, and handicraft, 16,210; and of those not comprised in the two preceding classes, 13,121. The annual value of the real property of the county, as assessed in 1813, was L.1,037,988. The number of houses in 1831 was thus estimated: Inhabited, 42,633, occupied by 46,267 families; uninhabited, 1415; and building, 253.</p><p>The towns whose population exceeded 1500 persons in 1831 are,</p><p>Shrewsbury	21,297 Wenlock town, 3,481 ; but in</p><p>Hales Owen	 9,765	the borough are included</p><p>Wellington	 9,671	several parishes, of which</p><p>Ellesmere	 6,540	Broseley contained 4,299,</p><p>Whitchurch	 5,736	and	Madeley 5,822,	or in</p><p>Bridgenorth	 5,298	the	whole	17,435</p><p>Ludlow	 5,253	Newport	 2,745</p><p>Shiffnal	 4,779	Bishop’s	Castle	 2,007</p><p>Oswestry	 4,478 Wem	 1,932</p><p>Drayton	 3,882	Hodnel	 l,767</p><p>Cleobury Mortimer... 1,716</p><p>The face of the county is very much diversified. On the western side it has the wild appearance of the adjoining principality of Wales. Throughout the rest of the county the land is rather undulating, tolerably wooded, and with many beautiful rivulets meandering along the different valleys. The whole tract of country, from Wellington to the termination of the county between Oswestry and Chirk, exhibits the mild beauties of a fertile and cultivated district, enclosed by well-formed hedges into fields, of dimensions well calculated for advantageous husbandry, and ornamented with several domains of noblemen and gentlemen, which present a most pleasing succession of pictures to the traveller.</p><p>That singular insulated mountain, the Wrekin, rising from a plain to the height of eleven hundred feet, exhibits its sugar-loaf form over the tops of the smaller elevations in its vicinity, and increases the interest of the scenery. In the southern division of the county, the Brown Clee Hill and the Titterson Clee Hill rise to greater elevations than the Wrekin, and produce much picturesque variety.</p><p>In a county of such extent the soil must be very varied. On the eastern side, the valleys are flat and warm, and the soil generally of a sandy nature. In the middle part, the soil is most tenacious, and the bottoms of the wider valleys have frequently a stiff but rich clay. On the most western parts, the soil is very shallow, resting upon rocks of varied descriptions ; and is better calculated for sheep-pasture than for producing grain. There are some moorlands, but enclosures and drainage have considerably diminished their extent. A very great portion of the soil rests on a limestone subsoil ; and almost the whole of the plains are easy to work with light ploughs and two or three horses. The easterly wind generally prevails in the spring, and the westerly in autumn ; but the former is more remarkable for regularity than the latter. The whole of the county enjoys a salubrious air ; but on the hills, on the western side, the cold of winter is most intensely felt.</p><p>The chief river is the Severn, which runs through the whole extent of the county from north-frest to south-east. It is navigable at all seasons to the Bristol Channel downwards, and in wet seasons upwards to Welshpool in Montgomeryshire. The navigation is, however, at all times impeded by many obstructions. In dry weather, the fords</p></body></text></TEI>