<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-19T20:10:27Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>nufactured here than in any other part of the province. The other towns or villages of Santa Catharina are small and of little importance. In 1812 the population, according to Cazal, was 31,530; but it has greatly increased. The province is divided into seven parishes, three of which are situated on the island of Santa Catharina, and four on the continent. The whole are included within the see of Rio de Janeiro. For a description of the island of Santa Catharina, see the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Catherine, St</hi>.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Santa Cruz,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">St Croix,</hi> a small and unhealthy island, situated in about sixty-four degrees west longitude and eighteen north latitude. In 1643 it was inhabited by the Dutch and the English, who soon became enemies to each other ; and in 1650 they were both driven out by twelve hundred Spaniards, who arrived there in five ships. The triumph of these lasted but a few months. The remains of that numerous body, which were left for the defence of the island, surrendered without resistance to a hundred and sixty French, who had embarked, in the year 1651, from St Christopher’s, to make themselves masters of the island. It continued without inhabitants and without cultivation till 1733, when it was sold by France to Denmark for L.30,750. Soon afterwards the Danes built there the fortress of Christianstadt. It was then that this northern power seemed likely to take deep root in America ; but, unfortunately, she laid her plantations under the yoke of exclusive privileges. Industrious people of all sects, particularly Moravians, strove in vain to overcome this great difficulty. Many attempts were made to reconcile the interests of the colonists and their oppressors, but without success. The two parties kept up a continual struggle of animosity, and not of industry. At length the government purchased, in 1754, the privileges and effects of the company. The price was fixed at L.4l2,500 ; and the navigation of the islands opened to all the subjects of the Danish dominions. It is the most valuable of the Danish possessions in the West Indies. The soil is fertile and well cultivated, and the principal productions are sugar, rum, and coffee. It is about eighty-one square miles in extent, and contains about 37,000 inhabitants, of whom 3000 are whites, 1200 free blacks and mulattoes, and the remainder slaves.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Santa Cruz,</hi> a small island among the Philippines, near the south coast of Luzon. Long. 121. 52. E. Lat. 13. 42. N. Also an island near the south-west coast of Mindanao. Long. 122. 12. E. Lat. 6. 40. N.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Santa Fe,</hi> a city of Spain, on the plains of Granada, and in the province of Andalusia. When, under Ferdinand and Isabella, the court of Spain determined to reduce to the Christian dominion the last refuge of the Moors in the city of Granada, as the siege was likely to be very protracted, this city was founded near it, as the head-quarters of the Catholic forces. It is in a fine situation, surrounded by the best cultivation, and enjoying the best soil in Spain, perhaps in the world ; and its powers of irrigation are always greater in proportion to the heat of the weather, as the waters are supplied from the melting of the snows on the summit of the Sierra Nevada. This city has been frequently injured by earthquakes, which have at times almost destroyed its edifices. One in 1807 was especially destructive; but, from the richness of the soil, it has speedily risen from its ruins, and been as flourishing as before the visitation. It is said that a narrow strip of land, extending the whole distance across the plain, and on one part of which this city is built, is periodically subject to this calamity, which, however the inhabitants may dread it, has not power to drive them from it. Near to this place is the residence and estate granted by the Spanish government to the Duke of Wellington for his services during the war. It is called the Sota de Roma, and is finely situated.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Santa Fe de Bogota,</hi> a town of South America, and capital of New Granada, is situated at the foot of a steep</p><p>mountain, at the entrance of a vast plain. It is the residence of a viceroy and an archbishop, and the seat of an audiencia and a university, and contains magnificent houses, five bridges, and thirty thousand inhabitants. The air is constantly temperate. The wheat of Europe and the sesame of Asia produce abundant crops, and at all seasons. The plateau on which the town of Santa Fe de Bogota is situated bears a resemblance in several respects to that which encloses the Mexican lakes. They are both more elevated than the convent of St Bernard, the former being 8190, the latter 7008 feet above the level of the sea. Long. 74.10. W. Lat. 4. 35. N.</p><p>SANTANDER, a city of Spain, in the province of Old Castille. It is situated on the northern coast, on the Bay of Biscay, and is one of the best ports on that shore. It carries on considerable commerce in fine wools, and imports large quantities of the salted fish of Newfoundland. The commerce with the interior has induced the construction of a good road to Reynosa, in spite of the rocks and quagmires which intervene. It is the see of a bishop, and has an ancient cathedral and several richly adorned churches. It is in north latitude 43. 28. 20. and west longitude 3. 5. 6. from London. It contains 10,000 inhabitants, one sugar refinery, some breweries, founderies, a royal one for anchors, and several tanneries.</p><p>SANTAREM, a city of Portugal, in the province of Estremadura. It is situated on a hill, which is washed by the river Tagus, and from it, such is the gradual declivity of the country, that the towers of Lisbon, though at fifty miles distance, are visible through the translucent atmosphere. The prospects from the heights above the city, either up or down the river, are enchanting. The place contains about eight thousand inhabitants, who, with the exception of a numerous body of ecclesiastics, are by no means rich. The number of churches and other religious houses is out of all proportion to the number of the inhabitants, there being thirteen churches and fourteen convents, besides places for divine worship in several of the hospitals. Great part of the town is in ruins ; and though no place may be kept clean at less expense, it is excessively filthy, both in its streets and its houses. Some parts of the country about the city are highly fertile, and yield abundant crops of grapes, olives, maize, and some wheat. It was long the station of a part of the British army during the late contest, and it was several times occupied by the French.</p><p>SANTEUIL, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Santeul, Jean Baptiste</hi> DE, an excellent Latin poet, was bom at Paris in the year 1630. Having finished his studies, he applied himself entirely to poetry, and celebrated in his verse the praises of several great men, by which he acquired universal applause. He enriched Paris with a great number of inscriptions, which are to be seen on the public fountains and the monuments consecrated to posterity. At length, some new hymns being to be composed for the Breviary of Paris, Claud Santeuil his brother, and M. Bossuet, persuaded him to undertake that work ; and he succeeded in it with the greatest applause. On this the order of Clugny having desired him to compose some for their Breviary, he complied with their request; and that order, out of gratitude, granted him letters of filiation, with an annual pension. Santeuil was caressed by all the learned men of his time, and had as his admirers the two princes of Condé, father and son, from whom he frequently received favours. Louis XIV. also gave him a proof of his esteem, by bestowing upon him a pension. He attended the Duke of Bourbon to Dijon, when that prince went thither in order to hold the states of Burgundy, and died there in 1697, as he was preparing to return to Paris. Besides his Latin hymns, he wrote a great number of Latin poems, which have all the marks of genius discoverable in the works of true poets.</p><p>SANTIAGO, a large city of Spain, in the province of</p></body></text></TEI>