<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-19T20:11:08Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>lamented was that of the province of Saxony, the cradle of the reigning dynasty, which was 5700 square miles in extent, and contained 875,000 inhabitants. Among the subjects of regret, the greatest was the loss of those portions of the kingdom which chiefly supplied the corn, the wood, and the salt.</p><p>Amidst the calamities that had been endured, not a complaint was made by the subjects against their monarch. They were universally satisfied, that in all the changes, he had acted more out of regard to the happiness of his people than his own aggrandisement ; and when he returned from his captivity to Dresden, he was received with the affectionate feeling which would be displayed in a domestic circle, when the virtuous head of a family returned home among scenes of distress and common suffering. The country was at that time, from having been so long occupied by numerous armies of various nations, in a most dreadful state of poverty, disease, and moral depravity ; but the return of peace, the restoration of the monarch, and the confidence reposed in his goodness and wisdom, produced in a very short time a wonderful effect. Order and credit in the finances were first established, and the fruitful soil, by the application of the skill and industry for which the natives are distinguished, soon produced abundance of the necessaries of life ; by breeding fine-woolled sheep, the means of restoring that manufacture was effected ; and the surplus wool being exported, brought in return much real wealth. The fabrics of linen, cotton, iron, and other goods, were much extended, whilst the great fairs at Leipsig became two central points yearly for beneficial commerce with foreign countries. As the tranquillity gradually produced prosperity, judicious improvements were made in the establishments for the education of the common people, as well as for the training of the medical students, of the civil and military engineers, and of the higher branches of knowledge. The king lived to a great age, the last twelve years of which were attended with improvements in every public department, and exhibited among all classes, whether agricultural, commercial, mining, or manufacturing, an advance which excited surprise in all who attentively watched its steps, and inspired that mutual confidence between the king and the people, which was retained till his death in 1827. The progress was continued under the successor of the king till the year 1831. At that time the revolution in France, which expelled the elder branch of the Bourbons, was felt in every part of Germany, and excited popular tumults. Dresden had its share, and a mob destroyed one or two of the inferior public buildings. It was, however, soon suppressed, by the discharge of a good but unpopular minister, by the division of the states into two chambers, and other trifling alterations. From that period peace has continued and prosperity has advanced.</p><p>The kingdom of Saxony, in its present state, is a compact and connected territory. It extends from 28° 5’ to 31° 13' east longitude, and from 50° 10' to 51° 31' north latitude. It is bounded on the north and north-east by Prussia, on the south-east and south by Austria, on the south-west by Bavaria, on the west by the principality of Reus and the duchy of Saxe-Gotha, and on the north-west by Prussia. By a recent arrangement it has been divided into four circles, and these again are subdivided into amts or bailiwicks in the following manner :</p><table><row><cell>Circles.</cell><cell>Amts.</cell><cell>Cities.</cell><cell>Villages.</cell><cell>Extent in English Acres.</cell><cell><p>Inhabi</p><p>tants.</p></cell></row><row><cell>Dresden..</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>32</cell><cell>998</cell><cell>1,098,240</cell><cell>411,864</cell></row><row><cell>Leipsig....</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>38</cell><cell>1001</cell><cell>887,040</cell><cell>361,251</cell></row><row><cell>Zwickau..</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>58</cell><cell>873</cell><cell>1,182,720</cell><cell>549,811</cell></row><row><cell>Bautzen...</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>13</cell><cell>629</cell><cell>633,600</cell><cell>257,444</cell></row><row><cell/><cell>15</cell><cell>141</cell><cell>3501</cell><cell>3,801,600</cell><cell>1,580,370</cell></row></table><p>By a subsequent addition of the births, and a deduction of the deaths, the population at the end of the year 1836 was found to be 1,618,495. In the year 1818 the population was found to be 1,282,082, having thus increased in eighteen years 336,413, being at the rate of about twenty- five per cent.</p><p>The cities whose inhabitants amount to more than 5000, with their present population, are,</p><p>Dresden (besides the	Glauchau	6229</p><p>garrison)	66,133	Zwickau	6127</p><p>Leipsig	44,802	Grossenhain	5582</p><p>Chemnitz	21,137	Dobeln	5559</p><p>Freyburg	 11,545	Mittweide	5506</p><p>Plauen	 8,570	Frankenberg	5415</p><p>Bautzen	 8,467	Reichenbach	5412</p><p>Zittau	 8,195	Zschopau	5384</p><p>Meissen	 7,525	Oschatz	5243</p><p>Schneeberg	 6,769	Perna	5214</p><p>Annaberg	 6,377</p><p>The northern part of the kingdom of Saxony is for the most part a level or an undulating country ; but on the south it is very mountainous. The mountains rise in three successive ridges, denominated the Vorgeberg, Mithelgeberg, and Hochgeberge ; the southernmost of these, bordering on Bohemia, is the loftiest. The highest points of these mountains are those of the Fichtelberg, 3730 feet ; Auersberg, 2931 feet ; the Lausche, 2400 feet ; and Hochwald, 2299 feet.</p><p>A part of this mountainous district, between Dresden and Bohemia, usually denominated Saxon Switzerland, has peculiar charms for the lovers of picturesque scenery. It is about twenty-eight miles in length and twenty-three in breadth, displaying deep chasms bordered by perpendicular rocks, some naked, and others clothed with every variety of trees. Rapid streams pour from declivities, forming cascades in some parts, and in others, in deep vales, meandering through verdant meadows, without their issue or their egress being discoverable by the observer from the precipices which enclose such recesses, and whence he can see no path by which the vales can be reached. Through this mass of mountains the river Elbe has worn itself a passage, by a most tortuous course, and washes the bases of rocks, in some parts of near a thousand feet in perpendicular height, from the summit of which that stream appears to the beholder as an insignificant rivulet. From the surface of this mountain plain rise pinnacles of rocks, on which castles in the feudal times were erected, some of the ruins of which add to the romantic grandeur of the prospect ; whilst others, such as Königstein and Litherstein, have had applied to them all the arts of modern fortification, and are the most impregnable fortresses in the Saxon dominions. Königstein especially, though, from its great height, it appears to terminate in a point, has on its apex strong walls, surrounding buildings in which the treasures of the crown are secured in times of danger, with ground to yield potatoes enough to feed the garrison, as that vegetable grows there to perfection, though, from being fourteen hundred feet in height, the rigid cold of winter is most severely felt This fortress, and that of Lillienstein on the opposite side of the Elbe, are considered as the keys to Bohemia. Few spots in Europe create greater interest in the geologist the botanist or the lover of picturesque scenery, than this portion of the country so appropriately denominated Saxon Switzerland.</p><p>The principal river of Saxony, and that to which almost all the others contribute their streams, though not till it has left this kingdom, is the Elbe. It enters from Bohemia, and is navigable for barges through the whole of its Saxon course. The other rivers are the Black Elster, which rises in Lusatia, and soon enters the Prussian territory ; and the Spree, which comes out of Bohemia, divides itself into two</p></body></text></TEI>