<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-19T20:10:07Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>SALUTE, in military matters, a discharge of artillery, or small arms, or both, in honour of some person of extraordinary quality. The colours likewise salute royal persons, and generals commanding in chief, which is done by lowering the point to the ground. In the field, when a regiment is to be reviewed by the king or his general, the drums beat a march as he passes along the line, and the officers salute one another, bowing their half-pikes or swords to the ground, then recover and take off their hats. The ensigns salute all together, by lowering their colours.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Salute,</hi> in the navy, a testimony of deference or homage rendered by the ships of one nation to those of another, or by ships of the same nation to those of a superior or equal.</p><p>This ceremony is variously performed, according to the circumstances, rank, or situation, of the parties. It consists in firing a certain number of cannon, or volleys, of small arms ; in striking the colours or top-sails ; or in one or more general shouts of the whole ship’s crew, mounted for that purpose on the masts or rigging.</p><p>SALWATTY, an island in the Pacific Ocean, near the north-west coast of New Guinea, from which it is separated by a narrow channel. It is about ninety miles in circumference. Long. 131. 15. E. Lat. 1. 6. S.</p><p>SALZBURG. At present this district forms a circle of the Austrian province of Upper Ens, extending over 2836 square miles. It was formerly one of the most valuable of the independent ecclesiastical states of Germany, in the circle of Bavaria, under its own archbishop, whose revenues and dignity were of the highest class. It then contained sixteen cities, twenty-three market-towns, and 250,000 inhabitants. Owing to a severe persecution of the Protestants, which the archbishop instituted between 1729 and 1733, many of that religious party emigrated, and established themselves in other parts of Germany, and thereby the population was more that) one third reduced ; and those who had abandoned it were the most active portion of the community. During the French revolution, the country was secularized, and by the treaty of 1802 was, with Eich- stadt, Berchtolsgaden, and a part of Passau, given to the archduke of Austria, Ferdinand, as an indemnification for the loss of Tuscany. By the peace of Presburg in 1805, Salzburg was secured to the emperor of Austria, and Eich- stadt, with Passau, ceded to Bavaria. The treaty of 1809 left Salzburg at the disposal of Napoleon, who, in 1810, transferred it to the kingdom of Bavaria ; but by the general peace of 1815 it was again delivered over to the Austrian monarchy, of which it still forms a portion. It is a most romantically interesting country, very rich in the long valley through which the river Salza flows, and in the smaller valleys which proceed from it, especially on the southern side of that stream. On both sides of these valleys are lofty mountains, forming a part of the Noric Alps, whose tops, especially that of the Nokehom, which is 10,380 feet in height, are covered with perpetual snow, and exhibit, like the Alps in Switzerland, the striking objects which attract such numerous visitors. There are various mines in the territory, the most prolific of which are those of rock-salt, which yield more than sufficient for the consumption of the inhabitants. Formerly, several mines of gold were worked, and some of silver ; but of late years that employment has been diminished, and applied to other subterranean objects. These are iron, arsenic, rock-crystal, marble, serpentine, saltpetre, cobalt, and asbestos. The iron is made into cutlery and other hardwares for domestic use, but no raw iron is exported. The circle yields flax and hemp, which, with the wool of their sheep, is spun and woven by the peasantry during the winter months, and converted by themselves into the necessary articles of clothing. The whole number of the inhabitants at present is 152,000.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Salzburg,</hi> a city, the capital of the Austrian circle of the same name. It stands on the beautiful valley of the Saltz,</p><p>on both sides the river of that name, over which there is a beautiful bridge three hundred and seventy feet long and forty feet broad. The city is surrounded with walls, but the suburbs are more extensive and more elegant, and extend to a considerable distance, containing the best of the modern residences. The streets within the city are narrow and crookcd, but there are several handsome open plazas or squares, and a great number of those large and striking buildings which are tokens of its former ecclesiastical sovereigns. On a hill overlooking the city, and six hundred feet above it, is the ancient fortress of Moncksberg, now dismantled of its artillery ; but it is an object of curiosity from a road having been hewn out of the solid rock on which it stands, forming an archway a hundred and fifty yards in length and eight in breadth, which terminates in a most delightful prospect of the surrounding country. It contains, with the suburbs, 16,500 inhabitants, who have little trade except at two large fairs, which become entrepôts for exchanging the productions of Italy with those of Germany. The environs are highly enchanting from the scenery they exhibit. Long. 13. 54. 5. E. Lat. 47. 43. 10. N.</p><p>SALZWEDEL, a city of Prussian Saxony, in the government of Magdeburg, the capital of a circle of the same name, which extends over 454 square miles, and contains a population of 31,600 persons. It is situated on the river Jeeke, which is navigable thus far, is surrounded with walls, and contains 930 houses, with 6300 inhabitants, employed in linen, cotton, and woollen manufactures, and in making leather, shoes, gloves, and refining salt.</p><p>SAMADONG, a large town in the island of Java, situated in a country of luxuriant fertility, 144 miles south-east from Batavia.</p><p>SAMAK, an island in the south-western part of the Gulf of Persia, about twelve leagues in circumference.</p><p>SAMANA, a town of Hindustan, in the province of Delhi, possessed by native chiefs in alliance with the British, 122 miles north-west from Delhi. Long. 75.48. E. Lat. 30.2. N.</p><p>SAMANAP, a large and populous town on the southeastern coast of the island of Madura, and the residence of a prince. It is situated on a fine bay, which, though rather shallow, will admit of large brigs or country prows lying close to the town. It carries on an extensive commerce, and the country abounds in rice, and teak-timber for building. Long. 114. E. Lat. 7. 5. S.</p><p>SAMAND, a town of Hindustan, in the province of Moultan, anil district of Bahar, which is tributary to the Afghans. It is situated on the eastern side of the river Indus. Long. 19. 57. E. Lat. 28. 11. N.</p><p>SAMANEANS, in <hi rend="italic">Antiquity,</hi> a kind of magicians or philosophers, who have been confounded by some with the Brahmins. They proceeded from Ariana, a province of Persia, and the neighbouring countries, spread themselves in India, and taught new doctrines.</p><p>The Brahmins, before their arrival, it is said, were in the highest period of their glory the only oracles of India ; and their principal residence was on the banks of the Ganges and in the adjacent mountains, whilst the Samaneans were settled towards the Indus. Others say that the Brahmins acquired all their knowledge from the Samaneans, before whose arrival it would be difficult to prove that the Brahmins were the religious teachers of the Indians. The most celebrated and ancient of the Samanean doctors was Boutta, or Buddha, who was born 683 years before Christ. His scholars paid him divine honours ; and his doctrine, which consisted chiefly in the transmigration of souls, and in the worship of cows, was adopted not only in India, but also in Japan, China, Siam, and Tartary. It was propagated, according to M. de Sainte Croix, in Thibet, in the eighth century, and succeeded there the ancient religion of Zamolxis. The Samaneans, or Buddhists, were entirely destroyed in India by the Brahmins ; but several of their books were preserv-</p></body></text></TEI>