<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-19T20:10:33Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>hood the name of <hi rend="italic">Domu de Orcu,</hi> or the house of death ; but the pottery being evidently Roman, and in some instances accompanied by coins of the lower empire, indicates only that such was the use made of them at a late period. Captain Smyth, who examined these ancient monuments, says, “ From their laborious construction, their number, and their general situation on <hi rend="italic">curureddus</hi> or eminences, more or less distant from each other, I cannot but suppose they were designed to answer the double purpose of mausolea for the eminent dead, and as asyla for the living, especially as many of them are flanked with smaller nuraggis having a subterraneous communication. But the mystery in which they are involved will probably remain impenetrable, since none of them exhibit the least trace of either literal or symbolical characters.”</p><p>At whatever periods these remarkable works were erected, a long time elaspsed before any precise notice is to be discovered of the history of Sardinia, until about the year 560 before Christ, when the Carthaginians under Machæus, after a victorious campaign in Sicily, attempted the conquest of the island. They were repulsed with such loss, however, as left it in repose until the contests commenced between the Punic and Roman republics.</p><p>By successive conquests it passed into the hands of the Vandals, the Mahommedans, and the Spaniards, in whose power it remained from 1324 till the period of the disputed succession of the crown of Spain between the houses of Bourbon and Austria in 1708, when the Austrian party, with the assistance of the English fleet under Sir John Leake, succeeded in obtaining possession of the island. In 1720 it was ceded by treaty to Victor Asmodeus, who assumed the title of king of Sardinia. After this event, notwithstanding the wars which agitated the rest of Europe, Sardinia experienced a peace of seventy years, during which period the princes of the house of Savoy, especially Charles Emanuel, made the greatest exertions to ameliorate the condition of the people.</p><p>The success of the French arms in Italy by the year 1798 had been such as to compel the king, Charles Emanuel IV., to abandon the capital, Turin, and the whole of his continental dominions. He withdrew to Leghorn, where he received with delight deputies from the stamente of Sardinia, assuring him of the entire devotion of the people to his person and government. Satisfied with these assurances, he embarked, and, escorted by an English frigate, arrived at Cagliari on the 3d of March 1799, where he was welcomed with the most enthusiastic affection.</p><p>The successes of the Russian General Suwarof induced his majesty to return to the Continent, till, hearing in Tuscany of the battle of Marengo, and being inconsolable for the death of his wife, the sister of Louis XVI., he abdicated in favour of the Duke of Aosta in March 1802, and resided in privacy at Rome, where he died in 1819. His successor, Victor Emanuel, remained some time in Italy in the hope of gaining his continental dominions ; but seeing little prospect of succeeding, he left Naples, where he had resided since his accession, and arrived in Sardinia on the 17th of February 1806, where he remained secure under the protection of England.</p><p>The son of Charles Emanuel followed the footsteps of his father in opposing the principles of the French revolution, which was then spreading its direful effects over all Europe, and nowhere more generally than in the continental part of the kingdom of Sardinia. The events of that period are to be found in this work in the historical parts of the two articles <hi rend="smallcaps">Europe</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">France.</hi> We need only state here, therefore, that the king of Sardinia returned to his continental capital in 1814, and by the treaty of Vienna the duchy or ancient republic of Genoa was added to his dominions ; and that by the same treaty he ceded to the state of Geneva the circles of Carouge and Chesne, containing</p><p>12,700 inhabitants. On the restoration of Victor Emanuel, he re-established, as far as could be done, the old constitution ; again introducing the Jesuists, and becoming a zealous member of the Holy Alliance. He confirmed to those who had made purchases under the French confiscation the property they had gained ; restored to their owners the few estates that had not been sold ; and allotted the annual sum of 400,000 lire as some compensation for the plunder which they had suffered. He however established a very severe censorship of the press, and introduced such restrictions on the process of education in the universities and the other seminaries as he judged necessary to check the prevailing tendency to infidelity and immorality. These measures, and the predisposition to revolution indulged throughout Italy, caused an insurrection in 1821, the particulars of which are narrated in this work under the head of <hi rend="smallcaps">Italy.</hi> The prosperity of the kingdom has been proceeding with regularity since the return of tranquillity, owing in a great measure to the increased demand for silk in England, Germany, France, and Russia, and in no inconsiderable degree from the annexation of Genoa to the territory, by which a trade is now carried on to almost every part of the habitable world.</p><p>The extent of the several divisions of this kingdom, and their population in 1833, were as follow :—</p><table><row><cell>Provinces.</cell><cell><p>Extent in</p><p>Square</p><p>Miles.</p></cell><cell>Population.</cell><cell>Cities.</cell><cell>Towns.</cell><cell>Villages</cell></row><row><cell>Turin	</cell><cell>3,278</cell><cell>808,526</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>54</cell><cell>347</cell></row><row><cell>Cuneo	</cell><cell>2,684</cell><cell>521,631</cell><cell>13</cell><cell>53</cell><cell>303</cell></row><row><cell>Alessandro.</cell><cell>2,420</cell><cell>547,622</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>40</cell><cell>453</cell></row><row><cell>Novara	</cell><cell>2,596</cell><cell>437,576</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>44</cell><cell>426</cell></row><row><cell>Aosta	</cell><cell>1,408</cell><cell>71,096</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>78</cell></row><row><cell>Savoy	</cell><cell>4,092</cell><cell>504,165</cell><cell>19</cell><cell>36</cell><cell>594</cell></row><row><cell>Nice	</cell><cell><p>1,496</p><p>2,288</p></cell><cell><p>204,538</p><p>583,233</p></cell><cell>6</cell><cell>16</cell><cell>160</cell></row><row><cell>Genoa	</cell><cell/><cell/><cell>19</cell><cell>25</cell><cell>700</cell></row><row><cell>Island of Sardinia.</cell><cell>19,856</cell><cell>491,050</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>377</cell></row><row><cell>Island of Capraja..</cell><cell>484</cell><cell>1,500</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>3</cell></row><row><cell/><cell>30,602</cell><cell>4,170,937</cell><cell>95</cell><cell>285</cell><cell>3441</cell></row></table><p>The whole of the inhabitants of this kingdom adhere to the Roman Catholic church, with the exception only of about 30,000 Jews, who have a restricted toleration, and some Protestants, well known under the name of Walden- ses, who are settled, after long and frequent persecutions, in the valleys of Lucerne, Perusa, and St Martin, in the western part of Piedmont. According to their own account, they occupy thirteen villages, and number nearly 20,000 souls, who are allowed the free exercise of their own mode of religious worship.</p><p>The religious establishment of the kingdom is very extensive, comprehending no less than nine archbishoprics and thirty-four bishoprics, who have under them ninety- seven chapters of ecclesiastics in the cities, with 3619 parish priests in the towns and villages, besides 300 monasteries of various orders, and about eighty nunneries for females. The state of education is generally very low, and few of the peasantry can either read or write. There is a university at Turin with about eight hundred students, another at Genoa with about four hundred, and a third in the island of Cagliari with two hundred and fifty. There are also about eighty colleges where Latin is taught, and forty seminaries for the education of the ecclesiastics.</p><p>The government is an absolute and hereditary monarchy, although in the island of Sardinia the assembly of the</p></body></text></TEI>