<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-19T20:10:26Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ed tribunals in the five principal cities of Judæa ; at Jerusalem, at Gadara, at Amathus, at Jericho, and at Sephora or Sephoris, a city of Galilee. Grotius places the origin of , the sanhedrim under Moses, as the rabbin do ; but he makes it terminate at the beginning of Herod’s reign. Mr Basnage at first thought that the sanhedrim began under Gabinius ; but afterwards he places it under Judas Maccabæus, or under his brother Jonathan. We see, indeed, under Jonathan Maccabæus, in the year 3860, that the senate along with the high priest sent an embassy to the Romans. The rabbin say, that Alexander Jannæus, king of the Jews, of the race of the Asmonæans, appeared before the sanhedrim, and claimed a right of sitting there, whether the senators would or not. Josephus informs us, that when Herod was but yet governor of Galilee, he was summoned before the senate, where he appeared. It must be therefore acknowledged that the sanhedrim was in being before the reign of Herod. It was in being afterwards, as we find from the Gospel and from the Acts. Jesus Christ in St Matthew (v. 22) distinguishes two tribunals. “ Whosoever is angry with his brother without a cause shall be in danger of the judgment this, they say, is the tribunal of the twenty-three judges. “ And whosoever shall say to his brother Raca, shall be in danger of the council ;” that is, of the great sanhedrim, which had the right of life and death, at least generally, and before this right was taken away by the Romans. Some think that the jurisdiction of the council of twenty-three extended to life and death also ; but it is certain that the sanhedrim was superior to this council.@@<hi rend="superscript">1</hi></p><p>From all this it may be concluded, that the origin of the sanhedrim is involved in uncertainty ; for the council of the seventy elders established by Moses was not what the Hebrews understand by the name of sanhedrim. Besides, we cannot perceive that this establishment subsisted either under Joshua, the judges, or the kings. We find nothing of it after the captivity till the time of Jonathan Maccabæus. The tribunals erected by Gabinius were very different from the sanhedrim, which was the supreme court of judicature, and fixed at Jerusalem, whereas Gabinins established five at five different cities. Lastly, it is certain that this senate was in being in the time of Jesus Christ ; but the Jews themselves inform us that they had then no longer the power of life and death (John, xviii. 31).</p><p>SANJORE, a Rajpoot town of Hindustan, in the province of Ajmeer and district of Saroway, situated on the east side of the river Bah, 115 miles west-south-west from Odeypoor. It is surrounded with the Beloochee plunderers, so that the road to it is impassable without a large escort. It is subject to the rajah of Joudpoor, who keeps a garrison stationed in it. It is 115 miles west-south-west from Odeypoor. Long. 72. 16. E. Lat. 25. 3. N.</p><p>SANKAN, a town of Arabia, in the province of Yemen, near the coast of the Red Sea, thirty-five miles north-north- west of Abu-Arisch.</p><p>SANNAZARIUS, <hi rend="smallcaps">James,</hi> a celebrated Latin and Italian poet, born at Naples in 1458. He by his wit ingratiated himself into the favour of King Frederick ; and when that prince was dethroned, he attended him into France, where he staid with him until his death, which happened in 1504. Sannazarius then returned into Italy, where he applied himself to polite literature, particularly to Latin and Italian poetry. His gay and facetious humour made him be sought for by all companies ; but he was so afflicted at the news that Phillibert prince of Orange, general of the emperor’s army, had demolished his country-house, that it threw him into an illness, of which he died in the year 1530. It is said that, being informed a few days before his death, that the Prince of Orange was killed in battle, he called</p><p>out, “ I shall die contented, since Mars has punished this barbarous enemy of the Muses.” He wrote a great number of Italian and Latin poems. Among those in Latin, his <hi rend="italic">De Partu Virginis</hi> and Eclogues are chiefly esteemed ; and the most celebrated of his Italian pieces is his <hi rend="italic">Arcadia.</hi></p><p>SANOK, a circle of the Austrian kingdom of Gallicia, extending over 2151 square miles, containing ten cities, ten market-towns, and 431 villages, with 230,600 inhabitants. The capital is the city of the same name, situated on the river San. It is a poor place, with but little trade, containing a castle, and 220 houses, with 1640 inhabitants. Long. 22. 7. E. Lat. 49.31.5. N.</p><p>SANQUHAR, a royal burgh in Scotland, on the left bank of the Nith, between the counties of Dumfries and Ayr. The town most probably owes its origin to a castle of some note, the ruins of which are still extant, on a high bank overlooking the river Nith. This castle was the chief residence of the Queensberry family, before William, the first duke, built the noble mansion of Drumlanrig. It is a place of little trade. The population in 1831 was 1527. It is one of the district of burghs which jointly with Dumfries scnds a member to parliament.</p><p>SANTA <hi rend="smallcaps">Catalina,</hi> one of the Solomon Islands, in long. 162. 31. 80. E. and lat. 10. 53. 50. S.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Santa Catharina</hi> a province of Brazil, comprehending the island of the same name, and a territory of sixty leagues in length from north to south on the neighbouring continent, reckoning from the Sahy Grande, which separates it from St Paulo on the north, to the Mampituba, which divides it from Rio Grande on the south. On the west, the heads of the Cordillera divide it from the same provinces, its greatest width not exceeding twenty leagues. The above limits include a territory extending from 25° 50' to 29° 20' of south latitude. On the continent, four miles south-east of the capital, stands the town of San Jose, the inhabitants of which are principally occupied in sawing timber into planks, making bricks, and growing rice. To the north of this town the shores are studded with houses, pleasantly situated amid bananarias, orangeries, and plantations of rice, coffee, and mandioca. Nine leagues from San Jose is the village of Armaçao, situated at the extremity of the Bay of St Miguel. It is a fishing station for whales, which were formerly very numerous on the coast, and in the bays that indent it. The conveniencies for the manufacture of oil are extensive and well contrived, and all the fish on the coast are brought to this quarter. Beyond the point of Armaçao is that of Dos Ganchos, forming the southern extremity of the spacious Bay of Tejuco or Tejucas, into which a river of the same name, fifty fathoms wide, discharges itself. Ten leagues north of this place is the fine capacious harbour of Gua- roupas, with its handsome town. Further northward is the Bay of St Francisco, in which there is an island with a town, both of the same name. The harbour is fine, and has three entrances, defended by forts. Ship-building is carried on at this place to some extent ; the cutting of the fine timber in the neighbourhood, and other labours connected with this art, being the chief occupation of the inhabitants, who may amount to about two thousand. The largest continental town in the province is Laguna, prettily situated upon the eastern margin of the lake from which it derives its name, two miles from the bar, and sixty miles south of Desterro. In the months of November, and December particularly, a prodigious quantity of a long fish, with a forked tail, called <hi rend="italic">bagre,</hi> enter the lake, supplying a lucrative branch of commerce. This place contains four thousand inhabitants. Fifteen miles north of Laguna is Villa Nova, or Santa Anna, situated on an elevation near the northern extremity of the same lake. More flax is ma-</p><p><hi rend="superscript">@@,</hi> See also Mark, xiii. 9, xiv. 55, xv. 1 ; Luke, xxii. 52, 66 ; John, xi. 47 ; Acts, iv. 15, v. 21 ; where mention is made of the synedrion or sanhedrim.</p></body></text></TEI>