<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-19T20:09:51Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ventual churches, a lyceum, which was formerly a university, and the remains of the celebrated medical school. The houses, though old, are large and grand, and the inhabitants are 10,650. A fair of the greatest trade in Italy was formerly held here ; but it has gradually fallen into decay of late years, owing to the insecurity of the roadstead, where ships must anchor, there being no harbour.</p><p>SALFORD, a township of the parish of Manchester, and a kind of suburb to that place, being separated from it only by a small bridge. It is chiefly inhabited by operatives in the cotton trade. It was created a borough by the law of 1832, for the purpose of returning one member to the House of Commons. The population amounted in 1801 to 13,611, in 1811 to 19,114, in 1821 to 25,772, and in 1831 to 40,786.</p><p>SALIANT, in <hi rend="italic">Fortification,</hi> denotes projecting. There are two kinds of angles ; the one saliant, which have their points outwards ; the other re-entering, which have their points inwards.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Saliant, Sament,</hi> or <hi rend="smallcaps">Saillant,</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Heraldry,</hi> is applied to a lion, or other beast, when its tore-legs are raised in a leaping posture.</p><p>SALIBABO <hi rend="smallcaps">Isles,</hi> a group of islands in the Eastern Seas, situated about the fourth degree of north latitude, and between 126 and 127 of east longitude. The island of Sali- babo is about fifteen miles in circumference, and is situated to the southward of Tulour, from which it is divided by a narrow strait, about one mile across. The names of the principal islands are Tulour or Kercolang, Salibabo, and Kabruang. Salibabo contains twelve villages, the united population of which amounts to 3000. All these islands are well cultivated and populous, abounding in potatoes, rice, goats, hogs, &amp;c. The inhabitants are of the Malay colour, with long hair; and have for arms lances, swords, targets, and daggers. They manufacture a coarse kind of cloth from the wild plantain tree. They are much oppressed by their chiefs, and sold as slaves for trifling offences. They barter provisions with such ships as pass, for coarse calicoes, red handkerchiefs, coarse cutlery, &amp;c. There is a good harbour on the east coast of the island of Salibabo.</p><p>SALIC or <hi rend="smallcaps">Salique Law (</hi><hi rend="italic">Lex Saliva),</hi> an ancient and fundamental law of the kingdom of France, usually supposed to have been made by Pharamond, or at least by Clovis, in virtue of which males only are to inherit.</p><p>Some, as Postellus, would have it to have been called <hi rend="italic">Salic,</hi> as if <hi rend="italic">Gallic,</hi> because peculiar to the Gauls. Montanus insists that it was so named because Pharamond was at first called <hi rend="italic">Salicus.</hi> Others will have it to be so named as having been made for the Salic lands. These were noble fiefs which the first kings used to bestow on the Sallians, that is, the great lords of their <hi rend="italic">solle</hi> or court, without any other tenure than military service ; and for this reason such fiefs were not to descend to women, as being by nature unfit for such a tenure. Some, again, derive the origin of this word from the Salians, a tribe of Franks that settled in Gaul in the reign of Julian, who is said to have given them lands upon condition of their personal service in war. He even passed the conditions into a law, which the new conquerors acquiesced in, and called it <hi rend="italic">salie,</hi> from the name of their former countrymen.</p><p>SALII, in Roman antiquity, priests of Mars, of which there were twelve, instituted by Numa, and wearing painted, parti-coloured garments, and high bonnets, with a steel cuirass on the breast. They were called <hi rend="italic">salii,</hi> from <hi rend="italic">sαltαre, </hi>to dance; because, after assisting at sacrifices, they went dancing about the streets, with bucklers in their left hand, and a rod in their right, striking musically with their rods on one another’s bucklers, and singing hymns in honour of the gods.</p><p>SALIM, a river of Asiatic Russia, which falls into the Obi, sixty miles from Sourgout.</p><p>SALINA, an island in the Mediterranean, belonging to the kingdom of the Two Sicilies. It is divided by a channel three miles across from Lipari to the north-west of that island. It is about fourteen miles in circuit. A valley between two mountains, called Fossa Felice, is extremely fertile, and produces a great revenue from the exportation of grain, fruit, pulse, capers, salt, alum, and wine, the last of which, known by the name Malvasia, is highly valued. It is evidently of volcanic origin, having vestiges of ancient craters and several thermal springs. It was known to the ancients by the name of Didyme, or twins, from the two conical mountains, which are prominent objects when seen from the sea. The population consists of 4000 persons. The chief town is Amalfi, near to which is good anchorage. Long. 14. 47. 35. E. Lat. of Amalfi church, 38. 35. 40. N.</p><p>SALINES, a city of France, in the department of the Jura, and arrondissement of Poligny. It is situated in a narrow valley on the river Furieuse, and is defended by two forts. In it arc some strong brine springs, from which culinary salt is prepared ; but much of the brine is conducted to Arp and Senans to be granulated. Near to it some excellent wine is produced, as well as much honey and bees-wax. In 1836 it contained 6554 inhabitants.</p><p>SALISBURY, or <hi rend="smallcaps">New Sarum,</hi> a city in the county of Wilts, and in the hundred of Underditch. It is the shire town of the county, where the assizes and the elections are held, and where, but in the village of Fisherton adjoining, is the county jail. It stands in a narrow valley, in which the small rivers Willy and Nadder unite with the Avon. These streams are, by means of small channels, conducted through most parts of the city, forming clear running brooks in several of the streets. By means of a canal the city communicates with the sea through Southampton. Among the public edifices for secular purposes, the most distinguished is the council-house, erected about forty-five years ago. It is a square building with a grand Doric portico, which forms on one side the entrance to the law-courts, and on the other to a large public room used for county meetings and other purposes. But the public building which most distinguishes this city is the magnificent cathedral, which is the most uniform structure, as well as being the most perfect and original example, of all the edifices dedicated to the choral service of the Church of England. The erection of it at the commencement of the reign of Henry III. marks a decided epoch in English architecture, the very beautiful pointed style having then been brought to its utmost perfection. A very experienced critic has given it as his opinion, that this very interesting church, so remarkable in its design for purity, simplicity, and grandeur, holds the same rank in English architecture which the Parthenon bears in the Grecian.</p><p>This edifice was founded in the year 1220, the fifth year of the reign of Henry III., the see having been then removed from Old Sarum, to which place it had been translated from Sherborn, in Dorsetshire, in 706, when the episcopal jurisdiction of it extended over what have since become the dioceses of Salisbury, Bristol, Wells, and Exeter. The extreme length of the cathedral outside from west to east is 480 feet. The length of the grand transept from south to north is 232 feet, and the extreme length of the eastern transept is 172 feet.</p><p>This church has an important advantage over many other edifices of a similar character, in not being so closely surrounded by other buildings. It is easy of access, and it affords a most delightful view from almost every point. As to outline and dimensions, a more splendid building can scarcely be imagined ; while the lofty proportions of the spire, which rises to the height of four hundred feet, become the more striking upon a near approach. The spire is a most interesting object from every part of the surrounding country. A slight settlement was observed to have taken place</p></body></text></TEI>