<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-19T20:13:28Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>We have not included the Jews in the foregoing enumeration, as they do not perhaps amount to above a hundred in all Scotland. Some of the dissenting congregations, besides, are very small ; and we do not think it probable that the dissenters amount to much more than the fourth part of the whole population of Scotland, assigning to the Established Church all who do not attend any dissenting place of worship.</p><p>The subject of education engaged the attention of the Scottish Parliament even in comparatively rude times, viz. as early as the year 1494. The protestant church zealously took up the subject, and many acts of the General Assembly were passed in support of it. But it was not till 1616 that the Privy Council interposed and passed an act in favour of parish schools; nor was it till seventeen years afterwards, that this act of Council was ratified by Parliament. The disturbed state of the times prevented the act from becoming operative; and it was not, in truth, till some time after the Revolution, namely, in 1696, that the celebrated statute of William and Mary was passed, which forms the foundation of the present parochial system. The provisions of this act were immediately carried into effect in most parishes; and now the system is in universal operation throughout Scotland. The landowners and clergymen have it in their power, according to law, to establish more than one school in a parish, if circumstances seem to demand it; in which case the salary assigned to each of the teachers is less than the maximum sum (L.34, 4s. 4<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">2</hi>d.) given when there is only one schoolmaster in a parish. From a Parliamentary paper,@@<hi rend="superscript">1</hi> we learn, that the number of parochial schools in Scotland is 1047; that the number of teachers is 1170; that the aggregate amount of the salaries paid to them is L.29,642, 18s. 11<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">4</hi>.; and that their total income, including salaries, fees, and all other emoluments, but exclusive of their dwelling-house and garden, is L.55,339, 17s. 1<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">2</hi>d., being an average of only L.47, 5s. 11<hi rend="superscript">3</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">4</hi>. to each teacher. But ill-paid though the teachers be, they are, generally speaking, a well educated and meritorious class of men; and the parochial system has given such a stimulus to education, that the endowed schools have been found, in the progress of society, to be too few to answer the demand for instruction on the part of the people. Hence it appears from the same official document, that the number of schools not parochial, is not less than 3995, and the number of teachers 4469, being nearly four times the amount of the parochial schools and teachers.@@<hi rend="superscript">2</hi> The greatest number of pupils attending the parochial schools between Lady- day and Michaelmas 1833, was 71,426; and the lowest number was 50,029∙ The greatest number attending the schools not parochial, between the same dates, was 189,427; and the lowest number was 139,237. What the incomes of the non-parochial teachers may be, we have no data to judge. They are pretty high in our large towns, but miserably low, perhaps not above ten shillings a-week, in rural districts. Taking the average of the preceding number of pupils, attending both the parochial and non-parochial schools, namely, 225,061, the inference is, that 10<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">2</hi> out of 100 of the population are at school; but when we take into account the number of female seminaries, of private boarding schools for boys, and children taught in private families by governesses and tutors, not to mention Sabbath evening schools and classes for religious instruction, we may with propriety conclude, that at least 9<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">2</hi> out of every 100 of the population are at the same time under tuition; a larger proportion than is known to be similarly situated, excepting in particular districts, in any other country of Europe.</p><p>The origin of the Scottish universities is not of any remote</p><p>date. But as early as the year 1282, Dervorgille, wife of John Balliol, founded and endowed a college at Oxford for the reception of Scottish students; and, in 1,326, a college, known by the name of the Scotch college, was founded and endowed at Paris by David Murray, bishop of Moray, for a similar purpose.@@<hi rend="superscript">3</hi> But at length Scotland enjoyed the advantages of universities within the limits of her own territory. That of St. Andrews, the oldest in the kingdom, was founded by papal authority in 1413; that of Glasgow, by the same authority, in 1450; that of Aberdeen, also under the sanction of the pope, in 1494, though education did not commence there till 1500; and that of Edinburgh, founded by the presbyterians, in 1582. The university of St. Andrews consisted at one time of three colleges, instituted at different periods, viz. St. Salvador’s, St. Leonard’s, and St. Mary’s; hut in 1748, the two first were united, and the buildings of St. Leonard’s were alienated and converted into dwelling-houses. The university of Aberdeen consists of two colleges; King’s, founded, as just stated, in 1494; and Marischal college, instituted and endowed by George Keith, Earl Marischal, in 1593. The universities of Glasgow and Edinburgh contain one college each; but embrace all the faculties in their course of instruction. The following table shews the number of professors in the different universities, with the date of their foundation.</p><table><row><cell/><cell><p>When</p><p>founded.</p></cell><cell>Principals.</cell><cell>Professors</cell></row><row><cell>St. Andrews	</cell><cell>1413</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>11</cell></row><row><cell>Glasgow,			</cell><cell>1450</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>19</cell></row><row><cell>Aberdeen, King’s College,...</cell><cell>1494</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>9</cell></row><row><cell>	Marischal College,</cell><cell>1593</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>12</cell></row><row><cell>Edinburgh,	</cell><cell>1582</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>30</cell></row></table><p>Each of these universities enjoys the privilege of conferring literary honours in all the faculties. The aggregate number of students attending all these seminaries is about 2900, of whom about 1300 belong to the university of Edinburgh ; 1100 to that of Glasgow ; and the remainder to Aberdeen and St. Andrews, the attendance on the latter not exceeding 130. There are no religious tests to exclude students from any of our Scottish colleges. Jews, Catholics, Protestants, enjoy the same privileges. But the professors should, according to law, belong to the Established Church, and are liable to be called upon to sign her standards. This condition, however, is not always exacted. The session extends from the beginning of November till the end of April. There are a few summer classes in the universities of Edinburgh and Glasgow, but these extend only to three months preceding the first of August. A Royal Commission was appointed in 1826 for visiting the universities and colleges of Scotland, and in 1830 gave in a voluminous report. Another Commission was nominated in 1836, for visiting the university of Aberdeen. Their report has just been presented. But though a bill was brought into Parliament in 1836, founded on the former report, providing for a general board of visitors appointed by the crown over all the universities, that bill was withdrawn ; and no measure on the subject has since been brought forward.</p><p>Though poor-rates are not generally imposed in Scotland, yet a law involving a compulsory assessment for the support of the impotent poor, was passed as early as the year 1576. But the very existence of such a statute seemed nearly unknown till about the middle of last century. “ As long as there was no secession of presbyterians from the Established Church, the weekly collections, under the</p><p><hi rend="superscript">@@@1</hi>	Educational Inquiry, Scotland, Session 1837, vol. xlvii.</p><p><hi rend="superscript">@@@2</hi>	Under the head of schools non-parochial, are included those established by the Society for Propagating Christian Knowledge, namely,</p><p>340; those founded by the General Assembly’s Education Committee, namely, 89 ; and those instituted by the different dissenting congregations.	</p><p><hi rend="superscript">@@@3</hi> Irving's Lives of Scottish Poets, 2d edit. vol. i. p. 61.</p></body></text></TEI>