<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-19T20:10:35Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ancient states is still continued ; but their power extends only to objects of a local and insignificant nature. In Genoa, too, some shadow of the ancient republican aristocracy exists, but it has little or no influence on the determinations of the monarch. The revenues of the kingdom are stated to amount to about two millions sterling annually, and the expenditure to be nearly the same. In the latter is included the interest on a national debt of five millions, a large portion of which is owing to foreigners, and among others to the capitalists of Geneva and other parts of Switzerland ; but by means of a sinking fund it is yearly diminishing. An army of thirty-five thousand men is maintained in time of peace, and a naval force, consisting of six frigates, three corvettes, six brigs, and several schooners and other small craft.</p><p>The continental parts of this kingdom present a face of the greatest possible variety. The part to the north, formerly the duchy of Savoy, is in appearance more a part of Switzerland than of ltaly. It is an alpine land, separated from the plains of the peninsula by an enormous chain of mountains known as the Gray Alps. It is peculiarly interesting, from the lofty heights, whose tops are covered with snow and ice, from the narrow and deep valleys, from its perpendicular cliffs, from the numerous cascades, and from the deep lakes ; and it is especially distinguished by the raging winds and violent storms of hail, rain, and snow, which occur with frequency in the more elevated regions.</p><p>The provinces of Piedmont, Milan, and Montserrat, form a vast valley, or rather plain, which was probably once covered with water, and which begins at the pass of Susa, and only terminates on the easternmost frontier of Italy. The river Po divides this valley into two nearly equal portions. Its northern side extends to the foot of the Alps, which separate it from Switzerland, some great projections of which enter it at Aosta and Ossola. The southern part of this valley is bordered in its whole length by the range of the Apennines, which separates it from the provinces on the sea-coast- This valley is bounded on the part in contact with France by the Cottian Alps.</p><p>The provinces on the sea-shore, comprehending Genoa and Nice, which surround the Gulf of Genoa, are separated from the other parts of the kingdom by the Apennines. They are collectively mountainous districts, which extend to the sea, and have only narrow valleys or strips on the shore, in which marshes, heaths, and sandy tracts of land, yielding but little, and thinly inhabited, are in fact the most cold, dreary, and uncomfortable of any part of the Apennine ranges.</p><p>The soil of Savoy is everywhere stony, and consequently not favourable to agriculture upon a great scale. There are few plains of any extent, the valleys are narrow, and the earth is very thin on the rocks, which, by the force of the mountain torrents, is often washed away, leaving the bare stone. The deposited soil in the great valley which contains Piedmont, Montserrat, and Milan, is in most parts rich and deep, except that at the foot of both the Apennines and the Alps there are vast accumulations of banks of pebbles, to which the practices of agriculture cannot be applied with any profit. The height of the mountains, which enclose the valley, give such force to the streams of water that rush down, as to prevent them from being generally under the direction of human art; but in many instances the water has been turned into channels and canals, where, by the help of sluices, it has been applied beneficially to the purpose of irrigation, and, as far as it has been accomplish, ed, with beneficial effect.</p><p>The provinces on the borders of the Mediterranean Sea have no resemblance to Piedmont, either in respect to the soil, the climate, or the vegetation. The soil is stony and poor, the stones are in enormous blocks, and in a few parts</p><p>only is it adapted for cultivation ; but the olive and the vine are found to flourish.</p><p>In the island of Sardinia the land is generally rather hilly than mountainous. Several ranges of hills intersect the whole land, and two large streams cause in many parts extensive marshes, while the scarcity of water in other parts causes cultivation to be much neglected. The soil is, however, productive, and is capable of becoming, with good management, much more than sufficient for the subsistence of the inhabitants. At present it is said that scarcely one third of the land is cultivated, whereas, if the whole were, it might become, as in the time of the Romans and Carthaginians, a granary for the countries on the Continent.</p><p>The mountains within the Sardinian dominions are objects which excite the greatest interest ; but a description of them will be found in this work under the general article <hi rend="smallcaps">Alps.</hi> The chains of mountains may be viewed as the cisterns for collecting those vast bodies of water which empty themselves into the Mediterranean and Adriatic Seas. The first of these seas receives the waters of the Rhone, which rises in Savoy, and at first forms the boundary towards France.</p><p>The river Var constitutes the boundary between Nice and France ; and the Paglion is a river of short course in the province of Nice, which rises near to Luce, and falls into the sea at a short distance from the capital. The great river of Sardinia, however, is the winding and lengthened Po, of which an account has been given under that head.</p><p>The larger lakes of the Alps belong only in part to this kingdom. The Leman, or lake of Geneva, is divided between Sardinia and the canton of Switzerland, the southern bank of it only belonging to the kingdom. Lake Maggiore has also only its western shores in the Sardinian dominions, the eastern side belonging to the Austro-Venetian kingdom of Lombardy, and the upper part forming a portion of Switzerland. The lakes exclusively Sardinian are of smaller extent than those which are but partly in the kingdom. The lake of Bourget, in Savoy, scarcely exceeds 100,000 acres in extent, but is about 240 feet in depth, and being connected by the Canal of Savières, discharges much water into the Rhone. The lake of Annency, in Savoy, is 1350 feet above the level of the sea, and is 180 feet in depth. It has an outlet by the rivers Thon and Fier into the Rhone. The lake of Orta is a long narrow piece of water by the side of Lake Maggiore, into which its surplus water is discharged. There are some smaller lakes, a few of which are dried up in the summer ; and others of them are on elevations of great height, the most remarkable of which is one on Mont Cenis, 5740 feet above the level of the sea.</p><p>The several states abound in mineral springs of great use to the healing art. In Savoy the sulphureous wells of Bon- neval have attained great celebrity ; but their reputation is excelled by that of the warm baths of Aix. In the valley of Aosta are the medicinal springs of St Vincenzio and of Cor- maggiore, and the baths of Pre and of St Didier. In the province of Piedmont are the baths of Aqui, Balieri, and Vi- nadio, and the springs of St Genesio.</p><p>The mountains on the island are small chains. The most remarkable of them are, Monti di Limbara in Gallura; Monti di Villanova, between Alghieri and Bosa; Monti Genargento, between Oleastra and the Barbagien ; and the Monti Arizzo and Founi, in the Barbagien itself. None of the mountains are of a height to be covered with perpetual snow. The general elevation of the range is from 1000 to 3000 feet ; but the peak of Limbara is 3686 feet, and that of Genargento has an altitude of 5276, and enables the people of the neighbouring town, Aritzu, to trade in snow for the consumption of the capital. These mountains are almost covered with wood to their summits, and the lower parts have olive-woods, yielding good oil.</p><p>The rivers of the island are the Oristano, which rises</p></body></text></TEI>