<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-19T20:10:14Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>this is viewed by the relatives as a deadly injury. They are in general a peaceable and harmless race, prone to intoxication, as most savages are, and immoderately fond of tobacco. Their favourite amusements are wrestling and dancing.</p><p>SAMPANMANGO <hi rend="smallcaps">Cape,</hi> the north-west point of the island of Borneo. Long. 116. 52. E. Lat. 7. 0. N.</p><p>SAMPIT, a town of the island of Borneo, on the south coast, near a river of the same name, 140 miles west of Ban- jar Massam.</p><p>SAMPOO, a small island in the Eastern Seas, near the south coast of Java. Long. 112. 26. E. Lat. 8. 23. S.</p><p>SAMRONGUR, a town of Hindustan, in the district of Ncpaul. It has a large artificial reservoir in the vicinity, which shows the country to have been better cultivated than at present. Long. 85. 30. E. Lat. 26. 45. N.</p><p>SAMSOE, an island belonging to the kingdom of Denmark, in the Cattegat, between Zealand and Jutland. It is forty-five square miles, or 28,800 acres, in extent, and is divided into six parishes, containing 2400 inhabitants. It is of moderate fertility, producing both corn, butter, and cheese, and occupying a part of the people in the fisheries.</p><p>SAMSON, one of the judges of Israel, memorable for his supernatural strength, his victories over the Philistines, and his tragical end, as related in the book of Judges.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Samson’s Post,</hi> a sort of pillar erected in a ship’s hold, between the lower deck and the kelson, under the edge of a hatchway, and furnished with several notches that serve as steps to mount or descend, as occasion requires. This post being firmly driven into its place, not only serves to support the beam and fortify the vessel in that place, but also to prevent the cargo or materials contained in the hold from shifting to the opposite side, by the rolling of the ship in a heavy sea.</p><p>SAMSOON, a port on the southern shore of the Black Sea, to the westward of Trebisond. It contains many well-built houses, seven mosques, one Armenian church, and 500 Ma- hommcdan and 200 Christian families. The vicinity has long been noted for silver and copper mines, two of which, lying between Samsoon and Kabback, and near the river Saracz Gourkhan, are deemed of gτeat antiquity, and are called Malett and Jumbish. They have been recently opened anew. From the earliest times all these districts, to the very margin of the Euxine, have also been famous for workers in iron, and they bear the same reputation now as in ancient times.</p><p>SAMUEL, <hi rend="smallcaps">Boors of,</hi> two canonical books of the Old Testament, being usually ascribed to the prophet Samuel. The books of Samuel and the books of Kings are a continued history of the reigns of the kings of Israel and Judah ; for which reason the books of Samuel are likewise styled the first and second books of Kings. Since the first twenty-four chapters contain all that relates to the history of Samuel, and the latter part of the first book and all the second include the relation of events that happened after the death of that prophet, it has been supposed that Samuel was author only of the first twenty-four chapters, and that the prophets Gad and Nathan finished the work. The first book of Samuel comprehends the transactions under the government of Eli and Samuel, and under Saul, the first king, and also the acts of David whilst he lived under Saul ; and is supposed to contain the space of a hundred and one years. The second book contains the history of about forty years, and is wholly spent in relating the transactions of David’s reign.</p><p>SAMULCOTTA, a town of Hindustan, in the province of the Circars, and district of Rajamundry. Pepper grows wild on the neighbouring hills. It is situatcd on the north bank of a small river, a few miles from the sea. Long. 82. 30. E. Lat. 17. 5. N.</p><p>SAMUR. a river of Persia, in the province of Shirvan,</p><p>which rises in the mountains of Lesghistan, and falls into the Caspian. At its mouth there is a small town of the same name, fifteen miles south of Derbend.</p><p>SAN, a river of China, which rises on the frontier of Tartary, and falls into the Gulf of Leatong. Long. 117. 28. E Lat. 39. 9. N.</p><p>SAN DEL <hi rend="smallcaps">Bose,</hi> an elevated island in the Eastern Seas. Long. 120. 31. E. Lat. 10. 27. S.</p><p>SAN <hi rend="smallcaps">Paloi,</hi> a small island near the west coast of Luzon. Long. 120. 10. E. Lat. 14. 45. N.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">San Juan de Puerto Rico</hi>. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Porto Rico</hi>.</p><p>SAN <hi rend="smallcaps">Lucar de Barrameda,</hi> a city of Spain, in the province of Andalusia. It is a good port, at the entrance of the river Guadalquivir, and the city is built on its eastern bank. The trade of Seville in a great degree centres here, as the larger vessels belonging to that city cannot ascend higher up the river. It is well fortified towards the sea. The country around it is cultivated quite to the shore, and produces rich crops of grapes, olives, and the other fruits of the climate, but little or no corn. It contains 15,200 inhabitants.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">San</hi> SEBASTIAN, a city of Spain, in the province of Gui- puscoa, at the mouth of the river Urumea, which runs from Navarre. Its harbour is excellent, and, as well as the city, is defended by the strong fortress La Mota, which overlooks both ; and it has other powerful fortifications towards the land as well as the sea. It has considerable trade by means of ships of great burden. The mole is a magnificent and well-executed work, as is the lighthouse, which is visible at sea at nine leagues distance. San Sebastian has always been considered, for its extent, the most commercial city of Spain, and its trade is as ancient, as its foundation. The city contains about seven hundred houses, mostly containing two or more families, and the population is 13,100 souls ; but the country around it is thickly studded with country residences, and is well peopled. The land in its neighbourhood is not fertile, but the hills which surround it abound with iron, and are a great source of wealth to the inhabitants. It is in latitude 43. 19. 39. north, and longitude 1. 30. 35. west from London.</p><p>SANA, the capital of the province of Yemen, in Arabia, and the residence of the Imam. It is situated in a barren and stony valley amidst lofty hills, and is surrounded in its immediate vicinity with fine gardens and luxuriant woods. It contains many handsome stone houses, and others substantially built of brick, and is said by Sir Henry Middle- ton to be somewhat larger than Bristol, in space at least, if not in population. It is defended by a strong mud-wall. Fruits are plentiful in the neighbourhood. It is 128 miles north-north-east of Mocha. Long. 44. 9. E. Lat. 15. 21. N.</p><p>SANADON, <hi rend="smallcaps">Noel Ετιεννε,</hi> a Jesuit, and a distinguished professor of humanity at Caen, was born at Rouen in 1676. He there became acquainted with Huet, bishop of Avranches, whose taste for literature and poetry was similar to his own. Sanadon afterwards taught rhetoric at the university of Paris, and upon the death of Du Morceau he was intrusted with the education of the prince of Conti. In 1728 he was made librarian to Louis XIV., an office which he retained to his death, which took place on the 2lst of September 1733, in the fifty-eighth year of his age.</p><p>His works are, 1. Latin Poems, in 12mo, 1715, reprinted by Barbou, in 8vo, 1754. His style possesses the graces of the Augustan age. His language is pure and nervous, his verses are harmonious, and his thoughts are delicate and well chosen, but sometimes his imagination flags. His Latin poems consist of odes, elegies, epigrams, and others, on various subjects. 2. A translation of Horace, with remarks, in two vols. 4to, printed at Paris in 1727. The best edition of this work, however, was printed at Amsterdam in 1735, in eight vols, l2mo, in which are also inserted the versions and notes of M. Dacier. In general, his version</p></body></text></TEI>