<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T20:10:35Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>of blood either in the vaginal coat or ſpermatic cord are to be laid open, and treated as in hydrocele. If bleeding veſſels appear, they are to be ſecured. Sometimes, however, theſe cannot be detected ; an oozing takes place which it is difficult to reſtrain, even by the uſe of bark, vitriolic acid, and other means generally employed in ſuch caſes. It has been uniformly found, that local remedies prove chiefly uſeful here, particularly the application of ardent ſpirits, sether, or tincture of myrrh, to the ſurface of the ſore. Pledgets of ſoft lint, ſoaked in one or other of theſe, not only ſerve to check the diſcharge of blood, but in general tend to promote the formation of good matter.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Chap.</hi> XXV. <hi rend="italic">Of Varicocele, Circocele, Spermatocele, and Pneumatocele.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Varicocele</hi> is a preternatural diſtenſion of the veins of the ſcrotum, which in this ſtate form a tumor of hard, knotty inequalities, ſeldom painful, and generally attended with no inconvenience excepting what ariſes from its bulk. Circocele is ſimilar in its nature to the former, but ſituated in the ſpermatic cord, extending from the abdominal ring to the superior part of the ſcrotum, and produced by a varicoſe ſtate of the ſpermatic vein. Both of theſe diſorders are occaſionally produced by obſtruction in the veins; but are moſt frequently owing to a relaxed ſtate of theſe vessels ; to which we may add, that on account of the ſmallneſs of the corresponding artery, they are not ſufficiently affected by its influence. The tumor produced by theſe diſorders is ſometimes ſo large as to appear like a hernia or hydrocele; but we diſtinguiſh it from theſe by the touch, for varicoſe veins are like worms filled with elaſtic matter. We have another mark upon which we can ſtill more depend : The tumor in the erect poſture of the body is much increaſed, while in the horizontal ſituation it almoſt entirely diſappears.</p><p>Another diſorder is obſerved by late authors, where a collection of blood is ſometimes found within the tunica albuginea teſtis, and is ſuppoſed to be a kind of hæmatocele, er more probably varicocele. Sometimes the collection is ſo conſiderable, that a fluctuation reſembling that of an hydrocele of the vaginal coat of the teſticle is obſervable. When this is miſtaken for hydrocele, and an opening is made into it with a trocar, a diſcharge is produced of a duſky-coloured blood, ſomewhat reſembling thin chocolate : But though the tumor may be diminiſhed by the evacuation thus obtained, yet the alteration is inconſiderable ; nor is the patient ever relieved, but on the contrary made worſe by ſuch an operation. Caſtration, after this, becomes necessary ; but even this has been found ineffectual : ſo that the patient had better be adviſed to truſt to nature, aſſiſted by a proper ſuſpenſory bandage, than to ſuffer the attempt of a radical cure ; for it has been obſerved, that in ſome inſtances they have remained ſtationary for many years, whereas they never fail to become much worſe by any attempt to evacuate the fluid.</p><p>When tumors, er the pressure of a truſs, has been the cauſe of ſuch complaints, a proper attention to theſe ought to be the firſt attempt towards a cure. But when a relaxed ſtate of the veins is ſuſpected, we ought to recommend a ſuſpenſory bandage, an horizontal poſture, the cold bath, and the application of a ſolution of alum and other aſtringents. By a proper exhibition of theſe, the diſeaſe may at leaſt be prevented from increaſing, ſo as to render any operation unneceſſary.</p><p>By ſpermatocele is underſtood a morbid diſtenſion of the vas deferens and epidydimis. The diſeaſe may ariſe from tumors, ſtricture, or inflammation about the vas deferens, or its termination in the penis ; but more probably from inflammation there. When an inflammatory dispoſition is diſcovered, general and topical blood letting, gentle laxatives, a low cooling diet, and reſt of body, will commonly be found the best remedies. When tumors are found to preſs upon the vas deferens, they ought either to be brought to a ſtate of ſuppuration, or entirely extirpated, if that can be properly effected. If the diſeaſe proceed from a venereal cauſe, nothing can be ſo uſeful as a courſe of mercury properly directed.</p><p>By pneumatocele is underſtood a diſtenſion of the ſcrotum from a collection of air.</p><p>The principal cauſe of this diſeaſe, which rarely happens, is wounds in the lungs, by which air passes through the common cellular ſubſtance into the ſcrotum ; but from whatever cauſe the tumor is produced, the diſeaſe is to be treated by making ſmall punctures with the point of a lancet, as in the case of anaſarcous ſwellings formed by water.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Chap.</hi> XXVI. <hi rend="italic">Of Sarcocele, or Scirrhous Testicle.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sarcocele</hi> implies a fleſhy, enlarged ſtate of the testicle, much firmer and harder to the touch than is obſerved in hernia humeralis or inflamed teſticle.</p><p>The ſymptoms vary exceedingly in different patients ; but the following are the moſt general : The firſt symptom is commonly a ſmall enlargement, without much pain, and no diſcoloration of the part. The tumor becomes gradually larger, and the hardneſs increaſes; but for a considerable time the ſurface remains ſmooth ; and when the conſtitution is otherwiſe good, the diſorder will ſometimes remain in this ſituation for a conſiderable number of years ; and in a few rare inſtances, by a moderate diet, keeping the belly open, ſuſpending the tumor properly, and avoiding violent exerciſe, or any thing which may conſiderably increaſe the impetus of the blood, the diſorder has not only been prevented from increaſing, but has in a gradual manner diſappeared entirely. More commonly, however, the tumor increaſes in ſize, and becomes ragged and unequal on its ſurface. Smart and ſevere ſhooting pains are frequently felt through its ſubſtance. Sometimes ſerum is extravaſated in the vaginal coat, or matter is collected in different parts of the tumor. The ſcrotum, now much distended, burſts, and thin, fetid, bloody matter diſcharging, the diſeaſe terminates in an ulcerated cancer of the worſt kind.</p><p>The ſpermatic cord is commonly unaffected till the tumor has acquired a conſiderable ſize, and generally not till collections of matter have been formed. After this, from being at firſt only ſlightly ſwelled, it gradually increaſes in hardneſs and bulk ; after which it becomes very painful, knotty, or unequal through its whole extent. The diſcharge from the ſcrotum ſtill continues ; but although the matter increaſes in quantity, the ſize of the tumor is not thereby diminiſhed, but, on the contrary, continually increaſes ; the edges of the ſore become hard, livid, and retorted, and fungous excreſcences puſh out from every part of it ; the health of the patient becomes entirely deſtroyed, and he is at laſt carried off in great miſery.</p><p>Hernia humeralis produced by venereal infection has been conſidered, by ſome authors, as a frequent cauſe of the worſt kind of ſcirrhous teſticle ; but the fact is very much otherwiſe ; and ſuch an idea has this bad tendency, that it prevents the perſeverance in the uſe of ſuch remedies as might have removed the diſeaſe without the neceſſity of extirpation.</p><p>Another cauſe mentioned by authors as producing</p></body></text></TEI>