<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T20:12:50Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>der of brothers. Sylla ordered 8000 wretches, who had thrown themſelves upon his clemency, to be butchered in the Campus Martius. In the mean time he entered the ſenate-houſe, and began to talk with great coolneſs about his exploits. The ſenate, alarmed at the horrid outcries of the ſufferers, at firſt thought that the city was given up to be plundered; but Sylla informed them, with an unembarraſſed air, that it was only ſome criminals puniſhing by his orders, and that they needed not be apprehenſive about their own fate.</p><p>To carry on theſe cruelties with the appearance of juſtice, he commanded the people to elect him dictator. He kept this office for more than two years ; and then, to the amazement of all, laid it down, and offered to ſtand his trial before the people. Soon afterwards he retired into the country, and plunged headlong into every kind of debauchery. Nor did he relinquiſh his cruelty together with his power : His wife falling ill in the midſt of a sumptuous feaſt, he divorced her immediately ; and ordered her to be carried away, lest her death ſhould interrupt the feſtivity of his houſe.</p><p>He died of the morbus pedicularis, in the doth year of his age. His body, according to his orders, was burnt. A little before his death he wrote his epitaph ; the tenor of which was, that no man had ever exceeded him in doing good to his friends or injury to his enemies.</p><p>His perſon was elegant, his air noble, his manners easy and apparently ſincere. He was fond of pleaſure, but fonder of glory ; indulging without ſcruple in ſensual delights, but never ſuffering them to interrupt his serious buſineſs : He was eloquent, liberal, crafty, insinuating ; a profound maſter of diſſimulation ; he ſpoke of himſelf with modeſty, while he laviſhed praiſes on every other perſon : He ſtooped even to an acquaintance with the meaneſt ſoldier, and conſtantly adapted himſelf to the humours, purſuits, and opinions, of those with whom he converſed. Such was his character during the earlier part of his life ; but when succeſs had raiſed him above the neceſſity of diſſimulation, he diſobyed a hideous train of vices, which his ambition had formerly taught him to conceal.—It was Sylla who recovered the works of Ariſtotle at the taking of Athens.</p><p>SYLLABLE, in grammar, one or more letters pronounced by a ſingle impulſe of the voice, forming a complete ſound, and conſtituting a word or a part of a word. No ſingle letter can form a ſyllable except a vowel. The longeſt ſyllable in the Engliſh language is the word st<hi rend="italic">rength.</hi></p><p>The moſt natural way of dividing words into ſyllables is, to ſeparate all the ſimple sounds of which any word conſiſts, ſo as not to divide thoſe letters which are joined cloſe together according to the moſt accurate pronunciation.</p><p>SYLLABUB, a kind of compound drink, moſt uſual in the ſummer ſeaſon ; ordinarily made of white wine and ſugar, into which is ſquirted new milk with a ſyringe or wooden cow. Sometimes it is made of canary in lieu of white wine ; in which caſe the ſugar is ſpared, and a little lemon and nutmeg are added in lieu of it. To prepare it the beſt way, the wine and other ingredients, except the milk, are to be mixed over night, and the milk or cream added in the morning. The proportion is, a pint of wine to three of milk. For</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Syllabub, </hi><hi rend="italic">whipt,</hi> to half a pint oſ white wine or Rheniſh is put a pint of cream, with the whites of three eggs. This they ſeaſon with ſugar, and beat with birchen rods, or work with a ſyringe. The froth is taken off as it riſes, and put into a pot ; where, after standing to settle two or three hours, it is fit to eat.</p><p>SYLLABUS, in matters of literature, denotes a table of contents, or an index of the chief heads of a book or diſcourſe.</p><p>SYLLOGISM, in logic, an argument or term of reasoning, conſiſting of three propositions ; the two firſt of which are called premises ; the laſt, the <hi rend="italic">conclusion.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Logic,</hi> Part III.</p><p>SYLVIA, in natural hiſtory, a new genus of birds, belonging to the order of passeres, formed by Dr Latham by limiting the motacilla to the wagtail, and arranging·; the other ſpecies, formerly claſſed under that genus, under the ſylvia.</p><p>The motacilla he thus describes : The beak is ſubulated, ſlender, and ſomewhat indented at the point. The tongue ſeems torn at the end, and the tail is long. He thus characterizes the ſylvia : ſhe beak is ſubulated, ſtraight, and ſmall ; the mandibles are nearly equal. The noſtrils are obovate, and a little depressed. The exterior toe is joined at the under part to the baſe of the middle one. The tounge is cloven, and the tail is small. He makes 13 ſpecies of the motacilla, and 174 ſpecies oſ the ſylvia. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Motacilla.</hi></p><p>SYMBOL, a ſign or repreſentation of ſomething moral, by the figures or properties of natural things. Hence ſymbols are or various kinds ; as hieroglyphics, types, enigmas, parables, fables, &amp;c.</p><p>SYMMACHUS, a citizen and ſenator of ancient Rome, and conſul in the year 391, has left us ten books of epiſtles ; from which, as well as from other things, we collect, that he was a warm oppoſer of the Chriſtian religion. He was baniſhed from Rome by Valentinian on ſome account or other, but afterwards recalled and received into favour by Theodosius Ammianus Marcellinus speaks of him as a man of great learning and modeſty. Scioppius, Parens, and other learned men, have written notes upon the epiſtles of Symmachus : we know of no later edition of them than that of Frankfort, 164.2, 8vo. Ambroſe biſhop of Milan wrote againſt Symmachus, and ſo did the Chriſtian poet, Prudentius.</p><p>SYMMETRY, the juſt proportion of the ſeveral parts of any thing, ſo as to compoſe a beautiful whole.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Symmetry,</hi> in painting. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Painting,</hi> Part I. Sect. III.</p><p>SYMONDSBOROUGH, a remarkable large barrow of Flints, near Wellington in Devonſhire, in the northern extremity of Hemyock. The common people have a notion that a king called <hi rend="italic">Symon</hi> was buried here. The tradition of the country plainly ſhows that it was the burial-place of ſome person or perſons of eminence.</p><p>SYMPATHETIC, ſomething that acts or is acted upon by ſympathy. Thus we lay, ſympathetic diseaſes, inks, &amp;c.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sympathetic</hi><hi rend="italic"> Inks.</hi> See <hi rend="italic">Sympathetic </hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Ink.</hi></p><p>SYMPATHY, an agreement of affections and inclinations, or a conformity of natural qualities, humours, temperaments, which make two perſons delighted and pleated with each other.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sympathy,</hi> alſo denotes the quality of being affected by the affection of another ; and may ſubſist either between different perſons or bodies, or between different parts of the ſame body. It is either ſimilar or diſſimilar ; ſimilar, when the affection or action in the ſympathiſer is ſimilar to the affection or action in the ſympathant ; and diſſimilar, when thoſe are different.—Sympathy, too, is often an imitative faculty, ſometimes involuntary, frequently without conſciouſneſs : thus we yawn when we see others yawn, and are made to laugh by the laughing of another.</p><p>Sympathy, according to Dr Jackſon @@*, relates to the operations of the affections of the mind, to the operations of the imagination, and to the affections of the external ſenſes.</p><p>I.	The paſſions and affections of the mind produce in the body different ſenſations and impressions, and, as ſympathies</p><p>@@@[m]* Treatise on Sympathy</p></body></text></TEI>