<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T20:11:49Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>post : but he did not long ſurvive him, for he died in 1682. Gaubius gave a tranſlation of all his works from the original Dutch into Latin, from which they were tranſlated into Engliſh, in folio, in 1758. The celebrated Boerhaave wrote his life.</p><p>SWAN, in ornithology. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Anas.</hi></p><p>SWANPAN, or Chineſe <hi rend="smallcaps">Abacus ; </hi>an inſtrument for performing arithmetical operations, deſcribed by Du Halde in his Hiſtory of China.</p><p>It is compoſed of a ſmall board, crossed with 10 or 12 parallel rods or wires, each ſtrung with ivory balls, which are ſo divided by a partition in the middle, that two are on one side of it, and five on the other. The two in the upper part ſtand each for five units, and each of the five in the lower part for one. “ In joining and ſeparating theſe balls, they reckon much as we do with counters ; but, according to our author, more expeditiouſly than Europeans do even with figures.” This is hardly credible ; but if all the Chineſe weights and meaſures be decimally divided, as by his very lame deſcription of the <hi rend="italic">ſwanpan</hi> they would appear to be, it is easy to conceive how computation may be made by this inſtrument very expeditiouſly. The infiniment, too, may be ſo contrived as to suit any diviſion of weights and meaſures, and in that form be useful to the blind ; but as we have elſewhere given deſcriptions of ſuperior inſtruments, for their accommodation (ſee <hi rend="smallcaps">Blind)</hi> it is needleſs to offer in this place any improvement of the s<hi rend="italic">wan- pan.</hi></p><p>SWANEMOTE, <hi rend="smallcaps">Swainmote,</hi> or <hi rend="smallcaps">Sweinmote.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Forest-C</hi>ourts<hi rend="italic">.</hi></p><p>SWEARING. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Oath.</hi></p><p>SWEAT, a ſenſible moiſture iſſuing from the pores of the ſkins of living animals.</p><p>The exceſs of it dries and weakens the body, deprives the humours of their watery parts, and induces the blood to an inflammatory and atrabiliary diſposition. A hidden ſuppreſſion of it will equally hurt as well as a ſuppreſſion of perspiration.</p><p>SWEATING <hi rend="smallcaps">sickness,</hi> a diſorder which appeared in England about the year 1481, and was by foreigners called the <hi rend="italic">English ſweat.</hi> It returned again in 1485 ; then in 1506 ; aſterwards in 1517. It appeared again in 1528, or 1529, at which time alone it ſpread itſelf to the Netherlands and Germany : a circumſtance which shows the impropriety of calling it <hi rend="italic">the Engliſh ſweat,</hi> in Latin s<hi rend="italic">udοr Anglicanus ;</hi> beſides, Sennertus takes notice, that it ſpread as far as Denmark, Norway, and France. It raged again in 1548. And the laſt return of it in London was in 1551, when it was ſo violent as in one day to take off 120 of the inhabitants of Weſtminſter. Some were ſeized abroad, and cut off in the road, others at home. Some when awake, others when faſt aſleep. Some died in a moment, and others in one, two, three, four, or more hours after they began to ſweat.</p><p>SWEDEN, one of the moſt northerly kingdoms of Europe, lying between Lat. 55. 20. and 69. 30. north, and between 12⁰ and 32⁰ eaſt from London. On the ſouth it is bounded by the Baltic, on the north by Danish Lapland, on the eaſt by Muſcovy, and on the weſt by the mountains of of Norway, being 800 miles in length and 350 in breadth.</p><p>The early hiſtory of Sweden is no leſs involved in lables than that of moſt other nations. Some hiſtorians have pretended to give regular catalogues of the princes who reigned in Sweden in very early times ; but they differ ſo much among themſelves, that no credit can be given to them. However, all agree that ancient Scandinavia was first governed by judges elected for a certain time by the voice of the people. Among theſe temporary princes the country was divided, until, in the year of the world 2054, according to ſome, or 1951, according to others, Eric, or, if we believe Puffendorf, Suenon was raiſed to the ſupreme power, with the prerogatives of all the temporary magiſtrates united in his perſon for life, or until his conduct ſhould merit depoſition.</p><p>From this very early period till the year 1366 of the Chriſtian era, the hiſtories of Sweden preſent us with nothing but what is common to all nations in their early periods, viz. the endleſs combats and massacres of barbarians, tending to no other purpoſe than the effuſion of blood. At the time juſt mentioned, however, Albert of Mecklenburg, having concluded a peace between Sweden and Denmark, which two kingdoms had been at violent war for ſome time before, was proclaimed king of Sweden. The peace was of ſhort duration, being broken in 1368; on which Albert entered into an offenſive and defenſive league with the earl of Holſtein, the Jutland nobility, the dukes of Selfwick, Mecklenburg, and the Hanſe-towns, againſt the kings of Denmark and Norway. Albert proved very ſucceſsful againſt Waldemar king of Denmark at that time, driving him entirely out of his dominions ; but he himſelf was defeated by the king of Norway, who laid ſiege to his capital. Soon after this, a new treaty of peace was concluded, by which Albert was allowed to enjoy the crown of Sweden in peace. However, having formed a deſign of rendering himſelf abſolute, he fell under the diſpleaſure of his ſubjects, and Margaret of Norway was proclaimed queen of Sweden by the malecontents. A war immediately enſued, in which Albert was defeated and taken priſoner ; but as the princes of Mecklenburg, the earls of Holſtein, and the Hanse towns, entered into a league in his favour, the war was ſo far from being extinguiſhed by this event, that it raged with more fury than ever.</p><p>At length, in 1394, the contending parties came to an accommodation. Albert was ſet at liberty, on condition that he ſhould in three years ſurrender to Margaret all pretenſions to the city of Stockholm; and the Hanſe-towns engaged to pay the ſum of 60,000 marks of ſilver in caſe of Albert’s breach of faith. Not long after this, Eric the ſon of Albert died ; and he, having no other child, did not think it worth his while to contend for the kingdom of Sweden : he therefore acquieſced in the pretenſions of Margaret, and passed the remainder of his days at Mecklenburg.</p><p>Margaret died in 1415, and was ſucceeded by Eric of Pomerania. This prince’s reign was cruel and oppreſſive to the laſt degree. The people were ruined by taxes ; and the Danes being every where preferred to the offices of power, committed the greateſt cruelties. The conſequence of this was a revolt ; and Charles Canutſon, grand mareſchal of Sweden and governor of Finland, having joined the malecontents, was declared commander in chief of their army. Eric was now formally depoſed, and commenced pirate : Canutſon was choſen regent : but beginning to oppreſs the people, and aſpiring openly at the crown, the Swedes and Danes revolted ; in conſequence of which a revolution took place, and Chriſtopher duke of Bavaria, nephew to Eric, was choſen king of Denmark, Sweden, and Norway, in 1442.</p><p>On the accession of the new prince, complaints againſt Canutſon were brought from all quarters; but, through the intereſt of his ſriends, he eſcaped the puniſhment due to him ; and in 1448, Chriſtopher having died after a tyrannical reign or ſomewhat more than five years, he was raised to the throne at which he had ſo long aſpired. However, the kingdoms of Denmark and Norway refuſed to own allegiance to him ; upon which a war immediately commenced.</p></body></text></TEI>