<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T20:12:55Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>curs, equal to that which occaſioned the driving, to make the number even, <hi rend="italic">e. gr.</hi> when an odd crotchet comes before two or three minims, or an odd quaver before two, three, or more crotchets. In ſyncopated or driving notes, the hand or foot is taken up, or put down, while the note is ſounding.</p><p>SYNCOPE, <hi rend="smallcaps">fainting ; </hi>a deep and ſudden ſwooning, wherein the patient continues without any ſenſible heat, motion, ſenſe, or reſpiration, and is ſeized with a cold ſweat over the whole body; all the parts, in the mean time, turning pale and cold, as if he was dead. Sec <hi rend="smallcaps">Medicine,</hi> n⁰ 98. and 272.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Syncope,</hi> in grammar, an eliſion or retrenchment of a letter or syllable out of the middle of a word, as <hi rend="italic">caldus</hi> for <hi rend="italic">calidus.</hi></p><p>SYNDIC, in government and commerce, an officer, in divers countries, intruſted with the affairs of a city or other community, who calls meetings, makes repreſentations and ſolicitations to the miniſtry, magiſtracy, &amp;c. according to the exigency of the caſe.</p><p>SYNECDOCHE, in rhetoric, a kind of trope frequent among orators and poets. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Oratory,</hi> n⁰ 56.</p><p>SYNECPHONESIS, in grammar, a coalition, whereby two ſyllables arc pronounced as one ; being much the same as <hi rend="smallcaps">Synaloepha</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Synæresis.</hi></p><p>SYNEUROSIS. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Anatomy,</hi> n⁰ 2.</p><p>SYNGENESIA, (συν and γενεσιϛ, “ congeneration),” thc name of the 19th claſs in Linnæus’s artificial ſyſtem ; comprehending thoſe plants which have the anthers united into a cylinder. The orders are six : I. Polygamia æqualis.</p><p>2.	Polygamia ſuperflua. 1. Polygamia fruſtranea. 4. Polygamia necessaria. 5. Polygamia ſegregata. 6. Monogamia. The five firſt orders contain the compound flowers, and form a claſs truly natural.</p><p>SYNGNATHUS, <hi rend="smallcaps">Pipe-fish,</hi> according to Linnaeus, a genus belonging to the claſs of <hi rend="italic">amphibia,</hi> and order of <hi rend="italic">nantes,</hi> but arranged by Gmelin more properly under the claſs of <hi rend="italic">pisces,</hi> and order of <hi rend="italic">branchiostegi.</hi> The head is ſmall ; the roſtrum ſomewhat cylindrical, long, and turned up at the point, where the mouth is placed, which is covered with a lid or valve. The gills are covered in the ſame manner. The body is covered with a ſtrong cruſt, and has no ventral fins. There are eight ſpecies ; the tetragonus, typhele, acus, pelagicus, æquoreus, ophidion, barbarus, and hippocampus. Three of theſe are found in the Britiſh ſeas, viz.</p><p>1.	The <hi rend="italic">barbarus,</hi> or longer pipe fiſh. One deſcribed by Sir Robert Sibbald, was two feet in length ; that examined by Mr Pennant only 16 inches. The noſe was an inch long, compreſſed ſidewise, and the end of the lower mandible turned up ; the aperture of the mouth was very ſmall. The irides were red ; behind each eye was a deep brown line. The body, in the thickeſt part, was about equal to a ſwan’s quill, hexangular from the end of the dorſal fin ; from thence to the tail, quadrangular. The belly was slightly carinated, and marked along the middle with a duſky line. Under the tail, commencing at the anus, is a fulcus or groove six inches and a half long, covered by two longitudinal valves, which concealed a multitude of young fiſh. On crushing this part, hundreds may be obſerved to crawl out</p><p>2.	The <hi rend="italic">acus,</hi> or ſhorter pipe-fiſh, is thicker than the former, yet it has been ſeen of the length of 16 inches. The middle of the body in ſome is hexangular, in others heptangular. The mouth is formed like that of the former : the irides are yellow ; cloſe behind the head are the pectoral fins, which are ſmall and ſhort. On the lower part of the back is one narrow fin ; beyond the vent the tail commences, which is long and quadrangular. At the extremity is a fin round and radiated. The body is covered with a ſtrong cruſt, elegantly divided into ſmall compartments. The belly is white ; the other parts are brown.</p><p>3.	The <hi rend="italic">ophidian,</hi> or little pipe-fiſh, ſeldom exceeds five inches in length, is very ſlender, and tapers off to a point. It wants both the pectoral and tail fins ; is covered with a ſmooth ſkin, not with a cruſt as the two former kinds are. The noſe is ſhort, and turns a little up ; the eyes are prominent. On the back is one narrow fin. This ſpecies is not viviparous : on the belly of the female is a long hollow, to which adhere the eggs, diſpoſed in two or three rows. They are large, and not numerous. The ſynonym of <hi rend="italic">ſerpent</hi> is uſed in ſeveral languages to expreſs theſe fiſh : the French call one ſpecies <hi rend="italic">orueul,</hi> from a sort of ſnake not unlike the blind worm : the Germans call it <hi rend="italic">meherschlange</hi> ; and the Corniſh the s<hi rend="italic">ea-adder.</hi></p><p>The Sea-horſe, which was claſſed by Artedi under the Syngnathus, is now, by later ichthyologiſts, arranged under <hi rend="smallcaps">Trichecus</hi> ; which ſee.</p><p>SYNOCHA, and <hi rend="smallcaps">Synochus,</hi> in medicine, the names of two ſpecies of continued fever. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Medicine,</hi> n⁰ 164.</p><p>SYNOD, in aſtronomy, a conjunction or concourſe of two or more ſtars or planets, in the ſame optical place of the heavens.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Synod</hi> ſignifies alſo a meeting or aſſembly of eccleſiaſtical perſons to conſult on matters of religion.</p><p>Of theſe there are four kinds, viz. 1. <hi rend="italic">General,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">oecumenical, </hi>where biſhops, &amp;c. meet from all nations. Theſe were firſt called by the emperors, afterwards by Chriſtian princes; till in later ages the pope uſurped to himſelf the greateſt ſhare in this busineſs, and by his legates preſided in them when called. 2. <hi rend="italic">National,</hi> where thoſe of one nation only come together, to determine any point of doctrine or discipline. The firſt of this sort which we read of in England, was that of Herudford or Hertford, in 673, and the laſt was that held by cardinal Pole, in 1555.	3. <hi rend="italic">Provincial, </hi>where thoſe only of one province meet, now called the <hi rend="italic">convocation.</hi> 4. <hi rend="italic">Dioceſan,</hi> where thoſe of but one dioceſe meet, to enforce canons made by general councils, or national and provincial <hi rend="italic">ſynods,</hi> and to consult and agree upon rules of discipline for themſelves. Theſe were not wholly laid aſide, till by the act of ſubmission, 25 Hen. VIII. c. 19. it was made unlawful for any <hi rend="italic">ſynod</hi> to meet, but by royal authority, See <hi rend="smallcaps">Council</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Convocation.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Synods, </hi><hi rend="italic">Provincial, in the Government of the Church of Scotland.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Presbyterians,</hi> n⁰ 14.</p><p>SYNODALS, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Synodies,</hi> were pecuniary rents (commonly of two ſhillings), paid to the biſhop, or archdeacon, at the time of their Eaſter viſitation, by every pariſh prieſt. They were thus called, becauſe uſually paid in ſynods ; becauſe anciently biſhops uſed to viſit and hold their dioceſam ſynods once.—For the ſame reaſon, they are ſometimes alſo denominated <hi rend="italic">ſynodalica</hi> ; but more uſually, <hi rend="italic">procurations.</hi></p><p>SYNODICAL, ſomething belonging to a ſynod. Thus, ſynodical epiſtles are circular letters written by the ſynods to the abſent prelates and churches ; or even theſe general ones directed to all the faithful, to inform them of what had passed in the ſynod.</p><p>SYNOECIA, in Grecian antiquity, a feaſt celebrated at Athens in memory of Theſeus’s having united all the petty communities of Attica into one single commonwealth ; the ſeat whereof was at Athens, where all the aſſemblies were to be held. This feaſt was dedicated to Minerva ; and, according to the ſcholiaſt on Thucydides, it was held in the month <hi rend="italic">Metagitnion.</hi></p><p>SYNONYMOUS, is applied to a word or term that has the ſame import or signification with another.</p></body></text></TEI>