<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T20:13:05Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>of it which was neareſt to Epipolæ, and which was ill guarded. He preſently after posseſſed himſelf of Epipolæ ; whereupon the inhabitants of Neapolis, as well as Tyche, ſent deputies to him, and ſubmitted. Marcellus granted life and liberty to all of free condition, but gave up thoſe quarters of the city to be plundered.</p><p>“ Notwithſtanding this, there was a great deal yet to do. Acradina and Ortygia, which were ſtrongly fortified, ſtill held out ; Hippocrates and Himilco arrived with their troops to the relief of the besieged ; and the Romans were forced to exert all their bravery and ſkill to maintain the advantages they had gained.</p><p>“ But now a plaque made terrible havock in both armies. At the firſt breaking out of the peſtilence, the Sicilians, who ſerved under Hippocrates and Himilco, diſbanded themſelves, and returned to their reſpective homes ; but all the Carthaginian ſoldiers periſhed, together with thoſe two generals. The Romans ſuffered leſs by the infection ; becauſe, having been a long time before Syracuſe, they were seaſoned to the air and water of the country.</p><p>“ About this time Bomilcar arrived on<hi rend="smallcaps">.</hi> the coaſt of Sicily from Carthage, with a fleet of 130 galleys and 700 ſhips of burden ; but was long hindered by contrary winds from doubling the cape of Pachynum. Epicydes, fearing the Carthaginian might sail back to Africa, left the command of Acradina to the generals of the mercenaries, and went to Bomilcar, in order to perſuade him to fight the Roman fleet. The admiral would not engage, but sailed away to Tarentum with all his galleys, ordering his ſhips of burden to return to Africa. Epicydes, thus fruſtrated of his hopes, and knowing himſelf unable to defend a city already half taken, retired to Agrigentum ; whereupon the Syracuſians maſſacred the commanders appointed by him, choſe new praetors to govern in the town, and ſent deputies to Marcellus to treat of peace. In the mean time, the deſerters, fearing to be given up to the vengeance of the Romans, perſuaded the mercenaries that they alſo would have the ſame fate, inſtantly the ſoldiers ran to arms, put to death the new prætors, together with many of the Syracuſians, and plundered part of the city. After this slaughter they choſe six generals, three to command in Acradina, and three in Ortygia. Upon the return of the deputies from Marcellus, the mercenaries finding that their caſe was different from that of the deſerters, and that there was no deſign againſt their lives, became perfectly satisfied, and the negotiation went on. During the courſe of the treaty, Marcellus found means to corrupt Mericus, a Spaniard, one of the six generals choſen by the ſoldiers, and engaged him to admit the Romans into that part of the city where he commanded. Mericus, the better to accompliſh this deſign, feigned an extraordinary zeal for the preſervation of that place ; pretended not to like that deputies ſhould have leave to go out and in at pleaſure ; and propoſed, that for the greater ſecurity of the town, each general ſhould have a diſtinct quarter aſſigned him, and be reſponſible for any neglect of duty in it. The motion was agreed to ; and upon the diviſion, that diſtrict of Ortygia which extended from the fountain of Arethuſa to the mouth of the great port fell to his care. Marcellus, informed of what was done, took his meaſures accordingly. He ſent a body of troops to that side where Mericus commanded, and the Spaniards admitted them at the gate of Arethuſa. At the ſame time, the proconſul ordered a falſe attack to be made on Acradina ; which drawing almoſt all the ſoldiers of the garriſon thither, Ortygia was in a manner left defenceleſs. Foreseing this, he had detached another party of ſoldiers to take advantage of it. Theſe entered Ortygia almoſt without fighting ; upon which the deſerters made their eſcape, the Romans giving them way ; and the Syracuſians in Acradina, thus delivered from the fear of the deſerters, immediately opened their gates to Marcellus, who thereby became master of the whole city.</p><p>“ And now the conqueror, who is ſaid to have wept during the ſiege with compaſſion for the inhabitants, gave up both Ortygia and Acradina to be plundered by his army, after he had ſecured the late king’s treasures for the uſe of his republic, and the ſtatues, paintings, and principal ornaments of Syracuſe to illuſtrate his triumph. The soldiers had orders to ſpare the lives of the citizens ; but they were cruel in their avarice, slew many of them, and among the reſt the incomparable Archimedes. He was very intent on a demonſtration in geometry, and calmly drawing his lines, when a ſoldier entered the room, and clapped a ſword to his throat. “ Hold ! (ſaid Archimedes) one moment, and my demonſtration will be finished." But the ſoldier, equally regardleſs of his prayer and his de- demonstration, killed him iniſtantly. There are different accounts of the manner of his death ; but all agree that Marcellus regretted it extremely, and ſhowed a ſingular favour to his relations for his ſake.”</p><p>The city of Syracuſe continued ſubject to the weſtern empire till its declenſion, when the iſtand of Sicily ; being ravaged by different barbarians, the capital alſo underwent various revolutions ; till at laſt, in the 9th century, it was ſo deſtroyed by the Saracens, that very few traces of its ancient grandeur are now to be ſeen. “ The ancient city of Syracuſe was of a triangular form, and conſiſted of five parts or towns. The circuit, according to Strabo, amounted to 180 ſtadia, or 22 Engliſh miles, and four furlongs. An account (says Mr Swinburne) which I once ſuſpected of exaggeration ; but, after spending two days in tracing the ruins, and making reasonable allowances for the encroachments of the ſea, I was convinced of the exactneſs of his meaſurement.</p><p>“ At preſent it is ſtrongly fortified towards the land, and the ditches of the bastions form the communications between the two havens. It is very weak towards the ſea, but the ſhelves render it hazardous to debark on that side. The garriſon is one oſ the beſt appointed in the kingdom, but the heights of Acradina command the works.</p><p>About eighteen thousand inhabitants are now contained in it. The dwellings are far from being memorials of ancient Syracuſan architecture or opulence. In any other ſituation they might be thought tolerable ; but to obſervers who reflect on the ſtyle of thoſe buildings that probably once covered the ſame ground, the preſent edifices muſt have a mean appearance. The ancient temple of Minerva is now turned into a cathedral. The walls of the cella are thrown down, and only as much left in pillars as is neceſſary to ſupport the roof ; the intercolumniations of the peryſtile are walled up. This temple is built in the old Doric proportions uſed in the reſt of Sicily ; its exterior dimenſions are 185 feet in length and 75 in breadth. There are alſo some remains of Diana’s temple, but now ſcarcely diſcernible. Besides theſe, there are few ruins in the iſland ; and one is ſurpriſed that any ſhould exiſt in a place which has been ſo often laid waſte by enemies, and ſo often ſhaken by earthquakes.</p><p>“ Every object here imprints a melancholy ſenſation on the mind, while it draws a compariſon between the preſent humble ſtate of things and their once flourishing condition. The ancients have left pompous descriptions of the traffic carried on in this well ſituated port, the almoſt incredible wealth poſſeſſed by its citizens, and the ſplendid edifices upon which they laviſhed a great part of their riches. I had already viewed (says Mr Swinburne) the deſert sites</p></body></text></TEI>