<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T20:13:01Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>arms, Having then embarked in two ſmall trading vessels, they arrived in 12 days at Cape Pachynum near Syracuſe. Their pilot adviſed them to land immediately, left they ſhould be overtaken by a violent ſtorm, which he perceived was approaching ; but Dion, judging it improper to land ſo near the enemy, commanded him to put to ſea again, and double the Cape. — This was no ſooner done than the ſtorm came on ; and the two vessels were driven on the coaſt of Africa, where they were in great danger of being loſt. At laſt they arrived at the port of Minoa, not far from Agrigentum. Here they received intelligence that Dionyſius had ſet sail for Italy, attended by a fleet of 80 galleys. On this Dion reſolved to take advantage of the tyrant’s abſence ; and immediately set sail for Syracuſe. On his march he prevailed upon the inhabitants of Agrigentum, Gela,  Camarina, and other cities, to join him. As ſoon as he entered the territories of Syracuſe, multitudes flocked to him ; and as nobody appeared to oppose him, he boldly entered the city, where he quickly found himſelf at the head of 50,000 men. As ſoon as he had landed in Sicily, Timocrates, to whom his wife Arete had been given by Dionyſius, and to whom the care of the city had been left, dispatched a courier to let the tyrant know the danger in which he was. The messenger, when almoſt at his journey’s end, found himſelf ſo much oppressed by fatigue, that he could not help lying down on the ground to take ſome reſt. In the mean time, a wolf, ſmelling ſome meat which he had in his wallet, came to the place, and carried off the bag in which was the meat, together with the diſpatches. By this means Dionyſius was prevented from receiving a timely account of Dion’s arrival ; ſo that when he entered the citadel by ſea, seven days after Dion’s arrival, he found his affairs in a desperate ſituation. Upon this he had recourſe to artifice ; and having amuſed the Syracuſians by a feigned negotiation, until he obſerved that they kept a negligent guard, he attacked them all at once with ſuch fury, that he had almoſt taken the city. But Dion encouraged the ſoldiers by his example ſo much, that he at laſt obtained a complete victory ; for which they preſented him with a crown of gold.</p><p>It was not long, however, before the ungrateful Syracuſians began to think of conferring quite different rewards on their benefactor. Dionyſius had the addrefs to render him ſuſpected by the multitude ; at the ſame time that Heraclides, an excellent officer, but a ſecret enemy to Dion, did all that lay in his power to ſink his credit. In a ſhort time Dionyſius was obliged to fly into Italy : after which Heraclides, in order to ingratiate himſelf with the populace, propoſed a new division of lands ; inſinuating, that they could never enjoy perfect liberty as long as there was so much inequality in wealth and power among the citizens. This ſcheme was oppoſed by Dion, in conſequence of which a general combination was formed againſt him ; and he was deſerted by all excepting the foreign troops whom he had brought with him into the iſland. The Syracuſians ſolicited even theſe to abandon the cauſe of their general : but their offers were rejected with diſdain ; and Dion, with his faithful adherents, getting clear of the tumultuous and riotous populace, took the road to Leontini. The rabble pursued him, but were ſoon driven back : and Dion reſided for ſome time at Leontini, where he was received with all the reſpect due to his character.</p><p>In the mean time, the citadel ſtill continued in the hands of the adherents of Dionyſius. Being blocked up on all ſides, they were reduced to great ſtraits, and were actually making proposals of capitulation, when Nypſius, an experienced general, and greatly attached to Dionyſius, appeared with a numerous ſquadron of galleys, and a large fleet of tranſports laden with proviſions. The general landed his men, and got them into the citadel ; but almoſt all his galleys and ſhips laden with corn were ſunk or taken. This victory proved the ruin of the Syracuſians ; for, giving themſelves up to feaſting and debauchery, the enemy sallied out in the night time from the citadel, and maſſacred the citizens without mercy. Being thus made ſenſible of the error they had committed, an embaſſy was sent to Dion, intreating him to return and lave the city a second time. To this he agreed without heſitation, and inſtantly ſet out on his march ; but in the mean time, as the ſoldiers of Dionyſius, ſatiated with ſlaughter, had retired into their fortreſs, the ungrateful Syracuſians began to repent of their having ſent an embaſſy to Dion. The chief commanders, therefore, ſent meſſengers to ſtop his march ; but as ſome of his friends ſent deputies to him at the ſame time, deſiring him to pay no regard to the former meſſage, he proceeded on his journey. The infatuated multitude ſeized the gates in order to diſpute his entrance ; but they paid dear for their frenzy. The Dionyſians again ſallied out upon them, and made ſuch ſlaughter, that one would have thought they had left none alive in the city. As the troops of the tyrant well knew that Dion was haſtening to the relief of the city, they uſed their utmoſt endeavours to deſtroy it entirely before his arrival ; for, after they had murdered all the inhabitants they could find, they ſet fire to the houſes, by which great numbers periſhed. During this confuſion Dion unexpectedly arrived ; and having briſkly attacked the enemy, at laſt defeated them with great ſlaughter, driving the remainder into the citadel. During the reſt of the night, inſtead of refreſhing themſelves after their fatigues, they aſſiſted in extinguiſhing the fire ; which was not done without great danger and difficulty. The citadel ſoon after ſurrendered ; and Dion allowed Apollocrates the tyrant’s ſon, who commanded there, to retire with five galleys to his father. As ſoon as Dion entered the citadel, he was met by his ſiſter and wife Arete, whom he received with affection, notwſthſtanding her having lived ſo long with Timocrates. He then left the Syracuſians in possession of the citadel, rewarded his followers, diſmissed his guards, and continued to live like a private citizen.</p><p>As ſoon as Dion had got posseſſion of the city, Heraclides had ſubmitted to him, and been received into favour ; but as his ſeditious and turbulent behaviour ſtill continued, Dion at laſt gave orders to put him to death. This action, however necessary, ſo affected the mind of Dion, that he became melancholy ; and ever after imagined himſelf haunted by a frightful spectre, reſembling a woman of gigantic ſtature, with the haggard looks and air of a fury. In a ſhort time after he loſt his life, through the baſe treachery of Calippus, or Gylippus, who pretended to be his intimate friend, and who immediately after cauſed his wife and ſiſter to be carried to priſon.</p><p>Calippus having thus removed Dion, ſoon made himſelf maſter of Syracuſe, where he committed all manner of cruelties ; but was driven out, and forced to fly to Rhegium, where he was murdered with the ſame dagger which had killed Dion. In 350 B. C. Dionyſius again made himſelf maſter of Syracuſe ; and being exaſperated by his past misfortunes, tyrannized worſe than ever. The Syracuſians first had recourſe to Icetas tyrant of Leontini ; but as the Carthaginians took this opportunity to invade them with a powerful fleet and army, they were obliged to apply to the Corinthians. By them Timoleon, a celebrated commander, was ſent to the aſſiſtance of the Syracuſians, whom he found in a very diſtreſſed ſituation ; Icetas being maſter of the city, the Carthaginians of the harbour, and Dionyſius of the citadel. As all parties were equally the enemies of Diony-</p></body></text></TEI>