<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T20:10:33Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>who are cured by the method of injections, and though it is to be regretted that hitherto the diſeaſe is found to return in a great proportion of thoſe upon whom this operation has been performed ; yet, on account of the facility with which it can be done, the comparatively ſmall pain with which it is attended, the quickneſs of the cure, and chiefly becauſe it does not, in caſe of a return of the diſeaſe, preclude the future operation of incision, it appears a method which, in all probability, will be more and more adopted into practice.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sect.</hi> III. <hi rend="italic">Of Hydrocele of the Spermatic Cord.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Anasarcous</hi> hydrocele of the ſpermatic cord ſometimes accompanies aſcites, and at other times it is found to be confined to the cellular ſubſtance in or about the ſpermatic cord. The cauſes of this diſeaſe may be, obſtructions in the lymphatics leading from the part in conſequence of ſcirrhous affections of the abdominal viſcera, or the preſſure of a truſs applied for the cure of hernia.</p><p>When the affection is connected with anaſarca in other parts, it is then ſo evident as to require no deſcription. When it is local, it is attended with a colourleſs tumor in the courſe of the ſpermatic cord, ſoft and inelaſtic to the touch, and unaccompanied with fluctuation. In an erect poſition of the body it is of an oblong figure ; but when the body is recumbent, it is flatter and ſomewhat round. Generally it is no longer than that part of the cord which lies in the groin, though ſometimes it extends as far as the teſticle, and even ſtretches the ſcrotum to an uncommon ſize ; an inſtance of which is related by Mr Pott, who from a ſwelling of this kind diſcharged 11 Engliſh pints at once. By preſſure a great part of the ſwelling can always be made to recede into the abdomen. It inſtantly, however, returns to its former ſituation on the preſſure being withdrawn.</p><p>When the tumor is connected with general anaſarca of the ſyſtem, it can only be cured along with the rest of the diſeaſe ; but when the ſwelling is local, the remedy is also to be locally applied. An inciſion is to be made of ſuch a ſize as may be ſufficient for diſcharging the whole of the water ; in the performance of which, attention is necessary to guard againſt hurting the ſpermatic veſſels. The contents of the tumor being diſcharged, the ſore is to be treated like any other simple wound.</p><p>Encyſted hydrocele of the ſpermatic cord ſometimes begins in the upper, but generally at the lower part of the ſpermatic cord. On its firſt appearance it is ſo ſmall as to give little or no trouble ; hence it is ſeldom particularly attended to till it has acquired a conſiderable ſize. By degrees it extends as far as the abdominal muſcles, and ſometimes reaches to the bottom of the ſcrotum; and to a person unacquainted with the appearance of the diſorder may be miſtaken for a hydrocele of the tunica vaginalis. But here the tumor is always above the teſticle, which is diſtinctly felt below ; and even in the advanced ſtate of the diſeaſe the teſticle is found in the back part of it perfectly unconnected with the ſwelling ; whereas, in the advanced ſtages of hydrocele in the vaginal coat, although ſome hardneſs is diſcovered where the tunica vaginalis adheres to the testicle, yet when the ſwelling is great the teſticle cannot be distinctly felt. In the encyſted hydrocele of the cord, the figure and ſize of the penis is little altered ; whereas, in caſes of common hydrocele, the penis frequently diſappears almoſt entirely. In other respects the two diſeaſes are nearly ſimilar. It ſometimes happens that the water is contained in two diſtinct cells. In that caſe the tumor is ſomewhat puckered up, or diminiſhed in its diameter. A ſimilar appearance alſo occurs, when this variety of the diſeaſe is connected with hydrocele of the tunica vaginalis, which ſometimes takes place.</p><p>The only other tumors with which this one may be confounded are, the anasarcous hydrocele of the ſpermatic cord, and a real hernia. But in neither of theſe is the fluctuation of a fluid perceptible, and to the touch they are both ſoft and inelaſtic ; whereas, in this variety of hydrocele, the tumor has a ſpringy feel, and a fluctuation is ſenſible to the touch ; and in both the one and the other the ſwelling recedes ſomewhat upon preſſure, which it never does here.</p><p>From hernia it is chiefly diſtinguished by the tumor beginning ſome way down the cord. In hernia the tumor turns leſs when the patient is in an horizontal poſture, and is conſiderably affected by coughing and ſneezing ; but this kind of hydrocele is not altered in ſize by any ſuch circumſtances, nor has it the common ſymptoms which attend a hernia.</p><p>Infants are frequently ſubject to this diſeaſe, as well as to an anaſarcous ſwelling of the cord, and an œdematous tumor of the ſcrotum. But here the complaint is ſeldom permanent ; for in moſt inſtances it readily yields to gentle friction, with any ſtimulating or aſtringent application, as a ſtrong ſolution of ſal ammoniac in vinegar, &amp;c. But in adults, the ciſt, in every variety of encyſted hydrocele, becomes ſo firm as not to be affected by external applications; ſo that when the tumor becomes large, it is neceſſary to uſe means for producing either a palliative or radical cure, in the same manner as is done for a hydrocele in the vaginal coat.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sect.</hi> IV. <hi rend="italic">Of Haematocele Scroti.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">We</hi> ſhall mention in this place the diſeaſe called ha<hi rend="italic">matocele scroti,</hi> which is occaſioned by blood extravalated in the inner ſubſtance of the ſcrotum, in the tunica vaginalis, or in the ſpermatic cord but the uſual ſituation is in the tunica vaginalis teſtis.</p><p>Tumors of this kind may be produced by any thing which ruptures the blood veſſels of the part, but they are commonly the conſequence of external violence. In the tunica vaginalis this diſorder may be produced by the point of a trocaror of a lancet in tapping for hydrocele. In ſuch a caſe, we are commonly informed of the accident by blood being diſcharged along with the water ; though ſometimes it does not appear till the whole of the water is evacuated, and then a tumor of a conſiderable ſize ſuddenly takes place. Sometimes it happens where the quantity of water has been ſo uncommonly great that the hidden dilcharge of it, by taking away the ſupport which the veſſels have been accuſtomed to receive, has been the cauſe of their rupture ; and it ſeems certain, that whenever a tumor is produced either in the ſcrotum or cord ſuddenly after the water of a hydrocele has been evacuated by tapping, that it is entirely owing to an extravaſation of blood.</p><p>In the ſpermatic cord injuries of the same kind will be attended with a ſimilar effect upon the veſſels of the ſac containing the water. The diſtinction between blood and water in the ſubſtance of the ſcrotum is readily made by the colour ; for where the diſeaſe is produced by blood, it forms a real eſchymoſis. The tumor feels heavier in the tunica vaginalis when filled with blood than where it is filled merely with water; the treatment is nearly the same with that in hydrocele. In the commencement of the anasarcous or diffuſed hæmatocele, when produced from slight external violence, the application of ſtimulating or aſtringent fluids will ſometimes diſcuſs it ; but if this prove ineffectual, the tumor is to be laid open, and treated exactly as was directed for hydrocele ; only if a ruptured veſsel be diſcovered, it muſt be ſecured by ligature. In like manner, all collections</p></body></text></TEI>