<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T20:12:59Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>cias being informed <hi rend="italic">of</hi> this misfortune, offered to pay the whole expence <hi rend="italic">of</hi> the war, provided he was allowed to march off with his men. But this being rejected, he ſet out, tho’ galled all the way by ſhowers of darts from his enemies. Arriving at a rivet called <hi rend="italic">Aſmarus,</hi> they ruſhed into it without any order; in which confuſion the Syracuſian cavalry attacked them ſo deſperately, that 18,000 periſhed, and the river for many miles was dyed with their blood. On this occaſion the Athenians were ſo preſſed with thirſt, that, unmindful of their danger, they drank the waters of the river all bloody as they were, which gave their enemies the better opportunity of ſlaughtering them without resiſtance. The remainder ſurrendered, on the ſingle condition of having their lives ſaved ; but the terms were ſhamefully broke by the Syracuſians. The generals were firſt ignominiouſly whipt, and then put to death : the common ſoldiers were thruſt down into quarries, where they were allowed only two ſmall meaſures of flour and one of water a-day ; and where, being crowded upon one another, they ſuffered inexpreſſible miſeries for many months. Moſt of them periſhed by this cruel treatment, and the few who ſurvived were sold for ſlaves.</p><p>The war was ſcarce ended, when a new and formidable invaſion by the Carthaginians took place ; but the event of that expedition was as unfortunate to the Carthaginians as the former had been, of which a particular account is given under the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Carthage,</hi> n⁰ 12. <hi rend="italic">et seq.</hi></p><p>In the mean time, however, a conſiderable revolution had happened in Syracuſe. The city of Agrigentum had been taken by the Carthaginians, and of the few inhabitants who eſcaped, ſome fled to Syracuſe, where they accuſed the Syracuſian commanders of having betrayed the city into the hands of the enemy. Dionyſius, a man of great valour and addreſs, but who had become very obnoxious to the populace, took this opportunity of attempting to retrieve his credit. He therefore ſupported the accuſations brought againſt his countrymen by the Agrigentines, and even impeached the magiſtrates as having a ſecret intelligence with the enemy, and attempting to introduce an oligarchy. As his ſpeech was entirely levelled againſt the more wealthy citizens, it was very agreeable to the lower claſs : the commanders were inſtantly degraded ; and others, among whom was Dionyſius, were appointed. Having once gained this point, he began to conſider how he might get all his colleagues turned out. For this purpoſe he never joined in any council of war with the other commanders, nor imparted to them his reſolutions, giving out that he could not truſt them, and that they had more regard for their own intereſt than the welfare of their country. But while he was proceeding in this manner, the more prudent part of the citizens, perceiving what he aimed at, complained of him to the ſenate and magiſtrates, and fined him as a diſturber of the public peace. According to the laws, the fine was to be paid before he could ſpeak in public, and the circumſtances of Dionyſius did not allow him to discharge it. In this dilemma he was aſſiſted by Philiſtus the hiſtorian, a man of great wealth, who not only paid this fine for him, but encouraged him to speak his mind freely, as it became a zealous citizen to do, promiſing to pay all the fines that ſhould be laid upon him.</p><p>Being extricated out of this difficulty, Dionyſius next proceeded to inveigh, with all the eloquence he was maſter of, againſt thoſe who by means of their power or intereſt were able to oppoſe his deſigns, and by degrees brought them into diſcredit. His next ſcheme was to get thoſe exiles recalled whom the nobility had baniſhed at different times ; as thinking that they would ſupport him with all their power, as well out of gratitude as out of hatred to the oppoſite party. Having gained this point alſo, he next found means to ingratiate himſelf with the ſoldiery to ſuch a degree, that, under pretence of taking proper meaſures for refilling the Carthagrinians, he was choſen commander in chief, with abſolute and unlimited power. This was no ſooner done, than, pretending that his life was in danger, he choſe out 1000 men for his guard, whom he attached to his intereſt by great promises. As no perſon durſt now oppoſe him, he poſſeſſed himſelf of the citadel, where all the arms and proviſions were kept ; after which he publicly took the title of king of Syracuſe in the year 404 B. C.</p><p>The Syracuſians did not tamely ſubmit to their new maſter : but Dionyſius managed matters ſo well, that their frequent revolts anſwered no other purpoſe than more certainly to entail ſlavery on themſelves; and he was allowed to poſſeſs the throne without much oppoſition till his death, which happened in the year 366 B. C.</p><p>On the death of Dionyſius, he was ſucceeded by his ſon, called also <hi rend="italic">Dionyſius.</hi> He was naturally of a mild and peaceable temper, averſe from cruelty, and inclined to learning ; but his father, to whom all merit, even in his own children, gave umbrage, ſtifled as far as poſſible his good qualities by a mean and obſcure education. He no ſooner aſcended the throne, than Dion, brother to Ariſtomache the other wife of Dionyſius the Elder, undertook to correct the faults of his education, and to inſpire him with thoughts ſuitable to the high ſtation in which he was placed. For this purpoſe he ſent for the philoſopher Plato, under whose care he immediately put the young king. This inſtantly produced a reformation on Dionyſius ; but the courtiers, dreading the effects of the philoſopher’s inſtructions, prevailed on him to baniſh Dion, and to keep Plato himſelf in a kind of impriſonment in the citadel. At laſt, however, he ſet him at liberty ; upon which Plato returned to his own country.</p><p>Dion, in the mean time, viſited ſeveral of the Grecian cities, and at laſt took up his reſidence in Athens ; but the honours which were everywhere paid him, raiſed ſuch jealouſies in the breaſt of the tyrant, that he stopped his revenue, and cauſed it to be paid into his own treaſury. In a ſhort time Dionyſius again ſent for Plato ; but finding it impoſſible to diſſolve the friendſhip between him and Dion, diſgraced, and placed him in a very dangerous ſituation, in the midſt of aſſaſſins who hated him. Not daring, however, to offer him any violence, he allowed him ſoon after to depart ; revenging himſelf on Dion, whoſe eſtate he fold, and gave his wife Arete in marriage to Timocrates one of his own flatterers.</p><p>Dion now reſolved to revenge himſelf on the tyrant for the many injuries he had ſuſtained, and at once to deliver his country from the oppression under which it groaned. He began with raising foreign troops privately, by proper agents, for the better execution of his deſign. Many Syracuſians of diſtinction entered into his ſcheme, and gave him intelligence of what paſſed in the city; but of the exiles, of whom there were upwards of 1000 diſperſed up and down Greece, only 25 joined him ; ſo much were they awed by the dread of the tyrant. The troops were aſſembſed at the iſland of Zacynthus, in number only about 800 ; but who had all been tried on many occaſions, were well diſciplined, and capable of animating by their example the forces which Dion hoped to find in Sicily. When they were about to ſail, Dion acquainted them with his deſign, the boldneſs of which at firſt occaſioned no ſmall conſternation among them ; but Dion ſoon removed their fears, by telling them that he did not lead them as ſoldiers, but as officers, to put them at the head of the Syracuſians and all the people of Sicily, who were ready to receive them with open</p></body></text></TEI>