<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T20:12:20Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ſome guest ought to be removed by force ſhould other means fail. Orders were therefore poſitively lent to Charles to depart ; and, in cafe of refuſal, to attack him in his quarters. Nothing could equal his obſtinacy on this occasion : in ſpite of the menaces of his enemies, in ſpite of the intrea ties of his friends, he perſiſted in his reſolution ; and at laſt determined to reſiſt, with 300 Swedes, being all the attendants he had, an army of 20,000 janiſaries well armed and furniſhed with cannon. At length he was attacked in good earneſt ; though it muſt be owned, that even in this ex tremity, the Turks showed their regard to him, and were tender of hrs life, which the king did not return at all in a ſimilar manner. Moſt of the Swedes ſurrendered at once, perhaps as thinking it the only method of saving the king's life. This miſconduct, however, had a quite contrary effect. Charles became the more obſtinate, the more deſperate his affairs teemed to be. With 40 menial servants only, and the generals Hord and Dardorff, he determined to defend himſelf to the laſt extremity. Seeing his ſoldiers lay down their arms', he told the generals, “ We muſt now defend the houle. Come, (adds he with a ſmile), let us fight <hi rend="italic">pro aris et focis.”</hi> The houſe had been already forced by the Tartars, all but a hall which was near the door, and where his domeſtics had aſſembled themſelves. Charles forced his way through the janiſaries, attended by the generals Hord and Dardoff, joined his people, and then barricaded the door. The moment he entered, the enemy, who were in the houſe, threw down their booty, and endeavoured to eſcape at the windows. Charles purſued them from room to room with much bloodſhed, and cleared the houſe in a few minutes. He then fired furiously from the windows, killed 200 of the Turks in a quarter of an hour, ſo that the baſhaw who commanded them was at length forced to ſet the houſe on fire. This was done by arrows with lighted matches ſhot into the roof ; but Charles, instead of quitting it gave orders for extinguiſhing the fire, in which he himſelf aſſiſted with great diligence. All efforts, however, were vain : the roof fell in ; and Charles, with his few faithful companions, was ready to be buried in the ruins. In this extremity one called out, that there was a neceſſity for iurren- dering. “ What a ſtrange fellow ! (cries the king) who would rather be a prisoner with the Turks than mix his aſhes with thoſe of his ſovereign.” Another had the preſence of mind to cry out, that the chancery was but 50 paces off, had a ſtone roof, and was proof againſt fire. Pleaſed with the thoughts of again coming to blows, the king exclaimed, “ A true Swede ! Let us take all the powder and ball we can carry.” He then put himſelf at the head of his troops, and ſallied out with ſuch fury that the Turks retreated 50 paces ; but faffing down in the hurry, they ruſhed in upon him, and carried him by the legs and arms to the baſhaw’s tent.</p><p>This extraordinary adventure, which favours not a little of inſanity, happened on the 12th of February 1713. He was now kept priſoner, with all his retinue ; and in this ſituation he was viſited by the unfortunate Staniſlaus. The latter, as we have already obſerved, came in the diſgniſe of a Swediſh officer, and had indeed ſerved in the Swediſh army in Pomerania, for which reaſon he was arreſted in the Turkiſh dominions ; but being known at Bender, notice was font to the baſhaw who was conducting the king of Sweden to Adrianople. The baſhaw communicated the news to Baron Fabricios, a favourite of Charles, who immediately imparted it to the king. “ Dear Fabricius, (ſays this inflexible monarch), run and tell him never to make peace with Auguſtus ; we ſhall ſoon have a change in our affairs.”</p><p>buch were the conſiderations that ſtill occurred to the mind of Charles ; however, at laſt he ſeemed inclined to ſubmit to his fate, and began ſeriouſly to think of returning to his kingdom, now reduced to the moſt deplorable ſituation. Hrs habitation was now fixed at Demotica, a ſmall town about six leagues from Adrianople. Here he was al lowed provisions for his own table and thoſe of his retinue ; but only 25 crowns a-day in money, inſtead oſ 500 which he had received at Bender. During his reſidence here he received a deputation from Heffe-Caſſel, ſoliciting his confient to the marriage of the landgrave with Eleonora princess royal of Sweden; to which he readily agreed; a deputation was alſo sent him by the regency of Sweden, requelling that he would prepare for returning to his own dominions, which were ready to fink under a ruinous war in his abſence. What determined him, however, more than any thing to haften his return, was the following accident. The new grand vizir Ibrahim Molla, having for private reaſons determined to come to a rupture with the czar, invited Charles to a conference, in the ſtyle and with the familiarity of an equal. Charles was ſo much chagrined at this indignity, that he ſent his chancellor Mullem to meet the vizir, with a pretence that he was sick. To avoid giving offence to this miniſter Charles was obliged to keep his bed during his reſidence at Demotica, which was for 10 months after. At laſt, this vizir being ſtrangled, and the Swediſh intereſt at the Porte thereby entirely ruined, he determined to quit Turkey at all events. His departure was to be negotiated by his favourite Grothuſen, whom he veſted with the character of ambassador extraordinary ; ſending him to Adrianople with a train of <hi rend="italic">14.</hi> perſons richly dreſſed. To equip this retinue the king was reduced to the moſt mortifying ſhifts, and to the neceſſity of borrowing money from uſurers at 50 <hi rend="italic">per cent.</hi> ſt he great object was, to obtain from the vizir money and a paſſport. Grothuſen was received with all the respect due to his rank ; but the vizir ſtarted difficulties. With regard to the paſſport, he laid, it could be of no uſe until the consent of the court of Vienna was firſt obtained ; and as to money, he ſaid, “ his maſter knew how to give when he thought proper, but it was beneath his dignity to <hi rend="italic">lend;</hi> that the king ſhould have every necessary provided for his journey, and poſſibly the Porte might make ſome pecuniary preſent, but he would not have it expected.” The imperial miniſter, however, removed every difficulty with regard to the passport, by granting it in the moſt lull and ample manner, in the name of the emperor, the princes and states of Germany. He lent alſo a preſent to the king, conſiſting of a tent of ſcarlet richly embroidered with gold ; a ſabre, the handle of which was ſtudded with jewels ; anti eight fine horses richly capariſoned. Money, the article moſt wanted, was entirely forgotten ; however, the day was fixed for Charles’s departure, and the vizir appointed 60 carriages loaded with all kinds of proviſions, and several companies or janiſaries and other troops to attend him to the frontiers oſ Transylvania.</p><p>On the 14th of October 1714 ,Charles quitted his bed at Demotica, and ſet out for Sweden. All the princes through whoſe territories he was to paſs, had given orders tor his entertainment in the moſt magnificent manner ; but the king, perceiving that theſe compliments only rendered his impriſonment and other misfortunes more conſpicuous, ſuddenly dilmiffed his Turkiſh attendants, and aſſembling his own people, bid them take no care about him, but make the beſt of their way to Stralsund. After this he ſet out poſt, in the habit of a German officer, attended only by Colonel During. Keeping the by-roads through Hungary, Moravia, Auſtria, Bavaria, Wirtemberg, the Palatinate, Westphalia, and Mecklenburg, he arrived on the 21st of November at midnight before the gates of Stralſund. Being unknown, he was admitted with difficulty ; but being ſoon recognized</p></body></text></TEI>