<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T20:11:45Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>“ Theſe are doubtleſs the lurking places of the later hatches, or of thoſe young birds which are incapable of diſtant migrations. There they continue inſenſible and rigid; but like flies may ſometimes be reanimated by an unſeaſonable hot day in the midſt of winter : for very near Christmas a ſew appeared on the moulding of a window of Merton college, Oxford, in a remarkably warm nook, which prematurely ſet their blood in motion, having the ſame effect as laying them before a fire at the ſame time of year. Others have been known to make this premature appearance ; but as ſoon as the cold natural to the ſeaſon returns, they withdraw again to their former retreats.</p><p>“ The above are circumſtances we cannot but assent to, though seemingly contradictory to the common courſe of nature in regard to other birds. We muſt, therefore, divide our belief relating to theſe two ſo different opinions ; and conclude, that one part of the ſwallow tribe migrate, and that others have their winter-quartets near home. If it should be demanded, why ſwallows alone are found in a torpid ſtate, and not the other many ſpecies oſ ſoft billed birds, which likewiſe disappear about the ſame time ? reaſons might be aſſigned :”</p><p>The third opinion we ſhall ſtate and ſupport in the words of Mr Kalm. “ Natural hiſtory (ſays he), as all other histories, depends not always upon the intrinsic degree of probability, but upon facts founded on the teſtimony of people of noted veracity.— Swallows are ſeldom ſeen sinking down into the water ; ſwallows have not such organs as frogs or lizards, which are torpid during winter ; <hi rend="italic">ergo,</hi> ſwallows live not, and cannot live, under water.—This way of arguing, I believe, would carry us, in a great many caſes, too far : for though it is not clear to every one, it may however be true ; and lizards and frogs are animals of a claſs widely different from that of birds, and muſt therefore of courſe have a different ſtructute ; hence it is they are classed ſeparately. The bear and the marmot are in winter in a torpid ſtate, and have, however, not ſuch organs as lizards and frogs ; and nobody doubts of their being, during ſome time, in the moſt rigid climates, in a torpid ſtate : for the Alpine nations hunt the marmots frequently by digging their holes up ; and find them ſo torpid, that they cut their throats, without their reviving or giving the least ſign of life during the operation ; but when the torpid marmot is brought into a warm room, and placed before the fire, it revives from its lethargy. The queſtion muſt therefore be decided by facts ; nor are theſe wanting here. Dr Wallerius, the celebrated Swediſh chemiſt, informs us, That he has ſeen, more than once, ſwallows aſſembling on a reed, till they were all immerſed and went to the bottom ; this being preceded by a dirge of a quarter of an hour’s length. He atteſts likewiſe, that he had ſeen a ſwallow caught during winter out of a lake with a net, drawn, as is common in northern countries, under the ice ; this bird was brought into a warm room, revived, fluttered about, and ſoon after died.</p><p>“ Mr Klein applied to many farmers-general of the king of Pruſſia’s domains, who had great lakes in their diſtricts, the fiſhery in them being a part of the revenue. In winter the fiſhery thereon is the moſt conſiderable under the ice, with nets ſpreading more than 200 or 300 fathoms, and they are often wound by ſcrews and engines on account of their weight. All the people that were queſtioned made affidavits upon oath before the magiſtrates. Firſt, The mother of the counteſs Lehndorf laid, that ſhe had ſeen a bundle of ſwallows brought from the Friſhe-Haff (a lake communicating with the Baltic at Pillaw), which, when brought into a moderately warm room, revived and fluttered about. Secondly, Count Schileben gave an inſtrument on ſtamped paper, importing, that by fiſhing on the lake belonging to his eſtate of Gerdauen in winter, he ſaw ſeveral ſwallows caught in the net, one of which he took up in his hand, brought it into a warm room, where it lay about an hour, when it began to ſtir, and half an hour after, it flew about in the room. Thirdly, Farmer general (Amtman) Witkouſki made affidavit, that, in the year 1740, three ſwallows were brought up with the net in the great pond at Didlacken ; in the year 1741 he got two ſwallows from another part of the pond, and took them home (they being all caught in his preſence) ; after an hour’s ſpace they revived all in a warm room, fluttered about, and died in three hours after. Fourthly, Amtman Bonke ſays, that having had the eſtate of Kleſkow in farm, he had ſeen nine ſwallows brought up in the net from under the ice, all which he took into a warm room, where ſhe diſtinctly obſerved how they gradually revived ; but a few horns after they all died. Another time his people got likewiſe ſome ſwallows in a net, but he ordered them to be again thrown into the water. Fifthly, Andrew Rutta, a maſter fiſherman at Oletſko, made affidavit, in 1747, that 22 years ago, two ſwallows were taken up by him in a net, under the ice, and, being brought into a warm room, they flew about. Sixthly, Jacob Kosiulo, a maſter fiſherman at Stradauen, made affidavit, that, in 1736, he brought up in winter, in a net, from under the ice of the lake at Raski, a ſeemingly dead ſwallow, which revived in half an hour’s time in a warm room ; and he ſaw, in a quarter of an hour after, the bird grow weaker, and ſoon after dying. Seventhly, I can reckon myſelf (ſays our author) among the eye-witneſſes of this paradox of natural hiſtory. In the year 1735, being a little boy, I ſaw ſeveral ſwallows brought in winter by the fiſhermen from the river Viſtula to my father’s houſe ; where two of them were brought into a warm room, revived, and flew about. I ſaw them ſeveral times settling on the warm ſtove (which the northern nations have in their rooms) ; and I recollect well, that the lame forenoon they died, and I had them, when dead, in my hand. In the year 1754, after the death of my uncle Godefroy Wolf, captain in the Polish regiment of foot-guards, being myſelf one of his heirs, I adminiſtered for my co heirs ſeveral eſtates called the <hi rend="italic">Starosty of Dischau,</hi> in Poliſh Prussia, which my late uncle farmed under the king. In January, the lake of Lybſhaw, belonging to theſe eſtates, being covered with ice, I ordered the fiſhermen to fiſh therein, and in my preſence ſeveral ſwallows were taken, which the fishermen threw in again ; but one I took up to myſelf, brought it home, which was five miles from thence, and it revived, but died about an hour after its reviving.</p><p>“ Theſe are facts atteſted by people of the higheſt quality, by ſome in public offices, and by others who, though of a low rank, however, made theſe affidavits upon oath. It is impoſſible to ſuppoſe indiſcriminately that they were prompted, by views of intereſt, to aſſert as a fact a thing which had no truth in it. It is therefore highly probable, or rather inconteſtably true, that ſwallows retire in the northern countries, during winter, into the water, and stay there in a torpid ſtate till the return of warmth revives them again in ſpring. The queſtion therefore, I believe, ought for the future to be thus ſtated : The ſwallows in Spain, Italy, France, and perhaps ſome from England, remove to warmer climates ; ſome Engliſh ones, and ſome in Germany and other mild countries, retire into clefts and holes in rocks, and remain there in a torpid ſtate. In the colder northern countries the ſwallows immerſe in the ſea, in lakes, and rivers ; and remain in a torpid ſtate, under ice, during winter. There are ſtill ſome objections to this latter</p></body></text></TEI>