<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T20:11:42Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>general for carp. It is remarkable, that all the rivers above-mentioned riſe and fall into the ſea within the county.</p><p>The air, as well as the soil, is various in different parts of the county. Upon the coaſt the air is aguiſh, upon the hills and downs pleaſant and wholeſome ; but ſomewhat moiſt and foggy in the valleys, the soil being deep and rich, and the vegetation in ſummer very vigorous. The downs in ſome places are very fertile in corn and graſs ; in others they feed great flocks of sheep, whoſe fleſh and wool are very fine ; but of the latter no inconſiderable quantity is clandeſtinely exported to France. In the Weald and the valleys the roads are very deep, eſpecially in winter. In the north quarter are many woods, and ſome foreſts in other places ; whence the king’s yards are ſupplied with the largeſt and beſt timber in England, beſide what is made into charcoal and confirmed in the iron-works ; for on the eaſt side is plenty of iron ore, with furnaces, forges, and mills for manufacturing it. The gunpowder of this county is ſaid to excel that of any other. Thoſe delicious birds called w<hi rend="italic">heat- ears</hi> are bred in this ſhire ; they are no bigger than a lark, but almoſt an entire lump of fat. That part now called the <hi rend="italic">Wild</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Weald</hi> of Suffex, was anciently a mere deſert for hogs and deer, of great extent, taking in a part of Kent and Surry ; and was called <hi rend="italic">Anderidα Silva, Coid Andred, </hi>and <hi rend="italic">Andradſwald,</hi> from Anderida an adjoining city. This county is in the home-circuit and diocese of Chicheſter, giving title of earl to the family of Yelverton, and sends 28 members to parliament, viz, two for the county, two for the city of Chicheſter, and two for each of the following towns, Horſham, Lewes, Bramber, Eaſt-Grinſtead, Midhurſt, Shoreham, Staining, Arundel, Haſtings, Rye, Winchelſea, and Seaford ; of which the four laſt are cinqueports.</p><p>SUTHERLAND, one of the moſt northerly counties of Scotland. Including Strathnavern, it borders on Caithneſs to the north and north-eaſt, is bounded by the ocean on the north, the country of Assynt on the west, Roſs on the ſouth, and by the German ſea on the eaſt and ſouth-eaſt. It ſtretches about 70 miles in length, and 40 in breadth ; is generally hilly, tho' in many parts arable ; well watered with ſmall rivers and ſtreams replete with fiſh, and exhibiting about 60 lakes, the habitation of various fiſh, ſwans, ducks, geeſe, &amp;c. One of the largeſt of theſe is Lochſhin, extending 18 miles in length. Some of them are interſperſed with ſmall verdant islands, which in ſummer yield a very agreeable proſpect. On the coaſt are many commodious harbours, and all the bays ſwarm with fiſh ; nay, the ſea in this place produces ſome valuable pearls. Sutherland affords iron-ſtone, free- ſtone, lime-ſtone, and ſlate, in abundance. Here are alſo quarries of marble, and mines of coal, though the people life turf and peat for fuel. Lead ore, impregnated with ſilver, and even ſome gold, hath been found in this province, together with cryſtals and pebbles.</p><p>The air is ſo temperate, and the ſoil ſo good, that ſaffron has here been brought to perfection. Many parts of the country are remarkably fruitful in corn, and the paſturage is excellent everywhere, Besides three great foreſts, there are many ſmaller woods in Sutherland, abounding with deer and other game. On the hills are fed numerous flocks of ſheep and black cattle ; ſmall, yet ſweet and juicy. There is one bird peculiar to this ſhire, called <hi rend="italic">knag,</hi> which reſembles a parrot, and digs its neſt with its beak in the trunks of oaks. The northern part, called <hi rend="italic">Strathnavern,</hi> and ſeparated from the rest by a ridge of mountains, is bounded on the north by the Deucaledoaian ſea, on the west by the channel called the <hi rend="italic">Minch,</hi> on the eaſt by Caithneſs, and on the ſouth by Aſſynt. The length of it, from eaſt to west, amounts to 34 miles; but the breadth from north to ſouth does not exceed 12 in ſome places. It is very hilly ; and the mountains are ſo high, that the ſnow remains on the tops of them till mid- ſummer. It is watered by Navern, from whence it derives its name : as this diſtrict gives a title to the eldeſt ſon of the earl of Sutherland. Here are ſeveral woods, frequented by deer and other game, which the people take great delight in hunting. Iron-mines have been worked in ſome places, but to no great advantage. Strathnavern has many freſh water lakes or lochs ; the chief of which arc Loch Navern and Loch Lyel : there are ſeveral iſlands on the northern coaſt ; and in various parts of the country we see monuments of victories obtained over the Danes or other foreign invaders. Sutherland boaſts of ſome towns, and a great many villages. The people are numerous, hardy, bold, and enterprising ; courteous to ſtrangers ; cheerful, open, frugal, and induſtrious. They, as well as their neighbours of Caithneſs, ſpeak the language, and wear the garb, uſed in the Lowlands of Scotland. They carry on a conſiderable ſalmon-f\iſhery. They drive a traffic with their black cattle, ſheep, and horſes, at the neighbouring fairs ; but export their corn, barley, ſalt, coal, ſalmon, ſalted beef, butter, cheeſe, wool-ſkins, hides, and tallow. Here are proviſions of all sorts in plenty ; and ſo cheap through all this country, that a gentleman may keep houſe and live much more ſumptuously for 200 l. a-year than he can live for three times the money in the ſouth of England.</p><p>SUTLER, in war, one who follows the army, and furniſhes the troops with provision. Sutlers pitch their tents, or build their huts, in the rear of each regiment, and about head-quarters.</p><p>SUTRIUM (anc. geog.), a famous city, and an ancient colony of the Romans, the key of Etruria ; founded about ſeven years after the taking of Rome by the Gauls (Velleius). Now <hi rend="italic">Sutri</hi> in St Peter’s patrimony, on the river Pozzolo ; ſurrounded on every side with rocks, 24 miles to the north west of Rome.</p><p>SUTTON (Samuel), was born at Alfretton in Derbyſhire, and going into the army ſerved under the duke of Marlborough in Queen Anne’s wars with great credit. He afterwards came to London, commenced brewer, and kept a coffee-houſe in Alderſgate-ſtreet, which was well frequented by the learned men of that time, by whom Mr Sutton was much reſpected, as a man of ſtrong natural parts and uncultivated genius. About the year 1740 he schemed a very ſimple and natural method for extracting the foul air from the wells of ſhips, by pipes communicating with the fire-places of the coppers ; which operated as long as any fire was kept burning for the ſhip’s uſe. He took out a patent in <hi rend="italic">1</hi>744, to ſecure the profits of his invention ; and died about the year 1752.</p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Sutton’s</hi><hi rend="italic"> Air-pipes.</hi> See <hi rend="italic">Air-Pipes.</hi></p><p>SUTURE, in anatomy, a kind of articulation peculiar to the cranium or ſkull. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Anatomy,</hi> Part I. Sect. ii. <hi rend="italic">paſſim.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Suture,</hi> in ſurgery, a method of uniting the lips of wounds together. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Surgery.</hi></p><p>SWABBER, an inferior officer on board ſhips of war, whoſe employment it is to ſee that the decks are kept clean and neat.</p><p>SWABIA. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Suabia.</hi></p><p>SWALLOW, in natural hiſtory, is classed under the genus of <hi rend="smallcaps">Hirundo,</hi> under which article the different ſpecies have been already deſcribed. Concerning this bird, one curious queſtion, however, ſtill remains to be diſcussed, What becomes of it in the winter ? Upon this ſubject there are three opinions. Some ſay that it migrates to a warmer cli-</p></body></text></TEI>