<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T20:12:13Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>fortune to break his thigh, by which he was confined six weeks ; and thus Auguſtus obtained ſome reſpite. The interval he made the beſt uſe of. Having convoked a diet firſt at Marienburg, and then at Lublin, from them he obtained the following resolutions ; that an army of 50,000 men ſhould be raised by the republic for the ſervice of the prince ; that six weeks ſhould be allowed the Swedes to determine whether they were for war or peace ; and that the ſame time ſhould be granted to the turbulent and discontented nobles of Poland to make their conceſſions. To counteract; the effects of theſe reſolutions, Charles assembled another diet at Warſaw ; and while the two assemblies disputed concerning their rights and privileges, he recovered of his wound, received a ſtrong reinforcement from Pomerania, and utterly defeated and disperſed the remains of the Saxon army.</p><p>The ill fortune of Auguſtus continued ſtill to perſecute him. In 1704 he was formally depoſed by the diet, and the crown conferred by Charles on Staniſlaus Lecsinſky palatine of Poſnania. Auguſtus, however, did not yet tamely give up his kingdom. His adherents daily skirmiſhed with the Swedes; and Auguſtus himſelf, being reinforced by 9000 Russians, retook Warsaw, and was very near ſurprising the new king, who lived in perfect ſecurity in the city while Charles fought in his cauſe. Count Horn, with 1500 Swedes, vigorously defended the citadel ; but at laſt, finding it no longer tenable, he was obliged to surrender at diſcretion. The reduction of Warſaw was among the laſt advantages gained by Auguſtus in the course of this war. His troops were now compoſed of Saxon recruits and undiſciplined Poles, who had no attachment to his person, and were ready on all occaſions to forſake him. Charles and Staniſlaus advanced with the victorious army; the Saxons fled before them, and the towns for ſeveral miles round lent their ſubmissions. The Poles and Saxons were under the command of Schullemberg, a moſt ſagacious and experienced general, who uſed every expedient to check the progreſs of the Swedes, by seizing on the advantageous ports, ſacrificing ſmall parties to the ſafety of the whole, and to miſlead the enemy, &amp;c. However, with all his conduct and caution, he found himſelf outwitted, and Charles in the neighbourhood of his camp ready to fall upon him, while he thought him at 50 leagues diſtance. The Swediſh monarch attacked him with a ſuperior army, but entirely compoſed of horſe. Schullemberg had polled his men in ſuch a manner as rendered it impoſſible to ſurround them. His firſt rank being armed with pikes and fuſees, preſented a kind of rampart of bayonets ; the ſecond line ſtooping over the firſt who kneeled, fired over their heads, wſhile the third rank, who stood upon their feet, kept up an inceſſant fire, by which the Swediſh horſe were exceedingly galled and put in diſorder. Charles loſt the opportunity of cutting off the whole Saxon army, by omitting to order his men to diſmount. This was almoſt the firſt time that infantry had been regularly oppoſed to cavalry, and the ſuperiority of the former was evident. After the engagement had continued about three hours, the Saxons retreated in good order ; which no enemy had ever done before in any engagement with Charles. The Swedes purſued their enemies towards the Oder, and forced them to retreat through thick woods, almoſt impervious even to infantry. The Swediſh horſe, however, puſhed their way, and at laſt incloſed Schullemberg between a wood and the river, where Charles had no doubt of obliging him to surrender at diſcretion, or die ſword in-hand, as having neither boats nor bridges; but the genius of Schullemberg ſupplied every defect. In the night he ordered planks and floats of trees to be faſtened together; upon which he carried over his troops, while the Swedes were employed in dislodging 300 men, which he had placed in a wind mill, for the purpoſe of defending his flank and keeping the enemy in play. Charles ſpoke of this retreat with admiration, and laid he had been conquered by Schullemberg.</p><p>No material advantage, however, reſulted from this to Auguſtus; who was again obliged to leave Poland, and fortify the capital of his hereditary dominions, which he expected every moment to see inverted. In the mean time, however, the Russians having recovered their ſpirits, fell upon the Swedes in Livonia with the utmoſt fury. Narva, Dorpt, and ſeveral other towns, were taken, and the inhabitants and garriſons treated with great barbarity. Soon after, an army of 100,000 Russians entered Poland. Sixty thouſand Cossacks under Mazeppa entered the country at the ſame time, and ravaged every thing with the fury of barbarians. Schullemberg, too, perhaps more formidable than either, advanced with 14,000 Saxons and 7000 Ruffians, diſciplined in Germany, and reputed excellent soldiers. Could numbers have determined the event of war, the Swedes muſt certainly have been at this time overpowered. Inſtead of this, however, Charles ſeemed to triumph over his enemies with more eaſe the more numerous they were. The Russians were defeated ſo fast, that they were all disperſed before one party had notice of the misfortunes of another. The defeating an army of 40,000 men ſcarcely obſtructed the march of the Swedes, while their astoniſhed enemies looked upon theſe actions as the effects of witchcraft, and imagined that the king of Sweden had dealings with infernal spirits. With theſe apprehenſions they fled beyond the Boriſthenes, leaving the unhappy Auguſtus to his ill fate. Schullemberg, with all his ſkill and experience, ſucceeded no better. The Swediſh general Renſchild engaged and defeated him in half an hour, though the Swedes were vaſtly inferior in number, and their enemies posted in a most advantageous ſituation. Nothing could be more complete than this victory. Whole regiments of Saxons threw down their aims, and begged their lives in the moſt ſuppliant poſture. Six thouſand were ſlain in the field, and 7000 taken priſoners. Thirty-six pieces of cannon, 11,000 muſkets, 40 pair of colours and ſtandards, with all the Saxon baggage, fell into the hands of the Swedes : and the conſequences were still more important ; for now a partage was opened into Saxony, and Auguſtus ſeemed to be in as great danger of loſing his hereditary dominions as he had been of loſing Poland. This extraordinary victory, indeed, is ſaid to have been owing to a panic which ſeized the troops of Schullemberg : however, it was looked upon with admiration, and thought to make the renown of Renſchild equal to that of his ſovereign. Charles himſelf was jealous, and could not help exclaiming, “ Surely Renſchild will not compare himſelf with me !” But the cruelty of this general ſullied his reputation ; for six hours after the engagement, he cauſed 1000 Russians to be maſſacred in cold blood, to revenge, as he ſaid, the cruelties they had committed in Poland.</p><p>Soon after this victory, which was gained on the 12th of February 1706, Charles entered Saxony at the head of 24,000 men. The diet at Ratiſbon declared him an enemy to the empire if he croſſed the Oder. But to this declaration no regard was paid. Charles purſued his march; while Auguſtus was reduced to the condition of a vagrant in Poland, where he poſſeſſed not a single town beſides Cracow. Into this city he threw himſelf with a few Saxon, Poliſh, and Russian regiments, and began to erect some fortifications for its defence ; but the approach of the Swediſh general Meyerſeldt, and the news of the invaſion of Saxony, diſconcerted all his meaſures, and threw him into deſpair. The Russians indeed were his faithful allies ; but he dread</p></body></text></TEI>