<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T20:11:54Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ately cauſed the houſe to be ſurrounded with ſoldiers, in ſuch a manner that it ſeemed impoſſible for Guſtavus to make his eſcape. In the interval, however, he eſcaped, being warned by Peterſon’s wife of the treachery of her husband, and by her direction fled to the houſe of a clergyman, her friend. By him Guſtavus was received with all the reſpect due to his own birth and merit ; and left the domeſtic who conducted him ſhould follow the treacherous example of his master, he removed him to the church, and conducted him to a ſmall cloſet, of which he kept the key. Having lived for ſome time in this manner, Guſtavus began to consult with his friend concerning the moſt proper method of putting their ſchemes in execution. The prieſt advised him to apply directly to the peaſants themſelves ; told him that it would be proper to spread a report, that the Danes were to enter Dalecarlia in order to eſtabliſh new taxes by force of arms ; and as the annual feaſt of all the neighbouring villages was in a few days to be held, he could not have a more favourable opportunity : at the ſame time he promised to engage the principal perſons of the dioceſe in his intereſt.</p><p>Agreeable to this advice Guſtavus ſet out for Mora, where the feaſt was to be held. He found the peaſants already informed of his designs, and impatient to see him. Being already prepossessed in his favour, they were ſoon excited to an enthuſiaſm in his cauſe, and inſtantly reſolved to throw off the Daniſh yoke. In this deſign they were more confirmed by their ſuperſtition ; ſome of their old men having obſerved that the wind had blown from the north while Guſtavus was ſpeaking, which among them was reckoned an infallible omen of ſucceſs. Guſtavus did not give their ardour time to cool, but inſtantly led them againſt the governor’s caſtle ; which he took by aſſault, and put the garriſon to the ſword. This inconsiderable enterpriſe was attended with the moſt happy conſequences. Great numbers of the peaſants flocked to his ſtandard ; ſome of the gentry openly eſpouſed his cauſe, and others ſupplied him with money. Chriſtian was ſoon acquainted with what had paſſed ; but deſpising ſuch an inconſiderable enemy, he ſent only a ſlender detachment under the command of one Soren Norby, to aſſiſt his adherents in Dalecarlia. Guſtavus advanced with 5000 men, and defeated a body of Danes commanded by one Meleen ; but he was ſtrenuouſly oppoſed by the archbishop of Upſal, who raiſed numerous forces for king Chriſtian. The fortune of Guſtavus, however, ſtill prevailed, and the archbiſhop was defeated with great loſs. Guſtavus then laid siege to Stockholm ; but his force being too inconſiderable for ſuch an undertaking, he was forced to abandon it with loſs.</p><p>This check did not prove in any conſiderable degree detrimental to the affairs of Guſtavus; the peaſants from all parts of the kingdom flocked to his camp, and he was joined by a reinforcement from Lubec. Chriſtian, unable to ſuppreſs the revolt, wreaked his vengeance on the mother and sisters of Gustavus, whom he put to death with the moſt excruciating torments. Several other Swediſh ladies he cauſed to be thrown into the ſea, after having impoſed on them the inhuman taſk of making the ſacks into which they were to be incloſed. His barbarities ſerved only to make his enemies more reſolute. Guſtavus having aſſembled the ſtates at Wadſtena, he was unanimouſly choſen regent, the diet taking an oath of fidelity to him, and promising to aſſiſt him to the utmoſt. Having thus obtained the ſanction of legal authority, he purſued his advantages againſt the Danes. A body of troops appointed to throw ſuccours into Stockholm were totally cut in pieces ; and the regent sending ſome troops into Finland, ſtruck the Danes there with ſuch terror, that the archbiſhop of Upſal, together with Slahog and Baldenacker the Daniſh governors, fled to Denmark. Chriſtian received them but very coldly, apprehending that their flight might be prejudicial to his affairs ; and in a ſhort time the two governors were put to death, that the king might have an opportunity oſ charging them with being guilty oſ the cruelties which they had committed by his order. He then ſent expreſs orders to all his governors and officers in Finland and Sweden to massacre the Swediſh gentry without distinction. The Swedes made repriſals by massacring all the Danes they could find ; ſo that the whole country was filled with bloodſhed and ſlaughter.</p><p>In the mean time Guſtavus had laid ſiege to the towns of Calmar, Abo, and Stockholm; but Norby found means to oblige him to raiſe all of them with great loſs. Guſtavus, in revenge, laid ſiege to the capital a third time, and petitioned the regency of Lubec for a ſquadron of ſhips and other ſuccours for carrying on the ſiege. This was complied with, but on very hard conditions, viz, that Guſtavus ſhould oblige himſelf, in the name of the ſtates, to pay 60,000 merks of ſilver as the expence of the armament ; that, until the kingdom ſhould be in a condition to pay that ſum, the Lubec merchants trading to Sweden ſhould be exempted from all duties on imports or exports ; that all other nations ſhould be prohibited from trading with Sweden, and that ſuch traffic ſhould be deemed illicit ; that Guſtavus ſhould neither conclude a peace, nor even agree to a truce, with Denmark, without the concurrence of the regency of Lubec ; and that in caſe the republic ſhould be attacked by Chriſtian, he ſhould enter Denmark at the head of 20,000 men. Upon theſe hard terms did Guſtavus obtain aſſiſtance from the regency of Lubec ; nor did his dear-bought allies prove very faithful. They did not indeed go over to the enemy ; but in a ſea-fight, where the Danes were entirely in the power of their enemies, they ſuffered them to eſcape, when their whole force might have been entirely deſtroyed. This treachery had well nigh ruined the affairs of Guſtavus ; for Norby was now making preparations effectually to relieve Stockholm ; in which he would probably have succeeded : but at this critical period news arrived that the Danes had unanimouſty revolted, and driven Chriſtian from the throne ; and that the king had retired into Germany, in hopes of being reſtored by the arms of his brother-in law the emperor. On hearing this news, Norby retired with his whole fleet to the iſland of Gothland, leaving but a ſlender garriſon in Calmar. Guſtavus did not fail to improve this opportunity to his own advantage, and quickly made himſelf maſter of Calmar. Mean time Stockholm continued cloſely inveſted ; but Guſtavus thought proper to protract the ſiege until he ſhould get himſelf elected king. Having for this purpoſe called a general diet, the firſt ſtep was to fill up the vacany in the ſenate occaſioned by the maſſacres of Chriſtian. Gustavus had the addreſs to get ſuch nominated as were in his intereſt ; and of conſequence the assembly was no ſooner met, than a ſpeech was made, containing the higheſt encomiums on Guſtavus, ſetting forth in the ſtrongeſt light the many eminent ſervices he had done for his country, and concluding that the ſtates would ſhow themſelves equally ungrateful and blind to their own intereſt if they did not immediately elect him king. This propoſal was acceded to by ſuch tumultuous acclamations that it was impoſſible to collect the votes ; ſo that Guſtavus himſelf acknowledged, that their affection exceeded his merit, and was more agreeable to him than the effects of their gratitude. He was urged to have the ceremony of his coronation immediately performed : but the king having ſome deſigns on the clergy, did not think proper to comply with their requeſt, as he would have been obliged to take an oath to preſerve them</p></body></text></TEI>