<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T20:11:15Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>twiſted or hare-lip suture. The firſt commonly made of ſilver, with a movable ſteel point ; the other of gold. See n⁰ 157.</p><p>Fig. 16. The tourniquet now moſt generally uſed. See n⁰ 160.</p><p>Fig. 17. The tenaculum uſed in ſecuring the mouths of bleeding veſſels. See n⁰ 162.</p><p>Fig. 18. A common ſcalpel. See n⁰ 174.</p><p>Fig. 19. A large lancet uſed for opening cavities of different kinds. See n⁰ 174.</p><p>Fig. 20. A blunt-pointed biſtoury. See n⁰ 174.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Plate</hi> CCCCLXXXVIII. fig. 2l. A raſpatory for removing the pericranium in the operation of the trepan. See n 186.</p><p>Fig. 22. The trephine with all its parts connected and ready for uſe. <hi rend="italic">a,</hi> The centre-pin, which can be raised or depreſſed by the slider <hi rend="italic">b. c,</hi> The part where the saw is united to the handle by means of the ſpring <hi rend="italic">d.</hi> See n⁰ 186.</p><p>Fig. 23. Handle of the trepan into which the head of the trephine is to be inſerted at a. See n⁰ 186.</p><p>Fig. 24. A perforator, which can be joined to the handle either of the trephine or trepan. See n⁰ 186.</p><p>Fig. 25. A bruſh for cleaning the teeth of the saw. See n⁰ 186.</p><p>Fig. 26. Forceps for removing the piece of bone when nearly cut through by the trephine or the trepan. See n⁰ 186</p><p>Fig. 26. <hi rend="italic">a,</hi> A levator alſo employed in removing the piece of bone. See n⁰ 186</p><p>Fig. 26. <hi rend="italic">b,</hi> Lenticular for ſmoothing the ragged edge of the perforated bone. See n⁰ 186.</p><p>Fig. 27. A common probe. See n⁰ 187.</p><p>Fig. 28. A directory. See n⁰ 187.</p><p>Fig. 29. A ſpeculum uſed for keeping the eyelids ſeparated, and the eye fixed, in performing various operations upon that organ. See n⁰ 205.</p><p>Fig. 30. A flat curved hook for elevating the upper eyelid, and fixing the eye, in performing various minute operations upon its ſurface. See n⁰ 205.</p><p>Fig. 31. A couching needle. See n⁰ 216.</p><p>Fig. 32. A couching needle for the right eye, fitted for the operator’s right hand. See n⁰ 217.</p><p>Fig. 33. A knife for extracting the cataract. See n⁰ 218.</p><p>Fig. 34. A flat probe for ſcratching the capſule in extracting the cryſtalline lens. See n⁰ 218.</p><p>Fig. 35. A flat probe or ſcoop for aſſiſting in removing the cataract. See n⁰ 218.</p><p>Fig. 36. A knife for extracting the cataract from the right eye. See n⁰ 218.</p><p>Fig. 37. One of Anel's probes for removing obſtructions of the lachrymal ducts. See n⁰ 224.</p><p>Fig. 38. A ſyringe and pipe (by the ſame) for injecting a liquid into the lachrymal ducts. See n⁰ 224.</p><p>Fig. 38. a, A crooked pipe which fits the ſyringe. See n⁰ 224.</p><p>Fig. 39. An inſtrument for compreſſing the lachrymal ſac. See n⁰ 226.</p><p>Fig. 40. A trocar and canula for perforating the os unguis in the operation for fiſtula lachrymalis See n⁰ 229.</p><p>Fig. 41, 42, 43. Inſtruments employed by Mr Pellier in the operation for fiſtula lachrymalis. Fig. 41. A conductor for clearing the naſal duct. Fig. 42. A conical tube to be left in the duct. Fig. 43. A compressor for fixing the tube in its place. See n⁰ 230.</p><p>Fig. 44. A trocar for making an artificial parotid duct. See Chap. XVI, Sect. 1.</p><p>Fig. 4 5. Forceps ſometimes uſed for laying hold of the lip in the operation for hare lip. See n⁰ 231.</p><p>Fig. 46. A pair of ſtrong ſcissars uſed in the operation for hare-lip. See n⁰ 231.</p><p>Fig. 47. Pins uſed in the operation for hare-lip. See n⁰ 231.</p><p>Fig. 48. Gum-phleme. See n⁰ 232.</p><p>Fig. 49. A trocar for perforating the antrum maxillare. See Chap. XVI. Sect. vi.</p><p>Fig. 50. An inſtrument of a tubular form for perforating the antrum maxillare. See as directed in Fig. 49.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Plate</hi> CCCCLXXXIX. Fig. 51. n⁰ 1, 2, 3, 4, 5. I,. A file for removing inequalities upon the teeth. 2, 3, 4, 5, Different forms of inſtruments for removing tartar, &amp;c. from the teeth. See n⁰ 235.</p><p>Fig. 52. n⁰ I, 2, 3. I, 2, Inſtruments for stuffing a hollow tooth. 3, The handle which fits the different inſtruments repreſented by fig 51, 52. See n⁰ ,37.</p><p>Fig. 53. Inſtrument termed a key for extracting teeth. See n⁰ 338.</p><p>Fig. 54. Forceps for extracting teeth. See n⁰ 338.</p><p>Fig. 55, A punch or lever for extracting ſtumps of teeth. See n⁰ 338.</p><p>Fig. 56. Mr Cheſelden’s needle, with an eye near the point, for tying a knot on ſcirrhous tonſils. See n⁰ 242.</p><p>Fig. 57. A ſpeculum oris firſt propoſed by Mr B Bell. See n⁰ 244.</p><p>Fig. 58. Mr Mudge’s inhaler for conveying steams of warm water, &amp;c. to the throat and breaſt. See Chap. XVII. Sect. xi.</p><p>Fig. 59 A ſcarificator for ſcarifying the amygdale, and for opening abſcesses in the throat. See Chap. XVII. Sect xi.</p><p>Fig. 60. Forceps for extracting extraneous ſubſtances from the outer passage of the ear. See n⁰ 246.</p><p>Fig. 61. A ſyringe for waſhing the outer passage of the ear. See n⁰ 247.</p><p>Fit’s. 62, 63. Inſtruments uſed for concentrating sound ire cases of deafneſs. See n⁰ 249.</p><p>Fig. 64. A tube by which the Euſtachian tube may be waſhed in certain caſes of deafneſs See n⁰ 250.</p><p>Fig 65. An inſtrument for perforating the lobes of the ear. See n⁰ 251.</p><p>Fig. 66 An inſtrument recommended by Mr B. Bell for ſupporting the head after the operation for wry neck. See n⁰ 253.</p><p>Fig. 67. An inſtrument invented by Dr Monro for fixing the canula after the operation of bronchotomy. See n⁰ 254.</p><p>Fig. 68. A glaſs for drawing milk from the breaſts of women. See Chap. XX</p><p>Fig 69. A ſilver canula for carrying off pus collected in the thorax. See n⁰ 262.</p><p>P<hi rend="smallcaps">late</hi> CCCCXC. Fig. 70. A bandage for the paracenteſis of the abdomen, originally invented by the late Dr Monro. See n⁰ 264.</p><p>Fig 71 The common round trocar, with a triangular point for tapping tor the aſcites. See n 264.</p><p>Fig 72. Mr André’s lancet-pointed trocar, the canula of which is made of two hollow plates of ſteel ſcrewed together at the larger extrcmity. See n⁰ 264.</p><p>Fig. 73. A director uſed in the operation for hernia. See n⁰ 278.</p></body></text></TEI>