<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T20:12:04Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>everything rather than ſuffer his army to be waſted by famine, advanced towards Perleberg, a place cloſely blocked up by the enemy. Here he drove from an advantageous poſt four regiments oſ Saxon cuiraſſiers, having killed or taken priſoners 400 men ; after which he ſoon forced them to a general engagement. The numbers were very unequal, Bannier’s army amounting to 9000 horſe and 7000 foot, and the Saxons to 15,000 horſe and 13 battalions of foot. The battle began with great fury ; the right wing of the Swedes was almost oppreſſed by numbers before the left could come to their assiſtance. They were ten times driven back, and as often returned to the charge. At last they made ſuch a deſperate effort, that the enemy were entirely broken and defeated. Five thouſand were killed on the ſpot, 3000 wounded, and as many taken priſoners, together with 150 colours and ſtandards, and ſeveral pieces of cannon.</p><p>Thus ended the campaign of 1636, in a manner highly honourable to the Swedes. Some fruitleſs negotiations were ſet on foot during the winter ; but theſe coming to nothing, Bannier quitted his winter-quarters very early in the ſeaſon ; and falling upon eight regiments of Saxons cantoned at Eulenburg, purified them to Torgau, where he obliged them to ſurrender at diſcretion. Another party of Saxons was defeated in the neighbourhood of Leipſic ; after which he propoſed inverting that city. But in this project he was diſappointed by the Imperralists penetrating into Thuringia. He then called in all his detachments, with a view to prevent them from croſſing a river named <hi rend="italic">Sala ;</hi> but in this alſo he was diſappointed. However, he had the good fortune to defeat 2000 Imperialists near Pegau, and to deſtroy ſeveral detachments that attempted to obstruct his march. Yet, notwithſtanding all theſe ſucceſſes, Bannier found his ſituation every day more straitened, from the continual increaſe of the enemy’s forces ; which obliged him at last to retreat into Pomerania, out of which he ſoon drove count Gallas.</p><p>The affairs of the Swedes were now once more reduced to the brink of ruin, through the unguarded conduct of general Wrangel, who had alſo an army in Pomerania. After Bannier had driven count Gallas out of the province as above mentioned, Wrangel, imagining himſelf perfectly ſecure, cantoned his troops, and extended his quarters, the better to accommodate his army. But Gallas, being informed of this proceeding, ſuddenly returned, ravaged all Upper Pomerania, and reduced the towns of Uſedom, Demmin, and Wollin ; after which, leaving garriſons in the fortreſſes, he returned to his winter-quarters in Saxony.</p><p>This unfortunate campaign counterbalanced all the advantages of the former. Wrangel was ſo struck with the ſuddenneſs of the blow, that he could take no meaſures for oppoſition. Some of the Swediſh allies again fell off, and took up arms against them. In 1638, the Swediſh affairs again began to revive in this quarter, through the excellent conduct of Bannier, who defeated count Gallas with the loſs of 3000 men killed and taken priſoners. Pursuing his good fortune, he ſo harassed the count, that he obliged him in great haste to repaſs the Elbe, and take ſhelter in the hereditary dominions of Austria. Great as Bannier’s exploits had been, however, they were eclipſed by thoſe of duke Bernard. That general had ſo increaſed his army in the Proteſtant cantons of Switzerland, and in Franche Comte, that he found himſelf in a condition to act without the aſſistance of the French, who indeed were but treacherous allies. Advancing to the Rhine, he ſeized on Seckingen and Lassuburg, and laid ſiege to Rheinfield. The Imperialists, in conjunction with the troops of Bavaria, advanced to the relief of the place. An engagement enſued, in which the victory was diſputed : the enemy threw ſuccours into the city, and the duke withdrew his army. Within a month he gave them battle a ſecond time; and ſo completely defeated them, that only one Imperial officer above the rank of a captain eſcaped being killed or taken priſoner. He then renewed the ſiege of Rheinfield ; which he reduced, as well as ſeveral other important places. Advancing to Briſac, he blocked it up with a deſign of forcing the garrison to ſurrender by famine. General Gotz, with 12,000 men, attempted to throw in 1000 waggons of proviſions; but he was defeated, with the loſs of all his men except 2500. Duke Charles of Lorrain, with 4000 men, joined the remains of Gotz’s army, in order to relieve the town ; but being ſurpriſed by Bernard, his whole army was cut in pieces. A third attempt was made by Gotz, but it proved as unſucceſsful as the former ; and the place being reduced to great ſtraits, was obliged to capitulate.</p><p>In January 1639, the two victorious generals Bernard and Bannier prepared to attack the enemy on their own ground. Bannier made an irruption into the territories or Anhalt and Halberstadt. Leaving his infantry behind, he puſhed on with his cavalry, and ſurpriſed Salis, grand-maſter of the Imperial artillery. After a bloody conflict, the Swedes gained a complete victory, ſeven regiments of the enemy being cut in pieces. Next entering Saxony, he defeated four regiments of the enemy, obliging a much larger body to take ſhelter under the cannon of Dreſden. Hearing that the Saxons were encamped near Chemnitz, where they waited to be joined by the Imperialists, he reſolved to attack them before this junction could be effected. The ſame good fortune still attended his arms, and the Saxons were almost all killed or taken. Bannier next entering into Bohemia, laid the country under contribution ; after which, returning croſs the Elbe, he fell on general Hofskirk, who was encamped near Brandeiz with 10 regiments of horſe and ſeveral battalions of foot. Him he defeated with the loſs of 2000 men. The remains of the Imperial forces were purſued to the walls of Prague, and the generals Hofskirk and Montecuculi were taken priſoners. Yet, notwithstanding theſe constant ſucceſſes, the enemies of Bannier multiplied daily. He had expected an inſurrection in his favour in Sileſia or Bohemia ; but no ſuch event took place. The Protestant princes, overawed by the enemy, did not ſend him the neceſſary aſſistance. Undiſmayed, however, by difficulties or danger, Bannier performed wonders. He defeated a body of Imperialists at Glatz ; three times he drove the Saxons from their camp at Firn ; and yet was forced to evacuate the place, becauſe he could not ſpare a garriſon. His army being deftitute of the means of recruiting, was conſiderably diminiſhed in number ; yet with it he reduced a number of towns, and obtained a variety of other important advantages, when on a ſudden all his hopes were blasted by the death of the duke of Saxe-Weymar ; poiſoned, as was ſuppoſed, by the French, who were deſirous of getting the town of Briſac into their hands, from which the duke prevented them.</p><p>The difficulties to which Bannier was now reduced proved extreme. The French monarch took upon him to diſpoſe of the army and conqueſts of Bernard as he thought proper. Briſac, and other places of importance, be kept to himſelf ; after getting poſſession of which, the French endeavoured, as much as poſſible, to ruin the army. In the mean time, the Imperial army under Piccolomini, in the Netherlands, was prodigiouſly augmented ; and the archduke Leopold-William, in quality of generaliſſimo, was assembling his whole strength to cruſh the Swedes at once. Bannier, however, did not deſpair. George duke of Lunenburg having conceived ſome diſgust at the emperor, Bannier hoped</p></body></text></TEI>