<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T20:12:29Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>names through the moſt diſtant countries, and ſhook the foundations of the greateſt empires. The principal nobility and gentry of Sweden are naturally brave, polite, and hoſpitable ; they have high and warm notions of honour, and are jealous of their national intereſts. The dreſs of the common people is almoſt the ſame with that of Denmark : the better sort are infatuated with French modes and faſhion. The common diverſions of the Swedes are, ſkating, running races in sledges, and ſailing in yachts upon the ice. They are not fond of marrying their daughters when young, as they have little to ſpare in their own life-time. The women go to plough, threſh out the corn, row upon the water, ſerve the brick layers, carry burdens, and do all the common drudgeries in huſbandry.</p><p>Chriſtianity was introduced here in the 9th century. Their religion is Lutheran, which was propagated among them by Gustavus Vaſa, about the year 1523, as we have already related. The Swedes are ſurpriſingly uniform and unremitting in religions matters ; and have ſuch an aversion to Popery, that caſtration is the fate of every Roman Catholic prieſt diſcovered in their country. The archbiſhop of Upsal has a revenue of about 400 l. a-year ; and has under him thirteen ſuffragans, besides superintendants, with moderate ſtipends. No clergyman has the leaſt direction in the affairs of ſtate ; but their morals, and the ſanctity of their lives, endear them ſo much to the people, that the government would repent making them its enemies. Their churches are neat, and often ornamented. A body of eccleſiaſtſeal laws and canons direct their religious economy. A converſion to Popery, or a long continuance under excommunication, which cannot pass without the king’s permiſſion, is punished by impriſonment and exile.</p><p>The Swediſh language is a dialect oſ the Teutonic, and reſembles that of Denmark. The Swediſh nobility and gentry are, in general, more converſant in polite literature than thoſe of many other more flouriſhing states. They have of late exhibited ſome noble ſpecimens of their munificence for the improvement of literature and ſcience, particularly natural hiſtory.</p><p>The Swediſh commonalty ſubſiſts by agriculture, mining, grazing, hunting, and fiſhing. Their materials for traffic are the bulky and uſeful commodities of maſts, beams, and other sorts of timber for ſhipping ; tar, pitch, bark of trees, potaſh, wooden utenſils, hides, flax, hemp, peltry, furs, copper, lead, iron, cordage, and fiſh.</p><p>Even the manufacturing of iron was introduced into Sweden ſo late as the 16th century ; for till that time they sold their own crude ore to the Hanſe-towns, and bought it back again manufactured into utenſils. About the middle of the 17th century, by the aſſiſtance of the Dutch and Flemings, they let up ſome manulactures of glaſs, ſtarch, tin, woollen, ſilk, ſoap, leather-dreſſing, and saw-mills. Bookſelling was at that time a trade unknown in Sweden. They have ſince had ſugar-baking, tobacco-plantations, and manufactures of ſail-cloth, cotton, fuſtian, and other stuffs ; alſo of linen, alum, brimstone, paper-mills, and gunpowdermills. Vaſt quantities of copper, braſs, ſteel, and iron, are now wrought in Sweden, dug from mines, ſome of them more than 1100 feet deep. The iron mine of Dannemora, which is much the moſt profitable of any of thoſe with which every part of Sweden abounds, is ſaid to yield 60lb. of metal in a 100lb. of ore, and the others about 30lb. The iron extracted from this is known in Europe under the name oſ <hi rend="italic">Oregrund ;</hi> which name is derived from a ſea-port on the Baltic. A large portion of it is employed by different nations for making the beſt ſteel. The mine was diſcovered in 1470. The unwrought ore was firſt ſold to the merchants of Lubeck. It was not until the reign of Guſtavus Vaſa that the Swedes worked it themſelves. It is asserted, that the mine of Dannemora yields about 49,000 ſtones of bar-iron <hi rend="italic">per</hi> year, which is ſuppoſed to be one tenth part of the quantity which all the iron-mines of Sweden produce. Of this product, amounting to 400,000 ſtones, 300,000 are annually exported ; the remainder is manufactured at home. It is calculated that no leſs than 25,600 men are employed in mining, and the branches immediately connected with it, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> 4000 for breaking the rocks, either by exploſion or manual labour; 10,800 to hew timber and burn it into charcoal ; 2000 are employed in smelting ; 1800 in tranſporting the metal from the furnaces to the forges ; 6co in tranſporting sand, fuel, &amp;c. 4000 for tranſporting the charcoal, and 2400 at the forges. They have alſo founderies for cannon, forgeries for fire-arms and anchors, armories, wire and flatting-mills, mills alſo for fulling, and for boring and ſtamping : and of late they have built many ſhips for ſale.</p><p>There are likewiſe in Sweden ſome ſilver mines, of which that of <hi rend="italic">Salha,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Salhberg,</hi> is the richeſt as well as the moſt ancient. It existed ſo early as 1188, and, during the whole of the 14th century, it yielded 24,000 marks of ſilver <hi rend="italic">per annum.</hi> In the 15th century the quantity was diminiſhed to 20,000. In the reign of Charles X. it give only 2000, and it furniſhes at preſent ſtill leſs, the ore yielding only one ounce of pure metal <hi rend="italic">per</hi> quintal. The chief gallery where the pureſt ſilver was obtained having fallen in, is not yet cleared, notwithstanding their inceſſant labour. They are alſo digging pits in a perpendicular direction, in order to arrive at the principal vein, which extends itſelf from the north to the ſouth-eaſt. Formerly lead employed in ſeparating the metal was imported from England ; but the mine furniſhes at preſent a sufficient quantity for the purpoſe.</p><p>Certain towns in Sweden, being 24 in number, are called <hi rend="italic">Staple-towns,</hi> where the merchants are allowed to import and export commodities in their own ſhips. Thoſe towns which have no foreign commerce, though lying near the ſea, are called <hi rend="italic">land-towns.</hi> A third kind are termed m<hi rend="italic">ine-towns,</hi> as belonging to mine-districts. The Swedes, about the year 1752, had greatly increaſed their exports, and diminiſhed their imports, moſt part of which arrive or are ſent off in Swediſh ſhips; the Swedes having now a kind of navigation act like that of the Engliſh. Those promiſing appearances were, however, blaſted by the madneſs and jealousies of the Swediſh government ; and the people ſo oppreſſed with taxes, that ſome important revolution was daily expected in that kingdom.</p><p>The revenue of Sweden, ſince the unfortunate wars of Charles XII. has been greatly reduced. Her gold and ſilver ſpecies, in the reign of Ad. Frederic, aroſe chiefly from the king’s German dominions. Formerly, the crown-lands, pollmoney, tithes, mines, and other articles, are ſaid to have produced a million ſterling. The payments that are made in copper, which is here the chief medium of commerce, is extremely inconvenient ; ſome of thoſe pieces being as large as tiles ; and a cart or wheelbarrow is often required to carry home a moderate ſum. The Swedes, however, have gold ducats, and eight-mark pieces of ſilver, valued each at 5s. 2d. and the ſubſidies paid them by France help to increaſe their currency.</p><p>No country in the world has produced greater heroes or braver troops than the Swedes ; and yet they cannot be ſaid to maintain a Handing army, as their forces conſiſt of a regulated militia. The cavalry is clothed, armed, and maintained, by a rate raised upon the nobility and gentry, according to their estates ; and the infantry by the peaſants. Each province is obliged to find its proportion of ſoldiers,</p></body></text></TEI>