<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb09-22-s04-0097-01" facs="encyclopediabrit22newyrich_raw_0113.jp2" type="entry"><p><label>SIREN</label>, . <hi rend="italic">Siren lacertina,</hi> Lin. <hi rend="italic">(Syst. Nat.,</hi> i., Addenda), is an animal belonging to the class Amphibia <hi rend="italic">(q.v.).</hi> It forms the type of the family <hi rend="italic">Sirenid</hi> <hi rend="italic">æ</hi> <hi rend="italic">,</hi> called by Prof. Huxley <hi rend="italic">Trachystomata,</hi> among the group <hi rend="italic">Perennibranchiata.</hi> The body is elongate and eel-like, only the anterior limbs being present ; the posterior are entirely wanting. The anterior limbs are short and feeble, and each is furnished with four digits pointed at the ends. The head is small ; the snout is short and broad, and the nostrils are placed at its extreme end. The tongue is free anteriorly. The jaws are destitute of teeth and covered with a horny sheath like a beak. There are numerous teeth on the vomer, arranged in two large patches converging anteriorly. The eyes are very small. On each side of the neck are three branched external gills attached to the first, second, and third branchial arches ; and below the gills are three reduced branchial apertures. The tail is shorter than the body, much compressed, and provided with a median membranous fin ; the tail terminates in a point. The skin is smooth, and black in colour, sometimes sprinkled with white dots. <hi rend="italic">Siren</hi> grows to a large size, some specimens measuring 3 feet in length ; the largest example in the British Museum is 670 mm. or about 2 feet 3 inches. The animal inhabits the stagnant waters of marshes in South Carolina and Texas.</p><p>The only other member of the family <hi rend="italic">Sirenid</hi> <hi rend="italic">æ</hi> is <hi rend="italic">Pseudobranchus striatus</hi> (Gray, <hi rend="italic">Brit. Mus. Cat.—Batrachia,</hi> 1st ed.). This animal resembles <hi rend="italic">Siren</hi> in most respects, but has only a single branchial aperture on each side, and only three digits to the anterior limb. Its colour is dark-brown with a broad yellow band on each side and a narrower one inferiorly. It occurs in Georgia, but seems to be very rare ; there are two specimens in the Paris Musée, none in the British Museum.</p><p>Figures of <hi rend="italic">Siren lacertina</hi> are to be found in the following works :—Cuvier in Humboldt’s <hi rend="italic">Obs. Zool.,</hi> i. pl. 11 ; Daudin, <hi rend="italic">Reptiles,</hi> viii. pl. 49 ; Holbr., <hi rend="italic">N. Amer. Herp.,</hi> pl. 34. <hi rend="italic">Pseudobranchus striatus</hi> is figured in Duméril and Bibron, <hi rend="italic">Erpétologie Générale,</hi> pi. 96; Holbr., <hi rend="italic">loc.</hi> <hi rend="italic">cit</hi>., pl. 36; Leconte, <hi rend="italic">Ann. Lyc. N.</hi> <hi rend="italic">Y</hi>., 1824, pl. 4 (under name <hi rend="italic">Siren striata).</hi></p></div></body></text></TEI>