<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb09-22-s04-0189-01" facs="encyclopediabrit22newyrich_raw_0205.jp2" type="entry"><p><label>SNAKE-ROOT</label>, . In most countries where snakes abound some root or herb is used by the natives as an antidote for the bites of venomous species, and many herbs have consequently received the name of snake-root. Botani-cally speaking, the name properly belongs to <hi rend="italic">Ophiorrhiza Mungos,</hi> L., a plant of the Cinchona family, used in the East Indies for the purpose above indicated. In medicine, however, the roots of <hi rend="italic">Aristolochia Serpentaria,</hi> L., <hi rend="italic">Polygala Senega,</hi> L., or <hi rend="italic">Cimicifuga racemosa,</hi> Elliott, are alike understood by this name, being distinguished respectively as the Virginian, Seneka, and Black Snake-roots. The first is now employed as an aromatic antiseptic tonic in typhoid fever, the second as a stimulant expectorant in bronchitis, and the third as a sedative in rheumatic or inflammatory affections, especially in muscular rheumatism and lumbago. The root of <hi rend="italic">Aristolochia reticulata,</hi> Nutt., which is known in the United States as Red River or Texan Snake-root, is the kind most frequently met with in the United Kingdom as Serpentary or Virginian Snake-root. (See Guaco.)</p><p>The roots or rhizome of <hi rend="italic">Liatris spicata,</hi> Willd., <hi rend="italic">Eryngium aquaticum,</hi> L., and <hi rend="italic">Eupatorium altissimum,</hi> L., have all been used in North America for snake-bites, the first two being known as Button Snake-root and the last as White Snake-root. The rhizome of <hi rend="italic">Asarum canadense,</hi> L., passes under the name of Canadian Snake-root. All of these contain acrid or aromatic principles which, when a warm decoction of the drug is taken, exercise a powerfully diaphoretic or, in some cases, diuretic action, to which any benefit that may be derived from their use must be attributed.</p></div></body></text></TEI>