<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T20:43:44Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Sonrhai<hi rend="italic"> or </hi>Songhai<hi rend="italic"> : An historical race whose empire stretched in the 16th century from the northern bend of the Niger to the Atlantic and Morocco; speech of a monosyllabic type, still current in the Timbuktu district and oases of Western Sahara ; population 2,000,000.</hi></p><p>Tombo, Mosso, Gurma<hi rend="italic"> : Three little known Negro peoples west of the Niger, within the great bend ; affinities uncertain ; form semi-independent petty states, apparently tributary to Moassina and Gando.</hi></p><p>Nupe<hi rend="italic"> or </hi>Nufe:<hi rend="italic"> Large Negro nation along both sides of the Niger from Rabba to the Binue confluence, subject to Gando.</hi></p><p>Yoruba <hi rend="italic">; Powerful Negro people between lower Niger and Dahomey ; capital Ilosin ; Mohammedans, pagans, and Christians (Protestant).</hi></p><p>Batta·.<hi rend="italic"> The chief Negro people in Adamawa, now subject to the Fulahs; pagans and Mohammedans.</hi></p><p>Haussa <hi rend="italic">: Largest, most widespread, and intelligent of all the Sudanese Negro peoples, mainly between the Niger and Bornu; speech very musical, the chief commercial medium in Western and Central Soudan, and current in parts of Tripolitana; shows distinct traces of Hamitic influences (Krause); mostly Mohammedans.</hi></p><p>Mosgu<hi rend="italic"> or </hi>Masa<hi rend="italic"> ; widespread Negro family between Lake Tchad and Adamawa and stretching east to the Shari ; chief subdivisions—Mandara, Margi, Logon, Gamergu, Margomi, Keribina; mostly pagans and uncultured.</hi></p><p>Yedina (Buduma)<hi rend="italic"> and </hi>Kuri<hi rend="italic"> : Predatory Negro tribes in the islands of Lake Tchad; appear to be related to the Kolokos or Mekari of Logon and Bornu ; nominal Mohammedans ; population 30,000.</hi></p><p>Baghirmi·.<hi rend="italic"> The dominant people in Baghirmi; cultured Mohammedans; very industrious and skilled weavers and dyers; population over a million.</hi></p><p>Maha ; <hi rend="italic">The chief Negro nation in Wadai, mainly in the Wara and Abeshr districts, about the headstreams of the Batha.</hi></p><p>Fur<hi rend="italic"> or </hi>For<hi rend="italic"> ; The dominant race in Dar-Fur, which takes its name from them ; akin to the Nubas; chief subdivision Kunjara.</hi></p><p>Nubas <hi rend="italic">; Large Negro nation ; Jebel Nuba, and other parts of Kordofan, the original stock of the Nile Nubians; chief subdivisions—Kargo, Kulfan, Kolaji, Tumali.</hi></p><p>Nilotic Negroes ·.<hi rend="italic"> Shilluks, Dinkas, Bongos, Baris, A-Madi (Mittu), and many others about the Bahr el-Jebel and south-western tributaries of the white Nile.</hi></p><p>Funj<hi rend="italic"> : A very mixed Negroid race, Senaar.</hi></p><p>Hamites—Pure and Mixed.</p><p>Tuaregs<hi rend="italic"> : A main branch of the Berber race, dominant throughout the Western Sahara and southern steppes ; powerful, especially in the Timbuktu district and on the north frontier of Bornu.</hi></p><p>Sorinka<hi rend="italic"> or </hi>Assuanek<hi rend="italic"> : Called also Serekuli or Serrakolet, </hi>i.e.,<hi rend="italic"> “ white people ”; half-caste Tuareg and Negro nation scattered in small communities front the Niger to the Atlantic, and numerous especially in Senegambia and Moassina ; cuitured Mohammedans, and active traders.</hi></p><p>Fulahs<hi rend="italic"> : The most powerful, intelligent, and widespread of all the Soudanese peoples; from their original home in Senegambia (Futa-Toro, Futa-Jallo) have spread since the 18th century throughout Western and Central Soudan, and as far east as Dar-Fur, everywhere propagating Islam, overthrowing the native Haussa and other states, and founding new kingdoms in the Niger basin, in Adamawa, and Central Soudan ; are called Fellani by the Haussas, Fulda by the Arabs, Felláta by the Kanuri, the term meaning “ fair” or “ light coloured " ; pure type, distinctly Caucasic, regular features, long black hair, brown or ruddy complexion, slim well-proportioned figures; but the language, which presents several remarkable features, shows only faint traces of Berber influence, and appears on the whole to be essentially a Negro form of speech, adopted probably during residence from the remotest times in Negroland; population seven to eight millions.</hi></p><p>Dasas : <hi rend="italic">The southern branch of the Tibus, chiefly in Kanem and northern Bornu; type and speech show distinct Negro influences.</hi></p><p>Kanembu : <hi rend="italic">The people of Kanem, with settlements in eastern Bornu ; also originally Tibus, but betraying still more decided Negro influence.</hi></p><p>Kanuri<hi rend="italic"> : The ruling race in Bornu ; speech a development of the Dasa and Kanem; type half-caste Tibu and Negro.</hi></p><p>Zogháwa, Baele, Ennedi<hi rend="italic"> ; Mixed Tibu and Negro tribes; northern Dar-Fur, originally from Borku and Wanganya, Eastern Sahara ; speech akin to Dasa.</hi></p><p>Semites.</p><p>Aulád Soleimán Arabs<hi rend="italic"> : In Kanem.</hi></p><p>Aulád Rashid, Mahámid:<hi rend="italic"> South-east of Borku, and in Dar-Fur.</hi></p><p>Salámát, Aulád Hamed<hi rend="italic"> : Between the lower Shari and Bahr el-Ghazál.</hi></p><p>Hamr, Hamrán<hi rend="italic"> : Kordofan.</hi></p><p>Kababish : <hi rend="italic">“ Goatherds ; ” widespread along west side Nile, from Kordofan to Dongola.</hi></p><p>Bakkára<hi rend="italic"> : “Cowherds; ” south of the Kababish to left bank of Bahr el-Arab.</hi></p><p>Politically Western and Central Soudan are divided into eight independent and semi-independent states, which in their order from west to east are as under : —</p><p><hi rend="italic">Bambarra,</hi> divided into two nearly equal sections by the Joliba, which traverses it from south-west to north-east, is ruled by the Negro Bambarras of Mandingo stock. It has recently been brought under the influence of the French penetrating eastwards from their possessions on the Senegal. The capital is Sego, on the right bank of the Joliba.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Moassina, Gando, Sokoto, Adamawa,</hi> the four so-called “Fulah States,” occupy the Niger basin between Bambarra and the Binue confluence, the whole of the Binue basin, and the region lying between the Niger and Bornu. <hi rend="italic">Moassina</hi> (Massina) lies on both banks of the Niger from Bambarra to Kabara, the port of Timbuktu, and is peopled by Fulahs, Bambarras, and Sonrhais ; capital Hamda-Alahi, on the right bank of the Niger, below Jenne, which is its chief trading place. Timbuktu, with surrounding district constitutes a separate territory governed by a kadia, or hereditary mayor, who lately sent an envoy to Paris for the purpose of seeking French protection against the rival Tuareg and Fulah tribes. <hi rend="italic">Gando,</hi> so called from its capital on an eastern tributary of the Niger, stretches along the main stream southwards to the Binue confluence, including the Nufe territory and part of Yoruba. The lower part is extremely fertile, abounding in cotton, indigo, rice, and all varieties of African grains. It comes within the limits of the region over which the British protectorate has recently been extended. Besides the capital, there are several large towns, such as Bida (30,000 to 50,000 inhabitants) in the north ; Rabba (40,000 to 50,000), head of the steam navigation on the Niger, and a chief station on the great trade route running from Lagos on the</p><p>Guinea Coast northwards to Gando and Sokoto ; Egga (8000), on the left bank of the Niger, centre of the British trade ; Lokoja, facing the Binue confluence, an English factory, headquarters of an Anglican mission and seat of a Negro bishop. <hi rend="italic">Sokoto,</hi> sometimes spoken of as the “ empire of Sokoto,” is the largest and most powerful of all the Soudanese states, stretching from Gando to Bornu, and from the Binue northwards to the Sahara (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Sokoto).</hi> In it are absorbed all the former “ Haussa States,” and to it Adamawa is also tributary. The inhabitants are chiefly Fulahs and Haussas, intermixed with many aboriginal Negro peoples, especially in the south and south-east. The land is generally fertile, yielding rich crops of cereals, cotton, tobacco, indigo, sugar, yams, black pepper, ginger, melons. The capital and residence of the sultan is Sokoto, in the extreme north-west. Other large towns are—Katsena, before the Fulah invasion a place of 100,000 inhabitants, now reduced to 7000; Kano, in Barth’s time the “London of Soudan,” and still with 50,000 souls (Matteucci) ; Wurnu (15,000) ; Gombe, in the province of Calam (20,000) ; Yakoba, or Garu n-Bauchi (150,000) ; Keffi Abd es-Senga (30,000), in Zegzeg, a great centre of the ivory trade, and converging point of the two great caravan routes from the north (Kano) and the west (Egga). <hi rend="italic">Adamawa,</hi> so named from its Fulah conqueror Adama, and formerly known as Fumbina, or “Southland,” is ruled by a Fulah vassal of Sokoto, who keeps in subjection the Battas and innumerable other Negro peoples; it lies between Sokoto, Bornu, and Baghirmi, merging southwards in the unexplored equatorial region back of the Cameroons. The capital is Yola, at the northern foot of Mount Alantika. Adamawa appears to be one of the finest and healthiest regions in Africa, splendidly diversified with lofty highlands, fertile valleys, and grassy plains, overgrown in some places with forests of bananas, baobabs, and plantains, in others yielding abundant harvests of cereals, cotton, and indigo. The horses and cattle introduced by the Fulahs thrive well on the rich pastures, and elephants abound in the woodlands.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Bornu,</hi> with <hi rend="italic">Kanem,</hi> in the north, now reduced, and the tributary state of <hi rend="italic">Logon</hi> in the south, completely encircles Lake Tchad, except at the south-east corner, where Baghirmi is wedged in between Logon and Wadai ; it is mostly a flat low-lying region with fertile plains yielding durrah, maize, cotton, and indigo, watered by the Komadugu, Logon, and Shari, all of which flood their banks for miles during the rainy season. The ruling race are the Kanuri, cultured but fanatical Mohammedans of mixed Tibu and Negro stock. The capital of Bornu is Kuka (50,000 to 60,000 inhabitants), near the west coast of Lake Tchad, a great centre of the Soudanese trade with the Sahara and Tripolitana, and terminus of the main caravan route from Murzuk (Fezzan) across the desert to the Tchad basin ; the capital of Logon is Logon-birni, residence of a vassal prince. Population of Bornu estimated at 5,000,000.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Baghirmi,</hi> a Negro state, since 1871 tributary to Wadai, comprises the rich and well-watered plains of the lower Shari, with undefined southern limits. Capital Masena ; population about 1,500,000, of whom three-fourths Baghirmi, the rest Kotokos, Fulahs, and Arabs.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Wadai,</hi> a powerful Mohammedan state occupying the whole region between Baghirmi and Kanem in the west and Dar-Fur in the east, and claiming exclusive ivory and slave-hunting rights in the southern (upper) Shari basin. The capital is Abeshr, on a head-stream of the Batha. The country is mainly a hilly plateau rising to 3000 feet above the sea, and yielding good crops of maize, dukhn, durrah, cotton, indigo. Population four to six millions, chiefly Mabas and other Negroes, and numerous Arab tribes, with</p><p>some scattered Baghirmi, Fulah, and Kanuri settlements.</p><p>Eastern Soudan, comprising Dar-Fur, Kordofan, Senaar, Taka, and the Negro countries on the White Nile and its south-western tributaries, respectively called the Equatorial and Bahr-Gazal Provinces, belonged politically to Egypt till the rebellion of the late Mahdi. Since his death in 1885 most of these provinces appear to have lapsed into a state of anarchy and barbarism, in which few vestiges remain of the peace and order introduced by the European officers of the khedive. The Equatorial Province, however, and the Suakin district have been exempt from these troubles,—the former being still held till 1886 by the governor, Emin Bey, for the khedive, while in the latter the natives themselves succeeded in the same year in putting down the “rebels ” or party of Osman Digma. For details of Eastern Soudan, see articles <hi rend="smallcaps">Nile, Nubia,</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Senaar.</hi>	(A. H. K.)</p><p>SOULT, <hi rend="smallcaps">Nicolas Jean de Dieu,</hi> duke of Dalmatia and marshal of France (1769-1851), was born at Saint- Amans-la-Bastide (now in department of the Tarn), on March 29, 1769, and was the elder son of a country notary at that place. He was fairly well educated, and intended for the bar, but his father’s death when he was still a boy made it necessary for him to seek his fortune, and he enlisted as a private in the regiment of royal infantry in 1785. His superior education ensured his promotion to the rank of sergeant after six years’ service, and in July</p></body></text></TEI>