<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T20:45:29Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>drop that <hi rend="italic">n,</hi> resume it in the plural before <hi rend="italic">s : homin-em</hi> makes <hi rend="italic">ome </hi>in the singular and <hi rend="italic">omens</hi> in the plural ; <hi rend="italic">asin-um</hi> makes <hi rend="italic">ase</hi> and <hi rend="italic">asens.</hi> (2) Words terminating in <hi rend="italic">s</hi> surd or sonant and in <hi rend="italic">x </hi>anciently formed their plural by adding to the singular the syllable <hi rend="italic">es (bras, brasses ; pres, preses ; matrix, matrixes),</hi> but subsequently, from about the 15th century, the Castilian influence substituted <hi rend="italic">os,</hi> so that one now hears <hi rend="italic">brasses, presos, mateixos.</hi> The words in <hi rend="italic">tx, sc, st</hi> have been assimilated to words in <hi rend="italic">s (x) ;</hi> from <hi rend="italic">bosch</hi> we originally had the plural <hi rend="italic">bosches,</hi> but now <hi rend="italic">boscos</hi> ; from <hi rend="italic">trist, tristes, </hi>but now <hi rend="italic">tristos.</hi> For these last in <hi rend="italic">st</hi> there exists a plural formation which is more in accordance with the genius of the language, and consists in the suppression of the <hi rend="italic">s</hi> before the <hi rend="italic">t ; </hi>from <hi rend="italic">aquest, </hi>for example, we have now side by side the two plurals <hi rend="italic">aguestos, </hi>in the Castilian manner, and <hi rend="italic">aquets.</hi> The article is <hi rend="italic">lo, los</hi> (pronounced <hi rend="italic">lu, lus</hi> in a portion of the domain), fem. <hi rend="italic">la, les (las'). </hi>Some instances of <hi rend="italic">li</hi> occur in the ancient tongue, applying indifferently to the nominative and the objective case ; <hi rend="italic">el</hi> applying to the singular is also not wholly unknown. On the north-western border of Catalonia, and in the island of Majorca, the article is not a derivative from <hi rend="italic">ille</hi> but from <hi rend="italic">ipse</hi> (sing, masc. <hi rend="italic">es</hi> or <hi rend="italic">so,</hi> fem. <hi rend="italic">sa ; </hi>pl. masc. <hi rend="italic">es,</hi> and also <hi rend="italic">ets,</hi> which appears to come from <hi rend="italic">istos,—ets</hi> for <hi rend="italic">ests,</hi> like <hi rend="italic">aguets</hi> for <hi rend="italic">aquests,—</hi>fern. <hi rend="italic">sas).</hi> Compare the corresponding Sardinian forms <hi rend="italic">su, sa,</hi> pl. <hi rend="italic">sos, sas.</hi> On the pronouns it has only to be remarked that the modern language has borrowed from Castilian the composite forms <hi rend="italic">nosaltres</hi> and <hi rend="italic">vosaltres</hi> (pronounced also <hi rend="italic">nosaltros </hi>and <hi rend="italic">nosatrus),</hi> as also the form <hi rend="italic">vosté</hi>, <hi rend="italic">vusté</hi> (Castilian <hi rend="italic">usted</hi> for <hi rend="italic">vuestra mereed).</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Conjugation.—</hi>Catalan, and especially modern Catalan, has greatly narrowed the domain of the 2d conjugation in ēre ; a large number of verbs of this conjugation have been treated as if they belonged to the 3d in ere; debere makes <hi rend="italic">deure,</hi> videre, <hi rend="italic">veure, </hi>and alongside of <hi rend="italic">haber,</hi> which answers to habere, there is a form <hi rend="italic">heure</hi> which points to habere. A curious fact, aud one which has arisen since the 15th century, is the addition of a paragogic <hi rend="italic">r</hi> to those infinitives which are accented on the radical ; in a portion of the Catalan domain one hears <hi rend="italic">creurer, νeurer.</hi> Some verbs originally belonging to the conjugation in ēre have passed over into that in <hi rend="italic">ir</hi> ; for example tenēre gives <hi rend="italic">tenir</hi> alongside of <hi rend="italic">tindre,</hi> remanēre <hi rend="italic">romanir</hi> and <hi rend="italic">romandre.</hi> In the gerundive and in the present participle Catalan differs from Provençal in still distinguishing the conjugation in <hi rend="italic">ir</hi> from that in <hi rend="italic">er, re,—</hi>saying, for example, <hi rend="italic">sentint.</hi> As in Provençal, the past participle of a large number of verbs of the 2d and 3d conjugations is formed, not from the infinitive, but from the perfect <hi rend="italic">(pogut, volgut, tingut</hi> suggest the perfects <hi rend="italic">poeh, volch, tinch,</hi> and not the infinitives <hi rend="italic">poder, voler, tenir).</hi> In the present indicative and subjunctive many verbs in <hi rend="italic">ir</hi> take the inchoative form already described, by lengthening the radical in the three persons of the singular and in the third person of the plural by means of the syllable <hi rend="italic">esc (ise). agrahir</hi> has the present indicative <hi rend="italic">agraesch, agraheixes, agraheix, agraheixen,</hi> the present subjunctive <hi rend="italic">agraesea, -as, -a, -an</hi> (or more usually now <hi rend="italic">agraesgui, -is, -i, -in).</hi> The old perfect of the conjugation in <hi rend="italic">ar </hi>had <hi rend="italic">é</hi> (also <hi rend="italic">i)</hi> in the 1st pers. sing, and <hi rend="italic">-á</hi> in the 3d ; alongside of the <hi rend="italic">-ά,</hi> which is proper to Catalan exclusively, we also find, in the first period of the language, <hi rend="italic">-et</hi> as in Provençal. Subsequently the perfect of the three conjugations has admitted forms in <hi rend="italic">-r (amáres, amárem, amáreu, amaren),</hi> derived from the ancient pluperfect <hi rend="italic">amara,</hi> &amp;c., which has held its ground down to the present day, with the meaning of a conditional in some verbs (one still hears <hi rend="italic">fora, haguera).</hi> But the simple perfect is no longer employed in the spoken language, which has substituted for it a periphrastic perfect, composed of the infinitive of the verb and the present of the auxiliary <hi rend="italic">anar : vaig pendre,</hi> for example, does not mean “ I am going to take,” but “I have taken.” The earliest example of this periphrastic perfect carries us back to the 15th century. The most usual form of the subj. pres. in spoken Catalan is that in <hi rend="italic">-i </hi>for all the three conjugations <hi rend="italic">(ami, -is, -i, -em, -eu, -in ; temi, -is, </hi>&amp;c. ; <hi rend="italic">senti, -is,</hi> &amp;c. ) ; it appears to be an abbreviation from <hi rend="italic">-ia,</hi> and in effect certain subjunctives, such as <hi rend="italic">cántia, témia, tinguia, vinguia </hi>(for <hi rend="italic">cante, tema, tinga, vingia),</hi> evidently formed upon <hi rend="italic">sia</hi> (subj. of <hi rend="italic">esser),</hi> have been and still are used. The same <hi rend="italic">i </hi>of the present subjunctive, whatever may be its origin, is still found in the imperfect : <hi rend="italic">amés, -essis, -es, -essim,</hi> &amp;c.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Catalan Dialect of Alghero (Sardinia).—</hi>As compared with that of the mainland, the Catalan of Alghero, introduced into this portion of Sardinia by the Aragonese conquerors and colonists, does not present any very important differences ; some of them, such as they are, are explicable by the influence of the indigenous dialects of Sassari and Logudoro. In phonetics one observes—(1) the change of <hi rend="italic">lj</hi> into <hi rend="italic">y</hi> as an initial before <hi rend="italic">i (yitx, yigis ; lego, legis),</hi> a change which does not take place in the Catalan of the mainland except in the interior, or at the end of the word ; (2) the frequent change of <hi rend="italic">l</hi> between vowels and of <hi rend="italic">l</hi> after <hi rend="italic">c</hi>, <hi rend="italic">g, f, p </hi>or<hi rend="italic"> b</hi> into <hi rend="italic">r (taura, tabula ; candera, candela·, sangrot, singultum·, frama, flama).</hi> In conjugation there are some notable peculiarities. The 1st pers. sing, does not take the o which continental Catalan has borrowed from Castilian <hi rend="italic">(cant,</hi> not <hi rend="italic">canto,</hi> &amp;c.); the imp. ind. of verbs of the 2d</p><p>and 3d conjugations has <hi rend="italic">eva, iva</hi> instead of <hi rend="italic">ia,</hi> a form which also occurs in the conditional <hi rend="italic">(cantariνa, drumiriva) ;</hi> the simple perfect, of which some types are still preserved in the actual language <hi rend="italic">(e.g., anighé, aghé),</hi> has likewise served for the formation not only of the past participle but also of the infinitive <hi rend="italic">(agher, habere,</hi> can only be explained by <hi rend="italic">ach,</hi> 3d person of the perfect) ; the infinitives with <hi rend="italic">r</hi> paragogic <hi rend="italic">(viurer, seurer, plourer)</hi> are not used <hi rend="italic">(viure, seure, ploure</hi> instead) ; in the conjugation of the present of the verb <hi rend="italic">essar</hi> or <hi rend="italic">esser,</hi> the 2d pers. sing, <hi rend="italic">ses</hi> formed upon the persons of the plural, while continental Catalan says <hi rend="italic">ets</hi> (anciently <hi rend="italic">est),</hi> as also, in the plural, <hi rend="italic">sem, seu,</hi> instead of <hi rend="italic">som, sou,</hi> are to be noted ; <hi rend="italic">tenere</hi> has passed over to the conjugation in <hi rend="italic">re (trenda=tendre), </hi>but it is at the same time true that in ordinary Catalan also we have <hi rend="italic">tindrer</hi> alongside of <hi rend="italic">tenir</hi> the habitual form ; <hi rend="italic">dicere</hi> gives not <hi rend="italic">dir</hi> but <hi rend="italic">diure,</hi> which is more regular.</p><p>II. <hi rend="smallcaps">Castilian.</hi>—This name (derived from the kingdom of Castile, the most powerful element in the Spanish monarchy) is the most convenient designation to apply to the linguistic domain which comprises the whole of central Spain and the vast regions of America and Asia colonized from the 16th century onwards by the Spaniards. We might also indeed call it the <hi rend="italic">Spanish</hi> domain, narrowing the essentially geographical meaning of the word <hi rend="italic">Español </hi>(derived, like the other old form <hi rend="italic">Españon,</hi> from <hi rend="italic">Hispania), </hi>and using it in a purely political sense. But the first expression is to be preferred, all the more because it has been long in use, and even the inhabitants of the domain outside the two Castiles fully accept it and are indeed the first to call their idiom <hi rend="italic">Castellano.</hi> It is agreed on all hands that Castilian is one of the two branches of the vulgar Latin of Spain, Portuguese-Galician being the other ; both idioms, now separated by very marked differences, can be traced back directly to one common source —the Hispanic Romance. One and the same vulgar tongue, diversely modified in the lapse of time, has produced Castilian and Portuguese as two varieties, while Catalan, the third language of the Peninsula, connects itself, as has already been pointed out, with the Gallo- Roman.</p><p>Within the Castilian domain, thus embracing all in Spain that is neither Portuguese nor Catalan, there exist linguistic varieties which it would perhaps be an exaggeration to call dialects, considering the meaning ordinarily attached to that word, but which are none the less worthy of attention. Generally speaking, from various circumstances, and especially that of the reconquest, by which the already-formed idiom of the Christian conquerors and colonists was gradually conveyed from north to south, Castilian has maintained a uniformity of which the Romance languages afford no other example. We shall proceed in the first instance to examine the most salient features of the <hi rend="italic">normal Castilian,</hi> spoken in the provinces more or less closely corresponding to the old limits of Old and New Castile, so as to be able afterwards to note the peculiarities of what, for want of a better expression, we must call the Castilian dialects.</p><p>In some respects Castilian is hardly further removed from classical Latin than is Italian ; in others it has approximately reached the same stage as Provençal. As regards the tonic accent and the treatment of the vowels which come after it, Castilian may be said to be essentially a paroxytonic language, though it does not altogether refuse proparoxytonic accentuation and it would be a mistake to regard vocables like <hi rend="italic">lámpara, lágrima, rápido, </hi>&amp;c., as learned words. In this feature, and in its almost universal conservation of the final vowels <hi rend="italic">e, i, u</hi> (o), Castilian comes very near Italian, while it separates from it and approaches the Gallo-Roman by its modification of the consonants.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Vowels.—</hi>Normal Castilian faithfully preserves the vowels <hi rend="italic">ē, ī, ō, ū</hi>; the comparatively infrequent instances in which <hi rend="italic">ē</hi> and <hi rend="italic">ō</hi> are treated like ĕ and ŏ must be attributed to the working of analogy. It diphthongizes ĕ in <hi rend="italic">ie, ō</hi> in <hi rend="italic">ue,</hi> which may be regarded as a</p></body></text></TEI>