<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T20:43:49Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>went a change. In fact he adhered successively to the triumphant party as represented by Cromwell, Charles, James, and William, and there are substantial grounds for the assertion of Anthony Wood that he was much indebted for his preferments to his zeal for “the powers that be.” On 10th August 1660 he was chosen public orator of the university, and in 1661 domestic chaplain to Lord Clarendon. In March 1663 he was made prebend of Westminster, and shortly afterwards he received from his university the degree of D.D. In 1667 he became chaplain to the duke of York. He was a zealous advocate of the doctrine of passive obedience, and also strongly opposed the Toleration Act, declaiming in unmeasured terms against the various nonconformist sects. In 1676 he was appointed chaplain to Lawrence Hyde (afterwards earl of Rochester), ambassador-extraordinary to the king of Poland, and of his visit he sent an interesting account to Dr Edward Pocock in a letter, dated Dantzic, 16th December 1677, which was printed along with South’s <hi rend="italic">Posthumous Works</hi> in 1717. In 1678 he was promoted by the chapter of Westminster to the rectory of Islip, Oxfordshire. Owing, it is said, to a personal grudge, South in 1693 published <hi rend="italic">Animadversions on Dr Sherlock’s Book, entitled a Vindication of the Holy and Ever Blessed Trinity,</hi> in which the views of Sherlock were attacked with much sarcastic bitterness. Sherlock, in answer, published a <hi rend="italic">Defence</hi> in 1694, to which South replied in <hi rend="italic">Tritheism Charged upon Dr Sherlock's New Notion of the Trinity, and the Charge Made Good.</hi> The controversy was carried by the rival parties into the pulpit, and occasioned such keen feeling that the king interposed to stop it. During the greater part of the reign of Anne South remained comparatively quiet, but in 1710 he showed himself a keen opponent of Sacheverell. He died 8th July 1716, and was buried in Westminster Abbey.</p><p>The style of South is vigorous, pungent, and brilliant, though tending to exuberance. His sermons are strongly practical, but his theory of life is not ascetic. His wit generally inclines towards sarcasm, and it was probably the knowledge of his quarrelsome temperament that prevented his promotion to a bishopric. If he sacrificed principle to his desire for preferment, his ambition was not of a sordid kind, for he was noted for the extent of his charities. He published a large number of single sermons, and they appeared in a collected form in 1692 in six volumes, reaching a second edition in his lifetime in 1715. His <hi rend="italic">Opera Posthuma Latina, </hi>including his will, his Latin poems, and his orations while public orator, with memoirs of his life, appeared in 1717. His <hi rend="italic">Works </hi>were published with a memoir by the Clarendon press in 1823, and have been several times reprinted. The contemporary notice of South by Wood in his <hi rend="italic">Athenæ</hi> is characterized by a strongly hostile tone, partly to be explained by a criticism of South at Wood’s expense.</p><p>SOUTH AFRICAN REPUBLIC. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Transvaal.</hi></p><p>SOUTHAMPTON, a municipal and parliamentary borough, which gives name to Hampshire, or the county of Southampton, and one of the principal seaports on the south coast of England, is beautifully situated at the head of Southampton Water, forming the mouth of the Test, on a sloping peninsula, bounded on the east by the Itchen, at the terminus of the South-Western Railway, 79 miles south-west of London, 13 south-south-west of Winchester, and 24 west-north-west of Portsmouth. Southampton is also a county of itself,—the county of the town of Southampton. It preserves much of its antique appearance, but, although in the older parts the streets if picturesque are narrow and irregular, it may still claim the distinction it enjoyed in Leland’s time of ranking “ as one of the fairest that is in England,” handsome and spacious shops lining the principal streets, while the suburbs are studded with numerous villas and mansions embosomed in woods. There are still considerable remains of the old town walls built in the time of Richard II., the most remarkable being a portion of the west walls, with an</p><p>arcade on its exterior face. Four of the seven gates are comparatively well preserved—North or Bar Gate, South Castle Gate, Westgate, and Blue Anchor Gate. The finest of these is Bargate, in a room above which is the ancient Guildhall, where the quarter sessions are held. The representations of Sir Bevis of Hampton and the giant Ascupart which formerly stood on each side have recently been obliterated. The castle, originally a Saxon fortress, and rebuilt when the walls were erected, was partly demolished in 1650. After its rebuilding had been begun by the marquis of Lansdowne in 1805, it was sold, and in 1818 the site was parcelled out for building plots. In the vicinity of the castle there are some houses of very ancient date, including King’s House (Early Norman). The two old churches, St Michael’s (originally Norman about the date of 1080) and Holyrood, have been in a great degree modernized ; the former contains a beautiful Byzantine font and a monument to Sir R. Lyster, chief- justice in the 16th century. The French chapel of St Julien, originally attached to the hospital of God’s House, founded by Henry VIII. for eight poor persons, is of Norman architecture; it contains the burial-place of the</p><p>earl of Cambridge, Lord Scrope, and Sir Thomas Grey, who in 1415 were executed outside the Bargate for conspiring against Henry V. Among the modern public buildings are the Watts memorial hall, erected in 1876 at a cost of £8000, the municipal office, occupying the old audit-house, the custom-house, the philharmonic hall, the assembly rooms, the county court-house, the corn exchange and chamber of commerce, and two theatres. The educational institutions include the Hartley Institution, founded by bequest for the advancement of natural history, astronomy, antiquities, and classical and Oriental literature, and now embracing a library, reading-room, museum, art gallery, laboratories, and schools of science and art associated with South Kensington ; the Edward VI. grammar school,</p></body></text></TEI>