<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T20:45:30Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>weakening of <hi rend="italic">uo</hi> (see <hi rend="italic">Romania,</hi> iv. SO). Sometimes <hi rend="italic">ie</hi> and <hi rend="italic">ue</hi> in the modem language are changed into <hi rend="italic">i</hi> and <hi rend="italic">e</hi>: <hi rend="italic">silla</hi> from sella (Old Cast, <hi rend="italic">siella), víspera</hi> from vespera (Old Cast, <hi rend="italic">viespera), castillo </hi>from castellum (Old Cast. <hi rend="italic">castiello), freute</hi> from frontem(Old Cast. <hi rend="italic">fruente), fleco</hi> from floccus (Old Cast, <hi rend="italic">flueeo).</hi> The words in which ĕ and ŏ have kept their ground are either learned words like <hi rend="italic">medico, mérito,</hi> or have been borrowed from dialects which do not suffer diphthongization. In many cases the old language is more rigorous ; thus, while modern Castilian has given the preference to <hi rend="italic">mente, como, modo,</hi> we find in old texts <hi rend="italic">miente, cuemo, muedo.</hi> Lat. au makes <hi rend="italic">o</hi> in all words of popular origin <hi rend="italic">(cosa, oro,</hi> &amp;c. ).</p><p><hi rend="italic">Consonants. —</hi>On the liquids <hi rend="italic">l, m, n, r</hi> there is little to be remarked, except that the last-named letter has two pronunciations— one soft (voiced), as in<hi rend="italic"> amor, bιιrla,</hi> the other hard (voiceless), as in <hi rend="italic">rendir, tierra</hi> (Old Cast. in this case goes so far as to double the initial consonant : <hi rend="italic">rrendir)—</hi>and that <hi rend="italic">n</hi> is often inserted before <hi rend="italic">s</hi> and <hi rend="italic">d: ensayo, mensage, rendir</hi> (reddere). <hi rend="italic">L</hi> mouillée (written <hi rend="italic">ll)</hi> represents not only the Latin <hi rend="italic">l, ll, lj,</hi> but also, at the beginning of words, the combinations <hi rend="italic">cl, gl, pl, bl,fl</hi>:<hi rend="italic"> llama</hi> (flamma), <hi rend="italic">llave</hi> (clavis), <hi rend="italic">llorar</hi> (plorare) ; the tendency of the modern language is, as in Catalan, to reduce <hi rend="italic">ll</hi> to <hi rend="italic">y</hi> ; thus one readily hears <hi rend="italic">yeno </hi>(plenum). <hi rend="italic">N</hi> mouillée <hi rend="italic">(n)</hi> corresponds to the Latin <hi rend="italic">nn, mn, nj, </hi>and sometimes to initial <hi rend="italic">n</hi>: <hi rend="italic">año</hi> (annum), <hi rend="italic">daño</hi> (damnum), <hi rend="italic">ñudo </hi>(nodum). Passing to the dentals, except as an initial, <hi rend="italic">t</hi> in words that are popularly current and belong to the old stock of the language, can only be derived from Lat. <hi rend="italic">tt, pt,</hi> and sometimes <hi rend="italic">ct, </hi>as in <hi rend="italic">meter</hi> (mittere), <hi rend="italic">catar</hi> (captare), <hi rend="italic">punto</hi> (punctum); but it is to be observed that the habitual mode of representing <hi rend="italic">ct</hi> in normal Castilian is by <hi rend="italic">ch</hi> (pron. <hi rend="italic">tch</hi>), as in <hi rend="italic">derecho</hi> (directum), <hi rend="italic">pecho</hi> (pectus), so that we may take those words in which <hi rend="italic">t</hi> alone represents <hi rend="italic">ct</hi> as secondary forms of learned words ; thus we have <hi rend="italic">bendito, otubre, santo</hi> as secondary forms of the learned words <hi rend="italic">bendicto, octubre, sancto,</hi> alongside of the old popular forms <hi rend="italic">bendicho, ochubre, sancho. D</hi> corresponds in Castilian to Latin <hi rend="italic">t</hi> between vowels, or <hi rend="italic">t</hi> before <hi rend="italic">r: amado</hi> (amatus), <hi rend="italic">padre</hi> (patrem). At the present day the <hi rend="italic">d</hi> of the suffixes <hi rend="italic">ado, ido</hi> is no longer pronounced throughout the whole extent of the domain, and the same holds good also of the final <hi rend="italic">d : salú, poné,</hi> for <hi rend="italic">salud, poned</hi> (from salutem, ponite). Sometimes <hi rend="italic">d</hi> takes the interdental sound of <hi rend="italic">z</hi> (English <hi rend="italic">th),</hi> or is changed into <hi rend="italic">l</hi> ; witness the two pronunciations of the name of the capital—<hi rend="italic">Madriz</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Madril</hi> (adj. <hi rend="italic">Madrileño).</hi> The study of the spirants <hi rend="italic">c, z, s ; g, j</hi> is made a very delicate one by the circumstance that the interdental pronunciation of <hi rend="italic">c, z</hi> on the one hand, and the guttural pronunciation of <hi rend="italic">g, j</hi> on the other, are of comparatively recent date, and convey no notion of the value of these letters before the 17th century. It is admitted, not without reason, that the spirants c, <hi rend="italic">z,</hi> which at present represent but one interdental sound (a lisped <hi rend="italic">s</hi>, or a sound between <hi rend="italic">s</hi> and Eng. <hi rend="italic">th</hi> in thing), had down till about the middle of the 16th century the voiceless sound <hi rend="italic">ts</hi> and the voiced sound <hi rend="italic">dz</hi> respectively, and that in like manner the palatal spirants <hi rend="italic">g, j, x,</hi> before assuming the uniform pronunciation of the guttural spirant ( = Germ. <hi rend="italic">ch</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Buch),</hi> had previously represented the voiced sound of ž (Fr. <hi rend="italic">j) </hi>and the voiceless sound of š (Fr. <hi rend="italic">ch),</hi> which are still found in Portuguese and in the Castilian dialects of the north-west. The substitution of these interdental and guttural sounds for the surd and sonant spirants respectively did certainly not take place simultaneously, but the vacillations of the old orthography, and afterwards the decision of the Spanish Academy, which suppressed <hi rend="italic">x</hi> (=š; <hi rend="italic">x</hi> was retained for <hi rend="italic">cs)</hi> and allows only <hi rend="italic">c</hi> and <hi rend="italic">g</hi> before <hi rend="italic">e</hi> and <hi rend="italic">i, z</hi> and <hi rend="italic">j </hi>before <hi rend="italic">a, o, u,</hi> make it impossible for us to follow, with the help of the written texts, the course of the transformation. <hi rend="italic">S</hi> now has the voiceless sound even between vowels : <hi rend="italic">casa</hi> (pronounced <hi rend="italic">cassa) ;</hi> final <hi rend="italic">s</hi> readily falls away, especially before liquids : <hi rend="italic">todo los</hi> for <hi rend="italic">todos los, vamono</hi> for <hi rend="italic">νamos nos.</hi> The principal sources of <hi rend="italic">j (g)</hi> are—Lat. <hi rend="italic">j </hi>and <hi rend="italic">g</hi> before <hi rend="italic">e</hi> and <hi rend="italic">i (juego,</hi> jocum ; <hi rend="italic">gente,</hi> gentem); Lat. initial <hi rend="italic">s (jabon,</hi> saponem); Lat. <hi rend="italic">x (cojo,</hi> coxum) ; <hi rend="italic">lj, cl (consejo,</hi> consilium; <hi rend="italic">ojo,</hi> oc’lum). The sources of <hi rend="italic">z (c)</hi> are Lat. <hi rend="italic">ce, cj, tj, s (cielo,</hi> caelum; <hi rend="italic">calza,</hi> calcea; <hi rend="italic">razon,</hi> rationem; <hi rend="italic">zampoña,</hi> symphonia). As regards the spirants <hi rend="italic">f </hi>and <hi rend="italic">ν,</hi> it is to be observed that at the beginning of a word <hi rend="italic">f</hi> has in many instances been replaced by the aspirated <hi rend="italic">h</hi> (afterwards silent), while in others no less current among the people the transformation has not taken place ; thus we have <hi rend="italic">hijo</hi> (filium) alongside of <hi rend="italic">fiesta</hi> (festa). In some cases the <hi rend="italic">f </hi>has been preserved in order to avoid confusion that might arise from identity of sound : the <hi rend="italic">f</hi> in <hi rend="italic">fiel</hi> (fidelis) has been kept for the sake of distinction from <hi rend="italic">hiel</hi> (fel). As for <hi rend="italic">v,</hi> it has a marked tendency to become confounded, especially as an initial letter, with the sonant explosive <hi rend="italic">b;</hi> Joseph Scaliger’s pun—<hi rend="italic">bibere est vivere—</hi>is applicable to the Castilians as well as to the Gascons. <hi rend="italic">II</hi> is now nothing more than a graphic sign, except in Andalusia, where the aspirate sound represented by it comes very near <hi rend="italic">j.</hi> Words beginning in <hi rend="italic">hue,</hi> where the <hi rend="italic">h,</hi> not etymologically derived, marks the inseparable aspiration of the initial diphthong <hi rend="italic">ue,</hi> are readily pronounced <hi rend="italic">güe</hi> throughout almost the whole extent of the domain : <hi rend="italic">güele</hi> for <hi rend="italic">huele</hi> (olet); <hi rend="italic">güeso</hi> for <hi rend="italic">hueso</hi> (os). This <hi rend="italic">güe</hi> extends also to words beginning with <hi rend="italic">bue : gueno </hi>for<hi rend="italic"> bueno</hi> (bonum).</p><p><hi rend="italic">Inflexion. —</hi>There is no trace of declension either in Castilian or in Portuguese. Some nominative forms—<hi rend="italic">Diós</hi> (anciently <hi rend="italic">Díos,</hi> and in the Castilian of the Jews <hi rend="italic">Dío), Cárlos, Márcos, sastre</hi> (sartor)— have been adopted instead of forms derived from the accusative, but the vulgar Latin of the Peninsula in no instance presents two forms (subjective and objective case) of the same substantive. The article is derived from ille, as it is almost everywhere throughout the Romance regions : <hi rend="italic">el, la,</hi> and a neuter <hi rend="italic">lo ; los, las.</hi> The plural of the first and second personal pronoun has in the modern language taken a composite form—<hi rend="italic">nosotros, vosotros—</hi>which has been imitated in Catalan. <hi rend="italic">Quien,</hi> the interrogative pronoun which has taken the place of the old <hi rend="italic">qui,</hi> seems to come from quem.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Conjugation.—</hi>The conjugation of Castilian (and Portuguese) derives a peculiar interest from the archaic features which it retains. The vulgar Latin of Spain has kept the pluperfect indicative, still in current use as a secondary form of the conditional <hi rend="italic">(cantára, vendiéra, partiéra),</hi> and, what is more remarkable still, as not occurring anywhere else, the future perfect <hi rend="italic">(cantáre, vendiére, partiére,</hi> formerly <hi rend="italic">cantáro, vendiéro, partiéro).</hi> The Latin future has been replaced, as everywhere, by the periphrasis (cantare habeo), but it is worth noticing that in certain old texts of the 13th century, and in the popular songs of a comparatively ancient date which have been preserved in Asturias, the auxiliary can still <hi rend="italic">precede</hi> the infinitive (habeo cantare), as with the Latin writers of the decadence: “Mucho de mayor preçio a seer el tu manto Que non sera el nuestro” (Berceo, <hi rend="italic">S. Laur.,</hi> str. 70), where <hi rend="italic">a seer</hi> (habet sedere) corresponds exactly to <hi rend="italic">sera</hi> (sedere habet). The vulgar Latin of the Peninsula, moreover, has preserved the 2d pers. pl. of the imperative <hi rend="italic">(cantad, voided, ρartid),</hi> which has disappeared from all the other Romance languages. Another special feature of Castilian-Portuguese is the complete absence of the form of conjugation known as inchoative (intercalation, in the present tense, of the syllable <hi rend="italic">isc</hi> or <hi rend="italic">esc</hi> between the radical and the inflexion), although in all the other tenses, except the present, Spanish shows a tendency to lay the accent upon the same syllable in all the six persons, which was the object aimed at by the inchoative form. Castilian displaces the accent on the 1st and 2d pers. pl. of the imperfect <hi rend="italic">(cantábamos, cantábais),</hi> of the pluperfect indicative <hi rend="italic">(cantáramos, cantárais),</hi> and of the imperfect subjunctive <hi rend="italic">(cantásemos, cantáseis) ;</hi> possibly the impulse to this was given by the forms of future perfect <hi rend="italic">cantáremos, cantáreis (cantavimus, canturitis).</hi> The 2d persons plural were formerly (except in the perfect) <hi rend="italic">-ades, -edes, -ides</hi> ; it was only in the course of the 16th century that they got reduced, by the falling away of <hi rend="italic">d,</hi> to <hi rend="italic">ais, eis,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">is.</hi> The verb essere has been mixed, not as in tho other Romance languages with stare, but with sedere, as is proved by older forms <hi rend="italic">seer, sicdes, sieden, seyendo,</hi> obviously derived from sedere, and which have in the texts sometimes the meaning of “to be seated,” sometimes that of “ to be, ” and sometimes both. In old Latin charters also sedere is frequently met with in the sense of esse: <hi rend="italic">e.g., “sedeat</hi> istum meum donativum quietum et securum” (anno 1134), where <hi rend="italic">sedeat=sit.</hi> The 2d pers. sing, of the present of s<hi rend="italic">er</hi> is <hi rend="italic">eres,</hi> which is best explained as borrowed from the imperfect <hi rend="italic">(eras),</hi> this tense being often used in Old Spanish with the meaning of the present ; alongside of <hi rend="italic">eres</hi> one finds (but only in old documents or in dialects) <hi rend="italic">sos,</hi> formed like <hi rend="italic">sois</hi> (2d pers. pl. ) upon <hi rend="italic">somos.</hi> The accentuation in the inflexion of perfects in the conjugation called strong, like <hi rend="italic">hubiéron, hiziéron,</hi> which correspond to habuerunt, fecerunt (while in the other Romance languages the Latin type is ěrunt: Fr. <hi rend="italic">eurent, firent),</hi> may be regarded as truly etymological, or rather as a result of the assimilation of these perfects to the perfects known as weak <hi rend="italic">(amáron),</hi> for there are dialectic forms having the accent on the radical, such as <hi rend="italic">dixon, hizon.</hi> The past participle of verbs in <hi rend="italic">er</hi> was formerly <hi rend="italic">udo</hi> (utus) in most cases ; at present <hi rend="italic">ido</hi> serves for all verbs in <hi rend="italic">er</hi> and <hi rend="italic">ir,</hi> except some ten or twelve in which the participle has retained the Latin form accented on the radical : <hi rend="italic">dicho, hecho, visto,</hi> &amp;c. It ought to be added that the past participle in normal Castilian derives its theme not from the perfect but from the infinitive : <hi rend="italic">habido, sabido, </hi>from <hi rend="italic">haber, saber,</hi> not from <hi rend="italic">hubo, supo.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Castilian Dialects.</hi>—To discover the features by which these are distinguished from normal Castilian we must turn to old charters and to certain modern compositions in which the provincial forms of speech have been reproduced more or less faithfully.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Asturian.—</hi>The Asturian idiom, called by the natives <hi rend="italic">bable,</hi> is differentiated from the Castilian by the following characters. <hi rend="italic">Ie </hi>occurs, as in Old Castilian, in words formed with the suffix <hi rend="italic">ellum (castiellu, portiellu,</hi> while modern Castilian has reduced <hi rend="italic">ie</hi> to <hi rend="italic">i. E, i, u,</hi> post-tonic for <hi rend="italic">a, e, o : penes (ρenas), gracies (gracias), esti (este), frenti (frente), llechi (leche), nuechi (noche), unu (uno), primeru (ρrimero).</hi> There is no guttural spirant, <hi rend="italic">j,</hi> but, according to circumstances, <hi rend="italic">y</hi> or <hi rend="italic">x</hi> (š) ; thus Lat. <hi rend="italic">cl, lj</hi> gives <hi rend="italic">y : veyu</hi> (*veclus), <hi rend="italic">espeyu</hi> (spec’lum), <hi rend="italic">conseyu</hi> (consilium); and after an <hi rend="italic">i</hi> this <hi rend="italic">y</hi> is hardly perceptible, to judge by the forms <hi rend="italic">fiu</hi> (filium), <hi rend="italic">escoidos </hi>(Cast. <hi rend="italic">escogidos), Castia (Castilla)</hi> ; Lat. <hi rend="italic">g</hi> before <hi rend="italic">e</hi> and <hi rend="italic">i,</hi> Lat. initial <hi rend="italic">j</hi>, and Lat. <hi rend="italic">ss, x,</hi> give <hi rend="italic">x (š)—xiente</hi> (gentem), <hi rend="italic">xudiu</hi> (Judaeus), <hi rend="italic">baxu</hi> (bassus), <hi rend="italic">coxu</hi> (coxus),  <hi rend="italic">floxu</hi> (fluxus). Lat. initial / has kept its ground, at least in part of the province : <hi rend="italic">fiu, fueya</hi> (Cast.</p></body></text></TEI>