<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T20:23:05Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>department of the Leman. In 1813 he visited Paris for the first time and abode there for some years, mixing much in literary society. Although a Liberal and in his earlier days almost an Anglomaniac, he did not welcome the fall of the empire. During the Hundred Days he defended Napoleon’s constitutional schemes or promises, and had an interview with the emperor himself which is one of the chief events of a not very eventful life. After the Restoration he left Paris. On completing his great book on the Italian republics he undertook a still greater, the <hi rend="italic">Histoire des Français,</hi> which he planned on a vast scale, and of which during the remaining twenty-three years of his life he published twenty-nine volumes. His untiring industry enabled him to compile many other books, but it is on these two that his fame chiefly rests. The earlier displays his qualities in the most favourable light, and has been least injuriously affected by subsequent writings and investigations. The <hi rend="italic">Histoire des Français,</hi> as a careful and accurate sketch on the great scale, has been entirely superseded by that of M. Henri Martin, while it is not to be mentioned, as a work of historical or literary genius, in the same category with that of Michelet. Sainte-Beuve has with benevolent sarcasm surnamed the author “ the Rollin of French History,” and the praise and the blame implied in the comparison are both perfectly well deserved. In April 1819 Sismondi married an English lady, Miss Allen, whose sister was the wife of Sir James Mackintosh, and the marriage appears to have been a very happy one. His later years were chiefly spent at Geneva, in the politics of which city he took a great, though as time and changes went on a more and more chagrined, interest. Indeed, in his later days he became a kind of reactionary. He died at Geneva on June 25, 1842. Besides the works above mentioned he had executed many others, his custom for a long period of years being never to work less than eight hours a day. The chief of these are <hi rend="italic">Nouveaux Principes d'Économie Politique</hi> (1819), an historical novel entitled J<hi rend="italic">ulia Severa ou l'An 492</hi> (1822), <hi rend="italic">Histoire de la Renaissance de la Liberté en Italie</hi> (1832), <hi rend="italic">Histoire de la Chute de l'Empire Romain</hi> (1835), <hi rend="italic">Précis de l'Histoire des Français, </hi>an abridgment of his own book (1839), with several others, chiefly political pamphlets.</p><p>Sismondi’s literary character has been hinted at in the above remarks on his French history. He was exceedingly laborious, for the most part (though not entirely) free from prejudice, and never violent even when he was prejudiced. He had (with much “ sensibility ”) plenty of common sense, though not perhaps any extraordinary amount of acuteness in estimating things uncommon, and he was a little deficient in historical grasp and in the power of taking large views of complicated series of events. His style corresponded to his thought, and (putting aside certain solecisms which French critics usually affect to discover in Swiss writers) lacks point, picturesqueness, and vigour. Of his moral character no one has ever spoken except in terms of praise, and it appears (which is not invariably the case) to have been as attractive as it was estimable. His chief weakness seems to have been a tendency, frequently observable in writers of very great industry, to rank his own productions somewhat too much on a level with those of writers who, if less industrious, were infinitely more gifted. Thus he has somewhere naively observed that “ he should not object to signing” a certain proportion of a certain book of Chateaubriand’s. But this overvaluation of self appears to have been merely <hi rend="italic">naïf,</hi> and not in the least arrogant.</p><p>Sismondi’s journals and his correspondence with Channing, with the countess of Albany, and others have been published chiefly by Mlle. Mongolfier (Paris, 1863) and M. de Saint-René Taillandier. The latter work serves as the chief text of two admirable <hi rend="italic">Lundis</hi> of Sainte-Beuve (September 1863), republished in the <hi rend="italic">Nouveaux Lundis,</hi> vol. vi.</p><p>SISTÁN, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Seistan (Sejistán),</hi> the ancient <hi rend="italic">Sacastane (Cakasthána,</hi> “land of the Sacæ”) and the <hi rend="italic">Nimrúz</hi> or “ meridies ” of the <hi rend="italic">Vendidad,</hi> is situated generally between 30° 0' and 31° 35' N. lat. and 61° 0' and (including Rudbár) 62° 40' E. long. Its extreme length is about 100 and its breadth varies from 70 to over 100 miles,—but the exact limits are vague, and the modern signification of the name practically comprehends the peninsula formed by the lower</p><p>Helmand and its embouchure on the one side and the “ Hámún ” or “ lake ” on the other. When British arbitration was brought to bear upon the disputed claims of Persia over this country in 1872, it was found necessary to suppose two territories—one compact and concentrated, which was called “Sistân Proper,” the other detached and irregular, called “ Outer Sistân.” Of each of these a brief description will be given.</p><p>1.	Sistán Proper is bounded on the north by the “Nâïzâr,” or reed-bed which fringes the “Hámún” or expanse ; west by the Hámún itself, of which the hill called “ Kuh-i-Khwájah ” marks the central point ; south by a line shutting in Sikuha and all villages and lands watered by the main Sistán Canal ; and east by the old bed of the Helmand, from a mile above the dam at Kohak to the mouth. Kal'ah-i-nau and Rindan are among the more northerly inhabited villages. The Kuh-i-Khwájah is a sufficient indication of the western side. Búrj-i-'Alam Khan should be included within the southern boundary as well as Sikuha. Khwájah Ahmad and Jahánabád, villages on the left bank, or west of the true bed of the Helmand, denote the eastern line. The whole area is estimated at 947 square miles. The fixed population may be roughly stated at 35,000,—some 20,000 Sistánis and 15,000 settlers,—the greater part of whom are Parsiwans, or rather, perhaps, a Persian-speaking people. To the above</p><p>numbers may be added 10,000 Baluch nomads. Taking the aggregate at 45,000, and looking at the extent of country comprehended, we find nearly 48 persons to the square mile. These figures are eight times in excess of the proportional result found for the whole of Persia. It should be explained that the designation Sistán Proper is not arbitrarily given. The territory comprehended in it is spoken of as Sistán by the dwellers on the right bank of the</p><p>Helmand, in contradistinction to their own lands. At the same time it could only be but a fractional part—as indeed the whole country under consideration could only be—of the Sistán of Persian history.</p><p>Sistán Proper is an extensive tract of sand and clay alluvium, generally flat, but irregular in detail. It has heaps, but no hills ; bushes, but no trees, unless indeed three or four tamarisks of aspiring height deserve the name ; many old ruins and vestiges of comparative civilization, but few monuments or relics of antiquity. It is well watered by rivers and canals, and its soil is of proved fertility. wheat or barley is perhaps the staple cultivation ; but pease, beans, oil-seeds, and cotton are also grown. Among fruits, grapes and mulberries are rare, but melons and water-melons, especially the latter, are abundant. Grazing and fodder are not wanting, and besides the reeds peculiar to Sistán there are two grasses which merit notice,—that called <hi rend="italic">bannu,</hi> with which the bed of the Hámún abounds on the south, and the taller and less salt <hi rend="italic">kirta</hi> on the higher ground.</p><p>2.	Outer Sistán, the country on the right bank of the Helmand, and east of its embouchure in the Hámún, extends more than 100 miles in length, or from a point between the Charboli and Khuspas rivers north to Rudbár south. In breadth the district of Chakhansúr, measuring from the old bed of the Helmand, inclusive of Nad Ali, to Kadah, may be estimated at some 30 miles. It</p></body></text></TEI>