<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>The order falls into several well-defined tribes which are distinguished by characters of the flower and fruit; all are </p><lb/><p>represented among British native or commonly grown garden plants.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Tribe I. Paeonieae,</hi>  peony group, are mostly herbs with deeply cut leaves and large solitary showy flowers in which the parts are spirally arranged, the sepals, generally five in number, passing gradually into the large coloured petals. The indefinite stamens are succeeded by 2-5 free carpels which bear a double row of ovules along the ventral suture. Honey is secreted by a ring-like swelling round the base of the carpels, which become fleshy or leathery in the fruit and dehisce along the ventral suture. There are only three genera, the largest of which, <hi rend="italic">Paeonia,</hi>  occurs in Europe, temperate Asia and western North America. <hi rend="italic">P</hi>. <hi rend="italic">officinalis</hi>  is the common peony.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Tribe II. Helleboreae</hi>  are almost exclusively north temperate or subarctic; there are 15 genera, several of which are represented in the British flora. The plants are herbs, either annual, <hi rend="italic">e.g. Nigella </hi>(love-in-a-mist), or perennial by means of a rhizome, as in<hi rend="italic">  Aconitum </hi>or<hi rend="italic">  Eranthis</hi>  (winter aconite). The leaves are simple, as in <hi rend="italic">Caltha, </hi>but more often palmately divided as in hellebore (fig. 6), aconite (fig. 5) and larkspur. The flowers are solitary <hi rend="italic">(Eranthis)</hi>  or in</p><lb/><p>cymes or racemes, and are generally regular as in <hi rend="italic">Caltha</hi>  (king-cup, marsh marigold), <hi rend="italic">Trollius</hi>  (globe-flower), <hi rend="italic">Helleborus, Aquilegia </hi>(columbine); sometimes medianly zygomorphic as in <hi rend="italic">Aconitum </hi>(monkshood, aconite) and <hi rend="italic">Delphinium</hi>  (larkspur). The carpels, generally 3 to 5 in number, form in the fruit a many-seeded follicle, except in <hi rend="italic">Actaea</hi>  (baneberry), where the single carpel develops to form a many-seeded berry, and in <hi rend="italic">Nigella,</hi>  where the five carpels unite to form a five-chambered ovary. There is considerable variety in the form of the floral envelopes and the arrangement of the parts. The outer series, or sepals, generally five in number, is generally white or bright-coloured, serving as an attraction for insects, especially bees, as well as a protection for the rest of the flower. Thus in <hi rend="italic">Caltha</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">Trollius</hi>  the sepals form a brilliant golden-yellow cup or globe, and in <hi rend="italic">Eranthis</hi>  a pale yellow star which contrasts with the green involucre of bracts immediately below it; in <hi rend="italic">Nigella</hi>  they are blue or yellow, and also coloured in <hi rend="italic">Aquilegia. </hi>In Hellebore the greenish sepals persist till the fruit is ripe. Aconitum and <hi rend="italic">Delphinium</hi>  differ in the irregular development of the sepals,</p><lb/><p>the posterior sepal being distinguished from the remaining four by its helmet-shape <hi rend="italic">(Aconitum) or</hi>  spur <hi rend="italic">(Delphinium).</hi>  In <hi rend="italic">Caltha</hi>  there are no petals, but in the other genera there are honey-secreting and storing structures varying in number and in form in the different genera. In <hi rend="italic">Trollius</hi>  they are long and narrow with a honey-secreting pit at the base, in <hi rend="italic">Nigella</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">Helleborus</hi>  (fig. 7) they form short-</p><lb/><p>stalked pitchers, in <hi rend="italic">Aquilegia</hi>  they are large and coloured with a showy petal-like upper portion and a long basal spur in the tip of which is the nectary. In <hi rend="italic">Delphinium</hi>  they are also spurred, and in <hi rend="italic">Aconitum</hi>  form a spur-like sac on a long stalk (fig. 8). The parts of the flower are generally arranged in a spiral (acyclic), but are sometimes hemicyclic, the perianth forming a whorl as in winter aconite; rarely is the flower cyclic, as in <hi rend="italic">Aquilegia</hi>  (fig. 9) where</p><lb/><p>the parts throughout are arranged in alternating whorls. In <hi rend="italic">Callha, </hi>where there are no petals, honey is secreted by two shallow depressions on the side of each carpel.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Tribe III. Anemoneae,</hi>  with 8 genera, are chiefly north temperate, arctic and alpine plants, but also pass beyond the tropics to the southern hemisphere. They differ from the two preceding tribes in the numerous carpels, each with only one ovule, forming a fruit of numerous achenes. They are annual or perennial herbs, erect as in <hi rend="italic">Anemone, Thalictrum</hi>  (meadow-rue) and many buttercups, or creeping as in <hi rend="italic">Ranunculus repens ;</hi>  the section <hi rend="italic">Batrachium</hi>  of the genus <hi rend="italic">Ranunculus (q.υ.)</hi>  contains aquatic plants with submerged or floating stems and leaves. The flowers are solitary, as in <hi rend="italic">Anemone Pulsatilla</hi>  (Pasque flower) and the wood anemone, or cymose as in species of <hi rend="italic">Ranunculus,</hi>  or in racemes or panicles as in <hi rend="italic">Thalictrum.</hi>  The parts are spirally arranged throughout as in <hi rend="italic">Myosurus</hi>  (mouse-tail), where the very numerous carpels are borne on a much elongated receptacle, or <hi rend="italic">Adonis</hi>  (pheasant’s eye), or the perianth is whorled as in <hi rend="italic">Anemone</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">Ranunculus.</hi>  In <hi rend="italic">Anemone</hi>  there is a whorl of foliage leaves below the flower, as in <hi rend="italic">Eranthis.</hi>  In <hi rend="italic">Anemone</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">Thalictrum</hi>  there is only one series of perianth leaves, which are petaloîd and attractive in <hi rend="italic">Anemone</hi>  where honey is secreted by modified stamens, as in <hi rend="italic">A. Pulsatilla,</hi>  or, as in <hi rend="italic">A.</hi><hi rend="italic">nemοrosa</hi>  (wood anemone), there is no honey and the flower is visited by insects for the sake of the pollen; in <hi rend="italic">Thalictrum</hi>  the perianth is greenish or</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>