<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>dwarfed since 1891 by the Siberian railway, built by the Russian government ëntirely across the continent of Asia from Cheliabinsk (1769 m. by rail east of St Petersburg) to Vladi-vostok, a distance of 4073 m., with a branch from Kharbin about 500 m. long to Dalny and Port Arthur. The main line was finished in 1902, except for a length of about 170 m. in very difficult country around the south end of Lake Baikal; this was constructed in 1904, communication being maintained in the interval by ferry-boats, which conveyed all the carriages of a train across the lake, more than 40 m., when the ice permitted. A transcontinental line was long ago undertaken across South America from Buenos Aires to Valparaiso, where the continent is only about 900 m. wide. The last section through the Andes was finished in 1910.     (H. M. R. )</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">General Statistics</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Mileage. </hi>the close of 1907 there were approximately 601, 808 miles of railway in the world, excluding tramways. On the whole, the best statistical source for this information is the annual computation published by the <hi rend="italic">Archiv für Eisenbahnwesen,</hi>  the official organ of the Prussian Ministry of Public Works; but the figure quoted above utilizes the Board of Trade returns for the United Kingdom and the report of the Interstate Commerce Commission for the United States. In the United States and in certain other countries, a fiscal year, ending on the 3oth of June or at some other irregular period, is substituted for the calendar year.</p><p>The partition of this total between the principal geographical divisions of the world is given in Table 1.</p><lb/><table><row><cell cols="1" rows="2"/><cell cols="3" rows="1"><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Table I. —Mileage of the World</hi></p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Miles.</p></cell><cell cols="2" rows="1"><p>Miles.</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Europe</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>199, 371</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Africa.</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>18, 516</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>America</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>309, 974</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Australia</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="2"><p>17, 766</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Asia</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>.    56, 181</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"/></row></table><p>Table II., classifying the mileage of Europe, shows that Russia has taken the lead, instead of Germany, as in former years. If the Asiatic portions of the Russian Empire were given in the same table, the total Russian mileage would appear nearly as large as that of Germany and Italy together.</p><lb/><table><row><cell cols="3" rows="1"><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Table II. —Railways of Europe in 1907</hi></p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Miles.</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"/><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Miles.</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="3"><p>Germany    .     .     .     36, 066</p><p>Austria-Hungary, including</p><p>Bosnia and Herzegovina 25, 853</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Portugal</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>1, 689</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Denmark</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>2, 141</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Norway</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>1, 607</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Great Britain and Ireland 23, 108</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Sweden</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>8, 322</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>France.    .     .     .     29, 717</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Servia....</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>379</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>European Russia, includ-</p><p>ing Finland    .     .     36, 280</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Rumania</p><p>Greece....</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="2"><p>1, 995 771</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="2"><p>Italy.... 10, 312 </p><p>Belgium.... 4, 874</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="2"><p>European Turkey, Bulgaria, Rumelia.</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>1, 968</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="3"><p>Holland....    2, 230</p><p>Switzerland.    .     .     2, 763</p><p>Spain....    9, 228</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Malta, Jersey, Isle of Man....</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>68</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="2"><p>Total</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"/></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>199, 371</p></cell></row></table><lb/><p>In the United States railway mileage now tends to increase at the rate of slightly over 5000 miles a year, which is about 2⅕% on the present main line mileage. In the ’eighties, the country passed through a period of competitive building, which was productive of much financial disaster. Thus, in 1882, 11, 569 m. were built—an addition equivalent to more than 11 % of mileage then existing—and in 1887, 12, 876 m. were built. Unjustifiable railway expansion had much to do with the American commercial panics of 1884 and 1893. After the reconstruction period of the 1893 panic, however, the tendency for a number of years was to spend larger sums in bettering existing railways rather than in new exten-sions. The decade from 1896 until 1905, inclusive, saw huge sums spent on yards, passing tracks, grade reduction, elimination of curves, substitution of large locomotives and cars for small ones, &amp;c. During those ten years, the route mileage increased 34, 991 m., or 17%, while the mileage of second, third, fourth and yard tracks and sidings increased 32, 666 m., or nearly 57 %. The number of locomotives increased 12, 407, or 35%, and the number of freight cars, 545, 222, or 42%. Moreover, the average tractive power per locomotive and the average capacity per freight car advanced greatly in this period, although specific figures cannot be given.</p><p>Thus it may fairly be said that the railway system of the United States was reconstructed between 1896 and 1905, so far as concerns rails, sleepers, ballast and the general capacity of a given group of lines to perform work. About 1905, however, a new tendency became apparent. At that time the so-called transcontinental</p><lb/><p>railways, connecting the Pacific coast of the United States with the central portions of the country, and thus with the group of railways reaching the Atlantic seaboard, consisted of five railways within the borders of the United States, and one in Canada, In Canada the Canadian Pacific was the only transcontinental line, extending from St John, on the bay of Fundy, and from Quebec, on the river St Lawrence, to Vancouver, on the strait of Georgia, the distance from St John to Vancouver being approximately 3379 m. Within the boundaries of the United States the northernmost of the trans-continental lines was the Great Northern railway, extending from a point opposite Vancouver, B. C., and from Seattle, Wash., to Duluth, on Lake Superior, and to St Paul and Minneapolis, Minn., where connexion through to Chicago was made over an allied line, the Chicago, Burlington &amp; Quincy, owned jointly by the Great Northern and the Northern Pacific.</p><p>Next, south of the Great Northern, lay the Northern Pacific railway, starting on the west from Portland, Ore., and from Seattle and Tacoma, Wash., and extending east to Duluth, St Paul and Minneapolis by way of Helena, Mont. The Central Pacific-Union Pacific route to the coast, with its important affiliated companies, the Oregon Short Line and the Oregon Railroad &amp; Navigation Company, extended from San Francisco, Cal., and Portland, Ore., to Omaha, Neb., by way of Salt Lake City; the Atchison, Topeka &amp; Santa Fé extended from San Francisco and Los Angeles, Cal., to Chicago and to Galveston, Tex.; while the Southern Pacific had its line from San Francisco and Los Angeles to Galveston and New Orleans, running for the greater part of the distance just north of the Mexican border.</p><p>Thus it will be observed that the five great cities of the Pacific coast—Seattle and Tacoma, Wash., Portland, Ore., and San Francisco and Los Angeles, Cal. —were already well supplied with railways; but the growth of the fertile region lying west of the transcontinental divide was most attractive to American railway builders; and railways serving this district, almost all of them in trouble ten years before, were showing great increases in earnings. In 1903 the Gould lines determined to enter this Pacific territory. Hitherto the western terminus of this group of lines had been Salt Lake City, Utah; by the exceedingly bold construction of the Western Pacific from Salt Lake City to Oakland, Cal., opposite San Francisco, an additional line to the Pacific coast was provided, having low grades and being in all respects well adapted for cheap operation.</p><p>Shortly after the plans were announced for building the Western Pacific, the Chicago, Milwaukee &amp; St Paul also decided to extend west. Before that time the St Paul had been a great local railway, operating primarily in the Dakotas, Minnesota, Iowa, Wisconsin and Illinois; but by the construction of a long arm from the Missouri river to Spokane, Seattle and Tacoma, it became a transcontinental line of the first importance, avoiding the mistakes of earlier railway builders by securing a line with easy gradients through the most favourable regions.</p><p>At the same time that these two extensions were being undertaken by old and well-established railways, a new company—the Kansas City, Mexico &amp; Orient—was engaged in constructing a line almost due south-west from Kansas City, Mo., to the lower part of the gulf of California in Mexico; while an additional independent line was under construction from Denver in a north-westerly direction towards the Pacific coast. The guarantee for this activity may be illustrated by a single fact: the combined building operations, in 1908, of San Francisco, Seattle, Portland, Los Angeles, Spokane and Salt Lake City exceeded thç combined building opera-tions of Philadelphia, Pittsburg, Kansas City, Boston, Baltimore and Cincinnati during the same year. San Francisco spent more in new permanent structures than Philadelphia, and Seattle spent more than Pittsburg.</p><p>Recent American railway development, viewed in its larger aspects, has thus been characterized by what may be described as the rediscovery of the Pacific coast. How far this movement will extend it is impossible to say; it is certain, however, that it will be enormously important in re-aligning trade conditions in the United States, Canada and Mexico.</p><p>Table III. illustrates the railway mileage in the continent of America at the close of 1907.</p><lb/><table><row><cell cols="4" rows="1"><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Table III. —Railways of America in 1907</hi></p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"/><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Miles.</p></cell><cell cols="2" rows="1"><p>Miles.</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>United States.</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>236, 949</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Dutch Guiana.</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>37</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Canada</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>22, 452</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Ecuador</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>186</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Newfoundland.</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>666</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Peru....</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>1, 332</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Mexico</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>13, 612</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Bolivia</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>702</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Central America.</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>1, 392</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Brazil....</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>10, 714</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Greater Antilles.</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>2, 430</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Paraguay.</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>157</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Lesser Antilles.</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>336</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Uruguay</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>1, 210</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Colombia.</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>449</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Chile.    ...</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>2, 939</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Venezuela.</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>634</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Argentina.</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>13, 673</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>British Guiana.</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>104</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Total.</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>309, 974</p></cell></row></table><p>Outside the United States and Canada, the most interesting American developments arc in Mexico and Argentina, these countries</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>