<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-15-r01-0798-04" facs="gri_33125011197759_0806.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>RAMUS</label>
in general, denotes a branch of any thing, as of a tree, an artery, &amp;c. Tn the anatomy of plants it means the ſirſt or lateral branches, which go off from the petiolum, or middle rib of a leaf. Tne ſubdiviſions of thefe are called <hi rend="italic">ſurculi ;</hi> and the final diviſions into the moſt minute of ail, are by ſome called <hi rend="italic">capiUamεηta ;</hi> but both kinds are generally denominated <hi rend="italic">ſurculus.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Ramus (Peter), was one of the moſt famous pro* feſſors of the 16th century. He was born in Picardy in 1515. A thirſt tor learning prompted him to go to Paris when very young, and he was admitted a ſervant in the college of Navarre. Spending the day in waiting on his maſters, and the greateſt part of the night in ſtudy, he made ſuch ſurpriſing progreſs, that, when he took his maſter of arts degree, he offered to maintain a quite oppoſite doctrine to that of Ariſtotle. This raifed him many enemies ; and the two firſt books he publiſhed,</hi> <hi rend="italic">Inβitutiones Dialectic#,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Arifio-telic&lt;e Aaimadverfiοnes,</hi> occaſioned great diſturbances in the univerſity of Paris : and the oppoſition againſt him was not a little heightened by his deſerting the Romiſh religion, and profeſſing that of the Reformed. Beiκg thus forced to retire from Paris, he viſited the univtr-ſities of Germany, and received great honours where-ever he came. He returned to France in 157r, and ioſt his life miſerably in the horrid maffacre of St Bartholomew’s day. He was a great orator, a man°of ur.i-verſal learning, and endowed with very fine moral quad-</p>
<pb xml:id="eb03-15-r01-0799" facs="gri_33125011197759_0807.tif"/>
<p>ties. He publiſhed many books, which Teiſſier eou-merates. Ramus’s merit in his oppoſition to Ariſtotle, and his firmneſs in undermining his authority, is unque-ſtionably great. But it has been doubted, and with much reaſon, whether he was equally ſucceſsful in his attempts after a new logical inſtitute. we have the following general outline of his plan in Dr Enfield’s Hiſtory of Philoſophy. “ Conſidering dialectics as the art of deducing concluſions from premiſes, he endeavours to improve this art, by uniting it with that of rhetoric. 0f the ſeveral branches ot rhetoric, he conſiders invention and diſpoſition as belonging equally to logic. Making Cicero his chief guide, he divides his treatiſe on dialectics into two parts, the firſt of which treats of the invention of arguments, the ſecond of judgments. Arguments he derives not only from what the Ariſtotelians call middle terms, but from any kind of propoſition, which, connected with another, may ſervc to prove any aſſertion. of theſe he enumerates various kinds. Judgments he divides into axioms, or ſelf-evi-dent propoſitions, and <hi rend="italic">diant&gt;'ea,</hi> or deductions by means of a ſeries of arguments. Both theſe he divides into various claſſes ; and illuſtrates the whole by examples from the ancient orators and poets.</p><p>" In the logic of Ramus, many things are borrowed from Ariſtotle, and only appear under new names ; and many others are derived from other Grecian ſources,</p><p>particularly from the dialogues of Plato, and the logic of the Stoics. The author has the merit of turning the art of reaſoning from the futile ſpeculations of the fchools to forenſic and common uſe ; Rut his plan is defective in confining the whole dialectic art to the ſingle object σf diſputation, and in omitting many things, which reſpect the general culture of the underſtanding and the inveſtigation of truth. Notwithſtanding the defects of his ſyſtem, we cannot, however, ſubſcribe to the ſevere cenſure which has been paſſed upon Ramus by Lord Bacon and others ; for much is, we think, due to him for having with ſo much firmneſs and perſeverance aſſerted the natural freedom of the human underſtanding. The logic of Ramus obtained great authority in the ſchools of Germany, Great Britain, Holland, and France ; and long and violent conteſts aroſe between his followers and thoſe of the Stagyrite, till his fame vaniſhed before that of Deſcartes.”</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>