<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0050-05"
                facs="gri_33125011196389_0056.tif" type="entry">
              <p>               <label><hi rend="smallcaps">Cities of</hi> REFUGE</label>, were places provided
                    as <hi rend="italic">Aſyla,</hi> for ſuch as againſt their will ſhould happen
                    to kill a man. of thefe cities there were three on each ſide Jordan: on this
                    ſide were Kedeſh of Naphtali, Hebron, and Schechem; beyond Jordan were Bezer,
                    Golan, and Ramoth-Gilead, when any of the Hebrews, or ſtrangers that dwelt in
                    their country, happened to ſpill the^ blood of a man, they might retire thither
                    to be out of the reach of the violent attempts of the relations of the deceaſed,
                    and to prepare for their defence and juſtifica-tion before the judges.
                    Themanſtayer underwent two, trials : ſirſt before the judges of the city of
                    refuge to which he had fled ; and ſecondly before the judges of his own city. If
                    found guilty, he was put to death-with all the ſeverity of the law. If he was
                    acquitted, he was not immediately ſet at liberty ;L&gt;ut, to inſpire a
                    degree of horror againſt even involuntary homicide, he <hi rend="sup">-</hi> was reconducted to the place of refuge, and obliged to-continue there in a fort
                    of baniſhment till the death of the high-prieſt. If, before this time, he
                    ventured out, the revenger of blood might freely kill him ; but after the
                    high-prieſt’s death he was at liberty to <hi rend="italic">go</hi> where he
                    pleaſed without moleſtation. It was neceffary that' the perſon. who fled to any
                    of the cſties of refuge ihould underhand ſome trade or calling, that: he might
                    not be burthenſome to the inhabitants. The cities of refuge were required to be
                    well ſupplied' with water and neceffary proviſtons. They were alſo to be of eaſy
                    acceſs, to have good roads leading to them,, with commodious bridges where there
                    was occaſion.. The width of the roads was to be 32 cubits or 48 feet at leaſh It
                    was further required, that at all cioſs-ways direction-polls ſhould be erected,
                    with an inſcriptiom pointing cut the road to the cities of refuge. The 15th of
                    Adar,, which anſwers to our February moon <hi rend="sub">r</hi> was appointed
                    for the city magiſtrates to ſee that the roads were in good condition. No perſon
                    in any of theſe cities was allowed to make weapons, leſt the relations of the
                    deceaſed ſhould be furniſhed with the means-of gratifying their revenge. Deut.
                    xix. 3. iv. 41. 43.;;. Joſh. xx. 7. Three other cities of refuge were
                    conditionally promiſed, butnever granted. See As v <hi rend="smallcaps">l u m.</hi></p>            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
