<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0125-01" facs="gri_33125011196389_0131.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>RESOLUTION</label>
of Ideas. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Logic,</hi> Parti, ch. 3,</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Resolution,</hi> in muſic. To <hi rend="italic">reſolve</hi> a diſcord or diſſonauce, fays Rouffeau, is to carry it according to rule into a conſonance in the ſubſequent chord. There is for that purpofe a procedure preſcribed, both for the fundamental baſs of the diffonant chord, and for the part by which the diffonance is formed.</p><p>There is no poſſible manner of reſolving a diffo-nance which is not derived from an operation of cadence: it is then by the kind of cadence which we wiſh to form, that the motion of the fundamental baſs is de-termined, (ſee Cadence), with reſpect to the part by which the diſibnance is formed, it ought neither to continue in its place, nor to move by disjointed gra-dations ; but to riſe or deſcend diatonically, accord-ing to the nature of the diffonance. Theoriſts ſay, that major diffonances ought to riſe, and minor to de-ſcend ; which is not however without exception, ſince in particular chords of harmony, a ſeventh, although major, ought not to riſe, but to deſcend, unleſs in that chord which is, very incorrectly, called <hi rend="italic">the chord of the ſeventh redundant.</hi> It is better then to ſay, that the ſeventh and all its derivative diffonanees ought to deſcend ; and that the ſixth ſnperadded, and all its de-rivative diffonances, ſhould riſe. This is a rule truly general, and without any exception. It is the ſame cafe with the rule of reſolving diffonances. There are ſome diffonances which cannot be prepared ; but there is by no means one which ought not to be reſolved.</p><p>with reſpect to the ſenſible note, improperly called a <hi rend="italic">major diſfonance,</hi> if it ought to aſcend, this is leſs on account of the rule for reſolving diffonanees, than on account of that which preſcribes a diatonic procedure, and prefers the ſhorteſt road ; and in reality, there are caſes, as that of the interrupted cadence, in which this fenſible note does not aſcend.</p><p>In chords by ſuppoſition, one ſingle chord often produces two diffonances ; as the ſeventh and ninth, the ninth and fourth, &amp;c.· Then theſe two diffonances ought to have been prepared, and both muff iikewiſe be reſolved ; it is becauſe regard ſhould be paid to every thing which is diſcordant, not only in the fun-damental, but even in the continued baſs.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Resolution, in chemiſtry, the reduction of a mixed body into its component parts or ſirſt principles, as far as can be done by a proper analyſis.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Resolution,</hi> in medicine, the diſappearing of any tumor without coming to fuppuration or forming an abſceſs.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>