<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-15-r01-0778-05" facs="gri_33125011197759_0786.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>RAIN</label>
the deſcent of water from the atmofphere^ in the form of drops of a conſiderable ſize. By this circumſtance it is diſtinguiſhed from dew and fog : in the former of which the drops are ſo ſmall that they are quite inviſible ; and in the latter, though their ſize is larger, they ſeem to have very little more fpecific gravity than the atmoſphere itſelf,. and may therefore be reckoned hollow ſpherules rather than drops.</p><p>It is univerſally agreed, that rain is produced by the water previouſly abſorbed by the heat of the ſun, or otherwiſe, from the terraqueous globe, into the atmoſphere ; but very great difficulties occur when we begin to explain why the water, once ſo cloſely united with the atmoſphere, begins to ſeparate from it. we cannot afcribε this ſeparation to cold, ſince rain often takes place in very warm weather ; and though we ſhould ſuppofe the condenfation owing to the ſuperior cold of the higher regions, yet there is a remarkable fact which will not allow us to have recourſe to this ſuppofition. It is certain that the drops of rain increaſe in ſize con-ſiderably as they deſcend. Οη the top of a hill, for inſtance, they will be finall and inconfiderable, forming only a drizzling ſhower ; but at the bottom of the ſame hill the drops will be exceſſively large, deſcending in an impetuous rain ; which ſhows that the atmoſphere is diſpoſed to condenſe the vapours, and actually does ſo, as well where it is warm as where it is cold.</p><p>For ſome time the ſuppoſitions concerning the cauſe of rain were exceedingly inſufficient and unſatisfactory. It was imagined, that when various conge-ries of clouds were driven together by the agitation of the winds, they mixed, and run into one body, by which means they were condenſed into water. The eoldnefs of the upper parts of the air alſo was thought to be a great means of collecting and condenſing the clouds into water ; which, being heavier than the air, muſt neceſſarily fall down through it in the form of rain. The reaſon why it falls in drops, and not in large quantities, was ſaid to be the refiſtance of the air; whereby being broken, and divided into ſmaller and ſmaller parts, it at laſt arrives to us in ſmall drops. But this hypotheſis is entirely contrary to almoſt all the phenomena : for the weather, when coldeſt, that is, in the time of ſevere fioſt, is generally the moſt ſerene ; the moſt violent rains alſo happen where there is little or no cold to condenſe the clouds ; and the drops of rain, inſtead of being divided into ſmaller and finaller ones as they approach the earth, are plainly increaſed in ſizc as they deſcend.</p>
<pb xml:id="eb03-15-r01-0779" facs="gri_33125011197759_0787.tif"/>
<p>Dr Derhatn accounted for the precipitation of the drops of ram from the veficulæ being full of air, and meeting with an air colder than they contained, the air they contained was of conſequence contracted into a fmaller ſpace ; and conſequently the watery ſhell rendered thicker, and thus ſpecifically heavier, than the common atmoſphere. But it has been ſhown, that the veficulæ, if ſuch they are, of vapour, are not ſilled with air, but with ſire, or heat ; and conſequent-ly, till they part with this latent heat, the vapour can-not be condenſtd §. Now, cold is not always ſufficient to effect this, ſince in the moſt ſevere froſts the air is very often ſerene, and parts with little or none of its va-pour for a very conſiderable time. Neither can we admit the winds to have any conſiderable agency in this matter, ſince we ſind that blowing upon vapour is ſo far from condenſing it, that it unites it more cloſely with the air, and wind is found to be a great promoter of evaporation.</p><p>According to Rohault, the great cauſe of rain is the heat of the air ; which, after continuing for ſome time near the earth, is raiſed on high by a wind, and there thawing the ſnowy villi or flocks of half-frozen veficulæ, reduces them to drops ; which, coaleſcing, de-ſcend. Here, however, we ought to be informed by what means theſe veficulæ are ſuſpended in their half-frozen ſtate ; fince the thawing of them can make but little difference in their ſpeciſic gravity, and it is cer-tain that they afcended through the air not in a fro-zen but in an aqueous ſtate.</p><p>Dr Clarke and others afcribe this defcent of the rain rather to an alteration of the atmoſphere than of the veficulæ ; and ſuppoſe it to ariſe from a diminution of the elaſtic force of the air. This elaſticity, which, they ſay, depends chiefly or wholly upon terrene exhalations, being weakened, the atmofphere links under its burden, and the clouds fall. Now, the little veſicles being once upon the deſcent, will continue there-in, notwithſtanding the increaſe of reſiſtance they <hi rend="sub">j</hi> every moment meet with. For, as they all tend to the centre of the earth, the farther they fall, the more coalitions they will make ; and the more coalitions, rhe more matter will there be under the ſame ſurface ; the furface increafing only as the ſquares, but the ſolidity as the cubes ; and the more matter under the ſame furface, the leſs reſiſtance will there be to the fame matter. Thus, if the cold, wind, &amp;c. act early enough to precipitate the aſcending veſicles before they are arrived at any conſiderable height, the coalitions being but few, the drops will be proportionably ſmall ; and thus is formed a dew. If the vapours be more copious, and riſe a little higher, we have a miſt or fog. A little higher ſtill, and they produce a ſmall ιain ; if they neither meet with cold nor wind, they form a heavy thick dark ſky. This hypotheſis is equally unſatisfactory with the' others ; for, granting that the de-ſcent and condenſation of the vapours are owing to a diminution of the atmofphere’s elaſticity, by what is this diminution occaſioned ? To fay that it is owing to ter-rene exhalations, is only ſolving one difficulty by another ; ſince we are totally unacquainted both with the mature and operation of theſe exhalations. Beſides, let us ſuppoſe the cauſe to be what it will, if it acts equally and at once upon all the vapour in the air, then ail that vapour muſt be precipitated at once ; and thus, inſtead of gentle ſhowers continuing for a confiderable length of time, we ſhould have the moſt violent water-ſpouts, continuing only for a few minutes, or perhaps ſeconds, which, inſtead of refreſhing the earth, would drown and lay waſte every thing before them.</p><p>Since philoſophers have admitted the electric fluid to ſuch a large ſhare in the operations of nature, al-moſt all the natural phenomena have been accounted for by the action of that fluid ; and rain, among others, has been reckoned an effect of electricity. But this word, unleſs it is explained, makes us no wiſer .than we were before ; the phenomena of artificial electricity having been explained on principles which could ſcarce apply in any degree to the electricity of nature : and therefore all the ſolution we can obtain of the natural appearances of which we ſpeak, comes to this, that rain is occaſioned by a moderate electrification, hail and ſnow by one more violent, and thunder by the moſt violent of all ; but in what manner this electrification is occa-ſioned, hath not yet been explained. Throughout the various parts of this work where electricity hath been occafionally mentioned, the principles of artificial electricity j∣, laid down in the treatiſe appropriated to that ſubject, have been applied to the ſolution ot the phenomena of nature ; thoſe which are necefl’ary to be attend-ed to here are the following :</p><p>1. The electric fluid and ſolar light are the ſame fubſtance in two different modifications.</p><p>2. Electricity is the motion of the fluid when running, or attempting to run, in a continued ſtream from one place to another : heat is when the fluid has no tendency but to vibrate outwards and inwards to and from a centre ; or at leaſt when its ſtreams converge to a point or focus.</p><p>3. The fluid acting as electricity, like water, or any other fluid, always tends to the place where there is leaſt reſiſtance.</p><p>Οη theſe three principles may the phenomena of at-moſpherical electricity, and the deſcent of rain by its means, be explained as follows :</p><p>i The light or heat of the ſun, acting in that pe-cüliar manner which we call <hi rend="italic">heat,</hi> unites itſelf with the moiſture of the earth, and forms it into vapour, which thus becomes ſpecifically lighter than air, and of conlequence aſcends in the atmoſphere to a certain height.</p><p>2. Befides the quantity of light which is thus united to the water, and forms it into vapour, a very con-fiderable quantity enters the earth, where it affumes the nature of electric fluid.</p><p>3. As the earth is always full of that fluid, every quantity which enters muſt difplace an equal quantity which is already there.</p><p>4. This quantity which is difplaced muſt eſcape ei-ther at a diitance from the place where the other en-ters, or very near it.</p><p>5. At whatever place a quantity of electric matter eſcapes, it muſt electrify the air above that place where it has eſcaped ; and as a confiderable quantity of light muſt always be reflected from the earth into the atmoſphere, where it does not combine with the aqueous vapour, we have thence another ſource of electricity to the air ; as this quantity muſt undoubt-edly affume the action of electric fluid, elpecially after the action of the ſun has ceaſed. Hence the rea-</p>
<pb xml:id="eb03-15-r01-0780" facs="gri_33125011197759_0788.tif"/>
<p>ſon why in ſerene weather the atmofphcrical electricity is always ſtrongeſt, and rather more ſo in the night than in the day.</p><p>6. From theſe conſiderations, we ſee an evident rea-ſon why there muſt commonly be a difference between the electricity of the earth and that of the atmo-ſphere, excepting when an earthquake is about to en-fue. The confequence of this muſt be, that as the action of the ſolar light continues to bring down the electric matter, and the earth continues to difcharge an equal quantity of it into the atmoſphere, ſome part of the atmoſphere muſt at laſt become overloaded with it, and attempt to throw it back into the earth. This attempt wiſl be vain, until a vent is found for the electricity at ſome other place ; and as foon as this happens, the electrified atmoſphere begins to throw off its ſuperfluous electricity, and the earth to receive it. As the atmoſphere itſelf is a bad conductor, and the more ſo the drier it is, the electric matter attacks the ſmaſl aqueous particles which are detained in it by means of the latent heat. Thefe being unable to bear the im-petus of the fluid, throw out their latent heat, which eaſily eſcapes, and thus makes a kind of vacuum in the electrified part of the atmoſphere. The conſequences of this are, that the aqueous particles being driven together in large quantity, at laſt become vi-ſible, and the <hi rend="italic">jky</hi> is covered with clouds ; at the fame time a wind blows againſt thefe clouds, and, if there is no reſiſtance in the atmoſphere, wiſl drive them away.</p><p>7. But if the atmofphere all round the cloud is ex-cεedingly electrified, and the earth is in no condition to receive the ſuperfluous fluid excepting in that place ■which is directly under the cloud, then the whole electricity of the atmofphere for a vaſt way round wiſl tend to that part only, and the cloud wiſl be electrified to an extreme degree. A wind wiſl now blow againſt the cloud from all quarters, more and more of the vapour wiſl be extricated from the air by the electric matter, and the cloud wiſl become darker and thicker, at the ſame time that it is' in a manner ſtationary, as· being acted upon by oppoſite winds ; though its ſize is enlarged with great rapidity by the continual ſupplies of vapour brought by the winds.</p><p>8. The vapours which were formerly ſuſpended in-viſibly by means of the latent heat are now ſuſpended viſibly by the electric fluid, which wiſl not let them" fall to the earth, until it is in a condition to rε-ceive the electric matter deſcending with the rain.— It is eaſy to ſee, however, that thus every thing is prepared for a violent ſtorm of thunder and lightning as well as rain. The ſurface of the earth becomes electrified from the atmoſphere : but when this has con-tinued for ſome time, a zone of earth conſiderably below the ſurface acquires an electricity oppoſite to that of the clouds and atmoſphere ; of conſequence the elec-tricity in the cloud being violently preſſed on aſl ſides, wiſl at laſt burſt out towards that zone where the re-ſiſtance is leaſt, as explained under the article Light-ning.—The vapours now having loſt that which ſup-ported them, wiſl fall down in rain, if there is not a ſufficient quantity of electric matter to keep them in the ſame ſtate in which they were before : but if this happens to be the cafe, the cloud wiſl inſtantly be charged again, while little or no rain wiſl faſl ; and hence very violent thunder fometimes takes place with-</p><p>out any rain at aſl, or ſuch as is quite inconfiderable in quantity.</p><p>9. when the electricity is leſs violent, the rain wilI deſcend in vaſt quantity, efpecially after every flaih of lightning ; and great quantities of electric matter wiſl thus be conveyed to the earth, inſomuch that ſometimes the drops have been obſerved to ſhine as if they were on fire, which has given occaſion to the reports of fiery rain having fallen on certain occaſions. If the quantity of electric matter is ſmaller, ſo that the rain can convey it all gradually to the ground, there wiſl be rain without any thunder ; and the greater the quantity of electricity the more violent wiſl be the rain.</p><p>From this account of the cauſes of rain, we may ſee the reaſon why in warm climates the rains are exceffive, and for the moſt part accompanied with thun-der ; for there the electricity of the atmoſphere is im-menfely greater than it is with us. we may alld fee why in certain places, according to the ſituation of mountains, ſeas, &amp;c. the rains will be greater than in others, and likewiſe why fome parts of the world are exempted from rain altogether ; but as a particular diſcuſſion of thefe would neceſſarily include an explana-tion of the cauſes and phenomena of Thunder, we ſhall foi this reaſon refer the whole to be treated of under that article.</p><p>whether this theory be juſt, however, it would be too ⅛ affuming in us to ſay. It may admit of difpute, for we muſt grant that in the very beſt ſyſtems, though an occur-rence ſo frequent, the theory of rain is but very imperfectly underſtood. Dr James Hutton, Fellow of the Royal Society of Edinburgh, whofe ſpeculations are always ingenious, though generally extraordinary, and much out of the common way, gives us a new theory of rain in the firſt volume of the Tranſactions of that ſociety. It is well known that atmoſpheric air is capable of diſſolving, with a certain degree of heat, a gi-ven quantity of water. The Doctor aſcertains the ra-tio of the diſſolving power of air, in relation to water, in different degrees of heat ; and ſhows, that by mixing a portion of tranfparent humid warm air with a portion of cold air, the mixture becomes opake, and part of the water wiſl be precipitated ; or, in other words, the va-pour yfill be condenſed into rain. The ratio which he ſtates, however, does not appear to us to be ſupported by experience. whether the electricity of the air changes in conſequence of its depoſiting the water diſ-ſolved in it, or the change is a caufe of this depoſition, muſt remain uncertain ; but, in either view, there muſt be an agent different from heat and cold, ſince the changes in theſe reſpects do not in other operations change the ſtate of electricity. Dr Hutton ſuppoſes that heat and folution do not increaſe by equal increments ; but that, in reality, if heat be ſuppoſed to in-creaſe by equal increments along a ſtraight line, ſolution wiſl be expreſſed by ordinates to a curve whoſe convex ſide is turned towards that line. That the power of ſolution is not increaſed in the ſame ratio with heat, is, however, hypothetical, except when we riſe pretty high in the ſcale, when its proportional increaſe is a littler doubtful ; and it is not, in this paper, fupported by ex-periment. The condenſation of the breath in air is not an obſervation in point, except in air already ſaturated with vapour. It can amount, in any view, to no more than this, that to render it viſible, the heat muſt be di-</p>
<pb xml:id="eb03-15-r01-0781" facs="gri_33125011197759_0789.tif"/>
<p>miniſhed in a greater proportion than can be compen-fated by the power of ſolution in the body of air, in which the portion expired is at firſt immerſed. To ex-plain rain ſrom this cauſe, we muſt always ſuppoſe a conſtant diminution of heat to take place at the moment of the condenſation of the vapour ; but we actu-ally find that the change from a ſtate of vapour to the fluid ſtate is attended with heat ; ſo that rain muſt at once oppoſe its own cauſe, and continued rains would be impoſſible, without calling in the aid of other caufes. From his own ſyſtem, Dr Hutton endcavourβ to ex-plain the regular and irregular ſeaſons of rain, either reſpecting the generality of its appearance, or the re-gularity of its return And to obviate the apparent ex-ceptions of the theory, from the generality of rain, he explains the proportional quantities of rain, and adds a comparative eſtimate of climates, in relation to rain, with the meteorological obſervations made in our own climate. As his principle is at leaſt inſufficient, and we think erroneous, it would be uſeleſs, even were this a proper place for it, to purſue theſe various brân-ches, which muſt partakc of the errors of the ſyſtem. In theſe branches we ought to obſerve, that there are ſeveral juſt obſervations, mixed with errors, becauſe eva-poration and condenſation muſt at laſt be the great ba-ſis of every theory : the miſtakes ariſe from not being aware of all the cauſes, and miſrepreſenting the opera-tion of thoſe which do exiſt.</p><p>In a work entitled Thoughts on Meteorology, V0-lume II. M. de Luc conſiders very particularly the grand phenomenon of rain, and the numerous circumſtances connected with it. He examines the ſeveral hypotheſes with conſiderable care ; but thinks them, even if admiffible, utterly inſufficient to account for the forma-tion of rain. The grand queſtion in this inquiry is, what becomes of the water that riſes in vapour into the atmoſphere ? or what ſtate it ſubſiſts in there, between the time of its evaporation and its falling down again in rain ? If it continues in the ſtate of watery vapour, or ſuch as is the immediate product of evaporation, it muſt poſſeſs the diſtinctive characters eſſential to that fluid : it muſt make the hygrometer move towards hu-midity, in proportion as the vapour is more or leſs· abundant in the air : on a diminution of heat, the humidity, as ſhown by the hygrometer, muſt increafe; and on an increaſe of the heat the humidity muſt diminiſh ∙, and the introduction of other hygroſcopic ſubſtances, drier than the air, muſt have the ſame effeéf as an aug-mentatioπ of heat. Theſe are the properties of watery vapour, on every hypotheſis of evaporation ; and there -fυre all the water that exiſts in the atmoſphere without poffeffing theſe properties, is no longer vapour, but muſt have changed its nature. M. de Luc ſhows, that the water which forms rain, though it has ever been, conſidered and reaſoned upon as producing humidity, does not poſſeſs theſe properties, and muſt therefore have paſſed into another ſtate. See a full account of his reaſoning, and the ſteps by which he proceeded, in the article Meteorology, n <hi rend="sup">o</hi> 7, &amp;c. Ashe thinks that the vapour paſſes into an inviſible ſtate in the interval be-tween evaporation and its falling again in rain, and that in that ſtate it is not ſenſible to the hygrometer, he conſiders the laws of hygrolυgy as inſufficient for explaining the formation of rain ; but he does not pre-tend tohave diſcovered thejmmediate cauſe of the ſor-e</p><p>mation of clouds and rain. If it is not in the imme-diate product of evaporation that rain has its ſource » if the vapours change their nature in the atmofphere&gt; ſo as no longer to be ſenſible to the hygrometer, or to the eye ; if they do not become vapour again till clouds appear ; and if, when the clouds are formed, no altera-tion is perceived in the quality of the air—we muſt acknowledge it to be very probable, that the interme-diate ſtate of vapour is no other than air—and that the clouds do not proceed from any diſtinct fluid contained in the atmoſphere, but from a decompoſition of a part of the air itſelf, perfectly ſimilar to the reſt.</p><p>It appears, to us at leaſt, that M. de Luc’s mode of reaſening on this ſubject agrees better with the phe-nomena than Dr Hutton’s. The Doctor, however, thinks differently, and publiſhed anſwers to the objections of M. de Luc with regard to his theory of rain ; to which M. de Luc replied in a letter which was printed in the Appendix to the 8iſt volume of the Monthly Review : but it would extend our article beyond its due bounds, to give a view of this controver-ſy. See vapour, water, weather, and wind.</p><p>As to the general quantity of rain that falls, and its-proportion in ſeveral places at the ſame time, and in the ſame place at ſeveral times, we have many obſervations, journals, &amp;c. in the Memoirs of the French A-cademy, the Philofophical Tranſactions, &amp;c. Upon meaſuring, then, the rain falling yearly, its depth, at a medium, and its proportion, in ſeveral places, is found as in the following table : Inches.</p><table> <row> <cell cols="2" rows="1"> <p>At Townley, in Lancaſhire, obſerved by Mr Townley - -</p><p>Upminſter, in Eſſex, by Dr Derham</p><p>Zurich, in Swiſſerland, by Dr Scheuchzer Piſa, in Italy, by Dr Mich. Ang. Tilli</p><p>Paris, in France, by M. de la Hire</p><p>Liſle, in Flanders, by M. de vauban</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>42⅛</p><p>19i 32τ 43⅛∙</p><p>L <hi rend="sub">9</hi></p><p>24</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>At Upminſter.</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>At Paris.</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"/> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>1700 19 Inch. .03</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>21 Inch. .37</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"/> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>1701 18 .69</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>27 .77</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"/> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>1702 20 .38</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p><hi rend="sup">1</hi> 7 ∙45</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"/> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>1703 23 .99</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>18 .51</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"/> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>1704 15 .80</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>21 .20</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"/> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>1705 16 .93</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>14 .82·</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"/> </row> </table> <p>From the Meteorological Journal of the Royal Society, kept by order of the preſident and council, it ap-pears that the whole quantity of rain at London, in each of the years ſpeciſied below, was as follows <hi rend="sub">j</hi></p><table> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>viz.</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"/> <cell cols="1" rows="1"/> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>Inches.</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>1774</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>»</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>26</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>.328</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>1775</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>-</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>24</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p><hi rend="smallcaps">∙ <hi rend="sup">c8</hi> 3 v</hi></p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>1776</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>-</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>20</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>•354</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>1777</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>-</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>25</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>•371</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>1778</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>-</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>20</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>•772-</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>17 79</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>-</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>26</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>.785</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>1780</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"/> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="sup"> 1</hi> 7</hi></p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>∙3 <hi rend="sup">1</hi> 3</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>The quantity of rain in</p></cell> <cell cols="3" rows="1"> <p>the four following years at Lon-</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>don was,</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"/> <cell cols="2" rows="1"> <p>Inches.</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>In 1789</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>-</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>21</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>•976</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>1790</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>-</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>16</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>.052</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>1791</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>-</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>15</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>.310</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>179-2</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>-</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p><hi rend="sup">1</hi> 9</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>.489</p></cell> </row> </table>
<pb xml:id="eb03-15-r01-0782" facs="gri_33125011197759_0790.tif"/>
<table> <row> <cell cols="8" rows="1"> <p><hi rend="italic">Proportion of the Rain of the fiver al St (font to one another.</hi></p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>170S</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>Depth at Piſa.</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>Depth at Up∏iiπf.</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>Depth at Zurich.</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>1708</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>Depth at Piſa.</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>Depth at Upminſ</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>Deptha¢</p><p>Zurich.</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>Jan.</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>Inch.</p><p>6 .41</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>Inch.</p><p><hi rend="italic">2</hi> .88</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>Inch.</p><p>I .64</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>July</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>Inch.</p><p>0 .00</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>Inch.</p><p>1 .11</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>Inch.</p><p>3 ∙5 <hi rend="sup">θ</hi></p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>Feb.</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>3 -28</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>0 .46</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>1 .65</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>Aug.</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>2 <hi rend="italic">.2J</hi></p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>2 .94</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>3 ∙i5</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>Mar.</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p><hi rend="italic">2</hi> .65</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>2 .03</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p><hi rend="sup">1</hi> ∙5 <hi rend="sup">1</hi></p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>Sept.</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p><hi rend="italic">7 .21</hi></p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>1 .46</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>3 ∙° <hi rend="sup">2</hi></p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>April</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>I .25</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>0 .96</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>4 ∙ <hi rend="sup">6</hi> 9</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>oct.</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p><hi rend="italic">5</hi> ∙33</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>0 .23</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>2 .44</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>May</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>3 ∙33</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p><hi rend="italic">2 .02</hi></p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>1 .91</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>Nov.</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>0 .13</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>0 .86</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>0 .62</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>June</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>4 ∙9°</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p><hi rend="italic">2</hi> .32</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>5 .91</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>Dec.</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>0 .00</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p><hi rend="sup">1</hi> ∙97</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>2 .62</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>Half</p><p>Year</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>21 .82</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>IO .67</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p><hi rend="sup">1</hi> 7 <hi rend="smallcaps">∙3 <hi rend="sup">i</hi></hi></p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>Half</p><p>Year</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p>_</p><p>14. .94</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p><hi rend="sup">8</hi> -57</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> <p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="sup"> 1</hi> 5</hi> ∙35</p></cell> </row> </table> <p>See Philofophical Tranſactions abridged, vol. iv. p. ii. p. 8ι, &amp;c. and alſo Meteorological Journal of the Royal Society, publiſhed annually in the Philolbphica∙l Tranſactions.</p><p>As to the uſe of rain, we may obferve, that it moi-ſtens and ſoftens the earth, and thus fits it for affording nouriſhment to plants ; by falling on high mountains, it carries down with it many particles of loofe earth, which ſerve to fertilize the ſurrounding valleys, and purifies the air from noxious exhalations, which tend in their return to the earth to meliorate the foil ; it moderates the heat of the air; and is one means of ſupplying foun-tains and rivers. However, vehement rains in many .countries are found to be attended with barrenneſs and poornefs of the lands, and miſcarriage of the crops in the ſucceeding year : and the reaſon is plain ; for thefe exceſſive ſtorms waſh away the fine mould into the rivers, which carry it into the fea, and it is a long time before the land recovers itſelf again. The remedy to the fa-mine, which ſome countries are ſubject to from this fort of mifchief, is the planting large orchards and groves oſ ſuch trees as bear eſculent fruit ; for it is an old ob-ſervation, that in years, when grain ſucceeds worſt, th'eſe trees produce moſt fruit of all. It may partly be owing to the thorough moiſtening of the earth, as deep as their roots go by thefe rains, and partly to their trunks ſtopping part of the light mould carried down by the rains, and by this means furniſhing themſelves with a coat of new earth.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Preternatural Rains,</hi> we have numerous accounts, in the hiſtorians of our own as well as other countries, of preternatural rains ; ſuch as the raining of ſtones, of duſt, of blood, nay, and of living animals, as young frogs, and the like. We are not to doubt the truth of what thofe who are authors of veracity and credit relate to us of this kind, ſo far as to ſuppoſe that the falling of ſtones and duſt never happened ; the whole miſtake is, the fuppoſing them to have fallen from the clouds : but as to the blood and frogs, it is very certain that they never fell at all, but the opinion has been a mere deception of the eyes. Men are extremely fond of the marvellous in their relations ; but the judicious reader is to examine ſtrictly whatever is reported oſ this kind, and is not to ſuffer himſelf to be deceived.</p><p>There are two natural methods by which quantities of ſtones and duſt may fall in certain places, without thcir having been generated in the clouds or fallen as rain. The one is by means of hurricanes : the wind which we frequently ſee tearing off the tiles of houſes, and carrying them to conſiderable diſtances, being equally able to take up a quantity of ſtones, and drop them again at ſome other place. But the other, which is much</p><p>the moſt powerful, and probably the moſt uſual way, is for ſhe eruptions of volcanoes and burning mountaina to toſs up, as they frequently do, a vaſt quantity of ſtones, aſhes, and cinders, to an immenſe height in the air : and theſe, being hurried away by the hurricanes and impetuous winds which ufually accompany thoſe eruptions, and being in themſelves much lighter than common ſtones, as being half calcined, may eaſily be thus carried to vaſt diſtances ; and there ſailing in pla-ces where the inhabitants know nothing of the occaſion, they cannot but be ſuppofed by the vulgar to fall on them from the clouds. It is well known, that, in the great eruptions of Ætna and veſuvius, ſhowers of aſhes, duſt, and ſmall cinders, have been ſeen to obſcure the air, and overſpread the ſurſace of the fea for a σ <hi rend="sub">r</hi> eat way, and cover the decks of ſhips ; and this at ſuch a diſtance, as it ſhould appear ſcarce conceivable that they ſhould have been carried to : and probably, if the ac-counts of all the ſhowers of thefe ſubſtances mentioned by authors be collected, they will all be found to have fallen within ſuch diſtances of volcanoes ; and if compared as to the time of their falling, will be found to correſpond in that alſo with the eruptions of thofe mountains. AVe have known inſtances of the aſhes from veſuvius having been carried thirty, nay, forty leagues, and peculiar accidents may have carried them yet farther. It is not to be ſuppofed that theſe ſhowers of ſtones and duſt fall for a continuance in the manner of ſhowers of rain, or that the fragments or pieces are as frequent as drops of water ; it is ſufficient that a number of ſtones, or a quantity of duſt, fall at once on a place, where the inhabitants can have no knowledge of the part from whence they came, and the vulgar will not doubt their dropping from the clouds. Nay,in the canton of Berne in Swiſſerland, the inhabitants accounted it &amp; miracle that it rained earth and ſulphur upon them at a time that a ſmall volcano terrified them ; and even while the wind was ſo boiſterous, and hurricanes ſo frequent, that they ſaw almoſt every moment the duſt, ſand, and little ſtones torn up from the ſurface of the earth in whirlwinds, and carried to a conſiderable height in the air, they never conſider¢d that both the ſulphur thrown up by the volcano, and the duſt, &amp;c. carried from their feet muſt fall ſoon after ſomewhere. It is very certain that in ſome of the terrible ſtorms of large hail, where the hail-ſhmes have been of many inches round, on breaking them there have been found what people have called <hi rend="italic">flones in their middle;</hi> but theſe obſervers needed only to have waited the diffolving of one of theſe hail-ſtones, to have ſeen the ſtone in its centre diſunite alſo, it being only formed oſ the parti-cles of looſe earthy matter, which the water, exhaled by the fun’s heat, had taken up in extremely ſmall mole-culæ with it ; and this only having ſerved to give an opake hue to the inner part of the congelation, to which the freezing of the water alone gave the apparent hard-neſs of ſtone.</p><p>The raining of <hi rend="italic">blood</hi> has been ever accounted a more terrible ſight and a more fatal omen than the other preternatural rains already mentioned. It is very certain that nature forms blood nowhere but in the veffels of animals; and therefore ſhowers of it from the clouds are by no means to be credited. Thofe who ſuppoſe that what has been taken for blood has been actually ſeen falling through the air, have had recourſe to flying infects for its origin, and ſuppoſe it the eggs or dung of</p>
<pb xml:id="eb03-15-r01-0783" facs="gri_33125011197759_0791.tif"/>
<p>certain butterflies diſcharged from them as they were high up in the air. But it ſeems a very wild conjec-ture, as we know of no butterfly whoſe excrements or eggs are of ſuch a colour, or whoſe abode is ſo high, or their flocks ſo numerous, as to be the occaſion of this.</p><p>It is moſt probable that theſe bloody waters were never ſeen falling ; but that people feeing the ſtanding ■waters b∙lood∙ coloured, were affured, from their not knowing how it ſhould elfe happen, that it had rained blood into them. A very memorable inſtance of this there was at the Hague in the year 1670. Swammerdam, who relates it, tells us, that one morning the whole town was in an uproar on finding their lakes and ditches full of blood, as they thought ; and having been certainly full of water the night before, they agreed it muſt have rained blood in the night : but a certain phy-ſician went down to one of the canals, and taking home a quantity of this blood-coloured water, he examined it by the microfcope, and found that the water was water ſtill, and had not at all changed its colour ; but that it was full of prodigious ſwarms of ſmall red animals, all alive, and very nimble in their motions, whoſe colour and prodigious number gave a red tinge to the whole body of the water they lived in, on a leſs accurate in-ſpection. The certainty that this was the caſe, did not however perſuade the Hollanders to part with the mi-racle : they prudently concluded, that the ſudden ap-pearancε of ſuch a number of animals was as great a prodigy as the raining of blood would have been ; and are aſſured to this day, that this portent foretold the ſcene of war and deſtruction which Louis XIV. afterwards brought into that country, which had before enjoyed 40 years uninterrupted peace.</p><p>The animals which thus colour the water of lakes and ponds are the <hi rend="italic">pulices arboreſcentes</hi> of Swammerdam, or the water-fleas with branched horns. Thefe creatures are of a reddiſh-yellow cr flame colour : they live about the ſides of ditches, under weeds, and among the mud. ; and are therefore the leſs viſible, except at a certain time, which is in the end or beginning of June : it is at this time that theſe little animals leave their receſſes to float looſe about the water, to meet for the propagation of their ſpecies, and by that means become viſible in the colour they give the water. This is viſible, more or leſs, in one part or other of almoſt all ſtanding waters at this feafon ; and it is always at this ſeaſon that the bloody waters have alarmed the ignorant. See <hi rend="italic">Pυ-IEX Moηocιιlus.</hi></p><p>The raining of <hi rend="italic">frogs</hi> is a thing not leſs wonderful in the accounts of authors who love the marvellous, than thoſe of blood or ſtones ; and this is ſuppofed to hap-pen ſo often, that there are multitudes who pretend to have been eye-witneſſes of it. Theſe rains of frogs always happen after very dry ſeaſons, and are much more frequent in the hotter countries than in the cold ones. In Italy they are very frequent ; and it is not uncommon to ſee the ſtreets of Rome ſwaiming both with young frogs and toads in an inſtant in a ſhower of rain ; they hopping everywhere between the people’s legs as they walk, though there was not the leaſt appearance of them before. Nay, they have been feen to fall through the air down upon the pavements. This ſeems a ſtrong circumſtance in favour of their being raincd down from the clouds ; but, when ſtrictly examined, it comes to nothing : for theſe frogs that are ſeen to fall, are always found dead, lamed, or bruiſed by the fall, and never hop about as the reſt; and they are never ſeen to fall, except cloſe under the walls of houſes, from the roofs and gutter of which they have accidentally flipped down. Some people, who love to add to ſtrange things yet ſtranger, affirm that they have had the young frogs fall into their hats in the midſt of an open field ; but this is idle, and wholly falſe.</p><p>others, who cannot agree to their falling from the clouds, have tried to ſolve the difficulty of their ſud-den appearance, by ſuppoſing them hatched out of the egg, or ſpawn, by theſe rains. Nay, fome have ſuppo-ſed them made immediatelyout of the duſt : but there are unanſwerable arguments againſt all theſe ſuppoſitions. Equivocal generation, or the fpontaneous production of animals out of duſt, is now wholly exploded. The fall from the clouds muſt deſtroy and kill thefe tender and ſoft-bodied animals : and they cannot be at this time hatched immediately out of eggs ; becauſe the young frog does not make its appearance from the egg in form, but has its hinder legs enveloped in a fl&lt;in, and is what we call a <hi rend="italic">tadpole ;</hi> and the young frogs are at leaſt 100 times larger at the time of their appearance, than the egg from which they ſhould be hatched.</p><p>It is beyond a doubt, that the frogs which make their appearance at this time, were hatched and in being long before : but that the dry feaſons had injured them, and kept them ſluggiſhly in holes or coverts ; and that all the rain does, is the enlivening them, giving them new ſpirits, and calling them forth to ſeek new habitations, and enjoy the element they were deſtined in great part to live in. Theophraſtus, the greateſt of all the naturaliſts of antiquity, has affirmed the fame thing, we find that the error of ſuppoſing theſe creatures to fall from the clouds was as early as that author’s time ; and alſo that the truth, in regard to their appearance, was as early known ; though, in the ages ſince, authors have taken care to conceal the truth, and to hand down to us the error, we find this venerable ſage, in a fragment of his on the generation of animals which appear on a ſudden, bantering the opinion, and aſſerting that they were hatched and living long before. The world owes, however, to the accurate Signior Redi the great proof of this truth, which Theophraſtus only has affirmed : for this gentleman, diſſecting ſome of thefe new-appearing frogs, found in their ſtomachs herbs and other half-di-geſted food ; and, openly ſhowing this to his credulous countrymen, aſked them whether they thought that na-ture, which engendered, according to their opinion, theſe animals in the clouds, had alfo been ſo provident as to engendcr grais there for their food and nouriſh-rnent ?</p><p>To the raining of frogs we ought to add the raining of <hi rend="italic">grajshοpι ers</hi> and <hi rend="italic">locυjis,</hi> which have ſometimes appeared in prodigious numbers, and devoured the fruits of the earth. There has not been the leaſt pretence for the luppoſing that theie animals defcended from the clouds, but that they appeared on a fudden in prodigious numbers. The naturaliſt, who knows the many ac-ciden∙ts attending the eggs of theie and other the like animals, cannot but know that ſome ſeafons will prove particularly favourable to the hatching them, and the prodigious number of eggs that many infects lay could not but every year bring us ſuch abundance of the young, were they not liable to many accidents, and had not provident nature taken care, as in many plants, to continue</p>
<pb xml:id="eb03-15-r01-0784" facs="gri_33125011197759_0792.tif"/>
<p>the ſpecies by a very numerous ſtock of fe :ds, of which perhaps not one in 500 need take root in order to continue an equal numbcr of plants. As it is thus alſo in regard to infects, it cannot but happen, that if a favourable ſeaſon encourage the hatching of all thofe eggs, a very ſmall number of which alone were neceſſiry to continue the ſpecies, we muſt, in ſuch ſeaſons, have a proportionate abundance oſ them. There appeared a-.bout 50 years ago, in London, fuch a prodigious lwarm of the little beetle we call the <hi rend="italic">lady-cow,</hi> that the very .poſts in the ſtreets were eveιγwhere covered with them. But thanks to the progreſs of philoſophy among us, we had no body to affert that it rained cow-ladies, but con-tented ourſelves with faying that it had been a favour-able ſeaſon for their eggs. The prodigious number of a fort of grub which did vaſt miſchief about the ſame period among the corn and graſs by-eating off their roots, might alſo have been ſuppoſed to proceed from its having rained grubs by people fond of making every thing a prodigy. ; but our knowledge in natural hiſtory aſſured us, that theſe were only the hexapode worms of the. common hedge-beetle called the <hi rend="italic">cock-chafer.</hi></p><p>' The raining of <hi rend="italic">fiſhes</hi> has been a prodigy alfo much talked of in.France, where the ſtreets of a town at ſome diſtance from Paris, after a terrible hurricane in the night, which tore up trees, blew down houfes, &amp;c. were found in a manner covered with fiſhes of various ſizes. Nobody here made any doubt of theſe having fallen from the clouds ; nor did the abſurdity of fiſh, of five or fix inches long, being generated in the air, at all ſtartle the</p><p>i&gt;eople, or ſhake their belief in the miracle, till they bund, upon inquiry, that a very well-ſtocked fiſh-pond, which ſtood on an eminence in the neighbourhood, had been blown dry by the hurricane, and only the great fiſh left at the bottom of it, all the ſmaller fry having been .toffed into their ſtreets.</p><p>Upon the whole, all the ſuppoſed marvellous rains have been owing to ſubſtances naturally produced on the -earth, and either never having been in the air at all, or only carried thither by accident.</p><p>In Slleſia, after a great dearth of wheat in that country, there happened a violent ſtorm of wind and rain, and the earth was afterwards covered, in many places, with ſmall round feeds. The vulgar cried out that Pro-vidence had ſent them food, and that it had rained <hi rend="italic">m'd-let :</hi> but theſe were, in reality, only the feeds of a ſpe-cies of veronica, or fpeed-well, very common in that country ; and whoſe feeds being juſt ripe at that time, the wind had diſlodged them from their capſules, and ſcattered them about. In our own country, we have hiſtories of rains of this marvellous kind, but all fabu-lous. It was once faid to rain <hi rend="italic">wheat</hi> in wiltſhire ; and the people were all alarmed at it as a miracle, till Mr Dole ſhowed them, that what they took for wheat was .only the feeds or kernels of the berries of ivy, which being then fully ripe, the wind had diſlodged from the fides oſ houfes, and trunks of trees, on which the ivy that produced them crept.</p><p>And we even once had a raining of fiſhes near the coaſt of Kent in a terrible hurricane, with thunder and lightning. The people who ſaw ſmall ſprats ſtrewed all about afterwards, would have it that they had fallen from the clouds ; but thoſe who confidered how far the high winds have been known to carry the ſea-water, did not wonder that they ſhould be able to carry ſmall fifh with it ſo ſmall a part of the way.</p><p>In the Philofophical Tranfactions for 1782 we have the following account of a preternatural kind of rain by Count de Gioeni : “ The morning of the 24th inſtant there appeared here a moſt ſingular phenomenon. Every place expofed to the air was found wet with a coloured cretaceous grey water, which, after evapoia-ting and filtrating away, left every place covered with it to the height of two or three lines ; and all the ironwork that was touched by it became ruſty.</p><p>" The public, inclined to the marvellous, fancied va--τious cauſes of this rain, and began to fear for the ani-mals and vegetables. *►</p><p>" In places where rain-water was uſed, they abſtain-ed from it : ſome ſufpecting vitriolic principles to be mixed with it, and others predicting ſome epidemical diforder.</p><p>" Thoſe who had obſerved the exploſions of Etna 20 days and more before, were inclined to believe it origi-nated from one of them.</p><p>" The ſhower extended from N.⅞N.E. to S.4S.W. ov¢r the fields, about 70 miles in a right line from the vertex of Etna.</p><p>" There is nothing new in volcanos having thrown up ſand, and alſo ſtones, by the violent expanſive force generated within them, which ſand has been carried by the wind to diſtant regions.</p><p>“ But the colour and ſubtilty of the matter occaſion-ed doubts concerning its origin ; which increafed from the remarkable circumſtance of the water in which it came incorporated ; for which reaſons ſome other principle or origin was ſuſpected.</p><p>“ It became, therefore, neceſſary by all means to aſ-certain the nature of this matter, in order to be con-vinced of its origin, and of the effects it might produce. This could not be done without the help of a chemical analyſis. To do this then with certainty, I endeavour-ed to collect this rain ſrom places where it was moſt probable no heterogeneous matter would be mixed with it. . I therefore chofe the plant called <hi rend="italic">brajfica capitata,</hi> which having large and turned-up leaves, they contain-ed enough of this coloured water : many of thefe I emptied into a veffel, and left the contents to fettle till the water became clear.</p><p>" This being ſeparated into another veſſel, I tried it with vegetable alkaline liquors and mineral acids ; but could obferve no decompoſition by either. I then evaporated the water in order to reunite the ſubſtances that might be in ſolution ; and touching it again with the aforeſaid liquors, it ſhowed a flight eſſerveſcence with the acids, when tried with the ſyrup of violets, this became a pale green ; ſo that I was perſuaded it contained a calcareous ſalt. with the decoction of galls no precipitation was produced.</p><p>" The matter being afterwards dried in the ſhade, it appeared a very ſubtile fine earth, of a cretaceous co-lυur, but inert, from having been diluted by the rain.</p><p>" I next thought of calcining it with a flow fire, and it aſſumed the colour of a brick. A portion of this being put into a crucible, I applied to it a ſtronger heat; by which it loſt almoſt all its acquired colour. Again, I expofed a portion of this for a longer time to a very violent heat (from which a vitrification might be</p>
<pb xml:id="eb03-15-r01-0785" facs="gri_33125011197759_0793.tif"/>
<p>expected) ; it remained, however, quite ſoſt, and was eaſily bruiſed, but returned to its original duſky co-lour.</p><p>" From the moſt accurate obſervations of the ſmoke from the three calcinations, I could not diſcover either colour or ſmell that indicated any arſenical or ſulphure-ous mixture.</p><p>“ Having therefore calcined this matter in three por-tions, with three different degrees of fire, I preſented a good magnet to each : it did not act either on the firſt or fecond ; a flight attraction was viſible in many places on the third : this perſuaded me, that this earth contains a martial principle in a metallic form, and not in a vitriolic ſubſtance.</p><p>" The nature of theſe ſubſtances then being difcover-ed, their volcanic origin appears ; for iron, the more it is expofed to violent calcination, the more it is divided by the loſs of its phlogiſtic principle ; which cannot naturally happen but in the great chimney of a volcano. Calcareous ſalt, being a marine falt combined with a calcareous ſubſtance by means of violent heat, cannot be otherwiſe compoſed than in a volcano.</p><p>" As to their dreaded effects on animals and <hi rend="italic">vegetables,</hi> every one knows the advantageous ufe, in medi-cine, both of the one and the other, and this in the ſame form as they are thus prepared in the great labo-ratory of nature.</p><p>" vegetables, even in flower, do not appear in the leaſt macerated, which has formerly happened from on-ly ſhowers of ſand.</p><p>" How this volcanic production came to be mixed with water may be conceived in various ways.</p><p>" Ætna, about its middle regions, is generally fur-rounded with clouds that do not always riſe above its ſnmmit, which is 2900 paces above the level of the ſea. This matter being thrown out, and deſcending upon the clouds below it, may happen to mix and fall in rain with them in the uſual way. It may alſo be conjectured, that the thick ſmoke which the volcanic matter contained might, by its rarefaction, be carried in the atmoſphere by the winds over that tract of country ; and then cooling ſo as to condenſe and become ſpeciſi-cally heavier than the air, might deſcend in that colour-ed rain.</p><p>" I muſt, however, leave to philofophers (to whom the knowledge of natural agents belongs) the examination and explanation of ſuch phenomena, confining myſelf to obſervation and chemical experiments.”</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Rain, a well built and fortified town of Bavaria, one of the keys of this electorate, on the Lech, 20 miles weſt of Ingolſtadt. N. Lat. 48. 51. E. Long. 11. 12.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">RAiN-Bird.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Cuculus,</hi> n <hi rend="sup">θ</hi> 8.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>