<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-15-r01-0791-06" facs="gri_33125011197759_0799.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>RAMSAY</label>
(Allan), the Scots paſtoral poet, was a barber in Edinburgh in the early part of the preſent century. His taſte in poetry, however, has juſtly raiſed him to a degree of fame that may in ſomc meafure be conſidered as a recompenſe for the frowns of fortune. His ſongs are in univerſal eſteem ; as is alſo the only dramatic performance attributed to him, viz. <hi rend="italic">Patte and R-)ger,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">The Gentle Shepherd,</hi> a Scots pa-ſtoral. He died in 1743 ; and was father to the ingenious Mr Ramſay, a celebrated painter of the preſent age, and who has likewiſe diſtinguiſhed himſelf by ſomc well-written tracts on various branches of polite literature, particularly the <hi rend="italic">Invelligator.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Ramsay (Andrew Michael), generally known bv the name of the</hi> <hi rend="italic">Chevalier Ramſay,</hi> was a polite Scots writer, born of a good family at Ayr in 1686. His good parts and learning recommended him to be tutor to the ſon of the earl of wemyſs ; after which, concei-. ving a diſguſt at the religion in which he had been edu-cated, he in the ſame ill humour reviewed other Chriſtian churches ; and, finding none to his liking, reſted for a while in Deifm. while he was in this uncertain ſtate of mind, he went to Leyden ; where, falling into the company of one Poiret a royſtic divine, he received the infection of myſticifm : which prompted him to con-ſult M. Fenelon, the celebrated archbiſhop of Cambrav, who had imbibed principles of the ſame nature ; and who gained him over to the Catholic religion in 1709. The ſubſequent courſe of his life received its direction from his friendſhip and connections with this prelate ; and being appointed, governor to the duke de Chateau Thierry, and the prince de Turenne, he was madc a knight of the order of St Lazarus, He was ſent for to Rome by the chevalier de St George, to undertake the education of his children ; but he found ſo many intrigues and diſſenſions on his arrival there in 1724, that he obtained the Chevalier’s leave to return to Pa-ris. He died in 1743, <hi rend="sup">1</hi> ' <hi rend="sup">n</hi> the °fſi <hi rend="sup">ce θ</hi> f intendant to the duke of Bouillon, prince de Turenne. The .moſt ca-pital work of his writing is the <hi rend="italic">Travels of Cyrus,</hi> which has been ſeveral times printed in Engliſh.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Ramsay (the Reverend James), ſo juſtly celebrated for his philanthropy, was, on the 25th of Ju-ly</hi> <hi rend="sup">1</hi> 733&gt; born at Fraferſhurgh, a ſmall town in the county of Aberdeen, North Britain. His defcent w <hi rend="sup">,</hi> as honourable, being, through his father, from the Ramſays of Melroſe in Banffshire, and through his mother, from the ogilvies of Purie in Angus. Hi⅜-parents were of characters the moſt reſpectable, but in circumſtances by no means affluent. From his earlieſt years he difcovered a ſerious diſpoſition, and a ſtrong thirſt for knowledge ; and aſter paſſing through the courſe of a Scotch grammar ſchool education, he was inclined to purſue the ſtudies requiſite to ſit him for the profeffion of a clergyman ; an inclination with which the wiſhes of his mother, a woman of eminent piety, powerfully concurred. Several circumſtances, however, conſpired to divert him for a time from his favourite purſuit.</p><p>He was educated in the epiſcopal perſuaſion ; and ha-ving been unhappy enough to loſe his father while yet very young, he found, upon his advancing towards the ſtate of manhood, that the joint fortunes of himſelf and..</p>
<pb xml:id="eb03-15-r01-0792" facs="gri_33125011197759_0800.tif"/>
<p>his mother coald not bear the expence oſ a regular edu-cation in either of the univerſities of oxford or Cam-bridge, which he doubtleſs thought abſolutely neceffary to one who aſpired to reſpectability in the church of England. Yielding therefore to neceſſity, he reſolved to ſtudy ſurgery and pharmacy ; and was with this vicw bound apprentice to Dr Findlay, a phyſician (a) in Fra-ſerſhurgh. But though obliged to relinquiſh for a time his favourite ſtudies, he did not think ignorance excu-ſable in a ſurgeon more than in a clergyman, or conceive that he could ever.become eminent in the profeſſion in which circumſtances had placed him, merely by ſkill in ſetting a bone or compounding a medicine. He deter-mined therefore, with the full approbation of his maſter, who very ſoon diſcovered his talents for literature, to make himſelf acquainted with at leaſt the outlines of the liberal arts and fcicnces ; and with this view he repaired in 1750 to the King’s College and univerſity of Aberdeen, where he obtained one of the <hi rend="italic">burſaries</hi> or <hi rend="italic">exhibitions</hi> which are there annually beſtowed upon ſuch can-didates for them as diſplay the ſhoſt accurate knowledge of the Latin language. The ſmall ſum of five pounds, however (which none of theſe burſaries exceed), was ſtill inadequate to the expence of reſidence in college ; but our young ſtudent was ſoon to obtain a more valu-âble exhibition, and to obtain it likewiſe by his own merit.</p><p>During the long vacation he returned to his maſter Dr Findlay, and was by him intruſted with a very deſpe-rate caſe in ſurgery, of which his management may be Laid to have laid the foundation of his future fortunes. A female fervant of one of the judges of the Court of Seffion, who, when the court was not fitting, reſided in the neighbourhood of Fraſerſhurgh, had been ſo dread-fully gored by a bull, that hardly any hopes werc enter-ſtained of her recovery; but Mr Ramſay, to whoſe care ſhe was entirely leſt, treated the wound with ſuch ſkil-ful attention, that, contrary to general expectation, his patient recovered. This attracted the judge’s notice, who having informed himſelf of the young man’s cir-eumſtances and character, recommended him ſo effec-tually to Sir Alexander Ramſay of Balmain, that he j&gt;refented him with a burfary of 15 pounds a-year, which commenced at the next <hi rend="italic">fejfioη</hi> or <hi rend="italic">term,</hi> in the fame college.</p><p>He now profecuted his ſtudies with comfort ; and thougſh he was detained in college a year longer than is uſual, being obliged, upon his acceptance of a ſecond burſary, to begin his courſe anew, he always conſidered this as a fortunate circumſtance, becauſe it gave him the celebrated Dr Reid three years for his preceptor. To that great and amiable philoſopher he fo recom-mended himſelf by his talents, his induſtry, and his vir-tues, that he was honoured with his friendſhip to the day of his death. Nor was it only to his maſters that his conduct recommended him ; Sir Alexander Ramſay, whom he viſited during fome of the vacations, was ſo Well pleaſed with his conversation, that he promiſed him</p><p>another burſary, in his gift, of 251. a-year, to com. ιnence immediately on the expiration of that which he enjoyed. This promiſe hc performed in the beginning of the year 1755 ; and at the ſolicitation of Dr Findlay even paid the money per advance to enable the cxhibi-tioner to travel for the purpoſe of improving himſelf in his profeſſion.</p><p>Thus provided, Mr Ramſay went to London, and ſtu-died ſurgery and pharmacy under the auſpices of Dr Macauly ; in whoſe family he lived ſor two years, careſſed and eſteemed both by him and by his lady. Afterwards, having paſſed the uſual examination at Surgeon’s-hall, he ſerved in his medical capacity for ſeveral years in the royal navy; but how long he was continued in the ſtation of a mate, or when and by whom he was firſt appoint-ed furgeon, we have not been able to learn. We can ſay, however,* upon the beſt authority, that by his humane and diligent diſcharge of his duty in either ſtation, he endeared himſelf to the ſeamen, and acquired the e-ſteem of his officers.</p><p>of his humanity there is indeed one memorable in-ſtance, which muſt not be omitted, whilſt he acted as ſurgeon of the Arundel, then commanded by Captain (now vice-admiral Sir Charles) Middleton, a ſlave-ſhip on her paſſage from Africa to the weſt Indies fell in with the fleet to which the Arundel belonged. An epidemical diſtemper, too common in ſuch veſſels, had fwept away not only a great number of the unfortunate negroes, but alſo many of the ſhip’s crew, and among others the ſurgeon. In this diſtreſſed ſituation the commander of the Guinea ſhip applied to the Engliſh Commodore for medical aſſiſtance ; but not a ſurgeon or ſurgeon’s mate in the whole fleet, except Mr Ramſay, would expoſe himſelf to the contagion of fo dangerous a diſtemper. Prompted, however, by his own innate benevolence, and fully authorized by his no leſs bene-volent commander, the ſurgeon of the Arundel, regard-leſs of perſonal danger, and truſting in that God to whom mercy is more acceptable than ſacrifice, went on board the infected ſhip, viſited all the patients, and re-mained long enough to leave behind him written direc∙ tions for their future treatment. If a cup of cold water given in charity be entitled to a reward, how much more ſuch an action as this ? But the rewards of Chriſtianity are not immediate. Mr Ramſay indeed eſcaped the contagion ; but on his return to his own ſhip, juſt as ſhe had got on the deck, he fell and broke his thighbone ; by which he was confined to his apartment for ten months, and rendered in a ſmall degree lame through the remainder of his life.</p><p>The fearleſs humanity which he diſplayed on this occaſion gained him the 'friendſhip and eſteem of Sir Charles Middleton, which no future action of his life had the ſmalleſt tendency to impair ; but the fracture of his thigh-bone and his ſubſequent lameneſs determin. ed him to quit the navy, and once more turn hie thoughts towards the church. Accordingly, while the Arundel lay at St Chriſtopher’s, he opened his views to</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">(a)</hi> In the remote towns of Scotland the ſame man generally acts in the triple capacity of phyſician, furgeon, and apothecary ; and we could mention doctors of phyſic of the firſt eminence, who practiſe' thus within forty i∑riles of Edinburgh,</p>
<pb xml:id="eb03-15-r01-0793" facs="gri_33125011197759_0801.tif"/>
<p>feme of the principal inhabitants of that iſland, by whpm he was ſo ſtrongly recommended to th¢ biſhop of Lon-don, that on his coming home with Sir Charles Mid-dleton, who warmly joined in the recommendation, he was admitted into orders ; after which he immediate-ly returned to St Chriſtopher’s, where hc was preſent-¢d by the governor to two rectories, valued at 70ol. a-year.</p><p>As ſooh as he took poſſeſſion of his livings, in 1763, he married Mifs Rebecca Akers, the daughter of a planter of the beſt family-connections in the iſland, and began to regulate his houſehold on the pious plan incul-cated in his <hi rend="italic">Eſſay on the Treatment and Converfion oſ the African Slaves in the Britiſh Sugar Colonies.</hi> He ſummoned all his own ſlaves daily to the prayers of the fa-mily, when he took an opportunity of pointing out to them their duty in the plaineſt terms, reproving thoſe that had done amiſs, and commending ſuch as lrad ſhown any thing like virtue 5 but he confeſſed that his occa-ſſons for reproof were more frequent than for commen-dation. As became his office and character, he incul-cated upon others what he practiſed himſelf, and knew to be equally the duty of all. " Οη his firſt fettlement BS a miniſter in the weſt Indies, he made ſome public attempts to inſtruct ſlaves. PIe began to draw up ſome caſy, plain diſcourſes for their inſtruction. He invited them to attend on Sundays, at particular hours. He appointed hours at home to inſtruct ſuch ſenſible ſlaves as would of themſelves attend. He repeatedly exhorted their maſters to encourage ſuch in their attendance. He re-commended the French cuſtom, of beginning and ending work by prayer. But inconceivable is the liſtleſſ-neſs with which he was heard, and bitter was the cenſure heaped on him in return. It was quickly ſuggeſt. ed, and generally believed, that he wanted to interrupt the work of ſlaves, to give them time, forſooth, to ſay their prayers ; that he aimed at the making of them Chriſtians, to render them incapable of being good ſlaves. In one word, he ſtood, in opinion, a rebel convict againſt the intereſt and majeſty of planterſhip. And as the Jews ſay, that in every puniſhment, with which they have been proved, ſince the bondage of Egypt, there has been an ounce of the golden caff of Horeb ; ſo might he ſay, that in every inſtance of prejudice (and they were not a few) with which, till within a year or two of his departure from the country, he was exerci-fed, there was an ounce of his fruitleſs attempts to improve the minds of ſlaves,, In the bidding prayer, he had inferted a petition for the converfion of thoſe per-ſons. But it was deemed ſo diſagreeable a memento, that ſeveral white people, on account oſ it, left off attending divine ſervice. He was obliged to omit the prayer entirely, to try and bring them back. In ſhort, neither were the ſlaves, at that time, deſirous oſ being taught, «or were their maſters inclined to encourage them.”</p><p>That he was hurt by this neglect cannot be queſtion-ed, for he had a mind benevolent, warm, and irritable ; but he ſtill retained many friends amongſt the moſt wor-thy members of the community : and as he was confci-ous of having done nothing more than his duty, he con-foled himſelf with reflecting, that thofe are " bleffed whom men revile, and perſecute, and ſpeak all manner of evil againſt falſely, for the ſake of the goſpel.”</p><p>Although his ſerious ſtudies were now theological, ⅛C conſidered himſelf as anſwerable to God, his country,</p><p>and his own family, for a proper uſe of every branch of knowledge which he poſſeſſed. He therefore took the charge of ſever al plantations around him in the capacity of a medical practitioner ; and attended them with unremitting diligence, and with great ſucceſs. Thus he lived <hi rend="sub">l</hi> till the year 1777, when relinquiſhing the practice of phyſic entirely, he paid a viſit to the place of his na-tivity, which he had not feen ſince 1755. mother, whofe latter days he had made comfortable by a handſome annuity, had been dead for fome years ; but he re-warded all who had been attentive to her, or in early life ferviceable to himſelf ; and he continued the penſion to a ſiſter who had a numerous family, for which kv* huſhand was unable to provide.</p><p>After remaining three weeks in Scotland, and near a year in England, during which time he was admitted into the confidence of Lord George Germaine, ſecre-tary of ſtate for the American department, Mr Ramſay was appointed chaplain to Admiral Barrington, then going out to take a command in the weſt In-dies. Under this gallant officer, and afterwards under Lord Rodney, he was preſent at ſeveral engage-ments, where he diſplayed a fortitude and zeal for the honour of his country which would not have diſgraeed the oldeſt admiral. To the navy, indeed, he ſeems to have been ſtrongly attached ; and he wrote, at an early period of his life, an <hi rend="italic">Fffαy on the Duty and Qualifications of a Sea-officer,</hi> with ſuch a knowledge of the fervice as would have done honour to the pen of the moſt ex-perienced commander, of the firſt edition of this eſſay the profits were by its benevolent author appropriated to the Magdalen and Britiſh lying-in hofpitals, as thoſe of the fecond and third (which laſt was publiſhed about the period of which we now write) were to the maritime ſchool, or, in the event of its failure, to the marine ſociety.</p><p>Although careſſed by both the admirals under whom he ſerved, and having ſuch influence with the latter as to be able to render eſſential fervices to the Jews and other perfons whom he thought harſhly treated at the capture of <hi rend="sup">,</hi> St Euſtatius, Mr Ramſay once more quitted the ſea-ſervice, and retired to his paſtoral charge in the Iſland of St Chriſtopher’s. There, however, though the former animoſities againſt him had entirely ſubſided, and though his friendſhip was now ſolicited by every perfon of conſequence in the iſland, he remained but a little while. Sick of the life of a planter and of the pro-ſpect of ſlavery around him, he reſigned' his livings, bade adieu to the iſland, and returned to England with his wife and family in the end of the year 1781. Immediately on his arrival, he was, through the intereſt of his ſteady friend Sir Charles Middleton, preſented to the livings of Teſton and Nettleſtead in the county of Kent.</p><p>Here he was ſoon determined, by the advice of thoſe whom he moſt reſpected, to publiſh an <hi rend="italic">fiſſiy,</hi> which had been written many years before, <hi rend="italic">on the Treatment and Converfion oſ African Slaves in the Britijh Sugar Colonies.</hi> The controveiſy in which this publication invol-ved him, and the acrimony with which it was carried on, are ſo freſh in the memory of all our readers, that no man who thinks of the narrow limits within which our biographical articles muſt be confined, will blame us for not entering into a detail of the particulars.-— Torrents of obloquy were poured upon the benevolent author by writers who were unfair enough to conceal</p>
<pb xml:id="eb03-15-r01-0794" facs="gri_33125011197759_0802.tif"/>
<p>their names ; and it muſt be confeſſed, that his replies abounded with ſarcaſms, which the moſt rational friends to the caufe which he ſupported would not have been ſorry to ſee blotted from his pages. The provocation, however, which he received was great ; and Mr Ram-fay, though an amiable, virtuous, and pious man, had a warmth of temper, which, though not deſerving of praiſe, will be cenſuredby none who reflect on the frailties of our common nature. That the particular calumnies propagated againſt him on this occaſion were wholly gronndleſs, it is impoffible to doubt, if we admit him to have been poſſeſſed of common underſtanding. when ſome years ago a ſtory was circulated, of Swift’s ha-ving, when prebendary of Kilroot, been convicted before a magiſtrate of an attempt to commit a rape on the body of one of his pariſhioners, it was thought a ſufficient confutation of the calumny to put the retail-er of it in mind, that the dean of St Patrick’s, though deteſted by the moſt powerful faction in the kingdom, lampooned without dread, and with great ſeverity, the dean of Ferns for the very crime of which, had thi3 anecdote been true, he muſt have been conſcious that all Ireland knew himſelf to be guilty ! Such conduct cannot be reconciled to common ſenſe. Had Swift been a raviſher, though he might have been penitent, and reaſoned in general terms againſt giving way to ſuch licentious paſſions, he would never have ſatyriſed a <hi rend="italic">particular perſon</hi> for the crime of which he himſelf ſtood convicted. In like manner, had Mr Ramſay been a tyrant to his own ſlaves, though he might have ar-gued againſt ſlavery in the abſtract, on the broad baſis of virtue and religion, he never could have arraigned for ſimilar cruelty a number of individuals in the very iſland which wſtneſſed his own enormities.</p><p>But the melancholy part of the narrative is behind. The agitation given to his mind by theſe calumnies, and the fatigues he underwent in his endeavours to re-ſcqe from mifery the moſt helpleſs portion of the human race, contributed to ſhorten a iife in no common degree uſeful. He had been for ſome time afflicted with a pain in his ſtomach, for which he was prevailed upon, tho’ with great reluctance, to try the effects of air and exerciſe, by attempting a journey of 100 miles. But in London, being ſeized with a violent vomiting of blood, he was unable either to proceed or to be removed home ; and in the houſe of Sir Charles Middleton he ended his days, on the 20th of July 1789, amidſt the groans of his family, and the tears of many friends.— Thus died a man, of whom it is not too much to fay, that " the bleſſing of many that were ready to periſh came upon him for whatever be the fate of the ſlave-trade (ſee Slavery), it is certain that his writings have contributed much to meliorate the treatment of ſlaves- He left behind him a widow and three daughters : and his works, beſides thoſe to which we have al-luded, conſiſt of a volume of <hi rend="italic">Seaſermons,</hi> preached on board his majeſty’s ſhip the Prince of wales, which ſhow him to have been a maſter of true pulpit-eloquence ; and a <hi rend="italic">Treatſe on Signals,</hi> which was certainly written, and we think printed, though we know not whether it was ever publiſhed.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>