<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-15-r01-0790-08" facs="gri_33125011197759_0798.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>RAMILLIES</label>
a imall village of Brabant, in the Auſtrian Low Countries, 12 milts north of Namur, and 22 ſouth-eaſt of Bruſſels. Lat. 50. 51. Long. 4. 48. hamous tor the battle fought by the allies commanded by the duke of Marlborough and M. D’Auverquirque, againſt that of the two crowns, commanded by the Duke of Bavaria and Marſhal villeroy, the 22d of May 1706. See Britain, n <hi rend="sup">0</hi> 357.</p><p>I he troops deſtined to compoſe the army of the allies being joined at the camp of Borchloon the 20th of May, baited the 2 iſt. Ο11 the 2 2d the army marched from Borchloon in four columns, and poſted itſelf the ſame day, with the right towards the Mill of Quorem, extending with the left towards Blehen: from this camp was diſcovered the army of the two crowns, which wd⅛ encamped with the left at over-Eſpen, and the right towards the wood of Chapiaraux, Heyliſſem in their iront, and 1 ιrlemont in their rear. It was reſolved tire ſame day to march the next morning towards the plain of Meerdorp or Mierdau, to view, the poſture of the enemies, and determine what would be the moſt proper means of attacking them according to the movement they ſhould make. 1 o this end, an advanced guard of 600 horſe and all the quarter-maſters of the army were lent forward on the <hi rend="italic">2</hi> 3d at break of day.</p><p>Γhe ſame morning about four, the army marched in eight columns towards the aforeſaid plain. The advan-ced guard and the quarter-maſters arrived about eight at the height of Meerdorp or Mierdau ; ſrom whence the army of the enemy was ſeen in motion : a little after it was perceived that the enemy was marching through the plain of Mount St Andrew in four columns, of which information was given to the duke of Maιlbo-rough and M. D’Auverquirque, who immediately repaired to the ſaid height ; and by the time theſe gene-rals were arrived there, the head of the enemy’s army already appeared at the tomb of ottomont upon the cauleway, near the Mehaigne : whereupon the Duke of Marlborough and M. D’Auverquirque made the army advance with all expedition.</p><p>T he enemy, as faſt as they advanced, ranged in order of battle, with their right towards the tomb of ottomont upon the Mehaigne, extending with their left to Autr’Eglile ; having Tranquiers in front of their right, into which they had thrown ſeveral battalions of infan-try and 14 ſquadrons of dragoons, who had diſmounted their horſes to ſupport them. They had placed many ot their infantry and a confiderable part of their artillery in the village of Ramillies, which fronted the right oi their main body, as well as into the village of oſſuz, which fronted the left of their infantry, and into the village of Autr’Egliſe, quite on their left. The front between the village of Ramillies and Autr’Egliſe was covered by a imall ſtream of water, which rendered the meadows in ſome places marſhes, and alſo by ſeveral roads covered with hedges ; which difficulties prevent-ed our cavalry ot the right wing from coming to action. As faſt as the army of the allies arrived it was ranged in Order of battle ; with the left towards</p>
<pb xml:id="eb03-15-r01-0791" facs="gri_33125011197759_0799.tif"/>
<p>Bonnef, and the right towards Folz, and every thing was diſpoſed in order to attack. To this end, four battalions were detached to attack the village of Fran-quenies, and twelve battalions to attack the village of Ramillies, which were to be ſupported by the whole in-fantry.</p><p>Gur artillery began to cannonade the enemy at one ; at about two, the attack began with the poſt of Fran-quenies, where our infantry had the good fortune to drive the enemy from the hedges, where they were ad-vantageouſly poſted, and at the ſame time all the caval-ry of our left wing advanced to attack that of the enemy’s right ; ſoon aſter aſl was in action. whilſt the cavalry were engaged, the village of Ramillies was likewiſe attacked, and forced after a vigorous reſiſtance.</p><p>The battle laſted about two hours, and was pretty obſtinate; butfo ſoon as our cavalry had gained ground enough to attack the enemy in flank, they began to give way ; at the ſame time all their infantry were put in diforder, ſo that the whole retreated in great cofiſu-ſion. The cavalry of their leſt wing formed a little upon the high ground, between oſſuz and Mount St Andrew, to favour their retreat : but after the infantry and cavalry of our right wing had filed off between the bottom of the village of Ramillies and oſſuz, the whole army marched in feveral columns to attack the enemy anew ; but they gave way before we could come up with them, and retired in great confuſion, ſome towards the defile of the Abbey De La Ramée and towards Dongelberge, others towards Judogne, and others again towards Hougarde. They were purſued aſl night ſo cloſely that they were obliged to abandon all their artillery and baggage, part of which was found at Judog-ne and at Hougarde, with their cheſts of ammunition.</p><p>The enemy loſt above 30,000 men, 60 cannon, 8 mortars, ſtandards, colours, baggage, &amp;c. ; we about 3000. The reſt of the campaign was ſpent in the ſie-ges of oſtend, Menin, and Aeth. In fourteen days the Duke defeated and diſperſed the beſt appointed ar~ my the Fçench ever had, and recovered all Spaniſh Brabant, the marquifate of the holy Roman empire. The army of the enemy conſiſted of 76 battalions and 142 ſquadrons, including the king’s houſhold troops <hi rend="italic">(La</hi> <hi rend="italic">Maifon du Roi);</hi> and the army of the allies was 74 bat-talions and 123 ſquadrons. Conſidering the import-ance of the victory, the loſs of the allies was very ſmaſl, not above 1100 being killed, and 2600 wounded.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>