<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0150-02"
                facs="gri_33125011196389_0156.tif" type="entry">

                <p><label><hi rend="smallcaps">Commission of </hi>REVIEW</label>, is a commiſſion
                    ſometimes granted, in extraordinary cafes, to revile the ſentence of the court
                    of delegates, when it is appre-hended they have been lcd into a material error.
                    This commiſſion the king may grant, although the ſtatutes 24 and 25 Hen. VIII.
                    declare the ſentence of the de-legates definitive : becaufe the pope, as ſupreme
                    head by the canon law, ufed to grant ſuch commiſſion of review; and ſuch
                    authority as the pope heretofore exerted is now annexed to the crown by ſtatutes
                    26 Hen. VIII, c. I. and 1 Eliz. c. I. But it is not matter of right, which the
                    subject may demand <hi rend="italic">ex debito jufiiti&lt;e ;</hi> but
                    merely a matter of favour, and which therefore is often denied.</p>              <p>               <hi rend="smallcaps">Review,</hi> is the drawing out ail or part of the army in
                    line of battle, to be viewed by the king,«or a general, that they may know the
                    condition of the troops.</p>                <p>At all reviews, the officers ſhould be properly arm-ed, ready in their exerciſe,
                    ſalute well, in good time, and with a good air ; their uniform genteel,
                    &amp;c. The men ſhould be clean and well dreſſed ; their accoutrements well
                    put on ; very well fized in their ranks ; the ſerjeants expert in their duty,
                    drummers perfect in their beatings, and the fifers play correct. The manual
                    ex-erciſe muſt be performed in good time, and with life ; and the men carry
                    their arms well ; march, wheel, and form with exactneſs. All manœuvres muſt be
                    performed with the utmoſt regularity, both in quick and flow -time. The firings
                    are generally 36 rounds; viz. by companies ; by grand diviſions ; by
                    ſubdiviſions ; ob-liquely, advancing, retreating ; by files ; in the ſquare ;
                    ſtreet firings, advancing and retreating ; and laſtly, a volley. The intention
                    of a review is, to know the condition of the troops, ſee that they are complete
                    and perform their exerciſe and evolutions well.</p>              <p>               <hi rend="smallcaps">Review</hi>is alſo applied to Literary Journals, which
                    give a periodical view of the ſtate of literature j as the Monthly Review, the
                    Critical Review, the Britiſh Critic, and Analytical Review, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
