<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0140-09" facs="gri_33125011196389_0146.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>RETICULAR BODY</label> <hi rend="italic">(corpus rcticulare),</hi> in anato-&lt;∙ my, a very fine membrane, perforated, in the manner of a net, with a multitude of foramina. It is placed im-mediately under the cuticle; and when that is ſeparated from the cutis, whether by art or accident, this adheres firmly to it, and is fcarce poſſible to be parted from it, ſeeming rather to bc its inner fuperficies than a diſtinct ſubſtance. In regard to this, we are to obſerve, firſt, the places in which it is found, being all thoſe in which the ſenſe of feeling is moſt acute, as in the palms of the hands, the extremities of the fingers, and on the ſoles of the feet. The tongue, however, is the part where it is moſt accurately to be obſerved : it is more eaſily diſtinguiſhable there than anywhere elſe,: and its nature and ſtructure are moſt evidently ſeen there.</p><p>Its colour in the Europeans is white ; but in the ne-groes and other black nations it is black ; in the tawny-it is yellowiſht the ſkin itſelf in both is white; and the. blackneſs and yellowneſs depend altogether on the co-lour of this membrane.</p><p>The ufes of the corpus reticulare are to preſerve the ſtructure of the other parts of the integuments, and? keep them in their determinate form and fituation. Its. apertures give paffage to the hairs and ſweat through the papillae and excretory ducts of the ſkin : it retains» theſe in a certain and determinate order, that they cannot be removed out of their places, and has ſome· ſhare in preſerving the ſoftneſs of the papille, which renders them fit for the ſenſe of feeling. See Anato--my, n <hi rend="sup">0</hi> 83.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Reticulum, is a Latin word, fιgnifying a //#/&lt;? or</hi> <hi rend="italic">cajling <hi rend="sup">net</hi> ∙</hi> It was applied by the Romans to a parti-' cular mode of conſtrncting their buildings. In the city· of Salino (ſee Sδlino) are ſtill to be ſeen remains of ſome walls, evidently of Roman origin from the <hi rend="italic">reticulum.</hi> This ſtructure confiſts of ſmall pieces of baked earth cut lozengewiſe, and difpoſed with great regularity on the angles, ſo as to exhibit to the eye the appearance of cut diamonds ; and was called <hi rend="italic">reticular,</hi> ſrom its reſem-blance to fiſhing-nets. The Romans always concealed it under a regular coating of other matter ; and Mr Houel informs us, that this was the only ſpecimen of it which he ſaw in all his travels through Sicily, Malta,, and Lipari. It appears to be the remains of fome baths,</p>
<pb xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0141" facs="gri_33125011196389_0147.tif"/>
<p>which <hi rend="sup">-</hi> have been built for the convenience of fea-bath- <hi rend="sup">in</hi> g∙</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>