<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0079-02"
                facs="gri_33125011196389_0085.tif" type="entry">

                <p><label>REMPHAN</label> an idol or Pagan god whom St Stephen ſays the Iſraelites
                    worſhipped in the wilderneſs as they paſſed from Egypt to the land of Promiſe :
                    “Yea, ye took up the tabernacle of Moloch, and the ſtar of your god Remphan ;
                    figures which ye made to worſhip them.” That the martyr here quotes the
                    foIlowing words of the prophet Amos, all commentators are a-greed : " Ye have
                    borne the tabernacle of your Moloch, and Chiun your images, the ſtar of your
                    god, which ye made to yourfelves.” But if this coincidence be-tween the
                    Chriſtian preacher and the Jewiſh prophet be admitted, it follows, that <hi
                        rend="italic"> Chiun</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Remphan</hi> are two
                    names of one and the fame deity. This is indeed farther evident from the LXX
                    tranſlators having ſub-ſtituted in their verſion the word ι <hi rend="sup">,</hi> α&lt;i&gt;α&gt;' <hi rend="sub">j</hi> inſtead of <hi
                        rend="italic"> Chiun,</hi> which we read in the Hebrew and Engliſh Bibles.
                    But the queſtion which ſtill remains to be anſwered is, what god was worſhipped
                    by the name of <hi rend="italic">Remphan, Raiphan,</hi> cr <hi rend="italic">Chiun ?</hi> for about the other divi-nity here mentioned there is no
                    difputc. See Moloch.</p>
                <p>That <hi rend="italic">Chiun</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Remphan</hi> was an
                    Egyptian divinity, cannot be queſtioned ; for at the era of the <hi
                        rend="italic"> Exodus</hi> the Hebrews muſt have been ſtrangers to the
                    idolatrous worſhip of all other nations ; nor are they ever accuſed of any other
                    than Egyptian idolatries during their 40 years wanderings in the wilderneſs,
                    till towards the end of that period that they became infected by the Moa-bites
                    with the worſhip of <hi rend="italic">Baal-peor.</hi> That <hi rend="italic">Moloch, Mo-leck, Melek,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Milcom,</hi> in its
                    original acceptation denotes a <hi rend="italic">king</hi> or <hi
                        rend="italic"> chief,</hi> is known to every oriental ſcholar ; and
                    therefore when it is uſed as the name of a god, it undoubtedly ſignifies the <hi
                        rend="italic"> fun,</hi> and is the fame divinity with the <hi
                        rend="italic"> Egyptian Oβris.</hi> Reaſoning in this way many critics, and
                    we believe Selden is in the number, have concluded that <hi rend="italic">Chiun,</hi> and of courſe <hi rend="italic">Remphan,</hi> is the planet <hi rend="italic">Saturn ;</hi> becauſe <hi rend="italic">Chiun</hi> is
                    written <hi rend="italic">Ciun, Cevaη, Ceuan, Chevvin ;</hi> all of which are
                    modern oriental names of that planet.</p>
                <p>But againſt this hypotheſis inſurmountable objections preſent themſelves to our
                    minds. It is univerſally allowed (ſee Polytheism), that the firſt objects of
                    idolatrous worſhip were theÿh» and <hi rend="italic">moon,</hi> conſidered</p>
                <p>as the king and queen of heaven. The fixed ſtars, indeed, and the planets, were
                    afterwards gradually admit -ted into the Pagan rubric ; but we may be ſure that
                    thoſe would be firſt aſſociated with the two prime luminaries which moſt
                    refembled them in brightneſs, and were ſuppoſed to be moſt benignant to man. But
                    the planet Saturn appears to the naked eye with ſo feeble a luſtre, that, in the
                    infancy of aſtronomy, it could not make ſuch an impreffidn on the mind as to
                    excite that admiration which we muſt conceive to have always preceded planetary
                    worſhip. It is to be ob-ſerved, too, that by the Pagan writers of antiquity
                    Saturn is conſtantly repreſented as a ſtar of baleful influence. He is termed
                    the <hi rend="italic">leaden planet ;</hi> the <hi rend="italic">planet of</hi> <hi rend="italic">malevolent afpect <hi rend="sub">i</hi></hi> the <hi rend="italic">difmal,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">inhumaneβar.</hi> That the Egyptians, at ſo early a period as that under conſi-deration,
                    ſhould have adored as one of their greateſt gods a planet obfcure in its
                    appearance, diſtant in its ſituation, and baleful in its influence, is wholly
                    incredible.</p>
                <p>There is, however, another ſtar which they might naturally adore, and which we
                    know they actually did adore, as one of their moſt beneficent gods, at a very
                    early period. This is the ασ7fαxvω∕ <hi rend="sub">or</hi> <hi rend="italic">σnςu&gt;ς</hi> <hi rend="sub">0</hi> f the Greeks, the <hi rend="italic">earns</hi> or <hi
                        rend="italic"> βella canicularis</hi> of the Romans, and the <hi
                        rend="italic"> dog-βar</hi> of modern Eurbpe. By the Egyptians it was
                    called <hi rend="italic">Sothis</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Soth,</hi> which
                    ſignifies y⅛∕i√y, <hi rend="italic">beηeβeηce, fecundity ;</hi> and it
                    received this name, becauſe making its appearance ip the heavens at the very
                    time when the Nile overflowed the country, it was ſuppoſed to regulate the
                    inundation. Οη this account Plutarch <hi rend="italic">(If. et Oβr.}</hi> tells us, they believed the foul of their illuſtrious benefactreſs <hi
                        rend="italic"> Ifis</hi> to have tranſmigrated into the
                    ftar0'o∕Z&gt;zj,∙ which they therefore worſhipped as the divinity which
                    rendered their country fruitful. It made its appearance, too, on the firſt day
                    of the month <hi rend="italic">Thοth</hi><note anchored="true" place="margin"
                        type="authorial" n="1">This was the caſe at a very remote period ; but- it
                        is otherwiſe at preſent, owing to the <hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps"> Precession</hi></hi> <hi rend="italic">of the Equinoxes.</hi> See that article. </note>, which·
                    was the beginning of the Egyptian year, and as ſuch celebrated with feaſting and
                    feſtivity ; and being by much the brighteſt ſtar in the heavens, Horopollo <hi
                        rend="italic"> (cap.</hi> 3.) informs us it was conſidered as ſovereign
                    over the reſt. A combination of fo many import-ant circumſtances might have
                    induced a people leſs ſuperſtitious than the Egyptians to pay divine homage to
                    that glorious luminary, which was confounded with <hi rend="italic">Iβs,</hi> who had been long regarded with the higheſt ve-neration ; and as Iſis was the
                    wife and lifter of oſiris, and always aſſociated with him, the ſtar of Iſis or <hi rend="italic">Remphan</hi> was naturally aſſociated with <hi
                        rend="italic"> Moloch,</hi> the fame with· oſiris.</p>
                <p>But it will be aſked, how the ſtar which by the E-gyptians was called <hi
                        rend="italic"> Soth</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Sothis</hi> came to be
                    woiſhip-ped by the Hebrews under the appellation of <hi rend="italic">Chiun</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Remphan ?</hi> This is a very pertinent queſtion,
                    and we ^ ſhall endeavour to anſwer it.</p>
                <p>Every one knows that the pronunciation of oriental, words is very uncertain ;
                    and that as the vowels were often omitted in writing, it is of very little
                    importance to the meaning how they be ſupplied, provided we re-tain the radical
                    conſonants. The word <hi rend="italic">Chiun</hi> may with equal propriety be
                    written <hi rend="italic">Kiun, Kion,</hi> or even <hi rend="italic">Kyoη,</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">(a)</hi> This was the caſe at a very remote period ; but-
                    it is otherwiſe at preſent, owing to the <hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps"> Precession</hi></hi> <hi rend="italic">of the Equinoxes.</hi> See that article.</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0080" facs="gri_33125011196389_0086.tif"/>
                <p>the Hebrew <hi rend="italic">jod</hi> being convertible into the Greek υ or
                    the Roman <hi rend="italic">y;</hi> but the words <hi rend="italic">Cane,
                        Chan, Kan,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Khan,</hi> which are often
                    diverſiſied into <hi rend="italic">hen, Kyn, Cohen, Cahan,</hi> .ſignifying <hi rend="italic">Head, Chief, Prince, King,</hi> &amp;c. are diffuſed
                    through a great part of Aſia and Europe, lu the Chineſe language <hi
                        rend="italic"> Sfgirι,</hi> which ſigniſies a <hi rend="italic">King,</hi> is ſo ſi-milar to the word <hi rend="italic">Chiun</hi> or <hi
                        rend="italic"> Khiun</hi> under'conſideration, that no etymologiſt will
                    hefitate&lt; to pronounce them of the ſame original and the ſame import. I
                    he word <hi rend="italic">Kan</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Khan</hi> is
                    univerſally known to be an honorary ■title in Tartary ; and <hi rend="italic">Kaian</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Kain,</hi> which is manifeſtly cognate of
                    the word <hi rend="italic">Chiun</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Kiun,</hi> is, in
                    the <hi rend="italic">Pihevi</hi> or old Peiſian language, the epithet applied
                    to the dy-naſty of princes which fucceeded Cyrus the Great. Among the Scythians
                    or ancient Tartars, <hi rend="italic">Ghiun</hi> ſigniſies the <hi
                        rend="italic"> Sun</hi> and likewiſe the <hi rend="italic">day ;</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Kung, Kinung, Kun,</hi> runs through all the -dialects
                    of the Gothic .tongue, every where denoting a <hi rend="italic">chief</hi> or <hi rend="italic">fovereign.</hi> In .the Syrian dialect, <hi
                        rend="italic"> Kon</hi> ſignifies a prince ; and hence the Almighty is
                    ſtyled (Gen. xiv. 19.) <hi rend="italic">Konah,</hi> which is tranſlated <hi
                        rend="italic"> poffeffor,</hi> but might have, &gt;with perhaps more
                    propriety, been rendered <hi rend="italic">Sovereign</hi> of heaven and earth.
                    In Hebrew, the word <hi rend="italic">Kahan</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Kahen,</hi> which λs the very fame with <hi rend="italic">Khan</hi> or <hi
                        rend="italic"> Kan,</hi> ſignifies either a <hi rend="italic">prieft</hi> or a <hi rend="italic">prince ;</hi> and in Egypt <hi rend="italic">Kon</hi> -was the name of the firſt Hercules or the <hi rend="italic">fun.</hi> Hence
                    the fame word in compofition denotes greatnefs, as <hi rend="italic">Can-obus</hi> the great .ſerpent ; <hi rend="italic">Can-athoth,</hi> the .great <hi
                        rend="italic"> Tkoth</hi> or Mercury; <hi rend="italic">Can-pfiris,</hi> the great <hi rend="italic">Oftris.</hi></p>
                <p>From tills deduction ∙ we would conclude, that the word, which is found in fo
                    many tongues, and always .denotes <hi rend="italic">Chief, Prince, Sovereign,</hi> is the very word <hi rend="italic">Chiun</hi> which the Egyptians and
                    Hebrews applied to <hi rend="italic">Sothis,</hi> as Being, in their
                    conceptions, the chief or fovereign of aſl the ſtars. This will appear ſtill
                    more probable, when Λve have afcertained the import of the word <hi
                        rend="italic"> Remphan,</hi> •or, as the LXX have it, <hi rend="italic">Raiphan.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Phan,</hi> the latter part of this word, is unqueſtionably
                    the ſame with <hi rend="italic">Pan,</hi> the moſt ancient of the Egyptian
                    gods (fee Pan). It is likewiſe a cognate of the Hebrew <hi rend="italic">Phanah,</hi> conſpexit, ſpectavit, vidit ; and the radical word ſeems to be
                    ph ah, which fignifies ſome-times the countenance, and ſometimes <hi
                        rend="italic"> tight.</hi> Hence <hi rend="italic">Phaethon,</hi> which
                    is compounded of <hi rend="italic">ph a</hi> light, <hi rend="italic">eth</hi> or <hi rend="italic">eft:</hi> fire, and <hi rend="italic">on</hi> ſtrength, came to be one of the names of the fun. <hi rend="italic">Rai,</hi> which we commonly write <hi rend="italic">Rajah,</hi> has long .dignified,
                    among the Indians, a ſiſhordinate prince ; and we know, that between India and
                    Egypt there was a very early intercourfe. <hi rend="italic">Raiphan,</hi> therefore, may be either the <hi rend="italic">royal tight</hi> or the <hi
                        rend="italic"> bright prince,</hi> ſubordinate to . Oſiris ; and in either
                    ſenſe, it was a very proper epithet of <hi rend="italic">Sothis</hi> in the
                    Egyptian kalendar. The w <hi rend="sup">r</hi> ord <hi rend="italic">Rem</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Rom,</hi> again (for it is fometimes written
                    Remphan, and ſometimes Rompha), is no other than the Hebrew an <hi rend="italic"
                        > Rum</hi> “ high, exalted.” Hence Remphan is the <hi rend="italic">high</hi> or <hi rend="italic">exalted tight,</hi> which Sothis certainly was.</p>
                <p>For this etymological diſquiſition we are indebted to Dr Doig, the learned
                    author of <hi rend="italic">Letters on the Savage State,</hi> who has written
                    a differtation on <hi rend="italic">Chiun</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Remphan,</hi> of ſuch value that we hope it will not be much longer with-held from the
                    public. The afcertaining the identity of thoſe names, and the god to which they
                    belonged, is the leaft of its merit; for it will be found to throw much light
                    upon many paffages in the üld Teſtament. what confirms his interpretation is,
                    that the</p>
                <p>idol conſecrated by the Egyptians to <hi rend="italic">Sothis</hi> or the
                    dog-ſtar, was a female figure with a ſtar on her head; and hence the prophet
                    upbraids his - countrymen with having borne the <hi rend="italic">Star</hi> of
                    their deity.</p>
               
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
