<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0143-05" facs="gri_33125011196389_0149.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>REVELATION</label>
the act of revealing, or making a thing public that was before unknown ; it is alſo uſtd for the diſcoveries made by God to his prophets, and by them to the world ; and more particularly for the books of the Qld and New Teſtament. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Bible <hi rend="sub">;</hi></hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Chrtstianitv, Miracle, Religion,</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Theolo-</hi></p><p>GY.</p><p>The principal teſts of the truth of any revelation, are the tendency of its practical doctrines ; its conliſten-cy with itſelf, and with the known attributes of God ; and ſome fatisfactory evidence that it cannot have been derived from a human ſouree.</p><p>Before any man can receive a written book as a re-velation from God, he muſt be convinced that God ex-iſts, and that he is poffeffed oſ almighty power, infinite wildom, and perfect jnſtice Now ſhould a book teaching abſurd or immoral doctrines (as many chapters of the Koran do, and as all the traditionary fyſtems of Paganiſm did), pretend to be revealed by a God of wiſdom and juſtice, we may ſafely reject its pretenfions without farther examination than what is neceffary to ſatisfy us that we have not mifunderſtood its doctrine. Should a book claiming this high origin, enjoin in one part oſ it, and forbid in another, the ſame thing to be done under the ſame circumſtances, we may reject it with contempt and indignation ; becauſe a being of infinite wiſdom can never act capriciouſly or abſurdlv. Still, however, as it is impoſſible for us to know how far the powers of men may reach in the inveſtigation or diſcovery of uſeful truth, ſome farther evidence is neceſ-ſary to prove a doctrine of divine origin, than its mere confiſtency with itſelf', and with the principles of morality ; and this evidence can be nothing but the power of working miracles exhibited by him by whom it was originally revealed. Tn every revelation confirmed by this evidence, many doctrines are to be looked for which human reaſon cannot fully comprehend ; and theſe are to be believed on the teſtimony oſ God, and ſuffered to produce their practical conſequences. At this kind of belief the ſhallow infidel may ſmile con-temptuouſiy ; but it has place in arts and ſciences as</p><p>well as in religion, whoever avails himfelf of the demon-ſtrations of Newton, Bernoulli, and others, refpectinœ the refiſtance of fluids, and applies their conclu lions to the art of flιip-h&gt;uilding, is as implicit a believer, if he underſtand not the principles of fluxions, as any Chri-ſtian ; and yet no man will fay that his faith is not pro-ductive of important practical confequences. He believes, however, in man, while the Chriſtian believes in God ; and therefore he cannot pretend that his faith reſts on a ſurer foundation.</p><p>Mr Locke, in laying down the diſtinct provinces of reaſon and faith, obſerves, 1. That the fame truths may be diſcovered by revelation which are discoverable to us by reaſon. 2. That no revelation can bc admitted againſt the clear evidence of reafon. 3. That there are many things of which we have but imper-fect notions, or none at all ; and ethers, of whoſe paſt, prefent, or future exiſtence, by the natural uſe of our faculties we cannot have the leaſt knowledge: and theſe, being beyond the diſcovery of our faculties, and above reafon, when revealed, become the proper object of our faith. He then adds, that our reafon is not injured or diſturbed, but aſſiſted and improved, by new diſcoveries of truth coming from the fountain of knowledge, whatever Gβd has revealed is certainly true ; but whether it be a divine re velation. or not, rea-fon muſt judge, which can never permit the mind to reject a greater evidence to embrace what is leſs evi-</p>
<pb xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0144" facs="gri_33125011196389_0150.tif"/>
<p>dent. There can be no evidence that any traditional revelation is of divine original, in the words we receive it, and the fenſe we underſtand it, ſo clear and ſo certain as that of the principles of reaſon: and, there-fore, nothing that is contrary to the clear and fclf-evident dictates of reafon, has a right to be urged or affented to as a matter of faith, wherein reafon has 'nothing to do.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Revelation</hi> <hi rend="italic">oſ St John.</hi> See Apocalypse.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>