<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0059-03" facs="gri_33125011196389_0065.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>RELIEVO</label>
or Relief, in ſculpture, &amp;c. is the projecture or ſtanding out of a figure which ariſes prominent from the ground or plane on which it is formed; whether that figure be cut with the chiſſel, moulded, or caſt.</p><p>There are three kinds or degrees of relievo, viz. alto, baſſo, and demi-relievo. The alto-relievo, called alſo <hi rend="italic">haut-relief,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">high-relievo,</hi> is when the figure is formed after nature, and projects as much as the life. Baſſo-relievo, baſs-relief, or low-relievo, is when the work is raiſed a little from the ground, as in medals, and the frontiſpieces of buildings ; and particularly in. the hiſto-</p>
<pb xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0060" facs="gri_33125011196389_0066.tif"/>
<p>ries, feſtorw. foliages, and other ornaments oſ friezes, Demi·relievo"is when one half of the figure riſes from the plane, when, in a baſſo-rehevo, there are parts that ſtand clear out, detached ſrom the reſt, the work is called a <hi rend="italic">demid&gt;∏Jfo,</hi></p><p>In architecture, the relievo or projecture of the orna-ments ought always to be proportioned to the magnitude of the building it adorns, and to the diſtance at which 'it is to be viewed.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Relievo, or</hi> <hi rend="italic">Relief,</hi> in painting, is the degree of bold-nefs with which the figures ſeem, at a due diſtance, to ſtand out from the ground of the painting.</p><p>The relievo depends much upon the depth of the ſhadow, and the ſtrength of the light ; or on the height of the different colours, bordering on one another ; and particularly on the difference of the colour of the figure from that of the ground : thus, when the light is fo diſpoſed as to make the neareſt paιts of the figure advance, and is well diffuſed on the maiſes, yet infenſibly diminiſhing, and terminating in a large ſpacious ſhadow, brought off inſenſibly, tbe relievo is ſaid to be bold, and the clair obſcure well under-ſtood.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>