<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0014-03" facs="gri_33125011196389_0020.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>RATIO</label>, 
    in arithmetic and geometry, is that relation of homogeneous things which determines the , quantity of one from the quantity of another, without the intervention of a third.</p><p>Two numbers, lines, or quantities, A and B, being propoſed, their relation one to another may be conſidered under one of tbeſe two heads : 1. How much A ex-ceeds B, or B exceeds A ? And this is found by taking A from B, or B from A, and is called <hi rend="italic">arithmetic rea-f,, <hi rend="sub">n</hi> ,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">ratio.</hi> 2. Ογ how many times, and parts of a time, A contains B, or B contains A ? And this is called <hi rend="italic">geometric reaſon</hi> or <hi rend="italic">ratio</hi> ; (or, as Euclid defines it, it is the <hi rend="italic">mutual habitude,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">reſpect,</hi> of two magnitudes of the ſame kind, according to quantity ; that is, as to how often the one contains, or is contained in, the other) ; and is found by dividing A by B, or B by A. And here note, that that quantity which is referred to another quantity is called the <hi rend="italic">antecedent of tho ratio ;</hi> and that to which the other is referred is called the <hi rend="italic">con</hi> <hi rend="italic">fie</hi> <hi rend="italic">queηt of the ratio.i</hi> as, in the ratio of A. to B, A is ’the antecedent, and B the ctnſequent. Therefore any quantity, as antecedent, divided by any quantity as a conſequent, gives the ratio of that antecedent to the conſequent.</p><p>'Γhus the ratio oſ A to B is ~, ſhut the ratio of B Jo</p><p>to A is —; and, in numbers, the ratio of 12 to 4 is A</p><p>—=3, or triple ; but the ratio of 4 to 12 is --- — -» or fubtriple.</p><p>And here note, that the quantifies thus compared</p><p>muſt be of the fame kind ; that is, ſuch as by nmltiρli-cation may be made to exceed one the other, or as theſc quantities are ſaid to have a ratio between them, which, being multiplied, may be made to exceed one another. Thus a line, how ſhoit foever, may be multiplied, that is, produced fo long as to exceed any given right line ; and conſequently theſe may be compared together, and the ratio expreſſed : but as a line can never, by any multiplication whatever, be made to have ſhreadth, that is, to be made equal to a fuperficies, how ſmall foever ; theſe can therefore never be compared together, and conſequently have no ratio or reſpect one to another, according to quantity ; that is, as to how often the one contains, or is contained in, the other. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Quantity.</hi></p> 
</div></body></text></TEI>