<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0015-09" facs="gri_33125011196389_0021.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>RAVENNA</label>
(anc. geog.), a noble city of Gallia Ciſ-padana; a colony of Theſſalians, on the Adriatic, in waft-es or a boggy ſituation, which proved a natural ſecurity to it. The houſes were all of wood, the communication by bridges and boats, and the town kept fweet and clean by the tides carrying away the mud and foil, (Strabo). Anciently it had a port at the mouth of the Bedeſis ; Auguſtus added a new port, capacious to hold a fleet, for the ſecurity of the Adriatic, between which and the city lay the via Cæfaris. In the lower age it was the ſeat of the oſtrogoths for 72 years ; but being recovered by Narſes, Juſtinian’s general, it became <hi rend="sub">i</hi> the reſidence of the exarchs, magiſtrates ſent by the emperor from Conſtantinople, for 175 years, when it was taken by the Longobards. It is ſtill called <hi rend="italic">Ravenna,</hi> capital of Romania. The ſeat of the weſtern or Roman Empire was by Honorius tranſlated to Ravenna about the year 404, and hence the country in which it ſtood was called <hi rend="italic">Romania,</hi> in the pope’s territory. It had a very flouriſhing trade till the ſea withdrew two miles from it, which has been a great detriment. The fortifica-tions are of little importance, and the citadel is gone to ruin. It is now moſt remarkable for the excellent wine produced in its neighbourhood. The mauſoleum of Theodoric is ſtill to be ſeen, remarkable for being covered by a ſingle ſtone 28 feet in diameter and 15 thick. It was at Ravenna that the duke of Nemours fell, after having gained a moſt decifive victory over thee, confederate army, in 1511. See France, n" 129, and Modern Univerſal Hiſtory, vol. xx. p. 324. &amp;c.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>