<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0204-01" facs="gri_33125011196389_0210.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>RHAMPHASTOS</label>
in ornithology, a genus be-longing to the order of picae. The bill is very large, and ſerrated outwardly. The noſtrils are ſituated behind the baſe of the beak ; and in moſt of the ſpecies the feet aie toed, and placed two forwards and two backwards. The tongue is long, narrow, and feathered on the edges. Mr Latham enumerates 15 diſſcrent ſpecies ; of which the toucans are the moſt remarkable, and were formerly divided into four or ſive varieties, though Mr Latham makes them diſtinct fpecies, of which we ſhali only defcribe that called the red-beaked toucan.</p><p>This bird is about the ſize of a jackdaw, and of a ſimilar ſhape, with a large head to ſupport its monſtrous bill : this bill, from the angles of the mouth to its point, is ſix inches and an half ; and its breadth in the thickeſt part is a little more than two. Its thickneſs near the head is one inch and a quarter ; and it is a little rounded along the top of the upper chap, the under ſide. being round alſo ; the whole of the bill extremely flight, and a little thicker tlian parchment. The upper chap is of a bright yellow, except on each ſide, which is of a fine ſearlet colour ; as is alfo the lower chap, except at the baſe, which is purple. Between the head and the bill there is a black liRe of ſeparation all round the baſe of the bill ; in the upper part of which the noſtrils are placed, and are almoſt covered with feathers ; which has occaſioned ſome writers to ſay that the toucan has no noſtrils. Round the eyes, on each ſide of the head, is a ſpace of bluiſh ſkin, void of feathers ; above which the head is black, except a white ſpot on each ſide joining to the baſe of the, upper chap. The hinder part of the neck, the back, wings, tail, belly, and thighs, are black. The under ſide of the head, throat, and the beginning of the breaſt, are white. Between the white on the breaſt, and the black on the belly, is a ſpace of red feathers, in the form of a new moon, with its horns upwards. The legs, ſeet, and claws, are of an aſh-colour ; and the toes ſtand like thoſe of parrots, two before and two behind.</p><p>It is reported by travellers, that this bird, though ſurniſhed with fo formidable a beak, is harmleſs and. gentle, being ſo eaſily made tame as to ſit and hatch its young in houſes. It ſeeds chiefly upon pepper, which it devours very greedily, gorging itſelf in ſuch a manner that it voids it crude and unconcocted. T'his, however, is no objection to the natives from uſing it again : they even prefer it before that pepper which is freſh gathered from the tree ; and ſeem perſuaded that the ſtiength and heat of the pepper is qualified by the bird, and that all its noxious qualities are thus ex-hauſted.</p><p>whatever be the truth of this report, nothing is more certain than that the toucan lives only upon a vegetable diet ; and, in a domeſtic ſtate, to which it is frequently brought in the warm countries where it is bred, it is ſeen to prefer ſuch food to all other. Pozzo, who bred one tame, afferts, that it leaped up and down, wagged the tail, and cried with a voice reſembling that of a magpie. It fed upon the fame things that parrots do; but was moſt greedy of grapes, which, being plucked off one by one, and thrown in the air, it would moſt dexterouſly catch before they ſell to the ground. Its bill, he adds, was hollow, and upon that account very light, ſo that it had but little ſtrength in fo apparently formidable a weapon ; nor could it peck or ſtrike ſmartly therewith. But its tongue ſeemed to affiſt the efforts of this unwieldy machine : it was long, thin, and flat, not unlike one of the feathers on the neck of a dunghill cock ; this it moved up and down, and often extended ſive or ſix inches from the bill. It was of a fleſh colour, and remarkably fringed on each ſide with very fmall ſilaments.. exactly reſembling a feather.</p><p>It is probable that tliis long tongue has greater ſtrength than the thin hollow beak that contains it. It is likely that the beak is only a kind of ſheath ſor this peculiar inſtrument, uſed by the toucan, not only in making itſelf a neſt, but alfo in obtaining its pro-viſion. Nothing is more certain, than that this bird builds its ueſt in holes of trees, which have been pre-</p>
<pb xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0205" facs="gri_33125011196389_0211.tif"/>
<p>viouily ſcooped out for this purpofe; and it is not.very likely that <hi rend="italic">ſo</hi> feeble a bill could be very ſcrviceable in working upon ſuch hard materials.</p><p>Be this as it will, there is no bird ſecures its young better from external injury than the toucan, it has not only birds, men, and ſerpents, to guard againſt ; but a numerous tribe of monkeys, ſtill more prying, miſchievous, and hungry, than all the reſt. The toucan, however, ſceops out its neſt into the hollow of ſome tree, leaving only a hole large enough to go in and out at. There it ſits, with its great beak, guarding the entrance ; and if the monkey ventures to offer a viſit of curioſity, the toucan gives him ſueh a wel-come, that he preſently thinks proper to pack off, and is glad to eſcape with ſafety.</p><p>This bird is only found in the warm climates of South America, where it is in great requeft, both for the de-licacy of its fleſh, which is tender and nouriſhing, and for the beauty of its plumage, particularly the fea-thers of the breaſt. The ſkin of this part the Indians pluck off, and when dry glue to their cheeks ; and this they conſider as an irreſiſtible addition to their beauty.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>