<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-15-r01-0773-04"
                facs="gri_33125011197759_0781.tif" type="entry">

                <p><label>RACINE</label> (John), of the. French academy, trea-ſurer of France in the
                    generality of Moulins, and fecretary to his majeſty, was born at Ferre-Milon in
                    1639. He had a fine genius for the <hi rend="italic">Belles Lettres,</hi> and
                    became one of the firſt poets of the age. He produced his <hi rend="italic"
                        >Thebαide</hi> when but very young ; and afterwards other pieces, which met
                    with great ſucceſs, though they appeared when Corneille was in his higheſt
                    reputation. In his career, however, he did not fail to meet with all that
                    oppoſition which envy and cabal are ever ready to ſet up againſt a ſuperior
                    genius. It was partly owing to a chagrin from this circumſtance that he took a
                    refolution to quit the theatre for ever ; although his genius was ſtill in full
                    vigour, being not more than 38 years of age. But he had alſo imbibed in his
                    in-fancy a deep ſenſe of religion ; and this, though it had been ſmothered for a
                    while by his connections with the theatre, and particularly with the famous
                    actreſs Champ-melle, whom he greatly loved, and by whom he had a ſon, now at
                    length broke out, and bore down all before it. In the ſirſt place, he reſolved
                    not only to write no more plays, but to do a rigorous penance for thoſe he had
                    written ; and he actually formed a deſign of be-coming a Carthuſian friar. His
                    religious director, however, a good deal wiſer than he, adviſed him to
                    think-more moderately, and to take meaſures more fuita⅛Ie to his character. He
                    put him upon marrying, and-ſettling in the world : with which propoſal this
                    humble and tractable penitent complied ; and immediately took to wife the
                    daughter of a treaſurer of France for Amiens, by whom he had ſeven children.</p>
                <p>He had been admitted a member of the French academy in 1673, * <hi rend="sup"
                        >n</hi> the <hi rend="sup">room θ</hi> f La Mothe le vayer deceaſed ; but
                    ſpoiled the ſpeech he had made upon that occaſion by pronouncing it with too
                    much timidity. In 1677, he was nominated with Boileau, with whom he was ever in
                    ſtrict friendſhip, to write the hiſtory of Louis XIV. ; and the public expected
                    great things from two writers of their diſtinction, but were difappointed.
                    Boileau and Racine, after having for ſome time laboured at this work, perceived
                    that it was en* tirely oppoſite to their genius.</p>
                <p>He ſpent the latter years of his life in compoſing a hiſtory of the houſe of
                    Port-Royal, the place of his education ; which, however, though finely drawn up,
                    as many have aſſerted, has not bcen publiſhed. Too great ſenfibility, ſay his
                    friends, but more properly an impotence of ſpirit, ſhortened the days of this
                    poet.—-Though he had converſed much with the court, he had not learned the
                    wiſdom, which is uſually learned there, cf diſguifing his real fentiments.
                    Having drawn up a well-reafoned and well-written memorial upon the mife-ries of
                    the people, and the means of relieving them, he one day lent it to Madam de
                    Maintenon to read ; when the king coming in, and demanding what and whoſe it
                    was, commended the zeal of Racine, but diſapproved of his meddling with things
                    that did not . concern him : and faid with an angry tone, " Becauſe he knows how
                    to make .good verſes, does he think he knows every thing? And would he be a
                    miniſter of ſtate, becauſe he is a great poct ?” Theſe words hurt Racine greatly
                    : he conceived dreadful ideas of the king’s diſpleaſure ; and his chagrin and
                    fears brought on a fever, of which he died the 2 2d of April 1699.</p>
                <p>the king, who was ſenſible of his great merit, and always loved him, ſent often
                    to him in his illneſs ; and finding after his death that he had more glory than
                    riches, ſettled a handſome penſion upon his family.— There is nothing in the
                    French language written with . more wit and elegance than his pieces in proſe.
                    Be-ſides his plays, ſeveral of his letters have been publiſhed-; he alſo wrote
                    ſpiritual ſongs, epigrams, &amp;c. Racine’s</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-15-r01-0774" facs="gri_33125011197759_0782.tif"/>
                <p>works were printed at Amſterdam in <hi rend="italic">17ii <hi rend="sub"
                        >i</hi></hi> in J vol§ 12 mo, and the next year a pompous edition was
                    printed in 2 vols quarto,</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
