<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0009-04" facs="gri_33125011196389_0015.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>RAPHIDIA</label>
    in zoology ; a genus of insects, of the neuroptera order ; the characters of which are theſe; The head is of a horny ſubſtance, and depreſſed or flattened : the mouth is armed with two teeth, and furniſhed with four palpi : the ſtemmata are three in number : the wings are deflected : the antennæ are filiform, as long as the thorax ; the anterior part of which is lengthened out, and of a cylindrical form : the tail of the female is terminated by an appendix, reſembling a flexible crooked briſtle.—There are three ſpecies. The moſt remarkable is the ophiopſis ; which for its ſhape is one of the moſt ſingular that can be ſeen <note anchored="true" place="margin" type="authorial" n="1">Plate <hi rend="smallcaps">cccxxxv.</hi></note>. It has an oblong Lead, ſhaped like a heart,</p><p>with its point joined to the thorax, and the broad part before. It is ſmooth, black, flattened, continually ſhakmg, with ſhort antennæ, yellowiſh maxilîæ, and tour palpi. Towards the middle of the upper part of the head, between the eyes, are the three ſtemmata, placed in a triangle. The thorax, to which this head is rahened, is narrow, long, and cylindrical. The ab-domen, broader, is black like the reſt of the body, with the ſcgments margined yellow. The feet are of a yellowiſh caſt. The wings, which are faſtigiated, are white, diaphanous, veined, and as it were covered with a very fine net-work of black. This inſect, in the figure of its head, reſembles a ſnake. It is found but ſeldom, and in woods only. Its larva, chryſalis, and habitation, are abſolutely unknown.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>