<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0126-06"
                facs="gri_33125011196389_0132.tif" type="entry">

                <p><label>RESURRECTION</label> in theology, is a rising again ſrom the state of the
                    dead and is that event, the belief of which conſtitutee one of the principal
                    articles in the Christian creed.</p>
                <p>In treating of this object of our faith, it has been uſual to mention, ſirſt,
                    the reſurrection of our Blessed Lord, with the character of the witneffes, and
                    the authenticity of the goſpel hiſtory by which it has been proved, and from
                    which, as a conſequence, ours is inferred. But as moſt of the arguments for his
                    reſurrection are contained in the goſpels, and as merely to re-peat them would
                    afford, we hope, but little information to moſt of our readers, we mean here to
                    take a view of the ſeveral grounds on which the belief of a future exiſtence is
                    ſuppoſed to be founded ; to collect together ſome of the ſentiments of authors
                    and nations concerning the place where departed fpirits reſide ; concerning the
                    nature of their preſent ſtate ; concerning the kinds of their future deſtination
                    ; that we may afterwards ſee how far their notions differ and agree with what we
                    conſider as the doctrines of Scripture.</p>
                <p>Of a future ſtate, there have ſometimes been found a few wandering and obſcure
                    tribes who ſeemed to enter-tain no notion at all ; though it ſhould be remarked,
                    that ſome oſ theſe were likewiſe obſerved in ſo low a degree oſ ſavage barbarity
                    as not to be acquainted with the uſe oſ the bow, the dart, or the ſling, and as
                    not knowing how to wield a club, or to throw a ſtone, as a weapon of
                        defence<note anchored="true" place="margin" type="authorial" n="1">See
                        Robertson's <hi rend="italic">Hist. of America</hi>.</note>.</p>
                <p>wherever the human mind has been cultivated, or properly ſpeaking, begun to be
                    cultivated, the opinion has likewiſe generally prevailed that human exiſtence is
                    not confined to the preſent ſcene ; nay, ſo very gene-ral has this notion been
                    found among mankind, that many are puzzled how to account for what they ſuppoſe
                    to be almoſt next to its univerſality.</p>
                <p>To explain the phenomenon, ſome have imagined that it is a notion derived by
                    tradition from primeval re-velation. They ſuppofe that the firſt parent of
                    mankind, as a moral agent accountable for his conduct, was informed by his Maker
                    of every thing which it was of importance for him to know ; that he muſt have
                    been acquainted with this doctrine of a future ſtate in parti-cular j and that
                    he could hardly fail to communicate a matter fo intereſting to his poſterity.
                    They ſuppoſ¢, too, that the hiſtory of the tranflatioa of Enoch muſt have made a
                    great noife in the world, and that the re-membrance of it muſt have been long
                    retained and widely diſſuſed ; and they find in the book of Job plain
                    intimations of a reſurrection from the dead, which, from the manner in which
                    they are introduced, they think that very ancient patriarch muſt have received
                    through this channel.</p>
                <p>It is not thought to be any objection to theſe fuppo∙ ſitions, that the Moſt
                    High, when delivering his laws from the top of Mount Sinai, did not enforce them
                    by the awful fonctions of a future ſtate. The intelligent reader of the
                    Scriptures knows that the fonctions of a future ſtate belong to a different and
                    more univerſal diſ-penſation than was that of Moſes ; that the primeval
                    revelation related to that diſpenfotion ; and that the Jewiſh law, with its
                    temporal fonctions, was introduced only to preſerve the knowledge and worſh¾p of
                    the true God among a people too groſs in their conceptions to have been properly
                    influenced by the view of future rewards and puniſhments, of fuch a nature as
                    eye hath not feen, nor ear heard, neither hath it entered into the heart of man
                    to conceive. He fees at the ſame time, everywhere ſcattered through the old
                    Teſtament, plain indications of the Moſaic economy, being no more than
                    preparatory to the bringing in of a better hope ; and he thinks it evident, that
                    ſuch Jews as underſtood any thing of the nature of that better hope, muſt have
                    been convinced, that, however the <hi rend="italic">ceremonial rites</hi> of <hi rend="italic">their</hi> religion might be ſuſſiciently guarded by
                    temporal ſanc-tions, the <hi rend="italic">fundamental principles</hi> of <hi
                        rend="italic"> all</hi> religion and virtue are ſupported by rewards and
                    puniſhments to be diſpen-ſed in a ſtate beyond the grave. See <hi
                        rend="smallcaps"> Prophecy</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Theology.</hi></p>
                <p>That the progenitors of the human race muſt have been inſpired by their Creator
                    with the knowledge of their immortality, and of every thing neceſſary to their
                    everlaſting welfare, cannot, we ſhould think, be queſ-tioned by any one who
                    believes that the world had a beginning, and that it is under the government of
                    good-neſs and juſtice. The progreſs from ſenfe to ſcience is ſo flow, that
                    however capable we may ſuppoſe the ear-lieſt inhabitants of this earth to have
                    been of making philofophical difeoveries, we cannot believe that the Father of
                    mercies left his helpleſs creature to difeover for himſelf his future exiſtence.
                    Death, when firſt preſented to him, muſt have been a ghaſtly object ; and had he
                    been left without any hope of redemption from it, he would undoubtedly have funk
                    into liſtleſsdeſpondency.</p>
                <p>But a proſpect of immortality is ſo pleafing to the human mind, that if it was
                    communicated to the firſt</p>
                <p>man, it would of courſe be cheriſhed by his poſterk ty ; and there is no
                    difficulty in conceiving how it might be handed down by tradition to very remote
                    ages, among ſuch of his defeendents as were not ſcattered over the face of the
                    earth in ſmall and ſavage tribes.—&gt; In the courfe of its progreſs, it
                    would frequently be new-modelled by the ever active imagination ; and at laſt
                    many abſurd and fantaſtic circumſtances would doubtlefs be combined with the
                    original truth, that death puts not an end to human exiſtence.</p>
                <p>But though we are firmly convinced that the flrſt principles of ufeful
                    knowledge, and among them the doctrine of a future ſtate, were communicated to
                    man</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0127" facs="gri_33125011196389_0133.tif"/>
                <p>by his Maker ; and though this doctrine, in large and permanent ſocieties, might
                    certainly be conveyed more or leſs pure to late poſterity through the channel of
                    tra-dition—we are far from attributing ſo much to tradition as fome writers are
                    difpoſed to do, or thinking it the only fource from which mankind could derive
                    the belief of their exiſtence beyond the grave. In fmall tribes of ſavages ſuch
                    a tradition could hardly be preſerved ; and yet ſome indiſtinct notions of a
                    future ſtate have been found among tribes who are ſaid to have loſt all
                    tradi-tionary notions even of the being of a God.</p>
                <p>others, therefore, are inclined to believe that, in-dependent of any traditions,
                    mankind might be led by certain phenomena to form ſome conjectures of a future <hi rend="sub">1</hi> ftate. They obſerve, that although a few individuals
                    perhaps may, yet it ſeldom happens that the whole individuals of any nation are
                    exempted from dreaming : They obſerve, too, and this obſervation is founded on
                    experience, that the images of the dead are from the remaining impreſſions of
                    memory frequently ſummoned up in the fancy ; and that it appears from all the
                    lan-guages of rude nations, who pay the greateſt attention to their dreams, and
                    who ſpeak of feeing the dead in their viſions, that theſe images<note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="2">Theſe images were
                        called by the Greeks E∙Jωλ* <hi rend="italic">Garni», </hi>; and among the
                        Romans they had various names, as <hi rend="italic">umbra, lemures, manes,
                            larvœ,</hi> and were ſometimes called <hi rend="italic">occurſacula
                            noctium, bustorum formidamina, sepulchrorum temculamenta, animœ
                            errantes,</hi> which are all comprehended under the <hi rend="italic">ſpecies mortuorum.</hi></note> have always been taken by them for
                    realities ; nay, ſome of the learned, and the celebrated Baxter is of the
                    number, are diſpo-ſed to doubt whether theſe appearances be not ſome-thing more
                    than illuſions of the brain : But whether they really be ſo or not, one thing is
                    certain, that all nations in all countries, in the darkeſt ages and the ru-deſt
                    periods, are accuſtomed to dream ; and whether ſleeping or waking, in the
                    ſtillneſs of the night, in the gloom of ſolitude, in the fondneſs of friendſhip,
                    in the rovings of love, the delirium of fever, and the anguiſh of remorfe, <hi
                        rend="sub"> l</hi> to ſee and converſe with the ſhades of the departed; and
                        Lucretius<note anchored="true" place="margin" type="authorial" n="3"><hi
                            rend="italic">Lucret.</hi> lib. 4.</note> has remarked,, that even the
                    inferior animals are not exempted from ſuch illuſions of a reſtleſs fancy.</p>
                <p>Fβr often ſleeping racers pant and fweat,</p>
                <p>Breathe ſhort, as if they ran their ſecond heat ;</p>
                <p>As if the barrier down with eager pace</p>
                <p>They ſtretch’d, as when contending for the race.</p>
                <p>And often hounds, when ſleep hath clos’d their eyes&gt;</p>
                <p>They toſs, and tumble, and attempt to riſe ;</p>
                <p>They open often, often ſnuff the air,</p>
                <p>As if they preſt the footſteps of the deer ;</p>
                <p>And ſometimes wak’d, purſue their fancy’d prey,</p>
                <p>The fancy’d deer, that ſcem to run away,</p>
                <p>Till quite awak’d, the follow’d ſhapes decay,</p>
                <p>And ſofter curs, that lie and ſleep at home,</p>
                <p>Do often rouſe, and walk about the room,</p>
                <p>And'bark, as if they ſaw ſome ſtrangers come?</p>
                <p>And birds will ſtart, and ſeek the woods, by night,} whene’er the fancy’d hawk
                    appears in fight, Ç</p>
                <p>Whene’er they ſee his wing or hear him fight. j</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Çkbech.</hi></p>
                <p>Theſe powers of fancy extend wide over animal crea</p>
                <p>tion ; and it is on this general principle that necr&lt;s-mancers and
                    dreamers have in all ages eſtabliſhed their trade, that the ſtories of goblins
                    have at all times ſo very eaſily procured belief, and that</p>
                <p>The village matron, round the blazing hearth, Suſpends the infant audience with
                    her tales, Breathing aſtoniſhment ! Qf witching rhymes And evil ſpirits ; of the
                    deathbed call of him who robb’d the widow and devour’d The orphan’s portion ; of
                    unquiet fouls Ris’n from the grave to eaſe the heavy guilt of deeds in life'
                    conceal’d ; of ſhapes that walk At dead of night, and clank their chains, and
                    wave The torch of hell around the murderer’s head.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Aikenside.</hi></p>
                <p>Mankind in general would willingly dſſpenſe with theſe troubleſome viſits of the
                    dead. To prevent the return of the <hi rend="italic">zumbi</hi> or the ghoſt,
                    fome nations of Afri-ca ufe many ſuperſtitious rites<note anchored="true"
                        place="margin" type="authorial" n="4"><hi rend="italic">Voyage to Congo and
                            Angola. Churchill's Voyages.</hi></note>; and Kolben tells us, that the
                    frighted Hottentots leave in the hut where a perſon has died all the utenſils
                    and furniture, leſt the angry ghoſt, incenſed at their avarice, ſhould haunt
                    them in their dreams, and infeſt. them in the night. Divines and moraliſts have
                    laboured to ſhow that theſe are merely imaginary terrors: but God and nature
                    ſeem to have determined that they ſhall produce the ſame effects upon certain
                    minds as if they were real y and that while there is any ſenſibility in the
                    heart, while there is any remembrance of the paſt, and any conju-ring power in
                    the fancy ; the ignorant, the benighted, the timid, ſhall often meet with the
                    goblins of darkneſs, the ſpectres of the tomb, the apparitions that hover round
                    the grave, and the forms of the dead in the midnight dream. See Spectre.</p>
                <p>From theſe phenomena, which have been fo common in all countries and in all
                    ages, what- would mankind naturally infer ? would they not infer, that there is
                    ſomething in the nature of man that ſurvives death, and that there is a future
                    ſtate of exiſtence beyond ſthc grave ? Are not ſtill many ſpecimens of this
                    reafoning preferved in the ancient poets ? and is it not thus that Achilles<note
                        anchored="true" place="margin" type="authorial" n="5"><hi rend="italic">Hom.
                            Iliad,</hi> ib. 23, l. 103.</note> reafons after imagining that he faw
                    the ghoſt of his friend Patroclus ?</p>
                <p><hi rend="sup">,</hi> Tis true, ’tis certain, man, though dead, retains</p>
                <p>Part of himſelf ; the immortal mind remains :</p>
                <p>The form ſubſiſts without the body’s aid,</p>
                <p>Aerial ſemblance, and an empty ſhade.</p>
                <p>This night my friend, ſo late in battle Ioſt,</p>
                <p>Stood at my ſide- a penfive plaintive ghoſt j</p>
                <p>Ev’n now familiar as in life he came,</p>
                <p>Alas! how diff’rent, yet how like the ſame. <hi rend="smallcaps">Pope,</hi></p>
                <p>Lucretius<note anchored="true" place="margin" type="authorial" n="6">Lib.
                        3.</note>, a ſtudious obſerver of nature, though no friend to the ſoul’s
                    immortality, acknowledges frankly that theſe phantoms often terrify the mind,
                    haunt us in our ſleep, and meet us while awake. He confeffes, too, that by ſuch
                    appearances mankind have been led</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0128" facs="gri_33125011196389_0134.tif"/>
                <p>to believe the future exiſtence of the ſoul; but, aware ot the conſequence,</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">-Ne forte animas richer unie rearnur</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Rjfogere, aut umbras inter vivos vo(ιtare,</hi></p>
                <p>he endeavours to explain theſe curious phenomena on ſorne of the odd and
                    fantaſtic principles of the Epicureans. In doing this, however, he pretends not
                    to deny that theſe images appear to be real ; but candidly .acknowledges that</p>
                <p>---They ſtrike and ſhake</p>
                <p>The airy ſoul, as when we are awake, with ſtroke fo lively, that we think we
                    view The abſent dead, and think the image true.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Creech.</hi></p>
                <p>we here ſee how the belief of the foul’s immortality came to be general among
                    mankind. But for this information we are much more indebted to the poets, who
                    have given us faithful tranſcripts of nature, than to the philoſophers who have
                    wiſhed to entertain us with their own theories, or to thoſe laborious men ot
                    erudition, who have dreaded as much to examine the ſource of an ancient report
                    as the friends of Ulyſſes to approach the coaſt of Cimmerian darknefs. with them
                    tradition is the ultimate boundary of reſearch : and as gorgons, chimeras, and
                    hydras, have come down to us by tradition ; ſo they, with great ſagacity, ſuſ
                    pect, that tradition muſt likewiſe be at the bottom of the ſoul’s immortality,
                    and occaſion the viſions and phantoms of the dead.</p>
                <p>To tradition we have allowed all that it can juſtly claim ; but we cannot allow
                    it to be the only ſource of this opinion : -and we have felt the higheſt
                    indignation upon hearing men of learning and genius affirm, from a ſalſe zeal
                    for the honour of revelation, that mankind, without this inſtruction, could
                    never have acquired the art of building huts to ſcreen them from the cold, or
                    have learned the method of propagating their ſpecies ! The reader muſt not here
                    fuppoſe that we allude to Polydore Virgil<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial" n="7">This writer allots part of a chapter to show, "Quis
                        primum inſtituerit artem meretriciam,” as being, in his opinion, a
                        traditionary practice. See Lib. iii. cap. 17. <hi rend="italic">De Rerum
                            Inventοribus.</hi></note>. We have in our eye perſons now alive, with
                    whom we have converged on the ſubject, and who (terrifiedat the length to which
                    ſome philoſophers have carried the doctrine of inſtincts, and others the
                    reaſoning powers of the mind) have contended, with the utmoſt earneſtnefs, that
                    we know nothing—not even the functions of our animal nature—but by tradition or
                    written revelation.</p>
                <p>Having now ſeen the ſource of the opinion concerning the future exiſtence of the
                    ſoul, and pointed out the natural phenomena by which mankind were led to embrace
                    it, we come next to review the arguments by which the philoſophers attempted to
                    confirm it.</p>
                <p>Pythagoras believed, with the reſt of his country, that annihilation was never
                    the end, and that nonentity was never the beginning, of any thing that is. His
                    general doctrine upon this ſubject was ſhortly expreſſed in very few words, <hi
                        rend="italic"> Omnia mutantur, nihil interit.</hi> He afterwards learned
                    from Egyptian prieſts that the foul migrates into new bodies ; and being, it
                    ſeems, a perſon of a moſt extraordinary and aſtoniſhing memory, he found there
                    was ſome truth in the ſtory: for after muſing, he began to remember that he was
                    Euphorbus, the ion, of Pan-theus, that was ſiain by Menelaus in the Trojan war ;
                    and upon a jaunt to Peloponneſus, recollected the ſhield which he had worn at
                    the time of the ſiege, in o⅛ne of the temples of Juno at Argos ! That none might
                    queſtion the truth of his aſſertion, his followers preſently removed all doubts
                    by the famous argument, the ipse dixit of Egyptian origin.</p>
                <p>As Pythagoras taught that human ſouls are frequent-ly thruſt into brute ſhapes,
                    and, as ſome imagined, by way of puniſhment; it occurred to Plato, that all
                    bodies, even the human, are a fort of priſons ; and that, in confequence of this
                    confinement, the foul was ſubjected to the rage of deſire, appetite, and
                    paffion, and to all the wretched miſeries of a jail. To explain this my-ſtery,
                    he fuppoſed that deſires and appetites belong to a foul that is purely animal
                    reſiding in the body. But he was perplexed with another difficulty ; for as he
                    thought highly of the goodnefs of Deity, he could not imagine how he ſhould
                    imprifon us without a crime. He ſuppoſed, therefore, that prior to its union
                    with the preſent body the foul had exiſted in one of ether, which it ſtill
                    retains; but that even in this etherialbody it had felt ſomething of impure
                    deſire ; and happening to indulge the vicious appetite, had contracted ſome
                    ſtains of pollution, for which it was confined in its preſent body as a houſe of
                    correction to do penance and improve its morals.</p>
                <p>To prove this ideal pre-exiſtence of the foul, Plato availed himfelf of an
                    opinion that was general in his time, that coincided with the doctrines of
                    Pythagoras, and that was partly founded on a fort of reaſoning and obfervation.
                    He thought that matter and intelligence are coeternal (see Platonism.) ; that
                    there are various orders of ſouls ; that thoſe of both the man and the brute are
                    parts or emanations<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="8"
                        >Γhe Deity was conceived by the ancients fometimes as a ſolid, when inferior
                        ſouls were called <hi rend="italic">ατοα-ττχσμχία. I. e.</hi> fragments or
                        parts broken off from him ; and ſometimes as a fluid, when they were
                        confidered as <hi rend="sub">α</hi> -ropp9iα∕ or emanations : but from
                        none of theſe hypotheſes did they reaſon conſequentially. Their <hi
                            rend="italic"> a*or*M&lt;r∕tMlΛ</hi> were often after death
                        reunited to the Deity; and their <hi rend="italic">&lt;χyppf&gt;o}χι</hi> often remained ſeparate and
                        diftiι&gt;ct for a long while, without flowing back as they ought to
                        have done, and mingling with, the great ocean oſ ſpirit.</note> of the <hi
                        rend="italic"> anima mundi,</hi> or ſoul of the world ; that all are
                    ultimately parts or emanations of Deity itſelf ; and that all their faculties
                    are more or lefs reſtricted and confined, according to thoſe organiſed ſyſtems
                    with which they are connected. Know firſt (ſays one delivering his doctrines),</p>
                <p>Know firſt, that heav’n and earth’s compacted frame,.</p>
                <p>And flowing waters, and the ſtarry flame,</p>
                <p>And both the radiant lights, one common ſoul</p>
                <p>Inſpires, and feeds, and animates, the whole.</p>

                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0129" facs="gri_33125011196389_0135.tif"/>
                <p>Th is active mind, infus’d through all the ſpace,</p>
                <p>Unites and mingles with the mighty maſs :</p>
                <p>Hence men and beaſts the breath of life obtain,</p>
                <p>And birds of air, and monſters of the main ;</p>
                <p>The ethereal vigour is in all the ſame,</p>
                <p>And every foul is fill’d with equal flame ;</p>
                <p>As much as earthy limbs, and groſs allay Ί</p>
                <p>of mortal members, ſubject to decay, &gt;</p>
                <p>Blunt not the beams of heav'ſh and edge of day<note anchored="true"
                        place="bottom" type="authorial" n="9">The general doctrine, as delivered
                        here in theſe verſes of virgil, is the ſame with that not only of
                        Pythagoras, but oſ the Stoics.</note>.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Dryden.</hi></p>
                <p>Beſides this hypotheſis, that in ſome meaſure was common to others, Plato had an
                    argument peculiarly his own. Happening to peep into the region of
                    me-t&lt;ιphyfics, he was ſomewhat ſurpriſed on obſerving the ideas which we
                    derive from reflection and conſciouſneſs; and ſuppoſing that they could not have
                    entered by the ſenſes, he naturally, though not very juſtly, concluded, that we
                    muſt have received them in ſome ſtate of prior exiſtence.</p>
                <p>As, according to him, the foul was eternal, as well as the matter which compoſed
                    the body, and as their union was only temporary and accidental, he might have
                    been ſatisfied that the death of the ſoul was not to be the conſequence of their
                    ſeparation. But, ſome how or other, ſatisfied he was not. He had recourſe to a
                    new argument. As the ſoul, he faid, was an active principle, and a ſelf-moving,
                    it did not depend for its life on another ; and therefore would always continue
                    to exiſt, though the body were reduced to the general mafs out of which it was
                    formed. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Metaphysics,</hi> Part III. chap. iv.</p>
                <p>Whether Plato had borrowed any of his doctrines from the eaſtern magi, we
                    pretend not to fay. We only observe a ſtriking limilarity, in fome reſpects,
                    between his and theirs. In Plato’s philoſophy, the ſun, moon, and ſtars, were
                    animated beings, and a fort of divinities that originally had ſprung from the
                    great fountain of Jιeat.and light, and our earthly bodies a fort of dungeons in
                    which our miferable fouls are benighted and debafed by deſires, appetites, and
                    paſſions. In the magian philoſophy, the Supreme Being was called <hi
                        rend="italic"> Oromaſdes ;</hi> was the god of light, or was light itſelf,
                    and re-preſented by Mithras, a ſubordinate divinity, and the ſame with the fun.
                    Another deity of very great power was Arimanes, the god of darkneſs, who
                    preſided over matter, and was the origin of all evil (ſee <hi rend="smallcaps">Polytheism).</hi></p>
                <p>The ancient Gnoſtics, who derived their tenets from this fource, believed, with
                    Pythagoras and Plato, in a great number of ſubordinate genii ; and ſaid, that
                    De-miurgus, the god of matter and the ſoul or ſpirit of this world, had
                    contrived the bodies of men and brutes; and in the former particularly, as in fo
                    many priſons, had confined a number of celeſtial ſpirits, that by expofing them
                    to the low deſires of appetite and paſſion, he might feduce them from their
                    allegiance to the God of light, and render them more fubmiſſive to himſelf. From
                    theſe priſons the Supreme Being was continually making attempts to reſcue them;
                    and in the mean time was frequently fending divine meffengers to en-lighten and
                    inſtruct them, and to render them capable oſ returning to the regions of light
                    and happineſs, to which they had belonged<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial" n="10"><p>Plato made the ſtars the native reſidence of
                            inferior ſouls; and when theſe were thoroughly purified below, returned
                            them home again : and therefore, ſays virgil, alluding to his doctrine,</p>
                        <p>---——— Some have taught</p>
                        <p>That bees have portions of ethereal thought,</p>
                        <p>Endu’d with particles of heav’nly fires ;</p>
                        <p>For God the whole created maſs inſpires :</p>
                        <p>Thro’ heav’n, and earth, and ocean's depth, he throws His influence
                            round, and kindles as he goes.</p>
                        <p>Hence flocks, and herds, and men, and beaſts, and ſowl¢, with breath are
                            quicken’d, and attract their ſouls :</p>
                        <p>Hence take the forms his preſcience did ordain,</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">And into him at length reſolve again.</hi></p>
                        <p>No room is leſt for death, they mount the ſky,</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">And to their own congenial planets fly.</hi> <hi rend="italic">Dryden.</hi>
                        </p></note>.</p>
                <p>The Stoics attempted to ſimplify this ſyſtem, which appears anciently to have
                    pervaded Egypt and the eaſt, and which would ſecm to be no more than variouſly
                    modified by orpheus, Pythagoras, Plato, and others of the more northerly and
                    weſtern nations. None of them allowed a creation out of nothing; and the
                    ſhapingand modelling of matter into forms was variouſiy explained, according as
                    they happened to be moſt addicted to ſuperſtition, to morals, or to phyfics.
                    Some afcribed theſe operations to ancient Time, Chaos, and Darkneſs, and
                    explained the future changes in nature by the genealo-gies of theſe deities ;
                    ſome obferving attraction and repulſion, or at leaſt a fort of agreement and
                    diſcor-dance among bodies, were inclined to afcribe them to Friendſhip and
                    Hatred, or Love and Antipathy ; ſome obſerving, that while one body roſe another
                    defcended, made Levity and Gravity primary agents ; and ſome taking notice that
                    living bodies ſprung from corruption, were diſpoſed to confer the ſame powers on
                    Moiſture and Heat.</p>
                <p>The phyfical hypotheſes were what had moſt charms for the Stoics. From their
                    ſyſtem immaterial beings were openly excluded ; all things were regulated by
                    phyfical laws or inexorable fate ; and all things origi-nated in the To 'Ey or
                    the <hi rend="italic">First One,</hi> which was probably ſuggeſted by the of
                    Pythagoras. This <hi rend="sup">l o</hi> ' <hi rend="sup">e</hi> &gt; <hi rend="sup">,</hi> appears to have been a <hi rend="italic">materia
                        prima</hi> devoid of all the qualities of body. In their language it was an <hi rend="italic">^ρχ <hi rend="sup">n</hi></hi> or <hi rend="italic">first principle,</hi> not ſubject to change, when
                    it was inveſted with the properties of body, it then became</p>

                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0130" facs="gri_33125011196389_0136.tif"/>
                <p>a 275i^(∣-&gt;v or an <hi rend="italic">element ;</hi> and then, fo far as
                    reſpected its qualities, eſpecially its forms, it was ſubject to chan-gcs almoſt
                    perpetual. The gods themſelves and the fouls of men were in this fyſtem only
                    modifications of matter<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                        n="11">The <hi rend="italic">Αρχη</hi> of the Stoics appears to be the ſame
                        with the <hi rend="italic">Li</hi> of the Chinese. </note>. Man was
                    compoſed of their four elements, Fire, Air, water, and Earth ; and upon
                    diffolution, every part returned to the element from which it had come, as the
                    water of a veffel ſwimming in the ſea unites with the ocean when the veffel is
                    broken. This fyftem, it is plain, cannct poſſibly admit of any ſeparate
                    confciouſneſs of exiſtence<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                        n="12">Yet without regarding the inconſiſtency, many of the Stoics believed,
                        that the foul continued ſeparate long after death; though all in general
                        ſeemed to deny a future ſtate of rewards and puniſhments.</note>. The ſame
                    may be foid of the ſyſtems of Deιnocrates and Epicurus, and all thoſe who
                    undertook to explain things upon physical principles<note anchored="true"
                        place="bottom" type="authorial" n="13">In his <hi rend="italic">Phyfical
                            Coſmogony,</hi> Plato differed but little from the Stoics ; but he had
                        another sort of coſmogony, in which all things appear to have ſprung from,
                        and to be almoſt wholly compofed of, metaphyſical entities, as ideas of
                        forms, numbers, and mathematical figures. Theſe kinds of notions were common
                        both to him and Py-thagoras ; and were originally borrowed ſrom Egypt, where
                        calculation and geometry were half deified. See Platonism.</note>. The chief
                    merit of the phyfical ſyſtems appears to be this : Abſurd as they were, it would
                    ſeem from the whimſical and the almoſt childiſh reafoning of Lucretius, that
                    they had a tendency to lead mankind ſrom extravagant hypotheſes to ſomething
                    that was ſimilar to obſervation.</p>
                <p>What Ariſtotle thought of the ſeparate exiſtence of the ſoul after death is not
                    very certain. The ſoul lie calls an Ev7sλe^s∣α ; and if the reader can divine
                    the meaning of the word, he perhaps can divine the meaning of the <hi
                        rend="italic"> Stagy rite,</hi> and will then be a better diviner than we.
                    At other times he fays, that the ſoul is ſomething divine ; that it reſembles
                    the element of the ſtars; that it is ſomething of a fiery nature ; that it is
                    the vicegerent ¢ff God in the body ; and that the acuteneſs of the ſenſes, the
                    powers of the intellect, with the various kinds of appetites, and paſſions,
                    depend entirely on the qualities of the blood<note anchored="true"
                        place="bottom" type="authorial" n="14">The immortal Harvey has collected
                        theſe different opinions of the Stagyrite in Exercit. 5, <hi rend="italic">De Generatione Animalium.</hi></note>.</p>
                <p>Another opinion of very old date was that of the late ingenious Mr Hunter.
                    According to him, the living principle reſides in the blood. This opinion, which
                    is mentioned by Moſes, was adopted by Critias and others of the ancients. Harvey
                    likewiſe embraced it. But Mr Hunter, who always wiſned to be thought an
                    original, inclines to ſtand at the head of the opinion, and ſupports. it by
                    experiments ſimilar to thoſe of the famed Taliacotius in mending noſes. Should
                    any of our readers wiſti to extract the foul’s immortality from ſuch an opinion,
                    we muſt refer them to the many reſources of ingenuity, ſophiſtry, and logic.</p>
                <p>Among the Jews, the belief of a future and feparate exiſtence for a long time
                    was deemed no effential article of their creed. Some thought that the foul was a
                    ſpark in the moving cf the heart ; ſome imagined that it was the breath, and
                    that upon the diffolution of the body it naturally vaniſhed into ſoft air. The
                    Sadducees denied the exiftence of either angel or lpirit. Many be-lieved the
                    doctrine of ghoſts, and were accuſtomed to invoke them at the grave. It is hence
                    that we hear the prophets complaining that they were leeking from the living God
                    unto dead men. Some imagined that there was a pre-exiſttnce of ſouls; and, in
                    the caſe of a blind man, aſked our Saviour, whether the man or his parents had
                    finned that he was born blind ? others, inclined to a revolution, of ſoul and
                    body, and thought that our Saviour was either Elias or one of the old prophets
                    returned ; and a great many new-modelled; their opinion of the foul’s
                    immortality according to certain paffages in Scripture. The inſpired mother of
                    Samuel had ſaid, " The Lordki!leth and maketh alive: he bringeth down to the
                    grave, and bringeth up.” Iſaiah had exclaimed, " Thy dead ſhall live; together
                    with my dead body ſhall they arife : Awake, and ſing, ye that dwell in the dull
                    ; for thy dew is as the dew of herbs,, and the earth ſhall caſt out the dead.”
                    Daniel had de-clared <hi rend="sup">l</hi> , that many of them that ſleep in
                    the duſt of the <hi rend="sup">ι</hi> earth ſhall awake to everlaſting life,
                    and ſome to ſharn¢ and everlaſting contempt. In the viſion of the valley, of dry
                    bones, Ezekiel had ſeen that " at the word of the Lord” the bones came together,
                    bone to his bone, the ſinews and the fleſh came upon them, and the ſkin covered
                    them above, and the breath came into the bodies, and they lived, and ſtood upon
                    their feet. And a. paffage of Job led them to ſuppoſe, that at ſome diſtant and
                    future period a particular time, which wap called <hi rend="italic">the lajl</hi> or the <hi rend="italic">Litter day,</hi> was appointed by heaven for
                    the general refuιτection of all thoſe who are ſleeping in their graves. “ I know
                    ( ſays Job) my Redeemer liveth, and that he ſhall ſtand at the latter day upon
                    the earth; and though after my ſkin worms deſtroy this body, yet in my fleſh
                    ſhall I see God.”</p>
                <p>Whether theſe passages were fairly interpreted agreeably to their true and
                    original meaning, it is not here our buſineſs to inquire. It is ſufficient for
                    us to ob-ſerve, that from them many of the Jews inferred the reality of a
                    general reſurrection<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="15"
                        >At preſent ſome are for allowing only thoſe of their own nation to ſhare in
                        the benefits of this refurrection ; and fome are not even for allowing them,
                        except they be men of piety and virtue. To render this reſurrection
                        probable, the rabbins fay, with ſome of the Mahometans, that there is a
                        certain bone in the body which reſifts putrefaction, and ſerves as a feed
                        for the next body<note anchored="true" place="margin" type="authorial"
                            n="16"><hi rend="italic">See Pharrisee.</hi></note>. What that bone is,
                        is of no great moment, as any bone, we believe, in the ſkeleton will anſwer
                        the purpoſe equally well. With refpect to the manner of this reſurrection,
                        the learned Hody has quoted ſeveral opinions of the Jews, and, among others,
                        that of the Chaldee paraphraſt of the Canticles, afferting that the prophet
                        Solomon had ſaid, " when the dead shall revive, it shall come to paſs that
                        the Mount of Olives ſhall be cleft, and all the dead of Iſrael ſhall come
                        out from thence; 'and the juſt too that died in captivity ſhall come through
                        the way of the caverns under the earth, and ſhall come forth out of the
                        Mount of olives.” He has likewife quoted Saunderſon’s voyage to the Holy
                        Land, in which, we are told that many of the Jews, by their own account, are
                        to riſe up in the valley of Jehoſaphet ; and that in the <hi rend="italic">rowling</hi> or <hi rend="italic">devolution</hi> of the caverns,
                        thoſe at a diſtance muſt ſcrape their way thither with their nails.</note>.
                    In this perſuaſion, Martha, ſpeaking of her brother Lazarus, ſays to our Lord, "
                    I know that he ſhall riſe again in the re-ſurrection at the laſt day.” This
                    reſurrection appears</p>

                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0131" facs="gri_33125011196389_0137.tif"/>
                <p>to have been a general opinion among the Phariſees ; for although it was a
                    notion of the ſect of the Sadducees that there was no refurrectiûn, neither
                    angel nor ſpirit, yet the Pharifees, we are told, confeffed both. And this
                    affertion is plainly confirmed by St Paul him-ſelf when his countrymen accufed
                    him before Felix, " I confeſs unto thee (ſays this eminent apoftle), that after
                    the way which they call hereſy ſo worlhip I the God of my fathers, believing all
                    things which are written in the law and in the prophets, and having hope toward
                    God, which they theml¢lves alſo allow, that there ſhall be a refurrection of the
                    dead, both of the juſt and un-juſt.”.</p>
                <p>This reſurrectiort of the dead to judgment, though not perhaps in the ſame ſenſe
                    in which the old Phariſees conceived it, is now generally and almoſt
                        univerſally<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="17">The
                        ſect of the Quakers explain it figuratively.</note> maintained by
                        Chriſtians<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="18">The
                        laſt quoted author<note anchored="true" place="margin" type="authorial"
                            n="19"><hi rend="italic">Hody.</hi></note> <hi rend="italic">(Reſurrection of the ſame Body, asserted from the
                            traditions of the Heathens, the ancient Jews, and the primitive Church)</hi> has endeavoured to ſhow that this doctrine, in the fame fenſe as we
                        -underſtand it, has been afferted by the ancient magi, and by the preſent
                        heathen gaurs of Perfia, the relics of the ancient magi ; by ſome of the
                        ancient Arabians ; by ſome of the banians of India ; by the preſent
                        inhabitants of the iſland of Ceylon, of Java, of Pegu, of Tranſiana ; by
                        ſome amongſt the Chineſe ; by the Arderians in Guinea ; and by the ancient
                        Pruſſians. The proofs which he brings, it muſt be confeffed, are not however
                        always very fatisfactory. It appears, even, from h∣s own account, that ſome
                        of theſe had derived their notions frorh certain Chriftians, Mahometans, or
                        Jews. But the reader may judge of the great accuracy of his 1dea3 from his
                        bringing old Pythagoras and the Stoics, and even Democritus and Epicurus, in
                        ſupport of the ſame or a £milar opinion. </note>. Yet the Chriſtians differ
                    conſiderably with reſpect to the nature of the human ſoul. Some imagine, that
                    this ſpirit is naturally mortal, and that it is propagated along with the Body
                    from the loins of the parent. In ſupport of this opinion, it has been obſerved
                    that a great number of infects and plants transfer their lives to their
                    poſterity, and die foon after the act of propagation ; that after this act the
                    vital principle is iu the moſt vigorous of plants and animals always found to be
                    much exhauſted; and that Tertullian a father of the church, in attempt-ing ſome
                    experiments of the kind, became fubject to a momentary blindneſs, and felt a
                    portion of his ſoul <hi rend="italic">going</hi> out of him<note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="20">In illo ipſo
                        voluptatis ultima? æftu quo genitale virus expellitur, nonne aliquid de
                        anima quoque ſentimui &lt;χire, at que adeo marceffimus-et devigeſcimus
                        cunt lucis detrimcnto.</note>.</p>
                <p>Tlreſe imagine that immortality was only conditionally promifed to man ; that
                    Adam forfeited this immortality by his diſobedience ; and that Chriſt has
                    teſtored lis to the hopes of it again by his ſufferings and death : for as in
                    Adam we have all died, ſo in Chriſt, they fay, we ſhall all be made alive,; and
                    that now the ſting is taken ſrom death, and the victory over our ſouls from the
                    grave.</p>
                <p>others have conceived the human ſoul as naturally -immortal, and as ſetting
                    death and the grave at defiance. Adam, they ſay, died only in a figure ; and
                    only from the conſequences oſ this figure, which means fin, has our Lord ſaved
                    us. In this ſenfe Adam died on the very day in which he had fumed ; or he died
                    literally in 1000 years, which with the Lord are as one day. To theſe arguments
                    their opponents reply, what then is the victory* over death and the grave ? You
                    muſt ſtill have recourfe to a new figure, and betake yourſelvefe to the ſecond
                    death ; though, after all, where is your grave ? To this it is anſwered, that
                    the ſoul of itſelf ⅛ naturally immortal, and that it depends not either for its
                    exiftence or the exerciſe of its faculties upon the body ; that the properties
                    of matter, as figure, magnitude, and motion, can produce nothing that is like to
                    per-ception, memory, and conſciouſneſs. This is true, rejoin their opponents ;
                    but beſides theſe few properties of matter, which are only the objects of that
                    philoſophf which has lately and properly been termed <hi rend="italic">mechanical,</hi> the chemical philoſophy has diſcovered other properties of
                    matter ; has found that matter is of various kinds ; that it very often does not
                    act mechanically ; that it acquires many new properties by combination ; and
                    that no man, till farther experiment and obſervation, ſhould venture to affert
                    how far the ſoul is or is not dependent on its preſent orgahiſed ſyſtenl. The
                    others, proceeding on their hypotheſis, maintain that the ſoul, as being
                    immaterial, is not diviſible; and though the body of a frog may live without the
                    head for a whole day ; though the body of a tortoife may live without the head
                    for a whole month ; though a human limb may for ſome mi-nutes after amputation
                    continue to perform a vital motion, independent of a brain, a ſtomach, or a
                    heart ; and though the parts of a plant, a polype, or a worm, may ſurvive their
                    ieparation and become living wholes<note anchored="true" place="margin"
                        type="authorial" n="21">See <hi rend="italic">Polypus</hi> and <hi
                            rend="italic">Reproduction.</hi></note>, yet the ſoul, they obferve, is
                    not to be compared with the vital principles of plants and animals, nor ought to
                    be divided on reafons ſo ſlender a8 thoſe of analogy. Even granting, they ſay,
                    that the foul were not naturally immortal of itſelf ; yet the juſtice of God,
                    which is not remarkable for its equal diſtribution of rewards and pnniſhments in
                    the preſent world, is bound to make fome amends in the next. And to this again
                    their opponents anſwer, as to the equal diſtribution of juſtice in a future
                    world, of that we are affured on much bet-</p>

                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0132" facs="gri_33125011196389_0138.tif"/>
                <p>ter grounds than any of your's : our Lord has declared it in expreſs terms ; and
                    whether the ſoul be immortal or not, we can eaſily believe what he ſaid is true,
                    as we know him whom we have truſted.</p>
                <p>Theſe, with Plato, ſuppoſe, that the foul is here as in prifon ; though how or
                    at what time it ſhould ſirſt have come into this dungeon they have not
                    determined. They have only agreed, that upon its enlargement all its faculties
                    are to receive an increaſe cf power ; and " ha-&gt;i(ig already equipped it
                    ſo exquiſitely with conſciouſneſs, activity, and perception in and of itſelf,
                    and put it into ſo complete a capacity for happinefs and miſery in a ſeparate
                    ſtate,” their hypotheſis does not require them to admît the leaſt occaſion for a
                    reſurrection ; which accordingly is ſaid to have been an article of Baxter’s
                        creed<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="22"><hi
                            rend="italic">An Historical View oſ the Controverſy concerning an
                            Intermediate State, and the Separate Exitence of the
                    Soul.</hi></note>.</p>
                <p>A third opinion, which extends likewife to every ſpe-cies of plant and animal,
                    is, that all ſouls were created at once with bodies of ether; that theſe bodies,
                    occupying only a very ſmall ſpace, were packed up in their firſt progenitors,
                    and there left to be afterwards evolved and clothed with matter of a groſſer
                    kind by acts of gene-ration and confequent nutrition. For the proof of this
                    theory we are referred to the ſmall animals ſeen through the microſcope, and
                    likewiſe to thoſe which are ſuppo-ſed to eſcape even microſcopic obſervation ;
                    but, above all, to the eggs of infects, which, though ſcarcely per-ceptſhle, yet
                    contain in embryo a future caterpillar and all its coats, and within theſe a
                    future butterfly with its legs and wings. Theſe philoſophers can per-haps
                    account for the general taint of original tin in fome other way than has
                    hitherto been done, we have only to add, that on their fcheme the reſurrection
                    is not a matter that feems to be indifferent.</p>
                <p>The next thing that falls to be conſidered is the place of the dead. From a
                    natural enough aſſociation of ideas, an opinion had very early prevailed, that
                    the ſpirit continued near to the body; and the offerings therefore intended for
                    the dead were by moſt nations pre-ſented at the grave ; and that on which the
                    departed ſpirit is ſuppoſed to reſt is always placed near the grave in China.</p>
                <p>From the dreams of the night and the natural tendency of the fancy to work and
                    to ſummon up ſpectres when the world around us is involved in darkneſs, it has
                    alſo been imagined, that theſe ſpirſts delight in the night and ſhadow of
                        death<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="23">Some
                        Turkiſh ghoſts are an exception, who uſe lamps or candles in their tombs,
                        when their friends-chooſe to ſupply them with thefe luxuries.</note>), or
                    have been prohibited from enjoying the exhilarating beams of day. And hence we
                    are told,</p>
                <p>That in the difmal regions of the dead</p>
                <p>Th’ infernal king once rais’d his horrid head ;</p>
                <p>Leap’d from his throne, leſt Neptune’s arm ſhould lay</p>
                <p>H is dark dominions open to the day,</p>
                <p>And pour in light.</p>
                <p>The nations, therefore, who have fancied a generaI receptacle for the dead, have
                    thus been induced to place it in the west<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial" n="24">The <hi rend="italic">west</hi> and <hi
                            rend="italic">darkneſs</hi> are ſynonymous in Homer. <hi rend="italic"><hi rend="sup"> il</hi> φ,∖ <hi rend="sub">0</hi> ∣, « γa <hi
                                rend="sub"> ρ</hi> ι <hi rend="sup">,</hi> <hi rend="sub">l</hi> tμιι S*» ζ <hi rend="sub">o</hi> &lt; <hi
                                rend="sub"> f</hi> oς,</hi> ouΓ <hi rend="italic">ox* t∣aς.
                            (Odys.</hi> “ O my friends! which is the weſt, or which is the eaſt,
                        the place of darkneſs, or that of the morning, we cannot learn."</note>,
                    where the night begins and the day ends. That part of the world which, in the
                    diviſion of his father’s dominions, fell to Pluto the in-fernal god, and where,
                    according to Lactantius, Satan holds the empire of darknefs, the Friendly
                    Iſlanders have placed to the weſtward of a certain iſland which they call <hi
                        rend="italic"> Tejee. ;</hi> ſome tribes of American Indians, in a country
                    beyond the weſtern mountains ; and Homer, ſomewhere to the weſtward of Greece at
                    the boundaries of the ocean,</p>
                <p>where in a lonely land and gloomy cells</p>
                <p>The duſky nation of Cimmeria dwells ;</p>
                <p>'ſ'he ſun ne’er views th’ uncomfortable feats when radiant he advances nor
                    retreats.</p>
                <p>Unhappy race ! whom endlefs night invades,</p>
                <p>Clouds the dull air, and wraps them round in ſhades.</p>
                <p>Another opinion entertained by the Greeks and fome other nations was, that the
                    place of departed ſpirits is under the earth. This opinion is frequently
                    mentioned in Homer, in virgil, and ; Jaded to by the Jewiſh prophets. As for the
                    prophets, we know the circumſtance from which they borrowed it : it was borrowed
                    from thofe ſubterraneous vaults where their chiefs were bu-ried, and which have
                    been deſcribed by modern travellers» In the ſides of theſe caverns there is
                    ranged a great number of cells; and in theſe cells the mighty lay in a fort of
                    ſtate, with their weapons of war and their ſwords at their head. To thefe kinds
                    of Egyptian cemeteries Ezekiel alludes, when he ſays, " that they ſhall not lie
                    with the mighty that are fallen of the uncircum-cifed, who are gone down to hell
                    with their weapons of war, and they have laid their ſwords under their head.”
                    And Iſaiah, when thus ſpeaking of the prince of Ba-bylon, " Thou ſhalt be
                    brought down to hell, <hi rend="italic">to the ſides of the pit.</hi> Hell
                    from beneath is moved for thee, to meet thee at thy coming ; it ſtirreth up the
                    dead for thee, even all the chief ones of the earth ; it hath raiſed up from
                    their thrones all the kings of the nations. All the kings of the nations, even
                    all of them, lie in glory, every one in his own houſe.”</p>
                <p>Many of the ancient fathers of the church aſſerted only, that the dead are now <hi rend="italic">in abditis receptaculis,</hi> or in certain hidden and
                    concealed places.</p>
                <p>orpheus, o∏gen, and forne others of the fathers, with the ancient Caledonian
                    bard oſſian, and the learn-ed Dodwell among the moderns, imagined that the fouI,
                    when it left the body, went into the air, and reſided ſomewhere between the
                    furfacc of the earth and the moon.</p>
                <p>Thoſe who believed in a tranſmigration cauſed the ſoul at death only to enter a
                    new body, and kept the departed always with the living. This creed has been
                    found in India, in Egypt, in Mexico, and in all thoſe countries where
                    picture-writing has been much uſed. In this ſpecies oſ writing, the ſame picture
                    is on fancied analogy transferred by metaphor to ſignify ei-</p>

                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0133" facs="gri_33125011196389_0139.tif"/>
                <p>ther a god or a man, a brute or a plant; and in thoſe countries where it was
                    practiſed, men had uſually their names from animals, and were repreſented by
                    their ſigure in writing<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                        n="25">A military gentleman who refided at Penobſcot during the late
                        American war, aſſured us that the Indians, when defired to ſubfcribe a
                        written agreement, drew always the picture of the object or animal whoſe
                        name they bore. But for fuller information on this ſubject, ſee Clavigero’s
                        Hiſt. of Mexico.</note>. From this laſt ſtage of the proceſs, a
                    tranſmigration was eaſily ſuppoſed : and hence we hear of the gods of Egypt
                    wandering about like ſo many vagrants in brute ſhapes, and of princes being
                    tranſlated into ſtars, becauſe a ſtar was their emblem in hieroglyphic, or ſtood
                    for their name in figurative lan-guage. And, in like manner, we ſee, from the
                    ſpecimen of this character -which is ſtill preſerved on celeſtial globes, how
                    the heavens aj firſt came to be filled with bears, ſeorpions, and dragons, and
                    with a va-riety of other animals.</p>
                <p>The opinions concerning the ſtate of the dead are ſtill more numerous than thoſe
                    concerning the place where they reiide. Rude nations have generally thought that
                    the future ſtate is limilar to the preſent; that plants, animals, and inanimate
                    things there, have their ſhades ; and that theſe contribute as much to the
                    pleaſures and conveniences of the dead as their realities do to the li-ving ;
                    that huſhands have their wives<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial" n="26">The queſtion which the Sadducees put to our Saviour
                        about the wife of the ſeven brothers, is a proof that the Phariſees thought
                        there was marriage and giving in marriage in the future ſtate, and that it
                        was ſome-what ſimilar to the preſent.</note>, lovers their miſtreſſes,
                    warriors their battles, huntſmen their ſport ; and that all their paſſions,
                    amuſements, and bufineſs, are the ſame as formerly. For this reaſon, that the
                    dead may not appear unprovided in the next world, like the ancient Gauls, ſome
                    tribes of India, America, and Africa, bury with them in the ſame grave their
                    wives, their arms, their favourite animals, and their neceffary utenfils.</p>
                <p>Ί he ancient Egyptians, who believed in tranſmigra-tion, ſuppoſed that the ſoul
                    was after death obliged to animate every ſpecies of bird and quadruped, of
                    reptile and infect, and was not to return to a human form till after a period of
                    3500 years, others have confined their tranſmigrations to particular animals, as
                    the ſoul oſ man to the human form, and the ſoul of the brute to the bodies of
                    the ſpecies to which it belonged. Some bave changed the brute into man, and man
                    into the brute, that man might ſuffer injuries ſimilar to what he had inflicted,
                    and the brute retaliate what he had ſuffered. others have confined the human
                    ſoul in plants and in ftones ; and Bell of Antermony mentions an Indiau who
                    ſuppoſed that his anceſtors might be in fiſhes.</p>
                <p>The notions of Homer were probably thoſe of many of his time. But theſe notions
                    were difimd indeed, when his hero Ulyffes vifited the ſhades, many of the ghoſts
                    ſeemed to retain the mangled and ghaſtly appearance which they had ct death 5
                    and, what is worſe, feemed to be all ſtarving with hunger, innumerable
                    multitudes, with loud ihrieks, flocking to the fleams of lus ſlain victim-as to
                    a moſt ſumptuoug and delicious banquet.</p>
                <p>For ſcarcely had the purple torrent flow’d,</p>
                <p>And all the caverns imok’d with ſtreaming blood, when, lo ! appear’d along the
                    duſky coaſts Thin airy flιoals oſ viſionary ghoſts ;</p>
                <p>Fair penfive youths, and ſoft enamour’d maids,.</p>
                <p>And wither’d elders, pale and wrinkl’d ſhades.</p>
                <p>Ghaſtly with wounds, the forms of warriors ſlain, Stalk’d with majeſtic port, a
                    martial train.</p>
                <p>Thςfe, and a thouſand more, ſwarrn’d o’er the ground, And all the dire aſſembly
                    ſhriek’d around.</p>
                <p>Ulyſſes ſaw, as ghoſt by ghoſt aroſe,</p>
                <p>All wailing with unutterable woes.</p>
                <p>Alone, apart, in diſcontented mood,</p>
                <p>A gloomy ihade, the ſullen Ajax ſtood ;</p>
                <p>For ever fad, with proud diidain he pin’d,</p>
                <p>And the loſt arms lor ever ſtung his mind.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Upon Ulyfſts faying to Achilles,</hi></p>
                <p>Alive, we hail’d thee with our guardian gods ;</p>
                <p>And, dead, thou rul’ſt a king in theſe abodes ;</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Thefhade replfd :</hi></p>
                <p>Talk not of ruling in this dol’rous gloom,</p>
                <p>Nor think vain words (he cry’d) can eaſe my doom ; Rather I ehυυfe laboriouſly
                    to bear</p>
                <p>A weight of woes, and breathe the vital air,</p>
                <p>A slave to some poor hind that toils for bread. Than live a scepter’d monarch of
                    the dead.</p>
                <p>In this gloomy region no one is rewarded for his virtue, nor is puniſhed for his
                    crimes, unleſs committed, like thoſe of Siſyphus, Tantalus, and Ixion, againſt
                    the gods. AU indeed are claifed into groups, from a certain analogy of age, fex,
                    fate, and diſpolition ; but all appear to be equally unhappy, having their whole
                    heart and affections concentrated in a world to which they are fated never to
                    return.</p>
                <p>The Elysium of Homer is allotted only for the relations and deſcendants of the
                    gods ; and Menelaus goes to this country of perpetual ſpring<note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="27">Homer fends the ghoſt
                        of Hercules to the ſhades, while Hercules himſelf is quaffing nectar with
                        Hebe in the ſkies. Οηε ſoul of the hero is therefore repining with the
                        ghoſts of mortals in the regions below, while the other is enjoying all the
                        happineſs of the gods above. (See odyssey, B. II. near the end).
                        Philoſophers ſince have improved on this hint oſ the poet ; and men have now
                        got rational, animal, and vegetable ſouls, to which ſometimes a fourth one
                        is added, as properly belonging to matter in general. Homer infιnuateε, that
                        Menelaus was to be tranſiated to Elyſium without taſting death. This Elyſium
                        is the habitation of men, and not of ghoſts, and is deſcribed as being
                        ſimilar to the feat of the gods. Compare <hi rend="italic">Odyss.</hi> iv.
                        1.563. and <hi rend="italic">Odyss.</hi> vi. 1. 43. in the Greek.</note>,
                    not as a perlon of ſuperior merit, but becauſe he had married the daughter of
                    Jove.</p>
                <p>Even long after a future ſtate had become the ſcene of rewards and puniſhments,
                    theſe for the moſt part were diſtributed, not according to moral, but phyfical
                    diſtinctions. with the Greeks and Romans,.the ſoul was condemned to many
                    calamities for a number of</p>

                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0134" facs="gri_33125011196389_0140.tif"/>
                <p>years, if the body was not honoured with funeral rites. Among the Scandinavians,
                    a natural death was attended with infamy, while a violent death, particularly in
                    battle, gave a title to ſit in the halls of odin, and to quaff beer from the
                    ikulls of enemies. Among the Tlaſcalans, it was only the great that were
                    permitted . to animate birds and the nobler quadrupeds ; the lower ranks were
                    transformed into weaſels, into paultry beetles, and fuch mean animals. Among the
                    Mexicans, thoſe who were drowned, who died of a dropſy, tumors, or wounds, or
                    ſuch like diſeaſes, went along with the children that had been ſacriſiced to the
                    god of water, and in a cool and delightful place were allowed to indulge in
                    delicious repaſts and varieties of pleaſures: thoſe who died of other diſeaſes,
                    were ſent to the north or centre of the earth, and were under the dominion of
                    the gods ot darkneſs. " Tlie loldiers who died in battle, or in captivity among
                    their enemies, and the women who died in labour, went to the houſe of the fun,
                    who was confidered as the prince of glory. In his manſions they led a life of
                    endleſs delight-. Every day the foldiers, on the firſt appearance of his rays,
                    hailed his birth with rejoicings and with dancings, and the muſic of inſtruments
                    and voices. At his meridian they met with the women, and in like feſtivity
                    accompanied him to his ſetting. After four years of this glorious life, they
                    went to animate clouds, and birds of beautiful feathers and of ſweet ſong.; but
                    always at liberty to rile again, if they pleaſed, to heaven, or deſcend to the
                    earth, to warble their ſongs, and to suck flowers<note anchored="true"
                        place="margin" type="authorial" n="28"><hi rend="italic">Clavigero's Hist.
                            of Mexico,</hi> vol. vi. p. 136.</note>.”</p>
                <p>Thefe ſentiments of a future ſtate, conceived in a ſavage and a rude period,
                    could not long prevail among an enlightened and civilized people, when the times
                    of rapine and violence therefore began to ceaſe ; when focieties regulated by
                    certain laws began to be eſtabliſhed ; when martial prowefs was leſs requisite,
                    and the qualities of the heart had begun to give an importance to the character,
                    the future ſtate was alſo modelled on a different plan. In the Æneid of virgil,
                    an author of a highly cultivated mind, and of poliſhed manners, it becomes a
                    place of the moſt impartial and unerring Juſtice ; every one now receives a
                    ſentence ſuited to the actions of his paſt life, and a god is made to preſide in
                    judgment;</p>
                <p>who hears and judges each committed crime,</p>
                <p>Inquires into the manner, place, and time.</p>
                <p>The confcious wretch muſt all his acts reveal,</p>
                <p>Loth to confeſs, unable to conceal,</p>
                <p>From the firſt moment of his vital breath,</p>
                <p>To the laſt hour of unrepenting death.</p>
                <p>The ſpirſts of the dead no longer mingle toge-ther-as in the leſs enlightened
                    period of Homer; the vicious are difmiffed to a place of torments, the virtuous
                    ſent to regions of blifs: indifferent characters are confined to a limbus<note
                        anchored="true" place="margin" type="authorial" n="29">Or paradise of
                        fools.</note>; and thoſe who are too virtuous for hell, but too much
                    polluted with the ſtains of vice to enter heaven without preparation, are for
                    fome time detained in a purgatory.</p>
                <p>For there are various penances enjoin’d,</p>
                <p>And ſome are hung to bleach upon the wind ?</p>
                <p>Same plung’d in waters, others purg’d in fires,</p>
                <p>Till all the dregs are drain’d, and ruſt expires ;</p>
                <p>Till nothing’s left of their habitual ſtams,</p>
                <p>But the pure ether of the foul remains.</p>
                <p>When thus purified, they become fitted to receive the rewards of their paſt
                    virtues, and now enter into thoſe regions of happineſs and joy.</p>
                <p>With ether veſted, and a purple ſky,</p>
                <p>The bliſsful ſeats of happy fouls below,</p>
                <p>Stars of their own, and their own suns they know</p>
                <p>Where patriots live, who, for their country’s good,</p>
                <p>In fighting fields were prodigal of blood.</p>
                <p>Prieſts of unblemiſh’d lives here make abode,</p>
                <p>And poets worthy their inſpiring god ;</p>
                <p>And ſearching wits, of more mechanic parts, who grac’d their age with
                    new-invented arts :</p>
                <p>Those who to worth their bounty did extei¢d ;</p>
                <p>And thoſe who knew that bounty to commend.</p>
                <p>Theſe good men are engaged in various amuſements, according to the taſte and
                    genius of each. Qrpħeus is ſtill playing on his harp, and the warriors are ſtill
                    delighted with their chariots, their hυrfes, and their arms.</p>
                <p>The place of torment is at fome diſtaace.</p>
                <p>A gaping gulph, which to the centre lies,</p>
                <p>And twice as deep as earth is diſtant from the ſkies;</p>
                <p>From hence are heard the groans of ghoſts, the pains</p>
                <p>Οf sounding laſhes, and of dragging chains.</p>
                <p>Here, those who brother’s better claim disown,</p>
                <p>Expel their parents, and uſurp the throne;</p>
                <p>Defraud their clients, and, to lucre sold,</p>
                <p>Sit brooding on unprofitable gold.</p>
                <p>Who dare not give, and even refuſe to lend,</p>
                <p>To their poor kindred, or a wanting friend.</p>
                <p>Vast is the throng of theſe ; nor leſs the train</p>
                <p>Of luſtful youths for foul adult'ry slain.</p>
                <p>Hoſts of deſerters, who their honour fold,</p>
                <p>And baſely broke their faith for bribes of gold:</p>
                <p>All theſe within the dungeon’s depth remain,</p>
                <p>Despairing pardon, and expecting pain.</p>
                <p>The fouls of babes, of unhappy lovers, and fome others, feem to be placed in a
                    paradiſe of fools reading in a quarter diſtinct from Elysian Tartarus and
                    Purgatory.</p>
                <p>It is curious to obſerve, how much thefe ideas of a future ſtate differ from the
                    vague and fimple conjec-tures of rude nations ; and yet from their ſimple and
                    rude conjectures, we can eaſily trace the ſucceiſive changes in the writings of
                    Homer, Plato, and virgil ; and may eaſily ſhow, that thofe laws which different
                    nations have preſcribed for their dead, have always borne the ſtrong-eſt analogy
                    to their ſtate of improvement, their ſyſtem of opinions, and their moral
                    attainments. Some na-tions, as thoſe of India, have fancied a number of hea-vens
                    and hells, correſponding to fome of their principal ſhadea in virtue and vice ;
                    and have ſilled each of theſe places refpectively with all the fceπes of
                    happineſs and mifery, which friendſhip and hatred, admiration, coh-tempt, or
                    rancour, could ſuggeſt, But haring already obſerved the progreſs of the human
                    mind in forming the grand and leading ideas of a future ſtate, we mean not to
                    deſcend to the modifications which may haye occurred tq particular nations,
                    ſects, or individuals.</p>
                <p>The belief ot Chrilliaus respecting futurity demands our attention, as being
                    founded on a different principle, namely, on expreſs revelations from heaven.
                    From many expreſs declarations in Scripture, all Chriſtians ſeem to be agreed»
                    that there is a heaven appointed for</p>

                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0135" facs="gri_33125011196389_0141.tif"/>
                <p>the good and a hell for the wicked. In this heaven the faints dwell in the
                    preſence of God and the unin-terrupted ſplendors- of day. Thoſe who have been
                    wife ſhine as the firmament, and thoſe who have converted many to righteouſneſs
                    as the ſtars. Their bodies are glorious, immortal, incorruptible, not ſubject to
                    diſeaſe, to pain, or to death. Their minds are ſtrangers to ſor-rtrw, to crying,
                    to diſappointment ; all their deſires are preſently ſatisſied ; while they are
                    calling, they are aπ-ſwered ; while they are fpeaking, they are heard. Their
                    mental faculties are alſo enlarged ; they no more ſee things obfcurely, and as
                    through a cloud, but continu-ally beholding new wonders and beauties in
                    creation, are conſtantly exclaiming^ " Holy, holy, holy ! is the Lord of Hoſts,
                    worthy is he to receive glory, and honour, and th’inkſgiving ; and to him be
                    afcribed wiſdom, and power, and might; for great and marvellous are his works,
                    and the whole univerſe is filled with his glory.”</p>
                <p>Their notions of hell differ conſiderably. Some un-derſtanding the Scriptures
                    literally, have plunged the v⅛ icſked into an abyſs without any bottom ; have
                    made this g∏lρh darker than night ; have ſilled it with rancorous and malignant
                    ſpirits, that are worſe than furies ; and have deſcribed it as lull of ſulphur,
                    burning for ever. This frightful gulph has by ſome been placed in the bowels of
                    the earth ; by ſome in the fun ; by ſome in the moon ; and by ſome in a comet :
                    but as the Scriptures have determined nothing on the ſubject, all ſuch
                    conjectures are idle and groundless.</p>
                <p>others imagine, that the fire and ſulphur are here to be taken in a figurative
                    ſenfe. Thefe fuppoſe the torments of hell to be troubles of mind and remorfes of
                    conſcience ; and ſupport their opinion by obſerving, that matter cannot act upon
                    ſpirit ; forgetting, perlιaps, that at the reſurrection the fpirſt is to he
                    clothed with a body, and, at any rate, that ſt is not for man vainly to
                    preſcribe bounds to omnipotence.</p>
                <p>what ſeems to have tortured the genius of divines much more than heaven or hell,
                    is a middle ſtate. Οη this ſubject there being little revealed in Scripture,
                    many have thought it incumbent upon them to lupply the defect ; which they ſeem
                    to have done in different ways. From the Scriptures ſpeaking frequently of the
                    dead as ſleeping in their graves, thoſe who imagine that the powers of the mind
                    are dependent on the body, ſuppoſe that they ſleep till the reſurrection, when
                    they are to be awakened by the trump &lt;⅛f God, reunited to their bodies,
                    have their faculties reſtored, and their ſentence awarded.</p>
                <p>This opinion they Γupport by what St Peter ſays in the Acts, that David is not
                    aſcended into heaven ; and that this patriarch could not poſſibly be ſpeaking of
                    himſelf when he ſaid, “ Thou wilt not leave my ſoul in hell, <hi rend="italic">i. e.</hi> the place of the dead.” They obſerve, too, that the victory of
                    Chriſt over death and the grave ſeems to imply, that our fouls are ſubject to
                    their power ; that accordingly the Scripture ſpeaks frequently of the foul’s
                    drawing near to, of its being redeemed from, and of its deſcending into, the
                    grave ; that the Pſalmiſt, however, declares plainly, that when the breath of
                    man goeth forth, he returneth to his earth, and that very day his thoughts
                    pcriſh. And ſhould any one choofe to con-fult Eccleſiaſtes, he will find, that
                    the living know that they ſhall die, but that the dead know not any thing : that
                    their love, and their hatred, and their envy, are periſhed-; aud- that there is
                    no work, nor device, nor wiſdom, nor knowledge, in the grave, whether theÿ are
                    gone.</p>
                <p>Thoſe who believe that the foul is not for the exer-cife of its faculties
                    dependent on the body, are upon its feparation at death obliged to diſpoſe of it
                    ſome other way. In eſtabliſhing their theory, they uſually begin with attempting
                    to prove, from Scripture or tradi-tion, both its active and ſeparate exiſtence ;
                    but with proofs from tradition we intend not to meddle. Their arguments from
                    Scripture being of more value, deſerve our ferions conſtderation ; and are
                    nearly as follow.</p>
                <p>Abraham, they ſay, Ifaac, and Jacob, are ſtill living, becauſe Jehovah is their
                    God, and he, it is allowed, is not the God of the dead, but of the living. But
                    their opponents reply, That this is the argument which our Saviour brought from
                    the writings of Mofes to prove a future refurrection of the dead ; and that aay
                    perfon who looks into the context, will ſee it was not meant ol a middle ſtate.
                    From the dead living unto God, our Saviour infers nothing more than that they
                    ihall live at the reſurrection ; and that theſe gentlemen would do well in
                    future to make a diſtinction between limply living and living unto God : For
                    though. Abιaham, lfaac, and Jacob, be living unto God, our Saviour~has affured
                    us that Abraham is dead, and thé prophets dead.</p>
                <p>A ſecond argument is that glimpfe which St PauI had oſ paradiſe about 14 years
                    before he had written his Second Epiſtle to the Corinthians. To this argument
                    their opponents reply, That as St Paul could not tell whether, on that occafion,
                    he was out of the body or in the body, it is more than probable that the whole
                    was a viſion ; and, at any rate, it is no prooſ oſ a ſeparate exiſtence.</p>
                <p>A third argument is, St Paul’s wiſhing to be abſent from the body, and preſent
                    with the Lord. But, say their opponents, St Paul desired not to be unclothed,
                    but to be clothed upon; and as ſome oſ thoſe who maintain a ſeparate exiſtence,
                    bring Scripture to prove that the body<note anchored="true" place="margin"
                        type="authorial" n="30"><hi rend="italic">Shorter Catechisism.</hi></note>
                    continues united to Chriſt till the reſurrec-tiυn ; in that cale, St. Paul, if
                    he wiſhed to be preſent with the Lord, ſhould have rather remained with his body
                    than leſt it.</p>
                <p>A fourth argument is, the appearance oſ Moſes and Elias upon the mount of
                    transfiguration. To which their opponents reply, that theſe ſaint's appeared in
                    their bodies ; that Elias was never diverted oſ his body; and that the account
                    which we have oſ the burial of Moſes, has led fome of the ableſt critics and
                    foundeſt divines to conclude, that he was likewiſe tranſlated to heaven without
                    tailing death. At any rate, ſay they, he might have beeιr raifed from the dead
                    for the very purpoſe of being preſent at the transfiguration, as the bodies of
                    other faints certainly were, to bear teſtimony to our Lord's reſurrection and
                    victory over the grave.</p>
                <p>A fifth argument is, what our Saviour ſaid to the thief, “ verily I ſay unto
                    thee, to-day thou ſhalt be with me in paradiſc.” The objection uſually made here
                    is, that the expreſſion is evidently ambiguous, and' that the ſenſe depends
                    entirely on the punctuation : for if the point be placed after <hi rend="italic"
                        > to-day,</hi> the meaning will be " verily, even now, I tell thee, thou
                    ſhalt be with me in paradiſe.” But the import of paradiſe in this place, ſay the
                    opponents, is likewiſe doubtful, we learn from St Peter’s explanation of the
                    16th Pſalm, that our Sa-</p>

                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0136" facs="gri_33125011196389_0142.tif"/>
                <p>viour’s ſoul was not to be left in hell 5 and we know that on the day of his
                    crucifixion he went not to hea-veil : for after he had riſen from the place of
                    the dead, he forbade one of the women to touch him, as he had not yet aſcended
                    to the Father. Hell, therefore, and paradiſe, continue they, ſeem to be in this
                    paſſage the very ſame thing, the place of the dead ; and our Savi-our’s
                    intention, they add, was not to go to heaven at that time, but to ſhow his
                    victory' over death and the grave, to whoſe power all mankind had become ſubject
                    by the diſobedience of their ſirſt parents.</p>
                <p>without pretending to enter into the merits of this difpute, the ingenious
                    Burnet, in his Theory of the Earth, endeavours to prove, upon the authority of
                    the ancient fathers, that paradiſe lies between the earth and the moon ; and the
                    learned Dodwell, on the ſame authority, has made it the common receptacle of
                    fouls till the reſurrection ; but has not told us whether or not they are to be
                    accountable for the actions of this ſeparate exiſtence at the latter day, or are
                    only to be judged according to the deeds that were done in their bodies.</p>
                <p>This notion of a common receptacle has diſpleaſed many. The ſtate of purgation,
                    obſcurely hinted in the doctrines of Pythagoras, and openly avowed by Plato and
                    virgil, has been adopted by the Romiſh divines, who ſupport their opinion on
                    certain obſcure paſſages of ſcripture, which are always of a yielding and a
                    waxen nature, may caſily be twilled to any hypotheſis, and like general lovers
                    efpouſe rather from intereſt than merit.</p>
                <p>It has diſpleaſed others, becauſe they are anxious that the righteous ſhould
                    have a fore-taſte of their joys, and the wicked of their torments, immediately
                    after death, which they infer to be certainly the caſe from the parable of the
                    rich man and Lazarus<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="31"
                        >Whitby ſhows that this parable was conformable to the notions of the Jews
                        at that time; and even the Mahometans, who believe in the reſurrection of
                        the dead, ſuppoſe likewiſe a ſtate ¢f rewards and puniſhments in the
                        grave.</note>. But to this it is objected, that the rich man is ſuppoſed to
                    be in hell, the place of torments, and that this puniſhment ought not to take
                    place on their own hypotheſis till after the ſentence at the reſurrection.</p>
                <p>Another argument uſed for the intermediate ſtate is the viſion of St John in the
                    Apocalypſe. In this viſion the Evangeliſt faw under the altar the fouls of thoſe
                    that were ſlain for the word of God and for the teſtimo-ny which they held.
                    Their opponents doubt whether theſe viſible fouls were immaterial, as St John
                    heard them cry with a loud voice, and ſaw white robes given unto every one of
                    them. If they had bodies, that circumſtance might chance to prove a refurrection
                    immediately after death, and ſo ſuperſede the general reſurrection at the laſt
                    day.</p>
                <p>while ſuch concluſions as are here drawn ſrom the parable and viſion, ſay the
                    oppoſers of an intermediate confcious exiſtence, imply that the dead are already
                    raifed, and are now receiving the reſpective rewards of their virtues and their
                    crimes ; thoſe who maintain an intermediate ſeparate exiſtence, who ſpeak of the
                    body as a prifon, and of the ſoul as receiving an increaſe of power when freed
                    from the body, are certainly not more than conſiſtent with themſelves, when they
                    think that this foul would derive an advantage from its after union with either
                    a new ſyſtem of matter or the old onc, how-ever much altered. Baxter, they ſay,
                    who ſaw the in-</p>
                <p>conſiſtency, was diſpoſed to reaſon ſomewhat like Æ-neaβ,</p>
                <p>O, Father ! can it be that fouls fublime</p>
                <p>Return to viſit our terreſtrial çlime ?</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Ογ that the gett’rous mind, releas’d at death,</hi></p>
                <p>Should covet lazy limbs and mortal breath ?</p>
                <p>In no one inſtance, they continue, have Chriſtiann perhaps more apparently than
                    in this argument wreſted the ſcriptures to their own hurt: by thus raſhly
                    at-temping to accommodate the ſacred doctrines of religion to a preconceived
                    philofophical hypotheſis, they have laid themfelves open to the ridicule of
                    deiſts, and have been obliged, for the fake of confiſtency, either to deny or to
                    ſpeak ſlightingly of the refurrection; which is certainly the ſureſt foundation
                    of their hope, feeing St Paul hath aſſured us, that if there be no reſurrection
                    of the dead, then they which are fallen aſleep in Chriſt are periſhed, and thoſe
                    who ſurvive may eat and drink, and act as they pleafe, for to-morrow they die;
                    and die, too, never to five again.</p>
                <p>Though this reproof may be rather ſevere, we are forry to obferve that there
                    ſeems to havc been fome-times too much reaſon for it. A certain divine<note
                        anchored="true" place="margin" type="aauthorial" n="32">Dr
                            W<unclear>atizo</unclear></note>, whoſe piety was eminent, and whoſe
                    memory we reſpect, having written " An Eſſay toward the proof of a ſeparate
                    State oſ Souls between Death and the Reſurrection, and the Commencement of the
                    Rewards of virtue and vice immediately after death,” has taken this motto, "
                    Becauſe ſentence againſt an evil work is not executed ſpeedily, therefore the
                    heart of the fons of men is fully ſet in them to do evil.” “ The doctrine, he
                    ſays, of the reſurrection of the body and the conſc-quent ſtates of heaven and
                    of hell, is a guard and motive of divine force, but it is renounced by the
                    enemies of our holy Chriſtianſty ; and ſhould we give up the re-compenfes of
                    ſeparate fouls, while the deiſt denies the reſurrection of the body, I fear,
                    between both we ſhould fadly enfeeble and expoſe the cauſe of virtue, and leave
                    it too naked and defenceleſs.”</p>
                <p>This author, who wiſhes much that the puniſhment of crimes ſhould follow
                    immediately after death, is of opinion, that if heaven intended to check vice
                    and impiety in the world, it has acted unwiſely, if it really has deferred the
                    puniſhment of the wicked to fo late a pe-riod as the reſurrection. " For ſuch,
                    he obſerves, is the weakneſs and folly of our natures, that men will not be fo
                    much influenced and alarmed by diſtant proſpects, nor fo folicttous to prepare
                    for an event which they ſuppoſe to be fo very far off, as they would for the
                    ſame event if it commences as foon as ever this mortal life expires. The vicious
                    man will indulge his ſenſualities, and lie down to ſleep in death with this
                    comfort, I ſhall take my reſt here for too or 1000 years, and perhaps in all
                    that fpace my offences may be forgotten ; or let the worſt come that can come, I
                    ſhall have a long ſweet nap before my ſorrows begin : and thus the force of
                    divine terrors is greatly enervated by this delay of puniſhment.”</p>
                <p>Thus far our author, who thinks that his hypothe-fis, if not true, is at leaſt
                    expedient, and that from motives of expediency it ought to be inculcated as a
                    doc-</p>

                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0137" facs="gri_33125011196389_0143.tif"/>
                <p>trine of Scripture ; but how far his reafons can be here juſtiſied we mean not
                    to determine ; we ihall leave that to be fettled by others, reminding them only
                    that the diſtance of future rewards and puniſhments is not greater on the
                    ſhppoſition oſ the ſleep of the ſoul than on the contrary hypotheſis. Every man
                    who has but dipt into the ſcience of metaphyſics knows, and no man ever knew
                    better than he who is believed to have been the author of the work before us,
                    that time unperceived paffes away as in an inſtant; and that if the ſoul be in a
                    ſtate void of conſciohſneſs between death and the reſurrection, the man who has
                    lain in his grave iooo years will appear to himſelf to have died in one moment
                    and been raifed in the next, we would likewiſe recommend to thoſe who may
                    henceforth be inclined to inculcate any thing as a doctrine of Scripture merely
                    on account of its ſuppoſed expediency, always to remember that God is above,
                    that they are below, that he is omniſcient, that they are of yeſtcrday aud know
                    little, that their words therefore ſhould be wary and few, and that they ſhould
                    always ſpeak with reſpect of whatever concerns the Sovereign of the univerſe, or
                    relates to his government either in the natural or mo∙ ral world. For wilt thou,
                    fays the Higheſt, diſannul my judgement? wilt thou condemn me that thou mayeſt
                    be righteous ? ſhall he that contendeth with the Almighty inſtruct him? He that
                    reproveth God let him anſwer it.</p>
                <p>If, in ſtating theſe oppoſite opinions, we may ſeem to have favoured what has
                    been called the ſleep of the ſoul, it is not from any conviction of its truth,
                    for there are particular texts of Scripture which appear to us to militate
                    againſt it. W6 are ſatisſied, however, that it is a very harmlefs opinion,
                    neither injurious to the reſt of the articles of the Chriſtian faith nor to
                    virtuous practice ; and that thoſe who have poured forth torrents of obloquy
                    upon ſuch as may have held it in ſimplicity and godly ſincerity, have either
                    miſtaken the doctrine which they condemned, or been poffeffed by a ſpirit leſs
                    mild than that of the gospel<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial" n="33">Perhaps no man has been more culpable in this
                        reſpect than the celebrated warburton, who ſeems at ſirſt to have himſelf
                        denied an intermediate ſtate of conſcions exiſtence. He afterwards imagined
                        that luch a ſtate is ſuppoſed, though not expreſsly afferted, in Scripture ;
                        and at laſt he maintained it with all the zeal and warmth of a profelyte. To
                        prove the ſincerity of his converſion, he treated his adverſaries with
                        ſcurrilous nicknames, banter, and abuſe ; a ſpecies of reaſoning which
                        ſeldom ſucceeds in recommending a bad cauſe, and which never confers credit
                        on one that is good.</note>.</p>
                <p>Whatever be the fate of the middle ſtate, the reſurrection ſtands on a different
                    baſis. It is repeatedly af-ſerted in Scripture; and thoſe grounds on which we
                    believe it are authenticated facts, which the affectation, the ingenuity, and
                    the hatred of ſceptics, have number-leſs times attempted in vain to diſprove.
                    Theſe facts we are now to conſider, referring our readers for the character of
                    the witneffes, the authenticity of the <hi rend="italic">go·</hi> ſpel-hiſtory, and the poſſibility of miracles, to the parts of this work where
                    theſe ſubjects are treated (See Miracle, Metaphysics, Part I. Chap. vii. and
                    Religion) ; or, ſhould more particular information be required, to the writings
                    of Ditton, Sherlock, and well.</p>
                <p>Our Lord, after proving his divine miſſion by the miracles which he wrought, and
                    by the completion of ancient predictions in which he was deſcribed, declared
                    that the doctrine of a refurrection was one of thofe truths which he came to
                    announce. To ſhow that ſuch an event was poſſible, he reftored to life the
                    daughter of Jairus, a ruler of the ſynagogue, a young man of Nain, who was
                    carried out on his bier to be buried, and his friend Lazarus, whoſe body at the
                    time was thought to have become the prey of corruption. Though the two ſirſt of
                    thefe miracles were wrought in the preſence of a number of witneſtes, yet the
                    laſt, owing to particular circumſtances, produced a much greater noiſe among the
                    Jews. It was performed on a perfon ſeemingly of ſome note, in the village of
                    Bethany, not far from Jeruſalem, and in the preſence of a great many perſons who
                    from the metropolis had come to condole with</p>
                <p>Mary and Martha. No doubts were entertained of the reality of Lazarus’s death,
                    ∩ur Lord was at a diſtance when he expired, and his body had already been lying
                    for ſome days in the grave, when he came forth at the voice of our Lord, all
                    were aſtoniihed. Thoſe from Jeruſalem, on returning home, are impatient to
                    relate what they had ſeen ; thoſe who heard of ſo memorable an event cannot
                    conceal it ; the report reaches the ears of the Phariſees and chief prieſts.
                    They are ſoon made acquainted with every circumſtance ; and dreading the iſtue,
                    they think it neceffary to call a council upon the occaſion, and concert the
                    meaſures that ought to be purſued in a matter which was likely to be attended
                    with ſo many and important conſequenccs. In this council, it feemed to be agreed
                    that our Lord had performed, and was ſtill continuing to perform, many mi-racles
                    : That this laff miracle, as being of an extraordinary kind, would make many
                    converts ; and that if meafnres were not ſpeedily taken to prevent theſe
                    uncommon diſplays of his power, all would believe on him : the jealouſy of the
                    Romans would be excited, the rulers depofed, and the nation of the Jews deprived
                    of its few remaining privileges. Yet, notwithſtanding theſe private conceſſions
                    made in the council, the members who dreaded to let their ſentiments be known to
                    the people, affect in public to treat our Saviour as an im-poftor. But he who
                    already had demonſtrated the abfurdity of their opinion, who ſuppoſed that his
                    miracles were wrought by Beelzebub prince of the devils, is again ready to
                    confute the ridiculous affertion of thoſe who pretended to ſay that they were a
                    deception. His friend Lazarus was ſtill living at the diſtance of only a few
                    miles, and many of the Jews who had gone to ſee him were ready to atteſt the
                    truth of the report. If the rulers, apprehending the conſequences of the truth,
                    be afraid to know it, and if they are unwilling to go to Bethany, or to ſend for
                    Lazarus and thoſe who were preſent at his reſurrection, our Lord gives them a
                    fair opportunity of detecting his fraud, if there was any ſuch to be found in
                    him. 'Γo preſerve their power, and re-move the jealous ſuſpicion of the Romans,
                    it had been already determined in council to put him to death ; and</p>

                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0138" facs="gri_33125011196389_0144.tif"/>
                <p>our Lord ſoretels that the third day after his death he ſhall riſe from the
                    grave. Here no place was reſerved ſor deception. The ſect of the Phariſees and
                    the chief prieſts are openly warned and put upon their guard ; and, very
                    fortunately for the cauſe of Chriſtianity, this ſingular prediction was not
                    heard with ſcorn, or indeed, if with ſcorn, it was only affected, we know from
                    the ſentiments expreffed in the council, that our Lord was ſecretly dreaded by
                    the rulers ; that his miracles were far from being diſcredited ; and that his
                    predictions, in their private opinion, were not to be flighted. The means
                    accordingly which they employed to prevent, even in the very appearance, the
                    completion of his prophecy, were admirably calculated to remove the ſcruples of
                    the moſt wary and ſceptical inquirers, if their object was only to ſearch after
                    truth. At the next feſtival of the paſs-over, when the ſcheme of Caiaphas was
                    put in execution, and when it was deemed expedient by the council that he ſhould
                    die, to fave the nation from the jealouſy of the Romans ; as a proof of their
                    ſteady loyalty to Rome he was apprehended, was tried as an enemy to her
                    government, was at laſt condemned upon falſe evidence, and ſuſpended on a croſs
                    until they were fully ſ-tisfied of his death. Even after his death, the fpear of
                    a ſoldier was thruſt into his ſide ; and the water that guſhed out with the
                    blood is a proof to thoſe who are acquainted with the ſtructure and economy of
                    living bodies, that he muſt have been ſome time dead.</p>
                <p>After he was taken down from the croſs, a ſeal was put on the door of the
                    ſepulchre in which he was laid, as the beſt check againſt ſecret fraud ; and a
                    guard of ſoldiers was ſtationed around it, as the beſt ſecurity againſt open
                    violence. In ſpite, however, of all theſe precautions, the prediction was
                    accompliſhed ; the angel of God, deſcending from heaven with a countenance like
                    lightning, and with raiment white as ſnow ; the watch ſhake, and become as dead
                    men ; the earth quakes ; the ſtone is rolled from the mouth of the fe-pulchre ;
                    thç angel fits on it, and our Lord comes forth.</p>
                <p>It was in vain for the Jews to allege that his difciples came in the night, and
                    ſtole him away, while the watch were aſleep. Οηε muſt ſmile at theſe puerile
                    aſ-ſertions. How came the diſciples to know that the watch were aſleep ; or what
                    excuſe had the watch for ſleeping, and incurring a puniſhment which they knew ⅛o
                    be capital in the Roman law ? and how came they, in the name of wonder, to be
                    brought as an evidence for thoſe tranſactions that happened at the time when
                    they were aſleep ?</p>
                <p>whatever credit may be given by modern infidels to this ill-framed ſtory, it is
                    paſt diſpute that it had none •among the Jewiſh rulers at the time that it was
                    current. Not long after our Saviour’s reſurrection, the apoſtles were called
                    before the council, and threatened with death for teaching in the name of Jeſus.
                    Their bold-neſs upon that occaſion was ſo provoking to the rulers, that the
                    threat would have been inſtantly put in execu-tion, had not Gamaliel, a doctor
                    of the law of high re-putation, put them in mind of other impoſtors who had
                    periſhed in their attempts to miſlead the people ; and concluded a very ſenſible
                    ſpeech with thefe remarkable words : " And now, I ſay unto you, refrain from
                    theſe men, and let them alone ; for if this counſel, or this work, be of men, it
                    will come to nought j but <hi rend="italic">if</hi> <hi rend="italic">of God,</hi> ye cannot overthrow it, leſt haply ye be found
                    even to light againſt God.” This advice the council followed. But is it poſſible
                    that Gamaliel could have given it, or the council paid the leaſt regard to it,
                    had the ſtory of the diſciples ſtealſhg the body been then credited ? Surely
                    ſome among them would have obſer-ved, that a work or counſel, founded on
                    impoſture and fraud, could not be <hi rend="italic">∕uppojed to be of God,</hi> and they .would unqueſtionably have ſlain the apoſtles.</p>
                <p>The ſtory of ſtealing the body is indeed one of the moſt ſenſeleſs fictions that
                    ever was invented in ſupport of a bad cauſe. our Lord was on earth 40 days after
                    he aroſe. He appeared frequently to his diſciples. He ate and drank in their
                    preſence ; atad when ſome of them doubted, he bade them handle him and ſee that
                    he was not a ſpectre, ſhowed the mark of the ſpear in his fide, and the prints
                    of the nails in his feet and hands. Be-ſides thus appearing to his diſciples, he
                    was ſeen by more than 500 brethren at one time ; all of whom, as well as his
                    diſciples, muſt neceffarily have known him previous to his ſuffering, and could
                    therefore atteſt that he was the perſon who was once dead, but was then alive.
                    Yet for ſtrangers in general, who had not ſeen him previous to his death, and
                    could not therefore iden-tify his perfon after he aroſe, our Lord reſerved many
                    other proofs that were equally convincing. Before his aſcenſion, he bade his
                    difciples wait till they received power, by the Holy Ghoſt deſcending upon them
                    : That then they ſhould be witneffes with him, both in Jeruſalem, and in all
                    Judea, and in Samaria, and unto the uttermoft ends of the earth ; in order that
                    the people of all theſe nations, obſerving the miracles wrought in his name,
                    might themſelves become ocular witneffes that thoſe who preached his
                    reſurrection were warranted to do fo by his authority ; and that this
                    au-thority, on which ſo numerous miracles attended, muſt be divine.</p>
                <p>we intend not here to examine the minute objections and cavils that have been
                    advanced reflecting the truth of this important fact. The kinds, however, we
                    ſhall mention iq general. Some have doubted of our Lord’s reſurrection, as being
                    an event which is not confirmed by general experience, becauſe they imagine that
                    what happens once ſhould happen again, and even repeatedly, in order to be true.
                    Some, taking their own to be pre-ferable ſchemes, have objected to the way in
                    which it happened, and to the manner in which it is narrated.—-Some have
                    imagined, that poſſibly the goſpel hiſtory may be falſe ; that poſſibly the
                    diſciples were very ig-norant, and might be deceived ; that poſſibly, too, they
                    were deep politicians, and a ſet of impoſtors ; and that poffιbly the writings
                    which detected their falſehoods may have been deſtroyed. It is difficult to
                    reaſon, and worſe to convince, againſt this evidence of poſſibilities : but we
                    flatter ourſelves, that to the candid reader it will appear ſuſſiciently
                    overturned in our article Miracle; where it is ſhown that neither clowns nor
                    politicians could have a ted the part that was acted by the apoſtles, had not
                    the reſurrection been an undoubted fact.</p>
                <p>Some of the objectors to it have alſo maintained, that poſſibly there is nothing
                    material without us, that there is nothing mental within us, and that poſſibly
                    the whole world is ideas. This mode of arguing we pretend not to explain ; it is
                    thought by ſome to proceed entirely from a perverſeneſs of mind or diſpofition,
                    whiic in books</p>

                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0139" facs="gri_33125011196389_0145.tif"/>
                <p>of medicine it is always confidered as a ſymptom of dif-eafe, and the patient
                    recommended to be treated in the hoſpital, and not in the academy.</p>
                <p>By his raiſing others, and particulary by riſing himſelf, from the dead, our
                    Saviour demonſtrated that a reſurrection from the dead is poſſible. And on that
                    au-thority, which by his miracles he proved to be divine, he declared to his
                    followers, that there is to be a gene-ral reſurection both of the juſt and of
                    the unjuſt, in-ſtructing his difciples to propagate this doctrine through all
                    nations ; St Paul confeſſing, that if there be no refur-rection of the dead,
                    preaching is vain, and our faith is vain.</p>
                <p>As to the order of fucceſſion in which the dead are to be raiſed, the Scriptures
                    are almoſt filent. St Paul fays, that every man is to riſe in his own order, and
                    that the dead in Chriſt are to riſe firſt: and St John ob-ſerved in his viſion,
                    that the fouls of them which were beheaded for the witneſs of Jeſus, and for the
                    word of God, and which had not worſhipped the beaſt, neither his image, neither
                    had received his mark upon their foreheads, or in their hapds, lived and reigned
                    with Chriſt a thouſand years ; but the reſt of the dead lived not again until
                    the thouſand years<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="34"
                        >Theſe thouſand years formed the happy millenium ſo often mentioned in the
                        ancient fathers ; and the learned Burnet, in his Theory ot the Earth, has
                        endeavoured to prove, that a ſimilar notion prevailed among the Jews. See
                        Millenium.</note> were finiſhed.</p>
                <p>A queſtion that has much oftener agitated the minds of men is, with what fort of
                    bodies are the dead to be raifed ? St Paul has anſwered, with incorruptible and
                    immortal bodies<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="35">our
                        Saviour rofe with the ſame body, both as to ſubſtance and qualities ;
                        becauſe it was neceſſary that his perfon ſhould be known and identified
                        after his reſurrection.</note>. And to ſilence the diſputatious caviller of
                    his day, he illuſtrated his doctrine by the growth of grain. " Thou fool (ſaid
                    he), that which thou ſoweſt, thou ſoweſt not that body that ſhall be, but bare
                    grain, it may chance of wheat or of ſome other grain.” To us it appears very
                    ſurpriſing, that any one who reads this paſſage with the ſlighteſt attention,
                    ſhould perplex himſelf, or diſturb the church with idle attempts to prove the
                    identity of the bodies with which we ſhall die and riſe again at the laſt day.
                    The apoſtle expreſsly affirms, that " fleſh and blood cannot inherit the kingdom
                    of God; that we ſhall all be changed, in a moment, in the twinkling of an eye,
                    at the laſt trump ; that there are celeſtial bodies and bodies terreſtrial ; and
                    that the glory of the celeſtial is one, and the glory of the terreſtrial
                    another.”</p>
                <p>That this implies a total change of qualities, will admit of no diſpute ; but
                    ſtill it has been conſidered as an article of the Chriſtian faith, that we ate
                    to rife with the ſame bodies in reſpect of ſubſtance. what is meant by the
                    identity of ſubſtance, with qualities wholly different, it is not very eaſy to
                    conceive. Perhaps the meaning may be, that our incorruptible bodies ſhall
                    conſiſt oſ the ſame material particles with our mortal bodies, though theſe
                    particles will be differently arranged to produce the different qualities. But
                    as the particles of our preſent bodies are conſtantly changing, and as different
                    particles compoſe the body atdiffeιent times, a queſtion has been put, with what
                    ſet of particles ſhall we riſe? Here a ſingular variety of opinions have been
                    held. Some<note anchored="true" place="margin" type="authorial" n="36"
                        >Leibnitz.</note> contend, that we ſhall riſe with the original ſtamina of
                    our bodies derived from our parents ; ſome are for riſing with that ſet of
                    particles which they had at birth ; ſome with the ſet which they are to have at
                    death ; and ſome with the particles which remain after maceration in water<note
                        anchored="true" place="margin" type="authorial" n="37"><hi rend="italic"
                            >Hody.</hi></note>; though, God knows, that if this maceration be
                    continued long, theſe may ariſe with few or no particles at all. Another query
                    has given much alarm, what if any of theſe particles ſhould enter a vegetable,
                    compoſe its fruit, and be eaten by a man, woman, or a child ? WÎ11 not a
                    diſpute, ſimilar to that apprehended by the Sadducees about the wife of the
                    ſeven brothers, neceffarily follow, whoſe particles are they to be at the
                    reſurrection ? Againſt this confuſion, they truſt that the goodnefs and wiſdom
                    of heaven will take all the proper and neceffary meaſures ; and they even
                    venture to point out a way in which that may be done. A foot deep of earth, they
                    obſerve, in two or three of the counties of England, ſuppoſing each perſon to
                    weigh on an average about ſeven ſtones and a few pounds, would amply ſupply with
                    material bodies 600,000,000 oſ fouls for no leſs a ſpace than 20,000 years<note
                        anchored="true" place="margin" type="authorial" n="38">See <hi rend="italic"
                            >Hody's Resurrection of the same body affected.</hi>
                    </note>; and therefore there ſeems to be no neceffity ſor the vamping up of
                    their old materials to lodge and accommodate new fouls.</p>
                <p>But, unluckily here, the queſtion is not about the poſſibility of keeping the
                    particles of different bodies ſeparate and diſtinct. The queſtion is rather,
                    what have the Scriptures determined on the ſubject ? Now the Scriptures ſay,
                    that the ſpirit returns unto God who gave it. And ſhould it be aſked, in what
                    place does he reſerve it till the reſurrection ? the Scriptures reply, in the
                    place of the dead ; becaufe the foul deſcends into the pit, is redeemed from the
                    grave ; and the ſting of death, the laſt enemy that is to be deſtroyed, ſhall be
                    taken away when the trumpet of God ſhall found : at which time the dead that
                    ſleep in their graves ihall awake, ſhall hear the voice, and ſhall come forth.
                    There is not here ſo much as a word concerning the body ; and therefore it was
                    aſked with what bodies are the dead to be raiſed ? To which it was anſwered, the
                    vile body is to be changed. The body which is, is not the body which ſhall be ;
                    for the incorruptible muſt put on incorruption, and that which is mortal, put on
                    immortality.</p>
                <p>This curious diſcovery of the ſentiments of Scripture we owe to a lay-man, the
                    celebrated Locke ; who, in one of his controversies with the biſhop of
                    worceſter, came to underſtand what he knew not before, namely, that nowhere have
                    the Scriptures fpoken of the reſurrection oi the ſame body in the ſenſe in which
                    it is uſu-ally conceived. The reſurrection of the ſame perſon is indeed promifed
                    ; and how that promiſe maybe fπlfill-ed, notwithſtanding the conſtant change of
                    the particles of the body, has been ſhown in another place. See Metaphysics,
                    Part III. Chap. iii.</p>
                <p>The advocatcs, therefore, for the refurrection of the mortal body, have again
                    been obliged to betake them-ſelves to the lhifts of reaſoning. It is proper, ſay
                    they,</p>

                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0140" facs="gri_33125011196389_0146.tif"/>
                <p>that the fame bodies which have been accomplices in our vices and virtues,
                    ſhould alſo ſhare in our rewards and puniſhments. Now, granting they will, ſhall
                    one ſet of particles be bound for the crimes, or be entitled to receive the
                    rewards, of the animal ſyſtem, ſrom its firſt commencement to its diffolution ?
                    or ſhall every particle ∏fe up ſucceſſively, and receive its dividend of rewards
                    and puniſhments for the vices and virtues that belonged' to the ſyſtern during
                    the time that they were in union with the ſentient principle ? and is the hand
                    that fell in defending a father to be (as is ſuppoſed in ſome of the eaſtern
                    countries) rewarded in heaven ; while the other that ftruck him when the ſon
                    became vicious, is diſmiffed into torments ?</p>
                <p>Finding this hypotheſis ſupported by neither Scripture nor reaſon, they next
                    appeal to the ancient fathers. And they, it is confeffed, are for the
                    reſurrection of the very ſame ſieſlr. But this notion is directly contrary to
                    the Scriptures, which have ſaid, that fleſh and blood are not to inherit the
                    kingdom of God.</p>
                <p>But whatever be the bodies with which the dead are to be raifed at the general
                    reſurrection, all mankind muſt appear in judgment, and receive ſentence
                    accord-ing to the deeds done in the body, without regard, ſo far as we know, to
                    their actions and conduct in the middle ſtate- After this ſentence, the
                    righteous are to enter into celeſtial and eternal joys, and the wicked to fnffer
                    the puniſhments of hell. Theſe puniſhments ſome have ſuppoſed to be everlaſting
                    ; others think, that after ſome temporary puniſhment, the fouls, of the wicked
                    are to be annihilated ; and others imagine, that after doing purgatorial penance
                    for a while in hell, they are to be again received into favour ; inclining to
                    explain the denunciations of the Almighty as a child would do the threatenings
                    of his mother, or a lover the affected chidings of his miftreſs<note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="39">The French
                        convention, whoſe principles are equally new, daring, and deſtructive of all
                        that is decent or of good report, have decided this queſtion in a very
                        ſummary way, by decreeing death to be an eternal ſleep ; a decree equally
                        abſurd in itſelf and fatal in its conſequences. Since this article went to
                        the preſs, however, we have learned, from the moſt reſpectable authority,
                        that wild and abſurd as the opinion is, it has been induſtriouſly propagated
                        in this country, and that in ſome places it has gained ground. The
                        conſequences of this, were it to become general, muſt indeed be baneful
                        beyond all conception; and we ſhall afterwards take occafion to expoſe the
                        opinion and its nefarious conſequences at greater length than it is now
                        poſſible to do in this place. See <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Theology</hi>.</note>.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
