<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0214-03" facs="gri_33125011196389_0220.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>RHIZOPHORA</label>
the mangrove, or <hi rend="italic">Mangle,</hi> in bo-tany : A genus of the monogynia order, belonging to the dodecandria claſs of plants ; and in the natural method ranking under the 12th order, <hi rend="italic">Holoraceœ.</hi> The calyx is quadripartite, the corolla partite; there is one ſeed, very long, and carnous at the baſe. Theſe plants are natives of the Eaſt and weſt Indies, and often grow 40 or 50 feet high. They grow only in water and 011 the banks of rivers, where the tide flows up twice a-day. They preſerve the verdure of their leaves throughout the year. From the loweſt branches iffue long roots, which hang down to the water, and penetrate into the earth. In this poſition they reſemble ſo many arcades, from five to ten feet high, which ſerve to ſupport the body of the tree, and even to advance it daily into the bed of the water. Theſe arcades are ſo cloſely intertwiſted one with another, that they form a kind of natural and tranſparent terrace, raiſed with ſuch ſolidity over the water, that one might walk upon them, were it not that the branches are too much encumbered with leaves. The moſt natural way of propagating theſe trees, is to ſuffer the ſeveral ſlender ſmall filaments which iſſue from the main branches to take root in the earth. The moſt common method, however, is that of laying the ſmall lower branches in baſkets of mould or earth till they have taken root.</p><p>The deſcription juſt given pertains chiefly to a particular ſpecies of mangrove, termed hy the weſt In-</p>
<pb xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0215" facs="gri_33125011196389_0221.tif"/>
<p>dians <hi rend="italic">black mangles,</hi> on account of the brown duſky colour of the wood. The bark is very brown, ſmooth, pliant when green, and generally uſed in the weſt In-dia iſlands for tanning of leather. Below this bark lies a cuticle, or ſkin, which is lighter, thinner, and more tender. The wood is nearly of the ſame colour as the bark ; hard, pliant, and very heavy. It is frequently uſed for fuel, for which purpoſe it is ſaid to Be remark-ably proper: the fires which are made of this wood being both clearer, more ardent and durable than thoſe made of any other materials whatever.—The wood is compact; almoſt incorruptible ; never ſplinters ; is eaſily worked; and were it not for its enormous weight, would be commodiouſly employed in almoſt all kinds of work, as it poſſeſſes every property of good timber. To the roots and branclies of mangroves that are immerſed in the water, oyſters frequently attach themſelves ; ſo that wherever this curious plant is found growing on the ſea-ſhore, oyfter-fiſhing is very eaſy ; as in ſuch cafes theſe ſhell-fifh may be literally ſaid to be gathered upon trees.</p><p>The red mangle or mangrove grows on tlie ſea-ſhore, and at the mouth of large rivers ; but does not advance, like the former, into the water. It generally riſes to the height of 20 or 30 feet, with crooked, knotty branches, which proceed from all parts of the trunk. The balk is ſlender, of a brown colour, and, when young, is ſmooth, and adheres very cloſely to the wood ; but when old, appears quite cracked, and is eaſily detached from it. Under this bark is a ſkin as thick as parchment, red, and adhering cloſely to the wood, from which it cannot be detached till the tree is felled and dry. The wood is hard, compact, heavy, of a deep red, with a very fine grain. The pith or heart of the wood being cut into ſmall pieces, and boiled in water, imparts a very beautiful red to the li-quid, which communicates the ſame colour to wool and linen. The great weight and hardneſs of the wood prevents it from being generally uſed. From the fruit of this tree, which, when ripe, is of a violet colour, and reſembles ſome grapes in taſte, is prepared an agreeable liquor, much eſteemed by the inhabitants of the Caribbee iſſands.</p><p>white mangle, ſo termed from the colour of its wood, grow, like the two former, upon the banks of rivers, but is ſeldom found near the ſea. The bark is grey ; the wood, as we have ſaid, white, and when green, ſupple ; but dries as ſoon as cut down, and be-comes very light and brittle. This ſpecies is generally called <hi rend="italic">rope-mangrove,</hi> from the uſe to which the bark is applied by the inhabitants of the weſt Indies. This bark, which, by reaſon of the great abundance of ſap, is eaſily detached when green from the wood, is beaten or bruiſed betwixt two ſtones, until the hard and woody part is totally ſeparated from that which is ſoft and tender. This laſt, which is the true cortical ſubſtance, is twiſted into ropes of all ſizes, which are exceedingly ſtrong, and not apt to rot in the water.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>