<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-15-r01-0794-01"
                facs="gri_33125011197759_0802.tif" type="entry">

                <p><label>RAMSDEN’S MACHINE</label> <hi rend="italic">ſor Dividing</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">Mathematical Instruments,</hi> is a late invention, by
                    which theſe diviſions can be performed with exceeding great accuracy, ſuch as
                    would formerly have been deemed in</p>
                <p>credible. On difcoveι⅛g the method of conſtruct'ng this machine, its inventor,
                    Mr Ramſdsn of Piccadilly, received 615 1. from the commiſſioners of longitude ;
                    engaging himſelf to inſtruct a certain number of perſons, not exceeding ten, in
                    the method of making and uſing this machine from the 28th october <hi
                        rend="italic"> 1775</hi> to 28th october 1777 : alſo binding himſelf to
                    divide all octants and fextants by the fame engine, at the rate of three
                    ſhillings for each octant, and ſix ſhillings for each braſs ſextant, with
                    Nonius’s diviſions to half minutes, for as long time as the commiffioners ſhould
                    think proper to let the engine remain in his poffeffion» Οί this fum of 615 1.
                    paid to Mr Ramſden, 3001. was given him as a reward for the improvement made by
                    him in diſcovering the engine, and the remaining 315l. for his giving up the
                    property of it to the commiſ-ſioners. The following deſcription of the engine,
                    is that given upon oath by Mr Ramſden himſelf.</p>
                <p>" This engine conſiſts of a large wheel of bell-metaI, ſupported on a mahogany
                    ſtand, having three legs, which are ſtrongly connected together by braces, ſo as
                    to make it perfectly ſteady. Οη each leg of the ſtand is placed a conical
                    friction-pulley, whereon the dividing-wheel reſts : to prevent the wheel from
                    Aiding off the friction-pulleys, the bell-metal centre under it turns in a
                    ſocket on the top of the ſtand.</p>
                <p>" The circumference of the wheel is ratched or cut (by a method which will be
                    deſcribed hereafter) into 2160 teeth, in which an endleſs ſcrew acts. Six
                    revolutions of the ſcrew will move the wheel a ſpace equal to one degree.</p>
                <p>" Now a circle of braſs being fixed on the ſcrew ar-bor, having its
                    circumference divided into 60 parts, each diviſion will conſequently anſwer to a
                    motion of the wheel of 10 ſeconds, ſix of them will be equal to a minute,
                    &amp;c.</p>
                <p>" Several different arbors of tempered ſteel are truly ground into the ſocket in
                    the centre of the wheel. The upper parts of the arbors that ſtand above the
                    plane are turned of various ſizes, to ſuſt the centres of different pieces of
                    work to be divided.</p>
                <p>" when any inſtrument is to be divided, the centre of it is very exactly fitted
                    on one of theſe arbors ; and the inſtrument is fixed down to the plane of the
                    dividing wheel, by means of ſcrews, which fit into holes made in the radii of
                    the wheel for that purpoſe.</p>
                <p>“ The inſtrument being thus fitted on the plane of the wheel, the frame which
                    carries the dividing-point is connected at one end by finger-ſcrews with the
                    frame which carries the endlefs ſcrew ; while the other end embraces that part
                    of the ſteel arbor, which ſtands above the inſtrument to be divided, by an
                    angular notch in a piece of hardened ſteel ; by this means both ends of the
                    frame are kept perfectly ſteady and free from any ſhake.</p>
                <p>" The frame carrying the dividing-point or tracer, is made to ſlide on the frame
                    which carries the endlefs ſcrew to any diſtance from the centre of the wheel as
                    the radius of the inſtrument to be divided may require, and may be there
                    faſtened by tightening two clamps ; and the dividing-point or tracer being
                    connected with the clamps by the double-jointed frame, admits a free and eafy
                    motion towards or from the centre for cutting the diviſions, without any lateral
                    ſhake.</p>
                <p>" From what has been ſaid, it appears, that an in-</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-15-r01-0795" facs="gri_33125011197759_0803.tif"/>
                <p>ſtrument thus fitted on the dividing-wheel may be moved to any angle by the
                    ſcrew and divided circle on its arbor, and that this angle may be marked on the
                    limb of the inſtrument with the greateſt exactneſs by the dividing-point or
                    tracer, which can only move in ■a direct line tending to the centre, and is
                    altogether freed from thofe inconveniences that attend cutting.by means cf a
                    ſtraight edge. This method of drawing lines will alfo prevent any error that
                    might ariſe irom an expanſion or contraction of the metal during the time of
                    dividing,</p>
                <p>. " The ſcrew-frame is fixed on the top of a conical pillar, wlιich turns freely
                    round its axis, and alſo moves freely towards or from the centre of the wheel,
                    ſo that the ſcrew-frame may be entirely guided^ by the frame which connects it
                    with the centre : by this means ∙ any exceπtricity of the wheel and the arbor
                    would not produce any error in the dividing ; and, by a particular contrivance
                    (which will be deſcribed hereafter), the fcrew when preſſed againſt the teeth of
                    the wheel always moves parallel to itfelf ; ſo that a line joining the centre of
                    the arbor and the tracer continued, will always make equal angles with the
                    ſcrew.</p>
                <p>" Figure I. repreſents a perſpective view of the en-gine.</p>
                <p>“ Fig. 2. is a plan, of which ſig. 3. repreſents a ſec-tion on the line <hi
                        rend="sup"> ΠΛ</hi> »</p>
                <p>" The large wheel A is 45 inches in diameter, and has ten radii, each being
                    ſupported by edge-bars, as repreſented in fig. 3· Fheſe bars and radii are
                    con-nected by the circular ring B, 24 inches in diameter and 3 deep ; and, for
                    greater ſtrength, the whole is caſt in one piecc in bell-metal.</p>
                <p>“ As the whole weight of the wheel A reſts on its ring B, the edge-bars are
                    deepeſt where they join it ; and from thence their depth diminiſhes, both
                    towards the centre and the circumference, as repreſented in fig. 3.</p>
                <p>“ The ſurface of the wheel A was worked very even and flat, and its
                    circumference turned true. The ring C, of fine braſs, was fitted very exactly on
                    the circumference of the wheel ; and vvas faſtened thereon with ſcrews, which,
                    after being ſcrewed as tight as poffible, were well rivetted. The face of a
                    large chuck being turned very true and fiat in the lath, the flattened ſurface A
                    of the wheel was faſtened agaſhſt it with hold-faſts ; and the two ſurfaces and
                    circumference of the ring C, a hole through the centre and the plane part round
                    (b) it, and the lower edge of the ring B, were turned at the ſame time.</p>
                <p>“ D is a piece of hard bell-metal, having the hole, which receives the
                    ſteel-arbor (d), made very ſtraight and true. This bell-metal was turned very
                    true on an arbor ; and the face, which reſts on the wheel at (b), was turned
                    very flat, ſo that the ſteel arbor (d} might ſtand perpendicular to the plane of
                    the wheel : this bell-metal was faſtened to the wheel by ſix ſteel ſcrews (1).</p>
                <p>" A braſs ſocket Z is faſtened on the centre of the mahogany ſtand, and receives
                    the lower part of the bell-metal piece D, being made to touch the bell-metal in
                    a narrow part near the mouth, to prevent any obliquity of the wheel from bending
                    the arbor : good fitting is by no means neceſſary. here ; ſince any ſtiake in
                    this ſocket will produce no bad effect, as will appear hereafter when we
                    deſcribe the cutting frame.</p>
                <p>“ The wheel was then put on its ſtand, the lower edge of the ring B reſting on
                    the circumference of three conical friction-pulleys W, to facilitate its motion
                    round its centre. The axis of one of theſe pulleys is in a line joining the
                    centre of the wheel and the middle of the endlefs ſcrew, and the other two
                    placed ſo as to be at equal diſtances from each other.</p>
                <p>" F is a block of wood ſtrongly faſtened to one of the legs of the ſtand; the
                    piece (g) is ſcrewed to the upper ſide of the block, and has half holes, in
                    which the tranſverſe axis (h) turns : the half holes are kept toge-ther by the
                    ſcrews (i).</p>
                <p>" The lower extremity of the conical pillar P termi-nates in a cylindrical
                    ſteel·pin (k), which paſſes through and turns in the tranſverſe axis (h), and is
                    confined by a cheek and ſcrew.</p>
                <p>" To the upper end of the conical pillar is faſtened the frame G, in which the
                    endlefs ſcrew turns : the pivots of the ſcrew are formed in the manner of two
                    fruſtums of cones joined by a cylinder, as repreſented at X. Thefe pivots are
                    confined between half poles, which preſs only on the conical parts, and do not
                    touch the cylindric parts ί the half holes are kept together by ſcrews (a),
                    which may be tightened at any time, to prevent the ſcrew from ſhaking in the
                    frame.</p>
                <p>“ Οη the fcrew-arbor is a ſmall wheel of braſs K, having its outſide edge
                    divided into 60 parts, and numbered at every 6th diviſion with 1, 2, &amp;c.
                    to 10. I he motion of this wheel is ſhown by the index (y) on the ſcrew-frame G.</p>
                <p>" H repreſents a part of the ſtand, having a parallel flit in the direction
                    towards the centre of the wheel, large enough to receive the upper part of the
                    conical braſs pillar P, which carries the ſcrew and its frame : and as the
                    reſiſtance, when the wheel is moved by the endleſs ſcrew, is againſt that ſide
                    of the flit H which is towards the left hand, that ſide of the flit is faced
                    with braſs, and the pillar is preſſed againſt it by a ſteel fpring on the
                    oppoſite ſide <hi rend="italic">i</hi> by this means the pillar is ſtrongly
                    ſupported laterally, and yet the ſcrew may be eaſily preffed from or againſt the
                    circumference of the wheel, and the pillar will turn freely on its axis to take
                    any direction given it by the frame L.</p>
                <p>“ At each corner of the piece I are ſcrews (n) of tempered ſteel, having
                    poliſhed conical points : two of them turn in conical holes in the ſcrew-frame
                    near (o), and the points of the oth¢r two fcrews turn in holes in the piece Qj
                    the ſcrews (p) are of ſteel, which being tightened, prevent the conical pointed
                    ſcrews from unturning when the frame is moved.</p>
                <p>“ L is a braſs frame, which ſerves to connect the end-leſs ſcrew, its frame,
                    &amp;c. with the centre of the wheel : each arm of this frame is terminated
                    by a ſteel ſcrew, that may be paſſed through any of the holes (q) in the piece
                    Q, as the thicknefs of work to be divided on the wheel may require, and are
                    faſtened by the finger-nuts (r).</p>
                <p>" At the other end of this frame is a flat piece of tempered ſteel (b), wherein
                    is an angular notch : when the endleſs ſcrew is preſſed againſt the teeth on the
                    circumference of the wheel, which may be done by turning the ſinger-ſcrew S, to
                    preſs againſt the ſpring (t),</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-15-r01-0796" facs="gri_33125011197759_0804.tif"/>
                <p>this notch embraces and preſſes againſt the ſteel arbor (d). This end of the
                    frame may be raiſed or depreſſed by moving the priſmatic ſlide (u), which may be
                    fixed at any height by the four ſteel-ſcrews (v).</p>
                <p>“ The bottom of this ſlide has a notch (k); whoſe pjane is parallel to the
                    endleſs-ſcrew; and by the point of the arbor (d) reſting in this notch, this end
                    of the frame is prevented from tilting. The ſcrew S is pre-vented from
                    unturning, by tightening the finger-nut (w).</p>
                <p>" The teeth on the circumference of the wheel were cut by the following method :</p>
                <p>" Having conſidered what number of teeth on the circumference would be moſt
                    convenient, which in this engine is 2160, or 360 multiplied by 6, I made two
                    ſcrews of the ſame dimenſions, of tempered ſteel, in the manner hereafter
                    deſcribed, the interval between the threads being ſuch as I knew by calculation
                    would come within the limits of what might be turned off the circumference of
                    the wheel : one of theſe ſcrews, which was intended for ratching or cutting the
                    teeth, was notched acroſs the threads, ſo that the fcrew, when preſſed againſt
                    the edge of the wheel and turned round, cut in the manner of a ſaw. Then having
                    a ſegment of a circle a little greater than 60 degrees, of about the ſame radius
                    with the wheel, and the circumference made true, from a very fine centre, I
                    defcribed an arch near the edge, and ſet off the chord of 60 degrees on this
                    arch. This ſegment was put in the place of the wheel, the edge of it was
                    ratched, and the number of revolutions and parts of the ſcrew contained between
                    the interval of the 60 degrees were counted. The radius was corrected in the
                    proportion of 360 revolu-tions, which ought to have been in 60 degrees, to the
                    number actually found ; and the radius, ſh corrected, was taken in a pair of
                    beam∙compaffes : while the wheel was on the lath, one foot of the compaffes was
                    put in the centre, and with the other a circle was de-ſcribed on the ring ; then
                    half the depth of the threads of the ſcrew being taken in dividers, was ſet from
                    this circle outwards, and another circle was deſcribed cutting this point ; a
                    hollow was then turned on the edge of the wheel of the ſame curvature as that of
                    the ſcrew at the bottom of the threads : the bottom of this hollow was turned to
                    the ſame radius or diſtance from the centre of the wheel, as the outward of the
                    two circles before-mentioned,</p>
                <p>" The wheel was now taken off the lath ; and the bell-metal piece D was fcrewed
                    on as before directed, which after this ought not to be removed.</p>
                <p>" From a very exact centre a circle was deſcribed on the ring C, about √⅛∙ of an
                    inch within where the bottom of the teeth would come. This circle was di-vided
                    with the greateſt exactneſs I was capable of, ſirſt into five parts, and each of
                    theſe into three. Theſe parts were then biſected four times : (that is to ſay)
                    ſuppoſing the whole circumference of the wheel to con-tain 2160 teeth, this
                    being divided into five parts, each would contain 432 teeth; which being divided
                    into three parts, each of them would contain 144 ; and this ſpace biſected four
                    times would givç 72, 36, 18, and $5 ther¢* fore each of the iaſt diviſions would
                    contain nine teeth. But, as I was apprehenſive ſome error might ariſe from
                    quinqueſection and triſcction, in order to examine the accuracy of the
                    diviſions, I deſcribed another circle on the ring C, <hi rend="sub">τ</hi> ⅛
                    inch within the former, and divided it by continual biſections, as 2160, 1080,
                    540, 270, 135, 67r, and 331 ; and as the fixed wire (to be deſcribed preſently)
                    croſſed both the circles, I could examine their agreement at every 135
                    revolutions; (after ratching, could examine it at every 33l) : but, not finding
                    any ſenſible difference between the two ſets of diviſions, I, for ratching, made
                    choice of the former ; and,aβ the coincidence of the fixed wire with an
                    interſection could be more exactly determined than with a dot or diviſion, I
                    therefore made uſe of interſections in both circles before deſcribed.</p>
                <p>" The arms of the frame L were connected by a thin piece of braſs of ∣ of an
                    inch broad, having a hole in the middle of √⅛ of an inch in diameter ; acroſs
                    this hole a ſilver wire was fixed exactly in a line to the centre of the wheel ;
                    the coincidence of this wire with the interſections was examined by a lens <hi
                        rend="sub"> ×</hi> ⅛ inch focus, fixed in a tube which was attached to one
                    of the arms L.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="1"> The
                        interſections are marked for the faite of illuſtration, though properly
                        inviſible, they lying under the braſs plate.</note> Now a handle or winch
                    being fixed on the end of the ſcrew, the diviſion marked 10 on the circle K was
                    ſet to its index, and, by means of a clamp and adjuſting ſcrew for that purpoſe,
                    the interſection mark-ed i on the circle C was ſet exactly to coincide with the
                    fixed wire ; the ſcrew was then carefully preſſed againſt the circumference of
                    the wheel, by turning the finger-ſcrew S ; then, removing the clamp, I turned
                    the ſcrew by its handle 9 revolutions, till the interfec-tion marked 240 came
                    nearly to the wire ; then, un-turning the finger-ſcrew S, I releaſed the ſcrew
                    from the wheel, and turned the wheel back till the interſection marked 2 exactly
                    coincided with the wire, and, by means of the clamp before-mentioned, the
                    diviſion 1 o on the circle being ſet to its index, the ſcrew was preſſed againſt
                    the edge of the wheel by the finger-ſcrew S ; the clamps were removed, and the
                    ſcrew turned nine revolutions till the interſection marked 1 nearly coincided
                    with the fixed wire ; the ſcrew was releaſed from the wheel by unturning the
                    finger-ſcrew S as before, the wheel was turned back till the interſection 3
                    coincided with the fixed wire; the diviſion 10 on the circle being ſet to its
                    index, the ſcrew was preſſed againſt the wheel as before, and the ſcrew was
                    turned 9 revolutions, till the interſection 2 nearly coincided with the fixed
                    wire, and the ſcrew was releaſed ; and I proceeded in this manner till the teeth
                    were marked round the whole circumference of the wheel. This was repeated three
                    times round, to make the impreffion of the ſcrew deeper. I then ratched the
                    wheel round continually in the ſame direction without ever diſengaging the
                    ſcrew; and, in ratching the wheel about 300 times round, the teeth were
                    finiſhed.</p>
                <p>" Now it is evident, if the circumference of the wheel was even one tooth or ten
                    minutes greater than the ſcrew would require, this error would in the firſt in-</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-15-r01-0797" facs="gri_33125011197759_0805.tif"/>
                <p>ſtanee be reduced to <hi rend="sub">τ</hi> J <hi rend="sub">5</hi> ∙ part of
                    a revolution, or twoſeconds and a half ; and theſe errors or inequalities of the
                    teeth were equally diſtributed round the wheel at the diſtance of nine teeth
                    from each other. Now, as the fcrew in ratching had continually hold of ſeveral
                    teeth at the ſame time, and, theſe conſtantly changing, the above-mentioned
                    inequalities ſoon corrected them· ſelves, and the teeth were reduced to a
                    perfect equality. The piece of braſs which carries the wire was how taken away,
                    and the cutting ſcrew was alſo removed, and a plain one (hereafter deſcribed)
                    put in its place : on one end of the ſcrew is a fmall braſs circle, having its
                    edge divided into 60 equal parts, and numbered at every ſixth diviſion, as
                    before-mentioned. Οη the other end of the ſcrew is a ratchet-wheel C, having 60
                    teeth, covered by the hollowed circle (d), which carries two clicks that catch
                    upon the oppoſite ſides of the ratchet when the ſcrew is to be moved forwards.
                    The cylinder S turns on a ſtrong ſteel aιbor F, which paſſes through and is
                    firmly ſcrewed to the piece Y : this piece, for greater firmneſs, is aftached to
                    the ſcrew-frame G by the braces (v) : a ſpiral groove or thread is cut on the
                    outſide of the cylinder S, which ſerves both for holding the firing, and alſo
                    giving motion to the lever J on its centre by means of a ſteel tooth (n), that
                    works between the threads of the ſpiral. I o the lever is attached a ſtrong
                    ſteel pin(m), on which a braſs ſocket (r) turns : this focket paſſes through a
                    flit in the piece (p), and may be tightened in any part of the flit by the
                    finger-nut (f) : this piece ſerves to regu-late the number of revolutions of the
                    ſcrew for each tread of the treadle R.</p>
                <p>" T is a braſs box containing a ſpiral ſpring ; a ſtrong gut is faſtened and
                    turned tnree or four times round the crrcumference of this box ; the gut then
                    paſſes ſeveral times round the cylinder S, and from thence down to the treadle
                    R. Now, when the treadle is preſſed down, the ſtring pulls the cylinder S round
                    its axis, and the clicks catching hold of the teeth on the ratchet carry the
                    ſcrew round with it, till, by the tooth (n) working in the ſpiral groove, the
                    lever J is brought near the wheel (d), and the cylinder ſtopped by the
                    ſcrew-head (x) ſtriking on the top of the lever J ; at the ſame time the ſpring
                    is wound up by the other end of the gut paſſing round the box T. Now, when the
                    foot is taken off the treadle, the ſpring unbending itſelf pulls back the
                    cylinder, the clicks leaving the ratchet and ſcrew at reſt till the piece (t)
                    ſtrikes on the end of the piece (p) : the number of revolutions of the fcrew at
                    each tread is limited by the number of revolutions the cylinder is allowed to
                    turn back before the ſtop ſtrikes on the piece (p).</p>
                <p>“ When the endleſs ſcrew was moved round its axis with a confiderable velocity,
                    it would continue that motion a little after the cylinder S was ſtopped : to</p>
                <p>prevent this, the angular leγer « was made ; that when the lever J comes near
                    to ſtop the ſcrew (x), it, by a ſmall chamfer, preſſes down the piece χ of the
                    angular lever ; this brings the other end ⅛" of the ſame lever forwards, and
                    ſtops the endleſs ſcrew by the ſteel pin μ ſtriking upon the top oſ it : the
                    foot of the lever is raiſed again by a ſmall ſpring preſſing on the biace (v).</p>
                <p>“ D, two clamps, connected by the piece «, ſlide</p>
                <p>one on each arm of the frame L, and may be fixed at</p>
                <p>pleaſure by the four finger-fςrcws <hi rend="sup">r</hi> , which preſs againſt
                    ſteel ſprings to avoid ſpoiljng the arms : the pieçe (q) is made to turn without
                    ſhake between two conical pointed ſcrews (f), which are prevented ſrom
                    untura-ing by tightening the finger-nuts N.</p>
                <p>“ The piece M is made to turn on the piece (q), byp^ the conical pointed ſcrews
                    (ſ) reſting in the hollow cen-ters (e).</p>
                <p>“ As there is frequent occaſion to cut diviſions on inclined planes, for that
                    purpoſe the piece ?, in which the tracer is fixed, has a conical axis at [each
                    end, which turn in half holes : when the tracer is ſet to any inclination, it
                    may be fixed there by tightening the ſteel ſcrews 6.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Deſcription oſ the Engine by which the endleſs ſcrew sſ thÿ
                        Dividing Engine was cut.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="sup">ti</hi> Fig. 9. repreſents this engine of its full dimen, fions
                    feen from one fide.</p>
                <p>“ Fig. 8. the upper fide of the ſame as ſeen from above.</p>
                <p>“ A repreſents a triangular bar of ſteel, to which the triangular holes in the
                    pieces B and C are accurately fitted, and may be fixed on any part of the bar by
                    the ſcrews D∙</p>
                <p>" E is a piece of ſteel whereon the ſcrew is intended to be cut ; which, after
                    being hardened and tempered, has its pivots turned in the form of two fruſtums
                    of c9nes, as repreſented in the drawings of the dividing engine (fig. ç.). Theſe
                    pivots were exactly fitted to the half holes F and T, which were kept together
                    by the ſcrews Z.</p>
                <p>" H repreſents a ſcrew of untempered ſteel, having a pivot I, which turns in the
                    hole K. At the other end of the ſcrew is a hollow centre, which receives the
                    hardened conical point of the ſteel pin M. when this point is fufficiently
                    preſſed againſt the ſcrew, to prevent its ſhaking, the ſteel pin may be fixed by
                    tightening the ſcrews Y.</p>
                <p>" N is a cylindric nut, moveable on the ſcrew H 5 which, to prevent any ſhake,
                    may be tightened by the ſcrews O. This nut is connected with the ſaddle-piece P
                    by means of the intermediate univerſal joint W, through which the arbor of the
                    ſcrew H paſſes. A front view of this piece, with a ſection acroſs the ſcrew
                    arbor, is repreſented at X. This joint is connected with the nut by means of two
                    ſteel flips S, which turn on pins between the cheeks T on the nut N. the other
                    ends of theſe flips S turn in like manner on pin&lt;</p>
                <p>(a) . Οηε axis of this joint turns in a hole in the cock</p>
                <p>(b) , which is fixed to the ſaddle-piece ; and the other turns in a hole (d),
                    made for that purpoſe in the ſame piece on which the cock (b) is fixed. By this
                    means, when the ſcrew is turned round, the ſaddle-piece will ſlide uniformly
                    along the triangular bar A.</p>
                <p>" K is a ſmall triangular bar of well-tempered ſteel, which Aides in a groove of
                    the fame form on the ſaddle-piece P. The point of this bar or cutter is formed
                    to the ſhape of the thread intended to be cut on the endleſs ſcrew. when the
                    cutter is ſet to take proper hold of the intended fcrew, it may be fixed by
                    tightening the fcrew (e), which preſs the two pieces of braſs G upon it.</p>
                <p>“ Having meaſured the circumference of the divi-ding-wheel, I found it would
                    require a ſcrew about one</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-15-r01-0798" facs="gri_33125011197759_0806.tif"/>
                <p>thread in a hundred coarſer than the guide-fcrew H. The wheels on the
                    guide-fcrew arbor H, and that on the ſteel E, on which the fcrew was to be cut,
                    were proportioned to each other to produce that effect, by giving the wheel L
                    198 teeth, and the wheel 200. Theſe wheels communicated with each other by means
                    of the intermediate wheel R, which alſo ſerved to give the threads on the two
                    ſcrews the ſame direction.</p>
                <p>" The ſaddle-piece P is confined on the bar A by means of the pieces (g), and
                    may be made to Aide with a proper degree of tightneſs by the ſcrews (n).”</p>
                <p>For Ramſden’s equatorial or portable obſervatorv, ſee Optics, n <hi rend="sup">0</hi> 102. and Astronomy, n <hi rend="sup">0</hi> 504. See alfo a long
                    account of an equatorial inſtrument made by Mr Ramſden by the direction of Sir
                    George Shuck-burgh in the Philofophical Tranſactions for r 793, art. x. p. 67.
                    In this inſtrument the circle of declinations is four feet in diameter, and may
                    be obſerved nearly to a fccond. The glaſs is placed between ſix pillars, which
                    form the axis of the machine, and turn round by two pivots placed on two blocks
                    of ſtone. See aſſo Barometer.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
