<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0141-01" facs="gri_33125011196389_0147.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>RETIMO</label>, the ancient <hi rend="italic">Rhitymn'm</hi> of Stephen the geographer, and called by Ptolemy <hi rend="italic">Rhiiymna,</hi> is a fine city, lying at one end of a rich and fertile plain, on the north coaſt of the iſland of Candia. It is but a ſmall place, containing ſcarce 6000 inhabitants ; but it is a bi-ſhop’s ſee, and the harbour is defended by a citadel, where a baſhaw reſides. It was taken by the Turks in 1647, and has been in their hands ever ſince. It is about 45 miles from Candia. E. Long. 24. 45. N.Lat. 35.22.</p><p>The citadel, which ſtands on a rock jutting out into the ſea, would be ſufficient for the defence of the city, were it not ſituated at the foot of an high hill, from which it might be cannonaded with great advantage. The harbour is now almoſt ſilled with ſand, and is no longer acceſſible to ſhipping ; nor do the Turks in any meaſure oppυfe the ravages of time, but behold with a careleſs eye the moſt valuable works in a ſtate of ruin. The trench had formerly a vice-conſul at Retimo, to which ſhips uied to repair ſor cargoes of oil ; but they haye been long unable to get into the harbour : to repair which, however, and to revive the commerce of Retimo, would be a moſt uſeful attempt. The plains around the city abound in a variety of productions. Great quantities of oil, cotton, ſaffron, and wax, are produced here ; and they would be produced in ſtill greater quantities if the inhabitants could export their commodities. The gardens oſ Retimo bear the beſt fruits in the iſland ; excellent pomegranates, almonds, piſtacho nuts, and oranges. The apricot-tree, bearing the michmich, the juice of which is ſo delicious, and its flavour ſo exquiiite, is found here. It is a kind of early peach, but ſmaller and more juicy than thofe oſ France,</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>