<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0092-07"
                facs="gri_33125011196389_0098.tif" type="entry">

                <p><label>RESIN</label>, in natural hiſtory, a viſcidjuice oozing either
                    ſpontaneouſiy, or by inciſion, from ſeveral trees, as the pine, fir,
                    &amp;c.— Â premium for ſeveral years has been offered by the London Society
                    for Encouraging Arts, &amp;c. for difcovering a mode of reducing the
                    inflammable quality of refin, ſo as to adapt it to the purpofes of making
                    candles; but no ſuch diſcovery has yet been madc.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Rlaftic</hi> <hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps"> Resin.</hi></hi> See Caoutchouc.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Gum Resin,</hi> a mixture of gum and refin. See Phar∙ Macy,
                    n <hi rend="sup">0</hi> 38.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Red Gum</hi> <hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps"> Resin,</hi></hi> is procured from the red gum tree, or eucalyptus refinifera ; a tree ſo
                    large and lofty as to exceed in fize the Engliih oak. The wood of the tree is
                    brittle, and of little uſe but for firewood, from the large quantity of refinous
                    gum it contains. The tree is diſtinguiſhed by having pedunculated flowers, and
                    an acute or pointed conical calyptra. To obtain the juice from this tree
                    incitions are made in the trunk of it, and ſometimes upwards oſ 60 gallons of
                    red refinous juice have been obtained from one of them. <note anchored="false"
                        place="margin" type="authorial" n="1"><hi rend="italics">White's Voyage,
                            Appendix.</hi></note>"When this juice is dried, it becomes a very
                    powerful aſtringent gum-refin, of a red colour, much reſerabling that known in
                    the ſhops by the name of <hi rend="italic">kino,</hi> and, for all medical
                    purpoſes, fully as efficacious. Mr white ad-miniſtered it to a great number of
                    patients in the dy-ſentery, which prevailed much ſoon after the landing of the
                    convicts, and in no one inſtance found it to fail. This gum-refin diffolves
                    almoſt entirely in ſpirit of wine, to which it gives a blood-red tincture, water
                    diſtblves about one fixth part only, and the watery folu-tion is cf a bright
                    red. Both theſe ſolutions are powerfully aſtringent.”</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Fellow Gum</hi> <hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps"> Resin,</hi></hi> is procured from the yellow re-ſin tree, which is as large as the Engliſh
                    walnut tree. The properties of this r.efin are equal to thoſe of the</p>
                <p>moſt fragrant balſams. It exudes from the bark ſperi-taneouſly, but more readily
                    if incitions are made. The colour of it is yellow, and at firſt it is ſtuid ;
                    but after being inſpiffated in the ſun, it becomes ſolid. When burnt on hot
                    coals, it ſmells like a mixture of balſam of Tolu and benzoin, approaching
                    ſomewhat to ſtorax. <note anchored="false" place="margin" type="authorial" n="2"
                            ><hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi></note>"It is perfectly ſoluble in ſpirit
                    of wine, but not in water, nor even in effential oil of turpentine, unlels it be
                    digeſted in a ſtrong heat. The varniſh which it makes with either is very weak,
                    and of little uſe. with re-fpect to its medicinal qualities, Mr white has found,
                    it, in many caſes, a good pectoral medicine, and very balfamιc. It is not
                    obtainable in io great abundance as the red gum produced by the eucalyptus
                    refinifera. The plant which produces the yellow gum ſeems to be perfectly
                    unknown to botaniſts, but Mr White has communicated no ſpecimens by which its
                    genus or even claſs could be determined.”</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
