<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0053-05" facs="gri_33125011196389_0059.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>REGIMEN</label>
the regulation of diet, and, in a more general fenle, of all the non-naturals, with a view to preſerve or reſtore health. See Abstinence, Aliment, Food, Diet, Drink, and Medicine.</p><p>The viciſſitude of excrciſe and reſt forms alſo a neceffary part of regimen. See Exercise.</p><p>it is beneficial to be at reſt now and then, ’ but more ſo frequently to uſe exerciſe ; becauſe inaction renders the body weak and liſtleſs, and labour ſtrengthens it. But a medium is to be obſerved in all things, and too much fatigue is to be avoided : for frequent and violent exerciſe overpowers the nat ural ſtrength, and waſtes the body ; but moderate exerciſe ought always to be uſed before meals. Now, of all kinds of exerciſe, riding on horfeback is the molt convenient : or if the perſon be too weak to bear it, riding in a coach, or at leaſt in a litter : next follow fencing, playing at ball, running, walking. But it is one of the inconveniences of old age, that there, is ſeldom ſuſſicient ſtrength for uſing bodily exerciſe, though it be extremely requiſtte for health:. wherefore frictions with the fleſh-bruſh are neceffary at this time of life ; which ſhould be performed by the perfon himſelf, if poſſible ; if not, by his ſervants.</p><p>Sleep is the ſweet ſoother of cares, and reſtorer of ſtreifbth ; as it repairs and replaces the waſtes that are made by the labours and exerciſes of the day. But exceſſive ſleep has its inconveniences ; for it blunts the ſenſes, and renders them leſs fit for the duties of life. The proper time for ſleep is the night, when darknefi&gt;-and filence invite and bring it on : day-ſleep is leſs re·· freſhing ; which rule if it be proper ſor the multitude to obſerve, much more is the obſervance of it neceffary for perſons addicted to literary ſtudies, whofe minds and bodies are more fiιfcept⅛le oſ injuries.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Regimen, in grammar, that part of ſyntax, or conſtruction, which regulates the dependency of words, and the alterations which one occaiions in another.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps"> Regimen for Seamen.</hi></hi> See Seamen.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>