<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0030-01" facs="gri_33125011196389_0036.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>RECORD</label>, an authentic teſtimony in writing, con-tained in rolls of parchment,
    and preſerved in a court of record. See Court.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Trial by Record,</hi> a ſpectes of trial which is ufed only
    in one particular inſtance: and that is where a matter of record is pleaded in.
    any action, as a fine, a judgment, or the like ; and the oppoſite party pleads, <hi rend="italic">nul tied record,</hi> that thefe fis no fuch matter of
    record exiſting.. Upon this, iſſue is tendered and joined in the following form,
    " and this he prays may be inquired of by the record, and the other doth the
    like and hereupon the party pleading the record has a day given him to bring it
    in, and proclamation is made in court for him to " bring forth the record by him
    in pleading alleged, or elſe he ſhall be condemned and, on his failure, his
    antagoniſt ſhall have judgment to recover. The trial, therefore, of this iſſue,
    is merely by the record : for, as Sir Edward Coke obſerves, a record or
    enrolment is a monument of ſo high· a nature, and im-porteth in itſelf ſnch
    abſolute verity, that if ſt be pleaded that there is no fuch record, it ſhall
    not receive any trial by witneſs, jury, or otherwiſe, but only by itſelf. Thus
    titles of nobility, as whether earl or not earl, ba-ron or not baron, ſhall be
    tried by the king’s writ or patent only, which is matter of record. Alſo in caſe
    of an alien, whether alien friend or enemy, ſhall be tried by the league or
    treaty between his ſovereign and ours; for every league or treaty is of record.
    And alſo, whether a manor be held in ancient demeſne or not, ſhall be tried by
    the record of domefday in. the king’s exchequer.</p></div></body></text></TEI>