<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0143-04" facs="gri_33125011196389_0149.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>REVEL</label>, a port town of Livonia, ſituated at the ſouth entrance of the gulph of Finland, partly in a plain and partly on a mountain ; 133 miles ſouth-weft of Pe-terſhurg, and 85 ſonth-eaſt of Abo. It is a place of great trade, and holds two Υtrirs yearly, which are vi-ſited by merchants from all countries, but particularly by thoſe oſ England and Holland. It is a ſtrong and a rich place, with a capital harbour. It is ſurrounded with high walls and deep ditches, and defended by a caſtle and ſtout baſtions. It was confirmed to the Swedes at the peace of oliva, conquered by Peter the Great in 1710, and ceded to Ruſſia in 1721. The conqueſt of it was again attempted by the Swedes in 1790. The duke of Sudermania, with the Swediih fleet, attempted to carry the harbour ; but after an ob-ſtinate engagement with the Ruffian fleet, he was obliged to give it up ; but it was but for a very ſhort while. He retired about 10 leagues from the harbour, to repair the damage his fleet had fuſtained, and to prepare for a ſecond attack before any relief could be afforded to the Ruſſian fleet. As ſoon as he had refitted, he failed for the harbour, at a league diſtant from which the Ruſſian fleet was diſcovered, ready to dispute with the Swedes the entrance. Upon a council being held by the Duke, it was reſolved to attack the Ruffians ; and the ſignals being given, the fleet bore down for the attack, which was maintained for near fix hours with the utmoſt fury : at length the Swedes broke the Ruſſian line, which threw them into much confuſion ; when the Swedes, taking the advantage of the general confuſion into which the Ruffians were thrown, followed them with their whole force into the harbour, where the conflict and carnage were dreadful on both ſides, though the Swedes certainly had the worſt of it ; at the fame time that their ſkill and bravery is indiſputable.</p><p>This valuable place was again confirmed to Ruſſia by the peace. The government of Revel or Eſt-honia is one of the diviſions of the Ruffian empire, containing five diſtricts. 1. Revel, on the Baltic ſea.</p><p>2. Baltic-port, about 40 verſts weſtward ſrom Revel.</p><p>3. Habſal, or Hapſal, a maritime town. 4. weiffen-ſtein, on the rivulet Saida, about 80 verſts from Revel. 5. weſenberg, about 100 verſts from Revel, at about an equal diſtance from that town and Naιva.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>