<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0087-05"
                facs="gri_33125011196389_0093.tif" type="entry">

                <p><label>RESEMBLANCE</label>, <hi rend="italic">and</hi>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Dissimilitude</hi>, the relations of likeneſs and
                    difference among objects. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Comparison</hi>.</p>
                <p>The connection that man hath with the beings around him, requires ſome
                    acquaintance with their nature, their powers, and their qualities, for
                    regulating his conduct. For acquiring a branch of knowledge ſo effential to our
                    well-being, motives alone of reaſon and intereſt are not ſuſſicient : nature
                    hath providentially ſuperadded curio-ſity, a vigorous propenſity, which never is
                    at reſt. This propenfity alone attaches ns to every new object<note
                        anchored="true" place="margin" type="authorial" n="1">See <hi rend="italic"
                            >Novelty.</hi></note>; and incites us to compare objects, in order to
                    difcover their differences and reſemblances.</p>
                <p>Reſemblance among objects of the ſame kind, and diſſimilitude among objects of
                    different kinds, are too obvious and familiar to gratify our curiofity in any
                    de-gree : its· gratification lies in diſcovering differences among things where
                    reſemblance prevails, and reſemblances where difference prevails. Thus a
                    difference, in individuals of the ſame kind of plants or animals, is deemed a
                    diſcovery, while the many particulars in which they agree are neglected ; and in
                    different kinds, any reſemblance is greedily remarked, without attending to the
                    many particulars in which they differ,.</p>
                <p>A compariſon of the former neither tends to gratify our curiofity, nor to ſct
                    the objects compared in a ſtronger light : two apartments in. a palace, fimilar
                    in ſhape, fize, and furniture, make feparately as good a figure as when compared
                    ; and the lame obſervation is applicable to, two fimilar compartments in a
                    garden ; on the other hand, oppoſe a regular building to a fall of water, or a
                    good picture to.a towering hill, or even a little dog to a large horſe, and the
                    contraſt will produce no effect. But a reſemblance between objects of different
                    kinds, and a difference between objects of' the ſame kind, have remarkably an
                    enlivening effect. the poets, filch of them as have a juft taſte, draw all their
                    ſtmilies from things that in the main differ widely from the principal ſubject ;
                    and they never attempt a contraſt, but where the things have a common ge-nus,
                    and a reſemblance in the capital circumſtances : place together a large and a
                    ſmall-ſized animal of the fame ſpecies, the one will appear greater, the other
                    leſs, than when viewed feparately : when we oppoſe beauty to deformity, each
                    makes a greater figure by the compariſon. λVe compare the drefs of different
                    nations with curiofity, but without ſurpriſe becauſe, they have no ſuch
                    refemblance in · the capital'parts as to pleaſe us. by contraſting the fmaller
                    parts. But a new cut of a ∩eeve, or of a pocket, enchants by its novelty ; and,
                    in oppoſition to the former faſhion, raiſes ſome degree of ſurpriſe.</p>
                <p>That reſemblance and diſſimilitude have an enliven-</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0088" facs="gri_33125011196389_0094.tif"/>
                <p>ing effect upon objects of ſight, is made ſufficiently evident ; and that they
                    have the ſame effect upon objects of the other ſenſes, is alſo certain. Nor is
                    that law confined to the external ſenſes ; ſor characters contraſted make a
                    greater figure by the oppoſition : Iago, in the tragedy of othello, ſays,</p>
                <p>He hath a daily beauty in his life That makes me ugly.</p>
                <p>The character of a fop, and of a rough warrior, are nowhere more ſucceſsfully
                    contraſted than in J3hake-ſpeare :</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Hotſpur.</hi> My liege, I did deny no prifoners :</p>
                <p>But I remember, when the ſight was done, . when I was dry with rage, and extreme
                    toil,</p>
                <p>Breathleſs and faint, leaning upon my ſword,</p>
                <p>Came there a certain lord, neat, trimly dreſs’d,</p>
                <p>Freſh as a bridegroom ; and his chin, new-reap’d, Show’d like a ſtubble-land at
                    harveſt-home.</p>
                <p>He was perfumed like a milliner ;</p>
                <p>And ſtwixt his finger and his thumb he held</p>
                <p>A pouncet-box, which ever and anon</p>
                <p>He gave his noſe :—-and ſtill he ſmil d and talk d ;</p>
                <p>And as the ſoldiers bare dead bodies by,</p>
                <p>He call’d them untaught knaves, unmannerly,</p>
                <p>To bring a ſiovenly, unhandfome corſe Betwixt the wind and his nobility, with
                    many holiday and lady terms He queſtion’d me : among the reſt, demanded My
                    pris’ners, in your majeſty’s behalf.</p>
                <p>I then, aſl ſmarting with my wounds ; being gall’d To be ſo peſter’d with a
                    popinjay,</p>
                <p>Dut of my grief, and my impatience,</p>
                <p>Anſwer’d, negle&lt;⅛ngly, I know not v⅛hat :</p>
                <p>He ſhould,· or ſhould not ; for hé made me mad,</p>
                <p>To ſee him ſhine ſo briſk, and ſmell fo ſweet,</p>
                <p>And talk ſo like a waiting gentlewoman,</p>
                <p>ΟΙ' guns, and drums, and wounds, ( God ſave the mark! ) And telling me, the
                    ſovereign’ſt thing on earth was parmacity for an inward bruiſe ;</p>
                <p>And that it was great pity, ſo it vvas,</p>
                <p>This villanous ſaltpetre ſhould be digg’d out of the bowels of the harmleſs
                    earth, which many a good, tall fellow had deſtroy’d So cowardly : and but for
                    theſe vile guns,</p>
                <p>He would hrnſelf have been a ſoldier.·--</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Firβ part, Henry</hi> IV. <hi rend="italic">act</hi> t. <hi rend="italic">ſc.</hi> 4</p>
                <p>Paſſions and emotions are alſo enſiamed by compariſon. A man of high rank
                    humbles the byſtanders even to annihilate them in their own opinion : Cæfar,
                    beholding the ſtatue of Alexander, was greatly mortified, that now, at the age
                    of 32, when Alexander died, he had not performed one memorable action.</p>
                <p>Ο11Γ opinions alſo are much influenced by companion. A man whoſe opulence
                    exceeds the ordinary ſtandard is reputed richer than he is in reality ; and
                    wiſdom or weakneſs, if at all remarkable in an individual, is generally carried
                    beyond the truth.</p>
                <p>The opinion a man forms of his preſent diſtreis is heightened by contraſting it
                    with his former happi-neſs :</p>
                <p>______Could I forget</p>
                <p>what I have been, I might the better bear IVhat Γm deſtin’d to. Γm not the ſirſt</p>
                <p>That have been wretched : but to think how much I have been happier.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Southern’s Innocent Adultery, act</hi> 2.</p>
                <p>The diſtreſs of a long journey makes even an indifferent inn agreeable : and, in
                    travelling, when the road is good, and the horſeman well covered, a bad day may
                    be agreeable, by making him ſenſible bow fnug he is.</p>
                <p>The ſame effect is equally remarkable, when a man oppoſes his condition to that
                    of others. A ſhip toſ-ſed about in a ſtorm, makes the ſpectator reflect upon his
                    own eaſe and ſecurity, and puts theſe in the ſtrong-eſt light.</p>
                <p>A man in grief cannot bear mirth ; it gives him a more lively notion of his
                    unhappineſs, and of courſe makes him more unhappy. Satan, contemplating the
                    heauties of the terreſtrial paradiſe, has the following exclamation :</p>
                <p>with what delight could I have walk’d thee round,</p>
                <p>If I could joy in ought, ſwect interchange Οί hill and valley, rivers, woods,
                    and plains,</p>
                <p>Now land, now fea, and ſhores with foreſt crown’d, Rocks, dcns, and caves ! but
                    I in none of theſe Find place or refuge ; and the more I ſee Pleaſures about me,
                    ſo much more I feel Torment within me, as from the hateful ſtege Qf contraries :
                    all good to me becomes Bane, and in heav’n much worſe would be my ſtate.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Paradiſe Loβ, book</hi> 9. ∕. 114,</p>
                <p>The appearance of danger gives ſometimes pleafure, ſometimes pain. A timorous
                    perſon upon the battlements of a high tower, is ſeized with fear, which even the
                    conſciouſnefs of ſecurity cannot diffipate. But upon one of a firm head, this
                    ſituation has a contrary effect : the appearance of danger heightens, by
                    oppoſition, the conſciouſnefs of ſecurity, and conſequently the fatisfaction
                    that ariſes from ſecurity ; here the feeling reſem-bles that above-mentioned,
                    occaſioned by a ſhip labouring in a ſtorm.</p>
                <p>The effect of magnifying or leſſening objects by means oſ compariſon is to be
                    attributed to the in-ſtuence of paſſion over our opinions. This will evidently
                    appear by reflecting in what manner a ſpectator is affected, when a very large
                    animal is for the firſt time pla-ced befide a very ſmall one of the ſame
                    ſpecies. The ſtrſt thing that ſtrikes the mind is the difference between the two
                    animals, which is ſo great as to occaſion ſurpriſe ; and this, like other
                    emotions, magnifying its object, makes ns conceive the difference to be the
                    greateſt that can be : we ſee, or ſeem to ſee, the one animal extremely little,
                    and the other extremely large. The emotion of ſurpriſe ariſing from any unuſual
                    reſemblance, ſerves equally to explain, why at ſirſt view we are apt to think
                    fuch reſemblance more entire than it is in reality. And it muſt be obſerved,
                    that the circumſtances of more and lefs, which are the proper ſubjects of
                    compariſon, raife a perception ſo indiſtinct and vague as to facilitate the
                    effect defcribed ; we have no mental ſtandard of great and little, nor of the
                    feveral degrees of any attribute ; and the mind, thus· unreſtrained, is
                    naturally diſpoſed to indulge its furprife to the utmoſt extent.</p>
                <p>In exploring the operations of the mind, ſome of which are extremely nice and
                    ſlippery, it is ncceffary</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0089" facs="gri_33125011196389_0095.tif"/>
                <p>to proceed with the utmoſt circumfpection : and after all, ſeldom it happens
                    that ſpeculations of that kind afford any fatisfaction. Luckily, in the preſent
                    caſe, our ſpeculations are ſupported by facts and ſolid argument. Firſt, a
                    -ſmall object of one ſpecies oppoſed to a great object of another, produces not,
                    in any degree, that deception which is ſo remarkable when both ob-jects are of
                    the ſame ſpecies. The greateſt diſparity between objects of different kinds, is
                    ſo common as to be obferved with perfect indifference ; but ſuch diſpa-rity
                    between the objects of the fame kind being uncommon, never fails to produce
                    ſurpriſe : and may we not fairly conclude, that ſurpriſe, in the latter caſe, is
                    what occafions the deception, when we ſind no deception in the former ? In the
                    npxt place, if ſurpriſe be the ſole cauſe of the deception, it follows
                    neceffarily that the deception will vaniſh as ſoon as the objects compared
                    become familiar. This holds ſo unerringly, as to leave no reaſonable doubt that
                    ſurpriſe is the prime mover: our ſurpriſe is great, the ſirſt time a ſmall
                    lapdog is ſeen with a large maſtiff ; but when two ſuch animals are conſtantly
                    together, there is no furprife, and it makes no difference whether they be
                    viewed feparately or in company. We ſet no bounds to the riches of- a man who
                    has recently made his fortune ; the ſurpriſing diſproportion between his preſent
                    and his paſt ſituation being carried to an extreme : but with regard to a family
                    that for many generations hath enjoyed great wealth, the ſame falſe reckoning is
                    not made. It is equally remarkable, that a trite ſimile has no effect : a lover
                    compared to a moth ſcorching itfelf at the flame of a candle, originally a
                    ſprightly ſimile, has by frequent ule loft all force ; love cannot now be
                    compared to ſire, without ſome degree of diſguft. It has been juftly obſerved
                    againft Homer, that the lion is too often introduced into his ſimiles ; all the
                    variety he is able to throw into them not being ſufficient to keep alive the
                    reader’s ſurpriſe.</p>
                <p>To explain the influence of compariſon upon the mind, we have choſen the
                    ſimpleft caſe, viz. the ſirſt ſight of two animals of the fame kind, differing
                    in ſize only ; but to complete the theory, other circumſtances muſt be taken in.
                    And the next ſuppoſition we make, is where both animals, feparately familiar to
                    the ſpectator, are brought together for the ſirſt time. In that cafe, the effect
                    of magnifying and dimiiiiſtſing is found remarkably greater than in that ſirſt
                    mentioned ; and the reaſon will appear upon analyſing the operation.; the ſtrft
                    feeling we have is of ſurpriſe at the uncommon difference of two creatures of
                    the ſame ſpecies ; we are next ſenfible, that the one appears leſs, the other
                    larger, than they did formerly ; and that new circumſtance increaſingour
                    ſurpriſe, makes us imagine a ſtill greater oppoſition between the animals, than
                    if we had formed no notion of them beforehand.</p>
                <p>Let us make one other ſuppoſition, that the ſpectator was acquainted beforehand
                    with one of the animals only ; the lapdog, for example. This new circumſtance
                    will vary the effect ; for, inſtead of widening the natural difference, by
                    enlarging in appearance the one animal, and diminifhing the other in proportion,
                    the whole apparent alteration will reft upon the lapdog : the ſurpriſe to ſind
                    it leſs than it appeared formerly, directs to it our whole attention, and makes
                    us conceive it to be a moſt diminutive creature : the maſtiff</p>
                <p>in the mean time is quite overlooked. To illuſtrate this effect by a familiar
                    example. Take a piece of pa-per or of linen tolerably white, and compare it with
                    a pure white of the ſame kind : the judgment we formed of the ſirſt object is
                    inſtantly varied ; and the ſurpriſe occafioned by finding it leſs white than was
                    thought, produceth a haſty conviction that it is much leſs white than it is in
                    reality : withdrawing now the pure white, and putting in its place a deep black,
                    the furpriſe occaſioned by that new circumſtance carries us to the other
                    extreme, and makes us conceive the object ſirſt mentioned to be a pure white :
                    and thus experience compels us to acknowledge, that our emotions have an
                    influence even upon our eye-light. 1 his experiment leads to a general
                    obſervation, that whatever is found more ſtrange and beautiful than was
                    expected, is judged to be more ſtrange and beautiful than it is in reality.
                    Hence a common artifice, to depreciate beforehand what we wiih to make a figure
                    in the opinion of others.</p>
                <p>The companions employed by poets and orators are of the kind laſt mentioned; for
                    it is always a known object that is to be magnified or lefleπed∙ The former is
                    effected by likening it to ſome grand object, or by contrafting it with one of
                    an oppoſite character. To effectuate the. latter, the method muſt be reverfed ⅛
                    the object muſt be contraſted with fomething ſuperior to it, or likened to
                    ſomething inferior. The whole effect is produced upon the principal object ;
                    which by that means is elevated above its rank, or depreffed below it.</p>
                <p>In accounting for the effect that any unufual reſemblance or diffimilſtude hath
                    upon the mind, no canſe has been mentioned but ſurpriſe ; and to prevent
                    confuſion, it was proper to diſcuſs that caufe ſirſt. But ſurpriſe is not the
                    only cauſe of the effect deſcribed ; another occurs, which operates perhaps not
                    leſs powerfully, viz. a principle in human nature that lies ſtill in obſcurity,
                    not having been unfolded by any writer, , though its effects are extenſive : and
                    as it is not diſtinguiſhed by a proper name, the reader muſt be ſatisſied with
                    the following deſcription. Every man who ſtu-dies himſelf or others, muſt be
                    ſenſible of a tendency or propenſity in the mind to complete every work that is
                    begun, and to carry things to their full perfection. There is little opportunity
                    to diſplay that propenſity upon natural operations, which are ſeldom left
                    imperfect ; but in the operations of art it hath great ſcope : it impels us to
                    perſevere in our own work, and to wiſli for the completion of what another is
                    doing : we feel a ſenſible pleaſure when the work is brought to perfection ; and
                    our pain is not leſs fenſible when we are difappointed. Hence our uneaſineſs
                    when an intereſting ſtory is broke off in the middle, when a piece of muſic ends
                    without a cloſe, or when a building or garden is left unſiniihed. The ſame
                    propenſity operates in making collections ; ſuch as the whole works, good and
                    bad, oſ any author. A certain perſon attempted to collect prints of all the
                    capital paintings, and fuc-ceeded except as to a few. La Bruyere remarks, that
                    an anxious ſearch was made for theſe ; not for their value, but to complete the
                    ſet.</p>
                <p>The final cauſe of the propenſity is an additional proof of its exiſtence. Human
                    works are of no ſigni-ſicancy till they be completed ; and reaſon is not always
                    a ſufficient counterbalance to indolence : ſome prin-</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0090" facs="gri_33125011196389_0096.tif"/>
                <p>ciple over and above is neceffary to excite our induſtry, and to prevent our
                    ſtopping ſhort in the middle of the courſe.</p>
                <p>V7e need not loſe time to defcribe the co-operation of the foregoing propenſity
                    with ſnrpriſe, in producing the effect that follows any unuſual reſemblance or
                    diſ-ſimilitude. Surpriſe firſt operates, and carries our opinion of the
                    reſemblance or diſſimilitude beyond truth. The propenfity we have been
                    deſcribing carries us ſtill farther ; for i.t forces upon the mind a conviction,
                    that the reſemblance or diſſimilitude is complete. λVe need no better
                    illuſtration, than the reſemblance that is fancied in ſome pebbles to a tree or
                    an infect ; which reſemblance, however faint in reality, is conceived to be
                    wonderfully perfect. The tendency to complete a reſemblance acting jointly with
                    ſurpriſe, carries the mind ſometimes ſo far, as even to preſume upon future
                    events. In the Greek tragedy entitled <hi rend="italic">Phimides,</hi> thoſe
                    unhappy women feeing the place where it was intended they fhould be ſlain, cried
                    out with anguiſh, <note anchored="false" place="margin" type="authorial" n="2"
                            ><hi rend="italic">Arist. Poet.</hi> cap. 17.</note>"They now saw their
                    cruel deſtiny bad condemned them to die in that place, being the fame where they
                    had been expo-fed in their infancy.”</p>
                <p>The propenfity to advance every thing to its perfection, not only co-operates
                    with ſurpriſe to deceive the mind, but of itſelf is able to produce that effect,
                    of this we ſee many iuſtances where there is no place for ſurpriſe ; and the
                    firſt we ſhall give is of reſem-blance. <hi rend="italic">Unumquodque eodem
                        modo dijſolvitur quo colh-gatum eβ,</hi> is a maxim in the Roman law that
                    has no foundation in truth ; for tying and loôfing, building and demoliſhſhg,
                    are acts oppofite to each other, and are performed by oppofite means : but when
                    tbeſe acts are connected by their relation to the fame ſubject, their connection
                    leads us to imagine a fort of reſem-blance between them, which by tbe foregoing
                    propen-ſity is conceived to be as complete as poſſible. The next inſtance ſhall
                    be of contraſt. Addiſon obferves, <note anchored="false" place="margin"
                        type="authorial" n="3"><hi rend="italic">Spectator,</hi> n<hi rend="sup"
                            >o</hi> 265.</note>"That the paleſt features look the moſt agreeable in
                    white ; that a face which is oveiſtuſhed appears to advantage in the deepeſt
                    ſcarlet ; and that a dark complexion is not a little alleviated by a black
                    hood.” The foregoing propenfity ſerves to account for theſe appearances ; to
                    make this evident, one of the caſes ſhall ſuſſice. A complexion, however dark,
                    never ap-proaches to black : when thefe colours appear together, their
                    oppofition ſtrikes us; and the. propenfity we have to complete the oppofition,
                    makes the dark-neſs of complexion vaniſh out of fight.</p>
                <p>The operation of this propensity, even where there is no ground for surpriſe, is
                    not confined to opinion or conviction : fo powerful it is, as to make us
                    fometimes proceed to action, in order to complete a reſemblance or
                    diſſimilitude. If this appear obſcure, it will be made clear by the following
                    inſtance. Upon what principle is the <hi rend="italic">lex talionis</hi> founded, other than to make the puniſhment referable the miſchief? Reafon
                    dic-tates, that there ought to be a conformity or refem-blance between a crime
                    and its puniſhment ; and the foregoing propenfity impels us to make the
                    reſemblance as complete as poſſible. Titus Livius<note anchored="true"
                        place="margin" type="authorial" n="4">Lib. 1. § 28.</note>, under the
                    influence of that propenfity, accounts for a certain puniſhment by a reſemblance
                    between it and the crime, too ſubtile for common apprehcnſion. Speaking of</p>
                <p>Mettus Fuffetius, the Alban general, who, for treachery to the Romans his
                    alliés, was ſentenced to be torn to pieces by horſes, he puts the following
                    ſpeech in the mouth of Tullus Hoſtilius, who decreed the puniſhment. <hi
                        rend="italic"> " Mette Fuffeû, inquit, ſi ipſe dijeere p <hi rend="sup">r</hi> ffβs ~, fidem ac fœdera ſervare, vivo tibi ea diſciplina a me adhibita
                        effet. Nunc, quoniam tuum infanabile ingenium eβ, at tu tno fupplicio doce
                        humanum genus ea fan id a credere, qux a te violata ſunt. Ut igitur paulo
                        ante animum inter Fi-denatem Romanamque rem ancipιtem geβffβi, itajam corpus
                        -paffim d'βrahendum dabis.”</hi> By the ſame influence, the ſentence is
                    often executed upon the very fpot where the crime was committed. In the <hi
                        rend="italic"> Plectra</hi> of Sophocles, Egiſtheus is dragged from the
                    theatre into an inner room of the ſuppofed palace, to fuffer death where he
                    murdered Agamemnon. Shakeſpeare, whoſe knowledge of nature is not leſs profound
                    than extenfive, has not overlooked this propenfity :</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">" Othello.</hi> Get me ſome poiſon, Iago, this night. I’ll
                    not expoſtulate with her, leſt her body and her beauty unprovide my mind again.
                    This night, Iago.”</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">" Iago.</hi> Do it not with poiſon ; ſtrangle her in her
                    bed, even in the bed ſhe hath contaminated.”</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">“ Othello.</hi> Good, good : the juſtice of it pleafes :
                    very good.” <hi rend="italic">Othello, act A <hi rend="sub">t</hi> ∙fc∙ ξ.</hi></p>
                <p>Perſons in their laſt moments are generally ſeized with an anxiety to be buried
                    with their relations. In the <hi rend="italic">Amynta</hi> of Taffo, the
                    lover, hearing that his miſtreſs was torn to pieces by a wolf, expreffes a
                    deſire to die tbe ſame death.</p>
                <p>Upon the ſubject in general we have two remarks to add. Tlie firſt. concerns
                    reſemblance, which, when too entire, hath no effect, however different in kind
                    the things compared may be. The remark is applicable to works of art only ; for
                    natural objects of different kinds have ſcarce ever an entire reſemblance. To
                    give an example in a work of art : Marble is a fort of matter very different
                    ſrom what compoſes an animal ; and marble cut into a human figure, produces
                    great plea-ſure by the reſemblance : but if a marble ſtatue be co-loured like a
                    picture, the reſemblance is ſo entire as at a diftance to make the ſtatue appear
                    a real perſon : we diſcover the miſtake when we approach ; and no other emotion
                    is raiſed, but ſurpriſe occaſioned by the de-ception : the figure ſtill appears
                    a real perſon, rather than an imitation ; and we muſt uſe reflection to correct
                    the miſtake. This cannot happen in a picture ; for the reſemblance can never be
                    ſo entire as to diſguiſe the imitation.</p>
                <p>The other remark belongs to contraſt. Emotion3 make the greateſt figure when
                    contraſted in ſucceſſion ; but then the ſucceſſion ought neither to be rapid,
                    nor immoderately flow : if too flow, the effect of contraſt becomes faint by the
                    diſtance of the emotions ; and if rapid, no ſtngle emotion has room to expand
                    itſelf to . its full fize, but is ſtiſted, as it were, in the birth by a
                    ſucceeding emotion. The funeral oration of the biſhop of Meux upon the ducheſs
                    of Qrleans, is a perfect hodge-podge of cheerful and melancholy
                    reprefeπ-tations, following each other in the quickeſt ſucceſſion : oppofite
                    emotions are belt felt in ſucceſſion ; but each emotion feparately ſſiould be
                    raiſed to its due pitch, before another be introduced..</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0091" facs="gri_33125011196389_0097.tif"/>
                <p>what is above laid down, will enable us to deter-miiie a very important queftion
                    concerning emotions raiſed by the fine arts, viz. whether ought ſimilar emotions
                    to ſucceed each other, or diſſimilar ? The emotions raiſed by the fine arts are
                    for the moft part too nearly related to make a figure by reſemblance ; and for
                    that reafon their fucceſſion ought to be regu-latcd as much as poſſible by
                    contrail. This holds confcffedly in epic and dramatic compoſitions ; and the
                    belt writers, led perhaps by taſte more than by rea-foning, have generally aimed
                    at that "beauty. It holds equally in muſic : in the ſame cantata all the variety
                    of emotions that are within the power of muſic, may not only be indulged, but,
                    to make the greateſt figure, ought to be contraſted. In gardening, there is an
                    ad-ditional reaſon for the rule : the emotions raiſed by that art, are at beſt
                    ſo faint, that every artifice ſirould be employed to give them their utmoſt
                    vigour : a field may be laid out in grand, ſweet, gay, neat, wild, melancholy
                    ſcenes ; and when theſe are viewed in ſucceſ</p>
                <p>ſion, grandeur ought to be contraſted with neatnefs, regularity with wildneſs,
                    and gaiety with melancholy, ſo as that each emotion may fucceed its oppoſite :
                    nay, it is an improvement to intermix in the fucceſſion rude uncultivated ſpots
                    as well as unbounded views, which in themſelves are diſagreeable, but in
                    ſucceſſion heighten the feeling of the agreeable object ; and we have nature for
                    our guide, which in her moſt beautiful landſcapes often intermixes rugged rocks,
                    dirty marſties, and barren ſtony heaths. The greateſt maſters of mu-ſic have the
                    ſame view in their compoſitions : the fecond part of an Italian ſong ſeldom
                    conveys any ſentiment : and, by lts harſhneſs, ſeems purpoſely contrived to give
                    a greater reliſli for the interefting parts of the compoſition.</p>
                <p>A ſmall garden, comprehended under a fingle view, affords little opportunity for
                    that embelliſhment. Diſſi-milar emotions require different tones of mind ; and
                    therefore in conjunction can never be pleaſant : gai-ety and ſweetneſs may be
                    combined, or wildneſs and gloomineſs ; but a compoſition of gaiety and
                    gloomi-neſs is diſtaſteſul. The rude uncultivated compartment of furze and broom
                    in Richmond garden, hath a good effect in the fucceſſion of objects ; but a ſpot
                    of that nature would be inſufferable in the midſt of a poliſhed parterre or
                    flower-plot. A garden, therefore, if not of great extent, admits not diſſimilar
                    emotions ; and in ornamenting a ſmall garden, the ſafeſt courſe is to confine it
                    to a ſingle expreſſion. For the ſame reafon, a landſcape ought alſo to be
                    confined to a fingle ex-preſſion ; and accordingly it is a rule in painting,
                    that if the ſubject be gay, every figure ought to contribute to that emotion.</p>
                <p>It follows from the foregoing train of reaſoning, that a garden near a great
                    city ought to have an air of ſolitude. The folitarineſs, again, of a waſte
                    country ought to be contraſted in forming a garden ; no temples, no obfcure
                    walks ; but <hi rend="italic">jets d’eau,</hi> caſcades, objects active, gay,
                    and ſplendid.. Nay, fuch a gat den ſhould in ſome meaſure avoid imitating
                    nature, by taking on an ex-traordſhary appearance of regularity and art, to ſhow
                    the buſy hand of man, which in a waſte country has a fine effect by contraſt.</p>
                <p>Wit and ridicule make not an agreeable mixture with grandeur. Diſſimilar
                    emotions have a fine effect in a slow ſucceſſion ; but in a rapid ſucceſſion,
                    which approaches to co-exiſtence, they will not be reliſhed. In the midſt of a
                    laboured and elevated deſcription of battle, virgil introduces a ludicrous
                    image, which is certainly out of its pla"ce :</p>
                <p>obvius ambuſtum torrem Chorinæus ab ara Corripit, ct veπienti Ebυfo plagamque
                    ferenti occupai os fiammis : illi ingens barba relûxit, Nidoremque ambuſta
                    dédit. <hi rend="italic">Æn.</hi> xii. 298,</p>
                <p>E quai tauro ferito, il fuo dolore verfo mugghiando e fofpirando fuore.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Gierufal</hi> cant. 4. ſt. 1.</p>
                <p>It would however be too auſtere to baniſh altogether ludicrous images from an
                    epic poem. This poem doth not always ſoar above the clouds : it admits great
                    variety ; and upon occafion can deſcertd even to the ground without finking. In
                    its more familiar tones, a ludicrous ſcene may be introduced without
                    impropriety. This is done by Virgil<note anchored="true" place="margin"
                        type="authorial" n="5"><hi rend="italic">Eneid,</hi> lib. v.</note> in a
                    foot-race : the circumſtances of which, not excepting the ludicrous part, are
                    copied from Homer<note anchored="true" place="margin" type="authorial" n="6"><hi
                            rend="italic">Iliad,</hi> xxiii. 879.</note>. After a fit of merriment,
                    we are, it is true, the leſs difpoſed to the ferious and fublime : but then, a
                    ludicrous ſcene, by unbending the mind from ſevere application to more
                    intereſting ſubjects, may prevent fatigue, and preſerve our reliſh entire.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
