<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-15-r01-0771-02" facs="gri_33125011197759_0779.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>RABAT</label>
a large and handfome ſea-port town of Africa, in the kingdom of Fez and province of Tremε-fen. It has fine mofques and handſome palaces, and is ſeated at the mouth of the river Burrigrig, almoſt in the mid-way between Fez and Tangier. W. Long. 5. 28. N. Lat. 34. 40.</p><p>Rabat, together with SaHee, which is oppoſite to it, was formerly famous for fitting out piratical veſſels ; but the late emperor Sidi Mahomet ſubdued them both, and annexed them to the empire ; ſince which time the harbour of Rabat has been ſo filled with the ſand waſhed in by the ſea as to render it unfit to carry on ſuch piracies in future.</p><p>The town of Rabat, whoſe walls incloſe a large ſpace of ground, is defended on the ſea-fide by three forts to-lerably well finiſhed, which were erected ſome little time ago by an Engliſh renegado, and furniſhed with guns from Gibraltar. The houſes in general are good, and many of the inhabitants are wealthy. The Jews, who are very numerous in this place, are generally in better circumſtances than thoſe of Larache or Tangier, and their women are extremely beautiful.</p><p>The caſtle, which is very extenſive, contains a ſtrong building, formerly uſed by the late emperor as his prin-cipal treaſury, and a noble terrace, which commands an extenfive proſpect oſ the town of Sallee, the ocean, and all the neighbouring country. There are alſo the ruins of another caſtle, which is ſaid to have been built by Jacob Almonzor, one of their former emperors, and of which at preſent very little remai∏3 but its walls, con-taining within them ſome very ſtrong magazines for powder and naval ſtores. Οη the outſide of theſe walls is a very high and ſquare tower, handſomely built of cut ſtone, and called the tower of <hi rend="italic">Hajfin.</hi> From the workmanſhip of this tower, contraſted with the other buildings, a very accurate idea may be formed how great-ly the Moors have degenerated from their former ſplen-dour and taſte for aιchitecture.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>