<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-15-r01-0773-03" facs="gri_33125011197759_0781.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>RACE</label>
in general, ſignifies running with others in order to obtain a prize, either on foot, or by riding on horſeback, in chariots, &amp;c.</p><p>The race was one of the exerciſes among the an-cient Grecian games, which was performed in a courſe containing 125 paces; and thofe who cβntended in thefe foot-races were frequently clothed in armour. Chariot and horſe races alſo made a part of thefe ancient games.</p><p>Races were known in England in very early times. Fitz-Stephen, who wrote in the days of Henry IT. mentions the great delight that the citizens of London took in the diverfioι‰ But by his words, it appears not to have been deſigned for the purpoſes of gaming, but merely to have ſprung from a generous emulation of ſhowing a fuperior ſkill in horſemanſhip.</p><p>Races appear to have been in vogue in the reign of Queen Elizabeth, and to have been carried to ſuch exceſs as to injure the fortunes of the nobility. The fa-mous George earl of Cumberland is recorded to have wafted more of his eſtate than any of his anceſtors ; and chiefly by his extreme love to horſe-races, tiltings, and other expenſive diverfions. It is probable that the parſimonious queen did not approve of it ; for races are not among the diverfions exhibited at Kennelworth by her favourite Leiceſter. In the following reign, were places allotted for the ſport: Croydon in the fouth, and Garterly in Yorkſhire, were celebrated courſes. Cam-den alſo fays, that in 1607 there were races near York, and the prize was a little golden bell. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Racing.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Race,</hi> in genealogy, a lineage or extraction conti-nued from father to ſon. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Descent.</hi></p>
</div></body></text></TEI>