<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0054-03" facs="gri_33125011196389_0060.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>REGISTER</label>
, a public book, in which are entered and recorded memoirs, acts, and minutes, to be had recourſe to occafionally for knowing and proving matters of fact. Οί theſe there are ſeveral kinds ; as,</p><p>i. Regiſter of deeds in Yorkſhire and Middleſex, in which are regiſtered all deeds, conveyances, wills, &amp;c\ -that affect any lands or tenements in thoſe counties, which are otherwife void againſt any ſubfequent purchafers or mortgagees, &amp;c. but this does not extend to any copyhold eſtate, nor to leaſes at a rack-rent, or where they do not exceed 21 years. The regiſtered memorials muſt be ingroffed on parchment, under the hand and ſcal of ſome of the granters or grantees, at-tefted by witneffes who are to prove the ſigning or ſeal· ing of them and the execution of the deed. But theſe regiſters, which are confined to two counties, are in Scotland general, by which the laws of North Britain are rendered very eaſy and regular. Οί theſe there are two kinds ; the one general, fixed at Edinburgh, under the direction of the lord-regiſter ; and the other is kept in the ſeveral ſhires, ſtewartries, and regalities, the clerks of which are obliged to tranſmit the regiſters of their reſpective courts to the general regiſter.</p><p>2. Pariſſi-regiſters are books in which are regiſtered the baptifms, marriages, and burials, of each pariſli.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Registers were kept both at Athens and Rome, in which were inferted the names of ſuch children as were to be brought up, as foon as they were born. Marcus Aurelius required all free perſons to give in accounts of their children, within 30 days after the birth, to the treaſurer of the empire, in order to their being depofited in the temple of Saturn, where the public acts were kept, officers were alſo appointed aa public regiſters in the provinces, that recourſe might be had to their lifts of names, for ſettling diſputes, or pro-ving any perſon’s freedom.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps"> Register Ships,</hi></hi> in commerce, are veffels which ob-tain a permiſſion either from the king of Spain, or the council of the Indies, to traffic in the ports of the Spaniſh weft Indies ; which are thus called, from their being regiſtered before they ſet ſail from Cadiz for Buenos Ayres.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>