<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-15-r01-0774-03" facs="gri_33125011197759_0782.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>RACK</label>
(Edmund), a perſon well known in the literary world by his attachment to, and promotion of, agricultural knowledge ; he was a native of Norfolk, a Quaker. His education was common, and he was ap-prenticed originally to a ſhopkeeper : his ſociety was ſelect in this ſituation, and by improving himſelf in learning, his converſation was enjoyed by a reſpectable acquaintance. He wrote many eſſays, poems, and letters, and ſome few controverſial tracts. At length he ſettled, about his 40th ye&amp;r, at Bath in 1775, and was ſoon introduced to the molt eminent literati of that place, among whom Dr wilſon and Mrs Macaulay highly eſteemed him for his integrity and abilities. In 1777 hc publiſhed <hi rend="italic">Msator <hi rend="sup">,</hi> s Letters,</hi> a moral work, which has run through many editions. But this year he gained great celebrity by his plan of an agricultural ſociety, which was ſoon adopted by four counties. He ſtill further advanced his fame by his papers in the Far-, mer’s Magazine, and his communications in the Bath So-ciety’s papers ; a work remarkable for its ingenuity and' ſpirit. His laſt engagement was in the Hiſtory of So-merſetſhire, where the topographical parochial furveys were his. Thia work, in 3 vols 4to, was publiſhed in 1791, by his colleague the Reverend Mr Collinſon.—. Mr Rack died of an aſthma in February 1787, aged 52.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Rack,</hi> an engine of torture, furniſhed with pulleys, cords, &amp;c. for extorting confeffion from criminals.— The trial by rack is utterly unknown to the law of England ; though once, when the dukes of Exeter and SuffoIk, and other miniſters of Henry VL had laid a deſign to introduce the civil law into this kingdom as the rule of government ; for a beginning thereof they erected a rack for torture, which was caffed in deriſion the duke of Exeter’s daughter, and ſtill remains in the I ower of London, where it was occafionally ufed aa an engine of ſtate, not of law, more than once in the reign of Queen Elizabeth. But when, upon the aſſaf-ſination orVilliers duke of Buckingham, by Felton, it was propoſed in the privy council to put the aſſaffin to the rack, in order to diſcover his acccomplices} the judges, being conſulted, declared unanimouſly, to their own honour and the honour of the EngIiſh law, that no ſuch proceeding was allowable by the laws of Eng-land, it ſeems aſtoniſhing that this ufage of admink ſtering the torture ſhould be ſaid to ariſe from a tenderneſs to the lives of men ; and yet this is the reaſon given for its introduction in the civil lav/, and its ſubſequent, adoption by the French and other foreign na» tions, viz. becauſe the laws cannot endure that any man ſhould die upon the evidence of a falſe, or even a ſingle witnef⅛, and therefore contrived this method that inno-cence ſhould manifeſt itſelf by a ſtout denial, or guilt by a plain confeffion : thus rating a man's virtue by the hardineſs of his conſtitution, and his guilt by the ſenſi-bility of his nerves, The Marquis Beccaria, in an ex-quifite. piece of raillery, has propoſed this problem, with a gravity and precifion that are truly mathematical :</p><p>" The force of the muſcles and the ſenſibility oif the. nerves of an innocent perſon being given ; it is reqni-red to find the degree of pain aecetΓary to make him</p>
<pb xml:id="eb03-15-r01-0775" facs="gri_33125011197759_0783.tif"/>
<p>eonfeſs himfelf guilty of a given crime.” See <hi rend="italic">Aςτ ef Faith,</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">Inquisition, and Torture.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Rack, a ſpirituous liquor made by the Tartars of Tonguſla. This kind of rack is made of mare’s milk, vſhich is left to be four, and afterwards diſtilled twice or thrice between two earthen pots cloſely ſtopped j whence the liquor runs through a fmall wooden pipe. This'liquor is more intoxicating than brandy diſtilled from wine.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Rack, or</hi> <hi rend="italic">Arack.</hi> See Arack.</p><p><hi rend="italic">To RACK Wines,</hi> £sV. To draw them off from their lees, after having ſtcod long enough to ebb and fettle. Hence rack-vintage is frequently uſed for the iecond voyage our wine-merchants uſe to make into France for racked wines.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>