<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0142-05" facs="gri_33125011196389_0148.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>RETURN</label> <hi rend="italic">(returna</hi> or <hi rend="italic">retorna),</hi> in law, is uſed in divers ſenſes. ι. Return of writs by ſheriffs and bailiffs is a certificate made by them to the court, of what they have done in relation to the execution of the writ directed to them. This is wrote on the back of the writ by the officer, who thus fends the writ back to the court from whence it iffued, in order that it may be filed. 2. Return oſ a commiſſion, is a certificate or anſwer ſent to the court from whence the commiſſion iffues, concerning what has been done by the commiſ-ſioners. 3. Returns, or days in bank, are certain days in each term, appointed for the return of writs, &amp;c. Thus Hillary term has four returns, viz. in the king’s-</p><p>bench, on the day next after the octave, or eighth day after Hillary day : on the day next after the fifteenth day from St Hillary; on the day after purification} and on the next after the octave of the purification. In the common pleas, in eight days of St Hillary : from the day of St Hillary, in fifteen days : on the day after the purification : in eight days of the purification. Eaſter term has five returns, viz. in the king’s-bench, on the day next after the fifteenth day from Eaſter : on the day next after the three weeks from Eafter : on the day next after one month from Eaſter : on the day next after five weeks from Eaſter: and on the day next alter the day following aſcenſton-day. In the common pleas, in fifteen days from the feaſt of Eaſter : in three weeks from the feaſt of Eaſter : in one month ſrom Eaſter day : in five weeks from Eaſter day : on the day after the aſcenſton-day. Trinity term has four re-turns, viz. on the day following the ſecond day after Trinity : on the day following the eighth’day after Trinity : on the day next after the fifteenth day from Tri-nity : on the day next after three weeks from Trinity. In the common pleas, on the day after Trinity : in eight days of Trinity: in fifteen days from Trinity : in three weeks from Trinity. Michaelmas term has fix returns, viz. on the day next after three weeks from St Michael : on the day next after one month of St Michael: on the day following'the ſecond day after All-fouls : on the day next after the ſecond day after St Martin : on the day following the octave of St Martin : on the day next after fifteen days of St Martin. In the common pleas, in three weeks from St Michael : in one month from St Michael : on the day after AU-ſouls : on the day after St Martin : on the octave of St Martin : in fifteen days from St Martin. It is to be obferved, that, as in the king’s-bench, all returns are to be made on ſome particular day of the week in each term, care muſt be taken not to make the writs out of that court returnable on a non-judicial day ; ſuch as Sunday, and All-faints, in Michaelmas term, the purification in Hillary, the afeenfion in Eaſter, and Midſummer-day, except it ſhould fall on the firſt day of Trinity term.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Returns, in a military ſenſe, are of various forts, but all tending to explain the ſtate of the army, regiment, or company ; namely, how many capable of doing duty, on duty, fick in quarters, barracks, infirmary, or hoſpital ; priſoners, abſent with or without leave ; total effective ; wanting to complete the eſtabliſhment, &amp;c.</hi></p>
</div></body></text></TEI>