<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb09-22-s05-0432-04" facs="encyclopediabrit22newyrich_raw_0456.jp2" type="entry"><p><label>SPRENGEL</label>, Kurt (1766-1833), German botanist and physician, was born on 3d August 1766 at Boldekow in Pomerania. His father, a clergyman, provided him with a thorough education of wide scope; and the boy at an early age distinguished himself as a linguist, not only in Latin and Greek, but also in Arabic. He appeared as an author at the age of fourteen, publishing a small work called <hi rend="italic">Anleitung zur Botanik für Frauenzimmer</hi> in 1780. In 1784 he commenced in the university of Halle to study theology and medicine, but soon relinquished the former. He graduated in medicine in 1787. In 1789 he was appointed an extraordinary professor of medicine in his <hi rend="italic">alma mater,</hi> and in 1795 was promoted to an ordinary professorship. He devoted much of his time to medical work and to investigations into the history of medicine; and he published several very valuable works in this department of knowledge, and made himself well known as one of the ablest medical men in Germany. He held a foremost rank in medicine and in botany as an original investigator, and in both published works of great value, besides numerous articles in scientific journals and in the proceedings of learned societies. His accomplishments as a linguist probably, in part at least, determined him in the choice of the department to which he most fully devoted himself, and in which he stood <hi rend="italic">facile princeps.</hi> Among the more important of his many services to the science of botany was the part he took in awakening and stimulating microscopic investigation into the anatomy of the tissues of the higher plants, though defective microscopic appliances rendered the conclusions arrived at by himself unreliable. He also made many improvements in the details of both the Linnæan and the “ natural ” systems of classification. His life passed quietly at Halle in the pursuit of the studies dear to him, and in the enjoyment of the honours bestowed upon him by over seventy learned societies, and also by monarchs. In 1828 the death of a son, professor of surgery at Greifswald, was felt by him very severely. He experienced several apoplectic seizures, and died in one on 15th March 1833.</p><p>Subjoined is a list of the more important of his works :— <hi rend="italic">Beiträge zur Geschichte d. Pulses,</hi> 1787; <hi rend="italic">Galeus Fieberlehre,</hi> 1788; <hi rend="italic">Apologie des Hippokrates,</hi> 1789; <hi rend="italic">Versuch einer pragmatischen Geschichte der Arzneikunde,</hi> 1792-99; <hi rend="italic">Handbuch der Pathologie,</hi> 1795-97; <hi rend="italic">Institutiones Medicæ,</hi> 1809-16 (in 6 vols.); <hi rend="italic">Geschichte der Meclicin,</hi> completed in 1820; <hi rend="italic">Antiquitatum botanicarum specimen,</hi> 1798; <hi rend="italic">Historia rei herbariae,</hi> 1807-8 ; <hi rend="italic">Anleitung zur Kenntniss der Gewächse,</hi> 1802-4, and again 1817-18 ; <hi rend="italic">Geschichte der Botanik,</hi> 1817-18; <hi rend="italic">Von dem Bau und der Natur der Gewächse,</hi> 1812; <hi rend="italic">Flora Halensis,</hi> 1806-15, and in 1832; <hi rend="italic">Species umbelliferarum minus coynitæ,</hi> 1818; <hi rend="italic">Neue Entdeckung im ganzen Umfang der Pflanzenkunde,</hi> 1820-22. He edited an edition of Linnaeus’s <hi rend="italic">Systema vegetabilium</hi> in 1824 and of the <hi rend="italic">Genera plantarum</hi> in 1830. His short papers are too numerous to be quoted ; a list of those in botany, from 1798 onwards, will be found in the Royal Society’s <hi rend="italic">Catalogue of Scientific Papers.</hi></p></div></body></text></TEI>