<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb09-22-s05-0289-04" facs="encyclopediabrit22newyrich_raw_0311.jp2" type="entry"><p><label>SOUTHEY</label>, Caroline (1786-1854), the second wife of Robert Southey, was born at Lymington, Hants, on December 6th, 1786. As a girl Caroline Ann Bowles showed a certain literary and artistic aptitude, the more remarkable perhaps from the loneliness of her early life and the morbidly delicate condition of her health,—an aptitude, however, of no real distinction. When money difficulties came upon her in middle age she determined to turn her talents to account in literature. Her first venture was the sending anonymously of a narrative poem called <hi rend="italic">Ellen Fitzarthur</hi> to Southey, and this led to the acquaintanceship and lifelong friendship which in 1839 culminated in their marriage. <hi rend="italic">Ellen Fitzarthur</hi> (1820) may be taken as typical, in its prosy simplicity, of the rest of its author’s work, which reproduced the studied unadornment of certain portions of Southey’s and Wordsworth’s poetry without that glamour which, especially with the second of these writers, so often redeemed simplicity from mere baldness. Mrs Southey’s poems were published in a collected edition in 1867. Her prose is on the whole more interesting than her verse, though— with rare exceptions—infected with like dulness. Among her prose writings may be mentioned <hi rend="italic">Chapters on Churchyards</hi> (1829), her best work; <hi rend="italic">Tales of the Moors</hi> (1828); and <hi rend="italic">Selwyn in Search of a Daughter</hi> (1835). Her most interesting memorial is her correspondence with Southey, which, somewhat unfairly overlooked in the edition of the poet’s <hi rend="italic">Life and Letters</hi> edited by his son, has been published by Prof. Dowden in the Dublin University Press Series. It was soon after her marriage that her husband’s mental state became hopeless, and from this time till his death in 1843, and indeed till her own, her life was one of much suffering. Mrs Southey died at Buckland Cottage, Lymington, on July 20th 1854, two years after the queen had granted her an annual pension of £200.</p><p>Besides the works already mentioned, she wrote <hi rend="italic">The Widow's Tale, and other Poems,</hi> 1822; <hi rend="italic">Solitary Hours</hi> (prose and verse), 1826; <hi rend="italic">Tales of the Factories,</hi> 1833; <hi rend="italic">The Birthday,</hi> 1836; <hi rend="italic">Robin Hood,</hi> written in conjunction with Southey, at whose death this metrical production was incomplete.</p></div></body></text></TEI>