<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb09-22-s05-0293-01" facs="encyclopediabrit22newyrich_raw_0315.jp2" type="entry"><p><label>SPAIN</label></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Part I.—Geography and Statistics.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Spain</hi>, a country rather more than twice the size of Great Britain including the adjacent small islands, constitutes in its mainland portion about eleven-thirteenths of the Iberian Peninsula, and has in addition an insular area (in the Balearic and Canary Islands) of nearly 5000 square miles. On all sides except that of Portugal the boundaries are natural, the Peninsula being separated from France by the Pyrenees and on every other side being surrounded by the sea. On the side of Portugal a tract of inhospitable country led originally to the separation between the two kingdoms, inasmuch as it caused the reconquest of the comparatively populous maritime tracts from the Moors to be carried out independently of that of the eastern kingdoms, which were also well peopled. The absence of any such means of intercommunication as navigable rivers afford has favoured the continuance of this isolation. The precise line of this western frontier is formed for a considerable length by portions of the chief rivers or by small tributaries, and on the north (between Portugal and Galicia) it is determined to a large extent by small mountain ranges. The British rock of Gibraltar, in the extreme south of the peninsula, is separated from Spain by a low isthmus known as the Neutral Ground. The coast-line on the north and northwest is everywhere steep and cliffy. On the north there are numerous small indentations, many of which form more or less convenient harbours, but the current flowing along the coast from the west often leaves in the stiller water at their mouths obstructive bars. The best harbours are to be found on the <hi rend="italic">rias</hi> or fiord-like indentations in the west of Galicia, where high tides keep the inlets well scoured ; here occur the fine natural harbours of Pontevedra and Vigo, Coruna and Ferrol, the last one of the chief stations of the Spanish fleet. Less varied in outline but more varied in character are the Spanish coasts on the south and east. Flat coasts prevail from the frontier of Portugal to the Straits of Gibraltar. Between the mouth of the Rio Tinto and that of the Guadalquivir they are sandy and lined by a series of sand-dunes (the tract known as the Arenas Gordas). Next follows a marshy tract at the mouth of the Guadalquivir, after which the coast-line becomes more varied, and includes the fine Bay of Cadiz. From the Straits of Gibraltar a bold and rocky coast is continued almost right round to Cape Palos, a little beyond the fine natural harbour of Cartagena. North of Cape Palos a line of flat coast, beginning with the narrow strip which cuts off the lagoon called the Mar Menor from the Mediterranean, bounds half of the province of Alicante, but in its northern half this province, becoming mountainous, runs out to the lofty headland of Cape Nao. The whole coast of the Bay of Valencia is low and ill-provided with harbours ; and along the east of Catalonia stretches of steep and rocky coast alternate with others of an opposite character.</p><p>The surface of Spain is remarkable at once for its striking contrasts and its vast expanses of dreary uniformity. There are mountains rising with Alpine grandeur above the snow-line, but often sheltering rich and magnificent valleys at their base. Naked walls of white limestone tower above dark woods of cork, oak, and olive. In other parts, as in the Basque country, in Galicia, in the Serrania de Cuenca (between the head waters of the Tagus and those of the Jucar), in the Albarracin (between the head waters of the Tagus and those of the Guadalaviar), there are extensive tracts of undulating forest-clad hill country, and almost contiguous to these there are apparently boundless plains, or tracts of level tableland, some almost uninhabitable, and some streaked with canals and richly cultivated—like the Requena of Valencia. While, again, continuous mountain ranges and broad plains and tablelands give the prevailing character to the scenery, there are here and there, on the one hand, lofty isolated peaks, landmarks for a wide distance round, such as Monseny, Monserrat, and Mont Sant in Catalonia, the Pena Golosa in Valencia, Moncayo on the borders of Aragon and Old Castile, and, on the other hand, small secluded valleys, such as those of Vich and Olot among the Catalonian Pyrenees.</p><p>The greater part of the interior of Spain is composed of a tableland bounded by the Cantabrian Mountains in the north and the Sierra Morena in the south, and divided into two by a series of mountain ranges stretching on the whole from east to west. The northern half of the tableland, made up of the provinces of Leon and Old Castile, has an average elevation estimated at about 2700 feet, while the southern half, made up of Estremadura and New Castile, is slightly lower—about 2600 feet. On all sides the tableland as a whole is remarkably isolated, and hence the passes on its boundary and the river valleys that lead up to it from the surrounding plains are geographical features of peculiar importance. The isolation on the side of Portugal, where the tableland gradually sinks to the sea in a succession of terraces, has already been referred to. On the north-west the valley of the Sil and a series of valleys further south, along both of which military roads have been carried from an early period, open up communication between Leon and the hill country of Galicia, which explains why this province was united to Leon even before the conquest of Portugal from the Moors. The passes across the Cantabrian Mountains in the north are tolerably numerous, and four of them are already crossed by railways. The two most remarkable are the Pass of Pájares, across which winds the railway from Leon to Oviedo and the seaport of Gijon, and that of Reinosa leading down to the deep valley of the Besaya, and now crossed by the railway from Valladolid to Santander. In its eastern section the chain is crossed by the railways from Burgos to Bilbao and San Sebastian, the latter of which winds through the wild and romantic gorge of Pancorbo (in the north-east of the province of Burgos) before it traverses the Cantabrian chain at Idiazabal.</p><p>On the north-east and east, where the edge of the tableland sweeps round in a wide curve, the surface sinks on the whole in broad terraces to the valley of the Ebro and the Bay of Valencia, and is crowned here and there by more or less isolated mountains, some of which have been already mentioned. On the north-east by far the most important communication with the Ebro valley is formed by the valley of the Jalon, which has thus always formed a military route of the highest consequence, and which is now traversed by the railway from Madrid to Saragossa. Further south the mountains clustered on the east of the tableland (Albarracin, Serrania de Cuenca) render direct communication between Valencia and Madrid extremely difficult, and the principal communications with the east and south-east are effected where the southern tableland of La Mancha merges in the hill country which connects the interior of Spain with the Sierra Nevada.</p><p>In the south the descent from the tableland to the</p><pb xml:id="eb09-22-s05-0294" facs="encyclopediabrit22newyrich_raw_0316.jp2"/><p>valley of the Guadalquivir is again comparatively gradual, but even here in the eastern half of the Sierra Morena the passes are few, the most important being the Puerto de Despeñaperros, where the Rio Magana has cut for itself a deep gorge through which the railway now ascends from Andalusia to Madrid. Between Andalusia and Estremadura farther west the communication is freer, the Sierra Morena being there broken up into series of small chains.</p><p>Of the mountains belonging to the tableland the most continuous are those of the Cantabrian chain, which stretches for the most part from east to west, parallel to the Bay of Biscay, but ultimately bends round towards the south between Leon and Galicia. Almost everywhere it consists of two parallel ranges, the higher of which, the more southerly, is the immediate continuation of the Pyrenees. The highest summits of the chain belong to the Jura limestones of the Penas de Europa, on the borders of the provinces of Santander, Oviedo, Leon, and Palencia. The highest of all is the Torre de Ceredo, which attains the height of at least 8750 feet, and next is the Pena Prieta (8300 feet). At the sources of the Sil the main chain divides into two branches, enclosing the fertile and thickly-populated district known as El Vierzo, once the bed of a lake, now watered by the stream just mentioned and its tributaries. The whole chain is remarkable for its intricate ramifications and its wild grandeur, but, as already indicated, is not so much of a barrier to communication as might be expected from its general aspect. Besides the railways above mentioned it is crossed at many points by bridle-paths and roads.</p><p>A peculiar feature of the chain and the neighbouring parts of the tableland is formed by the <hi rend="italic">parameras</hi> or isolated plateaus, surrounded by steep rocky mountains, sometimes even by walls of naked rock. Among the larger of these are the bleak districts of Siguenza and Soria, round the headwaters of the Duero,—districts which separate the mountains of the so-called Iberian system on the north-east of the tableland from the eastern portion of the central mountain chains of the peninsula. Of these chains, to which Spanish geographers give the name Carpetano-Vetonica, the most easterly is the Sierra de Guadarrama, the general trend of which is from southwest to north-east. It is the Montes Carpetani of the ancients, and a portion of it (due north of Madrid) still bears the name of Carpetanos. Composed almost entirely of granite, it has an aspect when seen from a distance highly characteristic of the mountains of the Iberian Peninsula in general, presenting the appearance of a sawlike ridge <hi rend="italic">(sierra)</hi> broken up into numerous sections. Its mean height is about 5250 feet, and near its centre it has three summits (the highest named the Pico de Penalara) rising to the height of nearly 8000 feet.</p><p>A region with a highly irregular surface, filled with hills and parameras, separates this sierra from the Sierra de Gredos farther west. This is the loftiest and grandest sierra in the whole series. Its culminating point, the Plaza de Almanzor, attains the height of 8725 feet, not far short of that of the highest Cantabrian summits. Its general trend is east and west ; towards the south it sinks precipitously, and on the north it descends with a somewhat more gentle slope towards the longitudinal valleys of the Tormes and Alberche which separate it from another rugged mountain range, forming the southern boundary of the paramera of Avila. On the west another rough and hilly tract, similar to that which divides it from the Sierra de Guadarrama in the east, separates it from the Sierra de Gata, the westernmost and the lowest of the Spanish sierras belonging to the series. These hilly intervals between the more continuous sierras greatly facilitate the communication between the northern and southern halves of the Spanish tableland. The Guadarrama is indeed crossed by three good pass-roads, and even the Sierra de Gredos has a road across it connecting Avila with Talavera de la Reina by the Puerto del Pico ; but for the most part there are only bridle-paths across the sierras, and up to the present date not a single railway crosses any one of the sierras directly. The only railway crossing the central system of mountains is that from Madrid to Avila, which traverses the interval between the Sierras de Gredos and Guadarrama, passing through numerous tunnels on the way. A railway from Madrid to Segovia to cross the latter sierra at the Puerto de Navacerrada (5830 feet),<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="1"> About 3700 feet above the level of Madrid, 2700 feet above that of Segovia. </note> the pass at present crossed by the principal high road across these mountains, is now (1886) in course of construction.</p><p>On the southern half of the tableland a shorter series of sierras, consisting of the Montes de Toledo in the east (highest elevation 4600 feet) and the Sierra de Guadalupe in the west (highest elevation 5100 feet), separates the basins of the Tagus and Guadiana. The southern system of mountains bounding the Iberian tableland—the Sierra Morena—is even less of a continuous chain than the two systems last described. As already intimated, its least continuous portion is in the west. In the east and middle portion it is composed of a countless number of irregularly-disposed undulating mountains all nearly equal in height.</p><p>Even more important than the mountains bounding or crossing the tableland are those in the north-east and in the south, which are connected with the tableland only at their extremities. The former are the Pyrenees <hi rend="italic">(q.v.),</hi> the latter are the Sierra Nevada, and the coast ranges still farther south. The Sierra Nevada, or “snowy sierra,” is a well-defined chain, between 50 and 60 miles in length, and about 25 miles in breadth, situated to the south of the valley of the Guadalquivir, and stretching from the upper part of the valley of the Jenil in the west to the deep valley of the Almeria in the east. It is composed chiefly of soft micaceous schists, sinking precipitously down on the north, but sloping more gently to the south and south-east. Its culminating summit, the Cerro de Mulahacen (11,660 feet), is the highest in Spain, and the range contains several other peaks upwards of 10,000 feet in height, and above the limit of perpetual snow. On both sides deep transverse valleys <hi rend="italic">(barrancas)</hi> follow one another in close succession, in many cases with round basin-shaped heads, like the <hi rend="italic">cirques</hi> of the Pyrenees. In many of these cirques repose alpine lakes, and in one of them, the Corral de Veleta, there is even a small glacier, the most southerly in Europe. On the south the transverse valleys of the Sierra Nevada open into the mountainous longitudinal valley of the Alpujarras, into which open also on the other side the transverse valleys from the most easterly of the coast sierras, the Sierra Contraviesa and the Sierra de Almijara. The latter are continued farther west by the Sierra de Alhama and Sierra de Abdalajiz. Immediately to the west of the latter sierra lies the gorge of the Guadal-horce, which now affords a passage for the railway from Malaga to Cordova ; and beyond that gorge, to the west and south-west, the Serrania de Ronda, a mountain group difficult of access, stretches out its sierras in all directions. To Spanish geographers the coast ranges just mentioned are known collectively as the Sierra Penibetica. Northeast of the Sierra Nevada two small ranges, Alcaraz and La Sagra, rise with remarkable abruptness from the plateau of Murcia, where it merges in that of the interior.</p><p>The only two important lowland valleys of Spain are those of the Ebro and the Guadalquivir. The former occupies the angle in the north-east between the Pyrenees</p><pb xml:id="eb09-22-s05-0295" facs="encyclopediabrit22newyrich_raw_0317.jp2"/><p>and the central tableland, and is divided by ranges of heights proceeding on the one side from the Pyrenees, on the other from the base of the Moncayo, into two portions. The uppermost of these, a plateau of between 1000 and 1300 feet above sea-level, is only about one-fourth of the size of the remaining portion, which is chiefly lowland, but is cut off from the coast by a highland tract connecting the interior tableland with spurs from the Pyrenees. The Guadalquivir basin is likewise divided by the configuration of the ground into a small upper portion of considerable elevation and a much larger lower portion mainly lowland, the latter composed from Seville downwards of a perfectly level and to a large extent unhealthy alluvium <hi rend="italic">(las marismas).</hi> The division between these two sections is indicated by the change in the course of the main stream from a due westerly to a more south-westerly direction.</p><p>The main water-parting of the peninsula is everywhere near the edge of the tableland on the north, east, and south, and hence describes a semicircle with the convexity to the east. The Ebro alone of the great rivers flows into the Mediterranean. The following table gives the length of the principal Iberian rivers, with the area of their basins,—the length according to different authorities, the area of the basins according to Strelbitsky, whose measurements of area appear to be more trustworthy than those made by him of the length of rivers :—</p><table> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="2"/> <cell cols="3" rows="1"><p>Length in English Miles.</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="2"><p>Area in Square Miles.</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Wagner.</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Ritter.</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Strelbitsky.</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Ebro......................</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>442</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>416</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>470</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>38,580</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Duero (Douro)..........</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>452</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>507</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>485</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>36,710</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Tagus.....................</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"/> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>553</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>566</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>31,865</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Guadiana................</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>510</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>490</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>316</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>25,300</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Guadalquivir............</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>337</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>350</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>374</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>21,580</p></cell> </row> </table><p>With the exception of the Guadalquivir, none of the Iberian rivers is of great service for inland navigation, so far as they lie within the Spanish frontier. On the other hand, those of the east and south are of great value for irrigation, and the Jucar and Segura in the south-east are employed in floating timber from the Serrania de Cuenca.</p><p>The Ebro and Tagus are described in separate articles <hi rend="italic">(q.v.).</hi></p><p>The Mino (Portug. <hi rend="italic">Minho,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Minius</hi> of the Romans) is formed by the union of two small streams in the north of the province of Lugo, and flows first southwards, then on the whole south-westwards to the Atlantic, forming in the lower part of its course the boundary between Spain and Portugal. It becomes navigable for small vessels at Salvaterra, 25 miles above its mouth. Large vessels cannot cross the bar at its mouth. Its only important tributary is the Sil (left), which at the confluence is the larger river of the two.</p><p>The Duero (Portug. <hi rend="italic">Douro,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Durius</hi> of the Romans) emerges from the rock as a small stream among the mountains of Urbion on the borders of the provinces of Logrono and Soria, and, after describing a wide sweep to the east, flows westwards across the northern half of the Spanish tableland and across Portugal. For a distance of nearly 60 miles it forms the boundary between the two countries. It begins to be navigable 80 miles above its mouth, but sea-going vessels ascend only to Oporto, and even so far, on account of a bar at the mouth, only at high tide. The principal tributaries on the right are the Pisuerga and Esla, on the left the Adaja, Tormes, and Coa (the last in Portugal).</p><p>The Guadiana (<hi rend="italic">i.e</hi>., <hi rend="italic">Wádi Ana,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Anas</hi> of the ancients) was long believed to take its rise in the district known as the Campo de Montiel, where a string of small lakes known as the Lagunas de Ruidera (partly in Ciudad Real, partly in Albacete) are connected by a stream which, on leaving the last of them, flows north-westwards towards the Zancara and then disappears within two or three miles of that river. About 22 miles to the south-west of the point of disappearance the stream was believed to re-emerge in the form of several large springs which form a number of lakes at no great distance from the Zancara, and these lakes are hence known as the “eyes of the Guadiana” (<hi rend="italic">los ojos de Guadiana).</hi> The small stream issuing from them is known as the Guadiana and soon joins the Zancara. It has now been ascertained, however, that the stream which disappears higher up can have no such course, but that in fact its waters flow or trickle underground to the Zancara itself, which is therefore entitled to be regarded as the upper Guadiana. It has its source not far from that of the Jucar in the east of the plateau of La Mancha, and flows westwards till, under the name of the Guadiana, it turns south-south-west on the Portuguese frontier. In piercing the Sierra Morena it forms a series of foaming rapids, and it begins to be navigable only at Mertola, about 42 miles above its mouth.</p><p>The Guadalquivir (<hi rend="italic">i.e</hi>., <hi rend="italic">Wádi-el-Kebir,</hi> “the great river,” the <hi rend="italic">Bætis</hi> of the ancients), though the shortest of the great rivers of the Peninsula, is the only one that at all seasons of the year is a full-bodied stream, being fed in winter by the rains, in summer by the melting of the snows on the Sierra Nevada. What is regarded as the main stream rises in the Sierra de Cazorla in the east of the province of Jaen, but it does not become a considerable river till after it is joined by the Guadiana Menor (from the Sierra Nevada), on the left bank and the Guadalimar on the right. Lower down the principal tributary which it receives is the Jenil (left). In the days of the Moors the Guadalquivir was navigable for large vessels to Cordova, but, having been allowed to become silted up in the lower part of its course, it has only recently again been made navigable for vessels of 1200 tons burden to Seville.</p><p>The only considerable lakes in Spain are three coast lagoons,—that of Albufera in the province of Valencia, the Mar Menor in Murcia, and the Laguna de la Janda in Cadiz behind Cape Trafalgar. Small alpine and other lakes are numerous, and small salt lakes are to be found in every steppe region.</p><p>The geological structure of the Spanish Peninsula is comparatively simple. Upon a fundamental platform of ancient crystalline rocks, which had previously been upraised into detached ridges, a series of sedimentary formations was laid down, among which occur representatives of most of the geological systems from the older Palæozoic rocks up to those of Quaternary date. Arranged in order of age, with their respective areas, these various groups of rock are shown in the subjoined table :—</p><table> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="2"><p>Quaternary..................</p><p>Pliocene......................</p></cell> <cell cols="2" rows="1"><p>covering 49,477 sq. kilom., or 10·00 of whole surface</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>„ 9,064</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>,, l∙80</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Miocene and oiigoccne.</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>„ 137,867</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>„ 27∙85 ,,</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Eocene.......................</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>„ 23,564</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>,, 4∙80 ,,</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Cretaceous..................</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>,, 47,002</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>,, 9·50 ,,</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Jurassic......................</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>., 22,697</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>,, 4·45 ,,</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Tπassic.......................</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>,, 22,343</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>,, 4·45</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Carboniferous............</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>„ 11,301</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>„ 2·22</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Devonian...................</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>,, 5.780</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>,, l∙40</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Silurian (and Cambrian)</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>„ 114,382</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>„ 23∙18</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Archæan.....................</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="2"><p>,, 49,665</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>„ 0∙35</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Eruptive rocks of various ages</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>,, 10·00 ,,</p></cell> </row> </table><p>Archæan rocks are exposed in the northern half of the Peninsula, particularly along the great Pyrenean axis, in Galicia, Estremadura, the Sierra Morena, the Sierra Nevada, and Serrania de Ronda. They consist of granites, gneisses, and mica-schists, with talc-schists, amphibolites, and crystalline limestones. The oldest Palæozoic strata are referred, from their included fossils, to the Cambrian and Silurian divisions. They range through a vast region of Andalusia, Estremadura, Castile, Salamanca, Leon, and Asturias, and along the flanks of the Pyrenean and Cantabrian chain. They consist of slates, greywackes, quartzites, and diabases. Grits, quartzites, and shales referable to the Devonian system occur in a few scattered areas, the largest and most fossiliferous of these occurring in the Asturias. The Carboniferous rocks of Spain are divisible into three groups, the lowest consisting of limestones with sandstones and shales, the middle of conglomerates and sandstones, and the upper of sandstones, conglomerates, shales, and coals. They lie in detached basins, and have not yet been well explored. One of these areas covers a considerable space in the Asturias, whence it stretches more or less continuously through the provinces of Leon, Palencia, and Santander, covering altogether an area of 6500 square kilometres. Another tract occurs at San Juan de las Abadesas in Catalonia, where it occupies about 200 square kilometres ; while a third, about 500 square kilometres in extent, runs from the province of Cordova into that of Badajoz. There are other smaller areas containing little or no coal, but showing by the included plant-remains that the strata undoubtedly belong to the Carboniferous system.</p><p>The Triassic system is well developed in the north of the Peninsula along the Cantabrian chain and eastwards to the Mediterranean. It is composed of red and variegated sandstones, dolomites, and marls, traversed in some places by ophitic rocks, and containing deposits of gypsum, aragonite, and rock-salt. These strata are overlain by members of the Jurassic series, which are especially conspicuous in the eastern part of the Peninsula</p><pb xml:id="eb09-22-s05-0296" facs="encyclopediabrit22newyrich_raw_0318.jp2"/><p>between Castile and Aragon, along the Mediterranean border, in Andalusia, and likewise along the flanks of the Pyrenees. The Lias is best represented. The Cretaceous system is distributed in four great districts: the largest of these extends through the kingdoms of Murcia and Valencia ; a second stretches between the two Castiles; a third is found in the Basque Provinces and the Asturias; and a fourth spreads out along the southern slopes of the Pyrenees from Navarre to the Mediterranean. The lower members of the Cretaceous series include an important freshwater formation (sandstones and clays), which extends from the Cantabrian coast through the provinces of Santander, Burgos, Soria, and Logrono, and is supposed to represent the English Wealden series. The higher members comprise massive hippurite limestones, and in the Pyrenean district representatives of the upper subdivisions of the system, including the Danian.</p><p>Deposits of Tertiary age cover rather more than a third of Spain. They are divisible into two great series, according to their mode of origin in the sea or in fresh water. The marine Tertiary accumulations commence with those that are referable to the Eocene series, consisting of nummulitic limestones, marls, and siliceous sandstones. These strata are developed in the basin of the Ebro, and in a belt which extends from Valencia through Murcia and Andalusia to Cadiz. Marine Miocene deposits occupy some small tracts, especially on the coast of Valencia. But most of the sandy Tertiary rocks of that district are Pliocene. The Tertiary masses of Andalusia have coarse conglomerates (Middle Miocene) at their base, followed by thick beds of Bryozoan molasse and younger (Pliocene) beds. These strata are specially noteworthy for containing an important metalliferous deposit, that of the native silver of Herrerias, which is found in a Pliocene bed in the form of flakes, needles, and crystals. But the most extensive and interesting Tertiary accumulations are those of the great lakes which in Oligocene and Miocene time spread over so large an expanse of the tableland. These sheets of fresh water covered the centre of the country, including the basins of the Ebro, Jucar, Guadalaviar, Guadalquivir, and Tagus. They have left behind them thick deposits of clays, marls, gypsum, and limestone, in which numerous remains of the land-animals of the time have been preserved.</p><p>Quaternary deposits spread over about a tenth of the area of the country. The largest tract of them is to be seen to the south of the Cantabrian chain ; but another, of hardly inferior extent, flanks the Sierra de Guadarrama, and spreads out over the great plain from Madrid to Caceres. Some of these alluvial accumulations indicate a former greater extension of the snowfields that are now so restricted in the Spanish sierras. Remains of the reindeer are found in caves in the Pyrenees.</p><p>Eruptive rocks of many different ages occur in different parts of Spain. The most important tract covered by them is that which stretches from Cape Ortegal to Coria in Estremadura and spreads over a large area of Portugal. They likewise appear in Castile, forming the sierras of Gredos and Guadarrama ; farther south they rise in the mountains of Toledo, in the Sierra Morena, and across the provinces of Cordova, Seville, Huelva, and Badajoz as far as Evora in Portugal. Among the minor areas occupied by them may be especially mentioned those which occur in the Triassic districts. Of rocks included in the eruptive series the most abundant is granite. There occur also quartz-porphyry (Sierra Morena, Pyrenees, &amp;amp;c. ), diorite, porphyrite, diabase (well developed in the north of Andalusia, where it plays a great part in the structure of the Sierra Morena), ophite (Pyrenees, Cadiz), serpentine (forming an enormous mass in the Serrania de Ronda), trachyte, liparite, andesite, basalt. The last four rocks occur as a volcanic series distributed in three chief districts—that of Cape Gata, including the south-east of Andalusia and the south of Murcia, that of Catalonia, and that of La Mancha.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Climate.—</hi> In accordance with its southerly position, its differences of elevation, and the variety in its superficial configuration in other respects, Spain presents within its borders examples of every kind of climate to be found on the northern hemisphere, with the sole exception of that of the torrid zone. As regards temperature, the heart of the tableland is characterized by extremes as great as are to be met with in almost any part of central Europe. The northern and north-western maritime provinces, on the other hand, have a climate as equable, and, it may be added, as moist, as that of the west of England or Scotland.</p><p>Four zones of climate are distinguished. The first zone may be called that of the tableland, although to it also the greater part of the Ebro basin may be referred. This is the zone of the greatest extremes of temperature. Even in summer the nights are often decidedly cold, and on the high parameras it is not a rare thing to see hoar-frost in the morning. In spring cold wetting mists occasionally envelop the land for entire days, while in summer the sky is often perfectly clear for weeks together. At all seasons of the year sudden changes of temperature, to the extent of from 30° to 50° F., are not infrequent. The air is extremely dry, which is all the more keenly felt from the fact that it is almost constantly in motion. At Madrid (2150 feet above sea-level) it regularly freezes so hard in December and January that skating is carried on on the sheet of water in the Buen Retiro ; and, as winter throughout Spain, except in the maritime provinces of the north and north-west, is the season of greatest atmospheric precipitation, snowfalls are frequent, though the snow seldom lies long except at high elevations. The summers, on the other hand, are not only extremely warm but almost rainless, the sea-winds being deprived of their moisture on the edge of the plateau. In July and August the plains of New Castile and Estremadura are sunburnt wastes ; the roads are several inches deep with dust ; the leaves of the few trees are withered and discoloured ; the atmosphere is filled with a fine dust, producing a haze known as <hi rend="italic">calina,</hi> which converts the blue of the sky into a dull grey. In the greater part of the Ebro basin the heat of summer is even more intense. The treeless mostly steppe-like valley with a bright-coloured soil acts like a concave mirror in reflecting the sun’s rays, and, moreover, the mountains and highlands by which the valley is enclosed prevent to a large extent the access of winds, and thus hinder the renewal of the air, which in the lowest parts is little disturbed.</p><p>The second zone is that of the Mediterranean provinces, exclusive of those of the extreme south. In this zone the extremes of temperature are less, though the summers here also are warm, and the winters decidedly cool, especially in the north-east.</p><p>The southern zone, to which the name of African has been given, embraces the whole of Andalusia as far as the Sierra Morena, the southern half of Murcia, and the province of Alicante. In this zone there prevails a genuine subtropical climate, with extremely warm and almost rainless summers and mild winters, the temperature hardly ever sinking below freezing-point. The hottest part of the region is not the most southerly district but the bright-coloured steppes of the coast of Granada, and the plains and hill terraces of the south-east coast from Almeria to Alicante. Snow and frost are here hardly known. It is said that at Malaga snow falls only about once in twenty-five years. The winter, in fact, is the season of the brightest vegetation : after the long drought of summer the surface gets covered once more in late autumn with a fresh green varied with bright-coloured flowers, and so it remains the whole winter through. On the other hand, the eastern part of this zone is the part of Spain which is liable to be visited from time to time by the scorching and blasting <hi rend="italic">leveche,</hi> the name given in Spain to the sirocco, as well as by the <hi rend="italic">solano,</hi> a moist and less noxious east wind.</p><p>The fourth zone, that of the north and north-west maritime provinces, presents a marked contrast to all the others. The temperature is mild and equable ; the rains are abundant all the year round, but fall chiefly in autumn, as in the west of Europe generally. Monthly roses bloom in the gardens at Christmas as beautifully and as plentifully as in summer. The chief drawback of the climate is an excess of rain in some parts, especially in the west. Santiago de Compostella, for example, has one of the highest rainfalls on the mainland of Europe (see table below).</p><p>The figures given in the following table (I.),<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="2"> By conversion from Th. Fischer's <hi rend="italic">Klima der Mittelmeerländer.</hi> </note> although based only on data of short periods (from 3/to 20 years), will help to illustrate the preceding general remarks. Greenwich is added for tho sake of comparison.</p><table> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"/> <cell cols="1" rows="1"/> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Height</p></cell> <cell cols="3" rows="1"><p>Mean Temperature, F.</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="2"><p>Rainfall in inches.</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="2" rows="1"/> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>in feet.</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Jan.</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>July.</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Year.</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Tableland</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Leon.............</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>2600</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>37°</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>73°</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>53°</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>19</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>zone</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Madrid..........</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>2150</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>41</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="6"><p>76</p><p>75</p><p>79</p><p>79</p><p>77</p><p>70</p><p>66</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="3"><p>56</p><p>63</p><p>70</p><p>63</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="2"><p>15</p><p>30</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Southern zone</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>San Fernando Malaga..........</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>90</p><p>75</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>52</p><p>54</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Mediterranean</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Murcia..........</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="2"><p>140</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>49</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>14</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="4"><p>zone</p><p>Northern maritime zone</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Mahon..........</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>52</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>64</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="2"><p>27</p><p>46</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Bilbao...........</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>50</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>46</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>58</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Oviedo..........</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>750</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>43</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>54</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>36</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Santiago........</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="2"><p>750</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="2"><p>45∙5</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="2"><p>66</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="2"><p>55</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="2"><p>66</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"/> <cell cols="1" rows="1"/> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"/> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Greenwich......</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>...</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>39</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>63</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>50</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>25</p></cell> </row> </table><p><hi rend="italic">Vegetation.—</hi> The vegetation of Spain exhibits a variety in keeping with the differences of climate just described. The number of endemic species is exceptionally large, the number of monotypic genera in the Peninsula greater than in any other part of the Mediterranean domain. The endemic species are naturally most numerous in the mountains, aud above all in the loftiest ranges, the Pyrenees and the Sierra Nevada ; but it is a peculiarity of the Spanish tableland, as compared with the plains and tablelands of central Europe, that it also possesses a considerable number of endemic plants and plants of extremely restricted range. This fact, however, is also in harmony with the physical conditions above described, being explained by the local varieties, not only of climate, but also of</p><pb xml:id="eb09-22-s05-0297" facs="encyclopediabrit22newyrich_raw_0319.jp2"/><p>soil. Altogether no other country in Europe of equal extent has so great a wealth of species as Spain. According to the <hi rend="italic">Prodromus Floræ Hispanicæ</hi> of Willkomm and Lange (completed in 1880), the number of species of vascular plants then ascertained to exist in the country was 5096.</p><p>Spain may be divided botanically into four provinces, corresponding to the four climatic zones.</p><p>In the tableland province (including the greater part of the Ebro valley) the flora is composed chiefly of species characteristic of the Mediterranean region, generally of species confined to the Peninsula. A peculiar character is imparted to the vegetation of this province by the growth over large tracts of evergreen shrubs and large herbaceous plants belonging to the <hi rend="italic">Cistineæ</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Labiatæ.</hi> Areas covered by plants of the former group are known to the Spaniards as <hi rend="italic">jarales,</hi> and are particularly extensive in the Mancha Alta and on the slopes of the Sierra Morena, where the ladanum bush <hi rend="italic">(Cistus ladaniferus)</hi> is specially abundant ; those covered by plants of the latter group are known as <hi rend="italic">tomillares</hi> (from <hi rend="italic">tomillo,</hi> thyme), and occur chiefly in the south, south-west, and east of the tableland of New Castile. In the central parts of the same tableland huge thistles (such as the <hi rend="italic">Onopordum nervosum),</hi> centaureas, artemisias, and other <hi rend="italic">Composilæ</hi> are scattered in great profusion. From the level parts of these tablelands trees are almost entirely absent. On the lofty parameras of Soria and other parts of Old Castile the vegetation has an almost alpine character.</p><p>The southern or African province is distinguished chiefly by the abundance of plants which have their true home in North Africa (a fact easily understood when we consider the geologically recent land connexion of Spain with that continent), but is also remarkable for the occurrence within it of numerous Eastern plants (natives of Syria and Asia Minor), and plants belonging to South Africa and the Canaries, as well as natives of tropical America which have become naturalized here (see below under <hi rend="italic">Agriculture).</hi> In this province the maritime parts of Malaga and Granada present scenes of almost tropical richness and beauty, while, on the other hand, in Murcia, Alicante, and Almeria the aspect is truly African, fertile oases appearing in the midst of rocky deserts or barren steppes. A peculiar vegetation, consisting mainly of low shrubs with fleshy glaucous leaves <hi rend="italic">(Inula crithmoides,</hi> &amp;amp;c. ), covers the marismas of the Guadalquivir and various parts of the south-west coast where salt-marshes prevail. Everywhere on moist sandy ground are to be seen tall thickets of <hi rend="italic">Arunolo Donax.</hi></p><p>The Mediterranean province is that in which the general aspect of the vegetation agrees most closely with that of southern France and the lowlands of the Mediterranean region generally. On the lower slopes of the mountains and on all the parts left uncultivated the prevailing form of vegetation consists of a dense growth of shrubs with thick leathery leaves, such as are known to the French as <hi rend="italic">maquis,</hi> to the Italians as <hi rend="italic">macchie,</hi> and are called in Spanish <hi rend="italic">monte bajo,</hi><note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="3"> As distinguished from <hi rend="italic">monte alto,</hi> the collective name for forest trees. </note> <hi rend="italic"/>shrubs which, however much they resemble each other in external appearance, belong botanically to a great variety of families.</p><p>The northern maritime province, in accordance with its climate, has a vegetation resembling that of central Europe. Here only are to be found rich grassy meadows adorned with flowers such as are seen in English fields, and here only do forests of oak, beech, and chestnut cover a large proportion of the area. The extraordinary abundance of ferns (as in western France) is likewise characteristic.</p><p>The forest area of Spain generally is relatively small. Tho whole extent of forests is estimated at little more than 3 millions of hectares (7/million acres), or less than 6 per cent. of the area of the kingdom. Evergreen oaks, chestnuts, and conifers are the prevailing trees. The cork oaks of the southern provinces and of Catalonia are of immense value, but the groves containing this tree have suffered greatly from the reckless way in which the product is collected. Among other characteristic trees are the Spanish pine <hi rend="italic">(Pinus hispanica),</hi> the Corsican pine <hi rend="italic">(P. Laricio),</hi> the Pinsapo fir <hi rend="italic">(Abies Pinsapo),</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Quercus Tozza,</hi> the last belonging to the slopes of the Sierra Nevada. Besides the date-palm the dwarf-palm grows spontaneously in some parts of the south, but it nowhere makes up a large element of the vegetation.</p><p>The Spanish steppes deserve a special notice, since they are not confined to one of the four botanical provinces, but are found in all of them except the last. Six considerable steppe regions are counted:—(1) that of Old Castile, situated to the south of Valladolid, and composed chiefly of hills of gypsum ; (2) that of New Castile, in the south-east (the district of La Mancha); (3) the Aragonese, occupying the upper part of the basin of the Ebro ; (4) the littoral, stretching along the south-east coast from Alicante to the neighbourhood of Almeria; (5) the Granadine, in the east of Upper Andalusia (the former kingdom of Granada); and (6) the Bætic, in Lower Andalusia, on both sides of the valley of the Jenil. All of these are originally salt-steppes, and, where the soil is still highly impregnated with salt, have only a sparse covering of shrubs,</p><p>mostly members of the <hi rend="italic">Salsolaceæ,</hi> with thick, greyish green, often downy leaves. A different aspect is presented by the grass steppes of Murcia, La Mancha, the plateaus of Guadix and Huescar in the province of Granada, &amp;amp;c., all of which are covered chiefly with the valuable esparto grass <hi rend="italic">(Macrochloa tenacissima).</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Fauna.—</hi> The Iberian Peninsula belongs to the Mediterranean subregion of the Palæarctic region of the animal kingdom, a division which includes also the north of Africa. The forms that betray African affinities are naturally to be found chiefly in the south. Among the mammals that fall under this head are the common genet <hi rend="italic">(Genetta vulgaris),</hi> which extends, however, pretty far north, and is found also in the south of France, the fallow-deer, the porcupine (very rare), and a species of ichneumon <hi rend="italic">(Herpestes widdringtonii),</hi> which is confined to the Peninsula, and is the only European species of this characteristically African genus. The magot or Barbary ape <hi rend="italic">(Inuus ecaudatus),</hi> the only species of monkey still found wild in Europe, is also a native of Spain, but the only flock still surviving, on the rock of Gibraltar, has often been on the point of extinction, and has to be renewed from time to time by importations from the north of Africa. Of the mammals in which Spain shows more affinity to the fauna of central and northern Europe, some of the most characteristic are the Spanish lynx <hi rend="italic">(Lynx pardinus),</hi> a species confined to the Peninsula, the Spanish hare <hi rend="italic">(Lepus madritensis),</hi> and the species mentioned in the article Pyrenees. The birds of Spain are very numerous, partly no doubt in consequence of the fact that the Peninsula lies in the route of those birds of passage which cross from Africa to Europe or Europe to Africa by way of the Straits of Gibraltar. Many species belonging to central Europe pass the winter in Spain, especially on the south-eastern coasts and in the valley of the Guadalquivir. Innumerable, for example, are the snipes which in that season are killed in the latter district and brought to tho market of Seville. Among the birds of prey may be mentioned, besides the cinereous and bearded vultures, the Spanish vulture <hi rend="italic">(Gyps occidentalis),</hi> the African or Egyptian vulture <hi rend="italic">(Neophron percnopterus),</hi> which is found among all the mountains of the Peninsula, the Spanish imperial eagle <hi rend="italic">(Aguila adalberti),</hi> the short-toed eagle <hi rend="italic">(Circactus gallicus),</hi> the southern eagle-owl <hi rend="italic">(Bubo atheniensis),</hi> besides various kites and falcons. Among gallinaceous birds, besides the red-legged partridge, which is met with everywhere on the steppes, there are found also the <hi rend="italic">Pterocles alchita</hi> and <hi rend="italic">P. arenarius</hi>; and from among the birds of other orders the-southern shrike <hi rend="italic">(Lanius meridionalis),</hi> the Spanish sparrow <hi rend="italic">(Passer cyaneus),</hi> and the blue magpie <hi rend="italic">(Cyanopica cooki)</hi> may be singled out as worthy of mention. The last is highly remarkable on account of its distribution, it being confined to Spain while the species most closely allied to it <hi rend="italic">(Cyanopica cyanea)</hi> belongs to the east of Asia. The flamingo is found native in the Balearic Islands and on the southern coasts, and occasionally a stray specimen is to be seen on the tableland of New Castile. Other birds peculiar to the south are two species of quails, the Andalusian hemipode <hi rend="italic">(Turnix sylvatica),</hi> confined to the plains of Andalusia, the southern shearwater <hi rend="italic">(Puffinus cinereuts),</hi> and other water-birds. Amphibians and reptiles are particularly numerous in the southern provinces, and among these the most remarkable are the large southern or eyed lizard <hi rend="italic">(Lacerta ocellata),</hi> which sometimes attains 3 feet in length and is very abundant, the <hi rend="italic">Platydactylus saccicularis,</hi> the. grey amphisbaena <hi rend="italic">(Blanus cinereus),</hi> the European pond-tortoise <hi rend="italic">(Emys europæa),</hi> aud another species, <hi rend="italic">Ernys siegrizii.</hi> Insect life is remarkably abundant and varied. More than 350 species of butterflies, many of them endemic, have been counted in the province of Madrid alone. Besides the ordinary European scorpion, which is generally distributed in southern Europe, there is another species, the sting of which is said to be still more severe, found chiefly in the basin of the Ebro. Trout abound in the mountain streams and lakes, barbel and many other species of <hi rend="italic">Cyprinidæ</hi> in the rivers of the plains. For the sea fauna, see under <hi rend="italic">Fisheries</hi> below.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Extent.—</hi> The total area of the mainland of Spain, according to the calculations of Strelbitsky, is 495,612 square kilometres or 191,365 square miles, that of the Balearic Islands 4982 square kilometres or 1923 square miles, and that of the Canary Islands, which, though belonging geographically to Africa, are administratively associated with the kingdom of Spain, 7611 square kilometres or 2939 square miles ; so that the total area of the kingdom is 508,205 square kilometres or 196,225 square miles. This total agrees pretty closely with that in Justus Perthes’s table given below (Table II.), although considerable differences will be observed in the areas assigned to the mainland provinces and the two island groups respectively. The length of the coast-line of the mainland, according to Strelbitsky, is 2662 miles, which is equivalent to 1 mile of coast for every 72 square miles of area, about the same proportion as in France. The greatest length from north-east to south-west is 420 miles.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Territorial Divisions and Population.—</hi> For administrative purposes the kingdom of Spain has since 1833 been divided into forty-nine provinces, forty-seven of which belong to the mainland.</p><pb xml:id="eb09-22-s05-0298" facs="encyclopediabrit22newyrich_raw_0320.jp2"/><p>Before 1833 the mainland was divided into thirteen provinces, also enumerated below, which took their names from the ancient kingdoms and principalities out of which the modern kingdom was gradually built up. The present provinces are subdivided into judicial districts (<hi rend="italic">partidos judiciales)</hi> and communes (<hi rend="italic">ayuntamientos).</hi></p><p>It is probable that the population of Spain attained its highest development during the period of the early Roman empire, when it has been estimated, though of course on imperfect data, to have numbered forty or fifty millions. The best evidence of a dense population in those days is that afforded by the specific estimates of ancient writers for some of the larger cities. The population of Tarraco (Tarragona) was estimated at 2/millions, and that of Nova Carthago (Cartagena), Italica (Sevilla la Vieja), and others at several hundreds of thousands. Emerita Augusta (Merida) had a Roman garrison of 90,000 men, which also implies a large population.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="4"> Garrido, <hi rend="italic">La Esρana Contemporanea,</hi> i. 489. </note></p><p><hi rend="italic">Table II.—Area and Population of the Former and Present Provinces</hi></p><table> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Provinces.</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Area in Square Miles.</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Population</p><p>1857.</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Population Dec. 31, 1877.</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Increase</p><p>or</p><p>Decrease.</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Pop. per sq. m. 1877.</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p><hi rend="smallcaps">New Castile.............</hi></p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>28,018</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>1,477,915</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>1,627,131</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>+ 10·1</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>58</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Madrid...................</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>2,997</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>475,785</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>594,194</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>+ 24∙8</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>198</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Guadalajara............</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>4,869</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>199,088</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>201,288</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>+ 1·1</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>41</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Toledo....................</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>5,586</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>328,755</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>335,038</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>+ 1∙8</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>60</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Cuenca...................</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="2"><p>6,726</p><p>7,840</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="2"><p>229,959</p><p>244,328</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>236,253</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="2"><p>+ 3∙3 + 6∙6</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>34</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Ciudad Real............</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>260,358</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>33</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Old Castile..............</hi></p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>25,409</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>1,609,948</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>1,654,718</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>+ 2∙8</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>65</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Burgos...................</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>5,65l</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>333.356</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>332,625</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>- 0∙2</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>59</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Logroiio.................</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>1,945</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>173,812</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>174,425</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>+ 0∙4</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>89</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Santander...............</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>2,112</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>214,441</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>235,299</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>+ 9∙7</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>111</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Avila......................</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>2,982</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>164,039</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>180,436</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>+ 10·0</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>60</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Segovia..................</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>2,714</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>146,839</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>150,052</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>+ 2·1</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>55</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Soria......................</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>3,836</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>147,468</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>153,652</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>+ 4∙2</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>40</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Palencia..................</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>3,126</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>185,970</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>180,771</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>- 2·8</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>58</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Valladolid..............</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>3,043</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>244,023</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>247,458</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>+ 1∙4</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>80</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Asturias..................</hi></p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>4,091</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>524,529</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>576,352</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>+ 9 <hi rend="sup">,</hi> 9</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>140</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Oviedo...................</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>4,091</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>524,529</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>576,352</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>+ 9∙9</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>140</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Leon........................</hi></p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>15,242</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>861,434</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>885,625</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>+ 3∙0</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>57</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Salamanca..............</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>4,940</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>263,516</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>285.695</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>+ 8∙3</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>5S</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Zamora..................</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>4,135</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>249.162</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>249,720</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>+ 0∙2</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>60</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Leon......................</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>6,167</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>348,756</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>350,210</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>+ 0∙4</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>57</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Estremadura............</hi></p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>16,702</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>707,115</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>739,403</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>+ 4∙6</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>44</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Badajoz..................</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>8,688</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>404,981</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>432,809</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>+ 6·9</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>50</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Caceres..................</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>8,014</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>302,134</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>306,594</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>+ 1·5</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>38</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Galicia....................</hi></p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>11,343</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>1,776,879</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>1,848,027</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>+ 4·0</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>163</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Coruña...................</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>3,078</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>551,989</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>596,436</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>+ 8∙0</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>193</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Lugo......................</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>3,787</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>424,186</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>410,810</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>- 33</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>110</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Orense...................</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>2,739</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>371,818</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>388,835</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>+ 4∙6</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>142</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Pontevedra.............</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>1,739</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>428,886</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>451,946</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>+ 5∙4</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>260</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Andalusia................</hi></p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>33,926</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>2,937,183</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>3,283,436</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>+ 11∙7</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>94</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Almeria..................</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>3,302</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>315,664</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>349,076</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>+ 10·8</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>106</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Granada.................</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>4,937</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>444,629</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>479,066</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>+ 7∙5</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>96</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Malaga..................</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>2,824</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>451,406</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>500,322</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>+ 10∙8</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>177</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Cordova.................</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>5,300</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>351,536</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>385,482</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>+ 9·7</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>73</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Jaen......................</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>5,184</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>345,879</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>423,025</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>+ 223</p></cell> <cell cols="1" rows="1"> 
</div></body></text></TEI>