<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb09-22-s05-0433-07" facs="encyclopediabrit22newyrich_raw_0457.jp2" type="entry"><p><label>SQUARING</label>, (or Quadrature) OF THE CIRCLE is the problem of finding a square equal in area to a given circle. Like all problems, it may be increased in difficulty by the imposition of restrictions ; consequently under the designation there may be embraced quite a variety of geometrical problems. It has to be noted, however, that, when the “ squaring ” of the circle is especially spoken of, it is almost always tacitly assumed that the restrictions are those of the Euclidean geometry.</p><p>Since the area of a circle equals that of the rectilineal triangle whose base has the same length as the circumference and whose altitude equals the radius (Archimedes, <hi rend="italic">Κύκλου</hi> <hi rend="italic">μέτρησις,</hi> prop. 1), it follows that, if a straight line could be drawn equal in length to the circumference, the required square could be found by an ordinary Euclidean construction ; also, it is evident that, conversely, if a square equal in area to the circle could be obtained, it would be possible to draw a straight line equal to the circumference. Rectification and quadrature of the circle have thus been, since the time of Archimedes at least, practically identical problems. Again, since the circumferences of circles are proportional to their diameters—a proposition assumed to be true from the dawn almost of practical geometry—the rectification of the circle is seen to be transformable into finding the ratio of the circumference to the diameter. This correlative numerical problem and the two purely geometrical problems are inseparably connected historically.</p><p>Probably the earliest value for the ratio was 3. It was so among the Jews (1 Kings vii. 23, 26), the Babylonians (Oppert, <hi rend="italic">Journ. Asiatique,</hi> August 1872, October 1874), the Chinese (Biot, <hi rend="italic">Journ. Asiatique,</hi> June 1841), and probably also the Greeks. Among the ancient Egyptians, as would appear from a calculation in the Rhind papyrus, the number (/), <hi rend="italic">i.e.,</hi> 3·16..., was at one time in use.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="1"> Eisenlohr, <hi rend="italic">Ein</hi> <hi rend="italic">math. Handbuch d. alien Aegypter, übers. u. erklärt,</hi> Leipsic, 1877 ; Rodet, <hi rend="italic">Bull. de la Soc. Math. de France,</hi> vi. pp. 139-149. </note> The first attempts to solve the purely geometrical problem appear to have been made by the Greeks (Anaxagoras, Ac.),<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="2"> Hankel, <hi rend="italic">Zur Gesch. d. Math. im Alterthum,</hi> &amp;c., chap. v., Leipsic, 1874 ; Cantor, <hi rend="italic">Vorlesungen über Gesch. d. Math.,</hi> i∙, Leipsic, 1880 , Tannery, <hi rend="italic">Mém. de la Soc.,</hi> &amp;c., <hi rend="italic">à Bordeaux</hi>; Allman, in <hi rend="italic">Hermathena.</hi> </note> one of whom, Hippocrates,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="3"> Tannery, <hi rend="italic">Bull. des Sc. Math.,</hi> [2], x. pp. 213-226. </note> doubtless raised hopes of a solution by his quadrature of the so-called <hi rend="italic">meniscοi.</hi> As for Euclid, it is sufficient to recall the facts that the original author of prop. 8 of book iv. had strict proof of the ratio being &amp;lt;4, and the author of prop. 15 of the ratio being &amp;gt;3, and to direct attention to the importance</p><pb xml:id="eb09-22-s05-0434" facs="encyclopediabrit22newyrich_raw_0458.jp2"/><p>of book X. on incommensurables and props. 2 and 16 of book xii., viz., that “circles are to one another as the squares on their diameters” and that “in the greater of two concentric circles a regular 2 <hi rend="italic">n</hi>-gon can be inscribed which shall not meet the circumference of the less,” however nearly equal the circles may be. With Archimedes (287-212 b.c.) a notable advance was made. Taking the circumference as intermediate between the perimeters of the inscribed and the circumscribed regular n-gons, he showed that, the radius of the circle being given and the perimeter of some particular circumscribed regular polygon obtainable, the perimeter of the circumscribed regular polygon of double the number of sides could be calculated ; that the like was true of the inscribed polygons; and that consequently a means was thus afforded of approximating to the circumference of the circle. As a matter of fact, he started with a semi-side AB of a circumscribed regular hexagon meeting the circle in B (see fig. 1), joined A and B with O the centre, bisected the AOB by OD, so that BD became the semi-side of a circumscribed regular 12-gon ; then as AB : BO : OA : : 1 : √3 : 2 he sought an approximation to √3 and found that AB : BO &amp;gt;153 : 265. Next he applied his theorem<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="4"> In modem trigonometrical notation, 1 + sec <hi rend="italic">θ</hi>: tan ½ </note> BO + OA : AB : : OB : BD to calculate BD ; from this in turn he cal</p><p>culated the semi-sides of the circumscribed</p><p>regular 24-gon, 48-gon, and 96-gon, and</p><p>so finally established for the circumscribed</p><p>regular 96-gon that perimeter : diameter</p><p>&amp;lt; 3/: 1. In a quite analogous manner he proved for the inscribed regular 96-gon that perimeter : diameter &amp;gt; 3/: 1. The conclusion from these therefore was that the ratio of circumference to diameter is &amp;lt;31 and &amp;gt;31/. This is a most notable piece of work ; the immature condition of arithmetic at the time was the only real obstacle preventing the evaluation of the ratio to any degree of accuracy whatever.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="5"> : : 1 : tan ½ <hi rend="italic">θ.</hi> </note></p><p>No advance of any importance was made upon the achievement of Archimedes until after the revival of learning. His immediate successors may have used his method to attain a greater degree of accuracy, but there is very little evidence pointing in this direction. Ptolemy (fl. 127-151), in the <hi rend="italic">Great Syntaxis,</hi> gives 3·141552 as the ratio<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="6"> Tannery, “ Sur la mesure du cercle d’Archimède, ” in <hi rend="italic">Mém. . . . Bordeaux,</hi> [2], iv. pp. 313-339 ; Menge, <hi rend="italic">Des Archimedes Kreismessung,</hi> Coblentz, 1874. </note>; and the Hindus (c. 500 a.d.), who were very probably indebted to the Greeks, used 62832/20000, that is, the now familiar 3·1416.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="7"> De Morgan, in <hi rend="italic">Penny Cyclop.,</hi> xix. p. 186. </note> It was not until the 15th century that attention in Europe began to be once more directed to the subject, and after the resuscitation a considerable length of time elapsed before any progress was made. The first advance in accuracy was due to a certain Adrian, son of Anthony, a native of Metz (1527), and father of the better-known Adrian Metius of Alkmaar. In refutation of Duchesne (Van der Eycke) he showed that the ratio was</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">&amp;lt; 3/ <hi rend="sub">120</hi></hi> and &amp;gt; 3/ <hi rend="sub">106</hi>, and thence made the exceedingly lucky step of taking a mean between the two by the quite unjustifiable process of halving the sum of the two numerators for a new numerator and halving the sum of the two denominators for a new denominator, thus arriving at the now well-known approximation 3/ <hi rend="sub">113</hi> or <hi rend="sup">355</hi> / <hi rend="sub">113</hi> which, being equal to 3·1415929..., is correct to the sixth fractional place.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="8"> Kern, <hi rend="italic">Aryahhattîyam,</hi> Leyden, 1874, trans, by Rodet, Paris, 1879. </note> The next to advance the calculation was Viète (De Viette, Vieta), the greatest mathematician of his age. By finding the perimeter of the inscribed and that of the circumscribed regular polygon of 393216 <hi rend="italic">(i.e.,</hi> 6 × 2) sides, he proved</p><p>that the ratio was &amp;gt;3∙1415926535 and &amp;lt;3T415926537, so that its value became known (in 1579) correctly to 10 fractional places. The theorem for angle-bisection which Viète used was not that of Archimedes, but that which would now appear in the form 1 - cos <hi rend="italic">θ</hi> = 2sin½ <hi rend="italic">θ</hi></p><p>. With Viète, by reason of the advance in arithmetic, the style of treatment becomes more strictly trigonometrical ; indeed, the <hi rend="italic">Universales Inspectiones,</hi> in which the calculation occurs, would now be called plane and spherical trigonometry, and the accompanying <hi rend="italic">Canon Mathematicus,</hi> a table of sines, tangents, and secants.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="9"> De Morgan, art. “Quadrature of the Circle,” in <hi rend="italic">English Cyclop. ;</hi> </note> Further, in comparing the labours of Archimedes and Viète, the effect of increased power of symbolical expression is very noticeable. Archimedes’s process of unending cycles of arithmetical operations could at best have been expressed in his time by a “rule” in words; in the 16th century it could be condensed into a “ formula.” Accordingly, we find in Viète a formula for the ratio of diameter to circumference, viz., the interminate product<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="10"> Vieta, <hi rend="italic">Opera Math.,</hi> Leyden, 1646; Marie, <hi rend="italic">Hist. des Sciences Math.,</hi> iii. p. 27 <hi rend="italic">sq.,</hi> Paris, 1884. </note> —</p><p>⅜V⅛∙λ∕ ⅛ + ⅛√⅛∙ n∕4 + ⅛√⅛ + ⅛V⅛∙ ■ ·</p><p>From this point onwards, therefore, no knowledge whatever of geometry was necessary in any one who aspired to determine the ratio to any required degree of accuracy : the mere arithmetician’s art and length of days were the only requisites. Thus in connexion with the subject a genus of workers became possible who may be styled “π-computers,”—a name which, if it connotes anything uncomplimentary, does so because of the almost entirely fruitless character of their labours. Passing over Adriaan van Roomen (Adrianus Romanus) of Louvain, who published the value of the ratio correct to 15 places in his <hi rend="italic">Idea Mathematica</hi> (1593),<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="11"> Klügel, <hi rend="italic">Math. Wörterb.,</hi> ii. pp. 606, 607. </note> we come to the notable computer Ludolph van Ceulen (d. 1610), a native of Germany, long resident in Holland. His book, <hi rend="italic">Van den Circkel</hi> (Delf, 1596), gave the ratio correct to 20 places, but he continued his calculations as long as he lived, and his best result was published on his tombstone in St Peter’s church, Leyden. The inscription, which is not known to be now in existence,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="12"> Kästner, <hi rend="italic">Gesch, d. Math.,</hi> i., Göttingen, 1796-1800. </note> is in part as follows :—</p><p>. . . Qui in vita sua multo labore circumferentiae circuli proximam rationem ad diametrum invenit sequentem—</p><p>quando diameter est 1 tum circuli circumferentia plus est</p><p>314159265358979323846264338327950288 quam 100000000000000000000000000000000000</p><p>et minus</p><p>314159265358979323846264338327950289 quam 100000000000000000000000000000000000...</p><p>This gives the ratio correct to 35 places. Van Ceulen’s process was essentially identical with that of Viète. Its numerous root extractions amply justify a stronger expression than “ multo labore,” especially in an epitaph. In Germany the “Ludolphische Zahl” is still a common name for the ratio.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="13"> But see <hi rend="italic">Les Délices de Leide,</hi> Leyden, 1712 ; or De Haan, <hi rend="italic">Mess. of Math.,</hi> iii. pp. 24-26. </note></p><p>Up to this point the credit of most that had been done may be set down to Archimedes. A new departure, however, was made by Willebrord Snell of Leyden in his <hi rend="italic">Cyclometria,</hi> published in 1621. His achievement was a closely approximate geometrical solu</p><p>Glaisher, <hi rend="italic">Mess</hi>. <hi rend="italic">of Math.,</hi> ii. pp. 119-128, iii. pp. 27-46 ; De Haan, <hi rend="italic">Nieuw Archief V. Wisk.,</hi> i. pp. 70-86, 206-211.</p><pb xml:id="eb09-22-s05-0435" facs="encyclopediabrit22newyrich_raw_0459.jp2"/><p>tion of the problem of rectification (see fig. 2). ACB being a semicircle whose centre is O, and AC the arc to be rectified, he produced AB to D, making BD equal to the radius, joined DC, and produced it to meet the tangent at A in E ; and then his assertion (not established by him) was that AE was nearly equal to the arc AC, the error being in defect. For the purposes of the calculator a solution erring in excess was also required, and this Snell gave by slightly varying the former construction. Instead of producing AB</p><p>(see fig. 3) so that BD</p><p>was equal to <hi rend="italic">r,</hi> he pro</p><p>duced it only so far that,</p><p>when the extremity D' was</p><p>joined with C, the part of</p><p>D'C outside the circle was equal to <hi rend="italic">r</hi>; in other words, by a non-Euclidean construction he trisected the angle AOC, for it is readily seen that, since FD' = FO = OC, the angle FOB =/AOC.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="14"> It is thus manifest that by his first construction Snell gave an approximate solution of two great problems of antiquity. </note> This couplet of constructions is as important from the calculator’s point of view as it is interesting geometrically. To compare it on this</p><p>score with the fundamental proposition of</p><p>Archimedes, the latter must be put into</p><p>a form similar to Snell’s. AMC being an</p><p>arc of a circle (see fig. 4) whose centre is</p><p>O, AC its chord, and HK the tangent</p><p>drawn at the middle point of the arc and</p><p>bounded by OA, OC produced, then, according to Archimedes, AMC&amp;lt;HK but &amp;gt;AC. In modern trigonometrical notation the propositions to be compared stand as follows :—</p><p>2tan/ <hi rend="italic">θ&amp;gt;θ&amp;gt;</hi> 2sin/ <hi rend="italic">θ</hi> (Archimedes); tan/ <hi rend="italic">θ</hi> + 2sin/ <hi rend="italic">θ</hi> &amp;gt; <hi rend="italic">θ</hi> &amp;gt; <hi rend="sup">3sin</hi> <hi rend="italic"><hi rend="sup">θ</hi></hi> / <hi rend="sub">2 + cos</hi> <hi rend="italic"><hi rend="sub">θ</hi></hi> (Snell).</p><p>It is readily shown that the latter gives the best approximation to <hi rend="italic">θ</hi>; but, while the former requires for its application a knowledge of the trigonometrical ratios of only one angle (in other words, the ratios of the sides of only one right-angled triangle), the latter requires the same for two angles, <hi rend="italic">θ</hi> and/ <hi rend="italic">θ.</hi> Grienberger, using Snell’s method, calculated the ratio correct to 39 fractional places.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="15"> <hi rend="italic">Elementa Trigonometrica,</hi> Rome, 1630 ; Glaisher, <hi rend="italic">Messenger of Math.,</hi> iii. p. 35 <hi rend="italic">sq.</hi> </note> Huygens, in his <hi rend="italic">De Circuli Magnitudine Inventa,</hi> 1654, proved the propositions of Snell, giving at the same time a number of other interesting theorems, for example, two inequalities which may be written as follows<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="16"> See Kiessling’s edition of the <hi rend="italic">De Circ. Magn. Inν.,</hi> Flensburg, 1869 ; or Pirie’s tract on <hi rend="italic">Geometrical Methods of Approx. to the Value of π,</hi> London, 1877. </note> —</p><p>chd <hi rend="italic">θ +</hi> ⅛(<hi rend="sup">c</hi> hd <hi rend="italic">θ</hi>- sin <hi rend="italic">θ') &amp;gt; θ</hi> &amp;gt; chd <hi rend="italic">θ</hi> + i(chd <hi rend="italic">θ -</hi> sin <hi rend="italic">θ).</hi></p><p>2 chd 0 + 3 sin ø <hi rend="sup">3v</hi> ' <hi rend="sup">3ξ 7</hi></p><p>As might be expected, a fresh view of the matter was taken by Descartes. The problem he set himself was the exact converse of that of Archimedes. A given straight line being viewed as equal in</p><p>length to the circumference of a</p><p>circle, he sought to find the dia</p><p>meter of the circle. His con</p><p>struction is as follows (see fig. 5).</p><p>Take AB equal to one-fourth of</p><p>the given line ; on AB describe a</p><p>square ABCD ; join AC ; in AC</p><p>produced find, by a known process,</p><p>a point Csuch that, when CB</p><p>is drawn perpendicular to AB pro</p><p>duced and CDperpendicular to BC produced, the rectangle BCwill be equal to/ABCD ; by the same process find a point Csuch that the rectangle BCwill be equal to/BC; and so on <hi rend="italic">ad infinitum.</hi> The diameter sought is the</p><p>straight line from A to the limiting position of the series of B’s, say the straight line AB <hi rend="sub">∞</hi>. As in the case of the process of Archimedes, we may direct our attention either to the infinite series of geometrical operations or to the corresponding infinite series of arithmetical operations. Denoting the number of units in AB by/ <hi rend="italic">c,</hi> we can express BB, BB, . . . in terms of 1/ <hi rend="italic">c,</hi> and the identity AB <hi rend="sub">∞</hi> = AB + BB+ BB+ ... gives us at once an expression for the diameter in terms of the circumference by means of an infinite series.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="17"> See Euler, “ Annotationes in Locum quendam Cartesii, in <hi rend="italic">Nov. Comm. Acad. Petrop.,</hi> viii. </note> The proof of the correctness of the construction is seen to be involved in the following theorem, which serves likewise to throw new light on the subject :—AB being any straight line whatever, and the above construction being made, then AB is the diameter of the circle circumscribed by the square ABCD (self-evident), ABis the diameter of the circle circumscribed by the regular 8-gon having the same perimeter as the square, ABis the diameter of the circle circumscribed by the regular 16-gon having the same perimeter as the square, and so on. Essentially, therefore, Descartes’s process is that known later as the process of <hi rend="italic">isoperimeters,</hi> and often attributed wholly to Schwab.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="18"> Gergonne, <hi rend="italic">Annales de Math.,</hi> vi. </note></p><p>In 1655 appeared the <hi rend="italic">Arithmetica Infinitorum</hi> of Wallis, where numerous problems of quadrature are dealt with, the curves being now represented in Cartesian coordinates, and algebra playing an important part. In a very curious manner, by viewing the circle <hi rend="italic">y</hi> = (1 <hi rend="italic">-x</hi>) <hi rend="sup">1/2</hi> as a member of the series of curves <hi rend="italic">y =</hi> (l <hi rend="italic">-x</hi>) <hi rend="italic">, y =</hi> (1 <hi rend="italic">-x</hi>) <hi rend="italic">,</hi> &amp;amp;c., he was led to the proposition that four times the reciprocal of the ratio of the circumference to the diameter is equal to</p><p>3.3.5.5. 7.7.9...</p><p>2.4.4. 6.6.8. 8.. .’</p><p>and; the result having been communicated to Lord Broun-ker, the latter discovered the equally curious equivalent expression ι ÷1-&amp;gt;</p><p>2 + — 5</p><p><hi rend="sup">+2+</hi> k...</p><p>The work of Wallis had evidently an important influence on the next notable personality in the history of the subject, James Gregory, who lived during the period when the higher algebraic analysis was coming into power, and whose genius helped materially to develop it. He had, however, in a certain sense one eye fixed on the past and the other towards the future. His first contribution<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="19"> See <hi rend="italic">Vera Circuli et Hyperbolæ Quadratura,</hi> Padua, 1667 ; and the <hi rend="italic">Appendicula</hi> to the same in his <hi rend="italic">Exercitationes Geometricae,</hi> London, 1668. </note> was a variation of the method of Archimedes. The latter, as we know, calculated the perimeters of successive polygons, passing from one polygon to another of double the number of sides ; in a similar manner Gregory calculated the areas. The general theorems which enabled him to do this, after a start had been made, are</p><p><hi rend="italic">A</hi> <hi rend="italic"><hi rend="sub">η</hi> =</hi> <hi rend="italic">∖</hi> <hi rend="italic">∕A <hi rend="sub">η</hi> A' <hi rend="sub">η</hi></hi> (Snell’s <hi rend="italic">Cyclom.),</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">., 2A <hi rend="sub">n</hi> A' <hi rend="sub">n</hi> 2A' <hi rend="sub">n</hi> A <hi rend="sub">in</hi>. <hi rend="sub">r</hi>, .</hi></p><p>-≈∙=⅛⅞. <hi rend="sup">or</hi> ⅛⅜∕ <hi rend="sup">0rβs01yλ</hi> where <hi rend="italic">A <hi rend="sub">n</hi>, A' <hi rend="sub">n</hi></hi> are the areas of the inscribed and the circumscribed regular <hi rend="italic">n</hi>-gons respectively. He also gave approximate rectifications of circular arcs after the manner of Huygens; and, what is very notable, he made an ingenious and, according to Montucla, successful attempt to show that quadrature of the circle by a Euclidean construction was impossible.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="20"> <hi rend="italic">Penny Cyclop.,</hi> xix. p. 187. </note> Besides all this, however, and far beyond it in importance, was his use of infinite series. This merit he shares with his contemporaries Mercator, Newton, and Leibnitz, and the exact dates of discovery are a little uncertain. As far as the circle-squaring functions are con-</p><pb xml:id="eb09-22-s05-0436" facs="encyclopediabrit22newyrich_raw_0460.jp2"/><p>cerned, it would seem that Gregory was the first (in 1670) to make known the series for the arc in terms of the tangent, the series for the tangent in terms of the arc, and the secant in terms of the arc; and in 1669 Newton showed to Barrow a little treatise in manuscript containing the series for the arc in terms of the sine, for the sine in terms of the arc, and for the cosine in terms of the arc. These discoveries formed an epoch in the history of mathematics generally, and had, of course, a marked influence on after investigations regarding circle-quadrature. Even among the mere computers the series</p><p><hi rend="italic">θ=</hi> tan <hi rend="italic">θ -</hi> /tan <hi rend="italic">θ</hi> +/tan <hi rend="italic">θ-...,</hi> specially known as Gregory’s series, has ever since been a necessity of their calling.</p><p>The calculator’s work having now become easier and more mechanical, calculation went on apace. In 1699 Abraham Sharp, on the suggestion of Halley, took Gregory’s series, and, putting tan <hi rend="italic">θ</hi> =/√3, found the ratio equal to</p><p>√12(1 -/ <hi rend="sub">3.3</hi> + *** - *** ),</p><p>from which he calculated it correct to 71 fractional places.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="21"> See Sherwin’s <hi rend="italic">Math. Tables,</hi> London, 1705, p. 59. </note> About the same time Machin calculated it correct to 100 places, and, what was of more importance, gave for the ratio the rapidly converging expression,</p><p>16/,1 ∖ 4 ∕ l l ∖</p><p>5∖3.5 <hi rend="sup">2 +</hi> 5.57.5 <hi rend="sup">β+</hi> ' <hi rend="sup">,</hi> √ 239∖ <hi rend="sup">i</hi> 3.239 <hi rend="sup">2 +</hi> 5.239”which long remained without explanation.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="22"> See W. Jones, <hi rend="italic">Synopsis Palmariorum Matheseos,</hi> London, 1706; </note> Fautet de Lagny, still using tan 30°, advanced to the 127th place.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="23"> Maseres, <hi rend="italic">Scriptores Logarithmici,</hi> London, 1791-96, vol. iii. pp. 159 <hi rend="italic">sq. ;</hi> Hutton, <hi rend="italic">Tracts,</hi> vol. i. p. 266. </note></p><p>Euler took up the subject several times during his life, effecting mainly improvements in the theory of the various series.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="24"> See <hi rend="italic">Hist. de l’Acad.,</hi> Paris, 1719 ; 7 appears instead of 8 in the 113th place. </note> With him, apparently, began the usage of denoting by π the ratio of the circumference to the diameter.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="25"> <hi rend="italic"/><hi rend="italic">Comment. Acad. Petrop.,</hi> ix., xi. ; <hi rend="italic">Nov. Comm. Ac. Pet.,</hi> xvi. ; <hi rend="italic">Nova Acta Acad. Pet.,</hi> xi. </note> The most important publication, however, on the subject in the 18th century was a paper by Lambert,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="26"> <hi rend="italic"/><hi rend="italic">Introd. in Analysin Infin.,</hi> Lausanne, 1748, chap, viii. </note> read before the Berlin Academy in 1761, in which he demonstrated the irrationality of <hi rend="italic">π.</hi> The general test of irrationality which he established is that, if</p><p>«1</p><p>T^-U <hi rend="sup">α</hi> 2</p><p>⅛±...</p><p>be an interminate continued fraction, <hi rend="italic">a</hi>, <hi rend="italic">a</hi>..., <hi rend="italic">b</hi>, <hi rend="italic">b...</hi></p><p>be integers, , ^,... be proper fractions, and the value of</p><p>h 4 . . . α,</p><p>every one of the interminate continued fractions</p><p><hi rend="italic">fτ</hi> <hi rend="sub">β β</hi> 1 — *</p><p>,— ,... be &amp;lt; 1, then the given continued fraction</p><p>δ±... <hi rend="sup">,</hi>. . .</p><p>represents an irrational quantity. If this be applied to the right-hand side of the identity</p><p><hi rend="italic">mm ,</hi> tan — = — ∞ ,</p><p><hi rend="italic">η n--^- rn <hi rend="sup">i</hi></hi> 3n- =—</p><p><hi rend="italic">5n -...,</hi></p><p>it follows that the tangent of every arc commensurable with the radius is irrational, so that, as a particular case, an arc of 45°, having its tangent rational, must be incom</p><p>mensurable with the radius; that is to say, <hi rend="sup">π</hi> /is an incommensurable number.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="27"> <hi rend="italic"/><hi rend="italic">Mém. sur quelques propriétés remarquables des quantités transcend</hi> </note> This incontestable result had no effect, apparently, in repressing the π-computers. Vega</p><p>in 1789, using series like Machin’s, viz., Gregory’s series and the identities</p><p><hi rend="sup">π</hi> /= 5 tan <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> /+ 2 tan <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> /(Euler, 1779),</p><p><hi rend="sup">π</hi> /= tan <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> /+ 2 tan <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> /(Hutton, 1776),</p><p>neither of which was nearly so advantageous as several found by Hutton, calculated <hi rend="italic">π</hi> correct to 136 places.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="28"> <hi rend="italic">antes, circulaires, et logarithmiques.</hi> </note> This achievement was anticipated or outdone by an unknown calculator, whose manuscript was seen in the Radcliffe Library, Oxford, by Baron von Zach towards the end of the century, and contained the ratio correct to 152 places. More astonishing still have been the deeds of the π-computers of the 19th century. A condensed record compiled by Mr Glaisher <hi rend="italic">(Messenger of Math.,</hi> ii. p. 122) is as follows :—</p><p>Date.</p><p>Computer.</p><p>No. of No. of fr.digits fr.digits calcd. correct.</p><p>Place of Publication.</p><p>1842</p><p>Rutherford</p><p>208</p><p>152</p><p><hi rend="italic">Trans. Roy. Soc.,</hi> Lond., 1841, p. 283.</p><p>1844</p><p>Dase ......</p><p>205</p><p>200</p><p><hi rend="italic">Crelle's Journ.,</hi> xxvii. p. 198.</p><p>1847</p><p>Clausen ...</p><p>250</p><p>248</p><p><hi rend="italic">Astron. Nachr.,</hi> xxv. col. 207.</p><p>1853</p><p>Shanks ...</p><p>318</p><p>318</p><p><hi rend="italic">Proc.Roy. Soc.,</hi> Lond.,1853, p. 273.</p><p>1853</p><p>Rutherford</p><p>440</p><p>440</p><p><hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi>.</p><p>1853</p><p>Shanks ...</p><p>530</p><p><hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi></p><p>1853</p><p>Shanks ...</p><p>607</p><p>W. Shanks, <hi rend="italic">Rectification of the Circle,</hi> London, 1853.</p><p>1853</p><p>Richter ...</p><p>333</p><p>330</p><p><hi rend="italic">Grunert’s Archiv,</hi> xxi. p. 119.</p><p>1854</p><p>Richter ...</p><p>400</p><p>330</p><p><hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi> xxii. p. 473.</p><p>1854</p><p>Richter ...</p><p>400</p><p>400</p><p><hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi> xxiii. p. 476.</p><p>1854</p><p>Richter ...</p><p>500</p><p>500</p><p><hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi> XXV. p. 472.</p><p>1873</p><p>Shanks ...</p><p>707</p><p><hi rend="italic">Proc. Roy. Soc.,</hi> Lond., xxi.</p><p>By these computers Machin’s identity, or identities analogous to it, <hi rend="italic">e.g.,</hi></p><p><hi rend="sup">π</hi> /= tan <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> /+ tan <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> /+ tan <hi rend="sup">-1 1</hi> /,</p><p><hi rend="sup">π</hi> /= 4 tan <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> /- tan <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> /+ tan <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> /,</p><p>and Gregory’s series were employed.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="29"> See Legendre, <hi rend="italic">Éléments de Geometrie,</hi> Paris, 1794, note iv. ; Schlö <hi rend="italic"/></note></p><p>A much less wise class than the π-computers of the 19th century are the pseudo-circle-squarers, or circle-squarers technically so called, that is to say, persons who, having obtained by illegitimate means a Euclidean construction for the quadrature or a finitely expressible value for <hi rend="italic">π,</hi> insist on using faulty reasoning and defective mathematics to establish their assertions. Such persons have flourished at all times in the history of mathematics ; but the interest attaching to them is more psychological than mathematical.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="30"> <hi rend="italic">Noca Acta Petrοp.,</hi> ix. p. 41; <hi rend="italic">Thesaurus Logarithm. Completus,</hi> p. 633. </note></p><p>It is of recent years that the most important advances in the theory of circle-quadrature have been made. In 1873 Hermite proved that the base ε of the Napierean logarithms cannot be a root of a rational algebraical equation of any degree.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="31"> On the calculations made before Shanks, see Lehmann, “Beitrag zur Berechnung der Zahl π,” in <hi rend="italic">Grunert's Archiv,</hi> xxi. pp. 121-174. </note> To prove the same proposition regarding <hi rend="italic">π</hi> is to prove that a Euclidean construction for circle-quadrature is impossible. For in such a construction every point of the figure is obtained by the intersection of two straight lines, a straight line and a circle, or two circles ; and, as this implies that, when a unit of length is introduced, numbers employed, and the problem transformed into one. of algebraic geometry, the equations to be solved can only be of the first or second degree, it follows that the equation to which we must be finally led is a rational equation of even degree. Hermite<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="32"> See Montucla, <hi rend="italic">Hist. des rech. sur la quad. du cercle,</hi> Paris, 1754, 2d ed. 1831 ; De Morgan, <hi rend="italic">Budget of Paradoxes,</hi> London, 1872. </note> did not</p><p>milch, <hi rend="italic">Handbuch d. algeb. Analysis,</hi> Jena, 1851, chap. xiii.</p><pb xml:id="eb09-22-s05-0437" facs="encyclopediabrit22newyrich_raw_0461.jp2"/><p>succeed in his attempt on <hi rend="italic">π</hi>; but in 1882 Lindemann, following exactly in Hermite’s steps, accomplished the desired result.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="33"> See “ Ueber die Zahl <hi rend="italic">π</hi>,” in <hi rend="italic">Math. Annalen,</hi> xx. p. 213. </note> Mathematicians are agreed that the full demonstration leaves something to be desired in the matter of simplicity, and attempts at simplification have already been made by Markoff and Rouché.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="34"> <hi rend="italic">Nouv. Annales,</hi> 3d ser., ii. p. 5. </note></p><p>Besides the various writings mentioned, see for the early history of the subject, Montucla, <hi rend="italic">Hist. des Math.,</hi> 6 vols., Paris, 1758, 2d ed. 1799-1802 ; Murhard, <hi rend="italic">Bibliotheca Mathematica,</hi> ii. pp. 106-123, Leipsic, 1798 ; Reuss, <hi rend="italic">Repertorium Comment.,</hi> vii. pp. 42-44, Gottingen, 1808. For a few approximate geometrical solutions, see Leybourn’s <hi rend="italic">Math. Repository,</hi> vi. pp. 151-154; <hi rend="italic">Grunert's Archiv,</hi> xii. p. 98, xlix. p. 3; <hi rend="italic">Nieuw Archief v. Wisk.,</hi> iv. pp. 200-204. For experimental determinations of π, dependent on the theory of probability, see <hi rend="italic">Mess. of Math.,</hi> ii. pp. 113, 119 ; <hi rend="italic">Casopis pro pǐstování math. a fys.,</hi> X. pp. 272-275 ; <hi rend="italic">Analyst,</hi> ix. p. 176. (T. MU.)</p></div></body></text></TEI>