<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb09-22-s05-0369-01" facs="encyclopediabrit22newyrich_raw_0393.jp2" type="entry"><p><label>SPARROW</label>, (A.S. <hi rend="italic">Spearwa</hi>; Icel. <hi rend="italic">Spörr;</hi> Old High Germ. <hi rend="italic">Sparo),</hi> a word perhaps (like the equivalent Latin <hi rend="italic">Passer)</hi> originally meaning almost any small bird, but gradually restricted in signification and nowadays in common English applied to only four kinds, which are further differentiated as Hedge-Sparrow, House-Sparrow, Tree-Sparrow, and Reed-Sparrow—the last being a Bunting (vol. iv. p. 525)—though when used without a prefix the second of these is usually intended.</p><p>1. The Hedge-Sparrow, called “Dunnock” in many parts of Britain, the <hi rend="italic">Accentor modularis</hi> of ornithologists, is the little brown-backed bird with an iron-grey head and neck that is to be seen in nearly every garden throughout the country, unobtrusively and yet tamely seeking its food, which consists almost wholly of insects, as it progresses over the ground in short jumps, each movement being accompanied by a slight jerk or shuffle of the wings. Though on the Continent it regularly migrates, it is one of the few soft-billed birds that reside throughout the year with us, and is one of the earliest breeders,—its well-known greenish-blue eggs, laid in a warmly-built nest, being recognized by hundreds as among the surest signs of returning spring ; but a second or even a third brood is produced later. The cock has a sweet but rather feeble song ; and the species has long been accounted, though not with accuracy, to be the most common dupe of the Cuckow. Several other species are assigned to the genus <hi rend="italic">Accentor</hi>; but all, except the Japanese <hi rend="italic">A. rubidus,</hi> which is the counterpart of the British Hedge-Sparrow, inhabit more or less rocky situations, and one, <hi rend="italic">A. collaris</hi> or <hi rend="italic">alpinus,</hi> is a denizen of the higher mountain-ranges of Europe, though it has several times strayed to England. The taxonomic position of the genus is regarded by some systematists as doubtful ; but to the present writer there seems no good reason for removing it from the group which contains the Thrushes and Warblers (<hi rend="italic">Turdidæ</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Sylviidæ),</hi> to which it was long referred.</p><p>2. The House-Sparrow, the <hi rend="italic">Fringilla domestica</hi> of Linnæus and <hi rend="italic">Passer domesticus</hi> of modern authors, is far too well known to need any description of its appearance or habits, being found, whether in country or town, more attached to human dwellings than any other wild bird ; nay, more than that, one may safely assert that it is not known to thrive anywhere far away from the habitations or works of men, extending its range in such countries as Northern Scandinavia and many parts of the Russian empire as new settlements are formed and land brought under cultivation. Thus questions arise as to whether it should not be considered a parasite throughout the greater portion of the area it now occupies, and as to what may have been its native country. Moreover, of late years it has been inconsiderately introduced to several of the large towns of North America and to many of the British colonies, in nearly all of which, as had been foreseen by ornithologists, it has multiplied to excess and has become an intolerable nuisance, being unrestrained by the natural checks which partly restrict its increase in Europe and Asia. Whether indeed in the older seats of civilization the House-Sparrow is not decidedly injurious to the agriculturist and horticulturist has long been a matter of discussion, and no definite result that a fair judge can accept has yet been reached. It is freely admitted that the damage done to growing crops is often enormous, but as yet the service frequently rendered by the destruction of insect-pests cannot be calculated. Both friends and foes of the House-Sparrow write as violent partisans,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="1"> The most recent attacks upon it are contained in the various issues of the <hi rend="italic">Report of Observations of Injurious Insects and Common Crop Pests,</hi> annually made by Miss Eleanor Ormerod, and in a little volume bearing the title of <hi rend="italic">The House Sparrow,</hi> published in 1885, </note> and the truth will not be known until a series of experiments,</p><p>conducted by scientifically-trained investigators, has been instituted, which, to the shame of numerous agricultural and horticultural societies, has not yet been done. It is quite likely that the result will be unfavourable to the House-Sparrow, from what has been said above as to its being so dependent on man for its subsistence ; but, while the evil it does is so apparent,—for instance, the damage to ripening grain-crops,—the extent of the counterbalancing benefit is quite uncertain, and from the nature of the case is often overlooked. In the South of Europe the House-Sparrow is in some measure replaced by two allied species, <hi rend="italic">P. hispaniolensis</hi> and <hi rend="italic">P. italiæ,</hi> whose habits are essentially identical with its own ; and it is doubtful whether the Sparrow of India, <hi rend="italic">P. indicus,</hi> is specifically distinct ; but Africa has several members of the genus which are decidedly so.</p><p>3. The Tree-Sparrow, the <hi rend="italic">Fringilla montana</hi> of Linnæus and <hi rend="italic">Passer montanus</hi> of modem writers, in appearance much resembling the House-Sparrow, but easily distinguishable by its reddish-brown crown, the black patch on the sides of its neck, and its doubly-barred wings,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="2"> A more important difference is that the two sexes have almost the same plumage, while in the House-Sparrow they are unlike in this respect. </note> is a much more local species, in England generally frequenting the rows of pollard-willows that line so many rivers and canals, in the holes of which it breeds ; but in some Eastern countries, and especially in China, it frequents houses, even in towns, and so fills the place of the House-Sparrow. Its geographical distribution is extensive, and marked by some curious characters, among which may be mentioned that, being a great wanderer, it has effected settlements even in such remote islands as the Færoes and some of the Outer Hebrides.</p><p>That the genus <hi rend="italic">Passer</hi> properly belongs to the <hi rend="italic">Fringill-idse</hi> is admitted by most ornithologists, yet there have been some who would refer it to the Weaver-birds, <hi rend="italic">Ploceidæ,</hi> if they are to be accounted as forming a distinct Family,—a matter which is not at all clear. The American birds called “ Sparrows ” have little in common with the members of the genus <hi rend="italic">Passer,</hi> and probably belong rather to the family <hi rend="italic">Emberizidæ</hi> than to the <hi rend="italic">Fringillidæ.</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">(a. n.)</hi></p></div></body></text></TEI>