<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb09-22-s05-0275-02" facs="encyclopediabrit22newyrich_raw_0293.jp2" type="entry"><p><label>SORA</label>, a city of Italy, at the head of a circondario in the province of Caserta (Terra di Lavoro), is built in a plain on the banks of the Garigliano and on the highway from Rome <hi rend="italic">via</hi> Tivoli and Avezzano to Naples. It is the seat of important manufactures,—wool-spinning, cloth-weaving, and paper-making,—this last industry dating from the time of Murat. The original cathedral, consecrated by Pope Adrian IV. in 1155, was destroyed by the earthquake of 1634. The population of the city was 8768 in 1861 and 5411 (commune 13,208) in 1881.</p><p>Sora, an ancient Volscian town, was thrice captured by the Romans, in 34δ, 314, and 305 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi>, before they managed, in 303, by means of a colony 4000 strong, to confirm its annexation. In 209 it was one of the colonies which refused further contributions. By the lex Julia it became a municipium, but under Augustus it was colonized by soldiers of the 4th legion. The castle of Sorella, built on the rocky height above the town, was in the Middle Ages a stronghold of some note ; on one occasion it held out successfully against a whole year’s vigorous siege by William II. of Sicily. Alfonso of Aragon made Sora a duchy for the Cantelmi ; it was afterwards seized by Pius II., but, being restored to the Cantelmi by Sixtus IV., it ultimately passed to the Della Rovere of Urbino. Against Cæsar Borgia the city was heroically defended by Giovanni di Montefeltro. Captured by the marquis of Pescara for Charles V., it was by him bestowed on Carlo Ceares, duke of Croy and Arescot, but, Ceares being afterwards bought out, the duchy was restored to the duke of Urbino. By Gregory XIII. it was purchased for 11,000 ducats and bestowed on his son Buoncompagni, the ancestor of the line of Buoncompagni-Ludovisi. In ancient times Sora was the birthplace of the Decii, Attilius Regulus, and Lucius Mummius ; aud of its modern celebrities Cardinal Baronius is one. The now ruined abbey church of San Domenico, founded in 1104 on the left bank of the Liri above the town, is believed to occupy the site of Cicero’s family villa and birthplace. It consisted of a nave and two aisles, all ending in circular apses.</p></div></body></text></TEI>