<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0714.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0708-10" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SPONGIA, <hi rend="smallcaps">Sponge,</hi></label>
 in natural hiſtory ; a genus of animals belonging to the claſs of and order of</p><p><hi rend="italic">voophyta.</hi> It is fixed, flexible, and very torpid, growing in a variety of forms, compoſed either of reticulated fibres, or maſſes of ſmall ſpines interwoven together, and clothed with a living gelatinous fleſh, full of ſmall mouths or holes on its ſurface, by which it ſucks in and throws out the water. Fifty ſpecies have already been diſcovered, of which 10 belong to the Britiſh coaſts.</p><p>1. <hi rend="italic">Oculata,</hi> or branched ſponge, is delicately ſoft and very much branched ; the branches are a little compreſſed, grow erect, and often united together. They have rows of cells on each margin, that project a little. This ſpecies is of a pale yellow colour, from five to ten inches high. The fibres are reticulated, and the fleſh or gelatinous part is ſo tender, that when it is taken out of the water it ſoon dries away. It is very common round the ſea-coaſt of Britain and Ireland. This deſcription will be better underſtood by Plate <hi rend="smallcaps">cccclxxv.</hi> fig. I. At <hi rend="italic">b, b,</hi> along the edges and on the ſurface of the branches, are rows of ſmall papillary holes, through which the animal receives its nouriſhment.</p><p>2. <hi rend="italic">Cristata,</hi> or cock’s comb ſponge, is flat, erect, and ſoft, growing in the ſhape of cock’s combs, with rows of little holes along the tops, which project a little. It abounds on the rocks to the eaſtward of Hastings in Suſſex, where it may be ſeen at low-water. It is commonly about three inches long, and two inches high, and of a pale yellowiſh colour. When put into a glaſs vessel of ſea-water, it has been obſerved to ſuck in and ſquirt out the water through little mouths along the tops, giving evident signs of life.</p><p>3. <hi rend="italic">Stupοsa,</hi> tow-ſponge, or downy branched ſponge, is ſoft like tow, with round branches, and covered with fine pointed hairs. It is of a pale yellow colour, and about three inches high. It is frequently thrown on the ſhore at Haſtings in Suſſex. Fig. 2. repreſents this ſponge ; but it is ſo cloſely covered with a fine down, that the numerous ſmall holes in its ſurface are not diſcernible.</p><p>4. <hi rend="italic">Dichοtoma,</hi> dichotomous or forked ſponge, is ſtiff, branched, with round, upright, elaſtic branches, covered with minute hairs. It is found on the coaſt of Norway, and alſo, according to Berkenhout, on the Corniſh and Yorkſhire coaſts. It is of a pale yellow colour, and full of very minute pores, guarded by minute ſpines.<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0715.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0709"/>
5. <hi rend="italic">Urens</hi> or <hi rend="italic">tomentoſa,</hi> ſtinging sponge, or crumb of bread ſponge, is of many forms, full of pores, very brittle and ſoft, and interwoven with very minute ſpines. It is full of ſmall protuberances, with a hole in each, by which it sucks in and throws out the water. It is very common on the Britiſh coaſt, and is frequently ſeen ſurrounding fucuſes. It is found alſo on the ſhores of North America, Africa, and in the Eaſt Indies. When newly taken out of the ſea, it is of a bright orange colour, and full of gelatinous fleſh ; but when dry, it becomes whitiſh, and when broken has the appearance of crumb of bread. If rubbed on the hand, it will raiſe bliſters ; and if dried in an oven, its power of flinging is much increaſed, eſpecially that variety of it which is found on the ſea-coaſt of North America.</p><p>6. <hi rend="italic">Palmata,</hi> palmated ſponge, is like a hand with fingers a little divided at the top. -The mouths are a little prominent, and irregularly diſpoſed on the ſurface. It is found on the beach at Brighthelmſtone. It is of a reddiſh colour, inclining to yellow, and of the ſame ſoft woolly texture with the ſpongia oculata, fig. 4.</p><p>7. <hi rend="italic">Coronata,</hi> coronet ſponge, is very ſmall, consiſting of a single tube ſurrounded at top by a crown or little ſpines. The tube is open at the top. The rays that compoſe the little crown are of a bright, ſhining pearl colour ; the body is of a pale yellow. It has been found in the harbour of Emſworth, between Suſſex and Hampſhire.</p><p>8. <hi rend="italic">Botryoides,</hi> grape ſponge, is very tender and branched, as if in bunches : the bunches are hollow, and are made up of oblong oval figures having the appearance of grapes ; and each bunch is open at top. This ſpecies is of a bright, ſhining colour. The openings at the top are evidently the mouths by which the animal imbibes and diſcharges moisture. When the ſurface is very much magnified, it appears covered with little maſſes of triple, equidiſtant, ſhining ſpines.</p><p>9. <hi rend="italic">Lacustris,</hi> creeping ſponge, has erect, cylindrical, and obtuſe branches. It is found in lakes in Sweden and England.</p><p>10. <hi rend="italic">Fluviatilis,</hi> river ſponge, is green, erect, brittle, and irregularly diſpoſed in numerous branches. It abounds in many parts of Europe, in the freſh rivers of Ruſſia and England, but particularly in the river Thames. It ſcarcely exhibits any ſymptoms of life, is of a fiſhy ſmell : its pores or mouths are ſometimes filled with green gelatinous globules. It differs very little from the lacuſtris.</p><p>So early as the days of Aristotle ſponges were ſuppoſed to poſſeſs animal life ; the persons employed in collecting them having obſerved them ſhrink when torn from the rocks, thus exhibiting ſymptoms of senſation. The ſame opinion prevailed in the time of Pliny : But no attention was paid to this ſubject till Count Marsigli examined them, and declared them vegetables. Dr Feyſonell, in a paper which he ſent to the Royal Society in the year 1752, and in a ſecond in 1757, affirmed they were not vegetables, but the production of animals ; and has accordingly described the animals, and the proceſs which they performed in making the ſponges. Mr Ellis, in the year 1762, was at great pains to diſcover theſe animals. For this purpoſe he diſſected the ſpongia urens, and was ſurpriſed to find a great number of ſmall worms of the genus of nereis or sea-ſcolopendra, which had pierced their way through the ſoft ſubſtance of the ſponge in queſt of a ſafe retreat. That this was really the caſe, he was fully aſſured of, by inſpecting a number of ſpecimens of the ſame sort of ſponge, juſt fresh from the ſea. He put them into a glaſs filled with ſea-water; and then, inſtead of ſeeing any of the little animals which Dr Peyſonell described, he obſerved the papillæ or ſmall holes with which the papillæ are ſurrounded contract and dilate themſelves. He examined another variety of the ſame ſpecies of ſponge, and plainly perceived the ſmall tubes inſpire and expire the water. He therefore concluded, that the ſponge is an animal, and that the ends or openings of the branched tubes are the mouths by which it receives its nouriſhment, and diſcharges its excrements.</p></div></body></text></TEI>