<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0806.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0800-03" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>STILPO</label>,
a celebrated philoſopher of Megara, flouriſhed under the reign of Ptolemy Euergetes. In his youth he had been addicted to licentious pleaſures, from which he religiouſly refrained from the moment that he ranked himſelf among philoſophers. When Ptolemy Soter, at the taking of Megara, offered him a large ſum of money, and requeſted that he would accompany him into Egypt, he accepted but a ſmall part of the offer, and retired to the iſland of Ægina, whence, on Ptolemy’s departure, he returned to Megara. That city being again taken by Demetrius the ſon of Antigonus, and the philoſopher required to give an account oſ any effects which he had loſt during the hurry of the plunder, he replied, that he had loſt nothing ; for no one could take from him his learning and eloquence. So great was the fame of Stilpo, that the moſt eminent philoſophers of Athens took pleaſure in attending upon his diſcourſes. His peculiar doctrines were, that ſpecies or univerſals have no real exiſtence, and that one thing cannot be predicated of another. With reſpect to the former of theſe opinions, he ſeems to have taught the same doctrine with the ſect afterwards known by the appellation of <hi rend="italic">Nοminalists.</hi> To prove that one thing cannot be predicated of another, he ſaid, that <hi rend="italic">goodness</hi> and <hi rend="italic">man,</hi> for inſtance, are different things, which cannot be confounded by aſſerting the one to be the other : he argued farther, that goodneſs is an univerſal, and univerſals have no real exiſtence ; conſequentlv, ſince nothing cannot be predicated of any thing, goodneſs cannot be predicated of man.<note anchored="true" n="1" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>Enfield's History of Philosophy, vol. i.</p></note> Thus, whilſt this ſubtle logician was, through his whole argument, predicating one thing of another, he denied that any one thing could be the accident or predicate of another. If Stilpo was ſerious in this reaſoning ; if he meant any thing more than to expoſe the ſophiſtry of the ſchools, he muſt be confeſſed to have been an eminent maſter of the art of wrangling ; and it was not wholly without reaſon that Glycera, a celebrated courtezan, when ſhe was reproved by him as a corrupter of youth, replied, that the charge might be juſtly retorted upon himſelf, who ſpent his time in filling their heads with sophiſtical quibbles and uſeleſs ſubtleties. In ethics he ſeems to have been a Stoic, and in religion he had a public and a private doctrine, the former for the multitude, and the latter for his friends. He admitted the exiſtence of a ſupreme divinity, but had no reverence for the Grecian ſuperſtitions.</p></div></body></text></TEI>