<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0812.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0806-07" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>STONE</label>
(Edmund), a diſtinguiſhed ſelf-taught mathematician, was born in Scotland ; but neither the place nor time of his birth are well known ; nor have we any memoirs of his life, except a letter from the Chevalier de Ramſay, author of the Travels of Cyrus, in a letter to father Caftel, a Jeſuit at Paris, and published in the Memoirs de Trevoux, p. 109, as follows: “ True genius overcomes all the diſadvantages of birth, fortune, and education ; of which Mr Stone is a rare example. Born a ſon of a gardener of the duke of Argyle, he arrived at eight years of age before he learnt to read.— By chance a servant having taught young Stone the letters of the alphabet, there needed nothing more to diſcover and expand his genius. He applied himſelf to ſtudy, and he arrived at the knowledge of the moſt sublime geometry and analyſis, without a maſter, without a conductor; without any other guide but pure genius.</p><p>“ At 18 years of age he had made theſe considerable advances without being known, and without knowing himſelf the prodigies of his acquiſitions. The duke of Argyle, who joined to his military talents a general knowledge of every ſcience that adorns the mind of a man of his rank, walking one day in his garden, ſaw lying on the graſs a Latin copy of Sir Iſaac Newton’s celebrated <hi rend="italic">Pricipia.</hi> He called ſome one to him to take and carry it back to his library. Our young gardener told him that the book belonged to him. ‘ To you ?’ replied the Duke. ‘ Do you underſtand geometry, Latin, Newton ?’ I know a little of them, replied the young man with an air of ſimplicity ariſing from a profound ignorance of his own knowledge and talents. The Duke was ſurpriſed ; and having a taste for the ſciences, he entered into converſation with the young mathematician : he aſked him ſeveral queſtions, and was aſtoniſhed at the force, the accuracy, and the candour of his anſwers. ‘ But how, ſaid the Duke, came you by the knowledge of all theſe things ?’ Stone replied, ‘A servant taught me, ten years ſince, to read: does one need to know any thing more than the 24 letters in order to learn every thing elle that one wishes?’ The Duke’s curioſity redoubled—he ſat down upon a bank, and requeſted a detail of all his proceedings in becoming ſo learned.</p><p>“ I firſt learned to read, ſaid Stone : the masons were then at work upon your houſe : I went near them one day, and I ſaw that the architect uſed a rule, compasses, and that he made calculations. I inquired what might be the meaning and uſe of theſe things ; and I was informed that there was a ſcience called Arithmetic : I purchaſed a book of arithmetic, and I learned it. — I was told there was another ſcience called Geometry : I bought the books, and I learnt geometry. By reading I found that there were good books in theſe two ſciences in Latin : I bought a dictionary, and I learned Latin. I understood alſo that there were good books of the ſame kind in French : I bought a dictionary, and I learned French. And this, my lord, is what I have done : it ſeems to me that we may learn every thing when we know the 24 letters of the alphabet.”</p><p>This account charmed the Duke. He drew this wonderful genius out of his obſcurity ; and he provided him with an employment which left him plenty of time to apply himſelf to the ſciences. He diſeovered in him alſo the ſame genius for muſic, for painting, for architecture, for all the ſciences which depend on calculations and proportions.”</p><p>“ I have ſeen Mr Stone. He is a man of great simplicity. He is at preſent ſenſible of his own knowledge ; but he is not puffed up with it. He is poſſeſſed with a pure and diſtinterested love for the mathematics, though he is not ſolicitous to pats for a mathematician ; vanity having no part in the great labour he ſuſtains to excel in that ſcience. He deſpiſes fortune alſo ; and he has ſolicited me twenty times to requeſt the duke to give him leſs employment, which may not be worth the half of that he now has, in order to be more retired, and leſs taken off from his favourite studies. He diſcovers ſometimes, by methods of his<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0813.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0807"/>
own, truths which others have diſcovered before him. He is charmed to find on theſe occasions that he is not a firſt inventor, and that others have made a greater progreſs than he thought. Far from being a plagiary, he attributes ingenious ſolutions, which he gives to certain problems, to the hints he has found in others, although the connection is but very diſtant,” &amp;c.</p><p>Mr Stone was author and tranſlator of ſeveral uſeful works ; viz. I. A New Mathematical Dictionary, in 1 vol. 8vo, firſt printed in 1726. 2. Fluxions, in 1</p><p>vol. 8vo, 1730. The Direct Method is a translation from the French, of Hospital’s Analyſe des Infiniments Petits ; and the Inverſe Method was ſupplied by Stone himſelf. 3. The Elements of Euclid, in 2 vols. 8vo, 1731. A neat and uſeful edition of thoſe Elements, with an account of the life and writings of Euclid, and a defence of his elements againſt modern objectors. Beſide other ſmaller works. Stone was a fellow of the Royal Society, and had inſerted in the Philoſophical Tranſactions (vol. 41, p. 218) an “ Account of two ſpecies of lines of the 3d order, not mentioned by Sir Iſaac Newton or Mr Stirling.”</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Stone</hi> (Jerome), the ſon of a reputable ſeaman, was born in the pariſh of Scoonie, in the county of Fife, North Britain. His father died abroad when he was but three years of age, and his mother, with her young family, was left in very narrow circumſtances. Jerome, like the rest of the children, having got the ordinary ſchool education, reading Engliſh, writing, and arithmetic, betook himſelf to the busineſs of a travelling chapman. But the dealing in buckles, garters, and ſuch ſmall articles, not ſuiting his ſuperior genius, he ſoon converted his little ſtock into books, and for ſome years went through the country, and attended the fairs as an itinerant bookſeller. There is great reaſon to believe that he engaged ill this new ſpecies of traffic, more with a view to the improvement of his mind than for any pecuniary emolument. Formed by nature for literature, he poſſeſſed a peculiar talent for acquiring languages with amazing facility. Whether from a desire to underſtand the Scriptures in their original languages, or from being informed that theſe languages are the parents of many others, he began his philological purſuits with the ſtudy of the Hebrew and Greek tongues ; and, by a wonderful effort of genius and application, made himſelf ſo far maſter of theſe, without any kind of aſſiſtance, as to be able to interpret the Hebrew Bible and Greek Teſtament into Engliſh <hi rend="italic">ad aperturam libri.</hi> At this time he did not know one word of Latin. Senſible that he could make no great progreſs in learning, without the knowledge of at leaſt the grammar of that language, he made application to the pariſh ſchoolmaſter for his aſſiſtance. Some time afterwards, he was encouraged to proſecute his ſtudies at the Univerſity of St Andrew’s. An unexampled proficiency in every branch of literature recommended him to the eſteem of the profeſſors ; and an uncommon fund of wit and pleaſantry rendered him, at the ſame time, the favourite of all his fellow ſtudents, ſome of whom ſpeak of him to this day with an enthusiaſtic degree of admiration and reſpect. About this period ſome very humorous poetical pieces of his composition were publiſhed in the Scots Magazine. Before he had finiſhed his third ſeſſion, or term, at St Andrew’s, on an application to the College by the maſter of the ſchool of Dunkeld for an uſher, Mr Stone was recommended as the beſt qualified for that office ; and about two or three years after, the maſter being removed to Perth, Mr Stone, by the favour of his Grace the Duke of Atholl, who had conceived a high opinion of his abilities, was appointed his ſuccessor.</p><p>When he firſt went to Dunkeld, he entertained but an unfavourable opinion of the Gaelic language, which he conſidered as nothing better than a barbarous inarticulate gibberiſh ; but being bent on inveſtigating the origin and deſcent of the ancient Scots, he ſuffered not his prejudices to make him neglect the ſtudy of their primitive tongue. Having, with his uſual aſſiduity and ſucceſs, mattered the grammatical difficulties which he encountered, he ſet himſelf to diſcover ſomething of the true genius and character of the language. He collected a number of ancient poems, the production, of Iriſh or Scottiſh bards, which, he ſaid, were daring, innocent, paſſionate, and bold. Some of theſe poems were tranſlated into Engliſh verſe, which ſeveral perſons now alive have ſeen in manuſcript, before Mr Macpherſon publiſhed any of his tranſlations from Offian.</p><p>He died while he was writing and preparing for the preſs a treatiſe, intitled, “ An Inquiry into the Original of the Nation and Language of the ancient Scots, with Conjectures about the Primitive State of the Celtic and other European Nations ;” an idea which could not have been conceived by an ordinary genius. In this treatiſe he proves that the Scots drew their original, as well as their language, from the ancient Gauls. Had Mr Stone lived to finish this work, which diſcovers great ingenuity, immenſe reading, and indefatigable industry, it would have thrown light upon the dark and early periods of the Scottiſh history, as he opens a new and plainpath for leading us through the unexplored labyrinths of antiquity. But a fever put an end to his life, his labours, and his uſefulneſs, in the year 1757, being then only in the 30th year of his age. He left, in manuſcript, a much eſteemed and well-known allegory, intitled “ The Immortality of Authors,” which has been publiſhed and often reprinted ſince his death, and will be a laſting monument of a lively fancy, ſound judgement, and correct taste. It was no ſmall ornament of this extraordinary character, that he paid a pious regard to his aged mother, who ſurvived him two years, and received an annual penſion from the Dutcheſs of Atholl as a testimony of reſpect to the memory of her ſon.</p></div></body></text></TEI>