<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="chi.28490924-1526168109_Page_0435.jpf" type="entry" xml:id="eb07-20-s03-0372-01" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SIZAR</label>,
or SIZER, in Latin <hi rend="italic">Sizator,</hi> an appellation by which the lowest order of students in some universities are distinguished, is derived from the word <hi rend="italic">size,</hi> which has a peculiar meaning. To <hi rend="italic">size,</hi> in the language of the university, is to get any sort of victuals from the kitchens, which the students may want in their own rooms, or in addition to their commons in the hall, and for which they pay the cooks or butchers at the end of each quarter. A size of any thing is the smallest quantity of that thing which can be thus bought ; two sizes, or a part of beef, being nearly equal to what a young person will eat of that dish to his dinner, and a size of ale or beer being equal to half an English pint. In Oxford, the order similar to that of sizar is denominated servitor, a name evidently derived from the menial duties which they perform. The sizars are not upon the foundation, and therefore whilst they continue sizars, are not capable of being elected fellows; but they may at any time, if they choose, become pensioners, and they generally sit for scholarships immediately before they take their first degrees. If successful, they are then on the foundation, and are entitled to become candidates for fellowships when they have got their degree. In the mean time, whilst they continue sizars, besides free commons they enjoy many benefactions, which have been made at different times, under the name of <hi rend="italic">sizar’s prætor, exhibitions,</hi> and the like, and the rate of tuition, the rent of rooms, and other things of that sort within their respective colleges, is less than to the other orders. But though their education is thus obtained at a less expence, they are not now considered as a menial order ; for sizars, pensioner-scholars, and even sometimes fellow-commoners, mix together with the utmost cordiality.</p></div></body></text></TEI>