<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0610.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0604-06" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SONCHUS, <hi rend="smallcaps">sow-thistle,</hi></label>
 in botany: A genus of plants belonging to the claſs of <hi rend="italic">ſyngeneſia,</hi> and to the order of <hi rend="italic">polygamia aequalis</hi>; and in the natural ſyſtem ranged under the 49th order, <hi rend="italic">Cοmpositae.</hi> The receptacle is naked; the calyx is imbricated, bellying and conical; the down of the seed is ſimple, feſſile, and very ſoft ; the ſeed is oval and pointed. There are 13 ſpecies ; the maritimus, paluſtris, fruticoſus, arvenſis, oleraceus, tenerrimus, plumieri, alpinus, floridanus, sibiricus, tataricus, tuberoſus, and canadeniis. Four of theſe are natives of Britain.— 1. <hi rend="italic">Palustris,</hi> marſh ſow-thistle. The ſtem is erect, from six to ten feet high, branched and hairy towards the top : the leaves are firm, broad, half pinnated, ſerrated, and ſharp-pointed ; the lower ones ſagittate at the baſe : the flowers are oſ a deep yellow, large, and diſperſed on the tops of the branches : the calyx is rough. It is frequent in marſhes, and flowers in July or Auguſt.— 2. <hi rend="italic">Arvenſis,</hi> corn ſow-thiſtle. The leaves are alternate, runcinate, and heart-ſhaped at the baſe ; the root creeps under ground ; the ſtem is three or four feet high, and branched at the top. It grows in corn fields, and flowers in Auguſt.— 3. <hi rend="italic">Oleraceus,</hi> common ſow-thiſtle. The ſtalk is ſucculent, piſtular, and a cubit high or more ; the leaves are broad, embracing the ſtem, generally deeply ſinuated, ſmooth or prickly at the edges; the flowers are of a pale yellow, numerous, in a kind of umbel, and terminal ; the calyx is ſmooth. It is frequent in waſte places and cultivated grounds.—4. <hi rend="italic">Alpinus,</hi> blue-flowered ſow-thiſtle. The ſtem is erect, purpliſh, branched, or ſimple, from three to six feet high : the leaves are large, ſmooth, and ſinu-<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0611.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0605"/>
ated ; the extreme ſegment large and triangular : the</p><p>flowers are blue, and grow on hairy viſcid pedicles, in long ſpikes : the calyx is brown. This species is found in Northumberland.</p></div></body></text></TEI>