<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0567.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0561-01" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SNEEZING</label>,
a convulſive motion of the muſcles of the breaſt, whereby the air is expelled from the noſe with much vehemence and noiſe. It is cauſed by the irritation of the upper membrane of the noſe, occaſioned by acrid ſubſtances floating in the air, or by medicines called st <hi rend="italic">ernutatory.</hi></p><p>This irritation is performed either externally, by ſtrong ſmells, as marjoram, roſes, &amp; c. or by dust floating in the air, and taken in by inſpiration ; or by ſharp pungent medicines, as creſſes and other ſternutatories, which vellicate the membrane of the noſe ; or internally, by the acrimony of the lympha or mucus, which naturally moiſtens that membrane. The matters caſt south in ſneezing come primarily from the noſe and throat ; the pituitary membrane continually exuding a mucus thither ; and, ſecondarily, from the breaſt, the trachea, and the bronchia of the lungs.</p><p>The practice of ſaluting the perſon who ſneezed exiſted in Africa, among nations unknown to the Greeks and Romans. The accounts we have of Monomotapa inform us<note anchored="true" n="1" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>* Strada, Prol. Acad.</p></note> *, that when the prince ſneezes, all his ſubjects in the capital are advertiſed of it, that they may offer up prayers for his ſafety. The author of the conqueſt of Peru aſſures us, that the cacique of Guachoia having ſneezed in preſence of the Spaniards, the Indians of his train fell proſtrate before him, ſtretched forth their hands, and displayed to him the accuſtomed marks of reſpect, while they invoked the ſun to enlighten him, to defend him, and to be his conſtant guard.</p><p>Every body knows that the Romans ſaluted each other on theſe ocaſions : and Pliny relates<note anchored="true" n="2" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>* Plin. Hist. Nat. lib. ii. cap. 2.</p></note> *, that Tiberius exacted theſe ſigns of homage when drawn in his chariot. Superſtition, whoſe influence can debaſe every thing, had degraded this custom for ſeveral ages, by attaching favourable or unfavourable omens to ſneezing according to the hour of the day or night, according to the ſigns of the zodiac, according as a work was more or leſs advanced, or according as one had ſneezed to the right or to the left<note anchored="true" n="3" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>* Spond. Homeri. Comment.</p></note> *. If a man ſneezed at rising from table or from his bed, it was neceſſary for him to sit or lie down again. You are ſtruck with aſtoniſhment, ſaid Timotheus to the Athenians, who wiſhed to return into the harbour with their fleet<note anchored="true" n="4" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>* Frontin. lib. i. cap. 11.</p></note> *, becauſe he had ſneezed; you are ſtruck with aſtoniſhment, becauſe among 10,000 there is one man whoſe brain is moiſt.</p><p>Polydore Virgil pretends, that in the time oſ Gregory the Great, there reigned in Italy an epidemic diſtemper, which carrried off by ſneezing all thoſe who were ſeized by it ; and that this pontiff ordered prayers to be made againſt it, accompanied by certain ſigns of the croſs. But beſides that, there are very few cases in which ſneezing can be considered as dangerous, and that it is frequently a favourable ſymptom<note anchored="true" n="5" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>*Hippocrat. Halleri. Phys.</p></note> * : it is evident, that we ought not to date from the sixth century the origin of acuſtom which lofes itſelf in the obscurity of antiquity. Avicenna and Cardan ſay, it is a fort of convulsion, which gives occaſion to dread an epilepſy, and that this diſeaſe is endeavoured to be warded off by prayers. Clement of Alexandria conſiders it as a mark of intemperance and effeminacy, which ought to be proſcribed. And he inveighs bitterly againſt thoſe<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0568.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0562"/>
who endeavour to procure ſneezing by external aid, Montaigne, on the contrary, explains this fact in a tone father cynical. It is ſingular enough, that ſo many ridiculous, contradictory, and ſuperſtitious opinions, have not aboliſhed thoſe customary civilities which are ſtill preſerved equally among high and low ; and which only the Anabaptists and Quakers have rejected, becauſe they have renounced ſalutations in every caſe.</p><p>Among the Greeks ſneezing was almoſt always a good omen. It excited marks of tenderneſs, of reſpect, and attachment. The genius of Socrates informed him by ſneezing, when it was neceſſary to perform any action<note anchored="true" n="6" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>* Plutarch de sen. Sonrat.</p></note> *. The young Parthenis, hurried on by her paſſion, resolved to write to Sarpedon an avowal of her love<note anchored="true" n="7" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>*Aristenat.</p></note> * ; ſhe ſneezes in the moſt tender and impaſſioned part of her letter : This is sufficient for her ; this incident ſupplies the place of an anſwer, and perſuades her that Sarpedon is her lover. Penelope, haraſſed by the vexatious courtſhip of her ſuitors, begins to curse them all, and to pour forth vows for the return of Ulyſſes<note anchored="true" n="8" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>*Homeri Odyss. lib. xvii.</p></note> *. Her ſon Telemachus interrupts her by a loud ſneeze. She inſtantly exults with joy, and regards this ſign as an aſſurance of the approaching return of her huſband. Xenophon was haranguing his troops ; a ſoldier ſneezed in the moment when he was exhorting them to embrace a dangerous but neceſſary reſolution. The whole army, moved by this preſage, determine to purſue the project of their general; and Xenophon orders ſacrifices to Jupiter the preserver<note anchored="true" n="9" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>*Xenoph. Anab.</p></note> *.</p><p>This religious reverence for ſneezing, so ancient and fo univerſal even in the times of Homer, always excited the curioſity of the Greek philoſophers and oſ the rabbins. Theſe laſt have ſpread a tradition, that, after the creation of the world, God made a general law to this purport, that every living man ſhould ſneeze but once in his life, and that at the ſame instant he ſhould render up his soul into the hand of his Creator<note anchored="true" n="10" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>*Acad. des Inscrip. vol. iv.</p></note> *, without any preceding indiſpoſition. Jacob obtained an exemption from the common law, and the favour of being informed of his laſt hour : He ſneezed and did not die ; and this ſign of death was changed into a ſign of life. Notice of this was ſent to all the princes of the earth; and they ordained, that in future ſneezing ſhould be accompanied with forms of bleſſing, and vows for the perſons who ſneezed.</p><p>Ariſtotle remounts likewiſe to the sources of natural religion. He obſerves, that the brain is the origin of the nerves, of our ſentiments, our ſenſations, the ſeat of the soul, the image of the Divinity<note anchored="true" n="11" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>* Aristot. in Prob.</p></note> * ; that upon all theſe accounts, the ſubſtance of the brain has ever been held in honour ; that the firſt men ſwore by their head ; that they durſt not touch nor eat the brains of any animal ; that it was even a ſacred word which they dared not to pronounce. Filled with theſe ideas, it is not wonderful that they extended their reverence even to ſneezing. Such is the opinion of the moſt ancient and ſagacious philoſophers of Greece.</p><p>According to mythology, the firſt ſign of life Prometheus’s artificial man gave was by ſternutation. This ſuppoſed creator is ſaid to have stolen a portion of the solar rays ; and filling with them a phial, which he had made on purpoſe, ſealed it up hermetically. He inſtantly flies back to his favourite automaton, and opening the phial holds it cloſe to the ſtatue ; the rays ſtill retaining all their activity, inſinuate themſelves through</p><p>the pores, and ſet the factitious man a ſneezing. Prometheus, tranſported with the ſucceſs of his machine, offers up a fervent prayer, with wiſhes for the preſervation of ſo ſingular a being. His automaton obſerved him, remembering his ejaculations, was very careful, on the like occaſions, to offer theſe wiſhes in behalf of his deſcendants, who perpetuated it from father to son in all their colonies.</p></div></body></text></TEI>