<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0615.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0609-01" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SOREX</label>,
the <hi rend="smallcaps">Shrew,</hi> in natural hiſtory; a genus of animals belonging to the claſs of <hi rend="italic">mammalia,</hi> and order of f <hi rend="italic">erae.</hi> It has two long fore-teeth in the upper jaw, which are divided into two points ; in the lower jaw are two or four fore-teeth, the two middle ones, in the latter caſe, being ſhorter than the others : On each ſide in both jaws are two or more tuſks : The grinders are knobbed. The animals of this genus have in general thick clumſy bodies, and five toes on each of their feet ; the head reſembles that of the mole, being thick at the fore-head, much elongated, and ending in a conical ſnout, and having very ſmall eyes ; in other circumſtances of general figure they reſemble the murine tribe of quadrupeds. They burrow in the ground, ſome ſpecies living moſtly about the ſides of waters ; and most of them feeding on worms and infects. There are 16 ſpecies ; of which the moſt remarkable are,</p><p>1. The <hi rend="italic">araneus,</hi> or field ſhrew-mouſe, with ſhort rounded ears ; eyes ſmall, and almoſt hid in the fur ; noſe long and ſlender, upper part the longeſt; head and upper part of the body of a browniſh red ; belly of a dirty white ; length from noſe to tail, two inches and a half ; tail one and a half. Inhabits Europe: lives in old walls and heaps of ſtones, or holes in the earth ; is frequently near hay-ricks, dung-hills, and neceſſary-houſes; lives on corn, insects, and any filth ; is often obſerved rooting in ordure like a hog ; from its food, or the places it frequents, has a diſagreeable ſmell ; cats will kill, but not eat it : it brings four or five young at a time. The ancients believed it was injurious to cattle; an error now detected. There ſeems to be an annual mortality of theſe animals in Auguſt, numbers being then found dead in the paths.</p><p>2. The <hi rend="italic">ſocliens,</hi> or water-ſhrew, has a long ſlender noſe ; very minute ears ; very ſmall eyes, hid in the fur ; colour of the head and upper part of the body black ; throat, breaſt and belly, of a light aſh colour ; beneath the tail, a triangular duſky ſpot ; much larger than the laſt ; length, from noſe to tail, three inches three quarters ; tail, two inches. Inhabits Europe : long ſince known in England, but loſt till May 1768, when it was diſcovered in the fens near Reveſley Ab-<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0616.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0610"/>
bey, Lincolnſhire ; burrows in the banks near the water ; is called by the fenmen the <hi rend="italic">blind-tnouſe.</hi></p><p>3. The <hi rend="italic">minutus,</hi> or minute ſhrew, has a head near as big as the body : very ſlender noſe ; broad ſhort naked ears ; whiſkers reaching to the eyes ; eyes ſmall, and capable of being drawn in ; hair very fine and ſhining ; grey above, white beneath ; no tail ; the leaſt of quadrupeds, according to Linnæus. Inhabits Siberia; lives in a neſt made of lichens, in ſome moiſt place beneath the roots of trees ; feeds on ſeeds, digs, runs ſwiftly, and has the voice of a bat.</p><p>4. The <hi rend="italic">tucan,</hi> or Mexican ſhrew, has a ſharp noſe ; ſmall round ears ; without sight ; two long fore-teeth above and below ; thick, fat, and fleſhy body ; ſhort legs, ſo that the belly almoſt touches the ground; long crooked claws ; tawny hair ; ſhort tail ; length, from noſe to tail, nine inches. Inhabits Mexico ; burrows, and makes ſuch a number of cavities, that travellers can ſcarce tread with ſafety ; if it gets out of its hole, does not know how to return, but begins to dig another ; grows very fat, and is eatable ; feeds on roots, kidney- beans, and other ſeeds, M. de Buffon thinks it a mole; but it ſeems more properly to belong to the genus of forex.</p></div></body></text></TEI>