<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0518.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0512-07" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SISON, B <hi rend="smallcaps">astard-stonE parsley,</hi></label>
 in botany : A genus of plants belonging to the claſs of <hi rend="italic">pentandria,</hi> and to the order of <hi rend="italic">digynia ;</hi> and in the natural ſyſtem arranged under the 45th order, <hi rend="italic">umbellatœ.</hi> The fruit is egg-ſhaped and ſtreaked ; the involucra are ſubtetraphyllous. There are ſeven ſpecies; the amomum, inundatum, ſegetum, verticillatum, ſalſum, canadenſe, and ammi. The four firſt are natives of Great Britain.</p><p>I. The <hi rend="italic">amomum,</hi> common barſtard parſley, or field ſtone- wort, is a biennial plant about three feet high, growing wild in many places of Britain. Its ſeeds are ſmall, ſtriated, of an oval figure and brown colour. Their taſte is warm and aromatic. Their whole flavour is extracted by ſpirit of wine, which elevates very little of it in diſtillation ; and hence the ſpirituous extract has the flavour in great perfection, while the watery extract has very little. A tincture drawn with pure ſpirit is of a green colour. The ſeeds have been eſteemed aperient, diuretic, and carminative ; but are little regarded in the preſent practice. 2. The <hi rend="italic">inundatum,</hi> leaſt water-parſnep. The ſtem is about eight or ten inches high, branched,<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0519.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0513"/>
and creeping : the leaves, below the water, are capillary ; above it are pinnated : the umbels are biſid. It grows in ditches and ponds. 3. <hi rend="italic">Segetum,</hi> corn parſley, or honeywort. The ſtems are numerous, ſlender, ſtriated, branched, and leaning ; the leaves are pinnated ; the pinnae are oval, pointed, and ſerrated, six or eight pair, and one at the end ; the umbels ſmall and drooping ; the flowers minute and white. It grows in corn-fields and hedges. 4. Ve <hi rend="italic">rticillatum,</hi> verticillate ſiſon, has ſmall leaves in whirls, and capillary ; the ſtem is two feet, with few leaves ; the common umbel is compoſed of 8 or 10 rays, the partial of 18 or 20; both involucra are compoſed of five or six oval acute foliola; the flowers are all hermaphrodite, and the petals white.</p></div></body></text></TEI>