<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0605.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0599-07" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SOLEN</label>,
razor-sheath, or Knife-handle Shell·, a genus belonging to the claſs of vermes, and order of testacea. The animal is an aſcidia. The ſhell is bivalve, oblong, and opening at both ſides: the hinge has a tooth ſhaped like an awl, bent back, often double, not inserted into the oppoſite shell ; the rim at the ſides ſomewhat worn away, and has a horny cartilaginous hinge. There are 23 ſpecies. Three of them, viz. the siliqua, vagina, and enſis, are found on the Britiſh coaſts, and lurk in the sand near the low-water mark in a perpendicular direction. When in want of food they elevate one end a little above the ſurface, and protrude their bodies far out of the ſhell. On the approach of danger they dart deep into the sand, ſometimes two feet at leaſt. Their place is known by a ſmall dimple on the ſurface. Sometimes they are dug out with a ſhovel ; at other times they are taken by ſtriking a barbed dart ſuddenly into them. When the ſea is down, theſe fiſh uſually run deep into the sand ; and to bring them up; the common cuſtom is to throw a little ſalt into the holes, on which the fiſh raiſes itſelf, and in a few minutes appears at the mouth of its hole. When half the ſhell is diſcovered, the fiſherman has nothing more to do than to take hold of it with his fingers and draw it out : but he muſt be cautious not to loſe the occaſion, for the creature does not continue a moment in that ſtate ; and if by any means the fiſherman has touched it, and let it slip away, it is gone for ever ; for it will not be decoyed again out of its hole by ſalt ; ſo that there is then no way of getting it but by digging under it, and throwing it up with the sand. The fiſh has two pipes, each compoſed of four or five rings or portions of a hollow cylinder, of unequal lengths, joined one to another ; and the places where they join are marked by a number of fine ſtreaks or rays. Now the reaſon why the ſalt makes theſe creatures come up out of their holes, is, that it gives them violent pain, and even corrodes theſe pipes. This is ſomewhat ſtrange,</p><p>as the creature is nourished by means of ſalt-water; but it is very evident, that if a little ſalt be ſtrewed upon theſe pipes in a fiſh taken out of ſts habitation, it will corrode the joinings of the rings, and often make one or more joints drop off: the creature, to avoid this miſchief, ariſes out of its hole, and throws off the ſalt, and then retires back again. The uſe of theſe pipes to the animal is the ſame with that of many other pipes of a like kind in other ſhell-fifh ; they all ſerve to take in water : they are only a continuation of the outer membrane of the fiſh, and ſerve indifferently for taking in and throwing out the water, one receiving, and the other diſcharging it, and either anſwering equally well to their purpoſe. See Animal Motion.</p><p>This fiſh was uſed as food by the ancients; and Athenæus, from Sophron, ſpeaks of it as a great delicacy, and particularly grateful to widows. It is often uſed as food at preſent, and is brought up to table fried in eggs.</p></div></body></text></TEI>