<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0484.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0478-04" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SILK</label>,
a very ſoft, fine, bright thread, the work of an infect called <hi rend="italic">bombyx,</hi> or the ſilk worm.</p><p>As the silk worm is a native of China, the culture of ſilk in ancient times was entirely confined to that country. We are told that the empresſes, ſurrounded by their women, ſpent their leiſure hours in hatching and rearing silk worms, and in weaving tiffues and silk veils. That this example was ſoon imitated by perſons of all ranks, we have reason to conclude ; for we are informed that the Chineſe, who were formerly clothed in ſkins, in a ſhort time after were dressed in veſtments of silk. Till the reign of Juſtinian, the ſilk worm was unknown beyond the territories of China, but ſilk was introduced into Perſia long before that period. After the conqueſt of the Perſiaſn empire by Alexander the Great, this valuable commodity was brought into Greece, and thence conveyed to Rome. The firſt of the Roman writers extant by whom ſilk is mentioned, are Virgil and Horace ; but it is probable that neither of them knew from what country it was obtained, nor how it was produced. By ſome of the ancients it was ſuppoſed to be a fine down adhering to the leaves of certain trees or flowers. Others imagined it to be a delicate ſpecies of wool or cotton ; and even thoſe who had learned that it was the work of an infect, ſhow by their deſcriptions that they had no diſtinct idea of the manner in which it was formed. Among the Romans, ſilk was deemed a dreſs too expensive and too delicate for men, and was appropriated wholly to women of eminent rank and opulence. Elagabulus is ſaid to have been the firſt man among the Romans who wore a garment of fine ſilk: Aurelian complained that a pound of ſilk was fold at Rome for 12 ounces of gold ; and it is ſaid he refuſed to give his wife permiſſion to wear it on account of its exorbitant price.</p><p>For ſeveral centuries the Perſians ſupplied the Roman empire with the ſilks of China. Caravans traversed the whole latitude of Alia, in 243 days, from the Chineſe ocean to the ſea-coaſt of Syria, carrying this commodity. Sometimes it was conveyed to the ports of Guzerat and Malabar, and thence transported by ſea to the Perſian Gulph. The Perſians, with the uſual rapacity of monopoliſts, raiſed the price of ſilk to ſuch an exorbitant height, that Juſtinian, eager not only to obtain a full and certain ſupply of a commodity which was become of indiſpenſable uſe, but ſolicitous to deliver the commerce of his ſubjects from the exactions of his enemies, endeavoured, by means oſ his ally, the Chriſtian monarch of Abyſſinia, to wreſt ſome portion of the ſilk trade from the Perſians. In this attempt he failed ; but when he leaſt expected it, he, by an unforeſeen event, attained, in ſome meaſure, the object which he had in view. Two Perſian monks having been employed as miſſionaries in ſome of the Chriſtian churches, which were eſtabliſhed (as we are informed by Coſmas) in different parts of India, had penetrated into the country of the Seres,, or China. There they obſerved the labours of the ſilk worm, and became acquainted with all the arts of man in working up its productions into ſuch a variety of elegant fabrics. The proſpect of gain, or perhaps an indignant zeal, excited by ſeeing this lucrative branch oſ commerce engroſſed by unbelieving<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0485.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0479"/>
nations, prompted them to repair to Conſtantinople. There they explained to the emperor the origin of ſilk, as well as the various modes of preparing and manufacturing it, myſteries hitherto unknown, or very imperfectly underſtood in Europe ; and encouraged by his liberal promiſes, they undertook to bring to the capital a ſufficient number of thoſe wonderful infects, to whoſe labours man is ſo much indebted. This they accompliſhed, by conveying the eggs of the ſilk worm in a hollow cane. They were hatched by the heat of a dunghill, fed with the leaves of a wild mulberry tree, and they multiplied and worked in the ſame manner as in thoſe climates where they firſt became objects of human attention and care. Vaſt numbers of theſe infects were ſoon reared in different parts of Greece, particularly in the Peloponneſus. Sicily afterwards undertook to breed ſilk worms with equal ſuccess, and was imitated, from time to time, in ſeveral towns of Italy. In all theſe places extenſive manufactures were eſtabliſhed and carried on with ſilk of domeſtic production. The demand for ſilk from the eaſt diminiſhed of courſe, the ſubjects of the Greek emperors were no longer obliged to have recourſe to the Persians for a ſupply of it, and a conſiderable change took place in the nature of the commercial intercourse between Europe and India.</p><p>As ſilk is the production of a worm, it will be firſt neceſſary to give a deſcription of its nature and mode of manufacturing. But before we give any account of the moſt approved methods of managing ſilk worms in Europe, it will be proper to preſent a ſhort deſcription of the methods practiſed in China, the original country of the ſilk worm. Theſe are two : they either permit them to remain at liberty on mulberry trees, or keep them in rooms. As the fineſt ſilk is produced by worms confined in rooms, and as the firſt method is very Ample, it will suffice to describe the second.</p><p>To begin with the eggs, which are laid on large ſheets of paper, to which they firmly adhere. The ſheets are hung up on a beam of the room, with the eggs inward, and the windows are opened in the front to admit the wind ; but no hempen ropes muſt ever come near the worms or their eggs. After ſome days the ſheets are taken down, rolled up looſely with the eggs inward, and then hung up again, during the ſummer and autumn. At the end of December, or the beginning of January, the eggs are put into cold water, with a little ſalt diſſolved in it. Two days after they take them out, hang them up again, and when dry roll them a little tighter, and encloſe each ſeparately, ſtanding on one end in an earthen veſſel. Some put them into a lye made of mulberry tree aſhes, and then lay them ſome moments in snow-water, or elſe hang them up three nights on a mulberry tree to receive the ſnow or rain, if not too violent. The time of hatching them is when the leaves of the mulberry trees begin to open, for they are haſtened or impeded according to the different degrees of heat or cold to which they are expoſed. When they are ready to come forth, the eggs ſwell, and become a little pointed.</p><p>The third day before they are hatched, the rolls of paper are taken out of the veſſel, ſtretched out, and hung up with their backs toward the ſun, till they receive a kindly warmth ; and then being rolled up cloſe, they are ſet upright in a veſſel in a warm place. This is repeated the next day, and the eggs change to an aſh-</p><p>grey, They then put two ſheets together, and rolling them cloſe tie the ends.</p><p>The third day, towards night, the ſheets are unrolled and ſtretched on a fine mat, when the eggs appear blackiſh. They then roll three ſheets together, and carry them into a pretty warm place, ſheltered from the ſouth wind. The next day the people taking out the rolls, and opening them, find them full of worms like ſmall black ants.</p><p>The apartment choſen for ſilk worms is on a dry ground, in a pure air, and free from noiſe. The rooms are ſquare, and very cloſe, for the sake of warmth ; the door faces the ſouth, and is covered with a double mat, to keep out the cold ; yet there ſhould be a window on every side, that when it is thought neceſſary the air may have a free paſſage. In opening a window to let in a refreſhing breeze, care muſt be taken to keep out the gnats and flies. The room muſt be furniſhed with nine or ten rows of frames, about nine inches one above the other. On theſe they place ruſh hurdles, upon which the worms are fed till they are ready to ſpin ; and, to preſerve a regular heat, ſtove fires are placed at the corners of the room, or elſe a warming pan is carried up and down it ; but it muſt not have the leaſt flame or ſmoke. Cow-dung, dried in the sun is eſteemed the moſt proper fuel.</p><p>The worms eat equally day and night. The Chineſe give them on the firſt day forty-eight meals; that is, one every half hour ; the next thirty ; the third day they have ſtill leſs. As cloudy and rainy weather takes away their ſtomach, just before their repaſt a wiſp of very dry ſtraw, the flame of which muſt be all alike, is held over the worms to free them from the cold and moiſture that benumbs them, or elſe the blinds are taken from the windows to let in the full day-light.</p><p>Eating ſo often haſtens their growth, on which the chief profit of the ſilk worm depends. If they come to maturity in 23 or 25 days, a large ſheet of paper covered with worms, which at their firſt Coming from the eggs weigh little more than a drachm, will produce 25 ounces of ſilk ; but if not till 28 days, they then yield only 20 ounces ; and if they are a month or 40 days in growing, they then produce but ten.</p><p>They are kept extremely clean, and are often removed; and when they are pretty well grown, the worms belonging to one hurdle are divided into three, afterwards they are placed on six, and ſo on to the number of 20 or more ; for being full of humours, they muſt be kept at a due diſtance from each other. The critical moment for removing them is when they are of a bright yellow and ready to ſpin ; they muſt be ſurrounded with mats at a ſmall diſtance, which muſt cover the top of the place to keep off the outward air ; and becauſe they love to work in the dark. However, after the third day’s labour, the mats are taken away from one o’clock till three, but the rays of the ſun muſt not ſhine upon them. They are at this time covered with the ſheets of paper that were uſed on the hurdles.</p><p>The cocoon s are completed in ſeven days, after which the worm is metamorphoſed into a chryſalis ; the cocoons are then gathered, and laid in heaps, having firſt ſet apart thoſe deſigned for propagation upon a hurdle, in a cool airy place. The next care is to kill the moths in thoſe cones which are not to be bored. The best way of doing this is to fill large earthen veſſels with<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0486.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0480"/>
cones in layers of ten pounds each, throwing in four ounces of ſalt with every layer, and covering it with large dry leaves like thoſe of the water-lily, and cloſely flopping the mouth of the veſſels. But in laying the cones into the veſſels, they ſeparate the long, white, and glittering ones, which yield a very fine ſilk, from thoſe that are thick, dark, and of the colour of the ſkin of an onion, which produce a coarſer ſilk.</p><p>The ſilk worm is a species of caterpillar, which, like all others of the ſame claſs, undergoes a variety of changes, that, to perſons who are not acquainted with objects of this kind, will appear to be not a little ſurpriſing.</p><p>It is produced from a yellowiſh coloured egg, about the ſize of a ſmall pin head, which has been laid by a kind of greyiſh coloured moth, which the vulgar confound with the butterfly.</p><p>Theſe eggs, in the temperature of this climate, if kept beyond the reach of the fire and sun ſhine, may be preserved during the whole of the winter and ſpring months without danger of hatching : and even in ſummer they may eaſily be prevented from hatching if they be kept in a cool place ; but in warmer climates it is ſcarcely poſſible to preſerve them from hatching, even for a few days, or from drying ſo much as to deſtroy them. Hence it is eaſy for a native of Britain to keep the eggs till the food on which the worm is to feed be ready for that purpoſe. When this food is in perfection, the eggs need only be expoſed to the fun for a day or two, when they will be hatched with great facility.</p><p>When the animal is firſt protruded from the egg, it is a ſmall black worm, which is active, and naturally aſcends to the top of the heap in ſearch of food. At this stage of his growth the ſilk worm requires to be fed with the youngeſt and moſt tender leaves. On theſe leaves, if good, he will feed very freely for about eight days, during which period he increaſes in ſize to about a quarter of an inch in length. He is then attacked with his first ſickneſs, which conſiſts in a kind of lethargic ſleep for about three days continuance ; during which time he refuſes to eat, and changes his ſkin, preſerving the ſame bulk. This ſleep being over, he begins to eat again, during five days, at which term he is grown to the ſize of full half an inch in length ; after which follows a ſecond ſickneſs in every reſpect like the former.</p><p>He then feeds for other five days ; during which time he will have increaſed to about three quarters of an inch in length, when he is attacked with his third ſickneſs. This being over, he begins to eat again, and continues to do ſo for five days more, when he is attacked by his fourth ſickneſs, at which time he is arrived at his full growth. When he recovers this ſickneſs, he feeds once more during five days with a moſt voracious appetite ; after which he diſdains his food, becomes tranſparent, a little on the yellowiſh caſt, and leaves his ſilky traces on the leaves where he paſſes. Theſe signs denote that he is ready to begin his cocoon, and will eat no more.</p><p>Thus it appears that the whole duration of the life of the worm, in this ſtate of its exiſtence, in our climate, is uſually about 46 days ; 28 of which days he takes food, and remains in his ſick or torpid ſtate 18 ; but it is to be obſerved, that during warm weather the periods of ſickneſs are ſhortened, and in cold weather lengthened, above the terms here ſpeciſied. In very hot cli</p><p>mates it may be ſaid to live faſter, and ſooner to attain maturity, than in thoſe that are colder. Dr Anderson informs us, that at Madras the worm undergoes its whole evolutions in the ſpace.of 22 days. It appears, however, that it feeds fully as many days in India as in Europe, the difference being entirely occasioned by ſhortening the period of ſickneſs. The longeſt ſickneſs he had ſeen them experience there did not exceed two days ; and during summer it only laſts a few hours.</p><p>When the worm has attained its ſull growth, it ſearches about for a convenient place for forming its cocoon, and mounts upon any branches or twigs that are put in its way for that purpoſe. After about two days ſpent in this manner, it settles in its place, and forms the cocoon, by winding the silk which it draws from its bowels round itſelf into an oblong roundiſh ball.</p><p>During this operation it gradually loses the appearance of a worm ; its length is much contracted, and its thickneſs augmented. By the time the web is finiſhed, it is found to be transformed into an oblong roundiſh ball, covered with a ſmooth ſhelly ſkin, and appears to be perfectly dead. In this ſtate of exiſtence it is called an <hi rend="italic">aurelia.</hi> Many animals in this ſtate may be oſtem ſeen ſticking on the walls of out-houſes, ſomewhat resembling a ſmall bean.</p><p>In this ſtate it remains for ſeveral days entirely motionleſs in the heart of the cocoon, after which it burſts like an egg hatching, and from that comes forth a heavy dull looking moth with wings ; but theſe wings it never uſes for flying ; it only crawls ſlowly about in the place it has been hatched. This creature forces its way through the ſilk covering which the worm had woven, goes immediately in queſt of its mate, after which the female lays her eggs; and both male and female, without taſting food in this ſtage of their exiſtence, die in a very ſhort time.</p><p>The silk worm, when at its full ſize, is from an inch and a quarter to an inch and a half in length, and about hall an inch in circumference. He is either of a milk or pearl colour, or blackiſh ; theſe laſt are eſteemed the beſt. His body is divided into ſeven rings, to each of which are joined two very ſhort feet. He has a ſmall point like a thorn exactly above the anus. The ſubſtance which forms the silk is in his ſtomach, which is very long, wound up, as it were, upon two ſpindles, as ſome ſay, and ſurrounded with a gum, commonly yellowiſh, ſometimcs white, but ſeldom greeniſh. When the worm ſpins his cocoon, he winds off a thread from each of his ſpindles, and joins them afterwards by means of two hooks which are placed in his mouth, ſo that the cocoon is formed of a double thread. Having opened a ſilk worm, you may take out the ſpindles, which are folded up in three plaits, and, on ſtretching them out, and drawing each extremity, you may extend them to near two ells in length. If you then ſcrape the thread ſo ſtretched out with your nail, you ſcrape off the gum, which is very like bees wax, and performs the same office to the ſilk it covers as gold leaf does to the ingot of ſilver it ſurrounds, when drawn out by the wire drawer. This thread, which is extremely ſtrong and even, is about the thickneſs of a middling pin.</p><p>Of ſilk worms, as of moſt other animals, there is a conſiderable variety of breeds, ſome of which are much more hardy, and poſſeſs qualities conſiderably different from others. This is a particular of much importance<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0487.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0481"/>
to he adverted to at the time of beginning to breed theſe creatures in any place ; for it will make a great difference in the profit on the whole to the undertaker if he rears a good or a bad sort<note anchored="true" n="1" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="smallcaps">(a) As</hi> the ſucceſs <hi rend="italic">of</hi> the ſilk manufacture muſt depend on the breed of worms, it is of great conſequence to bring them from thoſe countries where they are reckoned beſt.</p><p>Mr Andrew Wright, an ingenious ſilk manufacturer of Paiſley, has given the following directions for conveying the eggs of the ſilk worm from diſtant countries by ſea : As ſoon as the moth has laid her eggs, dry them immediately, and put them into glaſs vials ; ſeal them ſo cloſe that damp air or water will not penetrate into them. Put theſe phials that contain the eggs into earthen pots filled with cold water ; and as often as the water becomes warm renew it. Place the earthen veſſels in the coldeſt place of the ſhip, and let them remain until the end of the voyage. It muſt be ebſerved, that the ſhip choſen for this purpoſe ought to be one that would arrive in Britain in the months of June or July.</p></note> ( A ). This is a department in reſpect to the economy of animals that has been in every caſe much leſs adverted to than it deserves ; and in particular with regard to the silk worm it has been almoſt entirely overlooked. A few eggs of the silk worm can be eaſily tranſported by post in a letter from any part of Europe to another, eſpecially during the winter ſeaſon. It would therefore be an easy matter for any patriotic ſociety, ſuch as the Society of Arts in London, to obtain a ſpecimen of the eggs from every country in which silk is now reared, to put theſe under the care of a perſon who could be depended upon, and who underſtood the management of them, with orders to keep each kind diſtinct from another, and advert to every particular that occurred in their management, ſo as to make a fair eſtimate of their reſpective merits. By theſe means the beſt might be (elected, and thoſe of inferior value rejected. Forty or fifty of each sort might be enough for the experiment ; but <hi rend="italic">it</hi> ought to be repeated ſeveral times before conduirons could be drawn from it that might be altogether relied upon ; for it is well known that a variation of circumſtances will make a change in the reſult ; and it is by no means certain that the ſame particular would affect thoſe of one breed exactly in the same manner as it would do thoſe of a different breed. One may be more hardy with regard to cold, another more delicate in reſpect to food, and ſo on. It is experience alone that can aſcertain the circumſtances here inquired for.</p><p>From the above mentioned particulars, it is evident, that the management of silk worms muſt be very different in hot climates from what is required in thoſe that are colder. At Madras, it appears from Dr Anderſon’s experiments that it is very difficult to prevent the eggs from hatching for a very few days, ſo that many generations of them muſt be propagated in one year. In this hotteſt ſeaſon,” ſays he, in a letter to Sir Joſeph Banks, dated July 6. 1791, “ the ſhorteſt time I have been able to remark for the whole evolutions of the silk worm is 40 days ; that is to ſay, six days an egg, 22 a worm, 11 a grub in the cocoon, and one a moth or butterfly.” Fortunately, where the climate forces forward their production ſo rapidly, nature hath been equally provident of food for their ſubſiſtence ; for in theſe regions the mulberry continues to grow and puſh out leaves throughout the whole year.</p><p>Though the silk worm be a native of China, there is no doubt but it might eaſily be propagated perhaps in moſt parts of the temperate zones. The eggs</p><p>of this infect, indeed, require a conſiderable degree of warmth to hatch them, but they can alſo endure a ſevere froſt. No leſs than 5400 lbs of ſilk was raiſed in 1789 in the cold, ſandy territories of Pruſſia. In the province of Pekin, in China, where great quantities of ſilk are fabricated, the winter is much colder than even in Scotland. From the information of ſome Ruffians who were ſent thither to learn the Chineſe language, we find that Reaumur’s thermometer was obſerved from 10 to 15, and even 20 degrees below the freezing point. Nor is it difficult to rear the food of the ſilk worm in a temperate clime. The mulberry-tree is a hardy vegetable, which bears, without injury, the winters of Sweden, and cven of Siberia. Of the ſeven species oſ the mulberry (ſee Mows) enumerated by Linnæus, four of theſe (viz. the white, red, black, and Tartarian), there is every reaſon to believe could be reared both in Britain and Ireland. The <hi rend="italic">white</hi> grows in Sweden ; the <hi rend="italic">red</hi> is abundant round Quebec ; the <hi rend="italic">black</hi> delights in bleak fixations, expoſed to wind on the ſea ſhore ; and the <hi rend="italic">Tartarian</hi> mulberry is repreſented as growing in the chilly regions of Siberia.</p><p>As to the ſuperior qualities of the different ſpecies, probably there is very little to be pointed out amongſt the four juſt mentioned with regard to nouriſhment, except what may be drawn from the following fact : that if the firſt three are laid down together, the ſilk worm will firſt eat the white, then the red, and next the black, in the order of the tenderneſs of the leaves. The Tartarian ſeems to hold as high a place in its eſteem as either the red or black ; but all muſt yield to the white, which ſeems to be its natural food.</p><p>In Calabria the red mulberry is uſed ; in Valencia the white; and in Granada, where excellent ſilk is produced, the mulberries are all black. The white ſeems to prosper very well in a moiſt ſtiff soil : the black agrees well with a dry, ſandy, or gravelly ſoil ; and the white is moſt luxuriant in a moiſt rich loam.</p><p>It may juſtly be aſſerted, that Britain poſſeſſes ſome advantages in the raiſing of raw ſilk which are not enjoyed by warmer countries. Even in the ſouth of France, Mr Arthur Young informs us, the mulberry leaves are often nipped by froſt in the bud ; but this is ſcarcely ever the caſe with us. It is well known that thunder and lightning are hurtful to the ſilk worm. Now our climate can boaſt that it is almoſt wholly exempted from thoſe dreadful ſtorrns of thunder and lightning which prevail ſo much in hot climates. Nature has then furniſhed us with every thing requiſite for the ſilk manufacture ; it remains only for us to improve the advantages which we poſſeſs. Let mulberry trees be planted by proprietors of lands, and let a few perſons<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0488.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0482"/>
of ſkill and attention devote their time to the raiſing of ſilk worms. This is an employment that will not interfere with any manufacture already eſtabliſhed ; on the contrary, it would afford a reſpectable, a lucrative, and agreeable employment to ladies, or to females in general, who have at preſent too few profeſſions to which they can apply. The ſociety inſtituted at London for the encouragement of arts, manufactures, and commerce, much to their honour, have offered premiums to those who ſhall plant a certain number of mulberry trees.</p><p>The following method of raiſing mulberry trees from seed is practiſed in the ſouth of France, and has been repeated with ſucceſs in the Eaſt Indies by Dr Anderson of Madras. “ Take the ripe berries of the mulberry when it is full of juice and of feeds. Next take a rough horſe hair line or rope, ſuch as we dry linen on, and with a good handful of ripe mulberries run your hand along the line bruiſing the berries and maſhing them as much as poſſible as your hand runs along, ſo that the pulp and ſeeds of the berries may adhere in great abundance to the rope or hair line. Next dig a trench in the ground where you wiſh to plant them, much like what is practiſed in kitchen gardens in England for crops of various kinds. Next cut the rope or hair line into lengths according to the length of the trench you think fit to make, and plunge the line full of maſhed berries into the trench, and then cover it over well with earth, always remembering afterwards to water it well, which is eſſential to the ſucceſs. The ſeeds of the berries thus sown will grow, and ſoon ſhoot out young ſuckers, which will bear young leaves, which are the beſt food for the ſilk worm.</p><p>" The facility and rapidity with which young leaves may by this means be produced is evident, for as many rows of trenches may thus be filled as can be wiſhed ; and it can never be neceſſary to have mulberry trees higher than our raſpberries, currants, or gooſeberry buſhes. Whenever they get beyond that, they lose their value ; and if theſe trenches ſucceed, you may have a ſupply coming freſh up day after day, or any quantity you pleaſe.” Thus abundance of theſe trees might be reared. But as mulberry trees are not yet found in abundance in this country, it were to be wiſhed that ſome other food could be ſubſtituted in their place : attempts have accordingly been made by thoſe who have reared ſilk worms, and it has been found poſſible to ſupport the ſilk worm upon lettuce<note anchored="false" n="2" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>Bee, N⁰ 70. 12.</p></note> <hi rend="smallcaps">(b).</hi></p><p>Miſs Henrietta Rhodes, a lady who has made ſome ſucceſsful experiments on raiſing ſilk worms in England, had found that the ſilk worm could with ſafety be kept on lettuce for ſome time.<note anchored="true" n="3" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="smallcaps">(b)</hi> It is not improbable, ſays Dr Anderſon, to whoſe valuable work entitled the <hi rend="italic">Bee,</hi> we have been much indebted in the drawing up of this article, that other kinds of food may be found which will anſwer the ſame purpoſe. The chicorium intybus and common endive might be tried, as they have the ſame lacteſcent quality with the lettuce.</p></note> This is pretty generally known by ladies who have turned their attention to this ſubject ; but ſhe found that in general they could not with ſafety be kept upon that food above three weeks. If longer fed upon that plant, the worms for the moſt part die without ſpinning a web at all. She found, however, that they did not always die, but that in ſome caſes they produced very good cocoons, even when fed entirely on lettuce. She therefore with reaſon ſuſpected that the death of the animal muſt be occaſioned by ſome extraneous circumſtance, and not from the poiſonous quality of the food itſelf ; the circumſtance ſhe ſuſtpected, from ſome incidental obſervations, was the coldneſs of that food ; and therefore ſhe thought it was not impoſſible, but if they were kept in a very warm place, while fed on lettuce, they might attain, in all caſes, a due perfection.</p><p>General Mordaunt having been informed of this conjecture, reſolved to try the experiment. He got ſome ſilk worms eggs, had them hatched in his hot-houſe, and cauſed them to be all fed upon lettuce and nothing elſe. They proſpered as well as any worms could do, few or none of them died; and they afforded as fine cocoons as if they had been fed upon mulberry leaves. As far as one experiment can go, this affords a very exhilarating proſpect in many points of view. If one kind of food has been noxious, merely on account of an improper temperature, others may be found which have been hurtful only from a ſimilar cauſe ; ſo that it is not impoſſible but we may at laſt find that this delicate creature may be ſupported by a variety of kinds of food. Few, however, could be more eaſily obtained than lettuce ; and this plant, when cabbaged (the coſs, or ice lettuce eſpecially), would poſſeſs one quality that the mulberry leaf never can poſſeſs, from the want of which many millions of worms die in thoſe countries where ſilk is now reared ; for it is obſerved, that when the leaves are gathered wet, it is ſcarcely poſſible to preſerve the worms alive for any length of time ; ſo that during a continuance of rainy weather many of them are unavoidably cut off ; but a lettuce, when cabbaged, reſiſts moiſture. If gathered, even during rain, the heart of it is dry ; ſo that if the outer leaves be thrown aſide at that time, the worms would be continued in perfect health. The expence, too, of cultivating and gathering lettuce, would be ſo much leſs than that of gathering mulberry leaves, as to occasion a ſaving that would be much more than ſufficient to counterbalance the expence of heating the conſervatory, as a little reflection will ſhow.</p><p>But the great point to be now ascertained is, whether it is a fact that worms fed on lettuce, if kept in a due temperature, will continue in good health, in general, till they ſhall have perfected their cocoon ? One experiment is too little to eſtabliſh this fact with perfect certainty. It would therefore be neceſſary that more experiments ſhould be made on this ſubject.</p><p>It is ſaid that Dr Lodovico Bellardi, a learned and ingenious botaniſt of Turin, has, after a number of experiments, diſcovered a new method of feeding ſilk worms, when they are hatched before the mulberry trees have produced leaves, or when it happens that the froſt deſtroys the tender branches. This new method conſiſts in giving the worms dried leaves of the mulberry-tree. One would think that this dry nouriſh-<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0489.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0483"/>
ment would not be much reliſhed by theſe infects ; but repeated experiments made by our author, prove that they prefer it to any other, and eat it with the greateſt avidity. The mulberry leaves muſt be gathered about the end of autumn, before the froſts commence, in dry weather, and at times when the heat is greateſt. They muſt be dried afterwards in the sun, by ſpreading them upon large cloths, and laid up in a dry place after they have been reduced to powder. When it is neceſſary to give this powder to the worms, it ſhould be gently moiſtened with a little water, and a thin coat of it muſt be placed around the young worms, which will immediately begin to feed upon it.</p><p>We have mentioned all the different kinds of food, which, as far as we have heard, have been tried with any ſucceſs to nouriſh the ſilk worm ; not, however, with great confidence, but as experiments which it might be worth while carefully to conſider and perform. We muſt not omit to mention that one perſon, who has had much experience in the managing of ſilk worms, aſſures us, that the ſilk produced from any other food than mulberry leaves is of an inferior quality, and that the worms are ſickly. We think, however, that there is reason to suſpect that the experiment has not been ſkilfully performed ; and therefore, before every other food except mulberry leaves is diſcarded, the experiment ought to be performed with more attention and care. We know that many animals in a domeſtic ſtate can live upon food very different from that which ſupported them when running wild in the fields. Certain it is, however, that every animal, in its ſtate of nature, partakes of a food peculiar to itſelf, which is rejected by other animals as if it were of a poiſonous quality ; and it may be mentioned as a curious fact, as well as an admirable instance of the care of that Being who feeds the fowls of heaven, that notwithſtanding the numberleſs infects that prey upon animals and vegetables, the mulberry tree is left untouched by them all, as the excluſive property of the ſilk worm, the chief of the infect tribe, which toils and ſpins for the uſe of man.</p><p>Having now considered the food proper for the ſilk worm, we ſhall next conſider what ſituation is moſt favourable to them. In the opinion of ſome perſons in this country who have been in the practice of rearing ſilk worms, they ought always to be kept in a dry place, well ſheltered, and posſeſſing a conſiderable degree of warmth, and which is not expoſed to ſudden traditions from heat to cold. If the weather be too cold, a ſmall fire muſt be made : this is of moſt importance when the worms are ready for ſpinning. A ſouthern expoſure is therefore preferable. Some think light is of great utility to ſilk worms, others think that they thrive better in the dark. As to what apartments are beſt accommodated for promoting the health of ſilk worms, and moſt convenient for thoſe who have the care of them, they may be various according to the extent of the manufacture or the wealth of the proprietors. Silk worms may be kept in boxes or in ſhelves. When ſhelves are to be uſed,they maybe conſtructed in the following manner: The ſhelves may be of wicker, ranged at the diſtance of a foot and a half, and fixed in the middle of the room : their breadth ought to be ſuch, that any perſon can eaſily reach to the middle from either ſide. This is perhaps the simpleſt and cheapeſt apparatus for rearing ſilk worms ; but there is another apparatus which</p><p>may be recommended to those who are anxious to unite ſome degree of elegance with convenience. This apparatus is the invention of the Rev. George Swayne of Ruckle-church, a gentleman who, greatly to his honour, has ſtudied this ſubject much, in order to find out the way for promoting the culture of ſilk among the poor.This apparatus, with the description of it, we have borrowed from that valuable and patriotic work, the Tranſactions of the Society for encouraging Arts, Manufactures, and Commerce, Vol. VII. p. 148. The apparatus consiſts of a wooden frame four feet two inches high, each ſide 16 inches and a half wide, divided into eight partitions by ſmall pieces of wood which form grooves, into which the slides run,andare thus eaſily thruſt into or drawn out of the frame. The upper slide (a) in the model sent to the society by Mr Swayne is of paper only, and deſigned to receive the worms as soon as hatched ; the two next <hi rend="italic">(b, b)</hi> are of catgut, the threads about one-tenth of an inch diſtant from each other : theſe are for the infects when a little advanced in ſize : the five lower ones, marked <hi rend="italic">c, c, c, c, c,</hi> are of wickerwork; but, as Mr Swayne afterwards found, netting may be ſubſtituted with advantage inſtead of wicker bottoms. Under each of theſe, as well as under thoſe of catgut, are Aiders made of paper, to prevent the dung of the worms from falling on thoſe feeding below them.</p><p>The management of ſilk worms is next to be attended to. The proper time for hatching them is when the leaves of the mulberry are full grown, or nearly ſo ; that as ſoon as theſe infects are capable of receiving food they may obtain it in abundance. To attempt to hatch them sooner would be hurtful, as the weather would not be ſufficiently warm. Besides, as leaves are neceſſary to the life of a vegetable, if the young leaves of the mulberry-tree are cropped as ſoon as they are unfolded, the tree will be so much weakened as to be incapable of producing ſo many leaves as it would otherwiſe have done ; and if this practice be frequently repeated, will inevitably be deſtroyed.</p><p>When the proper ſeaſon is arrived, the eggs may be hatched either by the heat of the fun, when it happens to be ſtrong enough, or by placing them in a ſmall room moderately heated by a stove or fire; and after being expoſed for fix or ſeven days to a gentle heat, the ſilk worm issues from the egg in the form of a ſmall black hairy caterpillar. When Mr Swayne’s apparatus is used, the worms are to be kept on the drawers wfith, paper bottoms till they are grown ſo large as not readily to creep through the gauze-bottomed drawers : they are then to be placed on thoſe drawers, where they are to remain till their excrements are so large as not readily to fall through ; when this is the case, they muſt be removed to the drawers with the wicker or netting bottoms, and fed thereon till they ſhow ſymptoms of being about to ſpin. It is ſcarcely neceſſary to mention, that the paper hides beneath the gauze and wicker drawers are intended to receive the dung, which ſhould be emptied as often as the worms are fed, at leaſt once a-day ; or to direct, that when the worms are fed, the Aides are to be firſt drawn out a conſiderable way, and the drawers to rest upon them.</p><p>It has been already mentioned, that wet or damp food is exceedingly prejudicial to theſe infects. It produces contagious and fatal diſeaſes. To prevent the necessity of giving them wet or damp food, attention<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0490.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0484"/>
ought to be paid to the weather, so that when there is an immediate prospect of rain, a sufficient quantity of leaves may be gathered to ſerve the worms two or three days. In this country, the leaves of the black or red mulberry tree may be preſerved good for food, although kept four or five days, by the following method; When new gathered, lay them looſely in glazed earthen veſſels, place theſe in a cold place, well aired, not expoſed to drought.</p><p>The utmoſt attention muſt be paid to preſerve the place where ſilk worms are kept as clean as poſſible: the houſe or room muſt be well ventilated, that no noxious vapours be accumulated. By ſome experiments of Μ. Faujas de St Fond, which are recorded in his hiſtory of Languedoc, it appears that the ſilk worm is much injured by foul air. All decayed leaves muſt be removed from them, as it is now well known that they emit bad air in great abundance.</p><p><note anchored="false" n="4" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>Bee, N⁰ 95.</p></note> One of the most difficult brandies of the management of ſilk worms has hitherto been the cleaning without bruising them. To avoid this inconvenience, the peaſants in France and Italy frequently allow the whole litter to remain without ever cleaning them, which is the cauſe of that unwholeſome ſtench that has been ſo often remarked by thoſe who viſit the places for rearing ſilk worms in theſe countries. This difficulty may be effectually removed by providing a net, or, what would be ſtill better, a wire-bottomed frame, wrought into large meſhes like a riddle. Have that made of a ſize exactly ſufficient to cover the wooden box in which the worms are kept. When you mean to ſhift them, ſpread freſh leaves into the wire baſket ; and let it down gently over the worms till it comes within their reach. They no ſooner perceive the freſh food than they abandon the rubbiſh below, and creep through the meſhes, ſo as to fix themſelves upon the leaves ; then by gently raiſing the freſh baſket, and drawing out the board below (which ought to be made to flip out like the flip bottom of a bird’s cage), you get off all the excrements and decayed leaves, without incommoding the worms in the smalleſt degree ; and along with the litter you will draw off an inch or two in depth of the fouleſt mephitic vapours. To get entirely rid of theſe, the board, when thus taken out, ſhould be carried without doors, and there cleaned ; and the flip board immediately replaced to receive all the excrements and offals. After it is replaced, the wire frame that had been elevated a little, may be allowed to deſcend to a convenient diſtance above the board without touching it. Thus will there be left a vacant space for the mephitic air to fall below the worms, ſo as to allow them to inhabit a wholeſome region of the atmoſphere.</p><p>When a freſh ſupply of food is to be given before cleaning, the wire frame ought to be let down as cloſe to the board as can be ſafely done, and another wire- bottomed frame put over it, with freſh leaves, as before deſcribed. When the worms have abandoned that in their turn, let the slip-board, together with the lower wire frame, be drawn out and removed, and ſo on as often as neceſſary. To admit of this alternate change, every table, conſiſting of one slip-board, ought to have two ſets of wire-bottomed frames of the ſame ſize ; the slip board to be always put into its place immediately after it is cleaned, and the wire frames reſerved to be afterwards placed over the other. By this mode of management, it is probable that the worms would be ſaved from the diseases engendered by the mephitic air, and the numerous deaths that are the consequence of it avoided.</p><p>Dr Anderſon, to whom we have already acknowledged our obligations, and to whom this country has been much indebted for valuable works on agriculture, the fiſheries, &amp; c. adviſes thoſe who have the management of ſilk worms to ſtrew a thin ſtratum of freſh flaked quicklime upon the slip-board each time it is cleaned, immediately before it is put into its place. This would absorb the mephitic gas, for as ſoon as it is generated it would deſcend upon the ſurface of the quicklime. Thus would the worms be kept continually in an atmoſphere of pure air<note anchored="false" n="5" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>Transactions of the Society for the Encouragement of Arts, vol. vii. p. 12.</p></note> (c). Were the walls of the apartments to be frequently waſhed with quicklime and water, it would tend much to promote cleanlineſs at a ſmall expence, and augment the healthineſs of the worms as well as that of the perſons who attend them.</p><p>When the ſilk worm refuſes its food, and leaves silky traces on the leaves over which it paffes, it is a proof that it is ready to begin its cocoon. It is now neceſſary to form a new receptacle, which is commonly done by pinning together papers in the ſhape of inverted cones with broad baſes. ‘‘ This method (ſays Mr Swayne<note anchored="true" n="6" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>(c) To put this queſtion beyond a doubt, Mr Blancard made the following comparative experiments, which were ſeveral times repeated. “ I procured (says he) four glaſs jars nine inches high and five in diameter, doling the mouth with cork ſtoppers. After which I placed in each of them, in their ſecond life (ſo <hi rend="italic">mue may</hi> be tranſlated which means the ſtage between the different ſickneſſes), twelve ſilk worms, which were fed four times a-day ; and. which I confined in this kind of priſon all their life, without taking away either their dead companions or their ordure or litter. I ſprinkled with chalk the worms of only two of theſe jars, and kept the two others to compare with them.</p><p>“ In thoſe without lime, I never obtained neither more nor leſs than three ſmall and imperfect cocoons (<hi rend="italic">chiques ou bouffard),</hi> and in the two that were ſprinkled with lime, I had very often twelve, and never leſs than nine fine full-sized firm cocoons.”</p><p>This experiment affords the moſt ſatisfactory proof of the utility of this proceſs. From a number of trials he found, that even when the worms were covered with a very large proportion of lime, they never were in any way. incommoded by it.</p></note>), where there are many worms, is exceedingly tedious, waſtes much paper, and uſes a large number of pins ; beſides, as the ſilk worm always weaves an outer covering or defenſive web before it begins the cocoon or oval ball, I apprehended that it cauſed a needleſs waſte of ſilk in forming the broad web at the top. The method I make uſe of is, to roll a ſmall piece of paper (an uncut octavo leaf, ſuch as that of an old magazine, is<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0491.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0485"/>
ſufficient for three), round my fore-finger, and to give it a twiſt at the bottom ; which is done with the utmoſt expedition, and gives no occaſion for the uſe of pins. Theſe rolled paper-cases being likewiſe of a form more nearly reſembling that of a cocoon, with a much narrower opening on the top than the others, takes away the seceſſity of wasting much silk in the outer web, and conſequently leaves more to be employed in forming the ball. The ſilk is readily taken out of theſe cases by untwiſting the bottom ; and if this be done with moderate care, and the papers are preſerved, they will ſerve ſeveral times for the like purpoſe.”</p><p>Others adviſe, that when the ſilk worms are preparing to ſpin, little buſhes of heath, broom, or twigs, ſhould be ſtuck upright near the ſhelf or box in which they are incloſed : the worms mount theſe, and attach their web to them.</p><p>When the worms are ready to mount, in order to ſpin, if the weather be hot, attended with thunder, you will see them in a languiſhing condition ; your care muſt then be to revive them, which is effected thus : Take a few eggs and onions, and fry them in a pan with ſome ſtale hog’s lard, the ranker the better, and make pancake ; which done, carry it ſmoaking hot into the room where they are kept, and go round the chamber with it. You will be ſurpriſed to see how the ſmell revives them, excites thoſe to eat who have not done feeding, and makes the others that are ready to ſpin climb up the twigs.</p><p>In about ten or twelve days, according to the accounts which we have received from Mr Andrew Wright of Paiſley, it may be saſely concluded, that if the worms have finiſhed their work, the cocoons may be collected.</p><p>We ſhall now diſtinguiſh the cocoons from one another according to their value or their uſe, and conſider the method of managing each. They may be diſtinguiſhed into the good and bad. The good cocoons maybe known by theſe marks : they are little, ſtrong, and firm ; have a fine grain, both ends are round, and they are free from ſpots. Among the good cocoons alſo may be arranged thoſe which are called <hi rend="italic">calcined</hi> cocoons, in which</p><p>the worm, in conſequence of ſickneſs, is petrified or reduced to a fine powder. Theſe cocoons produce more ſilk than others, and are ſold in Piedmont at half as much again. They may be diſtinguiſhed by the noiſe which, the worm makes when the cocoon is ſhaken. Of the bad cocoons there are six ſpecies : 1. The <hi rend="italic">pointed cocoons,</hi> one extremity of which ends in a point ; the ſilk which covers the point is weak, and ſoon breaks or tears. 2. The <hi rend="italic">cocalons,</hi> which are bigger, but the contexture is weak. 3. The <hi rend="italic">dupions,</hi> or double cocoons, which have been formed by the joint labour of two and ſometimes of three worms. 4. The souff <hi rend="italic">lons,</hi> which have a looſe contexture, ſometimes ſo loose that they are transparent.</p><p>5. The <hi rend="italic">perforated cocoons,</hi> which have a hole at one end.</p><p>6. The <hi rend="italic">bad choquette,</hi> which is compoſed of defective cocoons, ſpotted or rotten. Beſides theſe there is the <hi rend="italic">good choquette,</hi> which does not properly belong to either of theſe two classes : it is formed of thoſe cocoons in which the worm dies before the ſilk is brought to perfection. The worms adhere to one side of the cocoon, and therefore when the cocoon is ſhaken will not rattle : the ſilk is as fine, but is not of ſo bright a colour, nor is ſo ſtrong and nervous, as that which is obtained from good cocoons.</p><p>The cocoons which are kept for breeding are called <hi rend="italic">royal</hi> cocoons. For ſelecting and preſerving theſe, we have been favoured with some valuable inſtructions by Mr Wright of Paiſley, which we ſhall preſent to our readers—The largeſt and beſt cocoons ought to be kept for breed, about an equal number of males and females; the cocoons that contain the former are ſharper pointed at the ends than thoſe that contain the latter. Although it ſhould happen that there are more females than males, little inconvenience or ill conſequences can ariſe from it, as one male will ſerve two or three females, if the time of their coming out of the cocoons anfwer. About 12 or 15 days after they begin to ſpin, the cocoons for breed may be laid on ſheets of white paper ; about this time the moth opens for itſelf a paſſage through the end of its cocoon, and iſſues out. When the female has laid her eggs, which on an average may amount to 250, they are ſpread upon ſheets of paper and hung up to dry in ſome place where they may not be expoſed to the heat of the ſun : after being dried they muſt be kept in a cool: well-aired place, where neither vapours nor moiſture can reach them. That they may be preſerved ſrom external accidents, as insects of different kinds will deſtroy them, and mice is their enemy in all the ſtages of their exiſtence, they ſhould be kept in ſtone pots or glaſs bottles with their mouths stopped, and there remain until brought out next ſeaſon to be hatched.</p><p>The cocoons from which the silk is to be immediately wound muſt be expoſed to the heat of an oven, in order to kill the chryſalis or aurelia, which would otherwiſe eat its way through the cocoon, and render it uſeleſs. The following directions are given for managing this proceſs. by one of the firſt silk manufacturers in Italy.</p><p>Put your cocoons in long fhallow baſkets, and fill them up within an inch of the top. You then cover them with paper, and put a wrapper over that. Theſe baſkets are to be diſpoſed in an oven, whoſe heat is as near as can be that of an oven from which the. bread is juſt drawn after being baked. When your cocoons have remained therein near an hour, you muſt draw them out; and to ſee whether all tire worms are dead, draw out a dupion from the middle of your baſket and open it : if the worm be dead, you may conclude all the reſt are ſo; becauſe the contexture of the dupion being ſtronger than that of the other cocoons, it is conſequently leſs eaſy to be penetrated by the heat. You muſt obſerve to take it from the middle of the baſket, becauſe in that part the heat is least perceptible. After you have drawn your baſkets from the oven, you muſt firſt cover each of them with a woollen, blanket or rug, leaving the wrapper besides, and then you pile them above one another. If your baking has ſucceeded, your woollen cover will be all over wet with a kind of dew, the thickness of your little finger. If there be leſs, it is a sign your coceons have been too much or too little baked. If too much baked, the worm, being over-dried, cannot transpire a humour he no longer contains, and your cocoon is then burnt. It not enough baked, the worm has not been ſufficiently penetrated by the heat to diſtil the liquor he contains, and in that case is not dead.</p><p>You muſt let your baſkets ſtand thus covered five or six hours if poſſible, in order to keep in the heat, as this makes an end of ſtifling thoſe worms which might have avoided the firſt impreſſion of the fire. You are like-<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0492.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0486"/>
wise to take great care to let your cocoons ſtand in the oven the time that is neceſſary; for if they do not ſtand long enough, your worms are only ſtunned for a time and will afterwards be revived. If, on the other hand, you leave them too long in the oven, you burn them : many inſtances of theſe two cafes are frequently to be met with. It is a good ſign when you ſee ſome of the butterflies ſpring out from the cocoons which have been baked, becauſe you may be certain they are not burnt. For if you would kill them all to the laſt worm, you would burn many cocopns which might be more expoſed to the heat than that particular worm.</p><p>The next operation is the winding of the ſilk. Before you begin to wind, you muſt prepare your cocoons as follows :</p><p>1. In ſtripping them of that waſte ſilk that ſurrounds them, and which ſerved to faſten them to the twigs. This burr is proper to fluff quilts, or other ſuch uſes ; you may likewiſe ſpin it to make ſtockings, but they will be coarſe and ordinary.</p><p>2. You muſt sort your cocoons, ſeparating them into different claſſes in order to wind them apart. Theſe claſſes are, the good white cocoons ; the good cocoons of all the other colours ; the dupions ; the cocalons, among which are included the weak cocoons ; the good choquette ; and, laſtly, the bad choquette. In sorting the cocoons, you will always find ſome perforated cocoons amongſt them, whoſe worm is already born ; thoſe you muſt ſet apart for fleuret. You will likewiſe find ſome fouillons, but very few ; for which reason you may put them among the bad choquette, and they run up into waſte.</p><p>The good cocoons, as well white as yellow, are the eaſieſt to wind ; thoſe which require the greateſt care and pains are the cocalons ; you muſt wind them in cooler water than the others, and if you take care to give them to a good windſter, you will have as good ſilk from them as the rest. You muſt likewiſe have careful windſters for the dupions and choquettes. Theſe two ſpecies require hotter water than the common cocoons.</p><p>The good cocoons are to be wound in the following manner : Firſt, chooſe an open convenient place for your filature, the longer the better, if you intend to have many furnaces and coppers. The building ſhould be high and open on one side, and walled on the other, as well to ſcreen you from the cold winds and receive the ſun, as to give a free paſſage to the ſteam or your basons or coppers.</p><p>Theſe coppers or basons are to be diſpoſed (when the building will admit of it) in a row on each ſide oſ the filature, as being the moſt convenient method of placing them, for by that means in walking up and down you ſee what every one is about. And theſe basons ſhould be two and two together, with a chimney between every couple.</p><p>Having prepared your reels (which are turned by hands, and require a quick eye), and your fire being a light one under every bason, your windſter muſt stay till the water is as hot as it can be without boiling. When every thing is ready, you throw into your basons two or three handfuls of cocoons, which you gently bruſh over with a wiſk about six inches long, cut ſtumpy like a broom worn out : by theſe means the threads of the cocoons ſtick to the wisk. You muſt</p><p>diſengage theſe threads from the wiſk, and purge them by drawing theſe ends with your fingers till they come off entirely clean. This operation is called <hi rend="italic">la Battue.</hi></p><p>When the threads are quite clear, you muſt paſs four of them (if you will wind fine ſilk) through each of the holes in a thin iron bar that is placed horizontally at the edge oſ your bason ; afterwards you twiſt the two ends (which conſiſt of four cocoons each) twenty or twenty-five times, that the four ends in each thread may the better join together in croſſing each other, and that your ſilk may be plump, which otherwiſe would be flat.</p><p>Your windſter muſt always have a bowl of cold water by her, to dip her fingers in, and to ſprinkle very often the ſaid bar, that the heat may not burn the thread.</p><p>Your threads, when thus twiſted, go upon two iron hooks called rampins, which are placed higher, and from thence they go upon the reel. At one end of the axis of the reel is a cog-wheel, which catching in the teeth of the poſt-rampin, moves it from the right to the left, and conſequently the thread that is upon it ; ſo that your ſilk is wound on the reel croſsways, and your threads form two hanks of about four fingers broad.</p><p>As often as the cocoons you wind are done, or break or diminiſh only, you muſt join freſh ones to keep up the number requiſite, or the proportion ; becauſe, as the cocoons wind off, the thread being finer, you muſt join two cocoons half wound to replace a new one : Thus you may wind three new ones and two half wound, and your ſilk is from four to five cocoons.</p><p>When you would join a freſh thread, you muſt lay one end on your finger, which you throw lightly on the other threads that are winding, and it joins them immediately, and continues to go up with the reft. You muſt not wind off your cocoons too bare or to the laſt, becauſe when they are near at an end, the <hi rend="italic">bairre,</hi> that is, the husk, joins in with the other threads, and makes the ſilk foul and gouty.</p><p>When you have finiſhed your firſt parcel, you muſt clean your basons, taking out all the ſtriped worms, as well as the cocoons, on which there is a little ſilk, which you firſt open and take out the worm, and then throw them into a baſket by you, into which you likewiſe caſt the looſe ſilk that comes off in making the battue.</p><p>You then proceed as before with other two or three handfuls of cocoons ; you make a new battue ; you purge them, and continue to wind the ſame number of cocoons or their equivalent, and ſo to the end.</p><p>As was already mentioned, the windſter muſt always have a bowl of cold water by her, to ſprinkle the bar, to cool her fingers every time she dips them in the hot water, and to pour into her bason when neceſſary, that is, when her water begins to boil. You muſt be very careful to twiſt your threads a ſufficient number of times, about 25, otherwiſe your ſilk remains flat, inſtead of being round and full ; beſides, when the ſilk is not well croſſed, it never can be clean, becauſe a gout or nub that comes from a cocoon will paſs through a ſmall number of theſe twiſts, though a greater will flop it. Your thread then breaks, and you paſs what foulness there may be in the middle of your reel be<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0493.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0487"/>
tween the two hanks, which ſerves for a head-band to tie them.</p><p>You muſt obſerve that your water be juſt in a proper degree of heat. When it is too hot, the thread is dead, and has no body ; when it is too cold, the ends which form the thread do not join well, and form a harſh ill-qualified ſilk.</p><p>You muſt change the water in your baſon four times a-day for your dupions and choquette, and twice only for good cocoons when you wind fine ſilk ; but if you wind coarſe ſilk, it is neceſſary to change it three or four times. For if you were not to change the water, the ſilk would not be ſo bright and gloſſy, becauſe the worm contained in the cocoons foul it very conſiderably. You muſt endeavour as much as poſſible to wind with clear water, for if there are too many worms in it, your ſilk is covered with a kind of dust which attracts the moth, and deſtroys your ſilk.</p><p>You may wind your ſilk of what ſize you pleaſe, from one cocoon to 1000 ; but it is difficult to wind more than 30 in a thread. The nicety, and that in which conſiſts the greateſt difficulty, is to wind even ; becauſe as the cocoon winds off, the end is finer, and you muſt then join other cocoons to keep up the ſame ſize. This difficulty of keeping the ſilk always even is ſo great, that (excepting a thread of two cocoons, which we call such) we do not ſay a ſilk of three, of four, or of ſix cocoons ; but a ſilk of three to four, of four to five, of fix to ſeven cocoons. If you proceed to a coarſer, ſilk, you cannot calculate ſo nicely as to one cocoon more or leſs. We ſay, for example, from 12 to 15, from 15 to 20, and ſo on.</p><p>What number of worms are neceſſary to produce a certain quantity of ſilk has not been aſcertained. And as different perſons who wished to determine this point have had different reſults, the truth ſeems to be, that from various circumſtances the ſame number of worms may produce more ſilk at one time than at another. It is related in the ſecond volume of the Tranſactions of the Society for encouraging Arts, &amp; c. that Mrs Williams obtained nearly an ounce and a half of ſilk from 244 cocoons. Mr Swayne from 50 cocoons procured 100 grains. Miſs Rhodes obtained from 250 of the largeſt cocoons, three quarters of an ounce and a dram. From a paper in the ſecond volume of the American Tranſactions, which we have before referred to in the courſe of this article, we are informed that 150 ounces oſ good cocoons yield about 11 ounces of ſilk from five to ſix cocoons : if you wind coarſer, ſomething more. But what appears aſtoniſhing, Mr Salvatore Bertezen, an Italian, to whom the Society for encouraging Arts, &amp; c. adjudged their gold medal, raiſed five pounds of excellent ſilk from 12,000 worms.</p><p>The cocoons produce a thread of very unequal length ; you may meet with ſome that yield 1200 elk, whilſt others will ſcarcely afford 200 ells. In general, you may calculate the production of a cocoon from 500 to 600 ells in length.</p><p>As there is every reaſon to hope that the ſilk manufacture will ſoon be carried on with ardour in this country, and to a great extent, we are happy to learn that the ſilk-loom has been much improved lately by Mr Sholl of Bethnal-Green. It appears from the evidence of ſeveral gentlemen converſant in that branch of ſilk weaving to which this loom is particularly adapted,<note anchored="false" n="7" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>Transactions of the Society for encouraging Arts, &amp;c. vol. viii.</p></note> that</p><p>the advantages oſ this conſtruction are, the gaining light, a power of ſhortening the porry occaſionally, ſo as to suit any kind of work, being more portable, and having the gibbet firmly fixed, together with the diminution of price ; which, compared with the old loom, is as five pounds, the price of a loom on the old conſtruction, to three pounds ten ſhillings, the price of one of thoſe contrived by Mr Sholl ; and that, as the proportion of light work is to ſtrong work as nine to one, this sort of loom promiſes to be of very conſiderable advantage, particularly in making modes, or other black work.</p><p>As a plate of this loom, with proper references, will render its advantages moſt intelligible, we ſhall ſubjoin theſe : Plate CCCCLXVI. A, A, The fills; B, B, The breaſt-roll poſts : C, The cut tree; D, F), The uprights ; E, The burdown ; F, The batton ; G, The reeds; H, The harneſs ; I. The breaſt-roll ; K, The cheeſe; L, The gibbet: M, The treddles ; N, The tumblers ; 0, Short eounter-meſhes ; P, Long counter- meſhes ; Q, The porry ; R, R, Cane roll poſts ; S, The cane-roll ; T, The weight bar and weight ; U, U, Counter-weights ; W, The breaking rod ; X, X, Crois rods.</p><p><hi rend="italic">SILK-Worm.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Silk.</hi></p></div></body></text></TEI>