<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0524.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0518-02" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SKATING</label>,
an exerciſe on ice, both graceful and healthy. Although the ancients were remarkable for their dexterity in moſt of the athletic ſports, yet skating ſeems to have been unknown to them. It may therefore be conſidered as a modern invention ; and probably it derived its origin in Holland, where it was practiſed, not only as a graceful and elegant amuſement, but as an expeditious mode of travelling when the lakes and canals were frozen up during winter. In Holland long journeys are made upon ſkates with eaſe and expedition ; but in general less attention is there paid to graceful and elegant movements, than to the expedition and celerity of what is called journey <hi rend="italic">ſkating.</hi> It is only in thoſe countries where it is conſidered as an amuſement, that its graceful attitudes and movements can be ſtudied ; and there is no exerciſe whatever better calculated to ſet off the human figure to advantage. The acquirement of moſt exerciſes may be attained at an advanced period of life ; but to become an expert skater, it is neceſſary to begin the practice of the art at a very early age. It is difficult to reduce the art of skating to a ſyſtem. It is principally by the imitation of a good ſkater that a young practitioner can form his own practice. The Engliſh, though often remarkable for feats of agility upon ſkates, are very deficient in gracefulneſs ; which is partly owing to the conſtruction of the ſkates. They are too much curved in the surface which embraces the ice, conſequently they involuntarily bring the tilers of them round on the outſide upon a quick and ſmall circle ; whereas the ſkater, by uſing ſkates of a different conſtruction, leſs curved, has the command of his ſtroke, and can enlarge or diminiſh the circle according to his own wiſh and desire. The metropolis of Scotland has produced more inſtances of elegant ſkaters than perhaps any other country whatever; and the inſtitution of a Skating Club about 40 years ago, has contributed not a little to the improvement of this elegant amuſement. We are indebted for this article to a gentleman of that Club, who has made the practice and improvement of ſkating his particular ſtudy ; and as the nature oſ our work will not permit the inſertion of a full treatiſe on ſkating, we ſhall preſent our readers with a few inſtructions.</p><p>Thoſe who wiſh to be proficients ſhould begin at an early period of life ; and ſhould firſt endeavour to throw off the fear which always attends the commencement of an apparently hazardous amuſement. They will ſoon acquire a facility of moving on the inside : when they have done this, they muſt endeavour to acquire the movement on the outſide of the ſkates; which is nothing more than throwing themſelves upon the outer edge of the ſkate, and making the balance of their body tend towards that<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0525.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0519"/>
ſide, which will neceſſarily enable them to form a ſemicircle. In this, much aſſiſtance may be derived from placing a bag of lead-ſhot in the pocket next to the foot employed in making the outſide ſtroke, which will produce an artificial poiſe of the body, which afterwards will become natural by practice. At the commencement of the outſide ſtroke, the knee of the employed limb ſhould be a little bended, and gradually brought to a rectilineal poſition when the ſtroke is completed. When the practitioner becomes expert in forming the ſemicircle with both feet, he is then to join them together, and proceed progreſſively and alternately with both feet, which will carry him forward with a graceful movement. Care ſhould be taken to uſe very little muſcular exertion, for the impelling motion ſhould proceed from the mechanical impulſe of the body thrown into ſuch a poſition as to regulate the stroke. At taking the outſide ſtroke, the body ought to be thrown forward eaſily, the unemployed limb kept in a direct line with the body, and the face and eyes directly looking forward : the unemployed foot ought to be ſtretched towards the ice, with the toes in a direct line with the leg. In the time of making the curve, the body muſt be gradually, and almoſt imperceptibly, raiſed, and the unemployed limb brought in the ſame manner forward ; ſo that, at finishing the curve, the body will bend a ſmall degree backward, and the unemployed foot will be about two inches before the other, ready to embrace the ice and form a correſpondent curve. The muſcular movement of the whole body muſt correſpond with the movement of the ſkate, and ſhould be regulated ſo as to be almoſt imperceptible to the ſpectators. Particular attention ſhould be paid in carrying round the head and eyes with a regular and imperceptible motion ; for nothing ſo much diminiſhes the grace and elegance of ſkating as ſudden jerks and exertions, which are too frequently uſed by the generality of ſkaters. The management of the arms likewiſe deserves attention. There is no mode of diſpoſing of them more gracefully in ſkating outſide, than folding the hands into each other, or uſing a muff.</p><p>There are various feats of activity and manœuvres uſed upon ſkates ; but they are ſo various that we cannot pretend to detail them. Moving on the outſide is the primary object for a ſkater to attain ; and when he becomes an adept in that, he will eaſily acquire a facility in executing other branches of the art. There are few exerciſes but will afford him hints of elegant and graceful attitudes. For example, nothing can be more beautiful than the attitude of drawing the bow and arrow whilſt the ſkater is making a large circle on the outſide : the manual exerciſe and military ſalutes have likewiſe a pretty effect when uſed by an expert ſkater.</p></div></body></text></TEI>