<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0612.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0606-08" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SOPHI</label>,
or SOFI, a title given to the emperor of</p><p>Persia ; importing as much as wiſe, ſage, or philoſopher.</p><p>The title is by ſome ſaid to have taken its riſe from a young ſhepherd named <hi rend="italic">Sοphi,</hi> who attained to the crown of Persia in 1370 ; others derive it from the <hi rend="italic">ſophoi</hi> or ſages anciently called <hi rend="italic">magi.</hi> Voſſius gives a different account of the word : sophi in Arabic, he obſerves, ſignifies <hi rend="italic">wool</hi>; and he adds, that it was applied by the Turks out of deriſion to the kings of Perſia ever ſince Iſhmael’s time; becauſe, according to their ſcheme of religion, he is to wear no other covering on his head but an ordinary red woollen fluff; whence the Persians are alſo called <hi rend="italic">hetzelbaſchs,</hi> q. d. <hi rend="italic">red-heads.</hi> But Bochart assures us, that sophi in the original Perſian language, ſignifies one that is pure in his religion, and who prefers the ſervice of God in all things : and derives it from an order of religious called by the ſame name. The ſophis value themſelves on their illuſtrious extraction. They are deſcended in a right line from Houſſein, ſecond son of Ali, Mahomet’s couſin, and Fatima, Mahomet’s daughter.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sophis,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Sofees.</hi> a kind of order of religious among the Mahometans in Perſia, anſwering to what are otherwiſe called <hi rend="italic">dervises,</hi> and among the Arabs and Indians <hi rend="italic">faquirs.</hi> Some will have them called ſophis from a kind of coarſe camblet which they wear called <hi rend="italic">ſouf,</hi> from the city Souf in Syria, where it is principally manufactured. The more eminent of thoſe ſophis are complimented with the title s <hi rend="italic">chiek,</hi> that is, <hi rend="italic">reverend,</hi> much as in Romiſh countries the religious are called <hi rend="italic">reverend fathers.</hi> Schiek sophi, who laid the foundation of the grandeur of the royal houſe of Perſia, was the founder, or rather the reſtorer of this order: Iſhmael, who conquered Perſia, was himſelf a sophi, and greatly valued himſelf on his being ſo. He choſe all the guards of his person from among the religious of this order; and would have all the great lords of his court ſophis. The king of Perſia is ſtill grandmaſter of the order; and the lords continue to enter into it, though it be now fallen under ſome contempt.</p></div></body></text></TEI>