<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0540.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0534-03" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SLEEP</label>,
that ſtate of the body in which, though the vital functions continue, the ſenſes are not affected by the ordinary impreſſions of external objects. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Dreams</hi>; and <hi rend="smallcaps">Physiology,</hi> n⁰ 287.</p><p><hi rend="italic">SLEEP-Walker,</hi> one who walks in his ſleep. Many intances might be related of perſons who were addicted to this practice ; but it will be ſufficient to ſelect one remarkable inſtance from a report made to the Phydical Society of Lauſanne, by a committee of gentlemen appointed to examine a young man who was accuſtomed to walk in his ſleep.</p><p>“ The dispoſition to sleep-walking ſeems, in the opinion of this committee, to depend on a particular affection of the nerves, which both seizes and quits the patient dining ſleep. Under the influence of this affection, the imagination repreſents to him the objects that ſtruck him while awake, with as much force as if they really affected his senses ; but does not make him perceive any of thoſe that are actually presented to his ſenſes, except in ſo far as they are connected with the dreams which engrols him at the time. If, during this ſtate, the imagination has no determined purpose, he receives the impreſſion of objects as if he were awake;</p><p>only, however, when the imagination is excited to bend its attention towards them. The perceptions obtained in this ſtate are very accurate, and, when once received, the imagination renews them occaſionally with as much force as if they were again acquired by means of the ſenſes. Laſtly, theſe academicians ſuppoſe, that the impreſſions received during this ſtate of the ſenſes diſappear entirely when the person awakes, and do not return till the return of the ſame dispoſition in the nervous system.</p><p>"Their remarks were made on the Sieur Devaud, a lad thirteen years and a half old, who lives in the town of Vevey, and who is ſubject to that ſingular affection or disease called S <hi rend="italic">omnambulism</hi> or ſleep-walking. This lad poſſeſſes a ſtrong and robuſt conſtitution, but his nervous ſyſtem appears to be organiſed with peculiar delicacy, and to diſcover marks of the greateſt senſibility and irritability. His ſenſes of ſmell, taſte, and touch, are exquiſite ; he is ſubject to fits of immoderate and involuntary laughter, and he ſometimes likewiſe weeps without any apparent cause.</p><p>“ This young man does not walk in his ſleep every night ; ſeveral weeks ſometimes paſs without any appearance of a fit. He is ſubject to the diſeaſe generally two nights succeſſively, one fit laſting for ſeveral hours. The longeſt are from three to four hours, and they commonly begin about three or four o’clock in the morning.</p><p>“ The fit may be prolonged, by gently paſſing the finger or a feather over his upper lip, and this flight irritation likewiſe accelerates it. Having once fallen aſleep upon a ſtaircale, his upper lip was thus irritated with a feather, when he immediately ran down the ſteps with great precipitation, and reſumed all his accuſtomed activity. This experiment was repeated ſeveral times.</p><p>“ The young Devaud thinks he has obſerved, that, on the evenings previous to a fit, he is ſensible of a certain heavineſs in his head, but eſpecially of a great weight in his eyelids.</p><p>“ His ſleep is at all times unquiet, but particularly wſhen the fits are about to ſeize him. During his ſleep, motions are observable in every part of his body, with flatting and palpitations; he utters broken words, ſometimes sits up in his bed, and afterwards lies down again. He then begins to pronounce words more diſtinctly, he riſes abruptly, and acts as he is inſtigated by the dream that then posseſſes him. He is ſometimes in ſleep ſubject to continued and involuntary motions.</p><p>The departure of the fit is always preceded by two or three minutes of calm ſleep, during wſhich he ſnores. He then awakes rubbing his eyes like a perſon who has ſlept quietly.</p><p>“ It is dangerous to awaken him during the fit, eſpecially if it is done suddenly ; for then he sometimes falls into convulſions. Having riſen one night with the intention of going to eat grapes, he left the houſe, paſſed through the town, and went to a vineyard where he expected good cheer. He was followed by ſeveral perlons, who kept at ſome diſtance from him, one of whom fired a piſtol, the noiſe of which inſtantly awakened him, and he fell down without ſenſe. He was carried home and brought to himſelf, when he recollected very well the having been awakened in the vineyard ; but nothing more, except the flight at being found there alone, which had made him swoon.</p><p>“ After the fits he generally feels a degree of laſſi-<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0541.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0535"/>
tude : ſometimes, though rarely, of indiſpoſition. At the end of one of thoſe fits, of which the gentlemen of the committee were witneſſes, he was affected with vomitings ; but he is always ſoon reſtored.</p><p>‘‘ When he is awaked, he never for the moſt part recollects any of the actions he has been doing during the fit.</p><p>“ The ſubject of his dreams is circumſcribed in a ſmall circle of objects, that relate to the few ideas with which at his age his mind is furniſhed ; ſuch as his leſſons, the church, the bells, and eſpecially tales of ghoſts. It is ſufficient to ſtrike his imagination the evening before a fit with ſome tale, to direct his ſomnambuliſm towards the object of it. There was read to him while in this ſituation the ſtory of a robber ; he imagined the very next moment that he ſaw robbers in the room. However, as he is much diſpoſed to dream that he is ſurrounded with them, it cannot be affirmed that this was an effect of the reading. It is obſerved, that when his ſupper has been more plentiful than uſual, his dreams are more dismal.</p><p>“ In their report, the gentlemen of the committee dwell much on the ſtate of this young man’s ſenſes, on the impreſſion made upon them by ſtrange objects, and on the life they are of to him.</p><p>“ A bit of ſtrong ſmelling wood produced in him a degree of reſtleſſneſs ; the fingers had the ſame effect, whether from their ſmell or their tranſpiration. He knew wine in which there was wormwood by the ſmell, and ſaid that it was not wine for his table. Metals make no impreſſion on him.</p><p>“ Having been preſented with a little common wine while he was in a ſtate of apathy, and all his motions were performed with languor, he drank oſ it willingly ; but the irritation which it occaſioned produced a deal of vivacity in all his words, motions, and actions, and cauſed him to make involuntary grimaces.</p><p>“ Once he was obſerved dreſſing himſelf in perfect darkneſs. His clothes were on a large table, mixed with thoſe of ſome other perſons ; he immediately perceived this, and complained of it much ; at laſt a ſmall light was brought, and then he dreſſed himſelf with ſufficient preciſion. If he is teaſed or gently pinched, he is always ſenſible of it, except he is at the time ſtrongly engroſſed with ſome other thing, and wiſhes to ſtrike the offender ; however, he never attacks the perſon who has done the ill, but an ideal being whom his imagination preſents to him, and whom he purſues thro’ the chamber without running againſt the furniture, nor can the perdons whom he meets in his way divert him from his purſuit.</p><p>“ While his imagination was employed on various ſubjects, he heard a clock ſtrike, which repeated at every ſtroke the note of the cuckoo. There are cuckoos here, ſaid he ; and, upon being deſired, he imitated the ſong of that bird immediately.</p><p>“ When he wiſhes to ſee an object, he makes an effort to lift his eyelids ; but they are ſo little under his command, that he can hardly raiſe them a line or two, while he draws up his eyebrows ; the iris at that time appears fixed, and his eye dim. When any thing is preſented to him, and he is told of it, he always half opens his eyes with a degree of difficulty, and then shuts them after he has taken what was offered to him.</p><p>“ The report infers ſrom theſe facts, and from many</p><p>others relative to the different ſenſes, that their functions are not ſuſpended as to what the sleep-walker wiſhes to ſee, that is, as to all thoſe perceptions which accord with the objects about which his imagination is occupied ; that he may alſo be diſpoſed to receive thoſe impreſſions, when his imagination has no other object at the time ; that in order to ſee, he is obliged to open his eyes as much as he can, but when the impreſſion is once made, it remains ; that objects may ſtrike his fight without ſtriking his imagination, if it is not intereſted in them ; and that he is ſometimes informed of the preſence of objects without either ſeeing or touching them.</p><p>“ Having engaged him to write a theme, ſay the committee, we ſaw him light a candle, take pen, ink, and paper, from the drawer of his table, and begin to write, while his maſter dictated. As he was writing, we put a thick paper before his eyes, notwithſtanding which he continued to write and to form his letters very diſtinctly ; ſhowing ſigns, however, that ſomething was incommoding him, which apparently proceeded from the obſtruction which the paper, being held too near his noſe, gave to his reſpiration.</p><p>“ Upon another occasion, the young ſomnambuliſt aroſe at five o’clock in the morning, and took the neceſſary materials for writing, with his copy-book. He meant to have begun at the top of a page ; but finding it already written on, he came to the blank part of the leaf, and wrote ſome time from the following words, <hi rend="italic">Fiunt ignari pigritia-ils deviennent ignorans par la pareſſe ;</hi> and, what is remarkable, after ſeveral lines he perceived he had forgot the <hi rend="italic">s</hi> in the word <hi rend="italic">ignorans,</hi> and had put erroneously a double <hi rend="italic">r</hi> in <hi rend="italic">pareſſe ;</hi> he then gave over writing, to add the <hi rend="italic">s</hi> he had forgot, and to eraſe the ſuperfluous r.</p><p>“ Another time he had made, oſ his own accord, a piece of writing, in order, as he ſaid, to pleaſe his maſter. It conſiſted of three kinds of writing, text, half text, and ſmall writ ; each of them performed with the proper pen. He drew, in the corner of the ſame paper, the figure of a hat ; he then aſked for a penknife to take out a blot of ink which he had made between two letters, and he eraſed it without injuring them. Laſtly, he made ſome arithmetical calculations with great accuracy.</p><p>“ In order to explain ſome of the facts obſerved by the academicians which we have here mentioned, they eſtabliſh two general obſervations, which reſult from what they have ſaid with reſpect to the ſenſes and the dreams of this sleep-walker.</p><p>“ 1. That he is obliged to open his eyes, in order to recogniſe objects which he wiſhes to ſee ; but the impreſſion once made, although rapidly, is vivid enough to ſuperſede the neceſſity of his opening them again, to view the ſame objects anew ; that is, the ſame objects are afterwards preſented to his imagination with as much force and preciſion as if he actually ſaw them.</p><p>“ 2. That his imagination, thus warmed, repreſents to him objects, and ſuch as he figures to himſelf, with as much vivacity as if he really ſaw them ; and, laſtly, that all his ſenſes, being ſubordinate to his imagination, ſeem concentrated in the object with which it is occupied, and have at that time no perception of any thing but what relates to that object.</p><p>“ Theſe two cauſes united ſeem to them ſufficient<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0542.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0536"/>
for explaining one of the moſt ſingular facts that occurred to their obſervation, to wit, how the young Devaud can write, although he has his eyes ſhut, and an obſtacle before them. His paper is imprinted on his imagination, and every letter which he means to write is alſo painted there, at the place in which it ought to ſtand on the paper, and without being confounded with the other letters ; now it is clear that his hand, which is obedient to the will of his imagination, will trace them on the real paper, in the same order in which they are repreſented on that which is pictured in his head. It is thus that he is able to write ſeveral letters, ſeveral ſentences, and entire pieces of writing ; and what ſeems to confirm the idea, that the young Devaud writes according to the paper painted on his imagination is, that a certain ſleep-walker, who is deſcribed in the French Encyclopedie (article <hi rend="italic">Somnambulism),</hi> having written ſomething on a paper, another piece of paper of the ſame ſize was ſubſtituted in its ſtead, which he took for his own, and made upon this blank paper the corrections he meant to have made on the other which had been taken away, preciſely in the places where they would have been.</p><p>“ It appears from the recital of another fact, that Devaud, intending to write at the top of the firſt leaf of a white paper book, <hi rend="italic">Vevey, le—</hi> flopped a moment as if to recollect the day of the month, left a blank ſpace, and then proceeded to <hi rend="italic">Decembre</hi> 1787 ; after which he aſked ſor an almanac : a little book, ſuch as is given to children for a new year’s gift, was offered to him; he took it, opened it, brought it near his eyes, then threw it down on the table. An almanac which he knew was then preſented to him ; this was in German, and of a form ſimilar to the almanac of Vevey : he took it, and then ſaid, ‘ What is this they have given me ; here, there is your German almanac.’ At laſt they gave him the almanac of Berne ; he took this likewiſe, and went to examine it at the bottom of an alcove that was perfectly dark. He was heard turning over the leaves, and saying 24, then a moment afterwards 34. Returning to his place, with the almanac open at the month of December, he laid it on the table and wrote in the ſpace which he had left blank the 24th. This ſcene happened on the 23d ; but as he imagined it to be the 24th, he did not miſtake. The following is the explication given of this fact by the authors of the report.</p><p>“ The dates 23d, 24th, and 25th, of the month of December, had long occupied the mind of the young Devaud. The 23d and 25th were holidays, which he expected with the impatience natural to perſons of his age, for the arrival of thoſe moments when their little daily labours are to be ſuſpended. The 25th eſpecially was the object of his hopes ; there was to be an illumination in the church, which had been deſcribed to him in a manner that quite tranſported him. The 24th was a day of labour, which came very diſagreeably between the two happy days. It may eaſily be conceived, how an imagination ſo irritable as that of the young Devaud would be ſtruck with thoſe pleaſing epochs. Accordingly, from the beginning of the month he had been perpetually turning over the almanac of Vevey. He calculated the days and the hours that were to elapſe before the arrival of his wished-for holidays ; he ſhowed to his friends and acquaintance the dates of thoſe days which he expected with ſo much impatience ; every time he took up the almanac, it was only to conſult the month of December. We now ſee why that date preſented itſelf to his mind. He was performing a taſk, becauſe he imagined the day to be the Monday which had ſo long engrossed him. It is not ſurpriſing, that it ſhould have occurred to his imagination, and that on opening the almanac in the dark he might have thought he ſaw this date which he was ſeeking, and that his imagination might have repreſented it to him in as lively a manner as if he had actually ſeen it. Neither is it ſurpriſing that he ſhould have opened the almanac at the month of December ; the cuſtom of peruſing this month muſt have made him find it in the dark by a mere mechanical operation. Man never ſeems to be a machine ſo much as in the ſtate of ſomnambuliſm ; it is then that habit comes to ſupply thoſe of the ſenſes that cannot be ſerviceable, and that it makes the person act with as much preciſion as if all his ſenſes were in the utmoſt activity. Theſe circumſtances deſtroy the idea of there being any thing miraculous in the behaviour of young Devaud with reſpect to the date and the month that he was in queſt of ; and the reader, who has entered into our explanations, will not be ſurpriſed at his knowing the German almanac ; the touch alone was ſufficient to point it out to him ; and the proof of this is the ſhortneſs of the time that it remained in his hands.</p><p>“ An experiment was made by changing the place of the ink-ſtandiſh during the time that Devaud was writing. He had a light beſide him, and had certified himſelf of the place where his ink-holder was ſtanding by means of sight. From that time he continued to take ink with preciſion, without being obliged to open his eyes again : but the ink-ſtandiſh being removed, he returned as uſual to the place where he thought it was: It muſt be obſerved, that the motion of his hand was rapid till it reached the height of the ſtandiſh, and then he moved it ſlowly, till the pen gently touched the table as he was ſeeking for the ink : he then perceived that a trick had been put on him, and complained of it ; he went in ſearch of his ink-ſtandiſh and put it in its place. This experiment was ſeveral times repeated, and always attended with the ſame circumſtances. Does not what we have here ſtated prove, that the ſtandiſh, the paper, the table, &amp; c. are painted on his imagination in as lively a manner as if he really ſaw them, as he fought the real ſtandiſh in the place where his imagination told him it ought to have been ? Does it not prove that the ſame lively imagination is the cauſe of the moſt ſingular actions of this sleep-walker ? And laſtly, does it not prove, that a mere glance of his eye is ſufficient to make his impreſſions as lively as durable?</p><p>“ The committee, upon the whole, recommend to ſuch as wiſh to repcat the ſame experiments, 1. To make their obſervations on different ſleep walkers. 2. To examine often whether they can read books that are unknown to them in perfect darkneſs. 3. To obſerve whether they can tell the hours on a watch in the dark. 4. To remove when they write the ink-ſtandiſh from its place, to ſee whether they will return to the ſame place in order to take ink, 5. And, laſtly, to take notice whether they walk with the ſame confidence in a dark<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0543.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0537"/>
and unknown place, as in one with which they are acquainted.</p><p>“ They likewiſe recommend to ſuch as would confirm or invalidate the above obſervations, to make all their experiments in the dark ; becauſe it has been hitherto ſuppoſed that the eyes of ſleep-walkers are oſ no uſe to them.”</p></div></body></text></TEI>