<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0603.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0597-03" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SOL</label>
. in muſic, the fifth note of the gamut, ut, <hi rend="italic">re, mi, fa, ſol, la.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Gamut.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sol,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Sou,</hi> a French coin made up of copper mixed with a little ſilver, and is worth upwards of an Engliſh halfpenny, or the 23d part of an Engliſh ſhilling. The ſol when firſt ſtruck was equal in value to 1 <hi rend="italic">2</hi> deniers Tournois, whence it was alſo called <hi rend="italic">douzain,</hi> a name it ſtill retains, tho’ its ancient value be changed ; the ſol having been ſince augmented by three deniers, and ſtruck with a puncheon of a fleur-de-lis, to make it current for 15 deniers. Soon after the old ſols were coined over again, and both old and new were indifferently made current for 15 deniers. In 1709, the value of the ſame ſols was raiſed to 18 deniers. Towards the latter end of the reign of Louis XIV. the ſol of 18 deniers was again lowered to 15; and by the late king it was reduced to the original value of <hi rend="italic">12.</hi> What it is at preſent poſterity may perhaps diſcover.</p><p>The Dutch have alſo two kinds of ſols: the one of ſilver, called s <hi rend="italic">ols de gros,</hi> and likewiſe <hi rend="italic">ſchelling;</hi> the other of copper, called alſo the st <hi rend="italic">uyver.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sol,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Sun,</hi> in aſtronomy, aſtrology, &amp; c. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Astronomy,</hi> <hi rend="italic">passim.</hi></p><p>Son, in chemiſtry, is gold ; thus called from an opinion that this metal is in a particular manner under the influence of the ſun.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sol,</hi> in heraldry, denotes Or, the golden colour in the arms of ſovereign princes.</p></div></body></text></TEI>