<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0468.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0462-02" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SIDUS <hi rend="smallcaps">GeORgium,</hi></label>
 in aſtronomy, a new primary planet, diſcovered by Dr Herſchell in the year 1781, By moſt foreign, and even by ſome Britiſh philoſophers, it is known by the name of <hi rend="italic">Herſchell,</hi> an honour which is due to the diſcoverer. As the other planets are diſtinguiſhed by marks or characters, the planet Herſchell is diſtinguiſhed by an H, the initial letter of the diſcoverer’s name, and a cross to ſhow that it is a Chriſtian planet. From many calculations of our beſt aſtrono-<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0469.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0463"/>
mers and mathematicians, ſays Dr Herlchell, I have collected the following particulars, as moſt to be depended upon.</p><p>Place of the node: 2 <hi rend="superscript"> s</hi> 11 <hi rend="superscript"> d</hi> 49' 3c''</p><p>Inclination of the orbit: 43' 35'</p><p>Place of the perihelion: 172 <hi rend="superscript"> d</hi> 13' 17'</p><p>Time of the perihelion paſſage: Sep. 7. 1799</p><p>Eccentricity of the orbit: 82034</p><p>Half the greater axis: 19,07904</p><p>Revolution: 83,3364 ſiderial years.</p><p>From my own obſervations on this planet’s apparent diameter, which I have found cannot well be less than 4'', nor indeed much greater, we infer, that its real diameter is to that of the earth as 4,454 to 1 ; and hence it appears to be of very conſiderable bulk, and, except Saturn and Jupiter, by far the largeſt of the remaining planets. Its light is of a bluiſh-white colour, and in brilliancy between that of the Moon and of. Venus. With a teleſcope which magnifies about 300 times, it appears to have a very well defined visible diſk ; but with inſtruments of a ſmall power, it can hardly be diſtinguiſhed from a fixed ſtar of between the sixth and ſeventh magnitude. In a very fine clear night, when the moon is abſent, it may alſo be ſeen by the naked</p></div></body></text></TEI>