<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="gri_33125011196363_0617.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0611-07"
                xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                <p><label>SOUND</label>, in phyſics, is a term of which it would be prepoſterous to
                    offer any definition, as it may almoſt be ſaid to expreſs a ſimple idea : But
                    when we conſider it as a <hi rend="smallcaps">sensation,</hi> and ſtill more
                    when we conſider it as a <hi rend="smallcaps">perception,</hi> it may not be
                    improper to give a deſcription of it ; becauſe this muſt involve certain
                    relations of external things, and certain trains of events in the material
                    world, which make it a proper object of philoſophical diſcuſſion. Sound is that
                    primary information which we get of external things by means of the ſenſe of
                    hearing. This, however, does not explain it : for were we in like manner to
                    deſcribe our ſenſe of hearing, we ſhould find ourſelves, obliged to ſay, that it
                    is the faculty by which we perceive found. Languages<pb
                        facs="gri_33125011196363_0618.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0612"/> are not the
                    invention of philoſophers ; and we muſt not expect preciſion, even in the
                    ſimpleſt caſes. Our methods of expreſſing the information given us by our
                    different ſenses are not ſimilar, as a philoſopher, cautiouſly contriving
                    language, would make them. We have no word to expreſs the primary or generic
                    object of our ſenſe of seeing ; for we believe, that even the vulgar conſider
                    light as the medium, but not the object. This is certainly the caſe (how juſtly
                    we do not ſay) with the philoſopher. On the other hand, the words ſmell, ſound,
                    and perhaps taſte, are conceived by moſt perſons as expreſſing the immediate
                    objects of the ſenfes of ſmelling, hearing, and taſting. Smell and ſound are
                    haſtily conceived as ſeparate exiſtences, and as mediums of information and of
                    intercourſe with the odoriferous and sounding bodies; and it is only the very
                    cautious philoſopher who diſtinguiſhes between the ſmell which he feels and the
                    perfume which fills the room. Thoſe of the ancients, therefore, who taught that
                    sounds were beings waited through the air, and felt by our ears, ſhould not,
                    even at this day, be conſidered as aukward obſervers of nature. It has required
                    the long, patient, and ſagacious conſideration of the moſt penetrating geniuſes,
                    from Zeno the stoic to Sir Iſaac Newton, to diſcover that what we call ſound,
                    the <hi rend="italic">immediate</hi> external object of the lense of hearing, is
                    nothing but a particular agitation of the parts of ſurrounding bodies, acting by
                    mechanical impulſe on our organs; and that it is not any ſeparate being, nor
                    even a ſpecific quality inherent in any particular thing, by which it can affect
                    the organ, as we ſuppoſe with reſpect to a perfume, but merely a mode oſ
                    exiſtence competent to every atom of matter. And thus the deſcription which we
                    propoſed to give of ſound muſt be a deſcription of that ſtate of external
                    contiguous matter which is the <hi rend="italic">cause</hi> of ſound. It is not
                    therefore prefatory to any theory or ſet of doctrines on this ſubject ; but, on
                    the contrary, is the ſum or reſult of them all.</p>
                <p>To diſcover this ſtate of external body by which, without any farther intermedium
                    of subſtance or of operation, it affects our ſenſitive faculties, muſt be
                    considered as a great ſtep in ſcience. It will ſhow us at leaſt one way by which
                    mind and body may be connected It is ſuppoſed that we have attained this
                    knowledge with reſpect to ſound. Our ſucceſs, therefore, is a very pleaſing
                    gratification to the philoſophic mind. It is ſtill more important in another
                    view : it has encouraged us to make ſimilar attempts in other caſes, and has
                    ſupplied us with a fact to which an ingenious mind can eaſily fancy ſomething
                    analogous in many abſtruſe operations of nature, and thus it enables us to give
                    ſome fort of explanation of them. Accordingly this uſe has been moſt liberally
                    made of the mechanical theory of ſound ; and there is now ſcarcely any
                    phenomenon, either of matter or mind, that has not been explained in a manner
                    ſomewhat ſimilar. But we are ſorry to ſay that theſe explanations have done no
                    credit to philoſophy. They are, for the moſt part, ſtrongly marked with that
                    precipitate and ſelf-conceited impatience which has always characteriſed the
                    inveſtigations conducted ſolely by ingenious fancy. The conſequences of this
                    procedure have been no less fatal to the progreſs of true knowledge in modern
                    times than in the ſchools of ancient Greece ; and the ethereal philoſophers of
                    this age, like the followers of Ariſtotle of old, have filled</p>
                <p>ponderous volumes with nonlenſe and error. It is ſtrange, however, that this
                    ſhould be the effect of a great and a ſucceſsful ſtep in philoſophy; But the
                    fault is in the philoſophers, not in the ſcience. Nothing can be more certain
                    than the account which Newton has given of the propagation of a certain claſs of
                    undulations in an elaſtic fluid. But this procedure of nature cannot be ſeen
                    with diſtinctneſs and preciſion by any but well-informed mathematicians. They
                    alone can reſt with unſhaken confidence on the concluſions legitimately deduced
                    from the Newtonian theorems ; and even they can inſure ſucceſs only by treading
                    with the moſt ſcrupulous caution the ſteps of this patient philoſopher. But few
                    have done this ; and we may venture to ſay, that not one in ten of thoſe who
                    employ the Newtonian doctrines of elaſtic undulations for the explanation of
                    other phenomena have taken the trouble, or indeed were able, to go through the
                    ſteps of the fundamental proposition (Prin. II. 50, &amp; c.) But the <hi
                        rend="italic">general</hi> reſults are ſo plain, and admit of ſuch
                    impreſſive illuſtration, that they draw the aſſent of the moſt careleſs reader ;
                    and all imagine that they underſtand the explanation, and perceive the whole
                    procedure of nature. Emboldened therefore by this ſucceſsful ſtep in philoſophy,
                    they, without heſitation, <hi rend="italic">fancy</hi> ſimilar intermediums in
                    other caſes; and as air has been found to be a vehicle for ſound, they have
                    ſuppoſed that ſomething which they call ether, ſomehow reſembling air, is the
                    vehicle of viſion. Others have proceeded farther, and have held that ether, or
                    another ſomething like air, is the vehicle of ſenfation in general, from the
                    organ to the brain : nay, we have got a great volume called A <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Theory of Man,</hi> where all our ſenſations, emotions,
                    affections, thoughts, and purpoſes or volitions, are said to be ſo many
                    vibrations of another ſomething equally unſeen, gratuitous, and incompetent ;
                    and, to crown all, this exalted doctrine, when logically proſecuted, muſt
                    terminate in the discovery of thoſe vibrations which pervade all others, and
                    which conſtitute what we have been accuſtomed to venerate by the name <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Deity.</hi> Such <hi rend="italic">must</hi> be the
                    termination of this philoſophy ; and a truly philoſophical diſſertation on the
                    attributes of the Divine Being c <hi rend="italic">an be nothing else</hi> than
                    an accurate deſcription of theſe vibrations !</p>
                <p>This is not a needleſs and declamatory rhapsody. If the explanation of ſound can
                    be legitimately transferred to thoſe other claſſes of phenomena, theſe are
                    certain reſults; and if ſo, all the diſcoveries made by Newton are but the
                    glimmerings of the morning, when compared with this meridian ſplendor. But if,
                    on the other hand, sound logic forbids us to make this transference of
                    explanation, we muſt continue to believe, for a little while longer, that mind
                    is ſomething different from vibrating matter, and that no kind of oſcillations
                    will conſtitute infinite wiſdom.</p>
                <p>It is of immenſe importance therefore to underſtand thoroughly this doctrine of
                    ſound, that we may ſee clearly and preciſely in what it conſiſts, what are the
                    phenomena of sound that are fully explained, what are the data and the
                    aſſumptions on which the explanations proceed, and what is the <hi rend="italic"
                        >precise mechanical fact</hi> in which it terminates. For this, or a fact
                    perfectly ſimilar, muſt terminate every explanation which we derive from this by
                    analogy, however perfect the analogy may be. This <hi rend="italic"
                        >previous</hi> knowledge muſt be completely poſſeſſed by eve-<pb
                        facs="gri_33125011196363_0619.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0613"/> ry perſon who
                    pretends to explain other phenomena in a ſimilar manner. Then, and not till
                    then, he is able to ſay what classes of phenomena will admit of the explanation
                    : and, when all this is done, his explanation is ſtill an <hi rend="italic"
                        >hypothesis,</hi> till he is able to prove, from other indisputable ſources,
                    the exiſtence and agency of the ſame thing analogous to the elaſtic fluid, from
                    which all is borrowed.</p>
                <p>Such conſiderations would juſtify us for conſidering with great attention the
                    nature of sound. But a work like this will not give room for a full diſcuſſion ;
                    and we muſt refer our readers to the writers who treat it more at large. Much
                    curious information may be got from the pains-taking authors of the laſt century
                    ; ſuch as Lord Bacon; Kircher; Merſennus ; Caſſerius in his great work <hi
                        rend="italic">De Voce et Auditu ;</hi> Perrault in his <hi rend="italic"
                        >Diſſertation du Bruit</hi>; Muſſenbroek in his great Syſtem of Natural
                    Philosophy, in 3 vols 4t0 ; and in his <hi rend="italic">Essais de
                    Physique</hi>; and the writings of the celebrated phyſiologiſts of the preſent
                    age. We alſo refer to what has been ſaid by us in the article <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Acoustics.</hi></p>
                <p>At preſent therefore we muſt content ourſelves with giving a ſhort hiſtory of the
                    ſpeculations of philosophers on this ſubject, tracing out the ſteps by which we
                    have arrived at the knowledge which we have of it. We apprehend this to be or
                    great importance ; becauſe it ſhows us what kind of evidence we have for its
                    truth, and the paths which we muſt ſhun if we wiſh to proceed farther: and we
                    truſt that the progreſs which we have made will appear to be so real, and the
                    object to be attained so alluring to a truly philoſophical mind, that men of
                    genius will be incited to exert their utmoſt efforts to paſs the preſent
                    boundaries of our real progress.</p>
                <p>In the infancy oſ philoſophy, sound was held to be a ſeparate exiſtence,
                    ſomething which would be, although no hearing animal exiſted. This was conceived
                    as wafted through the air to our organ of hearing, which it was ſuppoſed to
                    affect in a manner reſembling that in which our noſtrils are affected when they
                    give us the ſenſation of ſmell. It was one of the Platonic <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >species,</hi> fitted for exciting the intellectual ſpecies, which is the
                    immediate object of the soul’s contemplation.</p>
                <p>Yet, even in thoſe early years of ſcience, there were ſome, and, in particular,
                    the celebrated founder oſ the ſtoic ſchool, who held that sound, that is, the
                    cauſe of sound, was only the particular motion of external groſs matter,
                    propagated to the ear, and there producing that agitation of the organ by which
                    the soul is immediately affected with the ſenſation of sound. Zeno, as quoted by
                    Diogenes Laertius<note anchored="true" n="1" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                            ><p>[m] <gap/> B. vii. p. 158.</p></note> *, ſays, “ Hearing is produced
                    by the air which intervenes between the thing sounding and the ear. The air is
                    agitated in a ſpherical form, and moves off in waves, and falls on the ear, in
                    the ſame manner as the water in a ciſtern undulates in circles when a ſtone has
                    been thrown into it.” The ancients were not remarkable for preciſion, either of
                    conception or argument in their diſcuſſions, and they were contented with a
                    general and vague view of things. Some followed the Platonic notions, and many
                    the opinion of Zeno, but without any farther attempts to give a diſtinct
                    conception of the explanation, or to compare it with experiment.</p>
                <p>But in later times, during the ardent reſearches in the laſt century into the
                    phenomena of nature, this be</p>
                <p>came an intereſting ſubject of inquiry, the invention of the air-pump gave the
                    firſt opportunity of deciding by experiment whether the elastic undulations of
                    air were the cauſes of sound: and the trial fully eſtabliſhed this point ; for a
                    bell rung <hi rend="italic">in vacua</hi> gave no sound, and one rung in
                    condenſed air gave a very loud one. It was therefore received as a doctrine in
                    general phyſics that air was the vehicle of sound.</p>
                <p>The celebrated Galileo, the parent of mathematical philoſophy, diſcovered the
                    nature of that connection between the lengths of muſical cords and the notes
                    which they produced, which had been obſerved by Pythagoras, or learned by him in
                    his travels in the eaſt, and which he made the foundation of a refined and
                    beautiful ſcience, the theory of muſic. Galileo ſhowed, that the real connection
                    subſiſted between the tones and the vibrations of theſe cords, and that their
                    different degrees of acuteneſs corresponded to the different frequency of their
                    vibrations The very elementary and familiar demonſtration which he gave of this
                    connection did not ſatisfy the curious mathematicians of that inquiſitive age,
                    and the mechanical theory of muſical cords was proſecuted to a great degree of
                    refinement. In the courſe of this inveſtigation, it appeared that the cord
                    vibrated in a manner preciſely ſimilar to a pendulum vibrating in a cycloid. It
                    muſt therefore agitate the air contiguous to it in the ſame manner ; and thus
                    there is a particular kind of agitation which the air <hi rend="italic">can</hi>
                    receive and maintain, which is very intereſting.</p>
                <p>Sir Iſaac Newton took up this queſtion as worthy of his notice ; and endeavoured
                    to aſcertain with mathematical preciſion the mechaniſm of this particular claſs
                    of undulations, and gave us the fundamental theorems concerning the undulations
                    of elaſtic fluids, which make the 47, &amp;c. propositions of Book II. of his
                    Principles of Natural Philoſophy. They have been (perhaps haſtily) conſidered as
                    giving the fundamental doctrines concerning the propagation of sound. They are
                    therefore given in this work in the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Acoustics</hi>;
                    and a variety of facts are narrated in the article <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Pneumatics,</hi> to ſhow that ſuch undulations <hi rend="italic">actually
                        obtain</hi> in the air of our atmoſphere, and are accompanied by a ſet of
                    phenomena of sound which preciſely tally or correſpond to all the mechanical
                    circumſtances of theſe undulations. In the mean time, the anatomiſts and
                    phyſiologiſts were buſily employed in examining the ſtructure of our organs of
                    hearing. Impreſſed with the validity of this doctrine of aerial undulations
                    being the cauſes of sound, their reſearches were always directed with a view to
                    diſcover thoſe circumſtances in the ſtructure of the ear which rendered it an
                    organ ſuſceptible of agitations from this cauſe ; and they diſcovered many which
                    appeared as contrivances for making it, a drum, on which the aerial undulations
                    from without muſt make very forcible impulſes, so as to produce very sonorous
                    undulations in the air contained in it. Theſe therefore they conſidered as the
                        <hi rend="italic">immediate</hi> objects of ſenſation, or the immediate
                    cauſes of sound.</p>
                <p>But ſome anatomiſts ſaw that this would not be a full account of the matter : for
                    after a drum is agitated, it has done all that it can do ; it has produced a
                    noiſe. But a farther proceſs goes on in our tar : here is behind the membrane,
                    which is the head of this drum a curious mechanism, which communicates the
                        agitations<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0620.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0614"/>
                    of the membrane (the only thing acted on by the undulating air) to another
                    chamber of moſt Angular conſtruction, where the auditory nerve is greatly
                    expanded. They conceive, therefore, that the organ called the <hi rend="italic"
                        >drum</hi> does not act as a drum, but in ſome other way. Indeed it ſeems
                    bad logic to ſuppoſe that it acts as a drum merely by producing a noiſe. This is
                    in no reſpect different from the noiſe produced out of the ear; and if it is to
                    be heard as a noiſe, we muſt have another ear by which it may be heard, and this
                    ear muſt be another s <hi rend="italic">uch</hi> drum ; and this muſt have
                    another, and ſo on ſor ever. It is like the inaccurate notion that vision is the
                    contemplation of the picture on the retina. Theſe anatomiſts attended therefore
                    to the ſtructure. Here they obſerved a prodigious unfolding of the auditory
                    nerve of the ear, which is curiouſly diſtributed through every part of this
                    cavity, lining its sides, hung acroſs it like a curtain, and sending off fibres
                    in every direction, ſo as to leave hardly a point of it unoccupied. They thought
                    the machinery contained in the drum peculiarly fitted for producing undulations
                    of the air contained in this labyrinth, and that by theſe agitations of the air
                    the contiguous fibres of the auditory nerve are impelled, and that thus we get
                    the ſenſation of sound.</p>
                <p>The cavity intervening between the external air and this inner chamber appeared
                    to theſe anatomiſts to have no other uſe than to allow a very free motion to the
                        <hi rend="italic">ſlapes</hi> or little piſton that is employed to agitate
                    the air in the labyrinth. This piſton condenſes on a very ſmall ſurface the
                    impulſe which it receives from a much larger ſurface, ſtrained by the malleus on
                    the entry of the tympanum, on purpoſe to receive the gentle agitations of the
                    external air in the outer canal. This membranous ſurface could not be agitated,
                    unleſs completely detached from every thing round it ; therefore all animals
                    which have this mechaniſm have it in a cavity containing only air. But they
                    held, that nature had even taken precautions to prevent this cavity from acting
                    as a drum, by making it of ſueh an irregular rambling form ; for it is by no
                    means a cavity of a ſymmetrical ſhape, like a vessel, but rather reſembles the
                    rambling holes and blebs which are often ſeen in a piece of bread, ſcattered
                    through the ſubſtance of the cranium, and communicating with each other by ſmall
                    passages. The whole of theſe cavernulæ are lined with a ſoftiſh membrane, which
                    ſtill farther unfits this cavity for producing sound. This reaſoning is
                    ſpecious, but not very conclusive. We might even assert, that this anfractuous
                    form, with narrow passages, is well fitted for producing noiſe. If we place the
                    ear cloſe to the ſmall hole in the side of a military drum, we ſhall hear the
                    ſmalleſt tap of the drumſtick like a violent blow. The lining of the cavernulæ
                    is nervous, and may therefore be ſtrongly affected in the numerous narrow
                    paſtages between the cells.</p>
                <p>While theſe ſpeculations were going on with reſpect to the ear of the breathing
                    animals, obſervations were occasionally made on other animals, ſuch as reptiles,
                    ſerpents, and fiſhes, which give undoubted indications of hearing ; and many
                    very familiar facts were obſerved or recollected, where sounds are communicated
                    through or by means of solid bodies, or by water ; therefore, without inquiring
                    how or by what kind of mechaniſm it is brought about, it became a very general
                    belief among phyſiologiſts, that all fiſhes, and perhaps all</p>
                <p>animals hear, and that water in particular is a vehicle of sound. In 1767 or 1768
                    the writer of this article, at the ſuggeſtion of the late professor of aſtronomy
                    in the univerſity of Glaſgow, made an experiment in a lake in that
                    neighbourhood, by striking a large hand-bell under water, and heard it very
                    diſtinctly and ſtrongly when his head was plunged in the water at the diſtance
                    of more than 1200 feet. Many experiments are mentioned by Kircher and others on
                    the communication of sound through solid bodies, ſuch as mails, yards, and other
                    long beams of dry fir, with ſimilar reſults. Dr Monro has publiſhed a particular
                    account of very curious experiments on the propagation of sound through water in
                    his Dissertation on the Phyſiology of Fillies ; ſo that it now appears that air
                    is by no means the only vehicle of sound.</p>
                <p>In 1760 Cotunni publiſhed his important diſcovery, that the labyrinth or inmoſt
                    cavity of the ear in animals is completely filled with water. This, after ſome
                    conteſt, has been completely demonſtrated (ſee in particular Meckel Junior <hi
                        rend="italic">de Labyrinthi Auris Contentis,</hi> Argentor, 1777), and it
                    ſeems now to be admitted by all.</p>
                <p>This being the caſe, our notions of the immediate cauſe of sound muſt undergo a
                    great revolution, and a new reſearch muſt be made into the way in which the
                    nerve is affected : for it is not enough that we ſubstitute the undulations of
                    water for thoſe of air in the labyrinth. The well informed mechanician will ſee
                    at once, that the vivacity of the agitations of the nerve will be greatly
                    increaſed by this ſubſtitution ; for if water be perfectly elaſtic through the
                    whole extent of the undulatory agitation which it receives, its effect will be
                    greater in proportion to its speciſic gravity: and this is confirmed by an
                    experiment very eaſily made. Immerſe a table-bell in water contained in a large
                    thin glaſs veſſel. Strike it with a hammer. The sound will be heard as if the
                    bell had been immediately ſtruck on the ſides of the vessel. The filling of the
                    labyrinth of the ear with water is therefore an additional mark of the wiſdom of
                    the Great Artist. But this is not enough for informing us concerning the
                    ultimate mechanical event in the proceſs of hearing. The manner in which the
                    nerve is expoſed to theſe undulations muſt be totally different from what was
                    formerly imagined. The filaments and membranes, which have been deſcribed by
                    former anatomiſts, muſt have been found by them in a ſtate quite unlike to their
                    ſituation and condition in the living animal. Accordingly the moſt eminent
                    anatomiſts of Europe ſeem at preſent in great uncertainty as to the ſtate of the
                    nerve, and are keenly occupied in obſervations to this purpoſe. The deſcriptions
                    given by Monro, Scarpa, Camper, Comparetti, and others, are full of moſt curious
                    diſcoveries, which make almoſt a total change in our notions of this ſubject,
                    and will, we hope, be productive of moſt valuable information.</p>
                <p>Scarpa has diſcovered that the solid cavity called the <hi rend="italic"
                        >labyrinth</hi> contains a threefold expanſion of the auditory nerve. One
                    part of it, the cochlea, contains it in a fibrillous ſtate, ramified in a moſt
                    ſymmetrical manner through the whole of the <hi rend="italic">zona mollis</hi>
                    of the <hi rend="italic">lamina ſpiralis,</hi> where it anaſtomoſes with another
                    production of it diffuſed over the general lining of that cavity. Another
                    department of the nerve; alſo in a fibrous ſtate, is ſpread over the external
                    ſurface of a membranaceous<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0621.tif"
                        xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0615"/> bag, which nearly fills that part of the
                    veſtibule into which the ſemicircular canals open, and alſo that orifice which
                    receives the impreſſions of the ſtapes. This bag sends off tubular membranaceous
                    ducts, which, in like manner, nearly fill theſe ſemicircular canals. A third
                    department of the nerve is ſpread over the external surface of another
                    membranaceous bag, which lies between the one juſt now mentioned and the
                    cochlea, but haying no communication with either, almoſt completely filling the
                    remainder of the vestibule. Thus the veſtibule and canals ſeem only a cafe for
                    protecting this ſensitive membranaceous veſſel, which is almoſt, but not
                    altogether, in contact with the oſſeous cafe, being ſeparated by a delicate and
                    almoſt fluid cellular ſubſtance. The fibrillous expanſion of the nerve is not
                    indiſcriminately diffuſed over the ſurface of theſe sacculi, but evidently
                    directed to certain foci, where the fibres are conſtipated. And this is the laſt
                    appearance of the fibrous ſtate of the nerve; for when the inſide of theſe
                    ſacculi is inſpected, no fibres appear, but a pulp (judged to be nervous from
                    its ſimilarity to other pulpy productions of the brain) adhering to the
                    membranaceous coat, and not ſeparable from it by gently washing it. It is more
                    abundant, that is, of greater thickneſs, oppoſite to the external fibrous foci.
                    No organical ſtructure could be diſcovered in this pulp, but it probably is
                    organiſed ; for, beſides this adhering pulp, the water in the ſacculi was
                    obſerved to be clammy or mucous ; ſo that in all probability the vascular or
                    fibrous ſtate of the nerve is ſucceeded by an uninterrupted production (perhaps
                    columnar like basalt, though not cohering); and this at laſt ends in ſimple
                    diſſemination, ſymmetrical however, where water and nerve are alternate in every
                    direction.</p>
                <p>To theſe obſervations of Scarpa, Comparetti adds the curious circumſtances of
                    another and regular tympanum in the foramen rotundum, the cylindric cavity of
                    which is incloſed at both ends by a fine membrane. The membrane which ſeparates
                    it from the cochlea appears to be in a ſtate of variable tenſion, being drawn up
                    to an umbo by a cartilaginous speck in its middle, which he thinks adheres to
                    the lamina ſpiralis, and thus ſerves to ſtrain the drumhead, as the malleus
                    ſtrains the great membrane known to all.</p>
                <p>Theſe are moſt important obſervations, and muſt greatly excite the curiosity of a
                    truly philoſophical mind, and deserve the moſt careful inquiry into their
                    juſtneſs. If theſe are accurate deſcriptions of the organ, they ſeem to conduct
                    us farther into the ſecrets of nature than any thing yet known.</p>
                <p>We think that they promiſe to give us the greateſt step yet made in phyſiology,
                    viz. to ſhow us the laſt mechanical fact which occurs in the long train
                    interpoſed between the external body and the incitement of our ſensitive ſyſtem.
                    But there is, as yet, great and eſſential differences in the deſcription given
                    by thoſe celebrated naturaliſts. It cannot be otherwiſe. The containing
                    labyrinth can be laid open to our view in no other way than by deſtroying it ;
                    and its moſt delicate contents are the firſt ſufferers in the ſearch. They are
                    found in very different ſituations and conditions by different anatomiſts,
                    according to their addreſs or their good fortune. Add to this, that the natural
                    varieties are very conſiderable. Faithful deſcriptions muſt therefore give very
                    different notions of the ultimate action and reaction between the unorganiſed
                    matter in the labyrinth and the ultimate expanſion of the auditory nerve.</p>
                <p>We muſt therefore wait with patience. Since this work of ours was begun, the
                    progreſs which has been made in many parts of natural ſcience has been great and
                    wonderful ; and perhaps before it be completed, we may be furniſhed with ſuch a
                    collection of facts respecting the ſtructure and the contents of the organ of
                    hearing, as might enable us to give a juſter theory of sound than is yet to be
                    found in the writings of philoſophers. There ſeems to be no abatement of ardour
                    in the reſearches of the phyſiologiſts; and they will not remain long ignorant
                    of the truth or miſtake in the accounts given by Scarpa and Comparetti. Should
                    the reſult of their inquiries be what we expect, we ſhould be glad of a proper
                    opportunity of laying it before our readers, together with ſome diſquiſition on
                    the nature of hearing. A collection of accurate obſervations on the ſtructure of
                    the ear would give us principles on which to proceed in explaining the various
                    methods of producing external sounds. The nature of <hi rend="italic">continued
                        sounds</hi> might then be treated of, and would appear, we believe, very
                    different from what it is commonly ſuppoſed. Under this head animal voices might
                    be particularly conſidered, and the elements of human ſpeech. properly
                    aſcertained. When the production of continued sounds is once ſhown to be a thing
                    regulated by principle, it may be ſyſtematically treated, and this principle may
                    be conſidered as combined with every mechanical ſtate of body that may be
                    pointed out. This will ſuggeſt to us methods of producing ſound which have not
                    yet been thought of, and may therefore give us sounds with which we are
                    unacquainted. Such an acquiſition is not to be deſpiſed nor rejected. The
                    bountiful Author of our being and of all our faculties has made it an object of
                    most enchanting reliſh to the human mind. The Greeks, the moſt cultivated people
                    who have ever figured on the ſtage of life, enjoyed the pleaſures of music with
                    rapture. Even the poor negro, after toiling a whole day beneath the tropical
                    fun, will go ten miles in the dark to dance all night to the ſimple muſic of the
                    balafoe, and return without ſteep to his next day’s toil. The penetrating eye of
                    the anatomiſt has diſcovered in the human larynx an apparatus evidently
                    contrived for tempering the great movements of the glottis, ſo as to enable us
                    to produce the intended note with the utmoſt preciſion. There is no doubt
                    therefore that the conſummate Artiſt has not thought it unworthy of his
                    attention. We ought therefore to receive with thankfulneſs this preſent from our
                    Maker—this <hi rend="italic">laborum dulce lenimen ;</hi> and it is ſurely
                    worthy the attention of the philoſopher to add to this innocent elegance of
                    life. This, however, is not the time to enter upon the ſubject. From the jarring
                    obſervations which have yet been made, we could only amuſe the curious reader by
                    holding up to his view a ſpecious theory ; and we are not ſo deſirous of filling
                    our work with what is called <hi rend="italic">original matter,</hi> as to
                    attempt the attainment of that end by ſubſtiiuting fiction for fact and
                    hypotheſis for ſcience.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sound,</hi> in geography, denotes in general any strait or
                    inlet of the ſea between two headlands. It is given by way of eminence to the
                    strait between Sweden and<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0622.tif"
                        xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0616"/> Denmark, joining the German ocean to the Baltic,
                    being about three miles over. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Denmark,</hi> n⁰ 32. and
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Elsinore.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
