<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0523.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0517-01" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SIZAR</label>,
or <hi rend="smallcaps">Sizer,</hi> in Latin <hi rend="italic">Sizator,</hi> an appellation by which the lowed order oſ ſtudents in the univerſities of Cambridge and Dublin are diſtinguiſhed, is derived from the word size, which in Cambridge, and probably in Dublin likewiſe, has a peculiar meaning. To <hi rend="italic">ſize,</hi> in the language of the univerſity, is to <hi rend="italic">get</hi> any sort of victuals from the kitchens, which the ſtudents may want in their own rooms, or in addition to their commons in the hall, and for which they pay the cooks or butchers at the end of each quarter. A size of any thing is the ſmalleſt quantity of that thing which can be thus bought : two ſizes, or a part of beef, being nearly equal to what a young perſon will eat of that diſh to his dinner ; and a ſize of ale or beer being equal to half an Engliſh pint.</p><p>The ſizars are divided into two claſſes, viz. ſubſizatores or ſizars, and sizatores or proper ſizars. The former of theſe are ſupplied with commons from the table of the fellows and fellow-commoners ; and in former times, when theſe were more ſcanty than they are now, they were obliged to ſupply the deficiency by ſizing, as is ſometimes the case ſtill. The proper ſizars had formerly no commons at all, and were therefore obliged to ſize the whole. In St John’s college they have now ſome commons allowed them for dinner, from a benefaction, but they are ſtill obliged to ſize their ſuppers : in the other colleges they are allowed a part of the fellow-commons, but muſt ſize the rest ; and from being thus obliged to ſize the whole or part of their victuals, the whole order derived the name of siza <hi rend="italic">rs.</hi></p><p>In Oxford, the order ſimilar to that of ſizar is denominated <hi rend="italic">ſervitor,</hi> a name evidently derived from the menial duties which they perform. In both univerſities theſe orders were formerly diſtinguiſhed by round caps and gowns of different materials from thoſe of the penſioners or commoners, the order immediately above them. But about 30 years ago the round cap was entirely aboliſhed in both ſeminaries. There is ſtill, however, in Oxford, we believe, a diſtinction in the gowns, and there is alſo a trifling difference in ſome of the ſmall colleges in Cambridge ; but in the large colleges the dreſs of the penſioners and ſizars is entirely the ſame.</p><p>In Oxford, the ſervitors are ſtill obliged to wait at table on the fellows and gentlemen-commoners ; but much to the credit of the univerſity of Cambridge, this moſt degrading and diſgraceful cuſtom was entirely aboliſhed about 10 or 12 years ago, and of courſe the ſizars of Cambridge are now on a much more reſpectable footing than the ſervitors of Oxford.</p><p>The ſizars are not upon the foundation, and therefore while they continue ſizars are not capable of being elected fellows ; but they may at any time, if they<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0524.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0518"/>
choose, become penſioners : and. they generally fit for ſcholarſhips immediately before they take their firſt degree. If ſucceſsful, they are then on the foundation, and are entitled to become candidates for ſellowſhips when they have got that degree. In the mean time, while they continue ſizars, beſides free commons they enjoy many beneſactions, which have been made at different times, under the name of si <hi rend="italic">zar's praetor, exhibitions,</hi> &amp; c. and the rate of tuition, the rent of rooms, and other things of that sort within their reſpective colleges, is leſs than to the other orders. But tho’ their education is thus obtained at a leſs expence, they are not now conſidered as a menial order; for ſizars, penſioner-ſcholars, and even sometimes fellow-commoners, mix together with the utmoſt cordiality. It is worthy of remark, that at every period this order has supplied the univerſity with its moſt diſtinguiſhed officers ; and that many of the moſt illuſtrious members of the church, many of the moſt diſtinguiſhed men in the other liberal proſeſſions, have, when under-graduates, been ſizars, when that order was on a leſs reſpectable footing than it is now.</p></div></body></text></TEI>