<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0516.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0510-04" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SINDY</label>,
a province of Hindoſtan Proper, bounded on the west by Makran, a province of Perſia ; on the north by the territories of the king of Candahar ; on the north-eaſt by thoſe of the Seiks ; on the eaſt by a ſandy deſert ; and on the ſouth-eaſt by Cutch. It extends along the courſe of the river Sinde or Indus from its mouth to Behker or Bhakor, on the frontiers of Moultan. Reckoned that way, it is 300 miles long ; and its breadth, in its wideſt part, is about 160. In many particulars of soil and climate, and in the general appearance oſ the ſurface, Sindy reſembles Egypt ; the lower part of it being compoſed of rich vegetable mould, and extended into a wide dell ; while the upper part of it is a narrow slip of country, confined on one side by a ridge of mountains, and on the other by a ſandy deſert, the river Indus, equal at leaſt to the Nile, winding through the midſt of this level valley, and annually overflowing it. During great part of the ſouth-weſt monſoon, or at leaſt in the months of July, Auguſt, and part of September, which is the rainy ſeaſon in moſt other parts of India, the atmoſphere is here generally clouded ; but no rain falls except very near the ſea. Indeed, very few ſhowers fall during the whole year ; owing to which, and the neighbourhood of the ſandy deſerts, which bound it on the eaſt and on the north- west, the heats are ſo violent, and the winds from thoſe quarters ſo pernicious, that the houſes are contrived ſo as to be occaſionally ventilated by means of apertures on the tops of them, reſembling the funnels of ſmall chimneys. When the hot winds prevail, the windows are cloſely shut ; and the loweſt part oſ the current of air, which is always the hotteſt, being thus excluded, a cooler, becauſe more elevated, part deſcends into the houſe through the funnels. By this contrivance alſo vaſt clouds of dust are excluded ; the entrance of which would alone be ſufficient to render the houſes uninhabitable. The roofs are compoſed of thick layers of earth inſtead of terraces. Few countries are more unwholeſome to European conſtitutions, particularly the lower part of the Delta. The prince of this province is a Mahometan, tributary to the king of Candahar. He reſides at Hydrabad, although Tatta is the capital. The Hindoos, who were the original inhabitants of Sindy, are by their Mahometan governors treated with great rigour, and denied the public exerciſe of their religion ; and this ſeverity drives vaſt numbers of them into other countries. The inland parts of Sindy produce ſaltpetre, ſal-ammoniac, borax, bezoar, lapis la</p><p>zuli, and raw ſilk. They have alſo manufactories of cotton and ſilk of various kinds ; and they make fine cabinets, inlaid with ivory, and finely lackered. They alſo export great quantities of butter, clarified and wrapt up in duppas, made of the hides of cattle. The ladies wear hoops of ivory on both their arms and legs, which when they die are burnt with them. They have large black cattle, excellent mutton, and ſmall hardy horses. Their wild game are deer, hares, antelopes, and foxes, which they hunt with dogs, leopards, and a ſmall fierce creature called a ſhiahguſh.</p></div></body></text></TEI>