<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0482.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0476-01" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SIGNATURE</label>,
a ſign or mark impreſſed upon any thing, whether by nature or art. Such is the general ſignification of the word ; but in the plural number it has been uſed, in a particular ſenſe, to denote thoſe external marks by which phyſiognomiſts and other dabblers in the occult ſciences pretend to diſcover the nature and internal qualities of every thing on which they are found. According to Lavater, every corporeal object is characterized by ſignatures peculiar to itſelf.</p><p>The doctrine of ſignatures, like alchemy and aſtrology, was very prevalent during the 15th and 16th centuries ; and was conſidered as one of the occult ſciences which conferred no ſmall degree of honour on their respective profeſſors. Some of theſe philosophers, as they thought fit to ſtyle themselves, maintained that plants, minerals, and animals, but particularly plants, had ſignatures impreſſed on them by the hand of nature, indicating to the adept the <hi rend="italic">therapeutic</hi> uſes to which they might be applied. Others, ſuch as the myſtic theoſophiſts and chemiſts of that day, proceeded much farther in abſurdity, maintaining that every ſubſtance in nature lad either <hi rend="italic">external</hi> ſignatures immediately diſcernible, or <hi rend="italic">internal</hi> ſignatures, which, when brought into view by fire or menſtrua, denoted its connection with ſome fiderial or celestial archetype. Of the doctrine of signatures, as it relates merely to the therapeutic uſes of plants and minerals, traces are to be found in the works of ſome of the greateſt authors of antiquity ; but the celeſtial ſignatures, we believe, were diſcovered only by the moonlight of the moukiſh ages, Pliny informs us<note anchored="true" n="1" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>Hist. Nat. lib. 34.</p></note> *, that the marble called <hi rend="italic">aphites,</hi> from its being ſpotted ike a ſerpent, was diſcovered by thoſe ſpots to be a sovereign remedy for the bite of that animal ; and that he colour of the <hi rend="italic">haematites</hi> or blood-ſtone intimated that it was fit to be employed to ſtop an hemorrhagy ; but we do not recollect his attributing the virtues of theſe minerals to a ſiderial or celeſtial influence.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Signature,</hi> a ſigning of a perſon’s name at the botom of an act or deed written by his own hand.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Signature,</hi> in printing, is a letter put at the bottom of the firſt page at leaſt, in each ſheet, as a direction to the binder in folding, gathering, and. collating, hem. The ſignatures conſiſt of the capital, letters of the alphabet, which change in every ſheet : if there be tore ſheets than letters in the alphabet, to the capital letter is added a ſmall one of the ſame sort, as A a, B b ; which are repeated as often as neceſſary. In large volumes it is eaſy to diſtinguiſh the number of alphabets, after the firſt three or four, by placing a figure before he literature, as 5 B, 6 B, &amp; c.</p></div></body></text></TEI>