<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0461.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0455-05" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SICILY</label>,
is a large iſland in the Mediterranean Sea, adjoining to the ſouthern extremity of Italy, and extends from latitude 36° 25' to latitude 38⁰ 25', and from longitude 12⁰ 50' to longitude 16⁰ 5' eaſt from London. Its greateſt length <hi rend="italic">210</hi> miles, breadth 133, circumſerence 60; its form triangular, the three angles being the promontories of Pelorum, Pachynum, and Lilybæum, or as they are now called the Faro, Capo Passaro, arid Capo Boco. It is divided from Italy by the ſtraits of Meſſina, reaching from the Tower of Faro, which is the moſt northerly part of the iſland, to the <hi rend="italic">Capo dell' Arm's,</hi> or the Cape of Arms, the moſt ſouthern part of Calabria. Theſe ſtraits, by the Latins called <hi rend="italic">Fretum Siculum,</hi> by the Italians Il <hi rend="italic">Fare di Meſsina,</hi> and by us the <hi rend="italic">Fare of Meſſina,</hi> are between <hi rend="italic">12</hi> and 15 miles over in the broadeſt places, and in the narrowest about a mile and an half ; inſomuch that when<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0462.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0456"/>
Meſſina was taken by the Carthaginians, many of the inhabitants are said to have ſaved themſelves by ſwimming to the oppoſite coaſts of Italy. Hence has ariſen an opinion that the iſland of Sicily was originally joined to the continent, but afterwards ſeparated by an earthquake or ſome other natural cauſe. This ſeparation, however, is reckoned by the moſt judicious among the ancients to be fabulous ; and they content themſelves with ſpeaking of it as a thing ſaid to have happened.</p><p>Anciently this iſland was called <hi rend="italic">Sicania, Sicilia,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Trinacria</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Triquetra;</hi> the two former it had from the Sicani and Siculi, who peopled a conſiderable part of the country ; the two latter from its triangular figure. Its firſt inhabitants, according to the moſt reſpectable ancient authors, were the Cyclopes and Laeſtrigones, who are ſaid to have ſettled in the countries adjoining to Mount Etna ; but of their origin we know nothing, except what is related by the poets. After them came the Sicani, who called themſelves the original inhabitants of the country ; but ſeveral ancient hiſtorians inform us that they came from a country in Spain watered by the river Siconus. Diodorus, however, is of opinion, that the Sicani were the moſt ancient inhabitants of this iſland. He tells us that they were in poſſeſſion of the whole, and applied themſelves to cultivate and improve the ground in the neighbourhood of Etna, which was the moſt fruitful part of the iſland : they built ſeveral ſmall towns and villages on the hills to ſecure themſelves againſt thieves and robbers ; and were governed, not by one prince, but each city and diſtrict by its own king. Thus they lived till Etna began to throw out flames, and forced them to retire to the weitern parts of the iſland, which they continued to inhabit in the time of Thucydides. Some Trojans, after the deſtruction of their city, landed in the iſland, ſettled among the Sicani, and built the cities of Eryx and Egesta, uniting themſelves with them, and taking the general name of Elymi or Elymæi. They were afterwards joined by ſome Phocenſes, who ſettled here on their return from the ſiege of Γroy.</p><p>After the Sicani had for many ages enjoyed an undiſturbed poſſeſſion of the whole of Sicily, or ſuch parts of it as they choſe to inhabit, they were viſited by the Siculi, who were the ancient inhabitants of Auſonia properly ſo called ; but being driven out from thence by the Opici, they took refuge in the iſland of Sicily. Not being contented with the narrow bounds allowed them by the Sicani, they began to encroach upon their neighbours ; upon which a war enſuing, the Sicani were utterly defeated, and confined to a corner of the iſland, the name of which was now changed from <hi rend="italic">Sicania</hi> into that of <hi rend="italic">Sicilia.</hi></p><p>About 300 years after the arrival of the Siculi, the iſland firſt began to be known to the Greeks, who eſtabliſhed various colonies, and built many cities in different parts of the iſland ; and it is only from the time of their arrival that we have any hiſtory of the iſland. The firſt of the Greeks that came into Sicily were the Chalcidians of Eubœa, under the conduct of Thucles, who built Naxus, and a famous altar of Apollo, which, as Thucydides tells us, was ſtill ſtanding in his time without the city. The year after, which was, according to Dionyſius Halicarnaſſenſis, the third of the 17th Olympiad, Archias the Corinthian, one of the Hera</p><p>clidae, laid the foundations of Syracuſe. Seven years after, a new colony of Chalcidians founded Leontini and Catana, after having driven out the Siculi, who inhabited that tract. About the ſame time Lamis, with a colony from Megara, a city of Achaia, ſettled on the river Pantacius, at a place called <hi rend="italic">Trotilum,</hi> where his adventurers lived ſome time in common with the Chalcidians of Leontini ; but, being driven from thence by the Leontines, he built the city of Thapſus, where he died. Upon his death, the colony left Thapſus ; and under the conduct of Hyblon king of the Siculi, founded Megara Hyblæa, where they reſided 245 years, till they were driven out by Gelon tyrant of Syracuſe. During their abode at Megara, they ſent one Pamilus, who was come from Megara in Achaia, their original city, to build Selinus. This city was founded about 100 years after the foundation of Megara. Antiphemua and Entimus, the former a Rhodian, the other a Cretan, led each a colony of their countrymen, and jointly built the city of Gela on a river of the ſame name, eſtabliſhing in their new ſettlement the Doric cuſtoms, about 45 years after the founding of Syracuſe. The inhabitants of Gela founded Agrigentum 108 years after their arrival in Sicily, and introduced the ſame cuſtoms there. A few years after, Zancle was built by the pirates of Cumæ in Italy ; but chiefly peopled by the Chalcidians, Samians, and Ionians, who choſe rather to ſeek new ſettlements than live under the Perſian yoke. Some time after, Anaxales, tyrant of Rhegium, drove out the ancient proprietors ; and, dividing his lands amongſt his followers, called the city <hi rend="italic">Meſſana</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Meſſene,</hi> which was the name of his native city in Peloponneſus. The city of Himera was founded by the Zancleans under the direction of Eucleides, Simus, and Sacon ; but peopled by the Chalcidians and ſome Syracuſan exiſes, who had been driven out by the contrary faction.</p><p>The Syracuſians built Acræ, Chasmenæ, and Camarina ; the firſt 70 years, the second 90, and the third 135, after the foundation of their own city. This is the account which Thucydides, a moſt judicious and exact writer, gives us of the various nations, whether Greeks or Barbarians, who ſettled in Sicily. Strabo counts among the ancient inhabitants of Sicily the Morgetes, who being driven out of Italy by the Oenotrians, ſettled in that part of the iſland where the ancient city of Morgantium ſtood. The Campani, who aſſumed the name of <hi rend="italic">Mamertini,</hi> that is, <hi rend="italic">invincible warriors,</hi> and the Carthaginians, who ſettled very early in Sicily, ought likewiſe to be counted among the ancient inhabitants of the iſland.</p><p>Before this period the hiſtory of Sicily is blended with fables like the early hiſtory of almoſt every other country. After the ſettlement of the Greeks in the iſland, its various revolutions have been traced from their ſeveral ſources by many writers ; but by none with greater accuracy than Mr Swinburne. From his account of his Travels in the Two Sicilies, we have therefore taken the following conciſe hiſtory of this kingdom, which will at once gratify ſuch of our readers as intereſt themſelves in the fate of a generous people who long ſtruggled in vain for freedom ; and at the ſame time afford them a ſpecimen of the entertainment they may receive from the very elegant work of the author,<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0463.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0457"/>
"Ariſtocracy prevailed at firſt in the Greek ſettlements, but ſoon made way for tyranny ; which in its turn was expelled by democracy. One of the earlieſt deſtroyers of common liberty was Phalaris of Agrigentum, who reigned 600 years before Chriſt : his example was contagious ; a legion of tyrants ſprang up, and not a commonwealth in the iſland eſcaped the laſh of an uſurper. Syracuſe was moſt oppreſſed and torn to pieces by diſſenſion ; as its wealth and preponderance in the general ſcale held out a greater temptation than other cities to the ambition of wicked men. It requires the combined teſtimony of hiſtorians to enforce our belief of its wonderful proſperity, and the no leſs extraordinary tyranny of ſome of its ſovereigns. Theſe Grecian colonies attained to ſuch excellence in arts and ſciences as emboldened them frequently to vie with the learned and ingenious in the mother country ; nay, often enabled them to bear away the palm of victory : there needs no ſtronger proof of their literary merits than a bare recital of the names of Archimedes, Theocritus, Gorgias, and Charondas.</p><p>“ But the Sicilian Greeks were not deſtined to enjoy the ſweets of their ſituation without moleſtation. Very ſoon after their arrival, the inhabitants of the neighbouring coaſt of Africa began to aſpire to a ſhare of Sicily. Carthage ſent large bodies of forces at different times to eſtabliſh their power in the iſland, and about 500 years before the Chriſtan era had made themselves masters of all the weſtern parts of it. The Siculi retained poſſeſſion of the midland country, and the ſouthern and eaſtern coaſts were inhabited by the Greeks.</p><p>“ About that time Gelo was choſen prince of Syractuse on account of his virtues, which grew ſtill more conſpicuous after his exaltation : had the example he ſet been followed by his ſucceſſors, the advantages of freedom would never have been known or wished for by the Syracuſans. The Carthaginians found in him a vigorous opponent to their project of enſlaving Sicily, a project invariably purſued but never accompliſhed.</p><p>“ Hiero ſucceeded his brother Gelo, and, contrary to the uſual progreſſion, began his reign by a diſplay of bad qualities. Senſible of his error, and improved by experience, he afterwards adopted more equitable meaſures. At his death the Syracuſans threw off the yoke, and for ſixty years revelled in all the joys of freedom. Their peace was, however, diſturbed by the Athenians and the Carthaginians. The latter plundered Agrigentum, and threatened ruin to the rest of the Grecian ſtates ; but a treaty of peace averted that ſtorm.</p><p>The Athenians, under pretence of ſupporting their allies the people of Segeſta, but in reality from a thirſt of dominion, inverted Syracuſe with a formidable land and naval armament under the command of Nicias ; in conſequence of a raſh indigeſted plan, ill conducted attacks, and inadequate ſupplies, their whole hoſt was cut to pieces or led away into captivity.</p><p>“ Syracuſe had ſcarce time to breathe after her victory ere inteſtine wars broke out, and raiſed Dionyſius to ſupreme command. Avarice, deſpotism, and cruelty, marked every day of his reign ; but his military enterpriſes were crowned with conſtant ſucceſs. He died in peace, and bequeathed a powerful ſovereignty to a ſon of his name tainted with the ſame and worſe vices, but not endowed with equal capacity and martial abili</p><p>ty ; in ſuch hands the rod of tyranny ceaſed to be formidable, and the tyrant was driven out of Sicily by the patriotic party ; but matters were not ſufficiently settled for popular government, and Dionysius reſumed the ſceptre for a while, till Timoleon forced him into perpetual exile.”</p><p>Liberty ſeemed now to be eſtabliſhed on a permanent baſis ; but in Syracuſe ſuch proſpects always proved illuſory. Agathocles, a tyrant more inhuman than any preceding uſurper, ſeized the throne, and deluged the country with blood. He was involved in a perilous conteſt with the Carthaginians, who obtained many advantages over him, drove his troops from port to port, and at laſt blocked up his capital. In this deſperate ſituation, wſhen all foreign helps were precluded, and hardly a reſource remained at home, the genius of Agathocles compaſſed his deliverance by a plan that was imitated among the ancients by Hannibal, and among the moderns by the famous Cortes. He embarked with the flower of his army ; forced his way through innumerable obſtacles ; landed in Africa ; and, having burnt his fleet, routed the Carthaginians in a pitched battle, and laid their territory waſte. Carthage ſeemed to be on the brink of ruin, and that hour might have marked her downfal had the Sicilian hoſt been compoſed of patriotic ſoldiers, and not of ungovernable aſſaſſins ; diſcord pervaded the victorious camp, murder and riot enſued ; and the tyrant, after beholding his children and friends butchered before his face, eſcaped to Sicily, to meet a death as tragical as his crimes deſerved.</p><p>Anarchy now raged throughout the iſland, and every faction was reduced to the neceſſity of calling in the aſſiſtance of foreign powers; among whom Pyrrhus king of Epirus took the lead, and reduced all parties to ſome degree of order and obedience. But ambition ſoon prompted him to invade thoſe rights which he came to defend ; he caſt off the maſk, and made Sicily feel under his ſway as heavy a hand as that of its former oppreſſors ; but the Sicilians ſoon aſſumed courage and strength enough to drive him out of the iſland.</p><p>About this period the Mamertini, whom Mr Swinburne indignantly ſtyles a crew of miſcreants, ſurpriſed Meſſina, and, after a general maſſacre of the citizens, eſtabliſhed a republican form of government. Their commonwealth became ſo troubleſome a neighbour to the Greeks, that Hiero II. who had been raiſed to the chief command at Syracuſe in conſideration of his ſuperior wiſdom and warlike talents, found himſelf neceſſitated to form a league with Carthage, in order to deſtroy this neſt of villains. In their diſtreſs the Mamertini implored the aſſiſtance of Rome, though the ſenate had recently puniſhed with exemplary ſeverity one of their own legions for a ſimilar outrage committed at Rhegium. The virtue of the Romans gave way to the temptation, and the define of extending their empire beyond the limits of Italy, caſt a veil over every odious circumſtance attending this alliance. A Roman army croſſed the Faro, relieved Meſſina, defeated the Carthaginians, and humbled Hiero into an ally of the republic.</p><p>Thus began the firſt Punic war, which was carried on for many years in Sicily with various ſucceſs. The genius of Hamilcar Barcas ſupported the African cauſe under numberleſs diſappointments, and the repeated overthrows of his colleagues ; at laſt, finding his exer-<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0464.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0458"/>
tions ineffectual, he adviſed the Carthaginian rulers to purchaſe peace at the price of Sicily. Such a treaty was not likely to be obſerved longer than want of ſtrength ſhould curb the animoſity of the vanquiſhed party : when their vigour was recruited, Hannibal ſon of Hamilcar easily perſuaded them to reſume the conteſt, and for 16 years waged war in the heart of the Roman territories. Meanwhile Hiero conducted himſelf with ſo much prudence, that he retained the friendſhip of both parties, and preſerved his portion of Sicily in perfect tranquillity. He died in extreme old age, beloved and retpected both at home and abroad.</p><p>His granson Hieronymus, forſaking this happy line of politics, and contracting an alliance with Carthage, fell an early victim to the troubles which his own folly had excited. Once more, and for the laſt time, the Syracuſans found themſelves in poſſeſſion of their independence: but the times were no longer ſuited to ſuch a ſyſtem ; diſſenſions gained head, and diſtracted the public councils. Carthage could not ſupport them, or prevent Marcellus from under taking the siege of Syracuſe, immortalized by the mechanical efforts of Archimedes, and the immenſity of the plunder. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Syracuse.</hi></p><p>The Sicilians after this relinquiſhed all martial ideas, and during a long series of generations turned their attention ſolely to the arts of peace and the labours of agriculture. Their poſition in the centre of the Roman empire preſerved them both from civil and foreign foes, except in two inſtances of a ſervile war. The rapacity of their governors was a more conſtant and inſupportable evil. In this ſtate of apathy and opulence Sicily remained down to the 7th century of our era, when the Saracens began to diſturb its tranquillity. The barbarous nations of the north had before invaded and ravaged its coaſts, but had not long kept poſſeſſion. The Saracens were more fortunate. In 827 they availed themſelves of quarrels among the Sicilians to ſubdue the country. Palermo was choſen for their capital, and the ſtandard of Mahomet triumphed about 200 years. In 1038 George Maniaces was ſent by the Greek emperor with a great army to attack Sicily. He made good his landing, and puſhed his conqueſts with vigour : his ſucceſs aroſe from the valour of ſome Norman troops, which were at that time unemployed and ready to fell their ſervices to the beſt bidder. Maniaces repaid them with ingratitude ; and by his abſurd conduct gave the Muſſulmen time to breathe, and the Normans a pretext and opportunity of invading the Imperial dominions in Italy? Robert and Roger of Hauteville afterwards conquered Sicily on their own account, not as mercenaries ; for having ſubſtantially fettled their power on the continent, they turned their arms againſt this iſland in obedience to the dictates of zeal and ambition. After ten years ſtruggle, the Saracens yielded up the rich prize, and Robert ceded it to his brother Roger, who aſſumed the title of Great Earl of Sicily, ruled the ſtate with wiſdom, and ranks deſervedly among the greateſt characters in hiſtory. He raised himſelf from the humble ſtation of a poor younger ſon of a private gentleman, to the exalted dignity of a powerful monarch, by the ſole force of his own genius and courage ; he governed a nation of ſtrangers with vigour and juſtice, and transmitted his poſſeſſions undiſputed to his poſterity. Such an aſſemblage of great qualities is well intitled to our admiration.</p><p>He was ſucceeded by his ſon Simon, whole reign was ſhort, and made way for a second ſon called Roger. In 1127 this prince joined to his Sicilian poſſeſſions the whole inheritance of Robert Guiſcard (ſee <hi rend="smallcaps">Naples,</hi> n⁰ 23. ), and aſſumed the regal ſtyle. The greateſt part of his reign was taken up in quelling revolts in Italy, but Sicily enjoyed profound peace. In 1154 his ſon William aſcended the throne, and paſſed his life in war and confusion. William II. ſucceeded his father, and died without iſſue. Tancred, though baſely born, was elected his ſuccessor, and after him his ſon William III. who was vanquiſhed by Henry of Swabia. During the troubles that agitated the reign of his ſon the emperor Frederic, peace appears to have been the lot of Sicily. A ſhort lived ſedition, and a revolt of the Saracens, are the only commotions of which we read. For greater ſecurity, the Saracens were removed to Puglia 400 years after the conqueſt of Sicily by their anceſtors. Under Conrad and Manfred Sicily remained quiet ; and from that time the hiſtory of Sicily is related under the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Naples,</hi> n⁰ 26, &amp; c.</p><p>At the death of Charles II. of Spain, his ſpoils became an object of furious contention ; and at the peace of Utrecht, Sicily was ceded to Victor duke of Savoy, who, not many years after, was forced by the emperor Charles VI. to relinquiſh that fine iſland, and take Sardinia as an equivalent. But as the Spaniards had no concern in theſe bargains, they made a hidden attempt to recover Sicily, in which they failed through the vigilance of the Engliſh admiral Byng. He deſtroyed their fleet in 1718, and compelled them to drop their ſcheme for a time. In 1734 the Spanifh court resumed their deſign with ſucceſs. The infant Don Carlos drove the Germans out, and was crowned king of the two Sicilies at Palermo. When he paſsed into Spain to take poſſeſſion of that crown, he transferred the Sicilian diadem to his ſon Ferdinand III. of Sicily and IV. of Naples, and it has ever ſince remained in the poſſeſſion of the same family.</p><p>Sicily is ſeparated, as we have already obſerved, from Italy by a narrow strait called the <hi rend="italic">Faro of Messina.</hi> This ſtrait is ſtill remarkable for the rapidity of its currents and the irregular ebbing and flowing of the ſea, which ſometimes rushes in with ſuch violence as to endanger ſhips riding at anchor. Anciently it was much more remarkable for Scylla and Charybdis, the one a rock, and the other a whirlpool, between which it was very dangerous to ſteer, and concerning which ſo many fables have been related by the ancients. Scylla is a rock on the Italian side, oppoſite to Cape Pylores, which runs out into the ſea on the Sicilian ſide. Mr Brydone informs us, that the navigation of the ſtraits is not even yet performed without danger. He informs us, that the noiſe of the current which ſets through the ſtraits may be heard for ſeveral miles, like the roaring of ſome large impetuous river confined between narrow banks. In many places the water roſe into whirlpools and eddies, which are dangerous to ſhipping. The current ſet exactly for the rock of Scylla, and would certainly have carried any thing thrown into it againſt that point. Our author, however, is by no means of opinion that the ſtrait is ſo dangerous as the ancients have repreſented it ; though he thinks that the ſtrait is now probably much wider than formerly, which may have diminiſhed the danger. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Scylla.</hi> There are many ſmall rocks,<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0465.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0459"/>
which show their heads near the baſe of the large ones. Theſe are probably the dogs deſcribed by the ancient poets as howling round Scylla. The rock is near 200 feet high, and has a kind of caſtle or fort built on its ſummit with a town called <hi rend="italic">Scylla</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Sciglio,</hi> containing 300 or 4c0 inhabitants on its ſouth side, which gives the title of prince to a Calabreſe family.</p><p>Charybdis is now ſo much diminiſhed, that it ſeems almoſt reduced to nothing in compariſon of what it was, though even yet it is not to be paſſed without danger. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Charybdis.</hi></p><p>In the ſtraits, Mr Brydone informs us, a moſt ſurpriſing phenomenon is to be obſerved. In the heat of ſummer, after the ſea and air have been much agitated, there appears in the heavens over the ſtraits a great variety of singular forms, ſome at rest and others moving with great velocity. Theſe forms, in proportion as the light increaſes, ſeem to become more aerial, till at laſt, ſome time before ſun-riſe, they totally diſappear. The Sicilians repreſent this as the moſt beautiful ſight in nature. Leonti, one of their beſt and lateſt writers, ſays, that the heavens appear crowded with a variety of objects, ſuch as palaces, woods, gardens, &amp; c. beſides the figures of men and other animals that appear in motion among them. Some treatiſes have been written concerning this phenomenon ; but nothing ſatisfactory has been delivered concerning its cauſe.</p><p>Though Sicily lies in a warm climate, the air is healthful, being refreſhed with ſea-breezes on every ſide. It has at all times been remarkably fertile ; but the era of its greateſt proſperity was from the ſiege of Syracuſe by the Athenians to the Carthaginian conqueſts. Then and long after it supplied with grain in years of ſcarcity all the countries upon the Mediterranean except Egypt and the coaſts of Alia, and Rome and Carthage continually. Even now, under all the impediments of ſuperſtition and bad government, its productions are, in quantity and quality, the beſt in Europe. Of the vegetable are grain, wines, oil, fruits, tobacco, mulberry trees for the ſilkworm, cotton, medicinal roots, and ſugar canes. The laſt of theſe flouriſh near Avola and Merilli. They are of an inferior quality to thoſe of the West Indies, but their ſugar is ſweeter than any other. The animal production is similar to that of Italy, but the horned cattle are a ſmaller breed. The coaſts abound with fiſh, particularly with tunney and anchovies ; the export of which forms a very lucrative branch of commerce. There are mines of ſilver, copper, and lead, but none are worked. Near Palma are beds of the beſt ſulphur : at the mouth of the river Giaretta is found a yellow amber, preferable to that of the Baltic ; and in every part of the iſland quarries of marbles, that have furniſhed materials for all the noble edifices of Sicily. The moſt beautiful are in the neighbourhood of Palermo, particularly the yellow, and thoſe that reſemble the verde antique, porphyry, and lapis lazuli. The population of the iſland amounts to 1,300,000 fouls ; not as much again as the ſingle city of Syracuſe formerly contained.</p><p>Here are ſeveral rivers and good ſprings ; but few of the rivers are navigable, having but a ſhort courſe, and descending precipitately from the mountains. The chief are the Cantera, the Janetta, and the Salso ; of which, the two former run from west to eaſt, and the third from north to ſouth.</p><p>Of the mountains in this iſland the moſt noted is Mount Etna, now called <hi rend="italic">Monte Gibellο,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Mοngibellο,</hi> a volcano whoſe eruptions have often proved fatal to the neighbouring country. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Etna.</hi></p><p>Were the Sicilians a cultivated people, among whom thoſe arts were encouraged which not only promote the wealth and comfort of a nation, but also exerciſe the nobler faculties and extend the views of mankind, the circumſtances of their government are ſuch, that it might gradually be improved into a free conſtitution : but to this, the ignorance, ſuperſtition, and poverty, of the people ſeem to be invincible obſtacles. The monarchical power in Sicily is far from being absolute ; and the parliament claims a ſhare of public authority independently of the will of the king, deduced from a compact made between Roger and the Norman barons after the expulſion of the Saracens, This claim is denied by the king, who wiſhes the nobles to conſider their privileges as derived solely from his favour. Hence the government is in a ſituation which greatly reſembles that of our own and the other kingdoms of Europe in the feudal times ; there are continual jealouſies and oppoſitions between the king and the barons, of which an enlightened people might eaſily take advantage, and obtain that ſhare in the conſtitution which might ſecure them from future oppreſſion. In theſe diſputes, the king has the advantage at leaſt of power if not of right; and ſeveral works, in which the claims of the Sicilian barons have been aſſerted, were publicly burned a few years ago.</p><p>As the sovereign holds his court at Naples, Sicily is governed by a viceroy, who is appointed only for three years, though at the end of that term his commiſſion is sometimes renewed. He lives in great ſtate, and, as the repreſentative of the king, his power is very conſiderable. He preſides in all the courts and departments of government, and is commander in chief of all the forces : he calls or diſſolves the parliament when he pleaſes ; and by him all orders, laws, and ſentences, muſt be ſigned : but his office is far from being deſirable, as it generally renders him the object either of the jealouſy of the court of Naples, or of the hatred of the Sicilians.</p><p>The parliament conſiſts of the nobles, the biſhops, and abbots, and the repreſentatives of 43 cities, which are immediately ſubject to the crown. Thoſe cities which are ſubject to any of the nobles ſend no members to the parliament ; in theſe the king has not much authority, and derives little advantage from them. According to the laws, the parliament ought to be aſſembled at the end of every three years : but the government pays little attention to this rule. The common people are in general very much attached to the nobles, and are inclined to take their part in all their differences with the court : but the magiſtrates and principal inhabitants of the cities which belong to theſe feudal lords, wiſh to get rid of their authority, and imagine that they ſhould be leſs oppreſſed, if immediately ſubject to the king : theſe inclinations are not diſagreeable to the court, and are encouraged by moſt of the lawyers, who are of great ſervice to government in conteſt- ing the privileges of the nobles. Many of theſe privileges are now abridged ; and the power of the barons, with reſpect to the adminiſtration of juſtice in their domains, was very properly limited by the viceroy Ca-<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0466.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0460"/>
raccioli, in the year 1784. The government of this nobleman was very beneficial to Sicily, as he, in a great meaſure, cleared the island of the banditti that uſed to infeſt it, and made ſeveral excellent regulations for the eſtabliſhment of ſocial order and perſonal ſecurity. He deserves the thanks of every well-wiſher to mankind for Waving aboliſhed the court of inquiſition, which had been eſtabliſhed in this country by Ferdinand the Catholic, and made dependent on the authority of the grand inquiſitor of Spain. Its laſt <hi rend="italic">auto da fe</hi> was held in the year 1724, when two perſons were burned. At length Charles III. rendered it independent of the Spaniſh inquiſitor, and abridged its power, by forbidding it to make uſe of the torture, and to inflict public punishments. The Marcheſe Squillace, and his ſucceſſor the Marcheſe Tanucci, were both enemies to the hierarchy; and, during their viceroyalties, took care to appoint ſenſible and liberal men to the office of inquiſitor : the laſt of whom was Ventimiglia, a man of a moſt humane and amiable character, who heartily wiſhed for the abolition of this diabolical court, and readily contributed toward it. While he held the office of inquiſitor, he always endeavoured to procure the acquittal of the accuſed; and when he could ſuceed no other way, would pretend ſome informality in the trial. The total annihilation of this inſtrument of the worſt of tyranny was reſerved for Caraccioli. A prieſt being accuſed to the inquiſition, was dragged out of his houſe and thrown into the dungeon. He was condemned; but, on account of informality, and a violation of juſtice in the trial, he appealed to the viceroy, who appointed a committee of juriſts to examine the proceſs. The inquiſitor refuſed to acknowledge the authority of this commiſſion ; pretending that to expoſe the ſecrets of the holy office, and to ſubmit its deciſions to the examination of lay judges, would be ſo inconsiſtent with his duty, that he would see the inquiſition aboliſhed rather than consent to it. Caraccioli took him at his word, and procured a royal mandate by which the holy office was at once annihilated. He aſſembled all the nobility, judges, and biſhops, on the 27th of March 1782, in the palace of the inquiſition, and commanded the king’s order to be read ; after which he took poſſession of the archives, and cauſed all the prisons to be ſet open : in theſe were at that time only two priſoners, who had been condemned to perpetual confinement for witchcraft. The papers relating to the finances were preſerved ; but all the rest were publicly burned. The poſſeſſions of the holy office were aſſigned to the uſe of churches and charitable inſtitutions : but the officers then belonging to it retained their ſalaries during their lives. The palace itſelf is converted into a cuſtomhouſe, and the place where heretics were formerly roaſted alive for the honour of the Catholic faith, is now changed into a public garden. The cognizance of offences against orthodoxy is committed to the biſhops : but they cannot cite any one to appear before them without permiſſion from the viceroy ; neither can they confine any perſon to a ſolſtary priſon, nor deny him the privilege of writing to his friends, and converſing freely with his advocate. The nobility are ſo numerous in this iſland, that Labat ſays it is paved with noblemen. The general aſſembly of parliament is compoſed of 66 archbiſhops, biſhops, abbots, and priors, which form the Bracchio eccleſiaſtico.</p><p>Fifty-eight princes, 27 dukes, 37 marquisses, 27 counts, 1 viſcount, and 79 barons, form the militaire ; and the demaniale conſiſts of 43 repreſentatives of free towns. Out of each bracchio four deputies are choſen to conduct public buſineſs. But the viceroy, the prince of Butera, and the prætor of Palermo, are always the three firſt. <hi rend="italic">N. B.</hi> There are many titled perſons that have no ſeat in the aſſembly, viz. 62 princes, 55 dukes, 87 marquiſſes, 1 count, and 282 other feudatories. There are three archbiſhoprics and ſeven bishoprics ; and the iſland, ever ſince it was conquered by the Saracens, has been divided into three parts or valleys ; namely, the V <hi rend="italic">al di Demons, Pal di Noto,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Pal di Mazzara.</hi></p></div></body></text></TEI>