<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0510.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0504-01" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>STMSON</label>
(Dr Robert), profeſſor of mathematics in the univerſity of Glaſgow, was born in the year 1687 of a reſpectable family, which had held a ſmall eſtate in the county of Lanerk for ſome generations. He was, we think, the ſecond ſon of the family. A younger brother was profeſſor of medicine in the univerſity of St Andrew’s, and is known by ſome works of reputation, particularly a Diſſertation on the Nervous Syſtem, occasioned by the Diſſection of a Brain completely Oſſified.</p><p>Dr Simſon was educated in the univerſity of Glaſgow under the eye of ſome of his relations who were profeſſors. Eager after knowledge, he made great prgreſs in all his ſtudies ; and, as his mind did not, at the very firſt openings of ſcience, ſtrike into that path which afterwards ſo ſtrongly attracted him, and in which he proceeded ſo far almoſt without a companion, he acquired in every walk of ſcience a ſtock of information, which, though it had never been much augmented afterwards, would have done credit to a profeſſional man in any of his ſtudies. He became, at a very early period, an adept in the philoſophy and theology of the ſchools, was able to ſupply the place of a ſick relation in the claſs of oriental languages, was noted for hiſtorical knowledge, and one of the moſt knowing botaniſts of his time.</p><p>It was during his theological ſtudies, as preparatory for his entering into orders, that mathematics took hold of his fancy. He uſed to tell in his convivial moments how he amuſed himſelf when preparing his exerciſes for the divinity hall. When tired with vague ſpeculation, in which he did not meet with certainty to reward his labours, he turned up a book of oriental philology, in which he found ſomething which he could diſcover to be true or to be falſe, without going out of the line of ſtudy which was to be of ultimate uſe to</p><p>him, Sometimes even this could not relieve his fatigue. He then had recourſe to mathematics, which never tailed to ſatisfy and refreſh him. For a long while he reſtricted himſelf to a very moderate uſe of the cordial, fearing that he would ſoon exhauſt the ſmall ſtock which ſo limited and abſtract a ſcience could yield ; till at laſt he found, that the more he learned, a wider field opened to his view, and ſcenes that were inexhauſtible. Becoming acquainted with ſubjects far beyond the elements of the ſcience, and with numbers of names celebrated during that period of ardent reſearch all over Europe, he found it to be a manly and important ſtudy, by which he was as likely to acquire reputation as by any other. About this time, too, a proſpect began to open of making mathematics his profession for life. He then gave himſelf up to it without reserve.</p><p>His original incitement to this ſtudy as a treat, as ſomething to pleaſe and refreſh his mind in the midſt of ſeverer taſks, gave a particular turn to his mathematical ſtudies, from which he never could afterwards deviate. Perſpicuity and elegance are more attainable, and more diſcernible, in pure geometry, than in any other parts of the ſcience of meaſure. To this therefore he chiefly devoted himſelf. For the ſame reaſon he preferred the ancient method of ſtudying pure geometry, and even felt a dislike to the Carteſian method of ſubſtituting ſymbols for operations of the mind, and ſtill more was he diſguſted with the ſubſtitution of ſymbols for the very objects of diſcuſſion, for lines, ſurfaces, ſolids, and their affections. He was rather diſpoſed in the ſolution of an algebraic problem, where quantity alone was conſidered, to ſubſtitute figure and its affections for the algebraic ſymbols, and to convert the algebraic formula into an analogous geometrical theorem. And he came at laſt to conſider algebraic analyſis as little better than a kind of mechanical knack, in which we proceed without ideas of any kind, and obtain a reſult without meaning, and without being conſcious of any proceſs of reaſoning, and therefore without any conviction of its truth. And there is no denying, that if genuine unſophiſticated taste alone is to be conſulted, Dr Simſon was in the right : for though it muſt alſo be acknowledged, that the reaſoning in algebra is as ſtrict as in the pureſt geometry of Euclid or Apollonius, the <hi rend="italic">expert</hi> analyſt has little perception of it as he goes on, and his final equation is not felt by himſelf as the reſult of ratiocination, any more than if he had obtained it by Paſcal’s arithmetical mill. This does not in the leaſt diminiſh our admiration of the algebraic analyſis ; for its almoſt boundleſs graſp, its rapid and certain procedure, and the delicate metaphylics and great addreſs which may be diſplayed in conducting it. Such, however, was the ground of the ſtrong bias of Dr Simſon’s mind to the analyſis of the ancient geometers. It increaſed as he went forward ; and his veneration (we may call it his <hi rend="italic">love</hi> or <hi rend="italic">affection)</hi> for the ancient geometry was carried to a degree of idolatry. His chief labours were exerted in efforts to reſtore the works of the ancient geometers ; and he has nowhere bestowed much pains in advancing the modern discoveries in mathematics. The noble inventions, for example, of fluxions and of logarithms, by which our progreſs in mathematical knowledge, and in the uſeful application of this knowledge, is ſo much promoted, attracted the notice of Dr Simſon ; but he has contented himſelf with de-<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0511.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0505"/>
monſtrating their truth on the genuine principles of the ancient geometry. Yet was he very thoroughly acquainted with all the modern diſcoveries ; and there are to be ſeen among his papers diſcuſſions and inveſtigations in the Carteſian method, which ſhow him thoroughly acquainted with all the principles, and even expert in the <hi rend="italic">tours de main,</hi> of the moſt refined symbolical analyſis<note anchored="true" n="1" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="smallcaps">(a)</hi> In 1752 the writer of this article being then his ſcholar, requeſted him to examine an account which he gave him of what he thought a new curve (a conchoid having a circle for its bale ). Dr Simſon returned it next day with a regular list of its leading properties, and he inveſtigation of ſuch as he thought his scholar would not ſo eaſily trace. In this haſty ſcrawl the lines related to the circle were familiarly conſidered as arithmetical fractions of the radius conſidered as unity. This was before Euler published his Arithmetic of the Sines and Tangents, now in univerſal uſe.</p></note> <hi rend="smallcaps">(a).</hi></p><p>About the age of 25 Dr Simſon was choſen regius professor of mathematics in the univerſity of Glaſgow. He went to London immediately after his appointment, and there formed an acquaintance with the moſt eminent men, of that bright era of Britiſh ſcience. Among theſe he always mentioned Captain Halley (the celebrated Dr Edmund Halley) with particular reſpect ; ſaying, that he had the moſt acute penetration, and the moſt juſt taſte in that ſcience, of any man he had ever known. And, indeed, Dr Halley has ſtrongly exemplified both of theſe in his divination of the work of <hi rend="italic">Apollonius de Sectione Spatii,</hi> and the 8th book of his <hi rend="italic">Conics,</hi> and in ſome of the moſt beautiful theorems in Sir Iſaac Newton’s <hi rend="italic">Principia.</hi> Dr Simſon alſo admired the wide and maſterly ſteps which Newton was accuſtomed to take in his inveſtigations, and his manner of ſubſtituting geometrical figures for the quantities which are obſerved in the phenomena of nature. It was from Dr Simſon that the Writer of this article had the remarks which has been oftener than once repeated in the courſe of this Work, “ That the 39th propoſition of the firſt book of the <hi rend="italic">Principia</hi> was the moſt important propoſition that had ever been exhibited to the phyſico-mathematical philoſopher ;” and he uſed always to illuſtrate to his more advanced ſcholars the superrority of the geometrical over the algebraic analyſis, by comparing the ſolution given by Newton of the inverſe problem of centripetal forces, in the 42d propoſition of that book, with the one given by John Bernoulli in the Memoirs of the Academy of Sciences at Paris for 1713. We have heard him ſay,that to his own knowledge Newton frequently inveſtigated his propoſitions in the symbolical way, and that it was owing chiefly to Dr Halley that they did not finally appear in that dreſs. But if Dr Simſon was well informed, we think it a great argument in favour of the ſymbolic analyſis, when this moſt ſucceſsful <hi rend="italic">practical artist</hi> (for ſo we muſt call Newton when engaged in a taſk of discovery) found it conducive either to diſpatch or perhaps to his very progreſs.</p><p>Returning to his academical chair, Dr Simſon diſcharged the duties of a profeſſor for more than 50 years with great honour to the univerſity and to himſelf.</p><p>It is almoſt needleſs to ſay, that in his prelections he followed ſtrictly the Euclidian method in elementary geometry. He made uſe of Theodoſius as an introduction to spherical trigonometry In the higher geometry he prelected from his own Conics ; and he gave a ſmall ſpecimen of the <hi rend="italic">linear problems</hi> of the ancients, by explaining the properties, ſometimes ot the conchoid, ſometimes of the ciſſoid, with their application to the ſolution of ſuch problems. In the more advanced claſs he was accuſtomed to give Napier’s mode of conceiving logarithms, <hi rend="italic">i. e.</hi> quantities as generated by motion ; and Mr Cotes’s view of them, as the ſums of ratiunculæ ; and to demonſtrate Newton’s lemmas concerning the limits of ratios ; and then to give the elements of the fluxionary calculus ; and to finiſh his courſe with a ſelect ſet of propoſitions in optics, gnomonics, and central forces. His method of teaching was ſimple and perſpicuous, his elocution clear, and his manner easy and impreſſive. He had the reſpect, and ſtill more the affection, of his ſcholars.</p><p>With reſpect to his ſtudſes, we have already informed the reader that they got an early bias to pure geometry, and to the elegant but ſcrupulous methods of the ancients.</p><p>We have heard Dr Simſon ſay, that it was in a great meaſure owing to Dr Halley that he ſo early directed his efforts to the reſtoration of the ancient geometers. He had recommended this to him, as the moſt certain way for him, then a very young man, both to acquire reputation, and to improve his own knowledge and taſte, and he preſented him with a copy of Pappus’s Mathematical Collections, enriched with ſome of his own notes. The perſpicuity of the ancient geometrical analyſis, and a certain elegance in the nature of the ſolutions which it affords, eſpecially by means of the local theorems, ſoon took firm hold of his fancy, and made him, with the ſanguine expectation of a young man, direct his very firſt efforts to the recovery of this <hi rend="italic">in totο;</hi> and the reſtoration of Euclid’s Poriſms was the firſt taste which he ſet himſelf. The accompliſhed geometer knows what a deſperate talk this was, from the ſcanty and mutilated account which we have of this work in a single passage of Pappus. It was an ambition which nothing but ſucceſs could juſtify in ſo young an adventurer. He ſucceeded ; and ſo early as 1718 ſeemed to have been in complete poſſeſſion of this method of inveſtigation, which was conſidered by the eminent geometers of antiquity as their ſureſt guide through the labyrinths of the higher geometry. Dr Simſon gave a ſpecimen of his diſcovery in 1723 in the Philoſophical Tranſactions. And after this time he ceaſed not from his endeavours to recover that choice collection of Poriſms which Euclid had collected, as of the moſt general uſe in the ſolution of difficult queſtions. What ſome of theſe muſt have been was pointed out to Dr Simſon by the very nature of the general propoſition of Pappus, which he has reſtored. Others were pointed out by the lemmas which Pappus has given as helps to the young mathematician towards their demonſtration. And, being thus in poſſeſſion of a considerable number, their mutual relations pointed out a sort of syſtem, of which theſe made a part, and of which the blanks now remained to be filled up.</p><p>Dr Simſon, having thus gained his favourite point,<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0512.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0506"/>
had leisure to turn his attention to the other works oſ the ancient geometers, and the poriſms of Euclid now had only an occaſional ſhare. The <hi rend="italic">loci plani</hi> of Apollonius was another taſk which he very early engaged in, and completed about the year 1738. But, after it was printed, he imagined that he had not given the <hi rend="italic">ipsissimae proposιtiones</hi> of Apollonius, and in the preciſe spirit and order of that author. The impreſſion lay by him for ſome years ; and it was with great reluctance that he yielded to the intreaties of his mathematical friends, and publiſhed the work, in 1746, with ſome emendations, where he thought he had deviated fartheſt from his author. He quickly repented of this ſcanty conceſſion, and recalled what he could of the ſmall number of copies which he had given to the bookſellers, and the impreſſion again lay by him for years. He afterwards re-corrected the work, and ſtill with ſome reluctance allowed it to come abroad as the Reſtitution of Apollonius. The public, however, had not been ſo faſtidious as Dr Simſon, and the work had acquired great celebrity, and he was now conſidered as one of the firſt and the moſt elegant geometers of the age : for, in the mean time, he had publiſhed his Conic Sections, a work of uncommon merit, whether we conſider it as equivalent to a complete reſtitution of the celebrated work of Apollonius Pergæus, or as an excellent ſyſtem of this important part of mathematics. It is marked with the ſame features as the <hi rend="italic">loci plani,</hi> the moſt anxious ſolicitude to exhibit the very text of Apollonius, even in the propoſitions belonging to the books which had been completely lost. Theſe could be recovered in no other way but by a thorough knowledge of the preciſe plan propoſed by the author, and by taking it for granted that the author had accurately accompliſhed this plan. In this manner did Viviani proceed in the firſt attempt which was made to reſtore the conics of Apollonius ; and he has given us a detail of the proceſs of his conjectures, by which we may form an opinion of its juſtneſs, and of the probability how far be has attained the deſired object. Dr Simſon’s view in his performance was ſomething different, deviating a little in this one caſe from his general track. He was not altogether pleaſed with the work of Viviani, even as augmented by the eighth book added by Halley, and his wiſh was to reſtore the ancient original. But, in the mean time, an academical text book for conic ſections was much wanted. He was much dissatisfied with thoſe in common uſe ; and he was not inſenſible of the advantage reſulting from the consideration of theſe ſections, independent of the cone firſt introduced by Dr Wallis. He therefore compoſed this excellent treatiſe as an elementary book, not to ſuperſede, but to prepare for the ſtudy of Apollonius ; and accordingly accommodates it to this purpoſe, and gives ſeveral important propoſitions in their proper places, express <hi rend="italic">ly as restitutions of Apollonius,</hi> whom he keeps conſtantly in view through the whole work.</p><p>Much about this time Dr Simſon ſeriouſly began to prepare a perfect edition of Euclid’s Elements. The intimate acquaintance which he had by this time acquired with all the original works of the ancient geometers, and their ancient commentators and critics, encouraged him to hope that he could reſtore to his original luſtre this leader in mathematical ſcience ; and the errors which had crept into this celebrated work, and</p><p>which ſtill remained in it, appeared of magnitude ſufficient to merit the moſt careful efforts for their removal. The <hi rend="smallcaps">data</hi> also, which were in like manner the introduction to the whole art of geometrical inveſtigation, ſeemed to call more loudly for his amending hand. For it appears that the Saracens, who have preſerved to us the writings of the ancients, have contented themſelves with admiring theſe celebrated works, and have availed themſelves of the knowledge which they contain ; but they have ſhown no inclination to add to the ſtock, or to promote the ſciences which they had received. They could not do any thing without the synthetical books of the geometers ; but, not meaning to go beyond the diſcoveries which they had made, they neglected all the books which related to the analytic art alone, and the greateſt part of them (about 25 out of 30) have irrecoverably perished. The data of Euclid have fortunately been preſerved, but the book was neglected, and the only ancient copies, which are but three or four, are miſerably erroneous and mutilated. Fortunately, it is no very arduous matter to reinſtate this work in its original perfection. The plan is preciſe, both in its extent and its method. It had been reſtored, therefore, with ſucceſs by more than one author. But Dr Simſon’s comprehensive view of the whole analytical ſyſtem pointed out to him many occaſions for amendment. He therefore made its inſtitution a joint taſk with that of the elements. All the lovers of true geometry will acknowledge their obligations to him for the edition of the Elements and data which he publiſhed about 1758. The text is corrected with the moſt judicious and ſcrupulous care, and the notes are ineſtimable, both for their information, and for the tendency which they muſt have to form the mind of the itudent to a true judgment and taſte in mathematical ſubjects. The more accompliſhed reader will perhaps be sometimes diſpoſed to ſmile at the axiom which ſeems to pervade the notes, “ that a work of Euclid muſt be ſuppoſed without error or defect.” If this was not the caſe, Euclid has been obliged to his editor in more inſtances than one. Nor ſhould his greateſt admirers think it impoſſible that in the progreſs of human improvement; a geometrical truth ſhould occur to one of theſe latter days, which eſcaped the notice of even the Lincean Euclid. Such merit, however, Dr Simſon nowhere claims, but lays every blame of error, omiſſion, or obſcurity, to the charge of Proclus, Theon, and other editors and commentators of the renowned Grecian.</p><p>There is another work of Apollonius on which Dr Simſon has beſtowed great pains, and has reſtored, as we imagine, <hi rend="italic">omnibus numeris perfectum,</hi> viz. the <hi rend="smallcaps">Sectio determinata</hi>; one of thoſe performances which are of indiſpenſable uſe in the application of the ancient analyſis. This also ſeems to have been an early taſk, tho' we do not know the date of his labours on it. It did not appear till after his death, being then publiſhed along with the great work, the Poriſms of Euclid, at the expence of the late Earl Stanhope, a nobleman intimately converſant with the ancient geometry, and zealous for its reception among the mathematicians of the preſent age. He had kept up a conſtant correſpondence with Dr Simſon on mathematical ſubjects ; and at his death in 1768, engaged Mr Clow professor of logic in the univerſity of Glaſgow, to whoſe care the Doctor had left all his valuable papers, to make a<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0513.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0507"/>
ſelection of ſuch as would ſerve to ſupport and increaſe his well earned reputation as <hi rend="smallcaps">the Restorer</hi> of <hi rend="smallcaps">ancient Geometry.</hi></p><p>We have been thus particular in our account of Dr Simſon’s labours in theſe works, becauſe his manner of execution, while it does honour to his inventive powers, and ſhows his juſt taſte in mathematical compoſition, alſo confirms our former aſſertion, that he carried his reſpect for the ancient geometers to a degree of ſuperſtitious idolatry, and that his fancy, unchecked, viewed them as incapable of error or imperfection. This is diſtinctly to be ſeen in the emendations which he has given of the texts, particularly in his editions of Euclid. Not only every imperfection of the reading is aſcribed to the ignorance of copyiſts, and every indiſtinctneſs in the conception, inconcluſiveneſs in the reasoning, and defect in the method, is aſcribed to the ignorance or miſtake of the commentators ; but it is all along aſſumed that the work was perfect in its kind ; and that by exhibiting a perfect work, we reſtore the genuine original. This is ſurely gratuitous ; and it is very poſſible that it has, in ſome inſtances, made Dr Simſon fail of his anxious purpoſe, and give us even a better than the original. It has undoubtedly made him fail in what <hi rend="italic">ſhould have been</hi> his great purpoſe, viz. to give the world a connected ſyſtem of the ancient geometrical analyſis ; ſuch as would, in the firſt place, exhibit it in its moſt engaging form, elegant, perſpicuous, and comprehenſive ; and, in the next place, ſuch as ſhould engage the mathematicians of the preſent age to adopt it as the moſt certain and ſucceſsful conductor in thoſe laborious and difficult reſearches in which the demands of modern ſcience continually engage them. And this might have been expected, in the province of ſpeculative geometry at leaſt, from a perſon of ſuch extenſive knowledge of the properties of figure, and who had ſo eminently ſucceeded in the many trials which he had made of its powers. We might have expected that he would at leaſt have exhibited in one ſyſtematic point of view, what the ancients had done in ſeveral detached branches of the ſcience, and how far they had proceeded in the ſolution of the ſeveral ſucceſſive claſſes of problems ; and we might have hoped, that he would have inſtructed us in what manner we ſhould apply that method to the ſolution of problems oſ a more elevated kind, daily preſented to us in the queſtions of physico-mathematical ſcience. By this he would have acquired diſtinguiſhed honour, and ſcience would have received the moſt valuable improvement. But Dr Simſon has done little of all this ; and we cannot ſay that great helps have been derived from his labours by the eminent mathematicians of this age, who are ſucceſsfully occupied in advancing our knowledge of nature, or in improving the arts of life. He has indeed contributed greatly to the entertainment of the ſpeculative mathematician, who is more delighted with the conſcious exerciſe of his own reaſoning powers, than with the final reſult of his reſearches. Yet we are not even certain that Dr Simſon has done this to the extent he wiſhed and hoped. He has not engaged the liking of mathematicians to this analyſis, by preſenting it in the moſt agreeable form. His own extreme anxiety to tread in the very footſteps of the original authors, has, in a thouſand inſtances, precluded him from uſing his own extenſive knowledge, that he might not</p><p>employ principles which were not of a claſs inferior to that of the question in hand. Thus, of neceſſity, did the method appear trammelled. We are deterred from employing a proceſs which appears to reſtrain us in the application of the knowledge which we have already acquired ; and, diſguſted with the tedious, and perhaps indirect path, by which we muſt arrive at an object which we ſee clearly over the hedge, and which we could reach by a few ſteps, of the ſecurity of which we are otherwiſe perfectly aſſured. Theſe prepoſſeſſions are indeed founded on miſtake ; but the miſtake is ſuch, that all fall into it, till experience has enlarged their views. This circumſtance alone has hitherto prevented mathematicians from acquiring that knowledge of the ancient analyſis which would enable them to proceed in their reſearches with certainty, diſpatch, and delight. It is therefore deeply to be regretted, that this eminent genius has occupied, in this ſuperſtitious palaeology, a long and busy life, which might have been employed in original works of infinite advantage to the world, and honour to himſelf.</p><p>Our readers will, it is hoped, consider theſe obſervations as of general ſcientific importance, and as intimately connected with the hiſtory of mathematics ; and therefore as not improperly introduced in the biographical account of one of the moſt eminent writers on this ſcience. Dr Simſon claimed our notice as a mathematician ; and his affectionate admiration of the ancient analyſis is the prominent feature of his literary character. By this he is known all over Europe ; and his name is never mentioned by any foreign author without ſome very honourable allusion to his diſtinguiſhed geometrical elegance and ſkill. Dr James Moor, profeſſor of Greek in the univerſity of Glaſgow, no leſs eminent for his knowledge in ancient geometry than for his profeſſional talents, put the following appoſite inſcription below a portrait of Dr Simſon :</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Geometriam, sub Tyranno barbaro sæva</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Servitute diu squalentem,</hi> in <hi rend="smallcaps">Libertatem</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Et decus antiquum vindicavit</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Unus.</hi></p><p>Yet it muſt not be underſtood that Dr Simſon’s predilection for the geometrical analyſis of the ancients did ſo far miſlead him as to make him neglect the ſymbolical analyſis of the preſent times ; on the contrary, he was completely matter of it, as has been already obſerved, and frequently employed it. In his academical lectures to the ſtudents of his upper claſſes, he uſed to point out its proper province (which he by no means limited by a ſcanty boundary), and in what caſes it might be applied with ſafety and advantage even to queſtions of pure geometry. He once honoured the writer of this article with the sight of a very ſhort diſſertation on this ſubject (perhaps the one referred to in the preface to his Conic Sections). In this piece he was perhaps more liberal than the moſt zealous partiſans of the ſymbolical analyſis could desire, admitting as a ſufficient equation</p><p><hi rend="italic">of</hi> the Conic Sections L = p <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> c/x <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> where L is the <hi rend="italic">latus X</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">rectum, X</hi> is the diſtance of any point of the curve from the focus, <hi rend="italic">p</hi> is the perpendicular drawn from the focus to the tangent in the given point, and <hi rend="italic">c</hi> is the chord of the equicurve circle drawn thro’ the focus. Unfortunately this diſſertation was not found among his pa-<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0514.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0508"/>
pers. He ſpoke in high terms oſ the Analytical Works of Mr Cotes, and oſ the two Bernoullis. He was conſulted by Mr M'Laurin during the progreſs of his ineſtimable Treatiſe of Fluxions, and contributed not a little to the reputation of that work. The ſpirit of that moſt ingenious algebraic demonſtration of the fluxions of a rectangle, and the very proceſs of the argument, is the ſame with Dr Simſon’s in his diſſertation on the limits of quantities. It was therefore from a thorough acquaintance with the ſubject, and by a juſt taſte, that he was induced to prefer his favourite analyſis, or, to ſpeak more properly, to exhort mathematicians to employ it in its own ſphere, and not to become ignorant of geometry, while they ſucceſsfully employed the ſymbolical analyſis in cases which did not require it, and which ſuffered by its admiſſion. It muſt be acknowledged, however, that in his later years, the diſguſt which he felt at the artificial and ſlovenly employment on ſubjects of pure geometry, ſometimes hindered him from even looking at the moſt refined and ingenious improvements of the algebraic analyſis which occur in the writings of Euler, D’Alembert, and other eminent maſters. But, when properly informed of them, he never failed to give them their due praiſe ; and we remember him ſpeaking, in terms of great ſatisfaction, of an improvement of the infiniteſimal calculus, by D’Alembert and De la Grange, in their reſearches concerning the propagation of sound, and the vibrations of muſical cords.</p><p>And that Dr Simſon not only was maſter of this calculus and the ſymbolical calculus in general, but held them in proper eſteem, appears from two valuable diſſertations to be found in his poſthumous works; the one on logarithms, and the other on the limits of ratios. The laſt, in particular, ſhows how completely he was ſatisfied with reſpect to the ſolid foundation of the method of fluxions ; and it contains an elegant and ſtrict demonſtration of all the applications which have been made of the method by its illuſtrious author to the objects of pure geometry.</p><p>We hoped to have given a much more complete and inſtructive account of this eminent geometer and his works, by the aid of a perſon fully acquainted with both, and able to appreciate their value ; but an accident has deprived us of this aſſiſtance, when it was too late to procure an equivalent : and we muſt requeſt our readers to accept of this very imperfect account, ſince we cannot do juſtice to Dr Simſon’s merit, unleſs almoſt equally converſant in all the geometry of the ancient Greeks.</p><p>The life of a literary man rarely teems with anecdote; and a mathematician, devoted to his ſtudies, is perhaps more abſtracted than any other perſon from the ordinary occurrences of life, and even the ordinary topics of converſation. Dr Simſon was of this claſs ; and, having never married, lived entirely a college life. Having no occaſion for the commodious houſe to which his place in the univerſity intitled him, he contented himſelf with chambers, good indeed, and ſpacious enough for his ſober accommodation, and for receiving his choice collection of mathematical writers, but without any decoration or commodious furniture. His official fervant sufficed for valet, footman, and chambermaid. As this retirement, was entirely devoted to ſtudy, he entertained no company in his chambers, but in a neighbouring</p><p>houſe, where his apartment was ſacred to him and his gueſts.</p><p>Having in early life devoted himſelf to the reſtoration of the works of the ancient geometers, he ſtudied them with unremitting attention ; and, retiring from the promiſcuous intercourſe of the world, he contented himſelf with a ſmall ſociety of intimate friends, with whom he could lay aſide every reſtraint of ceremony or reſerve, and indulge in all the innocent frivolities of life. Every Friday evening was ſpent in a party at whiſt, in which he excelled, and took delight in inſtructing others, till increaſing years made him leſs patient with the dulneſs of a lcholar. The card-party was followed by an hour or two dedicated ſolely to playful converſation. In like manner, every Saturday he had a leſs ſelect party to dinner at a houſe about a mile from town. Tire Doctor’s long life gave him occaſion to ſee the <hi rend="italic">dramatis perſonae</hi> of this little theatre ſeveral times completely changed, while he continued to give it a perſonal identity ; ſo that, without any deſign or wiſh of his own, it became, as it were, his own houſe and his own family, and went by his name In this ſtate did the preſent writer firſt ſee it, with Dr Simſon as its father and head, reſpected and beloved by every branch ; for, as it was for relaxation, and not for the enjoyment of his acknowledged ſuperiority, that he continued this habit of his early youth ; and as his notions “ of a fine talk” did not conſiſt in the pleaſure of having “ toſſed and gored a good many to-day,” his companions were as much at their eaſe as he wiſhed to be himſelf ; and it was no ſmall part of their entertainment (and of his too), to ſmile at thoſe innocent deviations from common forms, and thoſe miſtakes with reſpect to life and manners, which an almoſt total retirement from the world, and inceſſant occupation in an abſtract ſcience, cauſed this venerable preſident frequently to exhibit. Theſe are remembered with a more affecting regret, that they are now “ with the days that are paſt,” than the moſt pithy apophthegms, ushered in with an emphatical, “ Why, Sir!” or “ No, Sir!” which precludes all reply. Dr Simſon never exerted his preſidial authority, unleſs it were to check ſome infringement of good breeding, or any thing that appeared unfriendly to religion or purity of manners ; for theſe he had the higheſt reverence. We have twice heard him sing (he had a fine voice and moſt accurate ear) ſome lines of a Latin hymn to the divine geometer, and each time the rapturous tear ſtood in his eye.</p><p>But we ask the reader’s pardon for this digreſſion ; it is not however uſeleſs, ſince it paints the man as much as any recital of his ſtudies ; and to his acquaintances we are certain that it will be an acceptable memorandum. To them it was often matter of regret, that a perſon of ſuch eminent talents, which would have made him ſhine equally in any line oſ life, ſhould have allowed himſelf to be so completely devoted to a ſtudy which abſtracted lum from the ordinary purſuits of men, unfitted him for the active enjoyment of life, and kept him out of thoſe walks which they frequented, and where they would have rejoiced to meet him.</p><p>Dr Simſon was of an advantageous stature, with a fine countenance; and even in his old age had a graceful carriage and manner, and always, except when in mourning, dreſſed in white cloth. He was of a cheerful diſpoſition: and though he did not make the firſt.<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0515.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0509"/>
advances to acquaintance, had the moſt affable manner, and ſtrangers were at perfect eaſe in his company. He enjoyed a long courſe of uninterrupted health ; but towards the cloſe of life ſuffered from an acute diſeaſe, and was obliged to employ an aſſiſtant in his profeſſional labours for a few years preceding his death, which happened in 1768, at the age of 81. He left to the univerſity his valuable library, which is now arranged apart ſrom the reſt of the books, and the public uſe of it is limited by particular rules. It is conſidered as the moſt choice collection of mathematical books and manuſcripts in the kingdom, and many of them are rendered doubly valuable by Dr Simfon’s notes.</p></div></body></text></TEI>