<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0508.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0502-02" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SIMOOM</label>,
a hot wind which blows occaſionally in the deſerts of Africa, and probably in other widely extended countries parched in the ſame manner by a vertical ſun. Its effects on the human body are dreadful. If inhaled in any quantity, it produces inſtant ſuffocation, or at leaſt leaves the unhappy ſufferer oppreſſed with althma and lowneſs of ſpirits. The approach of this awful ſcourge of God is indicated by a redneſs in the air, well underſtood by thoſe who are accuſtomed to journey through the deſert ; and the only refuge which they have from it, is to fall down with their faces cloſe to the ground, and to continue as long as poſſible without drawing in their breath.</p><p>Mr Bruce, who, in his journey through the deſert, ſuffered from the ſimoom, gives of it the following graphical deſcription : “ At eleven o’clock, while we contemplated with great pleaſure the rugged top of Chiggre, to which we were faſt approaching, and where we were to ſolace ourſelves with plenty of good water, Idris our guide cried out, with a loud voice, fall upon you faces, for here is the ſimoom. I ſaw from the ſouth-eaſt a haze come, in colour like the purple part of the rainbow, but not ſo compreſſed or thick. It did not occupy twenty yards in breadth, and was about twelve feet high from the ground. It was a kind of bluſh upon the air, and it moved very rapidly ; for I ſcarce could turn to fall upon the ground with my head to the northward, when I felt the heat of its current plainly upon my face. We all lay flat on the ground as if dead, till Idris told us it was blown over. The meteor or purple haze which I ſaw was indeed paſſed, but the light air that ſtill blew was of heat to<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0509.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0503"/>
threaten ſuffocation. For my part, I found diſtinctly in my breaſt that I had imbibed a part of it, nor was I free of an aſthmatic ſenſation till I had been ſome months in Italy, at the baths of Poretta, near two years afterwards.” Though the ſeverity of this blaſt ſeems to have paſſed over them almoſt inſtantaneouſly, it continued to blow ſo as to exhauſt them till twenty minutes before five in the afternoon, laſting through all its stages very near six hours, and leaving them in a ſtate of the utmoſt deſpondency.</p></div></body></text></TEI>