<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0521.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0515-03" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SIXTUS V</label>
. (Pope), was born the 13th December 1521, in La Marca, a village in the ſeigniory of Montalto. His father, Francis Peretti, was a gardener, and his mother a servant maid. He was their eldeſt child, and was called Felix. At the age of nine he was hired out to an inhabitant of the village to keep ſheep ; but diſobliging his maſter, he was ſoon after degraded to be keeper of the hogs. He was engaged in this employment when Father Michael Angelo Selleri, a Franciſcan friar, aſked the road to Aſcoli, where he was going to preach. Young Felix conducted him thither, and ſtruck the father ſo much with his converſation and eagerneſs for knowledge, that he recommended him to the fraternity to which he had come. Accordingly he was received among them, inveſted with the habit of a lay brother, and placed under the ſacriſtan, to aſſiſt in ſweeping the church, lighting the candles, and other offices of that nature ; for which he was to be taught the reſponſes, and the rudiments of grammar. His progreſs in learning was ſo ſurpriſing, that at the age of 14 he was thought qualified to be gin his noviciate, and was admitted the year following to make his profeſſion.</p><p>He purſued his ſtudies with ſuch unwearied aſſiduity, that he was ſoon reckoned equal to the beſt diſputants. He was ordained prieſt in 1545, when he aſſumed the name of Father Montalto ; ſoon after he took his doctor’s degree, and was appointed profeſſor of theology at Sienna. It was then that he ſo effectually recommended himſelf to Cardinal di Carpi, and his ſecretary Boſſius, that they ever remained his ſteady friends. Meanwhile the ſeverity and obſtinacy of his temper inceſſantly engaged him in diſputes with his monastic brethren. His reputation for eloquence, which was now ſpread over Italy, about this time gained him ſome new friends. Among theſe were the Colonna family, and Father Ghiſilieri, by whoſe recommendation he was appointed inquisitor-general at Venice ; but he exerciſed that office with ſo much ſeverity, that he was obliged to flee precipitately from that city. Upon this he went to Rome, where he was made procurator-general of his order, and ſoon after accompanied Cardinal Buon Compagnon into Spain, as a</p><p>chaplain and conſultor to the inquiſition. There hc was treated with great reſpect, and liberal offers were made him to induce him to continue in Spain, which, however, he could not be prevailed on to accept.</p><p>In the mean time, news were brought to Madrid that Pius IV. was dead, and that Father Ghiſilieri, who had been made Cardinal Alexandrino by Paul IV. had ſucceeded him under the name of Pius V. Theſe tidings filled Montalto with joy, and not without reaſon, for he was immediately inveſted by the pontiff with new dignities. He was made general of his order, bishop of St Agatha, was ſoon after raiſed to the dignity of cardinal, and received a penſion. About this time he was employed by the Pope to draw up the bill of excommunication againſt Queen Elizabeth.</p><p>He began now to caſt his eyes upon the papacy ; and, in order to obtain it, formed and executed a plan of hypocriſy with unparalleled conſtancy and ſucceſs. He became humble, patient, and affable. He changed his dreſs, his air, his words, and his actions, ſo completely, that his moſt intimate friends declared him a new man. Never was there ſuch an abſolute victory gained over the paſſions ; never was a fictitious character ſo long maintained, nor the foibles of human nature ſo artfully concealed. He courted the ambaſſadors of every foreign power, but attached himſelf to the intereſts of none; nor did he accept a single favour that would have laid him under any peculiar obligation. He had formerly treated his relations with the greateſt tenderneſs, but he now changed his behaviour altogether. When his brother Anthony came to viſit him, he lodged him in an inn, and ſent him home next day, charging him to inform his family that he was now dead to his relations and the world.</p><p>When Pius V. died in 1572, he entered the conclave with the other cardinals, but ſeemed altogether indifferent about the election, and never left his apartment except to his devotion. When ſolicited to join any party, he declined it, declaring that he was of no conſequence, and that he would leave the choice of a Pope entirely to perſons of greater knowledge and experience. When Cardinal Ruon Compagnon, who aſſumed the name of Gregory XIII. was elected, Montalto aſſured him that he never wiſhed for any thing ſo much in his life, and that he would always remember his goodneſs, and the favours he had conferred on him in Spain. But the new Pope treated him with the greateſt contempt, and deprived him of his penſion. The cardinals alſo, deceived by his artifices, paid him no greater reſpect, and uſed to call him, by way of ridicule, the Roman beaſt ; the aſs of La Marca.</p><p>He now aſſumed all the infirmities of old age ; his head hung down upon his ſhoulders ; he tottered as he walked, and ſupported himſelf on a ſtaff. His voice became feeble, and was often interrupted by a cough ſo exceedingly ſevere, that it ſeemed every moment to threaten his diſſolution. He interfered in no public tranſactions, but ſpent his whole time in acts of devotion and benevolence. Mean time he conſtantly employed the ableſt ſpies, who brought him intelligence of every particular.</p><p>When Gregory XIII. died in 1585, he entered the conclave with the greateſt reluctance, and immediately ſhut himſelf up in his chamber, and was no more thought of than if he had not exiſted. When he went<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0522.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0516"/>
to maſs, for which purpoſe alone he left his apartment, he appeared perfectly indifferent about the event of the election. He joined no party, yet flattered all.</p><p>He knew early that there would be great diviſions in the conclave, and he was aware that when the leaders of the different parties were disappointed in their own views, they all frequently agreed in the election of ſome old and infirm cardinal, the length of whole life would merely enable them to prepare themſelves ſufficiently for the next vacancy. Theſe views directed his conduct, nor was he miſtaken in his hopes of ſucceſs.</p><p>Three cardinals, the leaders of oppoſite factions, being unable to procure the election which each of them wiſhed, unanimouſly agreed to make choice of Montalto. When they came to acquaint him with their intention, he fell into ſuch a violent fit of coughing that every perſon thought he would expire on the ſpot. He told them that his reign would laſt but a few days ; that, besides a continual difficulty of breathing, he wanted ſtrength to ſupport ſuch a weight, and that his ſmall experience rendered him very unfit for ſo important a charge. He conjured them all three not to abandon him, but to take the whole weight of affairs upon their own ſhoulders ; and declared that he would never accept the mitre upon any other terms : “ If you are resolved,” added he, “ to make me Pope, it will only be placing yourſelves on the throne. For my part, I ſhall be ſatisfied with the bare title. Let the world call me Pope, and I make you heartily welcome to the power and authority. The cardinals ſwallowed the bait, and exerted themſelves ſo effectually that Montalto was elected. He now pulled off the maſk which he had worn for 14 years. No ſooner was his election ſecured, than he ſtarted from his ſeat, flung down his ſtaff in the middle of the hall, and appeared almoſt a foot taller than he had done for ſeveral years.</p><p>When he was aſked, according to cuſtom, if he would accept of the Papacy, he replied, “ It is trifling to aſk whether I will accept what I have already accepted.— However, to ſatisfy any ſcruple that may ariſe, I tell you that I accept it with great pleaſure, and would accept another if I could get it ; tor I find myſelf able, by the Divine aſſiſtance, to manage two papacies.” His former complaiſance and humility diſappeared, together with his infirmities, and he now treated all around him with reſerve and haughtineſs. The firſt care of Sixtus V. the name which Montalto aſſumed, was to correct the abuſes, and put a ſtop to the enormities, which were daily committed in every part of the ecelesiaſtical ſtate. The lenity of Gregory’s government had introduced a general licentiouſneſs of manners, which burſt forth with great violence, after that Pontiff’s death. It had been uſual with former Popes to releaſe delinquents on the day of their coronation, who were therefore accuſtomed to ſurrender themſelves voluntary priſoners immediately after the election of the Pope. At preſent, however, they were fatally diſappointed.— When the governor of Rome and the keeper of St Angelo waited on his Holineſs, to know his intention in this particular, he replied, “ What have you to do with pardons, and releaſing of priſoners ? Is it not ſufficient that our predeceſſor has ſuffered the judges to remain unemployed theſe 13 years? Shall we alſo ſtain our pontificate with the ſame neglect of juſtice ? We have too long ſeen, with inexpreſſible concern, the prodi</p><p>gious degree of wickedneſs that reigns in the ſtate to think of granting pardons. Let the priſoners be brought to a ſpeedy trial, and puniſhed as they deſerve, to ſhow the world chat Divine Providence has called ns to the chair of St Peter, to reward the good, and chaſtiſe the wicked; that we bear not the ſword in vain, but are the miniſters of God, and a revenger to execute wrath on them that do evil.”</p><p>He appointed commiſſioners to inſpect the conduct of the judges, diſplaced thoſe who were inclined to lenity, and put others of ſevere diſpositions in their room. He offered rewards to any perſon who could convict them of corruption or partiality. He ordered the ſyndics of all the towns and signiories to make out a complete list of the diſorderly perſons within their diſtricts, and threatened the ſtrapado for the ſmalleſt omiſſion. In conſequence of this edict, the ſyndic of Albino was ſcourged in the market-place, becauſe he had left his nephew, an incorrigible libertine, out of his lift.</p><p>He made very ſevere laws againſt robbers and aſſaſsins. Adulterers, when diſcovered, ſuffered death; and they who willingly ſubmitted to the proſtitution of their wives, a cuſtom then common in Rome, received the ſame puniſhment. He was particularly careful of the purity of the female ſex, and never forgave thoſe who attempted to debauch them.</p><p>His execution of juſtice was as prompt as his edicts were rigorous. A Swiſs happening to give a Spaniſh gentleman a blow with his halberd, was ſtruck by him so rudely with a pilgrim’s ſtaff that he expired on the spot. Sixtus informed the governor of Rome that he was to dine early, and that juſtice muſt be executed on the criminal before he sat down to table. The Spaniſh ambaſſador and four cardinals intreated him not to disgrace the gentleman by suffering him to die on a gibbet, but to order him to be beheaded. “ He ſhall be hanged (replied Sixtus), but I will alleviate his diſgrace by doing him the honour to aſſiſt perſonally at lira death.” He ordered a gibbet to be erected before his own windows, where he continued fitting during the whole execution. He then called to his ſervants to bring in dinner, declaring that the act oſ juſtice which he had juſt ſeen had increaſed his appetite. When he roſe from table, he exclaimed, “ God be praiſed for the good appetite with which I have dined!”</p><p>When Sixtus aſcended the throne, the whole eccleſtaſtical ſtate was infeſted with bands of robbers, who, from their numbers and outrages, were exceedingly formidable ; by his prudent and vigorous conduct, however, he in a ſhort time extirpated the whole of theſe banditti.</p><p>Nor was the vigour of his conduct leſs conſpicuous, in his tranſactions with foreign nations. Before he had been pope two months he quarrelled with Philip II. of Spain, Henry III. of France, and Henry king of Navarre. His intrigues indeed in ſome meaſure influenced all the councils of Europe.</p><p>After his acceſſion to the pontificate he ſent for his family to Rome, with expreſs orders that they ſhould appear in a decent and modeſt manner. Accordingly, his sister Camilla came thither, accompanied by her daughter and two grandchildren. Some cardinals, in order to pay court to the pope, went out to meet her, and introduced her in a very magnificent dreſs. Sixtus pretended not to know her, and asked two or three<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0523.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0517"/>
times who ſhe was : Upon this one of the cardinals ſaid, “ It is your sister, holy father.” “ I have but one sister (replied Sixtus with a frown), and ſhe is a poor woman at Le Grotte ; if you have introduced her in this diſguiſe, I declare I do not know her ; yet I think I would know her again, if I ſaw her in the clothes ſhe uſed to wear.”</p><p>Her conductors at laſt found it neceſſary to carry her to an inn, and ſtrip her of her finery. When Camilla was introduced a ſecond time, Sixtus embraced her tenderly, and said, “ Now we know indeed that it is our sister : nobody shall make a princeſs of you but ourſelves.” He ſtipulated with his ſiſter, that ſhe ſhould neither aſk any favour in matters of government, nor intercede for criminals, nor interfere in the adminiſtration of juſtice ; declaring that every requeſt of that kind would meet with a certain refuſal. Theſe terms being agreed to, and punctually obſerved, he made the moſt ample proviſion not only ſor Camilla but for his whole relations.</p><p>This great man was alſo an encourager of learning. He cauſed an Italian tranſlation of the Bible to be published, which raiſed a good deal of diſcontent among the Catholics. When ſome cardinals reproached him for his conduct in this reſpect, he replied, “ It was publiſhed for the benefit of you cardinals who cannot read Latin.”</p><p>Sixtus died in 1590, aſter having reigned little more than five years. His death was aſcribed to poiſon, ſaid to have been adminiſtered by the Spaniards ; but the story ſeems rather improbable.</p><p>It was to the indulgence of a diſpoſition naturally formed for ſeverity, that all the defects of this wonderful man are to be aſcribed. Clemency was a ſtranger to his boſom ; his puniſhments were often too cruel, and ſeemed ſometimes to border on revenge. Paſquin was dreſſed one morning in a very naſty ſhirt, and being aſked by Martorio why he wore ſuch dirty linen ? replied, that he could get no other, for the pope had made his waſherwoman a princeſs, alluding to Camilla, who had formerly been a laundreſs. The pope ordered ſtrict ſearch to be made for the author of this lampoon, and offered him his life and a thouſand piſtoles if he would discover himſelf. The author was ſimple enough to make his appearance and claim the reward. “ It is true (ſaid the pope) we made ſuch a promiſe, and we ſhall keep it ; your life ſhall be ſpared, and you ſhall receive the money preſently : but we have reſerved to ourſelves the power of cutting off your hands and boring your tongue through, to prevent your being ſo witty for the future.” It is needless to add, that the ſentence was immediately executed. This, however, is the only inſtance oſ his reſenting the many ſevere satires that were publiſhed againſt him.</p><p>But though the conduct of Sixtus ſeldom excites love, it generally commands our eſteem, and ſometimes our admiration. He ſtrenuouſly defended the cauſe of the poor, the widow, and the orphan : he never refuſed audience to the injured, however wretched or forlorn their appearance was. He never forgave thoſe magiſtrates who were capable of partiality or corruption ; nor buffered crimes to paſs unpuniſhed, whether committed by the rich or the poor. He was frugal, temperate, ſober, and never neglected to reward the ſmalleſt favour which had been conferred on him before his exaltation.</p><p>When he mounted the throne, the treaſury was not only exhauſted, but in debt ; at his death it contained five millions of gold.</p><p>Rome was indebted to him for ſeveral of her greateſt embelliſhments, particularly the Vatican library : it was by him, too, that trade was firſt introduced into the Eccleſiaſtical State.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">SIYA-ghush,</hi> the caracal of Buffon, an animal of the cat kind. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Felis,</hi> n⁰ xviii.</p></div></body></text></TEI>