<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0516.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0510-08" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SINGING</label>,
the action of making divers inflections of the voice, agreeable to the ear, and correſpondent to the notes of a long or piece of melody. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Melody.</hi></p><p>The firſt thing to be done in learning to sing, is to raiſe a ſcale of notes by tones and ſemitones to an octave, and deſcend by the ſame notes ; and then to rise and fall by greater intervals, as a third, fourth, fifth, &amp; c. and to do all this by notes of different pitch. Then theſe notes are repreſented by lines and ſpaces, to which the syllables <hi rend="italic">fa, ſol, la, mi,</hi> are applied, and the pupil taught to name each line and ſpace thereby ; whence this practice is called <hi rend="italic">ſol-faing,</hi> the nature, reaſon, effects, &amp; c. whereof, ſee under the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Solfaing.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Singing</hi> <hi rend="italic">of Birds.</hi> It is worthy of obſervation, that the female of no ſpecies of birds ever sings : with birds it is the reverſe of what occurs in human kind. Among the feathered tribe, all the cares of life fall to the lot of the tender ſex ; theirs is the fatigue of incubation ; and the principal ſhare in nurſing the helpleſs brool: to alleviate theſe fatigues, and to ſupport her under them, nature hath given to the male the ſong, with all the little blandiſhments and ſoothing arts ; theſe he fondly exerts (even after courtſhip) on ſome ſpray contiguous to the neſt, during the time his mate is performing her parental duties. But that ſhe ſhould be silent is alſo another wiſe proviſion of nature, for her ſong would diſcover her neſt ; as would a gaudineſs of plumage, which, for the same reaſon, ſeems to have been denied her.</p><p>On the ſong of birds ſeveral curious experiments and obſervations have been made by the Hon. Dairies Barrington. See <hi rend="italic">Phil. Tranſ.</hi> vol. lxiii.</p></div></body></text></TEI>