<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0568.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0562-03" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SNORING</label>,
in medicine, otherwiſe called st <hi rend="italic">ertor,</hi> is a ſound like that of the cerchnon, but greater and more maniſeſt.</p><p>Many confound thoſe affections, and make them to differ only in place and magnitude, calling by the name of st <hi rend="italic">ertor</hi> that found or noiſe which is heard or ſuppoſed to be made in the paffage between the palate and the noſtrils as in thoſe who ſleep ; that boiling or bubbling noiſe, which in reſpiration proceeds from the larynx, or or head, or orifice of the alpera arteria, they call <hi rend="italic">cerchon;</hi> but if the ſound comes from the aſpera arteria itſelf, they will have it called <hi rend="italic">cerchnos,</hi> that is, as ſome underhand it, a rattling, or as others a ſtridulous or wheezing roughneſs of the aſpera arteria. In dying persons this affection is called by the Greeks ρεχχος <hi rend="italic">rhenchοs,</hi> which is a ſnoring or rattling kind of noiſe, proceeding as it were from a conflict between the breath and the humours in the aſpera arteria.</p><p>This and ſuch like affections are owing to a weakneſs of nature, as when the lungs are full of pus or humours : to which purpoſe we read in the Prognoſtics of Hippocrates, “ it is a bad ſign when there is no expectoration, and no diſeharge from the lungs, but a noiſe as from an ebullition is heard in the aſpera arteria from a plenitude of humour.” Expectoration is ſuppressed either by the viſcidity of the humour, which requires, to be diſcharged, and which adhering to the aſpera arteria, and being there agitated by the breath, excites that bubbling noiſe or stertor ; or by an obſtruction of. the bronchia ; or, laſtly, by a compreſſion of the aſpera arteria and throat, whence the paſſage is ſtraitened, in which the humours being agitated, excite ſuch a kind of noiſe as before deſcribed. Hence Galen calls thoſe who are ſtrait-breaſted st <hi rend="italic">ertorous.</hi> That author aſſigns but two cauſes of this ſymptom, which arc either the ſtraitneſs of the paſſage of reſpiration or redundance of humours, or both together ; but it is necessary to add a third, to wit, the weakneſs of the faculty, which is the cauſe of the rhenchos in dying perſons, where nature is too weak to make diſcharges.</p><p>From what has been ſaid we conclude, that this ſymptom, or this fort of fervour or ebullition in the throat, is not always mortal, but only when nature is oppressed with the redundance of humour, in ſuch a manner, that the lungs cannot diſcharge themſelves by ſpitting ; or the paſſage appointed for the breath (being the aſpera arteria) is very much obſtructed, upon which.<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0569.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0563"/>
account many dying perſons labour under a ſtertor with their mouths gaping.</p></div></body></text></TEI>