<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0508.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0502-01" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SIMONY</label>,
is the corrupt preſentation of any one to an eccleſiaſtical benefice for money, gift, or reward. It is ſo called from the reſemblance it is ſaid to bear to the sin of Simon Magus, though the purchasing of holy orders ſeems to approach nearer to his offence. It was by the canon law a very grievous crime : and is ſo much</p><p>the more odious, becauſe, as Sir Edward Coke obſerves, it is ever accompanied with perjury ; for the preſentee is ſworn to have committed no ſimony. However, it was not an offence puniſhable in a criminal way at the common law : it being thought ſufficient to leave the clerk to eccleſiaſtical cenſures. But as theſe did not affect the ſimoniacal patron, nor were efficacious enough to repel the notorious practice of the thing, divers acts of parliament have been made to reſtrain it by means of civil forfeitures ; wſhich the modern prevailing uſage, with regard to ſpiritual preferments, calls aloud to be put in execution. The ſtatute 31 Eliz. c. 6. enacts, that if any patron, for money or any other corrupt conſideration or promiſe, directly or indirectly given, ſhall preſent, admit, inſtitute, induct, inſtall, or collate any person to an eccleſiaſtical benefice or dignity, both the giver and taker ſhall forfeit two years value of the benefice or dignity ; one moiety to the king, and the other to any one who will ſue for the ſame. If persons alſo corruptly reſign or exchange their benefices, both the giver and taker shall in like manner forfeit double the value of the money or other corrupt conſideration. And perlons who ſhall corruptly ordain or licenſe any miniſter, or procure him to be ordained or licensed (which is the true idea of ſimony), ſhall incur a like forfeiture of forty pounds ; and the miniſter himſelf of ten pounds, beſides an incapacity to hold any eccleſiaſtical preferment for ſeven years afterwards. Corrupt elections and reſignations in colleges, hoſpitals, and other eleemoſynary corporations, are alſo puniſhed, by the ſame ſtatute, with forfeiture of the double value, vacating the place or office, and a devolution of the right of election, for that turn, to the crown.</p></div></body></text></TEI>