<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0595.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0589-01" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SOCINIANS</label>,
in church-hiſtory, a ſect of Chriſtian heretics, ſo called from their founder Fauſtus Socinus (ſee SociNus). They maintain, “ That Jesus Christ was a mere man, who had no exiſtence before he was conceived by the Virgin Mary ; that the Holy Ghost is no diſtinct perſon, but that the Father is truly and properly God. They own, that the name of God is given in the Holy Scriptures to Jeſus Chriſt ; but contend, that it is only a deputed title, which, however, inveſts him with an abſolute ſovereignty over all created beings, and renders him an object of worship to men and angels. They deny the doctrines of ſatisfaction and imputed righteouſneſs ; and lay that Chriſt only preached the truth to mankind, ſet before them in himſelf an example of heroic virtue, and ſealed his doctrines with his blood. Original sin and absolute pre-deſtination they eſteem ſcholaſtic chimeras. They lika-<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0596.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0590"/>
wise maintain the sleep of the foul, which they ſay becomes inſenſible at death, and is raiſed again with the body at the reſurrection, when the good ſhall be eſtabliſhed in the posseſſion oſ eternal felicity, while the wicked, ſhall be consigned to a fire that will not torment them eternally, but for a certain duration proportioned to their demerits.”</p><p>This ſect has long becn indignant at being ſtyled <hi rend="italic">Sacinians.</hi> They diſclaim every human leader ; and profeſſing to be guided ſolely by the word of God and the deductions of reaſon, they call themſelves <hi rend="italic">Unitarians,</hi> and affect to conſider all other Chriſtians, even their friends the Arians, as <hi rend="italic">Polytheists.</hi> Modern Unitariarism, as taught by Dr Prieſtley, is, however, a very different thing from Socinſkniſm, as we find it in the Racovian catechiſm and other ſtandard works of the ſect. This far-famed philosopher has diſcovered what eſcaped the ſagacity oſ all the <hi rend="italic">ſratres pοlοni,</hi> that Jeſus Chriſt was the ſon of Joſeph as well as Mary ; that the evangeliſts miſtook the meaning of Iſaiah’s prophecy, that “ a virgin ſhould conceive and bear a ſon ;” that the applying of this prophecy to the birth of our Saviour, led them to conclude that his conception was miraculous ; and that we are not to wonder at this miſtake, as the apoſtles were not always inſpired, and were in general inconclusive reaſoners. The modesty of the writer in claiming the merit of ſuch diſcoveries will appear in its proper colours to all our readers : the truth of his doctrine ſhall be conſidered in another place. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Theology.</hi></p></div></body></text></TEI>