<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0520.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0514-03" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SIUM, <hi rend="smallcaps">Water Parsnep,</hi></label>
 in botany: A genus of plants belonging to the claſs of <hi rend="italic">pentandria,</hi> and order of <hi rend="italic">digynia,</hi> and in the natural ſyſtem ranging under the 45th order, <hi rend="italic">Umbellate.</hi> The fruit is a little ovated, and ſtreaked. The involucrum is polyphyllous, and the petals are heart-ſhaped. There are 12 ſpecies ; the latifolium, anguſtifolium, nodiflorum, ſiſarum, ninſi, rigidius, japonicum, falearica, græcum, ſiculum, repens, and decumbens. The three firſt are natives of Britain. I. The <hi rend="italic">latifolium,</hi> or great water-parſnep, which grows ſpontaneouſly in many places both of England and Scotland on the ſides of lakes, ponds, and rivulets. The ſtalk is erect and furrowed, a yard high or more. The leaves are pinnated with three or four pair of large elliptic pinnæ, with an odd one at the end, all ſerrated on the edges. The ſtalk and branches are terminated with erect umbels, which is the chief characteriſtic of the ſpecies. Cattle are ſaid to have run mad by feeding upon this plant. 2. The <hi rend="italic">angustifolium,</hi> or narrowleaved water-parſnep, has pinnated leaves ; the axillary umbels are pedunculated, and the general involucrum is pinnatifid. It grows in ditches and rivulets, but is not common. 3. The <hi rend="italic">nodiflorum,</hi> reclining water-parſnep, has pinnated leaves, but the axillary umbels are ſeſſile. It grows on the ſides of rivulets.</p><p>The si <hi rend="italic">um ſiſarum,</hi> or ſkirret, is a native of China, but has been for a long time cultivated in Europe, and particularly in Germany. The root is a bunch of fleſhy fibres, each of which is about as thick as a finger, but very uneven, covered with a whitiſh rough bark, and has a hard core or pith running thro' the centre. From the crown of this bunch come ſeveral winged leaves, conſiſting of two or three pair of oblong dentated lobes each, and terminated by an odd one. The ſtalk riſes to about two feet, is ſet with leaves at the joints, and breaks into branches towards the top, each terminating with an umbel of ſmall white flowers, which are ſucceeded by ſtriated<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0521.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0515"/>
ſeeds like thoſe of parſley, Skirrets come neareſt to parſneps of any of the eſculent roots, both for flavour and nutritive qualities. They are rather ſweeter than the parſnep, and therefore to ſome few palates are not altogether ſo agreeable.</p><p>Mr Margraaf extracted from ½ lb. of ſkirret root 1 ½ ounces of pure ſugar.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">SIX-Clerks,</hi> officers in chancery of great account, next in degree below the twelve maſters, whoſe busineſs is to inrol çommissions, pardons, patents, warrants, &amp; c. which paſs the great ſeal, and to tranſact and file all proceedings by bill, anſwer, &amp; c. They were anciently <hi rend="italic">clerici,</hi> and forfeited their places, if they married ; but when the conſtitution of the court began to alter, a law was made to permit them to marry. Stat. 14. and 15. Hen. VIII. cap. 8. They are alſo ſolicitors for parties in ſuits depending in the court of chancery. Under them are 6 deputies and 60 clerks, who, with the under clerks, do the busineſs of the office.</p></div></body></text></TEI>