<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0604.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0598-05" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SOLDIERING</label>,
the joining and faſtening together of two pieces of the ſame metal, or of two different metals, by the fuſion and application of ſome metallic compoſition on the extremities oſ the metals to be joined.</p><p>To folder upon ſilver, braſs, or iron : Take ſilver, five pennyweights ; braſs, four pennyweights ; melt them to ether for ſoft folder, which runs sooneſt. Take ſilver, five pennyweights; copper, three pennyweights; melt them together for hard folder. Beat the folder thin, and lay it on the place to be ſoldered, which muſt be firſt fitted and bound together with wire as occaſion requires ; then take borax in powder, and temper it like pap, and lay it upon the folder, letting it dry ; then cover it with live coals, and blow, and it will run immediately ; take it preſently out oſ the fire, and it is done. It is to be obſerved, that if any thing is to be ſoldered in two places, which cannot well be done at one time, you muſt firſt ſolder with the harder ſolder, and then with the ſoft ; ſor it it be firſt done with the ſoft, it will unsolder again before the other is faſtened. Let it be obſerved, that if you would not have your ſolder run about the piece that is to be ſoldered, you muſt rub ſuch places over with chalk—In the ſoldering either of gold, ſilver, copper, or either of the metals above mentioned, there is generally uſed borax in powder, and ſometimes rosin. As to iron, it is ſufficient that it be heated red-hot, and the two extremities thus hammered together, by which means they will become incorporated with each other. For the finer kinds of iron and ſteel inſtruments, however, gold proves an excellent folder. This metal will dissolve twice or thrice its weight of iron in a degree of heat very far leſs than that in which iron itſelf melts ; hence if a ſmall plate of<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0605.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0599"/>
gold is wrapped round the parts to be joined, and afterwards melted by a blow-pipe, it ſtrongly unites the pieces together without any injury to the inſtrument, however delicate.</p></div></body></text></TEI>