<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>of the four friends which La Fontaine draws in his <hi rend="italic">Psyche, </hi>Racine figuring as Acante, “ qui aimait extrêmement les jardins, les fleurs, les ombrages, ’’ in which surroundings he helped to compose the lampoon of <hi rend="italic">Chapelain décoiffé</hi>  on a writer who had helped him with criticism, obtained royal gifts for him, and, in a fashion, started him in the literary career.</p><p>We have no definite details as to Racine’s doings during the year 1664, but in February 1665 he read at the Hôtel de Nevers before La Rochefoucauld, Madame de la Fayette, Madame de Sévigné, and other scarcely less redoubtable judges the greater part of his second acted play, <hi rend="italic">Alexandre le Grand, </hi>or, as Pomponne (who tells the fact) calls it, <hi rend="italic">Porus.</hi>  It was anxiously expected by the public, and Molière’s company played it on the 4th of December—Monsieur, his wife Henrietta of England, and many other distinguished persons being present. The gazetteer, Adrien Perdou de Subligny vouches for its success, and the receipts were good and steady. But a fortnight afterwards <hi rend="italic">Alexandre</hi>  was played, “ de complot avec M. Racine, ” says La Grange, by the rival actors (who had four days before performed it in private) at the Hôtel de Bourgogne. A vast amount of ink has been spilt on this question, but no one has produced any valid justification for Racine. That the piece failed at the Palais Royal, as is stated in the earliest attempt to excuse Racine, and the only one made in his lifetime, is not true. His son simply says that he was “ mécontent des acteurs, ” which indeed is self-evident. It is certain that Molière and he ceased to be friends in consequence of this proceeding; and that Molière was in fault no one who has studied the character of the two men will easily believe. If, however, <hi rend="italic">Alexandre </hi>was the occasion of showing the defects of Racine’s character as a man, it raised him vastly in public estimation as a poet. He was now for the first time proposed as a serious rival to Corneille. There is a story that he read the piece to the author of the <hi rend="italic">Cid</hi>  and asked his verdict. Corneille praised the piece highly, but not as a drama, “ Il l’assurait qu’il n’était pas propre à la poésie dramatique. ” There is no reason for disbelieving this, for the character of Alexander could not fail to shock Corneille, and he was notorious for not mincing his words. The contrast between the two even at this early period was accurately apprehended and put by Saint Evremond in his masterly <hi rend="italic">Dissertation sur l'Alexandre,</hi>  but this was not published for a year or two. To this day it is the best criticism of the faults of Racine, though not, it may be, of the merits, which had not yet been fully seen. It may be added that in the preface of the printed play the poet showed the extreme sensitiveness to criticism which perhaps excuses, and which certainly often accompanies, a tendency to criticize others. These defects of character showed themselves still more fully in another matter. The Port Royalists, as has been said, detested the theatre, and in January 1666 Nicole, their chief writer, spoke in one of his <hi rend="italic">Lettres sur les visionnaires,</hi>  directed against Desmurets de Saint-Sulin, of dramatic poets as “ empoisonneurs publics. ’’ Racine immediately published a letter to the author. It is very smartly written, and if Racine had contented himself with protesting against the exaggeration of the decriers of the stage there would have been little harm done. But he filled the piece with personalities, telling an absurd story of Mère Angélique Arnauld’s supposed intolerance, drawing a ridiculous picture of Le Maître (a dead man and his own special teacher and friend), and sneering savagely at Nicole himself. The latter made no reply, but two lay adherents of Port Royal took up the quarrel with more zeal than discretion or ability. Racine wrote a second pamphlet as bitter and personal as the first, but less amusing, and was about to publish it when fortunately Boileau, who had been absent from Paris, returned and protested against the publication. It remained accordingly unprinted till after the author’s death, as well as a preface to both which he had prepared with a view to publishing them together and so discharging the accumulated resentment arising from a long course of “ excommunications. ’’</p><p>After this disagreeable episode Racine’s life, for ten years and more, becomes simply the history of his plays, if we except his liaisons with the actresses Mademoiselle du Parc and Mademoiselle de Champmeslé, and his election to the Academy on the 17th of July 1673. Mademoiselle du Parc (marquise de Gorla) was no very great actress, but was very beautiful, and she had previously captivated Molière. Racine induced her to leave the Palais Royal company and join the Hôtel. She died in 1668, and long afterwards the infamous Catherine Voisin accused Racine of having poisoned her. Mademoiselle de Champmeslé was plain, but an admirable actress, and apparently very attractive in some way, for not merely Racine but Charles de Sévigné and many others adored her. For five years before his marriage Racine seems to have been her <hi rend="italic">amant en titre,</hi>  but long afterwards, just before his own death, when he heard of her mortal illness, he spoke of her to his son without a flash of tenderness.</p><p>The series of his unquestioned dramatic triumphs began with <hi rend="italic">Andromaque,</hi>  and this play may perhaps dispute with <hi rend="italic">Phèdre </hi>and <hi rend="italic">Athalie</hi>  the title of his masterpiece. It is much more uniformly good than <hi rend="italic">Phèdre,</hi>  and the character of Hermione is the most personally interesting on the French tragic stage. It is said that the first representation of <hi rend="italic">Andromaque</hi>  was on 10th November 1667, in public and by the actors of the Hôtel de Bourgogne, but the first contemporary mention of it by the gazettes, prose and verse, is on the 17th, as performed in the queen’s apartment. Perrault, by no means a friendly critic as far as Racine is concerned, says that it made as much noise as the <hi rend="italic">Cid,</hi>  and so it ought to have done. Whatever may be thought of the <hi rend="italic">tragédie pathétique</hi>  (a less favourable criticism might call it the “ sentimental tragedy ”), it could hardly be better exemplified than in this admirable play. A ferocious epigram of Racine’s own tells us that some critics thought Pyrrhus too fond of his mistress, and Andromache too fond of her husband, but in the contemporary depreciations is to be found the avowal of its real merit. Pyrrhus was taken by Floridor, the best tragic actor by common consent of his time, and Orestes by Montfleury, also an accomplished player. But Mademoiselle du Parc, who played Andromache, had generally been thought below, not above, her parts, and Mademoiselle des Oeillets, who played the difficult rôle of Hermione, was old and had few physical advantages. No one who reads <hi rend="italic">Andromaque</hi>  without prejudice is likely to mistake the secret of its success, which is, in few words, the application of the most delicate art to the conception of really tragic passion. Before leaving the play it may be mentioned that it is said to have been in the part of Hermione, three years later, that Mademoiselle de Champmeslé captivated the author. <hi rend="italic">Andromaque</hi>  was succeeded, at the distance of not more than a year, by the charming comedietta of <hi rend="italic">Les Plaideurs.</hi>  We do not know exactly when it was played, but it was printed on the 5th of December 1668. Many anecdotes are told about its origin and composition. The <hi rend="italic">Wasps</hi>  of Aristophanes, and the known fact that Racine originally destined it, not for a French company, but for the Italian troupe which was then playing the <hi rend="italic">Commedia dell'arte</hi>  in Paris, dispense us from enumerating them. The result is a piece admirably dramatic, but sufficiently literary to shock the <hi rend="italic">profanum vulgus,</hi>  which too frequently gives the tone at theatres. It failed completely, the chief favouring voice being, according to a story sufficiently well attested and worthy of belief even without attestation, that of the man who was best qualified to praise and who might have been most tempted to blame of any man then living. Molière, says Valincourt, the special friend of Racine, said in leaving the house, “ Que ceux qui se moquoient de cette pièce meritoient qu’on se moquoient d’eux. ’’ But the piece was suddenly played at court a month later; the king laughed, and its fortunes were restored. It need only be added that, if Louis XIV. admired <hi rend="italic">Les Plaideurs,</hi>  Napoleon did not, and excluded it from his travelling library. It was followed by a very different work, <hi rend="italic">Britannicus,</hi>  which appeared on 13th December 1669. This was much less successful than <hi rend="italic">Andromaque,</hi>  and seems to have held its own but a very few nights. Afterwards it became very popular, and even from the first the</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>