<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>although in a strikingly different manner and with far more momentous results for the western world. Martin Luther was beyond doubt the most important single figure in the Protestant revolt. His influence was indeed by no means so decisive and so pervasive as has commonly been supposed, and his attacks on the evils in the Church were no bolder or more comprehensive than those of Marsiglio and Wycliffe, or of several among his contemporaries  who owed nothing to his example. Had the German princes not found it to their interests to enforce his principles, he might never have been more than the leader of an obscure mystic sect. He was, moreover, no statesman. He was recklessly impetuous in his temperament, coarse and grossly superstitious according to modern standards. Yet in spite of all these allowances he remains one of the great heroes of all history. Few come in contact with his writings without feeling his deep spiritual nature and an absolute genuineness and marvellous individuality which seem never to sink into mere routine or affectation. In his more important works almost every sentence is alive with that autochthonic quality which makes it unmistakably his. His fundamental religious conception  was his own hard-found answer to his own agonized question as to the nature and assurance of salvation. Even if others before him had reached the conviction that the Vulgate’s word <hi rend="italic">justitia</hi>  in Romans i. 16-17 meant “ righteousness ” rather than “ justice ’’ in a juridical sense, Luther exhibited supreme religious genius in his interpretation of “ God’s righteousness ” (<hi rend="italic">Gerechtigkeit)</hi>  as over against the “ good works ’’ of man, and in the overwhelming importance he attached to the promise that the just shall live by faith. It was his anxiety to remove everything that obscured this central idea which led him to revolt against the ancient Church, and this conception of faith served, when he became leader of the German Protestants, as a touchstone to test the expediency of every innovation. But only gradually did he come to realize that his source of spiritual consolation might undermine altogether the artfully constructed fabric of the medieval Church. As late as 1516 he declared that the life of a monk was never a more enviable one than at that day. He had, however, already begun to look sourly upon Aristotle and the current scholastic theology, which he believed hid the simple truth of the gospel and the desperate state of mankind, who were taught a vain reliance upon outward works and ceremonies, when the only safety lay in throwing oneself on God’s mercy. He was suddenly forced to take up the consideration of some of the most fundamental points in the orthodox theology by the appearance of Tetzel in 1517. In his hastily drafted Ninety-five Theses he sought to limit the potency of indulgences, and so indirectly raised the question as to the power of the pope. He was astonished to observe the wide circulation of the theses both in the Latin and German versions. They soon reached Rome, and a Dominican monk, Prierius, wrote a reply in defence of the papal power, in an insolent tone which first served to rouse Luther’s suspicion of the theology of the papal Curia. He was summoned to Rome, but, out of consideration for his patron, the important elector of Saxony, he was permitted to appear before the papal legate during the diet of Augsburg in 1518. He boldly contradicted the legate’s theological statements, refused to revoke anything and appealed to a future council. On returning to Wittenberg, he turned to the canon law, and was shocked to find it so completely at variance with his notions of Christianity. He reached the conclusion that the papacy was but four hundred years old. Yet, although of human origin, it was established by common consent and with God’s sanction, so that no one might withdraw his obedience without offence.</p><p>It was not, however, until 1520 that Luther became in a sense the leader of the German people by issuing his three great pamphlets, all of which were published in German as well as in Latin—his <hi rend="italic">Address to the Christian Nobility of the German Nation,</hi>  his <hi rend="italic">Babylonish Captivity of the Church,</hi>  and his <hi rend="italic">Freedom of the Christian.</hi>  In the first he urged that, since the Church had failed to reform itself, the secular government should come to the rescue. “ The Romanists have with great dexterity built themselves about with three walls, which have hitherto protected them against reform; and thereby is Christianity fearfully fallen. In the first place, when the temporal power has pressed them hard, they have affirmed and maintained that the temporal power has no jurisdiction over them—that, on the contrary, the spiritual is above the temporal. Secondly, when it was proposed to admonish them from the Holy Scriptures they said, ‘ It beseems no one but the pope to interpret the Scriptures,’ and, thirdly, when they were threatened with a council, they invented the idea that no one but the pope can call a council. Thus they have secretly stolen our three rods that they may go unpunished, and have entrenched themselves safely behind these three walls in order to carry on all the rascality and wickedness that we now see.”</p><p>He declares that the distinction between the “ spiritual estate,” composed of pope, bishops, priests and monks, as over against the “ temporal estate ’’ composed of princes, lords, artisans and peasants, is a very fine hypocritical invention of which no one should be afraid. “ A cobbler, a smith, a peasant, every man has his own calling and duty, just like the consecrated priests and bishops, and every one in his calling or office must help and serve the rest, so that all may work together for the common good.” After overthrowing the other two walls, Luther invites the attention of the German rulers to the old theme of the pomp of the pope and cardinals, for which the Germans must pay. “ What the Romanists really mean to do, the ‘drunken Germans’ are not to see until they have lost everything. ... If we rightly hang thieves and behead robbers, why do we leave the greed of Rome unpunished ? for Rome is the greatest thief and robber that has ever appeared on earth, or ever will; and all in the holy names of the Church and St Peter.” After proving that the secular rulers were free and in duty bound to correct the evils of the Church, Luther sketches a plan for preventing money from going to Italy, for reducing the number of idle, begging monks, harmful pilgrimages and excessive holidays. Luxury and drinking were to be suppressed, the universities, especially the divinity schools, reorganized, &amp;c.</p><p>Apart from fundamental rejection of the papal supremacy, there was little novel in Luther’s appeal. It had all been said before in the various protests of which we have spoken, and very recently by Ulrich von Hutten in his <hi rend="italic">Dialogues,</hi>  but no one had put the case so strongly, or so clearly, before. In addressing the German nobility Luther had refrained from taking up theological or religious doctrines; but in September 1520 he attacked the whole sacramental system of the medieval Church in his <hi rend="italic">Babylonish Captivity of the Church. </hi>Many reformers, like Glapion, the Franciscan confessor of, Charles V., who had read the <hi rend="italic">Address</hi>  with equanimity if not approval, were shocked by Luther’s audacity in rejecting the prevailing fundamental religious conceptions. Luther says: “ I must begin by denying that there are seven sacraments, and must lay down for the time being that there are only three— baptism, penance and the bread, and that by the court of Rome all these have been brought into miserable bondage, and the Church despoiled of her liberty.” It is, however, in the <hi rend="italic">Freedom of the Christian</hi>  that the essence of Luther’s religion is to be found. Man cannot save himself, but <hi rend="italic">is</hi>  saved then and there, so soon as he believes God’s promises, and to doubt these is the supreme crime. So salvation was to him not a painful <hi rend="italic">progress</hi>  toward a goal to be reached by the sacraments and by right conduct, but a <hi rend="italic">state</hi>  in which man found himself so soon as he despaired absolutely of his own efforts, and threw himself on God’s assurances. Man’s utter incapacity to do anything to please God, and his utter personal dependence on God’s grace seemed to render the whole system of the Church well-nigh gratuitous even if it were purged of all the “ sophistry ’’ which to Luther seemed to bury out of sight all that was essential in religion. Luther’s gospel was one of love and confidence, not of fear and trembling, and came as an overwhelming revelation to those who understood and accepted it.</p><p>The old question of Church reform inevitably reappeared</p></body></text></TEI>