<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>in character from the <hi rend="italic">State Papers Domestic.</hi>  The <hi rend="italic">Domestic Papers </hi>relating exclusively to Ireland have been calendared under the title of <hi rend="italic">State Papers, Ireland,</hi>  for the years 1509-1601 and 1603-1665, with a special volume dealing with the papers concerning <hi rend="italic">Adventurers for Land.</hi>  From 1670 these papers are calendared in the <hi rend="italic">Domestic</hi>  volumes.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Scotland.—</hi>Originally there were in the State Paper Office two sets of papers relating to Scotland, <hi rend="italic">State Papers Domestic, Border Papers,</hi>  containing papers concerning the Council of the North and the Wardens of the Marches; and <hi rend="italic">State Papers Foreign, Scotland, </hi>before the union of the two crowns. The first calendar of these was a <hi rend="italic">Calendar of Stale Papers, Scotland, 1509-1603,</hi>  containing brief notes of all the <hi rend="italic">State Papers Foreign, Scotland,</hi>  and of many of the <hi rend="italic">Border Papers</hi>  which were removed from their places without any record of the removal. Next came the <hi rend="italic">Calendar of State Papers Foreign,</hi>  in which were included apparently all the <hi rend="italic">Border Papers </hi>for the period covered which had escaped the previous raid; notes, however, were made of the papers so taken. Out of the original 75 volumes of <hi rend="italic">Border Papers</hi>  only 36 remained. At a later date the papers drawn for the Foreign Calendar were restored and now form the first 19 volumes of the series, while the 36 volumes originally remaining have now become the final 23. At the same time the <hi rend="italic">State Papers Foreign, Scotland,</hi>  were annexed, and became <hi rend="italic">State Papers Domestic, Scotland.</hi>  In their present arrangement the <hi rend="italic">Border Papers</hi>  have been calendared in the following volumes: vols. 1-19 in the <hi rend="italic">State Papers Foreign 1547-1560;</hi>  vols. 20-42 in the Scottish General Register Office <hi rend="italic">Calendar of Border Papers 1560-1603.</hi>  The <hi rend="italic">State Papers Domestic, Scotland,</hi>  from 1547 onwards, are being fully calendared in the Scottish General Register Office <hi rend="italic">Calendar of Scottish Papers</hi>  with other material. Those from 1509 to 1547 are dealt with in the <hi rend="italic">Letters and Papers of Henry VIII.</hi>  (see below, <hi rend="smallcaps">Special Collections).</hi>  A list of these three Classes has been published (No. III.).</p><p><hi rend="italic">Foreign.—</hi>Calendars of the <hi rend="italic">State Papers Foreign</hi>  have been published for the period 1547-1580. A few of these papers are also calendared in the first volume of the <hi rend="italic">State Papers Spanish </hi>(see below under <hi rend="smallcaps">Spain).</hi>  The Record Office has published a list of the <hi rend="italic">State Papers Foreign</hi>  (No. XIX.).</p><p><hi rend="italic">Colonial.—</hi>These papers are calendared in two sets, an “ East Indies” (1513-1634, which has been continued to 1639 by the India Office in Miss E. B. Sainsbury’s <hi rend="italic">Court Minutes of the East India Company)</hi>  and an “ America and West Indies ” (1574-1693, in progress).</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Departmental Records.</hi>—From time to time all the government departments, with the exception of the Γndia Office, deposit such papers as they wish to preserve in the Public Record Office; thus the <hi rend="italic">Treasury, Home Office, Foreign Office, Colonial Office, Admiralty, War Office, Local Government Board</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">Board of Trade </hi>have all placed important papers in the care of the Master of the Rolls. A calendar of the earlier Treasury Papers, which extends from 1660 to 1668 and 1720 to 1745 has been published; also a list of the Admiralty Records (No. XVII.). For each department a limiting date is fixed from time to time; documents before that time are open to students; later ones arc only accessible under special conditions.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Subordinate and Independent Jurisdictions.— </hi><hi rend="italic">Palatinate of Durham.—</hi>For the earlier records see G. T. Lapsley’s <hi rend="italic">County Palatine of Durham</hi>  (Harvard Historical Series, vol. viii.), pp. 327-337. The letters sent out from the bishops’ <hi rend="italic">chancery</hi>  are enrolled on the <hi rend="italic">Cursitors’ Records,</hi>  Nοs. 29 to 184. They arc calendared in Reports 31 to 37 and 40. One of the registers (Bishop Kellawe’s) has been printed in full in the Rolls scries (No. 62) with additions from the register of Bishop Bury. The <hi rend="italic">Cursitors’ Records</hi>  also include seven bundles of <hi rend="italic">Inquisitions Post Mortem</hi>  (Nos. 164-180), calendared in the 44th Report; and a volume (No. 2) contains transcripts of similar documents, calendared in the 45th Report. The records of the <hi rend="italic">Exchequer</hi>  of Durham, though deposited in the Public Record Office, are treated as the private records of the Ecclesiastical Commission, and are only accessible with a special permit. To the <hi rend="italic">judicial</hi>  records the only printed means of reference is the list of <hi rend="italic">Judgment Rolls</hi>  (20 Henry VII. to 7-8 Victoria) in the Record Office list of Plea Rolls (No. IV.)</p><p><hi rend="italic">Palatinate of Chester.—</hi>The letters sent out from the <hi rend="italic">chancery </hi>are enrolled upon the <hi rend="italic">Chester Recognizance</hi>  Rolls (1 Edward II. to 34 Charles II. with a few rolls down to 1 William IV.) calendared in Reports 36-37 and 39. The financial records of the <hi rend="italic">Exchequer </hi>of Chester are listed among the Ministers’ Accounts (List No. V.) of the county of Chester. The <hi rend="italic">Inquisitions post Mortem</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">ad quod damnum</hi>  (Edward III. to Charles I.) are indexed in the 25th report. The <hi rend="italic">judicial</hi>  records consist of Pleas in the Exchequer, a court of equity. Its records are <hi rend="italic">Bills and Answers</hi>  (Henry VIII. to George IV.), calendared in the 25th Report up to Philip and Mary; and <hi rend="italic">Decrees and Orders.</hi>  The court of the justices of Chester was at common law; its <hi rend="italic">Plea Rolls</hi>  (44 Henry III. to 1 William IV.), with a separate series for Flint (from 12 Edward I.) are listed among the Plea Rolls (List No. IV.). The <hi rend="italic">Deeds, Inquisitions</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">Writs of Dower</hi>  upon these rolls for the period Henry III. to Henry VIII. are calendared in the 26th-30th Reports without an index. The <hi rend="italic">Assize Rolls</hi>  for the counties of Chester and Flint and for the honour of Macclesfield are listed among the other assize rolls (List No. IV.).</p><p><hi rend="italic">Wales.—</hi>The following are the principal records of the principality of Wales: <hi rend="italic">Ministers’ Accounts</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">Court Rolls,</hi>  including those of the principality and of the honours and manors of the Lords Marchers, listed in Lists Nos. V. and VL Of the <hi rend="italic">judicial </hi>records of the Great Sessions of Wales, set up by the act 34 &amp; 35 Henry VIII., c. 26, the <hi rend="italic">Plea Rolls</hi>  are listed in the list of Plea Rolls (No. IV). For an account of the Court of the Marches in Wales, see C. A. Skeel's <hi rend="italic">The Council in the Marches of Wales.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">The Duchy and Palatinate of Lancaster.—</hi>The duchy of Lancaster comprises all the estates of the duke of Lancaster; the palatinate is limited to the county of Lancaster. The records of the palatinate, transferred to the Public Record Office from Lancaster castle, related to the county and are either <hi rend="italic">enrolments of writs</hi>  or of a <hi rend="italic">judicial</hi>  nature. The records of the duchy, transferred from the office of the duchy at Westminster, include similar records and others dealing with the manorial and financial records of all the estates within and without the county. For the <hi rend="italic">Duchy Records </hi>see the detailed list (No. XIV.), where the means of reference to this collection are fully described. Of the <hi rend="italic">Palatinate Records</hi>  the enrolments of writs are classified as <hi rend="italic">Patent</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">Close Rolls.</hi>  The former, a broken series from 5 John of Gaunt to 21 Henry VII., arc calendared in the 40th Report; the latter (in 3 rolls, a broken series, 11Henry IV. to 9 Edward IV.) in the 37th Report; but certain enrolments of the palatinate are among the duchy records. The <hi rend="italic">judicial</hi>  records of the <hi rend="italic">chancery</hi>  are not calendared; but the proceedings by way of appeal from that court to the Duchy Chamber at Westminster are dealt with in the duchy list. Pro-ceedings under common law include <hi rend="italic">Plea Rolls</hi>  (2 Henry IV. to 11 Victoria) listed in the list of Plea Rolls (No. IV.) ; and for criminal proceedings there are palatinate <hi rend="italic">Assize Rolls</hi>  (Henry VI. to 6 Victoria), of which there is a list in the same place. But certain rolls which were among the Duchy Records will be found apart at pages 139-140 of the same list.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Bishopric of Ely.—</hi>The act 1 &amp; 2 Victoria, c. 94, places the records of this palatinate under the charge of the Master of the Rolls. They have never been removed to the Record Office, but remain at Ely with the episcopal records, where they can be inspected. A valuable descriptive list has been published by Alfred Gibbons for private circulation.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Special Collections.</hi>—For the classification of the records hitherto described the knowledge preserved of their origin and purpose has been used. There exist, however, masses of records where this path is now inaccessible; these have been formed by putting together records of a similar nature either in ignorance of their history or without regarding it; the justification of this course of action must be found in the special circumstances of each case. These collections are as follows</p><p><hi rend="italic">Ministers’ Accounts</hi>  are the accounts of bailiffs, receivers, and other officers managing estates, including, first, those of the duchy of Lancaster; second, accounts of crown lands filed as vouchers in the King’s Remembrancer’s Office; third, accounts of monastiċ and other lands seized by the crown, or acquired by it by purchase; inheritance or marriage. A list of these accounts has been published by the Record Office (Nos. V. and VIII.) covering thd period down to 1485. For the accounts of the duchy of Lancaster a list will be found in the 45th Report, extending to the reign of George III.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Court Rolls</hi>  are records of the proceedings and profits of manorial and other private courts coming from the same sources as the Ministers’ Accounts, and closely connected with them. For a list see Record Office, <hi rend="italic">Lists and Indexes,</hi>  No. VI.; and for specimens <hi rend="italic">Select Pleas in Manorial Courts,</hi>  edited for the Selden Society by F. W. Maitland.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Ancient Deeds.—</hi>In this collection are placed all documents which appear to have formed part of a title to land, some original royal charters and other analogous records. There are five series, A, B, C, D, and E, distinguished by their former place of custody. Documents too large for the ordinary method of packing have a double letter, <hi rend="italic">e.g.</hi>  A.A., and to those bearing fine seals the letter S is added, <hi rend="italic">e.g.</hi>  AS or AAS. There arc thus in all fifteen classes. The A classes are derived from the <hi rend="italic">Treasury of Receipt,</hi>  or Chapter House at Westminster, and are largely monastic; the B classes arc from the court of <hi rend="italic">Augmentations∙,</hi>  the C classes are <hi rend="italic">chancery </hi>deeds, probably deposited as exhibits in suits or for enrolments; the D classes are from the <hi rend="italic">King’s Remembrancer’s</hi>  office; and the E classes are from the <hi rend="italic">Land Revenue</hi>  office. In 1907 five volumes of a descriptive catalogue had been published by the Record Office.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Ancient Correspondence</hi>  consists of documents which in form are rather of the nature of a letter than a writ or petition. Most of them were found detached in the chancery records, but similar documents from other sources have been added. The introduction to the Record Office List (No. XV.) contains some account of the formation of the class, and the list gives references to printed collections based upon these documents. Vol. 53 contains letters of the Cely Family and is published (Camden Society, 3rd series, vol. i.).</p><p><hi rend="italic">Ancient Petitions.—</hi>The history of the formation of this class</p></body></text></TEI>