<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T20:59:19Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>volve in a vertical plane, about a horizontal axis, and the control is given wholly by springs. An example is shown in fig. 100, which is the governor of the</p><p>Armington and Sims</p><p>engine referred to in</p><p>§ 197 below. Another</p><p>example is furnished</p><p>by the governor of</p><p>Brotherhood’s engine</p><p>(§ 203, fig. 128).</p><p>173. The throttle-</p><p>valve, as introduced</p><p>by Watt, was origin</p><p>ally a disk turning on</p><p>a transverse axis across</p><p>the centre of the steam-</p><p>pipe. It is now usually</p><p>a double - beat valve</p><p>(fig. 89) or a piston-</p><p>valve. When regula</p><p>tion is effected by</p><p>varying the cut-off, and</p><p>an expansion-valve of</p><p>the slide-valve type is used, the governor generally acts by changing the travel of the valve. Fig. 99 illustrates a common mode of doing</p><p>sion, and then, when the trip-action comes into play, it closes suddenly. The indicator diagram of a Corliss engine consequently has a nearly horizontal admission-line and a sharply defined cut-off. Generally the valves of Corliss engines are cylindrical plates turning in hollow cylindrical seats which extend across the width of the cylinder. Often, however, the admission-valves are of the disk or double-beat type, and spring into their seats when the trip-gear acts. Many forms of Corliss gear have been invented by Corliss himself and by others. One of these, the Spencer Inglis@@<hi rend="superscript">1</hi> trip-gear, by Messrs Hick, Hargreaves, &amp; Co., is shown in figs. 101 and 102. A wrist-plate A, which turns on a pin on the outside of the cylinder, receives a motion of oscillation from an eccentric. It opens the cylindrical rocking-valve B by pulling the link C, which consists of two parts, connected to each other by a pair of spring clips <hi rend="italic">a, a.</hi> Between the clips there is a rocking-cam <hi rend="italic">b,</hi> and as the link is pulled down this cam places itself more and more athwart the link, until at a certain point it forces the clips open. Then the upper part of the link springs back and allows the valve B to close by the action of a spring in the dash-pot D. When the wrist-plate makes its return stroke the clips re-engage the upper portion of the link C, and things are ready for the next stroke. The rocking-cam <hi rend="italic">b</hi> has its position controlled by the governor</p><p>this, by giving the expansion-valve its motion from an eccentric-rod through a link, the throw of which is varied by the displacement of the governor balls. In fig. 100, the governor acts on the main slide-valve of the engine (there being no separate expansion-valve), and the displacement of the revolving masses Μ, M changes both the throw and the angular advance of the eccentric, thereby producing a change in the steam supply similar to that produced by "notching up ” a link-motion. The eccentricity B is altered by the relative displacement of two parts C, D into which the eccentric sheave is divided. In other forms of automatic expansion-gear the lap of the valve is altered ; in others the governor acts by shifting the expansion-valve eccentric round on its shaft, and so changing its angular advance.</p><p>174. In large stationary engines the most usual plan of automatically regulating the expansion is to employ some form of trip-gear, the earliest type of which was introduced in 1849 by G. H. Corliss of Providence, U.S. In the Corliss system the valves which admit steam are distinct from the exhaust-valves. The latter are opened and closed by a reciprocating piece which takes its motion from an eccentric. The former are opened by a reciprocating piece, but are closed by springing back when released by a trip- or trigger-action. The trip occurs earlier or later in the piston’s stroke according to the position of the governor. The admissi on-valve is opened by the reciprocating piece with equal rapidity whether the cut-off is going to be early or late. It remains wide open during the admis-</p><p>through the link E in such a way that when the speed of the engine increases it stands more athwart the link C, and therefore</p><p>causes the clips to be released at an earlier point in the stroke. A precisely similar arrangement governs the admission of steam to the other end of the cylinder. The exhaust-valves are situated on the</p><p><hi rend="superscript">@@@1</hi><hi rend="italic"> Proc. Inst. Mech. Eng.,</hi> 1868.</p></body></text></TEI>