<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T21:01:52Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Struve’s name is best known by bis observations of double stars, which he carried on for many years. These bodies had first been regularly measured by W. Herschel, who discovered that many of them formed systems of two stars revolving round their common centre of gravity. After him J. Herschel (and for some time South) had observed them, but their labours were eclipsed by the systematic and more extensive ones of Struve. With the 9<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">2</hi>-inch refractor at Dorpat he discovered a great number of double stars, and published in 1827 a list of all the known objects of this kind (<hi rend="italic">Catalogus Novus Stellarum Duplicium}.</hi> His micrometric measurements of 2714 double stars were made from 1824 to 1837, and are contained in his principal work <hi rend="italic">Stellarum Duplicium et-Multiplicium Mensuræ Micrometricæ</hi> (St Petersburg, 1837, fol. ; a convenient summary of the results is given in vol. i. of the <hi rend="italic">Dunecht Observatory Publications,</hi> 1876). The places of the objects were at the same time determined with the Dorpat meridian circle <hi rend="italic">{Stellarum Firarum Imprimis Duplicium et Multiplicium Positiones Mediæ,</hi> St Petersburg, 1852, fol.). At Pulkova he determined anew the constant of aberration, but was chiefly occupied in working out the results of former years’ work and in the completion of the geodetic operations in which he had been engaged during the greater part of his life. He had commenced them with a survey of Livonia (1816-19), which was followed by the measurement of an arc of meridian of more than 3<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">2</hi>° in the Baltic provinces of Russia (<hi rend="italic">Beschreibung der Breitengradmessung in den Ostseeprovinzen Russlands,</hi> 2 vols. 4to, Dorpat, 1831). This work was afterwards extended by Struve and General Tenner into a measurement of a meridional arc from the north coast of Norway to Ismail on the Danube <hi rend="italic">{Arc du Méridien de 25° 20' entre le Danube et la Mer Glaciale, 2</hi> vols, and 1 vol. plates, St Petersburg, 1857-60, 4to).</p><p>STRY, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Stryj,</hi> a town of Galicia, Austria, is pleasantly situated on a tributary of the Dniester, about 40 miles to the south of Lemberg. In 1880 it contained 12,625 inhabitants, chiefly engaged in tanning and the manufacture of matches. In 1886, however, the town was almost wholly destroyed by fire, and its population was greatly reduced by the wholesale migration and deaths from privation consequent upon this calamity.</p><p>STRYCHNINE. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Poisons,</hi> vol. xix. p. 279, and Nux <hi rend="smallcaps">Vomica,</hi> vol. xvii. p 687.</p><p>STRYPE, <hi rend="smallcaps">John</hi> (1643-1737), historian and biographer, was the son of John Strype or Van Stryp, a native of Brabant, who to escape religious persecution went to England, and settled near London, in a locality afterwards known as Strype’s Yard, formerly in the parish of Stepney, but subsequently annexed to that of Christ Church, Spitalfields. Here he carried on the business of a merchant and silk throwster. The son was born 1st November 1643. He was educated at St Paul’s School, and on 5th July 1662 entered Jesus College, Cambridge. Thence he proceeded to Catherine Hall, where he graduated B.A. in 1665 and M.A. in 1669. On the 14th July of the latter year he was preferred to the curacy of Theydon-Bois, Essex, and a few months afterwards was chosen curate and lecturer of Low Leyton in the same county. On account of the smallness of the salary, the patron allowed the people to choose their own minister, the vacancy in the vicarage remaining unfilled during the life of Strype. He was never instituted or inducted, but in 1674 he was licensed by the bishop of London to preach and expound the word of God, and to perform the full office of priest and curate during the vacancy of the vicarage. In his later years he obtained from Archbishop Tenison the sinecure of Tarring, Sussex, and he discharged the duties of lecturer at Hackney till 1724. When he became infirm he took up his residence with Mr Harris, an apothecary at Hackney, who had married his daughter, and died there 11th December 1737, at the advanced age of ninety-four.</p><p>At an early period of his life Strype obtained access to the papers of Sir Michael Hicks, secretary to Lord Burghley, from which he made extensive transcripts; he also carried on an extensive correspondence with Archbishop Wake and Bishops Burnet, Atterbury, and Nicholson. The materials thus obtained formed the basis of his historical and biographical works, which relate chiefly to the period of the Reformation. The greater portion of his original materials have been preserved, and are included in the</p><p>Lansdowne manuscripts in the British Museum. His works can scarcely be entitled original compositions, his labour having consisted chiefly in the arrangement of his materials, but on this very account they are of considerable value as convenient books of reference, easier of access and almost as trustworthy as the original documents. Besides a number of single sermons published at various periods, he was the author of an edition of Lightfoot’s <hi rend="italic">Works,</hi> vol. ii., 1684; <hi rend="italic">Memorials of Archbishop Cranmer,</hi> 1694; <hi rend="italic">Life of Sir Thomas Smith,</hi> 1698 ; <hi rend="italic">Life and Actions of John Aylmer, Bishop of London,</hi> 1701 ; <hi rend="italic">Life of Sir John Cheke, with his Treatise on Superstition,</hi> 1705; <hi rend="italic">Annals of the Reformation in England, </hi>4 vols., vol. i. 1709 (reprinted 1725), vol. ii. 1725, vol. iii. 1728, vol. iv. 1731; 2d ed. 1735, 4 vols. ; 3d ed. 1736-38, 4 vols. ; <hi rend="italic">Life and Actions of Edmund Grindal, Archbishop of Canterbury, </hi>1710, <hi rend="italic">of Matthew Parker, Archbishop of Canterbury,</hi> 1711, and <hi rend="italic">of John Whitgift, Archbishop of Canterbury,</hi> 1818; <hi rend="italic">An Accurate Edition of Stow’s Survey of London,</hi> 1720, 2 vols, fol., the standard edition of Stow and of great value, although its interference with the original text is a method of editing which can scarcely be reckoned fair to the original author; and <hi rend="italic">Ecclesiastical Memorials, </hi>1721, 3 vols.; 1733, 3 vols.; new ed. 1816. His <hi rend="italic">Historical and Biographical Works</hi> were published in 10 vols., with a general index, 1820-40.</p><p>STUART, <hi rend="smallcaps">Stewart,</hi> or <hi rend="smallcaps">Steuart,</hi> the surname of a family who became heirs to the Scottish and ultimately to the English crown. Their descent is traced to a Norman baron Alan, whose eldest son William became progenitor of the earls of Arundel, and whose two younger sons Walter and Simon came to Scotland, Walter being appointed high steward of David I., who conferred on him various lands in Renfrewshire, including Paisley, where he founded the abbey in 1160. Walter, his grandson, third steward, was appointed by Alexander II. justiciary of Scotland, and, dying in 1246, left four sons and three daughters. The third son Walter obtained by marriage the earldom of Menteith, which ultimately came by marriage to Robert, duke of Albany, third son of Robert II. Alexander, fourth steward, the eldest son of Walter, third steward, inherited by his marriage with Jean, granddaughter of Somerled, the islands of Bute and Arran, and on 2d October 1263 defeated Haco at Largs. He had two sons, James and John. The latter, who commanded the men of Bute at the battle of Falkirk in 1298, had seven sons :—(1) Sir Alexander, whose grandson became in 1389 earl of Angus, the title afterwards passing in the female line to the Douglases, and in 1761 to the duke of Hamilton ; (2) Sir Alan of Dreghorn, ancestor of the earls and dukes of Lennox, from whom Lord Darnley, husband of Queen Mary, and also Arabella Stuart, were descended ; (3) Sir Walter, who obtained the barony of Garlies, Wigtownshire, from his uncle John Randolph, earl of Moray, and was the ancestor of the earls of Galloway, younger branches of the family being the Stewarts of Tonderghie, Wigtownshire, and also those of Physgill and Glenturk in the same county; (4) Sir James, who fell at Dupplin in 1332, ancestor of the lords of Lorn, on whose descendants were conferred at different periods the earldoms of Athole, Buchan, and Traquair, and who were also the progenitors of the Stewarts of Appin, Argyllshire, and of Grandtully, Perthshire; (5) Sir John, killed at Halidon Hill in 1333; (6) Sir Hugh, who fought under Edward Bruce in Ireland ; and (7) Sir Robert of Dal- dowie, ancestor of the Stewarts of Allanton and of Coltness. James Stewart, the eldest son of Alexander, fourth steward, succeeded his father in 1283, and, after distinguishing himself in the wars of Wallace and of Bruce, died in 1309. His son Walter, sixth steward, who had joint command with Douglas of the left wing at the battle of Bannockburn, married Marjory, daughter of Robert the Bruce, and during the latter’s absence in Ireland was entrusted with the government of the kingdom. He died in 1326, leaving an only son, who as Robert II. ascended the throne of Scotland in 1370 (see vol. xxi. p. 490). Sir Alexander Stewart, earl of Buchan, fourth son of</p></body></text></TEI>