<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T20:59:27Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>retained by Watt, and for many years it remained a favourite with builders of engines of the larger class. The beam formed a convenient driver for pump-rods and valve- rods ; and the parallel motion invented by Watt as a means of guiding the piston-rod, which could easily be applied to a beam-engine, was, in the early days of engine- building, an easier thing to construct than the plane surfaces which are the natural guides of the piston-rod in a direct-acting engine. In modern practice the direct- acting type has to a very great extent displaced the beam type. For mill-driving and the general purposes of a rotative engine the beam type is now rarely chosen. In pumping engines it is more common, but even there the tendency is to use direct-acting forms.</p><p>193. The only distinctive feature of beam-engines requiring special notice here is the “ parallel motion,” an ordinary form of which is shown diagram</p><p>matically in fig. 119. There MN</p><p>is the path in which the piston-</p><p>rod head, or crosshead, as it is</p><p>often called, is to be guided.</p><p>ABC is the middle line of half</p><p>the beam, C being the fixed centre</p><p>about which the beam oscillates.</p><p>A link BD connects a point in the beam with a radius link ED, which oscillates about a fixed centre at E. A point P in BD, taken so that BP : DP : : EN : CM, moves in a path which coincides very closely with the straight line MPN. Any other point F in the line CP or CP produced</p><p>below it, the guiding surfaces at Q are avoided, but the path of P is then only very nearly straight. An example of the linkage in this form, with the further modification that A is shifted out, and B is brought nearer to P, occurs in the pumping engine of fig. 130 below.</p><p>In by far the greater number of modern steam-engines the crosshead is guided by a block sliding on planed surfaces. In many beam-engines, even, this plan of guiding the piston has taken the place of the parallel motion.</p><p>is made to copy this motion by means of the links AF and FG, parallel to BD and AC. In the ordinary application of the parallel motion a point such as F is the point of attachment of the piston-rod, and P is used to drive a pump-rod. Other points in the line CP produced are occasionally made use of, by adding other links parallel to AC and BD.@@<hi rend="superscript">1</hi></p><p>Watt’s linkage gives no more than an approximation to straight-line motion, but in a well-designed example the amount of deviation need not exceed one four-thousandth of the length of stroke. It was for long believed that the production of an exact straight-line motion by pure linkage was impossible, until the problem was solved by the invention of the Peaucellier cell.@@<hi rend="superscript">2</hi> The Peaucellier linkage has not been applied to the steam-engine, except in isolated cases.</p><p>194. Another “ parallel motion ” which has been used in steam-engines is shown in fig. 120. AB is a link pivoted on a fixed centre at A, and connected to the middle of another link PQ, which is twice</p><p>the length of AB. Q is guided</p><p>to move in a straight line in the</p><p>direction of AQ. P then moves</p><p>in an exact straight line through</p><p>A. This is not a pure linkage,</p><p>since Q slides in a fixed guide,</p><p>but the distance through which</p><p>Q has to be guided is small compared with the stroke of P. If Q is guided to move in the arc of a circle of large radius, by using a radius rod from a fixed centre above or</p><p>195. No type of steam-engine is so common as the horizontal direct-acting. A small engine of this type, made by Messrs Tangye, and rated as a 10-horse-power engine, is illustrated in figs. 121 to 124. It furnishes a good example of a very numerous class, and serves to illustrate the principal parts of a complete engine. Fig. 121 is a side elevation, fig. 122 a plan, fig. 123 a transverse section through the bedplate in front of the cylinder, on the line</p><p><hi rend="superscript">@@@1</hi> The kinematics of the parallel motion are discussed in Rankine’s <hi rend="italic">Machinery and Mill Wark,</hi> p. 275, aud rules are given for the proportions and positions of the parts.</p><p><hi rend="superscript">@@@2</hi> See Kempe’s <hi rend="italic">How to Draw a Straight Line</hi> (“Nature Series,"), 1877.</p></body></text></TEI>