<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0543.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0537-06" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SLICH</label>,
in metallurgy, the ore of any metal, particularly of gold, when it has been pounded, and prepared for farther working.</p><p>The manner of preparing the slich at Chremnitz in Hungary is this ; they lay a foundation of wood three yards deep, upon this they place the ore, and over this there are 24 beams, armed at their bottoms with iron ; theſe, by a continual motion, beat and grind the ore, till it is reduced to powder : during this operation, the ore is covered with water. There are four wheels uſed to move theſe beams, each wheel moving six ; and the water, as it runs off, carrying ſome of the metalline particles with it, is received into ſeveral baſons, one placed behind another ; and finally, after having paſſed through them all, and depoſited ſome ſediment in each, it is let off into a very large pit, almoſt half an acre in extent ; in which it is ſuſſered to ſtand ſo long, as to depoſit all its ſediment, of whatever kind, and after this it is let out. This work is carried on day and night, and the ore taken away and replaced by more as often as occaſion requires. That ore which lies next the beams, by which it was pounded, is always the cleaneſt or richeſt.</p><p>When the slich is waſhed as much as they can, a hundred weight of it uſually contains about an ounce, or perhaps but half an ounce of metal, which is not all gold ; for there is always a mixture of gold and ſilver, but the gold is in the largeſt quantity, and uſually is two-thirds of the mixture : they then put the slich into a furnace with ſome limeſtone, and ſlacken, or the ſcoria of former meltings, and run them together. The firſt melting produces a ſubſtance called <hi rend="italic">lech ;</hi> this lech they burn with charcoal, to make it lighter, to open its body, and render it porous, after which it is called <hi rend="italic">rost;</hi> to this roſt they add sand in ſuch quantity as they find neceſſary, and then melt it over again.</p><p>At Chremnitz they have many other ways of reducing gold out of its ore, but particularly one, in which they employ no lead during the whole operation ; whereas, in general, lead is always neceſſary, after the before mentioned proceſſes. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Gold.</hi></p></div></body></text></TEI>