<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0569.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0563-01" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SNOW</label>,
a well-known meteor, formed by the freezing of the vapours in the atmoſphere. It differs from hail and hoar-froſt, in being as it were crystallized, which they are not. This appears on examining a flake of ſnow by a magnifying glaſs; when the whole of it will appear to be compoſed of fine ſhining ſpicula diverging like rays from a centre. As the flakes fall down through the atmoſphere, they are continually joined by more of theſe radiated ſpicula, and thus increaſe in bulk like the drops of rain or hailſtones. Dr Grew, in a diſcourſe of the nature of ſnow, obſerves, that many parts thereof are of a regular figure, for the most part stars of six points, and are as perfect and tranſparent ice as any we ſee on a pond, &amp; c. Upon each of theſe points are other collateral points, ſet at the ſame angles as the main points themſelves : among which there are divers other irregular, which are chiefly broken points, and fragments of the regular ones. Others alio, by various winds, ſeem to have been thawed and frozen again into irregular clusters ; ſo that it ſeems as if the whole body of ſnow were an infinite maſs of icicles irregularly figured. That is, a cloud of vapours being gathered into drops, the ſaid drops forthwith deſcend ; upon which deſcent, meeting with a freezing air as they paſs through a colder region, each drop is immediately frozen into an icicle, ſhooting itſelf forth into ſeveral points ; but theſe ſtill continuing their deſcent, and meeting with ſome intermitting gales of warmer air, or in their continual wastage to and fro touching upon each other, ſome oſ them are a little thawed, blunted, and again frozen into cluſters, or in- tangled ſo as to fall down in what we call <hi rend="italic">flakes.</hi></p><p>The lightneſs of ſnow, although it is firm ice, is owing to the exceſs of its ſurface, in compariſon to the matter contained under it ; as gold itſelf may be extended in ſurface till it will ride upon the leaſt breath of air.</p><p>The whiteneſs of ſnow is owing to the ſmall particles into which it is divided ; for ice, when pounded, will become equally white. An artificial ſnow has been made by the following experiment. A tall phial of aquafortis being placed by the fire till it is warm, and filings of pure silver, a few at a time, being put into it; after a briſk ebullition, the ſilver will dissolve ſlowly. The phial being then placed in a cold window, as it cools the ſilver particles will ſhoot into cryſtals, ſeveral of which running together will form a flake of ſnow, which will deſcend to the bottom of the phial. While they are deſcending, they repreſent perfectly a ſhower of ſilver ſnow, and the flakes will lie upon one another at the bottom like real ſnow upon the ground.</p><p>According to Signior Beccaria, clouds of ſnow differ in nothing from clouds of rain, but in the circumſtance of cold that freezes them. Both the regular diffusion</p><p>of the ſnow, and the regularity of the ſtructure of its parts (particularly ſome figures of ſnow or hail which fall about Turin, and which he calls <hi rend="italic">roſette),</hi> ſhow that clouds of ſnow are acted upon by ſome uniform cauſe like electricity ; and he endeavours to ſhow how electricity is capable of forming theſe figures. He was confirmed in his conjectures by obſerving, that his apparatus for obſerving the electricity of the atmoſphere never failed to be electrified by ſnow as well as rain. Professor Winthrop ſometimes found his apparatus electrified by ſnow when driven about by the wind, though it had not been affected by it when the ſnow itſelf was falling. A more intenſe electricity, according to Beccaria, unites the particles of hail more cloſely than the more moderate electricity does thoſe of ſnow, in the ſame manner as we see that the drops of rain which fall from thunder-clouds are larger than thoſe which fall from others, though the former deſcend through a leſs ſpace.</p><p>But we are not to conſider ſnow merely as a curious and beautiful phenomenon. The Great Diſpenſer of univerſal bounty has ſo ordered it, that it is eminently ſubſervient, as well as all the works of creation, to his benevolent deſigns. Were we to judge from appearances only, we might imagine, that ſo far from being uſeful to the earth, the cold humidity of ſnow would be detrimental to vegetation. But the experience of all ages aſſerts the contrary. Snow, particularly in thoſe northern regions where the ground is covered with it for ſeveral months, fructifies the earth, by guarding the corn or other vegetables from the intenſer cold of the air, and eſpecially from the cold piercing winds. It has been a vulgar opinion, very generally received, that ſnow fertilizes the lands on which it falls more than rain, in conſequence of the nitrous ſalts which it is ſuppoſed to acquire by freezing. But it appears from the experiments of Margraaf<note anchored="true" n="1" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="smallcaps">(a)</hi> Margraaf collected of the pureſt ſnow he could find as much as when melted afforded 100 meaſures of water, each meaſure containing 36 ounces. By diſtilling this quantity he obtained 60 grains, not of <hi rend="italic">nitre,</hi> but of <hi rend="italic">calcareous earth,</hi> with ſome grains of the acid of ſea-ſalt, impregnated with a nitrous vapour. The ſame quantity of rain-water collected in the winter months with equal attention, when diſtilled yielded 100 grains of calcareous earth with ſome grains of the acid of nitre and ſea-ſalt. The chemical difference therefore between rain and ſnow is very ſmall.</p></note> (A) in the year 1751, that the chemical difference between rain and ſnow-water is exceedingly ſmall ; that the latter is ſomewhat leſs nitrous, and contains a ſomewhat leſs proportion of earth than the former ; but neither of them contain either earth or any kind of ſalt in any quantity which can be ſenſibly efficacious in promoting vegetation. Allowing, therefore, that nitre is a fertilizer of lands, which many are upon good grounds dispoſed utterly to deny, yet ſo very ſmall is the quantity of it contained in ſnow, that it cannot be ſuppoſed to promote the vegetation of plants upon which the ſnow has fallen. The peculiar agency of ſnow, as a fertilizer in preference to rain, may admit of a very rational explanation, without recurring to nitrous ſalts ſuppoſed to be contained in it. It may be rationally aſcribed to its furniſhing a covering to the roots of vegetables, by which they are guarded from the influence of the atmoſpherical cold, and the internal heat of the earth is prevented from eſcaping.</p><p>The internal parts of the earth, by ſome principle<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0570.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0564"/>
which we do not underſtand, is heated uniformly to the 48th degree of Fahrenheit’s thermometer. This degree of heat is greater than that in which the watery juices of vegetables freeze, and it is propagated from the inward parts of the earth to the ſurface, on which the vegetables grow. The atmoſphere being variably heated by the action of the fun in different climates, and in the ſame climate at different ſeaſons, communicates to the ſurface of the earth and to ſome diſtance below it the degree of heat or cold which prevails in itſelf. Different vegetables are able to preſerve life under different degrees of cold, but all of them periſh when the cold which reaches their roots is extreme. Providence has therefore, in the coldeſt climates, provided a covering of ſnow for the roots of vegetables, by which they are protected from the influence of the atmoſpherical cold. The ſnow keeps in the internal heat of the earth, which ſurrounds the roots of vegetables, and defends them from the cold of the atmoſphere.</p><p>Snow or ice water is always deprived oſ its fixed air, which eſcapes during the proceſs of congelation. Accordingly, as ſome of the inhabitants of the Alps who uſe it for their conſtant drink have enormous wens upon their throats, it has been aſcribed to this circumſtance. If this were the cauſe of theſe wens, it would be eaſy to remove it by exposing the ſnow-water to the air for ſome time. But ſeveral eminent phyſicians have rejected the notion that ſnow-water is the cauſe of theſe wens ; for in Greenland, where ſnow-water is commonly uſed, the inhabitants are not affected with ſuch ſwellings : on the other hand, they are common in Sumatra where ſnow is never ſeen.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Snow,</hi> in ſea-affairs, is generally the largeſt of all two- maſted vessels employed by Europeans, and the moſt convenient for navigation.</p><p>The ſails and rigging on the mainmaſt and fqremaſt of a ſnow are exactly ſimilar to thoſe on the ſame marts in a ſhip ; only that there is a ſmall maſt behind the mainmaſt of the former, which carries a ſail nearly reſembling the mizen of a ſhip. The foot of this maſt is fixed on a block of wood on the quarter-deck abaft the mainmaſt ; and the head of it is attached to the aftertop of the maintop. The ſail which is called the <hi rend="italic">try- ſail</hi> is extended from its maſt towards the ſtern of the veſſel.</p><p>When the sloops of war are rigged as ſnows, they are furniſhed with a horſe, which anſwers the purpoſe of the tryſail-maſt, the fore-part of the sail being attached by rings to the ſaid horſe, in different places of its height.</p><p><hi rend="italic">SNOW-Grotto,</hi> an excavation made by the waters on the ſide of Mount Etna, by making their way under the layers of lava, and by carrying away the bed of pozzolana below them. It occurred to the proprietor, that this place was very ſuitable for a magazine of ſnow : for in Sicily, at Naples, and particularly at Malta, they are obliged for want of ice to make uſe of ſnow for cooling their wine, ſherbet, and other liquors, and for making ſweetmeats.</p><p>This grotto was hired or bought by the knights of Malta, who having neither ice nor ſnow on the burning rock which they inhabit, have hired ſeveral caverns on Etna, into which people whom they employ collect and preſerve quantities of ſnow to be ſent to Malta when needed. This grotto has therefore been repaired with</p><p>in at the expence oſ that order ; flights of ſteps are cut into it, as well as two openings from above, by which they throw in the ſnow, and through which the grotto is enlightened. Above the grotto they have alſo levelled a piece oſ ground of conſiderable extent : this they have incloſed with thick and lofty walls, ſo that when the winds, which at this elevation blow with great violence, carry the ſnow from the higher parts of the mountain, and depoſite it in this incloſure, it is retained and amassed by the walls. The people then remove it into the grotto through the two openings ; and it is there laid up, and preſerved in ſuch a manner as to refill the force of the ſummer heats ; as the layers of lava with which the grotto is arched above prevent them from making any impreſſion.</p><p>When the ſeaſon for exporting the ſnow comes on, it is put into large bags, into which it is preſſed as cloſely as poſſible ; it is then carried by men out of the grotto, and laid upon mules, which convey it to the ſhore, where ſmall vessels are waiting to carry it away.</p><p>But before thoſe lumps of ſnow are put into bags, they are wrapped in freſh leaves ; ſo that while they are conveyed from the grotto to the ſhore, the leaves may prevent the rays of the ſun from making any impreſſion upon them.</p><p>The Sicilians carry on a conſiderable trade in ſnow, which affords employment to ſome thouſands of mules, horſes, and men. They have magazines of it on the ſummits of their loftiest mountains, from which they diſtribute it through all their cities, towns, and houſes ; for every perſon in the iſland makes uſe of ſnow. They conſider the practice of cooling their liquors as abſolutely neceſſary for the preſervation of health ; and in a climate the heat of which is conſtantly relaxing the fibres, cooling liquors, by communicating a proper tone to the fibres of the ſtomach, muſt greatly ſtrengthen them for the performance of their functions.</p><p>In this climate a ſcarcity of ſnow is no leſs dreaded than a ſcarcity of corn, wine, or oil. We are informed by a gentleman who was at Syracuſe in the year 177 <hi rend="smallcaps">7,</hi> when there was a ſcarcity of ſnow, the people of the town learned that a ſmall veſſel loaded with that article was paſſing the coaſt : without a moment’s deliberation they ran in a body to the ſhore and demanded her cargo ; which when the crew refuſed to deliver up, the Syracuſans attacked and took, though with the loſs of ſeveral men.</p><p><hi rend="italic">SNOW-Drοp,</hi> in botany. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Chionanthus.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">SNOWDON-hill,</hi> the name of a mountain in Caernarvonſhire in Wales, generally thought to be the higheſt in Britain ; though ſome have been of opinion that its height is equalled, or even exceeded, by mountains in the Highlands of Scotland. The mountain is ſurrounded by many others, called in the Welſh language <hi rend="italic">Crib Coch, Crib y Distill, Lliweddy yr Arran,</hi> &amp; c.</p><p>According to Mr Pennant<note anchored="true" n="2" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>* Journey to Snowden.</p></note> *, this mountainous tract yields ſcarcely any corn. Its produce is cattle and ſheep; which, during ſummer, keep very high in the mountains, followed by their owners with their families, who reside during that ſeaſon in <hi rend="italic">havοdtys,</hi> or “ ſummer dairy- houſes,” as the ſarmers in the Swiſs Alps do in their <hi rend="italic">ſennes.</hi> Theſe houſes conſiſt of a long low room, with a hole at one end to let out the ſmoke from the fire which is made beneath. Their furniture is very ſimpſe; ſtones are ſubſtituted for stools, and their beds are of<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0571.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0565"/>
hay, ranged along the ſides. They manufacture their own clothes, and dye them with the <hi rend="italic">lichen omphaloides</hi> and <hi rend="italic">lichen parietinus,</hi> moſſes collected from the rocks. During ſummer the men paſs their time in tending their herds or in making hay, &amp; c. and the women in milking or in making butter and cheeſe. For their own uſe they milk both ewes and goats, and make cheeſe of the milk. Their diet conſiſts of milk, cheeſe, and butter : and their ordinary drink is whey ; though they have, by way of reserve, a few bottles of very ſtrong beer, which they uſc as a cordial when ſick. They are people of good underſtanding, wary, and circumſpect ; tall, thin, and of ſtrong conſtitutions. In the wintertime they deſcend into the <hi rend="italic">hen-dref,</hi> or “ old dwelling,” where they paſs their time in inactivity.</p><p>The view from the higheſt peak of Snowdon is very extenſive. From it Mr Pennant ſaw the county of Cheſter, the high hills of Yorkſhire, part of the north of England, Scotland, and Ireland; a plain view of the isle of Man; and that of Angleſea appeared like a map extended under his feet, with every rivulet viſible. Our author took much pains to have this view to advantage; ſat up at a farm on the west till about 12, and walked up the whole way. The night was remarkably fine and ſtarry ; towards morning the ſtars faded away, leaving an interval of darkneſs, which, however, was ſoon diſpelled by the dawn of day. The body of the ſun appeared moſt diſtinct, with the roundneſs of the moon, before, it appeared too brilliant to be looked at. The ſea, which bounded the weſtern part of the proſpect, appeared gilt with the ſun-beams, firſt in ſlender ſtreaks, and at length glowed with redneſs. The proſpect was diſcloſed like the gradual drawing up of a curtain in a theatre ; till at laſt the heat became sufficiently ſtrong to raiſe mills from the various lakes, which in a flight degree obſcured the proſpect. The ſhadow of the mountain extended many miles, and ſhowed its bicapitated form ; the Wyddfa making one head, and Crib y Distill the other. At this time he counted between 20 and 30 lakes either in Caernarvon or in Merionethſhire. In making another viſit, the ſky was obſcured very ſoon aſter he got up. A vaſt mist involved the whole circuit of the mountain, and the proſpect down was horrible. It gave an idea of numbers of abyſſes, concealed by a thick ſmoke furiouſly circulating around them. Very often a guſt of wind made an opening in the clouds, which gave a fine and diſtinct viſta of lake and valley. Sometimes they opened in one place, at others in many at once ; exhibiting a moſt ſtrange and perplexing fight of water, fields, rocks, and chaſms. They then cloſed again, and every thing was involved in darkneſs ; in a few minutes they would ſeparate again, and repeat the above-mentioned scene with infinite variety. From this proſpect our traveller deſcended with great reluctance ; but before he had reached the place where his horſes were left, he was overtaken by a thunder ſtorm. The rolling of the thunder-claps, being reiterated by the mountains, was inexpreſſibly awful ; and after he had mounted, he was in great danger of being ſwept away by the torrents which poured down in conſequence of a very heavy rain.</p><p>It is very rare (Mr Pennant obſerves) that the traveller gets a proper day to aſcend this hill : it indeed often appears clear ; but by the evident attraction of the</p><p>clouds by this lofty mountain, it becomes suddenly and unexpectedly enveloped in miſt, when the clouds have juſt before appeared very high and very remote. At times he obſerved them lower to hair their height ; and notwithſtanding they have been diſperſed to the right and left, yet they have met from both ſides, and united to involve the ſummit in one great obſcurity.</p><p>The height of Snowdon was meaſured, in 1682, by Mr Caſwell, with inſtruments made by Flamſtead : according to his menſuration, the height is 3720 feet ; but more modern computations make it only 3568, reckoning from the quay at Caernarvon to the higheſt peak. The ſtone that compoſes this mountain is exceſſively hard. Large coarſe cryſtals, and frequently cubic pyrites, are found in the fiſſures. An immenſe quantity of water ruſhes down the ſides of Snowdon and the neighbouring mountains, inſomuch that Mr Pennant ſuppoſes, if collected into one ſtream, they would exceed the waters of the Thames.</p></div></body></text></TEI>