<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0550.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0544-04" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SMILAX, <hi rend="smallcaps">rough bindweed,</hi></label>
 in botany : A genus of plants belonging to the claſs of <hi rend="italic">dioecia</hi> and order of <hi rend="italic">hexandria ;</hi> and in the natural ſyſtem ranging under the 11th order, <hi rend="italic">Sarmentacee.</hi> The male calyx is hexa- phyllous, and there is no corolla ; the female calyx is alſo hexaphyllous, without any corolla : there are three ſtyles, a trilocular berry, and two ſeeds. There are 18 ſpecies; the aſpera, excelſa, zeilanica, ſarſaparilla, china, rotundifolia, laurifolia, tamnoides, caduca, bona nox, herbacea, tetragona, lanceolata, and pſeudochina. Of theſe, the ſmilax ſarſaparilla, which affords the ſarſaparilla root, is the moſt valuable. This is well deſcribed in the London Medical Journal by Dr Wright, who, during a long reſidence in Jamaica, made botany his peculiar ſtudy.</p><p>“ This ſpecies (ſays he) has ſtems of the thickneſs of a man’s finger : they are jointed, triangular, and beſet with crooked ſpines. The leaves are alternate, ſmooth and ſhining on the upper ſide ; on the other side are three nerves or costæ, with ſundry ſmall crooked ſpines. The flower is yellow, mixed with red. The fruit is a black berry, containing ſeveral brown ſeeds.</p><p>“ Sarſaparilla delights in low moiſt grounds and near</p><p>the banks of rivers. The roots run ſuperficially under the ſurface of the ground. The gatherers have only to looſen the soil a little, and to draw out the long fibres with a wooden hook. In this manner they proceed till the whole root is got out. It is then cleared of the mud, dried, and made into bundles.</p><p>“ The ſenſible qualities of ſarſaparilla are mucilaginous and farinaceous, with a flight degree of acrimony. The latter, however, is ſo flight as not to be perceived by many ; and I am apt to believe that its medicinal powers may fairly be aſcribed to ifs demulcent and farinaceous qualities.</p><p>“ Since the publication of Sir William Fordyce’s paper on Sarſaparilla in the Medical Obſervations and Inquiries, Vol. I. ſarſaparilla has been in more general uſe than formerly. The planters in Jamaica ſupply their eſtates with great quantities of it ; and its exhibition has been attended wich very happy conſequences in the yaws and in venereal affections; as nodes, tophi, and exoſtolis ; pains of the bones, and carious or cancerous ulcers.</p><p>“ Sir William Fordyce ſeems to think ſarſaparilla a ſpecific in all ſtages of lues ; but from an attentive and careful obſervation of its effects in ſome thouſands of caſes, I muſt declare I could place no dependence on ſarſaparilla alone. But if mercury had formerly been tried, or was uſed along with ſarſaparilla, a cure was ſoon effected. Where the patients had been reduced by pain, diſonler, and mercury, I preſcribed a decoction of ſarſaparilla, and a table-spoonful of the powder of the ſame, twice a day, with the greateſt ſucceſs, in the moſt deplorable caſes of lues, ill-cured yaws, and carious or ill-diſpoſed fores or cancers.”</p><p>The china, or oriental ſpecies of china root, has roundiſh prickly ſtalks and red berries, and is a native of China and Japan. The pſeudochina, or occidental ſpecies, has rounder ſmooth ſtalks and black berries, grows wild in Jamaica and Virginia, and bears the colds of our own climate.<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0551.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0545"/>
Theſe roots have ſcarce any ſmell or particular taſte: when freſh, they are ſaid to be ſomewhat acrid, but as brought to us they diſcover, even when long-chewed, no other than a flight unctuosity in the mouth. Boiled in water, they impart a reddiſh colour, and a kind of vapid ſoftneſs : the decoction when inſpiſſated yields an unctuous, farinaceous, almoſt inſipid maſs, amounting to upwards of half the weight of the root. They give a gold yellow tincture to rectified ſpirit, but make no ſenſible alteration in its taſte : on drawing off the ſpirit from the filtered liquor, there remains an orange-coloured extract, nearly as inſipid as that obtained by water, but ſcarcely in half its quantity.</p><p>China root is generally ſuppoſed to promote perſpiration and urine, and by its ſoft unctuous quality to blunt acrimonious humours. It was firſt introduced into Europe about the year 1535, with the character of a ſpecific againſt venereal diſorders : the patient was kept warm, a weak decoction of china root was uſed for common drink, and a stronger decoction taken twice a day in bed to promote a ſweat. Such a regimen is doubtleſs a good auxiliary to mercurial alteratives : but whatever may be its effects in the warmer climates, it is found in this to be of itſelf greatly inſufficient. At preſent the china root is very rarely made uſe of, having for ſome time given place to ſarſaparilla, which is ſuppoſed to be more effectual. Proſper Alpinus informs us, that this root is in great eſteem among the Egyptian women for procuring fatneſs and plumpness.</p></div></body></text></TEI>