<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0606.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0600-01" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SOLFATERRA</label>,
a mountain of Italy in the kingdom of Naples, and Terra di Lavoro. This mountain appears evidently to have been a volcano in ancient times ; and the ſoil is yet ſo hot, that the workmen employed there in making alum need nothing elſe besides the heat of the ground for evaporating their liquids. Of this mountain we have the following account by Sir William Hamilton. “Near Aſtruni (another mountain, formerly a volcano likewiſe) riſes the Solfaterra, which not only retains its cone and crater, but much of its former heat. In the plain within the crater, ſmoke iſſues from many parts, as alſo from its ſides : here, by means of ſtones and tiles heaped over the crevices, through which the ſmoke passes, they collect in an awkward manner what they call <hi rend="italic">ſale armoniaco ;</hi> and from the sand of the plain they extract sulphur and alum. This ſpot, well attended to, might certainly produce a good revenue, whereas I doubt if they have hitherto ever cleared L. 200 a-year by it. The hollow ſound produced by throwing a heavy ſtone on the plain of the crater of the Solſaterra, ſeems to indicate that it is ſupported by a fort of arched natural vault and one is induced to think that there is a pool of water beneath this vault (which boils by the heat of a ſubterraneous fire ſtill deeper), by the very moiſt steam that iſſues from the cracks in the plain of the Solfaterra, which, like that of boiling water, runs off a sword, or knife, preſented to it, in great drops. On the outſide, and at the foot of the cone of the Solfaterra, towards the lake of Agnano, water ruſhes out of the rocks ſo hot as to raiie the quickſilver in Fahrenheit’s thermometer to the degree of boiling water<note anchored="true" n="1" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="smallcaps">(a)</hi> “I have remarked, that after a great fall of rain, the degree of heat in this water is much leſs ; which will account for what Padre Torre lays (in his book, intitled <hi rend="italic">Histoire et Phenonιenes du Veſuve),</hi> that when he tried it in company with Monſieur de la Condamine, the degree of heat, upon Reaumur’s thermometer, was 68⁰.</p></note> <hi rend="smallcaps">(a) ;</hi> a fact of which I was myſelf an eye-witneſs. This place, well worthy the obſervation of the curious, has been taken little notice of ; it is called the <hi rend="italic">Pisciarelli.</hi> The common people of Naples have great faith in the efficacy of this water ; and make much of it in all cutaneous disorders, as well as for another diſorder that prevails here. It ſeems to be impregnated chiefly with ſulphur and alum. When you approach your ear to the rocks of the Piſciarelli, from whence this water ouzes, you hear a horrid boiling noiſe, which ſeems to proceed from the huge cauldron that may be ſuppoſed to be under the plain of the Solfaterra, On the other ſide of the Solfaterra, next the ſea, there is a rock which has communicated with the ſea, till part of it was cut away to make the road to Puzzole; this was undoubtedly a considerable lava, that ran from the Solfaterra when it was an active volcano. Under this rock of dava, which is more than 70 feet high, there is a ſtratum of pumice and ashes. This ancient lava is about a quarter of a mile broad; you meet with it abruptly before you come in sight of Puzzole, and it finishes as abruptly within about 100 paces of the town. The ancient name of the Solfaterra was <hi rend="italic">Forum Vulcani ;</hi> a ſtrong proof of its origin from ſubterraneous fire. The degree of heat that the Solfaterra has preſerved for ſo many ages, ſeems to have calcined the stones upon its cone and in its crater, as they are very white and crumble eaſily in the hotteſt parts. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Chemistry,</hi> n⁰ 656.</p></div></body></text></TEI>