<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0498.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0492-01" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SILVERING</label>,
the covering of any thing with ſilver. It is uſual to ſilver metals, wood, paper, &amp; c. which is performed either with fire, oil, or ſize. Metal- gilders ſilver by the fire ; painter-gilders all the other ways. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Gilding.</hi></p><p>To ſilver copper or braſs. 1. Cleanſe the metal with aquafortis, by waſhing it lightly, and immediately throwing it into pure water ; or by heating it red-hot, and ſcouring it with ſalt and tartar and pure water with a ſmall wire bruſh. 2. Dissolve ſome ſilver in aquafortis, in a broad-bottomed glaſs veſſel, or of glazed earth ; then evaporate away the aquafortis over a chaffing diſh of coals. 3. Put five or six times its quantity of water, or as much as will be neceſſary to disſolve it perfectly, on the remaining dry calx ; evaporate this water with the like heat ; then put more freſh water, and evaporate again ; and, if need be, the third time, making the fire towards the latter end ſo ſtrong as to leave the calx perfectly dry, which, if your ſilver is good, will be of a pure white. 4. Take of this calx, common ſalt, cryſtal of tartar, of each a like quantity or bulk, and mixing well the whole compoſition, put the metal into pure water, and take of the ſaid powder with your wet fingers, and rub it well on, till you find every little cavity of the metal ſufficiently silvered over. 5. If you would have it richly done, you</p><p>muſt rub on more of the powder ; and in the laſt place waſh the ſilvered metal in pure water, and rub it hard with a dry cloth.</p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Silvering</hi> <hi rend="italic">of Glaſſes.</hi> See <hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Foliating</hi> <hi rend="italic">of Looking- glasses.</hi></p></div></body></text></TEI>