<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0625.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0619-05" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SPAIN</label>,
a country of Europe, famous both in ancient and modern hiſtory, ſituated in that large peninſula which forms the ſouth-weſtern part of Europe. It is bounded on the ſouth and eaſt by the Mediterranean ſea and ſtraits of Gibraltar, on the north and west by the Bay of Biſcay and Atlantic Ocean, on the ſouth- west by Portugal, and on the north-eaſt by the Pyrenees.</p><p>The moſt ancient name of Spain was <hi rend="italic">Iberia,</hi> ſuppoſed by ſome to be derived from the <hi rend="italic">Iberians,</hi> a people inhabiting Mount Caucaſus, a colony of whom ſettled in this country. Others derive it from the Phenician word <hi rend="italic">Ebra</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Ibra,</hi> ſignifying a paſſage or limit. By the Romans it was called <hi rend="italic">Spania</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Lliſpania,</hi> from the Phenician name <hi rend="italic">Sphanija ;</hi> and this again from <hi rend="italic">ſhaphan,</hi> a Phenician word ſignifying a rabbit, becauſe the weſtern part of Spain abounded with thoſe animals.</p><p>Spain, as well as the reſt of Europe, was probably peopled by the Celtes ; but the Spaniſh hiſtorians derive the origin of their nation from Tubal the fifth ſon of Japhet, asserting that Spain had been a monarchy for 2226 years before the coming of the Celtes into it. Till the coming of the Carthaginians into Spain, however, nothing certain can be affirmed of the Spaniards ; and this happened not long before the commencement of the firſt Punic war. Their ſucceſs in reducing the country, and their final expulſion by the Romans, has already been rclated under the articles <hi rend="smallcaps">Rome</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Carthage ;</hi> we have here therefore only to take notice of the ſtate oſ Spain under the Roman government, until the Romans were in their turn expelled by the northern barbarians.</p><p>At the time oſ the Roman conqueſt, Spain, though prodigious quantities of ſilver had been carried out of it by the Carthaginians and Tyrians, was yet a very rich country. In the most ancicnt times, indeed, its riches are ſaid to have exceeded what is related of the moſt wealthy country in America. Ariſtotle aſſures us, that when the Phenicians firſt arrived in Spain, they exchanged their naval commodities for ſuch immenſe quantities of ſilver, that their ſhips could neither contain nor ſuſtain its load, though they uſed it for ballaſt, and made their anchois and other implements oſ ſilver. When the Carthaginians firſt came to Spain, they found the quantity of ſilver nothing leſſened, ſince the inhabitants at that time made all their utensils, and even<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0626.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0620"/>
mangers, of that precious metal. In the time of the Romans this amazing plenty was very much diminiſhed ; however, their gleanings were by no means deſpicable, ſince in the ſpace of nine years they carried off 111,542 pounds of ſilver, and 4095 of gold, beſides an immenſe quantity of coin and other things of value. The Spaniards were always remarkable for their bravery, and ſome of Hannibal’s beſt troops were brought from thence. But as the Romans penetrated farther into the country than the Carthaginians had done, they met with nations whoſe love of liberty was equal to their valour, and whom the whole ſtrength of their empire was ſcarce able to ſubdue. Of theſe the moſt formidable were the Numantines, Cantabrians, and Aſturians.</p><p>In the time of the third Punic war, one Viriathus, a celebrated hunter, and afterwards the captain of a gang of banditti, took upon him the command of ſome nations who had been in alliance with Carthage, and ventured to oppoſe the Roman power in that part of Spain called <hi rend="italic">Lusitania,</hi> now Portugal. The praetor, named <hi rend="italic">Vetilius,</hi> who commanded in thoſe parts, marched againſt him with 10,000 men; but was defeated and killed, with the loss of 4000 of his troops The Romans immediately dispatched another praetor with 10,000 foot and 1300 horſe: but Viriathus having firſt cut off a detachment of 4000 of them, engaged the reſt in a pitched battle ; and having entirely defeated them, reduced great part oſ the country. Another praetor, who was ſent with a new army, met with the ſame fate ; ſo that, after the deſtruction of Carthage, the Romans thought proper to ſend a conſul named <hi rend="italic">Quintus Fabius,</hi> who defeated the Luſitanians in ſeveral battles, and regained two important places which had long been in the hands of the rebels. After the expiration of Fabius’s conſulate, Viriathus continued the war with his uſual ſucceſs, till the ſenate thought proper to ſend againſt him the conſul Q. Cæcilius Metellus, an officer of great valour and experience. With him Viriathus did not chooſe to venture a pitched battle, but contented himſelf with acting on the defenſive ; in conſequence of which the Romans recovered a great many cities, and the whole of Tarraconian Spain was obliged to ſubmit to their yoke. The other conſul, named <hi rend="italic">Servilianus,</hi> did not meet with the ſame ſucceſs ; his army was defeated in the field and his camp was nearly taken by Viriathus. Notwithſtanding the good fortune of Metellus, however, he could not withſtand the intrigues of his countrymen againſt him, and he was not allowcd to finiſh the war he had begun with ſo much ſucceſs. In reſentment for this he took all imaginable pains to weaken the army under his command: he diſhanded the flower of his troops, exhauſted the magazines, let the elephants die, broke in pieces the arrows which had been provided for the Cretan archers, and threw them into a river. Yet, after all, the army which he gave up to his ſuccessor Q. Pompeius, consiſting of 30,000 foot and 2000 horſe, was ſufficient to have cruſhed Viriathus if the general had known how to uſe it. But, inſtead of oppoſing Viriathus with ſucceſs, the imprudent conſul procured much more formidable enemies. The Termantians and Numantines, who had hitherto kept themſelves independent, offered very advantageous terms of peace and alliance with Rome ; but Pompeius insisted on their delivering up their arms. Upon this,</p><p>war was immediately commenced, The conſul with great confidence inveſted Numantia; but being repulſed with conſiderable loſs, he ſat down before Termantia, where he was attended with ſtill worſe ſucceſs. The very firſt day, the Termantines killed 700 of his legionaries ; took a great convoy which was coming to the Roman camp ; and having defeated a conſiderable body of their horſe, puſhed them from poſt to poſt till they came to the edge of a precipice, where they all tumbled down, and were daſhed to pieces. In the mean time Servilian, who had been continued in his command with the title of <hi rend="italic">proconſul,</hi> managed matters ſo ill, that Viriathus ſurrounded him on all ſides, and obliged him to ſue for peace. The terms offered to the Romans were very moderate ; being only that Viriathus ſhould keep the country he at that time poſſeſſed, and the Romans remain maſters of all the reſt. This peace the proconſul was very glad to ſign, and afterwards got it ſigned by the ſenate and people of Rome.</p><p>The next year Q. Pompeius was continued in his command againſt the Numantines in Farther Spain, while Servilius Cæpio, the new conſul, had for his province Hither Spain, where Viriathus had eſtabliſhed his new ſtate. Pompeius undertook to reduce Numantia by turning aſide the ſtrearn oſ the Durius, now the Douro, by which it was ſupplied with water ; but, in attempting this, ſuch numbers of his men were cut off, that, finding himſelf unable to contend with the enemy, he was glad to make peace with them on much worſe terms than they had offered of their own accord. The peace, however, was ratified at Rome; but in the mean time Cæpio, deſirous of ſhowing his proweſs againſt the renowned Viriathus, prevailed upon the Romans to declare war againſt him without any provocation. As Cæpio commanded an army greatly ſuperior to the Luſitanians, Viriathus thought proper to ſue for peace ; but finding that Cæpio would be ſatisfied with nothing leſs than a ſurrender at diſcretion, he resolved to ſtand his ground. In the mean time, the latter having bribed ſome of the intimate companions of Viriathus to murder him in his ſleep, he by that infamous method put an end to a war which had laſted 14 years, very little to the honour of the republic.</p><p>After the death of Viriathus, the Romans with like treachery ordered their new conſul Popilius to break the treaty with the Numantines. His infamous conduct met with the reward it deſerved ; the Numantines ſallying out, put the whole Roman army to flight with ſuch ſlaughter, that they were in no condition to act during the whole campaign. Mancinus, who ſucceeded Popilius, met with ſtill worſe ſucceſs ; his great army, conſiſting of 30,000 men, was utterly defeated by 4000 Numantines, and 20,000 of them killed in the purſuit. The remaining 10,000, with their general, were pent up by the Numantines in ſuch a manner that they could neither advance nor retreat, and would certainly have been all put to the sword or made priſoners, had not the Numantines, with a generoſity which their enemies never poſſeſſed, offered to let them depart upon condition that a treaty ſhould be concluded with them upon very moderate terms. This the conſul very willingly promiſed, but found himſelf unable to perform. On the contrary, the people, not ſatisfied with declaring his treaty null and void, ordered him to be delivered up to the Numantines. The latter refuſed to accept him, un-<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0627.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0621"/>
left he had along with him the 10,000 men whom they had relieved as above related. At laſt, after the conſul had remained a whole day before the city, his ſucceſſor Furius, thinking this a sufficient recompenſe to the Numantines for breaking the treaty, ordered him to be received again into the camp. However, Furius did not chooſe to engage with ſuch a deſperate and reſolute enemy as the Numantines had ſhowed themſelves; and the war with them was diſcontinued till the year 133 B. C. when Scipio Æmilianus, the deſtroyer of Carthage, was ſent againſt them. Againſt this renowned commander the Numantines with all their valour were not able to cope. Scipio, having with the utmoſt care introduced ſtrict diſcipline among his troops, and reformed the abuſes which his predeceſſors had suffered in their armies, by degrees brought the Romans to face their enemies, which at his arrival they had abſolutely refuſed to do. Having then ravaged all the country round about the town, it was ſoon blocked up on all ſides, and the inhabitants began to feel the want of provisions. At laſt they reſolved to make one deſperate attempt for their liberty, and either to break through their enemies, or periſh in the attempt. With this view they marched out in good order by two gates, and fell upon the works of the Romans with the utmoſt fury. The Romans, unable to ſtand this deſperate ſhock, were on the point of yielding ; but Scipio, haſtening to the places attacked, with no fewer than 20,000 men, the unhappy Numantines were at laſt driven into the city, where they ſuſtained for a little longer the miſeries of famine. Finding at laſt, however, that it was altogether impoſſible to hold out, it was reſolved by the majority to ſubmit to the pleaſure of the Roman commander. But this reſolution was not univerſally approved. Many ſhut themſelves up in their houſes, and died of hunger, while even thoſe who had agreed to surrender repented their offer, and ſetting fire to their houſes, periſhed in the flames with their wives and children, ſo that not a ſingle Numantine was left alive to grace the triumph of the conqueror of Carthage.</p><p>After the deſtruction of Numantia the whole of Spain ſubmitted to the Roman yoke; and nothing remarkable happened till the times of the Cimbri, when a prætorian army was cut off in Spain by the Luſitanians. From this time nothing remarkable occurs in the hiſtory of Spain till the civil war between Marius and Sylla. The latter having cruſhed the Marian faction, as related under the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Rome,</hi> proſcribed all thoſe that had ſided againſt him whom he could not immediately deſtroy. Among theſe was Sertorius, a man of conſummate valour and experience in war. He had by Marius been appointed praetor of Spain ; and upon the overthrow of Marius, retired to that province. Sylla no ſooner heard of his arrival in that country, than he ſent thither one Caius Annius with a powerful army to drive him out. As Sertorius had but few troops along with him, he diſpatched one Julius Salinator with a body of 6000 men to guard the paſſes of the Pyrenees, and to prevent Annius from entering the country. But Salinator having been treacherouſly murdered by aſſaſſins hired by Annius for that purpoſe, he no longer met with any obſtacle ; and Sertorius was obliged to embark for the coaſt of Africa with 3000 men, being all he had now remaining. With theſe he landed in Mauritania ; but as his men were ſtraggling careleſsly about,</p><p>great numbers oſ them were cut off by the Barbarians. This new misfortune obliged Sertorius to re-embark for Spain ; but finding the whole coaſt lined with the troops of Annius, he put to ſea again, not knowing what courſe to steer. In this new voyage he met with a ſmall fleet of Cilician pirates ; and having prevailed with them to join him, he made a deſcent on the coaſt of Yvica, overpowered the garriſon left there by Annius, and gained a conſiderable booty. On the news of this victory Annius ſet ſail for Yvica, with a conſiderable ſquadron, having 5000 land forces on board. Sertorius, not intimidated by the ſuperiority of the enemy, prepared to give them battle. But a violent ſtorm ariſing, moſt of the ſhips were driven on ſhore and daſhed to pieces, Sertorius himſelf with great difficulty eſcaping with the small remains of his fleet. For ſome time he continued in great danger, being prevented from putting to ſea by the fury of the waves, and from landing by the enemy ; at laſt, the ſtorm abating, he passed the ſtraits of Gades, now Gibraltar, and landed near the mouth of the liver Bæotis. Here he met with ſome ſeamen newly arrived from the Atlantic or Fortunate Iſlands; and was ſo taken with the account which they gave him of thoſe happy regions, that he reſolved to retire thither to ſpend the reſt of his life in quiet and happineſs. But having communicated this design to the Cilician pirates, they immediately abandoned him, and ſet ſail for Africa, with an intention to aſſiſt one of the barbarous kings againſt his ſubjects who had rebelled. Upon this Sertorius ſailed thither alſo, but took the oppoſite ſide ; and having defeated the king named <hi rend="italic">Aſcalis,</hi> obliged him to ſhut himſelf up in the city of Tingis, now Tangier, which he cloſely beſieged. But in the mean time Pacianus; who had been ſent by Sylla to aſſiſt the king, advanced with a conſiderable army againſt Sertorius. Upon this the latter, leaving part of his forces before the city, marched with the reſt to meet Pacianus, whoſe army, though greatly ſuperior to his own in number, he entirely defeated; killed the general, and took all his forces priſoners.—The fame of this victory ſoon reached Spain ; and the Luſitanians, being threatened with a new war from Annius, invited Sertorius to head their armies. With this requeſt he very readily complied, and ſoon became very formidable to the Romans. Titus Didius, governor oſ that part of Spain called <hi rend="italic">Baetica,</hi> firſt entered the lists with him ; but he being defeated, Sylla next diſpatched Metellus, reckoned one of the beſt commanders in Rome, to flop the progreſs of this new enemy. But Metellus, notwithſtanding all his experience, knew not how to act againſt Sertorius, who was continually changing his ſtation, putting his army into new forms, and contriving new ſtratagems. On his first arrival he ſent for L. Domitius, then praetor of Hither Spain, to, his aſſiſtance ; but Sertorius being informed of his march, detached Hirtuleius, or Herculeius, his quæstor, againſt him, who gave him a total overthrow. Metellus then diſpatched Lucius Lollius prætor of Narbonne Gaul againſt Hirtuleius ; but he met with no better ſucceſs, being utterly defeated, and his lieutenant-general killed.</p><p>The fame of theſe victories brought to the camp of Sertorius ſuch a number of illuſtrious Roman citizens of the Marian faction, that he formed a design of erecting Luſitania into a republic in oppoſition to that of Rome. Sylla was continually sending freſh ſupplies to<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0628.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0622"/>
Metellus ; but Sertorius with an handful of men, accuſtomed to range about the mountains, to endure hunger and thirſt, and live expoſed to the inclemencies of the weather, ſo haraſſed the Roman army, that Metellus himſelf began to be quite diſcouraged. At laſt, Sertorius, hearing that Metellus had ſpoken diſreſpectfully of his courage, challenged his antagoniſt to end the war by single combat ; but Metellus very prudently declined the combat, as being advanced in years; yet this refuſal brought upon him the contempt of the unthinking multitude, upon which Metellus reſolved to retrieve his reputation by ſome ſignal exploit, and therefore laid ſiege to Laeobriga, a conſiderable city in thoſe parts. This he hoped to reduce in two days, as there was but one well in the place ; but Sertorius, having previously removed all thoſe who could be of no ſervice during the liege, and conveyed 6000 ſkins full of water into the city, Metellus continued a long time before it without making any impreſſion. At laſt, his proviſions being almoſt ſpent, he ſent out Aquinus at the head of 6000 men to procure a new ſupply; but Sertorius falling unexpectedly upon them, cut in pieces or took the whole detachment; the commander himſelf being the only man who eſcaped to carry the news of the diſaſter ; upon which Metellus was obliged to raiſe the ſiege with diſgrace.</p><p>And now Sertorius, having gained ſome intervals of eaſe in conſequence of the many advantages he had obtained over the Romans, began to civilize his new ſubjects. Their ſavage and furious manner of fighting he changed for the regular order and diſcipline of a well- formed army ; he bellowed liberally upon them gold and ſilver to adorn their arms, and by converſing familiarly with them, prevailed upon them to lay aſide their own dreſs for the Roman <hi rend="italic">toga.</hi> He ſent for all the children of the principal people, and placed them in the great city of Oſea, now Hereſca, in the kingdom of Arragon, where he appointed them maſters to inſtruct them in the Roman and Greek learning, that they might, as he pretended, be capable of ſharing with him the government of the republic. Thus he made them really hoſtages for the good behaviour of their parents ; however, the latter were greatly pleaſed with the care he took of their children, and all Luſitania were in the higheſt degree attached to their new ſovereign. This attachment he took care to heighten by the power of ſuperſtition ; for having procured a young hind of a milk-white colour, he made it ſo tame that it followed him wherever he went ; and Sertorius gave out to the ignorant multitude, that this hind was inſpired by Diana, and revealed to him the deſigns of his enemies, of which he always took care to be well informed by the great numbers of ſpies he employed.</p><p>While Sertorius was thus employed in eſtabliſhing his authority, the republic of Rome, alarmed at his ſucceſs, reſolved to cruſh him at all events. Sylla was now dead, and all the eminent generals in Rome solicited this honourable though dangerous employment. After much debate a decree was paſſed in favour of Pompey the Great, but without recalling Metellus. In the mean time, the troops of one Perpenna, or Perperna, had, in ſpite of all that their general could do, abandoned him and taken the oath of allegiance to Sertorius. This was a moſt ſignal advantage to Settorius; for Perperna commanded an army of 33,000 men, and had</p><p>come into Spain with a deſign to ſettle there as Sertorius had done ; but as he was deſcended from one of the firſt families in Rome, he thought it below his dignity to ſerve under any general, however eminent he might be. But the troops of Perperna were of a different opinion; and therefore declaring that they would ſerve none but a general who could defend himſelf, they to a man joined Sertorius ; upon which Perperna himſelf, finding he could do no better, conſented to ſerve alſo as a ſubaltern.</p><p>On the arrival of Pompey in Spain, ſeveral of the cities which had hitherto continued faithful to Sertorius began to waver ; upon which the latter reſolved, by ſome ſignal exploit, to convince them that Pompey could no more ſcreen them from his reſentment than Metellus. With this view he laid ſiege to Lauron, now Lirias, a place of conſiderable ſtrength. Pompey, not doubting but he ſhould be able to raiſe the ſiege, marched quite up to the enemy’s lines, and found means to inform the garriſon that thoſe who beſieged them were themſelves beſieged, and would ſoon be obliged to retire with loſs and diſgrace. On hearing this meſſage, “ I will teach Sylla’s diſciple (ſaid Sertorius), that it is the duty of a general to look behind as well as before him.” Having thus ſpoken, he ſent orders to a detachment of 6000 men, who lay concealed among the mountains, to dome down and fall upon his rear if he ſhould offer to force the lines. Pompey, ſurpriſed at their ſudden appearance, durst not ſtir out of his camp ; and in the mean time the beſieged, deſpairing of relief, ſurrendered at diſcretion ; upon which Sertorius granted them their lives and liberty, but reduced their city to aſhes.</p><p>While Sertorius was thus ſucceſsfully contending with Pompey, his quaeſtor Hirtuleius was entirely defeated by Metellus, with the loſs of 20,000 men ; upon which Sertorius advanced with the utmoſt expedition to the banks of the Sucro in Tarraconian Spain, with a deſign to attack Pompey before he could be joined by Metellus. Pompey, on his part, did not decline the combat ; but, fearing that Metellus might ſhare the glory of the victory, advanced with the greateſt expedition. Sertorius put off the battle till towards the evening; Pompey, though he knew that the night would prove diſadvantageous to him, whether vanquiſhed or victorious, becauſe his troops were unacquainted with the country, reſolved to venture an engagement, eſpecially as he feared that Metellus might arrive in the mean time, and rob him of part of the glory of conquering ſo great a commander. Pompey, who commanded his own right wing, ſoon obliged Perperna, who commanded Sertorius’s left, to give way. Hereupon Sertorius himſelf taking upon him the command of that wing, brought back the fugitives to the charge, and obliged Pompey to fly in his turn. In his flight he was overtaken by a gigantic African, who had already lifted up his hand to diſcharge a blow at him with his broad ſword ; but Pompey prevented him by cutting off his right hand at one blow. As he ſtill continued his flight, he was wounded and thrown from his horſe ; so that he would certainly have been taken priſoner, had not the Africans who purſued him quarrelled about the rich furniture of his horſe. This gave an opportunity to the general to make his eſeape ; ſo that at length he reached his camp with much difficul-<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0629.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0623"/>
ty. But in the mean time Afranius, who commanded the left wing of the Roman army, had entirely defeated the wing which Sertorius had left, and even purſued them ſo cloſe that he entered the camp, along with them. Sertorius, returning ſuddenly, found the Romans buſy in plundering the tents; when, taking advantage of their ſituation, he drove them out with great ſlaughter, and retook his camp. Next day he offered battle a ſecond time to Pompey ; but Metellus then coming up with all his forces, he thought proper to decline an engagement with both commanders. In a few days, however, Pompey and Metellus agreed to attack the camp of Sertorius. Metellus attacked Perperna, and Pompey fell upon Sertorius. The event was ſimilar to that of the former battle ; Metellus defeated Perperna, and Sertorius routed Pompey. Being then informed of Perperna’s misfortune, he haſtened to his relief ; rallied the fugitives, and repulſed Metellus in his turn, wounded him with his lance, and would certainly have killed him, had not the. Romans, aſhamed to leave their general in diſtreſs, hastened to his aſſiſtance, and renewed the fight with great fury. At laſt Sertorius was obliged to quit the field, and retire to the mountains. Pompey and Metellus haſtened to beſiege him ; but while they were forming their camp, Sertorius broke through their lines, and eſcaped into Lulitania. Here he ſoon raiſed ſuch a powerful army, that the Roman generals, with their united forces, did not think proper to venture an engagement with him. They could not, however, refill the perpetual attacks of Sertorius, who now drove them from place to place, till he obliged them to ſeparate, the one went into Gaul, and the other to the foot of the Pyrenees.</p><p>Thus did this celebrated commander triumph over all the power of the Romans ; and there is little doubt but he would have continued to make head againſt all the other generals whom the republic could have ſent ; had he not been aſſaſſinated at an entertainment by the infamous treachery of Perperna, in 73 B. C. after he had made head againſt the Roman forces ſor alrnoſt ten years. Pompey was no ſooner informed of his death, than, without waiting for any new ſuccours, he marched againſt the traitor, whom he eaſily defeated and took prisoner ; and having cauſed him to be executed, thus put an end, with very little glory, to a moſt dangerous war.</p><p>Many of the Spaniſh nations, however, ſtill continued to bear the Roman yoke with great impatience ; and as the civil wars which took place firſt between Julius Cæsar and Pompey, and afterwards between Octavianus and Antony, diverted the attention of the republic from Spain, by the time that Auguſtus had become ſole maſter oſ the Roman empire, they were again in a condition to aſſert their liberty. The <hi rend="smallcaps">Cantabrians</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Asturians</hi> were the moſt powerful and valiant nations at that time in Spain; but, after incredible efforts, they were obliged to lay down their arms, or rather were alrnoſt exterminated, by Agrippa, as is related under theſe articles. From this time the Spaniards continued in quiet ſubjection to the Romans ; but on the decline of the empire they were attacked by the northern nations, who put an end to the Roman name in the weft. As the inhabitants had by that time entirely loſt their ancient valour, the barbarians met with no reſiſtance but from one another. In the reign of the em</p><p>peror Honorius, the Vandals, Alans, and Suevians, entered this country ; and having made themſelves matters of it, divided the provinces among themſelves. In 444 the Romans made one effort more to recover their power in this part of the world ; but being utterly defeated by the Suevians, the latter eſtabliſhed a kingdom there which laſted till the year 584, when it was utterly overthrown by the Viſigoths under Leovigilde. The Gothic princes continued to reign over a conſiderable part of Spain till the beginning of the 8th century, when their empire was entirely overthrown by the Saracens. During this period, they had entirely expelled the eaſtern emperors from what they poſſeſſed in Spain, and even made conſiderable conqueſts in Barbary; but towards the end of the 7th century the Saracens overran all that part of the world with a rapidity which nothing could resist ; and having ſoon poſſeſſed themſelves of the Gothic dominions in Barbary, they made a deſcent upon Spain about the year 711 or 712. The king of the Goths at that time was called <hi rend="italic">Roderic,</hi> and by his bad conduct had occaſioned great diſaffection among his ſubjects. He therefore determined to put all to the iſſue of a battle, knowing that he could not depend upon the fidelity of his own people if he allowed the enemy time to tamper with them. The two armies met in a plain near Xeres in Andaluſia. The Goths began the attack with great fury ; but though they fought like men in deſpair, they were at laſt defeated with exceſſive ſlaughter, and their king himself was ſuppoſed to have perished in the battle, being never more heard of.</p><p>By this battle the Moors in a ſhort time rendered themſelves maſters of almoſt all Spain. The poor remains of the Goths were obliged to retire into the mountainous parts of Aſturias, Burgos, and Biſeay: the inhabitants of Arragon, Catalonia, and Navarre, though they might have made a considerable ſtand againſt the enemy, choſe for the moſt part to retire into France. In 718, however, the power of the Goths began again to revive under Don Pelagio or Pelayo, a prince of the royal blood, who headed thoſe that had retired to the mountains after the fatal battle of Xeres. The place where he firſt laid the foundation of his government was in the Aſturias, in the province of Uebana, about nine leagues in length and four in breadth. This is the moſt inland part of the country, full of mountains enormouſly high, and ſo much fortified by nature, that its inhabitants are capable of reſiſting almoſt any number of invaders. Alakor the Saracen governor was no ſooner informed of this revival of the Gothiſh kingdom, than he ſent a powerful army, under the command of one Alchaman, to cruſh Don Pelagio before he had time to eſtabliſh his power. The king, though his forces were ſufficiently numerous (every one of his ſubjects arrived at man’s eſtate being a ſoldier), did not think proper to venture a general engagement in the open field ; but taking post with part of them himſelf in a cavern in a very high mountain, he concealed the reſt among precipices, giving orders to them to fall upon the enemy as ſoon as they ſhould perceive him attacked by them. Theſe orders were punctually executed, though indeed Don Pelagio himſelf had repulſed his enemies, but not without a miracle, as the Spaniſh hiſtorians pretend. The ſlaughter was dreadful ; for the troops who lay in ambuſcade joining the<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0630.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0624"/>
reſt, and rolling down huge ſtones from the mountains upon the Moors (the name by which the Saracens were known in Spain), no fewer than 124,000 of theſe unhappy people periſhed in one day. The remainder fled till they were ſtopped by a river, and beginning to coaſt it, part of a mountain ſuddenly fell down, ſtopped up the channel of the river, and either cruſhed or drowned, by the sudden riſing of the water, almoſt every one of that vaſt army.</p><p>The Moors were not ſo much diſheartened by this diſaſter, but that they made a ſecond attempt againſt Don Pelagio. Their ſucceſs was as bad as ever, the greateſt part of their army being cut in pieces or taken ; in conſequence of which, they loſt all the Aſturias, and never dared to enter the lifts with Pelagio afterwards. Indeed, their bad ſucceſs had in a great meaſure taken from them the desire of conquering a country where little or nothing was to be got ; and therefore they rather directed their force againſt France, where they hoped for more plunder. Into this country they poured in prodigious multitudes ; but were utterly defeated, in 732, by Charles Martel, with the loſs of 300,000 men, as the hiſtorians of thoſe times pretend.</p><p>Don Pelagio died in 737, and ſoon after his death ſuch inteſtine diviſions broke out among the Moors, as greatly favoured the increaſe of the Chriſtian power. In 745 Don Alonſo the Catholic, ſon-in-Iaw to Pelagio, in conjunction with his brother Froila, paſſed the mountains, and fell upon the northern part of Galicia ; and meeting with little reſiſtance, he recovered almoſt the whole of that province in a ſingle campaign. Next year he invaded the plains of Leon and Caſtile ; and before the Moors could aſſemble any force to oppose him, he reduced Aſtorgas, Leon, Saldagna, Montes de Oca, Amaya, Alava, and all the country at the foot of the mountains. The year following he puſhed his conqueſts as far as the borders of Portugal, and the next campaign ravaged the country as far as Caſtile. Being ſensible, however, that he was yet unable to defend the flat country which he had conquered, he laid the whole of it waste, obliged the Chriſtians to retire to the mountains, and carried off all the Moors for Haves. Thus ſecured by a deſert frontier, he met with no interruption for ſome years ; during which time, as his kingdom advanced in ſtrength, he allowed his ſubjects gradually to occupy part of the flat country, and to rebuild Leon and Aſtorgas, which he had demoliſhed. He died in 757, and was ſucceeded by his ſon Don Frυila. In his time Abdelrahman, the khaliff’s viceroy in Spain, threw off the yoke, and rendered himſelf independent, fixing the ſeat of his government at Cordova. Thus the inteſtine diviſions among the Moors were compoſed; yet their ſucceſs ſeems to have been little better than before ; for, ſoon after, Froila encountered the Moors with ſuch ſucceſs, that 54,000 of them were killed on the ſpot, and their general taken priſoner. Soon after he built the city of Oviedo, which he made the capital of his dominions, in order to be in a better condition to defend the flat country, which he now determined to people.</p><p>In the year 758 the power of the Saracens received another blow by the riſe of the kingdom of Navarre. This kingdom, we are told, took its origin from an accidental meeting of gentlemen, to the number of 600,</p><p>at the tomb oſ an hermit named <hi rend="italic">John,</hi> who had died among the Pyrenees. At this place, where they had met on account of the ſuppoſed ſanctity of the deceaſed, they took occaſion to converſe on the cruelty of the Moors, the miſeries to which the country was expoſed, and the glory that would reſult from throwing off their yoke ; which, they ſuppoſed, might eaſily be done, by reaſon of the ſtrength of their country. On mature deliberation, the project was approved; one Don Garcia Ximenes was appointed king, as being of illuſtrious birth, and looked upon as a perſon of great abilities. He recovered Ainſa, one of the principal towns oſ the country, out of the hands of the infidels, and his ſucceſſor Don Garcia Inigas extended his territories as far as Biſcay ; however, the Moors ſtill poſſeſſed Portugal, Murcia, Andaluſia, Valentia, Granada, Tortoſa, with the interior part of the country as far as the mountains of Caſtile and Saragoſſa. Their internal diſſenſions, which revived after the death of Abdelrahman, contributed greatly to reduce the power of the infidels in general. In 778, Charles the Great being invited by ſome diſcontented Mooriſh governors, entered Spain with two great armies ; one paſſing through Catalonia, and the other through Navarre, where he puſhed his conqueſts as far as the Ebro. On his return he was attacked and defeated by the Moors ; though this did not hinder him from keeping poſſeſſion of all thoſe places he had already reduced. At this time he ſeems to have been maſter of Navarre: however, in 831 count Azner, revolting from Pepin ſon to the emperor Louis, again revived the independency of Navarre ; but the</p><p>ſovereigns did not assume the title of kings till the time oſ Don Garcia, who began to reign in 857.</p><p>In the mean time, the kingdom founded by Don Pelagio, now called the kingdom of <hi rend="italic">Leon</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Oviedo,</hi> continued to increaſe rapidly in ſtrength, and many advantages were gained over the Moors, who having two enemies to contend with, loſt ground every day. In 921, however, they gained a great victory over the united forces of Navarre and Leon, by which the whole force of the Chriſtians in Spain muſt have been entirely broken, had not the victors conducted their affairs ſo wretchedly, that they ſuſſered themſelves to be almoſt entirely cut in pieces by the remains of the Chriſtian army. In ſhort, the Chriſtians became at length ſo terrible to the Moors, that it is probable they could not long have kept their footing in Spain, had not a great general, named <hi rend="italic">Mohammed Ebn Amir Almanzor,</hi> appeared, in 979, to ſupport their sinking cauſe. This man was visir to the king of Cordova, and being exceedingly provoked againſt the Chriſtians on account of what his countrymen had ſuffered from them, made war with the moſt implacable fury. He took the city of Leon, murdered the inhabitants, and reduced the houses to aſhes. Barcelona ſhared the ſame fate ; Caſtile was reduced to a deſert ; Galicia and Portugal ravaged ; and he is ſaid to have overcome the Chriſtians in fifty different engagements. At laſt, having taken and demoliſhed the city of Compoſtella, and carried off in triumph the gates of the church of St James, a flux happened to break out among his troops, which the ſuperſtitious Chriſtians ſuppoſed to be a divine judgement on account of his ſacrilege. Taking it for granted, therefore, that the Moors were now entirely deſtitute of all heavenly aid, they fell upon them with<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0631.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0625"/>
ſuch fury in the next engagement, that all the valour and conduct of Almanzor could not prevent a defeat. Overcome with ſhame and despair at this misfortune, he deſired his followers to ſhift for themſelves, while he himſelf retired to Medina Cœli, and put an end to his life by abſtinence in the year 998.</p><p>Dining this period a new Chriſtian principality appeared in Spain, namely that of Caſtile, which is now divided into the Old and New Caſtile. The Old Caſtile was recovered long before that called the <hi rend="italic">New.</hi> It was ſeparated from the kingdom <hi rend="italic">of</hi> Leon on one side by ſome little rivers ; on the other, it was bounded by the Aſturias, Biſcay, and the province of Rioja. On the ſouth it had the mountains of Segovia and Avila ; thus lying in the middle between the Chriſtian kingdom of Leon and Oviedo, and the Mooriſh kingdom of Cordova. Hence this diſtrict ſoon became an object of contention between the kings of Leon and thoſe of Cordova ; and as the former were generally victorious, ſome of the principal Caſtilian nobility retained their independency under the protection of the Chriſtian kings, even when the power of the Moors was at its greateſt height. In 884 we firſt hear of Don Rodriguez affirming the title of <hi rend="italic">count of Castile,</hi> though it does not appear that either his territory or title were given him by the king of Leon. Neverthelefs, this monarch having taken upon him to puniſh ſome of the Caſtilian lords as rebels, the inhabitants made a formal renunciation of their allegiance, and ſet up a new kind of government. The ſupreme power was now veſted in two perſons of quality ſtyled <hi rend="italic">judges ;</hi> however, this method did not long continue to give satisfaction, and the ſovereignty was once more veſted in a single perſon. By degrees Caſtile fell entirely under the power of the kings of Leon and Oviedo; and, in 1035, Don Sanchez bestowed it on his eldeſt ſon Don Ferdinand, with the title of <hi rend="italic">king;</hi> and thus the territories of Caſtile were firſt firmly united to thoſe of Leon and Oviedo, and the ſovereigns were thenceforth ſtyled <hi rend="italic">kings of Leon and Caſtle.</hi></p><p>Beſides all theſe, another Chriſtian kingdom was ſet up in Spain about the beginning of the 11th century. This was the kingdom of Arragon. The inhabitants were very brave, and lovers of liberty, ſo that it is probable they had in ſome degree maintained their independency, even when the power of the Moors was greateſt. The hiſtory of Arragon, however, during its infancy, is much leſs known than that of any of the others hitherto mentioned. We are only assured, that about the year 1035, Don Sanchez,ſurnamed the <hi rend="italic">Great,</hi> king of Navarre, erected Arragon into a kingdom in favour of his ſon Don Ramira, and afterwards it became very powerful. At this time, then, we may imagine the continent of Spain divided into two unequal parts hy a ſtraight line drawn from eaſt to west, from the coasts of Valentia to a little below the mouth of the Duro. The country north of this belonged to the Chriſtians, who, as yet, had the ſmalleſt and leaſt valuable ſhare, and all the rest to the Moors. In point of wealth and real power, both by land and ſea, the Moors were greatly ſuperior ; but their continual diſſenſions greatly weakened them, and every day facilitated the progreſs of the Chriſtians. Indeed, had either of the parties been united, the other muſt ſoon have yielded ; for though the Chriſtians did not make war</p><p>upon each other conſtantly as the Moors did, them mutual feuds were yet sufficient to have ruined them, had their adverſaries made the leaſt uſe of the advantages thus afforded them. But among the Moors almoſt every city was a kingdom ; and as theſe petty ſovereignties ſupported one another very indifferently, they fell a prey one after another to their enemies. In 1080, the king of Toledo was engaged in a war with the king of Seville, another Mooriſh potentate ; which being obſerved by Alphonſo king of Caſtile, he alſo invaded his territories ; and in four years made himſelf master of the city of Toledo, with all the places of importance in its neighbourhood ; from thenceforth making Toledo the capital of his dominions. In a ſhort time the whole province of New Caſtile ſubmitted ; aud Madrid, the preſent capital of Spain, fell into the hands of the Chriſtians, being at that time but a ſmall place.</p><p>The Moors were ſo much alarmed at theſe conqueſts, that they not only entered into a general confederacy againſt the Chriſtiasis, but invited to their aſſiſtance Mahomet Ben Joſeph the ſovereign of Barbary. He accordingly came, attended by an incredible multitude ; but was utterly defeated by the Chriſtians in the defiles of the Black Mountain, or Sierra Morena, on the borders of Andaluſta. This victory happened on the 16th of July 1212, and the anniverſary is ſtill celebrated at Toledo. This victory was not improved; the Chriſtian army immediately diſperſed themſelves, while the Moors of Andaluſia were ſtrengthened by the remains of the African army ; yet, inſtead of being taught, by their paſt misfortunes, to unite among themſelves, their dissenſions became worſe than ever, and the conqueſts of the Chriſtians became daily more rapid. In 1230, Don Ferdinand of Caſtile and Leon took the celebrated city of Cordova, the residence of the firſt Mooriſh kings ; at the same time that James I. of Arragon diſposſessed them of the iland of Majorca, and drove them out of Valentia. Two years after, Ferdinand made himſelf maſter of Murcia, and took the city of Seville ; and in 1303 Ferdinand IV. reduced Gibraltar.</p><p>In the time of Edward III. we find England, for the firſt time, interfering in the affairs of Spain, on the following occasion. In the year 1284 the kingdom of Navarre had been united to that of France by the marriage of Donna Joanna queen of Navarre with Philip the Fair of France. In 1328, however, the kingdoms were again ſeparated, though the ſovereigns of Navarre were ſtill related to thoſe of France. In 1350, Charles, ſurnamed the <hi rend="italic">Wicked,</hi> aſcended the throne of Navarre, and married the daughter of John king of France. Notwithſtanding this alliance, and that he himſelf was related to the royal family of France, he ſecretly entered into a negociation with England againſt the French monarch, and even drew into his ſchemes the dauphin Charles, afterwards ſurnamed <hi rend="italic">the Wife.</hi> The young prince, however, was ſoon after made fully ſenſible of the danger and folly of the connections into which he had entered ; and, by way of atonement, promised to ſacriſice his associates. Accordingly he invited the king of Navarre, and ſome of the principal nobility of the ſame party, to a feaſt at Rouen, where he betrayed them to his father. The moſt obnoxious were executed, and the king of Navarre was thrown into priſon. In this extremity, the party of the king of Navarre had recourſe to England. The prince of Wales, ſurnamed<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0632.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0626"/>
<hi rend="italic">the Black Prince,</hi> invaded France, defeated king John at Poictiers, and took him priſoner<note anchored="true" n="1" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>* See France n⁰ 44.</p></note> *; which unfortunate event produced the moſt violent diſturbances in that kingdom. The dauphin, now about 19 years of age, naturally aſſumed the royal power during his father’s captivity : but poſſeſſed neither experience nor authority ſufficient to remedy the prevailing evils. In order to obtain ſupplies, he aſſembled the ſtates of the kingdom : but that aſſembly, inſtead of ſupporting his adminiſtration, laid hold of the preſent opportunity to demand limitations of the prince’s power, the puniſhment of paſt malverſations, and the liberty of the king of Navarre. Marcel, provoſt of the merchants of Paris, and firſt magiſtrate of that city, put himſelf at the head of the unruly populace, and puſhed them to commit the moſt criminal outrages againſt the royal authority. They detained the dauphin in a kind of captivity, murdered in his preſence Robert de Clermont and John de Conflans, mareſchals of France ; threatened all the other miniſters with the like fate ; and when Charles, who had been obliged to temporize and diſſemble, made his eſcape from their hands, they levied war againſt him, and openly rebelled. The other cities of the kingdom, in imitation of the capital, ſhook off the dauphin’s authority, took the government into their own hands, and ſpread the contagion into every province.</p><p>Amidſt theſe diſorders, the king of Navarre made his eſcape from priſon, and preſented a dangerous leader to the furious malecontents. He revived his pretenſions to the crown of France : but in all his operations he acted more like a leader of banditti than one who aſpired to be the head of a regular government, and who was engaged by his ſtation to endeavour the reeſtabliſhment of order in the community. All the French, therefore, who wished to reſtore peace to their country, turned their eyes towards the dauphin ; who, though not remarkable for his military talents, daily gained by his prudence and vigilance the aſcendant over his enemies. Marcel, the ſeditious provoſt of Paris, was ſlain in attempting to deliver that city to the king of Navarre. The capital immediately returned to its duty : the moſt conſiderable bodies of the mutinous peaſants were diſperſed or put to the ſword ; ſome bands of military robbers underwent the ſame fate ; and France began once more to aſſume the appearance of civil government.</p><p>John was ſucceeded in the throne of France by his ſon Charles V. a prince educated in the ſchool of adverſity, and well qualified, by his prudence and experience, to repair the loſſes which the kingdom had ſuſtained from the errors of his predeceſſors. Contrary to the practice of all the great princes of thoſe times, who held nothing in eſtimation but military courage, he ſeems to have laid it down as a maxim, never to appear at the head of his armies ; and he was the firſt European monarch that ſhowed the advantage of policy and foresight over a raſh and precipitate valour.</p><p>Before Charles could think of counterbalancing ſo great a power as England, it was neceſſary for him to remedy the many diſorders to which his own kingdom was expoſed. He accordingly turned his arms againſt the king oſ Navarre, the great diſturber of France during that age ; and he defeated that prince, and reduced him to terms, by the valour and conduct of Bertrand du Gueſclin, one of the moſt accompliſhed cap</p><p>tains of thoſe times, whom Charles had the diſcernment to chooſe as the inſtrument of his victories. He alſo ſettled the affairs of Brittany, by acknowledging the title of Mountfort, and receiving homage for his dominions. But much was yet to be done. On the concluſion of the peace of Bretigni, the many military adventurers who had followed the fortunes of Edward, being diſperſed into the ſeveral provinces, and poſſeſſed of ſtrongholds, refuſed to lay down their arms, or relinquiſh a courſe oſ life to which they were now accuſtomed, and by which alone they could earn a ſubſiſtence. They aſſociated themſelves with the banditti, who were already inured to the habits of rapine and violence ; and, under the name of <hi rend="italic">companies</hi> and <hi rend="italic">companions,</hi> became a terror to all the peaceable inhabitants. Some Engliſh and Gaſcon gentlemen of character were not aſhamed to take the command of theſe ruffians, whoſe number amounted to near 40,000, and who bore the appearance of regular armies rather than bands of robbers. As Charles was not able by power to redreſs ſo enormous a grievance, he was led by neceſſity, as well as by the turn of his character, to correct it by policy; to diſcover ſome method of diſcharging into foreign countries this dangerous and inteſtine evil ; and an occasion now offered.</p><p>Alphonſo XI. king oſ Caſtile, who took the city of Algezira from the Moors, after a famous ſiege of two years, during which artillery are ſaid firſt to have been uſed by the beſieged, had been ſucceeded by his ſon Peter I. ſurnamed <hi rend="italic">the Cruel;</hi> a prince equally persidious, debauched, and bloody. He began his reign with the murder of his father’s miſtreſs Leonora de Guſman: his nobles fell every day the victims of his ſeverity : he put to death his couſin and one of his natural brothers, from groundleſs jealouſy ; and he cauſed his queen Blanche de Bourbon, of the blood of France, to be thrown into priſon, and afterwards poiſoned, that he might enjoy in quiet the embraces oſ Mary de Radella, with whom he was violently enamoured.</p><p>Henry count of Traſtamara, the king’s natural brother, alarmed at the fate of his family, and dreading his own, took arms againſt the tyrant ; but having failed in the attempt, he fled to France, where he found the minds of men much inflamed againſt Peter, on account of the murder of the French princeſs. He aſked permiſſion of Charles to enliſt the <hi rend="italic">companies</hi> in his ſervice, and to lead them into Caſtile againſt his brother. The French king, charmed with the project, employed du Gueſclin in negociating with the leaders of theſe banditti. The treaty was ſoon concluded ; and du Gueſclin having completed his levies, led the army firſt to Avignon, where the Pope then reſided, and demanded, ſword in hand, abſolution for his ruffian ſoldiers, who had been excommunicated, and the ſum of 200,000 livres for their ſubſiſtence. The firſt was readily promiſed him ; but ſome difficulty being made with regard to the ſecond, du Gueſclin replied, “ My fellows, I believe, may make a ſhift to do without your abſolution, but the money is abſolutely neceſſary.” His Holineſs then extorted from the inhabitants of the city and its neighbourhood the ſum of 100,000 livres, and offered it to du Gueſclin: “ It is not my purpoſe (cried that generous warrior ) to oppreſs the innocent people.” The pope and his cardinals can ſpare me double the ſum from their own pockets. I therefore insist, that<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0633.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0627"/>
this money be reſtored to the owners ; and if I hear they are defrauded of it, I will myſelf return from the other side of the Pyrenees, and oblige you to make them reſtitution.” The pope found the neceſſity of ſubmitting, and paid from his own treaſury the ſum demanded.</p><p>A body of experienced and hardy ſoldiers, conducted by ſo able a general, eaſily prevailed over the king of Caſtile, whole ſubjects were ready to join the enemy againſt their oppreſſor. Peter fled from his dominions, took ſhelter in Guſenne, and craved the protection of the prince of Wales, whom his father had inveſted with the ſovereignty of the ceded provinces, under the title of the <hi rend="italic">principality of Aquitaine.</hi> The prince promiſed his aſſiſtance to the dethroned monarch ; and having obtained his father’s conſent, he levied an army, and ſet out on his enterpriſe.</p><p>The firſt loſs which Henry of Traſtamara ſuffered from the interpoſition of the prince of Wales, was the recalling of the companies from his ſervice; and ſo much reverence did they pay to the name of Edward, that great numbers of them immediately withdrew from Spain, and insiſted under his ſtandard. Henry, however, beloved by his new ſubjects, and ſupported by the king of Arragon, was able to meet the enemy with an army of 100,000 men, three times the number of thoſe commanded by the Black Prince : yet du Gueſclin, and all his experienced officers, adviſed him to delay a deciſive action ; ſo high was their opinion of the valour and conduct of the Engliſh hero ! But Henry, truſting to his numbers, ventured to give Edward battle on the banks of the Ebro, between Najara and Navarette ; where the French and Spaniards were defeated, with the loſs of above 20,000 men, and du Gueſclin and other officers of diſtinction taken priſoners. All Caſtile ſubmitted to the victor ; Peter was reſtored to the throne, and Edward returned to Guienne with his uſual glory ; having not only overcome the greateſt general of his age, but reſtrained the moſt blood-thirſty tyrant from executing vengeance on his priſoners.</p><p>This gallant warrior had ſoon reaſon to repent of his connections with a man like Peter, loſt to all ſenſe of virtue and honour. The ungrateful monſter refuſed the ſtipulated pay to the Engliſh forces. Edward abandoned him : he treated his ſubjects with the utmoſt barbarity ; their animoſity was rouſed againſt him ; and du Gueſclin having obtained his ranſom, returned to Caſtile with the count of Traſtamara, and ſome forces levied anew in France. They were joined by the Spaniſh malecontents ; and having no longer the Black Prince to encounter, they gained a complete victory over Peter in the neighbourhood of Toledo. The tyrant now took refuge in a caſtle, where he was ſoon after beſieged by the victors, and taken priſoner in endeavouring to make his eſcape. He was conducted to his brother Henry ; again it whom he is ſaid to have ruſhed in a tranſport of rage, diſarmed as he was. Henry slew him with his own hand, in reſentment of his cruelties ; and, though a baſtard, was placed on the throne of Caſtile, which he tranfmitted to his poſterity.</p><p>After the death of Peter the Cruel, nothing remarkable happened in Spain for almoſt a whole century; but the debaucheries of Henry IV. of Caſtile rouſed the reſentment of his nobles, and produced a moſt ſingular inſurrection, which led to the aggrandizement of the Spaniſh monarchy.</p><p>This prince, ſurnamed the <hi rend="italic">Impotent,</hi> though continually ſurrounded with women, began his unhappy reign in 1454. He was totally enervated by his pleaſures ; and every thing in his court conſpired to ſet the Caſtilians an example of the moſt abject flattery and moſt abandoned licentiouſneſs. The queen, a daughter of Portugal, lived as openly with her paraſites and her gallants as the king did with his minions and his miſtreſſes. Pleaſure was the only object, and effeminacy the only recommendation to favour : the affairs of the ſtate went every day into diſorder ; till the nobility, with the archbiſhop of Toledo at their head, combining againſt the weak and flagitious adminiſtration of Henry, arrogated to themſelves, as one of the privileges of their order, the right of trying and paſſing ſentence on their ſovereign, which they executed in a manner unprecedented in hiſtory.</p><p>All the malecontent nobility were ſummoned to meet at Avila : a ſpacious theatre was erected in a plain without the walls of the town : an image, repreſenting the king, was ſeated on a throne, clad in royal robes, with a crown on its head, a ſceptre in its hand, and the ſword of juſtice by its side. The accuſation againſt Henry was read, and the ſentence of depoſition pronounced, in preſence of a numerous aſſembly. At the cloſe of the firſt article of the charge, the archbiſhop of Toledo advanced, and tore the crown from the head of the image ; at the cloſe of the ſecond, the Conde de Placentia ſnatched the ſword of juſtice from its side; at the cloſe of the third, the Conde de Benavente wreſted the ſceptre from its hand ; and at the cloſe of the laſt, Don Diego Lopez de Stuniga tumbled it headlong from the throne. At the ſame instant, Don Alphonſo, Henry’s brother, a boy of about twelve years of age, was proclaimed king of Caſtile and Leon in his ſtead.</p><p>This extraordinary proceeding was followed by a civil war, which did not ceaſe till ſome time after the death of the young prince, on whom the nobles had beſtowed the kingdom. The archbiſhop and his party then continued to carry on war in the name of Iſabella the king’s ſiſter, to whom they gave the title of <hi rend="italic">Infanta ;</hi> and Henry could not extricate himſelf out of theſe troubles, nor remain quiet upon his throne till he had ſigned one of the moſt humiliating treaties ever extorted from a ſovereign ; he acknowledged his ſiſter Iſabella the only lawful heireſs of his kingdom, in prejudice to the rights of his reputed daughter Joan, whom the malecontents affirmed to be the offspring of an adulterous commerce between the queen and Don la Cueva. The grand object of the malecontent party now was the marriage of the princeſs Iſabella, upon which, it was evident, the ſecurity of the crown and the happineſs of the people muſt in a great meaſure depend. The alliance was ſought by ſeveral princes : the king of Portugal offered her his hand ; the king of France demanded her for his brother, and the king of Arragon for his ſon Ferdinand. The malecontents very wiſely preferred the Arragonian prince, and Iſabella prudently made the ſame choice; articles were drawn up ; and they were privately married by the archbiſhop of Toledo.<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0634.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0628"/>
Henry was enraged at tins alliance, which he foreſaw would utterly ruin his authority, by furniſhing his rebellious ſubjects with the ſupport of a powerful neighbouring prince. He diſinherited his sister, and eſtabliſhed the rights of his daughter. A furious civil war deſolated the kingdom. The names of Joan and Iſabella reſounded from every quarter, and were everywhere the ſummons to arms. But peace was at length brought about. Henry was reconciled to his ſiſter and Ferdinand ; though it does not appear that he ever renewed Iſabella’s right to the ſucceſſion : for he affirmed in his laſt moments, that he believed Joan to be his own daughter. The queen ſwore to the ſame effect ; and Henry left a teſtamentary deed, tranſmitting the crown to this princeſs, who was proclaimed queen of Caſtile at Placentia. But the ſuperior fortune and ſuperior arms of Ferdinand and Iſabella prevailed : the king of Portugal was obliged to abandon his niece and intended bride, after many ineffectual ſtruggles, and ſeveral years of war. Joan retired into a convent ; and the death of Ferdinand’s father, which happened about this time, added the kingdoms of Arragon and Sicily to thoſe of Leon and Caſtile.</p><p>Ferdinand and Iſabella were perſons of great prudence, and, as Sovereigns, highly worthy of imitation: but they do not ſeem to have merited all the praiſes beſtowed upon them by the Spaniſh hiſtorians. They did not live like man and wife, having all things in common under the direction of the husband ; but like two princes in cloſe alliance ; they neither loved nor hated each other ; were ſeldom in company together ; had each a ſeparate council; and were frequently jealous of one another in the adminiſtration. But they were inſeparably united in their common intereſts ; always acting upon the same principles, and forwarding the ſame ends. Their firſt object was the regulation of their government, which the civil wars had thrown into the greateſt diſorder. Rapine, outrage, and murder, were become ſo common, as not only to interrupt commerce, but in a great meaſure to ſuſpend all intercourſe between one place and another. Theſe evils the joint ſovereigns ſuppreſſed by their wiſe policy, at the ſame time that they extended the royal prerogative.</p><p>About the middle of the 13th century, the cities in the kingdom of Arragon, and after their example thoſe in Caſtile, had formed themſelves into an association, diſtinguiſhed by the name of the <hi rend="italic">Holy Brotherhood.</hi> They exacted a certain contribution from each of the aſſociated towns ; they levied a conſiderable body of troops, in order to protect travellers and purſue criminals ; and they appointed judges, who opened courts in various parts of the kingdom. Whoever was guilty of murder, robbery, or any act that violated the public peace, and was ſeized by the troops of the Brotherhood, was carried before their judges ; who, without paying any regard to the exclusive juriſdiction which the lord of the place might claim, who was generally the author or abettor of the injuſtice, tried and condemned the criminals. The nobles often murmured againſt this ſalutary institution ; they complained of it as an encroachment on one of their moſt valuable privileges, and endeavoured to get it aboliſhed. But Ferdinand and Iſabella, ſenſible of the beneficial effects of the Brotherhood, not only in regard to the police of their kingdom, but in its tendency to abridge, and by de</p><p>grees annihilate, the territorial juriſdiction oſ the nobility, countenanccd the inſtitution upon every occaſion, and ſupported it with the whole force of royal authority ; by which means the prompt and impartial adminiſtration of juſtice was reſtored, and with it tranquillity and order returned.</p><p>But at the ſame time that their Catholic majeſties (for ſuch was the title they now bore) were giving vigour to their civil government, and ſecuring their ſubjects ſrom violence and oppression, an intemperate zeal led them to eſtabliſh an eccleſiaſtical tribunal, equally contrary to the natural rights of humanity and the mild ſpirit of the goſpel. This was the court of inquiſition; which decides upon the honour, fortune, and even the line, of the unhappy wretch who happens to fall under the ſuſpicion of hereſy, or a contempt of any thing preſcribed by the church, without his knowing, being confronted with his accusers, or permitted either defence or appeal. Six thouſand perſons were burnt by order of this ſanguinary tribunal within four years after the appointment of Torquemada, the firſt inquiſitor-general ; and upwards of 100,000 felt its fury. The ſame furious and blinded zeal which led to the depopulation of Spain, led also to its aggrandizement.</p><p>The kingdom of Granada now alone remained of all the Mahometan poſſeſſions in Spain. Princes equally zealous and ambitious were naturally diſpoſed to turn their eyes to that fertile territory, and to think of increaſing their hereditary dominions, by expelling the enemies of Chriſtianity, and extending its doctrines. Everything conſpired to favour their project : the Mooriſh kingdom was a prey to civil wars ; when Ferdinand, having obtained the bull of Sixtus IV. authorizing a cruſade, put himſelf at the head of his troops, and entered Granada. He continued the war with rapid ſucceſs: Isabella attended him in ſeveral expeditions ; and they were both in great danger at the ſiege of Malaga ; an important city, which was defended with great courage, and taken in 1487. Baza was reduced in 1489, alter the loss of 20,000 men. Guadix and Almeria were delivered up to them by the Mooriſh king Alzagel, who had firſt dethroned his brother Alboacen, and afterwards been chafed from his capital by his nephew Abdali. That prince engaged in the ſervice of Ferdinand and Iſabella ; who, after reducing every other place of eminence, undertook the ſiege of Granada. Abdali made a gallant defence ; but all communication with the country being cut off, and all hopes of relief at an end, he capitulated, after a ſiege of eight months, on condition that he ſhould enjoy the revenue of certain places in the fertile mountains of Alpujarros; that the inhabitants ſhould retain the undisturbed poſſeſſion of their houſes, goods, and inheritances; the uſe of their laws, and the free exerciſe of their religion. Thus ended the empire of the Arabs in Spain, after it had continued about 800 years. They introduced the arts and ſciences into Europe at a time when it was loſt in darkneſs ; they poſſeſſed many of the luxuries of life, when' they were not even known among the neighbouring nations ; and they ſeem to have given birth to that romantic gallantry which ſo eminently prevailed in the ages of chivalry, and which, blending itſelf with the veneration of the northern nations for the ſofter sex, ſtill particularly diſtinguiſhes ancient from modern man-<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0635.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0629"/>
uers, But the Moors, notwithſtanding theſe advantages, and the eulogies beſtowed upon them by ſome writers, appear always to have been deſtitute of the esſential qualities of a poliſhed people, humanity, generoſity, and mutual ſympathy.</p><p>The conqueſt of Granada was followed by the expulsion, or rather the pillage and baniſhment, of the Jews, who had engroſſed all the wealth and commerce of Spain. The inquiſition exhauſted its rage againſt theſe unhappy people, many of whom pretended to embrace Chriſtianity, in order to preſerve their property. About the ſame time their Catholic majesties concluded art alliance with the emperor Maximilian, and a treaty of marriage for their daughter Joan with his ſon Philip, archduke of Auſtria and ſovereign of the Netherlands. About this time alſo the contract was concluded with Chriſtopher Columbus for the diſcovery of new countries ; and the counties oſ Rouſſillon and Cerdagne were agreed to be reſtored by Charles VIII. of France, before his expedition into Italy. The diſcovery of America was ſoon followed by extenſive conqueſts in that quarter, as is related under the articled <hi rend="smallcaps">Mexico, Peru, Chili, &amp; c.</hi> which tended to raiſe the Spaniſh monarchy above any other in Europe.</p><p>On the death of Iſabella, which happened in 1506, Philip archduke of Auſtria came to Castile in order to take poſſession of that kingdom as heir to his mother- in law ; but he dying in a ſhort time after, his ſon Charles V. afterwards emperor oſ Germany, became heir to the crown of Spain. His father at his death left the king of France governor to the young prince, and Ferdinand at his death left cardinal Ximenes ſole regent of Gaſtile, till the arrival of his grandson. This man, whoſe character is no leſs ſingular than illuſtrious, who united the abilities of a great ſtateſman with the abject devotion of a ſuperſtitious monk, and the magnificence of a prime miniſter with the ſeverity of a mendicant, maintained order and tranquillity in Spain, notwithſtanding the diſcontents of a turbulent and high- ſpirited nobility. When they diſputed his right to the regency, he coolly ſhowed them the teſtament of Ferdinand, and the ratification of that deed by Charles ; but theſe not ſatisfying them, and argument proving ineffectual, he led them inſenſibly towards a balcony, whence they had a view oſ a large body of troops under arms, and a formidable train of artillery, "Behold (ſaid the cardinal) the powers which I have received from his Catholic majesty : by theſe I govern Castile; and will govern it, till the king, your maſter and mine, ſhall come to take poſſeſſion of his kingdom.” A declaration ſo bold and determined ſilenced all oppoſition; and Ximenes maintained his authority till the arrival of Charles in 517.</p><p>The young king was received with univerſal acclamations of joy ; but Ximenes found little cauſe to rejoice. He was ſeized with a violent diſorder, ſuppoſed to be the effect of poiſon ; and when he recovered, Charles, prejudiced againſt him by the Spaniſh grandees and his Flemiſh courtiers, slighted his advice, and allowed him every day to sink into neglect. The cardinal did not bear this treatment with his uſual fortitude of ſpirit. He expected a more grateful return from a prince to whom he delivered a kingdom more flouriſhing than it had been in any former age, and authority more extensive and better eſtabliſhed than the moſt illuſtrious of his</p><p>anceſtors had ever poſſeſſed. Conſcious of his own integrity and merit, he could not therefore refrain from giving vent, at times, to indignation and complaint. He lamented the fate of his country, and foretold the calamities to which it would be expoſed from the inſolence, the rapaciouſneſs, and the ignorance of ſtrangers. But in the mean time he received a letter from the king, diſmissing him from his councils, under pretence of eaſing his age of that burden which he had ſo long and ſo ably ſuſtained. This letter proved fatal to the miniſter ; for he expired in a few hours after reading it.</p><p>While Charles was taking poſſeſſion of the throne of Spain, in conſequence of the death of one grandfather, another was endeavouring to obtain for him the imperial crown. With this view Maximilian aſſembled a diet at Augſhurg, where he cultivated the favour of the electors by many acts of beneficence, in order to engage them to chooſe that young prince as his ſucceſſor. But Maximilian himſelf never having been crowned by the pope, a ceremony deemed eſſential in that age, as well as in the preceding, he was conſidered only as king of the Romans, or emperor elect ; and no example occurring in hiſtory of any perſon being choſen ſucceſſor to a king of the Romans, the Germans, always tenacious of their forms, obſtinately refused to confer upon Charles a dignity for which their conſtitution knew no name.</p><p>But though Maximilian could not prevail upon the German electors to chooſe his grandſon of Spain king of the Romans, he had diſpoſed their minds in favour of that prince ; and other circumſtances, on the death of the emperor, conſpired to the exaltation of Charles. The imperial crown had ſo long continued in the Auſtrian line, that it began to be conſidered as hereditary in that ſamily ; and Germany, torn by religious diſputes, ſtood in need of a powerful emperor, not only to preſerve its own internal tranquillity, but alſo to protect it againſt the victorious arms of the Turks, who under Selim I. threatened the liberties of Europe. This fierce and rapid conqueror had already ſubdued the Mamalukes, and made himſelf maſter of Egypt and Syria. The power of Charles appeared neceſſary to oppoſe that of Selim. The extenſive dominions of the houſe of Auſtria, which gave him an intereſt in the preſervation of Germany ; the rich ſovereignty of the Netherlands and Franche Compte ; the entire poſſeſſion of the great and warlike kingdom of Spain, together with that of Naples and Sicily, all united to hold him up to the firſt dignity among Chriſtian princes ; and the new world ſeemed only to be called into exiſtence that its treaſures might enable him to defend Chriſtendom againſt the infidels. Such was the language of his partisans.</p><p>Francis I. however, no ſooner received intelligence of the death of Maximilian, than he declared himſelf a candidate for the empire ; and with no leſs confidence of ſucceſs than Charles. He truſted to his ſuperior years and experience ; his great reputation in arms ; and it was farther urged in his favour, that the impetuoſity oſ the French cavalry, added to the firmness of the German infantry, would prove irreſiſtible, and not only be ſufficient, under a warlike emperor, to ſet limits to the ambition of Selim, but to break entirely the Ottoman power, and prevent it from ever becoming dangerous again to Germany.</p><p>Both claims were plauſible. The dominions of Fran-<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0636.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0630"/>
cis were leſs extenſive, but more united than thoſe of Charles. His ſubjects were numerous, active, brave, lovers of glory, and lovers of their king. Theſe were ſtrong arguments in favour of his power, ſo neceſſary at this juncture : but he had no natural intereſt in the Germanic body; and the electors, hearing ſo much of military force on each side, became more alarmed for their own privileges than the common ſafety. They determined to reject both candidates, and offered the imperial crown to Frederic, ſurnamed the <hi rend="italic">Wife,</hi> duke of Saxony. Rut he, undazzled by the ſplendour of an object courted with ſo much eagerneſs by two mighty monarchs, rejected it with a magnanimity no leſs lingular than great.</p><p>“ In times of tranquillity (ſaid Frederic), we wiſh for an emperor who has no power to invade our liberties ; times of danger demand one who is able to ſecure our ſafety. The Turkiſh armies, led by a warlike and victorious monarch, are now aſſembling: they are ready to pour in upon Germany with a violence unknown in former ages. New conjunctures call for new expedients. The imperial ſceptre muſt be committed to ſome hand more powerful than mine or that of any other German prince. We poſſeſs neither dominions, nor revenues, nor authority, which enable us to encounter ſuch a formidable enemy. Recourſe muſt be had, in this exigency, to one of the rival monarchs. Each of them can bring into the field forces sufficient for our defence. But as the king of Spain is of German extraction, as he is a member and prince of the empire by the territories which deſcend to him from his grandfather, and as his dominions ſtretch along that frontier which lies moſt exposed to the enemy, his claim, in my opinion, is preferable to that of a ſtranger to our language, to our blood, and to our country.” Charles was elected in conſequence of this ſpeech in the year 1520.</p><p>The two candidates had hitherto conducted their rivalſhip with emulation, but without enmity. They had even mingled in their competition many expreſſions of friendſhip and regard. Francis in particular declared with his uſual vivacity, that his brother Charles and he were fairly and openly ſuitors to the ſame miſtreſs : “ The moſt aſſiduous and fortunate (added he) will win her; and the other muſt reſt contented.” But the preference was no ſooner given to his rival, than Francis diſcovered all the paſſions natural to diſappointed ambition. He could not ſuppreſs his chagrin and indignation at being baulked in his favourite purſuit, and rejected, in the face of all Europe, for a youth yet unknown to fame. The ſpirit of Charles reſented ſuch contempt ; and from this jealouſy, as much as from oppoſition of intereſts, aroſe that emulation between thoſe two great monarchs which involved them in almoſt perpetual hostilities, and kept their whole age in movement.</p><p>Charles and Francis had many interfering claims in Italy ; and the latter thought himſelf bound in honour to reſtore the king of Navarre to his dominions, unjuſtly ſeized by the crown of Spain. They immediately began to negotiate ; and as Henry VIII. of England was the third prince of the age in power and in dignity, his friendſhip was eagerly courted by each of the rivals. He was the natural guardian of the liberties of Europe. Senſible of the conſequence which his ſituation gave him, and proud of his pre-eminence, Henry knew it to</p><p>be his intereſt to keep the balance even between the contending powers, and to reſtrain both, by not joining entirely with either ; but he was ſeldom able to reduce his ideas to practice. Vanity and reſentment were the great ſprings of all his undertakings ; and his neighbours, by touching theſe, found an eaſy way to draw him into their meaſures, and force him upon many raſh and inconſiderate enterpriſes.</p><p>All the impolitic ſteps in Henry’s government muſt not, however, be imputed to himſelf ; many of them were occaſioned by the ambition and avarice of his prime miniſter and favourite cardinal Wolſey. This man, who, by his talents and accompliſhments, had riſen from one of the loweſt conditions in life to the higheſt employments both in church and ſtate, enjoyed a greater degree of power and dignity than any Engliſh ſubject ever poſſeſſed, and governed the haughty, preſumptuous, and untractable ſpirit of Henry, with abſolute authority. Francis was equally well acquainted with the character of Henry and of his miniſter. He had ſucceſsfully flattered Wolſey’s pride, by honouring him with particular marks of his confidence, and beſtowing upon him the appellation of <hi rend="italic">Father, Tutor,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Governor ;</hi> and he had obtained the reſtitution of Tournay, by adding a penſion to thoſe reſpectful titles. He now ſolicited an interview with the king of England near: Calais; in hopes of being able, by familiar converſation, to attach him to his friendſhip and intereſt, while he gratified the cardinal’s vanity, by affording him an opportunity of diſplaying his magnificence in the preſence of two courts, and of diſcovering to the two nations his influence over their monarchs. Charles dreaded the effects of this projected interview between two gallant princes, whoſe hearts were no leſs ſuſceptible of friendſhip than their manners were of inſpiring it. Finding it impoſſible, however, to prevent a viſit, in which the vanity of all parties was ſo much concerned, he endeavoured to defeat its purpoſe, and to pre-occupy the favour of the Engliſh monarch, and of his miniſter, by an act of complaiſance ſtill more flattering and more uncommon. Relying wholly upon Henry’s generoſity for his ſafety, he landed at Dover, in his way from Spain to the Low Countries. The king of England, who was on his way to France, charmed with ſuch an inſtance of confidence, haſtened to receive his royal gueſt; and Charles, during his ſhort stay, had the addreſs not only to give Henry favourable impreſſions of his Character and intentions, but to detach Wolſey entirely from the intereſt of Francis. The tiara had attracted the eye of that ambitious prelate ; and as the emperor knew that the papacy was the ſole point of elevation, beyond his preſent greatneſs, at which he could aſpire, he made him an offer of his intereſt on the firſt vacancy.</p><p>The,day of Charles’s departure, Henry went over to Calais with his whole court, in order to meet Francis. Their interview was in an open plain between Guiſnes and Ardres ; where the two kings and their attendants diſplayed their magnificence with ſuch emulation and profuſe expence, as procured it the name of the <hi rend="italic">Field of the Cloth of Gold.</hi> Here Henry erected a ſpacious houſe of wood and canvas, framed in London, on which, under the figure of an Engliſh archer, was the following motto : “ He prevails whom I favour ;” alluding to his own political ſituation, as holding in his<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0637.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0631"/>
bands the balance of power among the potentates of Europe. Feats of chivalry however, parties of gallantry, and ſuch exerciſes as were in that age reckoned manly or elegant, rather than ſerious buſineſs, occupied the two courts during the time that they continued together, which was 18 days.</p><p>After taking leave of this ſcene of diſſipation, the king of England paid a viſit to the emperor and Margaret of Savoy at Gravelines, and engaged them to go along with him to Calais; where the artful and politic Charles completed the impreſſion which he had begun to make on Henry and his favourite, and effaced all the friendſhip to which the frank and generous nature of Francis had given birth. He renewed his aſſurances of aſſiſting Wolſey in obtaining the papacy ; and he put him in preſent poſſeſſion of the revenues belonging to the ſees oſ Badajox and Palencia in Spain. He flattered Henry’s pride, by convincing him of his own importance, and oſ the juſtneſs of the motto which he had choſen ; offering to ſubmit to his ſole arbitration any difference that might ariſe between him and Francis.</p><p>This important point being ſecured, Charles repaired to Aix-la-Chapelle, where he was ſolemnly inveſted with the crown and ſceptre of Charlemagne, in preſence of a more ſplendid and numerous aſſembly than had appeared on any former inauguration. About the ſame time Solyman the Magnificent, one of the moſt accompliſhed, enterpriſing, and victorious of the Turkiſh princes, and a conſtant and formidable rival to the emperor, aſcended the Ottoman throne.</p><p>The firſt act oſ Charles’s adminiſtration was to appoint a diet of the empire, to be held at Worms, in order to concert with the princes proper meaſures for checking the progreſs of “ thoſe new and dangerous opinions which threatened to diſturb the peace of Germany, and to overturn the religion of their anceſtors.” The opinions propagated by Luther and his followers were here meant. But all his efforts for that purpoſe were insufficient, as is related under the articles <hi rend="smallcaps">Luther</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Reformation,</hi></p><p>In 1521, the Spaniards, diſſatisſied with the departure of their ſovereign, whoſe election to the empire they foreſaw would interfere with the adminiſtration of his own kingdom, and incenſed at the avarice of the Flemings, to whom the direction of public affairs had been committed ſince the death of cardinal Ximenes, ſeveral grandees, in order to ſhake off this oppreſſion, entered into an aſſociation, to which they gave the name oſ the <hi rend="italic">Sancta Juncta ;</hi> and the ſword was appealed to as the means of redreſs. This ſeemed to Francis a favourable juncture for reinſtating the family of John d’Albert in the kingdom of Navarre. Charles was at a diſtance ſrom that part of his dominions, and the troops uſually ſtationed there had been called away to quell the commotions in Spain. A French army, under Andrew de Foix, ſpeedily conquered Navarre ; but that young and inexperienced nobleman, puſhed on by military ardour, ventured to enter Caſtile. The Spaniards, though divided among themſelves, united againſt a foreign enemy, routed his forces, took him prisoner, and recovered Navarre in a ſhorter time than he had ſpent in ſubduing it.</p><p>Hoſtilities thus begun in one quarter, between the rival monarchs, ſoon ſpread to another. The king of France encouraged the duke of Bouillon to make war</p><p>againſt the emperor, and to invade Luxembourg. Charles, after humbling the duke, attempted to enter France ; but was repelled and worſted before Mezieres by the famous chevalier Bayard, diſtinguifhed among his cotemporaries by the appellation of <hi rend="italic">The Knight without fear and without reproach ;</hi> and who united the talents of a great general to the punctilious honour and romantic gallantry of the heroes of chivalry. Francis broke into the Low Countries, where, by an exceſs of caution, an error not natural to him, he loſt an opportunity of cutting off the whole imperial army; and, what was of still more conſequence, he diſguſted the conſtable Bourbon,· by giving the command of the van to the duke of Alençon.</p><p>During theſe operations in the field, an unſucceſsful congreſs was held at Calais, under the mediation of Henry VIII. It ſerved only to exaſperate the parties which it was intended to reconcile. A league was ſoon after concluded, by the intrigues of Wolſey, between the pope, Henry, and Charles, againſt France. Leo had already entered into a ſeparate league with the emperor, and the French were faſt loſing ground in Italy.</p><p>The inſolence and exactions of Mareſhal de Lautrec, governor of Milan, had totally alienated the affections of the Milaneſe from France. They reſolved to expel the troops of that nation, and put themſelves under the government of Francis Sforza, brother to Maximilian their late duke. In this reſolution, they were encouraged by the pope, who excommunicated Lautrec, and took into his pay a conſiderable body of Swiſs. The papal army, commanded by Proſper Colonna, an experienced general, was joined by ſupplies from Germany and Naples ; while Lautrec, neglected by his court, and deſerted by the Swiſs in its pay, was unable to make head againſt the enemy. The city of Milan was betrayed by the inhabitants to the confederates ; Parma and Placentia were united to the eccleſiaſtieal ſtate ; and of their conqueſts in Lombardy, only the town of Cremona, the caſtle of Milan, and a few inconſiderable forts, remained in the hands of the French.</p><p>Leo X. received the accounts of this rapid ſucceſs with ſuch tranſports of joy, as are ſaid to have brought on a fever, which occaſioned his death. The ſpirit of the confederacy was broken, and its operations ſuſpended by this accident. The Swiſs were recalled ; ſome other mercenaries diſhanded for want of pay ; and only the Spaniards, and a few Germans in the emperor’s ſervice, remained to defend the duchy of Milan. Bub Lautrec, who with the remnant of his army had taken ſhelter in the Venetian territories, deſtitute both of men and money, was unable to improve this favourable opportunity as he wiſhed. All his efforts were rendered ineffectual by the vigilance and ability of Colonna and his aſſociates.</p><p>Meantime much diſcord prevailed in the conclave, Wolſey’s name, notwithſtanding all the emperor’s magnificent promiſes, was ſcarcely mentioned there. Julio de Medici, Leo’s nephew, thought himſelf ſure of the election ; when, by an unexpected turn of fortune, cardinal Adrian of Utrecht, Charles’s preceptor, who at that time governed Spain in the emperor’s name, was unanimouſly raiſed to the papacy, to the aſtoniſhment of all Europe and the great diſguſt of the Italians.<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0638.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0632"/>
Francis, routed by the rising conſequence of his rival, reſolved to exert himſelf with freſh vigour, in order to wreſt ſrom him his late conqueſts in Lombardy. Lautrec received a ſupply of money, and a reinforcement of 10,000 Swiſs. With this reinforcement he was enabled once more to act offenſively, and even to advance within a few miles of the city of Milan ; wſhen money again failing him, and the Swiſs growing mutinous, he was obliged to attack the imperialiſts in their camp at Bicocca, where he was repulſed with great ſlaughter, having loſt his braveſt officers and beſt troops. Such of the Swiſs as ſurvived ſet out immediately for their own country; and Lautrec, deſpairing of being able to keep the field, retired into France. Genoa, which ſtill remained ſubject to Francis, and made it eaſy to execute any scheme for the recovery of Milan, was ſoon after taken by Colonna : the authority of the emperor and his faction was everywhere eſtabliſhed in Italy. The citadel of Cremona was the ſole fortreſs which remained in the hands of the French.</p><p>The affliction of Francis for ſuch a ſucceſſion of misfortunes was augmented by the unexpected arrival of an Engliſh herald, who in the name of his ſovereign declared war againſt France. The courage of this excellent prince, however, did not forſake him ; though his treaſury was exhauſted by expensive pleasures, no leſs than by hoſtile enterpriſes, he aſſembled a conſiderable army, and put his kingdom in a poſture of defence for refilling this new enemy, without abandoning any of the ſchemes which he was forming againſt the emperor. He was ſurpriſed, but not alarmed, at ſuch a denunciation.</p><p>Meanwhile Charles, willing to draw as much advantage as poſſible from ſo powerful an ally, paid a ſecond viſit to the court of England in his way to Spain, where his preſence was become neceſſary. His ſucceſs exceeded his moſt ſanguine expectations. He not only gained the entire friendſhip of Henry, who publicly ratified the treaty of Bruges ; but diſarmed the reſentment of Wolſey, by alluring him of the papacy on Adrian’s death ; an event ſeemingly not diſtant, by reaſon of his age and infirmities. In conſequence of theſe negociations an Engliſh army invaded France, under the command of the earl of Surrey ; who, at the end of the campaign, was obliged to retire, with his forces greatly reduced, without being able to make himſelf maſter of one place within the French frontier. Charles was more fortunate in Spain : he ſoon quelled the tumults which had there ariſen in his abſence.</p><p>While the Chriſtian princes were thus waſting each other’s ſtrength, Solyman the Magnificent entered Hungary, and made himſelf maſter of Belgrade, reckoned the chief barrier of that kingdom againſt the Turkiſh power. Encouraged by this ſucceſs, he turned his victorious arms againſt the iſland of Rhodes, at that time the seat of the knights of St John of Jeruſalem ; and though every prince in that age acknowledged Rhodes to be the great bulwark of Chriſtendom in the eaſt, ſo violent was their animoſity againſt each other, that they ſuffered Solyman without diſturbance to carry on his operations againſt that city and iſland. Liſle Adam, the grandmaſter, made a gallant defence ; but, after incredible efforts of courage, patience, and military conduct, during a ſiege of six months, he was obliged to ſurrender the place, having obtained an honourable ca</p><p>pitulation from the sultan, who admired and reſpected his heroic qualities (ſee <hi rend="smallcaps">Rhodes</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Malta).</hi> Charles and Francis were equally aſhamed of having occaſioned ſuch a loſs to Chriſtendom by their conteſts ; and the emperor, by way of reparation, granted to the knights of St John the ſmall iſland of Malta, where they fixed their reſidence, and continued long to retain their ancient ſpirit, though much diminiſhed in power and ſplendour.</p><p>Adrian VI. though the creature of the emperor, and devoted to his intereſt, endeavoured to aſſume the impartiality which became the common father of Chriſtendom, and laboured to reconcile the contending princes, that they might unite in a league againſt Solyman, whoſe conqueſt of Rhodes rendered him more formidable than ever to Europe. The Italian ſtates were no leſs deſirous of peace than the pope : and ſo much regard was paid by the hoſtile powers to the exhortations of his holineſs, and to a bull which he iſsued, requiring all Chriſtian princes to conſent to a truce for three years, that the imperial, the French, and the Engliſh ambaſſadors at Rome, were empowered to treat of that matter ; but while they wasted their time in ſruitleſs negociations, their maſters were continuing their preparations for war ; and other negociations ſoon took place. The confederacy againſt France became more formidable than ever.</p><p>The Venetians, who had hitherto adhered to the French intereſt, formed engagements with the emperor for ſecuring Francis Sforza in the poſſeſſion of the duchy of Milan ; and the pope, from a perſuaſion that the ambition of the French monarch was the only obſtacle to peace, acceded to the ſame alliance. The Florentines, the dukes of Ferrara and Mantua, and all the Italian powers, followed this example. Francis was left without a ſingle ally, to refill the efforts of a multitude of enemies, whoſe armies everywhere threatened, and whoſe territories encompaſſed his dominions. The emperor in perſon menaced France with an invaſion on the ſide of Guienne ; the forces of England, and the Netherlands hovered over Picardy, and a numerous body of Germans was preparing to ravage Burgundy.</p><p>The dread of ſo many and ſuch powerful adversaries, it was thought, would have obliged Francis to keep wholly on the deſenſive, or at leaſt have prevented him from entertaining any thoughts of marching into Italy. But before his enemies were able to ſtiike a blow, Francis had aſſembled a great army, with which he hoped to diſconcert all the emperor’s ſchemes, by marching it in perſon into Italy : and this bold measure, the more formidable becauſe unexpected, could ſcarcely have failed of the desired effect, had it been immediately carried into execution. But the diſcovery of a domeſtic conſpiracy, which threatened the destruction of his kingdom, obliged Francis to ſtop ſhort at Lyons.</p><p>Charles duke of Bourbon, lord high conſtable of France, was a prince of the moſt ſhining merit : his great talents equally fitted him tor the council or the field, while his eminent services to the crown intitled him to its firſt favour. But unhappily Louiſa ducheſs of Angouleme, the king’s mother, had contracted a violent averſion againſt the houſe of Bourbon, and had taught her ſon, over whom ſhe had acquired an abſolute aſoendant, to view all the conſtable’s actions with a jealous eye. After repeated affronts he retired from court,<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0639.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0633"/>
and began to liſten to the advances of the emperor’s miniſters. Meantime the ducheſs of Bourbon died ; and as the conſtable was no leſs amiable than accompliſhed, the ducheſs of Angouleme, ſtill ſuſceptible of the tender paſſions, formed the ſcheme of marrying him. But Bourbon, who might have expected every thing to which an ambitious mind can aſpire, from the doating fondneſs of a woman who governed her ſon and the kingdom, incapable of imitating Louiſa in her ſudden transition from hate to love, or of meanly counterfeiting apaſſion for one who had ſo long purſued him with unprovoked malice, rejected the match with diſdain, and turned the propoſal into ridicule. At once deſpiſed and inſulted by the man whom love only could have made her ceaſe to perſecute, Louiſa was filled with all the rage of disappointed woman ; ſhe reſolved to ruin, ſince ſhe could not marry, Bourbon. For this purpoſe ſhe commenced an iniquitous suit againſt him ; and by the chicanery of chancellor du Prat, the conſtable was ſtripped of his whole family-eſtate. Driven to deſpair by so many injuries, he entered into a ſecret correſpondence with the emperor and the king of England ; and he propoſed, as ſoon as Francis ſhould have croſſed the Alps, to raiſe an inſurrection among his numerous vaſſals, and introduce foreign enemies into the heart of France.</p><p>Happily Francis got intimation of this conſpiracy before he left the kingdom ; but not being sufficiently convinced of the Conſtable’s guilt, he suffered ſo dangerous a foe to eſcape ; and Bourbon entering into the emperor’s ſervice, employed all the force of his enterpriſing genius, and his great talents for war, to the prejudice of his prince and his native country.</p><p>In conſequence of the diſcovery of this plot, and the eſcape of the powerful conſpirator, Francis relinquiſhed his intention of leading his army in perſon into Italy. He was ignorant how far the infection had ſpread among his ſubjects, and afraid that his abſence might encourage them to make ſome deſperate attempt in favour of a man ſo much beloved. He did not, however, abandon his design on the Milaneſe, but ſent forward an army of 30,000 men, under the command of admiral Bonnivet. Colonna, who was entruſted with the defence of that duchy, was in no condition to reſiſt ſuch a force ; and the city of Milan, on which the whole territory depends, muſt have fallen into the hands of the French, had not Bonnivet, who posseſſed none of the talents of a general, wasted his time in frivolous enterpriſes, till the inhabitants recovered from their conſternation. The imperial army was reinforced. Colonna died ; and Lannoy, viceroy of Naples, ſucceeded him in the command : but the chief direction of military operations was committed to Bourbon and the marquis de Peſcara, the greateſt generals of their age. Bonnivet, deſtitute of troops to oppoſe this new army, and ſtill more of the talents which could render him a match for its leaders, after various movements and encounters, was reduced to the neceſſity of attempting a retreat into France. He was followed by the imperial generals, and routed at Biagraſſa, where the famous chevalier Bayard was killed.</p><p>The emperor and his allies were leſs ſucceſsful in their attempts upon France. They were baffled in every quarter : and Francis, though ſtripped of his Italian dominions, might ſtill have enjoyed in ſafety</p><p>the glory of having defended his native kingdom againſt one half of Europe, and have bid defiance to all his enemies ; but underſtanding that the king of England, diſcouraged by his former fruitleſs enterpriſes, and diſguſted with the emperor, was making no preparations for any attempt on Picardy, his ancient ardour ſeized him for the conqueſt of Milan, and he determined, not- withſtanding the advanced ſeaſon, to march into Italy.</p><p>The French army no ſooner appeared in Piedmont, than the whole Milaneſe was thrown into conſternation. The capital opened its gates. The forces of the emperor and Sforza retired to Lodi : and had Francis been ſo fortunate as to purſue them, they muſt have abandoned that poſt, and been totally diſperſed ; but his evil genius led him to beſiege Pavia, a town of conſiderable ſtrength, well garriſoned, and defended by Antonio de Leyva, one of the braveſt officers in the Spaniſh ſervice ; before which place he was defeated and taken priſoner on the twenty-fourth day of February 1524∙</p><p>The captivity of Francis filled all Europe with alarm. Almoſt the whole French army was cut off; Milan was immediately abandoned ; and in a few weeks not a Frenchman was left in Italy. The power of the emperor, and ſtill more his ambition, became an object of univerſal terror; and reſolutions were everywhere taken to ſet bounds to it. Meanwhile Francis, deeply impreſſed with a ſenſe of his misfortune, wrote to his mother Louiſa, whom he had left regent of the kingdom, the following ſhort but expreſſive letter : .“ All, Madam, is loſt but honour.” The ſame courier that carried this letter, carried alſo dispatches to Charles ; who received the news of the ſignal and unexpected ſucceſs which had crowned his arms with the moſt hypocritical moderation. He would not ſuffer any public rejoicings to be made on account of it ; and ſaid, he only valued it, as it would prove the occaſion of reſtoring peace to Chriſtendom. Louiſa, however, did not truſt to thoſe appearances ; if ſhe could not preſerve what was yet left, ſhe determined at leaſt that nothing ſhould be loſt through her negligence or weakneſs. Inſtead of giving herſelf up to ſuch lamentations as were natural to a woman ſo remarkable for maternal tenderneſs, ſhe diſcovered all the foresight, and exerted all the activity, of a conſummate politician. She took every poſſible meaſure for putting the kingdom in a poſture of defence, while ſhe employed all her addreſs to appeaſe the reſentment and to gain the friendſhip of England ; and a ray of comfort from that quarter ſoon broke in upon the French affairs.</p><p>Though Henry VIII. had not entered into the war againſt France from any concerted political views, he had always retained ſome imperfect idea of that balance of power which it was neceſſary to maintain between Charles and Francis ; and the preſervation of which he boaſted to be his peculiar office. By his alliance with the emperor, he hoped to recover ſome part of thoſe territories on the continent which had belonged to his anceſtors ; and therefore willingly contributed to give him the aſcendency above his rival ; but having never dreamt of any event ſo decisive and fatal as the victory at Pavia, which ſeemed not only to have broken, but to have annihilated the power of Francis, he now became ſenſible of his own danger, as well as that of all Europe, from the loss of a proper counterpoiſe to the power of<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0640.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0634"/>
Charles. Inſtead oſ taking advantage of the diſtreſſed condition of France, Henry therefore determined to aſſiſt her in her preſent calamities. Some diſgusts alſo had taken place between him and Charles, and ſtill more between Charles and Wolſey. The elevation of the cardinal of Medici to St Peter’s chair, on the death of Adrian, under the name of Clement VII. had made the Engliſh miniſter ſensible of the inſincerity of the emperor’s promiſes, while it extinguiſhed all his hopes of the papacy ; and he reſolved on revenge. Charles, too, had ſo ill ſupported the appearance of moderation which he aſſumed, when firſt informed of his good fortune, that he had already changed his uſual ſtyle to Henry ; and inſtead of writing to him with his own hand, and ſubſcribing himſelf “ your affectionate ſon and couſin,” he dictated his letters to a ſecretary, and simply ſubſcribed himſelf “ Charles.” Influenced by all theſe motives, together with the glory of raising a fallen enemy, Henry liſtened to the flattering ſubmiſſions of Louiſa ; entered into a defenſive alliance with her as regent of France, and engaged to uſe his beſt offices in order to procure the deliverance of her ſon from a ſtate of captivity.</p><p>Meanwhile Francis was rigorouſly confined ; and ſevere conditions being propoſed to him as the price of his liberty, he drew his dagger, and, pointing it at his breaſt, cried, “ ’Twere better that a king ſhould die thus !” His hand was with-held : and flattering himſelf, when he grew cool, that ſuch propoſitions could not come directly from Charles, he deſired that he might be removed to Spain, where the emperor then reſided. His requeſt was complied with ; but he languiſhed long before he obtained a fight of his conqueror. At laſt he was favoured with a viſit ; and the emperor dreading a general combination againſt him, or that Francis, as he threatened, might, in the obſtinacy of his heart, resign his crown to the dauphin, agreed to abate ſomewhat of his former demands. A treaty was accordingly concluded at Madrid ; in conſequence of which Francis obtained his liberty. The chief article in this treaty was, that Burgundy ſhould be reſtored to Charles as the rightful inheritance of his anceſtors, and that Francis’s two eldeſt ſons ſhould be immediately delivered up as hoſtages for the performance of the conditions ſtipulated. The exchange of the captive monarch for his children was made on the borders between France and Spain. The moment that Francis entered his own dominions, he mounted a Turkiſh horſe, and putting it to its ſpeed, waved his hand, and cried aloud ſeveral times, “ I am yet a king ! I am yet a king·”</p><p>Francis never meant to execute the treaty of Madrid : he had even left a proteſt in the hands of notaries before he ſigned it, that his conſent ſhould be conſidered as an involuntary deed, and be deemed null and void. Accordingly, as ſoon as he arrived in France, he aſſembled the ſtates of Burgundy, who proteſted againſt the article relative to their province ; and Francis coldly replied to the imperial ambaſſadors, who urged the immediate execution of the treaty, that he would religiouſly perform the articles relative to himſelf, but in thoſe affecting the French monarchy, he muſt be directed by the ſenſe of the nation. He made the higheſt acknowledgments to the king of England for his friendly interpoſition, and offered to be entirely guided by his counſels. Charles and his miniſters ſaw</p><p>that they were over-reached in thoſe very arts of negociation in which they ſo much excelled, while the Italian ſtates obſerved with pleaſure, that Francis was reſolved not to execute a treaty which they conſidered as dangerous to the liberties of Europe. Clement abſolved him from the oath which he had taken at Madrid ; and the kings of France and England, the Pope, the Swiſs, the Venetians, the Florentines, and the duke of Milan, entered into an alliance, to which they gave the name of the <hi rend="italic">Holy League,</hi> becauſe his Holineſs was at the head of it, in order to oblige the emperor to deliver up Francis’s two ſons on the payment of a reaſonable ranſom, and to re-eſtabliſh Sforza in the quiet poſſession of the Milaneſe.</p><p>In conſequence of this league, the confederate army took the field, and Italy once more became the scene of war. But Francis, who it was thought would have inſuſed ſpirit and vigour into the whole body, had gone through ſuch a ſcene of diſtreſs, that he was become diffident of himſelf, diſtruſtful of his fortune, and deſirous of tranquillity. He flattered himſelf, that the dread alone of ſuch a confederacy would induce Charles to liſten to what was equitable, and therefore neglected to ſend due reinforcements to his allies in Italy. Meantime the duke of Bourbon, who commanded the Imperialiſts, had made himſelf maſter of the whole Milaneſe, of which the emperor had promiſed him the inveſtiture; and his troops beginning to mutiny for want of pay, he led them to Rome, and promiſed to enrich them with the ſpoils of that city. He was as good as his word ; for though he himſelf was ſlain in planting a ſcaling ladder againſt the walls, his ſoldiers, rather enraged than diſcouraged by his death, mounted to the aſſault with the utmoſt ardour, animated by the greatneſs of the prize, and, entering the city ſword in hand, plundered it for ſeveral days.</p><p>Never did Rome in any age ſuffer ſo many calamities, not even from the Barbarians, by whom ſhe was often ſubdued, the Huns, Vandals, or Goths, as now from the ſubjects of a Chriſtian and Catholic monarch. Whatever was reſpectable in modeſty, or ſacred in religion, ſeemed only the more to provoke the rage of the ſoldiery. Virgins ſuffered violation in the arms of their parents, and upon thoſe altars to which they had fled for ſafety. Venerable prelates, after enduring every indignity and every torture, were thrown into dungeons, and menaced with the moſt cruel death, in order to make them reveal their ſecret treaſures. Clement himſelf, who had neglected to make his eſcape in time, was taken priſoner, and found that the ſacredneſs of his character could neither procure him liberty nor reſpect. He was confined till he ſhould pay an enormous ranſom impoſed by the victorious army, and surrender to the emperor all the places of ſtrength belonging to the church.</p><p>Charles received the news of this extraordinary event with equal ſurpriſe and pleaſure ; but in order to conceal his joy from his Spaniſh ſubjects, who were filled with horror at the inſult offered to the ſovereign pontiff, and to lessen the indignation of the reſt of Europe, he expreſſed the moſt profound ſorrow for the ſucceſs of his arms. He put himſelf and his court into mourning; ſtopped the rejoicings for the birth of his ſon Philip, and ordered prayers to be put up in all the churches of Spain for the recovery of the pope’s liberty.<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0641.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0635"/>
which he could immediately have procured by a letter to his generals.</p><p>The concern expreſſed by Henry and Francis for the calamity of their ally was more sincere. Alarmed at the progreſs of the imperial arms, they had, even before the taking of Rome, entered into a cloſer alliance, and agreed to invade the Low Countries with a powerful army ; but no ſooner did they hear of the Pope’s captivity, than they changed, by a new treaty, the ſcene of the projected war ſrom the Netherlands to Italy, and reſolved to take the moſt vigorous meaſures for reſtoring him to liberty. Henry, however, contributed only money. A French army entered Italy, under the command of Marſhal Lautrec ; Clement obtained his freedom ; and war was for a time carried on by the confederates with ſucceſs ; but the death of Lautrec, and the revolt of Andrew Doria, a Genoeſe admiral in the ſervice of France, entirely changed the face oſ affairs. The French army was utterly ruined ; and Francis, diſcouraged and almoſt exhauſted by so many unſucceſsful enterpriſes, began to think of peace, and of obtaining the releaſe of his ſons by conceſſions, not by the terror of his arms.</p><p>At the ſame time Charles, notwithſtanding the advantages he had gained, had many reaſons to wiſh for an accommodation. Sultan Solyman having over-run Hungary, was ready to break in upon the Auſtrian territories with the whole force of the Eaſt ; and the progreſs of the Reformation in Germany threatened the tranquillity of the empire. In conſequence of this situation of affairs, though pride made both parties conceal or diſſemble their real ſentiments, two ladies were permitted to reſtore peace to Europe. Margaret of Auſtria, Charles’s aunt, and Louiſa, Francis’s mother, met in 1529 at Cambray, and ſettled the terms of accommodation between the French king and the emperor. Francis agreed to pay two millions of crowns as the ranſom of his two ſons, to resign the ſovereignty oſ Flanders and Artois, and to forego all his Italian claims; and Charles ceaſed to demand the reſtitution of Burgundy.</p><p>All the ſteps of this negociation had been communicated to the king of England ; and Henry was, on that occaſion, ſo generous to his friend and ally Francis, that he ſent him an acquittal of near six hundred thouſand crowns, in order to enable him to fulfil his agreement with Charles. But Francis’s Italian confederates were leſs ſatisfied with the treaty of Cambray, They were almoſt wholly abandoned to the will of the emperor ; and ſeemed to have no other means of ſecurity leſt but his equity and moderation. Of theſe, from his paſt conduct, they had not formed the moſt advantageous idea. But Charles’s preſent circumſtances, more eſpecially in regard to the Turks, obliged him to behave with a generoſity inconſiſtent with his character. The Florentines alone, whom he reduced under the dominion of the family of Medici, had reaſon to complain of his ſeverity. Sforza obtained the inveſtiture of Milan and his pardon ; and every other power experienced the lenity of the conqueror.</p><p>After having received the imperial crown from the hands of the Pope at Bologna, Charles proceeded on his journey to Germany, where his preſence was become highly neceſſary ; for although the conduct and valour of his brother Ferdinand, on whom he had conferred</p><p>the hereditary dominions of the houſe of Auſtria, and who had been elected king of Hungary, had obliged Solyman to retire with infamy and loss, his return was to be feared, and the diſorders of religion were daily increasing ; an account of which, and of the emperor’s tranſactions with the Proteſtants. is given under the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Reformation.</hi></p><p>Charles having exerted himſelf as much as he could againſt the reformers, undertook his firſt expedition againſt the piratical ſtates of Africa. Barbary, or that part of the African continent lying along the coaſt of the Mediterranean ſea, was then nearly in the ſame condition which it is at preſent. Morocco, Algiers, and Tunis, were its principal ſtates ; and the two laſt were neſts oſ pirates. Barbaroſſa, a famous Corſair, had ſucceeded his brother in the kingdom of Algiers, which he had formerly aſſiſted him to uſurp. He regulated with much prudence the interior police of his kingdom, carried on his piracies with great vigour, and extended his conqueſts on the continent of Africa ; but perceiving that the natives ſubmitted to his government with impatience, and fearing that his continual depredations would one day draw upon him a general combination of the Chriſtian powers, he put his dominions under the protection of the grand ſeignior. Solyman, flattered by ſuch an act of ſubmiſſion, and charmed with the boldness of the man, offered him the command of the Turkiſh fleet. Proud of this diſtinction, Barbaroſſa repaired to Conſtantinople, and made uſe of his influence with the ſultan to extend his own dominion. Partly by force, partly by treachery, he uſurped the kingdom of Tunis; and being now poſſeſſed of greater power, he carried on his depredations againſt the Chriſtian ſtates with more deſtructive violence than ever.</p><p>Daily complaints of the piracies and ravages committed by the galleys of Barbaroſſa were brought to the emperor by his ſubjects, both in Spain and Italy ; and all Chriſtendom ſeemed to look up to him, as its greateſt and moſt fortunate prince, for relief from this new and odious ſpecies of oppreſſion. At the ſame time Muley-Haſcen, the exiled king of Tunis, finding none of the African princes able or willing to ſupport him in recovering his throne, applied to Charles for aſsiſtance againſt the uſurper. Equally desirous of delivering his dominions from the dangerous neighbourhood of Barbaroſſa, of appearing as the protector of an unfortunate prince, and of acquiring the glory annexed in that age to every expedition againſt the Mahometans, the emperor readily concluded a treaty with Muley Haſcen, and ſet ſail for Tunis with a formidable armament. The Goletta, a ſea port town, fortified with 300 pieces of cannon, was taken, together with all Barbaroſſa’s fleet : he was defeated in a pitched battle, and 10,000 Chriſtian ſlaves, having knocked off their fetters, and made themſelves maſters of the citadel, Tunis was preparing to ſurrender. But while Charles was deliberating on the conditions, his troops fearing that they would be deprived of the booty which they had expected, broke ſuddenly into the town, and pillaged and maſſacred without diſtinction. Thirty thouſand perſons periſhed by the ſword, and 10,000 were made priſoners. The ſceptre was reſtored to Muley Haſcen, on condition that he ſhould acknowledge himſelf a vaſſal of the crown of Spain, put into the emperor’s hands all the fortified sea-ports in the kingdom of Tunis, and<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0642.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0636"/>
pay annually 12,000 crowns for the ſubsiſtence of the Spaniſh garrison in the Goletta. Theſe points being settled, and 20,000 Chriſtian ſlaves freed from bondage either by arms or by treaty, Charles returned to Europe, where his preſence was become necessary ; while Barbarossa, who had retired to Bona, recovered new ſtrength, and again became the tyrant of the ocean.</p><p>The king of France took advantage oſ the emperor’s abſence to revive his pretensions in Italy. The treaty of Cambray had covered up but not extinguiſhed the flames oſ diſcord. Francis in particular, who waited only for a favourable opportunity of recovering the territories and reputation which he had lost, continued to negotiate againſt his rival with different courts. But all his negotiations were disconcerted by unforeſeen accidents. The death of Clement VII. (whom he had gained by marrying his ſon the duke of Orleans, afterwards Henry II. to Catharine of Medici, the niece of that pontiff), deprived him of all the ſupport which he hoped to receive from the court of Rome. The king of England, occupied with domeſtic cares and projects, declined engaging in the affairs of the continent ; and the Proteſtant princes, associated by the league of Smalkalde, to whom Francis had alſo applied, and who ſeemed diſpoſed at firſt to liſten to him, filled with indignation and reſentment at the cruelty with which some of their reformed brethren had been treated in France, refuſed to have any connection with the enemy of their religion.</p><p>Francis was neither cruel nor bigotted : he was too indolent to concern himſelf about religious diſputes ; but his principles becoming ſuſpected, at a time when the emperor was gaining immortal glory by his expedition againſt the Infidels, he found it necessary to vindicate himſelf by ſome extraordinary demonstration of reverence for the eſtabliſhed faith. The indiſcreet zeal of ſome Proteſtant converts furniſhed him. with the occaſion. They had affixed to the gates of the Louvre and other public places papers containing indecent reflections on the rites of the Romiſh church. Six of the perſons concerned in this talk action were ſeized ; and the king, pretending to be struck with horror at their blasphemies, appointed a ſolemn proceſſion, in order to avert the wrath of heaven. The holy ſacrament was carried through the city of Paris in great pomp: Francis walked uncovered before it, bearing a torch in his hand ; the princes of the blood ſupported the canopy over it ; the nobles walked behind. In preſence of this numerous assembly, the king declared, that if one of his hands were infected with hereſy, he would cut it off with the other ; “ and I would ſacriſice (added he) even my own children, if found guilty of that crime.” As an awful proof of his ſincerity, the six unhappy perſons who had been ſeized were publicly burnt, before the proceſſion was finiſhed, and in the moſt cruel manner. They were fixed upon a machine which deſcended into the flames, and retired alternately, until they expired.—No wonder that the Proteſtant princes were incenſed at ſuch barbarity !</p><p>But Francis, though unſupported by any ally, commanded his army to advance towards the frontiers of Italy, under pretence of chaſtiſing the duke of Milan for a breach of the law oſ nations, in putting to death his ambassador. The operations oſ war, however, ſoon took a new direction. Inſtead of marching directly to</p><p>the Milaneſe, Francis commenced hoſtilitieg againſt the duke of Savoy, with whom he had cauſe to be dissatisfied, and on whom he had ſome claims ; and before the end of the campaign, that feeble prince ſaw himſelf ſtripped of all his dominions, except the province of Piedmont. To complete his misfortunes, the city of Geneva, the ſovereignty of which he claimed, and where the reformed opinions had already got footing, threw off his yoke ; and its revolt drew along with it the loſs of the adjacent territory. Geneva was then an imperial city, and has ever since remained entirely free.</p><p>In this extremity the duke of Savoy ſaw no reſource but in the emperor’s protection ; and as his misfortunes were chiefly occaſioned by his attachment to the imperial intereſt, he had a title to immediate aſſiſtance. But Charles, who was juſt returned from his African expedition, was not able to lend him the necessary ſupport. His treaſury was entirely drained, and he was obliged to diſhand his army till he could raiſe new ſupplies. Mean time the death of Sforza duke of Milan entirely changed the nature of the war, and afforded the emperor full leiſure to prepare ſor action. The French monarch’s pretext for taking up arms was at once cut off; but as the duke died without iſſue, all Francis’s rights to the duchy of Milan, which he had yielded only to Sforza and his deſcendants, returned to him in full force. He inſtantly renewed his claim to it ; and if he had ordered his army immediately to advance, he might have made himſelf maſter of it. But he unfortunately waited his time in fruitleſs negotiations, while his more politic rival took poſſeſſion of the duchy as a vacant fief of the empire ; and though Charles ſeemed ſtill to admit the equity of Francis’s claim, he delayed granting the inveſtiture under various pretences, and was ſecretly taking every poſſible meaſure to prevent him from regaining footing in Italy.</p><p>During the time gained in this manner Charles had recruited his finances, and of courſe his armies ; and finding himſelf in a condition for war, he at laſt threw off the maſk under which he had ſo long concealed his deſigns from the court of France. Entering Rome with great pomp, he pronounced before the pope and cardinals, assembled in full conſiſtory, a violent invective againſt Francis, by way of reply to his proposions concerning the inveſtiture of Milan. Yet Francis, by an unaccountable fatality, continued to negotiate, as if it had been ſtill poſſible to terminate their differences in an amicable manner; and Charles, finding him ſo eager to run into the ſnare, favoured the deception, and, by ſeeming to liſten to his propoſals, gained yet more time for the execution of his ambitious projects.</p><p>If misfortunes had rendered Francis too diffident, ſucceſs had made Charles too ſanguine. He preſumed on nothirg leſs than the ſubverſion of the French monarchy ; nay, he conſidered it as an infallible event. Having chafed the forces of his rival out of Piedmont and Savoy, he puſhed forward at the head of 50,000 men, contrary to the advice of his moſt experienced miniſters and generals, to invade the ſouthern provinces of France ; while other two armies were ordered to enter it, the one on the ſide of Picardy, the other on the side of Champagne. He thought it impoſſible that Francis could resiſt ſo many unexpected attacks on ſuch different quarters ; but he found himſelf miſtaken.</p><p>The French monarch fixed upon the moſt effectual<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0643.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0637"/>
plan for defeating the invaſion of a powerful enemy ; and he prudently perſevered in following it, though contrary to his own natural temper and to the genius of his people. He determined to remain altogether upon the defenſive, and to deprive the enemy of ſubſiſtence by laying waste the country before them. The execution of this plan was committed to the mareſchal Montmorency its author, a man happily fitted for ſuch a truſt by the inflexible ſeverity of his diſpoſition. He made choice of a ſtrong camp, under the walls of Avignon, at the confluence of the Rhone and Durance, where he aſſembled a conſiderable army ; while the king, with another body of troops, encamped at Valence, higher up the Rhone. Marſeilles and Arles were the only towns he thought it neceſſary to defend ; and each of theſe he furniſhed with a numerous garriſon of his beſt troops. The inhabitants of the other towns were compelled to abandon their habitations : the fortifications of ſuch places as might have afforded ſhelter to the enemy were thrown down ; corn, forage, and proviſions of every kind, were carried off or deſtroyed ; the mills and ovens were ruined, and the wells filled up or rendered uſeleſs.</p><p>This devaſtation extended from the Alps to Marſeilles, and from the ſea to the confines of Dauphiny ; ſo that the emperor, when he arrived with the van of his army on the confines of Provence, inſtead of that rich and populous country which he expected to enter, beheld nothing but one vaſt and deſert solitude. He did not, however, deſpair of ſucceſs, though he ſaw that he would have many difficulties to encounter; and as an encouragement to his officers, he made them liberal promiſes of lands and honours in France. But all the land which any of them obtained was a grave, and their maſter loſt much honour by this raſh and presumptuous enterprize. After unsucceſsfully inveſting Marſeilles and Arles, after attempting in vain to draw Montmorency from his camp at Avignon, and not daring to attack it, Charles having ſpent two inglorious months in Provence, and loſt one half of his troops by diſeaſe or by famine, was under the neceſſity of ordering a retreat ; and though he was ſome time in motion before the enemy ſuſpected his intention, it was conducted with ſo much precipitation and diſorder, as to deserve the name of a flight, ſince the light troops of France turned it into a perfect rout. The invaſion of Picardy was not more ſucceſsful: the imperial forces were obliged to retire without effecting any conqueſt oſ importance.</p><p>Charles had no ſooner conducted the ſhattered remains of his army to the frontiers of Milan, than he ſet out ſor Genoa ; and unwilling to expoſe himſelf to the ſcorn of the Italians after ſuch a reverſe of fortune, he embarked directly for Spain.</p><p>Meanwhile Francis gave himſelf up to that vain reſentment which had formerly diſgraced the proſperity of his rival. They had frequently, in the courſe of their quarrels, given each other the lie, and mutual challenges had been ſent ; which, though productive of no ſerious conſequences between the parties, had a powerful tendency to encourage the pernicious practice of duelling. Charles, in his invective pronounced at Rome, had publicly accuſed Francis of perfidy and breach of faith ; Francis now exceeded Charles in the indecency of his accuſations. The Dauphin dying ſuddenly, his death</p><p>was imputed to poiſon: Montecuculi his cup-bearer was put to the rack ; and that unhappy nobleman, in the agonies of torture, accuſed the emperor’s generals Gonzaga and de Leyva, of inſtigating him to the deteſtable act. The emperor himſelf was ſuſpected; nay, this extorted confeſſion, and ſome obſcure hints, were conſidered as inconteſtable proofs of his guilt ; though it was evident to all mankind, that neither Charles nor his generals could have any inducement to perpetrate ſuch a crime, as Francis was ſtill in the vigour of life himſelf, and had two ſons beſides the dauphin, grown up to a good age.</p><p>But the incenſed monarch’s reſentment did not ſtop here. Francis was not ſatisfied with endeavouring to blacken the character of his rival by an ambiguous teſtimony which led to the moſt injurious ſuſpicions, and upon which the moſt cruel conductions had been put; he was willing to add rebellion to murder. For this purpoſe he went to the parliament of Paris ; where being ſeated with the uſual ſolemnities, the advocate-general appeared, and accuſed Charles of Auſtria (ſo he affected to call the emperor) of having violated the treaty of Cambray, by which he was freed from the homage due to the crown of France for the counties of Artois and Flanders ; adding, that this treaty being now void, he was ſtill to be conſidered as a vaſſal of France, and conſequently had been guilty of rebellion in taking arms againſt his sovereign. The charge was ſuſtained, and Charles was ſummoned to appear before the parliament of Paris at a day fixed. The term expired ; and no perſon appearing in the emperor’s name, the parliament gave judgment, that Charles of Auſtria had forfeited, by rebellion and contumacy, the counties of Flanders and Artois, and declared theſe fiefs reunited to the crown of France.</p><p>Francis, ſoon after this vain diſplay of his animoſity, marched into the Low Countries, as if he had intended to execute the sentence pronounced by his parliament ; but a ſuſpenſion of arms took place, through the interpoſition of the queens of France and Hungary, before any thing of conſequence was effected : and this cesſation of hoſtilities was followed by a truce, concluded at Nice, through the mediation of the reigning pontiff Paul III. of the family of Farneſe, a man of a venerable character and pacific diſpoſition.</p><p>Each of theſe rival princes had ſtrong reaſons to incline them to peace. The finances of both were exhausted ; and the emperor, the moſt powerful of the two, was deeply impreſſed with the dread of the Turkiſh arms, which Francis had drawn upon him by a league with Solyman. In conſequence of this league, Barbaroſſa with a great fleet appeared on the coaſt of Naples; filled that kingdom with conſternation; landed without reſiſtance near Taranto ; obliged Caſtro, a place of ſome ſtrength, to ſurrender ; plundered the adjacent country ; and was taking meaſures for ſecuring and extending his conqueſts, when the unexpected arrival of Doria, the famous Genoele admiral, together with the pope’s galleys and a ſquadron of the Venetian fleet, made it prudent for him to retire. The ſultan’s forces alſo invaded Hungary, where Mahmet the Turkiſh general, after gaining ſeveral inferior advantages, defeated the Germans in a great battle at Eſſek on the Drave. Happily for Charles and Europe it was not in Francis’s power at this juncture either to join the Turks or aſ-<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0644.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0638"/>
ſemble an army ſtrong enough to penetrate into the Milaneſe. The emperor, however, was ſenſible that he could not long reſiſt the efforts of two ſuch powerful confederates, nor expect that the ſame fortunate circumſtances would concur a ſecond time in his favour ; he therefore thought it neceſſary, both for his ſafety and reputation, to give his conſent to a truce : and Francis choſe rather to run the riſk of diſobliging his new ally the ſultan, than to draw on his head the indignation, and perhaps the arms, of all Chriſtendom, by obſtinately obſtructing the re-eſtabliſhment of tranquillity, and contributing to the aggrandizement of the Infidels.</p><p>Theſe conſiderations inclined the contending monarchs to liſten to the arguments of the holy father ; but he found it impoſſible to bring about a final accommodation between them, each inflexibly perſiſting in aſſerting his own claims. Nor could he prevail on them to ſee one another, though both came to the place of rendezvous : ſo great was the remains of diſtruſt and rancour, or ſuch the difficulty of adjuſting the ceremonial ! Yet, improbable as it may ſeem, a few days after ſigning the truce, the emperor, in his paſſage to Barcelona, being driven on the coaſt of Provence, Francis invited him to come aſhore ; frankly viſited him on board his galley, and was received and entertained with the warmeſt demonſtrations of eſteem and affection. Charles, with an equal degree of confidence, paid the king next day a viſit at Aigues-mortes ; where theſe two hoſtile rivals and vindictive enemies, who had accuſed each other of every kind of baſeneſs, converſing together with all the cordiality of brothers, ſeemed to vie with each other in expreſſions of reſpect and friendſhip.</p><p>Beſides the glory of having reſtored tranquillity to Europe, the pope gained a point of much conſequence to his family. He obtained for his grandſon, Margaret of Auſtria, the emperor’s natural daughter, formerly wife of Alexander de Medici, whom Charles had raiſed to the ſupreme power in Florence. Lorenzo de Medici, the kinſman and intimate companion of Alexander, had aſſaſſinated him by one of the blackeſt treaſons recorded in hiſtory. Under pretence of having ſecured him an aſſignation with a lady of the higheſt rank and great beauty, he drew him into a ſecret apartment of his houſe, and there ſtabbed him as he lay careleſsly on a couch, expecting the embrace of the lovely fair, whom he had often ſolicited in vain. Lorenzo, however, did not reap the fruits of his crime ; for though ſome of his countrymen extolled him as a third Brutus, and endeavoured to ſeize this occaſion for recovering their liberties, the government of Florence paſſed into the hands of Coſmo II. another kinſman of Alexander. Coſmo was deſirous of marrying the widow of his predeceſſor ; but the emperor choſe rather to oblige the pope, by bellowing his daughter upon Octavio Farneſe, ſon of the duke of Parma.</p><p>Charles had ſoon farther cauſe to be ſenſible of his obligations to the holy father for bringing about the treaty of Nice. His troops everywhere mutinied for want of pay, and the ability of his generals only could have prevented a total revolt. He had depended, as his chief reſource for diſcharging the arrears due to his ſoldiers, upon the ſubſidies which he expected from his Caſtilian ſubiects. For this purpoſe he aſſembled the</p><p>Cortes of Caſtile at Toledo ; and having represented to them the great expence of his military operations, he propoſed to levy ſuch ſupplies as the preſent exigency of affairs demanded, by a general exciſe on commodities ; but the Spaniards, who already felt themſelves oppreſſed by a load of taxes unknown to their anceſtors, and who had often complained that their country was drained of its wealth and inhabitants, in order to proſecute quarrels in which they had no intereſt, determined not to add voluntarily to their own burdens. The nobles, in particular, inveighed with great vehemence againſt the imposition propoſed, as an encroachment on the valuable and diſtinguiſhing privilege of their order, that of being exempted from the payment of any tax. After employing arguments and promiſes in vain, Charles diſmiſſed the aſſembly with indignation ; and from that period neither the nobles nor the prelates have been called to the Cortes, on pretence that ſuch as pay no part of the public taxes ſhould not claim a vote in laying them on. Theſe aſſemblies have ſince conſiſted merely of the procurators or repreſentatives of 18 cities, two from each ; in all 36 members, who are abſolutely at the devotion of the crown.</p><p>The citizens of Ghent, ſtill more bold, broke out not long after into open rebellion againſt the emperor’s government, on account of a tax which they judged contrary to their ancient privileges, and a deciſion of the council of Mechlin in favour of the imperial authority. Enraged at an unjuſt impoſition, and rendered deſperate on ſeeing their rights betrayed by that very court which was bound to protect them, they flew to arms, ſeized ſeveral of the emperor’s officers, and drove ſuch of the nobility as reſided among them out of the city. Senſible, however, of their inability to ſupport what their zeal had prompted them to undertake, and deſirous of ſecuring a protector againſt the formidable forces with which they might expect ſoon to be attacked, they offered to acknowledge the king of France as their ſovereign, to put him into immediate poſſeſſion of their city, and to aſſiſt him in recovering thoſe provinces in the Netherlands which had anciently belonged to his crown. True policy directed Francis to comply with this propoſal. The counties of Flanders and Artois were more valuable than the duchy of Milan, for which he had ſo long contended ; and their ſituation in regard to France made it more eaſy to conquer or to defend them. But Francis overrated the Milaneſe. He had lived in friendſhip with the emperor ever ſince their interview at Aigues-mortes, and Charles had promiſed him the inveſtiture of that duchy. Forgetting, therefore, all his paſt injuries, and the deceitful promiſes by which he had been ſo often duped, the credulous, generous Francis, not only rejected the propoſitions of the citizens of Ghent, but communicated to the emperor his whole negociation with the malecontents.</p><p>Judging of Charles’s heart by his own, Francis hoped by this ſeemingly diſintereſted proceeding to obtain at once the inveſtiture of Milan ; and the emperor, well acquainted with the weakneſs of his rival, flattered him in this apprehenſion, for his own ſelfiſh purpoſes. His preſence being neceſſary in the Netherlands, he demanded a paſſage through France. It was immediately granted him ; and Charles, to whom every moment was precious, ſet out, notwithſtanding the remonſtrances of his council and the fears of his Spaniſh ſubjects, with a<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0645.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0639"/>
ſmall but ſplendid train of 100 perſons. He was met on the frontiers of France by the dauphin and the duke of Orleans, who offered to go into Spain, and remain there as hoſtages, till he ſhould reach his own dominions ; but Charles replied, that the king’s honour was sufficient for his ſafety, and proſecuted his journey without any other ſecurity. The king entertained him with the utmoſt magnificence at Paris, and the two young princes did not take leave of him till he entered the Low Countries ; yet he ſtill found means to evade his promiſe, and Francis continued to believe him ſincere.</p><p>The citizens of Ghent, alarmed at the approach of the emperor, who was joined by three armies, ſent ambaſſadors to implore his mercy, and offered to throw open their gates. Charles only condeſcended to reply,</p><p>“ That he would appear among them as a ſovereign and a judge, with the ſceptre and the ſword.” He accordingly entered the place of his nativity on the anniverſary of his birth ; and inſtead of that lenity which might have been expected, exhibited an awful example of his ſeverity. Twenty-six of the principal citizens were put to death ; a greater number were baniſhed ; the city was declared to have forfeited its privileges ; a new ſyſtem of laws and political adminiſtration was prescribed ; and a large fine was impoſed on the inhabitants, in order to defray the expence of erecting a citadel, together with an annual tax for the ſupport of a garriſon. They were not only deſpoiled of their ancient immunities, but made to pay, like conquered people, for the means of perpetuating their own ſlavery.</p><p>Having thus re-eſtabliſhed his authority in the Low Countries, and being now under no neceſſity of continuing that ſcene of falſehood and diſſimulation with which he had amuſed the French monarch, Charles began gradually to throw aſide the veil under which he had concealed his intentions with reſpect to the Milaneſe, and at laſt peremptorily refilled to give up a territory of ſuch value, or voluntarily to make ſuch a liberal addition to the ſtrength of an enemy by diminiſhing his own power. He even denied that he had ever made any promiſe which could bind him to an action ſo fooliſh, and ſo contrary to his own intereſt.</p><p>This tranſaction expoſed the king of France to as much ſcorn as it did the emperor to cenſure. The credulous ſimplicity of Francis ſeemed to merit no other return, after experiencing ſo often the duplicity and artifices of his rival. He remonſtrated, however, and exclaimed as if this had been the firſt circumſtance in which the emperor had deceived him. The inſult offered to his underſtanding affected him even more ſenſibly than the injury done to his intereſt ; and he diſcovered ſuch reſentment as made it obvious that he would ſeize on the firſt opportunity of revenge, and that a new war would ſoon deſolate the European continent.</p><p>Meanwhile Charles was obliged to turn his attention towards the affairs of Germany. The Proteſtants having in vain demanded a general council, preſſed him earneſtly to appoint a conference between a ſelect number of divines of each party, in order to examine the points in diſpute. For this purpoſe a diet was aſſembled at Ratiſhon: and ſuch a conference, notwithſtanding the oppoſition of the pope, was held with great ſolemnity in the preſence of the emperor. But the divines choſen to manage thc controverſy, though men of</p><p>learning and moderation, were only able to ſettle a few ſpeculative opinions, all points relative to worſhip and juriſdiction ſerving to inflame the minds of the diſputants. Charles, therefore, finding his endeavours to bring about an accommodation ineffectual, and being impatient to cloſe the diet, prevailed on a majority of the members to approve of the following edict of receſs; viz. that the articles concerning which the divines had agreed, ſhould be held as points decided ; that thoſe about which they had differed, ſhould be referred to the determination of a general council, or if that could not be obtained, to a national ſynod ; and ſhould it prove impracticable alſo to assemble a ſynod of Germany, that a general diet of the empire ſhould be called within 18 months, in order to give final judgment on the whole controverſy ; that, in the mean time, no innovations ſhould be attempted, nor any endeavours employed to gain proſelytes.</p><p>This diet gave great offence to the pope. The bare mention of allowing a diet, compoſed chiefly of laymen, to paſs judgment in regard to articles of faith, appeared to him no leſs criminal and profane than the worſt of thoſe hereſies which the emperor ſeemed ſo zealous to ſuppreſs. The Proteſtants alſo were diſſatisfied with it, as it considerably abridged the liberty which they at that time enjoyed. They murmured loudly againſt it ; and Charles, unwilling to leave any ſeeds of diſcontent in the empire, granted them a private declaration, exempting them from “whatever they thought injurious or oppreſſive in the receſs, and aſcertaining to them the full poſſeſſion of all their former privileges.</p><p>The ſituation of the emperor’s affairs at this juncture made theſe extraordinary conceſſions neceſſary. He foreſaw a rupture with France to be unavoidable, and he was alarmed at the rapid progreſs of the Turks in Hungary. A great revolution had happened in that kingdom. John Zapol Scæpus, by the aſſiſtance of Solyman, had wreſted from the king of the Romans a conſiderable part of the country. John died, and left an infant ſon. Ferdinand attempted to take advantage of the minority, in order to reposseſs himſelf of the whole kingdom ; but his ambition was diſappointed by the activity and addreſs of George Martinuzzi, biſhop of Waradin, who ſhared the regency with the queen. Senſible that he was unable to oppoſe the king of the Romans in the field, Martinuzzi ſatisfied himſelf with holding out the fortified towns, all of which he provided with every thing neceſſary for defence ; and at the ſame time he ſent ambaſſadors to Solyman, beſeeching him to extend towards the ſon that imperial protection which had ſo generouſly maintained the father on his throne. Ferdinand uſed his utmoſt endeavours to thwart this negotiation, and even meanly offered to hold the Hungarian crown on the ſame ignominious condition by which John had held it, that of paying tribute to the Porte. But the ſultan ſaw ſuch advantages from eſpouſing the intereſt of the young king, that he inſtantly marched into Hungary ; and the Germans, having formed the ſiege of Buda, were defeated with great ſlaughter before that city. Solyman, however, inſtead of becoming the protector of the infant ſovereign whom he had relieved, made uſe of this ſucceſs to extend his own dominions : he ſent the queen and her ſon into Tranſilvapia, which province he allotted them, and added Hungary to the Ottoman empire,<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0646.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0640"/>
Happily for the Proteſtants, Charles received intelligence of this revolution ſoon after the diet at Ratiſbon; and by the conceſſions which he made them, he obtained ſuch liberal ſupplies, both oſ men and money, as left him under little anxiety about the ſecurity of Germany.</p><p>He therefore haſtened to join his fleet and army in Italy, in order to carry into execution a great and favourite enterprize which he had concerted againſt Algiers : though it would certainly have been more conſiſtent with his dignity to have conducted the whole force of the empire againſt Solyman, the common enemy of Chriſtendom, who was ready to enter his Auſtrian dominions. But many reaſons induced Charles to prefer the African expedition : he wanted ſtrength, or at leaſt money, to combat the Turks in ſo diſtant a country as Hungary; and the glory which he had formerly acquired in Barbary led him to hope for the like ſucceſs, while the cries of his Spaniſh ſubjects rouſed him to take vengeance on their ravagers. But the unfortunate event of this expedition has already been related under the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Algiers,</hi> n⁰ 14—20.</p><p>The loſs which the emperor ſuffered in this calamitous expedition encouraged the king of France to begin hoſtilities, on which he had been for ſome time reſolved; and an action diſhonourable to civil ſociety furniſhed him with too good a pretext for taking arms. The marquis del Guaſto, governor oſ the Milaneſe, having got intelligence of the motions and deſtination of two ambaſſadors, Rincon and Fergoſo, whom Francis had diſpatched, the one to the Ottoman Porte, the other to the republic of Venice ; knowing how much his master wiſhed to diſcover the intentions of the French monarch, and of what conſequence it was to retard the execution of his meaſures, he employed ſome ſoldiers belonging to the garriſon oſ Pavia to lie in wait for theſe ambaſſadors as they ſailed down the Po, who murdered them and moſt of their attendants, and ſeized their papers. Francis immediately demanded reparation for this barbarous outrage ; and as Charles endeavoured to put him off with an evaſive anſwer, he appealed to all the courts of Europe, ſetting forth the heinouſneſs of the injury, the iniquity of the emperor in diſregarding his juſt requeſt, and the neceſſity of vengeance. But Charles, who was a more profound negotiator, defeated in a great meaſure the effects of theſe repreſentations : he ſecured the fidelity of the Proteſtant princes in Germany, by granting them new conceſſions ; and he engaged the king of England to eſpouſe his cauſe, under pretence of defending Europe againſt the Infidels ; while Francis was only able to form an alliance with the kings of Denmark and Sweden (who for the firſt time intereſted themſelves in the quarrels of the more potent monarchs of the ſouth), and to renew his treaty with Solyman, which drew on him the indignation of Chriſtendom.</p><p>But the activity oſ Francis ſupplied all the defects of his negotiation. Five armies were ſoon ready to take the field, under different generals, and with different deſtinations. Nor was Charles wanting in his preparations. He and Henry a ſecond time made an ideal diviſion of the kingdom of France. But as the hoſtilities which followed terminated in nothing deciſive, and were diſtinguiſhed by no remarkable event, except the battle of Ceriſoles (gained by count d’Enguien over the imperialiſts, and in which 10,000 of the emperor’s beſt</p><p>troops ſell), at laſt Francis and Charles, mutually tired of haraſſing each other, concluded at Creſpy a treaty of peace, in which the king of England was not mentioned ; and from being implacable enemies, became once more, to appearance, cordial friends, and even allies by the ties of blood.</p><p>The chief articles of this treaty were, that all the conqueſts which either party had made ſince the truce of Nice ſhould be reſtored ; that the emperor ſhould give in marriage to the duke of Orleans, either his own eldest daughter, with the Low Countries, or the ſecond daughter of his brother Ferdinand, with the inveſtiture of the Milaneſe ; that Francis should renounce all pretenſions to the kingdom of Naples, as well as to the ſovereignty of Flanders and Artois, and Charles give up his claim to the duchy of Burgundy ; and that both ſhould unite in making war againſt the Turks.</p><p>The emperor was chiefly induced to grant conditions ſo advantageous to France, by a desire of humbling the Proteſtant princes in Germany. With the papal juriſdiction, he foreſaw they would endeavour to throw off the imperial authority ; and he determined to make his zeal for the former a pretence for enforcing and extending the latter. However, the death of the duke of Orleans before the conſummation of his marriage, diſentangled the emperor from the moſt troubleſome ſtipulation in the treaty of Creſpy ; and the French monarch, being ſtill engaged in hoſtilities with England, was unable to obtain any reparation for the loſs which he ſuffered by this unforeſeen event. Theſe hoſtilities, like thoſe between Charles and Francis, terminated in nothing deciſive. Equally tired of a ſtruggle attended with no glory or advantage to either, the contending princes concluded, at Campe, near Ardies, a treaty of peace; in which it was ſtipulated, that France ſhould pay the arrears due by former treaties to England. But theſe arrears did not exceed one-third of the ſums expended by Henry on his military operations ; and Francis being in no condition to diſcharge them, Boulogne (a chargeable pledge) was left in the hands of the Engliſh as a ſecurity for the debt.</p><p>In conſequence of the emperor’s reſolution to humble the Proteſtant princes, he concluded a diſhonourable peace with the Porte, ſtipulating that his brother Ferdinand ſhould pay tribute for that part of Hungary which he ſtill possessed ; while the ſultan enjoyed the imperial and undiſturbed poſſeſſion of all the reſt. At the ſame time he entered into a league with pope Paul III. for the extirpation of hereſy ; but in reality with a view to oppreſs the liberties of Germany. Here, however, his ambition met with a ſevere check ; for though he was ſucceſsful at firſt, he was obliged in 1552 to conclude a peace with the Proteſtants on their own terms ; as has been related under the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Reformation,</hi> n⁰ 26—32.</p><p>By the peace concluded on this occaſion the emperor loſt Metz, Toul, and Verdun, which had formed the barrier of the empire on that quarter; and therefore ſoon after put himſelf at the head of an army, in order to recover theſe three biſhoprics. In order to conceal the deſtination of his army, he gave out, that he intended to lead it into Hungary, to ſecond Maurice in his operations againſt the Infidels ; and as that pretext failed him, when he began to advance towards the Rhine, he propagated a report that he was marching<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0647.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0641"/>
firſt to chaſtiſe Albert of Brandenburgh, who had refuſed to be included in the treaty of Paſſau, and whoſe cruel exactions in that part of Germany called loudly for redreſs.</p><p>The French, however, were not deceived by theſe arts. Henry immediately gueſſed the true object of Charles’s armament, and reſolved to defend his conqueſts with vigour. The defence of Metz, againſt which it was foreſeen the whole weight of the war would be turned, was committed to Francis of Lorraine, duke of Guile, who poſſeſſed in an eminent degree all the qualities that render men great in military command. He repaired with joy to the dangerous ſtation ; and many of the French nobility, and even princes of the blood, eager to diſtinguiſh themſelves under ſuch a leader, entered Metz as volunteers. The city was of great extent, ill fortified, and the ſuburbs large. For all theſe defects the duke endeavoured to provide a remedy. He repaired the old fortifications with all poſſible expedition, labouring with his own hands ; the officers imitated his example ; and the ſoldiers, thus encouraged, cheerfully submitted to the moſt ſevere toils ; he erected new works, and he levelled the ſuburbs with the ground. At the same time he filled the magazines with proviſions and military stores, compelled all uſeleſs perſons to leave the place, and laid waſte the neighbouring country; yet ſuch were his popular talents, as well as his arts of acquiring an aſcendant over the minds of men, that the citizens not only refrained from murmuring, but ſeconded him with no leſs ardour than the ſoldiers in all his operations— in the ruin of their eſtates, and in the havoc of their public and private buildings.</p><p>Meanwhile the emperor continued his march towards Lorraine, at the head of 60,000 men. On his approach Albert of Brandenburgh, whoſe army did not exceed 20,000, withdrew into that principality, as if he intended to join the French king ; and Charles, notwithstanding the advanced ſeaſon, it being towards the end of October, laid ſiege to Metz, contrary to the advice of his moſt experienced officers.</p><p>The attention of both the beſiegers and the beſieged was turned for ſome time towards the motions of Albert, who ſtill hovered in the neighbourhood, undetermined which ſide to take, though reſolved to ſell his ſervice. Charles at laſt came up to his price, and he joined the imperial army. The emperor now flattered himſelf that nothing could resist his force; but he found himſelf deceived. After a ſiege of almoſt 60 days, during which he had attempted all that was thought poſſible for art or valour to effect, and had loſt upwards of 30,000 men by the inclemency of the weather, diſeaſes, or the ſword of the enemy, he was obliged to abandon the enterpriſe.</p><p>When the French ſallied out to attack the enemy’s rear, the imperial camp was filled with the ſick and wounded, with the dead and the dying. All the roads by which the army retired were ſtrewed with the ſame miſerable objects ; who, having made an effort beyond their ſtrength to eſcape, and not being able to proceed, were left to periſh without aſſiſtance. Happily that, and all the kind offices which their friends had not the power to perform, they received ſrom their enemies. The duke of Guiſe ordered them all to be taken care of, and ſupplied with every necessary ; he appointed</p><p>phyſicians to attend, and direct what treatment was proper for the ſick and wounded, and what refreſhments for the feeble ; and ſuch as recovered he ſent home, under an eſcort of ſoldiers, and with money to bear their charges. By theſe acts of humanity, leſs common in that age, the duke of Guiſe completed that heroic character which he had juſtly acquired by his brave and ſucceſsful defence of Metz.</p><p>The emperor’s misfortunes were not confined to Germany. During his reſidence at Villach, he had been obliged to borrow 200,000 crowns of Coſmo de Medici ; and ſo low was his credit, that he was obliged to put Coſmo in poſſeſſion of the principality of Piombino as a ſecurity for that inconsiderable ſum ; by which means he loſt the footing he had hitherto maintained in Tuſcany. Much about the ſame time he loſt Sienna. The citizens, who had long enjoyed a republican government, roſe againſt the Spaniſh garriſon, which they had admitted as a check upon the tyranny of the nobility, but which they found was meant to enslave them ; forgetting their domeſtic animoſities, they recalled the exiled nobles ; they demoliſhed the citadel, and put themſelves under the protection of France.</p><p>To theſe unfortunate events one ſtill more fatal had almoſt ſucceeded. The ſevere adminiſtration of the viceroy of Naples had filled that kingdom with murmuring and diſſatisfaction. The prince of Salerno, the head of the malecontente, fled to the court of France. The French monarch, after the example of his father, applied to the grand ſignior ; and Solyman, at that time highly incensed againſt the houſe of Auſtria on account of the proceedings in Hungary, ſent a powerful fleet into the Mediterranean, under the command of the corſeir Dragut, an officer trained up under Barbaroſſa, and ſcarce inferior to his maſter in courage, talents, or in good fortune. Dragut appeared on the coaſt of Calabria at the time appointed ; but not being joined by the French fleet according to concert, he returned to Conſtantinople, after plundering and burning ſeveral places, and filling Naples with conſternation.</p><p>Highly mortified by ſo many diſaſters, Charles retired into the Low Countries, breathing vengeance againſt France : and here the war was carried on with conſiderable vigour. Impatient to efface the ſtain which his military reputation had received before Metz, Charles laid ſiege to Terouane ; and the fortifications being in diſrepair, that important place was carried by aſſault. Heſdin alſo was inveſted, and carried in the ſame manner. The king of France was too late in assembling his forces to afford relief to either of theſe places ; and the emperor afterwards cautiouſly avoided an engagement.</p><p>The imperial arms were leſs ſucceſsful in Italy. The viceroy of Naples failed in an attempt to recover Siena; and the French not only eſtabliſhed themſelves more firmly in Tuſcany, but conquered part of the iſland of Corsica. Nor did the affairs of the houſe of Auſtria go on better in Hungary during the courſe of this year. Iſabella and her son appeared once more in Tranſylvania, at a time when the people were ready for revolt, in order to revenge the death oſ Martinuzzi, whoſe loss they had ſeverely felt. Some noblemen of eminence declared in favour of the young king ; and the baſhaw of Belgrade, by Solyman’s order, espousing his cause,<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0648.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0642"/>
in oppoſition to Ferdinand, Caſtaldo, the Auſtrian general, was obliged to abandon Tranſylvania to Iſabella and the Turks.</p><p>In order to counterbalance theſe and other loſſes, the emperor, in 1554, concerted a marriage between his ſon Philip and Mary of England, in hopes of adding that kingdom to his other dominions. Meanwhile the war between Henry and Charles was carried on with various ſucceſs in the Low Countries, and in Italy much to the diſadvantage of France. The French, under the command of Strozzi, were defeated in the battle of Merciano ; Sienna was reduced by Medicino, the Florentine general, after a ſiege of ten months ; and the gallant Sienese were ſubjected to the Spaniſh yoke. Much about the ſame time a plot was formed by the Franciſcans, but happily diſcovered before it could be carried into execution, to betray Metz to the Imperialiſts. The father-guardian, and twenty other monks, received ſentence of death on account of this conſpiracy ; but the guardian, before the time appointed for his execution, was murdered by his incenſed accomplices, whom he had ſeduced ; and six of the youngeſt were pardoned.</p><p>While war thus raged in Italy and the Low Countries, Germany enjoyed ſuch profound tranquillity, as afforded the diet full leiſure to confirm and perfect the plan of religious pacification agreed upon at Paſſau, and referred to the conſideration of the next meeting of the Germanic body. During the negociation of this treaty, an event happened which aſtoniſhed all Europe, and confounded the reaſonings of the wiſeſt politicians. The emperor Charles V. though no more than 56, an age when objects of ambition operate with full force on the mind, and are generally purſued with the greateſt ardour, had for ſome time formed the reſolution of reſigning his hereditary dominions to his ſon Philip. He now determined to put it in execution. Various have been the opinions of hiſtorians concerning a reſolution ſo singular and unexpected; but the moſt probable ſeem to be, the diſappointments which Charles had met with in his ambitious hopes, and the daily decline of his health. He had early in life been attacked with the gout ; and the fits were now become ſo frequent and ſevere, that not only the vigour of his conſtitution was broken, but the faculties of his mind were ſenſibly impaired. He therefore judged it more decent to conceal his infirmities in ſome ſolitude, than to expoſe them any longer to the public eye ; and as he was unwilling to forfeit the same, or loſe the acquiſitions of his better years, by attempting to guide the reins of government when he was no longer able to hold them with ſteadiness, he determined to ſeek in the tranquillity of retirement, that happineſs which he had in vain purſued amidſt the tumults of war and the intrigues of ſtate.</p><p>In conſequence of this reſolution, Charles, who had already ceded to his ſon Philip the kingdom of Naples and the duchy of Milan, assembled the ſtates of the Low Countries at Bruſſels ; and ſeating himſelf for the laſt time in the chair of ſtate, he explained to his ſubjects the reaſons of his reſignation, and ſolemnly devolved his authority upon Philip. He recounted with dignity, but without oſtentation, all the great things which he had undertaken and performed ſince the commencement of his adminiſtration. “ I have dedicated</p><p>(obſerved he), from the 17th year of my age, all my thoughts and attention to public objects, reſerving no portion of my time for the indulgence of ease, and very little for the enjoyment of private pleaſure. Either in a pacific or hoſtile manner, I have visited Germany nine times, Spain six times, France four times, Italy ſeven times, the Low Countries ten times, England twice, Africa as often ; and while my health permitted me to diſcharge the duty of a ſovereign, and the vigour of my conſtitution was equal in any degree to the arduous office of governing ſuch extenſive dominions, I never ſhunned labour, nor repined under fatigue ; but now, when my health is broken, and my vigour exhauſted by the rage of an incurable diſtemper, my growing infirmities admoniſh me to retire ; nor am I ſo fond of reigning, as to retain the ſceptre in an impotent hand, which is no longer able to protect my ſubjects. Inſtead of a ſovereign worn out with diſeaſes (continued he), and ſcarce half alive, I give you one in the prime of life, already accuſtomed to govern, and who adds to the vigour of youth all the attention and ſagacity of maturer years.” Then turning towards Philip, who fell on his knees, and kiſſed his father’s hand, “ It is in your power (ſaid Charles), by a wiſe and virtuous adminiſtration, to juſtiſy the extraordinary proof which I give this day of my paternal affection, and to demonſtrate that you are worthy of the extraordinary confidence which I repoſe in you. Preſerve (added he) an inviolable regard tor religion ; maintain the Catholic faith in its purity ; let the laws of your country be ſacred in your eyes ; encroach not on the rights of your people; and if the time ſhould ever come when you ſhall wiſh to enjoy the tranquillity of private life, may you have a ſon to whom you can reſign your ſceptre with as much ſatisfaction as I give up mine to you.” A few weeks after, he reſigned to Philip the ſovereignty of Spain and America; reſeiving nothing to himſelf out of all theſe vaſt poſſeſſions but an annual penſion of 100,000 crowns.</p><p>Charles was now impatient to embark for Spain, where he had fixed on a place of retreat ; but by the advice of his phyſicians, he put off his voyage for ſome months, on account of the ſeverity of the ſeaſon ; and, by yielding to their judgment, he had the ſatisfaction before he left the Low Countries of taking a conſiderable ſtep towards a peace with France. This he ardently longed for; not only on his ſon’s account, whoſe adminiſtration he wiſhed to commence in quietneſs, but that he might have the glory, when quitting the world, of reſtoring to Europe that tranquillity which his ambition had baniſhed out of it almoſt from the time that he aſſumed the reins of government.</p><p>The great bar to ſuch a pacification, on the part of France, was the treaty which Henry had concluded with the Pope ; and the emperor’s claims were too numerous to hope for adjuſting them ſuddenly. A truce of five years was therefore propoſed by Charles ; during which term, without diſcuſſing their reſpective pretenſions, each ſhould retain what was in his poſſeſſion ; and Henry, through the perſuasion of the conſtable Montmorency, who repreſented the imprudence of ſacrificing the true intereſts of his kingdom to the raſh engagements that he had come under with Paul, authoriſed his ambaſſadors to ſign at Vaucelles a treaty,<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0649.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0643"/>
which would inſure to him for ſo conſiderable a period the important conqueſt which he had made on the German frontier, together with the greater part of the duke of Savoy’s dominions.</p><p>The Pope, when informed of this tranſaction, was no leſs filled with terror and aſtoniſhment than rage and indignation. But he took equal care to conceal his fear and his anger. He affected to approve highly of the truce; and he offered his mediation, as the common father of Chriſtendom, in order to bring about a definitive peace. Under this pretext, he appointed cardinal Rebibo his nuncio to the court of Bruſſels, and his nephew cardinal Caraſſa to that of Paris. The public instructions of both were the ſame ; but Caraſſa, beſides theſe, received a private cornmiſſion, to ſpare neither intreaties, promiſes, nor bribes, in order to induce the French monarch to renounce the truce and renew his engagements with the holy ſee. He flattered Henry with the conqueſt of Naples ; he gained by his addreſs the Guiſes, the queen, and even the famous Diana of Poictiers, ducheſs of Valentinois, the king’s miſtrels ; and they easily ſwayed the king himſelf, who already leaned to that ſide towards which they wiſhed to incline him. All Montmorency’s prudent remonſtrances were diſregarded ; the nuncio (by powers from Rome) abſolved Henry from his oath of truce ; and that weak prince ſigned a new treaty with the Pope ; which rekindled with freſh violence the flames oſ war, both in Italy and the Low Countries.</p><p>No ſooner was Paul made acquainted with the ſucceſs of this negotiation than he proceeded to the moſt indecent extremities againſt Philip. He ordered the Spaniſh ambaſſador to be impriſoned ; he excommunicated the Colonnas, becauſe of their attachment to the imperial houſe ; and he conſidered Philip as guilty of high treaſon, and to have forfeited his right to the kingdom of Naples, which he was ſuppoſed to hold of the holy ſee, for afterward affording them a retreat in his dominions.</p><p>Alarmed at a quarrel with the Pope, whom he had been taught to regard with the moſt ſuperſtitious veneration, as the vicegerent of Chriſt and the common father of Chriſtendom, Philip tried every gentle method before he made uſe of force. He even conſulted ſome Spaniſh divines on the lawfulneſs of taking arms againſt a perſon ſo ſacred. They decided in his favour ; and Paul continuing inexorable, the duke of Alva, to whom the negotiations as well as the war had been committed, entered the ecclesiaſtical ſtate at the head of 10,000 veterans, and carried terror to the gates of Rome.</p><p>The haughty pontiff, though ſtill inflexible and undaunted in himſelf, was forced to give way to the tears of the cardinals, and a truce was concluded for 40 days. Mean time the duke of Guiſe arriving with a ſupply of 20,000 French troops, Paul became more arrogant than ever, and baniſhed all thoughts from his mind but thoſe of war and revenge. The duke of Guiſe, however, who had precipitated his country into this war, chiefly from a deſire of gaining a field where he might diſplay his own talents, was able to perform nothing in Italy worthy of his former fame. He was obliged to abandon the ſiege of Civetella ; he could not bring the duke of Alva so a general engagement ; his army periſhed by diſeaſes ; and the Pope neglected to furniſh the neceſ</p><p>ſary reinforcements. He begged to be recalled ; and France ſtood in need of his abilities.</p><p>Philip, though willing to have avoided a rupture, was no ſooner informed that Henry had violated the truce of Vaucelles, than he determined to act with ſuch vigour, as ſhould convince Europe that his father had not erred in religning to him the reigns of government. He immediately assembled in the Low Countries a body of 50,000 men, and obtained a ſupply of 10,000 from England, which he had engaged in his quarrel ; and as he was not ambitious of military fame, he gave the command of his army to Emanuel Philibert duke of Savoy, one of the greateſt generals of that warlike age.</p><p>The duke of Savoy kept the enemy for ſome time in ſuſpenſe with regard to his deſtination ; at laſt he ſeemed to threaten Champagne; towards which the French drew all their troops ; then turning ſuddenly to the right, he advanced by rapid marches into Picardy, and laid ſiege to St Quintin. It was deemed in thoſe times a town of conſiderable ſtrength ; but the fortifications had been much neglected, and the garriſon did not amount to a fifth part of the number requisite ſor its defence : it muſt therefore have ſurrendered in a few days, if the admiral de Coligny had not taken the gallant reſolution of throwing himſelf into it with ſuch a body of men as could he collected on a ſudden. This he effected in ſpite of the enemy, breaking through their main body. The place, however, was cloſely inveſted; and the conſtable Montmorency, anxious to extricate his nephew out of that perilous ſituation, in which his zeal for the public had engaged him, as well as to ſave a town of ſuch importance, raſhly advanced to its relief with forces one half inferior to thoſe oſ the enemy. His army was cut in pieces, and he himſelf made priſoner.</p><p>The cautious temper of Philip on this occaſion ſaved France ſrom devaſtation, if not ruin. The duke of Savoy propoſed to overlook all inferior objects, and march ſpeedily to Paris, which, in its preſent conſternation, he could not have failed to make himſelf maſter of ; but Philip, afraid of the conſequences of ſuch a bold enterpriſe, deſired him to continue the ſiege of St Quintin, in order to ſecure a ſaſe retreat in caſe of any diſaſtrous event. The town, long and gallantly defended by Coligny, was at laſt taken by storm ; but not till France was in a ſtate of defence.</p><p>Philip was now ſensible that he had loſt an opportunity which could never be recalled, of diſtreſſing his enemy, and contented himſelf with reducing Horn and Catelet ; which petty towns, together with St Quintſh, were the ſole fruits of one of the moſt decisive victories gained in the 16th century. The Catholic king, however, continued in high exultation on account of his ſucceſs ; and as all his paſſions were tinged with superſtition, he vowed to build a church, a monaſtery, and a palace, in honour oſ St Laurence, on the day ſacred to whoſe memory the battle of St Quintin had been fought. He accordingly laid the foundation of an edifice, in which all theſe were included, and which he continued to forward at vaſt expence, for <hi rend="italic">22</hi> years. The ſame principle which dictated the vow directed the building. It was ſo formed as to reſemble a gridiron —on which culinary inſtrument, according to the legendary tale,<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0650.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0644"/>
St Laurence had ſuffered martyrdom. Such is the origin of the famous eſcurial near Madrid, the royal reſidence of the kings of Spain.</p><p>The firſt account oſ that fatal blow which France had received at St Quintin, was carried to Rome by the courier whom Henry had ſent to recal the duke of Guiſe. Paul remonſtrated warmly againſt the departure of the French army ; but Guiſe’s orders were peremptory. The arrogant pontiff therefore found it neceſſary to accommodate his conduct to the exigency of his affairs, and to employ the mediation of the Venetians, and of Coſmo de Mcdici, in order to obtain peace. The firſt overtures of this nature were eagerly liſtened to by the Catholic king, who ſtill doubted the juſtice of his cauſe, and conſidered it as his greateſt miſfortune to be obliged to contend with the Pope. Paul agreed to renounce his league with France; and Philip ſtipulated on his part, that the duke of Alva ſhould repair in perſon to Rome, and after aſking pardon of the holy father in his own name and in that of his maſter, for having invaded the patrimony of the church, ſhould receive abſolution ſrom that crime. Thus Paul, thro’ the ſuperſtitious timidity of Philip, only finiſhed an unpropitious war not without any detriment to the apoſtolic ſee, but ſaw his conqueror humbled at his feet : and ſo exceſſive was the veneration of the Spaniards in that age for the papal character, that the duke oſ Alva, the proudeſt man perhaps of his time, and accuſtomed from his infancy to converſe with princes, acknowledged, that when he approached Paul, he was ſo much overawed, that his voice failed, and his preſence of mind forſook him.</p><p>But though this war, which at its commencement threatened mighty revolutions, was terminated without occaſioning any alteration in thoſe ſtates which were its immediate object, it produced effects of conſiderable conſequence in other parts of Italy. In order to detach Octavio Farneſe, duke of Parma, from the French intereſt, Philip reſtored to him the city of Placentia and its territory, which had been ſeized by Charles V. and he granted to Coſmo de Medici the inveſtiture of Sienna, as an equivalent for the ſums due to him. By theſe treaties, the balance of power among the Italian ſtates was poiſed with more equality, and rendered leſs variable than it had been ſince it received the firſt violent ſhock from the invaſion of Charles VIII. and Italy henceforth ceaſed to be the theatre on which the monarchs of Spain, France, and Germany, contended for fame and dominion. Their hoſtilities, excited by new objects, ſtained other regions of Europe with blood, and made other ſtates feel, in their turn, the miſeries of war.</p><p>The duke of Guiſe, who left Rome the ſame day that his adverſary the duke of Alva made his humiliating ſubmiſſion to the Pope, was received in France as the guardian angel of the kingdom. He was appointed lieutenant-general in chief, with a juriſdiction almoſt unlimited ; and, eager to juſtify the extraordinary confidence which the king had repoſed in him, as well as to perform ſomething ſuitable to the high expectations of his countrymen, he undertook in winter the siege of Calais. Having taken that place, he next inveſted Thionville in the duchy of Luxembourg, one oſ the ſtrongeſt towns on the frontiers of the Netherlands; and forced it to capitulate after a ſiege of three weeks. But</p><p>the advantages on this quarter were more than balanced by an event which happened in another part of the Low Countries. The mareſchal de Termes governor of Calais, who had penetrated into Flanders and taken Dunkirk, was totally routed near Gravelines, and taken priſoner by count Egmont. This diſaſter obliged the duke of Guiſe to relinquiſh all his other ſchemes, and halten towards the frontiers of Picardy, that he might there oppoſe the progreſs of the enemy.</p><p>The eyes of all France were now turned towards the duke of Guiſe, as the only general on whoſe arms victory always attended, and in whoſe conduct as well as good fortune they could confide in every danger. His ſtrength was nearly equal to the duke of Savoy’s, each commanding about 40,000 men. They encamped at the diſtance of a few leagues from one another; and the French and Spaniſh monarchs having joined their reſpective armies, it was expected that, after the viciſſitudes of war, a deciſive battle would at laſt determine which of the rivals ſhould take the aſcendant for the future in the affairs of Europe. But both monarchs, as if by agreement, ſtood on the defenſive ; neither of them diſcovering any inclination, though each had it in his power, to reſt the deciſion of a point oſ ſuch importance on the iſſue of a ſingle battle.</p><p>During this ſtate of inaction, peace began to be mentioned in each camp, and both Henry and Philip diſcovered an equal diſpoſition to liſten to any overture that tended to re-eſtabliſh it. The private inclinations oſ both kings concurred with their political intereſts and the wiſhes of their people. Philip languiſhed to return to Spain, the place of his nativity ; and peace only could enable him, either with decency or ſafety, to quit the Low Countries. Henry was now deſirous of being freed from the avocations of war, that he might have leiſure to turn the whole force of his government towards ſuppreſſing the opinions of the reformers, which were ſpreading with ſuch rapidity in Paris and the other great towns, that they began to grow formidable to the eſtabliſhed church. Court-intrigues conlpired with theſe public and avowed motives to hasten the negotiation, and the abbey of Cercamp was fixed on as the place of congreſs.</p><p>While Philip and Henry were making theſe advances towards a treaty which reſtored tranquillity to Europe, Charles V. whoſe ambition had ſo long diſturbed it, but who had been for ſome time dead to the world, ended his days in the monaſtery of St Juſtus in Eſtremadura, which he had choſen as the place of his retreat, as is particularly related Under the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Charles</hi> V.</p><p>Aſter the death of Charles, the kingdom of Spain ſoon loſt great part of its conſequence. Though Charles had uſed all his intereſt to get his ſon Philip elected emperor of Germany, he had been totally diſappointed ; and thus the grandeur of Philip II. never equalled that of his father. His dominions were alſo considerably abridged by his tyrannical behaviour in the Netherlands. In conſequence of this, the United Provinces revolted; and after along and bloody war obtained their liberty<note anchored="true" n="2" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>* See United Provinces.</p></note> *. In this quarrel Elizabeth of England took part againſt Philip, which brought on a war with Spain. The great loſſes he ſuſtained in theſe wars exhauſted the kingdom both of men and money, notwithſtanding the great ſums imported from America. Indeed, the diſcovery and conqueſt of that country hath much impoveriſhed, in-<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0651.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0645"/>
ſtead oſ enriching Spain ; for thus the inhabitants have been rendered lazy and averſe from every kind of manufacture or traffic, which only can be a durable ſource of riches and ſtrength to any nation. The ruin of the kingdom in this reſpect, however, was completed by Philip III. who, at the inſtigation of the inquiſition, and by the advice of his prime miniſter the duke of Lerma, expelled from the kingdom all the Morescoes or Moors, deſcendants of the ancient conquerors of Spain. Thirty days only were allowed them to prepare for their departure, and it was death to remain beyond that time. The reaſon for this barbarous decree was, that theſe people were ſtill Mahometans in their hearts, though they conformed externally to the rites of Chriſtianity, and thus might corrupt the true faith. The Moreſcoes, however, choſe themſelves a king, and attempted to oppoſe the royal mandate ; but, being almoſt entirely unprovided with arms, they were ſoon obliged to submit, and all baniſhed the kingdom. By this violent and impolitic meaſure, Spain loſt almoſt a million of induſtrious inhabitants; and as the kingdom was already depopulated by bloody wars, by repeated emigrations to America, and enervated by luxury, it now ſank into a ſtate of languor from whence it has never recovered.</p><p>In conſequence of this languor, and the maladministration of the Spaniſh governors, Portugal, which had been reduced by Philip II. revolted, and has ever ſince been an independent kingdom<note anchored="true" n="3" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>*</p></note> *. However, the memory of what Spain once was, remained for a conſiderable time, and the power of that kingdom long continued to be feared after it had ceaſed to be powerful. In the time of queen Anne, a Britiſh army was ſeen for the firſt time in Spain, in order to ſupport Charles of Auſtria againſt Philip the grandſon of Louis XIV. The ill ſucceſs of that attempt is related under the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Britain,</hi> n⁰ 342—359 ; and thus the crown of Spain fell to a branch of the houſe of Bourbon, in conſequence of which the courts of France and Spain generally acted in the cloſeſt concert till the revolution, which at preſent aſtoniſhes Europe, put an end to monarchical government in the former country. The wars of theſe two courts with <hi rend="smallcaps">Britain</hi> are related under that article and <hi rend="smallcaps">America</hi>; and theſe, with an unſuccessful attempt on Algiers, and the threatened war reſpecting NOOTKA <hi rend="italic">Sound</hi> (ſee that article), conſtitute the moſt important part of the Spaniſh hiſtory till the deposition and murder of Louis XVI. of France. On that event Spain joined her forces to thoſe of the Empire, Britain, and Pruſſia, to chaſtiſe the Convention, and prevent thoſe democratical principles which had ruined France from being ſpread through the other nations of Europe. We cannot ſay that her exertions added much to the ſtrength of the alliance; and being unable to defend herſelf againſt the furious inroads of the republican troops, ſhe was glad to make a ſeparate peace with the Convention. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Revolution.</hi></p><p>The air of Spain, during the months of June, July, and Auguſt, is exceſſively hot in the day-time ; but the reſt of the year it is pleaſant and temperate. Even during the above months it is very cool in the ſhade ; and so cold in the night, that it makes a traveller ſhiver ; and in the day-time the violent heat continues only for about four or five hours. In the north, on</p><p>the mountains, and near the ſea-coaſt, the air is much leſs ſultry in ſummer than in the ſouth, eſpecially in the lower parts of the country, and at a diſtance from the ſea. It ſeldom rains here, except about the equinoxes : the froſts are very gentle towards the ſouth ; but on the mountains in the north and north-eaſt the air is very ſharp in winter.</p><p>Though there are ſome ſandy barren deſerts in the ſouth, and many barren mountains in the north, yet in the greater part of the country, particularly in the valleys and plains, the ſoil is good, producing a great variety of rich wines, oil, and fruits ; ſuch as oranges, lemons, prunes, citrons, almonds, raiſins, dates, figs, cheſnuts, pomegranates, capers, pears, and peaches ; but not a ſufficiency of grain, which is chiefly owing to the neglect of tillage. Wheat and barley are the moſt common grain ; the former of which is ſaid by ſome to be the beſt in Europe. There is not much flax, hemp, oats, or hay, in Spain : but there is plenty of honey, ſalt, fine wool, ſilk, and cotton ; and, in ſome places, of rice and ſugar-canes. Here alſo are abundance of mules, and, in ſome provinces, of horſes, together with, deer, wild fowl, and other game, chamois and other goats, but few horned cattle. Wolves are almoſt the only wild beaſts in the country. The herb kali, which is uſed in making ſalt, ſoap, and glaſs, grows in great plenty on the ſea-ſhore. The wild bulls, uſed in their bull-fights, are bred in Andaluſia. The ſeas about Spain: are well ſtored with fiſh; among which is the anchovy, in the Mediterranean. We may gueſs at the number of ſheep here by that of the ſhepherds, which is ſaid to be about forty thouſand. The ſheep that bear the fine wool move regularly, every ſummer, from ſouth to north, along the mountains, which yield a great variety of ſweet herbs and plants, and return again towards winter. During this progreſs, large quantities of ſalt are diſtributed among them, and all poſſible care is taken both of their health and fleeces.</p><p>The chief mountains are the Pyrenees, which ſtretch from the Mediterranean to the Atlantic Ocean, but not in a direct line, for near 200 miles : their breadth is, in ſome places, not leſs than 80. That called the <hi rend="italic">Pic de Midi</hi> is of a prodigious height. Over theſe mountains there are only about five paſſages out of Spain into France, and theſe alſo narrow ; even the valleys between the mountains are covered with thick and lofty woods. The other chains in Spain are the Sierra d’Occa, Sierra Molino, Sierra Moreno, and Sierra Nevada or the ſnowy mountains. Near Gibraltar, opposite to Mount Abyla in Africa, ſtands the celebrated Mount Calpe : theſe were anciently called <hi rend="italic">Hercules's pillars.</hi> The mountains yield great quantities of timber for ſhipping, which are conveyed by the Ebro and other rivers to the Mediterranean. According to the ancient and modern writers, they abound alſo with gold, ſilver, iron, lead, tin, cinnabar, quickſilver, alum, vitriol, copperas, lapis calaminaris, &amp; c. beſides gems, and mineral waters both hot and cold. The gold and ſilver mines are not worked at preſent, but those of iron are. The neglect of the former is owing partly to the indolence of the Spaniards, and partly to the gold and ſilver imported from America. Beſides the rivers Minho, Douro, Tagus, Monda, Lima, and Guadiana, mentioned in Portugal, but which have their ſources in Spain,<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0652.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0646"/>
the moſt conſiderable are the Ebro, formerly I <hi rend="italic">berus,</hi> Guadalavier, anciently <hi rend="italic">Turia,</hi> Guadalquiver or <hi rend="italic">Bcetis,</hi> Segura, and Xucar.</p><p>The Spaniards are zealous Romaniſts. Nowhere is there more pomp, farce, and parade, in what regards religion ; and nowhere leſs true Chriſtianity. Their zeal and their ſuperſtition exceed that of any other Roman Catholic country, unleſs perhaps we ſhould except Portugal. Nowhere did the inquiſition reign with greater terror; there being no ſubject who was not liable to be proſecuted by the <hi rend="italic">holy office,</hi> as it is called ; however, the powers of that tribunal are now greatly diminiſhed even in Spain. There are eight arehbiſhops in Spain, ſeven in America, and one in Aſia at Manilla ; each of which has his ſuffragan biſhops. The archbiſhop of Toledo is primate, chancellor of Caſtile, and, by virtue of his office, privy-counſellor. He is ſaid to have a revenue of 100,000 l. Sterling <hi rend="italic">per annum,</hi> or more. The king nominates all archbiſhops and biſhops ; and ſince 1753 all ſmall benefices are alſo in his gift. He has alſo lately obtained a power to tax eccleſiaſtical poſſeſſions, according to his pleaſure and the exigency of affairs. Though the reſt of the nation is poor, the clergy are immenſely rich, and their revenues of all kinds very great. Moſt of the towns and eſtates belong to them, and are exempt from all public burdens ; yet their avarice is inſatiable, eſpecially that of the Mendicant friars, though they profeſs poverty. Their commerce, which is free from all duties and impolis, is alſo a rich fund to them. Though the Spaniards are naturally men of wit and of an elevated genius, yet little progreſs in the ſciences is to be expected from them, while the clergy uſe their utmoſt efforts to keep them in ignorance, branding all literary researches with the name of heresy, and inveighing againſt the ſeats of the muſes as the ſchools of hell, where the devil teaches ſorcery. There are 22 univerſities, and ſeveral academies, in Spain ; but ſo conſtituted, and under ſuch reſtrictions, that they can never attain to any meaſure of true learning. There are few printing-houſes in Spain ; and moſt oſ the books in that language are publiſhed in other countries.</p><p>In regard to trade and manufactures, the Spaniards are far from making ſuch a figure as might be expected. Moſt of the laborious work in their husbandry, manufactures, and handicrafts, is performed by the French, eſpecially in the two Caſtiles and the midland provinces, the natives being either too lazy or too proud to ſtoop to ſuch employments. By theſe means, the French uſually return with large fortunes to their own country. The chief manufactures of Spain are thoſe of ſilk, wool, iron, copper, and other hardwares; but theſe fall far ſhort of the flouriſhing condition to which they might be brought: hence a great part of the treaſures of America go to the foreign merchants, who ſupply them with goods for that part of the world. However, it is certain, that Spain, ſince it hath had princes of the houſe of Bourbon upon the throne, hath improved its revenues, increaſed its forces by sea and land, and applied itſelf more than it did before to manufactures and husbandry ; having ſhaken off, in ſome meaſure, that idle indolent diſposition which rendered it ſo contemptible in the eyes of other nations ; but it will be a long time before they will be able to ſupply the wants of their own country, and thoſe of America, in any great</p><p>degree. Spain is extremely well ſituated for trade : but moſt of its produce is exported by foreigners, except what is carried to the Indies ; and even with regard to that trade, they are little better than factors to the Engliſh, French, Dutch, and Italians. Smuggling, which was formerly carried to a great height, is now in a great meaſure ſuppreſſed. Since the year 1750, the exportation of ſilver hath been allowed on the payment of 3 <hi rend="italic">per cent.</hi> From 1735 almoſt to 1756, the flotas and galleons were discontinued, and the trade to America carried on in regiſter-ſhips, which any merchant might ſend, on permiſſion obtained from the council of the Indies : but then the flotas and galleons were reſtored. The Aſſogue ſhips are two veſſels which carry quicksilver on the king’s account to Vera Cruz. There is a company which has an excluſive grant for trading to the Caraccas ; and another for trading to Porto Rico, the Bay of Honduras, the province of Guatimala and Hiſpaniola ; but the Spaniſh part of the laſt, it is ſaid, hath been lately ceded to the French. One ſhip, and ſometimes two, sails annually from Manilla, in the iſland of Luconia, one of the Philippines, for Acapulco in Mexico : her cargo, which belongs to the convents, conſiſts of the principal commodities of that part of the world ; but the return from Acapulco is for the moſt part made in money, and amounts to a vaſt ſum, as appeared from the treaſure found on board the Acapulco ſhip taken by Lord Anſon. In return for the manufactures ſent to America, the Spaniards receive gold, ſilver, cochineal, indigo, the cocoa or chocolate nut, logwood and other dyeing woods, ſugar, tobacco, ſnuff, and other productions of that part of the world ; ſupplying moſt part of Europe and Aſia with the ſilver which they bring from thence in their galleons. In the time of the Moors and Goths, this kingdom was exceedingly populous. It is ſaid to have then contained between twenty and thirty millions ; whereas now it does not contain above nine : and this, among other cauſes, is owing to the pride and lazineſs of the inhabitants, want of manufactures and good regulations, neglect of the mines and agriculture, the expulſion of the Moors, the peopling of America, heavy taxes, the great number of convents, exceſſive venery, and the consequent infecundity of both ſexes. Their debauchery and sterility are partly occaſioned by their way of living ; for they make great uſe of ſpices, and drink a great deal of chocolate, and ſtrong wine mixed with brandy. The cauſes aſſigned for the want of people in Spain will account in ſome meaſure for its poverty ; notwithſtanding it is computed that it receives one year with another, ſetting aſide other ſums, above 26 millions of pieces of eight, in regiſtered gold and ſilver. As moſt of the manufactures that are ſent to America are furniſhed by Britain, France, Italy, and Holland, ſo a great part of the treaſure brought home by the galleons is paid to the merchants of thoſe nations.</p><p>The conſtitution of Spain is at preſent an abſolute hereditary monarchy, where the females inherit in default of the males. The king, in his title, enumerates moſt of the provinces and particular parts of the dominions he has been or is poſſeſſed of. In ſpeaking of him, he is commonly called his <hi rend="italic">Catholic Majeſty,</hi> or the <hi rend="italic">Catholic King.</hi> The hereditary prince is commonly ſtyled <hi rend="italic">Prince of Asturias,</hi> and the other royal children <hi rend="italic">Infants,</hi> The kings of Spain are never crowned; they<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0653.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0647"/>
ſeem to have a power to difpoſe of the crown to what branch of the royal family they pleaſe. For the adminiſtration of the government and of juſtice, here are ſeveral councils and tribunals ; as the junto or cabinet- council, the privy-council, the council of war, the council of Caſtile, the council of the inquiſition, the council of finances, the council of the Indies, the ſeven courts of royal audiences, &amp; c.</p><p>The general hiſtory oſ Spain proves how great an influence the Cortes had in former times in the moſt important affairs of government ; ſuch as war or peace, and the levying of taxes. But during a long courſe of years they have not been aſſembled, except for the lake of form ; and the ſovereigns, without violence, or formally rejecting their intervention, have found means to elude their authority. They promulgate from the throne certain ordinances under the name of <hi rend="italic">Pragmatics,</hi> the preambles of which give us to underſtand, that they claim the ſame authority as if they had been publiſhed in the aſſembly of the Cortes ; who are never convoked but at the acceſſion of a new monarch, to adminiſter to him an oath in the name of the nation, and to ſwear fidelity to him. As this event happened ſo lately as the month of September 1789, when the preſent king of Spain received the homage of all his ſubjects in the church of St Jerome at Madrid, it may not be unacceptable to give an account of the uſual mode of aſſembling them.</p><p>“ On this occasion letters oſ convocation are ſent to all the Grandees ; to all perſons bearing titles of Caſtile ; to all the prelates ; and to every city which has a right to ſend deputies to the Cortes. The two firſt claſſes repreſent the nobility; the prieſts sit in the name of the clergy ; and the cities, which depute one of their magiſtrates, repreſent the people.” Except on the above-mentioned occasion, the Cortes of the whole kingdom have been aſſembled but twice during the preſent century, and only once upon public buſineſs, in the year 1713, when Philip V. convoked them to give their approbation to the Pragmatic Sanction, which changed the order oſ ſucceſſion to the throne. They are ſtill conſulted, for the ſake of form, in certain caſes ; but then, the members of which they are compoſed correſpond with each other without aſſembling. At their breaking up in 1713, it was regulated, that they ſhould be repreſented by a permanent committee, whoſe office it ſhould be to watch over the adminiſtration of that part of the taxes known by the name of <hi rend="italic">Millones,</hi> and which had been granted under Philip II. with the formal conſent of the Cortes, upon certain conditions, which the monarch ſwore to obſerve. They retained the adminiſtration of theſe impoſts until the year 1718, when cardinal Alberoni, whoſe ardent and imperious genius was irritated at ſuch ſhackles, transferred it to the hands of the sovereign. From that time, the aſſemblies of the deputies of the kingdom have received no more of the revenues of the ſtate than is neceſſary to pay the ſalaries and defray the expences of the members. Theſe are eight in number, and are choſen in the following manner : All the provinces of Caſtile unite to nominate six ; Catalonia and Majorca appoint one ; and the regencies of Valentia and Aragon elect the eighth. Theſe deputies hold their places six years, at the end of which a new election takes place in the ſame manner. As a relict oſ their ancient rights, they ſtill retain the privilege of being, by virtue of their places, members of the council of finances, by which the sovereign communicates to the nation the neceſſity of levying any new tax; and the approbation they are ſuppoſed to give to the royal reſolution, is a ſhadow of the conſent of the Cortes, without which taxes could not formerly be either levied or augmented. But it is eaſy to perceive how feeble this rampart oſ liberty muſt be, which is only formed of a ſmall number of citizens, who poſſeſs but little real power ; are under the controul of government, from which they expect favours and preferments; and who, after all, repreſent the moſt numerous indeed, but leaſt reſpected, part of the nation. The provinces of Biſcay and Navarre, which have aſſemblies and particular privileges, ſend alſo, on ſome occaſions, deputies to the throne ; but they do not make a part of the body of the deputies of the kingdom, and their conſtituents fix at pleaſure the object and duration of their temporary miſſion.</p><p>The adminiſtration of Spain is divided into six principal departments. The miniſter for foreign affairs is in many reſpects the directing miniſter, and receives, as a mark of diſtinction, the title of ſecretary of ſtate. The miniſter of war has but a circumſcribed authority. He is preſident of the council of war, which is rather a tribunal than a board of adminiſtration ; but the inſpectors of the infantry, and thoſe of the cavalry, dragoons, and provincial regiments, draw up a ſtatement of whatever relates to the corps of which they have the direction ; and the miniſter at war has only to preſent the memorials they give in to the king. The marine miniſter has no aſſociates. The chiefs of the three departments of Ferrol, Carthagena, and Cadiz, and inspectors of the marine, are named by the king, on the repreſentation of the miniſter ; but the marine ordinances prepared by him alone, require only the sanction of the king. The miniſter oſ the finances ſhould properly be under the inſpection of the ſuperintendant- general of that department ; but theſe two offices were ſome time ſince united, and will probably be ſo continued; for the ſeparation of them would multiply, without necessity, the ſprings of government ; and the intereſts of the ſtate require that they ſhould be ſimplified as much as permanent forms, thoſe ſacred bulwarks of juſtice and property, will admit.</p><p>The higher nobility conſiſt of counts, marquises, and dukes. The grandees, who have precedence of all others, next the king and princes of the blood, are named out of theſe. They have the privilege of being covered in the king’s preſence, who ſtyles them in his letters <hi rend="italic">Illustrious ;</hi> and in ſpeaking to them or of them, <hi rend="italic">their Eminences :</hi> but there are others beside the grandees who are covered in the king’s preſence ; as cardinals, nuncios, archbiſhops, the grand prior of Caſtile and the grand prior of Malta, the generals of the orders of St Dominic and St Francis, ambaſſadors of crowned heads, the knights of the golden fleece, and of the three military orders of St James, Calatrava, and Alcantara, when the king aſſiſts at their reſpective chapters in quality of grandmaſter. No grandee can be apprehended for any crime but by the expreſs order of the king ; and they have many other privileges beſides theſe. The inferior nobility ſtyle themſelves <hi rend="italic">Cavallerοs</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Hidalgos.</hi></p><p>Of the orders in Spain, that of the golden fleece is<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0654.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0648"/>
the principal ; which was inſtituted in 1430 by Philip the good duke of Burgundy, and is common now to the kings of Spain and the houſe of Auſtria. The order of St Jago de Compoſtella was inſtituted in the year 1175 by Ferdinand IL king of Leon. The order of Calatrava was founded by Sancho III. of Caſtile. The order of Alcantara owes its inſtitution to Ferdinand II, king of Leon. The three laſt orders have large commanderies or eſtates annexed to them. The maſters of them were once ſo powerful, that they diſputed the king’s authority over them ; whereupon the king procured thoſe maſterſhips to be conferred on himſelf by the Pope, that they might no longer aſſume an independency of the ſtate. The knights of theſe three orders are eſteemed noblemen.</p><p>In the laſt century, the revenues of Spain amounted to 32 or 33 millions of livres ; but afterwards they were so reduced, that they did not exceed ſeven or eight millions. At preſent, the revenues of the crown arising in Spain are computed at five millions Sterling <hi rend="italic">per annum, b</hi> eſides what ariſes from America. The ſilver mines there are inexhauſtible ; and of the produce of theſe a fifth belongs to the king. The taxes in Spain are numerous and heavy. The land forces, in time of peace, are computed at about 80,000 ; and in time of war, muſt be much more numerous. Their navy at preſent cannot be aſcertained.</p><p>The language of this country, eſpecially that ſpoken in Caſtile, which is by far the pureſt, approaches the neareſt to the Latin of any language in Europe, mixed with Arabic words and terminations introduced by the Moors. In ſome provinces, the vulgar tongue is a dialect of the old French, or rather Gaſcon, which is little underſtood in the others. In Biſcay, the language is ſaid to be a dialect of the Gothic or Celtic, and to have ſome analogy with the Welch and Iriſh. As to what regards the character of the Spaniards, they do not want either an inclination or capacity for the ſciences ; but have hardly an opportunity of acquiring any true learning or knowledge, at leaſt in their ſcirools and univerſities. They are admired for their ſecrecy, conſtancy, ravity, patience in adversity, and loyalty. They are alſo ſaid to be true to their word, great enemies to lying, and ſo nice and jealous in point of honour, that they will ſtick at nothing to wipe off any stain that is caſt upon it. Among their vices and defects are reckoned their pride and contempt of foreigners, their indolence, lazineſs, luſt, bigotry, and credulity in believing the feigned miracles and legends of their monks. They are alſo ſaid to be extremely paſſionate, jealous, and vindictive ; and are noted, above any other European nation, for deſpiſtng and neglecting agriculture, arts, and manufactures.</p><p>We will here ſubjoin ſome directions for travelling in Spain by Mr Townſend, a late reſpectable traveller; as they will enable the reader to form a more diſtinct notion of the ſtate of that country than he could obtain from general description.</p><p>“ To travel commodiouſly in Spain, a man ſhould have a good conſtitution, two good ſervants, letters of credit for the principal cities, and a proper introduction to the beſt families, both of the native inhabitants and of ſtrangers settled in the country.</p><p>“ The language will be eaſily acquired.</p><p>" His ſervants ſhould be a Spaniard and a Swiſs ; of</p><p>which one ſhould be sufficiently acquainted with the art of cooking, and with the ſuperior art of providing for the journey ; which implies a perfect knowledge of the country though which he is to paſs, that he may ſecure a ſtock of wine, bread, and meat, in places where theſe excel, and ſuch a ſtock as may be sufficient to carry him through the diſtricts in which theſe are not to be obtained, For himſelf, his ſervants, and his baggage, he ſhould purchaſe three ſtrong mules, able to ſupport the load which is to be put upon them. In his baggage he ſhould have ſheets, a matraſs, a blanket, and a quilt, a table-cloth, knives, forks, and ſpoons, with a copper vesſel sufficiently capacious to boil his meat. This ſhould be furniſhed with a cover and lock. Each of the ſervants ſhould have a gun slung by the ſide of his mule.</p><p>“ To travel as an economiſt in Spain, a man muſt be contented to take his chance for conveyance, and either go by the poſt, wherever it is eſtabliſhed ; or join with officers, going to their various dations; to hire a coach, or quietly reſign himſelf to a calaſh, a calaſine, a horſe, a mule, or a borrico. This laſt is the moſt convenient for the purpoſe of croſſing the country, or of wandering among the mountains. If he is to traverse any diſtrict infeſted by banditti, it will be ſafe for him to go by the common carriers, in which caſe he will be mounted on a good mule, and take the place which would have been occupied by ſome bale of goods. Any one, who is fond of botany, for ſhort excurſions, will make choice of a borrico. This is always to be had when, as in ſome villages, neither horse nor mule are to be obtained. I have uſed this honourable appellation for the moſt patient of all animals, becauſe I would not shock the delicacy of a young traveller, by telling him, at his firſt ſetting out, that he may ſometimes find himſelf under the neceſſity of riding upon an aſs. He muſt, however, know, for his conſolation, that an aſs does not appear ſo contemptible in Spain as in the colder regions of the north.</p><p>“ The beſt time ſor him to begin this expedition is in autumn, when he may go by Bayonne, Burgos, Valladolid, and Segovia, battening to the court at St Ildesonſo. Here he is to procure letters for the chief cities in Spain. On theſe will depend the whole plealure of his excurſion. During the winter he may see all the ſouth of Spain, Toledo, Cordova, Seville, Cadiz, Gibraltar, Malaga, Granada, Carthagena, Murcia, Alicant, Valencia, and Barcelona. Returning by Zaragoza to Aranjuez in the ſpring, he may follow the Merino flock to the mountains of the north, whilſt the country, on which he has turned his back, is rendered unfit for travelling, by the dissolving heats, by want of proviſions, and by malignant fevers. This ſeaſon will be beſt employed in Galicia, the Aſturias, and the provinces of Biſcay, taking Salamanca and Leon in the way.”</p><p><hi rend="italic">New</hi> <hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Spain.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Mexico.</hi></p></div></body></text></TEI>