<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0493.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0487-01" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SILPHA, <hi rend="smallcaps">Carrion-beetle,</hi></label>
 in natural hiſtory ; a genus of animals belonging to the claſs of <hi rend="italic">inſectae,</hi> and to the order of <hi rend="italic">coleopterae.</hi> The antennæ are clavated ; the clava are perfoliated ; the elytra marginated ; the head is prominent; and the thorax marginated. There are 94 ſpecies, of which ſeven only are natives of Britain and Ireland. I. The <hi rend="italic">veſpillo.</hi> The margin of the thorax broad. The ſhells abbreviated, black, with two yellow belts. The thighs of the hind legs large, with a ſpine near their origin. Length near one inch. It infeſts dead bodies. 2. The <hi rend="italic">biphuſtulata,</hi> is black ; the antennæ are long and ſmall, and there are two red ſpots on the middle of each ſhell. The length is one-third of an inch. 3. The <hi rend="italic">pustulala,</hi> is black and oblong : there are four brown ſpots on the ſhells : the length is one-fifth of an inch. It lives on trees. 4.<note anchored="false" n="1" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>Berkenhout, vol. i.</p></note> The <hi rend="italic">quadripunctata.</hi> The head, antennæ, and legs black- Margin oſ the thorax and ſhells are of a pale yellow, with four black ſpots. The length half an inch. It is found in Cain-wood, near Hampſtead. 5. The <hi rend="italic">ſabuloſa,</hi> is black ; the antennæ are ſhort and globular ; there are five striae on each ſhell. The ſhells and wings are ſhort. There are five joints on the two firſt feet, four on the rest. It lives in sand. 6. The <hi rend="italic">aquatica,</hi> is brown, with a green bronze tinge. There are four ribs on the thorax. On each ſhell there are 10 ſtriae. The length is one-fifth of an inch. 7. The <hi rend="italic">pulicaria,</hi> is black and oblong ; the ſhells are abbreviated ; the abdomen is rounded at the extremity ; the thorax and ſhells are ſcarce marginated ; the length is one line. It is found frequently running on flowers.</p></div></body></text></TEI>