<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0494.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0488-01" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SILVER</label>,
one of the perfect metals, and the whiteſt and moſt brilliant among them all, is oſ the ſpecific gravity, according to Bergman, of 10.552 ; but according to Kirwan, of 11.095. Its ductility is not greatly inferior to that of gold, as a grain of ſilver leaf meaſures ſomewhat more than 51 ſquare inches ; and the ſilver wire uſed for aſtronomical purpoſes meaſures only the 750th part of an inch in diameter; which is no more than half the thickneſs of the hair of the human head.<note anchored="false" n="1" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>*Cronstedt's Mineralogy, vol. ii. p. 536.</p></note> It is harder and more elaſtic than lead, tin, or gold ; but leſs ſo than copper, platina, or iron : like other metals it grows hard by hammering, but is eaſily reduced to its former ſtate by annealing. It is more deſtructible than gold, and is particularly acted upon by ſulphureous vapours ; hence its ſurface tarniſhes in the air, and aſtumes a dark brown colour.</p><p>“ It has been long thought (ſays Mr Fourcroy ) that ſilver is indeſtructible by the combined action of heat and air. It is certain, that this metal kept in fuſion, without contact of air, does not appear to be ſenſibly altered ; yet Junker had affirmed, that by treating it a long time in the reverberatory furnace, in the manner of Isaac Holland us, ſilver was changed into a vitreous calx. This experiment has been confirmed by Macquer. That learned chemiſt expoſed ſilver 20 times ſucceſſively in a porcelain crucible to the fire of the furnace at Seves; and at the 20th fuſion he obtained a vitriform matter of an olive green, which appeared to be a true glaſs of ſilver. This metal, when heated in the focus of a burning glaſs, has always exhibited a white pulverulent matter on its ſurface, and a greeniſh vitreous covering on the ſupport it reſted upon. Theſe two tacts remove all doubt reſpecting the alteration of ſilver : though it is much more difficult to calcine than other metallic matters, yet it is capable of being converted after a long time into a white calx, which, treated in a violent fire, affords an olive-coloured glaſs. It may be poſſible perhaps to obtain a calx of silver by heating this metal when reduced into very fine laminae, or into leaves, for a very long time in a matrass, as is done with mercury.”</p><p>Magellan informs us, that by melting in a due proportion with gold or steel, ſilver becomes greeniſh or bluiſh ; ſo that it is capable of producing the white, yellow, red, green, blue, and olive colours, more or leſs conſpicuouſly according to the various circumſtances of heat and proportions of the mixture. Though he makes mention of the vitrifications by Macquer already taken notice of, he denies that it can be calcined by heat alone. “ Silver (says he) is ſo fixed by itſelf in the fire, that, after being kept a whole month in fuſion, it had only loſt one 60th part of its weight, which might be on account of ſome alloy. It is therefore incapable of being calcined by mere heat ; and the calx of ſilver, which can only be made by means of its ſolution in acids, is reducible to its metallic form without the addition of any oxigenous ſubſtance. But when ſilver is expoſed to the violent heat of the ſolar rays collected by a powerful lens, a kind of ſmoke is ſeen ſurrounding it, which proves at laſt to be the minute particles of the metal raiſed and diſperſed by heat, as is evident if a thin plate of gold be expoſed to it ; for then the particles of ſilver are ſeen upon the gold in the ſame manner as thoſe of gold are ſeen upon ſilver in a similar experiment.”</p><p>By slow cooling after it has been melted, ſilver cryſtallizes into quadrangular pyramids. M. Baume obſerves, that, in cooling, it assumes a ſymmetrical form, obſervable on the ſurface by ſmall fibres reſembling the feathers of a pen. M. Fourcroy obſerves, that the fine button obtained by cupellation, often preſents on its surface five or six ſides arranged amongſt each other like a pavement ; but the cryſtallization in tetrahedral pyramids has not been obſerved particularly excepting by Meſſrs Tillet and Mongez. It has been ſuppoſed that ſilver melts with a ſmaller degree of heat than copper ; but the late improved thermometer of Mr Wedgewood ſhows that this is a miſtake ; ſilver requiring 130⁰ of Fahrenheit more than copper to bring it into fuſion. It is found in the earth,</p><p>I. <hi rend="italic">Native,</hi> generally of the fineneſs of 16 carats ; and of this there are ſeveral varieties. 1. Thin plated or leaved. 2. Capillary ſilver, of fine or coarſe fibres or arboreſcent, from Potoſi in America and Kunſberg in Norway. 3. A kind is alſo met with resembling coarſe linen in the ſurface, which in Saxony is called <hi rend="italic">knit cobalt.</hi> Abundance of this kind is to be met with in Potoſi, but more rarely in Saxony and Norway. 4. Sometimes native ſilver is met with in a cryſtalline or regularly figured ſtate with ſhining ſurfaces. This is found at Kunſberg, but is very ſcarce. There appears likewiſe a kind of cryſtallization on the thin plates of native silver, their ſurfaces being full of minute pyramidal cryſtals. Moſt of the American ſilver is of the native kind ; ſo is that at Kunſberg in Norway. It is not, however, met with native ſo commonly in other European mines. A very ſmall quantity of it is found in the mines of Salberg in Weſtmanland, and oſ Lofaſen in Dalarne, and ſeveral other places in Sweden. It has been found in pretty large lumps in clay mixed with nickel, partly decayed or withered ; in which ſituation it formed the compound called the st <hi rend="italic">ercus anſerinum,</hi> or gooſe dung ore. 5. A piece of native ſilver in coal is shown in the mineralogical academy at Freyberg; and Lahman, quoted by Le Camus, ſpeaks alſo of a ſimilar ſilver ore found in a mine of pit-coal<note anchored="true" n="2" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>*Cronstedt's Mineralogy, p. 542.</p></note> *.The capillary ſilver, according to the obſervarions of Henckel and Rome de Lisle, ſeems to have been produced by a decompoſition of red ſilver ore ; and Wallerius affirms, that if ſulphur is mixed in a gentle heat with ſilver, the latter takes a capillary form. 6. Native ſilver is likewiſe ſometimes found in the form of ſpider’s webs, and for that reaſon called by the Spaniards <hi rend="italic">arane.</hi> 7. It is met with in branches formed by octaedrons inſerted into one another. Some of theſe ſhow the mark of a leaf of fern or of a tree ; others are cubes or ſingle octaedrons, whoſe angles are truncated, tho' theſe laſt are but rare. 8. It is often found dispersed through sand and ochre, as well as in grey limeſtone in Lower Auſtria, and in a greeniſh clay near Schemnitz, or mixed with ochre, clay, and calciform nickel. It is generally alloyed with copper, ſometimes with gold, iron, or regulus of antimony ; and ſometimes it contains even five per cent of arſenic. That found near Kunſherg contains ſo much gold, that the colour of it is yellow.</p><p>Wallerius diſtinguiſhes ſeven ſpecies of native ſilver ; viz. 1. In irregular maſſes and lumps, at Kunſherg in Norway and other places, in a bed of clay. 2. In a granular and jagged form in America and Norway. 3. Arboreſcent, in the places already mentioned. 4. In<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0495.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0489"/>
thin leaves, between the fiſſures of ſtones, in Norway and Germany. In a capillary form, in the places already mentioned, including the cobweb ſilver of the Spaniards already mentioned. <hi rend="italic">6.</hi> Cryſtallized. 7. Superficial. Mr Daubenton enumerates eight varieties of native white silver, of different forms, moſt of which have been already enumerated. The materials in which this metal is moſt commonly found in its native ſtate are, bàro-selenite, limeſtone, ſelenite, quartz, chert, flint, ſerpentine, gneiſs, agate, mica, calcareous ſpar, pyrites, schiſtus, clay, &amp; c. Sometimes it is met with in large maſſes, of the weight of 60 pounds or more, in or near the veins of moſt metallic ores, particularly in Peru and in various parts of Europe, of a white, brown, or yellowiſh colour. In Norway and at Alſace it is found in the form of ſolitary cubes and octahedral lumps, of 50 and 60 pounds weight.</p><p>2. <hi rend="italic">Native ſilver alloyed with other metals.</hi> I. With gold, as in Norway, where it contains ſo much as to appear of a yellow colour. 2. With copper. 3. With gold and copper. 4. Amalgamated with mercury, as in the mines of Salberg. M. Rome de Liſle mentions a native amalgam of silver and mercury found at Muschel Landſberg in the duchy of Deux Ponts, in a ferruginous matrix, mixed with cinnabar, and cryſtallized in a hexagonal form, and of a large fize. It was before the French revolution preſerved in the king’s cabinet at Paris. 5. With iron. According to Bergman, this ore contains two per cent. of iron; but Mongez informs us, that it often does not exceed one per cent. 6. With lead. “ Silver (ſays Mr Magellan) is always contained in lead, though the quantity is generally inſufficient to defray the expence of ſeparating it. In the reign of Edward I. of England, however, near 1600 pounds weight of ſilver were obtained, in the courſe of three years, from a lead mine in Devonſhire, which had been diſcovered about the year 900. The lead mines in Cardiganſhire have at different periods afforded great quantities of silver ; ſo that Sir Hugh Middleton is ſaid to have cleared from them L. 2000 in a month. The ſame mines in the year 1745 yielded 80 ounces of filver out of every ton of lead. The lead in only one of the ſmelting houſes at Holywell in Flintſhire produced no leſs than 37521 ounces, or 3126 <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi> pounds of silver from the year 1754 to 1 756, and from 1774 to 1776. There are ſome lead ores in England, which, though very poor in that metal, contain between 300 and 400 ounces of silver in a ton of lead ; and it is commonly obſerved, that the pooreſt lead ores are the richeſt in silver ; so that a large quantity of silver is probably thrown away in England by not having the pooreſt sort of</p><p>lead ores properly eſſayed.” 7; Mr Monnet found silver united with arſenic among the ores which came from Guadanal canal in Spain, and an ore of the ſame kind is furniſhed by the Samſon mine near Andreaberg in the Hartz : but Mr Mongez very properly remarks, that theſe ores must be diſtinguiſhed from ſuch as have the arſenic in the form of an acid ; for in this case they are properly mineralized by it, whilſt there can only be a mixture of native silver, or ſome of its calces with arſenic in its reguline form. 8. Bergman mentions silver in a ſtate of union with antimony. The ore yields ſome ſmoke when roaſted, but has not the garlic ſmell obſervable in the arſenical ores. 9. The white silver ore, found in the mines near Freyberg, has the metal united</p><p>to the regulus of arſenic and iron, the three metallic ingredients being nearly in equal proportions. All the extraneous matters with which the silver is united are ſometimes in exceedingly ſmall proportion, but not to be neglected where they exceed the hundredth part of the whole maſs. 10. A particular kind of ſtony silver ores is mentioned by Wallerius under the title of <hi rend="italic">lapis deœ,</hi> and which contain the following varieties, viz. the calcareous silver ore at Annaberg in Auſtria, when the metal is mixed with an alkaline limeſtone ; the ſpathoſe ore, either white, variegated, or yellowiſh, found at Schemnitz in Hungary ; the quartzoſe white ore in a powdery form, mixed with ferruginous ſcoria, found at Potosi in America ; the dark and variegated quartzoſe ſilver ores, with many other ſubdiviſions diſtinguiſhed from one another by little elſe than their colour.</p><p>Silver is found mineralized by various ſubſtances; as, I. With ſulphur in the glaſſy or vitreous silver ore ; though this name ſeems rather to belong to the minera argenti cornea or horn silver ore, to be afterwards taken notice of more particularly. It is ductile, and of thc ſame colour with lead, but quickly becomes very black by expoſure to the air ; though ſometimes it is grey or black even when firſt broken. It is found either in large lumps, or inhering in quartz, gypſum, gneiſs, pyrites, &amp; c. Its ſpecific gravity, according to Kirwan, is 7,200. An hundred parts of it contain from 72 to 77 of silver, and it is rarely contaminated with any other metal.</p><p>Profeſſor Brunnich ſays that it contains 180 merks of silver in the hundred weight. The medium between the glaſs ore and the red gilder ore is called <hi rend="italic">roſch-gewaechs</hi> in Hungary, and <hi rend="italic">brittle glaſs ore</hi> in Saxony. It is black, and affords a powder of the ſame colour when pounded. In the mines of Himmelfurſt near Freyberg, it is ſaid to have held 140 merks, but theſe pieces are very ſcarce at preſent ; and indeed the Hungarian glaſs ores in general are now very ſcarce, as Profeſſor Brunnich informs us, though they are now and then found in the wind- ſhafts, which are frequently covered with a thin membrane or rather cruſt, of the colour of pyrites. Mr Magellan ſays that this ore is nothing elſe but native silver penetrated by ſulphur ; for, on being expoſed to a flow heat, the latter flies off, and the silver ſhoots into filaments. There are nine varieties of it. 1. Like <hi rend="italic">black lead.</hi> or plumbago, the most common kind of any. 2.Bruckman mentions a kind <hi rend="italic">brown</hi> on the outside and greeniſh within. 3. <hi rend="italic">The yellow ore</hi> has its colour from ſome arſenic contained in it, which forms an orpiment with the ſulphur. 4. It is alſo found of a <hi rend="italic">greeniſh,</hi> and 5. <hi rend="italic">bluiſh</hi> colour ; the latter is friable, like the ſcoria of metals, and is called at Freyberg <hi rend="italic">Schlarekenerz,</hi> or the ore of ſcoria.</p><p>6. It is found alſo in the a <hi rend="italic">rborescent. q.Lamellated. 8.Crystallized</hi> into octaedral or hexaedral priſms, and into ten pyramids with ten sides. 9. Laſtly, it is found su <hi rend="italic">perficial,</hi> or covering the ſtones or maſſes of other ores.</p><p>2.<note anchored="false" n="3" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>Cronstedt, p. 550.</p></note> The pyrites argenteus of Henckel contains ſilver and iron mineralized with arſenic. There are three varieties of it. 1. Hard, white, and shining ore, of a compact, lamellar, or fibrous texture. The brighteſt kind has leaſt silver, only giving 6 or 8 ounces per quintal, and the richeſt about ten per cent. It is found in Germany and Spain. It contains no ſulphur. 2. Of a yellowiſh white colour, and ſtriated texture reſembling biſmuth, but much harder. It is found in Spain, and yields about 60 per cent. of silver. 3. In another kind<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0496.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0490"/>
the quantity of arſenic is ſo great, that it would ſcarcely deserve the name of ſilver ore if the arſenic were not very eaſily diſſipated. It is ſoft and eaſily cut ; has a brilliant metallic appearance, and conſiſts of conchoidal laminae. A quintal contains only from four to six ounces of ſilver, but it is eaſily reduced by evaporating the arſenic, after which the ſilver is left behind ſlightly contaminated with iron.</p><p>3. The red or ruby ſilver ore, the <hi rend="italic">rothgulden of</hi> the Germans, has the metal combined with ſulphur and arſenic It is a heavy ſhining ſubſtance, ſometimes transparent, and ſometimes opaque ; the colour generally crimson, though ſometimes grey or blackiſh. It is found in ſhapeleſs maſſes, or cryſtallized in pyramids or polygons, ſometimes dendritical or plated, or with radiated incrustations. It is found in quartz, flint, ſpar, pyrites, ſparry iron ore, lead ore, cobalt ore, jaſper, baro-ſelenite, gneiſs, &amp; c. When radiated or ſtriated, it is called <hi rend="italic">rothgulden bluth.</hi> It cracks in the fire, and detonates with nitre. Its ſpecific gravity is from 7,400 to 5,684. Bergman informs us, that this kind contains, in the hundred, 60, ſometimes 70, pounds of ſilver, 27 of arſenic, and 13 of ſulphur. The darkeſt coloured ores are the richeſt, the yellow kinds much poorer ; but the moſt yellow do not belong to this ſpecies, being in fact an orpiment with 6 or 7 per cent. of ſilver. This laſt kind is brought chiefly from Potosi in America, and is called <hi rend="italic">roſi-cler</hi> by the Spaniards.</p><p>4. The <hi rend="italic">ſchuartz gulden,</hi> or s <hi rend="italic">ilber muim,</hi> contains the metal mineralized by ſulphur and a ſmall quantity of arſenic and iron. It is of a black ſooty colour, and was ſuppoſed by Cronſtedt to contain a good quantity of copper, to which its colour was owing ; but later experiments have evinced, that there is no copper at all in it. It is either of a ſolid or brittle consiſtence, and of a glaſſy appearance when broken, or of a looſer texture, and ſooty or deep black colour ; or it is found like moſs, or thin leaves, lying on the ſurface of other ſilver ores, or thoſe of lead and cobalt, or in clays, ponderous ſpar, gneiſs, &amp; c. It contains from 25 to 60 per cent. of ſilver.</p><p>5. The <hi rend="italic">minera argenti alba,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Weissgulden ore</hi> of the Germans, is a heavy, ſoft, opaque ſubſtance, fine grained or ſcaly, bright and ſhining in its fractures, of a whitiſh, steely, or lead colour ; ſometimes cryſtallized in pyramidical or cylindrical forms, but often in amorphous grains, or reſembling moſs, or in the form of thin laminæ incruſtating other bodies, found in quartz, ſpar, stelſtein, pyrites, blend, lead-ore, cobalt-ore, ſparry iron ore, fluors, &amp; c. It is very fuſible. Its ſpecific gravity is from 5 to 5,300. Its proportion of ſilver from 10 to 30 per cent. It is found, though not commonly, in Saxony, Hungary, the Hartz, and St Marie aux Mines.</p><p>6. The <hi rend="italic">weiſertz,</hi> or white ſilver ore, is an arſenical pyrites, containing ſilver. It is met with in the Saxon mines ſo exactly reſembling the common arlenical pyrites, that it cannot be diſtinguiſhed from it by inſpection. Cronſtedt ſuppoſes that the ſilver it contains may exiſt in a capillary form ; but Profeſſor Brunnich thinks this is not altogether the case. It is very ſcarce, but met with near Freyberg. There is likewiſe a brown <hi rend="italic">mulm</hi> having the appearance of rags, met with in the crevices and upon the lumps of cubic lead ore in a mine</p><p>near Clauſthal and other places, which contains a great quantity of ſilver. It is of a whitiſh ſhining colour ; hard, granulated, and ſolid, ſometimes ſtriking fire with ſteel. It diſcovers a mixture of arſenic, by emitting a garlic ſmell when heated.</p><p>7. The <hi rend="italic">leberertz</hi> of the Germans has the metal combined with ſulphurated antimony. It is of a dark grey and ſomewhat browniſh colour. A variety of a blackiſh blue colour is found in the form of capillary cryſtals, and called <hi rend="italic">ſederertz</hi> or plumoſe ſilver ore. It is met with in Saxony, and contains ſometimes a mark or half a pound, ſometimes only two, three, or four ounces, and ſometimes only a mere trifle of ſilver, per cent. There is another ſilver ore, alſo called <hi rend="italic">leberertz</hi> by the Germans, which contains arſenic and regulus of antimony. This ore is ſometimes alſo found of a dark grey colour; for the moſt part amorphous, but ſometimes cryſtallized into pyramids. It appears red when ſcraped, and contains from one to five per cent. of ſilver. The greateſt part of this ore is copper, and the next arſenic. According to Bergman, the copper amounts to 24 per cent. It is found in Transylvania ; and a kind was lately diſcovered in Spain, of a hard ſolid consiſtence, and of a greyiſh blue colour.</p><p>8. The <hi rend="italic">gooſe dung</hi> ores contain ſilver mineralized with ſulphur in combination with iron, arſenic, and cobalt. It looks like the <hi rend="italic">weſsgulden,</hi> excepting that the cobalt, by its decompoſition, gives it a roſy appearance. There are two varieties; one of a dull tarniſhed ſurface and ferruginous look ; the other has a ſhining appearance like the <hi rend="italic">leberertz.</hi> It contains from 10 to 40 or 50 per cent. of ſilver. The arſenic is in an acid ſtate, and united to the cobalt.</p><p>9. The <hi rend="italic">dal fahlertz</hi> contains ſilver mineralized with ſulphurated copper and antimony, and reſembles the dark-coloured <hi rend="italic">wejſsgulden,</hi> giving a red powder when rubbed. It is found either ſolid or cryſtallized, and is met with in the province of Dal, where it is melted by a very difficult proceſs, calculated to preſerve the different metals it contains. There is another kind which has arſenic united to the rest of the ingredients. It is only the grey copper ore impregnated with ſilver, of which it contains from one to twelve per cent. the quantity of copper being from 12 to 24 per cent. and the remainder conſiſting either of ſulphur or arſenic, with a little iron. It is the moſt common of all ſilver ores ; and M. Monnet remarks, that where copper is united to arſenic, ſilver is always to be found. A variety has been found at Schemnitz, containing a portion of gold alſo.</p><p>10. The pech <hi rend="italic">eblende</hi> is an ore of zinc containing ſilver, and is met with in the Saxon and Hungarian mines among the rich gold and ſilver ores. It is either of a metallic changeable colour or black. Of theſe there were formerly two varieties, viz. either in the form of fine ſcales or in balls, but the latter is now entirely unknown. A black blend is found in Bohemia, which is very heavy, with the ſurface ſomewhat elevated like ſome kinds of haematites, but no ſilver has yet been extracted from it</p><p>11. The <hi rend="italic">bleyglanz,</hi> potters ore, or galena, contains ſilver mineralized with ſulphurated lead. It is alſo called <hi rend="italic">pyritous ſilver,</hi> and is of a brown colour, yielding but a very ſmall portion of metal. It is met with at Kunſ-<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0497.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0491"/>
berg in Norway. When the ſilver is combined with ſulphurated lead and antimony, the ore is called str <hi rend="italic">iρerz.</hi></p><p>12. The <hi rend="italic">marcaſite</hi> containing ſilver has the metal united with ſulphurated iron. There are great varieties of this ore holding different proportions of the metal ; ſome produce only half an ounce of ſilver per cent. A liver-coloured marcaſite is found at Kunſherg in Norway, containing from three to three ounces and a half of ſilver per cent.</p><p>13. Silver is found mineralized with ſulphurated and arſenical cobalt ; the ſtone ſometimes containing <hi rend="italic">den drites.</hi> Theſe kinds keep well in water, but generally decay in the air, and loſe the ſilver they contain. It is found at Morgenſtern near Freyberg and Annaberg.</p><p>14. The <hi rend="italic">butter milk ore</hi> contains ſilver mineralized by sulphur, with regulus of antimony and barytes. It is found in the form of thin particles or granular ſpar. Wallerius ſays that it is ſoft like mud, and feels like butter. He ſuspects it to be produced from other ſilver ores waſhed away by running waters. Bomare adds, that the miners look upon it as a certain ſign of other ores in the neighbourhood, though ſome are perſuaded that it is only an unripened ſilver ore, which would ſoon become perfect.</p><p>15. The <hi rend="italic">combustible</hi> ſilver ore is a black brittle ſubſtance, leaving about six per cent. of ſilver in its aſhes. It is in fact a perfect coal in which ſilver is found.</p><p>16. The <hi rend="italic">hornertz,</hi> or horn ſilver ore, in which the ſilver is united with the muriatic acid, is the ſcarceſt of all the ſilver ores. It is ſometimes found in ſnowy cubical cryſtals, but is met with of many different colours. Its principal characteriſtic is to change to a violaceous browniſh colour when expoſed to the sunbeams, as happens alſo to the artificial luna cornea. It is frequently cryſtallized in a cubic form, though not always of a white colour. Sometimes it reſembles an earth eaſily fuſible without fmoke. There is a black kind, friable, and eaſily reducible to powder ; the other is in ſome degree malleable, may be cut with a knife, and takes a fort of poliſh when rubbed. The vitreous ſilver ore, which is ſometimes mixed with the horn ſilver, is ſoluble in nitrous acid ; and this affords a method of ſeparating them, the horn ſilver ore being inſoluble in that menſtruum. When the horn ſilver is free from iron, it generally contains 70 per cent. of ſilver at leaſt ; but theſe ores moſtly contain ſome portion of iron, a ſmall part of which is even united to the marine acid. This kind of ore was firſt analyſed by Mr Woulfe, who diſcovered the preſence of the vitriolic acid in it.</p><p>17. Another kind of horn ſilver ore is mentioned by Mr Bergman, in which the metal is mineralized by the vitriolic and marine acids, along with ſome sulphur. He doubts, however, whether the mineralization he perfect in this caſe, as the ſalt and sulphur do not admit of any other than a mechanical union. But ſince iron is often found in theſe ores, a marcaſite may thus be ſometimes formed.</p><p>18. The <hi rend="italic">ſilver gooſe dung ore</hi> is of a greeniſh colour, with a mixture of yellow and red. Some think it is a mixture of red ſilver ore and calx of nickel.</p><p>19. The f <hi rend="italic">oliaceous</hi> ſilver ore. The colour of this ore is <hi rend="italic">mortdore.</hi> Some imagine it to be a native ſilver ore ; others that it is a mixture of galena, ochre, and ſilver. it is ſometimes found in the mountain cork, and is ſo</p><p>light that it will ſwim upon water. It contains but one ounce of ſilver per quintal.</p><p>Theſe are all the varieties hitherto obſerved in which ſilver is met with in the earth, though it may perhaps occur in various other forms. It would be worth while to examinewhether, in thoſe countries where gold and ſilver are found in large quantities, the precious metals may not be contained in ſome proportion in the moſt common ores, more eſpecially when the particles of gold and ſilver have not been able to extricate themſelves in ſuch a manner as to lie ſeparate in fiſſures, veins, or hollow places of the mine. A mineralization of ſilver with alkali is ſaid to have been lately met with at Annaberg in Auſtria ; but the account of it as yet can ſcarcely be depended upon. Profeſſor Brunnich ſays, that the ſilver contained in the limeſtone at that place appears to be native when the ſtone is poliſhed.</p><p>The pureſt ſilver is that which is extracted from luna cornea, and is the only kind that ought to be truſted in the nice operations of chemiſtry. The proceſs, however, is very tedious, and preſents a very unexpected phenomenon, as this metal, though one of the moſt fixed, is nevertheleſs volatilized in the operation in ſuch a manner that it exhales through the pores of the crucible ; and ſmall globules of ſilver are afterwards found in the cover, and even in the ſupport of the crucible. According to Cramer, this loss may be prevented by ſmearing the crucible with black ſoap, and mixing with the luna cornea half its weight of oil or tallow, which laſt muſt alſo be added by little and little during the operation.</p><p>M. Magellan takes notice of a remarkable appearance obſervable in diſſolving ſilver in the nitrous acid. He obſerves, that this acid is its ſpecific menſtruum, attacking it even when cold with conſiderable eſſerveſcence, growing hot, and emitting a conſiderable quantity of orange-coloured fumes, which diminiſh in proportion as the ſaturation advances. The metal appears of a pale brown colour in the conflict, and the ſolution becomes quite black. This laſt appearance, however, is owing to a thin, black, fuliginous ſubſtance, like ſmut, which is at once formed into a cruſt on the ſurface of the thin plates of ſilver in the firſt attack of the acid upon them. This is a very singular phenomenon, and hitherto unaccounted for, theſe black crusts being comminuted into ſmaller and ſmaller particles by the action of the acid ; and, when the efferveſcence is over, they are seen diſtinctly to fall to the bottom of the vesſel, and to form a black ſediment, leaving the liquid ſolution quite transparent, but of a blue colour inclining to green.— This colour might be attributed to ſome ſmall mixture of copper, though the ſilver uſed in the experiment was oſ the purer kind. The chemiſts of Dijon say, that the nitrous ſolution of ſilver looks of a fine blue colour, if the acid be pure and well concentrated ; but if it has any mixture of vitriolic or marine, a precipitation of vitriolated ſilver or luna cornea takes place. Afterwards the ſolution becomes as colourlels as water, but gives a laſting black tinge to animal ſubſtances. This ſolution is of great uſe in chemiſtry, ſerving to form the lunar cauſtic, to purify the common aquafortis from a mixture of the vitriolic and marine acids, and is a very nice teſt of the exiſtence of theſe acids in mineral waters.</p><p>Silver does not combine with earths, even by the most violent heat, though Mr Fourcroy ſuppoſes that its calx<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0498.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0492"/>
might give an olive green to glaſs. Mr Magellan informs us, that its calx, precipitated by volatile alkali, gives a yellow colour to glaſs, and that he has ſeen it ſtained in this manner ſo high as almoſt to appear of a red colour. It unites with moſt metals, even with iron. The nature of this alloy has been but little inquired into, though Fourcroy is of opinion that it may probably be of the greateſt utility in the arts. It combines in all proportions with copper, by which it is not deprived of its ductility, but renders it harder and more ſonorous; by which means it is often uſed in bells. It is otherwiſe highly uſeful, on account of its indeſtructibility by fire and air, and its extreme ductility. Its fine colour renders it extremely proper for ornamental purpoſes, and it is applied like gold on the ſurface of different bodies, and even on copper. It likewiſe enters the texture of rich ſilks ; but its moſt conſiderable use is that of being employed as money of an inferior value to gold. In this case, it is alloyed with one-twelfth part of copper. It is likewiſe often employed in making houſehold utenſils of all kinds, though its great price renders it leſs common than it would otherwiſe be for this purpoſe. For plate, it is uſually alloyed with one twenty-fourth of copper, which gives it a greater degree of hardneſs and coherence, without rendering it in the leaſt noxious.</p><p>Silver has alſo been uſed in medicine : but its extreme cauſticity, when diſſolved in the nitrous acid, and its inactivity otherwiſe, have brought it into difuſe. The cryſtals of ſilver have been recommended in very ſmall quantity in dropſical caſes; but they are by no means ſuperior, or even equal in efficacy, to much ſafer medicines. The ſolution of ſilver, under the name of <hi rend="italic">Greek water,</hi> has been uſed for the purpoſe of dying hair of a dark colour ; and the ſame ſolution evaporated to a conſiſtence, and fuſed, forms the lunar cauſtic of the ſhops.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Shell SILV</hi> <hi rend="italic smallcaps"> er,</hi> is prepared of the ſhreds of ſilver leaf, or of the leaves themſelves, for the uſe of painters, after the ſame manner as ſhell gold. See <hi rend="italic">Shell-Gold.</hi></p></div></body></text></TEI>