<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0527.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0521-03" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SLATE</label>
(Stegania), a ſtone of a compact texture and laminated ſtructure, ſplitting into fine plates.</p><p>Dr Hill diſtinguiſhes four ſpecies oſ ſtegania. 1. The whitiſh ſteganium, being a ſoft, friable, ſlaty ſtone, of a tolerably ſine and cloſe texture, conſiderably heavy, perfectly dull and deſtitute of brightneſs, variegated with a pale brown or browniſh yellow. This ſpecies is common in many counties of England, lying near the surface of the ground. It is generally very full of perpendicular as well as horizontal cavities, many of which are filled up with a ſpar a little purer and more cryſtalline than the reſt; and is commonly uſed for covering houſes. 2. The red ſteganium is a very fine and elegant ſtate, of a ſmooth ſurface, firm and compact texture, conſiderably heavy, and of a very beautiful pale purple, glittering all over with ſmall glossy ſpangles : it is compoſed of a multitude of very thin plates or flakes, laid cloſely and evenly over one another, and cohering pretty firmly : this is very common in the northern parts of England, and is much valued as a ſtrong and beautiful covering for houſes. 3. The common blue ſteganium is very well known as an uſeful and valuable ſtone, of a fine ſmooth texture and glossy ſurface, moderately heavy, and of a pale greyiſh blue ; compoſed of a multi<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0528.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0522"/>
tude oſ even plates, laid cloſe upon one another, and eaſily ſplitting at the commiſſures of them : this is alſo very common in the north parts of England, and is uſed in moſt places ſor the covering of houſes. There are other ſpecies of this ſlate, viz. the browniſh blue friable ſteganium, uſually called <hi rend="italic">coalſlate ;</hi> the greyiſh black friable ſteganium, commonly called s <hi rend="italic">hiver;</hi> and the greyiſh blue ſparkling ſteganium. 4. The friable, aluminous, black ſteganium, being the Iriſh ſlate of the ſhops : this is compoſed of a multitude of thin flakes, laid very evenly and regularly over one another, and ſplits very regularly at the commiſſures of them. It is common in many parts of Ireland, and is found in ſome places in England always lying near the ſurface in very thick ſtrata. In medicine it is uſed in hemorrhagies of all kinds with ſucceſs, and is taken often as a good medicine in fevers.</p><p>The iſland of Euſdale, one of the Hebrides on the west coaſt of Scotland, is entirely compoſed of ſlate. The ſtratum is 36 feet thick. About two millions and a half, at the rate of twenty ſhillings per thouſand, are ſold annually to England, Canada, the West Indies, and Norway.</p></div></body></text></TEI>