<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title/>
    <author/>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <p/>
   </publicationStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>
   <div facs="gri_33125011196363_0519.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0513-06"
    xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <p><label>SITTA <hi rend="smallcaps">Nuthatch,</hi></label> in ornithology : A genus belonging
     to the claſs of <hi rend="italic">aves,</hi> and order of <hi rend="italic">pica.</hi> It is
     thus characterized by Dr Latham.<note anchored="true" n="1" place="bottom" type="authorial"
       ><p>[mu] Latham's Orthinology, vol. ii. p. 647, &amp;c.</p></note> The bill is for the moſt
     part ſtraight ; on the lower mandible there is a ſmall angle ; noſtrils ſmall, covered with
     briſtles reflected over them ; tongue ſhort, horny at the end, and jagged ; toes placed three
     forward and one backward ;<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0520.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0514"/>
     the middle toe joined cloſely at the baſe to both the outmoſt ; back toe as large as the middle
     one.— There are 11 ſpecies : the europæa, canadenſis, carolinensis, jamaicenſis, puſilla,
     major, nævia, ſurinamenſis, cafra, longiroſtra, and chloris. The europæa, or nuthatch, is in
     length near five inches three-quarters, in breadth nine inches ; the bill is ſtrong and
     ſtraight, about three-quarters of an inch long ; the upper mandible black, the lower white :
     the irides are hazel ; the crown of the head, back, and coverts of the wings, of a fine bluiſh
     grey ; a black ſtroke passes over the eye from the mouth : the cheeks and chin are white ; the
     breaſt and belly of a dull orange-colour ; the quill-feathers duſky ; the wings underneath are
     marked with two ſpots, one white at the root of the exterior quills, the other black at the
     joint of the baſtard-wing ; the tail conſiſts of twelve feathers ; the two middle are grey, the
     two exterior feathers tipt with grey ; then ſucceeds a tranſverſe white ſpot ; beneath that the
     reſt is black : the legs are of a pale yellow ; the back toe very ſtrong, and the claws large.
     The female is like the male, but leſs in ſize, and weighs commonly 5 or at moſt 6 drams. The
     eggs are ſix or ſeven in number, of a dirty white, dotted with rufous ; theſe are depoſited in
     ſome hole of a tree, frequently one which has been deſerted by a woodpecker, on the rotten wood
     mixed with a little moſs, &amp;c. If the entrance be too large, the bird nicely ſtops up part of
     it with clay, leaving only a ſmall hole for itſelf to paſs in and out by. While the hen is
     fitting, if any one puts a bit of ſtick into the hole, ſhe hisses like a ſnake, and is ſo
     attached to her eggs, that ſhe will ſooner ſuffer any one to pluck off her feathers than fly
     away. During the time of incubation, the male ſupplies her with ſuſtenance, with all the
     tenderneſs of an affectionate mate.</p>
    <p>The bird runs up and down the bodies of trees, like the woodpecker tribe ; and feeds not only
     on infects, but nuts, of which it lays up a conſiderable proviſion in the hollows of trees. “
     It is a pretty fight, ſays Mr Willoughby, to ſee her fetch a nut out of her hoard, place it
     faſt in a chink, and then, ſtanding above it with its head downwards, ſtriking it with all its
     force, break the ſhell, and catch up the kernel. It is ſuppoſed not to ſleep perched on a twig
     like other birds ; for when confined in a cage, it prefers ſleeping in a hole or corner. When
     at reſt it keeps the head down. In autumn it begins to make a chattering noiſe, being silent
     for the greateſt part of the year.” Dr Plott tells us, that this bird, by putting its bill into
     a crack in the bough of a tree, can make ſuch a violent found as if it was rending aſunder, ſo
     that the noiſe may be heard at leaſt twelve ſcore yards.</p>
   </div>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
