<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0596.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0590-04" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SOCRATES</label>,
the greateſt of the ancient philoſo phers, was born at Alopece, a village near Athens, in the fourth year of the 77th olympiad. His parents were of low rank ; his father Sophroniſcus being a statuary, and his mother Phænareta a midwife. Sophro-<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0597.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0591"/>
niscus brought up his ſon, contrary to his inclination, <hi rend="italic">in</hi> his own manual employment ; in which Socrates, though his mind was continually aſpiring after higher objects, was not unſucceſsful ; for whilſt he was a young man, he is ſaid to have formed ſtatues of the habited graces, which were allowed a place in the citadel of Athens. Upon the death of his father he was left in ſuch ſtraitened circumſtances as laid him under the neceſſity of exerciſing that art to procure the means of ſubſiſtence, though he devoted, at the ſame time, all the leisure which he could command to the ſtudy of philoſophy. His diſtreſs, however, was loon relieved by Crito, a wealthy Athenian ; who, remarking his ſtrong propenſity to ſtudy, and admiring his ingenuous diſpoſition and diſtinguiſhed abilities, generouſly took him under his patronage, and intruded him with the inſtruction of his children. The opportunities which Socrates by this means enjoyed of attending the public lectures of the moſt eminent philosophers, ſo far increaſed his thirſt after wiſdom, that he determined to relinquiſh his occupation, and every proſpect of emolument which that might afford, in order to devote himſelf entirely to his favourite pursuits. Under Anaxagoras and Archelaus he prosecuted the study of nature in the uſual manner of the philoſophers of the age, and became well acquainted with their doctrines. Prodicus the ſophiſt was his preceptor in eloquence, Evenus in poetry, Theodorus in geometry, and Damo in muſic. Aſpafta, a woman no leſs celebrated for her intellectual than her perſonal accompliſhments, whoſe houſe was frequented by the most celebrated characters, had alſo ſome ſhare in the education of Socrates. Under ſuch preceptors it cannot reaſonably be doubted but that he became master of every kind of learning which the age in which he lived could afford ; and being bleſſed with very uncommon talents by nature, he appeared in Athens, under the reſpectable characters of a good citizen and a true philoſopher Being called upon by his country to take arms in the long and ſevere ſtruggle between Athens and Sparta, he ſignalized himſelf at the siege of Potidæa, both by his valour and by the hardineſs with which he endured fatigue. During the ſeverity of a Thracian winter, whilſt others were clad in furs, he wore only his uſual clothing, and walked barefoot upon the ice. In an engagement in which he ſaw ALCEBIA <hi rend="smallcaps">des</hi> falling down wounded, he advanced to defend him, and ſaved both him and his arms : and though the prize of valour was on this occoſicn unqueſtionably due to Socrates, he generouſly gave his vote that it might be beſtowed upon Alcibiades, to encourage his riſing merit. He ſerved in other campaigns with diſtinguiſhed bravery, and had the happineſs on one occaſion to ſave the life of Xenophon, by bearing him, when covered with wounds, out of the reach of the enemy.</p><p>It was not till Socrates was upwards of 60 years oſ age that he undertook to ſerve his country in any civil office, when he was choſen to repreſent his own diſtrict, in the ſenate of five hundred. In this office, though he at firſt expoſed himſelf to ſome degree of ridicule from the want of experience in the forms of buſineſs, he ſoon convinced his colleagues that he was ſuperior to them all in wiſdom and integrity. Whilſt they, intimidated by the clamours of the populace, paſſed an unjuſt ſentence of condemnation upon the commanders, who, after the engagement at the Arginusian iſlands, had</p><p>been prevented by a ſtorm from paying funeral honours to the dead, Socrates ſtood forth ſingly in their defence, and to the laſt refilled to give his ſuffrage againſt them, declaring that no force ſhould compel him to act contrary to juſtice and the laws. Under the ſubſequent tyranny he never ceaſed to condemn the oppressive and cruel proceedings of the thirty tyrants ; and when his boldnels provoked their reſeritment, ſo that his life was in hazard, fearing neither treachery nor violence, he ſtill continued to support with undaunted firmneſs the rights of his fellow-citizens.</p><p>Having given theſe proofs of public virtue both in a military and civil capacity, he wiſhed to do il ill more for his country. Obſerving with regret how much the opinions of the Athenian youth were milled, and their principles and taſte corrupted by philoſophers who ſpent all their time in refined ſpeculations upon nature and the origin of things, and by ſophiſts who taught in their ſchools the arts of false eloquence and deceitful reaſoning ; Socrates formed the wife and generous deſign of inſtituting a new and more useful method of inſtruction. He juſtly conceived the true end of philoſophy to be, not to make an oſtentatious display of superior learning and ability in ſubtle diſpntations or ingenious conjectures, but to free mankind from the dominion of pernicious prejudices ; to correct their vices ; to inſpire them with the love of virtue ; and thus conduct them in the path of wiſdom to true felicity. He therefore aſſumed the character of a moral philoſopher ; and, looking upon the whole city of Athens as his school, and all who were diſpoſed to lend him their attention as his pupils, he ſeized every occaſion of communicating moral wiſedom to his fellow citizens. He paſſed the greater part of his time in public ; and the method of inſtruction of which he chiefly made uſe was, to propoſe a ſeriouS of queſtions to the perſon with whom he converſed, in order to lead him to ſome unſoreſeen concluſion. He firſt gained the conſent of his reſpondent to ſome obvious truths, and then obliged him to admit others from their relation or reſemblance to thoſe to which he had already assessed. Without making uſe oſ any direct argument or perſuaſion, he choſe to lead the perſon he meant to inſtruct, to deduce the truths of which he wiſhed to convince him, as a neceſſary conſequence from his own conceſſions. He commonly conducted theſe conferences with ſuch addreſs, as to conceal his design till the reſpondent had advanced too far to recede. On ſome occasions he made uſe of ironical language, that vain men might be caught in their own replies, and be obliged to confeſs their ignorance. He never aſſumed the air of a moroſe and rigid preceptor, but communicated uſeful inſtruction with all the eaſe and pleaſantry of polite conversation. Though eminently furniſhed with every kind of learning, he preferred moral to ſpeculative wiſdom. Convinced that philoſophy is valuable, not as it fwrniſhes queſtions for the ſchools, but as it provides men with a law of life, he cenſured his predeceſſors for ſpending all their time in abſtruſe reſearches into nature, and taking no pains to render themſelves uſeful to mankind. Elis favourite maxim was, whatever is above us doth not concern us. He eſtimated the value of knowledge by its utility, and recommended the ſtudy of geometry, aſtronomy, and other ſciences, only ſo far as they admit of a practical application to the purpoſes of human life. His great<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0598.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0592"/>
object in all his conferences and diſcourſes was, to lead men into an acquaintance with themſelves ; to convince them of their follies and vices; to inſpire them with the love of virtue ; and to furniſh them with uſeful moral inſtructions. Cicero might therefore very juſtly lay of Socrates, that he was the firſt who called down philoſophy from heaven to earth, and introduced her into the public walks and domeſtic retirements of men, that ſhe might inſtruct them concerning life and manners.</p><p>Through his whole life this good man diſcovered a mind ſuperior to the attractions of wealth and power. Contrary to the general practice of the preceptors of his time, he inſtructed his pupils without receiving from them any gratuity. He frequently refuſed rich presents, which were offered him by Alcibiades and others, though importunately urged to accept them by his wiſe. The chief men of Athens were his ſtewards : they ſent him in proviſions, as they apprehended he wanted them; he took what his preſent wants required, and returned the reſt. Obſerving the numerous articles of luxury which were expoſed to ſale in Athens, he exclaimed, “ How many things are there which I do not want !” With Socrates, moderation ſupplied the place of wealth. In his clothing and food, he conſulted only the demands oſ nature. He commonly appeared in a neat but plain clock, with his feet uncovered. Though his table was only ſupplied with ſimple fare, he did not ſcruple to invite men of ſuperior rank to partake of his meals ; and when his wife, upon ſome ſuch occaſion, expreſſed her diſſatisſaction on being no better provided, he delired her to give herſelf no concern ; for if his gueſts were wiſe men, they would be contented with whatever they found at his table ; if otherwiſe, they were unworthy of notice. Whilſt others, lays he, live to eat, wiſe men eat to live.</p><p>Though Socrates was exceedingly unfortunate in his domeſtic connection, he converted this infelicity into an occaſion of exerciſing his virtues. Xantippe, concerning whoſe ill humour ancient writers relate many amuſing tales, was certainly a woman of a high and unmanageable ſpirit. But Socrates, while he endeavoured to curb the violence of her temper, improved his own. When Alcibiades expreſſed his ſurpriſe that his friend could bear to live in the ſame houſe with ſo perverſe and quarrelſome a companion, Socrates replied, that being daily inured to ill humour at home, he was the better prepared to encounter perverſeneſs and injury abroad.</p><p>In the midſt of domeſtic vexations and public diſorders, Socrates retained ſuch an unruffled ſerenity, that he was never ſeen either to leave his own houſe or to return home with a diſturbed countenance. In acquiring this entire dominion over his paſſions and appetites, he had the greater merit, as it was not effected without a violent ſtruggle againſt his natural propensities. Zopyrus, an eminent phyſiognomiſt, declared, that he diſcovered in the features of the philoſopher evident traces of many vicious inclinations. The friends of Socrates who were preſent ridiculed the ignorance of this pretender to extraordinary ſagacity. But Socrates himſelf ingenuouſly acknowledged his penetration, and confeſſed that he was in his natural diſposition prone to vice, but that he had ſubdued his inclinations by the power of reaſon and philoſophy.</p><p>Through the whole of his life Socrates gave himſelf</p><p>up to the guidance of unbiaſſed reaſon, which is ſuppoſed by ſome to be all that he meant by the genius or <hi rend="italic">damon</hi> from which he profeſſed to receive inſtruction. But this opinion is inconſiſtent with the accounts given by his followers of that dæmon, and even with the language in which he ſpoke of it himſelf. Plato ſometimes calls it his <hi rend="italic">guardian,</hi> and Apuleius his god,∙ and as Xenophon atteſts that it was the belief of his maſter that the gods occasionally communicate to men the knowledge of future events, it is by no means improbable that Socrates admitted, with the generality of his countrymen, the exiſtence of thoſe intermediate beings called <hi rend="italic">damons,</hi> of one of which he might fancy himſelf the peculiar care.</p><p>It was one of the maxims of Socrates, “ That a wiſe man will worſhip the gods according to the inſtitutions of the ſtate to which he belongs.” Convinced of the weakneſs of the human underſtanding, and perceiving that the pride of philoſophy had led his predeceſſors into futile ſpeculations on the nature and origin of things, he judged it moſt conſiſtent with true wiſdom to ſpeak with caution and reverence concerning the divine nature.</p><p>The wiſdom and the virtues oſ this great man, whilſt they procured him many followers, created him alſo many enemies. The Sophists<note anchored="true" n="1" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>* See Sophist.</p></note> *, whoſe knavery and ignorance he took every opportunity of expoſing to public contempt, became inveterate in their enmity againſt ſo bold a reformer, and deviſed an expedient, by which they hoped to check the current of his popularity. They engaged Ariſtophanes, the firſt buffoon of the age, to write a comedy, in which Socrates ſhould be the principal character. Ariſtophanes, pleaſed with ſo promiſing an occaſion of diſplaying his low and malignant wit, undertook the taſk, and produced the comedy of <hi rend="italic">The Clouds,</hi> ſtill extant in his works. In this piece, Socrates is introduced hanging in a baſket in the air, and thence pouring forth abſurdity and prophaneneſs. But the philoſopher, ſhowing in a crouded theatre that he was wholly unmoved by this ribaldry, the satire failed of its effect ; and when Ariſtophanes attempted the year following to renew the piece with alterations and additions, the repreſentation was ſo much diſcouraged, that he was obliged to diſcontinue it.</p><p>From this time Socrates continued for many years to purſue without interruption his laudable deſign of inſtructing and reforming his fellow-citizens. At length, however, when the inflexible integrity with which he had diſcharged the duty of a ſenator, and the firmneſs with which he had oppoſed every kind oſ political corruption and oppreſſion, had greatly increaſed the number of his enemies, clandeſtine arts were employed to raiſe a general prejudice againſt him. The people were induſtriouſly reminded, that Critias, who had been one of the moſt cruel of the thirty tyrants, and Alcibiades, who had inſulted religion, by defacing the public ſtatues of Mercury, and performing a mock repreſentation of the Eleuſinian myſteries, had in their youth been diſciples of Socrates ; and the minds of the populace being thus prepared, a direct accuſation was preferred againſt him before the ſupreme court of judicature. His accuſers were Anytus a leather-dresser, who had long entertained a perſonal enmity againſt Socrates, for reprehending his avarice, in depriving his ſons of the benefits of learning, that they might purſue the gains of<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0599.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0593"/>
trade ; Melitus, a young rhetorician, who was capable of undertaking any thing for the ſake of gain ; and Lycon, who was glad of any opportunity of diſplaying his talents. The accusation, which was delivered to the ſenate under the name of Melitus, was this : “ Melitus, ſon of Melitus, of the tribe of Pythos, accuſeth Socrates, son of Sophroniſcus, oſ the tribe of Alopece. Socrates violates the laws, in not acknowledging the gods which the ſtate acknowledges, and by introducing new divinities. He also violates the laws by corrupting the youth. Be his puniſhment death.”</p><p>This charge was delivered upon oath to the ſenate ; and Crito a friend of Socrates became ſurety for his appearance on the day of trial. Anytus ſoon afterwards sent a private meſſage to Socrates, assuring him that if be would deſiſt from cenſuring his conduct, he would withdraw his accuſation. But Socrates refuſed to comply with ſo degrading a condition ; and with his uſual ſpirit replied, “ Whilſt I live I will never diſguiſe the truth, nor ſpeak otherwiſe than my duty requires.” The interval between the accuſation and the trial he ſpent in philoſophical conversations with his friends, chooſing to diſcourſe upon any other ſubject rather than his own ſituation.</p><p>When the day of trial arrived, his accusers appeared in the ſenate, and attempted to ſupport their charge in three diſtinct ſpeeches, which ſtrongly marked their reſpective characters. Plato, who was a young man, and a zealous follower of Socrates, then roſe up to addreſs the judges in defence of his maſter ; but whilſt he was attempting to apologiſe for his youth, he was abruptly commanded by the court to sit down. Socrates, however needed no advocate. Aſcending the chair with all the ſerenity of conſcious innocence, and with all the dignity of ſuperior merit, he delivered, in a firm and manly tone, an unpremeditated defence of himſelf, which silenced his opponents, and ought to have convinced his judges. After tracing the progreſs oſ the conſpiracy which had been raiſed againſt him to its true ſource, the jealouſy and reſentment of men whoſe ignorance he had expoſed, and whoſe vices he had ridiculed and reproved, he diſtinctly replied to the ſeveral charges brought againſt him by Melitus. To prove that he had not been guilty of impiety towards the gods of his country, he appealed to his frequent practice of attending the public religious feſtivals. The crime of introducing new divinities, with which he was charged, chiefly as it ſeems on the ground of the admonitions which he profeſſed to have received from an inviſible power, he diſclaimed, by pleading that it was no new thing for men to conſult the gods and receive inſtructions from them. To refute the charge of his having been a corrupter of youth, he urged the example which he had uniformly exhibited of juſtice, moderation, and temperance ; the moral ſpirit and tendency of his diſcourſes ; and the effect which had actually been produced by his doctrine upon the manners of the young. Then, disdaining. to ſolicit the mercy of his judges, he called upon them for that juſtice which their office and their oath obliged them to adminiſter ; and profesſing his faith and confidence in God, reſigned himſelf to their pleasure.</p><p>The judges, whoſe prejudices would not ſuffer them to pay due attention to this apology, or to examine</p><p>with impartiality the merits of the cauſe, immediately declared him guilty of the crimes of which he flood accuſed. Socrates, in this ſtage of the trial, had a right to enter his plea againſt the puniſhment which the accusers demanded, and inſtead of the ſentence of death, to propoſe ſome pecuniary amercement. But he at firſt peremptorily refuſed to make any propoſal of this kind, imagining that it might be conſtrued into an acknowledgment of guilt; and aſſerted, that his conduct merited from the ſtate reward rather than puniſhment. At length, however, he was prevailed upon by his friends to offer upon their credit a fine of thirty minae. The judges, notwithſtanding, ſtill remained inexorable : they proceeded, without farther delay, to pronounce ſentence upon him; and he was condemned to be put to death by the poiſon of hemlock.</p><p>The ſentence being paſſed, he was ſent to priſon : which, lays Seneca, he entered with the ſame reſolution and firmneſs with which he had oppoſed the thirty tyrants ; and took away all ignominy from the place, which could not be a priſon while he was there. He lay in fetters 30 days ; and was conſtantly viſited by Crito, Plato, and other friends, with whom he paſſed the time in diſpute after his uſual manner. Anxious to ſave ſo valuable a life, they urged him to attempt his eſcape, or at leaſt to permit them to convey him away; and Crito went ſo far, as to aſſure him that, by his intereſt with the jailor, it might be eaſily accompliſhed, and to offer him a retreat in Theſſaly ; but Socrates rejected the propoſal, as a criminal violation of the laws ; and aſked them, whether there was any place out of Attica which death could not reach.</p><p>At length the day arrived when the officers to whoſe care he was committed delivered to Socrates early in the morning the final order for his execution, and immediately, according to the law, let him at liberty from his bonds. His friends, who came thus early to the priſon that they might have an opportunity of conversing with their maſter through the day, found his wife fitting by him with a child in her arms. Socrates, that the tranquillity of his laſt moments might not be diſturbed by her unavailing lamentations, requeſted that ſhe might be conducted home. With the moſt frantic expreſsions of grief ſhe left the priſon. An intereſting converſation then paſſed between Socrates and his friends, which chiefly turned upon the immortality, of the foul. In the courſe of this conversation, he expressed his diſapprobation of the practice of ſuicide, and aſſured his friends that his chief ſupport in his preſent ſituation was an expectation, though not unmixed with doubts, of a happy exiſtence after death, “ It would be inexcuſable in me (ſaid he) to deſpiſe death, if I were not perſuaded that it will conduct me into the preſence of the gods, who are the moſt righteous governors, and into the ſociety of just and good men : but I derive confidence from the hope that ſomething of man remains after death, and that the condition of good men will then be much better than that of the bad.” Crito afterwards aſking him, in what manner he wiſhed to be buried ? Socrates replied, with a finile, “ As you pleaſe, provided I do not eſcape out of your hands.” Then, turning to the rest of his friends, he ſaid, “ Is it not ſtrange, after all that I have ſaid to convince you that I am going to the ſociety of the hap-<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0600.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0594"/>
py, that Crito ſtill thinks that this body, which will ſoon be a lifeleſs corpſe, is Socrates ? Let him dispoſe of my body as he pleaſes, but let him not at its interment mourn over it as if it were Socrates.”</p><p>Towards the cloſe of the day he retired into an adjoining apartment to bathe ; his friends, in the mean time, expreſſing to one another their grief at the proſpect of loſing ſo excellent a father, and being left to paſs the reſt of their days in the ſolitary ſtate of orphans. After a ſhort interval, during which he gave ſome neceſſary inſtructions to his domeſtics, and took his laſt leave of his children, the attendant of the priſon informed him, that the time for drinking the poiſon was come. The executioner, though accuſtomed to ſuch ſcenes, ſhed tears as he preſented the fatal cup. Socrates received it without change of countenance or the leaſt appearance of perturbation : then offering up a prayer to the gods that they would grant him a prosperous passage into the inviſible world, with perfect compoſure he ſwallowed the poiſonous draught. His friends around him burſt into tears. Socrates alone remained unmoved. He upbraided their puſillanimity, and entreated them to exerciſe a manly conſtancy worthy of the friends of virtue. He continued walking till the chilling operation of the hemlock obliged him to lie down upon his bed. After remaining for a ſhort time silent, he requeſted Crito (probably in order to refute a calumny which might prove injurious to his friends after his deceaſe) not to neglect the offering of a cock which he had vowed to Eſculapius. Then, covering himſelf with his cloak, he expired. Such was the fate of the virtuous Socrates ! A ſtory, ſays Cicero, which I never read without tears.</p><p>The friends and diſciples of this illuſtrious teacher of wiſdom were deeply afflicted by his death, and attended his funeral with every expreſſion of grief. Apprehenſive, however, for their own ſafety, they ſoon afterwards privately withdrew from the city, and took up their reſidence in diſtant places. Several of them vifited the philoſopher Euclid of Megara, by whom they were kindly received. No ſooner was the unjuſt condemnation of Socrates known through Greece, than a general indignation was kindled in the minds of good men, who universally regretted that ſo diſtinguiſhed an advocate for virtue ſhould have fallen a ſacrifice to jealouſy and envy. The Athenians themſelves, ſo remarkable for their caprice, who never knew the value of their great men till after their death, ſoon became ſenſible of the folly as well as criminality of putting to death the man who had been the chief ornament of their city and of the age, and turned their indignation againſt his accuſers. Melitus was condemned to death; and Anytus, to eſcape a ſimilar fate, went into voluntary exile. To give a farther proof of the ſincerity of their regret, the Athenians for a while interrupted public buſineſs ; decreed a general mourning ; recalled the exiled friends of Socrates ; and erected a ſtatue to his memory in one of the moſt frequented parts of the city. His death happened in the firſt year of the 96th olympiad, and in the 70th year of his age.</p><p>Socrates left behind him nothing in writing ; but his illuſtrious pupils Xenophon and Plato have in ſome meaſure supplied this defect. The Memoirs of Socrates, written by Xenophon, afford, however, a much</p><p>more accurate idea of the opinions of Socrates, and of his manner of teaching, than the Dialogues of Plato, who everywhere mixes his own conceptions and diction with the ideas and language of his maſter. It is related, that when Socrates heard Plato recite his Lyſis, he ſaid, “ How much does this young man make me ſay which I never conceived !”</p><p>His diſtinguiſhing character was that of a moral philoſopher ; and his doctrine concerning God and religion was rather practical than ſpeculative. But he did not neglect to build the ſtructure of religious faith upon the firm foundation of an appeal to natural appearances ; He taught, that the Supreme Being, though inviſrble, is clearly ſeen in his works ; which at once demonſtrate his exiſtence and his wife and benevolent providence. He admitted, beſides the one Supreme Deity, the exiſtence of beings who posseſs a middle ſtation between God and man, to whoſe immediate agency he aſcribed the ordinary phenomena of nature, and whom he ſuppoſed to be particularly concerned in the management of human affairs. Hence he declared it to be the duty of everyone, in the performance of religious rites, to follow the cuſtoms of his country. At the ſame time, he taught, that the merit of all religious offerings deoends upon the character of the worſhipper, and that the gods take pleaſure in the ſacrinces of none but the truly pious.</p><p>Concerning the human soul, the opinion of Socrates, according to Xenophon, was, that it is allied to the Divine Being, not by a participation of eſſence, but by a ſimilarity of nature ; that man excels all other animals in the faculty of reaſon ; and that the exiſtence of good men will be continued after death in a ſtate in which they will receive the reward of their virtue. Although it appears that on this latter topic he was not wholly free from uncertainty, the conſolation which he profeſſed to derive from this ſource in the immediate proſpect of death, leaves little room to doubt that he entertained a real expectation of immortality : and there is reaſon to believe that he was the only philoſopher of ancient Greece whoſe principles admitted of ſuch an expectation (ſee <hi rend="smallcaps">Metaphysics,</hi> Part III. Chap iv.) Of his moral ſyſtem, which was in a high degree pure, and founded on the ſureſt basis, the reader will find a ſhort view in our article <hi rend="smallcaps">Moral Philosophy,</hi> n⁰ 4.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Socrates</hi> was alſo the name of an eccleſiaſtical historian of the 5th century, born at Conſtantinople in the beginning of the reign of Theodoſius : he profeſſed the law and pleaded at the bar, whence he obtained the name of <hi rend="italic">Scholaſticus.</hi> He wrote an eccleſiaſtical hiſtory from the year 309, where Euſebius ended, down to 440 ; and wrote with great exactneſs and judgment. An edition of Euſebius and Socrates, in Greek and Latin, with notes by Reading, was publiſhed at London in 1720.</p></div></body></text></TEI>