<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0609.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0603-06" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SOMERS</label>
(John), lord high chancellor of England, was born at Worceſter in 1652. He was educated at Oxford, and afterwards entered himſelf at the Middle- Temple, where he ſtudied the law with great vigour. In 1688 he was one of the counſel for the ſeven biſhops at their trial, and argued with great learning and eloquence againſt the diſpenſing power. In the convention which met by the prince of Orange’s ſummons, January 22. 1689, he repreſented Worceſter ; and was one of the managers for the Houſe of Commons, at a conference with the Houſe of Lords upon the word <hi rend="italic">abdicated.</hi> Soon after the acceſſion of King William and Queen Mary to the throne, he was appointed ſolicitor-general, and received the honour of knighthood. In 1692 he was made attorney general, and in 1693 advanced to the poſt of lord keeper of the great ſeal of England. In 1695 he propoſed an expedient to prevent the practice of clipping the coin. In 1697 he was created lord Somers, baron of Eveſham, and made lord high chancellor of England. In the beginning of 1700 he was removed from his poſt of lord chancellor, and the year after was impeached of high crimes and miſdemeanors by the Houſe of Commons, of which he was acquitted upon trial by the Houſe of Lords. He then retired to a ſtudious courſe of life, and was choſen preſident of the Royal Society. In 1706 he propoſed a bill for the regulation of the law ; and the ſame year was one of the principal managers for the union between England and Scotland. In 1708 he was made lord preſident of the council; from which poſt he was removed in 1710, upon the change of the miniſtry. In the latter end of Queen Anne’s reign his lordſhip grew very infirm in his health ; which is ſuppoſed to be the reaſon that he held no other poſt than a ſeat at the council-table, after the acceſſion of King George I. He died of an apoplectic fit in 1716. Mr Addiſon has drawn his character very beautifully in the Freeholder.</p></div></body></text></TEI>