<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0473.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0467-06" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SIGN</label>,
in general, the mark or character of ſomething absent or inviſible. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Character.</hi></p><p>Among phyſicians, the term <hi rend="italic">ſign</hi> denotes ſome appearance in the human body which ſerves to indicate or</p><p>point out the condition of the patient with regard to health or diſeaſe.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sign,</hi> in algebra. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Algebra,</hi> Part I.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sign,</hi> in aſtronomy, a conſtellation containing a 12th part of the zodiac. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Astronomy,</hi> n⁰ 318.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Naval</hi> SIGNALS. When we read at our fire- ſide the account of an engagement, or other intereſting operation of an army, our attention is generally ſo much engaged by the reſults, that we give but little to the movements which led to them, and produced them, and we ſeldom form to ourſelves any diſtinct notion of the conduct of the day. But a profeſſional man, or one accuſtomed to reflection, and who is not ſatisfied with the mere indulgence of eager curioſity, follows every regiment in its movements, endeavours to see their connection and the influence which they have had on the fate of the day, and even to form to himſelf a general notion of the whole ſcene of action at its different intereſting periods. He looks with the eye of the general, and sees his orders ſucceed or fail.</p><p>But few trouble themſelves farther about the narration. The movement is ordered ; it is performed ; and the fortune of the day is determined. Few think how all this is brought about ; and when they are told that during the whole of the battle of Cuſtrin, Frederic the Great was in the upper room of a country inn, from whence he could view the whole field, while his aids de camp, on horseback, waited his orders in the yard below, they are ſtruck with wonder, and can hardly conceive how it can be done : but, on reflection, they ſee the poſſibility of the thing. Their imagination accompanies the meſſenger from the inn yard to the ſcene of action ; they hear the General’s orders delivered, and they expect its execution.</p><p>But when we think for a moment on the situation of the commander of a fleet, confined on board one ſhip, and this ſhip as much, or more cloſely, engaged, than any other of the fleet ; and when we reflect that here are no meſſengers ready to carry his orders to ſhips of the ſquadron at the diſtance of miles from him, and to deliver them with preciſion and diſtinctneſs, and that even if this were poſſible by sending small ſhips or boats, the viciſſitudes of wind and weather may render the communication ſo tedious that the favourable moment may be irretrievably lost before the order can be conveyed.—When we think of all theſe circumſtances, our thoughts are bewildered, and we are ready to imagine that a ſea-battle is nothing but the unconnected ſtruggle of individual ſhips ; and that when the admiral has once “ cried havoc, and let slip the dogs of war,” he has done all that his ſituation empowers him to do, and he muſt leave the fate of the day to the bravery and ſkill of his captains and bailors.</p><p>Yet it is in this ſituation, apparently the moſt unfavourable, that the orders of the commander can be conveyed, with a diſpatch that is not attainable in the operations of a laud army. The ſcene of action is unincumbered, ſo that the eye of the General can behold the whole without interruption. The movements which <hi rend="italic">it</hi> is poſſible to exccute are few, and they are preciſe. A few words are ſufficient to order them, and then the mere fighting the ſhips muſt always be left to their reſpective commanders. This ſimplicity in the duty to be performed has enabled us to frame a language fully adequate to the buſineſs in hand, by which a correſpondence can be kept up as far as the eye can ſee. This is<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0474.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0468"/>
the language of <hi rend="smallcaps">signals,</hi> a language by writing, addresſed to the eye, and which he that runneth may read. As in common writing certain arbitrary marks are agreed on to expreſs certain founds uſed in ſpeech, or rather, as in hieroglyphics certain arbitrary marks are agreed on to expreſs certain thoughts, or the ſubjects of theſe thoughts ; ſo here certain exhibitions are made, which are agreed on to expreſs certain movements to be executed by the commander to whom they are addreſſed, and all are enjoined to keep their eyes fixed on the ſhip of the conductor of the fleet, that they may learn his will.</p><p>It is ſcarcely poſſible for any number of ſhips to act in concert, without ſome ſuch mode of communication between the general and the commanders of private ſhips. We have no direct information of this circumſtance in the naval tactics of the ancient nations, the Greeks and Romans ; yet the neceſſity of the thing is ſo apparent, that we cannot ſuppoſe it to have been omitted by the moſt ingenious and the moſt cultivated people who have appeared on the great theatre of the world; and we are perſuaded that Themiſtocles, Conon, and other renowned ſea commanders of Athens, had lignais by which they directed the movements of their fleets. We read, that when Ægeus ſent his son Theſeus to Crete, it was agreed on, that if the ſhip ſhould bring the young prince back in ſafety, a white flag ſhould be diſplayed. But thoſe on board, in their joy for reviſiting their country after their perilous voyage, forgot to hoiſt the concerted ſignal. The anxious father was every day expecting the ſhip which ſhould bring back his darling ſon, and had gone to the ſhore to look out for her. He ſaw her, but without the ſignal agreed on. On which the old man threw himſelf into the ſea. We find, too, in the hiſtory of the Punic wars by Polybius, frequent alluſions to ſuch a mode of communication ; and Ammianus Marcellinus ſpeaks of the s <hi rend="italic">peculatores</hi> and <hi rend="italic">vexillarii,</hi> who were on board the ſhips in the Adriatic. The coins both of Greece and Rome exhibit both flags and ſtreamers. In ſhort, we cannot doubt of the ancients having practiſed this hieroglyphical language. It is somewhat ſurpriſing that Lord Dudley, in his A <hi rend="italic">rcanο del Mare,</hi> in which he makes an oſtentatious diſplay of his knowledge of every thing connected with the ſea ſervice, makes no expreſs mention of this very eſſential piece of knowledge, although he must, by his long reſidence in Italy, have known the marine diſcipline of the Venetians and Genoeſe, the greateſt maritime powers then in Europe.</p><p>In the naval occurrences of modern Europe, mention is frequently made of ſignals. Indeed, as we have already obſerved, it ſeems impoſſible for a number of ſhips to act in any kind of concert, without ſome method of communication. Numberleſs ſituations muſt occur, when it would be impoſſible to convey orders or information by meſſengers from one ſhip to another, and coaſt and alarm ſignals had long been practiſed by every nation. The idea was, therefore, familiar. We find, in particular, that Queen Elizabeth, on occaſion of the expedition to Cadiz, ordered her ſecretaries to draw up inſtructions, which were to be communicated to the admiral, the general, and the five counſellors of war, and by them to be copied and transmitted to the ſeveral ſhips of the navy, not to be opened till they ſhould arrive in a certain latitude. It was on this occaſion, (ſays our hiſtorian Guthrie), “ <hi rend="italic">that we meet</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">with the first regular ſets of ſignals and orders to the commanders of the English fleet.</hi> But, till the movements of a fleet have attained ſome sort of uniformity, regulated and connected by ſome principles of propriety, and agreed on by persons in the habit of directing a number of ſhips, we may with confidence affirm that ſignals would be nothing but a parcel of arbitrary marks, appropriated to particular pieces of naval ſervice, ſuch as attacking the enemy, lauding the ſoldiers, &amp; c. ; and that they would be conſidered merely as referring to the final reſult, but by no means pointing out the mode of execution, or directing the movements which were neceſſary for performing it.</p><p>It was James II. when duke of York, who firſt conſidered this practice as capable of being reduced into a ſyſtem, and who law the importance of ſuch a compoſition. He, as well as the king his brother, had always ſhowed a great predilection for the ſea ſervice ; and, when appointed admiral of England, he turned his whole attention to its improvement. He had ſtudied the art of war under Turenne, not as a paſtime, but as a ſcience, and was a favourite pupil of that moſt accompliſhed general. Turenne one day pointed him out, ſaying, “ Behold one who will be one of the firſt princes and greateſt generals of Europe.” When admiral of England, he endeavoured to introduce into the maritime ſervice all thoſe principles of concert and arrangement which made a number of individual regiments and ſquadrons compoſe a great army. When he commanded in the Dutch war, he found a fleet to be little better than a collection of ſhips, on board of each of which the commander and his ſhip’s company did their beſt to annoy the enemy, but with very little dependence on each other, or on the orders of the General ; and in the different actions which the Engliſh fleet had with the Dutch, every thing was confuſion as ſoon as the battle began. It is remarkable that the famous pensionary De Witt, who from a ſtateſenan became a navigator and a great ſea commander in a few weeks, made the ſame repreſentation to the States General on his return from his firſt campaign.</p><p>In the memoirs of James II. written by himſelf, we have the following paſſage : “ 1665. On the 15th of March the duke of York went to Gunfleet, the general rendezvous of the fleet, and haſtened their equipment. He ordered all the flag officers on board with him every morning, to agree on the order of battle and rank. In former battles, no order was kept, and this under the duke of York was the firſt in which fighting in a line and regular form of battle was obſerved.”</p><p>This muſt be conſidered as full authority for giving the duke of York the honour of the invention. For whatever faults may be laid to the charge of this unfortunate prince, his word and honour stands unimpeached. And we are anxious to vindicate his claim to it, becauſe our neighbours the French, as uſual, would take the merit of this invention, and oſ the whole of naval tactics, to themſelves. True it is, that Colbert, the great and juſtly celebrated miniſter of Louis XIV. created a navy for his ambitious and vain-glorious maſter, and gave it a conſtitution which may be a model for other nations to copy. By his encouragement, men of the greateſt ſcientific eminence were engaged to contribute to its improvement : and they gave us the firſt treatiſes of naval evolutions. But it muſt ever be remembered, that our accompliſhed, though miſguided sovereign, was then<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0475.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0469"/>
reſiding at the court of Louis ; that he had formerly acted in concert with the French as a commander and flag officer, and was at this very time aiding them with his knowledge of ſea affairs. In the memorable day at La Hogue, the gallant Ruſſel, obſerving one of Tourville’s movements, exclaimed, “ There ! they have got Pepys<note anchored="true" n="1" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>*Pepys was secretary to the duke of York.</p></note> * among them.” This anecdote we give on the authority of a friend, who heard an old and reſpectable officer (Admiral Clinton) say, that he had it from a gentleman who was in the action, and heard the words ſpoken ; and we truſt that our readers will not be displeaſed at having this matter of general opinion eſtabliſhed on ſome good grounds.</p><p>It was on this occaſion, then, that the duke of York made the movements and evolutions of a fleet the object of his particular ſtudy, reduced them to a ſyſtem, and compoſed that “ Syſtem of Sailing and Fighting Inſtructions,” which has ever ſince been conſidered as the code of diſcipline for the British navy, and which has been adopted by our rivals and neighbours as the foundation of their naval tactics. It does great honour to its author, although its merit will not appear very eminent to a careleſs ſurveyor, on account of that very ſimplicity which conſtitutes its chief excellence. It is unqueſtionably the reſult of much ſagacious reflection and painful combination of innumerable circumſtances, all of which have their influence ; and it is remarkable, that although succeeding commanders have improved the ſubject by ſeveral ſubordinate additions, no change has to this day been made in its general principles or maxims of evolution.</p><p>Till ſome ſuch code be eſtabliſhed, it is evident that ſignals can be nothing but arbitrary and unconnected hieroglyphics, to be learned by rote, and retained by memory, without any exercise of the judgment ; and the acquiſition of this branch of nautical ſkill muſt be a more irkſome talk than that of learning the Chinese writing. But ſuch a code being once ſettled, the character in which it may be expreſſed becomes a matter of rational diſcuſſion.</p><p>Accordingly, the ſailing and fighting inſtructions of the duke of York were accompanied by a ſet of ſignals for directing the chief or moſt frequent movements of the fleet. Theſe alſo were contrived with ſo much judgment, and ſuch attention to diſtinctneſs, ſimplicity, and propriety, that there has hardly been any change found neceſſary ; and they are ſtill retained in the Britiſh navy as the uſual ſignals in all caſes when we are not anxious to conceal our movements from an enemy.</p><p>Notwithſtanding this acknowledged merit of the duke of York’s ſignals, it muſt be admitted that great improvements have been made on this ſubject, conſidered as an art. The art military has, in the courſe of a century paſt, become almoſt an appropriate calling, and has therefore been made the peculiar ſtudy of its profeſſors. Our rivals the French were ſooner, and more formally, placed in this ſituation, and the miniſters of Louis XIV. took infinite and moſt judicious pains to make their military men superior to all others by their academical education. A more ſcientific turn was given to their education, and the aſſiſtance of ſcientific men was liberally given them ; and all the nations of Europe muſt acknowledge ſome obligations to them for information on every thing connected with the art of war. They have attended very much to this ſubject, have greatly improved it, and have even introduced a</p><p>new principle into the art ; and by this means have reduced it to the moſt ſimple form of reference to the code of ſailing and fighting inſtructions, by making the ſignals immediately expreſſive, not of orders, but of ſimple numbers. Theſe numbers being prefixed to the various articles of the code of inſtructions, the officer who sees a signal thrown out by the admiral reads the number, and reports it to his captain, perhaps without knowing to what it relates. Thus ſimplicity and ſecrecy, with an unlimited power of variation, are combined. We believe that M. de la Bourdonnais, a brave and intelligent officer, during the war 1758, was the author of this ingenious thought.</p><p>We do not propoſe to give a ſyſtem of Britiſh ſignals. This would evidently be improper. But we ſhall (how our readers the practicability of this curious language, the extent to which it may be carried, and the methods which may be practiſed in accompliſhing this purpoſe. This may make it an object of attention to ſcientific men, who can improve it ; and the young officer will not only be able to read the orders of the commander in chief, but will not be at a loſs, ſhould circumſtances place him in a ſituation where he muſt iſſue orders to others.</p><p>Signals may be divided into,</p><p>I. <hi rend="smallcaps">Day Signals.</hi></p><p>II. <hi rend="smallcaps">Night Signals</hi>; and,</p><p>III. <hi rend="smallcaps">Signals</hi> in a <hi rend="smallcaps">Fog.</hi></p><p>They muſt alſo be diſtinguiſhed into, 1. Signals of <hi rend="smallcaps">Evolution,</hi> addressed to the whole <hi rend="smallcaps">Fleet,</hi> or to <hi rend="smallcaps">Squadrons</hi> of the fleet, or to <hi rend="smallcaps">Divisions</hi> of theſe ſquadrons. 2. Signals of <hi rend="smallcaps">Movements</hi> to be made by particular ſhips ; and, 3. Signals of <hi rend="smallcaps">Service,</hi> which may be either general or particular.</p><p>The great extent of a large fleet, the ſmoke in time of battle, and the ſituation of the commander in chief, wſho is commonly in the midſt of the greateſt confuſion and hotteſt fire, frequently makes it very difficult for the officers of diſtant ſhips to perceive his ſignals with diſtinctneſs, Frigates, therefore, are ſtationed out of the line, to windward or to leeward, whoſe ſole office it is to obſerve the admiral’s ſignals, and inſtantly to repeat them. The eyes of all the ſignal officers in the private ships of war are directed to the repeating frigates, as well as to the admiral ; and the officers of the repeating frigate, having no other duty, obſerve the admiral inceſſantly, and, being unembarraſſed by the action, can diſplay the ſignal with deliberation, ſo that it may be very diſtinctly ſeen. Being minutely acquainted with the ſubſtitutions which muſt be made on board the admiral when his maſts and rigging are in diſorder, his (perhaps imperfect) ſignal is exhibited by the repeating frigate in its proper form, ſo as to be eaſily underſtood. And to facilitate this communication, the commanders of the different ſquadrons repeat the ſignals of the commander in chief, and the commanders of diviſion repeat the ſignals of the commanders of their ſquadron.</p><p>Every evolution ſignal is preceded by a ſignal of <hi rend="smallcaps">advertisement</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">preparation,</hi> which is general, and frequently by a gun, to call attention ; and when all the ſignals have been made which direct the different parts of that evolution, another ſignal is made, which marks the cloſe of the complex ſignal, and divides it from others which may immediately follow it : and as the orders of, the commander in chief may relate either to the movements of the whole fleet, thoſe of a Angle diviſion, or<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0476.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0470"/>
thoſe of certain private ſhips, the <hi rend="smallcaps">Executive Signal,</hi> which dictates the particular movement, is accompanied by a <hi rend="smallcaps">Directive Signal,</hi> by which theſe ſhips are pointed out, to which the order is addreſſed.</p><p>The commander of the ſhip to which any ſignal is addreſſed, is generally required to ſignify by a ſignal (which is general) that he has obſerved it. And if he does not thoroughly underſtand its meaning, he intimates this by another general ſignal. And here it is to be obſerved, that as ſoon as the ſignal is anſwered by the ſhips to which it is addreſſed, it is uſual to haul it down, to avoid the confuſion which might ariſe from others being hoiſted in the same place. The order remains till executed, notwithſtanding that the ſignal is hauled down.</p><p>It may happen that the commander who throws out the ſignal for any piece of ſervice, sees reaſons for altering his plan. He intimates this by a general <hi rend="smallcaps">Annulling</hi> ſignal, accompanying the ſignal already given. This will frequently be more ſimple than to make the ſignals for the movements which would be required for re-eſtabliſhing the ſhips in their former ſituation.</p><p>All theſe things are of very eaſy comprehenſion, and require little thought for their contrivance. But when we come to the particular evolutions and movements, and to combine theſe with the circumſtances of ſituation in which the fleet may be at the time, it is evident, that much reflection is neceſſary for framing a body of ſignals which may be eaſily exhibited, diſtinctly perceived, and well underſtood, with little risk of being miſtaken one for another. We ſhall take notice of the circumſtances which chiefly contribute to give them theſe qualities as we proceed in describing their different claſſes.</p><p>I. <hi rend="italic">Of</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">Day Signals.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">These</hi> are made by means of the ſhip’s sails, or by colours of various kinds.</p><p>Thoſe made with sails are but few in number, and are almoſt neceſſarily limited to the ſituation of a fleet at anchor. Thus,</p><table> <row> <cell><hi rend="italic">The following Signals</hi></cell> <cell><hi rend="italic">uſually signify,</hi></cell> </row> <row> <cell>Main top-gallant ſtayſail hoiſted</cell> <cell>Officers and men belonging to the ſhip to come on board.</cell> </row> <row> <cell>Fore top-ſail looſe</cell> <cell>To prepare for sailing.</cell> </row> <row> <cell>Main top-ſail looſe</cell> <cell>To unmoor.</cell> </row> <row> <cell>Main top-ſail ſheets hauled home</cell> <cell>To weigh.</cell> </row> <row> <cell>Main top-ſail ſheets clewed up, and the yard hoiſted</cell> <cell>Annul the former ſignal, and the ſhip to come to an anchor.</cell> </row> <row> <cell>Top-gallant sails looſe, and the ſheets flying</cell> <cell>Diſcovering ſtrange ſails.</cell> </row> <row> <cell>Main top-gallant sail looſe and hoiſted. Topſail- yard down</cell> <cell>Recal ſhips in chaſe.</cell> </row> <row> <cell>Mizen top-sail hoiſted, and the ſheets clewed up</cell> <cell>Moor.</cell> </row> </table><p>Before we proceed to the deſcription of the ſignals by means of colours, ſuch as <hi rend="smallcaps">flags, banners</hi> (or triangular flags), <hi rend="smallcaps">pendants</hi> or <hi rend="smallcaps">vanes,</hi> we muſt take notice of the oſtenſible diſtinctions of the various diviſions and</p><p>ſubdiviſions of a fleet, ſo that we may underſtand how the ſame ſignal may be addreſſed to a ſquadron, diviſion, or ſingle ſhip or ſhips. We ſuppose it known that a fleet of ſhips of war is diſtributed into three grand divisions (which we ſhall term <hi rend="italic">quadrons),</hi> called the <hi rend="italic">van, centre,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">rear.</hi> Theſe denominations have not always a relation to the one being more advanced than the other, either towards the enemy, or in the direction of their course.</p><p>In a land army, the poſition of every part is conceived from its reference to the enemy ; and the reader, conceiving himſelf as facing the enemy, eaſily underſtands the terms <hi rend="italic">van, centre,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">rear,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">right</hi> and <hi rend="italic">left wing,</hi> &amp; c. But the movements of a ſea army having a neceſſary dependence on the wind, they cannot be comprehended unleſs expreſſed in a language which keeps this circumſtance continually in view. The ſimpleſt and moſt eaſily conceived diſpoſition of a fleet, is that in which it is almoſt indiſpenſably obliged to form in order to engage an enemy. This is a ſtraight line, each ſhip directly a-head of its neighbour, and cloſe hauled. This is therefore called the <hi rend="italic">line oſ battle.</hi> In this poſition, the two extremities of the fleet correſpond to the right and left wings of an army. Suppose this line to be in the direction eaſt and west, the wind blowing from the north-north-weſt, and therefore the fleet on the ſtarboard tack ; the ſhips heads are to the west, and the weſtermoſt diviſion is undoubtedly the van of the fleet, and the eaſtermoſt diviſion is the rear. And it is in conformity to this arrangement and ſituation that the <hi rend="smallcaps">list of the fleet</hi> is drawn up. But the ſhips may be on the ſame eaſt and west line, cloſe hauled, with their heads to the west, but the wind blowing from the ſouth-ſouth-weſt. They muſt therefore be on the larboard tack. Tlre ſame ſhips, and the ſame diviſion, are ftill, in fact, the van or the fleet. But ſuppoſe the ſhips heads to be to the eaſtward, and that they are cloſe hauled, having the wind from the ſouth-ſouth-eaſt or the north-north-eaſt, the ſhips which were the real van on both tacks in the former ſituation are now, in fact, the rear on both tacks ; yet they retain the denomination of the <hi rend="italic">van ſquadron</hi> of this fleet, and are under the immediate direction of the officer of the second rank, while the other extremity is under the direction of the third officer. This subordination therefore is rather an arrangement of rank and precedence than of evolution. It is, however, conſidered as the <hi rend="smallcaps">natural order</hi> to which the general ſignals muſt be accommodated. For this reaſon, the diviſion which is denominated <hi rend="italic">van</hi> in the lift of this fleet, is <hi rend="italic">generally</hi> made to lead the fleet when in the line of battle on the ſtarboard tack, and to form the <hi rend="italic">weathermost</hi> column in <hi rend="italic">the order of sailing in columns ;</hi> and, in general, it occupies that ſtation from which it can moſt eaſily pass into the place of the leading diviſion on the ſtarboard line of battle ahead. Although this is a technical nicety of language, and may frequently puzzle a landſman in reading an account of naval operations, the reflecting and intelligent reader will ſee the propriety of retaining this mode of conceiving the ſubordrnate arrangement of a fleet, and will comprehend the employment of the ſignals which are neceſſary for re-eſtabliſhing this arrangement, or directing the movements while another arrangement is retained.</p><p>This being underſtood, it is eaſy to contrive various<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0477.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0471"/>
methods oſ diſtinguishing every ship by the place which ſhe occupies in the fleet, both with reſpect to the whole line, with reſpect to the particular ſquadron, the particular diviſion of that ſquadron, and the particular place in that diviſion. This may be done by a combination of the poſition and colour oſ the pendants and vanes of each ſhip. Thus the colour of the pendants may indicate the ſquadron, their poſition or maſt on which they are hoiſted may mark the diviſion of that ſquadron, and a diſtinguiſhing vane may mark the place of the private ſhip in her own diviſion. The advantages attending this method are many. In a large fleet it would hardly be poſſible for the commander in chief to find a ſufficient variety of ſingle lignais to mark the ſhip to which an order is addreſſed, by hoiſting it along with the ſignal appropriated to the intended movement. But by this contrivance one-third part of theſe ſignals oſ addreſs is ſufficient. It alſo enables the commander in chief to order a general change of poſition by a ſingle ſignal, which otherwiſe would require ſeveral. Thus, ſuppoſe that the fore, main, and mizen maſts, are appropriated (with the proper modifications) for exhibiting the ſignals addreſſed to the van, the centre, and the rear squadrons of the fleet, and that a red, a white, and a blue flag, are choſen for the diſtinguiſhing flags of the officers commanding theſe ſquadrons ; then, if the commander in chief ſhall hoiſt a red flag at his mizen top-gallant maſt head, it muſt direct the van ſquadron to take the poſition then occupied by the rear ſquadron, the evolution neceſſary for accompliſhing this end being ſuppoſed known by the commander of the ſquadron, who will immediately make the neceſſary ſignals to the ſquadron under his particular direction. In the ſame manner, the diſtinguiſhing ſignal for the leading ſhip of a ſquadron being hoiſted along with the ſignal of addreſs to the whole fleet, and the ſignal for any particular ſervice, will cauſe the three or the nine leading ſhips to execute that order, &amp; c. &amp; c.</p><p>All that has been laid hitherto may be conſidered as ſo many preparations for the real iſſuing of orders by the commander in chief. The moſt difficult part of the language remains, viz. to invent a number of ſignals which ſhall correſpond to that almoſt infinite variety of movements and ſervices which muſt be performed.</p><p>Diſtinctness, ſimplicity, and propriety, are the three eſſential qualities of all ſignals. A ſignal muſt be ſome object easily ſeen, ſtrongly marked, ſo that it may be readily underſtood, with little risk of its being miſtaken for another. When made by flags, banners, or pendants, they muſt be of the fulleſt colours, and ſtrongeſt contrails. The ſhips are frequently at a very great diſtance, ſo that the intervening air occasions a great degradation of colour. They are ſeen between the eye and a very variable sky ; and in this ſituation, eſpecially in the morning or evening, or a dark day, it is not easy to diſtinguiſh one full colour from another, all of them approaching to the appearance of a black. At the diſtance of a very few miles hardly any full colours can be diſtinguiſhed but a ſcarlet and a blue. Red, blue, yellow, and white, are the colours which can be diſtinguiſhed at greater diſtances than any others, and are therefore the only colours admitted as ſignals. Even theſe are ſometimes diſtinguiſhed with difficulty. A yellow is often confounded with a dirty white, and a</p><p>blue with a red. All other dark colours are found totally unfit. But as theſe afford but a ſmall variety, we muſt combine them in one flag, by making it ſtriped, ſpotted, or chequered, taking care that the oppoſition of colour may be as great as poſſible, and that the pieces of which the flags are made up may not be too minute. Red muſt never be ſtriped nor ſpotted with blue, and the ſtripes, ſpots, or chequers, ſhould never be leſs than one-third of the breadth of the flag. Plate CCCCLXVI. is a selection by an officer of experience as a let very eaſily recogniſed, and little liable to be con rounded. Their colours are repreiented by hatching, in the same manner as in heraldry (See <hi rend="smallcaps">Heraldry ).</hi></p><p>Difference of ſhape, as flags, banners, or pendants, is another diſtinction by which the expreſſion may be varied. And in doing this, we muſt recollect, that in light winds it may be difficult to diſtinguiſh a flag from a banner, as neither are fully displayed for want ot wind to detach the fly from the ſtaff.</p><p>And, laſtly, ſignals may be varied by their poſition,; which may be on any lofty and well detached part of the maſts, yards, or rigging.</p><p>Simplicity is an eminent property in all ſignals. They are addreſſed to persons not much accuſtomed to combinations, and who are probably much occupied by other preſſing duties. It were to be wiſhed that every piece of ſervice could be indicated by a ſingle flag. This is peculiarly definable with reſpect to the ſignals uſed in time of battle. The rapid ſuccession of events on this occaſion call for a multitude of orders from the commander in chief, and his ſhip is frequently clad over with flags and pendants, ſo that it is exceedingly difficult for the ſignal officer of a private ſhip to diſtinguiſh the different groups, each of which make a particular ſignal.</p><p>Theſe conſiderations are the foundation of a certain <hi rend="italic">propriety</hi> in ſignals, which directs us to a choice among marks which appear altogether arbitrary. Signals which run any riſk of being confounded, on account of ſome reſemblance, or becauſe their poſition hinders us from immediately perceiving their difference, ſhould be appropriated to pieces of ſervice which are hardly poſſible to be executed, or can hardly be wanted, in the ſame ſituation. No bad consequence could eaſily result though the ſignal for <hi rend="italic">coming to cloſer action</hi> ſhould reſemble that for <hi rend="italic">unmooring,</hi> becauſe the preſent ſituation of the ſhips makes the laſt operation impoſſible or abſurd. Such conſiderations direct us to lelect for battle ſignals, thoſe which are of eaſieſt exhibition, are the moſt ſimple, and have the leaſt dependence on the circumſtance of poſition ; ſo that their signification may not be affected by the damages ſuſtained in the maſts or rigging of the flag ſhip. Such ſignals as are leſs eaſily ſeen at a diſtance, ſhould be appropriated to orders which can occur only in the middle of the fleet, &amp; c. &amp; c. Signals which are made to the admiral by private ſhips may be the ſame with ſignals of command from the flag ſhip, which will conſiderably diminish the number of ſignals perfectly different from each other.</p><p>With all theſe attentions and precautions a ſyſtem of ſignals is at laſt made up, fitted to the code of sailing and fighting inſtructions. It is accompanied by another ſmall ſet for the duty of convoys. It muſt be engroſſed in two books ; one for the officer of the flag ſhip, who is to make the ſignals, and the other is<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0478.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0472"/>
delivered to every private ſhip. In the firſt, the evolutions, movements, and other operations of ſervice, are ſet down in one column, and their correſponding ſignals in another. The firſt column is arranged, either alphabetically, by the diſtinguiſhing phraſe, or ſyſtematically, according to the arrangement of the sailing and fighting inſtructions. The officer whoſe duty it is to make the ſignals, turns to this column for the order which he is to communicate, and in the other column he finds the appropriated ſignal.</p><p>In the other book, which is consulted for the interpretation of the ſignals, they are arranged in the leading column, either by the flags, or by the places of their exhibition. The firſt is the beſt method, becauſe the derangement of the flag ſhip’s maſts and rigging in time of action may occaſion a change in the place of the ſignal.</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">Tactique Navale</hi> of the Chevalier de Morogues contains a very full and elaborate treatiſe on ſignals. We recommend this work to every ſea-officer, as full of inſtruction. The art of ſignals has been greatly simplified ſince the publication of this work, but we cannot but aſcribe much of the improvements to it. We believe that the author is the inventor of that ſyſtematic manner of addreſſing the order or effective signal to the different squadrons and diviſions of the fleet, by which the art of ſignals is made more conciſe, the execution of orders is rendered more ſyſtematic, and the commanders of private ſhips are accuſtomed to conſider themſelves as parts of an army, with a mutual dependence and connection. We are ready enough to acknowledge the ſuperiority of the French in manoeuvring, but we affect to conſider this as an imputation on their courage. Nothing can be more unjuſt ; and dear- bought experience ſhould long ere now have taught us the value of this ſuperiority. What avails that courage which we would willingly arrogate to ourſelves, if we cannot come to action with our enemy, or muſt do it in a ſituation in which it is almoſt impoſſible to succeed, and which needleſsly throws away the lives of our gallant crews? Yet this muſt happen, if our admirals do not make evolutions their careful ſtudy, and our captains do not habituate themſelves, from their firſt hoiſting a pendant, to conſider their own ſhip as connected with the moſt remote ſhip in the line. We cannot think that this view of their ſituation would in the leaſt leſſen the character which they have ſo juſtly acquired, of fighting their ſhip with a courage and firmneſs unequalled by thoſe of any other nation. And we may add, that it is only by ſuch a rational ſtudy of their profeſſion, that the gentleman can be diſtinguiſhed from the mercenary commander of a privateer.</p><p>II. <hi rend="smallcaps">Night Signals.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">It</hi> is evident, that the communication of orders by night muſt be more difficult and more imperfect than by day. We muſt, in general, content ourſelves with ſuch orders as are neceſſary for keeping the fleet together, by directing the more general movements and evolutions which any change of circumſtances may render neceſſary. And here the diviſion and ſubordinate arrangement of the fleet is of indispenſable neceſſity, it being hardly possible to particulariſe every ſhip by a ſignal of addreſs, or to see her ſituation. The orders are therefore addreſſed to the commanders of the diffe</p><p>rent diviſions, each of whom is diſtinguiſhed by his poop and top-lights, and is in the midst of, and not very remote from, the ſhips under his more particular charge. Yet even in this unfavourable ſituation, it is frequently neceſſary to order the movements of particular ſhips. Actions during the night are not uncommon. Pursuits and rallyings are ſtill oſtener carried on at this time. The common dangers of the ſea are as frequent and more disaſtrous. The ſyſtem of ſignals therefore is very incomplete till this part be accompliſhed.</p><p>Night ſignals muſt be made by guns, or by lights, or by both combined.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Gun-ſignals</hi> are ſuſceptible of variety both in number and in difpoſition. The only diſtinct variation which can be made in this diſpoſition, is by means of the time elapſed between the diſcharges. This will easily admit of three varieties, flow, moderate, and quick.— Half-minute guns are as flow as can easily be liſtened to as appertaining to one ſignal. Quarter-minute guns are much better, and admit of two very diſtinct ſubdivisions. When the gunners, therefore, are well trained to this ſervice (eſpecially ſince the employment of firelocks for cannon), intervals of 15 or 12 seconds may be taken for slow firing, 8 or 10 ſeconds for moderate, and 4 or 5 ſeconds for quick firing. If theſe could be reduced one half, and made with certainty and preciſion, the expreſſion would be incomparably more diſtinct. A very ſmall number of firings varied in this way will give a conſiderable number of ſignals. Thus five guns, with the variety of only quick and moderate, will give 20 very diſtinguiſhable ſignals. The ſame principle muſt be attended to here as in the flag ſignals. The moſt simple muſt be appropriated to the moſt important orders, ſuch as occur in the worſt weather, or ſuch as are moſt liable to be miſtaken. Quick firing ſhould not make part of a ſignal to a very diſtant ſhip, becauſe the noiſe of a gun at a great diſtance is a lengthened found, and two of them, with a very ſhort interval, are apt to coalesce into one long continued found. This mode of varying gun-ſignals by the time muſt therefore be employed with great caution, and we muſt be very certain of the ſteady performance of the gunners.</p><p>Note, that a preparatory ſignal or advertiſement that an effective ſignal is to be made, is a very neceſſary circumſtance. It is uſual (at leaſt in hard weather) to make this by a double diſcharge, with an interval of half a ſecond, or at moſt a ſecond.</p><p>Gun-ſignals are seldom made alone, except in ordinary ſituations and moderate weather ; becauſe accident may derange them, and inattention may cauſe them to eſcape notice, and, once made, they are over, and their repetition would change their meaning. They are alſo improper on an enemy’s coaſt, or where an enemy’s cruiſers or fleets may be expected.</p><p>Signals by lights are either made with <hi rend="smallcaps">lights</hi> ſimply ſo called, <hi rend="italic">i. e.</hi> lanthorns ſhown in different parts of the ſhip, or by rockets. Lights may differ by number, and by poſition, and alſo by figure. For the flag ship always carrying poop or top-lights, or both, preſents an object in the darſkeſt night, ſo that we can tell whether the additional lights are exhibited about the mainmaſt, the foremaſt, the mizenmaſt, &amp; c. And if the lights ſhown from any of theſe ſituations are arranged in certain diſtinguiſhable ſituations in reſpect to each other, the<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0479.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0473"/>
number of ſignals may be greatly increaſed. Thus three lights may be in a vertical line, or in a horizontal line, or in a triangle, and the point of this triangle may be up, or down, or forward, or aft, and thus may have many significations.</p><p>Lights are alſo exhibited by falſe fires or rockets : Theſe can be varied by number, and by ſuch differences of appearance as to make them very diſtinguiſhable. Rockets may be with ſtars, with rain fire, or ſimple ſquibs.</p><p>By varying and combining theſe, a very great number of ſignals may be produced, fully ſufficient to direct every general movement or evolution, or any ordinary and important ſervice. The Chevalier de Morogues has given a ſpecimen oſ ſuch a ſyſtem of night ſignals, into which he has even introduced ſignals of addreſs or direction to every ſhip of a large fleet ; and has alſo given ſignals of number, by which depths of foundings, points of the compaſs, and other things of this kind, may be expreſſed both eaſily and diſtinctly. He has made the ſignals by rockets perfectly ſimilar in point of number to thoſe by lanthorns, ſo that the commander can take either ; a choice which may have its uſe, becauſe the ſignals by rockets may cauſe the preſence of a fleet to be more extenſively known than may be convenient.</p><p>The commander in chief will inform the fleet by ſignal, that guns, or perhaps rockets, are not to be uſed that night. This ſignal, at the ſame time, directs the fleet to cloſe the line or columns, that the light ſignals may be better obſerved.</p><p>It is indeed a general rule to ſhow as few lights as poſſible ; and the commander frequently puts out his own poop and top-lights, only ſhowing them from time to time, that his ſhips may keep around him.</p><p>The ſignal lanthorns on board the flag ſhip, and a lanthorn kept in readineſs on board of every private ſhip, to anſwer or acknowledge ſignals from the commander in chief, are all kept in bags, to conceal their lights till the moment they are fixed in their places, and the preparatory or advertiſing ſignal has been made.</p><p>The commander in chief sometimes orders by ſignal every ſhip to ſhow a light for a minute or two, that he may judge of the poſition of the fleet ; and the admiral’s ſignal muſt always be acknowledged by thoſe to whom it is addreſſed.</p><p>It is of particular importance that the fleet be kept together. Therefore the leading ſhips of the fleet, on either tack, are enjoined to acknowledge the ſignals of the commander in chief by a ſignal peculiar to their station. Thus the commander in chief learns the poſition of the extremities of his fleet.</p><p>In framing a ſet of night ſignals, great attention muſt be given to their poſition, that they be not obſcured by the ſails. The nature of the order to be given will frequently determine this. Thus, an order for the rear ſhips to make more ſail, will naturally direct us to exhibit the ſignal at the mizen peek ; and ſo of other pieces of ſervice. Lanthorns expoſed in groups, ſuch as triangles, lozenges, &amp; c. arc commonly ſuſpended at the corners of large frames of laths, at the diſtance of a fathom at leaſt from each other. Attempts have been made to ſhow lights of different colours; but the risk of miſtake or failure in the composition at the laboratory,</p><p>makes this rather hazardous. Coloured lanthorns are more certain ; but when the glaſſes are made of a colour ſufficiently intenſe, the vivacity of the light (which at no time is very great) is too much diminiſhed. Beſides, the very diſtance changes the colour exceedingly and unaccountably.</p><p>III. O <hi rend="italic">f</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">Signals</hi> <hi rend="italic">in a</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">Fog.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">These</hi> can be made only by noiſes, ſuch as the firing oſ cannon and muſkets, the beating of drums and ringing of bells, &amp; c. Fog ſignals are the moſt difficult to contrive of any, and are ſuſceptible of the leaſt variety. The commander in chief is principally concerned to keep his fleet together ; and unleſs something very urgent requires it, he will make no change in his courſe or rate of failing. But a ſhift of wind or other cauſes may make this neceſſary. The changes which he will order, it will be prudent to regulate by ſome fixed rule, which is in general convenient. Thus, when a fleet is in the order of sailing upon a wind, and a fog comes on, the fleet will hold on the ſame courſe. If the wind ſhould come a little more on the beam, the fleet will ſtill keep cloſe to the wind. Certain general rules of this kind being agreed on, no ſignals are neceſſary for keeping the fleet together; and the ſhips can ſeparate or run foul of each other only by difference in their rate of sailing, or by inaccurate ſteerage. To prevent this, the commander in chief fires a gun from time to time, and the ſhips of the fleet judge of his ſituation and diſtance by the found. The commanders of diviſions fire guns, with ſome diſtinction from thoſe of the commander in chief. This both informs the commander in chief of the poſition of his ſquadrons, and enables the private ſhips of each diviſion to keep in the neighbourhood of their own flag ſhip. On board of every private ſhip the drum is beaten, or the bell is chimed, every quarter of an hour, according as the ſhip is on the ſtarboard or larboard tack. By ſuch contrivances, it is never difficult to keep a fleet in very good order when sailing on a wind. The wind is almoſt always moderate, and the ſhips keep under a very eaſy ſail. It is much more difficult when going large, and ſeparation can be prevented only by the moſt unwearied attention. The greateſt riſk is the falling in with ſtrange ſhips ſteering another courſe.</p><p>But evolutions and other movements are frequently indiſpenſable. The courſe muſt be changed by tacking or wearing, and other ſervices muſt be performed. None, however, are admitted but the moſt probable, the moſt ſimple, and the moſt neceſſary.</p><p>The commander in chief firſt informs the fleet by the <hi rend="italic">preparatory fog signal,</hi> that he is about to order an evolution, and that he is to direct it by f <hi rend="italic">og signals.</hi> This precaution is indiſpenſable to prevent miſtakes. Along with this advertiſing ſignal he makes the ſignal of the movement intended. This not only calls the attention of the fleet, but makes the ſhips prepare for the preciſe execution of that movement. The commanders of diviſions repeat the advertiſing ſignal, which informs their ſhips of their ſituation, and the private ſhips beat their drums or chime their bells. Thus the whole ſhips of the fleet cloſe a little, and become a little better acquainted with their mutual poſition. It is now underſtood that a movement is to be made preciſely a quarter of an hour after the advertiſement. At<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0480.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0474"/>
the expiration of this time, the effective ſignal for this movement is made by the commander in chief, and muſt be inſtantly repeated by the commanders of diviſions, and then the movement muſt be made by each ship, according to the sailing and fighting inſtructions. This muſt be done with the utmoſt attention and preciſion, bccauſe it produces a prodigious change in the relative poſition of the ſhips ; and even although the good ſenſe of the commander in chief will ſelect ſuch movements for accomplishing his purpoſe as produce the ſmalleſt alterations, and the leaſt, riſk oſ ſeparation or running foul of each other ; it is ſtill extremely difficult to avoid theſe misfortunes. To prevent this as much as poſſible, each ſhip which has executed the movement, or which has come on a courſe thwarting that of the fleet, intimates this by a ſignal properly adapted, often adding the ſignal of the tack on which it is now standing, and even its particular ſignal of recognizance. This is particularly incumbent on the flag ſhips and the leading ſhips of each diviſion.</p><p>After a reaſonable interval, the commander in chief will make proper ſignals for bringing the fleet to a knowledge of their reunion in this new poſition.</p><p>This muſt ſerve for a general account of the circumstances which muſt be attended to in framing a code of ſignals. The arbitrary characters in which the language is written muſt be left to the ſagacity of the gentlemen of the profeſſion. It muſt be obſerved, that the ſtratagems of war make ſecrecy very neceſſary. It may be of immenſe hazard if the enemy ſhould understand our ſignals. In time of battle it might frequently fruſtrate our attempts to deſtroy them, and at all times would enable them to eſcape, or to throw us into disorder. Every commander of a ſquadron, therefore, iſſues private ſignals, ſuited to his particular destination ; and therefore it is neceſſary that our code of ſignals be ſuſceptible of endleſs variations. This is exceedingly eaſy without any increaſe of their number. The commander needs only intimate that ſuch and such a ſignal is ſo and ſo changed in its meaning during his command.</p><p>We cannot leave this article without returning to an obſervation which we made almoſt in the beginning, viz. that the ſyſtem of ſignals, or, to speak more properly, the manner of framing this ſyſtem, has received much improvement from the gentlemen of the French navy, and particularly from the moſt ingenious thought of M. de la Bourdonnais, of making the ſignals the immediate expreſſions of <hi rend="italic">numbers</hi> only, which numbers may be afterwards tiled to indicate any order whatever. We ſhall preſent our readers with a ſcheme or two of the manner in which this may be done for all ſignals, both day, night, and fog. This alone may be considered as a ſyſtem of ſignals, and is equally applicable to every kind of information at a diſtance. Without detracting in the ſmalleſt degree ſrom the praiſe due to M. de la Bourdonnais, we muſt obſerve, that this principle oſ <hi rend="italic">notation</hi> is of much older date. Biſhop Wilkins, in his Secret and Swift Meſſenger, expreſsly recommends it, and gives ſpecimens of the manner of execution ; ſo does Dr Hooke in ſome of his propoſals to the Royal Society. Gaſpar Schottus alſo mentions it in his <hi rend="italic">Technica Curiosa ;</hi> and Kircher, among others of his Curious Projects.</p><p>M. de la Bourdonnais’s method is as follows :</p><p>He chooſes pendants for his effective ſignals, becauſe they are the moſt eaſily displayed in the proper order. Several pendants, making part of one ſignal, may be hoiſted by one hallyard, being ſtopped on it at the diſtance of four or six feet from each other. If it be found proper to throw out another ſignal at the ſame time and place, they are ſeparated by a red pendant without a point. His colours are choſen with judgement, being very diſtinctly recogniſed, and not liable to be confounded with the addreſſing ſignals appropriated to the different ſhips of the fleet. They are,</p><p>For N⁰ I. Red. For N⁰ 6. Red, with blue tail.</p><p>2. White. 7. White, with blue tail.</p><p>3 Blue. 8. White, with red tail.</p><p>4. Yellow. 9. Blue, with yellow tail.</p><p>5. Red, with 0. Yellow, with blue tail.</p><p>white tail.</p><p>Three ſets oſ ſuch pendants will expreſs every number under a thouſand, by hoiſting one above the other, and reckoning the uppermoſt hundreds, the next below it tens, and the loweſt units. Thus the number 643 will be expreſſed by a pendant red with blue tail, a yellow pendant below it, and a blue one below the laſt.</p><p>This method has great advantages. The ſignals may be hoiſted in any place where beſt ſeen, and therefore the ſignification is not affected by the derangement of the flag ſhip’s mails and rigging. And by appropriating the ſmaller numbers to the battle ſignals, they are more ſimple, requiring fewer pendants.</p><p>As this nrethod requires a particular ſet of colours, it has its inconveniences. An admiral is often obliged to ſhift his flag, even in time of action. He cannot eaſily take the colours along with him. It is therefore better to make uſe of ſuch colours as every private ſhip, is provided with. One ſet of 11 will do, with the addition of three, at moſt oſ four pendants, of ſingular make, to mark 100, 200, 300, 400. Two of theſe flags, one above the other, will expreſs any number under 100, by uſing the 11th as a ſubſtitute for any flag that ſhould be repeated. Thus the 11th flag, along with the flag for eight or for six, will expreſs the number 88 or 66, &amp; c. Thus we are able to expreſs every number below 500, and this is iuſſicient for a very large code of ſignals.</p><p>And in order to diminiſh as much as poſſible the number of theſe compound ſignals, it will be proper that a number of ſingle flag ſignals be preſerved, and even varied by circumstances of poſition, for orders which are of very frequent occurrence, and which can hardly occur in ſituations where any obſtructions are occasioned by loss of maſts, &amp; c. And farther, to avoid all chance of miſtake, a particular ſignal can be added, intimating that the ſignals now exhibited are numerary ſignals ; or, which is ſtill better, all ſignals may be conſidered as numerary ſignals; and thoſe which we have juſt now called si <hi rend="italic">ngle flag signals</hi> may be ſet down oppoſite to, or as expreſſing, the largeſt numbers of the code.</p><p>This method requires the ſignal of advertiſement, the annulling ſignal, the ſignal of addreſs to the particular ſhip or diviſion, the ſignal of acknowledgment, the ſignal of indiſtinctneſs, of diſtreſs, of danger, and<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0481.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0475"/>
one or two more which, in every method, muſt be employed.</p><p>Another method of expreſſing numbers with fewer colours is as follows : Let the flags be A, B, C, D, E, F, and arrange them as follows :</p><table> <row> <cell>A</cell> <cell>B</cell> <cell>C</cell> <cell>D</cell> <cell>E</cell> <cell>F</cell> </row> <row> <cell>I</cell> <cell>2</cell> <cell>3</cell> <cell>4</cell> <cell><hi rend="italic">5</hi></cell> <cell>6</cell> </row> <row> <cell>A 7</cell> <cell>8</cell> <cell>9</cell> <cell>10</cell> <cell>11</cell> <cell>12</cell> </row> <row> <cell>B 13</cell> <cell>14</cell> <cell>15</cell> <cell>16</cell> <cell>17</cell> <cell>18</cell> </row> <row> <cell>C 19</cell> <cell>20</cell> <cell>21</cell> <cell>22</cell> <cell>23</cell> <cell>24</cell> </row> <row> <cell>D 25</cell> <cell>26</cell> <cell>27</cell> <cell>28</cell> <cell>29</cell> <cell>30</cell> </row> <row> <cell>5 31</cell> <cell>32</cell> <cell>33</cell> <cell>34</cell> <cell>35</cell> <cell>36</cell> </row> <row> <cell>F 37</cell> <cell>38</cell> <cell>39</cell> <cell>40</cell> <cell>41</cell> <cell>42</cell> </row> </table><p>The number expreſſed by any pair of flags is found in the interſection of the horizontal and perpendicular columns. Thus the flag D, hoiſted along with and above the flag F, expreſſes the number 40, &amp; c. In order to expreſs a greater number (but not exceeding 84) ſuppoſe 75, hoiſt the flags E, which expreſſes 33, or 75,</p><p>wanting 42, and above them a flag or ſignal G, which alone expreſſes 42.</p><p>This method may be ſtill farther improved by arranging the flags thus :</p><table> <row> <cell/> <cell><p>A</p><p>I</p></cell> <cell><p>B</p><p>2</p></cell> <cell><p>C</p><p>3</p></cell> <cell><p>D</p><p>4</p></cell> <cell><p>E</p><p>5</p></cell> <cell><p>F</p><p>6</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell>A</cell> <cell>7</cell> <cell>8</cell> <cell>9</cell> <cell>10</cell> <cell>11</cell> <cell>12</cell> </row> <row> <cell>B</cell> <cell>—</cell> <cell>13</cell> <cell>14</cell> <cell>15</cell> <cell>16</cell> <cell>17</cell> </row> <row> <cell>C</cell> <cell>—</cell> <cell>—</cell> <cell>18</cell> <cell>19</cell> <cell>20</cell> <cell>21</cell> </row> <row> <cell>D</cell> <cell>—</cell> <cell>—</cell> <cell>—</cell> <cell>22</cell> <cell>23</cell> <cell>24</cell> </row> <row> <cell>E</cell> <cell>—</cell> <cell>—</cell> <cell>—</cell> <cell>—</cell> <cell>25</cell> <cell>26</cell> </row> <row> <cell>F</cell> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> <cell>27</cell> </row> </table><p>In this laſt method the signification of the ſignal is totally independent of the poſition of the flags. In whatever parts of the ſhip the flags D and E are ſeen, they expreſs the number 23. This would suit battle ſignals.</p><p>Another method ſtill may be taken. Flags hoiſted anywhere on the foremaſt may be accounted units, thoſe on the mainmaſt tens, and thoſe on the mizenmaſt hundreds. Thus numeral ſignals may be made by a ſhip diſmaſted, or having only poles in their place.</p><p>Many other ways may be contrived for expreſſing numbers by colours, and there is great room for exerciſing the judgment of the contriver. For it muſt always be remembered, that theſe ſignals muſt be accompanied with a ſignal by which it is addreſſed to ſome particular ſhip or diviſion of the fleet, and it may be difficult to connect the one with the other, which is perhaps ſhown in another place, and along with other executive ſignals.</p><p>One great advantage of theſe numeral ſignals is, that they may be changed in their ſignification at pleaſure. Thus, in the firſt method, it can be ſettled, that on Sundays the colours A, B, C, D, &amp; c. expreſs the cyphers 1, 2, 3, 4, &amp; c. but that on Mondays they expreſs the cyphers 0, 1, 2, 3, &amp; c. and on 1 ueſdays the cyphers 9, 0, 1, 2, &amp; c. ; and ſo on through all the days of the week. This mean or secrecy is mentioned by Dr Hooke for the coaſt and alarm ſignals, where, by the by, he shews a method for conveying intelligence over land very ſimilar to what is now practised by the French with their telegraph.</p><p>It is equally eaſy to expreſs numbers by night ſignals. Thus M. de la Bourdonnais propoſes, that one diſcharge of a great gun ſhall expreſs 7, and that 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6 ſhall be expreſſed by lights. Therefore, to expreſs 24, we muſt fire three guns, and show three lights. This is the moſt perfect of all forms of night and fog ſignals. For both the manner of firing guns and of exhibiting lights may be varied to a ſufficient extent with very few guns or lights, and with great diſtinctneſs.</p><p>Thus, for guns. Let F mark the firing of a single gun at moderate intervals, and ff a double gun, that is, two diſcharged at the interval of a second. We may expreſs numbers thus :</p><table> <row> <cell>I</cell> <cell>F.</cell> </row> <row> <cell>2</cell> <cell>F, F.</cell> </row> <row> <cell>3</cell> <cell>F, F, F.</cell> </row> <row> <cell>4</cell> <cell>F, F, F, F.</cell> </row> <row> <cell>5</cell> <cell>F, ff.</cell> </row> <row> <cell>6</cell> <cell>F, F, ff.</cell> </row> <row> <cell>7</cell> <cell>F, ff, F.</cell> </row> <row> <cell>8</cell> <cell>F, ff, F, F.</cell> </row> <row> <cell>9</cell> <cell>F,∕∕, F,∕∕,</cell> </row> <row> <cell>10</cell> <cell>ff.</cell> </row> <row> <cell>100, &amp; c.</cell> <cell>ff, ff, or fff.</cell> </row> </table><p>It might be done with fewer guns if the f <hi rend="italic">f</hi> were admitted as the firſt firing. But it ſeems better to begin always with the single gun, and thus the double gun beginning a ſignal diſtinguiſhes the tens, &amp; c.</p><p>In like manner, a ſmall number of lights will admit of a great variety of very diſtinct poſitions, which may ſerve for all ſignals to ſhips not very remote from the commander in chief. For orders to be underſtood at a very great diſtance, it will be proper to appropriate the numbers which are indicated by ſignals made with rockets. Theſe can be varied in number and kind to a ſufficient extent, ſo as to be very easily diſtinguiſhed and underſtood. It is ſufficient to have ſhown how the whole, or nearly the whole, notation of ſignals may be limited to the expreſſion of numbers.</p><p>We have taken little notice of the ſignals made by private ſhips to the commander in chief. This is a very eaſy buſineſs, becauſe there is little risk of confounding them with other ſignals. Nor have we ſpoken of ſignals from the flag ſhips whoſe ultimate interpretation is number, as when ſhips are directed to change their courſe ſo many points. Thoſe alſo are easily contrived in any of the methods already deſcribed : alſo wſhen a private ſhip wiſhes to inform the commander in chief that soundings are found at ſo many fathoms. In like manner, by numbering the points of the compaſs, the admiral can direct to chace to any one of them, or may be informed of ſtrange ſhips being ſeen in any quarter, and what is their number.</p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Signals</hi> <hi rend="italic">by the Drum,</hi> made uſe of, in the exerciſe of the army, instead of the word of command, viz.</p><table> <row> <cell><hi rend="smallcaps">Signals.</hi></cell> <cell><hi rend="italic">Operations.</hi></cell> </row> <row> <cell><hi rend="italic">A short roll.</hi></cell> <cell>To caution.</cell> </row> <row> <cell><hi rend="italic">A flam,</hi></cell> <cell>To perform any diſtinct thing.</cell> </row> <row> <cell><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> To</hi> <hi rend="italic">arms,</hi></cell> <cell>To form the line or battalion.</cell> </row> <row> <cell><hi rend="italic">The march,</hi></cell> <cell>To advance, except when intended for a salute.</cell> </row> <row> <cell/> <cell/> </row> <row> <cell><hi rend="italic">The quick march,</hi></cell> <cell>To advance quick.</cell> </row> <row> <cell><hi rend="italic">The point of war,</hi></cell> <cell>To march and charge.</cell> </row> </table>
<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0482.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0476"/>
<table> <row> <cell><hi rend="italic">The retreat,</hi></cell> <cell>To retreat.</cell> </row> <row> <cell><hi rend="italic">Drum ceasing,</hi></cell> <cell>To halt.</cell> </row> <row> <cell><hi rend="italic">Two shοrt rolls,</hi></cell> <cell>To perform the flank firing.</cell> </row> <row> <cell><hi rend="italic">The dragoon march,</hi></cell> <cell>To open the battalion.</cell> </row> <row> <cell><hi rend="italic">The grenadier march,</hi></cell> <cell>To form the column.</cell> </row> <row> <cell><hi rend="italic">The troop,</hi></cell> <cell>To double divisions.</cell> </row> <row> <cell><hi rend="italic">The long roll,</hi></cell> <cell>To form the ſquare.</cell> </row> <row> <cell><hi rend="italic">The grenadier march,</hi></cell> <cell>To reduce the ſquare to the column.</cell> </row> <row> <cell><hi rend="italic">The preparative,</hi></cell> <cell>To make ready and fire.</cell> </row> <row> <cell><hi rend="italic">The general,</hi></cell> <cell>To ceaſe firing.</cell> </row> <row> <cell><hi rend="italic">Two long rolls,</hi></cell> <cell>To bring or lodge the colours.</cell> </row> </table>
</div></body></text></TEI>