<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0605.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0599-08" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SOLEURE</label>,
a canton oſ Swiſſerland, which holds the 11th rank in the Helvetic confederacy, into which it was admitted in the year 1481. It ſtretches partly through the plain, and partly along the chains of the Jura, and contains about 50,000 inhabitants. It is 35 miles in length from north to south, and 35 in breadth from eaſt to west. The soil for the moſt part is exceedingly fertile in corn ; and the diſtricts within the Jura abound in excellent paſtures. The trade both of the town and canton is of little value, although they are very commodiouſly ſituated for an extenſive commerce; It is divided into 11 bailiwicks, the inhabitants of which are all Roman Catholics except thoſe of the bailiwick of Buckegberg, who profeſs the reformed religion. The sovereign power reſides in the great council, which, compriſing the ſenate or little council of 36, conſiſts of 102 members, choſen by the ſenate in equal proportions from the 11 tribes or companies into which the ancient burghers are diſtributed ; and, owing to the diſtinction between the ancient and the new burghers (the former conſiſting of only 85 families) the government is a complete ariſtocracy.</p><p>Soleure, an ancient and extremely neat town of Swiſſerland, capital of the canton of the ſame name. It contains about 4000 inhabitants, and is pleaſantly ſeated on the Aar, which here expands into a noble river; Among the moſt remarkable objects of curioſity in this town is the new church of St Urs, which was begun in 1762 and finiſhed in 1772. It is a noble edifice of a whitiſh grey ſtone, drawn from the neighbouring quarries, which admits a poliſh, and is a ſpecies of rude marble. The lower part of the building is of the Corinthian, the upper of the Compoſite order. The facade, which conſiſts of a portico, ſurmounted by an elegant tower, preſents itſelf finely at the extremity of the principal ſtreet. It coſt at leaſt L. 80,000, a conſiderable ſum for ſuch a ſmall republic, whoſe revenue ſcarcely exceeds L. 12,000 a year. Soleure is ſurrounded by regular ſtone fortifications, and is 20 miles north north- eaſt of Bern, 27 south ſouth-weſt of Baſle, and 45 weſt of Zurich. E. Long. 7. 20. N. Lat. 47. 15.</p></div></body></text></TEI>