<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0553.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0547-04" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SMOKE</label>,
a dense elaſſic vapour, arising from burning bodies. As this vapour is extremely diſagreeable to the ſenſes, and often prejudicial to the health, man<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0554.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0548"/>
kind have fallen upon ſeveral contrivances to enjoy the benefit of fire, without being annoyed by ſmoke. The moſt univerſal of theſe contrivances is a tube leading from the chamber in which the fire is kindled to the top of the building, through which the ſmoke aſcends, and is diſperſed into the atmoſphere. Theſe tubes are called <hi rend="italic">chimneys ;</hi> which, when conſtructed in a proper manner, carry off the ſmoke entirely ; but, when improperly conſtructed, they carry off the ſmoke imperfectly, to the great annoyance of the inhabitants. As our maſons at preſent ſeem to have a very imperfect knowledge of the manner in which chimneys ought to be built, we can hardly perform a more acceptable ſervice to the public than to point out the manner in which they ought to be conſtructed, ſo as to carry off the ſmoke entirely ; as well as to explain the cauſes from which the defects ſo often complained of generally proceed, and the method of removing them.</p><p><note anchored="false" n="1" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>Transactions of the American Philosophical Society.</p></note> Thoſe who would be acquainted with this ſubject, ſhould begin by conſidering on what principle ſmoke aſcends in any chimney. At firſt many are apt to think that ſmoke is in its nature, and of itſelf, ſpecifically lighter than air, and riſes in it for the ſame reaſon that cork riſes in water. Theſe ſee no cauſe why ſmoke ſhould not riſe in the chimney though the room be ever ſo cloſe. Others think there is a power in chimneys to <hi rend="italic">draw</hi> up the ſmoke, and that there are different forms of chimneys which afford more or leſs of this power. Theſe amuſe themſelves with ſearching for the beſt form. The equal dimenſions of a funnel in its whole length is not thought artificial enough, and it is made, for fancied reaſons, ſometimes tapering and narrowing from below upwards, and ſometimes the contrary, &amp; c. &amp; c. A ſimple experiment or two may ſerve to give more correct ideas. Having lighted a pipe of tobacco, plunge the ſtem to the bottom of a decanter half filled with cold water; then putting a rag over the bowl, blow through it, and make the ſmoke deſcend in the ſtem of the pipe, from the end of which it will riſe in bubbles through the water ; and being thus cooled, will not afterwards riſe to go out through the neck of the decanter, but remain ſpreading itſelf and reſting on the ſurface of the water. This ſhows that ſmoke is really heavier than air, and that it is carried upwards only when attached to or acted upon by air that is heated, and thereby rarefied and rendered ſpecifically lighter than the air in its neighbourhood.</p><p>Smoke being rarely ſeen but in company with heated air, and its upward motion being viſible, though that of the rarefied air that drives it is not ſo, has naturally given riſe to the error. It is now well known that air is a fluid which has weight as well as others, though about 830 times lighter than water ; that heat makes the particles of air recede from each other, and take up more ſpace, ſo that the ſame weight of air heated will have more bulk than equal weights of cold air which may ſurround it, and in that caſe muſt riſe, being forced upwards by ſuch colder and heavier air, which preſſes to get under it and take its place. That air is ſo rarefied or expanded by heat, may be proved to their comprehenſion by a lank blown bladder, which laid before a fire, will ſoon ſwell, grow tight, and burſt.</p><p>Another experiment may be to take a glaſs tube about an inch in diameter, and 12 inches long, open at both ends, and fixed upright on legs ſo that it need not</p><p>be handled, for the hands might warm it. At the end of a quill fallen five or six inches of the fineſt light filament of silk, ſo that it may be held either above the upper end of the tube or under the lower end, your warm hand being at a diſtance by the length of the quill. If there were any motion of air through the tube, it would manifeſt itſelf by its effect on the silk ; but if the tube and the air in it are of the same temperature with the ſurrounding air, there will be no ſuch motion, whatever may be the form of the tube, whether crooked or ſtraight, narrow below and widening upwards, or the contrary, the air in it will be quieſcent. Warm the tube, and you will find as long as it continues warm, a constant current of air entering below and passing up through it till diſcharged at the top ; becauſe the warmth of the tube being communicated to the air it contains, rarefies that air, and makes it lighter than the air without; which therefore preſſes in below, forces it upwards, follows and takes its place, and is rarefied in its turn. And, without warming the tube, if you hold under it a knob of hot iron, the air thereby heated will riſe and fill the tube, going out at its top ; and this motion in the tube will continue as long as the knob remains hot, becauſe the air entering the tube below, is heated and rarefied by paſſing near and over that knob.</p><p>That this motion is produced merely by the difference of ſpecific gravity between the fluid within and that without the tube, and not by any fancied form of the tube itſelf, may appear by plunging it into water contained in a glaſs jar a foot deep, through which ſuch motion might be ſeen, The water within and without the tube being of the ſame ſpecific gravity, balance each other, and both remain at reſt. But take out the tube, ſtop its bottom with a finger, and fill it with olive oil, which is lighter than water ; then flopping the top, place it as before, its lower end under water, its top a very little above. As long as you keep the bottom flopped the fluids remain at reſt ; but the moment it is unſtopt, the heavier enters below, forces up the lighter, and takes its place : and the motion then ceaſes, merely becauſe the new fluid cannot be ſucceſsively made lighter, as air may be by a warm tube.</p><p>In fact, no form of the funnel of a chimney has any ſhare in its operation or effect reſpecting ſmoke except its height. The longer the funnel, if erect, the greater its force when filled with heated and rarefied air to draw in below and drive up the ſmoke, if one may, in compliance with cuſtom, uſe the expreſſion <hi rend="italic">draw,</hi> when in fact it is the ſuperior weight of the ſurrounding atmoſphere that preſſes to enter the funnel below, and ſo drives up before it the ſmoke and warm air it meets with in its paſſage.</p><p>What is it then which makes a ſmoky chimney, that is, a chimney which, inſtead of conveying up all the ſmoke, discharges a part of it into the room, offending the eyes and damaging the furniture ?</p><p>The cauſes of this effect may be reduced to <hi rend="italic">nine,</hi> differing from each other, and therefore requiring different remedies.</p><p>1. <hi rend="italic">Smoky chimneys in a new houſe are ſuch frequently from mere want of air.</hi> The workmanſhip of the rooms being all good, and juſt out of the workman’s hands, the joints of the boards of the flooring, and of the pannels of wainſcotting, are all true and tight ; the more ſo as<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0555.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0549"/>
the walls, perhaps not yet thoroughly dry, preserve a dampneſs in the air of the room which keeps the woodwork ſwelled and cloſe. The doors and the ſaſhes too, being worked with truth, ſhut with exactneſs, ſo that the room is as tight as a ſnuff-box, no paſſage being left open for air to enter except the key-hole, and even that is ſometimes covered by a little dropping ſhutter. Now if ſmoke cannot riſe but as connected with rarefied air, and a column of ſuch air, ſuppoſe it filling the funnel, cannot riſe unleſs other air be admitted to ſupply its place; and if therefore no current of air enter the opening of the chimney—there is nothing to prevent the ſmoke from coming out into the room. If the motion upwards of the air in a chimney that is freely ſupplied be obſerved by the riſing of the ſmoke or a feather in it, and it be conſidered that in the time ſuch feather takes in riſing from the fire to the top of the chimney, a column of air equal to the content of the funnel muſt be diſcharged, and an equal quantity ſupplied from the room below, it will appear abſolutely impoſſible that this operation ſhould go on if the tight room is kept ſhut ; for were there any force capable of drawing conſtantly ſo much air out of it, it muſt ſoon be exhauſted like the receiver of an air-pump, and no animal could live in it. Thoſe therefore who ſtop every crevice in a room to prevent the admiſſion of freſh air, and yet would have their chimney carry up the ſmoke, require inconſiſtencies, and expect impossibilities, Yet under this ſituation it is not uncommon to ſee the owner of a new houſe in deſpair, and ready to ſell it for much leſs than it coſt ; conceiving it. uninhabitable becauſe not a chimney in any one of its rooms will carry off the ſmoke unleſs a door or window be left open. Much expence has alſo been made to alter and amend new chimneys which had really no fault : in one houſe particularly which Dr Franklin knew that belonged to a nobleman in Weſtminſter, that expence amounted to no leſs than L. 300, after his houſe had been, as he thought, finiſhed and all charges paid. And after all, ſeveral of the alterations were ineffectual, for want of underſtanding the true principles.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Remedies.</hi> When yon find on trial that opening the door or a window enables the chimney to carry up all the ſmoke, you may be ſure that want of air from without was the cauſe of its ſmoking. “ I ſay from <hi rend="italic">without</hi> (adds Dr Franklin), to guard you againſt a common miſtake of thoſe who may tell you the room is large, contains abundance of air ſufficient to ſupply any chimney, and therefore it cannot be that the chimney wants air. Theſe reaſoners are ignorant that the largeneſs of a room, if tight, is in this case of ſmall importance, ſince it cannot part with a chimney full of its air without occaſioning ſo much vacuum ; which it requires a great force to effect, and could not be borne if effected.”</p><p>It appearing plainly then, that ſome of the outward air muſt be admitted, the queſtion will be, how much is abſolutely neceſſary ? for you would avoid admitting more, as being contrary to one of your intentions in having a fire, viz. that of warming your room. To diſcover this quantity, ſhut the door gradually while a middling fire is burning, till you find that before it is quite ſhut the ſmoke begins to come out into the room ; then open it a little till you perceive the ſmoke comes out no longer. There hold the door, and obſerve the</p><p>width of the open crevice between the edge of the door and the rabbet it ſhould ſhut into. Suppoſe the diſtance to be half an inch, and the door eight feet high; you find thence that your room requires an entrance for air equal in area to 96 half inches, or 48 ſquare inches, or a paſſage of 6 inches by 8. This, however, is a large ſuppoſition ; there being few chimneys that, having a moderate opening and a tolerable height of funnel, will not be ſatisfied with ſuch a crevice of a quarter of an inch : Dr Franklin found a ſquare of <hi rend="italic">6</hi> by 6, or 36 ſquare inches, to be a pretty good medium that will ſerve for moſt chimneys, High funnels with small and low openings may indeed be ſupplied through a leſs ſpace ; becauſe, for reasons that will appear hereafter, the force of levity, if one may ſo ſpeak, being greater in ſuch funnels, the cool air enters the room with greater velocity, and conſequently more enters in the ſame time. This, however, has its limits ; for experience ſhows, that no increaſed velocity ſo occaſioned. has made the admiſſion of air through the key-hole equal in quantity to that through an open door, though through the door the current moves ſlowly, and through the key-hole with great rapidity.</p><p>It remains then to be conſidered, how and where this neceſſary quantity of air from without is to be admitted ſo as to be leaſt inconvenient : for if at the door, left ſo much open, the air thence proceeds directly to the chimney, and in its way comes cold to your back and heels as you fit before your fire. If you keep the door ſhut, and raiſe a little the ſaſh of your window, you feel the ſame inconvenience. Various have been the contrivances to avoid this ; ſuch as bringing in freſh air through pipes in the jams of the chimney, which pointing upwards ſhould blow the ſmoke up the funnel; opening paſſages into the funnel above, to let in air for the ſame purpoſe. But theſe produce an effect contrary to that intended : for as it is the conſtant current of air paſſing from the room through the opening of the chimney into the funnel which prevents the ſmoke from coming out into the room, if you ſupply the funnel by other means or in other ways with the air which it wants, and eſpecially if that air be cold, you diminiſh the force of that current, and the ſmoke in its efforts to enter the room finds leſs reſiſtance.</p><p>The wanted air muſt then indiſpenſably be admitted into the room, to ſupply what goes off through the opening of the chimney. M. Gauger, a very ingenious and intelligent French writer on the ſubject, propoſes with judgment to admit it above the opening of the chimney ; and to prevent inconvenience from its coldneſs, he directs that it may be ſo made, that it ſhall paſs in its entrance through winding cavities made behind the iron back and ſides of the fire-place, and under the iron hearth-plate ; in which cavities it will be warmed, and even heated, ſo as to contribute much, inſtead of cooling, to the warming of the room. This invention is excellent in itſelf, and may be uſed with advantage in building new houſes ; becauſe the chimneys may then be ſo diſpoſed as to admit conveniently the cold air to enter ſuch paſſages : but in houſes built without ſuch views, the chimneys are often ſo ſituated as not to afford that convenience without great and expenſive alterations. Eaſy and cheap methods, though not quite ſo perfect in themſelves, are of more general utility ; and ſuch are the following.<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0556.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0550"/>
In all rooms where there is a fire, the body of air warmed and rarefied before the chimney is continually changing place, and making room for other air that is to be warmed in its turn. Part of it enters and goes up the chimney, and the reſt riſes and takes place near the ceiling. If the room be lofty, that warm air remains above our heads as long as it continues warm, and we are little benefited by it, becauſe it does not deſcend till it is cooler. Few can imagine the difference of climate between the upper and lower parts of ſuch a room, who have not tried it by the thermometer, or by going up a ladder till their heads are near the ceiling. It is then among this warm air that the wanted quantity of outward air is beſt admitted, with which being mixed, its coldneſs is abated, and its inconvenience diminiſhed ſo as to become ſcarce obſervable. This may be eaſily done by drawing down about an inch the upper ſaſh of a window ; or, if not moveable, by cutting ſuch a crevice through its frame ; in both which cales it will be well to place a thin ſhelf of the length to conceal the opening, and ſloping upwards, to direct the entering air horizontally along and under the ceiling. In ſome houſes the air may be admitted by ſuch a crevice made in the wainſcot, cornice, or plaſtering, near the ceiling and over the opening of the chimney. This, if practicable, is to be choſen, becauſe the entering cold air will there meet with the warmeſt rising air from before the fire, and be ſooneſt tempered by the mixture. The ſame kind of ſhelf ſhould alſo be placed here. Another way, and not a very difficult one, is to take out an upper pane of glaſs in one of your ſaſhes, ſet it in a tin frame, giving it two ſpringing angular ſides, and then replacing it, with hinges below on which it may be turned to open more or leſs above. It will then have the appearance of an internal ſky-light. By drawing this pane in, more or leſs, you may admit what air you find neceſſary. Its poſition will naturally throw that air up and along the ceiling. This is what is called in France a <hi rend="italic">Was ist das ?</hi> As this is a German queſtion, the invention is probably of that nation, and takes its name from the frequent aſking of that queſtion when it firſt appeared. In England ſome have of late years cut a round hole about five inches diameter in a pane of the ſaſh and placed againſt it a circular plate of tin hung on an axis, and cut into vanes; which, being ſeparately bent a little obliquely, are acted upon by the entering air, ſo as to force the plate continually round like the vanes of a windmill. This admits the outward air, and by the continual whirling of the vanes, does in ſome degree diſperſe it. The noiſe only is a little inconvenient.</p><p>2. A ſecond cauſe of the ſmoking of chimneys is, <hi rend="italic">their openings in the room being too large ;</hi> that is, too wide, too high, or both. Architects in general have no other ideas of proportion in the opening of a chimney than what relate to ſymmetry and beauty reſpecting the dimenſions of the room ; while its true proportion reſpecting its function and utility depends on quite other principles ; and they might as properly proportion the ſtep in a ſtaircaſe to the height of the ſtory, inſtead of the natural elevation of mens legs in mounting. The proportion then to be regarded, is what relates to the height of the funnel. For as the tunnels in the different ſtories of a houſe are neceſſarily of different heights or lengths, that from the loweſt floor be</p><p>ing the higheſt or longeſt, and thoſe of the other floors ſhorter and ſhorter, till we we come to thoſe in the garrets, which are of courſe the ſhorteſt ; and the force of draft being, as already ſaid, in proportion to the height of funnel filled with rarefied air, and a current of air from the room into the chimney, sufficient to fill the opening, being necessary to oppose and prevent the smoke from coming out into the room ; it follows, that the openings of the longeſt funnels may be larger, and that thoſe of the ſhorter funnels ſhould be ſmaller. For if there be a large opening to a chimney that does not drawſtrongly, the funnel may happen to be furniſhed with the air which it demands by a partial current entering on one fide of the opening, and leaving the other side free of any oppoſing current, may permit the ſmoke to iſſue there into the room. Much too of the force of draft in a funnel depends on the degree of rarefaction in the air it contains, and that depends on the nearneſis to the fire of its paſſage in entering the funnel. If it can enter far ſrom the fire on each side, or far above the fire, in a wide or high opening, it receives little heat in paſſing by the fire, and the contents of the funnel are by those means leſs different in levity from the ſurrounding atmosphere, and its force in drawing conſequently weaker. Hence if too large an opening be given to chimneys in upper rooms, thoſe rooms will be ſmoky : On the other hand, if too ſmall openings be given to chimneys in the lower rooms, the entering air operating too directly and violently on the fire, and afterwards ſtrengthening the draft as it aſcenda the funnel, will conſume the fuel too rapidly.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Remedy. A</hi> s different circumſtances frequently mix themſelves in theſe matters, it is difficult to give preciſe dimenſions for the openings of all chimneys. Our fathers made them generally much too large : we have lessened them ; but they are often ſtill of greater dimenſions than they ſhould be, the human eye not being eaſily reconciled to ſudden and great changes. If you ſuſpect that your chimney smokes ſrom the too great dimenſion of its opening, contract it by placing moveable boards ſo as to lower and narrow it gradually till you find the ſmoke no longer isſues into the room. The proportion ſo found will be that which is proper for that chimney, and you may employ the bricklayer or maſon to reduce it accordingly. However, as in building new houſes ſomething muſt be ſometimes hazarded, Dr Franklin propoſes to make the openings in the lower rooms about 30 inches ſquare and 18 deep, and thoſe in the upper only 18 inches ſquare and not quite ſo deep ; the intermediate ones diminiſhing in pro· portion as the height of the funnel is diminiſhed. In the larger openings, billets of two feet long, or half the common length of cordwood, may be burnt conveniently ; and for the ſmaller, ſuch wood may be ſawed into thirds. Where coals are the fuel, the grates will be proportioned to the openings. The ſame depth is nearly neceſſary to all, the funnels being all made of a ſize proper to admit a chimney-ſweeper. If in large and elegant rooms cuſtom or fancy ſhould require the appearance of a larger chimney, it may be formed of expensive marginal decorations, in marble, &amp; c. But in time perhaps, that which is fitteſt in the nature of things may come to be thought handſomeſt.</p><p>3. Another cauſe of ſmoky chimneys is <hi rend="italic">too ſhort a funnel.</hi> This happens neceſſarily in ſome caſes, as where<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0557.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0551"/>
a chimney is required in a low building ; for, it the funnel be raiſed high above the roof, in order to ſtrengthen its draft, it is then in danger of being blown down, and cruſhing the roof in its fall.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Remedies.</hi> Contract the opening of the chimney, ſo as to oblige all the entering air to paſs through or very near the fire ; whereby it will be more heated and rarefied, the funnel itſelf be more warmed, and its contents have more oſ what may be called the force of levity, ſo as to rise ſtrongly and maintain a good draft at the opening.</p><p>Or you may in ſome caſes, to advantage, build additional ſtories over the low building, which will ſupport a high funnel.</p><p>If the low building be uſed as a kitchen, and a contraction of the opening therefore inconvenient, a large one being necessary, at leaſt when there are great dinners, for the free management of ſo many cooking utenſils ; in ſuch caſe the beſt expedient perhaps would be to build two more funnels joining to the firſt, and having three moderate openings, one to each funnel, instead of one large one. When there is occasion to uſe but one, the other two may be kept ſhut by sliding plates, hereafter to be deſcribed ; and two or all of them may be uſed together when wanted. This will indeed be an expence, but not an uſeleſs one, ſince your cooks will work with more comfort, ſee better than in a ſmoky kitchen what they are about, your victuals will be cleaner dreſſed and not taſte of ſmoke, as is often the caſe ; and to render the effect more certain, a stack of three funnels may be ſafely built higher above the roof than a ſingle funnel.</p><p>The caſe of too ſhort a funnel is more general than would be imagined, and often found where one would not expect it. For it is not uncommon, in ill-contrived buildings, inſtead of having a funnel for each room or fire-place, to bend and turn the funnel of an upper room ſo as to make it enter the ſide of another funnel that comes from below. By theſe means the upper room funnel is made ſhort of courſe, ſince its length can only be reckoned from the place where it enters the lower room funnel ; and that funnel is alſo ſhortened by all the diſtance between the entrance of the ſecond funnel and the top oſ the ſtack : for all that part being readily supplied with air through the ſecond funnel, adds no ſtrength to the draft, eſpecially as that air is cold when there is no fire in the ſecond chimney. The only eaſy remedy here is, to keep the opening of that funnel ſhut in which there is no fire.</p><p>4. Another very common cauſe oſ the ſmoking of chimneys is, <hi rend="italic">their overpowering one another.</hi> For inſtance, if there be two chimneys in one large room, and you make fires in both of them, the doors and windows cloſe ſhut, you will find that the greater and ſtronger fire ſhall overpower the weaker, from the funnel of which it will draw air down to ſupply its own demand; which air deſcending in the weaker funnel, will drive down its ſmoke, and force it into the room. If, inſtead of being in one room, the two chimneys are in two different rooms, communicating by a door, the caſe is the ſame whenever that door is open. In a very tight houſe, a kitchen chimney on the loweſt floor, when it had a great fire in it, has been known to overpower any other chimney in the houſe, and draw air and ſmoke</p><p>into its room as often as the door communicating with the ſtaircaſe was opened.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Remedy.</hi> Take care that every room have the means of ſupplying itſelf from without with the air which its chimney may require, ſo that no one of them may be obliged to borrow from another, nor under the neceſſity of lending. A variety of theſe means have been already deſcribed.</p><p>5. Another cauſe of ſmoking is, <hi rend="italic">when the tops of chimneys are commanded by higher buildings, or by a hill,</hi> ſo that the wind blowing over ſuch eminences falls like water over a dam, sometimes almoſt perpendicularly on the tops of the chimneys that lie in its way, and heats down the ſmoke contained in them.</p><p>To illuſtrate this, let A (fig. 3.) repreſent a ſmall building at the ſide of a great rock B, and the wind coming in the direction CD ; when the current of air comes to the point D, being hurried forward with great velocity, it gtes a little forward, but ſoon deſcends downward, and gradually is reflected more and more inward, as repreſented by the dotted lines EE, &amp; c. ſo that, descending downwards upon the top oſ the chimney A, the ſmoke is beat back again into the apartments.</p><p>It is evident that houſes ſituated near high hills or thick woods will be in ſome meaſure expoſed to the same inconvenience; but it is likewiſe plain, that if a houſe be ſituated upon the slope of a lull (as at F, fig. 3.), it will not be in any danger oſ ſmoke when the wind blows towards that ſide of the hill upon which it is ſituated; for the current of air coming over the houſe-top in the direction GH, is immediately changed by the ſlope of the hill to the direction HC, which powerfully draws the ſmoke upward from the top of the chimney. But it is alſo evident, that a houſe in this ſituation will be liable to ſmoke when the wind blows from the hill ; for the current of air coming downward in the direction CH, will beat downward on the chimney F, and prevent the ſmoke from aſcending with freedom. The effect will be much heightened if the doors and windows are chiefly in the lower- moſt ſide of the houſe.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Remedy.</hi> That commonly applied to this caſe is a turncap made of tin or plate iron, covering the chimney above and on three ſides, open on one ſide, turning on a ſpindle ; and which being guided or governed by a vane always presents its back to the current. This may be generally effectual, though not certain, as there may be caſes in which it will not ſucceed. Raising your funnels if practicable, ſo as their tops may be higher, or at leaſt equal, with the commanding eminence, is more to be depended on. But the turning cap, being eaſier and cheaper, ſhould firſt be tried. “ If obliged to build in ſuch a ſituation, I would chooſe (ſays Dr Franklin) to place my doors on the ſide next the hill, and the backs of my chimneys on the fartheſt side ; for then the column of air falling over the eminence, and of courſe preſſing on that below, and forcing it to enter the doors or <hi rend="italic">was-ift-dases,</hi> on that ſide, would tend to balance the preſſure down the chimneys, and leave the funnels more free in the exerciſe of their functions.”</p><p>6. There is another caſe which is the reverſe of that laſt mentioned. It is where the commanding eminence<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0558.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0552"/>
is farther from the wind than the chimney commanded. To explain this a figure may be neceſſary. Suppoſe then a building whoſe side AB happens to be expoſed to the wind, and forms a kind of dam againſt its progreſs. Suppoſe the wind blowing in the direction FE. The air obſtructed by this dam or building AB will like water preſs and ſearch for paſſages through it; but finding none, it is beat back with violence, and ſpreads itſelf on every ſide, as is repreſented by the curved lines e, <hi rend="italic">e, e, e, e, e.</hi> It will therefore force itſelf down the ſmall chimney C, in order to get through by ſome door or window open on the other ſide of the building. And if there be a fire in ſuch chimney, its ſmoke is oſ courſe beat down, and fills the room.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Remedy.</hi> There is but one remedy, which is to raiſe ſuch a funnel higher than the roof, ſupporting it if neceſſary by iron bars. For a turncap in this caſe has no effect, the dammed up air preſſing down through it in whatever poſition the wind may have placed its opening.</p><p>Dr Franklin mentions a city in which many houſes are rendered ſmoky by this operation. For their kitchens being built behind, and connected by a paſſage with the houſes, and the tops of the kitchen-chimneys lower than the tops of the houſes, the whole ſide of a street when the wind blows againſt its back forms ſuch a dam as above deſcribed ; and the wind ſo obſtructed forces down thoſe kitchen-chimneys (eſpecially when they have but weak ſires in them) to paſs through the paſſage and houſe into the ſtreet. Kitchen chimneys ſo formed and ſituated have another inconvenience. In ſummer, if you open your upper room windows for air, a light breeze blowing over your kitchen chimney towards the houſe, though not ſtrong enough to force down its ſmoke as aforeſaid, is ſuſſicient to waft it into your windows, and fill the rooms with it ; which, beſides the diſagreeableneſs, damages your furniture.</p><p>7. Chimneys, otherwiſe drawing well, are ſometimes made to ſmoke by <hi rend="italic">the improper and inconvenient ſituation of a door.</hi> When the door and chimney are on the ſame side of the room, if the door being in the corner is made to open againſt the wall, which is common, as being there, when open, more out of the way, it follows, that when the door is only opened in part, a current of air ruſhing in paſſes along the wall into and acroſs the opening of the chimney, and flirts ſome of the ſmoke out into the room. This happens more certainly when the door is ſhutting, for then the force oſ the current is augmented, and becomes very inconvenient to thoſe who, warming themſelves by the tire, happen to fit in its way.</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">remedies</hi> are obvious and eaſy. Either put an intervening ſcreen from the wall round great part of the fireplace ; or, which is perhaps preferable, ſhift the hinges of your door, ſo as it may open the other way, and when open throw the air along the other wall.</p><p>8. A room that has no fire in its chimney is ſometimes filled with <hi rend="italic">ſmoke which is received at the top of its funnel, and deſcends into the room.</hi> Funnels without fires have an effect according to their degree of coldneſs or warmth on the air that happens to be contained in them. The ſurrounding atmoſphere is frequently changing its temperature ; but ſtacks of funnels covered from winds and fun by the houſe. that contains them, retain a more equal temperature. If, after a warm ſeaſon, the out</p><p>ward air ſuddenly grows cold, the empty warm funnels begin to draw ſtrongly upward; that is, they rarefy the air contained in them, which of courſe riſes, cooler air enters below to ſupply its place, is rarefied in its turn, and riſes ; and this operation continues till the funnel grows cooler, or the outward air warmer, or both, when the motion ceases∙. On the other hand, if after a cold ſeaſon the outward air ſuddenly grows warm and of courſe lighter, the air contained in the cool funnels being heavier deſcends into the room ; and the warmer air which enters their tops being cooled in its turn, and made heavier, continues to deſcend ; and this operation goes on till the funnels are warmed by the paſſing of warm air thro’ them, or the air itſelf grows cooler. When the temperature of the air and of the funnels is nearly equal, the difference of warmth in the air between day and night is sufficient to produce theſe currents : the air will begin to aſcend the funnels as the cool of the evening comes on, and this current will continue till perhaps nine or ten o’clock the next morning, when it begins to helitate ; and as the heat of the day approaches, it ſets downwards, and continues ſo till towards evening, when it again heſitates for ſome time, and then goes upwards conſtantly during the night, as before mentioned. Now when ſmoke iſſuing from the tops of neighbouring funnels paſſes over the tops of funnels which are at the time drawing downwards, as they often are in the middle part of the day, ſuch ſmoke is of neceſſity drawn into theſe funnels, and deſcends with the air into the chamber.</p><p>The remedy is to have a sliding plate that will ſhut perfectly the offending funnal. Dr Franklin has thus deſcribed it : “ The opening of the chimney is contracted by brick-work faced with marble ſlabs to about two feet between the jams, and the breaſt brought down to within about three feet of the hearth. An iron frame is placed juſt under the breaſt, and extending quite to the back of the chimney, so that a plate of the ſarne metal may ſlide horizontally backwards and forwards in the grooves on each ſide of the frame. This plate is juſt ſo large as to fill the whole ſpace, and ſhut the chimney entirely when thruſt quite in, which is convenient when there is no fire. Draw it out, ſo as to leave between its further edge and the back a ſpace of about two inches ; this ſpace is sufficient for the ſmoke to paſs ; and ſo large a part of the funnel being ſtopt by the rest of the plate, the paſſage of warm air out of the room, up the chimney, is obſtructed and retarded ; and by thoſe means much cold air is prevented from coming in through crevices, to ſupply its place. This effect is made maniſeſt three ways. 1. When the ſire burns briſkly in cold weather, the howling or whiſtling noiſe made by the wind, as it enters the room through the crevices, when the chimney is open as uſual, ceaſes as ſoon as the plate is slid in to its proper diſtance. 2. Opening the door of the room about half an inch, and holding your hand againſt the opening, near the top of the door, you feel the cold air coming in againſt your hand, but weakly, if the plate be in. Let another perſon ſuddenly draw it out, ſo as to let the air oſ the room go up the chimney, with its uſual freedom where chimneys are open, and you immediately feel the cold air ruſhing in ſtrongly. 3. If something be ſet againſt the door, juſt sufficient, when the plate is in, to keep the door nearly ſhut, by reſiſting the preſſure of the<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0559.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0553"/>
air that would force it open : then, when the plate is drawn out, the door will be forced open by the in- creaſed pressure of the outward cold air endeavouring to get in to ſupply the place oſ the warm air that now passes out of the room to go up the chimney. In our common open chimneys, half the fuel is wasted, and its effect loſt ; the air it has warmed being immediately drawn off.”</p><p>9. Chimneys which generally draw well, do nevertheleſs ſometimes give ſmoke into the rooms, <hi rend="italic">it being driven down by strong winds paſſing over the tops oſ their funnels,</hi> though not deſcending from any commanding eminence. This caſe is moſt frequent where the funnel is ſhort and the opening turned from the wind. It is the more grievous, when it happens to be a cold wind that produces the effect, becauſe when you moſt want your fire you are ſometimes obliged to extinguiſh it. To underhand this, it may be conſidered that the riſing light air, to obtain a free issue from the funnel, muſt puſh out of its way or oblige the air that is over it to riſe. In a time of calm or of little wind this is done viſibly ; for we ſee the smoke that is brought up by that air riſe in a column above the chimney : but when a violent current of air, that is, a ſtrong wind, passes over the top of a chimney, its particles have received ſo much force, which keeps them in a horizontal direction and follow each other ſo rapidly, that the riſing light air has not ſtrength sufficient to oblige them to quit that direction and move upwards to permit its issue.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Remedies.</hi> In Venice, the cuſtom is to open or widen the top of the flue rounding it in the true form of a funnel. In other places the contrary is practiſed ; the tops of the flues being narrowed inwards, ſo as to form a slit for the issue of the ſmoke, long as the breadth of the funnel, and only four inches wide. This ſeems to have been contrived on a ſuppoſition that the entry of the wind would thereby be obſtructed, and perhaps it might have been imagined, that the whole force of the riſing warm air being condenſed, as it were, in the narrow opening, would thereby be ſtrengthened, ſo as to overcome the reſiſtance of the wind. This, however, did not always ſucceed ; for when the wind was at north-east and blew freſh, the ſmoke was forced down by fits into the room where Dr Franklin commonly ſat, ſo as to oblige him to ſhift the ſire into another. The poſition of the flit of this funnel was indeed north-eaſt and ſouth-weſt. Perhaps if it had lain acroſs the wind, the effect might have been different. But on this we can give no certainty. It ſeems a matter proper to be referred to experiment. Poſſibly a turncap might have been ſerviceable, but it was not tried.</p><p>With all the ſcience, however, that a man ſhall ſuppoſe himſelf possesſed of in this article, he may ſometimes meet with caſes that ſhall puzzle him. “ I once lodged (ſays Dr Franklin) in a houſe at London, which in a little room had a ſingle chimney and funnel. The opening was very ſmall, yet it did not keep in the ſmoke, and all attempts to have a fire in this room were fruitleſs. I could not imagine the reaſon, till at length obſerving that the chamber over it, which had no fireplace in it, was always filled with ſmoke when a fire was kindled below, and that the ſmoke came through the cracks and crevices of the wainſcot ; I had the wainſcot taken down, and diſcovered that the funnel which went up behind it had a crack many ſeet in length, and wide</p><p>enough to admit my arm ; a breach very dangerous with regard to fire, and occasioned probably by an apparent irregular settling of one side of the houſe. The air entering this breech freely, deſtroyed the drawing force of the funnel. The remedy would have been, filling up the breach, or rather rebuilding the funnel : but the landlord rather choſe to flop up the chimney.</p><p>“ Another puzzling case I met with at a friend’s country houſe near London. His beſt room had a chimney in which, he told me, he never could have a fire, for all the ſmoke came out into the room. I flattered myſelf I could easily find the cauſe and preſcribe the cure. I had a fire made there, and found it as he ſaid. I opened the door, and perceived it was not want of air. I made a temporary contraction of the opening of the chimney, and found that it was not its being too large that cauſed the ſmoke to issue. I went out and looked up at the top of the chimney : Its funnel was joined in the ſame stack with others ; ſome of them ſhorter, that drew very well, and I ſaw nothing to prevent its doing the ſame. In fine, after every other examination I could think of, I was obliged to own the inſufficiency of my ſkill. But my friend, who made no pretension to ſuch kind of knowledge, afterwards diſcovered the cauſe himſelf. He got to the top of the funnel by a ladder, and looking down found it filled with twigs and ſtraw cemented by earth and lined with feathers. It ſeems the houſe, after being built, had flood empty ſome years before he occupied it ; and he concluded that ſome large birds had taken the advantage of its retired situation to make their neſt there. The rubbiſh, conſiderable in quantity, being removed, and the funnel cleared, the chimney drew well, and gave ſatisfaction.”</p><p>Chimneys whoſe funnels go up in the north wall of a houſe, and are expoſed to the north winds, are not ſo apt to draw well as thoſe in a ſouth wall; becauſe when rendered cold by thoſe winds, they draw downwards.</p><p>Chimneys incloſed in the body of a houſe are better than thoſe whoſe funnels are expoſed in cold walls.</p><p>Chimneys in ſtacks are apt to draw better than ſeparate funnels, becauſe the funnels that have conſtant fires in them warm the others in ſome degree that have none.</p><p><hi rend="italic">SMOKE-Jack.</hi> This ingenious machine is of German extraction ; and Meſſinger, in his <hi rend="italic">Collection oſ Mechanical Performances,</hi> ſays it is very ancient, being repreſented in a painting at Nurenbergh, which is known to be older than the year 1350.</p><p>Its conſtruction is abundantly simple.<note anchored="false" n="2" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>Plate CCCCLXXI.</p></note> An upright iron ſpindle GA (fig, 5.), placed in the narrow part of the kitchen chimney, turns round on two pivots H and I. The upper one H passes through an iron bar, which is built in acroſs the chimney ; and the lower pivot I is of tempered ſteel, and is conical or pointed, reſting in a conical bell-metal ſocket fixed on another croſs bar. On the upper end of the ſpindle is a circular fly G, consiſting of 4, 6, 8, or more thin iron plates, ſet obliquely on the ſpindle like the ſails of a windmill, as we ſhall deſcribe more particularly by and by. Near the lower end of the ſpindle is a pinion A, wſhich works in the teeth of a contrate or face wheel B, turning on a horizontal axis BC. One pivot of this axis turns in a cock fixed on the croſs bar, which ſupports the lower end of the upright ſpindle HI, and the other pivot<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0560.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0554"/>
turns in a cock fixed on the side wall oſ the chimney ; ſo that this axle is parallel to the front of the chimney. On the remote end of this horizontal axle there is a ſmall pulley C, having a deep angular groove. Over this pulley there paſſes a chain CDE, in the lower bight oſ which hangs the large pulley E oſ the ſpit. This end of the ſpit turns looſely between the branches of the fork of the rack or raxe F, but without reſting on it. This is on the top of a moveable ſtand, which can be ſhifted nearer to or farther from the fire. The other end turns in one of the notches of another rack. The number of teeth in the pinion A and wheel B, and the diameters of the pulleys C and E, are ſo proportioned that the fly G makes from 12 to 20 turns for one turn of the ſpit.</p><p>The manner of operation of this uſeful machine is eaſily underſtood. The air which contributes to the burning of the fuel, and paſſes through the midſt of it, is greatly heated, and expanding prodigiouſly in bulk, becomes lighter than the neighbouring air, and is therefore puſhed by it up the chimney. In like manner, all the air which comes near the fire is heated, expanded, becomes lighter, and is driven up the chimney. This is called the <hi rend="italic">draught</hi> or <hi rend="italic">ſuction,</hi> but would with greater propriety be termed the <hi rend="italic">drift</hi> of the chimney. As the chimney gradually contracts in its dimenſions, and as the ſame quantity of heated air paſſes through every ſection of it, it is plain that the rapidity of its aſcent muſt be greateſt in the narroweſt place. There the ſty G ſhould be placed, becauſe it will there be expoſed to the ſtrongeſt current. This air, ſtriking the fly vanes obliquely, puſhes them aſide, and thus turns them round with a conſiderable force. If the joint of meat is exactly balanced on the ſpit, it is plain that the only resistance to the motion of the fly is what ariſes from the friction of the pivots of the upright ſpindle, the friction of the pimion and wheel, the friction of the pivots of the horizontal axis, the friction of the ſmall end of the spit, and the friction of the chain in the two pulleys. The whole of this is but a mere trifle. But there is frequently a conſiderable inequality in the weight of the meat on different ſides of the ſpit : there muſt therefore be a sufficient overplus of force in the impulſe of the aſcending air on the vanes of the fly, to overcome this want of equilibrium occaſioned by the unskilfulneſs or negligence of the cook. There is, however, commonly enough of power when the machine is properly conſtructed. The utility of this machine will, we hope, procure us the indulgence of ſome of our readers, while we point out the circumſtances on which its performance depends, and the maxims which ſhould he followed in its conſtruction.</p><p>The upward current of air is the moving power, and ſhould be increaſed as much as poſſible, and applied in the moſt advantageous manner. Every thing will increaſe the current which improves the draught of the chimney, and ſecures it from ſmoking. A ſmoky chimney muſt always have a weak current. For this particular, therefore, we refer to what has been delivered in the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Pneumatics,</hi> n⁰ 359 ; and in the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Smoke.</hi></p><p>With reſpect to the manner of applying this force, it is evident that the beſt conſtruction of a windmill ſails will be nearly the beſt conſtruction for the fly. According to the uſual theory of the impulſe of fluids,</p><p>the greateſt effective impulſe (that is, in the direction of the fly’s motion) will be produced if the plane of the vane be inclined to the axis in an angle of 54 degrees 46 minutes. But, ſince we have pronounced this theory to be ſo very defective, we had better take a determination founded on the experiments on the impulſe of fluids made by the academy of Paris. Theſe authoriſe us to ſay, that 49 ½ or 50 degrees will be the beſt angle to give the vane : but this muſt be underſtood only of that part oſ it which is cloſe adjoining to the axis. The vane itſelf muſt be twiſted, or <hi rend="italic">weathered</hi> as the millwrights term it, and muſt be much more oblique at its outer extremity. The exact poſition cannot be determined with any precision ; becauſe this depends on the proportion oſ the velocity of the vane to that of the current of heated air. This is ſubject to no rule, being changed according to the load on the jack. We imagine that an obliquity of 65 degrees for the outer ends of the vanes will be a good poſition for the generality of caſes. Meſſinger deſcribes an ingenious contrivance for changing this angle at pleaſure, in order to vary the velocity of the motion. Each vane is made to turn round a midrib, which ſtands out like a radius from the ſpindle, and the vane is moved by a ſtiff wire attached to one of the corners adjoining to the axle. Theſe wires are attached to a ring which slides on the ſpindle like the ſpreader of an umbrella ; and it is flopped on any part of the ſpindle by a pin thruſt through a hole in the ſpindle and ring. We mention this briefly, it being eaſily underſtood by any mechanic, and but of little conſequence, becauſe the machine is not ſuſceptible of much precision.</p><p>It is eaſy to ſee that an increaſe of the ſurface of the vanes will increaſe the power : therefore they ſhould occupy the whole ſpace of the circle, and not conſiſt of four narrow arms like the ſails of a windmill. It is better to make many narrow vanes than a few broad ones; as will appear plain to one well acquainted with the mode of impulſe of fluids acting obliquely. We recommend 8 or 12 at leaſt ; and each vane ſhould be ſo broad, that when the whole is held perpendicular between the eye and the light, no light ſhall come through the fly, the vanes overlapping each other <hi rend="italic">a very ſmall matter.</hi> We alſo recommend the making them of ſtiff plate. Their weight contributes to the ſteady motion, and enables the fly, which has acquired a conſiderable velocity during a favourable poſition of things, to retain a momentum sufficient to pull round the ſpit while the heavy side of the meat is riſing from its loweſt poſition. In ſuch a ſituation a light fly ſoon loses its momentum, and the jack flaggers under its load.</p><p>It is plain, from what has been ſaid, that the fly ſhould occupy the whole of that ſection of the vent where it is placed. The vent muſt therefore be brought to a round form in that place, that none of the current may paſs uſeleſsly by it.</p><p>It is an important queſtion where the fly ſhould be placed. If in a wide part of the vent, it will have a great ſurface, and act by a long lever ; but the current in that place is slow, and its impulſe weak. This is a fit ſubject of calculation. Suppoſe that we have it in our choice to place it either as it is drawn in the figure, or farther up at <hi rend="italic">g,</hi> where its diameter muſt be one half of what it is at G. Since the ſame quantity of heated air paſſes through both ſections, and the ſection <hi rend="italic">g</hi> has only one-<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0561.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0555"/>
fourth of the area of the ſection G, it is plain that the ait muſt be moving four times faſter, and that its impulſe is 16 times greater. But the ſurface on which it is acting is the fourth part of that of the fly G ; the actual impulſe therefore is only four times greater, ſuppoſing both flies to be moving with the same relative velocity in reſpect of the current ; that is, the rim of each moving with the same portion of the velocity of the current. This will be the caſe when the ſmall fly turns eight times as often in a minute as the large fly ; for the air is moving four times as quick at <hi rend="italic">g,</hi> and the diameter of <hi rend="italic">g</hi> is one-half of that of G. Therefore, when the ſmall fly is turning eight times as quick as the great one, there is a quadruple impulſe acting at half the diſtance from the axis. The momentum or energy therefore of the current is double. Therefore, ſuppoſing the pinion, wheel, and pulleys of both jacks to be the ſame, the jack with the ſmall fly, placed in the narrow part of the vent, will be 16 times more powerful.</p><p>By this example, more eaſily underſtood than a general proceſs, it appears that it is of particular importance to place the fly in an elevated part of the vent, where the area may be much contracted. In order ſtill farther to increaſe the power of the machine, it would be very proper to lengthen the ſpindle ſtill more, and to put another fly on it at a conſiderable diſtance above the firſt, and a third above this, &amp; c.</p><p>As the velocity of the current changes by every change of the fire, the motion of this jack muſt be very unſteady. To render it as adjuſtable as may be to the particular purpoſe of the cook, the pulley E has ſeveral grooves of different diameters, and the ſpit turns more or leſs ſlowly, by the ſame motion of the fly, according as it hangs in the chain by a larger or ſmaller pulley or groove.</p><p>Such is the conſtruction of the ſmoke jack in its moſt ſimple form. Some are more artificial and complicated, having, in place of the pulleys and connecting chain, a ſpindle coming down from the horizontal axis BC. On the upper end of this ſpindle is a horizontal contrate wheel, driven by a pinion in place of the pulley C. On the lower end is a pinion, driving a contrate wheel in place of the pulley E. This conſtruction is repreſented in fig. 6. Others are conſtructed more simply, in the manner repreſented in fig. 7. But our firſt construction has great advantage in point of ſimplicity, and allows a more easy adjustment of the ſpit, which may be brought nearer to the fire or removed farther from it without any trouble ; whereas, in the others, with a train of wheels and pinions, this cannot be done without ſeveral changes of pins and ſcrews. The only imperfection of the pulley is, that by long uſe the grooves become ſlippery, and an ill balanced joint is apt to hold back the ſpit, while the chain ſſides in the grooves. This may be completely prevented by making the grooves flat inſtead of angular (which greatly diminiſhes the friction), and furniſhing them with ſhort studs or pins which take into every third or fourth link of the chain. If the chain be made of the ſimpleſt form, with flat links, and each link be made of an exact length (making them all on a mould), the motion will be as eaſy as with any wheelwork, and without the leaſt chance of flipping.</p><p>It is always of importance to avoid this flipping of the chain by balancing the loaded ſpit. For this purpoſe it will be extremely convenient to have what is called a <hi rend="italic">balance-ſkewer.</hi> Let a part of the ſpit, immediately adjoining to the pulley, be made round, and let an arm be made to turn on it ſtiffly, ſo that it may be made faſt in any poſition by a ſcrew. Let a leaden ball be made to slide along this arm, with a ſcrew to faſten it at any diſtance from the ſpit. When the meat is spitted, lay it on the racks, and the heavieſt ſide will immediately place itſelf undermoſt. Now turn round the balance-ſkewer, ſo that it may point ſtraight upwards, and make it faſt in that poſition by the ſcrew. Put the leaden ball on it, and slide it inwards or outwards till it exactly balances the heavy ſide, which will appear by the ſpit’s remaining in any poſition in which it is put.</p><p>The greateſt difficulty is to keep the machine in repair. The moſt conſequential part of it, the firſt mover, the fly, and the pinion and wheel, by which its motion is tranſmitted to the reſt of the machine, are ſituated in a place of difficult acceſs, and where they are expoſed to violent heat and to the ſmoke and foot. The whole weight of the fly, reſting on the lower pivot I, muſt exert a great preſſure there, and occaſion great friction, even when this pinion is reduced to the ſmalleſt ſize that is compatible with the neceſſary ſtrength. The pivot muſt be of hardened ſteel, tapered like an obtrite cone, and muſt turn in a conical ſocket, alſo of hardened ſteel or of bell-metal ; and this feat of pressure and friction muſt be continually ſupplied with oil, which it conſumes very quickly. It is not ſufficient that it be from time to time ſmeared with an oiled feather ; there muſt be an iron cup formed round the ſocket, and kept filled with oil. It is ſurpriſing how quickly it diſappears : it ſoon becomes clammy by evaporation, and by the ſoot which gathers about it. The continued rubbing of the pivot and ſocket wears them both very faſt ; and this is increaſed by hard powders, ſuch as ſandy duſt, that are hurried up by the rapid current every time that the cook ſtirs the fire. Theſe, getting between the rubbing parts, cauſe them to grind and wear each other prodigiouſly. It is a great improvement to invert theſe rubbing parts. Let the lower end of the ſpindle be of a conſiderable thickneſs, and have a conical hollow nicely drilled in its extremity. Let a blunt pointed conical pin riſe up in the middle of the oil-cup, on which the conical hollow of the ſpindle may reſt. Here will be the ſame ſteady ſupport, and the ſame friction as in the other way ; but no grinding duſt can now lodge between the pivot and its ſocket : and if this upright pin be ſcrewed up through the bottom of the cup, it may be ſcrewed farther up in proportion as it wears ; and thus the upper pivot <hi rend="italic">g</hi> will never deſert its hole, a thing which ſoon happens in the common way. We can ſay from experience, that a jack conſtructed in this way will not require the fifth part of the repairs of one done in the other way.</p><p>It is of importance that the whole be ſo put together as to be eaſily taken down, in order to ſweep the vent, or to be repaired, &amp; c. For this purpoſe, let the croſs bar which carries the lower end of the upright ſpindle be placed a little on one ſide of the perpendicular line from the upper pivot hole. Let the cock which<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0562.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0556"/>
cannes the oil-cup and the pivot of the horizontal axis BC be ſcrewed to one ſide of this croſs bar, ſo that the centre of the cup may be exactly under the upper pivot hole. By this conſtruction we have only to unſcrew this cock, and then both axles come out of their places at once, and may be replaced without any trouble. We have ſketched in fig. 8. the manner in which this may be done, where M repreſents a ſection of the lower croſs bar. BCDE is the cock, fixed to the bar by the pins which go through both with finger nuts, a and <hi rend="italic">b</hi> on the oppoſite ſide. F i is the hard steel pin with the conical top <hi rend="italic">i,</hi> on which the lower end I of the upright ſpindle AG refis, in the manner recommended as the best and the moſt durable. The pivot of the horizontal axis turns in a hole at E the top of the cock.</p><p>After all, we muſt acknowledge that the ſmoke jack is inferior to the common jack that is moved by a weight. It is more expensive at firſt, and requires more frequent repairs ; its motion is not ſo much under command ; it occaſions foot to be thrown about the fire, to the great annoyance of the cook ; and it is a great encumbrance when we would clean the vent.</p><p><hi rend="italic">SMOKE-Farthings.</hi> The pentecoſtals or cuſtomary oblations offered by the diſperſed inhabitants within a dioceſe when they made their proceſſion to the mother or cathedral church, came by degrees into a ſtanding annual rent called <hi rend="italic">ſmoke-farthings.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">SMOKE-Silver.</hi> Lands were holden in ſome places by the payment oſ the ſum of 6 d. yearly to the ſheriff, called <hi rend="italic">ſmoke-ſilver</hi> (Par. 4. Edw. VI.) Smoke-ſilver and ſmoke-penny are to be paid to the miniſters of divers pariſhes as a <hi rend="italic">modus</hi> in lieu of tithe-wood : and in ſome manors formerly belonging to religious houſes, there is ſtill paid, as appendant to the laid manors, the ancient Peter-pence, by the name of <hi rend="italic">ſmoke-money (Twisd. Hist. Vindicat. 77.)—</hi> The bishop of London <hi rend="italic">anno</hi> 1444 issued out his commiſſion, Ad <hi rend="italic">levandum le</hi> ſmoke-far- things, &amp; c.</p></div></body></text></TEI>