<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0616.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0610-03" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SORREL</label>,
in botany, a ſpecies of the <hi rend="smallcaps">rumex,</hi> which grows in paſtures and meadows, and is well known. The natives of Lapland boil large quantities of the leaves in water, and mix the juice when cold with the milk of their reindeers which they eſteem an agreeable and wholeſome food. The Dutch are ſaid to cultivate this plant for its uſefulneſs in the dyeing of woollen cloths black ; and we know that by means of the common broad-leaved ſorrel an excellent black colour is, in many places of Scotland, given to woollen ſtuffs without the aid of copperas. As this mode of dyeing does not in the ſmalleſt degree injure the texture of the cloth, which continues to the laſt ſoft and ſilky, without that hardneſs to the touch which it acquires when dyed black by means of copperas, our readers will probably thank us for the following receipt, with which we have been favoured by a learned phyſician:</p><p>Let the fluff to be dyed be well waſhed with ſoap and water, and afterwards completely dried. Then of the common broad-leaved ſorrel boil as much as ſhall make an acid decoction of sufficient quantity to let the ſtuff to be dyed lie in it open and eaſy to be ſtirred. The greater quantity of ſorrel that is uſed, the better will the colour be ; and therefore if the pot or cauldron will not hold enough at once, when part has bean sufficiently boiled, it muſt be taken out and wrung, and a freſh</p><p>quantity be boiled in the ſame juice or decoction. When the liquor is made sufficiently acid, ſtrain it from the ſorrel through a sieve, put the cloth or yarn into it, and let it boil for two hours, ſtirring it frequently. If ſtockings be among the ſtuff to be dyed, it will be expedient, after they have been an hour in the boiling liquor, to turn them inside out, and at the end of the ſecond hour let the whole be poured into a tub or any other veſſel. The pot or cauldron muſt then be waſh. ed, and water put into it, with half a pound of logwood chips for every pound oſ dry yarn or cloth. The logwood and water ſhould boil ſlowly for four hours ; and then the cloth or yarn being wrung from the four liquor, and put into the logwood decoction, the whole muſt be suffered to boil ſlowly for four hours, ſtockings, if there be any, being turned inside out at the end of two hours. Oſ this laſt decoction there muſt as of the former be enough to let the cloth lie open and eaſy to be ſtirred while boiling. At the end of the four hours the cloth muſt be taken out, and among the boiling liquor, firſt removed from the fire, muſt be poured a Scotch pint or Engliſh gallon of ſtale urine for every pound of dry cloth or other ſtuff to be dyed. When this compound liquor has been ſtirred and become cold, the cloth muſt be put into it and suffered to remain well covered for 1 2 hours, and then dried in the ſhade ; after which, to diveſt it of ſmell or any other impurity, it may be waſhed in cold water, and dried for uſe.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Wood-SORREL,</hi> in botany. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Oxalis.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">SORREL-Colour,</hi> in the manege, is a reddiſh colour, generally thought to be a ſign of a good horſe.</p></div></body></text></TEI>