<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0663.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0657-01" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SPARUS, <hi rend="smallcaps">Gilt head,</hi></label>
 in natural hiſtory ; a genus of animals belonging to the claſs of <hi rend="italic">piſces,</hi> and the order of <hi rend="italic">thoracici.</hi> The fore-teeth and dog-teeth are very ſtrong ; the grinders are obtuſe and thick ſet ; the lips are folded over ; there are five rays in the gill membrane ; and the opercula are ſcaly : the body is compressed ; the lateral line is crooked behind ; and the pectoral fins are roundiſh.</p><p>Gmelin enumerates 39 ſpecies, of which only three are found in the Britiſh ſeas, the pagrus, auratus, and dentatus. 1. The <hi rend="italic">pagrus,</hi> or ſea-bream, is of a reddiſh colour. The ſkin forms a ſinus at the roots of the dorſal and anal fins. The body is broad ; the back and belly ridged. There is only one dorſal fin. 2. The <hi rend="italic">auratus,</hi> or gilt-bream. The head and ſides of it are gilt, and there is a golden ſpot between the eyes ſhaped like a half-moon ; there is alſo a black purple ſpot on the gills ; and it weighs from eight lb. to ten lb. It is one<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0664.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0658"/>
of the <hi rend="italic">piſces saxatiles,</hi> or fiſh that haunts deep waters on bold rocky ſhores. They feed chiefly on ſhell-fiſh, which they comminute with their teeth before they ſwallow ; the teeth of this genus in particular being adapted for that purpoſe : the grinders are flat and ſtrong, like thoſe of certain quadrupeds : beſides which there are certain bones in the lower part of the mouth that aſſiſt in grinding their food. They are but a coarſe fiſh : they were known to the Romans, who did not eſteem them unleſs they were fed with Lucrine oyſters, as Martial informs us,</p><p><hi rend="italic">Non omnis laudem pretiumque</hi> <hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Aurata</hi> <hi rend="italic">meretur,</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Sed qui ſolus erit concha Lucrina cibus.</hi></p><p>Lib. xiii. Ep. 90.</p><p>3. The <hi rend="italic">dentatus,</hi> toothed ſea-bream, is black above, and of a ſilvery appearance below. The eyes and gills are very large. There are nine rows of teeth in the lower jaw, and one in the upper.</p><p>In the account of Captain Cook’s voyage publiſhed by Mr Forster, we are informed, that the giltheads are sometimes poiſonous, owing to their feeding on certain ſpecies of the raja, which have an extremely acrid and stimulating property.</p></div></body></text></TEI>