<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0266.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s03-0260-03" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SEMEN, <hi rend="smallcaps">seed.</hi></label>
 See <hi rend="smallcaps">Botany,</hi> ſect. iv. p. 435.</p><p>With reſpect to number, plants are either furniſhed with one ſeed, as ſea-pink and biſtort ; two, as wood- roof and the umbelliferous plants ; three, as spurge; four, as the lip flowers of Tourneſort and rough-leaved plants of Ray ; or many, as ranunculus, anemone, and poppy.</p><p>The form of ſeeds is likewiſe extremely various, being either large or small, round, oval, heart-ſhaped, kid- ney-ſhaped, angular, prickly, rough, hairy, wrinkled, ſleek or ſhining, black, white, or brown. Most ſeeds have only one cell or internal cavity ; thoſe of lesser burdock, valerian, lamb’s lettuce, cornelian cherry, and ſebeſten, have two.</p><p>With reſpect to ſubſtance, ſeeds are either ſoft, membranaceous, or of a hard bony ſubſtance ; as in grom- well, tamarind, and all the nuciferous plants.</p><p>In point of magnitude, ſeeds are either very large, as in the cocoanut ; or very ſmell, as in campanula, <hi rend="italic">ammannia,</hi> rampions, and throat-wort.</p><p>With reſpect to situation, they are either diſperſed promiſcuouſly through the pulp <hi rend="italic">(femina nidulantia),</hi> as in water-lily ; affixed to a future or joining of the valves of the ſeed-veſſel, as in the croſs-ſhaped and pea-bloom flowers ; or placed upon a <hi rend="italic">placenta</hi> or receptacle within the feed veſſel, as in tobacco and thorn-apple.</p><p>Seeds are ſaid to be naked <hi rend="italic">(femina nuda)</hi> which are not contained in a cover or veſſel : ſuch are thoſe of the lip and compound flowers, the umbelliferous and rough-leaved plants; covered ſeeds <hi rend="italic">(ſemina tecta)</hi> are<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0267.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s03-0261"/>
contained in ſome veſſel, whether of the capſule, pod, berry, apple, or cherry kind.</p><p>A simple seed is ſuch as bears neither crown, wing, nor downy <hi rend="italic">pappus ;</hi> the varieties in seeds, arising from theſe circumſtances, are particularly enumerated, under their respective heads.</p><p>In aſſimilating the animal and vegetable kingdoms, Linnaeus denominates ſeeds the eggs of plants. The fecundity of plants is frequently marvellous ; from a ſingle plant or ſtalk of Indian Turkey wheat, are produced, in one ſummer, 2000 ſeeds ; of elecampane, 3000; of ſun-flower, 4000; of poppy, 32,000; of a ſpike of cat’s tail, 10,000 and upwards : a ſingle fruit, or ſeed-veſſel, of tobacco, contains 1000 ſeeds ; that of white poppy, 8000. Mr Ray relates, from experiments made by himſelf, that 1012 tobacco-seeds are equal in weight to one grain ; and that the weight of the whole quantum of ſeeds in a ſingle tobacco-plant, is ſuch as muſt, according to the above proportion, determine their number to be 360,000. The ſame author eſtimates the annual produce of a ſingle ſtalk of ſpleen-wort to be upwards of one million of ſeeds.</p><p>The diſſemination of plants respects the different methods or vehicles by which nature has contrived to disperse their seeds for the purpoſe of increaſe. Theſe by naturaliſts are generally reckoned four.</p><p>1. Rivers and running waters. 2. The wind. 3. Animals. 4. An elaſtic spring, peculiar to the ſeeds themſelves.</p><p>1. The ſeeds which are carried along by rivers and torrents are frequently conveyed many hundreds of leagues from their native foil, and caſt upon a very different climate, to which, however, by degrees they render themselves familiar.</p><p>2. Thoſe which are carried by the wind, are either <hi rend="italic">winged,</hi> as in fir-tree, trumpet-flower, tulip-tree, birch, arbor-vitae, meadow rue, and Jeſſamine, and ſome umbelliferous plants ; furniſhed with a <hi rend="italic">pappus,</hi> or downy crown, as in valerian, poplar, reed, ſucculent ſwallow- wort, cotton-tree, and many of the compound flowers ; placed within a winged <hi rend="italic">calyx</hi> or ſeed-vessel, as in ſcabious, ſea-pink, dock, dioſcorea, aſh, maple, and elm- trees, logwood and woad ; or laſtly, contained within a swelled <hi rend="italic">calyx</hi> or ſeed-veffel, as in winter-cherry, cucubalus, melilot, bladder-nut, fumatory, bladder-ſena, heart- ſeed, and chick-peaſe.</p><p>3. Many birds fwallow the ſeeds of vanelloe, juniper, miſletoe, oats, millet, and other graſſes, and void them entire. Squirrels, rats, parrots, and other animals, ſuffer many of the ſeeds which they devour to eſcape, and thus in effect diſſeminate them. Moles, ants, earthworms, and other infects, by ploughing up the earth, admit a free paſſage to thoſe ſeeds which have been ſeattered upon its ſurface. Again, ſome ſeeds attach themſelves to animals, by means of hooks, crotchets, or hairs, which are either affixed to the ſeeds themſelves, as in hound’s tongue, mouſe-ear, vervain, carrot, baſtard-parsley, ſanicle, water hemp-agrimony, <hi rend="italic">arctopus</hi> and <hi rend="italic">verbeſina;</hi> to their calyx, as in burdock, agrimony, <hi rend="italic">rhexia,</hi> ſmall wild bugloſs, dock, nettle, pellitory, and lead wort; or to their fruit or ſeed-veſſel, as in liquorice, enchanter’s night ſhade, croſs-wort, clivers, French honey- ſuckle, and arrow-headed graſs.</p><p>4. The ſeeds which diſperſe themſelves by an elaſticn force, have that force reſident either in their <hi rend="italic">calyx,</hi> as in oats and the greater number of ferns ; in their <hi rend="italic">pappus,</hi> as in centaurea crupina ; or in their c <hi rend="italic">apſule,</hi> as in gerannium, herb-bennet, African spirae, fraxinella, horſe-tail, balſam, Malabar nut, cucumber, elaterium, and male balſam apple.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Semen,</hi> in the animal economy. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Physiology,</hi> ſect. xii. and <hi rend="smallcaps">Anatomy,</hi> n <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> 109.</p><p><hi rend="italic">SEMEN Sanctum,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Santonicum,</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Artemisia.</hi></p></div></body></text></TEI>