<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0347.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s03-0341-02" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SHEATHING</label>,
in the ſea-language, is the caſing that part of a ſhip which is to be under water with fir- board of an inch thick ; firſt laying hair and tar mixed together under the boards, and then nailing them on, in order to prevent worms from eating the ſhip’s bottom.—Ships of war are now generally ſheathed with copper : but copper ſheathing is liable to be corroded by the action of ſalt water, and ſomething is ſtill wanting to effect this purpoſe. It is very probable that tar might anſwer very well.</p><p>In the Corniſh mines, copper or braſs pumps are often placed in the deepeſt parts, and are conſequentlyexpoſed to the vitriolic or other mineral waters with which ſome of theſe mines abound, and which are known to have a much ſtronger effect on copper than ſea-water. Theſe pumps are generally about six feet long, and are ſcrewed together, and made tight by the interpoſition of a ring of lead, and the joinings are afterwards tarred. One of theſe pumps was ſo much corroded as to render it unfit for uſe ; but the ſpots of tar, which by accident had dropped on it, preſerved the parts they covered from the action of the water. Theſe projected in ſome places more than a quarter of an inch ; and the joints were ſo far defended by the thin coat of tar, that it was as perfect as when it came from the hands of the manufacturer. If tar thus effectually defends copper from theſe acrimonious waters, can there remain a doubt of its preſerving it from the much milder waters of the ſea ?</p></div></body></text></TEI>