<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0372.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s03-0366-04" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SHILOH</label>
is a term famous among interpreters and commentators upon Scripture. It is found (Gen. xlix. 10.) to denote the Meſſiah, The patriarch Jacob foretels his coming in theſe words ; “ The ſceptre ſhall not depart from Judah, nor a lawgiver from between his feet, until Shiloh come ; and unto him ſhall the gathering of the people be.” The Hebrew text reads, ∏⅛if N3 <hi rend="superscript"> 4</hi> ‘5 “Ψ until <hi rend="italic">Shiloh come.</hi> All Chriſtian commentators agree, that this word ought to be underſtooſt of the Meſſiah, or Jeſus Chriſt ; but all are not agreed<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0373.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s03-0367"/>
about its literal and grammatical ſignification. St Jerome, who translates it by Qui <hi rend="italic">mittendus est,</hi> manifeſtly reads Shi <hi rend="italic">loach</hi> “ ſent,” inſtead of <hi rend="italic">Shiloh,</hi> The Septuagint have it <hi rend="smallcaps">F.jj∙</hi> a» eλ⅛n <hi rend="italic">τa a-ra×uμ(ytc aυτω',</hi> or, Eως∙ <hi rend="italic">a∕ ι,λ,⅛n a a^o×fiτxι.</hi> (as iſ they had read l⅛w inſtead of n⅛w), <hi rend="italic">i. e.</hi> “ Until the coming of him to whom it is reſerved ;” or, “ Till we ſee arrive that which is reſerved for him.”</p><p>It muſt be owned, that the signification of the Hebrew word <hi rend="italic">Shiloh</hi> is not well known. Some tranſlate, “ thc ſceptre ſhall not depart from Judah, till he comes to whom it belongs ;” ∏ <hi rend="superscript"> l</hi> w or inſtead of I <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> ?* ' <hi rend="superscript"> t,</hi> Others, “ till the coming of the peace-maker ;” or, “ the pacific ;” or, “ of prosperity,” ∏bu <hi rend="superscript"> ,</hi> <hi rend="italic">proſperatus est. Shalah</hi> signifies, “ to be in peace, to be in proſperity ;” others, “ till the birth of him who ſhall be born of a woman that ſhall conceive without the knowledge of a man,” <hi rend="superscript"> li</hi> ' or <hi rend="italic">ſecundina, fluxus</hi><note anchored="true" n="1" place="margin" type="authorial"><p><gap> </gap> <hi rend="italic">rab. Lud dieu.</hi></p></note>; otherwiſe, “ the ſceptre ſhall not depart from Judah, till its end, its ruin ; till the downfal of the kingdom of the Jews,” ⅛κu' or rife- <hi rend="italic">it has ceased, it has finished</hi><note anchored="true" n="2" place="margin" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">Le Clerc <gap> </gap> Genes.</hi></p></note> *. Some Rabbins have taken the name <hi rend="italic">Siloh</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Shiloh,</hi> as if it ſignified the city of this name in Paleſtine : “ The ſceptre ſhall not be taken away from Judah till it comes to Shiloh ; till it ſhall be taken from him to be given to Saul at Shiloh.” But in what part of Scripture is it ſaid, that Saul was acknowledged as king or conſecrated at Shiloh ? If we would understand it of Jeroboam the ſon of Nebat, the matter is ſtill as uncertain. The Scripture mentions no aſſembly at Shiloh that admitted him as king. A more modern author derives <hi rend="italic">Shiloh</hi> from ∏bu∙, <hi rend="italic">ſatigare,</hi> which ſometimes figniſies <hi rend="italic">to be weary, to ſuffer ;</hi> “ till his labours, his ſufferings, his paſſion, ſhall happen.”</p><p>But not to anruſe ourſelves about ſeeking out the grammatical ſignification of Shiloh, it is ſufficient for us to ſhow, that the ancient Jews are in this matter agreed with the Chriſtians : they acknowledge, that this word ſtands for the <hi rend="italic">Messiah the King.</hi> It is thus that the paraphraſts Onkelos and Jonathan, that the ancient Hebrew commentaries upon Geneſis, and that the Talmudiſts themſelves, explain it. If Jeſus Chriſt and his apoſtles did not make uſe of this paſſage to prove the coming of the Meſſiah, it was becauſe then the completion of this prophecy was not ſufficiently manifeſt. The ſceptre ſtill continued among the Jews ; they had ſtill kings of their own nation in the perſons of the Herods ; but ſoon after the ſceptre was entirely taken away from them, and has never been reſtored to then ſince.</p><p>The conceited Jews ſeek in vain to put forced meanings upon this prophecy of Jacob ; ſaying, for example, that the ſceptre intimates the dominion of ſtrangers, to which they have been in ſubjection, or the hope of feeing one day the ſceptre or ſupreme power settled again among themſelves. It is eaſy to perceive, that all this is contrived to deliver themſelves out of perplexity. In vain likewiſe they take refuge in certain princes of the captivity, whom they pretend to have ſubſiſted beyond the Euphrates, exerciſing an authority over their nation little differing from abſolute, and being of the race of David. This pretended ſucceſſion of princes is perfectly chimerical; and though at certain times they could ſhow a ſucceſſion, it continued but a ſhort time, and their authority was too obſcure, and too much limited, to be the object of a prophecy ſo remarkable as</p><p>this was.</p></div></body></text></TEI>