<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0273.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s03-0267-04" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SENNAAR</label>,
a country of Africa, bordering upon Abyſtinia, with the title of a kingdom ; the preſent government of which was eſtabliſhed in the 16th century by a race of negroes named, in their own language, <hi rend="italic">Shillοok.</hi> This country, together with all the northern parts of Africa, had been over-run by the Saracens during the rapid conqueſts of the khalifs ; but inſtead of erecting any diſtinct principalities here, as in other parts, they had incorporated themſelves with the old inhabitants called <hi rend="italic">Shepherds,</hi> whom they found at their arrival; had converted them to their religion, and become one people with them. In 1504 the Shillook, a people before unknown, came from the western banks of the river Bahiar el Abiad, which empties itſelf into the Nile, and conquered the country; allowing the Arabs, however, to retain their poſſeſſions on condition of paying them a certain tribute, Theſe founded the city of Sennaar, and have ever ſince continued to carry on an intercourſe with Egypt in the way of merchandiſe. At the eſtabliſhment of their monarchy the whole nation were Pagans, but soon after became converts to Mohammedaniſm, and took the name of <hi rend="italic">Funge,</hi> an appellation ſignifying “lords or conquerors,” and like-<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0274.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s03-0268"/>
wiſe free citizens. Mr Bruce, who paſſed through this country in his return from Abyſſinia, gives a list of 20 kings who have reigned in it ſince the conqueſt of the Shillook.</p><p>This country is inhabited by a people ſo barbarous and brutiſh, that no hiſtory of them can be expected. One of the most remarkable of their cuſtoms is, that the king ascends the throne with the expectation of being murdered whenever the general council of the nation thinks proper. The dreadful office of executioner belongs to one ſingle officer, ſtyled, in the language of the country, <hi rend="italic">Sid el Coom ;</hi> and who is always a relation of the monarch himſelf. It was from his regiſters that Mr Bruce took the list of the kings already mentioned, with the number of years they reigned, and which may therefore be received as authentic. The Sid el Coom in office at the time that Mr Bruce viſited this country was named Achmet, and was one of his beſt friends. He had murdered the late king, with three of his ſons, one of whom was an infant at its mother’s breaſt ; he was alſo in daily expectation of performing the same office to the reigning sovereign. He was by no means reierved concerning the nature of his office, but anſwered freely every queſtion that was put to him. When aſked by Mr Bruce why he murdered the king’s young ſon in his father’s preſence? he anſwered, that he did it from a principle of duty to the king himſelf, who had a right to see his ſon killed in a lawful and regular manner, which was by cutting his throat with a ſword, and not in a more painful or ignominious way, which the malice of his enemies might possibly have inflicted.</p><p>The king, he ſaid, was very little concerned at the sight of his Ion’s death, but he was so very unwilling to die himſelf, that he often preſſed the executioner to let him eſcape; but finding his intreaties ineffectual, he submitted at last without reſiſtance. On being aſked, whether he was not afraid of coming into the preſence of the king, conſidering the office he might poſſibly have to perform? he replied, that he was not in the leaſt afraid on this account ; that it was his duty to be with the king every morning, and very late in the evening ; that the king knew he would have no hand in promoting his death ; but that, when the matter was abſolutely determined, the rest was only an affair of decency; and it would undoubtedly be his own choice, rather to fall by the hand of his own relation in private than by a hired aſſaſſin, an Arab, or a Chriſtian ſlave, in the light of the populace. Baady the king’s father, having the misfortune to be taken priſoner, was ſent to Atbara to Welled Haſſan the governor of that province to be put to death there. But the king, who was a ſtrong man, and always armed, kept ſo much upon his guard, that Welled could find no opportunity of killing him but by running him through the back with a lance as he was waſhing his hands. For this Welled himſelf was afterwards put to death ; not on account of the murder itſelf, but becauſe, in the first place, he, who was not the proper executioner, had preſumed to put the king to death; and, in the next, becauſe he had done it with a lance, whereas the only lawful inſtrument was a ſword.</p><p>On the death of any of the ſovereigns of this country, his eldeſt ſon ſucceeds to the throne of courſe ; on which as many of his brothers as can be found are ap</p><p>prehended, and put to death by the Sid el Coom in the manner already related. Women are excluded from the ſovereignty here as well as in Abyſſinia. The princeſſes of Sennaar, however, are worſe off than thoſe of Abyſſinia, having no settled income, nor being treated in any degree better than the daughters or private perſons. The king is obliged, once in his lifetime, to plough and ſow a piece of ground ; whence he is named <hi rend="italic">Baady,</hi> the “ countryman or peasant ;’’ a title as common among the monarchs of Sennaar as Cæsar was among the Romans. The royal family were originally negroes; but as the kings frequently marry Arab women, the white colour of the mother is communicated to the child. This, we are told by Mr Bruce, is invariably the caſe when a negro man of Sennaar marries an Arab woman ; and it holds equally good when an Arab man marries a negro woman; and he likewiſe informs us, that he never ſaw one black Arab all the time he was at Sennaar.</p><p>The soil and climate of this country is extremely unfavourable both to man and beast. The men are ſtrong· and remarkable for their size,but ſhortlived; and there is ſuch a mortality among the children, that were it not for a constant importation of slaves, the metropolis would be depopulated. The shortneſs of their lives, however, may perhaps be accounted for, from their indulging themſelves from their infancy in every kind of exceſs. No horſe, mule, nor aſs, will live at Sennaar or for many miles round it. The caſe is the ſame with bullocks, ſheep, dogs, cats, and poultry ; all of them muſt go to the ſands every half-year. It is difficult to account for this mortality ; though Mr Bruce aſſures us it is the caſe everywhere about the metropolis of this country, where the ſoil is a fat earth during the first leaſon of the rains. Two greyhounds which he brought along with him from Atbara, and the mules he brought from Abyssinia, lived only a few weeks after their arrival at Sennaar. Several of the kings of Sennaar have tried to keep lions, but it was always found impoſſible to preſerve them alive after the rains. They will live, however, as well as other quadrupeds, in the ſands, at no great diſtance from the capital. - No ſpecies of tree except the lemon flowers near this city ; the cultivation of the roſe has often been attempted, but always without ſucceſs. In other reſpects, however, the ſoil of Sennaar is exceedingly fertile, being ſaid to yield 300 fold ; but this is thought by Mr Bruce to be a great exaggeration. It is all ſown with dora or millet, which is the principal food of the people ; wheat and rice are alſo produced here, which are ſold by the pound, even in years of plenty. The ſoil all round is ſtrongly impregnated with ſalt, ſo that a ſufficient quantity to ſerve the inhabitants is extracted from it.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sennaar,</hi> a city of Africa, the capital of the kingdom of that name. It stands, according to Mr Bruce’s observations, in N. Lat. 13⁰ 34' 36" E. Long. 33⁰ 30' 30" on the western side of the Nile, and cloſe upon the banks of it ; the ground on which it stands being just high enough to prevent the inundation. The town is very populous, and contains a great many houſes. In Poncet’s time they were all of one ſtory ; but now most of the officers have houſes of two stories high. They are built of clay mixed with a very little ſtraw, and have all flat roofs ; which ſhows that the rains here<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0275.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s03-0269"/>
muſt be much leſs in quantity than to the ſouthward. During the time of Mr Bruce’s reſidence here, however, there was one week of continual rain, and the Nile, after loud thunder and great darkneſs to the ſouth, increaſed violently ; the whole ſtream being covered with the wrecks or houſes and their furniture ; so that he ſuppoſed it had deſtroyed many villages to the ſouthward. About 12 miles to the north-west of Sennaar is a collection of villages named <hi rend="italic">Shaddly,</hi> from a great ſaint of that name, who conſtructed ſeveral granaries here. Theſe are no other than large pits dug in the ground, and well plaſtered in the inside with clay, then filled with grain when it is at its loweſt price, and afterwards covered up and plaſtered again at top : theſe pits they call <hi rend="italic">matamores.</hi> On any proſpect of dearth they are opened, and the corn sold to the people. About 24 miles north of Shaddly there is another ſet of granaries named <hi rend="italic">Wed-Abοud,</hi> ſtill greater than Shaddly; and upon theſe two the ſubſiſtence of the Arabs principally depends : for as theſe people are at continual war with each other, and direct their fury rather againſt the crops than the perſons of their enemies, the whole of them would be unavoidably ſtarved, were it not for this extraordinary reſource. Small villages of ſoldiers are ſcattered up and down this country to guard the grain after it is ſown, which is only that ſpecies of millet named <hi rend="italic">Dora ;</hi> the soil, it is ſaid, being incapable of producing any other. There are great hollows made in the earth at proper diſtances throughout the country, which fill with water in the rainy ſeaſon, and are afterwards of great uſe to the Arabs as they paſs from the cultivated parts to the ſands. The fly, which is ſuch a dreadful enemy to the cattle, is never ſeen to the northward of Shaddly.</p><p>To the weſtward of theſe granaries the country is quite full of trees as far as the river Abiad, or Elaice. In this extenſive plain there ariſe two ridges of mountains, one called <hi rend="italic">Jibbel Moira,</hi> or the <hi rend="italic">Mountain oſ water ;</hi> the other <hi rend="italic">Jibbel Segud,</hi> or the <hi rend="italic">Cold Mountain.</hi> Both of them enjoy a fine climate, and ſerve for a protection to the farms about Shaddly and Aboud already mentioned. Here alſo are fortresses placed in the way of the Arabs, which ſerve to oblige them to pay tribute in their flight from the cultivated country, during the rains, to the dry lands of Atbara. Each of theſe diſtricts is governed by the deſcendant of their ancient and native princes, who long reſiſted all the power of the Arabs. Sacrifices of a horrid nature are ſaid to have been offered up on these mountains till about the year 1554, when one of the kings of Sennaar besieged firſt one and then the other of the princes in their mountains ; and having forced them to ſurrender, he faſtened a chain of gold to each of their ears, expoſed them in the market-place at Sennaar, and sold them for ſlaves at leſs than a farthing each. Soon after this they were circumciſed, converted to the Mahometan religion, and reſtored to their kingdoms.</p><p>“ Nothing (says Mr Bruce) is more pleaſant than the country around Sennaar in the end of Auguſt and beginning of September. The grain, being now ſprung up, makes the whole of this immenſe plain appear a level green land, interſperſed with great lakes of water, and ornamented at certain intervals with groups of villages ; the conical tops of the houſes preſenting at a diſtancc the appearance of ſmall encampments. Through</p><p>this very extenſive plain winds the Nile, a delightful river there, above a mile broad, full to the very brim, but never overflowing. Everywhere on theſe banks are ſeen herds of the most beautiful cattle of various kinds. The banks of the Nile about Sennaar reſemble the pleaſanteſt part of Holland in the ſummer ſeaſon ; but ſoon after, when the rains ceaſe, and the sun exerts its utmoſt influence, the dora begins to ripen, the leaves to turn yellow and to rot, the lakes to putrefy, ſmell, become full of vermin, and all its beauty ſuddenly disappears: bare ſcorched Nubia returns, and all its terrors of poiſonous winds and moving ſands, glowing and ventilated with ſultry blaſts, which are followed by a troop of terrible attendants ; epilepſies, apoplexies, violent fevers, obſtinate agues, and lingering painful dyſenteries, ſtill more obſtinate and mortal.</p><p>“ War and treason seem to be the only employment of this horrid people, whom Heaven has ſeparated by almoſt impaſſable deſerts from the rest of mankind; confining them to an accurſed ſpot, ſeemingly to give them an earneſt in time of the only other courſe which he has reſerved to them for an eternal hereafter.”</p><p>With regard to the climate of the country round Sennaar, Mr Bruce has ſeveral very curious obſervations. The thermometer riſes in the ſhade to 119 degrees ; but the degree indicated by this inſtrument does not at all correspond with the ſenſations occaſioned by it; nor with the colour of the people who live under it. “ Nations of blacks (ſays he) live within latitude 13 and 14 degrees; about 10 degrees ſouth of them, nearly under the line, all the people are white, as we had an opportunity of observing daily in the Galla Sennaar, which is in latitude 13 degrees, is hotter by the thermometer 50 degrees, when the sun is moſt diſtant from it, than Gondar, which is a degree farther ſouth, when the fun is vertical.—Cold and hot (ſays our author) are terms merely relative, not determined by the latitude, but elevation of the place. When, therefore, we ſay <hi rend="italic">hot,</hi> ſome other explanation is necessary concerning the place where we are, in order to give an adequate idea of the ſenſations of that heat upon the body, and the effects of it upon the lungs. The degree of the thermometer conveys this but very imperfectly ; 90 degrees is exceſſively hot at Loheia in Arabia Felix ; and yet the latitude of Loheia is but 15 degrees; whereas 90 degrees at Sennaar is only warm as so ſenſe ; though. Sennaar, as we have already ſaid, is in latitude 13 degrees.</p><p>“ At Sennaar, then, I call it <hi rend="italic">cold,</hi> when one fully clothed and at rest feels himſelf in want of fire. I call it <hi rend="italic">cool,</hi> when one fully clothed and at rest feels he could bear more covering all over, or in part, than he has at that time. I call it <hi rend="italic">temperate,</hi> when a man ſo clothed, and at rest, feels no ſuch want, and can take moderate exerciſe, ſuch as walking about a room without ſweating. I call it <hi rend="italic">warm,</hi> when a man, ſo clothed, does not ſweat when at rest; but, upon taking moderate exerciſe, ſweats, and again cools. I call it <hi rend="italic">hot,</hi> when a man at rest, or with moderate exerciſe, ſweats exceſſively. I call it <hi rend="italic">very hot,</hi> when a man with thin, or little clothing, ſweats much, though at rest. I call it <hi rend="italic">exceſſive hot,</hi> when a man, in his ſhirt and at rest, ſweats exceſſively, when all motion is painful, and the knees feel feeble, as if after a fever. I call it <hi rend="italic">extreme hot,</hi> when the ſtrength fails, a disposition to faint comes on, a ſtraitneſs is found<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0276.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s03-0270"/>
in the temples, as if a ſmall cord was drawn tight about the head, the voice impaired, the ſkin dry, and the head ſeems more than ordinarily large and light. This, I apprehend, denotes death at hand ; but this is rarely or never effected by the sun alone, without the addition of that poiſonous wind which purſued us through Atbara, where it has, no doubt, contributed to the total extinction of every thing that hath the breath of life. A thermometer, graduated upon this ſcale, would exhibit a figure very different from the common one ; for I am convinced by experiment, that a web of the fineſt muffin, wrapt round the body at Sennaar, will occasion at raid-day a greater ſenſation of heat in the body, than a riſe of 5 degrees in the thermometer of Fahrenheit.</p><p>“At Sennaar, from 70 to 78 degrees of Fahrenheit’s thermometer is cool ; from 79 to 92 temperate ; at 92 degrees begins warmth. Although the degree of the thermometer marks a greater heat than is felt by the body of us ſtrangers, it ſeems to me that the ſenſations of the natives bear ſtill a leſs proportion to that degree than ours On the 2d of Auguſt, while I was lying perfectly enervated on a carpet in a room deluged with water at 12 o’clock, the thermometer at 116, I ſaw ſeveral black labourers pulling down a houſe, working with great vigour, without any ſymptoms of being incommoded.”</p><p>The dreſs of the people of Sennaar conſiſts only of a long ſhirt of blue cloth, which wraps them up from the under part of the neck to the feet. It does not, however, conceal the neck in the men, though it does in the women. The men ſometimes have a ſaſh tied about their middle ; and both men and women go barefooted in the houſes, whatever their rank may be. The floors of their apartments, eſpecially thoſe of the women, are covered with Perſian carpets. Both men and women anoint themselves, at leaſt once a-day, with camel’s greaſe mixed with civet, which, they imagine, ſoftens their ſkins, and preſerves them from cutaneous eruptions ; of which they are ſo fearful, that they confine themſelves to the houſe if they obſerve the ſmalleſt pimple on their ſkins. With the same view of preserving their ſkins, though they have a clean ſhirt every day, they ſleep with a greaſed one at night, having no other covering but this. Their bed is a tanned bull’s hide, which this constant greaſing ſoſtens very much ; it is alſo very cool, though it gives a ſmell to their bodies from which they cannot be freed by any waſhing.</p><p>Our author gives a very curious deſcription of the queens and ladies of the court at Sennaar. He had acceſs to them as a phyſician, and was permitted to pay his viſit alone. He was firſt ſhown into a large ſquare apartment, where there were about 50 black women, all quite naked excepting a very narrow piece of cotton rag about their waiſts. As he was musing whether theſe were all queens, one of them took him by the hand, and led him into another apartment much better lighted than the former. Here he ſaw three women fitting upon a bench or ſofa covered with blue Surat cloth ; they themſelves being clothed from the neck to the feet with cotton ſhirts of the same colour. Theſe were three of the king’s wives ; his favourite, who was one of the number, appeared to be about six feet high, and ſo corpulent that our traveller imagined her to be the largeſt creature he had ſeen next to the elephant and rhinoceros. Her features perfectly reſembled thoſe of a negro: a ring of gold paſſed through her under lip, and weighed it down, till, like a flap, it covered her chin, leaving her teeth bare, which were ſmall and very fine. The inſide of her lip was made black with antimony. Her ears reached down to her ſhoulders, and had the appearance of wings : there was a gold ring in each of them about five inches in diameter, and somewhat smaller than a man’s little finger; the weight of which had drawn down the hole where her ear was pierced ſo much that three fingers might eaſily paſs above the ring. She had a gold necklace like that called E <hi rend="italic">ſclavage,</hi> of ſeveral rows, one below another ; to which were hung rows of ſequins pierced. She had two manacles of gold upon her ancles larger than thoſe uſed for chaining felons. Our author could not imagine how it was poſſible for her to walk with them, till he was informed that they were hollow. The others were dreſſed much in the same manner ; only there was one who had chains coming from her ears to the outſide of each noſtril, where they were faſtened. A ring was alſo put through the griſtle of her noſe, and which hung down to the opening of her mouth; having all together ſomething of the appearance of a horſe’s bridle ; and Mr Bruce thinks that ſhe muſt have breathed with difficulty.</p><p>The poorer sort of the people of Sennar Jive upon the flour or bread of millet ; the rich make puddings of this, toaſting the flour before the fire, and putting milk and butter into it ; beſides which they uſe beef partly roaſted and partly raw. They have very fine and fat horned cattle, but the meat commonly fold in the market is camel’s fleſh. The liver and ſpare rib of this animal are always eaten raw ; nor did our author ſee one inſtance to the contrary all the time he was in the country. Hog’s fleſh is not ſold in the market ; but all the common people of Sennaar eat it openly ; thoſe in office, who pretend to be Mahometans, doing the ſame in ſecret.</p><p>There are no manufactures in this country, and the principal article of trade is blue Surat cloth. In former times, when caravans could paſs with ſafety, Indian goods were brought in quantities from Jidda to Sennaar, and then diſperſed over the country of the blacks. The returns were made in gold, a powder called <hi rend="italic">Tibbar,</hi> civet, rhinocerotes horns, ivory, oſtrich feathers, and above all ſtaves or glaſs, more of theſe being exported from Sennaar than from all the Eaſt of Africa. This trade, however, as well as that of the gold and ivory, is almoſt deſtroyed ; though the gold is ſtill reputed to be the beſt and pureſt in Africa, and is therefore bought at Mocha to be carried to India, where it all centres at last.</p></div></body></text></TEI>