<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2018-12-30T23:24:34Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>A second group is typified by the warty pig, S. <hi rend="italic">verrucosus, of</hi> Java, in which the hinder or upper unenamelled surface of the lower tusk is narrower than the outer, concave, and set nearly in the long axis of the skull. The skull itself is elongated, with comparatively simple and primitive molars, the latter being relatively short. There are also three small warts on each side of the face, the largest of which is just below the eye and carries long bristles. The small S. <hi rend="italic">celebensis</hi> of Celebes and 5. <hi rend="italic">philip- pinensis</hi> are probably only varieties of this species. The bearded pig <hi rend="italic">S</hi>. <hi rend="italic">barbalus ( = longirostris)</hi> of Borneo is a very distinct member of this group, distinguished by the great elongation of the skull, and the presence of a tuft of long hair near the muzzle. In Sumatra it is represented by the subspecies S. <hi rend="italic">b. öi,</hi> and in south-west Borneo by 5. <hi rend="italic">b. gargantua.</hi></p><p>Some doubt exists whether the pygmy hog of the Nepal Terai, which is not much larger than a hare, is best regarded as a member of the typical genus, under the name of <hi rend="italic">Sus salvanius </hi>or as representing a genus by itself, with the title <hi rend="italic">Porcula sahania.</hi></p><p>Similar doubts have also been entertained with regard to the African bush-pigs or river-hogs, but from geographical considerations alone these are but regarded as representing a separate genus, <hi rend="italic">Polamochocrus,</hi> although they are nearly allied to the <hi rend="italic">verrucosus</hi> group of <hi rend="italic">Sus.</hi> They are specially distinguished by the great development of the anterior half of the zygomatic arch of the skull, and by the presence in the boars of a homy protuberance of the skin in front of each eye, which overlies a tuberosity on the nasal bone; the molars are also small and simple, and the anterior premolars are generally shed at an early stage of life. The group is represented in Madagascar, as well as in Africa south of the Sahara. (See <hi rend="smallcaps">River-Hog.)</hi></p><p>the recently discovered <hi rend="italic">Hylochoerus</hi> of the equatorial forest-districts of Africa comes nearest to the under-mentioned wart- hogs, but the skull is of a much less specialized type, while the upper tusks are much smaller although they have the same general curvature and direction, and the cheek-teeth lack the peculiar characteristics of those of <hi rend="italic">Phacochoerus,</hi> although they present a certain approximation thereto. On the other hand, resemblance to that genus is shown by the reduction of the upper incisors to a single pair. The skin is clothed with a thick coat of coarse black hair of a bristly nature, but there are a few whitish hairs on the face and in the groin.</p><p>In the African wart-hogs (<hi rend="italic">Phacochoerus),</hi> which take their name from the large warty lobes projecting from each side of the face, the teeth are remarkably modified. The milk-dentition, and even the early condition of the permanent dentition, is formed on the same general type as that of <hi rend="italic">Sus,</hi> except that certain teeth arc absent, the formula being <hi rend="italic">i</hi><hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">3</hi>, <hi rend="italic">c</hi><hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">1</hi>, <hi rend="italic">p</hi><hi rend="superscript">3</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">2</hi>, <hi rend="italic">m</hi><hi rend="superscript">3</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">3</hi><hi rend="italic">,</hi> total 34; but as age advances all the teeth have a tendency to disappear, except the canines and the posterior molars, but these, which in some cases are the only teeth left in the jaws, attain an extraordinary development. The upper canines especially are of great size, and curve outwards, forwards and upwards. Their enamel covering is confined to the apex, and soon wears away. The lower canines arc much more slender, but follow the same curve; except on the posterior surface, their crowns are covered with enamel; both pairs of canines are large in the two sexes. The third or last molar tooth of both jaws is of great size, and presents a structure at first sight unlike that of any other mammal, being composed of numerous (22-25) parallel cylinders or columns, each with pulp-cavity, dentine and enamel-covering, and packed together with cement. Examination will, however, show that a modification similar to that which has transformed the comparatively simple molar tooth of the mastodon into the extremely complex grinder of the Indian elephant has served to change the tooth of the common pig into that of <hi rend="italic">Phacochoerus.</hi> The tubercles which cluster over the surface of the crown of the common pig are elongated and drawn out into the columns of the wart-hog, as the low transverse ridges of the mastodon’s tooth become the leaf-like plates of the elephant’s molar. (See <hi rend="smallcaps">Wart-Hog.)</hi></p><p>The last existing representative oí the <hi rend="italic">Suidae</hi> is the babirusa of Celebes, alone representing the genus of the same name, and readily distinguished by the extraordinary size and form of the tusks of the old males. (For the characteristics of this animal see <hi rend="smallcaps">Babirusa.)</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Extinct Swine.—</hi>Species of <hi rend="italic">Sus</hi> arc met with in Pliocene strata of Europe and Asia, the Lower Pliocene 5. <hi rend="italic">erymanthius</hi> of Greece and <hi rend="italic">S. giganteus</hi> and 5. <hi rend="italic">titan</hi> of India being enormous animals; the last with comparatively simple molars. The European 5. <hi rend="italic">palaeochoerus </hi>and the Indian <hi rend="italic">S. hysudricus</hi> are smaller forms; the first exhibiting signs of relationship with <hi rend="italic">Potamochoerus.</hi> In India also occurs <hi rend="italic">Hippohyus</hi> distinguished by the extremely complicated structure of its molars. In the Europcan Miocene we have <hi rend="italic">Hyotherium</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Palaeochoerus,</hi> and in the Upper Oligocene <hi rend="italic">Propalaeochoerus,</hi> which have square molars without any tendency to a selenodont structure in their cusps. Curiously enough a selenodont type is, however, apparent in those of the imperfectly known Egyptian <hi rend="italic">Geniohyus of </hi>the Upper Eocene, the earliest species which can be included in the family. Even in this the forward direction of the lower incisors is noticeable. <hi rend="italic">Choeropotamus</hi> is a European Oligocene genus with bunodont molars which show a conspicuous basal cingulum in the lower dentition; the first premolar is absent. In the European Miocene <hi rend="italic">Listriodon,</hi> which also occurs in the Indian Tertiarics, the molars have a pair of transverse ridges, like those of the proboscidean <hi rend="italic">Dinotherium (q.v.);</hi> but the genus is believed to be related to the Oligocene <hi rend="italic">Doliochoerus</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Choerotherium,</hi> in which these teeth show a more normal type of structure.</p><p>For the genus <hi rend="italic">Elotherium,</hi> of the Lower Miocene and Upper Oligocene of both hemispheres, which is often placed next the Suidae, sec <hi rend="smallcaps">Artiodactyla.</hi> The American Dicotylinae are noticed under <hi rend="smallcaps">Peccary.</hi>	(R. L.*)</p><p>SWINEMÜNDE, a port and seaside resort of Germany, in the Prussian province of Pomerania, situated at the east extremity of the island of Usedom, and on the left bank of the river Swine which connects the Stettiner Haff with the Baltic. Pop. (1905), 13,272. It serves as the outer port of Stettin (<hi rend="italic">q.v.),</hi> 42 m. distant by water, with which, as with Heringsdorf, it has direct railway communication. Its broad unpaved streets and one-storey houses built in the Dutch style give it an almost rustic appearance. although its industries, beyond some fishing, are entirely connected with its shipping. The entrance to the harbour, the best on the Prussian Baltic coast, is protected by two long breakwaters, and is strongly fortified. The grand lighthouse, 216 ft. high, rises beside the new docks on the island of Wollin, on the other side of the narrow Swine. In 1897 the river continuation of the Kaiserfahrt was opened to navigation, and, further, the waterway between the Haff and the Baltic was deepened to 24 ft. in 1900-1901 and in other ways improved. The connexion between Swinemünde and Stettin is kept open in winter by ice breakers. Formerly ships of heavy burden bound for Stettin discharged or lightened their cargo at Swinemünde, but since the recent deepening of the river Oder they can proceed direct to the larger port.</p><p>The Swine, the central and shortest passage between the Stettiner Haff and the Baltic Sea, was formerly flanked by the fishing villages of West and East Swine. Towards the beginning of last century it was made navigable for large ships, and Swinemünde, which was founded on the site of West Swine in 1748, was fortified and raised to the dignity oí a town by Frederick the Great in 1765.</p><p>See Wittenberg, <hi rend="italic">Swinemünde, Ahlbeck und Heringsdorf</hi> (Linz, 1893).</p><p>SWING, DAVID (1830-1894), American clergyman, was born of Alsatian stock in Cincinnati, Ohio, on the 23rd of August 1830. He spent most of his boyhood on a farm and earned his schooling; graduated at Miami University in 1852; studied theology at Lane Seminary; and was principal of the preparatory school at Miami in 1853-1866. He became pastor in 1866 of the Westminster Presbyterian Church (after 1868 the Fourth Church) in Chicago, which was destroyed in the fire of 1871; he then preached in McVicker’s theatre until 1874, when a new building was completed. In April 1874 he was tried before the presbytery of Chicago on charges of heresy preferred by Dr Francis Landey Patton, who argued that Professor Swing preached that men were saved by works, that he held a “ modal” Trinity, that he did not believe in plenary inspiration, that he unduly countenanced Unitarianism, &amp;c. The presbytery acquitted Dr Swing, who resigned from the presbytery when he learned that the case was to be appealed to the synod. As an action was taken against the church, of which he had remained pastor, he resigned the pastorate, again leased McVicker’s theatre (and after 1880 leased Central Music Hall, which was built for the purpose), and in 1875 founded the Central Church, to which many of his former parishioners followed him, and in which he</p></body></text></TEI>