<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-24-s02-0010-06" facs="encyclopaediabri24chisrich_0027.jp2" type="entry"><p><label>ST JOHN, JAMES AUGUSTUS</label>, (1801-1875), British author and traveller, was born in Carmarthenshire, Wales, on the 24th</p><pb xml:id="eb11-24-s02-0011" facs="encyclopaediabri24chisrich_0028.jp2"/><p>of September 1801. He received private instruction in the classics, and also acquired proficiency in French, Italian, Spanish, Arabic and Persian. He obtained a connexion with a Plymouth newspaper, and when, in 1824, James Silk Buckingham started the <hi rend="italic">Oriental Herald,</hi> St John became assistant editor. In 1827, together with D. L. Richardson, he founded the <hi rend="italic">London Weekly Review,</hi> subsequently purchased by Colburn and transformed into the <hi rend="italic">Court Journal.</hi> He lived for some years on the Continent and went in 1832 to Egypt and Nubia, travelling mostly on foot. The results of his journey were published under the titles <hi rend="italic">Egypt and Mohammed Ali, or Travels in the Valley of the Nile</hi> (2 vols., 1834), <hi rend="italic">Egypt and Nubia</hi> (1844), and <hi rend="italic">Isis, an Egyptian Pilgrimage</hi> (2 vols., 1853). On his return he settled in London, and for many years wrote political “ leaders ” for the <hi rend="italic">Daily Telegraph.</hi> In 1868 he published a <hi rend="italic">Life of Sir Walter Raleigh,</hi> based on researches in the archives at Madrid and elsewhere. He died in London on the 22nd of September 1875.</p><p>Besides the works mentioned St John was also the author of <hi rend="italic">Journal of a Residence in Normandy</hi> (1830); <hi rend="italic">Lives of Celebrated Travellers</hi> (1830); <hi rend="italic">Anatomy of Society</hi> (1831); <hi rend="italic">History, Manners and Customs of the Hindus</hi> (1831); <hi rend="italic">Margaret Ravenscroft, or Second Loυe</hi> (3 vols., 1835); <hi rend="italic">The Hellenes, or Manners and Customs of Ancient Greece</hi> (1842); <hi rend="italic">Sir Cosmo Digby,</hi> a novel (1844); <hi rend="italic">There and Back Again in Search of Beauty</hi> (1853); <hi rend="italic">The Nemesis of Power</hi> (1854); <hi rend="italic">Philosophy at the Foot of the Cross</hi> (1854); <hi rend="italic">The Preaching of Christ</hi> (1855) ; <hi rend="italic">The Ring and the Veil,</hi> a novel (1856) ; <hi rend="italic">Life of Louis Napoleon</hi> (1857); <hi rend="italic">History of the Four Conquests of England</hi> (1862); and <hi rend="italic">Weighed in the Balance,</hi> a novel (1864). He also edited, with notes, various English classics.</p><p>Of his four sons, all journalists and authors of some literary distinction—Percy Bolingbroke (1821-1889), Bayle, Spenser and Horace Roscoe (1832-1888)—the second, Bayle St John (1822-1869), began contributing to the periodicals when only thirteen. When twenty he wrote a series of papers for <hi rend="italic">Fraser</hi> under the title “ De re vehiculari, or a Comic History of Chariots.” To the same magazine he contributed a series of essays on Montaigne, and published in 1857 <hi rend="italic">Montaigne the Essayist, a Biography,</hi> in 4 volumes. During a residence of two years in Egypt he wrote <hi rend="italic">The Libyan Desert</hi> (1849). While in Egypt he learnt Arabic and visited the oasis of Siwa. On his return he settled for some time in Paris and published <hi rend="italic">Two Years in a Levantine Family</hi> (1850) and <hi rend="italic">Views in the Oasis of Siwah</hi> (1850). After a second visit to the East he published <hi rend="italic">Village Life in Egypt</hi> (1852); <hi rend="italic">Purple Tints of Paris: Characters and Manners in the New Empire</hi> (1854); <hi rend="italic">The Louvre, or Biography of a Museum</hi> (1855); the <hi rend="italic">Subalpine Kingdom, or Experiences and Studies in Savoy</hi> (1856); <hi rend="italic">Travels of an Arab Merchant in the Soudan</hi> (1854); <hi rend="italic">Maretimo, a Story of Adventure</hi> (1856); and <hi rend="italic">Memoirs of the Duke of Saint-Simon in the Reign of Louis XIV.</hi> (4 vols., 1857).</p></div></body></text></TEI>