<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-24-s02-0225-01"
                facs="encyclopaediabri24chisrich_0244.jp2" type="entry">
                <p><label>SĀSANA VAṂSA</label>, a history of the Buddhist order in Burma, which was
                    composed, in that country, by Paññā-sāmi in 1851. It is written in Pali prose;
                    and is based on earlier documents, in Pali or Burmese, still extant, but not yet
                    edited. The earlier part of the work deals with the history of Buddhism outside
                    of Burma. This is based on the Mahāvamsa, and other well-known Ceylon works; and
                    has no independent value. The latter part of the work, about three-fifths of the
                    whole, deals with Buddhism in Burma, and contains information not obtainable
                    elsewhere. Down to the 11th century the account is meagre, legendary and
                    incredible. After that date it is sober, intelligible and in all probability
                    mostly accurate. This portion occupies about one hundred pages 8vo in the
                    excellent edition of the text prepared for the Pali Text Society in 1897 by Dr
                    Mabel Bode. It shows a continuous literary effort through the eight and a half
                    centuries, and constantly renewed ecclesiastical controversy. The latter is
                    concerned for the most part with minor questions relating to rules of the order,
                    there being a tendency, as relaxations of the rules crept in with the lapse of
                    time, to hark back to the original simplicity. Of differences in matters of
                    doctrine there is no mention in this manual. Dr Bode has prefixed to her edition
                    a detailed summary of the contents of the book. (T. W. R. D.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
