<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-24-s02-0102-02" facs="encyclopaediabri24chisrich_0119.jp2" type="entry"><p><label>SALVIA</label>, a large genus belonging to the natural order Labiatae (<hi rend="italic">q.v.</hi>) <hi rend="italic">,</hi> containing about 500 species in the temperate and warmer regions of both hemispheres. The name is derived from the Lat. <hi rend="italic">salvo,</hi> from the healing properties of sage, 5. <hi rend="italic">officinalis</hi> (see figure under Labiatae). S. <hi rend="italic">verbenaea,</hi> Clary, is a native of Britain found in dry pastures and waste places.</p><p>Some of the Salvias are among the most showy of the soft-wooded winter-flowering plants, the blossoms being of a bright glowing scarlet. The three most useful species are <hi rend="italic">S. splendens, S. Heerii</hi> and 5. <hi rend="italic">gesneriflora,</hi> the first beginning to flower early in the autumn and lasting till Christmas, while the others follow immediately in succession, and continue in full beauty till April. Young plants should be propagated annually about February, and after nursing through the spring should be grown outdoors in a fully exposed situation, where they can be plunged in some non-conducting material, such as half-decomposed leaves. The young shoots should be stopped to secure bushy plants, but not later than the middle of August. The most suitable compost for them is a mixture</p><p>of mellow fibry loam enriched with a little mild thoroughly decom-posed manure, made sufficiently porous by the addition of sand or grit. In spring, and during the blooming period, the temperature should be intermediate between that of a stove and greenhouse. There aye other very ornamental species of easy growth, increased by cuttings in spring, and succeeding well in ordinary rich loamy soil. Of these 5. <hi rend="italic">angustifolia</hi> bears spikes of fine bright-blue flowers in May or June; 5. <hi rend="italic">chamaedryoides,</hi> a dwarfish subject, has deep-blue flowers in August; 5. <hi rend="italic">fulgens</hi> produces scarlet flowers in August; and 5. <hi rend="italic">inυolucrata</hi> produces fine red flowers during the autumn. 5. <hi rend="italic">patens</hi> is a lovely blue free-blooming sort, flowering in August, the colour being unique.</p></div></body></text></TEI>