<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-24-s02-0010-03"
                facs="encyclopaediabri24chisrich_0027.jp2" type="entry">
                <p><label>ST JEAN-D'ANGÉLY</label>, a town of western France, capital of an
                    arrondissement in the department of Charente-Inférieure, 33 m. E. of Rochefort
                    by rail. Pop. (1906) 6242. St Jean lies on the right bank of the Boutonne, which
                    is navigable for small vessels. The parish church of St Jean stands on the site
                    of an abbey church of the 13th century, of which some remains are left. In 1568
                    the monastery was destroyed by the Huguenots, but much of it was rebuilt in the
                    17th and 18th centuries, to which period belong two towers and the façade of an
                    unfinished church.</p>
                <p>St Jean owes the suffix of its name to the neighbouring forest of Angéry <hi
                        rend="italic">(Angeriacum).</hi> Pippin I. of Aquitaine in the 9th century
                    established there a Benedictine monastery which was afterwards reputed to
                    possess the head of John the Baptist. This relic attracted hosts of pilgrims; a
                    town grew up, took the name of St Jean d'Angeri, afterwards d’Angély, was
                    fortified in 1131, and in 1204 received a charter from Philip Augustus. The
                    possession of the place was disputed between French and English in the Hundred
                    Years’ War, and between Catholics and Protestants at a later date. In 1569 it
                    capitulated to the duke of Anjou (afterwards Henry III.). Louis XIII. again took
                    it from the Protestants in 1621 and deprived it of its privileges and its very
                    name, which he changed to Bourg-Louis.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
