<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-24-s02-0103-01" facs="encyclopaediabri24chisrich_0120.jp2" type="entry"><p><label>SALVINI, TOMMASO</label>, (1829- ), Italian actor, was bom at Milan on the 1st of January 1829. His father and mother were both actors, and Tommaso first appeared when he was barely fourteen as Pasquino in Goldoni’s <hi rend="italic">Donne curiose.</hi> In 1847 he joined the company of Adelaide Ristori, who was then at the beginning of her brilliant career. It was with her as Elettra that he won his first success in tragedy, playing the title role in Alfiero’s <hi rend="italic">Oreste</hi> at the Teatro Valle in Rome. He fought in the cause of Italian independence in 1849; otherwise his life was an unbroken series of successes in his art. He acted frequently in England, and made five visits to America, his first in 1873 and his last in 1889. In 1886 he played there Othello to the Iago of Edwin Booth. Apart from Othello, which he played for the first time at Vicenza in June 1856, his most famous impersonations included Conrad in Paolo Giacometti’s <hi rend="italic">La Morte civile,</hi> Egisto in Alfieri’s <hi rend="italic">Merope,</hi> Saul in Alfieri’s <hi rend="italic">Saul,</hi> Paolo in Silvio Pellico's <hi rend="italic">Francesca da Rimini,</hi> Oedipus in Nicolini’s play of that name, Macbeth and King Lear. Salvini retired from the stage in 1890, but in January 1902 took part in the celebration in Rome of Ristori’s eightieth birthday (see the <hi rend="italic">Century Magazine</hi> for June 1902, vol. lxiii.). Salvini published a volume entitled <hi rend="italic">Ricordi, anedotli ed impressioni</hi> (Milan, 1895). Some idea of his career may be gathered from <hi rend="italic">Leaves from the Autobiography of Tommaso Salvini</hi> (London, 1893).</p><p>His son Allessandro (1861-1896), also an actor, had several notable successes in America, particularly as D’Artagnan in <hi rend="italic">The Three Guardsmen.</hi></p></div></body></text></TEI>