<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-24-s02-0019-03" facs="encyclopaediabri24chisrich_0036.jp2" type="entry"><p><label>SAINT JOHNSBURY</label>, a township and the county-seat of Caledonia county, Vermont, U.S.A., on the Passumpsic river, about 34 m. E.N.E. of Montpelier. Pop. (1890) 6567; (1900) 7010; (1910) 8098; of the village of the same name (1900) 5666 (1309 foreign-born); (1910) 6693. Area of the township, about 47 sq. m. Saint Johnsbury is served by the Boston &amp;amp; Maine and the Saint Johnsbury &amp;amp; Lake Champlain railways. The farms of the township are devoted largely to dairying. In the village are a Y.M.C.A. building (1885); the Saint Johnsbury Academy (1842); the Saint Johnsbury Athenaeum (1871), with a library (about 18,000 volumes in 1909) and an art gallery;</p><p>the Fairbanks Museum of Natural Science (1891), founded by Colonel Franklin Fairbanks; St Johnsbury Hospital (1895); Brightlook Hospital (1899, private); the large scales manufactory of the E. &amp;amp; T. Fairbanks Company (see Fairbanks, Erastus), and also manufactories of agricultural implements, steam hammers, granite work, furniture and carriages. There are two systems of water-works, one being owned by the village.</p><p>The township of Saint Johnsbury was granted to Dr Jonathan Arnold (1741-1793) and associates in 1786; in the same year a settlement was established and the place was named in honour of Jean Hector Saint John de Crèvecæur (1731-1813), who wrote <hi rend="italic">Letters of an American Farmer</hi> (1782), a glowing description of America, which brought thither many immigrants, and who intrduced potato planting into France. The township government was organized in 1790, and the village was incorporated in 1853.</p></div></body></text></TEI>