<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-24-s02-0032-01"
                facs="encyclopaediabri24chisrich_0049.jp2" type="entry">
                <p><label>ST MlCHAEL'S MOUNT</label>, a lofty pyramidal island, exhibiting a
                    curious combination of slate and granite, rising 400 yds. from the shore of
                    Mount’s Bay, in Cornwall, England. It is united with Marazion by a natural
                    causeway cast up by the sea, and passable only at low tide. If its identity with
                    the Mictis of Timaeus and the Ictis of Diodorus Siculus be allowed, St Michael’s
                    Mount is one of the most historic spots in the west of England. It was possibly
                    held by a body of religious in the Confessor’s time and given by Robert, count
                    of Mortain, to Mount St Michael, of which Norman abbey it continued to be a
                    priory until the dissolution of the alien houses by Henry V., when it was given
                    to the abbess and Convent of Syon. It was a resort of pilgrims, whose devotions
                    were encouraged by an indulgence granted by Pope Gregory in the 11th century.
                    The Mount was captured on behalf of Prince John by Henry Pomeroy in the reign of
                    Richard I. John de Vere, earl of Oxford, seized it and held it during a siege of
                    twenty-three weeks against 6000 of the king’s troops in 1473. Perkin Warbeck
                    occupied the Mount in 1497. Humphry Arundell, governor of St Michael’s Mount,
                    led the rebellion of 1549. During the reign of Queen Elizabeth it was given to
                    Robert, earl of Salisbury, by whose son it was sold to Sir Francis Basset. Sir
                    Arthur Basset, brother of Sir Francis, held the Mount against the parliament
                    until July 1646. It was sold in 1659 to Colonel John St Aubyn and is now the
                    property of his descendant Lord Levan. The chapel is extra-diocesan and the
                    castle is the residence of Lord St Levan.</p>
                <p>Many relics, chiefly armour and antique furniture, are preserved in the castle.
                    The chapel of St Michael, a beautiful 15th-century building, has an embattled
                    tower, in one angle of which is a small turret, which served for the guidance of
                    ships. Chapel rock, on the beach, marks the site of a shrine dedicated to the
                    Virgin Mary, where pilgrims paused to worship before ascending the Mount. A few
                    houses are built on the hillside facing Marazion, and a spring supplies them
                    with water. The harbour, widened in 1823 to allow vessels of 500 tons to enter,
                    has a pier dating from the 15th century, and subsequently enlarged and restored.
                    Pop. (1901), III.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
