<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-24-s02-0223-02"
                facs="encyclopaediabri24chisrich_0242.jp2" type="entry">
                <p><label>SARSFIELD, PATRICK</label>, (? -1693), titular earl of Lucan,</p>
                <p>Irish Jacobite and soldier, belonged to an Anglo-Norman family long settled in
                    Ireland. He was born at Lucan, but the date is unknown. His father Patrick
                    Sarsfield married Anne, daughter of Rory (Roger) O’Moore, who organized the
                    Irish rebellion of 1641. The family possessed an estate of £2000 a year.
                    Patrick, who was a younger son, entered Dongan’s regiment of foot on the 9th of
                    February 1678. In his early years he is known to have challenged Lord Grey for a
                    supposed reflection on the veracity of the Irish people (September 1681), and in
                    the December of that year he was run through the body in a duel in which he
                    engaged as second. During the last years of the reign of King Charles II. he saw
                    service in the English regiments which were attached to the army of Louis XIV.
                    of F rance. The accession of King James II. led to his return home.</p>
                <p>He took part in the suppression of the Western rebellion at the battle of
                    Sedgemoor on the 6th of July 1685. In the following year he was promoted to a
                    colonelcy. King James had adopted the dangerous policy of remodelling the Irish
                    army so as to turn it from a Protestant to a Roman Catholic force, and
                    Sarsfield, whose family adhered to the church of Rome, was selected to assist in
                    this re-organization. He went to Ireland with Richard Talbot, afterwards earl of
                    Tyrconnel (<hi rend="italic">q.v.),</hi> who was appointed commander-in-chief by
                    the king. In 1688 the death of his elder brother, who had no son, put him in
                    possession of the family estate, which in those troubled times can have been of
                    small advantage to him. When the king brought over a few Irish soldiers to
                    coerce the English, Sarsfield came in command of them. As the king was deserted
                    by his army there was no serious fighting, but Sarsfield had a brush with some
                    of the Scottish soldiers in the service of the prince of Orange at Wincanton.
                    When King James disbanded his army and fled to France, Sarsfield accompanied
                    him. In 1689 he returned to Ireland with the king. During the earlier part of
                    the war he did good service by securing Connaught for the Jacobites. The king,
                    who is said to have described him as a brave fellow who had no head, promoted
                    him to the rank of brigadier, and then major-general with some reluctance. It
                    was not till after the battle of the Boyne (1st of July 1690), and during the
                    siege of Limerick, that Sarsfield came prominently forward. His capture of a
                    convoy of military stores at one of the two places called Ballyneety between
                    Limerick and Tipperary, delayed the siege of the town till the winter rains
                    forced the English to retire. This achievement, which is said by the duke of
                    Berwick to have turned Sarsfield’s head, made him the popular hero of the war
                    with the</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-24-s02-0224" facs="encyclopaediabri24chisrich_0243.jp2"/>
                <p>Irish. His generosity, his courage and his commanding height, had already
                    commended him to the affection of the lrish. When the cause of King James was
                    ruined in Ireland, Sarsfield arranged the capitulation of Limerick and sailed to
                    France on the 22nd of December 1691 with many of his countrymen who entered the
                    French service. He received a commission as lieutenant-general (maréchal de
                    camp) from King Louis XIV. and fought with distinction in Flanders till he was
                    mortally wounded at the battle of Landen or Neerwinden, on the 19th of August
                    1693. He died at Huy two or three days after the battle. In 1691 he had been
                    created earl of Lucan by King James. He married Lady Honora de Burgh, by whom he
                    had one son James, who died childless in 1718. His widow married the duke of
                    Berwick.</p>
                <p>J. Todhunter, <hi rend="italic">Life of Patrick Sarsfield</hi> (London,
                    1895).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
