<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-24-s02-0225-04"
                facs="encyclopaediabri24chisrich_0244.jp2" type="entry">
                <p><label>SASKATCHEWAN</label>, a province of Western Canada, lying between the two
                    provinces of Alberta and Manitoba. Area, 250,650 sq. m. The south-eastern
                    portion is chiefly prairie, being the continuation of the second prairie steppe
                    found in</p>
                <p>Manitoba. About 104° W. the Missouri Coteau, an elevation of several hundred
                    feet, probably an old glacial moraine, crosses the southern boundary and runs
                    north-westward, being the eastern escarpment of the third prairie steppe which
                    runs to the Rocky Mountains. Several elevations of note are found in the
                    southern half of the province. On the central part of the southern boundary is
                    Wood Mountain, a succession of clay <hi rend="underline">hills</hi>, On the
                    lower level is Moose Mountain, and north of it Beaver</p>
                <p>Hills and Touchwood Hills. These are elevations of morainal or glacial deposits.
                    The river Saskatchewan <hi rend="italic">(q.v.)</hi> gives its name to the
                    province. In central Saskatchewan near the south bend of the South Saskatchewan
                    begins the river Qu’Appelle (“ Who Calls? ”), which runs eastward, and crossing
                    the western boundary of Manitoba falls into the Assiniboine river. Farther to
                    the south rises the Souris river, which flows parallel to the Missouri Coteau,
                    passes southward into N. Dakota, and again entering the province of Manitoba
                    finds its way at length into the Assiniboine river. North of the Saskatchewan
                    river the</p>

                <pb xml:id="eb11-24-s02-0226" facs="encyclopaediabri24chisrich_0245.jp2"/>
                <p>surface of the province becomes heavily wooded, and this great forest continues
                    through the broken Laurentian and Cambrian region, becoming dwarfed as it goes
                    north. In this portion of the province are found Reindeer Take, and north-west
                    of this the easterly portion of Lake Athabasca, which is on the provincial
                    boundary line of Alberta.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Climate.—</hi> Extending as the province does from north to
                    south for more than 750 m., it may be readily seen that, as in the case of
                    Alberta, there will be a great range of climate and temperature. The
                    south-western part of the province is influenced much by the Chinook winds which
                    from the Rocky Mountain valleys come through Alberta. The climate here is dry,
                    and portions of the country need irrigation. In south-eastern Saskatchewan the
                    prairie lies on a lower level, there is more moisture, and the climate in winter
                    is more steady. The whole province of Saskatchewan, except the south-western
                    part, is well watered. As in the case of Alberta, the southern third of
                    Saskatchewan has a moderate and changeable climate; in the central third ranging
                    from Regina to Prince Albert it is steady, while in the northern third, through
                    the Laurentian region to 60° N., it is severe. Compare the following table
                    :—</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="2"/>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="2"><p>Elevation.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="2" rows="1"><p>Mean Temperature.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="2"><p>Average</p><p>Precipitation.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Summer.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Winter.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Maple Creek .</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>2495 ft.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>62°</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>I5·3°</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>10·18 in.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Swift Current</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>2423 ..</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>60°</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>9·4°</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>17·04 "</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Regina . .</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>1885 „</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>50°</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>o°</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>9·03 "</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Prince Albert</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>1402 „</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>54·6°</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>·09°</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>14·45 "</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Battleford .</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>1615 "</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p><hi rend="smallcaps">61·4°</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>7.1°</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>13·62 „</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>The animal life of Saskatchewan resembles that of Alberta (<hi rend="italic"
                        >q.v.</hi>), excepting the mountain lion, mountain sheep and mountain goat,
                    which belong to the Rocky Mountains. The plant life of Saskat-chewan is much
                    like that of eastern Alberta. The Douglas fir and several varieties of pine
                    found in the Rocky Mountains do not occur.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Population.—</hi> By the census of 1906 the population of
                    Saskatchewan was found to be 257,763. It had grown from 91,279 in 1901 (the area
                    of the province being in 1906 somewhat greater than in 1901). The population is
                    to a large extent Canadian, and the immigration has been largely from (1) the
                    British Isles; (2) the United States; (3) the continent of Europe. Several large
                    bodies of foreigners are found. There is a community of upwards of 8000
                    Doukhobors—a sect of Russian Quakers. Their tenets are peculiar, involving
                    opposition to form in religion, to marriage and to submission to governmental
                    requirements. They desire to hold their land in common. The Russian writer
                    Tolstoy was a promoter of this immigration. Considerable bodies of Galicians are
                    also found in the province. On the Indian population there were 9049 in 1901 ;
                    and of Indian half-breeds 7949 in the same year. The Indians of Saskatchewan are
                    chiefly Plain or Wood Crees, with a mixture among them of Saulteaux. Toward the
                    south small bands of Assiniboines are found, and here and there small companies
                    of refugee Sioux from the United States. All the Indians are on government
                    reserves. In these reserves along the Qu’Appelle river are presented many
                    examples of the successful management of the Indians by the Dominion government.
                    These reserves are largely self-supporting; the Indians have comfortable houses,
                    grow considerable crops of grain, make large quantities of hay and possess herds
                    of cattIe. At Regina, Qu’Appelle, Crooked Lakes and other industrial schools,
                    young Indians—both male and female—receive a practical education. Many of these
                    are making excellent farmers.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Government, &amp;amp;c.</hi> —Throughout the province the
                    municipal system of self-government, especially in the cities, towns and
                    villages, is being introduced. There are two cities in the province, (1) Regina
                    (pop. 9804 in 1907), the capital; (2) Moose Jaw (pop. 6249). The latter is a
                    divisional point on the Canadian Pacific railway, and owes its importance
                    chiefly to its railway connexions. In the northern portion of the province are
                    two considerable towns (l) Prince Albert (pop. 3005), on the banks of the North
                    Saskatchewan river, giving promise of becoming a manufacturing centre, having as
                    it has the great forest on the north side of the Saskatchewan river, adjoining
                    it. (2) Saskat∞n (pop. 3011), on the South Saskatchewan river. This, though a
                    new town, bids fair to become a great railway centre. Here the Canadian Pacific,
                    the Canadian Northern and the Grand Trunk Pacific railways all cross the great
                    river of the province, and tributary to this town is a large area of arable and
                    prairie land.</p>
                <p>The Saskatchewan is to some extent navigated, but a serious obstacle, the Grand
                    Rapids, near the mouth of the river, requires a canal to allow the entrance of
                    steamers into Lake Winnipeg. The southern part of the province is being covered
                    by railways, the Canadian Pacific railway having its main line generally
                    parallel to the international boundary line, at a distance of one hundred to one
                    hundred and fifty miles. This railway has south of its main line two important
                    branches: (1) The “ Soo ” line from Moose Jaw to Estevan, and connecting with
                    the United States’ system of railways. (2) The Arcola branch from the
                    south-eastern corner of the province running to Regina. Another branch leaves
                    the main line for the north at Kirkella, and this will make a direct
                    communication with Edmonton, while another branch line enters the province at
                    Harrowby and runs westward to join the Kirkella branch on its way to Saskatoon
                    and Edmonton. The Canadian Northern railway has a line which enters the province
                    at Togo and following the Saskatchewan leaves the province at Lloydminster and
                    pushes on to Edmonton. The Grand Trunk Pacific railway follows a direct line
                    from Winnipeg to Edmonton, entering the province at 51° 25' N. and leaving it at
                    52° 35' N. for the west.</p>
                <p>The chief industries of Saskatchewan are cattle-rearing in the northern part and
                    grain growing in the south of the province. Coal is found on the Saskatchewan,
                    and a light variety of lignite on the Souris river near the international
                    boundary. The province follows in general the plan of government found in the
                    other provinces of the Dominion. The capital of the province is Regina <hi
                        rend="italic">(q.v.).</hi> A provincial governor lives at Regina and he has
                    a cabinet of four ministers. The legislature consists of twenty-five members.
                    The province has adopted a public schools act, which has a proviso for the
                    establishment of separate schools, but this is so surrounded by restrictions as
                    to be almost non-effective, every such school being required in all particulars
                    to follow the public school model. The system covers both secondary and primary
                    public schools. A normal school is in operation at Regina.</p>
                <p>The religions of the people are similar to those in the other western provinces
                    of Canada. The principal denominations were in 1901 as follows :—</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Presbyterians</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>17,151</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Baptists .</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>2618</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Roman Catholics</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>17,116</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Doukhobors .</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>8700</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Church of England .</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>16,418</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Greek Church.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>2579</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Methodists</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>11,528</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Mennonites .</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>3683</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Lutherans</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>12,098</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p><hi rend="italic">History.—</hi> The history of Saskatchewan gathers round the
                    Hudson’s Bay Company. The open plains of the south were the home of the buffalo
                    and few posts were established here, but the Saskatchewan river was the great
                    line of communication for the fur-traders. It was first reached by the Montreal
                    fur-traders in 1766, and by the Hudson’s Bay Company from Hudson Bay in 1772. By
                    this route the traders reached the great fur country of Mackenzie river, and the
                    forts on the Saskatchewan river were notable. These were Fort Cumberland, Fort
                    Carlton and Edmonton House. Alexander Mackenzie in 1789 left Edmonton and Fort
                    Chipewyan (on Lake Athabasca) and going northward discovered Mackenzie river and
                    reached the Arctic Sea. On his second voyage, leaving Fort Chipewyan, he gained
                    the Peace river, and by means of this crossed the Rocky Mountains and reached
                    the Pacific coast (July 22nd, 1793), being first of white men, north of Mexico,
                    to cross the continent. The Saskatchewan and Mackenzie river basins were the
                    real fur country of the traders. The northern portion of the province of
                    Saskatchewan is still the home of the fur-trader.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
