<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-24-s02-0068-02"
                facs="encyclopaediabri24chisrich_0085.jp2" type="entry">
                <p><label>SALICIN, SALICINUM,</label> C<hi rend="sub">13</hi>H<hi rend="sub">18</hi>O<hi rend="sub">y</hi>, the bitter principle of willow-bark,
                    discovered ’by Leroux in 1831. It exists in most species of <hi rend="italic"
                        >Salix</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Populus,</hi> and has been obtained to the
                    extent of 3 or 4% from the bark of <hi rend="italic">S</hi>. <hi rend="italic"
                        >helix</hi> and S. <hi rend="italic">pentandra.</hi></p>
                <p>Salicin is prepared from a decoction of the bark by first precipitating the
                    tannin by milk of lime, then evaporating the filtrate to a soft extract, and
                    dissolving out the salicin by alcohol. As met with in commerce it is usually in
                    the form of glossy white scales or needles. It is neutral, odourless, unaltered
                    by exposure to the air, and has a bitter taste. It is soluble in about 30 parts
                    of water and 8o parts of alcohol at the ordinary temperature, and in 0.7 of
                    boiling water or in 2 parts of boiling alcohol, and more freely in alkaline
                    liquids. It is also soluble in acetic acid without alteration, but is insoluble
                    in chloroform and benzol. From phloridzin it is distinguished by its ammoniacal
                    solution not becoming coloured when exposed to the air. Chemically, it is a
                    glucoside derived from glucose and <hi rend="italic">saligenin</hi>
                    (o-oxy-benzyl alcohol), into which it is decomposed by the enzymes ptyaline and
                    emulsin. Oxidation converts it into <hi rend="italic">helicin</hi>
                    (salicylaldehyde-glucose). <hi rend="italic">Populin,</hi> a benzoyl salicin, is
                    a glucoside found in the leaves and bark of <hi rend="italic">Populus
                        tremula.</hi></p>
                <p>Salicin is used in medicine for the same purposes as salicylic acid and the
                    salicylates. It is also used as a bitter tonic, <hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi> a
                    gastric stimulant, in doses of five grains. The ordinary dose may go up to forty
                    grains or more with perfect safety, though the British Pharma-copoeia limits it
                    to twenty. The remote action of the drug is that of salicylic acid or the
                    numerous compounds that contain it (see Salicylic Acid).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
