<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-24-s02-0208-02" facs="encyclopaediabri24chisrich_0225.jp2" type="entry"><p><label>SARCEY, FRANCISQUE</label>, (1827-1899), French journalist and dramatic critic, was bom at Dourdan (Seine-et-Oise), on the 8th of October 1827. He spent some years as schoolmaster, but his temperament was little fitted to the work. In 1858 he devoted himself to journalism. He contributed to the <hi rend="italic">Figaro, L'Illustration, Le Gaulois, Le XIX* Siècle</hi> and other periodicals; but his chief bent was towards dramatic criticism, of which he had his first experience in <hi rend="italic">L'Opinion nationale</hi> in 1859. In 1867 he began to contribute to <hi rend="italic">Le Temps</hi> the “ feuilleton ” with which his name was associated till his death. His position as dictator of dramatic criticism was unique. He had the secret of taking the public into his confidence, and his pronouncements upon new plays were accepted as final. He was a masterly judge of acting and of stage effect; his views as to the drama itself were somewhat narrow and indifferent to the march of events. He published several miscellaneous works, of which the most interesting are <hi rend="italic">Le Siège de Paris,</hi> an account compiled from his diary (1871), <hi rend="italic">Comédiens et comédiennes</hi> (1878-1884), <hi rend="italic">Souvenirs de jeunesse</hi> (1884) and <hi rend="italic">Souvenirs d’âge mûr</hi> (1892; Eng. trans., 1893). <hi rend="italic">Quarante ans de théâtre</hi> (1900, &amp;amp;c.) is a selection from his dramatic feuilletons edited by A. Brisson. He died in Paris, on the 16th of May 1899.</p></div></body></text></TEI>