<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-24-s02-0104-03" facs="encyclopaediabri24chisrich_0121.jp2" type="entry"><p><label>SALYES</label>, (Gr. Σάλvϵs: also Sallyes, SaLYI, SalluvII), in ancient geography, a people occupying the plain S. of the Druentia (Durance) between the Rhone and the Alps. According to Strabo (iv. p. 203) the older Greeks called them Ligyes, and their territory Ligystikē. By some authorities they were considered a mixed race of Galli and Ligurians (hence Celtoligyes) ; by others a purely Celtic people, who subjugated the Ligures in the Provincia. They are said to have been the first transalpine peopIe subdued by the Romans (Florus iii. 2). In 154 b.c. the inhabitants of Massilia, who had been connected with the Romans by ties of friendship since the second Punic war, appealed for aid against the Oxybii and Decietes (or Deciates). These people, called by Livy (<hi rend="italic">Epit</hi>. 47) “ transalpine Ligurians,” were perhaps two smaller tribes included under the general name of Salyes. They were defeated by Quintus Opimius. In 125-124 hostilities broke out between the Romans and the Salyes from the same cause. The successful operations of Marcus Fulvius Flaccus were continued by Gaius Sextius Calvinus (123-122), who definitely subdued the Salyes, destroyed their chief town, and founded near its ruins the colony of Aquae Sextiae (Aix). Part of their territory was handed over to the Massaliots. Their king, Tuto-motulus (or Teutomalius), took refuge with the Allobroges. From this time the Salyes practically disappear from history. Among other important Roman towns in their territory may be mentioned Tarusco or Tarasco (Tarascon), Arelate (Arles), Glanum (St Remy) and Ernaginum (St Gabriel).</p><p>For ancient authorities see A. Holder, <hi rend="italic">Altceltischer Sprachschatz,</hi> ii. (1904).</p></div></body></text></TEI>