<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-24-s02-0196-02"
                facs="encyclopaediabri24chisrich_0213.jp2" type="entry">
                <p><label>SANUTO (Sanudo), MARINO</label>, the elder, of Torcello (c. 1260-1338),
                    Venetian statesman, geographer, &amp;amp;c. He is best known</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-24-s02-0197" facs="encyclopaediabri24chisrich_0214.jp2"/>
                <p>for his life-long attempts to revive the crusading spirit and movement; with this
                    object he wrote his great work, the <hi rend="italic">Secreta</hi> (or <hi
                        rend="italic">Liber Secretorum) Fidelium Crucis,</hi> otherwise called <hi
                        rend="italic">Historia Hierosolymitana, Liber de expeditione Terrae
                        Sanclae,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Opus Terrae Sanctae,</hi> the last being
                    perhaps the proper title of the whole treatise as completed in three parts or “
                    books.” This work has much to say of trade and trade-routes as well as of
                    political and other history; and through its accompanying maps and plans it
                    occupies an important place in the development of cartography. It was begun in
                    March 1306, and finished (in its earliest form) in January 1307, when it was
                    offered to Pope Clement V. as a manual for true Crusaders who desired the
                    reconquest of the Holy Land. To this original <hi rend="italic">Liber
                        Secretorum</hi> Sanuto added largely; two other “ books ” were composed
                    between December 1312 and September 1321, when the entire work was presented by
                    the author to Pope John XXII., together with a map of the world, a map of
                    Palestine, a chart of the Mediterranean, Black Sea and west European coasts, and
                    plans of Jerusalem, Antioch and Acre. A copy was also offered to the king of
                    France, to whom Sanuto desired to commit the military and political leadership
                    of the new crusade. Marino himself tells us that he had spent the best part of
                    his fife in Romania, the lands of the Eastern empire; of the Morea he had
                    especially intimate knowledge; he had also visited Cyprus, Rhodes, parts of the
                    Syrian, Cilician and Egyptian coasts, France, Flanders and north Germany, both
                    west and east of Denmark. He had been in Acre, Alexandria, Constantinople,
                    Avignon, Bruges and Sluys, as well as (apparently) in Hamburg, Lübeck, Wismar,
                    Rostock, Stralsund, Greifswald and Stettin. Among his friends and correspondents
                    were Guglielmo Bernardi de Furvo, a Venetian nobleman who had travelled
                    extensively in Moslem and Mongol lands (to Tabriz, Bagdad, Damascus and Cairo),
                    Bishop Jerome of Kaffa, in the Crimea, who in 1312 had been sent to reinforce
                    the Catholic mission in China, and perhaps Peter, the English-born bishop of
                    Sevastopolis or Sukhum Kalé in western Caucasia, who makes an appeal for aid to
                    the prelates of England in 1330. Marino Sanuto’s ancestor, Marco, had founded
                    the greatness of his family after the Fourth Crusade as duke of the Archipelago
                    and conqueror of Naxos, Paros, &amp;amp;c. (from 1207); and his descendant wrote
                    with a personal interest in the question of crushing Moslem power in the
                    Levant.</p>
                <p>The crusading plans of the <hi rend="italic">Secreta</hi> are double: first,
                    Egypt and the Moslem world on the side towards Europe (Syria, Asia Minor, the
                    Barbary States, Granada, &amp;amp;c.) are to be ruined by the absolute stoppage
                    of all Christian trade with the same. By such an interdict Sanuto hopes that
                    Egypt, dependent on its European and other imports of metals, provisions,
                    weapons, timber, pitch and slaves, would be fatally weakened, and the way thus
                    prepared for the second part of the campaign—the armed attack of the crusading
                    fleet and army on the Nile delta. With the aid of the Mongol Tatars of Asia,
                    natural allies of western Christendom, and of the Nubian Christians, the
                    conquest of the Delta and of all Egypt was to be followed by that of Palestine,
                    invaded and held from Egypt. Sanuto deprecates any other route for the crusade,
                    and unfolds his plan of campaign, his bases of supply, his sources for the
                    supply of good seamen, with great detail. Not only Mediterranean seaports, but
                    the lakes of North Italy and central Europe, and the Hanseatic ports, are
                    enumerated as nurseries of crusading mariners and marine skill. Finally, after
                    the conquest of Egypt, Marino designs the establishment of a Christian fleet in
                    the Indian Ocean to dominate and subjugate its coasts and islands. He also gives
                    a sketch of the trade-routes crossing Persia and Egypt, as well as of the course
                    of Indian trade from Coromandel and Gujarat to Ormuz and the Persian Gulf, and
                    to Aden and the Nile. The maps and plans which illustrate the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Secreta</hi> are probably (in the main, at least) the work of the great
                    portolano-draughtsman Pietro Vesconte: practically the whole of this map-work
                    corresponds with what Vesconte has left under his own name; much of it is
                    indistinguishable. Among the plans that of Acre is of peculiar interest, being
                    the most complete representation known of the great crusading fortress on the
                    eve of its destruction, with the quarters of all its contingents of defenders
                    (Templars, &amp;amp;c.) indicated. The chart of the Mediterranean and Euxine and
                    of the Atlantic coasts of Europe is composed of five map-sheets, which together
                    form a good example of the earliest scientific design or <hi rend="italic"
                        >portolano;</hi> in the world-map a <hi rend="italic">portolano</hi> of the
                    Mediterranean world is combined with work of pre-portolan type in remoter
                    regions. Here the shore-lines of the countries well known to Italian mariners,
                    from Flanders to Azov, are well laid down; the Caspian and the north German and
                    Scandinavian coasts appear with an evident, though far slighter, relation to
                    practical knowledge; and some idea is shown of the great continental rivers of
                    the north, such as the Don, Volga, Vistula, Oxus and Syr Daria. Africa, away
                    from the Mediterranean, is conventional, with its south-east projected, after
                    the manner of Idrisi, so as to face Indian Asia, and with a western Nile
                    traversing the continent to the Atlantic. Chinese and Indian Asia show little
                    trace of the new knowledge which had been imparted by European pioneers from the
                    Polos' time, and which appears so strikingly in the <hi rend="italic">Catalan
                        Atlas.</hi> of 1375. Sanuto's Palestine map is remarkable for its
                    space-defining network of lines, which roughly answer to a kind of scheme of
                    latitude and longitude, though properly speaking they are not scientific at all.
                    Of the <hi rend="italic">Secreta,</hi> twenty-three MSS. exist, of which the
                    chief are: (1) Florence, Riccardian Library, No. 237, 162 fols. (<hi
                        rend="italic">Secreta</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Letters),</hi> with maps
                    and plans on fols. 141, v.-144., r. ; (2) London, British Museum, Addt. MSS.,
                    27,376, 178 fols. with maps, &amp;amp;c. on fols. 180, v.-190, r. ; (3) Paris,
                    National Library, MSS. Lat. 4039, with maps, &amp;amp;c. on fols. 9, r.-11, r.
                    27, 98-99. All these are of the 14th century. The <hi rend="italic">Secreta</hi>
                    has only once been printed entire, by Bongars, in <hi rend="italic">Gesta Dei
                        per Francos,</hi> vol. ii. pp. 1-288 (Hanover, 1611).</p>
                <p>See also Friedrich Kunstmann, “ Studien über Marino Sanudo den älteren, mit einem
                    Anhange seiner ungedruckten Briefe” in <hi rend="italic">Abhandlungen der
                        historisch. Classe der Königl. Bayerisch. Akademie der Wissenschaften,</hi>
                    vol. vii. pp. 695-819 (Munich, 1855); Foscarini, <hi rend="italic">Letteratura
                        Veneziana;</hi> Tiraboschi, <hi rend="italic">Storia della Letteratura
                        Italiana, vol. v.; Pοstansque, De Marino Sanuto</hi> (Montpellier, 1856); C.
                    R. Beazley, <hi rend="italic">Dawn of Modern Geography,</hi> iii. 309-319,
                    391-392, 520-521, 549, 555. (C. R. B.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
