<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-24-s02-0005-02"
                facs="encyclopaediabri24chisrich_0022.jp2" type="entry">
                <p><label>SAINT-GELAIS, MELIN DE</label> (1487-1558), French poet, was born at
                    Angoulême on the 3rd of November 1487. He was the natural son of Octavien de St
                    Gelais (1466-1502), afterwards bishop of Angoulême, himself a poet who had
                    translated the Aeneid into French. Melin, who had studied at Bologna and Padua,
                    had the reputation of being doctor, astrologer and musician as well as poet. He
                    returned to France in 1515, and soon gained favour at the court of Francis I. by
                    his skill in light verse. He was made almoner to the Dauphin, abbot of Reclus in
                    the diocese of Troyes and librarian to the king at Fontainebleau. He enjoyed
                    immense popularity until the appearance of Du Bellay’s <hi rend="italic"
                        >Deffense et illustration . .</hi>. in 1549, where St Gelais was not
                    excepted from the scorn poured on contemporary poets. He attempted to ridicule
                    the innovators by reading aloud the Odes of Ronsard with burlesque emphasis
                    before Henry II., when the king’s sister, Margaret of Valois, seized the book
                    and read them herself. Ronsard accepted Saint-Gelais’s apology for this
                    incident, but Du Bellay satirized the offender in the <hi rend="italic">Poète
                        courtisan.</hi> In 1554 he collaborated, perhaps with François</p>
                <p>Habert (1520-1574?), in a translation of the <hi rend="italic">Sophοnisbe</hi> of
                    Trissino which was represented (1554) before Catherine de Medicis at Blois.
                    Saint-Gelais was the champion of the <hi rend="italic">style</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">marotique</hi> and the earliest of French sonneteers. He died
                    in 1558.</p>
                <p>His <hi rend="italic">Œuvres</hi> were edited in 1873 (3 vols., <hi rend="italic"
                        >Bibl. elzévirienne)</hi> by Prosper Blanchemain.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
