<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-24-s02-0210-03"
                facs="encyclopaediabri24chisrich_0227.jp2" type="entry">
                <p><label>SARDINIA</label>, (Gr. 'Iχνουσα, from a fancied resemblance to a footprint
                    in its shape, Ital. <hi rend="italic">Sardegna),</hi> an island of the
                    Mediterranean Sea, belonging to the kingdom of Italy. It lies 7½ m. S. of
                    Corsica, from which it is separated by the Strait of Bonifacio, which is some 50
                    fathoms deep. The harbour of Golfo degli Aranci, in the north-eastern portion of
                    the island, is 138 m. S.W. of Civitavecchia, the nearest point on the mainland
                    of Italy. Sardinia lies between 8° 7' and 9° 49' E., and extends from 38° 52' to
                    41° 15' N. The length from Cape Teulada in the S.W. to Punta del Falcone in the
                    N. is about 160 m., the breadth from Cape Comino to Cape Caccia about 68 m. The
                    area of the island is 9187 sq. m.—that of the department <hi rend="italic"
                        >(compartimento),</hi> including the small islands adjacent, being 9294 sq.
                    m. It ranks sixth in point of size (after Sicily) among the islands of Europe,
                    but it is much more sparsely populated.</p>
                <p>The island is mountainous in the main, almost continuously so, indeed, along the
                    east coast, and very largely granitic, with a number of lofty upland plains in
                    the east, and volcanic in the west. The highest point in the north-east group of
                    the island (called Gallura) is Monte Limbara (4468 ft.), S.E. of Tempio. This
                    mountain group is bounded on the S.E. and S. W. by valleys, which are followed
                    by the railways from Golfo degli Aranci to Chilivani, and from Chilivani to
                    Sassari. The north-western portion of the island, called the Nurra, lies to the
                    west of Sassari and to the north of Alghero, and is entirely volcanic; so are
                    the mountains to the south of it, near the west coast; the highest point is the
                    Monte Ferru (3448 ft.). East of the railway from Chilivani to Oristano, on the
                    other hand, the granitic mountains continue. The highest points are Monte Rasu
                    (4127 ft.), S. of Ozieri, in the district called Logudoro, on the chain of the
                    Marghine, which runs to Macomer, and, farther S., in the region called
                    Barbargia, the Punta Bianca Spina, the highest summit of the chain of
                    Gennargentu (6016 ft.). These two groups are divided by the deep valley of the
                    Tirso, the only real river in Sardinia, which has a course of 94 m. and falls
                    into the sea in the Gulf of Oristano. South of Gennargentu, in the district of
                    the Sarcidano, is the Monte S. Vittoria (3980 ft.), to the west of which is the
                    deep valley of the Flumendosa, a stream 76 m. long, which rises south of
                    Gennargentu, and runs S.E., falling into the sea a little north of Muravera on
                    the east coast. Still farther W. is the volcanic upland plain of the Giara (1998
                    ft.) and south of the Sarcidano are the districts known as the Trexenta, with
                    lower, fertile hills, and the Sarrabus, which culminates in the Punta Serpeddi
                    (3507 ft.), and the Monte dei Sette Fratelli (3333 ft.), from the latter of
                    which a ridge descends to the Capo Carbonara, at the S.E. extremity of the
                    island. South of Oristano and west of the districts last described, and
                    traversed by the railway from Oristano to Cagliari, is the Campidano (often
                    divided in ordinary nomenclature into the Campidano of Oristano and the
                    Campidano of Cagliari), a low plain, the watershed of which, near S. Gavino, is
                    only about 100 ft. above sea-level. It is 60 m. long by 7-14 broad, and is the
                    most fertile part of the island, but much exposed to malaria. South-west of it,
                    and entirely separated by it from the rest of the island, are the mountain
                    groups to the north and south of Iglesias, the former culminating in the Punta
                    Perda de Sa Mesa or Monte Linas (4055 ft.), and the latter, in the district
                    known as the Sulcis, reaches 3661 ft. It is in this south-western portion of the
                    island, and more particularly in the group of mountains to the north of
                    Iglesias, that the mining industry of Sardinia is carried on.</p>
                <p>The scenery is fine, but wild and desolate in most parts, and of a kind that
                    appeals rather to the northern genius than to the Italian, to whom, as a rule,
                    Sardinia is not attractive. The railway between Mandas and Tortoli traverses
                    some of the boldest scenery in the island, passing close to the Monte S.
                    Vittoria. The mountains near Iglesias are also very fine.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Coast.—</hi> The coast of Sardinia contains few seaports, but a
                    good proportion of these are excellent natural harbours. At the northeastern
                    extremity is a group of islands, upon one of which is the naval station of La
                    Maddalena : farther S.E. is the well-protected Gulf of Terranova, a part of
                    which, Golfo degli Aranci, is the port of arrival for the mail steamers from
                    Civitavecchia, and a port of call of the British Mediterranean squadron. To the
                    south of Terranova there is no harbour of any importance on the east coast (the
                    Gulf of Orosei being exposed to the E., and shut in by a precipitous coast)
                    until Tortoli is reached, and beyond that to the Capo Carbonara at the
                    south-east extremity, and again along the south coast, there is no harbour
                    before Cagliari, the most important on the island. In the south-west portion of
                    Sardinia the island of S. Antioco, joined by a narrow isthmus and a group of
                    bridges to the mainland, forms a good natural harbour to the south of the
                    isthmus, the Golfo di Palmas; while the north portion of the peninsula, with the
                    island of S. Pietro, forms a more or less protected basin, upon the shores of
                    which are several small harbours (the most important being Carlo-forte), which
                    are centres of the export of minerals and of the tunny fishery. Not far from the
                    middle of the west coast, a little farther S. than the Gulf of Orosei on the
                    east coast, is the Gulf of Oristano, exposed to the west winds, into which,
                    besides the Tirso, several</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-24-s02-0211" facs="encyclopaediabri24chisrich_0228.jp2"/>
                <p>streams fall, forming considerable lagoons. For some way beyond the only seaport
                    is Bosa, which has only an open roadstead; and at the southern extremity of the
                    Nurra come the Gulf of Alghero and the Porto Conte to the W., the latter a fine
                    natural harbour but not easy of ingress or egress. The northern extremity of thè
                    Nurra, the Capo del Falcone, is continued to the N.N.E. by the island of
                    Asinara, about 11 m. in length, the highest point of which, the Punta della
                    Scomunica, is 1339 ft. high. This small island serves as a</p>
                <p>quarantine station. On the mainland, on the south shore of the Golfo dell’
                    Asinara, is the harbour of Porto Torres, the only one of any importance on the
                    north-west coast of Sardinia.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Geology.—</hi> Geologically Sardinia consists of two hilly
                    regions of</p>
                <p>Pre-Tertiary rock, separated by a broad depression filled with Tertiary deposits.
                    This depression runs nearly from north to south, from the Gulf of Asinara to the
                    Gulf of Cagliari. Physically its continuity is broken by Monte Urticu and
                    several smaller hills which rise within it, but these are all composed of
                    volcanic rock and are the remains of Tertiary volcanoes. It is in the south that
                    the depression remains most distinct and it is there known as the Campidano. In
                    the north it forms the plain of Sassari. Both to the east and to the west of
                    this depression the Archean and Palaeozoic rocks which form the greater part of
                    the island are strongly folded, with the exception of the uppermost beds, which
                    belong to the Permian system. In the eastern region this was the last folding
                    which has affected the country, and the Mesozoic and Tertiary beds are almost
                    undisturbed. In the western region, on the other hand, all the Mesozoic beds are
                    involved in a later system of folds; but here also the Tertiary beds lie nearly
                    horizontal. There were, therefore, two principal epochs of folding in the
                    island, one at the close of the Palaeozoic era which affected the whole of the
                    island, and one at the close of the Mesozoic which was felt only in the western
                    region. Corresponding with this difference of structure there is also a
                    difference in the geological succession. In the western region all the Mesozoic
                    systems, including the Trias, are well developed. The Trias does not belong, as
                    might have been expected, to the Alpine or Mediterranean type; but resembles
                    that of Germany and northern Europe. In the eastern region the Trias is entirely
                    absent and the Mesozoic series begins with the Upper Jurassic.</p>
                <p>Granite and Archean schists form nearly the whole of the eastern hills from the
                    Strait of Bonifacio southwards to the Flumendosa river, culminating in Monti del
                    Gennargentu. The Palaeozoic rocks form two extensive masses, one in the
                    south-east and the other in the south-west. They occur also on the extreme
                    north-western coast, in the Nurra. Cambrian, Ordovician and Silurian beds have
                    been recognized, the Upper Cambrian consisting of a limestone which is very rich
                    in metalliferous ores (especially galena and calamine). The Permian, which
                    contains workable coal seams, lies uncon-formably upon the older beds and seems
                    to have been deposited in isolated basins (<hi rend="italic">e.g.</hi> at Fondu
                    Corrongiu and San Sebastiano), like those of the Central Plateau of France. The
                    Mesozoic beds are limited in extent, the most extensive areas lying around the
                    Gulf of Orosei on the east and west of Sassari in the north. The Tertiary
                    deposits cover the whole of the central depression, where they are associated
                    with extensive flows of lava and beds of volcanic ash. The most widely spread of
                    the sedimentary beds belong to the Miocene period.<note anchored="true"
                        place="bottom" type="authorial" n="1"> See A. de la Marmora, <hi
                            rend="italic">Voyage en Sardaigne,</hi> vol. iii. (1857); J. C.
                        Bornemann, “ Die Versteinerungen des Cambrischen Schichten-systems der Insel
                        Sardinien,” <hi rend="italic">Nova Acta k. DC. Akad. Naturf.</hi> vol. li.
                        (1886), pp. 1-148, pls. i.-xxxiii., and <hi rend="italic">ib.</hi> vol. lvi.
                        (1891), pp. 427-528, pls. xix.-xxviii. ; A. Törnquist, “Ergebnisse einer
                        Bereisung der Insel Sardinien,” <hi rend="italic">Sitz. k. preuss.
                            Akad.</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">Wiss.</hi> (1902), pp. 808-829, and “ Der Gebirgsbau
                        Sardiniens und seine Beziehungen zu den jungen, circum-mediterranen
                        Faltenzügen,” <hi rend="italic">ib. (</hi> 1903 <hi rend="italic">),</hi>
                        pp. 685-699; A. Dannenberg, “ Der Vulkanberg Mte Ferru in Sardinien,” <hi
                            rend="italic">Neues Jahrb. f. Min.</hi> Beil. Bd. xxi. (1906), pp. 1-62,
                        pl. i. </note></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Climate.</hi> —The climate of Sardinia is more extreme than
                    that of Italy, but varies considerably in different districts. The mean winter
                    temperature for Sassari for 1871-1900 was 48° F., the mean summer temperature
                    73° F., while the mean of the extremes reached in each direction were 99° F. and
                    31·5° F. The island is subject to strong winds, which are especially felt at
                    Cagliari owing to its position at the south-east end of the Campidano, and the
                    autumn rains are sometimes of almost tropical violence. The lower districts are
                    hot and often unhealthy in the summer, while the climate of the mountainous
                    portion of the island is less oppressive, and would be still cooler if it
                    possessed more forest. There are comparatively few streams and no inland lakes.
                    Snow hardly ever falls near the coast, but is abundant in the higher parts of
                    the island, though none remains throughout the summer. The rainfall in the
                    south-west portion of the island is considerably greater than in other
                    districts. The mean annual rainfall for Sassari for 1871-1900 was 24∙45 in., the
                    average number of days on which rain fell being 109, of which 37 were in winter
                    and only 8 in summer—the latter equal with Palermo, but lower than any other
                    station in ltaly.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Malaria.</hi> —The island has a bad reputation for malaria, due
                    to the fact that it offers a considerable quantity of breeding places for the
                        <hi rend="italic">Anopheles claviger,</hi> the mosquito whose bite conveys
                    the infection. Such are the various coast lagoons, formed at the mouths of
                    streams</p>
                <p>for lack of proper canalization, while much of the harm is also due to the
                    disforestation of the mountains, owing to which the rains collect in the upland
                    vaïíeys, and are brought down by violent torrents, carrying the soil with them,
                    and so impeding the proper drainage and irrigation of these valleys, and
                    encouraging the formation of un-healthy swamps; moreover, the climate has become
                    much more tropical in character. The mortality from malaria in 1902 was higher
                    than for any other part of Italy—1037 persons, or 154 per 100,000 (Basilicata,
                    141; Apulia, 104; Calabria, 77; Sicily, 76; province of Rome, 27).</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Customs and Dress.</hi> —The population of Sardinia appears
                    (though further investigation is desirable) to have belonged in ancient times,
                    and to belong at present, to the so-called Mediterranean race (see G. Sergi, <hi
                        rend="italic">La Sardegna,</hi> Turin, 1907). In the aeneolithic necropolis
                    of Anghelu Ruju, near Alghero, of 63 skulls, 53 bdongtothe“ Mediterranean"
                    dolico-mesocephalic type and 10to a Eurasian brachycephalic type of Asiatic
                    origin, which has been found in prehistoric tombs of other parts of Europe. The
                    race has probably suffered less here than in most parts of the Mediterranean
                    basin from foreign intermixture, except for a few Catalan and Genoese
                    settlements on the coast (Alghero and Carloforte are respectively the most
                    important of these); and the population in general seems to have deteriorated
                    slightly since prehistoric times, the average cranial capacity of the
                    prehistoric skulls from the Anghelu Ruju being 1490 c.c. for males and 1308 for
                    females, while among the modern population 60% of males and females together
                    fall below 1250 c.c.; and the stature is generally lower than in other parts of
                    Italy, as is shown by the measurements of the recruits (R. Livi, <hi
                        rend="italic">Antropοmetria Militare,</hi> Rome 1896). Anthropologists,
                    indeed, have recently observed a large proportion of individuals of
                    exceptionally small stature, not found in Sardinia only, but elsewhere in south
                    Italy also; though in Sardinia they are distributed over the whole island, and
                    especially in the southern half. In the province of Cagliari 29∙99% of the
                    recruits born in 1862 were under 5 ft. 1 in., and in that of Sassari 21∙99%, the
                    percentage for ten provinces of south Italy being 24·35. These small individuals
                    present apparently no other differences, and Sergi maintains that the difference
                    is racial, these being the descendants of a race of pygmies who had emigrated
                    from central Africa. But the lowness of stature extends to the lower
                    animals—cattle, horses, donkeys, &amp;amp;c.— and this may indicate that
                    climatic causes have some part in the matter also, though Sergi denies this.</p>
                <p>The dialects differ very much in different parts of the island, so that those who
                    speak one often cannot understand those who speak another, and use Italian as
                    the medium of communication. They contain a considerable number of Latin words,
                    which have remained unchanged. The two main dialects are that of the Logudoro in
                    the north and that of Cagliari in the south of the island.</p>
                <p>The native costumes also vary considerably. In the south-east they have largely
                    gone out of use, but elsewhere, especially in the mountainous districts, they
                    are still habitually worn. In the Barbargia the men have a white shirt, a black
                    or red waistcoat and black or red coat, often with open sleeves; the cut and
                    decorations of these vary considerably in the different districts. They have a
                    kind of short kilt, stiff, made of black wool, with a band from back to front
                    between the legs; under this they wear short linen trousers, which come a little
                    below the knee, and black woollen leggings with boots. They wear a black cap,
                    about 1½ ft. long, the end of which falls down over one side of the head. In
                    other districts the costume varies considerably, but the long cap is almost
                    universal. Thus at Ozieri the men wear ordinary jackets and trousers with a
                    velvet waistcoat; the shepherds of the Sulcis wear short black trousers without
                    kilt and heavy black sheepskin coats, and the two rows of waistcoat buttons are
                    generally silver or copper coins. The costume of the women is different (often
                    entirely so) in each village or district. Bright colours (especially red) are
                    frequent, and the white chemise is an integral part of the dress. The skirts are
                    usually of the native wool (called <hi rend="italic">orbacia).</hi> For widows
                    or deep mourning the peculiar cut of the local costume is preserved, but carried
                    out entirely in black. The native costume is passing out of use in many places
                    (especially among the women, whose costume is more elaborate than that of the
                    men), partly owing to the spread of modern ideas, partly owing to its cost; and
                    in the Campidano and in the mining districts it is now rarely seen. The curious
                    customs, too, of which older writers tell us, are gradually dying out. But the
                    festivals, especially those of mountain villages or of pilgrimage churches,
                    attract in the summer a great concourse of people, all in their local costumes.
                    There may be seen the native dances and break-neck horse-races— the riders
                    bareback—through the main street of the village. The people are generally
                    courteous and kindly, the island being still</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-24-s02-0212" facs="encyclopaediabri24chisrich_0229.jp2"/>
                <p>comparatively rarely visited by foreigners, while Italians seem to regard it as
                    almost a place of exile. They have the virtues and defects of a somewhat
                    isolated mountain race—a strong sense of honour and respect for women, of
                    hospitality towards the stranger, and a natural gravity and dignity, accompanied
                    by a considerable distrust of change and lack of enterprise. Despite their
                    poverty begging is practically unknown. The houses are often of one storey only.
                    Chimneys are unknown in the older houses; the hearth is in the centre of the
                    chief room, and the smoke escapes through the roof. In the mountain villages the
                    parish priest takes the lead among his people, and is not infrequently the most
                    important person.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Agriculture.</hi> —The rest of the island is mainly devoted to
                    agriculture; according to the statistics of 1901, 151,853 individuals out of a
                    total rural population of 708,034 <hi rend="italic">(i.e.</hi> deducting the
                    population of Cagliari and Sassari) are occupied in it. Of these 41,661
                    cultivate their own land, 15,408 are fixed tenants, 24,031 are regular
                    labourers, and no less than 72,753 day labourers; while there are 35,056
                    shepherds. Emigration is a comparatively new phenomenon in Sardinia, which began
                    only in 1896, but is gaining ground. A considerable proportion of the emigrants
                    are miners who proceed to Tunis, and remain only a few years, but emigration to
                    America is increasing.</p>
                <p>Much of the island is stony and unproductive; but cultivation has not been
                    extended nearly as much as would be possible, and the implements are primitive.
                    Where rational cultivation has been introduced, it has almost always been by
                    non-Sardinian capitalists. Two-fifths of the land belongs to the state, and
                    two-fifths more to the various communes; the remaining fifth is minutely
                    subdivided among a large number of small proprietors, many of whom have been
                    expropriated from inability to pay the taxes, which, considering the low value
                    of the land, are too heavy; while the state is unable to let a large proportion
                    of its lands. Comparatively little grain is now produced, whereas under the
                    republic Sardinia was one of the chief granaries of Rome. The Campidano and
                    other fertile spots, such as the so-called Ogliastra on the east side of the
                    island, inland of Tortoli, the neighbourhood of Oliena, Bosa, &amp;amp;c.,
                    produce a considerable quantity of wine, the sweet, strong, white variety called
                    Vernaccia, produced near Oristano, being especially noteworthy. Improved methods
                    are being adopted for protecting vines against disease, and the importation of
                    American vines has now ensured immunity against a repetition of former
                    disasters. The cultivation of the vine prevails far more in the province of
                    Cagliari than in that of Sassari, considerable progress having been made both in
                    the extent of land under cultivation and in the ratio of produce to area. The
                    entire island produced 28,613,000 gallons of wine in the year 1899 and
                    19,809,000 in 1900. In 1902 the production fell to 13,491,517 gallons; in 1903
                    it was 26,997,680; in 1904 it reached the phenomenal figure of 63,105,577
                    gallons, of which the province of Cagliari produced 53,995,362 gallons; in 1905
                    it fell to 36,700,000, of which the province of Cagliari produced 32,500,000
                    gallons. Though much land previously devoted to grain culture has been planted
                    with vines, the area under wheat, barley, beans and maize is still considerable.
                    Most of the soil, except the rugged mountain regions, is adapted to corn
                    growing. In 1896 the grain area was 380,000 acres, a slight diminution having
                    taken place since 1882. The yield of corn varies from six to ten times the
                    amount sown. In 1902 the total production of wheat in the island was 2,946,070
                    bushels, but in 1903 it rose to 4,823,800 bushels, in 1904 it fell to 4,015,020,
                    and in 1905 rose again to 4,351,987 bushels,/of the whole production of Italy.
                    The cultivation of olives is widespread in the districts of Sassari, Bosa,
                    Iglesias, Alghero and the Gallura. The government, to check the decrease of
                    olive culture in Sassari, has offered prizes for the grafting of wild olive
                    trees, of which vast numbers grow throughout the island. Tobacco, vegetables and
                    other garden produce are much cultivated ; cotton could probably be grown with
                    profit.</p>
                <p>The houses of the Campidano are mostly built of sun-dried unbaked bricks. The
                    ox-wagons with their solid wheels, and the curious water-wheels of brushwood
                    with earthenware pots tied on to them and turned by a blindfolded donkey, are
                    picturesque. Both European and African fruit trees grow in the island; there are
                    in</p>
                <p>glaces considerable orange groves, especially at Milis, to the north of</p>
                <p>Oristano. The olive oil produced is mainly mixed with that from Genoa or
                    Provence, and placed on the market under the name of the latter. Among the
                    natural flora may be noted the wild olive, the lentisk (from which oil is
                    extracted) the prickly pear, the myrtle, broom, cytisus, the juniper. Large
                    tracts of mountain are clothed with fragrant scrub composed of these and other
                        plants.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="2"> The <hi
                            rend="italic">herba Sardoa,</hi> said to cause the <hi rend="italic"
                            >risus Sardonicus</hi> (sardonic laugh), cannot be certainly identified
                        (Pausanias x. 17, 13). </note> The higher regions produce cork trees, oaks,
                    pines, chestnuts, &amp;amp;c., but the forests have been largely destroyed by
                    speculators, who burned the trees for charcoal and potash, purchasing them on a
                    large scale from the state. This occurred especially in the last half of the
                    19th century, largely owing to the abolition of the so-called <hi rend="italic"
                        >beni adem-privíli.</hi> These were lands over which, in distinction from
                    the other feudal lands, rights of pasture, cutting of wood, &amp;amp;c.
                    &amp;amp;c., existed. When, in 1837, the baronial fiefs were suppressed by
                    Charles Albert, and the land transferred to the state, the <hi rend="italic"
                        >ademprivio</hi> was maintained on the lands subject to it, and it was thus
                    to the interest of all that</p>
                <p>the woods should be maintained. In 1865, however, it was suppressed, and one half
                    of the <hi rend="italic">beni adempriυili</hi> was assigned to the state, the
                    other half being given to the communes, with the obligation of compensating
                    those who claimed rights over these lands. The state, which had already sold not
                    only a considerable part of the domain land, but a large part of the <hi
                        rend="italic">beni ademprivili,</hi> continued the process, and the forests
                    of Sardinia were sacrificed; and, as has been said, the necessity of
                    reafforestation, of the regulation of streams, and of irrigation<note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="3"> By the law of 1906
                        the state has not assumed the responsibility of the construction of
                        reservoirs for irrigation. </note> is urgent. Laws to secure this object
                    have been</p>
                <p>passed, but funds are Jacking for their execution on a sufficiently arge scale.
                    Another difficulty is that Italian and foreign capitalists, have produced a
                    great rise in prices which has not been compensated by a rise in wages. Native
                    capital is lacking, and taxation on un-remunerative lands is, as elsewhere in
                    Italy, too heavy in proportion to what they may be expected to produce, and not
                    sufficiently elastic in case of a bad harvest.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Live-Stock.—</hi> A considerable portion of Sardinia,
                    especially in the higher regions, is devoted to pasture. The native Sardinian
                    cattle are small, but make good draught oxen. A considerable amount of cheese is
                    manufactured, but largely by Italian capitalists. Sheep’s milk cheese <hi
                        rend="italic">(pecorino)</hi> is largely made, but sold as the Roman
                    product. Horses are bred to some extent, while the native race of donkeys is
                    remarkably small in size. Pigs, sheep and goats are also kept in considerable
                    numbers. Whereas in 1881 Sardinia was estimated to possess only 157,000 head of
                    cattle, 478,000 sheep and 165,000 goats, the numbers in 1896 had increased to
                    1,159,000 head of cattle, 4,960,000 sheep and 1,780,000 goats. The nomadic
                    system prevails in the island. Breeding is unregulated and natural selection
                    prevails. A more progressive form of pastoral industry is that of the <hi
                        rend="italic">tanche</hi> (enclosed holdings), in which the owner is both
                    agriculturist and cattle raiser. On these farms the cultivation of the soil and
                    the rearing of stock go hand in hand, to the great advantage of both.
                    Nevertheless the idea of the value of improving breeds is gaining ground. Good
                    cattle for breeding purposes are being imported from Switzerland and Sicily, and
                    efforts are likewise being made to improve the breed of horses, which are bought
                    mainly for the army. The opportunity of utilizing the wool for textile
                    industries has not yet been taken, though Sardinian women are accustomed to
                    weave strong and durable cloth. Everywhere capital and enterprise are lacking.
                    Agricultural products require perfecting and fitting for export.</p>
                <p>Of wild animals may be noted the moufflon <hi rend="italic">(Ovis Ammon),</hi>
                    the stag, and the wild boar, and among birds various species of the vulture and
                    eagle in the mountains, and the pelican and flamingo (the latter coming in
                    August in large flocks from Africa) in the lagoons.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Fisheries.</hi> —The tunny fishery is considerable; it is
                    centred principally in the south-west. The sardine fishery, which might also be
                    important, at present serves mainly for local consumption. Lobsters are
                    exported, especially to Paris. The coral fishery— mainly on the west coast—has
                    lost its former importance. Neither the tunny nor the coral fishery is carried
                    on by the Sardinians themselves, who are not sailors by nature; the former is in
                    the hands of Genoese and the latter of Neapolitans. The unhealthy lagoons
                    contain abundance of fish. The mountain streams often contain small but good
                    trout.</p>
                <p>In Roman times Sardinia, relatively somewhat more prosperous than at present,
                    though not perhaps greatly different as regards its products, was especially
                    noted as a grain-producing country. It is also spoken of as a pastoral country
                    (Diod. v. 15), but we do not hear anything of its wine. Solinus (4, § 4) speaks
                    of its mines of silver and iron, Suidas (<hi rend="italic">s.v.</hi>) of its
                    purple and tunny fisheries, Horace (<hi rend="italic">Ars</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">Poet.</hi> 375) of the bitterness of its honey. Pausanias (x.
                    17, § 12) mentions its immunity from wolves and poisonous snakes—which it still
                    enjoys,—but Solinus <hi rend="italic">(l.c.)</hi> mentions a poisonous spider,
                    called <hi rend="italic">solifuga,</hi> peculiar to the island.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Minerals.</hi> —The mining industry in Sardinia is confined in
                    the main to the south-western portion of the island. The mines were known to the
                    Carthaginians, as discoγeries of lamps, coins, &amp;amp;c. (now in the museum at
                    Cagliari), testify. The Roman workings too, to judge from similar finds, seem to
                    have been considerable. The centre of the mining district <hi rend="italic"
                        >(Metalla</hi> of the itineraries) was probably about 5 m. south of
                    Fluminimaggiore, in a locality known as Antas, where are the remains of a Roman
                    temple <hi rend="italic">(Corpus Inscr. Lat.</hi> x. 7539), dedicated to an
                    emperor, probably Commodus—but the inscription is only in part preserved. A pig
                    of lead found near Fluminimaggiore bears the imprint <hi rend="italic">Imp.
                        Caes. Hadr.·Aug. (CLL.</hi> x. 8073, 1, 2). After the fall of the Roman
                    Empire the workings remained abandoned until the days of the Pisan
                        supremacy,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="4"> The
                        Pisan workings are only distinguished from the Roman by the character of the
                        small objects (lamps, coins, &amp;c.) found in them. </note> and were again
                    given up under the Spanish government, especially after the discovery of
                    America. When the island passed to Savoy, in 1720, the mines passed to the
                    state. The government let the mines to contractors for forty years and then took
                    them over; but in the period from 1720 to 1840 only 14,620 tons of galena were
                    extracted and 2772 of lead. In 1840 the freedom of mining was introduced,</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-24-s02-0213" facs="encyclopaediabri24chisrich_0230.jp2"/>
                <p>the state giving perpetual concessions in return for 3 % of the gross production.
                    In 1904-1905, 14,188 workmen were employed in the mines of the province of
                    Cagliari. The following table (from the consular report of 1905) shows the
                    amount and value of the minerals extracted, the whole amount being exported:</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Zinc—</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Tons.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Value £.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Calamine .</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>99,749</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>466,070</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Blende</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>26,051</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>I35,569</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Lead.....</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>24,798</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>140,534</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Silver.....</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>167</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>5,012</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Manganese .</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>2,362</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>3,360</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Antimony</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>1,005</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>4,700</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Lignite ....</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>15,429</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>8,778</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Anthracite</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>577</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>586</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Copper ....</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>98</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>445</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>170,236</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>765.054</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>The chief mines are those of Gennamare and Ingurtosu and others of the group
                    owned by the Pertusola Company, Monteponi and Montevecchio. The mining and
                    washing plant is extremely good and largely constructed at Cagliari. The most
                    important minerals are lead and zinc, obtained in lodes in the forms of galena
                    and calamine respectively. In most cases, owing to the mountainous character of
                    the country, horizontal galleries are possible. The Monteponi Company smelts its
                    own zinc, but the lead is almost all smelted at the furnaces of Pertusola near
                    Spezia. Silver has also been found in the district of Sarrabus, iron at S. Leone
                    to the west of Cagliari, and antimony and other metals near Lanusei, but in
                    smaller quantities than in the Iglesias district, so that comparatively little
                    mining has as yet been done there. Lignite is also mined at Bacu Abis, near
                    Gonnesa, and Anthracite in small quantities near Seui.</p>
                <p>The salt-pans at Cagliari and of Carloforte are of considerable importance; they
                    are let by the government to contractors, who have the sole right of
                    manufacture, but are bound to sell the salt necessary for Sardinian consumption
                    at 35 centesimi (3½d.) per cwt.; the government does not exercise the salt
                    monopoly in Sardinia any more than in Sicily, but in the latter island the right
                    of manufacture is unrestricted. The total production in 1905 was 149,431 tons;
                    the average price of salt for the island in 1905 was 2½d. per cwt. (unground),
                    and is. per cwt. ground; whereas for Italy, where the government monopoly
                    exists, the price is £1, 12s. the cwt.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Commerce.—</hi> The total exports of the province of Cagliari
                    in 1905 attained a value of £1,388,735, of which £550,023 was foreign trade,
                    while the imports amounted to £1,085,514, of which £360,758 was foreign trade.
                    Among the exports may be noticed minerals, wines and spirits, tobacco, hides,
                    live animals; and among the imports, groceries, cotton and cereals. The tonnage
                    of the shipping entering and clearing the ports of the province in 1905 was
                    1,756,866, of which 352,992 was foreign.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Communications.—</hi> The railway system of Sardinia is in the
                    hands of two companies—the Compagnia Reale delle Ferrovie Sarde, and the
                    Compagnia delle Ferrovie Secondarie della Sardegna. The former company’s lines
                    (of the ordinary gauge) run from Cagliari, past Macomer, to Chilivani (with a
                    branch at Decimomannu for Iglesias and Monteponi). From Chilivani the line to
                    Sassari and Porto Torres diverges to the N.W., and that to Golfo degli Aranci to
                    the N.E. The latter company owns narrow-gauge lines from Cagliari to Mandas
                    (whence lines diverge N. to Sorgono and E. to Tortoli, the latter having a short
                    branch from Gairo to Ierzu), from Macomer E. to Nuoro and W. to Bosa, from
                    Sassari S.W. to Alghero, from Chilivani S. to Tirso (on the line between Macomer
                    and Nuoro), and from Monti (on the line from Chilivani to Golfo degli Aranci)
                    N.W. to Tempio. In the south-western portion of the island are several private
                    railways belonging to various mining companies, of which the lines from
                    Monteponi to Portoscuso, and from S. Gavino to Montevecchio, are sometimes
                    available for ordinary passengers. There is also a steam tramway from Cagliari
                    to Quartu S. Elena. The trains are few and the speed on all these lines is
                    moderate, but the gradients are often very heavy.</p>
                <p>Communication is thus most wanted with the northern and south-eastern extremities
                    of the island, and between Tortoli and Nuoro, and Nuoro and Golfo degli Aranci.
                    The main road system, which dates from 1828, previous to which there were only
                    tracks, is good, and the roads well engineered; many of them are traversed daily
                    by post vehicles. Some road motor services have been instituted. The total
                    length of the railways is 602 m., and of the roads of all classes 3101 m., <hi
                        rend="italic">i.e.</hi> 596 yds. per sq. m.</p>
                <p>There is daily steam communication (often interrupted in bad weather) with
                    Civitavecchia from Golfo degli Aranci (the mail route), and weekly steamers run
                    from Cagliari to Naples, Genoa (via the east coast of the island), Palermo and
                    Tunis, and from Porto Torres to Genoa (calling at Bastia in Corsica and Leghorn)
                    and Leghorn direct. A fortnightly line also runs along the west coast of the
                    island from Cagliari to Porto Torres. All these lines (and also the minor lines
                    from Golfo degli Aranci to La Maddalena and from Carloforte to Porto Vesme and
                    Calasetta) are in the hands of the Navigazione Generale Italiana, there being no
                    Sardinian steamship companies. There is also a weekly French service between
                    Porto Torres and Ajaccio in Corsica.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Administration.—</hi> Sardinia is divided into two provinces—
                    Cagliari and Sassari; the chief towns of the former (with their communal
                    population in 1901) are: Cagliari (53,057); Iglesias (20,874); Quartu S. Elena
                    (8510), really a large village; Oristano (7107); Fluminimaggiore (9647); Lanusei
                    (3250); and the total population of the province is 486,767: while the chief
                    towns of the latter are Sassari (38,053); Alghero (10,741); Ozieri (9555); Nuoro
                    (7051); Tempio Pausania (14,573); Terranova Pausania (4348); Porto Torres
                    (4225); and the total population of the province 309,026. The density of
                    population is 85∙38 per sq. m. (294∙55 for the whole of Italy), by far the
                    lowest figure of any part of Italy.</p>
                <p>The archiepiscopal sees of the island are: Cagliari (under which are the
                    suffragan sees of Galtelli-Nuoro, Iglesias and Ogliastra), Oristano (with the
                    suffragan see of Ales and Terralba) and Sassari (under which are the suffragan
                    sees of Alghero, Ampurias and Tempio, Bisarchio and Bosa). The number of
                    monastic institutions in the island is very small.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Education.—</hi> The number of scholars in the elementary
                    schools for 1901-1902 was 59·09 per 1000 (Calabria 42∙27, Tuscany 67∙09,
                    Piedmont 118·00); the teachers are 1∙34 per 1000, a total of 1084 of both sexes
                    (among whom only one priest) (Calabria 1∙18, Tuscany 1∙29, Piedmont 2∙0), while
                    the rural schools are not buildings adapted for their purpose. In some of the
                    towns, however, and especially at Iglesias, they are good modern buildings.
                    Still, the percentage of those unable to read and write is 72∙8, while for the
                    whole of Italy it is 56∙0. The male scholars at the secondary schools amounted
                    in 190o to 2∙74 per 1000 inhabitants. The university of Cagliari, which in
                    1874-1875 had only 60 students, had 260 in 1902-1903. At Sassari in the same
                    year there were 162. There are besides in the island 10 gymnasia, 3 lycées, 6
                    technical and nautical schools and institutes (including a school of mines at
                    Iglesias), and 9 other institutes for various branches of special education. A
                    tendency is growing up towards the extension of technical and commercial
                    education in place of the exclusively classical instruction hitherto imparted.
                    To the growth of this tendency the excellent results of the agricultural schools
                    have especially contributed.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Crime.—</hi> For the years 1897-1901 statistics show that
                    Sardinia has more thefts and frauds than any other region of Italy (1068·15 for
                    Sardinia and 210·56 per 100,000 inhabitants per annum for the rest of Italy).
                    This is no doubt accounted for by the extreme poverty which prevails among the
                    lower classes, though beggars, on the other hand, are very few, the convictions
                    being 8∙95 per 100,000 against 258·15 per 100,000 for the province of Rome.
                    Sardinia has less convictions for serious crimes than any other <hi
                        rend="italic">compartimenta</hi> of south Italy. Public security is
                    considerably improved, and regular brigandage (as distinct from casual robbery)
                    hardly exists. The vendetta, too, is now hardly ever heard of.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Finance.—</hi> In 1887 a severe banking crisis occurred in
                    Sardinia. Though harmful to the economic condition of the island, it left
                    agriculture comparatively unaffected, because the insolvent institutions had
                    never fulfilled the objects of their foundation. Agricultural credit operations
                    in Sardinia are carried on by the Bank of Italy, which, however, displays such
                    caution that its action is almost imperceptible. An agricultural loan and credit
                    company has been formed on the ruins of the former institutions, but hitherto no
                    charter has been granted it. Institutions possessing a special character are the
                        <hi rend="italic">monti frumentarii,</hi> public grain deposits, founded for
                    the purpose of supplying peasant proprietors with seed corn, debts being paid in
                    kind with interest after harvest. But they, too, lack funds sufficient to assure
                    extensive and efficient working, even after the law of 1906. Meantime much evil
                    arises from usury in the poorer districts. It is estimated that Sardinia pays,
                    in local and</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-24-s02-0214" facs="encyclopaediabri24chisrich_0231.jp2"/>
                <p>general, direct and indirect taxation of all kinds, 23,000,000 lire (£920,000), a
                    sum corresponding to 35*44 lire per head.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">History and Archaeology.—</hi> The early history of Sardinia is
                    entirely unknown.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="5"> It
                        has been widely believed that the Shardana, who occur as foreign mercenaries
                        in Egypt from the time of Rameses 11. downwards, are to be identified with
                        the Sardinians; but the question is uncertain. There were certainly no
                        Egyptian colonies in Sardinia; the Egyptian objects and their imitations
                        found in the island were brought there by the Phoenicians (W. H. Roscher,
                            <hi rend="italic">Lexikon der griechischen und römischen
                            Mythologie,</hi> ii. 392). </note> The various accounts of Greek writers
                    of the early colonizations of the island cannot be accepted, and it appears
                    rather to have been the case that though there were various schemes formed by
                    Greeks for occupying it or parts of it <hi rend="italic">(e.g.</hi> that
                    recorded by Herodotus i. 170, when it was proposed, after the capture of Phocaea
                    and Teos in 545 b.c., that the remainder of the Ionian Greeks should emigrate to
                    Sardinia) none of them ever came to anything.</p>
                <p>On the other hand, the island contains a very large number of important
                    prehistoric monuments, belonging to the Bronze Age, during which it must have
                    been comparatively well populated. The most conspicuous and important of these
                    are the <hi rend="italic">nuraghi</hi> (the word is said to be a corruption of
                        <hi rend="italic">muraglie, i.e.</hi> large walls, but it is more probably a
                    native word). Of</p>
                <p>these there are, as has been estimated, as many as 6000 still traceable in the
                    island. The nuraghe in its simplest form is a circular tower about 30 ft. in
                    diameter at the base and decreasing in diameter as it ascends; it is built of
                    rough blocks of stone, as a rule about 2 ft. high (though this varies with the
                    material employed); they are not mortared together, but on the inside, at any
                    rate, the gaps between them were often filled with clay. The entrance almost
                    in-variably faces south, and measures, as a rule, 5 or 6 ft. in height by 2 in.
                    width. The architrave is flat, and there is a space over it, serving both to
                    admit light and to relieve the pressure on it from above, and the size decreases
                    slightly from the bottom to the top. Within the doorway is, as a rule, a niche
                    on the right, and a staircase ascending in the thickness of the wall to the
                    left; in front is another similar doorway leading to the chamber in the
                    interior, which is circular, and about 15 ft. in diameter; it has two or three
                    niches, and a conical roof formed by the gradual inclination of the walls to the
                    centre. It is lighted by the two doorways already mentioned. The staircase leads
                    either to a platform on the top of the nuràghe or, more frequently, to a second
                    chamber concentric with the first, lighted by a window which faces, as a rule,
                    in the same direction as the main doorway. A third chamber above the second does
                    not often occur. The majority perhaps of the nuraghi of Sardinia present this
                    simple type; but a very large number, and, among them, those best preserved,
                    have considerable additions. The construction varies with the site, obviously
                    with a view to the best use of the ground from a strategic point of view. Thus,
                    there may be a platform round the nuraghe, generally with two, three or four
                    bastions, each often containing a chamber; or the main nuraghe may have
                    additional chambers added to it. In a few cases, indeed, we find very
                    complicated systems of fortification—a wall of circum-vallation with towers at
                    the corners, protecting a small settlement of nuraghe-like buildings, as in the
                    case of the Nuraghe Losa near Abbasanta and the Nuraghe Saurecci near
                        Guspini;<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="6"> In
                        neither of these cases have the subsidiary buildings been fully traced out.
                        The plan of the former is given by Pinza <hi rend="italic">(op. cit.),</hi>
                        and that of the latter by La Marmora <hi rend="italic">(op. cit.).</hi> The
                        latter seen from a distance resembles a medieval castle crowning a hill-top.
                    </note> or, as in the</p>
                <p>Nuraghe Lugheras near Paulilatino, or the Nuraghe de S'Orcu near Domusnovas, the
                    entrance may be protected by a regular system of courtyards and subsidiary
                    nuraghi. Roughness of construction cannot be regarded as a proof of antiquity,
                    inasmuch as in some cases we find the additions less well built than the
                    original nuraghe; and it is often clear from the careful work at points where it
                    was necessary that the lack of finer construction was often simply economy of
                    labour. That the simpler forms, on the other hand, preceded those of more
                    complicated plan is probable. The manner of their arrangement seems to indicate
                    clearly that they were intended to be fortified habitations, not tombs or
                    temples. The niche at the entrance, which is rarely wanting, served, no doubt,
                    for the sentry on guard</p>
                <p>and would be on the unprotected side of any one coming in ; the door, t∞, is
                    narrow and low, and closed from within. The approach is, as we have seen, often
                    guarded by additional constructions; the fact that the door and window face
                    south is another argument in favour of this theory, and the access from one part
                    of the interior to another is sometimes purposely rendered difficult by a sudden
                    vertical rise of 5 or 6 ft. in the stairs; while the objects found in them—
                    household pottery, &amp;amp;c.—and near them (in some cases silos containing
                    carbonized grain and dolia) point to the same conclusion. Numer-ous fragments of
                    obsidian arrow-heads and chips are also found in and near them all over the
                    island. The only place where obsidian is known to be found in Sardinia in a
                    natural state is the Punta Trebina, a mountain south-east of Oristano. The
                    choice of site, too, is decisive. Sometimes they occupy the approaches to
                    tablelands, the narrowest points of gorges, or the fords of rivers; sometimes
                    almost inaccessible mountain tops or important points on ridges; and it may be
                    noticed that, where two important nuraghi are not visible from one another, a
                    small one is interpolated, showing that there was a system of signalling from
                    one to another. Or again, a group of them may occupy a fertile plain, a river
                    valley or a tableland,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                        n="7"> Those of the Giara are fully described by A. Taramelli and F.
                        Nissardi in <hi rend="italic">Monumenti dei Lincei,</hi> vol. xviii.;
                        Nissardi’s map of the Nurra, published by G. Pinza, ibid. vol. xi. sqq., may
                        also be consulted. </note> or they may stand close to the seashore.
                    Generally there is, if possible, a water-supply in the vicinity; sometimes a
                    nuraghe guards a spring, or there may be a well in the nuraghe itself.</p>
                <p>A final argument is the existence in some cases of a village of circular stone
                    buildings of similar construction to the nuraghi, but only 15 to 25 ft. in
                    diameter, at the foot of a nuraghe, which, like the baronial castle of a
                    medieval town, towered above the settlement.</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-24-s02-0215" facs="encyclopaediabri24chisrich_0234.jp2"/>
                <p>They are distributed over the whole island, but are perhaps most frequent towards
                    the centre and in the Nurra. They seem to be almost entirely lacking in the
                    north-east extremity, near Terranova, and in the mountains immediately to the
                    north of Iglesias, though they are found to the north of the Perda de sa Mesa.
                    In the district of Gennargentu they occur, rarely, as much as 3600 ft. above
                    sea-level. The tombs of their inhabitants are of two classes— the so-called <hi
                        rend="italic">tombe dei giganti,</hi> or giants’ tombs, and the <hi
                        rend="italic">domus de gianas,</hi> or houses of the spirits. The former are
                    generally found close to, or at least in sight of, the nuraghe to which they
                    belong. They consist of a chamber about 3⅛ ft. or less in height and width, with
                    the sides slightly inclined towards one another, and from 30 to 40 ft., or even
                    more, in length ; the sides are composed sometimes of slabs, sometimes of rough
                    walling, while the roof is composed of flat slabs; and the bodies were probably
                    disposed in a sitting position. At the front is a large slab, sometimes carved,
                    with a small aperture in it, through which offerings might be inserted. On each
                    side of this is a curve formed of two rows of</p>
                <p>slabs or two small walls ; the semicircular space thus formed has a diameter of
                    about 45 ft., and was probably intended for sacrifices. The tomb proper was no
                    doubt covered with a mound of earth, which has in most cases disappeared. Close
                    to these tombs smaller round enclosures, about 4 ft. in diameter, covered with a
                    heap of stones, like a small cairn, may sometimes be seen; these were possibly
                    intended for the burial of slaves or less important members of the tribe.
                    Dolmens (probably to be regarded as a simpler form of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >tomba dei giganti,</hi> inasmuch as specimens with chambers elongated after
                    their first construction have been found) and menhirs are also present in
                    Sardinia, though the former are very rare—that known as Sa Perda e S’altare,
                    near the railway to the south of Macomer is illustrated by A. Taramelli in <hi
                        rend="italic">Bullettino di Paleoetnologia,</hi> xxxii. (1906), 268, but
                    there are others. The latter, however, are widely distributed over the island,
                    being especially frequent in the central and most inaccessible part. The <hi
                        rend="italic">domus de gianas,</hi> on the other hand, resemble closely the
                    rock tombs of the prehistoric cemeteries of Sicily. They are small grottos cut
                    in the rock. We thus have two classes of tombs in connexion with the nuraghi,
                    and if these were to be held to be tombs also, habitations would be entirely
                        wanting.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="8"> The
                        whole question is well dealt with by F. Nissardi in <hi rend="italic">Atti
                            del Congresso delle</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">Scienze</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">Storiche</hi> (Rome,. 1903), vol. v. <hi rend="italic"
                            >(Archeologia),</hi> 651 sqq.;cf. <hi rend="italic">Builder,</hi> May
                        18, 1907 (xcii. 589), </note></p>
                <p>Among the most curious relics of the art of the period is a group of bronze
                    statuettes, some found at Uta near Cagliari and others near Teti, west of Fonni,
                    in the centre of the island, of which many specimens are now preserved in the
                    museum at Cagliari.</p>
                <p>It is thus clear that in the Bronze Age Sardinia was fairly thickly populated
                    over by far the greater part of its extent; this may explain the lack of Greek
                    colonies, except for Olbia, the modern Terranova, and Neapolis on the west
                    coast, which must from their names have been Greek, though we do not know when
                    or by whom they were founded. Pausanias (x. 17. 5) attributes the foundation of
                    Olbia to the Thespians and Athenians under Iolaus, while Solinus (i. 61) states
                    that he founded other cities also. In any case the Phoenician settlements are
                    the earliest of which we have any accurate knowledge. The date of the conquest
                    by</p>
                <p>Carthage may perhaps be fixed at about 500-480 b.c., following the chronology of
                    Justin Martyr (xviii. 7), inasmuch as up till that period colonization by the
                    Greeks seems to have been regarded as a possible enterprise. The cities which
                    they founded —Cornus, Tharros, Sulci, Nora, Carales— are all on the coast of the
                    island, and it is doubtful to what extent they penetrated into the interior.
                    Even in the 1st century B.c. there were still traces of Phoenician influence
                    (Cicero, <hi rend="italic">Pro Scauro,</hi> 15, 42, 45). There are signs of
                    trade with Etruria as early as the 7th century b.c. The Carthaginians made it
                    into an important grain-producing centre; and the Romans set foot in the island
                    more than once during the First Punic War.</p>
                <p>In 238 B.c. the Carthaginian mercenaries revolted, and the Romans took advantage
                    of the fact to demand that the island should be given up to them, which was
                    done.</p>
                <p>The native tribes opposed the Romans, but were conquered after several campaigns;
                    the island became a province under the government of a <hi rend="italic"
                        >praetor</hi> or <hi rend="italic">propraetor,</hi> to whose jurisdiction
                    Corsica was added soon afterwards. A rebellion in 215 B.c., fostered by the
                    Carthaginians, was quelled by T. Manlius Torquatus (Livy xxiii. 40). After this
                    the island began to furnish considerable supplies of corn; it was treated as a
                    conquered country, not containing a single free city, and the inhabitants were
                    obliged to pay a tithe in corn and a further money contribution. It was classed
                    with Sicily and Africa as one of the main</p>
                <p>sources of the corn-supply of Rome. There were salt-works in Sardinia too as
                    early as about 150 B.c., as is attested by an inscription assigned to this date
                    in Latin, Greek and Punic, being a dedication by one Cleon salari(us) soc(iorum)
                    s(ervus) <hi rend="italic">(Corp. Inscr. Lat.</hi> x. 7856). We only hear of two
                    insurrections of the mountain tribes, in 181, when no less than 80,000 Sardinian
                        slaves<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="9"> The large
                        number of slaves is said to have given rise to the phrase <hi rend="italic"
                            >Sardi venales</hi> for anything cheap or worthless. </note> were
                    brought to Rome by T. Sempronius Gracchus, and in 114 B.c., when M. Caecilius
                    Metellus was proconsul and earned a triumph after two years’ fighting: but even
                    in the time of Strabo there was considerable brigandage. Inscriptions record the
                    boundaries of the territories of various tribes with outlandish names otherwise
                    unknown to us <hi rend="italic">(Corp. Inscr. Lat.</hi> x. 7889. 7930).</p>
                <p>Some light is thrown on the condition and administration of the island in the 1st
                    century B.c. by Cicero’s speech (of which a part only is preserved) in defence
                    of M. Aemilius Scaurus (q.v.), praetor in 53 B.c. Cicero, speaking no doubt to
                    his brief, gives them a very bad character, adding “ ignoscent alii viri boni ex
                    Sardinia; credo enim esse quosdam ” (§ 43). In the division of provinces made
                    by</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-24-s02-0216" facs="encyclopaediabri24chisrich_0235.jp2"/>
                <p>Augustus, Sardinia and Corsica fell to the share of the senate, but in A.D. 6,
                    Augustus, owing to the frequent disturbances, took them over and placed them
                    under a <hi rend="italic">praefectus.</hi> Tiberius sent 4000 Jewish and
                    Egyptian freedmen to the island to bring the brigands to submission (Tac. <hi
                        rend="italic">Ann.</hi> ii. 85). Later on two cohorts were quartered there
                    and also detachments of the <hi rend="italic">Classis Misenas,</hi> as the
                    discharge certificates <hi rend="italic">(tabulae honestae missionis)</hi> of
                    the former and tombstones of the latter found in the island<note anchored="true"
                        place="bottom" type="authorial" n="10"> The discharge certificates of
                        sailors from the <hi rend="italic">Classis Misenas</hi> and <hi
                            rend="italic">Classis Ravennatis</hi> belonged to Sardinians who had
                        returned home after service in those fleets. </note> show (C.I.L. x. 777).
                    InA.D. 67 Nero restored Sardinia to the senate (but not Corsica) in exchange for
                    Achaea, and the former was then governed by a <hi rend="italic">legatus pro
                        praetore;</hi> but Vespasian took it over again before a.d. 78, and placed
                    it under an imperial <hi rend="italic">procurator</hi> as <hi rend="italic"
                        >praefectus.</hi> It returned to the senate, not before A.n. 83 but
                    certainly before the reign of M. Aurelius, when we find it governed by a
                    proconsul, as it was under Commodus; the latter, or perhaps Septimius Severus,
                    took it over again and placed it under a <hi rend="italic">procurator</hi> as
                        <hi rend="italic">praefectus</hi> once more (D. Vaglieri in <hi
                        rend="italic">Notizie degli scaυi,</hi> 1897, 280).</p>
                <p>A bronze tablet discovered in 1866 near the village of Esterzili is inscribed
                    with a decree of the time of Otho with regard to the boundaries of three tribes,
                    the Gallienses, Patulienses and Campani, who inhabited the eastern portion of
                    the island. The former tribe had crossed the boundaries of the other two, and
                    was ordered to with-draw immediately under pain of punishment <hi rend="italic"
                        >(Corp. iηscr. Lat.</hi> x. 7852). Carales was the only city with Roman
                    civic rights in Sardinia in PIiny's time (when it received the privilege is
                    unknown) and by far the most important place in the island; a Roman colony had
                    been founded at Turns Libisonis (Porto Torres) and others, later on, at Usellis
                    and Cornus.</p>
                <p>We hear little of the island under the Empire, except as a granary and as
                    remarkable for its unhealthiness and the audacity of its brigands. It was not
                    infrequently used as a place of exile.</p>
                <p>A number of Roman towns are known to us. Besides those already mentioned,
                    including the Phoenician cities (all of which continued to exist in Roman days)
                    the most important were Bosa <hi rend="italic">(q.v.),</hi> Forum Traiani (mod.
                    Fordungianus) <hi rend="italic">(q.v.),</hi> Neapolis and Othoca (mod. Oristano,
                        <hi rend="italic">q.v.).</hi> An interesting group of Roman houses was found
                    in 1878 at Bacu Abis, 5 m. W. of Iglesias, but has been covered up again (F.
                    Vivanet in <hi rend="italic">Notizie degli scavi,</hi> 1878, 271). The name
                    Barbaria for the mountainous district in the east centre of Sardinia, in the
                    district of Nuoro, which still exists in the form Barbargia, goes back to the
                    Roman period, the <hi rend="italic">ciυitates Barbariae</hi> being mentioned in
                    an inscription of the time of Tiberius <hi rend="italic">(Corp. inscr. Lat.</hi>
                    xiv. 2954). The Barbaricini are mentioned in the 6th century A.D. by Procopius,
                    who wrongly derives the name from several thousand Moors and Numidians who were
                    banished to the island by the Vandal kings, while Gregory the Great speaks of
                    them in a letter (iv. 23) to Hospito, their chief, as a still pagan race,
                    worshipping stocks and stones. The towns were connected by a</p>
                <p>considerable network of roads, with a total length of 958 Roman miles according
                    to the Itineraries, the most important of which ran from Carales to Tunis
                    Libisonis (Porto Torres) through the centre of the island, passing Othoca
                    (Oristano) and</p>
                <p>Forum Traiani. Its line is followed closely by the modern highroad and railway. A
                    portion of its course, however, between Forum Traiani and the modern Abbasanta,
                    is not so followed, and is still well preserved. Its width is as a rule about 24
                    ft.; at present its surface is formed of rough cobbling, upon which there was
                    probably a gravel layer, now washed away. Several milestones belonging to it
                    have been discovered, including one of the time of Augustus and one of Claudius
                    near Forum Traiani, and one of Nero near Turris Libisonis, though it was
                    probably not completed right through until a later period (T. Mommsen in <hi
                        rend="italic">Corp. inscr. Lat.</hi> x. 833 ; cf. <hi rend="italic">Eph.
                        epigr.</hi> νiii. 181-183). A branch from this road ran to Olbia (followed
                    closely by the modern highroad and railway also), and was perhaps the main line
                    of communication, though the itineraries state that the road from Carales to
                    Olbia ran through the centre of the island by Biora, Valentia, Sorabile (near
                    Fonni) and Caput Thyrsi.</p>
                <p>Many milestones belonging to the road from Carales to Olbia have been found, but
                    all but one of them (which was seen at Valentia) belong to the portion of the
                    road within 12 m. of the latter place, so that they might belong to either line
                    (see Olbia). The distance seems to be identical by either route. The itineraries
                    give it as 176 m.— the exact distance in English miles by the modern railway.
                    The difference between English and Roman miles would be compensated for by the
                    more devious course taken by the railway. Turris Libisonis was also connected
                    with Othoca by a road along the west coast, passing through Tharros, Cornus and
                    Bosa ; this road went on to Tibula<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial" n="11"> Excavations made in 1880 at Tibula and Sorabile
                        resulted in the discovery at the former of a necropolis of the late Empire,
                        in which the dead were buried in long amphorae, while at the latter Roman
                        baths were explored (F. Vivanet in <hi rend="italic">Notizie degli
                            scavi,</hi> 1879, 350; 1881, 29 sqq.). </note> (Capo della Testa) at the
                    north extremity of the island and so by the coast to Olbia. From Tibula another
                    road ran inland to join the road from Carales to Olbia some 16 m. west of the
                    latter.</p>
                <p>Carales was also connected with Olbia by a road along the east coast. The
                    south-west corner of the island was served by a direct road from Carales
                    westward through Decimomannu (note the name Decimo, a survival, no doubt, of a
                    Roman post-station <hi rend="italic">ad decimum lapidem),</hi> where there is a
                    fine Roman bridge over 100 yds. long of fourteen arches, still well preserved.
                    The width of the roadway is only 11 ft. There is also a road through Nora and
                    along the coast past Sulci to Metalla and Neapolis, and thence to Othoca.</p>
                <p>After the time of Constantine, the administration of Sardinia was separated from
                    that of Corsica, each island being governed by a <hi rend="italic">praeses</hi>
                    dependent on the <hi rend="italic">vicarius urbis Romae.</hi></p>
                <p>In 456 it was seized by Genseric. It was retaken for a short time by
                    Marcellianus, but was not finally recovered until the fall of the Vandal kingdom
                    in Africa in 534, by Cyril. In 551 it was taken by Totila, but reconquered after
                    his death by Narses for the Byzantine Empire. Under Byzantium it remained
                    nominally until the 10th century, when we find the chief magistrate still
                    bearing the title of αpχωv.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                        n="12"> Three inscriptions of the middle of this century, set up by the <hi
                            rend="italic">άρχων ∑apbnvia.z</hi> with the title <hi rend="italic"
                            >protospatarius,</hi> are illustrated by A. Taramelli in <hi
                            rend="italic">Notizie degli scavi</hi> (1906), 123 sqq.; cf. <hi
                            rend="italic">Archivio storico Sardo</hi> (1907), 92 ; and there are a
                        few churches of the Byzantine period and style, a considerable number of
                        Byzantine inscriptions, dedications to Greek saints, and other traces of the
                        influence of the Eastern Empire in the island. </note></p>
                <p>In the 8th century<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="13">
                        Some authorities attribute to 774, others to 817, a donation of Sardinia to
                        the papacy; we hearof Pope Nicholas I. sending legates in 865 to quell
                        disturbances and check evil practices in the island. </note> (720) the
                    period of Saracen invasion began; but the Saracens never secured a firm footing
                    in the island. In 725 Luidprand purchased and removed to Pavia the body of St
                    Augustine of Hippo from Cagliari, whither it had been brought in the 6th century
                    by the exiled bishop of Hippo. In 815 Sardinia submitted to Louis the Pious,
                    begging for his protection;<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                        n="14"> There is no authentic history for the intervening period; the famous
                        “ pergamene d’Arborea,” published by P. Martini in 1863 at Cagliari, have
                        been shown to be modern forgeries. </note> but the Saracens were not
                    entirely driven out, and about A.D. 1000 the Saracen chief Musat established
                    himself in Cagliari. Pope John XVIII. preached a crusade in 1004, promising to
                    bestow the island (when or whether it had ever definitely passed into the power
                    of the papacy is not absolutely clear) upon whoever should drive out the
                    Saracens. The Pisans took up the challenge, and Musat was driven out of Cagliari
                    with the help of the Genoese in 1022 for the third time. The Pisans and Genoese
                    now disputed about the ownership of Sardinia, but the pope and the emperor
                    decided in favour of Pisa. Musat returned to the island once more and made
                    himself master of it, but was defeated and taken prisoner under the walls of
                    Cagliari in 1050, when the dominion of Pisa was established.</p>
                <p>The island had (probably since the end of the 9th century) been divided into four
                    districts—Cagliari, Arborea, Torres (or Logudoro) and Gallura—each under a <hi
                        rend="italic">giudice or</hi> judge, in whom the dignity became hereditary.
                        <hi rend="italic">Judices</hi> are already mentioned as existing in the
                    account of the mission sent by Nicholas I. in 864 (Duchesne, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Liber pontificalls,</hi> ii. 162), as though the single authority of the
                    Byzantine <hi rend="italic">αρχωv</hi> was already weakened. The three <hi
                        rend="italic">άρχοντες</hi> who appear in the 10th-century inscriptions just
                    mentioned bear alternately the names Torcotorius and Salusius; and, inasmuch as
                    this is the case with the <hi rend="italic">judices</hi> of Cagliari from the
                    11th to the 13th century, there seems no doubt that they were the successors of
                    these Byzantine <hi rend="italic">άρχοντες,</hi> who were perhaps the actual
                    founders of the dynasty. These names, indeed, continue even after the Pisan
                    family of Lacon-Massa had by marriage succeeded to the judicature. The Greek
                    language occurs in their official seals down to the 13th century. Intermarriage
                    (sometimes illicit) was apparently freely used by the dominant families for the
                    concentration of their power. Thus we find that after the failure of Musat
                    members of the family of Lacon-Unali filled all the four judicatures of the
                    island (Taramelli, <hi rend="italic">Arch. slor. Sard., cit.</hi> 105). In the
                    continual struggles between Pisa and Genoa some of these princes took the side
                    of the latter. In 1164 Barisone, <hi rend="italic">giudice</hi> of Arborea, was
                    given the title of king of the whole island by Frederick Barbarossa, but his
                    supremacy was never effective. In 1241 Adelasia, heiress of Gallura and
                    Logudoro, was married as her third husband to Enzio, the natural son of
                    Frederick II., who received the title of king of Sardinia from his father, but
                    fell into the hands of the Bolognese in 1249, and</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-24-s02-0217" facs="encyclopaediabri24chisrich_0236.jp2"/>
                <p>remained a prisoner at Bologna until his death. After this the Pisan supremacy of
                    the island seems to have become more of a reality, but Arborea remained
                    independent, and after the defeat of the Pisans by the Genoese at the naval
                    battle of Meloria in 1284 they were obliged to surrender Sassari and Logudoro to
                    Genoa. In 1297 Boniface VIII. invested James II., the king of Aragon, with
                    Sardinia; but it was not until 1323 that he attempted its conquest, nor until
                    1326 that the Pisans were finally driven out of Cagliari, which they had
                    fortified in 1305— 1307 by the construction of the Torre di S. Pancrazio and the
                    Torre dell’ Elefante, and which became the seat of the Aragonese government. To
                    the Pisan period belong a number of fine Romanesque churches, among which may be
                    specially mentioned those of Ardara, S. Giusta near Oristano, La Trinità di
                    Saccargia and Tratalias (see D. Scano, <hi rend="italic">op. cit.
                    infra).</hi></p>
                <p>The Aragonese enjoyed at first the assistance of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >giudici</hi> of Arborea, who had remained in power; but in 1352 war broke
                    out between Mariano IV. and the Aragonese, and was carried on by his daughter
                    Eleonora, wife of Brancaleone Doria of Genoa, until her death in 1403. Peter</p>
                <p>IV. had meanwhile in 1355 called together the Cortes (parliament) of the three
                    estates (the nobles, the clergy and the representatives of the towns) for the
                    first time after the model of Aragon. After 1403 the Aragonese became masters of
                    Arborea also. The title of <hi rend="italic">giudice</hi> was abolished and a
                    feudal marquisate substituted. The <hi rend="italic">carta de logu</hi> (del
                    luogo) or code of laws issued by her was in 1421 extended to the whole island by
                    the cortes under the presidency of Alphonso V., who visited Sardinia in that
                    year. In 1478 the marquisate of Oristano was suppressed, and henceforth the
                    island was governed by Spanish viceroys with the feudal régime of the great
                    nobles under them, the Cortes being convoked once every ten years. Many of the
                    churches show characteristic Spanish Late Gothic architecture which survived
                    until a comparatively recent period. The Renaissance had little or no influence
                    on Sardinian architecture and culture.</p>
                <p>The island remained a Spanish province until the War of the Spanish Succession,
                    when in 1708 Cagliari capitulated to an English fleet, and the island became
                    Austrian; the <hi rend="italic">status quo</hi> was confirmed by the peace of
                    Utrecht in 1713. In 1717, however, Cardinal Alberoni retook</p>
                <p>Cagliari for Spain; but this state of things was short lived, for in 1720, by the
                    treaty of London, Sardinia passed in exchange for Sicily to the dukes of Savoy,
                    to whom it brought the royal title. The population was at that time a little
                    over 300,000; public security and education were alike lacking, and there were
                    considerable animosities between different parts of the island. Matters improved
                    considerably under Charles Emmanuel III., in whose reign of forty-three years
                    (1730-1773)the prosperity of the island was much increased. The French attacks
                    of 1792-1793 were repelled by the inhabitants, Cagliari being unsuccessfully
                    bombarded by the French fleet, and the refusal by Victor Amadeus III. to grant
                    them certain privileges promised in consideration of their bravery led to the
                    revolution of 1794-1796. In 1799 Charles Emmanuel IV. of Savoy took refuge in
                    Cagliari after his expulsion by the French, but soon returned to Italy. In 1802
                    he abdicated in favour of his brother Victor Emmanuel I., who in 1806 returned
                    to Cagliari and remained there until 1814, when he retired, leaving his brother,
                    Carlo Felice, as viceroy. Carlo was successful in repressing brigands, but had
                    to deal with much distress from famine. In 1821 he became king of Savoy by the
                    abdication of his brother, and the construction of the highroad from Cagliari to
                    Porto Torres was begun (not without opposition on the part of the inhabitants)
                    in 1822. Feudalism was abolished in 1836, and in 1848 complete political union
                    with Piedmont was granted, the viceregal government being suppressed, and the
                    island being divided into three divisions of which Cagliari, Sassari and Nuoro
                    were the capitals. General A. La Marmora was appointed royal commissioner to
                    supervise the transformation to the new régime.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Bibliography.—G. Manno,</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">Storia della Sardegna</hi> (1825); A. de La Marmora, <hi
                        rend="italic">Voyage en Sardaigne</hi> (Paris and Turin, 1826-1857);</p>
                <p>Valery, <hi rend="italic">Viaggi alle isole di Corsica e di Sardegna</hi> (Milan,
                    1842); Tyndal, <hi rend="italic">The Island of Sardinia</hi> (London, 1849) ; G.
                    Spano, <hi rend="italic">Bullettino archeologico Sardo</hi> (1855-1864) and
                    other works; A. Bresciani, <hi rend="italic">Dei costumi dell' isola di
                        Sardegna</hi> (Naples, 1861); H. von Maltzan, <hi rend="italic">Reise auf
                        der Inset Sardinien</hi> (Leipzig, 1869) ; E. Pais, “ La Sardegna avanti al
                    dominio dei Romani" in <hi rend="italic">Memorie dei Lincei</hi> (1881); R.
                    Tennant, <hi rend="italic">Sardinia and its Resources</hi> (London, 1885); G.
                    Straf-forello, <hi rend="italic">Sardegna</hi> (Turin, 1895); F. Pais-Serra, <hi
                        rend="italic">Relazione dell' inchiesta suite condizioni economiche della
                        Sardegna</hi> (Rome, 1896); G. Pinza, “ I Monumenti primitivi della Sardegna
                    ” in <hi rend="italic">Monumenti dei Lincei,</hi> xi. (1901); F. Nissardi,
                    “Contributo alla storia dei Nuraghi ” in <hi rend="italic">Atti del Congres so
                        delle Scienze Storiche</hi> (Rome, 1903), vol. v. (Archeologia) (1904), 651
                    sqq.; G. Sergi, <hi rend="italic">La Sardegna</hi> (Turin, 1907); <hi
                        rend="italic">Archivio storico Sardo</hi> from 1905; D. Scano, <hi
                        rend="italic">Storia dell' arte in Sardegna dal XI. al XIV. secolo</hi>
                    (Cagliari and Sassari, 1907) ; D. Mackenzie, <hi rend="italic">Ansonia,</hi>
                    iii. (Rome, 1908), 18, and <hi rend="italic">Memnon,</hi> ii. (Leipzig, 1909) ;
                    and “ Dolmens, Tombs of the Giants and Nuraghi of Sardinia, in <hi rend="italic"
                        >Papers of the British School at Rome.</hi> v. 89 (1910). (T. As.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
