<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-24-s02-0219-06"
                facs="encyclopaediabri24chisrich_0238.jp2" type="entry">
                <p><label>SĀRIPUTTA</label>, one of the two principal disciples of Gotama the
                    Buddha. He was bom in the middle of the 6th century B.c. at Nāla, a village in
                    the kingdom of Magadha, the modem Behar, just south of the Ganges and a little
                    east of where Patna now stands. His personal name was Upatissa; the name of his
                    father, who was a brahmin, is unknown; his mother’s name was Sārī, and it was by
                    the epithet or nickname of Sāriputta (that is “ Sārī’s son ”), that he was best
                    known. He had three sisters, all of whom subsequently entered the Buddhist
                    Order. When still a young man he devoted himself to the religious life, and
                    followed at first the system taught by Sañjaya of the Belattha clan. A summary
                    of the philosophical position of this teacher has been preserved in the Dialogue
                    called <hi rend="italic">The Perfect Net.</hi></p>
                <p>According to this account his main tendency was to avoid committing himself to
                    any decided conclusion on any one of the numerous points then discussed so
                    eagerly among the clansmen in the valley of the Ganges. Early in the Buddhist
                    movement Sãriputta had a conversation with one of the men who had just joined
                    it; and the Buddhist quoted to him the now famous stanza, “ Of all the things
                    that proceed from a cause, the Buddha the cause hath told; and he tells too how
                    each shall come to an end—such alone is the word of</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-24-s02-0220" facs="encyclopaediabri24chisrich_0239.jp2"/>
                <p>the Sage.” The result was that Sãriputta, with his friend Kolita and other
                    disciples of Sañjaya, asked for admission, and were <hi rend="italic"
                        >received</hi> into the Buddhist Order. He rapidly attained to mastery in
                    the Buddhist system of self-training, and is declared to have been the chief of
                    all the disciples in insight. He was present at a dialogue between the Buddha
                    and a Wanderer named Aggivessana on the nature of sensations; and at the end of
                    that discourse he attained to Arahatship. He is constantly represented as
                    discussing points, usually of ethics or philosophy, either with the Buddha
                    himself, or with one or other of the more prominent disciples. One whole book of
                    the Samyutta is therefore called after his name. A number of stanzas inscribed
                    to him are preserved in the <hi rend="italic">Songs of the Elders</hi>
                    (Thera-gãthã), and one of the poems in the Sutta Nipāta is based on a question
                    he addressed to the Buddha. Asoka the Great, in his Bhabra Edict, enjoins on the
                    Buddhists the study of seven passages in the Scriptures selected for their
                    especial beauty. One of these is called <hi rend="italic">The Question of
                        Upatissa,</hi> and this poem may be the passage referred to. Feeling his end
                    approaching, he went home, and died just six months before the death of the
                    Buddha, that is, approximately in 480 B.c. He was cremated with great ceremony,
                    and the ashes placed in a tope or burial-mound. An inscribed casket in such a
                    mound at Sãñchi opened by Cunningham in February 1851 contained a portion of
                    these ashes which had been removed to that spot, in General Cunningham’s opinion
                    by Asoka.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Bibliography.—For the birth, death, cremation and relics,
                        see Alex. Cunningham,</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">Bhüsa Topes</hi> (London, 1854); Rhys Davids and S. W.
                    Bushell, <hi rend="italic">Watters on Yuan Chwang</hi> (London, 1904, 1905). For
                    names of mother and sisters, <hi rend="italic">Therī Gāthā,</hi> ed. R. Pischel
                    (London, 1883). For conversion Rhys Davids and H. Oldenberg, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Vinaya Texts</hi> (Oxford, 1881), i. 144-151. For attainment of Arahatship,
                    V. Trenckner, <hi rend="italic">Majjhima Nikāya</hi> (London, 1888), i. 501.</p>
                <p>T. W. R. D.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
