<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-24-s02-0210-02"
                facs="encyclopaediabri24chisrich_0227.jp2" type="entry">
                <p><label>SARDICA, COUNCIL OF</label>, an ecclesiastical council convened in 343 by
                    the emperors Constantius and Constans, to attempt a settlement of the Arian
                    controversies, which were then at their height. Of the hundred and seventy
                    bishops assembled, about ninety were Homousians—principally from the West—while
                    on the other side were eighty Eusebians from the East. The anticipated
                    agreement, however, was not attained; and the result of the council was simply
                    to embitter the relations between the two great religious parties, and those
                    between the Western and Eastern halves of the Empire. For as Athanasius and
                    Marcellus of Ancyra appeared on the scene, and the Western bishops declined to
                    exclude them, the Eusebian bishops of the East absolutely refused to discuss,
                    and contented themselves with formulating a written protest addressed to
                    numerous foreign prelates. That they instituted a rival congress of their own in
                    Philippopolis is improbable. The bishops, however, who remained in Sardica (mod.
                        <hi rend="italic">Sofia</hi> in Bulgaria) formed themselves into a synod,
                    and naturally declared in favour of Athanasius and Marcellus, while at the same
                    time they anathematized the leaders of the Eusebian party. The proposal to draw
                    up a new creed was rejected.</p>
                <p>Especial importance attaches to this council through the fact that Canons 3-5
                    invest the Roman bishop with a prerogative which became of great historical
                    importance, as the first legal recognition of his jurisdiction oyer other sees
                    «and the basis for the further development of his primacy. “ In order to honour
                    the memory of St Peter,” it was enacted that any bishop, if deposed by his
                    provincial synod, should be entitled to appeal to the bishop of Rome, who was
                    then at liberty either to confirm the first decision or to order a new
                    investigation. In the latter case, the tribunal was to consist of bishops from
                    the neighbouring provinces assisted—if he so chose— by legates of the Roman
                    bishop. The clauses thus made the bishop of Rome president of a revisionary
                    court; and afterwards Zosimuà unsuccessfully attempted to employ these canons of
                    Sardica, as decisions of the council of Nice, against the Africans. In the
                    middle ages they were cited to justify the claim of the papacy to be the supreme
                    court of appeal. Attacks on their authenticity have been conclusively
                    repelled.</p>
                <p>The canons are printed in C. Mirbt, <hi rend="italic">Quellen zur Geschichte des
                        Papsttums</hi> (Tübingen, 1901), p. 46 f.; Hefele, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Conciliengeschichte,</hi> ed. 2, i. 533 sqq. See also, J. Friedrich, <hi
                        rend="italic">Die Unechtheit der Canones von Sardika</hi> (Vienna, 1902); on
                    the other side F. X. Funk, “ Die Echtheit der Canones von Sardica,” <hi
                        rend="italic">Historisches Jahrbuch der Görresgesellschaft,</hi> xxiii.
                    (1902), pp. 497-516; <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi> xxvi. (1905), pp. 1-18,
                    255-274; C. H. Turner, "The Genuineness of the Sardican Canons,” <hi
                        rend="italic">The Journal of Theological Studies,</hi> iii. (London, 1902),
                    ΡΡ- 370-397. (C. M.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
