<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-24-s02-0188-02"
                facs="encyclopaediabri24chisrich_0205.jp2" type="entry">
                <p><label>SANTAL (or Sonthal) PARGANAS, THE</label>, a district of British India,
                    in the Bhagalpur division of Bengal. Area 5470 sq. m.</p>
                <p>In the east a sharply defined belt of hills stretches for about 100 m. from the
                    Ganges to the river Naubil ; west of this a rolling tract of long ridges with
                    intervening depressions covers about 2500 sq. m.; while there is a narrow strip
                    of alluvial country about 170 m. long, lying for the most part along the loop
                    line of the East Indian railway. The Rajmahal hills occupy an area of 1366 sq.
                    m.; they nowhere exceed 2000 ft. There are several other hill ranges which with
                    few exceptions are covered almost to their summits with dense jungle ; they are
                    all difficult of access. There are, however, numerous passes through all the
                    ranges. Coal and iron are found in almost all parts, but of inferior quality.
                    The alluvial tract has the damp heat and moist soil characteristic of Bengal,
                    while the undulating and hilly portions are swept by the hot westerly winds of
                    Behar, and are very cool in the winter months. The annual rainfall averages 52
                    in. In 1901 the population was 1,809,737, showing an increase of 3 % in the
                    decade.</p>
                <p>The Santals, who give their name to the district, are the most numerous
                    aboriginal tribe in Bengal; they work the coal-mines of Raniganj and Karharbari
                    and migrate to the tea-gardens of Assam. In 1832 officials were deputed to
                    demarcate with solid masonry pillars the present area of the Daman-i-Koh, or “
                    skirts of the hills.” The permission to Santals to settle in the valleys and on
                    the lower slopes stimulated Santal immigration to an enormous extent. The Hindu
                    money-lender soon made his appearance among them, and caused the rebellion of
                    1855-56. The insurrection led to the establishment of a form of administration
                    congenial to the immigrants; and a land settlement has since been carried out on
                    conditions favourable to the occupants of the soil. The Church Missionary
                    Society and the Scandinavian Home Mission have been very successful, especially
                    in promoting education. The district is traversed by both the chord and loop
                    lines of the East Indian railway. It contains the old Mahommedan city of
                    Rajmahal and the modern commercial mart of Sahibganj, both on the Ganges; and
                    also the Hindu place of pilgrimage of Deogarh, which is important enough to have
                    a branch railway. The administrative headquarters are at Dumka, or Naya Dumka:
                    pop. (1901) 5326.</p>
                <p>See F. B. Bradley-Birt, <hi rend="italic">The Story of the Indian Upland</hi>
                    (1905).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
