<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-24-s02-0001-01"
                facs="encyclopaediabri24chisrich_0018.jp2" type="entry">
                <p><label>SAINTE-CLAIRE DEVILLE, ÉTIENNE HENRI</label>, (1818-1881), French chemist,
                    was born on the 11th of March 1818 in the island of St Thomas, West Indies,
                    where his father was French consul. Together with his elder brother Charles he
                    was educated in Paris at the Collège Rollin. In 1844, having graduated as doctor
                    of medicine and doctor of science, he was appointed to organize the new faculty
                    of science at Besançon, where he acted as dean and professor of chemistry from
                    1845 to 1851. Returning to Paris in the latter year he succeeded A. J. Balard at
                    the École Normale, and in 1859 became professor at the Sorbonne in place of J.
                    B. A. Dumas, for whom he had begun to lecture in 1853. He died at
                    Boulogne-sur-Seine on the 1st of July 1881.</p>
                <p>He began his experimental work in 1841 with investigations of oil of turpentine
                    and tolu balsam, in the course of which he discovered toluene. But his most
                    important work was in inorganic and thermal chemistry. In 1849 he discovered
                    anhydrous nitric acid (nitrogen pentoxide), a substance interesting as the first
                    obtained of the so-called “ anhydrides ” of the monobasic acids. In 1855,
                    ignorant of what Wöhler had done ten years previously, he succeeded in obtaining
                    metallic aluminium, and ultimately he devised a method by which the metal could
                    be prepared on a large scale by the aid of sodium, the manufacture of which he
                    also developed. With H. J. Debray (1827-1888) he worked at the platinum metals,
                    his object being on the one hand to prepare them pure, and on the other to find
                    a suitable metal for the standard metre for the International Metric Commission
                    then sitting at Paris. With L. J. Troost (b. 1825) he devised a method for
                    determining vapour densities at temperatures up to 1400° C., and, partly with F.
                    Wöhler, he investigated the allotropic forms of silicon and boron. The
                    artificial preparation of minerals, especially of apatite and isomor-phous
                    minerals and of crystalline oxides, was another subject in which he made many
                    experiments. But his best known contribution to general chemistry is his work on
                    the phenomena of reversible reactions, which he comprehended under a general
                    theory of “ dis-sociation.” He first took up the subject about 1857, and it was
                    in the course of his investigations on it that he devised the apparatus known as
                    the “ Deville hot and cold tube.”</p>
                <p>His brother, Charles Joseph Sainte-Claire Deville (1814-1876), geologist and
                    meteorologist, was born in St Thomas on the 26th of February 1814. Having
                    attended at the École des Mines in Paris, he assisted Elie de Beaumont in the
                    chair of geology at the Collège de France from 1855 until he succeeded him in
                    1874. He made researches on volcanic phenomena, especially on the gaseous
                    emanations. He investigated also the variations of temperature in the atmosphere
                    and ocean. He died at Paris on the 10th of October 1876.</p>
                <p>His published works include: <hi rend="italic">Études géologiques sur les îles de
                        Ténériffe et de Fogo</hi> (1848); <hi rend="italic">Voyage géologique aux
                        Antilles et aux Îles de Tênêriffe et de Fogo</hi> (1848-1859); <hi
                        rend="italic">Recherches sur les principaux phénomènes de météorologie et de
                        physique générale aux Antilles</hi> (1849); <hi rend="italic">Sur les
                        variations périodiques de la température</hi> (1866), and <hi rend="italic"
                        >Coup d'œil historique sur la géologie</hi> (1878).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
