<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-24-s02-0111-01" facs="encyclopaediabri24chisrich_0128.jp2" type="entry"><p><label>SAMARIUM</label>, [symbol Sm, atomic weight 150∙4 (O=16)], a rare earth metal (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Rare Earths).</hi> The separation has been worked at by A. v. Welsbach, L. de Boisbaudran, Urbain and Lacombe <hi rend="italic">(Comptes rendus,</hi> 1903, 137 pp. 568, 792); Demarçay <hi rend="italic">(ibid.</hi> 1900, 130, p. 1019); Benedicks; Feit and Przibylla <hi rend="italic">(Zeit. anorg. Chem.,</hi> 1905, 43, p. 202) and others. The metal may be obtained by reduction of its oxide with magnesium. It combines with hydrogen to form a hydride. The salts are mostly of a yellowish colour. The <hi rend="italic">chloride,</hi> SmCl. 6HO, is a deliquescent solid which when heated in hydrochloric acid gas to 180° C. yields the anhydrous chloride. This anhydrous chloride is reduced to a lower chloride, of composition SmCl, when heated to a high temperature in a current of hydrogen or ammonia (Matignon and Cazes, <hi rend="italic">Comptes rendus,</hi> 1906, 142, p. 183). The chloride, SmCl, is a brown crystalline powder which is decom-posed by water with liberation of hydrogen and the formation of the oxide, SmO, and an oxychloride, SmOCl. The <hi rend="italic">fluoride,</hi> SmF.HO, was prepared by H. Moissan by acting with fluorine on the carbide. The <hi rend="italic">sulphate,</hi> Sm(SO).8HO, is obtained by the action of sulphuric acid on the nitrate. It forms double salts with the alkaline sulphates. The <hi rend="italic">carbide,</hi> SmC2, is formed when the oxide is heated with carbon in the electric furnace.</p></div></body></text></TEI>