<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-24-s02-0204-05"
                facs="encyclopaediabri24chisrich_0221.jp2" type="entry">
                <p><label>SARASIN, or Sarrazin, JEAN FRANÇOIS</label> (1611-1654), French author,
                    son of Roger Sarasin, treasurer-general at Caen, was born at Hermanville near
                    Caen. He was educated at Caen, and settled in Paris. As a writer of <hi
                        rend="italic">vers de société</hi> he rivalled Voiture, but he was never
                    admitted to the inner circle of the hôtel de Rambouillet. He was on terms of
                    intimate friendship with Scarron, with whom he exchanged verses, with Ménage,
                    and with Pellisson. In 1639 he supported Georges de Scudéry in his attack on
                    Corneille with a <hi rend="italic">Discours de la tragédie.</hi> He accompanied
                    Léon Bouthillier, comte de Chavigny, secretary of state for foreign affairs, on
                    various diplomatic errands. He was to have been sent on an embassy to Rome, but
                    spent the money allotted for the purpose in Paris. This weakened his position
                    with Chavigny, from whom he parted in the winter of 1643-1644. To restore his
                    fallen fortunes he married a rich widow, but the alliance was of short duration.
                    He joined in the pamphlet war against Pierre de Montmaur, against whom he
                    directed his satire, <hi rend="italic">Bellum parasiticum</hi> (1644). He was
                    accused of writing satires on Mazarin, and for a short time gave up the practice
                    of verse. In 1648, supported by the cardinal</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-24-s02-0205" facs="encyclopaediabri24chisrich_0222.jp2"/>
                <p>de Retz and Madame de Longueville, he entered the household of Armand de Bourbon,
                    prince de Conti, whose marriage with Mazarin’s niece he helped to negotiate. He
                    died of fever at Pézénas, in Languedoc on the 5th of December 1654. His
                    biographers have variously stated on inadequate evidence that his death was
                    caused by the prince de Conti in a moment of passion, or that he was poisoned by
                    a jealous husband. The most considerable of his poems were the epic fragments of
                        <hi rend="italic">Rollon conquérant, la guerre espagnole,</hi> with <hi
                        rend="italic">Dulot vaincu</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Pompe funèbre</hi>
                    in honour of Voiture. As a poet he was overrated, but he was the author of two
                    excellent pieces of prose narration, the <hi rend="italic">Histoire du siège de
                        Dunkerque</hi> (1649) and the unfinished <hi rend="italic">Conspiration de
                        Walstein</hi> (1651). The <hi rend="italic">Walstein</hi> has been compared
                    for elegance and simplicity of style to Voltaire’s <hi rend="italic">Charles
                        XII.</hi></p>
                <p>His <hi rend="italic">Œuvres</hi> appeared in 1656, <hi rend="italic">Nouvelles
                        Œuvres</hi> (2 vols.) in 1674. His <hi rend="italic">Poésies</hi> were
                    edited in 1877 by Octave Uzanne with an introductory note. Much of his
                    correspondence is preserved in the library of the Arsenal, Paris. See Albert
                    Mennung’s <hi rend="italic">Jean François Sαrαsιns Leben und Werke</hi> (2
                    vols., Halle, 1902-1904).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
