<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-24-s02-0041-02"
                facs="encyclopaediabri24chisrich_0058.jp2" type="entry">
                <p><label>ST PIERRE and MIQUELON</label>, two islands 10 m. off the south coast of
                    Newfoundland, united area about 91 sq. m. Both are rugged masses of granite,
                    with a few small streams and lakes, a thin covering of soil and scanty
                    vegetation. Miquelon, the larger of the two, consists of Great Miquelon and
                    Little Miquelon, or Langlade; previous to 1783 these were separated by a
                    navigable channel, but they have since become connected by a dangerous mudbank.
                    St Pierre has a sheltered harbour with about 14 ft. of water, and a good
                    roadstead for large vessels. Their importance is due to their proximity to the
                    great Banks, which makes them the centre of the French Atlantic fisheries. These
                    are kept up by an elaborate system of bounties by the French government, which
                    considers them of great importance as training sailors for the navy. Fishing
                    lasts from May till October, and is carried on by nearly five hundred vessels,
                    of which about two-thirds are fitted out from St Pierre, the remainder coming
                    from St Malo, Cancale and other French coast towns. The resident population,
                    which centres in the town of St Pierre, is about 6500, swelled to over 10,000
                    for a time each year by extra fishing hands from France, but is steadily
                    declining owing to emigration into Canada. Owing to the low rates of duty, vast
                    quantities of goods, especially French wines and liquors, are imported, and
                    smuggled to Newfoundland, the United States and Canada, though of late years
                    this has been checked by a gradual rise in the scale of duties, and by the
                    presence since 1904 of a British consul. St Pierre is connected with Halifax
                    (N.S.) and St Johns (Newfoundland) by a regular packet service, and is a station
                    of the Anglo American Cable Co. and the <hi rend="italic">Compagnie française
                        des câbles télégraphiques.</hi> Excellent facilities for primary and
                    secondary education arc given, but the attraction of the fisheries prevents
                    their being fully used.</p>
                <p>The islands were occupied by the French in 1660, and fortified in 1700. In 1702
                    they were captured by the British, and held till 1763, when they were given back
                    to France as a fishing station. They are thus the sole remnant of the French
                    colonies in North America. Destroyed by the English in 1778, restored to France
                    in 1783, again captured and depopulated by the English in 1793, recovered by
                    France in 1802 and lost in 1803, the islands have remained in undisputed French
                    possession since 1814 (Treaty of Paris).</p>
                <p>See Henrique, <hi rend="italic">Les Colonies françaises, t.</hi> ii. (Paris,
                    1889) ; Levasseur, <hi rend="italic">La France,</hi> t. ii. (Paris, 1893); <hi
                        rend="italic">L'Année coloniale,</hi> yearly since 1899, contains statistics
                    and a complete bibliography; P. T. McGrath in <hi rend="italic">The New England
                        Magazine</hi> (May 1903) describes the daily life of the people. (W. L.
                    G.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
