<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-24-s02-0106-01" facs="encyclopaediabri24chisrich_0123.jp2" type="entry"><p><label>SALZKAMMERGUT</label>, a district of Austria in the S.W. angle of the duchy of Upper Austria situated between Salzburg and Styria. It forms a separate imperial domain of about 250 sq. m. and is famous for its fine scenery, which has gained for it the title of the “ Austrian Switzerland ”; but it owes its name (literally “ salt-exchequer property ”) and its economic import-ance to its valuable salt mines. It belongs to the region of the Eastern Alps, and contains the Dachstein group with the Dach-stein (9830 ft.) and the Thorstein (9657 ft.). In the Dachstein group are found the most easterly glaciers of the Alps, of which the largest is the Karls-Eisfeld, nearly 2½ m. long and 1½ m. broad; the Ischler Alps with the Gamsfeld (6640 ft.), the Höllengebirge with the great Höllenkogel (6106 ft.), and the Schafberg (5837 ft.), which is called the “ Austrian Rigi.” Then comes the Todtes Gebirge, with the Grosser Priel (8246 ft.) and the Traunstein (5446 ft.) on the E. shore of the Traun lake; the Pyhrgas group with the Grosser Pyhrgas (7360 ft.) and the Sengsen or Sensen group, with the Hoher Nock (6431 ft.). The chief lakes are the Traun-see or Lake of Gmunden (1383 ft. above sea-level, 9 sq. m. in extent, 623 ft. deep) ; the Hallstätter-see or Lake of Hallstatt (1629 ft. above sea-level, 3½ sq. m. in extent, 409 ft. deep ); the Atter-see or Kammer-see (1527 ft. above sea-level, 18 sq. m. in extent, 560 ft. deep), the largest lake in Austria; the Mond-see (1560 ft. above the sea, 9 sq. m. in extent, 222 ft. deep) and the Aber-see or Lake of St Wolfgang (1742 ft. above sea-level, 5½ sq. m. in extent, 369 ft. deep). Salzkammergut had in 1900 a population of over 18,000. The capital of the district is Gmunden, and other places of importance are Ischl, Hallstatt and Ebensee (7656), which are important salt-mining centres. The salt extracted in Salzkammergut amounts to nearly 30% of the total Austrian production. Cattle-rearing and forestry form the other principal occupations of the inhabitants.</p><p>See Kegele, <hi rend="italic">Das Salzkammergut</hi> (Wien, 1897).</p></div></body></text></TEI>