<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-24-s02-0082-02"
                facs="encyclopaediabri24chisrich_0099.jp2" type="entry">
                <p><label>SALMON and SALMONIDAE</label>.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial" n="1"> The Latin name <hi rend="italic">salmo</hi> possibly
                        means literally “ the leaper,” from <hi rend="italic">satire,</hi> to leap,
                        jump. </note> The Salmonidae are an important family of fishes belonging to
                    the Malacopterygian Teleosteans, characterized as follows: Margin of the upper
                    jaw formed by the premaxillaries and the maxillaries—supra-occipital in contact
                    with the frontals, but frequently overlapped by the parietals, which may meet in
                    a sagittal suture; opercular bones all well developed. Ribs sessile,
                    parapophyses very short or absent; epineurals, sometimes also epipleurals,
                    present. Post-temporal forked, the upper branch attached to the epiotic, the
                    lower to the opisthotic; postclavicle, as usual, applied to the inner side of
                    the clavicle. A small adipose dorsal fin. Air-bladder usually present, large.
                    Oviducts rudimentary or absent, the ova falling into the cavity of the abdomen
                    before extrusion.</p>
                <p>The Salmonidae are very closely related to the Clupeidae, or herring family, from
                    which they are principally distinguished by the position of the postclavicle and
                    by the presence of a rayless fin on the back, at a considerable distance from
                    the true or rayed dorsal fin; this so-called adipose fin is an easy
                    recognition-mark of this family, so far as British waters are concerned, for, if
                    it is present in several other families, these have no reprc-sentatives in the
                    area occupied by the fresh-water salmonids, with the exception of the North
                    American Siluridae and Percop-sidae, which are readily distinguished by the
                    pungent spine or spines which precede the rays of the first dorsal fin. The
                    imperfect condition of the oviducts, quite exceptional among fishes, owing to
                    which the large ripe eggs may be easily squeezed out of the abdomen, is a
                    feature of great practical importance, since it renders artificial impregnation
                    particularly easy, and to it is due the fact that the species of <hi
                        rend="italic">Salmo</hi> have always occupied the first place in the annals
                    of fish-culture.</p>
                <p>The Salmonidae inhabit mostly the temperate and arctic zones of the northern
                    hemisphere, and this is the case with all freshwater forms, with one exception,
                        <hi rend="italic">Retropinnα,</hi> a smelt-like fish from the coasts and
                    rivers of New Zealand. A few deep-sea forms (<hi rend="italic">Argentina,
                        Microstoma, Nansenia, Bathylagus)</hi> are known from the Arctic ocean, the
                    Mediterranean and the Antarctic ocean, down to 2000 fathoms. The question has
                    been discussed whether the salmonids, so many of which live in the sea, but
                    resort to rivers for breeding purposes, were originally marine or fresh-water.
                    The balance of opinion is in favour of the former hypothesis, which is supported
                    by the fact that the overwhelming majority of the members of the suborder of
                    which the salmonids form part permanently inhabit the sea. The clupeids,</p>
                <p>for instance, which are their nearest allies, are certainly of marine origin, as
                    proved by their abundance in Cretaceous seas, yet a few, like the shads, ascend
                    rivers to spawn, in the same way as the salmon does, without this ever having
                    been adduced as evidence in favour of a fresh-water origin of the genus <hi
                        rend="italic">Clupea</hi> to which they belong.</p>
                <p>No remains older than Miocene (<hi rend="italic">Osmerus, Prothymallus,
                        Thaumaturus)</hi> are certainly referable to this family, the various
                    Cretaceous forms originally referred to it, such as <hi rend="italic"
                        >Osmeroides</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Pachyrhizodus,</hi> being now placed
                    with the <hi rend="italic">Elopidae.</hi> There is probably no other group of
                    fishes to which so much attention has been paid as to the Salmonidae, and the
                    species have been unduly multiplied by some writers. Perhaps not more than 80
                    should be regarded as valid, but some of them fall into a number of local forms
                    which are distinguished as varieties or subspecies by some authors, whilst
                    others would assign them full specific rank. These differences of opinion
                    prevail whether we deal with <hi rend="italic">Salmo</hi> proper or with <hi
                        rend="italic">Coregonus.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Classification.—The</hi> recent genera may be arranged in five
                    groups: The first, which includes <hi rend="italic">Salmo, Brachymystax,
                        Stenodus, Coregonus, Phylogephyra</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Thymallus,</hi>
                    has 8 to 20 branchiostegal rays, 9 to 13 rays in the ventral fin, the pyloric
                    appendages more or less numerous (17 to 200) and breeding takes place in fresh
                    water. The second group, with the single genus <hi rend="italic">Argentina,</hi>
                    is, like the following, marine, and is characterized by 6 branchiostegal rays,
                    11 to 14 ventral rays, the stomach caecal, with pyloric appendages in moderate
                    numbers (12 to 20). The third group, genera <hi rend="italic">Osmerus,
                        Thaleichthys, Mαllotus, Plecoglossus, Hypomesus,</hi> has 6 to 10
                    branchiostegal rays, 6 to 8 ventral rays, the stomach caecal, with pyloric
                    appendages few (2 to 11) or rather numerous. The fourth group, genera <hi
                        rend="italic">Microstoma, Nαnseniα, Bathylagus,</hi> deep-sea forms with the
                    branchiostegal rays reduced to 3 or 4, ventral rays 8 to 10, the stomach caecal
                    and pyloric appendages absent; whilst the fifth group, with the genera <hi
                        rend="italic">Retropinna</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Salanx,</hi> is
                    distinguished from the preceding in having no air-bladder, branchiostegal rays 3
                    to 6, ventral rays 6 or 7, stomach siphonal and pyloric appendages absent.</p>
                <p>The genus <hi rend="italic">Salmo,</hi> the most important from the economical
                    and sporting points of view, is characterized by small smooth scales, which at
                    certain seasons may become embedded in the slimy skin, a moderately high dorsal
                    fin with 10 to 12 well-developed rays, and a large mouth provided with strong
                    teeth, which are present not only in the jaws and on the palate, but also on the
                    tongue; the maxillary or posterior bone of the upper jaw extends to below or
                    beyond the eye. Young specimens (see Parr) are marked with dark vertical bars on
                    the sides (parr-marks), which in some trout are retained throughout life, and
                    have the caudal fin more or less deeply forked or marginate, the form of the fin
                    changing with the age and sexual development of the fish. Adult males have the
                    jaws more produced in front than females, and both snout and chin may become
                    curved and hooked. As pointed out by A. Günther, who was the first to make a
                    profound study of the members of this genus, and especially of the British
                    forms, there is probably no other group of fishes which offers so many
                    difficulties to the ichthyologist with regard to the distinction of species, as
                    well as to certain points in their life-history, the almost infinite variations
                    which they undergo being dependent on age, sex and sexual development, food and
                    the properties of the water. The difficulties in their study have rather been
                    increased by the excessive multiplication of so-called specific forms. Opinions
                    also vary as to the importance to be attached to the characters which serve to
                    group the principal species into natural divisions. Whilst A. Günther admitted
                    two genera, <hi rend="italic">Salmo</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                        >Oncorhynchus,</hi> D. S. Jordan and B. W. Evermann go so far as to
                    recognize five, <hi rend="italic">Oncorhynchus, Salmo, Hucho, Cristivomer</hi>
                    and <hi rend="italic">Salvelinus.</hi> The latter arrangement is certainly the
                    more logical, the difference between the first genus and the second being of
                    rather less importance than that between the second and the third. However,
                    considering the slightness of the distinctive characters on which these
                    divisions are based, and the complete passage which obtains between them, the
                    writer of this article thinks it best to maintain the genus <hi rend="italic"
                        >Salmo</hi> in the wide sense, whilst retaining the divisions as subordinate
                    divisions or sub-genera, with the following definitions:—</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Oncorhynchus</hi> (Pacific salmon).—Vomer flat, toothed along
                    the shaft, at least in the young; anal fin with 12 to 17 well-developed
                    rays.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Salmo</hi> (true salmon and trout.—Vomer flat, toothed along
                    the shaft, at least in the young; anal fin with 8 to 12 well-developed rays.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Sαlυelinus</hi> (char).—Vomer boat-shaped, the shaft strongly
                    de-pressed behind the head, which alone is toothed, the teeth forming an
                    isolated fascicle; anal fin with 8 to 10 well-developed rays.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Hucho</hi> (huehens).—Vomer as in the preceding, but teeth
                    forming a single arched transverse series continuous with the palatine teeth;
                    anal fin with 8 to 10 well-developed rays.</p>
                <p>The salmon itself (<hi rend="italic">Salmo salar),</hi> the type of the family,
                    is a large fish, attaining a length of 4 or 5 ft., and living partly in the</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-24-s02-0083" facs="encyclopaediabri24chisrich_0100.jp2"/>
                <p>sea, partly in fresh water, breeding in the latter. Fish which thus ascend rivers
                    to spawn are called “ anadromous.” It may be briefly defined as of silvery
                    coloration, with small black spots usually confined to the side above the
                    lateral line, with the teeth on the shaft of the vomer disappearing in the
                    adult, with 18 to 22 gill-rakers on the first branchial arch, with 11 or 12
                    well-developed rays in the dorsal fin, 110 to 125 scales in the lateral line,
                    and 11 or 12 (exceptionally 13) between the latter and the posterior border of
                    the adipose fin. The young, called “parr” or “samlet,” characterized by a
                    smaller mouth, the maxillary bone not extending much beyond the vertical of the
                    centre of the eye, the presence of an alternating double or zigzag series of
                    teeth on the shaft of the vomer, the presence of dark vertical bars on the sides
                    of the body, together with more or less numerous small red spots, is hatched in
                    the spring, and usually remains for about two years in the rivers, descending at
                    the third spring to the sea, where it is known as “smolt.” In the sea it soon
                    assumes a more uniform silvery coloration and from this state, or “ grilse,”
                    develops its sexual organs and re-enters rivers to breed, after which operation,
                    much emaciated and unwholesome as food, it is known as “ kelt,” and returns to
                    the sea to recuperate. It has now been ascertained by the investigations
                    instituted in Norway by K. Dahl that the smolts, immediately after leaving the
                    rivers, make for the open sea, and do not return to the coast until they have
                    reached the grilse stage. Thus specimens measuring between 8 and 18 in. hardly
                    ever fall into the hands of the angler.</p>
                <p>The salmon inhabits the North Atlantic and its tributary waters. It is known to
                    extend as far north as Scandinavia, Lapland, Iceland, Greenland and Labrador,
                    and as far south as the north-west of Spain and the state of Connecticut. It
                    ascends the Rhine as far as Basel. There are land-locked forms in Scandinavia
                    and in Canada and Maine, which are regarded by some authors as distinct species
                    (5. <hi rend="italic">hardinii</hi> from Lake Wener, 5. <hi rend="italic"
                        >sebago</hi> from Sebago Lake in Maine, 5. <hi rend="italic">ouananiche</hi>
                    from Lake St John, Canada and neighbouring waters). These non-migratory forms
                    are smaller than the typical salmon, never exceeding a weight of 25 lb, the
                    ouananiche, the smallest of all, rarely weighing 7½lb and averaging 3½. Although
                    spending their whole life in fresh waters, the habits of these fish are very
                    similar to those of the sea salmon, ascending tributary streams to spawn in
                    their higher ranges, and then returning to the deep parts of the lakes, which
                    are to them what the sea is to the anadromous salmonids.</p>
                <p>The salmon breeds in the shallow running waters of the upper streams of the
                    rivers it ascends. The female, when about to deposit her eggs, scoops out a
                    trough in the gravel of the bed of the stream. This she effects by lying on her
                    side and ploughing into the gravel by energetic motions of her body. She then
                    deposits her eggs in the trough ; while she is engaged in these operations she
                    is attended by a male, who sheds milt over the eggs as the female extrudes them,
                    fertilization being, as in the great majority of <hi rend="italic"
                        >Teleostei,</hi> external. The parent fish then fill up the trough and heap
                    up the gravel over the eggs until these are covered to a depth of some feet. The
                    gravel heap thus formed is called a “ redd.” The period of the year at which
                    spawning takes place in the British lsles, and in similar latitudes of the
                    northern hemisphere, varies to a certain extent with the locality, and in a
                    given locality may vary in different years; but, with rare exceptions, spawning
                    is confined to the period between the beginning of September and the middle of
                    January.</p>
                <p>The eggs are spherical and non-adhesive; they are heavier than water, and are
                    moderately tough and elastic. The size varies slightly with the age of the
                    parent fish, those from full-sized females being slightly larger than those from
                    very young fish. According to rough calculations made at salmon-breeding
                    establishments, there are 25,000 eggs to a gallon ; the diameter is about a
                    quarter of an inch. It is usually estimated that a female salmon produces about
                    900 eggs for each pound of her own weight; but this average is often
                    exceeded.</p>
                <p>The time between fertilization and hatching, or the escape of the young fish from
                    the egg-membrane, varies considerably with the temperature to which the eggs are
                    exposed. It has been found that at a constant temperature of 41° F. the period
                    is 97 days; but the period may be as short as 70 days and as long as 150 days
                    without injury to the health of the embryo. It follows therefore that in the
                    natural conditions eggs deposited in the autumn are hatched in the early spring.
                    The newly hatched fish, or “ alevin,” is provided with a very large yolk-sac,
                    and by the absorption of the yolk is nourished for some time; although its mouth
                    is fully formed and open, it takes no food. The alevin stage lasts for about six
                    weeks, and at the end of it the young fish is about 1¼ in. long.</p>
                <p>The grilse, after spawning in autumn, return again to the sea in the winter or
                    following spring, and reascend the rivers as mature spawning salmon in the
                    following year. Both salmon and grilse after spawning are called “ kelts. The
                    following recorded experiment illustrates the growth of grilse into salmon: a
                    grilse-kelt of 2 lb was marked on March 31, 1858, and recaptured on August 2 of
                    the same year as a salmon of 8lb.</p>
                <p>The ascent of rivers by adult salmon is not so regular as that of grilse, and the
                    knowledge of the subject is not complete. Although salmon scarcely ever spawn
                    before the month of September, they do not ascend in shoals just before that
                    season; the time of ascent extends throughout the spring and summer. A salmon
                    newly arrived in fresh water from the sea is called a clean salmon, on account
                    of its bright, well-fed appearance; during their stay in the rivers the fish
                    lose the brilliancy of their scales and deteriorate in condition. The time of
                    year at which clean salmon ascend from the sea varies greatly in different
                    rivers; and rivers are, in relation to this subject, usually denominated early
                    or late. The Scottish rivers flowing into the German Ocean and Pentland Firth
                    are almost all early, while those of the Atlantic slope are late. The Thurso in
                    Caithness and the Naver in Sutherlandshire contain fresh-run salmon in December
                    and January; the same is the case with the Tay. In Yorkshire salmon commence
                    their ascent in July, August or September if the season is wet, but if it is dry
                    their migration is delayed till the autumn rains set in. In all rivers more
                    salmon ascend immediately after a spate or flood than when the river is low, and
                    more with the flood tide than during the ebb. In their ascent salmon are able to
                    pass obstructions, such as waterfalls and weirs of considerable height, and the
                    leaps they make in surmounting such impediments and the persistence of their
                    efforts are very remarkable.</p>
                <p>We reproduce here, with additions, Professor Noel Paton’s summary (published
                    first in the 10th edition of this <hi rend="italic">Encyclopedia)</hi> of
                    observations on the life-history of the salmon. Important advances in our
                    knowledge of the life-history of the salmon have been made through the
                    investigations of Professor F. Miescher on the Rhine at Basel, of Professor P.
                    P. C. Hoek in Holland, of Mr Archer as lessee of the river Sands in Norway and
                    as inspector of salmon fisheries for Scotland in conjunction with Messrs Gray
                    and Tosh, and of a number of workers in the laboratory of the Royal College of
                    Physicians of Edinburgh. With regard to the <hi rend="italic">food</hi> of
                    salmon, the enormously rapid growth of smolts to grilse and of salmon from year
                    to year shows that they feed in the sea. In a few months a smolt will increase
                    from a few ounces to 4 or 5 lb; while Archer’s weighings of 16 salmon which had
                    been marked and recaptured in the following year showed an average gain of 36%,
                    reckoned on from kelt stage to kelt stage. During the season of 1895 Tosh, at
                    Berwick-on-Tweed, opened between March and August 514 fish, and found food in
                    the stomachs of 76, or over 14% of the whole. As to the nature of the food, it
                    was found to be as follows:—</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Herring......</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>. 36 or</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>47%</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Crustacea, amphipods, &amp;amp;c.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>• i4 ,,</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>18%</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Sand eels .....</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>• 11 ,,</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>14%</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Haddock and whiting</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>. 8 „</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>10%</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Feathers and vegetable matter .</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>. . 7 ,,</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>9%</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>Excluding the feathers and vegetable matter, which are not really of the nature
                    of food, all the material found in the stomach was of marine origin. Hoek, out
                    of 2000 fish examined by him, found 7 with food in the stomach, and, curiously
                    enough, 4 of these were taken on the same day. In each case marine fish
                    constituted the food. As to where salmon go to feed in the sea, our information
                    is still very deficient, but the prevalence of herring in the stomach would seem
                    to indicate that they must follow the shoals of these fish which approach the
                    coast during the summer months. While there can be no doubt that salmon feed in
                    the sea, the question of whether they feed in fresh water has been much debated.
                    It is difficult for the popular mind to conceive of an active fish like the
                    salmon subsisting for several months without food, and the fact that the fish so
                    frequently not only takes into its mouth but actually swallows worms and various
                    lures has still further tended to confirm many people in the conviction that
                    salmon do feed in fresh water. In discussing the question it is well clearly to
                    understand what is meant by feeding. It is the taking, digesting and absorbing
                    of material of use in the economy in such quantities as to be of benefit to the
                    individual. Accepting this definition, it may at once be said that all the
                    evidence we possess is entirely opposed to the view that salmon feed when in
                    fresh water. Miescher examined the stomachs of about 2000 salmon captured at
                    Basel, about 500 m. from the mouth of the Rhine, and in only two did he find any
                    indication of feeding. These two fish were male kelts. One contained the remains
                    of a cyprinoid fish, and the other had a dilated stomach with an acid secretion,
                    but no food remains. Hoek, who, as already stated, examined about 2000 fish,
                    found food of marine origin in 7, but in none food derived from fresh water. Of
                    the 132 stomachs of salmon from the estuaries and upper waters of Scottish
                    rivers examined in the laboratory of the College of Physicians not one contained
                    any food remains. The stomach of salmon captured in fresh water is collapsed and
                    shrunken. Its mucous membrane is thrown into folds, and it contains a small
                    amount of mucus of a neutral reaction. The intestine, which usually contains
                    numerous</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-24-s02-0084" facs="encyclopaediabri24chisrich_0101.jp2"/>
                <p>tape-worms, is full of a greenish-yellow viscous material which, when examined
                    under the microscope, is found to consist of mucus with shed epithelial and
                    other cells and with masses of crystals of carbonate of lime. In no case does
                    the microscope reveal any food remains such as fish-scales, plates of Crustacea
                    or bristles of worms or annelids. In the fish taken in the estuaries up to the
                    month of August the gall-bladder is distended; in those taken later in the year
                    it is empty. In all the fish from the upper waters the gall-bladder is empty and
                    collapsed. According to the investigations of Hoek and of Gulland, the lining
                    membrane of the stomach and intestine degenerates while the fish is in the
                    river, but the correctness of these observations has been denied by F. B. Brown
                    and J. Kingston Barton. Gillespie finds that the activity of the digestive
                    processes is low in fish taken from the rivers, and that micro-organisms, which
                    would be killed by the hydrochloric acid of the gastric juice were it actively
                    secreted, flourish in the intestines of the fish from the upper waters. Those
                    who believe that the salmon feeds in fresh water explain the fact that the
                    stomach is always found empty by the supposition that the fish vomits any food
                    when it is captured, and several descriptions of cases in which this has been
                    observed might be quoted; but such observations must be accepted with caution,
                    and the contracted state of the stomach, the absence of the hydrochloric acid of
                    the gastric juice, and lastly the absence of any traces of digested food remains
                    in the contents of the intestine, negative this explanation.</p>
                <p>The question may be presented in another way. Is there any reason why the salmon
                    should feed while in fresh water? The investigations carried on in the
                    laboratory of the College of Physicians have definitely shown that the salmon
                    leaves the sea with an enormous supply of nourishment stored in its muscles, and
                    that during its sojourn in fresh water it gets its energy and builds up its
                    rapidly growing ovaries and testes from this stored material. Briefly stated,
                    these investigations show that the supply of albuminous material and fats stored
                    in the muscles and used while the fish is in the river is amply sufficient for
                    the greatest requirements of the fish. The amount of energy liberated from the
                    fats and albuminous material is 570 times more than is required to raise the
                    fish from the level of the estuary to that of the upper waters! These analyses
                    further show that all the materials required for the construction of the ovaries
                    and the testes are found in sufficient quantity in the muscles, with the
                    exception of iron, which is, however, abundantly present in the blood.</p>
                <p>It is a very common opinion that kelts feed voraciously while still in fresh
                    water, and this has been used as an argument that they should be destroyed. It
                    is not easy to bring forward such satisfactory evidence as has been adduced in
                    the case of unspawned salmon, since it is illegal to kill kelts; but none of the
                    25 kelts procured by the Scottish Fishery Board, and examined in the College of
                    Physicians* laboratory, contained any food, and Mr Anderson, formerly of
                    Dunkeld, informs Professor Paton that in the old days, when kelts were
                    habitually killed when captured, he has opened a large number and never found
                    any trace of food in the stomach. Some fishers declare that they have seen kelts
                    devouring salmon fry, but it is not easy to make accurate observations in deep
                    water. According to Dr Gulland's investigations, the mucous membrane of the
                    stomach and intestine is completely regenerated while the gall-bladder contains
                    bile, and the digestive activity of the alimentary canal is greater than in
                    salmon before spawning. Kelts thus appear at least to be capable of feeding.</p>
                <p>The rate of growth of the genitalia has been carefully studied by Miescher,
                    Archer and Hoek. From January till about the end of May the growth of the
                    ovaries is slow. In Hoek's series of observations, which are the most complete,
                    they increased from ∙35 to •85% of the body weight. After this they enlarge more
                    rapidly, and by the end of August are about 3% in salmon taken at the mouth of
                    the Tweed, about 4% in the salmon from the mouth of the Rhine and about 8% in
                    the salmon from the Basel fisheries. By November they have risen to 20% in the
                    Tweed and in Holland, and to 23 % in the upper reaches of the Rhine. According
                    to Archer’s observations, the development of the ovaries in grilse in the
                    earlier months somewhat lags behind that in the salmon. The growth of the testes
                    has been chiefly investigated by Archer and Tosh in the Tweed and by Miescher at
                    Basel. From March to the middle of July in the Tweed these organs increase from
                    about .19 to .35% of the weight of the fish. In July their rate of growth
                    increases, and they reach their maximum development at the end of September,
                    when they are about 6% of the body weight. In the Rhine in March they weigh
                    about .1%, and they reach their maximum development of about 5% in October.</p>
                <p>What leads to the migration of salmon from sea to river and river to sea? It is
                    usually supposed that they come to the river to spawn; that it is the <hi
                        rend="italic">nisus generations</hi> that drives them from the sea, where
                    their ova will not develop, to the fresh water where development is possible.
                    But it is found that salmon are passing from sea to river at all seasons of the
                    year, and with their genitalia in all stages of development—some fish, running
                    in March with ovaries only I % of the body weight, other fish not running till
                    October with ovaries 15 or 16% of the body weight. It is difficult, then, to
                    accept the theory that the sexual act is the governing factor. That it is a
                    secondary factor seems to be indicated by the great run of fish in June, July
                    and August, when the genitalia are most rapidly growing. There is one respect,
                    however, in which all the fish leaving the sea for the river agree, and that is
                    in the amount of stored material accumulated in their bodies. In the early
                    running fish this material is largely confined to the muscles, but in the later
                    coming fish it is more eqiîally distributed between muscles and genitalia. The
                    amount of stored material may be measured by the amount of solids, and if we
                    express the results of all the fish examined in terms of fish of uniform
                    size—100 cm. in length— the following results are obtained :—</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Nov.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                                    type="authorial" n="2"> Winter fish not due to spawn till
                                    following November. </note></p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Feb.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Mar.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>April.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>May</p><p>and</p><p>June.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>July</p><p>and</p><p>Aug.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Oct.</p><p>and</p><p>Nov.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Kelts.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Muscles</p><p>Ovaries</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>2481</p><p>23</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>2214</p><p>24</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>2355</p><p>'24</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>2599</p><p>33</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>2210</p><p>47</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>2270</p><p>72</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>1750</p><p>545</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>946</p><p>9</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Total</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>2504</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>2238</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>2379</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>2632</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>2257</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>2342</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>2295</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>955</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>It would thus appear that, when the salmon has in the sea accumulated a certain
                    definite amount of nourishment, it ceases to feed, and returns to the river
                    irrespective of the state of its genital organs. Nutrition, and not the <hi
                        rend="italic">nisus generations,</hi> appears to be the motive power. That
                    the fish after spawning returns to the sea in search of food is fully recognized
                    by all.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Course of Migration.—</hi> It is well known that while salmon
                    run all the year through in greater or lesser numbers, the run of grilse takes
                    place in the summer months, from May to August. But it is further possible to
                    divide the salmon into classes—the so-called winter salmon of the Rhine,. large
                    fish running from October to February, with unripe ovaries and testes; and the
                    summer salmon, running for the most part from March to October, with genitalia
                    more or less ripe. These summer fish are small in the early months, but increase
                    in size as the autumn advances. The winter salmon, along with the early summer
                    or spring fish, appear to pass directly to the upper reaches of the river, and
                    to spawn there, while the larger late-coming fish appear to populate the lower
                    waters. This seems to be indicated by the comparison of upper-water and estuary
                    fish throughout the year. The period at which male and female fish enter the
                    rivers also appears to be somewhat different. The observations of Tosh, Miescher
                    and Hoek show that throughout the year the female fish exceed the males in
                    number, and, secondly, that during the earlier months of the year female fish
                    run in much larger numbers than do male fish. It is only in September that
                    anything like an equality between the two sexes is established. But in Great
                    Britain it is not until the end of August that the nets are removed, and one
                    cannot but believe that the destruction of such a very large proportion of
                    females as are captured during the early months of the season must have a most
                    prejudicial effect upon the breeding stock.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Rate of Migration.—</hi> By a comparison of the first
                    appearance of winter salmon and of grilse in the markets of Holland and of
                    Basel— 500 m. up the river—Miescher gives some data for the determination of the
                    average rate at which salmon ascend an unobstructed stream. It was found that
                    winter salmon appeared at Basel about 54 days after their appearance in Holland,
                    which would give a rate of passage of about 10 m. per diem. From a smaller
                    number of observations on grilse, it appears that they travel at a somewhat
                    slower rate. It is, however, doubtful how far these figures are of value in
                    deciding the rate at which fish pass up the lower reaches of the river.</p>
                <p>Great difficulties have been experienced in ascertaining the age and rate of
                    growth of salmon. The practice has long ago been resorted to of “ marking ”
                    salmon, the most satisfactory mark being a small oblong silver label, oxidized
                    or blackened, bearing distinctive letters and numbers, to the dorsal fin. But of
                    late the structure of the scales has been studied with the object of obtaining
                    indications of the age, growth and spawning habit. H. W. Johnston in 1905
                    contributed an interesting paper on the subject. The scales bear concentric
                    lines, which vary in number and relative distance according to the growth of the
                    fish, and during the feeding periods these lines are added with more rapidity
                    and a greater degree of separation than at other times. Johnston has endeavoured
                    to ascertain their meaning in Tay salmon, and he has shown that the number of
                    lines external to their last annual ring gives some clue to the time at which
                    they left the sea; he is thus able to distinguish among ascending salmon such as
                    are on their first return from such as have made the journey once or oftener
                    before.</p>
                <p>The group of Pacific salmon, or king salmon, commonly designated as <hi
                        rend="italic">Oncorhynchns,</hi> contains the largest and commercially the
                    most important of the Salmonidae. They arc anadromous species inhabiting the
                    North Pacific and entering the rivers of America as well as of Asia. The best
                    known and most valuable is the quinnat <hi rend="italic">(S. quinnat),</hi>
                    ascending the large rivers in spring and summer, spawning from July to December.
                    They die after the breeding season is over, and never return to the sea. For the
                    important Sal-monidae known as Trout, Ciiar, Whitefish, Smelt, GraylIng,
                    &amp;amp;c., see the separate articles. The huchen <hi rend="italic">(S.
                        hncho)</hi> of the Danube is an elongate, somewhat pike-like form, growing
                    to the same size</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-24-s02-0085" facs="encyclopaediabri24chisrich_0102.jp2"/>
                <p>as the salmon, of silvery coloration, with numerous small black dots, extending
                    on the dorsal fin. Allied to it are <hi rend="italic">S. fluυiatilis</hi> from
                    Siberia and 5. <hi rend="italic">perryi</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                        >blackistoni</hi> from the northern island of Japan.</p>
                <p>The genus <hi rend="italic">Stenodus</hi> is intermediate between <hi
                        rend="italic">Salmo</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Coregonus</hi> (whitefish).
                    5. <hi rend="italic">leucichthys</hi> is an anadromous species, inhabiting the
                    Caspian Sea and ascending the Volga and the Ural; it is also found in the Arctic
                    ocean, ascending the Ob, Lena, &amp;amp;c. It grows to a length of 5 ft. A
                    second species occurs in Arctic North America; this is the “ Inconnu,” 5. <hi
                        rend="italic">mackenzii,</hi> from the Mackenzie river and its
                    tributaries.</p>
                <p>The capelin (<hi rend="italic">Mallotus villosus,</hi> so called from the villous
                    bands formed by the scales of mature males) is a salmonid of the coasts of
                    Arctic America and north-eastern Asia; it deposits its eggs in the sand along
                    the shores in incredible numbers, the beach becoming a quivering mass of eggs
                    and sand. <hi rend="italic">Plecoglossus,</hi> a salmonid from Japan and
                    Formosa, is highly remarkable for its lamellar, comb-like, lateral teeth. The
                    siel-smelts, <hi rend="italic">Argentina,</hi> are deep-sea salmonids, of which
                    examples have occasionally been taken off the coasts of Scotland and Ireland.
                        <hi rend="italic">Bathylagus,</hi> another salmonid discovered by the “
                    Challenger ” expedition, is still better adapted for life at great depths (down
                    to 1700 fathoms), the eyes being of enormous size.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Authorities.—On the systematic and life histories: A.
                        Gunther,</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">Catalogue of Fishes in the British Museum,</hi> vol. vi.
                    (1866); F. Day, <hi rend="italic">British and Irish Salmonidae</hi> (London,
                    1887); F. A. Smitt, <hi rend="italic">Kritisk Förteekning öfver de i Riksmuseum
                        befintliga Salmonider</hi> (Stockholm, 1886); V. Fatio, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Faune des vertébrés de la Suisse,</hi> vol. v. (1890); D. S. Jordan and B.
                    W. Evermann, <hi rend="italic">Fishes of North America,</hi> vol. i. (1896), and
                        <hi rend="italic">American Food and Game Fishes</hi> (London and New York,
                    1902); F. F. Kavraisky, <hi rend="italic">Die Lachse der Kaukasusländer</hi>
                    (Tiflis, 1896). On growth and migrations: <hi rend="italic">Die histochemischen
                        und physiologischen Arbeiten vοn Friedrich Miescher,</hi> Band ii., pp. 116,
                    192, 304, 325 (Leipzig, 1897); P. P. C. Hoek, <hi rend="italic">Statische und
                        biologische Untersuchungen an in den Niederländern gefangenen Lachsen</hi>
                    (Charlottenburg, 1895) ; <hi rend="italic">Annual Reports of the Fishery Board
                        for Scotland,</hi> part ii., “Report on Salmon Fisheries,” Nos. 11, 12, 13,
                    14 (1893-1894-95-96) ; <hi rend="italic">Report of Investigations on the
                        Life-History of the Salmon to the Fishery Board for Scotland,</hi> edited by
                    Noël Paton, presented to parliament and published 1898; K. Dahl, <hi
                        rend="italic">Orret og unglοhs samt lovgivningens forhold til dem</hi>
                    (Christiania, 1902) ; H. W. Johnston, "The Scales of Tay Salmon as indicative of
                    Age, Growth and Spawning Habit,” <hi rend="italic">Ann. Rep. Fish. Board,
                        Scotland,</hi> xxiii., appendix ii. (1905). Introduction in Tasmania and New
                    Zealand: M. Allport, <hi rend="italic">Proc. Zool. Soc.</hi> (1870), pp. 14 and
                    750; A. Nichol, <hi rend="italic">Acclimatization of the Salmonidae at the
                        Antipodes</hi> (London, 1882); W. Arthur, “ History of Fish Culture in New
                    Zealand,” <hi rend="italic">Tr. N. Zeal. Inst.</hi> xiv. (1881) p. 180; P. S.
                    Seager, “ Concise History of the Acclimatization of the Salmonids in Tasmania,”
                        <hi rend="italic">Proc. R. Sοc. Tasm.</hi> (1888) p. 1 ; also R. M.
                    Johnston, <hi rend="italic">l.c.</hi> p. 27. On the salmon disease: T. H.
                    Huxley, <hi rend="italic">Quart. Jour. Micr. Sci.</hi> xxii. (1882) p. 311. (G.
                    A. B.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
