<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196389_0646.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0640-02" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SANADON</label>
(Noel Etienne), a Jeſuit, was born at Rouen in 1676, and Was a diſtinguiſhed profeſſor of humanity at Caen. He there became acquainted with Huet biſhop of Avranches, whoſe taſte for literature and poetry was ſimilar to his own. Sanadon afterwards taught rhetoric at the univerſity of Paris, and was entruſted with the education of the prince of Conti, after the death of Du Morceau. In 1728 he was made librarian to Louis XIV. an office which he retained to his death. He died on the 21ſt September 1733, in the 58th year of his age.</p><p>His works are, I. Latin Poems, in 12mo, 1715 and reprinted by Barbou, in 8vo, 1754. His ſtyle poſſeſſes the graces of the Auguſtan age. His language is pure and nervous; his verſes are harmonious, and his thoughts are delicate and well choſen; but ſometimes his imagination flags. His Latin poems conſiſt of Odes, Elegies, Epigrams, and others, on various ſubjects. 2. A tranſlation of Horace, with Remarks, in 2 vols 4t0, printed at Paris in 1727; but the beſt edition ot this work was printed at Amſterdam in 1785, in 8vos 12m), in which are alſo inſerted the<pb facs="gri_33125011196389_0647.tif" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0641"/>
verſions and notes of M. Damer. Sanadon tranſlated with elegance and taſte; but he has not preſerved the ſublimity of the original in the odes, nor the energy and preciſion in the epiſtles and ſatires. In general, his verſion is rather a paraphraſe than a faithful tranſlation. Learned men have juſtly cenſured him for the liberty which he has taken in making conſiderable changes in the order and ſtructure of the odes. He has alſo given offence by his uncouth orthography. 3. A Collection of Diſcourſes delivered at different times, which afford ſtrong proofs of his knowledge of oratory and poetry. 4. A book entitled <hi rend="italic">Prieres et Inſtructions Chretiennes.</hi></p></div></body></text></TEI>