<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196389_0690.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0684-01" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SAXONY</label>,
the name of two circles of the German empire, an electorate, and a duchy of the fame. The lower circle is bounded to the ſouth by the circle of Upper Saxony, and a part of that of the Upper Rhine; to the north, by the duchy of Sleſwick, belonging to the king of Denmark, and the Baltic; to the well, by the circle of Weſtphalia and the north ſea; and to the eaſt by the circle of Upper Saxony. The ſtates belonging to it are the dukes and princes of Magdeburg and Bremen, Zell, Grubenhagen, Calenburg, Wolfenbuttle, Halberſtadt, Mecklenburg-Schwerin, Mecklen- burg-Guſtro, Holſtein-Gluckſtadt, Holſtein-Gottorf,</p><p>Hildeſheim, Saxe-Lawenburg; the archbiſhopric of Lubeck; the principalities of Schwerin, Ratzeburg, Blankenburg, Ranzau; the imperial cities of Lubeck, Gotzlar, Muhlhaufen, Nordhauſen, Hamburgh, and Bremen. The dukes of Bremen and Magdeburg are alternately directors and ſummoning princes; but, ever ſince the year 1682, the diets which uſed generally to be held at Brunſwick or Lunenburg have been diſcontinued. Towards the army of the empire, which, by a decree of the empire in 1681, was ſettled at 40,000 men, this circle was to furniſh 1322 horſemen and 2707 foot; and of the 300,000 florins granted to the imperial cheſt in 1707, its quota was 31,271 florins; both which aſſeſſments are the ſame with thoſe of Upper Saxony, Burgundy, Swabia, and Weſtphalia. This circle at preſent nominates only two aſſeſſors in the chamber- judicatory of the empire, of one of which the elector of Brunſwick-Lunenburg has the nomination, who muſt be a Lutheran, and is the ninth in rank. The inhabitants of this circle are almoſt all Lutherans.</p><p>The circle of Upper Saxony is bounded by that of Franconia, the Upper Rhine, and Lower Saxony; and alſo by the Baltic ſea, Pruſſia, Poland, Sileſia, Luſatia, and Bohemia. It is of great extent, and contains the following ſtates, viz. the electors of Saxony and Brandenburg, Saxe-Weimar, Saxe-Eifenach, Saxe-Cobourg, Saxe-Gotha, Saxe-Altenburg, Saxe-Querfurt, the Hither and Farther Pomerania, Camin, Anhalt, Quidlen- burg, Gernrode, Walkenried, Schwarzburg, Sonderſhauſen, Schwarzburg-Rudolſtadt, Mansfeld, Stolberg, Barby, the counts of Reuſſen, and the counts of Schonberg. No diets have been held in this circle ſince the year 1683. The elector of Saxony has always been the ſole ſummoning prince and director of it. Moſt of the inhabitants profeſs the Proteſtant religion. When the whole empire furniſhes 40,000 men, the quota of this circle is 1322 horſe and 2707 foot. Of the 300, 000 florins granted by the empire in 1707, it contributed only 31,271 florins, 28 kruitzers, being rated no higher than thoſe of Weſtphalia, Lower Saxony, Swabia, and Burgundy, though it is much larger. Agreeable to a reſolution and regulation in 1654, this circle nominates now only two aſſeſſors of the chamber-court.</p><p>The electorate conſiſts of the duchy of Saxony, the greateſt part of the margravate of Meiſſen, a part of the Vogtland, and the northern half of the landgravate of Thuringia. The Luſatias alſo, and a part of the country of Henneberg, belong to it, but are no part of this circle. The ſoil of the electoral dominions lying in this circle is in general exceeding rich and fruitful, yielding corn, fruits, and pulſe in abundance, together with hops, flax, hemp, (tobacco, aniſeed, wild ſaffron, wood; and in ſome places woad, wine, coals, porcelain clay, terra ſigillata, fullers-earth, fine ſhiver, various forts of beautiful marble, ſerpentine ſtone, and almoſt all the different ſpecies of precious ſtones. Sulphur alſo, alum, vitriol, fand, and free-stone, ſalt-ſprings, amber, turf, cinnabar, quickſilver, antimony, biſmuth, arſenic, cobalt, and other minerals, are found in it. This<pb facs="gri_33125011196389_0691.tif" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0685"/>
country, beſides the above articles, contains likewiſe valuable mines of ſilver, copper, tin, lead, and iron; and abounds in many places with horned cattle, ſheep, horſes, and venison. The principal rivers by which it is watered are the Elbe, the Schwerze-Elſter, the Mulde, the Saale, the Unſtrut, the Weiſſe-Elſter, and the Pleiſſe. Theſe rivers, as well as the lakes and rivulets, abound in fiſh; and in the White-Elſter are found beautiful pearls. This electorate is extremely well cultivated anti inhabited, and is ſaid to include about 250 great and ſmall towns, upwards of 5000 villages, 196 royal manors, and near as many royal caſtles, beſides private eſtates, and commanderies. The provincial diets here conſiſt of three claſſes. The firſt is compoſed of the prelates, the counts, and lords, and the two universities of Leipſic and Wittenberg. To the ſecond belong the nobility in general, immediate or mediate, that is, ſuch as ſtand immediately under the fief-chancery or the aulic judicatories, and ſuch as are immediately under the juriſdiction of the amtman. The third claſs is formed of the towns in general. The general provincial diets are ordinarily held every ſix years; but there are others, called <hi rend="italic">ſelection diets,</hi> which are convened commonly every two years. We would here obſerve, that not only theſe diets, but thoſe in moſt of the other ſtates of Germany, are at preſent extremely inſignificant and unimportant, retaining little more than the ſhadow of their former power and privileges; for even the petty princes, though they depend upon their more potent neighbours, and muſt be careful not to give them any umbrage, are almoſt as abſolute in their reſpective territories as the grand ſeignior himſelf. As to religion, it was in this country that the reformation took its riſe in the 16th century, to which it hath ever ſince adhered, according to the doctrines of Luther<note anchored="true" n="1" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">* See</hi> Reformation <hi rend="italic">, n</hi> ⁰ 8.</p></note> *. The two late electors, when they embraced Popery in order to qualify themſelves to be elected kings of Poland, gave the moſt ſolemn aſſurances to their people, that they would inviolably maintain the eſtabliſhed religion and its profeſſors in the full and free enjoyment of all their eccleſiaſtical rights, privileges, and prerogatives whatſoever, in regard to churches, worſhip, ceremonies, uſages, univerſities, ſchools, benefices, incomes, profits, juriſdictions, and immunities. The electoral families ſtill continue Roman Catholics, though they have loſt the crown of Poland, for which they at firſt embraced Popery. With reſpect to eccleſiaſtical matters, the country is divided into pariſhes, and theſe again into ſpiritual inſpections and conſiſtories, all ſubordinate to the eccleſiaſtical council and upper conſiſtory of Dreſden, in which city and Leipſic the Calviniſts and Roman Catholics enjoy the free exerciſe of their religion. Learning flouriſhes in this electorate; in which, beſides the free-ſchools and gymnaſia in moſt of the chief towns, are the two celebrated univerſities of Wittenberg and Leipzig, in the laſt of which are alſo ſocieties for the liberal arts and the German language, with bookſellers and printers of the greateſt eminence. A great variety of manufactures are alſo carried on in this country. The principal are thoſe of fine and coarſe linen, thread, fine lace, paper, fine glaſſes and mirrors; porcelain, equal it not ſuperior to that of China<note anchored="true" n="2" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>†See <hi rend="italic">Porcelain,</hi> n⁰ 23, 24.</p></note> †; iron, braſs, and ſteel wares; manufactures of gold and ſilver, cotton, wool, and ſilk; gloves, caps, hats, and tapeſtry;. in which, and the natural productions mentioned above, together with dye</p><p>ing, an important foreign commerce is carried on. A great addition has been made ſince the year 1718 to the electoral territories, by the extinction of the collateral branches of Zeitz, Merſeburg, and Weiſſenfels, whoſe dominions devolved to the elder electoral branch, deſcended from the margraves of Meiſſen. The firſt of theſe, who was elector of Saxony, was Frederick the Warlike, about the beginning of the 15th century.</p><p>This elector ſtyles himſelf duke of Saxony, Juliers, Cleve, and Berg, as alſo of Engern and Weſtphalia, arch-marſhal and elector of the Holy Roman empire, landgrave in Thuringia, margrave of Meiſſen, and of Upper and Lower Luſatia, burgrave of Magdeburg, princely count of Henneberg, count of La Mark, Ravenſherg, Barby, and Hanau, and lord of Ravenſtein. Among the electors he is reckoned the ſixth, as great-marſhal of the empire, of which he is alſo vicar, during an interregnum, in all places not ſubject to the vicariate of the count palatine of the Rhine. He is moreover ſole director of the circle; and in the vacancy of the ſee of Mentz claims the directorium at the diet of the empire. His matricular aſſeſſment, on account of the electorate, is 1984 florins, beſides what he pays for other diſtricts and territories. To the chamber-courts he contributes, each term, the ſum of 1545 rix dollars, together with 83 rix-dollars and 62 kruitzers on account of the county of Mansfeld. In this electorate, ſubordinate to the privy council, are various colleges for the departments of war, foreign affairs, the finances, fiefs, mines, police, and eccleſiaſtical affairs, together with high tribunals and courts of juſtice, to which appeals lie from the inferior. The revenues of this elector are as conſiderable as thoſe of any prince in the empire, if we except thoſe of the houſe of Auſtria. They ariſe from the ordinary and extraordinary ſubſidies of the ſtates; his own demeſnes, conſiſting of 72 bailiwics; the impoſt on beer, and the fine porcelain of the country; tenths of corn, fruit, wine, &amp;c. his own ſilver mines, and the tenths of thoſe that belong to particulars: all which, added together, bring in an yearly revenue of betwixt 700,000l. and 800,000l. yet the electorate is at preſent deeply in debt. The regular troops commonly amount to 20,000 men, excluſive of the militia of the ban, the arriere-ban, and the body of miners and hunters, who are obliged in time of war to bear arms. The whole electorate is divided into circles.</p><p>The electoral circle, or the duchy of Saxony, is bounded by the circles of Meiſſen, Leipzig, and Thur ringia, the principality of Anhalt, the marche of Brandenburg, and Luſatia. The principality of Anhalt lies acroſs it, and divides it into two parts. Its greateſt length and breadth is computed at about 40 miles; but though it is watered by the Elbe, the Black Elfter, and the Mulde, it is not very fruitful, the ſoil for the moſt part conſiſting of fand. It contains 24 towns, three boroughs, betwixt 400 and 500 villages,. 164 noblemens eſtates, 11 ſuperintendencies, three inspections, under one conſiſtory, and 11 prefecturates or diſtricts. The preſent duchy of Saxony is not to be confounded with the old; for the latter was of a much greater extent, and contained in it thoſe large tracts: anciently called <hi rend="italic">Eaſtphalia, Engern,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Weſtphalia,</hi> of which the electoral circle was no part, but was taken by Albert the Bear, margrave of Salzwedel, from the Venedi. His<pb facs="gri_33125011196389_0692.tif" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0686"/>
ſon Bernard obtaining the dignity of duke of Saxony from the emperor Frederic I. the name of <hi rend="italic">duchy</hi> was given to this country; and the electoral dignity having been afterwards annexed to the duchy, it acquired thereby alſo the name of the <hi rend="italic">electoral circle.</hi></p><p>The country of Saxony is remarkable for being the mother of the preſent Engliſh nation; but concerning the Saxons themſelves, previous to that period, we have very few particulars. The Saxons (ſays Mr Whitaker) have been derived by our hiſtorians from very different parts of the globe; India, the north of Aſia, and the foreſts of Germany. And their appellation has been equally referred to very different cauſes; the name of their Indian progenitor, the plundering diſpoſition of their Aſiatic lathers, and the ſhort hooked weapons of their warriors. But the real origin of the Saxons, and the genuine derivation of their name, ſeem clearly to be theſe.</p><p>In the earlier period of the Gallic hiſtory, the Celtae of Gaul croſſed the Rhine in conſiderable numbers, and planted various colonies in the regions beyond it. Thus the Volcae Tectoſages ſettled on one ſide of the Hercynian foreſt and about the banks of the Neckar, the Helvetii upon another and about the Rhine and Maine, the Boii beyond both, and the Senones in the heart of Germany. Thus alſo we ſee the Treviri, the Nervii, the Suevi, and the Marcomanni, the Quadi, the Venedi, and others, in that country; all plainly betrayed to be Gallic nations by the Gallic appellations which they bear, and all together poſſeſſing the greateſt part of it. And, even as late as the concluſion of the firſt century, we find one nation on the eaſtern fide of this great continent actually ſpeaking the language of Gaul, and another upon the northern uſing a dialect nearly related to the Britiſh. But as all the various tribes of the Germans are conſidered by Strabo to be γενησιοι ΓαλαΊαι or genuine Gauls in their origin; ſo thoſe particularly that lived immediately beyond the Rhine, and are afferted by Tacitus to be indubitably native Germans, are expreſsly denominated ΓαλαΊαι, or Gauls, by Diodorus, and as expreſsly declared by Dio to have been diſtinguiſhed by the equivalent appellation of <hi rend="italic">Celtae</hi> from the earlieſt period. And the broad line of nations, which extended along the ocean, and reached to the borders of Scythia, was all known to the learned in the days of Diodorus, by the ſame ſignificant appellation of ΓαλαΊαι or Gauls.</p><p>Of theſe, the moſt noted were the Si-Cambri and Cimbri; the former being ſeated near the channel of the Rhine, and the latter inhabiting the peninſula of Jutland. And the denominations of both declare their original; and ſhow them to have been derived from the common ſtock of the Celtae, and to be of the ſame Celtic kindred with the Cimbri of our own Somerſetſhire, and the Cymbri or Cambrians of our own Wales. The Cimbri are accordingly denominated <hi rend="italic">Celtae</hi> by Strabo and Appian. And they are equally aſſerted to be Gauls by Diodorus; to be the deſcendants of that nation which ſacked the city of Rome, plundered the temple of Delphi, and ſubdued a great part of Europe and ſome of Aſia.</p><p>Immediately to the ſouth of theſe were the Saxons, extending from the iſthmus of the Cherſoneſus to the current of the Elbe. And they were equally Cel</p><p>tic in their origin as their neighbours, They were denominated <hi rend="italic">Ambrοnes</hi> as well as Saxons; and, as ſuch, are included by Tacitus under the general appellation of <hi rend="italic">Cimbri,</hi> and comprehended in Plutarch under the equal one of <hi rend="italic">Celtο-Scythae.</hi> And the name of <hi rend="italic">Ambrones</hi> appears particularly to have been Gallic; being common to the Saxons beyond the Elbe, and the Ligurians in Ciſalpine Gaul; as both found to their ſurpriſe, on the irruption of the former into Italy with the Cimbri. And, what is equally ſurpriſing, and has been equally unnoticed by the critics, the Welſh diſtinguiſh England by the name of <hi rend="italic">Loegr</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Liguria,</hi> even to the preſent moment. In that irruption theſe Saxons, Ambrons, or Ligurians, compoſed a body of more than 30, 000 men, and were principally concerned in cutting to pieces the large armies of Manlius and Caepio. Nor is the appellation of <hi rend="italic">Saxons</hi> leſs Celtic than the other. It was originally the ſame with the Belgic Sueſſones of Gaul; the capital of that tribe being now intitled <hi rend="italic">Soiſons</hi> by the French, and the name of the Saxons pronounced <hi rend="italic">Saiſen</hi> by the Welſh, <hi rend="italic">Saſon</hi> by the Scotch, and <hi rend="italic">Saſenach</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Saxſenach</hi> by the Triſh. And the Sueſſones or Saxones of Gaul derived their own appellation from the poſition of their metropolis on a river, the ſtream at Soiſons being now denominated the <hi rend="italic">Aiſne,</hi> and formerly the <hi rend="italic">Axon;</hi> Ueſſ-on or Axon importing only waters or a river, and S-ueſſ-on or S-ax-on the waters or the river. The Sueſſones, therefore, are actually denominated the <hi rend="italic">Ueſſones by</hi> Ptolemy; and the Saxones are actually intitled the <hi rend="italic">Axones</hi> by Lucan.</p><p>Theſe, with their brethren and allies the Cimbri, having been more formidable enemies to the Romans by land, than the Samnites, Carthaginians, Spaniards, Gauls, or Parthians, in the ſecond century applied themſelves to navigation, and became nearly as terrible by ſea. They ſoon made themſelves known to the inhabitants of the Britiſh iſles by their piracies in the northern channels, and were denominated by them <hi rend="italic">Lochlyn</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Lochlynach;</hi> lucd-lyn ſignifying the people of the wave, and the D being quieſcent in the pronunciation. They took poſſeſſion of the Orkney iſlands, which were then merely large ſhoals of fand, uncovered with woods, and overgrown with ruſhes; and they landed in the north of Ireland, and ravaged the country. Before the middle of the third century they made a ſecond deſcent upon the latter, diſembarked a conſiderable body of men, and deſigned the abſolute ſubjection of the iſland. Before the concluſion of it, they carried their naval operations to the ſouth, infeſted the Britiſh channel with their little veſſels, and made frequent deſcents upon the coaſts. And in the fourth and fifth centuries, acting in conjunction with the Picts of Caledonia and the Scots of Ireland, they ravaged all the eaſtern and ſouth-eaſtern ſhores of Britain, began the formal conqueſt of the country, and finally ſettled their victorious ſoldiery in Lancaſhire.</p></div></body></text></TEI>