<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196389_0595.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0589-03" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SACKVILLE</label>
(Thomas, Lord Buckhurſt, and earl of Dorſet), a ſtatefman and poet, the ſon of Richard Sackville, Eſq; of Buckhurſt, in the pariſh of Withian in Suffex, was born in the year 1536. He was lent to Hart-hall in Oxford, in the latter end of the reign of Edward VI. whence he removed to Cambridge, where he took a maſter of arts degree, and thence to the Inner Temple. He now applied himſelf to the ſtudy of the law, and was called to the bar. We are told that he commenced poet whilſt at the univerſities, and that theſe his juvenile productions were much admired, none of which, however, have been preſerved. — In the fourth and fifth year of queen Mary, we find him a member of the houſe of commons; about which time, in 1557, he wrote a poetical piece, intitled <hi rend="italic">The Induction,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">The Mirror of Magiſlrates.</hi> This laſt was meant to comprehend all the unfortunate Great from the beginning of our hiſtory; but the deſign being dropped, it was inſerted in the body of the work. The</p><p>Mirror of Magiſtrates is formed on a dramatic plan; in which the perſons are introduced ſpeaking. The Induction is written much in the ſtyle of Spencer, who, with ſome probability, is ſuppoſed to have imitated this author.</p><p>In 1561, his tragedy of <hi rend="italic">Gorboduc</hi> was acted before queen Eliſabeth by the gentlemen of the Inner Temple. This was the firſt tolerable tragedy in our language. The Companion to the Play-houſe tells us, that the three firſt acts were written by Mr Tho. Norton. Sir Philip Sidney, in his Apology for Poetry, says, “it is full of ſtately ſpeeches, and well-founding phraſes, climbing to the height of Seneca in his ſtyle, &amp;c.” Rymer ſpeaks highly in its commendation. Mr Spence, at the inſtigation of Mr Pope, republiſhed it in 1736, with a pompous preface. It is ſaid to be our firſt dramatic piece written in verſe.</p><p>In the firſt parliament of this reign, Mr Sackville was member for Sussex, and for Bucks in the ſecond. In the mean time he made the tour of France and Italy, and in 1566 was impriſoned at Rome, when he was informed of his father’s death, by which he became poſſeſſed of a very conſiderable fortune.</p><p>Having now obtained his liberty, he returned to England; and being firſt knighted was created Lord Buckhurſt. In 1570 he was ſent ambaſſador to France. In 1586 he was one of the commiſſioners appointed to try the unfortunate Mary queen of Scots; and was the meſſenger employed to report the confirmation of her ſentence, and to ſee it executed. The year following he went ambaſſador to the States General, in consequence of their complaint againſt the earl of Leicester; who, diſliking his impartiality, prevailed on the queen to recal him, and confine him to his houſe. In this ſtate of confinement he continued about 10 months, when Leicester dying, he was reſtored to favour, and in 1580 was inſtalled knight of the garter: but the most incontrovertible proof of the queen’s partiality for lord Buckhurſt appeared in the year 1591, when ſhe cauſed him to be elected chancellor in the univerſity of Oxford, in oppoſition to her favourite Eſſex. In 1598, on the death of the treaſurer Burleigh, lord Buckhurſt ſucceeded him, and by virtue of his office became in effect prime miniſter; and when, in 1601, the earls of Eſſex and Southampton were brought to trial, he fat as lord high ſteward on that awful occaſion.</p><p>On the acceſſion of James I. he was graciouſly received, had the office of lord high treaſurer confirmed to him for life, and was created earl of Dorſet. He continued in high favour with the king till the day of his death; which happened ſuddenly, on the 19th of April 1608, in the council-chamber at Whitehall. He was interred with great ſolemnity in Weſtminſter abbey. He was a good poet, an able miniſter, and an honeſt man. From him is deſcended the preſent noble family of the Dorſets. “It were needleſs (says Mr Walpole! to add, that he was the patriarch of a race oſ genius and wit.”</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">SACKVILLE</hi> (Charles, earl of Dorſet), a celebrated wit and poet, deſcended from the foregoing, was born in 1637. He was, like Villiers, Rocheſter, Sedley, &amp;c. one of the libertines of king Charles’s court, and ſometimes indulged himſelf in inexcuſable excesses. He openly diſcountenanced the violent meaſures of James II. and engaged early for the prince of<pb facs="gri_33125011196389_0596.tif" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0590"/>
Orange, by whom he was made lord chamberlain of the houſehold, and taken into the privy-council. He died in 1706, and left ſeveral poetical pieces, which, though not conſiderable enough to make a volume by themſelves, may be found among the works of the minor poets, publiſhed in 1749.</p></div></body></text></TEI>