<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196389_0694.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0688-08" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SCAMMONY</label>,
a concreted vegetable juice of a ſpecies of convolvulus, partly of the reſin, and partly of the gum kind. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Convolvulus</hi></p><p>The beſt ſcammony comes from AIeppo, in light ſpongy maffes, eaſily friable, of a ſhining aſh-colour verging to black; when powdered, of a light grey or whitiſh colour: an inferior ſort is brought from Smyrna, in more compact ponderous pieces, of a darker colour, and full of fand and other impurities. This juice is chiefly of the reſinous kind; rectified ſpirit diſſolves five ounces out of fix, the remainder is a mucilaginous ſubſtance mixed with droſs; proof-ſpirit totally diffolves it, the impurities only being left. It has a faint unpleaſant ſmell, and a bitteriſh, ſomewhat acrimonious, taſte.</p><p>Scammony is an efficacious and ſtrong purgative. Some have condemned it as unſafe, and laid ſundry ill qualities to its charge; the principal of which is, that<pb facs="gri_33125011196389_0695.tif" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0689"/>
its operation is uncertain, a full doſe proving ſometimes ineffectual, whilſt at others a much ſmaller one occaſions dangerous hypercatharſes. This difference, however, is owing entirely to the different circumſtances of the patient, and not to any ill quality or irregularity of operation of the medicine: where the inteſtines are lined with an exceſſive load of mucus, the ſcammony paffes through without exerting itſelf upon them; where the natural mucus is deficient, a ſmall doſe of this or any other reſinous cathartic irritates and inflames. Many have endeavoured to abate the force of this drug, and correct its imaginary virulence, by ex- poſing it to the fume of ſulphur, diſſolving it in acid juices, and the like; but this could do no more than deſtroy as it were a part of the medicine, without making any alteration in the reft. Scammony in ſubſtance, judiciouſly managed, ſtands not in need of any corrector: if triturated with ſugar or with almonds, it becomes ſufficiently ſafe and mild in operation. It may likewiſe be conveniently diſſolved by trituration in a ſtrong decoction of liquorice, and then poured off from the faeces; the college of Wertemberg aſſures us, that by this treatment it becomes mildly purgative, without being attended with gripes, or other inconveniences; and that it likewiſe proves inoffenſive to the palate. The common doſe of ſcammony is from three to twelve grains.</p></div></body></text></TEI>