<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196389_0703.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0697-02" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SCEPTRE</label>,
a kind of royal ſtaff, or batoon, borne on ſolemn occaſions by kings, as a badge of their command and authority. Nicod derives the word from the Greek which he ſays originally ſignified</p><p>“a javelin, ” which the ancient kings uſually bore as a badge of their authority; that inſtrument being in very great veneration among the heathens. But σχηπτρον does not properly ſignify a javelin, but <hi rend="italic">a staff to rest upon,</hi> from οχηπΊω, <hi rend="italic">innitor,</hi> “I lean upon.” Accordingly, in the ſimplicity of the earlier ages of the world, the ſceptres of kings were no other than long walking-ſtaves: and Ovid, in ſpeaking of Jupiter, deſcribes him as reſting on his ſceptre (Met. i. v. 178. ) The ſceptre is an enſign of royalty of greater antiquity than the crown. The Greek tragic and other poets put ſceptres in the hands of the moſt ancient kings they ever introduce. Juſtin obſerves, that the ſceptre, in its original, was an <hi rend="italic">hasta,</hi> or ſpear. He adds, that, in the moſt remote antiquity, men adored the <hi rend="italic">hastae</hi> or ſceptres as immortal gods; and that it was upon this account, that, even in his time, they ſtill furniſhed the gods with ſceptres. —Neptune’s ſceptre is his trident. Tarquin the Elder was the firſt who aſſumed the ſceptre among the Romans. Le Gendre tells us, that, in the firſt race of the French kings, the ſceptre was a golden rod, almoſt always of the ſame height with the king who bore it, and crooked at one end like a crozier. Frequently inſtead of a ſceptre, kings are ſeen on medals with a palm in their hand. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Regalia.</hi></p></div></body></text></TEI>