<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196389_0664.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0658-11" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SARCOPHAGUS</label>,
in antiquity, a fort of ſtone coffin or grave, wherein the ancients laid thoſe they had not a mind to burn.</p><p>The word, as derived from the Greek, literally ſignifies <hi rend="italic">flesh-eater;</hi> becauſe at firſt they uſed a fort of ſtone for the making of tombs, which quickly confirmed the bodies. See the following article.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sarcophagus,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Lapis Λſſius,</hi> in the natural hiſtory of the ancients, a ſtone much uſed among the Greeks in their ſepultures, is recorded to have always perfectly confirmed the fleſh of human bodies buried in it in forty days. This property it was much famed for, and all the ancient naturaliſts mention it. There was another very Angular quality alſo in it, but whether in all, or only in ſome peculiar pieces of it, is not known: that is, its turning into ſtone any thing that was put into veſſels made of it. This is recorded<pb facs="gri_33125011196389_0665.tif" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0659"/>
only by Mutianus and Theophraſtus, except that Pliny had copied it from theſe authors, and ſome of the later writers on theſe ſubjects from him. The account Matianus gives of it is, that it converted into ſtone the ſhoes of perſons buried in it, as alſo the utenſils which it was in ſome places cuſtomary to bury with the dead, particularly thoſe which the perſon while living moſt delighted in. The utenſils this author mentions, are ſuch as muſt have been made of very different materials; and hence it appears that this ſtone had a power of conſuming not only fleſh, but that its petrifying quality extended to ſubſtances of very different kinds. Whether ever it really poſſeſſed this laſt quality has been much doubted; and many, from the ſeeming improbability of it, have been afraid to record it. What has much encouraged the general diſbelieſ of it is, Mutianus's account of its taking place on ſubſtances of very different kinds and textures; but this is no real objection, and the whole account has probably truth in it. Petrifactions in thoſe early days might not be diſtinguiſhed from incruſtations of ſparry and ſtony matter on the ſurfaces of bodies only, as we find they are not with the generality of the world even to this day; the incruſtations of ſpar on moſſes and other ſubſtances in ſome of our ſprings, being at this time called by many <hi rend="italic">petrified mo</hi> ſ <hi rend="italic">s. &amp;c.</hi> and incruſtations like theſe might eaſily be formed on ſubſtances encloſed in veſſels made of this ſtone, by water paſſing through its pores, diſlodging from the common maſs of the ſtone, and carrying with it particles of ſuch ſpar as it contained; and afterwards falling in repeated drops on whatever lay in its way, it might again depoſit them on ſuch ſubſtances in form of incruſtations. By this means, things made of ever ſo different matter, which happened to be incloſed, and in the way of the paſſage of the water, would be equally incruſted with and in appearance turned into ſtone, without regard to the different configuration of their pores and parts.</p><p>The place from whence the ancients tell us they had this ſtone was Aſſos, a city of Lycia, in the neighbourhood of which it was dug; and De Boot informs us, that in that country, and in ſome parts of the Eaſt, there are alſo ſtones of this kind, which, if tied to the bodies of living perſons, would in the ſame manner conſume their fleſh. <hi rend="italic">Hill's Notes on Theοphra</hi> ſt <hi rend="italic">us,</hi></p><p>P. 14.</p></div></body></text></TEI>