<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196389_0654.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0648-01" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SANDWICH</label>,
a town of Kent, one of the cinque ports, and which has the title of an earldom. It conflits of about 1500 houſes, molt of them old, and built with wood, though there are a few new ones built with brick and flints. It has three long narrow ſtreets paved, and thirty croſs-ſtreets or alleys, with about 6000 inhabitants, but no particular manufactory. The town is walled round, and alſo fortified with ditches and ramparts; but the walls are much decayed, on account of the harbour being ſo choaked up with fand that a ſhip of 100 tons burthen cannot get in. E. Long. I. 20. N. Lat. 51. 20.</p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Sandwich</hi> <hi rend="italic">Iſlands,</hi> a group of iſlands in the South Sea, lying near New Ireland, were among the laſt diſcoveries of captain Cook, who ſo named them in ho</p><p>nour of the Earl of Sandwich, under whoſe adminiſtration theſe diſcoveries were made. They conſiſt of eleven iſlands, extending in latitude from 18. 54. to 22. 15. N. and in longitude from 150. 54. to 160. 24. W. They are called by the natives, <hi rend="smallcaps">Owhykee Mowee, Ranai,</hi> <hi rend="italic">Moretoi,</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">Tahoorowa, Woahoo,</hi> ATOOI, <hi rend="italic">Neeheeheow, Oreehoua, Morotinne,</hi> and TAHOORA, all inhabited except the two laſt. An account of the moſt. remarkable of which will be found in their alphabetical order, in their proper places in this work. The climate of theſe iſlands differs very little from that of the Weft Indies in the ſame latitude, though perhaps more temperate; and there are no traces of thoſe violent winds and hurricanes, which render the ſtormy months in the Weſt Indies ſo dreadful. There is alſo more rain at the Sandwich Iſles, where the mountainous parts being generally enveloped in a cloud, fucceſſive ſhowers fall in the inland parts, with fine weather, and a clear ſky, on the ſea ſhore. Hence it is, that few of thoſe inconveniences, to which many tropical countries are ſubject, either from heat or moiſture, are experienced here. The winds, in the winter months, are generally from eaſt-ſouth-eaſt to north-eaſt. The vegetable productions are nearly the ſame as thoſe of the other iſlands in thiſ ocean; but the taro root is here of a ſuperior quality. The bread-fruit trees thrive not in ſuch abundance as in the rich plains of Otaheite, but produce double the quantity of fruit. The ſugar-canes are of a very unuſual ſize, ſome of them meaſuring eleven inches and a quarter in circumference, and having fourteen feet eatable. There is alſo a root of a brown colour, ſhaped like a yam, and from ſix to ten pounds in weight, the juice of which is very ſweet, of a pleaſant taſte, and is an excellent ſubſtitute for ſugar. The quadrupeds are confined to the three uſual forts, hogs, dogs, and rats. The fowls are alſo of the common fort; and the birds are beautiful and numerous, though not various. Goats, pigs, and European ſeeds, were left by captain Cook; but the poſſeſſion of the goats ſoon gave riſe to a conteſt between two diſtricts, in which the breed was entirely deſtroyed. The inhabitants are undoubtedly of the ſame race that poſſeſſes the iſlands ſouth of the equator; and in their perſons, language, cuſtoms, and manners, approach nearer to the New Zealanders than to their leſs diſtant neighbours, either of the Society or Friendly Iſlands. They are in general about the middle ſize, and well made; they walk very gracefully, run nimbly, and are capable of bearing very great fatigue. Many of both ſexes have fine open countenances; and the women in particular have good eyes and teeth, with a ſweetneſs and ſenſibility of look, that render them very engaging, There is one peculiarity, characteriſtic of every part of theſe iſlands, that even in the handſomeſt faces there is a fulneſs of the noſtril, without any flatneſs or ſpreading of the noſe. They ſuffer their beards to grow, and wear their hair after various faſhions. The dreſs of both men and women nearly reſemble thoſe of New Zealand, and both ſexes wear necklaces of ſmall variegated ſhells. Tattowing the body is practiſed by every colony of this nation. The hands and arms of the women are alſo very neatly marked, and they have the ſingular cuſtom of tattowing the tip of the tongue. Like the New Zealanders, they have adopted the method of living together in villages, containing from an hundred to two hundred<pb facs="gri_33125011196389_0655.tif" xml:id="eb03-16-s01-0649"/>
houſes, built pretty cloſely together, without any order, and having a winding path between them. They are generally flanked, towards the ſea, with detached walls, which are meant both for ſhelter and defence. Theſe walls conſiſt of looſe ſtones, and the inhabitants are very dexterous in ſhifting them ſuddenly to ſuch places as the direction of the attack may require. In the ſides of the hills, or ſurrounding eminences, they have alſo little holes, or caves, the entrance to which is alſo ſecured by a fence of the ſame kind. They ſerve for places of retreat in caſes of extremity, and may be defended by a ſingle perſon againſt ſeveral aſſailants. Their houſes are of different ſizes, ſome of them being large and commodious, from forty to fifty feet long, and from twenty to thirty broad; while others are mere hovels. The food of the lower claſs conſiſts principally of fiſh and vegetables, to which the people of higher rank add the fleſh of dogs and hogs. The manner of ſpending their time admits of little variety. They riſe with the ſun, and, after enjoying the cool of the evening, retire to reſt, a few hours after ſun-ſet. The making of canoes, mats, &amp;c. forms the occupations of the men; the women are employed in manufacturing cloth, and the ſervants are principally engaged in the plantations and ſiſhing. Their idle hours are filled up with various amuſements, ſuch as dancing, boxing, wreſtling, &amp;c. Their agriculture and navigation bear a great reſemblance to thoſe of the South-ſea iſlands. Their plantations, which are ſpread over the whole ſea coaſt, conſiſt of the taro, or eddy-root, and ſweet potatoes, with plants of the cloth-trees ſet in rows. The bottoms of their canoes are of a ſingle piece of wood, hollowed out to the thickneſs of an inch, and brought to a point at each end. The ſides conſiſt of three boards, each about an inch thick, neatly fitted and laſhed to the bottom part. Some of their double canoes meaſure 70 feet in length, three and a half in depth, and twelve in breadth. Their cordage, fiſh-hooks, and ſiſhing-tackle, differ but little from thoſe of the other iſlands. Among their arts muſt not be forgotten that of making ſalt, which they have in great abundance, and of a good quality. Their inſtruments of war are ſpears, daggers, clubs, and ſlings; and for defenſive armour they wear ſtrong mats, which are not eaſily penetrated by ſuch weapons as theirs. As the iſlands are not united under one ſovereign, wars are frequent among them, which, no doubt, contribute greatly to reduce the number of inhabitants, which, according to the proportion aſſigned to each iſland, does not exceed 400, 000. The ſame ſyſtem of ſubordination prevails here as at the other iſlands, the ſame abſolute authority on the part of the chiefs, and the ſame unreſiſting ſubmiſſion on the part of the people. The government is likewiſe monarchical and hereditary. At Owhyhee there is a regular ſociety of prieſts living by themſelves, and diſtinct in all reſpects from the reſt of the people. Human ſacriſices are here frequent; not only at the commencement of a war, or any ſignal enterpriſe, but the death of every conſiderable chief calls for a repetition of theſe horrid rites. Notwithſtanding the irreparable loſs in the death of captain Cook, who was here murdered through ſudden reſentment and violence, they are acknowledged to be of the moſt mild and affectionate diſpoſition. They live in the utmoſt harmony and friendſhip with each other; and in hoſpitality to ſtrangers they are not exceeded</p><p>even by the inhabitants of the Friendly Iſlands. Their natural capacity ſeems, in no reſpect, below the common ſtandard of mankind; and their improvements in agriculture, and the perfection of their manufactures, are certainly adequate to the circumſtances of their ſituation, and the natural advantages which they enjoy.</p></div></body></text></TEI>