<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>891. From the end of the 13th century it was the ordinary custom to choose the pope from the bishops ; and from 1592 to 1775 only three were elected who had not been bishops previously. Clement XIV., Pius V., and Gregory XVI. were simple priests when elected to the papacy. The cardinals, to whom the election of the pontiff is reserved, generally select one of their own body for this important position. The privilege of consecrating the pope is reserved to the cardinal bishop of Ostia. From the moment of election the pope may perform all acts appertaining to his jurisdiction, such as granting indulgences, issuing censures, giving dispensations, canonizing saints, instituting bishops, creating cardinals, and suchlike. The powers inherent in the priesthood and episcopate, such as the remission of sins, the administration of the sacraments of confirmation, holy orders, &lt;fec., he cannot exercise unless he be ordained and consecrated. Hence the office of sovereign pontiff is a dignity not of order but of jurisdiction. His pronouncements are regarded as infallible when he defines a doctrine regarding faith and morals to be held by the whole church.</p><p>The office of pope is elective (see Conclave), and lasts during the life of the occupant, although he may renounce his dignity. When the election has taken place the fact is made known by the cardinal dean. Many ceremonies follow, such as coronation and taking possession of the cathedral church of Rome, St John Lateran. This latter ceremony is not strictly necessary, for after his coronation the pope enjoys the papal power in all its plenitude ; but its object is his enthronization as bishop of the city and diocese of Rome and patriarch of the West. The cardinals are the princes and senators of the church, counsellors of the pontiff, co-operators with him, and vicars in the functions of the pontificate (see Cardinal). To Pope Evaris-tus, fifth successor of St Peter, is attributed the creation of the first <hi rend="italic">titles</hi>  or parishes of Rome, the occupants of which were afterwards known as cardinals. At the beginning of the 3d century twenty-five of these titles existed. In the course of time they were increased to fifty and afterwards to seventy. In the <hi rend="italic">Gerarchia Cattolica</hi>  the titles are thus divided : suburban sees (cardinal bishops), 6 ; titular churches (cardinal priests), 52 ; and diaconates (cardinal deacons), 16 ; making a total of 7 4. The cardinalate, in the sense at present attached to it, is different from what it was in earlier ages, being now the highest dignity after the papacy. The greater part of the administration of the church—the chief subject of this article—is directed by the cardinals who are members of congregations, which correspond, in a certain measure, to the political ministries in modern states. These congregations are established in Rome by the sovereign pontiff, and their objects are to inquire into, discuss, and decide the important affairs of the whole church and of the temporal dominions of the holy see. The cardinals are assisted by consultors or prelates, by distinguished ecclesiastics secular and regular, and by other officials appointed by the pope.</p><p>The head of every congregation is a cardinal prefect, though some congregations have the pope as prefect, <hi rend="italic">e.g., </hi>the holy office, the apostolic visit, and the consistory. The secretary is ordinarily a prelate ; in the holy office he is a cardinal. The acts, decrees, rescripts, and letters issued in the name of a congregation are subscribed generally by the prefect, and always by the secretary. These two officials chiefly regulate the affairs of the congregation and submit to the pope, at periodical audiences, the matters which require his approval. The following are the more important congregations : — inquisition, consistorial, apostolic visit, bishops and regulars, council, residence of bishops, state of regulars, ecclesiastical immunities, propaganda fide, propaganda fide for Oriental affairs, commission for correction of books of the Oriental Church, index, sacred rites, ceremonial, regular discipline, indulgences and relics, examination of bishops, <hi rend="italic">fabbrica</hi>  of St Peter’s, extraordinary ecclesiastical affairs and studies. The congregation of the <hi rend="italic">Holy Roman Inquisition</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">Holy Office</hi>  (see Inquisition) occupies the first place in regard to the quality of the matters of which it treats, as well as from its antiquity. Its object is the extirpation of heresies. It was formally established by Innocent III. (1198-1216), on the suggestion of St Dominic. The following class of cases falls within its judgment :—crimes of heresy and heretical blasphemy, simultaneous polygamy, robbery of the sacred particles accompanied by insult offered to the same, solicitations <hi rend="italic">ad turpia</hi>  with abuse of sacramental confession, affected sanctity, contempt of sacred images, divination and sorcery, retention and reading of heretical books, &amp;c. This congregation also proceeds against any one who, having been baptized, returns to paganism ; against any one who celebrates mass or hears confessions, not being a priest ; against false witnesses who depose in causes of faith, &lt;fcc. Its authority extends, in matters of faith, over every person of whatsoever grade, condition, or dignity, whether bishops, magistrates, or communities, and no local or personal privilege exempts from its jurisdiction. Bishops, according to the council of Trent, being subject to the pope only, the Inquisition may institute inquiries, but may not pronounce sentence, this being reserved to the pontiff. <hi rend="italic">Consistorial,</hi>  instituted by Sixtus V., 1587, considers and judges on matters appertaining to the erection of new metropolitan or cathedral churches, or their limits ; instances of bishops who desire to resign their churches ; matters relating to chapters and the confirmation or exclusion of subjects elected by them to metropolitan, episcopal, or monastic dignities ; the examination of coadjutors ; presentations or nominations of bishops made by sovereign princes and republics ; concession of rights to the pallium ; retention of dignities and major benefices incompatible with episcopal rights, and suchlike. The <hi rend="italic">Apostolic Visit</hi>  insists on the observance of that decree of the council of Trent which enjoins, as a duty, that every bishop shall visit in person or by means of a delegate the churches, pious institutions, &lt;fcc., in his diocese. <hi rend="italic">Bishops and Regulars</hi>  : this congregation has to do chiefly with the government of monasteries and with complaints from the inmates of these against bishops. It examines new institutions and their constitution ; the founding of new monasteries for both sexes, and the removal of subjects from one monastery to another ; questions regarding the alienation of the ecclesiastical property of regulars ; differences between ordinaries, parish priests, and regulars ; and a variety of questions of a similar nature. The <hi rend="italic">Council</hi>  : the fathers of the council of Trent, anticipating that doubts might arise concerning the interpretation of the doctrines and decrees published therein, besought Pius IV. to provide in the most fitting manner for such contingencies. This the pontiff did in approving and solemnly confirming the- council in the bull <hi rend="italic">Benedictus Deus</hi>  (1563), interdicting, under severe penalties, any person whatsoever, secular or ecclesiastic, from publishing commentaries, glosses, &amp;c., or any interpretation whatsoever, upon the decrees of the council of Trent, it being enacted that all controversies, questions, and doubts should be submitted to the congregation of the council. The object of this congregation, therefore, is the interpretation of these doctrines and decrees. The congregation of <hi rend="italic">Residence of Bishops</hi>  may be considered as auxiliary to that of the council. It treats of the questions which concern the bishops’ obligation to reside in their own dioceses, —-a most important matter treated of in the council of Trent. Even in 1352 Innocent VI. ordered, under pain</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>