<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Besides Skinks and Geckos, terrestrial Agamidæ and Varanidæ are well represented ; Pygopodidæ. EryeiJlæ, Rythonidæ, and Boidæ are autochthonous, whilst a small number of innocuous Colubriues are immigrants from the East Indies. The poisonous Snakes surpass in number the non-poisonous, and belong to the Elapidæ.</p><p>5.    Madagascar possesses Chelydidæ and Testudinidæ without Trionyx, like South America. A species of Crocodile. Chamæ-leontidæ more differentiated here than in Africa, with which it has also Cerrhosauridæ and Zonuridæ in common ; Agamidæ are replaced by the South-American Iguanidæ. Snakes chiefly South-American ; no poisonous Snake.</p><p>6.    The Tropical American Region is characterized by the full development of Testudinidæ and Chelydidæ and absence of Trionyx ; Emydoids are immigrants from the north. Crocodiles and Alligators. Lacertilians numerous in families and species, the majority being Iguanidæ ; the Old-World Lacertidæ replaced by Tejidæ. Other families, Angiddæ, Amq)hisbænidœ, Eiiblepharidæ, Helodermatidæ, &amp;c., well represented. Snakes numerous : Boidæ and Scytalidæ ; Ground Snakes, Colubers, and Tree Snakes abundant, less so Freshwater Snakes ; Tropidonotus almost absent. Poisonous Snakes in the proportion of species as 1 : 8, and comprising Crotalidæ and Elaps.</p><p>7.    The North-American Region differs from the Tropical in possessing the Emydidæ in their full development and Trionyx ; only one Testudo. One Alligator. As regards Lacertilians and Ophidians this region occupies the same relation to tropical South America as the Palæarctic region does to Africa and India.</p><p>8.    New Zealand is characterized by the possession of the Rhynchocephalian type, without any other Reptile with the exception of certain Skinks and Geckos.</p><p>Arranging these primary divisions of the globe in accordance with the distribution of the several orders of Reptiles, we find that with regard to Chelonians the regions stand in the following relation to each other :—</p><p>I. Emydidæ fully developed.</p><p>A. Trionycidæ fully developed.</p><p>1. Testudinidæ in small numbers or immigrants : a. Indian-Palæaretic regions, and b. North-American region (including Central America).</p><p>IL Chelydidæ fully developed.</p><p>A.    Trionycidæ fully developed.</p><p>1. Testudinidæ fully developed : African region.</p><p>B.    Trionycidæ absent.</p><p>1.    Testudinidæ fully developed : α. Tropical American</p><p>region, and b. Madagascar.</p><p>2.    Testudinidæ absent : Tropical Pacific region.</p><p>III. Chelonians entirely absent : New Zealand</p><p>The types of Crocodilian and Rhynchocephalian orders are too few in number and either very widely or very locally distributed, so that no general division of the globe’s surface can be based upon them alone.</p><p>The two large Lacertilian families <hi rend="italic">Geckonidæ</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">Scirtcidæ</hi>  are generally distributed over the warmer parts of the globe, and therefore not well adapted for the distinction of the primary regions. Nevertheless, in a more detailed account many of the genera would have to come into consideration, being confined to more or less limited areas. Both families are represented in great variety in Australia, but scantily in South America. With regard to other families the regions can be arranged thus :—</p><p>I. Agamidæ and Varanidæ fully developed.</p><p>A.    Chamæleontidæ, Lacertidæ, and Amphisbænidæ: African</p><p>region (including as sub-region the Western Palæarctic portion, characterized by Anguidæ).</p><p>B.    Amphisbænidæ and Chamæleons (except one species)</p><p>absent ; Lacertidæ few : Indian region with Manchurian sub-region.</p><p>C.    Pygopodidæ : Tropical Pacific region.</p><p>IL Iguanidæ fully developed.</p><p>A.    Chamæleontidæ : Madagascar.</p><p>B.    Tejidæ, Amphisbænidæ, and Anguidæ : Sοutlc-American</p><p>and North-American regions.</p><p>III. Skinks and Geckos only : New Zealand.</p><p>Of the families of Ophidians the <hi rend="italic">Pythonidæ</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">Boidæ,</hi>  the <hi rend="italic">Crotalidæ</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">Vipemdæ,</hi>  the <hi rend="italic">Lycodontidæ</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">Scytalidæ</hi>  replace each other in their distribution, and are, therefore, best adapted for determining the relations of the zoological regions. Although the first two are so far as we know at present the geologically oldest types, and therefore might be employed in the first instance in the arrangement of the regions, their distribution is limited to the equatorial zone, and fails to show the close relations existing between the temperate and equatorial parts of the Old World on the one hand and those of the New on the other. The relations of Madagascar to Tropical America are in the following scheme less distinctly expressed than they are in nature.</p><p>I. Viperidæ fully developed.</p><p>A.    Pythonidæ and Lycodontidæ : African region.</p><p>B.    Tropidonoti and true Colubers : western portion of the</p><p>Europo-Asiatic region.</p><p>IL Crotalidæ fully developed.</p><p>A.    Pythonidæ and Lycodontidæ in the tropical parts ;</p><p>Tropidonoti and true Colubers ; none of the Crotalines with rattles : Indian region (including Manchuria).</p><p>B.    Tropidonoti and true Colubers ; some of the Crotalines</p><p>with rattles ; intermediate between the Manchurian sub-region and tropical America : North-American region.</p><p>C.    Boidæ and Scytalidæ : Trop)ixal-American region</p><p>III.    Colubrine venomous Snakes only.</p><p>A. Pythonidæ and Boidæ : Tropical Pacific region.</p><p>IV.    Venomous Snakes entirely absent.</p><p>A. Boidæ : Madagascar.</p><p>V. Snakes entirely absent : New Zealand.    (A. Ç. G. )</p><p>REQUENA, a town of Spain, in the province of Valencia, 41 miles to the west of that city on the road to Cuenca, occupies a strong position near the river 01eana in the rocky mountainous district called Las Cabrillas separating Valencia from Castile. It is commanded by a castle, and still has traces of the walls that anciently encircled it. The tower of the church of San Salvador is the only other feature of architectural interest. The principal industries are those connected with the culture of grain, fruit, wine, saffron, and silk. The population of the municipality in 1877 was 13,527.</p><p>RESERVOIR. See Waterworks.</p><p>RESHAL, <hi rend="italic">i.e., </hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Rabbenu Shelomoh Loria (or Luria, </hi><hi rend="italic">vulgo</hi>  Lurye), was one of the famous “ Five@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi>  Sages ” (Rabbis) of the 16th century. His father’s name was</p><lb/><p>R. Yehiel of Ostroff (S. W. Russia), a descendant of Rashi@@<hi rend="smallcaps"><hi rend="sup">2</hi></hi>  (<hi rend="italic">q.v.</hi>). He is also known under the name of Rashal, or Maharshal (<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>, Morenu Harab R. Shelomoh Loria). He himself was chief rabbi of Lublin, where he died in 1573. His works are of importance on account of the numerous, though only incidental, notices they contain in connexion with the history of Jewish literature. We name six of these works—one edition of each</p><p>(1) Hokhmath Shelomoh, discussions on the Babylonian Talmud, Rashi, the Tosaphoth, &amp;c. This work is now an integral part of the Talmud editions. (2) Yamshel Shelomoh·.—(a) on Yomtob (or Besah), Lublin, 1636, and reprints ; (b) on Yebamoth, Altona, 1739 ; (c) on Kethuboth (first four perakim), Stettin, 1862 ; (d) on Kiddu-shin, Berlin, 1766 ; (e) on Gittin, Berlin, 1761, and reprint ; (f) on Bobo Kammo, Prague, 1616, and reprint ; (g) on Hullin, Cracow, 1646, and reprints. All these are in folio. (3) Yeri'oth Shelomoh, supercommentary on Rashi on the Pentateuch, with special reference to Mizrahi’s supercommentary, Prague, 1608, 4to. (4) 'Atereth Shelomoh, on the Illicüa et Licita of R. Yishak of Düren, Basel. 1599, and reprint, folio. (5) 'Ammτιde Shelomoh, on the Sephcr Hammisvoth of R. Mosheh of Coucy, Basel, 1599, 4to. (6) Re-sponsa, Lublin, 1574, 4to, and reprints in folio. (S. M. S.-S.)</p><lb/><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi> The other four were—(1) R. Mosheh Isserls of Cracow (the celebrated “ Rema”) ; (2) R. Lewa b. Besaleel (the great Halakhist and Cabbalist), chief rabbi of Prague ; (3) R. Mordekhai Yaphe (the author of the Lebushim∖ chief rabbi of Posen, &amp;c. ; and (4), last hut not least, R. Yoseph Caro, principal of the academy of Safed in Palestine, and compiler of the normative Shulhan Αrukh.</p><lb/><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">2</hi> Yarn shel Shelomoh, on Yebamoth, iv. 33.</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>