<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Giving Drink to the Thirsty, was made by Filippo Pala-dini of Pistoia in 1585; this last is of terra-cotta, not enamelled, but simply painted with oil colours. Giovanni also executed the medallions in the spandrels of the arches under this frieze, with reliefs of the Annunciation, the Visitation, and the Coronation of the Virgin.</p><p>A large octagonal font of enamelled clay, with pilasters at the angles and panels between them with scenes from the life of the Baptist, in the church of S. Leonardo at Cerreto Guidi, is a work of the school of Giovanni ; the reliefs are pictorial in style and coarse in execution. Giovanni’s chief pupil was a man named Santi, who was at first apprenticed to Buglioni,@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi>  and when the latter died in 1521 lie went into Giovanni’s bottega. His work is very inferior to that of his master.</p><p>VII. Girolamo della Robbia (1488-1566), another of Andrea’s sons, was an architect and a sculptor in marble and bronze as well as in enamelled clay. During the first part of his life he, like his brothers, worked with his father, but in 1528 he went to France and spent nearly forty years in the service of the French royal family. Francis I. employed him to build a palace in the Bois de Boulogne called the Château de Madrid. This was a large well-designed building, four stories high, two of them having open loggie in the Italian fashion. Girolamo decorated it richly with terra-cotta medallions, friezes, and other architectural features.@@<hi rend="sup">2</hi>  For this purpose he set up kilns at Suresnes. Though the palace itself has been destroyed, drawings of it exist.@@<hi rend="sup">3</hi></p><p>The best collections of Robbia ware are in the Florentine Bargello and Accademia, the South Kensington Museum (the finest out of Italy), the Louvre, the Cluny, and the Berlin Museums. Many fine specimens exist in Paris in the private collections of M. Alphonse de Rothschild, M. Gavel, and M. Dreyfus. The greater part of the Robbia work still remains in the churches and other buildings of Italy, especially in Florence, Fiesole, Arezzo, La Verna, Volterrä, Barga, Montepulciano, Lucca, Pistoia, Prato, and Siena. The best accounts of the Della Robbia family are those given by De Jouy, <hi rend="italic">Les Della Robbia,</hi>  Paris, 1855 ; Bode, <hi rend="italic">Die Künstlerfamilie Della Robbia,</hi>  Leipsic, 1878 ; and Cavallucci and Molinier, <hi rend="italic">Les Della Robbia,</hi>  Paris, 1884, an ably-written and well-illustrated work. See also Vasari, ed. Milanesi, Florence, 1880, ii. p. 167 <hi rend="italic">sq.</hi>, and various works on Italian sculpture.    (J. H. M.)</p><p>ROBERT I., king of France, son and successor of Hugh Capet, was born at Orleans in 971 and died at Melun in 1031. See France, vol. ix. p. 536. He is sometimes cited as Robert II., Robert I. being then taken to mean Robert, duke of France (ο<hi rend="italic">b</hi>. 923), the second son of Robert “ the Strong ” <hi rend="italic">(ob.</hi>  866) ; comp. France, vol. ix. p. 535.</p><p>ROBERT, called The Bruce@@<hi rend="smallcaps"><hi rend="sup">4</hi></hi>  (1274-1329), king of Scotland, was the son of the seventh Robert de Bruce, lord of Annandale in his own right and earl of Carrick in right of his wife Marjory, daughter of Neil, second earl, and thus was of mingled Norman @@<hi rend="sup">5</hi>  and Celtic blood. His grandfather, the sixth Robert de Bruce, claimed the crown of Scotland as son of Isabella, second daughter of David, earl of Huntingdon ; but Baliol, grandson of Margaret, the eldest daughter, was preferred by the commissioners of Edward I. The birthplace of the Bruce—perhaps Turn-berry, his mother’s castle, on the coast of Ayr—is not certainly known. His youth is said by an English chronicle to have been passed at the court of Edward I. At an age when the mind is quick to receive the impressions which give the bent to life he must have watched the progress of the great suit for the crown of Scotland. Its issue in favour of Baliol led to the resignation of Annandale by Bruce the competitor to his son, the Bruce’s father, who, either then or after the death of the aged competitor in 1295, assumed the title of lord of Annandale. Two years before he had resigned, on the death of his wife, the earldom of Carrick to Robert the Bruce, who presented the deed of resignation to Baliol at Stirling on 3d August 1293, and offered the homage which his father, like his grandfather, was unwilling to render. Feudal law required that the king should take sasine of the earldom before regranting it and receiving the homage, and the sheriff of Ayr was directed to take it on Baliol’s behalf. As the disputes between Edward and Baliol, which ended in Baliol losing the kingdom, commenced in this year it is doubtful whether Bruce ever rendered homage ; but he is henceforth known as earl of Carrick, though in a few instances this title is still given to his father. Both father and son sided with Edward against Baliol. Towards the end of 1292 the elder Robert had a safe-conduct from Edward to visit Norway with a daughter, Isabella, who married Erik, king of Norway, the widower of Margaret of Scotland,—a fact marking the high standing of the family of Bruce. On 20th April 1294 the younger Robert, earl of Carrick, had a similar safe-conduct or permission to visit Ireland till Michaelmas and a year following, and a further mark of Edward’s favour by a respite for the same period of all debts due by him to the exchequer. His father, having done homage to Edward, was entrusted in October 1295 with the custody of the castle of Carlisle by a patent in which he is styled lord of Annandale; and Baliol retaliated by seizing Annandale, which he conferred on John Cornyn, earl of Buchan. On 28th August 1296 Robert de Bruce “ le vieil ” and Robert de Bruce “ le jeune,” earl of Carrick, swore fealty to Edward at Berwick ; but (according to Hemingford), in breach of this oath, renewed at Carlisle on the Gospels and the sword of Thomas a Becket, the young earl joined Wallace, who had raised the standard of Scottish independence in the name of Baliol after that weak king had himself surrendered his kingdom to Edward. Urgent letters were sent ordering Bruce to support Warenne, Edward’s general, in the summer of 1297; but, instead of complying, he, along with the bishop of Glasgow and the steward of Scotland, laid waste the lands of those who adhered to Edward. On 7th July Percy forced Bruce and his friends to make terms by the treaty called the Capitulation of Irvine. The Scottish lords were not to serve beyond the sea against their will and were pardoned for their recent violence, while in return they owned allegiance to Edward. The bishop of Glasgow, the steward, and Sir Alexander Lindesay became sureties for Bruce until he delivered his daughter Marjory as a hostage. Wallace almost alone maintained the struggle for freedom which the nobles as well as Baliol had given up, and Bruce had no part in the honour of Stirling Bridge or the reverse of Falkirk, where in the following year Edward in person recovered what his generals had lost and drove Wallace into exile. Shortly afterwards Bruce appears again to have sided with his countrymen ; Annandale was wasted and Lochmaben taken by Clifford, while Bruce (according</p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi>    Benedetto Buglioni (1461-1521) appears to have produced enamelled ware independently of the Robbia family. In 1484 he made a relief of the Harrowing of Hell for the Servite monks at Florence; see Baldinucci,<hi rend="italic">NotiziedF Prοfcssοri del Disegno,</hi>  Milan, 1811, vi. p. 18.</p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">2</hi>    The Sèvres Museum possesses some fragments of these decorations.</p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">3</hi>    See Laborde,<hi rend="italic">Château de Madrid,</hi>  Paris, 1853, and <hi rend="italic">Comptes des Bâtiments du Roi,</hi>  Paris, 1877-80, in which a full account is given of Girolamo’s work in connexion with this palace.</p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">4</hi>    For Robert II. (1316-1390) and Robert III. (d. 1406) of Scotland, see Scotland.</p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">5</hi>    The first Robert de Bruce, a follower of William the Conqueror, was rewarded by the gift of many manors, chiefly in Yorkshire, of which Skelton was the principal. His son, the second Robert, received from David I., his comrade at the court of Henry I., a grant of the lordship of Annandale, and his grandson, the third Robert, siding with David against Stephen at the battle of the Standard, became a Scottish instead of an English baron. The fourth Robert maιτied Isobel, natural daughter of William the Lion, and their son, the fifth Robert, married Isabella, second daughter of David, earl of Huntingdon, niece of the same Scottish king. Thus royal kin made natural the ambition to gain a crown,—an object not beyond the ambition of a powerful noble in feudal times.</p><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>