<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>of his situations and the names of the English localities in which his scenes are laid. Three other Spanish romances may be mentioned here. Though the earliest printed edition of <hi rend="italic">Oliveros y Artus</hi>  is in French, the work (printed in Spanish at Burgos in 1499) is undoubtedly of Spanish origin. It has been popular in all languages. An English version came from the press of Wynkyn de Worde in 1518. <hi rend="italic">Felix Marte de Hyrcania</hi>  (Valladolid, 1556), by Melchor Ortega, is chiefly remarkable as having been read by Dr Samuel Johnson, who is likely to have been the only person since the 16th century capable of such a feat. The <hi rend="italic">Guerras de Granada</hi>  (1595-1619) of Perez de Hita contains some of the finest ballads in the language, and is an interesting and well-written fiction. The first (and best) part deals with the reign of the last Moorish king of Granada, and the second part relates the final ruin of the Moors in Philip III.’s reign.—Another favourite fiction in many lands is that in which a chaste wife is wrongfully accused of infidelity and punished. The character even appears among the earliest ballads of the Charlemagne cycle (Z&lt;τ <hi rend="italic">reine Sibelle)</hi>  ; but here we have to mention three distinct narratives which have attracted generations of readers, and which are widely known from their adoption by many writers. These are <hi rend="italic">Patient Grizel (Griseldis), Genevieve of Brabant,</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">La belle Helene.</hi>  The story in each is similar, and the plot or some of the incidents may be traced in the <hi rend="italic">Lai del Fresne</hi>  of Marie de France (c. 1220), in the Latin legendary history of St Geneviève (written about 1272), in several old monkish lives of St Helena of Constantinople, in the late romances of <hi rend="italic">Valentine and Orson, Florent et Lyon,</hi>  and other stories,—the heroine being variously described as the Chaste Empress, the Chaste Queen, or the Chaste Duchess. The most celebrated of these stories is that of Griseldis. She is said to have been the wife of Walter, marquis of Saluces or Saluzzo, in the llth century, and her misfortunes were considered to belong to actual history when they were handled by Boccaccio and Petrarch, although the probability is that Boccaccio borrowed his narrative from a Provençal <hi rend="italic">fabliau. </hi>He included it in the recitations of the tenth day <hi rend="italic">(Deca-merone),</hi>  and must have written it about 1350. Petrarch Latinized it in 1373, and his translation formed the basis of much of the later literature. These works, however, really belong to a different class from that treated here, and may be referred to popular tales, like the narratives which have been repeated in many forms and in many lands from the time of Bidpai downwards. The prose French romance, <hi rend="italic">La Patience de Griselidis</hi>  (Bréhan-Loudéac, 1484), was derived from Petrarch, as also Chaucer’s narrative in the <hi rend="italic">Canterbury Tales,</hi>  and the Elizabethan drama in which Dekker was a collaborateur.—The <hi rend="italic">De Duobus Amantibus</hi>  (or <hi rend="italic">Eurialus and Lucretiaj</hi>  of Æneas Sylvius is usually included amongst romances, but it is rather an historical novel based upon the imperial court gossip of his own day.—The Spanish <hi rend="italic">Carcel de Amor,</hi>  composed about 1480-90 by Diego de San Pedro, is also a novel; the famous or infamous <hi rend="italic">Cdestina</hi>  is a drama of surpassing vigour and interest ; and the pastoral romances of <hi rend="italic">Diana, Pastor Fido,</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">Arcadia</hi>  belong to a different class from that of mediæval romance.—As much may be said of the English romances produced in the 16th and the earlier part of the 17th century, which are chiefly weak novelistic imitations of the later adjuncts to <hi rend="italic">Amαdis</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">Palmerin.— </hi>The <hi rend="italic">Seven Champions of Christendom</hi>  is a popular tale.— The <hi rend="italic">Romance of the Fox {Reynard the Fox)</hi>  and the <hi rend="italic">Roman de la Rose</hi>  likewise belong to totally distinct orders of literature, the former to that of tales ( <hi rend="italic">Volksbücher)</hi>  and the latter to the large class of allegorical poems.—The Norman stories of <hi rend="italic">Robert the Devil</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">Robert of Sicily </hi>are also popular tales.</p><p>III. Modern Romance to the 17th Century.</p><p>The inspiration of mediæval romance is gone ; but it is necessary briefly to trace its final reflexions to the close of the 17 th century, when prose fiction began to assume more definitely the character of the modern novel.</p><p>We have seen how large a place in the history of romances is occupied by France down to the end of the 16th century. We first meet with the so-called “pastoral romance” in French in <hi rend="italic">HAstree</hi>  (1612) of Honoré d’Urfé, an enormous work inspired by Montemayor, which, however, La Rochefoucauld found interesting. It was frequently reprinted and had many continuations and imitations. Camus de Pontcarré wrote in opposition religious pastorals such as <hi rend="italic">Palombe.</hi>  ∙ To the same class belong <hi rend="italic">Florù et Cleonthe</hi>  (1613) by Moulinet du Parc, <hi rend="italic">Les Bergeries de Vesper</hi>  (1618) by G. Coste, <hi rend="italic">Chryserionte de Gaule</hi>  (1620) by De Sonan, <hi rend="italic">Le Courtisan Solitaire</hi>  (1622) by J. Lourdelot, <hi rend="italic">Le Mêlante</hi>  (1624) by L. Videl, <hi rend="italic">L'Endimion</hi>  (1624) by J. Ogier de Gombauld, <hi rend="italic">Cleomèdes et Sophonisbe</hi>  (1627) by De Gerzan, <hi rend="italic">Le Berger Extravagant</hi>  (1627) by Ch. Sorel, <hi rend="italic">Anax-andre et Grazie</hi>  (1629) by Boisrobert, <hi rend="italic">Ariane</hi>  (1632) and <hi rend="italic">Roxane</hi>  (1639) by J. Des Marets. Le Roy de Gomberville led the way to the new school of French romance in <hi rend="italic">Polexaηdre</hi>  (1632-39) and <hi rend="italic">La Cytheree</hi>  (1640-42), which were the models for the still more ponderous productions of La Calprenède and De Scudéry. <hi rend="italic">La jeune Alcidiane </hi>(1651), an unfinished continuation of <hi rend="italic">Polexaηdre,</hi>  was completed by Mademoiselle M. A. Gomez. These form a link between the genuine romance of chivalry and the so-called heroic style. We still meet with giants and extravagant exploits. The adventures with pirates and the sea scenes show the influence of translations of Greek novels. Madeleine de Scudéry produced her romances under the name of her eccentric brother Georges, but the authorship was well known. The first to appear was <hi rend="italic">Ibrahim, ou VIllustre Passa</hi>  (1641); then the work for which she is best known, <hi rend="italic">Aitamène, ou le Grand Cyrus</hi>  (10 vols., 1649-53); <hi rend="italic">Clelie, histoire romaine</hi>  (10 vols., 1650-53), contains the famous “carte du pays de Tendre”; then came <hi rend="italic">Almahide, ou VEsclave Reyne</hi>  (1660), <hi rend="italic">Les Femmes Illustres</hi>  (1665), and <hi rend="italic">La Promenade de Versailles</hi>  (1669). One of the causes of her great popularity was her representation of living characters under flimsy disguise. Keys to <hi rend="italic">Le Grand Cyrus </hi>have been published. Gauthier de Costes, chevalier de la Calprenède, wrote <hi rend="italic">Cassandre</hi>  (1642-50); <hi rend="italic">Cléopâtre</hi>  (12 vols., 1647-58), the best of his works, which contains the character of Juba satirized by Boileau; <hi rend="italic">Faramond</hi>  (12 vols., 1661-70), continued by Pierre Dortigue de Vau-morière; and <hi rend="italic">Les Nouvelles</hi>  (1661). In spite of their appalling length and their tedious conversations and descriptions, La Calprenède’s romances are not without merit. The author has imagination, and his heroes have a share of the noble sentiments of their predecessors. <hi rend="italic">Berenice </hi>(1648) by J. R. de Segrais, <hi rend="italic">La Précieuse</hi>  (1656-58) by Mich, de Pure, <hi rend="italic">Histoire du Temps</hi>  (1654) and <hi rend="italic">Marcarise </hi>(1664), both by Hédelin, and the mystical romances of the Jesuit Ceriziers, belong to the same school. Nearly all the familiar machinery of the old romances is now absent : we no longer meet with dragons, necromancers, giants, and enchanted castles. Formerly love was secondary to heroic achievement ; now it becomes the ruling passion, and knightly deeds are performed only to excite the applauding smile of a mistress and not for the sake of military glory. The jargon of gallantry used in these fictions exercised an evil influence upon contemporary literature, until it was laughed out of existence by the <hi rend="italic">Précieuses Ridicules</hi>  of Molière and the dialogue of Boileau on <hi rend="italic">Les Héros de Roman.</hi>  Such works as <hi rend="italic">Marie Stuart</hi>  (1675) by P. Le Pesant de Boisguilbert, <hi rend="italic">Nouvelles d<hi rend="sup">,</hi>Elisabeth</hi>  (1680),</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>