<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>margin of the jaws and the palatines soon wear down to form mere enamelled cutting edges to the bones, with which they become immediately anchyloscd. The extinct Dicynodonts, with their large</p><lb/><p>canine-like teeth, growing from permanent pulps, behind the edentulous beak-like front part of the mouth, and those Ornitho-sauria which similarly have an edentulous beak in front of the toothed parts of their jaws, may but have</p><p>carried out further and more completely</p><p>that process of tooth reduction which wo</p><p>find to be effected with age in Hatteria.</p><p>The liver consists of two lateral lobes.</p><p>There is a pair of anal glands.</p><p>The Crocodilia have teeth in the max-</p><p>illæ, premaxillæ, and mandible, but none</p><p>in the palatines or pterygoids. They are</p><p>implanted in distinct alveoli. The tongue</p><p>is so flat and closely attached to the floor</p><p>of the mouth that it can hardly be con</p><p>sidered as having a distinct existence. A</p><p>transverse fold of membrane extends along</p><p>its hinder border and another similar fold</p><p>descends in front of the posterior nares.</p><p>There are no salivary glands.</p><p>The oesophagus is wide, and the stomach</p><p>nearly circular and gizzard-like, having thick muscular walls formed of fibres radiating from central tendons. The small intestine consists of two parts,—an anterior part much convoluted, thin-walled, and lined with villi, which is succeeded by a thicker-walled part with internal zig-zag folds. There is no cæcum, but a circular prominence marks the commencement of the large intestine, which is short and wide with a smooth lining. It is funnel-shaped, and opens by a very narrow aperture into a very elongated cloaca, the external opening of which is rather longitudinal.</p><p>The liver, like that of Hatteria, is in two lobes, and the gallbladder is beside the right lobe. The spleen lies behind the</p><lb/><p>pancreas between the folds of the duodenum. The various viscera of the abdominal cavity lie, as in Birds, in separate serous sacs.@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi></p><p>In the Chelonia there are horny sheaths to the jaws but no teeth, though numerous rudiments of teeth have been found in the embryo of Triοηyx.@@<hi rend="sup">2</hi> The tongue is not extensible, but is differently conditioned in different genera. There appears to be only a sublingual salivary gland, though the palate of the Land Tortoise exhibits the apertures of numerous cutaneous follicles.</p><p>The oesophagus leads to the left part of the transversely placed stomach. The extent of both the small and the large intestine varies; the latter is at its shortest in Trionyx. The cloaca opens externally by a somewhat rounded aperture.</p><p>The liver is mostly large, and in two lobes connected by one or more transverse bands of its substance. The gall-bladder lies on its right and may be sunk within its substance. The pancreas has often several excretory ducts, and the spleen is generally of large size.</p><p><hi rend="italic">The Respiratory System.</hi></p><p>All the <hi rend="italic">Reptilia</hi>  breathe air from the first moment of their separate existence, and are never furnished with anything in the shape of gills. The apparatus by which their respiration is effected is always a pair of sacs or lungs —whereof one sometimes aborts—into and from which air is introduced and removed by the intervention of an azygous tube, the trachea, which, passing forwards ventrally to the oesophagus, or beside it, opens in the floor of the mouth behind the tongue. The more or less dilated most anterior portion of the azygous tube is the larynx, which may become a vocal organ.</p><p>In the Laeertilia the external opening of the larynx may, by rare exception, as in Phryηosoma, be placed in front of the hind-most margin of the tongue, so that the larynx seems to perforate that organ, but is in fact merely enclosed by the posterior, exterior, and median junction of two lingual processes. A membranous or cartilaginous epiglottis may protect the entrance to the larynx as in Mammals. The larynx may be composed of one cartilage, which is produced anteriorly into two arytenoid processes, but generally these latter are distinct cartilages. Folds of membrane or vocal cords may exist, as in the Geckos and Chamæleons, and the latter have also a wide membranous sac connected with the larynx. The trachea is generally short, but may be long, as in Amphisbæna and Lepidosternon. It is never convoluted, and its cartilages may or may not form complete rings. It ends posteriorly by dividing into two bronchi, which are usually very short, but may be of moderate length, as in Psamrnosaurιιs. The lungs are generally of about equal size, but in the Snake-like Lizards the right lung is the longer, and sometimes, as in Typhline and Acοntias, the left lung may be quite rudimentary. The lungs may be simple bags or may give out lateral processes or pouches of varying extent. In the Chamæleons their hinder halves are prolonged into narrow tubular processes. Each lung is enclosed in a fold of peritoneum.</p><p>The Ophidia have the opening of the larynx behind the tongue rather prominent, with only a rudimentary epiglottis. The nature of their prey and their mode of eating do not readily expose them to the danger of small particles of food finding their way into the trachea. The cartilaginous framework of the larynx is very elongated. The trachea has its more anterior cartilages in the form of complete rings. The lungs are unsymmetrical in all the genera, but much more so in some than in others—one lung entirely aborting in Typhlops, Aeroelwrdus, and Viρera amongst others. The two lungs are both of tolerable size in Python, Boa, and Eryx, which have the bronchi leading from the trachea to the two pulmonary sacs. These sacs may or may not be divided into subordinate cells towards the hinder end of each. Sometimes part of the trachea itself may be dilated dorsally into cellular prominences like an accessory lung, as in Hydroplds, or ventrally, as in Aerochordus. A pulmonary sac may extend not only far backwards but also forwards to the hyoidean region, as in Heterodon.</p><p>In the Chelonia the opening of the larynx or glottis is longitudinal. It may be furnished with a membranous epiglottis, or may have none, as in Testudo. There may be cricoid and arytenoid cartilages in addition to main cartilages, but the details of structure differ in different genera. There are no vocal cords. The trachea and bronchi vary in length, the former being long in most forms, the latter in Testudo. In Cinixys the trachea and bronchi arc contorted. The lungs arc invested anteriorly and on their ventral side by peritoneum, and also by the diaphragm as they lie between it and the carapace, and therefore they do not project freely into the abdominal cavity.</p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi> Stannius pointed out emphatically, as long ago as 1856, the resemblance which exists in many points between Crocodiles and Birds. See his Amphibien, p. 193, note 1.</p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">2</hi> See Owen, Odontog., p. 179.</p></body></text></TEI>