<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p><hi rend="italic">gordo,</hi>  “stupid," Mod. Span, “fat,”—comp, <hi rend="italic">pinguis</hi>  Minerva; <hi rend="italic">pittaeium,</hi>  “patch,” “label,” <hi rend="italic">= πvrτ&lt;iιaοv,</hi>  Span, <hi rend="italic">ρedazo,</hi>  “piece”; <hi rend="italic">nanus,</hi>  “dwarf," = j'cwos, Ital. nano, Fr. nain ; <hi rend="italic">botulus,</hi>  “sausage" (also Petron.), dim. <hi rend="italic">bοtellus</hi>  (Martial), later = “bowels,” Ital. budello, plur. budella, Fr. boyaux. Lucretius (94-55) : <hi rend="italic">baubare, </hi>“bark,” Ital. abbajare, Fr. aboyer, Eng. bay; <hi rend="italic">russus,</hi>  “red”— a rare word, <hi rend="italic">russa</hi>  gingiva (Catull. ), mentioned as usual by Gellius —I tai. <hi rend="italic">r6sso,</hi>  “red,” Fr. <hi rend="italic">roux, rousse,</hi>  “red-haired.” Old words mentioned by Grammarians: <hi rend="italic">burrus</hi>  (see 11, above); <hi rend="italic">artitus=-</hi>bonis instructus artibus, Prov. <hi rend="italic">artisia,</hi>  “trade,” Fr. <hi rend="italic">artisan·, gluto</hi>  (Fest.), <hi rend="italic">glu,tto</hi>  (Persius and later), Ital. ghiottone, Fr. glouton (comp. Lat. <hi rend="italic">glut glut,</hi>  Fr. <hi rend="italic">glouglou) ; ρlanea</hi>  tabula plana, Fr. <hi rend="italic">planche,</hi>  Eng. plank; <hi rend="italic">sarpere</hi>  putare, “to imp,” Fr. <hi rend="italic">serpe,</hi>  “pruning knife."</p><p>C. <hi rend="italic">Grammar</hi>  (Plautine, when no author quoted).—Gender: <hi rend="italic">coUus</hi>  collum, Old Fr. <hi rend="italic">cols,</hi>  now <hi rend="italic">eou ; dor sus,</hi>  &amp;c. Declensions : <hi rend="italic">lade</hi>  lac, I tai. latte (Petron. unum <hi rend="italic">laetem</hi>  biberunt) ; <hi rend="italic">vasum, </hi>Umb. <hi rend="italic">vaso(r),</hi>  Ital. vaso ; <hi rend="italic">ossum,</hi>  Ital. osso, Fr. os; <hi rend="italic">pauper,-a,-um </hi>(also Petron. ), Ital. povero. Comparison : <hi rend="italic">magis</hi>  pulcer = Span. <hi rend="italic">mas</hi>  hermoso ; even <hi rend="italic">magis majores,</hi>  as vulg. Ital. <hi rend="italic">ρiiι meglio,</hi>  vulg. Fr. <hi rend="italic">plus meilleur,</hi>  vulg. Eng. <hi rend="italic">more better (er).</hi>  The ordinary Romance formation with <hi rend="italic">plus</hi>  only appears in the 3d period. With ego <hi rend="italic">ipsissumus,</hi>  “ my very self,” comp, <hi rend="italic">ipsimus,</hi>  “himself,” <hi rend="italic">ix., </hi>the master of the house (Petron.). Out of <hi rend="italic">(ρgp)md-iρsimυs</hi>  grew Ital. <hi rend="italic">medesimo,</hi>  Span, <hi rend="italic">mismo,</hi>  Fr. <hi rend="italic">même.</hi>  Pronouns : dat. fern, <hi rend="italic">illae </hi>for illî, Ital. <hi rend="italic">le</hi>  ; eccRm = ecce eum, Ital. <hi rend="italic">eeeo—</hi>pater eccwmadvenit= <hi rend="italic">eeeo</hi>  ehe viene il padre; <hi rend="italic">eeeiste,</hi>  eccZsZα = Old Fr. cist, ceste, Mod. Fr. ce, cet, cette; <hi rend="italic">eeeille, eeeilla =</hi>  Old Fr. cil, cele, Mod. Fr. celui, celle. In Italian these were replaced by <hi rend="italic">eeeum istum,</hi>  Ital. <hi rend="italic">questo, </hi>and <hi rend="italic">eeeum ilium,</hi>  Ital. <hi rend="italic">quello,</hi>  analogous to the Plautine <hi rend="italic">eeeum ipsum, eeeam eampse, kx. ; quotumus,</hi>  “which of the number”— <hi rend="italic">quotumo</hi>  die hue pervenisti ? Ital. lavorare a <hi rend="italic">eöttimo,</hi>  “work by the job.” <hi rend="italic">Unus</hi>  indefinite was sometimes very like the modern indefinite article—Huic filia <hi rend="italic">una</hi>  est, “he has a daughter,” Ital. quest’uomo ha wnα figlia. <hi rend="italic">Ille</hi>  was sometimes used very like the modern definite article—Imponit geminorum alterum in nave pater, <hi rend="italic">ilium</hi>  reliquit <hi rend="italic">alterum</hi>  apud matrem domi, Ital. lasciδ <hi rend="italic">l'altro</hi>  colla madré a casa. Note also <hi rend="italic">ηatus</hi>  nemo in aedibus, “not a living soul,” “not a mother’s son,” Span, <hi rend="italic">nαeiie,</hi>  “nobody,” likewise from <hi rend="italic">nata</hi>  (res), Span, <hi rend="italic">nada,</hi>  “nothing,” whereas the Catalan prefers <hi rend="italic">res,</hi>  Prov. <hi rend="italic">ren, re,</hi>  Fr. <hi rend="italic">rien</hi>  (rem). <hi rend="italic">Homo</hi>  is sometimes like an indefinite pronoun—Nequior nemo, quisquamst, quern <hi rend="italic">homo</hi>  aut amet aut adeat, Fr. <hi rend="italic">on.</hi>  Verbs : <hi rend="italic">moriri</hi>  mori, Ital. <hi rend="italic">morire,</hi>  Fr. mourir. Active for deponent—<hi rend="italic">joeare,</hi>  Ital. giocare, Fr. jouer, <hi rend="italic">part ire</hi>  = I tai. ; <hi rend="italic">fabu,lare,</hi>  Span, <hi rend="italic">hablar.</hi>  Perfects in <hi rend="italic">si—-parsi,</hi>  prae-<hi rend="italic">morsi,</hi>  Ital. <hi rend="italic">morsi</hi>  ; the formation in <hi rend="italic">si</hi>  greatly increased in Romance. <hi rend="italic">Habere</hi>  with past part, often approaches to modern compound tenses, Res omnis <hi rend="italic">relidas habeo,</hi>  Ital. ho lasciato tutto. Adverbs : <hi rend="italic">A liorsum</hi>  ire for alio, Prov. alhors, Fr. ailleurs. Prepositions : <hi rend="italic">de</hi>  for genitive, dimidium <hi rend="italic">de praeda</hi>  mihi dare, Ital. la meta del bottino ; mZ for dative, te <hi rend="italic">ad patrem</hi>  esse mortuom re-nuntiem, Ital. dire <hi rend="italic">al padre ; cum</hi>  instrumental, <hi rend="italic">eum</hi>  virgis caseum rädere, ItaL <hi rend="italic">eon ; de</hi>  instr., quam ilia <hi rend="italic">de meis opulentiis</hi>  fiat pro-pensior, Ital. <hi rend="italic">di.</hi>  Peculiar local uses are <hi rend="italic">in</hi>  Ephesum ire, <hi rend="italic">in</hi>  Epheso esse, <hi rend="italic">ab domo, “</hi>  from home,” <hi rend="italic">ex Epheso, “</hi>  from Ephesus ”; <hi rend="italic">ab,</hi>  from (at) one’s house, as Esne tu <hi rend="italic">ab illo milite,</hi>  servus ejus = from (at) the soldier’s, foris concrepuit <hi rend="italic">a vieino sene,</hi>  Ital. <hi rend="italic">dal soldato, dal veeehio vieino</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Syntax and Phraseology.—</hi>Pater tuus <hi rend="italic">is</hi>  erat patruelis meus ; comp. Fr. le père est-ZZ, Ital. il padre <hi rend="italic">lo</hi>  conosco. Pone aedem <hi rend="italic">ibi sunt</hi>  homines, Ital. <hi rend="italic">vi sono</hi>  degli uomini. Scio jam quid <hi rend="italic">vis</hi>  dicere, Ital. so (quel) ehe <hi rend="italic">vuoi</hi>  dire. <hi rend="italic">Ne time, ne fae,</hi>  Fr. ne fais pas cela. <hi rend="italic">Totus</hi>  gaudeo, <hi rend="italic">tota</hi>  sum misera, even Cic. falsum est id <hi rend="italic">totum,</hi>  “it is all false,” Ital. è tutto falso, son tutta contenta, Fr. elle est toute joyeuse. <hi rend="italic">Multum</hi>  miseri, even Cic. fam. <hi rend="italic">multum</hi>  bonus, Ital. molto buono, Span, muy bueno, Port, muito bom. <hi rend="italic">Bene</hi>  morigerus (Plaut.), <hi rend="italic">bene</hi>  saepe (Enn.), <hi rend="italic">bene</hi>  mane (Cic.), Ital. ben bene, ben tosto, Fr. bien bon, bientôt, bien souvent. <hi rend="italic">Bene velle alieui,</hi>  Ital. voler bene ad alcuno. Epityrum estur <hi rend="italic">insane bene</hi>  (Plaut. ), showing that the <hi rend="italic">furieusement bien</hi>  of the <hi rend="italic">Précieuses</hi>  was no novelty. Aequo animo <hi rend="italic">stare,</hi>  Ital. star di buon animo ; <hi rend="italic">stabam</hi>  tanquam mortuus (Petron.), Ital. <hi rend="italic">stava</hi>  come morto, <hi rend="italic">stare</hi>  in letto, <hi rend="italic">star</hi>  seduto, &amp;c. <hi rend="italic">Dictum</hi>  (αc) <hi rend="italic">factum</hi>  (Ter.), Ital. detto fatto, “said and done.” <hi rend="italic">Cum (bona) gratia,</hi>  “with a good grace ” (Ter.), Fr. de bonne grâce. <hi rend="italic">Id restabat (deerat, ut),</hi>  used ironically, (Ter.), It. questa mancava aucora, Fr. il ne manquait (plus) que cela.</p><p>II. <hi rend="italic">Second {Classical) Period·.</hi>  80 B.c. <hi rend="italic">to</hi>  100 (150) a.d.</p><p>At this time we begin to have an idea of what South Latin was, of which the chief characteristics were—(1) its conservative character, supported by the antique forms of the Oscan language ; (2) its preferring <hi rend="italic">i</hi>  to <hi rend="italic">e,</hi>  as in <hi rend="italic">siηaturn, einsuerint, eintum, rim, ris, diibus </hi>(Lex Jul. ; Heraclea) ; <hi rend="italic">nigatis, tenimus, Lueritivs, dieembres, oeilli </hi>(Pompeii), ZeraZiZMω = Mod. Neap, <hi rend="italic">tenimmo ; fmιmiηte), siptim</hi>  (Pute-oli) ; <hi rend="italic">venirandax</hi>  (Nap.); later <hi rend="italic">sieundo, siptim</hi>  (Borgia, 386); (3) its preferring <hi rend="italic">u</hi>  to <hi rend="italic">o,</hi>  as in <hi rend="italic">fτι,rtunilla, postera, aliu</hi>  (Pompeii). These forms are constant in Modern South Italian. Now classical</p><p>Latin was an approach to South Latin, and there arose a strong reaction against the vulgar North Latin forms. But even a purist like Cicero could not always abstain from using colloquial forms, and he sometimes gives us precious information about familiar pronunciations, as cun <hi rend="italic">nobis</hi>  for <hi rend="italic">eum nobis,</hi>  showing the assimilation of <hi rend="italic">mn</hi>  to <hi rend="italic">nn.</hi>  He hesitates to use the new word <hi rend="italic">medietas,</hi>  which later became the ordinary expression, Ital. meta, Span, mitad, Fr. moitié. Catullus has <hi rend="italic">involare,</hi>  “steal,” Ital. involare, Fr. voler, and <hi rend="italic">basium,</hi>  Ital. bacio (for <hi rend="italic">basio, bagio,</hi>  like <hi rend="italic">eaxio</hi>  caseus), Span, beso, Fr. baiser, and the familiar caressing <hi rend="italic">issa</hi>  for <hi rend="italic">ipsa,</hi>  Ital. essa. He and Horace have <hi rend="italic">ρlatea, ‘ ‘</hi>  street ” (for platêa = πλατεία), Ital. piazza, Fr. place. Vitruvius has <hi rend="italic">octuaginta,</hi>  Ital. ottanta, <hi rend="italic">aperegre </hi>= <hi rend="sup">,,</hi>from abroad,” and the Greek words<hi rend="italic">chalare,</hi>  Ital. calare, <hi rend="italic">zelus, </hi>Ital. geloso, Fr. jaloux, and <hi rend="italic">sehidia,</hi>  “wooden chip,” “splinter,” Ital. scheggia. The transition from <hi rend="italic">b</hi>  to <hi rend="italic">v</hi>  begins, <hi rend="italic">triumphavit</hi>  for <hi rend="italic">-bit </hi>(Lex Jul. ). Gradually the popular speech undermined the classical correctness of the brief Golden Age, and at the beginning of the empire again rose to the surface. The emperor Augustus was fond of talking slang and bad grammar, as <hi rend="italic">simus</hi>  for <hi rend="italic">sumus,</hi>  and he wrote as he spoke in his familiar letters, although he was very hard upon a poor <hi rend="italic">legatus eonsularis</hi>  for barbarously writing <hi rend="italic">ixi</hi>  instead of <hi rend="italic">ipsi (fin&amp;ï., Aug.,</hi>  88; comp, <hi rend="italic">proxirnus</hi>  for <hi rend="italic">propsimus).</hi></p><p>At Pompeii and Herculaneum we find a town dialect fully developed, half South Latin, half vulgar Roman. Final consonants were dropped, for instance <hi rend="italic">m</hi>  in the acc. <hi rend="italic">puella, laudata ; t</hi>  in the verse “quisquis <hi rend="italic">ama valia, peria</hi>  qui <hi rend="italic">nosei</hi>  (? = nescit) amare (Pomp. ) ; s rarely, <hi rend="italic">valea =</hi>  valeas (Pomp. ). <hi rend="italic">II,</hi>  the right pronunciation of which had become a mark of education, just as in English (Rusticus fit sermo, si aspires perperam ; Nigid. Figulus), was constantly dropped, as in <hi rend="italic">abeto, abuaerit</hi>  (Pomp.), <hi rend="italic">abiat</hi>  (Here.). <hi rend="italic">Nη </hi>took the place of <hi rend="italic">nd : vereeuηnus</hi>  (Pomp.), later <hi rend="italic">innulgen.</hi>  (Abella, 170 a.d.), <hi rend="italic">αgeηnae</hi>  (Puteoli), were generally Italic ; comp. Umb. <hi rend="italic">ρihαηer</hi>  piandi <hi rend="italic">(distennite, dispennite,</hi>  Plaut. ), Ose. <hi rend="italic">opsannam </hi>operandam ; now South Italian — Roman <hi rend="italic">monno,</hi>  Neap. munno, Sicil. <hi rend="italic">munnu=</hi>  Ital. mondo, Lat. mundus. Ns was used for <hi rend="italic">es (x) </hi>as in words in <hi rend="italic">-triss</hi>  for <hi rend="italic">-true</hi>  (Pomp.). Φ popularly became<hi rend="italic">p,</hi>  as <hi rend="italic">Aprodite,</hi>  but with those who tried to speak fine <hi rend="italic">f,</hi>  just as they made the Greek <hi rend="italic">υ</hi>  an <hi rend="italic">i—Iαointus, Amarillis, Dafne, Filetus,</hi>  Ital. <hi rend="italic">fisieo, fisonomia,</hi>  &amp;c. <hi rend="italic">E</hi>  for <hi rend="italic">oe</hi>  seems first to occur during the empire, for example, <hi rend="italic">pomerii</hi>  (8 <hi rend="italic">n.c.), ρomerium</hi>  (49 a.d. ), <hi rend="italic">Phebιιs </hi>(Pomp.). There is no certain evidence of the sound of Germ, <hi rend="italic">o, </hi>Fr. <hi rend="italic">eu ; </hi>we see that the first vowel is absorbed by the second. According to Diez, <hi rend="italic">oe</hi>  becomes close <hi rend="italic">e, ax</hi>  open <hi rend="italic">e,</hi>  which is true for popular words like Ital. <hi rend="italic">pena,</hi>  Fr. peine, but untrue for Latinisms like <hi rend="italic">fete, fèdo, amène), eèto, eommèdia, tragèdia, Fèbo, oe</hi>  in Low Lat. being constantly confounded with <hi rend="italic">ae.</hi>  Original <hi rend="italic">oe</hi>  never becomes <hi rend="italic">ie,</hi>  as <hi rend="italic">ae</hi>  does (cZeZo, <hi rend="italic">fieno).</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Vocabulary.—</hi>We remark at Pompeii <hi rend="italic">exmueeαvit</hi>  emunxit, Ital. dial, <hi rend="italic">smoeeare,</hi>  “snuff (the candle)”; mi <hi rend="italic">similat,</hi>  Ital. mi somiglia, Fr. il me ressemble, elsewhere only in Late Latin. Petronius : <hi rend="italic">bisaeeium,</hi>  Ital. bisaccia, Fr. besace; <hi rend="italic">nxsapius,</hi>  “unwise,” Ital. sâvio, sâggio, Span, sâbio, Fr. sage; <hi rend="italic">berbex,</hi>  Fr. brebis; <hi rend="italic">peduelus, </hi>Ital. pidocchio, Fr. pou <hi rend="italic">(ρaηus</hi>  facit diminutivum yxmwciiZa, Fest., Ital. pannocchia—comp. L. Lat. <hi rend="italic">geηueulum, axucula,</hi>  Ital. ginocchio, agocchia, Span, hinojo, aguja, Fr. genou, aiguille); <hi rend="italic">striga, </hi>“witch,” Ital. strega ; <hi rend="italic">fatuus,</hi>  Fr. fat; basiavit me <hi rend="italic">sρissius,</hi>  Ital. spésso, “often.” Instances of Petronius’s grammar are—<hi rend="italic">virus, eaelιιs,</hi>  comp. Old Fr. <hi rend="italic">vins, ciels</hi>  ; jacebat tanquam <hi rend="italic">bovis,</hi>  Ital. bove, bue; hoc vetare nec <hi rend="italic">Jovis</hi>  potest (Old Lat. <hi rend="italic">Jovis pater=</hi>Jupiter), Ital. Giove ; munus <hi rend="italic">excellente,</hi>  neuter, shows the L. Lat. declension, Ital. eccellente ; habet <hi rend="italic">wnele=i∖</hi>  a de quoi (vivre) ; unus <hi rend="italic">de nobis= </hi>uno di noi (see also Latin). Pliny mentions <hi rend="italic">sanguisuga</hi>  as vulgar for <hi rend="italic">hirudo,</hi>  Ital. sanguisuga, Fr. sangsue ; he has <hi rend="italic">gyτare </hi>= Ital. girare, “turn,” “roam about.” Persius (34-62) has <hi rend="italic">stloρpo </hi>tumidas rumpere buccas, “a slap,” L. Lat. sclopus, sclupare, Ital. schioppo, “gun.” Quintilian (c. 40-118): <hi rend="italic">5υvατοv</hi>  quod nostri <hi rend="italic">possibile</hi>  nominant, quae ut dura videatur appellatio, tarnen sola est, Ital. possibile, &amp;c. Juvenal has buccâ <hi rend="italic">foeulum</hi>  excitât, Ital. fuoco, Fr. feu, and Tacitus <hi rend="italic">spatha,</hi>  Ital. spada, Fr. épée (see also Latin).</p><p>III. <hi rend="italic">Third {Post-Classical) Period·.</hi>  100 (150) <hi rend="italic">to</hi>  300 (350).</p><p>This period is represented by the latest pagan inscriptions, by Gellius, Apuleius, &amp;c. On the decay of classical Latin, see Latin. In pronunciation only few decided changes appear.</p><p>1.    <hi rend="italic">I</hi>  is inserted before s impurum, as <hi rend="italic">iseripta</hi>  (Afr., 197), <hi rend="italic">nστreLρeι,τω = ispirito</hi>  (Rome, 269); later this was universal, but in Italian only after consonants—<hi rend="italic">non ista</hi>  (colloq. <hi rend="italic">non stà), in isρirito, in iscrUto</hi>  ; Span, always, as espiritu, esta, escribir, escuela ; Fr. esprit, écrire, école.</p><p>2.    <hi rend="italic">Tt</hi>  is put for <hi rend="italic">pt,</hi>  as <hi rend="italic">Setemb.</hi>  (Helvet., 219), <hi rend="italic">Setimus</hi>  (Afr., 3d century), later frequent. This assimilation originally came from the north ; comp. Etrus. Lat. <hi rend="italic">Nethunus (th=t),</hi>  Etrus. <hi rend="italic">Neθuns, </hi>Neptunus, Etrus. Lat. <hi rend="italic">Setχιmnal,</hi>  Etrus. <hi rend="italic">Sehtmnal—</hi>Septimienâ nata</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>