<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb09-22-s06-0611-04" facs="encyclopediabrit22newyrich_raw_0635.jp2" type="entry"><p><label>STURGEON</label>
. Sturgeons <hi rend="italic">(Acipenser)</hi> are a small group of fishes, of which some twenty different species are known, from European, Asiatic, and North American rivers. The distinguishing characters of this group, as well as its position in the system, have been sufficiently indicated in the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Ichthyology</hi> (vol. xii. p. 687). They pass a great part of the year in the sea, but periodically ascend large rivers, some in spring to deposit their spawn, others later in the season for some purpose unknown ; only a few of the species are exclusively confined to fresh water. None occur in the tropics or in the southern hemisphere.</p><p>Sturgeons are found in the greatest abundance in the rivers of southern Russia, more than ten thousand fish being sometimes caught at a single fishing-station in the fortnight during which the up-stream migration lasts. They occur in less abundance in the fresh waters of North America, where their capture is not confined to the rivers, the majority being caught in shallow portions of the shores of the great lakes. In Russia the fisheries are of immense value ; yet but little is known of the sturgeon’s habits, life, and early stages of development or growth. Early in summer the fish migrate into the rivers or towards the shores of freshwater lakes in large shoals for breeding purposes. The ova are very small, and so numerous that one female has been calculated to produce about three millions in one season. The ova of some species have been observed to hatch within a very few days after exclusion. Probably the growth of the young is very rapid, but we have no knowledge as to the length of time for which the fry remain in fresh water before their first migration to the sea. After they have attained maturity their growth appears to be much slower, although continuing for many years. Frederick the Great attempted to introduce the sterlet into Prussia, and placed a number of this fish in the Görland Lake in Pomerania about 1780; some of these were found to be still alive in 1866, and therefore had reached an age of nearly ninety years. Prof. Von Baer also states, as the result of direct observations made in Russia, that the hausen <hi rend="italic">(Acipenser huso</hi>) attains to an age of from 200 to 300 years. Sturgeons ranging from 8 to 11 feet in length are by no means scarce, and some species grow to a much larger size.</p><p>Sturgeons are ground-feeders. With their projecting wedge-shaped snout they stir up the soft bottom, and by means of their sensitive barbels detect shells, crustaceans, and small fishes, on which they feed. Destitute of teeth, they are unable to seize larger prey.</p><p>In countries like England, where few sturgeons are</p><pb xml:id="eb09-22-s06-0612" facs="encyclopediabrit22newyrich_raw_0636.jp2"/><p><label><?xml version="I.O" encoding="utf-8"?> unknown title unknown author <editionStmt> <edition> <date> unknown date <,date> <,edition> <,editionStmt>  unknown <,p>  Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei. <,p> <encodingDesc> <appInfo> <application ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.I5.O" xml:id="docxtotei">  Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI  <,application> <,appInfo> <,encodingDesc> <revisionDesc> <listChange> <change> <date> 2OI9-OI-2OT22:44:34Z <,date> <name> unknown author <,name> <,change> <,listChange> <,revisionDesc>  caught, the fish is consumed fresh, the flesh being firmer than that of ordinary fishes, well-flavoured, though somewhat oily. The sturgeon is included as a royal fish in an Act of King Edward II., which assigns to the sovereign all wrecks and whales, although it probably but rarely graces the royal table of the present period, or even that of the lord mayor of London, who can claim all sturgeons caught in the Thames above London Bridge. Where sturgeons are regularly caught in <,p>  large quantities, as on <,p>  the rivers of southern <,p>  Russia and on the <,p>  great lakes of North <,p>  America, their flesh <,p>  is dried, smoked, or <,p>  salted. The ovaries, <,p>  which are of large size, <,p>  are prepared for caviare ; for this purpose they are beaten with switches, and then pressed through sieves, leaving the membranous and fibrous tissues in the sieve, whilst the eggs are collected in a tub. The quantity of salt added to them before they are finally packed varies with the season, scarcely any being used at the beginning of winter. Finally, one of the best sorts of isinglass is manufactured from the air-bladder. After it has been carefully removed from the body, it is washed in hot water, and cut open in its whole length, to separate the inner membrane, which has a soft consistency, and contains 7O per cent. of glutin. <,p>  The twenty species of sturgeons <hi rend="italic">(Acipenser) <,hi> are nearly equally divided between the Old and New Worlds. The more important are the following :— <,p>  (I) The Common Sturgeon of Europe (<hi rend="italic">Acipenser sturio) <,hi> occurs on all the coasts of Europe, but is absent in the Black Sea. Almost all the British specimens of sturgeon belong to this species; it crosses the Atlantic and is not rare on the coasts of North America. It reaches a large size (a length of I2 feet), but is always caught singly or in pairs, so that it cannot be regarded as a fish of commercial importance. The form of its snout varies with age (as in the other species), being much more blunt and abbreviated in old than in young examples. There are II-I3 bony shields along the back and 29-3I along the side of the body. <,p>  (2) <hi rend="italic">Acipenser gülclenslädlii <,hi> is one of the most valuable species of the rivers of Russia, where it is known under the name “ Ossétr” ; it is said to inhabit the Siberian rivers also, and to range eastwards as far as Lake Baikal. It attains to the same large size as the common sturgeon, and is so abundant in the rivers of the Black and Caspian Seas that more than one-fourth of the caviare and isinglass manufactured in Russia is derived from this species. <,p>  (3) <hi rend="italic">Acipenser stellatus, <,hi> the “ Seuruga ” of the Russians, occurs likewise in great abundance in the rivers of the Black Sea and of the Sea of Azoff. It has a remarkably long and pointed snout, like the sterlet, but simple barbels without fringes. Though growing only to about half the size of the preceding species, it is of no less value, its flesh being more highly esteemed, and its caviare and isinglass fetching a higher price. In I85O it was reported that more than a million of this sturgeon are caught annually. <,p>  (4) The sturgeon of the great lakes of North America, <hi rend="italic">Acipenser rubicundus, <,hi> with which, in the opinion of American ichthyologists, the sea-going sturgeon of the rivers of eastern North America, <hi rend="italic">Acipenser maculosus, <,hi> is identical, has of late years been made the object of a large and profitable industry at various places on Lakes Michigan and Erie ; the flesh is smoked after being cut into strips and after a slight pickling in brine ; the thin portions and offal are boiled down for oil ; nearly all the caviare is shipped to Europe. One firm alone uses from ten to eighteen thousand sturgeons a year, averaging fifty pounds each. The sturgeons of the lakes are unable to migrate to the sea, whilst those below the Falls of Niagara are great wanderers; and it is quite possible that a specimen of this species said to have been obtained from the Firth of Tay was really captured on the coast of Scotland. <,p>  (5) <hi rend="italic">Acipenser huso, <,hi> the “Hausen” of Germany, is recognized by the absence of osseous scutes on the snout and by its flattened, tape-like barbels. It is one of the largest species, reaching the enormous length of 24 feet and a weight of 2OOO pounds. It inhabits the Caspian and Black Seas and the Sea of Azoff, whence in former years large shoals of the fish entered the large rivers of Russia and the Danube. But its numbers have been much thinned, and specimens of I2OO pounds in weight have now become <,p>  scarce. Its flesh, caviare, and air-bladder are of less value than those of the smaller kinds. <,p>  (6) The Sterlet (<hi rend="italic">Acipenser ruthenus) <,hi> is one of the smaller species, which likewise inhabits both the Black and Caspian Seas, and ascends rivers to a greater distance from the sea than any of the other sturgeons; thus, for instance, it is not uncommon in the Danube at Vienna, but specimens have been caught as high up as Ratisbon and Ulm. It is more abundant in the rivers of Russia, where it is held in high esteem on account of its excellent flesh, contributing also to the best kinds of caviare and isinglass. As <,p>  early as last century attempts were made to introduce this valuable fish into Prussia and Sweden, but without success. The sterlet is distinguished from the other European species by its long and narrow snout and fringed barbels. It <,p>  rarely exceeds a length of three feet. <,p>  Sturgeons with the snout prolonged in an extraordinary manner, <,p>  so as to form a long spade-like or conical process (<hi rend="italic">Spatularia, Polyodon, Psephurus), <,hi> occur in the Mississippi and the great rivers of China and Central Asia. None of them have been made objects of trade, but special interest is attached to them from a geographical as well as palæontological point of view, the two genera last named being represented as far back as the Lias by an allied fossil genus, <hi rend="italic">Chondrosteus, <,hi> and all affording a striking proof of the close affinity of the North-American and North-Asiatic faunas of the recent period. <,p> 
<,div</label>>