<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb09-22-s06-0589-03" facs="encyclopediabrit22newyrich_raw_0613.jp2" type="entry"><p><label>STRATFORD</label>,
usually designated <hi rend="smallcaps">Stratford-on-Avon,</hi> a market-town and municipal borough of England, in Warwickshire, near the Gloucestershire border, is pleasantly situated on the Avon, and on the Great Western and Midland Railway lines, 26 miles south of Birmingham and 8 south-west of Warwick. The Avon is crossed by a stone bridge of fourteen arches, built by Sir Hugh Clopton in the</p><pb xml:id="eb09-22-s06-0590" facs="encyclopediabrit22newyrich_raw_0614.jp2"/><p><label><?xml version="I.O" encoding="utf-8"?> unknown title unknown author <editionStmt> <edition> <date> unknown date <,date> <,edition> <,editionStmt>  unknown <,p>  Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei. <,p> <encodingDesc> <appInfo> <application ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.I5.O" xml:id="docxtotei">  Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI  <,application> <,appInfo> <,encodingDesc> <revisionDesc> <listChange> <change> <date> 2OI9-OI-2OT22:43:3OZ <,date> <name> unknown author <,name> <,change> <,listChange> <,revisionDesc>  reign of Henry VIL, and widened in I8I4 ; by a bridge of nine arches, built of brick in I826 ; and by a foot-bridge erected in I867, at a cost of £5OO, on the site of a footbridge originally erected in I599, and rebuilt in I8I2. The streets are wide and regular, crossing each other generally at right angles, and, says J. O. Halliwell-Phillipps, “ with the exception of a few diffused buildings, scarcely one of which is in its original condition, there is no resemblance between the present town and the Shakespearean borough ” (compare article <hi rend="smallcaps">Shakespeare, <,hi> vol. xxi. pp. 74I <hi rend="italic">sq.). <,hi> The church of the Holy Trinity occupies the site of a Saxon monastery, which existed before 69I, when the bishop of Worcester received it in exchange from Ethelred, king of Mercia. It is a fine cruciform structure, partly Early English and partly Perpendicular, with a central tower and lofty octagonal spire. It was greatly improved in the reign of Edward III. by John de Stratford, who rebuilt the south aisle. He also in I332 founded a chantry for priests, and in I35I Ralph de Stratford built for John’s chantry priests “ a house of square stone,” which came to be known as the college, and in connexion with which the church became collegiate. The present beautiful choir was built by Dean Balshall (I465-9I), and in the reign of Henry VII. the north and south transepts were erected. The mural monument of Shakespeare, who is buried in the chancel, is of special interest from its effigy of the poet, undoubtedly an authentic representation, though somewhat altered and damaged by time. The foundation of the chapel of the guild of the Holy Cross was laid by Robert de Stratford. The guild, to which both sexes were admitted, was in existence early in the I3th century, and it was incorporated by a charter from Edward III. in I322. It was dissolved in I547. The house in which Shakespeare was born still stands,—although its external appearance is much altered, —and an apartment is by immemorial tradition pointed out as his birth-room. In I597 Shakespeare purchased New Place for his residence (see vol. xxi. p. 765). Shakespeare’s house was pulled down by Sir John Clopton in I7O2, and the large new mansion erected on its site was pulled down by Sir Francis Gastrell in I759. Chiefly through the exertions of J. O. Halliwell-Phillipps, the site of New Place was purchased by public subscription, and in I876 handed over to the trustees of the birthplace. The old theatre, which had occupied part of the ground, was taken down in I872, and in I877 a new memorial theatre was erected at a cost of £3O,OOO. The other principal buildings of the town are the town-hall, originally erected in I633, almost entirely rebuilt in I767-68, after having been severely injured by an explosion, and greatly altered in I863 at a cost of £2OOO ; the market-house (I82O); the corn exchange (I85O) ; the children’s hospital (I87I); and the new hospital (I884). The Edward VI. grammar school, where Shakespeare received his education, was founded in I553. The town is chiefly dependent on the agriculture of the neighbourhood. The population of the borough in I87I was 7I83, and in I88I (area extended in I879 to 3865 acres) it was 8O54. <,p>  There is no authentic mention of Stratford earlier than the 7th century. It received a charter for a market in the reign of Richard I., but was not incorporated till the reign of Edward VI. The charter of Charles II., granted in his 26th year, remained the governing charter of the town till the passing of the Municipal Act in I835. The town suffered from a severe epidemic in I564, from inundations in I588, and from fire in I598. <,p>  See S. L. Lee, <hi rend="italic">Stratford-on-Avon, <,hi> I884 ; J. O. Halliwell-Phillipps, <hi rend="italic">Outlines of the Life of Shakspeare, <,hi> sixth edition (with a history of New Place), I886 ; and the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Shakespeare. <,hi> <,p> 
<,div</label>>