<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb09-22-s06-0556-02" facs="encyclopediabrit22newyrich_raw_0580.jp2" type="entry"><p><label>STOBÆUS</label>,
<hi rend="smallcaps">Joannes,</hi> a native of Stobi in Macedonia,— whence the surname Stobæus or Stobensis,—is known to us as the compiler of a very valuable series of extracts from Greek authors. Of his life nothing is known, but he probably belongs to the latter half of the 5th century. From his silence in regard to Christian authors, it is inferred with some probability that he was not a Christian; that he was a man of wide culture and general reading is clear from the anthology which bears his name.</p><p>The extracts were intended by Stobæus for his son Septimius, and were preceded by a letter briefly explaining the purpose of the work and giving a summary of the contents. From this summary (which is preserved in Photius’s <hi rend="italic">Bibliotheca)</hi> we learn that Stobæus divided his work into four books ; the first contained sixty chapters, the second forty-six, the third forty-two, and the fourth fifty-eight. In most of our MSS. the work is divided into three books, of which the first and second are generally called 'Ε <hi rend="italic">κλoγαὶ ϕυσικαὶ καὶ ἠ</hi> <hi rend="italic bold"> θικaὶ,</hi> and the third ’A <hi rend="italic">vθoλόγιον (Florilegium</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Sermones).</hi> As each of the four books is sometimes called Α <hi rend="italic">vθoλόγιον</hi>, it is probable that this name originally belonged to the entire work;</p><p>the full title, as we know from Photius, was ’Ε <hi rend="italic">κλογων ἀ</hi> <hi rend="italic bold"> ποφθεγμάτων υποθηκων βιβλί</hi> <hi rend="italic">α</hi> <hi rend="italic bold"> τέτταρα.</hi> Between the account which Photius gives of Stobæus’s work and the form in which we have it there are several marked discrepancies. The second book in particular is little more than a fragment. From this and other indications Wachsmuth has made it probable that our Stobæus is only an epitome of the original work, made about the end of the 11th century at Byzantium, “ ab homine Platonis Aristotelisque amantissimo.”</p><p>The didactic aim of Stobæus’s work is apparent throughout. The first book teaches physics—in the wide sense which the Greeks assigned to this term—by means of extracts. It is often untrustworthy : Stobæus betrays a tendency to confound the dogmas of the early Ionic philosophers, and he occasionally mixes up Platonism with Pythagoreanism. For part of this book and much of book ii. he depended on the works of Aetius, a Peripatetic philosopher, and Didymus. The third and fourth books, like the larger part of the second, treat of ethics ; the third, of virtues and vices, in pairs ; the fourth, of more general ethical and political subjects, frequently citing extracts to illustrate the pros and cons of a question in two successive chapters. In all, Stobæus quotes more than five hundred writers, generally beginning with the poets, and then proceeding to the historians, orators, philosophers, and physicians. It is to him that we owe many of our most important fragments of the dramatists, particularly of Euripides.</p><p>The first complete edition of Stobæus was published at Geneva in 1609 ; the last is Meineke’s (Leipsic, 1855-1864). The best critical edition of books i. and ii. is by Wachsmuth (Berlin, 1884) ; a companion edition of books iii. and iv. (the <hi rend="italic">Florilegium)</hi> is promised by Otto Hense.</p></div></body></text></TEI>