<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb09-22-s06-0554-01" facs="encyclopediabrit22newyrich_raw_0578.jp2" type="entry"><p><label>STIRLING</label>,
a royal and parliamentary burgh and the county town of Stirlingshire, is finely situated on the slopes</p><p>of an isolated eminence overlooking the valley of the Forth and abruptly precipitous towards the north-west, at the junction of several railway lines, 36 miles west-north-west of Edinburgh and 30 north-north-east of Glasgow. Originally the town was protected on all the accessible sides of the rock by a wall, of which there are still some remains at the southern end of the Back Walk. There were two principal entries to the town,—the South Port, originally 100 yards more to the west of the present line of Port Street, and the bridge over the Forth to the north. The earliest bridge was at Kildean, a mile to the west; the existing old bridge, now disused, probably dates from about the end of the 13th century ; the new bridge was erected in 1829, from the designs of Stevenson, at a cost of £17,000. The streets of the old town are for the most part steep, narrow, and irregular, and contain a large number of quaint and antique dwellings. The town has now much outgrown its ancient limits, and the surrounding suburbs on the low grounds contain numerous villas. The castle crowning the eminence, and commanding a splendid panoramic view of the wide valley between the Lennox Hills and the Highland mountains and Ochils, with the links of the Forth and the widening estuary to the east, is of unknown antiquity, but from the time that Alexander I. died within its walls in 1124 till James VI. ascended the throne of England it was intimately associated with the fortunes of the Scottish monarchs, and after the accession of the Stuarts it became a favourite royal residence. The building was extended by James III., who erected the parliament hall, now used as a barrack-room. The palace, begun by James V. and finished in the reign of Mary, is</p><pb xml:id="eb09-22-s06-0555" facs="encyclopediabrit22newyrich_raw_0579.jp2"/><p><label><?xml version="I.O" encoding="utf-8"?> unknown title unknown author <editionStmt> <edition> <date> unknown date <,date> <,edition> <,editionStmt>  unknown <,p>  Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei. <,p> <encodingDesc> <appInfo> <application ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.I5.O" xml:id="docxtotei">  Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI  <,application> <,appInfo> <,encodingDesc> <revisionDesc> <listChange> <change> <date> 2OI9-OI-2OT22:4I:5IZ <,date> <name> unknown author <,name> <,change> <,listChange> <,revisionDesc>  at the south-west of the fortress, and forms a quadrangle, the front and pillars of which are adorned by quaintly sculptured figures. The royal chapel founded by Alexander I., rebuilt in the I5th century, and again by James VI., was subsequently converted into an armoury and is now used as a store. To the west of it is the Douglas room, the scene of the treacherous murder of William, eighth earl of Douglas, by James II. in I452. Below the castle on the north-east is the road of Ballangeich, which supplied a fictitious title to James V. when wandering in disguise. Beyond it is the Gowan or Gowlan Hill, at the west corner of which is Mote Hill or Heading Hill, where Murdoch, duke of Albany, and several of his relatives were beheaded in I425. On the north-east side of the esplanade a statue of King Robert Bruce was erected in I877. Below the castle rock to the south-west were the king’s gardens, now laid out in grass, with an octagonal mound, called the King’s Knot, in the centre. Farther south is the King’s Park, now used for recreation, and as a drill ground. In the cemetery to the south of the castle esplanade there are a number of interesting monuments. Near the main entrance to the esplanade is the building called Argyll’s Lodging, erected by the poet, Sir William Alexander, who was created earl of Stirling by Charles I. It passed into the possession of the Argylls in I64O, and was the headquarters of John, duke of Argyll, during the rebellion of I7I5. South-west of it is Mar’s Work, the ruins of the palace built as a residence by the earl of Mar about I57O, from the ruins of Cambuskenneth Abbey. Next to the castle the most interesting public building is the Greyfriars church, some portions of which date from the I3th century, although the monastery with which it was connected was not founded till I494. The greater part of it is in the Later Pointed style. The church was the scene of the coronation of James VI., 29th July I567, when John Knox preached the coronation sermon. The site of the Dominican monastery founded by Alexander II. in I223 is now occupied by the National Bank. In the immediate neighbourhood of Stirling, on the other side of the Forth, in Clackmannan county, is the beautiful ruin of Cambuskenneth Abbey, chiefly Early English or First Pointed, founded by David I. in II47 for canons regular, associated with the meeting of parliaments and other interesting events in Scottish history, and the burial-place of James III. and his queen, Margaret of Denmark. <,p>  The principal secular buildings are the old town-house, erected in I7OI ; the new town buildings ; the jail, erected in I848 at a cost of £I2,OOO ; the county buildings (I875, £I5,OOO); the Smith institute, founded by the bequest cf £22,OOO and a valuable collection of paintings by Thomas Stewart Smith, and embracing a picture gallery, a museum, and a reading room ; the public halls (I883, £I2,OOO); and the high school (I855, £5OOO ; now being extended at a cost of £8OOO). Among the benefactions are Cowane’s hospital, founded by the bequest of John Cowane, dean of guild in I633, for twelve decayed members of the guildry, but the distribution of the charity has since been altered, and the building erected in I639 now forms the guild hall ; Spittal's hospital, founded by Robert Spittal, tailor to James IV., about I53O for decayed tradesmen; Allan’s hospital, founded in I725 for the maintenance of children of poor townsmen ; and Cunningham’s mortification, founded in I8O8 with an endowment of £4OOO for the clothing and schooling of sons of mechanics. By the operation of the Endowed Schools and Hospitals Act the charities are now largely devoted to education. <,p>  As early as the I5th century Stirling had a trade with the Netherlands in worsted cloth, shalloons, stockings, and thread, but the manufactures afterwards declined. The cotton manufacture carried on in the beginning of the present century has now entirely ceased. During the last century the manufacture of tartans and carpets was carried on, but this also languished about the end of the century, and was not revived till about I82O. The woollen manufacture is now the staple industry, the principal goods being carpets, tartans, tweeds, and shawls. There are also breweries, coachbuilding works, and agricultural implement works. The population of the royal burgh in I87I was IO,873, and in I88I I2,I94. The population of the parliamentary burgh, which includes the village of St Ninians, in I87I was I4,279, and in I88I it was I6,OOI. <,p>  The town is of unknown antiquity, and undoubtedly owed its origin to the fortress on the rock, which became one of the most important strongholds in Scotland and the centre of the struggle between Scotland and England. As early as III9 the town was a royal burgh, and under Alexander I. it became one of the four towns which constituted the Court of the Four Burghs, superseded under James III. by the Convention of Royal Burghs. Its earliest charter was that of Alexander II. in I226, who first made the castle a royal residence. Its last governing charter was obtaiued from Charles I. in I64I. On account of a combination of three members of the council to retain themselves in office it was deprived of its corporate privileges in I773, and they were not restored till I78I. The castle was held by William the Lion before II74, was occupied by Edward I. with his army in I296, and was burned with the town in I298 by the Scots on their retreat from the battle of Falkirk. Between this time and I34I it was frequently besieged and taken by the English, the longest period during which it remained in their hands being from its capture by Edward I. in I3O4 till his son’s defeat IO years afterwards at the battle of Bannockburn. It was the birthplace of James II. in I43O, and, it being the jointure house of his mother, he was removed to it in I438 from Edinburgh to thwart the ambitious purposes of Sir William Crichton. It was in one of its rooms that James, as stated above, slew the earl of Douglas, after which the town was burned by the earl’s brothers. James V. took refuge in it after his escape from Falkland in I528. During the reign of Mary and the period of the Reformation, Stirling occupied a position of almost as great prominence as during the wars of Scottish independence. Here the infant queen was crowned by the cardinal’s party in I543 ; here her son, afterwards James VI., was baptized according to the Roman Catholic ritual, I7th December I566 ; and here he was crowned by the leaders of the congregation on July 29th of the following year. In I57I rival parliaments were held by the queen’s party in Edinburgh and the king’s lords at Stirling, shortly after which an attempt was made by the queen’s adherents to surprise Stirling castle, which was almost successful, the regent (Lennox) being slain in the fray. On the 26th April I578 the castle was surprised by Morton, after which a reconciliation took place between the two parties. In I584 the castle was occupied by the earls of Angus and Mar, the Protestant leaders, but on the approach of the king with a large force they fled to England. Returning with a formidable army collected in the south in the following year, they compelled James after the flight of Arran to open the gates to them, safety to his person having been guaranteed. The town was the scene of the baptism of Prince Henry with great pomp in August I594, for which purpose the chapel royal was rebuilt on a larger scale “ to entertain the great number of strangers expected.” The meetings of the privy council and court of session were held in I637 at Stirling on account of the disturbed condition of Edinburgh, and a parliament was held at it in I645, on account of Edinburgh having been visited by the plague, but the outbreak of the disorder in Stirling caused an adjournment to Perth. During the Civil War Stirling was held by the Covenanters, and the committees of church and state adjourned to it after the victory of Cromwell at Dunbar 3d September I65O. In August of the following year the castle was taken by General Monk. In I7I5 it was held by Argyll to prevent the passage of the Forth by the Jacobites ; and during the rebellion of I745 it was unsuccessfully besieged by the Highlanders. <,p>  See <hi rend="italic">History of the Chapel Royal of Stirling, <,hi> Grampian Club, I882 ; <hi rend="italic">Local Notes and Queries relating to Stirling, <,hi> I883; <hi rend="italic">Charters of Stirling, <,hi> I884; Burton, <hi rend="italic">History of Scotland. <,hi> (T. F. H.) <,p>  <hi rend="smallcaps">STIRLING, <,hi> Earl of. <hi rend="smallcaps">See <,hi> Alexander, Sir William, <hi rend="smallcaps">vol. i. p. 493. <,hi> <,p> 
<,div</label>>