<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb09-22-s06-0651-01" facs="encyclopediabrit22newyrich_raw_0679.jp2" type="entry"><p><label>SUN-BIRD</label>,
a name more or less in use for many years, <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> and now generally accepted as that of a group of</p><p><hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> Certainly since 1826 (<hi rend="italic">cf</hi>. Stephens, <hi rend="italic">Gen. Zoology,</hi> xiv. pt. 1, p. 229). Swainson (<hi rend="italic">Nat. Hist. and Classif. Birds,</hi> i. p. 145) says they are “ so called by the natives of Asia in allusion to their splendid and shining plumage,” but gives uo hint as to the nation or language wherein the name originated. By the French they have been much longer known as “ Souimangas,” from the Madagascar name of one of the species given in 1658 by Flacourt as <hi rend="italic">Soumangha.</hi></p><pb xml:id="eb09-22-s06-0652" facs="encyclopediabrit22newyrich_raw_0680.jp2"/><p><label><?xml version="I.O" encoding="utf-8"?> unknown title unknown author <editionStmt> <edition> <date> unknown date <,date> <,edition> <,editionStmt>  unknown <,p>  Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei. <,p> <encodingDesc> <appInfo> <application ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.I5.O" xml:id="docxtotei">  Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI  <,application> <,appInfo> <,encodingDesc> <revisionDesc> <listChange> <change> <date> 2OI9-OI-2OT22:46:27Z <,date> <name> unknown author <,name> <,change> <,listChange> <,revisionDesc>  over IOO species of small birds, but when or by whom it was first applied is uncertain. Most of them are remarkable for their gaudy plumage, and, though those known to the older naturalists were for a long while referred to the genus <hi rend="italic">Certhia <,hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">(Tree-creeper, <,hi> <hi rend="italic">q.v.) <,hi> or some other group, they are now fully recognized as forming a valid Family <hi rend="italic">Nectariniidæ, <,hi> from the name <hi rend="italic">Nectarinia <,hi> invented in I8II by Illiger. They inhabit the Ethiopian, Indian, and Australian Regions,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="1"> One species occurs in Baluchistan, which is perhaps outside of the Indian Region, but the fact of its being found there may be a reason for including that country within the Region, just as the presence of another species in the Jordan valley induces zoographers to regard the Ghór as an outlier of the Ethiopian Region. <,note> and, with some notable exceptions, the species mostly have but a limited range. They are considered to have their nearest allies in the <hi rend="italic">Meliphagidæ (cf. <,hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">Honey-eater, <,hi> vol. xii. p. I39) and the members of the genus Zosterops ; but their relations to the last require further investigation. Some of them are called “ Humming-birds ” by Anglo-Indians and colonists, but with that group, which, as before indicated <hi rend="smallcaps">(Humming-bird, <,hi> vol. xii. p. 357), belongs to the <hi rend="italic">Picamεe, <,hi> the Sun-birds, being true <hi rend="italic">Passeres, <,hi> have nothing to do. Though part of the plumage in many Sun-birds gleams with metallic lustre, they owe much of their beauty to feathers which are not lustrous, though yet almost as vivid,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="1"> <hi rend="italic">Cf. <,hi> Gadow, <hi rend="italic">Proc. Zool. Society, <,hi> I882, pp. 4O9-42I, pls. xxvii. xxviii. <,note> and the most wonderful combination of the brightest colours—scarlet, purple, blue, green, and yellow—is often seen in one and the same bird. One group, however, is dull in hue, and but for the presence in some of its members of yellow or flame-coloured precostal tufts, which are very characteristic of the Family, might at first sight be thought not to belong here. Graceful in form and active in motion, Sun-birds flit from flower to flower, feeding chiefly on small insects which are attracted by the nectar ; but this is always done while perched, and never on the wing as is the habit of Humming-birds. The extensible tongue, though practically serving the same end in both groups, is essentially different in its quasi-tubular structure, and there is also considerable difference between this organ in the <hi rend="italic">Nectariniidae <,hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Meliphagidæ <,hi> .<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="1"> <hi rend="italic">Cf. <,hi> Gadow, <hi rend="italic">Proc. Zool. Society, <,hi> I883, pp. 62-69, pl. xvi. <,note> The nests of the Sun-birds, domed with a penthouse porch, and pensile from the end of a bough or leaf, are very neatly built. The eggs are generally three in number, of a dull white covered with confluent specks of greenish grey. <,p>  The <hi rend="italic">Nectariniidae <,hi> form the subject of a sumptuous <hi rend="italic">Monograph <,hi> by Capt. Shelley (4to, London, I876-I88O), in the coloured plates of which full justice is done to the varied beauties which these gloriously arrayed little beings display, while, almost every available source of information having been consulted and the results embodied, the text leaves little to be desired, and of course supersedes all that had before been published about them. This author divides the Family into three subfamilies :— <hi rend="italic">Neodrepaninæ, <,hi> consisting of a single genus and species peculiar to Madagascar; <hi rend="italic">Nectariniinæ, <,hi> containing 9 genera, one of which, <hi rend="italic">Cinnyris, <,hi> has more than half the number of species in the whole group ; and <hi rend="italic">Arachnotherinæ <,hi> (sometimes known as “ Spider-hunters ”), with 2 genera including II species— all large in size and plain in hue. To these he also adds the genus <hi rend="italic">Promerops <,hi> ,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="1"> According to Brisson <hi rend="italic">(Ornithologie, <,hi> ii. p. 46O), this name was the invention of Reaumur. It seems to have become Anglicized. <,note> composed of 2 species of South- African birds, of very different appearance, and the affinity of which to the rest can as yet hardly be taken as proved. According to Mr Layard, the habits of the Cape Promerops, its mode of nidification, and the character of its eggs are very unlike those of the ordinary <hi rend="italic">Nectariniidæ. <,hi> In the <,p>  British Museum <hi rend="italic">Catalogue of Birds <,hi> (vol. ix. pp. I-I26, and 29I) Dr Gadow has more recently treated of this Family, reducing the number of both genera and species, though adding a new genus discovered since the publication of Capt. Shelley’s work. <hi rend="smallcaps">(a. n.) <,hi> <,p> 
<,div</label>>