<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb09-22-s06-0658-02" facs="encyclopediabrit22newyrich_raw_0686.jp2" type="entry"><p><label>SUN-FISH</label>
. This name is chiefly and properly applied to a marine fish <hi rend="italic">{Orthagoriscus)</hi> which by its large size, grotesque appearance, and numerous peculiarities of organization has attracted the attention equally of fishermen as of naturalists. Only two species are known,—the rough or short sun-fish (<hi rend="italic">O</hi>. <hi rend="italic">mola),</hi> which is found in all seas of the temperate and tropical zones ; and the much smaller and scarcer smooth or oblong sun-fish (<hi rend="italic">O</hi>. <hi rend="italic">truncatus),</hi> of which only a small number of specimens have been obtained from the Atlantic and Indian Oceans. That this genus belongs to the order <hi rend="italic">Plectognathi</hi> and is allied more especially to the globe-fishes (<hi rend="italic">Diodon</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Tetrodon)</hi> has been indicated in the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Ichthyology</hi> (vol. ix. pp. 663, 694), where also the principal anatomical peculiarities have been noticed, and where illustrations of the young have been given (see figs. 64, 65).</p><p>Sun-fishes have the appearance of tailless fish. This is due to the extreme shortening of the tail, which is supported by only a few short vertebræ and reduced to a broad fringe of the trunk. Directly in front of it rise dorsal and anal fins, high and broad, similar to each other in size and triangular in form. The head is completely merged in the trunk, the boundary between them being indicated only by a very small and narrow gill-opening and a comparatively small pectoral fin. This fin can be of but little use in locomotion, and the horizontal and vertical movements of the fish, as well as the maintenance of its body in a vertical position, are evidently executed by</p><pb xml:id="eb09-22-s06-0659" facs="encyclopediabrit22newyrich_raw_0687.jp2"/><p><label><?xml version="I.O" encoding="utf-8"?> unknown title unknown author <editionStmt> <edition> <date> unknown date <,date> <,edition> <,editionStmt>  unknown <,p>  Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei. <,p> <encodingDesc> <appInfo> <application ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.I5.O" xml:id="docxtotei">  Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI  <,application> <,appInfo> <,encodingDesc> <revisionDesc> <listChange> <change> <date> 2OI9-OI-2OT22:46:46Z <,date> <name> unknown author <,name> <,change> <,listChange> <,revisionDesc>  the powerful dorsal and anal fins. The small mouth, situated in front of the head, is armed with an undivided dental plate above and below, similar to but weaker than the teeth of the globe-fish <hi rend="italic">(Diodon). <,hi> <,p>  Sun-fishes are truly pelagic, propagating their species in the open sea, and only occasionally approach the coast. During the stormy season they live probably at some depth, but in calm bright weather they rise and rest or play on the surface with their dorsal fin high above the water. This habit has given rise to the popular name “ sun-fish,” a term also sometimes applied to the basking- shark (vol. xxi. p. 777), which in like manner enjoys the warmth of a sunny day. In some years the rough sun-fish is by no means scarce on the south coast of England and on the Irish coasts, where it appears principally in the summer months. The usual size is from 3 to 4 feet in length, but this species attains to 7 feet and more. One of the largest specimens (see the accompanying figure) was caught near Portland (Dorsetshire) in I846, and is now in the British Museum; its length is 7 feet 6 inches. The sun-fish has no economic value, <,p>  and is rarely, if ever, eaten. <,p>  Whilst the rough sun-fish has a granulated, rough, shagreen-like skin, the second species <hi rend="italic">(O. truncatus) <,hi> has the surface of the body smooth and polished, with its small dermal scutes arranged in a tesselated fashion. It is oblong in shape, the body being much longer than it is deep. The sides are finely ornamented with transverse silvery, black-edged stripes running downwards to the lower part of the abdomen. It has not been found to exceed 2 feet in length, but is very scarce, only a few specimens having been captured on the coasts of Europe, at the Cape of Good Hope, and off Mauritius. <,p> 
<,div</label>>