<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb09-22-s06-0574-02" facs="encyclopediabrit22newyrich_raw_0598.jp2" type="entry"><p><label>STOLBERG</label>,
<hi rend="smallcaps">Count Christian</hi> (1748-1821), German poet, was born at Hamburg on the 15th October 1748. His father, Count Christian Günther, was a privy councillor in Denmark. Stolberg studied at Göttingen, where he formed one of a “ Dichterbund,” which afterwards became famous. It included, besides Stolberg and his brother, Boie, Bürger, Miller, Voss, Hölty, and Leisewitz. In 1777 he became an official in the civil service at Tremsbüttel in Holstein, and married Louise, the countess of Reventlow, whoso beauty he had often celebrated in his verses. He resigned his office in 1800, and afterwards lived upon his estate in Schleswig. He died January 18, 1821.</p><p>Stolberg was not a poet of high originality, but in some of his poems he gave vigorous expression to sincere and ardent feeling. He excelled, too, in the utterance of gentle and delicate sentiment. Much of his work appeared in association with that of his brother, whose genius was bolder and more impressive than his own. They published together a volume of poems in 1779, and <hi rend="italic">Schauspiele mit Choren</hi> in 1787, their object in the latter work being to revive a love for the Greek drama. The dramas contributed to this volume by Christian Stolberg are <hi rend="italic">Balsazar</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Otanes.</hi> In 1815 the brothers issued a volume of <hi rend="italic">Vaterländische Gedichte.</hi> Christian Stolberg was the sole author of <hi rend="italic">Gedichte aus dem Griechischen</hi> (1782) and of a translation of the works of Sophocles (1787). All his poetical works are included in the <hi rend="italic">Werke der Bruder Stolberg</hi> (20 vols., 1820-25).</p></div></body></text></TEI>