<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb09-22-s06-0532-06" facs="encyclopediabrit22newyrich_raw_0556.jp2" type="entry"><p><label>STEPHEN LL</label>,
pope from March 752 to April 757, was in deacon’s orders when chosen to the vacant see within twelve days after the death of Zacharias.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="1"> Zacharias died March 15, 752, and a presbyter named Stephen was forthwith chosen to succeed him, who, however, died four days afterwards and before consecration. This Stephen is occasionally called Stephen II., the number of popes of the name being thus raised to ten. </note> The main</p><pb xml:id="eb09-22-s06-0533" facs="encyclopediabrit22newyrich_raw_0557.jp2"/><p><label><?xml version="I.O" encoding="utf-8"?> unknown title unknown author <editionStmt> <edition> <date> unknown date <,date> <,edition> <,editionStmt>  unknown <,p>  Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei. <,p> <encodingDesc> <appInfo> <application ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.I5.O" xml:id="docxtotei">  Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI  <,application> <,appInfo> <,encodingDesc> <revisionDesc> <listChange> <change> <date> 2OI9-OI-2OT22:4O:5OZ <,date> <name> unknown author <,name> <,change> <,listChange> <,revisionDesc>  difficulty of his pontificate was in connexion with the aggressive attitude of Aistulf, king of the Lombards. After unsuccessful embassies to Aistulf himself and appeals to the emperor Constantine, he, though in feeble health, set out to seek the aid of Pippin, by whom he was received in the neighbourhood of Vitry le Brulé in the beginning of 754. He spent the greater part of that year at St Denis. The result of his negotiations was the Frankish invasion of Aistulf’s territory and the famous “ donation ” of Pippin (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Popedom, <,hi> vol. xix. p. 495 ; and compare <hi rend="smallcaps">France, <,hi> vol. ix. p. 53I). The death of Stephen took place not long after that of Aistulf. He was succeeded by Paul I. <,p> 
<,div</label>>