<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb09-22-s06-0631-01" facs="encyclopediabrit22newyrich_raw_0657.jp2" type="entry"><p><label>SUIDAS</label>,
the author of a Greek lexicon. His personal life is totally unknown and even his date is uncertain. He must have lived before Eustathius (12th century), who quotes him repeatedly. Under the heading “Adam the author of the lexicon gives a brief chronology of the</p><pb xml:id="eb09-22-s06-0632" facs="encyclopediabrit22newyrich_raw_0658.jp2"/><p><label><?xml version="I.O" encoding="utf-8"?> unknown title unknown author <editionStmt> <edition> <date> unknown date <,date> <,edition> <,editionStmt>  unknown <,p>  Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei. <,p> <encodingDesc> <appInfo> <application ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.I5.O" xml:id="docxtotei">  Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI  <,application> <,appInfo> <,encodingDesc> <revisionDesc> <listChange> <change> <date> 2OI9-OI-2OT22:45:3IZ <,date> <name> unknown author <,name> <,change> <,listChange> <,revisionDesc>  world, ending with the death of the emperor John Zimisces. Under “Constantinople” are mentioned the emperors Basil and Constantine, who succeeded John Zimisces in 975. It would thus appear that Suidas lived in the latter part of the IOth century. The passages in which Michael Psellus (who lived at the end of the IIth century) are referred to are thought by Küster to be later interpolations ; one of them is wanting in the Paris MSS. The lexicon of Suidas is arranged alphabetically, with some slight deviations from the strict alphabetical order. It partakes of the nature of a dictionary and encyclopaedia, containing not only definitions of words but also short articles on historical, biographical, geographical, and antiquarian subjects. It includes numerous quotations from ancient writers ; the scholiast on Aristophanes in particular is much used. Although the work is uncritical and the value of the articles very unequal, it contains a great deal of important information on ancient history and life. It deals with Scriptural as well as pagan subjects, from which we infer that the writer was a Christian. Prefixed to the work is a notice stating “ the present book is by Suidas, but its arrangement is the work of twelve learned men,” and then follow their names. <,p>  The first edition of Suidas was that by Demetrius Chalcondylas (Milan, I499), the next by Aldus (Venice, I5I4). The chief later editions are those by L. Küster (Cambridge, I7O5), by T. Gaisford (Oxford, I834), and by G. Bemhardy (Halle, I834-I853). There is a cheap and convenient edition by Im. Bekker (Berlin, I854). <,p> 
<,div</label>>