<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb09-22-s06-0555-02" facs="encyclopediabrit22newyrich_raw_0579.jp2" type="entry"><p><label>STIRLING</label>, James (1692-1770), mathematician, third son of Archibald Stirling of Garden, and grandson of Sir Archibald Stirling of Keir (Lord Garden, a lord of session), was born at Garden, Stirlingshire, in 1692. Part of his early education was probably obtained at Glasgow, but at eighteen years of age he went to Oxford, where, chiefly through the influence of the earl of Mar he was nominated (1711) one of Bishop Warner’s exhibitioners at Balliol. During his residence at Oxford he made for himself considerable reputation as a student of mathematics. In 1715, however, he was expelled on account of his correspondence with members of the Keir and Garden families, who were noted Jacobites, and had been accessory to the “ Gathering of the Brig of Turk ” in 17 08. From Oxford he made his way to Venice, where he occupied himself as a professor of mathematics. In 1717 appeared his <hi rend="italic">Lineæ Tertii Ordinis Newtonianæ, sive</hi>.... (8vo, Oxford), which contained one or two notable additions to the theory. While in Venice, also, he communicated,</p><pb xml:id="eb09-22-s06-0556" facs="encyclopediabrit22newyrich_raw_0580.jp2"/><p>through Sir Isaac Newton, to the Royal Society a paper entitled “ Methodus Differentialis Newtoniana illustrata ” <hi rend="italic">(Phil. Trans.,</hi> 1718, p. 1050 ; Abridg., vi. p. 428). Fearing assassination on account of having discovered a trade secret of the glass-makers of Venice, he returned with Newton’s help to London about the year 1725. In London he remained for ten years, being most part of the time connected with an academy in Tower Street, and devoting his leisure to mathematics and correspondence with eminent mathematicians. In 1730 his most important work was published, the <hi rend="italic">Methodus Differentialis, sive Tractatus de Summatione et Interpolatione Serierum Infinitarum</hi> (4to, London), which, it must be noted, is something more than an expansion of the paper of 1718. In 1735 he communicated to the Royal Society a paper “ On the Figure of the Earth, and on the Variation of the Force of Gravity at its Surface” <hi rend="italic">(Phil. Trans.,</hi> Abridg., viii. pp. 26-30). In the same year his worldly fortunes changed permanently for the better, through his appointment to be manager for the Scots Mining Company at Leadhills, an appointment which gave scope both to his scientific talents and to his great, though hitherto latent, administrative ability, and which was eminently fortunate for his employers. We are thus prepared to find that his next paper to the Royal Society was concerned, not with pure, but with applied science—“ Description of a Machine to blow Fire by the Fall of Water” <hi rend="italic">(Phil. Trans.,</hi> 1745, p. 315 ; Abridg., ix. pp. 109, 110). His name is also connected with another practical undertaking since grown to vast dimensions. The accounts of the city of Glasgow show that the very first instalment of ten millions sterling spent in making Glasgow a seaport, viz., a sum of £28, 4s. 4d., was for a silver tea-kettle to be presented to “James Stirling, mathematician, for his service, pains, and trouble in surveying the river towards deepening it by locks.” This was in 1752. Stirling died in Edinburgh on 5th December 1770.</p><p>See W. Fraser, <hi rend="italic">The Stirlings of Keir, and their Family Papers,</hi> Edinburgh, 1858; “Modem History of Leadhills,” in <hi rend="italic">Gentleman’s Magazine,</hi> June 1853 ; Brewster, <hi rend="italic">Memoirs of Sir Isaac Newton,</hi> ii. pp. 300, 307, 411, 516 ; J. Nicol, <hi rend="italic">Vital Statistics of Glasgow,</hi> 1881-5, p. 70 ; <hi rend="italic">Glasgow Herald,</hi> 5th August 1886.</p><p>Another edition of the <hi rend="italic">Lineæ Tertii Ordinis</hi> was published in Paris in 1797 ; another edition of the <hi rend="italic">Methodus Differentialis</hi> in London in 1764 ; and a translation of the latter into English by Halliday in London in 1749. A considerable collection of literary remains, consisting of papers, letters, and two manuscript volumes of a treatise on weights and measures, are still preserved at Garden by Stirling’s great-grandson and namesake.</p></div></body></text></TEI></body></text></TEI>