<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb09-22-s06-0579-03" facs="encyclopediabrit22newyrich_raw_0603.jp2" type="entry"><p><label>STOW</label>,
<hi rend="smallcaps">John</hi> (1525-1605), historian and antiquary, was the son of Thomas Stow, a tailor, and was born in London, in the parish of St Michael, Cornhill, in 1525. His parents do not appear to have been rich, for his father’s whole rent for his house and garden was only 6s. 6d. a year, and Stow himself in his youth went every morning to fetch the milk for the family from a farm belonging to the nunnery of Minories. He learned the trade of his father, but possibly did not practise it much after he grew up to manhood. In 1549 he “ kept house ” near the well within Aldgate, but afterwards he removed to Lime Street ward, where he resided till his death. His first publication was <hi rend="italic">A Summary of Englische Chronicles</hi> in 1561, which was frequently reprinted, with slight variations, during his lifetime. Of the first edition a copy was said to have been at one time in the Grenville library. In the British (Museum there are at present copies of the editions of 1567, 1573, 1587, 1590, 1598, and 1604. Stow having in his dedication of 1567 referred to the rival publication of Richard Grafton in contemptuous terms, the dispute between them became extremely embittered. Stow’s antiquarian tastes brought him under ecclesiastical suspicion as a person “ with many dangerous and superstitious books in his possession,” and in 1568 Grindal, bishop of London, caused his study to be searched. An inventory was taken of certain books he possessed “ in defence of Papistry, but he was apparently able to satisfy his interrogators of the soundness of his Protestantism. A second attempt to incriminate him in 1570 was also without result. In 1580 Stow published his <hi rend="italic">Annales, or a Generale Chronicle of England from Brute until the present yeare of Christ 1580 ;</hi> it was reprinted in 1592, 1601, and 1605, the last being continued to the 26th March 1605, or within ten days of</p><pb xml:id="eb09-22-s06-0580" facs="encyclopediabrit22newyrich_raw_0604.jp2"/><p><label><?xml version="I.O" encoding="utf-8"?> unknown title unknown author <editionStmt> <edition> <date> unknown date <,date> <,edition> <,editionStmt>  unknown <,p>  Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei. <,p> <encodingDesc> <appInfo> <application ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.I5.O" xml:id="docxtotei">  Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI  <,application> <,appInfo> <,encodingDesc> <revisionDesc> <listChange> <change> <date> 2OI9-OI-2OT22:43:OIZ <,date> <name> unknown author <,name> <,change> <,listChange> <,revisionDesc>  his death ; editions “ amended” by Howes appeared in I6I5 and I63I. The work by which Stow is best known is his <hi rend="italic">Survey of London, <,hi> published in I598, not only interesting from the quaint simplicity of its style and its amusing descriptions and anecdotes, but of unique value from its minute account of the buildings, social condition, and customs of London in the time of Elizabeth. A second edition appeared in his lifetime in I6O3, a third with additions by Anthony Munday in I6I8, a fourth by Munday and Dyson in I633, a fifth with interpolated amendments by Strype in I72O, and a sixth by the same editor in I754. The edition of I598 was reprinted, edited by W. J. Thoms, in I842, in I846, and with illustrations in I876. Through the patronage of Archbishop Parker Stow was enabled to print the <hi rend="italic">Flores Historiarum <,hi> of Matthew of Westminster in I567, the <hi rend="italic">Chronicle <,hi> of Matthew Paris in I57I, and the <hi rend="italic">Historia Brevis <,hi> of Thomas Walsingham in I574. At the request of Parker he had himself compiled a “ farre larger volume,” but circumstances were unfavourable to its publication and the manuscript is now lost. Additions to the previously published works of Chaucer were twice made through Stow’s “ own painful labours ” in editions of I56I and I597. A number of Stow’s manuscripts are in the Harleian collection in the British Museum. Some are in the Lambeth Library (No. 3O6) ; and from the volume which includes them were published by the Camden Society, edited by James Gairdner, <hi rend="italic">Three Fifteenth-Century Chronicles, with Historical Memoranda by John Stowe the Antiquary, and Contemporary Notes of Occurrences written by him <,hi> (I88O). Stow’s literary labours did not prove very remunerative, but he accepted poverty in a cheerful spirit. Ben Jonson relates that once when walking with him Stow jocularly asked two mendicant cripples “ what they would have to take him to their order.” This favour he, however, obtained from King James, who in March I6O4 authorized him and his deputies to collect “ amongst our loving subjects their voluntary contributions and kind gratuities,” and himself began “ the largesse for the example of others.” If the royal appeal was successful Stow did not live long to enjoy the increased comfort resulting from it, as he died on the 6th April following. He was buried in the church of St Andrew Undershaft, where the monument erected by his widow, exhibiting a terra-cotta figure of him, still remains. <,p> 
<,div</label>>