<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T17:50:28Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>SWANPAN, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Chinese Abacus,</hi> an instrument for performing arithmetical operations. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Abacus.</hi></p><p>SWANSEA, a seaport town of South Wales, in the county of Glamorgan, 206 miles from London. It stands at the mouth of the river Tawy, which serves as its haven. It is a tidal harbour, and can only be entered with the flood-tides, but it has a good dry dock. The town is in a semicircular form, on a rising ground, and has a good appearance. Thc chief street is wide and long, and contains some very handsome houses of private persons, but scarcely a public building worthy of notice. The shipping that arrives and departs is numerous. The copper ore raised in Cornwall is brought to this town to be smelted in its vicinity. A vast quantity of coal is raised in the neighbour</p><p>hood, part of which is used in the several manufactories ; but a large portion is also exported to Cornwall, Devon, and Somerset. There are establishments for making pottery-ware, tin, cast and wrought iron, and beer. Swansea has of late become a much-frequented bathing place, and has been supplied with all the institutions usually found in similar towns, lt is a borough, and for municipal purposes is divided into three wards, and is governed by a portreeve, six aldermen, and seventeen councillors. Jointly with Aber- avon, Kenfig, Loughor, and Neath, it returns one member to the House of Commons. It has several fine gentlemen’s seats near it. The market is on Wednesday, but the town is well supplied with provisions daily. The inhabitants amounted in 1821 to 10,007, and in 1831 to 13,256.</p><p>SWEDEN.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Τηε</hi> early history of Sweden is not less involved in fable than that of most other nations. Some historians have pretended to exhibit regular catalogues of the princes who reigned in Sweden in very early times ; but they differ so much from each other, that no credit can be given to them. All indeed agree that ancient Scandinavia was first governed by judges elected for a certain time by the voice of the people. Among these temporary princes the country was divided, until, in the year of the world 2054 according to some, or 1951 according to others, Eric, or, if we believe Pufendorf, Sueno, was raised to the supreme power, with the prerogatives of all the temporary magistrates united in his person during his lifetime, or so long as his administration should be satisfactory to the people.</p><p>From this very early period till the year 1366 of the Christian era, the histories of Sweden present us with nothing but what is common to all nations in their early periods, the endless combats of barbarians, tending to no other purpose than the effusion of blood. At length, however, Albert of Mecklenburg, having concluded a peace between Sweden and Denmark, which had been at violent war for some time before, was proclaimed king of Sweden. Thc peace was of short duration, being broken in 1368 ; and Albert then entered into a league, offensive and defensive, with the earl of Holstein, the Jutland nobility, the dukes of Sleswick, Mecklenburg, and the Hanse Towns, against the kings of Denmark and Norway. At that time he proved very successful against Waldemar king of Denmark, driving him entirely out of his dominions ; but he himself was defeated by the king of Norway, who laid siege to his capital. A new treaty was soon afterwards concluded, by which Albert was allowed to enjoy the crown of Sweden in peace. Having, however, formed a design of rendering himself absolute, he so displeased his subjects that Margaret of Norway was proclaimed queen of Sweden by the malecontents. A war immediately ensued, in which Albert was defeated and taken prisoner ; but as the princes of Mecklenburg, the earls of Holstein, and the Hanse Towns, entered into a league in his favour, the war raged with more fury than ever.</p><p>The contending parties were at length reconciled. Albert was set at liberty, on condition that he should in three years resign to Margaret all pretensions to the city of Stockholm ; and the Hanse Towns engaged to pay the sum of 60,000 marks of silver if Albert should break that treaty. Eric, the son of Albert, died not long afterwards ; and having no other child, he did not think it worth his while to contend for the kingdom of Sweden : he therefore acquiesced in the pretensions of Margaret, and passed the remainder of his days at Mecklenburg.</p><p>Margaret died in 1415, and was succeeded by Eric of Pomerania. This prince’s reign was cruel and oppressive.</p><p>His misdeeds produced a revolt ; and Charles Canutson, grand mareschal of Sweden and governor of Finland, having joined the malecontents,was declared commander-in-chief of their army. Eric was now formally deposed, and Canutson was chosen regent ; but beginning to oppress the people, and aspiring openly to the crown, the Swedes and Danes revolted. This event was followed by a revolution ; and Christopher, duke of Bavaria, nephew to Eric, was chosen king of Denmark, Sweden, and Norway, in 1442.</p><p>On the accession of this prince, complaints against Canutson were presented from all quarters ; but through the interest of his friends he escaped punishment ; and in 1448, Christopher having died, after a tyrannical reign of about five years, he was raised to the throne to which he had so long aspired. The kingdoms of Denmark and Norway however refused allegiance to him, and a war immediately ensued. In 1454 peace was concluded, and Denmark for the present freed from the Swedish yoke. Nor did Canutson long enjoy the crown of Sweden. Having quarrelled with the magistrates and the archbishop of Upsala, the latter formed so strong a party that the king could not resist him. Canutson died in 1470, after a long and turbulent reign.</p><p>The affairs of Sweden continued to be involved in the utmost confusion till the year 1520, when a great revolution was effected by Gustavus Ericson, a nobleman of the first rank, who restored the kingdom to its liberty, and laid the foundation of its future grandeur. In 1518, Christiern king of Denmark had invaded Sweden, with a design to subdue the whole country ; but being defeated with great loss by young Steen Sture, at that time regent, he set sail for Denmark. Meeting with contrary winds, he made several descents on the Swedish coast, which he ravaged with all the fury of an incensed barbarian. The inhabitants bravely defended themselves, and Christiern was reduced to the utmost distress ; one half of his forces having perished with hunger, and the rest being in the most imminent danger by the approach of a rigorous winter. He then thought of a stratagem, which had almost proved fatal to the regent ; for having invited him to a conference, at which he designed either to assassinate or take him prisoner, Sture was about to comply, when the senate, who suspected the plot, interposed to prevent him. Christiern then offered to proceed in person to Stockholm in order to confer with Sture, on condition that six hostages should be sent in his place. They were accordingly sent ; but the wind happening then to prove favourable, he set sail for Denmark with the hostages, of whom Gustavus Ericson was one. Next year he returned, and having drawn Sture into an ambush, the regent received a wound, of which he died some time after. The kingdom being thus left without a head, matters soon came to the most desperate crisis. The army disbanded itself ;</p></body></text></TEI>