<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-05-22T20:47:25Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>condition to have resisted till the arrival of the Swedish army. The elector, enraged at the loss of these valuable places, ordered his army to join the Swedes with all expedition, and pressed the king so warmly to engage, that at last he yielded to his desire. On the 7th of September 1631, Gustavus led out his army in the finest order, the Swedes forming one column on the right, and the Saxons another on the left; each amounting to 15,000 men. Tilly drew up his men in one vast column, probably with a view of surrounding the flanks of the king’s army. The king led his troops against that wing of the Imperialists commanded by Pappenheim, whom he drove back to a considerable distance. General Bannier in thc mean time cut in pieces the troops of Holstein, and mortally wounded the duke, who commanded them. Pappenheim conducted his troops seven times to the charge, but was as often repulsed by the Swedes. Tilly all this while was engaged with the Saxons ; but having at last driven them off the field, the whole strength of the Imperial army was turned against the Swedish left wing. The Swedes sustained the attack with the greatest firmness, until the king detached the centre to assist them. The Imperialists then were no longer able to maintain their ground ; but gave way everywhere except in the centre, which was composed of eighteen regiments of veterans accustomed to victory, and deemed invincible. They made incredible efforts to maintain their reputation ; and, though swept off in great numbers by the Swedish artillery, never shrunk or fell into confusion. Four regiments, after their officers had been killed, formed themselves, and withdrew to the skirt of a wood. Tilly retired at the head of 600 men, and escaped by the coming on of the night. Seven thousand Imperialists lay dead on the field of battle ; 4000 were taken prisoners ; a fine train of artillery was lost, with upwards of 100 standards, ensigns, and other military trophies.</p><p>Gustavus now determined to penetrate into Franconia, where he reduced several places, especially the fortress of Würzburg. Tilly having collected his scattered troops, which formed an army still superior in number to that of Gustavus, marched to the relief of this place, but came too late. He then directed his march towards Rottenberg, where four regiments were cut in pieces by a Swedish detachment. After this, the king reduced Hanau, Frankfurt on the Maine, and Mentz, having destroyed a body of Spaniards who had attempted to obstruct his passage.</p><p>The court of Vienna was now thrown into the utmost confusion, and sent everywhere begging assistance, and soliciting the Catholic princes to arm in defence of their religion. The emperor was most embarrassed in finding a general capable of opposing Gustavus in the field ; for the late misfortunes of Count Tilly had entirely sunk his reputation. Wallenstein, an old experienced officer, was selected ; but as he had formerly been disgraced, it was apprehended that he would not accept of the command of which he had once been deprived. This objection however was surmounted ; and Wallenstein not only accepted of the command, but, at his own expense, augmented the army to 40,000 men.</p><p>During tlie whole winter the Swedish army kept the field, and before the approach of summer had reduced a great number of places, while the landgrave William made great progress in Westphalia. Gustavus Horn was repulsed before Bamberg, but soon had his revenge, by entirely destroying two regiments of Imperialists. To prevent the troops from being affected by the loss before Bamberg, the king resolved to give battle to Tilly, who was marching into Bavaria to prevent the Swedes from gaining a footing in that electorate. He pursued the Imperial general through a vast tract of country, defeated his rearguard, and having reduced a variety of towns and fortresses on the Danube, penetrated as far as Ulm. Ad</p><p>vancing to the river Leck, the count posted himself in a wood on the opposite side, to dispute his passage. Gustavus endeavoured to dislodge him by a regular fire from seventy pieces of cannon. The slaughter was dreadful ; and Tilly himself, being wounded by a cannon-ball in the knee, died a few days before he was to have been superseded by Wallenstein. The following night the Imperial army evacuated the post. Gustavus immediately crossed the river, and seized the towns of Rain and Neuburg, which the enemy had abandoned, and Augsburg next submitted. From Augsburg the Swedes advanced towards Ratisbon, but were disappointed in their design of obtaining possession of that city, as the Bavarians had thrown a numerous garrison into the place. In the mean time, ambassadors arrived from Denmark, offering the mediation of that crown for obtaining a lasting peace between the contending parties. This negociation however failed of success, as the ambassadors had not been instructed to offer terms favourable to the protestants. Gustavus, now resolving to retort on themselves the cruelties which the Bavarians had inflicted on thc protestants, laid the towns of Morzburg, Friesengen, and Landshut, in ashes. The inhabitants of Munich saved themselves by submission. Gustavus also defeated the forces of the elector, who had been joined by a considerable body of militia.</p><p>While the king was thus employed, Wallenstein had assembled a very numerous army. He was strongly solicited by the elector of Bavaria to come to his assistance ; but, in revenge of the elector’s having formerly obtained the command for Tilly in preference to himself, he drew off towards Bohemia to encounter the Saxons. Arnheim, who commanded the Saxon forces in that place, was an enemy to Gustavus, who had formerly rallied him for his cowardice. He therefore permitted Wallenstein to gain an easy victory, in hopes that his master, the elector of Saxony, a prince entirely devoted to his pleasures, might be induced to relinquish the friendship of such a restless and warlike ally as Gustavus; and indeed he used all the eloquence of which he was master to detach him from the Swedish cause. Several advantages were in the mean time gained by the Imperialists. Pappenheim defeated the archbishop of Bremen’s cavalry at Werden ; and three Swedish regiments were cut off near Kadingen. Pappenheim was however forced to retire, and to withdraw his forces from Stade, of which the Swedes took possession. Wallenstein and the elector of Bavaria, who had now joined their forces, threatened Gustavus with greatly superior numbers. The king, being reinforced with 15,000 men, no longer declined the engagement ; but Wallenstein was too wise to trust the fate of the empire to a single battle against such an enemy as the king of Sweden. Gustavus attacked bis camp, but was repulsed with the loss of 2000 men. Several other misfortunes happened to the Swedes ; and at last, after various manœuvres, Wallenstein directed his course towards Misnia, in order to oblige the elector of Saxony to declare against the Swedes, and to draw them out of Bavaria. Gustavus, notwithstanding the inconstancy of Augustus, immediately set out to assist him. With incredible diligence he marched to Misnia, where the lmperiaiists were assembling their whole strengtli. Hearing that the enemy were encamped at Weissenfels, and that Pappenheim had been detached with a strong corps, Gustavus resolved to engage them before they could effect a junction. With this view he marched to Lützen, where he attacked Wallenstein with incredible fury. The Swedish infantry broke the Imperialists in spite of their utmost efforts, and took all their artillery. The cavalry not being able to pass the river so expeditiously as the king thought necessary, he led the way, attended only by a single regiment and the duke of Saxe- Lauenburg. Here, after charging impetuously, he was killed. The news of his death was in an instant spread</p></body></text></TEI>