<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-05-22T20:47:12Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Description of Kent and Sussex ; Gilpin’s Observations ; Pennant’s Journey from London to the Isle of Wight ; Beauties of England and Wales.</p><p>SUTALURY, a town of Bengal, province of Bakergunge, which trades to some extent in grain. Long. 90. 10. E. Lat. 22. 38. N.</p><p>SUTCHANA, a town of Hindustan, province of Guje- rat, situated to the east of Noanagur, to the chief of which it belongs. An extensive fishery is carτied on along this part of the Gulf of Cutch. The pearl-oyster fishery is also carried on here, and is a source of revenue. Lat. not ascertained.</p><p>SUTHERLAND, an extensive county in the north of Scotland, situated between 57° 53' and 58° 36' north latitude, and between 3° 39' and 5° 15' west longitude from Greenwich ; having the sea on the south-east, west, and north, Caithness on the north-east, and Ross-shire on the south. From north to south it extends from 35 to 50 miles, and from west to east from 45 to 50, and contains, according to the latest authorities, 1754 square miles, or 1,112,560 English acres divided into thirteen parishes, which belong to the synod of Sutherland and Caithness. Of the other divisions, the principal are, Assynt and Edderachylis on the west, and Strathnaver on the east; names recognised by the inhabitants, and which still serve to designate the locality of the natural objects and other circumstances of the country.</p><p>The coast of Sutherland, like that of the other Highland counties of Scotland, presents a succession of inlets of the sea, and bold promontories, with a number of rocks and islets. The principal arms of the sea are Lochs Assynt, Laxford, and Inchard, on the west ; Durness Bay, Loch Eriboll, the Kyle of Tongue, and the bays of Torrisdale and Strathy, on the north ; and Loch Fleet in the Frith of Dornoch, on the south-east : and the more remarkable promontories are, Ru Stoir, on the south side of Loch Assynt ; Cape Wrath, on the north-west extremity of the county ; Far-out Head and Whitten Head, on the north ; and Strathy Head, on the north-east. The interior consists of mountains, mosses, lakes, and streams, presenting great variety in form, but almost all having the same general character of being barren, rugged, and dismal, more especially on the western side ; and so closely thrown together, that there is no valley of any extent, and seldom a tree or a shrub, to relieve the eye. The Assynt mountains have not even heath to cover their nakedness, except in patches among the rocks near their base. Exceptions to this general character occur on the eastern coast, along the Dornoch Frith, and on the banks of a few of the lakes and rivulets. From its latitude, and exposure to the winds of the German and Northern Ocean, the climate of Sutherland is sharp and cold. On the east coast, however, it is not so severe as to prevent the growth of wheat, which sometimes ripens as early here as in many parts of England.</p><p>The principal streams are, Oickel, Fleet, Brora, and Helmsdale, which fall into the Dornoch Frith on the southeast. The tide renders the Oickel navigable by vessels of fifty tons for about twelve miles, and for boats for about eight miles farther ; and they have all good salmon fisheries. These rivulets have their sources among the mountains in the centre of the district, and flow south-east- In the same quarter various streams take their rise, and flow in a northerly direction ; such as Strathy, the Naver, which gives its name to the tract called Strathnaver, the Dinart, &amp;c., most of them containing salmon. The most considerable lake is Loch Shin, about twenty miles long and one broad, situated on the southern side of the county, through which flows a stream of the same name, which falls into the Oickel. There are several others of considerable extent in different parts, the whole occupying about fifty-three square miles, or nearly 34,000 acres. On the north coast the sea has formed some remarkable caves in the limestone rock, particularly one at Smow, to the east of Balnakeel of Durness, thirty-two yards wide and twenty yards high ; and another at Fraisgill, fifty feet high, and twenty feet wide at its entrance, but contracting by degress till its termination, more than half a mile under ground.</p><p>The oldest formation of rocks in Sutherland is gneiss, which extends over the whole county, and affords a great diversity of aspect in the stratification. This formation is traversed by granite veins, which abound in various places in the south-east part of the county, as also in the upper part of the parishes of Reay and Edderachylis. The gneiss is also traversed by veins of greenstone and porphyry. Those of the greenstone are found in great abundance in the south-east district of Assynt, and in the country around Scourie in Edderachylis parish. Porphyry veins are of rare occurrence. Mica-slate is developed to a considerable extent in two parts of the county ; in that portion of the district of Moin which stretches southwards, and constitutes the whole of the mountains of Ben-Hope, Ben-Hee, and Meal-Rynies ; and that part of the county between Loch Fleet and Bonar Bridge. Granite fields prevail in the lower part of the parish of Reay, and in the parishes of Loth and Kogart. Syenite is to be met with in several places. It is most abundant in the mountain of Ben-Laoghal, and that considerable tract of hilly country which intervenes between the head of Loch Fleet and Lairg, at the foot of Loch Shin. The quartz series of rocks occurs principally in greater or less fields in the west part of the county, from Loch Eriboll on the north, to Loch Vattie on the south. This series is connected with sandstone and limestone. The latter is divided into four great fields connected with each other, and running in the same direction as the quartz. There is also a portion of nearly six miles in length at Durness, between Loch Eriboll and Cape Wrath. Red stone and conglomerate are extensively displayed on the east side, and at several points on the north coast and the interior. The oolite scries of rocks, consisting of white sandstone, sandstone flag, slate-clay, limestone, and coal, forms the coast between Golspie and the Ord of Caithness, and has a breadth at the river Brora of three miles. At Brora, coal occurs at several points, but it has been found not to be worth the working. Calcareous sinter and bog iron ore are the only chemical alluvial deposits to be found in the county.</p><p>This county, which is valued in the cess-books at L.26,193. 9s. 7d. Scots, is almost entirely the property of the duke of Sutherland. In 1812 the gross rental of the lands and houses, as returned under the property-tax act, was L.28,458. 8s. 4d. including about L.1700 as the rent of the salmon and other fisheries. Since that period, the great and extensive improvements effected by the spirited proprietors must have augmented the rental in a corresponding degree. More than half the valuation is held under entail. The principal seats are, Dunrobin Castle, duke of Sutherland, on the coast of the Dornoch Frith, in the parish of Golspie ; Skibo, Dempster, on an inlet of the same frith, near the south-eastern corner of the county ; and Tongue Castle, on the Kyle of Tongue, on the north coast. Most of the other proprietors have good modern bouses, all of which are situated near the coast. In no part of Britain has a greater change been effected in so short at period as in Sutherland, and this chiefly by the spirit and liberality of its greatest proprietor, the duke of Sutherland. Within these twenty or thirty years, roads, bridges, harbours, and villages, have been constructed wherever they seemed to be required ; and both the natural and moral obstructions to the improvement of this extensive territory have, as far as it appears practicable, been in a great measure overcome. Before the beginning of the present century, Sutherland was almost in a state of nature, excluded from the benefits of that civilization which had spread over</p></body></text></TEI>