<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T17:51:09Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>when his arms are raised, he would immediately sink to the bottom.</p><p>When a man plunges into the water, and has reached the bottom, he has only to give a small stroke with his foot against the ground in order to rise ; but an experienced swimmer, if he misses the ground, has recourse to another expedient, which is very pretty, and which has not been much considered. Suppose him at a considerable depth, when he perceives that he cannot reach the bottom. In such a case, he first puts his hands before his face, at the height of his forehead, with the palms turned outwardly ; then holding the fore part of his arm vertically, he makes them move backwards and forwards from right to left; that is to say, these two parts of his arms, having the elbow as a kind of pivot, describe very quickly, both the hands being open and the fingers joined, two small portions of a circle before the forehead, as if he would make the water retire, which he in fact does ; and from these strokes given to the water, there results an oblique force, one part of which carries the swimmer upwards.</p><p>SWINDON, a town of the hundred of Kingsbridge in Wiltshire, eighty-three miles from London. It is a neat, well-built town, with a market on Monday, and several fairs. The inhabitants amounted in 1811 to 1341, in 1821 to 1580. and in 1831 to 1742.</p><p>SWINESHEAD, a town in the hundred of Kirton and county of Lincoln, 120 miles from London. It is a place of inconsiderable trade, with a market on Thursday. The inhabitants amounted in 1811 to 1561, in 1821 to 1696, and in 1831 to 1994.</p><p>SWITZERLAND.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Switzerland</hi> is situate in western Europe, having France on the west, Germany on the north, Austria on the east and south-east, and Savoy and Piedmont on the south-west. This country was anciently called Helvetia, from its first known inhabitants : its more modem name is supposed to be derived from the canton of Schwytz, the cradle of Swiss independence. Little is known of the inhabitants of Switzerland till about one hundred years before Christ, when the Cimbri, a race of barbarians inhabiting the northern regions now known as Friesland and Sweden, crossed the Rhine and extended their conquests into Gaul. Several of the Helvetian tribes, tempted by the immense spoils gained by thc Cimbri, entered into an alliance with them, and carried their united ravages nearly to the mouths of the Rhone. In this extremity the Gauls applied for assistance to the Romans, who speedily sent a powerful army to their assistance, under the command of the consul Lucius Cassius. This force, however, was suddenly attacked on the banks of the lake of Geneva, by the Tigurini, a tribe of the Helvetii, led by a young general named Divico. The Romans were totally defeated, the consul and his lieutenant Piso left dead on the field, and the survivors only permitted to retreat after they had given hostages and marched under the yoke. Emboldened by this success, Divico rejoined the Cimbri, and with their united forces crossed the Alps and entered Italy itself, where, however, they were defeated by Marius with tremendous slaughter, and the few who escaped sought refuge among the fastnesses of the Helvetian mountains.</p><p>For nearly half a century after this decisive defeat, the Helvetii confined themselves to their own country. But the recollection of the rich pastures and fertile plains of Gaul outlived the terror of the Roman arms, and made them resolve once more to quit their rocky fastnesses. After spending three years in preparation, they set out with their wives and families, cattle and possessions, led by the same Divico who had commanded their fathers fifty years before. The number who marched out on this expedition is computed at 368,000 souls, of whom 92,000 were able- bodied warriors.</p><p>The Roman province of Gaul was at that time under the government of Julius Cæsar, and that consummate general no sooner heard of the emigration of the Helvetians than he took effectual measures to defeat their plans. After some abortive attempts at negociation, he attacked and defeated them in two engagements with tremendous slaughter. Their strength and spirit were completely broken, and, overwhelmed with shame and grief, their numbers reduced to scarcely 110,000, they returned to their desolated country and rebuilt their ruined habitations. In order to watch and overawe them, Cæsar erected a fortress at Noviodunum (Nyon), on the banks of the lake of Geneva, and established several other garrisons in different parts of the country.</p><p>The Helvetii were at first the allies of the Roman people, but in the reign of Augustus they were reduced to complete subjection, and their country remained in the condition of a Roman province for upwards of three centuries, and underwent various reverses of fortune, according to the prosperous or adverse fortune of the empire to which it was subject. When the innumerable swarms of barbarians issuing from the unknown regions of the north and east overran Italy and destroyed the Roman empire, Switzerland also became their prey. The Goths established themselves in that portion of the country which bordered on Italy ; the Burgundians fixed their residence on both sides of the Jura, on the lake of Geneva, and in the lower Valais, as far as the Aar ; and the Allemanni took possession of the country to the eastward of that country, and of great part of Germany.</p><p>After this state of affairs had continued about a century, a new swarm of adventurers obtained the ascendency. These were the Franks, another German race, who, after traversing the Netherlands, gained possession of the whole of Gaul, and pouring their resistless myriads into Switzerland, forcibly dispossessed the inhabitants, and at length, after various changes, succeeded in obtaining exclusive dominion over the whole of Rhætia and Helvetia. Rhætia and the country between the lake of Constance and the Rhine, the Aar and St Gothard, in which German was the current language, were united to Suabia, while Geneva, the Valais, Neuchâtel, and the present country of Berne, Soleure, Freyburg, and Vaud, the districts in which Romance was the prevailing language, were united to Savoy, under the denomination of Little Burgundy. The Franks introduced into Helvetia the feudal system and other peculiar institutions and laws of the Germanic tribes. To them also the inhabitants were indebted for the blessings of the Christian religion, which contributed powerfully to the progress of civilization, and the revival of the country from its waste and desolate state. Switzerland remained subject to the Franks till after the death of Charlemagne, when, in consequence of the feuds of that monarch’s successors, the vast empire which he had founded was entirely dismembered, and Switzerland was portioned out among France, Italy, and Germany. But this arrangement was of short duration, for the disorders and confusion produced by the continued wars enabled the provincial governors to throw off all allegiance to their feudal superiors, or to secure real independence while yielding nominal obedience. Switzerland was thus divided into a great number of petty states, generally engaged in hostilities with each other, and seldom uniting among themselves unless when menaced by some great and common danger. Such a case presented itself in the reign</p></body></text></TEI>