<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-05-22T20:48:19Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>mind freely, as it became a zealous citizen to do, promising to pay all the fines which should be imposed upon him.</p><p>Being extricated out of this difficulty, Dionysius next proceeded, with all the eloquence of which he was master, to inveigh against those who by means of their power or interest were able to oppose his designs, and by degrees brought them into discredit. His next scheme was to get those exiles recalled whom the nobility had banished at different times ; as thinking that they would support him with all their power, as well out of gratitude, as out of hatred to the opposite party. Having likewise gained this point, he next found means to ingratiate himself with the soldiery to such a degree that, under pretence of taking proper measures for resisting the Carthaginians, he was chosen commander in chief, with absolute and unlimited power. This was no sooner done than, pretending his life was in danger, he selected 1000 men for his guard, whom he attached to his interest by great promises. As no person durst now oppose him, he possessed himself of the capital, where all the arms and provisions were kept ; after which he publicly took the title of king of Syracuse in the year 404 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi> The Syracusans did not tamely submit to their new master ; but Dionysius managed matters so well, that their frequent revolts answered no other purpose than more certainly to entail slavery on themselves ; and he was allowed to possess the throne without much opposition till his death, which happened in the year 366 <hi rend="smallcaps">b. c.</hi></p><p>On the death of Dionysius, he was succeeded by his son, likewise called Dionysius. He was naturally of a mild and peaceable temper, averse to cruelty, and inclined to learning ; but his father, to whom all merit, even in his own children, gave umbrage, stifled as far as possible his good qualities by a mean and obscure education. He no sooner ascended the throne, than Dion, brother to Aristomache, wife of the elder Dionysius, undertook to correct the faults of his education, and to inspire him with thoughts suitable to the high station in which he was placed. For this purpose he sent for the philosopher Plato, under whose care he immediately placed the young king. This instantly produced a reformation on Dionysius ; but the courtiers, dreading the effects of the philosopher’s instructions, prevailed on him to banish Dion, and to keep Plato himself in a kind of imprisonment in the citadel. At last, however, he set him at liberty ; and Plato then returned to his own country.</p><p>Dion, in the mean time, visited several of the Grecian cities, and at last took up his residence in Athens ; but the honours which were everywhere paid him raised such jealousies in the breast of the tyrant, that he stopped his revenue, and caused it to be paid into his own treasury. In a short time Dionysius again sent for Plato ; but, finding it impossible to dissolve the friendship between him and Dion, disgraced, and placed him in a very dangerous situation, in the midst of assassins who hated him. Not daring, however, to offer him any violence, he allowed him soon after to depart ; revenging himself on Dion, whose estate he sold, and gave his wife Arete in marriage to Timocrates, one of his flatterers.</p><p>Dion now resolved to revenge himself on the tyrant for the many injuries which he had sustained, and at once to deliver his country from the oppression under which it groaned. He began with raising foreign troops privately, by proper agents, for the better execution of his design. Many Syracusans of distinction entered into his scheme, and gave him intelligence of what passed in the city ; but of the exiles, of whom there were upwards of 1000 dispersed up and down Greece, only twenty-five joined him ; so much were they awed by the dread of the tyrant. The troops were assembled at the island of Zacynthus, in number only about 800 ; but who had all been tried on many occasions, were well disciplined, and capable of animating by their</p><p>example the forces which Dion hoped to find in Sicily. When they were about to sail, Dion acquainted them with his design, the boldness of which at first occasioned among them no small consternation ; but he soon removed their fears, by telling them that he did not lead them as soldiers, but as officers, to put them at the head of the Syracusans and all the people of Sicily, who were ready to receive them with open arms. Having then embarked in two small trading vessels, they arrived in twelve days at Cape Pachynum, near Syracuse. They at length reached the port of Minoa, not far from Agrigentum, and here they received intelligence that Dionysius had set sail for Italy, attended by a fleet of eighty galleys. Dion now resolved to take advantage of the tyrant’s absence, and immediately proceeded to Syracuse. On his march he prevailed on the inhabitants of Agrigentum, Gela, Camarina, and otlier cities, to join him. As soon as he entered the territories of Syracuse, multitudes flocked to him ; and as nobody appeared to oppose him, he boldly entered the city, where he quickly found himself at the head of 50,000 men. As soon as he had landed in Sicily, Timocrates, to whom his wife Arete had been given by Dionysius, and to whom the care of the city had been left, despatched a courier to let the tyrant know the danger to which he was exposed. Dionysius was, however, accidentally prevented from receiving a timely account of Dion’s arrival ; so that when he entered the citadel by sea, seven days after Dion’s arrival, he found his affairs in a desperate situation. Upon this he had recourse to artifice ; and having amused the Syracusans by a feigned negociation, until he observed that they kept a negligent guard, he attacked them all at once with such fury, that he had almost taken the city. But Dion encouraged the soldiers by his example so much, that he at last obtained a complete victory ; for which they presented him with a crown of gold. It was not long, however, before the ungrateful Syracusans began to think of conferring quite different rewards on their benefactor. Dionysius had the address to render him suspected by the multitude ; at the same time that Heraclides, an excellent officer, but a secret enemy to Dion, did all that lay in his power to sink his credit. Dionysius was soon obliged to fly into Italy, but left Heraclides to oppose Dion.</p><p>Dion at length obtained possession of the city, and Heraclides having submitted to him, was received into favour ; but as his seditious and turbulent behaviour still continued, Dion at last gave orders to put him to death. This action, however necessary, so affected the mind of Dion, that he became melancholy ; and ever after imagined himself haunted by a frightful spectre, resembling a woman of gigantic stature, with the haggard looks and air of a fury. In a short time after he lost his life, through the treachery of Calip- pus, or Gylippus, who pretended to be his intimate friend, and who immediately after caused his wife and sister to be carried to prison. Calippus having removed Dion, soon made himself master of Syracuse, where he committed all manner of cruelties; but he was driven out, and forced to fly to Rhegium, where he was murdered by the same dagger which had killed Dion. In 350 <hi rend="smallcaps">b. c.</hi> Dionysius again made himself master of Syracuse ; and being exasperated by his past misfortunes, became more tyrannical than ever. The Syracusans first had recourse to Icetas, tyrant of Leontini ; but as the Carthaginians t∞k this opportunity to invade them with a powerful fleet and army, they were obliged to apply to the Corinthians. By them Timoleon, a celebrated commander, was sent to the assistance of the Syracusans, whom he found in a very distressed situation ; Icetas being master of the city, the Carthaginians of the harbour, and Dionysius of the citadel. As all parties were equally the enemies of Dionysius, he found it impossible to resist, and therefore surrendered himself to Timoleon, by whom he was sent to Corinth ; where at last he was reduced to the necessity of teaching a school for his support.</p></body></text></TEI>