<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-05-22T20:47:28Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>campaign in Lithuania, were obliged to retire without accomplishing more than the reduction of a single fortress. Charles then returned with the Swedish army to Prussia.</p><p>Leopold, the young king of Hungary, having long beheld the Swedes with a jealous eye, now resolved to declare for Poland. The more effectually to curb the ambition of the Swedish monarch, he solicited the king of Denmark to come to a rupture with him. This application was attended with immediate success, and the Danes invaded Bremen. Charles hastened to oppose this new enemy, and he thus gave such offence to Ragotski, that, neglecting to take the proper measures for his own defence in the absence of the Swedes, he suffered his army to be destroyed by the Poles and Tartars. At the same time the Turks invaded Transylvania, under pretence that Ragotski, being a vassal of the grand signier, had no right to invade Poland without his permission. Ragotski, opposing them in the field, was defeated and killed, leaving Charles destitute of the only ally on whom he could depend.</p><p>The king, however, not dismayed by this misfortune, traversed Pomerania and the duchy of Mecklenburg ; after which he attacked Holstein, while General Wrangel with another corps entered the duchy of Bremen. The general executed his measures with the utmost vigour. In fifteen days he retook all the towns which the enemy had reduced ; defeated and drove the Danish army out of the country, killing 3000 of their best soldiers. In Holstein the king reduced several fortresses, laid Itzehoe in ashes, defeated a body of Danes, and laid siege to Frederic Udda, into which the Danes had thrown a strong garrison. Leaving to Wrangel the conduct of this siege, he himself retired to Wismar in order to observe the situation of affairs in Poland ; and no sooner was he departed than Wrangel attacked the place with such fury, that he became master of it in two hours. In the province of Holland the Swedes were defeated, but the enemy derived no advantage from their victory. At sea the fleets met, and maintained an engagement for two days, without any considerable advantage on either side. In Poland affairs were not better conducted. The house of Austria had now declared for Casimir ; and a German army having entered Poland, reduced Cracow, though not without sustaining great loss.</p><p>The king of Sweden was now surrounded by enemies. The elector of Brandenburg had declared against him ; and he had besides to engage the armies of Austria, Poland, Russia, and Denmark. In this dangerous situation he resolved to attack Denmark, so as to oblige that state to come to a speedy accommodation. His designs were forwarded by a very early frost, which enabled him to transport his troops without shipping. Having marched over the ice to the island of Funen, he cut in pieces a body of 4000 Danish soldiers and 500 peasants. The whole island was reduced in a few days ; after which he passed to Langland, then to Laaland, after that to Falster, and lastly to Zealand. The Danes were terrified at this unexpected invasion, and were resigning themselves to despair, when Charles offered to conclude a peace on equitable terms. The king of Denmark gladly consented, intending to renew the war as soon as he thought it could be done with safety.</p><p>Charles was no sooner retired, than the king of Denmark began to act secretly against him ; on which, resolving to anticipate him in his designs, he appeared unexpectedly with a fleet before Copenhagen. The Swedish monarch laid siege to the capital, but with so little prudence that he made no progress, and was at length compelled to turn the siege into a blockade, which continued to the end of the war. Charles X. died of an epidemic fever, and was succeeded by his son Charles XI.</p><p>The new king, Charles XI. was a minor at the time of his father’s death ; and as the kingdom was involved in a dangerous war with so many enemies, the regency deter</p><p>mined to conclude a peace, if it could be obtained on reasonable terms. A treaty was accordingly concluded at Olivia, by which Casimir renounced his pretensions to the crown of Poland, and that state gave up all pretensions to Livonia. Bornholm and Drontheim were ceded to Denmark, and an equivalent in Schonen remained with Sweden. During the minority of the king, nothing remarkable occurs in the history of Sweden. In 1672 he entered into alliance with Louis XIV. which two years after involved him in a war with the elector of Brandenburg. At first the Swedes carried all before them. Almost all thc towns in Brandenburg were reduced, when the elector arrived with an army to the relief of his distressed subjects. He retook several towns, defeated the Swedes in a general engagement, and soon after forced them to abandon all their conquests. In conjunction with the Danes, he then invaded the Swedish dominions : many places of importance were reduced ; and, in 1676, Sweden received a most destructive blow by the defeat of her fleet in an engagement with the combined fleets of Denmark and Holland. The king soon afterwards took the government into his own hands, and in some degree restored the fortune of Sweden ; but although he was more successful where he commanded in person, the same losses and disgrace attended the Swedish arms in every other quarter. In 1678, the Swedish fleet was defeated in two engagements. At Landscrona a most obstinate battle was fought, from ten in the morning till six at night, when both parties were obliged, by fatigue, to retire to their respective camps. At Oldeval, in Norway, the Swedes were defeated ; and the Danes laid desolate the islands of Oeland, Smaaland, Unno, and Kuno ; while the electoral troops and Imperialists reduced Count Königsmark to the utmost distress in the neighbourhood of Stralsund. In this deplorable situation of affairs Königsmark found an opportunity of attacking his enemies to such advantage, that he obtained a complete victory ; after which he ravaged the duchy of Mecklenburg. Notwithstanding this success, he could not prevent the elector from reducing Stralsund. He was afterwards obliged to evacuate Pomerania ; and, to complete his distress, the fleet which transported the Swedish army from Pomerania was wrecked on the coast of Bornholm.</p><p>At this unprosperous crisis a peace was concluded at St Germains between France and her enemies, by which the Swedes and Danes were left to decide their quarrel between themselves. Denmark was by no means a match for Sweden, even in the distressed situation to which she was reduced ; and a treaty was therefore concluded, on terms much more favourable to Sweden than could have been expected. The peace was confirmed by a marriage between Charles, and Ulrica Eleonora, daughter to the king of Denmark. From this time the Swedish monarch applied himself to the reformation of the state ; and by artfully managing the disputes between the nobility and the peasants, he obtained a decree empowering him to alter the constitution as he pleased. The proceedings of the king after this decree were such as to exaspcrate the nobility, and produce violent commotions. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Patkul.</hi></p><p>On the 15th of April 1697, died Charles XI. leaving his crown to his son, the celebrated Charles XII. at that time a minor. On his accession, he found himself under the tuition of his grandmother Eleonora, who had governed the kingdom during the minority of the late king. Though Charles was at that time only fifteen years of age, he showed a desire of taking the government into his own hands. His counsellors, Count Piper and Axel Sparre, signified his desire to the queen-regent. By her they were referred to the states, and there all were unanimous ; so that the queen, finding that opposition would be vain, resigned her power with a good grace ; and Charles was invested with absolute authority in three days after he had expressed his desire of</p></body></text></TEI>