<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-05-22T20:48:24Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>cing wheat, oil, hemp, tobacco, fruits, and several kinds of delicious wines. The antiquities of this, formerly one of the most populous cities of Europe, are very numerous, and call to remembrance some of the most striking events of the history of the ancient world. The lighthouse is in long. 15. 16. 50. E. and lat. 37. 2. 58. N.</p><p>SYRIA.</p><p>SYRIA, a beautiful and extensive country of Asia, extending along the shore of the Mediterranean, is estimated to be 200 miles in length, and 100 in breadth. It is bounded on the west by the Mediterranean, and is divided from Asia Minor on the north by Mount Taurus and its branches ; while on the east it has a vast and trackless desert, which stretches northwards from Arabia, and which separates it, though not by any distinct boundary, from the countries of Kurdistan and Irak Arabi. On the south it is bounded by Palestine. In ancient history the boundaries of Syria were never accurately defined. They have frequently extended so far south as to comprehend Palestine ; while towards the east also, they were made to range indefinitely over the desert, or as far as the Euphrates. The stricter geography of modem times has assigned more definite and narrower limits to this country. The geographical features of Syria are chiefly formed by the great mountain chain of Lebanon or Libanus, and the minor chain of Anti-Libanus, which, branching off from Mount Taurus, on the frontier of Asia Minor, stretch southward along the whole length of the country in an irregular line, and interlock with the mountains of Judæa. Thc great chain of Libanus rises to its height at the distance generally of 60 or 70 miles from the shore of the Mediterranean ; the intervening country consisting of luxuriant and fertile valleys, diversified with lower ranges of hills ; the land rising, however, gradually, until it reaches its height. The ascent is extremely rugged ; thc road narrow, and often over craggy rocks ; and the cold is intense, the mountains rising above the level of perpetual snow, which lies here to an unknown depth. Mr Buckingham found great difficulty in ascending the heights of Lebanon. The horses sunk deep in the snow, from which they could hardly be extricated. From the united effects of the constant glare of the snow, the lightness of the air, and the fatigue of the ascent, he experienced a giddiness as if he were intoxicated, and found it difficult to walk in a straight line. It occupied the party four hours from the cedars to the summit, and they were so fatigued that they were obliged to stretch themselves on the snow to recover breath. The prospect which the travellers enjoyed when they reached the top was grand and magnificent. On the west they had a view of the lower plain, and beyond, the boundless ocean ; while to the east was seen the lower range of Anti- Libanus, still high, and covered witli snow at its summit, which overlooks the Syrian desert. Burckhardt also mentions, that when he was near the summit he had an extensive view of the sea near Tripoli on the west ; and to the east the Anti-Libanus range, with the intervening lakes. In this manner the country is everywhere diversified, in its interior, with mountains varying in their levels, situation, and appearance ; and it may be divided into the higher and the lower regions, namely, those tracts which lie between the great mountain ranges of Libanus and Anti- Libanus ; those, again, which lie eastward of this last interior range, extending southwards from Aleppo, and also from Damascus, and which are bounded to the eastward by other districts rocky and mountainous, and finally by the Syrian district ; and, lastly, the lower tract, which descends from the mountains of Lebanon to the sea, which is still interspersed with lower ranges of hills.</p><p>The coast is generally low and flat ; and where it is of any breadth between the Lebanon mountains and the Mediterranean, the country is blessed with extreme fertility. The valleys are productive, and yield abundantly the most valuable grains, as well as fruits, in great variety. The oranges of Tripoli, the figs of Beirout, and the pistachios of Aleppo, are held in particular esteem. The coast from Acre to Sidon, through which the road runs, presents a rich tract overgrown with thorns and thistles. The shore is abrupt, and the water deep ; the villages thinly scattered, and the population apparently small, though this fine plain is capable of the highest fertility. The immediate neighbourhood of Sidon is a fine district; the plain at the foot of the hills, which is not above two miles wide, being entirely appropriated to extensive and shady groves and gardens, with lanes between them. The hills are also fruitful, and of a lower level than those farther to the south and to the east of the plains of Tyre. From Tripoli to Beirout the whole coast appears to be formed of sand accumulated by the prevailing westerly winds, and hardened into rocks, where, in order to form an artificial shelter, recourse must have been had to excavation. The plains in the vicinity of most of the towns along the coast have a pleasing and picturesque aspect, being generally covered with olive groves, and fine gardens filled with fruit-trees. This lower country is also well watered, numerous streams flowing down from the mountains, and supplying the means of irrigation, and of fertilizing the ground.</p><p>In ascending the eloping sides of Lebanon, all the varieties of European climate are experienced ; and it is remarkable how successfully the industry of the inhabitants has triumphed over the inequalities of the ground, and other natural difficulties. Burckhardt mentions, that at Bshirrai, which is on a very elevated situation on Mount Lebanon, not far from its summit, and where nature seems to afford nothing for the sustenance of the inhabitants, numerous villages flourish, and every inch of ground is cultivated.@@<hi rend="superscript">l </hi>The town is surrounded with fruit trees, mulberry plantations, vineyards, fields of dhourra and other grain, though there is scarcely a natural plain twenty feet square. But the inhabitants meet this difficulty by building terraces, and thus, with singular industry, securing a portion of level ground to prevent the earth from being swept down by the winter rains, and retaining at the same time the water requisite for the irrigation of their crops. Water is abundant, and streams from numerous springs descend on all parts of the mountain country, and refresh the ground. Volney concurs in the same description. “ By dint of skill and labour,” he observes, “ they have compelled a rocky soil to become fertile. Sometimes, to avail themselves of the waters, they have made a channel for them by means of a thousand windings on the declivities, or have arrested them in the valleys by embankments. At other times they have propt up the earth that was ready to roll down, by terraces and walls;” so that the mountains present the appearance of a staircase, or of an amphitheatre, each tier of which is a row of vines or mulberry trees, of which Volney mentions that he had counted from 100 to 120 tiers from the bottom of the valley to the top of the hill. This elevated and craggy region also presents singular appearances,</p><p><hi rend="superscript">@@@1</hi> Burckhardt’s Travels in Syria and the Holy Land, p. 20.</p></body></text></TEI>