<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-05-22T20:48:21Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>After the expulsion of the tyrant, Timoleon withdrew to Catena, leaving only 400 Corinthians, under the command of an experienced officer named Leon, to guard the citadel. These were immediately besieged by Icetas and the Carthaginians, but Timoleon found means to relieve them in spite of all opposition ; and having dispersed emissaries through the army of Mago the Carthaginian general, exhorting the mercenary Greeks to forsake him, he was so much intimidated, that in spite of all the remonstrances which Icetas could make, he set sail for Africa, leaving his colleague to carry on the war in the best manner he could.</p><p>The day after the departure of Mago, Timoleon assaulted the city so fiercely, that the troops of Icetas were driven from the walls, and the Corinthians became masters of the place. Timoleon, by sound of trumpet, invited the inhabitants to come and assist in demolishing the citadel and other castles, which he called the <hi rend="italic">nests of tyrants ;</hi> after which he caused edifices for the administration of justice to be erected in the place where the citadel had stood. He found the city in a most miserable condition ; for many having perished in the wars and seditions, and others having fled to avoid the oppression of tyrants, Syracuse, once so wealthy and populous, was now become almost a desert ; insomuch that the horses were fed on the grass which grew in the market-place. Timoleon supplied the city with inhabitants from Corinth and other cities of Greece, at the same time that great multitudes from Italy and the other parts of Sicily resorted thither. Timoleon distributed the lands among them ; but sold the houses, and with the money arising from the sale established a fund for the support of the poor. Having thus restored Syracuse, he next delivered all the Greek cities of Sicily from the tyrants who had taken possession of them, all of whom he put to death. After this he resigned his authority, and led a retired life, venerated in the highest degree by the Syracusans, and by all the cities in Sicily. After his death he was honoured as a god ; the expense of his funeral was defrayed by the public ; sports, with horse-races and gymnastic exercises, were held annually on the day of his death ; and it was decreed, that whenever the Syracusans were at war with the barbarians, they should send to Corinth for a general.</p><p>For twenty years the Syracusans enjoyed the fruits of Timoleon's victories ; but new disturbances arising, in a short time another tyrant started up, who exceeded all that had gone before him in cruelty and other vices. This was the celebrated Agathocles, of whose exploits against the Carthaginians a full account is given under the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Carthage.</hi> He was poisoned by one Moenon in the year 289 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c</hi>., after having reigned twenty-eight and lived ninety-five years. A succession of tyrants followed, till at last the city, being held by two rivals, Toenion and Sosistratus, who made war within the very walls, Pyrrhus king of Epirus was invited into Sicily, in order to put an end to these distractions. He willingly complied with the invitation, and was everywhere received with loud acclamations, as the deliverer, not only of Syracuse, but of all Sicily. As he had a fine army of 30,000 foot and 5000 horse, with a fleet of 200 sail, he drove the Carthaginians from place to place, till he left them only the two strong posts of Eryx and Lilybaeum. The former of these he took by assault, and was <hi rend="italic">himself</hi> the first man who mounted the walls, after having killed a great number of Africans with his own hand. The Mamertines, likewise, who had conquered a considerable part of the island, were everywhere defeated and driven out, till at last they were shut up in the city of Messana. The Carthaginians, alarmed at the rapidity of his conquests, sent ambassadors with proposals of peace upon very advantageous terms ; but Pyrrhus, elated by the expectation of reducing the whole island, refused to hearken to any terms unless they would instantly abandon it. So sanguine were his anticipations, that he caused his son to assume the title of king of Sicily; but in the mean time, having displeased the Sicilians by his arbitrary behaviour, they deserted from him in such numbers that he was glad to set out for Italy, for which retreat the embassies he received from the Samnites, Tarentines, and other Italians, furnished him with an honourable pretext. He embarked in the ships which he had brought with him from Italy, but was met at sea by the Carthaginians, who sunk seventy of his vessels, and dispersed or took the rest, so that he saved himself in Italy with only twelve vessels, the poor remains of a fleet of 200 sail. No sooner were the Mamertines apprised of his departure, than they despatched a body of 18000 men to harass him after his landing. These having passed the straits before him, posted themselves on the road which Pyrrhus must take in marching by land to Tarentum, and concealing themselves among woods and rocks, attacked him unexpectedly, and with great resolution. But Pyrrhus be haved on this occasion with his usual bravery. The attack being made on his rear, he hastened thither, and made a dreadful slaughter of the enemy, till a wound in the head obliged him to retire.</p><p>After the departure of Pyrrhus, Hiero the son of Hierocles, a descendant of Gelon, the first king of Syracuse, was chosen general of the forces, along with another named Artemidorus. The two generals had nothing more at heart than to put an end to the confusion and disorder which reigned in the city ; and with this view they entered it at the head of their forces. On this occasion Hiero discovered extraordinary talents for government. By mere dint of insinuation and address, without shedding blood or hurting a single citizen, he calmed the minds of thc people, reconciled the factions, and so gained the affections of all, that he was invested with the whole civil as well as military power in the state. He soon afterwards married the daughter of one of the first citizens ; and having distinguished himself by his exploits against the Mamertines, was unanimously elected king of Syracuse in the year 265 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c</hi>.</p><p>Some time after Hiero's accession to the throne, he again defeated the Mamertines, and reduced them to such straits that they were obliged to call in the Romans to their assistance. The consequences of this have been fully related under the articles <hi rend="smallcaps">Rome</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Carthage.</hi> Hiero, who had allied himself with the Carthaginians, being himself defeated by the Romans, and finding his allies unable to protect him against the power of that republic, concluded an alliance with them, and continued faithful to them even in the time of the second Punic war, when they were in the greatest distress. In his reign flourished the celebrated mathematician Archimedes, whose genius he employed in fortifying the city of Syracuse, by innumerable machines, in such a manner as rendered it absolutely impregnable to every method of attack known at that time.</p><p>Hiero died about 211 <hi rend="smallcaps">b. c.</hi> and was succeeded by his grandson Hieronymus ; but he imprudently forsook the counsels of his grandfather, and entered into an alliance with the Carthaginians. He was soon afterwards murdered, in consequence of his tyranny and cruelty; and the greatest disorders took place in the city, which Hannibal, though then in Italy, found means to foment, in hopes of keeping the Syracusans in his interest. This indeed he effected ; but as his own affaire in Italy began to decline, he could not prevent Marcellus from landing in Sicily with a formidable army, which the Sicilians had no means of resisting. Syracuse was soon invested ; but the machines invented by Archimedes baffled all attempts to take it by assault. The immense preparations which the consul had made for taking the city by storm, could not have failed to accomplish his purpose, had the place been otherwise defended than by the genius of Archimedes. The Roman fleet consisted of sixty quinqueremes, besides a far greater number of other ships. The decks were covered with soldiers armed with</p></body></text></TEI>