<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T17:51:19Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>siderable quantities of wines and cheeses, and has very extensive manufactories of watches and jewellery, lace and printed cottons. Within these few years the making of sparkling wine has been greatly extended. The principal manufactures are watches, printed cottons, and lace. The probable production of printed cottons in Neuchâtel is now about 80,000 pieces per annum, each containing about thirty-two English yards. Watch-making is carried on to an immense and increasing extent in the mountainous districts of this canton, in the French portion of the canton of Berne, and in the town and neighbourhood of Geneva. It has been a source of wealth and comfort to many thousands of the inhabitants, who, in the remote villages of the Jura, have gathered around them a large portion of the enjoyments of life. Switzerland has long furnished the markets of France ; and though the names of certain French watchmakers have obtained a European celebrity, yet an examination into this trade has elicited the fact, that not ten watches are made in Paris in the course of a year, the immense consumption of France being furnished from Switzerland, and the Swiss works being only examined and rectified by the French manufacturers. The contraband trade into France was immense, but they are now admitted into that country at six per cent. for gold, and ten per cent. for silver watches ; and a considerable quantity pays regularly this moderate duty. The Jura Mountains have been the cradle of the most exquisite productions of the mechanical arts. During the winter, which lasts from six to seven months, the inhabitants are almost imprisoned in their dwellings, and occupy themselves in those works which require the utmost development of skilful ingenuity. Nearly 120,000 watches are produced annually in the elevated regions of Neuchâtel. The largest proportion of these is exported to the United States of America. It is not easy to state the exact number of workmen who are engaged in watchmaking, because nearly the whole of the population are more or less occupied in this branch of industry, which they carry on in their own houses and amidst their own families. The manufactures of Neuchâtel are admitted into Prussia on diminished duties. Watches and such articles pay only one half of the duty stipulated by the tariff.</p><p>The main source of the trade in the canton of Thurgau is the manufacture of cotton, flax, and silk, with their various establishments for weaving, printing, and dyeing. The exports are principally wine, fruit, and cider, oats, brandy, linen, cattle, &amp;c. The imports principally consist of iron, iron-wares, and metal manufactures, salt, woollen goods, fine cloths, sugar, coffee, chicory, madder, drugs, and dye-stuffs, tobacco, wheat, fine cotton yarns, &amp;c.</p><p>The canton of Schaffhausen possesses a considerable transit trade, which is facilitated by the navigation of the Rhine. This canton has suffered more than any other from the Prussian commercial league, its principal export being wine, of which the German markets were the main seats of consumption. Nature has blessed this small district with a fertile soil, which places it in the class of the agricultural rather than that of the commercial cantons of Switzerland.</p><p>Basel is almost entirely a commercial and manufacturing territory ; its industry is principally engaged in the production of ribbands and some silks. The former are exported to thc value of about 10,000,000 of French francs. About one half of these goes to the United States, the remainder is sent to Germany, France, Holland, Denmark, Sweden, &amp;c. Since 1814, and particularly within a few years, the progress of Basel has been very great, both as regards the quantity and the quality of its manufactures.</p><p>The manufactures of Zurich are of ancient date. The silk manufacture of this town dates as far back as the thirteenth century, and it still forms a very important article in the trade of this canton. The silk manufactures of Zurich consist of florentines, gros de Naples, gros de Berlin, marcelines, taffetas, serges, levantines, silk handkerchiefs, a few shawls, &amp;c. The number of looms at present employed in the silk trade may be reckoned at 10,000 ; and the total annual produce of the silk manufacture of Zürich has been estimated at L.600,000 sterling. The silk manufacture of Switzerland is constantly increasing, and it is in the town and canton of Zürich that it is most extensively carried on. Great improvements have been made, and are constantly making, in this branch of industry. Zürich also possesses some cotton manufactures. About 800,000 pieces of cotton are manufactured yearly. The imports of Zürich consist mainly of cotton yarns from England, woollen cloths, bark, straw hats, linens, furs, glass, stationery, wheat principally from Suabia, wine from France, Neuchâtel, and Vaud, brandy, fruits, tobacco, fir-wood, cotton and silk, wool and colonial cattle, butter and cheese, minerals, &amp;c.</p><p>The principal manufacture of Aargau is cotton in its various branches ; the second in importance is that of silk. The exportation of these articles is principally to Italy, Piedmont, the northern states of Germany, Turkey, and North and South America. The principal articles of import are wheat, wine, salt, and leather, iron and other metals, hard ware, tobacco and snuff, hemp and flax, chicory, oil, raw cotton, cotton twist, fine cotton manufactures from England, woollen cloths, raw silk, spices, drugs, dye-stuffs, dry goods, indigo, &amp;c.</p><p>The canton of Geneva, for its small extent of surface, presents a remarkable scene of manufacturing industry. Jewellery, watches, and musical boxes, are three of the most important branches of trade, employing a great number of hands, and imparting the utmost activity to a commerce which conveys these productions to all quarters of the globe. The watchmakers of Great Britain buy largely both in Geneva and Neuchâtel. The average annual export to England is from 8000 to 10,000 watches, and the average price about L.10 sterling. The jewellery sent from Geneva to England represents a value of about L.60,000 per annum. In an article of such small bulk as a watch, it has been found impossible to guard against illicit introduction ; the contraband trade is consequently very large, and scarcely a single watch pays the duty of twenty-five per cent. The smuggling is carried on almost wholly by French houses, who reap the profits of the smuggling premium, and who, it appears by the small amount of seizures, really run scarcely any risk. The English consumer pays the gains of the French smuggler, and pays too for that damage, delay, and risk which accompany fraudulent transactions. Of other sorts of merchandise Geneva exports annually about 120,000 quintals. The amount of British manufactures sold in the canton is estimated at about L.200,000 per annum. One half of this is supposed to be consumed in the town and neighbourhood, the other half is smuggled into France.</p><p>There are several striking peculiarities in the condition and employments of the labouring classes of Switzerland. There are few weaving factories or buildings in which the labouring weavers are congregated together. Their looms are in their own abodes, which are scattered over the country. They receive from the manufacturer the chain and the woof, and return to him the woven article. Weaving can hardly indeed be called a manufacturing industry ; it is a sort of domestic labour, associated with, and often subordinate to, agricultural employment. It is in fact but one of two means of existence, the labouring population being only in part dependent on it. It is very common to find many looms in the cottage of a small farming labourer, the whole of which may be worked by its members when the weather, or the seasons, or other circumstances, withdraw them from the field. In the common apartment of the family of the country people, one or two members of the family may be seen weaving, and carrying on at the same</p></body></text></TEI>