<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-05-22T20:47:29Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>reigning alone. He was scarcely seated on the throne when a powerful combination was formed against him. Augustus king of Poland formed designs on Livonia ; the king of Denmark revived his disputes with the duke of Holstein, as a prelude to a war with Sweden ; and Peter the Great of Russia began to form designs on Ingria, formerly a province of Russia. In 1699 the king of Denmark marched an army into Holstein. Charles sent a considerable body of troops to the duke’s assistance ; but before their arrival the Danes had ravaged the country, taken the castle of Got- torp, and laid close siege to Tonningen. Here the king of Denmark commanded in person, and was assisted by the troops of Saxony, Brandenburg, Wolfenbuttel, and Hesse- Cassel. Britain and Holland, as guarantees of the last treaty with Denmark, in concert with Sweden, joined Charles against this confederacy, and sent fleets to thc Baltic. They proposed a termination of the war on equitable terms ; but these were haughtily refused by the Danish monarch, who despised the youth and inexperience of Charles, and relied too much on the alliance which he had formed with Saxony, Brandenburg, Poland, and Russia. Tonningen, however, resisted all his efforts ; and when he ordered the place to be stormed, he had the mortification to sec his troops driven headlong from the walls by a handful of Swedes.</p><p>In the year 1700, Charles, having intrusted the affairs of the nation with a council chosen out of the senate, set out on the 8th May from his capital, to which he never afterwards returned. He embarked at Carlscrona, and defeated the fleet of the allies. Having made a descent on the island of Zealand, he defeated a body of cavalry that opposed his march, and then proceeded to invest Copenhagen by sea and land. The king of Denmark saw the necessity of either having his capital destroyed, or of doing justice to the duke of Holstein. He chose the latter ; and a treaty was concluded on much the same terms as formerly. Charles, being thus at liberty to turn his arms against the other princes who had conspired his destruction, resolved to lead his army against Augustus king of Poland. On the road, however, he received intelligence that the czar of Russia was on his march to oppose him, and had laid siege to Narva with an army of 100,000 men. The contest that ensued between Charles and Peter, with the celebrated battles of Narva and Pultava, have been already related under <hi rend="smallcaps">Russia, so</hi> that we shall here confine ourselves chiefly to those events in which Peter the Great was not immediately concerned. Peter was the chief support of Augustus, and he took the most active measures to oppose the progress of the Swedish monarch. His want of success, and the subsequent contests between him and Charles, till the decisive battles of Pultava, are related in the same article.</p><p>In 1701, as early as the season permitted, Charles, having received a reinforcement from Sweden, took the field, and appeared suddenly on the banks of the Duna, along which the Saxon army was posted to receive him. The king of Poland being at that time sick, the army was commanded by Ferdinand duke of Courland, Marshal Stenau, and General Paykel, all officers of valour and experience. They had fortified some islands in the mouth of the river, and taken every other precaution against an attack ; the soldiers were hardy, well disciplined, and nearly equal to thc Swedes in number ; yet Charles, having passed the river in boats with high sides, to screen the men from the fire of the enemy, attacked them with such fury, that they were entirely defeated, and with great loss. This victory was followed by the surrender of all the towns and fortresses in the duchy of Courland. Charles then passed into Lithuania, where every town opened its gates to him. At Birsen, an army of 20,000 Russians retired with the utmost precipitation on the news of his approach. Here Charles, perceiving that the kingdom of Poland was greatly disaffected to Augustus, began to project the scheme of dethroning him by means of his own subjects. This scheme he executed with more policy than he ever showed on any other occasion.</p><p>Augustus, in the mean time, finding his scheme of peace frustrated, had recourse to the senate ; but met with such a rough answer from them, that he determined to apply to Charles. To him therefore he sent his chamberlain ; but a passport being forgotten, the ambassador was arrested. Charles continued his march to Warsaw, which surrendered on the first summons ; but the citadel held out for some days. Augustus, finding at last that no dependence was to be placed on the Poles, determined to trust his fortune wholly to the Saxon army and the nobility of the palatinate of Cracow, who offered to support him to the utmost of their power. The Saxon army had now advanced to the frontiers, and Augustus immediately put himself at its head. Being joined by the nobility of Cracow, he found that his forces amounted to 30,000 men, all brave and well disciplined. With these he marched in quest of his enemy ; nor did the Swedish monarch decline the combat, though he had with him only 12,000 men. Though the Saxons were strongly posted, having their front covered by a morass, besides being fortified with pallisadoes and chevaux de frise, they were attacked with irresistible impetuosity, and entirely defeated. This victory was followed by the loss of Cracow. Charles then set out in pursuit of the flying army, with a design of preventing them from re-assembling ; but his horse falling under him, he had the misfortune to break his thigh, by which he was confined six weeks, and thus Augustus obtained some respite. He improved this interval. Having convoked a diet, first at Marienburg, and then at Lublin, he obtained the following resolutions; that an army of 50,000 men should be raised by the republic for the service of the prince ; that six weeks should be allowed the Swedes to determine whether they were for war or peace ; and that the same time should be granted to the turbulent and discontented nobles of Poland to make their concessions. To counteract the effects of these resolutions, Charles assembled another diet at Warsaw ; and while the two assemblies disputed concerning their rights and privileges, he recovered from his wound, received a strong reinforcement from Pomerania, and utterly defeated and dispersed the remains of the Saxon army.</p><p>The ill fortune of Augustus continued still to prevail. In 1704 he was formally deposed by the diet, and the crown was conferred by Charles on Stanislas Lecsinsky, palatine of Posnania. Augustus however did not yet tamely relinquish his kingdom. His adherents daily skirmished with the Swedes ; and Augustus himself, being reinforced by 9000 Russians, retook Warsaw, and had nearly surprised the new king, who lived in perfect security in the city while Charles fought his battles. Count Hom, with 1500 Swedes, vigorously defended the citadel ; but at last, finding it no longer tenable, he was obliged to surrender at discretion. Thc reduction of Warsaw was among the last advantages gained by Augustus in the course of this war. His troops were now composed of Saxon recruits and undisciplined Poles, w ho had no attachment to his person, and were ready on all occasions to forsake him. Charles and Stanislas advanced with the victorious army ; the Saxons fled before them, and the towns several miles round tendered their submission. The Poles and Saxons were under the command of Schullemberg, a most sagacious and experienced general, who used every expedient to check the progress of the Swedes. With all his conduct and caution he found himself outwitted, and Charles in the neighbourhood of his camp, ready to fall on him, while he thought him at fifty leagues distance. The Swedish monarch attacked him with a superior army, but entirely composed of horse. Schul- lemberg had posted his men in such a manner as rendered it impossible to surround them. His first rank, being armed with pikes and muskets, presented a rampart of bayonets; the</p></body></text></TEI>