<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T17:50:49Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>lead in person, to co-operate with the emperor and the king of Prussia, he was obliged to negociate large loans, and to impose on his subjects heavy taxes. The nobles took advantage of that circumstance to prejudice the minds of many of the people against the sovereign who had laboured so long for their good. On the 16th of March 1792 he received an anonymous letter, warning him of his immediate danger from a plot that was laid to take away his life ; requesting him to remain at home, and avoid balls for a year ; and assuring him that, if he should go to the masquerade for which he was preparing, he would be assassinated that very night. The king read the note with contempt, and at a late hour entered the ball-room. After some time, he sat down in a box with Count d’Essen, and observed that he was not deceived in his contempt for the letter, since, had there been any design against his life, no time could be more favourable than that moment. He then mingled, without apprehension, among the crowd ; and just as he was preparing to retire in company with the Prussian ambassador, he was surrounded by several persons in masks, one of whom fired a pistol at the back of the king, and lodged tlie contents in his body. A scene of dreadful confusion immediately ensued. The conspirators, amidst the general tumult and alarm, had time to retire to other parts of the room ; but one of them had previously dropped his pistols and a dagger close by the wounded king. A general order was given to all the company to unmask, and the doors were immediately closed ; but no person appeared with any particular distinguishing marks of guilt. The king was immediately conveyed to his apartment ; and the surgeon, after extracting a ball and some slugs, gave favourable hopes of his recovery. But the prognostication of his medical attendants soon appeared to be fallacious, and on the 28th of March a mortification was found to have taken place. He expired on the following day ; and on opening his body there were found within the ribs a square piece of lead and two rusty nails.</p><p>The king had by his will appointed a council of regency ; but convinced by recent experience how little dependence was to be placed on the attachment of his nobles, and aware of the necessity of a vigorous government in times of such difficulty and danger, he appointed his brother, the duke of Sudermania, sole regent, till his son, then a minor, should attain the age of eighteen years. In his dying moments he desired that all the conspirators, except the perpetrator of his murder, might be pardoned.</p><p>The young king, who was about fourteen at his father’s death, was proclaimed by the name of Gustavus IV. The regent soon took the most vigorous and active measures to apprehend and punish the projectors and perpetrators of the murder of his brother. A nobleman of the name of Ankarström confessed himself the assassin, and gloried in the action, which he called liberating his country from a monster and a tyrant. He was executed in a most cruel manner on the 17th of May. Other two noblemen, and two officers, also suffered death ; but the rest of the conspirators were either pardoned, or punished only by fine and imprisonment.</p><p>From the accession of Gustavus IV. till the revolution which has been recently effected in Sweden, few transactions of any importance have occurred. Soon after the king had assumed the administration of affairs, he engaged warmly in the war against France, and till the time of his deposition continued a most faithful ally of Britain. The efforts of thc Swedish monarch towards humbling the power of Bonaparte have been already noticed under the articles <hi rend="smallcaps">Britain</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">France;</hi> and the war with Russia, in which his alliance with Britain had involved him, has been sufficiently touched in the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Russia.</hi> This prince seems to have been endowed with amiable qualities; but he was certainly rash and imprudent, and perhaps in some degree tinctured with insanity. He thus materially injured his kingdom, and alienated the affections of his principal nobles, especially of his uncle the duke of Sudermania.</p><p>In the beginning of March 1809, the plan which appears to have been concerted between the duke of Sudermania and the principal nobility was carried into effect. The king was arrested ; the duke assumed the reins of government, and issued a proclamation, announcing that, under existing circumstances, the king was incapable of conducting the affairs of the nation. Gustavus, now in close custody, was easily prevailed upon to abdicate the government. The diet was assembled ; the duke of Sudermania was declared king of Sweden, under the title of Charles XIII.; Prince Augustenberg was chosen crown prince ; and various changes were introduced into the constitution, confirming the powers of the diet, and removing what the prevailing party held to be encroachments of the crown during the late and preceding reigns. The people, wearied or disgusted by the late king’s folly and rashness, readily acquiesced in all the alterations. Peace was then made with Russia ; a measure which had become absolutely necessary, as the military force of the kingdom was completely broken, and no means were left for checking the progress of the enemy. By this peace Sweden lost Finland, a country of peculiar importance to her, on account of the supplies of grain which she was accustomed to draw from it ; but in the treaty she reserved the right of yearly importing a certain quantity of grain, duty free. Swedish Finland, with Lapmark, now annexed to Russia, was estimated to contain about 120,000 square English milcs, with 895,000 inhabitants. On the 6th of January 1810, peace was also concluded with France, which restored Pomerania.</p><p>Sweden was now enjoying tranquillity, when the sudden and unexpected death of the crown prince Augustenberg, in April 1810, became a new source of perplexity. The duke of Sudermania was old and in a feeble state of health ; and as there was no person within the kingdom who had any title by blood to the throne, it was necessary, for the security of the new order of things, to choose a successor. The threatening position which the acquisition of Finland gave to Russia induced the noblemen who in concert with the court took a lead in this business, to look for some man of military talents. It happened that Bernadotte, prince of Ponte Corvo, who had lately commanded in the north of Germany, had, by his liberal and kind treatment, gained the peculiar esteem of the Swedish officers and soldiers whom be had made prisoners in Gustavus’s ill-concerted operations in Pomerania. He was besides highly respected for his military skill ; and had been still further raised in general estimation, in consequence of Napoleon having removed him from his command for his lenity and humanity in the exercise of his power. Some of the Swedish officers, to whom his character was known, first conceived the idea of offering him the succession to the crown. The scheme was for some time kept as secret as possible ; but it received so much countenance from the most considerable men, that it was at length opened to Bernadotte himself at Paris. He received it as might be expected, and his friends redoubled their intrigues. The prince of Denmark had been proposed, but the ancient enmity against that country was an invincible obstacle to his success. At length, when every thing was prepared, the diet was called, and Bernadotte was with acclamation elected crown prince by all the four orders, on the 21st of July. Of all the changes in the fortune and station of individuals which arose out of the French revolution, this is perhaps the most singular. Bonaparte seized thc royal power and dignity for himself, and by force of arms he compelled some of the weaker states to accept his relations and followers as kings. But it does not appear that he was ever consulted as to Bernadotte's elevation, or hail the smallest influence in it, except that</p></body></text></TEI>