<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-05-22T20:47:35Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>change his station, but he remained obstinate. At last he was seen to fall on the parapet, and was heard to utter a deep groan. He soon afterwards expired, having been mortally wounded, as is supposed, by a cannon-ball.</p><p>Charles XII. was succeeded by his sister the princess Ulrica Eleonora, wife to the hereditary prince of Hesse. On this occasion the states took care to make a previous stipulation for the preservation of their liberties, and obliged the princess, before entering on the government, to sign a document to this effect. Their first care was to make peace with Great Britain, which the late king intended to have invaded. In order to prevent their further losses by the progress of the Russian, the Danish, the Saxon, and other arms, the Swedes made many great sacrifices to obtain peace from these powers. The French, however, about the year 1738, formed a dangerous party in the kingdom, which not only broke its internal quiet, but led it into a ruinous war with Russia, by which it lost the province of Finland. Their Swedish majesties having no children, it was necessary to settle the succession ; especially as the duke of Holstein was descended from the queen’s eldest sister, and was, at the same time, the presumptive heir to the empire of Russia. Four competitors appeared ; the duke of Holstein Gottorp, Prince Frederic of Hesse-Cassel, nephew to the king, the prince of Denmark, and the duke of Deux-Ponts. The duke of Holstein would have carried the election, had he not embraced the Greek religion that he might mount the throne of Russia. The czarina interposed, and offered to restore all the conquests she had made from Sweden, excepting a small district in Finland, if the Swedes would receive the duke of Holstein’s uncle, Adolphus Frederic, bishop of Lübeck, as their hereditary prince and the successor to the crown. This was agreed to ; and a peace concluded at Abo, under the mediation of his Britannic majesty. The peace was so firmly maintained by the empress of Russia, that his Danish majesty thought proper to drop all resentment for the indignity offered his son. The prince-successor married the princess Ulrica, third sister to the king of Prussia; and in 1751 he entered into the possession of his new dignity, which proved to him a crown of thorns. The French had acquired great influence in all the deliberations of the Swedish senate, who of late had been little better than pensioners to that crown. The intrigues of the senators forced Adolphus to take part in the war against Prussia ; but as that war was disagreeable, not only to the people, but also to the king of Sweden, the nation never made so mean an appearance ; and on Russia’s making peace with the king of Prussia, the Swedes followed the example. Adolphus died dispirited in 1771, after a turbulent reign of twenty years, and was succeeded by his son Gustavus.</p><p>The most remarkable transaction of this reign is the revolution which took place in the government in the year 1772, by which the king, from being the most limited, became one of the most despotic monarchs in Europe. Ever since the death of Charles XII. the whole power of the kingdom had been lodged in the states ; and this power they had much abused. Gustavus therefore determined either to seize on that power of which they made such a bad use, or to perish in the attempt. The revolution was effected in the following manner. On the morning of the 19th of August 1772, a considerable number of officers, as well as other persons known to be attached to the royal cause, had been summoned to attend his majesty. Before ten he was on horseback, and visited the regiment of artillery. As he passed through the streets he was more than usually courteous to all he met, bowing familiarly to the lowest of the people. On the king’s return to his palace, the detachment which was to mount guard that day being drawn up together with that which was to be relieved, his majesty retired with the officers into the guard-room. He then addressed them with all that eloquence of which he is said to have been a master ; and after insinuating to them that his life was in danger, he exposed to them in the strongest colours the wretched state of thc kingdom, the shacldes in which it was held by means of foreign gold, and the dissensions and troubles arising from the same cause which had distracted the diet during the course of fourteen months. He assured them that his only design was to put an end to these disorders, to banish corruption, restore true liberty, and revive the ancient lustre of the Swedish name, which had been long tarnished by a venality as notorious as it was disgraceful. Then assuring them in the strongest terms that he disclaimed for ever all absolute power, or what the Swedes call <hi rend="italic">sovereignty,</hi> he concluded with these words: “ I am obliged to defend my own liberty and that of the kingdom against the aristocracy, which reigns. Will you be faithful to me, as your forefathers were to Gustavus Vasa and Gustavus Adolphus ? I will then risk my life for your welfare and that of my country.” The officers, most of them young men, of whose attachment the king had been long secure, and who did not perhaps perceive the real tendency of his majesty’s request, were allowed no time to reflect, immediately gave their assent, and took an oath of fidelity to him. Only three refused. One of these, Frederic Cederström, captain of a company of the guards, alleged he had already, and very lately, taken an oath to be faithful to the states, and consequently could not take that which his majesty then exacted. The king, looking at him sternly, answered, “ Think of what you are doing.” “ I do,” replied Cederström ; “ and what I think to-day I shall think to-morrow ; and were I capable of breaking the oath by which I am already bound to the states, I should be likewise capable of breaking that which your majesty now requires me to take.” The king having then ordered Cederström to deliver up his sword, placed him under arrest. His majesty, however, apprehensive of the impression which his proper and resolute conduct might make on the minds of the other officers, soon afterwards softened his tone ; and again addressing himself to Cederström, told him, that as a proof of the opinion which he entertained of him, and the confidence which he placed in him, he would return him his sword without insisting on his taking the oath, and would only desire his attendance that day. The undaunted captain continued firm ; he answered, that his majesty could place no confidence in him, and that he begged to be excused from the service.</p><p>While Gustavus was shut up with the officers, senator Ralling, to whom the command of the troops in the town had been given two days before, came to the door of the guard-room, and was told that he could not be admitted. The senator insisted on being present at the distribution of the orders, and sent to the king to desire it ; but was answered, he must go to the senate, where his majesty would speak to him. The officers then received their orders from the king ; the first of which was, that the two regiments of guards and of artillery should be immediately assembled, and that a detachment of thirty-six grenadiers should be posted at the door of the council-chamber to prevent any of the senators from coming out. But before the orders could be carried into execution, it was necessary that Gustavus should address himself to the soldiers ; men wholly unacquainted with his designs, and accustomed to pay obedience only to the orders of the senate, whom they had been taught to hold in the highest reverence. As his majesty, followed by the officers, was advancing from the guard-room to the parade for this purpose, some of them, more cautious, or perhaps more timid, than the rest, became, on a short reflection, apprehensive of the consequences of the measure in which they were engaged : they began to express their fears to the king, that unless some person of greater weight and influence than themselves</p></body></text></TEI>