<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-05-22T20:47:13Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>the rest of Britain ; and this exclusion was principally owing to the want of roads and other means of communication.</p><p>During the last twenty years the greatest changes have taken place. “ Before that period, the injurious system of sub-letting prevailed, and both the knowledge and the practice of farming were exceedingly defective. The place of Dunrobin excepted, there was neither draining, trenching, nor fallow, and very little green crop, besides potatoes and a little pease. There were few fences, and these few bad. The plough, which was rudely constructed, had no part of it iron but the coulter, the sock, and the hook at the end of the beam. Four country garrans, or highland ponies, were yoked to the plough abreast, and the driver walked in front of them backwards. There were few wheeled vehicles that deserved the name. Corn, fuel, &amp;c. were carried in a kind of frame called crubags, fastened on horseback to a wooden saddle, that rested on a straw-mat. The public road was the only one, and that itself indifferent. The dwellings of the subtenants were wooden frames, thatched with turf; and of these, one end accommodated cattle, horses, and. sometimes pigs. One end also of the turf-coverings of these huts, saturated as it was with soot, was annually stript off and converted into manure. With such dwellings the dress of their tenants corresponded. The state of things is now very different. Farming is brought to the highest degree of excellence that industry, skill, and expense, can bring it. Nor is it too much to say, that the system of farming at present followed in the county does not fall short of the best modes of farming in any part of the kingdom. The farmers have very good houses, with two public rooms ; and they have their wheeled carriages for personal and family use. Sub-letting is abolished. The small tenants or cottars live in decent cottages, built with stone and lime, or clay, with glass windows; and their fare is correspondingly better; and the tradesmen and ploughmen wear good clothes. In no county of Scotland was there ever, in so short a time, the same length of road made, as there has been within the last twenty years in the county of Sutherland, In former times the internal communication was by mere paths or tracks, and many parts of it were all but inaccessible. Now, several hundred miles of good road, unchecked by tolls, intersect the county in every direction ; and there is free and easy access to every part of it. These roads were made, partly by the parliamentary commissioners and the county, but chiefly at the expense of the noble proprietors, and under the able management of James Loch, Esq. M. P. their commissioner.”@@<hi rend="superscript">1</hi></p><p>Sutherland is eminently adapted by nature for sheepgrazing ; and the plans of converting it into extensive sheep- walks, which have been for some years carrying into execution, have greatly augmented the revenue of the proprietors, and added to the commercial wealth of the nation ; but they have doubtless been attended with much suffering to the small tenants whom it was necessary to dispossess. The people who had been removed from the interior in 1818 and 1819, when these great changes took place, are densely settled along the sea-coast ; in some instances about thirty cottagers occupying the land formerly in the possession of twelve. They have likewise been obliged to make a' violent change in their occupations and habits : instead of tending flocks, and following other rural occupations, they have been forced to encounter the hardships and dangers of the sea, and occupy themselves with the fisheries ; and many families have preferred emigration from their native country, to engaging in occupations so entirely foreign to their previous habits.</p><p>The ordinary system of husbandry adopted is the five- course shift rotation of crops ; and trenching and draining have been executed to a great extent. The rent of arable land is from 20s. to 30s. per acre. The corn-farms are generally of such an extent as yield from L.50 to L.200 of annual rent ; few exceed L.300. The average rate of grazing is L.1. 10s. per ox or cow grazed, and 2s. per sheep. The leases of farms are generally for nineteen years; but the cottagers on the coast are almost always tenants at will, which is evidently a bar to the improvement of their cots. But the greater part of the county is laid out in extensive sheep-farms, yielding about L.500 of yearly rent each. The Cheviot or white-faced breed of sheep is that which is generally kept. The Dunrobin breed of cattle, originally from Argyleshire, is excellent. Some Ayrshire cows are kept for dairy use. On some farms the breed of Galloway black-polled cattle, and highland black cattle, are chiefly reared. Goats were once a part of the stock of the farmers, but they have now nearly disappeared.</p><p>Until the recent establishments of the duke of Sutherland, there was no manufacture in this county, if we except that of kelp, of which the quantity used to be 250 tons. A cotton-mill had been erected at Spinningdale, on a branch of the Dornoch Frith, by a Glasgow company ; but the building having been burnt down in 1806, the undertaking was abandoned. A good many boats are employed in the fisheries on the west and north coast for cod, ling, haddock, and herring; and lobsters and mussels are found in considerable quantities. At Helmsdale, on the east coast, many of those small tenants who were removed by the introduction of sheep-farming, have also embarked in the fisheries with considerable success ; and large sums have been expended within these few years by the noble proprietor of the Sutherland estate in erecting the necessary buildings. The principal exports are sheep, wool, cattle, horses, salmon, and cod. Their butter and cheese are nearly all consumed at home ; and besides the usual imports of cloths, groceries, &amp;c., they require some corn, chiefly oatmeal, especially on the west and north sides of the county, where they have very little corn-land.</p><p>Dornoch, a royal borough, situated on the south-eastern extremity, on the frith of that name, is the only town, and contains little more than 500 inhabitants. Golspie, Helmsdale, and Brora, are the principal villages. With these exceptions, the inhabitants are scattered along the coast, and in some of the principal straths, passing much of their time in idleness; a healthy, robust, and simple, though not ill-informed race, who have contributed largely to the public service. For the last half century, the Sutherland family have raised among them, at the commencement of every war, a corps of a thousand men, well known by the name of the Sutherland Fencibles ; but this military spirit, founded in attachment to their chiefs, has now become much weaker than formerly.</p><p>The schools in the county are the parish schools, and those of the Society for propagating Christian Knowledge and the Gaelic School Society. According to the last parliamentary returns, there was neither printer nor bookseller in the whole county ; a circumstance indicating eitlier great poverty or little literary taste among the inhabitants. Sutherland is distinguished from every other county in the kingdom in being undisturbed by religious dissent ; there is not a single dissenting place of worship within its limits. Savings banks have been established in some of the parishes. The only prison in the county is at Dornoch. The number of prisoners during the year 1833 was twenty, of whom six were committed for smuggling, and ten for assaults.</p><p>In various districts along the coast, there are some remains of antiquity. The most interesting are two circular buildings, called Dun Domadil, or Dornadilla’s Tower, and</p><p>@@@* Statistical Account of Scotland.</p></body></text></TEI>