<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-05-22T20:48:18Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>thus proceeding by a regular chain, till we come to the conclusion. Such is the method in Euclid’s Elements, and most demonstrations of the ancient mathematicians, which proceed from definitions and axioms, to prove propositions, &amp;c. and from those propositions proved to prove others. This method we also call <hi rend="italic">composition,</hi> in opposition to <hi rend="italic">analysis</hi> or <hi rend="italic">resolution.</hi></p><p>SYRA, an island in the Grecian archipelago, classed among the Cyclades, anciently called Syros. The south-west point of the island is north-east from Serpho-Poulo about five leagues, and the summit of its high land, which is towards the east, is in longitude 24° 55' 13" east, and latitude 37° 28' 56" north. It is three leagues long from north to south, and about one league and a half in breadth. It is mountainous and destitute of wood ; but being well watered and well cultivated, produces barley, wine, figs, cotton, olives, and a small portion of wheat. There is a good harbour on the eastern side, very secure for vessels of an easy draught, and where two or three frigates might find shelter. The land has a very picturesque appearance from this harbour, near to which is the town, reaching half way down the side of a conical hill. The whole inhabitants are calculated to be about 2000, mostly adhering to the Roman Catholic church.</p><p>SYRACUSE, a celebrated city of Sicily, and once the capital of the island. According to Thucydides and Strabo, it was built by Archias, one of the Heraclidae, who came from Corinth into Sicily in the second year of the 11 th Olympiad, and derived its name from a neighbouring marsh named <hi rend="italic">Sgraco.</hi> What form of government first prevailed in the city, is not known. Many have supposed it originally to have been governed by kings : but if this was the case, the monarchical government continued only for a very short time ; since Aristotle, Diodorus Siculus, and Justin, mention it as being very early subject to a democracy. The history is obscure and unimportant till the time of Gelon, when Syracuse first began to make a conspicuous figure.</p><p>Gelon was bom in the city of Gela in Sicily, of the family of Telines, who had been created priest of the infernal gods. He signalized himself in a war carried on against the Syracusans, by Hippocratcs, tyrant of Gela, whom he defeated in a pitched battle. Having thus become very powerful among his countrymen, he soon found means to seize on the sovereignty for himself. In a short time, having put himself at the head of some Syracusan exiles, he marched towards that place, where he was received with loud acclamations, and obtained possession of the city.</p><p>In order to people the capital of his new dominions, Gelon first demolished the neighbouring city of Camarina, and transplanted the inhabitants to Syracuse. Soon afterwards, entering into a war with the Megareans, he defeated them, took and razed their cities, and in like manner transplanted the people. Syracuse thus became powerful, and full of inhabitants ; and the friendship of Gelon was courted both by Athens and Lacedæmon at the time of the Persian invasion. In the mean time the Carthaginians had entered into a treaty with the Persians ; by which it was agreed, that the former should attack those of the Greek name in Sicily and Italy, in order to divert them from assisting each other. Sicily was accordingly invaded by the Carthaginians with a vast army ; but they were utterly overthrown by Gelon, as is related under the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Carthage.</hi> After this victory, the people out of gratitude obliged him to assume the title of king, which till that time he had refused. A decree also passed by which the crown was settled on his two brothers Hiero and Thrasybulus after his death. The new king, instead of keeping his subjects in greater awe, studied to make them happy, and was the first man who became more virtuous by being raised to a throne. He was particularly famous for his honesty, truth, and sin</p><p>cerity ; is said never to have wronged the meanest of his subjects, and never to have made a promise which he did not perform.</p><p>Gelon died in the year 471 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c</hi>. after having reigned three or four years ; and was succeeded by his brother Hiero, whose character is differently drawn by different historians. He is highly celebrated in the odes of Pindar ; and it is certain that his court was the resort of men of wit and learning, to whom he behaved in the most courteous manner and with the greatest liberality.</p><p>In 459 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi> Hiero was succeeded by. Thrasybulus ; who proving a tyrant, was in ten months dethroned, and a popular government restored, which continued for the space of fifty-five years.</p><p>About this time the Syracusans entered into a war with the Siculi, which terminated in the total subjection of the latter ; after which Syracuse became so powerful, that it in a manner gave law to the whole island. The Greek cities indeed enjoyed a perfect liberty, but they all acknowledged Syracuse as their metropolis. By degrees, however, the latter began to assume such an authority over them as was totally inconsistent with liberty ; and this occasioned many wars, which involved them in much distress and danger. They began with the Leontines, whose territory they laid waste, and reduced their city to great straits. Leontini was an Athenian colony ; and this furnished the Athenians, who had already meditated the conquest of Sicily, with a pretence to attack the Syracusans with their whole force. Under colour of assisting their countrymen, therefore, they sent a fleet of 250 sail to Sicily ; but the Leontines, sensible that their pretended allies aimed at nothing less than the conquest of the whole island, concluded a peace with Syracuse ; and the disappointed Athenians vented their rage on those who had advised and conducted the expedition.</p><p>During thc continuance of the popular government, the Syracusans took part in the long war between Athens and Sparta. This war was scarcely ended, when a new and formidable invasion by the Carthaginians took place ; but the event of that expedition was as unfortunate to the Carthaginians as the former had been. In the mean time, a considerable revolution had happened in Syracuse. The city of Agrigentum had been taken by the Carthaginians ; and of the few inhabitants who escaped, some fled to Syracuse, where they accused the Syracusan commanders of having betrayed the city into the hands of the enemy. Dionysius, a man of great valour and address, but who had become very obnoxious to the populace, took this opportunity of attempting to retrieve his credit. He therefore supported the accusations brought against his countrymen by the Agrigentines, and even impeached the magistrates as having a secret intelligence with the enemy, and attempting to introduce an oligarchy. As his speech was entirely levelled against the more wealthy, it was very agreeable to the poorer citizens : the commanders were instantly degraded; and others, among whom was Dionysius, were appointed. Having once gained this point, he began to consider how he might effect the dismission of his colleagues. For this purpose, he never joined in any council of war with the other commanders, nor imparted to them his resolutions, giving out that he could not trust them, and that they had more regard for their own interest than the welfare of their country. But while he was proceeding in this manner, the more prudent part of the citizens, perceiving what he aimed at, complained of him to the senate and magistrates, and fined him as a disturber of the public peace. According to the laws, the fine was to be paid before he could speak in public, and the circumstances of Dionysius did not allow him to discharge it. In this dilemma he was assisted by Philistus the historian, a man of great wealth, who not only paid this fine for him, but encouraged liim to speak his</p></body></text></TEI>