<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-05-22T20:47:19Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>that country, if he should fail in the attempt of exciting the inhabitants to revolt.</p><p>Attended by a peasant, to whom he was known, he travelled in disguise through Sudermania, Nericia, and Wes- termania, and, after a laborious and painful journey, arrived in the mountains of Dalecarlia. Scarcely had he finished his journey, when he found himself deserted by his companion and guide, who carried off with him all the money which he had provided for his subsistence. Thus forlorn and destitute, he entered among the miners, without relinquishing his hopes of one day ascending the throne of Sweden. His only object for the present was to live concealed, and gain a maintenance, till fortune should effect something in his favour ; nor was it long before this happened. A woman in the mines perceived, under the habit of a peasant, that the collar of his shirt was embroidered. This circumstance excited curiosity ; and the graces of his person and conversation, which had something in them to attract the notice of the meanest of the vulgar, afforded room for suspicion that he was some person of quality in disguise, forced by the tyranny of the government to seek shelter in those remote regions. The story came to the ears of a neighbouring gentleman, who immediately went to the mines to offer his protection to the unfortunate stranger ; and was astonished on recognising the features of Gustavus, to whom he had been known at the university of Upsala. Touched with compassion at the deplorable situation of so distinguished a nobleman, he could scarcely refrain from tears. At night he sent for the illustrious wanderer, made him an offer of his house, and gave him the strongest assurances of his friendship and protection. He told him he would there meet with better accommodations, and as much security as in the mines ; and that, should he chance to be discovered, he would, with all his friends and vassals, take arms in his defence.</p><p>This offer Gustavus very gladly embraced, and he remained for some time at his friend’s house ; but finding it impossible to induce him to take part in his designs, he quitted him, and fled to one Peterson, a gentleman whom he had formerly known in the service. This man received Gustavus with all the appearance of kindness ; and on the very first proposal, offered to raise his vassals. He even named the nobles and peasants whom he pretended to have engaged in his service ; but in a few days he secretly went to a Danish officer, and gave him information of what had passed. The officer immediately caused the house to be surrounded with soldiers, in such a manner that it seemed impossible for Gustavus to escape. Being warned by Peterson’s wife of the treachery of her husband, he, by her direction, contrived to fly to the house of a clergyman, her friend, by whom he was received with all the respect due to his birth and merit ; and lest the domestic who conducted him should follow the treacherous example of his master, he removed him to the church, and conducted him to a small closet, of which he kept the key. Having lived for some time in this manner, Gustavus began to consult with his friend concerning the most proper method of putting their schemes in execution. The priest advised him to apply directly to the peasants themselves ; told him that it would be proper to spread a report that the Danes were to enter Dalecarlia in order to establish new taxes by force of arms ; and as the annual feast of all the neighbouring villages was to be held in a few days, he could not have a more favourable opportunity. He also promised to engage the principal persons of the diocese in his interest.</p><p>In compliance with his advice, Gustavus repaired to Mora, where the feast was to be held. He found the peasants already informed of his designs, and impatient to see him. Being prepossessed in his favour, they were soon excited to enthusiasm in his cause, and instantly resolved to throw off the Danish yoke. In this design they were more confirm</p><p>ed by their superstition ; some of their old men having observed that the wind had blown from the north while Gustavus was speaking, which among them was reckoned an infallible omen of success. Gustavus did not allow their ardour to cool, but instantly led them against the governor’s castle, which he took by assault, and put the garrison to the sword. This inconsiderable enterprise was attended with the most happy consequences. Great numbers of the peasants flocked to his standard ; some of the gentry openly espoused his cause, and others supplied him with money. Christiern was soon informed of what had passed ; but despising such an inconsiderable enemy, he sent only a slender detachment to assist his adherents in Dalecarlia. Gustavus advanced with 5000 men, and defeated a body of Dades ; but he was strenuously opposed by the archbishop of Upsala, who raised numerous forces for Christiern. The fortune of Gustavus, however, still prevailed, and the archbishop was defeated with great loss. Gustavus then laid siege to Stockholm; but his force being unequal to such an undertaking, he was forced to abandon it with loss.</p><p>This check did not prove in any considerable degree detrimental to the affaire of Gustavus: the peasants from all parts of the kingdom flocked to his camp, and he was joined by a reinforcement from Lübeck. Christiern, unable to suppress the revolt, wreaked his vengeance on the mother and sisters of Gustavus, whom he put to death. His barbarities served only to make his enemies more resolute. Gustavus having assembled the states at Wadstena, he was unanimously chosen regent, the diet taking an oath of fidelity to him, and promising to assist him to the utmost. Having thus obtained the sanction of legal authority, he pursued his advantages against the Danes. A body of troops appointed to throw succours into Stockholm was cut in pieces ; and the regent sending some forces into Finland, struck the Danes there with such terror, that the archbishop of Upsala, together with the Danish governors, fled to Denmark. Christiern then sent express orders to all his governors and officers in Finland and Sweden, to massacre the Swedish gentry without distinction. The Swedes made reprisals by massacring all the Danes that they could find, so that the country was filled with slaughter.</p><p>In the mean time Gustavus had laid siege to the towns of Calmar, Abo, and Stockholm ; but Norby found means to oblige him to retire with loss. Gustavus, in revenge, laid siege to the capital a third time, and applied to the regency of Lübeck for a squadron of ships and other succours for carrying on the siege. This request was granted on condition that Gustavus should oblige himself, in the name of the states, to pay 60,000 marks of silver as the expense of the armament ; that, until the kingdom should be in a condition to pay that sum, the Lübeck merchants trading to Sweden should be exempted from all duties on imports or exports ; that all other nations should be prohibited from trading with Sweden, and that such traffic should be deemed illicit ; that Gustavus should neither conclude a peace, nor even agree to a truce, with Denmark, without the concurrence of the regency of Lübeck ; and that if the republic should be attacked by Christiern, he should enter Denmark at the head of 20,000 men. On these hard terms Gustavus obtained assistance from the regency of Lübeck ; nor did his dear-bought allies prove very faithful. They did not indeed transfer their services to his enemy ; but in a sea- fight, where the Danes were entirely in their power, they suffered them to escape, when their whole force might have been entirely destroyed. This treachery had nearly ruined the affairs of Gustavus ; for Norby was now making preparations effectually to relieve Stockholm, and would probably have succeeded in the attempt, if at this critical period news had not arrived that the Danes had revolted, and driven Christiern from the throne ; and that the king had retired into Germany, in hopes of being restored by the arms of</p></body></text></TEI>