<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-05-22T20:47:32Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>fortune of Charles. It was not in Poland alone that the Swedish affairs began to suffer in consequence of the defeat at Pultava. The Danes invaded the province of Schonen with an army of 13,000 foot and 2500 horse. Only 13,000 Swedish forces remained to defend all the territories possessed by Charles in Germany, and of these only a small part was allotted for the defence of Schonen. The regency of Sweden, however, exerted themselves to the utmost to repel this ungenerous invasion ; and having collected an army of 12,000 militia and 8000 regulars, despatched them under General Steenboek into Schonen. Some Saxon troops were incorporated in this army ; but among these a prodigious desertion took place, which the general found it impossible to prevent ; and thus the Danes gained several advantages, and at last took Christianstadt. Their insolence on this success was so great that the Swedes demanded to be instantly led against them. Here the good fortune of Sweden seemed once more to revive. The Danes were driven from a very strong situation, with the loss of 8000 killed and taken prisoners, besides a vast number wounded. The king received the intelligence of this victory with the greatest exultation, and could not help exclaiming, “ My brave Swedes, should it please God that I once more join you, we shall conquer them all.”</p><p>In the mean time, Charles, by means of his agents the count Poniatoffski and Neugebar, used his utmost efforts to procure a rupture between the Porte and Russia. For a long interval the money bestowed by Peter on the vizirs and janisaries prevailed ; but at last the grand sig- nior, influenced by his mother, who was strongly in the interest of Charles, and had been used to call him <hi rend="italic">her lion,</hi> determined to support his quarrel with Peter. He therefore gave orders to the vizir to fall on the Russians with an army of 200,000 men. The vizir promised obedience, but at the same time professed his ignorance in the art of war, and dislike to the present expedition. The khan of Crim Tartary, who had been gained over by the reputation and presents of the king of Sweden, had orders to take the field with 40,000 of his men, and had the liberty of assembling his army at Bender, that Charles might sec that the war was undertaken on his account. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Russia.</hi></p><p>The treaty of the Pruth was most violently opposed by Poniatoffski and the khan of Tartary. The former had made the king acquainted with the situation of both armies ; on which he instantly set out from Bender, filled with the hopes of fighting the Russians, and taking ample vengeance. Having ridden fifty leagues post, he arrived at the camp just as the czar was drawing off his half-famished troops. He alighted at Poniatoffski’s tent ; and being informed of particulars, instantly flew in a rage to the vizir, whom loaded with reproaches, and accused of treachery. Recollecting himself, however, he proposed a method by which the fault might be remedied ; but finding his proposal rejected, he posted back to Bender, after having by the grossest insults showed his contempt of the vizir.</p><p>The violent behaviour of Charles did not promote his interest. The vizir perceived that his stay in Turkey might prove fatal to himself, and he therefore determined to remove him as soon as possible. Succeeding vizirs adopted the same plan ; and at last the grand signior himself wrote a letter to Charles, in which he desired him to depart by next winter, promising to supply him with a sufficient guard, with money, and every thing else necessary for his journey. Charles gave an evasive answer, and determined to procrastinate his journey, as well to gratify his own stubborn temper, as because he discovered a correspondence between Augustus and the khan of Tartary, the object of which, he had reason to believe, was to betray him to the Saxons. When he was again pressed to fix the day of his departure, he replied, that he could not think of going before his debts were paid. Being asked how much was necessary for this purpose, he replied, a thousand purses. A purse, it is to be remarked, consists of thirty sequins. Twelve hundred purses were instantly sent to the seraskier at Bender, with orders to deliver them to the king of Sweden, but not before he should have begun his journey. By fair promises, Charles persuaded him to part with the money ; after which, instead of setting out, he squandered away his treasure in presents and gratifications, and then demanded a thousand purses more before he would set out. The seraskier was astonished at this behaviour. He shed tears ; and turning to the king told him that his head would be the forfeit of liaving obliged him with the money. The grand signior, on being acquainted with the shameful behaviour of Charles, flew into a rage, and called an extraordinary divan, where he himself spoke ; a practice very unusual for the Turkish monarchs. It was unanimously agreed that such a troublesome guest ought to be removed by force, should other means fail. Positive orders were therefore sent to Charles to depart ; and, in case of his refusal, instructions were given for attacking him in his quarters. Nothing could equal his obstinacy on this occasion : in spite of the menaces of his enemies, in spite of the entreaties of his friends, he persisted in his resolution ; and at last determined to resist, with 300 Swedes, being the entire number of his attendants, an army of 20,000 janisaries well armed and furnished with cannon. At length he was attacked in good earnest ; though it must be owned, that even in this extremity, the Turks showed their regard to him, and were tender of his safety. Most of the Swedes surrendered at once, perhaps as thinking it the only method of saving the king’s life. This conduct, however, had an opposite effect. Charles became the more obstinate, the more desperate his affairs seemed to be. With only forty menial servants, and the generals Hord and Dardorff, he determined to defend himself to the last extremity. Seeing his soldiers lay down their arms, he told the generals, “ We must now defend the house. Come,” added he with a smile, “ let us fight <hi rend="italic">pro aris et focis.”</hi> The house had been already forced by the Tartars, all but a hall which was near the door, and where his domestics had assembled. Charles forced his way through the janisaries, attended by the generals Hord and Dardorff, joined his people, and then barricaded the door. The moment he entered, the enemy who were in the house threw down their booty, and endeavoured to escape at the windows. Charles pursued them from room to room with much bloodshed, and cleared the house in a few minutes. He then fired furiously from the windows, killed two hundred of the Turks in a quarter of an hour, so that the pacha who commanded them was at length forced to set the house on fire. This was effected by discharging arrows with lighted matches into the roof; but Charles, instead of quitting his post, gave orders for extinguishing the fire, and he himself assisted with great diligence. All efforts were however vain : the roof fell in, and Charles, with his few faithful companions, was ready to be buried in the ruins. In this extremity one called out that there was a necessity for surrendering. “ What a strange fellow !” cries the king, “ who would rather be a prisoner with the Turks than mix his ashes with those of his sovereign.” Another had the presence of mind to cry out, that the chancery was but fifty paces off, had a stone roof, and was proof against fire. Pleased with the thoughts of again coming to blows, the king exclaimed, “ A true Swede ! Let us take all the powder and ball we can carry.” He then put himself at the head of his troops, and sallied out with such impetuosity, that the Turks retreated fifty paces ; but having fallen in the midst of his fury, they rushed upon him, and carried him by the legs and arms to the pacha’s tent. This extraordinary adventure, which savours not a little of insanity, happened on the l2th of February 1713. He was now kept prisoner with all his retinue ; and in this situation</p></body></text></TEI>