<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-05-22T20:47:31Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>second line, stooping over the first, who kneeled, fired over their heads ; while the third rank, who stood upon their feet, kept up an incessant fire, by which the Swedish horse were exceedingly galled and put in disorder. Charles lost the opportunity of cutting off the whole Saxon army, by omitting to order his men to dismount. This was almost the first time that infantry had been regularly opposed to cavalry, ■ and the superiority of the former was evident. After the engagement had continued about three hours, the Saxons retreated in good order ; which no enemy had ever done before in any engagement with Charles. The Swedes pursued their enemies towards the Oder, and forced them to retreat through thick woods, almost impervious even to infantry. The Swedish horse, however, pushed their way, and at last enclosed Schullemberg between a wood and the river, where Charles had no doubt of obliging him to surrender at discretion, or die sword in hand, as having neither boats nor bridges ; but the genius of Schullemberg supplied every defect. In the night he ordered planks and floats of trees to be fastened together, on which he carried over his troops, while the Swedes were employed in dislodging 300 men, whom he had placed in a wind-mill for the purpose of defending his flank, and diverting the attention of the enemy. Charles spoke of this retreat with admiration, and said he had been conquered by Schullemberg.</p><p>No material advantage however resulted to Augustus, who was again obliged to leave Poland, and fortify the capital of his hereditary dominions, which he expected every moment to sec invested. In the mean time, the Russians having recovered their spirits, attacked the Swedes in Livonia with the utmost fury. Narva, Dorpat, and several other towns, were taken, and the inhabitants and garrison treated with great barbarity. An army of 100,000 Russians soon afterwards entered Poland. Sixty thousand Cossacks under Mazeppa entered the country at the same time, and committed every outrage with the fury of barbarians. Schullemberg, perhaps more formidable than either, advanced with 14,000 Saxons and 7000 Russians, disciplined in Germany, and reputed excellent soldiers. Could numbers have determined the event of war, the Swedes must certainly have been at this time overpowered ; but Charles seemed to triumph over his enemies with more ease the more numerous they were. The Russians were so speedily defeated, that they were all dispersed before one party had notice of the misfortunes of another. The defeating an army of 40,000 men scarcely obstructed the march of the Swedes, while their astonished enemies looked on these actions as the effects of witchcraft, and imagined that the king of Sweden had dealings with infernal spirits. With these apprehensions they fled beyond the Dnieper, leaving the unhappy Augustus to his fate. Schullemberg, with all his skill and experience, was not more successful. The Swedish general Renschild engaged and defeated him in half an hour, though the Swedes were vastly inferior in number, and their enemies posted in a most advantageous situation. Nothing could be more complete than the victory. This extraordinary victory, indeed, is said to have been owing to a panic which seized the troops of Schullemberg; but it was regarded witli admiration, and thought to make the renown of Renschild equal to that of his sovereign. Charles himself was jealous, and could not help exclaiming, “ Surely Renschild will not compare himself with me !”</p><p>Soon after this victory, which was gained on the 12th of February 1706, Charles entered Saxony at the head of 24,000 men. The diet at Ratisbon declared him an enemy to the empire if he crossed the Oder. But to this declaration no regard was paid : Charles pursued his march, while Augustus was reduced to the condition of a vagrant in Poland, where he possessed not a single town except Cracow. Into this city he threw himself with a few Saxon, Polish, and Russian regiments, and began to erect some</p><p>fortifications for his defence ; but the approach of the Swedish general Meyerfeldt, and the news of the invasion of Saxony, disconcerted all his measures, and plunged him into despair. The Russians indeed were his faithful allies, but he dreaded them almost as much as the Swedes ; so that he was reduced to the necessity of writing a letter to Charles with his own hand, begging for peace on whatever terms he thought proper to grant. As he was then at the mercy of the Russians, this transaction was concealed with the greatest care. His emissaries were introduced to the Swedish court in the night-time, and being presented to Charles, received the following answer : that King Augustus should for ever renounce the crown of Poland, acknowledge Stanislas, and promise never to re-ascend the throne, should an opportunity offer ; that he should release the princes Sobieski, and all the Swedish prisoners made in the course of the war ; surrender Patkul, at that time resident at his court as ambassador for the czar of Russia, and stop proceedings against all who had passed from his into the Swedish service. These articles Charles wrote with his own hand, and delivered to Count Piper, ordering him to finish them with the Saxon ambassadors.</p><p>After his defeat at Pultava by the Russians, Charles fled in a mean calash, attended by a little troop inviolably attached to his person, some on foot, and some on horseback. They were obliged to cross a sandy desert, where neither herb nor tree was to be seen, and where the burning heat and want of water were more intolerable than the extremities of cold which they had formerly endured. The whole had almost perished for want of water, when a spring was fortunately discovered. They reached Otchakoff, a town in the Turkish dominions, the pacha of which supplied thc king with every necessary. It was, however, some time before boats could be got ready for transporting the whole of the king’s attendants ; by which accident 500 Swedes and Cossacks fell into the hands of the enemy. This loss affected him more than all his other misfortunes. He shed tears at seeing, across the river Bog, the greater part of his few remaining friends carried into captivity, without having it in his power to assist them. Thc pacha waited on him to apologise for the delay, and was as severely reprimanded by Charles as if he had been his own subject.</p><p>The king remained but a few days at Otchakoff, when the seraskier of Bender sent an aga to compliment him on his arrival in the Turkish dominions, and to invite him to that city. Here he was treated with hospitality. The Turks practised to its full extent their generous maxim of regarding as sacred the persons of unfortunate princes who had taken shelter in their dominions; and they perhaps regarded him, notwithstanding his misfortunes, as an ally that might be useful to themselves against the Russians. Every one indeed regarded him in his distress. The French king offered him a safe passage from the Levant to Marseilles, from whence he might easily return to his own dominions. But Charles was too obstinate to receive advice. Puffed up with the notion of imitating Alexander the Great, he disdained to return except at the head of a numerous army ; and he yet expected, by means of the Turks, to dethrone his adversary the czar. Negociations for this purpose were carried on in the Turkish divan, and it was proposed to escort Charles with a numerous army to the frontiers of Poland ; but the revolution which there took place put an end to all such projects. Augustus thought himself no longer bound to observe the treaty which he had made, than when Charles was at hand to compel him. After the battle of Pultava, he entered Poland, and took every measure, in concert with the czar, for the recovery of his kingdom. Stanislas was not able to encounter such enemies, but was obliged to leave his dominions and fly to Bender, in the disguise of a Swedish officer, in order to share the</p></body></text></TEI>