<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r03-0576-08" facs="gri_33125011196389_0582.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>RUTHERGLEN</label>
or by contraction Ruglen, the head borough of the netherward of Lanarkſhire in Scotland, is ſituated in N. Lat. 55 <hi rend="sup">0</hi> yι', and W. Long. 4 <hi rend="sup">c</hi> 13' ; about two miles ſouth-eaſt of Glaſgow, and nine weſt of Hamilton. Few towns in Scotland can lay greater claim to antiquity than Rutherglen. Maitland, in his Hiſtory of the Antiquities of Scotland, vol. i. p. 92. tells us, that it was founded by a king Reuther, from whom it derived its name ; and a tradition of the ſame import prevails among the inhabitants. But without laying any ſtreſs on the authority of tradition, which is often falſe and always doubtful, we find, from ſeveral original charters ſtill preſerved, that it was erected into a royal borough by king David I. about the year 1126.</p><p>The territory under the juriſdiction of the borough was extenſive, and the inhabitants enjoyed many diſtin-guiſhed privileges, which were however gradually wreſted from them, by political influence, in favour of Glaſgow, which in latter times roſe into conſequence by trade and manufactures. The ancient dimenſions oſ the place are now unknown ; but in the fields and gardens towards the eaſt the foundations of houſes are occaſion-ally diſeovered. It is now of a very reduced ſize, conſiſting but of one principal ſtreet and a few lanes, and containing about 1 63 ι inhabitants.</p><p>About 150 yar&lt;⅛ to the ſouth of.the main ſtreet</p>
<pb xml:id="eb03-16-r03-0577" facs="gri_33125011196389_0583.tif"/>
<p>is a kind of lane, known by the name of <hi rend="italic">Dlns-dykes.</hi> A circumſtance which beſel the unfortunate queen Mary, immediately after her forces were routed at the battle of Langſide, has ever ſince continued to cha-racteriſe this place with an indelible mark of opprobrium. Her majeſty, during the battle, ſtood on a riſing ground about a mile ſrom Rutherglen. She no ſooner ſaw her army defeated than ſhe took her precipitate flight to the ſouth. Dms-dykes unfortunately lay in her way. Two ruſtics, who were at that inſtant cutting graſs hard by, ſeeing her majeſty fleeing in hafte, rudely attempted to intercept her, and threatened to cut her in pieces with their ſcythes if ſhe preſumed to proceed a ſtep further. Neither beauty, nor even royalty itſelf, can at all times ſecure the unfortunate when they have to do With the unfeeling or the revengeful. Relief however was at hand ; and her majeſty proceeded in her flight.</p><p>Adjoining to a lane called the <hi rend="italic">Back-row</hi> ſtood the caſtle of Rutherglen, originally built at a period coeval, it is reported, with the foundation of the town. This ancient ſortreſs underwent ſeveral lieges during the unhappy wars in the days of king Robert Bruce, and it remained a place of ſtrength until the battle of Langſide ; ſoon after which it was deſtroyed by order of the regent, to revenge himſelf on the Hamilton family, in whole cuſtody it then was. The foundations of the buildings are now eraſed, and the ſite converted into dwelling-houſes and gardens.</p><p>The kirk of Rutherglen, an ancient building of. the Saxon· Gothic ſtyle, was rendered famous by two tranſ-nctions, in which the fate of Sir William Wallace and his country' was deeply concerned. In it a truce was concluded between Scotland and England in the year 1397 (Henry’s Life of Wallace, Book VI. verſe 862.), and in it Sir John Monteath bargained with the Engliſh to betray Wallace his friend and companion (Life of Wallace, Book XI. verſe 796)· This ancient building, having become incommodious, was, in 1794, pulled down, and one oſ a modern ſtyle was erected in its place. Buried in the area were found vaſt quantities oſ human bones, and ſome relics of antiquity.</p><p>No borough probably in Britain poffeſſes a political conſtitution or ſett more free and unembarraffed than Rutherglen. It was anciently under the. influence of a ſelf-elected magiſtracy, many oſ whom lived at a diſtance from the borough, and who continued long in office without interruption. Negligence on the one hand, and an undue exertion of power on the other, at length excited the burgeſſes, about the middle of the laſt century, to apply an effectual remedy to this evil. The community who, at that period, poſſeſſed the power of reforming the abuſes that had long prevailed in the management of the borough, were much aſſiſted in their exertions by <hi rend="sup">,</hi> a Mr David Spens town-clerk, a gentleman unbiaſſedby falſe politics, and who was animated with a high degree of true patriotiſm. Great oppoſition was at ſirſt made to the reform ; but the plan adopted by the burgeſſes was wifely laid, and was proſecuted with unremitting aſſiduity. They were proof againſt the influence and bribery of a party that ſtruggled to continue the old practice ; and having at length ſur-mounted every difficulty, they formed a new conſtitution or ſett for the borough, which, in 167 1, was approved of by <hi rend="sup">r</hi> all the inhabitants of the town, and afterwards inſerted in the records of the general convention of the royal boroughs of Scotland.</p><p>Rutherglen, in conjunction with Glaſgow, Renfrew, and Dumbarton, fonds a member to the Britiſh parliament. The fairs of this town are generally well attended, and have long been famous for a great ſliow of horſes, of the Lanarkſhire breed, which are eſteemed the beſt draught-horſes in Britain. The inhabitants of this borough ſtill retain fome cuſtoms of a very remote antiquity. One of theſe is the making of <hi rend="italic">Rutherglen four cakes.</hi> The operation is attended with ſome peculiar rites, which lead us to conclude that the practice is of Pagan origin. An account of theſe rites is given in Ure’s Hiſtory of Rutherglen and Kilbride, p. 94. ; from whence we have taken the above account of this place, and which we do not heſitate to recommend to the attention of ſuch of our readers as are fond of natural and local hiſtory, being perſuaded that they will find it to be both an uſeful and entertaining performance.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>