<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r03-0551-01" facs="gri_33125011196389_0557.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>RUM</label>
a ſpecies of brandy or vinous ſpirits, diſtilled from ſugar-canes.</p><p>Rum, according to Dr Shaw, differs from ſimple fugar-ſpirit, in that it contains more of the natural flavour or eſſential oil of the ſugar-cane ; a great deal of raw juice and parts of the cane itſelf being often fermented in the liquor or ſolution of which the rum is prepared. The unctuous or oily flavour of rum is often ſuppoſed to proceed from the large quantity of fat uſed in boiling the ſugar ; which fat, indeed, if coarſe, will uſually give a ſtinking flavour to the ſpirit in our diſtillations of the ſugar liquor or waft, from our refining ſugar-houſes ;, but this is nothing of kin to the flavour of the rum, which is really the effect of the natural flavour of the cane.</p><p>The method of making rum is this : When a ſuſſicient ſtock of the materials are got together, they add water to them, and ferment them in the common method, though the fermentation is always carried on very ſlewly at firſt ; becauſe at the beginning of the ſeaſon for making rum in the iſlands, they want yeaſt or fome other ferment to make it work : but by degrees, after this, they procure a ſuſſicient quantity of the ferment, which riſes up as a head to the liquor in the operation ; and thus they are able afterwards to ferment and make their rum with a great deal of expedition, and in large quantities.</p><p>When the waſh is fully fermented, or to a due degree of acidity, the diſtillation is carried on in the. common way, and the ſpirit is made up proof : though ſometimes it is reduced to a much greater ſtrength, nearly approaching to that of alcohol or ſpirit of wine ; and it is then called <hi rend="italic">double-diβilled rum.</hi> It might be eaſy to rectify the ſpirit, and bring it to much greater purity than we uſually find it to be of : for it brings over in the diſtillation a very large quantity of the oil ; and this is often ſo diſagreeable, that the rum muſt be ſuf-Iered to lie by a long time to mellow before it can be uſed ; whereas, if well rectified, it would grow mellow much ſooner, and would have a much leſs potent flavour.</p><p>The beſt ſtate to keep rum in, both ſor exportation and other uſes, is doubtleſs. that of alcohol or rectified ſpirit. In this manner it would be tranſported in one half the bulk it uſually is, and might be let down to the common proof-ſtrengtſh with water when neceſſary : for the common uſe of making punch, it would likewiſe ſerve much better' in the ſtate of alcohol ; as. the taſte would be cleaner, and the ſtrength might always be regulated to a much greater exactneſs than in the ordinary way.</p><p>The only uſe to which, it would not ſo well ſerve in this ſtate, would be the common practice of adulteration among our diſtillers ; for when they want to mix a large portion of cheaper ſpirit with the rum, their bufineſs is to have it of the proof-ſtrength, and as full of the flavouring oil as they can, that it may drown the flavour of the ſpirits they mix with it, and extend its o,wn. If the bufineſs of rectifying rum was more nicely managed, it ſeems a very practicable ſcheme to throw out ſo much of the oil, as to have it in the fine light ſtate of a clear ſpirit, but lightly impregnated with it : in this caſe it would very nearly reſemble arac, as is</p><p>proved by the mixing a very ſmall quantity oſ it with a taſteleſs ſpirit, in which caſe the whole bears a very near reſemblance to arac in flavour.</p><p>Rum is uſually very much adulterated in Britain ; ſome are ſo bare-faced as to do it with malt-ſpirit ; but when it is done with molaffes ſpirit, the taſtes of both are ſo nearly allied, that it is not eaſily diſcovered. The beſt method of judging of it is by ſetting fire to a little of it ; and, when it has burnt away all the inflammable part, examining the phlegm both by the taſte and ſmell.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Rum is a conſiderable iſland, one of the Hebrides,·' or rather one continued rock, of nearly 30 miles in circumference. It is the property of Mr Maclean of Coll; contains 300 inhabitants ; grazes cattle and ſheep ; pays 200 1. rent annually : but has neither kelp, free-ſtone, nor lime.</hi></p>
</div></body></text></TEI>