<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r03-0544-04" facs="gri_33125011196389_0550.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>RUDDER</label>
in navigation, a piece of timber turning on hinges in the ſtern of the ſhip, and which, oppoſing ſometimes one ſide in the water and ſometimes another, turns or directs the veſſel this way or that. See Helm.</p><p>In the ſeventh volume of the Tranſactions of the Society inſtituted at London for the Encouragement of Arts, Manufactures, and Commerce, there is explained a method of ſupplying the loſs of a ſhip’s rudder at ſea. The invention, which is Captain Pakenham’s of the roy <hi rend="sup">r</hi> al navy, has been approved by Admiral Cornwallis, the commiſſioners of the admiralty, by the ſociety in whoſe tranſactions the account of it was firſt publiſhed, and who preſented to Captain Pakenham their gold medal, by the Trinity-houſe, by the managing owners of Eaſt India ſhipping, by the duke of Sudermania the preſent regent of Sweden, and by the ſociety for the improvement of naval architecture. The ſubſtitute here recommended for a loſt rudder, ſays the inventor, is formed of thoſe materials without which no ſhip goes to ſea, and its conſtruction is ſimple and ſpeedy. Captain Pakenham, however, did not give a particular account of his invention to the ſociety whom he addreſſed, and to whom he ſent a model of his invention, till ſuch time as he had an opportunity of reducing the theory he had conceived to practice. On the 7th of July 1788, he made this trial with the Merlin of Newfoundland ; and he declares that, during the different, manœuvres of tacking and wearing, he could not diſcover the leaſt variation between the operation of the machine and that of the ſhip’s rudder : ſhe was ſteered with the ſame eaſe by one man, and anſwered the helm in every ſituation fully as quick. Admiral Cornwallis certifies the ſame with reſpect to the Crown of 64 guns, which loſt her rudder on the Kentiſh Knock, when with the ſubſtitute ſhe was ſteered to Portſmouth with the utmoſt eaſe in a heavy gale, and, as the admiral aſ-ſerts, it would have taken her to the Eaſt Indies.</p><p>The materials and conſtruction are thus deſcribed in the Tranſactions. “ N <hi rend="smallcaps"><hi rend="sup"> j</hi></hi> .l. a top-maſt inverted ; the fid-hole to ſiiip the tiller in, and ſecured with hoops from the anchor {locks ; the heel forming the head of the rudder. N <hi rend="sup">o</hi> 2. The inner half of a jibb-boom. N <hi rend="sup">o</hi> 3. The outer half of a jibb-boom. N <hi rend="sup">j</hi> 4. A fiſh: the whole of theſe materials well-bolted together :—in a merchantman her ruff-tree. N <hi rend="sup">0</hi> 5. A cap, with the ſquare part cut out to fit the ſtern-poſt, and acting as a lower gudgeon, ſecured to the ſtern-poſt with hawſers, leading from the bolts of the cap, under the ſhip’s bottom, into the hawſe-holes, and hove well tort. N <hi rend="sup">j</hi> 6. A plank, or, if none on board the ſhips, gangboards. N <hi rend="sup">u</hi> 7. An-chor-ſtocks, made to fit the topmaſt as partners, ſecured to the deck, and ſupplying the place of the upper gudgeon, and in a merchant-ſhip the clamps of her wind-laſs. N <hi rend="sup">o</hi> 8. A ſtern-poſt. N <hi rend="sup">o</hi> 9. Hoops from the anchor ſtocks. N <hi rend="sup">o</hi> 10. Pigs of ballaſt, to fink the lower part. The head of the rudder to paſs through as many decks as you wiſh.”</p><p>On this the Captain makes the following remarks : “ It might probably be ſuppoſed, that a difficulty would occur in bringing the jaws of the cap to embrace the ſtern-poſt ; but this will at once be obviated, when it is remembered that the top-chains, or hawſers, leading from each end of the jaws, under the ſhip’s bottom, are in fact a continuance of the jaws themſelves. Nor can it be apprehended that the cap, when fixed, may be impelled from its ſtation, either by the efforts of the ſea, or the courſe of the ſhip through the water, tho* even the hawſers, which confine it in the firſt inſtance, ſhould be relaxed:—the experiment proves, that the partners muſt be firſt torn away, or the main-piece broken off.</p><p>“ Since the improved ſtate of navigation, notwithſtanding· remedies have been found in general for the moſt diſaſtrous accidents at ſea, experience has evinced that nothing complete, had been hitherto invented to ſupply the loſs of a rudder. The firſt expedient within my knowledge were cables veered altern, with tackles leading from them to the ſhip’s quarters. This practice was ſuperſeded by the invention of the machine uſually called <hi rend="italic">the Ipſwich machine</hi> ; but the conſtruction of it is complex and unwieldy, and veffels are ſeldom found in poſſeſſion of the materials which form it. Commodore Byron, in the Journal of his Voyage round the World, ſays, that the Tamer, with every aſſiſtance from his own ſhip, was five days in conſtructing it, Beſides, like the</p>
<pb xml:id="eb03-16-r03-0545" facs="gri_33125011196389_0551.tif"/>
<p>beforr-mciittoned ſcheme, it can only operate to ſteer a ſhip large (and that but very wildly), and of courſe, under the circumſtance of a lee-ſhore, defeat the moſt ſkilful exertions of a ſeaman. Several other expedients have been adopted, which I ſhall not mention here, as the ſame defects equally appear in all.</p><p>“ Thus it was apparent, that ample room was left for the diſcovery of ſome more certain reſource than any of the former ; and the ſcheme which has ſuggeſted itſelf to me, will, I truſt, be found fully to anſwer the purpoſe intended. The materials are ſuch as ſcarcely any ſhip can venture to ſea without ; and the conſtruction •ſo ſpeedy, eaſy, and ſimple, that the capacity of the meaneſt ſailor will at once conceive it. I need not, from mathematical principles, ſhow the certainty of its effect, as it is formed and managed in the ſame manner ns a ſhip’s common rudder : and as the common rudder is certainly of all inventions the beſt calculated for guiding a vcſſel through the water, it wall of courſe follow, that whatever ſubſtitute the neareſt reſembles that, muſt be beſt adapted to ſupplyits loſs.”</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>