<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r03-0502-03" facs="gri_33125011196389_0508.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>ROSTOCK</label>
a town of Germany, in the circle of Upper Saxony, and duchy of Mecklenburg, with an univerfity and a very good harbour. It is the beſt town in this country; and has good fortifications, with an arſenal. The duke has a ſtrong caſtle, which may be looked upon as a citadel It is divided into three parts, the Old, the New’, and the Middle Towns. It was formerly one of the Hanſeatic towns, and is ſtill Imperial, under the protection of the duke of Mecklenburg. It is ſeated on a lake where the river Varne falls into it, and carries large boats. The government is in the hands of 24 aldermen, elected out of the nobility, univerfity, and principal merchants ; four of whom are burgomaſters, two chamberlains, twβ ſtewards for the river, and two judges of civil and criminal matters. Theſe 24 are called the Upper Houſe, and have in a manner the whole executive power lodged in them, with the power of coining money, and elect⅛g officers. There is alſo a common council of 100 inferior citizens, who are ſummoned to give their advice upon extraordinary emergencies relating to the whole community. The principal things worth ſeeing are the fortifications, the prince’s palace, the ſtadthouie, the arſenal, and the public library. The town is famous for good beer, which they export in great quantities. Some years ago they had no leſs than 250 privileged brcwers, who, it is ſaid, brewed ſo many thouſand tuns a year, befides what particular perſons brew for their own uſe. E. Long, j 2. 55. N. Lat. 54. 8.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>