<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r03-0578-01" facs="gri_33125011196389_0584.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>RUYTER</label>
(Michael Adrian), a diſtinguiſhed naval officer, was born at Fleſſingue, a town oſ Zealand, in 1607. He entered on a ſea-faring life when he was only 11 years old, and w <hi rend="sup">,</hi> as ſirſt a cabin-boy. While he advanced ſucceſſively to ſhe rank of mate, maſter, and captain, he acquitted himſelf wfith ability and honour in all theſe employments. He repulfed the Iriſh, who attempted to take Dublin out of the hands of' the Eng-liſh. He made eight voyages to the Weſt Indies and ten to Brazil. He was then promoted to the rank of rear-admiral, and ſent to aſſiſt the Portugueſe againſt the Spaniards. When the enemy came in fight, he advanced boldly to meet them, and gave ſuch unqueſtionable proofs of valour as drew from ſhe Portugueſe monarch the warmeſt applauſe. His gallantry was ſtill more conſpicuous before Salee, a towm of Barbary. Wiſh one ſingle veffel he ſailed through the roads of that place in defiance of five Algerine Corſairs who came to attack him.</p><p>In 1Ç53 a ſquadron qf ſeventy veſſels was diſpatched againſt the Engliſh under the command of Van Tromp. Ruyter, who accompanied the admiral in this expedition, ſeconded him with great ſkill and bravery in the three battles which the Engliſh ſo glorioufly won. He was afterwards ſtationed in the Mediterranean, where</p><p>he captured* ſeveral Turkiſh veſſels. In 1659 lie received a commiſſion to join the king of Denmark in his war with the Swedes; and he not only maintained his former reputation, but even raiſed it higher. As the reward of his ſervices, the king of Denmark ennobled him and gave him a penſion. In 1661 he run aſhore a veffel belonging to Tunis, releaſed 40 Chriſtian flaves, made a treaty with the Tιιnilians, and reduced the Algerine corſairs to ſubmiſſion. FI is country, as a teiti-mony of her gratitude for ſuch illuſtrious ſervices, raiſed him to ſhe rank of vice-admiral and commander in chief. To the latter dignity, the higheſt that could be conferred upon him, he was well intitled by the ſignal victory which he obtained over the combined fleets of France and Spain. This battle was fought in 1672 about the. time oſ the conqueſt of Holland. The fight w <hi rend="sup">r</hi> as maintained between the Engliſh and Dutch with the ob∙-ſtinate bravery of nations which were accuſtomed to diſpute the empire of the main. Ruyter having thus made himſelf maſter of the ſea, conducted a fleet of Indiamen ſafely into the Texel 4 thus defending and enriching his country, while it was become the prey of hoſtile invaders. The next year he had three engagements wiſh the fleets of France and England, in which,, if poſſible, his bravery was ſtill more diſtinguiſhed than, ever. D’Eſtrees the French vice-admiral wrote to Colbert in theſe words : “ I would purchaſe with my life the glory of De Ruyter.” But he did not long enjoy the triumphs which he had ſo honourably won. Inara engagement with the French fleet off the coaſt of Sicily, he loſt the day, and received a mortal wound, which put an end to hi? life in a few days. His corpſe was carried to Amſterdam, and a magnificent monument was there erected by ſhe command of the ſtates-general. The Spaniſh council beſtowed on him the title of duke, and tranſmitted a patent inveſting him with that dignity ; but he died before it arrived.</p><p>When ſome perſon was congratulating Louis XIV, upon De Ruyter’s death, telling him he had now got rid of one dangerous enemy ; he replied, “ Every one muſt be lorry at the death of ſo great a man.”</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>