<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-19T20:24:00Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>by the French, however, quickly found their way to this country, and being applied with energy, soon produced a re-action in favour of Scotch manufacturers, and caused the French to suffer in their turn, from having made too large quantities in the hopes of retaining the London trade. British figured shawls are now manufactured equal, in point of elegance, with any produced in France, and superior to those of every other country in lowness of price. They are manufactured from the wool of the Thibet-goat, which is as soft as, and more perfect in figure than, the best Cashmere, and probably less than a tenth part of the cost. The material, however, used for the flowering, being finer, and the colours being more durable in the manufactures of Cashmere, they still retain a superiority over those of Europe.</p><p>Edinburgh, from the commencement of this manufacture, has taken the lead in most of the improvements connected with it, always producing the best goods of the kind ; but from the circumstance of labour of various kinds being lower in Paisley and Glasgow, the manufacture has mostly been transferred to these places. At one time there were about a thousand hands employed in Edinburgh in this manufacture ; now it scarcely gives work to one hundred.</p><p>Shawls in imitation of Cashmere are made of a very great variety of qualities. While some of those made of the finest materials and richest patterns still sell for L.8 or L.10 each, there are a great many made of a mixture of silk and cotton, silk and wool, cotton and wool, and some are made wholly of cotton, so that figured shawls can be purchased at five shillings each. It is computed that, at the present time, this description of shawls gives employment to at least 20,000 hands. A great many are exported to America, as well as to other parts of the world. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Weaving. (b. y.)</hi></p><p>SHAWPOOR,a town of Hindustan, province of Gund- waneh, situated on the Rhair, a considerable river, which runs by the south side of the town, over a bed of rock, which impedes its navigation. It is a straggling town, with a small fort built of rubble-stone and mud. Long. 83. 23. E. Lat. 23. 34. N.</p><p>SHEATHING, in the nautical language, is the casing of that part of a ship which is to be under water, with fir- board an inch thick ; first laying hair and tar mixed together under the boards, and then nailing them on, in order to prevent worms from eating the ship’s bottom. Ships of war are now generally sheathed with copper ; but copper sheathing is liable to be corroded by the action of salt water, and something is still wanting to effect this purpose. It is very probable that tar might answer very well.</p><p>SHEATS, in a ship, are ropes bent to the clews of the sails, serving in the lower sails to haul aft the clews of the sail ; but in topsails they serve to haul home the clew of the sail close to the yard-arm.</p><p>SHEAVE, in <hi rend="italic">Mechanics,</hi> a solid cylindrical wheel, fixed in a channel, and moveable about an axis, being used to raise or increase the mechanical powers applied to remove any body.</p><p>SHEBBEARE, <hi rend="smallcaps">John</hi>, a political writer, was born at Bideford, in Devonshire, in the year 1709. He received the rudiments of his education at the free grammar-school of Exeter. It has often been observed that the future life of a man may be gathered from his puerile character ; and accordingly Shebbeare, while a boy at school, gave the strongest indications of his future eminence in misanthropy and learning, by the extraordinary tenaciousness of his memory and the readiness of his wit, as well as the malignity of his disposition. He was universally regarded as a young man of surprising genius, while at the same time he was despised for his malicious temper.</p><p>About the age of sixteen, Shebbeare was bound apprentice to an eminent surgeon in his native town, under whom he acquired a considerable share of medical knowledge. His talent for lampoon appeared at this early period, and he</p><p>could not forbear from exercising it on his master ; but the chief marks for the arrows of his wit were the gentlemen of the corporation, some of whom laughed at such trifles, while such as were irritable often commenced prosecutions against him, but without success. He was frequently summoned to appear at the sessions, for daring to speak and write disrespectfully of the magistrates ; but the laugh was always on the side of Shebbeare.</p><p>When his time was out, he set up for himself, then discovering a taste for chemistry ; soon after which he married an amiable young woman with no fortune, but of respectable connections. Failing in business at Bideford, he went to Bristol in 1736, entered into partnership with a chemist, and never afterwards visited his native town.</p><p>He was at Paris in 1752, where he obtained, it is said, the degree of doctor in medicine ; a fact, however, which many are disposed to question.</p><p>His most celebrated performances were a series of letters to the People of England, written in a vigorous and energetic style, well calculated to make an impression on common readers. They galled the ministry, who at first were too eager to punish the author. On the 12th of January 1758, Lord Holdernesse signed a general warrant for apprehending the author, printer, and publishers of a wicked, audacious, and treasonable libel, entitled “A Sixth Letter to the People of England, on the progress of National Ruin ; in which is shown that the present grandeur of France and calamities of this nation are owing to the influence of Hanover on the councils of England and having found them, to seize and apprehend them, together with their books and papers.</p><p>Government having received information that a seventh letter was in the press, all the copies were seized and suppressed by virtue of another warrant, dated the 23d of January. In Easter term an information was filed against him by the attorney-general, and on the 17th of June the information was tried, when Shebbeare was found guilty ; and on the 28th of November he received sentence, by which he was fined L.5, ordered to stand in the pillory on the 5th of December at Charing Cross, to be confined three years, and to give security for his good behaviour for seven years, himself in L.500, and two others in L.250 each. During his confinement, he declared he never received as presents more than twenty guineas from all the world.</p><p>He was detained in prison during the whole time of the sentence, and with some degree of rigour. At the termination of his sentence, a new reign commenced ; and shortly afterwards, during Mr Grenville’s administration, a pension of L.200 a year was granted him by the crown, through the influence of Sir John Philips, and he ever after became devoted to the service of government. He was of course abused in almost every periodical work, which he seems in general to have had the good sense to neglect. Dr Smollett introduced him, in no very respectful light, under the name of Ferret, in Sir Launcelot Greaves ; and Mr Hogarth made him one of the group in the third election print.</p><p>His publications of a satirical, political, and medical nature amount to thirty-four, besides a novel, called Filial Piety, in which hypocrisy and blustering courage are very properly chastised. He died on the 1st of August 1788.</p><p>SHEERGOTTA, a town of Hindustan, in the province of Bahar, eighty miles south by west from Patna. Long. 84. 55. E. Lau 24. 32. N.</p><p>SHEERNESS, a town of the county of Kent, situated on the island of Sheppey. It stands at the point where the river Medway forms its junction with the Thames, on the right bank of the former river. It has been long a place of vast importance in a military point of view. The works having been suffered to fall into decay in the war with Holland in the reign of Charles IL, the Dutch fleet attacked and destroyed the fortifications, and thus opened</p></body></text></TEI>