<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-19T20:21:31Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>rinding ; the others are Albreda, on the river Gambia, which has 7000 inhabitants, and Jellifree, on the same river, a Portuguese settlement, where there is also an English factory. Salt is the principal article of trade. 7. Badiboo, situated to the east of the former, on the right bank of the Gambia, is about 600 square miles in extent. The capital is a small place of the same name. The population of the country may amount to 150,000. 8. Yani, also situated on the Gambia. The chief towns are Pisania, where there is an English factory, and Jonkadouda, where are several other European factories. There is a trade carried on in gold, ivory, and other products of the country. 9. Wally, or Bembook, is situated to the east of the former, and is rich in wood, corn, rice, garden-stuffs, cotton, indigo, cattle, and fish. Malchme is the chief town, where resides the king, who exercises a limited sovereignty. 10. Wooli, a Mandigo kingdom, extends along the northern bank of Gambia, between Salum and Bondoo. The country is generally covered with extensive woods ; the soil is everywhere fertile, producing cotton, tobacco, and esculent vegetables; and there are a number of towns situated in the valleys, which are the tracts chiefly cultivated. Medina, the capital, is a walled town, the residence of the king and state officers. It does not appear that this is a place of any considerable trade. 11. Gedumah, situatcd on the northern bank of the Senegal, and inhabited by nomadic Moors, who here find pasture for their cattle. It appears to be destitute of either town or village. 12. Combo, Foini, Caen, Jemaroa, Tom- mani, and Kolar, are the names of small kingdoms or territories, generally productive in rice, wax, goats, poultry, and the like, and in the principal towns of which are European factories. 13. The land of the Soosoos, which is situated between the sources and head waters of the Senegal and Gambia. This country is inhabited by an active race of men, who appear to live under a monarchy. From the conflicting statements of travellers and geographers, it seems doubtful if these people do not form a part of the Foulahs. 14. The land of the Fel∞ps, situated upon the banks of the Casamanza, and on the upper course of the Vintain, is about twenty-five leagues in length by fifteen in breadth. The country is very fertile, and the inhabitants rear cattle, which they defend with much courage against lions and other wild animals, with which their forests abound. Rice, goats, poultry, bees’ wax, and honey, are abundant, and partly exported. The population may amount to fifty thousand, who inhabit about sixty villages. 15. Kaboo is a territory situated on the upper part of the rivers St Domingo and Geba. It is subject to a king, who trades with the Portuguese in slaves, gold, and ivory. His residence, which is in the chief town, lies on the lake from which the river Geba flows. The Portuguese have here a settlement. Kaboo is very fertile in rice, millet, maize, indigo, and cotton. It is inhabited by a mixture of nations, chiefly Pagan Mandingoes, whose language prevails. 16. The important kingdom of Foota Torra, which extends considerably both to the north and south of the middle Senegal, but whose interior has not yet been explored by Europeans. There are a number of other kingdoms or territories in Senegambia, but they do not require particular notice. The most distinguished are the kingdom of Jallonkadoo, in which the river Senegal takes its rise ; and the kingdom of Soolimana, which extends along the rocky Rokelle, and the Camaranca and Mungo.</p><p>Besides those places we have mentioned as possessing European factories, the English, French, and Portuguese have also settlements. The English have factories on the rich gum coast at Portendik, to the north of the Senegal ; the island of James, situated a few miles from the mouth of the Gambia, with the fort of the same name ; the island of Boolam, with a secure and spacious harbour, and formerly one of the Sierra Leone Company’s stations, for promoting</p><p>civilization amongst the Indians, for assisting in putting down the slave-trade, and for cultivating West Indian products ; and the island of St Maria, on the Gambia, with twelve thousand inhabitants.</p><p>The French possess the island of St Louis or Senegal, at the mouth of the river of the same name, with 16,130 inhabitants, and the Fort St Louis, whence ships proceed on their voyage up the Senegal ; but navigation is very much embarrassed by a dangerous bank across the mouth of the river. The trade between this place and the mother country was at one time very considerable, amounting to L.750,000 annually ; and the English disposed of an equal amount of goods on the Gambia. At the French settlement a considerable quantity of cotton is still grown, and gum collected. The names of the other places are, the island of Goree, which is separated from the mainland by the canal of Dakar, 1500 toises in breadth. It is a great basaltic rock, with a town upon it, which bears the same name, and a fort, which bears that of St Michael. The French have also in the neighbourhood of Cape Verd a place called Riofresco. On the left bank of the Senegal is the settlement of Bakel, a hundred and five miles from St Louis, to which there is a steam-boat sent annually with goods. There are, besides, St Charles, formerly called Fort St Joseph; and the islands of Babaghee, Safal, and Geber.</p><p>The Portuguese possess St Cachao or Cacheu, situated on the north-east of the island of Bassao, at the mouth of the river St Domingo, in the kingdom of Koombo. It is fortified, has a Catholic church and a monastery, is the seat of a Portuguese governor, trades with the Cape Verd and Azore Islands, and contains 8000 inhabitants. The Portuguese also possess the island of Bissago, and the posts of Farim, Zeguichor, and Geba, which belong to the government of Cape Verd.	(<hi rend="smallcaps">r</hi>. <hi rend="smallcaps">r</hi>. <hi rend="smallcaps">r</hi>.)</p><p>SENESCHAL <hi rend="italic">(Seneschallas),</hi> derived from the German <hi rend="italic">sein,</hi> “ a house or place,” and <hi rend="italic">scale,</hi> “ an officer,” is a steward, and signifies one who has the dispensing of justice in some particular cases : as the high seneschal or steward of England ; <hi rend="italic">seneschal de la hôtel de roi,</hi> “ steward of the king’s household, seneschal or steward of courts.” <hi rend="italic">( co. Lit.</hi> 61 ; Croke’s <hi rend="italic">Juried.</hi> 102; Kitch. 83.)</p><p>SENGBEST, a town of Persia, in the province of Khorassan, twenty-five miles south-east of Meshed.</p><p>SENGEN, a city of China, of the first rank, in Quangsce, situated in a small and mountainous district. Long. 107. 34. E. Lat 23. 24. N.</p><p>SENGOA, a village of Persia, in the province of Azer- bijan, forty-eight miles south-east of Tabreez.</p><p>SENJEN, one of the largest islands of the kingdom of Norway, after Hindoen. It is separated from the continent by a narrow strait, and is about fifty miles in length and thirty-nine in breadth. It is surrounded by cliffs of more than 600 feet in height, which are covered with birch and pine trees ; and, considering the climate, there are some tolerably good sections of pasture-land, upon which black cattle are reared. It comprehends three parishes, viz. Bergfiord cum Medfiord, with 370 inhabitants ; Torask, with 350; and Tronoe, with 1560. There are two trading ports on the shore, Klowen and Gabostad, where small vessels repair.</p><p>SENLIS, an arrondissement of the department of the Oise, in France, which extends over 516 square miles. It contains seven cantons and 132 communes, with, in 1836, 78,790 inhabitants. The capital is the city of the same name, situated on the river Nonnette, an ancient place, with walls built at some remote period. The cathedral is also antique, and has the loftiest tower in France. It contains nine churches, and 950 houses, with 5016 inhabitants.</p><p>SENNA, a town of Persia, the capital of the eastern part of Kurdistan, known under the name of the province of Ar- delan. It is situated in the bosom of a luxuriant valley,</p></body></text></TEI>