<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-19T20:20:41Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>find a place on board all large ships of war (high-pressure engines of course); for the absurd and totally unsubstantial prejudice against this modification of steam power will, in the event of a war, if not long before, give way to the prodigious convenience in the way of stowage, and other advantages, which point out the expediency of its use in all</p><p>sea-going vessels without exception. To what extent ships of war may require to be fitted with steam power, is a question which must depend on circumstances that cannot be foreseen ; but that, eventually, they must have, within themselves, some such means of locomotion, besides what they may borrow from tug boats, we hold to be quite certain. (<hi rend="smallcaps">b. t.</hi>)</p><p>SEARCH-W<hi rend="smallcaps">arrant</hi>, in <hi rend="italic">Law,</hi> a kind of general warrant issued by justices of peace or by magistrates of towns, for searching all suspected places for stolen goods. In Scotland this was often done formerly ; and in some English lawbooks there are precedents requiring the constable to search all such suspected places as he and the party complaining shall think convenient ; but such practice is condemned by Lord Hale, Mr Hawkins, and the best authorities both among the English and the Scotch lawyers. However, in case of a complaint, and oath made of goods stolen, and that the party suspects that those goods are in a particular house, and shows the cause of such suspicion, the justice may grant a warrant to search not only that house, but other suspected places, and to attach the goods, and the party in whose custody they are found, and bring them before him or some other justice, to give an account how he came by them, and to abide such order as to law shall appertain. This warrant should be directed to the constable or other public officer, who may enter a suspected house and make search.</p><p>SEATON, a town in the hundred of Colyton, in the county of Devon, 150 miles from London. It consists chiefly of one street, and stands on the sea-shore, in a very pleasant but secluded situation. It is much resorted to as a sea-bathing place during the summer months ; and there is a considerable fishery carried on from hence. It has a parish church and an Independent chapel. The population amounted in 1821 to 1745, and in 1831 to 1803, taken at a period of the year when there is no occasional residence.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Seaton-Carew,</hi> a township in the parish of Stranton, in the county of Durham, in the ward of Stockton, two miles from Hartlepool, seven from Stockton, and 256 from London. It stands close to the sea-shore, near the influx of the river Tees into the sea. It is well adapted for seabathing, which has caused an increase in the number of the houses. The chief occupation of the inhabitants is that of fishing. Their number amounted in 1821 to 704, and in 1831 to 736 ; but it has much increased in the last seven years.</p><p>SEBACIC A<hi rend="smallcaps">cid</hi>, <hi rend="smallcaps">so</hi> called because it is procured from fat.</p><p>SEBASTIANO, called <hi rend="italic">Del Piombo,</hi> from an office in the lead-mines given him by Pope Clement VII., was an eminent Venetian painter, born in the year 1485. He was first a disciple of old Giovanni Bellino ; continued his studies under Giorgione ; and having attained an excellent manner of colouring, went to Rome, where he insinuated himself into the favour of Michel Angelo. He has the reputation of being the first who invented the art of preparing plaster-walls for oil-painting ; but he was so slow and lazy in his work, that other hands were often employed to finish what he had begun. He died in 1547.</p><p>SEBASTIAN, Sτ, a considerable and strongly fortified city of Spain, the capital of the province of Guipuscoa. It is built on a tongue of land projecting into the sea. The north point of the mountain Orgullo, being the high land of St Sebastian, is about three miles to the west of Port Passage, on which is built the castle of Mota, which serves as a guide on one side, as the light-house does on the other entrance to the bay, which is a very narrow strait, not admitting through it more than two vessels at a time ; but the bay, when entered, is secure for vessels furnished with good ground-tackle, which sunken rocks make very necessary.</p><p>For the protection of vessels trading with the town, there</p><p>are piers, within which ships of 300 tons may enter at low water ; but when the tide is out they lie dry on a hard bottom.</p><p>The city is defended by strong works on the land side, and has only two gates. St Sebastian is better built than most Spanish towns, the streets being wide, straight, and well paved. The houses, also, are large and well built. The town contains, besides warehouses, about 700 houses, three parish churches, five monasteries, a hospital, and about 12,000 or 13,000 inhabitants. The plaza, or square, is a very fine object.</p><p>This place was the seat of the Guipuscoa Society, one of the largest trading associations in Spain, which formed a junction with the Manilla Company ; and these had almost a monopoly of the trade with Caraccas in the western colonies of Spain, and with the Philippine Islands in the East Indies. It was then a port of vast commercial importance, having, besides those branches, a considerable share <hi rend="italic">of</hi> the export trade of wool. At that period there were large establishments for making ropes and cables, many anchor- smiths and nail-smiths, and such other occupations as are connected with the equipment of ships ; but political circumstances have changed and much diminished the commerce of this place.</p><p>The important position of this place has drawn upon it much of the calamity of war. In former times it had been frequently besieged and occupied by opposing parties. It was treacherously seized by the French in 1808, and was occupied by them till 1813. When the battle of Vittoria had been gained by the Duke of Wellington on the 21st of June, a way was opened for the British army to attack this city, into which the French had thrown a powerful garrison, who defended it with great bravery and skill. The British army invested the place, and attempted to storm it on the 25th July ; but having been repulsed, they besieged it in regιdar form, and with the loss of many lives it was stormed and carried on the 31st of August. During the assault the town was set on fire and nearly destroyed ; and a scene of misery was exhibited to the unfortunate people, in the rage of the storming soldiery, as well as in the progress of the flames, which will long be recollected with horror by the wτetched sufferers. The city was, however, speedily rebuilt, and commerce gradually returned. The civil war in some measure centred here, it being the chief point by which the queen’s party received their supply of warlike stores from England. Its trade has, however, received a most disastrous check. The castle of Mota is in lat. 43. 19. N., and long. 1. 59. W.</p><p>SEBESE, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Pulo Βιciε,</hi> a small island in the Straits of Sunda. Long. 105. 27. E. Lat. 5. 50. S.</p><p>SEBSVAR, a town of Khorassan, in Persia, 180 miles north-west of Herat. It was taken in 1381 by Timur, who made a cruel example of the inhabitants who revolted from his yoke, burying alive ten thousand of their number.</p><p>SEBURAI, <hi rend="smallcaps">Seburæi,</hi> a name which the Jews give to such of their rabbin or doctors as lived and taught some time after the finishing of the Talmud.</p><p>SECALE, <hi rend="smallcaps">Rye.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Agriculture.</hi></p><p>SECANT, in <hi rend="italic">Geometry,</hi> a line that cuts another, or divides it into parts.</p><p>SECANT, in <hi rend="italic">Trigonometry,</hi> denotes a right line drawn from the centre of a circle, which, cutting the circumference, proceeds till it meets with a tangent to the same circle.</p></body></text></TEI>