<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-19T20:21:05Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>the province of Lahore, between the thirty-first and thirty- second degrees of north latitude. The district is hilly, and covered with wood ; and the town is fortified, being situated a hundred miles cast by south from the city of Lahore. Long. 75. 34. E. Lat. 31. 39. N.</p><p>SEEBGUNGE, a town of Bengal, in the district of Di- nagepoor, eighty-four miles north-north-east from Moorshedabad. Long. 89. 12. E. Lat. 25. 3. N.</p><p>SEEDGHUR, a celebrated fortress of Hindustan, in the province of Bejapore, taken, with scarcely any loss, from the Mahrattas in 1818.</p><p>SEEDLINGS, among gardeners, denote such roots of gilliflowers and others as come from seed sown ; also the young and tender shoots of any plants that are newly sown.</p><p>SEEKS, or SIKHS, a religious sect settled at Patna, and so called from a word contained in one of the commandments of their founder, which signifies <hi rend="italic">learn thou.</hi> In books giving an account of the oriental sects and oriental customs, we find mention made both of the Seeks and the Sikhs ; and we are strongly inclined to think that the same tribe is meant to be denominated by both words. If so, however, different authors write very differently of their principles and manners. (See Mr Wilkins’s account of them in the Asiatic Researches.)</p><p>SEENGHOO, a town of the Birman empire, situatcd on the banks of the lrrawaddy.</p><p>SEEOR, a town of Hindustan, in the Mahratta territories, and province of Malwah, twenty-two miles west by south from Bopal, situated on the small river Rootah Seein. It has a considcrable manufactory of striped and chequered muslins.</p><p>SEEPARRAN, a small island in the Eastern Seas, near the east coast of Borneo. Long. 118. 23. E. Lat. 4. 8. N.</p><p>SEER,	a principality of Arabia, in the province of Om- mon, extending from Cape Mussendoon, along the shores of the Persian Gulf. This country not long since acknowledged the sovereign authority of the Imam ; but the scheich has shaken off this dependence, and is often at war with his former master. His navy is one of the most considerable in the Persian Gulf; his subjects are much employed in navigation, and carry on an extensive trade.</p><p>SEERDHUNA, a town of Hindustan, in the province of Delhi, and district of Merat. This place was formerly the residence of Somroo Begum, and the capital of a small principality under her government, about twenty miles in length by twelve in breadth, which, with the town, were assigned to Somroo, who was originally a German, his real name being Walter Reinihard, who went to Bengal and entered the French service, and afterwards that of Gregory, an Armenian, who was high in favour with Cossim Ali, to whom he recommended Somroo. It was this adventurer who massacred the English prisoners at Patna in 1763. He died in 1776, leaving a favourite concubine, who resided at Delhi, under the protection of the British government, in 1807, and invested her property in the East India Company’s funds at Calcutta. The district is fertile, producing all kinds of grain, sugar, and cotton. Long, of the town 77. 28. E. Lat. 29. U. N.</p><p>SEERPOOR, a town in the province of Bengal, and district of Raujeshy, seventy-four miles north-east from Moorshedabad. Long. 89. 20. E. Lat. 24. 38. N.</p><p>SEES,	a city of France, in the department of the Orne, and arrondissement of Alençon. It stands in a fruitful plain on the river Orne, near its source, is the seat of a bishop, and contains 900 houses, with 5860 inhabitants, who are employed in making black lace, hosiery, and cotton goods. Long. 6. 4. 44. E. Lat. 48. 36. 21. N.</p><p>SEETACOOND, a town of Bengal, in the district of Chittagong, remarkable for a warm spring, from which issues a flame, which is considered by the ignorant Hindus as an emanation from the deity, and consequently worthy of</p><p>being worshipped. It is seventeen miles north from Islamabad. Long. 91. 36. E. Lat. 22. 37. N.</p><p>SEGALIEN. See SAGHALIEN.</p><p>SEGMENT <hi rend="italic">of a </hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Circle,</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Geometry,</hi> is that part of the circle which is contained between a chord and an arc of the same circle.</p><p>SEGMENTS, L<hi rend="smallcaps">ine of,</hi> two particular lines on Gunter’s sector. They lie between the lines of sines and superficies, and are numbered 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10. They represent the diameter of a circle, so divided into 100 parts, that a right line drawn through these parts, and perpendicular to the diameter, shall cut the circle into two segments, the greater of which shall have the same proportion to the whole circle as the parts cut ofl' have to 100.</p><p>SEGO. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Bambarra.</hi></p><p>SEGORBE, a city of Spain, upon the Palaneia, in the province of Valencia, and in the neighbourhood of the Marmor Marsh, with 5000 inhabitants, whose trade consists of a few potteries, and the distillation of brandy.</p><p>SEGOVIA, one of the four provinces into which Old Castille, in Spain, is divided. It is generally an open and arid district, with scanty water, and little to merit description, except its capital, and the royal residences of Ildefonso and the Escurial, each of which is described under its appropriate article. The extent of the province is 290 square leagues, and its population amounts to 221,379 souls. The greater part of the province is destined to feed merino flocks, and the largest portion, particularly those with the finest wool, are shorn within it, as the weather is sufficiently warm to enable the sheep to bear that operation without feeling any inconvenience. Though it grows wine, oil, and corn, the harvests are by no means adequate to the consumption, and their wants must be supplied from other lands than their own. It is watered by the Ebro, the Cresma, the Xarama, and the Duraton ; and it possesses mineral springs at Cinchon, Caballar, and Bartariejo. It belongs to the captain-generalship of Zamora.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Segovia,</hi> a city of Spain, and capital of the province of the same name, in Old Castille. It is situated on the right bank of the river Duero, not far from its source, and near to the ruins of the ancient Roman city of Numantia. Around it are most excellent pastures for sheep, and the wool of the best of the merinos takes its name from this city. The usual quantity of fine wool annually sent from this city is about 2,250,000 lbs., and the management of such extensive concerns necessarily creates considerable trade. There is in this city a manufactory of fine cloths, cassimeres, and other articles composed of the native wool, which is carried on by the government.</p><p>The remains of antiquity in this city are, however, the most interesting attractions to all travellers. The aqueduct, of very ancient construction, is yet in perfect preservation, and still conveys the water to the city. It is carried over one of the suburbs or arches, some of which are a hundred and four feet in height; the arches are in double rows, one above the other, and on the uppermost a channel is made, covered with large flag-stones, through which the water runs. It is a wonderful relic of antiquity, on account of the excellence of the masonry, which has withstood the ravages of time for so many centuries. The period of its erection is doubtful. The Spaniards, who delight in tracing every ancient monument to the highest antiquity, ascribe it to Hercules ; it is, however, evidently of Roman construction, and none give it a later date than the reign of Trajan. It discovers as yet no marks of decay, and as the city to which it conveys water is on the top of a rock, if it were demolished the inhabitants would be greatly distressed for that necessary of life.</p><p>The ancient castle, or alcazar, is another of the curiosities of Segovia. It stands on a rude mass of rocks overlooking the surrounding country, whose base is washed by</p></body></text></TEI>