<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-19T20:19:56Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>quent acts. It consists of 23 members, viz. the lord mayor and sheriffs of Dublin, three aldermen chosen by the board of aldermen from their own body, and 17 members appointed in the first instance by the act of incorporation, and who are on all future vacancies empowered to elect new members. The board devotes one day a-week to the business of the lighthouses.</p><p>There are thirty-six land lights, and three floating lights, supported by the Ballast board in Ireland. Of these land lights, twenty-six are public lights, and ten are local or harbour lights. There are besides five other harbour lights on the coast, supported by the trustees of the respective harbours.</p><p>It appears from the Parliamentary Report of 1834, that the revenue derived from collection of lighthouse dues in Ireland during the year 1833, was L.42,060 The mode of charging the light dues was formerly as follows :—Any British or Irish vessel and foreign privileged vessels on oversea voyages, paid one farthing per ton for every light they passed in the track of their voyage; foreign ships not privileged paid one halfpenny per ton. Coasters, loaded, paid one far thing per ton for every lighthouse or floating light they passed; ifin ballast, one eighth of a penny only per ton; and rules were laid down as to the number of lights to be paid for by vessels navigating St. George’s Channel, to or from the Atlantic Ocean ; as well as for passing through the northern channel bound to the northward, and returning ; for going down St. George’s Channel, to the eastward; and for sailing from a western port of Ireland to the eastward, without entering St. George’s Channel.</p><p>The last act of Parliament regarding lighthouses, was the result of a report of a select committee on lighthouses, which was moved for by Mr. Joseph Hume, M.P. and which sat in 1834. The act was passed in 1836. The chief alterations upon the former state of the Boards in which the management of the lights is vested, are the following. The duties levied under all former acts were repealed ; and it was enacted, that every British vessel, and every privileged foreign vessel, should pay the toll of one halfpenny, for every time of passing or deriving advantage from any light, with exception of the Bell-rock, for which one penny per ton is the toll. Every foreign vessel not privileged, must pay double toll. The only exemptions from the payment of duties, are in favour of the King’s vessels, those of the Trinity House, and all vessels going in ballast, or engaged in the herring fisheries. Power was also given to the Commissioners of the Northern Lighthouses, to erect beacons, and moor buoys ; and the harbour lights on the Scotch coast were placed under their controul. The Act confers upon the Trinity House, the power of entering any lighthouse under the charge of the other boards, to inspect their condition, and gives them a controul as to the erection of new lighthouses, or the alteration of those already existing, both in Scotland and Ireland. But in the event of a difference of opinion arising between the Trinity House and either of the two other Boards, appeal may be made to the Privy Council. The Act further provides that an account of the receipt of all money, and a report of all alterations made during the preceding year, should be annually laid before each House of Parliament, one month after its meeting.</p><p>The average expense of maintaining a land light in Great Britain, is found to be about L.500, and that of a floating light about L.1200.</p><p>The French lights, of which there are upwards of 100, including about 60 harbour lights, are managed by a particular section of the <hi rend="italic">Direction Generale des Ponts et chaussées,</hi> which is called the <hi rend="italic">commission des Phares ;</hi> and more than half of the lights are on the dioptric principle of Fresnel.</p><p>By an imperial decree of7th March 1806, the lighthouses</p><p>and beacons were placed under the charge of the Minister of the Interior; before which time they had been under the immediate direction of the Administration of Roads and Bridges. This decree required that the establishment of every new beacon or light, should proceed upon the joint recommendation of the Ministers of the Marine and the Interior, and gave rise, in 1811, to the institution of the <hi rend="italic">Commission des Phares,</hi> the members of which, with the exception of the secretary, who is also engineer-in-chief, act without any special remuneration, and in consequence of their holding other official situations. At the time of its first constitution, it appears by the report of Admiral de Rossel, that this Commission consisted of the following gentlemen, viz. Baron Becquey, councillor of state, director- general of roads and bridges, President of the Commission ; M. Halgan, rear-admiral, and councillor of state; M. De Prony, inspector-general of roads and bridges ; M. Arago, astronomer-royal, member of the Institute ; M. Sganzin, inspector-general of roads and bridges ; M. Rolland, inspector-general of naval works ; M. Tarbe De Vauxclairs, inspector-general of roads and bridges ; M. Mathieu, member of the Institute ; and M. Augustin Fresnel, member of the Institute, secretary and engineer-in-chief to the Commission.</p><p>All the more important plans for the improvement and establishment of lights, are submitted to this Commission ; but the plans for new lighthouse towers are only discussed in reference to their fitness for the lights ; and every question regarding the buildings or estimates, is submitted to the General Council of the Administration of Roads and Bridges, for their final approbation. The Engineer of the Commission prepares all the plans, and directs the fitting up of the optical apparatus and the lanterns, and sends to the engineers of the departments, the schemes for new lights, that they may make the plans for the necessary buildings connected with them. He also inspects the lights on the coast, and is responsible for their efficient condition. In the discharge of these duties, he is assisted by three <hi rend="italic">conducteurs</hi> of works, who generally see the apparatus fitted up, and attend to the due performance of the light-room duty.</p><p>As soon as a new light is ready, the Administration causes advertisements to be made in the roost extensively circulated journals of Paris, containing a notice to mariners regarding its position, appearance, and time of exhibition. This notice is also circulated in every French port by means of placards, which are affixed by the maritime authorities, and generally appear about three months before the exhibition of the light. By a late decree, too, of the Director- general of roads and bridges, the Engineer publishes every year a summary description of all the lights on the coast of France.</p><p>The other lights of Europe are, with the exceptions already mentioned, on the catoptric principle. The writer of this article has seen the greater number of the lights along the coast, between St. Petersburgh and the Spanish fron tier ; and so far as he has been able to learn, their management is generally vested in some department of the executive government.</p><p>The Americans have been very active in the establishment of lighthouses. There are upwards of two hundred land lights along the coast of the United States, and twenty- eight floating lights. Their management is entrusted to a board called the General Lighthouse Establishment, which appears to have been regularly organised so early as the year 1791. The total expenditure connected with the Lighthouse Establishment in the year 1837, was about L.71,352 ; a sum which includes about L.7000 for the maintenance of upwards of 600 buoys and beacons, which are also under the care of the Lighthouse Establishment. The Fifth Auditor of the Treasury is the chief officer of the lighthouse board.</p></body></text></TEI>