<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-19T20:22:46Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>then slowly and cautiously unfolded himself, till the goat fell dead from his
                monstrous embrace, when he began to prepare himself for swallowing it. Placing his
                mouth in front of the dead animal, he commenced by lubricating with his saliva that
                part of the goat ; and then taking its muzzle into his mouth, which had, and indeed
                always has, the appearance of a raw, lacerated wound, he sucked it in as far as the
                horns would allow. These protuberances opposed some little difficulty, not so much
                from their extent, as from their points ; however, they also in a very short time
                disappeared, that is to say, externally ; but their progress was still to be traced
                very distinctly on the outside, threatening every moment to protrude through the
                skin. The victim had now descended as far as the shoulders ; and it was an
                astonishing sight to observe the extraordinary action of the snake’s muscles when
                stretched to such an unnatural extent,—an extent which must have utterly destroyed
                all muscular power in any animal that was not, like himself, endowed with very
                peculiar faculties of expansion and action at the same time. When his head and neck
                had no other appearance than that of a serpent’s skin, stuffed almost to bursting,
                still the workings of the muscles were evident, and his power of suction, as it is
                erroneously called, unabated ; it was, in fact, the effect of a contractile muscular
                power, assisted by two rows of strong, hooked teeth. With all this, he must be so
                formed as to be able to suspend, for a time, his respiration ; for it is impossible
                to conceive that the process of breathing could be carried on while the mouth and
                throat were <hi rend="italic">so </hi>completely stuffed and expanded by the body of
                the goat, and the lungs themselves (admitting the trachea to be ever so hard)
                compressed, as they must have been, by its passage downwards.</p>
            <p>“ The whole operation of completely gorging the goat occupied about two hours and
                twenty minutes ; at the end of which time the tumefaction was confined to the middle
                part of the body, or stomach, the superior parts, which had been so much distended,
                having resumed their natural dimensions. He then coiled himself up again, and lay
                quietly in his usual torpid state for about three weeks or a month, when, his last
                meal appearing to be completely digested and dissolved, he was presented with
                another goat, which he killed and devoured with equal facility.”@@<hi
                    rend="superscript">1</hi></p>
            <p>As the vessel, which was sailing from Batavia to England, approached the Cape of Good
                Hope, this gigantic reptile began to droop, as was at first supposed, from the
                increasing cold. It refused to kill some fowls which were presented, and died before
                reaching St Helena. On dissection, the coats of the stomach were found to be “
                excoriated and pierced by worms!” Nothing of either goat remained except a single
                horn. During a prior captivity of some months at Whidah, in the kingdom of Dahomey,
                Mr Macleod had enjoyed opportunities of observing snakes “ double the size of the
                one just described.” These killed their prey in the same manner ; but from their
                superior bulk were capable of swallowing much larger animals than either goats or
                sheep. Governor Abson, who had resided for nearly forty years at Fort William, a
                settlement of the African Company, used to describe some desperate struggles which
                had taken place between these great serpents and various wild beasts, as well as
                smaller cattle. A negro herdsman was once seized by the thigh, but the monster, in
                attempting to entwine itself around him, got en</p>
            <p>tangled by a tree, and the man being armed with a knife, had presence of mind to
                inflict several severe gashes on the neck and throat, which enabled him to disengage
                himself from the dreadful coils which were closing fast around him. But he remained
                lame for life, in consequence of the wound and heavy pressure inflicted by the
                jaws.</p>
            <p>The natural colours, which are various in this family, disappear speedily after
                death. Some are brown upon a yellowish ground, others exhibit a uniformly greenish
                hue, red prevails among certain species, while a few are nearly black. Almost all
                are more or less spotted ; and it has been observed that, unlike the smaller tribes
                of serpents, these markings continue equally, or rather more distinct, as the
                individual increases in years. The body of the Boas is thickest at the middle,
                tapers towards either end, and is always considerably compressed. The abdomen is
                broad, and slightly convex or keeled. The tail is shaped like the body, but is more
                slender, not very conical, and usually terminates in a blunted point. It is always
                prehensile, that is, possesses the power of rolling inwards upon itself, or forming
                convolutions around other bodies. The scales in general are rather small, and as
                they encroach considerably on the under surface, it follows that the abdominal
                plates arc narrower than usual. There are sometimes from sixty to seventy ranges of
                scales, and about two hundred and fifty abdominal plates. The number of these,
                however, is greater in the Boas of the ancient world than among the American
                species, which moreover differ in several other respects; while the genus <hi
                    rend="italic">Aerochordus</hi> is distinguished from all its congeners by the
                small granular scales which clothe the entire surface, and of which a double series
                prevails along the median line of the abdomen, forming a kind of projecting ridge or
                keel.</p>
            <p>The head of the Boas is always distinguishable from the trunk, being thick, rather
                lengthened, conical, depressed, and terminated by a muzzle for the most part
                elongated, and truncated at the point. The eyes are placed at some distance from the
                nostrils, and are lateral in the terrestrial species, of which the head is flattened
                above, and more or less angular on the sides ; but the more aquatic kinds have the
                eyes rather vertical. These organs are always small in our present family, and,
                excepting <hi rend="italic">Aerochordus,</hi> have the</p>
            <p>pupil horizontally elongated. The nostrils are broad, close- y approached to the end
                of the muzzle, and in some are placed upon its summit. They open upwards in the
                genus just named, and assume a tubular form. All the species are provided with
                palatine teeth, nearly as much developed as the maxillary ones ; but there are no
                intermaxillary teeth except among the Pythons. The glands of the head are less
                developed in this family than among the majority of Ophidian reptiles.</p>
            <p>Genus <hi rend="smallcaps">Boa. No</hi> intermaxillary teeth. Space between the
                orbits formed solely by the frontale properly so called. Sub- caudal plates
                    simple.@@<hi rend="superscript">3</hi> See Plate CCCCXLIII. figs. 8-11.</p>
            <p>This restricted genus includes the largest of Ophidian reptiles, and although
                composed chiefly of South American snakes, it also contains three Asiatic species,
                which, though of much smaller size, cannot be regarded otherwise than as a
                geographical division.</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Boa constrictor,</hi> Linn., is a middle-sized species, which
                rarely exceeds the length of ten or twelve feet.@@<hi rend="superscript">3</hi> It
                is of a reddish tint, elegantly marked by irregular reticulations of</p>
            <p>@@@ Macleod's <hi rend="italic">Voyage of the
                    Alceste,</hi> p. 290.</p>
            <p>@@@ This is the prevailing character of these parts, although we find in this, as in
                many other cases, a difficulty in seizing upon single determinate features of
                constant application. Thus we sometimes meet with several divided plates in the
                sub-caudal region of these so-called Boas.</p>
            <p><hi rend="superscript">@@@</hi> The true <hi rend="italic">Β. constrictor</hi> is
                often confounded with the more gigantic <hi rend="italic">B. murina,</hi> and its
                dimensions have in consequence been greatly exaggerated. We doubt if any existing
                species ever attains to the alleged size of the so-called <hi rend="italic">B.
                    constrictor.</hi> Mr Swainson, however, who has travelled in South America, and
                is himself a zealous student of the facts of zoology, both as recorded in books and
                as existing in nature, states that the young individuals frequent in our menageries
                are mere pigmies in comparison to the <pb n="145"/>adults, “which have been <hi
                    rend="italic">often found</hi> to exceed <hi rend="italic">forty feet</hi> in
                length” <hi rend="italic">(Cabinet Cyelopædia,</hi> vol. cxvi. p. 143). Yet he does
                not state thia as a result of observation, or as connected with his own knowledge as
                well as belief A single specimen of such gigantic reptile would be the wonder of
                Europe, and would make a fortune for its owner. A Dutch friend of Mr Waterton’s
                killed a Boa (he does not say of what species) twenty-two feet long, with a pair of
                stag’s horns in its mouth. It had swallowed the stag, but could not swallow the
                horns (at which we are not much surprised), and so had to wait in patience with that
                uncomfortable mouthful till its stomach had digested the body, “ and then the horns
                would drop out.” It was in this expectant plight that the Dutchman found it, as he
                was going in his canoe up the river, and sent a ball through its head <hi
                    rend="italic">(Wanderings in South America,</hi> third edit. p. 209). The large
                serpent <hi rend="italic">bagged</hi> by Mr Waterton, after “ a sharp fray in the
                den, the rotten sticks flying on all sides, and each party struggling for
                superiority,” measured rather more than fourteen feet in length. It was of the kind
                called <hi rend="italic">Coulacanara,</hi> a rare species, and so much thicker in
                proportion to its length than any other snake of the forest, that an individual of the
                extent just elated “ is as thick as a common Boa of twenty-four.” Its jaws are so
                extensile, that Mr Waterton, after skinning his specimen, could easily get his head
                into its mouth.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
