<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-19T20:21:19Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Population of Selkirkshire.</p><table><row><cell/><cell cols="3">HOUSES.</cell><cell cols="3"><hi rend="smallcaps">occupations.</hi></cell><cell cols="3">PERSONS.</cell></row><row><cell/><cell/><cell><p>Families.</p></cell><cell/><cell>Families chiefly em-</cell><cell><p>Families chiefly employed in Trade, Manufactures, and Handi</p><p>craft.</p></cell><cell>All other Families not coin-</cell><cell>Males.</cell><cell>Females.</cell><cell/></row><row><cell>YEARS.</cell><cell>Inhabited.</cell><cell/><cell>Uninhabited.</cell><cell>ployed in Agriculture.</cell><cell/><cell>prised in the two preceding classes.</cell><cell/><cell/><cell>Persona.</cell></row><row><cell>1811</cell><cell>1080</cell><cell>1258</cell><cell>41</cell><cell>500</cell><cell>363</cell><cell>395</cell><cell>2750</cell><cell>3139</cell><cell>5889</cell></row><row><cell>1821</cell><cell>1081</cell><cell>1372</cell><cell>36</cell><cell>421</cell><cell>409</cell><cell>542</cell><cell>3205</cell><cell>3432</cell><cell>6637</cell></row><row><cell>1831</cell><cell>1094</cell><cell>1391</cell><cell>62</cell><cell>474</cell><cell>450</cell><cell>467</cell><cell>3394</cell><cell>3439</cell><cell>6833</cell></row></table><p>SELLA, a town of Spain, in what is called the kingdom of Valentia, in the province of Alcoy. It is situated on the banks of the river Alcoy, and near to its entrance into the Mediterranean Sea. It contains about 2000 inhabitants, who are chiefly employed in making cordage and fishing- nets from esparto, which grows abundantly in the neighbourhood.</p><p>SELMAST, a town of Persia, in the province of Azerbi- jan, containing about 2000 inhabitants, principally Nestorian Christians. It is famed for its lofty poplars and delightful gardens. It is seventv-five miles west-south-west of Ta- breez.</p><p>SELTERS, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Seltzers,</hi> a village of the principality of Nassau, in Germany, about ten miles from Coblentz. The name of the mineral spring here is celebrated in every part of Europe. Seltzer water is brought to this country in stone bottles, which are closely corked and sealed, and contain about three pints each ; and when they are well secured, it keeps unchanged for a considerable time. Seltzer water, according to the analysis of Bergman, contains, in an English wine pint,</p><p>Grains.</p><p>Carbonate of lime		 3</p><p>Ditto of magnesia	 5</p><p>Ditto of soda	 4</p><p>Muriate of soda	17∙5</p><p>29∙5</p><p>The same quantity of water also yields seventeen cubic inches of a gaseous substance, which is found to be almost entirely pure carbonic acid gas. This water has been long in high repute on account of its medicinal virtues, and we have no doubt that it may be used with considerable benefit in many of those complaints which arise from a deranged state of the stomach and bowels. The usual dose of this water is from half a pint to a pint ; but in most cases it may be drunk freely. From its agreeable taste, and its exhilarating effects on the spirits, it is extensively employed at table as a common drink in Germany and Holland. In this country also both the real and the artificial Seltzer water is largely used for the same purpose. Seltzer water may be artificially imitated, by adding the ingredients discoverable by analysis, and in the same proportion.</p><p>SEMAO, an island in the Eastern Seas, about twenty- four miles in length from north to south, and from six to ten in breadth. A strait, called the Strait of Semao, separates it from the south-west end of the island of Timor. This strait, which has a good depth of water, affords secure shelter to ships during the strength of the westerly monsoons. Long. 123. 45. E. Lat. 10. 15. S.</p><p>SEMENDRA, a city in the north-west of Turkey in Europe, the capital of a province of the same name in the ancient Servia. It is built on the western branch of the river Morava, where it falls into the Danube. It is fortified and defended by an ancient castle, and contains the</p><p>cathedral of a Greek bishop, several mosques, and about 8000 inhabitants, who subsist by trading and fishing on the rivers. Long. 21. 23. E. Lat. 44. 37. N.</p><p>SEMENTINÆ <hi rend="smallcaps">Feriæ,</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Antiquity,</hi> were feasts held annually among the Romans, to obtain of the gods a plentiful harvest. They were celebrated in the temple of Tellus, where solemn sacrifices were offered to Tellus and Ceres. These feasts were held about seed-time, usually in the month of January ; for, as Macrobius observes, they were moveable feasts.</p><p>SEMI, a word borrowed from the Latin, signifying <hi rend="italic">half </hi>but only used in composition with other words.</p><p>SEMI-ARIANS, in <hi rend="italic">Bcclesiastical History,</hi> a branch of the ancient Arians, consisting, according to Epiphanius, of such as, in appearance, condemned the errors of that heresi- arch, but yet acquiesced in some of his principles, only palliating and hiding them under softer and more moderate"terms. Though they separated from the Arian faction, they could never be brought to acknowledge that the Son was “ ho- moousios,” that is, consubstantial, or of the same substance with the Father ; they would only allow him to be “ ho- moiousios,” that is, of a like substance with the Father, or similar to the Father in his essence, not by nature, but by a peculiar privilege.</p><p>The Semi-Arianism of the modems consists in their maintaining that the Son was from all eternity begotten by the will of the Father, contrary to the doctrine of the orthodox, who seem to teach that eternal generation is necessary. Such, at least, are the respective opinions of Dr Clarke and Bishop Bull.</p><p>SEMICIRCLE in <hi rend="italic">eometry,</hi> is half a circle, or that figure which is comprehended between the diameter of the circle and half its circumference.</p><p>SEMICOLON, in <hi rend="italic">Grammar,</hi> one of the points or stops used to distinguish the several members of a sentence from each other.</p><p>The mark or character of a semicolon is (;), and it has its name from being of somewhat less effect than a colon, or as demanding a shorter pause.</p><p>The proper use of the semicolon is to distinguish the conjunct members of a sentence. Now, by a conjunct member of a sentence is meant such a one as contains at least two simple members. Whenever, then, a sentence can be divided into several members of the same degree, which are again divisible into other simple members, the former are to be separated by a semicolon. For instance, “ If fortune bear a great sway over him, who has nicely stated and concerted every circumstance of an affair ; we must not commit every thing, without reserve, to fortune, lest she should have too great a hold of us.”</p><p>SEMIDIAMETER, half the diameter, or a right line drawn from the centre of a circle to its circumference ; being the same with what is otherwise called the <hi rend="italic">radius.</hi></p><p>SEMIPALATNOI, a fortress of Asiatic Russia, in the southern part of the government of Tomsk, erected for the</p></body></text></TEI>