<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-19T20:22:48Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>brownish black, and other hucs, and is subject to a great variety of aspect, so fur
                as colour is concerned. It is, however, well characterized by the small smooth
                scales which cover both head and body, and of which there are sixty- seven rows. The
                head is heart-shaped, and the tail short. Abdominal plates 243, caudal fifty-eight.
                This species is native to the intertropical countries of South America, and not only
                have its size and voracity been greatly exaggerated, but many traits have been
                applied to it which truly belong only to the Pythons of the ancient continent. Thus
                the very name of <hi rend="italic">Devin,</hi> bestowed upon it by Lacépède, is
                borrowed from what Bosman relates of the worship accorded by the negroes to certain
                African reptiles. It is met with in Surinam and Brazil, in woody districts, being
                sometimes seen suspended from the branch of a tree, sometimes concealed in the
                hollows of rocks, or beneath an ancient trunk. It is feared by no one, is often
                killed with a short walking- stick, and is commonly known by the name of <hi
                    rend="italic">Jiboya.</hi> It feeds on small and middle-sized mammalia, such as
                mice, rats, agoutis, pacas, and capybaras, as well as on various reptiles. A hunter,
                however, assured the Prince of Neuwied, that his dog on one occasion would have
                fallen a victim to a Boa of this species, had he not contrived to shoot it during
                the combat. The true constrictor does not enter the water. The Brazilians take it by
                means of gins, and employ its skin for making boots and saddle-cloths. They also use
                its fat. All engraved representations of this species, having been made from
                ill-prepared museum specimcns, are worse than indifferent.@@<hi rend="superscript"
                    >1</hi></p>
            <p>The rat-eating Boa, <hi rend="italic">B. murina,</hi> Linn. <hi rend="italic">(B.
                    Anaconda, </hi>Daud.@@<hi rend="superscript">2</hi>
                <hi rend="italic">B. aguatica,</hi> Neuw.@@<hi rend="superscript">3</hi>), is the
                largest Ophidian reptile of America, and probably the most gigantic of known
                species. It is distinguished in Brazil by the title of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Cucuriuba,</hi> and passes a great portion of its time in the water, either
                swimming about in various directions, or floating lazily with the current. It dives
                with great dexterity, can remain for a length of time beneath the surface, and is
                said to prey on fish as well as quadrupeds. It is tenacious of life, and is killed
                by the natives either with bow or musket in the water, or with sticks when met with
                on shore, where its movements are somewhat sluggish. Both its skin and fat are used
                for various purposes, and its flesh is eaten by the Botocudes. M. Fermin measured
                one which had attained the length of twenty-three and a half feet ; and the Prince
                of Neuwied was assured by the natives that it is often much longer, although he
                himself never saw one above twenty feet. This species exhibits less varied markings
                than the preceding. The general hue of the upper parts is sooty brown, with two rows
                of orbicular blackish spots along the back. The under surface and sides are of an
                ochry yellow, the latter marked with a double row of irregular eye-shaped spots,
                which confound themselves with numerous squarer spots upon the belly. The nostrils
                are vertical, the eyes also directed upwards. The head is of</p>
            <p>an elongated form, with a rounded muzzle. Abdominal plates 250, caudal sixty-six.</p>
            <p>The other species of this genus are <hi rend="italic">B. cenchria, canina </hi>(Plate
                CCCCXLIII. figs. 8-11), <hi rend="italic">hortulana,</hi> from South America ; <hi
                    rend="italic">B. Dussumieri,</hi> from a small island near the Mauritius ; <hi
                    rend="italic">B. carinata,</hi> from the Moluccas and New Guinea ; <hi
                    rend="italic">B. conica,</hi> from Bengal ; and <hi rend="italic">B.
                    melanura,</hi> from the island of Cuba.</p>
            <p>Genus <hi rend="smallcaps">Ρυτηον.</hi> Several intermaxillary teeth. Upper portion
                of the orbit formed by a particular bone incased among the three frontals, and named
                super-orbital by Cuvier. Sub-caudal plates usually divided. Lips hollowed out in
                front. Plates of the head larger and more regular than in Boa. See Plate CCCCXLIII.
                figs. 1<hi rend="italic">b</hi>, le, and 3, and Plate CCCCXLIV. fig. 5.</p>
            <p>This genus was established by M. Daudin for the reception of the great serpents of
                the ancient world. Brown, black, and yellow, are their prevailing colours. Certain
                of the species cqual (some say exceed) the Boas of America in size, for example the
                    <hi rend="italic">Ular-sawa (Python bivitratus, </hi>Khul,—<hi rend="italic"
                    >col. Javanicus, </hi>Shaw). This species is of a yellowish tint, relieved by a
                pattern of broad alternate brown spots. The top of the head is margined by two rays
                of the ground colour. The flanks are variously adorned by black and white, and the
                under surface is marked by deep square spots. There are sixty-three ranges of smooth
                small scales, 270 abdominal and seventy caudal plates. This great reptile is spread,
                according to M. Schlegel, over a vast extent of territory, being known to occur from
                the western coast of Africa, over the whole of intertropical Asia, as far cast as
                China and the island of Java. It is said to attain the length of twenty-five feet,
                and individuals of twenty feet in length have been seen and described by trustworthy
                naturalists. A fine specimen lived for some time in Holland, and was observed to be
                slow in its movements, mild in its temper, and never inclined to bite even when
                provoked. It was kept in a large box enveloped in woollen cloths, where it lay in
                continued tranquillity, and suffered itself to be drawn out for frequent exhibition
                without manifesting any signs of anger or impatience. We suspect that the senses of
                this, and of other large tropical snakes, are so far benumbed by the change of
                climate in Europe as to produce stupefaction rather than tameness. The specimen in
                question was presented with food every eight days, which, however, it often refused
                for several successive times. It was most easily excited to eat by the sight of a
                live rabbit, into the head of which it would fix its teeth, and then, placing it
                within a fold of its body, deprived it almost instantly of life. After the
                commission of this murder, it was in no hurry to swallow its victim, but sometimes
                licked it for a while, occasionally taking two or three hours to effect the final
                deglutition. This is supposed to be the <hi rend="italic">Pedda-poda </hi>of Dr
                Russel, called rock-snake by the Anglo-Indians.@@<hi rend="superscript">4</hi></p>
            <p>We do not happen to know to what extent this or any</p>
            
            <p>@@@ See Scheuchzer, <hi rend="italic">Βiblia Sacra,</hi> pl. 746, fig. 1 :—Lace'p.
                    <hi rend="italic">Quad. Ouip,</hi> ii. pl. 16, fig. 1 :—Daudin, <hi
                    rend="italic">Reptiles,</hi> v. pl. 92, fig. 1. There are various figures of our
                    <hi rend="italic">B. oonstrictor</hi> in Seba's <hi rend="italic"
                    >Thesaurus,</hi> and from these Laurenti seems to have composed such species as
                    <hi rend="italic">Constrictor formosissimus, Res serpentum, diviniloquus,</hi>
                and several others.</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">@@@’ Reptiles,</hi> v. 161, pl. 63. </p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">@@@ Abbild.</hi> livrais ii. pl. 6, and <hi rend="italic"
                    >Beitr.</hi> p. 226.</p>
            <p><hi rend="superscript">@@@4</hi> Numerous nominal species have arisen from the
                superficial observance of different varieties of this Python. See Russel’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Serpents</hi>, pl. 20, 23, 24, and 29 ; and Daudin's <hi
                    rend="italic">Reptiles,</hi> v. pl. 64, fig. 1, and pl. 59, fig. 4.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
