<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-19T20:22:34Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>occur there have each only a single representative. These reptiles belong almost without exception to species peculiar to the African continent. <hi rend="italic">Lycodon Horstokii</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Naja rhombeata</hi> occur on the coast of Guinea, which produces likewise <hi rend="italic">Psammophis moniliger,—</hi>but a local variety, resembling that which is found in Egypt. In Senegambia we find three species of tree-serpents, of the genus <hi rend="italic">Dendro- phis,</hi> which differ from those of the Cape, but of which one</p><p><hi rend="italic">(Den. picta)</hi> is spread over a vast extent of the Asiatic world, as far south-eastwards as New Guinea. The intertropical countries of Africa produce <hi rend="italic">Python bivittatus,</hi> characterized by an equally great extension, as it is found both in Java and the Chinese empire. <hi rend="italic">Viperus arietans</hi> of the Cape is found as far north as Abyssinia, where it forms a variety of a paler hue. Northern Africa produces several serpents of species different from those of other parts of that continent. Such are <hi rend="italic">Tortrix eryx</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Vipera echis, </hi>which elsewhere inhabitas far south as Hindustan,—the <hi rend="italic">cerastes,</hi> a species of <hi rend="italic">Dipsas,</hi> and several kinds of <hi rend="italic">coluber. </hi>Other species, such as <hi rend="italic">Naja haje</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Psammophis monili- ger,</hi> differ more or less from their southern representatives. The Mediterranean countries of Africa nourish several kinds which occur in the south of Europe ; and this analogy between the two continents is very striking when we compare, not the serpents alone, but the zoological productions in general, of Barbary, with those of Portugal and Spain. No serpents have been yet observed in the islands situate within the radius of Africa, and it appears certain that they do not exist in the Canary Islands.</p><p>The great island of Madagascar, of which the natural productions are as yet but slightly known, appears to be zoologically allied to Africa chiefly by the species of its western side ; and although the eastern slopes of its great mountain chain exhibit features of an Asiatic character, its totality presents a very distinct and peculiar complexion. With the exception of <hi rend="italic">Tropidοnotus schistosus,</hi> all the known serpents belong to particular and elsewhere undiscovered species. For example, the <hi rend="italic">Lanhαga,</hi> an anomalous and very remarkable species of <hi rend="italic">Dryοphis, Herpetodryas Goudotii</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Rhodogaster,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Dipsas Gaimardii,</hi> are all peculiar to Madagascar. The Mauritius produces a very beautiful species, <hi rend="italic">coluber miniatus,</hi> and a small Boa (<hi rend="italic">B. Dussumieri)</hi> of an extremely attenuated form. From the Seychelles Islands we know of no serpent but a species of the genus <hi rend="italic">Psammophis.</hi></p><p>With the exception of its two magnificent Indian peninsulas, Asia is not so productive as might be expected of the reptile race. The temperature of a vast portion of the loftier and central, and <hi rend="italic">a fortiori</hi> of the northern districts, is subjected to a low temperature during many months of the year. We know that Northern Asia, Siberia more especially, produces several animals of the higher orders, identical with some which inhabit the more rigorous parts of Europe ; but the alleged identity of the Siberian species of <hi rend="italic">Tropidonotus</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Viperus</hi> may possibly require confirmation. A curious Ophidian, peculiar to the southern countries of Siberia, is <hi rend="italic">Trigonocephalus halys,</hi> intermediate organically between the vipers of Europe and those species of its own genus which have the head furnished with scaly plates. The deserts to the south of the Caspian Sea, which are prolonged on the one side into Hindustan, on the other by means of the Iran, into Arabia and Syria, thus connecting with the desert tracts of Africa, produce a few species common alike to corresponding portions of both continents. We are still in almost total ignorance of the snakes of the great plateaus and other portions of Central India.</p><p>The reptiles of Japan present this peculiarity, that while the Batrachian and Chelonian orders exhibit several species identical with those of Europe <hi rend="italic">(Rana esculenta</hi> and <hi rend="italic">temporaria, Hyla arborea, Emys vulgaris,</hi> &amp;c.), the Saurian and Ophidian groups seem to consist of species alto</p><p>gether unknown in Europe. However, we know as yet but in part, for the Japanese species hitherto collected comprise, in addition to the genus <hi rend="italic">Hydrophis,</hi> merely three species of <hi rend="italic">coluber,</hi> two of <hi rend="italic">Tropidonotus,</hi> and a single <hi rend="italic">Trigonocephalus.</hi></p><p>The island of Ceylon, though not extremely remote from the coast of Coromandel, produces several serpents not known in continental India, such as <hi rend="italic">Tortrix maculata, Calamaria scytale, Lycodon caripatus,</hi> and two species of <hi rend="italic">Trigonocephalus,— Trig, hypnale</hi> and <hi rend="italic">nigromαrginatus.</hi> It is along the Ceylonese shores that we first perceive certain species of the genus <hi rend="italic">Hydrophis,</hi> those singular snakes which dwell exclusively in the sea, and occur from the island in question over all the intertropical marine waters east of Malabar, and as far as Polynesia The number of Ophidian species which inhabit the Gangetic Peninsula, without spreading into the great islands of the Indian Archipelago, is limited. Such, however, are <hi rend="italic">Tortrix eryx, Coronellα Russelii</hi> and <hi rend="italic">οctolineara,</hi> several species of <hi rend="italic">Coluber</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Lycodorι, Dipsas rrigοnara,</hi> several kinds of <hi rend="italic">Tropidonotus, Elaps trimaculatus,</hi> and some vipers. The great islands themselves, with their smaller dependencies, are regarded by M. Schlegel as presenting a most interesting field for the study of zoological geography, and the observation of those local races, constituted by the diversities observable in apparently identical species placed in different localities. These islands are of the first rank as to size, situate within the tropics, covered by an abundant vegetation, and inhabited by innumerable tribes of living creatures of every class and kind. They are separated from each other by seas of no great breadth, yet sufficient to present, as matters are now constituted, an insurmountable barrier to the migration of the majority of species. Now when we find the same creatures inhabiting many different and distant islands having no communication with each other, we may reasonably infer that each insulated tract of land has borne its own inhabitants since the relations of our earth’s surface became as they now exist, and that the individuals of each species form in every island a family group, which will exhibit, when compared with the corresponding species in other islands, certain modifications produced by the disparities of their position. Experience has proved the accuracy of this assumption. It has not unfrequently happened, that the same species has been discovered to inhabit Sumatra, Java, Borneo, Timor, the Celebes, the Philippine Islands, and continental Asia, and in each locality has been observed to present some constant though extremely slight distinction. Now it would never do to regard these as so many distinct species. They are only local or climatic varieties, the origin of which may be obscure or incomprehensible (as are many things besides), but which we doubt not would show their identity, by each recognising the individuals of their kind, and by breeding together, could they be transported from one to another of their sea-girt isles. Innumerable examples of these climatic differences might be adduced, were we to extend our observations throughout the vast range of the animal kingdom ; but here a few examples from the reptile races must suffice. The <hi rend="italic">Najas</hi> from the isles of Sunda constantly differ in several characters from those of Bengal and the Philippine Islands. <hi rend="italic">Tortrix rufα</hi> from the Celebes is distinguishable from individuals of the same species from Bengal and Java, by the uniform tint of the back, and by two small spots upon the occiput. <hi rend="italic">Calamar oligodon</hi> of Java exhibits in Sumatra a difference in the dorsal tinting, and forms in Ceylon and the Philippine Islands a third local variety of great beauty. Analogous differences exist between the individuals of <hi rend="italic">Coronella baliοdeira</hi> of Java and Sumatra. <hi rend="italic">Lycodon hebe</hi> of Java is smaller in size, and not so pale in colour, as that same species in Bengal, while those from Timor are still more diminutive, and of darker hue. The</p></body></text></TEI>