<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-19T20:21:06Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>a rapid and limpid stream, whilst the houses of the city stretch themselves from it in both directions, and terminate in woody declivities. It is an astonishing pile of building, and contains some apartments of stupendous extent. The foundation and the lower part of the walls are obviously of Roman origin, whilst the upper part, and what may be called the keep, are as plainly the execution of the Moors, whose contrivances for shooting their arrows at the heads of assailants, without being themselves subject to annoyance, are in the most perfect preservation. Within this castle is a state-prison, which is well described by Le Sage in his Adventures of Gil Bias. A part of the building is used by the artillery department of government. The mint is below the castle, and furnished with all the machinery requisite for coining money, which is principally set in motion by water.</p><p>The cathedral of Segovia is one of the most complete specimens of the later Gothic style of architecture of any religious edifice in Spain. Excepting the antiquities of this celebrated city, the rest deserves little notice. The streets are crooked and narrow. Many of the houses are of wood, and most of them very dirty ; and in spite of the great trade carried on in wool by some individuals, an air of poverty pervades the mass of the inhabitants.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Segovia,</hi> a town of America, in Terra Firma, and in the province of Venezuela, situated on a river, near a very high mountain, where there are mines of gold. Long. 65. 30. W. Lat 8. 20. N.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Segovia,</hi> a town of Asia, in the island of Manilla, and one of the largest of the Philippines, situated at the north end of the island, 240 miles north of Manilla, and subject to Spain. Long. 120. 50. E. Lat. 18. 36. N.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Segovia, </hi><hi rend="italic">New,</hi> a town of North America, in New Spain, and in the audiencia of Guatimala, situated on the river Yare, on the confines of the province of Honduras. Long. 84. 30. W. Lat. 13. 25. N.</p><p>SEGRE, an arrondissement of the department of the Maine and Loire, in France, extending over 408<hi rend="superscript">2</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">3</hi> square miles. It is divided into six cantons, and these into seventy-seven communes, and in 1836 contained 58,109 inhabitants. The capital is a small town of the same name, with some trade in linen goods. Its population in 1836 amounted to 2130.</p><p>SEGREANT is the herald’s word for a griffin when drawn in a leaping position, and displaying his wings as if ready to fly.</p><p>SEGUE, in Italian music, is often found before <hi rend="italic">aria, alleluja, amen,</hi> and some others, to show that those portions or parts are to be sung immediately after the last note of that part over which it is written ; but if these words <hi rend="italic">si placet,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">ad libitum,</hi> are joined with it, it signifies that the portions may be sung or not at pleasure.</p><p>SEGUIDILLA, the Spanish name of a quick and ani- mated melody in - time, much used in Spain in singing and in dancing.</p><p>SEGURA, a city of Spain, the capital of a department of the same name, lying between La Mancha and Granada, in the province of Murcia Near to it rises the river Seguro, which traverses the whole province, and falls into the Mediterranean Sea about sixteen miles to the south-west of Alicant. The town is surrounded with walls, and is an episcopal see. It contains 820 houses, and 4000 inhabitants, who are mostly occupied in agriculture, producing wine, fruit, especially figs, and oil. Another town bears thé same name in the province of Zaragoza, and department of Da- roca. It stands on the river Xiloca, and contains 1800 inhabitants. There is also a Segura in the province of Guipus- coa, and department of St Sebastian, on the banks of the river Oria. It was once fortified, but its works have gone</p><p>to decay.</p><p>SEGWIN, a small territory in Northern Hindustan, situated between Nepaul and Bootan, about the 28th degree of north latitude, and extending along the banks of the river Teesta, which bounds it to the west. In 1792, when the Chinese invaded Nepaul, the rajah of Segwin submitted to become a subject of China ; and here accordingly the Chinese established a military post immediately adjoining the dominions of the East India Company in Bengal.</p><p>SEIGNIOR, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Signior,</hi> is, in its general signification, the same with lord, but is particularly used for the lord of the fee or of a manor, as seigneur among the feudists is he who grants a fee or benefit out of the land to another ; and the reason is, because, having granted away the use and profit of the land, the property or dominion he still retains in himself.</p><p>SEIGNIORAGE is a royalty or prerogative of the king, by which he claims an allowance of gold and silver brought in the mass to be exchanged for coin. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Coinage.</hi></p><p>SEIGNIORY is borrowed from the French <hi rend="italic">seigneurie, </hi>which means <hi rend="italic">dominatus, imperium, principatus,</hi> and signifies with us a manor or lordship, <hi rend="italic">seigniory de sokemans. Seigniory in gross</hi> seems to be the title of him who is not lord by means of any manor, but immediately in his own person ; as <hi rend="italic">tenure in capite,</hi> by which one holds of the king, as of his crown, is <hi rend="italic">seigniory in gross.</hi></p><p>SEINE, one of the departments of the north-eastern part of France, taking its name from the river which passes through it, and containing Paris, the capital of that mighty kingdom. As that city is the most important portion of the department, the account of it in this work comprehends what is most remarkable. It is on every side surrounded by the department of the Seine and Oise, and extends over 47,548 French hectares, equal to 167<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">6</hi> square miles, or 106,983 English acres. It is generally a level district, but intersected with some hills of inconsiderable height. The river Seine receives within the department the navigable river Marne, and the smaller streams of the Ourcq anil the Erould. The Canal of St Denis unites the Seine with the Oise ; and the Canal of Ourcq, which terminates in a reservoir between La Vilette and La Chapelle, supplies Paris with water, and being navigable, serves to maintain an intercourse between that city and the north of France. The canal is supplied with water from the small streams of the Grisette, the Mai, the Therouanne, and the Beuvronne. The soil is for the most part by nature poor and sandy, but brought to a highly productive state by the vast quantities of manure furnished by the capital, and by the high state of the cultivation, which is mostly garden husbandry, whose products find advantageous markets in the metropolis. There are still some woods preserved, but mostly for the purpose of ornament, and to serve for the recreation of the inhabitants of Paris. The woods of Boulogne and of Vincennes occupy together about six thousand English acres. It is divided into three arrondissements, eight cantons, and eighty-one communes. The population, which includes Paris, amounted in 1821 to 822,171, in 1831 to 935,108, and in 1836 to 1,106,891, of which 909,126 were within the city.</p><p>S<hi rend="smallcaps">eine</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Lower,</hi> a department of the north-west of France, formed out of those northern parts of Upper Normandy which were in ancient times distinguished as the Roumais, Bezin-Normandy, Caux, and Bray. It is bounded on the north by the sea, on the east by the departments of the Somme and of the Oise, on the south by Eure and Calvados, and on the west by the Channel. It is 2144¼ square miles in extent, and comprehends five arrondissements, fifty cantons, and 757 communes. The population amounted in 1836 to 720,525 persons, who mostly adhere to the Kυman Catholic church ; but among them are 55,000 Protestants, having two consistorial and 113 other churches.</p><p>The surface is generally level, but intersected by some hills of moderate height, mostly composed of chalk. To-</p></body></text></TEI>