<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r02-0307-01" facs="gri_33125011196389_0313.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>ROBERTSON</label>
(Dr William), one of the moſt celebrated hiſtorians of his age, was one of thoſe great characters whoſe private life, flowing in an even and unvaried ſtream, can afford no important information to the biographer, although his writings will be read to the lateſt poſterity with undiminiſhed pleaſure. He was born at the manſe of Borthwick in the year 1 721. His father was, at the time of his death, one of the miniſters of the Old Grey Friars church in Edinburgh, which the Doctor came afterwards to ſupply. In 1743 he was licenced preacher, and placed in the pariſh of Glads-muir in 1744 ; whence, in τ 758, he was tranſlated to Lady Yeſter’s pariſh in Edinburgh. In 1761, on the death of Principal Goldie, he was elected principal of the university of Edinburgh, and appointed one of the miniſters of the Old Grey Friars church. About this period he received the degree of Doctor of Divinity, and was appointed hiltoriographer to his majeſty for Scotland, and one of his majeſty’s chaplains for that kingdom.</p><p>We find it not eafy to aſeertain at what period were firſt unfolded the great and Angular talents which de-ſtined Dr Robertſon to be one of the firſt writers that reſcued this iſland from the reproach of not having any good hiſtorians. . We are, however, aſſured, that betöre the publication or any of his literary performances,</p>
<pb xml:id="eb03-16-r02-0308" facs="gri_33125011196389_0314.tif"/>
<p>even from his firſt appearance in public life, his abilities had begun to attract the.notice of obſerving men ; and to his more intimate friends he diſcovered marks of ſuch high-minded ambition, as, ſeconded by thoſe abilities, could not have failed to carry him to the firſt honours of his profeſſion, in whatever ſphere he had been placed, and whatever oppoſition he might have had to combat.</p><p>The firſt theatre that offered for the diſplay of his talents, was the General Aſſembly of the Church of Scotland. It iε the annual meetings of this court that produce to view men who would otherwiſe remain in τhe deepeſt obſcuritv. Ί here the humble paſtor, whole lot has been call in the remoteſt corner of the Highland wilds, feels himſelf, for a time, on a footing of equality with the firſt citizen in the kingdom : he can there diſpute with him the prize of eloquence, the moſt flattering diſtinction to a liberal mind ; a diſtinction which is naturally ſought after with the greater eager-neſs in that aſſembly, as the ſimple eſtabliſhment of the church of Scotland has rendered it the only pre-eminence to which the greateſt part of its members can ever hope to attain.</p><p>From the moment Dr Robertſon firſt appeared in this aſſembly, he became the object of univerſal attention and applauſe. His ſpeeches were marked with the ſame manly and perſuaſive eloquence that diſtin-guiſhcs his hiſtorical compoſitions ; and it was obſerved by all, that while his young rivals in oratory contented themſelves with opening a cauſe, or delivering a ſtudied harangue, he ſhowed equal ability to ſtart objections, to anſwer, or to reply ; and that even his moſt unpremeditated eſſuſions were not unadorned with thoſe harmonious and ſeemingly meaſured periods, which have been ſo much admired in his works of labour and reflection. He ſoon came to be conſidered as the ableſt ſupporter of the cauſe he choſe to eſpouſe, and was now the unrivalled leader of one of the great parties which have long divided the church of which he was a member.</p><p>When we reflect upon this circumſtance, and conſider how much mankind are the ſame in every ſociety, we ſhall be the leſs ſurpriſed to find, in the literary works of Dr Robertſon, an acquaintance with the human heart, and a knowledge of the world, which we look for in vain in other hiſtorians. The man who has ſpent his life in the difficult taſlc of conducting the deliberations of a popular aſſembly, in regulating the paſſions, the interdis, the prejudices, of a numerous faction, has advantages over the pedant, or mere man of letters, which no ability, no ſtudy, no ſecond-hand information, can ever compenſate.</p><p>The firſt work which extended the Doctor’s reputation beyond the walls of the general aſſembly, was a ſermon preached at Edinburgh before the ſociety for propagating Chriſtian knowledge, and afterwards publiſhed ; the ſubject of which was, ‘ The ſtate of the world at the appearance of Jeſus Chriſt.’ The ingenuity with which a number of detached circumſtances are there collected, and ſhown to tend to one Angle point, may perhaps rival the art which is ſo much admired in the b’ſhop of Meaux’s celebrated Univerſal Hiſtory.</p><p>This ſermon did great honour to the author ; and it is probably to the reputation he gained by it, that we</p><p>ought to attribute the unanimity with which he was called to be one of the miniſters of Edinburgh—an event which happened not long after, viz. in the year 1758. In 1759, he publiſhed, in two volumes quarto,</p><p>‘ The Hiſtory of Scotland, during the reigns of Queen Mary and of King James VI. till his Acceſſion to the Crown of England, wiſh a Review of the Scots Hiſtory previous to that period.’ This work in its ſtructure is one of the moſt complete of all modern hiſtories. It is not a dry jejune narrative of events, deſtitute of ornament ; nor is it a mere frothy relation, all glow and colouring. <hi rend="sup">r</hi> Ihe hiftoria∙.ι diſcovers a ſufficient ſtore of imagination to engage the reader’s attention, wiſh a due proportion of judgment to check the exuberance of fancy. The arrangtment of his work is admirable, and his deſcriptions are animated. His ſtyle is copious, nervous, and correct. He has diſplay ed conſummate ſkill in rendering ſuch paſſages of our hiſtory as are familiar to our recollection agreeable and entertaining. He has embelliſhed old materials with all the elegance of modern dreſs. He has very judſeiouſly avoided too circumſtantial a detail of trite facts. His narratives arc ſuccinct and ſpirited ; his reflections copious, frequent, and generally pertinent. His ſentiments reſpecting the guilt of Mary have indeed been warmly controverted by Meſſrs Tytler, Stuart, and Whitaker ; and the general opinion now ſeems to be, that their victory is complete.</p><p>1 hat victory, however, on the part of Whitaker, is ſullied by the acrimony with which he writes. Dr Robertſon was no rancorous or malignant enemy of the unfortunate queen. While relating, what he doubtleſs believed, he makes every poſſible allowance for Mary from the circumſtances in which ſhe was placed ; and his hiſtory will be read with pleaſure by candid men of all parties as long as the language in which it is com·, poſed ſhall continue to be underſtood.</p><p>In 1769, Dr Robertſon publiſhed, in three volumes quarto, The Hiſtory of the Reign of the Emperor Charles V. with a View of the Progreſs of Society in Europe, from the Subverſion of the Roman Empire to the beginning of the 16th century.—The vaſt and general importance of the period which this hiſtory compriſes, together with the reputation which our hi-ſtorian had deſervedly acquired, co-operated to raiſe ſuch high expectations in the public, that no work perhaps was ever more impatiently wiſhed for, or peruſed « with greater avidity. The firſt volume (which is a preliminary one, containing the progreſs of ſociety in Europe, as mentioned in the title) is a very valuable part of the work ; for it ſerves not only as a key to the pages that follow, but may be conſidered as a general introduction to the ſtudy of hiſtory in that period in which the ſeveral powers of Europe were formed into one great political ſyſtem, in which each took a ſtation, wherein it has ſince remained (till within a very few years at leaſt) with leſs alterations than could have been expected, after the ſhocks occaſioned by ſo many internal revolutions, and ſo many foreign wars. Of the hiſtory itſelf, it may be ſufficient to obſerve, that it is juſtly ranked among the capital pieces of hiſtorical excellence. There is an elegance of expreſſion, a depth of diſcernment, and a correctneſs of judgment, which do honour to the hiſtorian. The characters are inimitably penned. They are not contraſted by a ſtudied antitheſis, but by an oppoſition which reſults from a</p>
<pb xml:id="eb03-16-r02-0309" facs="gri_33125011196389_0315.tif"/>
<p>very acute and penetrating inſight into the real merits of each character, fairly deduced from the ſeveral circumſtances of his conduct exemplified in the hiſtory. For this work the Doctor got L.45oo Sterling.</p><p>In 1779, -^ <hi rend="sup">r</hi> Robertſon publiſhed The Hiſtory of America, in two volumes quarto. This celebrated work may be conſidered with great propriety as a lequel to the preceding hiſtory. From the cloſe of the 15th centuι^y we date the moſt ſplendid era in the annals t&gt;f modern times. Diſeoveries were then made, the influence of which deſeended to poſterity ; and events happened that gave a new direction to the ſpirit of nations.</p><p>To the inhabitants of Europe, America was in every reſpect a new world. There the face of the earth changed its appearance. The plants and trees and animals were ſtrange ; and nature ſeemed no longer the ſame. A continent opened that appeared to have recently come ſrom the hands of the Creator, and which ſhowed lakes, rivers, and mountains, on a grander ſcale, and the vegetable kingdom in greater magnificence, than in the other quarters of the globe ; but the animal tribes in a ſtate of degradation, few in number, degenerated in kind, imperfect, and unfiniſhed. The human ſpecies in the earlieſt ſtage of its progreſs, vaſt and numerous nations in the rudeſt form of the ſavage ſtate which philoſophers have contemplated, and two great empires in the loweſt degree of civilization which any records have tranſmitted to our review, preſented to the philoſophic eye at this period the moſt fruitful ſubject of ſpeculation that was to be found in the annals of hiſtory.</p><p>The diſeovery of the New World, moreover, was not only a curious ſpcctacle to the philoſopher, but, by the change which it effected, an intereſting ſpectacle to the human race. When Columbus ſet ſail for unknown lands, he little expected that he was to make a revolution in the ſyſtem of human affairs, and to form the deſtiny of Europe for ages to come. d he importance and celebrity therefore of the ſubject had attracted the attention of philoſophers and hiſtorians. Views and ſketches of the new world had been given by able writers, and ſplendid portions of the American ſtory had been adorned with all the beauties of eloquence. But, prior to the appearance of Dr Robertſon’s hiſtory, no author had beſtowed the mature and profound inveſti-gation which ſuch a ſubject required, or had finiſhed, upon a regular plan, that complete narration and perfect whole which it is the province of the hiſtorian to tranſmit to poſterity. And as the ſubject upon which our author entered was grand, his execution was naaſterly. The character of his former works was immediately diſeerned in it. They had been read with uncommon admiration. When the Hiſtory of Scotland was firſt publiſhed, and the author altogether unknown, Lord Cheſterſield pronounced it to be equal in eloquence and beauty to the productions of Livy, the pu-reſt and moſt claflical of all the Roman hiſtorians. His literary reputation was not confined to his own country : the teſtimony of Europe was ſoon added to the voice of Britain. It may be mentioned, indeed, as the characteriſtic quality of our author’s manner, that he poſſeſſed in no common degree that ſupported elevation which is ſuitable to compoſitions of the higher claſs ; and, in his Hiſtory of America, he diſplayed that hap</p><p>py union of ſtrength and grace which becomes the majeſty of the hiſtoric muſe. In the fourth book of his firſt volume, which contains a deſcription of America when firſt diſcovered, and a philoſophſeal inquiry into the manners and policy of its ancient inhabitants, he diſ-plays, moreover, ſo much patient inveſtigation and found philoſophy, abounds in ſuch beautiful or intereſting deſcription, and exhibits ſuch variety and copiouſneſs of elegant writing, that future times will probably refer to it as that part of his works which gives the beſt idea of his genius, and is the moſt finiſhed of all his productions.</p><p>In 1787 appeared a tranſlation of the Abbé Clavi-gero’s Hiſtory of Mexico ; in which work the author threw out various reflections, tending in ſeveral inſtan-ces to impeach the credit of Dr Robertſon’s Hiſtory of America. This attack induced our learned hiſtorian to reviſe his work, and to inquire into the truth of the charges brought againſt it by the hiſtorian of New-Spain : and this he appears to have done with a becoming attention to the importance of the facts that are controverted, and to the common intereſts of truth. The reſult he publiſhed in 1788, under the title of Additions and Corrections to the former Editions of Dr Robertſon’s Hiſtory of America.—In many of the diſputed paſſages, he fully anſwered the Abbé Clavige-ro, and vindicated himſelf : in others he candidly ſub-mitted to correction, and thus gave additional value to his own work.</p><p>The literary labours of Dr Robertſon appear to have been terminated in 1791 by the publication of An Hiſtorical Diſquiſition concerning the Knowledge which the Ancients had of Tndia, and the Progreſs of Trade with that Country prior to the Diſeovery of the Paſſage to it by the Cape of Good Hope ; with an Appendix, containing Obſervations on the Civil Polity, the Laws, and Judicial Proceedings, the Arts, the Sciences, and Religious Inſtitutions of the Indians.— The perufal of Major RennelΓs Memoir, for illuſtrating his map of Hindoſtan, ſuggeſted to Dr Robertſon the deſign of examining more fully than he had done, in his Hiſtory of America, into the knowledge which the ancients had of India, and of conſidering what is certain, what is obſcure, and what is fabulous, in their accounts of that remote country. Of his various performances, this is not that of which the deſign is the moſt extenſive, or the execution the moſt elaborate ; but in this hiſtorical diſquiſition we perceive the ſame patient aſſiduity in collecting his materials, the ſame diſcernment in arranging them, the ſame perſpicuity of narrative, and the ſame power of illuſtration, which ſo eminently diſtinguiſh his other writings, and which have long rendered them the delight of the Britiſh reader at home and an honour to Britiſh literature abroad.</p><p>A truly uſeful life Dr Robertſon cloſed on the nth of June 1793, at Grange-Houſe, near Edinburgh, after a lingering illneſs, which he endured with exemplary fortitude and reſignation. It may be truly obſerved of him, that no man lived more reſpected, or died more ſincerely lamented. Indefatigable in his literary re-ſearches, and poſſeſſing from nature a found and vigorous underſtanding, he acquired a ſtore of uſeful knowledge, which afforded ample ſcope for the exertion of his extraordinary abilities, and raiſed him to the moſt diſtinguiſhed eminence ix» the republic of letters. As ∙</p>
<pb xml:id="eb03-16-r02-0310" facs="gri_33125011196389_0316.tif"/>
<p>a miniſter of the goſpel, he was a ſaithful paſtor, and juſtly merited the eſteem and veneration of his flock. In a word, he may be pronounced to be one of the moſt perfect characters of the age ; and his name will be a laſting honour to the iſland that gave him birth. His converſation was cheerful, entertaining, and inſtruc-tive ; his manners affable, pleaſing, and endearing.</p><p>Dr Robertſon left three ſons and two daughters. The eldeſt ſon is procurator for the church of Scotland, and an advocate. The other two are officers in the army ; and one of them diſtinguiſhed himſelf under Lord Cornwallis in ſuch a manner as to command the warmeſt praiſe from that illuſtrious general.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>