<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r02-0247-03" facs="gri_33125011196389_0253.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>RIGOLL</label>
or Regals, a kind of muſical infiniment, conſiſting of ſeveral ſticks bound together, only ſeparated by beads. It is tolerably harmonious, being well ſtruck with a ball at the end of a ſtick. Such is the account which Graſſineau gives of this inſtrument. Skinner, upon the authority of an old Engliſh dictionary, represents it as a clavichord, or claricord ; poſſibly founding his opinion on the nature of the office of the tuner of the régals, who ſtill fubſiſts in the eſtabliſh-ment of the king’s chapel at St James’s, and whoſe bu-ſineſs is to keep the organ of the chapel royal in tune ; and not knowing that ſuch wind inſtruments as the organ need frequent tuning, as well as the clavichord and other ſtringed inſtruments. Sir Henry Spelman derives the word <hi rend="italic">rigoll</hi> from the Italian <hi rend="italic">Pιgabello,</hi> a muſical inſtrument, anciently uſed in churches inſtead of the organ. Walther, in his description of the regal, makes it to be a reed-work in an organ, with metal and alſo wooden pipes and bellows adapted to it. And he adds,, that the name of it is ſuppoſed to be own ng to its having been preſented by the inventor to ſome king.— From an account of the regal uſed in Germany, and other parts of Europe, it appears to conſiſt of pipes and keys on one ſide, and the bellows and wind-cheſt on the other. We may add, that Lord Bacon (Nat. Hilt, cent. ii. §. 102,) diſtinguiſhes between the regal and organ, in a manner which ſhows them to be inſtruments of the ſame claſs. Upon the whole, there is reaſon tα conclude, that the regal orrigoll was a pneumatic, and not a ſtringed inſtrument.</p><p>Merſennus relates, that the Flemings invented an in» ſtrugient, <hi rend="italic">les regales de bois,</hi> conſiſting of 17 cylindrical</p>
<pb xml:id="eb03-16-r02-0248" facs="gri_33125011196389_0254.tif"/>
<p>pieces of wood, decreaſing gradually in length, ſo as to produce a ſucceſſion of tones and ſemitones in the diatonic ſeries, which had keys, and was played on as a ſpinet ; the hint of which, he ſays, was taken from an inſtrument in uſe among the Turks, conſiſting of 12 wooden cylinders, of different lengths, ſtrung together, which being ſuſpended and ſtruck with a ſtick, having a ball at the end, produced muſic. Hawkins’s Hilt. Muſi vol. ii. p. 449.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>