<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r02-0320-03" facs="gri_33125011196389_0326.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>ROLL</label>
in manufactories, ſomething wound and folded up in a cylindrical form.</p><p>Few fluffs are made up in rolls, except ſatins, gaw-ſes, and crapes ; which are apt to break, and take plaits not eaſy to be got out, if folded otherwiſe. Ribbons, laces, gallons, and paduas of all kinds, are alſo thus rolled.</p><p>A roll of tobacco, is tobacco in the leaf, twiſted on the mill, and wound twiſt over twill about a ſtick or roller. A great deal of tobacco is ſold in America in rolls of various weights ; and it is not till its arrival in England, Spain, France, and Holland, that it is cut.</p><p>A roll of parchment, properly denotes the quantity of 60 ſhins.</p><p>The ancients made all their books up in the form of rolls ; and in Cicero’s time the libraries conſiſted wholly of ſuch rolls.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Roll, in law, ſigniſies a ſchedule or parchment</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Calves-head Roti,</hi> a roll in the two temples, in which every bencher is taxed yearly at 2 s. every barri-ſter at ί s. 6 d. and every gentleman under the bar at I s. to the cook and other officers of the houſe, in conſideration of a dinner of calves·heads provided in E after-term.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Muſter-RoLt,</hi> that in which are entered the ſoldiers of every troop, company, regiment, &amp;c. As ſoon as a ſoldier’s name is writtea down on the roll, it is death for him to deſert.</p><p><hi rend="italic">RoLLs∙Ojftce <hi rend="sub">i</hi></hi> is an office in Chancery-lane, London, appointed for the cuſtody of the rolls and records in chancery.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Maſter of the Rolls.</hi> See <hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps"> Master of the Rolls.</hi></hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Ruler-Roll,</hi> a ſchedule of parchment frequently ſew-ed or added to ſome part of a roll or record.</p><p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps"> Rolls</hi></hi> <hi rend="italic">of Parliament,</hi> are the manuſcript regiſters or rolls of the proceedings of our ancient parliaments, which before the invention of printing were all engroſs-ed on parchment, and proclaimed openly in every county. In theſe rolls are alſo contained a great many deciſions of difficult points of law, which were frequently in former times referred to the deciſion of that high court.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Roll, or</hi> <hi rend="italic">Roller,</hi> is alſo a piece of wood, iron, braſs, &amp;c. of a cylindrical form, uſed in the conſtruction of ſeveral machines, and in ſeveral works and manufactures.</p><p>Thus in the glaſs manufacture they have a running-roll, which is a thick cylinder of caſt braſs, which ſerves to conduct the melted glaſs to the end of the table on which large looking-glaſſes, &amp;c. are caſt.</p><p>Founders alſo uſe a roll to work the fand which they uſe in making their moulds.</p><p>The preſſes called <hi rend="italic">calendars,</hi> as ſerving to calendar fluffs withal, conſiſt, among other eſſential parts, of two rollers. It is alſo between the two rollers that the waves are given to ſilks, mohairs, and other fluffs proper to be tabbied.</p><p>Impreſſions from copper-plates are alſo taken by paſſing the plate and paper between two rollers. Sec <hi rend="italic">Rolling-preſs</hi> <hi rend="italic">PRINTING.</hi></p><p>Rolls, in flatting-mills, &amp;c. are two iron inſtruments of a cylindrical form, which ſerve to draw or ſtretch out plates of gold, ſilver, and other metals.</p><p>Rolls, in ſugar-works, are two large iron barrels which ſerve to bruiſe the canes, and to expreſs the juice. Theſe are caſt hollow, and their cavities are filled up with wood, the cylinders of which are properly the rollers.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>