<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r02-0242-05" facs="gri_33125011196389_0248.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>RIGGING</label> <hi rend="italic">oſα Ship,</hi> a general name given to all the ropes employed to ſupport the marts, and to extend or reduce the fails, or arrange them to the diſpoſition of the wind. The former, which are uſed to fuſtain the maſts, remain uſually in a fixed poſition, and are called <hi rend="italic">ftanding rigging;</hi> ſuch are the ſhrouds, ſtays, and back∙ltays. The latter, whoſe office is to manage the ſails, by communicating with various blocks or pulleys, ſituated in different places of the maſts, yards, ſhrouds, &amp;c. are comprehended in the general term of <hi rend="italic">running rigging ;</hi> ſuch are the braces, ſheets, haliards, clue-lines, brails, &amp;c.</p><p>In rigging a malt, the firſt thing uſually fixed upon its head is a circular w <hi rend="sup">r</hi> reath or rope, called the <hi rend="italic">gromet,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">collar,</hi> which is firmly beat down upon the top of the hounds. The intent of this is to prevent the ſhrouds from being fretted or worn by the treſtle-trees, or ſhoulders of the maſt ; after this are laid on the two pendants, ſrom whoſe lower ends the main or fore tackles are ſuſpended ; and next, the ſhrouds of the ſtarboard and larboard ſide, in pairs, alternately. The wiιole is covered by the ſtays, which are the largeſt ropes of the rigging.—When a yard is to be rigged, a gromet is alſo driven firſt on each of its extremities ; next to this are fitted on the horſes, the braces, and laſtly the lifts or top-ſail ſheet-blocks.</p><p>The principal objects to be conſidered in rigging a ſhip, appear to be ſtrength, convenience, and ſimpli-city : or, the properties of affording ſufficient ſecurity to the maſts,. yards, and ſails ; of arranging the whole machinery in the moſt advantageous manner, to ſu-ſtain the maſts, and facilitate the management of the ſails ; and of avoiding perplexity, and rejecting whatever is ſuperfluous or unneceſſary. The perfection of this art, then, corſſiſts in retaining all thoſe qualities, and in preſerving a judicious medium between them. See Ship-building.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>