<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r02-0250-02" facs="gri_33125011196389_0256.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>RIPHATH</label>
or Rip hat, ſecond ſon of Gomer, and grandſon of Japhet (Gen. x. 3. run <hi rend="italic">Riphatſ</hi> In moſt copies he is called <hi rend="italic">Diρhath</hi> in the Chronicles (1 Chr. i. 6. γ <hi rend="smallcaps"><hi rend="sup"> -</hi> &gt;b*t</hi> <hi rend="italic">Diρhαf).</hi> The reſemblance of the two Hebrew letters Ί <hi rend="italic">Reſh</hi> and π <hi rend="italic">Daleth</hi> is ſo much, that they are very often confounded. But, to the credit of the tranſlators of our Engliſh verſion be it ſaid, that in this inſtance, as well as in many others, they have reſtored the original reading, and rendered it Ri-phath. The learned are not agreed about the country that was peopled by the deſcendants of Riphath. The Chaldee and Arabic take it for France ; Euſebius for the country of the Sauromatæ ; the Chronicon Alex-andrinum for that of the Garamantæ ; Joſephus for Pa-phlagonia. Mela aſſures us, that anciently the people of this province were called <hi rend="italic">Riphatœi,</hi> or R <hi rend="sup">,</hi> .phaces ;</p><p>and in Bithynia, bordering upon Paphlagonia, may be found the river Rhebeus, a people called <hi rend="italic">Rhebantes,</hi> and a canton of the ſame name. Theſe reaſons have prevailed with Bochart to believe, that Riphath peopled Paphlagonia. Others think he peopled the Montes Riphei ; and this opinion ſeems the moſt reaſonable to us, becauſe the other ſons of Gomer peopled the northern countries towards Scythia, and beyond the Eux-ine ſea.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>