<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r02-0248-05" facs="gri_33125011196389_0254.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>RINGS</label>
. The antiquity of rings is known from Scripture and profane authors. Judah left his ring or ſignet w <hi rend="sup">τ</hi> ith Tamar (Gen. xxxviii. 18). When Pharaoh committed the government of all Egypt to Joſeph, he took his ring from his finger, and gave it to Joſeph (Gen. xli. 42). After the victory that the jſraelites obtained over the Midianites, they offered to the Lord the rings, the bracelets, and the golden necklaces, and the ear-rings, that they had taken from the enemy (Numb, xxxi. 50). The Iſraelitiſh women wore rings not only on their fingers, but alſo in their noſtrils and their ears. St James diſtinguiſhes a man of wealth and dignity by the ring of gold that he wore on his finger (James ii. 2). At the return of the prodigal ſon, his father orders him to be dreſſed in a new fuit of clothes, and to have a ring put upon his finger (Luke xv. 22). When the Lord threatened King Jeconiah with the utmoſt effects of his auger, he tells him, that though he wore the ſignet or ring upon his finger, yet he ſhould be torn off (Jer. xxii. 24 )</p><p>The ring was uſed chiefly to <hi rend="sup">,</hi> fεal with; and the Scripture generally puts it in the hands of princes and great perſons ; as the king of Egypt, Joſeph, Ahaz, Jezebel, King Ahaſuerus, his favourite Haman, Mordecai, who ſucceeded Haman in his dignity, King Darius ( 1 Kings xxi. 8. ; Eſther iii. Ίο, &amp;c. ; Dan. vi. 17). The patents and orders of theſe princes were ſealed with their rings or ſignets ; and it was this that ſecured to them their authority and reſpect. Sec the article Seal.</p><p><hi rend="italic">R iNG∙Bone.</hi> See Farr jer γ, Sect, xxxi.</p><p><hi rend="italic">R</hi> <hi rend="italic">∣</hi> <hi rend="italic">NG-0uſel,</hi> in ornithology, a ſpecies of T URDUS.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>