<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r02-0305-04" facs="gri_33125011196389_0311.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>ROBBERY</label>
the <hi rend="italic">rapina</hi> of the civilians, is the felonious and forcible taking, ſrom the perſon of another, of goods or money to any value, by violence or putting him in fear. 1. There muſt be a taking, otherwiſe it is no robbery. A mere attempt to rob was indeed held to be felony ſo late as Henry IVth’s time ; but afterwards it was taken to be only a miſdemeanour, and puniſhabie with fine and impriſonment ; till the ſtatute 7 Geo. II. c. 21. which makes it a felony (tranſportable for {'even years) unlawfully and malici-ouſly to aſſault another, with any offenſive weapon or inſtrument ;—or by menaces, or by other forcible or violent manner, to demand any money or goods ; — with a felonious intent to rob. If the thief, having once taken a purſe, returns it, ſtill it is a robbery : and ſo</p><p>it is whether the taking be ſtrictly from the perſon of another, or in his preſence only ; as where a robber by menaces and violence puts a man in fear, and drives away his lheep or his cattle before his face. 2. It is immaterial of what value the thing taken is: ä penny, as well as a pound thus forcibly extorted, makes a robbery. 3. Laſtly, the taking muſt be by force, or a previous putting in fear ; which makes the violation of the perſon more atrocious than privately ſtealing. For, according to the maxim of the civil law, “ <hi rend="italic">qui vi rapuit, fur improbior ejſe videtur. <hi rend="sup">f,</hi></hi> This previous violence, or putting in fear, is the criterion that diſtinguiſh-cs robbery ſrom other larcenies. For if one privately ſteals ſixpence from the perſon of another, and afterwards keeps it by putting him in fear, this is no robbery, for the fear is ſubſequent : «either is it capital as privately ſtealing, being under the value of twelve-pence. Not that it is indeed neceſſary, though uſual, to lay in the indictment that the robbery was committed by <hi rend="italic">putting in feα <hi rend="sup">r</hi> :</hi> it is ſufficient, if laid to be done by <hi rend="italic">violence.</hi> And when it is laid to be done by putting in ſear, this does not imply any great degree of terror <hi rend="sup">f</hi> ∙or affright in the party robbed : it is enough that ſo much force or threatening, by word or geſture, be uſed, "as might create an apprehenſion of danger, or induce a man to part with his property without or againſt his confient. Thus, if a man be knocked down without previous warning, and ſtripped of his property while ſenſeleſs, though ſtrictly he cannot be ſaid to be <hi rend="italic">put in jeαr <hi rend="sub">y</hi> -</hi> yet this is undoubtedly a robbery. Or, if a per</p><p>ſon with a ſword drawn begs an alms, and I give it him through miſtruſt and apprehenſion of violence, this is a felonious robbery. So if, under a pretence of ſale, a man forcibly extorts money ſrom another, neither ſhall this ſubterfuge avail him. But it is doubted, whether the forcing a higler, or other chapman, to ſell his wares, and giving him the full value of them, amounts to ſo heinous a crime as robbery.</p><p>This ſpecies of larceny is debarred of the benefit of clergy by ſtatute 23 Hen. VIII. c. 1. and other ſubſequent ſtatutes ; not indeed in general, but only when committed in a dwelling-houſe, or in or near the king’s highway. A robbery therefore in a diſtant field, or footpath, was not puniſhed with death ; but was open to the benefit of clergy, till the ſtatute 3 &amp; 4 W. and M. c. 9. which takes away clergy from both principals and acceſſories before the fact, in robbery, whereſoever committed. See Law, N <hi rend="sup">o</hi> clxxxvi. 3°∙ .</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>