<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r02-0321-01" facs="gri_33125011196389_0327.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>ROLLIN</label>
(Charles), a juſtly celebrated French writer, was the ſon of a cutler at Paris, and was born there on the 30th of January 1661. He ſtudied at the college Du Pleſſis, in which he obtained a burſary through the intereſt of a Benedictine monk of the White Mantle, whom he had ſerved at table, and who diſcovered in him ſome marks of genius. Here he acquired the regard of M. Gobinet, principal of that college, who had a particular eſteem for him. After having ſtudied humanity and philoſophy at the college of Du Pleſſis, he applied to divinity three years at the Sorbonne ; but he did not proſecute this ſtudy, and never roſe in the church higher than to the rank of a tonſured prieſt. He afterwards became profeſſor of rhetoric in the ſame college ; and, in 1688, ſucceeded Horſan, his maſter, as profeſſor of eloquence, in the royal college. No man. ever exerciſed the functions of it with greater eclat : he often made Latin orations, to celebrate the memorable events of the times ; and frequently accompanied them with poems, which were read and eſteemed by every body. In ‘69 4, he was choſen rector of the univerſity ; and continued in that office two years, which was then a great mark of diſtinction. By virtue of his office, he ſpoke the annual panegyric upon Louis XIV. He made many very "uſeful regulations in the univerſity ; and particularly revived the ſtudy of the Greek language, which was then much neglected. He ſubſtituted academical exerciſes in the place of tragedies ; and introduced the practice which had been formerly obſerved, of cauſing the ſtudents to get by heart paſſages of Scripture. He was a man of indefatigable attention ; and trained innumerable perſons, who did honour to the church, the ſtate, and the army. The firſt preſident Portail was phaſed one day to reproach Rollin in a jocular ſtrain, as if he exceeded even himſelf in doing buſineſs : to whom Rollin replied, with that plainneſs and ſincerity which was natural to him, “ It becomes you well, Sir, to reproach me with this ; it is this habit of labour in me which has diſtinguiſhed you in the place of</p><p>advocate-general, which has raiſed you to that of firſt preſident : you owe the greatneſs of your fortune to me.”</p><p>Upon the expiration of the rectorſliip, cardinal No-ailles engaged him to ſuperintend the ſtudies of his nephews, who were in the college of Laon ; and in this office he was agreeably employed, when, in 1699, he was with great reluctance made coadjutor to the principal of the college of Beauvais. This college was then a kind of deſert, inhabited by very few ſtudents, and without any manner of diſcipline : but Rollin’« great reputation and induſtry ſoon re-peopled it, and made it that flouriſhing ſociety it has ever ſince continued. In this ſituation he continued till 1712 ; when the war between the Jeſuits and the Janſeniſts drawing towards a criſis, he ſell a ſacriſice to the prevalence of the former. Father le Tellſer, the king’s conſeſſor, a furious agent of the Jeſuits, infuſed into his maſter prejudices againſt Rollin, whoſe connections with cardinal de Noailles would alone have ſufficed to have made him a Janſeniſt ; and on this account he loſt his ſhare in the principality of Beauvais. No man, however, could have loſt leſs in this than Rollin, who had every thine»· left him that was neceſſary to make him happy ; retirement, books, and enough to live on. He now began to be employed upon Quinctilian ; an author he juſtly valued, and ſaw neglected not without uueaſt-neſs. He retrenched in him whatever he thought rather curious than uſeful for the inſtruction of youth ; he placed ſummaries or contents at the head of each chapter ; and he accompanied the text with ſhort ſelect notes. His edition appeared in <hi rend="italic">1</hi> 7 ∙ 5, in 2 vols 12 mo, with an elegant preface, ſetting forth his method and views.</p><p>In 1710, the univerſity of Paris, willing to have a head ſuitable to the importance of their intereſts in the then critical conjuncture of affairs, choſe Rollin again rector : but he was diſplaced in about two months by a lettre de cachet. The univerſity had preſented to the parliament a petition, in which it proteſted againſt taking any part in the adjuſtment of the late diſputes; and their being congratulated in a public oration by Rollin on this ſtep, occaſioned the letter which ordered them to chooſe a rector of more moderation. Whatever the univerſity might ſuffer by the removal of Rollin, the public was probably a gainer ; for he now applied himſelf to compoſe his treatiſe upon the Manner of Studying and Teaching the Belles Lettres, which was publiſhed, two volumes in 1726, and two more in 1728, 8vo∙</p><p>This work has been juſtly eſteemed for the ſentiments of religion which animate its author, whoſe zeal for the public good prompted him to ſelect the choiceſt paſſages of Greek and Latin authors. The ſtyle is ſufficiently elegant, but the language on ſome occaſions is not remarkable ſor delicacy; and in the book altogether there is neither much order nor depth. The author has indeed ſpoken of common things agreeably, and has ſpoken as an orator on ſubjects which demanded the inveſtigation of the philoſopher. One can ſcarcely reduce any thing in him to principles.—For example, the three ſpecies of eloquence ; the ſimple, the temperate, and the ſublime, can ſcarcely be underſtood from him when we read that the one reſembles a frugal table; the ſecond abeautiful ruin, with green wood growing</p>
<pb xml:id="eb03-16-r02-0322" facs="gri_33125011196389_0328.tif"/>
<p>on its banks ; and the third, thunder and an impetuous liver which overthrows every thing that oppoſes it.</p><p>The work, however, has been exceedingly ſucceſsful, and juſtly ſo ; and its ſucceſs encouraged its author to undertake another work of equal uſe and entertainment ; his <hi rend="italic">Hillc&gt;ire Ancienne,</hi> &amp;c. or “ Ancient Hiſtory of the E-gyptians, Carthaginians, Aſſyrians, Babylonians, Medes and Perſians, Macedonians, and Greeks,” which he fi-niſhed in 13 vols 8vo. and publiſhed between 1730 and 1738. M. Voltaire, after having obſerved that Rollin was “ the firſt member of the univerſity of Paris who wrote French with dignity and correctneſs,” ſays of this work, that “ though the laſt volumes, which were written in too great a hurry, are not equal to the firſt, it is nevertheless the heft compilation that has yet appeared in any language ; becauſe it is ſeldom that compilers are eloquent, and Rollin was remarkably ſo.” This is perhaps ſaying too much. There are indeed in this work ſome paſſages very well handled ; but they are only ſuch as he had taken from the ancient authors, in doing juſtice to whom he was always very happy. The reader will eaſily diſcover in this work the lame attachment to religion, the ſame deſire for the public good, and the ſame love of virtue, which appears in that on the Belles Lettres. But it is to be lamented that his chronology is neither exact nor correſponding ; that he ſtates facts inaccurately ; that he has not ſufficiently examined the exaggerations of ancient hiſtorians ; that he often interrupts the moſt ſolemn narrations with mere trifles ; that his ſtyle is not uniform ; and this want oſ uniformity ariſes from his borrowing from writers of a modern date 43 or 50 pages at a time. Nothing can be more noble and more reſined than his reflections; but they are ſtrewed with too ſparing a hand, and want that lively and laconic turn ort account of which the hiſtorians of antiquity are read with ſo much pleaſure. He tranſgreſſes the rule which he himſelf had eſtabliſhed in his Treatiſe on Studies. “ The precepts which have a reſpect to manners (ſays he) ought, in order to make an impreſſion, to be ſhort and lively, and pointed like a dart. That is the moſt certain method of making them enter and remain on the mind.” There is a viſible negligence in his diction with regard to grammatical cuſtom, and the choice of his expreſſions, which he does not chooſe at all times with ſufficient taſte, although, on the whole, he writes well, and has preſerved himſelf free from many of the faults of modern authors. While the laſt volumes of his ancient hiſtory were printing, he publiſhed the firſt of his Roman Hiſtory; which he lived to carry on, through the eighth and into part of the ninth, to the war againſt the Cimbri, about 70 years before the battle of Actium. Mr Crevier, the worthy diſciple of Rollin, continued the hiſtory to the battle of Actium, which cloſes the tenth volume ; and has ſince completed the original plan of Rollin in 16 vols I2mo, which was to bring it down from the foundation of the city to the reign of Conſtantinc the Great. This hiſtory had not ſo great ſucceſs as his Ancient Hiſtory had. Indeed it is rather a moral and hiſtorical diſcourſe than a formal hiſtory ; for the author does little more than point out ſome more remarkable events, while he dwells with a ſort of prolixity on thoſe parts which furniſh him a free field for moralizing. It is alternately diffuſe and barren ; and the greateſt advantage of the work is, that there are ſeveral paſſage» from T.</p><p>Livy tranſlated with great elegance into Frecch, He alſo publiſhed A Latin Tranſlation of moſt of the Theological Writings relative to the diſputes of the Time« in which he lived. Rollin was one of the moſt zealous adherents of deacon Paris ; and before the iιιclofαre of the cemetery of St Medard, this diſtinguiſhed character might have been often ſeen praying at the foot of his tomb. This he confeſſes in his Letters. He publiſhed alſo Leſſer Pieces ; containing different Letters, Latin Harangues, Diſcourſes, Complimentary Addreſſes, &amp;c. Paris 1771, 2 vols. 12mo. A collection which might have been contained in one volume, by keeping in only the beſt pieces. It is notwithſtanding valuable for ſome good pieces which it contains, for the favourable opinion which it exhibits of ſolid probity, found reaſon, and the zeal of the author ſor the progreſs of virtue and the preſervr.tion of taſte. The Latin of RoUin is very correct, and much after the Ciceronian ſtyle, and embelliſhed with moſt judicious thoughts and agreeable images. Full of the reading of the ancients,, from which he brought quotations with as much propriety as plenty’, he expreſſed himſelf with much ſpirit and excellence. His Latin poems deſerve the ſame eulo-gium.</p><p>This excellent perſon died in 1741. He had been named by the king a member of the academy of in-ſcriptions and belles lettres in 1701 : but as he had not then brought the college of Beauvais into repute, and found he had more buſineſs upon his hands than was conſiſtent with a decent attendance upon the functions of an academician, he begged the privileges of a veteran, which were honourably granted him. Nevertheleſs, he maintained his connections with the academy, attended their aſſemblies as often as he could, laid the plan of his ancient hiſtory before them, and demanded an academician for his cenſor. Rollin was a man of an admirable compoſition ; very ingenious, conſummate in polite learning, of rigid morals, and eminently pious. He was rather too religious; his religion carrying him into the territories of ſuperſtition ; and he wanted nothing but a mixture of the philoſophic in his nature to make him a very perfect character. Nothing could be more benign, more pacific, more ſweet, more moderate, than Rollin’s temper. He ſhowed, it muſt be owned, ſome zeal ſor the cauſe of Janſeniſm ; but in all other reſpects he was exceedingly moderate. The celebrated poet Rouſſeau conceived ſuch a veneration for him, that he came out of baniſhment incognito to Paris, on purpoſe to viſit him and pay his reſpects to him. He looked upon his hiſtories, not only as the beſt models of the hiſtoric kind, but as a complete ſyſtem of politics and morals, and a moſt inſtructive ſchool for princes as well as ſubjects to learn all their duties in.</p><p>Inſtead of bluſhing at the lowneſs of his birth, Rollin on no occaſion heſitated to ſpeak of it. “ It is from the Cyclops’s ſhop (ſays he, in a Latin epigram to one of his friends, to whom he had ſent a ſmall ſword) that I have taken my flight towards Parnaſſus.” He was not, however, without ſome ſhare of vanity, eſpecially at hearing mention made of his writings, of which the well-timed praiſes of his adherents had given him a veιγ high opinion. He ſpoke without any diſſimulation what he thought ; and his opinions were leſs the effect of preſumption than of openneſs of heart. He was one <hi rend="italic">of</hi> thoſe mei» who are vain without any mixture of</p>
<pb xml:id="eb03-16-r02-0323" facs="gri_33125011196389_0329.tif"/>
<p>pride. Rollin ſpoke pretty well; but he had a greater readineſs of writing than ſpeakingt; and much more ſa-tisfaction might be derived from his works than from his ∙co∙nveι ſation. His name became famous throughout Europe ; ſeveral princes ſought the honour of his friendſhip. The duke of Cumberland and the prince-royal of Pruſſia (afterwards king) were among the lift of his admirers. This monarch honoured him with ſeveral letters ; in one of which he pays him the following compliment, “ Men of your character are fit companions for kings.” As to the literary merit of this author, it was, we ſuſpect, too much extolled in his own time, and has been too much undervalued in ours.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>