<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196348_0043.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-18-s06-0037-02" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>STROKING</label>,
or rubbing gently with the hand, a method which has been employed by ſome perſons for curing diſeaſes.</p><p>Mr Greatrakes or Greatrix, the famous Iriſh ſtroker, is ſaid to have performed many wonderful cures. He gives the following account of his diſcovery of this art, and of the ſucceſs with which he practiſed it “<note anchored="false" n="1" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>Brief Account of Mr. Valentine Greatrakes, London 1666, 4to.</p></note> About 1662 I had an impulse (says he), or a ſtrange perſuaſion in my own mind (of which I am not able to give any rational account to another), which did very frequently ſuggeſt to me, that there was bestowed on me the gift of curing the king’s evil; which, for the extraordinarineſs of it, I thought fit to conceal for ſome time : but at length I communicated this to my wife, and told her, that I did verily believe that God had given me the bleſſing of curing the king’s evil; for whether I were in private or public, ſleeping or waking, ſtill I had the ſame impulſe. But her reply to me was, that ſhe conceived this was a ſtrange imagination ; yet, to prove the contrary, a few days after there was one William Mather of Salterbridge in the pariſh of Lismore, who brought his ſon William to my house, desiring my wife to cure him, who was a perſon ready to afford her charity to her neighbours, according to her ſmall ſkill in chirurgery. On which my wife told me, there was one that had the king’s evil very grievouſly in the eyes, cheek, and throat ; whereupon I told her, that ſhe ſhould now ſee whether this were a bare fancy or imagination, as ſhe thought it, or the dictates of God’s Spirit on my heart. Then I laid my hands on the places affected, and prayed to God for Jeſus sake to heal him; and bid the parent two or three days afterwards to bring the child to me again, which accordingly he did; and I then saw the eye was almoſt quite whole; and the node, which was almoſt as big as a pullet’s egg, was ſuppurated ; and the throat ſtrangely amended ; and, to be brief (to God’s glory I ſpeak it) within a month diſcharged itself quite, and was perfectly healed, and ſo continues, God be praiſed.”</p><p>Then there came to him one Margaret Macſhane of Ballinecly, in the pariſh of Liſmore, who had been afflicted with the evil above ſeven years, in a much more violent degree ; and ſoon after, his fame increaſing, he cured the ſame diſeaſe in many other perſons for three years. He did not meddle all this time with any other diſtemper; till about the end of theſe three years, the ague growing epidemical, he found, as formerly, that there was bellowed on him the gift of curing that diſeaſe. He cured Colonel Phaire, of Cahirmony in the county of Corke, of an ague, and afterwards many other perſons of different diſtempers, by ſtroking ; ſo that his name was wonderfully cried up, as if ſome divine perſon had been sent from above. January 1665-6, he came over to England, at the requeſt of the earl of Orrery ; in order to cure the lady of the lord-viſcount Conway, of Ragley in Warwickſhire, who had for many years laboured under a moſt violent headache. He ſtaid at Ragley three weeks or a month ; and though he failed in his endeavours to relieve that lady, he cured vast numbers of people in thoſe parts and at Worceſter.</p><p>Though we are no friends to the marvellous, nor believe it poſſible that either the king’s evil or ague can be cured by ſtroking or friction of any kind, whether gentle or ſevere, we have no heſitation to acknowledge that many cures might be performed by Mr Greatrakes. Every reflecting perſon who reads the foregoing account which he gives of himſelf will ſee that he was an enthuſiaſt, and believed himſelf guided by a particular revelation ; and ſuch is the credulity of mankind, that his pretensions were readily admitted, and men crouded with eagerneſs to be relieved of their diſeaſes. But it is well known to phyſicians, that in many caſes the imagination has accompliſhed cures as wonderful as the force of medicine. It is owing chiefly to the influence of imagination that we have ſo many accounts from people of veracity of the wonderful effects of quack medicines. We are perfectly aſſured that theſe medicines, by their natural operation, can never produce the effects aſcribed to them ; for there is no kind of proportion between the medicine and the effect produced, and often no connection between the medicine and the diſeaſe.</p></div></body></text></TEI>