<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196348_0080.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-18-s06-0074-10" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SUPERSTITION</label>,
a word that has been uſed ſo indefinitely, that it is difficult to determine its preciſe meaning. From its reſemblance in sound to the Latin word <hi rend="italic">ſuperstes,</hi> “ a survivor," it is evidently derived from it, and different attempts have been made to trace their connection in lignification. Balbus, in the dialogue <hi rend="italic">De Natura Deorum</hi> of Cicero, ſays, that they who prayed and ſacrificed whole days that their children might <hi rend="italic">ſurvive</hi> them, were called ſuperstitious. Lactantius cenſures this etymology, and ſays they were not called ſuperſtitious who wiſhed that their children might ſurvive them (for this we all wiſh), but becauſe they who ſurvived their parents worſhipped their images. Others again ſay, that ſuperſtition is derived from <hi rend="italic">ſuperstes,</hi> becauſe it consiſted in considering the dead as if they were alive. But theſe etymologies are ſolely conjectural ; and we consider conjectures as abſurd in philology as we do in ſcience; they may miſlead, but are ſeldom of any benefit. The uſual meaning affixed to the word s <hi rend="italic">uperstition,</hi> both in the Latin and Engliſh languages, is ſo different from superst <hi rend="italic">es,</hi> that its change of meaning muſt be owing to ſome accident which it is in vain to inquire after. If we had not known that the word <hi rend="italic">paganus</hi> “ a pagan” was derived from <hi rend="italic">pagus</hi> “ a village,” becauſe the heathens in a certain period of the Chriſtian hiſtory lived in villages, the whims and fancies of etymologiſts would not have thrown much light on the ſubject.</p><p>Without labouring, from the aid of etymology, to define ſuperſtition, which is a word of a very extenſive ſignification, we will conſider to what objects it is applied ; and then, by obſerving what is common to them all, we ſhall be enabled to fix with ſome degree of precision the meaning of the term. We apply it to the idolatry of the heathens ;we apply it alſo to the Jews, who made the will of God of no effect by their traditions, and ſubſtituted ceremonies in place of the religion of their fathers. We ſay alſo that Chriſtians are guilty of ſuperſtition ; the Roman Catholics, who believe in tranſubſtantiation and in the efficacy of prayers to ſaints ; and thoſe Proteſtants who eſteem baptiſm and the Lord’s ſupper, and the punctual performance of other ceremonies, without regard to morality, as ſufficient to enfure ſalvation. Thoſe perſons alſo are reckoned ſuperſtitious who believe, without any evidence, that prophecies are ſtill uttered by the divine inſpiration, and that miracles are ſtill performed. The word is alſo extended to thoſe who believe in witchcraft, magic, and apparitions, or that the divine will is declared by omens or augury ; that the fortune of individuals can be affected by things indifferent, by things deemed lucky or unlucky, or that diſeaſes can be cured by words, charms, and incantations.</p><p>Through all the particulars which we have enumerated, there runs one general idea, the belief of what is falſe and contrary to reaſon. From this, however, we muſt not ſuppose that whatever is falſe and contrary to reaſon may be denominated ſuperſtition. We think that it is falſe and irrational to ſuppoſe that there ever lived on earth a race of men who walked on one leg, and had their eyes in their breaſt ; or that there were giants 90 feet high : yet we do not call the philoſopher who believes theſe chimeras ſuperſtitious, but credulous. Superſtition has always a reference to God, to religion, or to beings ſuperior to man. We do not however diſtinguiſh all falſe and irrational opinions in religion by the name of ſuperſtition. We do not, for inſtance, apply this name to the opinions which ſome of the ancients entertained, that God is the ſoul of the world, and that men are only portions of him ſeparated for a time, or that the ſoul after death lives ſucceſſively in different bodies. If we examine the ſubject with more attention, we ſhall diſcover that the foundation of ſuperſtition is ignorance of the moral attributes of God ; for we never ſay a man is ſuperſtitious for entertaining erroneous opinions of the natural attributes of God. Some of the Socinians have denied the preſcience of God ; and a French philoſopher has not only rejected the belief that He is a ſpirit, but has preſumed to ſay that he is compoſed of a ſpecies of cryſtals. The first of theſe opinions diſcovers very imperfect ideas of God, and the second is the height of impiety and abſurdity ; yet the<pb facs="gri_33125011196348_0081.tif" xml:id="eb03-18-s06-0075"/>
Socinians have not been accuſed of ſuperſtition, nor can this French philoſopher be ſuſpected of it. We do not call every falſe opinion concerning the unity or moral attributes of God by the name of ſuperſtition, as, for inſtance, the opinion which ſome ſceptics have ſupported, that God is not good ; for, as was mentioned before, ſuperſtition always involves the idea of credulity. It does not conſiſt in falſely denying that God posseſſes any particular moral attributes, but in believing more than what is true concerning them ; in forming mean, unworthy ideas of them ; in ſuppoſing that he is guided by blind paſſion like mankind, and enjoins upon his creatures commandments which are irrational and abſurd.</p><p>As ſuperſtition ariſes from ignorance and credulity in the underſtanding, ſo it has alſo a ſeat in the paſſions. Fear has been commonly conſidered as the paſſion of the human mind from which it chiefly derives its origin; and there is no doubt that more ſuperſtition has ariſen from fear united with ignorance and credulity than from any other paſſion. Yet it would certainly be improper to exclude all other paſſions. We cannot account for the ſuperſtition of the Egyptians, without ſuppoſing that much of it aroſe from gratitude. They worſhipped the Nile, becauſe it diſtributed fertility and abundance over the land of Egypt ; and they worſhipped ſome animals, merely becauſe they prevented the increaſe of other animals which were noxious. Thus they adored the ibis, becauſe it deſtroyed the eggs of the crocodile.</p><p>Having thus endeavoured to analyze the ideas comprehended under the word ſuperſtition, we may ſum them up in a few words. It reſpects God and beings ſuperior to man, and extends to our religious opinions, worſhip, and practices ; and may be defined <hi rend="italic">abſurd opinions and actions arising from mean and defective ideas of the moral attributes of God.</hi> Let us apply this definition to the different ſpecies of ſuperstition already mentioned.</p><p>But before entering upon this application, it may be proper to obſerve, that ſuperſtition involves the idea of a blameable inattention to reaſon, or a credulity ariſing from an indolence of underſtanding. We generally make a diſtinction between the imperfect opinions which a ſavage, from the neceſſary effects of his ſituation, forms of the attributes of God, and thoſe which civilized nations entertain. We ſay the ſavage is ignorant, and we aſcribe his ignorance to his ſituation ; but we call the Roman Catholic ſuperſtitious, and we blame him for not having thoſe juſt ideas of God which he might have obtained by opening his Bible, or by the exerciſe of his underſtanding in the favourable ſituation in which he is placed. Superſtition then does not originate ſo much from the natural weakneſs of the human underſtanding, as from a miſapplication or a neglect of it<note anchored="true" n="1" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="smallcaps">(a)</hi> We do not pretend to ſay that this is the ſenſe in which ſuperſtition is always uſed, becauſe it is often uſed improperly.</p></note> <hi rend="smallcaps">(a).</hi></p><p>We cannot therefore with any propriety apply the name sup <hi rend="italic">erstition</hi> to polytheiſm in general ; for what all the ancient philoſophers, after much ſtudy and reflection, concluded to be true, could never proceed from credulity and inattention, but from their ſituation. We ſpeak very properly, however, when we call idolatry by the name of ſuperſtition ; becauſe there is no man ſo devoid of underſtanding as not to be capable of diſcovering, that a piece of metal, or wood, or ſtone, can neither hear nor anſwer petitions. <hi rend="italic">Superstition</hi> was a name which the ancient philoſophers gave to thoſe who entertained mean opinions of the gods, or did fooliſh things to obtain their favour. According to Theophraſtus, the ſuperſtitious man is one who, having waſhed his hands, and ſprinkled himſelf all round, leaves the temple with a laurel leaf in his mouth, with which he walks about the whole day. Or, if a weaſel ſhould croſs the road, he will not advance a step till he has thrown three ſtones over the road. If he finds a ſerpent in his house, he rears a place of devotion on the ſpot. He purifies his houſe often, will not sit upon a grave, nor touch a dead perſon. He is anxious about the interpretation of his dreams, will not offer a ſacrifice unleſs his wife go along with him, or, if ſhe is engaged, he takes the nurſe and the little children. He purifies himſelf with onions ; and when he ſees a mad or an epileptic perſon, he ſpits in their boſom. Such was the character of ſuperſtition in the days of Theophraſtus. All theſe whimſical ceremonies were done to prevent miſchief, and to avert the wrath of the gods;and therefore perfectly correſpond with the definition given above.</p><p>It is only neceſſary to conſider a little the ſuperſtitious opinions and practices among Jews and Christians, to be ſenſible that they have all ariſen from mean and abſurd ideas of the moral attributes of God ; for they have generally entertained noble opinions of his natural attributes. The Jews conſidered God as a partial Being, who had a predilection for their nation in preference to all others, and preferred external homage and ceremony to moral purity. If the Roman Catholics think consiſtently, they muſt eſteem God as a Being who can be prevailed upon by the importunity of one dead man to aſſiſt another, or as a Being whoſe patience would be fatigued with hearing prayers conſtantly. Hence their practice of praying to saints. They in effect believe, however they may deceive themſelves, that God is unjuſt, or they could not believe tranſubſtantiation ; for it ſuppoſes that God can give commands directly contrary to thoſe principles of belief with which he has endued the human mind. They conſider a ſtrict adherence to a variety of ceremonies, to forms, to pomp, and ſhow, as essential to the worſhip of God : this is treating God as a vainglorious Being. They thought it their duty to extirpate heretics : this was ſuppoſing God a cruel and revengeful Being. Even among Proteſtants, we are ſorry to ſay, a great deal of ſuperſtition remains : we have not yet learned to conſider God as a ſpirit, who is to be worſhiped in ſpirit and in truth, as a pure moral benevolent Being ; and hence ariſes all the ſuperſtitious practices which prevail among us.</p><p>Beſides thoſe ſuperſtitious opinions and practices which entirely reſpect our duty to God, there are others which may be termed <hi rend="italic">vulgar ſuperstitions.</hi> Theſe alſo ariſe from imperfect and mean ideas oſ the moral attributes oſ God. To believe vulgar prophecies, which are always the effuſions of madneſs or knavery, is to ſuppoſe that God, who has drawn a veil over futurity, and only delivers prophecies to accomplish ſome great moral purpoſe, ſometimes gives them for no purpoſe at all, or to gratify idle curiosity, or to diſcloſe ſuch a knowledge of what is to happen as is inconſiſtent with the free agency of man and the moral adminiſtration of the world. Nor is it leſs ſuperſtitious to believe in vulgar miracles. To believe in them, is to believe that God ſuſpends the laws of nature for the moſt trivial purpoſes, or to countenance fraud and worldly ambition : it is to receive the moſt extraordinary facts upon the moſt unſatisfactory evidence. The belief of witchcraft, of apparitions, and the ſecond ſight, may be reſolved into the ſame principle. To ſuppoſe that God would communicate the power of doing miſchief, and of controuling his laws, to any being merely for gratifying their own paſſions, is unworthy of God. The belief of apparitions is equally inconſiſtent with the goodneſs of God (ſee <hi rend="smallcaps">Spectre).</hi> The ſame objection riſes againſt the ſecond ſight as againſt the belief of vulgar prophecies, and may also be extended to omens, to aſtrology, to things lucky and unlucky, to fortune-telling, &amp;c. As to the different devices and charms for preventing and curing diſorders, they reſemble in every reſpect falſe miracles.<pb facs="gri_33125011196348_0082.tif" xml:id="eb03-18-s06-0076"/>
A judicious hiſtory of ſuperſtition would be a curious and entertaining work, and would exhibit the human character in a remarkable point of view. Superſtition is moſt prevalent among men of weak and uncultivated minds ; it is more frequent in the female sex than among men ; and abounds more in the rude than in the refined ſtages of society. The general features of it have been the ſame in all ages ; but it aſſumes certain peculiarities according to the diverſity of character of different nations. It gained admiſsion into the ſcience of medicine at an early period. He who was endowed with ſuperior genius and knowledge was reckoned a magician. Dr Bartolo was ſeized by the inquiſition at Rome in the laſt century, becauſe he unexpectedly cured a nobleman of the gout.<note anchored="false" n="2" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>Manchester Transactions, vol. iii.</p></note> Diſeaſes were imputed to faſcination, and hundreds of poor wretches were dragged to the ſtake ſor being acceſſary to them. Mercatus, phyſician to Philip II. of Spain, a writer of uncommon accuracy and information, appears ſtrongly inclined to deny the exiſtence of faſcinatory diſeaſes : but he is conſtrained to acknowledge them for two reaſons ; 1st <hi rend="italic">,</hi> Becauſe the inquiſition had decided in favour of their reality; 2dly, Becauſe he had feen a very beautiful woman break a ſteel-mirror to pieces, and blaſt ſome trees by a ſingle glance of her eyes.</p><p>As the opinions concerning the cauſe of diſeaſes were superſtitious, thoſe concerning the method of curing them were not leſs ſo. In the Odyssey we read of a cure performed by a ſong. Joſephus relates, that he ſaw a certain Jew, named <hi rend="italic">Eleazar,</hi> draw the devil out of an old woman’s noſtrils by the application of Solomon’s ſeal to her noſe in preſence of the Emperor Veſpaſian. Many different kinds of applications were uſed for expelling the devil. Flagellation ſometimes succeeded admirably ; purgatives and antiſpaſmodics were other modes of discharging him. Dr Mynſight cured ſeveral bewitched perſons with a plaſter of aſſafœtida. How the aſſafoetida was ſo efficacious, was much disputed. Some thought the devil might conſider ſo vile an application as an inſult, and run off in a paſſion ; but others very ſagely obſerved, that as devils are ſuppoſed to have eyes and ears, it is probable they may have noses too.</p><p>Nor was it only in medicine theſe ſuperſtitious opinions were entertained ; they prevailed alſo in natural philoſophy. The pernicious effects in mines, which we now know are occaſioned by noxious air, were confidently imputed to the demons of the mine. Even Van Helmont, Bodinus, Strozza, and Luther, attributed thunder and meteors to the devil. Chemiſts were employed for centuries in ſearch of the philoſopher’s ſtone, with which they were to do miracles. It was a common queſtion among philoſophers in the laſt century, whether the imagination could move external objects ? A queſtion generally decided in the affirmative.</p><p>Though ſuperſtition be generally the mark of a weak mind, ſuch is the infirmity of human nature, that we find many inſtances of it among men of the moſt ſublime genius and moſt enlightened minds. Socrates believed that he was guided by a demon. Lord Bacon believed in witchcraft ; and relates that he was cured of warts by rubbing them with a piece of lard with the ſkin on, and then nailing it with the fat towards the fun on the poſt of a chamber window facing the ſun. Henry IV. one of the moſt illuſtrious of monarchs, was very uneaſy before his aſſaſſination on account of ſome prophecies<note anchored="true" n="3" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>* Memoirs of Sully.</p></note> *. Sully declares, that one of the conſiderations that kept him faithfal to his maſter in the moſt unpromiſing ſtate of his affairs, was a prediction of La Broſſe, that Henry would make his fortune<note anchored="true" n="4" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>* Ibid.</p></note> *. The aſtrologer Morin directed Cardinal Richelieu’s motions in ſome of his journeys<note anchored="true" n="5" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>* Boyle, Art. Morin.</p></note> *. The enlightened Cudworth defended prophecies in general, and called thoſe who oppoſed the belief of witchcraft by the name of <hi rend="italic">atheists;</hi> and the predictions of Rice Evans have been ſupported in the preſent century by the celebrated names ol W <hi rend="italic">arburton and Jortin.</hi> DrHoffman, the father of the Modern Theory and Practice of Medicine, in a diſſertation publiſhed in the large edition of his works in 1747, ſays, that the devil can raiſe ſtorms, produce insects, and act upon the animal ſpirits and imagination ; and, in fine, that he is an <hi rend="italic">excellent optician and natural philοsopher</hi> on account of his long experience. Dr Johnſon, the leviathan of literature, is ſuppoſed to have believed the ſecond light.</p><p>With respect to the effects of ſuperſtition on the human mind, they are indeed deplorable. It chains down the underſtanding, and links it into the moſt abject and fordid ſtate, and keeps it under the dominion of fear, and ſometimes of cruelty. Where once it takes posseſſion, it has a tendency to become extreme, and generally becomes ſo intolerable, that men of reflection and learning conſpire its deſtruction. The Chriſtian religion gave a violent ſhock to the heathen ſuperſtition ; the reformation in a great meaſure demoliſhed the ſuperſtition of the church of Rome ; and the ſuperſtition which remained among Proteſtants after their ſeparation from that church has been gradually yielding to the influence of enlightened reaſon, or to the bold and daring attacks of infidelity and deism. We behold the proſpect of its ruins with pleaſure, and thank the deiſts for their zeal ; but it is from the firm hope that the religion of Jeſus will ariſe in all its beauty and ſimple majeſty, and be admired and reſpected as it deserves : for mean and contemptible as ſuperſtition certainly is, we would rather ſee men do what they reckon their duty from ſuperſtitious principles, than ſee anarchy and vice prevail, even though attended with all the knowledge and liberality of ſentiment which deiſm and infidelity can inſpire.</p></div></body></text></TEI>