<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196348_0073.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-18-s06-0067-02" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SUIT</label>,
is uſed in different ſenſes ; as, 1. Suit of court, or ſuit-ſervice, which is an attendance the tenant owes to his lord’s court. 2. Suit-covenant, where a perſon has covenanted to do ſervice in the court of the lord. 3. Suit- custom, which is where one and his anceſtors have owed suit time out of mind. 4, It is used for a petition to the king or any person of dignity, where a lord diſtrains his tenant for suit, and none is due. In this caſe, the party may have an attachment againſt him to appear in the king’s court.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Suit,</hi> in law, the ſame with action. The Romans introduced pretty early ſet forms for actions and ſuits into their law, after the example of the Greeks ; and made it a rule, that each injury ſhould be redreſſed by its proper remedy only. <hi rend="italic">“ Actiones,</hi> (ſay the Pandects) <hi rend="italic">compositae ſunt quilus inter se homines diſceptarent, quas actiones ne populus prout vellet institueret, certas solemneſque esſe voluerunt."</hi> The forms of theſe actions were originally preferred in the books of the pontifical college as choice and ineſtimable ſecrets, till one Cneius Flavius, the ſecretary of Appius Claudius, ſtole a copy and publiſhed them to the people. The concealment was ridiculous :<note anchored="false" n="1" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>Blackst Comments.</p></note> but the eſtabliſhment of ſome ſtandard was undoubtedly neceſſary to fix the true ſtate of a question of right ; left, in a long and arbitrary proceſs, it might be ſhifted continually, and be at length no longer diſcernible. Or, as Cicero expreſſes it, “ <hi rend="italic">ſunt jura, ſunt formula, de omnibus rebus constitutae, ne quis ant in genere injuria, aut in ratione actionis, errare poſsit. Expresſae enim ſunt ex uniuſcujuſque damno, dolore, incommodo, calamitate, injuria, publicae a praetore formula, ad quas privata lis accommodatur."</hi> And in the ſame manner Bracton, ſpeaking of the original writs upon which all our actions are founded, declares them to be fixed and immutable, unleſs by authority of parliament. And all the modern legiſlators of Europe have found it expedient, from the ſame reaſons, to fall into the ſame or a ſimilar method. In England, the ſeveral ſuits, or remedial inſtruments of juſtice, are, from the ſubject of them, diſtnguiſhed into three kinds ; actions <hi rend="italic">perſonal, real,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">mixed.</hi></p><p>Perſonal actions are ſuch whereby a man claims a debt, or perſonal duty, or damages in lieu thereof ; and likewise whereby a man claims a ſatisfaction in damages for ſome injury done to his perſon or property. The former are ſaid to be founded upon contracts, the latter upon t <hi rend="italic">orts</hi> or wrongs : and they are the ſame which the civil law calls <hi rend="italic">“ actiones in perſonam, qua adverſus eum intenduntur qui ex contractu vel delicto obligatus est aliquid dare vel concedere."</hi> Of the former nature are all actions upon debt or promiſes ; of the latter are all actions of treſpaſſes, nuisances, aſſaults, defamatory words, and the like.</p><p>Real actions (or, as they are called in the Mirror, <hi rend="italic">ſeodal actions),</hi> which concern real property only, are ſuch whereby the plaintiff, here called the <hi rend="italic">demandant,</hi> claims title to have any lands or tenements, rents, commons, or other hereditaments, in fee-ſimple, fee-tail, or for term of life. By theſe actions formerly all diſputes concerning real eſtates were decided ; but they are now pretty generally laid aſide in practice, upon account of the great nicety required in their management, and the inconvenient length of their proceſs ; a much more expeditious method of trying titles being ſince introduced, by other actions perſonal and mixed.</p><p>Mixed actions are ſuits partaking of the mixture of the other two, wherein ſome real property is demanded, and alſo perſonal damages for a wrong suſtained. As for inſtance, an action of waſte : which is brought by him who hath the inheritance, in remainder or reversion, againſt the tenant for life, who hath committed waſte therein, to recover not only the land wasted, which would make it merely a real action ; but alſo treble damages, in purſuance of the ſtatute of Glouceſter, which is a perſonal recompenſe ; and ſo both, being joined together, denominate it a <hi rend="italic">mixed actiοn.</hi><pb facs="gri_33125011196348_0074.tif" xml:id="eb03-18-s06-0068"/>
The orderly parts of a suit are theſe: 1. The original <hi rend="italic">writ.</hi> 2. The <hi rend="italic">proceſs.</hi> 3. The <hi rend="italic">pleadings.</hi> 4. The <hi rend="italic">issue</hi> or demurrer. 5. The <hi rend="italic">trial.</hi> 6. The <hi rend="italic">judgment,</hi> and its incidents. 7. The proceedings in nature of <hi rend="italic">appeals.</hi> 8. The <hi rend="italic">execution.</hi> See theſe articles.</p></div></body></text></TEI>