<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="encyclopediabrit21newyrich_raw_0645.jp2" type="entry" xml:id="eb09-21-s02-0619-05" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SEDITION</label>
in Roman law was considered as <hi rend="italic">majestas</hi> or treason. In English law it is a very elastic term, including offences ranging from libel to <hi rend="smallcaps">Treason</hi> <hi rend="italic">(q.v.).</hi> It is rarely used except in its adjectival form, <hi rend="italic">e.g.,</hi> seditious libel, seditious meeting, or seditious conspiracy. “As to sedition itself,” says Mr Justice Stephen, “I do not think that any such offence is known to English law ” <hi rend="italic">(Hist. Crim. Law,</hi> vol. ii. chap, xxiv.).<note anchored="true" n="1" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The word “sedition” occurs, however, in 40 and 41 Vict. c. 21, s. 40.</p></note> The same high authority lays down the law in the following terms, which were substantially adopted by the Draft Criminal Code Commissioners.</p><p>“ Every one commits a misdemeanour who publishes verbally or otherwise any words or any document with a seditious intention. If the matter so published consists of words spoken, the offence is called the speaking of seditious words. If the matter so published is contained in anything capable of being a libel, the offence is called the publication of a seditious libel. Every one commits a misdemeanour who agrees with any other person or persons to do any act for the furtherance of any seditious intention common to both or all of them. Such an offence is called a seditious conspiracy. A seditious intention is an intention to bring into hatred or contempt or to excite disaffection against the person of Her Majesty, her heirs and successors, or the Government and constitution of the</p></div></body></text></TEI>