<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="encyclopediabrit21newyrich_raw_0409.jp2" type="entry" xml:id="eb09-21-s02-0387-06" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SCHÄSSBURG</label>
(Hung. <hi rend="italic">Segesvár),</hi> chief town of the Transylvanian county of Nagy-Küküllö, Hungary, stands on the river Nagy-Küküllö, 24 miles east-south-east of Maros-Vásárhely, in 46° 10' N. lat., 24° 47' E. long. It consists of two parts,—the one which formerly served as a fortress on the top of a hill, and the other in the valley below,—the two being connected by a covered passage. Schässburg is the seat of various public offices and of a district court of justice; its other institutions include a Franciscan convent, a Protestant upper gymnasium, a teachers’ institute and seminary, two savings banks, a free library, hospital, barracks, &amp;c. As a station on the eastern system of the Hungarian State Railways, Schässburg has a good woollen and linen trade, as well as exports of wine and fruit. Among its principal buildings an old Gothic church and the lofty town-hall are specially worthy of mention. The population in 1884 amounted to 8810, the majority being Germans (Saxons), and the remainder Roumanians and Hungarians.</p><p>Schässburg was founded by Saxon colonists at the end of the 12th century ; its Latin name was <hi rend="italic">Castrum Sex.</hi> The most important event in its history was the battle on the 31st July 1849, in which the Hungarian army under Bern was defeated by the overwhelming numbers of the Russian General Lüders. The great national poet, Petöfi, was last seen, and is generally believed to have met his end, in this engagement.</p></div></body></text></TEI>