<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r02-0236-07"
                facs="gri_33125011196389_0242.tif" type="entry">

                <p><label>RIDICULE</label>, in matters of literature, is that ſpecies of writing
                    which excites contempt with laughter.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">ridiculous,</hi> however, differs from the <hi
                        rend="italic"> riſible,</hi> (ſee RISIBLE. ) A riſible object produceth an
                    emotion of laughter merely: a ridiculous object is improper as well as riſible;
                    and produceth a mixed emotion, which is vented by a laugh of deriſion or ſcorn.</p>
                <p>Burleſque, though a great engine of ridicule, is not confined to that ſubject;
                    for it is clearly diſtinguilh-able into burleſque that excites laughter merely,
                    and</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r02-0237" facs="gri_33125011196389_0243.tif"/>
                <p>burleſque that provokes deriſion or ridicule. A grave ſubject in which there is
                    no impropriety, may be brought down by a certain colouring ſo as to be riſi-ble;
                    which is the caſe of <hi rend="italic">Virgil Traveſlie,</hi> and alſo the
                    caſe of the <hi rend="italic">Secchia Repita;</hi> the authors laugh firſt, in
                    order to make their readers laugh. The <hi rend="italic">Lutrin</hi><note
                        anchored="false" place="margin" type="authorial"><hi rend="italic"
                            >Elements of Criticism.</hi></note> is a burleſque poem of the other
                    ſort, laying hold of a low and trifling incident, to expoſe the luxury,
                    indolence, and contentious ſpirit of a ſet of monks. Boileau, the author, gives
                    a ridiculous air to the ſubject, by dreſſing it in the heroic ſtyle, and
                    affecting to conſider it as of the utmoſt dignity and importance. In a
                    compoſition of this kind, no image profeſſedly ludicrous ought to find quarter,
                    becauſe ſuch images deſtroy the contraſt; and accordingly the author ſhows
                    always the grave face, and never once betrays a ſmile.</p>
                <p>Though the burleſque that aims at ridicule produces its effects by elevating the
                    ſtyle far above the ſubject, yet it has limits beyond which the elevation ought
                    not to be carried: the poet, conſulting the imagination of his readers, ought to
                    confine himſelf to ſuch images as are lively and readily apprehended: a ſtrained
                    elevation, ſoaring above an ordinary reach of fancy, makes not a pleaſant
                    impreſſion: the reader, fatigued with being always upon the ſtretch, is ſoon
                    diſguſted; and, if he perſevere, becomes thoughtleſs and indifferent. — Further,
                    a fiction gives no pleaſure unleſs it be painted in colours ſo lively as to
                    produce ſome perception of reality; which never can be done effectually where
                    the images are formed with labour or difficulty. For theſe reaſons, we cannot
                    avoid condemning the <hi rend="italic">Batrachomuo-machia,</hi> ſaid to be the
                    compoſition of Homer: it is beyond the power of imagination to form a clear and
                    lively image of frogs and mice acting with the dignity of the higheſt of our
                    ſpecies; nor can we form a conception of the reality of ſuch an action, in any
                    manner ſo diſtinct as to intereſt our affections even in the ſlighteſt degree.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Rape of the Lock</hi> is of a character clearly
                    diſtin-guiſhable- from thoſe now mentioned; it is not properly a burleſque
                    performance, but what may rather be termed <hi rend="italic">an heroi-comical
                        poem</hi> : it treats a gay and familiar ſubject with pleaſantry, and with
                    a moderate degree of dignity: the author puts not on a maſk like Boileau, nor
                    profeſſes to make us laugh like Taſſoni. The <hi rend="italic">Rape</hi> <hi rend="italic">of</hi> <hi rend="italic">the Lock</hi> is a genteel ſpecies of writing, leſs ſtrained
                    than thoſe mentioned; and is pleaſant or ludicrous without having ridicule for
                    its chief aim; giving way, however, to ridicule where it ariſes naturally from a
                    particular character, ſuch as that of Sir Plume. Addi-ſon’s <hi rend="italic">Spectator</hi><note anchored="true" place="margin" type="authorial"
                            >N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 102.</note>, upon the exerciſe of the fan, is
                    extremely gay and ludicrous, reſembling in its ſubject the <hi rend="italic">Rape of the Lock.</hi></p>
                <p>There remains to ſhow, by examples, the manner of treating ſubjects ſo as to
                    give them a ridiculous appearance.</p>
                <p>Il ne dit jamais, je vous donne, mais, je vous prete le bon jour. <hi
                        rend="italic"> Moliere.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Orleans.</hi> I know him to be valiant.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Conſlable.</hi> I was told that by one that knows him better
                    than you.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Orleans.</hi> What’s he?</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Conſtable.</hi> Marry, he told me ſo himſelf; and he ſaid,
                    he ear’d not who knew it. <hi rend="italic">Henry</hi> V. <hi rend="italic">Shakeſpeare.</hi></p>
                <p>He never broke any man’s head but his own, and that was againſt a poſt when he
                    was drunk. <hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Millamont.</hi> Sententious Mirabel! prithee don’t look with
                    that violent and inflexible wiſe face, like Solomon at the dividing of the child
                    in an old tapeſtry-hanging.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Way of the World.</hi></p>
                <p>A true critic, in the peruſal of a book, is like a dog at a feaſt, whoſe
                    thoughts and ſtomach are wholly ſet upon what the gueſts fling away, and
                    conſequently is apt to ſnarl moſt when there are the fewtſt bones.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Tale of a Tub.</hi></p>
                <p>In the following inſtances, the ridicule ariſes from abſurd conceptions in the
                    perſons introduced.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Maſcarille.</hi> Te ſouvient-il, vicomte, de cette
                    demi-lune, que nous emportames ſur les enemis au ſiege d’Afras?</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Jodelet.</hi> Que veux-tu dire avec ta demi-lune? c’etoit
                    bien une lune tout entiere.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Molière, les Precieuſes Ridicules, ſc.</hi> 11.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Slander.</hi> I came yonder at Eaton to marry Mrs Anne Page;
                    and ſhe’s a great lubberly boy.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Page.</hi> Upon my life then you took the wrong—</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Slander.</hi> What need you tell me that? I think ſo when I
                    took a boy for a girl: if I had been married to him, for all he was in woman’s
                    apparel, I would not have had him. <hi rend="italic">Merry Wives of Windſor.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Valentine.</hi> Your bleſſing, Sir.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Sir Sampſon.</hi> You’ve had it already, Sir: I think I ſent
                    it you to-day in a bill for four thouſand pound; a great deal of money, brother
                    Foreſight-</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Foreſight.</hi> Ay, indeed, Sir Sampſon, a great deal of
                    money for a young man; I wonder what he can do with it. <hi rend="italic">Love
                        for Love,</hi> act 2. ſc. 7.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Millament.</hi> I nauſeate walking; 'tis a country
                    di-verſion; I lothe the country, and every thing that relates to it.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Sir Wilfull.</hi> Indeed, hah! look ye, look ye, you do?
                    nay, ’tis like you may——here are choice of paſtimes here in town, as plays and
                    the like; that muſt be confeſs’d, indeed.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Millament.</hi> Ah l’etourdie! I hate the town too.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Sir Wilſull.</hi> Dear heart, that’s much——hah! that</p>
                <p>you ſhould hate ’em both! hah! ’tis like you may; there are ſome can’t reliſh
                    the town, and others can’t</p>
                <p>away with the country——’tis like you may be one of</p>
                <p>theſe, Couſin. <hi rend="italic">Way of the World,</hi> act 4. ſc. 4.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Lord Froth.</hi> I aſſure you, Sir Paul, I laugh at nobody’s
                    jeſts but my own, or a lady’s: I aſſure you, Sir Paul.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Briſk.</hi> How? how, my Lord? what, affront my wit? Let me
                    periſh, do I never lay any thing worthy to be laugh’d at?</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Lord Froth.</hi> O foy, don’t miſapprehend me, I don’t ſay
                    fo, for I often ſmile at your conceptions. But there is nothing more unbecoming
                    a man of quality than to laugh; ’tis ſuch a vulgar expreſſion of the paſ-ſions!
                    every body can laugh. Then eſpecially to laugh at the jeſt of an inferior
                    perſon, or when any body elſe of the lame quality does not laugh with one;
                    ridiculous! To be pleas’d with what pleaſes the crowd! Now, when I laugh. I
                    always laugh alone.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Double Dealer,</hi> act 1. ſc. 4.</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r02-0238" facs="gri_33125011196389_0244.tif"/>
                <p>So ſharp-fighted is pride in biemiſhes, and ſo willing to be gratified, that it
                    takes up with the very flighteſt improprieties: filch as a blunder by a
                    foreigner in ſpeaking our language, eſpecially if the blunder can bear a ſenſe
                    that reflects on the ſpeaker:</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Quickly.</hi> The young man is an honeſt man.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Caius.</hi> What ſhall de honeſt man do in my cloſet ? dere
                    is no honeſt man dat ſhall come in my cloſet</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Merry Wives of Windfor.</hi></p>
                <p>Love ſpeeches are finely ridiculed in the following ρa∩'age,</p>
                <p>Quoth he, My faith as adamantine,</p>
                <p>As chains of deſtiny, I’ll maintain ;</p>
                <p>True as Apollo ever ſpoke,</p>
                <p>Or oracle from heart of oak ;</p>
                <p>And if you’ll give my flame but vent,</p>
                <p>Now in cloſe hugger-mugger pent,</p>
                <p>And ſhine upon me but benignly,</p>
                <p>With that one and that other pigſney,</p>
                <p>The ſun and day ſhall ſooner part Than love, or you, ſhake off my heart ;</p>
                <p>The fun, that ſhall no more diſpenſe His own, but your bright influence :</p>
                <p>I’ll carve your name on barks of trees,</p>
                <p>With true love-knots and flouriſhes ;</p>
                <p>That ſhall infuſe eternal ſpring,</p>
                <p>And everlaſting flouriſhing :</p>
                <p>Drink every letter on’t in ſtum,</p>
                <p>And make it briſh champaign become.</p>
                <p>Where’er you tread, your foot ſhall ſet The primroſe and the violet ;</p>
                <p>AH ſpices, perfumes, and ſweet powders,</p>
                <p>Shall borrow from your breath their odours ; Nature her charter ſhall renew And
                    take all lives of things from you j The world depend upon your eye,</p>
                <p>And, when you frown upon it, die.</p>
                <p>Only our loves ſhall ſtill ſurvive,</p>
                <p>New-worlds and natures to out-live ;</p>
                <p>And, like to herald’s moons, remain All creſcents, without change or wane.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Hudιbras, part</hi> 2. <hi rend="italic">canto</hi> I.</p>
                <p>Thoſe who have a talent for ridicule, which is ſeldom united with a taſte for
                    delicate and refined beauties, are quick-ſighted in improprieties ; and theſe
                    they eagerly graſp, in order to gratiſy their favourite propen-ſity. Perfons
                    galled are provoked to maintain that ridicule is improper for grave ſubjects.
                    Subjects really grave are by no means fit for ridicule ; but then it is urged
                    againſt them, that, when called in queſtion whether a certain ſubject be really
                    grave, ridicule is the only means of determining the controverſy. Hence a
                    celebrated queſtion, Whether ridicule be or be not a teſt of truth ?</p>
                <p>On one ſide, it is obſerved, that the objects of ridicule are falſehood,
                    incongruity, impropriety, or turpitude of certain kinds : but as the object of
                    every excited paſſion muſt be examined by reaſon, before we can determine
                    whether it be proper or improper ; ſo ridicule muſt, apparently at leaſt,
                    eſtabliſh the truth of the improprieties deſigned to excite the paſſion of
                    contempt. Hence it comes in to the aid of argument and reaſon, when its
                    impreſſions on the imagination are conſiſtent with the nature of things; but
                    when it ſtrikes the fancy</p>
                <p>and affections with fictitious images, it becomes the in-ſtrument of deceit. But
                    however ridicule may impreſs the idea of apparent turpitude or falſehood in the
                    imagination, yet ſtill reaſon remains the ſupreme judge ; and thus ridicule can
                    never be the final teſt or touch-ſtone of truth and falſehood.</p>
                <p>On the other ſide, it is contended that ridicule is not a ſubject of reaſoning,
                    but of ſenſe or taſte ; (ſee and compare the articles Risible and Congrui-ty.
                    Stating the queſtion, then, in more accurate terms, Whether the ſenſe of
                    ridicule be the proper teſt for diſtinguiſhing ridiculous objects from what are
                    not ſo ? they proceed thus : No perſon doubts that our fenſe of beauty is the
                    true teſt of what is beautiful; and our ſenſe of grandeur, of what is great or
                    ſublime. Is it more doubtful whether our ſenſe of ridicule be the true teſt of
                    what is ridiculous ? It is not only the true teſt, but indeed the only teſt ;
                    for this ſubject comes not, more than beauty or grandeur, under the province of
                    reaſon. If any ſubject, by the influence of faſhion or cuſtom, have acquired a
                    degree of vene* ration to which naturally it is not entitled, what are the
                    proper means for wiping off the artificial colouring, and diſplaying the ſubject
                    in its true light ? A man of true taſte fees the ſubject without diſguiſe ; but
                    if he heſitate, let him apply the teſt of ridicule, which ſeparates it from its
                    artificial connections, and expoſes it naked with all its native
                    improprieties.—But it is urged, that the graveſt and moſt ſerious matters may be
                    ſet in a ridiculous light. Hardly ſo; for where an object is neither rifible nor
                    improper, it lies not open in any quarter to an attack from ridicule.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
