<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>eb09-r01</title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Latin Christianity. The Reformation, inspired by the same energy of resuscitated life as the Renaissance, assisted by the same engines of the printing-press and paper, using the same apparatus of scholarship, criticism, literary skill, being in truth another manifestation of the same world-movement under a diverse form, now posed itself as an irreconcilable antagonist to Renaissance Italy. It would be difficult to draw any comparison between German and Italian humanists to the disparagement of the former. Reuchlin was no less learned than Pico; Melanchthon no less humane than Ficino ; Erasmus no less witty, and far more trenchant, than Petrarch; Ulrich von Hutten no less humorous than Folengo; Paracelsus no less fantastically learned than Cardano. But the cause in which German intellect and will were enlisted was so different that it is difficult not to make a formal separation between that movement which evolved culture in Italy and that which restored religion in Germany, establishing the freedom of intelligence in the one sphere and the freedom of the conscience in the other. The truth is that the Reformation was the Teutonic Renaissance. It was the emancipation of the reason on a line neglected by the Italians, more important indeed in its political consequences, more Aveighty in its bearing on rationalistic developments than the Italian Renaissance, but none the less an outcome of the same ground-influences. We have already in this century reached a point at which, in spite of stubborn Protestant dogmatism and bitter Catholic reaction, we can perceive how the ultimate affranchisement of man will be the work of both.</p><p>The German Reformation Avas incapable of propagating <hi rend="sup">:</hi> itself in Italy, chiefly for the reason that the intellectual forces which it represented and employed had already found specific outlet in that country. It Avas not in the nature of the Italians, sceptical and paganized by the Revival, to be keenly interested about questions which seemed to revive the scholastic disputes of the Middle Ages. It was not in their external conditions, suffering as they were from invasions, enthralled by despots, to use the Reformation as a lever for political revolution. Yet Avhen a tumultuary army of so-called Lutherans sacked Rome in 1527 no sober thinker doubted that a new agent had appeared in Europe Avhich Avould alter the destinies of the peninsula. The Renaissance Avas virtually closed, so far as it concerned Italy, Avhen Clement VII. and Charles V. struck their compact at Bologna in 1530. This compact proclaimed the principle of monarchical absolutism, supported by papal authority, itself monarchically absolute, which influenced Europe until the outbreak of the Revolution. A reaction immediately set in both against the Renaissance and the Reformation. The council of Trent, opened in 1545 and closed in 1563, decreed a formal purgation of the church, affirmed the fundamental doctrines of Catholicism, strengthened the papal supremacy, and inaugurated that movement of resistance Avhich is knoAAm as the Counter-Reformation. The complex onward effort of the modern nations, expressing itself in Italy as Renaissance, in Germany as Reformation, had aroused the forces of conservatism. The four main instruments of the reaction Avere the papacy, Avhich had done so much by its sympathy with the revival to promote the humanistic spirit it now dreaded, the strength of Spain, and tAvo Spanish institutions planted on Roman soil—the Inquisition and the Order of Jesus. The principle contended for and established by this reaction was absolutism as opposed to freedom—monarchical absolutism, papal absolutism, the suppression of energies liberated by the Renaissance and Reformation. The partial triumph of this principle Avas secure, inasmuch as the majority of established poAvers in church and state felt threatened bv the revolutionary opinions afloat in Europe. Renaissance and Reformatioi were, moreover, already at strife. Both too Avere spiritua and elastic tendencies toAvard progress, ideals rather thai solid organisms.</p><p>The part played by Spain in this period of history wa determined in large measure by external circumstance The Spaniards became one nation by the conquest o Granada and the union of the crowns of Castile ant Aragon. The Avar of national aggrandizement, being ii its nature a crusade, inflamed the religious enthusiasm o the people. It Avas folloAved by the expulsion of Jews ant Moors, and by the establishment of the Inquisition on ! solid basis, Avith powers formidable to the freedom of al Spaniards from the peasant to the throne. These fact explain the decisive action of the Spanish nation on th&lt; side of Catholic conservatism, and help us to understam Avhy their brilliant achievements in the field of culture during the 16th century Avere speedily folloAved by stag nation. It will be Avell, in dealing Avith the Renaissance in Spain, to touch first upon the arts and literature, an&lt; then to consider those qualities of character in actio! Avhereby the nation most distinguished itself from the res of Europe. Architecture in Spain, emerging from the Gothic stage, developed an Early Renaissance style o beAvildering richness by adopting elements of Arabic an&lt; Moorish decoration. Sculpture exhibited realistic vigou of indubitably native stamp; and the minor plastic craft Avere cultivated Avith success on lines of striking originality Painting greAv from a homely stock, until the work o Velazquez showed that Spanish masters in this branch Aver fully abreast of their Italian compeers and contemporaries To dwell here upon the Italianizing versifiers, moralists, an&lt; pastoral romancers who attempted to refine the vernacula of the <hi rend="italic">Romancero</hi>  Avould be superfluous. They are mainl; noticeable as proving that certain coteries in Spain wer Avilling to accept the Italian Renaissance. But the rea force of the people Avas not in this courtly literary style It expressed itself at last in the monumental Avork of <hi rend="italic">Do¡ Quixote,</hi>  which places Cervantes beside Rabelais, Ariosto and Shakespeare as one of the four supreme exponents o the Renaissance. The affectations of decadent chivaln disappeared before its humour; the lineaments of a nobh nation, animated by the youth of modern Europe emerging from the Middle Ages, were portrayed in its enduring pic tures of human experience. The Spanish drama, mean Avhile, untrammelled by those false canons of pseudo classic taste which fettered the theatre in Italy ant afterAvards in France, rose to an eminence in the hands o: Lope de Vega and Calderon Avhich only the English, ant the English only in the masterpieces of three or four play Avrights, can rival. Camoeus, in the <hi rend="italic">Lusiad,</hi>  if we may here group Portugal with Spain, was the first modern poel to compose an epic on a purely modern theme, vying Avitl: Virgil, but not bending to pedantic rules, and breathing the spirit of the age of heroic adventures and-almost fabu lous discoveries into his melodious numbers. What has chiefly to be noted regarding the achievements of the Spanish race in arts and letters at this epoch is then potent national originality. The revival of learning pro duced in Spain no slavish imitation as it did in Italy, nc formal humanism, and, it may be added, very little ol fruitful scholarship. The Renaissance here, as in England, displayed essential qualities of intellectual freedom, delight in life, exultation over rediscovered earth and man. Tin note of Renaissance Avork in Germany Avas still Gothic This we feel in the penetrative earnestness of Dürer, in the homeliness of Hans Sachs, in the grotesque humoui of <hi rend="italic">Eidenspiegel</hi>  and the <hi rend="italic">Narrenschif,</hi>  the sombre pregnancy of the Faust legend, the almost stolid mastery of Holbein. It lay not in the German genius to escape from the pre</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>