<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ſelf on the throne. Such of the ſenators as were in the faction he found already in their places (for he had given them private notice to be there early) ; and the reſt, being ſummoned to aſſemble in Tarquin’s name, made what haſte they could to the appointed place, thinking that Servius was dead, ſince Tarquin aſſumed the title and functions of king. When they were all aſſembled, Tarquin made a long ſpeech, reviling his father-in-law, and repeating the invectives againſt him, which he had ſo oſten uttered, calling him a {lave, an uſurper, a favourer of the populace, and an enemy to the ſenate and patricians. When he was yet ſpeaking, Servius arrived ; and, raſhly giving way to the motions cſ his courage, without conſidering his ſtrength, drew near the throne, to pull Tarquin down ſrom it. This raiſed a great noiſe in the aſſembly, which drew the people into the temple ; but nobody ventured to part the two rivals. Tarquin therefore, being more ſtrong and vigorous, ſeized the old man by the waiſt, and, hurrying him through the temple, threw him down from the top of the ſteps into the forum. The king, who was grievouſly wounded, raiſed himſelf up with ſome difficulty : but all his friends had abandoned him ; only two or three of the people, touched with compaſſion, lent him their arms to conduct him to his palace.</p><p>As they were leading him on ſo ſlowly, the cruel Tullia appeared in the forum, whither ſhe had haſtened in her chariot on the firſt report of what had paſſed in the ſenate. She found her huſhand on the top of the ſteps of the temple ; and, tranſported with joy, was the firſt who ſaluted him king. The example was immediately followed by the ſenators of Tarquin’s party. Nor was this enough for the unnatural daughter : ſhe took aſide her huſhand, and ſuggeſted to him, that he would never be ſafe ſo long as the uſurper of his crown was alive. Hereupon Tarquin inſtantly diſpatched ſome of his domeſtics to take away the remains of the unfortunate king’s life. The orders ſor the wicked parricide were no ſooner given than Tullia mounted her diariot again, with an air of triumph, to return home. The way to her houſe was through a narrow ſtreet, called <hi rend="italic">vicus cyρrιus,</hi>  or the <hi rend="italic">goodJlreet.</hi>  There the aſſaſſins had left the king’s body, which was ſtill panting. At this fight, the charioteer, ſtruck with horror, checked his horſes, and made a ſtop : but Tullia forccd him to go on ; and the blood of the father is ſaid to have dyed the wheels of the chariot, and even the clothes of the inhuman daughter, whence the ſtreet was called ever after <hi rend="italic">vicus ſceleratus.</hi></p><p>The new king proved a moſt deſpotic and cruel tyrant ; receiving, in the very beginning of his reign, the ſurname of <hi rend="italic">proud,</hi>  on account of his capricious humour and haughty behaviour. All controverſies whatever were decided by himſelf and his friends ; and he ba-»iſhed, fined, and even executed, whom he pleaſed. The cenſus and luſtrum, the diviſion of citizens into claſſes and centuries, were aboliſhed ; and all kinds of aſſemblies, even thoſe ſor amuſement and recreation, were prohibited, both in town and country. Nay, to ſuch a height did Tarquin carry his inſolence and tyranny, that the moſt virtuous of the ſenators went into voluntary baniſhment ; while many of thoſe who remain, ed were cut off on various pretences, that the king might enjoy their eſtates.</p><p>Tarquin could not but be ſenſible of the extreme dan-..</p><lb/><p>ger in which he ſtood by lofing the affections of his people in ſuch a manner. He therefore provided a ſuf-ficient number of ſoldiers, by way of guard, to prevent attempts upon his perſon ; and gave his daughter to Octavius Mamilius, one of the moſt conſiderable men among the Latins, in order to ſtrengthen his intereſt by this foreign alliance, in caſe of a revolt among his ſubjects. Mamilius accordingly procured many friends to his father-in-law, but he had like to have loſt them again by his haughty behaviour. He had deſired the Latins to call a national council at Ferentinum, where he would meet them on a day appointed by himſelf. The Latins accordingly met ; but after waiting for ſeveral hours, Tarquin did not appear. On this, one Turnus Hcrdonius, an enterpriſing and eloquent man, who hated Tarquin, and wàs jealous of Mamilius, made a ſpeech, in which he inveighed againſt the haughty behaviour of Tarquin, ſet forth the contempt which he had put upon the Latins, and concluded with deſiring the council to break up and return home without taking any further notice of him. Mamilius, however, prevailed upon them to return the day following; when Tarquin made his appearance, and told the aſſembly that his deſign in calling them together was to claim his right of commanding the Latin armies, which he ſaid was derived from his grandfather, but which he deſired to be confirmed to him by them. Theſe words were ſcarce out of his mouth, when Herdonius, riſing up, entered into a detail of Tarquin’s tyranny and arbitrary behaviour at Rome, which, he ſaid, the Latins would ſoon feel in an equal degree, if they complied with Tarquin’s demand. To this ſpeech the king made no reply at that time, but promiſed to anſwer him next day. In the mean time, however, he bribed the domeſtics of Herdonius to admit among his baggage a large quantity of arms : and then, telling the Latins that Herdonius’s oppoſition proceeded only ſrom Tarquin’s having refuſed him his daughter in marriage, accuſed him of having laid a plot to cut off all the deputies there preſent, and to uſurp a juriſdiction over the Latin cities ; as a proof of which he appealed to the arms hid among the baggage of Herdonius. The accuſed, conſcious of his innocence, deſired that his baggage might be ſearched; which being accordingly done, and the arme found, he was hurried away without being allowed to make any defence, and thrown into a baſon at the head of the ſpring of Ferentinum, where a. hurdle being laid upon him, and ſtones laid upon the hurdle, he was preſſed down into the water and drowned.</p><p>In conſequence of this monſtrous treachery, Tarquin was looked upon by the Latins as their deliverer, and declared general of the Latin armies ; ſoon after which, the Hernici and two tribes of the Volſci entered into an alliance with him on the ſame terms. In order to keep theſe confederates together, Tarquin, with their conſent, erected a temple to Jupiter Latialis on an hill near the ruins of Alba, where he appointed certain feaſts called <hi rend="italic">Feri&lt;t Latina</hi>  to be held on the 27th of April, where the ſeveral nations were to ſacriſice together, and on no account to commit any hoſtilities againſt each other during their continuance. The king then proceeded to make war on the reſt of the Volſci who had refuſed to<hi rend="sup">-</hi>enter into an alliance with him. Some deρredatiρnswhich they had committed in the, territo-</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>