<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>timidity rendered him the ſlave of his attendants, who gradually corrupted his mind. His cruelty, which at firſt obeyed the dictates of others, degenerated into</p><lb/><p>habit, and at length became the ruling paſſion of his ſoul. ” But, however this may be, it is certain that the actions of this emperor were flagitious almoſt beyond</p><lb/><p>may diſcover, that notwithſtanding the inceſſant demands of wars and colonies, the citizens, who, in the time of Servius Tullius, amounted to no more than 83, 000, were multiplied, before the end of the ſocial war, to the number of 463, 000 men able to bear arms in the ſervice of their country. When the allies of Rome claimed an equal ſhare of honours and privileges, the ſenate preferred the chance of war to a conceſſion; however, at laſt, all the Italian ſtates, except the Samnites and Lucanians, were admitted into the boſom of the republic, and ſoon contributed to the ruin of public freedom. When the popular aſſemblies had been ſuppreſſed by the adminiſtration of the emperors, the conquerors were diſtinguiſhed from the vanquiſhed nations only as the firſt and moſt honourable order of ſubjects; and their increaſe, however rapid·, was no longer expoſed to the ſame dangers. Yet the princes who adopted the maxims of Auguſtus, guarded with the ſtricteſt care the dignity of the Roman name, and diffuſed the freedom of the city with a prudent liberality.</p><p>“ Till the privileges of the Romans had been progreſſively extended to all the inhabitants of the empire, an important diſtinction was preſerved between Italy and the provinces. The eſtates of the Italians were exempted from taxes, and their perſons from the arbitrary juriſdiction of governors. From the foot of the Alps to the extremity of Calabria, all the natives of Italy were born citizens of Rome. The provinces of the empire were deſtitute of any public force or conſtitutional freedom. The free ſtates and cities, which had embraced the cauſe of Rome, were inſenſibly ſunk into real ſervitude. The public authority was everywhere engroſſed by the mi-niſters of the ſenate and of the emperors, and that authority was abſolute. But the ſame ſalutary maxims of government which had ſecured the peace and obedience of Italy, were extended to the moſt diſtant conqueſts. A nation of Romans was gradually formed in the provinces, by the double expedient of introducing colonies, and of admitting the moſt faithful and deſerving provincials to the freedom of Rome.</p><p>“ So ſenſible were the Romans of the influence of language over national manners, that it  was their moſt ſe-rious care to extend, with the progreſs of their arms, the uſe of the Latin tongue. The eaſtern provinces, however, were leſs docile in this reſpect than the weſtern ones; and this, obvious difference made a diſtinction between the two portions of the empire, which became very remarkable when it began to decline. Nor was the influence of the Greek language and ſentiments confined to the narrow limits of that once celebrated country. Their em-pire, by the progreſs of colonies and conqueſt, had been diffuſed from the Adriatic to the Euphrates and Nile. Aſia was covered with Greek cities, and the long reign of the Macedonian kings had introduced a ſilent revolution into Syria and Egypt. In their pompous courts, thoſe princes united the elegance of Athens with the luxury of the eaſt; and the example of the court was imitated, at an humble diſtance, by the higher ranks of their ſubjects. Such was the general diviſion of the Roman empire into the Latin and Greek languages; to which we may add a third diſtinction for the body of the natives in Syria, and eſpecially in Egypt. The uſe of their ancient dialects, by ſecluding them from the commerce of mankind, checked the improvements of theſe barbarians. The ſlothful effeminacy of the former expoſed them to the contempt, the fullen ferociouſneſs of the latter excited the averſion, of the Roman conquerors. They ſeldom deſired or deſerved the freedom of the city; and it is remarked, that more than 230 years elapſed after the ruin of the Ptolemies, before a native Egyptian was admitted into the ſenate of Rome.</p><p>“ The number of ſubjects who acknowledged the laws of Rome, of citizens, of provincials, and of ſlaves, cannot now- be fixed with ſuch accuracy as the importance of the object would deſerve. We are informed, that when the emperor Claudius exerciſed the office of cenfor, he took an account of 6, 945, 000 Roman citizens; who, with the proportion of women and children, muſt have amounted to about 20, 000, 000 of ſouls. The multitude of ſubjects of an inferior rank was uncertain and fluctuating: but after weighing with attention every circumſtance which could influence the balance, it ſeems probable that there exiſted, in the time of Claudius, about twice as many provincials as there were Roman citizens, of either ſex, and of every age; and that the ſlaves were at leaſt equal in number to the free inhabitants of the Roman world. The total amount of this imperfect calculation would riſe to about 120 millions of perſons; a degree of population which poſſibly exceeds that of modern Europe, and forms the moſt numerous ſociety that has ever been united under the ſame ſyſtem of government.</p><p>“ Domeſtic peace and union were the natural conſequences of the moderate and comprehenſive policy embraced by the Romans. The vanquiſhed nations, blended into one great people, reſigned the hope, nay even the wiſh, of reſuming their independence, and ſcarcely conſidered their own exiſtence as diſtinct from the exiſtence of Rome. The eſtabliſhed authority of the emperors pervaded, without an effort, the wide extent of their dominions, and was exerciſed with the ſame facility on the banks of the Thames, or of the Nile, as on thoſe of the Tiber. The legions were deſtined to ſerve againſt the public enemy, and the civil magiſtrate ſeldom required the aid of a military force.</p><p>“ It was ſcarcely poſſible that the eyes of contemporaries ſhould diſcover in the public felicity the latent cauſes of decay and corruption. This long peace, and the uniform government of the Romans, introduced a flow and ſecret poiſon into the vitals of the empire. The minds of men were gradually reduced to the ſame level; the fire of genius was extinguiſhed, and even the military ſpirit evaporated. The natives of Europe were brave and robuſt. Spain, Gaul, Britain, and Illyricum, ſupplied the legions with excellent ſoldiers, and conftituted the</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>