<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>bitants, to the number of 300,003, gave him the value of as much food as each conſumed in a day. But notwithſtanding all this, as he had loſt one eye, and from his wounds continued lame throughout the remainder of his life, theſe defects prevented his ever being raiſed to the conſulate, or invtſted with any military command.</p><p>The city was not yet fully inveſted ; but as it was very difficult to find proviſions for ſuch a multitude, the inhabitants ſoon began to be in want. Porſena being informed of their difficulties, told them that he would ſupply them with proviſions if they would take back their old maſters ; but to this they replied, that hunger was a leſs evil than ſlavery and oppreſſion. Tire conſtancy of the Romans, however, was on the point of failing, when a young patrician, named <hi rend="italic">Muûus Cordas,</hi>  with the conſent of the ſenate and conſuls, undertook to aſſaſſinate Porſena. He got acceſs to the Hetrurian camp, diſguiſed like a peaſant, and made his way to the king’s tent. It happened to be the day on which the troops were all reviewed and paid ; and Por-ſena’s ſecretary, magnificently dreſſed, was ſitting on the ſame tribunal with the king. Mutius, miſtaking him for Porſena, inſtantly leaped upon the tribunal and killed him. He then attempted to make his eſcape ; but being ſeized and brought back, he owned his deſign ; and with a countenance expreſſive of deſperate rage and diſappointment, thruſt his hand which had miſſed the blow into a pan of burning coals which ſtood by, and there held it for a conſiderable time. On this, Porſena, changing his reſentment into admiration, granted him his life and liberty, and even reſtored him the dagger with which he intended to have ſtabbed himſelf. Mutius took it with his left hand, having loſt the uſe of the other ; and from this time had the name of <hi rend="italic">Scαvc&gt;la,</hi>  or “ left-handed.” He then, in order to induce Porſena to break up the ſiege, invented a ſtory that 300 young Romans, all of them as reſolute as himſelf, had ſworn to take aw<hi rend="sup">,</hi>ay the life of the king of Hetruria, or to periſh in the attempt. This had the deſired effect.; Porſena ſent deputies to Rome, whoſe only demands were, that the Romans ſhould reſtore the eſtates of the Tarquins, or give them an equivalent, and give back the ſeven ſmall towns which had been formerly taken from the Veientes. The latter of theſe demands was cheerfully complied with ; but the former was ſtill refuſed, until Porſena ſhould hear the ſtrong reaſons they had to urge againſt it. A truce being agreed on, deputies were ſent to the Hetrurian camp to plead the Roman cauſe againſt the Tarquins, and with tlrem ten young men, and as many virgins, by way of hoſtages for performing the other article.</p><p>The reception which Porſena gave the deputies raiſed the jealouſy of the Tarquins ; who ſtill retaining their ancient pride, refuſed to admit Porſena for a judge between them and the Romans. But the king, without any regard to their oppoſition, reſolved to ſatisfy himſelf, by an exact inquiry, whether the protection he had given the Tarquins was juſt. But while the cauſe was ready to be opened before the Roman deputies, news were brought that the young women whom the Romans had ſent as hoſtages had ventured to ſwim acroſs the Tiber, and were returned to Rome. They had gone to bathe in the river, and Clælia happening to tuvn her eyes towards her native city, that</p><p>fight raiſed in her a deſire of returning to it. She therefore ventured to ſwim acroſs the river ; and having encouraged her companions to follow her, they all got ſafe to the oppoſite ſhore, and returned to their ſathera houſes. The return of the hoſtages gave the conſul Poplicola great uneaſineſs ; he w<hi rend="sup">τ</hi>as afraid left this raſh action might be imputed to want of fidelity in the Romans. To remove therefore all ſuſpicions, he ſent a deputation to the Hetrurian camp, aſſuring the king that Rome had no ſhare in the fooliſh attempt of the young women ; and promiſing to ſend them immediately back to the camp from whence they had fled. Porſena was eaſily appeaſed ; but the news of the ſpeedy return of the hoſtages being known in the camp, the Tarquins, without any regard to the truce, or reſpect to the king their protector, lay in ambuſh on the road to ſurpriſe them. Poplicola having put himſelf at the head of the Roman troops who eſcorted them, ſuſtained the attack of the Tarquins, though ſudden and unexpected, till his daughter Valeria rode full ſpeed to the Hetrurian camp, and gave notice of the danger her father and companions were in ; and then Arunx, the king’s ſon, flying with a great body of cavalry to their relief, put the ag-greſſors to the rout.</p><p>This notorious piece of treachery in the Tarquins gave Porſena ſtrong fuſpicions of the badneſs of their cauſe. He therefore aſſembled the chief commanders of the Hetrurians ; and having heard in their preſence the complaints of the Romans, and the juſtiſication of their proceedings againſt the Tarquins, he w<hi rend="sup">ι</hi>as ſo ſtruck with horror at the recital of the crimes the Tarquins were charged with, that he immediately ordered them to leave his camp ; declaring, that he renounced his alliance with them, and would no longer continue the hoſ-pitality he had ſhown them. He then commanded the ten young virgins to be brought before him, and inquired who was the firſt author and chief manager of the enterpriſe. They all kept ſilence, till Clælia her-ſelf, with an air of intrepidity, conſeſſed, that ſhe alone was guilty, and that ſhe had encouraged the others by her advice. Upon this the king, extolling her reſolution above the bravery of Horatius and the intrepidity of Mutius, made her a preſent of a fine horſe, with ſumptuous furniture. After this he concluded a peace with the Romans, and reſtored to them all their hoſtages ; declaring, that their bare word, was to him a ſuffi-ciεnt ſecurity for the performance of the articles.</p><p>And now Porſena being about to return to Cluſium, gave, before his departure, a further teſtimony of his reſpect and friendſhip for the Romans. He knew that Rome was greatly diſtreſſed for want of proviſions; but being afraid to offend the inhabitants by relieving them in a direct manner, he ordered his ſoldiersrto leave behind them their tents and proviſions, and to carry nothing with them but their arms. As his camp abounded with all ſorts of proviſions, Rome was hereby much ∙ relieved in her wants. The moveables and corn of the Hetrurians were ſold by auction to private perſons <hi rend="italic">t </hi>and on this occaſion the Romans took up the cuſtom of making a proclamation by an herald, whenever any effects belonging to the public were to be ſold, in the ſollowirig words, <hi rend="italic">Theſe are Porſena's goods.</hi>  The deſign of this was to preſerve the memory of that prince’s-kindneſs. The ſenate, not ſatisfied with this, erected a ſtatue of the king «ear the εomitium, and ſent aα</p></body></text></TEI>