<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>equal to — except when √ <hi rend="italic">s</hi>  is very great, and deviate the more from this quantity as √ <hi rend="italic">s</hi>  is ſmaller ; we may repreſent the velocities by the ordinates of another curve PGT, which approaches very near to the hyperbola, at a great diſtance from A along AB : but ſeparates from it when the abſciſſæ are ſmaller : ſo that if AQ repreſents that value of √ <hi rend="italic">s</hi>  (which we have ſeen may become leſs than unity), which Correſponds to art infinite velocity, the line QO maybe the aſſymptote of the new curve. Its ordinates are equal to while Jv</p><p>thoſe of the hyperbola are equal to -. Therefore the ratio of theſe ordinates or ſhould be ſuch that it ſhall be ſo much nearer to unity as √ <hi rend="italic">s</hi>  greater, and ſhall ſurpaſs it ſo much the more as √ <hi rend="italic">s</hi>  is ſmaller.</p><p>To expreſs X therefore as ſome function of √ <hi rend="italic">s </hi>ſo as to anſwer theſe conditions, we ſee in general that X muſt be leſs than √∙<hi rend="sup">r</hi>∙ And it muſt not be equal to any power of √<hi rend="sup">,</hi>∙<hi rend="sup">f</hi>  whole index is leſs than unity, be-cauſe then would differ ſo much the more from unity as √Γ is greater. Nor muſt it be any multiple of √j ſuch as y√<hi rend="sup">,</hi>j∙, for the ſame reaſem. If we make <hi rend="smallcaps">X = √<hi rend="sub">j</hi></hi>  —K, K being a conſtant quantity, we may anſwer the firſt condition pretty well. But K muſt be very ſmall, that X may not become equal to nothing, except in ſome exceedingly ſmall value of √<hi rend="italic">s.</hi>  Now the experiments will not admit of this, becauſe the ratio - does not increaſe ſufficiently to correſpond with the velocities which we obſerve in certain ſlopes, unleſs we make K greater than unity, which again is in-conſiſtent with other experiments. We learn from ſuch canvaſſing that it will not do to make K a conſtant quantity. If we ſhould make it any fractionary power of √<hi rend="sup">r</hi>x, it would make X = o, that is, nothing, when<hi rend="italic">s</hi>  is = I, which is alſo contrary to experience. It would ſeem, therefore, that nothing will anſwer for K but ſome power of √h which has a variable index. The logarithm of V<hi rend="sup">z</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">j has this property. We may therefore try to make X = √r—log. √r. Accordingly if we try the equation V= , we ſhall find a</hi></p><p>very great agreement with the experiments till the declivity becomes conſiderable, or about √-, which is much greater than any river. But it will not agree with the velocities obſerved in ſome mill courſes, and in pipes of a ſtill greater declivity, and gives a velocity that is too ſmall ; and in vertical pipes the velocity is not above one half of the true one. We ſhall get rid of molt of theſe incongruities if we make K conſiſt of the hyperbolic logarithm of <hi rend="italic">V s</hi>  augmented by a ſmall conſtant quantity, and by trying various values for this conſtant quantity, and comparing the reſults with experiment, we may hit on one ſufficiently exact for all practical purpoſes.</p><p>Mr l)e Buat, after repeated trials, found that he would have a very great conformity with experiment by making K= log. λΛγ-{- i, 6, and that the Velocities exhibited in his experiments would be very well repreſented by the formula V ≈ -ji</p><p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="sup">z</hi>    Vs—</hi>  Lvct∙j,6</p><p>There is a circumſtance which our author ſeems tö have overlooked on this occaſion, and which is undoubtedly of great effect in theſe motions, viz. the mutual adhelion of the particles of water. This cauſes the water which is deſcending (in a vertical pipe for example) to drag more water after it, and thus greatly in-Creaſes its velocity. We have ſeeh an experiment in which the water iſſued from the bottom of a reſervoir through a long vertical pipe having a very gentle taper. It Was 15 feet long, one inch diameter at the upper end, and two inches at the lower. The depth of the water in the reſervoir was exactly one foot ; in a minute there were diſcharged 2<hi rend="sub">τ</hi><hi rend="sup">9</hi><hi rend="sub">5</hi>∙ cubic feet of water. It muſt therefore have iſſued through the hole in the bottom of the reſervoir with the velocity of 8,8y feet per ſecond. And yet we know that this head of water could not make it paſs through the hole with a velocity greater than 6,y6 feet per ſecond. This increaſe muſt therefore have ariſen from the cauſe we have mentioned, and is a proof of the great intenſity of this force. We doubt not but that the diſcharge might have been much more increaſed by proper contrivances ; and we know many inſtances in water pipes where this effect is produced in a very great degree.</p><p>The following caſe is very diſtinct: Water is brought into the town of Dunbar in the county of Eaſt Lothian from a ſpring at the diſtance of about 3200 yards. It is conveyed along the firſt 1100 yards in a pipe of two inches diameter, and the declivity is 12 feet nine inches ; from thence the water flows in a pipe of 1⅛ diameter, with a declivity of 44 feet 3 inches, making in all 57 feet. When the work was carried as far as the two-inch pipe reached, the diſcharge was found to be 27 Scotch pints, of 103⅛ cubic inches each in a minute. When it was brought into the town, the diſcharge was 28. Here it is plain that the deſcent along the ſecond ſtretch of the pipe could derive no impulſion from the firſt. This was only able to ſupply 2 7 pints* and to <hi rend="italic">deliver</hi>  it into a pipe of equal bore. It was not equivalent to the forcing it into a ſmaller pipe, and almoſt doubling its velocity. It muſt therefore have been <hi rend="italic">dragged</hi>  into this ſmaller pipe by the weight of what was deſcending along it, and this water was exerting a force· equivalent to a head of 16 inches, increaſing the velocity from 14 to about 28.</p><p>It muſt be obſerved, that if this formula be juft, there can be no declivity ſo ſmall that a current of water will not take place in it. And accordingly none has been obſerved in the ſurface of a ſtream when this did not happen. But it alſo ſhould happen with re-ſpect to any declivity of bottom. Yet we know that water will hang on the ſloping ſurface of a board without proceeding further. The cauſe of this ſeems to be the adheſiort of the water combined with its viſcidity. The viſcidity of a fluid preſents a certain force which muſt be overcome before any current can take place.</p><p>A ſeries of important experiments were made by our author in order to aſcertain the relation between the velocity at the ſurface of any ſtream and that at</p></body></text></TEI>