<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>except Cato. The aſſociation of the triumvirs was for a long time kept ſecret ; and nothing appeared to the people except the reconciliation of Pompey and Craſſiis, for which the ſtate reckoned itſelf indebted to Cæſar. The firſt conſequence of the triumvirate was the conſulſhip of Julius Cæſar. But though this was obtained by the favour of Pompey and Craſſus, he found himſelſ diſappointed in the colleague hc wanted to aſſociate with him in that office. He had pitched upon one whom he knew he could manage as he pleaſed, and diſtributed large ſums among the people in order to engage them to vote for him. The ſenate, however, and even Cato himſelf, reſolved to defeat the triumvir at his own weapons ; and having therefore ſet up another candidate, diſtributed ſuch immenſe ſums on the oppoſite ſide, that Cæſar, notwithſtanding the vaſt riches he had acquired, was forced to yield. This defeat proved of ſmall conſequence. Cæſar ſet himſelf to engage the affections of the people ; and this he did, by an agrarian law, ſo effectually, that he was in a manner idolized. The law was in itſelf very reaſonable and juſt ; nevertheleſs, the ſenate, perceiving the deſign with which it was propoſed, thought themſelves bound to oppoſe it. Their oppoſition, however, proved fruitleſs : the conſul Bibulus, who ſhewed himſelf moſt active in his endeavours againſt it, was driven out of the aſſembly with the greateſt indignity, and from that day became of no conſideration ; ſo that Cæſar was reckoned the ſole conſul.</p><p>The next ſtep taken by Cæſar was to ſecure the knights, as he had already done the people ; and for this purpoſe he abated a third of the rents which they «annually paid into the treaſury ; after which he governed Rome with an abſolute ſway during the time of his conſulate. The reign of this triumvir, however, was ended by his expedition into Gaul, where his military exploits acquired him the higheſt reputation.— Pompey and Craſſus in the mean time became conſuls, and governed as deſpotically as Cæſar himſelſ had done. On the expiration of their firſt conſulate, the republic fell into a kind of anarchy, entirely owing to the diſor-&lt;]eιs occaſioned by the two late conſuls. At laſt, however, this confuſion was ended by raiſing Craſſus and Pompey to the conſulate a ſecond time. This was no ſooner done, than a new partition of the empire was propoſed. Craſſus was to have Syria and all the eaſtern provinces, Pompey was to govern Africa and Spain, and Cæſar to be continued in Gaul, and all this for the ſpace of five years. This law was paſſed by a great majority ; upon which Craſſus undertook an expedition againſt the Parthians, whom he imagined he ſhould eaſily overcome, and then enrich himſelf with their ſpoils ; Cæſar applied with great aſſiduity to the completing of the conqueſt of Gaul ; and Pompey having nothing to do in his province, ſtaid at Rome to govern the republic alone.</p><p>The affairs of the Romans were now haſtening to a criſis. Craſſus, having oppreſſed all the provinces of the eaſt, was totally defeated and killed by the Parthians * ; after which the two great rivals Cæſar and Pompey were left alone, without any third perſon who could hold the balance between them, or prevent the deadly quarrels which were about to enſue. Matters, however, continued pretty quiet till Gaul was reduced to a Roman province ÿ. The queſtion then was, whether Cæſar or Pompey ſhould firſt reſign the eommanl of their armies, and return to the rank of private perſons. As both parties ſaw·, that whoever firſt laid down his arms muſt of courſe ſubmit to the other, both refuſed to diſarm themſelves. As Cæſar, however, had a naſſed immenſe riches in Gaul, he was now in a condition not only to maintain an army oapable of vying with Pompey, but even to buy over the leading men in Rome to lſis intereſt. One of the conſuls, named <hi rend="italic">ÆmiHut Paulus,</hi>  coſt. him no leſs than ί 500 talents, or 310,62 j 1. ſterling ; but the other, named <hi rend="italic">Marcellus,</hi>  could not be gained at any price. Pompey had put at the head of the tribunes one Scribonius Curio, a young patrician of great abilities, but ſo exceedingly debauched and extravagant, that he owed upwards of four millions and a half of our money. Cæſar, by enabling him to ſatisfy his creditors, and ſupplying him with money to purſue his debaucheries, ſecured him in his intereſt ; and Curio, without ſeeming to be in Cæſar’s intereſt, found means to do hi n the moſt eſſential ſervice. He propoſed that both generals ſhould be recalled ; being well aſſured that Pompey would never conſent to part with his army, or lay down the government of Spain with which he had been inveſted, io that Cæſar might draw ſrom Pom-pey’s refuſal a pretence for continuing himſelſ in his province at the head of his troops. This propoſal threw the oppoſite party into great embarraſſments ; and while both profeſſed their pacific intentions, both continued in readineſs for the moſt obſtinate and bloody war.— Cicero took upon himſelf the office of mediator ; but Pompey would hearken to no terms of accommodation. The orator, ſurpriſed to find him ſo obſtinate, at the ſame time that he neglected to ſtrengthen his army, alked him with what forces he deſigned to make head againſt Cæſar? To which the other anſwered, that he needed but ſtamp with his foot, and an army would liait up out of the ground. This confidence he aſſumed becauſe he perſuaded himſelf that Cæſar’s mpn would abandon him if matters came to extremities. Cæſar, however, though he affected great moderation, yet kept himſelf in readineſs for the worſt ; and therefore, when the ſenate palled the fatal decree for a civil war, he was not in the leaſt alarmed. This decree was iſſued in the year 49 B. C. and was expreſſed in the following words: “ Let the conſuls for the year, the proconſul Pompey, the prætors, and all thoſe in or near Rome who have been conſuls, provide lor the public ſafety by the moſt proper means.” This decree was no ſooner paſſed, than the conſul Marcellus went, with his colleague Lentulus, to an houſe at a ſmall diſtance from the town, where Pompey then was ; and preſenting him with a ſword, “ We require you (ſaid he) to take upon you with this the defence of the republic, and the command of her troops.” Pompey obeyed ; and Cæſar was by the fame decree diveſted of his office, and one Lucius Domitius appointed to ſucceed him, the new governor being empowered to raiſe 4000 men in order to take poſſeſſion of his province.</p><p>War being thus reſolved on, the ſenate and Pompey began to make the neceſſary preparations for oppoſing Cæſar. The attempt of the latter to withſtand their authority they termed a <hi rend="italic">tumult ;</hi>  from which contemptible epithet it appeared that they either did not know, or did not dread, the enemy whom they wert· bringing upon themſelves. However, they ordered 30,000 Ro-</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>