<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>whom he entirely reduced, after they had waged war with the Romans for the ſpace of 107 years. Having ſubdued this untractable people, he penetrated into Hetruria, in order to relieve Sutrium, a town in that country in alliance with Rome, and beſieged by a numerous army of Hetrurians. But, notwithſtanding all the expedition Camillus could uſe, be did not reach the place before it had capitulated. The Sutrini, being greatly diſtreſſed for want of proviſions, and exhauſted with labour, had ſurrendered to the Hetrurians, who had granted them nothing but their lives, and the cloaths on their backs. In this deſtitute condition they had left their own country, and were going in ſearch of new habitations, when they met Camillus leading an-army to their relief.</p><p>The unfortunate multitude no ſooner ſaw the Romans, but they threw themſelves at the dictator’s ſeet, who, moved at this melancholy fight, deſired them to take a little reſt, and refreſh themſelves, adding, that he would ſoon dry up their tears, and transfer their ſorrows from them to their enemies. He imagined, that the Hetrurians would be wholly taken up in plundering the city, without being upon their guard, or obſerving any diſcipline. And herein he was not miſtaken. The Hetrurians did not dream that the dictator could come ſo ſpeedily from ſuch a diſtance to ſurpriſe them ; and therefore were wholly employed in plundering the houſes and carrying off the booty, or feaſting on the proviſions they had found in them. Many of them were put to the ſword, and an incredible number made priſoners ; and the city was reſtored to its ancient inhabitants, who had not waited in vain for the performance of the dictator’s promiſe. And now, after theſe glorious exploits, which were finiſhed in ſo ſhort a time, the great Camillus entered Rome in triumph a third time.</p><p>, Camillus having reſigned his dictatorſhip, the republic choſe. ſix new military tribunes, Q. Quinctius, Q-_ Servius, L. Julius, L. Aquilius, L. Lucretius, and Ser. Sulpitius. During their adminiſtration the country of the Æqui was laid waſte, in order to put it out of their power to revolt anew ; and the two cities of Cortuoſa and Contenebra, in the lucumony of the Tarquinienſes, were taken from the Hetrurians, and entirely demoliſhed. At this time it was thought proper to repair the Capitol, and add new works to that part of the hill where the Gauls had endeavoured to ſcale the citadel. Theſe works were eſteemed very beautiful, as Livy informs us, even in the time of Auguſtus, after the city was embelliſhed with moſt magnificent decorations.</p><p>And now Rome being reinſtated in her former flouriſhing condition, the tribunes of the people, who had been for ſome time quiet, began to renew their ſeditious harangues, and revive the old quarrel about the diviſion of the conquered lands. The patricians had appropriated to themſelves the Pomptin territory lately •taken from the Volſci, and the tribunes laid hold of this opportunity to raiſe new diſturbances. But the citizens being ſo drained of their money that they had not enough left to cultivate new farms and ſtock them with cattle, the declamations of the tribunes made no impreſſion upon their minds ; ſo that the project vaniſhed. As for the military tribunes, they owned that their election had been defective ; and, leſt the irregularities «f the former comitia ſhould be continued in the ſuc</p><p>ceeding ones, they voluntarily laid down their office. So that, after a ſhort interregnum, during which M. Manlius, Ser. Sulpitius, and L. Valerius Potſtus, governed the republic, fix new military tribunes L. Papirius, C. Sergius, L. Æmilius, L. Menenius, L. Vale· rius, and C. Cornelius, were choſen for the enſuing year, which was ſpent in works of peace. A temple, which had been vowed to Mars during the war with the Gauls, was built, and conſecrated by T. Quinctius, who preſided over the affairs of religion. As there had hitherto been but few Roman tribes beyond the Tiber which had a right of ſuffrage in the comitia, four new ones were added, under the. name of the <hi rend="italic">SteHatina, Tra-montina, Sabatιna,</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">Arntenſis;</hi>  ſo that the tribes were now in all 25, which enjoyed the ſame rights and privileges.</p><p>The expectation of an approaching war induced the centuries to chooſe Camillus one of the military tribunes for the next year. His colleagues were Ser. Cornelius, Q. Servilius, L. Quinctius, L. Horatius, and P. Valerius. As all theſe were men of moderation, they-agreed to inveſt Camillus with the ſole management of affairs in time of war ; and accordingly in full ſenate transferred all their power into his hands ; ſo that he » became in effect dictator. It had been already determined in the ſenate to turn the arms of the republic againſt the Hetrurians ; but, upon advice that the Antiates had entered the Pomptin territory, and obliged the Romans who had taken poſſeſſion of it to retire, it was thought neceſſary to humble them before the republic engaged in any other enterpriſe. The xAntiates had joined the Latin.9 and Hernici near Satricum ; ſo that the Romans, being terrified at their prodigious numbers, ſhewed themſelves very backward to engage : which Camillus perceiving, he inſtantly mounted his horſe, and riding through all the ranks of the army, encouraged them by a proper ſpeech ; after which he diſmounted, took the next ſtandard-bearer by the hand, led him towards the enemy, and cried out, <hi rend="italic">Soldiers, advance.</hi>  The ſoldiery were aſhamed not tς&gt; follow a ge</p><p>neral who expoſed himſelſ to the firſt attack ; and therefore, having made a great ſhout, they fell upon the enemy with incredible fory. Camillus, in order to increaſe their eagerneſs ſtill more, commanded a ſtandard to be thrown into the middle of the enemy’s battalions ; which made the ſoldiers, who were fighting in the firſt ranks, exert all the reſolution they could to recover it. The Antiates, not being able any longer to make head againſt the Romans, gave way, and were entirely defeated. The Latins and Hernici ſeparated from the Volſci, and returned home. The Volſci, ſeeing themſelves thus abandoned by their allies, took refuge in the neighbouring'city of Satricum; which'Camillus immediately inveſted, and took by aſſault. The Volſei threw down their arms, and ſurrendered at diſcretion. He then left his army under the command of Valerius ; and returned to Rome to ſolicit the conſent of the ſenate, and to make the neceſſary preparations for undertaking the ſiege of Antium.</p><p>But, while he was propoſtng this affair to the ſenate, deputies arrived from Nepet and Sutrium, two cities in alliance with Rome in the neighbourhood of He-truria, demanding ſuccours againſt the Hetrurians, who threatened to beſiege theſe two cities, which were the keys of Hetruria. Hereupon the expedition againſt</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>