<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p><hi rend="italic">roader.</hi>  A ſhip is rarely ſaid to <hi rend="italic">ride</hi>  when ſhe is ſaſten-ed at both the ends, as in a harbour or river, that ſitua-tion being comprehended in the article MooRing.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Riding, a diſtrict viſited by an officer.—Yorkſhire is divided into three ridings, viz. the eaſt, weft, and north ridings. In all indictments in that county, both the town and riding muſt be expreſſed.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Riding, as connected with gardening, and ſuſcep-tſhle of embelliſhment. See Gardening.</hi></p><p>A riding, though in extent differing ſo widely from a garden, yet agrees with it in many particulars : for, excluſive of that community of character which reſults from their being both improvements, and both deſtined to pleaſure, a cloſer relation ariſes from the property of a riding, <hi rend="italic">to extend the idea of a ſeat</hi>  and appropriate a whole country to the manſion ; for which purpoſe it muſt be diſtinguiſhed from common roads, and the marks of diſtinction muſt be borrowed from a garden. Thoſe  which a farm or a park can ſupply are faint and few ; but whenever circumſtances belonging to a garden occur, they are immediately received as evidence of the domain. The ſpecies of the trees will often be deci-ſive : plantations of firs, whether placed on the ſides of the way, or in clumps or woods in the view, denote the neighbourhood of a ſeat : even limes and horſe-cheſ-nuts are not indifferent ; for they have always been frequent in improvements, and rare in the ordinary ſcenes of cultivated nature. If the riding be carried through a wood, the ſhrubs, which for their beauty or their fragrance have been tranſplanted from the country into gardens, ſuch as the ſweet-briar, .the viburnum, the euonymus, and the wood-bine, ſhould be encouraged in the underwood ; and to theſe may be added ſeveral which are ſtill peculiar to ihrubberies, but which might eaſily be transferred to the wildeſt coverts, and would</p><p>require no further care.</p><p>Where the ſpecies are not, the diſpoſition may be particular, and any appearance of deſign is a mark of improvement. A few trees ſtanding out from a hedgerow, raiſe it to an elegance above common ruſticity : and ſtill more may be done by clumps in a field ; they give it the air of a park. A cloſe lane may be decorated with plantations in all the little vacant ſpaces : and even the groups originally on the ſpot (whether it be a wood, a field, or a lane), if properly ſelected, and thoſe only left which are elegant, will have an effect : though every beauty of this kind may be found in nature, yet many of them are ſeldom ſeen together, and never unmixed. The number and the choice are ſymptoms of deſign.</p><p>Another ſymptom is variety. If the appendages of the riding be different in different fields, if in a lane, or a wood, ſome diſtinguiſhing circumſtance be provided for every bend ; or when, carried ever an open expo-ſure, it winds to ſeveral points of view ; if this be the conduct throughout, the intention is evident, to amuſe the length of the way : variety of ground is alio a eharacteriſtic of a riding, when it ſeems to have proceeded from choice ; and pleaſure being the pursuit, the changes of the ſcene both compenſate and account for the circuity.</p><p>But apart undiſtinguiſhed from a common road, ſuc-ceeding to others more adorned, will by the contraſt alone be ſometimes agreeable ; and there are beauties frequent in the high-way, and almoſt peculiar to it,</p><p>which may be very acceptable in a riding : a green lane is always delightful; a paſſage winding between thickets of brambles and briars, ſometimes with ſometimes without a little ſpring-wood riſing amongſt them, or a cut in a continued ſweep through the furze of a down or the fern of a heath, is generally pleaſant. Nor will the character be abſolutely loſt in the interruption, it will ſoon be reſumed, and never forgotten ; when it has been once ſtrongly impreſſed, very flight means will preſerve the idea.</p><p>Simplicity may prevail the whole length of the way when the way is all naturally pleaſant, but eſpecially if it be a communication between ſeveral ſpots, which in character are railed above the reſt of the country : A fine open grove is unuſual, except in a park or a garden ; it has an elegance in the diſpoſition which cannot be attributed to accident, and it ſeems to require a degree of preſervation beyond the care of mere huſhandry. A neat railing on the edge of a ſteep which commands a proſpect, alone diſtinguiſhes that from other points of view. A building is ſtill more ſtrongly characteriſtic : it may be only ornamental, or it may be accommodated to the reception of company ; for though a place to alight at interrupts the range of a riding, yet, as the object of an airing, it may often be acceptable. A ſmall ſpot which may be kept by the labour of one man, incloſed from the fields, and converted into a ſhrubbery or any other ſcene of a garden, will ſometimes be a pleaſing end to a ſhort excur-ſion from home : nothing ſo effectually extends the idea of a ſeat to a diſtance ; and not being conſtantly viſited, it will always retain the charms of novelty and variety.</p><p>When a riding is carried along a high road, a kind of property may in appearance be claimed even there, by planting on both ſidcs trees equidiſtant from each other, to give it the air of an approach : regularity intimates the neighbourhood of a manſion. A village therefore ſeems to be within the domain, if any of the inlets to it are avenues : other formal plantations about it, and ſtill more trivial circumſtances, when they are evidently ornamental, ſometimes produce and always corroborate ſuch an effect ; but even without railing this idea, if the village be remarkable for its beauty, or only for its Angularity, a paſſage through it may be an agreeable incident in a riding.</p><p>The ſame ground which in the fields is no more than rough, often ſeems to be romantic when it is the ſite of a village ; the buildings and other circumſtances mark and aggravate the irregularity. To ſtrengthen this appearance, one cottage may be placed on the edge of a ſteep, and ſome winding ſteps of unhewn ſtonelead up to the door ; another in a hollow, with all its little appurtenances hanging above it. The poſition of a few trees will ſometimes anſwer the ſame purpoſe ; a footbridge here and there for a communication between the ſides of a narrow dip, will add to the character ; and if there be any rills, they may be conducted ſo as greatly to improve it.</p><p>A village which has not theſe advantages of ground, may, however, be beautiful ; it is diſtinguiſhed by its elegance, when the larger intervals between the houſes are filled with open groves, and little clumps are introduced upon other occaſions. The church often is, it generally may be, made a pictureſque object. Even the cottages may be neat and ſometimes grouped</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>