<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>came bodies of ſound doctrine; and the deductions from their respective theories were found fair repreſentations of the phenomena of nature. Whenever a man has diſcovered a law of nature, he has laid the foundation of a ſcience, and he has given us a new mean of ſubjecting to our ſervice ſome element hitherto independent: and ſo long as groups of natural operations follow a route which appears to us whimſical, and will not admit our calculations, we may be aſſured that we are ignorant of the principle which connects them all, and regulates their procedure.</p><p>This is remarkably the caſe with ſeveral phenomena in the motions of fluids, and particularly in the motion of water in a bed or conduit of any kind. Although the firſt geniuſes of Europe have for this century paſt turned much of their attention to this ſubject, we are almoſt ignorant of the <hi rend="italic">general laws</hi>  which may be obſerved in their motions. We have been able to ſclect very few points of reſemblance, and every caſe remains nearly an individual. About 150 years ago we diſcovered, by experience only, the quantity and velocity of water iſſuing from a ſmall orifice, and, after much labour, have extended this to any orifice; and this is almoſt the whole of our confidential knowledge. But as to the uniform courſe of the ſtreams which water the face of the earth, and the maxims which will certainly negulate this agreeably to our wiſhes, we are in a manner totally ignorant. Who can pretend to ſay what is the velocity of a river of which you tell him the breadth, the depth, and the declivity? Who can ſay what ſwell will be produced in different parts of its courſe, if a dam or weir of given dimenſions be made in it, or a bridge be thrown acroſs it? or how much its waters will be raiſed by turning another ſtream into it, or ſunk by taking off a branch to drive a mill? Who can ſay with confidence what muſt be the dimenſions or ſlope of this branch, in order to furniſh the water that is wanted, or the dimenſions and ſlope of a canal which ſhall effectually drain a fenny diſtrict? Who can ſay what form will cauſe or will prevent the undermining of banks, he forming of elbows, the pooling of the bed, or the de-poſition of lands? Yet theſe are the moſt important queſtions.</p><p>The cauſes of this ignorance are the want or uncertainty of our principles; the falſity of our only theory, which is belied by experience and the ſmall number of proper obſervations or experiments, and difficulty of making ſuch as ſhall be ſerviceable. We have, it is true, made a few experiments on the efflux of water ſrom ſmall orifices, and from them we have deduced a ſort of theory, dependant on the fall of heavy bodies and the laws of hydroſtatic preſſure. Hydroſtatics is indeed founded on very ſimple principles, which give a very good account of the laws of the quieſcent equilibrium of fluids, in conſequence of gravity and perfect fluidity. But by what train of reaſoning can we connect theſe with the phenomena of the uniform motion of the waters of a river or open ſtream, which can derive its motion only from the ſlope of its ſurface, and the modifications of this motion or its velocity only from the width and depth of the ſtream? Theſe are the only circumſtances which can diſtinguiſh a portion of a river from a veſſel of the ſame ſize and ſhape, in which, however, the water is at reſt. In both, gιavity is the ſole cauſe of preſſure and motion; but there muſt be ſome</p><p>circumſtance peculiar to running waters which modifies the exertions of this active principle, and which, when diſcovered, muſt be the baſis of hydraulics, and muſt oblige us to reject every theory founded on fancied hy-potheſes, and which can only lead to abſurd conclu-ſions: and ſurely abſurd conſequences, when legitimately drawn, are complete evidence of improper principles.</p><p>When it was diſcovered experimentally, that the velocities of water iſſuing from orifices at various depths under the ſurface were as the ſquare roots of thoſe depths, and the fact was verified by repeated experiments, this principle was immediately and without modification applied to every motion of water. Mariotte, Varignon, Guglielmini, made it the baſis of complete ſyſtems of hydraulics, which prevail to this day, after having received various amendments and modifications. The ſame reaſoning obtains through them all, though frequently obſcured by other circumſtances, which are more perſpicuouſly expreſſed by Guglielmini in his. Fundamental Theorems.</p><p>He conſiders every point P (fig. 1. ) in a maſs of fluid as an orifice in the ſide of a veſſel, and conceives the particle as having a tendency to move with the ſame velocity with which it would iſſue from the orifice. Therefore, if a vertical line AFC be drawn thro* that point, and if this be made the axis of a parabolic ADE, of which A at the ſurface of the fluid is the vertex, and AB (four times the height through which a heavy body would fall in a ſecond) is the parameter, the velocity of this particle will be repreſented by the ordinate PD of this parabola; that is, PD is the ſpace which it would uniformly deſcribe in a ſecond.</p><p>From this principle is derived the following theory of running waters.</p><p>Let DC (fig. 2. ) be the horizontal bottom of a reſervoir, to which is joined a ſloping channel CK of uniform breadth, and let AB be the ſurface of the ſtand-ing water in the reſervoir. Suppoſe the vertical plane BC pierced with an infinity of holes, through each of which the water iſſues. The velocity of each filament will be that which is acquired by falling from the ſur-face AB j∙. The filament C, iſſuing with this velocity, will then glide down the inclined plane like any other heavy body; and (by the common doctrine of the motion down an inclined plane ) when it has arrived at F, it will have the ſame velocity which it would have acquired by falling through the height OF, the point O being in the horizontal plane AB produced. The ſame may be ſaid of its velocity when it arrives at H or K. The filament immediately above C will alſo iſſue with a velocity which is in the ſubduplicate ratio of its depth, and will then glide down above the firſt filament. The ſame may be affirmed of all the filaments; and of the ſuperficial filament, which will occupy the ſurface of the deſcending ſtream.</p><p>From this account of the geneſis of a running ſtream of water, we may fairly draw the following conſequences.</p><p>1.    The velocity of any particle R, in any part of the ſtream, is that acquired by falling from the horizontal plane AN.</p><p>2.    The velocity at the bottom of the ſtream is everywhere greater than anywhere above it, and is leaſt of all at the ſurface.</p><p>3.    The velocity of the ſtream increaſes continually as the ſtream recedes from its ſource.</p></body></text></TEI>