<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>lnto Spain, where he erected a republic independent oſ Ro e. Pompey and Metellus, two of the beſt reputed generals in Ro ∙ e, were ſent againſt hi r ; but inſtead of conquering, they were on all occaſions conquered by him, and obliged to abandon their enterpriſe with diſgrace. At lait Sertorius was treacherouſly murdered ; and the traitors, who after his death uſurped the command, being totally deſſtute of his abilites, were eaſily defeated by Pompey : and thus that general reaped an undeſerved honour from concluding the war with ſucceſs.</p><p>The Spaniſh war was ſcarce ended, when a very dangerous one was excited by Spartacus, a Thracian gladiator. For ſome time this rebel proved very luc-ceſsful ; but at laſt was totally defeated and killed by Craſſus. The fugitives, however, rallied again, to the number of 5000 ; but, being totally defeated by Pompey, the latter took occaſion from thence to claim the glory which was juſtly due to Craſſus. Being thus become extremely popular, and ſetting no bounds to his ambiti<hi rend="sup">z</hi>on, he was choſen conſul along with Craſſus. .Both generals were at the head of powerful armies ; and * conteſt between them immediately began about who ſhould firſt lay down their arms. With difficulty they were in appearance reconciled, and immediately began to oppoſe one another in a new way. Pompey courted the favour of the people, by reinſtating the tribunes in their ancient power, which had been greatly abridged by Sylla. Craſſus. though naturally covetous, entertained the populace with ſurpriſing profuſion at ιc,oco tables, and at the ſame time diſtributed corn ſufficient to maintain their families for three months.— Theſe prodigious expences will ſeem leſs ſurpriſing, when we conſider that Craſſus was the richeſt man in Rome, and that his eſtate amounted to upwards of 70Ö0 talents, <hi rend="italic">i. e.</hi>  1,356,250 1. ſterling. Notwithſtanding his utmoſt efforts, however, Pompey ſtill had the ſuperiority ; and was therefore propoſed as a proper perſon to be employed for clearing the ſeas of pirates. -In this new ſtation a moſt extenſive power was to be granted to him. He was to have an abſolute authority for three years over all the ſeas within the ſtraits or pillars of Hercules, and over all the countries for the ſpace of 400 furlongs from the ſea. He was empowered to raiſe as many ſoldiers and mariners as he thought proper ; to take what ſums o'f money he pleaſed out of the public treaſury without being accountable for them ; and to chooſe out of the ſenate fifteen ſenators to be his lieutenants, and to execute his orders when he himſelf could not be preſent. I he ſenſible part of the people were againſt inveſting one man with ſo much power ; but the unthinking multitude rendered all oppoſition fruitleſs. The tribune Roſeius attempted to ſpeak againſt it, but was prevented by the clamours of the people. He then held up two of lus fingers, to ſhow that he was for dividing that extenſive commiſſion between two perſons : byt on this the aſſembly burſt out into ſuch hideous outcries, that a crow flying accidentally over the comitium, was ſtunned with the noiſe, and ſell down among the rabble. This law being agreed to, Pompey executed his commiſſion ſo much to the public ſatisfaction, that on his return a new law was .propoſed in bis favour. By this he was to be appointed general of all the forces in Aſia ; and as he was ſtill <hi rend="sub">t</hi>o.retain the ſovereignty of the ſeas, he was now in</p><p>fact made ſovereign of all the Roman empire.— This law was ſupported by Cicero and Cæſar, the former aſpiring at the conſulate, and the latter pleaſed to ſee the Romans ſo readily appointing themſelves a maſter. Pompey, however, executed his commiſſion with the utmoſt fidelity and ſucceſs, completing the conqueſt of Pontus, Albania, Iberia, &amp;c. which had been ſucceſsfully begun by Sylla and Lu-∙cullus.</p><p>But while Pompey was thus aggrandiſing himſelf, the republic was on the point of being ſubverted by a conſpiracy formed by Lucius Sergius Catiline. He was deſeended from an illuſtrious family ; but having •quite ruined his eſtate, and rendered himſelf infamous by a ſeries of the moſt deteſtable crimes, he aſſociated with a number of others in circumſtances ſimilar to his own, in order to repair their broken fortunes by ruining their country. Their ſeheme was to murder the conſuls together with the greateſt part of the ſenators, ſet fire to the city in different places, and then ſeize the government. This wicked deſign miſcarried twice'; but was not on that account dropped by the conſpirators. Their party increaſed every day ; and both Cæſar and Craſſus, who ſince the departure of Pompey had ſtudied to gain the affections of the people as far as poſſible, were thought to have been privy to the conſpiracy. At laſt, however, the matter was diſcovered by means of a young knight, who had indiſe creetly revealed the ſecret to his paramour. Catiline then openly took the field, and ſoon raiſed a conſiderable army : but was utterly defeated and killed about 62 B. C. ; and thus the republic was freed from the preſent danger.</p><p>In the mean time, Cæſar continued to advance in popularity and in power. Soon after the defeat' of Catiline, he was created pontifex maximus ; and after that was ſent into Spain, where he ſubdued ſeveral nations that had never before been ſubject to Rome.— While he was thus employed, his rival Pompey returned from the eaſt, and was received with the higheſt honours ; but though ſtill as ambitious as ever, he now affected extraordinary modeſty, and declined accepting of the applauſe which was offered him. His aim was to aiſu e a ſovereign authority without ſeeming to deſire it ; but he was ſoon convinced, that, if he deſired to reign over his fellow-citizens, it muſt be by force of 'arms. He therefore renewed his intrigues, and ſpared no pains, however mean and ſcandalous, to increaſe his popularity. Cæſar, on his return from Spain, found the ſovereignty divided between Craſſus and Pompey, each of whom was ineffectually ſtruggling to get the better of the other. Cælar, no leſs ambitious than the other two, propoſed that they ſhould put an end to their differences, and take him for a partner in their power. In ihort, he projected a triumvirate, or aſſociation of three perſons, (Pompey, Craſſus, and himſelf), in which ſhould be lodged the whole power of the ſenate and people ; and, in order to .make their confederacy more laſting, they bound themſelves by mutual oaths and promiſes to ſtand by each other, and ſuffer nothing to be undertaken or carried into execution without the unanimous conſent of all the three.</p><p>Thus was the liberty of the Ro trans taken away a ſecond time, nor did they ever afterwards recover it .; though at preſent none perceived that this was the caſe,</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>