<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>camp at 50 Roman denarii <hi rend="italic">per</hi>  buſhel, that is, I 1. 12 s.</p><p>1 ⅛ d. ſterling. He tried to rebuild his bridges, hut in vain ; the violence of the ſtream rendering all his endeavours fruitleſs.</p><p>Upon the news of Cæſar’s diſtreſs, Pompey’s party at Rome began to .take courage. Several perſons of diſtinction went to congratulate Afranius’s wiſe on the ſucceſs of her huſhand’s arms in Spain. Many of the ſenators who had hitherto ſtood neuter, haſtened to Pompey’s camp, taking it for granted that Cæſar was reduced to the laſt extremity, and all hopes of his party loſt. Of this number was Cicero ; who, without any regard to the remonſlrances of Atticus, or the letters Cæſar himſelf wrote to him, deſiring him to join neither party, he leſt Italy, and landed at Dyrrhachium, where Pompey received him with great marks of joy and friendſhip. -But. the joy of pompey’s party was not long-lived. For Cæſar, after having attempted ſeveral times in vain to rebuild his bridges, cauſed boats to be made with all poſſible expedition ; and while the enemy were diverted by endeavouring to intercept the ſuccours that were ſent him from Gaul, he laid hold of that opportunity to convey his boats in the night on carriages 22 miles from his camp ; where with wonderful quickneſs a great detachment paſſed the Sicoris, and encamping on the oppoſite bank unknown to the enemy, built a bridge in two days, opened a communication with the neighbouring country, received the ſupplies ſrom Gaul, and relieved the wants of his ſoldiers. Cæſar being thus delivered from danger, purſued the armies of Afranius and Petreius with inch ſuperior addreſs and conduct, that he forced them to ſub-mſt without coming to a battle, and by that means became maſter of all Hither Spain. The two generals diſhanded their troops, ſent them out of the province, and returned to Italy, after having ſolemnly promiſed never to aſſemble forces again, or make war upon Cæſar. Upon the news of the reduction of Hither Spain, the Spaniards in Farther Spain, and one Roman legion, deſerted from Varro, Pompey’s governor in that province, which obliged him to ſurrender his other legion and all his,.money.</p><p>Cæſar having thus reduced all Spain in a few months, appointed Caſſius Longinus to govern the two provinces with four legions, and then returned to Marſeilles ; which city was juſt upon the point of ſurrendering after a moſt vigorous reſiſtance. Though the inhabitants had by their late treachery deſerved a ſevere puniſhment, yet he granted them their lives and liberty ; but ſtripped their arſenals of arms, and obliged them to deliver up «11 their ſhips.. From Marſeilles Cæſar marched into Ciſalpine Gaul ; and from thence haſtened to Rome, where he laid the foundation of his future grandeur. He found the city in a very different ſtate from that in which he had left it. Moſt of the ſenators and magiſtrates were fled to Pompey at Dyrrhachiυm. However, there were ſtill prætors there ; and among them M. Æmilius Lepidus, who was afterwards one of the triumvirs with Octavius and Marc Antony. The præ-tor, to ingratiate himſelf with Cæſar, nominated him dictator of his own authority, and againſt the inclination of the ſenate. Cæſar accepted the new dignity but neither abuſed his power, as Sylla had done, nor retained it ſo long. During the 11 days of his dictate! ſhip, he governed with great moderation, and gained the affections both of the people and tlrt patricians. He recalled the exiles, granted the rights and privileges of Roman citizens to all the Gauls beyond the Po, and, as pontifex maximus, filled up the vacancies of the ſa, cerdotal colleges with his own friends. Though it was expected that he would have abſolutely cancelled all debts contracted ſince the beginning of the troubles, he only reduced the intereſt to one-fourth. But the chief uſe he made of his dictatorſhip was to preſide at the election of conſuls for the next year, when he got himſelf, and Servilius Iſauricus, one of his moſt zealous par-tilans, promoted to that dignity.</p><p>And now being reſolved to follow Pompey, and carry the war into the eaſt, he ſet out for Brunduſium, whither he had ordered 12 leg∙ons to repair with all poſſible expedition. But on his arrival he found only five there. The reſt, being afraid of the dangers of the ſea, and unwilling to engage in a new war, had marched leiſurely, complaining of their general for allowing them no reſpite, but hurrying them continually from one country to another. However, Cæſar did not wait for them, but ſet ſail with only five legions and 600 horſe iu the beginning of January. While the reſt were waiting at Brunduſium for ſhips to tranſport them over into E-pirus, Cæſar arrived ſafe with his five legions in Chao-nia, the northern part of Epirus, near the Ceraunian mountains. There he landed his troops, and ſent the ſhips back to Brunduſium to bring over the legions that were left behind. The war he was now entering upon was the moſt difficult he had yet undertaken. Pompey had for a whole year been aſſembling troops from all the eaſtern countries. When he left Italy, he had only live legions ; but ſince his arrival at Dyrrhachium he had been reinforced with one from Sicily, another ſrom Crete, and two from Syria. Three thouſand archers, ſix cohorts of flingers, and ſeven thouſand horſe, had been ſent him by princes in alliance with Rome. All the free cities of Alia had reinforced his army with their beſt troops ; nay, if we give credit to an hiſtorical poet, ſuccours were brought him from the Indus and the Ganges to the eaſt, and from Arabia and Ethiopia to the ſouth ; at leaſt it is certain, that Greece, Aſia Minor, Syria, Paleſtine, Egypt, and all the nations ſrom the Mediterranean to the Euphrates, took up aι ms in his favour. He had almoſt all the Roman knights, that is, the flower of the young nobility, in his lqua∙ drons, and his legions conſiſted moſtly of veterans inured to dangers and the toils of war. Pompey himſelf was a general of great experience and addreſs ; and had under him ſome of the beſt commanders of the republic, who had formerly conducted armies themſelves. As for his navy, he had above 500 ſhips of war, beſides a far greater number of ſmall veſtels, which were continually cruiſing on the coaſts, and intercepted ſuch ſhips as carried arms or proviſions to the enemy. He had likewiſe with him above 2c0 ſenators, who formed a more  numerous ſenate than that at Rome. Cornelius Lentulus and Claudius Marcellus, the laſt year’s conſuls, preſided in it ; but under the direction of Pompey their protector, who ordered them to aſſemble at Theſ-ſalonica, where he built a ſtately hall for that purpoſe. There, in one of their aſſemblies, ,at the motion of Cato, it was decreed, that no Roman citizen ſhould be put to death but in battle, and that no city ſubject to the republic ſhould be lacked.. At the ſame tune the</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>