<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>reſolved to take ſignal vengeance of their diſobedience, and meditated new ſchemes of cruelty, when he ſell into ſuch faintings, as all believed were fatal. It was in this ſituation, that, by Macro’s advice, Caligula prepared to ſecure the ſucceſſion. He received the congratulations of the whole court, cauſed himſelf to be acknowledged by the Praetorian ſoldiers, and went forth from the emperor’s apartment amidſt the applauſes of the multitude ; when all of a ſudden hc was informed that the emperor was recovered, that he had besann to ſpeak, and deſired to eat. This unexpected account filled the whole court with terror and alarm : every one who had before been earneft in teſtifying their jov, now re-ailumed their pretended ſorrow, and left the new emperor, through a feigned ſolicitude ſor the ſate of the old. Caligula himſelf ſeemed thunder-ſtruck ; he preſerved a gloomy ſilence, expecting nothing but death, inſtead of the empire at which he had aſpired. Macro, however, who was hardened in crimes, ordered that the dying emperor ſhould be diſpatched, by ſmothering him with pillows, or, as others will have it, by poiſon. In this manner Tiberius died, in the 78th year of his age, after reigning 22.</p><p>The Romans were, at this time, arrived at their higheſt pitch of effeminacy and vice. The wealth of almoſt every nation of the empire, having, for ſome time, circulated through the city, brought with it the luxuries peculiar to each country ; ſo that Rome preſented a deteſtable picture of various pollution. In this reign lived Aρicius, ſo well khow<hi rend="sup">,</hi>n for having reduced gluttony into a ſyſtem ; ſome of the moſt notorious in this way, thought it no ſhame to give near ιco pounds for a ſingle fiſh, and exhauſt a fortune of 50,000 pounds in one entertainment. Debaucheries of every other kind kept pace with this ; while the deteſtable folly of the times thought it was refining upon pleaſure to make it unnatural. There were at Rome men called<hi rend="italic">ſpintriæ, w</hi>hoſe ſole trade it was to ſtudy new modes of pleaſure ; and theſe were univerſally favourites of the great. The ſenators were long fallen from their authority, and were no leſs eſtranged from their integrity and honour. Their whole ſtudy ſeemed to be, how to invent new ways of flattering the emperor, and various methods of tormenting his ſuppoſed enemies. The people were ſtill more corrupt : they had, for ſome years, been accuſtomed to live in idleneſs, upon the donations of the emperor ; and, being ſatisfied with ſeibſiſtence, entirely gave up their freedom. Too effeminate and cowardly to go to war, they only railed againſt their governors ; ſo that they were bad ſoldiers and ſeditious citizens. In the 18th year of this monarch’s reign, ∙Chrift was crucified. Shortly after his death, Pilate is ſaid to have written to Tiberius an account of his paſſion, reſurrection, and miracles ; upon which the emperor made a report of the whole to the ſenate, deſiring that Chriſt might be accounted a god by the Romans. But the ſenate being diſpleaſed that the propoſal had not come firſt from themſelves, reſuſed to allow of his apotheoſiS ; alleging an ancient law, which gave them the ſuperintendance in all matters of religion. They even went ſo far, as by an edict to command that all Chriſtians ſhould leave the city : but Tiberius, by another edict, threatened death to all ſuch as ſhould accuſe them ; by which means they continued unmoleſted during the reſt of his reign.</p><p>No monarch ever came to the throne with more advantages than Caligula. He was the ſon of Germanicus, who had been the darling of the army and the people. He was bred among the ſoldiers, from whom he received the name of <hi rend="italic">Caligula,</hi>  from the ſhort buſ-kin, called <hi rend="italic">cαligα,</hi>  that was worn by the common centinels, and which was alſo uſually worn by him. As hc approached Romç, the principal men of the ſtate went out in crowds to meet him. He received the congratulations of the people on every ſide, all equally pleaſed in being fee from the cruelties of Tiberius, and in hoping new advantages from the virtues of his ſucceffor.</p><p>Caligula ſeemed to take every precaution to impreſs them with the opinion of an happy change. Amidſt the rejoicings of the multitude, he advanced mourning, with the dead body of Tiberius, which the ſoldiers brought to be burnt at Rome, according to the cuſtom of that time. Upon his entrance into the city, he was received with new titles of honour by the ſenate, whoſe chief employτnent ſeemed now to be, the art of increaſing their emperor’s vanity. He was left co-heir with Gemellus, grandſon to Tiberius ; but they ſet aſide the nomination, and declared Caligula ſole ſucceffor to the empire. The joy for this election was not confined to the narrow bounds of Italy ; it ſpread through the whole empire, and victims without number were ſacrificed upon the occaſion. Some of the people, Upon his going into the iſland of Campania, made vows for his return; and ſhortly after, when he fell ſick, the multitudes crowded whole nights round his palace, and ſome even devoted themſelves to death in caſe he recovered, ſetting up bills of their reſolutions in the ſtreets. In this affection of the citizens, ſtrangers themſelves ſeemed ambitious of ſharing. Artabanus, king of Parthia, ſought the emperor’s alliance with aſſiduity. He came to a perſonal conference with one of his legates ; paſſed the Euphrates, adored the Roman eagles, and kiſſed the emperor’s images ; ſo that the whole wOrld ſeemed combined to praiſe him for virtues which they ſuppoſed him to poſſeſs.</p><p>I hc new emperor at firſt ſeemed extremely careful of the public favour ; and having performed the funeral ſolemnities of Tiberius, he haſtened to the iſlands of Pandataria and Pontia, to remove the aſhes of his mother and brothers, expofing himſelf to the dangers of tempeſtuous weather, to give a luſtre to his piety. Having brought them to Rome, he inſtituted annual ſolemnities in their honour, and ordered the month of September to be called <hi rend="italic">Germαηi</hi>∣<hi rend="italic">  us,</hi>  in memory of his father. Theſe ceremonies being over, he conferred the ſame honours upon his grandmother Antonia, which had before been given to Livia ; and ordered all informations to be burnt', that any ways expoſed the enemies of his family. He even refuſed a paper that was offered him, tending to the diſcovery of a conſpiracy againſt him; alleging, That he was conſeious of nothſhg to defetve any man’s hatred, and therefore had no fears from their machinations. He cauſed the inſtitutions of Auguſtus, which had been diſetſed in the reign of Tiberius, to be revived ; undertook to reform many abuſes in the ſtate, and ſeverely puniſhed corrupt governors. Among others, he baniſhed Pontius Pilate into Gaul, where firs unjuſt magiſtrate afterwards put an· end to his Uſe by ſuicide. He baniſhed the ſpintriæ,</p><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>