<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>CF</p><p>equally reſiſting fibre at F, muſt be ≈=∕× ς∙^r. And ſo on of all the reſt.</p><p>If we ſuppoſe all the fibres to exert equal reſiſtances at the inſtant of fracture, we know, from the ſimpleſt elements of mechanics, that the reſiſtance of all the particles in the line CD, each acting equally in its own place, is the ſame as if all the individual reſiſtances were united in the middle point <hi rend="italic">g.</hi>  Now this total reſiſtance is the reſiſtance or ſtrength<hi rend="italic">ſ</hi>of each particle, multiplied by the number of particles. This number may be expreſſed by the line CD, becauſe we have no reaſon to ſuppoſe that they are at unequal diſtances. Therefore, in comparing different ſections together, the number of particles in each are as the ſections themſelves. Therefore DC may repreſent the number of particles in the line DC'. Let us call this line the depth of the beam, and expreſs it by the ſymbol <hi rend="italic">ci.</hi>  And ſince we are at preſent treating of roofs whole rafters and other parts are commonly of uniform breadth, let us call AH or BI the breadth of the beam, and expreſs it by <hi rend="italic">b,</hi>  and let CA be called its length, <hi rend="italic">l.</hi>  We may now expreſs the ſtrength of the whole line CD by <hi rend="italic">f~&gt;id,</hi>  and we may ſuppoſe it all concentrated in the middle point <hi rend="italic">g. </hi>Its mechanical energy, therefore, by which it reſiſts the energy of the weight <hi rend="italic">vυ,</hi>  applied at the diſtance ∕, is<hi rend="italic">ſ.</hi>  CD. Cy, while the momentum of <hi rend="italic">w</hi>  is <hi rend="italic">w.</hi>  CA. We muſt therefore have <hi rend="italic">ſ.</hi>  CD. Cy=∞. CA, or <hi rend="italic">fd.fd z= nv.</hi>  ∕, and <hi rend="italic">fd : <hi rend="sup">r</hi>w~ I</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">ſd '. <hi rend="sup">r</hi>w~ 2l : &lt;l.</hi>  That is, twice the length of the beam is to its depth as the abſolute ſtrength of one of its vertical planes to its relative ſtrength, or its pow<hi rend="sup">,</hi>er of reſiſting this tranſverſe fracture.</p><p>It is evident, that what has been now demonſtrated of the reſiſtance exerted in the line CD, is equally true of every line parallel to CD in the thickneſs or breadth of the beam. The abſolute ſtrength of the whole ſection of fracture is properly repreſented by <hi rend="italic">f. d. b<hi rend="sub">i</hi></hi>  and we ſtill have 2/ : <hi rend="italic">d—ſdb</hi>  : ⅛&gt;.,∙ or twice the length of the beam is to its depth as the abſolute ſtrength to the relative ſtrength. Suppoſe the beam 12 feet long and one foot deep ; then whatever is its abſolute ſtrength, the 24th part of this will break it if hung at its extremity.</p><p>But even this is too favourable a ſtatement ; all the fibres are ſuppoſed to meet alike in the inſtant of fracture. But this is not true. At the inſtant that the fibre at D breaks, it is ſtretched to the utmoſt, and is exerting its whole force. But at this inſtant the fibre at <hi rend="italic">g</hi>  is not ſo much ſtretched, and it is not then exerting its utmoſt force. If we ſuppoſe the extenſion of the fibres to be as their diſtance from C, and the actual exertion, of each to be as their extenſions, it may eaſily be ſhown (ſee Strength and Strain), that the whole reſiſtance is the ſame as if the full force of all the fibres were united at a point <hi rend="italic">r</hi>  diſtant from C by one third of CD. In this caſe we muſt ſay, that the abſolute ſtrength is to the relative ſtrength as three times the length to the depth ; ſo that the beam is wêaker than by the former ſtatement in the proportion of two to three.</p><p>Even this is more ſtrength than experiment juſtiſies ; and we can ſee an evident reaſon for it. When the beam is ſtrained, not only are the upper fibres ſtretched, but the lower fibres are compreſſed. This is</p><lb/><p>very diſtinctly ſeen, if we attempt to break a piece oſ cork cut into the ſhape of a beam : this being the caſe,</p><p>C is not the centre of fracture. There is ſome point <hi rend="italic">c </hi>which lies between the fibres which are ſtretched and thoſe that are compreſſed. This fibre is neither ſtretched nor ſqueezed ; and this point is the real centre of fracture : and the lever by which a fibre D reſiſts, is not DC, but a ſhorter one Dr; and the energy of the whole reſiſtances muſt be leſs than by the ſecond ſtatement. Till we know the proportion between the dilatability and compreſſibility of the parts, apd the relation between the dilatations of the fibres and the reſiſtances which they exert in this ſtate of dilatation, we cannot poſitively ſay where the point <hi rend="italic">c</hi>  is ſituated, nor what is the ſum of the actual reſiſtances, or the point where their action may be ſuppoſed concentrated. The firmer w<hi rend="sup">,</hi>oods, ſuch as oak and cheſnut, may be ſuppoſed to be but ffightly compreſſible ; we know that willow and other ſoft woods are very comprejſible. Theſe laſt muſt therefore be weaker : for it is evident, that the fibres which are in a ſtate of compreſſion do nqt reſiſt the fracture. It is well known, that a beam of willow may be cut through from C to<hi rend="italic">g</hi>  without weakening it in the leaſt, if the cut be filled up by a wedge of hard wood ſtuck in</p><p>We can only ſay, that very ſound oak and red fir have the centre of effort ſo ſituated, that the abſolute ſtrength is to the relative ſtrength in a proportion not leſs than that of three and a half times the length of the beam to its depth. .-∖ ſquare inch of found oak will carry about 8000 pounds. If this bar be firmly fixed in a wall, and project 12 inches, and be loaded at the extremity with 200 pounds, it will be broken. It will juſt bear 190, its relative ſtrength being -<hi rend="sub">3</hi>∙<hi rend="sup">,</hi>-<hi rend="sub">r</hi> of its abſolute ſtrength ; and this is the caſe only with the ſineſt pieces, ſo placed that their annual plates or layers are in a vertical poſition. A larger log is not fo ſtrong tranſverſely, becauſe its plates lie in various directions round the heart.</p><p>Theſe obſervations are enough to give us a diſtinct notion of the vaſt diminution of the ſtrength of timber when the ſtrain is acroſs it ; and w<hi rend="sup">,</hi>e ſee the juſtice of the maxim which we inculcated, that the carpenter, in framing roofs, ſhould avoid as much as poſſible the ex-poſing his timbers to tranſverſe ſtrains. But this cannot be avoided in all caſes. Nay, the ultimate ſtrain, ariſing ſrom the very nature of a roof, is tranſverſe. The rafters muſt carry their own weight, and this tends to break them acroſs : an oak beam a foot deep will not carry its own weight if it project more than 60 ſeet. Beſides this, the rafters muſt carry the lead, tyling, or fiâtes. We muſt therefore conſider this tranſverſe ſtrain a little more particularly, ſo as to know what ſtrain will be laid on any part by an unavoidable load, laid on either at that part or at any other.</p><p>We have hitherto ſuppoſed, that the beam had one of its ends fixed in a wall, and that it was loaded at the other end. This is not an uſual arrangement, and was taken merely as affording a ſimple application of the mechanical principles. It is much more uſual to have the beam ſupported at the ends, and loaded in the middle. Let the beam FEGH (ſig. 2.) reſt on the props E and G, and be loaded at its middle point C with a weight W. It is required to determine t he ſtrain at the ſection CD ? It is plain that the beam will</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>