<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>than the Caralitini, now the inhabitants of Cagliari, drove out Aurelius Cotta, who commanded there for the ſenate, and put Cæſar’s lieutenant in poſſeſſion both of their city and iſland.</p><p>In the mean time the general himſelſ advanced towards Rome ; and on his march wrote to all the ſenators then in Italy, deſiring them to repair to the capital, and aſſiſt him with their counſel. Above all, he was deſirous to ſee Cicero ; but could not prevail upon him to return to Rome. As Cæſar drew near the capital, he quartered his troops in the neighbouring mu-nicipia ; and then advancing to the city, out of a pretended reſpect to the ancient cuſtoms, he took up his quarters in the ſuburbs, whether the whole city crowded to ſee the famous conqueror of Gaul, who had been abſent near ten years. And now ſuch of the tribunes of the people as had fled to him for refuge reaſſumed their functions, mounted the roſtra, and endeavoured by their ſpeeches to reconcile the people to the head of their party. Marc Antony particularly, and' Caſſius Longinus, two of Cæſar’s moſt zealous partiſans, moved that the ſenate ſhould meet in the ſuburbs, that the general might give them an account of his conduct. Accordingly, ſuch of the ſenators as were at Rome aſſembled ; when Cæſar made a ſpeech in juſtiſication of all his proceedings, and concluded his harangue with pro-pofing a deputation to Pompey, with offers of an accommodation in an amicable manner. He even deſired the conſcript fathers, to whom in appearance he paid great deference, to nominate ſome of their venerable body to carry propofals of peace to the conſuls, and the general of the conſular'army ; but none of the ſenators would take upon him that commiſſion. He then began to think of providing himſelf with the neceſſary ſums ſor carrying on the war, and had recourſe to the public treaſury. But Metellus, one of the tribunes, oppoſed him ; alleging a law forbidding any one to open the treaſury, but in the preſence and with the conſent of the conſuls. Cæſar, however, without regarding the tribune, went directly to the temple of Saturn, where the public money was kept. But the keys of the treaſury having been carried away by the conſul Lentulus, he ordered the doors to be broken open. This Metellus oppoſed : but Cæſar, in a paſſion, laying his hand on his ſword, threatened to kill him if he gave him any farther diſturbance ; which ſo terrified Metellus, that he withdrew. Cæſar took out of the treaſury, which was ever after at his command, an immenſe ſum ; fς&gt;me ſay, 300,000 pounds weight of gold. With this ſupply of money he raiſed troops all over Italy, and ſent governors into all the provinces ſubject to the republic.</p><p>Cæſar now made Marc Antony commander in chief of the armies in Italy, ſent his brother C. Antonins to govern Illyricum, aſſigned Ciſalpine Gaul to Licinius Craſſus, appointed M. Æmilius Lepidus governor of the capital ; and having got together ſome ſhips to cruiſe in the Adriatic and Mediterranean ſeas, he gave the command of one of his fleets to P. Cornelius Dolabella, and of the other to young Hortenſins, the ſon of the famous orator. As Pompey had ſent governors into the ſame provinces, by this means a general war was kindled in almoſt all the parts of the known world. However, Cæſar would not truſt any of his lieutenants with the conduct of the war in Spain, which was Pompey’s favourite province, but took it upon himſelf ; and having ſettled his affairs in great haſte at Rome, returned to Ariminum, aſſembled his legions there, and paſſing the Alps, entered Tranſalpine Gaul. There he was informed that the inhabitants of Marſeilles had reſolved to refuſe him entrance into their city ; and that L. Domitius Ahenobarbus, whom he had generouſly pardoned and ſet at liberty after the reduction of Corfinium, had ſet ſail for Marſeilles with ſeven galleys, having on board a great number of his clients and ſlaves, with a deſign to raiſe the city in favour of Pompey. Cæſar, thinking it dangerous to let the enemy take poſſeſſion of ſuch an important place, ſent for the 15 chief magiſtrates of the city, and adviſed them not to begin a war with him, but rather follow the example of Italy, and ſubmit. The magiſtrates returned to the city, and ſoon after informed him that they were to ſtand neuter ; but in the mean time Domitius arriving with his ſmall ſquadron, was received into the city, and declared general of all their forces. Hereupon Cæſar immediately inveſted the town with three legions, and ordered twelve galleys to be built at Arelas, now <hi rend="italic">Arles, </hi>in order to block up the port. But as the ſiege was like to detain him too long, he left C. Trebonius to carry it on, and D. Brutus to command the fleet, while he continued his march into Spain, where he began the war with all the valour, ability, and ſucceſs of a great general. Pompey had three generals in this continent, which was divided into two Roman provinces. V;ſrro commanded in Farther Spain ; and Petreius and Afranius, with equal power, and two conſiderable armies, in Hither Spain. Cæſar, while he was yet at,Marſeilles, ſent Q. Fabius, one of his lieutenants, with three legions, to take poſſeſſion of the paſſes of the Pyrenees, which Afranius had ſeized. Fabius executed his commiſſion with great bravery, entered Spain, and left the way open for Cæſar, who quickly followed him. As ſoon as he had croſſed the mountains, he ſent out ſcouts to obſerve the ſituation of the enemy ; by whom he was informed, that Afranius and Petreius having joined their forces, conſiſting of five legions, 20 cohorts of the natives, and 5000 horſe, were advantageouſly poſted on an hill of a¾ eaſy aſcent in the neighbourhood of Ilerda, now <hi rend="italic">Lerida<hi rend="sub">t </hi></hi>in Catalonia. Upon this advice Cæſar advanced within light of the enemy, and encamped in a plain between the Sicoris and Cinga, now the <hi rend="italic">Sεgro</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">Cincα.</hi>  Between the eminence on which Afranius had poſted himſelf, and the city of Ilerda, was a ſmall plain, and in the middle of it a riſing ground, which Cæſfar attempted to ſeize, in order to cut off by that means the communication between the enemy’s camp and the city, from whence they had all their proviſions. This occaſioned a iharp diſpute between three of Cæſar’s legions and an equal number of the enemy, which laſted five hours with equal ſucceſs, both parties claiming the victory. But after all, Afranius’s men, who had firſt ſeized the poſt, maintained themſelves in poſſeſſion of it in ſpite of Cæſar’s utmoſt efforts. Two days after this battle, continual rains, with the melting of the ſnow on the mountains, ſo ſwelled the two rivers between which Cæſar was encamped, that they overflowed, broke down his bridges, and laid under water the neighbouring country to a great diſtance. ſhis cut off the communication between his camp and the cities tlrat had declared for him ; and reduced him to ſuch ſtraits, that his army was ready to die for famine, wheat being ſold in his</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>