<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>been highly pleaſing to Antony, as Hiparchus had left him to join the fortunes of his more ſucceſsful rival.</p><p>Meanwhile, the operations of the war were carried vigorouſly forward, and Egypt was once more the theatre of the contending armies of Rome. Gallus, the lieutenant of Oéfavianus, took Paretonium, which opened the whole country to his incurſions. On the other ſide, Antony, who had ſtill conſiderable forces by ſea and land, wanted to take that important place from the enemy. He therefore marched towards it, flattering himſelf, that as ſoon as he ſhould ſhow himſelf to the legions which he had once commanded, their affection for their ancient general would revive. He approached, therefore, and exhorted them to remember their former vows of fidelity. Gallus, however, ordered all the trumpets to ſound, in order to hinder Antony from being heard, ſo that he was obliged to retire.</p><p>Octavianus himſelf was in the mean time advancing with another army before Peluſium, which, by its ſtrong ſituation, might have retarded his progreſs for ſo ne time. But the governor of the city, either wanting courage to defend it, or previouſly inſtructed by Cleopatra to give it up, permitted him to take poſſeſſion of the place ; ſo that Octavianus had now no obſtacle in his way to Alexandria, whither he marched with all expedition. Antony, upon his arrival, ſallied out to oppoſe him, fighting with great deſperation, and putting the enemy’s cavalry to flight. This flight advantage once more revived his declining hopes ; and, being naturally vain, he re-entered Alexandria in triumph. Then going, all armed as he was, to the palace, he embraced Cleopatra, and preſented her a ſoldier who had diſtinguiſhed himſelf in the late engagement. The queen rewarded him very magnificently ; preſenting him with an head-piece and breaft~plate of gold. With theſe, however, the ſoldier went off the next night to the other army. /Antony could not bear this defection without freſh indignation ; he reſolved, therefore, to make a bold expiring effort by ſea and land, but previouſly offered to ſight his adverſary in ſingle combat. Octavianus too well knew the inequality of their ſituations to comply with this forlorn offer ; he only<hi rend="sub">r</hi> therefore, coolly replied, that Antony had ways enough to die beſides ſingle combat.</p><p>The evening before the day appointed for the laſt deſperate attempt, he ordered a grand entertainment to be prepared. At day-break he poſted the few troops he had remaining upon a riſing ground near the city : from whence he ſent orders to his galleys to engage the enemy. There he waited to be a ſpectator of the combat ; and, at firſt, he had the ſatisfaction to ſee them advance in good order ; but his approbation was ſoon turned into rage, when he ſaw his ſhips only ſaluting thoſe of Octavianus, and both fleets uniting together, and foiling back into the harbour. At the very ſame time his cavalry deſerted him. He tried, however, to lead on his infantry ; which were eaſily vanquiſhed, and he himſelf compelled to return into the town. His anger was now ungovernable ; he could not help crying out aloud as he paſſed, that he was betrayed by Cleopatra, and delivered by her to thoſe who, for her ſake alone, were his enemies. In theſe ſuſpicions he was not deceived ; for it was by ſecret orders from the queen that the fleet had paſſed over to the enemy.</p><p>Cleopatra had, ſor a long while, dreaded the effects of Antony’s jealouſy ; and had, ſome time before, prepared a method of obviating any ſudden follies it might produce. Near the temple of lſis ſhe had erected a building, which was ſeemingly deſigned for a ſepulchre. Hither ſhe removed all her treaſure and moſt valuable effects, covering them over with torches, faggots, and other combuſtible matter. This ſepulchre ſhe deſigned to anſwer a double purpoſe ; as well to ſcreen her from the ſudden reſentments of Antony, as to make Octavianus believe that ſhe would burn all her treaſures in caſe he refuſed her proper terms of capitulation. Here, therefore, ſhe retired from Antony’s preſent fury ; (hutting the gates, which were fortified with bolts and bars of iron : but in the mean time gave orders that a report ſhould be ſpread of her death.— This news, which ſoon reached Antony, recalled all his former love and tenderneſs. He now lamented her death with the ſame violence he had but a few minutes before ſeemed to deſire it ; and called one of his freed-men, named <hi rend="italic">Eros,</hi>  whom he had engaged by oath to kill him whenever fortune ſhould drive him to this laſt reſource. Eros being now commanded to perform his promiſe, this faithful follower drew the ſword, as if going to execute hie orders ; but turning his face, plunged it into his own boſom, and died at his maſter’s feet. Antony for a while hung over his faithful ſer-vant, and, commending his fidelity, took up the ſword, with which ſtabbing himſelf in the belly, he fell backward upon a little couch. Though the wound was mortal, yet the blood ſtopping he recovered his ſpirits, and earneſtly conjured thoſe who were come into the room to put an end to his life ; but they all fled, being ſeized with fright and horror. He therefore continued in agonies for ſome time ; till he was informed by one of the queen’s ſecretaries that his miſtreſs was ſtill alive. He then earneſtly deſired to be carried to the place where ſhe was. They accordingly brought him to the gate of the ſepulchre ; but Cleopatra, who would not permit it to be opened, appeared at the window, and threw down cords in order to pull him up. In this manner, aſſiſted by her two female attendants, ſhe raiſed him all bloody from the ground ; and while yet fuſpended in the air, he continued ſtretching out his-hands to encourage her. Cleopotra and her maids had only juſt ſtrength ſufficient to raiſe him ; and at laſt, with much ſtraining, they effected their purpoſe, and carried him to a couch, on which they gently laid him. Here ſhe gave way to her ſorrow, tearing her clothes, beating her breaſt, and kiſſing the wound of which he was dying. She called upon him as her lord, her huſhand, her emperor, and ſeemed to have forgot her own diſtreſſes in the greatneſs of his ſufferings, Antony entreated her to moderate the tranſports of her grief, and allied for ſome wine. After he had drank, he entreated Cleopatra to endeavour to preſerve her life, if ſhe could do it with honour ; and recommended Proculus, a friend of Octavianus, as one ſhe might rely on to be her interceſſor. Juſt as he had done ſpeaking, he expired ; and Proculus made his appearance by command of Octavianus, who had been informed of Antony’s deſperate conduct. He was ſent to try all means of getting Cleopatra into his power ; his maſter having a double motive for his ſolicitude on this occaſion ; one, to prevent her deſtroying the treaſures ſhe had taken with her into the tomb j the other,</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>