<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>king of Parthia. There entering the opulent kingdom of Mefoρυtamia, he reduced it into the form of a Roman province. From thence he went againſt the Pap∙ thians, marching on foot at the head of his army ; in this manner croſſing the rivers, and conforming to all the ſeverities of diſcipline which were impoſed on the meaneſt ſoldier. His ſucceſſes againſt the Parthians were great and numerous. He conquered Syria and Chaldea, and took the famous city of Babylon. Here, attempting to crois the Euphrates, he was oppoſed by the enemy, who were reſolved to ſtop his paſſage : but he ſecretly cauſed boats to be made upon the adjoining mountains; and bringing them to the water ſide, paſſed his army with great expedition, not, however, without great ſlaughter on both ſides. From thence he tra-verſed tracts of country which had never before been invaded by a Roman army, and ſeemed to take a pleaſure in purſuing the ſame march which Alexander the Great had formerly marked out for him. Having paſſed the rapid ſtreams of the Tigris, he advanced to the city Cteſiphon, which he took, and opened himſelf a paſſage into Perlia, where he made many conqueſts, that were rather ſplendid than ſerviceable. After ſubduing all the country bordering on the Tigris, he marched ſouthward to the Perſian gulph, where he ſubdued a monarch who poſſeſſed a conſiderable iſland made by the divided ſtreams of that river. Here, winter coming on, he was in danger of loſing the greateſt part of his army by the inclemency of the climate and the inundations of the river. He therefore with indefatigable pains fitted out a fleet, and ſailing down the Perſian gulph, entered the Indian ocean, conquering, even to the Indies, and ſubduing a part of them to the</p><p>Roman empire. He was prevented from purſuing further conqueſts in this diſtant country, both by the revolt of many of the provinces he had already ſubdued, and by the ſcarcity of proviſions, which ſeemed to contradict the reports of the fertility of the countries he was induced to invade. The inconveniences of increaſing age alſo contributed to damp the ardour of this enterpriſe, which at one time he intended to purſue to the confines of the earth. Returning, therefore, along the Perſian gulph, and ſending the ſenate a particular account of all the nations he had conquered, the names of which alone compoſed a long catalogue, he prepared to puniſh thoſe countries which had revolted from him. He began by laying the famous city of Edeſſa, in Me-ſopotamia, in allies ; and in a ſhort ſpace of time, not only retook all thoſe places which had before acknowledged ſubjection, but conquered many other provinces, ſo as to make himſelf maſter of the moſt fertile kingdoms of all Aſia. In this train of ſucceſſes he ſcarce met with a repulſe, except before the city Atra, in the deſerts of Arabia. Wherefore judging that this was a proper time for bounding his conqueſts, he reſolved to give a maſter to the countries he had ſubdued. With this reſolution he repaired to the city Cteſiphon, in. Rerſia ; and there, with great ceremony, crowned Par-thamaſpates king of Parthia, to the great joy of all his ſubjects. Fie eſtabliſhed another king alſo over the kingdom of Albania, near the Caſpian ſea. Then placing governors and lieutenants in other provinces, he reſolved to return to his capital in a more magnificent manner than any of his predeceſſors had done before him. He accordingly leſt Adrian general of ail</p><lb/><p>his forces in the eaſt ; and continued his journey towards Rome, where the moſt magnificent preparations were made for his arrival. However, he had not got farther than the province of Cilicia, when he found himſelf too weak to proceed in his uſual manner. He therefore cauſed himſelf to be carried on ſhip-board to the city of Seleucia, where he died of the apoplexy, having been attacked by that diſorder once before. During the time of his indiſpoſition, his wife Plotina conſtantly attended near him ; and, knowing the emperor’s diſlike to Adrian, it is thought forged the will, by which, he was adopted to ſucceed.</p><p>Trajan died in the 63d year of his age, after a reign of nineteen years ſix months and fifteen days. How highly he was eſteemed by his ſubjects appears by their manner of bleſſing his ſucceſſors, always wiſhing them the fortune of Auguſtus, and the goodneſs of Trajan. His military virtues, however, upon which he chiefly valued himſelf, produced no real advantages to his country ; and all his conqueſts diſappeared, when the power was withdrawn that enforced them.</p><p>Adrian was by deſcent a Spaniard, and his anceſtors were of the ſame city where Trajan was born. He was nephew to Trajan, and married to Sabina∣his grand-niece. When Trajan was adopted to the empire, Adrian was a tribune of the army in Maeſia, and was ſent by the troops to congratulate the emperor on his advancement. However, his brother-in-law, who deſired to have an opportunity of congratulating Trajan himſelf, ſupplied Adrian with a carriage that broke down on the way. But Adrian w<hi rend="sup">,</hi>as reſolved to loſe no time, and performed the reſt of the journey on foot. This aſſiduity was very pleaſing to the emperor ; but he diſliked Adrian from ſeveral more prevailing motives. His kinſman was expenſive, and involved in debt. He was, beſides, inconſtant, capricious, and apt to envy another’s reputation. Theſe were faults, that, in Trajan’s opinion, could not be compenſated either by his learning or his talents. His great ſkill in the Greek and Latin languages, his intimate acquaintance with the laws of lſis country and the philoſophy of the times, were no inducement to Trajan, who, being bred himſelf a ſoldier, deſired to have a military man to ſucceed him. For this reaſon it was that the dying emperor would by no means appoint a ſucceſſor ; fearful, perhaps, of injuring his great reputation, by adopting a perſon that was unworthy. His death, therefore, was concealed for ſome time by Plotina his wiſe, till Adrian had founded the inclinations of the army, and found them firm in his intereſts. 'Γhey then produced a forged inſtrument, importing that Adrian was adopted to ſucceed in the empire. By this artifice he was elected by-all orders of the ſtate, though then abſent from Rome, being left at Antioch as general of the forces in the eaſt.</p><p>Upon Adrian’s election, his firſt care was to write the ſenate, excuſing himſelf for aſſuming the empire without their previous approbation ; imputing it to the haſty zeal of the army, who rightly judged that the ſenate ought not long to remain without a head. He then began to purſeie a courſe quite oppoſite to that of his predeceſſor, taking every method of declining war, and promoting the arts of peace. He was quite ſatisfied with preſerving the ancient limits of the empire, and ſeemed no way ambitious of extenſive conqueſt.</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>