<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ſection to the magnitude of the rubbing part, but made no change on the ratio of the velocities. This is a thing which no theory could point out.</p><p>Another moſt important fact was alſo the reſult of his obſervation, viz. that <hi rend="italic">the mean velocity in any pipe or openflream is the arithmetical mean between the velocity in the axis and the velocity at the ltdes of a pipe or bottom of an open flream.</hi>  We have already obſerved, that the ratio of the velocity in the axis to the velocity at the bottom diminiſhed as the mean velocity increaſed. This variation he was enabled to expreſs in a very ſimple manner, ſo as to be eaſily remembered, and to enable us to tell any one of them by obſerving another.</p><p><hi rend="italic">If we take unity from the ſquare root of the ſuperficial velocity, expreſſed in inches, the ſquare of the remainder is the velocity at the bottom ; and the mean velocity is the half ſum of theſe two.</hi>  Thus, if the velocity in the middle of the ſtream be 25 inches per ſecond, its ſquare root is five ; from which if we take unity, there remains four. The ſquare of this, or · 16, is the velocity at</p><p>25 -J- 16</p><p>the bottom, and----’ or 20⅜, is the mean velo</p><p>city.</p><p>This is a very curious and moſt uſeful piece of information. The velocity in the middle of the ſtream is the eaſieſt meaſured of all, by<hi rend="sup">4</hi>any light ſmall body floating down it ; and the mean velocity is the one which regulates the train, the diſcharge, the effect on machines, and all the moſt important conſequences.</p><p>We may expreſs this by a formula of moſt eaſy recollection. Let V be the mean velocity, <hi rend="italic">v</hi>  the velocity in the axis, and <hi rend="italic">u</hi>  the velocity at the bottom ; we</p><p>—; —---x    <hi rend="italic">v -}- u</hi></p><p>have <hi rend="italic">u — </hi><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps">ύ</hi></hi><hi rend="italic">  v —</hi>  1, and V = —— <hi rend="sub">#</hi></p><p>Alſo <hi rend="italic">v</hi>  = (√v —4 + i)∖ and &lt;y = (√~ + ι)±. V=(√⅛⅝ andV= (√<hi rend="sub">a</hi>+l)<hi rend="sup">4</hi>+ι.</p><p>« ~ (√^-~ <hi rend="underline">x)<hi rend="sup">ι</hi>  an</hi>d <hi rend="italic">u</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">  ≈ (<hi rend="sub">λ</hi>∕V-∣~4)</hi><hi rend="sup">l</hi>∙</p><p>Alſo <hi rend="italic">v—u —</hi>  2 √<hi rend="sup">,</hi>v_⅛ and <hi rend="sup">ν</hi>  — V, = V — », —</p><p>√V-√ = that is, the difference between theſe velocities increaſes in the ratio of the ſquare roots of the mean velocities diminiſhed by a ſmall conſtant quantity.</p><p>This may perhaps give the mathematicians ſome help in aſcertaining the law ol degradation from the axis to the ſides. Thus, in a cylindrical pipe, we may conceive the current as conſiſting of an infinite number of cylindrical ſhells Aiding within each other like the draw tubes of a ſpy-glaſs. Each of theſe is in equilibrio, or as much accelerated by the one within it as it is retarded by the one without ; therefore as the <hi rend="italic">momentum </hi>of each diminiſhes in the proportion of its diameter (the thickneſs being ſuppoſed the ſame in all), the ve-locitv of ſeparation muſt increaſe by a certain law from the ſides to the axis. The magnitude of the ſmall conſtant quantity here ſpoken of ſeems to fix this law.</p><p>The place of the mean velocity could not be diſcovered with any preciſion. In moderate velocities it was not more than one-fourth or one-fifth of the depth diſtant from the bottom. In very great velocities it was ſenſibly higher, but never in the middle of the depth.</p><p>The knowledge of theſe three velocities is of great importance. The ſuperſlcial velocity is eaſily obſerved; hence the mean velocity is eaſily computed. This multiplied by the ſection gives the expence ; and if we alſo . meaſure the expanded border, and then obtain the mean depth (or ), we can, by the formula of uniform motion, deduce the ſlope ; or, knowing the ſlope, we can. deduce any of the other circumſtances.</p><p>The following table of theſe three velocities will ſave the trouble of calculation in one of the moſt frequent-·, queſtions of hydrauliç».</p></body></text></TEI>