<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>are ſuppoſed to know the diſcharge of the river and its ſlope and other circumſtances before barring it with a dam ; and we know the height of the dam Η, and therefore the new velocity at A, or immediately above A, and conſequently the ſlope S. Therefore, drawing the horizontal lines DC, AG, it is plain that CB and CA will be the primary ſlope of the river, and the ſlope S correſponding to the velocity in the immediate neighbourhood of A, becauſe theſe verticals have the ſame horizontal diſtance DC. We have therefore CB : CA <hi rend="italic">= S : s very</hi>  nearly, and S—<hi rend="italic">s : s—</hi>  CB—CA : CA,</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">„    ABXj</hi></p><p>=AB (nearly) : CA. Therefore CA = g—y &gt;== -Q——. But DA≈CA×S, by our definition of</p><p>O — <hi rend="italic">S</hi></p><p><hi rend="sub">λ</hi> H.S.χ ſlope; therefore D A=~g—y~</p><p>This is all that we can ſay with preciſion of this curve. Mr Buat examined what would reſult from ſuppoſing it an arch of a circle. In this caſe we ſhould "have DA=DF, and AF very nearly equal to 2 AD : and as we can thus find AD, we get the whole length FIA of the ſwell, and alſo the diſtances of any part of the curve from the primitive ſurface FB of the river ; for theſe will be very nearly in the duplicate proportion of their diſtances from F. Thus ID will be 4 of AB, &amp;c. Therefore we ſhould obtain the depth I <hi rend="italic">cl</hi>  of the ſtream in that place. Getting the depth of the ſtream, and knowing the diſcharge, we get the velocity, and can compare this with the Hope of the ſurface at 1. This ſhould be the ſlope of that part of the arch of the circle. Making this compariſon, he found theſe circumſtances to be incompatible. He found that the fec-* ion and ſwell at I, correſponding to an arch of a circle, gave a diſcharge nearly fith too great (they were as 405216 to 492142). Therefore the curve is ſuch, that AD is greater than DF, and that it is more incur-vated at F than at A. He found, that making DA to DF as 10 to 9, and the curve FIA an arch oſ an ellipſe whoſe longer axis was vertical, would give a very nice correſpondence of the ſections, velocities, and ſlopes. The whole extent of the ſwell therefore can never be double of AD, and muſt always greatly ſur-paſs AD ; and theſe limits will do very well for every practical queſtion. Therefore making DF <hi rend="sub">τ</hi>⅜ of AD, and drawing the chord AD, and making DI fi- of D r, we ſhall be very near the truth. Then we get the ſwell with ſufficient preciſion for any point H between F and D, by making FD<hi rend="sup">2</hi>  : FH<hi rend="sup">i</hi>  — ID : H<hi rend="italic">h ;</hi>  and if H is between D and A, we get its diſtance from the tangent DA by a ſimilar proceſs.</p><p>It only remains to determine the ſwell produced in the waters of a river by the erection of a bridge or cleaning ſluice which contracts the paſſage. This requires the ſolution of</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Prob. V. Given the depth, breadth, and ſlope of a river, to determine the ſwell occaſioned by the piers of a bridge or ſides of a cleaning ſluice, which contract the paſſage by a given quantity, for a given length of channel.</hi></p><p>This ſwell depends on two circumſtances.</p><p>1.    The whole river muſt paſs through a narrow ſpace, with a velocity proportionably increaſed ; and this requires a certain head of water above the bridge.</p><p>2.    The water, in paſſing the length of the piers with a velocity greater than that correſponding to the primary ſlope of the river, will require a greater ſlope in order to acquire this velocity.</p><p>Let V be the velocity of the river before the erection of the bridge, and K the quotient of the width of the river divided by the ſum of the widths between the piers. If the length of the piers, or their dimenſion in the direction of the ſtream, is not very great, KV will nearly expreſs the velocity of the river under the arches; and if we ſuppoſe for a moment the contraction (in the ſenſe hitherto uſed) to be nothing, the height produ-</p><p>K<hi rend="sup">i</hi> V*</p><p>cing this velocity will be -. But the river will</p><p><hi rend="sup">2</hi>-<hi rend="sup">ξr</hi></p><p>not riſe ſo high, having already a ſlope and velocity before getting under the arches, and the height correſponding to this velocity is — ; therefore the height</p><p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="sup">2</hi>g</hi></p><p>K<hi rend="sup">l</hi> V<hi rend="sup">1</hi></p><p>for producing the augmentation of velocity is—_-</p><p>V<hi rend="sup">,</hi>    &amp; '</p><p>— —. But if we make allowance for contraction, we</p><p><hi rend="italic">2g</hi></p><p>muſt employ a 2 G leſs than <hi rend="italic">2 g,</hi>  and we muſt multiply</p><p>the height now found by ~,. It will then become 2 G</p><p><hi rend="sub">z</hi>K<hi rend="sup">l</hi>V<hi rend="sup">l</hi> V∖<hi rend="italic">2g v<hi rend="sup">ι</hi>  , <hi rend="sub">1r1</hi>     . <hi rend="sub">τ</hi>,. . ,</hi></p><p>∕--—λ —<hi rend="sub">v</hi>, = — ( K — I ). This is that</p><p>k <hi rend="sup">2</hi>£    2J2G<hi rend="sub">1</hi> 2G</p><p>part of the ſwell which muſt produce the augmentation of velocity.</p><p>With reſpect to what is neceſſary for producing the additional ſlope between the piers, let <hi rend="italic">p</hi>  be the natural ſlope of the river (or rather the difference of level in the length of the piers) before the erection of the bridge, and correſponding to the velocity V ; K<hi rend="sup">2</hi>∕&gt; will very nearly expreſs the difference of ſuperficial level for the length of the piers, which is neceſſary for maintaining the velocity KV through the ſame length. The<hi rend="italic">increaſe </hi>of ſlope therefore is K^∕&gt; — <hi rend="italic">p — p</hi>  ( K<hi rend="sup">i</hi>  —<hi rend="italic">1 ). </hi>Therefore the whole ſwell will be <hi rend="italic">+ p</hi>  K<hi rend="sup">i</hi>— 1.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">These are the chief queſtions or problems on this ſubject which occur in the practice of an engineer; and the ſolutions which we have given may in every caſe be depended on as very near the truth, and we are confident that the errors will never amount to one-fifth of the whole quantity. We are equally certain, that of thoſe who call themſelves engineers, and who, without heſitation, undertake jobs of enormous expence, not one in ten is able even to gueſs at the reſult of ſuch operations, unleſs the circumſtances of the caſe happen to coincide with thoſe of ſome other project which he has executed, or has diſtinctly examined ; and very few have the ſagacity and penetration neceſſary for appreciating the effects of the diſtinguiſhing circumſtances which yet remain. The ſociety eſtabliſhed for the encouragement of arts and manufactures could ſcarcely do a more important ſervice to the public in the line of their inſtitution, than by publiſhing in their Tranſac-tions a deſcription of every work of this kind executed in the kingdom, with an account of its performance. This would be a moſt valuable collection of experiments and facts. The unlearned practitioner would find among them ſomething which reſembles in its chief circumſtance» almoſt any project which could occur to him in</hi></p><lb/></body></text></TEI>