<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>army being diſtreſſed for want of proviſions, he ſent out parties to pillage the fields, and raiſe contributions in the neighbouring cities. One of theſe parties appeared before Ardea, where the great Camillus had now ſpent two years in a private liſe. Notwithſtanding the affront he had received at Rome, the love he bore his country was not in the leaſt diminiſhed. The ſenate of Ardea being met to deliberate on the meaſures to be taken with relation to the Gauls, Camillus, more afflicted at the calamities of his country than at his own baniſhment, deſired to be admitted into the council, where, with his eloquence, he prevailed upon the Ardeates to arm their youth in their own defence, and refuſe the Gauls admittance into their city.</p><p>Hereupon the Gauls encamped before the city ; and as they deſpiſed the Ardeates alter they had made themſelves maſters of Rome, they preſerved neither order nor diſcipline in the camp, but ſpent whole days in drinking. Hereupon Camillus, having eaſily perſuaded the youth of the city to follow him, marched out of Aιdeaina very dark night, ſurpriſed the Gauls drowned in wine, and made a dreadful ∩aughter of them. Thoſe who made their eſcape under the ſhelter of the night fell next day into the hands of the peaſants, by whom they were maſſacred without mercy. This defeat of the enemy revived the courage of the Romans ſcattered about the country, eſpecially of thoſe who had retired to Veii after the unfortunate battle of Allia. There was not one of them who did not condemn himſelf for the exile of Camillus, as if he had been the author of it ; and looking upon that great man as their laſt reſource, they reſolved to chooſe him for their leader. Accordingly, they ſent without delay ambaſſadors to him, beſetching him to take into his protection the fugitive Romans, and the wrecks of the defeat at Allia. But Camillus would not accept of the command of the troops till the people aſſembled by curiæ had legally conferred it upon him. He thought the public authority was lodged in the hands of thoſe who were ſhut up iu the citadel, and therefore would undertake nothing at the head of the Roman troops till a commiſſion. was brought him from thence.</p><p>To do this was very difficult, the place being inveſted on all ſides by the enemy. However, one Pontius Co-minius, a man of mean birth, but bold, and very ambitious of glory, undertook it. He put on a light habit, and, providing himſelf with cork, to keep the longer above water, threw himſelf into the Tiber above Rome in the beginning of the night, and ſuffered himſelf to be carried down with the ſtream. At length he came to the foot of the capitol, and landed at a ſteep place where the Gauls had not thought it neceſſary to poſt any centinels. There he mounted with great difficulty to the rampart of the citadel ; and having made himſelf known to the guards, he was admitted into the place, and conducted, to the magiſtrates. The ſenate being immediately aſſembled, Pontius gave them an account of Camillus’s victory ; and in the name of all the Romans at Veii demanded that great captain for their general. There was not much time ſpent in debates: the curiæ being called* together, the act of condemnation which had been paſſed on Camillus was abrogated, and he named dictator with one voice. Pontius was immediately diſpatched with the decree ; and the ſame good fortune which had attended him to the capitol accompanied him in his return. Thus was Camillus, ſrom the ſtate of baniſhment, raiſed at once to be ſovereign magiſtrate of his country. His promotion to the command was no ſooner known, but ſoldiers flocked from all parts to his camp ; inſomuch that he ſoon ſaw himſelf at the head of above 40,000 men, partly Romans and partly allies,.who all thought themſelves invincible under ſo great a general.</p><p>While he was taking proper meaſures to raiſe the blockade of the citadel, ſome Gauls rambling round the place, perceived on the ſide of the hill the print of Pontius’s hands and ſeet. They obſerved likewiſe, that the moſs on the rocks was in ſeveral places torn up. From theſe marks they concluded, that ſomebody had lately gone up to and returned from the capitol. The Gauls immediately made their report to Brennus of what they had obſerved ; and that experienced commander laid a deſign, which he imparted to nobody, of ſurpriſing the place by the ſame way that the Roman had aſcended. With this view he choſe out of the army ſuch ſoldiers as had dwelt in mountainous countries, and been accuſtomed from their youth to climb precipices. Theſe he ordered, after he had well examined the nature of the place, to aſcend in the night the ſame way that was marked out ſor them ; climbing two abreaſt, that one might ſupport the other in getting up the ſteep parts of the precipice. By this means they advanced with much difficulty from rock to rock, till they arrived at the foot of the wall. They proceeded with ſuch ſilence, that they were not diſcovered or heard, either by the centinels who were upon guard in the citadel, or even by the dogs, that are uſually awaked and alarmed at the leaſt noiſe. But though they eluded the ſagacity of the dogs, they could not eſcape the vigilance of the geeſe. A flock of theſe birds was kept in a court of the capitol in honour of Juno, and near her temple. Notwithſtanding the want of proviſions in the garriſon, they had been ſpared out of religion ; and as theſe creatures are naturally quick of hearing, they were alarmed at the firſt approach of the Gauls ; ſo that running up and down, with their cackling and beating of their wings, they awaked 'Manlius, a gallant ſoldier, who ſome years before had been conſul. He founded an alarm, and was the firſt man who mounted the ram-part, where he found two Gauls already upon the wall. One of theſe offered to diſeharge a blow at him with his battle-ax; but Manlius cut off his right hand at one blow, and gave the other ſuch a puſh with his buckler, that he threw him headlong from the top of the rock to the bottom. He, in his fall, drew many others with him ; and, in the mean time, the Romans crowding to the place, preſſed upon the Gauls, and tumbled them one over another. As the nature of the ground would not ſuffer them to make a regular retreat, or even to fly, moſt of them, to avoid the ſwords of the enemy, threw themſelves down the precipice, ſo that very few &lt;τ<hi rend="sub">θ</hi>t ſafe back to their camp..</p><p>As it was the cuſtom of the Romans at that time not to ſuffer any commendable action to go unrewarded, the tribune Sulpitius aſſembled his troops the next morning, in order to beſtow the military rewards on thoſe who, the night before,, had deſerved them. Among theie Manlius was firſt named; and, in acknowledgment of the important ſervice he had juſt rendered the ſtate every ſoldier gave him part of the coin which he receil</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>