<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>the ſemicircular hanging wood is full in fight ; over part of it the great rock appears ; all its baſe, all its accompaniments, are ſeen ; the country immediately beyond it is full of lovely hillocks ; and the higher grounds in the counties of Somerſet and Glouccſter riſe in the horizon. The Severn ſeems to be, as it really is, above Chepſtowe, three or ſour miles wide; below the town it ſpreads almoſt to a ſea ; the county of Monmouth is there the hither ſhore, and between its beautiful, hills appear at a great diſtance the mountains of Brecknock and Glamorganſhire. In extent, in variety, and grandeur, few proſpects are equal to this. It comprehends all the noble ſcenes of Persfield, encompaſſed by ſome of the fineſt country in Britain. See Gardening.</p><p>RIDLEY (Nicholas), biſhop of London, and a martyr to the Reformation, was deſcended of an ancient family, and born in the beginning of the l6th century, at Wilmontſwick in Northumberland. From the grammar-ſchool at Newcaſtle upon Tyne, he was lent to Pembroke-hall in Cambridge, in the year 1518, where he was ſupported by his uncle Dr Robert Ridley, fellow of Queen’s college. In 1522 he took his firſt degree in arts ; two years after, was elected fellow ; and, in 1725, he commenced matter of arts. In 1527, having taken orders, he was lent by his uncle, for further improvement, to the Sorbonne at Paris ; from thence he went to Louvain, and continued abroad till the year 1529. On his return to Cambridge, he was choſen under-treaſurer of the univerſity ; and, in 1533. was elected ſenior proctor. He afterwards proceeded bachelor of divinity, and was choſen chaplain of the univerſity, orator, and <hi rend="italic">magijler glomeriœ. </hi>At this time he was much admired as a preacher and diſputant. He loſt his kind uncle in 1536 ; but was ſoon after patroniſed by Dr Cranmer, archbiſhop of Canterbury, who made him his domeſtic chaplain, and preſented him to the vicarage of Herne in Eaſt Kent ; where, we are told, he preached the doctrine of the Reformation. In 154'∙&gt;, having commenced doctor of divinity, he was made king’s chaplain ; and, in the iame year, was elected maſter of his college in Cambridge. Soon after, Ridley was collaced to a prebend in the church of Canterbury ; and it was not long before he was accuſed in the biſhop’s court, at the inſti-gation of biſhop Gardiner, of preaching againſt the doctrine of the Six Articles. The matter being referred to Cranmer, Ridley was acquitted. In 1545, he was made a prebendary of Weſtminſter abbey; in 1547 was preſented, by the fellows of Pembroke-hall, to the living of Soham, in the dioceſe of Norwich ; and the ſame year was conſecrated biſhop of Rocheſter. In 1550 he was tranſlated to the ſee of London; in which year he was one of the commiſſioners for examining biſhop Gardiner, and concurred in his depri-- vation. In the year 1552, our prelate returning from Cambridge, unfortunately for himſelf, paid a viſit to the Princeſs, afterwards Queen Mary ; to whom, prompted by his zeal for reformation, he expreſſed himſelf with too much freedom ; for ſhe was ſcarce-ly ſeated on the throne when Ridley was doomed a victim to her revenge. With Cranmer and Latimer he was burnt alive at Oxford, on the 16th of October <hi rend="italic">355</hi>j. He wrote, 1. A treatiſe concerning images in churches. 3» Brief declaration of the Lord’s Supper,</p><lb/><p>3. Certain godly and comfortable conferences between biſhop Ridley and Mr Hugh Latimer, during their impriſonment, 4. A compariſon between the comfortable doctrine of the Goſpel and the traditions of the Popiſh religion ; and other works.</p><p>RIFLE, in gunnery. See GunneRy, n<hi rend="sup">0</hi> 36,<hi rend="italic">tt</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">ſeq.</hi></p><p>RIGA, a large, ſtrong, populous, and rich town of the Ruffian empire, and capital of Livonia. It is a large trading place, and has a very conſiderable for-treſs ; the trade is chiefly in corn, ſkins, leather, and naval ſtores. It was taken by the Ruffians in 17 10, after they had blocked it up a long while, during which the inhabitants were afflicted with the plague. The caſtle is ſquare, and defended by four towers and fix battions ; beſides which, it has a fine arſenal. The Proteſtants have ſtill a handſome college here. It is. ſeated on a large plain on the river Dwina. E. Long. 24. 25. N. Lat. 57. o.</p><p>RIGADOON, a gay and briſk dance, borrowed originally from Provence in France, and performed in figure by a man and woman.</p><p>RIGGING <hi rend="italic">oſα Ship,</hi>  a general name given to all the ropes employed to ſupport the marts, and to extend or reduce the fails, or arrange them to the diſpoſition of the wind. The former, which are uſed to fuſtain the maſts, remain uſually in a fixed poſition, and are called <hi rend="italic">ftanding rigging;</hi>  ſuch are the ſhrouds, ſtays, and back∙ltays. The latter, whoſe office is to manage the ſails, by communicating with various blocks or pulleys, ſituated in different places of the maſts, yards, ſhrouds, &amp;c. are comprehended in the general term of <hi rend="italic">running rigging ;</hi>  ſuch are the braces, ſheets, haliards, clue-lines, brails, &amp;c.</p><p>In rigging a malt, the firſt thing uſually fixed upon its head is a circular w<hi rend="sup">r</hi>reath or rope, called the<hi rend="italic">gromet, </hi>or <hi rend="italic">collar,</hi>  which is firmly beat down upon the top of the hounds. The intent of this is to prevent the ſhrouds from being fretted or worn by the treſtle-trees, or ſhoulders of the maſt ; after this are laid on the two pendants, ſrom whoſe lower ends the main or fore tackles are ſuſpended ; and next, the ſhrouds of the ſtarboard and larboard ſide, in pairs, alternately. The wiιole is covered by the ſtays, which are the largeſt ropes of the rigging.—When a yard is to be rigged, a gromet is alſo driven firſt on each of its extremities ; next to this are fitted on the horſes, the braces, and laſtly the lifts or top-ſail ſheet-blocks.</p><p>The principal objects to be conſidered in rigging a ſhip, appear to be ſtrength, convenience, and ſimpli-city : or, the properties of affording ſufficient ſecurity to the maſts,. yards, and ſails ; of arranging the whole machinery in the moſt advantageous manner, to ſu-ſtain the maſts, and facilitate the management of the ſails ; and of avoiding perplexity, and rejecting whatever is ſuperfluous or unneceſſary. The perfection of this art, then, corſſiſts in retaining all thoſe qualities, and in preſerving a judicious medium between them. See Ship-building.</p><p>RIGHT, in geometry, ſignifies the ſame with ſtraight ; thus, a ſtraight line is called a <hi rend="italic">right</hi>  one.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Right is a title conferred, 1. Together with </hi><hi rend="italic">Reverend,</hi>  upon all biſhops. 2. Together with <hi rend="italic">Honourable,</hi>  upon earls, viſcounts, and barons. 3. By courtefy&gt; together with <hi rend="italic">Hoηoural(e,</hi>  upon the ſons of dukes, mar-</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>