<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>water delivered was about one-ſixth of the quantity which he promiſed, and about one-eleventh of the quantity which the no leſs celebrated M'Laurin calculated from the ſame plan.</p><p>Such being the ſtate of our theoretical knowledge (if it can be called by this name), naturaliſts began to be perſuaded that it was but loſing time to make any uſe of a theory ſo incongruous with obſerva-tion, and that the only ſafe method of proceeding was to multiply experiments in every variety of circum-ſtances, and to make a ſeries of experiments in every important caſe, which ſhould comprehend all the practicable modifications of that caſe. Perhaps circum-ſtances of reſemblance might occur, which would enable us to connect many of them together, and at laſt diſ-cover the principles which occaſioned this connection; by which means a theory founded on ſcience might be obtained. And if this point ſhould not be gained, we might perhaps find a few general facts, which are modified in all theſe particular caſes, in ſuch a manner that we can ſtill trace the general facts, and ſee the part of the particular caſe which depends on it. This would be the acquiſition of what may be called an empirical theory, by which every phenomenon would be explained, in ſo far as the explanation of a phenomenon is nothing more than the pointing out the general fact or law under which it is comprehended; and this theory would anſwer every practical purpoſe, becauſe we ſhould confidently forefee what conſequences would reſult from ſuch and ſuch premiſes; or if we ſhould fail even in this, we ſhould ſtill have a ſeries of experiments ſo comprehenſive, that we could tell what place in the ſeries would correſpond to any particular caſe which might be propoſed.</p><p>There are two gentlemen, whoſe labours in this re-ſpect deſerve very particular notice, profeſſor Miche-lotti at Turin, and Abbe Boſſut at Paris. The firſt made a prodigious number of experiments both on the motion of water through pipes and in open canals. They were performed at the expence of the ſovereign, and no expence was ſpared. A tower was built of the fineſt maſonry, to ſerve as a veſſel from which the water was to iſſue through holes of various ſizes, under preſſures from 5 to 22 feet. The water was received into baſons conſtructed of maſonry and nicely lined with ſtucco, from whence it was conveyed in canals of brickwork lined with ſtucco, and of various forms and declivities. The experiments on the expence of water through pipes are of all that have yet been made the moſt numerous and exact, and may be appealed to on every occaſion. Thoſe made in open canals are ſtill more numerous, and are no doubt equally accurate; but they have not been ſo contrived as to be ſo generally uſeful, being in general very unlike the important caſes which will occur in practice, and they ſeem to have been contrived chiefly with the view of eſtabliih-ing or overturning certain points of hydraulic doctrine which were probably prevalent at the time among the practical hydrauliſts.</p><p>The experiments of Boſſut are alſo of both kinds; and though on a much ſmaller ſcale than thoſe of Mi-chelotti, ſeem to deſerve equal confidence. As far as they follow the ſame track, they perfectly coincide in their results, which ſhould procure confidence in the other; and they are made in ſituations much more analogous to the uſual practical eaſts. This makes</p><lb/><p>them doubly valuable, They are  to be found in his two volumes intitled <hi rend="italic">Hydrodynamique.</hi>  He has opened this path of procedure in a manner ſo new and ſo judicious, that he has in ſome meaſure the merit of ſuch as ſhall follow him in the ſame path.</p><p>This has been moſt candidly and liberally allowed him by the chevalier de Buat, who has taken up this matter where the Abbé Boſſut left it, and has proſe-cuted his experiments with great aſſiduity; and we muſt now add with ſingular ſucceſs. By a very judicious conſideration of the ſubject, he hit on a particular view of it, which ſaved him the trouble of a minute conſideration of the ſmall internal motions, and enabled him to proceed from a very general and evident propoſition, which may be received as the key to a complete ſyſtem of practical hydraulics. We ſhall follow this ingenious author in what we have farther to ſay on the ſubject; and we doubt not but that our readers will think we do a ſervice to the public by making theſe diſcuſ-ſions of the chevalier de Buat more generally known in this country. It muſt not however be expected that we ſhall give more than a ſynoptical view of them, connected by ſuch familiar reaſoning as ſhall be either comprehended or confided in by perſons not deeply verſed in mathematical ſcience.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sect.</hi>  I. <hi rend="italic">Theory of Rivers.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">It is certain that the motion of open ſtreams muſt, in ſome reſpects, reſemble that of bodies ſliding down inclined planes perfectly poliſhed; and that they would accelerate continually, were they not obſtructed: but they are obſtructed, and frequently move uniformly. This can only ariſe ſrom an equilibrium between the forces which promote their deſcent and thoſe which oppoſe it. Mr Buat, therefore, aſſumes the leading propoſition, that</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">When water flows uniformly on any channel or bed, the accelerating force which obliges it to move is equal to the ſum of all the reſiſtances which it meets with, whether ari-ſing from its own viſcidity, or from the friction of its bed.</hi></p><p>This law is as old as the formation of rivers, and ſhould be the key of hydraulic ſcience. Its evidence is clear; and it is, at any rate, the bails of all uniform motion. And ſince it is ſo, there muſt be ſome con-ſiderable analogy between the motion in pipes and in open channels. Both owe their origin to an inequa∙ of preſſure; both would accelerate continually, if nothing hindered; and both are reduced to uniformity by the viſcidity of the fluid and the friction of the channel.</p><p>It will therefore be convenient to examine the phenomena of water moving in pipes by the action of its weight only along the ſloping channel. But previous to this, we muſt take ſome notice of the obſtruction to the entry of water into a channel of any kind, ariſing. from the deflection of the many different filaments which preſs into the channel from the reſervoir from every ſide. Then we ſhall be able to ſeparate this diminution of motion ſrom the ſum total that is obſerved, and aſcertain what part remains as produced by the ſubſequent obſtructions.</p><p>We then ſhall conſider the principle of uniform motion, the equilibrium between the power and the re-ſiſtance. The power is the relative height of the column of fluid which tends to move along the in-dined plane of its bed; the reſiſtance is the friction</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>