<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>peaτed in London in 1735, in 8vo. They conſiſt of odes in blank verſe, elegies, ſongs, and other things, after the manner of Catullus. There is likewiſe, by him, a Collection of Epigrams, printed at Florence in 1776, in 8vo, and preceded with his life by the abbé Fondini. What Martial ſaid of his own Collection may be ſaid of this, “ That there are few good, but many indifferent or bad, pieces in it.” Rolli, however, bore the character of one of the beſt Italian poets of his age. During his ſtay in London, he procured editions of ſeveral authors, of his own country. The principal of theſe were, the Satires of Arioſto, the Burleſque Works of Berni, Varchi, 8tc. 2 vols, in 8vo, which poſſeſs conſiderable merit. The Decameron of Boccace, 1727, in 4t0 and folio; in which he has faithfully copied the celebrated and valuable edition publiſhed by the <hi rend="italic">ſſantes</hi>  in ι Ç27 : and, laſtly, of the elegant Lucretia of Marchetti, which, after the manuſcript was reviſed, was printed at London in 1 717, in Svo, through the influence and attention of Rolli. This edition is beautiful ; but the work is thought of pernicious tendency. There are likewiſe, by him, tranſlations into Italian verſe of the Paradiſe Loſt of Milton, printed at London in folio in 1735’ ; and of the Odes of Anacreon, London 1739, in 8vo.</p><p>ROLLIN (Charles), a juſtly celebrated French writer, was the ſon of a cutler at Paris, and was born there on the 30th of January 1661. He ſtudied at the college Du Pleſſis, in which he obtained a burſary through the intereſt of a Benedictine monk of the White Mantle, whom he had ſerved at table, and who diſcovered in him ſome marks of genius. Here he acquired the regard of M. Gobinet, principal of that college, who had a particular eſteem for him. After having ſtudied humanity and philoſophy at the college of Du Pleſſis, he applied to divinity three years at the Sorbonne ; but he did not proſecute this ſtudy, and never roſe in the church higher than to the rank of a tonſured prieſt. He afterwards became profeſſor of rhetoric in the ſame college ; and, in 1688, ſucceeded Horſan, his maſter, as profeſſor of eloquence, in the royal college. No man. ever exerciſed the functions of it with greater eclat : he often made Latin orations, to celebrate the memorable events of the times ; and frequently accompanied them with poems, which were read and eſteemed by every body. In ‘69 4, he was choſen rector of the univerſity ; and continued in that office two years, which was then a great mark of diſtinction. By virtue of his office, he ſpoke the annual panegyric upon Louis XIV. He made many very "uſeful regulations in the univerſity ; and particularly revived the ſtudy of the Greek language, which was then much neglected. He ſubſtituted academical exerciſes in the place of tragedies ; and introduced the practice which had been formerly obſerved, of cauſing the ſtudents to get by heart paſſages of Scripture. He was a man of indefatigable attention ; and trained innumerable perſons, who did honour to the church, the ſtate, and the army. The firſt preſident Portail was phaſed one day to reproach Rollin in a jocular ſtrain, as if he exceeded even himſelf in doing buſineſs : to whom Rollin replied, with that plainneſs and ſincerity which was natural to him, “ It becomes you well, Sir, to reproach me with this ; it is this habit of labour in me which has diſtinguiſhed you in the place of</p><lb/><p>advocate-general, which has raiſed you to that of firſt preſident : you owe the greatneſs of your fortune to me.”</p><p>Upon the expiration of the rectorſliip, cardinal No-ailles engaged him to ſuperintend the ſtudies of his nephews, who were in the college of Laon ; and in this office he was agreeably employed, when, in 1699, he was with great reluctance made coadjutor to the principal of the college of Beauvais. This college was then a kind of deſert, inhabited by very few ſtudents, and without any manner of diſcipline : but Rollin’« great reputation and induſtry ſoon re-peopled it, and made it that flouriſhing ſociety it has ever ſince continued. In this ſituation he continued till 1712 ; when the war between the Jeſuits and the Janſeniſts drawing towards a criſis, he ſell a ſacriſice to the prevalence of the former. Father le Tellſer, the king’s conſeſſor, a furious agent of the Jeſuits, infuſed into his maſter prejudices againſt Rollin, whoſe connections with cardinal de Noailles would alone have ſufficed to have made him a Janſeniſt ; and on this account he loſt his ſhare in the principality of Beauvais. No man, however, could have loſt leſs in this than Rollin, who had every thine»· left him that was neceſſary to make him happy ; retirement, books, and enough to live on. He now began to be employed upon Quinctilian ; an author he juſtly valued, and ſaw neglected not without uueaſt-neſs. He retrenched in him whatever he thought rather curious than uſeful for the inſtruction of youth ; he placed ſummaries or contents at the head of each chapter ; and he accompanied the text with ſhort ſelect notes. His edition appeared in <hi rend="italic">1</hi>7 ∙ 5, in 2 vols 12 mo, with an elegant preface, ſetting forth his method and views.</p><p>In 1710, the univerſity of Paris, willing to have a head ſuitable to the importance of their intereſts in the then critical conjuncture of affairs, choſe Rollin again rector : but he was diſplaced in about two months by a lettre de cachet. The univerſity had preſented to the parliament a petition, in which it proteſted againſt taking any part in the adjuſtment of the late diſputes; and their being congratulated in a public oration by Rollin on this ſtep, occaſioned the letter which ordered them to chooſe a rector of more moderation. Whatever the univerſity might ſuffer by the removal of Rollin, the public was probably a gainer ; for he now applied himſelf to compoſe his treatiſe upon the Manner of Studying and Teaching the Belles Lettres, which was publiſhed, two volumes in 1726, and two more in 1728, 8vo∙</p><p>This work has been juſtly eſteemed for the ſentiments of religion which animate its author, whoſe zeal for the public good prompted him to ſelect the choiceſt paſſages of Greek and Latin authors. The ſtyle is ſufficiently elegant, but the language on ſome occaſions is not remarkable ſor delicacy; and in the book altogether there is neither much order nor depth. The author has indeed ſpoken of common things agreeably, and has ſpoken as an orator on ſubjects which demanded the inveſtigation of the philoſopher. One can ſcarcely reduce any thing in him to principles.—For example, the three ſpecies of eloquence ; the ſimple, the temperate, and the ſublime, can ſcarcely be underſtood from him when we read that the one reſembles a frugal table; the ſecond abeautiful ruin, with green wood growing</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>