<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>vcurable to his deſigns, now began to addreſs the aſ-ſembly in a more pathetic ſtrain : he preſented before them Cæſar's bloody robe, and, as he unfolded it, took care they ſhould obſerve the number of ſtabs in it : he then diſplayed an image, which to them appeared the body of Cæſar, all covered with wounds. The people could now no longer contain their indignation ; they unanimouſiy cried out for revenge ; all the old ſoldiers who had fought under him, burnt, with his body, their coronets, and other marks of conqueſt with which he had honoured them. A great number of the firſt matrons in the city threw in their ornaments alſo ; till at length, rage ſucceeding to ſorrow, the multitude ran with flaming brands from the pile to ſet fire to the conſpirators houſes. In this rage of reſentment, meeting with one C'irma, whom they miſtook for another of the ſame name who was in the conſpiracy, they tore him in pieces, The conſpirators themſelves, however, being well guarded, repulſed the multitude with no great trouble ; but perceiving the rage of the people, they thought it ſafeſt to retire from the city. Divine honours were then granted him ; and an altar was erected on the place where his body was burnt, where afterwards was erected a column inſcribed, <hi rend="italic">To the father of his country.</hi></p><p>In the mean time, Antony, who had excited this flame, reſolved to make the beſt of the occaſion. Having gained the people by his zeal in Cæſar’s cauſe, he next endeavoured to bring over the ſenate, by a ſee.ring concern for the freedom of the ſtate. He therefore propoſed to recal Sextus, Pompey’s only remaining ſon, who had concealed himſelf in .Spain ſince the death of his father : and to grant him the command of all the fleets of the empire. His next ſtep to their confidence, was the quelling a ſedition of the people, who roſe to revenge the death of Cæſar, and putting their leader Amathus to death, who pretended to be the ſon of Marius. He after thi3 pretended to dread the reſentment of the multitude, and demanded a, guard for the ſecurity of his perſon. The ſenate granted his requeſt; and, under this pretext, he drew round him a body of 6000 reſolute men, attached to his intereſt, and ready to execute liis commands. Thus be continued every day making rapid ſtrides to abſolute power ; all the authority of government was lodged in his hands and thoſe of his two brothers alone, who ſhared among them the conſular, tribunitian, and pras-torian power. His vows to revenge Cæſar’s death ſeemed either poſtponed, or totally forgotten ; and his only aim ſeemed to be to confirm himſelf in that power which he had thus artfully acquired. But an obſtacle to his ambition ſeemed to ariſe from a quarter on which he leaſt expected it. This was from Octavius, or Oc-tavianus Cæſar, afterwards called <hi rend="italic">Auguſtus,</hi>  who was the grand-nephew, and adopted ſon of Cæſar, and was at Apollonia when his kinſman was ſlain. He was then about 18 years old, and had been ſent to that city to improve himſelf in the ſtudy of Grecian literature·. Upon the news of Cæſar’s death, notwithſtanding the earneſt diſſuaſions of all his friends, he reſolved to return to Rome, to claim the inheritance, and revenge the death of his uncle. From the former profeſſions of Antony, he expected to find him a warm aſſiſtant to his afrits ; and he doubted not, by his concurrence, to take ſignal vengeance on all who had a hand in the con</p><p>ſpiracy. However, he was greatly diſappointed. Antony, whoſe projects were all to aggrandize himſelf, gave him but a very cold reception, and, inſtead of granting him the fortune left him by the will, delayed the payment of it upon various pretences, hoping to check his ambition by limiting his circumſtances. But Octavianus, inſtead of abating his claims, even ſold hie own patrimonial eſtate, to pay ſuch legacies as Cæſar had left, and particularly that to the people. By theſe means he gained a degree of popularity, which his enemies vainly laboured to diminiſh, and which in fact he had many other methods to procure. His converſation was elegant and inſinuating, his face comely and graceful, and his affection to the late dictator ſo ſincere, that every perſon was charmed either with his piety or his addreſs. But what added ſtill more to his intereſt was the name of Cæſar, which he had aſſumed, and, in conſequencc of which, the former followers of his uncle now flocked in great numbers to him. All theſe he managed with ſuch art, that Antony now began to conceive a violent jealouſy for the talents of his young opponent, and ſecretly laboured to counteract all his deſigns. In fact, he did not want reaſon ; for the army near Rome, that had long wiſhed to ſee the conſpirators puniſhed, began to turn from him to his rival, whom they ſaw more ſincerely bent on gratifying their deſires. Antony having procured alſo the government of Hither Gaul from the people, two of his legions that he had brought home from his former government of Macedonia, went over to Octavianus, notwithſtanding all his remonſtrances to detain them. This produced, as uſual, interviews, complaints, recriminations, and pretended reconciliations, which only tended to widen the difference ; ſo that, at length, both ſides prepared for war. Ί hus the ſtate was divided into three diſtinct factious ; that of Octavianus, who aimed at procuring Cæſar’s inheritance, and revenging his death ; that of Antony, whoſe ſole view was to obtain abſolute power ; and that of the conſpirators, who endeavoured to reſtore the ſenate to its former authority.</p><p>Antony being raiſed by the people to his new government of Ciſalpine Gaul, contrary to the inclinations of the ſenate, reſolved to enter upon his province immediately, and oppoſe Brutus, who commanded a ſmall body of troops there, while his army was yet entire. He accordingly left Rome, and marching thither, commanded Brutus to depart. Brutus, being unable to oppoſe him, retired with his forces ; but being purſued by Antony, he was at laſt beſieged in the city of Mutina, of which he ſent word to the ſenate.</p><p>In the mean while, Octavianus, who by this time had raiſed a body of 10,'00 men, returned to Rome; and being reſolved, before he attempted to take vengeance on the conſpirators, if poſſible to diminiſh the power of Antony, began by bringing over the ſenate to ſecond his deſigns. In this he ſucceeded by the credit of Cicero, who had long hated Antony becauſe he thought him the enemy of the ſtate. Accordingly, by means of his eloquence, a decree was paſſed, ordering Antony to raiſe the ſiege of Mutina, to evacuate Ciſalpine Gaul, and to await the further orders of the ſenate upon the banks of the Rubicon. Antony treated the order wish contempt ; and inſtead of</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>