<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>opened in it named <hi rend="italic">Carmentalis,</hi>  from Carmenta the mother of Evander, who either lived there, or had ſome chapel or altar erected to her.</p><p>Romulus had now become ſo formidable to his neighbours, and had ſo well eſtabliſhed his reputation for clemency, that ſeveral cities of Hetruria voluntarily ſubmitted to him. Ccelius, an Hetrurian general, led the troops under his command to Rome, and ſettled on an hill near the city, which from him took the name of <hi rend="italic">Mount Callus.</hi>  The Sabines, however, not in the leaſt diſmayed at this increaſe of the Roman forces, ſent a deputation to Romulus, demanding reſtitution of the young women who had been carried off ; and, upon his refuſal, marched to Rome with an army of 25,000 foot and xoco horſe, under the command of their king Titus Tatius. Romulus, having received ſupplies from Numitor and from Hetruria, likewiſe took the field, with 20,000 foot and 800 horſe, with whom he ſeized an advantageons poſt, and fortified himſelf ſo ſtrongly, that he could not be attacked. The Sabine monarch, perceiving the military ſkill of Romulus, began to be apprehenſive of the event ; but was extricated out of his difficulties by the treachery of Tarpeia daughter to the governor of the citadel, who agreed to betray that important fortreſs to the enemy, on condition of being rewarded with the bracelets which the Sabines wore on their left arms. But when once they became maſters of this important place, they are ſaid to have cruſlred Tarpeia under the weight of their bucklers, pretending that thus they diſeharged their promiſe, as they wore their bucklers alſo on their left arms. Ί he poſſeſſion of the citadel enabled the Babines to carry on the war with more ſucceſs ; but, at laſt, in a general engagement, they had the miſ-fortune to be driven back into the citadel, whither they were purſued by the Romans, who expected to have retaken that important poſt ; but the enemy, rolling down great ſtones from the top of the hill, wounded Romulus on the head, ſo that he was carried inſenſible out of the field of battle, while, in the mean time, his troops were repulſed, and puiſuedto the very gates of Rome. However, the king ſoon recovering himſelf, encouraged his routed troops, and drove the enemy back into the citadel. But while the two nations were thus fiercely contending, the women, for whoſe cauſe the war had been commenced, undertook the office of mediators ; and having obtained leave from the ſenate, marched in a body to the camp of the Sabines, where they pleaded the cauſe of their huſhands ſo effectually, that a treaty of union between the two nations was ſet on foot, and a peace was at laſt concluded, on the following terms. 1. That the two kings ſhould reſide and reign jointly at Rome. 2. That the city ſhould ſtill, from Romulus, be called <hi rend="italic">Rome ; </hi>but the inhabitants <hi rend="italic">Quirites,</hi>  a name till then peculiar to the Sabines. 3. That the two nations ſhould become one ; and that the Sabines ſhould be made free in Rome, and enjoy all the privileges of Roman citizens. As Rome was chiefly indebted for this increaſe of her power and ſplendor to the Sabine women, honourable privileges and marks of diſtinction were allowed them. Every one was commanded to give way to them ; in capital cauſes they were exempted from the juriſdic-tion of the ordinary judges ; and their childιen were allowed to wear a golden ball hanging from their necks&gt;</p><lb/><p>and a particular kind of robe called <hi rend="italic">prateχta,</hi>  to diſtinguiſh them from the vulgar.</p><p>The two kings reigned with great harmony for the ſpace of five years; during which time the only military exploit they accompliſhed was the reduction of the city of Cameria, at a ſmall diſtance from Rome. Four thouſand of the Camerini were tranſplanted to Rome, and a Roman colony ſent to repeople Cameria ; ſoon after which the Sabine king was murdered by the Lavinians, on account of his granting protection to ſome of his friends who had ravaged their territories. The Lavinians, fearing the reſentment of Romulus, delivered up the aſſaſſins into his hands ; but he ſent them back un-puniſhed, which gave occaſion to ſuſpect that he was not diſpleaſed with the death of . his colleague.</p><p>Soon after the death of Tatius, Rome was afflicted with famine and peſtilence, which encouraged the Camerini to revolt ; but Romulus marching againſt them ſuddenly, defeated them with the loſs of 6000 men. After which he attacked the Fidenates, whoſe city ſtood about five miles from Rome, took their capital, and made it a Roman colony. This drew upon him the reſentment of the Veientes, a powerful nation in the neighbourhood, who claimed Fidenæ as within their juriſdiction ; but their forces being defeated in two engagements, and a great number of them taken priſoners, they were obliged to ſue for peace. Romulus granted them a truce for 100 years, on condition that they delivered to him ſeven ſmall towns on the Tiber, together with ſome ſalt-pits near the mouth of that river, and ſent 50 of their chief citizens as hoſtages to Rome. The priſoners taken in this war were all ſold for ſlaves.</p><p>The remaining part of the life of Romulus was ſpent in making laws for the good of his people ; but towards the latter end of his reign, being elated with ſucceſs, he began to enlarge the bounds formerly ſet to his prerogative, and to behave in an arbitrary manner. He paid no longer any regard to the voice of the ſenate, but aſſembled them only for form’s ſake to ratify his commands. The ſenate therefore conſpired to deſtroy him, and accompliſhed their puιpole while he was reviewing his troops. A violent florin of hail and thunder diſperſed the army ; and the ſenators taking this opportunity, when they were left alone with the king, inſtantly killed him, and conveyed his body out of light. Some writers tell us<hi rend="sub">;</hi> that, the better to conceal the fact, they cut his body in pieces, each of them carrying away a part under his robe ; after which they told the multitude, that their king was on a ſudden ſurrounded by flame, and ſnatched up into heaven. This ſtratagem, however, did not ſatisfy the ſoldiery, and violent diſturbances were about to enſue, when Julius Proculus, a ſenator of great diſtinction, having aſſembled the Curiæ, told them that Romulus had appeared to him, and enjoined him to acquaint the people, that their king was returned to the gods from whom he originally came, but that he would continue to be propitious to them under the name of<hi rend="italic">Quirinus ;</hi>  and to the truth of this ſtory Julius ſwore.</p><p>Romulus reigned, according to the common computation, 37 years: but ſome hiſtorians reduce the length of his reign to little more than 1 7 ; it being very unlikely, as they obſerve, that a prince of ſuch an active diſpoſition ſhould perform nothing worthy of</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>