<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Solving to ruin the inhabitants, and to deſtroy the. whole ſenate. His ſoldiers, however, upon approaching the capital began to waver in their reſolutions : wherefore he was obliged to have recourſe to intreaties, imploring them not to abandon him ; and, retiring by the ſame route by which he had advanced, made Licinius, who was originally the ſon of a poor labourer in Dacia, Cæſar, in the room of Severus who was ſlain. This ſeemed to be the laſt act of his power ; for ſhortly after he was ſeized with a very extraordinary diſorder in his privities, which baffled all the ſkill of his phyſicians, and carried him off, after he had languiſhed in torments for near the ſpace of a year. His cruelty to the Chri-ſtians was one of the many crimes alleged againſt him ; and their hiſtorians have not failed to aggravate the circumſtances of his death as a judgment from Heaven for his former impiety. However this be, he abated much of his ſeverities againſt them on his deathbed ; and revoked thoſe edicts which he had formerly publiſhed, tending to their perſecution, a little before his death.</p><p>Conſtantine being thus delivered from his greateſt opponent, might now be conſidered as poſſeſſing more power than any of his rivals who were yet remaining. The empire was at that time divided between him and three others : Maxentius, who governed in Rome, a perſon of a cruel diſpoſition, and a ſtedfaſt ſupporter of paganiſm ; Licinius, who was adopted by Galerius, and commanded in the eaſt ; and likewiſe Maximin, who had formerly been declared Cæſar with Severus, and who alſo governed ſome of the eaſtern provinces.</p><p>For ſome time all things ſeemed to wear a peaceful appearance ; till at length, either ambition, or the tyrannical conduct of Maxentius, induced Conſtantine to engage in an expedition to expel that commander from Rome, and to make the proper preparations for marching into Italy. It was upon this occaſion that he formed a reſolution which produced a mighty change in the politics as well as the morals of mankind, and gave a new turn to the councils of the wife, and the purſuſts ambition. One evening, as we are told by Euſebius, the army being upon its march toward Rome, Conſtantine was taken up with various conſiderations upon the fate of ſublunary things, and the dangers of his approaching expedition : ſenſible of his own incapacity to ſucceed without divine aſſiſtance, he employed his meditations upon the opinions that then were chiefly agitated among mankind, and ſent up his ejaculations to Heaven to inſpire him with wiſdom to chooſe the path he ought to purſue. It was then, as the ſun was declining, that there ſuddenly appeared a pillar of light in the heavens, in the faſhion of a croſs, with this inſcription, τoττn νίκη “ In this overcome.” So extraordinary an appearance did not fail to create aſtoniſhment both in the emperor and his whole army, who conſidered it as their dilpoſitions led them to believe. Thoſe who were attached to paganiſm, prompted by their auſpices, pronounced it a moſt inauſpicious omen, portending the moſt unfortunate events. But it made a different impreſſion on the emperor’s mind ; who, as the account goes, was farther encouraged by viſions the ſime night. He therefore, the day following, cauſed a royal ſtandard to be made, like that which he had ſeen in the heavens ; and commanded it to be carried before him in his wars, as an enſign of victory and celeſtial protection. After this, he conſulted with ſeveral of the principal teachers of Chriſtianity, and made a public avowal of that ſacred perſuafion.</p><p>Conſtantine having thus attached his ſoldiers to his intereſt, who were moſtly of the Chriſtian perſuafion, loſt no time in entering Italy with 90,000 foot and 8000 horſe ; and ſoon advanced to the very gates of Rome. The unfortunate Maxentius, who had long given himſelf up to eaſe and debauchery, now began to<hi rend="sub">t </hi>make preparations when it was too late. He ſirlh put in practice all the ſupeiſtitious rites which paganiſm_ taught to be neceſſary; and then conſulted the Sibylline books ; from whence he was informed, that on that great day the enemy of Rome ſhould periſh. This prediction, which was equivocal, he applied to Conſtantine ; -wherefore, leaving all things in the beſt poſture, he advanced from the city with an army of 100,000 foot and 18,000 horſe. The engagement was for ſome time fierce and bloody, till his cavalry being routed, victory declared upon the ſide of his opponent, and be himſelf was drowned in his flight by the breaking down of a bridge as he attempted to croſs the river Tiber.</p><p>Conſtantine, in conſequence of this victory, entering the city, diſclaimed all praiſes which the ſenate and people were ready to offer ; alcribiug his ſucceſs to a ſuperior power. He even cauſed the croſs, which he was ſaid to have ſeen in the heavens, to be placed at the right of all his ſtatues, with this inſcription : “That under the influence of that victorious croſs, Conſtantine had delivered the city from the yoke of tyrannical power, and had reſtored the ſenate and people of Rome to their ancient authority.” He afterwards ordained, that no criminal ſhould for the future ſuffer death by the croſs ; which had formerly been the moſt uſual way of puniſhing ſlaves convicted of capital offences. Edicts were ſoon after iſſued, declaring that the Chriſtians ſhould be eaſed from all their grievances, and received into places of truſt and authority. Thus the new religion was ſeen at once to prevail over the whole Roman empire; and as that enormous fabric had been built and guided upon pagan principles, it loſt a great deal of it» ſtrength and coherence when thoſe principles were thus at once ſubverted.</p><p>Things continued in this ſtate for ſome time, Conſtantine all the while contributing what was in his power to the intereſt of religion, and the revival of learning, which had long been upon the decline, and was almoſt wholly extinct in the empire. But in the midſt of theſe aſſiduities, the peace of the empire was again diſturbed by the preparations of Maximin, who governed in the eaſt, and who, deſirous of a full participation of power,, marched againſt Licinius with a very numerous army. In conſequence of this ſtep, after many conflicts, a general engagement enſued, in which Maximin ſuffered a total deteat ; many of his troops were cut to pieces, and thoſe that ſurvived ſubmitted to the conqueror. Maximin, however, having eſcaped the general carnage, once more put himſelſ at the head of another army, reſolving to try the fortune of the field ; but death prevented his deſign. As he died by-a very extraordinary kind of madneſs, the Chriſtians, of whom he was the declared enemy, did not fail to aſeribe his end to a judgment from heaven ; but this was the age in which falſe judgments and falſe miracles made up the bulk of their uninſtructive hiſtory'.</p></body></text></TEI>