<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>was, that when Marinus had rebelled, he averred in the ſenate, That the traitor’s preſumption would be very ſhortly his ruin ; which, when it happened accordingly, Philip appointed him to ſucceed in the command of the rebellious army. Decius, who was a man of great ſubtlety, being thus entruſted with ſo much power, upon arriving at the army found that the ſoldiers were reſolved on inveſting him with the ſupreme authority. He therefore ſeemed to ſuffer -their importunities, as if through conſtraint ; and, in the mean time, ſent Philip word, that he had unwillingly aſſumed the title of emperor, the better to ſecure it for the rightful poſſeſſor ; adding, that he only looked for a convenient opportunity of giving up his pretenſions and title together. Philip knew mankind too well, to rely upon ſuch profeſſions: he therefore got together what forces he could ſrom the ſeveral provinces, and led them forward towards the confines of Italy. However, the army was ſcarce arrived at Verona, when it revolted in favour of Decius, and ſetting violently upon Philip, a centinel, with one blow, cut off his head, or rather cleaved it afunder, ſeparating the under jaw from the upper. Such was the deſerved death of Philip, in the 45th year of his age, after a reign of about five years ; Decius being univerſally acknowledged as his ſucceſſor, A. D. 248.</p><p>The activity and wiſdom of Decius in ſome meaſure flopped the haſtening decline of the Roman empire. The ſenate ſeemed to think ſo highly of his merits, that they voted him not inferior to Trajan ; and indeed he ſeemed in evety inſtance to conſult their dignity in particular, and the welfare of all inferior ranks of people. He permitted them to chooſe a cenſor, as was the cuſtom in the flouriſhing times of Rome ; and Valerian, his general, a man of ſuch ſtrict morals, that bis liſe was ſaid to be a continual cenſorſhip, was choſen to that dignity.—But no virtues could now prevent the approaching downfall of the ſtate : the obſtinate diſputes between the Pagans and the Chriſtians within the empire, and the unceaſing irruptions of barbarous nations from without, enfeebled it beyond the power of a remedy. To ſtop theſe, a perſecution of the Chri-ftians, who were now grown the moſt numerous body of the people, was impolitically, not to ſay unjuſtly, begun ; in which thouſands were put to death, and all the arts of cruelty tried in vain to leſſen their growing number. This perſecution was ſucceeded by dreadful devaſtations from the Goths, particularly in Thrace and Mæfia, where they had been moſt ſucceſsful. Theſe irruptions Decius went to oppoſe in perſon ; and coming to an engagement with them, flew 30,000 of the barbarians in one battle. However, being reſolved to purſue his victory, he was, by the treachery of Gallus his own general, led into a defile, where the king of the Goths had ſecret information to attack him. In this diſadvantageous ſituation, Decius firſt ſaw his ſon killed with an arrow, and ſoon after his whole army put to the rout. Wherefore, reſolving not to ſurvive his loſs, he put ſpurs to his horſe, and inſtantly plunging into a quagmire, was ſwallowed up, and his body could never be found after. He died in the 5<hi rend="sup">,</hi>oth year of his age, after a ſhort reign of two years and ſix months ; leaving the character of an excellent prince, and one capable of averting the de</p><lb/><p>ſtruction of the empire, if human means could have effected it.</p><p>Gallus, who had thus betrayed the Roman army, had'addreſs enough to get himſelf declared emperor by that part of it which ſurvived the defeat ; he was 45 years old when he began to reign, and was deſeended from an honourable family in Rome. He bought a diſhonourable peace from the enemies of the ſtate, agreeing to pay a conſiderable annual tribute to the Goths, whom it was his duty to repreſs. Having thus purchaſed a ſhort remiſſion from war, by the diſgrace of his country, he returned to Rome, to give a looſe to his pleaſures, regardleſs of the wretched ſituation of the empire.</p><p>Nothing can be more deplorable than the ſtate of the Roman provinces at this time. The Goths and other barbarous nations, not ſatisfied with their late bribes to continue in peace, broke in upon the eaſtern parts of Europe. On the other ſide, the Perſians and Scythians committed unheard of ravages in Meſope-tamia and Syria. The emperor, regardleſs of every national calamity, was loſt in debauch and ſenſuality at home ; and the Pagans were allowed a power of perſecuting the Chriſtians through all parts of the ſtate ; theſe calamities were ſucceeded by a peſtilence, that ſeemed to have in general ſpread over every part of the earth, and which continued raging for ſeveral years in an unheard of manner ; and all theſe by a civil war, which followed ſhortly after, between Gallus and his general Æmilianus, who having gained a victory over the Goths, was proclaimed emperor by his conquering army. Gallus hearing this, was ſoon rouſed from the intoxications of pleaſure, and prepared to oppoſe his dangerous rival. Both armies met in Mœ-ſia, and a battle, enſued, in which Æmilianus was victorious, and Gallus, with his ſon, were ſlain. His death was merited, and his vices were ſuch as to deſerve the deteſtation of poſterity. He died in the 47th year of his age, alter an unhappy reign of two years and four months, in which the empire ſuffered inex-preſſible calamities. Æmilianus, after his victory over Gallus, expected to be acknowledged emperor ; but he ſoon found himſelf miſerably diſappointed., Thc ſenate refuſed to acknowledge his claims ; and an army that was ſtationed near the Alps choſe Valerian, their own commander, to ſucceed to the throne. In conſequence of this, Æmilianus’s ſoldiers began to confi-der their general as an obſtacle to the univerſal tranquillity, and flew him in order to avoid the miſchiefs of a civil war.</p><p>Valerian being thus univerſally acknowledged as emperor, although arrived at the age of 70, ſet about reforming the ſtate with a ſpirit that ſeemed to mark a good mind and unabated vigour. But reformation was then grown almoſt impracticable. The diſputes between the Pagans and Chriſtians divided the empire as before ; and a dreadful persecution of the latter enſued. The northern nations over-ran the Roman dominions in a more formidable manner than ever ; and the empire began to be uſurped by a multitude of petty leaders, each of whom, neglecting the general ſtate, ſet up ſor himſelf. To add to theſe calamities, the Perſians, under their king Sapor, invaded Syria ; and coming into Meſopotamia, took the unfortunate Valerian pr,i-</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>