<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>The conſpirators, to give a colour of juſtice to their proceedings, remitted the execution of this deſign to the ides of March, the day on which it was reported that Cæſar was to be offered the crown. The augurs had foretold that this day would be fatal to him ; and the night preceding, he heard his wife Calphurnia lamenting in her ſleep, and being awakened, ihe con-feſſed to him that the dreamt of his being aiΓaffιnated in her arms. Theſe omens, in ſome meaſure, began to change his intentions of going to the ſenate, as he had reſolved, that day ; but one of the conſpirators coming in, prevailed upon him to keep his reſolution, telling him of the reproach which would attend his Haying at home till his wife had lucky dreams,, and of the preparations that were made for his appearance. As he went along to the ſenate, a ſlave, who haſtened to him with information of the conſpiracy, attempted to come near him, but could not lor the crowd. Arte-rnidorus, a Greek philoſopher, who had diſcovered the whole plot, delivered to him a memorial, containing the heads of lſis information ; but Cæſar gave it, with other papers, to one of his ſecretaries without reading, as was uſual in things of this nature. As ſoon as he had taken his place in the ſenate, the conſpirators came near him, under a pretence of ſaluting him ; and Cimber, who was one of them, approached in a ſup-pliant poſture, pretending to ſue for his brother’s pardon, who was baniſhed by his order. All the conſpirators ſeconded him with great tenderneſs ; and Cim-ber, ſeeming to ſue with ſtill greater ſubmiſſion, took hold of the bottom of his robe, holding him ſo as to prevent his riſing. TTιis was the ſignal agreed on. Caſca, who was behind, ſtabbed him, though flightly, in the ihoulder. Cæſar inſtantly turned round, and with the ſtyle of lſis tablet wounded him in the arm. However, all the conſpirators were now alarmed ; and incloſing him round, he received a ſecond ſtah from an unknown hand in the breaſt, while Caffius wounded him in the face. He ſtill defended himſelf with great vigour, ruihing among them, and throwing down ſuch as oppoſed him, till he ſaw Brutus among the conſpira-tors, who, coming up, ſtruck his dagger in his thigh. From that moment Cæſar thought no more of defending himſelf, but looking upon this conſpirator, cried out, ** And you too, Brutus !” Then covering his head, and ſpreading his robe before him in order to fall with greater decency, he ſunk down at the baſe of Pompey’s ſtatue, after receiving three and twenty wounds, in the 56th year of his age, and 4th of his reign.</p><p>As ſoon as the conſpirators had diſpatched Cæſar, they began to addreſs themſelves to the ſenate, in order to vindicate the motives of their enterpriſe, and to excite them to join in procuring their country’s freedom; but all the ſenators who were not accomplices fled with ſuch precipitation, that the lives of ſome of them were endangered in the throng. The people alſo being now alarmed, left their uſual occupations, and ran tumul-tuouily through «the city ; ſome actuated by their fears, and ſtill more by a deſire of plunder. In this ſtate of confuſion, the conſpirators all retired to the capitol, and guarded its acceiſes by a body of gladiators which Brutus had in pay.. It was in vain<hi rend="sub">1</hi> they alleged they only ſtruck for freedom, and that they killed a tyrant who uſurped the rights of mankind : the people, accuſtom-ed te luxury and eaſe, little regarded their profeſ-</p><p>ſions, dreading more the dangers of poverty than e&gt;* ſubjection.</p><p>The friends of the late dictator now began to find that this was the time for coming into greater power than before, and for ſatisfying their ambition under the veil of promoting juſtice. Of this number was Antony, whom we have already ſeen acting as a lieutenant under Cæſar. He was a man of moderate abilities and exceſſive vices ; ambitious of power, but ſkilled in war, to which be had been trained from his youth. He was conſul for this year ; and reſolved, with Lepidus, who was fond of commotions like himſelf, to ſeize this opportunity of aſſuming the ſovereign power. Lepidus, therefore, took poſſeſſion of the forum with a band of ſoldiers at his devotion ; and Antony, being conſul, was permitted to command them. Their firſt ſtep was to poſſeſs themſelves of all Cæſar’s papers and money ; and the next to convene the ſenate, in order to determine whether Cæſar had been a legal magiſtrate or a tyrannical uſurper, and whether thoſe who killed him merited rewards or puniſhments. There were many of theſe who had received their promotions ſrom Cæſar, and had acquired large fortunes in conſequence of his appointments : to vote him an uſurper,'»therefore, would be to endanger their property ; and yet to vote him innocent, might endanger the ſtate. In this dilemma they ſeemed willing to reconcile extremes ; wherefore they approved all the acts of Cæſar, and yet granted a general pardon to all the conſpirators.</p><p>This decree was very far from giving Antony ſatisſaction, as it granted ſecurity to a number of men who were the avowed enemies of tyranny, and who would be foremoſt in oppoſing his ſchemes of reſtoring abſolute power. As therefore the ſenate had ratified all Cæſar’s acts without diſtinction, he formed a ſeheme upon tlſis of making him rule when dead as imperiouſ-ly as he had done when living. Being, as was ſaid, poſſeſſed of Cæſar’s books of accounts, he ſo ſar gained upon his ſecretary as to make him inſert whatever he thought proper. By theſe means, great ſums of money, which Cæſar never would have beſtowed, were here diſtributed among the people ; and every man who was averſe to republican principles was here ſure of finding a gratuity. He then demanded that Cæſar’s funeral obſequies ſhould be performed ; which the ſenate now could not decently forbid, as they had never declared him a tyrant. Accordingly, the body was brought forth into the forum with the utmoſt ſolem-nity ; and Antony began his operations upon the paſſions of the people, by the prevailing motives of private intereſt. He firſt read Cæſar’s will, in which he had left Octavius, his fiſter’s grandſon, his heir, permitting him to take the name of <hi rend="italic">Cæſar ;</hi>  and three parts of his private fortune Brutus was to inherit in caſe of his death. The Roman people were left the gardens which he had on the other ſide the Tiber ; and every citizen, in particular, was to receive 300 ſeſter-ces. This laſt bequeſt not a little contributed to increaſe the people’s affection for their late dictator ; they now began to conſider Cæſar as a father, who, not ſa-tisfied with doing them the greateſt good while living, thought of benefiting them even after his death. As Antony, continued reading, the multitude began to be moved, and fighs and lamentations were heard from every quarter. Antony, ſeeing the audience fa-</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>