<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>there expoſe his baſeneſs and her own, invoking all the furies to her aſſiſtance. Theſe menaces ſerved to alarm the ſuſpicions of Nero ; who, though apparently guided by his governors, yet had begun to give way to his natural depravity. He, therefore, determined upon the death of Britannicus, and contrived lo have him poiſoned at a public banquet. Agrippina, however, ſtill retained her natural ferocity : ſhe took every opportunity of obliging and flattering the tribunes and centurions ; ſhe heaped up treaſures with a rapacity beyond her natural avarice ; all her actions ſeemed calculated to raiſe a faction, and make herſelf formidable to the emperor. Whereupon Nero commanded her German guard to be taken ſrom her, and obliged her to lodge out of the palace. He alſo forbid particular perſons to viſit her, and went himſelf but rarely and ceremo-niouſly to pay her his reſpects. She now, therefore, began to find, that, with the emperor’s favour, ſhe had loſt the aſſiduity of her friends. She was even accuſed by Silana of conſpiring againſt her ſon, and of deſigning to marry Plautius, a perſon deſeended from Auguſtus, and of making him emperor. A ſhort time aſter, Pallas, her favourite, together with Burrhus, were arralgned for a ſimilar offence, and intending to ſet up Cornelius Sylla. Theſe informations being proved void of any foundation, the informers were baniſhed ; a puniſhment which was conſidered as very inadequate to the greatneſs of the offence.</p><p>As Nero increaſed in years, his crimes ſeemed to increaſe in equal proportion. He now began to find a pleaſure in running about the city by night, diſguiſed like a ſlave. In this vile habit he entered taverns and brothels, attended' by the lewd miniſters of his pleaſure,«, attempting the lives of ſuch as oppoſed him, and frequently endangering his own. In imitation of the emperor’s example, numbers of profligate young jr en inſeſted the ſtreets likewiſe ; ſo that every night the city was filled with tumult and diſorder. However, the people bore all theſe levities, which they aſ-cribed to the emperor’s youth, with patience, having occaſion every day to experience his liberality, and having alſo been gratified by the abolition of many of their taxes. The provinces alſo were no way affected by theſe riots ; for except diſturbances on the ſide of the Parthians, which were ſoon ſuppreſſed, they enjoyed the moſt perfect tranquillity.</p><p>But thoſe ſenſualitie», which, ſor the firſt four years of his reign, produced but tew diſorders, in the fifth became alarming. He firſt began to tranſgreſs the bounds of decency, by publicly abandoning Octavia, his preſent wife, and then by taking Poppea, the wiſe of his favourite Otho, a woman more celebrated ſor her beauty than her virtues. This was another grating circumſtance to Agrippina, who vainly uſed all her intereſt to diſgrace Poppea, and reinſtate herſelf in her ſon’s loſt favour. Hiſtorians aſſert, that ſhe even offered to ſatisfy his paſſion herſelf, by an inceſtuous compliance and that, had not Seneca interpoſed, the ſon would have joined in the mother’s crime. This, however, does not ſeem probable, ſince we find Poppea vic-torious, ſoon after, in the contention of intereſts ;· and at laſt impelling Nero to parricide, to ſatisfy her revenge. She began her aits by urging him to divorce his preſent wife, and marry herſelf : ſhe reproached him a; <hi rend="italic">ύ</hi>  pupil, who wanted not only power over others, but.</p><p>liberty to direct himſelf. She inſinuated the danger0u3 deſigns of Agrippina ; and, by degrees, accuſtomed his mind to reflect on parricide without horror, H13 cruelties againſt his mother began rather by various circumſtances of petty malice than by any downright in. jury. He encouraged ſeveral perlons to teaſe her with litigious ſuits; and employed ſome of the meaneſt of the people to ling ſatirical ſongs againſt her, under her windows : but, at laſt, finding theſe ineffectual in breaking her ſpirit, he reſolved on putting her to death. His firſt attempt was by poiſon ; but this, though twice repeated, proved ineffectual, as ſhe had fortified her conſtitution againſt it by antidotes. This failing, a ſhip was contrived in ſo artificial a manner as to fall 10 pieces in the water ; on board of which ſhe was invited to ſail to the coaſts of Calabria. However, this plot was as ineffectual as the former : the mariners, not being ap-priſed of the ſecret, diſturbed each other’s operations ; ſo that the ſhip not finking as readily as was expected, Agrippina found means to continue ſwimming, till ſhe was taken up by ſome trading veſſels paſſing that way. Nero finding all his machinations were diſcovered, reſolved to throw off the maſk, and put her openly to death, without further delay. He therefore cauſed a report to be ſpread, that ſhe had conſpired againſt him, and that a poniard was dropped at his ſeet by one who pretended a command from Agrippina to aſſaſſinate him. In conſequence of this, he applied to his governors Seneca and Burrhus, for their advice how to act, and their aſſiſtance in ridding him of his fears. Things were now come to ſuch a criſis, that no middle way could bε taken ; and either Nero or Agrippina was to fall. Seneca, therefore, kept a profound ſilence ; while Burt hus, with more reſolution, refuſed to be perpetrator of ſo great a crime ; alleging, that the army was entirely devoted to all the deicendants of Cæſar, and would never be brought to imbrue their hands in the blood of any of his family. In this embarraſſment, Anicetus, the contriver of the ſhip above-mentioned, offered his ſervices ; which Nero accepted with the greateſt joy, crying out, “ That then was the firſt moment he ever found himſelſ an emperor.” This freedman, therefore, taking with him a body of ſoldiers, ſurrounded the houſe of Agrippina, and then forced open the doors. The executioners having diſpatched her with ſeveral wounds, left her dead on the couch, and went to inform Nero of what they had done. Some hiſtorians ſay, that Nero came immediately to view the body ; that he continued to gaze upon it with pleaſure, and ended his horrid ſurvey, by coolly obſerving, that he never thought his mother had been ſo handſome»— However this be, he vindicated his conduct, next day to the ſenate ; who not only excuſed, but applauded his impiety.</p><p>AH the bounds of virtue being thus broken down,. Nero now gave a looſe to his appetites* that were not only fordid but inhuman. There ſeemed an odd cop-traſt in his diſpoſition ; for while he practiſed cruelties which were ſufficient to make the mind ſhudder with horror, he was fond of thoſe amuſing arts that ſoften and refine the heart. He was particularly addicted, even, from childhood, to muſic, and not totally ignorant of poetry. But chariot-driving was his favourite purſuit. He never miſſed the circus, when chariot-races were to be exhibited there ; appearing at firſt privately, and</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>