<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>we may preſume that t∩e formula gives the greateſt velocities which can be expected. In ordinary works, where joints are rough or leaky, where drops of ſolder hang in the inſide, where cocks intervene with deficient water-ways, where pipes have âukward bendings, contractions, or enlargements, and where they may contain fand or air, we ſhould reckon on a ſmaller velocity than what reſults from our calculation ; and we preſume that an undertaker may with confidence promiſe ∣ of this quantity without any rifl&lt; of diſappointing his employer. We imagine that the actual performance of canals will be much nearer to the formula.</p><p>We have made inquiry after works of this kind executed in Britain, that we might compare them with the formula. But all our canals are locked and without motion ; and we have only learned by an accidental information from Mr Watt, that a canal in his neighbourhood, which is 18 feet wide at the ſurface, and ſe-ven feet at the bottom, and four feet deep, and has a ſlope of one inch in a quarter of a mile, runs with the velocity of 17 inches per ſecond at the ſurface, 10 at the bottom, and 1 4 in the middle. If we compute the motion of this canal by our formula, we ſhall find the mean velocity to be 13-5.</p><p>No river in the world has had its motions ſo much ſcrutiniſed as the Pυ about the end of the laſt century. It had been a ſubject of 100 years continual litigation between the inhabitants of the Bologneſe and the Fer-rareſe, whether the waters of the Rheno ſhould be thrown into the Tronco de Venezia or Po Grande. This occaſioned very numerous meaſures to be taken of its ſections and declivity, and the quantities of water which it contained in its different liâtes of fullneſs. But, unfortunately, the long eſtabliſhed methods of meaſuring waters, which were in force in Lombardy, made no account of the velocity, and not all the intreaties of Caſtelli, Grandi, and other moderns, could prevail on the viſitors in this proceſs to deviate from the eſtabliſhed methods. We have therefore no minute accounts of its velocity, though there are many rough eſtimates to be met with in that valuable collection publiſhed at Florence in 1723, of the writings on the motion of rivers. From them we have extracted the <hi rend="italic">only preciſe obſervations</hi>  which are to be found in the whole work.</p><p>The Po Grande receives no river from Stellata to the ſea, and its ſlope in that interval is found moſt ſur-priſingly uniform, namely fix inches in the mile (reduced to Engliſh meaſure). The breadth in its great freſhes is 759 ſeet at Lago Scuro, with a very uniform depth of 31 ſeet. In its loweſt ſtate (in which it is called <hi rend="italic">Po Magra),</hi>  its breadth is not leſs than 70c, and its depth about 10⅛.</p><p>The Rheno has a uniform declivity from the Ponte Emilio to Vigarano of 1 ς inches per mile. Its breadth in its greateſt freſhes is 189 ſeet, and its depth 9.</p><p>Signor Corrade in his report ſays, that in the ſtate of the great freſhes the velocity of the Rheno is moſt exactly I of that of the Po.</p><p>Grandi ſays that a great freſh in the Rheno employs 12 hours (by many obſervations of his own) to come from Ponte Emilio to Vigarano, which is 30 miles. This is a velocity of 44 inches per ſecond. And, by Corrade’s proportion, the velocity of the. Po Grande muſt be 55 inches per ſecond.</p><p>Montanan’s obſervation gives the Po Magra a velocity of 31 inches per ſecond.</p><p>Let us compare theſe velocities with the velocities calculated by Buat’s formula.</p><p>The hydraulic mean depths <hi rend="italic">d</hi>  and D of the Rheno and Po in the great freſhes deduced from the above meaſures, are 98,6 and 344 inches ; and their ſlopes <hi rend="italic">s</hi>  and S are <hi rend="sub">τr</hi>√<hi rend="sub">τ7</hi>  and τc⅛5∙ This will give = 52,176 inches 307 ( V<hi rend="sup">z</hi><hi rend="italic">d</hi>—o,ι )    <hi rend="sub">z</hi>_</p><p><hi rend="sup">and</hi> √r∑L√7+T6-°&gt;3 (V<hi rend="sup">j</hi>-°∙') =46,727 inches.</p><p>Theſe reſults differ very little from the velocities above mentioned. And if the velocity correſponding to a depth of 31 feet be deduced from that obſerved by Montanari in the Po Magra 10 ſeet deep, on the ſuppoſition that they are in the proportion of V<hi rend="sup">z</hi><hi rend="italic">d,</hi>  it will be found to be about 53∙∣ inches per ſecoad.</p><p>This compariſon is therefore highly to the credit oſ the theory, and would have been very agreeable to M. de Buat, had he known it, as we,hope it is to our readers.</p><p>We have collected many accounts of water pipes, and made the compariſons, and we flatter ourſelves that theſe have enabled us to improve the theory. They ſhall appear in their proper place; and we may juſt obſerve here, that the two-inch pipe, which we formerly ſpokc of as conveying the water to Dunbar, ſhould have yielded only 25 * Scotch pints per minute by the formula, inſtead of-27; a ſmall error.</p><p>We have, therefore, no heſitation in ſaying that this ſingle formula of the uniform motion of water is one of the moſt valuable preſents which natural ſcience and the arts have received during the courſe of this century.</p><p>We hoped to have made this fortunate inveſtigation of the chevalier de Buat ſtill more acceptable to our readers by another table, which ſhould contain the va-307</p><p>lues of —τ-÷—-—7-ττ—-. ready calculated for every de-V j — Lv j-J- 1,6</p><p>clivity that can occur in water pipes, canals, or rivers. Aided by this, which ſuperſedes the only difficult part of the computation, a perſon could calculate the velocity for any propoſed caſe in leſs than two minutes. But we have not been able to get it ready for 1t3 appeal ance in this article, but we ſhall not fail to give it when we relume the ſubject in' the article <hi rend="italic">WATER-Works ;</hi>  and we hope even to give its reſults on a ſcale which may be carried in the pocket, and will enable the unlearned practitioner to lolve any queſtion with accuracy in half a minute.</p><p>W<hi rend="sup">r</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">e have now eſtabliſhed in ſome meaſure a Theory of Hydraulics, by exhibiting a general theorem which expreſſes the relation of the chief circumſtances of all ſuch motions as have attained a ſtate of permanency, in ſo far as this depends on the magnitude,, form, and ſlope of the channel. This permanency we have expreſſed by the term traih, ſaying that the ſtream is </hi><hi rend="italic">in train.</hi></p><p>We proceed to conſider the ſubordinate circumſtances contained in this theorem ; ſuch as, ιy∕, The forms which nature or art may give to the bed of a running ſtream, and the manner of expreſſing this, form in our theorem. <hi rend="italic">2d<hi rend="sub">1</hi></hi>  The gradations of the velocity, by which</p></body></text></TEI>