<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>the diviners at that time, violently oppoſed the king<hi rend="sup">,</hi>3 will. On this Tarquin, deſirous to expoſe the deceit of theſe people, ſuramoned Nævius before an aſſembly of the people, and deſired him to ſhow a ſpecimen of his art, by telling the king if what he thought of at that time could be done or not. The augur replied, after conſulting his birds, that the thing was very poſſible. On which Tarquin told him, that he had been thinking whether it was poſſible to cut a flint with a razor, pulling at the ſame time a razor and flint from below his robe. This ſet the people a-laughing ; but Nævius gravely deſiring the king to try it, he was ſurpriſed to find that the flint yielded to the razor; and that with ſo much eaſe as to draw blood ſrom his hand. The people teſtified their ſurpriſe by loud acclamations, and Tarquin himſelf continued to have a great veneration for augurs ever after. A ſtatue of braſs was erected to the memory of Nævius, which continued till the time of Auguſtus ; the razor and flint were buried near it, under an altar, at which witneſſes were afterwards ſworn in civil cauſes.</p><p>This adventure, whatever was the truth of it, cauſed Tarquin to abandon his deſign of increaſing the number of bodies of horſe, and content himſelf with augmenting the number in each body. He then renewed the war with the Sabines, ravaged their country, defeated them in three pitched battles, obliging them at laſt to ſubmit to him and put him in poſſeſſion of their country. In the decline of life he employed himſelf in further decorating the city, building temples, &amp;c. He was aſſaſſinated in his palace, in the 8oth year of iιis age, by the ſons of Ancus Martius, whom he had originally deprived of the kingdom.</p><p>After the death of Tarquin I. his wife Tanaquil preſerved the kingdom to her ſon-in-law Servius Tullius, by artfully giving out that the king was only ſtunned, and would ſoon recover ; upon which the ſons of Ancus went voluntarily into baniſhment. The ſecond day after his deceaſe, Servius Tullius heard cauſes from the throne in the royal robes and attended by the lictors ; but as he pretended only to ſupply the king’s place till he ſhould recover, and thought it incumbent on him to revenge the wicked attempt upon his life, he ſummoned the ſons of Ancus to appear before his tribunal ; and on their non-appearance, cauſed them to be declared infamous, and their eſtates to be confiſca-ted. After he had thus managed matters for ſome time in ſuch a manner as to engage the affections of the people, the death of Tarquin was publiſhed as a thing that had newly happened, and Servius Tullius aſſumed the enſigns of royalty, having none to diſpute the honour with him.</p><p>The new king ſhowed himſelf every way worthy of the throne. No ſooner were the Hetrurians informed of Tarquin’s death, than they ſhook off the yoke ; but Sdrvius quickly reduced them to obedience, depriving them of their lands, which he ſhared among the poor Roman citizens who had none. For this he was decreed a triumph by the people, in ſpite of the oppoſition of the ſenate, who could never be brought to approve of his election to the kingdom, though he was ſoon after legally choſen by the tribes.</p><p>After Servius had obtained the fonction of the po pular voice, he marched a ſecond time againſt the revolted Hetrurians ; and having again vanquiſhed them,</p><lb/><p>was decreed another triumph. He then applied himſelf to the enlarging and adorning the city. To the hills Palatinus, Tarpeius, Quirinalis, Cœlius, and Aventinus, he added the Eſquilmus and Viminalis,. fixing his own palace, on the Eſquilinus, in order to draw inhabitants thither. He likewiſe added a fourth tribe, which he called <hi rend="italic">Tribus Eſquilina,</hi>  to thoſe inſtituted by Romulus. He divided alſo the whole Roman territory into diſtinct tribes, commanding that there ſhould be at leaſt one place of refuge in each tribe, ſituated on a riſing ground, and- ſtrong enough to ſecure the effects of the peafonts in caſe of a ſudden alarm·. Theſe ſtrong-holds he called <hi rend="italic">pagi,</hi>  that is, “ villages ;” and commanded that each of them ſhould have their peculiar temple, tutelary god, and magiſtrates. Each of them had likewiſe their peculiar feſtival, called <hi rend="italic">paga-ηαliα ;</hi>  when every perſen was to pay into the hands of thoſe who preſided at the ſacrifices a piece of money, the men of one kind, the women of another, and the children of a third. By this means an exact computation was made of the men, women, and children, in each tribe.</p><p>In the mean time, his two wards, Lucius Tarquinius and Afunx, the grandchildren of Tarquin, being grown up, in order to ſecure their fidelity, he married them to his two daughters. And though the elder of theſe daughters, who was of a mild and tractable diſpoſition, reſembled in- character the younger of his pupils, as the elder of his pupils did the younger of his daughters, who was of a violent and vicious temper, yet he thought it adviſable to give his elder daughter to Tarquin, and the younger to Arunx ; for by that means he matched them according to their ages, and at the ſame time hoped that the elder Tullia’s ſweet diſpoſition would temper Tarquin’s impetuoſity, and the younger Tullia’s vivacity rouſe the indolence of A-runx.</p><p>During the public rejoicing for this double marriage, the twelve lucumonies of Hetruria uniting their forces, attempted to ſhake off the Roman yoke ; but were in ſeveral battles defeated by Servius, and obliged to ſubmit to him on the ſame conditions on which they had ſubmitted to his predeceſſor. For this ſucceſs Servius was honoured with a third triumph.</p><p>The king being thus diſengaged from a troubleſome war, returned to the purſuit of his political ſchemes; and put in execution that maſterpiece of policy which Rome made uſe of ever after, and which eſtabliſhed a perpetual order and regularity in all the members of the ſtate, with reſpect to wars, to the public revenues, and the ſuffrages of the comitia. I he public ſupplies had hitherto been raiſed upon the people at ſo much an head, without any diſtinction of rich and poor ; whence it likewiſe followed, that when levies were made for the war, the rich and poor were equally obliged to take the field, according to the order of their tribe ; and as they all ſerved at their own expence, the poorer fort could hardly bear the charges of a campaign. Beſides, as the moſt indigent of the people ſaw themſelves burdened with the lame taxes as the rich, they pretended to an equal authority in the comitia : ſo that the election of kings and magiſtrates, the making of peace or war, and the judging of criminals, were given up into the hands of a populace who were eaſily corrupted, and had notſiing to loſe. Bervιus formed a project to reme-</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>