<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>make accurate diſeoveries reſpecting an Jſland which was ſuppoſed to lie about 50<hi rend="sup">w</hi>  N. L. and about 300 leagues W. of England : but he returned without having ſeen any ſuch iſland as that which he was appointed to ſurvey. In the war which ſoon followed this voyage of diſcovery, he was promoted to the rank of a rear-admiral, and was employed to bombard Havre-de-Grace ; which in 1759 and x 760 he conſiderably damaged, together with ſome ſhipping. In 1761 he was ſent on an expedition againſt Martinico, which was reduced in the beginning of the year 1762, and about the ſame time St Lucia ſurrendered to Captain Harvey. Both theſe iſlands were reſtored to the French at the peace of</p><p><hi rend="sup">i763</hi>∙ <hi rend="sub">e</hi> . <hi rend="sub">1</hi> . , In reward for his ſervices, he was created a knight</p><p>ς&gt;f the Bath ; but being inattentive, as many ſeamen are, to the rules of economy, his circumſtances became ſo embarraſſed that he was obliged to fly from his country, with very flight hopes of ever being able to return. He was in France when the ill-adviſed policy of that court made them take a decided part with America againſt Great Britain ; and it is ſaid that ſome men in power, no ſtrangers to the deſperate ſtate of Sir George’s affairs, offered him a high command in the French navy, if he would carry arms againſt his own country. This offer he rejected with becoming indignation. Soon after this gallant behaviour, the Duke de Chartres, afterwards the inſamous Orleans, told Sir George that he was to have a command in the fleet which was to be oppoſed to that under the command of his countryman Mr Keppel ; and with an inſulting air aſhed him what he thought would be the conſequence of their meeting ? “ That my countryman will carry your Highneſs with him to learn Engliſh,” was the high-ſpirited reply.— When the diviſions, which the mutual recriminations of Admiral Keppel and Sir Hugh Palliſer excited in the Britiſh navy, made it difficult for the miniſtry to procure experienced, and at the ſame time popular, commanders for their fleets, Lord Sandwich wrote to Sir George Bridges Rodney, offering him a principal command ; but the difficulty was ſor the veteran to find money to pay his accounts in France, ſo that he might be permitted to leave that kingdom- The money, it has been repeatedly affirmed, was advanced to him by the courtiers whoſe offer he had before indignantly rejected. He arrived, therefore, in England, and was again employed in the ſervice of his country. His firſt exploit after his appointment was in January 1780, when he took 19 Spaniſh tranſports bound to Cadiz from Bilboa, together with a 64 gun ſhip and 5 ſrigates, their convoy. Gn the 16th of the ſame month he fell in with the Spaniſh fleet, conſiſting of 11 ſail of the line, under the commmand of Don Juan de Langara ; of which one was blown up during the engagement, five were taken and carried into Gibraltar, among which was the admiral’s ſhip, and the reſt were much ſhattered. In April the ſame year, he fell in with the French fleet, under the command of Admiral Guichen, at Martinico, whom he obliged to fight, and whom he completely beat; though from the ſhattered ſtate of his own fleet, and the un-willingneſs of the enemy to riſk another action, he took none of their ſhips. The ſucceſsful efforts of our gallant admiral during the year 1780 were generally applauded through the nation. He received the thanks of both Houſea of Parliament, and addreſſes of thanks from</p><p>various parts of Great Britain, and the iſlands to which his victories were more particularly ſerviceable. In December the ſame year, he made an attempt, together with General Vaughan, on St Vincent’s, but failed. In 1781, he continued his exertions, with much ſucceſs, in defending the Weſt India iſlands ; and, along with the above named general, he conquered St Euſtatius; on which occaſion his conduct to the inhabitants has been much, though perhaps unjuſtly, cenſured. The iſland was certainly a neſt of contraband traders.</p><p>On the ί 2th of April 1782, he came to a cloſe action with the French fleet under Count de Graffe; du-ring which he ſunk one ſhip and took five, of which the admiral’s ſhip, the Ville de Paris, was one. The following year brought peace ; but, as a reward for his numerous ſervices, he had a grant of L. 2000 a-year for himſelf and his two ſucceſſors. He had long before been created a baronet, was rear-admiral of Great Britain, and at length was juſtly promoted to the peerape, by the title of Baron Rodney of Stoke, Somerſetſhire, and made vice-admiral of Great Britain, He was once alſo governor of Greenwich Hoſpital.</p><p>Lord Rodney had been twice married ; firſt to the ſiſttr of the Earl of Northampton, and ſecondly to the daughter of John dies, Eſq; with whom he did not re-ſide for ſeveral years before his death, which happened on the 24th of May 1792. He was ſucceeded in title and eſtates by his ſon George, who married in 1781 Martha, daughter of the Right Hon. Alderman Harley, by whom he has iſſue.</p><p>Of the private life of Lord Rodney we know but little. His attention to the wants of the ſeamen, and the warrant officers ſerving under him, indicated that humanity which is always allied to true courage. He has often, ſrom the number of diſhes which his rank brought to his table, ſelected ſomething very plain for himſelf, and ſent the reſt to the midſhipmens meſs.— His public tranſactions will tranſmit his name with honour to poſterity ; his bravery was unqueſtionable, and his ſucceſs has been ſeldom equalled. It has, indeed, been very generally ſaid, that his ſkill in naval tactics was not great, and that he was indebted to the ſuperior abilities of Capt. Young and Sir Charles Douglas for the manœuvres by which he was ſo ſucceſsful againſt Lan-gara and De Graſſe. But, ſuppoſing this to be true, it detracts not from his merit. A weak or fooliſh commander could not always make choice of the ableſt officers for his firſt captains, nor would ſuch a man be guided by their advice.</p><p>Whatever was Lord Rodney’s ſkill in the ſcience of naval war, or however much he may have been beholden to the counſels of others, he certainly poſſeſſed himſelf the diſtinguiſhed merit of indefatigable exertion ; ſor he never omitted any thing within the compaſs of his power to bring the enemy to action. He therefore unqueſtion-ably deſerves the reſpect and the gratitude of his country. In the year 1783 the Houſe of Aſſembly in Ja. maica voted L. 1000 towards erecting a marble ſtatue to him, as a mark of their gratitude and veneration for his gallant ſervices, ſo timely and gloriouſly performed for the ſalvation of that iſland in particular, as well as the whole of the Britiſh Weſt India iſlands and trade in general. We have not, however, heard of any ſuch tribute being paid to him in Britain either before or ſince his death.</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>