<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>whatever; and this velocity increaſes continually, according to ſome law, to be diſcovered by theory or experiment, as the poſition of the pipe changes, from being horizontal till it becomes vertical; in which poſition it has the greateſt uniform velocity poſſible relative to its inclination, or depending on inclination alone.</p><p>Let this velocity be called the train, or the rate of each pipe.</p><p>It is evident that this principle is of the utmoſt conſequence in the theory of hydraulics ; for by experiment we can find the train of any pipe. It is in train when an increaſe of length makes no change in the velocity. If lengthening the pipe increaſes the velocity, the ſlope of the pipe is too great, and <hi rend="italic">vice verſa.</hi>  And having diſcovered the train of a pipe, and obſerved its velocity, and computed the head productive of this velocity with the contraction at the entry, the remainder of the head, that is, the ſlope (for this is equivalent to EA), is the meaſure of the reſiſtance. Thus we obtain the meaſure of the reſiſtance to the motion with a given velocity in a pipe of given diameter. If we change only the velocity, we get the meaſure of the new reſiſtance relative to the velocity ; and thus diſcover the law of relation between the reſiſtance and velocity. Then, changing only the diameter of the pipe, we get the meaſure of the reſiſtance relative to the diameter. This is the aim of a prodigious number of experiments made and collected by Buat, and which we , ſhall not repeat, but only give the reſults of the' different parts of his inveſtigation.</p><p>We may expreſs the ſlope of a pipe by the ſymbol</p><p>2, I being an inch for inſtance, and j being the ſlant <hi rend="italic">s</hi></p><p>length of a pipe which is one inch more elevated at one end than at the other. Thus a river which has a declivity of an inch and a half in 120 fathoms or 8640</p><p>inches, has its ſlope = -ſ  -, or ——. But in order 8640    5760</p><p>to obtain the hydraulic ſlope of a conduit pipe, the h,eights of the reſervoir and place of diſcharge being given, we muſt ſubtract from the difference of elevation the height or head of water neceſſary for propelling the water into any pipe with the velocity V, which it is V<hi rend="sup">1</hi></p><p>ſuppoſed actually to have. This is ——. The remainder <hi rend="italic">d</hi>  is to be conſidered as the height of the declivity, which is to be diſtributed equally over the whole length ∕ of the pipe, and the ſlope is then -, = -.</p><p>There is another important view to be taken of the ſlope, which the reader ſhould make very familiar to his thoughts. It expreſſes the proportion between the weight of the whole column which is in motion and the weight which is employed in overcoming the reſiſtance ; and the reſiſtance to the motion of any column of water is equal to the weight of that column multiplied by the</p><p>fraction 2, which expreſſes its ſlope. f.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">We come now to conſider more particularly the reſiſtances which in this manner bring the motions to a ſtate of uniformity. If we conſider the reſiſtances which ariſe from a cauſe analogous to friction, we ſee that they muſt depend entirely on the inertia of the</hi></p><lb/><p>water. What we call the reſiſtance is the diminution of a motion which <hi rend="italic">would</hi>  have obtained but for theſe reſiſtances ; and the beſt way we have of meaſuring them is by the force which we muſt employ in order to keep up or reſtore this motion. We eſtimate this motion by a progreſſive velocity, which we meaſure by the expence of water in a given time. We judge the velocity to diminiſh, when the quantity diſcharged di-miniſhes ; yet it may be otherwiſe, and probably is otherwiſe. The abſolute velocity of many, if not all, of the particles, may even be increaſed ; but many of the motions, being tranſverſe to the general direction, the quantity of motion in this direction may be leſs, while the ſum of the abſolute motions of all the particles may be greater. When we increaſe the general velocity, it is not unreaſonable to ſuppoſe that the im-pulſes on all the inequalities are increaſed in this proportion ; and the number of particles thus impelling and deflected at the ſame time will increaſe in the ſame proportion. The whole quantity therefore of theſe uſeleſs and loſt motions will increaſe in the duplicate ratio of the velocities, and the force neceſſary for keeping up the motion will do ſo alſo ; that is, the reſiſtances ſhould increaſe as the ſquares of the velocities.</p><p>Or if we conſider the reſiſtances as ariſing merely from the curvature of the imperceptible internal motions occaſioned by the inequalities of the ſides of the pipe, and as meaſured by the forces neceſſary for producing theſe curvilineal motions ; then, becauſe the curves will be the ſame whatever are the velocities, the deflecting forces will be as the ſquares of the velocities; but theſe deflecting forces are preſſures, propagated from the parts urged or preſſed by the external force, and are proportional to theſe external preſſures by the principles of hydroſtatics. Therefore the preſſures or forces neceſſary for keeping up the velocities are as the ſquares of theſe velocities ; and they are our only meaſures of the reſiſtances which muſt be conſidered as following the ſame ratio. Whatever view therefore we take of the nature of theſe reſiſtances, we are led to conſider them as proportional to the ſquares of the velocities.</p><p>We may therefore expreſs the reſiſtances by the ſymbol ~, <hi rend="italic">m</hi>  being ſome number to be diſcovered by experiment. Thus, in a particular pipe, the diminution of the motion or the reſiſtance may be the 1000th part of the ſquare of the velocity, and R = <hi rend="sub">i</hi>'<hi rend="sub">qq</hi>"</p><p>Now if <hi rend="italic">g</hi>  be the accelerating power of gravity on any particle, — will be its accelerating power, by which</p><p>it would urge it down the pipe whoſe ſlope is “. Therefore, by the principle of uniform motion, the equality of the accelerating force, and the reſiſtance, we ſhall have V* £    _</p><p>— = γ, and V√ι = √ <hi rend="italic">mg</hi>  &gt; that is, the product</p><p>of the velocity, and the reciprocal of the ſquare root of the ſlope, or the quotient of the velocity divided by the ſlope, is a conſtant quantity <hi rend="italic"><hi rend="sub">m</hi>  g</hi>  for any given pipe ; and the· primary formula for all the uniform velo r    ∙    ∙ it    <hi rend="italic"><hi rend="sup">m</hi>S</hi></p><p>cities of one pipe is V = --,</p><p>√τ</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>