<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>thoſe of the emperor ; people ſwore by his fortune, in the ſame manner as they would have done had he been actually upon the throne, and he was more dreaded than even the tyrant who actually enjoyed the empire. But the rapidity of his riſe ſeemed only preparatory to the greatneſs of his downfall. All we know of his firſt diſgrace with the emperor is, that Satrius Sec un dus was the man who had the boldneſs to accuſe him. Antonia, the mother of Germanicus, ſeconded the accuſation. What were the particulars of his crimes, we cannot learn ; but certain it is, that he attempted to uſurp the empire, by aiming at the life of Tiberius. He was very near diſpatching hi n, when his practices were diſcovered, and his ow<hi rend="sup">,</hi>n life was ſubſtituted ſor that againſt which he aimed. Tiberius, ſenſible of the traitor’s power, proceeded with his uſual diſſimulation in having him apprehended. He granted hin new honours at the very time he reſolved his death, and took him as his colleague in the conſulſhip. The emperor’s letter to the ſenate began only with flight complaints againſt his ſriend, but ended with an order for putting him in priſon. He intreated the ſenators to protect a poor old &gt;an, as he was, abandoned by all; and, in the ιrean ti ce, prepared ſhips ſor his flight, and ordered ſoldiers ſor his ſecurity. The ſenate, who had long been jealous of the favourite’s power, and dreaded his cruelty, immediately took this ορροί tunity of going beyond their orders. Inſtead of ſentencing him to impriſonment, they directed his execution. A ſtrange revolution now appeared in the city ; of thoſe numbers that but a moment before were preſſing into the preſence of Sejanus, with offers of ſervice and adulation, not one was found that would ſeem to be of his acquaintance : he was deſerted by all ; and thoſe who had formerly received the greateſt benefits ſrom him, ſeemed now converted into his moſt inveterate enemies. As he was conducting to execution,· the people loaded him with inſult and execration. He attempted to hide his face with his hands ; but even this was denied him, and his hands were ſecured. Nor did the rage of his enemies ſub-ſide with his death ; his body was ignominiouſly dragged about the ſtreets, and his whole family executed with him.</p><p>His death only lighted up the emperor’s rage for further executions. The priſons were crowded with pretended accomplices in the conſpiracy of Sejanus. Tiberius began to grow weary of particular executions ; he therefore gave orders that all the accuſed ſhould be put to death together without further examination. Of 20 ſenators, whom he choſe for his council, he put 16 to death. “ Let them hate me (cried he) ſo long as they obey me.” He then averred, that Priam was an happy man, who outlived all his poſterity. In this manner there was not a day without ſome barbarous execution, in which the ſufferers were obliged to undergo the moſt ſhameftil indignities and exquiſite torments. When one Camillus had killed himſelf to avoid the torture “ Ah (cried Tiberius), how that man has been able to eſeape me!” When a priſoner earneſtly intreated that he would not defer his death : “ No (cried the tyrant), I am not ſufficiently your friend, to ſharten your torment.” He often ſatisfied his eyes with the tortures of the wretches that were put to death before him ; and in the days of Suetonius the rock was to be ſeen, from which he ordered ſuch as had diſpleaſed him to be thrown headlong. As he was one day examining ſome perſons upon the rack, he was told that an old friend of his was come from Rhodes to ſee him. Tiberius ſuppofing him brought for the purpoſe of information, immediately ordered him to the torture ; and when he was convinced of his miſtake, he ordered him to be put to death, to prevent farther diſeovery.</p><p>In this manner did the tyrant continue to torment others, although hc was himſelf ſtill more tortured by h is own ſuſpicions ; ſo that in one of his letters to the ſenate, he conſeſſed that the gods and goddeſſe3 had ſo afflicted and confounded him, that he knew not what or how to write. In the mean time, the frontier provinces were invaded with impunity by the barbarians. Mæfia was ſeized on by the Dacians and Sar-matians ; Gaul was waſted by the Germans, and Armenia conquered by the king of Parthia. Tiberius, however, was ſo much a Have to his brutal appetites, that he left his provinces wholly to the care of his lieutenants, and they were intent rather on the accumulation of private fortune than the ſafety of the ſtate. Such a total diſorder in the empire produced ſuch a degree of anxiety in him who governed it, that he was heard to wiſh, that heaven and earth might periſh when he died. At length, however, in the 22d year of his reign, he began to feel the approaches of his diſſolution, and all his appetites totally to forſake him. He now, therefore, found it was time to think of a ſucceſſor, and heſitated for a long while, whether he ſhould chooſe Caligula, whoſe vices were too apparent to eſcape his obſervation. He had been often heard to ſay, that this youth had all the faults of Sylla, without his virtues ; that he w<hi rend="sup">τ</hi>as a ſerpent that would ſting the empire, and a Phaeton that would ſet the world in a flame. However, notwithſtanding all his w’ell-grounded apprehenſions, he named him for his ſucceſſor ; willing, perhaps, by the enormity of Caligula’s conduct to cover the memory of his own.</p><p>But though he thought fit to chooſe a ſucceſſor, he concealed his approaching decline with the utmoſt care, as if he was willing at once to hide it from the world and himſelf. He long had a contempt for phyfic, and refuſed the advice of ſuch as attended him : he even ſeemed to take a pleaſure in being preſent at the ſports of the ſoldiers, and ventured himſelf to throw a javelin at a boar that was let looſe before him. The effort which he made upon this occaſion cauſed a pain in his ſide, which haſtened the approaches of death : ſtill, however, he ſeemed willing to avoid his end ; and ſtrove, by change of place, to put off the inquietude of his ow<hi rend="sup">,</hi>n reflections. He left his favourite iſland, and went upon the continent, where he at laſt fixed at the promontory of Miſenum. It was here that Charicles, his phyſician, pretending to kiſs his hand, felt the failure of his pulſe ; and appriſed Macro, the emperor’s preſent favourite, that he had not above two days to live. Tiberius, on the contrary, who had perceived the art of Charicles, did all in his power to impreis his attendants with an opinion of his health : he continued at table till the evening ; he ſaluted all his gueſts as they left the room, and read the acts of the ſenate, in which they had abſolved ſome perſons he had written againſt, with great indignation. He</p><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>