<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>where the Romans were in danger of being deſtroyed, or compelled to fly the province. Wherefore, after appointing liis two ſons Caracalla and Geta joint ſucceſſors in the empire, and taking them with him, he land’ ed in Britain, to the great terror of ſuch as had drawn down his reſentment. Upon his progreſs into the country, he left his ſon Geta in the ſouthern part of the province, which had continued in obedience, and marched with his ſon Caracalla againſt the Caledonians. In this expedition, his army ſuffered prodigious hardſhips in purſuing the enemy ; they were obliged to hew their way through intricate ſoreſts, to drain extenſive marſhes, and form bridges over rapid rivers ; ſo that he loſt 50,000 men by fatigue and ſickneſs. However, he ſupported all theſe inconveniences with the greateſt bravery ; and is ſaid to have proſecuted his ſucceſſes with ſuch vigour, that he compelled the enemy to ſue for peace ; which they obtained, not without the fur-render of a conſiderable part of their country. We muſt here obſerve, however, that the Picts and Caledonians are ſo often confounded together by hiſtorians, that many miſtakes have thence ariſen concerning the progreſs and conqueſts of the Romans in the north of Britain. But from the boundary formed by the famous wall of Severus (ſee <hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps">Sekfrus’s Wall),</hi></hi>  we muſt con-lude, that no part of Caledonia, properly ſo called, had been either on this or any other occaſion ceded to him.; and there is reaſon to believe, that he rather received checks ſrom the people of that territory, than was ever able to make any conſiderable impreſſion upon them. Be this, however, as it may, after having made peace, and built his wall, he retired to York ; where, partly through age and fatigue, and partly through grief at the irreclaimable life of Caracalla, he found himſelf daily declining, having already loſt the uſe of his ſeet. To add to the diſtreſs of his ſituation, he was informed that the ſoldiers had revolted, and declared his ſon emperor. In this exigence, he ſeemed once more to recal his natural vigour ; he got himſelf immediately put into his litter, and commanded the new emperor, with the tribunes and centurions, to be brought before him. Though all were willing to court the favour of the young emperor, ſuch was the authority of Severus, that none dared tα diſobey. They appeared before him confounded and trembling, and implored pardon upon their knees. Upon which, putting his hand to his head, he cried out, “ Know, that it is the head that governs, and not the feet.” However, ſoon perceiving his diſorder to increaſe, and knowing that he could not outlive it, he called for poiſon ; which being reſuſed him, he loaded his ſtomach with food ; which not being able to digeſt, it ſoon brought him to his end, in the 56th year oſhis age, after an active though cruel reign of about 18 years.</p><p>Caracalla and Geta being acknowledged as emperors by the army, began to ſhow a mutual hatred to each other even before their arrival at Rome. Their only agreement was, in reſolving to deify Severus their father ; but ſoon after, each ſought to attach the ſenate and army to. bis own particular intereſt. They were of very oppoſite diſpoſitions : Caracalla was fierce and cruel to an extreme degree ; Geta was mild and. merciful; ſo that the city ſoon found the dangerous effects of being governed by two princes of equal power and contrary inclinations.</p><p>But this oppoſition was of no long continuance; for . Caracalla being reſolved to govern alone, furiouſly entered Gcta’s apartment, and, followed by ruffians, (lew him in his mother’s arms. Having committed this deteſtable murder, he iſſued with great haſte from the palace, crying out, That his brother would have ſlain him ; and that he was obliged, in ſelf-deſence, to retaliate the intended injury. He then took refuge among the prætorian cohorts, and in a pathetic tone began to implore their aſſiſtance, ſtill making the ſame excuſe for his conduct. To this he added a much more prevailing argument, promiſing to beſtow upon them the largeſſes uſually given upon the election of new emperors, and diſtributing among them almoſt all the treaſures which had been amaſſed by his father. By ſuch perſuaſives the ſoldiers did not heſitate to proclaim him ſole emperor, and to ſtigmatize the memory of his brother Geta as a traitor and an enemy to the commonwealth. The ſenators were ſoon after induced, either through favour or fear, to approve what had been done by the army : Caracalla wept for the death of his brother whom he had ſlain ; and, to carry his hypocriſy to the utmoſt extreme, ordered him to be adored as a god.</p><p>Being now emperor, he went on to mark his courſe with blood. Whatever was done by Domitian or Nero ſell ſhort of this monſter’s barbarities. Lætus, who firſt adviſed him to murder his brother, was the firſt who fell a ſacriſice to his jealouſy. His own wife Plau-tina followed. Papinian, the renowned civilian, was beheaded for refuſing to write in vindication of his cruelty ; anſwering the emperor’s requeſt, by obſerving, That it was much eaſier to commit a. parricide than to defend it. He commanded all governors to be ſlain that his brother had appointed ; and deſtroyed not leſs than 2000 perſons who had adhered to his party. Whole nights were ſpent in the execution of his bloody decrees ; and the dead bodies of people of all ranks were carried out of the city in carts, where they were burnt in heaps, without any of the ceremonies of a funeral. Upon a certain occaſion, he ordered his ſoldiers to ſet upon a crowded audience in the theatre, only for diſcountenancing a charioteer whom ha happened to favour. Perceiving himſelf hated by the people, he publicly ſaid, that he could inſure his own ſafety though not their love; ſo that he neither valued their reproaches nor feared their hatred.</p><p>This ſafety which he ſo much built upon was placed in the protection of his ſoldiers. He had exhauſted the treaſury, drained the provinces, and committed a thouſand acts of rapacity, merely to keep them ſtedfaſt in his intereſts ; and being diſpoſed to truſt himſelf with them particularly, he reſolved to lead them upon a viſit through all the provinces of the empire. He firſt went into Germany ; where, to oblige the natives, he dreſſed himſelf in the habit of their country. From thence he travelled into Macedonia, where he pretended to be a great admirer of Alexander the Great ; and among other extravagancies cauſed a ſtatue of that monarch to be made with two faces; one of which reſembled Alexander and the other himſelf. He was ſo corrupted by flattery, that he called himſelf <hi rend="italic">Alexander-; </hi>walked as he was told that monarch had walked ; and, like him, bent his head to one ſhoulder. Shortly after, arriving at Leſſer Aſia and the ruins of Troy, as he</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>