<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>For this reaſon he abandoned all the conqueſts which Trajan had made, judging them to be rather an inconvenience than an advantage to the empire; and made ; the river Euphrates the boundary of the empire, placing the legions along its banks to prevent the incurſions of the enemy.</p><p>Having thus ſettled the affairs of the eaſt, and leaving Severus governor of Syria, he took his journey by land to Rome, ſending the aſhes of Trajan thither by ſea. Upon his approach to the city, he was informed of a magnificent triumph that was preparing for him; but this he modeſtly declined, deſiring that thoſe honours might be paid to Trajan’s memory which they had deſigned for him. In conſequence of this command, a moſt ſuperb triumph was decreed, in which Trajan’s ſtatue was carried as a principal figure in the proceſſion, it being remarked that he was the only man that ever triumphed after he was dead. Not content with paying him theſe extraordinary honours, his aſhes were placed in a golden urn, upon the top of a column 140 feet high. On this were engraven the particulars of all his exploits in baſſo relievo; a work of great labour, and which is ſtill remaining. Theſe teſtimonies of reſpect to the memory of his predeceſſor did great honour to the heart of Adrian. His virtues, however, were contraſted by a ſtrange mixture of vices; or to ſay the truth, he wanted ſtrength of mind to preſerve his general rectitude of character without deviation. As an emperor, however, his conduct was moſt admirable, as all his public tranſactions appear dictated by the ſoundeſt policy and the moſt diſin-tereſted wiſdom. But theſe being already enumerated under the article Adrian, it would be ſuperfluous to repeat them in this place. He was ſucceeded by Marcus Antoninus, afterwards ſurnamed the <hi rend="italic">Pious, </hi>whom he had adopted ſome time before his death. See <hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps">Antoninus Pius.</hi></hi></p><p>From the beginning of the reign of Antoninus Pius, we may date the decline of the Roman empire. From the time of Cæſar to that of Trajan, ſcarce any of the emperors had either abilities or inclination to extend the limits of the empire, or even to defend it againſt the barbarous nations who ſurrounded it. During all this ſpace, only ſome inconſiderable provinces to the northward of Italy, and part of the iſland of Britain, had Keen ſubjugated. However, as yet, nothing was loſt; but the degeneracy and corruption of the people had ſown thoſe ſeeds of diſſolution which the empire quickly began to feel. The diſorders were grown to ſuch an height, that even Trajan himſelſ could not cure them. Indeed his eaſtern conqueſts could ſcarce have been preſerved though the republic had been exiſting in all its glory; and therefore they were quietly reſigned by his ſucceſſor Adrian, as too diſtant, diſaffected, and ready to be over-run by the barbarous nations. The province of Dacia, being nearer to the centre of government, was more eaſily preſerved; and of conſequence remained for a long time ſubject to Rome. During the 23 years of the reign of Antoninus, few remarkable events happened. The hiſtorians of thoſe times are exceſſive in their praiſes of his juſtice, generoſity, and other virtues, both public and private. He put a ſtop to the perſecution of the Chriſtians, which raged in the time of Trajan and Adrian, and reduced the Brigantes, a tribe of Britons, who had revolted. However, during his reign, ſeveral calamities befel the empire. The Tiber, overflowing its banks, laid the lower part of Rome under water. The inundation was followed by a fire, and this by a famine, which ſwept off great numbers, though the emperor took the utmoſt care to ſupply the city from the moſt diſtant provinces. At the ſame time the cities of Narbonne in Gaul, and Antioch in Syria, together with the great ſquare in Garthage, were deſtroyed by fire; however, the emperor ſoon reſtored them to their former condition. He died in the year 163, univerſally lamented by his ſubjects, and was ſucceeded by Marcus Aurelius, ſurnamed the <hi rend="italic">Philoſopher,</hi>  whom he had adopted towards the latter end of his reign.</p><p>The tranſactions of this emperor the reader will find related under the article <hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps">Antoninus Philoſophus @@</hi></hi><hi rend="smallcaps">(A).</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">@@@(a) As, after the death of Marcus Aurelius, the Roman empire declined very faſt, it may not be amiſs here to give ſome account of the military and other eſtabliſhments of the Roman emperors. Mr Gibbon obſerves, that, in the times of the commonwealth, the uſe of arms was confined to thoſe who had ſome property to defend, and an intereſt in maintaining the laws which were propoſed to be enacted. But, as the public freedom declined, and war became degraded into a trade, thoſe who had the property of the country choſe rather to hire others than to expoſe their own perſons, as is the caſe with our modern armies. Yet, even after all conſideration of property had been laid aſide among the common ſoldiers, the officers continued to be choſen from among thoſe who had a liberal education, together with a good ſhare of property. However, as the common ſoldiers, in which the ſtrength of an army conſiſts, had now no more of that virtue called </hi><hi rend="italic">patriotiſm,</hi>  the legions which were formerly almoſt invincible, no longer fought with the ſame ardour as before. In former times, the profeſſion of a ſoldier was more honourable than any other; but, when the ſoldiers came to be looked upon as hire-, lings, the honour of the profeſſion funk of courſe, and, by this means, one of the ſtrongeſt motives which the ſoldiers had to ſubmit to their ſevere diſcipline, and exert themſelves againſt their enemies, was removed. On the very firſt entrance of a ſoldier into the Roman ſervice, a ſolemn oath was adminiſtered to him, by which he engaged never to deſert his ſtandard; to ſubmit his own will to that of his leaders, and to ſacriſice his life for the ſafety of the emperor and the empire. The attachment which the Romans had to their ſtandards was indeed aſtoniſhing. The golden eagle, which appeared in the front of the legion, was almoſt an object of adoration with them; and it was eſteemed impious, as well as ignominious, to abandon that ſacred enſign in the time of danger. The centurions had a right to puniſh with blows, the generals with death; and it was an inflexible maxim of the Roman diſcipline, that a good ſoldier ſhould dread his officers much more than the enemy.</p><p>Notwithſtanding all this, ſo ſenſible were the Romans of the inſufficiency of mere valour without ſkill, that</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>