<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>record during a period of 20 years. Be this as it will, however, the death of Romulus was followed by an interregnum, during which the ſenators, to prevent anarchy and confuſion, took the government into their own hands. Tatius added another hundred to that body ; and theſe 200 ſenators divided themſelves into decuries or tens. Theſe decuries drew lots which ſhould govern firſt ; and the decury to whoſe lot it fell enjoyed the ſupreme authority for five days ; yet in ſuch a manner, that one perſon only of the governing decury had the enſigns of ſovereignty at a time. To theſe another decury ſucceeded, each of them fitting on the throne in his turn, &amp;c. But the people ſoon growing weary of ſuch frequent change of maſters, obliged the ſenate to reſolve on the election of a king. The ſenate referred the election to the people, and the people to the ſenate, who at laſt undertook the taſlc. Some difficulties, however, occurred : the Remans did not chooſe to be ſubject to a Sabine ; and the Sabines, as they had been ſubject to Romulus after the death of Tatius, inſiſted that the king ſhould be choſen out of their nation. At laſt it was agreed, that the king ſhould be a Sabine, but that the Romans ſhould make the choice.</p><p>In conſequence of this determination, the Romans elected Numa Pompilius, an auſtere philoſopher, who had married Tatia, the daughter of Tatius the late king. After the death of his wife, he gave himſelf entirely up to philoſophy and ſuperſtition, wandering from ſolitude to ſolitude, in ſearch of ſacred woods and fountains, which gave the people a great opinion of his fanctſty. The philoſopher at firſt rejected the offer of the kingdom ; but being at laſt prevailed upon, he ſet out for Rome, where he was received with loud acclamations, and had his election unanimouſiy confirmed by the ſenate.</p><p>The reign of Numa is by no means memorable for battles or conqueſts. He was averſe to war ; and made it his ſtudy to ſoften the manners of the Romans, rather than to exalt them to ſuperiorſty over their neighbours. He diſmiſſed the celeres, encouraged agriculture, and divided the citizens into diſtinct bodies of tradeſmen. This laſt meaſure he took on purpoſe to aboliſh the diſtinction between Romans and Sabines, which had hitherto rent the city into two factions ; and this effectually anſwered his end : for now all of tach particular profeſſion, whether Romans or Sabines, were obliged to aſſociate together, and had each their reſpective courts and privileges. In this diviſion the muſicians held the firſt rank, becauſe they were employed in the offices of religion. The goldſmiths, carpenters, curriers, dyers, taylore, &amp;c. formed alſo diſtinct communities ; and were allowed to make byelaws among themſelves, to have their own feſtivals, particular ſacrifices, &amp;c.</p><p>Though Numa himſelf is ſaid by Plutarch to have had pretty juſt notions of the Supreme Being, he nevertheleſs added innumerable ſuperſtitions to thoſe he found in Rome. He divided the miniſters of religion into eight claſſes, appointing to each their office with the greateſt preciſion ; he erected a temple to Janus, the ſymbol of prudence, which was tθι remain open in time of war, and to be ſhut in time of peace. Another temple was erected to <hi rend="italic">Bona Fides ;</hi>  and he invented a new kind of deities called <hi rend="italic">Dii Termini,</hi>  or</p><lb/><p>boundaries, which he cauſed to be placed on the borde rs of the Roman ſtate, and of each man’s particular lands.—The laſt reformation which Numa undertook, was that of the kalendar. Romulus had divided his year into ten months, which, according to Plutarch, had no certain or equal number of days ; ſome conſiſting of 20, ſome of 35, &amp;c. However, by other hiſtorians, we are informed that he allotted to March,</p><p>. May, Quintilis, and October, 31 days ; to April, June, Sextilis, November, and December 30 ; making in all 304 days. But Numa being better acquainted<hi rend="sub">t</hi>with the celeſtial motions, added to theſe the two months of January and February. To compoſe theſe two months he added 50 days to the 304 ; and thus made the year anſwer to the courſe of the moon. He then took fix more from the months that had even days ; and added one day merely out of ſuperſtition, that the year might prove fortunate ; for the pagans looked upon even numbers as unlucky, but imagined odd numbers to be fortunate. However, he could make out no more than 28 for February, and therefore that month was always reckoned unlucky among the Romans. Beſides this, he obſerved the difference between the ſolar and lunar year to be 1 r days ; and to remedy the inequality, he added an intercalary month named<hi rend="italic">Mercedinus</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">Mercedonius,</hi>  of <hi rend="italic">22</hi>  days every two years : but as he knew alſo that the ſolar year conſiſted of 363 days 6 hours, he ordered that every fourth year the month Mercedinus ſhould conſiſt of 23 days. The care of theſe intercalations was left to the prieſts, who left out or put in the intercalary day or month as they imagined it to be lucky or unlucky ; and by that means created ſuch confuſion, that the feſtivals came in proceſs of time to be kept at a ſeaſon quite oppoſite to what they had been formerly.</p><p>Theſe are all the remarkable tranſactions of the reign of Numa, which is ſaid to have continued 43 years ; though ſome think that its duration could not be above 15 or 16. His death was followed by a ſhort interregnum; after which Tullus Hoſtilius, the ſon or grandſon of the famous Herlllia, was unanimouſiy choſen king. Being of a bold and fiery temper, he did not long continue to imitate his peaceful predeceſſor. The Albans, indeed, ſoon gave him an opportunity of exerciſiug his martial diſpoſition. Cœlius, or, as he is called by Livy, <hi rend="italic">Cluilius,</hi>  who was at the head of the Alban republic, jealous of the growing greatneſs of Rome, privately commiſſioned ſome of the moſt indigent of his ſubjects to waſte the Roman territory ; in conſequence of which, a Roman army entered the territories of Alba, engaged the robbers, killed many, and took a great number priſoners. A war ſoon commenced, in conſequence of this, between the two nations ; but when the armies came in fight of each other, their ardour cooled, neither of them ſeeming inclined to come to an engagement. This inaction raiſed a great diſcontent in the Alban army againſt Cluilius ; inſomuch that he came to a reſolution of giving battle to the Romans next morning, or of ſtorming their trenches if they ſhould decline it. Next morning, however, he was found dead in his bed ; after which the Albans choſe in hi« ſtead one Mettus Fuffetius, a man remarkable for his hatred to the Roman name, as Cluilius had been before him, Fuffetius, however continued in the ſamr</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>