<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>find the depth of water in the new channel correſponding to this diſcharge, and the ſame ſlope, we muſt take the method of approximation formerly exemplified, remembering that the diſcharge D is 130849, and the breadth B is 1760,8 at the bottom (the fiant ſides being y). Theſe data will produce a depth of water — 64- inches. To obtain four feet therefore behind any of the flood-gates, we muſt have a ſwell of 41¾ inches produced by the gate below.</p><p>We muſt now determine the width of paſſage which muſt be given at the gates. This will regulate the thickneſs of the ſheet of water which flows over them when ſhut ; and this, with the height of the gate, fixes the ſwell at the gate. The extent of this ſwell, and the elevation of every point of its curved ſurface above the new ſurface of the river, requires a combination oſ the height of ſwell at the flood-gate, with the primitive Hope and the new velocity. Theſe being computed, the ſtations of the gates may be aſſigned, which will ſecure four feet of water behind each in ſummer. We need not give theſe computations, having already exemplified them all with relation to another river.</p><p>This example not only illuſtrates the method of proceeding, ſo as to be enſured of ſucceſs, but alſo gives us a preciſe inſtance of what muſt be done in a caſe which cannot but frequently occur. We ſee what a prodigious excavation is neceſſary, in order to obtain permanency. We have been obliged to enlarge the primitive bed to about thrice its former ſize, ſo that the excavation is at leaſt two·thirds of what the other method required. The expence, however, will ſtill be vaſtly inferior to the other, both from the nature of the work and the quantity of ground occupied. At all events, the expence is enormous, and what could never be repaid by the navigation, except in a very rich and populous country.</p><p>There is another circumſtance to be attended to.— The navigation of this river by ſluices muſt be very de-ſultory, unleſs they are extremely numerous, and of ſmall heights. The natural ſurface of the ſwell being Concave upwards, the additions made by its different parts to the primitive height of the river decreaſe rapidly as they approach to the place A (fig. 2θ), where the ſwell terminates; and three gates, each oſ which raiſes the water one foot when placed at the proper diſtance from each other, will raiſe the water much more than two gates at twice this diſtance, each raifing the water two ſeet. Moreover, when the elevation produced by a flood-gate is conſiderable, exceeding a very few inches, the fall and current produced by the opening of the gate is ſuch, that no boat can poſſibly paſs up the river, and it runs imminent riſlc of being overſet and funk, in the attempt to go down the ſtream. This renders the navigation deſultory. A number of lighters collect themſelves at the gates, and wait their opening. They paſs through as ſoon as the current becomes moderate. This would not, perhaps, be very hurtful in a regulated navigation, if they could then proceed on their voyage. But the boats bound up the river muſt ſtay on the upper ſide of the gate which they have juſt now paſſed, becauſe the channel is now too ſhallow for them to proceed. Thoſe bound down the river can only go to the next gate, unleſs it has been opened- at a time nicely adjuſted to the opening of the one above it. The paſſage</p><p>downwards <hi rend="italic">may<hi rend="sub">i</hi></hi>  in many caſes, be continued, by very intelligent and attentive lockmen, but the paſſage up <hi rend="italic">mu/l</hi>  be exceedingly tedious. Nay, we may ſay, that <hi rend="italic">nυlfιle</hi>  the paſſage downwards is continuous, it is but in a very few caſes that the paſſage upward is practicable. If we add to theſe inconveniences the great danger of paſſage during the freſhes, while all the gates are open, and the immenſe and unavoidable accumulations of ice, on occaſion even of flight froſts, we may ſee that this method of procuring an inland navigation is amazingly expenſive, deſultory, tedious, and hazardous. It did not therefore merit, on its own account, the attention we have beſtowed on it. But the diſcuſſion was abfo-lutely neceſſary, in order to ſhow what muſt be done in order to obtain effect and permanency, and thus to prevent us from engaging in a project which, to a perſon not duly and confidently informed, is ſo feaſible and promiſing. Many profeſſional engineers are ready, and with honeſt intentions, to undertake ſuch taſks ; and by avoiding this immenſe ex pence, and contenting themſelves with a much narrower channel, they ſucceed, (witneſs the old navigation of the river Merſey). But the work has no duration ; and, not having been found very ſerviceable, its ceſſation is not matter of much regret. The work is not much ſpoken of during its continuance. It is ſoon forgotten, as well as its failure, and engineers are found ready to engage for ſuch another.</p><p>It was not a very refined thought to change this imperfect mode for another free ſrom moſt of its inconveniences. A boat was brought up the river, through one of theſe gates, only by raiſing the waters of the inferior reach, and depreſſing thoſe of the upper : and it could not eſcape obſervation, that when the gates were far aſunder, a vaſt body of water muſt be diſeharged before this could be done, and that it would be a great improvement to double each gate, with a very ſmall diſtance between. Thus a very ſmall quantity of water woιdd fill the interval to the deſired height, and allow the boat to come through ; and this thought was the more obvious, from a ſimilar practice having preceded it, ∙υ∕z. that of navigating a ſmall river by means of double bars, the loweſt of which lay flat' in the bottom of the river, but could be raiſed up on hinges. We have mentioned this already ; and it appears to have been an old practice, being mentioned by Stevinus in his valuable work on ſluices, publiſhed about the beginning of the laſt century ; yet no trace of this method is to be found of much older dates. It .occurred, however, accidentally, pretty often in the flat countries of Holland and Flanders, which being the ſeat of frequent wars, almoſt every town and village was- fortified with wet ditches, connected with the adjoining rivers. Stevinus mention particularly the works of Condé,', as. having been long employed, with great ingenuity, for rendering navigable a very long ſtretch of the Scheldt. The boats were received into the lower part of the foffee, which was ſeparated from the reſt by a ſtone batardeau, ſerving to keep up the waters in thereſt of the foſſee about eight ſeet. In this was a ſluice and another dam, by which the boats could be taken into the upper foſſee, which communicated with a remote part of the Scheldt by a long canal. This appears to. be one of the earlieſt locks.</p><p>In the firſt attempt to introduce this improvement in</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>