<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ſhall, in moſt caſes, be able to make the diſpoſition ſuch as to derive the greateſt poſſible advantage from the materials which he employs.</p><p>It is evident that the whole muſt depend on the principles which regulate the ſtrength of the materials, relative to the manner in which this ſtrength is exerted, and the manner in which the ſtrain is laid on the piece of matter. With reſpect to the firſt, this is not the proper place ſor conſidering it, and we muſt refer the reader to the article <hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps">Strength of Materials in Mechanics.</hi></hi>  We (hall juſt borrow from that article two or three propoſitions ſuited to our purpoſe.</p><p>The force with which the materials of our edifices, roofs, floors, machines, and framings of every kind, reſiſt being broken or cruſhed, or pulled aſunder, is, immediately or ultimately, the coheſion of their particles. When a weight hangs by a rope, it tends either immediately to break all the fibres, overcoming the coheſion among the particles of each, or it tends to pull one parcel of them from among the reſt, with which they are joined. This union of the fibres is brought about by ſome kind of gluten, or by twiſting, which cauſes them to bind each other ſo hard that any one will break rather than come out, ſo much is it withheld by friction. The ultimate reſiſtance is therefore the coheſion of the fibre ; the force or ſtrength of all fibrous materials, ſuch as timber, is exerted in much the fame manner. The fibres are either broken or pulled out from among the reſt. Metals, ſtone, glaſs, and the like, reſiſt being pulled aſunder by the ſimple coheſion of their parts.</p><p>The force which is neceſſary for breaking a rope or wire is a proper meaſure of its ſtrength. In like manner, the force neceſſary for tearing directly aſunder any rod of wood or metal, breaking all its fibres, or tearing them from among each other, is a proper meaſure of the united ſtrength of all theſe fibres. And it is the limpleſt ſtrain to which they can be expoſed, being juſt equal to the ſum of the forces neceſſary for breaking or diſengagſhg each fibre. And, if the body is not of a fibrous ſtructure, which is the caſe with metals, ſtones, glaſs, and many other ſub-ſtances, this force is ſtill equal to the ſimple ſum of the coheſive forces of each particle which is ſeparated by the fracture. Let us diſtinguiſh this mode of exertion of the coheſion of the body by the name of its Ab* solute Strength.</p><p>When ſolid bodies are, on the contrary, expoſed to great compreſſion, they can reſiſt only to a certain degree. A piece of clay or lead will be ſqueezed out ; a piece of freeſtone will be cruſhed to powder ; a beam of wood will be crippled, ſwelling out in the middle, and its fibres loſe their mutual coheſion, after which it is eaſily cruſhed by the load. A notion may be formed of the manner in which theſe ſtrains are reſiſted by conceiving a cylindrical pipe filled with ſmall ſhot, well ſhaken together, ſo that each ſphericle is lying in the cloſeſt manner poſſible, that is, in contact with ſix others in the ſame vertical plane (this being the poſition in which the ſhot will take the leaſt room). Thus each touches the reſt in fix points : Now ſuppoſe them all united, in theſe ſix points only, by ſome cement. This aſſemblage will flick together and form a cylindrical pillar, which may be taken out of its mould. Sup</p><lb/><p>poſe this pillar ſtanding upright, and loaded above. The ſupports ariſing ſrom the cement act obliquely, and the load tends either to force them aſunder laterally, or to make Jſhem Aide on each other : either of theſe things happening, the whole is cruſhed to pieces. The reſiſtance of fibrous materials to ſuch a ſtrain is a little more intricate, but may be explained in a way very ſimilar.</p><p>A piece of matter of any kind may alſo be deſtroyed by wrenching or twiſting it. We can eaſily form a notion of its reſiſtance to this kind of ſtrain by confi-dering what would happen to the cylinder of ſmall ſhot if treated in this way.</p><p>And laſtly, a beam, or a bar of metal, or a piece of ſtone or other matter, may be broken tranſverſely. This will happen to a rafter or joiſt ſupported at the, ends when overloaded, or to a beam having one end ſtuck faſt in a wall and a load laid on its projecting part. This is the ſtrain to which materials are moſt commonly expoſed in roofs; and, unfortunately, it is . the ſtrain which they are the leaſt able to bear ; or rather it is the manner of application which cauſes an ex-ternal force to excite the greateſt poſſible immediate ſtrain on the particles. It is againſt this that the carpenter muſt chiefly guard, avoiding it when i∣ι his power, and, in every caſe, diminiſhing it as much as poſſible. It is neceſſary to give the reader a clear notion of the great weakneſs of materials in relation to this tranſverſe ſtrain. But we ſhall do nothing more, referring him to the articles Strain, Stress, Strength.</p><p>Let ACBD (fig. i.) repreſent the ſide of a beam projecting horizontally from a wall in which it is firmly fixed, and let it be loaded with a weight W appended to its extremity. This tends to break it;· and the leaſt reflection will convince any perſon that if the beam is equally ſtrong throughout, it will break in the line CD, even with the ſurface of the wall. It will open at D, while C will ſerve as a ſort of joint, round which it will turn. The croſs ſection through the line CD is, for this reaſon, called the <hi rend="italic">ſeaion of frαcture,</hi>  and the horizontal line, drawn through C on its under ſurſace, is called the <hi rend="italic">axis offrα8ure.</hi>  The fracture is made by tearing aſunder the fibres, ſuch as DE or FG. Let us ſuppoſe a real joint at C, and that the beam is really ſawed through along CD, and that in place of its natural fibres threads are ſubſtituted all over the ſection of fracture. The weight now tends to break theſe threads ; and it is our buſineſs to find the force neceſſary for this purpoſe.</p><p>It is evident that DCA may be conſidered as a bended lever, of which C is the fulcrum. If /be the force which will juſt balance the coheſion of a thread when hung on it ſo that the ſmalleſt addition will break it, we may find the weight which will be ſufficient for this purpoſe when hung on at A, by ſaying, AC : CD <hi rend="italic">—j</hi>  : ?, and <hi rend="italic">φ</hi>  will be the weight which will juſt break the thread, by hanging <hi rend="italic">φ</hi>  by the point A. This gives</p><p>CD</p><p>us pZ×<hi rend="sup">-</hi>ζjyγ∙ U the weight be hung on at<hi rend="italic">a,</hi>  the force</p><p>juſt ſufficient for breaking the ſame thread will be CD.</p><p><hi rend="italic">— ffff</hi>  lik<hi rend="sup">,e</hi>  manner the force $&gt;, w<hi rend="sup">,</hi>hich muſt be hung on at A in order to break an equally ſtrong or as</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>