<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>proportional to the cubes of the heights in rectangular beds, and in their correſponding trapeziums.</p><p>1.    Knowing the mean depth and the proportion of the width and real depth, we can determine the dimenſions of the bed, and we have <hi rend="italic">ιυ — q d-f2d,</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">h —d</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">+<hi rend="sup">2</hi>-d</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">q ∙</hi></p><p>2.    If we know the area and mean depth, we can in Hike manner find the dimenſions, that is, <hi rend="italic"><hi rend="sup">r</hi>tυ</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">h ; </hi>for</p><p>A='∑uZ&gt;, and <hi rend="italic">d~—</hi>— A.  ; therefore w— ί —2Ä <hi rend="italic">io-j-2 h</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">+ -.</hi></p><p>2 <hi rend="italic">d</hi></p><p>3.    If <hi rend="italic">d</hi>  be known, and one of the dimenſions be</p><p>given, we can find the other ; for √=—<hi rend="italic">1L!D</hi>  gives w + 2 <hi rend="italic">h</hi></p><p>2 <hi rend="italic">h d , <hi rend="sub">1</hi><hi rend="sup">t</hi>w d &lt;ιυ~ -</hi>-,, and ∕j =--.</p><p><hi rend="italic">h—a    nυ—2d</hi></p><p>4.    If the velocity V and-the ſlope S for a river in train be given, we can find the mean depth ; for V = . Whence we reduce , and  √ <hi rend="italic">d </hi>= to this quantity + 0,1. </p><p>5.    We can deduce the ſlope which will put in train a river whoſe channel has given dimenſions. We make</p><p><hi rend="underline"><hi rend="sup">2</hi>97 (√√-0,1)</hi>     <hi rend="sub">=</hi>  √ S. This ſhould be =c √ S</p><p>V+O,3 (√r∕-O, I )</p><p>•—L √S ⅛ι,6, which we correct by trials, which will be exemplified when we apply theſe doctrines to practice'.</p><p>Having thus eſtabliſhed the relation betw<hi rend="sup">,</hi>een the different circumſtances of the form of the channel to our general formula, we proceed to conſider,</p><p>§ 2. <hi rend="italic">The gradations of velocity from the middle of the<hi rend="sup"/>ſtream to the lld<hi rend="sup">a</hi>s.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">’The knowledge of this is neceſſary for underſtanding the regimen of a river ; for it is the velocity of the filaments in contact with the bed which produces any change in it, and occaſions any preference of one to another, in reſpect of regimen or ſtability. Did theſe circumſtances not operate, the water, true to the laws of hydraulics, and confined within the bounds which have been aſſigned them, would neither enlarge nor di-rniniſh the area of the channel. But this is all that we can promiſe of waters perfectly clear, running in pipes or hewn channels. But rivers, brooks, and ſmaller ſtreams, carry along waters loaded with mud or fand, which they depoſit wherever their velocity is checked ; and they tear up, on the other hand, the materials of the channel wherever their velocity is ſufficiently great. Nature, indeed, aims continually at an equilibrium, and works without ceaſing to perpetuate her own performances, by eſtabliſhing an equality of action and reaction, and proportioning the forms and direction of the motions to her agents, and to local circumſtances. Her work is Row but unceaſing ; and what ſhe cannot ac-</hi></p><lb/><p>compliſh in a year ſhe will do in a century. The beds· of our rivers have acquired ſome ſtability, becauſe they are the )abour of ages ; and it is to time that we owe<hi rend="sup">, </hi>thoſe deep and wide valleys which receive- and confine our rivers in channels, which are now conlolidated, and with ſlopes which have been gradually moderated, ſo that they no longer either ravage our habitations or confound our boundaries. Art may imitate nature, and by directing her operations (which ſhe ſtill carries on according to lier own impreſcriptible law’s) according to our views, we can halten her progreſs, and accompliſh our purpoſe, during the ſhort period of human life. But we can do this only by ſtudying the unalterable laws of mechaniſm. Theſe are preſented to us by ſpontaneous nature. Frequently we remain ignorant of their foundation : but ſt is not neceſſary for the proſpe-rity of the ſubject that he have the talents of the ſena-tor ; he can profit by the ſtatute without underſtanding its grounds. It is ſo in the preſent inſtance. We have not as yet been able to infer the law of retardation obſerved in the filaments of a running ſtream from any found mechanical principle. The problem, however, does not appear beyond our powers, if we aſſume, with Sir Iſaac Newton, that the velocity of any particular filament is the arithmetical mean between thoſe of the filaments immediately adjoining. We may be aſſured, that the filament in the axis of an inclined cylindrical tube, of which the current is in train, moves the faſteſt, and that all thoſe in the ſame circumference round it are moving with one velocity, and that the ſlow’eſt are thoſe which glide along the pipe. We may affirm the ſame thing of the motions in a ſemi-cylindrical inclined channel conveying an open ſtream. But even in theſe we have not yet demonſtrated the ratio between the extreme velocities, nor in the different circles. This muſt be decided experimentally.</p><p>And here we are under great obligations to Mr de Buat. He has compared the velocity in the axis of a prodigious number and variety of ſtreams, differing in ſize, form, ſlope, and velocity, and has computed in them all the mean velocity, by meaſuring the quantities of water diſcharged in a given time. His method of meaſuring the bottom velocity was ſimple and juſt. He threw in a gooſeſherry, as nearly as poſſible, of the ſame ſpecific gravity with the water. It was carried along the bottom almoſt without touching it. See <hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps">Résistance of Fluids,</hi></hi>  n<hi rend="sup">o</hi>  67.</p><p>He diſcovered the following laws : 1. In ſmall velocities the velocity in the axis is to that at the bottom in a ratio of conſiderable inequality. 2. This ratio diminiſhes as the velocity increaſes, and in very great velocities approaches to the ratio of equality. 3. What was moſt remarkable was, that neither the magnitude of the channel, nor its ſlope, had any influence in changing this proportion, while the mean velocity remained the ſame. Nay, though the ſtream ran on a channel covered with pebbles or coarſe fand, no difference worth minding was to be obſerved from the velocity over a poliſhed channel. 4. And if the velocity in the axis is conſtant, the velocity at the bottom is alſo conſtant, and is not affected by the depth of water or magnitude of the ſtream. In ſome experiments the depth was thrice thd width, and in others the width was thrice the depth. This changed the proportion of the magnitude of the</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>