<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>cheap and certain conveyance of goods is there obtained by means of ſtreams which we would think no better than boundary ditches, and unfit for every purpoſe of this kind. By means of a bar the water is kept up a very few inches, and the ſtream has free courſe to the ſea. The ſhoot over the bar is prevented by means of another bar placed a little way below it, lying flat in the bottom of the ditch, but which may be raiſed up on hinges. The lighterman makes his boat faſt to a flake immediately above the bar, raiſes the lower bar, brings over his boat, again makes it ſaſt, and, having laid down the other bar again, proceeds on his journey. This contrivance anſwers the end of a lock at a very trifling expence ; and though it does not admit of what we are accuſtomed to call navigation, it gives a very ſure conveyance, which would otherwiſe be impoſſible. When the waters can be raiſed by bars, ſo that they may be drawn off for machinery or other purpoſes, they are preferable to weirs, becauſe they do not obſtruct floating with rafts, and are not deſtroyed by the ice.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Prob. III. Given the height of a bar, the depth of water both above and below it, and the width of the river, to determine the diſeharge ?</hi></p><p>This is by no means ſo eaſily ſolved as the diſcharge over a weir, and we cannot do it with the ſame degree of evidence. We imagine, however, that the following obſervations will not be very far from a true account of the matter.</p><p>We may firſt ſuppoſe a reſervoir LFBM (fig. 19.) of ſtagnant water, and that it has a waſteboard of the height CB. We may then determine, by the foregoing problems, the diſcharge through the plane E C. With reſpect to the diſcharge through the part C A, it ſhould be equal to this product of the part of the ſection by the velocity correſponding to the fall EC, which is the difference of the heights of water above and below the bar ; for, becauſe the difference of E <hi rend="italic">a</hi>  and C <hi rend="italic">a</hi>  is equal to E C, every particle <hi rend="italic">a</hi>  of water in the plane CA is preſſed in the direction of this ſtream with the ſame force, &lt;z√z. the weight of the column E C. The ſum of theſe diſcharges ſhould be the whole diſcharge over the bar ; but ſince the bar is ſet up acroſs a running river, its diſcharge muſt be the ſame with that of the river. The water of the river, when ſt comes to the place of the bar, has acquired ſome velocity by its ſlope or other cauſes, and this correſponds to ſome height F E. This velocity, multiplied by the ſection of the river, having the height E B, ſhould give a diſcharge equal to the diſeharge over the bar.</p><p>To avoid this complication of conditions, we may firſt compute the diſcharge of the bar in the manner now pointed out, without the conſideration of the previous velocity of the ſtream. This diſcharge will be a little too ſmall. If we divide it by the ſection F B, it will give a primary velocity too ſmall, but not far from the truth. Therefore we ſhall get the height F E, by means of which we ſhall be able to determine a velocity intermediate between D G and C H, which would correſpond to a weir, as alſo the velocity C H, which correſponds to the part of the ſection C A, which is wholly under water. Then we correct all theſe quantities by repeating the operation with them inſtead of our firſt aſſumptions.</p><p>Mr Buat found this computation extremely near the</p><p>truth, but in all caſes a little greater than obſervation exhibited.</p><p>We may now ſolve the problem in the moſt general terms.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Prob. IV. Given the breadth, depth, and the ſlope of a river, if we confine its paſſage by a bar or weir of a known height and width, to determine the riſe of the waters above the bar.</hi></p><p>The ſlope and dimenſions of the channel being given, our formula will give us the velocity and the quantity of water diſeharged. Then, by the preceding problem, find the height of water above the waſteboard. From the ſum of theſe two heights deduct the ordinary depth of the river. The remainder is the riſe of the waters. For example :</p><p>Let there be a river whoſe ordinary depth is 3 feet, arid breadth 40, and whoſe ſlope is ι∣ inches in 100 fathoms, or ∙j-g⅛o∙ Suppoſe a weir on this river 6 feet high and 1 8 feet wide.</p><p>We muſt firſt find the velocity and diſcharge of the river in its natural ſtate, we have <hi rend="italic">l</hi>  =480 inches, <hi rend="italic">h = </hi>36, — = 5-ffVσ∙ Our formula of uniform motion gives</p><p>V = 23,45, and D = 405216 cubic inches.</p><p>The contraction obtains here on the three ſides of the orifice. We may therefore take √Tg = 26,τ.— TV. <hi rend="italic">B.</hi>  This example is*Mr Buat’s, and all the meaſures are French. We have alſo <hi rend="italic">a</hi>  (the height of the weir) 72, and 2 <hi rend="italic">g =.</hi>  724. Therefore the equation <hi rend="italic">h =</hi></p><p>(ô.«7√⅛^∕) ÷~ (7√⅛ (α<hi rend="sub">+</hi>i )* <hi rend="sup">becomes</hi> 3°'<hi rend="sup">l82</hi>∙</p><p>Add this to the height of the weir, and the depth of the river above the ſluice is 102,182, = 8 feet and 6,τ82 inches. From this take 3 ſeet, and there remai ,<hi rend="sub">+ </hi>5 feet and 6,182 inches for the riſe of the waters.</p><p>There is, however, an important circumſtance in this riſe of the waters, which muſt be diſtinctly underſtood before we can ſay what are the intereſting effects of this weir. This ſwell extends, as we all know, to a conſiderable diſtance up the ſtream, but is leſs fenſible as we go away from the weir. What is the diſtance to which the ſwell extends, and what increaſe does it produce in the depth at different diſtances from the weir ?</p><p>If we ſuppoſe that the ſlope and the breadth of the channel remain as before, it is plain, that as we come down the ſtream from that point where the ſwell is inſenſible, the depth of the channel increaſes all the way to the dam. Therefore, as the ſame quantity of water paſſes through every ſection of the river, the velocity muſt diminiſh in the ſame proportion (very nearly) that the ſection increaſes. But this being an open ſtream, and therefore the velocity being iuſeparably connected with the ſlope of the ſurface, it follows, that the ſlope of the ſurface muſt diminiſh ail the way from that point where the ſwell of the water is inſenſible to the dam. The ſurface, therefore, cannot be a ſimple inclined plane, but muſt be concave upwards, as repreſented in ſig. 20. where FKLB repreſents the channel of a river, and FB the ſurface of the water running in it. If this be kept up to A by a weir AL, the ſurface will be a curve FIA, touching the natural ſurface F at the beginning of the ſwell, and the line AD which touches it in A will have the ſlope S correſponding to the velocity which the waters have immediately before going over the weir. We know this ſlope, becauſe we</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>