<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>carried by one Aſpolodorus into the very chamber of Cæſar. Her addreſs at firſt pleaſed him ; but her calefies, which were carried beyond the bounds of innocence, entirely brought him over to ſecond her claims.</p><p>While Cleopatra was thus employed in forwarding her own views, her ſiſter Arſmoe was alſo ſtrenuouſly engaged in the, camp in purſuing a ſeparate intereſt. Sire had found means, by the aſſiſtance of one Ganymede her confident, to make a large diviſion in the Egyptian army in her favour ; and ſoon after cauſed Achillas to be murdered, and Ganymede to take the command in his ſtead, and to carry on the ſiege with greater vigour than before. Ganymede’s principal effort was by letting in the ſea upon thoſe canals which ſup-plied the palace with ſreſli water; but this inconvenience Cæſar remedied by digging a great number of wells. His next endeavour was to prevent the junction of Cæſar’s 24th legion, which he twice attempted in vain. He ſoon after made himſelf maſter of a bridge which joined the iſle of Pharos to the continent, from which poſt Cæſar was reſolved to diſlodge him. In the heat of action, ſome mariners came and joined the combatants ; but being ſeized with a panic, inſtantly fled, and ſpread a general terror through the army. All Cæſar’s endeavours to rally his forces were in vain, the confuſion was paſt remedy, and numbers were drowned or put to the ſword in attempting to eſcape; on which, ſeeing the irremediable diſorder of his troops, he retired to a ſhip in order to get to the palace that was juſt oppoſite. However, he was no ſooner on board than great crowds entered at the ſame time with him ; upon which, apprehenſive of the ſhip’s finking, he jumped into the ſea, and ſwam 200 paces to the fleet that lay before the palace.</p><p>The Alexandrians, finding their efforts to take the. palace ineffectual, endeavoured at leaſt to get their king out of Cæſar’s power, as he had ſeized upon his perſen in the beginning of their diſputes. For this purpoſe they made uſe of their cuſtomary arts of diſſimulation, profeſſing the utmoſt deſire for peace, and only wanting the preſence of their lawful prince to give a fonction to the treaty. Cæſar, who was ſenſible of their perfidy, nevertheleſs concealed his ſuſpicions, and gave them their king, as he was under no apprehenſions from the abilities of a boy. Ptolemy, however, the inſtant he was ſet at liberty, inſtead of promoting peace, made every effort to give vigour to hoſtilities.</p><p>In this manner Cæſar was hemmed in ſor ſome time: but he was at laſt relieved from this mortifying ſituation by Mithridates Pergamenus, one of his moſt faithful partizans ; who, collecting a numerous army in Syria, marched into Egypt, took the city of Peluſium, repulſed the Egyptian army with loſs, and at laſt, joining with Cæſar, attacked their camp, and made a great ſtaughter of the Egyptians. Ptolemy himſelf, attempting to eſcape on board a veſſel that was foiling down the river, was drowned by the ſhip’s ſinking ; and Cæſar thus became maſter of all Egypt without any further oppoſition. He therefore appointed, that Cleopatra, with her younger brother, who was then but an infant, ſhould jointly govern, according to the intent of their father’s will ; and drove out Arſinoe with Ganymede into baniſhment.</p><p>Cæſar now for a while ſeemed to relax ſrom the «foal activity of his conduct, captivated with the charms</p><lb/><p>of Cleopatra. Inſtead of quitting Egypt to go and quell the remains of Pompey’s party, he abandoned himſelf to, his pleaſures, palling whole nights in feaſts with the young queen. He even reſolved to attend her up the Nile into Ethiopia ; but the brave veterans, who had long followed his fortune, boldly reprehended his conduct, and refuſed to be partners in ſe infomous an expedition. Thus, at length, rouzed from his lethargy, he left Cleopatra, by whom he had a ſon who was afterwards named <hi rend="italic">Ceeſario,</hi>  in order to oppoſe Pharnaces the king of Pontus, who had now made ſome inroads upon the dominions of Rome. Here he was attended with the greateſt ſucceſs, as we have related under the article Pontus ; and having ſettled affairs in this part of the empire, as well as time would permit, he embarked for Italy, where he arrived ſooner than his enemies could expect, but not before his affairs there abſolutely required his preſence. He had been, during his abſence, created conſul for five years, dictator for one year, and tribune of the people for life. But Antony, who in the mean time governed in Rome for him, had filled the city with riot and debauchery, and many commotions enſued, which nothing but the arrival of Cæſar could appeaſe. However, by his moderation and humanity, he ſoon reſtored tranquillity to the city, ſcarce making any diſtinction between thoſe of his own and the oppoſite party. Thus having, by gentle means, reſtored his authority at home, he prepared to march into Africa, where Pompey’s party had found time to rally under Scipio and Cato, aſſiſted by Juba king of Mauritania. But the vigour of his proceedings had like to have been retarded by a mutiny in his own ar. my. Thoſe veteran legions, who had hitherto conquered all that came before them, began to murmur for not having received the rewards which they had expected for their paſt ſervices, and now inſiſted upon their diſcharge. However, Cæſar found means to quell the mutiny ; and then, according to his uſual diligence, landed with a ſmall party in Africa, the reſt of the army following ſoon after. After many movements and ikirmiſhes, he reſolved at laſt, to come to a deciſive battle. For this purpoſe he inveſted the city of Tap-ſus, ſuppoſing that Scipio would attempt its relief, which turned out according to his expectation. Scipio, joining with the young kingof Mauritania, advanced with, his army, and encamping near Cæſar, they ſoon came to a general battle. Cæſar’s ſucceſs was as uſual ; the enemy received a complete and final overthrow, with little loſs on his ſide. Juba, and Petreius his general, killed each other in deſpair ; Scipio, attempting to eſcape by ſea into Spain, ſell in among the enemy, and was ſlain ; ſo that, of all the generals of that undone party, Cato was now alone remaining.</p><p>This extraordinary man, havinq retired into Africa after the battle of Pharſalia, had led the wretched remains of that defeat through burning deſerts and tracts inſeſted with ſerpents of various malignity, and was now in the city of Utica, which he had been left to deſeud. Still, however, in love with even the ſhow of Roman government, he had formed the principal citizens into a ſenate, and conceived a reſolution of holding out the town. He accordingly aſſembled his ſenators upon this occaſion, and exhorted them to ſtand a ſiege; but finding his admonitions ineffectual, lie ſtabbed himſelf with his ſword j∙. Upon his death,</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>