<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>have invented their tales of knights-errant, monſters, and giants.</p><p>“ De Saint Foix, in his Hiſtorical EiΓays on this ſubject, thus expreſſes himſelf: ‘ Women and girls were not in greater ſecurity when they paſſed by abbeys. The monks ſuſtained an aſſault rather than relinquiſh their prey: if they ſaw themſelves lofing ground, they brought to their walls the relics of ſome ſaint. Then it generally happened that the aſſailants, ſeized with awful veneration, retired, and dared not to purſue their vengeance. This is the origin of the enchanters, of the enchantments, and of the enchanted caſtles, deſcribed . in romances.’</p><p>“ To theſe may be added what the author of Northern Antiquities, Vol, I. p. 243, writes, that ‘ as the walls of the caſtles ran winding round them, they often called them by a name which ſignified <hi rend="italic">ſrpents</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">dragons;</hi>  and in theſe were commonly ſecured the women and young maids of diſtinction, who were ſeldom ſafe at a time when ſo many bold warriors were rambling up and down in ſearch of adventures. It was this cuſtom which gave occaſion to ancient romancers, who knew not how to deſcribe any thing limply, to invent ſo many fables concerning princeſſes of great beauty, guarded by dragons.’</p><p>“ The Italian romances of the 14th century were ſpread abroad in great numbers. They formed the polite literature of the day. But if it is not permitted to authors freely to expreſs their ideas, and give full play to the imagination, theſe works muſt never be placed in the ſtudy of the rigid moraliſt. They indeed puſhed their indelicacy to the verge of groſſneſs, and ſeemed rather to ſeek than to avoid ſcenes which a modern would bluſh to deſcribe. They (to employ the expreſſion of one of their authors) were not aſhamed to name what God had created. Cinthio, Bandello, and others, but chiefly Boccacio, rendered libertiniſm agreeable, by the faſcinating charms of a poliſhed ſtyle, and a luxuriant imagination.</p><p>“ This however muſt not be admitted as an apology for immoral works ; for poiſon is ſtill poiſon, even when it is delicious. Such works were, and ſtill continue to be, the favourites of a nation which is ſtigmatiſed for being prone to illicit pleaſures and impure amours. They are. ſtill curious in their editions, and are not par* ſimonious in their price for what they call an uncaſtra-ted copy. There are many Italians, not literary men, who are in poſſeſſion of an ample library of theſe old noveliſts.</p><p>“ If we paſs over the moral irregularities of theſe romances, we may diſcover a rich vein of invention, which only requires to be releaſed from that rubbiſh which disfigures it to become of an invaluable price. The Decamerons, the Hecatommiti, and the Novellas of theſe writers, made no inconſiderable figure in the little library of our Shakeſpeare. Chaucer is a notorious imitator and lover of them; his Knight’s Tale is little more than a paraphraſe of Boccacio’s <hi rend="sup">r</hi>Γefeoide. Fontaine has caught all their charms with all their licentiouſneſs. From ſuch works, theſe great poets, and many of their contemporaries, frequently borrowed their plots ; not uncommonly kindled at their flame the ardour of their genius ; but bending too ſubmiſſively to their own peculiar taſte, or that of their age, in extracting the ore, they haγe not purified it of the alloy.</p><lb/><p>“ We muſt now turn our contemplation to the Frendh romances of the laſt century. They were then carried to a point of perfection, which as romances they cannot exeeed. To this the Aſtyea of D’Urſe greatly contributed. It was "followed by the illuſtrious Baſſa, the great Cyrus, Clelia, &amp;c. which, though not adapt” ed to the preſent age, gave celebrity to their authors. Their ſtyle, as well as that of the Aſtrea, is diffuſe and inſipid. Zaide (attributed by ſome to Segrais, but by Huet to Madame La Fayette) and the princeſs of Cleves are tranſlated, and though they are maſterpieces of the kind, were never popular in our country, and are little adapted to its genius.</p><p>“ It is not ſurpriſing that romances have been regarded as pernicious to good ſenſe, morals, taſte, and literature. It was in this light they were conſidered by Boileau ; becauſe a few had ſucceeded, a croud imitated their examples. Gombervilk and Scudery, and a few more were admired ; but the ſatiiiſt diſſolved the illuſion. 1 his he did moſt effectually by a dialogue, in which he ridicules thoſe citizens of a certain diſtrict, whoſe characters were concealed in theſe romances, under the names of Brutus, Horace Codes, Lucretius, and Clelia. This dialogue he only read to his friends, and did not give it ſor a long time to the public, as he eſteemed mademoiſelle de Scudery : but when at length it was publiſhed, it united all the romance writers againſt our ſatiriſt.</p><p>“ From romances, which had now exhauſted the patience of the public, ſprung novels. They attempted to allure attention by this inviting title, and reducing<hi rend="sup">-</hi>their works from ten to two volumes. The name of romance diſguſted ; and they ſubſtituted thoſe of hiſtories, lives, memoirs, and adventures. In theſe works (obſerves Irail) they quitted the unnatural incidents, the heroic projects, the complicated and endleſs intrigues, and the exertion of noble paſſions ; heroes were not now taken from the throne, they were ſought for even amongſt the loweſt ranks of the people. On this ſubject, I ſhall juſt obſerve, that a novel is a very dangerous poiſon in the hand of a libertine ; it may be a ſalutary medicine in that of a virtuous writer.” See Novel.</p><p>ROMAGNA, a province of Italy, in the pope’s territories, bounded on the north by the Ferrareſe, on the ſouth by Tuſcany and the duchy of Urbino, on the eaſt by the Gulf of Venice, and on the well by the Bolognefe and. a part of Tuſcany. It is fertile in corn, wine, oil, fine fruits, and paſtures. It has alſo mines, mineral waters, and ſalt-works, which make its principal revenue. Ravenna is the capital town.</p><p>ROMANIA, a province of Turkey in Europe, bounded on the north by Bulgaria, on the eaſt by the Black Sea, on the ſouth by the Archipelago and the ſea of Marmora, and on the weſt by Macedonia and Bulgaria; being 200 miles in length and 130 in breadth. It was formerly called <hi rend="italic">Thrace,</hi>  and is the principal and largeſt of all the provinces the Turks poſ-ſeſs in Europe. It is a fruitful country in corn and paſtures,. and there are mines of ſilver, lead, and alum.</p><p>It is divided into three great governments or ſangia-cates ; namely, Kirkel, of which Philipoli is the capital ; Galipoli, whoſe capital is of the ſame name 5 and Byzantium, or Byzia, or Viza, of which Con-ftantinople is the capital. The Turks beſtow the</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>