<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>RHODES CONTD vour, and greatly honoured by the ſenate. In the Mithridatic war, their alliance
                with Rome brought upon them the king of Pontus with all his force; but having loſt
                the greateſt part of his fleet before the city, he was obliged to raiſe the ſiege
                without performing any remarkable exploit. In the war which Pompey made on the
                Cilician pirates, the Rhodians aſſiſted him with all their naval force, and had a
                great ſhare in the victories which he gained. In the civil war between Cæſar
                and Pompey, they aſſiſted the latter with a very numerous fleet. After his death
                they ſided with Cæſar; which drew upon them the reſentment of C. Caſſius, who
                advanced to the iſland of Rhodes with a powerful fleet, after having reduced the
                greateſt part of the continent. The Rhodians, terrified at his approach, ſent
                ambaſ-ſadors intreating him to make up matters in an amicable manner, and promiſing
                to ſtand neuter, and recal the ſhips which they had ſent to the aſſiſtance of the
                triumviri. Caſſius inſiſted upon their delivering up their fleet to him, and putting
                him in poſſeſſion both of their harbour and city. This demand the Rhodians would by
                no means comply with, and therefore began to put themſelves in a condition to ſtand
                a ſiege; but firſt ſent Archelaus, who had taught Caſſius the Greek tongue while he
                ſtudied at Rhodes, to intercede with his diſciple in their behalf. Archelaus could
                not, with all his authority, prevail upon him to moderate his demands; wherefore the
                Rhodians, having created one Alexander, a bold and enterpriſing man, their prætor or
                prytanis, equipped a fleet of 33 ſail, and ſent it out under the command of Mnaſeus,
                an experienced ſea-officer, to offer Caſſius battle. Both fleets fought with
                incredible bravery, and the victory was long doubtful: but the Rhodians, being at
                length overpowered by numbers, were forced to return with their fleet to Rhodes;
                two of their ſhips being ſunk, and the reſt very much damaged by the heavy ſhips of
                the Romans. This was the firſt time, as our author obſerves, that the Rhodians
                were fairly overcome in a ſea-fight.</p>
            <p>Caſſius, who had beheld this fight from a neighbouring hill, having refitted his
                fleet, which had been no leſs damaged than that of the Rhodians, repaired to Loryma,
                a ſtronghold on the continent belonging to the Rhodians. This caſtle he took by
                aſſault; and from hence conveyed his land-forces, under the conduct of Fannius and
                Lentulus, over into the iſland. His fleet Conſiſted of 80 ſhips of war and above 203
                tranſports. The Rhodians no ſooner ſaw this mighty fleet appear, but they went out
                again to meet the enemy. The ſecond engagement was far more bloody than the
                firſt; many ſhips were ſunk, and great numbers of men killed on both ſides. But
                victory anew declared for the Romans; who immediately blocked up the city of Rhodes
                both by ſea and land. As the Rhodians had not had time to furniſh the city with
                ſufficient ſtore of proviſions, ſome of the inhabitants, fearing that if it were
                taken either by aſſault or by famine, Caſſius would put all the inhabitants to the
                ſword, as Brutus had lately done at Xanthus, privately opened the gate to him, and
                put him in poſſeſſion of the town, which he nevertheleſs treated as if it had been
                taken by aſſault. He commanded 50 of the chief citizens, who were ſu-ſpected to
                favour the adverſe party, to be brought before him, and ſentenced them all to die;
                others, to the number of 25, who had commanded the fleet or army</p>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>
            <p>becauſe they did not appear when ſummoned, he pro-ſcribed. Having thus puniſhed ſuch
                as had either acted or ſpoken againſt him or his party, he commanded the Rhodians to
                deliver up to him all their ſhips, and whatever money they had in the public
                treaſury. He then plundered the temples; ſtripping them of all their valuable
                furniture, veſſels, and ſtatues. He is ſaid not to have left one ſtatue in the whole
                city, except that of the ſun; bragging, at his departure, that he had ſtripped the
                Rhodians of all they had, leaving them nothing but the ſun. As to private perſons,
                he commanded them, under ſevere penalties, to bring to him all the gold and ſilver
                they had, promiſing, by a public crier, a tenth part to ſuch as ſhould diſcover any
                hidden trea-ſures. The Rhodians at firſt concealed ſome part of their wealth,
                imagining that Caſſius intended by this proclamation only to terrify them; but when
                they found he was in earneſt, and ſaw ſeveral wealthy citizens put to death for
                concealing only a ſmall portion of their riches, they deſired that the time prefixed
                for the bringing in their gold and ſilver might be prolonged. Caſſius willingly
                granted them their requeſt; and then through fear they dug up what they had hid
                under ground, and laid at his feet all they were worth in the world. By this means
                he extorted from private perſons above 8000 talents. He then fined the city in 500
                more; and leaving L. Varus there with a ſtrong garriſon to exact the fine without
                any abatement, he returned to the continent.</p>
            <p>After the death of Caſſius, Marc Antony reſtored the Rhodians to their ancient rights
                and privileges 5-beſtowing upon them the iſlands of Andros, Naxos, Tenos, and the
                city of Myndus. But theſe the Rhodians ſo oppreſſed and loaded with taxes, that the
                ſame Antony, though a great friend to the Rhodian republic, was obliged to diveſt
                her of the ſovereignty over thoſe places, which he had a little before ſo
                liberally beſtowed upon her. From this time to the reign of the Emperor Claudius we
                find no mention made of the Rhodians. That prince, as Dion informs us, deprived them
                of their liberty for having crucified ſome Roman citizens. However, he ſoon reſtored
                them to their former condition, as we read in Suetonius and Tacitus. The latter
                adds, that they had been as often deprived of, as reſtored to, their liberty, by way
                of puniſhment or reward for their different behaviour, as they had obliged the
                Romans with their aſſiſtance in foreign wars, or provoked them with their ſeditions
                at home. Pliny, who wrote in the beginning of Veſpaſian’s reign, ſtyles Rhodes a <hi
                    rend="italic">beautiſul and free town.</hi> But this liberty they did not long
                enjoy, the iſland being ſoon after reduced by the lame Veſpaſian to a Roman
                province, and obliged to pay a yearly tribute to their new mailers. This province
                was called the <hi rend="italic">province of the iſlands.</hi> The Roman pretor who
                governed it reſided at Rhodes, as the chief city under his juriſdiction; and Rome,
                notwith-ſtanding the eminemt ſervices rendered her by this republic, thenceforth
                treated the Rhodians not as allies, but vaſſals.</p>
            <p>The iſland of Rhodes continued ſubject to the Romans till the reign of the emperor
                Andronicus; when Villaret, grand-maſter of the knights of Jeruſalem, then reſiding
                in Cyprus, finding himſelf much expoſed to the attacks of the Saracens in that
                iſland, reſolved to exchange it for that of Rhodes. This iſland too was</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
