<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>infinite variety of circumſtances, a powerful obſtacle to the practice of moral virtues, to the progreſs of truth, and a weight which prevents them from riſing to that degree of knowledge and perfection of which human nature is capable. They multiply without ceaſing the occaſions of vice, by the facility which they give to ſa-tisfy a multitude of irregular paſſions, and to turn at length thoſe who are attached to them from the road of virtue, and from the deſire of inquiring after truth.</p><p>It is this which Seneca means to expreſs, when he ſays, “ that riches in a vaſt number of caſes have been a great obſtacle to philoſophy ; and that, to enjoy freedom of mind neceſſary for ſtudy, a man muſt live in poverty, or as if he were poor. Everyman (adds he) who wiſhes to lead a pleaſant, tranquil, and ſecure life, muſt avoid, as much as poſſible, the deceitfulneſs of riches, which are a bait with which we allow ourſelves to be taken as in a ſnare, without afterwards having the power to extricate ourſelves, being ſo much the more unhappy, that we believe we poſſeſs them, while, on the contrary, they tyrrannize over us.” <hi rend="italic">Senec. Epiſt. 17.</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">Epiſt.</hi>  8.</p><p>“ The wiſe man (ſays the ſame author in another place) does not love riches to exceſs, but he would not .choofe wholly to diveſt himſelf of them ; he does not receive them into his ſoul, but into his houſe ; he is careful of them, and employs them for the purpoſe of opening a wide field for virtue, and of making it appear in all its ſplendor. Who can doubt that a wiſe man has not more occaſions of diſplaying the elevation and greatneſs of his mind when he is poſſeſſed of riches than when he labours under indigence, ſince, in the laſt condition, he can exerciſe only one virtue, namely, resignation ; whereas, riches give him an opportunity of diſplaying, in their greateſt luſtre, the virtues of temperance, liberality, diligence, regularity, and magnificence. There is no occaſion, then, to prohibit philosophers from the uſe of wealth, or to condemn wiſdom to poverty. The philoſopher may poſſeſs the greateſt riches, provided he has not employed force or ſhed blood in acquiring them ; provided he has not gained them by unjuſt or illegal means ; in a word, provided the uſe which he makes of them be as pure as the ſource from which they were derived, and no perſon (the envious excepted) regretting his poſſeſſion ; he will not refuſe the kindneſsof fortune, and will enjoy, without ſhame or pride, the wealth acquired by honeſt means ; he will have more reaſon to glory, if, after ex-poſinghis riches to the view of the whole world, he can deſire any perſon to carry away the reward of treachery or the fruits of oppreſſion. If, after theſe words, his riches continue undiminiſhed, this man is truly great, and worthy to be rich. If he has not allowed to enter into his poſſeſſion the ſinalleſt piece of money gained by unwarrantable means, neither will he refuſe the greateſt riches, which are the bleſſings of fortune, and the huit of virtue : if he can be rich, he will chooſe to be ſo, and he ſhall have riches ; but he will regard them as bleſſings of uncertain poſſeſſion, and of which he may be every moment deprived ; he will not permit them to be a load to himſelf or to others ; he will give them to the good, or to thoſe whom he would make good ; but he will give them with the niceſt wiſ-dom, taking care always to diſtribute them to the moil worthy, and to thoſe who remember that they muſt give an account, as well of the wealth which they receive from heaven, as of the purpoſes to which it is ap∙ plied.” <hi rend="italic">Senec. de Vita Beata.,</hi>  cap. 21, 22, &amp; 23.</p><p>RICHLIEU (John Armand du Pleſſis de), cardinal of Richlieu and Fronſac, biſhop of Lucon, &amp;c. was born at Paris in 1585. He was of excellent parts ; and at the age of 2 2 had the addref3 to obtain a diſpen ∙ ſation to enjoy the biſhopric of Lucon in 1607. Returning into France, he applied himſelf in a particular manner to the function of preaching ; and his reputation this way procured him the office of almoner to the queen Mary de Medicis. His abilities in the management of affairs advanced him to be ſecretary of ſtate in 1616 ; aftd the king ſoon gave him the preference to all his other ſecretaries. The death of the marquis d’Ancre having produced a revolution in ſtate affairs, Richlieu retired to Avignon ; where he employed himſelf in compoſing books of controverſy and piety. The king having recalled him to court, he was made a cardinal in 1622 ; and, two years after, firſt miniſter of ſtate, and grand maſter of the navigation. In 1626, the iſle of Rhée was preſerved by his care, and Rochelle taken, having ſtopped up the haven by that famous dyke which he ordered to be made there. He accompanied the king to the ſiege of Cazal, and contributed not a little to the raiſing of it in 1629. He alſo obliged the Huguenots to the peace at Akts, which proved the ruin of that party ; he took Pamerol, and ſuccoured Cazal be-ſieged by Spinola. In the mean time the nobles found fault with his conduct, and perſuaded the king to diſ-card him. The cardinal, for his part, was unmoved with it ; and by his reaſonings overthrew what was thought to be determined againſt him ; ſo that, inſtead of being diſgraced, he from that moment became more powerful than ever. He puniſhed all his enemies in the ſame manner as they would have had him ſuffer ; and the day which produced this event, ſo glorious to cardinal Richlieu, was called the <hi rend="italic">day of dupes.</hi>  This able miniſter had from thenceforwards an aſcendancy over the king’s mind ; and he now reſolved to humble the exceſſive pride of the houſe of Auſtria. For that purpoſe he concluded a treaty with Guſtaphus Adolphus king of Sweden, for carrying the war into the heart of Germany. He alſo entered into a league with the duke of Bavaria ; ſecured Lorrain ; railed a part of the princes of the empire againſt the emperor ; treated with the Dutch to continue the war againſt Spain ; favoured the Catalans and Portugueſe till they ſhook off the Spaniſh yoke ; and, in ſhort, took ſo many different meaſures, that he accompliſhed his deſign ; and after having carried on the war with ſucceſs, was thinking of concluding it by a peace, when he died at Paris on the 4th of December 1642, aged 58. He was interred in the Sorbonne, where a magnificent mauſoleum is erected to his memory. This great politician made the arts and ſciences flouriſh; formed the botanical garden at Paris, called the <hi rend="italic">kings garden ;</hi>  founded the French academy ; eſtabliſh-ed the royal printingſhouſe ; erected the palace afterwards called <hi rend="italic">Le Palais Royal,</hi>  which he preſented to the king; and rebuilt the Sorbonne with a magnificence that appears truly royal. Beſides his books of controverſy and piety, there go under the name of this miniſter, A Journal, in 2 vols 12mo ; and a Political Teſtament, in 12mo ; all treating of politics and ſtate affairs. Cardi∙</p></body></text></TEI>