<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>the children propagated during their marriage to be their own (a belief unattainable by the father in a ſtate of promiſcous concubinage), they come by a natural proceſs of the human paſſions (ſee Passion) to love each other through the medium of their offspring. But if it be the duty of man to acquire a ſpirit firſt pure, then peaceable, gentle, and eaſy to be intreated, it muſt be agreeable to the will of God, and a branch of the fitneſs of things, that the ſexual union laſt during the joint lives of the parties ; and therefore the excluſive right of marriage, though adventitious, muſt be equally ſacred with thoſe which are natural.</p><p>But to return from this digreiſion, into which the importance -of the ſubject led us, <hi rend="italic">rights,</hi>  beſides being natural or adventitious, are likewiſe <hi rend="italic">alienable</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">unalienable.</hi>  Every man, when he becomes the member of a civil community, alienates a part of his natural rights. In a ſtate of nature, no man has a ſuperior on earth, and each has a right to defend his life, liberty, and property, by ail the means which nature has put in his power. In civil ſociety, however, theſe rights are all transferred to the laws and the magiſtrate, except in caſes of ſuch extreme urgency as leave not time ſor legal interpoſition. This ſingle conſideration is ſufficient to ſhow, that the right to civil- liberty is alienable ; though, in the vehemence of men’s zeal ſor it, and in the language of ſome political remonſtrances, it has often been pronounced to be an unalienable right. “ The truc reaſon (ſays Mr Paley) why mankind hold in deteſtation the memory of thoſe who have fold their liberty to a tyrant is, that, together with their own, they fold commonly or endangered the liberty of others; of which they had certainly no right to-diſpoſe.” The rights of a prince over his people, and of a huſhand over his wife, are generally and naturally unalienable.</p><p>Another diviſion of rights is into thoſe which are perfect and thoſe which are imperfect. Perfect rights are ſuch as may be preciſely aſcertained and aſſerted by force, or in civil ſociety by the courſe of law. To imperfect rights neither .force nor law is applicable. A man’s rights to his life, perſon, and property, are all perfect ; for if any of theſe be attacked, he may repel the attack by inſtant violence, puniſh the aggreſſor by the courſe of law, or compel the author of the injury to make reſtitution or ſatisfaction. A woman’s right to her honour is likewiſe perfect ; for if ſhe can-Hθt otherwiſe eſcape, ſhe may kill the raviſher. Every poor man has undoubted right to relief from the rich : but his right is imperfect, ſor if the relief be not voluntarily given, he cannot compel it either by law or by violence. There is no duty upon which the Chriſtian religion puts a greater value than alms-giving ; and every preacher of the goſpel has an undoubted right to inculcate the practice of it upon his audience : but even this right is imperfect, for he cannot refuſe the communion to a man merely on account of his illiberality to the poor, as he can to another for the neglect of any duty comprehended under the term juſtice. In elections or apppointments to offices, where the qualifications are preſcribed, the beſt qualified candidate has un-queſtionably a right to ſucceſs ; yet if he be rejected, he can neither ſeize the office by force, nor obtain re-dreſs at law. His right, therefore, is imperfect.</p><p>Here a queſtion naturally offers itſelf to our conſideration : “ How comes a perſon to have a right to a thing,</p><p>and yet have no right to uſe the means neceſſary to obtain it ?” The anſwer is, That in ſuch caſes the object or the circumſtances of the right are ſo indeterminate, that the permiſſion of force, even where the right is real and certain, would lead to force in other caſes where there exiſts no right at all. Thus, though the poor man has a right to relief, who ſhall aſcertain the mode, ſeaſon, and quantum of it, or the perſon by whom it ſhall be adminiſtered ? Theſe things muſt be aſcertained before the right to relief can be enforced by law ; but to allow them to be aſcertained by the poor themſelves, would be to expoſe property to endleſs claims. In like manner, the comparative qualifications of the candidate muſt be aſcertained, before he can enforce his right to the office ; but to allow him to aſcertain his qualifications himſelf, would be to make him judge in his own cauſe between himſelf and his neighbour.</p><p>Wherever the right is imperfect on one ſide, the cor-reſponding obligation on the other muſt be imperfect likewiſe. The violation of it, however, is often not leſs criminal in a moral and religious view than of a perfect obligation. It is well obſerved by Mr Paley, that greater guilt is incurred by diſappointing a worthy candidate of a place upon which perhaps his livelihood depends, and in which he could eminently ſerve the public, than by filching a book out of a library, or picking a pocket of a handkerchief. The ſame ſentiment has been expreſſed by Mr Godwin, but in terms by much too ſtrong, and ſuch as ſhow that he was not at the time complete maſter of his ſubject. “ My neighbour (ſays he) has juſt as much right to put an end to my exiſtence with dagger or poiſon, as to deny me that pecuniary aſſiſtance without which I mult ſtarve, or as to deny me that aſſiſtance without which my intellectual attainments, or my moral exertions, will be materially injured. He has juſt as much right to arauſe himſelf with burning my houſe, or torturing my children .upon the rack, as to ſhut himſelf up in a cell, careleſs about his fellow- men, and to hide ‘ his talent in a napkin.”</p><p>It is certainly true, that the man who ſhould ſuffer another to ſtarve for want of that relief which he <hi rend="italic">knew</hi>  that he <hi rend="italic">alone</hi>  could afford him, would be guilty of murder, and murder of the cruelleſt kind ; but there is an immenſe difference between depriving ſociety of one of its members, and with-holding from that member what might be neceſſary to enable him to make the greateſt poſſible intellectual attainments. Newton might have been uſeful and happy though he had never been acquainted with the elements of mathematics ; and the late celebrated Mr Ferguiſon might have been a valuable member of ſociety, though he had never emerged from lus original condition of a ihepherd. The remainder of the paragraph is too abſurd to require a formal confutation. Had our author, burying his talent in a napkin, ſhut himſelf up ſeven years ago in a cell, careleſs about his fellow men and <hi rend="italic">political jaſtice,</hi>  he would have deprived the public of what he doubtleſs believes to be much uſeful inſtruction ; but had he at that period amuſed himſelf with burning his neighbour’s houſe, and torturing on the rack two or three children, he would have cut off, for any thing he could know, two or three future Newtons, and have himſelf been cut off by the inſulted laws of his country. Now, without ſuppoling the value</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>