<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>imperfect and precarious, that the revolutions of the north might eſeape the knowledge of the court of Ravenna ; till the dark cloud which was collected along the coaſt of the Baltic burſt in thunder upon the banks of the Upper Danube. The emperor of the weft, if his miniſters diſturbed his amuſements by the news of the impending danger, was ſatisfied,with being the occaſion and the ſpectator of the war. The ſafety of Rome was intruſted to the counſels and the ſword of Stilicho ; but ſuch was the feeble and exhauſted ſtatc of the empire, that it was impoſſible to reſtore the fortifications of the Danube, or to prevent, by a vigorous effort, the invaſion of the Germans. The hopes of the vigilant miniſter of Honorius were confined to the defence of Italy. He once more abandoned the provinces; recalled the troops ; preſſed the new levies, which were rigorouſly exacted, and puſillanimouſly eluded ; employed the moſt efficacious means to arreſt or allure the deſerters ; and offered the gift of freedom, and of two pieces of gold, to all the ſlaves who would enliſt. By theſe efforts he painfully collected from the ſubjects of a great empire an army of 30,000 or 40,000 men ; which, in the days of Scipio or Camillus, would have been inſtantly furniſhed by the free citizens of the territory of Rome. The 30 legions of Stilicho were reinforced by a large body of barbarian auxiliaries ; the faithful Alani were perſonally attached to his ſervice ; and the troops of Huns and of Goths, who inarched under the banners of their native princes Hulden and Sarus, were animated by intereſt and reſentment to oppoſe the ambition of Radagaiſus. The king of the confederate Germans paſſed, without reſiſtance, the Alps, the Po, and the Appenine : leaving on one hand the inacceſſible palace of Honorius, ſe-curely buried among the marſhes of Ravenna; and on the*other, the camp of Stilicho, who had fixed his head-quarters at Ticinum, or Pavia, but who ſeems to have avoided a deciſive battle till he had aſſembled his diſtant forces. Many cities of Italy were pillaged, or deſtroyed ; and the ſiege of Florence by Radagaiſus is one of the earlieſt events in the hiſtory of that celebrated republic, whoſe firmneſs checked and delayed the unlkilful fury of the barbarians. The ſenate and people trembled at their approach within 180 miles of</p><p>Rome ; and anxiouſly compared the danger which they had eſcaped with the new perils to which they were expoſed. Alaric was a Chriſtian and a ſoldier, the leader of a diſciplined army ; who underſtood the laws of war, who reſpected the ſanctity of treaties, and who had familiarly converſed with the fubjects of the empire in the ſame camps and the ſame churches. The ſavage Radagaiſus was a ſtranger to the manners, the religion, and even the language, of the civilized nations of the fouth. The fierceneſs of his temper was exaſperated by cruel ſuperſtition ; and it was univerſally believed, that he had bound himſelf by a ſolemn vow to reduce the city into a heap of ſtones and aſhes, and to ſacriſice the moſt illuſtrious of the Roman ſenators on the altars of thoſe gods who were appeaſed by human blood. The public danger, which ſhould have reconciled all domeſtic animoſities, diſplayed the incurable madneſs of religious faction. The oppreſſed votaries of Jupiter and Mercury reſpected, in the implacable enemy of Rome, the character of a devout pagan ; loudly declared, that they were more apprehenſive of the ſacrifices than of the arms of Radagai</p><lb/><p>ſus ; and fect<hi rend="sup">,</hi>etly rejoiced in the calamities of their country, which condemned the faith of their Chriſtian adverfaries.</p><p>“ Florence was reduced to the laſt extremity ; and the fainting courage of the citizens was ſupported only by the authority of St Ambroſe, who had communicated in a dream the promiſe of a ſpeedy deliverance. On a ſudden they beheld from their walls the banners of Stilicho, who advanced with his united force to the relief of the faithful city-, and who ſoon marked that fatal ſpot ſor the grave of the barbarian hoſt. The apparent contradictions of thoſe writers who variouſly relate the defeat of Radagaiſus, may be reconciled without offering much violence to their reſpective teſtimonies. Oroſius and Auguſtin, who were intimately connected by friendſhip and religion, aſeribe this miraculous victory to the providence of God rather than to the valour of man. They ſtrictly exclude every idea of chance, or even of bloodſhed ; and poſitively affirm, that the Romans, whoſe camp was the ſcene of plenty and idleneſs, enjoyed the diſtreſs of the barbarians, ſlowly expiring on the ſharp and barren ridge of the hills of Fæfulæ, which riſe above the city of Florence. Their extravagant aſſertion, that not a ſingle ſoldier of the Chriſtian army was killed, or even wounded, may be diſmiſſed with ſilent contempt ; but the reſt of the narrative of Auguſtin and Oroſius is conſiſtent with the ſtate of the war and the character of Stilicho. Conſcious that he commanded the laſt army of the republic, his prudence would not expoſe it in the open field to the headſtrong fury of the Germans. The method of ſurrounding the enemy with ſtrong lines of circumvallation, which he had twice employed againſt the Gothic king, was repeated on a larger ſcale, and with more conſiderable effect. The examples of Cæſar muſt have been familiar to the moſt illiterate of the Roman warriors ; and the fortifications of Dyrrhachium, which connected 24 caſtles by a perpetual ditch and rampart of 15 miles, afforded the model of an intrenchment which might confine and ſtarve the moſt numerous hoſt of barbarians. The Roman troops had leſs degenerated from the induſtry than from the valour of their anceſtors ; and if the ſervile and laborious work offended the pride of the ſoldiers, Tuſcany could ſupply many thouſand peaſants, who would labour, though perhaps they would</p><p>not fight, for the ſalvation of their native country.— The impriſoned multitude of horſes and men was gradually deſtroyed by famine, rather than by the ſword ; but the Romans were expoſed, during the progreſs of ſuch an extenſive work, to the frequent attacks of an impatient enemy. The deſpair of the hungry barbarians would precipitate them againſt the fortifications of Stilicho ; the general might ſometimes indulge the ardour of his brave auxiliaries, who eagerly preſſed to aſſault the camp of the Germans ; and theſe various incidents might produce the ſharp and bloody conflicts which dignify the narrative of Zoſimus, and the Chronicles of Proſper and Marcellinus. A ſeaſonable ſupply ot men and proviſions had been introduced into the walls of Florence ; and the famiſhed hoſt of Radagaiſus was in its turn beſieged. The proud monarch of ſo many warlike nations, after the loſs of his braveſt warriors, was reduced to confide either in the faith of a capitulation, or in the clemency of Stilicho. But the death of the royal captive, who was ignominiouſly beheaded, diſgraced the triumph of Rome and of Chriſtianity ; and</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>