<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ly underſtaiid it to be, would be to reduce it to a heap of unintelligible jargon and inconliſtency. If one man have a right to be free, another man cannot have a right to make him a ſlave ; if one man have a right to inflict chaſtifement upon me, I cannot have a right to withdraw myſelf ſrom chaſtifement ; if my neighbour have a right to a ſum of money in my poſſeſſion, I cannot</p><p>. have a right to retain it in my pocket. It cannot be leſs incontrovertible, that I have no right to omit what my duty preſcribes. From hence it inevitably follows that men have no rights.</p><p>“ It is commonly ſaid, ‘ that a man has a right to the diſpoſal of his fortune, a right to the employment of his time, a right to the uncontrolled choice of his profeſſion or purfuits.<hi rend="sup">,</hi> But this can never be confidently affirmed till it can be ſhown that he has no duties, preſcribing and limiting his mode of proceeding in all theſe reſpects.</p><p>“ In reality, nothing can appear more wonderful to a careful inquirer, than that two ideas ſo incompatible as <hi rend="italic">man</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">rights</hi>  ſliould ever have been aſſociated toge-gether. Certain it is, that one of them muſt be utterly excluſive and annihilatory of the other. Before we aſcribe rights to man, we muſt conceive of him as a being endowed with intellect, and capable of diſcerning the differences and tendencies of things. But a being endowed with intellect, and capable of diſcerning the differences and tendencies of things, inſtantly becomes a moral being, and has duties incumbent on him to diſcharge : and duties and rights, as has already been ſhown, are abſolutely excluſive of each other.</p><p>“ It has been affirmed by the zealous advocates of liberty, ‘ that princes and magiſtrates have no rights ;’ and no poſition can be more incontrovertible. There is no ſituation of their lives that has not its correspondent duties. There is no power intruded to them that they are not bound to exerciſe excluſively for the public good. It is ſtrange, that perſons adopting this principle did not go a ſtep farther, and perceive that the ſame reſtrictions were applicable to ſubjects and citizens.”</p><p>This reaſoning is unanſwerable ; but it militates not againft the <hi rend="italic">rights of man</hi>  in the uſual acceptation of the words, which are never employed to denote diſcretionary power, but a juſt claim on the one hand, implying a correſponding obligation on the other. Whether the phraſe be abſolutely proper is not worth the debating : it is authoriſed by cuſtom—the <hi rend="italic">jus et norma loquendi— </hi>and is univerſally underſtood except by ſuch as the dæ-mons of faction, in the form of paradoxical writers on political juſtice, have been able to miſlead by ſophiſtical reaſonings.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Rights,</hi>  in the common acceptation of the word, are of various kinds : they are <hi rend="italic">natural</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">adventitious, alienable</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">unalienable, perfect</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">imperſect, particular</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">general.</hi>  See the article LibeRty.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Natural</hi>  rights are thoſe which a man has to his life, limbs, and liberty ; to the produce of his perſonal labour; to the uſe, in common with others, of air, light, and water, &amp;c. That every man has a natural right or juſt claim to theſe things, is evident ſrom their being abſolutely neceſſary to enable him to anſwer that purpoſe, whatever it may be, for which he was made a living and a rational being. This ſhows undeniably, that the Author of his nature deſigned that he ſhould have the uſe of them, and that the man who ſhould wantonly deprive him of any one of them, would be guilty of a breach of the divine law, as well as act inconſiſtently with the fitneſs of things in evere ſenſe in which that phraſe can poſſibly be underſtood.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Adventitious</hi>  rights are thoſe which a king has over his ſubjects, a general over his ſoldicrs, a huſhand to the perſon and affections of his wife, and which every man has to the greater part of his property. That the rights of the king and the general are adventitious, is univerſally admitted. The rights of property have been conſidered elſewhere (ſee Property); and though the human conſtitution ſhows ſufficiently that men and women have a natural right to the uſe of each other, yet it is evident that the <hi rend="italic">excluſive</hi>  right of any one man to any one woman, and <hi rend="italic">vice νerfα,</hi>  muſt be an adventitious right : But the important queſtion is, How are adventitious rights acquired ?</p><p>In anſwer to this queſtion, the moraliſt who deduces the laws of virtue from the will of God, obſerves, that as God appears from his works to be a benevolent Being, who wills the happineſs of all his creatures (ſee Metaphysics, n<hi rend="sup">0</hi>312.), he muſt of courſe will every thing which naturally tjnds to promote that happineſs» But the exiſtence of civil ſociety evidently contributes in a great degree to promote the ſum of human happineſs (ſee Society) ; and therefore whatever is neceſſary for the ſupport of civil ſociety in general, or for the conduct of particular ſocieties already eſtabliſhed, muſt be agreeable to the will of God : But the allegiance of ſubjects to their ſovereign, the obedience of ſoldiers to their leader, the protection of private property, and the fulfilling of contracts, are all abſolutely neceſſary to the ſupport of ſociety: and hence the rights of kings, generals, huſhands, and wives, &amp;c. though adventitious, and immediately derived ſrom human appointment, are not leſs ſacredthan natural rights, ſince tney may all be ultimately traced to the ſame ſource. The ſame concluſion may eaſily be drawn by the philoſopher, who reſts moral obligation on the fitneſs of things or on a moral ſenſe; only it muſt in each of theſe caſes partake of the inſtability of its foundation.</p><p>To the ſacredneſs of the rights of marriage, an author already quoted has lately urged ſome declamatory objections. “ It is abſurd (ſays he) to expect, that the inclinations and wiſhes of two human beings ſhould coincide through any long period of time. To oblige them to act and to live together, is to ſubject them to ſome inevitable portion of thwarting, bickering, and unhappineſs. Ί his cannot be otherwiſe, ſo long as man has failed to reach the ſtandard of abſolute perfection. The ſuppofition that I muſt have a companion for life, is the reſult of a complication of vices. It is the dictate of cowardice, and not of fortitude. It flows from the deine of being loved and eſteemed for ſome-thing that is not deſert.</p><p>“ But the evil of marriage, as it is practiſed in European countries, lies deeper than this. The habit is, for a thoughtleſs and romantic youth of each ſex to come together, to ſee each other for a few times, and under circumſtances full of deluſion, and then to vow to each other eternal attachment. What is the conſequence of this? In almoſt every inſtance they find themſelves deceived. They are reduced to make the bell of an irretrievable miſtake. They are preſented with the ſtrongeſt imaginable temptation to become the dupes</p></body></text></TEI>