<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>contribute to the ſupport of his power, he took every precaution to provide for their ſafety ; ſo that we find but two inſurrections in this reign.—In the fourth year of his reign, Antiochus king of Comagena, holding a private correſpondence with the Parthians. the declared enemies of Rome, was taken priſoner in Cilicia, by Pyrrhus the governor, and font bound to Rome. But Veſpaſian generouſly prevented all ill treatment, by giving him a reſidence at Lacedæmon, and allowing him a revenue ſuitable to his dignity. About the ſame time alſo, the Alani, a barbarous people inhabiting along the river Tanais, abandoned their barren wilds, and invaded the kingdom of Media. From thence paſſing into Armenia, after great ravages, they overthrew Tiridates, the king of that country, with prodigious ſlaughter. Titus was at length ſeitt to chaſtiſe their inſolence : but the barbarians retired at the approach of the Roman army, loaded with plunder ; being compelled to wait a more favourable opportunity of renewing their irruptions. Theſe incurſions, however, were but a tranſient ſtorm, the effects of which were ſoon repaired by the emperor’s moderation and aſſiduity. We are told, that he now formed and eſtabliſhed a thouſand nations, which had ſcarcely before amounted to <hi rend="italic">too.</hi>  No provinces in the</p><p>empire lay out of his view and protection» He had, during his whole reign, a particular regard to Britain ; his generals, Petilius Cerealis, and Julius Frontinus, brought the greateſt part of the iſland into ſubjection ; and Agricola, who ſucceeded ſoon after, completed what they had begun. See England.</p><p>In this manner, having reigned io years, loved by his ſubjects, and deſerving their affection, he was ſurpriſed by an indiſpoſition at Campania, which he at once declared would be fatal, crying out, in the ſpirit of Paganiſm, “ Methinks I am going to be a god.” Removing from thence to the city, and afterwards to a country-ſeat near Reate, he was there taken with a flux, which brought him to the laſt extremity. However, perceiving his end approach, and juſt going to expire, he cried out, that an emperor ought to die ſtanding ; •wherefore, raiſing himſelf upon his feet, he expired in the hands of thoſe that ſuſtained him.</p><p>Titus being joyfully received as emperor, notwithſtanding a flight oppoſition from his brother Domitian, who maintained that he himſelf was appointed, and that Titus had falſified the will, began his reign with every virtue that became an emperor and a man. During the liſe of his ſather there had been many imputations againſt him ; but upon his exaltation to the throne he ſeemed entirely to take leave of his former vices, and became an.example of the greateſt moderation and humanity. He had long loved Berenice, ſiſter to Agrippa king of Judea, a woman of the greateſt beauty and allurements. But knowing that the connection with her was entirely diſagreeable to the people of Rome, he ſent her away, notwithſtanding their mutual paſſion and the many arts ſhe uſed to induce him to change his reſolutions. He next diſcarded all thoſe who had been the former miniſters of his pleaſures, and forbore to coιa<hi rend="sup">ι</hi>tenance the companions of his looſer recreations, though he had formerly taken great pains in the ſelec-tion. This moderation, added to his juſtice and gene-τofity, procured him tne love of all good men, and the appellation of the<hi rend="italic">delight of mankind,</hi>  which all his ac</p><lb/><p>tions ſeemed calculated to enſure. As he came to the throne with all the advantages of his father’s popularity, he was reſolved to uſe every method to increaſe it. He therefore took particular care to puniſh all informers, falſe witneſſes, and promoters of diſſenſion, condemning them to be ſcourged in the moſt public ſtreets, next to be dragged through the theatre, and then to be baniſhed to the uninhabited parts of the empire, and ſold as ſlaves. His courteſy and readineſs to do good have been celebrated even by Chriſtian writers ; his principal rule being, never to ſend any petitioner diſſatisſied away. One night, recollecting that he had done nothing beneficial to mankind the day preceding, he cried out among his friends, “ I have loſt a day.” A ſentence too remarkable not to be univerſally known.</p><p>In this reign, an eruption of mount Vefuvius did conſiderable damage, overwhelming many towns, and ſending its aſhes into countries more than ιoo miles diſtant. Upon this !remorable occaſion, Pliny the naturaliſt loſt his life ; for, being impe'ſted by too eager a curioſity to obſerve the eruption, he was ſuffocated in the flames j∙. There happened alſo about this time a fire at Rome, which continued three days and nights ſucceſſively, which was followed by a plague, in which 10,0 O men were buried in a day. The emperor, how· ever, did all that lay in his power to repair the damage ſuſtained by the public ; and, with reſpect to the city, declared that he would take the whole loſs of it upon himſelf. Theſe diſaſters were in ſome meaſure counterbalanced by the ſucceſſes in Britain, under Agricola. This excellent general having been ſent into that country towards the latter end of Veſpaſian’s reign, ſhowed himſelf equally expert in quelling the refractory, and civilizing thoſe who had formerly ſubmitted to the Roman power. The Ordovices, or inhabitants of North Wales, were the firſt that were ſubdued. He then made a deſcent upon Mona, or the iſland of Angleſea ; which ſurrendered at diſcretion. Having thus rendered himſelf maſter of the whole country, he took every method to reſtore diſcipline to his own army, and to introduce ſome ſhare of politeneſs among thoſe whom he had conquered. He exhorted them, both by advice and example, to build temples, theatres, and ſtately houſes. He cauſed the ſons of their nobility to be inſtructed in the liberal arts ; he had them taught the Latin language, and induced them to imitate the Roman modes of dreſſing and living. Thus, by degrees, this barbarous people began to aſſume the luxurious manners of their conquerors, and in time even outdid them in all the refinements of ſenſual pleaſure. For the ſucceſs in Britain, Titus was ſaluted emperor the j 5th time ; but he did not long ſurvive his honours, being ſeized with a violent fever at a little diſtance from Rome. Perceiving his death to approach, he declared, that during the whole courſe of his liſe he knew but of one action which he repented of ; but that action he did not think proper to expreſs. Shortly after, he died (not without ſuſpicion of treachery from his brother Domitian, who had long wiſhed to govern) in the 41 ſt year of his age, having reigned two years two months and twenty days.</p><p>The love which ail ranks of people bore to Tituà, facilitated the election of his brother Domitian, notwithſtanding the ill opinion many had already conceived of him. Hie ambition was already but too well</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>