<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>cluded the war in a few months, he returned in triumph to Rome.</p><p>Antony, who, during this interval, was revelling in all the ſtudied luxuries procured him by his inſidious miſtreſs, having heard of his brother’s overthrow, and his wife’s being compelled to leave Italy, was reſolved to oppoſe Octavianus without delay. He accordingly ſailed at the head of a conſiderable fleet from Alexandria to Tyre, from thence to Cyprus and Rhodes, and had an interview with Fulvia his wife at Athens. He much blamed her for occaſioning the late diſorders, teſtified the utmoſt contempt for her perſon, and, leaving her upon her death-bed at Sycion, haſtened into Italy to fight Octavianus. They both met at Brunduſium; and it was now thought that the flames of a civil war were going to blaze out once more. The forces of Antony were numerous, but moſtly newly raiſed; however, he was aſſiſted by Sextus Pompeius, who in theſe oppoſitions of intereſts was daily coming into power. Octavianus was at the head of thoſe veterans who had always been irreſiſtible, but who ſeemed no way diſpoſed to fight againſt Antony their former general. A negociation was therefore propoſed; and a reconciliation was effected. All offences and affronts were mutually forgiven; and to cement the union, a marriage was concluded between Antony and</p><p>Octavia, the ſiſter of Octavianus. A new diviſion of the Roman empire was made between them; Octavianus was to have the command of the weſt, Antony of the eaſt, while Lepidus was obliged to content himſelf with the provinces in Africa. As for Sextus Pompeius, he was permitted to retain all the iſlands he had already poſſeſſed, together with Peloponneſus: he was alſo granted the privilege of demanding the conſulſhip in his abſence, and of diſcharging that office by any of his friends. It was likewiſe ſtipulated to leave the ſea open, and pay the people what corn was due out of Sicily. Thus a general peace was concluded, to the great ſatisfaction of the people, who now expected a ceſſation from all their calamities.</p><p>This calm ſeemed to continue for ſome time: Antony led his forces againſt the Parthians, over whom his lieutenant, Ventidius, had gained great advantages. Octavianus drew the greateſt part of his army into Gaul, where there were ſome diſturbances; and Pom-pcy went to ſecure his newly ceded province to his intereſt. It was on this quarter that freſh motives were given for renewing the war. Antony, who was obliged by treaty to quit Peloponneſus, refuſed to evacuate it till Pompey had ſatisfied him for ſuch debts as were due to him from the inhabitants. This Pompey would by no means comply with; but immediately fitted out a new fleet, and renewed his former enterpriſes, by cutting off ſuch corn and proviſions as were conſigned to Italy. Thus the grievances of the poor were again renewed; and the people began to complain, that inſtead of three tyrants they were now oppreſſed by four.</p><p>In this exigence, Octavianus, who had long meditated the beſt means of diminiſhing the number, reſolved to begin by getting rid of Pompey, who kept the ſtate in continual alarms. He was maſter of two fleets; one of which he had cauſed to be built at Ravenna; and another which Menodorus, who revolted from Pompey, brought to his aid. His firſt attempt was to invadeSicily; but being overpowered in his paſſage by</p><p>Pompey, and afterwards ſhattered in a ſtorm, he was obliged to defer his deſigns to the enſuing year. During this interval he was reinforced by a fleet of 120 ſhips, given him by Antony, with which he reſolved once more to invade Sicily on three ſeveral quarters. But fortune ſeemed ſtill determined to oppoſe him. He was a ſecond time diſabled and ſhattered by a ſtorm: which ſo raiſed the vanity of Pompey, that he began to ſtyle himſelf the <hi rend="italic">ſon of Neptune.</hi>  However, Octavianus was not to be intimidated by any diſgraces; for having ſhortly refitted his navy, and recruited his forces, he gave the command ef both to Agrippa, his faithful friend and aſſociate in war. Agrippa proved himſelf worthy of the truſt repoſed in him: he began his operations by a victory over Pompey; and, though he was ſhortly after worſted himſelf, he ſoon after gave his adverſary a complete and final overthrow. Thus undone, Pompey reſolved to fly to Antony, ſrom whom he expected refuge, as he had formerly obliged that triumvir by giving protection to his mother. However, he tried once more, at the head of a ſmall body of men, to make himſelf independent, and even ſurpriſed Antony’s officers who had been ſent to accept of his ſubmiſſions. Nevertheleſs, he was at laſt abandoned by his ſoldiers, and delivered up to Titus, Antony’s lieutenant, who ſhortly after cauſed him to be ſlain.</p><p>The death of this general removed one very powerful obſtacle to the ambition of Octavianus, and he reſolved to take the earlieſt opportunity to get rid of the reſt of his aſſociates. An offence was ſoon furniſhed by Lepidus, that ſerved as a ſufficient pretext for depriving him of his ſhare in the triumvirate. Being now at the head of 22 legions, with a ſtrong body of cavalry, he idly ſuppoſed that his preſent power was more than an equivalent to the popularity of Octavianus. He therefore reſolved upon adding Sicily, where he then was, to his province; pretending a right, as having firſt invaded it. His colleague ſent to expoſtulate upon theſe proceedings; but Lepidus fiercely replied, ‘ that he was determined to have his ſhare in the adminiſtration, and would no longer ſubmit to let one alone poſ-ſeſs all the authority. ’ Octavianus was previouſly informed of the diſpoſition of Lepidus’s ſoldiers; for he had, by his ſecret intrigues and largeſſes, entirely attached them to himſelf. Wherefore, without further delay, he with great boldneſs went alone to the camp ef Lepidus, and with no other aſſiſtance than his private bounties, and the authority he had gained by his former victories, he reſolved to depoſe his rival. The ſoldiers thronged round him with the moſt dutiful alacrity, while Lepidus haſtened to prevent their defection. But Octavianus, though he received a wound from one of the centurions, went with great preſence of mind to the place where the military enſigns were planted, and, flouriſhing one of them in the air, all the legionary ſoldiers ran in crowds and ſaluted him as their general. Lepidus being thus abandoned by his men, diveſted himſelf of all the marks of his authority, which he could no longer keep, and ſuhmiſſively threw himſelf at the feet of Octavianus. This general ſpared his life, notwithſtanding the remonſtrances of his army; but deprived him of all his former authority, and baniſhed him to Circæum.</p><p>Octavianus was received upon his return to Rome with univerſal joy; the ſenators met him at the gates,</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>