<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>cenſors were Papirius and Sempronius, 'both patricians; ajιd from this order they continued to be elected for near ιoo years.</p><p>This new creation ſerved to reſtore peace for ſome time among the orders ; and the triumph gained over the Volſcians by Geganius the conſul, added to the univerſal ſatisfaction that reigned among the people.</p><p>This calm, however, was but of ſhort continuance : for, ſome time after, a famine preſſing hard upon the poor, the uſual complaints againſt the rich were renewed ; and theſe, as before, proving ineffectual, produced new ſeditious. The conſuls were accuſed of neglect in not having laid in proper quantities of corn : they, however, diſregarded the murmurs of the populace, content with exerting all their care in attempts to ſupply the preſſing neceſſities. But though they did all that could be expected ſrom active magiſtrates, in providing and diſtributing proviſions to the poor ; yet Spurius Mælius, a rich knight, who had bought up all the corn of Tuſcany, by ſar outſhone them in liberality. This demagogue, inflamed with a ſecret deſire of becoming powerful by the contentions in the ſtate, diſtributed corn in great quantities among the poorer fort each day, till his houſe became the aſylum of all ſuch as wiſhed to exchange a liſe of labour for one of lazy dependence. When he had thus gained a ſufficient number of partizans, he procured large quantities of arms to be brought into his houſe by night, and formed a conſpiracy,, by which he was to obtain, the command, while ſome of the tribunes, whom he had found means to corrupt, were to act under him, in ſeizing upon the liberties of his country. Minucius ſoon diſcovered the plot ; and informing the ſenate thereoſ, they immediately formed the reſolution of creating a dictator, who ſhould have the power of quelling the conspiracy, without appealing to the people. Cincin-nat-us, who was now 8o years old, was choſen once more to reſcue his country from impending danger. He began by ſummoning Mælius to appear ; who refiiſed to obey. He next ſent Ahala, the maſter of his horſe, to force him ; who, meeting him in the forum, and preſſing Mælius to follow him to the dictator’s tribunal, upon his refuſal Ahala killed him upon the ſpot. The dictator applauded the reſolution of his officer, and commanded the. conſpiraror’s goods to be fold, and his houſe tobe demoliſhed, diſtributing his ſtores among the people.</p><p>The tribunes of the people were much enraged at the death of Mælius ; and, in order to puniſh the ſenate, at the next election, inſtead of conſuls, inſiſted upon reſtoring their military tribunes. With this the ſenate were obliged to comply. The next year, however, the government returned to its ancient channel, and conſuls were choſen.</p><p>The Veientes had long been the rivals of Rome ; they had ever taken the opportunity of its internal diſtreſſes to ravage its territories, and had even threatened its ambaſſadors, ſent to complain of theſe injuries, with outrage. In war they had been extremely formidable, and had cut off almoſt all the Fabian family ; who, to the number of 306 perſons, had voluntarily undertaken to defend the frontiers againſt their in-•curſions. It ſeemed now therefore determined, that the city of Veii, whatever it ſhould coſt, was to fall; and the Romans accordingly ſat regularly down before it, prepared for a long and painful reſiſtance. The ſtrength of the place, or the unikilſulneſs of the befie-gers, may be inferred from the continuance of the ſiege, which laſted for 10.years; during which time the army continued encamped round it, lying in winter under tents made of the ſkins of beaſts, and in ſummer driving oi) the operations of the attack. Varions was the ſucceſs, and many were the commanders that directed the ſiege : ſiunetimes all the beſiegers works were ſe·-ſtroyed, and many of their men cut off by ſallies fron» the town ; ſometimes they were annoyed by an army of Veians, who attempted to bring aſſiſtance fron» without. A liege ſo bloody ſeemed to threaten depopulation to Rome itſelf, by draining its forces continually away ; ſo that a law w?s obliged to be mad« for all the bachelors to marry the widows of the ſoldiers who were (lain. In order to carry it on with greater vigour, Furius Camillus was created dictator, and to him was intruſted the ſole power of managing the long protracted war. Camillus, who, without intrigue or any ſolicitation, had raiſed himſelf to the firfl eminence in the ſtate, had been made one of the cen-fors ſome time before, and was conſidered as the head of that office ; he was afterwards made a military tribune, and had in this poſt gained ſeveral advantage% over the enemy. It was his great courage and abilities in the above offices that made him thought moſt worthy to ſerve his country on this preſſing occaſion.. Upon his appointment, numbers of the people flocked to his ſtandard, confident of ſucceſs under ſo experienced a commander. Conſcious, however, that he was unable to take the city by ſtorm, he ſecretly wrought a mine into it with vaſt labour, which opened into the midſt of the citadel. Certain thus of ſucceſs, and finding the city incapable of relief, he ſent to the ſenate, deſiring that all who choſe to ſhare in the plunder of Veii ſhould immediately repair to the army. Then giving his men directions how to enter at the breach, the city was inſtantly filled with his legions,, to the amazement and conſternation of the beſieged, who, but a moment before, had reſted in perfect ſecurity. Thus, like a ſecond Troy, was the city of Veii 1 taken, after a 10 years liege, and with its ſpoils enriched the conquerors ; while Camillus himſelf, tranſported with the honour of having ſubdued the rival of his native city, triumphed after the manner of the kings of Rome, having his chariot drawn by four milk-white horſes ; a diſtinction which did not fail to diſguſt the majority of the ſpectators, as they conſidered thoſe as ſacred, and more proper for doing honour to their gods than their generals.</p><p>His uſual good fortune attended Camillus in another expedition againſt the Faliſei ; he routed their army, and beſieged their capital city Falerii, which threatened a long and vigorous reſiſtance. Here a ſchoolmaſter, who had the care of the chilſhen belonging to the principal men of the city, having found means to decoy them into the Roman camp, offered to put them, into the hands of Camillus, as the ſureſt means of inducing the citizens to a ſpeedy ſurrender. The general was ſtruck with the treachery of a wretch whoſe duty it was to protect innocence, and not to betray it ; and immediately ordered him to be ſtripped, his hands tied behind him, and in that ignominious manner to be whipped into the town by Iris own ſeboſers.</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>