<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>eqnſeript fathers aſſembled at Theſſalonſea decreed, that they alone repreſented the Roman ſenate, and that thoſe who reſided at Rome were encouragers of tyranny, and friends to the tyrant. And indeed, as the flower of the nobility was with Pompey, and the moſt virtuous men in the republic had taken refuge in his camp, he was generally looked upon as the only hope and ſupport of the public liberty. Hence many perſons- of eminent probity, who had hitherto ſtood neuter, flocked to him from all parts. Anlong theſe were young Brutus, who afterwards conſpired againſt Cæſar, Tidius Sextius, and Labienus. Brutus, whoſe father had been put to death in Galatia by Pompey’s order, had never ſpoken to him, or ſo much as ſaluted him ſince that time : but as he now looked upon him as the defender of the public liberty, he joined him, ſacriſicing therein his private reſentment to the intereſt of the public. Pompey received him with great joy, and was willing to confer upon him ſome command ; but he declined the offer. Tidius Sextius, though extremely old and lame, yet left Rome, and went as far as Macedonia to join Pompey there. Labienus likewiſe forſook his old benefactor, under whom he had ſerved during the whole courſe of the Gauliſh war, and went over to his rival, though Cæſar had appointed him commander in chief of all the forces on the other ſide the Alps. Tn ſhort, Pompey’s partv grew into ſuch reputation, that his cauſe was generally called the <hi rend="italic">good envle,</hi>  while Cæſar’s adherents were looked upon as enemies to their country, and abettors of tyranny.</p><p>As ſoon as Cæſar landed, he marched directly .to Oricurn, the neareſt city in Epirus, which was taken without oppoſition, The like ſucceſs attended him at Apollonia, which was in no condition to ſtanda ſiege ; and theſe two conqueſts opened a way to Dyrrhachium, where Pompey had his magazines of arms and proviſions. This ſucceſs, however, was interrupted by the news that the fleet which he had ſent back to Brunduſium to tranſport the reſt of his troops had been attacked by Bibulus, one of Pompey’s admirals, who had taken 30, and inhumanly burnt them with the ſeamen on board. This gave Cæſar great uneaſineſs, eſpecially as he heard that Bibulus, with 1 10 ſhips of war, had taken poſſeſſion of all the harbours between Salonium and Oricurn ; ſo that the legions at Brunduſium could not venture to croſs the ſea without great danger of falling into the enemy’s hands. By this Cæſar was ſo much embarraſſed, that he made propoſals of accommodation upon very moderate terms ; being no other than that both Pompey and he ſhould diſhand their armies within three days, renew their former friendſhip with ſolemn oaths, and return together to Italy. Theſe propoſals were ſent by Vibullius Rufus, an intimate ſriend of Pompey, whom Cæſar had twice taken priſoner. Pompey, however, probably elated with his late good fortune, anſwered that he would not hearken to any terms, leſt it ſhould be ſaid that he owed his liſe and return to Italy to Cæſar’s ſavour. However, the latter again ſent one Vatinius to confer with Pompey about a treaty of peace. Labienus was appointed to receive the propoſals ; but while they were conferring together, a party of Pompey’s men coming up to them, diſeharged their darts at Vatinius and thoſe who attended him. Some of the guards were wounded, and Vatinius narrowly eſeaped with his life«·</p><lb/><p>In the jnean time Cæſar advanced towards Dyrrhachium, in hopes of ſurpriſing that important place ; but Pompey unexpectedly appearing, he halted on the other ſide of the river Aρ.us, where he intrenched himſelf, as having but a ſmall number of troops in com· pariſon of the formidable army which attended Pompey. The Utter, however, notwithſtanding his ſuperiority, durſt not croſs the river in Cæſar s light; ſo that the two armies continued for ſome time quiet in their reſpective camps. Cæſar wrote letter after letter to· Marc Antony, who commanded the legions he had left in Italy, to come to his aſſiſtance; but receiving no anſwer, Cæſar diſguiſed himſelf in the habit of a ſlave, and with all imaginable ſecrecy went on board a ſiſher-man’s bark, with a deſign to go over to Brunduſium, though the enemy’s fleet was cruiſing on the coaſts both of Greece and Italy. This deſign, however, miſcarried, by reaſon of the boat being put back by contrary winds; and thus Cæſar was reſtored to his ſoldiers, who had been very uneaſy at his abſence. He was no ſooner landed than he diſpatched Poſthumius, one of his lieutenants, with moſt preſſing orders to Marc Antony, Gabinius, and Calenus, to bring the troops to him at all adventures. Gabinius, unwilling to expoſe all the hopes of his general to the hazards of the ſea, thought it ſafer to march a great way about by Illyricum, and therefore engaged all the legionaries he could to follow him by land. But the Illyrians, who had, unknown to him, declared for Pompey, fell unexpectedly upon him and killed him and his men, not one eſcaping. Marc Antony and Calenus, who went by ſea, were in the greateſt danger from one of Pompey's∙ admirals ; but had the good luck to bring their troops ſafe to ſhore at Nyphæum, in the neighbourhood of Apollonia. As loon as it was known that Antony was landed, Po n-pey marched to prevent his joining Cæſar. On the other hand, Cæſar inſtantly de&lt;,kimped, and haſtening to the relief of his lieutenant, joined him before Pompey came up. Then Pompey,, not caring to engage them when united, retired to an advantageous poſt in the neighbourhood of Dyrrhachium, known by the name of <hi rend="italic">Aſparagium</hi>, and there encamped. Cæſar having thus at length got all his troops together, reſolved to finiſh the war by one general action, and determine the fate of the world, either by his own death or by that of his rival. To this end he offered Pompey battle, and kept his army a great while drawn up in light of the enemy. But Pompey declining an engagement, he decamped, and turned towards Dyrrhachium, as if he deſigned to ſur</p><p>priſe it, hoping by this means to draw Pompey into the plain. But Pompey, looking upon the taking of Dyrrhachium as a chimerical project, followed Cæſar at ſome diſtance, and letting him draw near to the city, encamped on a hill called <hi rend="italic">Petra,</hi>  which commanded the ſea, whence he could be ſupplied with proviſions ſrom Greece and Aſia, while Cæſar was forced to bring corn by land from Epirus, at a vaſt expence, and· through many dangers.</p><p>This inconvenience put Cæſar upon a new deſign, which was to ſurround an army far more numerous than his own, and, by {hutting them up within a narrow tract of ground, diſtreſs them as much ſor want of forage as his troops were diſtreſſed for want of corn. Pu-ſuant to this deſign, be drew a line of circιιmvalla-tion from the ſea quite round Pompey’s camp, and kept</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>