<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>my into three parts ; whereof one continued with Appius in the city, to keep it in awe ; the other two were commanded by his colleagues, and were led, one againſt the Æqui, and the other againſt the Sabines. The Roman ſoldiers had now got into a method of pu-niffιing the generals whom they diſliked, by ſuffering themſelves to be vanquiſhed in the field. They put it in practice upon this occaſion, and ſhamefully abandoned their camp upon the approach of the enemy. Never was the news of a victory more joyfully received at Rome than the tidings of this defeat : the generals, as is always the caſe, were blamed for the treachery of their men : ſome demanded that they ſhould be depoſed ; others cried out for a dictator to lead the trrops to conqueſt : but among the reſt, old Sicinius Dentatus the tribune ſpoke his ſentiments with his uſual openneſs ; and treating the generals with contempt, ſhowed all the faults of their diſcipline in the camp, and of their conduct in the field. Appius, in the mean time, was not remiſs in obſerving the diſpoſition of the people. Dentatus, in particular, was marked out for vengeance, and, under pretence of doing him particular honour, he was appointed legate, and put at the head of the ſupplies which were ſent from Rome to reinforce the army. The office of legate was held ſacred among the Romans, as in it were united the authority of a general, with the reverence due to the prieſthood. Dentatus, no way ſuſpecting his deſign, went to the camp with alacrity, where ſhe was received with all the external marks of reſpect. But the generals ſoon found means of indulging their deſire of revenge. He was appointed at the head of ιoo men to go and examine a more commodious place for encampment, as he had very candidly aſſiired the commanders that their preſent ſituation was wrong. The ſoldiers, however, who were given as his attendants, were aſſaſſins ; wretches who had long been miniſters of the vengeance of the decemviri, and who now engaged to murder him, though with all thoſe apprehenſions which his reputation, as he was called the <hi rend="italic">Roman A-Mies,</hi>  might be ſuppoſed to inſpire. With theſe deſigns, they led him from the way into the hollow boſom of a retired mountain, where they began to ſet upon him from behind. Dentatus, now too late, perceived the treachery of the decemviri, and was reſolved to ſell his liſe as dearly as he could ; he therefore put his back to a rock, and defended himſelf againſt thoſe who preſſed moſt cloſely. Though now grown old, he had ſtill the remains of his former valour, and killed no leſs than 15 of the aſſailants, and wounded 30. The aiſaffins now therefore, terriſted at his amazing bravery, ihower-ed in their javelins upon him at a diſtance ; all which he received in his ſhield with undaunted reſolution. 7 he combat, though ſo unequal in numbers, was managed for ſome time with doubtful ſucceſs, till at length his aſtailants bethought themſelves of aſcending the rock againſt which he ſtood, and thus poured down ſtones upon him from above. This ſucceeded ; the old ſoldier fell beneath their united efforts, after having ſhown by his death that he owed ſt to his fortitude, and not his fortune, that he had come off ſo many times victorious. The decemviri pretended to join in the general ſorrow for ſo brave a man, and decreed him a funeral, with the firſt military honours : but the greatneſs of their apparent diſtreſs, compared with their</p><lb/><p>known hatred, only rendered them ſtill more deteſtabltf to the people.</p><p>But a tranſaction ſtill more atrocious than the former ſerved to inſpire the citizens with a reſolution to break all meaſures of obedience, and at laſt to reſtore freedom. Appius, who ſtill remained at Rome, ſitting one day on his tribunal to diſpenſe juſtice, ſaw a maiden of exquiſtte beauty, and aged about 15, paſſing to one of the public ſchools, attended by a matron her nurſe. Conceiving a violent paſſion for her, he reſolved to obtain the gratification of his deſire, whatever ſhould be the conſequence, and found means to inform himſelf of her name and family. Her name was <hi rend="italic">Pirginia,</hi>  the daughter of Virginius a centurion, then with the army in the field ; and ſhe had been contracted to Icilius, formerly a tribune of the people, who had agreed to marry her at the end of the preſent campaign. Appius, at firſt, reſolved to break this match, and to eſpouſe her himſelf : but the laws of the Twelve Tables had forbidden the patricians to intermarry with the plebeians ; and he could not infringe theſe, as he was the enacter of them. Nothing therefore remained but a criminal enjoyment ; which, as he was long uſed to the indulgence of his paſſions, he reſolved to obtain. After having vainly tried to corrupt the fidelity of her nurſe, he had recourſe to another expedient, ſtill more guilty. He pitched upon one Claudius, who had long been the miniſter of his pleaſures, to aſſert the beautiful maid was his Have, and to refer thé cauſe to his tribunal for deciſion. Claudius behaved exactly according to his inſtructions ; for entering into the ſchool, where Virginia was playing among her female companions, he ſeized upon her as his property, and was going to drag her away by force, but was prevented by the people drawn together by her cries. At length, after the firſt heat of oppoſition was over, he led the weeping virgin to the tribunal of Appius, and there plauſibly expoſed his pretenſions. He aſſerted, that ſhe was born in his houſe, of a female Have, who ſold her to the wife of Virginius, who had been barren. That he had feve-ral credible evidences to prove the truth of what he ſaid ; but that, until they could come together, it was but reaſonable the Have ſhould be delivered into his cuſtody, being her proper maſter. Appius ſeemed to be ſtruck with the juſtice of his claims. He obſerved, that if the reputed father himſelf were preſent, he might indeed be willing to delay the delivery of the maiden for ſome time ; but that it was not lawful for him, in the preſent <hi rend="sup">-</hi>caſe, to detain her from her maſter. He therefore adjudged her to Claudius, as his flave, to be kept by him till Virginius ſhould be able to prove his paternity. This ſentence was received with loud clamours and reproaches by the multitude : the women, in particular, came round Virginia, as if willing to protect her from the judge’s fury ; while Icilius, her lover, boldly oppoſed the decree, and obliged Claudius to take refuge under the tribunal of the decemvir. All things now threatened an open infαrrection ; when Appius, fearing the event, thought proper to ſuſpend his judgment till the arrival of Virginius, who was then about 11 miles from Rome, with the army. The day following was fixed ſor the trial ; and, in the mean time, Appius ſent letters to the generals to coniine Virginius, as his arrival in town might only ſerve to</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>