<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>rteers were headed by one PercenιuuS, a common ſoldier ; who, before he ſerved in the army, had made it his whole buſineſs to form parties in the theatres and play houſes to hiſs or applaud ſuch actors as he liked or diſliked. Inflamed by the ſpeeches of this man, they openly revolted ; and though Tiberius himſelf wrote to them, and lent his ſon Druſus to endeavour to quell the tumult, they maſſacred ſome of their officers, and inſulted others, till at laſt, being frightened by an eclipſe of the moon, they began to ſhow ſome ſigns of repentance. Of this favourable diſpofιtion Druſus took advantage ; and even got the ringleaders of the revolt condemned and executed. Immediately after this they were again terrified by ſuch violent ſtorms and dreadful rains, that they quietly ſubmitted, and every thing in that quarter was reſtored to tranquillity.</p><p>The revolt of the German legions threatened much more danger, as they were more numerous than thoſe of Pannonia. They proceeded nearly in the ſame way as the Pannonian legions, falling upon their officers, eſpecially the centurions, and beating them till they almoſt expired, drove them out of the camp, and ſome of them were even thrown into the Rhine. Germanicus, who was at that time in Gaul, haſtened to the camp on the firſt news of the diſturbance ; but being unable to prevail on them to return to their duty, he was obliged to feign letters from Tiberius, granting all their demands. Theſe werc, That all thoſe who had ſerved 20 years ſhould be diſeharged 5 that ſuch as had ſerved 16 ſhould be deemed veterans; and that ſome legacies which had been left them by Auguſtus ſhoiild not only be paid immediately, but doubled. This laſt article he was obliged to diſcharge without delay out of the money which he and hi3 friends had brought to defray the expences of their journey ; and on receiving it, the troops quietly retired to their winter-quarters. But, in the mean time, ſome deputies ſent either by Tiberius or the ſenate, probably to quell the ſedition, occaſioned freſh diſturbances ; for the legionaries, taking it into their heads that theſe deputies were come to revoke the conceſſions which Germanicus had made, were with difficulty prevented from tearing them in pieces ; and, notwithſtanding the utmoſt endeavours of Germanicus, behaved in ſuch an outrageous manner, that the general thought proper to ſend off his wiſe A-grippina, with her infant ſon Claudius, ſhe herſelf at the ſame being big with child. As ihe was attended by many women of diſtinction, wives of the chief officers in the camp, their tears and lamentations in parting with their huſhands occaſioned a great uproar, and drew together the ſoldiers from all quarters. A new ſcene enſued, which made an impreſſion even upon the moſt obſtinate. They could not behold, without ſhame and compaſſion, ſo many women of rank travelling thus forlorn, without a centurion to attend them, or a ſoldier to guard them ; and their general’s wiſe among the teſt, carrying her infant child in her arms, and preparing to fly ſor ſhelter againſt the treachery of the Roman legions. This made ſuch a deep impreſſion on the minds of many of them, that ſome ran to ſtop her, while the reſt recurred to Germanicus, earneſtly in-treating him to recall his wiſe, and to prevent her from being obliged to ſeek a ſanctuary among foreigners. The general improved this favourable diſpoſition, and in a ſhort time they of their own accord ſeized and maſſacred the ringleaders of the revolt. Still, however, two of the legions continued in their difobedi-ence. Againſt them therefore Germanicus determined to lead thoſe who had returned to their duty. With this view he prepared veſſels ; but before he embarked his troops, he wrote a letter to Cagcina who commanded them, acquainting him that he approached with a powerful army, reſolved to put them all to the ſword without diſtinction, if they did not prevent him by taking vengeance on the guilty themſelves. This letter Caecina communicated only to the chief officers and ſuch of the ſoldiets as had all along diſapproved of the revolt, exhorting them at the fame time to enter into an aſſociation againſt the ſeditious, and put to the ſword ſuch as had involved them in the preſent ignominy and guilt. This propoſal was approved of, and a cruel maſſacre immediately took place ; inſomuch that when Germanicus came to the camp, he found the greateſt part of the legions deſtroyed. This greatly affected the humane Germanicus, who cauſed the bodies of the ſlain to be burnt, and celebrated their obſequies with the uſual ſolemnities ; however, the ſedition was thus effectually quelled, after which he led his army into Germany. There he performed many great exploits f ; hut ſtill all that he could perform was far from freeing the empire from ſo dangerous and trouble-ſome an enemy. In the year 19, he died, of poiſon, as was ſuppoſed, given by Piſo, his partner in the government of Syria, to which Germanicus had been promoted after his return from the north.</p><p>In the mean time, Tiberius, though he affected to court the favour of the people by various methods, yet ſhowed himſelf in general ſuch a cruel and blood-thirſty tyrant, that he became the object of univerſal abhorrence. Though he had hated Germanicus in his heart, he puniſhed Piſo with death ; but in about a year after the death of Germanicus, having now no object of jealouſy to keep him in awe, he" began to pull off the'maſli, and appear more in his natural character than before. He took upon himſelf the interpretation of all political meaſures, and began daily to diminiſh the authority of the ſenate ; which deſign was much facilitated, by their own aptitude to ſlavery ; ſo that he deſpiſed their meanneſs, while he enjoyed its effects. A law at that time ſubliſted, which made it treaſon to form any injurious attempt againſt the ,majefty of the people. Tiberius aſſumed to himſelf the interpretation and enforcement of this law ; and extended it not only to the caſes which really affected the ſafety of the ſtate, but to every conjuncture that could poſſibly be favourable to his hatred or ſuſpicions. All freedom was now therefore baniſhed from convivial meetings, and diffidence reigned amongſt the deareſt relations. The law of offended majeſty being revived, many perſons of diſtinction fell a ſacriſice to it.</p><p>In the beginning of theſe cruelties, Tiberius took into his confidence Sejanus, a Roman knight, but by birth a Volſcian, who found out the method of gaining his confidence, by the moſt refined degree of diſſimulation, being an over-match for his maſter in his own arts. He was made by tſhe emperor captain of the Prætotian guards, one of the moſt confidential truſts in the ſtate, and extolled in the ſenate as a worthy aſſociate in his labours. The ſervile ſenators, with</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>