<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>and vigour, before the ſuccours which he apprehended were coming from Europe, obliged him to raiſe the ſiege. Achmed inſtantly obeyed, railed a battery of 17 large cannon againſt the baſtion of Italy, and quickly after made himſelf maſter of it, obliging the garriſon to retire farther into the city. Here the grand-maſter was forced to demoliſh two of the churches, to prevent the enemy’s ſeizing on them; and, with their materials, cauſed ſome new works and entrenchments to be made to hinder their proceeding farther.</p><p>The Turks, however, gained ground every day, though they ſtill loſt vaſt numbers of their men: at length the 30th of November came, when the grand-maſter, and both the beſiegers and beſieged, thought the laſt aſſault was to be given. The baſhaw Pyrrus, who commanded it, led his men directly to the entrenchments; upon which the bells of all the churches ſounded the alarm. The grand-maſter, and his few knights, troops, and citizens, ran in crowds, and in a confuſed diſorderly manner, to the entrenchments, each fighting in his own way, or rather as his fear directed him. This attack would have proved one of the moſt deſperate that had yet been felt, had not a moſt vehement rain intervened, which carried away all the earth which the enemy had reared to ſerve them as a rampart againſt the artillery of the baſtion of Auvergne; ſo that being now quite expoſed to their continual fire, they fell in ſuch great numbers, that the baſhaw could no longer make them ſtand their ground, but all precipitately fled towards their camp. This laſt repulfe threw the proud ſultan into ſuch a fury, that none of his officers dared to come near him; and the ſhame of his having now ſpent near ſix whole months with ſuch a numerous army before the place, and having loſt ſuch myriads of his brave troops with ſo little advantage, had made him quite deſperate, and they all dreaded the conſequences of his reſentment.</p><p>Pyrrus at length, having given it time to cool, ventured to approach him, and propoſe a new project to him, which, if approved, could hardly fail of ſucceſs; which was, to offer the town a generous capitulation; and he obſerved, that in caſe the ſtubborn knights ſhould reject it, yet being now reduced to ſo ſmall a number, as well as their forces and fortifications almoſt deſtroyed, the citizens, who were moſt of them Greeks, and leſs ambitious of glory than ſolicitous for their own preſer-vation, would undoubtedly accept of any compoſition that ſhould ſecure to them their lives and effects.</p><p>This propoſal being reliſhed by the ſultan, letters were immediately diſperſed about the city in his name, exhorting them to ſubmit to his government, and threatening them at the fame time with the moſt dreadful effects of his reſentment if they perſiſted in their obſtinacy. Pyrrus likewiſe diſpatched a Genoeſe to approach as near as he could to the baſtion of Auvergne, and to intreat the knights to take pity of ſo many of their Chriſtian brethren, and not expoſe them to the dreadful effects which muſt follow their refuſal of a capitulation, ſo generouſly offered them at their laſt extremity. Other agents were likewiſe employed in other places: to all of whom the grand-maſter ordered ſome of his men to return this anſwer, That his order never treated with infidels but with ſword in hand. An Albanian was ſent next with a letter from the ſultan to him, who met with the fame repulſe;</p><p>after which, he ordered his men to fire upon any that ſhould preſent themſelves upon the ſame pretence; which was actually done. But this did not prevent the Rhodians from liſtening to the terms offered by the Turks, and holding frequent cabals upon that ſub-ject; in which the general maſſacre of a town taken by aſſault, the dreadful ſlavery of thoſe that eſcaped, the rape of their wives and daughters, the deſtruction of their churches, the profanation of their holy relics and ſacred utenſils, and other dire conſequences of an obſtinate refuſal, being duly weighed againſt the ſul-tan’s offers, quickly determined them which party to take. The grand-maſter, however, proving inexorable to all their intreaties, they applied to their Greek metropolitan, who readily went and repreſented all theſe things to him in the moſt pathetic terms: Yet he met with no better reception; but was told, that he and his knights were determined to be buried under the ruins of the city if their ſwords could no longer defend it, and he hoped their example would not permit them to ſhow leſs courage on that occaſion. This anſwer produced a quite contrary effect; and, as the citizens thought delays dangerous at ſuch a juncture, they came in a body to him by the very next morning, and plainly told him, that if he paid no greater regard to their preſervation, they would not fail of taking the moſt proper meaſures to preſerve the lives and chaſtity of their wives and children.</p><p>This reſolution could not but greatly alarm the grand-maſter; who thereupon called a council of all the knights, and informed them himſelf of the condition of the place. Theſe all agreed, particularly the engineer Martinengo, that it was no longer defenſible, and no other reſource left but to accept the ſultan’s offers; adding, at the ſame time, that though they were all ready, according to the obligations of their order, to fight to the laſt drop of their blood, yet it was no leſs their duty to provide for the ſafety of the inhabitants, who, not being bound by the ſame obligations, ought not to be made a ſacrifice to their glory. It was therefore agreed, with the grand-maſter’s conſent, to accept of the next offers the ſultan ſhould make. He did not let them wait long: for the fear he was in of a freſh ſuccour from Europe, the intrepidity of the knights, and the ſhame of being forced to raiſe the ſiege, prevailed upon him to hang out his pacific flag, which was quickly anſwered by another on the Rhodian ſide; upon which the Turks, coming out of their trenches, delivered up the ſultan’s letter for the grand-maſter, to the grand-prior of St Giles, and the engineer Martinengo. The terms offered in it by Soly-man appeared ſo advantageous, that they immediately exchanged hoſtages; and the knights that were ſent to him had the honour to be introduced to him, and to hear them confirmed by his own mouth, though not without threats of putting all to fire and ſword in caſe of refuſal, or even delay. Two ambaſſadors were forthwith ſent to him, to demand a truce of three days to ſettle the capitulation and intereſts of the inhabitants, who were part Greeks and part Latins; but this was abfolutely refuſed by the impatient monarch, out of a ſuſpicion of the rumoured ſuccour being near, and that the truce was only to gain time till it was come.</p><p>He therefore ordered the hoſtilities to be renewed</p></body></text></TEI>