<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>almoſt entirely occupied by the Saracens; Andronicus the eaſtern emperor poſſeſſing little more in it than a caſtle. Neverthleſs he refuſed to grant the inveſtiture of the iſland to Villaret. The latter, without ſpending time in fruitleſs negociations, ſailed directly for Rhodes, where he landed his troops, proviſions, and warlike ſtores, in ſpite of the oppoſition made by the Saracens, who then united againſt the common enemy. As Villaret foreſaw that the capital muſt be taken before he could reduce the iſland, he inſtantly laid ſiege to it. The inhabitants defended themſelves obſtinately, upon which the grand-maſter thought proper to turn the ſiege into a blockade; but he ſoon found himſelf ſo cloſely ſurrounded by the Greeks and Saracens, that he could get no ſupply either of forage or proviſions for his army. But having at length obtained a ſupply of proviſions by means of large ſums borrowed of the Florentines, he came out of his trenches and attacked the Saracens, with a full reſolution either to conquer or die. A bloody fight enſued, in which a great number of the braveſt knights were killed: but at length the Saracens gave way, and fled to their ſhips; upon which the city was immediately aſſaulted and taken. The</p><p>Greeks and other Chriſtians had their lives and liberties given them, but the Saracens were all cut to pieces. The reduction of the capital was followed by that of all the other places of inferior ſtrength throughout the iſland; and in four years after their landing, the whole was ſubjugated, and the conquerors took the title of the <hi rend="italic">Knights of Rhodes.</hi>  For many years thoſe knights continued the terror of the Saracens and Turks, and ſuſtained a ſevere ſiege from Mohammed II. who was compelled to abandon the enterpriſe; but at length the Turkiſh ſultan Solyman reſolved at all events to drive them from it. Before he undertook the expedition, he ſent a meſſage commanding them to depart the iſland without delay; in which caſe he promiſed that neither they nor the inhabitants ſhould ſuffer any injury, but threatened them with his utmoſt vengeance if they refuſed his offer. The knights, however, proving ob-ſtinate, Solyman attacked the city with a fleet of 400 ſail and an army of 140, 000 men.</p><p>The trenches were ſoon brought cloſe to the coun-terſcarp, and a ſtrong battery raiſed againſt the town; which, however, did but little damage, till the ſultan being informed by a ſpy of this particular, and that he was in danger of receiving ſome fatal ſhot from the tower of St John which overlooked his camp, he planted a battery againſt that tower, and quickly brought it down. Solyman, however, finding the whole place in ſome meaſure covered with ſtrong fortifications of ſuch height as to command all his batteries, ordered an immenſe quantity of ſtones and earth to be brought; in which ſo great a number of hands were employed night and day by turns, that they quickly raiſed a couple of hillocks high enough to overtop the city-walls. They plied them accordingly with ſuch a continual fire, that the grand-maſter was obliged to cauſe them to be ſtrongly propped within with earth and timber. All this while the beſieged, who, from the top of the grand-maſter’s palace, could diſcover how their batteries were planted, de-moliſhed them with their cannon almoſt as faſt as they raiſed them.</p><p>Here the enemy thought proper to alter their measures, and to plant a ſtrong battery againſt the tower of</p><p>St Nicholas, which, in the former ſiege by Mohammed, had reſiſted all the efforts of the then grand-vizier. This the baſhaw of Romania cauſed to be battered with 12 large pieces of braſs cannon, but had the mortification to ſee them all diſmounted by thoſe of the tower; to prevent which in future, he ordered them to be fired only in the night, and in the day had them covered with gabions and earth. This had ſuch ſucceſs, that, alter 500 cannon-ſhot, the wall began to ſhake and tumble into the ditch; but he was ſurpriſed to find another wall behind it, well terraced, and bordered with artillery, and himſelf obliged either to begin afreſh or give up the enterpriſe: and yet this laſt was what Soly-ιhan preferred, when he was told of its being built on a hard rock, incapable of being ſapped, and how firmly it had held out againſt all the effort of Mohammed’s vizier. The next attack was therefore ordered by him to be made againſt the baſtions of the town, and that with a vaſt number of the largeſt artillery, which continued firing during a whole month; ſo that the new wall of the baſtion of England was quite demoliſhed, though the old one ſtood proof againſt all their ſhot. That of Italy, which was battered by 17 large pieces of cannon, was ſtill worſe damaged; upon which Mar-tinengo the engineer adviſed the grand-maſter to cauſe a ſally to be made on the trenches of the enemy out</p><p>of the breach, whilſt he was making freſh entrenchments behind it. His advice ſucceeded; and the 200 men that ſallied out ſword in hand having ſurpriſed the Turks in the trench, cut moſt of them in pieces. At the ſame time a new detachment, which was ſent to repulſe them, being obliged, as that engineer rightly judged, to paſs by a ſpot which lay open to their artillery, were likewiſe moſtly deſtroyed by the continual fire that came from it, whilſt the aſſailants were employed in filling up ſeveral fathoms of the trench before they retired. By that time the breach had been repaired with ſuch new works, that all the efforts to mount it by aſſault proved equally ineffectual and de-ſtructive.</p><p>Unfortunately for the beſieged, the continual fire they had made cauſed ſuch a conſumption of their powder, that they began to feel the want of it; the perfidious d’Amarald, whoſe province it had been to viſit the magazines of it, having amuſed the council with a falſe report, that there was more than ſufficient to maintain the ſiege, though it ſhould laſt a whole twelve-month. But here the grand-maſter found means to ſupply in ſome meaſure that unexpected defect, by the cautious provifion he had made of a large quantity of ſaltpetre, which was immediately ground and made into gunpowder, though he was at the ſame time obliged to order the engineers to be more ſparing of it for the future, and to make uſe of it only in the defence of ſuch breaches as the enemy ſhould make.</p><p>All this while the Turks had not gained an inch of ground; and the breaches they had made were ſo ſud-denly either repaired or defended by new entrenchments, that the very rubbiſh of them muſt be mounted by aſſault. Solyman, therefore, thought it now adviſable to ſet his numerous pioneers at work, in five different parts, in digging of mines, each of which led to the baſtion oppoſite to it. Some of theſe were countermined by a new invented method of Martinengo; who, by the help of braced ſkins, or drums, could diſcover</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>