<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>quickly deepened its bed ; and this circqmſtance increaſing its velocity, as we have ſeen, would extend this deepening backward to the lake, and draw off more of its waters. The work would go on rapidly at firſt, while earth and ſmall ſtones only reſiſted the labours of nature ; but theſe being waſhed away, and the channel hollowed out to the firm rock on all ſides, the operation muſt go on very ſlowly, till the immenſe caſcade ſhall undermine what it cannot break off, and then a new diſcharge will commence, and a quantity of flat ground will emerge all round the lake. The torrent, in the mean time, makes its way down the country, and digs a canal, which may be called the firſt ſhetch of a river, which will deepen and widen its bed continually. The waters of ſeveral baſons united, and running together in a great body, will (according to the principles we have eſtabliſhed) have a much greater velocity, with the fame ſlope, than thoſe of the lakes in the interior parts of the continent ; and the ſum of them all united in the baſon next the ſea, after having broken through its natural mound, 'will make a prodigious torrent, which will dig for itſelf a bed ſo much the deeper as it has more ſlope and a greater body of waters.</p><p>The formation of the firſt valleys, by cutting open many ſprings which were formerly concealed under ground, will add to the maſs of running waters, and contribute to drain off the waters of theſe baſons. In courſe of time many of them will diſappear, and flat valleys among the mountains and hills are the traces of their former exiſtence.</p><p>When nature thus traces out the courſes of future rivers, it is to be expected that thoſe ſtreams will moſt deepen their channels which in their approach to the ſea receive into their bed the greateſt quantities of rain and ſpring waters, and that towards the middle of the continent they will deepen their channels leſs. In theſe laſt ſituations the natural ſlope of the fields cauſes the rain-water, rills, and the little rivulets from the ſprings, to ſeek their way to the rivers. The ground can fink only by the flattening of the hills and high grounds ; and this muſt proceed with extreme ſlowneſs, becauſe it is only the gentle, though inceſſant, work of the rains and ſprings. But the rivers, increaſing in bulk and ſtrength, and of neceſſity ſlowing over every thing, form to themſelves capacious beds in a more yielding foil, and dig them even to the level of the ocean.</p><p>The beds of rivers by no means form themſelves in one inclined plane. If we ſhould ſuppoſe a canal AB (fig. 12.) perfectly ſtraight and horizontal at B, where it joins with the ſea, this canal would really be an inclined channel of greater and greater ſlope as it is farther from B. This is evident ; becauſe gravity is directed towards the centre of the earth, and the angle CAB contained between the channel and the plumb-line at A is ſmaller than the ſimilar angle CDB ; and conſequently the inclination to the horizon is greater in A. than in D. Such a canal therefore would make the bed of a river ; and ſome have thought that this was the real form of nature’s work ; but the ſuppoſition is a whim, and it is falle. No river has a ſlope at all approaching to this. It would be 8 inches declivity in the mile next the ocean, 24 inches in the ſecond mile, 40 inches in the third, and ſo on in the duplicate ratio (for the whole elevation) of the diſtances from the ſea. Such a river would quickly tear up its bed in the moun</p><p>tains (were there any grounds high enough to receive it), and, except its firſt caſcade, would ſoon acquire a more gentle ſlope. But the fact is, and it is the reſult of the impreſcriptible laws of nature, that the continued track of a river is a ſucceſſion of inclined channels, whoſe ſlope diminiſhes by ſteps as the river approaches to the ſea. It is not enough to ſay that this reſults from the natural ſlope of the .countries through which it flows, which we obſerve to increaſe in declivity as we go to the interior parts of the continent. Were it otherwiſe, the equilibrium to which nature aims in all her operations w<hi rend="sup">r</hi>ould ſtill produce the gradual diminution of the ſlope of rivers. Without it they could not be in a permanent train.</p><p>That we may more eaſily form a notion of the manner in which the permanent courſe of a river is eſtabliſhed, let us ſuppoſe a ſtream or rivulet <hi rend="italic">sa</hi>  (fig. 13.) far up the country, make its way through a ſoil perfectly uniform to the ſea, taking the courſe <hi rend="italic">sabedeſ, </hi>and receiving t)be <hi rend="italic">permanent additions</hi>  of the ſtreams <hi rend="italic">g a, h b, i c, k d, le,</hi>  and that its velocity and ſlope in all its parts are ſo ſuited to the tenacity of the ſoil and ►  magnitude of its ſection, that neither do its w aters during the annual frtſhes tear up its banks or deepen its bed, nor do they bring down from the high lands materials which they depolit in the channel in times of ſmaller velocity. Such a riveç may be ſaid to be in a <hi rend="italic">permanentſlate,</hi>  to be in <hi rend="italic">conſervntion,</hi>  or to have<hi rend="italic">Jlability. </hi>Let us call this ſtate of a river fits regimen, denoting by the word the proper adjuſtment of the velocity of the ſtream to the tenacity of the channel. Ί he velocity of its regimen muſt be the ſame throughout, becauſe it is this which regulates its action on the bottom, which is the ſame from its head to the ſea. That its bed may have ſtability, the mean velocity of the current muſt be conſtant, notwithſtanding the inequality of diſcharge through its different fictions by the brocks which it receives in its courſe, and notwithſtanding the augmentation of its ſection as it approaches the ſea.</p><p>On the other hand, it behoved this exact regimen to commence at the mouth of the river, by the working of the whole body of the river, in concert with the waters of the ocean, which always keep within the fame limits, and make the ultimate level invariable. This working will begin to dig the bed, giving it as little breadth as poſſible : for this working conſiſts chiefly in the efforts of falls and rapid llreâms, which ariſe of themſelves in every channel which has too much ſlope. <hi rend="sup">r</hi>l he bottom deepens, and the ſides remain very ſteep, till they, are undermined and crumble down ; and being-then diluted in the water, they are carried down the ſtream, and depoſited where the ocean checks its ſpeed. The banks crumble down anew, the valley or hollow forms ; but the ſection, always confined to its bottom, cannot acquire a great breadth, and it retains a good deal of the form of the trapezium formerly mentioned. In this manner does the regimen begin to be eſtabliſhed from<hi rend="italic">f</hi>  to <hi rend="italic">e.</hi></p><p>With reſpect to the next part <hi rend="italic">de,</hi>  the diſcharge or produce isdiminiſhed by the want of the brook <hi rend="italic">le.</hi>  It muſt take a ſimilar form, but its area will be diminiſhed, in order that its velocity may be the ſame; and its mean depth <hi rend="italic">d</hi>  being leſs than in the portion <hi rend="italic">eſ</hi>  below, the ſlope muſt be greater. Without theſe conditions we could not have the uniform velocity, which the aſſumed</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>