<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>town in Apulia, and were then actually beſieging it. The Roman general, hot ſuſpecting the ſtratagem that was laid againſt him, marched directly by the ſhorteſt road, which lay through the defiles, to relieve the city ; and was not undeceived till he ſaw his army ſurrounded, and blocked up on every ſide. Pontius thus having the Romans entirely in his power, firſt obliged the army to paſs under the yoke, having been previouſly ſtripped of all but their garments ; he then ſtipulated that they ſhould wholly quit the territories of the Samnites, and that they ſhould continue to live upon terms of former confederacy. The Romans were conſtrained to ſubmit to this ignominious treaty, and marched into Capua diſarmed and half naked. When the army arrived at Rome, the whole city was moſt ſurpriſingly afflicted at their ſhameful return ; nothing but grief and reſentment was to be ſeen, and the whole city was put into mourning.</p><p>But this was a tranſitory calamity : the war was carried on as uſual for many years ; the power of the Samnites declining every day, while that of the Romans continually increaſed. Under the conduct of Papirius Curſor, who was at different times conſul and dictator, repeated triumphs were gained. Fabius Maximus alſo had his ſhare in the glory of conquering them ; and Decius, the ſon of that Decius whom we ſaw devoting himſelf for his country about 40 years before, followed the example of his father, and ruſhed into the midſt of the enemy, imagining that he could ſave the lives of his countrymen with the loſs of his own.</p><p>The ſucceſs of the Romans againſt the Samnites alarmed all Italy. The Tarentines in particular, who had long plotted underhand againſt the republic, now Openly declared themſelves ; and invited into Italy Pyrrhus king of Epirus, in hopes of being able by his means to ſubdue the Romans. The offer was readily accepted by that ambitious monarch, who had nothing leſs in view than the conqueſt of all Italy.— Their ambaſſadors carried magnificent preſents for the king, with inſtructions to acquaint him, that they only wanted a general of fame and experience ; and that, as for troops, they could themſelves furniſh a numerous army of 20,000 horſe and 350,000 foot, made up of Lucanians, Meſſapians, Samnites, and Tarentines. As ſoon as the news of this deputation were brought to the Roman camp, Æmilius, who had hitherto made war on the Tarentines but gently, in hopes of adjuſting matters by way of negociation, took other meaſures, and began to commit all ſorts of hoſtilities. He took cities, ſtormed caſtles, and laid the whole country waſte, burning and deſtroying all before him. The Tarentines brought their army into the field ; but Æmilius ſoon obliged them to take refuge within their walls. However, to induce them to lay aſide the deſign of receiving Pyrrhus, he uſed the priſoners he had taken with great moderation, and even ſent them back without ranſom. Theſe highly extolled the generoſity of the conſul, inſomuch that many of the inhabitants were brought over to the Roman party, and they all began to repent of their having rejected a peace and ſent for Pyrrhus.</p><p>But, in the mean time, the Tarentine ambaſſadors arriving in Epirus, purſuant to the powers they had received, made an abſolute treaty with the kirg.j who</p><lb/><p>immediately ſent before him the famous Cyneas, with 3000 men, to take poſſeſſion of the citadel of Tarentum. This eloquent miniſter ſoon found means to depoſe Agis, whom the Tarentines had choſen to be their general and the governor of the city, though a fincere friend to the Romans. He likewiſe prevailed upon the Tarentines to deliver up the citadel into his hands ; which he no ſooner got poſſeſſion of, than he diſpatched meſſengers to Pyrrhus, ſoiicſting him to haften his departure for Italy. In the mean time, the conſul Æmilius, finding that he could not attempt anything with ſucceſs againſt the Tarentines this campaign, reſolved to put his troops into winter-quarters in A-pulia, which was not far from the territory of Tarentum, that was ſoon to become the ſeat of the war. As he was obliged to paſs through certain defiles, with the ſea on one ſide and high hills on the other, he was there attacked by the Tarentines and Epirots from great numbers of barks fraught with baliftæ (that is, engines for throwing ſtones of a vaſt weight), and from the hills, on which were poſted a great many archers and flingers. Hereupon Æmilius placed the Tarentine priſoners between him and the enemy ; which the Tarentines perceiving, ſoon left off moleſting the Romans, out of compaſſion to their own countrymen ; ſo that the Romans arrived ſafe in Apulia, and there took up their winter-quarters.</p><p>The next year Æmilius was continued in the command of his own troops, with the title of <hi rend="italic">proconſul;</hi>  and was ordered to make war upon the Salentines, who had declared for the Tarentines. The preſent exigence of affairs obliged the Romans to enliſt the proletarii, who were the meaneſt of the people, and therefore by way of contempt called <hi rend="italic">proletarii,</hi>  as being thought incapable of doing the ſtate any other ſervice than that of peopling the city, and {locking the republic with ſubjects. Hitherto they had never been ſuffered to bear arms ; but were now, to their great ſatisfaction, enrolled as well as others. In the mean time Pyrrhus arrived at 'Γarentum, having narrowly eſeaped ſhip-wreck ; and being conducted into the city by his faithful Cyneas, was received there with loud acclamations.</p><p>The Tarentines, who were entirely devoted to their pleaſures, expected that he ſhould take all the fatigues of the war on himſelf, and expoſe only his Epirots to danger. And indeed Pyrrhus for ſome days diffembled his deſign, and ſuffered the Tarentines to indulge without reſtraint in their uſual diverſions. But his ſhips, which had been diſperſed all over the Ionian ſea, arriving one after another, and with them the troops which he had put on board at Epirus, he began to reform the diſorders that prevailed in tire city. The theatre was the place to which the idle Tarentines re-ſorted daily in great numbers, and where the incendiaries ſtirred up the people to ſedition with their harangues : he therefore cauſed it to be ſhut up, as he did likewiſe the public gardens, porticoes, and places of exerciſe, where the inhabitants uſed to.entertain themſelves with news, and ſpeak with great freedom of their governors, cenſuring their conduct, and ſettling the government according to their different humours, which occaſioned great diviſions, and rent the city into various factions. As they were a very voluptuous and indolent people, they ſpent whole days aι∙d nights in feaſts, maſquerades, plays, &amp;c. Theſe therefore Pyrrhus ab-</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>