<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>gellinus, captain of the guard, who, from being the moſt abandoned man in Rome, was now become his principal miniſter and favourite.</p><p>Nor were the Roman provinces in a better ſituation than the capital city. The example of the tyrant ſeemed to influence his governors, who gave inſtances not only of their rapacity, but of their cruelty, in every part of the empire. In the ſeventh year of his reign, the Britons revolted, under the conduct of their queen Boadicea* ; but were at laſt ſo completely defeated, that ever after, during the continuance of the Romans among them, they loſt not only all hopes, but even all deſire of freedom.</p><p>A war alſo was carried on againſt the Parthians for the greateſt part of this reign, conducted by Corbulo ; who, after many ſucceſſes, had diſpoſſeſſed Tiridates, and ſettled Tigranes in Armenia in his room. Tiridates, however, was ſoon after reſtored by an invaſion of the Parthians into that country ; but being once more oppoſed by Corbulo, the Romans and Parthians came to an agreement, that Tiridates ſhould continue to govern Armenia, upon condition that he ſhould lay down his crown at the ſeet of the emperor’s ſtatue, and receive it as coming from him ; all which he ſhortly after performed. A ceremony, however, which Nero deſired to have repeated to his perſon ; wherefore by letters and promiſes he invited Tiridates to Rome, granting him the moſt magnificent ſupplies ſor his journey. Nero attended liis arrival with very ſumptuous preparations. He received him ſeated on a throne, accompanied by the ſenate ſtanding round him, and the whole army drawn out with all imaginable ſplendor.— Tiridates aſcended the throne with great reverence ; and approaching the emperor ſell down at his ſeet, and in the moſt abject terms acknowledged himſelf his ſlave. Nero raiſed him up, telling him with equal arrogance, that he did well, and that by his ſubmiflion he had gained a kingdom which his anceſtors could never acquire by their arms. He then placed the crown on his head, and, after the moſt coſtly ceremonies and entertainments, he was ſent back bo Armenia, with incredible ſums of money to defray the expences of his return.</p><p>In the X2th year of this emperor’s reign, the Jews alſo revolted, having been ſeverely oppreſſed by the Roman governor. It is ſaid that Florus, in particular, was arrived at that degree of tyranny, that by public proclamation he gave permiſſion to plunder the country, provided he received half the ſpoil. Theſe oppreſſions drew ſuch a train of calamities after them, that the ſufferings of all other nations were flight in compariſon to what this devoted people afterwards endured, as is related under the article Jews. In the mean time, Nero proceeded in his cruelties at Rome with unabated ſeverity.</p><p>The valiant Corbulo, who had gained ſo many victories over the Parthians, could not eſcape his fury. Nor did the empreſs Poppæa herſelſ eſcape ; whom, in a fit of anger, he kicked when ſhe was pregnant, by which ſhe miſcarried and died. At laſt the Romans began to grow weary of ſuch a monſter, and there appeared a general revolution in all the provinces.</p><p>The firſt appeared in Gaul, under Julius Vindex, who commanded the legions there, and publicly proteſted againſt the tyrannical government of Nero. He appeared to have no other motive for tlſis revolt than that of freeing the world from an oppreffor ; for when it was told him that Nero had ſet a reward upon his head of I o, ooo,ooo of ſeſterces, he made this gallant anſwer, “ Whoever brings me Nero’s head, ſhall, if he pleaſes, have mine.” But ſtill more to ſhow that he was not actuated by motives of private ambition, he proclaimed Sergius Galba empepor, and invited him to join in the revolt. Galba, who was at that time governor of Spain, was equally remarkable for his wiſdom in peace and his courage in war. But as all talents under corrupt princes are dangerous, he for ſome years had ſeemed willing to court obſcurity, giving himſelf up to an inactive liſe, and avoiding all opportunities of ſig-nalizing his valour. He now therefore, either through the caution attending old age, or from a total want of ambition, appeared little inclined to join with Vindex, and continued for ſome time to deliberate with his friends on the part he ſhould take.</p><p>In the mean time, Nero, who had been appriſed of the proceedings againſt him in Gaul, appeared totally regardleſs of the danger, privately flattering himſelf that the ſupprefiion of this revolt would give him an opportunity of freſh confiſcations. But the actual revolt of Galba, the news of which arrived ſoon after, affected him in a very different manner. The reputation of that general was ſuch, that from the moment he declared againſt him, Nero conſidered himſelf as undone. He received the account as he was at ſupper ; and inſtantly, ſtruck with terror, overturned the table with his foot, breaking two cryſtal vaſes of immenſe value. He then ſell into a ſwoon ; from which when he recovered he tore his clothes, and ſtruck his head, crying out, “ that he was utterly undone.” He then began to meditate ſlaughters moιe extenſive than he yet had committed. He reſolved to maſſacre all the governors of provinces, to deſtroy all exiles, and to murder all the Gauls in Rome, as a puniſhment for the treachery of their countrymen. In ſhort, in the wildneſs of his rage, he thought of poiſoning the whole ſenate, of burning the city, and turning the lions kept for the purpoſes of the theatre out upon the people. »· Theſe deſigns being impracticable, he reſolved at laſt to face the danger in perſon. But his very preparations ſerved to mark the infatuation of his mind. His principal care was, to provide waggons for the convenient carriage of his mu-ſical inſtruments ; and to dreſs out his concubines like. Amazons, with whom he intended to face the enemy. He alſo made a reſolution, that if he came off with ſafe-ty and empire, he would appear again upon the theatre with the lute, and would equip himſelf as a pantomime.</p><p>While Nero was thus frivolouſly employed, the revolt became general. Not only the armies in Spain and Gaul, but alſo the legions in Germany, Africa, and Luſitania, declared againſt him. Virginius Rufus alone, who commanded an army on the Upper Rhine, for a while continued in ſuſpenſe ; during which his forces, without his permiſſion, falling upon the Gauls, routed them with great ſtaughter, and Vindex flew himſelf. But this ill ſucceſs no way advanced the intereſts of Nero ; he was ſo deteſted by the whole empire, that he could find none of the armies faithful to him, however they might diſagree with each other. He therefore called for Locuſta to furniſh him with poiſon ; and, thus, prepared for the worſt, he retired to the Servilian gar-</p></body></text></TEI>