<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>HL of the water is lower, or at leaſt not higher, than F.</p><p>If the water could be ſupported at the height BF, BF might be conſidered as an orifice in the ſide of a veſſel. In which caſe, the diſcharge Would be the ſame as if the whole water were flowing with the velocity acquired from the height -~ BF, or <hi rend="sub">τ</hi>*<hi rend="italic">h.</hi>  And if we ſuppoſe that there is no contraction at the orifice, the mean velocity would be 5/2 <hi rend="italic">g⅜ <hi rend="sup">h</hi>&gt; — Vqq2γhD<hi rend="sup">n</hi></hi>  Engliſh inches per ſecond. The area of this orifice is <hi rend="italic">I h* </hi>Therefore the diſcharge would be <hi rend="italic">lh VqfiDſh,</hi>  all being meaſured in inches. This is the uſual theory ; but it is not an exact repreſentation of the manner in which the efflux really happens. The water cannot remain at the height BF ; but in drawing towards the waſteboard from all ſides, it forms a convex ſurface AlH, ſo that the point I, where the vertical drawn from the edge of the waſteboard meets the curve, is conſiderably lower than B. But as all the mafε above F is ſuppoſed perfectly fluid, the preſſure of the incumbent water is propagated, in the opinion of Mr de Buat, to the filament paſſing over at F without any diminution. The ſame may be ſaid of any filament between F and I* Each tends, therefore, to move ill the ſame manner as if it were really impelled through an orifice in Its place. Therefore the motions through every part of the line or plane IF are the ſame as if the water were eſcaping through an orifice IF, made by a ſluice let down on the water, and keeping up the water of the reſervoir to the level AB. It is beyond a doubt (ſays he) that</p><p>the height IF muſt depend on the whole height BF, and that there muſt be a certain determined proportion between them, tie does not attempt to determine this proportion theoretically, but ſays, that his experiments aſeertain it with great preciſion to be the proportion of one to two, or that IF is always orte-half of BF. He ſays, however, that this determination was not by an immediate and direct meaſetrement ; he concluded it from the compariſon of the quantities of water dif-charged under different heights of the water in the reſervoir.</p><p>We -Cannot help thinking that this reaſoning is very defective in ſeveral particulars. It cannot be inferred, from the laws of hydroſtatical preſſure, that the filament at I is preſſed forward with all the weight of the column BI. The particle I is really at the ſurface; and conſidering it as making part of the ſurface of a running ſtream, it is ſubjected to hardly any preſſure, any mote than the particles on the ſurface of a cup of water held in the hand, while it is carried round the axis of the earth and round the ſun·. Reaſoning according to his own principles, and availing himſelf of his own diſeovery, he ſhould ſay, that the particle at I has an accelerating force depending on its ſlope only $ and then he ſhould have endeavoured to aſeertain this ſlope. The motion of the particle at I has no immediate connection with the preſſure of the column BI 3 and if it had, the motion would be extremely different from what it is : for this preſſure alone would give it the velocity which Mr Buat aſſigns it. Now it is already paſſing through the point I with the velocity which it has acquired in deſcending along the curve AI ; and this is the real ſtate of the caſe. The particles are paſſing through with a velocity already acquired by a hoping current} and they are accelerated</p><p>by the hydroſtatical preſſure of the water above them. The internal mechaniſm of theſe motions is infinitely more complex than Mr Buat here ſuppoſes; and on this ſuppoſition, he very nearly abandons the theory which he has ſo ſhgeniouſly eſtabliſhed, and adopts the theory of Gnglſelmini which he had exploded. At the ſame time, we think that he is not much miſtaken when he aſſerts, that the motions are nearly the ſame as if a ſluice had been let down from the ſurface to I. For the filament which paſſes at I has been gliding down a cur» ved ſurface, and has not been expoſed to any friction. It is perhaps the very caſe of hydraulics, where the obſtructions are the ſmalleſt ; and we ſhould therefore expect that its motion will be the leaſt retarded.</p><p>We have therefore no heſitation in ſaying,that the filament at I is in the very ſtate of motion which the theory would aſſign to it if it were paſſing under a ſluice, as Mr Buat ſuppoſes. And with reſpect to the inferior filaments, without attempting the very difficult talk of inveſtigating their motions, we ſhall juſt ſay, that we do not ſee any reaſon for ſuppoſing that they will move flower than our author ſuppoſes. Therefore, though we reject his theory, we admit his experimental propo-fition in general ; that is, we admit that the <hi rend="italic">whole</hi>  water which paſſes through the plane IF moves with the velocity (though notin the ſame direction) with which it would have run through a ſluice of the ſame depth ; and we may proceed with his determination of the quantity of water diſeharged.</p><p>If we make BC the axis of a parabola BEGH, the velocities of the filaments palling at I and F will be repreſented by the ordinates IE and FG, and the diſcharge by the area IEGF. This allows a very neat ſolution of the problem. Let the quantity diſeharged per ſecond be D, and let the whole height BF be A Let 2 G be the quantity by which we muſt divide the ſquare of the mean velocity, in order to have the producing height. This will be leſs than 2y, the acceleration of gravity, on account of the convergency at the fides and the tendency to convergence at the lip F. We formerly gave for its meaſure 726 inches, inſtead of 772, and ſaid that the inches diſeharged per ſecond from an orifice of one inch were 26,49, inſtead of 27,78. Let <hi rend="italic">x</hi>  be the diſtance of any filament from the horizontal line AB. An element of the orifice, therefore, (for we may give it this name) is <hi rend="italic">l x.</hi>  The velocity of this element is y∕ <hi rend="sub">2</hi><hi rend="italic">Qſ, or</hi>  √<hi rend="sup">,</hi><hi rend="sub">2</hi>  G ×<hi rend="italic">V<hi rend="sup">x</hi>∙</hi>  The</p><p>1 <hi rend="sub">e</hi></p><p>diſcharge from it is ∕    2 G <hi rend="italic">x x,</hi>  and the fluent of</p><p>this, orD = <hi rend="italic">Jl</hi>  5/ <hi rend="sup">2</hi>  Gx<hi rend="sup">i</hi>  which is y ∕ 5/2 Gx <hi rend="sup">1</hi>  ſhC.</p><p>To determine the conſtant quantity C, obſerve that Mr de Buat found by experiment that BI was in all caſee 4 BF. Therefore D muſt be nothing when <hi rend="italic">x ≈ ⅛hj </hi>conſequently C ≈ — ∣ ∕ √2 G <hi rend="sup">1</hi>  and the com»</p><p><hi rend="italic">h</hi><hi rend="italic">∖</hi><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="sup">,</hi></hi><hi rend="italic">∖</hi></p><p>pleted fluent, will be D — γ ∕ √<hi rend="sup">,</hi>2 G ζ*{- — ζgj y»</p><p>Now make <hi rend="italic">x = h,</hi>  and we have</p><p>D=∣Z √ <hi rend="smallcaps"><hi rend="sub">2</hi>q</hi>  (∕-<hi rend="sup">,</hi>*^—Q) <hi rend="sup">1</hi>)≈Vv<hi rend="sup">z</hi>  2G</p><p>But ί —(4) l = 0,64645, and ⅔  of this is 0,43« t Therefore, finally,</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>