<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ved ſparingly from the public ſtock, and  a little meaſure of wine out of his ſcanty allowance. An inconſiderable preſent indeed in itſelf, but very acceptable at that time to the perſon on whom it was beſtowed. The tribune’s next care was to puniſh the negligent: accordingly the captain of the guard, who ought to have had an eye over the centinels, was condemned to die, and, purſuant to his ſentence, thrown down ſrom the top of the capitol. The Romans extended their puniſhments and rewards even to the animals. Geeſe were ever after had in honour at Rome, and a flock of them always kept at the expence of the public. A golden image of a gooſe was erected in memory of them, and a gooſe every year carried in triumph upon a ſoft litter finely adorned; whilſt dogs were held in abhorrence by the Romans, who every year impaled one of them on a branch of elder.</p><p>The blockade of the Capitol had already laſted ſeven months; ſo that the famine began to be very ſenſibly felt both by the beſieged and beſiegers. Camillus, ſince his nomination to the dictatorſhip, being maſter of the country, had poſted ſtrong guards on all the roads; ſo that the Gauls dared not ſtir out for fear of being cut to pieces. Thus Brennus, who beſieged the Capitol, was beſieged himſelf, and ſuffered the ſame inconveniences which he made the Romans undergo. Beſides, a plague raged in his camp, which was placed in the midſt of the ruins of the demoliſhed city, his men lying confuſedly among the dead carcaſes of the Romans, whom they had ſlain, and not buried. So great a number of them died in one quarter of the city, that it was afterwards called <hi rend="italic">Buſta Gallica,</hi>  or the place where the dead bodies of the Gauls were burnt. But, in the mean time, the Romans in the Capitol were more pinched with want than the Gauls. They were reduced to the laſt extremity, and at the ſame time ignorant both of the lamentable condition to which the enemy’s army was brought, and of the ſteps Camillus was taking to relieve them. That great general only waited for a favourable opportunity to fall upon the enemy; but, in the mean time, ſuffered them to pine away in their infected camp, not knowing the extreme want the Romans endured in the Capitol, where they were ſo deſtitute of all ſorts of proviſions, that they could no longer ſubſiſt. Matters being brought to this ſad paſs on both ſides, the centinels of the Capitol, and thoſe of the enemy’s army, began to talk to one another of an accommodation. Their diſcourſes came at length to the ears of their leaders, who were not averſe to the deſign.</p><p>The ſenate, not knowing what was become of Camillus, and finding themſelves hard pinched by hunger, reſolved to enter upon a negotiation, and empowered Sulpitius, one of the military tribunes, to treat with the Gauls; who made no great difficulty in coming to terms, they being no leſs deſirous than the Romans to put an end to the war. In a conference, therefore, between Brennus and Sulpitius, an agreement was made, and ſworn to. The Romans were to pay to the Gauls 1000 pounds weight of gold, that is, 45, 000l. Sterling; and the latter were to raiſe the ſiege of the Capitol, and quit all the Roman territories. On the day appointed, Sulpitius brought the ſum agreed on, and Brennus the ſcales and weights; for there were no gold or ſilver coins at that time, metals paſſing only by</p><lb/><p>weight. We are told, that the weights of the Gauls were falſe, and their ſcales untrue; which Sulpitius complaining of, Brennus, inſtead of redreſſing the injuſtice, threw his ſword and belt into the ſcale where the weights were; and when the tribune aſked him the meaning of ſo extraordinary a behaviour, the only anſwer he gave was, <hi rend="italic">Ve</hi><hi rend="italic">victis!</hi>  “ Wo to the conquered! ” Sulpitius was ſo ſtung with this haughty anſwer, that he was for carrying the gold back into the Capitol, and ſuſtaining the ſiege to the laſt extremity; but others thought it adviſable to put up the affront, ſince they had ſubmitted to a far greater one, which was to pay any thing at all.</p><p>During theſe diſputes of the Roman deputies among themſelves and with the Gauls, Camillus advanced with, his army to the very gates of the city; and being there informed of what was doing, he commanded the main body to follow him ſlowly and in good order, while he, with the choiceſt of his men, haſtened to the place of the parley. The Romans, overjoyed at his unexpected arrival, opened to make room for him as the ſupreme magiſtrate of the republic, gave him an account of the treaty they had made with the Gauls, and complained of the wrong Brennus did them in the execution of it. They had ſcarce done ſpeaking, when Camillus cried out, “ Carry back this gold into the Capitol; and you; Gauls, retire with your ſcales and weights. Rome muſt not be redeemed with gold, but with ſteel. Brennus replied, That he contravened a treaty which was concluded and confirmed with mutual oaths. “ Be it ſo (anſwered Camillus); yet it is of no force, having been made by an inferior magiſtrate, without the privity or conſent of the dictator. I, who am inveſted with the ſupreme authority over the Romans, declare the contract void. ” At theſe words Brennus flew into a rage; and both ſides drawing their ſwords, a confuſed ſcuffle enſued among the ruins of the houſes, and in the narrow lanes. The Gauls, after an inconſiderable loſs, thought fit to retire within their camp; which they abandoned in the night, not caring to engage Camillus’s whole army, and, having marched eight miles, encamped on the Gabinian way. Camillus purſued them as ſoon as it was day, and, coming up with them, gave them a total overthrow. The Gauls, according to Livy, made but a faint reſiſtance, being diſheartened at the loſs they had ſuſtained the day before. It was not, ſays that author, ſo much a battle as a ſlaughter. Many of the Gauls were ſlain in the action, more in the purſuit; but the greater number were cut off, as they wandered up and down in the fields, by the inhabitants of the neighbouring villages. In ſhort, there was not one ſingle Gaul leſt to carry to his countrymen the news of this fatal cataſtrophe. The camp of the barbarians was plundered; and Camillus, loaded with ſpoils, returned in triumph to the city, the ſoldiers in their ſongs ſtyling him, <hi rend="italic">Romulus, Father of his country, </hi>and <hi rend="italic">Second founder of Rome.</hi></p><p>As the houſes of Rome were all demoliſhed, and the walls razed, the tribunes of the people renewed, with more warmth than ever, an old project which had occa-ſioned great diſputes. They had formerly propoſed a law ſor dividing the ſenate. and government between the cities of Veii and Rome. Now this law was revived; nay, moſt of the tribunes were for entirely abandoning their old ruined city, and making Veii the ſole</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>