<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>camped in the night, and returned to their reſpective countries before bi eak of day.</p><p>The Latins having now no remedy but an entire ſubmiſſion, ſent ambaſſadors to ſolicit a peace at Rome, yielding themſelves abſolutely to the judgment of the ſenate. As Rome had long ſince made it a maxim to ſpare the nations that ſubmitted, the motion of Titus Lartius, the late dictator, prevailed ; and the ancient treaties with the Latins were renewed, on condition, however, that they ſhould reſtore the priſoners they had taken, deliver up the deſerters, and drive the Roman exiles out of Latium. Thus ended the laſt war which the Romans waged with their neighbours on account of their baniſhed king ; who, being now abandoned by the Latins, Hetrurians, and Sabines, retired into Campania, to Ariſtodemus tyrant of Cumae, and there died, in the 9cth year of his age and 14th of his exile.</p><p>The Romans were no ſooner freed ſrom theſe dangerous wars, than they began to oppreſs one another ; •and thoſe domeſtic fends took place which continued more or leſs during the whole time of the republic. 'T he firſt diſturbances were occaſioned by the oppreſſion of the plebeians who were debtors to the patricians. The ſenate, who were at the head of the patricians, choſe to the conſulate one Appius Claudius, who violently oppoſed the pretenſions of the plebeians ; but gave him for his colleague one P. Servilius, who was of a quite contrary opinion and diſpoſition. The conſequence of this was, that the conſuls diſagreed ; the ſenate did not know what to determine, and the people were ready to revolt. In the midſt of theſe diſtur-bances, an army of the Volſci advanced towards Rome; the people refuſed to ſerve; and had not Servilius procured ſome troops who ſerved out of a perſonal affection to himſelf, the city would have been in great danger.</p><p>But though the Volſci were ſor this time driven back, they had ran intention of dropping their deſigns; they engaged in an alliance with them the Hernici and •Sabines. In the mean time, the diſputes at Rome continued with as much violence as ever. Nay, though they were expreſsly told that the Volſcian army was on its •way to beſiege the city, the plebeians abſolutely refilled to march againſt them ; ſaying, that it was the ſame thing whether they were chained by their own countrymen or by 'the enemy. In this extremity Servilius promiled, that when the enemy were repulſed the ſenate would remit all the debts of the plebeians. This having engaged them to ſerve, the conſul marched out at their head, defeated the enemy in a pitched battle, and took their capital, giving it up to be plundered by his ſoldiers, without reſerving any pail for the pu-ſhlic treaſury.</p><p>Whatever might have been the reaſons of Servilius for this ſtep, it furniſhed Appius with a pretence for refilling him a triumph, as a man of a ſeditious diſpoſition, who aimed at popularity by an exceſſive indulgence and profuſeneſs to his ſoldiers. Servilius, incenſed at this injuſtice, and encouraged by the acclamations of the people, decreed himſelf a triumph m ſpite x&gt;f Appius and the ſenate. After this he marched againſt the Aurunci, who had -entered Latium ; and, in ’conjunction with Poſthumius Regillens, he utterly defeated them, and obliged them to retire into their own country. But neither the ſervicre of the general nor</p><p>his ſoldiers could mollify the ſenate and patrician party. Appius even doubled the ſeverity of his judgments, and impriſoned all thoſe who had been ſet at liberty during the war. The priſoners cried for relief to Ser-vilins ; but he could not obtain the aceomplilhment oſ thoſe promiſes which the ſenate never had meant to perform ; neither did he chooſe to quarrel openly with the whole patrician body ; ſo that, ſtriving to preſerv; the friendſhip of both parties, he incurred the hatred of the one and the contempt of the other. Perceiving therefore that he had loſt all his intereſt with the pk beians, he joined with the patricians againſt theιn ; but the plebeians ruſhing tumultuouſly into the forum, made ſuch a noiſe, that no ſentence pronounced by th <hi rend="sup">, </hi>judges could be heard, and the utmoſt confuſion prevailed through the whole city. Several propoſals were made to accommodate matters $ but through the obſtinacy of Appius and the majority of the ſenators, they all came to nothing. In the mean time it was nec&lt;fi-ſary to raiſe an army againſt the Sabines, who had invaded the territories of the republic ; but the people refuſed to ſerve. Manius Valerius, however, brother to the celebrated Poplicola, once more prevailed upon them to march out againſt the common enemy ; having previouſly obtained aſſurances from the ſenate that dιeir grievances ſhould be redreſſed. But no ſooner had victory declared in favour of the Romans, than the ſenate, apprehending that the ſoldiers at their return would challenge Valerius, who had been nominated dictator, for the performance of tſheir promiſes, deſired him and the two conſuls to detain them ſtill in the field, under pretence that the war was not quite finilh-ed. The conſuls obeyed ; but the dictator, whoſe an* thority did not depend on the ſenate, diſbanded his army, and declared his foſhſhers free from the oath which they had taken ; and as a further proof of his attachment to the plebeians, he choſe out of that order 400, whom he inveſted with the dignity of knights. After this he claimed the accomphſhment of the promiſes made by the ſenate : but inſtead of performing them, he had the mortification to hear himſelf loaded with reproaches ; on which he reſigned his office as dictator, and acquainted the people with his inability to fulfil his engagements to them. No ſooner were theſe tranſactions known in the army, than the ſoldiers, to a man, deſerted the conſuls and other officers, and retired to a hill called afierwatds <hi rend="italic">Mans Surer,</hi>  three miles from Rome, where they continued to obſerve an exact diſcipline, offering no ſort of violence whatever. The ſenate, after taking proper meaſures for the defence of the city, ſent a deputation to the malecontents ; but it was anſwered with contempt. In ſhort, all things tended to a civil war, when at laſt matters were com-promiſed by the inſtitution of tribunes of the people, who had power to prevent the paſſing of any law that might be prejudicial to the people, and whoſe perſons were declared ſacred, inſomuch that whoever offered the leaſt violence to the perſen of a tribune was declared accurſed, his effects were to be conſecrated to Ceres, and he himſelf might be killed with impunity ; and all the Remans were to engage themſelves, in their own name and that of their poſterity, never to repeal this law<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. The people, after theſe regulations, erected an altar to Jupiter the Terrible, on the top of the bill where their camp had ſtood ; and when they had offer-</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>