<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>it depoſits : but as ſoon as it overflows its banks, the ' very enlargement of its ſection diminiſhes the velocity of the water ; and it may be obſerved ſtill running in the track of its bed with great velocity, while the waters on each ſide are ſtagnant at a very ſmall diſtance : Therefore the water, on getting over the banks, muſt depoſit the heavieſt, the firmeſt, and even the greateſt part of its burden, and muſt become gradually clearer to it approaches the hills. Thus a gentle ſlope is given as the valley in a direction which is the reverſe of what one would expect. It is, however, almoſt always the caſe in wide valleys, eſpecially if the great river comes through a ſoft country. The banks of the brooks and ditches are obſerved to be deeper as they approach the river, and the merely ſuperſicial drains run backwards</p><p>from it.</p><p>We have already obſerved, that the enlargement of-the bed of a river, in its approach to the ſea, is not in proportion to the increaſe of its waters. This would be the caſe even if the velocity continued the ſame : and therefore, ſince the velocity even increaſes, in con-ſequence of the greater energy of a large body of ∖ya-ter, which we now underſtand diſtinctly, a ſtill ſmaller bed is ſufficient for conveying all the water to the ſea.</p><p>This general law is broken, however, in the immediate neighbourhood of the ſea ; becauſe in this ſituation the velocity of the water is checked by the paſſing flood-tides of the ocean. As the whole waters muſt ſtill be diſeharged, they require a larger bed, and the enlargement will be chiefly in width. The fand and mud are depoſited when the motion is retarded. The depth of the mouth of the channel is therefore dimi-niihed. It muſt therefore become wider. If this be done on a coaſt expoſed to the force of a regular tide, which carries the waters of the ocean acroſs the mouth of the river, this regular enlargement of the mouth will ' be the only conſequence, and it will generally widen till it waſhes the foot of the adjoining hills ; but if</p><p>- there be no tide in the ſea, or a tide which does not <hi rend="italic">ſet</hi>  acroſs the mouth of the river, the ſands muſt be depoſited at the ſides of the opening, and become additions to the ſliore, lengthening the mouth of the chan-.nel. In this ſheltered ſituation, every trivial circumſtance will cauſe the river' to work more on particular parts of the bottom, and deepen the channel there. This keeps the mud ſuſpended in ſuch parts of the channel, and it is not depoſited till the ſtream has ſhot farther out into the ſea. It is depoſited on the ſides of thoſe deeper parts of the channel, and increaſes the velocity in them, and thus ſtill farther protracts the de-poſition. Rivers ſo ſituated will not only lengthen their channels, but will divide them, and produce iſlands at their mouths. A buſh, a tree, torn up by the roots by a mountain torrent, and floated down the ſtream, will thus inevitably produce an iſland; and rivers in which this is common will be continually ſhifting their mouths. The Miſſiflippi is a moſt remarkable inſtance of this. It has a long courſe through a rich- ſoil, and diſembogucs itſelf into the bay of Mexico, in a place where there is no <hi rend="italic">Paſſing tide,</hi>  as may be ſeen by comparing the hours of high water in different places. No river that we know carries down its ſtream ſuch numbers of rooted-up trees : they frequently interrupt the navigation, and render it always dangerous in the nighU-</p><p>time. This river is ſo beſet with flats and ſhifting ſands at its mouth, that the moſt experienced pilots are puzzled ; and it has protruded its channel above 50 miles in the ſhort period that we have known it. The diſcharge of the Danube is very ſimilar : ſo is that of the Nile ; for it is diſeharged into a ſtill corner of the Mediterranean. It may now be ſaid to have acquired conſiderable permanency; but much of this is owing to human induſtry, which ſtrips it as much as poſſible of its ſubſideable matter. The Ganges too is in a ſituation pretty ſimilar, and exhibits ſimilar phenomena. The Maragnon might be noticed as an exception ; but. it is not an exception. It has flowed very ſar in a level bed, and its waters come pretty clear to Para ; but beſides, there is a ſtrong tranſverle tide, or rather current, at its mouth, ſetting to the ſouth-eaſt both during flood and ebb. The mouth of the Po is perhaps the moſt remarkable of any on the ſurface of this globe, and exhibits appearances extremely Angular. Its diſcharge is into a ſequeſtered corner of the Adriatic. Though there be a more remarkable tide in this gulf than in any part of the Mediterranean, it is ſtill but trifling, and it either ſets directly in upon the mouth of the river, or retires ſtraight away from it. The river has many mouths, and they ſhift prodigiouſly. There has been a general increaſe of the land very remarkable. The marſhes where Venice now ſtands were, in the Auguſtan age, everywhere penetrable by the ſiſhing boats, and in the yth century could only bear a few miſerable huts ; now<hi rend="sup">r</hi>  they are covered with crowds of ſtately buildings. Ravenna, ſi-tuated on the ſouthernmoſt mouth of the Po, was, in the Auguſtan age, at the extremity of a ſwamp, and the road to it was along the top of an artificial mound, made by Auguſtus at immenſe expence. It was, however, a fine city, containing extenſive docks, arſenals, and other maſſy buildings, being the great military port of the empire, where Auguſtus laid up his great ſhips ,of war. In the Gothic times it became almoſt the capital of the Weſtern empire, and was the ſeat of government and of luxury. It muſt, therefore, be ſuppo-ſed to have every accommodation of opulence, and we cannot doubt of its having paved ſtreets, wharfs, &amp;c. ; ſo that its wealthy inhabitants were at leaſt walking dryfooted from houſe to houſc. But now it is an Italian mile from the ſea, and ſurrounded with vineyards and cultivated fields, and is acceſſible in every direction. All this muſt have been formed by depoiitions from the-Po, flowing through Lombardy loaded with the ſpoils of the Alp», which were here arreſted by the reeds and bulruſhes of the marſh. Theſe things are in common courſe ; but when wells are dug, we come to the pavements of the ancient city, and theſe. pavements are all on one exact level, and they<hi rend="italic">are eigh t ſeet below the ſurface of the ſea at low water.</hi>  This cannot be aſeribed to the fubſiding. of the ancient city. This would be irregular, and greateſt among the heavy buildings. The tomb of Theodoric remains, and the pavement round it is on a level with all the others. The lower ſtory is always full of water ; ſo is the lower ſtory of the cathedral to the depth of three feet. The ornaments of both theſe buildings leave no room to doubt that they were formerly dry ; and ſuch a building as the cathedral could not fink without crumbling into pieces.</p><p>It is by no means eaſy to account for all this. The.</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>