<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>firſt. Brennus, looking upon the promotion of the Fabii as an high affront on his nation, haſtened his march to Rome.</p><p>As his army was very numerous, the inhabitants of the towns and villages through which he paſſed left their habitations at his approach ; but he flopped nowhere, declaring that his deſign was only to be revenged on the Romans. The ſix military tribunes, to wit, Fabius, Caeſo Fabius, Caius Fabius, Sulpitius, Q<hi rend="smallcaps"><hi rend="sub">l</hi></hi>  Servilius, and Sextus Cornelius, marched out of Rome at the head of 40,000 men, without either ſacri-ſicing to the gods or conſulting the auſpices ; eſſential ceremonies among a people that drew their courage and confidence from the propitious ſigns which the augurs declared to them. As moſt of the military tribunes were young, and men of more valour than experience, they advanced boldly againſt the Gauls, whoſe army was 7Q,000 ſtrong. The two armies met near the river Allia, about ſio furlongs from Rome. The Romans, that they might not be ſurrounded by the enemy, extended their wings ſo ſar as to make their centre very thin. T heir beſt troops, to the number of 24,000 men, they poſted between the river and the adjoining hills ; the reſt they placed on the hills. The Gauls firſt attacked the latter, who being ſoon put into confuſion, the forces in the plain were ſtruck with ſuch terror that they fled without drawing their ſwords. In this general diſorder, moſt of the ſoldiers, inſtead of returning to Rome fled to Veii : ſome were drowned as they endeavoured to ſwim acroſs the Tiber ; many fell in the purſuit by the ſword of the conquerors ; and ſome got to Rome, which they filled with terror and conſternation, it being believed there that all the reſt were cutoff. The day after the battle, Brennus marched his troops into the neighbourhood of Rome, and encamped on the banks of the Anio. Thither his ſcouts brought him word, that the gates of the city lay open, and that not one Roman was to be ſeen on the ramparts. This made him apprehenſive of ſome ambuſcade, it being un-reaſonable to ſuppoſe that the Romans would abandon their city to be plundered and ſacked without making any reſiſtance. On this conſideration he advanced ſlowly, which gave the Romans an opportunity to throw into the Capitol all the men who were fit to bear arms. They carried into it all the proviſions they could get ; and, that they might laſt the longer, admitted none into the place but ſuch as were capable of defending it.</p><p>As for the city, they had not ſufficient forces to defend it ; and therefore the old men, women, and children, ſeeing themſelves abandoned, fled to the neighbouring towns. The Veſtals, before they left Rome, took care to hide every thing appropriated to the gods which they could not carry off. The two palladiums, and the ſacred fire, they took with them. When they came to the Janieulus, one Albinius, a plebeian, who was conveying his wife and children in a caιriage to a place of ſafety, ſeeing the ſacred virgins bending under their load, and their ſeet bloody, made his family alight, put the prieſteſſes and their gods into the carriage, and conducted them to Caere, a city of Hetruria, where they met with a favourable reception. The Veſtals remained at Caere, and there continued to perform the uſual rites of religion ; and hence thoſe rites were called <hi rend="italic">ceremonies.</hi>  But while the reſt of the citizens at Rome were providing for their ſafety, about 80 of the moſt illuſtrious and venerable old men, rather than fly from their native city, choſe to devote themſelves to death by a vow, which Fabius the high pontiff pronounced in their names. The Romans believed, that, by theſe voluntary devotements to the infernal gods, 'diſorder and confuſion was brought among the enemy. Of theſe brave old men ſome were pontifices, others had been conſuls, and others generals of armies, who had been honoured with triumphs. To complete their ſacriſice with a ſolemnity and pomp becoming the magnanimity and conſtancy of the Romans, they dreſſed themſelves in their pontifical, conſular, and triumphal robes ; and repairing to the forum, ſeated themſelves there in their curule chairs, expecting the enemy and death with the greateſt conſtancy.</p><p>At length Brennus, having ſpent three days in uſeleſs precaution«, entered the city the fourth day after the battle. He found the gates open, the walls without defence, and the houſes without inhabitants. Rome appeared to him like a mere deſart ; and this ſolitude increaſed his anxiety. He could not believe, either that all the Romans were lodged in the Capitol, or that ſo numerous a people ſhould abandon the place of their nativity. On the other hand, he could nowhere ſee any armed men but on the walls of the citadel. However, having firſt ſecured all the avenues to the Capitol with ſtrong bodies of guards, he gave the reſt of his ſoldiers leave to diſperſe themſelves all over the city and plunder it. Brennus himſelf advanced into the forum with the troops under his command, in good order ; and there he was ſtruck with admiration at the unex·. pected fight of the venerable old men who had devoted themſelves to death. Their magnificent habits, the majeſty of their countenances, the ſilence they kept, their modeſty and conſtancy at the approach of his troops, made him take them for ſo many deities : for they continued as motionleſs as ſtatues, and ſaw the enemy advance without ſhowing the leaſt concern. The Gauls kept a great while at an awful diſtance from them, being afraid to come near them. But at length one ſoldier bolder than the reſt, having out of curioſity touched the beard of M. Papirius, the venerable old man, not being uſed to ſuch familiarity, gave him a blow on the head with his ivory ſtaff. The ſoldier in revenge immediately killed him ; and the reſt of the Gauls following’ his example, ilaughtered all thoſe venerable old men without mercy.</p><p>After this the enemy ſet no bounds to their rage and fury. They plundered all places, dragging ſuch of the Romans as had ſhut themſelves up in their houſes into the ſtreets, and there putting them to the ſword without diſtinction of age or ſex. Brennus then inveſted the Capitol ; but being repulſed with great loſs, in order to be revenged of the Romans for their refifl<hi rend="sub">τ </hi>ance, hg reſolved to lay the city in aſhes. Accordingly, by his command, the ſoldiers ſet fire to the houſes, demoliſhed the temples and public edifices, and raſed the walls to the ground. Thus was the famous city of Rome entirely deſtroyed ; nothing was to be ſeen in the place where it ſtood but a few little hills covered with ruins, and a wide waſte, in which the Gauls who inveſted the Çapitol were encamped. Brennus, finding he ſhould never be able to take a place which nature had ſo well fortified otherwiſe than by famine, turned the ſiege into a blockade. But in the mean time, his</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>