<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>rennis; who in oppreſſion and cruelty ſeems to have been nothing inferior to thoſe of the moſt tyrannical emperors. During the firſt part of the reign of Commodus, he ruled with an abſolute ſway; but at laſt was torn in pieces by the enraged ſoldiery, whom he had offended by his too great ſeverity. He was ſucceeded in his place by a freedman named <hi rend="italic">Cleander;</hi>  for the emperor himſelf was ſo much taken up with his plea-lures, that he could not beſtow even a moment on the affairs of ſtate. The new miniſter abuſed his power in a more flagrant manner than even his predeceſſor lutd done. By him all things were openly ſet to ſale; offices, provinces, public revenues, juſtice, and the lives of men both innocent and guilty. The miniſter, who ruled the emperor without controul, infuſed ſuch terrors into his timorous mind, that he changed the captains of his guards almoſt continually. One Niger enjoyed the dignity only fix hours; another only five days; and ſeveral others a ſtill ſhorter ſpace. Moſt of thoſe officers loſt their lives along with their employments; being accuſed of treaſon by Cleander, who continually ſolicited, and at laſt obtained, that important poſt for himſelf.</p><p>In the year 187 happened a remarkable revolt. One Maternus, a common ſoldier, having fled from his colours, and being joined by many others guilty of the ſame crime, grew in a ſhort time ſo powerful, the banditti flocking to him from all parts, that he over-ran and plundered great part of Gaul and Spain ; ſtormed the ſtrongeſt cities ; and ſtruck the emperor and people of Rome with ſuch terror, that troops were raiſed, and armies diſpatched againſt him. Peſcennius Niger was ſent to make head againſt him in Gaul, where he became very intimate with Severus, who was then governor of Lyons, and who wrote a letter to the emperor, commending the prudent and gallant behaviour of Niger in purſuing the rebels. Maternus, finding himſelf reduced to great ſtraits, divided his men into ſeveral ſmall bands, and marched privately with them by different ways into Italy ; having nothing leſs in view than to murder the emperor during the ſolemnity which was kept annually in honour of the mother of the gods, and on his death to ſeize upon the empire for himſelf. They all arrived at Rome undiſcovered ; and ſeveral of his men had already mixed themſelves with the emperor’s guards, when others of his own party betrayed him. He was immediately ſeized and executed ; and his death put an end to the diſturbances which ſome of his followers had begun to raiſe in other provinces. In the ſame year broke out the moſt dreadful plague, ſays Dio Caſſius, that had been known. It laſted two or three years ; and raged with the greateſt violence at Rome, where it frequently earned off 2000 perſons a-day. The following year a dreadſul fire, which conſumed a great part of the city, was kindled by lightning ; and at the ſame time the people were afflicted with a dreadſul famine, occaſioned, according to ſome authors, by Cleander, who, having now in view nothing leſs than the ſovereignty itſelf, bought up underhand all the corn, in order to raiſe the price of it, and gain tire affections of the ſoldiery and people by diſtributing it among them. Others tell us, however, that Papirius Dionyſius, whoſe province it was to ſupply the city with profilions, 'contributed towards the famine, in order to make the people riſe againſt Clean</p><p>der. ' Be this as it will, the populace aſeribed all their calamities to this hated miniſter; and one day, while the people were celebrating the Circaſſian games, a troop of children, having at their head a young woman of an extraordinary ſtature and fierce aſpect, entering the circus, began to utter aloud many bitter invectives and dreadful curſes againſt Cleander ; which being for ſome time anſwered by the people with other invectives and curſes, the whole multitude roſe all of a ſudden, and flew to the place where Cleander at that time reſided with the emperor. There, renewing their invectives, they demanded the head of the miniſter who had been the occaſion of ſo many calamities. Hereupon Cleander ordered the prætorian cavalry to charge the multitude ; which they did accordingly, driving them with great ſlaughter into the city. But the populace diſeharging ſhowers of ſtones, bricks, and tiles, lrom the tops of the houſes and from the windows, and the city-guards at the ſame time taking part with the people, the prætorian horſe were ſoon obliged to ' ſave themſelves by flight : nor was the ſlaughter ended till the emperor, appriſed of the tumult, cauſed the head of Cleander to be ſtruck off and thrown out to the enraged populace. The emperor himſelf did not long ſurvive Cleander ; being cut off' by a conſpiracy of Marcia his favourite concubine, Lætus captain of the guards, and Eclectus his chamberlain..</p><p>No ſooner was the death of Commodus known, than the ſenate aſſembled, and declared him a public enemy, loading him with curſes, ordering his ſtatues to be broken to pieces, and his name to be raſed out of all public inſeriptions ; and demanded his body, that it might be dragged through the ſlreets, and thrown into the Tiber. But Helvius Pertinax, whom the conſpirators had previouſly deſigned for the empire, and who had already aſſumed it, prevented ſuch an outrage, by letting the ſenators know that Commodus was already buried. This extraordinary perſonage had paſſed through many changes of fortune. He was originally the ſon of an enfranchiſed ſlave, called <hi rend="italic">Ælius,</hi>  who only gave him ſo much learning as to qualify him for keeping a little ſhop in the city. He then became a ſchoolmaſter, afterwards ſtudied the law, and after that became a ſoldier; in which ſtation his behaviour was ſuch as cauſed him to be ſoon made Captain of a cohort againſt the Parthians. Being thus introduced to arms he went through the uſual gradation of military preferment in Britain and Mæfia, until he became the commander of a legion under Aurelius. In this ſtation he performed ſuch excellent ſervices againſt the barbarians, that he was made conſul, and ſucceſe ſively governor of Dacia, Syria, and Aſia Minor. In the reign of Commodus he was baniſhed; but ſoon after recalled, and font into Britain to reform the abuſes in the army. In this employment his uſual extraordinary fortune attended him : he was oppoſed by a ſedition among the legions, and left for dead among many others that were ſlain. However, he got over this danger, ſeverely puniſhed the mutineers, and eſtabliſhed regularity and diſcipline among the troops he was ſent to command. From thence he was removed into Africa, where the ſedition of the ſoldiers had like to have been as fatal to him as in his former government. Removing from Africa, and fatigued with an active liſe, he betook himſelf to retirement : but Commodus, </p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>