<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>are accuſtomed , to attend chiefly to the appearances which prognoſticate miſchief, and we interpret the appearances of a permanent bed in the ſame way, and frequently form very falſe judgments. When we ſee one bank low and flat, and the other high and abrupt, we ſuppoſe that the waters are paſſing along the firſt; in peace, and with a gentle ſtream, but that they are rapid on the other ſide, and are tearing away the bank ; but it is juſt the contrary. The bed being permanent, things are in equilibrio, and each bank is of a form juſt competent to that equilibrium. If »he ſoil on both ſides be uniform, the ſtream is moſt rapid on that ſide where the bank is low and flat, for in no other form would it withſtand the action of the ſtream ; and it has been worn away till its flatneſs compenſates for the greater force of the ſtream. The ſtream on the other ſide muſt be more gentle, otherwiſe the bank could not remain abrupt. In ſhort, in a ſtate of permanency, the velocity of the ſtream and form of the bank are juſt ſuited to each other. It is quite otherwiſe before the river has acquired its proper regimen.</p><p>A careful conſideration therefore of the general features of rivers which have ſettled their regimen, is of uſe for informing us concerning their internal motions, and directing us to the moſt effectual methods of regulating their courſe.</p><p>We have already ſaid that perpendicular brims are inconſiſtent with ſtability. A ſemicircular ſection is the form which would produce the quickeſt train of a river whoſe expence and Hope are given ; but the banks at B and D (fig. 14.) would crumble in, and lie at the bottom, where their horizontal ſurface would ſecure them from farther change. The bed will acquire the form G <hi rend="italic">c</hi>  F, of equal ſection, but greater width, and with brims leſs ſhelving. The proportion of the velocities at A and <hi rend="italic">c</hi>  may be the fame with that of the velocities at A and C ; but the velocity at G and F will be leſs than it was formerly at B, C, or D; and the velocity in any intermediate point E, being ſomewhat between thoſe at F and <hi rend="italic">c,</hi>  muſt be leſs than it was in any intermediate point of the ſemicircular bed. The velocities will therefore decreaſe along the border ſrom <hi rend="italic">c</hi>  towards G and F, and the ſteepneſs of the border will augment at the ſame time, till, in every point of the new border GcF, theſe two circumſtances will be ſo adjuſted that the neceſſary equilibrium is eſtabliſhed.</p><p>The ſame thing muſt happen in our trapezium. The ſlope of the brims may be exact, and will be retained ; it will, however, be too great anywhere below, where the velocity is greater, and the ſides will be worn away till the bankδ are undermined and crumble down, and the river will maintain its ſection by increaſing its width. In ſhort, no border made up of ſtraight lines is conſiſtent with that gradation of velocity which will take place whenever we depart from a ſemicircular form. And we accordingly ſee, that in all natural channels the ſection has a curvilineal border, with the ſlope increaſing gradually from the bottom to the brim.</p><p>Theſe obſervations will enable us to underſtand how nature operates when the inequality of ſurface or of tenacity obliges the current to change its direction, and the river forms an elbow.</p><p>Suppoſinjg always that the diſcharge continues the fame, and that the mean velocity is either preſerved or</p><p>reſtored, the following conditions are neceſſary for a permanent regimen.</p><p>ί. The depth of water muſt be greater in the elbow than anywhere elſe.</p><p>2.    The main ſtream, after having ſtruck the concave bank, muſt be reflected in an equal angle, and muſt then be in the direction of the next reach of the river.</p><p>3.    The angle of-incidence muſt be proportioned to the tenacity of the ſoil.</p><p>4.    There muſt be in the elbow an increaſe of ſlope, or of head of water, capable of overcoming the reſiſtance occaſioned by the elbow.</p><p><hi rend="sub">s</hi> The reaſonableneſs, at leaſt, of theſe conditions will appear from the following conſiderations.</p><p>]. It is certain that force is expended in producing this change of direction in a channel which by ſuppoſition diminiſhes the current. The diminution aτifing from any cauſe which can be compared with friction muſt be greater when the ſtream is directed againſt one of the banks. It may be very difficult to ſtate the proportion, and it would occupy too mach of our time to attempt it ; but it is ſufficient that we be convinced that the retardation is greater in this caſe. We ſee no cauſe to increaſe the mean velocity in the elbow, and we muſt therefore conclude that it is diminiſhed. But we are ſuppoſing that the diſcharge continues the ſame; the ſection muſt therefore augment, or the channel increaſe its tranſverſe dimenſions. The only queſtion is, In what manner it does this, and what change of form does it affect, and what form is competent to the final equilibrium and the conſequent permanency of the bed ? Here there is much room for conjecture. Mr Buat reaſons as ſollows. If we ſuppoſe that the points B and C (fig. 15.) continue on a level, and that the points H and I at the beginning of the next reach are alſo on a level, it is an inevitable conſequence that the ſlope along CMl muſt be greater than along BEH, becauſe the depreſſion of H below B is equal to that of I below C, and BEH is longer than CMI. Therefore the velocity along the convex bank CMI muſt be greater than along BEH. There may even be a ſtagnation and an eddy in the contrary direction along the concave bank. Therefore, if the form of the ſection were the ſame as up the ſtream, the ſides could not ſtand on the convex bank. When therefore the ſection has attained a permanent form, and the banks are again in equilibrio with the action of the current, the convex bank muſt be much flatter than the concave. If the water is really ſtill on the concave bank, that bank will be abfo-lutely perpendicular ; nay, may overhang.—Accordingly, this ſtate of things is matter of daily obſervation, and juſtiſies our reaſoning, and entitles us to ſay, that this is the nature of the internal motion of the filaments which we cannot diſtinctly obſerve. The water moves moſt rapidly along the convex bank, and the thread of the ſtream is neareſt to this ſide. Reaſoning in this way, the ſection, which we may ſuppoſe to have been originally of the form MiaE (fig. 16.) aſſumes the ſhape MBAE.</p><p>2. Without preſuming to know the mechaniſm of the internal motions of fluids, we know that ſuperſicial waves are reflected preciſely as if they were ehtſtſe bodies, making the angles of incidence and reflection equal,. In as far therefore as the ſuperficial wave is concerned in the operation, Mr Buat’s ſecond poſition is juſt».</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>