<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ject. The fame principles of mutual preſſure and equilibrium have a place in roofs and many wooden edifices; and if they had been as much ſtudied as the Normans and Saracens ſeem to have ſtudied ſuch of them as were applicable to their purpoſes, we might have produced wooden buildings as ſar ſuperior to what we are familiarly acquainted with, as the bold and wonderful churches ſtill remaining in Europe are ſuperior to the timid productions of our ſtone architecture. The cein-tres uſed in building the bridge of Orleans and the corn-market ⅜f Paris, are late inſtances of what may be done in this way. The laſt mentioned is a dome of 200 feet diameter, built of fir planks ; and there is not a piece of timber in it more than nine feet long, a foot broad, and three inches thick.</p><p>The Norman architects frequently roofed with ſtone. Their wooden roofs were in general very fimple, and their profeſſed aim was to diſpenſe with them altogether. Fond of their own ſcience, they copied nothing from a wooden building, and ran into a ſimilar fault with the ancient Greeks. The parts of their buildings which were neceſſarily of timber were made to imitate ſtone-buildings; and Gothic ornament conſiſts in cramming every thing full of arches and ſpaundrels. Nothing elſe is to be ſeen in their timber works, nay even in their ſculpture. Took at any of the maces or ſceptres ſtill to be found about the old cathedrals; they are ſilver ſteeples.</p><p>But there appears to have been a rivalſhip in old times between the maſons and the carpenters. Many of the baronial halls are of prodigious width, and are roofed with timber : and the carpenters appeared to have borrowed much knowledge from the maſons of thoſe times, and their wide roofs are frequently conſtructed with great ingenuity. Their aim, like the maſons, was to throw a roof over a very wide building without employing great logs of timber. We have ſeen roofs 6o ſeet wide, without having a piece of timber in it above io ſeet long and 4 inches ſquare. The Parliament Houſe and Tron-Church of Edinburgh, the great hall of Tarnaway caſtle near Elgin, are ſpecimens of thoſe roofs. They are very numerous on the continent. Indeed Britain retains few monuments of private magnificence. Ariſtocratic ſtate never was ſo great with us ; and the rancour of our civil wars gave moſt of the performances of the carpenter to the flames. Weſtminſter-hall exhibits a ſpecimen of the falſe taſte of the Norman roofs. It contains the eſſential parts indeed, very properly diſpoſed ; but they are hidden, or intentionally covered, with what is conceived to be ornamental ; and this is an imitation of ſtone arches, crammed in between ſlender pillars which hang down from the principal frames, truſſes, or rafters. In a pure Norman roof, ſuch as Tarnaway hall, the eſſential parts are exhibited as things underſtood, and therefore reliſhed. They are refined and ornamented ; and it is here that the inferior kind of taſte or the want of it may appear. And here we do not mean to defend all the whims of our anceſtors ; but we aſſert that it is no more neceſſary to conſider the members of a roof as things to be concealed like a ganet or privy, than the members of a ceiling, which form the moſt beautiſul part of the Greek architecture. Should it be ſaid that a roof is only a thing to keep off the rain, it may be anſwered,</p><lb/><p>that a ceiling is only to keep off the duſt, or the floor to be trodden underfoot, and that we ſhould have neither copartments in the one nor inlaid work or carpets on the other. The ſtructure of a roof may therefore be exhibited with propriety, and made an ornamental feature. This has been done even in Italy. The church of St Maria Maggiore in Rome and ſeveral others are ſpecimens: but it muſt be acknowledged, that the forms of the principal ſrames of theſe roofs, which reſemble thoſe of our modern buildings, are very unfit for agreeable ornament. As we have already obſerved, our imaginations have not been made ſufficiently familiar with the principles, and we are rather alarmed than pleaſed with the appearance of the immenſe logs of timber which form the couples of theſe roofs, and hang over our heads with every appearance of weight and danger. It is quite otherwiſe with the ingenious roofs of the German and Norman architects. Slender timbers, interlaced with great ſymmetry, and thrown by neceſſity into figures which are naturally pretty, form altogether an object which no carpenter can view without pleaſure. And why ſhould the gentleman refuſe himſelf the ſame pleaſure of beholding ſcientific ingenuity ?</p><p>The roof is in fact the part of the building which requires the greateſt degree of fl∙cill, and where ſcience will be of more ſervice than in any other part. The architect ſeldom knows much of the matter, and leaves the taſlc to the carpenter. The carpenter conſiders the framing of a great roof as the touchſtone of his art; and nothing indeed tends ſo much to ſhow his judgment and his fertility of reſource.</p><p>It muſt therefore be very acceptable to the artiſt to have a clear view of the principles by which this difficult problem may be folved in the beſt manner, ſo that the roof may have all the ſtrength and ſecurity that can be wiſhed for, without an extravagant expence of timber and iron. We have ſaid that mechanical ſcience can give great aſſiſtance in this matter. We may add that the framing of carpentry, whether for roofs, floors, or any other purpoſe, affords one of the moſt elegant and moſt ſatisfactory applications which can be made of mechanical ſcience to the arts&gt;of common liſe. Unfortunately the practical artiſt is ſeldom poſſefl'ed even of the ſmall portion of ſcience which would almoſt inſure his practice from all riſh of failure ; and even our moſt experienced carpenters have ſeldom any more knowledge than what ariſes from their experience and natural ſagacity. The moſt approved author in our language is Price in his Britiſh Carpenter. Mathurin Jouſſe is in like manner the author moſt in repute in France ; and the publications of both theſe authors are void of every appearance of principle. It is not uncommon to ſee the works of carpenters of the greateſt reputation tumble down., in conſequence of miſtakes from which the moſt elementary knowledge would have ſaved them.</p><p>We ſhall attempt, in this artide, to give an account of the leading principles of this art in a manner ſo familiar and palpâble, that any perſon who know<hi rend="sup">,</hi>sthecommon properties of the lever, and<hi rend="sup">x</hi>the Oompoſition of motion, ſhall ſo far underſtand them as to be able, on every occaſion, ſo to diſpoſe his materials, with reſpect to the ſtrains to which they are to be expoſed, that he ſhall always know the effective ſtrain on every piece, and</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>