<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>togers began to prognoſticate his ruin. A writing was ſet up in the forum to this effect : “ We, in the name of the ancient Chaldeans, give Vitellius warning to depart this life by the kalends of October.” Vitellius, on his part, received this information with terror, and ordered all the aſtrologers to be baniſhed from Rome. An old woman having foretold, that if he ſurvived his mother, he ſhould reign many years in happineſs and ſecurity, this gave him a deſire of putting her to death ; which he did, by refuſing her ſuſtenance, under the pretence of its being prejudicial to her health. But he ſoon ſaw the futility of relying upon ſuch vain prognoſtications ; for his ſoldiers, by their cruelty and rapine, having become inſupportable to the inhabitants of Rome, the legions of the Eaſt, who had at firſt acquieſced in his dominion, began to revolt, and ſhortly after unanimouſiy reſolved to make Veſpalian emperor.</p><p>Veſpaſian, who was appointed commander againſt the rebellious Jews, had reduced moſt of their country, except Jeruſalem, to ſubjection. The death of Nero, however, had at firſt interrupted the progreſs of his arms, and the ſucceſſion of Galba gave a temporary check to his conqueſts, as he was obliged to ſend his ſon Titus to Rome, to receive that emperor’s commands. Titus, however, was ſo long detained by contrary winds, that he received news of Galba’s death before he ſet ſail. He then reſolved to continue neuter during the civil wars between Otho and Vitellius ; and when the latter prevailed, he gave him his homage with reluctance. But being deſirous of acquiring reputation, though he diſliked the government, he determined to lay liege to Jeruſalem, and actually made preparations for that great undertaking, when he was given to underſtand that Vitellius was deteſted by all ranks in the empire. Theſe murmurings increaſed every day, while Veſpaſian ſecretly endeavoured to advance the diſcontents of the army. By theſe means they began at length to fix their eyes upon him as the perſon the moſt capable and willing to terminate the miſeries of his country, and put a period to. the injuries it ſuffered. Not only the legions under his command, but thoſe in Mæfia and Pannonia, came to the ſame reſolution, ſo that they declared themſelves for Veſpaſian. He was alſo without his own conſent proclaimed emperor at Alexandria, the army there confirming it with extraordinary applauſe, and paying their accuſtomed homage. Still, however, Veſpaſian ſeemed to decline the honour done him ; till at length his ſoldiers compelled him, with their threats of immediate death, to accept a title which, in all probability, he wiſhed to enjoy. He now, therefore, called a council of war : where it was reſolved, that his ſon Titus ſhould carry on the war againſt the Jews ; and that Mutianus, one of his generals, ſhould, with the greateſt part of his legions, enter Italy ; while Veſpaſian himſelf ſhould levy forces in all parts of the eaſt, in order to reinforce them in caſe of neceſſity.</p><p>During theſe preparations, Vitelliu3, though buried in ſloth and luxury, was reſolved to make an effort to defend the empire ; wherefore his chief commanders, Valens and Cecina, were ordered to make all poſſible preparations to reſiſt the invaders. The firſt army that entered Italy with an hoſtile intention was under the command of Antonius Primus, who was met by Ce-cina near Cremona. A battle was expected to enſue j but a negociation taking place, Cecina was prevailed upon to change ſides, and declare for Veſpaſian. His army, however, quickly repented of what they had done ; and' impriſoning their general, attacked Antonius, though without a leader. The engagement con-’ tinued during the whole night : in the morning, after <hi rend="italic">a<hi rend="sup">, </hi></hi>ſhort repaſt, both armies engaged a ſecond time ; when the ſoldiers of Antonius ſaluting the riſing ſun, according to cuſtom, the Vitellians ſuppoſing that they had received new reinforcements, betook themſelves to flight, with the loſs of 30,0c0 men. Shortly after, freeing their general Cecina from priſon, they prevailed upon him to intercede with the conquerors for pardon ; which they obtained, though not without the moſt horrid barbarities committed upon Cremona, the city to which they had retired for ſhelter.</p><p>When Vitellius was informed of the defeat of his army, his former inſolence was converted into an extreme of timidity and irreſolution. At length he commanded Julius Priſcus and Alphenus Varus, with ſome forces that were in readineſs, to guard the paſſes of the Apennines, to prevent the enemy’s march to Rome ; reſerving the principal body of his army to ſecure the city, under the command of his brother Lucius. But being perfoaded to repair to his army in perſon, his preſence only ſerved to increaſe the contempt of his ſoldiers. He there appeared irreſolute* and ſtill luxurious, without counſel or conduct, ignorant of war, and demanding from others thoſe iιi-ſtructions which ſt was his duty to give. After a ſhort continuance in the camp, and' underſtanding the revolt of his fleet, he returned once more to Rome : but every day only ſerved to render his affairs ſtill more deſperate ; till at laſt he made offers to Veſpaſian of reſigning the empire, provided his life were granted, and a ſufficient revenue for his ſnpport. In order to enforce his requeſt, he iſſued from his palace in deep mourning, with all his domeſtics weeping round him. He then went to offer the ſword of juſtice to Cecilius,, the conſul which he refuſing, the abject emperor prepared to lay down the enſigns of the empire in the temple of Concord. But being interrrupted by ſome, who cried out, That he himſelf was Concord<hi rend="sub">r </hi>he reſolved, upon ſo weak an encouragement, ſtill to maintain his power, and immediately prepared for his defence.</p><p>During this fluctuation of counſels, one Sabinus, who had adviſed Vitellius to reſign, perceiving his deſperate ſituation, reſolved, by a bold ſtep, to oblige Veſpaſian, and accordingly ſeized upon the Capitol. But he was premature in his attempt ; for the ſoldiers of Vitellius attacked him with great fury, and, prevailing by their numbers, ſoon laid that beautiful building in aſhes. During this dreadful conflagration, Vitellius was feaſting in the palace of Tiberius, and beholding all the horrors of the aſſault with great ſatisfaction. Sabinus was taken priſoner, and ſhortly after executed by the emperor’s command. Young Domitian,, his nephew, who was afterwards emperor, eſcaped by flight, in the habit of a prieſt ; and all the reſt who ſurvived the fire were put to the ſword.</p><p>But this ſucceſs ſerved little to improve the affairs of Vitellius. He vainly lent meſſenger after meſſenger to. bring Veſpaiian’s general, Antonius, to a compoſition»,</p></body></text></TEI>