<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>effect of viſcidity is moil ſenſible in great maſſes of water in flow motion, and is almoſt inſenſible in ſmall pipes, ſo as not to diſturb theſe experiments. We may therefore aſſume 297 as the general value of .    _</p><p>Since we have, we have alſo . This we may expreſs by . And thus, when we have expreſſed the effect of friction by , the quantity <hi rend="italic">m</hi>  is variable, and its general value is , in which <hi rend="italic">n</hi>is an invariable abſtract number equal to 243,7, given by the nature of the reliſtance which water ſuſtains from its bed, and which indicates its intenſity.</p><p>And, laſtly, ſince <hi rend="italic">m = n</hi>  (√<hi rend="italic">d</hi>—o,1)<hi rend="sup">2</hi>, we have , and the expreſſion of the velocity V, which water acquires and maintains along any channel whatever, now becomes V =<hi rend="italic">,</hi>  or ,i in which X is alſo a variable quantity, depending on the ſlope of the ſurface or channel, and expreſſing the accelerating force which, in the caſe of water in train, is in equilibrio with the reſiſtances expreſſed by the numerator of the fraction.</p><p>Having ſo happily ſucceeded in aſcertaining the variations of reſiſtance, let us accompany Mr Buat in his inveſtigation of the law of acceleration, expreſſed by the value of X.</p><p>Experience, in perfect agreement with any diſtinct opinions that we can form on this ſubject, had already ſhowed him, that the reſiſtances increaſed in a flower ratio than that of the ſquares of the velocities, or that the velocities increaſed flower than √ <hi rend="italic">s.</hi>  Therefore, in the formula V = , which, for one</p><p>A</p><p>channel, we may expreſs thus, V =, we muſt admit</p><p>that X is ſenſibly equal to √<hi rend="italic">s</hi>  when the ſlope is very ſmall or <hi rend="italic">s</hi>  very great. But, that we may accurately expreſs the velocity in proportion as the ſlope augments, we muſt have X greater than √<hi rend="italic">s</hi>  ; and moreover, muſt increaſe as √<hi rend="italic">s</hi>  diminiſhes. Theſe condi-tions are neceſſary, that our values of V, deduced from the formula V = , may agree with the experiment.</p><p>In order to comprehend every degree of ſlope, we muſt particularly attend to the motion through pipes, becauſe open canals will not furniſh us with inſtances of exact trains with great ſlopes and velocities We can make pipes vertical. In this caſe is , and the velocity is the greateſt poſſible for a train by the action of gravity : But we can give greater velocities than this</p><p>by increaſing the head of water beyond what produces the velocity of the train.</p><p>Let AB (fig. 10.) be a vertical tube, and let CA be the head competent to the velocity in the tube, which we ſuppoſe to be in train. The ſlope is 1, and the full weight of the column in motion is the preciſe meaſute of the reſiſtance. The value of , conſidered as a ſlope, is now a maximum ; but, conſidered as expreſſing the proportion of the weight of the column in motion to the weight which is in equilibrio with the reſiſtance, it may not be a maximum ; it may ſurpaſs unity, and <hi rend="italic">s</hi>  may be leſs than 1. For if the veſſel be filled to E, the head of water is increaſed, and will produce a greater velocity, and this will produce a greater reſiſtance. The velocity being now greater,, the head EF which imparts it muff be greater than CA. But it will not be equal to EA, becauſe the uniform velocities <hi rend="italic">are found</hi>  to increaſe faſter than the ſquare roots of the preſſures. This is the general fact. Therefore F is above A, and<hi rend="sup">,</hi>the weight of the column FB, now employed to overcome the reſiſtance, is greater than the weight of the column AB in motion. In ſuch caſes, therefore, —, greater than unity, is a fort</p><p>of fictitious ſlope, and only repreſents the proportion of the reſiſtance to the weight of the moving column. This proportion may ſurpaſs unity.</p><p>But it cannot be infinite: For ſuppoſing the head of water infinite ; if this produce a finite velocity, and we deduct from the whole height the height corre-ſponding to this finite velocity, there will remain an infinite head, the meaſure of an infinite reſiſtance produced by a finite velocity. This does not accord with the obſerved law of the velocities, where the reſiſtances actually do not increaſe as fail as the ſquares of the velocities. Therefore an infinite head would have produced an infinite velocity, in oppoſition to the reſiſtances : taking off the head of the tube, competent to this velocity, at the entry of the tube, which head would alſo be infinite, the remainder would in all probability be finite, balancing a finite reſiſtance.</p><p>Therefore the value of <hi rend="italic">s</hi>  may remain finite, although the velocity be infinite ; and this is agreeable to all our cleareſt notions of the reſiſtances.</p><p>Adopting this principle, we muſt find a value of X which will anſwer all theſe conditions. 2. It muſt be ſenſibly proportional to √ <hi rend="italic">s,</hi>  while <hi rend="italic">s</hi>  is great. It mult always be leſs than √ <hi rend="italic">s</hi>. 3. It muſt deviate from the proportion of √ <hi rend="italic">s,</hi>  ſo much the more as √ <hi rend="italic">s</hi>  is ſmaller. 4. It muſt not vaniſh when the velocity is infinite. 5. It muſt agree with a range of experiments with every variety of channel and of ſlope.</p><p>We ſhall underſtand the nature of this quantity X better by repreſenting by lines the quantities concerned im forming it.</p><p>If the velocities were exactly as the ſquare roots of the ſlopes, the equilateral hyperbola NKS (fig. 10. n<hi rend="sup">0</hi> 2 ) between its aſſymptotes MA, AB, would repreſent the equation V = ——. The values of √<hi rend="italic">s </hi>would be repreſented by the abſeiſſæ, and the velocities by the ordinates, and V √ <hi rend="italic">s</hi>  = A would be the power of the. hyperbola. But ſince theſe velocities are not ſenſibly.</p></body></text></TEI>