<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Tn this advice Otho acquieſced : he had been for ſome time ſo uneaſy under the war, that he ſeemed willing to exchange ſuſpenſe ſor danger. However, he was fo ſurrounded with flatterers, that he was prohibited from being perſonally preſent in the engagement, but prevailed upon to reſerve himſelf ſor the fortune of the empire, and wait the event at Brixellum. The affairs of both armies being thus adjuſted, they came to an engagement at Bedriacum ; where, in the beginning, thoſe on the ſide of Otho ſeemed to have the advantage. At length, the ſuperior discipline of the legions of Vitellius turned the ſcale of victory. Otho’s army fled in great confuſion towards Bedriacum, being purſued with a miſerable ſlaughter all the way.</p><p>In the mean time, Otho waited for the news of the battle with great impatience, and ſeemed to tax his meſſengers with delay. The firſt account of his defeat was brought him by a common ſoldier, who had eſcaped from the field of battle. However, Otho, who was ſtill ſurrounded by flatterers, was deſired to give no credit to a baſe fugitive, who was guilty of falſehood only to cover his own cowardice. The ſoldier, however, ſtill perſiſted in the veracity of his report ; and, finding none inclined to believe him, immediately ſell upon his ſword, and expired at the emperor’s feet. Otho was ſo much ſtruck with the death of this man, that he cried out, that he would cauſe the ruin of no more ſuch valiant and worthy ſoldiers, but would end the conteſt the ſhorteſt way ; and therefore having exhorted his followers to ſubmit to’Vitellius, he put an end to his own liſe.</p><p>It was no ſooner known that Otho had killed himſelf, than all the ſoldiers repaired to Virginius, the commander of the German legions, earneſtly intreating him to take upon him the reins of government ; or at leaſt, intredting his mediation with the generals of Vitellius in their favour. Upon his declining their requeſt, Rubrius Gallus, a perſon of conſiderable note, undertook their embaſſy to the generals of the conquering army ; and ſoon after obtained a pardon for all the adherents of Otho.</p><p>Vitellius was immediately after declared emperor by the ſenate ; and received the marks of diſtinction which were now accuſtomed to follow the appointment of the ſtrongeſt ſide. At the ſame time, Italy was ſeverely diſtreſſed by the ſoldiers, who committed ſuch outrages as exceeded all the oppreſſions of the moſt calamitous war. Vitellius, who was yet in Gaul, reſolved, before hc ſet out for Rome, to puniſh the prætorian cohorts, who had been the inſtruments of all the late diſturbances in the ſtate. He therefore cauſed them to be diſarmed, and deprived of the name and honour of ſoldiers. He alſo ordered 150 of thoſe who were moſt guilty to be put to death.</p><p>As he approached towards Rome, he paſſed through the towns with all imaginable ſplendor ; his paſſage by water was in painted galleys, adorned with garlands of flowers, and profuſely furniſhed with the greateſt delicacies. In his journey there was neither order nor diſcipline among his ſoldiers; they plundered wherever they came with impunity ; and he ſeemed no way diſpleaſed with the licentiouſneſs of their behaviour.</p><p>Upon his arrival at Rome, he entered the city, not as a place he came to govern with juſtice, but as a town that became his own by the laws of conqueſt. He</p><lb/><p>marched through the ſtreets mounted on horſeback, all in armour ; the ſenate and people going before him, as if the captives of his late victory. He the next day made the ſenate a ſpeech, in which he magnified his own actions, and promiſed them extraordinary advantages from his adminiſtration. He then harangued the people, who, being now long accuſtomed to flatter all in authority, highly applauded and bleſſed their new emperor.</p><p>In the mean time, his ſoldiers being permitted to ſa-tiate themſelves in the debaucheries of the city, grew totally unfit for war. The principal affairs of the ſtate were managed by the loweſt wretches. Vitellius, more abandoned than they, gave himſelf up to all kinds of luxury and profiiſeneſs : but gluttony was his favourite vice, ſo that he brought himſelf to a habit of vomiting, in order to renew his meals at pleaſure. His entertainments, though ſeldom at his own coſt, were prodigiouſly expenſive ; he frequently invited himſelf to the tables of his ſubjects, breakfaſting with one, dining with another, and ſupping with a third, all in the ſame day. The moſt memorable of theſe entertainments was that made for him by his brother on his arrival at Rome. In this were ſerved up 2000 ſeveral diſhes of ſiſh, and 70cc of fowl, of the moſt valuable kinds. But in one particular diſh he ſeemed to have outdone all the former profuſion of the moſt luxurious Romans. This diſh, which was of ſuch magnitude as to be called, the <hi rend="italic">jldeld of Minerva,</hi>  was filled with an olio made ſrom the founds of the fiſh called <hi rend="italic">ſcarri,</hi>  the brains of phea-ſants and woodcocks, the tongues of the moſt coſtly birds, and the ſpawn of lampreys brought from the Carpathian ſea. In order to cook this diſh properly, a furnace was built in the fields, as it was too large for any kitchen to contain it.</p><p>In this manner did Vitellius proceed ; ſo that Joſe-phus tells us, if he had reigned long, the whole empire would not have been ſufficient to have maintained his gluttony. All the attendants of his court ſought to raiſe themſelves, not by their virtues and abilities, but the ſumptuouſneſs of their entertainments. This prodigality produced its attendant, want; and that, in turn,, gave riſe to cruelty.</p><p>Thoſe who had formerly been his aſſociates were now deſtroyed without mercy. Going to viſit one of them in a violent fever, he mingled poiſon with his water, and delivered it to him with his own hands. He never pardoned thoſe money-lenders who came to demand payment of his former debts. One of the number coming to ſalute him, he immediately ordered him to be carried off to execution ; but ſhortly after, commanding him to be brought back, when all his attend--ants thought it was to pardon the unhappy creditor, Vitellius gave them ſoon to underſtood that it was merely to have the pleaſure of feeding his eyes with: his torments. Having condemned another to death,, he executed his two ſons with him, only for their preſuming to intercede for their father. A Roman knight being dragged away to execution, and crying out that he had made the emperor his heir, Vitellius demanded to ſee the will, where finding himſelf joint heir with another, he ordered both to be executed, that he might enjoy the legacy without a partner.</p><p>By the continuance of ſuch vices and cruelties as theſe he became odious to all mankind, and the aſtro∙</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>