<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>rived from the verb <hi rend="italic">portare,</hi>  “ to carry’.” As mount Palatine ſtood by itſelf, the whole was incloſed within the line made by the plough, which formed almoſt the figure of a ſquare ; whence, by Dionyſius Halicarnaf-ſenſis, it is called <hi rend="italic">Roma ſſyadrata.</hi></p><p>As to the exact year of the foundation of Rome, there is a great diſagreement among hiſtorians and chronolo-gers. Fabius Pictor, the moſt ancient of all the Roman writers, places it in the end of the ſeventh Olympiad ; that is, according to the computation of Uſher, in the year of the world 3256, of the flood 1600, and 748 before the Chriſtian sera. The Romans, if we may ſo call them, began to build, as Plutarch and others inform us, on the 2tſt of April; which day was then conſecrated to Pales, goddeſs of the ſhephercls ; whence the feſtival of Pales, and that of the foundation of the city, were afterwards jointly celebrated at Rome.</p><p>When Rome had received the utmoſt perfection which its poor and rude founder could give it, it conſiſted of about 1000 houſes, or rather huts ; and was properly ſpeaking a beggarly- village, whereof the principal inhabitants followed the plough, being obliged to cultivate with their own hands the ungrateful ſoil of a barren country which they had ſhared among themſelves. Even the walls of Romulus’s palace were made of ruſhes, and covered with thatch. As every one had choſen his ground to build upon, without any regard to the regularity and beauty of the whole, the ſtreets, if we may ſo call them, were both crooked and narrow. In ſhort, Rome, till it was rebuilt after the burning of it by the Gauls, was rather a diſorderly heap of huts, than a city built with any regularity or order.</p><p>As ſoon as the building of the city was finiſhed, Romulus aſſembled the people, and deſired them to chooſe what kind of government they would obey. At that time monarchy was the unanimous voice of the Romans, and Romulus was elected king. Before he aſcended the throne, however, he conſulted the will of the gods by augury ; and having received a favourable anſwer, it thence became an eſtabliſhed cuſtom to have recourſe to augury before the raiſing any one to the dignity of king, prieſt, or any public employment. After this he applied himſelf to the eſtabliſhment of good order and ſubordination among his ſubjects. He put on a habit of diſtinction for himſelf, appointed j 2 lictors to attend him as guards, divided his ſubjects, who at this time conſiſted only of 33,000 men, into <hi rend="italic">curia. decurine. patricians, plebeians, patrons, clients,</hi>  &amp;c. for an account of which, ſee theſe articles as they occur in the order of the alphabet. - After this he formed a ſenate conſiſting of too perſons, choſen from among the patricians ; and a guard of }OO young men called <hi rend="italic">celer es,</hi>  who attended the king, and ſought either on foot or on horſeback as occaſion required. The king’s office at home was to take care of religious affairs, to be the guardian of laws and cuſtoms ; to decide the weightier cauſes between man and man, referring thoſe of ſmaller moment to the ſenate ; to call together the ſenators, and aſſemble the people, firſt delivering his own opinion concerning the affair 1 e propoſed, and then ratifying by his confient what was agreed on by the majority. Abroad, and in the time of war, he was to command the army with abſolute authority, and to take care of the public money. The ſenate were not only to be judges in matters of ſmall</p><p>importance, but to debate and reſolve upon ſuch public affairs as the king propoſed, and to determine them by a plurality of voices. The people were allowed to create magiſtrates, enact laws, and reſolve upon any war which the king propoſed ; but in all theſe things the confient of the ſenate was neceſſary.</p><p>Romulus next proceeded to ſettle the religious affairs of his people. Many of the Trojan and Phry« gian deities were added to thoſe whom the Aborigines or Italian natives already worſhipped. He choſe prieſts, inſtituted feſtivals, and laid the foundation of a regular ſyſtem of religion ; after which, as his colony was ſtill thinly peopled, he opened an aſylum for fugitive ſlaves, homicides, outlaws, and debtors. Theſe, however, he did not at firſt receive within the walls, but appointed for their habitation the hill Saturnius called afterward3 <hi rend="italic">Capitolinas,</hi>  on which he erected a temple to a divinity of his own invention, whom he named the <hi rend="italic">Alyleaη god, </hi>under whoſe protection all criminals were to live ſecure-ly. But afterwards, when the city was enlarged, the aſylum was incloſed within the walls, and thoſe who who dwelt in it included among the citizens of Rome.</p><p>When Romulus had thus ſettled every thing relating to his new colony, it was found that a ſupply of women was wanting to perpetuate its duration. This occaſioned ſome difficulty ; for the neighbouring nations refuſed to give their daughters in marriage to ſuch a crew of vagabonds as had ſettled in Rome ; wherefore Romulus at laſt reſolved on the following expedient. By the advice of his grandfather Numitor, and with thecon-ſent of the ſenate, he proclaimed a ſolemn feaſt and public games in honour of the Equeſtrian Neptune called <hi rend="italic">Cotiſus.</hi>  This occaſioned a great concourir of people, who flocked from the adjacent parts to behold theſe pompous ſhows, together with the new city. But, in the midſt of the ſolemnity, the Romane, ruſhing in with their ſwords drawn, ſeized all the young women, to the number of 683, for whom Romulus choſe huſhands. Among all thoſe who were thus ſeized, only one married woman, named <hi rend="italic">Herlllia,</hi>  was found ; and Romulus is ſaid to have kept her ſor himſelf.</p><p>This violence ſoon brought on a war with the neighbouring nations. Acron king of Cænina, a city on the confines of Latium, having entered into a league with the inhabitants of Cruſtuminum and Antemnæ, invaded the Roman territories. Romulus marched againſt them without delay, defeated the confederate army, killed their king in Angle combat, decreed himſelf a triumph, and conſecrated the ſpoils of Acron to Jupiter Feretrius, under the name of <hi rend="italic">Opima Spolia.</hi>  The city of Cænina was razed to the ground, and the inhabitants tranſplanted to Rome, where they were admitted to the privileges of citizens. The king then marched with one legion (conſiſting at this time of 3003 foot and 3so horſe) againſt the Cruſtumini and Antemnates, both of whom he defeated in battle, and tranſplanted the inhabitants to Rome ; which being incapable of holding ſuch a number, Romulus took in the hill Saturnius above-mentioned, on the top of which he built a citadel, committing the care of it to a noble Roman named <hi rend="italic">Tarpe&gt;us.</hi>  The citadel was ſurrounded on all ſides with ramparts and towers, which equally commanded the city and country. From the loot of the hill Saturnius a wall was carried on quite to the Tiber, and a gate</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>