<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>I τtil and 12th of his preſent majeſty, which ſecures to biſhops and eccleſiaſtical perſons repayment by their ſuc-ceſſors of expenditures in purchaſing glebes and houſes, or building new houſes, originated from this excellent man, and muſt ever endear his name to the clergy. The other acts for repairing churches, and facilitating the recovery of eccleſiaſtical dues, were among the many happy exertions of the primate.</p><p>But it was at Armagh, the ancient ſeat of the primacy, that he diſplayed a princely munificence. A very elegant palace, 90 feet by 60, and 40 high, adorns that town ; it is light and pleaſing, without the addi-tion*of wings or leſſer parts; which too frequently wanting a ſufficient uniformity with the body of the edifice, are unconnected with it in effect, and divide thé attention. Large and ample offices are conveniently placed behind a plantation at a ſmall diſtance. Around the palace is a large lawn, which ſpreads on every ſide over the hills, ſhirted by young plantations, in one of which is a terrace, which commands a moſt beautiful view of cultivated hill and dale ; this view from the palace is much improved by the barracks, the ſchool, and a new church at a diſtance ; all which are ſo placed as to be exceedingly ornamental to the whole country’.</p><p>The barracks were erected under the primate’s direction, and form a large and handſome edifice. The ſchool is a building of conſiderable extent, and admirably adapted for the purpoſe ; a more beautiful or better contrived one is nowhere to be ſeen ; there are apartments for a maſter, a ſchool-room 56 feet by 28, a large dining room and ſpacious airy dormitories, with every other neceſſary, and a ſpacious play-ground walled in ; the whole forming a handſome fιont : and attention being paid to the reſidence of the maſter (the ſalary is 400l. a year), the ſchool flouriſhes, and muſt prove one of the greateſt advantages to the country. This edifice was built entirely at the primate’s expence. The church is erected of white ſtone, and having a tall ſpire, makes a very agreeable object, in a country where churches and ſpires do not abound. The primate built three other churches, and made conſiderable reparations to the cathedral ; he was alſo the means of erecting a public infirmary, contributing amply to it himſelf : he likewiſe conſtructed a public library at his own coſt, endowed it, and gave it a large collection of books ; -the room is 45 feet by 25, and 20 high, with a gallery and apartments for the librarian. - The town he ornamented with a mai ket-houſe and ſhambles, and was the direct means, by giving leaſes upon that condition, of 'almoſt new-building the whole place. He found it a neſt of mud cabins, and he left it a well-built city of ſtone and date. Theſe are noble and ſpirited works, in which the primate expended not leſs than L. 30,0c0. Had this ſum been laid out in improving a paternal eſtate, even then they would be deſerving great praiſe ; but it is not for his poſterity but the public good that his grace was ſo munificest. A medal was ſtruck by the ingenious William Moſſop of Dublin, which has on one ſide the head of the primate, inſcribed “ Richard Robinſon, Baron Rokeby, Lord Pιimate of all Ireland.” And on the reverſe, the ſouth front of the obſervatory at Armagh, erected by his grace, with this admirable motto, “ The Heavens declare the glory of God.” MDCCLXXXIX.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Robinson (Robert), a diſſenting miniſter of conſi</hi></p><p>derable note, was born on the 8th of October I7 35 at Swaffham in Norfolk. His father died when he was young ; and his maternal grandfather Robert Wilkin, of Milden-hall, Suffolk, gent, who had ever been diſſa-tisſied with his daughter’s marriage, deprived him of bis maternal inheritance, cutting him off with half-a-guinea. His uncle, however, who was a ſubſtantial farmer, in ſome meaſure ſupplied this loſs. He took Mr Robinſon home, and placed him under the Rev. Joſeph Brett, at Seaming ſchool in Norfolk, with a view to the miniſtry of the church of England ; where he had for one of his ſchool-ſellows the lord chancellor Thurlow. When about the age of 1 ç or 16, h»e imbibed the notions of George Whitfield ; on which account he was diſcarded by his uncle, and again expoſed to poverty and want. He firſt directed his thoughts towards the miniſtry in the year 1754, and commenced preacher in the following year at the age of 20; preaching his firſt ſermon to a congregation of poor people at Milden-hall. He continued for a year or two as one of Mr Whitfield’s preachers, and during that period he married. In the year 1758, however, he determined to ſeparate from the Methodiſts ; after which he ſettled at Norwich with a ſmall congregation formed chiefly of his methodiſtic friends, being at that time an Independent. In the year 1759 he was invited to Cambridge, and for two years preached on trial to a congregation conſiſting of no more than 34 people, and ſo poor that they could only raiſe L. 3 : 6 : o a quarter for his ſub-ſiſtence. In June 1761 he ſettled as their paſtor, and was ordained in the uſual manner; at which time we are told he exerciſed the office of a barber. In 1774, his congregation had ſo much increaſed as to conſiſt of 1000 ſouls, including children and ſervants.</p><p>In Cambridge Mr Robinſon’s talents ſoon attracted notice, and he quickly ſet up a Sunday evening lecture, which was well attended. His preaching was altogether without notes ; a method in which he was peculiarly happy : not by trufting to his memory entirely, nor by working himſelf up to a degree of warmth and paſſion, to which the preachers among whom he firſt appeared commonly owe their ready utterance ; but by thoroughly ſtudying and making himſelf perfectly maſter of his ſubject, and a certain faculty of expreſſion which is never at a loſs for ſuitable and proper words. In ſhort, his manner was admirably adapted to enlighten the underſtanding, and to affect and reform the heart. He had ſuch a plainneſs of ſpeech, ſuch an eaſy and apparent method in dividing a diſcourſe, and ſuch a familiär way of reaſoning, as diſcovered an heart filled with the tendereſt concern for the meaneſt of his hearers ; and yet there was a decency, propriety, and juſt-neſs, that the moſt judicious could not but approve. Several gentlemen of the univerlity, eminent for character and abilities, we are told, were his conſtant hearers.</p><p>The circumſtances which loſt him his uncle’s patronage paved the way for the future events of his liſe. The incident which made him diſcard the common ſentiments· on the ſeſhject of baptiſm, at once marked the turn of his mind, and ſhows what apparently flight cauſes frequently determine the lot and uſefuln-eſs of our lives. He was invited to the baptiſm of a child ; the miniſter who was to perform the ſervice keeping the company in long expectation of his appearance, ſome</p></body></text></TEI>