<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-25T20:16:59Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>angular flags and pendants, without any regard to their colour. They are numeral, and each has its signification attached to its number in the general signal-book. The distinctive mark of a distant signal is a ball, which is used as a preparative, a stop, or an answer.</p><p>In the general signal-book are detailed sets of instructions relative to the line of battle and order of sailing, each signal for a specific evolution being accompanied by a plate, explanatory of the measure contemplated.</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">Night Signals</hi> are made with lanterns, rockets, blue lights, and guns. The numbers are not many, and care is taken to confine the signals to those objects of the most general application in practice, so as not to complicate or confuse ; for it may be observed, that night signals are almost always very difficult both to make and to interpret.</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">Vocabulary Signals</hi> are made by means of twenty- one symbols, named A, B, &amp;c., to Y inclusive, (all the alphabet, omitting J, U, W, X, and Z, but retaining I and V). There are no numeral flags used in this code, and no more than three symbols are used at one time. These symbols are made with square and triangular flags, with the occasional use of pendants, to distinguish the alphabetical, the military, and the geographical, parts of the vocabulary from one another. The vocabulary signals, with their significations, are arranged in the following order : words and sentences, alphabet, military phrases and terms, geographical table, and list of the navy. The words and sentences are placed together, the words being arranged in alphabetical order, the sentences immediately following their most prominent words. This book is divided into three parts, but as the number of words required to be used would exceed the power of combination of three symbols, a distinctive pendant is used, to signify which portion of the book is to be referred to, and in this way the same combinations may be used several times over. The military table consists of such technical terms and phrases as are likely to occur on general service. The geographical table contains the names of places, while the body of the volume consists of words and sentences for universal use.</p><p>A code of signals for the use of the mercantile marine was published by Captain Marryat, of the Royal Navy, in 1817 ; it has, we believe, been in general use ever since, and has run through many editions.</p><p>The flags and pendants used in Captain Marryat’s mercantile code of signals are fifteen, exclusive of the Union Jack, which, by order in Council, when used in the merchant service, is to have a white border all round, such border being one-fifth of the breadth of the Jack itself without the border.</p><p>There are ten numerical flags, which represent the figures in arithmetic, and are used throughout the whole of Captain Marryat’s code of signals.</p><p>The Union Jack, as above distinguished from that used by men of war, which Jack, we may mention, viz. that with the white border, is now used in the navy only as a signal for a pilot.</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">first distinguishing pendant</hi> is hoisted over the number, or at some other mast-head, when the number of a merchant ship is shown in part <hi rend="italic">second</hi> of the code.</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">rendezvous flag</hi> is hoisted over the number of the port in part <hi rend="italic">third.</hi></p><p>The sentences in part <hi rend="italic">fourth</hi> are expressed by the <hi rend="italic">numerical flags</hi> alone.</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">second distinguishing pendant</hi> is hoisted over the numbers in the first division of the vocabulary.</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">telegraph flag</hi> is hoisted at some other mast-head, when the numbers in the second division of the vocabulary are shown.</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">numerical pendant</hi> is hoisted over a number, when merely the figures are intended to be shown.</p><p>The code of signals consists of six parts.</p><p>1st, A list of the names of men-of-war.</p><p>2d, A list of the names of merchant ships, copied from Lloyd’s Register.</p><p>3d, A list of ports, headlands, rocks, reefs, shoals, &amp;c. 4th, A selection of sentences.</p><p>5th. The first division of the vocabulary consists of compass signals, ships’ stores, auxiliary verbs, and final terminations, to assist in spelling words.</p><p>6th, The second division of the vocabulary consists of the alphabet, and words most likely to be used in commercial and maritime affairs. The alphabet is introduced for the purpose of spelling words which are not found in the vocabulary.</p><p>It is certainly much to be washed, that every means should be used to induce merchant ships to adopt some code of signals ; and we trust the gallant and accomplished author, who is so well known in other walks of literature, will not relax his exertions in this humble but very useful department of writing, but that he will study, by fresh editions, to keep his code always up to the wants of the day.</p><p>For the rest, we are of opinion that the subject of signals, both in the navy and in the merchant service, is one which requires more attention than it has yet met with. It would seem highly desirable, for instance, that a universal code, sanctioned by their respective governments, should be adopted amongst all the trading nations of the world. If the great maritime countries were to promulgate one grand code, it would speedily be adopted by all, and every ship would then be able to communicate with any other at sea, without the necessity of coming within hail, which is always troublesome, and often impossible. We all now use the same or similar charts ; we all use the same methods of navigating our ships, by chronometers, lunars, and so forth ; the manipulations of our seamanship are all alike ; and why should not our means of communicating by signal be the same ?	(u. τ.)</p><p>SIGNATURE, in <hi rend="italic">Printing,</hi> is a letter put at the bottom of the first page at least, in each sheet, as a direction to the binder in folding, gathering, and collating them. The signatures consist of the capital letters of the alphabet, which change in every sheet ; and if there be more sheets than letters in the alphabet,a figure is placed before the signature, as 2 A, 2 B, &amp;c., which are repeated as often as necessaιy.</p><p>SIGNET, one of the king’s seals, made use of in sealing his private letters, and all grants that pass by bill signed under his Majesty’s hand. It is always in the custody of the Secretaries of State.</p><p>SILBERBERG, a town of the Prussian province of Silesia, in the circle of Frankenstein. It is an open town in a mining district in a narrow valley, surrounded with hills, on whose sides the streets are built, but the valley is 1350 feet above the level of the sea. The inhabitants are occupied in making cloth, and in exploring the mines. It is chiefly remarkable from fortified points on five hills, which overlook the town, and which are so connected with each other by works, as to form a most complete citadel, which is surrounded by a ditch seventy feet in depth, and which has within its barracks a natural cavern, sufficiently commodious to lodge securely a garrison of 5000 men. When, in the campaigns of 1806 and 1807, the whole of Prussia was subdued by the French, this place alone defended itself up to the conclusion of the peace of Tilsit.</p><p>SILESIA, a large tract of country, now divided between Austria and Prussia. In ancient times, it was inhabited by two rude tribes, called the Lygiern and the Quadi, who were subdued in the sixth century by the Sclavonians, by which it became subject to Poland. Their manners and language, as well as the Christian religion, were introduced by the conquerors. The first bishopric was founded in 966, at Schmogen, from whence it was subsequently removed to the city of Breslau.</p></body></text></TEI>