<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-03-25T20:16:56Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>every private ship the drum is beaten, or the bell is chimed every quarter of an
                hour, according as the ship is on the starboard or larboard tack. By such
                contrivances, it is never difficult to keep a fleet in very good order when sailing
                on a wind. The wind is almost always moderate, and the ships keep under a very easy
                sail. It is much more difficult when going large, and separation can be prevented
                only by the most unwearied attention. The greatest risk is the falling in with
                strange ships steering another course. But evolutions and other movements are
                frequently indispensable. The course must be changed by tacking or wearing, and
                other services must be performed. None, however, are admitted but the most probable,
                the most simple, and the most necessary.</p>
            <p>The commander-in-chief first informs the fleet by the preparatory fog signal, that he
                is about to order an evolution, and that he is to direct it by fog signals. This
                precaution is indispensable to prevent mistakes. Along with this advertising signal
                he makes the signal of the movement intended. This not only calls the attention of
                the fleet, but makes the ships prepare for the precise execution of that movement.
                The commanders of divisions repeat the advertising signal, which informs their ships
                of their situation, and the private ships beat their drums or chime their bells.
                Thus the whole ships of the fleet close a little, and become a little better
                acquainted with their mutual position. It is now understood that a movement is to be
                made precisely a quarter of an hour after the advertisement. At the expiration of
                this time, the effective signal for this movement is made by the commander-in-chief,
                and must be instantly repeated by the commanders of divisions, and then the movement
                must be made by each ship, according to the sailing and fighting instructions. This
                must be done with the utmost attention and precision, because it produces a
                prodigious change in the relative position of the ships ; and even although the good
                sense of the commander-in-chief will select such movements for accomplishing bis
                purpose as produce the smallest alterations, and the least risk of separation or
                running foul of each other ; it is still extremely difficult to avoid these
                misfortunes. To prevent this as much as possible, each ship which has executed the
                movement, or which has come on a course thwarting that of the fleet, intimates this
                by a signal properly adapted, often adding the signal of the tack on which it is now
                standing, and even its particular signal of recognizance. This is particularly
                incumbent on the flag ships and the leading ships of each division. After a
                reasonable interval, the commander-in-chief will make proper signals for bringing
                the fleet to a knowledge of their reunion in this new position.</p>
            <p>This must serve for a general account of the circumstances which must be attended to
                in framing a code of signals. The arbitrary characters in which the language is
                written must be left to the sagacity of the gentlemen of the profession. It must be
                observed, that the stratagems of war make secrecy very’ necessary. It may be of
                immense hazard if the enemy should understand our signals. In time of battle it
                might frequently frustrate our attempts to destroy them, and at all times would
                enable them to escape, or to throw us into disorder. Every commander of a squadron,
                therefore, issues private signals, suited to his particular destination ; and
                therefore it is necessary that our code of signals be susceptible of endless
                variations. This is exceedingly easy, with out any increase of their number. The
                commander needs only intimate that such and such a signal is so and so changed in
                its meaning during his command.</p>
            <p>We cannot leave this article without returning to an observation which we made almost
                in the beginning, viz. that the system of signals, or, to speak more properly, the
                manner of framing this system, has received much improvement from the gentlemen of
                the French navy, and particularly from the most ingenious thought of M. de la
                Bourdonnais,</p>
            <p>of making the signals the immediate expressions of numbers only, which numbers may be
                afterwards used to indicate any order whatever. We shall present our readers with a
                scheme or two of the manner in which this may be done for all signals, both day,
                night, and fog. This alone may be considered as a system of signals, and is equally
                applicable to every kind of information at a distance. Without detracting in the
                smallest degree from the praise due to M. de la Bourdonnais, we must observe, that
                this principle of notation is of much older date. Bishop Wilkins, in his <hi
                    rend="italic">Secret and Sιvift Messenger,</hi> expressly recommends it, and
                gives specimens of the manner of execution ; so does Dr. Hook in some of his
                proposals to the Royal Society. Gaspar Schottus also mentions it in his <hi
                    rend="italic">Technica Curiosa; </hi>and Kircher, amongst others of his <hi
                    rend="italic">curious Projects.</hi></p>
            <p>M. de la Bourdonnais’s method is as follows :—He chooses pendants for his effective
                signals, because they are the most easily displayed in the proper order. Several
                pendants, making part of one signal, may be hoisted by one halyard, being stopped on
                it at the distance of four or six feet from each other. If it be found proper to
                throw out another signal at the same time and place, they are separated by a red
                pendant without a point. His colours are chosen with judgment, being very distinctly
                recognised, and not liable to he confounded with the addressing signals appropriated
                to the different ships of the fleet. They are, for</p>
            <p>No.</p>
            <list type="ordered">
                <item>Red.</item>
                <item>White.</item>
                <item>Blue.</item>
                <item>Yellow.</item>
                <item>Red, with white tail.</item>
                <item>Red, with blue tail.</item>
                <item>White, with blue tail.</item>
                <item>White, with red tail.</item>
                <item>Blue, with yellow tail.</item>
            </list>
            <p>10. Yellow, with blue tail.</p>
            <p>Three sets of such pendants will express every number under a thousand, by hoisting
                one above the other, and reckoning the uppermost hundreds, the next below it tens,
                and the lowest units. Thus the number 643 will be expressed by a pendant red with
                blue tail, a yellow pendant below it, and a blue one below the last.</p>
            <p>This method has great advantages. The signals may be hoisted in any place where best
                seen, and therefore the signification is not affected by the derangement of the
                flagship’s masts and rigging. And by appropriating the smaller numbers to the battle
                signals, they are more simple, requiring fewer pendants.</p>
            <p>As this method requires a particular set of colours, it has its inconveniences. An
                admiral is often obliged to shift his flag, even in time of action. He cannot easily
                take the colours along with him. It is therefore better to make use of such colours
                as every private ship is provided with. One set of 11 will do, with the addition of
                three, or at most of four pendants, of singular make, to mark 100, 200, .300, 400.
                Two of these flags, one above the other, will express any number under 100, by using
                the 11th as a substitute for any flag that should be repeated. Thus the 11th flag,
                along with the flag for eight or for six, will express the number 88 or 66. Thus we
                are able to express every number below 500, and this is sufficient for a very large
                code of signals.</p>
            <p>And in order to diminish as much as possible the number of these compound signals, it
                will be proper that a number of single flag signals be preserved, and even varied by
                circumstances of position, for orders which are of very frequent occurrence, and
                which can hardly occur in situations where any obstructions are occasioned by loss
                of masts or otherwise. And farther, to avoid all chance of mistake, a particular
                signal can be added, intimating that the signals now exhibited are numeracy signals
                ; or, which is still better, all signals may be considered as numerary signals ; and
                those which we have just now called single flat signals may be set down opposite to,
                or as expressing the largest numbers of the code.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
