<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-25T20:17:46Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>lower by galleries and chambers which cover the streets. The houses and walls are for the most part built of natron or mineral soda, and rock salt mixed with sand, coated with a gypseous earth, which preserves the salt from melting. The total population of the town is from 2000 to 2500 ; that of the whole oasis is supposed to amount to 8000 souls.</p><p>The great object of interest connected with this place, is, as we have said, the ruins of what is conjectured to have been the famous temple of Ammon. They are situated a league and a half east of the town, and are called by the natives Om Beydeh. The edifice has been built in the Egyptian style of architecture. The vestiges of a triple enclosure, enormous stones lying on the ground, and masses still standing, prove it to have been a monument of the first order. The part which is in tolerable preservation is thirty feet in length, and consists of part of a gateway and two great walls, which are covered with three immense stones, measuring thirty-four feet by twenty-seven. The only apartment which has been distinctly made out is 112 feet in length ; the whole area of ruins being a rectangular space about 360 feet by 300. The decorations are observed to bear the closest resemblance to those of the Egyptian monuments ; the figures, scenes, and arrangements being entirely the same. Here are seen the identical style, cast of countenance, costumes and sacrifices, as in the monuments of Thebaid. Here is the god with the ram’s head, priests in long procession, multitudes of hieroglyphic tables, and at the entrance is sculptured in full relief the figure of Typhon, or the evil genius, about five feet in height. Nearly a mile from these ruins is situated the fountain of the sun, dedicated of old to the Ammonian deity. It is a small marsh rather than a well, extending about ninety feet in length by sixty in breadth, but is at the same time perfectly transparent. The diurnal change of temperature recorded by the father of history is quite perceptible. A temple stands near this spring, and there are other temples and lakes extending in succession towards the west. Major Rennel has employed much learning to prove that Siwah is the site of the famous temple of Ammon, and with considerable success. See his work, <hi rend="italic">The Geographical System of Herodotus Examined and Explained.</hi> &amp;c. vol. ii. p. 230.</p><p>SIX <hi rend="smallcaps">Islands,</hi> small islands in the eastern seas, near the north coast of Java. Long. 110. 49. E. Lat. 6. 36. S.</p><p>SIXTH, <hi rend="italic">in Music.</hi> (See <hi rend="smallcaps">Interval.</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Music</hi>.)</p><p>SIXTUS V., <hi rend="smallcaps">Pope,</hi> was born on the 13th of December 1521, in La Marca, a village in the seigniory of Montalto. His father, Francis Peretti, was a gardener, and his mother a servant maid. He was their eldest child, and was called Felix. At the age of nine he was hired out to an inhabitant of the village to keep sheep ; but disobliging his master, he was soon afterwards degraded to be keeper of the hogs. He was engaged in this employment when father Michael Angelo Selleri, a Franciscan friar, asked the road to Ascoli, where he was going to preach. Young Felix conducted him thither, and struck the father so much with his conversation and eagerness for knowledge, that he recommended him to the fraternity to which he had come. Accordingly he was received amongst them, invested with the habit of a lay brother, and placed under the sacristan, to assist in sweeping the church, lighting the candles, and other offices of that nature, for which he was to be taught the responses, and the rudiments of grammar. His progress in learning was so surprising, that at the age of fourteen he was thought qualified to begin his noviciate, and was admitted the year following to make his profession.</p><p>He pursued his studies with such unwearied assiduity, that he was soon reckoned equal to the best disputants. He was ordained priest in 1545, when he assumed the name of father Montalto; soon afterwards he took his doctor’s degree, and was appointed professor of theology at Sienna. It was then that he so effectually recommended himself to Cardinal Carpi, and his secretary Bossius, that they ever remained his steady friends. Meanwhile the severity and obstinacy of his temper incessantly engaged him in disputes with his monastic brethren. His reputation for eloquence, which was now spread about this time over Italy, gained him some new friends. Amongst these were the Colonna family, and father Ghisilieri, by whose recommendation he was appointed inquisitor-general at Venice ; but he exercised that office with so much severity, that he was obliged to flee precipitately from that city. Upon this he went to Rome, where he was made procurator-general of his order, and soon afterwards accompanied Cardinal Buon Compagnon into Spain, as a chaplain and consultor to the inquisition. There he was treated with great respect, and liberal offers were made to induce him to continue in Spain, which, however, he could not be prevailed on to accept.</p><p>In the meantime news were brought to Madrid that Pius IV. was dead, and that father Ghisilieri, who had been made Cardinal Alexandrino by Paul IV. had succeeded him under the name of Pius V. These tidings filled Montalto with joy, and not without reason, for he was immediately invested by the pontiff with new dignities. He was made general of his order, bishop of St. Agatha, soon afterwards raised to the dignity of cardinal, and received a pension. About this time he was employed by the pope to draw up the bill of excommunication against queen Elizabeth.</p><p>He began now to cast his eyes upon the papacy; and, in order to obtain it, formed and executed a plan of hypocrisy with unparalleled constancy and success. He became humble, patient, and affable. He changed his dress, his air, his words, and his actions, so completely, that his most intimate friends declared him a new’ man. Never was there such an absolute victory gained over the passions ; never was a fictitious character so long maintained, nor the foibles of human nature so artfully concealed. He courted the ambassadors of every foreign power, but attached himself to the interests of none ; nor did he accept a single favour that would have laid him under any peculiar obligation. He had formerly treated his relations with the greatest tenderness, but he now changed his behaviour altogether. When his brother Anthony came to visit him, he lodged him in an inn, and sent him home next day, charging him to inform his family that he was now dead to his relations and the world.</p><p>When Pius V. died in 1572, he entered the conclave with the other cardinals, but seemed altogether indifferent about the election, and never left his apartments except to his devotion. When solicited to join any party, he declined it, declaring that he was of no consequence, and that he would leave the choice of a pope entirely to persons of greater knowledge and experience. When Cardinal Boon Compagnon, who assumed the name of Gregory XIII. was elected, Montalto assured him that he never wished for any thing so much in his life, and that he would always remember his goodness, and the favours he had conferred on him in Spain. But the new pope treated him with the greatest contempt, and deprived him of his pension. The cardinals also, deceived by his artifices, paid him no greater respect, and used to call him, by way of ridicule, the Roman beast, the ass of La Marca.</p><p>He now assumed all the infirmities of old age ; his head hung down upon his shoulders ; he tottered as he walked, and supported himself on a staff. His voice became feeble, and was often interrupted by a cough so exceedingly severe, that it seemed every moment to threaten his dissolution. He interfered in no public transactions, but spent his whole time in acts of devotion and benevolence. Mean time he constantly employed the ablest spies, who brought him intelligence of every particular</p><p>When Gregory XIII. died in 1585, he entered the con-</p></body></text></TEI>