<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-25T20:16:46Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>of Ochus king of Persia. That monarch having come against them with an army on account of their rebellion, the city was betrayed by its king ; upon which the wretched inhabitants, seized with despair, set fire to their houses, and forty thousand, with their wives and children, perished in the flames. It is forty-five miles west from Damascus. E. long. 36. 5. N. lat. 37.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">SIDUS,Georgium,</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Astronomy,</hi> a new primary planet, discovered by Dr. Herschel in the year 1781. By most foreign, and even by some British philosophers, it is known by the name of <hi rend="italic">Herschel,</hi> in honour of the discoverer. As the other planets are distinguished by marks or characters, the planet Herschel is distinguished by an H, the initial letter of the discoverer’s name, and a cross to shew that it is a Christian planet.</p><p>SIEBENBURGEN. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Transylvania.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">SIENNA </hi>or<hi rend="smallcaps"> Siena,</hi> a district of Italy, still called a duchy, though now a part of the grand duchy of Tuscany. It is mostly situated on the Apennines, and was an independent state, till it was subdued and united with Tuscany in 1557. The capital is the city of that name, on the great road from Florence to Rome. It is surrounded with walls, and, when approached from Rome, has a magnificent appearance, but, on the side towards Florence, the view of it is hidden by woods and gardens. The city is old and rather ill built, but it contains many fine palaces belonging to noble families. It is the see of an archbishop, the cathedral, 330 feet in length, is celebrated for its fine cupola. There is a spacious market-place, with a council house and theatre, that are ornamental. It contains twenty-three churches, several of which are adorned with the finest paintings in fresco. The university, founded in 1321, once enjoyed the greatest fame of any in Italy, but at present has not more than two hundred and sixty students, though it still retains its museum, an anatomical theatre, a library, and other similar institutions. Its manufactures are a few woollen cloths, hats, strings for musical instruments, paper, and objects formed of marble or of ivory. Its population is 24,500 persons. Lat. 43. 22. Long. 11. 5. E.</p><p>SIERRA LEONE, a colony of Great Britain, situated on the western coast of Africa. Lat.8.10. Long. 12. 30. It is a peninsula, bounded on the north by the river called sierra Leone, on the south and west by the sea at Calmont creek, and on the east by a line up the Calmont to the Watslod creek, and down this last to the Dunce, which is indeed a part of the Sierra Leone river. These boundaries enclose a tract of country extending eighteen miles from north to south, and twelve miles from east to west ; but there is an additional tract of country adjoining Sierra Leone, which was ceded to Great Britain by an African chief in 1819. sierra Leone, as its name indicates, is a mountainous tract of country, but with numerous intervening valleys. The heights are covered to their summit with lofty forests, giving to the distant scenery a rich and romantic appearance. The territory on the north side of the river is, however, low and level. Numerous streams descend from the hills, which collect into a basin called the Bay of Franca, celebrated as a watering-place. The sierra Leone is more of an estuary than a river ; it is twenty miles in length, by ten in breadth, at its mouth. The Rokelle affords a water communication for some distance into the interior. The range of the thermometer at Sierra Leone is very slight, and the average heat throughout the year is 82<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. The rains continue for six months, and the torrents which descend from the mountains deluge the plains beneath. The mountains in the vicinity of Free Town, the capital, have now been cleared and cultivated, which has greatly added to the salubrity of the climate. Indeed, the settlement is now stated in the medical reports to be as healthy for Europeans as any other tropical country, so that it is no longer the pestiferous charnel-house which it was formerly considered. The edible fruits of Sierra Leone are</p><p>numerous and luscious, including pine apples, superior in flavour to those cultivated in England;the baobab, or monkey bread, a valuable tree ; oranges, plantains, bananas, limes, and many others. The country is prolific in various precious products of the soil, besides fruits. The animal kingdom is very abundant, comprising many species of antelopes, monkeys, and other denizens of a tropical country.</p><p>Free Town, the capital of the colony, is built upon the south side of the Sierra Leone river, and at the northern extremity of the peninsula. Immediately in front of the town, the river forms a bay, where there is good and commodious anchorage for vessels of all classes, and timber ships of considerable size proceed with facility nearly twenty miles higher up the stream, for the purpose of taking in their cargoes. The town is beautifully situated on an inclined plane, at the foot of some hills, on which stand the fort and other public buildings, that overlook it and the roads ; whence there is a fine prospect of the town rising in the form of an amphitheatre from the water’s edge, above which it is elevated seventy feet. It is regularly laid out into streets, stretching three quarters of a mile in length, intersected by others at right angles, and parallel with the river. The buildings are commodious, and substantially built of stone, which at once contribute to the beauty of the place, and to the health and comfort of the inhabitants. Numbers of cocoa-nut, orange, lime, and banana trees, are dispersed all over the town, imparting to it a peculiarly picturesque appearance. The Madeira and Teneriffe vines flourish well in the gardens. Nearly all our garden vegetables are raised there ; and what with yams, cassada, and pompions, there is rarely any want of vegetable products for the table. There are good meat, poultry, and fish markets and almost every article of housekeeping can be procured at the shops of the British merchants. The population of the capital may be estimated at 10,000.</p><p>Throughout the peninsula, several villages have been formed, viz., Leicester, founded in 1809 ; Regent, in 1812; Gloucester, in 1816; Kissey and Leopold, in 1817 ; Charlotte, Wilberforce, and Bothwell, in 1818; Kent, York, Wellington, and Waterloo, in 1819. These villages are generally situated in different parts of the mountain, but all are connected by good roads with each other, and with the capital. The two Banana islands, situated to the south-west of Free Town, were ceded to the British government in 1819, by a family who receive an annual payment tor them. The total population of sierra Leone is about 35,000, of whom not more than 200 are Europeans ; the remainder are captured or liberated slaves, or their descendants, together with some native Africans. Many of the colonists, besides the Europeans, possess considerable wealth. The total number of slaves emancipated in sierra Leone, between June 1819 and January 1833, was 27,697. Some of these, no doubt, retain their habits of indolence, but in general the freed African relishes liberty, and is grateful for the boon conferred on him, and several, by their industry and economy, are said to have acquired property amounting to L.1000 sterling. There are public schools in each parish, and from 3000 to 4000 children attend them. A large portion of the colony are enjoying, and all have access to, the means of moral and religious instruction. Upwards of one-fourth are regular attendants on the public ordinances of religion. They have built for themselves various and expensive places of worship ; some of them are employed as spiritual instructors of their sable brethren ; and all together, considering its circumstances, this negro colony is composed of an orderly and well-conducted people. Agriculture has not, indeed, been sufficiently prosecuted hitherto, but matters will improve in this respect when population increases, and presses upon the means of supply. The soil is in part very fertile, and more might be rendered so by clearing.</p><p>The trade of this settlement is as follows : For the year</p></body></text></TEI>