<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-03-25T20:19:07Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>valley of the Leven, in which Smollett first saw the light, is surpassed by no other
                spot in our island, either for the grandeur of its scenery, or for the venerable
                associations with which it is connected. Nor was the ground which had been dignified
                by the tread of Wallace, Bruce, Napier, and Buchanan, dishonoured by the steps of
                Smollett.</p>
            <p>From the grammar-school of Dunbarton, in which he had imbibed the rudiments of
                classical learning, Smollett was transferred to the University of Glasgow, where he
                prosecuted his more advanced studies with application and success. He was afterwards
                bound an apprentice to Mr. John Gordon, an eminent medical practitioner in that
                city. His elder brother James had adopted the profession of arms, an example which
                he was ambitious of following; but the old knight probably illustrated the
                advantages of the study of physic by reasoning which it would have been vain to
                controvert. When the young student had attained his eighteenth year, his grandfather
                died, without having made any adequate provision for the children of bis youngest
                son. For this omission, his descendant furnished him with a niche in <hi
                    rend="italic">Roderick Random,</hi> more conspicuous than desirable.</p>
            <p>The term of his apprenticeship having expired in his nineteenth year, and being now
                thrown upon his own resources, Smollett proceeded to London, where he attracted the
                notice of Lord Lyttelton. He had carried with him his tragedy of <hi rend="italic"
                    >The Regicide,</hi> a juvenile performance of uncommon merit, but indifferently
                adapted to the purpose of representation. The various efforts which he ineffectually
                used to bring his play upon the stage, are detailed with indignant prolixity in the
                preface to that production, which he sent to the press some years afterwards, with a
                view of heaping confusion upon the lukewarm patronage of Lyttelton, and upon the
                shuffling evasions of Garrick. The patron and the manager were visited with many
                other tokens of his displeasure ; but he lived to repent of the severe retribution
                which he had exacted for trivial wrongs, and made honourable mention of both in his
                History of England.</p>
            <p>Thwarted in his expectations of earning fame and profit as a writer for the stage,
                Smollett was glad to accept the situation of surgeon’s mate on board the Cumberland.
                That vessel, an eighty-gun ship, belonged to the armament which was bound to the
                West Indies, to join the fleet under the command of Admiral Vernon. Of the
                disastrous expedition against Carthagena, Smollett inserted an animated narrative in
                    <hi rend="italic">Roderick Random,</hi> and afterwards published a more detailed
                account in the <hi rend="italic">compendium of Voyages. </hi>When the discomfited
                squadrons returned to Jamaica, he quitted the service in disgust, and fixed his
                residence on the island. With Miss Lascelles, a fascinating West Indian, he there
                formed an acquaintance, which afterwards ripened into a matrimonial union. In 1746
                he returned to London, which then resounded with acclamations occasioned by the
                victory at Culloden. With these were mingled some expressions of indignation at the
                atrocities inflicted by the royal army upon the helpless families of the insurgents.
                The voice of Smollett swelled the weaker cry, and he produced his pathetic ode, <hi
                    rend="italic">The Tears of Scotland. </hi>During the same year was published,
                    <hi rend="italic">Advice, a Satire.</hi> His next literary effort was <hi
                    rend="italic">Alceste, an Opera,</hi> which he wrote at the suggestion of Mr.
                Rich of Covent Garden Theatre. In consequence of some dispute with that patentee,
                the piece was withdrawn, and has never appeared in print. In 1747 he published <hi
                    rend="italic">Reproof,</hi> a second part of his former satirical production.
                The versification of these poems is sufficiently harmonious, and they abound with
                impetuous</p>
            <p>invective ; but the rage of the satirist is without dignity, and rabid, without being
                infectious to readers of the present day. About this period he married Miss
                Lascelles, who was possessed of a small estate in the island of Jamaica ; a
                precarious species of property, from which her husband appears to have derived
                little or no ultimate benefit.</p>
            <p>In the year 1748, appeared <hi rend="italic">The Adventures of Roderick Random.</hi>
                Fielding had already evinced himself a noble follower of Cervantes, and Smollett now
                stood forth, a no less worthy disciple of Le Sage. It must be owned that in this,
                and in all the other novels of Smollett, humour frequently appears in very loose
                attire. These scenes, however, like sheet-lightning, are alarming, but perfectly
                innocuous. The solemn depravity of Rousseau is more dangerous than the ludicrous
                indecorum of Smollett. In 1749, <hi rend="italic">The Regicide</hi> was published by
                subscription. During the same year Smollett took the degree of M.D., in what
                University has not been ascertained. In 1750 he went to Paris, where he is supposed
                to have occupied himself in composing <hi rend="italic">The Adventures of Peregrine
                    Pickle,</hi> which were published in</p>
            <list type="ordered">
                <item>This admirable novel is disfigured by the introduction of an impertinent
                    episode, in which are detailed, with unrelenting minuteness, the tedious
                    intrigues of Lady Vane ; who is said to have rewarded Smollett handsomely for
                    the drudgery of compiling that durable record of her infamy. To compensate for
                    this blemish, and for some rash sallies of humour, <hi rend="italic">Peregrine
                        Pickle</hi> is an absolute mine of character and adventure. The
                    entertainment prepared by the learned physician, in the manner of the ancients,
                    is perhaps the most irresistible piece of pleasantry that w as ever devised by a
                    ludicrous fancy. In his heroes and heroines, Smollett is not happy. For Random
                    we have no respect; for Pickle we have no esteem ; and Narcissa and Emilia are
                    only the objects of appetite. Since the days of Tom Bowling and the Commodore,
                    we have seen many sailors in print, who display an accurate and profound
                    knowledge of technical <hi rend="italic">minutiae;</hi> but their humour, if
                    they have any, will not pass muster ashore, the medium through which it is
                    conveyed being to uninstructed ears a mere succession of unintelligible
                    gibberish. And these modem tars have all a striking family likeness to each
                    other, with the exception of some sentimental rope-haulers of the American
                    school, who are evidently monsters of the imagination. But each of Smollett’s
                    seamen, though drawn to the life, exhibits the strongest idiosyncrasy of
                    character, and converses in a dialect which can be readily understood by those
                    who have never seen a ship.@@<hi rend="superscript">1</hi></item>
            </list>
            <p>The next production of Smollett’s pen was “ An Essay on the External Use of Water, in
                a letter to Dr.—;</p>
            <p>with particular remarks upon the present method of using the Mineral Waters at Bath,
                in Somersetshire ; and a plan for rendering them more safe, agreeable, and
                efficacious.”</p>
            <list type="ordered">
                <item>4to. At the period of this publication, Smollett resided at Bath, where he
                    solicited professional employment ; but the reputation of the satirist
                    effectually marred the prospects of the physician. Despairing of success in bis
                    profession, Dr. Smollett now hired a house at Chelsea, where he entirely devoted
                    himself to literary pursuits. The first fruits of his retirement were, <hi
                        rend="italic">The Adventures of Ferdinand count Fathom,</hi> which appeared
                    in 1753. The author’s object in this production is, to set up the principal
                    character “ as a beacon for the benefit of the inexperienced and unwary.” This
                    personage is as much below, as one of Richardson’s heroes is above, the standard
                    of general nature. Few men are so virtuous or depraved as to have much sympathy
                    with either ; and it may very reasonably be ques-</item>
            </list>
            <p><hi rend="superscript">@@@1</hi> The incident of Tom Pipes’s concealing in his shoe
                his master’s letter to Emilia, it is curious to trace to the following passage in
                Ovid’s Art of Love ; which has not escaped ιhe laborious research of Hugo, <hi
                    rend="italic">De prima Scribendi Origine,</hi> p. 154.</p>
            <p>Cum possit solea chartas celare ligatae,</p>
            <p>Et vincto blandas sub pede ferre nous.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
