<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-25T20:17:19Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>is ascribed by many authors to the vast quantity of mulberry trees there cultivated In 1130, Roger, king of Sicily, having conquered many portions of the Morea, transported the white mulberry into his own kingdom, along with a supply of silk worms, and of artizans who understood their cultivation, and the manufacture of their natural product. About the year 1493, in the reign of Charles the Eighth, some nobles who had accompanied that Prince into Italy, brought the mulberry from Naples, and planted it in the environs of Montélimart. Not many years have gone by since those parent trees, the source of so rich a branch of commercial industry to France, were exhibited with an almost religious veneration. The mulberry was cultivated not only in the south of France, but Henry the Fourth brought a great many to Paris, which he planted in the gardens of the Tuilleries, where an establishment was founded for the rearing of the worms, and the preparation of their silk. No vestige of this plantation now remains.</p><p>It was long supposed that the cultivation of the white mulberry required a high temperature, but the contrary is proved by the fact of its thriving well in so many northern provinces of Germany. Even in Russia it is reared with considerable success. In France, however, it is not raised in large quantities with a view to the feeding of silk-worms, except in the central and southern provinces, as far north as the environs of Lyons. Government does not seem to have held out any encouragement to its extension, otherwise we doubt not that both the tree and caterpillar might be more extensively and abundantly spread over the more northern departments. The white mulberry is by no means nice in regard to the constituent character of its soil, and it is known to flourish in a great variety of situations. At the same time, the nature both of soil and situation seems to exercise considerable influence over the produce of the caterpillars which feed upon its leaves; the silk being finer, ampler, and more resistant, in proportion as the plant is successfully cultivated in a dry and rather elevated position. In the south of France it is customary to cut off all the medium-sized branches every year, with a view to facilitate the production of a greater number of young shoots, these bearing the largest and most numerous leaves. The leaves of the black mulberry <hi rend="italic">(Mortis nigra),</hi> and in general those of all the other species of the genus, are adapted to the nourishment of the silk-worm. But not only are they apparently less grateful to their taste, but they actually produce a silk much inferior both in quantity and quality.</p><p>We have said that the silk-worm cultivated in Europe is the same as that which produces the greater proportion of the Chinese manufacture. But in Bengal and other parts of India, valuable silk is procured from the cocoons of other species of moth. The first of these is described by Dr. Roxburgh under the title of <hi rend="italic">Phalœna paphia, and</hi> occurs in such abundance over many parts of Bengal, and the adjoining provinces, as to have afforded to the natives, from time immemorial, an abundant supply of a very durable, though coarse, and dark-coloured silk, called <hi rend="italic">Tussch,</hi> much used by the Brahmins, and other sects of Hindoos. This species, however, cannot be domesticated; so the hill people go into the jungles, and when they perceive the dung of the caterpillars under a tree, they immediately search for them among the branches, and carry off w hat they require. These they distribute on the Asseen trees <hi rend="italic">(Terminalia alata glabra</hi> of Roxb.), and as long as they continue in the caterpillar state, the Pariahs guard them from birds by day, and from bats by night. The natural food of this species is the <hi rend="italic">Byer</hi> tree of the Hindoos, called <hi rend="italic">Rhamnus jujuba</hi> by botanists. The Jaroo cocoons are produced from a rare variety of the kind just mentioned. This tusseh silk-worm moth appears to be synonymous with <hi rend="italic">Bombyx mylitta </hi>of Fabricius,and is figured by Drury.@@<hi rend="superscript">1</hi> The Arrindy silk-worms, however, belong to an entirely different species, <hi rend="italic">Phalæna cynthia</hi> of the last named author.@@<hi rend="superscript">2</hi> It seems to be peculiar to two districts in the interior of Bengal, viz. Runpore and Dinagepore, where it is reared in a domestic state. The food of this kind of silk-worm consists entirely of the leaves of the common <hi rend="italic">Ricinus,</hi> or Palma Christi, which the natives call <hi rend="italic">Arrindy,</hi> and hence the name by which the insect is itself distinguished. The cocoons in general are about a couple of inches in length, three inches in circumference, and pointed at both ends. They are of a white or yellowish colour, and their texture is extremely soft and delicate. The filament, indeed, is so extremely fine, that the silk cannot be wound off, but must be spun like cotton. The yarn is wove into a kind of coarse white cloth, of a seemingly loose texture, but of such extreme durability, that the file of one person seldom suffices to wear out a garment of it ; so that the same piece frequently descends from parent to child. It must always be washed in cold water.@@<hi rend="superscript">3</hi></p><p>The only other species with which we are acquainted is that alluded to by Mr. Arthur Young, in an extract of a letter published in the <hi rend="italic">Annals of Agriculture,</hi> It has been introduced into our Eastern possessions for a considerable number of years. “ We have obtained,” says the writer of the letter, “ a monthly silk-worm from China, which I have reared with my own hands, and in twenty-five days have had the cocoons in my basins, and by the twenty-ninth or thirty- first day, a new progeny feeding in my trays. This makes it a mine to whoever would undertake the cultivation of it.”</p><p>The practice of rearing silk worms in this country is usually followed rather as an amusing occupation than for purposes of gain. The female moth is induced to lay her eggs upon sheets of paper, to which they adhere by a natural viscosity. The period of hatching may be hastened or retarded by a higher or lower temperature, and the chief point for the breeder to bear in mind is, that the worms should not make their appearance till an abundance of natural food is near at hand. The eggs are at first of a very pale hue, but such as are to produce worms speedily become of a bluish grey colour ; the unproductive ones continuing of a pale yellow. As there are tricks in all trades, the foreign dealers often favour their old useless eggs with a wash in dark-coloured muddy wine, which gives them for a time a deceptive healthy aspect. A stove-room, or other apartment, with a temperature of 64° will suffice for the hatching of eggs, and the heat may afterwards be raised with advantage a few degrees every other day, for about ten days, but not so as to exceed about 80<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. They will, however, thrive well enough in summer in any comfortably kept apartment, though a continuous warmth by night as well as by day is of great advantage. Whatever broods are hatched at the same period, should be kept together, and those of different ages ought never to be fed in the same trays.</p><p>The best and simplest apparatus for keeping silk worms is that p∣oposed by Mr. Swayne. It consists of an open quadrangular wooden frame, about four feet two inches high, provided with eight uncovered slides or drawers a few inches apart from each other, and which, moving in a groove or ledge, can easily be shifted out or in. The upper slide is made of paper, and is devoted to the reception of the newly hatched worms, which it is desirable to feed at first with young and delicate leaves, chopped into small pieces. The flooring of the second and third slides is made of catgut, the reticulations being about the tenth part of an inch asunder. In these the worms are placed during what may be called the second and third stages. The five remaining slides are made of wicker-work or netting, and in them the insects are distributed “ fewer and far between,” as they increase in size. Beneath every drawer except the uppermost,</p><p><hi rend="superscript">@@@,</hi> Illustrations of Natural History, ii. tab. 5.	</p><p><hi rend="superscript">@@@,</hi> Ibid. tab. 6.</p><p>@@@* See Account of the Tusseh and Arrindy silk worms of Bengal, by William Roxburgh, M.D. Linn- Trans, viii. 33; and British India (in Edin. Cab. Library), iii. 154.</p></body></text></TEI>