<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-25T20:18:23Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>where the son was born, at Killieagh, on the 19th of April 1660. At a very early period, he displayed a strong inclination for natural history; and this propensity being encouraged by a suitable education, he employed those hours which young people generally lose by pursuing low and trifling amusements, in the study of nature, and contemplating her works. When about sixteen, he was attacked by a spitting of blood, which threatened to be attended with considerable danger, and which interrupted the regular course of his application for three years. He had, however, already learned enough of physic to know that a malady of this kind was not to be suddenly removed, and be prudently abstained from wine and other liquors that were likely to increase it.</p><p>By strictly observing this severe regimen, which he in some measure continued ever afterwards, he was enabled to prolong his life beyond the ordinary bounds; being an example of the truth of his own favourite maxim, that sobriety, temperance, and moderation, are the best and most powerful preservatives that nature has granted to mankind. As soon as he recovered from this infirmity, he resolved to perfect himself in the different branches of physic, which was the profession he had made choice of; and with this view lie repaired to London, where he hoped to receive that assistance which he could not find in his own country.</p><p>On his arrival in the metropolis, he entered himself as a pupil of Stafforth, an excellent chemist, bred under the illustrious Stahl ; and by his instructions he gained a perfect knowledge of the composition and preparation of the different kinds of medicines then in use. At the same time, he studied botany at the garden at Chelsea, assiduously attended the public lectures of anatomy and physic, and in short neglected nothing that he thought likely to prove serviceable to him in his future practice. His principal merit, however, was his knowledge of natural history ; and it was this part of his character which introduced him early to the acquaintance of Mr. Boyle and Mr. Ray, two of the most eminent naturalists of that age. His intimacy with these distinguished characters continued as long as they lived; and as he was careful to communicate to them every object of curiosity that attracted his attention, the observations which he occasionally made often excited their admiration and obtained their applause.</p><p>After studying four years at London with unremitting severity, Mr. Sloane determined to visit foreign countries for further improvement. In this view he set out for France in the company of two other students, and having crossed to Dieppe, proceeded to Paris. In the way thither they were elegantly entertained by M. Lemery the elder; and in return Mr. Sloane presented that eminent chemist with a specimen of four different kinds of phosphorus, of which, upon the credit of other writers, Μ. Lemery had treated in his book of chemistry, though he bad never seen any of them. At Paris Mr. Sloane lived as he had done in London. He attended the hospitals, heard the lectures of Tournefort, De Verney, and other eminent masters; visited all the literati, who received him with particular marks of esteem ; and employed himself wholly in study.</p><p>From Paris he proceeded to Montpellier ; and, being furnished with letters of recommendation from Μ. Tournefort to M. Chirac, then chancellor of that university, he found easy access, through his means, to all the learned men of the province, particularly to M. Magnol, whom he always accompanied in bis botanical excursions in the environs of that city, where he beheld with pleasure and admiration the spontaneous productions of nature, and learned under his instructions to class them in a proper manner.</p><p>Having here found an ample field for contemplation, which was entirely suited to his taste, he took leave of his two companions, whom a curiosity of a different kind led into Italy. After spending a whole year in collecting plants, he travelled through Languedoc with the same design ; and passing through Toulouse and Bordeaux, returned to Paris, where he made a short stay. About the end of the year 1684 he set out for England, with an intention of settling there as a physician. On his arrival in London, he made it his first business to visit his two illustrious friends Mr. Ray and Mr. Boyle, in order to communicate to them the discoveries which he had made in his travels. The latter be found at home, but the former had retired to Essex; to which place Mr.Sloane transmitted a great variety of plants and seeds, which Mr. Ray has described in his <hi rend="italic">History of Plants,</hi> and for which he makes a proper acknowledgment.</p><p>About the year 1706 Sloane became acquainted with Sydenham, who soon contracted so warm an affection for him that he took him into his house, and recommended him in the strongest manner to his patients. He had not been long in London before he was proposed by Dr. Martin Lister as a candidate to be admitted a fellow of the Royal society, on the 26th of November 1684; and being approved, he was elected on the 21st of January following.</p><p>In 1685 he communicated some curiosities to the Society; and in July the same year he was a candidate for the office of assistant secretary, but without success, as he was obliged to give way to the superior interest of his competitor Dr. Halley. On the 12th of April 1687, he was chosen a fellow of the College of Physicians in London ; and the same year his friend and fellow traveller Dr. Tancred Robinson, having mentioned to the society the plant called the star of the earth as a remedy newly discovered for the bite of a mad dog, Dr. Sloane acquainted them that this virtue of the plant was to be found in a book called De Grey’s <hi rend="italic">Farriery;</hi> and that he knew a man who had cured will) it twenty couple of dogs. This observation he made on the l3th of July, and on the 12th of September following he embarked at Portsmouth for Jamaica with the duke of Albemarle, who had been appointed governor of that island. The doctor attended his grace in quality of physician, and arrived at Jamaica on the 19th of December following. Here a new field was opened for fresh discoveries in natural productions; but the world would have been deprived of the fruits of them, had not Sloane, by incredible application, converted, as we may say, his minutes into hours. The duke of Albemarle died soon after he landed, and the duchess determined to return to England whenever an answer should be received to the letter which she had sent to court on that melancholy occasion. As he could not think of leaving her grace in her distress, whilst the rest of her retinue were preparing for their departure, he improved it in making collections of natural curiosities; so that, though his whole stay in Jamaica was not above fifteen months, he brought together such a prodigious number of plants, that on bis return to England, Mr. Ray was astonished that one man could procure in one island, and in so short a space, so vast a variety.</p><p>On his arrival in London, he applied himself to the practice of his profession, and soon became so eminent, that he was chosen physician to Christ’s Hospital on the 17th October 1694 ; and this office he held till the year 1730, when, on account of his great age and infirmities, he found it necessary to resign. It is somewhat singular, and redounds much to the doctor’s honour, that though he received the emoluments of his office punctually, because he would not lay down a precedent which might hurt his successors, yet be constantly applied the money to the relief of those who were the greatest objects of compassion in the hospital, that it might never be said he enriched himself by giving health to the poor. He had been elected secretary to the Royal Society on the 30th of November 1693; and upon this occasion he revived the publication of the <hi rend="italic">Philosophical Transactions. </hi>which had for some time been neglected. He continued to be the editor of this work till the year 1712; and the vo-</p></body></text></TEI>