<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-25T20:16:23Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>yards from him. It is usual, however, to allow the hare a chance of escape, by starting her before firing at her ; it is accounted unsportsmanlike to kill puss on her seat. In January, hares are found on fallows, marshes, or in pastures, or in or near to gardens.</p><p>The shooter should fire well forward at a hare, and not too high. He should not fire at a long distance, as the probability of his wounding her would be greater than that of killing her. If running direct from him, a hare should not be fired at, unless within twenty-five paces from the gun, or she will often run off, though severely wounded in the hind-quarters. A beater will render essential service to the shooter in quest of hares, in the early part of the season ; the beater walks on the contrary side of the hedge to the shooter, and a few yards in advance, so that the hare, to avoid the former, jumps out on the side of the latter. When beating hedges in the vicinity of covers, the shooter should take care to place himself on that side nearest the covers. When shooting at the edge of a cover, if the hare fired at is not quite deprived of the use of her legs, it would be advisable to fire again immediately, for should she crawl through the hedge, the chances would be against her being retrieved.</p><p><hi rend="italic">The Rabbit.</hi> Rabbits are alternately deemed game and vermin. They are sometimes shot for sport, sometimes for profit, and sometimes on account of the mischief they do to trees and other vegetation. They sometimes seat themselves all day long, after the manner of hares, but more frequently they remain the greater portion of the day in their burrows. As they are shy of approach, and run under ground on the least alarm, the shooter frequently finds it expedient to hide himself at a little distance from the warren, and wait until they come out. Where rabbits are numerous, as in most warrens they are, some will be continually playing within a few yards of the entrance of the burrows, and when found in such situations (for they are very tenacious of life), they should be struck very hard, or they will contrive to crawl, or rather roll into their earths, before the shooter can pick them up. It is astonishing what efforts they will make to escape, though three legs be broken, when near to the entrance of a burrow. It is of little use firing at them when they are more than twenty paces distant from the gun. Rabbits afford more what are termed snap-shots than any other game, as they are mostly found in or near to plantations, or amongst brambles, hollies, gorse or deep fern, in places of extreme difficulty. It requires a quick eye and steady hand to stop a rabbit running across furrows, or over uneven ground. Rabbits for sale, or when destroyed as vermin, are oftener taken by means of ferrets and nets, than killed by the gun. A short gun, having a large bore, and charged heavily with powder, and a small quantity of No. 4 shot, is best for rabbit shooting. It would be well that a companion or servant should lead a dog in a slip—a terrier is as good as any—to be loosed the moment the gun is fired ; thus many a rabbit will be secured, that would else have run into its hole. When earthed, it frequently happens that a rabbit is not able to crawl more than three or four feet deep from the surface, where it dies, when it may be recovered by thrusting a bramble down the hole, and twisting it so as to entangle the rabbit ; but a more certain method, if the rabbit is not too far down, is to screw the worm of the ramrod into its body, and so drag it out, as a cartridge is drawn from the barrel of a gun The best time for rabbit shooting is in the evening, or during sunshine just after a shower, when great numbers of the rabbits venture from their burrows.</p><p><hi rend="italic">The Bustard.</hi> The bustard is a rare but valuable acquisition to the game-bag. As it cannot be approached unless the shooter takes advantage of some adventitious circumstances, it is seldom an object of pursuit to the sportsman. Bustard shooting commences on the first of September, and ends on the first of March.</p><p><hi rend="italic">The Snipe.</hi> There are three kinds of snipes, viz. the solitary or double snipe, the full or whole snipe, and the jack or half snipe. The last is considered to be scarcely worth powder and shot ; it is the full snipe which principally engages the shooter’s attention. We have before given directions for shooting this bird. “ The common or full snipe is a shy bird when in company, but when alone will allow the shooter to approach within a dozen paces of it before it springe. When it does spring, however, it moves with a velocity that defies the epithet <hi rend="italic">slow !</hi> It is best to shoot as soon as possible. The shooter will bring down a snipe with much less difficulty at from fifteen to twenty paces than at any other distance. The aim is thus taken before the bird begins to make its cross flights, and before it has attained its full speed. The irregularity of its flight is of little consequence during the first and second twirling, before the bird is safely on the wing, since its flight is then comparatively tardy. But let the snipe fly ten yards from whence it sprang,—let it be, for instance, twenty-five paces distant from the gun, it is then at the top of its speed, and in the very midst of its sidelong, elliptical gyrations, and more than a match for the majority of shooters, especially if the day be windy. A snipe killed at fifteen or twenty paces distance, with No. 7 shot, the aim being true, will be struck by twenty or thirty pellets, but the chances are more than twenty to one against the aim being true. The snipe, when struck, is generally three or four inches from the centre of the cone which the shot forms as it flies, which is very different from being in the exact centre. A section of the body of a snipe does not present a surface as large as that of a penny-piece. If any person will fire at a target at fifteen yards distance, he will find that a snipe would not be cut to pieces even at that distance, unless it chanced to be precisely in the centre of the charge as thrown. When speaking of a snipe presenting no larger a surface as a mark than a penny-piece, we of course mean a snipe flying directly from the shooter. It would be imprudent to shoot at a snipe flying across at less than twenty-five paces distance, as it then presents more than double the surface of one going straight from the shooter Thirty paces is the distance we should prefer for a cross or oblique shot. At thirty, or even at twenty-five yards, unless the barrel throws shot remarkably close, there are interstices in the charge as thrown, in which a snipe would escape untouched. Provided the flight of a snipe were equally steady at all distances, and that in every instance the shooter could choose</p></body></text></TEI>