<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-25T20:17:35Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>the two parties lead them to unite in the spoliation of the helpless villager.</p><p>The principal articles of domestic produce, which are exported chiefly from Kurachee, are rice, ghee, hides, shark fins, potash, saltpetre, assafoetida, bdellium, madder, frankincense, Tatta-cloths, indigo, oleaginous and other seeds. From Mooltan, and the countries to the northward, are imported for re-exportation, alum, musk, horses, Kashmeer shawls, dried fruit, diamonds, lapis lazuli, turquoise, and other precious stones and gums. Other imports are tin, iron, lead, steel, ivory, European manufactures, sandal and other scented woods, from the south of India ; swords and carpets from Khorasan and Candal&gt;ar, silk and other articles from the Persian Gulf. The merchants who are settled here from Mooltan are the principal traders, and the wealthiest part of the community. The exports from Sinde to Bombay consist of sharks’ fins and flesh, bdellium, ghee, potash, saltpetre, hides, oil of sesame, wheat, assafoetida, oil, raisins, almonds, colouring plants, pistachio flowers and nuts, shawls, cloths, mustard, wild saffron, black cummin seed from Kerman, white cummin seed, chintzes both from Sinde and Khorasan. In return are received from Bombay, sugar, sugar-candy, steel, iron, tin, tutenaque, lead, cochineal, betel-nut, black pepper, dried cocoa nuts, vermillion, red lead, quicksilver, Bengal and China silks and cloths, cinnamon, cardamoms, cloves, nutmegs, sandal-wood, grapes, china ware, pearls, aloes, and amuttas. A considerable trade is carried on with Muscat, Cutch, and with Mooltan and Cabul. To Muscat the exports are dressed leather, rice, wheat, sirshif oil, ghee, bdellium, chintzes, and other cloths ; for which the returns are dates, limes, roses, silk from the Persian province of Ghilan, elephants’ teeth, pearls, almonds, preserved fruit, cowries, slaves, arsenic, senna from Mecca, quince seeds, and gum. From Cutch it derives a supply of cotton, snuff, unwrought iron found in Cutch, and the small Arabian aloe. The Indus affords an easy means of intercourse with this province and the countries to the northward, being navigable for small vessels to a great distance from the sea. With Mooltan and Cabul the trade is carried on chiefly by caravans, and also by merchants and travellers. It is proper to add, that the trade in the Indus had greatly decayed, and had become merely nominal, the ignorant and tyrannical policy of the Ameers having nearly crushed it in that province, and the unsettled state of the countries to the northward rendering it precarious in that quarter. In 1808 it was carried on by a few boats passing up and down with grain, saltpetre, salt, and firewood ; though, with the increasing ascendancy of the British in this quarter, and the restoration of order and peace in these former regions of anarchy, the former intercourse has revived, and will now be carried on with greater security than ever. A factory, established at Tatta in 1756 by the East India Company, which carried on a considerable trade with the province of Sinde, and was withdrawn, probably from the demoralised state and poverty of the country ; though so late as the beginning of the present century, Mr. Crow was a commercial resident at Tatta. An unsuccessful attempt was since made in 1808 to renew the intercourse ; but the haughty and jealous chieftains who ruled in this province rejected all advances on the part of the British. Ever since the occupation of Cutch by the British troops in 1819, they viewed the extension of their dominions with distrust, and maintained a cold and unfriendly attitude. No European officer was allowed to cross the frontier from Cutch ; and even a special envoy, who had proceeded from Bombay in 1820, on the invitation of their own minister, was coldly received, and it was only in 1825 that a most friendly letter was received, with an invitation to Dr. Burnes to proceed without delay to Hydrabad, on account of the alleged sickness of one of the principal chiefs. The invitation vas accepted, and he was received with every mark of confidence. A treaty has been since ratified in 1838 by the Ameers of Sinde, providing for the reception of a British resident ; to which office Colonel Pottinger has been appointed.</p><p>The government of Sinde is a military despotism. After a long era of civil commotion, Futteh Ali Khan was called to exercise the supreme power, who generously admitted his three brothers, Ghoolam Ali, Kurm Ali, and Mourad Ali, to a participation in his high destiny. He died in 1801, and Ghoolam Ali in 1811. The supreme power in Sinde is now vested in the two youngest and surviving brothers, Meers Kurm and Mourad Ali, who are known as the chief Ameers, and whose seals are affixed to all public documents issued in the name of the government. But there are others of the family who are scarcely inferior in rank to these princes, on whom has devolved the executive government. The two deceased brothers, Futteh and Ghoolam Ali, left sons, to whom they bequeathed their shares in the administration, and who, though they have been kept back by their youth, and the grasping spirit of their uncles, had, when Dr. Burnes was at Hydrabad in 1827, acquired ascendancy in the state; and since his departure, one of them had risen in successful rebellion, and had raised himself to a political equality with his relatives. The two sons of Mourad Ali, Noor Mahommed and Nusseer Khan, are also among the heads of the government. All these chiefs are in possession of respective portions of the revenues of Sinde. After the death of Futteh Ali, the province was partitioned into four shares, of which the largest belongs to Mourad Ali, who, on the plea of his having descendants, continued to despoil his brother and Meer Mahommed of much of their possessions. There are other nobles who are related to the royal family, and who are allowed to assume the title of meer, or lord, but are not permitted to interfere in the affairs of state, deriving their importance solely from their alliance with the reigning princes. The real power centres in Meer Mourad Ali, who is represented as a gloomy tyrant, a slave to avarice, and a plunderer of his people. At the court of the Ameers, every thing is conducted on a scale of magnificence scarcely equalled at any other court in Hindustan. The parade that was exhibited when Colonel Pottinger and Dr. Burnes were severally received at court, is described by these travellers; and they both agree in celebrating the surpassing richness and splendour of the scene. The princes, says the former writer, wore a vast number of jewels, beside those that were set in the hilts and scabbards of their swords and daggers ; and their waist-belts displayed some extraordinary emeralds and rubies. They were seated on a thin felt, that extended all round the circle, and over which was laid a silk mattrass, about an inch thick, spread with a muslin cloth, embroidered in a most exquisite manner with gold and silver flowers. They reclined on three large pillows, covered with similar embroidery, which, with the display of jewels, gave the whole an inconceivably rich effect. “ Many of the officers of government,” he continues, “ appeared in very good style ; and the general splendour and richness of the scene far surpassed any thing we had expected to see at the court of Hydrabad.”@@<hi rend="superscript">1</hi> The dress of the princes, which was not ornamental, consisted in fine muslin tunics, with costly sashes tied round their waists, and their turbans of thin transparent gauze were of the largest dimensions, about 2<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">2</hi> feet in diameter, and yet so neatly folded up, as to give them a very becoming appearance. Dr. Burnes observes, that when he was first introduced at court,</p><p><hi rend="superscript">@@@1</hi> Travel in Balochistan and in Sinde, chap. x. p. 367.</p></body></text></TEI>