<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-25T20:16:26Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>There are seldom more than a dozen grouse in a brood; rarely indeed so many. Towards the end of autumn, the broods congregate together, and are seldom seen afterwards until pairing time in January or February, except in great numbers. Broods thus associated are termed packs. When it happens that the birds are well grown at the opening of the season, and much fired at in August, they will pack before September. When there is fine weather in August, grouse, until the broods are packed, will suffer the shooter to approach very near to them before they rise. In wet or windy weather they are wild. Very few grouse are killed by the sportsman after August ; they are then scarcely approachable. Grouse delight in tall young heather, when there are plenty of bare places or pads or tracks. Hares also, and cocks, and we may perhaps add, pheasants, in their respective covers, delight in those parts where they can run about freely. The brow of a hill is more likely ground than either extreme heights or valleys, or flats. Solitary birds lie better than broods. When birds are wild, the shooter should follow an individual rather than a brood. It is well understood by sportsmen, that the fewer birds there are in a brood, nide, or covey, the better will they lie. Grouse bask on the sunny hill-side, oftentimes under a rock, or in a stone pit, during the middle of the day, at which time the task of ranging for them is toilsome in the extreme. Grouse shooters should be accompanied by a guide and markers. The former is indispensable to a person not intimately acquainted with every turn and knoll, during the mist that nine mornings out of ten envelopes the hills in August. It is inconceivable how completely bewildered a person who fancies he is acquainted with every inch of ground may be when surrounded by the haze. Neither sun, moon, nor stars are visible ; nor is there a fence, road, or building to direct him. A stone pit, or mountain rill, are often the only objects that present themselves, except the interminable- heather. The distant hills that would else be his guides, are shut out from his view, which does not extend beyond the range of his fowling-piece. At such times it requires no ordinary precaution to prevent losing young dogs, which can scarcely be prevented running off when a gun is fired in the distance. During the continuance of the mist, which generally disappears about eight o’clock, markers can be of but little use, except that they may be employed in carrying a basket, extra guns and shot, or leading dogs, of which it is well to have a change. No dog can range two days successively for grouse. Pointers, for reasons we have before given, are preferable to setters, or any other kind of dogs, for grouse shooting. Grouse shooters should separate and range singly ; they should have no noisy attendants ; nor any dogs that require rating. The sport cannot be carried on too quietly. If the shooter throws off before eight o’clock, which it is not prudent to do unless there are many guns on the moors or foul weather is expected in the afternoon, he should run only one dog as long as the heather is wet, afterwards two, and in the afternoon three dogs. In wet weather one dog is quite sufficient. If hot weather, we advise rest from eleven to two. If the shooter have not exhausted himself during the middle of the day he will best fill his bag in the afternoon ; he may net, indeed, then find so many, but those he does find will be dispersed birds that will almost lie to be trodden on. An old sh∞ter thus on a dry afternoon following a wet morning will sometimes load himself or his attendant, after the less experienced have left the moor disgusted, with scarcely a bird in their possession. Shooters are generally recommended to carry as heavy a gun as they can conveniently manage on the moors. It should be borne in mind that the heaviest gun will do most execution; but none except those accustomed to such exercise, can carry a heavy gun with comfort all day long, exposed to an autumnal sun. We would therefore not recommend barrels more than thirty inches long, nor of a larger guage than sixteen, on account of the excessive heat of the weather at this season. As the sportsman, in grouse shooting, has ever an opportunity of choosing his own distance when birds rise near to him, he will be more certain of killing if he let the birds fly twenty-five yards from him before he fires the first barrel, when, if he have both barrels cocked, he will have ample time to throw in the reserve barrel while the birds are within reasonable distance. In nothing is the superiority of the detonating over the flint lock more apparent than in its allowing the shooter to fire the second so soon after the first barrel. We suspect that the habit of taking the gun from the shoulder after the first barrel was fired, originated in the necessity of waiting until the smoke from the pan was blown away, which nuisance no longer exists. A person who is a decidedly bad shot should not use the cartridge in the first barrel, as the loose charge gives a larger circle at a short distance, and consequently increases the chance of killing.</p><p><hi rend="italic">The Blackcock.</hi> Black game shooting commences on the 20th of August, and ends, with red grouse shooting, on the 10th of December. Black game frequent moors covered with heather, but they are as often found in rushy fields, or even in stubbles adjoining to moors. They are not met with at any great altitude, but confine themselves chiefly to the lower hills, or the base of the loftier mountains. They are seldom found, except where there are plantations or forests of fir trees. Black game do not frequent the central parts of large wastes so much as those parts bordering on inclosed lands. Red grouse recede where civilization progresses; and they are consequently in a fair way, at no very distant period, of being banished from England. As a vast extent of heath-land is not requisite for black game, there is no room to fear their extinction for some centuries to come. Although not so numerous as red grouse, they are more widely scattered over England. Even in the south of England there is cover congenial to them. Should both black and red game become extinct in England, the hills of Scotland will long afford shelter to each. With the exception of the pheasant, black game is the only species of game not yearly diminishing in number in Britain. A full- grown blackcock weighs the same as a fine pheasant cock, about three pounds and a half. The female, which is called the grey-hen, and ought never to be fired at, is much smaller. Black game shooting on moors resembles red grouse shooting, and in the woods, pheasant shooting. The black cock is a magnificent bird, and an old one is ever deemed a valuable addition to the contents of the game bag. Black game have increased very considerably in England during the last few years, still they are much more abundant in Scotland. Sweden is perhaps the country best suited to them.</p><p><hi rend="italic">The capercailzie.</hi> Similar to the blackcock, in many respects, is the capercailzie, or cock of the wood, once the native, and now the denizen of the Highland forests. The</p></body></text></TEI>