<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-25T20:16:17Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>is inconceivable that the mastiff, terrier, cur, and numberless other dogs besides the pointer, could ever have been in a wild state, as they do not seem to be possessed of any instincts or faculties that could enable them to subsist un- attached to the human race.</p><p>The long received opinion that the lion, as the king of brutes, is possessed of the highest degree of physical cou- rage, is exploded. The palm of courage is now awarded to the dog. Courage, however, in the common acceptation of the term, is not a characteristic trait of the pointer or set- ter, which are, perhaps, except the cur, the least courageous of the canine race. The dog is the only brute animal that prefers the society of man to that of its own species ; and no dog is more affectionate or faithful to man than the pointer or the setter.</p><p>England is not less famous for its horses than for its sport- ing dogs. Our grey-hounds, fox-hounds, and harriers are unequalled, and that they are so results from the care that has been taken to keep each species distinct. All our pointers are, in some degree, of Spanish extraction ; and such of them as have most Spanish blood in their veins are unquestionably the best. The Spanish pointer is about twenty-one inches in height. He has a large head, is heavily made, broad-chested, stout-limbed, with a large dew-lap ; his eyes are full, and widely apart, and his nose is broad ; his tail is straight, short, and thick, and his ears large, pen- dulous, and fine ; he should have a round, and not a flat foot. When pointing, he stands on three legs, one of the fore legs being raised, and his face and tail are in a line with his back. This is his invariable position when he comes gradually upon the scent ; but whenever, by running with the wind, or from any other circumstance, he comes suddenly upon game, he will stand in the most picturesque and sometimes indeed grotesque attitude, frequently with his body almost doubled. A pointer may be sometimes seen standing with all four feet collected together on the surface of a small stone on a wall when the birds are almost under him. A very old dog of this description, when fatigued with ranging and too enfeebled to maintain his point long in the natural position, will sit down on his haunches with his face towards the game, yet ever and anon turning his head wistfully to see whether the gun be approaching. Notwithstanding however the vaunted excellence of British pointers, the generality of them are not such as they ought to be. It is much to be lamented that the same care is not taken in the breeding of pointers and setters as of hounds. Scarcely two pointers are to be seen so much alike that a naturalist would pronounce them to belong to the same class of dogs, inasmuch as they are dissimilar in size, weight, and appearance. There are, properly speaking, but two classes, the Spaniard and the mongrel. Nearly all the pointers we see are, in fact, mongrels, although each may have more or less of the original Spanish blood. Such, however, is the force of nature that a dog having in him very little of the blood of the pointer may prove a very ser- viceable dog to the shooter. We frequently meet with very good dogs, dogs deemed by their owners first-rate, which bear little resemblance, in point of shape and appearance, to the true pointer. Some have the sharp nose of the fox, others the snubbed nose of the bull-dog ; some are slenderly formed ; some long-legged, others short-legged ; some heavy-bodied, others light ; in short, there is every possible diversity.</p><p>The attempt to lay down a written rule whereby to dis- tinguish between a good and an indifferent pointer would be futile. How much of the blood of the pointer a dog has in him will be read in his countenance, rather than inferred from his general shape and appearance. There is an indescribable something in the countenance of a thoroughbred or nearly thorough-bred pointer, which a little habit of observation will enable the sportsman to detect with to-</p><p>lerable accuracy, so that he may judge of the capabilities of a dog, as a physiognomist will read at a glance a person’s disposition and ability in his countenance. It is to the disciplined eye only that these all but infallible tokens are discernible.</p><p>The instinct of pointing, we apprehend, is an inextinguishable and indestructible principle in the blood of the pointer, which, however it may be mingled with inferior blood, will always, in some degree, manifest itself ; and on this ground we build our theory that the further any dog is removed from the original Spanish pointer the worse the dog is ; and, consequently, that all attempts to cross the pointer with any other blood must necessarily deteriorate the breed. The grey-hound is seldom or never crossed to give him ad- ditional fleetness, nor the hound to improve his nose ; why then should the pointer be crossed with dogs which, in so far as the sports of the field are concerned, scarcely inherit one quality in common with him ? Attempts, however, are constantly made to improve the pointer by a cross with the blood-hound, fox-hound, Newfoundland dog, or mastiff, sometimes with a view of improving his appearance, and bringing him to some fancied standard of perfection ; but in reality inducing a deformity. One of these imaginary standards of perfection is, that to one part thorough Span- ish blood, the pointer should have in him an eighth of the fox-hound, and a sixteenth of the blood-hound. A cross will sometimes produce dogs which are, to some eyes, the <hi rend="italic">beau idéal</hi> of beauty ; but however handsome such dogs may be, they will necessarily possess some quality not be- longing to the pointer ; for instance, a cross with the hound gives the propensity to trace hares, if not to give tongue. A thorough-bred pointer carries his head well up when rang- ing; he will not give tongue, nor has he much desire to chase footed game. The hound pointer may be sometimes de- tected by his coarse ears, by his tail being curled upwards, and being carried high, or by his rough coat. An occasional cross with the mastiff or Newfoundland dog is said to increase the fineness of nose, but it is converting the pointer into a mere retriever. The pointer, as we before observed, is naturally cowardly, as compared with other dogs; there- fore, whenever a pointer is ferocious or courageous, it may be inferred that the blood of some of the larger or stronger dogs runs in his veins. Another and the main source of the unsightliness of sporting dogs is the allowing an indis- criminate intercourse between pointers and setters. Good dogs may be thus obtained sometimes, but they are invariably misshapen ; they have generally the head and brush tail of the setter, with the body of the pointer, and their coats are not sleek, and instead of standing at their point, they will crouch. When the sire is nearly thorough-bred, dogs of a superior description, but certainly not the best dogs, are sometimes produced by the Newfoundland or some other bitch not strictly a pointer. We are not willing to allow that the pointer is improved in any quality that renders him valuable to the sportsman, by a cross with the hound or any other sort of dog ; though we cannot deny that the setter is materially improved in appearance by a cross with the Newfoundland dog, but what it gains in ap- pearance, it loses in other respects.</p><p>Breeding mongrels, especially crossing with hounds, has given the gamekeepers and dog-breakers an infinity of trouble which might have been avoided by keeping the blood pure. The best pointer is the offspring of a pointerbitch by a pointer-dog ; such a dog is nearly broken by na- ture. The Spanish pointer seldom requires the whip ; the hound pointer has never enough of it. One of the main sources of the sportsman’s pleasure is to see the dogs point well. A deal is said about this and that dog being remarkably fine-looking; the only time to appreciate the beauty of a dog is when he is ranging and pointing ; then let the sportsman compare the real pointer with the spurious one.</p></body></text></TEI>