<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-25T20:17:38Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>echoes from their walls; they are subjected to other shocking and degrading cruelties revolting to humanity ; any two of the true believers, by declaring that they have heard a Hindoo repeat a verse in the Koran, or the words “ Mahomed the prophet,” may procure his immediate circumcision, which this degraded and persecuted class consider the most cruel calamity that can befal them, in which, as it is resorted to on the slightest provocation, and performed with the deriding pretence that it is for their eternal happiness, the torture of the mind is added to that of the body. On the other hand, the most bigotted veneration is expressed for the Seynds, or descendants of the prophet. The meanest wretch who can boast a connection, however remote, with this holy stock, enjoys a station in society such as no temporal man can bestow. If any one, under whatever provocation, would dare to retaliate, by abusing or striking any one of this favoured class, he would be torn to pieces by the enraged populace ; and, in consequence of this high favour which they enjoy, an idle herd of these wretches flock into Sinde from the neighbouring countries, where, besides being useless members of the community, and withal insolent and lazy, they debase the minds and drain the purses of the deluded inhabitants.</p><p>The Ameers commence business about two hours before day-break, each holding a levee to hear compliments, and to adjust the affairs belonging to his department. About sun-rise they repair to their apartments to dress, and appear shortly afterwards in durbar, where the whole family regularly assemble for transacting public business ; all letters are then laid before them, which, being read and considered, and some time passed in conversation, they withdraw to their morning repast about ten or eleven o’clock. They again appear abroad about two o’clock and remain together until dark, when they repair for the night to their respective apartments. At the residences of the younger princes every thing forms a contrast to the stately ceremonial of the elder Ameers ; all restraint is thrown aside, and every species of amusement, such as boar-baiting, fencing, ball practice, and wrestling, are pursued with avidity. At the public audiences in the durbar the Ameers, though courteous, are for the most part haughty and reserved in their manners ; nothing approaching to familiarity being allowed between them and their most favoured servants. Under such a government as has been described, justice is very imperfectly administered. The Koran is the foundation of law as it is of religion ; and between man and man disputes are generally settled fairly enough by the cadi, except where bribery is employed, when the best security for justice is a weighty purse. The Hindus generally settle all disputes among themselves by punchayets or juries, as is practised in many parts of Hindustan, as they have no encouragement to come before the ruling authorities. The native inhabitants, the Beloches, according to their military notions, generally take the law into their own hands, and act on the simple principle of retaliation ; nor do the authorities interfere, except where the dispute extends to whole tribes, and seriously endangers the peace of the country. In this case they interfere to settle matters by force or by conciliation. A serious quarrel of this nature occurred when Dr. Burnes was at Hydrabad, when the contending parties were sent for by the princes, who, with much flattery and address, obtained a promise from them to desist.</p><p>The military force of Sinde is very inefficient ; their armed retainers are few in number and contemptible in appearance. Several of the chiefs of the tribes reside at court, and they can collect in a few days their followers, who are generally employed in agriculture and other occupations. In this manner it is estimated that 40,000 men may be collected. But though the iron rod of oppression has repressed the daring spirit of the military classes, yet the anarchy which has prevailed in this, as in other parts of Hindustan, has nurtured, among the great body of the people, a spirit of disorder and a love of plunder which is ready to break out on all occasions. The country is, in short, filled with licentious banditti, and would have been, in the evil days that are passed, a fit nursery of recruits for the Pindarie bands. “ Like hungry vultures,” says Dr. Burnes, “ they would almost seem to scent the battle from afar, for the train of dissension is no sooner lighted than war becomes their universal cry, and it is incredible in how short time they flock to the rendezvous.” The late insurrection of the princes was settled in a few days ; yet, in that short time, about 20,000 or 30,000 volunteers had joined the different standards, and they were hourly crowding in when the adjustment took place. In military qualities, the Sindian soldier ranks very low ; he has no discipline nor steadiness in the field, though he is brave and hardy ; and his vanity and gasconading are proverbial. The army presents, when assembled, a motley and ill-accoutred assemblage of mercenaries from all quarters, chiefly composed of ferocious adventurers from the mountains of Belochistan, to one of whose rude tribes the reigning house traces its origin. The Ameers are well aware of the inefficient state of their military force, and of the utter hopelessness of any conflict with the British arms. And this furnishes the explanation of their distance and reserve, justly fearing that any close intercourse would only expose the nakedness of the land. It is not easy to obtain any exact estimate of the revenue of Sinde. Colonel Pottinger states its total amount, including those of all the collateral branches of the reigning family, at sixty-one lacs of rupees yearly, equal to L.767,500 sterling, which shews an increase, since 1809, several years previous to his estimate, of L.232,750, the amount being, at that time, forty-two lacs and 78,000, or L.534,000 sterling.</p><p>The men of Sinde are dark in colour but are an exceedingly handsome race; above the medium height of Asiatics, with good features and well-formed limbs. The beauty of the women is proverbial, and it is remarked by Pottinger in his instructive and excellent work, that though he had only casual opportunities of seeing any of the higher class of females, yet among the dancing girls who came to exhibit before them, there was not one who was not distinguished by loveliness of face or the symmetry of her figure, and in most instances both these requisites of beauty were strikingly combined. The dress of the men consists of a loose shirt, a pair of trousers, puckered at the ancles, and a quilted cotton or cloth cap, ornamented with flowers of silk or gold sewed round the bottom : that of the women, with the exception of the cap, is much the same ; they wear beside, underneath their shifts, a silk jacket made to fit the form, that laces behind ; and when abroad, a cloth shirt wraps round the body, having one end brought round the crown of the head, and serving as a veil to cover the face from strangers. This traveller does not, however, commend, in the same degree, the character of the people, in which the bad qualities, according to his estimate, greatly predominate. They are, he observes, avaricious, full of deceit, cruel, ungrateful, and strangers to veracity ; and all the extenuation which he offers for these vices is, that the present generation has grown up under a government whose extortion, ignorance, and tyranny, is unequalled in the world. The Sindians, however, he does not rate lower in the scale of morality than the population and society of the other nations of Asia. Their good qualities consist in personal braveτy, abstinence, and obedience to their superiors ; for which they are reckoned the best mercenary soldiers in Hindustan. In manners they are generally forward and unpolished ; in intellect dark and inapt, and in hospitality and fidelity signally regardless and deficient.</p><p>The ancient history of Sinde is involved in obscurity. When Alexander of Macedon invaded the country, it was</p></body></text></TEI>