<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-25T20:18:00Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>and should refuse to appear in any posture of adoration be- fore it, since they cannot but know that God will not vouch- safe to be present in it, but in the way and method of his own appointment.” According to this pure and enlightened theology, the divine presence, utterly withheld from all non-episcopalian assemblies of worshippers, is regularly manifested wherever a popish or half-popish priest “ offers the unbloody sacrifice.” It is truly pitiful that any man, calling himself a protestant, should be so besotted as to represent all this as the way and method of God’s own appointment. It is the very essence of such an adulterated form of Christianity, that, without the supplementary aid of bishops and priests, Christ has died in vain, and in vain has risen from the dead.	(x.)</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Skinner</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Stephen,</hi> an English lexicographer, was born in the year 1622. He travelled, and studied in several foreign universities during the civil wars; and in 1654, he return- ed and settled at Lincoln, where he practised physic with success until the year 1667, when he died of a malignant fever. His posthumous work was published in folio in 1671, by Mr. Henshaw, under the title of <hi rend="italic">Etymolog icon Lingua; Anglicanæ.</hi></p><p>SKIPTON, commonly called Skipton in Craven. It is in the wapentake of Staincliffe, in the West Riding of Yorkshire, 216 miles from London. It stands on the river Aire, in a wild and romantic district near two lofty mountains. Being on the canal from Leeds to Liverpool it has some trade with both these places, and of late years it has become the seat of some manufactures of glass, of silk, and of cotton goods. The ancient castle has been preserved, and is now a mansion of the Earl of Thanet. The quarter sessions for the West Riding are held here. It has a well supplied market on Saturdays, and several fairs for the sale of cattle. The inhabitants were, in 1801, 2305; in 1811, 2868; in 1821, 3411 ; and in 1831, 4181.</p><p>SKIROS, an island of Turkey, on the western side of the Archipelago, about twenty-three miles from the mainland. It is sixty-three square miles in extent, and contains 1800 Greek inhabitants, who grow oil and cotton, and feed cattle in the valleys between the rocky hills which cover the greater part of the surface. The chief town is of the same name, and has a small harbour.</p><p>SKYE, the largest of the western islands of Scotland, is situated between the outer range of the Hebrides, and the mainland of Scotland, from which it is separated by a nar- row strait, varying from a gun-shot to three miles in breadth. It forms part of the county of Inverness, and is divided in- to seven parishes. The extreme length of the island is about forty-five miles, and its extreme breadth twenty-four miles ; but a better idea of its dimensions will be formed, by measuring it across the middle, which will give a mean breadth of fifteen miles. These measurements do not, how- ever, give any idea of the superficial extent of the island, in consequence of the remarkable indentations of the coast, no part of the island being distant four miles from the sea- shore. The area of the island is computed at 700 square miles, and contains therefore 448,000 acres, of which 30,000 are arable. It is divided into five districts. The south-east district, which is close upon the mainland, is called S1eat. The greater portion of the central part of the island is named Minginish, whilst the northern extremity is divided by Loch Snizort and Loch Follart into three extensive tracts of land, called Trottemish, on the north-eastern, Water- nish on the north-west, and Kilmuir on the west side.</p><p>The position of Skye protects it in some measure from the storms that assail the outer range of islands. The numerous lochs provide it with a variety of excellent bays and harbours, which point it out as admirably adapted for carrying on the fisheries, but which, from the habits of the people, has never been prosecuted to any extent. The surface of the island is invariably hilly, and may be called one great</p><p>mountainous moorland, presenting three distinct assemblages of mountains, which are separated by intervening tracts of high and undulating land. Kilmuir plain, and a small tract of land near Loch Braccadale, are the only exceptions.</p><p>In that part of the country, in the southern border of Minginish, occurs the greatest assemblage of mountains. They are divided into two portions, intimately united, but characterised by striking differences in their external outlines and general features. The range called the Cuchullins, so often mentioned by Ossian, average in height from 2000 to 3000 feet above the level of the sea. On the: west side of the island, the land is from 600 to 1000 feet in height, and its surface is covered with brown heath. The north- eastern portion of the island, Trotternish, offers more va- riety, and it attains an altitude of 2000 feet in height. The shore scenery is famed for the caves with which they abound, and the mountainous parts of the island for wild and rugged scenery, equal in grandeur to any in the Highlands.</p><p>The south-east portion of the island, from the point of Sleat to Kyle-rhea, consists of regular stratified rock, which, whether primary or secondary, extend in a line from southwest to north-east ; but the remaining mass of the island must be considered as formed of unstratified rock, all be- longing to the family of trap, (including under that term syenite), and all incumbent on the stratified rocks, and of posterior date.</p><p>From the height of the hills, and the proximity of the sea, the air seldom continues long of the same temperature ; sometimes it is dry, offener moist, and in the latter end of winter and beginning of spring cold and piercing. At an average, three days in twelve, throughout the whole year, are scarcely free from rain, far less from clouds. These, attracted by the hills, sometimes break in useful and refreshing showers ; at other times suddenly bursting, they pour down their contents with tremendous noise, and impetuous torrents deluge the plains below, and render the smallest rivulet impassable, which, together with the stormy winds so common in this country in the months of August and September, frequently blast the hopes of the husbandman. Snow has been often known to lie on the ground from three to seven weeks.</p><p>Skye is not well adapted for agriculture. The soil is good, but too light for the culture of wheat ; oats are rais- ed in considerable quantities, which, with barley and po- tatoes, form the agricultural produce of the island. Much might be done in the improvement of the land, for the subsoil is every where of the finest quality, and both in the trap and the gneiss districts, the calcareous rock is found to be decomposed to the depth of several feet, and yielding a loam of excellent quality. The greater part, however, is suffocated with peat or stones, and is swampy and rocky. The peat is nevertheless thin, and by burning the peat, and turning up the rock, either by manual labour, or by the subsoil plough, and proper drainage, the agriculture of the island, in course of time, would be much improved. The land is also ren- dered cold by the want of trees, for which the soil and climate are well adapted. Skye is unquestionably a grazing country, and the proprietors have wisely directed their at- tention to the improvement of the stock of black cattle and sheep, and to the enlargement of their farms, of which they have latterly in many places given leases. Kelp in former years was manufactured to a considerable extent, but that branch of industry is now nearly annihilated. The climate is, as already stated, damp, and the farmers in consequence are all provided with wattled barns, in which they may dry their scanty crops in the rainy season. The <hi rend="italic">caschrome,</hi> or ancient crooked spade, is a good deal used by the poor, and the <hi rend="italic">quern,</hi> or handmill, is still to be found in some of the remote districts of the island. The roads in Skye are much superior to those of Mull, and they traverse the island in various directions.</p></body></text></TEI>