<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T21:07:21Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>London ; and the municipal boroughs of Godaiming (2505), Guildford (10,858), Kingston-upon-Thames (20,648), and Reigate (18,662). A considerable portion (22,472 acres, with a population in 1881 of 980,522) is within the metropolitan district of London, in addition to which there are the following urban sanitary districts—Aider- shot (20,l55), Croydon (78,953), Dorking (6328), East Moulsey (3289), Epsom (6916), Farnham (4488), Ham Common (1349), Hampton Wick (2164), New Malden (2δ38), Richmond (19,066), Surbiton (9406), Teddington (6δ99), and Wimbledon (l5,950). The county has one court of quarter sessions, and is divided into twelve petty and special sessional divisions. The central criminal court has jurisdiction over certain parishes in this county. The borough of Guildford has a separate court of quarter sessions and commission of the peace ; the boroughs of Reigate and Kingston-upon-Thames have commissions of the peace ; the borough of Southwark is included in the petty sessional division of Newington ; and the borough of Godaiming, in which the mayor and ex-mayor are magistrates, forms part of the petty sessional division of Guildford, the county justices having concurrent jurisdiction. The county contains 152 civil parishes, with parts of two others. It is shared among the dioceses of Canterbury, Rochester, and Winchester. Until 1885 the county for parliamentary purposes was divided into East, Mid, and West Surrey ; it is now rearranged in six divisions, viz., Kingston, Mid (Epsom), North-East (Wimbledon), North- West (Chertsey), South-East (Reigate), and South-West (Guildford). The portion of Surrey formerly included in the borough of Greenwich was in 1885 included in the borough of Deptford (Kent) ; the borough of Guildford was disfranchised ; one member was given to Croydon ; and instead of the two metropolitan boroughs of Lambeth and Southwark the following fifteen constituencies (each returning one member) were created: — Battersea and Clapham, constituting two divisions ; Camberwell, embracing the divisions of North Camberwell, Dulwich, and Peckham ; Lambeth, embracing the divisions of Brixton, Kennington, Lambeth North, and Norwood; Southwark, containing the divisions of Bermondsey, Rotherhithe, and Southwark West; Wandsworth; and Newington, with the divisions of Walworth and West Newington.</p><p>Since the beginning of the 19th century the population has increased nearly 600 per cent. From 268,233 in 1801 it had increased by 1821 to 399,417, by 1851 to 683,082, by 1871 to 1,091,635, and by 1881 to 1,436,899, of whom 683,228 were males and 753,671 females. The number of persons to an acre is 2·96 and of acres to a person 0·34. Within the last decade the increase has been 35·1 per cent.,—much greater than the increase in the general town population of England and Wales, which was 19·63 per cent., the increase in the whole population being only 14·34. Nearly two- thirds (980,522) of the population belong to the metropolitan district of London, but the suburbs of London extend practically throughout the greater part of the county, its increase in population being chiefly due to the building of residences for those who have business or professional interests in London.</p><p><hi rend="italic">History and Antiquities.—</hi>Notwithstanding its proximity to London, Surrey has been associated with few great events in English history. Roman remains have been discovered at Albury, Kingston, Titsey, Woodcote, and a few other places, but none are of much importance. On several of the hills there are remains of camps of either Roman or British origin. The Roman Stane Street from London to Chichester in Sussex passed by Kingston, Chessington, Leatherhead, Dorking (where its remains are specially well marked), Leith Hill, and Ockley. During the Saxon period Surrey was included in the dominions of the South Saxons and afterwards of Wessex. Its name Surrey or “south kingdom” has apparently reference to its position south of London or south of the Thames. Kingston in Surrey was in 838 the seat of a witana- gemot convened by Egbert ; and after the capture of Winchester by the Danes it was from 901 to 978 the place where the Anglo- Saxon kings were crowned. Surrey was an earldom of Godwine ; and after the conquest was bestowed on William de Warren, who had married Gundrada, supposed to have been a daughter of the Conqueror. From the time that the great charter was on 15th June 1215 signed by King John at Runnymede near Egham the historical annals of the county are a blank, until the period of the Civil War, when a skirmish took place, 7th June 1648, at Kingston.</p><p>The only ecclesiastical ruins worthy of special mention are the picturesque walls of Newark Priory, founded for Augustinians in the time of Richard Cœur de Lion ; and the Early English crypt and part of the refectory of Waverley Abbey, the earliest house of the Cistercians in England, founded in 1128 by William Gifford, bishop of Winchester. The <hi rend="italic">Annales Waverlicnscs,</hi> published by Gale in his <hi rend="italic">Scriptores</hi> and afterwards in the Record series of <hi rend="italic">Chronicles,</hi> are supposed to have suggested to Sir Walter Scott the name of his first novel. The church architecture is of a very varied kind, and has no peculiarly special features. Among the more interesting churches are Albury, the tower of which is of Saxon or very early Norman date ; Beddington, a fine example of the Perpendicular, and containing monuments of the Carew family ; Chaldon, remarkable for its fresco wall-paintings of the 12th century,</p><p>discovered during restoration in 1870 ; Compton, which, though mentioned in Domesday, possesses little of its original architecture, but is worthy of notice for its two-storied chancel, and its carved wooden balustrade surmounting the pointed Transition Norman arch which separates the nave from the chancel ; St. Mary’s, Guildford, containing examples of Norman, Early English, Decorated, and Perpendicular, but is of interest chiefly for the grotesque carving on the corbels of the aisles and the coloured medallions on the roof of the north chapel ; Leigh, Perpendicular, possessing some very fine brasses of the 15th century ; Lingfield, Perpendicular, containing ancient tombs and brasses of the Cobhams ; Ockham, chiefly Decorated, with a lofty embattled tower, containing the mausoleum of Lord Chancellor King (d. 1734), with full-length statue of the chancellor by Rysbroeck ; Reigate, chiefly Perpendicular, but with Transition Norman pillars in the nave ; Stoke d’Abernon, Early English, with the earliest extant English brass, that of Sir John d’Abernon, 1277 ; and Woking, Decorated, with Early English chancel. Of old castles the only examples are Farnham, occupied as a palace by the bishops of Winchester, originally built by Henry of Blois, and restored by Henry III. ; and Guildford, with a strong quadrangular Norman keep. Ancient domestic architecture is, however, well represented, the examples including Beddington Hall, now a female orphan asylum ; the ancient mansion of the Carews, rebuilt in the reign of Queen Anne, hut still retaining the hall of the Elizabethan building ; Crowhurst Place, built in the time of Henry VII., the ancient seat of the Gaynesfords, and frequently visited by Henry VIII. ; portions of Croydon Palace, an ancient seat of the archbishops of Canterbury ; the gate tower of Esher Place, built by William of Waynflete, bishop of Winchester, and repaired by Cardinal Wolsey ; Archbishop Abbot’s hospital, Guildford, in the Tudor style ; the fine old Elizabethan house of Losely near Guildford ; Cowley House, Chertsey, originally of the time of James I., inhabited by the poet Cowley from the Restoration till his death ; Smallfield Place, now a farmhouse, at one time the seat of Sir Edward Bysshe, garter king-at-arms ; and Sutton Place, dating from the time of Henry VIII., possessing curious mouldings and ornaments in terra-cotta. Among the eminent persons specially connected with Surrey may be mentioned George Abbot, archbishop of Canterbury, the son of a cloth worker in Guildford ; Arthur Onslow, born at Merrow in 1691, who became member for Guildford and speaker of the House of Commons ; Sir William Temple, who had his residence at Moor Park, where he died in 1699 ; Sir Nicolas Carew, beheaded for conspiracy in 1539, and other members of the family, who had their ancestral seat at Beddington ; John Evelyn, the diarist, who was horn at Wotton in 1620 ; Malthus, the political economist, who was born at the Rooke, near the same place, in 1766 ; William Cobbett, who was born near Farnham in 1762 ; Horne Tooke, who was born at Westminster, wrote his well-known book at Purley, and died at Wimbledon in 1812 ; the historian Gibbon, who was born at Putney in 1737, which was also the birthplace of Cromwell, the minister of Henry VIII.</p><p>See Topley’s <hi rend="italic">Geology of the Weald</hi> and whitaker’s <hi rend="italic">Geology of London Basin, </hi>forming part of the <hi rend="italic">Memoirs of Geological Survey of United Kingdom ; Surrey Archæological Collections</hi> ; Aubrey, <hi rend="italic">Natural History and Antiquities of Surrey, </hi>5 vols., 1718-19 ; Manning and Bray, <hi rend="italic">Hist. and Antiq. of Surrey,</hi> 1809-14; Brayley, <hi rend="italic">Topograph. Hist. of Surrey,</hi> 5 vols., 1S41-46 ; Lysons, <hi rend="italic">Environs of London, </hi>5 vols., 1800-11 ; Baxter, <hi rend="italic">Domesday Book of Surrey,</hi> 1876.	(T. P. H.)</p><p>SURREY, <hi rend="smallcaps">Henry Howard, Earl of</hi> (1516?-1547), one of the leaders in the poetic movement under Henry VIIT. that heralded the great outburst of the Elizabethan period. Of his personal life outside his poetry only the barest outline is known, and till comparatively of late even that outline was not free from confusion. Three different men— the grandfather of the poet, his father, and the poet himself—bore the title within a period of ten or eleven years ; and at one time the poet was confounded with his grandfather, and supposed to have been present at the battle of Flodden (1513). He was not born till at least two years after that event. It was his grandfather who distinguished himself at Flodden under the title of the earl of Surrey, and was created duke of Norfolk as a reward for his services, surrendering the title of Surrey to his son, the poet’s father, for his lifetime. Although the poet has always been most familiarly known as the earl of Surrey, he really held the title only by courtesy, succeeding to it on that footing in 1524, when his father became duke of Norfolk. In one of his poems he speaks of having passed “his childish years” at Windsor “with a king’s son.” This was Henry VIII.’s natural son, Henry Fitzroy, duke of Richmond, who was affianced to Surrey’s sister, Mary, but died before he was out of his teens. It is</p></body></text></TEI>