<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T21:11:29Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>to be lost. The <hi rend="italic">turgāmē</hi> are collected in a MS. at Berlin, Alter Bestand 41, 4. His commentary on an enigmatical poem of Simeon Shankēlāwī we have already mentioned (see above, p. 852). To us his most useful work decidedly is the <hi rend="italic">Catalogue of Books,</hi> which forms the basis of vol. iii. part 1 of Assemani’s <hi rend="italic">Bibl. Orient.</hi> There is an older edition of it by Abraham Ecchellensis, Rome, 1653. It has been translated into English by Badger.@@<hi rend="superscript">1</hi> The <hi rend="italic">Catalogue</hi> consists of four parts, viz., (1) the Scriptures of the Old Testament, with sundry apocrypha, <hi rend="italic">B.O.,</hi> iii. 1, 5; (2) the Scriptures of the New Testament, p. 8 ; (3) the Greek fathers who were translated into Syriac, p. 13 ; (4) the Syriac fathers, chiefly, of course, of the Nestorian Church, pp. 65-362. It is to be regretted that 'Abhd-īshō' contented himself merely with enumerating the titles of</p><p>books, and never thought it worth his while to give the date of the writers, nor even to arrange his notices in any kind of chronological order.@@<hi rend="superscript">2</hi></p><p>After 'Abhd-īshō' there are hardly any names among the Nestorians worthy of a place in the literary history of the Syrian nation. We may make an exception in favour of the catholicus Timothy II., who was elected in succession to Yabh-alāhā III. in 1318, having previously been metropolitan of Mosul and Irbil under the name of Joseph.@@<hi rend="superscript">3</hi> He wrote a work on the sacraments of the church, of which Assemani has given an analysis in<hi rend="italic">H.Ο., </hi>iii. 1, 572-580.@@<hi rend="superscript">4</hi> His death took place in 1328.	(W. W*.)</p><p>SYZRAN, a district town of Russia, in the government of Simbirsk, lies 90 miles to the south of Simbirsk, a few miles from the Volga. It originated in a fort, erected in 1683, to protect the district from Tatars and Circassians. Most of its inhabitants (24,500 in 1882) are engaged in gardening and tillage. In the large villages of the surrounding district, one of the richest in Simbirsk, various petty trades are carried on. Syzran has long been in repute for its tanneries and manufactures of leather (£20,000 annually). Several flour-mills and other manufactures have recently sprung up. The town is connected by rail with Penza and Morshansk in the west, and with Orenburg in the east, and much grain is exported; timber is brought from the upper Volga, and manufactured wares from Nijni-Novgorod. In 1882 the goods shipped from Syzran and Batraki (a port on the Volga) were valued at £153,540. In the same year the grain and other wares sent by rail exceeded one million cwts. Syzran is a badly built town, most of the houses being of wood.</p><p>SZABADKA (German, <hi rend="italic">Maria-Theresiopel),</hi> a royal free town of Hungary, in the county of Bācs, on Lake Palics, in 46° 8' N. lat. and 19° 42' E. long. It is the centre of an immense agricultural district and has little claim to special distinction. There are a chamber of advocates, an upper gymnasium, a state training institute for governesses, and an industrial and commercial school. The population (61,367 in 1880) was about 63,500 in 1885, mostly Hungarians, but partly Bunyevāczs (a branch of Servians).</p><p>SZARVAS, a town of Hungary, on the Körös, in the county of Békés, is a place noted for the wealth of its peasantry and the excellence of its breed of horses. The population was 22,504 in 1880, and about 24,000 in 1885, chiefly Slovaks, but all speaking Hungarian.</p><p>SZATMāR-NÉMETI, a royal free town of Hungary, in the county of Szatmār, is situated on the river Szamos and the Hungarian North-Eastern Railway, in 47° 49' N. lat. and 22° 51' E. long. It is the seat of a Roman Catholic bishop and has a seminary, a male and female normal school, and several Government offices. The town has a considerable trade in wine and wood. The population numbered 19,708 in 1880, and about 22,000 in 1885. They are mostly Magyars, and by religion Romanists, Protestants, and Greeks in almost equal proportions.</p><p>SZEGEDIN, a royal free city of Hungary, second only to Budapest, is situated on both banks of the Theiss at the influx of the Maros, in 46° 16' N. lat. and 20° 10' E. long., in the county of Csongrād. It is a great centre of the commerce and agriculture of the Alfōld, has a Roman</p><p>Catholic gymnasium, a state real school, and a library with about 80,000 volumes. There are a Franciscan, a Piarist, and a Minorite convent, and a large hospital, as well as various Government offices, a superior law court, and a chamber of advocates. The inner town consists of fine broad streets and large squares adorned with many palatial edifices, but the suburbs, inhabited by the peasantry, are little superior to ordinary Hungarian villages. The river is spanned by a railway bridge of stone and a fine suspension bridge. Szegedin possesses factories of soap, soda, matches, candles, leather, and spirits, steam and saw mills, and salt and tobacco magazines. It is the chief seat of the manufacture of <hi rend="italic">paprika</hi> (a kind of pepsicum) and of a pastry <hi rend="italic">tarhonya,</hi> both largely exported to all parts of the world. During the summer the shipping trade is very brisk, especially in corn and timber. Szegedin is an important station on the Alföld-Fiume and the Austrian-Hungarian State Railways, and is a terminus of the Arad-Csanād Railway. The inhabitants in 1880 numbered 73,675, and in 1885 76,600 (estimated), entirely Magyars.</p><p>Since the 15th century Szegedin has been one of the most prominent cities in Hungary. From 1526 till 1686 it was in possession of the Turks, who fortified it. It is also notorious for its many witchcraft trials. In 1848 it sent strong detachments to the national Hungarian army. In July 1849 the seat of the Government was transferred hither for a short time. In March 1879 the town was almost completely destroyed by an inundation. In the reconstruction the site of the old fortress was. laid out as a public garden.</p><p>SZENTES, a market town of Hungary, in the county of Csongrād, on the left bank of the Theiss, 30 miles north of Szegedin. It has a county-hall (1885) and a promenade. The inhabitants are chiefly employed in agriculture, in breeding geese, and in fishing. The population (28,712 in 1880) numbered about 30,000 in 1885, all Magyars.</p><p>SZIGET <hi rend="italic">(Mármaros-Sziget),</hi> chief town of the county of Mārmaros in the north-east of Hungary, is the centre of a salt-mining district, with mining and forestry head departments. The town lies in a valley which abounds in picturesque scenery and is rich in mineral springs. It has a county-hall, Protestant and Catholic gymnasia, a convent, a nunnery, and a training-school for teachers. The population (10,852 in 1880) was about 11,200 in 1885.</p><p>SZOLNOK, the capital of the county of Jász-Nagy- Kun-Szolnok, Hungary, is situated on the Theiss and the Zagyva, and is the junction of four railways. It carries on a brisk trade in tobacco, salt, and especially in wood. In 1880 the population (Magyars), chiefly Roman Catholics, numbered 18,247, and in 1885 about 19,000.</p><p><hi rend="italic superscript">@@@1</hi><hi rend="italic"> The Nestorians,</hi> ii. 361. Badger ascribes the work to the year 1298, probably on the authority of his MS.</p><p><hi rend="superscript">@@@2</hi> MSS.—Cod. Vat. clxxvi. ; RAS. Add. 76 (imperfect); Rome, Bibl. Vitt. Eman. A. 1194, MSS. Sessor.162 ; Cambridge, coll, of the S. P.C.K.</p><p><hi rend="italic superscript">@@@3</hi><hi rend="italic"> B.</hi>O.,iii. 1, 567.	</p><p><hi rend="superscript">@@@4</hi> Vat. cii.</p></body></text></TEI>