<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T21:08:19Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>bling Bewick’s Swan, but with the coloured patches on the bill of less extent and deepening almost into scarlet. South America produces two very distinct birds commonly regarded as Swans,— the Black-necked Swan and that which is called <hi rend="italic">Cascaroba</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Coscaroba.</hi> This last, which inhabits the southern extremity of the continent to Chili and the Argentine territory, and visits the Falkland Islands, is the smallest species known,—pure white in colour except the tip of its primaries, but having a red bill and red feet.@@<hi rend="superscript">1</hi> The former, <hi rend="italic">C. melanocorypha</hi> or <hi rend="italic">nigricollis,</hi> if not discovered by earlier navigators, was observed by Narbrough 2d August 1670 in the Strait of Magellan, as announced in 1691 in the first edition of his <hi rend="italic">Voyage</hi> (p. 52). It was subsequently found on the Falkland Islands during the French settlement there in 1764-65, as stated by Pernetty <hi rend="italic">(Voyage,</hi> ed. 2, ii. pp. 26, 99), and was first technically described in 1782 by Molina <hi rend="italic">{Saggio sulla Stor. Nat. del Chile,</hi> pp. 234, 344). Its range seems to be much the same as that of the Cascaroba, except that it comes further to the northward, to the coast of southern Brazil on the east, and perhaps into Bolivia on the west. It is a very handsome bird, of large size, with a bright red nasal knob, a black neck, and the rest of its plumage pure white. It has been introduced into Europe, and breeds freely in confinement.</p><p>A greater interest than attaches to the South-American birds last mentioned is that which invests the Black Swan of Australia. Considered for so many centuries to be an impossibility, the knowledge of its existence seems to have impressed (more perhaps than anything else) the popular mind with the notion of the extreme divergence—not to say the contrariety—of the organic products of that country. By a singular stroke of fortune we are able to name the precise day on which this unexpected discovery was made. The Dutch navigator Willem de Vlaming, visiting the west coast of Zuidland (Southland), sent two of his boats on the 6th of January 1697 to explore an estuary he had found. There their crews saw at first two and then more Black Swans, of which they caught four, taking two of them alive to Batavia; and Valentyn, who several years later recounted this voyage, gives in his work@@<hi rend="superscript">2</hi> a plate representing the ship, boats, and birds, at the mouth of what is now known from this circumstance as Swan River, the most important stream of the thriving colony of West Australia, which has adopted this very bird as its armorial symbol. Valentyn, however, was not the first to publish this interesting discovery. News of it soon reached Amsterdam, and the burgomaster of that city, Witsen by name, himself a fellow of the Royal Society, lost no time in communicating the chief facts ascertained, and among them the finding of the Black Swans, to Martin Lister, by whom they were laid before that society in October 1698, and printed in its <hi rend="italic">Philosophical Transactions</hi> (xx. p. 361). Subsequent voyagers, Cook and others, found that the range of the species extended over the greater part of Australia, in many districts of which it was abundant. It has since rapidly decreased in numbers, and will most likely soon cease to exist as a wild bird, but its singular and ornamental appearance will probably preserve it as a modified captive in most civilized countries, and perhaps even now there are more Black Swans in a reclaimed condition in other lands than are at large in their mother-country. The species scarcely needs description : the sooty black of its general plumage is relieved by the snowy white of its flight-feathers and its coral-like bill banded with ivory.</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">Cygninæ</hi> admittedly form a well-defined group of the Family <hi rend="italic">Anatidæ,</hi> and there is now no doubt as to its limits, except in the case of the Cascaroba above mentioned. This bird would seem to be, as is so often found in members of the South-American fauna, a more generalized form, presenting several characteristics of the <hi rend="italic">Anatinæ, </hi>while the rest, even its Black-necked compatriot and the almost wholly Black Swan of Australia, have a higher morphological rank. Excluding from consideration the little-known <hi rend="italic">C. davidi,</hi> of the five or six@@<hi rend="superscript">3</hi> species of the</p><p>Northern hemisphere four present the curious character somewhat analogous to that found in certain <hi rend="smallcaps">Cranes</hi> (vol. vi. p. 546), of the penetration of the sternum by the trachea nearly to the posterior end of the keel, whence it returns forward and upward again to revert and enter the lungs ; but in the two larger of these species, when adult, the loop of the trachea between the walls of the keel takes a vertical direction, while in the two smaller the bend is horizontal, thus affording an easy mode of recognizing the respective species of each.@@<hi rend="superscript">4</hi> Fossil remains of more than one species of Swan have been found. The most remarkable is <hi rend="italic">C. falconeri,</hi> which was nearly a third larger than the Mute Swan, and was described from a Maltese cave by Prof. Parker in the Zoological <hi rend="italic">Transactions</hi> (vi. pp. 119— 124, pl. 30). 	<hi rend="smallcaps">(a. n.)</hi></p><p>SWANSEA, a municipal and parliamentary borough and large seaport of Glamorganshire, South Wales, is finely situated in an angle between lofty hills, on the river Tawe,</p><p>near its mouth in the beautiful Swansea Bay, a recess of the Bristol Channel, and on the Great Western, London and North-Western, Midland, and Rhondda and Swansea Bay railway lines, 45 miles west-north-west of Cardiff. Being for the most part of comparatively modern growth, the streets are laid out with great regularity. Swansea retains few traces of antiquity, and some of its more picturesque features have been destroyed to make room for the construction of docks. Of the old castle,</p><p><hi rend="superscript">@@@1</hi> Dr Stejneger (<hi rend="italic">Proc. U. S. Nat. Museum,</hi> 1882, pp. 177-179) has been at much pains to shew that this is no Swan at all, but merely a large Anatine form. Further research may prove that his views are well founded, and that this, with another very imperfectly known species, <hi rend="italic">C. daνidi,</hi> described by Swinhoe <hi rend="italic">{Proc. Zool. Society, </hi>1870, p. 430) from a single specimen in the Museum of Peking, should be removed from the Sub-Family <hi rend="italic">Cygninæ.</hi> Of <hi rend="italic">C. coscοroba </hi>Mr Gibson remarks <hi rend="italic">{Ibis,</hi> 1880, pp. 36, 37) that its “note is a loud trumpet-call,” and that it swims with “the neck curved and the  wings raised after the true Swan model. ”</p><p><hi rend="superscript">@@@2</hi> Commonly quoted as <hi rend="italic">Oud en Niemv Cost Indien</hi> (Amsterdam, 1726). The incidents of the voyage are related in Deel iii. Hoofdst. iv. (which has for its title Description of Banda) pp. 68-71.</p><p><hi rend="superscript">@@@3</hi> The <hi rend="italic">C. unwini</hi> doubtfully described by Mr Hume <hi rend="italic">{Ibis,</hi> 1871, pp. 412, 413) from India, though recognized by Dr Stejneger (<hi rend="italic">ut supra), </hi>seems to be only the immature of the Mute Swan.</p><p><hi rend="superscript">@@@4</hi> The correct scientific nomenclature of the Swans is a matter that offers many difficulties, but they are of a kind far too technical to have any interest for the general reader. Dr Stejneger, in his learned “Outlines of a Monograph” of the group (<hi rend="italic">ut supra),</hi> has employed much research on the subject, with the result (which can only be deemed unhappy) of upsetting nearly all other views hitherto existing, and propounding some which few ornithologists outside of his adopted country are likely to accept, since the principles on which he has gone are not those commonly received, nor (it may perhaps be added) are based on common sense. In the text, as above written, care has been taken to use names which will cause little if any misunderstanding, and this probably is all that can be said in the present state of confusion.</p></body></text></TEI>