<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T21:07:19Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>purchaser, an entry of the surrender and admittance being made upon the court rolls. Formerly a devise of copy- holds could only have been made by surrender to the use of the testator’s will, followed by admittance of the devisee. The Wills Act of 1837 now allows the devise of copyholds without surrender, though admittance of the devisee is still necessary. A surrender must since 8 and 9 Vict. c. 106 be by deed, except in the case of copyholds and of surrender by operation of law. Surrender of the latter kind generally takes place by merger, that is, the combination of the greater and less estate by descent or other means without the act of the party. It has been dealt with by recent legislation (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Remainder).</hi> In Scotch law surrender in the case of a lease is represented by renunciation. The nearest approach to surrender of a copyhold is resignation <hi rend="italic">in remanentiam</hi> (to the lord) or resignation <hi rend="italic">in favorem</hi> (to a purchaser). These modes of conveyance are now practically superseded by the simpler forms introduced by the Conveyancing Act, 1874.</p><p>SURREY, a metropolitan county of England, is bounded north by the Thames, which separates it from Berks and Middlesex, east' by Kent, south by Sussex, and west by Hampshire. Owing to the fact that it includes a portion of London, it ranks fourth among the counties of England in point of population, but in point of size it is only the thirtieth, the total area being 485,129 acres, or 758 square miles.</p><p>The geological structure of Surrey is reflected in its varied and picturesque scenery, the charms of which are enhanced by the large proportion of ground still remaining uncultivated. The extent of common land is also very great, a circumstance which, from its proximity to London, must be considered as specially fortunate. The northern portion of the county, in the London basin, belongs to the Eocene formation : the lower ground is occupied chiefly by the London clay of the Lower Eocene group, stretching (with interruptions) from London to Farnham ; this is fringed on its southern edge by the plastic clays or Woolwich beds of the same group, which also appear in isolated patches at Headley near Leatherhead ; and the Thanet sands of the same group crop out under the London clay between Beddington, Banstead, and Leatherhead. The north-western portion of the county, covered chiefly by heath and Scotch fir, belongs to the Middle Eocene group, or Bagshot sands : the Fox Hills and the bleak Chobham Ridges are formed of the upper series of the group, which rests upon the middle beds occupying the greater part of Bagshot Heath and Bisley and Pirbright Commons, while eastwards the commons of Chobham, Woking, and Esher belong to the lower division of the group. To the south of the Eocene formations the smooth rounded outlines of the chalk hills extend through the centre of the county from Farnham to Westerham (Kent). From Farnham to Guildford they form a narrow ridge called the Hog’s Back, about half a mile in breadth with a high northern dip, the greatest elevation reached in this section being 505 feet. East of Guildford the northern dip decreases, and the outcrop widens, throwing out picturesque summits, frequently partly wooded, and commanding widely variegated views, the highest elevation being Botley Hill near Titsey, 866 feet. The Upper Greensand or grey chalk marl, locally known as firestone, crops out underneath the Chalk along the southern escarpment of the Downs, and the Gault, a dark blue marl, rests beneath the Upper Greensand in the bottom of the long narrow valley which separates the chalk Downs from the well-marked Lower Greensand hills. Leith Hill of this formation reaches a height of 967 feet, and from its isolated position commands one of the finest views in the south of England, the next highest summits being Hindhead Hill (894 feet) and Holmbury Hill (857</p><p>feet). The southern part of the county belongs to the Wealden formation of freshwater origin : the lower strata or Hastings beds occupy a small portion at the southeastern corner, but the greater part consists of a blue or brown shaly clay, amid which are deposited river shells, plants of tropical origin, and reptilian remains.</p><p>The whole of the county north of the Downs is in the basin of the Thames. Besides a number of smaller streams, its chief affluents from Surrey are the Wey at Weybridge, the Mole at East Moulsey, and the Wandle at Wandsworth. The Eden, a tributary of the Medway, takes its rise in the south-east corner of Surrey.</p><p>According to the agricultural returns for 1886, of the total area of the county 299,034 acres were under cultivation, 77,553 being under corn crops, 44,998 under green crops, 26,741 rotation grasses, 138,117 permanent pasture, 2547 hops, and 9078 fallow. There are considerable varieties of soil, ranging from plastic clay to calcareous earth and bare rocky heath. The plastic clay is well adapted for wheat, the most largely grown of the corn crops, occupying 29,694 acres in 1886, while barley, oats, and pease’ which grow well on the loamy soils in different parts of the county, occupied respectively 15,439, 24,705, and 4587 acres, beans occupying 1872 and rye 1256. Of green crops there were 6432 acres under potatoes, 15,975 under turnips and swedes, 9995 mangolds, 860 carrots, 2660 cabbage, kohl-rabi, and rape, and 9076 vetches and other green crops. A considerable proportion of the area under green crops is occupied by the market gardens on the alluvial soil along the banks of the Thames, especially in the vicinity of London. The total area of nursery grounds in 1886 was 1466, and of market gardens 2953 acres. In early times the market gardeners were Flemings, who introduced the culture of asparagus at Battersea and of carrots at Chertsey, for which this district is still famous. The area under orchards in 1886 was 2144 acres. Rhododendrons and azaleas are largely grown in the north-western district of the county. In the neighbourhood of Mitcham various medicinal plants are extensively cultivated for the London herb-sellers and druggists, such as lavender, mint, camomile, anise, rosemary, liquorice, hyssop, &amp;c. The calcareous soil in the neighbourhood of Farnham is well adapted for hops, but this crop in Surrey is of minor importance. There is a considerable area under wood (42,974 acres in 1881). Oak, chestnut, walnut, ash, and elm are extensively planted ; alder and willow plantations are common ; and the Scotch fir propagates naturally from seed on the commons in the north-west of the county. The extent of pasture land is not great, with the exception of the Downs, which are chiefly occupied as sheep-runs. Dairy-farming is a more important industry than cattle-feeding, large quantities of milk being sent to London. The number of horses in 1886 was 9930, of which 3273 were unbroken horses and mares kept solely for breeding; of cattle 49,986, of which 24,869 were cows and heifers in milk or in calf and 8699 other cattle two years old and above ; of sheep 87,658 ; and of pigs 25,172.</p><p>According to the latest (1873) landowners <hi rend="italic">Return</hi> for England, Surrey was divided among 17,293 proprietors possessing 398,746 acres at an annual value of £2,285,814, in addition to which there were 40,037 acres of common lands. Of the proprietors 12,712, or nearly two-thirds, possessed less than one acre each, the total which they owned being 2861 acres. The average annual rental per acre of the land all over was about £5,14s. 9d. The following proprietors held over 5000 acres each:—earl of Lovelace, 9958; crown, 7496; earl of Onslow, 6563 ; Sir W. R. Clayton, 6505; G. W. G. Leveson- Gower, 6368.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Manufactures.—</hi>The more important manufactures are chiefly confined to London and its immediate neighbourhood (see <hi rend="smallcaps">London, </hi>vol. xiv. p. 832). There are paper-mills at Wandsworth, and along the valley of the Wandle there are snuff, drug, and copper mills. Calico bleaching and printing are carried on to a small extent in the same valley, and there are also a few silk mills and tanneries. Ropes, snuff, and drugs are likewise manufactured along the banks of the Mole. Woollen goods and hosiery are made at Godaiming, and gunpowder is largely manufactured at Chilworth.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Communication.—</hi>In addition to the navigation by. barges, steamers ply on the Thames as far as Hampton. The Basingstoke Canal from Basingstoke to the Wey at Weybridge crosses the northwest corner of the county, and the Surrey and Sussex Canal passes southwards from the Wey near Guildford to the Arun. Surrey is more completely supplied by railways than any other county in England, the London, Chatham, and Dover, the South-Eastern, the London, Brighton, and South Coast, and the London and South-Western Railways intersecting it by their main lines as well as by various branches.	.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Administration and Population.—</hi>Surrey contains 14 hundreds ; the borough of Southwark (pop. 221,946), which has.no municipal government, but for certain purposes is connected with the city of</p></body></text></TEI>