<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-19T20:09:57Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>are only passable with difficulty, and in very wet weather the floods cover the banks, and extend so far over the level land on both sides, that the barges cannot be drawn up, from wanting a path on which the men who draw them can securely walk. It is one of the singularities of this navigation, that men are employed instead of horses, as on other rivers, to draw the vessels against the stream. Imperfect as this navigation is, it is, however, the chief source of the wealth of the county, as affording the means of conveying to good markets the various heavy productions which it yields. The fish found in the Severn, in its course through Shropshire, are salmon, pike, flounders, grayling, and eels. There are also some lampreys in the Shropshire part of the Severn, but they are less abundant than in the lower parts of the river. The principal tributary rivers are the Camlet, the Vyrnwey, the Tern, the Clun, the Ony, and the Teme. There are, besides, innumerable rivulets and streams, which adorn and fertilize the country. The lakes of Shropshire, though neither numerous nor extensive, form a variety in its landscapes rarely to be seen in the midland counties of England. Adjoining the town of Ellesmere is a beautiful lake of a hundred and sixteen acres, with some others smaller near it. On the western side of the county is Marton Pool, of forty-five acres. On the north of the Severn are Fennymere, Llynclyspool, and Ancot ; and at Shrawardine is a fine lake of forty acres. That side of the county which most abounds in running streams has few or no lakes. The canals of this county, if not equal in extent to those ip some others, yield to none in their construction, or in the obstacles they have surmounted, or in the beneficial consequences by which they have been followed. The first canal was a private undertaking by a Mr Reynolds, completed in the year 1788, for the conveyance of his ironstone and coals. It was a short canal, but a descent of seventy-three feet was conducted by a well-contrived inclined plane and double railroad, by means of which the loaded boat passing down drew up another with a load nearly equal to one third of its own weight. This contrivance was found to be applicable to similar purposes upon a larger scale, and was speedily adopted by a company who, under the power of an act of parliament, soon constructed the Shropshire Canal, which passes through the most considerable iron and coal works, till it reaches the Severn. The Ellesmere Canal is a most important undertaking, as by it a communication is opened between the Severn and all the great canals and rivers in the north of England. Bristol and Liverpool are thus become connected by inland navigation ; and the rivers Severn, Dee, Mersey, Trent, and Humber, are united for the purposes of conveyance. In districts where the inequalities of the surface would not admit of canals, iron railways have been constructed, on which heavy goods are conveyed, in appropriate waggons, with a great saving in the expense of carriage.</p><p>There are few counties in which the agricultural business is, on the whole, better conducted than Shropshire. The land is very well adapted for the turnip cultivation, and the large flocks of sheep which are commonly fed on that valuable root a great part of the year, supply abundance of manure for the due cultivation of the different kinds of grain. The most prevailing breed of sheep are the Southdown, but many of the New Leicesters are to be seen, and in the hilly parts of the county are many of the fine-woolled Welsh sheep. The meadows on the banks of the Severn, and on the flat lands contiguous to the smaller streams, afford pasturage for numerous cows, whose milk, when converted into cheese, is commonly sold under the denomination of Cheshire. The corn generally cultivated is either wheat, barley, oats, or pease, and the crops on an average equal in productiveness those of the best districts of the kingdom. Hops are grown in small quantities upon that part of the county which adjoins to Herefordshire.</p><p>Some small portions of land are appropriated to the growth of hemp and flax. The cultivation of potatoes has been very much extended of late years, and now furnishes a large proportion of the aliment of the labouring part of the population. The growth of hay, and the cultivation of artificial grasses, are more neglected than any other branch of rural economy. On the flat lands, the deposits from the overflowing of the streams sufficiently enrich them without any artificial manure ; but from the embankments being neglected, the hay produced on such situations is liable to be much injured by the floods that frequently occur in summer.</p><p>A great portion of the wealth of this county consists in the mineral productions, which are most profusely found beneath its surface. The chief of these are lead, iron, limestone, freestone, pipe-clay, and coals. The lead is procured in considerable quantities, chiefly from the mines of the Hope and Snailbeach. The matrix of the ore is crystallized quartz, sulphate and carbonate of barytes, and carbonate of lime. The iron ore is found contiguous to the coal, and frequently close to it. This is especially the case about Colebrook Dale, a division peculiarly rich in those minerals. This district is about eight miles long and two broad, on the banks of the Severn, on the western side of the Wrekin, and running parallel with it, from north-east to south-west. The whole, but especially the southern part, of the coal district, is considerably above the plain of Shropshire, so that at one part the height is five hundred feet above the Severn. The works of the dale supply both ore and coal, as well as limestone, in great quantities ; and every part of the process, from digging the ore to the completion of the manufacture, including the conversion of the coal into coke, is performed on the spot. Arthur Young, describing this part of the county, says, “ Colebrook Dale is a winding glen, between two immense hills, which break into various forms, being all thickly covered, and forming most beautiful sheets of hanging woods. The noise of the forges, mills, furnaces, &amp;c., with all their vast machinery, the flames bursting from the furnaces, with the burning coal, and the smoke of the limekilns, are altogether horribly sublime.” A bridge of cast iron, the first, we believe, constructed in this kingdom, thrown over the Severn, gives to the whole scenery a most romantic appearance. Soon after it was ascertained that iron might be made with coals reduced to the state of coke, as well as from wood, the operation of coking was begun here by Lord Dundonald, with a view to obtain the fossil tar in the course of the process. This operation led to the discovery of that gas, extracted from coal, whose brilliant light now serves to illuminate so many of our streets and public buildings. In this dale was discovered, in opening a coal-mine, a copious spring of fossil tar. It yielded, at first, very plenteously, but the quantity diminished in a few years, and although it still runs, its produce is but of small amount. Though the iron-works in this dale were the first begun, on a large scale, they are by no means confined to it ; for in many other parts of the county they are carried on to an extent that is unequalled in any other country but Great Britain.</p><p>Besides the process of separating the iron from its ore, and bringing it into the state of bar-iron and pig-iron, the other steps in the application of that mineral to general purposes are made within this county. The larger kind of iron goods, whether cast or wrought, are prepared, and most of the iron bridges which have been erected in different parts of the kingdom have been formed here into such a state as only to require to be put together in the places where they were destined to be ultimately fixed. Some of the largest establishments for making porcelain have been formed here, especially that for iron-stone china in Colebrook Dale, which has lowered the price of that beautiful commodity so as to bring it within the reach of <hi rend="italic">a</hi> greater</p></body></text></TEI>