<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-19T20:11:32Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>a most excusable interest in his own play, the young poet clandestinely went. On his return he was placed under arrest. And soon afterwards, being now thoroughly disgusted, and, with some reason, alarmed by the tyranny of the duke, Schiller finally eloped to Mannheim, availing himself of the confusion created in Stuttgard by the visit of a foreign prince.</p><p>At Mannheim he lived in the house of Dalberg, a man of some rank and of sounding titles, but in Mannheim known chiefly as the literary manager (or what is called director) of the theatre. This connection aided in determining the subsequent direction of Schiller’s talents ; and his Fiesco, his Intrigue and Love, his Don Carlos, and his Maria Stuart, followed within a short period of years. None of these are so far free from the faults of the Robbers as to merit a separate notice ; for with less power, they are almost equally licentious. Finally, however, he brought out his Wallenstein, an immortal drama, and, beyond all competition, the nearest in point of excellence to the dramas of Shakspeare. The position of the characters of Max. Piccolomini and the Princess Thekla is the finest instance of what, in a critical sense, is called <hi rend="italic">relief,</hi> that literature offers. Young, innocent, unfortunate, among a camp of ambitious, guilty, and bloodstained men, they offer a depth and solemnity of impression which is equally required by way of contrast and of final repose.</p><p>From Mannheim, where he had a transient love affair with Laura Dalberg, the daughter of his friend the director, Schiller removed to Jena, the celebrated university in the territory of Weimar. The grand duke of that German Florence was at this time gathering around him the most eminent of the German intellects ; and he was eager to enrol Schiller in the body of his professors. In 1799 Schiller received the chair of civil history ; and not long after he married Miss Lengefeld, with whom he had been for some time acquainted. In 1803 he was ennobled ; that is, he was raised to the rank of gentleman, and entitled to attach the prefix of <hi rend="italic">Von</hi> to his name. His income was now sufficient for domestic comfort and respectable independence ; while in the society of Goethe. Herder, and other eminent wits, he found even more relaxation for his intellect, than his intellect, so fervent and so self-sustained, could require.</p><p>Meantime the health of Schiller was gradually undermined : his lungs had been long subject to attacks of disease ; and the warning indications which constantly arose of some deep-seated organic injuries in his pulmonary system ought to have put him on his guard for some years before his death. Of all men, however, it is remarkable that Schiller was the most criminally negligent of his health ; remarkable, we say, because for a period of four years Schiller had applied himself seriously to the study of medicine. The strong coffee, and the wine, which he drank, may not have been so injurious as his biographers suppose ; but his habit of sitting up through the night, and defrauding his wasted frame of all natural and restorative sleep, had something in it of that guilt which belongs to suicide. On the 9th of May 1805 his complaint reached its crisis. Early in the morning he became delirious ; at noon his delirium abated ; and at four in the afternoon he fell into a gentle unagitated sleep, from which he soon awoke. Conscious that he now stood on the very edge of the grave, he calmly and fervently took a last farewell of his friends. At six in the evening he fell again into sleep, from which, however, he again awoke once more to utter the memorable declaration, “ that many things were growing plain and clear to his understanding.” After this the cloud of sleep again settled upon him ; a sleep which soon changed into the cloud of death.</p><p>This event produced a profound impression throughout Germany. The theatres were closed at Weimar, and the funeral was conducted with public honours. The position in point of time, and the peculiar services of Schiller to the</p><p>German literature, we have already stated : it remains to add, that in person he was tall, and of a strong bony structure, but not muscular, and strikingly lean. His forehead was lofty, his nose aquiline, and his mouth almost of Grecian beauty. With other good points about his face, and with auburn hair, it may be presumed that his whole appearance was pleasing and impressive, while in later years the character of sadness and contemplative scnsibility deepened the impression of his countenance. We have said enough of his intellectual merit, which places him in our judgment at the head of the Trans-Rhenish literature. But we add in concluding, that Frederick von Schiller was something more than a great author ; he was also in an eminent sense a great man ; and his works are not more worthy of being studied for their singular force and originality, than his moral character from its nobility and aspiring grandeur.	(w. w. w.)</p><p>SCH1O, a city of the delegation of Verona, in Austrian Lombardy. It stands on the river Timanchio, and carries on some large cloth manufactories, which produce excellent goods of various kinds. It contains 6950 inhabitants.</p><p>SCHIRAS, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Schirauz.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Shiraz.</hi></p><p>SCHISM (from the Greek <hi rend="italic">σχισμα, a rent</hi> or <hi rend="italic">fissure),</hi> in its general acceptation signifies division or separation ; but it is chiefly used in speaking of separations happening from diversity of opinions among people of the same religion and faith. Thus we say the schism of the ten tribes of Judah and Benjamin, the schism of the Persians from the Turks and other Mahommedans, &amp;c. Among ecclesiastical authors, the great schism of the West is that which happened in the times of Clement VII. and Urban VI., which divided the church for forty or fifty years, and was at length ended by the election of Martin V. at the council of Constance. The Romanists number thirty-four schisms in their church, and bestow the name of English schism on the reformation of religion in this kingdom. Those of the church of England apply the term schism to the separation of the nonconformists, viz. the presbyterians, independents, and anabaptists, for a further reformation.</p><p>SCHISMA (<hi rend="italic">σχισμα</hi>), a small theoretical interval in music, arising from the division of the monochord. Two <hi rend="italic">σχισματα </hi>make up a <hi rend="italic">δεισις,</hi> or a <hi rend="italic">λειμμα</hi>.</p><p>SCHISTUS, a name given to several kinds of stones. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Mineralogy.</hi></p><p>SCHITTUAR, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Shitwar,</hi> a small island in the Persian Gulf. Long. 53. 24. E. Lat. 26. 59. N.</p><p>SCHLEGEL, <hi rend="smallcaps">Frederick,</hi> an eminent German critic and philosophical writer, was born at Hanover in 1772, of a family which had already produced more than one writer of ability. He was the third son of the family, being three years younger than his distinguished brother, who is still alive, Augustus William. In his earlier years he is said to have displayed no remarkable genius. Though intended for the mercantile profession, he received an admirable classical education ; and ultimately prevailed on his father to allow him to follow the bent of his own inclination, and to devote himself to literature. He then began to devote himself in earnest to study, which he pursued first at Göttingen and afterwards at Leipsig. From the age of seventeen, as he himself informs us, the writings of the Greek tragedians, and of Plato, combined with Winkelmann’s enthusiastic criticisms on art, formed the intellectual world in which he lived. This admiration for the antique was increased by a visit which he was enabled to pay to Dresden in 1789, where he was for the first time enabled to contemplate, in their marble forms, those gods, heroes, and sages, who had been the companions of his thoughts. “ These firm indelible impressions,” he adds, “ were in succeeding years the firm enduring groundwork for my study of classical antiquity.”</p><p>As might be expected, his first literary effort, which appeared in 1794, took the direction of these his early studies.</p></body></text></TEI>