<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-19T20:11:13Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>is not mentioned in the letters of naturalization which he obtained in France in 1528. He learned the first rudiments of the Latin tongue in his own country ; and in his twelfth year was presented to the Emperor Maximilian, who made him one of his pages. He served that emperor seventeen years, and gave signal proofs of his valour and conduct in several expeditions. He was present at the battle of Ravenna in April 1512, in which he had the misfortune to lose his father Benedict Scaliger, and his brother Titus, on which his mother died with grief ; when, being reduced to necessitous circumstances, he entered into the order of the Franciscans, and applied himself to study at Bologna. But soon afterwards, changing his mind with respect to his becoming a monk, he took arms again, and served in Piedmont ; at which time a physician persuaded him to study physic, which he did at his leisure hours, and also learned Greek ; and at last the gout determined him, at forty years of age, to abandon a military life. He soon afterwards settled at Agen, where he married, and began to apply himself seriously to his studies. He learned first the French tongue, which he spoke perfectly in three months ; and then made himself master of the Gascon, Italian, Spanish, German, Hungarian, and Sclavonian ; but the chief object of his studies was polite literature. Meanwhile, he supported his family by the practice of physic. He did not publish any of his works till he was forty-seven years of age, when he soon gained a great name in the republic of letters. He had a graceful person, and so strong a memory, even in his old age, that he dictated to his son two hundred verses which he had composed the day before, and retained without writing them down. He was so charitable, that his house was as it were an hospital for the poor and sick ; and he had such an aversion to lying, that he would have no correspondence with those who were given to that vice ; but, on the other hand, he had much vanity, and possessed a satirical spirit, which created him many enemies. He died of a retention of urine in 1558. He wrote in Latin, 1. A treatise on the Art of Poetry, and, 2. Exercitatione against Cardan, which works are much esteemed ; 3. Commentaries on Aristotle’s History of Animals, and on Theophrastus on Plants ; 4. Some treatises on Physic ; 5. Letters, Orations, Poems, and other works, in Latin.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Scaliger, </hi><hi rend="italic">Joseph Justus,</hi> one of the most learned critics and writers of his time. He was the son of the former, and was born at Agen, in France, in 1540. He studied in the college of Bordeaux ; after which his father took him under his own care, and employed him in transcribing his poems. By this means he obtained such a taste for poetry, that before he was seventeen years old he wrote a tragedy upon the subject of Œdipus, in which he introduced all the poetical ornaments of style and sentiment. His father having died in 1558, he went to Paris the year following, with a desire to apply himself to the Greek tongue. For this purpose he for two months attended the lectures of Tumebus ; but finding that in the usual course he should be a long time in gaining his point, he shut himself up in his closet, and by constant application for two years gained a perfect knowledge of that language. After this he applied to the Hebrew, which he learned by himself with great facility. He made no less progress in the sciences ; and his writings procured him the reputation of one of the greatest men of that or of any other age. He embraced the reformed religion at twenty-two years of age. In 1563, he attached himself to Louis Casteignier de la Roche Pozay, whom he attended in several journeys ; and, in 1593, he was invited to accept of the place of honorary professor of the university of Leyden, which he complied with. He died of a dropsy in that city in 1609. He was a man of great temperance, was never married, and was so close a student that he often spent whole days in his study without eating ; and though his circumstances were always very narrow, he</p><p>constantly refused the presents that were offered him. He published many works, the principal of which are, 1. Notes on Seneca’s Tragedies, on Varro, Ausonius, Pompeius Festus, &amp;c. ; 2. His Latin Poems ; 3. A treatise de Emendatione Temporum ; 4. Eusebius’s Chronicle, with Notes ; 5. Canones Isagogici ; and many other works. The collections entitled <hi rend="italic">Scaligeriana</hi> were collected from his conversations by one of his friends ; and being ranged into alphabetical order, were published by Isaac Vossius.</p><p>SCALPING, in military history, a barbarous custom, in practice among the Indian warriors, of taking off the tops of the scalps of the enemies’ skulls with their hair on. They preserve them as trophies of their victories, and are rewarded by their chiefs according to the number of scalps which they bring in.</p><p>SCANDARIEH, a village of Irak Arabi, situated on a canal which forms a communication between the Tigris and Euphrates, 120 miles north-west of Bassorah.</p><p>SCANDERBEG, the surname of George Castriot, king of Albania, a province of Turkey in Europe, dependent upon the Ottoman empire. He was delivered up with his three elder brothers as hostages, by their father, to Amurath II. sultan of the Turks, who poisoned his brothers, but spared him on account of his youth, being likewise pleased with his juvenile wit and amiable person. In a short time he became one of the most renowned generals of the age; and revolting from Amurath, he joined Hunniade Corvin, a most formidable enemy of the Ottoman power. He defeated the sultan’s army, took Amurath’s secretary prisoner, and obliged him to sign and seal an order to the governor of Croia, the capital of Albania, to deliver up the citadel and city to the bearer of that order, in the name of the sultan. With this forged order he repaired to Croia, and thus recovered the throne of his ancestors ; and maintained the independency of his country against the numerous armies of Amurath and his successor Mahommed II. who was obliged to make peace with this hero in 1461. He then proceeded to the assistance of Ferdinand of Aragon, at the request of Pope Pius II., and by his assistance Ferdinand gained a complete victory over his enemy the Count of Anjou. Scan- derbeg died in 1467.</p><p>SCANDEROON, a seaport of Syria, on a bay in the south-eastern part of the Mediterranean. About half a mile south is an octagonal castle, well built of hewn stone, called the Castle of Scanderberg, or Alexander. It is surround&lt;<hi rend="superscript">a</hi>d by walls, which are now low ; but each side is defended by a tower. To the north is an old square tower, which is inaccessible on account of the morass. It is now reduced to a village of 185 houses, which owes all its importance to its road, the only one in Syria affording good anchorage, but still subject to sudden squalls. The village is extremely unhealthy, as is indicated by the sallow looks of the inhabitants. It is never exempt from a pestilential fever, which is occasioned by putrid exhalations from the neighbouring marshes during the heats of summer. It is thirty miles north of Antioch, and seventy north-west of Aleppo. Long. 36. 15. E. Lat. 36. 36. N.</p><p>SCANDINAVIA, a general name for the countries of Norway, Sweden, and Denmark, anciently under the dominion of one prince. The inhabitants of these countries, in former times, were excessively addicted to war. From their earliest years they applied themselves to the military art, and accustomed themselves to cold, fatigue, and hunger. Even the very sports of youth and childhood were dangerous. They consisted in taking frightful leaps, climbing up the steepest rocks, fighting naked with offensive weapons, and wrestling with the utmost fury ; so that it was usual to see them grown up to be robust men. and terrible in the combat, at the age of fifteen. At this early age the young men became their own masters, which they did by receiving a sword, a buckler, and a lance. The ceremony</p></body></text></TEI>