<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-19T20:11:04Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>of hills. Some of the streams run into the Elbe, some into the Weser, and others into the Rhine. The land is better ‘ calculated for pasture than for agriculture, and does not produce corn equal to the consumption, but receives supplies from Gotha. There are mines producing copper, others iron, and some coal. These afford some employment to ■ the inhabitants ; but the country is poor, and the means of obtaining subsistence are scanty. The villagers are generally occupied in spinning flax, or in making wood ware and potash from the forests. The cities are Gotha with</p><p>18,321, and Coburg with 9067 inhabitants.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Saxe-Meiningen-Hildburghausen,</hi> a sovereign duchy in Germany. It was two duchies, though now both united under one of the great branches of the Saxon Ernestine family. It extends over 896 square miles, and comprehends thirty-two cities or towns, and 381 villages, with 149,294 inhabitants, of whom 128,000 adhere to the Lutheran profession, and the remainder consists of Catholics and Calvinists, with some Jews. The income of the state amounts to L.110,000, and the expenditure to nearly the same ; but in the latter is included the interest on the public debt, which is heavy when compared with that of the other Saxon duchies, being L.550,000. It is bound to furnish a force of 1150 men to the German Confederation. Meiningen is generally a mountainous country, though none of the hills are higher than 2700 feet, and few exceed 2000 feet. The valleys between these hills are tolerably fertile, and are drained by several small streams, all of which unite in the Werra in its progress to the ocean.</p><p>The agriculture is in a backward state, and, but for the great cultivation of potatoes, would not yield sufficient for the population. Flax is grown equal to the furnishing of employment for the females ; but the chief product for sale beyond the limits of the duchy is timber, and there is also some trade in wool, which has been lately improved by the introduction of merino sheep. Some tobacco is raised ; and a little inferior wine is made in the southernmost parts. The duchy of Hildburghausen is of nearly the same character, except that the soil is more sandy, and the forests of less extent. The meadows are better, and produce some well- fattened black cattle ; and it has some manufactories of iron and glass ware. The only cities in these duchies are Meiningen with 4500 inhabitants, Saatfeld with 4500, and Hildburghausen and Posnect with 3500 each.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Saxe-Weimar-Eisnach,</hi> a sovereign state in Germany, distinguished as a grand duchy, or rather composed of two duchies, which are not contiguous, but are separated by a part of Saxe-Gotha and a part of the Prussian province of Saxony being interposed between them. Some portions also of this dominion are separated from both parts, and surrounded by the territories of other princes. The whole of the grand duchy is 1436 square miles in extent, the duchy of Weimar being 985, and that of Eisenach 451. The population of the whole, which in 1817 amounted to 197,712, had in 1835 increased to 241,046 persons, of whom about one quarter live in the cities and towns, and the remainder in villages and on detached farms. About 220,000 are Lutherans, 10,000 Catholics, 6600 Calvinists, and the remainder are either Jews, or some of the smaller protestant sects. The number of births in 1831 was 7559, and of deaths 5280. The marriages in the same year were 1707. The whole of the dominion is rather hilly, some of the elevations reaching to 1900, and one of them to 2460 feet. Between these hills the valleys are extensive, and of considerable fertility. The most flourishing arc those vales through which run the rivers Saale, Werra, and Ilmenau. The climate, like that of all Thuringia, is raw and cold, and the snow lies late in the summer on the hills; but it is considered as healthy. As the business of husbandry is mostly in the hands of small peasants, and the land cultivated on the common field system, it is, with a few exceptions, imper</p><p>fectly conducted ; but it yields, in the duchy of Weimar, a surplus equal to the deficiency which is annually experienced in the duchy of Eisenach ; and in good seasons is enabled to furnish rye to the mining districts in the kingdom of Saxony. The chief subsistence of the lower orders is potatoes, the extension of which has kept pace with the growth of the population. Flax, hemp, rape, poppies, and hops are grown ; and the sides of the hills, on the red soil, are well planted with plum, cherry, apple, and pear trees, that yield abundant fruit. The extensive forests supply a sufficiency of fuel and timber, and afford employment to large numbers, who manufacture a variety of articles from the wood. The country is most abundantly stocked with game, which, to the annoyance of the peasantry, was most sedulously preserved by the last grand duke. It is said that more than 20,000 hares and 1400 deer have been taken in one year, besides great numbers of wild boars, and some thousands of pheasants. The rivers are also well stocked with fish. The domesticated animals are not numerous, and, except sheep, whose wool has been improved in fineness, deserve no particular mention.</p><p>The chief manufactures are carried on at Eisenach and in its vicinity. They consist of woollen, linen, and cotton cloths, carpets, hosiery, earthenware, glass, leather, and seed- oil. There are mills for spinning cotton, and flax is spun by the peasants in every cottage. In each of the cities there are breweries and distilleries. Much trade arises from the passage of the goods and passengers on the great road through the state from Frankfort to Leipsig, especially at the time of the great fairs at those cities. This grand duchy has a constitution formed by the late sovereign. The states, consisting of twenty-nine members, meet at Weimar for legislative purposes ; but their proceedings attract very little attention. The annual revenue, derived mostly from domains, but partly from direct taxes, amounts to L.130,285 ; and the expenditure, including the interest of the state debt, is L.120,460. The amount of the debt at present is about L.450,000, but it is diminishing yearly. The military force consists of one regiment of infantry and a small corps of hussars. The contingent to be furnished to the German Confederation is 2010 men. Education is sedulously attended to. There is a university at Iena of considerable celebrity, with 590 students and many able professors. There are two gymnasia, sixty-nine burgher schools, and 543 village schools. The cities containing more than 5000 inhabitants were (in 1835) Weimar, 11,005; Eisenach, 9270; and Iena, 5792.</p><p>SAXMUNDHAM, a town and parish of the hundred of Plomsgate, in the county of Suffolk, eighty-nine miles from London. It is situated on a hill, with good prospects around it, and is not well built, but has a large church. It has very little trade, but a market is held on Thursday. The population amounted in 1801 to 855, in 1811 to 957, in 1821 to 989, and in 1831 to 1048.</p><p>SAXO-GRAMMATICUS, descended from an illustrious Danish family, was bom about the middle of the twelfth century. Stephens, in his edition of Saxo-Grammaticus, printed at Soroë, indubitably proves that he must have been alive in 1156; but he cannot ascertain the exact place and time of his birth. On account of his uncommon learning, Saxo was distinguished by the name of <hi rend="italic">Grammaticus.</hi> He was provost of the cathedral church of Roskild, and warmly patronized by the learned and warlike Absalon, the celebrated archbishop of Lunden, at whose instigation he wrote the History of Denmark. His epitaph, which is a dry panegyric in bad Latin verses, gives no account of the era of his death, which happened, according to Stephens, in 1204. His history, consisting of sixteen books, begins from the earliest account of the Danish annals, and concludes with the year 1186. According to the opinion of an accurate writer, the first part, which relates to the origin of the Danes, and the</p></body></text></TEI>