<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-19T20:10:49Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>covery ; but his strength was exhausted. A languor succeeded the vigour which he had formerly enjoyed ; his slow pronunciation did not correspond with the vivacity of his mind, and formed a melancholy contrast to the pleasantness which he had formerly exhibited. He tried in vain to procure the re-establishment of his health ; for all the remedies prescribed by the ablest physicians were wholly ineffectual. His mind afterwards lost its activity; and on the 22d of March 1799, he finished his mortal career, in the fifty-ninth year of his age, lamented by a family to whom he was dear, by a country to which he had done great honour, and by Europe, the knowledge of which he had extended.</p><p>SAUTGUR, a town of the south of India, in the province of Barramahal, among the Eastern Ghauts, thirty miles west from Vellore. Long. 78. 54. E. Lat. 12. 58. N. The pass in the Ghaut beyond this place, approaching the Mysore, has been levelled and improved since the conquest of the country by the British.</p><p>SAUVEUR, <hi rend="smallcaps">Joseph</hi>, an eminent French mathematician, born at La Flèche in 1653. He was absolutely dumb until he was seven years of age ; and even then his organs of speech were not evolved so fully as to permit him to speak without great deliberation. Mathematics were the only studies he had any relish for, and these he cultivated with extraordinary success ; so that he commenced teacher at twenty years of age, and rose so rapidly into vogue, that he had Prince Eugene for his scholar. He became mathematical professor in the royal college in 1686 ; and ten years afterwards was admitted a member of the Academy of Sciences. He died in 1716 ; and his writings, which consist rather of detached papers than of connected treatises, are all inserted in the Memoirs of the Academy of Sciences. He was twice married; and by the last wife he had a son, who, like himself, was dumb for the first seven years of his life.</p><p>SAVA, a town of Persia, now in ruins, in the northern part of the province of Irak. It is still the capital of a district which yields excellent pasture, though strongly impregnated with salt. It is one hundred and eighty miles north-west from Ispahan.</p><p>SAVAGE is a word so well understood as scarcely to require explanation. When applied to inferior animals, it denotes that they are wild, untamed, and cruel ; when applied to man, it is of much the same import with barbarian, and means a person that is untaught and uncivilized, or who is in the rudest state of uncultivated nature.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Savage </hi><hi rend="italic">Island,</hi> in the South Pacific Ocean, discovered by Captain Cook in 1774. It is about thirty-three miles in circumference. Long. 169. 37. W. Lat. 19. 1. S.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Savage, </hi><hi rend="italic">Richard,</hi> one of the most remarkable characters that is to be met with in all the records of biography, was, according to her own confession, the son of Anne countess of Macclesfield by the Earl of Rivers, and was born in 1698. This confession of adultery was made in order to procure a separation from her husband the Earl of Macclesfield ; yet, having obtained this desired end, no sooner was her spurious offspring brought into the world, than, without the dread of shame or poverty to excuse her, she discovered the resolution of disowning him, and, as long as he lived, treated him with the most unnatural cruelty. She delivered him over to a poor woman to educate as her own ; prevented the Earl of Rivers from leaving him a legacy of L.6000, by declaring him dead ; and in effect deprived him of another legacy which his godmother Mrs Lloyd had left him, by concealing from him his birth, and thereby rendering it impossible for him to prosecute his claim. She endeavoured to send him secretly to the plantations ; but this plan being either laid aside or frustrated, she placed him apprentice with a shoemaker. In this situation, however, he did not long continue ; for his nurse having died, he went to take care of the effects of his supposed mother, and found</p><p>in her boxes some letters which discovered to young Savage his birth, and the cause of its concealment.</p><p>From the moment of this discovery it was natural for him to become dissatisfied with his situation as a shoemaker. He now conceived that he had a right to share in the affluence of his real mother ; and therefore he directly, and perhaps indiscreetly, applied to her, and made use of every art to awaken her tenderness and attract her regard. But in vain did he solicit this unnatural parent. She avoided him with the utmost precaution, and took measures to prevent his ever entering her house on any pretence whatever.</p><p>Savage was at this time so touched with the discovery of his birth, that he frequently made it his practice to walk before his mother’s door in hopes of seeing her by accident ; and often did he warmly solicit her to admit him to see her ; but all to no purpose. He could neither soften her heart nor open her hand.</p><p>In the mean time, whilst he was assiduously endeavouring to rouse the affections of a mother in whom all natural affection was extinct, he was destitute of the means of support, and reduced to the miseries of want. We are not told by what means he got rid of his obligation to the shoemaker, or whether he ever was actually bound to him ; but we now find him very differently employed in order to procure a subsistence. In short, the youth had parts, and a strong inclination towards literary pursuits, especially poetry. He wrote a poem, and afterwards two plays, Woman’s a Riddle, and Love in a Veil ; but the author was allowed no part of the profits from the first ; and from the second he received no other advantage than the acquaintance of Sir Richard Steele and of Mr Wilkes, by whom he was pitied, caressed, and relieved. However, the kindness of his friends not affording him a constant supply, he wrote the tragedy of Sir Thomas Overbury, which not only procured him the esteem of many persons of wit, but brought him in L.200. The celebrated Aaron Hill was of great service to him in correcting and fitting this piece for the stage and the press ; and he extended his patronage still further. But Savage was, like many other wits, a bad manager, and was ever in distress. As fast as his friends raised him out of one difficulty, he sunk into another ; and, when he found himself greatly involved, he would ramble about like a vagabond, with scarcely a shirt to his back.</p><p>Mr Hill also earnestly promoted a subscription to a volume of Miscellanies by Savage, and likewise furnished part of the poems of which the volume was composed. To this miscellany Savage wrote a preface, in which he gives an account of his mother’s cruelty in an uncommon strain of humour. The profits of his tragedy and his Miscellanies together had now, for a time, somewhat raised poor Savage both in circumstances and in credit ; so that the world just began to behold him with a more favourable eye than formerly, when both his fame and his life were endangered by a most unhappy event. A drunken frolic in which he one night engaged, ended in a fray, and Savage unfortunately killed a man, for which he was condemned to be hanged. His friends earnestly solicited the mercy of the crown, whilst his mother as earnestly exerted herself to prevent his receiving it. The Countess of Hertford at length laid his whole case before Queen Caroline, and Savage obtained a pardon.</p><p>Savage had now lost that tenderness for his mother which the whole series of her cruelty had not been able wholly to repress ; and considering her as an implacable enemy, whom nothing but his blood could satisfy, threatened to harass her with lampoons, and to publish a copious narrative of her conduct, unless she consented to allow him a pension. This expedient proved successful ; and the Lord Tyrconnel, upon his promise of laying aside his design of exposing his mother’s cruelty, look him into his family, treated him as an equal, and engaged to allow him a pension of L.200 a year. This was the golden part of Savage’s life. He was courted</p></body></text></TEI>