<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-19T20:13:35Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>The silk manufacture in Scotland is still less considerable than that of woollen. The principal seats of it are at Paisley, Glasgow, and Edinburgh. Broad silks, or manufactured goods of entire silk, sold by the yard, viz. gauzes, Persians, satins, and, in general, all broad silks, plain or figured, are made at these places, particularly the two first. Silk mills were established in Edinburgh so late as the year 1838. Handkerchiefs, such as Bandanas and Barcelonas, are made at Paisley and Glasgow, and a few adjacent places in connexion with these towns. Paisley is celebrated for “ mixed goods,” that is, all varieties of manufacture in which silk forms a component part. Edinburgh is eminent chiefly for its shawls of the finest fabrics, but perhaps is surpassed even in this its staple silk production by Paisley. The silk factories contain about 1000 workers. The whole of the factories, of all kinds, in Scotland, namely, those of linen, cotton, woollen, and silk, amounted, in 1837, to 462, (of which 102 are situated in Lanarkshire, 94 in Forfarshire, including Dundee, Arbroath, and other manufacturing towns, and 62 in Renfrewshire,) employing 55,159 persons ; but the number of both has increased considerably since that time.</p><p>Soap has long been manufactured to a very great extent in Scotland ; and the principal seats of the manufacture are Glasgow, Leith, Paisley, Aberdeen, Prestonpans, and Montrose. The quantity made, in 1837, was 12,958,856 lbs., viz. of hard soap, 9,553,855, and of soft, 3,4050,01. The</p><p>quantity exported was 450,956 lbs., the rest being retained or home consumption. The number of licences issued to soapmakers was twenty-one.</p><p>The quantity of whisky produced in Scotland cannot be ascertained before the year 1823, because, previously to that time, owing to the high rate of duty, (5s. 6d. per English wine gallon,) smuggling prevailed to a great extent in almost every district of the country, particularly in the Highlands. But in 1823 the duty was reduced to 2s., though subsequently, namely, in 1826 and 1830, it has been successively raised to 2s. 10d. and 3s. 4d. The following table will shew the quantity that paid duty for home consumption since that time :</p><table><row><cell>Year.</cell><cell>Number of</cell></row><row><cell/><cell>gallons.</cell></row><row><cell>1824</cell><cell>4,350,301</cell></row><row><cell>1831</cell><cell>5,700,689</cell></row><row><cell>1833</cell><cell>5,988,556</cell></row><row><cell>1835</cell><cell>6,013,935</cell></row><row><cell>1838</cell><cell>6,124,035</cell></row></table><p>This is exclusive of the quantity produced for the foreign market. In 1838 there were exported to England, at a duty of 7s. 6d. per gallon, 2,215,329 gallons; and to Ireland, at a duty of 2s. 4d., 861,069 gallons.</p><p><hi rend="italic">official account of the number of distillers, rectifiers, dealers in, and retailers of, spirits in Scotland in</hi> 1833 <hi rend="italic">and</hi> 1834.</p><table><row><cell/><cell>1883.</cell><cell>1834.</cell></row><row><cell>Distillers and rectifiers	</cell><cell>241</cell><cell>209</cell></row><row><cell>Dealers in spirits, not being retailers</cell><cell>543</cell><cell>534</cell></row><row><cell>Retailers of spirits whose premises ) are rated under L.10 per annum J</cell><cell>11,659</cell><cell>11,494</cell></row><row><cell>Retailers at L.10 and under L.20....</cell><cell>4301</cell><cell>4109</cell></row><row><cell>	L.20	—	L.25....</cell><cell>259</cell><cell>222</cell></row><row><cell>	 L.25	_	L.30....</cell><cell>131</cell><cell>133</cell></row><row><cell>	L.30	„	L.40....</cell><cell>151</cell><cell>156</cell></row><row><cell>	 L.40	__	L.50....</cell><cell>64</cell><cell>63</cell></row><row><cell>	 L.50 and upwards	</cell><cell>165</cell><cell>166</cell></row></table><p>The principal seat of this manufacture is Edinburgh and its neighbourhood ; but it prevails extensively in other places. By the following statement it appears that the quantity of strong ale brewed on an average of five years previous to 1830, was 119,551 barrels annually, (the duty being 9s. 10d. per barrel,) and of table beer, on an average of the same time, 250,698 barrels, the duty being 1s. 11<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">2</hi>d. But the duty being repealed in 1830, there are no later accounts of the quantity breweιl. The duty on malt is 20s. 8d. per quarter, and on hops 2d. per lb. The following table gives the number of brewers in Scotland in 1833 and 1834.</p><table><row><cell/><cell>1833.</cell><cell>1834.</cell></row><row><cell>Brewers of strong beer, not exceeding 20 barrels	 </cell><cell>145</cell><cell>154</cell></row><row><cell>Ditto above 20 and not above 50	</cell><cell>43</cell><cell>45</cell></row><row><cell>50	100	</cell><cell>43</cell><cell>33</cell></row><row><cell>100 1000.....</cell><cell>209</cell><cell>204</cell></row><row><cell>1000	</cell><cell>103</cell><cell>116</cell></row><row><cell>Brewers of table beer	</cell><cell>62</cell><cell>52</cell></row></table><p>The manufacture of kelp, which was formed by the incineration of the common sea-wrack, has altogether ceased ; but during the late war it was prosecuted to such an extent, particularly on the shores of the Highlands and Islands, that the total amount produced in Scotland was about 20,000 tons, which usually brought about L.10 per ton, or L.200,000 yearly. At some periods it brought L.20, at others it was as low as L.4 per ton. But since the reduction of the duty on barilla and salt, the manufacture has altogether ceased.</p><p>Scotland has long been famous for its fisheries, which were fora time the subject of bounties and premiums on the part of government ; but it is questionable whether such factitious encouragement was productive of any real or permanent good. Boards for protecting, extending, and encouraging the fisheries were instituted in 1749, 1786, and 1808. But all bounties and premiums have now ceased ; and the branch of industry in question is now thriving at least as well as when encumbered with factitious aid. The salmon fishery of Scotland has long been very considerable. The fishery in the Tweed is the most important, not only in Scotland, but in the empire, though there has of late years been a great decline in the quantity caught. About the end of the late war, the Tweed fishery yielded a rental of from L.15,000 to L.18,000 a-year ; but owing to the falling off in the quantity caught, it does not now yield above L.4000 a-year. In addition to the Tweed, the other most valuable salmon fisheries are in the Forth, Tay, Dee, Don, Findhorn, Spey, Ness, Conon, and other rivers throughout Scotland. The London market is supplied with salmon chiefly by Scotland. The total value of the salmon caught in Scotland has been estimated at L.150,000 a-year.@@<hi rend="superscript">1</hi> Salmon fisheries north of the Tweed and Solway, but not these rivers themselves, are to be shut from the 14th of September to the 1st of February. In the Tweed and its tributary streams, the taking of salmon with the net is prohibited between the 15th of October and 15th February, or with the rod between 7th of November and 15th February. The Solway fisheries, according to the act of Parliament, include all streams that fall into the Solway Firth, embracing the Piltanton, the Luce, and the Bladenoch in Wigtonshire ; the Cree, Fleet, Dee, and Urr in the Stewartry of Kirkcudbright ; as well as the Nith and other rivers in Dumfries-shire. The close season with all of these rivers begins on the 25th of September, and terminates with Piltanton, Luce, Bladenoch, and Cree, as early as the 3lst of December ; with the Fleet</p><p><hi rend="superscript">@@@1</hi> Loudon’s Encyclopedia of Agriculture. General Report of Scotland, iii. 327.</p></body></text></TEI>