<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-19T20:14:08Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sect.</hi> XL—<hi rend="italic">Quotations by the early Ecclesiastical Writers from the Sacred Scriptures.</hi></p><p>Besides the object to which these have been already applied, as showing the authenticity of the sacred documents, they serve also a useful purpose to the critic, in furnishing him with numerous readings, in assisting to determine the age, origin, and country, of remarkable readings, and in illustrating the whole history of the Greek texts of Scripture. Care, however, must be taken to discriminate between passages quoted freely from memory, or adapted to the construction and sentiment of the writer himself who quotes, and those which are formally cited from the codex. We must also be sure that the work in which the quotation occurs is genuine, and that the common text of the places in which the citation occurs is correct.</p><p>Ernesti’s Principles of Interpretation, by Terrot, vol. ii. p. 90-113 ; Schott, <hi rend="italic">Isagοge,</hi> p. 629.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sect.</hi> XII.—<hi rend="italic">Laws for the Determination of various Readings.</hi></p><p>1. That reading is to be regarded as true, which is supported by far the greater number of copies and witnesses ; but still readings supported by a few books are not entirely to be disregarded, especially when they harmonise with the <hi rend="italic">usus loquendi</hi> of the author. 2. That reading which the better copies exhibit, unless special reasons prohibit it, is to be preferred to the one which the inferior copies exhibit, although most numerous. Neither the antiquity nor propriety of a reading, solely considered, always proves it to be a true one. 3. That reading which is more harsh, obscure, difficult, unusual, or delicately chosen, if supported by the authority of a proper witness, is preferable to one which is plain, easy, usual, and common. 4. That reading which approaches nearest to the popular and familiar method of speaking, if it be supported by external testimonies, is preferable to one which is more artificial and subtle. 5. The shorter reading, when supported by testimony of importance, and not incongruous with the style and design of the writer, is preferable to a more verbose one. Still there are cases where the more copious reading is to be preferred. 6. That reading which gives the best sense is peculiarly preferable. But to determine this, the nature of the whole passage, and the genius of the writer, not the mere opinions and sentiments of particular interpreters, are to be consulted. 7. The reading which produces an unworthy or incongruous sense is to be rejected. Good care, however, must be taken not to condemn a reading as unworthy or incongruous, which a more correct grammatical and historical investigation would prove to be a true reading, or at least a probable one. 8. A reading which agrees with the <hi rend="italic">usus loquendi</hi> of the writer, is preferable to that which disagrees with it. It must be remembered in judging here, that the style of an author sometimes varies with increasing age. 9. A reading is to be rejected, in respect to which plain evidence is</p><p>found that it has undergone a <hi rend="italic">designed</hi> alteration. Such alteration may have taken place, <hi rend="italic">first,</hi> from doctrinal reasons, Matthew, i. 18 ; Mark, viii. 31, xiιi. 32 : <hi rend="italic">second,</hi> from moral and practical reasons, Matthew, v. 22 : <hi rend="italic">third,</hi> from historical and geographical doubts, Matthew, viii. 28, comp. Mark, v. 1 : <hi rend="italic">fourth,</hi> from the desire of reconciling pas sages inconsistent with each other, Mark, viii. 31 : <hi rend="italic">fifth, </hi>from desire to make the discourse more intensive ; hence many emphatic readings have originated : <hi rend="italic">sixth,</hi> from the comparison of many manuscripts, the readings of which have been amalgamated : <hi rend="italic">seventh,</hi> from a comparison of parallel passages. Corrections of the more celebrated manuscripts have been sometimes detected. 10. Various readings are to be <hi rend="italic">rejected</hi> which spring from the mere negligence of copyists, and from those errors which are very common in all kinds of books. To these belong, <hi rend="italic">first,</hi> the commutation of unusual forms for those of the common dialect ; the Alexandrine or common form, however, has the preference over others in the New Testament ; and this dialect itself also admitted some Attic forms : <hi rend="italic">second,</hi> the commutation of single letters and syllables, by an error of either the eye or the ear ; the former resulting from obscure and compendious methods of writing, or from the similarity of certain letters, such as A Δ Λ, Ο Θ, &amp;c. ; the latter, from copying after the reading of one who was misunderstood, or who read erroneously : <hi rend="italic">third,</hi> the commutation of synonyms : <hi rend="italic">fourth,</hi> from transferring into the text words written in the margin of copies, and thus uniting both readings, James, v. 2 : <hi rend="italic">fifth,</hi> from the omission or insertion of a word or a verse, by an error of the sight : <hi rend="italic">sixth,</hi> from the transposition of words and passages, whence it may have happened that some error has crept into most of our books : <hi rend="italic">seventh,</hi> from words which ended with the like sound, or appeared alike ; and from proximate words, one ending and the other beginning with the same syllable : <hi rend="italic">eighth,</hi> from incorrectly uniting or separating words, which naturally resulted, in some cases, from the ancient method of <hi rend="italic">continuous writing ;</hi> and, <hi rend="italic">ninth,</hi> from an erroneous inter- punction and distinction of passages. 11. A reading is to be rejected which plainly betrays a gloss or interpretation. This may be a word or a whole passage. Sometimes these glosses are united to the true text, and sometimes they have thrust it out. All interpretations, however, are not spurious glosses ; for authors themselves sometimes add them, in order to explain their own language. 12. Readings deduced merely from versions or the commentaries of interpreters are to be rejected.</p><p>The above are taken, with a few slight alterations, from Beckii <hi rend="italic">Monogramιnata Hermenctιtices, Lib. Nov. Test.</hi> Lips. 1803, as translated by Mr Moses Stuart in his Elements of Biblical Criticism and Interpretation, London (reprinted with additional observations by E. Henderson, D. Ph.), 1827. See also Michaelis, Introd. vol. i. p. 246—339 ; Ernesti’s Principles of Interpretation, by Terrot, vol. ii. p. 114 ; Marsh’s Lectures, lect. iii. ; Horne’s Introd. vol. ii. p. 251-260.</p><p>For remarks upon particular books of the Bible, see the articles in this work under the names of the different books, or their authors, as <hi rend="smallcaps">PeNTAteucH, Moses, Joshua, Paul, Peter, &amp;c.	(ν. ν. ν. ν.)</hi></p><p>SCRIVENER, one who draws contracts, or whose business it is to place money at interest.</p><p>SCROLL, in <hi rend="italic">Heraldry.</hi> See that article.</p><p>SCRUPLE, <hi rend="smallcaps">Scrupulus,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Scrupulum,</hi> the least of the</p><p>weights used by the ancients, which amongst the Romans was the twenty-fourth part of an ounce, or the third part of a dram. The scruple is still among us a weight, containing the third part of a dram, or twenty grains. Among goldsmiths it is twenty-four grains.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Scruple,</hi> in Chaldæan chronology, is the <hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">1080</hi>th part of an hour, called by the Hebrews <hi rend="italic">helakin.</hi> These scruples are</p><p>much used by the Jews, Arabs, and other eastern people, in computations of time.</p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Scruples</hi><hi rend="italic"> of half Duration,</hi> an arc of the moon’s orbit, which the moon’s centre describes from the beginning of an eclipse to its middle.</p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Scruples</hi><hi rend="italic"> of Immersion or Incidence,</hi> an arc of the moon’s orbit, which her centre describes from the beginning of the eclipse to the time when its centre falls into the shadow.</p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Scruples</hi><hi rend="italic"> of Emersion,</hi> an arc of the moon’s orbit, which her centre describes in the time from the first emersion of the moon’s limb to the end of the eclipse.</p></body></text></TEI>