<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-19T20:09:37Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>esteemed by a large number of his townsmen, his reputation as an anti-reformer preponderated over his less equivocal merits, and he lost his election.</p><p>In his public career Mr Sadler was generally associated with the old constitutional Tories. We have already mentioned his strenuous opposition to the Roman Catholic Relief Bill. To the policy of free trade he was also most decidedly hostile ; nor was he less unfriendly to the settlement of the currency question, which he considered should have been effected upon a more equitable adjustment. Mr Sadler was likewise very hostile to the Reform Bill, to which he recorded his objections in a speech when seconding General Gascoigne’s motion, the effect of carrying which was the dissolution of parliament. For Ireland he always expressed the deepest interest, and twice introduced a poor-law bill for that country into parliament. During the last session he sat in parliament, he was almost constantly occupied in prosecuting the bill he had brought before the legislature for the protection of children employed in the manufactories, and which is familiarly called the Ten Hours Bill. This measure was referred to a select committee, of which Mr Sadler was appointed chairman ; and it is believed that the fatigue and responsibility thus imposed on him, of collecting the mass of evidence contained in the report, laid the foundation of his long and fatal illness. Neither, after all, were his efforts successful in passing this measure.</p><p>Mr Sadler was some years a member of the Royal Society, and author of several works, the most important of which are, 1. Ireland, its Evils, and their Remedies ; and, 2. An Essay on the Law of Population, in two volumes, written principally to controvert the opinions of Mr Malthus. A third volume, intended to complete this treatise, the author was engaged upon at the time of his death, which took place at New Lodge, near Belfast, on the 29th of July 1835. Mr Sadler’s disease appears to have been an incurable affection of the heart, brought on by severe study and intense anxiety. At the time of his death, he was the leading partner of the firm of Sadler, Fenton, and Company, of Belfast.	<hi rend="smallcaps">(a.)</hi></p><p>SADO, an island of Japan, about ninety miles in circumference, on the northern coast of the island of Niphon, in a large bay. Long. 138. 54. E. Lat. 37. 40. N.</p><p>SADOC, a famous Jewish rabbi, and founder of the sect of the Sadducees.</p><p>SADOLET, <hi rend="smallcaps">James,</hi> a learned cardinal, was born at Modena in 1477. Leo X. made him and Peter Bembo his secretaries, an office for which they were both well qualified; and Sadolet was soon afterwards made bishop of Carpen- tras, near Avignon. He was made a cardinal in 1536 by Paul III. ; employed in several negotiations and embassies ; and died in 1547, not without the suspicion of poison, for corresponding too familiarly with the Protestants, and testifying too much regard for some of their doctors. His works, which are all in Latin, were collected in 1607 at Mentz, in one volume 8vo. All his contemporaries spoke of him in the highest terms.</p><p>SADRAS, a town of Southern India, in the Carnatic, on the sea-coast. It was formerly a small village, which was purchased by the Dutch about the middle of the seventeenth century; and under their protection it grew up into a populous place, the seat of a flourishing manufacture of ginghams of a superior quality. It was surrounded by them with a brick wall fifteen feet in height, and close to the sea. The fort was seized by the French general Lally in the year 1759, while the French were besieging Madras, though the Dutch were neutral in the war. It was afterwards restored to Holland, and was finally taken possession of by the British in 1795. The town has now fallen into a state of decay. At a short distance are some hills, on which are situated seven Hindu temples, held in great estimation. Long. 80. 16. E. Lat. 12. 27. N.</p><p>SAFAD, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Saphet,</hi> a village of Palestine, in an elevated situation, which overlooks the western coast of the Lake of Tiberias, and was of some consideration in the time of the crusades; but in 1759, being destroyed by an earthquake, and since regarded with an evil eye by the Turks, it has now dwindled into a poor village. Pococke found in it the ruins of a very strong old castle, which appeared to have commanded the whole surrounding district, which takes its name from the place. It is sixty-five miles south-west from Damascus.</p><p>SAFFRON is formed of the stigmata of the <hi rend="italic">crocus officinalis,</hi> dried upon a kiln, and pressed together into cake;. There are two kinds of saffron, the English and Spanish ; but the latter is by far the most esteemed. Saffron is principally cultivated in Cambridgeshire. This drug has been reckoned a very elegant and useful aromatic. Besides the virtues it has in common with other substances of the same class, it has been accounted one of the highest cordial.</p><p>SAFFRON-WALDEN, a town in the hundred of Ut- tlesford, in the county of Essex, forty-two miles from London. It has a good market for corn, which is held on Saturday. It is a borough, whose charter was granted by Edward VI., and is governed by a mayor and aldermen ; but it does not return a member to the House of Commons. The chief trade is preparing malt for the great breweries in London. The church is a fine Gothic building of great extent, and adorned by the monuments of many eminent persons who have been buried in it. Adjoining to the town is the magnificent house of Audley End, belonging to Lord Howard of Walden. The town has the benefit of water-communication with London. The population amounted in 1801 to 3181, in 1811 to 3403, in 1821 to 4154, and in 1831 to 4762.</p><p>SAFFY, <hi rend="smallcaps">Saffee, SaFI, Azafi,</hi> or <hi rend="smallcaps">Asfee,</hi> is a seaport town of Morocco, capital of the province of Ahda. It is situated between two hills, and at the foot of a steep and high mountain, a part of Atlas. Its position renders it extremely hot, and in winter very disagreeable, as the waters from the neighbouring mountains, occasioned by the rains, discharge themselves through the main street into the ocean, deluging the lower apartments of the houses. The walls of Saffy are extremely thick and high. It is a very ancient town, and was the chief seat of European commerce till the monopolizing predilections of the Emperor Sidi Mahommed transferred it to Mogadore. The roadstead is safe in summer ; but in winter, w hen the winds blow from the south or south-west, vessels are obliged to run to sea, sometimes more than once whilst taking in their cargoes. The surrounding country abounds in corn, and two falls of rain a year are sufficient to bring the crops to maturity. There are many sanctuaries in the environs, on which account the Jews are obliged to enter the town barefooted, taking off their sandals when they approach these consecrated places ; and if riding, they must descend from their mules and enter the town on foot. There is here a neat palace, and a fort stands at a little distance north of the town. Sally is still supposed to retain a population of 12,000. Long. 9. 5. W. Lat. 32. 20. N.</p><p>SAFIA, a small river of Arabia, which falls into the Red Sea two miles north of Tor.</p><p>SAFRA, a town of Hedjaz, in Arabia, forty miles south- south-west of Medina.</p><p>SAGAING, a town in the Burmese dominions, situated on the Irrawaddy, opposite to Ava, the capital. It is a large, straggling place, where the houses are of a mean description, and thinly scattered among groves of fruit-trees, with temples and monasteries innumerable. A considerable portion of the inhabitants are Cassay captives or their descendants. On the river face it has a brick-wall, which extends for about half a mile ; it is not above ten feet in height, but has a parapet and embrasures. To each flank of the brick-</p></body></text></TEI>