<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-19T20:09:19Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>tempt by the surrounding nations, who derided them no less for their sabbaths than
                for their circumcision. All sorts of writers ridiculed them on this account. Seneca
                charged them with spending the seventh part of their time in sloth. Tacitus said,
                that not only the seventh day, but also the seventh year, was unprofitably wasted.
                Juvenal brings forward the same charge ; and Persius upbraided them with their <hi
                    rend="italic">recutita sabbata.</hi> Plutarch said that they kept it in honour
                of Bacchus ; Tacitus affirmed that it was in honour of Saturn ; but the most
                abominable assertion of all is that of Apion, who said that they observed the
                Sabbath in memory of their being cured on that day of a shameful disease, called by
                the Egyptians <hi rend="italic">sabbo.</hi></p>
            <p>Some, perceiving the force of this objection, have contended that time was divided
                into weeks of seven days, that each of the planetary gods, the Sun, Moon, Mercury,
                Venus, Mars, Jupiter, and Saturn, who were the <hi rend="italic">Dii majorum
                    gentium,</hi> might have a day appropriated to his service. But if such was the
                origin of weeks, how came the great and ancient goddess Tellus to be omitted ? She
                was worshipped by the early idolaters as well as the other planets, and must surely
                have been deemed by them as worthy of a particular day set apart to her honour as
                the planet Saturn, who was long undiscovered, afterwards seen but occasionally, and
                at all times considered as of malign aspect.</p>
            <p>Others have supposed, that as the year was divided into lunar months of something
                more than twenty-eight days, it was natural to divide the months into quarters from
                the different phases of the moon, which would produce as many weeks of seven days.
                But this supposition is less tenable than the former. The phases of the moon are not
                so precisely marked at the quarters as to attract to them any particular notice ;
                nor are the quarterly appearances of one month commonly like those of another. We
                cannot, therefore, conceive what should have induced the earliest observers of the
                phases of the moon to divide the month into four parts rather than into three, or
                five, or seven. Had the ancient week consisted of fourteen days, it might have been
                inferred, with some degree of plausibility, that its length was regulated by the
                phases of the moon, because the shape of that luminary, at the end of the second
                quarter, is very precisely marked; but there is nothing which, in the present
                hypothesis, could have everywhere led mankind to make their weeks consist of seven
                days. This division of time, therefore, can be accounted for only by admitting the
                primeval institution of the Sabbath, as related by Moses in the book of Genesis.
                That institution was absolutely necessary to preserve among men a sense of religion
                ; and it was renewed to the Jews at the giving of the law, and its observance
                enforced by the severest penalties. It was accordingly observed by them with more or
                less strictness in every part of their commonwealth ; and there is none of the
                institutions of their divine lawgiver which, in their present state of dispersion,
                they more highly honour. They regard it, indeed, with a superstitious reverence,
                call it their spouse, their delight, and speak of it in the most magnificent terms.
                They have often varied in their opinions of the manner in which it ought to be kept.
                In the time of the Maccabees, they carried their respect for the sabbath so very
                high, that they would not on that day defend themselves from the attacks of their
                enemies. But afterwards they did not scruple to stand upon their necessary defence,
                although they would do nothing to prevent the enemy from carrying on their
                operations. When our Saviour was on earth, it was no sin to loose a beast from the
                stall and lead him to water ; and if he had chanced to fall into a ditch, they
                pulled him out. But now it is absolutely unlawful to give a creature in that
                situation any other assistance than that of f∞d ; and if they lead an animal to
                water, they must take care not to let the bridle or halter hang loose, otherwise
                they are transgressors.</p>
            <p>As the law enjoins rest on that day from all servile employments, in order to comply
                with the injunction, they undertake no kind of work on Friday but such as can easily
                be accomplished before evening. In the afternoon they put into proper places the
                meat that they have prepared to eat the day following. They afterwards set out a
                table covered with a clean cloth, and place bread upon it, which they also cover
                with another cloth ; and during the sabbath the table is never moved out of its
                place. About an hour before sunset, the women light the sabbath lamps, which hang in
                the places where they eat. They then stretch forth their hands to the light, and
                pronounce the following benediction. “ Blessed be thou, O God, king of the world,
                who hast enjoined us, that are sanctified by thy commandments, to light the sabbath
                lamp.” These lamps are two or more in number, according to the size of the chamber
                in which they are suspended, and continue to burn during the greater part of the
                night. In order to begin the sabbath well, they wash their hands and faces, trim
                their hair, and pair their nails, beginning at the fourth finger, then going to the
                second, then the fifth, then the third, and ending with the thumb. If a Jew casts
                the parings of his nails to the ground, he is <hi rend="italic">rascah,</hi> that
                is, a wicked man ; for Satan has great power over those parings of nails ; and it
                seems they are of great use to the wizards, who know how to employ them in their
                enchantments. If he buries them in the earth, he is <hi rend="italic">tzedic,</hi>
                that is, a just man ; if he burns them in the fire, he is <hi rend="italic"
                    >chesid,</hi> that is, worthy of honour, or an holy man. When they have
                performed these preparatory ceremonies, they repair to the synagogue, and enter upon
                their devotions. As soon as prayers begin, the departed souls spring out of the
                purgatorial flames, and have liberty to cool themselves in water while the sabbath
                lasts, for which reason the Jews prolong the continuance of it as much as they can ;
                and the rabbin have strictly commanded them not to exhaust all the water on the
                sabbath day, lest those miserable souls should by these means be deprived of the
                refreshing element. When they have ended their prayers, they return home, and salute
                one another, by wishing a good sabbath. They then sit down to table. The master of
                the family takes a cup full of wine, and lifting up his hand, says, “ Blessed be
                thou, O God our Lord, king of the world, who hast created the fruit of the vine.
                Blessed be thou, O God our Lord, king of the world, who hast sanctified us by thy
                commandments, and given us thy holy sabbath ; and of thy good will and pleasure hast
                left it to us an inheritance, the memorial of thy works of creation. For it is the
                beginning of the congregation of saints, and the memorial of the coming out of
                Egypt. And thou hast also chosen us from all other people, and sanctified us, and
                with love and pleasure hast left thy holy sabbath an inheritance. Blessed be thou, O
                God, who sanctifiest the sabbath.” After this benediction is ended, he drinks, and
                gives the cup to all who are present. He then removes the cloth, and taking bread,
                says, “ Blessed be thou, O God our Lord, king of the world, who bringest bread out
                of the earth.” Then he breaks off a bit, and eats, and also gives a piece of it to
                every one of the company.</p>
            <p>On the morning of the sabbath, the Jews do not rise so early as they do at other
                times, thinking, the greater pleasure they take on that day, the more devoutly they
                keep it. When they come into the synagogue, they pray as usual, only the devotions
                are somewhat longer, being intermingled with psalmody, in honour of the sabbath. The
                pentateuch is then produced, and seven sections of it are read in order by seven
                persons chosen for the purpose. Several lessons are likewise read out of the
                prophets, which have some relation to what was read out of the law. After morning
                prayers, they return to their houses, and eat the second sabbath-meal, showing every
                token of joy, in honour of the festival. But if one has seen any thing ominous in
                his</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
