<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-19T20:13:13Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>the Roman law is well known. Accordingly in 1503, the court of daily council., which
                was essentially a revival of the former court of the session, was established by
                means of Bishop Elphinstone. And at length, whilst the kingdom was yet in a state of
                distraction from the fatal losses at Flodden, the present Court of Session or
                College of Justice was instituted ; and of the numerous attempts of the clergy to
                establish the Roman law as the common law of the land, this was the last and most
                successful.</p>
            <p>According to the simple principles of our old law, all suits originated by plaint,
                claim, or summary application to the judge, setting forth the cause of action; and
                the judge was bound of common right to administer justice therein. But afterwards, a
                maxim was introduced that the judges were substitutes of the crown, and consequently
                should take cognisance only of what was specially referred to them. Brieves or
                mandatory letters from the king to the judges were then invented ; and the chancel
                of the royal chapel became the great <hi rend="italic">officina justitiæ,</hi> the
                shop or mint where the king’s writs were framed, and sold out to parties injured,
                according to the exigency of the case. These writs issued out from the chancel or
                chancery until the institution of the College of Justice, when the chancellor and
                clergy, who were the principal judges there, began a mint or shop of their own in
                the <hi rend="italic">Bill chamber</hi> of the court, so called because the brieves,
                or, as they are here termed <hi rend="italic">letters,</hi> issue out, not on the
                oral application of the party, but on his “ bill” or written supplication. This
                course of proceeding was adopted from the court of Rome ; and it is observable, that
                in both cases the language employed is sometimes identical. Thus, when the request
                or prayer of the bill is granted, the judgment is, <hi rend="italic">Fiat ut
                    petitur,</hi> which are the very words used by the Pope in the like case ; and
                tire odd phrase, “Finds the letters orderly proceeded,” is but a verbal translation
                of the <hi rend="italic">Male appellatum et bene processum</hi> of the papal court.
                The names of the letters are also the same, letters of advocation ion, suspension,
                and reduction, being equally well known in both places ; and letters of horning,
                caption, and relaxation, have their papal origin impressed upon them. The comparison
                might be carried through our whole process to its minutest technicality, and also to
                the style and habit of the judges. After the manner of the ecclesiastical tribunals,
                too, the judges deliberated in secret conclave with shut doors, parties and their
                counsel, and all others being removed (1537, c. 66); and there was no report of the
                judges’ opinions, or of the reasons of the judgment, but only of the vote or
                sentence. At the Revolution, however, the court was thrown open ; but so powerful is
                custom over all men, that to this day the great body of the practitioners continue
                to walk the Outer House.</p>
            <p>In modem times the court has been altered in almost every particular; its
                constitution and jurisdiction, the number of the judges, the distribution of the
                business, and the forms of proceeding. The machinery was indeed bad, but the spirit
                which pervaded it was worse ; and the best antidote to this would perhaps be the
                full force of public opinion, that is, perfect publicity, not merely of hearing and
                judgment, but of every step in the administration of justice.</p>
            <p>According to its first institution, the court consisted of a president and fourteen
                ordinary lords, half of the temporal estate and half spiritual, of which the
                president likewise was one. The Lord Chancellor, who was also an ecclesiastic, was
                made principal of the college, as it was termed, and as such had a vote with the
                judges; and there was a</p>
            <p>reserved power to the king to appoint, at his pleasure, three or four extraordinary
                lords, a power which the crown always exercised, and also sometimes greatly abused.
                It was the Reformation which gave the first blow to the court. From that event it
                began to lose its ecclesiastical, which had been its earliest and most
                distinguishing feature. The Revolution followed, and opened up to the public eye the
                heretofore secret tribunal. And at the union with England it ceased to be supreme,
                though this last peculiarity, and that by which <hi rend="italic">the Lords</hi>
                became so formidable in the country, was long struggled for, and is yet perhaps but
                imperfectly given up by the court. These important changes, however, affected the
                spirit and character of the court, rather than its external form, which remained
                much as it was before. But they prepared the way for alterations there too ; and
                during the last thirty years, a great number of public statutes have been passed,
                altering the details of the court, and otherwise regulating the administration of
                justice throughout the kingdom.</p>
            <p>In 1808, the commencement of the period just referred to, the court was formed into
                two divisions; or, in effect, two communicating but equal and independent courts.
                The reason assigned for this change, was the greatly increased number of lawsuits
                from the great extension of agriculture, commerce, manufactures, and population, and
                the consequent multiplication of transactions in Scotland. There is every ground to
                believe, however, that much of the supposed business was caused by the tedious
                methods of proof and written pleadings adopted by the court, and its endless
                judgments and rehearings; for in the degree in which these have been abolished, the
                court has been able to absorb and dispatch the business of the other superior
                courts, and still to allow a decrease in the number of its judges. These are now
                only thirteen in all. Each division is composed of four judges ; the Lord President,
                who is properly head of the whole court, presiding in the First Division, and the
                Lord Justice-Clerk presiding in the Second. The remaining judges sit separately in
                the Outer House, as Lords Ordinary. This term was originally given to all the judges
                under the president, and they served in the Outer House by rotation; but amongst
                other recent changes, the five junior judges were at first made permanent Lords
                Ordinary, as attached to a particular division of the Inner House, but now without
                any such relation. The junior or youngest Lord Ordinary of all is Ordinary on the
                Bills, and has a peculiar class of cases assigned to him. But it is to be observed,
                that from him, and from the other Ordinaries, an appeal lies, or a proceeding in the
                nature of an appeal, to the Inner House; which, besides this appellate, has also
                some original jurisdiction. It is not necessary to add, that there is much
                imperfection in this whole system of judicature. There appears to have been little
                unity of design in its formation ; there is considerable complexity in its actual
                working, and there is no great satisfaction in its results.@@<hi rend="superscript"
                    >1</hi></p>
            <p>Let us now turn our attention to the local courts throughout the kingdom.</p>
            <p>In early times the realm was divided into provinces, clanships, or counties, in each
                of which was a maormor, maor, mayor or mair, as the king’s executive and ministerial
                officer; and in every county or province there were divers judges, each exercising
                judicial functions. The provinces and judicial districts of those times, however,
                are now but imperfectly known; and, as might be expected, the series of mayors and
                judges cannot by any means be made out. With re-</p>
            <p><hi rend="superscript">@@@1</hi> In the year 1800, the number of causes enrolled in
                the Outer House, was 2413 ; in 1810, it was 2643 ; in 1820, it was 2069 ; and in
                1831, it was 1056. In the years 1836 and 1837, the business stood thus :—</p>
            <table>
                <row>
                    <cell>Year.</cell>
                    <cell>Causes Enrolled.</cell>
                    <cell>Decrees in Absence.</cell>
                    <cell>Decrees in force by Lords Ordinary.</cell>
                    <cell>Reclaiming Notes to Inner House.</cell>
                    <cell>Decrees in force by Inner House.</cell>
                    <cell>Average Number of Appeals to House of Lords.</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>1836.</cell>
                    <cell>1.770</cell>
                    <cell>546</cell>
                    <cell>710</cell>
                    <cell>456</cell>
                    <cell>382</cell>
                    <cell rows="2"> 45</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>1837,</cell>
                    <cell>1,565</cell>
                    <cell>564</cell>
                    <cell>600</cell>
                    <cell>356</cell>
                    <cell>375</cell>
                </row>
            </table>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
