<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-19T20:13:15Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>spect to the latter, viz., the Celtic judge, we have not traced him to a later period
                than the beginning of the fourteenth century. He was in all probability extinguished
                during king Edward’s invasion of Scotland in the unhappy times which followed on the
                death of king Alexander the Third. The sheriff was then universally established ;
                and as that officer engrossed to himself the functions both of the judge and mair,
                the former disappeared entirely from our annals, whilst the latter gradually
                degenerated into the sheriff's officer, with whom, accordingly, he is, to the
                present day, found mixed up in some of the northern counties.</p>
            <p>The most ancient sheriff was certainly the <hi rend="italic">comes</hi> or earl.
                There is no direct evidence to that effect, however ; and from a remote time, the
                officer so called was the <hi rend="italic">vice-cornes. </hi>The office was not a
                century in existence amongst us, when, falling into the hands of the great local
                proprietors, it began to descend to heirs with the paternal estate. The sheriffship
                of Ayr, which was erected in the year 1221, out of the bailiaries of Kyle, Carrick,
                and Cuningham, was from the first hereditary. It is not surprising that the
                hereditary <hi rend="italic">vice-cornes</hi> should soon cense to perform in person
                the duties of his office; these were accordingly devolved on a deputy or <hi
                    rend="italic">sub-vice-comes.</hi> The earliest officer of this sort we have met
                with, is <hi rend="italic">Alan de Pilch,</hi> or Alan of the hairy garment,
                sub-vice-comes de Inverness, temp. Robert I.;@@<hi rend="superscript">1</hi> but
                sheriff- deputes are mentioned much earlier,@@<hi rend="superscript">1</hi> and to
                such an extent was the abuse of deputation carried, that in some counties, that of
                Cromarty for instance, the district was partitioned into various
                deputy-sheriffships, and individuals appointed, such as officers of the army,
                medical men, and others, in situations of life perfectly incompatible with the due
                discharge of the office. The office also in many instances became hereditary; and
                another was required to execute the active duties of the place, or <hi rend="italic"
                    >pro-sub-vice-cornes.</hi> Thus, at the time of the jurisdiction act in 1747,
                there were in most or all of the counties, omitting the <hi rend="italic"
                    >comes,</hi> count or earl, a sheriff-principal or high sheriff, and
                sheriff-depute, and a sheriff-substitute. All these were continued by the above act;
                but the judicial powers were confined to the two last, whose duties and
                qualifications have also been repeatedly regulated. It would undoubtedly have been
                more agreeable to principle, however, to have abolished offices which grew out of
                the abuses of the times, and assigned to every sheriff a reasonable district in
                respect of extent and population, with constant residence therein, and the exercise
                of judicial functions only. In determining the number, character, and situation of
                courts in a country, the great problem evidently is, so to distribute them as to
                secure two things, namely, to bring justice home to every man’s door, and to mature
                a sound and fixed system of jurisprudence. In England, the latter object appears to
                have been principally regarded since the days of Edward the First, before whose time
                England and Scotland were equally distinguished for their local courts. But what, we
                may ask, avails the best system of law, if it be remote or difficult of access ? The
                end is in such case sacrificed to the means; and a multitude of petty courts, with a
                few practitioners in each, would prove the ruin not only of the legal profession,
                but of the law itself.</p>
            <p>The sheriff-principal, or high sheriff, is lord lieutenant of his county, and
                appointed at pleasure by the crown. The sheriff-depute, so called, is also appointed
                by the crown ; but he is quite independent of the high sheriff. He must be an
                advocate of at least three years’ standing; he holds his office during life, or good
                behaviour; and he receives a salary, varying, according to the shire, from L.350 to
                L.1200 a-year. The sheriff-substitute must be of the profession of the law,</p>
            <p>though not necessarily a member of the bar. He is named by the sheriff-depute of the
                shire, but paid by the crown, and is otherwise an independent officer. In every
                county there is a high sheriff or lord lieutenant. The same may be said of the
                sheriff-depute, except as to the united shires of Clackmannan and Kinross, Elgin and
                Nairn, Ross and Cromarty. Ross, Sutherland, and Caithness, were originally parts of
                the great shire of Inverness; but in the seventeenth century they became disjoined,
                and were erected into separate shires. By the jurisdiction act, however, Ross was
                put under the same sheriff with the ancient shire of Cromarty, and has continued so
                ever since. Sutherland and Caithness were then also re-united; but in 1806 these
                were again separated. Kinross was originally part of Fife; but it was afterwards
                separated, then re-united, and in 1807 disjoined again, and united to Clackmannan.
                With respect to the sheriff-substitute, in every shire there is at least one ; but
                Edinburgh, Fife, Forfar, Perth, Renfrew, and Sutherland, have each two,
                Kirkcudbright and Argyle have each three, Lanark and Inverness have each four, and
                in one of the districts of Ross there is a sort of assistant substitute.</p>
            <p>The jurisdiction of the county courts was originally most extensive ; and as to civil
                suits in particular, there seems to have been scarcely any limitation. It was the
                policy of the Court of Session, however, to make itself the great law court of the
                kingdom ; and as it gradually absorbed the civil jurisdiction of the justiciary, so,
                by a bold stratagem, it stripped the sheriff of all power to decide upon questions
                of real property. Such questions were formerly tried under the brieve of right, a
                judicial writ so named, because issued to try what was esteemed the highest right,
                that of property in land ; and it is clear that this brieve was <hi rend="italic">in
                    viridi observantia,</hi> and competent to sheriffs, till within a very few years
                of the institution of the Court of Session. This is clear from the act 1503, c. 95,
                which was passed to regulate it; and it is familiarly referred to by the poet
                Dunbar, in his Dance of the Seven Deadly Sins, where, speaking of the occupations of
                the damned, he says,</p>
            <lg>
                <l>“ Nae minstrels playit to them bot doubt,</l>
                <l>For glee-men there were holden out</l>
                <l>Be day and eik be night,</l>
                <l>Except a minstrel that slew a man :</l>
                <l>Swa tith his heritage be wan,</l>
                <l>Entering be <hi rend="italic">brieve of right !”</hi></l>
            </lg>
            <p>Yet the Court of Session was scarcely established, when it boldly adjudged this
                brieve “ nocht to have bene, nor yet to be thir mony yeires in use ;”@@<hi
                    rend="superscript">3</hi> and having thus, by repressing the writ, ousted the
                sheriff of his real jurisdiction, Boon took it to itself exclusively,@@<hi
                    rend="superscript">4</hi> by letters prepared for the court in its own
                Bill-chamber. The sheriff, however, still continued competent to possessory actions
                ; and by a recent statute, his jurisdiction has even extended to all actions and
                proceedings relative to nuisance or damages, arising from an undue exercise of the
                right of property, and also to questions touching the constitution or exercise of
                real or judicial servitudes, which is so far a restoration of his ancient powers.
                Besides the ordinary jurisdiction, civil and criminal, of the county court, the
                sheriff is empowered to decide summarily in questions of debt, when the sum in
                dispute does not exceed eight pounds. These small debt courts were instituted in
                1825, with a view to extend and improve the like jurisdiction, which had been
                conferred upon justices of the peace about thirty years before. The summary redress
                which such courts afford is of the greatest benefit to trade and to good
                neighbourhood, in consequence of the little sacrifice of time, money, and feeling
                they require ; and they are accordingly now extensively established, not only in
                this</p>
            <p><hi rend="superscript">@@@1</hi> Robertson’s Index, p. 29. </p>
            <p><hi rend="superscript">@@@,</hi> Stat. Will. c. 14. Stat. Alex. II. c. 14.</p>
            <p>@@@» Skene <hi rend="italic">voce</hi> Breve de recto. </p>
            <p><hi rend="superscript">@@@4 </hi>Bishop of Aberdeen <hi rend="italic">v</hi>. Ogilvy,
                3d July 1563.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
