<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-19T20:10:42Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>The father of the late rajah was a commandant of horse ; but being unfortunately of the blood of Sevajee, he was immured in the state-prison of Satarab. He died in 1808, and the Peishwa Bajerow immediately proceeded from Poo- nah, his residence, to superintend his obsequies, and to invest his successor with his empty dignity, and the misery of a prison thereto annexed. The Peishwa Bajerow was expelled from his throne in 1818, in consequence of joining in the coalition of the native powers against the British ; and it was determined to take the Satarah rajah from his confinement as a state prisoner, and to reinstate him in a portion of his ancient dominions. The territory granted him, and which he now enjoys, is bounded by the Western Ghaut Mountains, on the south by the Warner and Krishna rivers, on the north by the Neera and Beema rivers, and on the east by the frontier of the nizam’s dominions. The whole area occupies 11,000 square miles.</p><p>SATELLITE, an island in D’Entrecasteaux Channel, Van Diemen’s Land, partly covered with an impenetrable thicket.</p><p>SATGONG, formerly a large trading city, in which the Europeans had their factories ; but it is now an inconsiderable village, on a small creek of the river Hooghly, about four miles to the north-west of the town of Hooghly, in Bengal.</p><p>SATIMANGALUM, a town of Hindustan, in the northern district of Coimbetoor, situated on the river Bhawani. The fort is said to have been built about two hundred years ago. The town, which formerly contained eight hundred, but has now only six hundred houses, is scattered over the plain. Here is a temple of some repute dedicated to Vishnu. Coarse cotton goods are manufactured in the town and neighbourhood. Long. 77. 20. E. Lat. 10. 28. N.</p><p>SATTERAM, a town of Hindustan, in the Mysore rajah’s territories, situated twenty miles south from Seringa- patam. Long. 76. 53. E. Lat. 12. 9. N.</p><p>SATTIAVERAM, a town of Hindustan, on the sea-coast of the Northern Circars. It is fifty-six miles south-west from Vizagapatam. Long. 82. 45. E. Lat. 17. 15. N.</p><p>SATURDAY, the seventh and last day of the week, so called from the idol Seater, worshipped on this day by the ancient Saxons, and thought to be the same as the Saturn of the Latins.</p><p>SATURN, in <hi rend="italic">Astronomy,</hi> one of the planets of our solar system, revolving at the distance of more than nine hundred millions of miles from the sun.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Saturn,</hi> in <hi rend="italic">chemistry,</hi> is an appellation which was formerly given to lead.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sλturn,</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Heraldry,</hi> denotes the black colour in blazoning the arms of sovereign princes.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Saturn,</hi> one of the principal of the Pagan deities, was the son of Coelus and Terra, and the father of Jupiter. He deposed and castrated his father, and obliged his brother Titan to resign to him his crown, on condition of his bringing up none of his male issue, that the succession might at length devolve on him. For this purpose he devoured all the sons he had by his wife Rhea or Cybele ; but she bringing forth at one time Jupiter and Juno, presented the latter to her husband, and sent the boy to be nursed on Mount Ida, when Saturn, being informed of her having a son, demanded the child, but in his stead his wife gave him a stone swaddled up like an infant, which he instantly swallowed. Titan, finding that Saturn had violated the contract he had made with him, put himself at the head of his children and made war on his brother, and having taken him and Cybele prisoners, confined them in Tartarus ; but Jupiter being in the mean time grown up, raised an army in Crete, went to his father’s assistance, defeated Titan, and restored Saturn to the throne. Some time after this, Saturn being told that Jupiter intended to dethrone him, endeavoured to prevent it ; but the latter being informed of his intention, deposed his father, and threw him into Tartarus. Saturn having es</p><p>caped from thence, however, fled into Italy, where he was kindly received by Janus, king of the country, who associated him in the government ; and hence Italy obtained the name of <hi rend="italic">Saturnia Tellus,</hi> as also that of <hi rend="italic">Latium,</hi> from <hi rend="italic">lateo, </hi>to lie hidden. There Saturn, by the wisdom and mildness of his government, is said to have produced the golden age.</p><p>Saturn is represented as an old man with four wings, armed with a scythe ; and sometimes he is delineated under the figure of a serpent with its tail in its mouth. This is emblematical of the seasons, which roll perpetually in the same circle. Sometimes also Saturn is painted with a sandglass in his hand. The Greeks say that the story of his mutilating his father and destroying his children is an allegory, which signifies, that Time devours the past and present, and will also devour the future. The Romans, in honour of him, built a temple, and celebrated a festival which they denominated <hi rend="italic">Saturnalia.</hi> During this festival no business or profession was allowed to be carried on except cookery ; all distinctions of rank ceased ; slaves could say with impunity what they pleased to their masters, and they could even rally them to their faces with their faults.</p><p>SATURNALIA, in Roman antiquity, a festival observed about the middle of December, in honour of the god Saturn, whom Lucan introduces giving an account of the ceremonies observed upon this occasion. “ During my whole reign,” says he, “ which lasts but for one week, no public business is done ; there is nothing but drinking, singing, playing, creating imaginary kings, placing servants with their masters at table, &amp;c. There shall be no disputes or reproaches, but the rich and poor, masters and slaves, shall be equal.” On this festival the Romans sacrificed bareheaded, contrary to their custom at other sacrifices.</p><p>SATURNINE, an appellation given to persons of a melancholy disposition, as being supposed to be under the influence of the planet Saturn.</p><p>SATYAVRATA, or <hi rend="smallcaps">MeNü,</hi> in Indian mythology, is believed by the Hindus to have reigned over the whole world in the earliest age of their chronology, and to have resided in the country of Dravira, on the coast of the eastern Indian peninsula. His patronymic name was Vaivaswata, or Child of the Sun. Sir William Jones has shown it to be in the highest degree probable, that the Satyavrata of India is the Kronus of Greece and the Saturn of Italy. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Saturn, </hi>and Asiatic Researches, vol. i. p. 230.</p><p>SATYRS, in ancient mythology, a species of demi-gods, who dwelt in the woods. They are represented as monsters, half men and half goats ; having horns on their heads, and a hairy body, with the feet and tail of a goat. They are generally delineated in the train that follows Bacchus. As the poets supposed that they were remarkable for piercing eyes and keen raillery, they have placed them in the same pictures with the Graces, Loves, and even with Venus herself.</p><p>SAUL the son of Kish, of the tribe of Benjamin, was the first king of the Israelites. On account of his disobedient conduct, the kingdom was taken from his family and given to David.</p><p>SAUMUR, an arrondissement of the department of the Maine et Loire, in France, extending over 516 square miles. It is divided into eight cantons and ninety-three communes, and, in 1836, contained 91,159 inhabitants. The capital is the city of the same name, situated at the influx of the Thouet into the Loire, which here forms several islands. It contains 11,925 inhabitants. There is much linen trade carried on, some tanning, some copper and cutlery goods made, and some saltpetre refineries. Long. 0. 9. 55. W. Lat. 47. 15. 24. N.</p><p>SAUNDERS’ <hi rend="smallcaps">Island,</hi> in the South Atlantic Ocean, ten leagues in circumference, and discovered by Captain Cook in 1775. Long. 26. 44. W. Lat. 57. 49. S.</p><p>SAUNDERSON, <hi rend="smallcaps">Dr Robert,</hi> an eminent casuist, was</p></body></text></TEI>