<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-19T20:13:07Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>ployed Mr. James Walker, engineer, to institute a minute investigation of the entire
                works, and to report. The report was presented to the House of Commons in 1838; and
                a select Committee was appointed to take the whole subject into consideration. The
                result of their investigations was, a recommendation that steam tugs should be
                employed in the locks, so as to ensure a speedy navigation, and that a sum not
                exceeding L.200,000 be placed at the disposal of the government, to be expended in
                the repair and improvement of the canal, under the authority of an act of
                Parliament, which should be procured for the purpose.@@’ This recommendation will,
                it is hoped, be acted upon. (<hi rend="smallcaps">Navigation, Inland</hi>). The
                Crinan canal is situated in Argyleshire, and is intended to afford a communication
                between Loch Gi!p and the Western Ocean, so as to avoid the difficult and circuitous
                passage round the Mull of Cantyre. It was originally undertaken in 1793 by
                subscription of share-holders; but the sum subscribed(L.108,000) being quite
                insufficient for the completion of the work, the government advanced the money, and
                the canal was transferred on mortgage to the Barons of Exchequer in Scotland. The
                management has since 1817 been lodged in the hands of the Commissioners of the
                Caledonian Canal. It is nine miles long, and twelve feet deep, admitting vessels of
                200 tons burden. The income scarcely covers the expenditure.@@<hi rend="superscript"
                    >3 </hi>The Forth and Clyde Canal, sometimes called the Great Canal, though
                begun in 1768, was not finally completed till 1790. The length from Grangemouth on
                the Forth to Bowling Bay on the Clyde, is 35 miles, and, including the lateral
                branch to Port-Dundas, Glasgow, 38<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript"
                    >2</hi>. Its depth is ten feet; and it has in all thirty-nine locks. Though iron
                swift boats and other lighters ply upon it, its staple trade consists in the transit
                of sailing vessels of 120 tons and under. The Edinburgh and Glasgow Union Canal,
                which was finished in 1822, stretches from Port-Hopetoun, Edinburgh, until it joins
                the Forth and Clyde Canal at Port-Downie, near Falkirk, a distance of 31<hi
                    rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">2</hi> miles. Its depth is only
                five feet, so that its traffic is quite limited. The Monkland Canal stretches from
                Glasgow to Woodhall, about two miles south-east of Airdrie, a distance of twelve
                miles, and communicates by a lateral branch with the Forth and Clyde Canal at
                Port-Dundas. The Glasgow, Paisley, and Ardrossan Canal has not been completed ;
                indeed it is not now intended to complete it. The progress of railways seems
                partially to supersede the use of canal communication. The canal in question has
                been constructed from Port-Eglinton, near Glasgow, to the village of Johnstone, a
                distance of eleven miles, and was opened in 1811. It was on this canal that the
                experiment was made in rapid travelling by canals, demonstrating that it was
                practicable for a properly constructed boat, carrying passengers and goods along a
                canal, to go at a rate of nine or ten miles an hour, without injury to the banks.
                These light boats are now common on canals suited for such travelling. The
                Aberdeenshire Canal, completed in 1807, stretches from the harbour of Aberdeen to
                Inventury. The length is 18<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">4</hi>
                miles, and the number of locks is seventeen.</p>
            <p>The first act obtained, in 1808, for a railway in Scotland, was for that between
                Kilmarnock and Troon, a distance of 9<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi
                    rend="subscript">2</hi> miles. The Monkland and Kirkintilloch railway connects
                the rich coal and ironstone district of New and Old Monkland, and, within fourteen
                miles of the city of Glasgow, with the Forth and Clyde Canal, near Kirkintilloch.
                The Ballochney railway, which has been in operation for about ten years, is merely
                an elongation of the last mentioned line, four miles eastward into the interior. The
                Glasgow and Garnkirk railway stretches eight miles west from Glasgow, till it
                communicates with the Monkland and Kirkintilloch line, forming a direct
                communication with Glasgow, and avoiding</p>
            <p>the circuitous route of that line. The Wishaw and Coltness railway, which is meant to
                connect the Monkland and Kirkintilloch branch with the rich coal and ironstone beds
                of Wishaw, Coltness, and Allanton, has not yet been completed, though the act was
                passed in 1829. The Slamannan railway, which is in progress of construction, is to
                extend from the eastern termination of the Ballochney line to the Union Canal,
                within a mile of Linlithgow, a distance of 12<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi
                    rend="subscript">2</hi> miles. An act has been passed (1837) for forming a
                branch to the town of Bathgate. The Pollock and Govan railway, which was meant to
                connect these two places, which lye on the south of Glasgow, with that city, an
                interval of three miles, is in the same unfinished state. The Paisley and Renfrew
                railway, which extends from Paisley to the river Clyde at Renfrew ferry, a distance
                of 3<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">2</hi> miles, was opened in
                1837. The Glasgow, Paisley, and Greenock railway is meant to connect Glasgow and
                Greenock by way of Paisley. It runs nearly parallel with the Clyde, and is meant to
                be completed in 1840. The Glasgow, Paisley, Kilmarnock, and Ayr railway is intended
                to connect these towns and the adjacent districts. The line from Glasgow to Paisley
                is declared to be common to the latter line, and that of the Glasgow, Paisley, and
                Greenock railway, and to be executed at the joint expense of both companies. The
                Glasgow and Paisley railway is to send branches out to the different towns in the
                district through which it passes. An act was obtained in 1838 for constructing a
                railway between Edinburgh and Glasgow. The line is to run nearly on a parallel with
                the Union Canal, past Ratho, Winchburgh, Linlithgow, and Falkirk, to pass that canal
                near Port-Downie, and to proceed onward to Glasgow by a line nearly parallel to the
                Great Canal. The distance will be forty-six miles. The capital of the company is
                L.900,000. Twenty-nine miles of the line have already been contracted for, and the
                work will be completed at farthest in 1842. The Edinburgh and Dalkeith railway was
                opened in 1832. It extends to Dalhousie Mains on the South Esk, but a private branch
                has been carried over that river by a viaduct, and extends southwards for upwards of
                a mile. The Dalkeith line is about to be carried over the North Esk, in order to
                connect extensive coal fields in that quarter with the city of Edinburgh. There are
                also branches to Leith and Fisherrow. On this railway upwards of 100,000 tons of
                goods, and 300,000 passengers are annually conveyed. The Edinburgh, Leith, and
                Newhaven railway is only meant to extend 2<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi
                    rend="subscript">2</hi> miles. It is to commence at Canal Street, at the cast
                end of Princes Street gardens, and proceed by a tunnel of 2800 feet, or rather more
                than a fifth of the whole line, under St. Andrews Street, St. Andrews Square, Duke
                Street, Drummond Place, &amp;c. to the foot of Scotland Street, and thence to
                Newhaven in nearly a straight line, with a branch along the north side of the Water
                of Leith, to the wet docks at Leith. The work has been begun, but when it will be
                completed is uncertain. If the terminus of the line were to be united with that of
                the Edinburgh and Glasgow railway, much advantage would accrue to both speculations.
                But, according to act of Parliament, a mile intervenes at present between the dépôts
                of the two. The Dundee and Newtyle railway is eleven miles in length, but branches
                are in progress to Cupar-Angus and to Glammis. There are on the line three inclined
                planes, and a tunnel of 340 yards. The Dundee and Forfar railway was opened in</p>
            <p>1838. Its length is 16<hi rend="superscript">3</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">4</hi>
                miles. The Arbroath and Forfar railway is just completed. The distance is 15<hi
                    rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">4</hi> miles.</p>
            <p>About the middle of the seventeenth century, the lands of Scotland were valued, with
                a view to ascertain what proportion of the land-tax and others should be paid by
                each county ; and this valuation, called the “valued rent,” which had been
                undertaken by the authority of Cromwell, was afterwards</p>
            <p><hi rend="superscript">@@@,</hi> See Thirty fourth Report of the Canal Commission,
                Mr. Walker’s Report, and Report of Secret Committee.</p>
            <p>@@@* Ibid.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
