<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-19T20:11:07Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Suessones, therefore, arc actually denominated the Ues- sones by Ptolemy, and the Saxones are actually entitled the Axones by Lucan.</p><p>These, with their brethren and allies the Cimbri, having been more formidable enemies to the Romans by land, than the Samnites, Carthaginians, Spaniards, Gauls, or Parthians, in the second century applied themselves to navigation, and became nearly as terrible by sea. They soon made themselves known to the inhabitants of the British isles by their piracies in the northern channels, and were denominated by them Lochlyn or Lochlynach ; <hi rend="italic">lucd-lyn</hi> signifying the people of the wave, and the <hi rend="italic">d</hi> being quiescent in the pronunciation. They took possession of the Orkney Islands, which were then merely large shoals of sand, uncovered with wood, and overgrown with rushes ; and they landed in the north of Ireland, where they ravaged the country. Before the middle of the third century they made a second descent upon the latter, disembarked a considerable body of men, and designed the absolute subjection of the island. Before the conclusion of it, they carried their naval operations to the south, infested the British channel with their little vessels, and made frequent descents upon the coasts. And in the fourth and fifth centuries, acting in conjunction with the Picts of Caledonia and the Scots of Ireland, they ravaged all the eastern and south-eastern shores of Britain, began the formal conquest of the country, and finally settled their victorious soldiery in Lancashire.</p><p>In the course of time these barbarous tribes were civilized, and settled in their lands, on which they began to exercise their industry in cultivation, and in various manufactures for their own convenience. Their possessions extended from beyond the north-western part of Germany to the southern extremity of the Erzgebirge, and were denominated the Duchy of Saxony, forming one of the most powerful German states, which was governed till the commencement of the tenth century by various Vandal houses, when Henry I. took from them the land lying between the Saale and the Elbe, and founded for its protection the margravate of Meissen, which was governed at first by various houses, but latterly became hereditary in the Askanian family. When the duchy of Saxony was taken from Henry the Lion, in the twelfth century, it was split into so many parts, that Bernhard of Askania, who succeeded to this duchy, being unable to procure any thing but the mere title, transferred the name of Saxony to the lands which he already possessed, and which still constitute a principal part of the present kingdom. After the death of Bernhard, and the extinction of his family, Frederick, landgrave of Thuringia, succeeded in the year 1423 to his titles and property. In 1485, however, his family divided itself into two distinct lines; the elder, or Ernestine, which possessed Thuringia and the electorship, and the younger, or Albertine, which possessed Meissen and the title of duke.</p><p>In the year 1547, Frederick the Magnanimous was made prisoner, and forced to resign a great part of his territory and his electorship to his cousin Maurice, of the Albertinian line ; and thus the kings of Saxony are descended from the younger of the Thuringian family. In 1697, the royal family went over to the Catholic church, in the reign of Augustus I. and thereby procured for a season the crown of Poland.</p><p>During the early stages of the French revolution, Saxony took little or no part in the struggle, and only as a member of the Germanic empire furnished the contingent of troops required by that relation, which were withdrawn when Prussia formed a combination of the northern states of Germany to counteract the confederation which France had formed in the southern states. To this extent Saxony was in alliance with Prussia when France, in 1806, began the war with that power. At the decisive battle of Iena, in October of that year, a body of twenty thousand Saxons were joined to the Prussian army. The complete victory of Napoleon in</p><p>duced the Duke of Saxony to conclude a peace with him, and to become a member of the Rhenish confederation, of which the French emperor was acknowledged the protector.</p><p>In July 1807, the peace of Tilsit, between Russia, France, and Prussia, was concluded. In conformity with its conditions, the whole of the dominions of Prussia on the left bank of the Elbe, including the strong fortresses which commanded the passages over that river, were ceded to Saxony, and the duke was acknowledged as king. A part also of Poland, which at the last division of that country had been shared by Prussia, was, with the capital, erected into a grand duchy, called by the name of Warsaw, and the sovereignty of it was conferred on the king of Saxony. After the peace between Austria and France, which followed the battle of Wagram, the newly-created grand duchy of Warsaw was extended by additions from Austria of West Gallicia and the city of Cracow, with the vast salt mines of Wielicsla, whilst to the Saxon crown there were conveyed some portions of the kingdom of Bohemia.</p><p>When Napoleon declared war with Russia in 1812, the Saxon capital was the spot on which the several monarchs of Europe were assembled to pay homage to him whose dependents they had become. In the grand army that invaded Russia, the troops of the king of Saxony formed a part of the right wing, and advanced into Russia. They had little opportunity of distinguishing themselves, and after the burning of Moscow retired to their own country.</p><p>When in the following year the French army advanced into Germany to oppose the Russians and Prussians, the king of Saxony treated with Austria, with the pretext that it was only for the purpose of obtaining a peace. He declared his own neutrality, and gave orders to his general, Thielman, to refuse admission to the troops of any of the belligerent parties into his fortress of Torgau on the Elbe. While these negotiations with Austria were proceeding, the king left Dresden, and repaired first to Ratisbon, and from thence to Prague, whilst the French general Davoust entered his capital. About five weeks afterwards (2d May), Napoleon had gained a battle at Lutzen, over the united army of Russia and Prussia. Upon this the French emperor, who by the victory was master of Leipsig, and the whole of the king’s dominions, peremptorily demanded by a special messenger to Prague, “ Je veux que le roi se déclare ; je saurai alors ce que j’aurai à faire ; mais s’il est contre moi, il perdra tout ce qu’il a.” This determined the conduct of the king. He returned to Dresden. His forces joined the French army, and the troops of that nation occupied Torgau and the other fortresses. His troops joined those of Napoleon in the successful resistance of the attack by the Russians and Prussians on Dresden, when the French general Moreau was killed ; and at length, after an armistice, proceeded to Leipsig with the French. At the fatal battle before that city on the 19th of October, when the French retreated, the king was left in that city, where he was made a prisoner by the confederate armies of Austria, Russia, Prussia, and Sweden, and was removed to Berlin. The king remained under restraint from October 1813 till June 1815; whilst the allied powers were fully occupied, first, in annihilating the government of Napoleon, then in quelling his attempts to resume that power, and, finally, in settling the arrangements which the state of Europe demanded. At the congress of Vienna, the first intention seems to have been to depose the king of Saxony, and allot to other powers the whole of the territory ; but gradually a more tender feeling prevailed. He was compelled to sign a treaty soon after Napoleon had arrived in Paris from Elba, by which he consented to the partition of his dominions, and joined his forces to those of the allies then advancing towards France.</p><p>By the partition Prussia received from Saxony more in extent than one half of its territory, and somewhat less than half as regarded the number of inhabitants. The loss most</p></body></text></TEI>