<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-19T20:11:11Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>way, of sheep’s wool, fine woollen goods, linen and thread lace, yam and worsted, ironmongery, cutlery, and braziery, and also books. It receives in return corn, wine, salt, wood, and colonial wares. Although the river Elbe is navigable from the ocean to the interior of Saxony, it is only used for the conveyance of the heaviest goods, and for them but partially. It is found that the tolls on that river, with the risk of damage and of robbery, make it more advantageous to convey commodities by land than by water.</p><p>The government is a monarchy hereditary in the Saxon Albertine line, and in failure of that, in the Ernestine or Saxe-Weimar branch of the family. The monarchy may be called limited ; but the limitations are of such a nature that the liberties of the people have been more secured by the mildness of the reigning family than by any restrictions that the states have or could exercise. The king enjoys the whole executive power, confirms pardons, bestows commissions, nominates the supreme judges, and enjoys the power of making peace and war, and of concluding all treaties. In making new laws, and in imposing new taxes, the states have the right to be consulted. According to the ancient constitution, which is still adhered to, the states are constituted of various elements ; and, in fact, are an amalgamation of various corporations, each of which thinks only of its own peculiar interests, and contrives to cast the weight of all public burdens from the cities and the nobles, who are represented, to the country people, who have no voices. The assembly consists, first, of members chosen by the provincial representatives of the nobility ; secondly, of the representatives of the prelates, who, before the Reformation, had seats, but who have since been chosen by the higher class of nobles in right of their possessing certain estates of which the prelates were deprived ; and, thirdly, the university of Leipsig. These states represent only the circles of Meissen, Leipsig, Erzgebirge, and Voightland ; for that of Lausatia has its own peculiar assembly of states, which differs but little from those of the other four, except that the members from the land possessors must have at least sixteen quarterings in their coats of arms. When the king pleases, these states are convoked ; but as it has not been found necessary to impose new taxes, or to make alterations in the laws, they have seldom been assembled, and their session has usually been very short. The administration is conducted by a cabinet council, under which, through the medium of the privy council, orders are communicated to the departments of finance, war, domains, police, and foreign affairs..</p><p>The financial affairs of the kingdom and the credit of the government have rapidly improved. According to the budget of 1837, the income, a great part of which is derived from the estates of the crown, amountcd to 5,194,873 rix-thalers, valued at about three shillings each. The expenditure amounted to the same sum, but in that was included 145,424 thalers appropriated to a reserve fund to meet unforeseen contingencies, 321,545 thalers to pay the interest of the debt, and 171,806 thalers which forms a sinking fund to extinguish the debt, which, at the rate now proceeding, a few years will accomplish, as at the close of the war it was near L.4,000,000 sterling, and is, according to the budget, reduced to L.l,l77,740 sterling.</p><p>The armed force is no more than the contingent: required from the kingdom by the German Confederation. It is composed of the following arms :—</p><p>The guards	 370</p><p>Infantry of the line	7,080</p><p>Cavalry	2,066</p><p>Artillery	1,032</p><p>Sharp-shooters	1,454</p><p>Engineers	 191</p><p>12,193</p><p>Although the royal family profess the Catholic religion,</p><p>and are zealous in discharging its injunctions, the established faith is the Lutheran, and, until the year 1811, no person of any other sect was eligible to seats in the several corporations in the provincial or general assembly of the states. At that period all sects were placed on the same footing. The whole number of Catholics is about 28,000, some of whom are attached to the royal household ; but most of them are found among the inhabitants of the province of Lausatia. The number of Protestants dissenting from the established church, including Moravians and Calvinists, is not supposed to exceed two thousand. The Lutheran church is governed by four consistories or assemblies of divines, differing in the number of superintendents, but comprising together twenty-five of that order. The Catholics in Lausatia are governed by the abbot of Bautzen, on whom the pope generally bestows the title of bishop <hi rend="italic">in partibus infidelium.</hi></p><p>Education is well conducted in the university of Leipsig, and in the endowed classical schools of Meissen, Wurzen, and Grimma, as well as in several gymnasia. The popular education is not so well managed as in the other Protestant German states ; but some steps have been taken, and others are in contemplation, which may soon make the Saxon system as effective as that of Prussia. The fine arts have been cultivated with considerable success, and both statuary and painting receive valuable assistance from the fine productions which are contained in the collections of Dresden.</p><p>SAYANSKIE, a chain of mountains in Siberia, forming a prolongation of the Altai chain, and, like them, separating Siberia from Chinese Tartary. They extend between the river Yenisei and Lake Baikal, and consist of naked rocks of red granite.</p><p>SAYMBRUMBACUM, a small town of India, in the province of the Carnatic. Near it is a remarkably fine reservoir of water, eight miles in length by three in average breadth, which in the dry season is rendered subservient to the purposes of cultivation, and being let out in small streams, serves to irrigate the lands of thirty-two villages. Long. 80. 5. E. Lat. 13. 2. N.</p><p>SAYPAN, one of the Ladrone Isles, in the Eastern Seas, about twenty miles in circumference. It was once the best peopled island of the Ladrones, but is now uninhabited ; and very opposite accounts are given of its productiveness by different voyagers. Anson mentions that it presents as pleasant an aspect as Tinian ; and on the west side of the island lies a safe and commodious port. Long. 145. 55. E. Lat. 15. 13. N.</p><p>SCALDS, in the history of literature, a name given by the ancient inhabitants of the northern countries to their poets, in whose writings their history is recorded.</p><p>SCALE, a mathematical instrument, consisting of several lines drawn on wood, brass, or silver, and variously divided, according to the purposes it is intended to serve ; whence it acquires various denominations, as the <hi rend="italic">plain scale, diagonal scale, plotting scale,</hi> and the like.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Scale,</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Music,</hi> see <hi rend="smallcaps">Music</hi>. The name is derived from <hi rend="italic">scala, a</hi> ladder, or flight of stairs, and has reference to the disposition of the notes that ascend or descend upon the written or printed musical stave.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Scale,</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Architecture</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Geography,</hi> a line divided into equal parts, and placed at the bottom of a map or draught, to serve as a common measure to all the parts of the building, or all the distances and places of the map.</p><p>SCALENE, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Scalenous Triangle, </hi><hi rend="italic">scalenum,</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Geometry,</hi> a triangle the sides and angles of which are unequal.</p><p>SCALIGER, <hi rend="smallcaps">Julius Cæsar,</hi> a learned critic, poet, physician, and philosopher, was born at the castle of Ripa, in the territories of Verona, in 1484 ; and is said to have been descended from the ancient princes of Verona, though this</p></body></text></TEI>