<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-19T20:09:16Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>was taken by the Moors, and carried to Algiers, where he continued a captive five
                years and a half. Then he returned to Spain, and applied himself to the writing of
                comedies and tragedies ; and he composed several, all of which were well received by
                the public, and acted with great applause. In the year 1584 he published his
                Galatea, a novel in six books, which he presented to Ascanio Colonna, a man of high
                rank in the church, as the first fruits of his wit. But the work which has done him
                the greatest honour, and will immortalize his name, is the history of Don Quixote,
                the first part of which was printed at Madrid in the year 1605. This is a satire
                upon books of knight- errantry, and the principal if not the sole end of it was to
                destroy the reputation of those books which had so infatuated the greater part of
                mankind, and especially those of the Spanish nation. This work was universally read
                ; and the most eminent painters, tapestry-workers, engravers, and sculptors, have
                been employed in representing the history of Don Quixote. Cervantes, even in his
                lifetime, obtained the glory of having his work receive a royal approbation. As
                Philip III. was standing in a balcony of his palace at Madrid, viewing the country,
                he observed a student on the banks of the river Manzanares reading in a book, and
                from time to time breaking off, and beating his forehead with extraordinary tokens
                of pleasure and delight ; upon which the king remarked to those about him, “ 'fhat
                scholar is either mad or is reading Don Quixote.” The latter proved to be the case.
                But <hi rend="italic">virtus laudatur et alget.</hi> Notwithstanding the vast
                applause his book everywhere met with, he had not interest enough to procure a small
                pension, for he could scarcely keep himself from starving. In the year 1615 he
                published a second part; to which he was partly moved by the presumption of some
                scribbler, who had the year before published a continuation of this work. He wrote
                also several novels, and amongst the rest the Troubles of Persiles and Sigismunda.
                He had employed many years in writing this novel, and finished it just before his
                death ; for he did not live to see it published. His sickness was of such a nature
                that he himself was able to be, and actually was, his own historian. At the end of
                the preface to the Troubles of Persiles and Sigismunda, he represents himself on
                horseback upon the road, and a student, who had overtaken him, engaged in
                conversation with him. “ And happening to talk of my illness,” says he, “ the
                student soon let me know my doom, by saying it was a dropsy I had got ; the thirst
                attending which, all the water of the ocean, though it were not salt, would not
                suffice to quench. Therefore Señor Cervantes, says he, you must drink nothing at
                all, but do not forget to eat ; for this alone will recover you without any other
                physic. I have been told the same by others, answered I ; but I can no more forbear
                tippling, than if I were born to do nothing else. My life is drawing to an end ; and
                from the daily journal of my pulse, I shall have finished my course by next Sunday
                at the farthest. But adieu, my merry friends all, for I am going to die ; and I hope
                to see you ere long in the other world, as happy as heart can wish.” His dropsy
                increased, and at last proved fatal to him ; yet he continued to say and to write
                bon mots. He received the last sacrament on the l8th of April 1616 ; yet the day
                after, he wrote a dedication of the Troubles of Persiles and Sigismunda to the Conde
                de Lemos. The particular day of his death is not known.</p>
            <p>SABAGAN <hi rend="smallcaps">Islands,</hi> a group of small islands in the Red Sea.
                Long. 41. 54. E. Lat. 14. 55. N.</p>
            <p>SABAZIA, in Greek antiquity, were nocturnal mysteries in honour of Jupiter Sabazius.
                All the initiated had a golden serpent put in at their breasts, and taken out at the
                lower part of their garments, in memory of Jupiter’s ravishing Proserpina in the
                form of a serpent. There were also other feasts and sacrifices distinguished by this
                appel</p>
            <p>lation, in honour of Mithras, the deity of the Persians, and of Bacchus, who was thus
                denominated by the Sabians, a people of Thrace.</p>
            <p>SABBATARIANS, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Seventh-Day Baptists,</hi> a sect of
                Anabaptists, so called because they observed the Jewish or Saturday-Sabbath, from a
                persuasion that it was never abrogated in the New Testament by the institution of
                any other.</p>
            <p>SABBATH, in the Hebrew language, signifies <hi rend="italic">rest.</hi> The seventh
                day was denominated the <hi rend="italic">Sabbath,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">dug of
                    rest, </hi>because in it God rested from all his works which he had created.
                From that time the seventh day seems to have been set apart for religious services ;
                and, in consequence of a particular injunction, it was afterwards observed by the
                Hebrews as a holiday. They were commanded to set it apart for sacred purposes in
                honour of the creation, and likewise in memorial of their own redemption from
                Egyptian bondage.</p>
            <p>The importance of the institution may be gathered from the different laws respecting
                it. When the ten commandments were published from Mount Sinai in tremendous pomp,
                the law of the Sabbath held a place in what is commonly called the first table ; and
                by subsequent statutes the violation of it was to be punished with death. Six days
                were allowed for the use and service of man ; but the seventh day God reserved to
                himself, and appointed it to be observed as a stated time for holy offices, and to
                be spent in the duties of piety and devotion. On this day the ministers of the
                temple entered upon their week ; and those who had attended on the temple service
                the preceding week went out at the same time. New loaves of shew-bread were placed
                upon the golden table, and the old ones were taken away. Two lambs were offered for
                a burnt-offering, together with a certain proportion of fine flour, mingled with
                oil, for a bread offering, and wine for a libation. The Sabbath, like all other
                festivals, was celebrated from evening to evening. It began at six in the evening on
                Friday, and ended at the same time the next day.</p>
            <p>Concerning the time at which the Sabbath was first instituted, different opinions
                have been held. Some have maintained, that the sanctification of the seventh day,
                mentioned in Genesis ii., is only there spoken of as <hi rend="italic">b∣α</hi>
                irjoλs∙ψ∕r, or by anticipation ; and is to be understood of the Sabbath afterwards
                cnjoined the children of Israel at the commencement of the Mosaic dispensation. But
                without entering into a particular examination of all the arguments produced in
                support of this opinion, a few observations, it is presumed, will be sufficient to
                show that it rests upon no solid foundation.</p>
            <p>It cannot easily be supposed that the inspired penman would have mentioned the
                sanctification of the seventh day amongst the primeval transactions, if such
                sanctification had not taken place until 2500 years afterwards. Writers, ambitious
                of that artificial elegance which the rules of criticism have established, often
                bring together in their narrative events which were themselves far distant, for the
                sake of giving form to their discourse ; but Moses appears to have despised all such
                flimsy refinements, and to have constructed his narrative in conformity to the
                series of events.</p>
            <p>From the accounts we have of the religious service practised in the patriarchal age,
                it appears that, immediately after the fall, when Adam was restored to favour
                through a Mediator, a stated form of public worship was instituted, which man was
                required to observe, in testimony, not only of his dependence on the Creator, but
                also of his faith and hope in the promise made to our first parents, and seen by
                them afar off. Of an institution, then, so grand and important, no circumstance
                would be omitted that is necessary to preserve it, or that contributes to render the
                observance of it regular and solemn.</p>
            <p>That determined times are necessary for the due celebra-</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
