<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-19T20:10:08Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ed, and still continue to be respected on the coasts of Malabar.</p><p>SAMAR, one of the Philippine Islands, 140 miles in length by sixty in average breadth. It is situated southeast from the large island of Luzon, from which it is separated by a strait five leagues in breadth. It is of an extremely fertile soil, which, besides other grain, produces abundance of rice, that is wholly appropriated to the use of the parochial clergy. The common food of the natives consists chiefly in a species of potato, yams, and a sort of root named gaby. The soil is favourable for the production of the sugar-cane, and fruits, such as lemons, melons, figs, of which there are about fourteen different species, the pumplemous, a species of orange, which is nearly five inches in diameter, and other vegetables besides, namely, cabbages, garlic, onions, and the like. Pepper, honey, and wax are found in the woods ; and from the sap of the cocoa, nipe, and cabonegro trees, excellent materials are found for the manufacture of brandy. The woods afford an excellent cover for many animals, and monkeys abound ; also a remarkably large deer, wild buffaloes, and other quadrupeds. They swarm also with every description of birds, particularly the common fowl. There are three species of the turtle-dove. The parroquet, cockatoo, and another pretty little bird of the same genus, and of the size of a linnet, are quite common. A diminutive bird, of the size of a w asp, is also seen, of the most vivid and beautiful Colom’s, consisting of a shade of yellow mixed with red and blue. There is a curious production found in this island. It consists in numerous folds of the bark of a tree, which in a certain period of putrefaction are separable without art or difficulty. These pieced together afford a species of fine linen, harsh, indeed, and disagreeable to the skin, but which is softened by a preparation of lime. Besides serving as the materials of linen, it is likewise useful for the purposes of cordage. The iron-tree, ebony, and dyeing-wood, grow everywhere ; and gold dust is found in small quantities in the interior.</p><p>The natives, especially those who reside upon the seacoast, were formerly Mahommedans ; but being converted by the missionary Jesuits, they embraced the religion and submitted to the authority of Spain. Their houses are constructed of bamboos, and being raised a few feet from the ground, they admit a circulation of air from beneath. The natives are extremely simple in their habits, and are clothed with very little trouble or expense. The priests exercise over them both spiritual and temporal authority. They give them advice and admonition, which is always accompanied with presents of wine and medicines, or food ; and when punishment is necessary, it is promptly inflicted. Long. 124. 15. to 125. 52. E. Lat. 11. 15. to 12. 45. N.</p><p>SAMARA, a town of Irak Arabi, on the Tigris, revered by Mussulmen as containing the tomb of Mahommed al Mahudi, the twelfth imam. It was known in antiquity, and was in the ninth century the residence of several caliphs of the house of Abbas. It now only contains about four hundred houses. It is sixty miles north of Bagdad.</p><p>SAMARANG, a fortified town on the north-east coast of the island of Java, and the principal central station in the island, being the capital of a large district. It has a considerable European population, and ranks next in importance to Batavia. The town is defended by a stone parapet, with bastions and a wet ditch ; but is in no condition to withstand a siege by European troops, being only calculated for defence against a native power. It has a good hospital, and a public school, chiefly for the teaching of mathematics, where numbers of Dutch and half-caste children were formerly educated for the military profession; and also a theatre, a fine large church, and a variety of other public buildings, both elegant and commodious, within and without the city. Between the town and the sea-coast is</p><p>an impassable morass, through which the access to the town is by two fine roads east and west, both of which are raised, and communicate with each other. Owing to shoals, ships are obliged to lie at the distance of five or six miles from the shore, the anchorage being six fathoms, with a muddy bottom. The river is navigable for prows and coasting vessels as far as the town. In blowing weather the bar at the mouth is very dangerous. The surrounding country is remarkably fertile, and provisions in the town are consequently abundant and cheap. The climate is more healthy than that of Batavia, and the European inhabitants have more active habits. In the environs are numerous villas, which, from their elevated situation, command a view of the neat garden-houses and beautifully verdant fields below. There is here a numerous population of natives and Chinese, and crowded villages overspread the neighbourhood. Samarang was always the seat of a separate governor, who was called the governor of Java, his authority extending from Cheribon to the eastern extremity of the island. This government is one of the most lucrative in the gift of the Dutch East India Company, and is surpassed only by that of the governor-general. It is 343 miles east from Batavia. Long. 110. 38. E. Lat. 6. 54. S.</p><p>SAMARCAND. This city, which was once the capital of Independent Tartary, and the favourite residence of the great Timour, is now little better than a mass of ruins. Until the time of Shah Murad, the place was not only ruinous, but desert, the haunt of the wolf and the lion. That sovereign used all his efforts to restore and to repeople this place; and though it is still small, it is daily increasing. It formerly covered more ground than Bokhara ; and although the original walls, which tradition declares, though this is no doubt an exaggeration, to have been forty-eight miles in circuit, have mouldered into dust, Clavijo, a Spanish ambassador, who visited it about the year 1400, estimates the population of the city at 150,000 ; and a considerable number besides, for want of habitations, were obliged to shelter themselves in the caves of the surrounding rocks. The surrounding country also had a flourishing and populous appearance, being entirely covered with large villages, gardens, and country-houses, the residence of Tartar chiefs. A great proportion of the inhabitants consisted of persons who had been collected by Timour from every part of Asia, whose policy it was to bring hither all who were famous for the exercise of any art not followed in Samar- cand. It carried on, besides, a great inland commerce with Russia, Tartary, India, Turkey, and particularly China. The splendour of Timour’s court is said to have surpassed description, and his palaces vied with each other in magnificence. They were adorned with the spoils of conquered countries, and were resplendent with hangings of silk, gold and silver embroidery, tables of solid gold, and a display of rubies and precious stones that formed a dazzling scene. The city is still protected with a mud-wall, and has a citadel of the same materials ; but the principal buildings and most of the houses are constructed of stone. The mausoleum of Timour may still be seen here. It is a large building, with a very lofty dome, which was once covered with gold ; but this covering has since been taken off by Shall Murad. Within this building is the tomb, covered by a large flag of green stone, adorned with jewels, and sculptured over with the genealogical tree of the great Timour. Here, too, was the observatory of Oolugh Beg, which was destroyed by one of the many barbarous invaders of this country, and it is now a heap of dust. There were here also the tombs of many other distinguished persons, but they are all going to decay. Samarcand was a seat of religion and learning as well as of an extensive commerce ; and it contained many colleges, the finest of which was the Khanums, which is now all in ruins, and its extensive buildings laid waste. Some, however, are still inhabited.</p></body></text></TEI>