<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-19T20:10:52Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>benefit of the air and exercise ; so that, in reality, Savage endured fewer hardships in this place than he had usually , suffered during the greater part of his life. Whilst he remained in this not intolerable prison, his ingratitude again broke out, in a bitter satire on the city of Bristol, to which he certainly owed great obligations, notwithstanding the circumstances of his arrest, which was but the act of an individual, and that attended with no circumstances of injustice or cruelty.</p><p>When Savage had remained about six months in this hospitable prison, he received a letter from Mr Pope, who still continued to allow him L.20 a year, containing a charge of very atrocious ingratitude. What were the particulars of this charge we are not informed ; but, from the notorious character of the man, there is reason to fear that Savage was but too justly accused. He, however, solemnly protested his innocence ; but he was very unusually affected on this occasion. In a few days afterwards he was seized with a disorder, which at first was not suspected to be dangerous ; but growing daily more languid and dejected, at last a fever seized him, and he expired on the 1st of August 1743, in the forty-sixth year of his age.</p><p>SAVANNAH, formerly the capital of Georgia, in North America. This city is advantageously situated for a commercial town, being accessible to large vessels from the sea, and communicating with the interior by the noble river of the same name. It is built on a high bank rising about forty feet above the water; and its spacious and regular streets and handsome buildings, mingling with the groves of ornamental trees, have an imposing appearance. The site was formerly unhealthy, on account of the surrounding swamps ; but this evil has been remedied by judicious drainings, and by the substitution of the dry for the wet cultivation of rice around the city. Savannah was founded by General Oglethorpe in 1733, on a spot then known as the Yamacrow Bluff. It was captured by the British in 1778, and unsuccessfully besieged and assaulted by the French and Americans in the following year. In 1820 it suffered so much from a terrible fire, that its prosperity received a temporary check, and the population, which in 1820 had been 7523, was only 7423 in 1830; but it has since recovered from this shock, and has been for a number of years one of the most flourishing towns in the southern states, its population having increased to about 11,000 in 1835. Although the railroad from Augusta to Charlestown, and the security of the inland passage from the Savannah to that city, have of late tended to divert much of the trade thither, yet Savannah is the chief commercial dépôt in the state, and much of the cotton and rice of Georgia, with large quantities of the other exported articles, are shipped from its wharfs. In 1835, the exports included 250,000 bales of cotton, and 24,000 casks of rice ; and the whole value of exported articles in 1836 amounted to 15,469,000 dollars. Twenty steam-boats of a large class, and fifty steam tug-boats, are employed on the river ; and the shipping of the port amounts to 8375 tons. The banking institutions in the city are five, with an aggregate capital of 1,682,525 dollars. Long. 81. 10. W. Lat. 32.8. N.</p><p>SAVARY, <hi rend="smallcaps">James,</hi> an eminent French writer on the subject of trade, was born at Done, in Anjou, in 1622. Being bred to merchandise, he continued in trade until 1658, when he left off the practice, to cultivate the theory. He had married in 1650; and in 1660, when the king declared his purpose of assigning privileges and pensions to such of his subjects as had twelve children alive, Mr Sa- vary was not too rich to put in his claim to the royal bounty. He was afterwards admitted of the council for the reformation of commerce, and the orders which passed in 1670 were drawn up by his instructions and advice. He wrote <hi rend="italic">Le Parfait Negociant,</hi> 4to ; and <hi rend="italic">Avis et conseils sur les Importantes Matières du commerce,</hi> in 4to. He died in 1690;</p><p>and out of seventeen children whom he had by one wife, he left eleven. Two of his sons, James and Philemon Louis, laboured jointly on a great work, <hi rend="italic">Dictionnaire Universelle du commerce,</hi> in two vols. folio. This work was begun by James, who was inspector-general of the manufactures at the custom-house, Paris, and who called in the assistance of his brother Philemon Louis, although a canon of the royal church of St Maur, and by his death left him to finish it. This work appeared in 1723, and Philemon afterwards added a third supplemental volume. Postlethwayte’s English Dictionary of Trade and Commerce is a translation, with considerable improvements, from Savary.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sλvary, </hi><hi rend="italic">M.,</hi> an eminent French traveller and writer, was born at Vitre, in Bretagne, about the year 1748. He studied with applause at Rennes, and in 1776 travelled into Egypt, where he remained nearly three years. During this period he was wholly engaged in the study of the Arabian language, in searching out ancient monuments, and in examining the national manners. After making himself acquainted with the knowledge and philosophy of Egypt, he visited the islands in the Archipelago, where he spent eighteen months. On his return to France in the year 1780, he published, 1. A Translation of the Koran, with a short Life of Mahommed, in 1783, two vols. 8vo ; 2. The Morality of the Koran, or a Collection of the most excellent Maxims in the Koran ; 3. Letters on Egypt, in three vols. 8vo, in 1785. In these the author makes his observations with accuracy, paints with vivacity, and renders interesting everything he relates. His descriptions are in general faithful, but are perhaps in some instances too much ornamented. He has been justly censured for painting modem Egypt and its inhabitants in too high colours. He died on the 4th of February 1788.</p><p>SAVE, a river of Germany, which has its source in Upper Carniola, on the frontiers of Carinthia. It runs through Carniola from west to east, afterwards separates Sclavonia from Croatia, Bosnia, and part of Servia, and then falls into the Danube at Belgrade.</p><p>SA VENAY, an arrondissement of the department of the Lower Loire, in France, extending over 210,279 hectares, which, in English measure, is equal to 739<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/4 square miles. It is divided into eleven cantons, and these into fifty-one communes, with (in 1836) 114,256 inhabitants. The capital is a town of the same name, which, in 1836, contained 2079 inhabitants.</p><p>SAVENDROOG, a celebrated fortress of the south of India, in Mysore. It is strongly situated on the summit of an immense rock, half a mile in nearly perpendicular height, and surrounded by a thick wood. It was taken by the British in 1791, without the loss of a man. Long. 77. 29. E. Lat. 12. 56. N.</p><p>SAVERNE, an arrondissement of the department of the Lower Rhine, in France. Its extent is 297,104 acres, equal to 464 square miles ; and is divided into seven cantons, and these into 165 communes, with a population, in the year 1836, of 112,260 persons. The capital, a city of the same name, stands on the river Zorn, at the foot of the Vosges Mountains, in one of the most luxuriant parts of ancient Alsace. It is antiquely built, and contains 5352 inhabitants, who generally speak the German language. Long. 7. 48. 21. E. Lat. 48. 44. 20. N.</p><p>SAVIGLIANO, a city of Italy, in the kingdom of Sardinia and province of Turin. It stands on a fine plain watered by the river Maira. It is well built, and has a fine market-place, magnificcnt palaces, several churches and monasteries, and 18,750 inhabitants, among whom are many of the nobility. It has some considerable manufactures of silk and linen goods, and considerable trade in cattle, wine, and corn, especially in maize. Long. 6. 33. E. Lat. 44. 30. N.</p><p>SAVIGNANO, a town of Italy, in the papal delegation</p></body></text></TEI>