<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-19T20:10:29Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Galicia, of which it is the capital. It is about six leagues from the sea, on a little river not navigable, called the Sar,</p><p>which unites with another called the Sancta, and then flows into the Ulla, and joins the river Arosa, which has at its entrance to the ocean some secure harbours for small vessels. This is an archiepiscopal city, and is one of the most richly endowed of all the cathedrals of the kingdom. In former times this church was the resort of pilgrims from every part of Spain, and a great part of the rest of Europe. The votive offerings have therefore been prodigious, and though the veneration for the shrine of St Iago has been on the decline for many years, yet the accumulation of past periods now serves to keep in idleness, if not in profligacy, a great number of ecclesiastics. The city contains a university of considerable celebrity, a very large and well-regulated hospital, and several smaller ones, besides other sumptuous public edifices. It contains about 25,000 inhabitants, the greater part of whom depend on the religious houses, especially some thousands of poor, who are not disposed to work, because the donations in food and in money from the different pious establishments are sufficient to keep them alive, and allow them to indulge in their habitual indolence. There are indeed some few manufactories of linens, laces, and tapes ; they languish, however, and give employment but to very few. The surrounding country is cold and sterile, and therefore the donations of the pious are expended in obtaining necessaries from the more distant parts of the province.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Santiago</hi>, or <hi rend="italic">Sr Jago,</hi> the capital of the republic of Chili, in South America, is delightfully situated in an extensive plain on the southern shore of the river Mapocho, on each side of which large mounds of stone have been raised as a security against inundation. On the opposite side of the river lie the suburbs, of Chimba, Cannadilla, and Renca, which are connected with the city by means of a beautiful bridge. The streets are straight, wide, well paved, and cross each other at right angles, which divides the city into quadras or solid squares. Water is conveyed from the river by means of aqueducts, which not only supply the inhabitants, but, running through the streets, keep the town very clean. The houses are flat-roofed, of one story, and, being white-washed, give the town a very gay appearance. They are built in a quadrangular form, and all the rooms may be entered from a square court in the middle, or from doors of communication from one to the other. The entrance from the street is by a broad porch, on either side of which are stables, &amp;c. The great square is 450 feet on each side, in the middle of which there is a fine bronze fountain. The north side is occupied by the directorial palace, a splendid building, having the city prison under the same roof. On the western side are the cathedral, and a mean-looking palace of the bishop. The most remarkable edifices are the cathedral, the church of St Dominick, the great college, which formerly belonged to the Jesuits, and the town-hall. The mint is situated in an obscure part of the town. Being the centre of the commerce of Chili, it abounds with all sorts of provisions, which are very cheap. The inhabitants are gay, hospitable, more inclined to hold intercourse with strangers, and less bigoted, than their countrymen generally are. The population is about 45,000. It is thirty leagues distant from the Pacific Ocean, seven from the Andes, and fifty-five miles east- south-east from the port of Valparaiso. Long. 70. 44. W. Lat. 33. 26. S.</p><p>SANTIPONTE, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Santiponce,</hi> a town of Spain, in the division of Andalusia and government of Seville, about five miles from that city, situated on the right bank of the river Guadiana. It is celebrated for its antiquity, having been the seat of the old Roman Italica, the city of which the Emperor Trajan was a native. The remains of Roman magnificence still visible prove it to have been a place of</p><p>considerable importance. The most remarkable object is the amphitheatre, which, though in ruins, still shows its dimensions and the plan of its original construction. It is formed of Roman bricks for the foundation, and stone benches of ten rows rising one above the other, so as to seat conveniently ten thousand spectators. The ruins of the ancient city are scattered over the fields near the amphitheatre, and abundance of coins and inscriptions are to be found. A beautiful tessellated pavement, lately discovered, has upon it figures which represent the Muses and the signs of the zodiac, the outlines of which are correct, and the colours fresh and brilliant. ' There is, or was till lately, a rich convent of St Jerome, with many hospitable monks. A very large fair is annually held at this place, and the church of the monastery has several exquisite paintings.</p><p>SANTIPORE, a town of Bengal, in the district of Kish- enagur, situated on a sandy soil, two miles east of the Bhagurutty river. Long. 28. 34. E. Lat. 23. 13. N.</p><p>SANTORIN, one of the Greek islands in the Ægean Sea, and among the richest and best peopled of their number. It is about seventy-eight square miles in extent. Its appearance is that of a mountain perpendicularly cut downwards from the sea, composed of various volcanic matters, such as basalt, puzzolana, and pumice. The surface is much covered with the latter substance in almost every part, but mixed with good vegetable mould. This soil is peculiarly adapted to the growth of wine, of which a vast quantity is made, and forms the chief drink, as there is little and in many parts no good water, but rain that is preserved. Some barley is grown, but far short of what is consumed. There are some figs, almonds, and pulse, and a little cotton wool, raised. The inhabitants amount to twelve thousand, all Greeks, some adhering to the Greek religion, but some are Catholics, and each sect has its own bishop. There are five small towns and several villages. The capital is on the east side, and called Emporia. Long. 26. 15. E. Lat. 36. 21. N.</p><p>SANTUR, a Turkish stringed instrument, resembling that kind of German psaltery which is especially used in Hungary in the dances of the common people.</p><p>SAONE, a considerable river of France, which has its source in the Vosges, near Darney, and falls into the Rhone at Lyons.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Saone</hi>, <hi rend="smallcaps">Upper,</hi> a department of France, formed out of a part of the ancient province of High Burgundy, or Franche Comté. It is bounded on the north by the Upper Marne and the Vosges, on the east by the Upper Rhine, on the south by the Doubs and the Jura, and on the west by the Cote d’Or and the Upper Marne. It extends, according to the <hi rend="italic">Statistique de la France,</hi> over 530,990 hectares, equal to 1867 square miles, and is divided into three arrondissements, twenty-eight cantons, and 651 communes, with a population of 343,298 persons. The chief river is that from which the name is taken, which rises in the Vosges, and is navigable for only a short portion of its course through this department. The other rivers are the Oignon, the Drageon, the Amance, the Auterne, the Saolon, and the Branchin. The surface consists of mountains, hills, and valleys. A spur from the Vosges Mountains enters the eastern side of the department, but to the south-west it is quite level. The soil for the most part consists of clay, and is very stony ; but much of it is fertile, and a great part covered with woods. Although the husbandry is conducted in a slovenly manner, yet it yields sufficient corn for the consumption, and more of wheat than of rye. There are abundance of good meadows which afford pasturage for cows, and the dairies produce excellent butter. Fruit is plentiful, especially walnuts, from which much valuable oil is extracted. The vine is extensively cultivated, the vineyards occupying about 20,000 acres, which enables the inhabitants to export some wine. There are mines of iron</p></body></text></TEI>