<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-19T20:13:16Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>country, but in England. There can be no doubt, however, that they had their origin
                in Scotland.@@<hi rend="superscript">1</hi></p>
            <p>The courts we have now adverted to comprehend the public and general courts of the
                kingdom, which have a public and general jurisdiction ; but besides these, there
                are, or rather were, some whose jurisdiction was limited to particular sorts of
                causes only. We allude to the Court of Exchequer, and the ecclesiastical and
                maritime courts.</p>
            <p>With respect to the first of these, the old Scotch court, composed of the treasurer
                and lords auditors of exchequer, was superseded at the union by a Court of
                Exchequer, composed of a lord chief-baron and four puisne barons ; and in addition
                to certain ministerial powers continued from the old court, it had the like
                authority, jurisdiction, and course of procedure as the Court of Exchequer in
                England, after which generally it was modelled. It was an absurdly large and
                expensive establishment. It had comparatively nothing to do ; and as the judges
                might be, and some of them commonly were, English barristers, it never could be
                opened up, like the exchequer of England, to the ordinary law business of the
                country. Accordingly the barons were gradually reduced, and the business is now
                transacted by a lord of session sitting as a judge in exchequer.</p>
            <p>The Commission of Teinds, which was first erected at the Reformation, was in like
                manner remodelled at the Union. It was formerly vested with powers for the planting
                of churches, assigning and modifying stipends, and the valuation and sale of teinds.
                But by a recent statute, all actions for the valuation or sale of teinds, all
                actions of suspension or reduction of localities, and all actions of declarator or
                reduction connected with teinds, must be brought and decided in the Court of
                Session.</p>
            <p>In times of popery, causes ecclesiastical were tried by the archdeacon’s official,
                the bishop’s commissary, and the auditor or official principal of the province ;
                from which last an appeal lay to the pope, who generally determined the matter by
                commission. But at the Reformation, commissaries named by tne crown were appointed
                in every commissariat ; and a Commissary Court, with original and appellate
                jurisdiction, was also established at Edinburgh, of which Sir James Balfour, the
                former official of St. Andrews, within the archdeaconry of Lothian, was the first
                chief- judge. The commissary courts continued till recent times, when the office of
                the local commissaries was abolished, and soon afterwards the Commissary Court of
                Edinburgh, their powers and jurisdiction being transferred to the Court of</p>
            <p>Session, and, in as far as regards confirmation pf testaments, to the sheriff or
                county courts.</p>
            <p>The jurisdiction of the Admiralty cannot perhaps be traced to an earlier period than
                the beginning of the sixteenth century, when the office of lord justiciar, who was
                of old the supreme judge in all manner of causes, became hereditary in the noble
                family of Argyll, and the authority of the Admiralty was also long very limited. It
                was confined to seafaring causes, and in these it had no exclusive
                    jurisdiction.@@<hi rend="superscript">2</hi> The earliest collection of maritime
                laws in Scotland, is that contained in Balfour’s <hi rend="italic">Practicks,</hi>
                and entitled “ The Sea Laws, collectit furth of the Actis of Parliament, the prac-
                tiques and lawis of Oberon, and the lawis of Wisbeig, and the constitutions of
                Francois, king of France, 1543, 1557.” This we conceive was the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Lib. Kintor.</hi> referred to by Balfour, and the work of David Kintore, then
                judge of the Admiralty. Towards the end of the same century, Alexander King,
                advocate, filled the same office ; and from the date of his <hi rend="italic"
                    >Treatise on Maritime Law,</hi> apparently the first regular treatise on that
                branch of jurisprudence in Great Britain, the court of Admiralty rose into
                importance. By the act 1609, c. 15, it was declared a sovereign judicatory, and
                letters of homing were allowed on its decrees ; and the reputation of the court
                being afterwards sustained by a succession of eminent judges, such as Acheson of
                Glencairney, Roberton of Beidlay, and Lyon of Carse, all of whom became lords of
                Session, it began to extend its jurisdiction generally to mercantile, and not, as
                before, to mere seafaring causes. The above act was then ratified by that of 1681,
                c. 16, by which the ground of the court was farther cleared and enlarged ; the
                admiral being now also styled the high admiral, and declared the king’s lieutenant
                and justice-general on the high seas. By a later statute, provision was made for a
                stated salary of L.100 to the judge of the Admiralty. This was renewed by the act
                1704, c. 8; and by 26 Geo. III. c. 47, the salary was made L.400, which was
                afterwards raised to L.800 a-year. The court, however, did not long enjoy this flow
                of prosperity By the 6 Geo. IV. c. 120, jurisdiction in prize and capture was
                withdrawn, and vested in the Admiralty of England ; and by a later statute the court
                was altogether abolished, and its remaining jurisdiction transferred to the Court of
                Session, and Sheriff courts ; the High Court of Justiciary having also previously
                re-acquired, as of old, a co-ordinate jurisdiction in crimes at sea.</p>
            <p>An ancient species of exempt territory was that of <hi rend="italic">sanctuary.</hi>
                The first of the sort were probably churches ; and</p>
            <p>@@@ The following table, from official returns, of causes brought for the five years
                preceding 1882, will give an idea of the working of the ordinary civil courts of the
                sheriffs in some of the principal counties.</p>
            <table cols="6">
                <row>
                    <cell/>
                    <cell>Actions brought.</cell>
                    <cell>Decreets in Absence.</cell>
                    <cell>Litigated.</cell>
                    <cell>Appealed to Sheriff-Depute.</cell>
                    <cell>Taken to Court of Session or Justiciary.</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Edinburgh </cell>
                    <cell> 6,782</cell>
                    <cell>2,322</cell>
                    <cell>2,248</cell>
                    <cell>611</cell>
                    <cell>91</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Lanark, </cell>
                    <cell> 10,227</cell>
                    <cell>4,320</cell>
                    <cell>5,907</cell>
                    <cell>1,725</cell>
                    <cell>181 </cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Perth </cell>
                    <cell> 6,823</cell>
                    <cell>3,377</cell>
                    <cell>2,971</cell>
                    <cell>887</cell>
                    <cell>85</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Aberdeen, </cell>
                    <cell> 6,033</cell>
                    <cell>3,777</cell>
                    <cell>2,256</cell>
                    <cell>543</cell>
                    <cell>71</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Forfar </cell>
                    <cell> 3.531</cell>
                    <cell>1,636</cell>
                    <cell>1,823</cell>
                    <cell>298</cell>
                    <cell>7</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Argyle </cell>
                    <cell> 3,033</cell>
                    <cell>1,580</cell>
                    <cell>679</cell>
                    <cell>No return.</cell>
                    <cell>9</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Ayr, </cell>
                    <cell> 2,764</cell>
                    <cell>938</cell>
                    <cell>1,826</cell>
                    <cell>1,461</cell>
                    <cell>54</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Dumfries, </cell>
                    <cell> 2,653</cell>
                    <cell>1,420</cell>
                    <cell>1,233</cell>
                    <cell>No return.</cell>
                    <cell>47</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Fife </cell>
                    <cell> 2,442</cell>
                    <cell>1,1083</cell>
                    <cell>1,596</cell>
                    <cell>382</cell>
                    <cell>34</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Inverness, </cell>
                    <cell> 2,385</cell>
                    <cell>1,413</cell>
                    <cell>801</cell>
                    <cell>232</cell>
                    <cell>28</cell>
                </row>
            </table>
            <p>The following table, from official returns, will show the working of the small debt
                courts, and at the same time point out the preference given to the sheriff, or to
                the justices of the peace, in the counties named.</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Number of Small Debt Causes decided in the year</hi> 1832.</p>
            <table cols="7">
                <row>
                    <cell/>
                    <cell>By the Justices.</cell>
                    <cell>By the Sheriff. </cell>
                    <cell rows="6"/>
                    <cell/>
                    <cell>By the Justices.</cell>
                    <cell>By the Sheriff.</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Edinburgh,..</cell>
                    <cell> 9,254</cell>
                    <cell>4,055</cell>
                    <cell>Argyle, </cell>
                    <cell>338</cell>
                    <cell> 1,133</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Lanark, </cell>
                    <cell> 9,001</cell>
                    <cell>11,182</cell>
                    <cell>Ross </cell>
                    <cell> 190</cell>
                    <cell>1,320</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Aberdeen,...</cell>
                    <cell> 2,322</cell>
                    <cell>2,769</cell>
                    <cell>Inverness</cell>
                    <cell> 141</cell>
                    <cell>1,531</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Forfar, </cell>
                    <cell> 1,767</cell>
                    <cell>2,093</cell>
                    <cell>Clackmannan,</cell>
                    <cell> 21</cell>
                    <cell>224</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Perth, </cell>
                    <cell> 993</cell>
                    <cell>1,543</cell>
                    <cell>Haddington, </cell>
                    <cell> 2</cell>
                    <cell>282</cell>
                </row>
            </table>
            <p>@@@* See Leg. Burg. c. 27; Pitcairn's Criminal Trials, vol. i. part i. p. 129, and
                part ii. p. 83; and A. S., 16th January 1554.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
