<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-19T20:11:05Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>reigns of the ancient kings, is full of fables ; but the eight last books, and particularly those which regard the events of his own times, deserve the utmost credit. He wrote in Latin ; and the style, if we consider the barbarous age in which he flourished, is in general extremely elegant, but rather too poetical for history. Mallet, in his <hi rend="italic">Histoire de I)annemarc</hi> (vol. i. p. 182), says that “ Sperling;, a writer of great erudition, has proved, in contradiction to the assertions of Stephens and others, that Saxo-Grammaticus was secretary to Absalon, and that the Saxo, provost of Roskild, was another person, and lived earlier.”</p><p>SAXONY, one of the provinces of the kingdom of Prussia. It has been formed out of several of the hereditary states of the monarchy, and also by the addition of the territory of some mediatized princes, and in a great measure by extensive parts of the kingdom of Saxony which were transferred to Prussia by the negotiations for the general peace of 1814. The parts then conveyed from Saxony were the duchy of that name and its province of Thuringia. The actual province now extends in north latitude from 50° 27' to 53° 5', and in east longitude from 9° 44' bo 13° 58', being 9902 square miles. The division of the province is into three governments, assuming the names of the cities where the several administrative boards are established, viz. Magdeburg, Merseburg, and Erfurt. The population amounted in 1817 to 1,214,219, but had, like that of the other parts of Prussia, increased so as to amount in 1831, according to the census at the end of that year, to 1,449,587. Of these persons, two thirds adhere to the Lutheran church, and the other third are mostly Catholics, but with a small number of other protestant sects, and some Jews. The Catholics are chiefly found in the circles of Upper and Lower Reichsfeld, and in that of Erfurt.</p><p>The greater part of the province is a plain, with a few undulations ; but on the western side, in the circles of Merseburg and Erfurt, are the Thuringian Hills, which are elevated but fertile, and include a part of the Hartz Forest, which is mountainous and woody. The whole is well watered by various small rivulets, which form the rivers Mulda, Saale, Ohre, Aland, Black-Alster, and Havel, all of which run through the Elbe to the German Ocean. There are three canals, viz. the Plauen, which unites the Havel with the Elbe, which is about twenty miles in length, and is used for navigation ; the Shiffigraben, between Magdeburg and Brunswick, which is chiefly constructed for draining a rich tract of land ; and the Flossgraben, in Merseburg, which connects the Elster and the Pegau, and is chiefly used for floating timber. The rivers, lakes, and ponds are very fully stocked with a variety of fishes.</p><p>No part of Germany is better cultivated than this province, and as the land is of a moderate quality, it yields abundant crops, and is considered as the granary of the Prussian dominions. The number of sheep is very great, and the wool of them, which has been much improved of late years, both supplies the home manufacturers, and also exports much to other countries. The inhabitants are industrious, cleanly, and temperate, like all the Saxons ; and there is the appearance of ease in the villages and towns, where the manufacture of linens and woollens is the usual employment. There are mines, in that part which is within the Hartz, that produce silver, copper, iron, and coals ; but the most productive of the mines are those of salt, which are found at a great depth in various parts of the province, and supply abundance of culinary salt when refined.</p><p>The country of Saxony is remarkable for bcing∙ the cradle of the present English nation ; but concerning the Saxons themselves previous to that period, we have very few particulars. The Saxons, says Mr Whitaker, have been derived by our historians from very different parts of the globe ; India, the north of Asia, and the forests of Germany. Their appellation, too, has been equally referred</p><p>to very different causes ; the name of their Indian progenitor, the plundering disposition of their Asiatic fathers, and the short, hooked weapons of their warriors. But the real origin of the Saxons, and the genuine derivation of their name, seem to be different.</p><p>In the earlier period of the Gallic history, the Celtæ of Gaul crossed the Rhine in considerable numbers, and planted various colonies in the regions beyond it. Thus the Volcæ Tectosages settled on one side of the Hercynian Forest and about the banks of the Neckar; the Helvetii upon another and about the Rhine and Maine ; the Boii beyond both ; and the Senones in the heart of Germany. Thus also we see the Treviri, the Nervii, the Suevi, and the Marcomanni, the Quadi, the Venedi, and others in that country, all plainly indicated as Gallic nations, by the Gallic appellations which they bear, and all together possessing the greatest part of it. And, even as late as the conclusion of the first century, we find one nation on the eastern side of this great continent actually speaking the language of Gaul, and another upon the northern side using a dialect nearly related to the British. But as all the various tribes of the Germans are considered by Strabo as <hi rend="italic">γεvησιoι </hi>Γ<hi rend="italic">αλαται,</hi> or genuine Gauls in their origin, so those particularly that lived immediately beyond the Rhine, and are asserted by Tacitus to be indubitably native Germans, are expressly denominated  Γ<hi rend="italic">αλαται</hi>, or Gauls, by Diodorus, and declared by Dio to have been from the earliest period distinguished by the equivalent appellation of <hi rend="italic">Celtæ.</hi> And the broad line of nations which extended along the ocean, and reached to the borders of Scythia, was all known to the learned in the days of Diodorus by the same significant appellation of Γ<hi rend="italic">αλαται</hi>, Gauls.</p><p>Of these the most noted were the Sicambri and Cimbri, the former being situated near the channel of the Rhine, and the latter inhabiting the peninsula of Jutland. The denominations of both declare their original, showing them to have been derived from the common stock of the Celtæ, and to be of the same Celtic kindred with the Cimbri of our Somersetshire, and the Cymbri or Cambrians of our Wales. The Cimbri are accordingly denominated Celtæ by Strabo and Appian ; and they are equally asserted to be Gauls by Diodorus, descendants of that nation which sacked the city of Rome, plundered the temple of Delphi, and subdued a great part of Europe and some of Asia.</p><p>Immediately to the south of these were the Saxons, extending from the isthmus of the Chersonesus to the current of the Elbe ; and they were equally Celtic in their origin as their neighbours. They were denominated Ambrones as well as Saxons; and as such, they are included by Tacitus under the general appellation of <hi rend="italic">Cimbri,</hi> and comprehended in Plutarch under the equal one of <hi rend="italic">Cello-Scythœ.</hi> The name of Ambrones appears particularly to have been Gallic, being common to the Saxons beyond the Elbe, and the Ligurians in Cisalpine Gaul ; as both found to their surprise, on the irruption of the former into Italy with the Cimbri. And, what is equally surprising, and has been equally unnoticed by the critics, the Welsh distinguish England by the name of <hi rend="italic">Loegr</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Liguria,</hi> even to the present moment. In that irruption these Saxons, Ambrones, or Ligurians, composed a body of more than thirty thousand men, and were principally concerned in cutting to pieces the large armies of Manlius and Cæpio. Nor is the appellation of Saxons less Celtic than the other. It was originally the same with the Belgic Suessones of Gaul ; the capital of that tribe being now entitled Soisons by the French, and the name of the Saxons pronounced Saisen by the Welsh, Sason by the Scotch, and Sasenach by the Irish. And the Suessones or Saxones of Gaul derived their own appellation from the position of their metropolis on a river, the stream at Soisons being now denominated the Aisne, and formerly the Axon ; Uesson or Axon importing only waters or a river, and S-uess-on or S-ax-on on the waters or the river. The</p></body></text></TEI>