<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-19T20:11:48Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>interminable marshes, the mountainous ranges which presented such formidable obstacles to the march of a regular army, the rivers, of which the fords were unknown, and the want of subsistence for his troops, except what he carried along with him, must have combined to throw infinite difficulties in his way. The classical writers who have described his campaign inform us, in general terms, that he was obliged to fell the forests, to drain the marshes, to open up the country by roads, and to construct bridges ; and they affirm that the Roman emperor did not retrace his steps till he had proceeded so far north, that the soldiers remarked the extraordinary length of the days and shortness of the nights, in comparison with those of Italy.@@<hi rend="superscript">1</hi> There seems good reason to believe that the spot where the Roman eagles terminated their flight in this memorable expedition, was the promontory separating the Cromarty and the Moray Friths. Here, according to Chalmers, the Caledonians sought for peace, surrendered their arms, and relinquished a portion of their country.@@<hi rend="superscript">1</hi> The critical student must pardon the vagueness of these expressions, as the historians of the time do not enable us to be more definite.</p><p>Severus retired to York in a feeble state of health ; but it was not to repose upon his laurels, for scarcely had he reached that station when news arrived that the Caledonians were again in arms. Irritated by disappointment and disease, he determined instantly to renew the war ; intrusted the leading of the army to his son Caracalla ; and issued orders to spare neither age nor sex. But death happily arrested these inhuman projects. The emperor expired at York, and the son does not appear, on any good evidence, to have executed the orders of the father.</p><p>Previously to his celebrated northern campaign, Severus is said to have reconstructed the rampart originally built by Hadrian between the Tyne and the Solway ; a circumstance from which there arises a strong presumption that the Caledonians had encroached upon the Roman provinces, and regained much of the intermediate country between the walls of Hadrian and Antoninus.</p><p>From this period, <hi rend="smallcaps">(a.D.</hi> 211), which marks the commencement of the third, to nearly the middle of the fifth century, (446), the Romans appear to have abandoned all thoughts of extending their conquests. The vast fabric of their empire was now, as is well known, in a state of melancholy feebleness and decay ; attacked on every side by those fierce tribes who were destined to destroy it ; and unable to retain provinces far nearer and more important than those in Britain. For some time, however, an effort was made to defend the northern Romanized Britons from the repeated incursions of the Caledonians. In the commencement of the fourth century, <hi rend="smallcaps">(a.D.</hi> 306), Constans revisited Britain for this purpose ; in the year 368, after a sanguinary and destructive invasion of the barbarians, a temporary tranquillity was restored by the arms of Theodosius; in 398, Stilicho, alarmed by new excesses and increasing weakness in the northern provinces, sent such effectual aid as enabled the Roman governors once more to repel the enemy; and, lastly, in the year 422, the emperor Honorius, having in vain endeavoured to rouse the provincial inhabitants to a vigorous effort in</p><p>their own defence, sent a legion to their assistance, by whose efforts the fortifications of the two walls were repaired, and the barbarians once more driven back into their more northern seats. But this was the last relief which could be wrung by her miserable children from a parent who was herself expiring; and it secured for them but a brief period of tranquillity. Imperial Rome, with a tardy and ostentatious justice, conferred freedom on the southern Britons ; and restoring a country which she was no longer able to hold, informed them that henceforth they must trust to their own efforts for the defence of their independence. Having given this parting advice to men who appear to have been little able to follow it, the Romans abandoned Britain for ever.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sect.</hi> II.—<hi rend="italic">The Pictish Period.</hi></p><p>In the brief sketch which has been given of the Roman dominion in north Britain, which extended from the year 85 to 446, a period of little more than three centuries and a half, we have seen that the Romanized Britons were constantly exposed to the invasions of their more northern neighbours, who threatened at last to wrest from them the whole of the country, which had been fortified by Roman skill and mainly defended by Roman soldiers. The question now arises, who were these fierce and indomitable tribes ? And to this inquiry, in which antiquaries have spilt almost as much ink as the Romans did blood, the research of a laborious writer enables us to give a satisfactory answer. It appears from the investigation of Chalmers that “at the epoch of Agricola’s invasion, the ample extent of north Britain was inhabited by one-and-twenty tribes, who were connected by such slight ties as scarcely to enjoy a social state. These were the <hi rend="italic">Ottadini,</hi> who appear to have occupied the whole extent of coast from the southern Tyne to the Frith of Forth ;@@<hi rend="superscript">3</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Gadeni,</hi> whose seats lay in the interior country, from the Tyne on the south to the Frith on the north ; the <hi rend="italic">Selgovæ,</hi> whose western boundary was the Dee, and their southern limit the Solway Frith; the <hi rend="italic">Novantes,</hi> who inhabited the midland and western parts of Galloway ; and the <hi rend="italic">Damnii,</hi> who possessed the shires of Ayr, Renfrew, and Stirling, with a portion of Dunbarton and Perth. Such were the five tribes,” says this author, “which occupied, during the first century, that ample region extending from the Tyne and the Solway on the south, to the Forth and the Clyde on the north, varying their limits with the fluctuations of war, conquest, or internal dissensions, during the succession of many ages.”@@* Beyond the Forth we find the Horestii, the Venricones, the Taixali, the Vacomagi, the Albani, the Attacotti, the Caledonii, the Cante, the Logi, the Carnabii, the Catini, the Merte, the Carnonacæ, the Creones, and the Epidii. The names of these twenty-one original tribes, which are taken from Chalmers, are by him transcribed from the account of Ptolemy, checked by the ancient treatise and map of Richard of Cirencester.@@<hi rend="superscript">4</hi> Of the manners of this ancient people, it is impossible, in the absence of all authentic documents, to speak with certainty. From the general account given by Cæsar, they were little removed in the scale of social life or of civil government</p><p><hi rend="superscript">@@@1</hi> Caledonia, vol. i. p. 186, 187.</p><p><hi rend="superscript">@@@!</hi> The son of Severus is indeed affirmed to have fought on the banks of the Carron with the heroes of Ossian ; but much has yet to be proved before we venture to transplant these shadowy contests into the field of history.</p><p><hi rend="superscript">@@@3</hi>	Including the half of Northumberland, the eastern portion of Roxburghshire, all Berwickshire, and East Lothian.</p><p><hi rend="superscript">@@@4</hi>	Caledonia, vol. i. p. 62.</p><p><hi rend="superscript">@@@4</hi> It ought however to be stated, that some grave doubts bang over the genuineness of this early writer. Dr. Stukeley's account of him is vague, and the story told by Professor Bertram regarding his discovery of the manuscript and the map is still more suspicious. I have abstained from giving from Chalmers the exact limits of the possessions held by the last sixteen tribes, who inhabited the whole extent of country beyond the Forth to the extremity of Caithness. The research and erudition which he has displayed is entitled to all praise ; but it is difficult to believe that the boundaries of these remote, fierce, and wandering aborigines should be ascertainable with us much precision after the lapse of eighteen centuries as the <hi rend="italic">marches</hi> of Middlesex or Yorkshire. Two points, however, and these of leading importance, Chalmers conceives that he has established : the first, that Britain, from its extreme southern to its most remote northern point, was peopled from Gaul ; and the second, that the aborigines over the whole island were a Celtic race.</p></body></text></TEI>