<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-22-r01-0880-02" facs="encyclopaediabri22chisrich_0905.jp2" type="entry">

<p><label>RAMSAY, SIR WILLIAM MITCHELL</label>
(1851- ), British</p><p>archaeologist, was born on the 15th of March 1851. He was educated at the universities of Aberdeen, Oxford and Göttingen, and was a fellow of Exeter College, Oxford (1882; honorary fellow 1898), and Lincoln College (1885; honorary 1899). In 1885 he was elected professor of classical art at Oxford, and in the next year professor of humanity at Aberdeen. From 1880 onwards he travelled widely in Asia Minor and rapidly became the recognized authority on all matters relating to the districts associ-ated with St Paul’s missionary journeys and on Christianity in the early Roman Empire. He received the honorary degrees of D.C.L. Oxford, LL.D. St Andrews and Glasgow, D.D. Edinburgh, and was knighted in 1906. He was elected a member of learned societies in Europe and America, and has been awarded medals by the Royal Geographical Society, the Royal Scottish Geographical Society and the University of Pennsylvania. His numerous publications include: <hi rend="italic">The Historical Geography of Asia Minor</hi> (1890); <hi rend="italic">The Church in the Roman Empire</hi> (1893); <hi rend="italic">The Cities and Bishoprics of Phrygia</hi> (2 vols., 1895, 1897); <hi rend="italic">St Paul the Traveller and the Roman Citizen</hi> (1895; Germ. trans., 1898); <hi rend="italic">Impressions of Turkey</hi> (1897); <hi rend="italic">Was Christ born at Bethlehem?</hi> (1898); <hi rend="italic">Historical Commentary on Galatians</hi> (1899); <hi rend="italic">The Education of Christ</hi> (1902); <hi rend="italic">The Letters io the Seven Churches of Asia</hi> (1905); <hi rend="italic">Pauline and other Studies in Early Christian History</hi> (1906) ; <hi rend="italic">Studies in the History and Art of the Eastern Provinces of the Roman Empire</hi> (1906); <hi rend="italic">The Cities of St Paul</hi> (1907); <hi rend="italic">Lucan and Pauline Studies</hi> (1908) ; <hi rend="italic">The Thousand and One Churches</hi> (with Miss Gertrude L. Bell, 1909); and articles in learned periodicals and the 9th, 10th and nth editions of the <hi rend="italic">Encyclopaedia Britannica.</hi> His wife, Lady Ramsay, granddaughter of Dr Andrew Marshall of Kirkintilloch, accompanied him in many of his journeys and is the author of <hi rend="italic">Everyday Life in Turkey</hi> (1897) and <hi rend="italic">The Romance of Elisaυet</hi> (1899).</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>