<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-22-r01-0793-02"
                facs="encyclopaediabri22chisrich_0818.jp2" type="entry">

                <p><label>RADIOACTIVITY</label>. The subject of radioactivity deals with phenomena
                    exhibited by a special class of bodies of high atomic weight of which uranium,
                    thorium, radium and actinium are the best known examples. These substances
                    possess the property of spontaneously emitting radiations of a special character
                    which are able to penetrate through matter opaque to ordinary light. The
                    beginning of this subject dates from 1896, and was an indirect consequence of
                    the discovery of the X rays made a few months before by Röntgen. It was known
                    that the production of X rays in a vacuum tube was accompanied by a strong
                    phosphorescence of the glass, and it occurred to several investigators that
                    ordinary substances made phos-phorescent by visible light might emit a
                    penetrating radiation similar to X rays. Following out this idea, H. Becquerel
                    (1), <note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="1"> These numbers
                        refer to papers noted under <hi rend="italic">References</hi> (below). </note> <hi rend="sup">l</hi> a distinguished French physicist, exposed amongst other
                    substances a phosphorescent compound of uranium, uranium-</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-22-r01-0794" facs="encyclopaediabri22chisrich_0819.jp2"/>
               <p>potassium sulphate, enveloped in paper beneath a photographic plate. A weak
                    photographic effect was obtained. This was shown to be due to a penetrating
                    radiation capable of passing through sheets of matter opaque to ordinary light.
                    Further investigation showed that this photographic action was ex-hibited by all
                    compounds of uranium and by the metal itself, and had nothing to do with
                    phosphorescence. It was shown equally if the uranium were kept in darkness and
                    did not vary appreciably with time. Becquerel showed that the rays from uranium
                    like X rays were capable of discharging a body whether positively or negatively
                    electrified. A uranium compound brought close to the charged plate of a gold
                    leaf electroscope causes a rapid collapse of the gold leaves. This property of
                    uranium, and also of the radioactive bodies in general, has supplied a delicate
                    and quantitative method of accurate comparison of the intensity of the
                    radiations from substances under varying conditions. A modified form of gold
                    leaf electroscope has come into general use for comparison of the radioactivity
                    of substances. Rutherford (2) made a systematic examination of the discharging
                    effect produced by the rays from uranium and showed that it was due to the
                    pro-duction of charged carriers or ions in the volume of the gas through which
                    the radiations pass. In an electric field, the positive ions travel to the
                    negative electrode and vice versa, thus causing a discharge of the electrified
                    body. If a suffi-ciently strong field is used, the ions are all swept to the
                    electrodes before appreciable loss of their number can occur by recombination.
                    The rate of discharge then reaches a steady maximum value which is not altered
                    by a large increase in voltage. This maximum current through the gas is called
                    the saturation current. The ions produced in gases by the rays from uranium and
                    other radioactive substances are in general identical with those produced by X
                    rays, and the mechanism of conductivity of the gas is very similar in both cases
                    (see Conduction, Electric: § <hi rend="italic">Through Gases</hi> ) <hi
                        rend="italic"> .</hi></p>
               <p>Some time after Becquerel’s discovery, Mme Curie (3) made a systematic
                    examination or the electric method of a large number of chemical elements and
                    their compounds to test whether they possessed the “ radioactive ” property of
                    uranium. Only one other element, thorium, was found to show this effect to a
                    degree comparable with that of uranium—a result inde-pendently observed by
                    Schmidt. Mme Curie examined the activity of the various compounds of uranium and
                    found that their radioactivity was an atomic property, <hi rend="italic">i. e.</hi> the activity was proportional to the amount of the element uranium
                    present, and was independent of its combination with other sub-stances. In
                    testing the activity of the minerals containing uranium, Mme Curie found that
                    the activity was always four to five times as great as that to be expected from
                    their content of uranium. If the radioactivity were an atomic phenomenon, this
                    could only be explained by the presence in these minerals of another substance
                    more active than uranium itself. Relying on this hypothesis, Mme Curie made a
                    chemical examination of uranium minerals in order to try to separate this new
                    radio-active substance. In these experiments, the Austrian Government generously
                    provided Mme Curie with a ton of the residues from the State manufactory of
                    uranium at Joachimstahl, Bohemia. At that place there are extensive deposits of
                    pitch-blende or uranite which are mined for the uranium. After separation of the
                    latter, the residues are three to five times as radioactive weight for weight as
                    the uranium. From this residue Mme Curie separated a substance far more
                    radio-active than uranium, which she called polonium in honour of the country of
                    her birth. This substance is usually separated with bismuth in the mineral, but
                    by special methods can be partly separated from it. A further examination
                    revealed the presence of a second radioactive substance which is normally
                    separated with the barium, to which the name “ radium ” was given. This name was
                    happily chosen, for in the pure state radium bromide has a very great
                    activity—about two million times as great as an equal weight of uranium. By
                    means of successive fractionations of the chloride, the radium was gradually
                    concentrated, until finally the radium was obtained so that the barium lines
                    showed very faintly. The atomic weight was found by Mme Curie to be 225. In a
                    recent redetermination, using a larger quantity of 0∙4 grams of pure radium
                    chloride, Mme Curie (4) found the atomic weight to be 226∙2. Thorpe (5) using a
                    smaller quantity obtained a value 227. The spectrum of the purified sample of
                    radium chloride obtained by Mme Curie was first examined by Demarçay. It was
                    found to have a characteristic spark spectrum of bright lines analogous in many
                    respects to the spectra of the alkaline earths. Giesel (6) found that pure
                    radium bromide gives a brilliant carmine colour to the bunsen flame. The flame
                    spectrum shows two broad bright bands in the orange-red. There is also a line in
                    the blue-green and two weak lines in the violet. Giesel (7) has taken an active
                    part in the preparation of pure radium compounds, and was the first to place
                    preparations of pure radium bromide on the market. He found that the separation
                    of radium from the barium mixed with it proceeded much more rapidly if the
                    crystallizations were carried out using thebromide instead of the chloride. He
                    states that six to eight crystallizations are sufficient for an almost complete
                    separation. From the chemical point of view radium possesses all the
                    characteristic properties of a new element. It has a definite atomic weight, a
                    well-marked and characteristic spectrum, and distinct chemical properties. Its
                    comparative ease of separation and great activity has attracted much attention
                    to this substance, although we shall see that very similar radioactive
                    properties are possessed by a large number of distinct substances.</p>
               <p>Radium emits three distinct types of radiation, known as the <hi rend="italic">α</hi> , <hi rend="italic">ß</hi> and γ rays, of which an account will be
                    given later. It produces in addition a radioactive emanation or gas which is
                    about 100,000 times as active weight for weight as radium itself. The emanation
                    released from 10 milligrams of pure radium bromide causes a glass tube into
                    which it is introduced to phosphoresce brightly. A brilliant luminosity is
                    produced in phosphorescent substances like zinc sulphide, willemite and barium
                    platino-cyanide when introduced into a tube containing the emanation. The radium
                    emanation, a more detailed account of which will be given later, has proved of
                    the greatest utility in radioactive experiments. The property of radium of
                    pro-ducing the emanation has been utilized as a very delicate and certain
                    method, not only of detection but of estimation of small quantities of radium.
                    This “ emanation method ” depends upon the introduction of the emanation,
                    liberated from a substance by boiling or heating, into a suitable electroscope.
                    The rate of discharge of the electroscope due to the emanation affords a
                    quantitative measure of the amount of radium present. In this way, it is not
                    difficult to determine with certainty the</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-22-r01-0795" facs="encyclopaediabri22chisrich_0820.jp2"/>
               <p>presence of radium in a body which contains only 10 <hi rend="sup">-11</hi> gram of radium. With care, 10 <hi rend="sup">-12</hi> gram can just be
                    detected. This emanation method has been employed with great success in
                    measuring the quantity of radium in minerals and in rocks. A very simple method
                    has been devised of determining the quantity of radium present when it is not
                    less than 1∕100 milligram. The tube containing the radium is placed some
                    distance from an electroscope which is surrounded by a lead screen about 3 mms.
                    thick. This cuts off the <hi rend="italic">α</hi> and <hi rend="italic">ß</hi> rays and the effect in the electroscope is then due to the penetrating 7
                    rays. By comparison of the rate of discharge with that of a standard preparation
                    of radium at the same distance, the quantity of radium can at once be deduced,
                    provided the radium is in equilibrium with its emanation. This is usually the
                    case if the radium preparation is one month old. This method is simple and
                    direct, and has the great advantage that the radium tube under test need not be
                    opened, nor its contents weighed. We shall sec later that the amount of radium
                    in an old mineral is always proportional to the amount of uranium present.
                    Rutherford and Boltwood (8) found that 3‧4 parts of radium by weight arc present
                    in ten million parts of uranium. Consequently an old mineral containing 1000
                    kilos of uranium should contain 340 milligrams of pure radium.</p>
               <p>In addition to radium and polonium, a number of other radioactive substances
                    have been found in uranium minerals. With the exception of the radium emanation,
                    none of these have yet been isolated in a pure state, although preparations of
                    some of them have been obtained comparable in activity with radium itself.
                    Debierne (9) found a radioactive substance which was separated from pitchblende
                    with the rare earths and had chemical properties similar to those of thorium.
                    This he called <hi rend="italic">actinium.</hi> Giesel (10) independently
                    noted the presence of a new radio-active substance which was usually separated
                    with lanthanum and cerium from the minerals. It possessed the property of giving
                    out a radioactive emanation or gas, the activity of which died away in a few
                    seconds. For this reason he called it the <hi rend="italic">emanating substance</hi> and afterwards <hi rend="italic">emanium.</hi> Later work has shown that
                    emanium is identical in chemical and radioactive properities with actinium, so
                    that the former name will be retained.</p>
               <p>We have already seen that Mme Curie gave the name polonium to a radioactive
                    substance separated with bismuth. Later Marckwald found that a very radioactive
                    substance was deposited from a solution of a radioactive mineral on a polished
                    bismuth plate. The active matter was found to be deposited in the bismuth with
                    tellurium, and he gave the name <hi rend="italic">radio-tellurium</hi> to this
                    substance. In later work, he showed that the new substance could be chemically
                    separated from tellurium. By treating the residues from 15 tons of Joachimsthal
                    pitch-blende, Marckwald (11) finally obtained 3 milligrams of intensely active
                    material—far more active weight for weight than radium. It has been definitely
                    settled that the active substance of Marckwald is identical with polonium. Both
                    substances give out a type of easily absorbed <hi rend="italic">a</hi> rays
                    and both lose their activity at the same rate. The activity of polonium decays
                    in a geo-metrical progression with the time and falls to half its initial value
                    in 140 days. This law of decay, as we shall see, is characteristic of all
                    radioactive products, although the period of decay is different in each case.</p>
               <p>Mme Curie and Debierne (12) have described further experiments with polonium.
                    The latter substance was extracted from several tons of pitchblende and purified
                    until 2 milligrams of material were obtained containing about 1/10 milligram of
                    pure polonium. From a knowledge of the relative periods of transformation of
                    radium and polonium, it can be calculated that the amount of polonium in a
                    radium mineral is 1/5000 of the amount of radium, while the activity of pure
                    polonium measured by the α rays should be 5000 times greater than that of
                    radium. As we have seen, polonium is rapidly transformed, and it is of great
                    interest to determine the nature of the substance into which polonium changes.
                    We shall see later that there is considerable evidence that polonium changes
                    into lead.</p>
               <p>Recently Boltwood (13) has separated another substance from uranium minerals
                    which he has called “ ionium. ” This substance is sometimes separated from the
                    mineral with actinium and has chemical properties very similar to those of
                    thorium. Preparations of ionium have been obtained several thousand times as
                    active as uranium. Ionium emits <hi rend="italic">α</hi> rays of short range
                    and has a period of transformation probably much longer than that of radium.
                    Ionium has a special interest inasmuch as it is the substance which changes
                    directly into radium. A preparation of ionium initially free from radium grows
                    radium at a rapid rate. Hofmann found that the lead separated from uranium
                    minerals and named it radiolead. The active con-stituent in the lead is radium
                    D, which changes into radium E and then into radium F (polonium). Both radium D
                    and radium F arc products of the transformation of radium. In addition to these
                    radioactive substances mentioned above, a large number of other radioactive
                    substances have been discovered. Most of these lose their activity in the course
                    of a few hours or days. The properties of these substances and their position in
                    the radioactive series will be discussed later.</p>
               <p><hi rend="italic">Radiations from Radioactive Substances. —</hi> All the
                    radioactive substances possess in common the property of emitting radiations
                    which darken a photographic plate and cause a discharge of electrified bodies.
                    Very active preparations of radium, actinium and polonium also possess the
                    property of causing strong phosphorescence in some substances. Bodies which
                    phosphoresce under X rays usually do so under the rays from radioactive matter.
                    Barium platinocyanide, the mineral willemite (zinc silicate) and zinc sulphide
                    are the best known examples.</p>
               <p>There are in general three types of radiation emitted by the radioactive bodies,
                    called the <hi rend="italic">α</hi> , <hi rend="italic">ß</hi> and 7 rays.
                    Ruther-ford (2) in 1899 showed that the radiation from uranium was complex and
                    consisted of <hi rend="italic">(a)</hi> an easily absorbed radiation stopped
                    by a sheet of paper or a few centimetres of air which he called the a rays and <hi rend="italic">(b)</hi> a far more penetrating radiation capable of
                    passing through several millimetres of aluminium, called the <hi rend="italic">ß</hi> rays. Later Villard found that radium emitted a very pene-trating
                    kind of radiation called the γ rays capable of passing before absorption through
                    twenty centimetres of iron and several centimetres of lead.</p>
               <p>Giesel and, later, Curie and Becquerel showed that the <hi rend="italic">ß</hi> rays of radium were deflected by a magnetic field. By the work of
                    Becquerel and Kaufmann the <hi rend="italic">ß</hi> rays have been shown to
                    consist of negatively charged particles projected with a velocity ap-proaching
                    that of light, and having the same small mass as the electrons set free in a
                    vacuum tube. In fact the <hi rend="italic">ß</hi> rays are electrons
                    spontaneously ejected from the radioactive matter at a speed on an average much
                    greater than that observed in the electrons set free in a vacuum tube.</p>
               <p>The very penetrating γ rays are not deflected in a magnetic or electric field
                    and are believed to be a type of radiation similar to X rays. The γ rays are
                    only observed in radioactive substances which emit <hi rend="italic">ß</hi> rays, and the penetrating power of the 7 rays appears to be connected with the
                    initial velocity of expulsion of the <hi rend="italic">ß</hi> rays. Two
                    general theories have been advanced to account for the properties of these rays.
                    On one view, the γ rays are to be regarded as electromagnetic pulses which have
                    their origin in the expulsion of the <hi rend="italic">ß</hi> particle from
                    the atom. On the other hand Bragg has collected evidence in support of the view
                    that the γ rays arc corpuscular and con-sist of uncharged particles or “ neutral
                    doublets. ” There is as yet no general consensus of opinion as to the true
                    nature of the γ rays.</p>
               <p>Rutherford (14) showed in 1903 that the <hi rend="italic">α</hi> rays were
                    deflected in a powerful magnetic or electric field. The amount of deflection is
                    very small compared with the <hi rend="italic">ß</hi> rays under similar
                    conditions. The direction of deflection in a magnetic field is opposite to that
                    of the <hi rend="italic">ß</hi> rays, showing that the <hi rend="italic">α</hi> rays consist of a stream of positively charged particles. A pencil of rays
                    from a thick layer of radioactive matter is complex and con-sists of particles
                    moving at varying velocities If, however,</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-22-r01-0796" facs="encyclopaediabri22chisrich_0821.jp2"/>
               <p>a thin film of radioactive matter of one kind is taken, the particles which
                    escape without absorption are found to be homo-geneous and consist of particles
                    projected at an identical speed. Observations of the velocity and mass of the
                    particle have been made by Rutherford. The general method employed for this
                    purpose is similar to that used for the determination of the velocity and mass
                    of the electron in a vacuum tube. The deflection of a pencil of rays in a vacuum
                    is determined for both a magnetic and electric field. From these observations
                    the velocity and value <hi rend="italic">e</hi> <hi rend="italic">∣</hi> <hi rend="italic">m</hi> (the ratio of the charge carried by the particle to
                    its mass) are determined. The value of <hi rend="italic">e</hi> / <hi
                        rend="italic"> m</hi> has been found to be the same for the particles from
                    all the types of radioactive matter that have been examined, indicating that the <hi rend="italic">α</hi> particles from all radioactive substances are
                    identical in mass. The value of <hi rend="italic">e</hi> / <hi rend="italic">m</hi> found for the <hi rend="italic">α</hi> particle is 5‧07 X 10 <hi
                        rend="sup"> 3</hi> . Now the value of <hi rend="italic">e</hi> / <hi
                        rend="italic"> m</hi> for the hydrogen atom set free in the electrolysis of
                    water is 9660. On the assumption that the value of the charge <hi rend="italic">e</hi> is the same for the <hi rend="italic">α</hi> particle as for the
                    hydrogen atom, the value would indicate that the <hi rend="italic">α</hi> particle has about twice the mass of the hydrogen atom, <hi rend="italic">i. e.</hi> has the same mass as the hydrogen molecule. If the charge on the <hi
                        rend="italic"> α</hi> particle is twice that on the hydrogen atom, the
                    value of <hi rend="italic">e</hi> / <hi rend="italic">m</hi> indicates that
                    the <hi rend="italic">α</hi> particle is a helium atom, for the latter has an
                    atomic weight of four times that of hydrogen. It was difficult at first to
                    decide between these and other hypotheses, but we shall show later that there is
                    now no doubt that the <hi rend="italic">α</hi> particle is in reality a helium
                    atom carrying two elementary charges. We may consequently regard the <hi
                        rend="italic"> α</hi> rays as a stream of helium atoms which are projected
                    from a radio-active substance with a high velocity. The maximum velocity of the <hi rend="italic">α</hi> particle from radium is 2×10 <hi rend="sup">9</hi> cms. per second, or one-fifteenth of the velocity of light. Although the <hi rend="italic">α</hi> rays are the least penetrating of the radiations,
                    it will be seen that they play an extremely important part in radioactive
                    phenomena. They are responsible for the greater part of the ionization and
                    heating effects of radioactive matter and are closely connected with the
                    transformations occurring in them.</p>
               <p>Under ordinary experimental conditions the greater part of the ionization
                    observed in a gas is due to the <hi rend="italic">α</hi> particles. This
                    ionization due to the <hi rend="italic">α</hi> rays does not extend in air at
                    atmospheric pressure for more than 7 cms. from radium, and 8∙6 cms. from
                    thorium. If a screen of aluminium about ‧01 cms. thick is placed over the active
                    material, the <hi rend="italic">α</hi> rays are completely absorbed, and the
                    ionization above the screen is then due to the <hi rend="italic">ß</hi> and <hi rend="italic">γ</hi> rays alone. If a layer of lead about 2 mms. thick
                    is placed over the active material, the <hi rend="italic">ß</hi> rays are
                    stopped, and the ionization is then due almost entirely to the penetrating γ
                    rays. By the use of screens of suitable thickness we are thus able to sift out
                    the various types of rays. These three types of radiations all set up secondary
                    radiations in passing through matter. A pencil of <hi rend="italic">ß</hi> rays falling on matter is widely scattered in all directions. This scattered
                    radiation is sometimes called the secondary <hi rend="italic">ß</hi> rays. The
                    7 rays give rise to secondary rays which consist in part of scattered 7 rays and
                    in part electrons moving with a high velocity. These secondary rays in turn
                    produce tertiary rays and so on. The impact of the <hi rend="italic">α</hi> rays on matter sets free a number of slow moving electrons which are very easily
                    deflected by a magnetic or electric field. This type of radiation was first
                    observed by J. J. Thomson, and has been called by him the δ rays.</p>
               <p><hi rend="italic">Emanations or Radioactive Gases. —</hi> In addition to their
                    power of emitting penetrating radiations, the substances thorium, actinium and
                    radium possess another very striking and im-portant property. Rutherford (15) in
                    1900 showed that thorium compounds (especially the oxide) continuously emitted a
                    radioactive emanation or gas. This emanation can be carried away by a current of
                    air and its properties tested apart from the substance which produces it. A
                    little later Dorn showed that radium possesses a similar property, while Giesel
                    and Debierne observed a similar effect with actinium. These emanations all
                    possess the property of ionizing a gas and, if sufficiently intense, of
                    producing marked photographic and phosphorescent action. The activity of the
                    radioactive gases is not permanent but disappears according to a definite law
                    with the time, viz. the activity falls off in a geometric progression with the
                    time. The emanations are distinguished by the different rates at which they lose
                    their activity. The emanation of actinium is very shortlived, the time for the
                    activity to fall to half value, <hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi> the period of the
                    emanation, being 3∙7 seconds. The period of the thorium emanation is 54 seconds
                    and of the radium emanation 3*9 days. This property of emitting an emanation is
                    shown in a very striking manner by actinium. A compound of actinium is wrapped
                    in a sheet of thin paper and laid on a screen of phosphorescent zinc sulphide.
                    In a dark room the phosphorescence, marked by the characteristic scintillation,
                    is seen to extend on all sides from the active body. A puff of air is seen to
                    remove the emanation and with it the greater part of the phosphorescence. Fresh
                    emanation immediately diffuses out and the experiment may be repeated
                    indefinitely. The emanations have all the properties of radioactive gases. They
                    can be transferred from point to point by currents of air. The emanations can be
                    separated from the air or other gas with which they are mixed by the action of
                    extreme cold. Rutherford and Soddy (16) showed that under ordinary conditions
                    the temperature of condensation of the radium emanation mixed was - 150 <hi
                        rend="sup"> 0</hi> C.</p>
               <p>The emanations are produced from the parent matter and escape into the air under
                    some conditions. Rutherford and Soddy (17) made a systematic examination of the
                    emanating power of thorium compounds under different conditions. The hydroxide
                    emanates most freely, while in thorium nitrate, practically none of the
                    emanation escapes into the air. Most of the compounds of actinium emanate very
                    freely. Radium compounds, except in very thin films, retain most of the
                    emanation in the compound. The occluded emanation can in all cases be released
                    by solution or by heating. On account of its very slow period of decay, the
                    emanation of radium can be collected like a gas and stored, when it retains its
                    characteristic properties for a month or more.</p>
               <p><hi rend="italic">Induced Activity. —</hi> Curie (18) showed that radium
                    possessed another remarkable property. The surface of any body placed near
                    radium, or still better, immersed in the emanation from it, acquires a new
                    property. The surface after removal is found to be strongly active. Like the
                    emanations, this induced activity in a body decays with the time, though at
                    quite a different rate from the emanation itself. Rutherford (19) independently
                    showed that thorium possessed a like property. He showed that the bodies made
                    active behaved as if a thin film of intensely active matter were deposited on
                    their surface. The active matter could be partly removed by rubbing, and could
                    be dissolved off by strong acids. When the acid was evaporated the active matter
                    remained behind. It was shown that induced activity was due to the emanations,
                    and could not be produced if no emanation was present. We shall see that induced
                    activity on bodies is due to a deposit of non-gaseous matter derived from the
                    transformation of the emanations. Each emanation gives a distinctive active
                    deposit which decays at different rates. The active deposits of radium, thorium
                    and actinium are very complex, and consist of several types of matter. Several
                    hours after removal from the emanation the active deposit from radium decays to
                    half-value—26 minutes, for actinium half-value—34 minutes, for thorium
                    half-value— 10∙5 hours. The active deposits obtained on a platinum wire or plate
                    are volatilized before a white heat, and are again de-posited on the cooler
                    bodies in the neighbourhood. Rutherford showed that the induced activity could
                    be concentrated on the negative electrode in a strong electric field, indicating
                    that the radioactive carriers had a positive charge. The distribution of the
                    active deposit in a gas at low pressure has been investigated in detail by
                    Makower and Russ.</p>
               <p><hi rend="italic">Theory of Radioactive Transformations. —</hi> We have seen
                    that the radioactive bodies spontaneously and continuously emit a great number
                    of <hi rend="italic">α</hi> and <hi rend="italic">ß</hi> particles. In
                    addition, new types of radioactive matter like the emanations and active
                    deposits</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-22-r01-0797" facs="encyclopaediabri22chisrich_0822.jp2"/>
               <p>appear, and these are quite distinct in chemical and physical properties from
                    the parent matter. The radiating power is an atomic property, for it is
                    unaffected by combination of the active element with inactive bodies, and is
                    uninfluenced by the most powerful chemical and physical agencies at our command.
                    In order to explain these results, Rutherford and Soddy (2o) in 1903 put forward
                    a simple but comprehensive theory. The atoms of radioactive matter are unstable,
                    and each second a definite fraction of the number of atoms present break up with
                    explosive violence, in most cases expelling an <hi rend="italic">a</hi> or <hi
                        rend="italic"> ß</hi> particle with great velocity. Taking as a simple
                    illustration that an <hi rend="italic">α</hi> particle is expelled during the
                    explosion, the resulting atom has decreased in mass and possesses chemical and
                    physical properties entirely distinct from the parent atom. A new type of matter
                    has thus appeared as a result of the transformation. The atoms of this new
                    matter are again unstable and break up in turn, the process of successive
                    disintegration of the atom continuing through a number of distinct stages. On
                    this view, a substance like the radium emanation is derived from the
                    transformation of radium. The atoms of the emanation are far more unstable than
                    the atoms of radium, and break up at a much quicker rate. We shall now consider
                    the law of radioactive transformation according to this theory. It is
                    experi-mentally observed that in all simple radioactive substances, the tensity
                    of the radiation decreases in a geometrical progression with the time, <hi
                        rend="italic"> i. e.</hi> I∕I <hi rend="sub">o</hi> = <hi rend="italic">e <hi rend="sup">-</hi></hi> <hi rend="sup">λt</hi> where I is the intensity of the radiation at any time <hi rend="italic">t,</hi> I <hi rend="sub">o</hi> the initial intensity,
                    and λ a constant. Now according to this theory, the intensity of the radiation
                    is proportional to the number of atoms breaking up per second. From this it
                    follows that the atoms of active matter present decrease in a geometrical
                    progression with the time, <hi rend="italic">i.</hi> <hi rend="italic">e.</hi> N∕N <hi rend="sub">o</hi> =e <hi rend="sup">-λt</hi> where N is the number of atoms present at a time <hi rend="italic">t</hi> , N <hi rend="sub">o</hi> the initial number, and λ the same constant as
                    before. Differentiating, we have <hi rend="italic">d</hi> N∕ <hi rend="italic"
                        > dt</hi> = -λN, <hi rend="italic">i.</hi> <hi rend="italic">e. λ</hi> represents the fraction of the total number of
                    atoms present which break up per second. The radioactive constant λ has a
                    definite and characteristic value for each type of matter. Since λ is usually a
                    very small fraction, it is convenient to distinguish the products by stating the
                    time required for half the matter to be transformed. This will be called the
                    period of the product, and is numerically equal to log <hi rend="italic"><hi rend="sub"> c</hi></hi> ∕λ. As far as our observation has gone, the law of radioactive change is
                    applicable to all radioactive matter without exception. It appears to be an
                    expression of the law of probability, for the average number breaking up per
                    second is proportional to the number present. Viewed from this point of view,
                    the number of atoms breaking up per second should have a certain average value,
                    but the number from second to second should vary within certain limits according
                    to the theory of probability. The theory of this effect was first put" forward
                    by Schweidler, and has since been verified by a number of experimenters,
                    including Kohl-rausch, Meyer, and Begener and H. Geiger. This variation in the
                    number of atoms breaking up from moment to moment becomes marked with weak
                    radioactive matter, where only a few atoms break up per second. The variations
                    observed are in good agreement with those to be expected from the theory of
                    probability. This effect does not in any way invalidate the law of radioactive
                    change. On an average the number of atoms of any simple kind of matter breaking
                    up per second is proportional to the number present. We shall now consider how
                    the amount of radioactive matter which is supplied at a constant rate from a
                    source varies with the time. For clear-ness, we shall take the case of the
                    production of emanation, by radium. The rate of transformation of radium is so
                    slow compared with that of the emanation that we may assume without sensible
                    error that the number of atoms of radium breaking up per second, <hi
                        rend="italic"> Le.</hi> the supply of fresh emanation, is on the average
                    constant over the interval required. Suppose that initially radium is completely
                    freed from emanation. In consequence of the steady supply, the amount of
                    emanation present increases, but not at a constant rate, for the emanation is in
                    turn breaking up. Let <hi rend="italic">q</hi> be the number of atoms of
                    emanation produced by the radium per second and N the number present after an
                    interval <hi rend="italic">t</hi> , then <hi rend="italic">dN</hi> <hi rend="italic">∣</hi> <hi rend="italic">dt=q-λ</hi> N where λ is the radioactive constant of the
                    emanation. It is obvious that a steady state will ultimately be reached when the
                    number of atoms of emanation supplied per second are on the average to the atoms
                    which break up per second. If N <hi rend="sub">o</hi> be the maximum number, <hi rend="italic">q</hi> =XN <hi rend="sub">o</hi> . Integrating the
                    above equation, it follows that N∕N <hi rend="sub">o</hi> =1-e" <hi rend="sup"
                        > λi</hi> . If a curve be plotted with N as ordinates and time as
                    abscissae, it is seen that the recovery curve is complementary to the decay
                    curve. The two curves for the radium emanation period, 3∙9 days, are shown in
                    fig. 1, the maximum ordinate being in each case 100.</p>
               <p>This process of production and disappearance of active* matter holds for all the
                    radioactive bodies. We shall now consider some special cases of the variation of
                    the amount of active matter with time which have proved of great importance in
                    the analysis of radioactive changes.</p>
               <p>(a) Suppose that initially the matter A is present, and this changes into B and
                    B into C, it is required to find the number of atoms P, Q and R of A, B and C
                    present at any subsequent time <hi rend="italic">t..</hi></p>
               <p>Let λ <hi rend="sub">1</hi> , λ <hi rend="sub">2</hi> , λ <hi rend="sub">3</hi> be the constants of transformation of A, B and C respectively. Suppose <hi
                        rend="italic"> n</hi> be the number of atoms of A initially present. From
                    the law of radioactive change it follows:</p>
               <p>P= <hi rend="italic">ne <hi rend="sup">-</hi></hi> <hi rend="sup">λ</hi> 1 <hi rend="italic"><hi rend="sup"> c</hi></hi></p>
               <p><hi rend="italic">d</hi> Q∕ <hi rend="italic">dt</hi> = λ <hi rend="sub">1</hi> P-λ <hi rend="sub">2</hi> Q.........(1)</p>
               <p><hi rend="italic">d</hi> R <hi rend="italic">∕dt=λ <hi rend="sub">2</hi></hi> Q <hi rend="italic">-</hi> λ <hi rend="sub">2</hi> R ......(2)</p>
               <p>Substituting the value of P in terms of <hi rend="italic">n</hi> in(1), dQ∕ <hi rend="italic">dt</hi> =λ <hi rend="sub">1</hi> <hi rend="italic">ne <hi rend="sup">-</hi></hi> <hi rend="sup">λ1t</hi> -λ <hi rend="sub">2</hi> Q; the solution of which is
                    of the form</p>
               <p>Q = n( <hi rend="italic">ae <hi rend="sup">-</hi></hi> <hi rend="sup">λ1</hi> '+ <hi rend="italic">be <hi rend="sup">-</hi></hi> <hi rend="sup">λ</hi> 2 <hi rend="sup">t</hi> ),</p>
               <p>where <hi rend="italic">a</hi> and <hi rend="italic">b</hi> are constants.
                    By substitution it is seen that <hi rend="italic">a</hi> = λι∕(λ <hi
                        rend="sub"> 2</hi> -λ <hi rend="sub">1</hi> ). Since Q=0 when <hi
                        rend="italic"> t</hi> =o, <hi rend="italic">b=</hi> — λ <hi rend="sub">1</hi> ∕(λ <hi rend="sub">2</hi> -λ <hi rend="sub">i</hi> )</p>
               <p>Thus Q= <hi rend="sub">ξ</hi> 2k. ( <hi rend="sub">e</hi> -⅜'-e-M')........(3)</p>
               <p>Similarly it can be shown that</p>
               <p>R = <hi rend="italic">n</hi> ( <hi rend="italic">ae</hi> <hi rend="sup">-λ1'</hi> + <hi rend="italic">be</hi> <hi rend="sup">-λ2'</hi> + <hi rend="italic">ce <hi rend="sup">-</hi></hi> <hi rend="sup">λ3'</hi> )......(4)</p>
               <p>λ <hi rend="sub">l</hi> λ <hi rend="sub">2</hi> , λ <hi rend="sub">l</hi> λ <hi rend="sub">2</hi> λ <hi rend="sub">l</hi> λ <hi rend="sub">2</hi></p>
               <p>where <hi rend="italic">a=</hi> ( <hi rend="sub">λl</hi> - <hi rend="sub">λj</hi> )( <hi rend="sub">λl</hi> - <hi rend="sub">λ4</hi> )∙ <hi
                        rend="italic"> b</hi> = (λ <hi rend="sub">2</hi> - λ <hi rend="sub">l</hi> ) (λ, - λ,? (λ <hi rend="sub">i</hi> -λ <hi rend="sub">l</hi> ) (λ <hi
                        rend="sub"> i</hi> -λ, )*</p>
               <p>It will be seen from (3), that the value of Q, initially zero, increases to a
                    maximum and then decays; finally, according to an exponential law, with the
                    period of the more slowly transformed product, whether A or B.</p>
               <p>( <hi rend="italic">b</hi> ) A primary source supplies the matter A at a
                    constant rate, and the process has continued so long that the amounts of the
                    products A, B, C have reached a steady limiting value. The primary source is
                    then suddenly removed. It is required to find the amounts of A, B and C
                    remaining at any subsequent time <hi rend="italic">t.</hi></p>
               <p>In this case of equilibrium, the number <hi rend="italic">n</hi> <hi rend="sub">o</hi> of particles of A supplied per second from the source is
                    equal to the number of particles which change into B per second, and also of B
                    into C. This requires the relation</p>
               <p><hi rend="italic">n</hi> <hi rend="sub">0</hi> =λ <hi rend="sub">1</hi> P <hi rend="sub">0</hi> =y <hi rend="sub">2</hi> Q <hi rend="sub">0</hi> =λ <hi rend="sub">2</hi> R <hi rend="sub">0</hi></p>
               <p>where P <hi rend="sub">o</hi> , Q <hi rend="sub">o</hi> , R <hi rend="sub">o</hi> are the initial number of particles of A, B, C present, and λ <hi
                        rend="sub"> 1</hi> , λ <hi rend="sub">2</hi> , λ <hi rend="sub">2</hi> are their constants of transformation.</p>
               <p>Using the same quotations as in case (1), but remembering the new initial
                    conditions, it can easily be shown that the number of particles P, Q and R of
                    the matter A, B and C existing at the time <hi rend="italic">t</hi> after
                    removal are given by</p>
               <p>P-⅞&lt;-w.</p>
               <p>Q-⅛, frl</p>
               <p>R=n <hi rend="sub">o</hi> (ae- <hi rend="sup">λ1t</hi> +be <hi rend="sup">-λ2t</hi> +ce <hi rend="sup">-λ3t</hi> ),</p>
               <p>_ <hi rend="underline">λ¾</hi> . _ <hi rend="underline">—λt</hi> __ <hi
                        rend="underline"> λ1λ3</hi></p>
               <p><hi rend="sup">where a</hi> = (λl — λj) (λi^ “ λl) ’ (λl <hi rend="sup">-</hi> λj)(×2 <hi rend="sup">-</hi> λj)* ×*(λl — λ j) (λj - λ&gt;)*</p>
               <p>The curves expressing the rate of variation of P, Q, R with time are in these
                    cases very different from case (l).</p>
               <p>(c) The matter A is supplied at a constant rate from a primary source. Required
                    to find the number of particles of A, B and C present at any time <hi
                        rend="italic"> t</hi> later, when initially A, B, and C were absent.</p>
               <p>This is a converse case from case (2) and the solutions can be obtained from
                    general considerations. Initially suppose A, B and C arc in equilibrium with the
                    primary source which supplied A at a constant rate. The source is then removed
                    and the amounts of A, B and C vary according to the equation given in case (2).
                    The source after removal continues to supply A at the same rate as before. Since
                    initially the product A was in equilibrium with the source, and the radioactive
                    processes are in no way changed by the removal of the source, it is clear that
                    the amount of A present in the two parts in which the matter is distributed is
                    unchanged. If P <hi rend="sub">1</hi> be the amount of A produced by the
                    source in the time <hi rend="italic">t</hi> , and P</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-22-r01-0798" facs="encyclopaediabri22chisrich_0823.jp2"/>
               <p>the amount remaining in the part removed, then P <hi rend="sub">1</hi> +P = P <hi rend="sub">o</hi> where P <hi rend="sub">o</hi> is the equilibrium
                    value. Thus</p>
               <p>P <hi rend="sub">1</hi> /P <hi rend="sub">o</hi> = I —P <hi rend="sub">1</hi> ∕P <hi rend="sub">o</hi> .</p>
               <p>The ratio P∕P <hi rend="sub">o</hi> can be written down from the solution
                    given in case (2). Similarly the corresponding values of Q <hi rend="sub">1</hi> ∕Q <hi rend="sub">0</hi> , R <hi rend="sub">1</hi> ∕R <hi rend="sub">0</hi> may be at once derived. It is obvious in these cases that the curve
                    plotted with P∕P <hi rend="sub">o</hi> as ordinates and time as abscissae is
                    complementary to the corresponding curve with P <hi rend="sub">1</hi> /P <hi
                        rend="sub"> o</hi> as ordinates. This simple relation holds for all
                    recovery and decay curves of radioactive products in general.</p>
               <p>We have so far considered the variation in the number of atoms of successive
                    products with time when the periods of the products are known. In practice, the
                    variation of the number of atoms is deduced from measurements of activity,
                    usually made by the electric method. Using the same notation as before, the
                    activity of any product is proportional to its rate of breaking up, <hi
                        rend="italic"> i. e.</hi> to λ <hi rend="sub">l</hi> P where P is the
                    number of atoms present. If two products are present, the activity is the sum of
                    two corresponding terms λ <hi rend="sub">l</hi> P and λ <hi rend="sub">2</hi> Q. In practice, however, no two products emit α or <hi rend="italic">ß</hi> particles, with the same velocity. The difference in ionizing power of a
                    single α particle from the two products has thus to be taken into account. If,
                    under the experimental conditions, the ionization produced by an α particle from
                    the second product is K times that from the first product, the activity observed
                    is proportional to λ <hi rend="sub">l</hi> P+Kλ2Q. In this way, it is possible
                    to compare the theoretical activity curves of a mixture of products with those
                    deduced experimentally.</p>
               <p><hi rend="italic">Analysis of Radioactive Changes. —</hi> The analysis of the
                    sucessive changes occurring in uranium, thorium, radium and actinium has proved
                    a very difficult matter. In order to establish the existence of a new product
                    and to fix its position in the scheme of changes, it is necessary to show ( <hi
                        rend="italic"> a</hi> ) that the new product has a distinctive period of
                    decay and shows some distinctive physical or chemical properties; ( <hi
                        rend="italic"> b</hi> ) that the product under consideration arises
                    directly from the product preceding it in the scheme of changes, and is
                    transformed into the product succeeding it.</p>
               <p>In general, it has been found that each product shows some distinctive chemical
                    or physical behaviour which allows of its partial or complete separation from a
                    mixture of other products. It must be remembered that in most cases the amount
                    of radioactive matter under examination is too small to detect by weight, but
                    its presence is inferred from its characteristic radiations and rate of change.
                    In some cases, a separation may be effected by ordinary chemical methods; for
                    example thorium X is separated from thorium by precipitation of thorium with
                    ammonia. The Th X remains in the filtrate and is practically free from thorium.
                    In other cases, a separation is effected by a separation of a metal in the
                    solution of active matter. For example, polonium (radium F) always comes down
                    with bismuth and may be separated by placing a bismuth plate in a solution.
                    Radium C is separated from radium B by adding nickel filings to a solution of
                    the two. Radium C is deposited on the nickel. In other cases, a partial
                    separation may be effected by electrolysis or by differences in volatility when
                    heated. For example, when radium A, B and C are deposited on a platinum plate,
                    on heating the plate, radium B is volatilized and is deposited on any cold
                    surface in the neighbourhood. A very striking method of separating certain
                    products has been recently observed depend-ing upon the recoil of an atom which
                    breaks up with the expulsion' of an α particle. The residual atom acquires
                    sufficient velocity in consequence of the ejection of an α particle to escape
                    and be deposited on bodies in the neighbourhood. This is especially marked in a
                    low vacuum. This property was independently investigated by Russ and Makower
                    (21) and by Hahn (22). The latter has shown that by means of the recoil,
                    actinium C may be obtained pure from the active deposit containing actinium A, B
                    and C, for B emits α rays, and actinium C is driven from the plate by the
                    recoil. In a similar way a new product, thorium D, has been isolated. By the
                    recoil method, radium B may be separated from radium A and C. The recoil method
                    is one of the most definite and certain methods of settling whether an α ray
                    product is simple or complex.</p>
               <p>While in the majority of cases the products break up either with the emission of
                    α or <hi rend="italic">ß</hi> particles, some products have been observed
                    which do not emit any characteristic radiation and have been called “ rayless
                    products. ” For example, radium D and thorium A are changing substances which
                    break up without emitting either penetrating α or <hi rend="italic">ß</hi> rays. They appear to emit slow δ rays which can only be detected by special
                    methods. The presence and properties of a fayless product can be easily inferred
                    if it is transformed into a product emitting a radiation, for the variation in
                    activity of the latter affords a method of determining the amount of the parent
                    product present. The distinction between a “ ray ” and a “ rayless ” product is
                    not clear. It may be that the atom of a rayless product undergoes a
                    re-arrangement of its constituent parts giving rise to an atom of the same mass
                    but of different properties. In the case of an α ray or <hi rend="italic">ß</hi> ray product, the expulsion of an α or <hi rend="italic">ß</hi> particle
                    affords an obvious explanation of the appearance of a new product with
                    distinctive physical properties.</p>
               <p>In the table a list of the known products of transformation is given. In each
                    case, the half period of transformation is given and the type of radiation
                    emitted. If the product emits α rays, the range of ionization of the α particle
                    in air is given.</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="4" rows="1">
                           <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Table of Radioactive Products</hi></p>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>Product.</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>Half Period of</p>
                           <p>Transforma-</p>
                           <p>tîon.</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>Rays.</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>Range of Rays in Air in</p>
                           <p>Cms.</p>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>URANIUM—</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>5×10 <hi rend="sup">9</hi> years</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>α</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>3‧5</p>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>Uranium X</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>22 days</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p><hi rend="italic">β</hi> +γ</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>Ionium.</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>?</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>α</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>2∙8</p>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>RADIUM —</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>1760 years</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>α</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>3‧5</p>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>Ra Emanation.</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>3·86 days</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>α</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>4‧33</p>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>Radium A</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>3 mins.</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>α</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>4‧83</p>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>Radium B</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>26 mins.</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>slow <hi rend="italic">ß</hi></p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>Radium C</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>19 mins.</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>a+β+γ</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>7∙06</p>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>Radium D</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>17 years</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>slow β</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>Radium E</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>5 days</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p><hi rend="italic">ß</hi></p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>Radium F</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>140 days</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>α</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>3‧86</p>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>Radium G = lead?</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>THORIUM—</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>about 10 <hi rend="sup">10</hi> yrs.</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>3∙5</p>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>(Th. I)</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>5‧5 years</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>rayless</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>Mesothorium (Th. 2)</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>6∙2 hours</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p><hi rend="italic">ß+γ</hi></p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>Radiothorium.</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>737 days</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>α</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>3∙9</p>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>Thorium X</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>3∙6 days</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>α</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>5∙7</p>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>Th Emanation</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>54 secs</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>α</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>5‧5</p>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>Thorium A</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>10∙6 hours</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>slow <hi rend="italic">ß</hi></p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>Thorium B</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>55 mins.</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>α</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>5‧0</p>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>Thorium C</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>very short?</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>α</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>8‧6</p>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>Thorium D</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>3 mins.</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p><hi rend="italic">β+γ</hi></p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Actinium—</hi></p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>?</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>rayless</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>Radioactinium.</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>19‧5 days</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>α+ <hi rend="italic">β</hi></p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>4‧8</p>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>Actinium X</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>11 ∙8 days</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>α</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>6‧55</p>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>Act Emanation</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>3‧7 secs.</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>α</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>5∙8</p>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>Actinium A</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>36 mins.</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>slow <hi rend="italic">ß</hi></p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>Actinium B</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>2‧15 mins.</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>α</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>5∙5o</p>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>Actinium C</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>5·1 mins.</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p><hi rend="italic">ß+y</hi></p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                </table>
               <p>In each of the groups under the heading uranium, thorium and actinium, each
                    product is derived from the direct transformation of the product above it.</p>
               <p><hi rend="italic">Products of Radium. —</hi> Radium is transformed directly
                    into the emanation which in turn goes through a rapid series of trans-formations
                    called radium A, B and C. The complete analysis of these changes has involved a
                    large amount of work. The emanation changes first into radium A, a substance of
                    period 3 minutes emitting only α rays. Radium A changes into radium B, a product
                    of period 26 minutes emitting <hi rend="italic">ß</hi> rays of penetrating
                    power small compared with those emitted from the next product radium C. The
                    product radium C has proved of considerable importance, for it not only emits
                    very penetrating α rays and <hi rend="italic">ß</hi> rays, but is the origin
                    of the 7 rays arising from radium in equilibrium. When a wire charged negatively
                    has been exposed for some time in the presence of the radium emanation, it
                    becomes coated with an invisible film of radium A, B and C. After</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-22-r01-0799" facs="encyclopaediabri22chisrich_0824.jp2"/>
               <p>removal from the emanation for 20 minutes, radium A has practically disappeared
                    and the α rays arise entirely from radium C. Radium C has proved very valuable
                    in radioactive measurements as providing an intense source of homogeneous α
                    rays. Twenty-four hours after removal, the activity due to radium B and C has
                    become exceedingly small. The wire, however, still shows a very small residual
                    activity, first noted by Mme Curie. This residual activity measured by the α
                    rays rapidly increases with the time and reaches a maximum in about three years.
                    The active deposit of slow change has been examined in detail by Rutherford (23)
                    and by Meyer and Schweidler (24). It has been shown to consist of three
                    successive products called radium D, E and F. Radium D is a rayless substance of
                    slow period of transformation. Its period has been calculated by Rutherford to
                    be about 40 years, and by Meyer and Schweidler about 12 years. Antonoff (25)
                    fixes the period of about 17 years. Radium D changes into E, a <hi rend="italic"
                        > ß</hi> ray product of period about 5 days, and E into F, an α ray product
                    of period 140 days. It was at first thought that radium E was complex, but no
                    evidence of this has been observed by Antonoff. The product radium F is of
                    special interest, for it is identical with polonium—the first active body
                    separated by Mme Curie. In a similar way it has been shown that radium D is the
                    primary source of the activity observed in lead or “ radiolead ” separated by
                    Hofmann. It is interesting to note what valuable results have been obtained from
                    an examination of the minute residual activity observed on bodies exposed in the
                    presence of the radium emanation.</p>
               <p><hi rend="italic">Radium Emanation. —</hi> The radium emanation is to be
                    regarded as a typical radioactive product or transition element which exists in
                    a gaseous form. It is produced from radium at a constant rate, and is
                    transformed into radium A and helium. Its half-period of transformation is 3·86
                    days. The emanation from radium has been purified by condensing it in liquid
                    air, and pumping out the residual gases. The volume (26) of the emanation at
                    normal pressure and temperature to be derived from one gram of radium in
                    equilibrium is about o∙6 cubic milli-mctrcs. This small quantity of gas contains
                    initially more than three-quarters of the total activity of the radium before
                    its separation. In a pure state, the emanation is 100, 000 times as active
                    weight for weight as pure radium. Pure emanation in a spectrum tube gives a
                    characteristic spectrum of bright lines (27). The discharge in the gas is bluish
                    in colour. With continued sparking, the emanation is driven into the walls of
                    the tube and the electrodes. Notwithstanding the minute volume of emanation
                    available, the boiling-point of the emana-tion has been determined at various
                    pressures. At atmo-spheric pressure Rutherford (28) found the boiling-point to
                    be — 67° C., and Gray and Ramsay (29) 71° C. Liquid emanation appears colourless
                    when first condensed; when the temperature is lowered, the liquid emanation
                    freezes, and at the temperature of liquid air glows with a bright rose colour.
                    The density of liquid emanation has been estimated at 5 or 6.</p>
               <p>Approximate estimates of the molecular weight of the radium emanation were early
                    made by diffusion methods. The molecular weight in most cases came out about
                    100. In a comparison by Perkins of the rate of diffusion of the emanation with
                    that of a monatomic vapour of high molecular weight, viz. mercury, the value
                    deduced was 234. Since the radium atom in breaking up gives rise to one atom of
                    the emanation and one atom of helium, its atomic weight should be 226—4=222. The
                    emanation appears to have no definite chemical properties, and in this respect
                    belongs to the group of inert monatomic gases of which helium and argon are the
                    best known examples. It is partially soluble in water, and readily absorbed by
                    charcoal.</p>
               <p><hi rend="italic">Thorium.</hi> —The first product observed in thorium was the
                    emanation. This gives rise to the active deposit which has been analysed by
                    Rutherford, Miss Brooks and by Hahn, and shown to consist of probably four
                    products—thorium A, B, C and D. Thorium A is a rayless product of period 10‧5
                    hours; thorium B an α ray product of period about one hour. The presence of
                    thorium C has been inferred from the two types of α rays present in the active
                    deposit, but no chemical separation of B and C has yet been found possible. Hahn
                    has shown that thorium D—a <hi rend="italic">ß</hi> ray product of period 3
                    minutes—can easily be separated by the recoil method. A special interest
                    attaches to the product thorium X (30), which was first separated by Rutherford
                    and Soddy, since experiments with this substance laid the foundation of the
                    general theory of radioactive trans-formations. A close analysis of thorium has
                    led to the separation of a number of new products. Hahn (31) found that a very
                    active substance emitting α rays, which gave rise to thorium X, could be
                    separated from thorium minerals. This active substance, called <hi rend="italic"
                        > radiothorium,</hi> has been closely examined by Hahn and Blanc. Its
                    period of decay was found by Hahn to be about 2 years, and by Blanc to be 737
                    days. From an examination of the activity of commercial thorium nitrate of
                    different ages, Hahn showed that another product must be present, which he
                    called <hi rend="italic">mesothorium.</hi> This is separated from thorium with
                    Th X by precipitation with ammonia. Thorium is first transformed into the
                    rayless product mesothorium, of period about 5 years. This gives rise to a <hi
                        rend="italic"> ß</hi> ray product of quick transformation, which in turn
                    changes into <hi rend="italic">radiothorium.</hi> This changes into thorium X,
                    and so on through a long series of changes. When isolated in the pure state,
                    radiothorium would have an activity about a thousand times greater than radium,
                    but would lose its activity with time with a period of about 2 years.
                    Mesothorium, when first separated, would be inactive, but in consequence of the
                    production of radiothorium, its activity would rapidly increase for several
                    years. After reaching a maximum, it would finally decay with a period of five
                    years. Since a large amount of thorium is separated annually from thorium
                    minerals, it would be of great importance at the same time to separate the
                    radiothorium and mesothorium present. For many purposes active preparations of
                    these substances would be as valuable as radium itself, and the amount of active
                    matter from this source would be greater than that at present available from the
                    separation of radium from uranium minerals.</p>
               <p><hi rend="italic">Actinium. —</hi> The transformations observed in actinium
                    are very analogous to those in thorium. Actinium itself is a rayless product
                    which changes into radioactinium, an α ray product of period 19‧5 days, first
                    separated by Hahn (32). This changes into actinium X, of period 10∙2 days, first
                    separated by Godlewski (33). Actinium X is transformed into the emanation which
                    in turn gives rise to three further products, called actinium A, B and C.
                    Although very active preparations of actinium have been prepared, it has so far
                    not been found possible to separate the actinium from the rare earths with which
                    it is mixed. We do not in consequence know its atomic weight or spectrum.</p>
               <p><hi rend="italic">Origin of Radium.</hi> —According to the transformation
                    theory, radium, like all other radioactive products, must be regarded as a
                    changing element. Preliminary calculations showed that radium must have a period
                    of transformation of several thousand years. Consequently in order that any
                    radium could exist in old minerals, the supply must be kept up by the
                    transformation of some other substance. Since radium is always found asso-ciated
                    with uranium minerals, it seemed probable from the beginning that uranium must
                    be the primary element from which radium is derived. If this were the case, in
                    old minerals which have not been altered by the action of percolating waters,
                    the ratio of the amount of radium to uranium in a mineral must be a constant.
                    This must evidently be the case, for in a state of equilibrium the rate of
                    breaking up of radium must equal the rate of supply of radium from uranium. If
                    P, Q be the number of atoms of uranium and radium respectively in equilibrium,
                    and λ <hi rend="sub">l</hi> , λ <hi rend="sub">2</hi> their constants of
                    change, then</p>
               <p>λ2Q=λ <hi rend="sub">l</hi> P or Q/P =λ <hi rend="sub">1</hi> ∕λ <hi
                        rend="sub"> 2</hi> =T <hi rend="sub">2</hi> ∕T <hi rend="sub">1</hi> .</p>
               <p>where T <hi rend="sub">2</hi> and T <hi rend="sub">1</hi> are the
                    half-periods of transformation of uranium and radium respectively. The work of
                    Boltwood (34), Strutt (35) and McCoy (36) has conclusively shown that the ratio
                    of radium to uranium in old minerals is a constant. Boltwood and Strutt
                    determined the quantity of radium present in a mineral by the emanation method,
                    and the amount of uranium by analysis.</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-22-r01-0800" facs="encyclopaediabri22chisrich_0825.jp2"/>
               <p>In order, however, to obtain a direct proof of the genetic relation between
                    uranium and radium, it is necessary to show that radium appears after some time
                    in a uranium compound from which all trace of radium has been initially removed.
                    It can readily be calculated that the growth of radium should be easily observed
                    by the emanation method in the course of one week, using a kilogram of uranium
                    nitrate.. Experiments of this kind were first made by Soddy (37), but initially
                    no definite evidence was obtained that radium grew in the solution at all. The
                    rate of production of radium, if it took place at all, was certainly less than
                    1/10, 000th part of the amount to be expected if uranium were transformed
                    directly into radium. It thus appeared probable that one or more products of
                    slow period of trans-formation existed between uranium and radium. Since uranium
                    must be transformed through these intermediate stages before radium appears, it
                    is evident that the initial rate of production of radium under these conditions
                    might be extremely small. This conclusion has been confirmed by Soddy, who has
                    shown that radium does appear in the solution which has been placed aside for
                    several years.</p>
               <p>Since the direct parent of radium must be present in radio-active minerals, one
                    of the constituents separated from the mineral must grow radium. This was shown
                    to be the case by Boltwood (38), who found that actinium preparations produced
                    radium at a fairly rapid rate. By the work of Rutherford and Boltwood, it was
                    found that the growth of radium was not due to actinium itself, but to a new
                    substance separated in some cases with the actinium. This new substance, which
                    emits α rays, was separated by Boltwood (38), and called by him “ Ionium. ” It
                    has chemical properties very similar to thorium. Soddy has shown that the period
                    of ionium is probably not less than 20, 000 years, indicating that ionium must
                    exist in uranium minerals in not less than ten times the quantity of radium. It
                    has not yet been directly shown that uranium produces ionium, but there can be
                    no doubt that it does do so. Since ionium produces radium, Boltwood (38) has
                    determined by direct experiment that radium is half transformed in 2000 years—a
                    number in good agreement with other data on that subject. The constant relation
                    between uranium and radium will only hold for old minerals where there has been
                    no opportunity for chemical alteration or removal of its constituents by the
                    action of percolating water or other agencies. It is quite possible that altered
                    minerals of no great age will not show this constant relation. It seems probable
                    that this is the explanation of some results of Mlle Gleditsch, where the
                    relation between uranium and radium has been found not to be constant for some
                    mineral specimens.</p>
               <p><hi rend="italic">Connexion of the Radioelements. —</hi> We have already seen
                    that a number of slowly transforming radioactive substances, viz. polonium
                    (radium F), radiolead (radium D) and ionium are linked up to the uranium-radium
                    series of transformations. Boltwood (39) has made a systematic examination of
                    the relative activity in the form of very thin films due to each of the products
                    present in the uranium-radium family. The results are shown in the following
                    table, where the activity of pure uranium itself is taken as unity: —</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>Uranium</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>• 1∙00</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>Radium B.</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>0·04(? )</p>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>Ionium</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>• 0∙34</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>Radium C.</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>0∙91</p>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>Radium.</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>• 0∙45</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>Radium F.</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>0∙46</p>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>Emanation</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>. 0∙62</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>Actinium and its</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>Radium A</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>• 0∙54</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>products.</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>0∙28</p>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="4" rows="1">
                           <p>Total activity mineral, 4∙64 times uranium.</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                </table>
               <p>Taking into account the differences in the ionization due to an α particle from
                    the various products, the results indicate that uranium expels two α particles
                    for one from each of the other α ray products in the series of transformations.
                    This indicates either that two particles are expelled during the transformation
                    of the atom of uranium, or that another α ray product is present which has so
                    far not been separated from the uranium.</p>
               <p>Although thorium is nearly always present in old uranium minerals and uranium in
                    thorium minerals, there does not appear to be any radioactive connexion between
                    these two elements. Uranium and thorium are to he regarded as two distinct
                    radioactive elements. With regard to actinium, there is still no definite
                    information of its place in the scheme of transformations. Boltwood has shown
                    that the amount of actinium in uranium minerals is proportional to the content
                    of uranium. This indicates that actinium, like radium, is in genetic connexion
                    with uranium. On the other hand, the activity of actinium with its series of α
                    ray products is less than that of radium itself or uranium. In order to explain
                    this anomaly, Rutherford has suggested that at a certain stage of disintegration
                    of the uranium-radium series, the disintegration is complex, and two distinct
                    kinds of matter appear, one in much larger quantity than the other. On this
                    view, the smaller fraction is actinium, so that the latter is a branch
                    descendant of the main uranium-radium series.</p>
               <p><hi rend="italic">End Products of Transformation. —</hi> It is now definitely
                    established that the α particle expelled from any type of radioactive matter is
                    an atom of helium, so that helium is a necessary accom-paniment of radioactive
                    changes involving the expulsion of α particles. - After the radioactive
                    transformations have come to an end, each of the elements uranium and thorium
                    and actinium should give rise to an end or final product, which may be either a
                    known element or some unknown element of very slow period of transformation.
                    Supposing, as seems probable, that the expulsion of an α particle lowers the
                    atomic weight of an element by four units—the atomic weight of helium—the atomic
                    weights of each of the products in the uranium and radium series can be simply
                    calculated. Since uranium expels two α particles, the atomic weight of the next
                    ray product, ionium, is 238‧5-8 or 230‧5. The atomic weight of radium comes out
                    to be 266‧5, a number in good agreement with the experimental value. Similarly
                    the atomic weight of polonium is 210‧5, and that of the final product after the
                    trans-formation of polonium should be 206‧5. This value is very close to the
                    atomic weight of lead, and indicates that this sub-stance is the final product
                    of the transformation of radium.</p>
               <p>This suggestion was first put forward by Boltwood (40), who has collected a
                    large amount of evidence bearing on this subject. Since in old minerals the
                    transformations have been in progress for periods of time, in some cases
                    measured by hundreds of millions of years, it is obvious that the end product,
                    if a stable element, should be an invariable companion of the radioelement and
                    be present in considerable quantity. Boltwood has shown that lead always occurs
                    in radioactive minerals, and in many cases in amount about that to be expected
                    from their uranium content and age. It is difficult to settle definitely this
                    very important problem until it can be experimentally shown that radium is
                    transformed into lead, or, what should prove simpler in practice, that polonium
                    changes into helium and lead. Unfortunately for a solution of this problem
                    within a reasonable time, a very large quantity of polonium would be necessary.
                    Mme. Curie and Debierne have obtained a very active pre-paration of polonium
                    containing about ⅒th milligram of pure polonium. Rutherford and Boltwood and
                    Curie and Debierne have both independently shown that polonium produces helium
                    —a result to be expected, since it emits α particles.</p>
               <p><hi rend="italic">Production of Helium. —</hi> In 1902 Rutherford and Soddy
                    sug-gested that the helium which is invariably found in radioactive minerals was
                    derived from the disintegration of radioactive matter. In 1903 Ramsay and Soddy
                    definitely showed that helium was produced by radium and also by its emanation.
                    From the observed mass of the α particle, it seemed probable from the first that
                    the a particle was an atom of helium. This conclusion was confirmed by the work
                    of Rutherford and Geiger (41), who showed that the α particle was an atom of
                    helium carrying two unit charges of electricity. In order to prove definitely
                    this relation, it was necessary to show that the α particles, quite
                    independently of the active matter from which they were expelled, gave rise to
                    helium. This was done by Rutherford and Royds (42), who allowed the α particles
                    from a large quantity of emanation to be fired through the</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-22-r01-0801" facs="encyclopaediabri22chisrich_0826.jp2"/>
               <p>very thin glass walls of the containing tube. The collected particle gave the
                    spectrum of helium, showing, without doubt, that the α particle must be a helium
                    atom.</p>
               <p>Since the α particle is an atom of helium, all radioactive matter which expels <hi rend="italic">a</hi> particles must give rise to helium. In agreement
                    with this, Debiernc and Giesel have shown that actinium as well as radium
                    produces helium. Observations of the production of helium by radium have been
                    made by Ramsay and Soddy, Curie and Dewar, Himstedt and others. The rate of
                    production of helium per gram of radium was first definitely measured by Dewar
                    (43). His preliminary measurements gave a value of 134 cubic mms. of helium per
                    year per gram of radium and its products. Later observations extending over a
                    larger interval give a rate of production about 168 cubic mms. per year. As a
                    result of preliminary measurements, Boltwood and Rutherford (44) have found a
                    growth of 163 cubic mms. per year. It is of interest to note that the rate of
                    production of helium by radium is in excellent agreement with the value
                    calculated theoretically. From their work of counting the particles and
                    measuring their charge, Rutherford and Geiger showed that the rate of production
                    of helium should be 158 cubic mms. per year.</p>
               <p><hi rend="italic">Properties of the α Rays.</hi> —We have seen that the rays
                    are positively charged atoms of helium projected at a high velocity, which are
                    capable of penetrating through thin metal sheets and several centimetres of air.
                    Early observations indicated that the ionization due to a layer of radioactive
                    matter decreased approximately according to an exponential law with the
                    thick-ness of the absorbing matter placed over the active matter. The true
                    nature of the absorption of the α rays was first shown by Bragg and by Bragg and
                    Kleeman (45). The active particles projected from a thin film of active matter
                    of one kind have identical velocities, and are able to ionize the air for a
                    definite distance, termed the “ range ” of the α particle. It was found that the
                    ionization per centimetre of path due to a narrow pencil of α rays increases
                    with the distance from the active matter, at first slowly, then more rapidly,
                    near the end of the range. After passing through a maximum value the ionization
                    falls off rapidly to zero. The range of an α particle in air has a definite
                    value which can be accurately measured. If a uniform screen of matter is placed
                    in the path of the pencil of rays the range is reduced by a definite amount
                    proportional to the thickness of the screen. All the α particles have their
                    velocity reduced by the same amount in their passage through the screen. The
                    ranges in air of the α rays from the various products of the radioelements have
                    been measured. The ranges for the different products vary between 2‧8 cms. and
                    8∙6 cms.</p>
               <p>Bragg has shown that the range of an α particle in different elements is nearly
                    proportional to the square roots of their atomic weights. Using the photographic
                    method, Rutherford (46) showed that the velocity V of an α particle of range R
                    cms. in air is given by V <hi rend="sup">2</hi> = K(R + I∙25), where K is a
                    constant. In his experiments he was unable to detect particles which had a
                    velocity lower than 8∙8×10 <hi rend="sup">8</hi> cms. per second. Geiger (47),
                    using the scintillation method, has recently found that α particles of still
                    lower velocity can be detected under suitable conditions by the scintillations
                    produced on a zinc sulphide screen. He has found that the connexion between
                    velocity and range can be closely expressed by V <hi rend="sup">3</hi> =KR,
                    where K is a constant.</p>
               <p>On account of the great energy of motion of the α particle, it was at first
                    thought that it pursued a rectilinear path in the gas without appreciable
                    deflection due to its encounters with the molecules. Geiger (48) has, however,
                    shown by the scintillation method that the α particles are scattered to a marked
                    extent in passing through matter. The scattering increases with the atomic
                    weight of the substance traversed, and becomes more marked with decreasing
                    velocity of the α particle. A small fraction of the α particles falling on a
                    thick screen are deflected through more than a right angle, and emerge again on
                    the side of incidence.</p>
               <p>Rutherford and Geiger (49) have devised an electrical method of counting the α
                    particles expelled from radioactive matter. The α particle enters through a
                    small opening into a metal tube containing a gas at a reduced pressure. The
                    ionization produced by the α particle in its passage through the gas is
                    magnified several thousand times by the movement of the ions in a strong
                    electric field. In this way, the entrance of an α particle into the detecting
                    vessel is shown by a sudden and large deflection of the measuring instrument. By
                    this method, they determined that 3∙4 × 10 <hi rend="sup">l0</hi> α particles
                    are ejected per second from one gram of radium itseíf and from each of its α ray
                    products in equilibrium with it. By measuring the charge on a counted number of
                    α particles, it was found that the α particle carries a positive charge of 9∙3 ×
                    10 <hi rend="sup">-l0</hi> electrostatic units. From other evidence, it is
                    known that this must be twice the fundamental unit of charge carried by the
                    hydrogen atom. It follows that this unit charge is 4∙65 × 10 <hi rend="sup">-10</hi> units. This value is in good agreement with numerous recent
                    detcr-minations of this fundamental quantity by other methods. With this data,
                    it is possible to calculate directly the values of some important radioactive
                    data. The calculated and observed values are given below: —</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="2" rows="1">
                           <p>Calculated.</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>Observed.</p>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>Volume of the emanation in cubic milli-metres per gram of radium
                           </p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>•585</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>•6</p>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>Volume of helium in cubic millimetres produced per year per gram of
                                radium.</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>•58</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>169</p>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>Heating effect of radium per gram per hour in gram calories.....
                           </p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>113</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>118</p>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>Half-period of transformation of radium in year ......</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>1760</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>2000</p>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
               <p>The calculated values are in all cases in good agreement with the experimental
                    numbers.</p>
               <p>It is well known from the experiments of Sir William Crookes (50) that the α
                    rays produce visible scintillations when they fall on a screen of phosphorescent
                    zinc sulphide. This is shown in the instrument called the spinthariscope. By
                    means of a suitable microscope, the number of these scintillations on a given
                    area in a given time can be counted. The number so obtained is practically
                    identical with the number of α particles incident on the screen, determined by
                    the electrical method of counting. This shows that each α particle produces a
                    visible flash of light when it falls on a suitable zinc sulphide screen. The
                    scintillations produced by α rays are observed in certain diamonds, and their
                    number has been counted by Regener (51) and the charge on each particle has been
                    deduced. The latter was the first to employ the scintillation method for actual
                    counting of α particles. Kinoshita has shown that the number of α particles can
                    also be counted by the photographic method, and that each particle must produce
                    a detectable effect.</p>
               <p><hi rend="italic">Absorption of ß Rays.</hi> —We have seen that the <hi
                        rend="italic"> β</hi> particles, which arc emitted from a number of
                    radioactive products, carry a negative charge and have the same small mass as
                    the particles constituting the cathode rays. The velocity of expulsion and
                    penetrating power of the <hi rend="italic">ß</hi> rays varies widely for
                    different products. For example, the rays from radium B are very easily
                    absorbed, while some of the rays from radium C are of a very penetrating type.
                    It has been found that for a single <hi rend="italic">ß</hi> ray product, the
                    particles are absorbed according to an exponential law with the thickness of
                    matter traversed, and Hahn has made use of this fact to isolate a number of new
                    products. It has been generally assumed that the exponential law of absorption
                    is a criterion that the <hi rend="italic">ß</hi> rays are all expelled at the
                    same speed. In addition, it has been supposed that the <hi rend="italic">β</hi> particles do not decrease much in velocity in passing through matter.
                    Wilson has recently made experiments upon homogeneous <hi rend="italic">ß</hi> rays, and finds that the intensity of the radiation falls off in some cases
                    according to a linear rather than to an exponential law, and that there is
                    undoubted evidence that the <hi rend="italic">ß</hi> particles decrease in
                    velocity in traversing matter. Experiments upon the absorption of <hi
                        rend="italic"> ß</hi> rays are greatly complicated by the scattering of the <hi rend="italic">ß</hi> rays in their encounters with the molecules. For
                    example, if a pencil of <hi rend="italic">ß</hi> rays falls on a metal, a
                    large fraction of the rays are scattered</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-22-r01-0802" facs="encyclopaediabri22chisrich_0827.jp2"/>
               <p>sufficiently to emerge on the side of incidence. This scattering of the <hi
                        rend="italic"> ß</hi> rays has been investigated by Eve, McLennan, Schmidt,
                    Crowther and others. It has been found that the scattering for different
                    chemical elements is connected with their atomic weight and their position in
                    the periodic table. McCelland and Schmidt have given theories to account for the
                    absorption of <hi rend="italic">ß</hi> rays by matter. The whole problem of
                    absorption and scattering of particles by substances is very complicated, and
                    the question is still under active examination and discussion. The negative
                    charge carried by the <hi rend="italic">ß</hi> rays has been measured by a
                    number of observers. It has been shown by Rutherford and Makower that the number
                    of <hi rend="italic">β</hi> particles expelled per second from one gram of
                    radium in equilibrium is about that to be ex-pected if each atom of the <hi
                        rend="italic"> β</hi> ray products in breaking up emits one <hi
                        rend="italic"> β</hi> particle.</p>
               <p><hi rend="italic">Heat Emission of Radioactive Matter. —</hi> In 1903 it was
                    shown by Curie and Laborde (52) that a radium compound was always hotter than
                    the surrounding medium, and radiated heat at a constant rate of about 100 gram
                    calories per hour per gram of radium. The rate of evolution of heat by radium
                    has been measured subsequently by a number of observers. The latest and most
                    accurate determination by Schweidler and Hess, using about half a gram of
                    radium, gave 118 gram calories per gram per hour (53). There is now no doubt
                    that the evolution of heat by radium and other radioactive matter is mainly a
                    second-ary phenomenon, resulting mainly from the expulsion of α particles. Since
                    the latter have a large kinetic energy and are easily absorbed by matter, all of
                    these particles are stopped in the radium itself or in the envelope surrounding
                    it, and their energy of motion is transformed into heat. On this view, the
                    evolution of heat from any type of radioactive matter is proportional to the
                    kinetic energy of the expelled α particles. The view that the heating effect of
                    radium was a measure of the kinetic energy of the α particles was strongly
                    confirmed by the experiments of Rutherford and Barnes (54). They showed that the
                    emanation and its products when removed from radium were responsible for about
                    three-quarters of the heating effect of radium in equilibrium. The heating
                    effect of the radium emanation decayed at the same rate as its activity. In
                    addition, it was found that the ray products, viz. the emanation radium A and
                    radium C, each gave a heating effect approximately proportional to their
                    activity. Measurements have been made on the heating effect of uranium and
                    thorium and of pitchblende and polonium. In each case, the evolution of heat has
                    been shown to be approximately a measure of the kinetic energy of the α
                    particles.</p>
               <p>Experiments on the evolution of heat from radium and its emanation have brought
                    to light the enormous amount of energy accompanying the transformation of
                    radioactive matter where α particles are emitted. For example, the emanation
                    from one gram of radium in equilibrium with its products emits heat initially at
                    the rate of about 90 gram calories per hour. The total heat emitted during its
                    transformation is about 12, 000 gram calories. Now the initial volume of the
                    emanation from one gram of radium is ∙6 cubic millimetres. Consequently one
                    cubic centimetre of emanation during its life emits 2 × 10 <hi rend="sup">7</hi> gram calories. Taking the atomic weight of the emanation as 222, one gram
                    of the emanation emits during its life 2 × 10 <hi rend="sup">9</hi> gram
                    calories of heat. This evolution of heat is enormous compared with that emitted
                    in any known chemical reaction. There is every reason to believe that the total
                    emission of energy from any type of radioactive matter during its transformation
                    is of the same order of magnitude as for the emanation. The atoms of matter must
                    consequently be regarded as containing enormous stores of energy which are only
                    released by the dis-integration of the atom.</p>
               <p>A large amount of work has been done in measuring the amount of the thorium and
                    radium emanation in the atmo-sphere, and in determining the quantity of radium
                    and thorium distributed on the surface of the earth. The information already
                    obtained has an important bearing on geology and atmospheric electricity.</p>
               <p><hi rend="smallcaps">References. —I. H. Becquerel,</hi> <hi rend="italic">Comptes Rendus,</hi> 1896, pp. 420, 501, 559, 689, 762,
                    1086; 2. Rutherford, <hi rend="italic">Phil. Mag.,</hi> Jan. 1899; 3. Mme
                    Curie, <hi rend="italic">Comptes Rendus,</hi> 1898, 126, p. 1101; M and Mme
                    Curie and G. Bémont, <hi rend="italic">ib.,</hi> 1898, 127. ρ. 1215; 4. Mme
                    Curie, <hi rend="italic">ib.,</hi> 1907, 145. p. 422; 5. Thorpe, <hi
                        rend="italic"> Proc. Roy. Soc.,</hi> 1908, 80. p. 298; 6. Giesd, <hi
                        rend="italic"> Phys. Zeit.,</hi> 1902, 3. p. 578; 7. Giesel, <hi
                        rend="italic"> Annal.</hi> <hi rend="italic">d.</hi> <hi rend="italic">Phys.,</hi> 1899, 69. p. 91; <hi rend="italic">Ber.,</hi> 1902, p. 3608; 8. Rutherford and Boltwood, <hi rend="italic">Amer. Journ. Sci.,</hi> July 1906; 9. Debierne, <hi rend="italic">Comptes Rendus,</hi> 1899,
                    129. p. 593; 1900, 130. p. 206; 10. Giesel, <hi rend="italic">Ber.,</hi> 1902,
                    p. 3608; 1903, p. 342; 11. Marckwald, <hi rend="italic">ib</hi> ., 1903, p.
                    2662; 12. Mme Curie and Debierne, <hi rend="italic">Comptes Rendus,</hi> 1910,
                    150. p. 386; 13. Boltwood, <hi rend="italic">Amer. Jοurn. Sd.,</hi> May 1908;
                    14. Rutherford, <hi rend="italic">Phil. Mαg.,</hi> Feb. 1903, Oct. 1906; 15.
                    Rutherford, <hi rend="italic">ib.,</hi> Jan. 1900; 16. Rutherford and Soddy, <hi rend="italic">ib.,</hi> May 1903; 17. Rutherford and Soddy, <hi
                        rend="italic"> ib.,</hi> Nov. 1902; 18. M and Mme Curie, <hi rend="italic">Comptes Rendus,</hi> 1899, 129. ρ. 714; 19. Rutherford, <hi rend="italic">Phil. Mag.,</hi> Jan. and Feb. 1900; 20. Rutherford and Soddy, <hi
                        rend="italic"> ib.,</hi> Sept. and Nov. 1902, April and May 1903;
                    Rutherford, <hi rend="italic">Phil. Trans.</hi> , 1904, 204A. p. 169; 21. Russ
                    and Makower, <hi rend="italic">Proc. Roy. Soc.,</hi> 1909, 82A. p. 205; 22.
                    Hahn, <hi rend="italic">Phys. Zeit.,</hi> 1909, 10. p. 81; 23. Rutherford, <hi
                        rend="italic"> Phil. Mag.,</hi> Nov. 1904, Sept. 1905; 24. Meyer and
                    Schweidler, <hi rend="italic">Wien. Βer.,</hi> July 1905; 25. Antonoff, <hi
                        rend="italic"> Phil. Mαg.,</hi> June 1910; 26. Cameron and Ramsay, <hi
                        rend="italic"> Trans. Chem. Soc.,</hi> 1907, p. 1266; Rutherford, <hi
                        rend="italic"> Phil. Mag.,</hi> Aug. 1908; 27. Cameron and Ramsay, <hi
                        rend="italic"> Proc. Roy. Soc.,</hi> 1908, 81 A. p. 210; Rutherford and
                    Royds, <hi rend="italic">Phil. Mag.,</hi> 1908, 16. p. 313; Royds, <hi
                        rend="italic"> Proc. Roy. Soc.,</hi> 1909, 82A. p. 22; Watson, <hi
                        rend="italic"> ib</hi> ., 1910, 83a. p. 50; 28. Rutherford, <hi
                        rend="italic"> Phil. Mag.,</hi> 1909; 29. Gray and Ramsay, <hi
                        rend="italic"> Trans. Chem. Soc.,</hi> 1909, pp. 354. 1073; 30. Rutherford
                    and Soddy, <hi rend="italic">Phil. Μag.,</hi> Sept. and Nov, 1902; 31. Hahn, <hi rend="italic">Proc. Roy. Soc.,</hi> March 1905; <hi rend="italic">Phil. Mag.,</hi> June 1906; <hi rend="italic">Ber.,</hi> 40. pp. 1462,
                    3304; <hi rend="italic">Phys. Zeit.,</hi> 1908, 9. pp. 245, 246; 32. Hahn, <hi
                        rend="italic"> Phil. Mag.,</hi> Sept. 1906; 33. Godlewski, <hi
                        rend="italic"> ib.,</hi> July 1905; 34. Boltwood, <hi rend="italic">ib.,</hi> April 1905; 35. Strutt, <hi rend="italic">Trans. Roy. Soc.,</hi> 1905Α.;
                    36. McCoy, <hi rend="italic">Ber.,</hi> 1904, p. 2641; 37. Soddy, <hi
                        rend="italic"> Phil. Mag.,</hi> June 1905, Aug. 1907, Oct. 1908, Jan. 1909;
                    38. Boltwood, <hi rend="italic">Amer. Journ. Sd.,</hi> Dec. 1906, Oct. 1907,
                    May 1908, June 1908; 39. Boltwood, <hi rend="italic">ib.,</hi> April 1908; 40.
                    Boltwood, <hi rend="italic">ib.,</hi> Oct. 1905, Feb. 1907; 41. Rutherford and
                    Geiger, <hi rend="italic">Prοc. Roy. Soc.,</hi> 1908, 81a. p. 141; 42.
                    Rutherford and Royds, <hi rend="italic">Phil. Mag.,</hi> Feb. 1909; 43. Dewar, <hi rend="italic">Proc. Roy. Sοc.,</hi> 1908, 81A. p. 280; 1910, 83. p.
                    404; 44. Boltwood and Rutherford, <hi rend="italic">Manch. Lit. and Phil. Soc.,</hi> 1909, 54. No. 6; 45. Bragg and Kleeman, <hi rend="italic">Phil. Mag.,</hi> Dec. 1904, Sept. 1905; 46. Rutherford, <hi rend="italic">ib.,</hi> Aug.
                    1906; 47. Geiger, <hi rend="italic">Prοc. Roy. Sοc.,</hi> 1910, 83a. p. 505;
                    48. Geiger, <hi rend="italic">ib.,</hi> 1910, 83A. p. 492; 49. Rutherford and
                    Geiger, <hi rend="italic">ib.,</hi> 1908, 81a. pp. 141, 163; 50. Crookes, <hi
                        rend="italic"> ib.,</hi> 1903; 51. Regener, <hi rend="italic">Verhandl. d.
                        D. Pnys. Ges.,</hi> 1908, 10. p. 28; 52. Curie and Laborde, <hi
                        rend="italic"> Comptes Rendus,</hi> 1904, 136. p. 673; 53. Schweidler and
                    Hess, <hi rend="italic">Wien.</hi> <hi rend="italic">Ber.,</hi> June 1908, 117; 54. Rutherford and Barnes, <hi
                        rend="italic"> Phil. Mag.,</hi> Feb. 1904.</p>
               <p>General treatises are: P. Curie, <hi rend="italic">Œuvres,</hi> 1908; E.
                    Rutherford, <hi rend="italic">Radioactive Transformations,</hi> 1906; F.
                    Soddy, <hi rend="italic">Interpretation of Radium,</hi> 1909; R. J. Strutt, <hi rend="italic">Becquerel Rays and Radium,</hi> 1904; W. Makower, <hi
                        rend="italic"> Radioactive Substances,</hi> 1908; J. Joly, <hi
                        rend="italic"> Radioactivity and Geology,</hi> 1909. See also <hi
                        rend="italic"> Annual Reports of the Chemical Society.</hi></p>
               <p>(E. Ru. )</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
