<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="chi.28490931-1526160593_Page_649.jpf" type="entry" xml:id="eb07-19-s01-0594-01" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SS</label>
or s, the eighteenth letter and fourteenth consonant of our alphabet. The sound of it is formed by driving the breath through a narrow passage between the palate and the tongue elevated near it, together with a motion of the lower jaw and teeth towards the upper, the lips being a little way open, with such a configuration of every part of the mouth and larynx as renders the voice somewhat sibilous and hissing. Its sound, however, varies, being strong in some words, as <hi rend="italic">this, thus,</hi> and soft in words which have a final <hi rend="italic">e,</hi> as <hi rend="italic">muse, wise.</hi> It is generally doubled at the end of words, by which they become hard and harsh, as in <hi rend="italic">kiss, loss.</hi> In some words it is silent, as <hi rend="italic">isle, island, viscount.</hi></p><p>In abbreviation, S. stands for <hi rend="italic">societas</hi> or <hi rend="italic">socius ;</hi> as R. S. S. for <hi rend="italic">regiœ societatis socius,</hi> fellow of the royal society. In medicinal prescriptions, S. A. signifies <hi rend="italic">secundum artem,</hi> according to the rules of art. And in the notes of the ancients, S. stands for <hi rend="italic">Sextus ;</hi> S. P. for <hi rend="italic">Spurius ;</hi> S. C. for <hi rend="italic">senatus consultum ;</hi> S. P. Q. R. for <hi rend="italic">senatus populusque Romanns ;</hi> S. S. S. for <hi rend="italic">stratum superstrαtum,</hi> one layer above another alternately ; S. V. B. E. E. Q. V. for <hi rend="italic">si vales bene est, ego quoque valeo,</hi> a form used in Cicero’s time in the beginning of letters. Used as a numeral, S. anciently denoted seven ; in the Italian music, S. signifies <hi rend="italic">solo ;</hi> and in books of navigation, S. stands for south, S. E. for south-east, S. W. for south-west, S. S. E. for south-south-east, S. S. W. for south- south-west, &amp;c.</p></div></body></text></TEI>