<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="chi.28490931-1526160593_Page_733.jpf" type="entry" xml:id="eb07-19-s01-0676-02" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SCENE</label>,
in its primary sense, denotes a theatre, or the place where dramatic pieces and other public shows are exhibited. It does not appear that the ancient poets were at all acquainted with the modern way of changing the scenes in the different parts of the play, in order to raise the idea of the persons represented by the actors being in different places.</p><p>The original scene for the acting of plays was as simple as the representations themselves. It consisted only of a plain plot of ground proper for the occasion, which was in some degree shaded by the neighbouring trees, the branches of which were made to meet together, and their vacancies supplied with boards, sticks, and the like ; and to complete the shelter, these were sometimes covered with skins, and sometimes with only the branches of other trees newly cut down, and full of leaves. Afterwards more artificial scenes, or scenical representations, were introduced, and paintings used instead of the objects themselves. Scenes were then of three sorts ; tragic, comic, and satiric. The tragic scene represented stately magnificent edifices, with decorations of pillars, statues, and other things suitable to the palaces of kings. The comic exhibited private houses with balconies and windows, in imitation of common buildings. And the satiric was the representation of groves, mountains, dens, and other rural appearances ; and these decorations either turned on pivots, or slid along grooves as those in our theatres.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Scene</hi> is also a part or division of a dramatic poem. Thus plays are divided into acts, and acts are again subdivided into scenes ; in which sense the scene is properly the persons present at or concerned in the action on the stage at such a time. Whenever, therefore, a new actor appears, or an old one disappears, the action is changed into other hands ; and therefore a new scene then commences.</p><p>It is one of the laws of the stage, that the scenes be well connected ; in other words, that one succeed another in such a manner as that the stage be never quite empty till the end of the act.</p></div></body></text></TEI>