<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>translated from HTML to TEI</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-23-r02-0041-01"
                facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0064.jp2" type="entry">

                <p><label>REGISTRATION</label> . In all systems of law the registration of certain
                    legal facts has been regarded as necessary, chiefly for the purpose of ensuring
                    publicity and simplifying evidence. Registers, when made in performance of a
                    public duty, are as a general rule admissible in evidence merely on the
                    production from the proper custody of the registers themselves or (in most
                    cases) of examined or certified copies. The extent to which registration is
                    carried varies very much in different countries. For obvious reasons, judicial
                    decisions are registered in all countries alike. In other matters no general
                    rule can be laid down, except perhaps that on the whole registration is not as
                    fully enforced in the United Kingdom and the United States as in continental
                    states. The most important uses of registration occur in the case of judicial
                    proceedings, land, ships, bills of sale, births, marriages and deaths,
                    companies, friendly and other societies, newspapers, copyrights, patents,
                    designs, trade marks and professions and occupations. In England registrars are
                    attached to the privy council, the Supreme Court and the county courts. In the
                    king’s bench division (except in its bankruptcy jurisdiction) the duty of
                    registrars is performed by the masters. Besides exercising limited judicial
                    authority, registrars are responsible for the drawing up and recording of
                    various stages of the proceedings from the petition, writ or plaint to the final
                    decision. <note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="1"> The
                        antiquity of registration of this kind is proved by the age of the <hi
                            rend="italic">Registrum Brevium,</hi> or register of writs, called by
                        Lord Coke " a most ancient book of the Common Law”
                        (Coke-upon-Littleton, 159a). </note> With them are filed affidavits,
                    depositions, pleadings, &amp;c., when such filing is necessary. The
                    difference between filing and registration is that the documents filed are filed
                    without alteration, while only an epitome is usually registered. The Judicature
                    Act 1873 created district registries in the chief towns, the district registrar
                    having an authority similar to that of a registrar of the Supreme Court. In the
                    admiralty division cases of account are usually referred to the registrar and
                    merchants. The registration in the central office of the supreme court of
                    judgments affecting lands, writ3 of execution, recognizances and <hi
                        rend="italic">liles pendentes</hi> in England, and the registration in
                    Scotland of abbreviates of adjudications and of inhibitions, are governed by
                    special legislation. All these are among the incumbrances for which search is
                    made on investigating a title. Decisions of criminal courts are said to be
                    recorded, not registered, except in the case of courts of summary jurisdiction,
                    in which, by the Summary Jurisdiction Act 1879, a register of convictions is
                    kept. Probates of wills and letters of administration, which arc really judicial
                    decisions, are registered in the principal or district registries of the probate
                    division. In Scotland registration is used for giving a summary remedy on
                    obligations without action by means of the fiction of a judicial decision having
                    been given establishing the obligation.</p>
               <p>See also the separate articles <hi rend="smallcaps">Land Registration; Shipping;
                        Bill of Sale; Companies; Friendly Societies; Building Societies; Press Laws;
                        Copyright; Trade Marks; Patents,</hi>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>                    <hi rend="italic">Registration of Voters,—</hi> Prior to 1832 the right of
                    parliamentary electors in England was determined at the moment of the tender of
                    the vote at the election, or, in the event of a petition against the return, by
                    a scrutiny, a committee of the House of Commons striking off those whose
                    qualification was held to be insufficient, and, on the other hand, adding those
                    who, having tendered their votes at the poll, with a good title to do so, were
                    rejected at the time. A conspicuous feature of the Reform Act of that year was
                    the introduction of a new mode of ascertaining the rights of electors by means
                    of an entirely new system of published lists, subject to claims and objections,
                    and after due inquiry and revision forming a register of voters. Registration
                    was not altogether unknown in Great Britain in connexion with the parliamentary
                    franchise before the Reform Acts of 1832. Thus in the Scottish counties the
                    right to vote depended on the voter’s name being upon the roll of freeholders
                    established by an act of Charles II.; a similar register existed in Ireland of
                    freeholders whose freeholds were under £20 annual value; and in the universities
                    of Oxford and Cambridge the rolls of members of Convocation and of the Senate
                    were, as they still arc, the registers of parliamentary voters. But except in
                    such cases as the above, the right of a voter had to be determined by the
                    returning officer upon the evidence produced before him when the vote was
                    tendered at a poll. This necessarily took time, and the result was that a
                    contested election in a large constituency might last for weeks. The celebrated
                    Westminster election of 1784, in which the poll began on the ist of April and
                    ended on the 17th of May, may be mentioned as an illustration. Moreover, the
                    decision of the returning officer was not conclusive; the title of every one who
                    claimed to vote was liable to be reconsidered on an election petition, or, in
                    the case of a rejected vote, in an action for damages by the voter against the
                    returning officer.</p>
               <p>The inconvenience of such a state of things would have been greatly aggravated
                    had the old practice continued after the enlargement of the franchise in 1832.
                    The establishment of a general system of registration was therefore a necessary
                    and important part of the reform then effected. It has enabled an election in
                    the most populous constituency to be completed in a single day. It has also been
                    instrumental in the extinction</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-23-r02-0042" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0065.jp2"/>
               <p>of the “ occasional voter,” who formerly gave so much trouble to returning
                    officers and election committees—the person, namely, who acquired a qualifying
                    tenement with the view of using it for a particular election and then disposing
                    of it. The period of qualification now required in all cases, being fixed with
                    reference to the formation of the register, is necessarily so long anterior to
                    any election which it could effect, that the purpose or intention of the voter
                    in acquiring the qualifying tenement has ceased to be material, and is not
                    investigated.</p>
               <p>                    <hi rend="italic">England.—</hi> The reform of parliamentary representation in
                    1832 was followed in 1835 by that of the constitution of municipal corporations,
                    which included the creation of a uniform qualification (now known as the old
                    burgess qualification) for the municipal franchise. In 1888 the municipal
                    franchise was enlarged, and was at the same time extended to the whole country
                    for the formation of constituencies to elect county councils; and in 1894
                    parochial electors were called into existence for the election of parish
                    councils and for other purposes. Inasmuch as provision was made for the
                    registering of persons entitled to votes for the above purposes, there are now
                    three registers of voters, namely, the parliamentary register, the local
                    government register (i.e. in boroughs under the Municipal Corporation Acts, the
                    burgess rolls, and elsewhere the county registers) and the register of parochial
                    electors. Under the Municipal Corporations Act 1835 the registration of
                    burgesses, though on similar lines to that of parliamentary voters, was entirely
                    separate from it. Since, however, the qualification for the municipaI franchise
                    covered to a great extent the same ground as that for the parliamentary
                    franchise in boroughs which sent members to parliament, a considerable number of
                    voters in such boroughs were entitled in respect of the same tenement to be upon
                    both parliamentary register and burgess roll. The waste. of labour involved in
                    settling their rights twice over was put an end to in 1878, when the system of
                    parliamentary registration was extended to the boroughs in question for
                    municipal purposes, and the lists were directed to be made out in such a shape
                    that the portion common to the two registers could be detached and combined with
                    the portion peculiar to each, so as to form the parliamentary register and the
                    burgess roll respectively. This system of registration was extended to the
                    non-parliamentary boroughs and to the whole country in 1888, the separate
                    municipal registration being completely aboIished.</p>
               <p>The procedure of parliamentary registration is to be found in its main lines in
                    the Parliamentary Registration Act 1843, which superseded that provided by the
                    Reform Act of 1832, and has itself been considerably amended by later
                    legislation. The acts applying and adapting the system to local government and
                    parochial registration are the Parliamentary and Municipal Registration Act
                    1878, the County Electors Act 1888, and the Local Government Act 1894.
                    Registration is carried out by local machinery, the common-law parish being
                    taken as the registration unit; and the work of preparing and publishing the
                    lists, which when revised are to form the register, is committed to the
                    overseers. The selection of these officers was no doubt due to their position as
                    the rating authority, and to their, consequent opportunities for knowing the
                    ownership and occupation of tenements within their parish. They do not always
                    perform the duties themselves, other persons being empowered to act for them in
                    many parishes by general or local acts of parliament; but in all or almost all
                    cases they are entitled to act personally if they think fit, they sign the
                    lists, and the proceedings are conducted in their</p>
               <p>name.</p>
               <p>In order to render intelligible the following summary of the procedure, it will
                    be necessary to divide the voters to be registered into classes based on the
                    nature of their qualification, since the practice differs in regard to each
                    class. The classes are as follows: (1) Owners, including the old forty-shilling
                    freeholders, and the copyholders, long leaseholders and others entitled under
                    the Reform Act of 1832 to vote at parliamentary elections for counties; (2)
                    occupiers, including those entitled to (a) the £10 occupation qualification, (b)
                    the household qualification and (c) the old burgess qualification; (3) lodgers,
                    subdivided into (a) old, <hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi> those on the previous
                    register for the same lodgings, and (b) new; (4) those entitled to reserved
                    rights, <hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi> in addition to those (if ,any still
                    remain),, who were entitled to votes before the Reform Act of 1832:111 respect
                    of qualifications abolished by that act, (a) freehold and burgage tenants in
                    Bristol, Exeter, Norwich, and Nottingham, and <hi rend="italic">(b)</hi>
                    liverymen of the City of London and freemen of certain old cities and boroughs,
                    whose right to the parliamentary franchise was permanently retained by the same
                    act. In regard to these classes it may be said that the general scheme is that
                    owners must make a claim in the first instance before they can get their names
                    upon the register, but that, once entered on the register, the names will be
                    retained from year to year until removed by the revising barrister; that the
                    lists of occupiers and of freehold and burgage tenants arc made out afresh every
                    year by the overseers from, their own information and inquiries, without any act
                    being required on the part of the voters, who need only make claims in case
                    their names are omitted; that lodgers must make claims every year; and that
                    liverymen and freemen are in the same position as occupiers, except that the
                    lists of liverymen are made out by the clerks of the several companies, and
                    those of freemen by the town clerks, the overseers having nothing to do with
                    these voters, whose qualifications are personal and not locally connected with
                    any parish.</p>
               <p>The overseers and other officers concerned are required to perform their duties
                    in connexion with registration in accordance with the instructions and precepts,
                    and to use the notices and forms prescribed by Order in Council from time to
                    time. The Registration Order, 1895, directs the clerk of every county council,
                    on or within seven days before the 15th of April in every year, to send to the
                    overseers of each parish in his county a precept with regard to the registration
                    of ownership, electors, and to every parish not within a parliamentary or
                    municipal borough a precept with regard to the registration of occupation
                    electors (which expression for this purpose includes lodgers as well as
                    occupiers proper). The town clerk of every borough, municipal or parliamentary,
                    is to send to the overseers of every parish in his borough a precept with regard
                    to the registration of occupation electors. These precepts are set out in the
                    Registration Order, and those issued by the town clerks differ according as the
                    borough is parliamentary only, or municipal only, or both parliamentary and
                    municipal; in the cases of Bristol, Exeter, Norwich and Nottingham they contain
                    directions as to freehold and burgage tenants. , The duties of the overseers in
                    regard to registration are set out in detail in the precepts. Along with the
                    precepts are forwarded forms of the various lists and notices required to be
                    used, and with the ownership precept a certain number of copies of that portion
                    of the parliamentary register of the county at the time in force which contains
                    the ownership voters for the parish, the register being so printed that the
                    portion relating to each parish can be detached. It is the duty of the overseers
                    to publish on the 20th of June, in manner hereinafter described, the portion of
                    the register so received, together with a notice to owners not already
                    registered to send in claims by the 20th of July. Meanwhile the overseers are
                    making the inquiries necessary for the preparation of the occupier list. For
                    this purpose they may require returns to be furnished by owners of houses let
                    out in separate tenements, and by employers who have servants entitled to the
                    service franchise. The registrars of births, deaths and marriages are required
                    to furnish the overseers with returns of deaths, as must the assessed tax
                    collectors with returns of defaulters; the relieving officers are to give
                    information as to recipients of parochial relief. On or before the 31st of July
                    the overseers are to make out and sign the lists of voters. Theseare the
                    following: the list of ownership electors, consisting of the portion of the
                    register previously published with a supplemental list, of those who have sent
                    in claims by the, 20th of July; the occupier list; and the old lodger list, the
                    last being formed from claims sent in by the 25th of July. The overseers do not
                    select the names in the first and last of these lists; they take them as
                    supplied in the register and claims. It is, however, their duty to write " dead
                    ” or “ objected ” in the margin against the names of persons whom they have
                    reason to believe to be dead or not entitled to vote in respect of the
                    qualification described. The ownership and old lodger lists will be divided into
                    two parts, if the register contains names of owners entitled to a parochial vote
                    only, or if claims by owners or old lodgers have been made limited to that
                    franchise. The occupier list contains the names of persons whom the overseers
                    believe to be qualified, and no others, and therefore will be free from marginal
                    objections. Except in the administrative county of London, it is made out in
                    three divisions—division 1 giving the names of occupiers of property qualifying
                    for both parliamentary and local government votes, divisions 2 and 3 those of
                    occupiers of property qualifying only for parliamentary and only for local
                    government votes respectively. It happens so frequently that a tenement, if not
                    of sufficient value to qualify for the £10 occupation franchise (parliamentary
                    and local government), qualifies both for the household franchise
                    (parliamentary) aftd for the old burgess franchise (local government), that
                    division 1 would in most cases be the whole list, but for two circumstances. The
                    service franchise is a special modification of the household franchise only; and
                    the service occupants, being therefore restricted to the parliamentary vote,
                    form the bulk of division 2 ; while peers and women, being excluded, from the
                    parliamentary vote, are consequently relegated to division 3. In the
                    administrative county of London the local government register, being coextensive
                    with the register of parochial electors, includes</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-23-r02-0043" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0066.jp2"/>
               <p>the whole of the parliamentary register. The occupier lists are consequently
                    there made out in two divisions only, the names which would elsewhere appear in
                    division 2 being placed in division 1. The lists of freehold and burgage tenants
                    in Bristol, Exeter, Norwich and Nottingham are to be made out and signed by the
                    same date. The overseers have also to make out and sign a list of persons
                    qualified as occupiers to be elected aldermen or councillors, but as
                    non-residents disqualified from being on the local government register. By the
                    same date also the clerks of the livery companies are to make out, sign and
                    deliver to the secondary (who performs in the City of London the registration
                    duties which elsewhere fall on the town clerk) the lists of liverymen entitled
                    as such to the parliamentary vote; and the town clerks are to make out and sign
                    the lists of freemen so entitled in towns where this franchise exists.</p>
               <p>On the 1st of August all the above lists are to be published, the livery lists
                    by the secondary, lists of freemen by the town clerks and the rest by the
                    overseers. In addition the overseers may have to publish a list of persons
                    disqualified by having been found guilty of corrupt or illegal practices; this
                    list they will receive, when it exists, from the clerk of the county council or
                    town clerk with the precept. Publication of lists and notices by overseers is
                    made by affixing copies on the doors of the church and other places of worship
                    of the parish (or, if there be none, in some public or conspicuous situation in
                    the parish), and also, with the exception to be mentioned, in the case of a
                    parish wholly or partly within a municipal borough or urban district, in or near
                    every public or municipal or parochial office and every post and telegraph
                    office in the parish. The exception is that lists and notices relating to
                    ownership electors need not be published at the offices mentioned when the
                    parish is within a parliamentary borough. Publication by the secondary is made
                    by affixing copies outside the Guildhall and Royal Exchange ; publication by
                    town clerks is. made by affixing copies outside their town hall, or, where there
                    is none, in some public or conspicuous place in their borough. From the 1st to
                    the 20th of August inclusive is allowed for the sending in of claims and
                    objections. Those whose names have been omitted from the occupier or reserved
                    rights lists, or the non-resident list, or whose names, place of abode or
                    particulars of qualification have been incorrectly stated in such lists, may
                    send in claims to have their names registered; lodgers who are not qualified as
                    old lodgers, or who have omitted to claim as such, may claim as new lodgers;
                    persons whose names are on the corrupt and illegal practices list may claim to
                    have them omitted. Any person whose name is on the list of parliamentary’, local
                    government. or parochial electors for the same parliamentary county,
                    administrative county, borough or parish, may object to names on the same lists.
                    Notices of claim and objection in the case of liverymen and freemen are to be
                    sent to the secondary and town clerk, and in other cases to the overseers ; and
                    notices of objection must also in all cases be sent to the person objected to.
                    All notices must be sent inby the 20th of August, and on or before the 25th of
                    August the overseers, secondary and town clerks are to make out, sign and
                    publish lists of the claimants and persons objected to. It remains to be added
                    that any person on a Fist of voters <hi rend="italic">(i.e.</hi> on one of the
                    lists published on the 1st of August) may make a declaration before a magistrate
                    or commissioner for oaths correcting the entry relating to him. In the case of
                    ownership electors the correction can only deal with the place of abode; in the
                    case of other lists it extends to all particulars stated, and is. useful
                    inasmuch as it enables the revising barrister to make corrections as to the
                    qualification which he could not make in the absence of a declaration. The
                    declarations must be delivered to the clerk of the county council or town clerk
                    on or before the 5th of September.</p>
               <p>The next stage is the revision of the lists. For this, purpose revising
                    barristers are appointed yearly. The period within which revision courts can be
                    held is from the 8th of September to the 12th of October, both days inclusive.
                    The clerk of the county council attends the first court held for each
                    parliamentary division of his county, and the town clerk the first court held
                    for his city or borough; and they respectively produce all lists, notices and
                    declarations in. their custody, and answer any questions put to them by the
                    revising, barrister. The overseers also attend the courts held for their parish,
                    produce the rate books, original notices of claim and objection, &amp;c.,
                    and answer questions. The claimants, objectors and persons objected to appear
                    personally or by representative to support their several contentions. Any person
                    qualified to be an objector may also appear to oppose any claims, upon giving
                    notice to the barrister before such claims are reached. The powers of the
                    revising barristers are as follows: As regards persons whose names are on the
                    lists of voters published on the ist of August, he is to expunge the names,
                    whether objected to or not, of those who are dead or subject to personal
                    incapacity, such as infants and aliens, and for parliamentary purposes peers and
                    women. If an entry is imperfect, the name must be removed, unless the
                    particulars necessary for completing it are supplied to the barrister. All names
                    marginally objected to by overseers must be expunged, unless the voters prove to
                    the barrister that they ought to be retained. Objections made by other objectors
                    must be supported by prima facie proof, and if this is not rebutted the name is
                    struck out. Claimants must be ready to support their claims. The declaration
                    attached to a lodger claim is indeed prima facie proof of the facts stated in
                    it, but other claimants require evidence to make out even a prima facie case,
                    and if they fail to produce it their claims will be disallowed. The barrister is
                    required to correct errors in the lists of voters, and has a discretion to
                    rectify mistakes in claims and objections upon evidence produced to him,
                    although his power in this respect is limited. Lastly, the barrister has to deal
                    with duplicates, as a voter is entitled to be on the register once, but not more
                    than once, as a parliamentary voter for each parliamentary county or borough, as
                    a burgess for each municipal borough, as a county elector Jor each electoral
                    division, and as a parochial elector for each parish in which he holds a
                    qualification. Consequently, he deals with duplicate entries by expunging or
                    transferring them to separate parochial, lists. The decision of the revising
                    barrister is final and conclusive on all questions of fact ; but an appeal lies
                    from him on questions of law at the instance of any person aggrieved by the
                    removal of his name from a list of voters, by the rejection of his claim or
                    objection or by the allowance of a claim which he has opposed. Notice of the
                    intention to appeal must be given to the barrister in writing on the day when
                    nis decision is given. The barrister may refuse to state a case for appeal ; but
                    if he does so without due cause he may be ordered by the High Court to state a
                    case. The appeal is heard by a divisional court, from whose decision an appeal
                    lies (by leave either of the divisional court or of the court of appeal) to the
                    court of appeal, whose decision is final.</p>
               <p>On the completion of the revision the barrister hands the county and borough
                    lists (every page signed and every alteration initialled by him) to the clerk of
                    the county council and the town clerk respectively, to be printed. With the
                    following exceptions the revised lists are to be made up and printed by the 20th
                    of December, and come into force as the register for all purposes on the ist of
                    January. In the boroughs created by the London Government Act 1899, the whole
                    register is to be made up and printed by the 20th of October, and to come into
                    force for the purpose of borough elections under the act on the ist of November.
                    In boroughs subject to the Municipal Corporations Acts, divisions 1 and 3 of the
                    occupiers’ list are to be made up and printed by the 20th of October, and come
                    into force for the purpose of municipal and county council elections on the ist
                    of November. Corrections ordered in consequence of a successful appeal from a
                    revising barrister are to be made by the officers having the custody of the
                    registers, but a pending appeal does not affect any right of voting. The
                    register in its final form will consist of the lists published on the ist of
                    August as corrected, with the claims which have been allowed on revision
                    incorporated with them. It is printed in. such form that each list and each
                    division of a list for. every parish can be separated from the rest for the
                    purpose of making up the parliamentary, local government and parochial registers
                    respectively. The alphabetical order is followed, except in London and some
                    other large towns, where street order is adopted for all except the ownership
                    lists and lists of liverymen and freemen. The parliamentary register for a
                    parliamentary county will consist of the ownership lists for all parishes in the
                    county, and of the lodger, lists and divisions 1 and 2 of the occupier lists for
                    parishes within the county and not within a parliamentary borough. The
                    parliamentary register for a parliamentary borough will consist of the lodger
                    lists, of the lists of freehold and burgage tenants (if any), and of divisions 1
                    and 2 of the occupier lists for all parishes within the borough, and also of the
                    borough lists (if any) of liverymen or freemen. The local government register
                    for an administrative county will consist of divisions 1 and 3 of the occupier
                    lists for all parishes in the county, and the burgess roll for a municipal
                    borough of divisions i and 3 of the occupier lists for all parishes in the
                    borough. It will be seen, therefore, that, except in county boroughs, the
                    burgess roll, is also a part of the local government register of the
                    administrative county within which the borough is situate. The register of
                    parochial electors consists of the complete set of lists for each parish; but
                    this does not include the lists of liverymen and freemen, which, as has been
                    stated, are not parish lists.</p>
               <p>No one whose name is not on the register can vote at an election. The. fact that
                    a. man’s name is on the register is now so far conclusive of his right that the
                    returning officer is bound to receive his vote. Only two questions may be asked
                    of him when he tenders his vote, namely, whether he is the person whose name is
                    on the register, and whether he has voted before at the election. The Reform Act
                    1832 allowed him to be asked at parliamentary elections whether he retained the
                    qualification for which he had been registered; but the Registration Act 1843
                    disallowed the question, and. made the register conclusive as to the retention
                    of the qualification. When, however, a petition is presented against an
                    election, the register, although conclusive as to the retention of the
                    qualification, does not prevent the court from inquiring into the existence of
                    personal incapacities, arising in connexion with the election or otherwise, and
                    striking off on scrutiny the votes of persons subject thereto, <hi rend="italic"
                        >e.g.</hi> aliens, infants, or in parliamentary elections peers, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The City of London is not within the Municipal Corporations Acts, and is not
                    subject to the general registration law in the formation of its roll of citizens
                    for municipal purposes. But a register of parliamentary, county and parochial
                    electors is made in</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-23-r02-0044" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0067.jp2"/>
               <p>the 'ordinary way.' The universities are also exempt from the general law of
                    registration. At Oxford and Cambridge the members of Convocation and the Senate
                    respectively have always formed the parliamentary constituencies; and, as has
                    been already stated, the registers of those members were before 1832, and still
                    arc, the parliamentary registers. Similarly, the Reform Act of 1867, which gave
                    parliamentary representation to the university of London, simply enacted that
                    the register of graduates constituting the Convocation should be the
                    parliamentary register of that body.</p>
               <p>                    <hi rend="italic">Scotland.—</hi> In Scotland the qualifications for local
                    government and parish electors are the same as those for parliamentary voters,
                    the only difference in the registers being in respect of personal incapacities
                    for the parliamentary franchise, incapacity for the other franchises by reason
                    of non-payment of rates,, and duplicates. The principal act regulating
                    registration in burghs is 19 &amp; 20 Vict. c. 58, amended in some
                    particulars as to dates by 31 &amp; 32 Vict. c. 48, § 20. County
                    registration, formerly regulated by 24 &amp; 25 Vict. c. 83, has been
                    assimilated to burgh registration by 48 &amp; 49 Vict. c. 3, § 8 (6). The
                    procedure consists, as in. England, of the making and publication of lists of
                    voters, the making of claims and objections and the holding of revision courts;
                    but there are important differences of detail. Though the parish is the
                    registration unit, parochial machinery is not used for the formation of the
                    register. The parliamentary lists for a county are made up yearly by one or more
                    of the assessors of the county, and those for a burgh by one or more of the
                    assessors for the burgh, or by the clerk of the commissioners. They are
                    published on the 15th of September; and claims and objections must be sent in by
                    the 21st and are published on the 25th of the same month. Publication is made in
                    burghs by posting on or near the town hall, or in some other conspicuous place,
                    in counties by posting the part relating to each parish on the parish church
                    door, and in both cases giving notice by newspaper advertisement of a place
                    where the lists may be perused. The revision is conducted by the sheriff, the
                    time within which his courts may be held being from the 25th of September to the
                    16th of October, both days inclusive. An appeal lies to three judges of the
                    Court of Session, one taken from each division of the Inner House, and one from
                    the Lords Ordinary of the Outer House. The revised lists are delivered in
                    counties to the sheriff clerk, in burghs to the town clerk, or person to. whom
                    the registration duties of town clerk are assigned. The register comes into
                    force for all purposes on the ist of November.</p>
               <p>The municipal register of a royal burgh which is coextensive, or of that part of
                    a royal burgh which is coextensive with a parliamentary burgh, consists of the
                    parliamentary register with a supplemental list of women who but for their sex
                    would be qualified for the parliamentary vote. The municipal register for a
                    burgh, or for that part of one which is not within a parliamentary burgh,
                    consists of . persons possessed of qualifications within the burgh which, if
                    within a parliamentary burgh, would entitle them, or but for their sex would
                    entitle them, to the parliamentary vote. The register of county electors
                    consists of the parliamentary register for a county with the supplemental list
                    hereafter mentioned; but inasmuch as exemption, from or* failure to pay the
                    consolidated county rate is a disqualification for the county electors’
                    franchise, the names of persons so disqualified are to be marked with a
                    distinctive mark on the register; as are also the names of persons whose
                    qualifications are situated within a burgh, such marks indicating that the
                    persons to whose names they are attached are not entitled to vote as county
                    electors. Every third year, in preparation for the triennial elections of county
                    and parish councils (casual vacancies being filled up by co-optation), a
                    supplemental list is to be made of peers and women possessed of qualifications
                    which but for their rank and sex would entitle them to parliamentary votes. The
                    register of county electors in a county and the municipal register in a burgh
                    form the registers of parish electors for the parishes comprised in each
                    respectively.. Inasmuch, however, as a man is entitled to be registered as a
                    parish elector in every parish where he is qualified, duplicate entries are,
                    when required, to be made in the register, with distinctive marks to all but
                    one, to indicate that they confer the parish vote only. These distinctive marks
                    and those previously mentioned are to be made in the lists, by the assessors,
                    subject to revision by the sheriff. The register is conclusive to the same
                    extent as in England, except that the vote of a parish elector who is one year
                    in arrear in payment of a parish rate is not to be received. The clerk of the
                    parish council is. to furnish the returning officer one week before an election,
                    with the names of persons so in arrear; and the returning officer is to reject
                    their votes except upon the production of a written receipt.. Provision is made
                    by 31 &amp; 32 Vict. c. 48, §§ 27-41, for the. formation of registers of
                    parliamentary electors for the universities. The register for each university is
                    to be made annually by the university registrar, with the assistance of two
                    members of, the council, from whose decisions an appeal lies to the university
                    court.</p>
               <p>                    <hi rend="italic">Ireland.</hi> —There are no parish councils in Ireland, and no
                    parochial electors. There are therefore but two registers of voters, the
                    parliamentary and the local government registers, the latter of which consists
                    of the former with a local government supplement containing the names of those
                    excluded from the parliamentary register by reason of their being peers or
                    women, and- duplicate entries relating to those whose names are registered
                    elsewhere for the same parliamentary constituency. The principal acts regulating
                    registration are 13'&amp; 14 Vict. c. 69, 31 &amp; 32 Vict. c. 112, 48
                    &amp; 49 Vict. c. 17, and 61 &amp; 62 Viet. c. 2. The lord lieutenant is
                    empowered to make by Order in Council rules for registration, and to prescribe
                    forms; and under this power has made the Registration (Ireland) Rules 1899, now
                    in force. The registration unit is not the parish, but the district electoral
                    division, except where such division is subdivided -into wards, or is partly
                    within and partly without any town or ward of a borough or town, in which cases
                    each ward of the division or part of a division is a separate registration unit.</p>
               <p>The procedure is as follows, subject to variation in cases where there are
                    clerks of unions who held office on the 31st of March 1898, and have not agreed
                    to transfer their registration duties. The clerk of the peace sends out on the
                    ist of June a precept in the form prescribed for county registration to the
                    secretary of the county council and clerks of urban district councils, together
                    with a copy of the existing register for their county or district; and a precept
                    in the form prescribed for borough registration to town clerks of boroughs. As
                    regards registration units not in a parliamentary or municipal borough, the
                    secretary of the county council or clerk of the urban district council is to put
                    marginal objections, “ dead ” or “ objected,” where required, to £10 occupiers
                    and householders in the copy of the register, both in the parliamentary list and
                    in the local government supplement. He is also to make out supplemental
                    parliamentary and local government lists of £10 occupiers and householders not
                    on the existing register, and to put marginal objections where required to
                    these. He is to verify on oath before a magistrate the copy of the register and
                    supplemental lists, and to return them to the clerk of the peace by the 8th ’of
                    July. As regards registration units in a parliamentary borough, but outside a
                    municipal borough, the secretary of the county council or clerk of the urban
                    district council is to make out lists of £10 occupiers and householders with
                    local government supplement, and transmit them to the town clerk of the
                    municipal borough or town. The clerk of the peace is to publish the copy of the
                    register, after himself placing marginal objections where required to voters
                    other than £10 occupiers and householders, and the supplemental lists as
                    received, and also the corrupt and illegal practices list, if any, on the 22nd
                    of July. On the same day the town clerk will publish the lists received as
                    aforesaid for registration units outside the municipal borough, and the lists,
                    which he will have made out himself for the municipal borough, including the
                    freemen’s list and corrupt and illegal practices list. Freemen being entitled to
                    the local government vote will, if resident, be placed on the list of the
                    registration unit, where they reside, and will, if non-resident, be allotted by
                    the revising barrister among the registration units of the borough for local
                    government purposes in proportion to the number of electors in each registration
                    unit. Claims are to be sent in to the clerk of the peace and.town clerk by the
                    4th of August, including old lodger claims and, in the case of the clerk of the
                    peace, ownership, claims. Lists of claimants with marginal objections, where
                    required, are to be published by the clerk of the peace and town clerk by the
                    nth of August. Notices of objection to voters or claimants may be given by the
                    20th of August; and lists of persons objected to are to be published by the
                    clerk of the peace and town clerk by the 24th of the same, month. Publication of
                    lists and notices by a clerk of the peace is made by posting copies of those
                    relating to each registration unit outside every court-house, petty sessions
                    court, and other public offices in the unit; publication by a town clerk is made
                    by posting copies outside the town hall, or, if there be none, in some public
                    and conspicuous place in the borough.</p>
               <p>Revising barristers are specially appointed for the county and city of Dublin by
                    the lord lieutenant; elsewhere the county court judges and chairmen of quarter
                    sessions act as such <hi rend="italic">ex Officio <hi rend="sub">1</hi></hi> assisted, when necessary, by additional barristers appointed by the lord
                    lieutenant. The time for the holding of revision courts is from the 8th of
                    September to the 25th of October inclusive. An appeal lies to the court of
                    appeal, whose decision is final. The revised lists are handed to the clerk of
                    the peace; they are to be made up by him by the 31st of December, and come into
                    force on the ist of January.</p>
               <p>The registrar of the university of Dublin is to make out in December a list of
                    the persons entitled to the parliamentary vote for the university, and to print
                    the same in January, and to publish a copy in the university calendar, or in one
                    or. more public journals circulating in Irelapd. He is to revise the list
                    annually, and expunge the names of those dead or disqualified; but an elector
                    whose, name has been expunged because he . was supposed to be dead is entitled,
                    if alive, to have his name immediately restored and to vote at any election. (L.
                    L. S.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
