<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0083-01" facs="gri_33125011196389_0089.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>REPROBATION</label>
in theology, means the act of abandoning, or ſtate of being abandoned, to eternal de-ſtruction, and is applied to that decree or reſolve which God has taken from all eternity to puniſh ſinners who ſhall die in impenitence ; in which ſenſe it is directly op-poſed to election. When a ſinner is ſo hardened as to feel no remorſe or miſgiving of conſcience, it is conſidered as a ſign of reprobation ; which by the caſuiſts has been diſtinguiſhed into pofitive and negative. The ſirſt is that whereby God is ſuppoſed to create men with a pofitive and abſolute refolution to damn them eternally. This opinion is countenanced by St Auguſ-tſhe and other Chriſtian fathers, and is a peculiar tenet of Calvin and moſt of his followers. The church of England, in <hi rend="italic">The thirty-nine Articles,</hi> teaches fomething like it ; and the church of Scotland, in the <hi rend="italic">Confejfion of Faith,</hi> maintains it in the ſtrongeſt terms. But the notion is generally exploded, and is believed by no rational divine in either church, being totally injurious to the juſtice of the Deity. Negative or conditional reprobation is that whereby God, though he has a ſincere deſire to ſave men, and furniſhes them with the neceffary means, fo that all if they will may be ſaved, yet fees that there are many who will not be ſaved by the means, however powerful, that are afforded them; tho* by other means which the Deity fees, but will not afford them, they might be ſaved. Reprobation reſpects angels as well as men, and reſpects the latter either fallen or unfallen. See Predestination.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>