<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0085-04" facs="gri_33125011196389_0091.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>REPULSION</label>
in phyfics, that property of bodies whereby they recede from each other, and, on certain occafions, mutually avoid coming into contact.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Repulsion, as well as attraction, has of late been confidered as one of the primary qualities of all matter, and has been much uſed in explaining the phenomena of nature : thus the particles of air, fire, ſteam, electric fluid, &amp;c. are all ſaid to have a repullιve power with refpect to one another.—That this is the cafe with the air, and vapour of all kinds, is certain ; becaufe when they are compreffed into</hi> a ſmall ſpace,. they expand:</p>
<pb xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0086" facs="gri_33125011196389_0092.tif"/>
<p>.with great force : but as to fire, light, and electricity, our experiments fail; nay, the ſuppoſition of a repulſtve power among the particles of the electric fluid is incon-ſiſtent with the phenomena, as has been demonſtrated under the article Electricity, Sect. V. and VI. E-ven in thofe fluids, air and ſteam, wherc a repulſtve power moſt manifeſtly exiſts, it is demonſtrable that the repulſion cannot be a <hi rend="italic">primary</hi> quality, ſince it can be increaſed to a great degree by heat, and diminiſhed by cold : but it is impoſſible that a <hi rend="italic">primary</hi> quality ol matter can be increaſed or diminiſhed by any external circumſtances whatever; for whatever property depends upon external circumftances, is not a primary but a ſe-condary one.—The repulſion of electrified bodies is explained under the article Electricity : that of others ⅛ leſs ſubject to inveſtigation ; and the moſt that can be ſaid concerning it is, that in many caſes it ſeems to ■be the conſequence of a modi; cation ot dire, and in others of electricity.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>