<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0092-09"
                facs="gri_33125011196389_0098.tif" type="entry">

                <p><label>RESISTANCE</label> or <hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps"> Resisting</hi></hi> <hi rend="italic">Force,</hi> in philoſophy, denotes, in general,- any power
                    which acts in an oppofite direction to another, ſo as to deſtroy or diminiſh its
                    effect. See Mechanics, Hydrostatics, and Pneumatics.</p>
                <p>Gf all the refiſtances of bodies to each, there is undoubtedly noue of greater
                    importance than the refiſtance or reaction of fluids. It is here that we muſt
                    look for a theory of naval architecture,, for the impulſe of the air is our
                    moving power, and this muſt be modified ſo as to produce every motion we want by
                    the form and diſpofition of our fails ; and it is the refiſtance of the water
                    which muſt be overcome, that the ſhip may proceed in her courſe ; and this muſt
                    alſo be modified to our purpoſe, that the ſhip may not drive like a log to
                    leeward, but on ∣he contrary may ply to windward, that ſhe may anſwer her helm
                    briſkly, and that ſhe may be eaſy in all her motions on the ſurface of the
                    troubled ocean. The im-pulſe of wind and water makes them ready and
                    inde-fatigable ſervants in a thouſand ſhapes for driving our machines ; and we
                    ſhould lofe much of their ſervice did we remain ignorant of the laws of their
                    action : they would ſometimes become terrible maſters, if we did not fall upon
                    methods of eluding or ſoftening their attacks.</p>
                <p>we cannot refuſe the ancients a confiderable knowledge of this ſnbject. It was
                    equally intereſting to them as to us ; and we cannot read the accounts of the
                    naval exertions of Phoenicia, Carthage, and of Rome, exertions which have not
                    been ſurpaffed hy any thing of modern date, without believing that they
                    poffeffed much practical and experimental knowledge of this ſubject. It was not,
                    perhaps, poffeffed by them in a ſtrict and ſyftematic form, as it is now taught
                    by our mathema-ticians; but the maſter-builders, in their dockyards, did
                    undoubtedly exerciſe their genius in comparing the forms of their ſtneſt ſhips,
                    and in. marking thoſe circumſtances of form and dimenſton which were <hi
                        rend="italic"> in fa£t</hi> accompanied with the deſirable properties of a
                    ſhip, and thus framing to themſelves maxims of naval architecture in the fame
                    xnanncr as we do now. For we</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0093" facs="gri_33125011196389_0099.tif"/>
                <p>peheve that eur naval architects are not diflpoſed to grant that they have
                    profited much by all the labours of the mathematicians. But the ancients had not
                    made any great progreſs in the phyſicomathematical ſciences, which conſiſt
                    chiefly in the application of calculus to the phenomena of nature. In this
                    branch they could make none, becaufe they had not the means of inveſtigation. A
                    knowledge of the motions and actions of fluids is acceſſible only to thoſe who
                    are familiarly acquainted with the fluχionary mathematics; and with-out this key
                    there is no admittance. Even when poffeffed of this guide, our progreſs has been
                    very flow, heſitating, and devious ; and we have not yet been able to eſtabliſti
                    any ſet of doctrines which are ſuſceptible of an eafy and confident application
                    to the arts of life. If we have advanced farther than the ancients, it is
                    becauſe we have come after them, and have proſited by their labours, and even by
                    their miſtakes.</p>
                <p>Sir Ifaac Newton was the firſt (as far as we can recollect) who attempted to
                    make the motions and ac-tions of fluids the ſubject of mathematical diſcuſſion.
                    Ηe had invented the method of fluxions long before he engaged in his phyfical
                    reſearches ; and he proceeded in theſe <hi rend="italic">ſua mαthfi facem
                        pr¢ſerente.</hi> Yet even with this guide he was often obliged to grope his
                    way, and to try various bye-paths, in the hopes of obtaining a legitimate
                    theory. Having exerted all his powers in eſtabliſhing a theory of the lunar
                    motions, he was obliged to reſt contented with an approximation inſtead oſ a
                    perfect folution of the problem which aſcer-tains the motions of three bodies
                    mutually acting on each other. This convinced him that it was in vain to expect
                    an accurate inveſtigation of the motions and actions of fluids, where millions
                    of unfeen particles combine their influence. He therefore caſt about to ſind
                    ſome particular caſe of the problem which would admit of an accurate
                    determination, and at the ſame time furniſh circumftances of analogy or
                    reſemblance ſuſſiciently numerous for giving limiting caſes, which ſhould
                    include between them thoſe other caſes that did not admit of this accurate
                    inveſtigation. And thus, by knowing the limit to which the cafe propoſed did
                    approximate, and the circumſtance which regulated the approximation, many uſeful
                    propoſitions might be deduced for directing us in the application of theſe
                    doc-trines to the arts of life.</p>
                <p>He therefore figured to himſelf a hypothetical collection of matter which
                    poffeffed the characteriſtic pro-perty of fluidity, viz. the <hi rend="italic">quaqudverfum</hi> propagation of preffure, and the moſt perfect
                    intermobility (pardon the uncouth term) of parts, and which formed a phy. ſical
                    whole or aggregate, whoſe parts were connected by mechanical forces, determined
                    both in degree and in direction, and ſuch as rendered the determination of
                    certain important circumſtances of their motion ſuſceptible of preciſe
                    inveſtigation. And he conςluded, that the laws which he ſhould difcover in theſe
                    motions muſt have a great analogy with the laws of the motions of real fluids :
                    And from this hypotheſis he deduced a ſe-rιes of propoiitions, which form the
                    baſis of almoſt all the theories of the impulfe and reſiftance of fluids which
                    have been offered to the public ſince his time.</p>
                <p>It muſt be acknowledged, that the reſults of this theory agree but ill with
                    experiment, and that, <hi rend="italic">in the way in which it has been
                        zealouſly proj'ecuted by ſubſequent mathematicians,</hi> it proceeds on
                    principles or aſſumptions which are not only gratuitous, but even falſe. But it
                    affords ſuch a beautiful appl ication of geometry and calculus, that
                    mathematicians have been as it were faf-cinated by it, and have publiſhed
                    ſyſtems ſo elegant and ſo extenſively applicable, that one cannot help lamenting
                    that the foundation is ſo flimſy. John Bernoulli’s theory, in his differtation
                    on the communica-' tion of motion, and Bouguer’s in his <hi rend="italic">Traité du Navire,</hi> and in his <hi rend="italic">Theoriedu Manœuvre et
                        delà Mâture des k <hi rend="sup">r</hi> aif-feau ∖,</hi> muſt ever be
                    conſidered as among the fineſt ſpecimens of phyſicomathematical ſcience which
                    the world has ſeen. And, with all its imperfections, this theory ſtill furniſhes
                    (as w’as expected by its illuſtrious author) many propoſitions of immenfe
                    practical uſe, they being the limits to which the real phenomena of the impulſe
                    and refiſtance of fluids really approximate. So that when the law by which th'e
                    phenomena deviate from the theory is once determined by a well choſen ſeries of
                    experiments, this hypothetical theory becomes almoſt as valuable as a true one.
                    And we may add, that although Mr d’Alembert, by treading warily in the ſteps oi
                    Sir lſaac Newton in another route, has diſcovered a genuine and unexceptionable
                    theory, the proceſs of inveſtigation is ſo intricate, requiring every fineffe of
                    the moſt abſtruſe analyfis, and the final equations aie ſo complicated, that
                    even their moſt expert author has not been able to deduce more than one-fimple
                    propofition (which too was diſcovered by Daniel Bernoulli by a more fimple
                    proceſs) which can be applied to any uſe. The hypothetical theory of Newton,
                    therefore, continues to be the groundwork of all our practical knowledge of the
                    ſubject.</p>
                <p>we ſhall therefore lay before our readers a very ſhort view of the theory, and
                    the manner of applying it. we ihall then ſhow its defects (all of which were
                    pointed out by its great author), and give an hiſtorical account of the many
                    attempts which have been made to amend it or to ſubſtitute another: in all which
                    we think it our duty to ſhow, that Sir Iſaac Newton took the lead, and pointed
                    out every path which others have taken, if we except Daniel Bernoulli and
                    d’Alembert ; and we ſhall give an account of the chief ſets of experiments
                    which’ have been made on this important ſubject, in the hopes of eſtabliſhing an
                    empirical theory, which may be employed with confidence in the arts of life.</p>
                <p>we know by experience that force muſt be applied to a body in order that it may
                    move through a fluid, ſuch as air or water ; and that a body projected with any
                    velocity is gradually retarded in its motion, and generally brought to reſt. The
                    analogy of nature makes us imagine that there is a force acting in the oppofite
                    direction, or oppofing the motion, and that this force relides in, or is exerted
                    by, the fluid. And the phenomena referable thoſe which accompany the known
                    refiſtance of active beings, ſuch as animals. Therefore we give to this ſuppoſed
                    force the metaphorical name of Resistance, <hi rend="sup">,</hi> we alſh know
                    that a fluid in-motion will hurry a ſolid body along with the ſtream, and that
                    it requires force to maintain it in its place. A fimilar analogy makes us
                    ſuppoſe that the fluid exerts force, in the ſame manner as when an active being
                    impels the body before him ; therefore we call this the <hi rend="italic">IMPULSION of a Fluid.</hi> And as our knowledge of nature inlorms∙ us that
                    the mutual actions of bodies are in-</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0094" facs="gri_33125011196389_0100.tif"/>
                <p>every caſe equal and oppoſite, and that the obſerved change of motion is the
                    only indication, characteriſtic, and meaſure, of the changing force, the forces
                    are the ſame (whether we call them impulſions or reſiſtances) when the relative
                    motions are the ſame, and therefore depend entirely on theſe relative motions.
                    The force, therefore, which is neceffary for keeping a body immoveable in a
                    ſtream of water, flowing with a certain velocity, is the ſame with what is
                    required for moving this body with this velocity through ſtagnant water. To auy
                    one who admits the motion of the earth round the fun, it is evident that we can
                    neither obſerve nor reaſon from a caſe of a body moving through ſtill water, nor
                    of a ſtream of water preſſing upon or impelling a quieſcent body.</p>
                <p>A body in motion appears to be reſiſted by a ſtagnant fluid, becauſe it is a law
                    of mechanical nature that force muſt be employed in order to put any body in
                    motion. Now the body cannot move forward without putting the contiguous fluid in
                    motion, and force muſt be employed for producing this motion. In like manner, a
                    quieſcent body is impelled by a ſtream of fluid, becauſe the motion oſ the
                    contiguous fluid is diminiſhed by this ſolid obſtacle ; the reſiſtance,
                    therefore, or impnlſe, no way differs from the ordinary communica-tions of
                    motion among ſolid bodies.</p>
                <p>Sir Iſaac Newton, therefore, begins his theory of the reſiſtance and impulſe of
                    fluids, by ſelecting a cale where, although he cannot pretend to aſcertain the
                    motions themſelves which are produced iu the particles of a contiguous ſtuid, he
                    can tell preciſely their mutual ra-tios.</p>
                <p>He ſuppoſes two ſyſtems oſ bodies ſuch, that each body oſ the firſt is fimilar
                    to a correſponding body of the ſecond, and that each is to each in a conſtant
                    ratio. He alſo ſuppoſes them to be limilarly iituated, that is, at the angles oſ
                    fimilar figures, and that the homologous lines of theſe figures are in the ſame
                    ratio with the dia-meters of the bodies. He farther ſuppoſes, that they attract
                    or repel each other in fimilar directions, and that the accelerating connecting
                    forces are aſſo propor-tional ; that is, the forces in the one ſyſtem are to the
                    correſponding forces in tne other ſyſtem in a eonſtant ra^ tio, and that, in
                    each ſyſtem taken apart, the forces are as the ſquares of the velocities
                    directly, and as the dia-meters of the correfponding bodies, or their diſtances,
                    inverſely.</p>
                <p>This being the, caſe, it legitimately follows, that if fimilar parts-of the two
                    ſyſtems are put into fimilar mo-tions, in any given inſtant, they will <hi
                        rend="italic"> continue</hi> to move fimilarly, each correſpondent body
                    deſcribing fimilar curves, with proportional velocities : For the bodies be-ing
                    fimilarly fituated,the forces which act on a body in one fyſtem, arifing from
                    the combination of any number of adjoining particles, will have the ſame
                    direction with the force acting on the coι reſponding body in the other ſyſtem,
                    arifing from the combined action of the ſimilar and fimilarly directed forces of
                    the adjoining correſpon-. dent bodies of the other ſyſtem ; and theſe compound
                    forces will have the ſame ratio with the ſimple forces which conſtitute them,
                    and will be as the fquares of the velocities directly, and as the diſtances, or
                    any homologous lines inverſely ; and therefore the chords of curvature, having
                    the direction of the centripetal or centrifugal forces, and fimilarly inclined
                    to the tangents</p>
                <p>of the curves defcribed by the correfponding bodies, will have the ſame ratio
                    with the diſtances of the pan tides. The curves deſcribed by the correſponding
                    bodies will therefore be ſimilar, the velocities will be propor-tional, and the
                    bodies will be ſimilarly ſttuated at the end of the firſt moment, and expofed to
                    the action of ſimilar and fimilarly fituated centripetal or centrifugal forces;
                    and this will again produce fimilar motions during the next moment, and fo on
                    for ever. All this is evident to any perſon acquainted with the elementary
                    doctrines of curvilineal motions, as delivered in the theory of phyfical
                    aſtronomy.</p>
                <p>From this fundamental propofition, it clearly follows, that if two ſimilar
                    bodies, having their homologous lines proportional to thoſe of the two ſyſtems,
                    be fimi-larly projected among the bodies of thoſe two ſyſterirs with any
                    velocities, they will produce fimilar.motions in the two ſyſtems, and will
                    themſelves continue to move fimilarly ; and therefore will, in every ſubſequent
                    moment, ſuffer fimilar diminutions or retardations. If the initial velocities of
                    projection be the ſame, but the denfities of the two ſyſtems, that is, the
                    quantities of matter con-tained in an equal bulk or extent, be different, it is
                    evi-dent that the quantities of motion produced in the two ſyſtems in the ſame
                    time will be proportional to the denſities ; and if the denſities are the ſame,
                    and uniform in each ſyſtem, the quantities of motion produced will be as the
                    ſquares of the velocities, becaufe the motion communicated to each correfponding
                    body will be pro-portional to the velocity communicated, that is, to the
                    velocity of the impelling body ; and the number of ſimilarly fituated particles
                    which will be agitated will aſſo be proportional to. this velocity. Therefore,
                    the whole quantities of motion produced in the fame moment of time will be
                    proportional to the ſquares of the velocities. And laſtly, if the denſtties of
                    the two ſyſtems are uniform, or the ſame through the whole extent of the
                    ſyſtems, the number of particles impelled by fimilar bodies will be as the
                    ſurfaces of theſe bodies.</p>
                <p>Now the diminutions of the motions of the projected bodies are (by Newton’s
                    third law of motion) equal to the motions produced in the ſyſtems; and theſe
                    diminu-tions are the meaſures of what are called the reſtſtances oppofed to the
                    motions of the projected bodies. Therefore, combining all theſe circumſtances,
                    the refiſtances are proportional to the fimilar ſurfaces of the moving bodies,
                    to the denſities of the ſyſtems through which the motions are performed, and to
                    the fquares of the velocities, jointly.</p>
                <p>we cannot form to ourſelves auy diſtinct notion of a fluid, otherwiſe than as a
                    ſyſtem of ſmall bodies, or a collection of particles, ſimilarly or ſymmetrically
                    arranged, the centres of each being fituated in the angles of regular folids. We
                    muſt form this notion of it, whether we ſuppoſc, with the vulgar, that the
                    particles are little globules in mutual contact, or, with the partiſans of
                    corpufcular attractions and repulfιons, we ſuppoſe the particles kept at a
                    diſtance from each other by means of theſe attractions and repιdfions mutually
                    balancing each other. In this laſt caſe, no other arrangement is confiſtent with
                    a quielcent equilibrium : and in this caſe, it is evident, from the theory of
                    curvilineal motions, that the agitations of the particles will always be ſuch,
                    that the connecting forces, in actual exertion,</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0095" facs="gri_33125011196389_0101.tif"/>
                <p>will be proportional to the fquares of the velocities directly, and to the
                    chords of curvature haviag the direc-tion of the forces inverſely.</p>
                <p>From theſe premiſes, therefore, we deduce, jit the ſtricteſt manner, the
                    demonſtration of the leading theo- <hi rend="sub">r</hi> em of the reſiſtance
                    and impulfe of fluids ; namely,</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">cîProp. I. The refiſtances, and (by the third law of
                        motion), the impulſions of fluids on ſimilar bodies, are proportional to the
                        ſurfaces of the ſolid bodies, to the denſities of the fluids, and to the
                        fquaιes of the velocities, jointly.</hi></p>
                <p>We muſt now obferve, that when we ſuppofe the par-ticles of the fluid to be in
                    mutual contact, we may ei-ther fuppoſe them elaſtic or unelaſtic. The motion
                    communicated to the collection of elaſtic particles muſt be double of what the
                    ſame body, moving in the ſame manner, would communicate to the particles of an
                    unelaſtic fluid. The impnlſe and reſiſtance of elaſtic fluids muſt therefore be
                    double of thoſe of unelaſtic fluids.— But we muſt caution our readers not to
                    judge of the elaſticity oſ fluids by their ſenfible compreffibility. A diamond
                    is incomparably more elaſtic than the ſineſt football, though not compreſſible
                    in any fenfible degree.— It remains to be decided, by well choſen experiments,
                    whether water be not as elaſtic as air. If we ſuppoſe, with Boſcovich, the
                    particles of perfect fluids to be at a diſtance from each other, we ſſiall find
                    it difficult to conceive a fluid void of elafticity. we hope that the theory of
                    their impulſe and reſtſtance wiſl l'uggeſt experiments which wiſl decide this
                    queſtion, by pointing out what ought to be the abſolute impulſe or reiiſtance in
                    either caſe. And thus the fundamental propoſttion of the impulſe and reſiſtance
                    of fluids, taken in its pro-per meaning, is ſufceptible of a rigid
                    demonſtration, re-lative to the only diſtinct notion that we can form of the
                    internal conſtitution of a fluid. We lay, <hi rend="italic">taken in its proper
                        meaning ;</hi> namely, that the impulſe or refiſtance of fluids is a
                    preffure, oppoſed and meaſured by another preffure, ſuch as a pound weight, the
                    force of a ſpring, the preffure of the atmoſphere, and the like. And we
                    apprehend that it would he very difficult to find any legitimate demonftration
                    of this leading propoſttion different from this, which we have now borrowed from
                    Sir lſaac Newton, Prop. 23,. B. II. <hi rend="italic">Princip. We</hi> ac-knowledge that it is prolix and even circuitous : but in all the-attempts
                    made by his commentators and their copyiſts to ſimplify it, we ſee great defects
                    of logical argument, or affumption of principles, which are not only gratuitous,
                    but inadmiſſible. we ſſiall have occa-ſion, as we proceed, to point out ſome of
                    thefe defects ; and doubt not but the illuſtrious author of this demon-ſtration
                    hadexercifed his uncommon patience and ſagacity in ſimilar attempts, and was
                    diffatisſied with them aſl.</p>
                <p>Before we proceed further, it vyill be proper to rn&gt;ke a general remark,
                    which wiſl fave a great deal of diſcuſſion. Since it is a matter of univerfal
                    experience, that every action of a body on others is accompanied by an equal and
                    contrary re-action ; and ſince all that we can demonſtrate concerning the
                    reſiſtance of bodies during their motions through fluids proceeds on this
                    ſup-poſition, (the reſiſtance of ∣the body being <hi rend="italic">ajfumed</hi> as equal and oppoſite to the ſum of motions communicated to the particles
                    of the fluid, eſtimated in the direction of the bodies motion), we are intitled
                    to proceed in the contrary ordfer, and to conſider the impulſions which each of
                    the particles of fluid exerts on the body at reſt, as equal and oppofite to the
                    motion which the body would communicate to that particle if the fluid were at
                    reſt, and the body were moving equaſly ſwift in the oppoſite direction. And
                    therefore the whole impulſion of the fluid muſt be conceived as the meaſure of
                    the whole motion which the body would thus communicate to the fluid. It muſt
                    therefore be alſo conſidered as themeaſurcof the reſiſtance which the body,
                    moving wiſh the ſame velocity, would ſuſtain from the fluid, when, therefore, we
                    ſſiall demonſtrate any thing concerning the impulſion of a fluid, eſtimated in
                    the direction of its motion, we muſt conſider it as demonſtrated concerning the
                    refift= ance of a quieſcent fluid to the motion of that body, having the ſame
                    velocity in the oppoſite direction. The determination of theſe impulſions being
                    much eaſier than the determination of the motions communicated by the body to
                    the particles oſ the ſiuid, this method wiſl be followed in moſt of the
                    ſubſequent diſcuſſions.</p>
                <p>Tlie general propofition already delivered is by no means ſuſſicient for
                    explaining the various important phenomena obſerved in the mutual actions oſ
                    ſolids and fluids. In particular, it gives us no aſſiſtance in aſcer-tainſhg ſhe
                    modifications of this reſtſtance or impulfe, which depend on the ſhape of ſhe
                    body and the ineli-nation of its impelled or reſiſted ſurface to the direction
                    of the motion. Sir Iſaac Newton found another hypothefis neceffary ; namely,
                    that the ſtuid ſhould be ſo extremely rare that the diſtance of the particles
                    may be incomparably greater than their diameters. This addi-tional condition is
                    neceſſary for conſidering their actions as ſo many ſeparate codifions or
                    impuliι&lt;ans on the ſolid body. Each particle mnſt be ſuppoſed to have
                    abundant room to rebound, or otherwiſe eſcape, after having made its ſtroke,
                    without ſenfibly affecting the ſituations and motions of the particles which
                    have not yet made their ftroke : and the motion mnſt be ſo ſwiſt as not to give
                    time for the ſenſible exertion of their mutual forces of attractions and
                    repulſions.</p>
                <p>Keeping theſe conditions in mind, we may proceed to determine the impuliions
                    made by a fluid on ſurfaces of every kind : And the mo⅛ convenient method to
                    purſue in this determination, is to compare them all either with the inιpulfε
                    which the <hi rend="italic">fame Jurfiqce</hi> would receive from the fluid
                    impinging on it perpendicularly, or with the impulſe which the <hi rend="italic"
                        > fame fiream of fiuid</hi> would, make when coming perpendicularly on a
                    ſurface of ſuch extent as to occupy the whole ſtream.</p>
                <p>It will greatly abbreviate-language, if we make uſe of a few terms in an
                    appropriated ſenſe.</p>
                <p>By <hi rend="italic">3. fiream,</hi> we ſhall mean a quantity of ſiuid moving
                    in one direction, that is, each particle moving in paral-lel lines ; and the <hi
                        rend="italic"> breadth</hi> of the ſtream is a line perpen-dicular to all
                    theſe parallels.</p>
                <p>A <hi rend="italic">filament</hi> means a portion of this ſtream of very ſmall
                    breadth, and it conſiſts of an indefinite number of particles following one
                    another in the ſame direction, and ſucceſſively impinging on, or gliding
                    alom&gt;-, the ſurface of the ſolid body.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">baſe</hi> of any lurface'expofed to a. ſtream of ſiuid,
                    is that portion of a plane perpendicular to the ſtream, which is covered or
                    protected from the action of the ſtream by the furface expofed to its impulſe.
                    Thus the baſe of a ſphere expofed to a ſtream of fluid is its great</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0096" facs="gri_33125011196389_0102.tif"/>
                <p>circle, whoſe plane is perpendicular to th¢ ftτeam. If BC (fig. I.) be a plane
                    ſurface expofed to the action of a ſtream of ſtuid, moving in the direction DC,
                    then BR, or SE, perpendicular to DC, is its baſe.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Direct impulſe</hi> ſhall expreſs the energy or action of
                    the particle or filament, or ſtream of fluid, when meeting the ſurface
                    perpendicularly, or when tlie furface is perpendicular to the direction of the
                    ſtream.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Abſolute impu/ſe</hi> means the actual preffure on the
                    impelled ſurface, arifing from the action of the fluid, whether ſtriking the
                    ſurface perpendicularly or obliquely ; or it is the force impreffed on the
                    ſurface, or tendency to motion which it acquires, and which muſt be oppoled by
                    an equal force in the oppoſite direction, in order that the ſurface may be
                    maintained in its place. It is of importance to keep in mind, that this preffure
                    is always perpendicular to the ſurfacc. It is a propoſttion found-ed on
                    univerſal and uncontradicted experience, that the mutual actions of bodies on
                    each other are always exerted in a direction perpendicular to the touching
                    fur-faces. Thus, it is obferved, that when a billiard ball A is ſtruck by
                    another B, moving in any direction what-ever, the ball A always moves off in the
                    direction perpendicular to the plane which touches the two balls in the point of
                    mutual contact, or point of impulſe. This inductive propoſition is fupported by
                    every argument which can be drawn from what we know concerning the forces which
                    connect the particles of matter together, and are the immediate cauſes of the
                    communication of motion. It would employ much time and room to ſtate them here ;
                    and we apprehend that it is unneceffary : for no reaſon can be aſſigned why the
                    preffure ſhould be in <hi rend="italic">any particular</hi> oblique direction.
                    If any one ſhould ſay that the impulſe will be in the direction of the ſtream,
                    we have only to deſire him to take notice of the effect of the rudder of a ſhip.
                    This ſhows that the impulſe <hi rend="italic">is not in the direction of the
                        fir earn,</hi> and is therefore in ſome direction tranſverſe to the
                    ftream.— He will alſo find, that when a plane ſurface is impelled obliquely by a
                    fluid, there is no direction in which it can be ſupported but the direction
                    perpendicular to it-ſelf. It is quite ſafe, in the mean time, to take it as an
                    experimental truth, we may, perhaps, in ſome other part of this work, give what
                    will be received as a rigorous demonſtration.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Relative or effective impulſe</hi> means the preffure on the
                    ſurface eſtimated in ſome particular direction. Thus BC (fig. i.) may repreſent
                    the ſail of a ſhip, impelled by the wind blowing in the direction DC. G Ο may be
                    the direction of the ſhip’s keel, or the line of her courſe. The wind ſtrikes
                    the ſail in the direction GH parallel to DC ; the ſail is urged or preffed in
                    the di-rection GI, perpendicular to BC. But we are intereſted to know what
                    tendency this will give the ſhip to move in the direction GO. This is the
                    effective or relative impulſe. Ογ BC may be the tranſverfe ſection of the ſail
                    of a common wind-mill. This, by the conſtruction of the machine, can move only
                    in the direction GP, perpendicular to the direction of the wind ; and it is only
                    in this direction that the impulſe produces the deſired effect. Ογ BC may be
                    half of the prow of a punt or lighter, riding at anchor by means of the cable '
                    DC, attached to the prow C. In this caſe, GfiL. pa-rallel to DC, is that part of
                    the abſolute impulfe which <hi rend="italic">is</hi> employed in ſtraining the
                    cable.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">angle of incidence</hi> is the angle F G C contained
                    between the direction of the ſtream FG and the plane BC.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">angle oſ obliquity</hi> is the angle OGC contained
                    between the plane and the direction GO, in which we wiſh to eſtimate the
                    impulſe.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Prop. II. The direct impulfe of a fluid on a plane
                        ſurface, is to its abſolute oblique impulſe on the ſame furface, as the
                        ſquare of the radius to the ſquare of the fine of the angle of incidence.</hi></p>
                <p>Let a ſtream of fluid, moving in the direction DC,</p>
                <p>(fig. ι.), act on the plane BC. with the radius CB deſcribe the quadrant ABE ;
                    draw CA perpendicular to CE, and draw MN BS parallel to CE. Let t,he particle E,
                    moving in the direction FG, meet the plane in G, and in F G produced take GH to
                    reprefent the magnitude of the direct impulſe, or the impulſe which the particle
                    would exert on the plane AC, by meeting it in V. Draw GI and HR perpendicular to
                    BC, and HI perpendicular to G I. Alſo draw BR perpendicular to DC.</p>
                <p>The force GH is equivalent to the two forces GI and GK ; and GK being in the
                    direction of the plane has no ſhare in the impnlſe. The abſolute impulſe,
                    therefore, is reprefeπted by GI ; the angle GHI is equal to FGC, the angle of
                    incidence; and there·» fore GH is to GI as radius - to the fine of the angle of
                    incidence : Therefore the direct impulſe of each particle or filament is to its
                    abſolute ob-lique impulſe as radius to the fine of the angle of inci-dence. But
                    further, the number of particles or filaments which ſtrike the ſurface AC, is to
                    the number of thoſe which ſtrike the ſurſhce B C as A C to NC : for all the
                    filaments between LA and MB go paſt the ob-lique furface BC without ſtriking it.
                    But BC : NC≈ rad. : fin. NBC, = rad. : fin. FGC, = rad. : fin. incidence. Now
                    the whole impulſe is as the impulſe of each filament, and as the number of
                    filaments exerting equal impulſes jointly ; therefore the whole direct im-pulſe
                    on AC is to the whole abſolute impulſe on BC, as the ſquare of radius to the
                    ſquare of the fine of the angle of incidence.</p>
                <p>Let S expreſs the extent of the ſurface, <hi rend="italic">i</hi> the angle of
                    incidence, <hi rend="italic">o</hi> the angle of obliquity, <hi rend="italic">v</hi> the velocity of the fluid, and <hi rend="italic">d</hi> its
                    denfity. Let F repreſent the direct impulſe, <hi rend="italic">f</hi> the
                    abſolute oblique impulſe, and <hi rend="italic">φ</hi> the relative or
                    effective impulſe : And let the tabular fines and coſines be coniidered as
                    decimal fractions of the radius unity.</p>
                <p>This propofition gives us F : ∕ = R <hi rend="sup">z</hi> : Sin.’ <hi
                        rend="italic"> i, =</hi> ι : Sin.’ <hi rend="italic">i,</hi> and
                    therefore <hi rend="italic">f</hi> = F × Sin.’ z. Alſo, becauſe impulſes are
                    in the proportion of the extent of ſurface fimilarly impelled, we have, in
                    general, ∕= F S X Sind, <hi rend="italic">i.</hi></p>
                <p>The firſt who publiſhed this theorem was Pardies, in his <hi rend="italic">Oeuvres de Mathématique,</hi> in 1673. we., know that Newton had
                    inveſtigated the chief propoſitions of the Principia before 1670.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Prop. III. The direct impulſe on any ſurſace is to the
                        effective oblique impulſe on the ſame ſurface, as the cube of radius to the
                        ſolid, which has for its baſe the ſquare of the fine of incidence, and the
                        fine of obliquity for its height.</hi></p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0097" facs="gri_33125011196389_0103.tif"/>
                <p>For, when GH repreſents the direct impulfe of a particle, GI is the abfolute
                    oblique impulſe, and GO is the effective impulſe in the direction G Ο : Now GI
                    is to GO as radius to the fine of G10, and G10 is the complement of IG0, and is
                    therefore equal to CG0, "the angle of obliquity.</p>
                <p>Therefore <hi rend="italic">f</hi> : &lt;r~R : Sin. 0.</p>
                <p>But F : <hi rend="italic">ſ~</hi> R <hi rend="sup">1</hi> : Sin.*z'</p>
                <p>Therefore F : τ = R <hi rend="sup">3</hi> : Sir∣. <hi rend="sup">,</hi> i ×
                    Sin.0. and</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">'φ</hi> ~F × Sin. <hi rend="sup">5</hi> / × Sin. O.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Cor.—</hi> The direct impulſe on any ſurface is to the
                    effective oblique impiſtfe in the direction of the ftream, as the cube of radius
                    to the cube of the fine of incidence. For draw I Q^and GP perpendicular'to GH,
                    and IP perpendicular to GP ; then the abſolute im-pulſe GI is equivalent to the
                    impulſe GQJ∏ the direc-tion ol the ſtream, and GP, which may be called the
                    tranfverſe impulfe. The angle G I QJs evidently equal to the angle GHI, or FGC,
                    the angle of incidence.</p>
                <p>Therefore ∕ : <hi rend="sub">p</hi> =GI : GQ <hi rend="sub">j</hi> = R :
                    Sin. <hi rend="italic">i.</hi></p>
                <p>"But F : <hi rend="italic">ſ ~</hi> R’ : Sin.’/.</p>
                <p>Therefore F : <hi rend="italic">&lt;P —</hi> R ’ : Sin. <hi rend="sup">3</hi> <hi rend="italic">i.</hi></p>
                <p>And ¢ — F × Sin.’/.</p>
                <p>Before we proceed further, we ſhall conſider the im-pulſe on a ſuiface which is
                    alſo in motion. This is evidently a frequent and an important cafe. It is
                    perhaps the moſt frequent and important : It is the caſe of a ſhip under fail,
                    and of a wind or water-mill at work.</p>
                <p>Tlιerefore, let a ſtream of ſiuid, moving with the direction and velocity DE,
                    meet a plane BC, (fig. I. <hi rend="sup">l</hi> ∙ n <hi rend="sup">o</hi> 2.
                    ), which is moving parallel to itſelf in the direction and with the velocity DF
                    : It is required to determine</p>
                <p>the impulſe ?</p>
                <p>Nothing is more eaſy : The mutual actions of bodies depend on their relative
                    motions only. The motion DE of the fluid relative to BC, which is alſo in
                    motion, is compounded of the real motion of the fluid and the oppofite to the
                    real motion of the body. There-fore produce FD till D ∕~E&gt;F, and complete
                    the pa-'rallelogram D <hi rend="italic">f e</hi> E, and draw the diagonal D <hi rend="italic">e.</hi> The ⅛∏pulfe on the plane is the ſame as if the
                    plane were at reſt, and evcιy particle of the fluid impelled it in the direction
                    and with the velocity D <hi rend="italic">e</hi> ; and may therefore be
                    determined by the foregoing propoſition. This pro-pofition applies to every
                    poſſible caſe ; and we ſhall not beſtow more time on it, but reſerve the
                    important mo-dification of the general propofition for the caſes which ſhall
                    occur in the practical applications of the whole doctrine of the impulſe and
                    refiſtance of fluids.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Prop. IV. The direct impulſe of a ſtream of fluid, whoſe
                        breadth is given, is to its oblique effective impulfe in the direction of
                        the ſtream, as the ſquare of radius to the ſquare of the fine of the angle
                        of incidence.</hi></p>
                <p>For the number of filaments which occupy the ob-lique plane BC, would occupy the
                    portion NC of a perpendicular plane, and therefore we have only to compare the
                    perpendicular impulfe on any point V with the effective impulſe made by the ſame
                    filament FV on the oblique plane at G. Now GH fepreſents the impulſe which this
                    filament would make at V ; and G Q~ is the effective impulſe oſ the ſame
                    filament at G, eſtimated in the direction G H of the ſtream ; and G H is tβ GQ
                    as G H <hi rend="sup">i</hi> to GΣ <hi rend="sup">1</hi> , that is, as rad. <hi rend="sup">i</hi> to fin/fi</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Cor.</hi> I. The effective impulſe in the direction oſ the
                    ſtream on any plane ſurface BC, is to the direct impulfe on its baſe BR or SE,
                    as the ſquare of the fine of the angle of incidence to the fquare of the radius.</p>
                <p>2. If an ifoſceles wedge ACB (fig. 2.) be expofed to a ſtream of fluid moving in
                    the direction of its 'height CD, the impulſe on the fides is to the direct
                    impulfe on the baſe as the ſquare of half the bafe AD to the ſquare of the fide
                    AC, or as the fquare of the fine of half the angle of the wedge to the ſquare of
                    the radius. For it is evident, that in this caſe the two tranſverſe impulſes,
                    ſuch as GP in fig. ι, balance each other, and the only impulſe which can be
                    obferved is the ſum of the two impulfes, luch as GQjff ſig. ι, which are to be
                    compared with the impulſes on the two halves AD, DB of the baſe. Now AC : AB ≈
                    rad. : fin. ACD, and ACD is equal to the angle of incidence.</p>
                <p>Therefore, if the angle ACB is a right angle, and ACD is half a right angle, the
                    ſquare of AC is twice the ſquare of AD, ’ and the impulſe on the ſides of a
                    rectangular wedge is half the impulſe on its baſe.</p>
                <p>Alſo, if a cube ACBE (ſig. 3.) be expofed to a ſtream moving in a direction
                    perpendicular to one of its ſides, and then to a ſtream moving in a direction
                    perpendicular to one of its diagonal planes, the impulſe in the ſirſt caſe will
                    be to the irapulſe in the ſecond as */ ?, to i. Call the perpendicular impulſe
                    on a ſide F, and the perpendicular impulſe on its diagonal plane <hi
                        rend="italic"> f <hi rend="sub">t</hi></hi> and the effective oblique impulſe on its ſides <hi rend="italic">&lt;p</hi> ;—we have</p>
                <p>F :/= AC : AB ≈ 1 : V <hi rend="sup">z</hi> 2, and</p>
                <p>/: f = AChAD <hi rend="sup">,</hi> = 2:1. Therefore</p>
                <p>E : ;&gt; — 2 : √ <hi rend="sup">,</hi> 2, = √2 : 1, or</p>
                <p>very nearly as 10 to 7.</p>
                <p>The ſame reaſoning will apply to a pyramid whoſe baſe is a regular polygon, and
                    whofe axis is perpendicu-lar to the bafe. If ſuch a pyramid is expofed to a
                    ſtream of fluid moving in the direction of the axis, the direct impulſe on the
                    baſe is to the effective impulſe on the pyramid, as the ſquare of the radius to
                    the fquare of the fine of the angle which the axis makes with the ſides of the
                    pyramid. *</p>
                <p>And, in like manner, the direct impulſion on the baſe of a right cone is to the
                    effective impulſion on the conical ſurface, as the ſquare of the radius to the
                    ſquare of the fine of half the angle at the vertex of the cone. This is
                    demonitrated, by ſuppoſing the cone to be a pyramid of an infinite number of
                    ſides.</p>
                <p>we may in this manner compare the impulſe on any polygonal ſurface with the
                    impulſe on its baſe, by comparing apart the impulſes on each plane with thoſe in
                    their correfponding bales, and taking their ſum.</p>
                <p>And we may compare the impulſe on a curved fur-face with that on its baſe, by
                    reſolving the curved ſurface into, elementary planes, each of which is impelled
                    by an elementary filament of the ftream.</p>
                <p>The following beautiful propofition, given by Le Seur and Jaquier, in their
                    Commentary on the ſecond Book of Newton’s Principia, with a few examples of its
                    application, will ſuſſice for any further account of this theory.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Prop.</hi> V.—Let ADB (fig. 4.) be the ſection of a
                    ſurface of fimple curvature, ſuch as is the fnrface of a cylinder. Let this be
                    expofed to the action of a ſtuid moving in the direction AC. Let BC be the</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0098" facs="gri_33125011196389_0104.tif"/>
                <p>fecti¢n of the plane (which we have ealled its baſe), perpendicular to the
                    direction of the ſtream. In AC produced, take any leαgth CG; and on CG deſcribe
                    the ſemicircle CHG, and complete the rectangle BCGO. Through any point p of the
                    curve draw ED parallel to AC, and meeting BC and Ο G in Q_ and P- Let DF touch
                    the curve in D, and draw the chord GH parallel to DF, aud HKM perpendi-cular to
                    CG, meeting ED in M. Suppoſe this to be done for every point of the curve ADB,
                    and let LMN be the curve which paffes through all the points of interſection of
                    the parallels EDP and the correſponding perpendiculars HKM.</p>
                <p>The effective impulſe on the curve furface ADB in the direction of the ſtream,
                    is to its direct impnlſe on the baſe BC as the area BCNL is to the rectangle
                    BCGO.</p>
                <p>Draw <hi rend="italic">edqτnp</hi> parallel to EP and extremely near it. The
                    arch D <hi rend="italic">d</hi> of the curve may be conceived as the ſection
                    of an elementary plane, having the pofitioπ of the tangent DF. The angle EDF is
                    the angle of in-cidence of the filament ED <hi rend="italic">d e.</hi> T his
                    is equal to COH, becaufe ED, DF, are parallel to CG, GH ; and (be-caufe CHG is a
                    ſemicircle) CH is perpendicular to GH. Aſſo CG : CH = CH : CK, and CG : CK ==
                    CG’ : CH <hi rend="sup">2</hi> , = rad. <hi rend="sup">1</hi> : find, CGH,
                    =rad. <hi rend="sup">i</hi> : find in-cid. Therefore if CG, or its equal DP,
                    repreſent the direct impulſe on the point Q^of tlie baſe, CK, or its equal QM,
                    will repreſent the effective iιnpulfe on the point D of the curve. And thus, Q y
                    ∕&gt; P will repreſent the direct impulſe of the filament on the element Q 7
                    of the baſe, and Qjr <hi rend="italic">m</hi> M will repreſent the effective
                    impulſe of the ſame ſilament on the element D <hi rend="italic">d</hi> of the
                    curve. Aud, as this is true of the whole curve ADB, the effective impulſe on the
                    whole curve will be repreſented by the area BCNML ; and the direct impulſe on
                    the baſe will be repreſented by the rectangle BCGO; and therefore the impulſe on
                    the curve-furface is to the impulſe on the baſe as the area BLMNC is to the
                    rectangle BOGC.</p>
                <p>It is plain, from the conftruction, that if the tangent to the curve at A is
                    perpendicular to AC, the point N will coincide with G. Alſo, if the tangent to
                    the curve at B is parallel to AC, the point L will coincide with B.</p>
                <p>whenever, therefore, the curve ADB is fuch that an equation can be had to
                    exhibit the general relation between the abſciffa AR and the ordinate DR, we
                    ihall deduce an equation which exhibits the relation between the abfciſs CK and
                    the ordinate KM of the curve LMN ; and this will give us the ratio of BLNC to
                    BOGC.</p>
                <p>Thus, if the ſurface is that of a cylinder, fo that the curve BDA <hi
                        rend="italic"> b</hi> (fig. 5.), which receives the impulſe of the fluid,
                    is a ſemicircle, make CG equal to AC, and conftruct the figure as before. The
                    curve BMG is a parabola, whoſe axis is CG, whoſe vertex is G, and whoſe
                    parameter is equal to CG. For it is plain, that CG = DC, and GH = <hi
                        rend="smallcaps"> CQ <hi rend="sub">λ</hi> = MK.</hi> And CG × GK = GH <hi rend="sup">2</hi> — KM <hi rend="sup">3</hi> . That is, the curve is
                    ſueh, that the ſquare of the ordinate KM is equal to the rectangle of the
                    abſciffa GK arfd a conftant line GC; and it is.there-fore a parabola whoſe
                    vertex is G. Now, jt iβ well</p>
                <p>known, that the parabolic area BMGC is two thirds of the parallelogram BCGO.
                    Therefore the impull'e on the quadrant ADB is two thirds of the impulfe on the
                    baſe BC. The ſame may bc faid of the quadrant <hi rend="italic">fodb</hi> and
                    its baſe <hi rend="italic">c b.</hi> Therefore, <hi rend="italic">The impulſe
                        on</hi> α <hi rend="italic">cylinder or half cylinder is t wo thirds of
                        the direct impulfe on its tranfverſe plane through the axis ;</hi> or it is
                    two thirds of the direct impulſe on one ſide of a parallelopiped of the ſame
                    breadth and height.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Pk,op.</hi> VI,—If the body be a ſolid generated by the
                    revolution of the figure BDAC (ſig. 4.) round the axis AC ; and if it be expoi¢d
                    to the action of a ſtream <hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps"> q(</hi></hi> ſiuid moving in the direction of the axis AC; then the effective impulſe
                    in the direction of the ſtream is to the direct impulſe on its baſe, as the
                    ſolid generated by the revolution of the figure BLMNC round the axis CN to the
                    cylinder generated by th¢ revolution of the rectangle BOGC.</p>
                <p>This ſcarcely needs â demonſtration. The figure</p>
                <p>ADBLMNA is a ſection of theſe folids by a plane paſſing through the axis ; and
                    what has been demon-ſtrated of this ſection is true of every other, becauſe they
                    are all equal and ſimilar. It 15 therefore true of the whole ſolids, and (their
                    baſe) the circle generated by the revolution of BC round the axis AC.</p>
                <p>Hence we eaſily deduce, that <hi rend="italic">The impulfe on a ſphere is one
                        half of the direct impulſe on its great circle, or on the bafe of a cylinder
                        of equal diameter.</hi></p>
                <p>For in this caſe the curve BMN (ſig. 5.) which generates the ſolid expreſſiug
                    the impulſe on the ſphere is a parabola, and the ſolid is a parabolic conoid.
                    Now this conoid is to the cylinder generated by the revolution of the rectangle
                    BOGC round the axis CG, as the film of all the circles generated by the
                    revolution of ordinates to the parabola fuch as KM, to the ſum of as many
                    circles generated by the ordinates to the rectangle ſuch as K’ſ; or as the ſum
                    of all the ſquares deſcribed on the ordinates KM to the ſum of as many ſquares
                    deſcribed on the ordinates KT. Draw BG cut-ting MK in S. The ſquare on MK is to
                    the ſquare on BC or TK as the abfcifla GK to the abſciffa GC (by the nature of
                    the parabola), or as SK to BC ; becauſe SK and BCare refpectively equal toGK
                    andGC. 1 herefore the ſum of all the ſquares on ordinates, ſuch as MK, is to the
                    ſum of as many fquares on ordinates, ſuch as TK, as the ſum of all the lines SK
                    to the film of as many lines TK ; that is, as the triangle BGC to the rectangle
                    BOGC ; that is, as one to two : and therefore the impulſe on the ſphere is one
                    half of the direct impulſe on its great circle.</p>
                <p>From the ſame conſtruction we may very eafily deduce a very curious and
                    ſeemingly uſeful truth, that of all conical bodies having the circle whoſe
                    diameter is AB (fig. 2.) for its baſe, and FD for its height, the one which
                    ſuſtains the ſmalleſt impulſe or meets with the ſmalleſt refiſtance is the
                    fruſtum AGHB of a cone ACB ſo conſtructed, that EF being taken equal to ED, EA
                    is equal to EC. This fruſtum, though more capacious than the cone AFB of the
                    ſame height, will be leſs reſiſted.</p>
                <p>Alſo, if the ſolid generated by the revolution of BDAC (ſig. 4.) have its
                    anterior part covered with 3 fruſtum of a cone generated by the lines D <hi
                        rend="italic"> a, a A,</hi></p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0099" facs="gri_33125011196389_0105.tif"/>
                <p>forming <hi rend="italic">the</hi> angle at « of 135 degrees; this ſolid,
                    though more capacious than the included ſolid, will be lefs leſiſted.</p>
                <p>And, from the fame principles, Sir Iſaac Newtcn determined the form of the curve
                    ADB which would generate the ſolid which, of all others of the ſame length and
                    baſ¢, ſhould have the leaſt reſiſtance.</p>
                <p>Theſe are curious and important deductions, but are not introduced here, for
                    reafons which will ſoon ap-pear.</p>
                <p>The reader cannot fail to obſerve, that all that we ⅛tve hitherto delivered on
                    this ſubject, relates to the comparιfon of different impulſes or refinances. we
                    have always compared the oblique impulfions with the direct, and by their
                    intervention we compare the ob-lique impulſions with each other. But it remains
                    to give abſolute meaſures of ſome individual impulſion ; to which, as to an
                    unit, we may refer every other. And as it is by their preſſure that they become
                    uſe-ful or hurtful, and they muſt be oppoſed by other preſſures, it becomes
                    extremely convenient to compare them all with that preſſure with which we are
                    moſt familiarly acquainted, the preſſure of gravity.</p>
                <p>The manner in which the companion is made, is this, when a body advances in a
                    fluid with a known velocity, it puts a known quantity of the fluid into motion
                    (as is fuppoſed) with this velocity ; and this is done in a known time, we have
                    only to examine what weight will put this quantity of fluid into the fume
                    motion, by acting on it during the ſame time. This weight is conceived as equal
                    to the reſiſtance. Thus, let us fuppoſe that a ſtream of water, moving at the
                    rate of eight feet <hi rend="italic">per</hi> ſecond, is perpendicularly
                    obſtructed by a ſquare foot of folid furface held faſt in its place. Conceiving
                    water to act in the manner of the hypothetical fluid now defcribed, and to be
                    without elaſticity, the whole effect is the gradual annihilation of the motion
                    of eight cubic feet of water mo-ving eight feet in a ſecond. And this is done in
                    a ſe-cond of time. It is equivalent to the gradually put-ting eight cubic feet
                    of' water into motion with this velocity ; and doing this by acting uniformly
                    during a fecond. what weight is able to produce this effect ? The weight of
                    eight feet of water, acting du-ring a ſecond on it, will, as is well known, give
                    it the velocity of thirty-two feet <hi rend="italic">per</hi> ſecond ; that
                    is, four times greater. Therefore, the weight of the fourth part of eight cubic
                    feet, that is, the weight of two cubic feet, acting during a ſecond, will do the
                    fame thing, or the weight of a column of water whoſe bafe is a ſquare foot, and
                    whofe height is two feet. This will not only produce this effect in the ſame
                    time with the impulſion of the ſolid body, but it will alſo do it by the fame
                    degrees, as any one will clearly perceive, by at-tending to the gradual
                    acceleration of the mafs of water urged by ∣ of its weight, and comparing this
                    with the gradual production or extinction of motion in the fluid by the progreſs
                    of the reſiſted ſurface.</p>
                <p>Now it is well known that 8 cubic feet of water, by felling one foot, which it
                    will do in one-fourth of a fe-¢ond, will acquire the velocity of eight feet per
                    ſecond by its weight ; therefore the force which produces the feme effect in a
                    whole ſecond is one-fourth of this. This ferce is therefore equal to the weight
                    of a column of</p>
                <p>water, whofe baſe is a ſquare foot, and whoſe height is two feet} that is, twice
                    the height neceffary for acquiring the velocity of the motion by gravity. The
                    con-cluſion is the ſame whatever be the ſurface that is reſiſted, whatever be
                    the fluid that reſiſts, and whatever be the velocity of the motion. In this
                    inductive and fa-miliar manner we learn, that <hi rend="italic">the direct
                        impulfe or rfifi-ance of an unelajlicfiuid on any plane ſurface, is equal to
                        the weight of</hi> <hi rend="italic">a</hi> <hi rend="italic">column of the fiuid having the furface for its bafe, and
                        twice the fall necejfary for acquiring the velocity of the motion for its
                        height :</hi> and if the fluid is conſidered as elaſtic, the impulſe or
                    refiſtance is twice as great. See Newt. <hi rend="italic">Princip.</hi> B. II.
                    prop. 35. and 38.</p>
                <p>It now remains to compare this theory with experi-ment. Many have been made,
                    both by Sir Ifaac Newton and by ſubſequent writers. It is much to be la-mented,
                    that in a matter of fuch importance, both to the philofopher and to the artiſt,
                    there is ſuch a difa-greement in the reſults with each other, we ſliall mention
                    the experiments which ſeem to have been made with the greateſt judgment and
                    care. Thoſe of Sir Iſaac Newton were chiefly made by the oſcillations of
                    pendulums in water, and by the deſcent of balls both in water and in air. Many
                    have been made by Mariotte <hi rend="italic">(Traité de Mouvement des Eaux).</hi> Gravefande has pub-liihed, in his <hi rend="italic">Syfiem of Natural
                        Philoſophy,</hi> experiments made on the reſiſtance or impulſions on ſolids
                    in the midſt of a pipe or canal. They are extremely well con-trived, but are on
                    ſo fmall a ſcale that they are of very little uſe. Daniel Bernoulli, and his
                    pupil Profeffor Krafft, have publiſtied, in the <hi rend="italic">Comment.
                        Acad. PetropοI</hi> experiments on the impulſe of a ſtream or vein of water
                    from an oriſice or tube: Theſe are of great value. The Abbé Boffut has publiihed
                    others of the ſame kind in his <hi rend="italic">Hydrodynamique.</hi> Mr
                    Robins has publiſhed, in life <hi rend="italic">New Principles of Gunnery,</hi> many valuable experiments on the impulſe and reſiſtance of air. The Chev.
                    de Borda, in the <hi rend="italic">Mem. Acad. Paris,</hi> 1763 and 1767, has
                    given experiments on the reſiſtance of air and alſo of water, which are very
                    intereſting. The moſt complete collection of experiments on the reſiſtance of
                    water are thoſe made at the public expence by a committee of the academy of
                    ſciences, conſiſting of the marquis de Condorcet, Mr d’Alembert, Abbe Boffut,
                    and others. The Chev. de Buat, in his <hi rend="italic">Hydraulique,</hi> has
                    publiihed ſome</p>
                <p>moſt curious and valuable experiments, where many im-portant circumftances are
                    taken notice of, which had never been attended to before, and which give a view
                    of the ſubject totally different from what is uſually ta-ken of it. Don George
                    d’Ulloa, in his <hi rend="italic">Examine Ma-ritimo,</hi> has alſo given ſome
                    important experiments, ſimilar to thoſe adduced by Bougeur in his <hi
                        rend="italic"> Manœuvre des Vaiffeaux,</hi> but leading to very different
                    concluſions. All theſe ihould be conſulted by ſuch as would acquire a practical
                    knowledge of this ſubject. we muſt content ourſelves with giving their moſt
                    general and ſteady re-ſults. Such as,</p>
                <p>I. It is very conſonant to experiment that the reſiſtances are proportional to
                    the ſquares of the velocities, when the velocities of water do not exceed a few
                    feet per ſecond, no ſenſible deviation is obferved. In very ſmall velocities the
                    reſiſtances are fenſibly greater than in this proportion, and this exceſs is
                    plainly owing to the viſcidity or imperfect fluidity of water. Sir Iſaac</p>
                <p>N a</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0100" facs="gri_33125011196389_0106.tif"/>
                <p>Newton has ſhown that the reſiſtance ariſing from this cauſe is conſtant, or the
                    ſame in every velocity ; and when he has taken off a certain part of the total
                    reſiſt-ance, he found the remainder was very exactly proportionable to the
                    ſquare of the velocity. His experiments to this purpoſe were made with balls a
                    very little heavier than water, ſo as to deſcend very flowly ; and they were
                    made with his uſual care and accuracy, and may be depended on.</p>
                <p>In the expcriments made with bodies floating on the ſurface of water, there is
                    an addition to the reſiſtance ariſing from the inertia of the water. The water
                    heaps up a little on the anterior ſurface of the floating body, and is depreffed
                    behind it. Hence ariſes a hydroſtatical preffure, acting in concert with the
                    true reſiſtance. A ſimilar thing is obſerved in the reſiſtance of air, which is
                    condenſed before the body and rarefied behind it, and thus an additional
                    refiſtance is produced by. the unbalanced elaſticity of the air ; and alſo
                    becauſe the air, which is <hi rend="italic">actually</hi> diſplaced, is denſer
                    than common air. Theſe circumſtances cauſe the refiſtances to increaſe faſter
                    than the ſquares of the velocities : but, even independent of this, there is an
                    additional refiſtance arifing from the tendency to rarefaction behind a very
                    ſwift body ; becaufe the preffure of the ſurrounding fluid can only make the
                    ſiuid fill the ſpace left with a determined velocity.</p>
                <p>we have had occaſion to ſpeak of this circumſtance more particularly under
                    Gunnery and Pneumatics, when co.nſidering very rapid motions. Mr Robins had
                    remarked that the velocity at which the obſerved reſiſtance of the air began to
                    increaſe ſo prodigioufly, was that of about noo or 1200 feet per ſecond, and
                    that this was the velocity with which air would-ruſh into a void. He concluded,
                    that when the velocity was great-er than this, the ball was expofed to the
                    additional re-fiſtance ariſing from the unbalanced ſtatical preffure of the air,
                    and that this conſtant quantity behoved to be added to the reſiſtance ariſing
                    from the air's inertia in all greater velocities. This is very reaſonable : But
                    he imagined that in ſmaller velocities there was no ſuch unbalanced preffure.
                    But this cannot be the caſe : for although in ſmaller velocities the air will
                    ftill fill up the fpace behind the body, it will not fill it up .with air of the
                    fâme denſity. This would be to ſuppoſe the motion of the air into the deſerted
                    place to be inſtantane-ous. There muſt therefore be a rarefaction behind the
                    body, and a preffure backward ; ariſing from unbalan-ced elafticity, independent
                    of the condenſation on the anterior part. The condenſation and rarefaction are
                    cauſed by the ſame thing, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> the limited elafticity
                    of the air. were this infinitely great, the ſmalleſt ∙conden-fation before the
                    body would be inſtantly diffuſed over the whole air, and ſo would the
                    rarefaction, ſo that no preffure of unbalanced elaſticity would be obſerved; but
                    the elaſticity is fuch as to propagate the condenfation with the velocity of
                    found only, z. <hi rend="italic">e.</hi> the velocity of 1142 feet per ſecond.
                    Therefore this additional re-ſiſtance does not commence preciſely at this
                    velocity, but is ſenſible in all ſmaller velocities, as is very juſtly obſerved
                    by Euler. But we are not yet able to aſcer-tain the law of its increaſe,
                    although it is a problem which ſeems ſuſceptible of a tolerably accurate
                    ſolu-tion.</p>
                <p>Preciſely fimilar to this is the reſiſtance to the mo-tion of floating bodies,
                    ariſing from the accumulation or gorging up of the water on their anterior
                    furface, and its depreſſion behind them, were the gravity of the water infinite,
                    while its inertia remains the fame, the wave raiſed up at the prow of a ſhip
                    would be inſtantly diſſuſed over the whole ocean, and it would therefore be
                    infinitely ſmall, as alſo the depreſſion be-hind the poop. But this wave
                    requires time for its diſſufion ; and while it is not diſſuſed, it acts
                    byſhydrofe-tieal preſſure. AVe are equally unable to alcertain the law of
                    variation of this part of the reſiſtance, the me-chaniſm of waves being but very
                    imperfectly under-ſtood. The height of the wave in the experiments of the French
                    academy could not be meaſured with ſuffi-cient preciſion (being only obſerved <hi rend="italic">en pafiant)</hi> tor afcertaining its relation to the
                    velocity. The Chev. Buat attempted it in his experiments, butwithoutſucceſs.
                    Thia muſt evidently make a part of the reſiſtance in all velo-cities : and it
                    ſtill remains an undecided queſtion, "what relation it bears to the velocities?”
                    when the ſolid body is wholly buried in the ſiuid, this accumulation doea not
                    take place, or at leaſt not in the ſame way : It</p>
                <p>may, however, be obſerved. Every perſon may recol-lect, that in a very ſwift
                    running ſtream a large ſtone at the bottom will produce a ſmall ſwell above it ;
                    un-leſs it lies very deep, a nice eye may ſtill obſerve it. The water, on
                    arriving at the obſtacle, glides paſt it in every direction, and is deflected on
                    all hands; and therefore what paſſes over it is alſo deflected upwards, and
                    cauſes the water over it to riſe above its level. The nearer that the body is to
                    the ſurface, the greater will be the perpendicular riſe of the water, but it
                    will be leſs diſſuſed; and it is uncertain whether the <hi rend="italic">whole</hi> elevation will be greater or leſs. By the whole elevation we mean the area
                    of a perpendicular ſection of the ele-vation by a plane perpendicular to the
                    direction of the ſtream. we are rather diſpoſed to think that this area will be
                    greateſt when the body is near the ſurface. D’Ulloa has attempted to conſider
                    this ſubject ſcienti-fically ; and is of a very different opinion, which he
                    confirms by the ſingle experiment to he mentioned by and by. Mean time, it is
                    evident, that if the water which glides paſt the body cannot fall in behind it
                    with ſuſſicient velocity for filling up the ſpace behind, there muſt be a void
                    there ; and thus a hydroſtatical preſſure muſt be ſuperadded to the reſiſtance
                    ariſing from the inertia of the water. All muſt have obſerved, that if the end
                    of a ſtick held in the hand be drawn ſlowly through the water, the water will
                    fill the place left by the ſtick, and there will be no curled wave : but .if the
                    motion be very rapid, a hollow trough or gutter is left behind, and is not
                    ſilled up till at ſome diſtance from the ſtick, and the wave which forms its
                    fides is very much broken and curled. The writer of this article has often
                    looked into the water from the poop of a ſecond rate man of war when ſhe was
                    failing 11 miles per hour, which is a velocity of 16 feet per ſecond nearly ;
                    and he not only obſerved that the back of the rudder was naked for about two
                    feet below the load water-line, but alſo that the trough or wake made by the
                    ſhip was filled up with water which was broken and foaming to a conſiderable
                    depth, and to a confiderable diſtance from the veſſel: There muſt therefore have
                    been</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0101" facs="gri_33125011196389_0107.tif"/>
                <p>a voi&lt;L He never ſaw the wake perfectly tranfparent (and therefore
                    completely ſilled with water) when the velocity exceeded 9 or ι o feet per
                    ſecond. while this broken water is obferved, there can be no doubt that there is
                    a void and an additional refiſtance. But even when the ſpace left by the body,
                    or the ſpace behind a ſtill body expofed to a ſtream, is completely ſilled, it
                    may not be ſilled ſuſſiciently faſt, and there may be («and certainly is, as we
                    ſhall fee afterwards)· a quantity of water behind the body, which is moving more
                    ſlowly away than the reſt, and therefore hangs in ſome ſhape by the body, and is
                    dragged by it, increafing the reſiſtance. The quantity of this muſt depend
                    partly on the velocity of the body or ſtream, and partly on the rapidity with
                    which the ſurrounding water comes in behind. This laſt muſt depend on the
                    preſſure of the ſurrounding water. It would appear, that when this adjoining-
                    preſſure is very great, as muſt happen when the depth is great, the augmentation
                    of reſiſtance now ſpoken of would be lefs. Accordingly this appears in Newton’s
                    experiments, where the balls were leſs retarded as they were deeper under water.</p>
                <p>Theſe experiments are ſo ſimple in their nature, and were made with fuch care,
                    and by a perſon ſo able to detect and appreciate every circumſtance, that they
                    de-ſerve great credit, and the concluſions <hi rend="italic">legitimately</hi> drawn from them deſerve to be conſidered as phyfical laws, we think that the
                    preſent deduction is unexception-able : for in the motion of balls, which hardly
                    deſcen-ded, their preponderancy being hardly ſenſible, the effect of depth muſt
                    have borne a very great proportion to the whole reſiſtance, and muſt have
                    greatly influenced their motions ; yet they were obſerved to fall as if the
                    refiſtance had no way depended on the depth.</p>
                <p>The ſame thing appears in Borda’s experiments, where a ſphere which was deeply
                    immerſed in the water was leſs reſiſted than one that moved with the ſame
                    velocity near the ſurface ; and this was very conſtant and regular in a courſe
                    of experiments. D’Ulloa, however, affirms the contrary : He ſays that the
                    reſiſtance of a board, which was a foot broad, immerfed one foot in a ſtream
                    moving two feet per ſecond, was 15⅜ lbs⅛ and the reſiſtance to the ſame board,
                    when immerſed 2 ſeet in a ſtream moving if feet per ſecond (in which caſe the
                    ſurface was 2 feet), was 264 pounds<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial" n="1">There is ſomething very unaccountable in theſe
                        experiments. The·reſiſtances are much greater than any other author has
                        obſerved. </note>.</p>
                <p>we are very ſorry that we cannot give a proper account of this theory of
                    reſiſtance by Don George Juan D’Ul-loa, an author of great mathematical
                    reputation, and the inlpector of the marine academies in Spain, we have not been
                    able to procure either the original or the French tranſlation, and judge of it
                    only by an extract by Mr Prony in his <hi rend="italic">Architecture
                        Hydraulique, §</hi> 868. &amp;c. The theory is enveloped (according to
                    Mr Prony’s cuſtom) in the moſt complicated expreſſions, ſo that the phyſical
                    principles are kept almoſt out of ſight. when accommodated to the ſimpleſt
                    poſſible caſe, it is nearly as follows.</p>
                <p>Let <hi rend="italic">0</hi> be an elementary oriſice or portion of the
                    ſurface of the ſide of a veſſel ſilled with a heavy fluid, and let <hi
                        rend="italic"> h</hi> be its depth under the horizontal ſurface of the
                    fluid. Let ί be the denſity of the fluid, and ;&gt; the ac-celerative power
                    of gravity, =32 feet velocity acqui-red in a ſecond.</p>
                <p>It is known, ſays he, that the water would flow out at this hole with the
                    velocity <hi rend="italic">u</hi> ≈ V <hi rend="sup">,</hi> 2 <hi
                        rend="italic"> fh,</hi> anda <hi rend="sup">2</hi> ^3ιA</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">u <hi rend="sup">z</hi></hi></p>
                <p>and <hi rend="italic">h —— ∙</hi> It is alſo known that the preſſure <hi
                        rend="italic"> p</hi> on</p>
                <p>the oriſice <hi rend="italic">0 is φ 0 $ h, :=:&lt;;&gt; 0 $ <hi
                            rend="sup"> t</hi> ^~, ~</hi> ∙∣∙ ί 0 a <hi rend="sup">,</hi> .</p>
                <p>2 <hi rend="italic">T&gt;</hi></p>
                <p>Now let this little ſurface <hi rend="italic">0</hi> be ſuppoſed to mov¢" with
                    the velocity <hi rend="italic"><hi rend="sup"> t</hi> υ.</hi> The ſiuid would meet it with the velocity <hi rend="italic">u -fi v,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">u — v,</hi> according as it moved in the oppoſite or in the ſame direction with the efflux.
                    In the equation <hi rend="italic">p ~ l <hi rend="sub">r</hi> S 0 u <hi
                            rend="sup"> 1</hi> ,</hi> ſubſtitute <hi rend="italic">u τ±z</hi> &lt;u for <hi rend="italic">u,</hi> and we have the preſſure on <hi
                        rend="italic"> 0 ~ ρ ■=. -~- (u</hi> ∑±c <hi rend="italic">v} =</hi></p>
                <p>( V <hi rend="sup">z</hi> <hi rend="italic">2d z±z</hi> &lt;υ <hi rend="sup">1</hi> ).</p>
                <p>This preſſure is a weight, that is, a maſs of matter <hi rend="italic">m</hi> actuated by gravity <hi rend="italic">t,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">p = f m,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">m = o</hi></p>
                <p>r√^→ <hi rend="sub">z</hi> -2L.y.</p>
                <p>∖ √2f∕</p>
                <p>This elementary ſurface being immerſed in a ſtag-nant ſtuid, and moved with the
                    velocity <hi rend="italic">v,</hi> will ſuſtaiiv on one ſide a preſſure <hi
                        rend="italic"> 0</hi> ( <hi rend="sup">vzz,+</hi> √rj'and on the</p>
                <p>other ſide a preſſure &lt;- <hi rend="sup">r</hi> <hi rend="italic">0 h —</hi> ζZ~) ’ <hi rend="sup">an</hi> ^ <hi rend="sup">t</hi> ^ <hi rend="sup">ιe</hi> ^ <hi rend="sup">en</hi> ' ſible
                    reſiſtance will be the difference of theſe two preffures, which is <hi
                        rend="italic"> $ 0</hi> 4 5/ <hi rend="italic">h —— ,</hi> or &lt;f <hi rend="italic">0</hi> 4 <hi rend="italic">h —</hi> , that</p>
                <p>√2P 8</p>
                <p>is, —--γ <hi rend="sup">r</hi> becaufe <hi rend="italic">f2T <hi rend="sub">f</hi> &gt;= S ;</hi> a quantity which is 2</p>
                <p>in the ſubduplicate ratio of the depth under the ſurface of the fluid, and the
                    ſimple ratio of the velocity of the reſiſted furface jointly.</p>
                <p>There is nothing in experimental philoſophy more certain than that the
                    reſiſtances are very nearly in the duplicate ratio of the velocities ; and we
                    cannot conceive by what experiments the ingenious author has ſupported this
                    concluſion.</p>
                <p>But there is, beſides, what appears to us to be an eſſential defect in this
                    inveſtigation. The equation ex-hibits no reſiſtance in the caſe of a fluid
                    without weight. Now a theory of the reſiſtance of fluids ſhould exhibit the
                    retardation ariſing from inertia alone, and ſhould di-ſtinguiſh it from that
                    ariſing from any other cauſe: and. moreover, while it <hi rend="italic">ajfigns</hi> an ultimate ſenſible reſiſtance proportional <hi rend="italic">(c&amp;teris paribus)</hi> to the ſimple velocity, it <hi rend="italic"
                        > aj]umes</hi> as a ſirſt principle that the preſſure <hi rend="italic">p</hi> is as <hi rend="italic">u u±zv ∙</hi> It alſo gives a falſe meaſure of
                    the ſſatical preſſures ⅞ for theſe (in the caſe of bodies immerſed in our waters
                    at leaſt) are made up of the preſſure of the incumbent water, which is meaſured
                    by <hi rend="italic">h,</hi> and the preſſure of the atmoſphere, a conſtant
                    quantity.</p>
                <p>whatever 1eafon can be given for ſetting out with-the principle that the
                    preſſure on the little furface 0, moving with the velocity <hi rend="italic">u,</hi> is equal to ⅜ <hi rend="italic">io</hi> (w=±&gt;u) <hi rend="sup">i</hi> , makes it indiſpenſably neceſſary to take for the velocity</p>

                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0102" facs="gri_33125011196389_0108.tif"/>
                <p>tf, not that with which water would iſſue from a hole whoſe depth under the
                    ſurface is A, but the velocity with which it will iffue from a hole whoſe depth
                    is <hi rend="italic">h</hi> -J- 33 feet Becauſe the preffure of the atmo∙
                    ſphere is equal to that of a column of water 3 3 feet high: for this is the
                    acknowledged velocity with which it would ruſh in to the void leſt by the body.
                    If therefore this velocity (which does not exiſt) has any ſhare in the effort,
                    we mu <hi rend="underline">ſt have</hi> for the fluxion of</p>
                <p>„ 4√Z&gt; <hi rend="italic">v,</hi> 4V <hi rend="sup">z</hi> Z&gt;4-33j∙υ</p>
                <p>preffure not -- <hi rend="sub">z</hi> ∙-■ but-—, This would not</p>
                <p>√2 ¢&gt; v 2 ?</p>
                <p>only give preffure or reſiſtances many times exceeding thoſe that have been
                    obſerved in our experiments, but would alfo totally change the proportions which
                    this theory determines. It was at any rate improper to em-barraſs an
                    uiveſtigation, already very intricate, with the preffure of gravity, and with
                    two motions of efflux, which do not exiſt, and are neceffary for making the
                    preffures in the ratio of tt-f- <hi rend="sup">c</hi> i∕ and «—τΛ</p>
                <p>Mr Prony has been at no pains to inform his readers of his reafons for adopting
                    this theory of reſiftance, ſo contrary to all received opinions, and to the moſt
                    diſtinct experiments. Thoſe of the French academy, made un-der greater
                    preffures, gave a much ſmaller reſiſtance ; and the very experiments adduced in
                    ſupport of this theory are extremely deficient, wanting fully Jd of what the
                    theory requires. The reſiſtances by experiment were 15∣ and 26J, and the theory
                    required 20⅜ and 39, The equation, however, deduced ſrom the theory is greatly
                    deficient in the expreſſion of the preffures cau' fed by the accumulation and
                    depreſſion, ſtating the</p>
                <p>heights of them as ≈ —, They can never be ſo high,</p>
                <p>3 ?</p>
                <p>becauſe the heaped up water flows off at the ſides, and it alſo comes in behind
                    by the ſides j ſo that the preſſure is much leſs than half the weight oſ a
                    column whoſe</p>
                <p>height is —; both becauſe the accumulation and de-2∙P</p>
                <p>preffion are leſs at the ſides than in the middle, and be-cauſe, when the body
                    is wholly immerſed, the accumu-Jation is greatly diminiſhed. Indeed in this caſe
                    the final equation does not include their effects, though as real in this caſe
                    as when part of the body is above water.</p>
                <p>Upon the whole, we are ſomewhat ſurpriſed that an author of D’Ulioa’s eminence
                    ſhould have adopted a theory ſo unneceſſarily and ſo improperly embarraſſed with
                    foreign circumſtances ; and that Mr Prony ſhould have inferted it with the
                    explanation by which he was to abide, in a work deſtined ſor practical uſe.</p>
                <p>This point, or the effect oſ deep immerſion, is ſtill much esnteſted ; and it 13
                    a received opinion, by many not ac-cuſtomed to mathematical reſearches, that the
                    reſiſtance is greater in greater depths. This is aſſumed as an important
                    principle by Mr Gordon, author of <hi rend="italic">A Theory of Naval
                        Architecture ;</hi> but on very vague and flight grounds ; and the author
                    ſeems unacquainted with the manner of reafoning on ſuch ſubjects. It ſhall be
                    con-ſidered afterwards.</p>
                <p>with theſe corrections, it may be aſſerted that theory and experiment agree very
                    well in this reſpect, and that the reſiſtance may be aſſerted to be in the
                    duplicate ratio of the velocity,</p>
                <p>we have been more minute on this ſubject, becaujfe it is the leading propofition
                    in the theory of the ac</p>
                <p>tion of fluids., Newton’s demonſtration of it take» na notice of the manner in
                    which the various particles of the fluid are put into motion, or the motion
                    which each in particular acquires. He only ſhows, that if there ba nothing
                    concerned in the communication but pure ⅛-ertia, the ſum total of the motions of
                    the particles, eſti-mated in the direction of the bodies motion, or that of the
                    ſtream, will be in the duplicate ratio of the velocity. It was therefore of
                    importance to ſhow that thia part of the theory was juſt, To do this, we had to
                    conſider the effect of every circumſtance which could be combined with the
                    inertia of the fluid, AU theſe had been forefeen by that great man, and are moſt
                    briefly, though perſpicuouſly, mentioned in the laſt ſ¢hoHum to prop. 36. B. II.</p>
                <p>2. It appears from a compariſon of all the expert-ments, that the impulſes and
                    reſiſtances are very nearly in the proportion of the ſurfaces. They appear,
                    how-ever, to ſhcreaſe fomewhat faſter than the ſurfaces. The Chevalier Borda
                    found that the reſiſtance, with the ſame velocity, to a ſurface of</p>
                <p>9 inches') ( 9 ) C 9</p>
                <p>*1 <hi rend="italic">Γ</hi> <hi rend="sup">WaS</hi> A</p>
                <p>3 <hi rend="sup">6</hi> C ∕ 42,750c Jj¢</p>
                <p>81 <hi rend="italic">J</hi> V104&gt;737J K-8x</p>
                <p>The deviation in thefe experiments from the theory increaſes with the ſurface,
                    and is probably much greater in the extenſive ſurfaces of the fads of ſhips and
                    windmills, and the hulls of ſhips.</p>
                <p>3. The reſiſtances do by no means vary in the du« plicate ratio of the fines of
                    the angles of incidence.</p>
                <p>As this is the moſt intereſting circumſtance, having a chief influence on all
                    the particular modifications of the reſiſtance of fluids, aqd as on this depends
                    the whole theory of the conſtruction and working of ihips, and the action of
                    water on oui moſt important machines, and ſeems moſt immediately connected with
                    the media' niſm of fluids, it merits a very particular confideration, we cannot
                    do a greater fervice than by rendering more generally known the excellent
                    experiments oſ the French academy.</p>
                <p>Fifteen boxes or veſſels were conſtructed, which were two feet wide, and two
                    feet deep, and four feet long. One of them was a parallelopiped of thefe
                    dimenfions ⅛ the others had prows of a wedge-form, the angle ACB (ſig. 7.)
                    varying by 12 <hi rend="sup">0</hi> degrees from 12° to 180° j fo that the
                    angle of incidence increaſed by <hi rend="italic">6 <hi rend="sup">q</hi></hi> from one to another. Thefe boxes were dragged acroſs a very large bafon of
                    ſmooth water (in which they were immerſed two feet) by mean# of a line paffing
                    over a wheel connected with a cylinder, from which the actu∙</p>
                <p>, ating weight was ſuſpended. The motion became per-fectly uniform after a very
                    little way } and the time of paſſmg over 96 French feet with this uniform motion
                    was very carefully noted. The reſiſtance was meaſu-red by the weight employed,
                    after deducting a certain quantity (properly eſtimated) for friction, and for
                    the accumulation of the water againſt the anterior ſurfac¢. The reſults of the
                    many experiments arc given in the following table ; where column iſt contains
                    the angle of the prow, column zd contains the reſiſtance as given by the
                    preceding theory, column 3d contains the reſiſtan¢e exhibited in the
                    experiments, and column 4th contain# the deviation of the experiment from the
                    theory,</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0103" facs="gri_33125011196389_0109.tif"/>
                <p>Γ. IL ∏L IV,</p>
                <p>x8a ΙΟΟΟΟ IOOOQ ο</p>
                <p>1&lt;58 9⅜ <hi rend="sup">0</hi> 9 <hi rend="sup">s</hi> 93 ÷3</p>
                <p>156 95 <hi rend="sup">68</hi> 9578 ÷iQ</p>
                <p>144 9045 9° <hi rend="sup">s</hi> 4 +39</p>
                <p>132 8346 8446 ÷ wo</p>
                <p>J3Q 7500 77iQ 4-210</p>
                <p>jo8 6545 6925 4-380</p>
                <p>96 5523 6148 +625</p>
                <p>84 4478 543J +955</p>
                <p>72 3455 4800 +1345</p>
                <p>60 2500 4404 + <hi rend="sup">1</hi> 9 <hi rend="sup">o</hi> 4</p>
                <p>48 1654 4240 -j-2586</p>
                <p>36 955 4142 ÷3 <hi rend="sup">l8</hi> 7</p>
                <p>24 43 g 4063 + 3 <hi rend="smallcaps"><hi rend="sup"> 6</hi> 3 <hi rend="sup">i</hi></hi></p>
                <p>12 109 3999 4-3890</p>
                <p>The reſiſtance to 1 ſquare foot, French meaſure, moving with the velocity of
                    2,56 feet pci ſecond, was ve-ry nearly 7,625 pounds French.</p>
                <p>Reducing theſe to Engliſh meaſures, we have the ſuiface = l√363 feet, the
                    velocity of the motion equal to 2,7263 feet per ſecond, and the reſiſtance equal
                    to 8,234 pounds avoirdupois. The weight of a column of ireſh water of this baſe,
                    and having for its height the fall neceffary for communicating this velocity, is
                    8,264 pounds avoirdupois. TlTe reſiſtances to other velocities were accurately
                    proportional to the ſquares of the velocities.</p>
                <p>There is great diverſity in the value which different authors have deduced for
                    the abſolute reſiſtance of wa-ter from their experiments. In the value now given
                    nothing is taken into account but the inertia of the water. The accumulation
                    againſt the forepart of the boχ was carefully noted, and the ſtatical preffure
                    backwards, ariſing from this cauſe, was ſubtracted from the whole reſiſtance to
                    the drag. There had not been a ſufficient variety of experiments for diſeovering
                    the ſhare which tenacity and friction produced ; fo that the number of pounds
                    ſet down here may be conſidered as fomewhat ſuperior to the mere effects of the
                    inertia of the water, we think, upon the whole, that it is the moſt accurate
                    determination yet given of the reſiſtance to a body in motion : but we ſhall
                    afterwards ſee reafons for belie -ving, that the impulſe of a running ſtream
                    having the ſame velocity is ſomewhat greater ; and this is the form in which
                    moſt of the experiments have been made.</p>
                <p>Alſo obſerve, that the refiſtance here given is that to a veffel two feet broad
                    and deep and four feet long. The refiſtance to a plane of two feet broad and
                    deep would probably have exceeded this in the proportion of 15,22 to 14,54, for
                    reafons we ſhall ſee afterwards.</p>
                <p>From the experiments of Chevalier Buat, it appears that a body of one foot
                    ſquare, French meaſure, and two feet long, having its centre 15 inches under
                    water, moving three French feet per ſecond, fuſtained a preffure of 14,54 French
                    pounds, or 15,63 Engliſh. This redu-ced in the proportion of 3 <hi rend="sup">1</hi> to 2,56 <hi rend="sup">i</hi> gives 11,43 pounds, conſiderably exceeding
                    the 8,24.</p>
                <p>Mr Bouguer, in his <hi rend="italic">Manœuvre des Vajſeaux,</hi> fays, that he
                    found the reſiſtance of ſea-water to a velocity of one foot to be 23 ounces <hi
                        rend="italic"> poids des Marc.</hi></p>
                <p>The Chevalier Borda found the reſiſtance of ſea-water to the face of a cubic
                    foot, moving againſt the water one foot per ſecond, to be 21 ounces nearly. But
                    this experiment iβ complicated ; the wave wag net de. ducted ; and it was not a
                    plane, but a cube.</p>
                <p>Don George d’Ulloa found the impulfe of a ſtream of fea-water, running two feet
                    per fecond on a foot ſquare, to be 15Î pounds Engliſh meaſure. This greatly
                    exceeds all the values given by others.</p>
                <p>From theſe experiments we learn, in the firſt place, that the direct refiſtance
                    to a motion of a plane furface through water, is very nearly equal to the weight
                    of a column of water having that ſurface for its baſc, and for its height the
                    fall producing the velocity of the motion. This is but one half of the
                    refiſtance determined by the preceding theory. It agrees, however, very well
                    with the beſt experiments made by other philoſo-phers on bodies totally immerfed
                    or ſurrounded by the fluid ; and ſuſſiciently ſhows, that there muſt be ſome
                    fallacy in the principles or reaſoning by which this re-ſult of the theory is
                    ſuppoſed to be deduced. We ſhall have occafion to return to this again.</p>
                <p>But we ſee that the effects of the obliquity of inci-dence deviate enormouſly
                    from the theory, and thafc this deviation increaſes rapidly as the acuteneſs of
                    the prow increaſes. In the prow of 6o <hi rend="sup">0</hi> the deviation is
                    nearly equal to the whole refiſtance pointed out by the theory, and in the prow
                    of 12 <hi rend="sup">0</hi> it is nearly 40 times greater than the theoretical
                    refiſtance.</p>
                <p>The refiſtance of the prow of 90 <hi rend="sup">o</hi> ſhould be one half the
                    reſtſtance of the baſe. we have not fitch a prow ; but the medium between the
                    reſiſtance of the prow of 96 and 84 is 5790, inſtead of 500.</p>
                <p>Theſe experiments are very conform to thoſe of other authors on plane ſurfaces.
                    M <hi rend="sup">r</hi> Robins found the re-ſiſtance of the air to a pyramid
                    of 45 <hi rend="sup">0</hi> , with its apex foremoſt, was to that of its bafe
                    as 1000 to 1411, in-ſtead of-O∏e to two. Chevalier Borda found the refiſtance of
                    a cube, moving in water in the direction of the fide, was to the oblique
                    refiſtance, when it was moved in the direction of the diagonal, in the
                    proportion of 5∣∙ to 7 ; whereas it ſhould have been that of √2 to 1, or of 10
                    to 7 nearly. He alſo found, that a wedge whoſe angle was 90°, moving in air,
                    gave for the proportion of the reſiſtances of the edge and baſe 7281 : 10000,
                    inſtead of 5000 : 10000, Alfo when the angle of the wedge was 60 <hi rend="sup">0</hi> , the refiſtances of the edge and baſe were 52 and 100, inſtead of
                    25 and 100.</p>
                <p>In ſhort, in all the cafes oſ oblique plane ſurfaces, the reſiſtances were
                    greater than thoſe which are affigned by the theory. The theoretical law agrees
                    tolerably with obſervation in large angles of incidence, that is, in incidences
                    not differing very far from the perpendicular ; but in more acute prows the
                    reſiſtances are more nearly proportional to the fines of incidence than to their
                    ſquares.</p>
                <p>The academicians deduced from theſe experiments an expreſſion of the general
                    value of the refiſtance, which correſponds tolerably well with obſervation. Thus
                    let <hi rend="italic">x</hi> be the complement of the half angle of the prow,
                    and let P be the direct preffure or reſiftance, with an incidence of 90 <hi
                        rend="sup"> o</hi> , and <hi rend="italic">p</hi> the effective oblique
                    preffure : then <hi rend="italic">p ~</hi> P × coſine <hi rend="sup">,</hi> * + 3,t53 ‘ This</p>
                <p>gives for a prow of 12 <hi rend="sup">0</hi> an error in defect about <hi
                        rend="sub"> τ</hi> ⅛, and in larger angles it is much nearer the truth ;and
                    this is exact enough for aβ!y practice.</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0104" facs="gri_33125011196389_0110.tif"/>
                <p>Thia is an abundantly ſimple formula ; but if we introduce it in our
                    calculations of the reſiftances of curvilineal prows, it renders them ſo
                    complicated as to be al-moft uſeleſs ; and what is worſe, when the calculation
                    is completed for a curvilineal prow, the reſiſiance which refults is found to
                    differ widely from experiment. This ſhows that the motion of the fluid is ſo
                    modified by the action of the moft prominent part of the prow, that its impulſe
                    on what ſucceeds is greatly affected, fo that we are not allowed to conſider the
                    prow as compoſed of a number of parts, each of which is affected as if it were
                    detached from all the reft.</p>
                <p>As the very nature of naval architecture ſeems to require curvilineal forms, in
                    order to give the neceffary ſtrength, it ſeemed of importance to examine more
                    particulary the deviations of the reſiftances of ſuch prows . from the
                    refiſtances affigned by the theory. The academicians therefore made veffels with
                    prows of a cylindrical ſhape ; one of theſe was a half cylinder, and the other
                    was one-third of a cylinder, both having the ſame breadth, viz. two feet, the
                    ſame depth, alſo two feet, and the ſame length, four feet. The reſiſtance of the
                    half cylinder was to the reſiſtance of the perpendicular prow in the proportion
                    of 13 to 25, inſtead of being as 13 to 19,5. The Chevalier Borda found nearly
                    the ſame ratio oſ the refiſtances of the half cylin-der, and its diametrical
                    plane when moved in air. He alſo compared the reſiſtances of two priſms or
                    wedges, of the ſame breadth and 'height. The ſirſt had its ſides plane, inclined
                    to the baſe in angles of 60°; the ſecond had its ſides portions oſ cylinders, of
                    which the planes were the chords, that is, their ſections were arches of circles
                    of 60 <hi rend="sup">,</hi> . Their reſiſtances were as 133 to 100, inſtead of
                    being as 133 to 220, as required by the theory ; and as the reſiſtance of the
                    ſirſt was greater in proportion to that of the baſe than the theory allows, the
                    reſiſtance of the laſt was leſs.</p>
                <p>Mr Robins found the reſiſtance of a ſphere moving in air to be to the refiſtance
                    of its great circle as 1 to 2,27 ; whereas theory requires them to be as I to 2.
                    He found, at the fame time, that the abſolute refiſtance was greater than the
                    weight of a cylinder of air of the ſame diameter, and having the height
                    neceffary for acquiring the velocity. It was greater in the proportion •of 49 to
                    40 nearly.</p>
                <p>Borda found the rcfiſtance of the ſphere moving in water to be to that of its
                    great circle as 1000 to 2508, and it was one-ninth greater than the weight of
                    the column of water whoſe height was that neceffary for producing the velocity.
                    He alſo found the refiſt-smee of air to the ſphere was to its reſiſtance to its
                    great circle as 1 to 2,45.</p>
                <p>It appears, on the whole, that the theory gives the refiſtance of oblique plane
                    ſurfaces too ſmall, and that of curved ſurfaces too great ; and that it is quite
                    unfit for afcertaining the modifications of reſiſtance arifing from the figure
                    of the body. The moſt prominent part of the prow changes the action of the fluid
                    on the ſucceeding parts, rendering it totally different from what it would be
                    were that part detached from the reſt, and expofed to the ſtream with the ſame
                    obliquity. It is of no conſequence, therefore, to deduce any formula from the
                    valuable experiments of the French academy. The experiments themſelves are of
                    great importance, jjecauſe they give us the impulſes on plane ſurfaces with</p>
                <p>every obliquity. They therefore put it in our power to ſelect the moſt proper
                    obliquity in a thouſand im-portant caſes. By appealing to them, we can tell what
                    is the proper angle of the ſail for producing the great-eſt impnlſe in the
                    direction of the ſhip’s courſe ; or the beſt inclination of the ſail of a
                    wind-mill, or the beſt in-clination of the float of a water-wheel, &amp;c.
                    &amp;c. Theſe deductions will be made in their proper places in the courſc
                    of this work, we ſee alſo, that the deviation from the ſrmple theory is not very
                    confiderable till the obliquity is great ; and that, in the inclinations which
                    other circumſtances would induce us to give to the floats of water-wheels, the
                    fails of wind-mills, and the like, the reſults of the theory are ſuſſiciently
                    agreeable to experiment, for rendering this theory of very great uſe in the
                    conſtruction of machines. Its great défect is in the impulſions on curved
                    ſurſaces, which puts a ſtop to our improvement of the ſcience of naval
                    arcħi-lecture, and the working of ſhips.</p>
                <p>But it is not enough to detect the ſaults oſ this theo-ry : we ſhould try to
                    amend it, or to ſubſtitute ano-ther. It is a pity that ſo much ingenuity ſhould
                    have been thrown away in the application of a theory ſo defective.
                    Mathematicians were ſeduced, as has been al-ready obſerved, by the opportunity
                    which it gave for exercifing their calculus, which was a new thing at the time
                    of publiſhing this theory. Newton ſaw clearly the defects of it, and makes no
                    uie of any part of it in his ſubſequent diſcuſſions, and plainly has uſed it
                    merely as an introduction, in order to give ſome gene-ral notions in a ſnbject
                    quite new, and to give a demon* ſtration of one leading truth, viz. the
                    proportion <hi rend="sup">-</hi> ility of the impulfions to the ſquares of the
                    velocities, while we proſeſs the higheſt reſpect for the talents and labours of
                    the great mathematicians who have followed New-ton in this moſt difficult
                    refearch, we cannot help being ſorry that ſome of the greateſt of them continued
                    to attach themſelves to a theory which he neglected, mere-ly becauſe it afforded
                    an opportunity of diſplaying their profound knowledge of the new calculus, of
                    which they were willing to afcribe the diſcovery to Leibnitz. It has been in a
                    great meaſure owing to this that we have been ſo late in diſcovering our
                    ignorance of the ſubject. Newton had himſelf pointed out all the defects of this
                    theory ; and he ſet himſelf to work to diſcover another which ſholftd be more
                    conformable to the nature of things, retaining only ſuch deductions ſrom the
                    other as his great ſagacity affured him would ſtand the teſt oſ experiment. Even
                    in this he ſeems to have been miſtaken by his followers. He retained the
                    proportionality of the reſiſtance to the ſquare oſ the velocity. This they have
                    endeavoured to demonſtrate in a manner conformable to Newton’s determination of
                    the oblique impulſes of fluids ; and under the cover of the agreement of this
                    propoſition with experiment, they in* troduced into mechanics a mode of
                    expreffion, and even oſ conception, which is inconſiſtent with all accurate
                    notions on theſc ſubjects. Newton’s propofition was, that the motions
                    communicated to the fluid, and therefore the motions loſt by the body, in equal
                    times, were as the ſquares of the velocities ; and he conceived theſe as proper
                    meaſures of the reſiſtances. It is a matter of experience, that the forces or
                    preſſures by which a body muſt be ſupported in oppoiition to the impulſes of
                    fluids, are in this very proportion. In determining the</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0105" facs="gri_33125011196389_0111.tif"/>
                <p><hi rend="italic">proportion</hi> of the direct and oblique refiſtances of
                    plane furſaces, he conſiders the refiſtances to ariſe from mutual colliſions of
                    the furface and fluid, repeated at intervals of time too fmall to be perceived.
                    But in making this compariſon, he has no occaſion whatever to conſi. der this <hi rend="italic">repetition ;</hi> and when he aſſigns the proportion
                    between the reſiftance of a cone and of its baſe, he, in fact, aſſigns the
                    proportion between two <hi rend="italic">fimultaneous</hi> and inftantaneous
                    impulſes. But the mathematicians who followed him have conſidered this
                    repetition as equivalent to an augmentation of the initial or ſirft im-pulſe ;
                    and in this way have attempted to demonftrate that the reſiſtances are as the
                    ſquares of the velocities, when the velocity is double, each impulſe is double,
                    and the number in a given time is double ; therefore, ſay they, the reſiſtance,
                    and the force which will with-ſtand it, is quadruple ; and obſervation confirms
                    their deduction : yet nothing is more gratuitous and illogi-cal. It is very true
                    that the refiſtance, conceived as Newton conceives it, the loſs of motion
                    ſuſtained by a body moving in the fluid, is quadruple ; but the ſhſtan-taneous
                    impulſe, and the force which can withſtand it, is, by all the laws of mechanics,
                    only double, wha tis the force which can withſtand a double impulſe ? Nothing
                    but a double impulſe. Nothing but impulſe can be oppoſed to impulſe ; and it is
                    a groſs miſconception to think of ſtating any kind of compariſon between
                    im-pulſe and preffure. It is this which has given riſe to much jargon and falſe
                    reaſoning about the force of percuſſion. This is ſtated as infinitely greater
                    than any preffure, and as equivalent to a preffure infinitely repeated. It
                    forced the abettors of theſe doctrines at laſt to deny the exiſtence of all
                    preffures whatever, and to affert that all motion, and tendency to motion, was
                    the reſult of impulſe. The celebrated Euler, perhaps the firſt mathematician,
                    and the loweſt philoſopher, of this century, fays, “ ſince motion and impulfe
                    are ſeen to exiſt, and fince we ſee that by means of motion preſ-ſure may be
                    produced, as when a body in motion ſtrikes another, or as when a body moving in
                    a curved channel preffes upon it, merely in conſequence of its curvilineal
                    motion, and the exertion of a centrifugal force ; and fince Nature is moſt
                    wifely economical in all her operations; it is abſurd to ſuppoſe that preffure,
                    or tendency to motion, has any other origin ; and it is the buſineſs of a
                    philoſopher to diſcover by what motions any obſerved preffure is produced.”
                    whenever any preffure is ob-ferved, iuch as the preffure of gravity, of
                    magnetiſm, of electricity, of condenſed air, nay, of a ſpri'ng, and of
                    elaſticity and cohefιon themſelves, however difparate, nay, oppoſite, the
                    philoſopher muft immediately caſt about, and contrive a ſet of motions (creating <hi rend="italic">pro re natd</hi> the movers) which will produce a
                    preffure like the one obſerved. Having pleaſed his fancy with this, he cries out
                    ⅛"** “ this <hi rend="italic">will produce</hi> the preffure;” <hi
                        rend="italic"> et frujlra fit per ρlura quod fieri potefi per pauciora, <hi
                            rend="sup"> ii</hi></hi> therefore in this way the preffure <hi rend="italic">is</hi> produced.”
                    Thus the vortices of Deſcartes are brought back in triumph, and have produced
                    vortices without number, which fill the univerſe with motion and preffure.</p>
                <p>Such bold attempts to overturn long-received doc-trines in mechanics, could not
                    be received without much criticiſm and oppofition ; and many able differtations
                    appeared from time to time in defence of the common doctrines. In conſequence of
                    the many objections to the compariſon of pure preffure with pure percuffion or
                    impulſe, John Bernoulli and others were at laft obli-ged to affert that there
                    were no perfectly hard bodies in nature, nor could be, but that all bodies were
                    elaſtic ; and that in the communication of motion by percuſſion, the velocities
                    of both bodies were <hi rend="italic">gradually</hi> changed by their mutual
                    elaſticity acting during the finite but imperceptible time of the collifion.
                    This was, in fact, giving up the whole argument, and baniſhing percuſ-fion,
                    while their aim was to get rid of preffure. For what is elafticity but a
                    preffure ? and how ſhall <hi rend="italic">it</hi> be produced ? To act in
                    this inſtance, muſt it ariſe from a ſtill ſmaller impulſe ? But this will
                    require another ela-fticity, and ſo on without end.</p>
                <p>Theſe are all legitimate conſequences of this attempt to ſtate a compariſon
                    between percuſſion and preffure. Numberleſs experiments have been made to
                    confirm the ſtatement ; and there is hardly an itinerant-lecturing ſhowman who
                    does not exhibit among his apparatus Graveſande’s machine (V0I. I. plate xxxv.
                    fig. 4). But nothing affords ſo ſpecious an argument as the ex-perimented
                    proportionality of the impulſe of fluids to the ſquare oſ the velocity. Here is
                    every appearance of the accumulation of an inſtnity of minute impulſes, in the
                    known ratio of the velocity, each to each, pro-ducing preffures which are in the
                    ratio of the ſquares of the velocities.</p>
                <p>The preffures are obſerved ; but the impulſes or per-cuſſions, whoſe
                    accumulation produces theſe preffures, are only ſuppoſed. The rare fluid,
                    introduced by New-ton for the purpoſe already mentioned, either does not exiſt
                    in nature, or does not act in the manner we have ſaid, the particles making
                    their impulſe, and then eſcaping through among the reſt without affecting their
                    motion. we cannot indeed ſay what may be the proportion between the diameter and
                    the diftance of the particles. The firft may be incomparably ſmaller than the
                    ſecond, even in mercury, the denſeſt fluid which we are familiarly acquainted
                    with ; but although they do not touch each other, they act. nearly as if they
                    did, in conſequence of their mutual attractions and repulfions, we have ſeen air
                    a thouſand times rarer in ſome experi-ments than in others, and therefore the
                    diſtance of the particles at leaſt ten times greater than their diameters ; and
                    yet, in this rare ſtate, it propagates all preſthres or impulſes made on any
                    part of it to a great diſtance, almoft in an inftant. It cannot be, therefore,
                    that fluids act on bodies by impulſe. It is very poſſible to conceive a fluid
                    advancing with a flat iurface againſt the flat ſurface of a ſolid. The very
                    firſt and iuperficial particles may make an impulſe ; and if they were
                    annihi-lated, the next might do the ſame : and if the velocity were double,
                    theſe impulſes would be double, and would be withſtood by a double force, and
                    not a quadruple, a&amp; is obſerved : and this very circumſtance, that a
                    qua-druple force is neceffary, ſhould have made us conclude that it was not to
                    impulſe that this force was oppoſed. The firſt particles having made their
                    ſtroke, and not be-ing annihilated, muſt eſcape laterally. In their efca-ping,
                    they effectually prevent every farther impulſe, becaufe they come in the way of
                    thofe filaments which would have ſtruck the body. The whole proceſs teems to be
                    ſomewhat as follows :</p>
                <p>when the flat ſurface of the fluid has come into con-tact with the plane ſurface
                    AD (fig, 6.), perpendicular</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0106" facs="gri_33125011196389_0112.tif"/>
                <p>to the direction DC of their motion, they muſt deflect to both ſides equally,
                    and in equal portions, becauſe no reaſon can be affigned why more ſhould go to
                    either ſide. By this means the filament EF, which would have ſtruck the ſurface
                    in G, is deflected <hi rend="italic">before it arrives at</hi> the ſurface,
                    and deſcribes a curved path EFIHK, continuing its rectilineal motion to I, where
                    it is inter-cepted by a filament immediately adjoining to EF, on the fide of the
                    middle filament DC. The different particles of DC may be ſuppoſed to impinge in
                    fucceſſion at C, and to be deflected at right angles ; and gliding along CB, to
                    eſcape at B. Each filament in ſucceſſion, outwards from DC, is deflected in its
                    turn ; and being hindered from even touching the ſurface C B, it glides off in a
                    direction parallel to it ; and thus EF is deflected in I, moves parallel to CB
                    from Ito H, and is again deflected at right angles, and deſcribes H K parallel
                    to DC. The ſame thing may be ſuppoſed to happen on the other ſide of DC.</p>
                <p>And thus it would appear, that except two filaments immediately adjoining to the
                    line DC, which bifects the ſurface at right angles, no part of the fluid makes
                    any impulſe on the furface AB. All the other filaments are merely preffed
                    againſt it by the lateral filaments without them, which they turn aſide, and
                    prevent from ſtriking the ſurface.</p>
                <p>In like manner, when the fluid ſtrikes the edge of a priſm or wedge ACB (fig.
                    7.), it cannot be ſaid-that any real impulfe is made. Nothing hinders us from
                    fuppoſing C a mathematical angle or indiviſible point, not fufceptibiè of any
                    impulſe, and ſerving merely to di-vide the ſtream. Each filament EF is
                    effectually pre-vented from impinging at G in the line of its. direction, and
                    with the obliquity of incidence EGC, by the filaments between EF and DC, which
                    glide along the furface CA ; and it may be ſuppoſed to be deflected when it
                    comes to the line CF which bifects the angle DCA, and again deflected and
                    rendered parallel to D C at I. The lame thing happens on the other ſide of DC ;
                    and we cannot in this caſe affert that there is any impulſe.</p>
                <p>we now ſee plainly how the ordinary theory muſt be totally unfit for furniſhing
                    principles of naval architec-ture, even although a formula could be deduced from
                    fueh a feri.es of experiments as thoſe. of the French Aca-demy. Although we
                    ſhould know preciſely the im-pulſe, or, to ſpeak now more cautiouſly, the
                    action, of the fluid on a furface G L (fig8.) of any obliquity, when it is
                    alone, detached from all others, we cannot' in the ſmalleſt degree tell what
                    will be the action of <hi rend="italic">part</hi> of a ſtream of ſtuid
                    advancing towards it, with the fame obliquity, when it is preceded by an
                    adjoining fur-face CG, having a different inclination ; for the ſtuid will not
                    glide along G L in the ſame manner as if it made part of a more extenfive
                    furface having the ſame inclination. The previous deflexions are extremely
                    different in theſe two caſes ; and the previous deflections are the only changes
                    which we can obſerve in the motions of the fluid, and the only cauſes of that
                    pfeffure which we obferve the body to ſuſtain* and which we call the impulfe on
                    it. This theory muſt, therefore, be quite unfit for afcertaining the action on a
                    curved furface, which may be confidered as made up of an indeſi-n∙ite number of
                    ſucceſſive planes.</p>
                <p>We now feewit⅛ equal evidence how it happens that</p>
                <p>the action of fluids on ſolid bodies may and muſt be oppoſed by preffures, and
                    may be compared with and mea-ſured by the preffure of gravity, we are not
                    compa-ring forces of different kinds&gt; percuſſions with-preffwesj but
                    preffures with each other. Let us ſee whether this view of the ſubject will
                    afford us any method ol compariſon or abſolute meafurement.</p>
                <p>when a filament cf fluid, that is, a row- of corpuſcles, are turned out of their
                    courſe EF (ſig. 6. ), and forced to take another courſe IH, force is required to
                    produce this change of direction. The filament is prevented from proceeding by
                    other filaments which lie between it and the body, and which deflect it in the
                    ſame manner as if it were contained in a bended tube, and it will prefs on the
                    concave filament next to it as it would prefs on the concave ſide of the tube.
                    Suppoſe ſuch a bend-ed tube ABE (ſig. 9.), and that a ball A is projected along
                    it with any velocity, and moves in it without fric∙ tron : it is demonftrated,
                    in elementary mechanics, that the ball will move with undiminilhed velocity, and
                    will preſs on every point, fuch as B, of the concave ſide of the tube, in a
                    direction BF perpendicular to the plane CBD, which touches the tube in the point
                    B* This preffure on the adjoining filament, on the concave ſide of its path,
                    muſt be withſtood by that filament which deflects it ; and it muſt be propagated
                    aeroſs that Alarment to the next, and thus augment the preffure upon that next
                    filament already preffed by the deflection of the intermediate filament and thus
                    there is a preffure towards the middle filament, and towards the body, ari-ſing
                    from the deflection of all the outer filaments ; and their accumulated ſum muſt
                    be conceived as immediate* ly exerted on the middle filaments and on the body,
                    be* cauſe a perfect ſiuid tranſmits every preffure undimi» niſhed.</p>
                <p>The preffure BF is equivalent to the two BH, BG, one of which is· perpendicular,
                    and. tlie other parallel, to the direction, of the original motion. By the ſirſt
                    (taken in any point of the curvilineal motion of any filament), the two halves
                    of the ſtream are preffed together ; and in the caſe of ſig. 6. and 7. exactly
                    balance each other.. But the preffures, ſuch as BG, muſt be ultimately withſtood
                    by the ſurface ACB ; and it is by theſe accumulated preffures that the ſolid
                    body is urged down the ſtream ;.and it is theſe accumulated preffures which we
                    obſerve and meafure in our experiments. WC ſhall anticipate a little, and ſay
                    that ibis moſt eaſily de-monſtrated, that when a ball A (ſig. 9. ) moves with
                    un-diminiſhed velocity in a tube ſo incurvated that its axis at E is at right
                    angles to its axis at A, the accumulated action of the preii’ures, ſuch
                    as&lt; B G-, taken for every point of the path, is preciſely equal to the
                    force which would produce or extinguiſh the original motion.</p>
                <p>This being the caſe, it follows moſt obvioufly, that if the. two motions oſ the
                    filaments are ſuch as we have de-ſcribed and repreſented by fig. 6. the whole
                    preffure in the direction of the ſtream, that is, the whole preffure which can
                    be obſerved on the ſurface, is equal to the weight of a column of fluid having
                    the ſarface for its baſe, and twice the fall productive of the velocity for its
                    height, pre-ciſely as Newtcn deduced it from other conſiderations ; and it feems
                    to make no odds whether the fluid be elaſ-tic or unelaſtic, if the deflections
                    and velocities are the fame. Now it is a fact, that no difference in this re-</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0107" facs="gri_33125011196389_0113.tif"/>
                <p>ſpect can be obſerved in the actions of air and water ; and this had always
                    appeared a great defect in Newton’s theory : but it was only a defect of the
                    theory attributed to him. But it is alſo true, that the obſerved action is but
                    one-half of what is juft now deduced ſrom this improved view of the ſubject.
                    whence arifes this difference ? The reafon is this : we have given a very
                    erroneous account of the motions of the filaments. A filament Έ F does not move
                    as repreſented in ſig. 6. with two rectangular inflexions at I and at H, and a
                    path IH between them parallel to C B. The proceſs of na-ture is more like what
                    is repreſented in ſig. io. <hi rend="italic">It is obfirved,</hi> that at the
                    anterior part of the body A B, there remains a quantity of fluid AD B, almoft,
                    if not alto-gether, ftagnant, of a ſingular ſhape, having two curved concave
                    ſides A <hi rend="italic">a</hi> D, B <hi rend="italic">b</hi> D, along
                    which the middle filaments glide. This fluid is very {lowly changed.— The late
                    Sir Charles Knowles, an officer of the Britiſh navy, equally eminent for his
                    fcientiſic profeſſional knowledge and for his military talents, made many
                    beautiful experiments for aſceitaining the paths of the filaments of water. At a
                    diftance up the ftream, he allowed ſmall jets of à coloured ſiuid, which did not
                    mix with water, to make part of the ftream ; and the experiments were made in
                    troughs with ſides and bottom of plate-glaſs. A ſmall taper was placed at a
                    conſider-able height above, by which the ſhadows of the colour-ed filaments were
                    moft diſtinctly projected on a white plane held below the trough, fo that they
                    were accu-rately drawn with a pencil. A few important parti-eulars may be here
                    mentioned.</p>
                <p>The ftill water ADC lafted for a long while be-fore it was renewed ; and it
                    ſeemed to be gradually wafted by abraſion, by the adheſion of the ſurrounding
                    water, which gradually licked away the outer parts from D to A and B ; and it
                    ſeemed to renew itſelf in the direction CD, oppoſite to the motion of the
                    ftream. There was, however, a conſiderable intricacy and eddy in this motion.
                    Some (ſeemingly ſuperſicial) water was continually, but ſiowly, flowing outward
                    from the line DC, while other water was feen within and below it, coming inwards
                    and going backwards.</p>
                <p>The coloured lateral filaments were moft conftant in their form, while the body
                    was the fame, although the ve-locity was in idrne caſes quadrupled. Any change
                    which this produced ſeemed confined to the ſuperſicial filaments.</p>
                <p>As the filaments were deflected, they were alſo con-ftipated, that is, the
                    curved parts of the filaments were nearer each other than the parallel ftraight
                    filaments up the ftream ; and this conftipation was more conſiderable as the.
                    prow was more obtuſe and the deflexion greater.</p>
                <p>The inner filaments were ultimately more deflected than thoſe without them.;
                    that is, if a line be drawn touching the curve EFIH in the point H of contrary
                    flexure, wherc the concavity begins to be on the ſide next the body, the angle
                    HKC, contained between the axis and this tangent line, is ſo much the greater as
                    the filament is nearer the axis.</p>
                <p>when the body expofed to the ftream was a box of upright ſides, flat bottom, and
                    angular prow, like a wedge, having its edge alfo upright, the filaments were not
                    all deflected laterally, as theory would make us expect ; but the filaments near
                    the bottom were alſo deflected downwards as well as laterally, and glided alon^</p>
                <p>at ſome diftance under the bottom, forming lines of double curvature.</p>
                <p>1 he breadth of the ftream that was deflected was much greater than that of the
                    body ; and the ſenſible deflection begun at a conſiderable diftance up the
                    ftream, eſpecially in the outer filaments.</p>
                <p>Laſily, the form of the curves was greatly influenced by the proportion between
                    the width of the trough and that of the body. The curvature was always leſs when
                    the trough was very wide in proportion to the body.</p>
                <p>Great varieties were alſo obferved in the motion or velocity of the filaments.
                    In general, the filaments increaſed in velocity outwards from the body to a
                    certain ſmall diftance, which was nearly the ſame in all caſes, and then
                    diminiſhed all the way outward. This was obferved by inequalities in the colour
                    of the filaments, <hi rend="italic">hγ</hi> which one could be obſerved to
                    outftrip an-other. I he retardation of thoſe next the body ſeemed to proceed
                    from friction; and it was imagined that without this the velocity there would
                    always have been greateft.</p>
                <p>I heſe obſervations give us conſiderable information reſpectſhg the mechaniſm of
                    theſe motions, and the action of fluids upon ſolids. The preffure in the
                    duplicate ratio of the velocities comes here agqin into view, we found, that
                    although the velocities were very different, the curves were preciſely the ſame.
                    Now the obferved preffures arife from the tranſverſe forces by which each
                    particle of a filament is retained in its curvilineal path ; and we know that
                    the force by which a body is retain-ed in any curve is directly as the fquare of
                    the velocity, and inverſely as the radius of curvature. The curvature,
                    therefore, remaining the ſame, the tranſverſe forces, and conſequently the
                    preffure on the body, muft be as the ſquare of the velocity : and, on the other
                    hand, we can ſee pretty clearly (indeed it is rigorouſly demonſtrated by D
                    Alembert), that whatever be the velocities, the curves <hi rend="italic">wit/</hi> be the ſame. For it is known in hydraulics, that it requires a fourfold or
                    ninefold preffure to pro-duce a double or triple velocity. And as all preffures
                    are propagated through a perfect fluid without diminution, this fourfold
                    preffure, while it produces a double velocity,. produces alio fourfold
                    tranſverſe preffures, which wiſl retain the particles, moving twice as faſt, in
                    the ſame curvilineal paths. And thus we ſee that the impulſes, as they are
                    called, and reſiſtances of fluids, haye a certain relation to the weight of a
                    column of fluid, whofe height is the height neceſlary for producing the
                    velocity. . How it happens that a plane ſurface, im-merſed in an extended fluid,
                    ſuſtains juſt half the pref-ſure which it would have ſuſtained had the motions
                    been ſuch as are ſketched in figure 6th, is a matter of more curious and
                    difficult inveſtigation. But we fee evidently that the preffure muſt be leſs
                    than what is there affigned; for the ſtagnant water a-head of the body greatly
                    di-mimſhes the ultimate deflections of the filaments : And it may be
                    demonſtrated, that when the part BE of the</p>
                <p>canal, ſig. 9. is inclined to the part AB in an angle leſs than 90 <hi
                        rend="sup"> 0</hi> , the preffures B G along the whole canal are as the
                    verſed fine of the ultimate angle oſ deflection, or the verſed fine of the angle
                    which the part BE makes with the part AB. Therefore, ſince the deflexions
                    re-ſemble more the ſketch given in ſig. 1 o. the accumulated ſum of all theſe
                    forces BG of ſig. 9. muſt be lefs than the ſimilar ſum correſponding to ſig. 6.
                    that is, leſs than</p>
                <p>O 2</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0108" facs="gri_33125011196389_0114.tif"/>
                <p>the weight of the column of fluid, having twice the productive height for its
                    height. How it is juft one-half, ihall be our next inquiry.</p>
                <p>And here we muſt return to the labours of Sir Iſaac Newton. After many beautiful
                    obſervations on the na-ture and mechanifm of continued fluids, he ſays, that the
                    reſiftance which they occaſion is but one-half of that occaſioned by the rare
                    fluid which had been the ſubject of his former propoſition ; " which truth,”
                    (ſays he, with his uſual caution andmυdefty), " I ihall endeavour to {how.”</p>
                <p>He then enters into another, as novel and as difficult an inveftigation, viz.
                    the laws of hydraulics, and endeavours to aſcertain the motion of fluids through
                    orifices when urged by preffures of any kind. He endeavours to afoertain the
                    velocity with which a ſiuid eſcapes through a horizontal oriſice in the bottom
                    of a veſſel, by the action of its weight, and the preſſure which this vein of
                    fluid will exert on a little circle which occupies part of the oriſice. To
                    obtain this, he employs a kind of approximation and trial, of which it would be
                    extremely difficult to give an extract ; and then, by increafing the diameter oſ
                    the veſſcl and oi the hole to infinity, he accommodates his reaſoning to the
                    caſe of a plane ſurface expofed to an indeſinitely extended ftream of fluid; and
                    laftly, giving to the little circular furface-the motion which he had before
                    aſcrſhed to the fluid, he fays, that the reſiftance to a plane ſurface -moving
                    through au unelaftic continuous fluid, is equal to the weight of a column of the
                    ſiuid whoſe height is one-half of that neceſſary for acquiring the velocity ;
                    and he ſays, that· the reſiſtance of a globe is, in this caſe, the ſame with
                    that of a cylinder of the ſame diameter. The reſiſſance, therefore, of the
                    cylinder or circle is four times leſs,’ and that of the globe is twice leſs than
                    their reſiſtances on a rare elaſtic medium.</p>
                <p>But this determination, though founded on principles or aſſumptions, which are
                    much nearer to the real Hate of things, is liable to great objections. It
                    depends on his method for afcertaining the velocity of the iſſuing fluid ; a
                    method extremely ingenious, but defective. The cataract, which he ſuppoſes,
                    cannot ex-ift as he ſuppoſes, deſcending by the full action off gravity, and
                    ſurrounded by a funnel of ftagnant fluid. For, in ſuch circumftances, there is
                    nothing to balance the hydroſtatical preſſure of this ſurrounding fluid ;
                    be-cauſe the whole preſſure of the central cataract is exn-ployed in producing
                    its own deſcent. In the next place, the preſſure which he determines is beyond
                    all doubt only half of what is obſerved on a plane ſurface in all our
                    experiments. And, in the third place, it is repugnant to all our experience,
                    that the reſiftance of <hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps"> sl</hi></hi> globe or of a pointed body is as great as that of its circular baſe. His
                    reafons are by no means convincing. He ſuppoſes them placed in a tube or canal ;
                    and ſince they are ſuppoſed of the ſame diameter, and therefore leave equal
                    ſpaces at their ſides, he concludes, that be-cauſe the water eſcapes by their
                    ſides with the ſame <hi rend="italic">velocity,</hi> they will have the ſame
                    reſiſtance. But this is by no means a neeeſſary conſequence. Even if the water
                    ſſiould be allowed to exert equal preſſures on them, the preſſures being
                    perpendicular to their ſurfaces, and theſe ſurfaces being inclined to the axis,
                    while in the caſe of the baſe of a cylinder it is in tl⅜e direction of the axis,
                    there muſt be a difference in</p>
                <p>the accumulated or compound preſſure in the direction of the axis. He indeed
                    ſays, that in the caſe of the cylinder or the circle obſtructing the canal, a
                    quantity of water remains ſtagnant on its upper ſurface ; viz. all the water
                    whoſe motion would not contribute to the moſt ready paſſage of the ſiuid between
                    the cy-liuder and the ſides of the canal or tube ; and that this water may be
                    conſidered as frozen. If this be the caſe, it is indifferent what is the form of
                    the body that is covered with this maſs of frozen or ſtagnant water. It may be a
                    bemiſphere or a cone ; the reſiſtance will be the ſame. -But Newton by no means
                    aſſigns, ei-ther with preciſion or with diſtinct evidence, the form and
                    magnitude of this ſtagnant water, ſo as to give con-ſidence in the reſults. He
                    contents himſelf with iay-ing, that it is that water whoſe motion is not
                    neceſſary or cannot contribute to the moſt eaſy paſſage of the water.</p>
                <p>i here remains, therefore, many imperfections in this theory. But
                    notwithſtanding theſe defects, we cannot but admire the efforts and ſagacity of
                    this great philoſopher, who, after having difcovered ſo many ſublime truths of
                    mechanical nature, ventured to trace out a path for the folution of a pr⅛blem
                    which no perſon had yet attempted to bring within the range of mathematical
                    inveſtigation. And his folution, though inac-curate, ihines throughout with that
                    inventive genius and that fertility of refource, which no man ever poſ-ſeſſed in
                    ſo eminent a degree.</p>
                <p>Tlroſe who have attacked the folution of Sir Iſaac Newton have not been more
                    ſucceſsful. Moſt of them, inſtead of principles, have given a great deal of
                    calculus’; and the chief merit which any of them can claim, is that of having
                    deduced ſome ſingle propoſition whiclt. happens to quadrate with fome <hi
                        rend="sup"> l</hi> - ſingle caſe of experiment, while their general
                    theories are either inapplicable, from difficulty and obfcurity, or are
                    diſcordant with more general obfervation.</p>
                <p>we muſt, however, except from this number Daniel Bernoulli, who was not only a
                    great geometer, but one of the ſirſt philoſophers of the age. He poſſeſſed all
                    the talents, and was free from the faults of that celebrated family ; and while
                    he was the mathematician of Europe who penetrated fartheſt in the inveftigation
                    of this great problem, he was the only perfon who felt, or at leaſt who
                    acknowledged, its great difficulty.</p>
                <p>In the 2d volume of the <hi rend="italic">Comment. Petropol.</hi> 1727, he
                    propoſes a formula for the reſiſtance of fluids, de-duced from conſiderations
                    quite different from thoſe on which Newton founded his folution. But he delivers
                    it with modeſt diffidence; becauſe he found that it gave a reſiſtance four times
                    greater than experiment. In the ſame differtation he determines the reſiſtance
                    of a ſphere to be one half of that of its great circle. But in his ſubiequent
                    theory . of Hydrodynamics (a work which muſt ever rank among the ſirſt
                    productions of the age, and is equally eminent for refined and elegant
                    mathematics, and ingenious and original thoughts in dynamics), he calls this
                    determination in queſtion. It is indeed founded on the fame hypothetical
                    principles which have been unſkilfully detached from the reſt of Newton’s
                    phyſics, and made the ground-work of all the ſubſequent theories on this
                    ſubject.</p>
                <p>In 1741 Mr Daniel Bernoulli publiſhed another diſ-</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0109" facs="gri_33125011196389_0115.tif"/>
                <p>fèrtation (in the 8th volume of the <hi rend="italic">Com. Petropol.}</hi> on
                    the action and reſiftance of fluids, limited to a very particular caſe ; namely,
                    to the impulfe of a vein of fluid falling perpendicularly on an infinitely
                    extended plane ſurface. This he demonſirates to be equal to the weight of a
                    column ot the fluid whoſe baſe is the area oſ the vein, and whoſe height is
                    twice the fall producing the velocity. Tins demonftration is drawn front the
                    true principles of mechanics and the acknowledged laws of hydraulics, and may be
                    received as a ſtrict phy-flcal demonftration. As it is the only propofition in
                    the whole theory that has as yet received a demonftration acceſſible to readers
                    not verfant in all the refinement of modern analyfis·; and as the principles on
                    which it pro-ceeds will undoubtedly lead to a folution of every pro-blem which
                    can be propoled, once that our mathemati-cal knowledge ſſiall enable us to apply
                    them—we think it our duty to give it in this place, although we muſt
                    acknowledge, that this problem is ſo very limited, that, it will hardly bear an
                    applicatiαn to any caſe that dif</p>
                <p>fers but a little from the expreſs conditions of the pro-blem. 1 here do occur
                    caſes however in practice, where it may be applied to very great advantage.</p>
                <p>Daniel Bernoulli gives two demonſtrations ; one of which may be called a popular
                    one, and the other is more fcientil∣c and introductory to further inveft⅛ιtion.
                    we ſſiall give both.</p>
                <p>Bernoulli firſt determines the whole action exerted m the efflux of the vein of
                    fluid. Suppofe the velocity of efflux <hi rend="italic">v</hi> is that which
                    would be acquired by falling through the height <hi rend="italic">h.</hi> It
                    is well known that a body moving during the time of this fall with the velocity <hi rend="italic">v</hi> would deſcribe a ſpace 2 <hi rend="italic">h.</hi> The effect, therefore, of the hydraulic action is, that in the time <hi
                        rend="italic"> t</hi> of the fall <hi rend="italic">h,</hi> there iffues
                    a cylinder or prifrn of water whoſe baſe is the croſs lection <hi rend="italic">J</hi> or area of the vein, and whofe length is 2∕&gt;. And this
                    quantity of matter is now moving with the velocity τ&gt;. The quantity of
                    motion, therefore, which is thus produced is 2 <hi rend="italic">s hν ;</hi> and this quantity of motion is produced in the time Λ And this is the
                    ac-cumulated effect of all the expelling forces, eſtimated in. the direction of
                    the efflux. Now, to compare this with trie exertion oi ſome preſſing power with
                    which we. are familiarly acquainted, let us fuppoſe this pillar 2 <hi
                        rend="italic"> s h</hi> to be frozen, and, being held in the hand, to be
                    dropped. It is well known, that in the time <hi rend="italic">t</hi> it will
                    fall through the height Z&gt;, and will acquire the velocity</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">v,</hi> and now poffeſſes the quantity of motion 2 <hi
                        rend="italic"> s h ∙υ_</hi></p>
                <p>and all this is the effect of its weight. The weight, theιefore, of the pillar 2 <hi rend="italic">s h</hi> produces the ſame effect, and in the ſame time,
                    and (as may eahly be ſeen j in the fame .gιadual manner, with the expelling
                    forces of the fluid in the veffel, which expelling forces ariſe from the
                    preffure of all the fluid in the veffel. Therefore the accumulated hydraulic
                    preffure, by which a vein of a heavy fluid is forced out through an orifice in
                    the bottom or fide oi a veffel, is equal (when eſtimated in thedirec-ι∙ion of
                    the efflux) to the weight of a column of the fluid, having for its baſe the
                    lection of the vein, and twice the fall productive of the velocity of efflux for
                    its height.</p>
                <p>Now let ABDC (fig. 11.) be a quadrangular veffel v. ιth upιight plane fides, in
                    one of which is an orifice EF. From every point of the circumference of this</p>
                <p>orifice, ſuppoſe horizontal lines Ef, F∕, &amp;c. which will mark a fimilar
                    ſurface on the oppofite fide of the veffel. Suppoſe the orifice EF to be ſſiut.
                    There can be no doubt but that the ſurfaces EF and <hi rend="italic">ef</hi> will be equally preffed in oppofite directions. Now open the orifice EF ; the
                    water will ruſh out, and the preffure on EF is now removed. There will therefore
                    be a tendency in the veffel to move back in the direction E <hi rend="italic">e.</hi> And this tendency mnſt be preciſely equal and oppofite to the whole
                    effort of the expelling forces. This is a conclu-lion as evident as any
                    propofition in mechanics. It is thus that a gun recoils and a rocket riſes in
                    the air; and on this is founded the operation of Mr Parents or Dr Barker’s mill,
                    defcribed in all treatiſes of mechanics, and moſt learnedly treated by Euler in
                    the Berlin Memoirs.</p>
                <p>Now, let this ſtream of water be received on a circular plane MN, perpendicular
                    to its axis, and let this circular plane be of ſuch extent, that the vein
                    eſcapes from its fides in an infinitely thin ſſieet, the water flowing off in a
                    direction parallel to the plane. The vein by this means will expand into a
                    trumpet-like ſſiape, having curved fides, EKG,FLH. w <hi rend="sub">e</hi> abftract at pre-ſent the action of gravity which would cauſe the vein to bend
                    downwards, and occafion a greater velocity at II than at G ; and we fuppoſe the
                    velocity equal in every point of the circumference. It is plain, that if the
                    action of gravity be neglected after the water has iffued through the orifice
                    EF, the velocity in every point of the circumference of the plane MN will be
                    that of the efflux through EF.</p>
                <p>Now, becauſe EKG is the natural ſſiape affirmed by the vein, it is plain, that
                    if the whole vein were covered by a tube or mouth-piece, fitted to its ihape,
                    and perfectly poliſhed, ſo that the water ſſiall glide along it, without any
                    friction (a thing which we may always iuppoie), the water will exert no preffure
                    whatever on this trumpet mouth-piece. Laftly, let us ſuppoſe that the plane MN
                    is attached to the mouth-piece by ſome bits of wire, lo as to allow the water to
                    eſcape all round ∙ by the narrow chink between the mouth-piece and the plane :
                    We have now a veffel confiſting of the upright</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">K <hi rend="sup">ab</hi> , <hi rend="sup">dc,</hi></hi> the tr. <hi rend="sup">um</hi> P <hi rend="sup">et</hi> GKEFLH, and
                    the plane MN ; and the water is eſcaping from every point oſ the circumference
                    of the chink GHNM with the velocity <hi rend="italic">ν.</hi> If any part of
                    this chink were ſſiut up, there would be a preffure on that part equivalent to
                    the force of efflux from the oppofite parr. Therefore, when all is <hi
                        rend="sup"> o</hi> pe∏, thete efforts oi efflux balance each other all
                    round.</p>
                <p>1 here is not therefore any tendency in this compound veffel to move to any
                    fide. . But take away the plane MN, and there would immediately ariſe a preffure
                    in the direction E <hi rend="italic">e</hi> equal to the weight of the column</p>
                <p>2 j /?. This is therefore balanced by the preffure on the circular plane MN,
                    which is therefore equal to this weight, and the propofition is demonſtrated. "</p>
                <p>A number of experiments were made by Profeffor Kraft at St Peterſhurg, by
                    receiving the vein on a plane MN (hg. <hi rend="smallcaps">ii.)</hi> which was
                    faſtened to the arm of a balance having a ſcale R hanging on the oppofite</p>
                <p>arm. I he refiſtance or preffure on the plane was mea-iùred by weights put into
                    the ſcale R; and the velocity of the jet was meaſured by means of the diſtance
                    KR, to which it· fpouted on a horizontal' plane.</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0110" facs="gri_33125011196389_0116.tif"/>
                <p>The reſults of theſe experiments were as-conformable to the theory as could be
                    wiſhed. The reſiſtance was always a little leſs than what the theory required,
                    but greatly exceeded its half ; the reſult of the generally re-ceived theories.
                    This defcct ſhould be expected ; for the demonſtration ſuppoſes· the plane MN to
                    be infinitely extended, fo that the film of water which iffues through the chink
                    may be accurately parallel to the plane. This never can be completely effected.
                    Alſo it was ſuppoſed, that the velocity was juſtly meaſured by the amplitude of
                    the parabola EGK. But it is well known that the. very putting the plane MN in
                    the way of the jet, though at the diſtance of an inch from the orifice, will
                    diminiſh the velocity, of the efflux through this orifice. This is eaſily
                    verified by experiment, 05-ferve the time in which the veſſel will be emptied
                    when there is no plane in the way. Repeat the experiment .with the plane in its
                    place ; and more time will be ne-ceſſary. The following is a note of a courſe of
                    ex-periments, taken as they ſtand, without any ſelection.</p>
                <p>N <hi rend="sup">o</hi> i » 3 4 5 <hi rend="sup">6</hi></p>
                <p>Refill, by theory 1701 1720 165 r ι6oa 1528 107»</p>
                <p>&lt;Refiih by experiment <hi rend="underline">1403 1463 1486 140t 1403 ιo¾ι</hi></p>
                <p>Difference ay 8 45 7 165 201 ιaj 51</p>
                <p>In order to demonſtrate this propofition in ſuch a manner as to furniſh the
                    means of inveſtigating the jwhole mechaniſm and action of moving fluids, it is
                    neceffary to premife an elementary theorem of curvilineal motions.</p>
                <p>If .a particle of matter deſcribes a curve line ABCE (fig. 13∙) by the continual
                    action of deflecting forces, which vary in any manner, both with reſpect to
                    inten-fity and direction, and if the action of thfeſe forces, in .every point of
                    the curve, be reſolved into two directions, perpendicular and parallel to the
                    initial direction AK; then,</p>
                <p>i. The accumulated effect of the deflecting forces, eſtimated in a direction AD
                    perpendicular to AK, is to the final quantity of motion as the fine of the final
                    change of direction is to radius.</p>
                <p>Let us ſirſt fuppofe that the accelerating forces act by ſtarts, at equal
                    intervals of time, when the body is in the points A, B, C, E. And let AN be the
                    de-flecting force, which, acting at A, changes the origi-nal direction AK to AB.
                    Produce AB till BH= AB, and complete the parallelogram BFCH. Then FB is the
                    force which, by acting at B, changed the motion BH (the continuation of AB) to
                    BC. In like manner make <hi rend="italic">Ch</hi> (in BC produced) equal to
                    BC, and complete the parallelogram C/EÂ <hi rend="italic">Cſ</hi> is the
                    deflecting force at C, &amp;c. Draw BO parallel to AN, and GBK perpendicular
                    to AK. Alſo draw lines through C and E perpendicular to AK, and draw through B
                    and C lines parallel to AK. Draw alſo HL, <hi rend="italic">h∕</hi> per-pendicular, and FG, HI, <hi rend="italic">hi,</hi> parallel to AK.</p>
                <p>It is plain that BK is BO or AN eſtimated in the direction perpendicular to AK,
                    and that BG is BF eſtimated in the ſame way. And fince BH = AB, HL or IM is
                    equal to BK. Alſo CI is equal to BG. Therefore CM is equal to AP+BG. By ſimilar
                    rea-ſcning it appears that E∕w = Ez-f-Z&gt;∕,=∑C⅛ <hi rend="sup">r</hi> 4-CM, = C^~f-BG, ſt-AP.</p>
                <p>Therefore if CE be taken for the meaſure of the final velocity or quantity of
                    motion, Em will be the accumulated effect of the deflecting forces eſtimated in
                    the direction AD perpendicular to AK. But Em is</p>
                <p>to CE as the fine of mCE is to radius; and the angle wCE is the angle contained
                    between the initial and final directions, becauſe <hi rend="italic">Cm</hi> is
                    parallel to AK. Now let the intervals of time diminiſh continually and the
                    frequency of the impulſes increaſe. The deflection be-eomes ultimately
                    continuous, and the motion curvili* iieal, and the propofition is demonfl rated.</p>
                <p>we ſee that the initial velocity and its ſubſequent changes do not affect the
                    conclufion, which depends entirely on the final quantity of motion.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">2.</hi> The accumulated effect of the accelerating forces,
                    when eſtimated in the direction AK of the original motion, or in the oppofite
                    direction, is equal to the difference between the initial quantity of motion and
                    the product of the final quantity of motion by the cofine of the change of
                    direction.</p>
                <p>For Cmr=C <hi rend="italic">I— rn l,</hi> =BM— <hi rend="italic">-ſq</hi> BM=BL-ML,=AK- FG <hi rend="smallcaps">AK=Ao-oK,~Ao-</hi> PN.</p>
                <p>Therefore PN+FG+∕Qj(the accumulated impulfe in the direction ΟΑ)~ ΑΟ—CM, —AO—CE×
                    coi fine of ECM.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Cor.</hi> I. The ſame action, in the direction oppofite to
                    that of the original motion, is neceffary for caufing a body to move at right
                    angles to its former direction as for ſtopping its motion. For in this caſe, the
                    co-fine of the change of direction is <hi rend="italic">— 0,</hi> and A Ο—CE
                    ×cofine ECM=Ao—ο, “ΑΟ, = the original motion.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Cor. 2.</hi> If the initial and final velocities are the
                    ſame, the accumulated action of the accelerating forces, eſti-mated in the
                    direction OA, is equal to the product of the original quantity of motion by the
                    verſed fine of the change of direction.</p>
                <p>The application of theſe theorems, particularly the ſecond, to our preſent
                    purpoſe is very obvious. All the filaments of the jet were originally moving in
                    the direction of its axis, and they are finally moving along the reſiſting
                    plane, or perpendicular to their former motion. Therefore their tranſverſe
                    forces in the direction of th&lt;s axis are <hi rend="italic">(in cumulo)</hi> equal to the force which would ſtop the motion. For the aggregate of the
                    ſimulta-neous forces of every particle in the whole filament is the ſame with
                    that of the ſucceſſive forces of one particle, as it arrives at different points
                    of its curvineal path. All the tranſverſe forces, eſtimated in a direction
                    per-pendicular to the axis of the vein, preciſely balance and ſuſtain each
                    other; and the only forces which can pro-duce a ſenſtble effect are thoſe in a
                    direction parallel to the axis. By theſe all the inner filaments are preſſed
                    towards the plane MN, and muſt be withſtood by it. It is highly probable, nay
                    certain, that there is a quantity of ſtagnant water in the middle of the vein
                    which ſuſtains the preffures of the moving filaments without it, and tranſmits
                    it to the ſolid plane. But this does not alter the caſe. And, fortunately^ it is
                    of no conſequence what changes happen in the velocities of the particles while
                    each is deſcribing its own curve. And it is from this circumſtance, peculiar to
                    this particular caſe of per-peudicular impulſe, that we are able to draw the
                    con-clufion. It is by no means difficult to demonſtrate that the velocity of the
                    external ſurface of this jet is con-ſtant, and indeed of every jet which is not
                    acted on by external forces after it has quitted the orifice : but this
                    diſcuſſion is quite unneceffary here. It is however extremely difficult to
                    aſcertain, even in this moſt fimp <hi rend="sup">,</hi> e</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0111" facs="gri_33125011196389_0117.tif"/>
                <p>caſe, what is the velocity of the internal fiîaments in the different points of
                    their progreſs.</p>
                <p>Such is the dtmonſtration which Mr Bernouilli has given of this propofition.
                    Limited as it is, it is highly valuable, becauſe derived from the true
                    principles of hydraulics.</p>
                <p>He hoped to render it more extenfive and applicable to oblique impulfes, when
                    the axis AC of the vein (fig. 13. n <hi rend="sup">0</hi> 2.) is inclined to
                    the plane in an angle ACN. But here all the ſimplicity of the caſe is gone, and
                    we are now obliged to aſcertain the motion of each filament. It might not
                    perhaps be impoſſible to determine what muſt happen in the plane of the figure,
                    that is, in a plane paſſing through the axis of the vein, and perpendicular to
                    the plane MN. Bat even in this cafe it would be extremely difficult to determine
                    how much of the fluid will go in the direction EKG, and what will go in the path
                    FLH, and to aſcertain the form of each filament, and the velocity in its
                    different points. But in the real ſtate of the caſe, the water will diffipate
                    from the centre C on every ſide ; and we cannot tell in what proportions. Let us
                    however eon-ſider a little what happens in the plane of the figure, and ſuppofe
                    that all the water goes either in the courſe EKG or in the courſe FLH. Let the
                    quantities of water which take theſe two eourfes have the proportions of <hi
                        rend="italic"> p</hi> aud <hi rend="sup">π</hi> . Letv <hi rend="sup">z</hi> 2α be the velocity at A, <hi rend="italic">fTb</hi> be the velocity at
                    G, and <hi rend="italic">*∕ 2 β</hi> be the velocity at H. ACG and ACH are the
                    two changes of di-rection, of which let <hi rend="italic">c</hi> and —¢ be the
                    coſines. Then, adopting the former reaſoning, we have the preſſure of the watery
                    plate GKEACM on the plane in the di- <hi rend="italic">p--</hi></p>
                <p>rectιon AC = ~~— ×2 <hi rend="italic">a—lc b,</hi> and the preffure of the ? +
                    n &lt; <hi rend="sup">r</hi></p>
                <p>∏--</p>
                <p>,ate HLFACN = —r—,× <hi rend="italic">2a</hi> 4- <hi rend="italic">2cβ,</hi> and their ſum</p>
                <p>pi _ <hi rend="underline">∕+ <hi rend="sup">π</hi></hi></p>
                <p>∕&gt;×2a-2r5+∏×2a-t-2c^ . . <hi rend="sub">1</hi> . ,. ,.</p>
                <p>= ----’ <hi rend="sup">w</hi> h' <hi rend="sup">c</hi> * <hi rend="sup">1</hi> being multiplied by</p>
                <p>the fine of ACM or *∕ 1—c <hi rend="sup">1</hi> , gives the preſſure
                    perpendicular to the plane MN- --—^~^^ <hi rend="sup">π</hi></p>
                <p>1_ ’ ∕+ <hi rend="sup">π</hi></p>
                <p>+ 2f∕3 .- <hi rend="sub">r</hi></p>
                <p>But there remains a preſſure in the direction- perpendicular to the axis of the
                    veiu, which is not balanced, as in the former caſe, by the equality on oppofite
                    ſides ot the axis. The preſſure. ariſing from the water which eſcapes at G has
                    an effect oppoſite to that pro-duced by the water· which eſeapes at H. when this
                    is taken into account, we ſhall find that their joint ef-</p>
                <p>r ,∙ <hi rend="italic">P— <hi rend="sup">π</hi> ∕-</hi></p>
                <p>forts perpendicular to AC are-^ψpp×2av ι—which, being multiplied by the cofinç-
                    of. ACM,- gives -the aβ-</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">. , p—∏ __</hi></p>
                <p>tion perpendicular to MN=— <hi rend="italic">~×2∏c∖I i-c <hi rend="sup">2</hi> .</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">P + <hi rend="sup">τ</hi> ∖</hi></p>
                <p>The ſum or joint effort of all thefe preſſures· is <hi rend="underline">∕X2a-2^4-∏×2a+2^</hi></p>
                <p>p÷∏ ∕+ <hi rend="sup">rι</hi></p>
                <p>Thus, ſrom this caſe, which is much ſimpler than can happen in nature, teeing
                    that there will always be a lateral efflux, the determination of the impulſe is
                    as uncertain and vague as it was ſure and preciſe in the former cate.</p>
                <p>It is therefore without proper authority that the abfolute impulſe of a vein of
                    fluid on a plane which re-ceives it wholly, is afferted to be proportional to
                    the fine of incidence. If indeed we fuppoſe the velocity in G and H are equal to
                    that at A, then <hi rend="italic">b-β <hi rend="sub">t</hi> z=a,</hi> and
                    the whole impulſe is 2aV <hi rend="sup">z</hi> 1—&lt; <hi rend="sup">z</hi> , as is commonly ſup-poted. But this cannot be. Both the velocity and
                    quantity at H are leſs than thote at G. Nay, frequent-ly there is no efflux on
                    the fide H when the obliquity is very great, we may conclude in general, that
                    the oblique impulte will always bear to the direct impulſe a greater proportion
                    than that of the fine of incidence to radius. If the whole water eſcapes at G,
                    and none goes off laterally, the preſſure will be <hi rend="italic">2a+2ac—2bcX,</hi></p>
                <p>1 —Λ The experiments of the Abbé Boſſut ſhow in the plaineſt manner that the
                    preſſure of a vein, ſtriking obliquely on a plane which receives it wholly,
                    diminiſhes faſter than in the ratio of the ſquare of the fine of incidence ;
                    whereas, when the oblique plane is wholly immerted in the ſtream, the impulfe is
                    much greater than in this proportion, and in great obliquities is nearly as the
                    fiue.</p>
                <p>Nor will this propoſition determine the impulfe of a fiuid on a plane wholly
                    immerted in it, even when the impulfe is perpendicular to the plane. The
                    circumſtance is now wanting on which we can eſtabliſh a calculation, namely, the
                    angle of final deflection. Could this be afcertained for each filament, and the
                    velocity of the filament, the principles are completely adequate to an accurate
                    folution of the problem. In the experiments which we mentioned to have been made
                    under the inſpection of Sir Charles Knowles, a-cylinder of fix inches diameter
                    was expoſcd to the action of a ſtream moving precitely one foot per ſecond ; and
                    when certain deductions were made for the water which was held adhering to the
                    poſterior baſe (as will be noticed afterwards), the impulte was found equal to
                    3∣ ounces avoirdupois. There were 36coloured filaments diſtributed on the
                    ſtream, in fuch ſituations as to give the moſt ufefal indications of their
                    curvature. If was found neceſſary to have ſome which paſſed under the body and
                    ſome above it ; for the form of theſe filaments, at the ſame diſtance from the
                    axis of the cylinder, was conſiderably. different : and thoſe filaments which
                    were ſituated in planes neither horizontal nor vertical took a double curvature»
                    In ſhort, the curves were ail’traced with great care, and the deflecting forces
                    were computed for each, and reduced to the direction of the axis ; and they were
                    ſnmrned up in ſuch' a manner as to give the impuite of the whole ſtream. The
                    deflections were marked as far a-head of the cylinder as they could be aſſuredly
                    ob-ſerved. By this method the impulſe was computed to be 2J-¾∙ ounces,,
                    differing from obtervation √ <hi rend="sub">δ</hi> - of an ounce, or about <hi
                        rend="sub"> τ</hi> ⅛ of the whole; a difference which may moſt reaſonably
                    be afcribed to the adheſion of the water, which muſt be moſt ſenfible in ſuch
                    ſmall velo-citiee. T∩ete experiments may therefore be confidered as giving all
                    the confirmation that can be deſired of the jiiſtnefs of the principles.· This
                    indeed hardly admits of a doubt :, but, alas ! it gives us but fmall’aſſiſtance
                    ; for all this is empirical, in as far as it leaves us in every caſe the taſk of
                    obſerving the form of the curves and the velocities in their different points.
                    To derive fer-vice from this moſt judicious method of Daniel Bernoulli, we muſt
                    diſcover feme method of determining,-»</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0112" facs="gri_33125011196389_0118.tif"/>
                <p><hi rend="italic">a</hi> <hi rend="italic">pmom,</hi> what will be the motion of the fluid whoſe courſe
                    is obſtructed by a body of any form. And here we cannot omit taking notice of
                    the caſual ob-fervation of Sir Iſaac Newton when attempting to de-termine the
                    reſiſtance of the plane ſurface or cylinder, or ſphere expofed to a ſtream
                    moving in a canal. He fays that the form of the reſiſt ing ſurface is of leſs
                    con-ſequence, becauſe there is always a quantity of water ſtagnant upon it, and
                    which may therefore be conſider-ed as frozen,; and he therefore conſiders that
                    water only whoſe motion is neceffary for the moſt expedi-tious diſcharge of the
                    water in the veffel. He endeavours to diſcriminate that water from the reſt ;
                    and although it muſt be acknowledged that the principle which he affumes for
                    this purpoſe is very gratuitous, becauſe it only ſhows that <hi rend="italic">iſ certain portions oſ the water,</hi> which he determines very
                    ingeniouſly, were really frozen, the reſt will iffue as he ſays, and will exert
                    the preffure which he aſſigns ; ſtill we muſt admire his fertility of reſource,
                    and his ſagacity in thus foreſeeing what ſubſequent obſervation has completely
                    confirmed, we are even diſpoſed to think, that in this caſual ob--ſervation Sir
                    Iſaac Newton has pointed out the only method of arriving at a folution of the
                    problem ; and that if we could diſcover <hi rend="italic">what motions are not
                        neceſſary ſor the mοβ expeditious paſſage oſ the water,</hi> and could thus
                    determine the form and magnitude of the ſtagnant water which adheres to the
                    body, we ſhould much more eaſily aſcertain the real motions which occaſion the
                    obſerved reſiſtance. we are here diſpoſed to have recourſe to the economy of
                    nature, the improper uſe of which we have ſometimes taken the liberty of
                    reprehend-jng. Mr Maupertuis publiſhed as a great diſcovery his principle of
                    ſmalleſt action, where he ſhowed that in all the mutual actions of bodies the
                    quantity of action was a minimum ; and he applied this to the folution of many
                    difficult problems with great ſucceſs, ima-gining that he was really reaſoning
                    from a contingent law of nature, ſelected by its infinitely wiſe Author, viz.
                    that in all occaſions there is the ſmalleſt poſſible exertion of natural powers.
                    Mr D’Alembert has, however, ſhown <hi rend="italic">(vi&amp;. Encyclopédie
                        Françoifi,</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">Action) that this was but a whim, and that the minimum
                        obſerved by Mau-pertuis is merely a minimum of calculus, peculiar to a
                        formula which happens to expreſs a combination of mathematical quantities
                        which frequently occurs in our way of conſidering the phenomena of nature,
                        but which is no natural meaſure of action.</hi></p>
                <p>But the chevalier D’Arcy has ſhown, that in the trains of natural operations
                    which terminate in the pro-duction of motion in a particular direction, the
                    interme-diate communications of motion are ſuch that the ſmall-eſt poſſible
                    quantity of motion is produced, we ſeem obliged to conclude, that this law.will
                    be obſerved in the preſent initance ; and it ſeems a problem not above our reach
                    to determine the motions which reſult from it. we would recommend the problem to
                    the eminent mathematicians in ſome ſimple caſe, ſuch as the propo-ſition already
                    demonſtrated by Daniel Bernoulli, or the perpendicular impulſe on a cylinder
                    included in a tubular canal ; and if they ſucceed in this, great things may be
                    expected, we think that experience gives great encouragement, we ſee that the
                    r£ſiſiance to a plane ſurface is a very ſmall matter greater than the weight of
                    a column of the fluid having the fall productive of</p>
                <p>the velocity for its height, and the ſmall exceſs is moſt probably owing to
                    adheſion, and the meaſure of the real reſiſtance is probably preciſely this
                    weight. The velocity oſ a ſpouting fluid was found, in fact, to be that acquired
                    by falling from the ſurface of the fluid ; and it was by looking at this, as at
                    a pole ſtar, that Newton, Bernoulli, and others, have with great ſagaci-ty and
                    ingenuity diſcovered much of the laws of hy-draulics, by ſearching for
                    principles which would give this reſult. we may hope for ſimilar ſucceſs.</p>
                <p>In the mean time, we may receive this as a phyfical truth, that the
                    perpendicular impulſe or reſiſtance of a plane ſurſace, wholly immerſed in the
                    fluid, is equal to the weight of the column haring the ſurface for its baſe, and
                    the fall producing the velocity for its height.</p>
                <p>This is the medium reſult of all experiments made in tbeſe precife
                    circumftances. And it is confirmed by a ſet of experiments of a kind wholly
                    different, and which feem to point it out more certainly as an im-mediate
                    conſequence of hydraulic principles.</p>
                <p>If Mr Pitot’s tube be expofed to a ſtream of fluid iffuing from a reſervoir or
                    veffel, as repreſented in ſig. 14. with the open mouth I pointed directly
                    againſt the ftream, the fluid is obſerved to Hand at K in the upright tube,
                    preciſely on a level with the fluid AB in the reſervoir. Here is a moſt
                    unexceptionable experi-ment, in which the impulſe of the ſtream is actually
                    oppoſed to the hydroſtatical preffure of the fluid on the tube. Preffure is in
                    this caſe oppoſed to preffure, be-cauſe the iffuing fluid is deflected by what
                    flays in the mouth of the tube, in the ſame way in which it would be deflected
                    by a firm ſurface. we ſſiall have occafion by and by to mention ſome moſt
                    valuable and inſtruc-tive experiments made with this tube.</p>
                <p>It was this which ſuggeſted to the great mathema-tician Euler another theory of
                    thé impulſe and reſiſtance of fluids, which muſt not be omitted, as it is
                    applied in his elaborate performance Οη the Theory of the Conſtruction and
                    working of Ships, in two vo-lumes 4to, which was afterwards abridged and uſed as
                    a text book in ſome marine academies. He fuppoſes a ſtream of fluid ABCD (fig.
                    15.), moving with any ve-locity, to ſtrike the plane ËD perpendicularly, and
                    that part of it goes through a hole EF, forming a jet EGHF. Mr Euler ſays, that
                    the velocity of this jet will be the ſame with the velocity of the ſtream. Now
                    compare this with an equal ſtream iffuing from a hole in the ſide of a veffel
                    with the fame velocity. The one ftream is urged out by the preffure occaſioned
                    by the impulſe of the fluid ; the other is urged out by the preffure of gravity.
                    The effects are equal, and the modifying circumftances are the fame. The cauſes
                    are therefore equal, and the preffure occaſioned by the im-pulſe of a ſtream of
                    fluid, moving with any velocity, is equal to the weight of a column of fluid
                    whoſe height is productive of this velocity, &amp;c. He then determines the
                    oblique impulſe by the refolution of motion, and deduces the common rules of
                    reſiſtance, &amp;c.</p>
                <p>But all this is without juſt grounds. This gentle-man was always ſatisſied with
                    the ſlighteſt analogies which would give him. an opportunity of exhibiting his
                    great dexterity in algebraic analyſis, and was not afterwards llartled by any
                    diſcordancy with obſervation. <hi rend="italic">Analyfit magis fidendum</hi> is a frequent affertion with him.</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0113" facs="gri_33125011196389_0119.tif"/>
                <p>Though he wrote a large volume, containing a theory of light and colours totally
                    oppoſite to Newton’s, he has publiſhed many differtations on optical phenomena
                    on the Newtonian principles, expreſsly becaufe hi6 own principles <hi
                        rend="italic"> non ideo facile anſam prod ebat analyfi inftru-endœ.</hi></p>
                <p>Not a ſhadow of argument is given for the leading principle in this theory,
                    t&gt;z⅛. that the velocity of the jet is the ſame with the velocity of the
                    ſtream. None can be given, but faying that the preffure is equivalent to its
                    production ; and this is affirming the very thing he la-bours to prove. The
                    matter of fact is, that the velocity of the jet is greater than that of the
                    ſtream, and may be greater almoſt in any proportion, which curious circumſtance
                    was difcovered and ingeniouſly explained long ago by Daniel Bernoulli in his <hi
                        rend="italic"> Hydrodyna-mica.</hi> It is evident that the velocity muſt be
                    greater, were a ſtream of ſand to come againſt the plane, what goes through
                    would indeed preſerve its velocity unchanged : but when a real ſiuid ſtrikes the
                    plane, all that does not paſs through is deflected on all ſides ; and by theſe
                    deflections forces are excited, by which the filaments which ſurround the
                    cylinder immediately fronting the hole are made to preſs this cylinder on all
                    fides, and as it were ſqueeze it between them : and thus the particles at the
                    hole muſt of neceſſity be accelerated, and the velocity of the jet muſt be
                    greater than that of the ſtream. λVe are diſpoſed to think that, in a fluid
                    perfectly incompreſſible, the velocity will be doubled, or at leaſt increafed in
                    the proportion of ι to √L If the fluid is in the finalleſt degree compreſſible,
                    even in the very ſmall degree that water is, the velocity at the ſirſt impulſe
                    may be much greater. D. Bernoulli found that a column of water moving y feet per
                    ſecond, in a tube ſome hundred feet long, produced a velocity of 136 ſeet per
                    fecond in the firſt moment.</p>
                <p>There being this radical defect in the theory of Mr Euler, it is needleſs to
                    take notice of its total inſuſſi-ciency for explaining oblique impulſesand the
                    refiſtance of curvilineal prows.</p>
                <p>we are extremely ſorry that our readers are deriving ſo little advantage from
                    all that we have ſaid ; and that having taken them by the hand, we are thus
                    obliged to grope about, with only a few ſcattered rays of light to direct our
                    ſteps. Let us ſee what aſſiſtance we can get from Mr d’Alembert, who has
                    attempted a folution of this problem in a method entirely new and extremely
                    ingenious. He ſaw clearly that all the followers of Newton had forſaken the path
                    which he had marked out for them in the ſecond part of his inveſtigation, and
                    had merely amuſed themſelves with the mathematical difcuſſions with which his
                    introductory hypothefis gave them an opportunity of occupying themſelves. He
                    paid the deſerved tribute oſ applauſe to Daniel Bernoulli for having introduced
                    the notion of pure preſſure as the chief agent in this bufineſs ; and he ſaw
                    that he was in the right road, and that it was from hydroſtati-cal principles
                    alone that we had any chance of explaining the phenomena of hydraulics.
                    Bernoulli had only confidered the preſſures which were excited in conſequence of
                    the curvilineal motions of the particles. Mr d’Alembert even thought that thefe
                    preſſures were not the conſequences, but tlie caufes, of theſe curvilineal
                    motions. No internal motion can happen in a fluid-blit in conſequence of an
                    unbalanced preſſure ; and every</p>
                <p>ſuch motion will produce an inequality of preffure, which will determine the
                    ſucceeding motions. He there-fore endeavoured to reduce all to the diſcovery of
                    thofe diſturbing preſſures, and thus to the laws of hydroſta-tics. Fie had long
                    before this hit on a very refined and ingenious view oſ the action of bodies on
                    each other, which had enabled him to ſolve many of the moſt difficult problems
                    concerning the motions of bodies, ſuch as the centre of oſcillation, of
                    ſpentaneous converſion, the preceſſion of the equinoxes, &amp;c. &amp;c.
                    with great facility and elegance. He ſaw that the fame principle would apply to
                    the action of fluid bodies. The principle is this.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">" In whatever manner any number of bodies are ſuppofed to act
                        on each other, and by theſe actions come to change their preſent motions, if
                        we conceive that the motion which each body would have in the following
                        infant ( if it became free), is refolved into two other motions ; one of
                        which is the motion which it really takes in the following infant ; the
                        other will be fuch, that iſ each body had no other motion but this ſecond,
                        the whole bodies would have remained in equilibria.” VIe</hi> here obſerve,
                    that " the motion which each body would have in the following inſtant, if it
                    became free,” is a continuation of the motion which it has in the firſt inſtant.
                    It may therefore perhaps be better expreſſed thus :</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">If the motions of bodies, anyhow acting on each other, be
                        cοnfdered in two confecuùve irfants, and if we conceive the motion which it
                        has in the frf infant as compounded of two others, one of which is the
                        motion which it actually takes in the ſecond infant, the other is ſueh, that
                        if each body had only thoſe ſecond motions, the whole fyfem would have
                        remained in equilibrio.</hi></p>
                <p>The propoſition itſelf is evident. For if theſe fe-cond motions be not ſuch as
                    that an equilibrium of the whole ſyftem would reſult from them, the other
                    component motions would not be thoſe which the bodies really have after the
                    change ; for they would neceſſari. ly be altered by theſe unbalanced motions.
                    See D’A-lembert <hi rend="italic">IIffai de Dynamique.</hi></p>
                <p>Aſſiſted by this inconteſtable principle, Mr d’Alem-bert demonſtrates, in a
                    manner equally new and fimple, thofe propofitions which Newton had ſo cautioufly
                    deduced from his hypothetical fluid, ſhowing that they were not limited to this
                    hypothefis, *u∕z. that the motions produced by fimilar bodies, limilarly
                    projected in them, would be fimilar ; that whatever were the preſ-ſures, the
                    curves deſcribed by the particles would be the ſame ; and that the refiſtance3
                    would be proportional to the ſquares of the velocities. He then comes to
                    confider the fluid as having its motions conſtrained by the form oſ the canal or
                    by ſolid obſtacles interpoſed.</p>
                <p>we ſhall here give a ſummary account of his fundamental propofitioπ.</p>
                <p>It is evident, that if the body ADCE (fig. 16.) did not form an obſtruction to
                    the motion of the water, the particles would deſcribe parallel lines TF, OK, PS,
                    &amp;c. But while yet at a diſtance from the body in F, K, S, they gradually
                    change their directions, and deſcribe the curves FM, K <hi rend="italic">nι,</hi> S <hi rend="italic">n,</hi> fo much more incflrvated as they are nearer
                    to the body. At a certain diſtance ZY this curvature will be inſenſible, and the
                    fluid included in the fpace ZYHQjvill move uniformly as if the fo!id body were
                    not there. The motions on the other fide oi the axis AC will be the ſame ; and
                    we need only</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0114" facs="gri_33125011196389_0120.tif"/>
                <p>attend to onc half, and we ſhall conſider theſe as in a ſtate of permanency.</p>
                <p>No body changes either its direction or velocity otherwiſe than by inſenſible
                    degrees : therefore the particle which is moving in the axis will not reach the
                    vertex A of the body, where it behoved to deflect inſtantane-ouſly at right
                    angles. It will therefore begin to be de-flected at ſome point F a head of the
                    body, and will de-ſcribe a curve FM, -touching the axis in F, and the body in M
                    ; and then, gliding along the body, will quit it at ſome point L, deſcribing a
                    tangent curve, which will join the axis again (touching it) in R; and thus there
                    will be a quantity of ſtagnant water FAM before or a head of the body, and
                    another LCR behind or aſtern of it.</p>
                <p>Let <hi rend="italic">a</hi> be the velocity of a particle of the fluid in any
                    inſtant, and <hi rend="italic">a'</hi> its velocity in the next inſtant. The
                    velocity <hi rend="italic">a</hi> may be conſidered as compounded of ct and <hi rend="italic">a".</hi> If the particles tended to move with the
                    velocities α <hi rend="sup">,</hi> 'only, the whole fluid would be in
                    equiiibrio (general principle), and the preffure of the fluid would be the fame
                    as if all were itagnant, and each particle were urged by a force —, <hi
                        rend="italic"> t <hi rend="sup">,</hi></hi> expreſſing an. indefinitely ſmall β <hi rend="sup">,</hi> '</p>
                <p>moment of time. <hi rend="italic">(N. B. —</hi> is the proper expreſſion of</p>
                <p>the accelerating force, which, by acting during the moment ∕∙, would generate
                    the velocity λ"; and «" is ſuppoſed an indeterminate quantity, different perhaps
                    for each particle). Now let <hi rend="italic">a</hi> be ſuppofed conſtant, or <hi rend="italic">a ~ ct.</hi> In this caſe <hi rend="italic">d' — o.</hi> That is to ſay, no preſſure whatever will be exerted on the ſolid body
                    unleſs there happen changes fin the velocities or directions of the particles.</p>
                <p>Let <hi rend="italic">a</hi> and a' then be the motions of the particles in
                    two conſecutive inſtants. They would be in equilibrio <hi rend="italic">. a"</hi></p>
                <p>if urged only by the forces —. Therefore if <hi rend="italic">y</hi> be the</p>
                <p>point where the particles which deſcribe the curve FM begin to change their
                    velocity, the preffure in D would be equal to the preffure which the fluid
                    contained in the canal <hi rend="italic">y</hi> FMD would exert, if each
                    particle were folicited by its force —, The queſtion is therefore reduced to the
                    finding the curvature in the canal <hi rend="italic">γ</hi> FMD, and the
                    ac-celerating forces — in its different parts.</p>
                <p>It appears, in the firſt place, that no preffure is ex-erted by any of the
                    particles along the curve FM : for ſuppoſe that the particle <hi rend="italic">a</hi> (fig. 17.) deſcribes the in-definitely ſmall ftraight line <hi
                        rend="italic"> a b</hi> in the firff inſtant, and <hi rend="italic">I c</hi> in the fecond inſtant ; produce <hi rend="italic">a b</hi> till <hi
                        rend="italic"> b d — a b,</hi> and joining <hi rend="italic">dc,</hi> the
                    motion <hi rend="italic">ab</hi> or <hi rend="italic">b d</hi> may be
                    confidered as compoſed of <hi rend="italic">b c,</hi> which the particle
                    really takes in the next inſtant, and a motion <hi rend="italic">d c</hi> which ſhould be deſtroyed. Draw <hi rend="italic">b i</hi> parallel to <hi
                        rend="italic"> d c,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">i t</hi> perpendicular to <hi rend="italic">b c.</hi> It is plain that the particle <hi
                        rend="italic"> b,</hi> ſolicited by the forces <hi rend="italic">be, ei</hi> (equivalent to <hi rend="italic">dc}</hi> ſhould be in equilibrio.
                    This-being eſtabliſhed, <hi rend="italic">.b e</hi> muſt be = o, that is,
                    there will be. no accelerating or retarding force at <hi rend="italic">b ;</hi> for if there be, draw <hi rend="italic">b m</hi> (fig.. 18.)
                    perpendicular to <hi rend="italic">b</hi> F, and the parallel <hi
                        rend="italic"> n q</hi> infinitely near it. The part <hi rend="italic">b n</hi> of the fluid contained in the canal <hi rend="italic">bn qm</hi> would
                    ſuſtain ſome preſ-</p>
                <p>ſure from <hi rend="italic">b</hi> towards <hi rend="italic">n,</hi> or from
                    « towards <hi rend="italic">b.</hi> Therefore ſince the fluid in this ſtagnant
                    canal ſhould be in equilibrio, there muſt alſo be ſome action, at leaſt in one
                    of the parts <hi rend="italic">b m, m q, qn,</hi> to counterbalance the action
                    on the partez/. But the fluid is ſtagnant in the ſpace FAM (in conſequence of
                    the law of continuity). Therefore there is no force which can act on <hi
                        rend="italic"> b m, τnq, ^ q n;</hi> and the preffure in the canal in the
                    direction <hi rend="italic">b n</hi> or <hi rend="italic">« b</hi> is
                    nothing, or the force <hi rend="italic">b e = 0,</hi> and the force &lt; <hi rend="italic">e</hi> is perpendicular to the canal ; and there is
                    therefore no preffure in the canal FM, except what proceeds from the part <hi
                        rend="italic"> γ</hi> F, or from the force &lt;∙z ; which laft being
                    perpendicular to the canal, there can be no force exerted on the point M, but
                    what is propagated from the part <hi rend="italic">y</hi> F.</p>
                <p>The velocity therefore in the canal FM is confient if finite, or infinitely
                    ſmall if variable : for, in the firſt caſe, the force <hi rend="italic">b e</hi> would be abſolutely nothing ; and Tn the ſecond caſe, it would be an
                    infiniteſimal of the ſe-coπd order, and may be conſidered as nothing in
                    com-pariſon with the velocity, which is of the ſirſt order. λVe ſhall ſee by and
                    by that the laſt is the real ſtate of the caſe. Therefore the ſiuid, before it
                    begins to-change its direction in F, begins to change its velocity in ſome point <hi rend="italic">y</hi> a-head of F, and by the time that it reaches F
                    its velocity is as it were annihilated.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Cor.</hi> i. Therefore the preffure in any point D ariſes
                    both from the retardations in the part <hi rend="italic">y</hi> F, and from
                    the particles which are in the canal MD : as theſe laſt.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">a "</hi></p>
                <p>move along the ſurface of the body, the force —&gt; de~</p>
                <p>ftroyed in every particle, is compounded of two others <hi rend="sub">r</hi> one in the direction of the ſurface, and the other per-pendicular to it ; call
                    theſe <hi rend="italic">p</hi> and <hi rend="italic">p'.</hi> The point D ia
                    preffed perpendicularly to the ſurface MD ; iſt, by all the forces <hi
                        rend="italic"> p</hi> in the curve MD ; 2d, by the force <hi rend="italic">ρ'</hi> acting on the ſingle point D. This may be neglected in compariſon
                    of the indefinite number of the others : therefore taking in the arch MD, an
                    infinitely fmaît portion· N <hi rend="italic">m, — s,</hi> the preffure on D,
                    perpendicular to the ſurface of the body, will be ≈s yQ&gt; and this fluent
                    muſt be ſo taken as to be — <hi rend="italic">0</hi> in the point M.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Cor.</hi> 2. Therefore, to find the preffure on D, we muſt
                    find the force <hi rend="italic">p</hi> on any point N. Let <hi rend="italic">u</hi> be the velocity of the particle N, in the direction N <hi
                        rend="italic"> m</hi> in any inſtant, and a + <hi rend="italic">u</hi> its velocity in the following inſtant ; we muſt have <hi rend="italic">p —</hi> Therefore the whole queſtion</p>
                <p>is reduced to finding the velocity <hi rend="italic">u</hi> in every pcſint N,
                    in the direction N w.</p>
                <p>And this is the aim of a ſeries of propoſitions which follow, in which the
                    author diſplays the moſt accurate and preciſe conception of the ſubject, and
                    great addrefs and elegance in his mathematical analyſis. He at length brings out
                    an equation which expreffes the preffure on the body in the moſt general and
                    unexceptionable manner. we cannot give an abſtract, becauſe the train of
                    reaſoning is already conciſe in the extreme : nor can we even exhibit the final
                    equation ; for it is conceived in the moſt refined and abſtruſe form of
                    indeterminate, functions, in order to embrace every poſſible circum-ſtance. But
                    we can affure our readers, that it truly expreffes the folution of the problem.
                    But, alas ! it is of</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0115" facs="gri_33125011196389_0121.tif"/>
                <p>no uΓe. So imperfect is our mathematical knowledge, that even Mr d’Alembert has
                    not been able to exem-plify the application of the equation to the ſimpleſt caſe
                    which can be propoſed, ſuch as the direct impulſe on a plane ſurface wholly
                    immerſed in the ſtuid. All that he is enabled to do, is to apply it (by ſome
                    modifications and ſubſtitutions which take it out of its ſtate of extreme
                    generality) to the direct impulſe of a vein of ſiuid on a plane which deflects
                    it wholly, and thus to ſhow its conformity to the ſolutioh given by Daniel
                    Bernoulli, and to obſervation and experience. He ſhows, that this impulſe
                    (independent of the deficiency arifing from the plane’s not being of infinite
                    extent) is ſomewhat lefs than the weight of a column whoſe baſe is the ſection
                    of the vein, and whoſe height is twice the fall neceffary for communicating the
                    velocity. This great philoſopher and geometer concludes by faying, that he does
                    not believe that any method can be found for ſolving this problem that is more
                    direct and ſimple ; and imagines, that if the deductions from it ſhall be found
                    not to agree with experiment, we muſt give up all hopes of determining the
                    reſiſtance of fluids by theory and analytical calculus. He ſays <hi
                        rend="italic"> analytical calculus ;</hi> for all the phyfical principles
                    on which the calculus pro-ceeds are rigorouſly demonſtrated, and will not admit
                    of a doubt. There is only one hypotheſis introduced in his inveſtigation, and
                    this is not a phyſtcal hypothe-ſis, but a hypotheſis of calculation. It is, that
                    the quantities which determine the ratios of the fecond ſiu-xions of the
                    velocities, eſtimated in the directions pa-railel and perpendicular to the axis
                    AC (fig. 16.) are functions of the abſciffa AP, and ordinate PM of the curve.
                    Any perſon, in the leaſt acquainted with mathematical analyſis, will ſee, that
                    without this ſuppoſi-tion no analyſis or calculus whatever can be inſtituted.
                    But let üs ſee what is the <hi rend="italic">phyβcal</hi> meaning of this
                    hypothecs. It is ſimply this, that the motion of the par-ticle M depends on its
                    ſituation only. It appears im-poſſible to form any other opinion ; and if we
                    could form Juch an opinion, it is as clear as day-light that the caſe is
                    deſperate, and that we muſt renounce all hopes.</p>
                <p>W¢ are forry to bring our labours to this concluſion; but we are of opinion,
                    that the only thing that remains is, for mathematicians to attach themſelves
                    with ſirm-neſs and vigour to fome ſimple cafes ; and, without aiming at
                    generality, to apply Mr d’Alembert’s or Bernoulli’s mode of procedure to the
                    particular circum-ſtances of the cafe. It is not improbable but that, in the
                    ſolutions which may be obtained of theſc particular cafes, circumftances may
                    occur which are of a more ge-neral nature. Theſe will be ſo many laws of
                    hydraulics to be added to our preſent very ſcanty ſtock ; and thele may have
                    points of reſemblance, which will give birth to laws of ſtill greater
                    generality. And we repeat our expreſſion of hopes of ſome ſucceſs, by
                    endea-vouring to determine, in ſome ſimple caſes, the <hi rend="italic">minimum
                        poflibile</hi> of motion. The attempts of the Jeſuit commentators on the <hi rend="italic">Prindpia</hi> to aſcertain this on the New-tonian
                    hypotheſis do them honour, anil have really given us great aſſiſtance in the
                    particular caſe which came through their hands.</p>
                <p>And we ſhould multiply experiments on the reſiſtance of bodies. Thoſe of the
                    French academy are undoubtedly of ineſtimable value, and will always be ap-</p>
                <p>peaied to. But there are circumſtaiices in thofe experiments which render them
                    more complicated than is proper tor a general theory, and which therefore limit
                    the concluſions which we wiſh to draw from them. The bodies Were floating on the
                    ſurface. This greatly modifies the deflections of the filaments of water,
                    cauſing ſome to deflect laterally, which would otherwiſe have remained in one
                    vertical plane ; and this circumſtance alſo neceffarily produced what the
                    academicians callcd the <hi rend="italic">remou,</hi> or accumulation on the
                    anterior part of the body, and depreſſion behind it. This produced an
                    ad-ditional reſiſtance, which was meaſured with great diffi-culty and
                    uncertainty. The effect of adheſion mull alſo havc been very conſiderable, and
                    very different ill the different caſes ; and it is of difficult calculation. It
                    cannot perhaps be totally removed in any experiment, and it is neceffary to
                    conſider it as making part of the reſiſtance in the moil important practical
                    caſes, viz. the motion of ſhips. Here we ſee that its effect is very great.
                    Every ſeaman knows that the ſpeed, even of a copper-ſheathed ſhip, is <hi
                        rend="italic"> greatly</hi> increaſed bygrealing her bottom. The difference
                    is too remarkable to admit of a doubt : nor ſhould we be ſurpriſed at this, when
                    we attend to the diminution of the motion of water in long pipes. A fmooth pipe
                    four and an half inches diameter, and 500 yards long, yields but one-fifth of
                    the quantity which it ought to do independent of friction. But adheſion does a
                    great deal which cannot be corn-pared with friction, we ſee that water flowing
                    thro’ a hole in a thin plate will be increaſed in quantity fully one-third, by
                    adding a little tube wlioſe length is about twice the diameter of the hole. The
                    adheſion therefore will greatly modify the action of the fila-ments both on the
                    ſolid body and on each other, and will change both the forms of the curves and
                    the velo-cities in different points ; and this is a fort of objec-tion to the
                    only hypotheſis introduced by d'Alembert&gt;, Yet it is only a fort oſ
                    objection ; for the effect of this adheſion, too, mull undoubtedly depend on the
                    fituation of the particle.</p>
                <p>The form of thefe experiments of the academy is ilI-fuited to the examination of
                    the reſiſtance of bodies wholly immerſed in the fluid. The form of experiment
                    adopted by Robins for the reſiſtance of air, and afterwards by the Chevalier
                    Borda for water, is tree from theſe inconveniences, and is ſuſceptible of equal
                    accuracy. The great advantage of both is the exact knowledge which they give us
                    of the velocity of the motion ; a circumſtance effentially ncceffary, and but
                    imperfectly known in the experiments of Mariotte and others, who examined
                    quieſcent bodies expofed to the action oſ a- ſtream. It is extremely difficult
                    to meaſure the velocity of a ſtream. It is very different in its different
                    parts. It is ſwifteft of all in the middle ſuperſi-cial filament, and diminiſhes
                    as we recede from this towards the ſides or bottom, and the rate of diminution
                    is not preciſely known. Could this be afcertained with the neceffary preciſion,
                    we ſhould recommend the fol-lowing form of experiment as the moſt ſtmple, eaſy,
                    eco-Homical, and accurate.</p>
                <p>Let /7, <hi rend="italic">b, c, d,</hi> (ſig. 19.) be four hooks placed in a
                    horizontal plane at the corners of a rectangular parallelogram, the ſides <hi
                        rend="italic"> tιr, Id</hi> being parallel to the direction of the ſtream
                    ABCD, and "the ſides <hi rend="italic">ab, ai</hi> being perpendicular to it.
                    Let the body G be fattened to</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0116" facs="gri_33125011196389_0122.tif"/>
                <p>an axis <hi rend="italic">e f</hi> of ſtiff-tempered ſteel-wire, ſo that the
                    fur-face on which the fluid is to act may be inclined to the ſtream in the
                    preciſe angle we deſire. Let this axis have hooks at its extremities, which are
                    hitched into the loops of four equal threads, ſuſpeuded fιom the hooks <hi
                        rend="italic"> a, b,</hi> c, <hi rend="italic">cl ;</hi> and let He be a
                    ſilth thread, ſuſpended from the middle of the line joining the points of
                    fuſpenſion <hi rend="italic">a, b.</hi> Let HIK be a graduated arch, whole
                    centre is H, and whoſe plane is in the direction of the ſtream. It is evident
                    that the impulle on the body G will be meaſured (by a proceſs well known to
                    every mathematician) by the deviation of the thread He from the vertical line HI
                    ; and this will be done without any intricacy of calculation, or any attention
                    to the centres of gravity, of oſcillation, or of percuſſion. Theſe muſt be
                    accurately afcertained with reſpect to that form in which the pendulum has
                    always been employed for meafuring the impulſe or velocity of a ſtream. Theſe
                    advantages ariſe from the circumſtance, that the axis <hi rend="italic">cſ</hi> remains always parallel to the horizon, we may be allowed to obſerve, by
                    the by, that this would have been a great improvement of the beautiful
                    experiments of Mr Robins and Dr Hutton on the velocities of cannon-ſhot, and
                    would have ſaved much intricate calculation, and been attended with many
                    important ad-vantages.</p>
                <p>The great difficulty is, as we have obſerved, to mea-fure the velocity of the
                    ſtream. Even this may be done in this way w <hi rend="sup">τ</hi> ith fome
                    preciſion. Let two floating bo-dies be dragged along the ſurface, as in the
                    experiments of the academy, at fome diſtance from each other late-rally, ſo.
                    that the water between them may not be ſen-ſibly diſturbed. Let a horizontal bar
                    be attached to them, tranſverſe to the direction of their motion, at a proper
                    height above the furface, and let a ſpherical pen-duλum be iuſpended from this,
                    or let it be ſuſpended from four points, as here deſcribed. Now let the
                    deviation of this pendulum be noted in a variety of velo-cities. This will give
                    us the law of relation between the velocity and the deviation of the pendulum.
                    Now, in making experiments on the refiſtance of bodies, let the velocity of the
                    ſtream, in the very filament in which the refiſtance is meafnred, be determined
                    by the devia-t.ion of this pendulum.</p>
                <p>It were greatly to be wiſhed that ſome more palpable argument could be found for
                    the exiſtence of a quantity of ſtagnant fluid at the anterior and poſterior
                    patts of tlie body. The one already given, derived from the confideration that
                    no motion changes either its velocity or direction by finite quantities in an
                    inſtant, is unex-ceptionable. But it gives us little information. The finalleit
                    conceivable extent of the curve FM in fig. 16. will anſwer this condition,
                    provided only that it touch-es the axis in ſome peint F, and the body in ſome
                    point M, fo as not to make a finite angle with either. But ſurely there are
                    circumſtances which rigorouſiy determine the extent of this ſtagnant fluid. And
                    it appears without doubt, that if there were no coheſion or fric-tion, this
                    ſpace will have a determined ratio to the fize of the body (the figures of the
                    bodies being ſuppoſed ſimilar).. Suppoſe a plane ſurfaee AB, as in ſig. io.
                    there can be no doubt but that the figure A <hi rend="italic">a</hi> D <hi
                        rend="italic"> b</hi> B will in every caſe be ſimilar. But if we ſuppoſe an
                    adheſion or tenacity which is conſtant, this may make θ change both in its
                    extent and its form : ſor its con-ſtancy oſ form depends on the diſturbing
                    forces being alwayβ as the ſquares of the velocity ; and this ratio oſ the
                    diſturbing forces is preſerved, while the inertia of the fluid is the only agent
                    and patient in the proceſs. But when we add to this the conſtant (that is,
                    invariable) diſturbing force of tenacity, a change of form and dimenlions muſt
                    happen. In like manner, the friction, or ſomething analogous to friction, which
                    produces an effect proportional to the velocity, muſt alter this ne-ceſlhry
                    ratio of the whole diſturbing forces. We may conclude, that the effect of both
                    theſe circumſtances will be to diminiſh the quantity of this ſtagnant fluid, by
                    licking it away externally ; and to this we muſt afcribe the fact, that the part
                    FAM is never perfectly ſtagnant, but is generally diſturbed with a whirling
                    motion. we may alſo conclude, that this ſtagnant ſiuid. will be more ineurvated
                    between F and M than it would, have been, independent of tenacity and friction ;
                    and that the arch LR. will, on the contrary, be leſs incur-vated.—And, laſtly,
                    we may conclude, that there will be ſomething oppoſite to preffure, or ſomething
                    which we may call <hi rend="italic">abjtra£lion,</hi> exerted on the poſterior
                    part of the body which moves in a tenacious fluid, or is expo-fed to the ſtream
                    of ſuch a fluid ; lor the ſtagnant ſtuid LCR adheres to the ſurfaee LC ; and the
                    paſ-ſing ſtuid tends to draw it away both by its tenacity and by its friction.
                    This mnſt augment the apparent impulſe of the ſtream on fuch a body ; and it
                    muſt greatly augment the reſiſtance, that is, the motion loſt by this body in
                    its progrefs through the tenacious fluid : for the body muſt drag along with it
                    this ſtagnant fluid, and drag it in oppoſition. to the tenacity and friction of
                    the ſurrounding fluid. The effect of this is moſt remarkably ſeen in the
                    reſiſtances to the motion of pen-dulums : and the chevalier Boat, in his
                    examination of Newton’s experiments, clearly ſhows that this conſti-tutes the
                    greateſt part of the reſiſtance.</p>
                <p>This moſt ingenious writer has paid great attention to this part of the proceſs
                    of nature, and has laid the foundation of a theory of reſiſtance entirely
                    different from all the preceding. We cannot abridge it ; and it is too imperfect
                    in its preſent condition to be offered as a body βf doctrine : but we hope that
                    the ingenious au-thor wiſl proſecute the ſubject.</p>
                <p>WE cannot conclude this differtation (which we acknowledge to be very
                    unſatisfactory and imperfect) better, than by giving an account of ſome
                    experiments of the chevalier Buat, which ſeem of immenſe conſequence, and tend
                    to give us very new views of the fub-ject. Mr Buat obſerved the motion of water
                    iffuing from a glaſs cylinder through a narrow ring formed by a bottom of
                    ſmaller diameter ; that is, the cylinder was open at both ends, and there was
                    placed at its lower end a circle of ſmaller diameter, by way of bottom, which
                    left a ring all around. He threw ſome powdered ſealing wax into the water, and
                    obſerved with great attention the motion of its ſmall particles. He law thoſe
                    which happened to be in the very axis of the cylinder deſcend along the axis
                    with a motion pretty uniform, till they came very near the bottom from <hi
                        rend="sub"> i</hi> this they continued to deſcend very ſlowly, till they
                    were almoſt in contact with the bottom ; they then deviated from the centre, and
                    approached the orifice in.</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0117" facs="gri_33125011196389_0123.tif"/>
                <p>ſtraiglit lines and with an accelerated motion, and at laſt darted into the
                    orifice with great rapidity. He had obſerved a thing ſimilar to this in a
                    horizontal ca-nal, in which he had fet up a ſmall board like a dam or bar, over
                    wh'eh the water flowed. He had thrown a gooſtberry into the water, in order to
                    meaſure the velo-city at the bottom, the goofet&gt;erry being a fmall matter
                    heavier than water. It approached the dam uniformly till about three inches from
                    it. Here it almoſt ſtood ſtill, but it continued to advance till almoſt in
                    contact. It then roſe from the bottom along the inlide of the dam with an
                    accelerated motion, and quickly eſcaped over the top.</p>
                <p>Hence he concluded, that the water which covers the anterior part of the body
                    expofed to the ſtream is not perfectly ſtag.nant, and that the filaments recede
                    from the axis in curves, which converge to the ſurface of the body as different
                    hyperbolas converge to the fame affymptote, and that they move with a velocity
                    continually increafing till they eſcape round the ſides ef the body.</p>
                <p>He had eſtabliſhed (by a pretty reaſonable theory, confirmed by experiment) a
                    propoſition concerning the preffure which water in motion exerts on the ſurface
                    along which it glides, viz. <hi rend="italic">that the prejfure is equal to
                        that which it would exert if at reft</hi> minus <hi rend="italic">the
                        weight of the column whoſe height would produce the velocity of the paftlng
                        (lream.</hi> Conſequently the preffure which the ftream exerts on the
                    ſurface perpendicularly expofed to it will depend on the velocity with which it
                    glides along it, and will diminiſh from the centre to the circumference. This,
                    ſays he, may be the reaſon why the impnlſe on a plane wholly immerſed is but one
                    half of that on a plane which deflects the whole ſtream.</p>
                <p>He contrived a very ingenious inſtrument ſor exami-ning this theory. A fquare
                    braſs plate ABGF (fig.</p>
                <p>20. ) was pierced with a great number of holes, and fixed in the front of a
                    ſhallow box repreſented edgewiſe in fig.</p>
                <p>21. The back of this box was pierced with a hole r, in which was inferted the
                    tube of glaſs CDE, bent fquare at D. This inſtrument was expofed to a ſtream of
                    water, which beat on the braſs plate. The water having ſilled the box through
                    the holes, ſiood at an equal height in the glaſs tube when the ſurrounding water
                    was ſtagnant ; but when it was in motion, it always ſiood in the tube above the
                    level of the ſmooth water without, and thus indicated the preffure occaſion-ed
                    by the action of the ſtream.</p>
                <p>when the inſtrument was not wholly immerfed, there was always a conſiderable
                    accumulation againſt the front of the box, and a depreſſion behind it. The water
                    before it was by no means ſtagnant : indeed it ſhould not be, as Mr Buat
                    obſerves ; for it conſiſts of the water which was eſcaping on all ſides, and
                    therefore upwards from the axis of the ſtream, which meets the plate
                    perpendi-cularly in <hi rend="italic">c</hi> conſiderably under the ſurface.
                    It eſcapes upwards ; and if the body were fuſſiciently immerſed, it would eſcape
                    in this direction almoſt as eaſily as laterally. But in the preſent
                    circumſtances, it heaps up, till the elevation occaſions it to fall off ſidewiſe
                    as faſt as it is renewed, when the inſtrument was immerfed more than its
                    ſemidiameter under the ſurface, the water- ſtill roſe above the level, and there
                    was a great depreſſion immediately behind this elevation. In con-Lquence of this
                    difficulty of eſcaping upwards, the wa-ter flows off laterally ; and if the
                    horizontal dim¢nſions of the lurface is great, this lateral efflux becomes more
                    difficult, and requires a greater accumulation. From this it happens, that the
                    reſiſtance of broad ſurfaces equally immerſed is greater than in the proportion
                    of the breadth. A plane of two feet wide and one foot deep, when it is not
                    completely immerſed, will be more refilled than a plane two feet deep and one
                    foot wide ; ſor there will be an accumulation againſt both : and even if theſe
                    were equal in height, the additional fur-face will be greateſt in the wideſt
                    body ; and- the ele-vation will be greater, becaufe the lateral eſcape is more
                    difficult.</p>
                <p>The circumſtances chiefly to be attended to are theſe.</p>
                <p>The preffure on the centre was much greater than towards the border, and, in
                    general, the height oſ the water in the tube DE was more than ∙∣ of the height
                    ue-ceffary for producing the velocity when only the central hole was open, when
                    various holes were opened at different diſtances from the centre, the height of
                    the water in DH continually diminiſhed as the hole was nearer the border. At a
                    certain diſtance from the border the water at E was level with the ſurrounding
                    water, ſo that no preffure was exerted on that hole. But the moft unexpected and
                    remarkable circumſtance was, that, in great velocities, the holes at the very
                    border, and even to a ſmall diſtance from it, not only ſuſtained no preffure,
                    but even gave out water ; for the water in the tube was lower than the
                    ſurrounding water. Mr Buat calls this a <hi rend="italic">r.on-prejfιυn.</hi> In a caſe in which the velocity ot the ſtream was three feet, and the preffure
                    on the central hole cauſed the water in the vertical tube to ſtahd 33 lines or
                    ⅜⅜ of an inch above the level of the ſuriounding ſmooth water, the action on a
                    hole at the lower corner of the ſquare cauſed it to ſtand 12 line» lower than
                    the furrounding water. Now the velocity of the ſtream in this experiment was 36
                    inches <hi rend="italic">per</hi> ſecond. This requires 21⅜ lines for its
                    productive fall ; whereas the preffure on the central hole was 33. This
                    approaches to the preffure on a ſurface which deflects it wholly. The
                    intermediate holes gave every variation of preffure, and the diminution was more
                    rapid as the holes were nearer the edge j but the law of diminution could not be
                    obferved.</p>
                <p>This is quite a new and moſt unexpected circumſtance in the action of fluids on
                    ſolid bodies, and renders the ſubject more intricate than ever ; yet it is by no
                    means inconliſtent with the genuine principles of hydroſtatics or hydraulics. In
                    as far as Mr Buat’s propoſttion conccrning the preffure of moving fluids is
                    true, it is very reaſonable to fay, that when the lateral velocity with which
                    the fluid tends to eſcape exceeds the velocity of percuiſion, the height
                    neceffa-ry for producing this velocity muſt exceed that which would produce the
                    other, and a non-preffion muſt be obſerved. And if we conſider the forms of the
                    la-teral filaments near the edge of the body, we ſee that the concavity of the
                    curve is turned towards the body, and that the centrifugal forces tend to
                    diminiſh. their preffure on the body. If the middle alone were ſtruck with a
                    confiderable velocity, the water might even rebound, as is frequently obferved.
                    This <hi rend="italic">actual</hi> rebounding is here prevented by the
                    ſurrounding water, which is moving with the fame velocity ; but</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0118" facs="gri_33125011196389_0124.tif"/>
                <p>the prcffurê may be almoſt annihilated by the <hi rend="italic">tendency</hi> to rebound of the inner filaments.</p>
                <p>Part (and perhaps a conſiderable part) of this appa-rent non-preſſion is
                    undoubtedly produced by the tenacity of the water, which licks off with it the
                    water lying in the hole. But, at any rate, this is an important fact, and gives
                    great value to theſe experiments. It gives a key to many curious pnenome-na in
                    the rehſtance of fluids ; and the theory of Mr Buat deſerves a very ſerious
                    confideration. It is all contained in the two following propoſitions.</p>
                <p>1. " <hi rend="italic">If by any cauſe whatever, a column of fluid, whether
                        making part of an indefinitefiuid, or contained in ſolid canals, comes to
                        move with a given velocity, the prejfure • which it exerted laterally before
                        its motion, either on the adjoining fiuid or on the fides of the canal, is
                        diminijhed by the</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">weight of a column having the height necejfary for
                        communicating the velocity of the motion.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">2. " The prefl'ure On the centre of a plane furface
                        perpendicular to theJlream, and wholly immcrfed in it, is ⅜ of the weight of
                        a column having the height necejfιry for communicating the velocity. For</hi> 33 h ⅜ ¾f 2l-r∙"</p>
                <p>He attempted to aſcertain the medium preffure on the whole ſurface,. by opening
                    625 holes diſperſed all over it. with the ſame velocity of current, he found the
                    height in the tube to be 29 lines, or 7 more than the height neceffary for
                    producing the velocity. But he juftly concluded this to be too great a meaſure,
                    be-cauſe the holes were ⅛ of an inch from the edge : had there been holes at the
                    very edge, they would have ſuſ-tained a non-preſſion, which would have
                    diminiſhed the height in the tube very conſiderably. He expofed to the ſame
                    ftream a conical funnel, which raiſed the water to 34 lines. But this could not
                    be conſidered as a meaſure of the preffure on a plane ſolid ſurface : for the
                    central water was undoubtedly ſcooped out, as it were, and the filaments much
                    more deflected than they would have been by a plane ſurface. Perhaps ſomething
                    of this happened even in every ſmall hole in the for-mer experiments. And this
                    ſuggeſts ſome doubt as to the accuracy of the meafurement of the preffure and of
                    the velocity of a current by Mr Pitot’s tube. It ſurely renders ſome corrections
                    abſolutely neceffary. It is a faſt, that when expofid to a vein of ſtuid coming
                    through a ſhort paffage, the water in the tube Hands on a level with that in the
                    reſervoir. Now we know that the velocity of this ſtream <hi rend="italic">does
                        not</hi> exceed what would be produced by a fall equal to <hi rend="sub">τ</hi> <hi rend="sup">8</hi> θ⅛ of the head of water in the refirvoir. Mr Buat made
                    many valuable ob∙ firvations and improvements on this moſt uſeful inſtrument,
                    which will be taken notice of in the articles Rivers and <hi rend="italic">WATF.R-Wsrks.</hi></p>
                <p>Mr Buat, by a ſcrupulous attention to all the circum-ſtances, concludes, that
                    the medium of preffure on the</p>
                <p>25.5</p>
                <p>whole ſurface is equal to-of the weight of a co.</p>
                <p>21.5</p>
                <p>lumn, having the ſurface for its bafc, and the produc-tive fall for its height.
                    But we think that there is an uncertainty in this conclufion ; becaufe the
                    height of the water in the vertical tube was undoubtedly augmented by an
                    hydroftatical preffure ariſtng from the accumulation of water above the. body
                    which was expofed to the ftream.</p>
                <p>Since the preffures are as the ſquares of tlie veloci-</p>
                <p>ties, or as the heights <hi rend="italic">h</hi> which produce the velocities,</p>
                <p>we may expreſs this preffure by the fmybol~— <hi rend="italic">'~b,</hi> or</p>
                <p>t,ι86∕&gt;, or <hi rend="italic">mh,</hi> the value of <hi rend="italic">m</hi> being 1,186. This exceeds confιderably the reſult of the experiments
                    of the French academy. In theſe it does not appear that <hi rend="italic">m</hi> ſenfibly exceeds unity. Note, that in theſe experi-ments the body was
                    moved through ſtill water ; here it is expofed to a ſtream. Thefi are generally
                    fupρofid to be equivalent, on the authority of the third law of mo∙ tion, which
                    makes every action depend on the 1 elative motions. we ſhall by and by fie ſome
                    cauſes of difference.</p>
                <p>The writers on this ſubject ſeem to think their taſk completed when they have
                    conſidered the action of the ſiuid on the anterior part of the body, or that
                    part of it which is before the broadeſt fiction, and have paid little or no
                    attention to the hinder part. Yet thofi who are moſt intereſted in the ſubject,
                    the naval architects, ſeem convinced that it is of no leſs importance to attend
                    to the form of the hinder part of a ſhip. And the univerſal practice of all
                    nations has been to make the hinder part more acute than the fore-part. This has
                    undoubtedly been deduced from experience; for it is in direct oppoſition to any
                    notions which a perſon would naturally form on this ſubject. Mr Buat therefore
                    thought it very neceffary to examine the action of the water on the hinder part
                    of a body by the fame method. And, previous to this examination, in order to
                    acquire ſome ſcientiſic notions of the ſubject, he made the following very
                    curious and inſtruſtive experiment.</p>
                <p>Two little conical pipes AB (fig. 22.) were inferted into the upright ſide of a
                    priſmatic veffel. They were an inch long, and their diameters at the inner and
                    outer ends were five and four lines. A was ς7 lines under the ſurface, and B was
                    73. A glaſs ſyphon was made of the ſhape repreſented in the figure, and its
                    internal diameter was 1 £ lines. It was placed with its mouth in the axis, and
                    even with the bafe of the conical pipe. The pipes being lhut, the veffel was
                    ſilled with water, and it was made to ſtand on a level in the two legs of the
                    ſyphon, the upper part being full of air. when this fyphon was applied to the
                    pipe A, and the water running freely, it rofe 3 2 lines in the ſhort leg', and
                    funk as much in the other, when it was applied to the pipe B, the water rofe 41
                    lines in the one leg of the ſyphon, and ſunk as much in the other.</p>
                <p>He reafons in this manner ſrom the experiment. The ring comprehended between the
                    end of the ſyphon and the ſides of the conical tube being the narroweſt part of
                    the orifice, the water iffued with the velocity cor-reſponding to the height of
                    the water in the veffel above the orifice, diminiſhed for the contraction. If
                    therefore the cylindcr of water immediately before the mouth of the ſyphon
                    iffued with the ſame velocity, the tube would be emptied through a height equal
                    to this head of water. <hi rend="italic">(charge j.</hi> If, on the contrary,
                    this cylinder of water, immediately before the mouth of the ſyphon, were
                    ſtagnant, the water in it would exert its full preffure on the mouth of the
                    ſyphon, and the water in the ſyphon would be level with the water in the veffel.
                    Between theſe extremes we muſt find the real ſtate of the caſe, and we muſt
                    meafure the force of non-preffure by the riſe of the water in the fyphon.</p>
                <p>we fie that in both experiments it bears an accurate</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0119" facs="gri_33125011196389_0125.tif"/>
                <p>proportion to the depth under the ſurface. For 57 : 73r=32 : 41 very nearly. He
                    therefore eſtimates the non-preffure to be of the height of the water above the
                    orifice.</p>
                <p>we are difpoſed to think that the ingenious author has not reaſoned accurately
                    from the experiment. In the firſt place, the force indicated by the experiment,
                    whatever be its origin, is certainly double of what he fuppofes ; for it muſt be
                    meaſured by the ſum of the riſe of the water in one leg, and its depreſſion in
                    the «ther, the weight of the air in the bend of the ſyphon being neglected. It
                    is preciſely analogous to the force acting on the water oſeillatmg in a fyphon,
                    which is acknowledged to be the ſum of the elevation and de-preſſion. The force
                    indicated by the experiment therefore is ∙i-⅛⅜ θf the height of the water above
                    the orifice. The force exhibited in this experiment bears a ſtill greater
                    proportion to the productive height ; ſor it is certain that the water <hi
                        rend="italic"> did not</hi> iffue with the velo--*'city acquired by the
                    fall from the ſurface, and probably did not exceed -J oſ it. The effect of
                    contraction muſt have been confiderable and uncertain. The velocity ſhould have
                    been meaſured both by the amplitude of the jet and by the quantity oſ water
                    diſcharged. In the next place, we apprehend that much oſ the effect is produced
                    by the tenacity oſ the water, which drags along with it the water which would
                    have ſlowly iffued from the fyphon, had the other end not dipped into the water
                    of the veffel. we know, that if the hori-zontal part of the ſyphon had been
                    continued far enough, and if no retardation were occafioned by fric-tion, the
                    column of water in the upright leg would have accelerated like any heavy body ;
                    and when the laft of it had arrived at the bottom of that leg, the whole in the
                    horizontal part would be moving with the velocity acquiredby falling from the
                    ſurface. The water of the vef-ſel which iiΓues through the ſurrounding ring very
                    quickly acquires a much greater velocity than what the water deſcending in the
                    ſyphon would acquire in the ſame time, and it drags this laſt water along with
                    it both by tenacity and friction, and it drags it out till its action is oppoſed
                    by the want of equilibrium produced in the ſyphon, by the elevation in the one
                    leg and the depreſſion in the other. We imagine that little can be concluded
                    from the experiment with reſpect to the real non-preffure. Nay, if the ſides of
                    the ſyphon be ſuppoſed infinitely thin, ſo that there would be no curvature of
                    the fila-ments of the ſurrounding water at the mouth of the ſyphon, we do not
                    very diſtinctly fee any fouree of non-preffure : For we are not altogether
                    fatisfièd with the proof which Mr Buat offers for this meaſure of the preffure
                    of a ffream of fluid gliding along a ſurface, <hi rend="italic">and οbβructed
                        by friction or any other caufe.·</hi> we imagine that the paſſing water in
                    the preſent experiment would be a little retarded by accelerating continually
                    the water de-ſcending in the ſyphon, and renewed a-top, ſuppofing tlie upper end
                    open; becauſe this water would not of it-ſelf acquire more than half this
                    velocity. It however drags it out, till it not only refiſts with a force equal
                    to the weight of the whole vertical column, but even ex-ceeds it by <hi
                        rend="sub"> τ</hi> ⅛⅛∙. This it is able to do, becauſe the whole preffure
                    by which the water iffues from an orifice has been ſhown (by Daniel Bernoulli)
                    to be equal to twice this weight, we therefore confider this beauti-Sil
                    experiment as chiefly valuable, by giving us a mea-</p>
                <p>ſure of the tenacity of the water; and we wiſh that it were repeated in a
                    variety of depths, in order to diſco-ver what relation the force exerted bears
                    to the depth. It would ſeem that the tenacity, being a certain deter-minate
                    thing, the proportion of 100 to 112 would not be conſtant; and that the obſerved
                    ratio would be made up of two parts, one of them conſtant, and the other
                    proportional to the depth under the ſurface.</p>
                <p>But ſtill this experiment is intimately connected with the matter in hand ; and
                    this apparent non-preſ-ſure'on the hinder part of a body expofed to a ſtream,
                    from whatever cauſes it proceeds, does operate in the action of water on this
                    hinder part, and mult be taken into the account.</p>
                <p>_ we muſt therefore follow the Chevalier de Buat in his diſcuſſions on this
                    ſubject. A priſmatic body, ha-ving its prow and poop equal and parallel
                    ſurfaces,. and plunged horizontally into a fluid, will require a force to keep
                    it firm in the direction of its axis preciſely equal to the difference between
                    the real preffures exerted on its prow and poop. If the fluid is at reſt, this
                    difference will be nothing, becauſe the oppofite dead preffures of the fluid
                    will be equal : but in a ſtream, there is ſuperadded to the dead preffure on the
                    prow the active preffure ariſing from the deflections of the filaments-of this
                    fluid.</p>
                <p>If the dead preffure on the poop remained in its full intenſity by the perfect
                    ſtagnation of the water be-hind it, the whole fenſible preffure on the body
                    would be the active preffure only on the prow, repreſented by <hi rend="italic">m h.</hi> If, on the other hand, we could ſuppoſe that the water behind the
                    body moved continually away from it ( being renewed laterally ) with the
                    velocity of the ftream, the dead preffure would be entirely removed from its
                    poop, and the whole ſenfible preffure, or what muff be oppoſed by ſome external
                    force, would be <hi rend="italic">m h</hi> -j- <hi rend="italic">h.</hi> Neither of theſe can happen ; and the real ſtate of the caſe muſt be between
                    thefo extremes.·</p>
                <p>The following experiments were tried : The perfo-rated box with its vertical
                    tube was expofed to the ſtream, the braſs plate being turned down the ſtream.
                    The velocity was again 36 inches per ſecond.</p>
                <p>The central hole A alone being opened, gave a non-preffure of _ - . 1 <hi
                        rend="sub"> 3</hi> lines..</p>
                <p>A hole B, ⅜ of an inch from the edge; gave - - 15</p>
                <p>A hole C, near the ſurfaee - <hi rend="sup">1</hi> 5&gt;7</p>
                <p>A hole D, at the lower angle - 1y,j</p>
                <p>Here it appears that there is a very confiderable non-preffure, increafing from
                    the centre to the border.. This increaſe undoubtedly-proceeds from the greater
                    la-teral velocity with which the water is gliding in from the ſides. The water
                    behind was by no means ſtag-nant, although moving off with a much fmaller
                    velocity than that of the paſſing ſtream, and it was viſtbly removed from the
                    fides, and gradually licked away at its further extremity.</p>
                <p>Another box, having a great number of holes, all open, indicated a medium off
                    non-preffure equal to 13,i lines.</p>
                <p>A nother of larger dimenfions, but having fewer holes, indicated a non-preffure
                    of 12⅛.</p>
                <p>But the moſt remarkable,, and the moſt important phenomena, were the following :</p>
                <p>The ſirſt box wa <hi rend="sub">l</hi> s fixed to the ſide of another box,</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0120" facs="gri_33125011196389_0126.tif"/>
                <p>Γo that, when all was made ſmooth, it madc a perfect cube, of which the
                    perforated braſs plate made the poop.</p>
                <p>The apparatus being now expofed to the ſtream, with the perforated plate looking
                    down the ſtream,</p>
                <p>The hole A indicated a non-preſſion - = 7,2</p>
                <p>B - . - 8</p>
                <p><hi rend="sup">C</hi> . ’ <hi rend="sup">6</hi></p>
                <p>Here was a great diminution of the non-preſſions produced by the diſtance
                    between the prow and the poop.</p>
                <p>This box was then fitted in the ſame manner, ſo as to make the poop of a box
                    three feet long. In this •fituation the non-preſſures were as follow î</p>
                <p>Hole A - - - <hi rend="sub">k</hi> <hi rend="sup">1</hi> &gt;5</p>
                <p>B 3&gt;. <hi rend="sup">2</hi></p>
                <p>The non-preſſions were ſtill farther diminiſhed by this increaſe of length.</p>
                <p>The box was then expofed with all the holes open, in three different iituations
                    :</p>
                <p>ift, Single, giving a non-preffute - I3’ <hi rend="sup">1</hi></p>
                <p>ad, Making the poop of a cube - 5’3</p>
                <p>3d, Making the poop of a box three feet long 3,0</p>
                <p>Another larger box :</p>
                <p>iſt, Single . - 12,2</p>
                <p>2d, Poop of a cube - - 5’</p>
                <p>3d, Poop of the long box - 3’ <hi rend="sup">2</hi></p>
                <p>Theſe are moſt valuable experiments. They plainly ſhow how important it is to
                    confider the action on the hinder part of the body. For the whole impulſe or
                    refiſtance, which muſt be withſtood or overcome by the external force, is the
                    ſum of the active preffure on the fore-part, and of the non-preffure on the
                    hinder-part ; and they ſſiow that this does not depend ſolely on the form of the
                    prow and poop, but alſo, and perhaps chiefly, on the length of the body. We ſee
                    that the non-preffure on the hinder-part was prodigiouſly diminiſhed (reduced to
                    one-fourth) by making the length of the body triple of the breadth. And hence it
                    appears, that merely lengthening a ſhip, without making any change in the form
                    either of her prow or her poop, will greatly diminiſh the refiſtance to her
                    motion through the water ; and this increaſe of length may be made by continuing
                    the form of the midſhip frame in ſeveral timbers along the keel, by which the
                    capacity of the ſhip, and her power of carrying fail, will be greatly increaſed,
                    and her other qualities improved, while her ſpeed is augmented.</p>
                <p>It is ſurely of importance to confider a little the phyfical cauſe of this
                    change. The motions are extremely complicated, and we muſt be contented if we
                    can but perceive a few leading circumſtances.</p>
                <p>The water is turned aſide by the anterior part of the body, and the velocity of
                    the filaments is increafed, and they acquire a divergent motion, by which they
                    alſo puſh afide the ſurrounding water. Οη each fide of the body, therefore, they
                    are moving in a divergent direc-tion, and with an increaſed velocity. But as
                    they are on all tides preſſed by the fluid without them, their motions gradually
                    approach to parallelism, and their velocities to an equality with the ſtream.
                    The progreſ-five velocity, or that in the direction of the ſtream, is checked,
                    at leaſt at firſt. But fince we obſerve the fi-laments conſtipated round the
                    body, and that they are got deflected at right angles to their former direction,</p>
                <p>it is plain that the real velocity of a filament in its ob-lique path is
                    augmented. We always obferve, that a ſtone lying in the ſand, and expofed to the
                    waih of the lea, is laid bare at the bottom, and the ſand is generally waſhed
                    away to ſome diſtance all round. This is owing to the increaſed velocity of the
                    water which comes into contact with the ſtone. It takes up more ſand than it can
                    keep floating, and it depofits it at a little diſtance all around, forming a
                    little bank, which fur-rounds the ſtone at a ſmall diſtance. when the filaments
                    of water have paffed the body, they are preſſid by the ambient fluid into the
                    place which it has quitted, and they glide round its ſtern, and fill up the
                    ſpace behind. '1 he more divergent and the more rapid they are, when about to
                    fall in behind, the more of the circumambient preffure muſt be employed to turn
                    them in-to the trough behind the body, and leſs of it will remain to preſs them
                    to the body itſelf. The extreme of this muſt obtain when the liream is
                    obſtructed by a thin plane only. But when there is fome diſtance between the
                    prow and the poop, the divergency of the fi-laments which had been turned afide
                    by the prow, ia diminiſhed by the time that they have come abreaſt of the ſtern,
                    and ſhould turn in behind it. They are therefore more readily made to converge
                    behind the body, and a more confiderable part of the ſurrounding preſſure
                    remains unexpended, and therefore preſſes the water againſt the fiern ; and it
                    is evident that this advantage muſt be ſo much the greater as the body is
                    longer. But the advantage will ſoon be ſuſceptible of no very confiderable
                    increaſe : for the lateral and divergent, and accelerated filaments, will ſoon
                    become ſo nearly parallel and equally rapid with the reſt of the ſtream, that a
                    great increafe of length will not make any confiderable change in thefe
                    particulars ; and it muſt be accompanied with an increaſe of friction.</p>
                <p>Theſe are very obvious reflections. And if we attend minutςly to the way in
                    which the almoſt ſtagnant ſtuid behind the body is expended and renewed, we
                    ſhall ſee all theſe effects confirmed and augmented. But as we cannot ſay any
                    thing on this ſubject that is preciſe, or that can be made the ſubject of
                    computation, it is needleſs to enter into a more minute diſcuſſion. The
                    diminution of the non-preſſure towards the centra moſt probably arifes from the
                    ſmaller force which is ne-ceſſary to be expended in the inflection of the
                    lateral fi . laments, already inflected in ſome degree, and having their
                    velocity diminiſhed. But it 13 a ſubject highly defer vi ng the attention of the
                    mathematicians ; and we preſume to invite them to the ſtudy of the motions of
                    thefe lateral filaments, paſſing the body, and preſſed into its wake by forces
                    which are ſufceptible of no difficult inveſtigation. It ſeems highly probable,
                    that if a prifmatic box, with a fquare ſtern, were fitted with an addition
                    precifely ſhaped like the water which would (abſtracting tenacity and friction)
                    have been ſtagnant behind it, the quantity of non-preſſion would be the fmalleſt
                    poſſible. The mathematician would ſurely diſ-cover circumſtances which would
                    furniſh ſome maxims of conſtruction for the hinder part as well as for the prow.
                    And as h,is ſpeculations on tins laſt have not been wholly fruitleſs, we may
                    expect advantages from his attention to this part, ſo much neglected.</p>
                <p>In the mean time, let us attend to the deductions' which Mr de Buat has made
                    from his few experiments.</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0121" facs="gri_33125011196389_0127.tif"/>
                <p>V∏ιen the velocity is three feet per ſecond, requiring the productive Height 2 ι
                    ,5 lines, the heights correſponding to the non-preffure on the poop of a thin
                    plane is 14,41 lines (taking in ſeveral circumſtances of judicious correction,
                    which we have not mentioned), that of a foot cube is 5,83, and that of a box of
                    triple length is 3,-31.</p>
                <p>Let <hi rend="italic">q</hi> expreſs the variable ratio of theſe to the height
                    producing the velocity, ſo that <hi rend="italic">q h</hi> may expreſs the
                    non-preffnre in every cafe ; we have,</p>
                <p>For a thin plane - - <hi rend="italic">q ~</hi> 0,67</p>
                <p>a cube - 0,271</p>
                <p>a box ~ 3 cubes - - o, 153</p>
                <p>It is evident that the value of <hi rend="italic">q</hi> has a dependence on
                    the proportion of the length, and the tranſverſe fiction of the body. A firies
                    oſ experiments oil priſmatic bo-dies ſhowed Mr de Bπat that the deviation of the
                    ſila-meπts was ſimilar in ſimilar bodies, and that this ob-tained even in
                    diſſimilar priſms, when the lengths were as the ſquare-roots of the tranfverſe
                    fictions. Although therefore the experiments were not ſufficiently numerous for
                    deducing the precifi law, it ſeemed not impoſ-ſible to derive from them a very
                    ufeful approximation. By a dexterous compariſon he found, that if Z expreffes
                    the length of the priſm, and r the area of the tranſverſe fiction, and ∑ <hi
                        rend="sub"> j</hi> expreffes the common logarithm of the quantity to which
                    it is prefixed, we ſhall expreſs the non-preffure pretty accurately by the
                    formula <hi rend="sup">1</hi> ~-</p>
                <p>Hence arifis an important remark, that when the height correſponding to the
                    non-preſſion is greater than <hi rend="italic">»,/s,</hi> and the body is
                    little immerfid in the fluid, there will be a void behind it.. Thus a ſurface of
                    a ſquare inch, juſt immerfid in a current of three feet per ſe--cond, will have
                    a void behind it. A foot ſquare will be in a fimilar condition when the velocity
                    is 12 feet.</p>
                <p>we muſt be careful to diſtinguiſh this non-preffure from the other caufis of
                    reſtſtance, which are always neceffarily combined with it. It is fuperadditive
                    to the active impreffion on the prow, to the ftatical preſ-ffure of the
                    accumulation a-head of the body, the llaticaî preffure ariſing from the
                    depreſſion behind it, the effects of friction, and the effects of tenacity. It
                    is indeed next to impoſſible to eſtimate them feparately, and many of them are
                    actually combined in the meafures now given. Nothing can determine the pure
                    nou-preffures till we can aſcertain the motions of the filaments.</p>
                <p>Mr de Buat here takes occaſion to controvert the univerſally adopted maxim, that
                    the preffure &lt;3ccaf1oned by a ſtream of ſtuid on a fixed body is the ſame
                    with that on a body moving with equal velocity in a qui-efcent fluid. He
                    repeated all theſe experiments with the perforated box in ſtill water. The
                    general diſtinc-tipn was, that both the preffures and the non-preffure in this
                    caſe was leſs, and that the odds was chiefly to be obfirved near the edges of
                    the ſurface. The gene-ral factor of the preffure of a ftream on the anterior
                    fur-face was <hi rend="italic">m</hi> ~ 1,186; but that on a body moving
                    through a ſtill ſtuid is only <hi rend="italic">m</hi> — 1. Fie obſerved no
                    non-preffure even at the very edge of the prow, but even a finſible preffure.
                    The preffure, therefore, or re-ſiſtance, is more equably diffufid over the
                    ſurface of the prow than the impulſe is.— He alfo found that the reſiſtances
                    diminiſhed in a leſs ratio than the ſquares of the velocities, eſpecially in
                    ſmall velocities.</p>
                <p>The non-preſſures increaſed in a greater ratio than the ſquares of the
                    velocities. The ratio of the velocities to a ſmall velocity of <hi rend="italic"
                        > 2(</hi> inches <hi rend="italic">per</hi> ſecond increaſed
                    geome-trically, the value of <hi rend="italic">q</hi> increafid arithmetically
                    ; and we may determine <hi rend="italic">q for any</hi> velocity V by this
                    proportion</p>
                <p><hi rend="sub">l</hi> V,</p>
                <p>L — : L ~ = 0,5 :y, and <hi rend="italic">q -</hi> --- <hi rend="sup">2</hi> &gt;,. <hi rend="sup">2</hi> . That is,</p>
                <p>2,2 22 <hi rend="sup">y,</hi> ■* <hi rend="sub">2</hi> ,8 ∙</p>
                <p>let the common logarithm of the velocity, divided by 2ſ, be conſidered as a
                    common number ; divide this common number by 2 <hi rend="sub">1</hi> ⅞∙, the
                    quotient is y, which muſt be multiplied by the productive height. The pro-duct
                    is the preffure.</p>
                <p>when Pitot’s tube was expofid to the ſtream, we had <hi rend="italic">m —</hi> 1 ; but rvhen it is carried through ſtill water, <hi rend="italic">m</hi> is =
                    1,22. when it was turned from the ſtream, we had <hi rend="italic">q —</hi> 0,157 ; but when carried through ſtili water, <hi rend="italic">q</hi> is
                    =0,138. A remarkable experiment.</p>
                <p>when the tube was moved laterally through the wa-ter, ſo that the motion was in
                    the direction of the plane of its mouth, the non-preffure was — 1. This is one
                    of his chief arguments for his theory of non-preſſion. Fie does not give the
                    detail of the experiment, and only infirts the reſult in his table.</p>
                <p>As a body expofid to a ftream deflects the ſtuid, heaps it up, and increaſes its
                    velocity; fo a body moved through a ſtill fluid turns it aſide, caufis it to
                    ſwell up before it, and gives it a real motion alongiide of it in the oppoſite
                    direction. And as the body expofid to a ſtream has a quantity of fluid almoſt
                    ſtagnant both before and behind; ſo a body moved through a ſtill fluid carries
                    before it and drags after it a quantity of fluid, which accompanies it with
                    nearly an equal velocity. This addition to the quantity of matter in motion muſt
                    make a diminution of its velocity ; and this forms a very conſiderable part of
                    the obfirved reſiſtauce.</p>
                <p>we cannot, however, help remarking that it would require very diſtinct and
                    ſtrong proof indeed to overturn the common opinion, which is founded on our moſt
                    certain and ſxmple conceptions of motion, and on a law of nature to which we
                    have never obferved an exception. Mr de Buat’s experiments, tho’ moſt
                    judiciouſiy contrived, and executed with ſcrupulous care, are by no means of
                    this kind. They were, of abſolute neceſſity, veιy complicated ; and many
                    circumſtances, impoſſible to avoid or to appreciate, rendered the obfirvatiυn,
                    or at leaſt the compariſon, of the velocities, veιy uncertain.</p>
                <p>we can fie but two circumſtances which do not admit of an· eaſy or immediate
                    compariſon in the two ſtates of the problem, when a body is expofid to a ftream <hi rend="italic">in</hi> <hi rend="italic">our experiments,</hi> in order to have an impulſe made on
                    it, there is a force tending to move the body backwards, independent of the real
                    impulſe or preffure occaſtoned by the deflection of the ftream. we cannot have a
                    ſtream except in eonfiquence of a Hoping ſurface. Suppofe a body floating on
                    this ſtrearti. It will not only fail down <hi rend="italic">along with the
                        flream,</hi> but it will fail <hi rend="italic">down the flream,</hi> and
                    will therefore go faſter along the canal than the ſtream does : for it is
                    floating on an inclined plane ; and if we examine it by the laws of
                    hydroſtatics, we ſliall find, that befides its own tendency to <hi rend="italic"
                        > flide</hi> down this inclined plane, there is an odds of hydroſtatical
                    preffure, which <hi rend="italic">pujhes</hi> it down this plane. It will
                    therefore go along the canal faſter than</p>
                <p>the ſtream For this acceleration depends on the différence of preffure at the
                    two ends, and will be more re-</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0122" facs="gri_33125011196389_0128.tif"/>
                <p>markabIe as the body is larger, and eſpecially as it is longer. This may be
                    diſtinctly obſerved. All floating bodies go into the ſtream of the river,
                    becaufe there they find the ſmalleſt obſtruction to the acquiſition of this
                    motion along the inclined plane ; and when a number of bodies are thus floating
                    down the ftream, the largeft and longeft outſtrip the reft. A log of wood
                    floating down in this manner may be obſerved to make its way very faſt among the
                    chips and ſaw-duſt which float a-longſide of it.</p>
                <p>Now when, in the courſe of our experiments, a body is ſupported againſt the
                    action of a ſtream, and the im-pulſe is meaſured by .the force employed to
                    fupport it, it ⅛ plain that part of this force is employed to act againſt that
                    tendency which the body has to outſtrip the ſtream. This does not appear in our
                    experiment, when we move a body with the velocity of this ſtream through ſtill
                    water having a horizontal furface.</p>
                <p>The other diſtinguiſhing circumſtance is, that the re-tardations of a ſtream
                    ariſing from friction are found to be nearly as the velocities, when, therefore,
                    a ſtream moving in a limited canal is checked by a body put in its way, the
                    diminution of velocity occaſioned by the friction of the ſtream having already
                    produced its effect, the impulſe is not affected by it ; but when the body puts
                    the ftill water in motion, the friction of the bottom produces ſome effect, by
                    retarding the receſs of the water. This, however, muſt be next to no-thing.</p>
                <p>The chief difference will ariſe from its being almoſt impoſſible to make an
                    exact compariſon of the veloci-ties : for when a body is moved againſt the
                    ftream, the relative velocity is the ſame in all the filaments. But ■when we
                    expoſe a body to a ftream, the velocity of the different filaments is not the
                    ſame ; becauſe it decreaſes from the middle of the flream to the ſides.</p>
                <p>Mr Buat found the total ſenſible refιftance of a plate 12 inches ſquare, and
                    meaſured, not by the height of water in the tube of the perforated box, but by
                    weights acting on the arm of a balance, having its centre 15 inches under the
                    ſurface of a ſtream moving three feet per ſecond, to be 19,46 pounds; that of a
                    cube of the ſame dimenfions was 15,22 ; and that of a priſm three feet long was
                    13,87 ; that of a priſm fix feet long was 14,27. The three ſirſt agree extremely
                    well with the determination of <hi rend="italic">m</hi> and <hi rend="italic">q,</hi> by the experiments with the perforated box. The total reſiſtance of
                    the laſt was undoubtedly much increaſed by friction, and by the retrograde force
                    of ſo long a priſm floating in an in-clined ſtream. This laſt by computation is
                    0,223 pounds; this added to <hi rend="italic">h (m</hi> -j- y), which is
                    13,59,gives <hi rend="sup">l</hi> 3&gt;θ <hi rend="sup">1</hi> , leaving
                    0,46 for the effect of friction.</p>
                <p>If the ſame reſiſtances be computed on the ſuppoſi-tion that the body moves in
                    ſtill water, in which caſe we have <hi rend="italic">m</hi> = 1, and <hi
                        rend="italic"> q</hi> for a thin plate = 0,433 » and if <hi rend="italic">q</hi> be computed for the lengths of the other two bo-</p>
                <p>dies by the formula 1 — L 1,42 +^^7- ; we ſhall get for <hi rend="italic">q Vs</hi></p>
                <p>the reſiſtances 14,94; 12,22 ; and 11,49.</p>
                <p>Hence Mr Buat concludes, that the reſiſtances in theſe two ſtates are nearly in
                    the ratio of 13 to ιo⅛ This, he thinks, will account for the difference
                    ohſer-ved in the experiments of different authors.</p>
                <p>Mr Buat next endeavours to afeertain the quantity of water which is made to
                    adhere in ſome degree to a</p>
                <p>body which is carried along thro’ ſtill water, or which remains nearly ſtagnant
                    in the midſt of a ſtream. He takes the ſum of the motions in the direction of
                    the ſtream, viz. the ſum of the actual motions of all thoſe particles which have
                    loſt part of their motion, and he divides this ſum by the general velocity of
                    the ſtream. The quotient is equivalent to a certain quantity of water perfectly
                    ſtagnant round the body, without being able to determine this with precilion, he
                    obſerves, that it augments as the reſiſtance diminiſhes ; for in the caſe of a
                    longer body, the filaments are obferved to con-verge to a greater diſtance
                    behind the body. The ſtagnant maſs a-head of the body is more conſtant ; for the
                    deflection and reſiſtance at the prow are obſervcd not to be affected by the
                    length of the body. Mr Buat, by a very nice analyſis of many circumſtances,
                    comes to this conclufion, that the whole quantity of fluid, which in this manner
                    accompanies the ſolid body, re-mains the ſame whatever is the velocity. He might
                    have deduced it at once, from the conſtderation that the curves deſcribed by the
                    filaments are the ſame in all ve-locities.</p>
                <p>He then relates a number of experiments made to ſ certain the abſolute quantity
                    thus made to accompany the body. Theſe were made by cauſing pendulums to
                    oſcillate in fluids. Newton had determined the re-ſiſtances to fuch oſcillation
                    by the diminution of the arches of vibration. Mr Buat determines the quantity of
                    dragged fluid by the increaſe of their duration ; for this ſtagnation or
                    dragging is in fact adding a quantity of matter to be moved, without any
                    addition to the moving force. It was ingeniouſly obſerved by Newton, that the
                    time of oſcillation was not fenſibly affected by the reſiſtance of the fluid : a
                    compenfation, almoſt complete, being made by the diminution of the arches of
                    vihration ; and experiment confirmed this. If, there-fore, a great augmentation
                    of the time of vibration be obſerved, it muſt be afcribed to the additional
                    quantity of matter which is thus dragged into motion, and it may be employed for
                    its meafurement. Thus, let a be the length of a pendulum ſwinging féconds in
                    vacuo, and <hi rend="italic">I</hi> the length of a ſecond’s pendulum ſwinging
                    in a fluid. Let <hi rend="italic">p</hi> be the weight of the body in the
                    fluid, and P the weight of the fluid diſplaced by it j. P -j- <hi rend="italic">p</hi> will ex-</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">P+λ</hi></p>
                <p>preſs its weight in vacuo, and ■ ∙~ will be the ratio p 4. A</p>
                <p>of theſe weights. We ſhall therefore have ■—- —</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps"><hi rend="sup"> a</hi> - j ,</hi> <hi rend="sup">a</hi> P</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">I</hi> and ∕- <hi rend="sub">p+</hi> ^.</p>
                <p>Let <hi rend="italic">η</hi> P expreſs the ſum of the fluid difp!⅛ced, and the
                    fluid dragged along, <hi rend="italic">n</hi> being a number greater than
                    unity, to be determined by experiment. The maſs in motion is no longer P -f- <hi
                        rend="italic"> p <hi rend="sub">y</hi></hi> but P 4- <hi rend="italic">η</hi> P, while its weight in the fluid is
                    ſtill <hi rend="italic">ρ.</hi> Therefore we nauſt have</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">, <hi rend="sup">a</hi> P “_ , _( ∕ <hi rend="sup">a</hi> ∖</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="sup"> l</hi> ~nPJ <hi rend="sub">r</hi> p=</hi> <hi rend="sup">P</hi> V~"~ <hi rend="sup">1</hi> )'</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">P <hi rend="sup">+</hi></hi></p>
                <p>A prodigious number of experiments· made by Mr Baat on ſpheres vibrating in
                    water gave values of », which were very conſtant, namely, ſrom 1,5 to 1,7 ; and
                    by conſidering the circumſtances which accompa-nied the variations of <hi
                        rend="italic"> n (</hi> which he found to ariſe chiefly from the curvature
                    of the path deſcribed by the</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0123" facs="gri_33125011196389_0129.tif"/>
                <p>ball), he ſtAtes the mean value of the number <hi rend="italic">n</hi> at
                    1,583. So that a ſphere in motion drags along with it about - <hi rend="sub">1</hi> ⅞ of its own bulk of fluid with a velocity equal to its own.</p>
                <p>He made ſimilar experiments with priſms, pyramids, and other bodies, and found a
                    complete confirmation of his affertion, that priſms of equal lengths and
                    ſec-tions, though diſſhnilar, dragged equal quantities of fluid ; that ſimilar
                    priſms. and priſms not ſimilar, but whofe length were as the ſquare-root of
                    their fictions, dragged quantities proportional to their bulks.</p>
                <p>He found a general value of <hi rend="italic">n</hi> for priſmatic bodies,
                    which alone may be conſidered as a valuable truth ;</p>
                <p>V <hi rend="sup">z</hi> ί</p>
                <p>namely, that « = 0,705 — + 1,13.</p>
                <p>From all theſe circumftances, we fee an intimate connection between the
                    preffures, non∙preffures, and the fluid dragged along with the body. Indeed this
                    is immediately deducible from the ſirſt principles ; for what Mr Buat calls the <hi rend="italic">dragged fluid</hi> is in fact a cer-tain portion of the
                    whole change of motion produced in the direction of the bodies motion.</p>
                <p>It was found, that with reſpect to thin planes, ſpheres, and pyramidal bodies of
                    equal bafis, the reſiſtances were inverfily as the quantities of fluid dragged
                    along.</p>
                <p>The inte∏igent reader will readily obferve, that theſe views of the Chevalier
                    Buat are not ſo much diſcoveries of new principles as they are claſſiſications
                    of conſe-quences, which may all be deduced from the general prin-¢iples employed
                    by D’Alembert and other mathemati-cians. But they greatly aſſiſt us in forming
                    notions of different parts of the procedure of nature in the mutual action of
                    fluids and ſolids on each other. This rauſt be very acceptable in a ſubject
                    which it is by no means probable that we ſhall be able to inveftigate with
                    mathematical preciſion. we have given an account of theſe laſt obſervations,
                    that we may omit nothing of confiquence that has been written on the ſubject ;
                    and we take this opportunity of recommending the <hi rend="italic">Hydraulique</hi> of Mr Buat as a moſt ingenious work, containing more original, ingenious,
                    and practically uſeful thoughts, than all the performances we have met with. His
                    doctrine of <hi rend="italic">the principle of uniform motion oſ βuids in pipes
                        and open canals,</hi> will be of immenſe fervice to all engi-F,eers, and
                    enable them to determine with ſuſſicient preciſion the moft important queſtions
                    in their profeſſion ; queſtions which at preſent they are hardly able to gueſs
                    at. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Rivers</hi> and <hi rend="italic">WATER Works.</hi></p>
                <p>The only circumſtance which we have not noticed in detail, is the change of
                    reſiſtance produced by the void, or tendency to a, void, which obtains behind
                    the body ; and we omitted a particular difcuſſion, merely becauie we could ſay
                    nothing ſuſſiciently preciſe on the ſubject. Perfons not accuſtomed to the
                    difiuſſions in the phyſico-mathematical ſciences, are apt to entertain doubts or
                    falfi notions connected with this circumſtance, which we ſhall attempt to remove
                    ; and with this we ſhall conclude this long and unſatisfactory differtation.</p>
                <p>If a fluid were perfectly incoropreſſible, and were contained in a vefftl
                    incapable of extenſion, it is impoſſible that any void could be formed behind
                    the body; and in this caſe it is not very eaſy to fie how motion could be
                    performed in it. A ſphere moved in ſuch a medium could not advance the ſmalleſt
                    diſtance, unleſs <hi rend="italic">fame</hi> particles of the fluid, in
                    filling up the fpace left ⅜y it, moved with a velocity next to infinite. Some</p>
                <p>degree oſ compreffibility, however ſmall, ſcems neceſlary. If this be
                    inſenſible, it may be rigidly demonſtrated, that an external force of
                    compreſſion will make no <hi rend="italic">ſenfible</hi> change in the
                    internal motions, or in the reſiſtances. <hi rend="sup">r</hi> Γhis indeed is
                    not obvious, but is an immediate conſequence of the <hi rend="italic">quaquaverpum</hi> preffure of fluids. As much as the preſſiire <hi
                        rend="italic"> is</hi> augmented by the externaI compreſſions on one ſide
                    of a body, fo much is <hi rend="italic">it</hi> augmented on the other ſide ;
                    and the fame muſt be faid of every particle. Nothing more is neceffary for
                    ficuring the ſame motions by the ſame partial and internal forces; and this is
                    fully verified by experiment, water re-mains equally fluid under any
                    compreffion3. In ſome of Sir Iſaac Newton’s experiments balls of four inches
                    diameter were made ſo light as to preponderate in wa-ter only three grains. '1
                    heſe balls defcended in the ſame manner as they would have defcended in a fluid
                    where the reſiſtance was equal in every part ; yet, when they were near the
                    bottom of a veſtel nine feet deep, the compreſſion round them was at laſt 2400
                    times the moving force ; whereas, when near the top of the veffel, it was not
                    above 50 or 60 times.</p>
                <p>But in a fluid ſenſibly compreſſible, or which is not confined, a void may be
                    left behind the body. Its motion may be ſo ſwift that the ſurrounding preffure
                    may not ſuffice for filling up the deſerted ſpace ; and, in this caſe, a
                    ſtatical preffure will be added to the reſiſtance. This may be the caſe in a
                    veffel or pond of water having an open ſurface expofed to the finite or limited
                    preffure of the atmoſphere. The queftion now is, whe-ther the reſiftance will be
                    increafid by an increaſe of external preffure ? Suppoſing a ſphere moving near
                    the ſurface oſ water, and another moving equally faſt at four times the depth.
                    If the motion be ſo ſwift that a void is formed in both caſes, there is no doubt
                    but that the ſphere which moves at the greateſt depth is moſt reſiſted by the
                    preffure of the water. If there is no void in either cafi, then, becauſe the
                    quadruple depth would cauſe the water to flow in with only a double velocity, it
                    would ſeem that the reſiftance would be greater ; and indeed the water flowing
                    in laterally with a double velocity produces a quadruple non-preffure.— But, on
                    the other hand, the preffure at a ſmall depth may be inſufficient for preventing
                    a void, while that below effectually prevents it ; and this was obfirved in ſome
                    experiments of Chevalier de Borda. The effect, therefore, of greater immeriion,
                    or of greater compreſſion, in an elaſtic fluid, does not follow a preciſe ratio
                    oſ the preffure, but depends partly on abſolute quantities. It cannot,
                    therefore, be ftated by any very ſimple formula what increaſe or diminution of
                    reſiſtance will reſult from a greater depth ; and it is chiefly on this account
                    that experiments made with models of ſhips and mills are not concluſive with
                    reſpect to the performance of a large machine of the ſame proportions, without
                    corrections, ſometimes pretty intricate, we affert, however, with great
                    confidence, that this is of all methods the moſt exact, and infinitely more
                    certain than any thing that can be deduced from the moſt elaborate calculation
                    from theory. If the reſiſtances at all depths be equal, the proportionality of
                    the total reſiſtance to the body is exact, and perfectly conformable to
                    obfirvation&lt;,</p>
                <p>It is only in great velocities where the depth has any material influence, and
                    the influence is not near ſo con-ſiderable as we ſhould, at ſirſt light, ſuppofi
                    ; for, in eſtimating the effect oi immerſion, which has a relation</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0124" facs="gri_33125011196389_0130.tif"/>
                <p>to the difference of preſſure, we muſt always take in the preffure of the
                    atmoſphere ; and thus the preffure at 33 feet deep is not 33 times the preffure
                    at one foot deep, but only double, or twice as great. The atmo-fpheric preffure
                    is omitted only when the reſiſted plane is at the very furface. D’Ulloa, in his <hi rend="italic">Examino Mori· timo,</hi> has introduced an equation
                    expreſſing this relation ; but, except with very limited conditions, it will
                    miſiead us prodigiouſly. To give a general notion of its foundation, let AB
                    (ſig. 23.) be the fiction of a plane moving through a fluid in the direction CD,
                    with a known velocity. The fluid will bc heaped up before it above its natural
                    level CD, becaufe the water will not be puſhed before it like a ſolid body, but
                    will be puſh-ed aſide. And it cannot acquire a lateral motion any other way than
                    by an accumulation, which will diffuſe itfilf in all directions by the law of
                    undulatory motion. The water will alſo be left lower behind the plane, becaufe
                    time <hi rend="italic">muβ</hi> elapſe before-the preffure of the water behind
                    can make it fill the ſpace. We may acquire ſome notion of the extent oſ both the
                    accumulation and depreſſion in this way. There is a certain</p>
                <p>&lt;υ <hi rend="sup">1</hi></p>
                <p>depth CF (= —, where ∙υ is the velocity, and ;· the</p>
                <p>accelerating power of gravity) under the ſurface, fucſh that water would flow
                    through a hole at F with the velocity of the plane’s motion. Draw a horizontal
                    line FG. The water will certainly touch the plane in G, and we may ſuppoſe that
                    it touches it no higher up. Therefore there will be a hollow, fuch as CGE. The
                    elevation HE will be regulated by confiderations nearly fimilar. ED muff be
                    equal to the velocity of the plane, and HE asuſt be its productive height. Thus,
                    if the velocity ¢ff the plane be one foot <hi rend="italic">per</hi> feeond,
                    HE and EG will be -,⅛of an inch. This is ſnſſicient (though not exact) for
                    giving us a notion of the thing. We fie that from this muſt ariſe a preffure in
                    the direction DC, viz. the preffure of the whole column HG.</p>
                <p>Something of the ſame kind will happen although the plane AB be wholly immerged,
                    and this even to fome depth, we fie ſuch elevations in a ſwift running ſtream,
                    where there are large ftones at the bottom.— This occafions an excels of
                    preffure in the direction op-poſite to the plane’s motion ; and we ſee that
                    there muſt, in every caſe, be a relation between the velocity and this exceſs of
                    preſſure. This D’Ulloa expreſſes by an equation. But it is very exceptionable,
                    not taking properly into the account the comparative facility with which the
                    water can heap up and diſſuſe itfilf. It muſt always heap up till it acquires a
                    ſuſſicient head of water to produce a lateral and progreſſive diſſufion
                    ſufficient for the purpofe. It is evident, that a ſmaller elevation will ſuſſice
                    when the body is more immerfid, becaufe the check or impulfi given by the body
                    below is propagated, not vertically only, but in every direction ; and therefore
                    the elevation is not confined to that part of the ſurface which is immediately
                    above the moving body, but extends ſo much farther laterally as the centre of
                    agitation is deeper : Thus, the elevation neceſſary for the paſſage of the body
                    is ſo much ſmaller ; and it is the <hi rend="italic">height</hi> only of this
                    accumulation or wave which de-termines the backward preſſure on the body.
                    D’Ulloa’s equation may happen to quadrate with two experiments at different
                    depths, without being nearly juſt ; for <hi rend="italic">any two</hi> points
                    may be in a curves without exhibiting its</p>
                <p>equation. Three points will do it with ſome approach to precifion ; but four, at
                    leaſt, are neceſſary for giving any notion of its nature. D’Ulloa has only given
                    two experiments, which we mentioned in another place.</p>
                <p>we may here obſerve, that it is this circumſtance which immediately produces the
                    great reſiſtance to the motion of a body through a fluid in a narrow canal.—.
                    The fluid cannot paſs the body, unleſs the area of the fiction be ſufficiently
                    extenſive. A narrow canal pre-vents the extenſion ſidewiſe. The water muſt
                    therefore heap up, till the fiction and velocity of diſſuſton are ſuſſiciently
                    enlarged, and thus a great backward preſſure is produced. (See the ficondfiries
                    of Experiments by the French Academicians ; fie alſo Franklin’s Eſſays.) It is
                    important, and will be conſidered in another place,.</p>
                <p>T h us have we attempted to give our readers ſome account of one of the moſt
                    intereſting problems in the whole of mechanical philoſophy. we are ſorry that ſo
                    little advantage can be derived from the united efforts of the .firſt
                    mathematicians of Europe, and that there is ſo little hope of greatly improving
                    our ſcientific knowledge of the ſubjtct. what we have delivered will, however,
                    enable our readers to perufi the writings of thofi who have applied the theories
                    to practical pur-pofis. Such, for inſtance, are the treatifis of John Bernoulli,
                    of Bouguer, and of Euler, on the conſtruc-tion and working of ihips, and the
                    occaſtonal diſſerta-tions of different authors on water-mills. In this laſt
                    application the ordinary theory is not without its value, for the itnpulſes are
                    nearly perpendicular ; in which caſe they do not materially deviate from the
                    duplicate proportion of the fine of incidence. But even here this theory,
                    applied as it commonly is, miileads us exceedingly. The impulſe on one float may
                    be accurately enough ſtated by it ; but the authors have not been attentive to
                    the motion of the water after it has made its impulfi ; and the impulſe on the
                    next float is ſtated the ſame as if the parallel filaments of water, which were
                    not ſtopped by the preceding float, did impinge on the oppofite part of the
                    ficond, in the ſame manner, and with the ſame obliquity and energy, as if it
                    were detached ſrom the reſt. But this does not in the leaſt re-fcmble the real
                    proceſs of nature.</p>
                <p>Suppoſe the floats B, C, D, H (fig. 24.) oſ a wheel immerſed in a ſtream whoſe
                    ſurface moves in the direction AK, and that this ſurface meets the float B in E.
                    The part B E alone is ſuppoſed to be impelled ; whereas the water, checked by
                    the float, heaps up on it to <hi rend="italic">e.—∙</hi> Then drawing the
                    horizontal line BF, the part CF of the next float is ſuppofid to be all that is
                    impelled by the parallel filaments of the ſtream ; whereas the water bends round
                    the lower edge of the float B by the fur-rounding preſſure, and riles on the
                    float <hi rend="italic">c</hi> all the way to <hi rend="italic">f.</hi> In
                    like manner, the float D, inſtead of receiving an impulſe on the very fmall
                    portion D G, is impelled all the way from D to <hi rend="italic">g,</hi> not
                    much below the lurface of the ſtream. The ſurfaces impelled at once, therefore,
                    greatly exceed what this ſiovenly application of the theory ſuppoſes, and the
                    whole impulſe is much greater; but this is a fault in the application, and not
                    in the theory. It will not be a very difficult thing to acquire a knowledge of
                    the motion of the water which has paſſed the preceding float, which, though not
                    accurate, will yet approximate conſiderably to the truth; and</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0125" facs="gri_33125011196389_0131.tif"/>
                <p>then the ordinary theory will furniſh maxims of con· ftruction which will be
                    very ſerviceable. This will be attempted in its proper place ; and we ſhall
                    endeavour, in our treatment of all the practical queſtions, to derive uſeful
                    information from all that has been delivered on the preſent occaſion.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
