<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T21:02:11Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>for pigs. The breed most common is small and very compact, and black in colour. Pigs numbered 121,866 in 1886.</p><p>The following table gives classifications of holdings in 1875 and 1885:—</p><table><row><cell>Years.</cell><cell cols="2">50 acres and under.</cell><cell cols="2">From 50 to 100 acres.</cell><cell>From 100 to 300 acres.</cell><cell cols="2">From 300 to 500 acres.</cell><cell cols="2">From 500 to 1000 acres.</cell><cell cols="2">Above 1000 acres.</cell></row><row><cell/><cell>No.</cell><cell>Area.</cell><cell>No.</cell><cell>Area.</cell><cell>No. Area.</cell><cell>No.</cell><cell>Area.</cell><cell>No.</cell><cell>Area.</cell><cell>No.</cell><cell>Area.</cell></row><row><cell>1875</cell><cell>5667</cell><cell>66,251</cell><cell>1436</cell><cell>101,644</cell><cell>2043∣336,3S3</cell><cell>387</cell><cell>137, 894</cell><cell>169</cell><cell>110,169</cell><cell>12</cell><cell><p>14,744</p><p>22,314</p></cell></row><row><cell>1885</cell><cell>5607</cell><cell cols="2">64,899 127S</cell><cell>94,994</cell><cell>1872 330,133</cell><cell>409</cell><cell>154,590</cell><cell>174</cell><cell>115,089</cell><cell>17</cell><cell/></row></table><p>Thus in 1875 there were in all 9714 holdings with 767,085 acres, and in 1885 9357 with 782,019 acres. According to the latest landowners <hi rend="italic">Return</hi> (1873) Suffolk was divided among 19,276 proprietors, holding 920,268 acres, at a valued rental of £1,784,827, or an average all over of about £1, 18s. 9<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">2</hi>d. per acre. Of the owners 12,511 or nearly three-fourths possessed less than one acre each. The following possessed over 10,000 acres each :—Lord Rendlesham, 19,869 ; George Tomline, 18,473 ; marquis of Bristol, 16,954 ; the maharajah Dhuleep H. H. Singh, 14,615 ; Lord Hunt- ingfield, 11,713 ; earl of Stradbroke, 11,697 ; Sir Richard Wallace, 11,223 ; Lord Henniker, 10,910.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Communication.—</hi>The river navigation affords means of communication with different ports, and supplies facilities for a considerable amount of traffic. The county is intersected in all directions by branches of the Great Eastern Railway, which touch at almost every town of importance.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Manufactures and Trade. —</hi>The county is essentially agricultural, and the most important manufactures relate to this branch of industry. They include that of agricultural implements, especially at Ipswich, Bury St Edmunds, and Stowmarket, and that of artificial manures at Ipswich and Stowmarket, for which coprolites are dug. Malting is extensively carried on throughout the county. There is a gun-cotton manufactory at Stowmarket, and gun flints are still made at Brandon. At different towns a variety of small miscellaneous manufactures are carried on, including silk, cotton, linen, woollen, and horsehair and cocoa-nut matting. The principal ports are Yarmouth (situated chiefly in Norfolk), Lowestoft, South- wold, Aldeburgh, Woodbridge, and Ipswich. Yarmouth is one of the most important fishing stations on the east coast of England ; within the county Lowestoft is the chief fishing town. Herrings and mackerel are the fish most abundant on the coasts.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Administration and Popidation. —</hi>Suffolk comprises 21 hundreds ; the boroughs of Beccles (pop. 5721), which has several large mattings ; Bury St Edmunds (16,111), the chief town in West Suffolk; Eye (2296), an ancient market town ; Ipswich (50,546), the largest town and principal port of the county ; Aldeburgh (2106), the birthplace of Crabbe ; Southwold (2107), a fishing town and bathing resort ; the largest part (5855) of Sudbury (6584), a market and manufacturing town ; and small portions of the boroughs of Thetford and Great Yarmouth, which are situated chiefly in Norfolk. The other principal towns are Hadleigh (3237), with a considerable trade in corn and malt ; Haverhill (3685) (partly in Essex), of great antiquity, and possessing important silk manufactures ; Lowestoft (16,755), a port and fishing station; Stowmarket (4052); and Woodbridge (4544), with some coasting trade. Suffolk is divided into geldable portions, in which the sovereign has the chief rights, and liberties. The liberties are those of St Etheldreda, St Edmund, and the dukedom of Norfolk. The court of quarter sessions is at Ipswich for the eastern division and by adjournment at Bury St Edmunds for the western. There are nineteen petty and sessional divisions. The hundreds of Hartismere and Stow and the borough of Eye are for petty sessional purposes included in the eastern division, and for other purposes in the western. The boroughs of Bury St Edmunds, Ipswich, Great Yarmouth, and Sudbury have commissions of the peace and separate courts of quarter sessions ; and Eye and Southwold have commissions of the peace. For parliamentary purposes the county was until 1885 divided into East and West Suffolk, but it now constitutes five divisions, each returning one member, viz., North or Lowestoft division, North-east or Eye, North-west or Stowmarket, South or Sudbury, and South-east or Woodbridge. Bury St Edmunds returns one member and Ipswich two ; Eye, which formerly returned one member, was merged in the North-east division of the county in 1885. The county contains 517 civil parishes with parts of 7 others. It is mostly in the diocese of Norwich. From 214,404 in 1801 the population had increased by 1821 to 271,541, by 1841 to 315,073, by 1861 to 337,070, and by 1881 to 356,893, of whom 174,606 were males and 182,287 females. The number of persons to an acre was 0·38 and of acres to a person 2·65.</p><p><hi rend="italic">History and Antiquities.—</hi>The district which now includes Norfolk, Suffolk, and a portion of Cambridge, and afterwards formed East Anglia, had in early times, on account of the marshes to the west, practically the character of a peninsula. It was inhabited by the Iceni, who had their capital at Icklingham, in the north-west of Suffolk. Of the numerous barrows and tumuli belonging to this</p><p>period mention may be made of those at Fornham St Geneveve and those between Aldeburgh and Snape. Many of the mediæval castles were built on ancient mounds. The district submitted to the Romans during the campaign of Aulus Plautius, and, although the Iceni joined the Trinobantes under Boadicea, the resistance made was ultimately fruitless. A Roman road from London crossed the centre of Suffolk northwards by Stratford St Mary, Needham Market, and Billingford (Norfolk) to Norwich, another passing in a more westerly direction to Thetford. Walton, where important Roman relics have been found, Dunwich (possibly <hi rend="italic">Sitomagus),</hi> and Burgh Castle (probably <hi rend="italic">Combretonium),</hi> one of the most perfect specimens of a Roman fort in England, enclosing an area of five acres, are supposed to have been Roman fortified stations erected for the defence of the Saxon shore. Other Roman stations were at Stratford St Mary, Thetford, and Icklingham. The capital of the kingdom of East Anglia was at Dunwich in Suffolk. Afterwards East Anglia was divided into Norfolk and Suffolk. Sigebert established an ecclesiastical diocese at Dunwich in 630, and erected a palace and a church partly out of the Roman remains. The earldom of Norfolk and Suffolk was bestowed by the Conqueror on Ralph le Guader. Though Suffolk suffered from incursions of the Danes, they did not effect a complete subjugation of it. The prevailing terminations of the place names are Anglian. The remains of old castles are comparatively unimportant, the principal being the entrenchments and part of the walls of Bungay, the ancient stronghold of the Bigods ; the picturesque ruins of Mettingham, built by John de Norwich in the reign of Edward III. ; Wingfield, surrounded by a deep moat, with the turret walls and the drawbridge still existing ; the splendid ruin of Framlingham, with high and massive walls, originally founded in the 6th century, but restored in the 12th ; the outlines of the extensive fortress of Clare Castle, anciently the baronial residence of the earls of Clare ; and the fine Norman keep of Orford Castle, on an eminence overlooking the sea. Among the many fine residences within the county there are several interesting examples of domestic architecture of the reigns of Henry VIII. and Elizabeth. Throughout its whole history the annals of Suffolk have been comparatively uneventful. It adhered with Norfolk to the cause of the Parliament. James duke of York twice defeated the Dutch off the coast,—viz., Van Tromp off Lowestoft on 3d June 1665 and De Ruyter in Southwold Bay on 28th May 1672. Of monastic remains the most important are those of the great Benedictine abbey of Bury St Edmunds, noticed under that town ; the college of Clare, originally a cell to the abbey of Bec in Normandy and afterwards to St Peter’s, Westminster, converted into a college of secular canons in the reign of Henry VI., and still retaining much of its ancient architecture, and now used as a boarding-school ; the decorated gateway of the Augustinian priory of Butley ; and the remains of the Grey Friars monastery at Dunwich. A peculiarity of the church architecture is the use of flint for purposes of ornamentation, often of a very elaborate kind, especially on the porches and parapets of the towers. Another characteristic is the round towers, which are confined to East Anglia, but are considerably more numerous in Norfolk than in Suffolk, the principal being those of Little Saxham and Herringfleet, both good examples of Norman. It is questionable whether there are any remains of Saxon architecture in the county. The Decorated is well represented, but by far the greater proportion of the churches are Perpendicular, special features being the open roofs and woodwork and the fine fonts.</p><p>See Blome’s <hi rend="italic">Description of Suffolk,</hi> 1673 ; Kirby’s <hi rend="italic">Description,</hi> 1748, 2d ed. 1829 ; Suckling’s <hi rend="italic">History of Suffolk,</hi> 1846-48 ; Hervey's <hi rend="italic">Visitation of Suffolk in 1561, </hi>ed., with additions, by Dr J. J. Howard, 1866 ; and Browne’s <hi rend="italic">History of Congregationalism and Memorial of Churches in Suffolk,</hi> 1877.	(T. F. H.)</p><p>SUFISM. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Mohammedanism,</hi> vol. xvi. p. 594; <hi rend="smallcaps">Mysticism,</hi> vol. xvii. p. 130 ; and <hi rend="smallcaps">Sunnites,</hi> p. 659 <hi rend="italic">sq. infra.</hi></p><p>SUGAR. Formerly chemists called everything a “sugar” which had a sweet taste, and acetate of lead to this day is known as “sugar of lead” in commerce and familiar chemical parlance; but the term in its scientific sense soon came to be restricted to the sweet principles in vegetable and animal juices. Only one of these—cane sugar—was known as a pure substance until 1619, when Fabrizio Bar- toletti isolated the sugar of milk and proved its individuality. In regard to all other “sugars” besides these two the knowledge of chemists was in the highest degree indefinite, and remained so until about the middle of the 18th century, when Marggraf made the important discovery that the sugars of the juices of beet, carrots, and certain other fleshy roots are identical with one another and with the sugar of the cane. Lowitz subsequently showed that the granular part of honey is something different from cane sugar ; this was confirmed by Proust, who found also</p></body></text></TEI>