<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T21:00:29Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>of Buchanan and Drymen, and oaks grow extensively on the borders of Loch Lomond. Larch and Scotch firs principally occupy the modern plantations in the other parts of the county. In 1886 there were only 31 acres under orchards, 27 under market gardens, and 53 under nursery grounds.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Manufactures. —</hi>The Carron ironworks, founded in 1760, for a long time led the van in British iron manufacture, and are still among the most extensive in the kingdom. The Falkirk ironworks, founded in 1819, are the next to them in importance in the county, but there are many others in the same district. The woollen manufacture is next to iron in importance. It includes carpets, tartans, shawls, and tweeds, the principal seats of the industry being Alva, Bannockburn, Cambusbarron, and Stirling. Calico printing is carried on in the western part of the county, especially at Campsie and Milngavie. There are chemical works at Stirling, Falkirk, Denny, and Campsie. Throughout the county there are a considerable number of breweries and distilleries. At Grangemouth, the principal</p><p>port in the county, shipbuilding is carried on.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Administration and Population.—</hi>Stirling is included with Dumbarton and Clackmannan in the same sheriffdom, but has two sheriff-substitutes, who sit at Stirling and Falkirk respectively, and there are prisons in both towns. The high court of justiciary holds circuit courts at Stirling. There are 21 entire civil parishes within the county and parts of 5 others, Stirling (population 12,194) is a royal and police burgh, Falkirk (13,170) a police burgh and burgh of regality, Kilsyth (5405) a police burgh and burgh of barony, and Alva (4961), Bridge of Allan (3005), Denny and Dunipace (4080), Grangemouth (4424), and Milngavie (2636) police burghs. In addition to these the following places had each upwards of 2000 inhabitants:</p><p>Bannockburn (2549), Lennoxtown (3249), and Stenhousemuir (2617). From 39,761 in 1765 the population of the county had by 1801 increased to 50,825, by 1831 to 72,621, by 1861 to 91,926, by 1871 to 98,176, and by 1881 to 112,443, of whom 56,147 were males and 56,296 were females. The number of persons to the square mile is 251, and in point of density Stirling ranks ninth among the counties of Scotland.</p><p>One member is returned to parliament by the county, and Stirling and Falkirk are members of separate districts of burghs, which are respectively named from them, each returning one member.</p><p><hi rend="italic">History.—</hi>In 81 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.</hi> the Romans under Agricola penetrated as far north as the firths of Clyde (Clota) and Forth (Bodotria). To secure their conquests they erected between these a line of forts or <hi rend="italic">præsidia,</hi> generally two miles apart. In 139 Lollius Urbicus erected along the line of the forts the rampart of Antoninus’s wall, afterwards known as Graham’s dyke. The wall, after crossing the parish of East Kilpatrick, passed outside the present county of Stirling, till it reached Castlecary, whence it passed by Camelon and Falkirk to Carriden in Linlithgowshire. Castlecary, where many Roman remains have been found, was perhaps the principal Roman station on the line of the wall, and there was another important one at Camelon. A Roman road, the Camelon causeway, passed eastwards from Castlecary to the south of the rampart, and after two miles crossed it and held on to Camelon, whence it went northward by Bannockburn, St Ninians, and Stirling to the Forth, where there was an important station near the present bridge of Drip. Thence it passed north by Keir to Dunblane. To the north-east of the Carron ironworks there was at one time a finely-preserved circular Roman building, called Arthur’s Oon (oven) or Julius’s Hof, which was demolished in 1743, but of which a drawing is preserved in Camden’s <hi rend="italic">Britannia.</hi> In the parish of Dunipace are two beautiful mounds called “the Hills of Dunipace,” which some have supposed to have been erected as monuments of peace between the Romans and Caledonians, but which are more probably of natural origin. Tho remains of what was supposed to have been an early British stronghold were discovered at Torwood in 1864. A group of cairns at Craigmaddie, near Milngavie, is supposed to mark the scene of a battle between the Picts and Danes. Among the remains of old feudal castles may be mentioned Graham’s castle, among the Fintry Hills, which belonged to Sir John de Graham, who was killed in the battle of Falkirk in 1298 ; Herbertshire, on the north bank of the Carron near Denny, originally a royal hunting seat, and still one of the finest embattled residences in the county (now a boarding school) ; the ancient keep of Castlecary, partly destroyed by the Highlanders in 1715 ; Torwood, surrounded by the remains of the Caledonian forest, in one of the oaks of which Wallace took refuge; and the round tower of Carnock, called Bruce’s castle, of unknown history. Sir William Wallace lived occasionally with his uncle, the parson of Dunipace, and the county is specially associated with</p><p>his exploits and those of Robert Bruce, being the scene of some of the principal battles in the struggle for Scottish independence (Stirling bridge, September 10, 1297; Falkirk, July 22, 1298; Bannockburn, June 24, 1314). At Sauchieburn, 11th June 1488, James III. was defeated by his insurgent nobles, and during his flight, having stopped at a cottage in the village of Milton, was there stabbed to death. Kilsyth saw the defeat of the Covenanters by Montrose, 15th August 1645, a result which for a time laid Scotland at Montrose’s feet ; and a hundred years afterwards—17th January 1746—the Highlanders under Prince Charles Edward routed the Hanoverians at Falkirk.</p><p>See Sir Robert Sibbald's <hi rend="italic">Description of Stirlingshire,</hi> 1710 ; and Nimmo’s <hi rend="italic">History of Stirlingshire,</hi> 1777 (MacGregor Stirling's edition is the best). (T. F. H.)</p><p>STIRLING, a royal and parliamentary burgh and the county town of Stirlingshire, is finely situated on the slopes</p><p>of an isolated eminence overlooking the valley of the Forth and abruptly precipitous towards the north-west, at the junction of several railway lines, 36 miles west-north-west of Edinburgh and 30 north-north-east of Glasgow. Originally the town was protected on all the accessible sides of the rock by a wall, of which there are still some remains at the southern end of the Back Walk. There were two principal entries to the town,—the South Port, originally 100 yards more to the west of the present line of Port Street, and the bridge over the Forth to the north. The earliest bridge was at Kildean, a mile to the west; the existing old bridge, now disused, probably dates from about the end of the 13th century ; the new bridge was erected in 1829, from the designs of Stevenson, at a cost of £17,000. The streets of the old town are for the most part steep, narrow, and irregular, and contain a large number of quaint and antique dwellings. The town has now much outgrown its ancient limits, and the surrounding suburbs on the low grounds contain numerous villas. The castle crowning the eminence, and commanding a splendid panoramic view of the wide valley between the Lennox Hills and the Highland mountains and Ochils, with the links of the Forth and the widening estuary to the east, is of unknown antiquity, but from the time that Alexander I. died within its walls in 1124 till James VI. ascended the throne of England it was intimately associated with the fortunes of the Scottish monarchs, and after the accession of the Stuarts it became a favourite royal residence. The building was extended by James III., who erected the parliament hall, now used as a barrack-room. The palace, begun by James V. and finished in the reign of Mary, is</p></body></text></TEI>