<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T21:00:36Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>period, was destroyed by fire in 1697, the body of Charles</p><p>XI.	being with difficulty rescued from the flames. A new palace, after plans by Nicodemus Tessin, was not completed (owing to wars and the general distress) until 1754 ; it is a quadrangular structure on the summit of the hill, with two wings towards the east and four towards the west (two straight and two in a semicircle). The style of the building is noble and refined, the royal apartments rich in treasures of art. In the immediate vicinity of the palace is the church of St Nicholas, the oldest in Stockholm, but in many parts changed from what it was ; the chancel was demolished in the 16th century to give more room for the palace. Staden is the commercial centre of the city, containing the exchange, the bank of Sweden, and the custom-house, as well as the offices of many merchants. On the eastern side a very large quay, called the Skeppsbro (“the bridge of ships”), extends from the statue of Gustavus III. opposite the palace to where the traffic between Lake Mälar and the Baltic is carried on through a sluice or lock. The Skeppsbro is the landing-place for steamers to the northern provinces of Sweden and foreign ports. On the other side of the palace is the Kanslihus, containing the offices of most of the ministries ; and a little farther on is a market, named from the palace on its northern side, the Riddarhus, belonging to the Swedish nobility. The principal hall of the Riddarhus has its walls adorned with the armorial bearings of the noble families of Sweden. The representatives of these families meet here every third year for consultation as to their common interests. In front of the building stands the statue of Gustavus I. The town-hall stands in the same square. (2) <hi rend="italic">Riddarholmen</hi> contains the old Franciscan church, which, however, is not now used for divine service. Since the time of Gustavus Adolphus it has been the burial-place of the royal family ; it also contains many trophies from the European wars of Sweden. On one side of the church stand the houses of parliament ; on the other is the statue of Birger Jarl, the founder of Stockholm. A large part of the island is occupied by Government offices, including the record office. Along the shore most of the steamers for different parts of Lake Mälar and farther on through the canal of Södertelge, for the Baltic, have their landing- places. (3) <hi rend="italic">Helgeandsholmen</hi> (“the isle of the Holy Ghost ”) is at present occupied by the royal stables. The Norrbro (“ north bridge ”), connecting the old town with the northern shore, passes the eastern extremity of the island. (4) <hi rend="italic">Norrmalmen</hi> (“ the northern suburb ”) begins at the Norrbro with the market of Gustavus Adolphus, where his statue stands between the theatre royal and the crown prince’s palace. Norrmalmen is one of the best- built parts of the city, with broad straight streets ; it contains four parish churches and also the English church, the Roman Catholic church, and the Jewish synagogue. In the south-eastern corner is a large open space, Kungs- trädgården (“the royal garden”), with the statues of Charles</p><p>XII.	and Charles XIII. and a fountain, one of the prin</p><p>cipal playgrounds for children. Near it is another park, with the statue of Berzelius. Norrmalmen has several public buildings, such as the post-office, the principal railway station, the academy of art, the academy of sciences, the high technical school, and the school of metallurgy, the technical school, the observatory, &amp;c. On the northern side of Norrmalmen lies the principal cemetery. (5) <hi rend="italic">Blasie- holmen,</hi> united with Norrmalmen since the filling up of the canal which formerly separated them, contains the national museum, the academy of music, &amp;c.	(6) <hi rend="italic">Skeppsholmen</hi></p><p>(“the isle of ships”) and (7) <hi rend="italic">Castellholmen</hi> both belong to the admiralty. (8) <hi rend="italic">Kungsholmen</hi> (“ the isle of the king ”), to the west of Norrmalmen, contains a parish church, the mint, the high school of medicine, several hospitals, and</p><p>many factories. (9) <hi rend="italic">Ladugardslandet</hi> takes its name from the farm yard <hi rend="italic">(ladugård</hi>) of the royal castle, which formerly occupied a great part of its area. It became a part of the city in the middle of the 17th century, but until recently played a very subordinate part, owing to want of water. Since the introduction of the new water-supply this part of Stockholm has grown wonderfully, and is now the finest part of the city, with more than 40,000 inhabitants. It has a fine park, Humlegården (“hop garden”), with the royal library and the statue of Linnæus. Most of the barracks of Stockholm, as well as the high military school, are situated in this quarter of the town. (10) <hi rend="italic">Djurg</hi>å<hi rend="italic">rden </hi>(“deer garden’) is a royal park, with villas, restaurants, shipbuilding yards, &amp;c. (11) <hi rend="italic">Södermalmen</hi> (“ the southern suburb ”) is separated from Staden by the sluice already mentioned. On an open space at the side of the channel stands the statue of Charles XIV. (Bernadotte). The larger part of this suburb, with its two parish churches, chapels, hospitals, &amp;c., stands at a considerable elevation, and communication has been facilitated by the construction of two elevators. On the outskirts are factories, foundries, &amp;c.</p><p>A glance at the map at once shows how important have been its water-facilities in forming the character of Stockholm. From all sides the water permeates the different parts of the city, separating them, yet at the same time helping to unite them. Stretching far away to east and to west between shores and islands sometimes open and cultivated, sometimes rocky and covered with trees, the water entices the inhabitants to make excursions and to reside for a part of the year in the country ; in the summer the city is largely deserted. The site is universally recognized as extremely picturesque. The great water-surface has also a beneficent influence upon the climate. In 1884 the mean temperature was 42°·47 Fahr., the highest temperature of the year being 72°·4 Fahr. (2nd and 5th July), the lowest -0°·4 Fahr. (30th November). The year’s rainfall amounted to 18·3 inches, the number of rainy days being 129. The best time for visiting Stockholm is the latter half of June, when the evening and morning lights, reflected from the water and seen through the young and luxuriant verdure, produce singularly beautiful and varied effects.</p><p>In Sweden the cities formerly played a comparatively subordinate part. During the Swedish Middle Ages the prominent classes were the nobility, the clergy, and the peasantry. The anti-aristocratic revolution of the 14th and the 15th centuries had in Sweden its principal supporters among the peasants. But the importance of the cities has gradually increased, and recent times have witnessed an accelerated development, which is best exemplified by the history of Stockholm. The number of inhabitants was, in 1800, 75,517; in 1825, 79,473; in 1850, 93,070; in 1860, 112,391; in 1870, 136,016; in 1880, 168,775; in 1884, 205,123; and in December 1885, 215,688. In 1884 11,916 were qualified to take part in the election of members of the lower house of parliament. Along with the rapid increase of population went a correspondingly increased industrial activity and a considerable development in the means of communication. The number of mechanics in 1884 was 11,064 (8716 of the wage-earning class), the corresponding numbers for 1880 being 9664 and 7483. The number of factories in 1884 was 275, employing 9810 workpeople (including 2638 women), and producing to the value of 32,355,565 Swedish crowns (£1,797,531). The merchants in 1884 numbered 3828, with 6554 assistants. In the same year 37,561 vessels entered (21,460 steamers), while 37,699 (21,565 steamers) cleared. Of these 1688 entered from and 1159 cleared for foreign ports. In former times Stockholm had the command of all the foreign commerce for the country round Lake Mälar, and for the whole of northern Sweden; but more recently the northern cities have made themselves to a certain extent independent of the capital.</p><p>For communication between the different parts of Stockholm omnibuses and small rowing boats have now given place to small steamers; in 1884 sixty-three of these were in use in the city and its immediate vicinity. In 1880 tramways were constructed for Staden, Norrmalmen, Kungsholmen, and Ladugårdslandet.</p><p>The city forms a separate administrative district under a governor <hi rend="italic">(öfverst</hi>å<hi rend="italic">lh</hi>å<hi rend="italic">llare).</hi> In ecclesiastical matters it belongs to the archbishopric of Upsala, and the archbishop has the light to preside in its consistory, of which the president generally is the <hi rend="italic">pastor primarius,</hi> the rector of St Nicholas. The members of this consistory are the rectors of the other seven territorial parishes and the rectors of the Finnish and German congregations. There is also a court consistory, presided over by the chief court preacher.</p><p>It was not until modern times that Stockholm became the capital of Sweden. The mediæval kings visited year by year</p></body></text></TEI>