<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T21:00:14Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>that of the Vulcan Company deserves mention) have comparatively recently attained some reputation for their ironclads and war-vessels. Machinery, cement, chemicals, and soap are produced in large quantities, and there are also</p><p>large sugar-refineries, besides a vast miscellany of other smaller industrial establishments. The trade of Stettin is very flourishing. More than any other harbour it may be regarded as the port of Berlin, from which it is 93 miles north-east by railway ; and a larger number of vessels enter and clear at Stettin than at any other German port except Hamburg and Bremerhaven. <hi rend="smallcaps">Swinemünde </hi><hi rend="italic">{q.v.) </hi>serves as its fore-port. The forest and river scenery of the neighbourhood of Stettin is picturesque, but the low level and swampy nature of the soil render the climate bleak and unhealthy. In 1885 the population was 99,475 ; in 1880 it was 91,756, of whom 85,727 were Protestants, 3112 Roman Catholics, and 2388 Jews.</p><p>In 1885 3809 ocean vessels (2207 steamers) and 1965 coasting and river craft, besides 10,039 Oder barges, entered the port. In 1885 Stettin possessed (besides a large number of river craft) a fleet of 127 sea-going ships, with a burden of 47,066 tons, of which 26,754 tons were distributed in 59 steamers. The chief exports are grain, spirits, and wood; the chief imports petroleum, train-oil, wine, and herrings. The annual value of the former is about £7,500,000 and of the latter about £6,000,000.</p><p>Stettin is said to have existed as a Wendish fishing-village as early as 830 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.,</hi> and it appears as Stedyn in the time of the Saxon emperors. From the 12th century it was the seat of the dukes of Pomerania, who became extinct in 1637. Passing then to Sweden, it remained united with that kingdom for eighty-three years, with one brief interval, but in 1720 it was ceded to Prussia. Gustavus Adolphus undertook to improve its fortifications in 1630, but Frederick the Great was the first to convert it into a strong modern fortress. From 1806 till 1813 it was held by the French to whom it was surrendered without a blow. Known even in the12th century as the leading trading-town on the Oder, Stettin entered the Hanseatic League in 1360. The development of its trade in modern times dates chiefly from the deepening and protection of the Swine in the former half of last century. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Oder.</hi></p><p>STEUART, <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir James Denham</hi> (1712-1780), <hi rend="smallcaps">Bart., </hi>author of An <hi rend="italic">Inquiry into the Principles of Political Economy</hi> (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Political Economy,</hi> vol. xix. p. 365), was the only son of Sir James Steuart, solicitor-general for Scotland under Queen Anne and George I., and was born at Edinburgh on October 21, 1712. After passing through the university of Edinburgh he was admitted to the Scottish bar at the age of twenty-four. He then spent some years on the Continent, and while in Rome entered into relations with the Pretender. He was in Edinburgh in 1745, and so compromised himself that after the battle of Culloden he found it necessary to return to the Continent, where he remained until 1763. It was not indeed until 1771 he was fully pardoned for any complicity he may have had in the rebellion. He died at his family seat, Coltness, in Lanarkshire, on November 26, 1780.</p><p><hi rend="italic">The Works, Political, Metaphysical, and Chronological, of the late Sir James Steuart of Coltness, Bark, now first collected, with Anecdotes of the Author, by his Son, General Sir James Denham Steuart,</hi> were published in 6 vols. 8vo in 1805. Besides the <hi rend="italic">Inquiry</hi> (originally published in 2 vols. 4to in 1767), they include— <hi rend="italic">A Dissertation upon the Doctrines and Principles of Money applied to the German Coin</hi> (1758), <hi rend="italic">Apologie du Sentiment de M. le Chevalier Newton sur l’Ancienne Chronologie des Grecs</hi> (4to, Frankfort-on-the- Main, 1757), <hi rend="italic">The Principles of Money applied to the Present State of Bengal,</hi> published at the request of the East India Company (4to, 1772), <hi rend="italic">A Dissertation on the Policy of Grain</hi> (1783), <hi rend="italic">Plan for Introducing Uniformity in Weights and Measures within the Limits of the British Empire</hi> (1790), <hi rend="italic">Observations</hi> on Beattie’s <hi rend="italic">Essay on Truth, A Dissertation concerning the Motive of Obedience to the Law of God,</hi> and other treatises.</p><p>STEUBENVILLE, a city of the United States, county seat of Jefferson county, Ohio, lies 43 miles west of Pittsburgh, on the west bank of the Ohio river, here a third of a mile wide and crossed by a railway bridge. Built above a productive coalfield, and with an abundant supply of natural gas for fuel purposes, Steubenville has naturally become a manufacturing centre (foundries, rolling-mills, nail and glass factories, potteries, machine-shops, flourmills, &amp;c.), and as the surrounding district is a good farming, wool-growing, and stock-raising country it is the seat of considerable commercial activity. The court-house is a particularly fine building. In 1870 the population was 8107, in 1880 12,093. Steubenville, so called after Baron Steuben, one of Washington’s generals, grew up round a fort erected in 1787. It became a city in 1851.</p><p>STEVENS, <hi rend="smallcaps">Alfred.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Sculpture,</hi> vol. xxi. p. 561.</p><p>STEVENS, <hi rend="smallcaps">Thaddeus</hi> (1792-1868), was born at Peacham, Vermont, U.S., April 4, 1792, graduated at Dartmouth College in 1814, and then settled in Pennsylvania. He soon became a leading lawyer of Lancaster, Pa., so far interested in politics as to be elected by the Whig party to the State legislature for several terms and to the federal house of representatives 1849-63. When the mass of the Northern Whig party went into the new Republican party he went with it, and returned to Washington as a Republican representative in 1859, just before the outbreak of the Civil War. This position he retained until his death, just outlasting the Civil War and reconstruction. During this period of American history he was one of the leading characters. The methods on which he proposed to conduct the war were always drastic : the wholesale confiscation of lands in the seceding States, the disfranchisement of insurgent citizens, the emancipation and enfranchisement of the negroes, all found in him their earliest and warmest advocate. While other parties and leaders were continually shifting their ground, changing their theories of the relations of the Union to the seceding States as the struggle grew more intense, Stevens was consistent from beginning to end. The almost universal theory was that the war was prosecuted only to enforce the constitution ; it was therefore incumbent on those who prosecuted it to obey the constitution punctiliously, how-</p></body></text></TEI>