<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T20:58:07Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>armies to have been in command of the cavalry under the constable, and to have in some measure superseded him as master of the horse in the royal palace. He exercised joint and co-ordinate jurisdiction with the constable in the court of chivalry, and afterwards became the sole judge of that tribunal. The marshalship of England was made hereditary in the Clares and Marshals, earls of Pembroke, in the reign of Stephen or Henry II., and through a coheiress passed to the Bigots, earls of Norfolk, and by Roger Bigot, fifth earl of Norfolk, it was surrendered with his other dignities to Edward I. It was granted by Edward II. to his brother Thomas of Brotherton, earl of Norfolk, and, after it had been variously disposed of by Edward III., was by Richard II. erected into an earldom and conferred on Thomas Mowbray, duke of Norfolk, who was the great-grandson and heir of Thomas of Brotherton. One of the coheiresses of the Mowbrays was the mother of John Howard, duke of Norfolk, who was created earl marshal by Richard III. After several attainders and partial restorations in the reigns of the Tudors and the Stuarts, the earl marshalship was finally entailed by Charles II. on the male line of the Howards, with many specific remainders and limitations, under which settlement it has regularly descended to the present duke of Norfolk. The Clares and Marshals, earls of Pembroke, and the Lords Morley appear to have been hereditary marshals of Ireland from the invasion of the island until the end of the 15th century. The Keiths were Earls Marischal of Scotland from the institution of the office by James II. in 1458 until the attainder of George, the tenth earl, in 1716.</p><p>On the subject of the great offices of state generally, see Stubbs, <hi rend="italic">Constitutional History,</hi> ch. xi. : Freeman, <hi rend="italic">Norman Conquest,</hi> ch. xxiv. ; Gneist, <hi rend="italic">Constitution of England,</hi> ch. xvi., xxxv., and liv. ; also Gibbon, <hi rend="italic">Decline and Fall,</hi> ch. liii., and Bryce, <hi rend="italic">Holy Roman Empire,</hi> ch. xiv.	(F. DR.)</p><p>STATEN ISLAND, an island of New York State, forming, with some adjacent islands, Richmond county, with a population of 38,991 in 1880, is situated about 5 miles south of New York city, from which it is separated by New York Bay, while the Narrows, commanded by Forts Wadsworth and Tompkins and a line of water-batteries, separate it from Long Island on the north-east, Staten Island Sound from New Jersey on the west, and Newark Bay and the Kill van Kull from the same State on the north. It is of an irregular triangular shape, its greatest length being about 13 miles, its greatest breadth about 8, and the total area 58<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">2</hi> square miles. The surface is gently undulating, but a range of hills attaining 310 feet in height extends across the northern portion. Iron ore is found. The island contains many detached villa residences of persons in business in New York. On an artificial island off the east shore is the New York quarantine establishment, and Staten Island is the seat of the “ Sailors’ Snug Harbour, ” a retreat for superannuated seamen. Steam ferries ply half-hourly to New York, and on the island there is a railway line from Tompkinsville to Tottenville.</p><p>STATE PAPERS. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Records, Public.</hi></p><p>STATES OF THE CHURCH, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Papal States</hi> (Ital.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Stato della Chiesa, Stato Pontificio, Stato Romano, Stato Ecclesiastico</hi>; Fr. <hi rend="italic">États de l'Église, Pontificat Souverain de Rome,</hi> &amp;c.; Germ. <hi rend="italic">Kirchenstaat ;</hi> in ecclesiastical Latin often <hi rend="italic">Patrimonium Sancti Petri),</hi> that portion of central Italy which, previous to the unification of the kingdom, was under the direct government of the see of Rome. The territory stood at the close as in the annexed table.</p><p>With the exception of Benevento, surrounded by the Neapolitan province of Principato Ulteriore, and the small state of Pontecorvo, enclosed within the Terra di Lavoro, the States of the Church formed a compact territory, bounded on the N.W. by the Lombardo-Venetian kingdom,</p><p>on the N.E. by the Adriatic, on the S.E. by the kingdom of Naples, on the S.W. by the Mediterranean, and on the W. by the grand-duchy of Tuscany and the duchy of</p><table><row><cell cols="2"/><cell><p>Area in</p><p>English Square Miles.</p></cell><cell>Population in 1853.</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Comarca of Rome	 . 	</cell><cell>1752∙8</cell><cell><p>326,509</p><p>375,631</p></cell></row><row><cell/><cell>Bologna	</cell><cell>1359∙2</cell><cell/></row><row><cell/><cell>Ferrara	</cell><cell>1094</cell><cell><p>244,524</p><p>218,433</p><p>175,994</p></cell></row><row><cell/><cell>Forlì	</cell><cell>718∙8</cell><cell/></row><row><cell/><cell>Ravenna	</cell><cell>701∙5</cell><cell/></row><row><cell/><cell>Urbino, with Pesaro	</cell><cell>1414∙6</cell><cell><p>257,751</p><p>62,013</p></cell></row><row><cell/><cell>Velletri	</cell><cell>571∙3</cell><cell/></row><row><cell/><cell>Ancona	</cell><cell>441∙8</cell><cell><p>176,519</p><p>243,104</p><p>42,991</p><p>110,321</p><p>91,916</p><p>234,533</p><p>135,029</p><p>73,683</p><p>128,324</p><p>29,047</p><p>20,701</p><p>154,559</p></cell></row><row><cell/><cell>Macerata	</cell><cell>895</cell><cell/></row><row><cell/><cell>Camerino	</cell><cell>320</cell><cell/></row><row><cell/><cell>Fermo	</cell><cell>335∙7</cell><cell/></row><row><cell/><cell>Ascoli	</cell><cell>476·3</cell><cell/></row><row><cell/><cell>Perugia	</cell><cell>1555∙5</cell><cell/></row><row><cell/><cell>Spoleto		</cell><cell>1175∙9</cell><cell/></row><row><cell/><cell>Rieti	</cell><cell>531∙7</cell><cell/></row><row><cell/><cell>Viterbo	</cell><cell>1158∙9</cell><cell/></row><row><cell/><cell>Orvieto	</cell><cell>316∙6</cell><cell/></row><row><cell/><cell>Cività Vecchia	</cell><cell>380</cell><cell/></row><row><cell/><cell>Frosinone, with Pontecorvo	</cell><cell>739∙9</cell><cell/></row><row><cell cols="2">Benevento	</cell><cell>61∙3</cell><cell>23,176</cell></row><row><cell/><cell/><cell/><cell/></row><row><cell/><cell/><cell>16,000∙8</cell><cell>3,124,758</cell></row></table><p>Modena. On the Adriatic the coast extended 140 miles, from the mouth of the Tronto (Truentus) to the southern mouth of the Po, and on the Tyrrhenian Sea 130 miles, from 41° 20' to 42° 22' N. lat. See vol. xiii. Plate VI.</p><p>The divisions shown above were adopted on December 21, 1827, the legations being ruled by a cardinal and the delegations by a prelate. Previously the several districts formally recognized were Latium, the Marittima (or seaboard) and Campagna, the Patrimony of Saint Peter, the duchy of Castro, the Orvietano, the Sabina, Umbria, the Perugino, the March of Ancona, Romagna, the Bolognese, the Ferrarese, and the duchies of Benevento and of Pontecorvo.</p><p>The question of the origin of the territorial jurisdiction of the pope has been treated under <hi rend="smallcaps">Popedom</hi> (vol. xix. p. 495). With the moral and ecclesiastical decay of the papacy in the 9th and 10th centuries much of its territorial authority slipped from its grasp ; and by the middle of the 11th century its rule was not recognized beyond Rome and the immediate vicinity. By the treaty of Sutri (February 1111) Paschal II. was compelled by the emperor Henry V. to surrender all the possessions and royalties of the church ; but this treaty was soon afterwards repudiated, and by the will of Matilda, countess of Tuscany, the papal see was enabled to lay claim to new territories of great value. By the capitulation of Neuss (1201) Otto IV. recognized the papal authority over the whole tract from Radicofani in Tuscany to the pass of Ceperano on the Neapolitan frontier—the exarchate of Ravenna, the Pentapolis, the March of Ancona, the bishopric of Spoleto, Matilda’s personal estates, and the countship of Brittenoro ; but a good deal of the territory thus described remained for centuries an object of ambition only on the part of the popes. The actual annexation of Ravenna, Ancona, Bologna, Ferrara, &amp;c., dates from the 16th century. The States of the Church were of course submerged for a time by the ground-swell of the French Revolution, but they appeared again in 1814. In 1849 they received a constitution. On the formation of the kingdom of Italy in 1860 they were reduced to the Comarca of Rome, the legation of Velletri, and the three delegations of Viterbo, Cività Vecchia, and Frosinone ; and in 1870 they disappeared from the political map of Europe.</p><p>STATICS. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Mechanics.</hi></p><p>STATIONERY. Under the name of stationery are embraced all writing materials and implements, together with the numerous appliances of the desk and of mercantile and commercial offices. In addition to these, the term fancy stationery covers a miscellaneous assemblage of leather and other goods, such as pocket-books, purses, bags, card-cases, and many kindred objects which cannot be classified. The principal articles and operations of the stationery trade are dealt with in detail under separate headings—<hi rend="smallcaps">Bookbinding, Embossing, Ink, Lithography,</hi></p></body></text></TEI>