<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196348_0044.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-18-s06-0038-01" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>STRONTITES</label>,
or STRONTIAN <hi rend="smallcaps">earth,</hi> a new ſpecies of earth lately diſcovered at Strontian in Scotland.</p><p>Who the diſcoverer of this earth was we have not learned ; but Dr Kirwan ſays, the first information he received of it was from Dr Crawford in the year 1790. In the Miners Journal for February 1791 a good deſcription of its external appearance, with ſome account of its chemical properties, was publiſhed from the obſervations of Mr Sulzer. Dr Kirwan examined it in October 1793, and found it to be a new earth between the barytic and common limeſtone. Dr Hope, who is now joint profeſſor of chemiſtry with Dr Black in the univerſity of Edinburgh, read a paper on the 4th November 1793 before the Royal Society of Edinburgh, intitled “ An Aβcount of a Mineral from Strontian, and of a peculiar Species of Earth which it contains ;” an abridgment of which is publiſhed in the third volume of the Edinburgh Philoſophical Tranſactions. Mr Schmeiſſer read a paper on the ſame ſubject before the Royal Society of London in May 1794, which is publiſhed in their Tranſactions for that year, p. 418, &amp;c.</p><p><note anchored="false" n="1" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>Transactions of the Irish Academy, vol. v.</p></note> Its external characters are theſe : Its colour is whitiſh or light green ; its luſtre common ; its transparency intermediate between the ſemitranſparent and opaque ; its fracture ſtriated, preſenting oblong diſtinct concretions, ſomewhat uneven and bent; its hardneſſs moderate, being eaſily ſcratched, but not ſcraped. It is very brittle ; and its ſpecific gravity from 3,4 to 3,644.</p><p>For a full account of its chemical qualities we muſt refer to the books already mentioned, as all the accounts of it which we have ſeen are too long to insert here, and as we do not conſider the circumſtance of its being a newly discovered earth a ſufficient reaſon for running into a tedious detail till its utility be aſcertained. We ſhall, however, mention ſome of its moſt remarkable qualities. It requires 180 times its weight of water at a low temperature to diſſolve it. When diſſolved in boiling water, and allowed to cool, it depoſits tranſparent cryſtals, which when expoſed to the air become white and powdery. It is not affected by the ſulphuric acid ; but when diluted, 10,000 parts of it will diſſolve one of ſtrontites. Diluted nitric acid dissolves it rapidly. The muriatic acid, whether diluted or oxygenated, diſſolves it in a ſimilar manner.</p><p>Strontites has a ſtrong reſemblance to barytes, but eſſentially differs from it. Its ſpeciſic gravity is leſs; it parts with its carbonic acid when urged by heat ſomewhat more readily, and without ſuffering fuſion<note anchored="false" n="2" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>Transactions of the Royal Society of Edinburgh, vol. iii.</p></note>; when calcined, it imbibes moiſture with vaſtly greater avidity, ſwelling and cracking with more heat and noiſe. Strontites diſſolves much more abundantly in hot water than barytes ; and the form of the cryſtals of theſe pure earths is very diſſimilar. The compounds generated by ſtrontites differ from thoſe of barytes. It will ſuffice to mention the nitrate and muriate. This earth, united to nitric and muriatic acid, forms salts that ſuffer changes from expoſure to air, which do not happen to the nitrate and muriate of barytes. They are likewiſe much more ſoluble in water, and have cryſtals of a peculiar figure. The combinations of ſtrontites with acids are not, like thoſe of barytes, decompoſed by pruſſiate of lime or of potaſh. Strontites and its compounds tinge flame, which barytes does not. Laſtly, theſe earths diſagree in the order of their attractions. From theſe conſiderations it is concluded, that the mineral is not aerated barytes.</p><p>It alſo is diſtinguiſhed from calcareous ſpar or limeſtone : for it is much heavier, and retains its fixed air with more obſtinacy in the fire. The incomparably greater ſolubility of the pure earth in hot than in cold water, and the cryſtalline form it aſſumes, ſufficiently diſtinguiſh it from lime, which the diſpoſition of the nitrate and muriate to cryſtallize no leſs tends to do.</p><p>The moſt remarkable quality of ſtrontites is that of tinging flame of a red colour, The muriate has it in the moſt eminent degree, and its effects are well exhibited by putting a portion of the salt on the wick of a candle, which is thereby made to burn with a very beautiful blood-red flame. The nitrate ſtands next, then cryſtallized ſtrontites, and after it the acetite. A hundred parts of ſtrontites are compoſed of 61.21 of earth, 30.20 of carbonic acid, and 8.59 of water.</p></div></body></text></TEI>