<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196348_0055.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-18-s06-0049-02" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SUABIA</label>,
a circle of Germany, bounded on the north by the circle of Franconia and that of the Lower Rhine ; on the west by the circle of the Lower Rhine and Alſace ; on the ſouth by Switzerland ; and on the eaſt by the circle of Bavaria. Of all the circles of the empire, Suabia is the moſt divided ; it contains four eccleſiaſtic and thirteen lay principalities, nineteen independent prelacies and abbeys, twenty-six earldoms and lordships, and thirty-one tree cities. The prime directors of the circle, as they are termed, are the biſhop of Constance and the duke of Wirtemberg. The duke has the ſole direction of all that relates to war.</p><p>The mixture of the various forms of government and religious ſects ; the oppreſſion exerciſed by the great on the poor ; the game conſtantly played by the emperor, who poſseſſes many pieces of detached country in Suabia, which depend not on the circle, and can, in conſequence of his privileges as archduke of Auſtria, extend his posſeſſions in it by various ways; are circumſtances (ſays baron Rſeſheck<note anchored="false" n="1" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>Baron Riesbeck's Travels through Germany, vol. i.</p></note>) which give the cultivation of the country, and the character of the inhabitants, a moſt extraordinary caſt. In ſeveral of the poſt towns where you stop, you ſee the higheſt degree of cultivation in the midſt of the moſt savage wildneſs ; a great degree of knowledge and poliſh of manners, mixed with the grosseſt ignorance and ſuperſtition ; traces of liberty, under the deepeſt oppreſſion ; national pride, together with the contempt and neglect of the native country ; in ſhort, all the ſocial qualities in ſtriking contraſt and oppoſition to each other. Thoſe parts of Suabia which belong to the great potentates, ſuch as Wirtemberg, Auſtria, and Baden, are certainly the moſt improved. The whole of Suabia may comprehend about nine hundred German ſquare miles, and two millions of people. More than half of theſe are ſubjects of the three above mentioned princes, though they are not proprietors of near one half of the lands.</p></div></body></text></TEI>