<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196348_0052.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-18-s06-0046-11" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>STURMIUS</label>
(John), a learned philologer and rhetorician, was born at Sleida in Eiſel near Cologne in 1507. He studied at firſt in his native country with the ſons of count de Manderscheid, whoſe receiver his father was. He afterward purſued his ſtudy at Liege in the college of St Jerom, and then went to Louvain in 1524. Five years he spent there, three in learning and two in teaching. He ſet up a printing-press with Rudger Reſcius profeſſor of the Greek tongue, and printed ſeveral Greek authors. He went to Paris in 1529, where he was highly eſteemed, and read public lectures on the Greek and Latin writers, and on logic. He married there, and kept a great number of boarders : but as he liked what were called the <hi rend="italic">new opinions,</hi> he was more than once in danger ; and this undoubtedly was the reaſon why he removed to Straſburg in 1537, in order to take poſſeſſion of the place offered him by the magiſtrates. The year following he opened a ſchool, which became famous, and by his means obtained of Maximilian IL the title of an univerſity in 1566. He was very well ſkilled in polite literature, wrote Latin with great purity, and was a good teacher. His talents were not confined to the ſchool ; for he was frequently intruſted with deputations in Germany and foreign countries, and diſcharged theſe employments with great honour and diligence. He ſhowed extreme charity to the refugees on account of religion : He not only laboured to aſſiſt them by his advice and recommendations ; but he even impoveriſhed himſelf for them. He died in his 82d year, after he had been for ſome time blind. He published many books ; the principal of which are, 1. <hi rend="italic">Partitiones Dialectica.</hi> 2. <hi rend="italic">De Educatione Principum, 3. De Nobilitate Anglicana.</hi> 4. <hi rend="italic">Lingua Latinae resolvendae Ratio. 5.</hi> Excellent Notes on Ariſtotle’s and Hermogenes’s Rhetoric, &amp;c.</p><p>He ought not to be confounded with <hi rend="italic">John Sturmius,</hi> a native of Mechlin, and phyſician and proſeſſor of mathematics at Louvain, who alſo wrote ſeveral works.</p></div></body></text></TEI>