<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196348_0074.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-18-s06-0068-03" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SULPHUR</label>,
a well known ſubſtance, which is yellow, taſteleſs, hard, brittle, and when rubbed becomes electric. Its ſpecific gravity is from 1,9 to 2,35. According to Bergman, it gently evaporates at 170, melts at 185, and flames at 302 of Fahrenheit. It burns with a blue flame, and a diſagreeable ſuffocating ſmell ; in cloſe vessels it ſublimes without decompoſition, or only a decomposition proportionable to the quantity of air they contain ; when melted it becomes red, but recovers its colour on cooling<note anchored="false" n="1" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>Kirwan's Minerology.</p></note>. It is inſoluble in water, though by long trituration it is ſaid water will take up ſome of it, but it is rather diffuſed than diſſolved in it ; neither can ſpirit of wine unite to it, except when both are in a vaporous ſtate, and then 72 parts of ſpirit of wine take up 1 of sulphur ; it is ſoluble in hot oils, and alſo in fixed alkalis, both in the dry and liquid way ; it is decompoſed by boiling in concentrated nitrous acid, partly decompoſed and partly diſſolved by the vitriolic and oxygenated muriatic acid. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Chemistry-index.</hi></p><p>Sulphur was formerly ſuppoſed to conſiſt of ſulphuric acid and phlogiſton, in the proportion of 60 parts of the former to 40 of the latter ; but by the new fyſtem which is now generally adopted, ſulphur is reckoned a simple ſubſtance, and the ſulphuric acid a cqmpound of ſulphur and oxygene or vital air. This concluſion is founded on the following facts : 1. Sulphur does not burn unleſs vital air have acceſs to it. 2. During combuſtion it abſorbs vital air from the atmoſphere. 3. The ſulphuric produced by the combuſtion of ſulphur is equal in weight to the ſulphur employed and the quantity of air that has been conſumed.</p><p>Sulphur is found ſometimes pure, and ſometimes in combination with other subſtances. Of pure ſulphur there are ſeven varieties. 1.<note anchored="false" n="2" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>Fourcroy's Chemistry.</p></note> Tranſparent ſulphur, in eight-ſided cryſtals, with two truncated pyramids. It is generally depoſited by water on the ſurface of calcareous ſpar. Cadiz ſulphur is of this kind. 2. Tranſparent ſulphur in irregular fragments. Such is the ſulphur of Switzerland. 3. Whitiſh pulverulent ſulphur, deposited in ſiliceous geodes. In Franche Compté there are flints full of ſulphur. 4. Pulverulent ſulphur depoſited on the ſurface of mineral waters, ſuch as thoſe of Aix-la-Chapelle. 5. Cryſtalline ſulphur that has been ſublimed, found in the neighbourhood of volcanoes. 6. Pulverulent ſulphur ſublimed from volcanoes, found in abundance at Solfatara in the vicinity of Naples. 7. Sulphur in ſtalactites, formed by volcanic fires.</p><p>Sulphur is alſo found united with different ſubſtances, as with metals, when it is called <hi rend="italic">pyrites ;</hi> a ſhort account of which may be ſeen under the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Pyrites.</hi> Sometimes it is combined with calcareous earth, as in fetid calcareous stones and ſwine-ſtone. It has lately been diſcovered, that ſulphur is formed by a natural proceſs in animals and vegetables beginning to putrefy. It is found on ſtable-walls and in privies. It is alſo extracted from vegetables, from dock-root, cochlearia, &amp;c. M. Deyeux obtained it from the white of eggs. It has been alſo procured from horſe- dung.</p><p>The ſulphur uſed in Great Britain is generally brought is a pure ſtate from volcanic countries, where it abounds in an inexhauſtible quantity. It is well known, however, that ſome of the metallic ores in this country abound with it ; but from the common mode of purifying them, the ſulphur is diſſipated and loſt. Dr Watſon has ſhown, in a paper on lead-ore in the Philoſophical Tranſactions, that not leſs than 700 tons are annually diſſipated in the various lead-mines of England.</p><p>It is extracted from pyrites in the following manner in Saxony and Bohemia. The pyrites is put in ſmall pieces into earthen tubes : one of the tubes is placed on a furnace, and the other passes into a ſquare veſſel of caſt iron containing water. The ſulphur is diſunited by the heat from the pyrites, and paſſes into the veſſel ; but it is then very impure. It is afterwards melted in an iron ladle, when the earthy and metallic particles are depoſited by their weight, and the ſulphur being light riſes to the top. It is then poured off into a copper boiler, where it is farther purified, and afterwards poured into cylindrical moulds of wood, from which it receives the ſhape in which it is uſually ſold.</p><p>When melted ſulphur is gently heated, it flies off in a yellow powder, which is called <hi rend="italic">flowers of ſulphur.</hi> The operation is performed in this manner : Common ſulphur in powder is put into an earthen cucurbit, to the top of which a number of earthen pots inſerted in one another is fixed, known by the name of <hi rend="italic">aludels.</hi> The cucurbit is then heated till the ſulphur become liquid : it then riſes and attaches itself to the tides of the aludels.</p><p>Sulphur combined with an alkali is called <hi rend="italic">hepar ſulphuris, liver of sulphur,</hi> becauſe it reſembles in colour the liver of animals. In the French nomenclature it is called <hi rend="italic">ſulphure,</hi> and by thoſe Britiſh chemiſts who have adopted the new ſyſtem <hi rend="italic">ſulphuret.</hi></p><p>Water decompoſes the ſulphuret. The ſulphur is precipitated by acids, when a particular gas is extricated commonly called <hi rend="italic">hepatic gas,</hi> or, what is more expreſſive of its compoſition, <hi rend="italic">ſulphurated hydrogenous gas.</hi> The fetor of this gas is inſuſſerable, and is fatal to animals. It communicates a green colour to ſyrup of violets, and burns with a lightblue flame. It acts on metals and metallic oxides, eſpecially thoſe of lead and biſmuth, which it ſoon blackens. lt is decompoſed by vital air ; and accordingly, when it comes into contact with atmoſpheric air, a portion of the ſulphur is ſeparated. For this reaſon ſulphureous waters do not contain genuine liver of ſulphur.</p><p>The mineral acids act differently on ſulphur. If the ſulphuric acid be boiled on ſulphur, the acid acquires an amber colour, and a ſulphureous ſmell ; the ſulphur melts and ſwims like oil. When cooled, it concretes into globules of a greeniſh hue ; but a ſmall portion of the ſulphur is dissolved in the acid, which may be precipitated by an alkali. The flaming red nitrous acid acts powerfully on ſulphur. When poured upon melted ſulphur, it occaſions detonation and inflammation. The common muriatic acid produces no effect upon it ; but the oxygenated muriatic acid acts upon it with force.</p><p>Sulphur unites readily with all metallic ſubſtances, excepting gold, platina, and zinc ; at leaſt we have not found the means of uniting it with theſe directly, and without ſome intermediate ſubſtance. The degrees of affinity with which ſulphur combines with thoſe metals to which it may be readily united are different ; for it not only unites more eaſily and abundantly with ſome than with others, but it alſo quits thoſe with which it has a leſs affinity, to unite with others to which it has a ſtronger affinity.</p><p>The affinities of ſulphur, according to Mr Geoffroy’s table, are, fixed alkali, iron, copper, lead, ſilver, regulus of antimony, mercury, and gold ; and, according to Mr Gellert’s table, they are, iron, copper, tin, lead, ſilver, bismuth,<pb facs="gri_33125011196348_0075.tif" xml:id="eb03-18-s06-0069"/>
regulus oſ antimony, mercury, arſenic, and cobalt ; gold and zinc are marked in this table as being incapable of uniting with ſulphur.</p><p>The compounds formed by ſulphur with different metals are different ; but all of them poſſeſs a metallic lustre, without any ductility : theſe combinations of sulphur and of metals are very frequently found in a natural ſtate. Almoſt all the metals which we dig from the earth are naturally found combined with ſulphur, forming moſt of the ores and metallic minerals.</p><p>It is a curious phenomenon, that nitre mixed with ſulphur burns rapidly, even in cloſe vessels ; this is eaſily explained by the new ſyſtem. Nitre, when heat is applied to it, yields a great quantity of vital air ; and ſulphur is a combuſtible body, or, which is the ſame thing, has a ſtrong attraction for vital air. As vital air is thus ſupplied, which is the only principle neceſſary to combuſtion, communication with the atmoſpheric air is unneceſſary. The ſulphur will burn till the whole vital air which the nitre furniſhes be conſumed. The products obtained by this proceſs are different according to the proportions of nitre and ſulphur which are employed. If eight parts of ſulphur and one of nitre be ſet on fire in a cloſe veſſel, ſulphuric acid is produced ; and this is the method by which oil of vitriol or ſtrong ſulphuric acid was formerly made in Great Britain. The vessels in which the operation was performed were large glaſs balloons, with very large necks, each containing 400 or 500 pints. But it was attended with great expence, on account of the high price and brittleneſs of the balloons. A few years ago a cheaper method has been attempted with ſucceſs in France. The ſulphur is burned on a kind of gridirons, in large apartments lined with lead. As the acid condenſes it is conveyed by gutters into a reſervoir, and afterwards concentrated. It muſt be obſerved, that the ſulphuric acid thus obtained is always combined with a little sulphur and ſulphat of pot-aſh, a ſmall quantity of aluminous ſulphat and ſulphat of lead; but theſe ſubſtances are in ſo ſmall a proportion, that for common uſe it is not neceſſary to separate them. If neceſſary, however, it may eaſily be done by diſtilling the acid to dryneſs.</p><p>Gunpowder, the terrible effects of which are owing to its ſtrong tendency to combuſtion, is a mixture oſ ſulphur, nitre, and charcoal. (See <hi rend="smallcaps">Gunpowder).</hi> But there is another mixture of which ſulphur is an ingredient ſtill more violent in its effects : This is called fulminating <hi rend="italic">powder,</hi> and is compoſed of three parts of nitre, two parts of the carbonate of pot-aſh, and one of powdered ſulphur. Theſe being cloſely united together by trituration in a hot marble mortar, when expoſed to a flight degree of heat, will melt, and produce a violent detonation like the report of a cannon. A dram oſ this mixture is ſufficient for the experiment.</p><p>Sulphur is of great uſe in chemiſtry, in medicine, and the arts. Sulphur is uſeful in making ſome fuſions, precipitations, and ſeparations of metals and minerals ; but is particularly uſeful, as being the ſubſtance from which the ſulphuric acid is obtained. Hepar ſulphuris is employed in chemiſtry for making ſeveral ſolutions.</p><p>Sulphur is employed in medicine both internally and externally. It is given either in flowers or in lozenges, made up with ſugar, or joined to magneſia, cryſtals of tartar, manna, caffia, lenitive electuary, &amp;c. Two or three drams generally prove laxative ; and it is given in ſuch doſes in cafes ot piles of uterine, and other hoemorrhagies ; becauſe it does not ſtimulate nor heat during its operation, nor leave a dispoſition to coſtiveneſs, as rhubarb, aloes, and other hot reſinous purges do. Sulphur was formerly much recommended in coughs and diſeaſes of the breaſt, but of late its virtues as a pectoral have been much doubted. When applied externally, it is mixed with ſome unctuous ſubſtance, as hogs lard, butter, &amp;c. and is rubbed on ſuch parts oſ the body as are affected with eruptions.</p><p>Some phyſicians and chemiſts, conſidering that ſulphur is infallible in water, and capable of reſiſting the action of moſt menſtruums, have affirmed, that it can produce no effect when taken internally, single and unaltered ; but this aſſertion ſeems to be without foundation ; for it is certain, that the sweat and perlpiration of thoſe who take ſulphur internally have a ſmell evidently ſulphureous. Belides, sulphur is much more fallible than is generally believed. It is attacked by all oily and ſaponaceous ſubſtances, and conſequently by almoſt all animal liquors.</p><p>We cannot eaſily form a very diſtinct and clear idea of the manner in which ſulphur acts internally upon our bodies ; but, from obſervations made upon its effects, it appears to be dividing, ſtimulating, and ſomewhat heating : it principally acts upon the perſpirable parts of the body, the chief of which are the ſkin and lungs ; and from this property it is particularly uſeful in ſome diſeaſes of theſe parts.</p><p>Sulphur is alſo a powerful repellent, as appears from its curing ſeveral kinds of itch, merely by external application, in form of ointments and pomatums. Several mineral waters, which are drunk or uſed as baths for ſome diſeaſes, owe their good qualities to ſulphur contained in them.</p><p>Sulphur is allo uſed in several arts. By means of it fine impreſſions of engraved ſtones are taken. Matches are formed of it ; and its utility as an ingredient in the preparation of gunpowder and fireworks is well known. Laſtly, it is uſed for whitening wool, ſilk, and many other matters expoſed to its vapour during its combuſtion ; the colours and redneſs of which could not be deſtroyed by any other ſubſtance, but are quickly effaced by this acid vapour.</p><p><hi rend="italic">SULPHUR-Wort,</hi> in botany. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Peucedanum.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">SULPHURIC-acid,</hi> the name adopted by the French chemiſts for the vitriolic acid. It is formed by a combination of ſulphur with vital air, as deſcribed under the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Sulphur.</hi> When ſulphur is burned with a low degree of heat, it burns with a blue flame, and diffuſes a ſuffocating vapour, which, when collected, is called <hi rend="italic">ſulphureous acid.</hi> When ſulphur is expoſed to ſtrong heat it burns rapidly, and emits a lively white flame, and has no ſmell ;. the reſidue is called <hi rend="italic">ſulphuric acid.</hi> The ſulphureous is a weaker acid than the ſulphuric, owing to its containing a leſs quantity of oxygene.</p></div></body></text></TEI>