<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196348_0054.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-18-s06-0048-03" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>STYRAX</label>,
the <hi rend="smallcaps">stor.ax-tr.ee,</hi> in botany : A genus of plants belonging to the claſs of <hi rend="italic">decandria,</hi> and to the order of <hi rend="italic">monοgynia ;</hi> and in the natural ſystem ranging under the 18th order, <hi rend="italic">bicornes.</hi> Linnæus only mentions one ſpecies of this genus, the st <hi rend="italic">yrax-officinale ;</hi> but Aiton, in his <hi rend="italic">Hortus Kewensis,</hi> has added two more ; namely, the <hi rend="italic">grande folium</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Levigatum</hi>; and we believe a fourth may now be added, the st <hi rend="italic">yrax benzoin.</hi></p><p>The <hi rend="italic">officinale</hi> uſually riſes above twenty feet in height ; it sends off many ſtrong branches, which are covered with a roughiſh bark of a grey colour: the leaves are broad, elliptical, entire, ſomewhat pointed, on the upper ſurface ſmooth, and of a light green colour, on the under ſurface covered with a whitish down ; they are placed alternately, and ſtand upon ſhort footſtalks :<note anchored="false" n="1" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>Woodville's Medical Botany, vol. ii.</p></note> the flowers are large, white, and diſpoſed in cluſters upon ſhort peduncles, which terminate the branches : the corolla is monopetalous, funnel-ſhaped, and divided at the limb into five lance-ſhaped ſegments : the filaments are ten, placed in a regular circle, and ſeem to adhere towards the baſe : the antheræ are erect and oblong : the germen is oval, and ſupports a ſlender ſtyle, with a ſimple stigma : the fruit is a pulpy pericarpium, which contains one or two nuts of an oval compreſſed figure.</p><p>The reſinous drug called st <hi rend="italic">orax</hi> iſſues in a fluid ſtate from inciſions made in the trunk or branches of the tree. Two sorts of this reſin have been commonly diſtinguiſhed in the ſhops.<note anchored="false" n="2" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>Lewis' Materia Medica, vol. ii.</p></note>. <hi rend="italic">Storax in the tear:</hi> is ſcarcely, if ever, found in ſeparate tears, but in maſſes, ſometimes compoſed of whitiſh and pale reddiſh brown tears, and sometimes of an uniform reddiſh yellow or browniſh appearance ; unctuous and ſoft like wax, and free from viſible impurities. This is ſuppoſed to be the sort which the ancients received from Pamphylia in reeds or canes, and which was thence named c <hi rend="italic">alamita.</hi></p><p>2. <hi rend="italic">Common storax :</hi> in large maſſes, conſiderably lighter and leſs compact than the former, and having a larger admixture of woody matter like ſaw-duſt. This appears to be the kind intended by the London college, as they direct their ſtyrax calamita to be purified, for medicinal uſe, by ſoftening it with boiling water, and preſſing it out from the feces betwixt warm iron plates ; a proceſs which the firſt sort does not ſtand in need of. And indeed there is rarely any other than this impure ſtorax to be met with in the ſhops.</p><p>Storax, with ſome of the ancients, was a familiar remedy as a resolvent, and particularly uſed in catarrhal complaints, coughs, aſthmas, menſtrual obſtructions, &amp;c. and from its affinity to the balſams it was alſo preſcribed in ulcerations of the lungs, and other ſtates of pulmonary conſumption. And our pharmacopoeias formerly directed the pilulae e st <hi rend="italic">yrace;</hi> but this odoriferous drug has now no place in any of the officinal compounds ; and though a medicine which might ſeem to promiſe ſome efficacy in nervous debilities, yet by modern practitioners it is almoſt totally diſregarded.</p><p>The styrax <hi rend="italic">benzoin</hi> is deſcribed by Dr Dryander in the Philoſophical Tranſactions for 1787, p. 308, &amp;c. It has been characterized by oblong acuminated leaves, which are downy underneath, and nearly of the length of the racemi. The botanical character of this tree was miſtaken by modern botanists till Dr Dryander aſcertained it to be a ſtyrax. Benzoin was long ſuppoſed to be the produce of a ſpecies of <hi rend="italic">laurus.</hi> Linnæus detected this error ; but he committed another; for he tells us, that it is furniſhed by a ſhrub which, in the country where it grows, is called <hi rend="italic">croton bezoe ;</hi> and afterwards, in his <hi rend="italic">Supplementum Plantarum,</hi> deſcribes the ſame plant a ſecond time, under the name of <hi rend="italic">terminalia benzoin.</hi></p><p>This tree, which is a native of Sumatra, is deemed in six years of ſufficient age for affording the benzoin, or when its trunk acquires about ſeven or eight inches in diameter ; the bark is then cut through longitudinally, or ſomewhat obliquely, at the origin of the principal lower branches, from which the drug exudes in a liquid ſtate, and by expoſure to the sun and air ſoon concretes, when it is ſcraped off from the bark with a knife or chiſel. The quantity of benzoin which one tree affords never exceeds three pounds, nor are the trees found to ſuſtain the effects of theſe annual inciſions longer than ten or twelve years. The benzoin which iſſues firſt from the wounded bark is the pureſt, being ſoft, extremely fragrant, and very white ; that which is leſs eſteemed is of a browniſh colour, very hard, and mixed with various impurities, which it acquires during its long continuance upon the trees. Eſchelſkron diſtinguishes benzoin into three kinds, viz. <hi rend="italic">camayan poeti,</hi> or white benjamin, which, upon being melted in a bladder by the heat of the ſun, appears marked with red ſtreaks or veins. <hi rend="italic">Camayan bamatta</hi> is leſs white than the former, and often ſpotted with white circles, called eyes, from the number of which its goodneſs is eſtimated : it likewiſe melts by the heat of the ſun. <hi rend="italic">Camayan itam,</hi> or black benjamin, which requires to be melted in hot water for its preſervation in bladders. In Arabia, Perſia, and other parts of the Eaſt, the coarſer kinds of benjamin are consumed for fumigating and perfuming the temples, and for deſtroying infects.</p><p>The benzoin which we find here in the ſhops is in large brittle maſſes, compoſed partly of white, partly of yellowiſh or light brown, and often alſo of darker coloured pieces : that which is cleared, and contains the moſt white matter, called by authors <hi rend="italic">benzοe amygdalοides,</hi> is accounted the beſt. This reſin has very little taſte, impreſſing on the palate only a slight ſweetneſs : its ſmell, eſpecially when rubbed or heated, is extremely fragrant and agreeable. It totally diſſolves in rectified ſpirit, (the impurities excepted, which are generally in a very ſmall quantity), into a deep yellowiſh red liquor, and in this ſtate diſcovers a degree of warmth and pungency, as well as ſweetneſs. It imparts, by digeſtion, to water alſo a conſiderable ſhare of its fragrance, and a slight pungency : the filtered liquor, gently exhaled, leaves nor a reſinous or mucilaginous extract, but a crystalline matter, ſeemingly of a ſaline nature, amounting to one-tenth or one eighth of the weight of the benzoin. Exposed to the fire in proper veſſels, it yields a quantity of a white ſaline concrete, called fl <hi rend="italic">ores benzoes,</hi> of an acidulous taſte and grateful odour, ſoluble in rectified ſpirit, and in water by the assiſtance of heat.<pb facs="gri_33125011196348_0055.tif" xml:id="eb03-18-s06-0049"/>
The principal uſe of this fragrant resin is in perfumes, and as a cosmetic ; for which laſt purpose, a solution of it in ſpirit of wine is mixed with ſo much water as is ſufficient to render it milky, as twenty times its quantity or more. It promiſes, however, to be applicable to other uſes, and to approach in virtue, as in fragrance, to ſtorax and balſam of Tolu. It is ſaid to be of great ſervice in diſorders of the breaſt, for reſolving obſtructions of the pulmonary vesſels, and promoting expectoration : in which intentions the flowers are ſometimes given, from three or four grains to fifteen. The white powder, precipitated by water from ſolutions of the benzoin in ſpirit, has been employed by ſome as ſimilar and ſuperior to the flowers, but appears to be little other than the pure benzoin in ſubſtance ; it is not the ſaline, but the reſinous matter of the benzoin, that is moſt diſpoſed to be precipitated from ſpirit by water. The flowers, ſnuffed up the noſe, are ſaid to be a powerful errhine.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Liquid storax</hi> is a reſinous juice obtained from a tree called by Linnæus <hi rend="italic">liquidambar styraciflua,</hi> a native of Virginia and Mexico, and lately naturalized in this country. The juice called liquidambar is ſaid to exude from inciſions made in the trunk of this tree, and the liquid ſtorax to be obtained by boiling the bark or branches in water. Two sorts of liquid ſtorax are diſtinguished by authors ; one, the purer part of the reſinous matter that riſes to the ſurface in boiling, separated by a ſtrainer, of the consiſtence of honey, tenacious like turpentine, of a reddiſh or aſh brown colour, moderately tranſparent, of an acrid unctuous taſte, and a fragrant ſmell, faintly reſembling that of the ſolid ſtorax, but ſomewhat diſagreeable: the other, the more impure part, which remains on the ſtrainer, is not tranſparent, in ſmell and taſte is much weaker, and contains a conſiderable proportion of the ſubſtance of the bark. What is moſt commonly met with under this name in the shops is of a weak ſmell and a grey colour, and is ſuppoſed to be an artificial compoſition.</p><p>Liquid ſtorax has been employed chiefly in external applications. Among us, it is at preſent almoſt wholly in diſuſe.</p></div></body></text></TEI>