<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="chi.28490924-1526168109_Page_0555.jpf" type="entry" xml:id="eb07-20-s04-0488-02" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SOUTHAMPTON</label>,
a town of Hampshire, seventy seven miles from London. It is finely situated at the junc tion of the river Test with the Itchen ; these form an ex panse of water, by which vessels may approach the town. It was anciently fortified, and the remains of its walls and castle still exist. It is one of the bestbuilt towns of Eng 1and. The High Street is broad and well paved. South ampton contains five parish churches, several almshouses, a grammar school, some convenient bathinghouses, public rooms, and an elegant theatre. The borough was incor porated by Charles I., and is governed by a mayor, re corder, bailiffs, sheriff, and commoncouncil men. It returns two members to parliament. It is in fact a county of itself, having its own magistrates, of whom the bishop of Winchester is one. This town has long been a place of great trade with Portugal, chiefly for the importation of portwine and fruit. It has also some trade with France, with the islands of Guernsey, Jersey, Alderney, and espe cially with the Isle of Wight, to which place packetboats are constantly sailing. The mildness of the air, the facility of making excursions by water as well as by land, the vicinity of the lsle of Wight and of New Forest, contribute to render the town a desirable place for either a temporary or a permanent residence, which is further recommended by the excellent supplies of fish, fruit, meat, and other ne cessaries. The railway which connects Southampton with the metropolis will greatly tend to promote its prosperity. The inhabitants amounted in 1801 to 7629, in 1811 to 9258, in 1821 to 13,913, and in 1831 to 19,324.</p></div></body></text></TEI>