<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="chi.28490924-1526168109_Page_0658.jpf" type="entry"
                xml:id="eb07-20-s04-0577-01" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                <p><label>SECT</label> . II.—EXPERIMENTAL RESEARCHES CONCERNING THE ELASTIC FORCE OP
                    STEAM AT DIFFERENT TEMPERATURES.</p>
                <p>23. The earliest researches we have met with into the phenomena of steam, under
                    taken with the philosophical purpose of obtaining experimental data for the
                    scientific investigation of its properties and relations, are to be met with in
                    a scarce work, printed at Basle in 1769, and entitled,</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">“ Specimen physico-chernicurn de Digestore Papini; primitias
                        experimentorum novorum circa fuidοrum a calore rarefactionem et vapoream
                        elasticitatem exhibens, &amp;·c.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Auctore Jo. Henrico Ziegler.”</hi> His experimental boiler
                    consisted of a copper vessel (fig. 7) AA, silvered internally, and belted
                    externally with massive iron hoops BB. A strong framework of iron, attached to
                    the upper hoop, gives support to the circular cover B, (fig. 8,) in which there
                    are an opening P for admitting water, an other D into which an elaterometer is
                    inserted, consisting of a bottle G, containing mercury, and a glass tube c c
                    cased in iron, open at both ends, and immersed in the mercury at the bottom ;
                    the third or central aperture E being occupied by a copper tube F, closed below,
                    and containing oil or other viscid liquid, to act as a bath for the bulb of the
                    thermometer F and its protector from the pressure of the vapour. The method of
                    using this apparatus was as follows. The digester being partly filled with
                    water, closed and placed on the fire, the generation of the steam would raise
                    the oil or mercury in the bath<pb facs="chi.28490924-1526168109_Page_0659.jpf"
                        xml:id="eb07-20-s04-0578"/> (E) to the temperature of the water and steam
                    within, so as to give to the thermometer F an indication of the temperature ;
                    and, at the same time, the elastic force of the steam flowing or moving by would
                    raise it in C to a certain number of inches, so as to cause the corresponding
                    pressure. This apparatus is both appropriate and ingenious, and indicates
                    considerable mechanical knowledge in its inventor, a physician of Winterthour in
                    Switzerland. Un happily he lived too remote from the scene of the philosophical
                    discoveries of that period, to adopt the precautions necessary to give value to
                    his experiments. He allowed atmospheric air to mingle with the steam to such an
                    extent as greatly to vitiate his results.</p>
                <p>24. M. Betancourt visited England about the end of last century ; and having been
                    employed to select ma chines, models, and drawings for the Spanish government,
                    made himself acquainted with the use of steam in Great Britain at that period.
                    On his return, he immediately undertook a series of experiments on the force of
                    the vapour of water, alcohol, and other liquids, at various temperatures. His
                    apparatus is tolerably perfect; and the precautions which he adopted for the
                    removal of atmospheric air from intermixture with the vapour, give his
                    experiments considerable value and precision. Some of his experiments were made
                    in vacuo ; and he seems to have been one of the first philosophers who examined
                    the production of steam at temperatures below the ordinary point of ebullition,
                    under the pressure of the atmosphere His experiments extend from 32° up to 279°,
                    being 67° above the ordinary boiling point.</p>
                <p>His apparatus (Fig. 9) consisted of a spheroidal copper boiler A, about eight
                    inches in diameter, fifteen inches high, and a tenth of an inch in thickness ; a
                    flat cover was soldered on the top of it, and three apertures were formed into
                    which were inserted a thermometer EC, a glass tube D, and a plug B for admitting
                    water. The glass tube being bent downwards at F, was recurved upwards at G,
                    leaving an upright stem, ten feet high, and hermetically sealed at the top, so
                    as to leave a perfect vacuum in that end of the tube, over a column of mercury
                    of about 30 inches in the two</p>
                <p>branches of the recurvation at the bottom. The boiler was provided with a
                    stopcock <hi rend="italic">b</hi>, by which the air was extracted from the
                    boiler pτevious to experiment, by means of an air-pump TV, communicating with W
                    ; and when this was accomplished so as to obtain a vacuum on both ends of the
                    mercurial column, the mercury stood, as in the figure, on nearly the same level
                    in both its branches. The fire was instantly applied, and the crackling noise
                    which followed informed him that the ebullition had commenced, and the steam in
                    the boiler pressing on that end of the mercurial column nearest to it, raised
                    the other in the vacuum a certain quantity above its outer level, indicating its
                    elastic force, which gradually increased until it became at the usual heat of
                    boiling water, equal to twenty eight French inches, the mean pressure of the
                    atmosphere. The following table will enable us to estimate the value of these
                    experiments ; it is given in degrees of Reaumur’s thermometer, of which 0°
                    coincides with 32° of our common scale, and 80° with our boiling point 212°
                    Fahren heit, each degree of Reaumur being equal to 2¼ of our scale. The pressure
                    is in French inches of mercury :—</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Degrees of Fahrenheit.</cell>
                        <cell>Reaumur's Scale.</cell>
                        <cell>First Series of Observations.</cell>
                        <cell>Second Scries of Observations</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>32°</cell>
                        <cell>0°</cell>
                        <cell>Inches of Mercury. 0∙0</cell>
                        <cell>Inches of Mercury 0∙0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>43∙25</cell>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>0∙05</cell>
                        <cell>0∙02</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>54∙50</cell>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell>0∙17</cell>
                        <cell>0∙15</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>65∙75</cell>
                        <cell>15</cell>
                        <cell>035</cell>
                        <cell>0∙35</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>7700</cell>
                        <cell>20</cell>
                        <cell>0∙62</cell>
                        <cell>0∙65</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>88∙25</cell>
                        <cell>25</cell>
                        <cell>1∙00</cell>
                        <cell>1∙05</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>99∙50</cell>
                        <cell>30</cell>
                        <cell>1∙50</cell>
                        <cell>1∙52</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>110∙75</cell>
                        <cell>35</cell>
                        <cell>2∙12</cell>
                        <cell>2∙15</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>12200</cell>
                        <cell>40</cell>
                        <cell>290</cell>
                        <cell>292</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>13325</cell>
                        <cell>45</cell>
                        <cell>4∙00</cell>
                        <cell>3∙95</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>144∙50</cell>
                        <cell>50</cell>
                        <cell>5∙50</cell>
                        <cell>5∙35</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>155∙75</cell>
                        <cell>55</cell>
                        <cell>7∙55</cell>
                        <cell>7∙32</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>16700</cell>
                        <cell>60</cell>
                        <cell>10∙10</cell>
                        <cell>9∙95</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>178∙25</cell>
                        <cell>65</cell>
                        <cell>13∙25</cell>
                        <cell>13∙20</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>189∙50</cell>
                        <cell>70</cell>
                        <cell>17∙50</cell>
                        <cell>16∙90</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>200∙75</cell>
                        <cell>75</cell>
                        <cell>22∙35</cell>
                        <cell>21∙75</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>21200</cell>
                        <cell>80</cell>
                        <cell>2860</cell>
                        <cell>2800</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>22325</cell>
                        <cell>85</cell>
                        <cell>3700</cell>
                        <cell>36∙45</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>234∙50</cell>
                        <cell>90</cell>
                        <cell>47∙20</cell>
                        <cell>46∙40</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>24575</cell>
                        <cell>95</cell>
                        <cell>58∙20</cell>
                        <cell>57∙80</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>25700</cell>
                        <cell>100</cell>
                        <cell>7240</cell>
                        <cell>7180</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>268∙25</cell>
                        <cell>105</cell>
                        <cell>84∙90</cell>
                        <cell>86∙80</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>279∙50</cell>
                        <cell>110</cell>
                        <cell>9800</cell>
                        <cell>9800</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>The slight deviation of these experiments from each other indicates considerable
                    accuracy of experiment ; and the slight excess in the former of the two series
                    is attributed to the formation of a less perfect vacuum at the commencement of
                    the observations, arising from the smaller quantity of water in the boiler when
                    the experiments were made.</p>
                <p>It should, however, he noticed, that there is one omis sion of some importance in
                    the experiments of M. Betan court. He inserts the <hi rend="italic">bare
                        bulb</hi> of his thermometer into the reservoir among the water, so as to
                    suffer all the variations imposed on it by the varying elasticity of the steam.
                    By following the method adopted by his predecessor, M. Ziegler, of inserting a
                    metallic tube to sustain the pressure of the steam, and forming it into a
                    mercurial bath for containing the thermometer, and so transmitting the heat of
                    the steam to it without exposure to variable pressure, a source of considerable
                    error might have been avoided. This precaution is essential to a good set of
                    experiments on steam ; for a very slight pressure, even of the finger, on the
                    bulb of a thermometer will raise it several degrees.</p>
                <p>25. Of British philosophers, Dr Robison was one of the first to make accurate and
                    systematic experiments on the<pb facs="chi.28490924-1526168109_Page_0660.jpf"
                        xml:id="eb07-20-s04-0579"/> phenomena of the temperature and elastic force
                    of steam. They appear to have been made in 1778. His apparatus is represented in
                    the accompanying fissure.</p>
                <p>* ABCD (Fig. 10.) is the section of a small digester made of copper.</p>
                <p>Its lid, which was fasterιed to the body with screws, was pierced with three
                    holes, each of which had a small pipe soldered into it. The first hole was
                    furnished with a brass safety-valve V,</p>
                <p>nicely fitted to it by grinding. The area of this valve was exactly ½th of an
                    inch. There rested on the stalk at the top of this valve the arm of a steelyard
                    carrying a sliding weight. This arm had a scale of equal parts, so adjusted to
                    the weight, that the number on the scale corresponded to the inches of mercury,
                    whose pressure on the under surface of the valve is equal to that of the
                    steelyard ou its top ; so that when the weight was at the division 10, the
                    pressure of the steelyard on the valve was just equal to that of a column of
                    mercury 10 inches high, and ½th of an inch base.</p>
                <p>The middle hole contained a thermometer T firmly fixed into it, so that no vapour
                    could escape by its sides. The ball of this thermometer was but a little way
                    below the lid. The third hole received occasionally the end of a glass pipe SGF,
                    whose descending leg was about 36 inches long. When this syphon was not used,
                    the hole was properly shut with a plug.</p>
                <p>* The vessel was half filled with distilled water which had been purged of air by
                    boiling. The lid was then fixed on, having the third hole S plugged up. A lamp
                    being placed under the vessel, the water boiled, and the steam issued copiously
                    by the safety-valve. The thermometer stood at 213°, and a barometer in the room
                    at 29∙9 inches. The weight was then put on the fifth division. The thermometer
                    immediately began to rise ; and when it was at 220, the steam issued by the
                    sides of the valve. The weight was removed to the 10th division ; but, before
                    the thermometer could be distinctly observed, the steam was issuing at the
                    valve. The lamp was removed further from the bottom of the vessel, that the
                    progress of heating might be more moderate ; and when the steam ceased to issue
                    from the valve, the thermometer was at 227∙ The weight was now shifted to 15 ;
                    and, by gradually ap proaching the lamp, the steam again issued, and the
                    thermometer was at 232½. This mode of trial was continued all the way to the
                    75th division of the scale. The experiments were then repeated in the contrary
                    order ; that is, the weight being suspended at the 75th division, and the steam
                    issuing strongly at the valve, the lamp was withdrawn, and the moment</p>
                <p>the steam ceased to come out, the thermometer was obser ved. The same was done at
                    the 70th, 65th division, &amp;c.</p>
                <p>These experiments were several times repeated both ways ; and the means of all
                    the results for each division are expressed in the subjoin ed table, where
                    column 1st expresses the elasticity of the steam, being the sum of 29∙9 ; and
                    the division of the steel yard, column 2d, expresses the temperature of the
                    steam corresponding to this elasticity.</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Elasticity.</cell>
                        <cell>Temperature.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>35 inches.</cell>
                        <cell>209°</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>40</cell>
                        <cell>226</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>45 .</cell>
                        <cell>232</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>50</cell>
                        <cell>237</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>55</cell>
                        <cell>242</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>60</cell>
                        <cell>247</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>65</cell>
                        <cell>251</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>70</cell>
                        <cell>255</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>75</cell>
                        <cell>259</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>80</cell>
                        <cell>263</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>85</cell>
                        <cell>267</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>90</cell>
                        <cell>270½</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>95</cell>
                        <cell>274½</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>100</cell>
                        <cell>278</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>105</cell>
                        <cell>281</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>* A very different process was necessary for ascertaining the elasticity of the
                    steam in lower temperatures, and consequently under smaller pressures than that
                    of the atmosphere. The glass syphon SGF was now fixed into its hole in the lid
                    of the digester. The water was made to boil smartly for some time, and the steam
                    issued co piously both at the valve and at the syphon. The lower end of the
                    syphon was now immersed into a broad saucer of mercury, and the lamp instantly
                    removed, and every thing was allowed to grow cold. By this the steam was
                    gradually condensed, and the mercury rose in the syphon, without sensibly
                    sinking in the saucer. The valve and all the joints were smeared with a thick
                    clammy cement, composed of oil, tallow, and rosin, which effectually pre vented
                    all ingress of air. The weather was clear and frosty, and the barometer standing
                    at 29.84, and the thermometer in the vessel at 42°. The mercury in the syphon
                    stood at 297, or somewhat higher, thus showing a very complete condensation. The
                    whole vessel was surrounded with pounded ice, of the temperature 32°. This made
                    no sensible change in the height of the mercury. A mark was now made at the
                    surface of the mercury. One observer was stationed at the thermometer, with
                    instructions to call out as the thermometer reached the divisions 42, 47, 52,
                    57, and so on by every five degrees till it should attain the boiling heat.
                    Another observer noted the corresponding descents of the mercury by a scale of
                    inches, which had its beginning placed at 29∙84 from the surface of the mercury
                    in the saucer.</p>
                <p>* The pounded ice was now removed, and the lamp placed at a considerable distance
                    below the vesseI, so as to warm its contents very slowly. These observations
                    being very easily made, were several times repeated, and their mean results are
                    set down in the following table: only ob serve, that it was found difficult to
                    note down the descents for every fifth degree, because they succeeded each other
                    so fast. Every 10th was judged sufficient for establishing the law of variation.
                    The first column of the table contains the temperature, and the second the
                    descent (in inches) of the mercury from the mark 29.84.</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Temperature.</cell>
                        <cell>Elasticity.</cell>
                        <cell>Temperature.</cell>
                        <cell>Elasticity.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>32°</cell>
                        <cell>0.0</cell>
                        <cell>130 <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi></cell>
                        <cell>3.95</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>40</cell>
                        <cell>0.1</cell>
                        <cell>140</cell>
                        <cell>5.15</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>50</cell>
                        <cell>0.2</cell>
                        <cell>150</cell>
                        <cell>6.72</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>60</cell>
                        <cell>0.35</cell>
                        <cell>160</cell>
                        <cell>8.65</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>70</cell>
                        <cell>0.55</cell>
                        <cell>170</cell>
                        <cell>11.05</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>80</cell>
                        <cell>0.82</cell>
                        <cell>180</cell>
                        <cell>14.05</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>90</cell>
                        <cell>1.18</cell>
                        <cell>190</cell>
                        <cell>17.85</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>100</cell>
                        <cell>1.61</cell>
                        <cell>200</cell>
                        <cell>22.62</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>110</cell>
                        <cell>2.25</cell>
                        <cell>210</cell>
                        <cell>28.65</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>120</cell>
                        <cell>3.00</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>Four or five numbers at the top of the column of elasticities, are not so
                    accurate as the others, because the mercury passed pretty quickly through these
                    points. But the progress was extremely regular through the remaining points ; so
                    that the elasticities corresponding to temperutures above 70° may be considered
                    as very accurately ascertained.</p>
                <p>* Not being altogether satisfied with the method employed for measuring the
                    elasticity in temperatures above that of boiling water, a better form of
                    experiment was adopted. Indeed it was the want of other apparatus which made it
                    necessary to employ the former. À glass tube was procured of the form
                    represented in Fig. 11, having a little cistern L, from the top and bottom of
                    which proceeded the syphons K and MN. The cistern contained mercury, and the
                    tube MN was of a slender bore, and was about six feet two inches long. The end K
                    was firmly fixed in the third hole of the lid, and the long leg of the syphon
                    was furnished with a scale of in ches, and firmly fastened to an upright
                        post.<pb facs="chi.28490924-1526168109_Page_0661.jpf"
                        xml:id="eb07-20-s04-0580"/> The lamp was now applied at such a distance from
                    the vessel as to warm it slowly, and make the water boil, the steam escaping for
                    some time through the safety-valve. A heavy weight was then sus pended on the
                    steelyard ; such as it was known that the vessel would support, and, at the same
                    time, such as would not allow the steam to force the mercury out of the long
                    tube. The thermometer began im mediately to rise, as also</p>
                <p>the mercury in the tube</p>
                <p>MN. Their correspondent stations are marked</p>
                <p>in the following table.</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Temperature.</cell>
                        <cell>Elasticity.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>212°</cell>
                        <cell>0.0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>220</cell>
                        <cell>5.9</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>230</cell>
                        <cell>14.6</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>240</cell>
                        <cell>25.0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>250</cell>
                        <cell>36.9</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>260</cell>
                        <cell>50.4</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>270</cell>
                        <cell>64.2</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>280</cell>
                        <cell>76.0</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>This form of the experiment is much more susceptible of accuracy than the other,
                    and the measures of elasticity are more to be depended on. In repeating the
                    experiment, they were found much more constant ; whereas, in the former method,
                    differences occurred of two inches and upwards.</p>
                <p>* We may now connect the two sets of experiments into ne table, by adding to the
                    numbers in this last table the constant height 29∙9, which was the height of the
                    mercury in the barometer during the last set of observations.</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Temperature.</cell>
                        <cell>Elasticity.</cell>
                        <cell>Temperature.</cell>
                        <cell>Elasticity.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>32°</cell>
                        <cell>0.0</cell>
                        <cell>160</cell>
                        <cell>8.65</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>40</cell>
                        <cell>0.1</cell>
                        <cell>170</cell>
                        <cell>11.05</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>50</cell>
                        <cell>0.2</cell>
                        <cell>180</cell>
                        <cell>14.05</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>60</cell>
                        <cell>0.35</cell>
                        <cell>190</cell>
                        <cell>17.85</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>70</cell>
                        <cell>0.55</cell>
                        <cell>200</cell>
                        <cell>22.62</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>80</cell>
                        <cell>0.82</cell>
                        <cell>210</cell>
                        <cell>28.65</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>90</cell>
                        <cell>1.18</cell>
                        <cell>220</cell>
                        <cell>35.8</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>100</cell>
                        <cell>1.6</cell>
                        <cell>230</cell>
                        <cell>44.5</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>110</cell>
                        <cell>2.25</cell>
                        <cell>240</cell>
                        <cell>54.9</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>120</cell>
                        <cell>3.0</cell>
                        <cell>250</cell>
                        <cell>66.8</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>130</cell>
                        <cell>3.95</cell>
                        <cell>260</cell>
                        <cell>80.3</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>140</cell>
                        <cell>5.15</cell>
                        <cell>270</cell>
                        <cell>94.1</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>150</cell>
                        <cell>6.72</cell>
                        <cell>280</cell>
                        <cell>105.9</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>26. In the mean time, however, Mr Watt had been led, in the course of his
                    invention of the steam-engine, to make experiments on the elastic force of
                    steam, of which he has given the following account, and which was annexed by
                    himself to Dr Robison’s original article in this work.</p>
                <p>In the winter of 1764-5, I made experiments at G1as gow on the subject, in the
                    course of my endeavours to improve the steam-engine, and as I did not then think
                    of any <hi rend="italic">simple</hi> method of trying the elasticities of steam
                    at temperatures less than that of boiling water, and had at hand a digester by
                    which the elasticities at greater heats could be tried, I considered that, by
                    establishing the ratios in which they proceeded, the elasticities at lower heats
                    might be found nearly enough for my purpose. I there fore fitted a thermometer
                    to the digester, with its bulb in the inside, placed a small cistern with
                    mercury also within</p>
                <p>the digester, fixed a small barometer tube with its end in the mercury, and left
                    the upper end open. I then made the digester boil for some time, the steam
                    issuing at the safety-valve, until the air contained in the digester was
                    supposed to be expelled. The safety-valve being shut, the steam acted upon the
                    surface of the mercury in the cistern, and made it rise in the tube. When it
                    reached to 15 inches above the surface of the mercury in the cis tern, the heat
                    was 236° ; and at 30 inches above that surface, the heat was 252°. Here I was
                    obliged to stop, as I had no tube longer than 34 inches, and there was no white
                    glass made nearer than Newcastle-upon-Tyne. I therefore sealed the upper end of
                    the tube hermetically, whilst it was empty, and when it was cool immersed the
                    lower end in the mercury, which now could only rise in the tube by compressing
                    the air it contained. The tube was somewhat conical ; but, by ascertaining how
                    much it was so, and making allowances accordingly, the following points were
                    found, which, though not exact, were tolerably near for an <hi rend="italic"
                        >aperçu.</hi> At 29½ inches (with the sealed tube) the heat was 252°, at 75½
                    inches the heat was 264°, and at H0½ inches 292°. (That is, after making
                    allowances for the pillar of mercury supported, and the pillar which would be
                    necessary to compress the air into the space which it occupied,</p>
                <p>these were the results). From these elements I laid down a curve, in which the
                    abscissae represented the tempera tures, and the ordinates the pressures, and
                    thereby found the law by which they were governed, sufficiently near for my then
                    purpose. It was not till the years 1773—4, that I found leisure to make further
                    experiments on this sub ject, of which, though I do not consider the results as
                    accurate, I shall give an account here, as they were in point of date prior to
                    any others that I was then acquainted with.</p>
                <p>A tin pan, of about five inches in diameter and four inches deep, had a hole made
                    in its bottom, near one side, and in this hole was soldered a socket somewhat
                    conical, which nearly fitted a barometer tube with which the experiments were to
                    be made. This tube was about 36 inches long, and had a ball at one end about 1½
                    inches diameter, the contents of which were nearly equal to those of the stem of
                    the tube ; some paper was lapped round the tube near the ball, and it was forced
                    tight into the conical socket of the pan, so that the ball was within the
                    latter, at such a height that it might be immersed in water. The tube and pan
                    were then inverted, and the ball was filled with clean mercury, and the stem
                    with distilled water fresh boiled. The tube was re-inverted, so that the ball
                    and pan were uppermost ; the lower end of the tube being shut by the finger, the
                    water ascended into the ball, and the mercury occupied the tube. The lower end
                    of the Iatter being then placed in a cistern of mercury, and released from the
                    finger, the mercury and water descended, and the ball was Ieft partly empty :
                    being agitated in this position, and let stand some time, much air was
                    extricated from the water ; the tube was inclined as much as it could be, and
                    again inverted, the air let out, and its place supplied with boiling water. It
                    was again •placed with the ball uppermost, the end of the tube stop ped, the pan
                    filled with hot water which was made to boil by means of a lamp, the lower end
                    of the tube being<pb facs="chi.28490924-1526168109_Page_0662.jpf"
                        xml:id="eb07-20-s04-0581"/> placed in the cistern, and released from the
                    finger, the mercury descended into the cistern, but upon the water in the pan
                    being suffered to cool, partly rose again into the tube. Much air was thus
                    liberated, and more was got rid of by agitation, in the manner of the water
                    hammer, and by leaving it standing for some time erect, until at last I got it
                    so free from air, that when I raised it upright, it supported a column of
                    mercury 34 inches high ; and no vacuum was formed until it was violently shaken,
                    when it fell down suddenly and settled at 28.75 inches, but upon being inclined,
                    a speck of air always remained, though, when it was expanded by a pillar of
                    mercury 27 inches high, this speck was not larger than a pin’s head.</p>
                <p>In this state, when the tube was perpendicular, I found the mercury to stand at
                    28.75 inches, the column of water above it was about 6½ inches, = half an inch
                    of mercury. The whole then being 29.25 inches, when the stationary barometer
                    stood at 29.4, the difference, or pillar supported by the elasticity of the
                    steam = 0.15 inch. The water in the pan was then heated exceedingly slowly by a
                    lamp, and stirred continually by a feather to make the heat as equal as
                    possible. The results are shown in the following table :—∙</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Table No.</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">I.</hi></p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Heats.</cell>
                        <cell><p>Elastici</p><p>ties.</p></cell>
                        <cell>Heats.</cell>
                        <cell>Elasticities.</cell>
                        <cell>Heats.</cell>
                        <cell><p>Elastici</p><p>ties.</p></cell>
                        <cell>Heats.</cell>
                        <cell><p>Elastici</p><p>ties.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>55°</cell>
                        <cell><p>Inches.</p><p>0.15</p></cell>
                        <cell>135°</cell>
                        <cell><p>Inches.</p><p>4.53</p></cell>
                        <cell>167°</cell>
                        <cell><p>Inches.</p><p>11.07</p></cell>
                        <cell>187°</cell>
                        <cell><p>Indies.</p><p>17.51</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>74</cell>
                        <cell>0 65</cell>
                        <cell>142</cell>
                        <cell>5.46</cell>
                        <cell>172</cell>
                        <cell>11.95</cell>
                        <cell>189</cell>
                        <cell>18.45</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>81</cell>
                        <cell>0.80</cell>
                        <cell>148</cell>
                        <cell>6.40</cell>
                        <cell>175</cell>
                        <cell>12.88</cell>
                        <cell>191</cell>
                        <cell>19.38</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>95</cell>
                        <cell>1.30</cell>
                        <cell>153</cell>
                        <cell>7.325</cell>
                        <cell>177.5</cell>
                        <cell>13.81</cell>
                        <cell>193.5</cell>
                        <cell>20.34</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>104</cell>
                        <cell>1.75</cell>
                        <cell>157</cell>
                        <cell>8.25</cell>
                        <cell>180</cell>
                        <cell>14.73</cell>
                        <cell>196.5</cell>
                        <cell>21.26</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>118</p><p>128</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>2.68</p><p>3.60</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>161</p><p>164</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>9.18</p><p>10.10</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>182.5</p><p>185</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>15.66</p><p>16.58</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>At this time (1774) I tried a set of experiments in the same manner on a
                    saturated solution of common salt. When this solution was perfectly saturated by
                    boiling, and was put into the tube, it precipitated a quantity of salt which
                    disturbed the experiment. I was therefore obliged to take it out, and filter it,
                    during which process it attracted moisture from the air, and appeared, by its
                    boiling point, not to be perfectly saturated. Though it was more free from air
                    than water is, yet it parted from what it contained with great difficulty, and
                    would part with none when shaken as a water-hammer, though it opened in all
                    parts of the liquor. The result of this experiment is contained in the annexed
                    table :—</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Table No.</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">II.—</hi> Stationary Barometer, <hi rend="italic"
                    >29.5.</hi></p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Heats.</cell>
                        <cell><p>Elastici</p><p>ties.</p></cell>
                        <cell>Heats.</cell>
                        <cell><p>Elastici</p><p>ties.</p></cell>
                        <cell>Heats.</cell>
                        <cell><p>Elastici</p><p>ties.</p></cell>
                        <cell>Heats.</cell>
                        <cell><p>Elastici</p><p>ties.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>46°</cell>
                        <cell><p>Inches.</p><p>0.01</p></cell>
                        <cell>154°</cell>
                        <cell><p>Inches.</p><p>5.36</p></cell>
                        <cell>187°</cell>
                        <cell><p>Indies.</p><p>12.67</p></cell>
                        <cell>208°</cell>
                        <cell><p>Inches.</p><p>20.86</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>76</cell>
                        <cell>0.36</cell>
                        <cell>160</cell>
                        <cell>6.27</cell>
                        <cell>193.5</cell>
                        <cell>145</cell>
                        <cell>210</cell>
                        <cell>21.8</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>85</cell>
                        <cell>0.58</cell>
                        <cell>165</cell>
                        <cell>7∙2</cell>
                        <cell>195.5</cell>
                        <cell>15.34</cell>
                        <cell>212</cell>
                        <cell>2274</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>92</cell>
                        <cell>0.81</cell>
                        <cell>169</cell>
                        <cell>8.12</cell>
                        <cell>198.5</cell>
                        <cell>16.25</cell>
                        <cell>214</cell>
                        <cell>23.66</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>113</cell>
                        <cell>1.72</cell>
                        <cell>173</cell>
                        <cell>9.03</cell>
                        <cell>201.5</cell>
                        <cell>17.16</cell>
                        <cell>216</cell>
                        <cell>24.6</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>129</cell>
                        <cell>2.63</cell>
                        <cell>177</cell>
                        <cell>994</cell>
                        <cell>203.5</cell>
                        <cell>18.1</cell>
                        <cell>218</cell>
                        <cell>25 52</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>139</cell>
                        <cell>3 54</cell>
                        <cell>180</cell>
                        <cell>10.85</cell>
                        <cell>205.5</cell>
                        <cell>1903</cell>
                        <cell>220</cell>
                        <cell>26.5</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>147</cell>
                        <cell>4.45</cell>
                        <cell>183</cell>
                        <cell>11.76</cell>
                        <cell>207</cell>
                        <cell>19∙94</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>In the same manner I tried a set of experiments upon spirit of wine, the results
                    of which are contained in the annexed table :—</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Table No.</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">III.</hi></p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Heats.</cell>
                        <cell>Elasticities.</cell>
                        <cell>Heats.</cell>
                        <cell>Elasticities.</cell>
                        <cell>Heats.</cell>
                        <cell><p>Elastici</p><p>ties.</p></cell>
                        <cell>Heats.</cell>
                        <cell><p>Elastici</p><p>ties.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>34°</cell>
                        <cell><p>Inches,</p><p>0.22</p></cell>
                        <cell>120°</cell>
                        <cell><p>Inches.</p><p>7.12</p></cell>
                        <cell>146.5°</cell>
                        <cell><p>Inches.</p><p>15.03</p></cell>
                        <cell>164°</cell>
                        <cell><p>Inches.</p><p>22.59</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>40</cell>
                        <cell>0.929</cell>
                        <cell>124.5</cell>
                        <cell>8.46</cell>
                        <cell>148.5</cell>
                        <cell>15.974</cell>
                        <cell>166</cell>
                        <cell>23.53</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>67</cell>
                        <cell>1897</cell>
                        <cell>128</cell>
                        <cell>9.4</cell>
                        <cell>151</cell>
                        <cell>16.908</cell>
                        <cell>167</cell>
                        <cell>24.47</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>84</cell>
                        <cell>2.806</cell>
                        <cell>132</cell>
                        <cell>10.34</cell>
                        <cell>152.5</cell>
                        <cell>17.85</cell>
                        <cell>168</cell>
                        <cell>25.4</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>95</cell>
                        <cell>3.744</cell>
                        <cell>135</cell>
                        <cell>11.32</cell>
                        <cell>155</cell>
                        <cell>18.8</cell>
                        <cell>169</cell>
                        <cell>26.35</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>103</cell>
                        <cell>4.728</cell>
                        <cell>139</cell>
                        <cell>12.21</cell>
                        <cell>157</cell>
                        <cell>1975</cell>
                        <cell>171</cell>
                        <cell>27∙3</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>110</cell>
                        <cell>5.63</cell>
                        <cell>141.5</cell>
                        <cell>13.15</cell>
                        <cell>160</cell>
                        <cell>20.71</cell>
                        <cell cols="2">Stat. Bar. 29.4</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>114</cell>
                        <cell>6.58</cell>
                        <cell>144</cell>
                        <cell>14.1</cell>
                        <cell>162—5</cell>
                        <cell>21.65</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>Upon considering the probable cause of the difference, especially in the lower
                    heats, between my experiments and those of Mr Southern, related in his letter
                    annexed to this essay, I can only reconcilo them by supposing that the
                    stationary barometer, with which the comparison was made, had its scale placed
                    0.2 of an inch too low, and by adding that quantity to the elasticities in table
                    lst, they approach nearly to Mr Southern’s experiments.</p>
                <p>If that conjecture is adopted, the same addition will be necessary to tables 2d
                    and 3d, as they were compared with the same stationary barometer.</p>
                <p>To determine the heats at which water boils when pressed by columns of mercury
                    above 30 inches, a tube of 55 inches long was employed ; one end was put through
                    a hole in the cover of a digester, and made tight by being lapped round with
                    paper, and within the digester the end of the tube was immersed in a cistern of
                    mercury. A thermometer was fixed in another opening, so that the bulb was in the
                    inside of the digester, and the stem and scale without ; and the bulb was kept
                    half an inch from the cover of the digester by a wooden collar. The cover being
                    fixed on tight, and the digester half filled with water, it was heated by means
                    of a large lamp.</p>
                <p>The air in the upper part of the digester expanding by heat, the column of
                    mercury in the tube was considerably raised by that expansion before the water
                    boiled. The air was let out, and the water heated to boiling ; still, however,
                    some air remained, for the mercury stood at 213½°. That deduction being made,
                    the following table shows the heats and corresponding elasticitics.</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Heats.</cell>
                        <cell><p>Elasti</p><p>cities.</p></cell>
                        <cell>Heats.</cell>
                        <cell><p>Elasti</p><p>cities.</p></cell>
                        <cell>Heats.</cell>
                        <cell><p>Elasti</p><p>cities.</p></cell>
                        <cell>Heats.</cell>
                        <cell>Elasticities.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>213°</cell>
                        <cell>30</cell>
                        <cell>228°</cell>
                        <cell>39</cell>
                        <cell>240°</cell>
                        <cell>49</cell>
                        <cell>259°</cell>
                        <cell>66</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>215</cell>
                        <cell>31</cell>
                        <cell>229.5</cell>
                        <cell>40</cell>
                        <cell>242.5</cell>
                        <cell>50</cell>
                        <cell>261</cell>
                        <cell>68</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>217</cell>
                        <cell>32</cell>
                        <cell>231</cell>
                        <cell>41</cell>
                        <cell>244.5</cell>
                        <cell>52</cell>
                        <cell>262.5</cell>
                        <cell>70</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>219</cell>
                        <cell>33</cell>
                        <cell>232.5</cell>
                        <cell>42</cell>
                        <cell>247</cell>
                        <cell>54</cell>
                        <cell>264.5</cell>
                        <cell>72</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>220.5</cell>
                        <cell>34</cell>
                        <cell>234</cell>
                        <cell>43</cell>
                        <cell>248.5</cell>
                        <cell>56</cell>
                        <cell>266.5</cell>
                        <cell>74</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>222</cell>
                        <cell>35</cell>
                        <cell>235</cell>
                        <cell>44</cell>
                        <cell>250.5</cell>
                        <cell>58</cell>
                        <cell>268</cell>
                        <cell>76</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>223.5</cell>
                        <cell>36</cell>
                        <cell>236.5</cell>
                        <cell>45</cell>
                        <cell>252.5</cell>
                        <cell>60</cell>
                        <cell>269.5</cell>
                        <cell>78</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>225</cell>
                        <cell>37</cell>
                        <cell>237.5</cell>
                        <cell>46</cell>
                        <cell>255</cell>
                        <cell>62</cell>
                        <cell>271</cell>
                        <cell>80</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>2265</cell>
                        <cell>38</cell>
                        <cell>238.5</cell>
                        <cell>47</cell>
                        <cell>257</cell>
                        <cell>64</cell>
                        <cell>272.5</cell>
                        <cell>82</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>In making these experiments, the digester was heated very slowly, and the heat
                    was kept stationary as much as was possible at each observation, so that the
                    whole series occupied some hours. The degrees of elasticity were observed by my
                    friend Dr Irvine, whilst I observed those of the thermometer in all these
                    experiments.</p>
                <p>With the whole of the observations, I was, after all, by no means satisfied, as I
                    perceived there were irregularities in the results which my more urgent
                    avocations did not permit me to explore the causes of and to correct.</p>
                <p>The matter remained in that state till 1796, when I requested Mr Southern to try
                    them over again, in the<pb facs="chi.28490924-1526168109_Page_0663.jpf"
                        xml:id="eb07-20-s04-0582"/> performance of which he was assisted by Mr
                    William Creighton. The results of these observations are con</p>
                <p>tained in Mr Southern’s letter to me, which follows this memoir ; and, from the
                    very great care with which the experiments were made, the known accuracy of both
                    Mr Southern and Mr Creighton, and the agreement of the experiments with one
                    another, I have reason to believe them as nearly perfect as the subject admits
                    of. The method he adopted of trying the elasticities above the temperature of
                    boiling water by a piston, accurately fitted to a cylinder, is much to be
                    preferred to that adopted by Dr Robison, and is more manageable under great
                    elasticities than that of a long pillar of mercury..</p>
                <p>27. The reference which is here made applies to the following letter from Mr <hi
                        rend="italic">Southern</hi><note anchored="true" n="1" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial"><p>* In all these experime nts Mr Southern was assisted by
                            Mr William Creighton.</p></note>
                    <hi rend="italic">*</hi> to Mr Watt :—</p>
                <p>“ <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Sir</hi>,—The experiments of which the particular
                    circumstances are hereafter related, were made in 1803, with the view of
                    ascertaining chiefly the density of steam raised from water under different
                    pressures above that of the atmosphere, an apparatus having then been made for a
                    different purpose, which seemed pretty well adapted to this object.</p>
                <p>“ Besides the experiments now to be related, in which the temperature of steam
                    raised under <hi rend="italic">high</hi> pressures was observed in 1803, others
                    had been made some years before, in 1797 and 98, for that purpose only ; and, as
                    they were made with the greatest circumspection, both the manner of making them
                    and their results may be here described, as may also the results of other
                    experiments, made with equal care, to ascertain the temperature of steam raised
                    under <hi rend="italic">low</hi> pressures.</p>
                <p>“ The instrument used in the former was a Papin’s digester, similar to what you
                    had used ; the leading differences being in adapting a metallic tube to it to
                    con tain the thermometer, or rather as much of it as coatained mercury, in the
                    manner mentioned in the beginning of this letter, and instead of a valve, by the
                    load on which to measure the elasticity of the contained s team, a nicely bored
                    cylinder was applied, with a piston fitting it, so as to have very little
                    friction, and to the rod of this was applied a lever, constructed to work on
                    edges like those of a scale-beam, by which the resistance against the elastic
                    force of the steam could be accurately determined ; and at your suggestion, to
                    be assured that no inaccuracy had crept into tne calculation, by which this
                    resistance, through the medium of the lever, was ascertained, an actual column
                    of mercury of 30 inches high was substi tuted, and the correspondence was found
                    to be within <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 100</hi> of
                    an inch.</p>
                <p>“ The observations at each of the points of pressure noted were continued some
                    minutes, the temperature at each being alternately raised and lowered, so as to
                    make the pressure of the steam on the under side of the piston alternately too
                    much and too little for the weight with which it was loaded ; and thence a mean
                    temperature was adopted, the extremes of which were, as well as I now recollect,
                    not more than half a degree on each side of it. The load on the piston,
                    including its own weight, &amp;c., &amp;c., was calculated to be successively
                    just equal to 1, 2, 4, and 8 atmospheres of 29∙8 inches of mercury each, and the
                    temperature of the steam was varied as above till that of each point was
                    determined ; the results were thus :—</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Atmospheres.</cell>
                        <cell>Pressure in inches of Mercury.</cell>
                        <cell>Temperatures.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>29.8</cell>
                        <cell>212°</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>09.6</cell>
                        <cell>250 3</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>119.2</cell>
                        <cell>293.4</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>8</cell>
                        <cell>238.4</cell>
                        <cell>343.6</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>“ The experiments for ascertaining the temperature of steam below the atmospheric
                    pressure were made with an apparatus essentially similar to that which you
                    originally used, and with scrupulous care and attention : and I met with the
                    same incidents as you had done ; such as, the production of a bubble of air
                    whenever, after any experi ment, the tube was inclined to refill the ball ; and
                    also the extraordinary suspension of a column of mercury of 35 inches vertical
                    height, and of 7 inches of water above that, although the counterpoise was only
                    that of the atmosphere, then under 30 inches. I found also that the tube
                    required a considerable degree of tabouring or shaking to make the column
                    subside and leave a space in the ball. This phenomenon was not produced till
                    after much pains taken in inverting and re-inverting the tube again and again,
                    nor till it had been suffered, after these operations, to stand for three or
                    four days undistm∙bed in the exhausting position, and then discharging the air
                    that had been accumulating in the interval.</p>
                <p>“ The results to be found in the table below, were deduced from the observations
                    as you had done—viz., by adding to the height of the column of mercury in the
                    tube (ascertained by a gauge floating on the surface of the mercury in the
                    basin), that of the water above it, or rather of an equivalent column of
                    mercury, and subtracting their sum from the height of the common barometer at
                    the time. All these results were taken from observations made after the
                    apparatus had been so perfectly exhausted of air as to produce the phenomenon
                    just mentioned.</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="5"/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Temperature.</cell>
                        <cell cols="3"/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>1st Set.</cell>
                        <cell>2d Set.</cell>
                        <cell>3d Set.</cell>
                        <cell>Mean.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Inches.</cell>
                        <cell>Inches.</cell>
                        <cell>Inches.</cell>
                        <cell>Inches.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>52°</cell>
                        <cell>0.</cell>
                        <cell>0.42</cell>
                        <cell>0 40</cell>
                        <cell>0.41</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>62</cell>
                        <cell>0.53</cell>
                        <cell>0.52</cell>
                        <cell>0.52</cell>
                        <cell>0.52</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>72</cell>
                        <cell>0.73</cell>
                        <cell>0.73</cell>
                        <cell>0.73</cell>
                        <cell>0.73</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>82</cell>
                        <cell>1.03</cell>
                        <cell>1.02</cell>
                        <cell>1.02</cell>
                        <cell>1.02</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>92</cell>
                        <cell>1.42</cell>
                        <cell>1.41</cell>
                        <cell>1.42</cell>
                        <cell>1.42</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>102</cell>
                        <cell>1∙98</cell>
                        <cell>1.92</cell>
                        <cell>1.95</cell>
                        <cell>1.95</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>112</cell>
                        <cell>2.67</cell>
                        <cell>2.63</cell>
                        <cell>2.66</cell>
                        <cell>2.65</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>122</cell>
                        <cell>3.58</cell>
                        <cell>3.54</cell>
                        <cell>3 58</cell>
                        <cell>3.57</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>132</cell>
                        <cell>4.68</cell>
                        <cell>4.65</cell>
                        <cell>4.72</cell>
                        <cell>4 68</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>142</cell>
                        <cell>6.05</cell>
                        <cell>6.00</cell>
                        <cell>6.14</cell>
                        <cell>6.06</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>152</cell>
                        <cell>7∙86</cell>
                        <cell>7.80</cell>
                        <cell>7.89</cell>
                        <cell>7∙85</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>162</cell>
                        <cell>9∙98</cell>
                        <cell>996</cell>
                        <cell>10.04</cell>
                        <cell>9∙99</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>172</cell>
                        <cell>12.54</cell>
                        <cell>12 72</cell>
                        <cell>12.67</cell>
                        <cell>12.64</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>182</cell>
                        <cell>16.01</cell>
                        <cell>15.84</cell>
                        <cell>15.88</cell>
                        <cell>15.91</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>" The following formula will be found to give the elasticity belonging to a given
                    temperature, and <hi rend="italic">vice versa,</hi> with a sufficient degree of
                    accuracy for most purposes, within the range of the experiments, at least, from
                    which they have been formed.</p>
                <p>Let Z = temperature, <hi rend="italic">e —</hi> elasticity, in inches of mercury
                    ;</p>
                <p>T = t+52, and E=e— <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> / <hi rend="subscript">
                    10</hi>, <hi rend="italic">m=</hi> 94250,000000 ;</p>
                <p>Then</p>
                <p>T <hi rend="superscript"> 5.11</hi></p>
                <p>— =E</p>
                <p>»n</p>
                <p>β.n</p>
                <p>V Em ≈ T</p>
                <p>“ But as the calculation is most easily performed by logarithms, let L signify
                    the logarithm of the quantity to which it is prefixed :</p>
                <p>Then 5.14 LT—1097427=LE LE+10.97427</p>
                <p>5.14 <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> '</p>
                <p>“ The following table shows the observed elasticities, those derived from
                    calculation by the formula, and the differences of the two, which appear to me
                    to be as small as can be expected, taking a general view.</p>
                <pb facs="chi.28490924-1526168109_Page_0664.jpf" xml:id="eb07-20-s04-0583"/>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Temperature.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Observed</p><p>Elasticities.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Calculated</p><p>Elasticities.</p></cell>
                        <cell>Differences.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Inches.</cell>
                        <cell>Inches.</cell>
                        <cell>Inches.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>32o</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>0.18</cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>42</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>0.25</cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>52</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>0.35</cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>62</cell>
                        <cell>0.52</cell>
                        <cell>050</cell>
                        <cell>—0.02</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>72</cell>
                        <cell>0.73</cell>
                        <cell>0.71</cell>
                        <cell>—0.02</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>82</cell>
                        <cell>1.02</cell>
                        <cell>1.01</cell>
                        <cell>—0.01</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>92</cell>
                        <cell>1.42</cell>
                        <cell>1.42</cell>
                        <cell>0.00</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>102</cell>
                        <cell>1.95</cell>
                        <cell>1.96</cell>
                        <cell>+ 001</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>112</cell>
                        <cell>2.65</cell>
                        <cell>2 67</cell>
                        <cell>+ 0.02</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>122</cell>
                        <cell>3.57</cell>
                        <cell>358</cell>
                        <cell>+ 0.01</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>132</cell>
                        <cell>4.68</cell>
                        <cell>4.74</cell>
                        <cell>+ 0.06</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>142</cell>
                        <cell>6.06</cell>
                        <cell>6.20</cell>
                        <cell>+ 0.14</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>152</cell>
                        <cell>7∙85</cell>
                        <cell>7.99</cell>
                        <cell>+ 0.14</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>162</cell>
                        <cell>9∙99</cell>
                        <cell>10.19</cell>
                        <cell>+ 0.20</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>172</cell>
                        <cell>12.64</cell>
                        <cell>12.86</cell>
                        <cell>+ 0.22</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>182</cell>
                        <cell>15.91</cell>
                        <cell>1608</cell>
                        <cell>+ 0.17</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>192</cell>
                        <cell>• ∙ ∙</cell>
                        <cell>19∙91</cell>
                        <cell>. ∙ .</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>202</cell>
                        <cell>• . .</cell>
                        <cell>24.45</cell>
                        <cell>. . .</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>212</cell>
                        <cell>29.80</cell>
                        <cell>29.80</cell>
                        <cell>0.00</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>250.3</cell>
                        <cell>59.60</cell>
                        <cell>59.69</cell>
                        <cell>+ 0.09</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>293.4</cell>
                        <cell>119.20</cell>
                        <cell>118.32</cell>
                        <cell>—0.88</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>343.6</cell>
                        <cell>238.40</cell>
                        <cell>2.3760</cell>
                        <cell>—0.80</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>Temperature.</p>
                <p>Observed</p>
                <p>Elasticities.</p>
                <p>Calculated</p>
                <p>Elasticities.</p>
                <p>“ I believe it is now generally considered that the temperature 212° is that of
                    water boiling when the barometer is at 30 inches instead of 29∙8 ; and if, in
                    the above algebraic expressions, the following alterations be made, the results
                    from the formulæ will correspond with the adjustment of that point, and fully as
                    well with the experiments generally.</p>
                <p>“ Let T=∕ + 51.3 ; the index of the power and of the root be 5.13, instead of
                    5.14 ; and <hi rend="italic">m=</hi> 87344,000000. So the two last equations
                    will be : 5.13 LT—10.94123=LE;</p>
                <p>and <hi rend="superscript"> LE+10.94123</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 5.13</hi> =
                    LT.</p>
                <p>“ The table will stand as follows, supposing the thermo meter had been graduated
                    for 212° to correspond with 30 inches of the barometer :—</p>
                <table cols="9">
                    <row>
                        <cell>Temp.</cell>
                        <cell>Observd. Elasticities.</cell>
                        <cell>Calcul. Elasticities.</cell>
                        <cell>Differences.</cell>
                        <cell rows="13"/>
                        <cell>Temp.</cell>
                        <cell>Observd. Elasticities.</cell>
                        <cell>Calcul. Elasticities.</cell>
                        <cell>Differences.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Inches.</cell>
                        <cell>Inches.</cell>
                        <cell>Inches.</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Inches.</cell>
                        <cell>Inches.</cell>
                        <cell>Inches.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>32</cell>
                        <cell><note anchored="true" n="2" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>* These
                                    are inserted from numerous experiments made by Mr W.
                                    Creighton.</p></note>*0.16</cell>
                        <cell>0.18</cell>
                        <cell>+ 0.02</cell>
                        <cell>142°</cell>
                        <cell>6.10</cell>
                        <cell>6.22</cell>
                        <cell>+ 0.12</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>42</cell>
                        <cell><note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>* These are
                                    inserted from numerous experiments made by Mr W.
                                Creighton.</p></note>*0.23</cell>
                        <cell>0.25</cell>
                        <cell>+0.02</cell>
                        <cell>152</cell>
                        <cell>7.90</cell>
                        <cell>8 03</cell>
                        <cell>+ 0.13</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>52</cell>
                        <cell><note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>* These are
                                    inserted from numerous experiments made by Mr W.
                                Creighton.</p></note>*035</cell>
                        <cell>0.35</cell>
                        <cell>0.00</cell>
                        <cell>162</cell>
                        <cell>10 05</cell>
                        <cell>10.25</cell>
                        <cell>+ 0.20</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>62</cell>
                        <cell>052</cell>
                        <cell>0.50</cell>
                        <cell>—0.02</cell>
                        <cell>172</cell>
                        <cell>12.72</cell>
                        <cell>1294</cell>
                        <cell>+ 0.22</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>72</cell>
                        <cell>0.73</cell>
                        <cell>0.71</cell>
                        <cell>—0 01</cell>
                        <cell>182</cell>
                        <cell>16.01</cell>
                        <cell>16.17</cell>
                        <cell>+ 0.16</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>82</cell>
                        <cell>1.02</cell>
                        <cell>1.01</cell>
                        <cell>—0 01</cell>
                        <cell>192</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>20 04</cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>92</cell>
                        <cell>1.42</cell>
                        <cell>1.42</cell>
                        <cell>0.00</cell>
                        <cell>202</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>24.61</cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>102</cell>
                        <cell>1.96</cell>
                        <cell>1.97</cell>
                        <cell>+ 0.01</cell>
                        <cell>212</cell>
                        <cell>30.00</cell>
                        <cell>30.00</cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>112</cell>
                        <cell>2.66</cell>
                        <cell>2 68</cell>
                        <cell>+ 0 02</cell>
                        <cell>250.3</cell>
                        <cell>60.00</cell>
                        <cell>60.11</cell>
                        <cell>+ 0.11</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>122</cell>
                        <cell>3.58</cell>
                        <cell>3.60</cell>
                        <cell>+ 0.02</cell>
                        <cell>293.4</cell>
                        <cell>120.00</cell>
                        <cell>119.17</cell>
                        <cell>—0.3</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>132</cell>
                        <cell>4.71 1</cell>
                        <cell>4.76</cell>
                        <cell>+ 0.05</cell>
                        <cell>343.6</cell>
                        <cell>240.00</cell>
                        <cell>239.28</cell>
                        <cell>—02</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>“ I remain, with the greatest esteem and respect, Dear</p>
                <p>Sir, Your very obedient Servant,</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">“ Oakhill, 20th March,</hi> 1811." “<hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >John</hi> SOUTHERN.</p>
                <p>“ To <hi rend="smallcaps">James Watt,</hi> Esq., Heathfield.”</p>
                <p>28. In the <hi rend="italic">Memoirs of the Royal Academy of Berlin</hi></p>
                <p>for 1782, there is an account of some experiments made by M. Achard on the
                    elastic force of steam, from the temperature 32° to 212°. They agree extremely
                    well with those mentioned here, rarely differing more than two or three-tenths
                    of an inch. He also examined the elasticity of the vapour produced from alcohol,
                    and when the elasticity was equal to that of the vapour of water, he found that
                    the temperature was about 35° lower. Thus, when the elasticity of both was
                    measured by 28.1 inches</p>
                <p>of mercury, the temperature of the watery vapour was 209°, and that of the
                    spirituous vapour was 173°. When the elasticity was 18.5, the temperature of the
                    water was 189.5 <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi>, and that of the alcohol 154.6°.
                    When the elasticity was 11.05, the water was 168°, and the alcohol 134.4°
                    Observing the difference between the temperature of equaIly elastic vapours of
                    water and alcohol not to be con stant, but gradually to diminish, in M. Achard’s
                    experi ments, along with the elasticity, it became interesting to discover
                    whether, and at what temperature, this difference would vanish altogether.
                    Experiments were accordingly made by the writer of this article, similar to
                    those made with water. They were not made with the same scrunulous care, nor
                    repeated as they deserved, but they furnished rather an unexpected result. The
                    following table will give the reader a distinct notion of them.</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Temperature.</cell>
                        <cell>Temperature.</cell>
                        <cell>Temperature.</cell>
                        <cell>Elasticity.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>32°</cell>
                        <cell>0.0</cell>
                        <cell>140</cell>
                        <cell>12.2</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>40</cell>
                        <cell>0.1</cell>
                        <cell>160</cell>
                        <cell>21.3</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>60</cell>
                        <cell>0.8</cell>
                        <cell>180</cell>
                        <cell>34.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>80</cell>
                        <cell>1.8</cell>
                        <cell>200</cell>
                        <cell>524</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>100</cell>
                        <cell>3.9</cell>
                        <cell>220</cell>
                        <cell>78.5</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>120</cell>
                        <cell>69</cell>
                        <cell>240</cell>
                        <cell>115.</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>29. Dr Dalton appears to have been the first to escape from the natural enough
                    error of assuming that the vapour of water at 32° would be = 0. His apparatus is
                    the most simple and refined of any that have been employed for temperatures
                    below 212°, and his experiments are those which, to the present day, have the
                    greatest authority. Dr Dalton’s first experiments were published in 1793, in his
                        <hi rend="italic">Meteorological Essays ;</hi> afterwards, when more
                    extended, in the <hi rend="italic">Manchester Memoirs,</hi> 1802 ; then in the
                    first volume of his <hi rend="italic">System of Chemistry,</hi> 1808; and
                    finally in the second volume of the same work, 1827. The following is the
                    account given by himself, of his early experiments, in the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Manchester Memoirs.</hi></p>
                <p>“ My method is this : I take a barometer tube AB, (Fig. 13,) perfectly dry, and
                    fill it with mercury just boiled, marking the place (30) where it is stationary
                    ; then, having graduated the tube, I pour a little water, or any other liquid,
                    the subject of experiment, into it, so as to moisten the whole inside : after
                    this I again pour in mercury, and carefully inverting the tube, exclude all air
                    ; the barometer, by standing some time, exhibits a portion of water of <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 1</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 8</hi> or <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 1</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 10</hi> th of an inch, W,
                    on the top of the mercurial column ; because, being lighter, it ascends by the
                    side of the tube, which may now be inclined, and the mercury will rise to the
                    top, manifesting a perfect vacuum from air. I next take a cylindrical glass tube
                    CD,</p>
                <p>open at both ends, of two inches diameter and fourteen inches in length,</p>
                <p>to each end of which a cork is adapted,</p>
                <p>perforated in the middle, so as to admit a barometer tube to be put through,</p>
                <p>and to be held fast by them ; the upper cork, C, is fixed two or three inches
                    below the top of the tube, and is one-half cut away, so as to admit water,
                    &amp;c., to pass by, its service being merely to keep the tube steady. Things
                    being thus circumstanced ; water of any temperature may be poured into the wide
                    tube, and thus made to surround the upper part or vacuum of the barometer, and
                    the effect of temperature in the production of vapour within can be observed
                    from the depression of the mercurial column at the top. In this way I have had
                    water as high as 155° surrounding the vacuum ; but as the higher temperatures
                    might endanger a glass apparatus, instead of it I used the following :—<pb
                        facs="chi.28490924-1526168109_Page_0665.jpf" xml:id="eb07-20-s04-0584"/>
                    Having procured a tin tube CD, four inches in diameter, and two feet long with a
                    circular plate soldered to one end, having a round hole in the centre, like the
                    tube of a reflecting telescope, I got another smaller tube of the same length
                    soldered into the larger, so as to be in the axis or centre of it ; the small
                    tube was open at both ends, and on this construction water could be poured into
                    the large vessel to fill it, while the central tube was exposed to its
                    temperature. Into this central tube I could insert the upper half of a syphon
                    barometer, and fix it by a cork, the top of the narrow tube, also, being
                    corked—thus the effect of any temperature under 212° could be ascertained, the
                    depression of the mercurial column being known by the ascent in the exterior leg
                    of the syphon. The force of vapour from water between 80° and 212°, may also be
                    determined by means of an air-pump, and the result exactly agrees with those
                    determined as above.”</p>
                <p>“ After repeated experiments by all those methods, and a careful comparison of
                    the results, I was enabled to digest the following :—</p>
                <p>Table of the Force of Steam from Water in the temperatures from <hi rend="italic"
                        >32°</hi> to <hi rend="italic">212° (1802.)</hi></p>
                <table cols="8">
                    <row>
                        <cell>Temperature.</cell>
                        <cell>Force of Vapour in inches of Mercury.</cell>
                        <cell>Temperature.</cell>
                        <cell>Force of Vapour in inches of Mercury.</cell>
                        <cell>Temperature.</cell>
                        <cell>Force of Vapour in inches of Mercury.</cell>
                        <cell>Temperature.</cell>
                        <cell>Force of Vapour in inches of Mercury.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>32°</cell>
                        <cell>.200</cell>
                        <cell>78°</cell>
                        <cell>.940</cell>
                        <cell>123°</cell>
                        <cell>3.59</cell>
                        <cell>168°</cell>
                        <cell>11.54</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>33</cell>
                        <cell>.207</cell>
                        <cell>79</cell>
                        <cell>.971</cell>
                        <cell>124</cell>
                        <cell>3.69</cell>
                        <cell>169</cell>
                        <cell>11.83</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>34</cell>
                        <cell>.214</cell>
                        <cell>80</cell>
                        <cell>1.00</cell>
                        <cell>125</cell>
                        <cell>3.79</cell>
                        <cell>170</cell>
                        <cell>12.13</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>35</cell>
                        <cell>.221</cell>
                        <cell>81</cell>
                        <cell>1.04</cell>
                        <cell>126</cell>
                        <cell>3.89</cell>
                        <cell>171</cell>
                        <cell>12.43</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>36</cell>
                        <cell>.229</cell>
                        <cell>82</cell>
                        <cell>1.07</cell>
                        <cell>127</cell>
                        <cell>4.00</cell>
                        <cell>172</cell>
                        <cell>12.73</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>37</cell>
                        <cell>.237</cell>
                        <cell>83</cell>
                        <cell>1.10</cell>
                        <cell>128</cell>
                        <cell>4.11</cell>
                        <cell>173</cell>
                        <cell>13.02</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>38</cell>
                        <cell>.245</cell>
                        <cell>84</cell>
                        <cell>1.14</cell>
                        <cell>129</cell>
                        <cell>4.22</cell>
                        <cell>174</cell>
                        <cell>13.32</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>30</cell>
                        <cell>.254</cell>
                        <cell>85</cell>
                        <cell>1.17</cell>
                        <cell>130</cell>
                        <cell>4.34</cell>
                        <cell>175</cell>
                        <cell>13.62</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>40</cell>
                        <cell>.263</cell>
                        <cell>86</cell>
                        <cell>1.21</cell>
                        <cell>131</cell>
                        <cell>4.47</cell>
                        <cell>176</cell>
                        <cell>13.92</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>41</cell>
                        <cell>.273</cell>
                        <cell>87</cell>
                        <cell>1.24</cell>
                        <cell>132</cell>
                        <cell>4.60</cell>
                        <cell>177</cell>
                        <cell>14.22</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>42</cell>
                        <cell>.283</cell>
                        <cell>88</cell>
                        <cell>1.28</cell>
                        <cell>133</cell>
                        <cell>4.73</cell>
                        <cell>178</cell>
                        <cell>14.52</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>43</cell>
                        <cell>.294</cell>
                        <cell>89</cell>
                        <cell>1.32</cell>
                        <cell>134</cell>
                        <cell>4.86</cell>
                        <cell>179</cell>
                        <cell>14.83</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>44</cell>
                        <cell>.305</cell>
                        <cell>90</cell>
                        <cell>1.36</cell>
                        <cell>1.35</cell>
                        <cell>5.00</cell>
                        <cell>180</cell>
                        <cell>15.15</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>45</cell>
                        <cell>.316</cell>
                        <cell>91</cell>
                        <cell>1.40</cell>
                        <cell>136</cell>
                        <cell>5.14</cell>
                        <cell>181</cell>
                        <cell>15.50</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>46</cell>
                        <cell>.328</cell>
                        <cell>92</cell>
                        <cell>1.44</cell>
                        <cell>137</cell>
                        <cell>5.29</cell>
                        <cell>182</cell>
                        <cell>15.86</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>47</cell>
                        <cell>.339</cell>
                        <cell>93</cell>
                        <cell>1.48</cell>
                        <cell>138</cell>
                        <cell>5.44</cell>
                        <cell>183</cell>
                        <cell>16.23</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>48</cell>
                        <cell>.351</cell>
                        <cell>94</cell>
                        <cell>1.53</cell>
                        <cell>139</cell>
                        <cell>5.59</cell>
                        <cell>184</cell>
                        <cell>16.61</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>49</cell>
                        <cell>.363</cell>
                        <cell>95</cell>
                        <cell>1.58</cell>
                        <cell>140</cell>
                        <cell>5.74</cell>
                        <cell>186</cell>
                        <cell>17.00</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>50</cell>
                        <cell>.375</cell>
                        <cell>96</cell>
                        <cell>1.63</cell>
                        <cell>141</cell>
                        <cell>5.90</cell>
                        <cell>186</cell>
                        <cell>17.40</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>51</cell>
                        <cell>.388</cell>
                        <cell>97</cell>
                        <cell>1.68</cell>
                        <cell>142</cell>
                        <cell>6.05</cell>
                        <cell>187</cell>
                        <cell>17.80</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>62</cell>
                        <cell>.401</cell>
                        <cell>98</cell>
                        <cell>1.74</cell>
                        <cell>143</cell>
                        <cell>6.21</cell>
                        <cell>188</cell>
                        <cell>18.20</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>53</cell>
                        <cell>.415</cell>
                        <cell>99</cell>
                        <cell>1.80</cell>
                        <cell>144</cell>
                        <cell>6.37</cell>
                        <cell>189</cell>
                        <cell>18.60</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>54</cell>
                        <cell>.429</cell>
                        <cell>100</cell>
                        <cell>1.86</cell>
                        <cell>145</cell>
                        <cell>6.53</cell>
                        <cell>100</cell>
                        <cell>19.00</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>55</cell>
                        <cell>.443</cell>
                        <cell>101</cell>
                        <cell>1.92</cell>
                        <cell>146</cell>
                        <cell>6.70</cell>
                        <cell>191</cell>
                        <cell>19.42</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>50</cell>
                        <cell>.458</cell>
                        <cell>102</cell>
                        <cell>1.98</cell>
                        <cell>147</cell>
                        <cell>6.87</cell>
                        <cell>192</cell>
                        <cell>19.80</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>57</cell>
                        <cell>.474</cell>
                        <cell>103</cell>
                        <cell>2.04</cell>
                        <cell>148</cell>
                        <cell>7.05</cell>
                        <cell>193</cell>
                        <cell>20.32</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>68</cell>
                        <cell>.490</cell>
                        <cell>104</cell>
                        <cell>2.11</cell>
                        <cell>149</cell>
                        <cell>7.23</cell>
                        <cell>194</cell>
                        <cell>20.77</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>59</cell>
                        <cell>.507</cell>
                        <cell>105</cell>
                        <cell>2.18</cell>
                        <cell>150</cell>
                        <cell>7.42</cell>
                        <cell>195</cell>
                        <cell>21.22</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>60</cell>
                        <cell>.524</cell>
                        <cell>106</cell>
                        <cell>2.25</cell>
                        <cell>151</cell>
                        <cell>7.01</cell>
                        <cell>196</cell>
                        <cell>21.68</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>61</cell>
                        <cell>.542</cell>
                        <cell>107</cell>
                        <cell>2.32</cell>
                        <cell>152</cell>
                        <cell>7.81</cell>
                        <cell>197</cell>
                        <cell>22.13</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>62</cell>
                        <cell>.560</cell>
                        <cell>108</cell>
                        <cell>2.39</cell>
                        <cell>153</cell>
                        <cell>8.01</cell>
                        <cell>198</cell>
                        <cell>22.09</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>63</cell>
                        <cell>.578</cell>
                        <cell>109</cell>
                        <cell>2.46</cell>
                        <cell>154</cell>
                        <cell>8.20</cell>
                        <cell>199</cell>
                        <cell>23.16</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>54</cell>
                        <cell>.597</cell>
                        <cell>110</cell>
                        <cell>2.53</cell>
                        <cell>155</cell>
                        <cell>8.40</cell>
                        <cell>200</cell>
                        <cell>23.64</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>S5</cell>
                        <cell>.616</cell>
                        <cell>111</cell>
                        <cell>2.00</cell>
                        <cell>150</cell>
                        <cell>8.60</cell>
                        <cell><p>201</p><p>202</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>24.12</p><p>24.51</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>66</cell>
                        <cell>.635</cell>
                        <cell>112</cell>
                        <cell>2.68</cell>
                        <cell>157</cell>
                        <cell>8.81</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>37</cell>
                        <cell>.655</cell>
                        <cell>113</cell>
                        <cell>2.76</cell>
                        <cell>158</cell>
                        <cell>9.02</cell>
                        <cell>203</cell>
                        <cell>25.10</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>88</cell>
                        <cell>.676</cell>
                        <cell>114</cell>
                        <cell>2.84</cell>
                        <cell>159</cell>
                        <cell>9.24</cell>
                        <cell>204</cell>
                        <cell>2δ.61</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>69</cell>
                        <cell>.698</cell>
                        <cell>115</cell>
                        <cell>2.92</cell>
                        <cell>160</cell>
                        <cell>9.46</cell>
                        <cell>205</cell>
                        <cell>26.13</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>70</cell>
                        <cell>.721</cell>
                        <cell>116</cell>
                        <cell>3.00</cell>
                        <cell>161</cell>
                        <cell>9.68</cell>
                        <cell>206</cell>
                        <cell>26.66</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>71</cell>
                        <cell>.745</cell>
                        <cell>117</cell>
                        <cell>3.08</cell>
                        <cell>162</cell>
                        <cell>9.91</cell>
                        <cell>207</cell>
                        <cell>27.20</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>72</cell>
                        <cell>.770</cell>
                        <cell>118</cell>
                        <cell>3.10</cell>
                        <cell>163</cell>
                        <cell>10.15</cell>
                        <cell>208</cell>
                        <cell>27.74</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>73</cell>
                        <cell>.796</cell>
                        <cell>119</cell>
                        <cell>3.25</cell>
                        <cell>164</cell>
                        <cell>10.41</cell>
                        <cell>209</cell>
                        <cell>28.29</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>74</cell>
                        <cell>.823</cell>
                        <cell>120</cell>
                        <cell>3.33</cell>
                        <cell>165</cell>
                        <cell>10.68</cell>
                        <cell>210</cell>
                        <cell>28.84</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>75</cell>
                        <cell>.851</cell>
                        <cell>121</cell>
                        <cell>3.42</cell>
                        <cell>166</cell>
                        <cell>10.96</cell>
                        <cell>211</cell>
                        <cell>29.41</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>76</cell>
                        <cell>.880</cell>
                        <cell>122</cell>
                        <cell>3.50</cell>
                        <cell>167</cell>
                        <cell>11.25</cell>
                        <cell>212</cell>
                        <cell>30.00</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>77</cell>
                        <cell>.910</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>Dr Dalton afterwards resumed the experimental ex amination of this subject, and
                    was induced to modify these numbers slightly, as will be seen from our final
                    table.</p>
                <p>30. Passing over the experiments of Schmidt, Goldner, and others, as presenting
                    no important differences from some of these we have already noticed, we come to
                    those of Dr Ure, published in the <hi rend="italic">Philosophical
                        Transactions</hi> of 1818, and made at Glasgow during 1817. The ad joining
                    figures represent his apparatus.</p>
                <p>Fig. 15. represents the construction used for temperatures under and a little
                    above the boiling point. Figs. 16. and 17. are those used for higher
                    temperatures, the last being the more convenient of the two ; each was suspended
                    from a lofty window ceiling, and placed in a truly vertical position, by means
                    of a plumb line. Dr Ure gives the following account of his mode of
                    experimenting. “ One simple principle pervades the whole train of experiments
                    —which is, that the progressive increase of elastic force developed by heat from
                    the liquid, incumbent on the mercury at L <hi rend="italic">l',</hi> is measured
                    by the length of column which must be <hi rend="italic">added</hi> over L, the
                    primitive level below, in order to restore the quick silver to its primitive
                    level above, at <hi rend="italic">l.</hi></p>
                <p>These two stations or points of departure are nicely defined by a ring of fine
                    platina wire, twisted firmly round the tube.</p>
                <p>“ At the commencement of the experi ment, after the liquid, well freed from air,
                    has been let up, the quicksilver is made a tangent to the edge of the upper
                    ring, by cautiously pouring mercury, in a slender stream, into the open leg of
                    the syphon B, the level ring below is then carefully adjusted.</p>
                <p>“ From the mode of conducting my experiments, there remained always a quantity of
                    liquid m contact with the vapour, a circumstance essential to accuracy in this
                    research.</p>
                <p>“ Suppose the temperature of the water or the oil in A to be 32° Fahrenheit, as
                    denoted by a delicate thermo meter, or by the liquefaction of ice ; communicate
                    heat to the cylinder A, by means of two argand flames, playing gently on its
                    shoulder at each side. When the thermo meter indicates 42°, modify the flames,
                    or remove them so as to maintain a uniform temperature for a few minutes. A film
                    or line of light will now be perceived between the mercury and the ring at <hi
                        rend="italic">l,</hi> as is seen under the vernier of a mountain barometer,
                    when it is raised a few feet off the ground ; were the tube at <hi rend="italic"
                        >l</hi> and L, of equal area, or were the relation of the areas experiment
                    ally determined, then the rise of the quicksilver above L would be one-half, or
                    a known submultiple of the total depression, equivalent to the additional
                    elasticity of the vapour at 42° above that at 32°. Since the depressions,
                    however, for 30 or 40° in this part of the scale are exceedingly small, one-half
                    of the quantity can scarcely be ascertained with suitable precision, even after
                    taking the above precautions ; and besides, the other sources of error, or at
                    least embarrassment, from the inequalities of the tube, and from the lengthening
                    space occupied by the vapour, as the temperature ascends, render this method of
                    reduction very ineligible.</p>
                <p>“ By the other plan we avoid all these evils ; for what ever additional
                    elasticity be communicated to the vapour above <hi rend="italic">l</hi>, it will
                    be faithfully represented and measured by the mercurial column, which we must
                    add over L, in order to overcome it and restore the quicksilver under <hi
                        rend="italic">I,</hi> to its zero or initial level, when the platina ring
                    becomes once more a tangent to the mercury. At E, a piece of<pb
                        facs="chi.28490924-1526168109_Page_0666.jpf" xml:id="eb07-20-s04-0585"/>
                    cork is fixed between the parallel legs of the syphon to sustain it, and to
                    serve as a point by which the whole is steadily suspended. For temperatures
                    above the boiling point, the part of the syphon under E is evidently
                    superfluous, merely containing in its two legs a useless weight of equipoised
                    mercury. Accordingly, for high heats, the apparatus, Figs. 16 or 17, is
                    employed, and the same method of procedure is adopted ; the aperture at O, Fig.
                    17, admits the bulb of the thermometer, which rests as usual on <hi
                        rend="italic">l'.</hi> The recurved part of the tube isfilled with mercury,
                    and then a little liquid is passed through it to the sealed end. Heat is now
                    applied by an argand flame to the bottom of C, which is filled with oil or
                    water, and the temperature is kept steadily at 212° for some minutes. Then a few
                    drops of quicksilver may be required to be added to D', till L and <hi
                        rend="italic">l'</hi> be in the same horizontal plane. The further conduct
                    of the experiment differs in no respect from what has been already
                    described the liquid in C is progressively heated, and at each stage mercury is
                    progressively added over L to restore the initial level or volume at <hi
                        rend="italic">l',</hi> by equipoising the progressive elas ticity. The
                    column above L being measured, represents the succession of elastic forces: when
                    this column is wished to extend very high, the vertical tube requires to be
                    placed for support in the groove of a long wooden prism.</p>
                <p>“ The height of the column in some of my experiments being nearly twelve feet, it
                    became necessary to employ a ladder to reach its top. I found it to be
                    convenient, in this case, after observing that the column of vapour had attained
                    its primitive magnitude, to note down the temperature with the altitude of the
                    column, then immediately to pour in a measured quantity of mercury nearly equal
                    to three vertical inches, and to wait till the slow progress of the heating
                    again brought the vapour in equilibrio with this new pressure, which at first
                    had pushed the mercury within the platina ring at <hi rend="italic">l.</hi> When
                    the lower surface of the mercury was again a tangent to this ring, the
                    temperature and altitude were both instantly observed.</p>
                <p>“ This mode of conducting the process will account for the experimental
                    temperatures being very often odd and fractional numbers. I present them to the
                    public, as they were recorded on the instant in that particular repetition of
                    the experiment which I consider most entitled to confidence. To trim and fashion
                    the results into an orderly looking series, would have been an easy task ; but,
                    in my opinion, this is a species of deception very injurious to the cause of
                    science, and a deviation from the rigid truth of observation, which ought never
                    to be made for any hypo thesis : we shall afterwards have ample opportunities of
                    exposing the fallacy of such premature geometrical refinements.</p>
                <p>The thermometers were constructed by Creighton with his well-known nicety, and
                    the divisions were read off with a lens, so that <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi>
                    / <hi rend="subscript"> 10</hi> th of a degree could be distinguished. After
                    bestowing the utmost pains in repeating the experi ments, during a period of
                    nearly two months, I found that the only way of removing the little
                    discrepancies which crept in between contiguous measures, was to adopt the
                    astronomical plan of multiplying observations, and deducing truth from the mean.
                    It is essential to heat with extreme slowness and circumspection the vessels A,
                    B, C. One repetition of the experiment occupies on an average seven hours.</p>
                <p>“ The apparatus employed in obtaining these results, has</p>
                <p>the peculiar advantage, over all others, that the mercurial column is never
                    heated. It is the concurrent opinion of all chemical philosophers, that caloric
                    travels downwards in liquids with extreme slowness and difficulty. Indeed, Count
                    Rumford’s experiments led him to infer, that heat could not descend in fluids at
                    all.</p>
                <p>“ It is evident that, in my constructions, figures 15, 16, and 17, only that
                    small portion of quicksilver within the</p>
                <p>vessels A, B, and C, will be affected by the heat, but the measuring column is
                    beyond the reach of its influence.”</p>
                <p>The Elastic Force of the Vapour of Water in inches of Mercury, obtained from
                    Experiments by Dr Ure.</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Temp.</cell>
                        <cell>Force.</cell>
                        <cell>Temp.</cell>
                        <cell>Force.</cell>
                        <cell>Temp.</cell>
                        <cell>Force.</cell>
                        <cell>Temp.</cell>
                        <cell>Force.</cell>
                        <cell>Temp.</cell>
                        <cell>Force.</cell>
                        <cell>Temp.</cell>
                        <cell>Force.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>24</cell>
                        <cell>0∙170</cell>
                        <cell>115°</cell>
                        <cell>2∙820</cell>
                        <cell>195°</cell>
                        <cell>21∙100</cell>
                        <cell>242»</cell>
                        <cell>53∙600</cell>
                        <cell>270»</cell>
                        <cell>86∙300</cell>
                        <cell>295·6°</cell>
                        <cell>130∙400</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>32</cell>
                        <cell>0∙200</cell>
                        <cell>120</cell>
                        <cell>3∙300</cell>
                        <cell>200</cell>
                        <cell>23∙600</cell>
                        <cell>245</cell>
                        <cell>56∙340</cell>
                        <cell>271∙2</cell>
                        <cell>88 000</cell>
                        <cell>295</cell>
                        <cell>129·000</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>40</cell>
                        <cell>0250</cell>
                        <cell>125</cell>
                        <cell>3∙830</cell>
                        <cell>205</cell>
                        <cell>25∙900</cell>
                        <cell>245∙8</cell>
                        <cell>57∙100</cell>
                        <cell>273∙7</cell>
                        <cell>91∙200</cell>
                        <cell>297∙1</cell>
                        <cell>133∙900</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>50</cell>
                        <cell>0∙360</cell>
                        <cell>130</cell>
                        <cell>4∙366</cell>
                        <cell>210</cell>
                        <cell>28∙880</cell>
                        <cell>248∙5</cell>
                        <cell>60∙400</cell>
                        <cell>275</cell>
                        <cell>93∙480</cell>
                        <cell>298∙8</cell>
                        <cell>137∙400</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>55</cell>
                        <cell>0∙416</cell>
                        <cell>135</cell>
                        <cell>5∙070</cell>
                        <cell>212</cell>
                        <cell>30000</cell>
                        <cell>250</cell>
                        <cell>61∙900</cell>
                        <cell>275∙7</cell>
                        <cell>94∙600</cell>
                        <cell>300</cell>
                        <cell>139700</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>60</cell>
                        <cell>0∙516</cell>
                        <cell>140</cell>
                        <cell>5∙770</cell>
                        <cell>216∙6</cell>
                        <cell>33∙400</cell>
                        <cell>251∙6</cell>
                        <cell>63∙500</cell>
                        <cell>277∙9</cell>
                        <cell>97∙800</cell>
                        <cell>300∙6</cell>
                        <cell>140·900</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>65</cell>
                        <cell>0∙630</cell>
                        <cell>145</cell>
                        <cell>6∙600</cell>
                        <cell>220</cell>
                        <cell>35∙540</cell>
                        <cell>254∙5</cell>
                        <cell>66∙700</cell>
                        <cell>279.5</cell>
                        <cell>101∙600</cell>
                        <cell>302</cell>
                        <cell>144∙300</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>70</cell>
                        <cell>0∙726</cell>
                        <cell>150</cell>
                        <cell>7∙530</cell>
                        <cell>221∙6</cell>
                        <cell>36∙700</cell>
                        <cell>255</cell>
                        <cell>67.250</cell>
                        <cell>280</cell>
                        <cell>101∙900</cell>
                        <cell>303∙8</cell>
                        <cell>147∙700</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>75</cell>
                        <cell>0∙860</cell>
                        <cell>155</cell>
                        <cell>8∙500</cell>
                        <cell>225</cell>
                        <cell>39∙110</cell>
                        <cell>257∙5</cell>
                        <cell>69∙800</cell>
                        <cell>281∙8</cell>
                        <cell>104∙400</cell>
                        <cell>305</cell>
                        <cell>150∙560</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>80</cell>
                        <cell>1∙010</cell>
                        <cell>160</cell>
                        <cell>9∙600</cell>
                        <cell>226∙3</cell>
                        <cell>40∙100</cell>
                        <cell>260</cell>
                        <cell>72∙300</cell>
                        <cell>283∙8</cell>
                        <cell>107·700</cell>
                        <cell>306∙8</cell>
                        <cell>154∙400</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>85</cell>
                        <cell>1∙170</cell>
                        <cell>165</cell>
                        <cell>10∙800</cell>
                        <cell>230</cell>
                        <cell>43∙100</cell>
                        <cell>260∙4</cell>
                        <cell>72∙800</cell>
                        <cell>285∙2</cell>
                        <cell>112∙200</cell>
                        <cell>308</cell>
                        <cell>157∙700</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>90</cell>
                        <cell>1360</cell>
                        <cell>170</cell>
                        <cell>12∙050</cell>
                        <cell>230∙5</cell>
                        <cell>43∙500</cell>
                        <cell>262∙8</cell>
                        <cell>75∙900</cell>
                        <cell>287∙2</cell>
                        <cell>114∙800</cell>
                        <cell>310</cell>
                        <cell>161∙300</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>95</cell>
                        <cell>1∙640</cell>
                        <cell>175</cell>
                        <cell>13∙550</cell>
                        <cell>234∙5</cell>
                        <cell>46∙800</cell>
                        <cell>264∙9</cell>
                        <cell>77∙900</cell>
                        <cell>289</cell>
                        <cell>118·200</cell>
                        <cell>311∙4</cell>
                        <cell>164800</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>100</cell>
                        <cell>1∙860</cell>
                        <cell>180</cell>
                        <cell>15∙160</cell>
                        <cell>235</cell>
                        <cell>47∙220</cell>
                        <cell>265</cell>
                        <cell>78∙040</cell>
                        <cell>290</cell>
                        <cell>120∙150</cell>
                        <cell>312</cell>
                        <cell>167·000</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>105</cell>
                        <cell>2∙100</cell>
                        <cell>185</cell>
                        <cell>16∙900</cell>
                        <cell>238∙5</cell>
                        <cell>50∙300</cell>
                        <cell>267</cell>
                        <cell>81∙900</cell>
                        <cell>292∙3</cell>
                        <cell>123∙100</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>110</cell>
                        <cell>2∙456</cell>
                        <cell>190</cell>
                        <cell>19·000</cell>
                        <cell>240</cell>
                        <cell>51∙700</cell>
                        <cell>269</cell>
                        <cell>84∙900</cell>
                        <cell>294</cell>
                        <cell>126∙700</cell>
                        <cell>312</cell>
                        <cell>1655</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>31. A senes of experiments on high-pressure steam was subsequently made by Mr
                    Philip Taylor, but he has not described his apparatus. A similar series was also
                    made by Professor Arsberger of Vienna. As their results may be useful for
                    comparison, we have united them in the following table :—<pb
                        facs="chi.28490924-1526168109_Page_0667.jpf" xml:id="eb07-20-s04-0586"/>
                    TayloVsand Arsberger's Experiments on High-Pressure Steam.</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Temperature</cell>
                        <cell>Taylor.</cell>
                        <cell>Arsberger.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>212°</cell>
                        <cell>30∙0</cell>
                        <cell>"</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>220</cell>
                        <cell>34∙9</cell>
                        <cell><hi rend="italic">"</hi></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>230</cell>
                        <cell>41∙5</cell>
                        <cell>"</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>232</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>44∙4</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>240</cell>
                        <cell>500</cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>249</cell>
                        <cell>"</cell>
                        <cell>59∙1</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>250</cell>
                        <cell>59∙1</cell>
                        <cell>"</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>260</cell>
                        <cell>70∙1</cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>270</cell>
                        <cell>82∙5</cell>
                        <cell>"</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>274</cell>
                        <cell>J,</cell>
                        <cell>88∙9</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>280</cell>
                        <cell>97*7</cell>
                        <cell>"</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>290</cell>
                        <cell>114∙5</cell>
                        <cell>"</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>293∙4</cell>
                        <cell>1204</cell>
                        <cell><hi rend="italic">"</hi></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>300</cell>
                        <cell>1337</cell>
                        <cell><hi rend="smallcaps">"</hi></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>320</cell>
                        <cell>1794</cell>
                        <cell><hi rend="italic">99</hi></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>322</cell>
                        <cell>"</cell>
                        <cell>1760</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>372</cell>
                        <cell>"</cell>
                        <cell>3250</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>432</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>620∙0</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>32. We now come to the most imposing series of experiments hitherto conducted. In
                    1823, the government of France having resolved to legislate on the means for
                    obtaining security in the use of steam-engines, consulted the Academy of
                    Sciences, upon the mode of most effectually promoting the public safety, without
                    placing useless restraints on commercial enterprise and manufacturing industry.
                    The examination into the state of knowledge concerning the phenomena of vapour
                    at elevated temperatures, which resulted from this application, having brought
                    the imperfections of this part of science prominently into notice, the Academy
                    were induced to undertake a long and laborious enquiry, not entirely free from
                    personal danger, into the law connecting temperature with the pressure of steam.
                    The commission consisted of the illustrious mem bent of the Academy, Baron de
                    Prony, Arago, Girard, and Dulong ; and the results of their investigation,
                    finish ed in 1829, are given in the tenth volume of the Memoirs of the Academy
                    of Sciences, printed in 1831. These experiments, conducted principally by the
                    MM. Arago and</p>
                <p>Dulong, were on a scale of magnitude and expense suited to the munificence of the
                    French government and the re</p>
                <p>sources of the Academy. The precautions adopted to ensure minute accuracy,
                    entitle them to confidence, no less than the names of two philosophers, so well
                    versed in experiments of a similar nature. They were carried as high as to the
                    twenty-fourth atmosphere of pressure.</p>
                <p>The experiments were made in one of the courts of the Observatory. Fig. 18
                    represents a section of the principal portions of the apparatus. The boiler <hi
                        rend="italic">a</hi> consists of a cylindrical body, having its axis
                    vertical ; the two ends forming top and bottom are spherical segments, strongly
                    riveted to the body, the whole being made of the finest plate iron. The material
                    of the cylindrical part is half an inch thick, the top and bottom being
                    considerably thicker. The aperture at the top, six inches in diameter, was
                    closed by a plate of wrought iron, an inch and three-quarters thick, overlapping
                    the hole, about two inches all round, and having on its lower surface a
                    projecting ring, adapting it to a groove on the upper side of the top of the
                    boiler : between these two surfaces was interposed a thick ring of lead, and the
                    cover was then strongly screwed down by six steel bolts, the nuts of which had
                    head-washers, so that, on screwing the whole together, the cover became
                    hermetically closed. This experimental boiler was built in a furnace of
                    considerable size and mass, intended to produce a temperature of the requisite
                    constancy ; <hi rend="italic">x x</hi> are bars upon which the fire rests ; <hi
                        rend="italic">y</hi> is the flue leading to the chimney.</p>
                <p>The other parts of the apparatus connected with the boiler are <hi rend="italic"
                        >b</hi> A, a lever, safety-valve, and weights ; <hi rend="italic">y y</hi>
                    (fig. 19) the thermometer scales; and <hi rend="italic">w w</hi> reservoirs of
                    cold water, for maintaining uniform temperatures on the vertical parts of the
                    instruments.</p>
                <p>During the process of proving the boiler by a hydraulic pump, the common
                    safety-valve, when used as an instrument for measuring with precision the
                    pressure of the fluid in the boiler, was observed to give very erroneous
                    indications, and the necessity of a more delicate apparatus was demonstrated.
                    The improved index of pressure, made use of in the experiments, is shown in fig.
                    18. For measuring the great pressures to be used, a tube of mercury, 80 feet
                    high, would have been requisite ; but there was used, as a substitute for it, a
                    glass tube <hi rend="italic">z z,</hi> closed at the upper end, filled with dry
                    atmospheric air, and having a length of only five feet seven inches, and an
                    internal diameter of <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> / <hi rend="subscript">
                        5</hi> of an inch, and of a thickness nearly equal to its diameter. It was
                    so arranged as to furnish a convenient manometer, capable of giving the same
                    indications, by the contraction of the contained air, as would have been given
                    in similar circumstances, by a column of mercury of the height due to the
                    diminished volume of the air. The graduation of this manometer, however,
                    presented new difficulties.</p>
                <p>These difficulties were successfully encountered by the skill and ardour of the
                    academicians. Every one knows that it is impossible to obtain a glass tube of
                    considerable length and magnitude which shall have a tolerably cylindrical
                    interior ; and that there are a number of practical<pb
                        facs="chi.28490924-1526168109_Page_0668.jpf" xml:id="eb07-20-s04-0587"/>
                    difficulties, which render it impossible to obtain even such a tube as that of a
                    common thermometer, which shall possess the uniformity necessary to a good
                    instrument. To make the proper allowance for this inevitable imperfection, the
                    academicians easily might have adopted the same method as that used in the case
                    of thermometer tubes, by determining the volume of successive small portions of
                    its interior ; but even this would have furnished a very partial remedy for the
                    evil, because it had not been ascertained that the space occupied by the air in
                    the manometer would diminish in bulk exactly in the proportion of the increase
                    of compressing force, or of the corresponding increase in the height of the
                    equivalent column of mercury. Two problems were therefore to be resolved at
                    once, the elimination of the error of the tube, and the determination of the
                    elasticity of air under high pressures. Both of them were satisfactorily
                    accomplished, by the following 1abori ous research.</p>
                <p>As a preliminary measure, it was resolved to graduate the manometer, and
                    determine the law of the elastic force of air under high pressures, by direct
                    comparison with a column of mercury, from 75 to 80 feet in height. Such an
                    experiment required a suitable <hi rend="italic">locale</hi> and a stupendous
                    apparatus. Among tire buildings of the Royal College of Henri Quatre, there may
                    be observed an old square tower, sole relic of the ancient church of Sainte
                    Genevieve : there exist still in the interior three vaulted floors, pierced in
                    the centre, and affording the very supports that were required for the erection
                    of this stupendous mercurial gauge. In the centre of this opening there was
                    raised a squared tree of the required height, and to this it was determined to
                    attach the glass tube of 80 feet in height. To form a single glass tube of so
                    great length was impossible ; its own weight, when constructed, under the
                    pressure of the mercury, would have endangered its existence. The glass column
                    was built of separate portions, united in mastic, with great care, in viroles of
                    steel. Each portion of tube was suspended in the air by an exact counterpoise,
                    acting over pulleys fixed to the tree ; and the whole of the parts were so
                    united in equilibrio, that each sustained only its own weight, and the pressure
                    of the mercury due to the height of the superior portion of the column. A
                    homogeneous metallic scale was attached, and its divisions read by a vernier, as
                    in the common barometer.</p>
                <p>The manometer to be graduated, and this column of mercury, were both connected by
                    tubes with a strong cylindrical vase <hi rend="italic">f</hi> holding about 100
                    lbs. of mercury. When thus placed in communication, a column of water was forced
                    into the vase above the mercury by a hydraulic pump, and the pressure thus
                    produced raised the metal with equal force up into the glass tube column on the
                    one hand, and into the manometric tube on the other. The point to which the air
                    was compressed was read off by a vernier, and the corresponding height of the
                    mercury having been determined, it was manifest that the same degree of
                    compression of the less instrument would ever after serve as the index of an
                    equivalent column of mercury. In this manner the whole tube was graduated by
                    careful experi ment. The result of this graduation was satisfactory and very
                    instructive. In forming the scale of the manometer, no room was left for errors
                    of practical execution ; and the comparison of the volume of the air with the
                    height of the mercurial column demonstrated the diminution of the volume of the
                    air to be precisely in the ratio of the pres sure, so that the law of Marriotte
                    is rigidly correct, even when extended to the extreme case, where the air is
                    reduced to less than <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> / <hi rend="subscript">
                        25</hi> part of its usual volume.</p>
                <p>This preliminary process having been successfully terminated, the enormous column
                    of glass was now laid aside, and the manometer, with its reservoir of mercury,
                    transported to the court of the Observatory, for the purpose of being attached
                    to the experimental boiler. Figure 18 shows the manometer <hi rend="italic">in
                        situ.</hi> An iron tube <hi rend="italic">d d',g',</hi> com</p>
                <p>posed of gun barrels welded together, connects the cover of the boiler <hi
                        rend="italic">a</hi>, with the reservoir of the manometer <hi rend="italic"
                        >f,</hi> so as to conduct the pressure of the steam to the surface, which
                    formerly had sustained the mercurial column. The vacant space above the mercury
                    was filled with water, which, by condensation from a stream of water on the
                    outside, was kept full to the constant height v. A column of water contained in
                    the glass tube <hi rend="italic">z z,</hi> and constantly replenished, preserved
                    the column of air, and other parts of the apparatus, at a constant temperature,
                    indicated by a thermometer. A tube o <hi rend="italic">p,</hi> of glass,
                    communicating with the reservoir of mercury above and below, indicates, on the
                    scale <hi rend="italic">I, m,</hi> the variation of level arising from the
                    recession of the mercury into the manometer tube.</p>
                <p>To ascertain the temperature of the water and steam of the boiler, it had been
                    considered sufficient in the ruder experiments of earlier observers to insert
                    thermometers directly into the boiler itself. Every one who has an acquaintance
                    with these instruments knows, that any difference of pres sure on the glass
                    produces a false indication of the instru ments, so that even the few inches of
                    mercury in the instrument itself, when inverted, alter its indications, and a
                    slight pressure of the finger would raise it a degree ; the inaccuracy of the
                    old method, when used under a pressure of 70 or 80 feet of mercury, or 450
                    pounds on every inch of the immersed surface of the instrument would have been
                    great. The French academicians avoided this error, by immersing strong iron
                    tubes <hi rend="italic">t t,</hi> (figs. 18 and 19,) in the water and steam, in
                    which the thermometers, surrounded by liquid metal, were kept in close
                    communication with the heat of the fluids, without exposure to their force. By
                    adopting only very slow variations of temperature, the error arising from the
                    motion of heat was rendered insensible.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">The following Table contains the results of Thirty of the most
                        unexceptionable Experiments :—</hi></p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>1.</cell>
                        <cell>2.</cell>
                        <cell>3.</cell>
                        <cell>4.</cell>
                        <cell cols="2">5.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>Smaller</p><p>Centigrade</p><p>Thermo</p><p>meter.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Larger</p><p>Centigrade</p><p>Thermo</p><p>meter.</p></cell>
                        <cell>Elastic Forcemeters, in feet of Mercury at 32 degrees.</cell>
                        <cell>In Atmospheres of 76 degrees.</cell>
                        <cell>Condition in which the Observations were</cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>made.</cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>122∙97</cell>
                        <cell>123∙7</cell>
                        <cell>1∙62916</cell>
                        <cell>2∙14</cell>
                        <cell>max.</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>132∙58</cell>
                        <cell>132∙82</cell>
                        <cell>2.1767</cell>
                        <cell>2∙87</cell>
                        <cell>a</cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>132∙64</cell>
                        <cell>133∙3</cell>
                        <cell>2∙1816</cell>
                        <cell>2∙88</cell>
                        <cell>p. max.</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>137∙70</cell>
                        <cell>138∙3</cell>
                        <cell>2∙5386</cell>
                        <cell>3∙348</cell>
                        <cell>a</cell>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>149∙54</cell>
                        <cell>149∙7</cell>
                        <cell>3∙4759</cell>
                        <cell>4∙584</cell>
                        <cell>max.</cell>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                        <cell>151∙87</cell>
                        <cell>151∙9</cell>
                        <cell>3∙6868</cell>
                        <cell>4∙86</cell>
                        <cell>a</cell>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>7</cell>
                        <cell>15364</cell>
                        <cell>153∙7</cell>
                        <cell>3∙881</cell>
                        <cell>5∙12</cell>
                        <cell>a</cell>
                        <cell>7</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>8</cell>
                        <cell>163∙00</cell>
                        <cell>163∙4</cell>
                        <cell>4∙9383</cell>
                        <cell>6∙51</cell>
                        <cell>max.</cell>
                        <cell>8</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>9</cell>
                        <cell>168∙40</cell>
                        <cell>168∙5</cell>
                        <cell>5∙6054</cell>
                        <cell>7∙391</cell>
                        <cell>max.</cell>
                        <cell>9</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell>169∙57</cell>
                        <cell>169∙4</cell>
                        <cell>5∙7737</cell>
                        <cell>7∙613</cell>
                        <cell>a. s.</cell>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>11</cell>
                        <cell>171∙88</cell>
                        <cell>172∙34</cell>
                        <cell>6151</cell>
                        <cell>8∙114</cell>
                        <cell>a</cell>
                        <cell>11</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>12</cell>
                        <cell>180∙71</cell>
                        <cell>180∙7</cell>
                        <cell>7∙5001</cell>
                        <cell>9∙893</cell>
                        <cell>p.mαx.</cell>
                        <cell>12</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>13</cell>
                        <cell>183·70</cell>
                        <cell>183·70</cell>
                        <cell>8∙0352</cell>
                        <cell>10∙6</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>13</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>14</cell>
                        <cell>186∙80</cell>
                        <cell>1871</cell>
                        <cell>8∙6995</cell>
                        <cell>11∙48</cell>
                        <cell>a. s.</cell>
                        <cell>14</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>15</cell>
                        <cell>188∙30</cell>
                        <cell>188∙5</cell>
                        <cell>8∙840</cell>
                        <cell>11·66</cell>
                        <cell>max.</cell>
                        <cell>15</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>16</cell>
                        <cell>193·70</cell>
                        <cell>1937</cell>
                        <cell>9·9989</cell>
                        <cell>13·19</cell>
                        <cell>a</cell>
                        <cell>16</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>17</cell>
                        <cell>198∙55</cell>
                        <cell>198·5</cell>
                        <cell>11·019</cell>
                        <cell>1453</cell>
                        <cell>a. s.</cell>
                        <cell>17</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>18</cell>
                        <cell>20200</cell>
                        <cell>20175</cell>
                        <cell>11∙862</cell>
                        <cell>15∙65</cell>
                        <cell>a</cell>
                        <cell>18</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>19</cell>
                        <cell>203∙40</cell>
                        <cell>20417</cell>
                        <cell>12·2903</cell>
                        <cell>16·21</cell>
                        <cell>a. s.</cell>
                        <cell>19</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>20</cell>
                        <cell>206·17</cell>
                        <cell>206∙10</cell>
                        <cell>129872</cell>
                        <cell>17∙13</cell>
                        <cell>a</cell>
                        <cell>20</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>21</cell>
                        <cell>206∙40</cell>
                        <cell>206∙8</cell>
                        <cell>13·061</cell>
                        <cell>17.23</cell>
                        <cell>max.</cell>
                        <cell>21</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>22</cell>
                        <cell>207∙09</cell>
                        <cell>207∙4</cell>
                        <cell>131276</cell>
                        <cell>17.3</cell>
                        <cell>p.max.</cell>
                        <cell>22</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>23</cell>
                        <cell>20845</cell>
                        <cell>208·9</cell>
                        <cell>13∙6843</cell>
                        <cell>18.05</cell>
                        <cell>a</cell>
                        <cell>23</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>24</cell>
                        <cell>209·10</cell>
                        <cell>209∙13</cell>
                        <cell>13·769</cell>
                        <cell>18.16</cell>
                        <cell>a</cell>
                        <cell>24</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>25</cell>
                        <cell>210·47</cell>
                        <cell>210·5</cell>
                        <cell>14∙0634</cell>
                        <cell>18.55</cell>
                        <cell>p.max.</cell>
                        <cell>25</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>26</cell>
                        <cell>21507</cell>
                        <cell>215∙3</cell>
                        <cell>15∙4995</cell>
                        <cell>20∙44</cell>
                        <cell>a</cell>
                        <cell>26</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>27</cell>
                        <cell>217∙23</cell>
                        <cell>2175</cell>
                        <cell>161528</cell>
                        <cell>21∙3l</cell>
                        <cell>a</cell>
                        <cell>27</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>28</cell>
                        <cell>218∙3</cell>
                        <cell>218∙4</cell>
                        <cell>163816</cell>
                        <cell>2I∙6</cell>
                        <cell>p.max.</cell>
                        <cell>28</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>29</cell>
                        <cell>220∙4</cell>
                        <cell>220∙8</cell>
                        <cell>17∙1826</cell>
                        <cell>22∙66</cell>
                        <cell>a</cell>
                        <cell>29</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>30</cell>
                        <cell>223∙88</cell>
                        <cell>224∙15</cell>
                        <cell>18·1894</cell>
                        <cell>23.994</cell>
                        <cell>max.</cell>
                        <cell>30</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <pb facs="chi.28490924-1526168109_Page_0669.jpf" xml:id="eb07-20-s04-0588"/>
                <p>A table of temperatures, from 1 to 50 atmospheres, calculated in coincidence with
                    the experiments of the French academicians, and adapted to English measures, is
                    given by us in Article 57, for the purpose of convenient practical
                    reference.</p>
                <p>33. The latest series of experiments on the elastic force of high-pressure steam,
                    we owe to America. At the re quest of the Hon. S. D. Ingham, Secretary of the
                    Treasury of the United States, a committee of the Franklin Institute, of the
                    State of Pennsylvania, was appointed “ to examine into the causes of the
                    explosions of the boilers used on board of steamboats, and to devise the most
                    effectual means of preventing the accidents, or of diminishing the extent of
                    their injurious effects.” Among other subjects, such as the strength of boilers,
                    the construction of safety-valves, to which we shall refer in another place,
                    this committee took into consideration the elastic force of high-pressure steam
                    at different temperatures. Funds were placed at their disposal by the House of
                    Representatives, and the committee consisted of such a combination of scientific
                    and practical men, as to give high authority to their results. On the 1st day of
                    November, 1830, the subject was placed in the hands of the following gentle men
                    :—Professor Alex. Dallas Bache, Mr Benjamin Reeves, Mr λV. H. Keating, Mr M. W.
                    Balwin, Mr S. V. Berrick, and Isaiah Sukens.</p>
                <p>We shall enter more fully on the description of their apparatus of experiment
                    than we should otherwise have done, because we shall have frequent reference to
                    make to the whole of their experiments, not only in this article, but in our
                    article on the Steam-Engine, where we treat of explosions of boilers and their
                    causes.</p>
                <p>The boiler used by the committee is represented in figs. 20, 21, 22. It is a
                    cylinder, twelve inches in internal diameter, two feet ten inches and a quarter
                    in length within, and a quarter of an inch thick, of rolled iron, with the ends
                    rivetted in the usual manner. Fig. 21 is a side view. Figs. 20 and 22 are end
                    views of the boiler,</p>
                <p>and of the apparatus connected with it. The boiler was placed horizontally in a
                    furnace, the fire surface extending about halfway round the cylinder. The
                    furnace was arranged for a charcoal fire, the grate bars extending the whole
                    length of the boiler, and the fire being applied nearly the whole length. The
                    draught entered by an</p>
                <p>opening, closed in the usual manner, and left the furnace through a flue placed
                    at one end and side of the boiler. In fig. 20, A is the ashpit door, B the
                    furnace door, and in 21 and 22, C is the furnace chimney.</p>
                <p>In order to examine, readily, the interior of the boiler during the progress of
                    the experiments, each end was provided with a glass window (D, figs. 20 and 22).
                    The glass used was three-eighths of an inch thick. The openιngs in the ends,
                    which were rectangular, were two and a half by one and three quarters inches
                    wide.</p>
                <p>Three gauge cocks were placed in the front end of the boiler ; their positions
                    will be particularly stated hereafter; they are shown in figs. 20 and 21, at <hi
                        rend="italic">a, b,</hi> and c.</p>
                <p>To the same end and by the side of the gauge cocks, a glass water gauge (<hi
                        rend="italic">w</hi>, <hi rend="italic">x,</hi> figs. 20 and 21) was
                    attached, a particular description of which will be given in the detail of
                    experiments made to compare its performance with that of the gauge cocks.</p>
                <p>To supply the boiler with water, a forcing pump EE'<pb
                        facs="chi.28490924-1526168109_Page_0670.jpf" xml:id="eb07-20-s04-0589"/> FG,
                    figs. 21 and 22, was placed near the back end. This pump was of the ordinary
                    construction, with a solid plunger and conical valves ; the diameter of the pump
                    was one inch, and the play of the piston one inch and three-quarters. The
                    diameter of the pipe F G, by which the water was conveyed from the pump to the
                    boiler, was three-hundredths of an inch. By a coupling screw, this pipe could be
                    connected with either of the stop cocks <hi rend="italic">d e,</hi> fig. 22, in
                    the back end of the boiler : the opening of these cocks was two-hundredths of an
                    inch in diameter.</p>
                <p>To ascertain the elasticity of the steam within the boiler, a closed steam gauge
                    (H, figs. 21 and 22), was used, a particular description of the construction,
                    &amp;e. of which will he given. This instrument was placed upon the same stand
                    (I, figs. 21 and 22) which supported the pump, so that the same experimenter
                    could observe its indications and attend to the working of the pump. The cistern
                    of the gauge was connected by a flexible pipe <hi rend="italic">f g,</hi> with
                    the upper part of the boiler.</p>
                <p>The safety-valve is shown on the top of the boiler (K, fig. 21), midway between
                    the ends. The graduation of it required much pains, and will receive a separate
                    discussion.</p>
                <p>Near the safety-valve is represented (at L, fig. 21,) the fusible plate
                    apparatus, consisting of a sliding plate of iron, moved by a lever. On the other
                    side of the safety-valve are the thermometers (M and N, fig. 21) plunged into
                    iron tubes to give the temperature of the steam and water within the boiler.
                    Above this appears the reservoir O, containing the water intended to maintain
                    the scales of the thermometers at a constant temperature. All these parts
                    require a more detailed description.</p>
                <p>The steam gauge consisted of a glass tube closed at the upper, and open at the
                    lower end, which passed steam tight into a reservoir for mercury : when this
                    reservoir was connected with the boiler the pressure of the steam raised the
                    mercury into the gauge tube, compressing the air which the tube contained. The
                    first mercurial gauge which was made, was broken by a sudden access of sur
                    charged steam, in the experiments upon that subject, and was replaced by a
                    second one. The method of graduation, and in general the description of the
                    second gauge, will serve also for the first ; the details, only varied
                    slightly.</p>
                <p>The glass gauge tube was 26.43 inches in length. To the lower end was connected
                    an iron ferule, terminated above by a projecting ring. This ring was pressed
                    upon the upper end of the pipe A, by a coupling screw, which served to form a
                    tight juncture between the gauge and the cistern. The cistern <hi rend="italic"
                        >i</hi> was a cylindrical vessel of cast iron, having the two projecting
                    tubes <hi rend="italic">h</hi> and <hi rend="italic">k,</hi> upon which screws
                    were cut : the first of them has been alluded to as giving a passage to the
                    glass tube of the gauge; the second was coupled, by the pipe <hi rend="italic">f
                        g,</hi> to the boiler.</p>
                <p>The gauge tube was not of precisely equal diameter throughout, and it was judged
                    more accurate to graduate small portions of it into equal volumes. This was done
                    by introducing equal measures of air from the point of a sliding-rod gas measure
                    (Hare’s) ; this operation was performed repeatedly, and by multiple measures, to
                    verify the results, until the marks made for the equal volumes, on a paper scale
                    attached to the tube, coincided, in the various trials. The lengths of the
                    spaces occupied by the equal volumes were then carefully measured upon the brass
                    scale to be used with the gauge. The slight differences between the lengths
                    given by adjacent parts of the tube, showed that it might be considered as
                    divided into so many small portions of uniform diameter. The mercury rising into
                    the gauge tube from the cistern when pressure is applied, the level of the
                    cistern is necessarily depressed ; the amount of the correction for this depends
                    upon the relation between the areas of the cistern and tube, supposed uniform.
                    The areas of the cistern were found to be, within the limits of its use,
                    sensibly the same ;</p>
                <p>those of the tube might be so assumed for such a purpose : the ratio was
                    therefore found by filling the gauge tube with mercury, and pouring this into
                    the cistern, noting the rise produced ; comparing this with the mean length of
                    of the tube, the ratio of depression in the gauge for elevation in the tube was
                    found to be as .01 to 1. The air within the tube was next carefully dried by the
                    introduction of a receptacle of chloride of calcium, of the same length with the
                    tube ; the air having been in contact with this substance for a sufficient time,
                    the receptacle was withdrawn through the mercury over which the drying had been
                    effected ; the tube was next placed over a dish of mercury, in the receiver of
                    an air-pump, and the air withdrawn, until, on readmitting air to the receiver,
                    the mercury rose in the tube above the iron ferule.</p>
                <p>The gauge tube was next introduced into the cistern, the level of which,
                    corresponding to the zero of the brass scale was then arranged, and tne point of
                    the scale at which the mercury stood was ascertained, the barometer and
                    thermometer being noted.</p>
                <p>It was intended in the experiments to keep the pipe from the gauge to the boiler
                    cool, so that it might contain water, and thus give a nearly constant pressure
                    upon the mercury of the cistern, besides preventing the exposure of the
                    apparatus to heat ; the height of this column, above the level of the cistcern,
                    was therefore ascertained, after the gauge was put in its place by screwing the
                    cistern i to the stand.</p>
                <p>All the elements for calculating the elasticity of the steam within the boiler,
                    from the height of the mercury of the gauge, were thus known ; the temperature
                    of the apparatus being supposed constant.</p>
                <p>The elastic force of the steam within the boiler, together with the column of
                    water in the steam-pipe, balances the elasticity of the compressed air within
                    the guage, together with the column of mercury above the level of that in the
                    cistern. This level is not the original zero, but lower than that, by the
                    depression produced by the rise of mercury in the gauge tube. The depression of
                    the mercury changes the level above which the pressure of the column of water in
                    the steam-pipe is measured, but the change in the pressure, by the column of
                    water, is altogether inconsiderable. The law of the elastic force of dry air,
                    which has been recently shown, by Dulong and Arago, to be accurate, at pressures
                    from one to fifty atmospheres, was made use of in determining the elasticity of
                    the air in the gauge : this elasticity is inversely as the space occupied by the
                    air. From the data already obtained, and upon the principles just stated, a
                    table was calculated, by which the observed heights of the gauge were converted
                    into the corresponding pressures in inches of mercury or in atmospheres. The
                    calculations were rendered rather tedious by the unequal diameter of the bore of
                    the tube, on ac count of which equal lengths did not correspond to equal
                    volumes. The usual method of calculation was resorted to, namely, to determine,
                    by rigid calculation, the pres sures, for points sufficiently near each other,
                    and then to interpolate for intermediate heights.</p>
                <p>The foregoing remarks take for granted that the temperature of the air in the
                    gauge, as well as that of the mercury, remains constant ; to secure this, an
                    arrangement was adopted similar to that employed by Dulong and Arago for the
                    same purpose. The gauge and scale were surrounded by a glass tube <hi
                        rend="italic">l,</hi> cemented below into a brass cap <hi rend="italic"
                        >m,</hi> which had an opening in the side, communicating with a discharge
                    pipe n, fig. 21. The tube was attached above, by an airtight juncture, to a tin
                    vessel P, of considerable capacity, compared with the tube. Water being
                    introduced into the glass tube surrounding the gauge, the flow through this tube
                    was regulated by a stopcock o, placed at the end of the dis charge pipe, the
                    cistern above being filled with water.</p>
                <p>To ascertain the temperature of the column of water<pb
                        facs="chi.28490924-1526168109_Page_0671.jpf" xml:id="eb07-20-s04-0590"/>
                    surrounding the gauge, a thermometer <hi rend="italic">(p,</hi> fig. 22) with a
                    very small bulb, was attached to the scale at the middle of its height: by this
                    instrument, the flow of water through the casing of the gauge was regulated so
                    as to keep the temperature nearly constant, and any deviations from a constant
                    temperature were ascertained and noted, that the proper correction might be
                    applied. The correction for the expansion of the air in the gauge, by a rise in
                    its temperature during the progress of the experiments, was made according to
                    the rules furnished by the rate of expansion of the gases, as determined by Gay
                    Lussac, extended to compressed air by the experiments of Davy. The correction
                    for the changes of height of the mercurial column, within the range to which the
                    temperature was suffered to increase, could not have been appreciable if acting
                    entirely, and the counteracting effect of the expansion of the glass further
                    justified its being neglected. For similar reasons no reference was made to the
                    effects of heat on the mercury in the cistern i, on the cistern itself, and on
                    the water within the pipe communicating with the boiler.</p>
                <p>In most of the researches of the committee, refinements in the mode of using the
                    common thermometer would have been out of place. Results which might be obtained
                    with little additional labour, and which would be interesting in both a
                    practical and scientific point of view, were not to be neglected, and to some of
                    them great accuracy was essential. In the questions of the first class, the
                    thermometers were provided with wooden scales, and were graduated by immersion
                    up to the point at which the scale commenced, the scale and upper part of the
                    tube being exposed to the air : this was proper, as they were intended to be
                    immersed in mercury nearly up to the scale. These instruments were examined
                    after coming from the maker’s hands, and the instrumental error ascertained. The
                    tubes in which the thermometers were placed, and which contained mercury, were
                    at first placed horizontally in one of the ends of the boiler ; this had the
                    advantage of rendering the tube for indicating the temperature of the water
                    entirely independent of the steam, and thus any difference between the
                    temperature of one and the other might be more effectually ascertained, than
                    when the tube giving the temperature of the water passed through the steam. The
                    position of these instruments interfered so much with other parts of the
                    apparatus, and so much in convenience and danger of error was experienced from
                    the separation of the column of mercury in the thermo meter, that these tubes
                    were not used after the first weeks of experiment, and two vertical tubes,
                    placed as already shown, were substituted for them.</p>
                <p>The thermometers used, when the relation between the temperature of the steam and
                    water, and the elasticity of the steam were to be observed in conjunction with
                    some of the subjects more directly under the cognizance of the committee, had
                    much pains bestowed upon them.</p>
                <p>The scales (M and N,) were metallic, and surrounded by glass tubes, fitting into
                    a cup <hi rend="italic">a',</hi> through the bottom of which the stem of the
                    thermometer passed water tight ; a pipe <hi rend="italic">b' c, fig.</hi> 20,
                    from the side of each cup, and provided with a stopcock <hi rend="italic"
                        >d,</hi> regulated the flow of water through the enveloping tubes : a tight
                    connexion above with a reservoir (O) served, as in the case of the gauge, to
                    supply the tubes with water. Small thermo meters on the back of the scale of the
                    large ones, showed the temperature of the water which surrounded them. The
                    enveloping tubes being filled with water at 60°, the position of the boiling
                    point of water and of the fusing point of tin, were used to verify the accuracy
                    of graduation. The latter point, which is high upon the scale of the
                    thermomoter, having been very accurately determined, and being easily and with
                    certainty ascertainable, serves as an excellent check upon the graduation. The
                    greatest error within the limits just stated, was in one instrument,
                    three-fourths of a degree, and in the other one degτee of Fahrenheit. The scales
                    were graduated from two to two degrees, one quarter of a degree being readily
                    estimated upon them. The corrections required by this examination were made
                    through the medium of a table prepared for the purpose. In order to call the
                    attention to the temperature of the water sur rounding the scales, this
                    temperature was recorded from time to lime, when the height of the thermometers
                    was observed, At no time did the rise of temperature, permitted in the water,
                    make it necessary to apply a correction for the expansion of the scale. None was
                    required for the cooling effect of the water around the stem upon the mercury,
                    owing to the method of verifying the scale.</p>
                <p>The other parts of the apparatus, less general in their use, as the water-gauge,
                    safety-valve, fusible plate appa ratus, &amp;c., will be more conveniently
                    described in connexion with the experiments for which they were devised.”</p>
                <p>34. With this apparatus, and these precautions, a series of experiments were
                    made, the results of which are contained in the following tables :—</p>
                <p>The Table, No. 1, contains the temperature observed by the thermometer in the
                    water, corrected for the error of the graduation ; the temperature of the scale
                    of the thermo meter, with a view to show that it was not allowed to vary too
                    considerably ; the observed height of the mercury in the gauge, reduced to its
                    mean height ; the temperature</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Table, No.</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">I.—</hi> Of the Elastic Force of Steam at different
                    Temperatures.</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Temperature of steam.</cell>
                        <cell>Temp. of scale of thermometer.</cell>
                        <cell>Height of mercury in air gauge.</cell>
                        <cell>Temperature of air in gauge.</cell>
                        <cell>Volume of air in observed temperature.</cell>
                        <cell>Volume of air at 48 <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> Fahrenheit.</cell>
                        <cell>Elasticity of air in inches of mercury.</cell>
                        <cell>.01 Height of gauge.</cell>
                        <cell>Height + .01 height.</cell>
                        <cell>Height + .01 height —1.29 inches.</cell>
                        <cell>Total elasticity in inches of mercury.</cell>
                        <cell>Elastic force in atmosphere of 30 inches.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Fah.°</cell>
                        <cell>Fah.°</cell>
                        <cell>Inches.</cell>
                        <cell>Fob.°</cell>
                        <cell>Vols.</cell>
                        <cell>Vole.</cell>
                        <cell>Inches.</cell>
                        <cell>Inches,</cell>
                        <cell>Inches.</cell>
                        <cell>Inches.</cell>
                        <cell>Inches.</cell>
                        <cell>Atmos.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>3.99*</cell>
                        <cell>62</cell>
                        <cell>8.33</cell>
                        <cell>8.101</cell>
                        <cell>27.26</cell>
                        <cell>.04</cell>
                        <cell>4.03</cell>
                        <cell>2.74</cell>
                        <cell>30.00</cell>
                        <cell>1.00</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>262¼</cell>
                        <cell>63</cell>
                        <cell>15.04</cell>
                        <cell>74</cell>
                        <cell>393</cell>
                        <cell>3.737</cell>
                        <cell>59.09</cell>
                        <cell>.15</cell>
                        <cell>15.19</cell>
                        <cell>13.90</cell>
                        <cell>72.99</cell>
                        <cell>2.43</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>268½</cell>
                        <cell>71</cell>
                        <cell>16 34</cell>
                        <cell><hi rend="italic">"</hi></cell>
                        <cell>3.43</cell>
                        <cell>3.259</cell>
                        <cell>67.76</cell>
                        <cell>.16</cell>
                        <cell>16.50</cell>
                        <cell>15.21</cell>
                        <cell>82.97</cell>
                        <cell>2.76</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>275½</cell>
                        <cell>"</cell>
                        <cell>1734</cell>
                        <cell>"</cell>
                        <cell>3.05</cell>
                        <cell>2.898</cell>
                        <cell>76.20</cell>
                        <cell>.17</cell>
                        <cell>17.51</cell>
                        <cell>16.22</cell>
                        <cell>92.42</cell>
                        <cell>3.08</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>286½</cell>
                        <cell>"</cell>
                        <cell>18.94</cell>
                        <cell>"</cell>
                        <cell>2.44</cell>
                        <cell>2.319</cell>
                        <cell>95.23</cell>
                        <cell>.19</cell>
                        <cell>19.13</cell>
                        <cell>17.84</cell>
                        <cell>113.07</cell>
                        <cell>3.77</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>296½</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>19∙94</cell>
                        <cell>"</cell>
                        <cell>2.05</cell>
                        <cell>1.948</cell>
                        <cell>113.36</cell>
                        <cell>.20</cell>
                        <cell>20.14</cell>
                        <cell>18.85</cell>
                        <cell>132.21</cell>
                        <cell>4.41</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>298½</cell>
                        <cell>73</cell>
                        <cell>20.11</cell>
                        <cell>"</cell>
                        <cell>L99</cell>
                        <cell>1.891</cell>
                        <cell>116.76</cell>
                        <cell>.20</cell>
                        <cell>20.31</cell>
                        <cell>19 02</cell>
                        <cell>135.80</cell>
                        <cell>4.53</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>302</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>20.44</cell>
                        <cell>"</cell>
                        <cell>1.86</cell>
                        <cell>1.767</cell>
                        <cell>124.98</cell>
                        <cell>.20</cell>
                        <cell>20.64</cell>
                        <cell>19.35</cell>
                        <cell>144.33</cell>
                        <cell>4.81</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>305½</cell>
                        <cell>76</cell>
                        <cell>20.79</cell>
                        <cell>75</cell>
                        <cell>1.73</cell>
                        <cell>1.641</cell>
                        <cell>134.57</cell>
                        <cell>.21</cell>
                        <cell>21.00</cell>
                        <cell>19.71</cell>
                        <cell>154.28</cell>
                        <cell>5.14</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>313¼</cell>
                        <cell>79</cell>
                        <cell>21.39</cell>
                        <cell>»</cell>
                        <cell>140</cell>
                        <cell>1.422</cell>
                        <cell>155.30</cell>
                        <cell>.21</cell>
                        <cell>21.60</cell>
                        <cell>20.31</cell>
                        <cell>175.61</cell>
                        <cell>5.85§</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>317¾</cell>
                        <cell>80</cell>
                        <cell>21.64</cell>
                        <cell>"</cell>
                        <cell>1.405</cell>
                        <cell>1.332</cell>
                        <cell>165.79</cell>
                        <cell>.22</cell>
                        <cell>21.86</cell>
                        <cell>20.57</cell>
                        <cell>186.36</cell>
                        <cell>6.21</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>320¾</cell>
                        <cell><hi rend="italic">"</hi></cell>
                        <cell>21.79</cell>
                        <cell>76</cell>
                        <cell>1.347</cell>
                        <cell>1.275</cell>
                        <cell>173.20</cell>
                        <cell>.22</cell>
                        <cell>22.01</cell>
                        <cell>20.72</cell>
                        <cell>193.92</cell>
                        <cell>6.46</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>327¾</cell>
                        <cell>"</cell>
                        <cell>22.24</cell>
                        <cell>"</cell>
                        <cell>1.176</cell>
                        <cell>1.113</cell>
                        <cell>198.41</cell>
                        <cell>.22</cell>
                        <cell>22.02</cell>
                        <cell>20.73</cell>
                        <cell>219.14</cell>
                        <cell>7.30</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>333¾</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>22.69</cell>
                        <cell>"</cell>
                        <cell>1.004</cell>
                        <cell>0.950</cell>
                        <cell>232.46</cell>
                        <cell>.23</cell>
                        <cell>22.92</cell>
                        <cell>21.63</cell>
                        <cell>254.09</cell>
                        <cell>8.47</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p><hi rend="italic">* This observation shows the height of the gauge before the
                        experiment, corrected for the height of the barometer, Mean of four
                        observations Mean of two observations. Mean of two observations.</hi><pb
                        facs="chi.28490924-1526168109_Page_0672.jpf" xml:id="eb07-20-s04-0591"/> of
                    the air in the gauge ; its volume at the observed temperature ; the volume
                    reduced to 48°, the temperature of graduation of the gauge at which the column
                    of mercury, equivalent to an atmosphere, is very nearly 30 inches ; the
                    elasticity of the compressed air, in inches of mercury ; the correction in the
                    height of the column of mercury, for the depression produced in the cistern
                    below ; the height thus corrected : the height, after subtracting the sensibly
                    constant number for the column of water be tween the level of the steam-pipe
                    from the boiler and the cistern of the gauge ; the total elasticity in inches of
                    mercury ; the elasticity in atmospheres. The first line of numbers in the table
                    is merely introduced for the convenience of presenting certain data required for
                    subsequent calculation ; it gives the height of the mercury in the gauge before
                    beginning the observations, after correcting for the height of the
                    barometer.</p>
                <p>A curve traced to represent these observations, the ordinates representing the
                    pressures, and the abscissæ the</p>
                <p>temperatures, is quite regular, until the temperature cor responding to eight
                    atmospheres is attained, when it rises abruptly. This fact was explained, by
                    examining the gauge ; it was found that the cement us&lt; d in attaching the
                    glass tube to its ferule had become softened, and had permitted the tube to
                    rise. This defect was remedied and its recurrence prevented. It was then
                    determined to repeat the entire series of observations, and to carry them as
                    high as could be done, with reasonable convenience, aiming particularly, to
                    embrace the range of working, pressures of the American engines.</p>
                <p>The results are contained in the following table in which the observed data, and
                    calculated numbers, are arranged as in the last table. This table extends to
                    9∙91 atmospheres, and to the temperature of 352° Fahrenheit.</p>
                <p>Care was taken that the elasticities were increased not too rapidly, and the last
                    numbers obtained, were verified by keeping the temperature sensibly constant for
                    a considerable time.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Ταβle No.</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">II.—</hi> Of the Elastic Force of Steam at Different
                    Temperatures.</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Temperature of Steam.</cell>
                        <cell><p>Temperature of thermometer</p><p>scale.</p></cell>
                        <cell>Height of mercury in air gauge.</cell>
                        <cell>Temperature of air in gauge.</cell>
                        <cell>Volume of air nt observed temperature.</cell>
                        <cell>Volume of air at 48° Fah.</cell>
                        <cell>Elasticity of air in inches of mercury</cell>
                        <cell>.01 Height of gauge.</cell>
                        <cell>Height ½ .01 height.</cell>
                        <cell>Height + .01 height — 1.29 inches.</cell>
                        <cell>Total elasticity in inches of mercury.</cell>
                        <cell>Elastic force in atmospheres of 30 inches.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Fah.°</cell>
                        <cell>Fah.°</cell>
                        <cell>Inches.</cell>
                        <cell>Fah.°</cell>
                        <cell>Vols.</cell>
                        <cell>Vols.</cell>
                        <cell>Inches.</cell>
                        <cell>Inches.</cell>
                        <cell>Inches.</cell>
                        <cell>Inches.</cell>
                        <cell>Inches.</cell>
                        <cell>Atmos.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>5.56*</cell>
                        <cell>48</cell>
                        <cell>7.695</cell>
                        <cell>7∙695</cell>
                        <cell>25.67</cell>
                        <cell>.06</cell>
                        <cell>5.84</cell>
                        <cell>4.55</cell>
                        <cell>30.00</cell>
                        <cell>1.00</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>248¼</cell>
                        <cell>54</cell>
                        <cell>14.04</cell>
                        <cell>53</cell>
                        <cell>4.32</cell>
                        <cell>4.277</cell>
                        <cell>46.19</cell>
                        <cell>.14</cell>
                        <cell>14.18</cell>
                        <cell>12.89</cell>
                        <cell>59.08</cell>
                        <cell>1.97</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>269½</cell>
                        <cell>—</cell>
                        <cell>17.34</cell>
                        <cell>52</cell>
                        <cell>3.05</cell>
                        <cell>3.026</cell>
                        <cell>65.29</cell>
                        <cell>.17</cell>
                        <cell>17.51</cell>
                        <cell>16.22</cell>
                        <cell>8151</cell>
                        <cell>2.72</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>284½</cell>
                        <cell>—</cell>
                        <cell>19.64</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>2.17</cell>
                        <cell>2.152</cell>
                        <cell>91.76</cell>
                        <cell>.19</cell>
                        <cell>19.83</cell>
                        <cell>18.54</cell>
                        <cell>110.30</cell>
                        <cell>3.68</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>289½</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>20.06</cell>
                        <cell>"</cell>
                        <cell>1.99</cell>
                        <cell>1.974</cell>
                        <cell>100.05</cell>
                        <cell>.20</cell>
                        <cell>20.26</cell>
                        <cell>18.97</cell>
                        <cell>119.02</cell>
                        <cell>3.97</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>294½</cell>
                        <cell>—</cell>
                        <cell>20 56</cell>
                        <cell>53</cell>
                        <cell>1.82</cell>
                        <cell>1.802</cell>
                        <cell>109.63</cell>
                        <cell>.21</cell>
                        <cell>20.77</cell>
                        <cell>19.48</cell>
                        <cell>129.11</cell>
                        <cell>4.30</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>299½</cell>
                        <cell><hi rend="italic">—</hi></cell>
                        <cell>21.04</cell>
                        <cell>54</cell>
                        <cell>1.63</cell>
                        <cell>1.611</cell>
                        <cell>122.66</cell>
                        <cell>.21</cell>
                        <cell>21.25</cell>
                        <cell>19∙96</cell>
                        <cell>142.62</cell>
                        <cell>4.75</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>304½</cell>
                        <cell><hi rend="italic">—</hi></cell>
                        <cell>21.34</cell>
                        <cell>54½</cell>
                        <cell>1.52</cell>
                        <cell>1.500</cell>
                        <cell>131.66</cell>
                        <cell>.21</cell>
                        <cell>21.55</cell>
                        <cell>20.26</cell>
                        <cell>151.92</cell>
                        <cell>5.06</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>310½</cell>
                        <cell><hi rend="italic">—</hi></cell>
                        <cell>21.64</cell>
                        <cell>"</cell>
                        <cell>1.405</cell>
                        <cell>1.382</cell>
                        <cell>142.94</cell>
                        <cell>.22</cell>
                        <cell>21.86</cell>
                        <cell>20.57</cell>
                        <cell>163.51</cell>
                        <cell>5.45</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>314¾</cell>
                        <cell>58</cell>
                        <cell>22.04</cell>
                        <cell>55</cell>
                        <cell>1.25</cell>
                        <cell>1.233</cell>
                        <cell>160.26</cell>
                        <cell>.22</cell>
                        <cell>22.26</cell>
                        <cell>20.97</cell>
                        <cell>181.23</cell>
                        <cell>6.04</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>319¾</cell>
                        <cell>—</cell>
                        <cell>22.34</cell>
                        <cell>55½</cell>
                        <cell>1.14</cell>
                        <cell>1.124</cell>
                        <cell>175.86</cell>
                        <cell>.22</cell>
                        <cell>22.56</cell>
                        <cell>21.27</cell>
                        <cell>197∙13</cell>
                        <cell>6.57</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>329¾</cell>
                        <cell>—</cell>
                        <cell>22.84</cell>
                        <cell>56</cell>
                        <cell>0.95</cell>
                        <cell>0.937</cell>
                        <cell>210.84</cell>
                        <cell>.23</cell>
                        <cell>23.07</cell>
                        <cell>21.78</cell>
                        <cell>232.62</cell>
                        <cell>7.75</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>334½</cell>
                        <cell>66</cell>
                        <cell>22.94</cell>
                        <cell>57</cell>
                        <cell>0.92</cell>
                        <cell>0.904</cell>
                        <cell>218.60</cell>
                        <cell>.23</cell>
                        <cell>23.17</cell>
                        <cell>21.88</cell>
                        <cell>240.48</cell>
                        <cell>8.02</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>338¾</cell>
                        <cell>—</cell>
                        <cell>23 04</cell>
                        <cell>57½</cell>
                        <cell>0.887</cell>
                        <cell>0.870</cell>
                        <cell>226.92</cell>
                        <cell>.23</cell>
                        <cell>23.29</cell>
                        <cell>22.00</cell>
                        <cell>248.92</cell>
                        <cell>8.30</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>345</cell>
                        <cell>—</cell>
                        <cell>23.24</cell>
                        <cell>"</cell>
                        <cell>0.82</cell>
                        <cell>0.805</cell>
                        <cell>245.44</cell>
                        <cell>.23</cell>
                        <cell>23.47</cell>
                        <cell>32.18</cell>
                        <cell>267.62</cell>
                        <cell>8.92</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>348</cell>
                        <cell>—</cell>
                        <cell>23.34</cell>
                        <cell>58</cell>
                        <cell>0.787</cell>
                        <cell>0.771</cell>
                        <cell>256.05</cell>
                        <cell>.33</cell>
                        <cell>23.57</cell>
                        <cell>22.28</cell>
                        <cell>278.33</cell>
                        <cell>9∙28</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>350</cell>
                        <cell>—</cell>
                        <cell>23.44</cell>
                        <cell>"</cell>
                        <cell>0.752</cell>
                        <cell>0.737</cell>
                        <cell>267∙97</cell>
                        <cell>.23</cell>
                        <cell>23.67</cell>
                        <cell>22.38</cell>
                        <cell>290.35</cell>
                        <cell>9.68</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>352</cell>
                        <cell>— '</cell>
                        <cell>23.50</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>0.733</cell>
                        <cell>0.719</cell>
                        <cell>274.92</cell>
                        <cell>.23</cell>
                        <cell>23.73</cell>
                        <cell>22.44</cell>
                        <cell>297.36</cell>
                        <cell>9.91</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>346</cell>
                        <cell>—</cell>
                        <cell>23.28</cell>
                        <cell>62</cell>
                        <cell>0.807</cell>
                        <cell>0.785</cell>
                        <cell>251.78</cell>
                        <cell>.23</cell>
                        <cell>23.61</cell>
                        <cell>22.22</cell>
                        <cell>274.00</cell>
                        <cell>913</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p><hi rend="italic">* This observation shows the corrected height of the gauge
                        before the experiments.</hi></p>
                <p>There is one observation, namely, that at 329¾°, which observations of
                    temperatures and pressures incidentally is certainly recorded erroneously ; but
                    omitting this one, made during the other experiments of the committee, are the
                    rest which are given, present very tolerable regu brought together in the
                    annexed table.</p>
                <p>larity in the curve traced to represent them. For the A column is added to the
                    table, to show the number sake of adding to the force of these results, the
                    scattered of observations employed in obtaining the results.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">TablE</hi> No. III <hi rend="italic">Of the Elastic Force of
                        Steam at Different Temperatures.</hi></p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Temperature of Steam.</cell>
                        <cell><p>Temperature of thermometer</p><p>scale.</p></cell>
                        <cell>Height of mercury</cell>
                        <cell>Temperature of</cell>
                        <cell>Volume of</cell>
                        <cell>Volume of air at 48° Fah.</cell>
                        <cell>Elasticity of air in</cell>
                        <cell>+ .01 Height of gauge.</cell>
                        <cell>Height of gauge</cell>
                        <cell>Height +.01 height—1.29 inches.</cell>
                        <cell>Elasticity of steam in</cell>
                        <cell>Elastic force in atmospheres.</cell>
                        <cell>No. of ob</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>in air gauge.</cell>
                        <cell>air in gauge.</cell>
                        <cell>served temperatures.</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Inches of mercury.</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>+ .01 height.</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>inches of mercury.</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>serva</p><p>tions.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Fah.°</cell>
                        <cell>Fah.°</cell>
                        <cell>Inches.</cell>
                        <cell>Fah. <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi></cell>
                        <cell>Vole.</cell>
                        <cell>Vole.</cell>
                        <cell>Inches.</cell>
                        <cell>Inches.</cell>
                        <cell>Inches.</cell>
                        <cell>Inches.</cell>
                        <cell>Inches.</cell>
                        <cell>Atmos.</cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>3.91*</cell>
                        <cell>59</cell>
                        <cell>8.35</cell>
                        <cell>8.169</cell>
                        <cell>27.34</cell>
                        <cell>.04</cell>
                        <cell>3.95</cell>
                        <cell>2.66</cell>
                        <cell>30.00</cell>
                        <cell>1.00</cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>234</cell>
                        <cell>54</cell>
                        <cell>8.80</cell>
                        <cell>55</cell>
                        <cell>6.39</cell>
                        <cell>6.301</cell>
                        <cell>35.45</cell>
                        <cell>.09</cell>
                        <cell>8.89</cell>
                        <cell>7.60</cell>
                        <cell>43.05</cell>
                        <cell>1.43</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>239¼</cell>
                        <cell>62</cell>
                        <cell>9.94</cell>
                        <cell>61</cell>
                        <cell>5.94</cell>
                        <cell>5.788</cell>
                        <cell>38.59</cell>
                        <cell>.10</cell>
                        <cell>10.04</cell>
                        <cell>8.75</cell>
                        <cell>47.34</cell>
                        <cell>1.58</cell>
                        <cell>"</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>245¼</cell>
                        <cell>68</cell>
                        <cell>11.16</cell>
                        <cell>63</cell>
                        <cell>5.46</cell>
                        <cell>5.300</cell>
                        <cell>42.14</cell>
                        <cell>.11</cell>
                        <cell>11.27</cell>
                        <cell>9∙98</cell>
                        <cell>52.12</cell>
                        <cell>1.74</cell>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>250¼</cell>
                        <cell>70</cell>
                        <cell>12.54</cell>
                        <cell>63</cell>
                        <cell>4.92</cell>
                        <cell>4.776</cell>
                        <cell>46.77</cell>
                        <cell>.12</cell>
                        <cell>12.66</cell>
                        <cell>11.37</cell>
                        <cell>58.14</cell>
                        <cell>1.94</cell>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>256¼</cell>
                        <cell>73</cell>
                        <cell>13.88</cell>
                        <cell>64</cell>
                        <cell>4.38</cell>
                        <cell>4.243</cell>
                        <cell>52.64</cell>
                        <cell>.14</cell>
                        <cell>14.02</cell>
                        <cell>12.73</cell>
                        <cell>65.37</cell>
                        <cell>2.18</cell>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>262¾</cell>
                        <cell>77</cell>
                        <cell>15.14</cell>
                        <cell>64</cell>
                        <cell>3.89</cell>
                        <cell>3.768</cell>
                        <cell>59.27</cell>
                        <cell>.15</cell>
                        <cell>15.99</cell>
                        <cell>14.00</cell>
                        <cell>73.27</cell>
                        <cell>2.44</cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>271</cell>
                        <cell>70</cell>
                        <cell>16.34</cell>
                        <cell>65</cell>
                        <cell>3.43</cell>
                        <cell>3.316</cell>
                        <cell>67.35</cell>
                        <cell>.16</cell>
                        <cell>16.50</cell>
                        <cell>15.21</cell>
                        <cell>82.56</cell>
                        <cell>2.75</cell>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>278</cell>
                        <cell>75</cell>
                        <cell>17.44</cell>
                        <cell>70</cell>
                        <cell>3.01</cell>
                        <cell>2.882</cell>
                        <cell>77.49</cell>
                        <cell>.17</cell>
                        <cell>17.61</cell>
                        <cell>16.32</cell>
                        <cell>93.81</cell>
                        <cell>3.13</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>288½</cell>
                        <cell>75</cell>
                        <cell>18.74</cell>
                        <cell>68</cell>
                        <cell>2.50</cell>
                        <cell>2.403</cell>
                        <cell>92.94</cell>
                        <cell>.19</cell>
                        <cell>18.93</cell>
                        <cell>17.64</cell>
                        <cell>110.58</cell>
                        <cell>3.69</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>291</cell>
                        <cell>76</cell>
                        <cell>19.14</cell>
                        <cell>65</cell>
                        <cell>2.36</cell>
                        <cell>2.282</cell>
                        <cell>97.88</cell>
                        <cell>.19</cell>
                        <cell>19.33</cell>
                        <cell>18.04</cell>
                        <cell>115.92</cell>
                        <cell>3.86</cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>292½</cell>
                        <cell>65</cell>
                        <cell>19∙44</cell>
                        <cell>63</cell>
                        <cell>2.25</cell>
                        <cell>2.184</cell>
                        <cell>102.26</cell>
                        <cell>.19</cell>
                        <cell>19.63</cell>
                        <cell>18.34</cell>
                        <cell>120.60</cell>
                        <cell>4.02</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>300</cell>
                        <cell>73</cell>
                        <cell>20.12</cell>
                        <cell>65</cell>
                        <cell>1.98</cell>
                        <cell>1.494</cell>
                        <cell>117.33</cell>
                        <cell>.20</cell>
                        <cell>20.32</cell>
                        <cell>19.03</cell>
                        <cell>136.36</cell>
                        <cell>4.55</cell>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>.303½</cell>
                        <cell>74</cell>
                        <cell>20.54</cell>
                        <cell>66</cell>
                        <cell>1.82</cell>
                        <cell>1.756</cell>
                        <cell>127.27</cell>
                        <cell>.20</cell>
                        <cell>20.74</cell>
                        <cell>19.45</cell>
                        <cell>146.72</cell>
                        <cell>4.89</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p><hi rend="italic">* This observation shows the corrected height of the gauge
                        before the experiments.</hi><pb facs="chi.28490924-1526168109_Page_0673.jpf"
                        xml:id="eb07-20-s04-0592"/> This table enables us to go as low as 1.43
                    atmospheres’ and is strikingly accordant with the two others as far as they
                    extend in common.</p>
                <p>À curve which would be traced by the following table, which may be considered to
                    represent the mean of the foregoing, would differ little more than one-tenth of
                    an atmosphere in any part of the range, from the observations, omitting one
                    noticed in the first, and another noticed in the second table ; the pressures in
                    general differing less than one-tenth of an atmosphere from the observed
                    pressures.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Table of the Elastic Force of Steam from One to Ten
                        Atmospheres.</hi></p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Pres</p><p>sure.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Ob</p><p>served</p><p>Temp.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Pres</p><p>sure.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Ob</p><p>served</p><p>Temp.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Pres</p><p>sure.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Ob</p><p>served</p><p>Temp.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Pres</p><p>sure</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Ob</p><p>served</p><p>Temp.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Pres</p><p>sure</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Ob</p><p>served</p><p>Temp</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Atmo.</cell>
                        <cell>Fah.°</cell>
                        <cell>Atmo.</cell>
                        <cell>Fah.°</cell>
                        <cell>Atmo.</cell>
                        <cell>Fah.°</cell>
                        <cell>Atmo</cell>
                        <cell>Fah.°</cell>
                        <cell>Atmo.</cell>
                        <cell>Fall.°</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>212</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>275</cell>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>304½</cell>
                        <cell>7</cell>
                        <cell>326</cell>
                        <cell>9</cell>
                        <cell>345</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1½</cell>
                        <cell>235</cell>
                        <cell>3⅛</cell>
                        <cell>284</cell>
                        <cell>5½</cell>
                        <cell>310</cell>
                        <cell>7½</cell>
                        <cell>331</cell>
                        <cell>9½</cell>
                        <cell>349</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>250</cell>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>291½</cell>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                        <cell>315½</cell>
                        <cell>8</cell>
                        <cell>336</cell>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell>352½</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>2½</cell>
                        <cell>264</cell>
                        <cell>4½</cell>
                        <cell>298½</cell>
                        <cell>6½</cell>
                        <cell>321</cell>
                        <cell>∞</cell>
                        <cell>340½</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>To compare our results with those given by the committee of the French Academy,
                    we have traced a curve, from the above table, and another from those of the
                    thirty observations, selected by the committee of the Academy, from their
                    experiments which are below ten atmospheres. The curve of our observations,
                    passes at low pressures nearer to the line AB than that of the French
                    experimenters, and after coinciding at the medium pressures of the table,
                    crosses the latter, differing at 10 atmospheres 5 degrees, or at 352½ degrees
                    .65 of an atmosphere.</p>
                <p>The difference here noticed is too considerable to be admitted as within the
                    limits of errors in the apparatus or in observation. Having an authority of so
                    much weight against them, the committee have been driven to examine their
                    results very closely. The care employed in the graduation of the gauge seems to
                    exclude the idea of error from it ; the upper portion of the scale was divided
                    to .05 of an inch, and could easily be read to half of that distance, making
                    about .1 of an atmosphere at the highest pressure attained. A specific
                    correction for capillarity was ascertained and employed. In one point of
                    manipulation, namely, the method employed to dry the air, the committee differed
                    from what was usual, and though they think there is reason to confide in that
                    method, they have examined what effect would be produced if air were saturated
                    with moisture. Recent experiments on the passage of gases, out and into vessels
                    placed over mercury, and observations connected with them, warrant, moreover, a
                    suspicion, that dry air standing in a glass vessel over mercury, the surface of
                    which is covered by water, may become impregnated with vapour. The effect of
                    such a source of error they have calculated in the highest and lowest results of
                    table No. II. and find it to be as follows :—</p>
                <p>For 248¼° the tension of the vapour is 1.96 instead of 1.97, and 352 „ 9.78 „
                    9.91.</p>
                <p>Differing from the numbers given in table No. II. by .01 and . 13 of an
                    atmosphere.</p>
                <p>This supposition is thus shown to be inadequate to explain the discordance, and
                    must, in fact, be deemed, to a certain extent, gratuitous.</p>
                <p>The committee have next compared the results furnished by the safety-valves
                    graduated independently of the gauge, and these, as has already been shown, gave
                    calculated pressures four per cent and ten per cent higher</p>
                <p>than the pressures indicated by the gauge. From these independent experimental
                    data we have then an evidence that our results are, probably, not too high."</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
