<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>eb03-r03</title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>effect would be to preſs the axis on its ſupports. But AP, the direction of the preffure, being inclined to AC, the point A is forced aſide, and in ſome ſmall moment of time deſcribes the little arch A <hi rend="italic">a</hi>  round the centre C. The point P will therefore deſcribe a ſmall arch P<hi rend="italic">p,</hi>  ſubtending an angle PC∕&gt; = ACtf. Draw <hi rend="italic">a o</hi>  perpendicular to AP, and <hi rend="italic">a d</hi>  perpendicular to AD. The triangles JAo, ACP are ſimilar, and A <hi rend="italic">a</hi>  : Ao~ AC : CP. But the angles AC <hi rend="italic">a,</hi>  PC <hi rend="italic">p</hi>  being equal, the arches are as their radii, and A <hi rend="italic">a : Pp</hi>  = AC : CP, = A <hi rend="italic">a</hi>  : A <hi rend="italic">o ;</hi>  therefore <hi rend="italic">tp—</hi>  A <hi rend="italic">o.</hi></p><p>Now ſince, in conſequence of the impulſe, A deſcribes A a in the moment of time, it is plain that A <hi rend="italic">o</hi>  is the ſpace through which the impelling body continues to advance in the direction oſ the preffure ; and if V be taken equal to the ſpace which it deſeribed in an equal moment before the ſtroke, <hi rend="italic">v</hi>  will expreſs the remaining velocity, and V—<hi rend="italic">v</hi>  is the velocity loſt, and ∏(V—<hi rend="italic">v)</hi>  is the quantity of motion loſt by the impelling body, and is the true meaſure oſ the preffure exerted. This gives us the whole circumſtances of the rotatory motion. The angular velocity will be    and the velocity</p><p>of the point A will be    CP CA. <hi rend="sub">t</hi>j<hi rend="sub">ι</hi>∙<hi rend="sub">g</hi></p><p>locſty μ. The ſimilarity of triangles gives us CA : CP=Aa (or «) : Ao (or <hi rend="italic">v)</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">u — </hi><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps"><hi rend="sup">V</hi>-q^·</hi></hi>  There-fore yCA=√V^)CRCA    <hi rend="sub">we</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">cp </hi><hi rend="italic">SM*</hi></p><p>τy Pp<hi rend="sup">2</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">v — _</hi><hi rend="italic">1</hi>-----, and thus we have obtained the va-</p><p><hi rend="italic">ſpR+n.CP<hi rend="sup">2</hi> ...</hi></p><p>lue of <hi rend="italic">v</hi>  in known quantities ; for <hi rend="italic">η</hi>  was given, or ſuppoſed known ; ſo alſo was V : and ſince the direction FA was given, its diſtance CP from the axis is given ; and the form of the body being known, we can find the value of <hi rend="italic">ſp r<hi rend="sup">t</hi>.</hi>  Now we have ſeen that <hi rend="italic">ν</hi>  is alſo the velocity of the point P ; therefore we know the abſolute velocity oſ a given point of the body or machine, and conſequently the wſhole rotatory motion.</p><p><hi rend="italic">•    n</hi>  V’CP</p><p>We have the angular velocity =---: we</p><p><hi rend="italic">ſp</hi>  r<hi rend="sup">2</hi>-f- «.CP<hi rend="sup">2</hi></p><p>ſhall find this a maxi<hi rend="underline">mum w</hi>ſhen <hi rend="italic">f p r<hi rend="sup">z</hi>- n.CP<hi rend="sup">2</hi></hi>  ; and in</p><p>this caſe CP —    ∕    , and ι&gt; = ⅜V. So that the</p><p>√ <hi rend="sup">n</hi>.</p><p>greateſt velocity of rotation will be produced when the ſtriking body lotes ½ of its velocity.</p><p>What we have now delivered is ſufficient for explaining all the motions of bodies turning round fixed axes ; and we preſume it to be agreeable to our readers, that we have given the inveſtigation of the centres of gyration, oſcillation, and percuſſion. Tlιe curious reader will find the application of theſe theorems to the theory of machines in tw<hi rend="sup">,</hi>o very valuable differtations by Mr Euler in the Memoirs of the Academy of Berlin, vols viii. and x. and occafionally by other authors who have treated mechanics in a ſcientific and uſeful manner, going beyond the ſchool-boy elements of equilibrium.</p><p>There remains a very important caſe of the rotation of bodies, w<hi rend="sup">,</hi>ithout wſhich the knowledge of the motion of ſolid bodies is incomplete ; namely, the rotation of free bodies, that is, of bodies unconnected w<hi rend="sup">r</hi>ith any fixed points. We hardly ſee an inſtance of motion of a</p><p>free body without ſome rotation. A ſtone thrown from the hand, a ball from a cannon, the planets themſelves, are obſerved not only to advance, but alſo to whirl round. The famous problem of the preceſſion of the' equinoxes depends for its ſolution on this doctrine ; and the theory of the working of ſhips has the ſame foundation. We can only touch on the leading proportions.</p><p>We need not begin by demonſtrating, that when the direction of the external force paffes through the centre of the body, the body will advance without any rotation. This we conſider as familiarly known to every perſon verſant in mechanics ; nor is it neceffary to de-monſtrate, that when the direction of the moving force does not paſs through the centre of gravity, this centre will ſtill advance in a direction parallel to that of the moving force, and with the ſame velocity as if the direction of the moving force had paffed through it. This is the immediate conſequence of the equality of action and reaction obſerved in all the mechanical phenomena of the univerſe.</p><p>But it is incumbent on us to demonſtrate, that when the direction of the moving force does not paſs thro’ the centre of gravity, the body will not only advance in the direction of the moving force, but will alſo turn round an axis, and we muſt determine the poſition of this axis·, and the relation ſubſiſting between the progreſſive and rotatory motions.</p><p>The celebrated John Bernoulli w’as the firſt who con-fιdered this ſubject ; and, in his <hi rend="italic">Diſqutſitionet Mechanico-dynamic#,</hi>  he has demonſtrated ſeveral propofitions concerning the ſpontaneous axis of converfion, and the motions arifing from eccentric external forces : and although he affumed for the leading principle a propoiition which is true only in a great number of caſes, he has determined the rotation of ſpherical bodies with great accuracy.</p><p>This combination of motions wall be palpable in ſome fimple caſes, ſuch as the following : Let two equal bodies A and B (ſig. 9.) be connected by an inflexible rod (of which,we may neglect the inertia for the preſent). Let G be the middle point, and therefore the centre of gravity. Let an external force act on the point P in the direction FP perpendicular to AB, and let AP be double of PB, Alſo let the force be ſuch, that it would have cauſed the ſyſtem to have moved from the fituation AB to the ſituation <hi rend="italic">a b,</hi>  in an indefinitely ſmall moment of time, had it acted immediately on the centre G. G would in this caſe have deſeribed Gy, A would have deſeribed A <hi rend="italic">a,</hi>  and B would have deſeribed B <hi rend="italic">b,</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">a b</hi>  would have been parallel to AB : for the force impreſſed on A would have been equal to the force impreſſed on B ; but becauſe the force acts on P, the force imprfcſſed on A is but one half of that impreffed on B by the property oſ the lever : therefore the initial motion or acceleration of A will be only half of the initial motion of B ; yet the centre G muſt ſtill be at<hi rend="sub">ι</hi>y. We ſhall therefore aſcertain the initial motion of the ſyſtem, by drawing through<hi rend="italic">g</hi>  a line <hi rend="italic">a g ß,</hi>  ſo that A « ſhall be ⅛ of B <hi rend="italic">ß.</hi>  This we ſhall do by making AC= AB, and drawing <hi rend="italic">C &lt;* </hi><hi rend="italic">g β.</hi>  Then « <hi rend="italic">β </hi>will be the poſition of the ſyſtem at the end of the moment of time. Thus we ſee that the body muſt have a motion of rotation combined with its progreſſive motion,</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>