<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>eb03-r03</title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>and uſe ; for it having a thick pulp of an agreeable acid relilh, is often made into a tolerable good ſweet-meat.</p><p>9.    The pimpinellifolia, or burnet-leaved roſe, grows about a yard high, aculeated ſparſedly ; ſmall neatly pinnated ſeven-lobed leaves, having obtuſe folioles and rough petioles, ſmooth pedu∏cules, a globular ſmooth germen, and ſmall fingle flowers. There are varieties with red flowers—and with white flowers. They grow wild in England, &amp;c. and are cultivated in ſhrubbe-ries for variety.</p><p>10.    The ſpinofiſſima, or moil ſpinous, dwarf bιlrnet-leaved roſe, commonly called <hi rend="italic">Scotch roſe,</hi>  grows but two or three feet high, very cloſely armed with ſpines ; ſmall neatly pinnated ſeven-lobed leaves, with prickly foot-ſtalks, prickly pedunculi, oval ſmooth germen, and numerous ſmall fingle flowers, filcceeded by round dark«· purple heps. The varieties are, common white-flowered</p><p>--red-flowered—ſtriped-flowered--marbled-flowered.</p><p>They grow naturally in England, Scotland, &amp;c. The firſt variety riſes near a yard high, the others but one or two feet, all of which are fingle-flowered ; but the flowers being numerous all over the branches, make à pretty appearance in the collection.</p><p>11.    The eglanteria, eglantine roſe, or ſweet briar, grows five or fix feet high, having green branches, armed with ſtrong ſpines ſparſedly ; pinnated ſeven-lobed odoriferous leaves, with acute folioles and rough foot-ſtalks, ſmooth pedunculi, globular ſmooth germiha, and ſmall pale-red flowers. The varieties are, common ſingle-flowered—ſemi-double flowered—double-flowered—bluſh double-flowered—-yellow-flowered. Tliisſpe-cies grows naturally in ſome parts of England, and in Switzerland. It claims culture in every garden for the odoriferous property of its leaves ; and ſhould be planted in the borders, and other compartments contiguous to walks, or near the habitation, where the plants will impart their refreſhing fragrance very profulely all around ; and the young branches arc excellent for improving the odour of noſe-gays and bow-pots.</p><p>12.    The moſehata, or muſk-roſe, ſuppoſed to be a variety only of the ever-green muſk-roſe, hath weak ſmooth green ſtalks and branches, rifing by ſupport from fix to eight or ten feet high or more, thinly armed with ſtrong ſpines ; pinnated ſeven-lobed ſmooth leaves, with prickly foot-ſtalks ; hifpid peduncles ; oval hilj&gt;id germen; and all the branches terminated by large umbellate cluſters of pure-white muſk-ſcented flowers in Auguſt, &amp;c.</p><p>13.    The ſempervirens, or ever-green mulk roſe, hath a ſomewhat trailing ſtalk and branches, rifing by ſupport five or fix feet high or more, having a ſmooth bark armed with prickles; pinnated five-lobed ſmooth ſhining evergreen leaves, with prickly petioles, hifpid pedunculi, oval hifpid germen ; and all the branches terminated by dufters of pure-white flowers of a muſky fragrance ; appearing the end of July, and in Auguſt. The ſemper-virent property of this elegant ſpecies renders it a curi-ofity among the roſy tribe ; it alſo makes a fine appearance as a ſtowering ſhrub. There is one variety, the deciduous muſk-roſe above-mentioned. This ſpecies and variety flower in Auguſt, and is remarkable for producing them numerouſly in cluſttrs, continuing in ſucceſſion till October or November.</p><p>The above 13 ſpecies of roſa, and their refpective va</p><lb/><p>rieties, are of the ſhrub kind ; all deciduous, except the laſt fort, and of hardy growth, ſucceeding in any common foil and fituation, and flowering annually in great abundance from May till October, in different forts ; though the general flowering ſeaſon for the principal part of them is June and July : but in a full collection of the different ſpecies, the blow is continued in conſtant ſucceſſion ſeveral months, even ſometimes from May till near Chriſtmas ; producing their flowers uni* verſally on the fame year’s ſſioots, rifing from thoſe the year before, generally on long pedunculi, each terminated by one or more roſes, which in their eharacteri-ſtſe ſtate conſiſt each of five large petals and many ſta-mina; but in the doubles, the petals are very numerous; and in ſome forts, the flowers are ſucceeded by fruit ripening to a red colour in autumn and winter, from the feed of which the plants may be raiſed : but the moſt certain and eligible mode of propagating moſt of the forts is by fuckers and layers ; and by which methods they may be increaſed very expeditiouſly in great abundance.</p><p>The white and red roſes are uſed ill medicine. The former diſtſlled with water yields a ſmall portion of a butyraceoys oil, whoſe flavour exactly reſembles that of the roſes themſelves. This oil and the diſtilled water are very uſeful and agreeable cordials. Theſe roſes alſo, befides the cordial and aromatic virtues which refιde in their volatile parts, have a mild purgative one, which remains entire in the decoction left after diſtſllation. The red roſe, on the contrary, has an aſtringent and gratefully corroborating virtue.</p><p>ROSA (Salvator), an admirable painter, born at Naples in 1614. He was firſt inſtructed by Franceſco Francazano, a kinſman : but the death of his father reduced him to fell drawings ſketched upon paper for any thing he could get ; one of which happening to fall into the hands of Lanfranc, he took him under his protection, and enabled him to enter the ſchool of Spagnoletto, and to be taught moreover by Daniel Falcone, a diſtinguiſked painter of battles at Naples, Salvator had a fertile imagination. He ſtudied nature with attention and judgment ; and always repreſented her to the greateſt advantage ; for every tree, rock, cloud, or fituation, that enters into his compofition, ſhows an elevation of thought that extorts admiration. He was equally eminent for painting battles, animals, ſea or land ſtorms ; and he executed theſe different ſubjects in ſuch taſte as renders his works readily di-ſtinguiſkable from all others. His pieces are exceedingly ſcarce and valuable ; one of the moſt capital is that repreſenting Saul and the witch of Endor, which was preſerved at Verſailles. He died in 1673; and as his paintings are in few hands, he is more generally known by his prints; of which he etched a great number. He painted landſcapes more than hiilory ; but his prints are chiefly hiſtorical. The capital landſcape of this matter at Chiſwick is a noble picture. However, he is ſaid to have been ignorant of the management of light, and to have ſometimes ſhaded faces in a diſagreeable manned He was however a man of undoubted genius; of which he has given frequent ſpeciinens in hiε works. A roving diſpofition, to which he is ſaid to have given full ſcope, ſeems to have added a wildneſs to all his thoughts. We are told that he ſpent the early part of his life in a troop of banditti ; and that the rocky defolate ſcenes</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>