<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>eb03-r03</title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>it ready to receive him, becauſe the empty bucket is made heavier than the empty ftage.</p><p>Now, if there be no water in the bucket, it is evident, that although the motion of the machine will be the quickeſt poſſible, there will be no work performed. On the other hand, if the loaded ſtage and the full bucket are of equal weight, which is the uſual ſtatc-rnent of ſuch a machine in elementary treatiſes of mechanics, the machine will ſtand ſtill, and no work will be performed. In every intermediate ſtate of things thc machine will move, and work will be performed. Therefore the different values of the work performed muſt be a ſeries of quantities which increaſe from nothing to a certain magnitude, and then diminiſh to nothing again. The maxim which is uſually received as a fundamental propoſition in mechanics, viz. that what is gained in force by the intervention of a machihe is loft in time, is therefore falſe. There muſt be a particular proportion of the velocities of the impelled and working-points, which will give the greateſt performance when the power and reſiſtance are given ; and there is a certain proportion oſ the power and reſiſtance which will have the ſame effect when thb ſtructure of the machine lias previouſly fixed the velocities of the impelled and working points.</p><p>This proportion will be found by treating the formula which expreſſes the work as a fluxionaty quantity, and finding its maximum. Thus, when the ratio of the power and reſiſtance is given, and we wiſh to know what muſt be the proportion of the velocities <hi rend="sub">r</hi>∏ and<hi rend="italic">n,</hi>  that we may conſtruct the machine accordingly, we have only to conſider <hi rend="italic">n</hi>  as the variable quantity in the third formula. This gives us    √</p><p><hi rend="italic">½ct× r+ſ<hi rend="sup">1</hi> -<hi rend="sup">s</hi>Uρ<hi rend="sup">,</hi>'<hi rend="sup">χ</hi></hi><hi rend="smallcaps">&lt;j÷j∣</hi>—<hi rend="sup">κr</hi>+y∙</p><p><hi rend="italic">n — mX.---—cv=ez----—</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">pa-↑~y</hi></p><p>This is a fundamental propoſition in the theory of working machines : but the application requires much attention. Some natural powers are not accompanied by any inertia worth minding; in which caſe <hi rend="italic">x</hi>  may be omitted. Some works, in like manner, are not accompanied by any inertia ; and this is a very general caſe. In many caſes the work exerts no contrary ſtrain on the machine at reſt, and r is nothing. In moſt inſtances the intenſity of the power varies with the velocity of the impelled point, and is diminiſhed when this increaſes; the reſiſtance or actual preſſure at the working-point frequently increaſes with the velocity of the working-point. All theſe circumſtances muſt be attended to ; but ſtill they only modify the general propoſition. Theſe are matters which do not come within the limits of the preſent article. We only took this opportunity of ſhowing how imperſect is the theory of machines in equilibrio for giving us any knowledge of their performance or juſt principles of their conſtruction.</p><p>One thing, however, muſt be particularly attended to. in this theory. The forces which are applied to the body moveable round an axis are conſidered in the <hi rend="sub">i</hi> theory as preſſures actually exerted on the impelled points of the body or machine, as when a weight is appended to a lever or wheel and axle, and, by deſeending uniformly, acts with its whole weight In this caſe the ■weight multiplied by its diſtance from the axis will always expreſs its momentum, and the rotation will <hi rend="italic">fa-tens paribus)</hi>  be proportional to this product. But in many important caſes our machines are actuated by external impulſions. A body in motion ſtrikes on the impelled point of the machine, and cauſes it to turn round its axis. It is natural for us to conſider the quantity of motion of this impelling body as the meaſure of our moving force. Suppoſing <hi rend="italic">n</hi>  to be its quantity of matter, and V its velocity, <hi rend="italic">η</hi>  V appears a very proper meaſure of its intenſity. And if it be applied at the diſtance CP from the axis of rotation, nV*CP ſhould expreſs its energy, momentum, or power to turn the machine round C ; and we ſhould expreſs the angular velocity by <hi rend="sup">n</hi>-^-—<hi rend="sub">j</hi>-. Accordingly, this is the</p><p>manner in which calculations are uſually made for the conſtruction and performance of the machine, as may be ſeen in almoſt every treatiſe oſ mechanics.</p><p>But nothing can be more erroneous, as we ſhall ſhow by a very ſimple inſtance. It ſhould refuît from theſe principles that the angular velocity will be proportional<hi rend="sup">1 </hi>to CP. Let us ſuppoſe our moving power to bea ſtream of water moving at the rate of ten feet per ſecond, and that every ſecond there paſſes ιoo pounds of water. We ſhould then call our moving force ιcoo, It is evident, that iſ we ſuppoſe the arm of the float-board on which it ſtrikes to be infinitely long, the impelled point can never move faſter than ι o ſeet in a ſecond, and this will make the angular velocity infinitely ſmall, inſtead of being the greateſt of all. The rotation will therefore certainly be greater if CP be ſhorter. We need not examine the caſe more minutely.</p><p>We muſt therefore carefully diſtinguiſh between the quantity of motion of the impelling body and its moſ ving power, as it is modified by its manner of acting, <hi rend="sub">j </hi>The moving power is the<hi rend="italic">preſſure actually exerted</hi>  on the impelled point of the machine. Now thc univerſal fact of the equality of action and reaction in the colliſion of bodies aſſures us, that their mutual preſſure in their col-liſion is meaſured by the <hi rend="italic">change</hi>  of motion which each ſuſtains: for this change of motion is the only indication and meaſure of the preſſure which we ſuppoſe to be its cauſe. A way therefore of aſcertaining what is the real moving force on a machine actuated by the iιn-pulſion of a moving body, is to diſeover what quantity of motion is loſt by the body or gained by the machine; for theſe are equal. Having diſcovered this, we may proceed according to the propoſitions of rotatory mo,· tion.</p><p>Therefore let AEF (fig. 8.) repreſent a body move-able round an axis paſſing through C, perpendicular to the plane of the figure. Let this body be ſtruck in the point A by a body moving in the direction FA, and. let BAD be a tangent, to the two bodies in the point of colliſion. It is well known that the mutual actions of two folid bodies are always exerted in a direction perpendicular to the touching ſurfaces. Therefore the mutual preſſure oſ the two bodies is in the direction AP perpendicular to AD. Thereſorc let the motion of the impelling body be reſolved into the directions AP and AD. The force AD has<hi rend="sub">t</hi> no ſhare in the preſſure. Therefore letV be, the velocity of the impelling body eſtimated in the direction AP, and let <hi rend="italic">n </hi>be its quantity of matter. Its quantity of motion in the direction AP will be <hi rend="italic">η</hi>  V.</p><p>Did AP paſs through C, it is evident that the only</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>