<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>eb03-r03</title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p><hi rend="italic">; m .</hi>  CP . CG = GT : CG ; or, that <hi rend="italic">f.p</hi>  . r<hi rend="sup">,</hi>  is to « . CP . CG as the velocity of the body moving freely to the velocity of the centre of gravity round the axis of rotation.</p><p>. m.GI CP.CG Therefore the velocity of the centre ιs=-<hi rend="italic">~fρ~r<hi rend="sup">i</hi>~~*</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">. '    . rn</hi>. GI. CP. CB</p><p>The velocity of any point B is ==-<hi rend="italic">~Jf~r<hi rend="sup">i</hi>--"</hi></p><p>This fraction repreſents the length of the arch de-ſcribed by the point B in the ſame time that the body unconnected with any fixed points would have deſcri-bed G I.</p><p>Therefore the angular velocity (the arch divided by <hi rend="sub">ι</hi> . τfl.GI.CP</p><p>the radius) common to the whole body is ≈ fpt^—*</p><p>It may be here aſked, how this fraction can eχprefs an angle ? It evidently expreſſes a number ; for both the numerator and denominator are of the ſame dimenſions, namely, ſurfaces. It therefore expreſſes the portion of the radius which is equal to the arch meaſuring the angle, ſuch as 4, {, &lt;, &amp;c. And to have this angle in degrees, we have only to recollect that the radius is =≈</p><p>57'<hi rend="sup">2</hi>958∙    <hi rend="sub">a</hi>    .</p><p>This angular velocity will be a maximum wſhen the axis of rotation paſſes through the centre of gravity G. For draw ſrom any particle A the line A <hi rend="italic">a'</hi>  perpendicular to CG, and join AG. Then CA* = GA* -}-CG* →= 2 CG × G <hi rend="italic">α.</hi>  Therefore ∕C A<hi rend="sup">5</hi>  = ∕G A*+ ∕CG''±∕2 CG×Gff, =∕GA*+<hi rend="italic">Tn.</hi>  CG<hi rend="sup">;</hi>± <hi rend="italic">ſ</hi>  2 CG × G <hi rend="italic">a.</hi>  But, by the nature of the centre of gravity, the ſum of all the + G <hi rend="italic">α</hi>  is equal to that of all the — G <hi rend="italic">a</hi>  ; and therefore z±r<hi rend="sub">-</hi>∕ 2 GC X G<hi rend="italic">a</hi>  is nothing ; and therefore <hi rend="italic">ſ</hi>  CA’ ≈ <hi rend="italic">ſ</hi>  GA* -f∙ <hi rend="italic">tn </hi>. CG*.</p><p><hi rend="italic">„ <hi rend="sub">t</hi>, <hi rend="sub">η</hi> m</hi>. Gl. CP</p><p>Therefore/CA’or <hi rend="italic">fpR</hi>  is ſmalleſt, and -—<hi rend="italic">^Jp^f-</hi></p><p>is greateſt when <hi rend="italic">m .</hi>  CG’ is nothing, or when CG is nothing ; that is, when C and G coincide.</p><p>The abſolute quantity of motion in the whirling body, or the ſum of the motions of all its particles, is</p><p>rz.GI <hi rend="italic">.CV.fp.r <hi rend="sub">τ</hi>, <hi rend="sub">1    c λ</hi>  . <hi rend="sub">1</hi>  .</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">-<hi rend="sub">7</hi>r—.-</hi>. For the motion of each particle is</p><p><hi rend="italic">∕P <hi rend="sup">r</hi></hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">m .</hi>  GI. CP <hi rend="italic">.p r</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">fp r*</hi></p><p>The reſiſtance which a given quantity of matter makes to a motion of rotation is proportional to∕∕&gt; r*. For this muſt be meaſured by the forces which muſt be ſimilarly applied in order to give it the ſame angular <hi rend="sub">ι</hi> motion or angular velocity. Thus let one external , force be<hi rend="italic">m </hi>. GI, and the other <hi rend="italic">m .y∣—</hi>  Let both be applied at the diſtance CP. Let <hi rend="italic">r</hi>  be the radius vector in the one body, and p in the other ; now the angular</p><p>Tfl.GI CP <hi rend="sub">m</hi>.<hi rend="sub">γt</hi> .CP    <hi rend="sub">1</hi>, <hi rend="sub">r</hi></p><p>velocities —<hi rend="italic">~jffl</hi>— and <hi rend="italic">~fψ<hi rend="sub">f</hi>  i</hi>∏~ <hi rend="sup">are c</hi>ff<hi rend="sup">ual</hi>  ⅛<hi rend="sup">r iu</hi>PP<hi rend="sup">0</hi>'</p><p>ſition. Therefore <hi rend="italic">m </hi>. GI : <hi rend="italic">m . y ‘ ==ſp r<hi rend="sup">i</hi>  ;ſp P.</hi></p><p>As m the communication of motion to bodies in free ſpace a given force always produces the ſame quantity of motion; ſo in the communication of motion to bodies obliged to turn round axes, a given force, applied at a given diſtance from the axes, always produces the ſame quantity of momentum. Whence it χnay eaſily be deduced (and we ſhall do it afterwards), that as in the communication of motion among free bodies the ſame ■quantity of motion is preſerved, ſo in the communication of motion among whirling bodies the ſame quan-tity oſ whirling motion is preſerved.</p><p>This is a propoſition of the utmoſt importance in practical mechanics, and may indeed be conſidered as the fundamental propoſition with reſpect to all machines of the rotatory kind when performing work ; that is, of all machines which derive their efficacy from levers or wheels. There is a valuable ſet of experiments by Mr Smeaton in the Philoſophical Tranſactions, Volume LXVI. which fully confirm it. We ſhall give an example by and by of the utility of thc propoſition, ſhowing how exceedingly imperfect the uſual theories of mechanics are which do not proceed on this principle.</p><p>With reſpect to the general propoſition ſrom which all theſe deductions have been made, we muſt obſerve, that the demonſtration is not reſtricted to the time neceſſary for cauſing each particle to deſcribe an arch equal to the radius vector. We aſſumed the radius vector as the meaſure of the velocity merely to ſimpliſy the notation. Both the progreſſive motion of the free body and the rotation of the whirling body are uniformly accelerated, when we ſuppoſe the external force to act uniformly during any time whatever ; and the ſpaces deſcri-bed by each motion in the ſame time are in a confiant ratio. The formulæ may therefore with equal propriety repreſent the momentary accelerations in the different caſes.</p><p>It muſt alſo be obſerved, that it is not neceſſary to ſuppoie that all the particles of the body are in one plane, and that the moving force acts in a line FP lying alſo in this plane. This was tacitly allowed, merely to make the preſent inveſtigation (which is addreſſed chiefly to the practical mechanic) more familiar and eaſy. The equilibrium between the force A × CA, which is immediately urging the particle A, and the force <hi rend="italic">rn.G i</hi>  employed at P or F, in order to excite that force at A, would have been preciſely the ſame although the lines AC and FP had been in different planes, provided only that theſe planes were parallel. This is known ςo every perſon in the leaſt acquainted with the wheel and axle. But iſ the external moving force does not act in a plane parallel to the circles of rotation of the different particles, it muſt bç reſolved into two forces, one of which is perpendicular to theſe planes, or parallel to the axis of rotation, and the other lying in a plane of rotation. And it is this laſt only that we conſider as the moving force; the other tends merely to puſh the body in the direction of its axis, but has no tendency to turn it round that axis. When we come to conſider the rotation of a body perf ectly free, it will be neceſſary to attend particularly to this circumſtance. But there are ſeveral important mechanical propoſit.ons which do not require this.</p><p>The motion of any body is eſtimated by that of its centre of gravity, as is well known. '1 he difference between the motion of the centre of ,a free body and the motion of the centre of a body turning round an axis, is evidently owing to the connection which the parts of the body have with this axis, and to the action of the points of ſupport on this axis. This action muſt be conſidered as another <hi rend="italic">externat</hi>  force, combined with that which acts on the particle P, and therefore muſt be ſuch as, if combined with it, would produce the very motion which we obſerve. That is, if</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>