<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>eb03-r03</title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p><hi rend="italic">d!gnitate regali,</hi>  no man can marry a queen-dowager without ſpecial licence from the king, on pain of forfeiting his lands and goods. "This Sir Edward Coke tells us, was enacted in parliament in 6 Henry VI. though the ſtatute be not in print. But ſhe, though an alien born, ſhall ſtill be entitled to dower after the king’s demiſe, wſhich no other alien is. A queen-dowager when married again to a ſubject, doth not loſe her regal dignity,, as peereffes-dowager do wſhen they marry commoners. For Katharine, queen dowager of Henry V. though ſhe married a private gentleman, Owen ap Meredith ap Theodore, commonly called <hi rend="italic">Owen Tudor;</hi>  yet, by the name of <hi rend="italic">Katharine queen of England,</hi>  maintained an action againſt the biſhop of Carliſle. And ſo the dowager of Navarre marrying with Edmond the brother of king Edward I. maintained an action of dower by the name of <hi rend="italic">queen oſ Navarre.</hi></p><p>3.    The prince of Wales, or heir apparent to the crow<hi rend="sup">r</hi>n, and alſo his royal conſort, and the princeſs royal, or eldeſt daughter oſ the king, are likew<hi rend="sup">r</hi>ife peculiarly regarded by the laws. For, by ſtatute 2 ç Edw. III. to compaſs or conſpire the death of the former, or to violate the chaſtity of either of the latter, are as much high treaſon as to conſpire the death of the king, or violate the chaſtity of the queen. And this upon the ſame reaſon as was before given ; becauſe the prince of Wales is next in ſucceſſion to the erow<hi rend="sup">r</hi>11, and to violate his wife might taint the blood-royal with baſtardy ; and the eldeſt daughter of the king is alſo alone inheritable to the crown on failure of ilfue male, and therefore more reſpected by the laws than any of her younger fiſters ; rnſomuch that upon_ this, united with other (feodal) principles, while our military tenures were in force, the king might levy an aid for marrying his eldeſt daughter, and her only. The heir apparent to the crown is uſually made prince of Wales and earl of Cheſter, by ſpecial creation and inveſtiture ; but being the king’s eldeſt ſon, he is by inheritance duke of Cornwall, w<hi rend="sup">r</hi>ithout any new creation.</p><p>4.    The reſt of the royal family may be conſidered in two different lights, according to the different ſenſes in wſhich the term <hi rend="italic">royal family</hi>  is uſed. Ί lie larger ſenſe includes all thoſe who are by any pofſibility inheritable to the crown. Such, before the revolution, were all the deſeendants of William the Conqueror ; who had branched into an amazing extent by intermarriages w<hi rend="sup">,</hi>ith the ancient nobility. Since the revolution and act of ſettlement, it means the Proteſtant j iſſue of the princeſs Sophia 3 now comparatively few in number, but wſhich in proceſs of time may poſſibly be as largely diſſuſed. The more confined ſenſe includes only thoſe wſho are in a certain degree of propinquity to the reigning prince, and to whom therefore the law pays an extraordinary regard and relpect ; but after that degree is paſt, they fall into the rank of ordinary ſubjects, and are ſeldom conſidered any farther, unleſs, called to the ſucceſſion upon failure of the nearer lines. For though collateral conſanguinity is regarded indefinitely with reſpect to inheritance or ſueceſſion, yet it is and can only be regarded within ſome certain limits in any other reſpect, by the natural conſtitution of things and the dictates of pofitive law<hi rend="sup">r</hi>.</p><p>The vounger fons∙ and daughters of the king, and</p><p>other branches or the royal family, who are not in the immediate line of ſucceſſion, were therefore little farther regarded by the ancient law, than to give them a certain degree of precedence before all peers and public officers as vzell ecclefiaſtical as temporal. This is done by the ſtatute 31 Henry VIII. c. 10. which enacts, that no perfon except the king’s children ſhall preſume to fix or have place at the fide of the cloth of eſtate in the parliament chamber ; and that certain great officers therein named ſhall have precedence above all dukes, except only ſuch as ſhall happen to be the king’s ſon, brother, uncle, nephew (wſhich Sir Edward Coke explains to fignify grandſon or <hi rend="italic">nePos),</hi>  or brother’s or filler’s ſon. But under the deſeription of the king’s <hi rend="italic">children,</hi>  his <hi rend="italic">grandſons</hi>  are held to be included, without having recourſe to Sir Edward Coke’s interpretation of <hi rend="italic">nephew ;</hi>  and. therefore when his late majeſty king George II. created his grandſon Edward, the ſecond ſon of Frederick prince of Wale« deceaſed, duke of York, and referred it to the houſe of lords to fettle his place and precedence, they certified that he ought to have precedence next to the late duke of Cumberland, the then king’s youngeſt ſon ; and that he might have a ſeat on the left hand oſ the cloth of eſtate. But when, on the acceſſion of his preſent majefty<hi rend="sub">r </hi>theſe royal perſonages ceaſed to take place as the<hi rend="italic">children,</hi>  and ranked only as the <hi rend="italic">brother</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">uncle</hi>  of the king, they alſo left their ſeats on the fide of the cloth of eſtate ; ſo that wſhen the duke of Glouceſter, his majeſty’s ſecond brother, took his ſeat in the houſe of peers, he was placed on the upper end of the earls bench (on which the dukes uſually fit) next to his royal highneſs the duke of York. And in 1717, upon a queſtion referred to all the judges by king George 1. it w<hi rend="sup">,</hi>as reſolved, by the opinion of ten againſt the other two, that the education and care of all the king’s grandchildren, while minors, did belong of right to his majeſty as king of this realm, even during their father’s life. But they all agreed, that the care and approbation of their marriages, wſhen grown up, belonged to the king their grandfather. And the judges have more recently concurred in opinion, that this care and approbation extend alſo to the preſumptive heir of the crown; though to wſhat other branches oſ the royal family the ſame did extend, they did not find preciſely determined. The moſt frequent inſtances of the crown’s interpofition go no farther than nephews and nieces ; but examples are not w<hi rend="sup">,</hi>anting of its reaching to more diftant collaterals. And the ſtatute 6 Henry VI. before mentioned, which prohibits the marriage of a queen-dovzager without the conſent of the king, aſſigns this reaſon for it ; “ becauſe the diſparagement of the c,ueen ſhall give greater comfort and example to other ladies of eſtate, wſho are of the blood-royal, more lightly to diſparage themſelves.” Therefore by the ſtatute 28 Hen. VIII. c. ’8. (repealed, among other ſtatutes of treaſons, by 1 Edw. VI. c. 12.)· it was made high treaſon for any man to contract marriage with the king’s children or reputed children·, his fiſters or aunts <hi rend="italic">ex parte βaterna,</hi>  or the children of his brethren or fillers ; being exactly the fame degrees?to which precedence is allowed by the ſtatute 31 Hen. VIII. before-mentioned And now, by ſtatute 12 Geo. III. c. ιr. no deſeendant of the body of king George II. (other than the iffiιe of prin-ceiſes married into foreign families) is capable of con-</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>