<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>eb03-r03</title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>honey, by which the peaſant is oſten enriched. He cuts down a great number of trees in the foreſt, and ſawing the trunks into a number of parts, bores each of theſe, and ſtops up the hollow at both~eπds, leaving only a little hole for the admittance of the bees ; thus the honey is ſecured from all the attempts of the bear, who is extremely fond of it, and tries many different experiments for making himſelf maſter of the luſcious treaſure.— Of this honey the Ruffians make a great quantity of ſtrong metheglin for their ordinary drink. They likewiſe extract from rye a ſpirit, which they prefer to brandy.</p><p>The wild beaſts in the northern part of Ruſſia are the ſame with thoſe we have mentioned in the articles of Norway and Lapland : ſuch as rein-deer, bears, foxes, ermins, martens, fables, hares, and ſquirrels In the more ſouthern provinces the Muſcovites breed black cattle, ſmall but hardy horſes, ſheep, goats, and camels. The breed of cattle and horſes has been enlarged by the care and under the protection of Peter and ſuc-eeeding fovereigns. The whole empire abounds with wild-fowl and game of all forts, and a variety of birds of prey ; beſides the different kinds of poultry, which are raiſed in this as well as in other countries. The external parts and provinces of Muſcovy are well ſupplied with’ſea-fiſh from the Northern ocean, the Baltic, or gulph of Finland, the White ſea, the Black ſea, and the Caſpian ; but the whole empire is plentifully provided with freſh-water fiſh ſrom the numerous lakes and rivers, yielding immenſe quantities of ſalinon, trout, pike, ſturgeon, and belluga : the laſt being a large fiſh, of whoſe roe the beſt caviare is made. Innumerable infects, like thoſe of Lapland, are hatched by the ſummer’s heat in the fand, moraſſes, and foreſts, with which this empire abounds ; and are ſo troubleſome as to render great part of the country altogether uninhabitable.</p><p>The Ruſſian empire is inhabited by no leſs than 16 different nations, of which our limits will hardly permit us to give the names. The firſt are the Sclavonic nations, comprehending the Ruffians, who are the predo∙ minant inhabitants of the whole empire, and the Poles, who beſides occupying the countries lately wreſted from the republic, lire in the governments of Polatſk and Moghilev, as well as in the diſtrict of Salcnghinlk and along the river Irtiſh. 2. The Germanic nations,, comprehending the Germans properly ſo called, who inhabit Eſthonia and Livonia ; the Swedes inhabiting the Ruſſian Finland, as well as ſome of the iſlands on the Baltic ſea ; and the Danes, who inhabit the iſlands of the Baltic ſea, the Worms, and Groſs or Great Roge. 3. The Lettonian or Livonian nations, under which are claſſed the original or real Lettonians or Letiſhr, inhabiting Livonia ; and the Lithuanians, who live in the government of Polatſk and Moghilev. 4. The Finns, or Tchudi, nations who inhabit the governments of Viberg and St Peterſhurgh,. with many other diſtricts of the empire, being branched out into no fewer than 12 different tribes. 5. The Tartarian nations, who are all either Mahometans or idolaters. The Mahometan Tartars, commonly called by the Ruffians <hi rend="italic">Tartars, </hi>dwell in Kazane, and the places adjacent; at Keſimov; at Ouſe, in the government of Parma ; at Tomſk and its neighbourhood, and are in general a ſober, induſtri-ous, cleanly, and generous people. The other Tartars inhabit different parts of Siberia, and arc intermixed with ſtill different races, called after the towns, rivers, and other places to which their habitations are neareſt.— They are, as we have ſaid, idolaters, and governed by ſhamens. (See Shλmen.) Beſides theſe, there are in the Ruſſian dominions the Nagay Tartars ; the Crim-Tartars, inhabiting the Crimea, who, together with the land belonging to them, came under the ſubjection oſ Ruſſia in 1783; the Meſclieraki; the Baſhkirs ; the Kirghiſtzi or Kirghisſkaifaks ; theYakouti; and the white Kalmuks. 6. The Caucaſian nations, which are ſix in number, and are each ſubdivided into many<hi rend="sup">r</hi>  different tribes, of which it is probable that few of our readers have ever heard the names, except of the Circaſe fians, who live in different ſettlements bordering on the river Kubane. 7. The Samoyeds or Samoeds, comprehending the Oſtiacks *. Ί heſe inhabit the nυrthern-moſt part of Ruſſia, along the coaſt of the Icy ſea.— 8. The Mungalian nations, comprehending the original Muπgals, who are chiefly diſperſed in the deſerts of Gobey ; the Bourati, who live on the banks of the Baikal, and other places in the government of Irkoutſk ; and the Kalmuks, conſiſting of four different tribes.— All theſe hordes ſpeak the Mungalian language, obſerve the religion of Lama and the Kalmuks live in large tents. 9. The Tongooſi, a very populous tribe, diſe perſed from the river Eniffey as far as the ſea of Ok-hotſk, and from the Penjinſkaya Gooba beyond the Chineſe frontier. They are all idolaters, and live by hunting and fiſhing. 10. The Kamtchadels. xι. The Koriaki. 12. The Kouriltzi. Of theſe three nations we have given ſome account under the article Kamtschatka. 13. The Aleouti, who dwell in the iſlands between Siberia and America, and very much reſemble the Eſquimaux and the inhabitants of Greenland.— They live in large huts, and ſeem to be idolaters.— 14. The Ariπtzi, a very numerous people ſcattered in the government oſ Kolhivane. 15. The Yukaghiri, Who are diſperſed on the coaſts of the Glacial ſea, about the rivers Vana, Kolhima, and Lena, and as far as the ſource of the Anadir. 16. The Tchouktchi, wſho occupy the north-eaſtern part of Siberia, between the rivers Kolhima and Anadir. Beſides theſe ſixteen different nations, there are ſcattered through the Ruffian empire vaſt numbers of Buckharian Tartars, Perfians, Georgians, Indians, Greeks, Servians, Albanians, Bulgarians, Moldavians, Valekians, Armenians, and Jews.</p><p>The empire of Ruſſia is ſo widely extended, that notwithſtanding the number of nations which it comprehends, it muſt be conſidered as by no means populous. At the laſt reviſion it was found to contain 26. millions, of ſouls ; but it is to be obſerved, that the nobility, clergy, land as well as ſea forces, different officers, ſervants belonging to the court, perſons employed under government in civil and other offices ; the ſtudents of different univerſities, academies, ſeminaries, and other ſchools ; hoſpitals of different denominations ; likewiſe all the irregular troops, the roving hordes of different tribes, foreigners and coloniſts, or ſettlers oſ different nations— are not included in the above-mentioned number : but with the addition of all theſe, the population of Ruſſia, of both ſexes, may be ſuppoſed to come near to 28 millions-</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>