<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>eb03-r03</title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>found in every part of this country. The valleys, or ſtraths, are generally covered with wood ; and near Al-frag there are foreſts of fir ιy ôr 20 miles in length, well ſtocked with deer and game of all forts. Great numbers of black cattle, horſes flιeep, and goats, are fed upon the mountains ; and the ſea, rivers, and lakes, teem with fiſh and fowl. The lochs on the weſtern coaſt abound with herrings in the ſeaſon, particularly Loch Eu, about nine miles long, and three in breadth ; one part of this is formed by a bay, or inlet of the ſea ; and the other is a lake of freſh water. The Tides of it are covered with wood, where formerly abundance of iron was ſmelted. Though the middle part of Roſs, called <hi rend="italic">Ardroſs,</hi>  is mountainous and ſcarce inhabited, the north-eaſt parts on the rivers Okel, Charron, and Frith of Tayne, are fruitful, and abound with villages. Coygach and Aſsgut, two northerly diſtricts, are bare and hilly ; yet they abound with deer and black cattle; and we ſee ſeveral good houſes towards the coaſt, where there are alſo promontories, and huge r0ck3 of marble. Ardmeanach part of the peninſula betwixt the bays cf Cromarty and Murray, is a barony, which of old be owed a title on the king of Scotland’s ſecond ſon. The di rict of Glen-elchig, on the ſouth-we ‘, as the paternal e '.ate of the earl of Seafo th, chief of the clan of Mackenzie : but the la I earl of that name, having riſen in rebellion, was in the year 1719 defeated at Glen-ihiel, in th∣s very quarter, together with a ſmall body of Spaniards by whom he had been joined. His auxiliaries were taken ; and though he himſelf, with ſome of his friends, eſeaped to the continent, his e <hi rend="sup">ι</hi>ate and honours were forfeited. At the ſame time, the king’s troops, who obtained this victory, diſmantled the caſtle of Yion donnen, ſituated on an iſland in a bay that fronts the ifle of Sky. It belonged to the crown ; but the office of hereditary governor was<hi rend="italic">ve'</hi>  ed in the earl of Seaforth, and here he had erected his magazine. Roſs is chiefly peopled by the Mackenzies and Fraſers, two warlike clans, who ſpeak Erſe, and live in the Highland faſhion. There are fiſheries carried on along the coa<hi rend="sup">ι</hi>' ; but their chief traffic is with ſſieep and black cattle. The chief towns of Roſs are Channerie, Dingwall, Tayne, and Fortroſe.</p><p>ROSSANO, a ſtrong town of Italy, in the kingdom βf Naples, and in the Hither Calabria, with an archbi-ſhop’s ſee, and the title of a principality. It is pretty large, well peopled, and ſeated on an eminence ſurrounded with rocks. There is nothing in this archiepiſco-pal city that claims much notice ; the buildings are mean, the ſtreets vilely paved and contrived. The number of inhabitants does not exceed 6000, wſho ſubſiſt by the ſale of their oil, the principal object of their attention, though the territory produces a great deal of good wine and corn.</p><p>Roffano probably owes its origin to the Roman emperors, who conſidered it as a poll equally valuable for ſtrength and convenience of traffic. The Marfans, a family of French extraction, poffeffed this territory, with the title of prince, from the time of Charles II. to that of Alphonſus II. when the laſt male heir was, by that prince’s order, put to death in Iſchia, where he</p><p>was confined for treaſon. It afterwards belonged to ∙ ∙ <hi rend="sup">o</hi></p><p>Bona, queen of Poland, in right of her mother Iſabella, daughter to Alphonſus II. and at her deceaſe returned &lt;0 the crown. It was next in the poſſeſſion of the Al-</p><p>dobrandini, from whom the Borgheſi inherited it. So late as the 16th century, the inhabitants of this city ſpoke the Greek language, and followed the rites of the eaſtern church. Here was formerly the moſt celebrated rendezvous of the Bafilian monks in Magna Graecia. E. Long. 16. 52. N. Lat. 39. 45.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">ROS-solis, </hi><hi rend="italic">Sun-devυ,</hi>  an agreeable ſpirituous liquor, compoſed of burnt brandy, ſugar, cinnamon, and milk-water ; and ſometimes perfumed with a little mulk. It has its name from being at firſt prepared wholly of the juice of the plant ros ſolis, or droſera. See Drosera.</p><p>ROSTOCK, a town of Germany, in the circle of Upper Saxony, and duchy of Mecklenburg, with an univerfity and a very good harbour. It is the beſt town in this country; and has good fortifications, with an arſenal. The duke has a ſtrong caſtle, which may be looked upon as a citadel It is divided into three parts, the Old, the New’, and the Middle Towns. It was formerly one of the Hanſeatic towns, and is ſtill Imperial, under the protection of the duke of Mecklenburg. It is ſeated on a lake where the river Varne falls into it, and carries large boats. The government is in the hands of 24 aldermen, elected out of the nobility, univerfity, and principal merchants ; four of whom are burgomaſters, two chamberlains, twβ ſtewards for the river, and two judges of civil and criminal matters. Theſe 24 are called the Upper Houſe, and have in a manner the whole executive power lodged in them, with the power of coining money, and elect⅛g officers. There is alſo a common council of 100 inferior citizens, who are ſummoned to give their advice upon extraordinary emergencies relating to the whole community. The principal things worth ſeeing are the fortifications, the prince’s palace, the ſtadthouie, the arſenal, and the public library. The town is famous for good beer, wſhich they export in great quantities. Some years ago they had no leſs than 250 privileged brcwers, who, it is ſaid, brewed ſo many thouſand tuns a year, befides wſhat particular perſons brew for their own uſe. E. Long, j 2. 55. N. Lat. 54. 8.</p><p>ROSTOFF, or Rosτow, a large town of the Ruffian empire, and capital of a territory of the ſame name, w<hi rend="sup">,</hi>ith an archbiſhop’s ſee, ſeated on the lake Coteri, in E. Long. 40. 25. N. Lat. 57. I he duchy of Roſ-toff is bounded on the north by Jaroſlow, on the eaſt by Sutdal, on the ſouth by the duchy of Moi’cow, and on the weft by that of Tuere.</p><p>ROSTRA, in antiquity, a part of the Roman forum, wherein orations, pleadings, funeral harangues, &amp;c. were delivered</p><p>ROSTRUM, literally denotes the beak or bill of a bird ; and hence it has been figuratively applied to the beak or head of a ſſiip.</p><p>ROSYCRUCIANS. See Rosicrucians.</p><p>ROT, a very fatal diſeaſe incident to ſheep, arifing from wet<hi rend="sub">t</hi>feafυns, and too moiſt paſture. It is very difficult of cure, and is attended with the fingular cir-cumſtance of a kind of animals being found in the blood-veffels∙ See Ovιs and Sheep.</p><p>ROTA, the nameol an ecclefiaſtical court of Rome, compoſed of 12 prelates, of whom one muſt be a Gelman, another a Frenchman, and two Spaniards ; the other eight are Italians, three of whom muſt be Romans, and the other five a Bologneſe, a Ferraran, a Milaneſe, a Venetian, and a Tuſcan.—This is one of</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>