<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>eb03-r03</title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>opinions have been entertained, which we have noticed <hi rend="sup">l</hi>'elfewhere. They ſeem now to be almoſt forgotten. See</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Chatterton.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Rowley (William), who ſtands in the third claſs of dramatic writers, lived in the reign of king Charles I. and received his education at the univerfity of Cambridge ; but vhether he took any degree there, is not evident ; there being but few particulars preſerved in regard to him more than his cloſe intimacy and connection with all the principal wits and poetical geniuſes of that age, by whom he was well beloved, and with ſome of whom he joined in their writings. Wood ftyles him </hi><hi rend="sup">tt</hi>  the ornament, for wit and ingenuity, of Pembroke-hall in Cambridge.” In a word, he was a very great benefactor to the Engliſh ſtage, having, exclufive of his aid lent to Middleton, Day, Hey wood, Webſter, &amp;c. left us five plays of his own compofing, and one in which even the immortal Shakeſpeare afforded him ſome aſ-ſiſtance.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">ROXBURGH-shire, or Teviotdale, a county of Scotland, deriving its name from the town of Roxburgh, which is now deſtroyed, and the river Teviot, that runs through the ſhire into the Tweed, is divided into the three diſtricts of </hi><hi rend="italic">Teviotdale, Liddiβdale,</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">Eβdale,</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">Euſdale,</hi>  ſo called from their refpective rivers, Teviot, IAddal, and Eſk. It is bounded on the eaſt and ſouth-eaſt by Northumberland and Cumberland, on the ſouth and ſouth-weſt by Annandale, on the weſt by Tweeddale, on the north by the Merſe and Lauderdale; extending about 30 miles from eaſt t© weſt, and about 15 in breadth from the border of England to the Blue Cairn in Lauder-moor. The ſhire exhibits a rough irregular appearance of hills, moffes, and mountains, interſperſed, however, with narrow valleys, and watered with delightful ſtreams. Though the face of the country is bare of woods, the valleys yield plenty of corn, and the hills abound with paſture for ſheep and black cattle. The principal mountains of this country are known by the name of <hi rend="italic">Cockraw :</hi>  from whence a range of very high hills runs weſtward, dividing Scotland from England. On the confines of this ſhire are the debateable lands ; the property of which was formerly diſputed by the Scots and Engliſh borderers, but adjudged to the Scots at the union of the crowns.— Roxburghſhiie yields plenty of lime and freeſtone, which in former times was freely uſed by the inhabitants in building cattles to defend them from the invafions of their Engliſh neighbours. The moſt diſtinguiſhed families in this county are the Scots and Kers, who raiſed themſelves to wealth and honours by their bravery and ſucceſs in a fort of predatory war with their enemies of South Britain. The ſhire is very populous ; and the people are ſtout and valiant. They were formerly inured to military diſeipline and all the dangers of war, by living on dry marches contiguous to thoſe of England ; being ſo numerous and alert, that this and the neighbouring ſhire of Berwick could in 24 hours produce ιo,ooo men on horſeback, well armed and accoutred. In the ſhire of Roxburgh we ſtill meet with a great number of old caſtles and ſeats belonging to private gentlemen, whoſe anceſtors fignalized themſelves</p><p>in this manner ; and we find the remains of old encampments, and a Roman military way, vulgarly called the <hi rend="italic">cauſewny,</hi>  rιmning from Haunυm to the Tweed. The principal town, called <hi rend="italic">Roxburgh,</hi>  giving the title of</p><p><hi rend="italic">duke</hi>  to the chief of the Kers, was anciently a royal borough, containing divers pariſhes, large and fiouriſhing, defended by a ſtrong citadel, which was often alternately reduced by the Engliſh and Scotch adventurers. It was in befieging this caſtle that James II. of Scotland loſt his life by the burſting of a cannon. In conſequence of the almoſt continual wars between the two. nations, this fortreſs was razed, the town ruined, and its royalty tranflated to Jedburgh, which is now a royal borough, ſituated between the Tefy and Jed.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">ROXENT-cape, or </hi><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps">Rock oſLiſbon,</hi></hi>  a mountain and remarkable promontory in Portugal, fituated in the Atlantic ocean, at the north entrance of the Tagus, 22 miles north of Liſhon.</p><p>ROYAL, fomething belonging to a king : thus we ſay, royal family, royal affent, royal exchange, &amp;c.</p><p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps">Roυal Family.</hi></hi>  The firſt and moſt conſiderable branch of the king’s royal family, regarded by the laws of England, is the queen.</p><p>I. The queen of England is either queen <hi rend="italic">regent, </hi>queen <hi rend="italic">conſort,</hi>  or queen <hi rend="italic">dowager.</hi>  The queen <hi rend="italic">regent,, regnant,</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">ſovereign,</hi>  is ſhe who holds the crown in her own right ; as the firſt (and perhaps the ſecond) queen Mary, queen Eliſabeth, and queen Anne ; and ſuch a one has the ſame powers, prerogatives, rights», dignities, and duties, as if ſhe had been a king. This-is expreſsly declared by ſtatute I Mar. I. ſt. 3. c. I. But the queen <hi rend="italic">conſort</hi>  is the wife of the reigning king ; and ſhe by virtue of her marriage is participant of divers prerogatives above other women.</p><p>And, firſt, ſhe is a public perſon, exempt and diſtinct from the king ; and not, like other married women», ſo cloſely connected as to have loſt all legal or ſeparate exiſtence ſo long as the marriage continues. For the queen is of ability to purchaſe lands and to convey them, to make leaſes, to grant copyholds, and do other acts of ownerſhip, without the concurrence of her lord ; which no other married woman can do : a privilege as old as the Saxon era. She is alſo capable of taking a grant from the king, which no other wife is from her huſhand ; and in this particular ſhe agrees with the <hi rend="italic">au-guβa</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">piiſjima regina coηjux divi imperatoris</hi>  of the Roman laws ; who, according to Juſtinian, was equally capable of making a grant to, and receiving one from, the emperor. The queen of England hath ſeparate courts and officers diſtinct from the king’s, not only in matters of ceremony, but even of law ; and her attorney and ſolicitor general are entitled to a place within the bar of his majeſty’s courts, together with the king’s counſel. She may likewiſe ſue and be ſued alone, without joining her huſhand. She may alſo have a ſeparate property in goods as well as lands, and ha3 a right to diſpoſe of them by will. In ſhort, ſhe is in all legal proceedings looked upon as a feme ſole, and not as a feme covert ; as a fingle, not as a married woman. For which the reaſon given by Sir Edward Cok⅛ is this : becauſe the wiſdom of the common law would not have the king (whoſe continual care and ſtudy is for the public, and <hi rend="italic">circa ardua regpi')</hi>  to be troubled and diſquieted on account of his wife’s domeſtic affairs ; and therefore it veſts in the queen a power of tranſacting her own concerns, without, the intervention of the king, as if ſhe vf⅛5 an unmarried woman.</p><p>The queen hath alſo many exemptions, and minute prerogatives. For inſtance : ſhe pays no toll ; nor is</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>