<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>eb03-r03</title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>returned to Bruſſels, and thence paffed over into Eng-' land in 1630 with a commiſſion from the Catholic king to negociate a peace between the two crowns. He was ſucceſsful in his negociation, and a treaty was concluded. Charles I. who then filled the Britiſh throne, could not receive Rubens in a public character on ac* count of his proſeſſion ; nevertheleſs, he treated him with every mark of reſpect. Having engaged him to paint ſome of the apartments of Whitehall, he not only gave him a handſome ſum of money, but, as an acknowledgment of his merit, created him a knight ; and the duke of Buckingham, his friend and patron, purchaſed</p><p>of him a collection of pictures, ſtatues, medals, and antiques, with the ſum ©f L. 10,000.</p><p>He returned to Spain, where be was magnificently honoured and rewarded for his ſervices. He was created a gentleman of ⅛the king’s bedchamber, and named ſecretary to the council of ſtate in the Netherlands. Rubens, however, did not lay aſide his proſeſſion. He returned to Antwerp, where he married a ſecond wife called <hi rend="italic">Helena Forment,</hi>  who, being an eminent beauty, helped him much in the figures of his women. He died on 30th May 1640, in the 63d year of his age ; leaving vaſt riches to his children. Albert his eldeſt ſon ſucceeded him in the office of ſecretary of ſtate in Flan-ders.</p><p>As Rubens was poſſeſſed of all the ornaments and advantages that render a man worthy to be eſteemed or courted, he was always treated as a perſon of conſequence. His figure was noble, his manners engaging, and his converſation lively ; his learning was univerſal. Though his favourite ſtudy muſt have occupied him much, yet he found time to read the works of the moſt celebrated authors, and eſpecially the poets. He ſpoke ſeveral languages perfectly, and was an excellent ſtates-man.</p><p>His houſe at Antwerp was enriched with everything in the arts that was rare and valuable. It contained one ſpacious apartment, in imitation of the rotunda at Rome, adorned with a choice collection of pictures which he had purchaſed in Italy; part of which he fold to the duke of Buckingham.</p><p>His genius qualified him to excel equally in every thing that can enter into the compoſition of a picture. His invention was ſo fertile, that, if he had occaſion to paint the ſame ſubject ſeveral times, his imagination always ſupplied him with ſomething ſtriking and new. The attitudes of his figures are natural and varied, the carriage of the head is peculiarly graceful, and his ex-preffion noble and animated.</p><p>He is by all allowed to have carried the art of colouring to its higheſt pitch; he underſtood ſo thoroughly the true principles of the chiaro-ſcuro, that he gave to his figures the utmoſt harmony, and a prominence reſembling real life. His pencil is mellowed, his ſtrokes bold and eaſy, his carnation glows with life, and his drapery is ſimple, but grand, broad, and hung with much ſkill.</p><p>The great excellence of Rubens appears in his grand compoſitions; for as they are to be viewed at a diſtance, he laid on a proper body of colours with uncommon boldneſs, and fixed all his tints in their proper places ; ſo that he never impaired their luſtre by breaking or torturing them ; but touched them in ſuch a manner as to give them a laſting force, beauty, and harmony.</p><p>It is generally allowed, that Rubens wanted correct-</p><p>neſs in drawing and deſigning ; ſome of his figures being heavy and too ſhort, and the limbs in ſome parts not being juſtly ſketched in the outline. Though he had ſpent ſeven years in Italy in ſtudying thoſe antiques by which other celebrated artiſts had modelled their taſte; though he had examined them with ſuch minute attention as not only to perceive their beauties, but to be qualified to deſcribe them in a Diſſertation which he wrote on that ſubject : yet he ſeems never to have diverted htm-ielſ oſ that heavy ſtyle of painting, which, being pe-culiar to his native country, he had inſenfibly acquired. The aſtoniſhing rapidity too with which he painted, made him fall into inaccuracies, from which thoſe works that he ſiniſhed with care are entirely exempted.</p><p>Among his finiſhed pieces may be mentioned the Crucifixion of Jeſus Chriſt between the two Thieves, which was very lately to be ſeen at Antwerp·; but of all his works the. paintings in the palace^of Luxemburg beſt diſplay his genius and his ſtyle.</p><p>It is the obſervation of Algarotti, that he was more moderate in his movements than Tintoretto, and more ſoft in his chiaro-ſcuro than Carravaggio ; but not ſo rich in his compoſitions, nor ſo light in his touches, as Paolo Veroneſe ; in his carnations leſs true than Titian, and leſs delicate than Vandyck. Yet he contrived to give his colours the utmoſt tranſparency and harmony, notwithſtanding the extraordinary deepneſs of them ; and he had a ſtrength and grandeur of ſtyle entirely his own.</p><p>RUBIA, madder : A genus of the monogynia order, belonging to the tetrandria claſs of plants ; and in the natural method ranking under the 47th order, <hi rend="italic">Stellate</hi>  The corolla is monopetalous and campanulated; and there are two monoſpermous berries. There are three ſpecies, of which the moſt remarkable is the tinc-torum, or dyer’s madder, ſo much uſed by the dyer’s and callico-printers. This hath a perennial root and annual ſtalk: the root is compoſed of many long, thick, ſucculent fibres, almoſt as large as a man’s little finger; theſe are joined at the top in a head like aſparagus, and run very deep into the ground. From the upper part, or head of the root, come out many ſide-roots, which extend juſt under the ſurface of the ground to a great diſtance, whereby it propagates very faſt ; for theſe ſend up a great number of ſhoots, which, if carefully taken off in the ſpring ſoon after they are above ground, become ſo many plants. Theſe roots are of a reddiſh colour, ſomewhat tranſparent ; and have a yel-lowiſh pith in the middle, which is tough and of a bit-teriſh taſte. From this root ariſe many’ large four-cornered jointed ſtalks, which, in good land, wall grow live or ſix feet long, and, if ſupported, ſometimes ſeven or eight: they are armed with ſhort herbaceous prickles; and at each joint are placed five or ſix ſpear-ſhaped leaves: their upper ſurfaces are ſmooth: but their midrib on the under ſide is armed with rough herbaceous ſpines, and the leaves fit cloſe to the branches in whorls. From the joints of the ſtalk come out the branches, wſhich ſuſtain the flowers : they .are placed by pairs oppoſite ; each pair croffing the other : theſe have a few ſmall leaves towaιd the bottom, which are by threes, and upwards by pairs oppoſite : the branches are terminated by looſe branching ſpikes of yellow flowers, which are cut into four parts reſembling ſtars. Theſe appear in June, and are ſometimes ſucceeded by ſeeds,</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>