<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>eb03-r03</title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>has been already obſerved ; and the operation of uniting them with a permanent twiſt is called <hi rend="italic">laying</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">doling, </hi>ſthe latter term being chiefly appropriated to cables and other very large cordage.</p><p><hi rend="sup">n</hi> Lines and cordage leſs than 1J inches circumference are laid at the ſpinning-wheel. The workman fattens the ends of eachof two or three yarns to ſeparatewhirl-lrooks. The remote ends are united in a knot. This is put on one of the hooks of a ſwivel called the<hi rend="italic">loper,</hi>  repreſent-ed in fig. 6. and care is taken that the yarns are of equal lengths and twiſt. A piece of ſoft cord is put on the other hook of the loper ; and, being put over a pulley ſeveral feet from the ground, a weight is hung on it, which ſtretches the yarn. When the workman ſees that they are equally ſtretched, he orders the wheel to be turned in the ſame direction as when twining the yarns. This would twine them harder ; but the ſwivel of the loper gives way to the ſtrain, and the yarns immediately twiſt around each other, and form a lſne or cord. In doing this the yarns lofe their twiſt. This is reſtored by the wheel. But this ſimple operation would make a very bad line, which wς&gt;uld be flack, and would not hold its twiſt ; for, by the turning of the loper, the ſtrands twiſt immediately together, to a great diſtance from the loper. By this turning of the loper the yarns are untwiſted. The wheel reſtores their twiſt only to that part of the yarns that remains feparate from the others, but cannot do it in that part where they are already twined round each other, be-ςaufe their mutual preſſure prevents the twiſt from advancing. It is, therefore, neceſſary to retard this tendency to twine, by keeping the yams apart. This is done by a little tool called the top, repreſented in fig. 7.</p><p>It is a truncated cone, having three or more, notches along its ſides, and a handle called the. ſtaſſi This is put between the ſtrands, the ſmall end next the loper, and it is preſſed gently into the angle formed by the yarns which lie in the notches. The wheel being now turned, the yarns are more twiſted, or <hi rend="italic">hardened up,</hi>  and their preſſure on the top gives it a ſtrong tendency to come out oſ the angle, and alſo to turn round. The workman does not allow this till he thinks the yarns ſuſſiciently hardened. Then he yields to the preſſure, and the top comes away from the ſwivel, which immediately turns round, and the line begins ta lay.— Gradually yielding to this preſſure, the workman flowly comes up towards the wheel, and the laying goes on, till the top is at laſt cloſe to the wheel, and the work is done. In the mean time, the yarns are ſhortened, both by the twining of each and the laying of the cord. The weight, therefore, gradually riſes. The uſe of this weight is evidently to oblige the yarn to take a proper degree of twiſt, and not run into kinks.</p><p>A cord or line made in this way has always ſome tendency to twiſt.a little more. However little friction there may be in the loper, there is ſome, ſo that the turns which the cord has made in the laying are not enough to balance completely the elaſticity of the yams; and the weight being appended cauſes the ſtrands to be more nearly in the direction of the axis, in the ſame manner as it would ſtretch and untwiſt a little any rope to which it is hung. On the whole, however, the twiſt</p><p>of a laid line is permanent, and not like that upon thread doubled or thrown in a mill, which remains only</p><p>in conſequence of the great ſoſtneſs and flexibility oſ the yarn.</p><p>The proceſs for laying or cloſing large cordage is conſiderably different from this. The ſtrands of which the rope is compoſed conſiſt of many yarns, and re-quire a conſiderable degree of hardening. This cannot be done by a whirl driven by a wheel-band"; it requires the power of a crank turned by the hand. The ſtrands, when properly hardened, become very ſtiff, and when bent round the top are not able to tranſmit force enough for laying the heavy and unpliant rope which forms beyond it. The elaſtic twiſt of the hardened ſtrands muſt, therefore, be aſſiſted ,by an external force. All this requires a different machinery. and a different proceſs.</p><p>- At the upper end of the walk is fixed up the <hi rend="italic">tackle, board,</hi>  fig. 8. This conflits of a ſtrong oaken plank called a <hi rend="italic">breaβ board,</hi>  having tlpee or more holes in it, ſuch as A, B, C, fitted with braſs or iron plates. Into theſe are put iron cranks, called heavers, which have hooks, or forelocks, and keys, on the ends of their ſpindies. They are placed at ſuch a diſtance front each other, that the workmen do not interfere with each other while turning them round. This breaſt-board is fixed to the top of ſtrong poſts well ſecured by ſtruts or braces facing the lower end of the walk. At the lower end is another breaſt-board fixed to the upright poſts of a fledge, which may be loaded with ſtones or other weights. Similar cranks are placed in the holes of this breaſt-board. The whole goes by the name of <hi rend="italic">fledge ;</hi>  (ſee fig. 9.) The top neceſſary for cloſing large cordage is too heavy to be held in the hand. It therefore has a long ſtaff, which has a truck on the end. This reſts on the ground ; but even this is not enough in laying great cables. The top muſt be ſupported on a carriage, as ſhown in fig. 10. where it muſt lie. very ſteady, and netd no attendance, becauſe the matter workman has ſuſſicient employment in attending to the manner in which the ſtrands cloſe behind the top, and in helping them by various methods. The top is, therefore, fixed to the carriage by laſhing its ſtaff to the two upright poſts. A piece of ſoft rope, or ſtrap, is attached to the handle of the top by the middle, and its two ends are brought back and wrapped ſeveral times tight round the rope, in the direction of its twiſt, and bound down. This is ſhown at W, and it greatly aſ-ſiſts the laying of the rope by its friction. This both keeps the top from flying too far from the point of union of the ſtrands, and brings the ſtrands more regularly into their places.</p><p>The firſt operation is <hi rend="italic">warping</hi>  the yarns. At each end of the walk are frames called warping frames, which carry a great number of reels or winches filled with rope-yarn. The foreman of the walk takes off a yarn end from each, till he has made up the number neceſſary for his rope or ſtrand, and bringing the ends together, he paſſes the whole through an iron ring fixed to the top of a flake driven into the ground, and draws them through : then a knot is tied on the end of the bundle, and a workman pulls it through this ring till &gt; the intended length is drawn off the reels. The end is made faſt at the bottom of the walk, or at the fledge, and the foreman comes back along the ſkain of yarns, , to ſee that none are hanging flacker than the reſt. Ha</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>