<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>eb03-r03</title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>t leaves among the ſpikes of flowcrs to the top. The flowers ſtand upon ſlender footſtalks, which are reflexed; tſhey are of an herbaceous colour, appear in June, and the feeds ripen in autumn.</p><p>4. The acutus, or ſharnpointed dock, (the oxyla-pâthum of the ſhops) ; but the markets are ſupplied with roots of the common docks which are indifferently gathered by thoſe who collect them in the fields, wſhere the kind commonly called <hi rend="italic">butter dock</hi>  (from its leaves being uſed to wrap up butter) is much more common than this. The roots of this are ſlender, and run downright, ſending Out a few ſmall fibres ; the ſtalks riſe about two feet high, garniſhed at bottom with leaves four inches long, and one and an half broad in the middle. They are rounded at their baſe, where'they -are ſlightly indented, but end in acute points. From the joints of the ſtalks come out alternately long foot-ſtalks, which ſuſtain the ſpikes of flowers, which grow in ſmall whorls round the ſtalks, at about an inch diftant.</p><p>Theſe plants are but ſeldom cultivated ; and ſo eaſily multiply by their numerous ſeeds, that they ſoon become troubleſome weeds where they once get an entrance.</p><p>RUMINANT, in natural hiſtory, is applied to an animal wſhich chews over again wſhat it has eat before ; which is popularly called <hi rend="italic">chewing the cud. </hi>Peyer, in a treatiſe <hi rend="italic">De Rurmnaniibus et Ru&gt;ninatione, </hi>ſhows that there are ſome animals wſhich really ruminate ; as oxen, ſheep, deer, goats, camels, hares, and ſquirtels : and that there are others which only appear to do ſo, as moles, crickets, bees, beetles, crabs, mullets, &amp;c. The latter claſs, he obſerves, have their ſto-machs compoſed of muſeular ſibres, by which the food is ground up and down as in thoſe which really ruminate. Mr Ray obſerves, that ruminants are all four-footed, hairy, and viviparous ; ſome with hollow and perpetual horns, others with deciduous ones.</p><p>KUMP of the sacrifices. Moſes had ordained, that the rump and fat of the ſheep that were offered for a peace-offering ſhould be put upon the fire of the altar (Lev. iii. 9. vii. 3. viii. 25. ix. 19.). The rump was eſteemed the moſt delicate part of the animal.</p><p>RUMPHIA, in botany : A genus of the monogy-nia order, belonging to the triandria claſs of plants: and in the natural method ranking with thoſe of which the order is doubtful. The calyx is trifid; the petals three; the fruit a trilocular plum.</p><p>RUNDLET, or Runlet, a ſmall veffel, containing an uncertain quantity of any liquor, from 3 to 20 gallons.</p><p>RUNGS, in a ſhip, the ſame with the floor or ground timbers ; being the timbers which conftitute her floor ; and are bolted to the keel, wſhoſe ends are rung-heads.</p><p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps">Rung-Heads,</hi></hi>  in a ſhip, are made a little bending to direct the f∖veep or mold of the futtocks and navel-timbers ; for here the lines begin which make the compaſs and bearing of thé ſhip.</p><p>RUNIC, a term applied to the language and letter« of the ancient Goths, Danes, and other northern nations. See Alphabet.</p><p>REΓNNER, in the ſea-language, a rope belonging to the garnet and the two bolt-tackles. It is reeved <hi rend="italic">in</hi>  a ſingſe block joined to the end of a pendant ; it</p><p>has at one end a hook to hitch into any thing ; and, at the other, a double block, into which is reeved the fall of the tackle, or the garnet, by which means it purchaſes more than the tackle would without it.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">RUNNING-thrush, among farriers. See Farri« Ery, ſect. xliv.</hi></p><p>RUNNET, or Rennet, is the concreted milk found in the ftomachs of fucking quadrupeds, wſhich as yet have received no other ſhouriſtiment than their mother’s milk. In ruminating animals, wſhich have ſeveral ſto-machs, it is generally found in the laſt, though ſometimes in the next to it. If the runnet is dried in the fun, and then kept cloſe, it may be preſerved in perfection for years. Not only the runnet itſelf, but alſo the ſtomach in which it is found, curdles milk without any previous preparation. But tlιe common method</p><p>is,    to take the inner membrane of a calf’s ſtomach, to clean it well, to ſalt and hang it up in brown paper : when this is uſed the ſalt is waſhed off, then it is macerated in a little water during the night, and in the morning the infuſion is poured into the milk to curdle</p><p>it.    But ſee more particularly the article Cheese for a proper receipt to make runnet, upon wſhich the quality of the cheeſe greatly depends—The medicinal qualities of runnet are its acrimony, its reſolvent power, and itsuſefulneſs in forfeits from food of difficult digeſ-tkιn.</p><p>RUPEE, a ſilver coin current in the Eaſt Indies, worth about 2 s. 6 d.</p><p>RUPERT, or Robert. See Robert.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Rupert, prince palatine of the Rhine, &amp;c. ſon of Frederic prince elector palatine oſ the Rhine and Eliſabeth daughter to king James I of England, was born in 1619. He gave proofs of his bravery at the age of T 3 ; and in 1642 came over into England, and offered his ſervice to king Charles I. his uncle, who gave him a command in his army. At Edgehiſl he charged with incredible bravery, and made a great ſlaugſhter of the parliamentarians. In 1643 he ſeized the town of Cirenceiter ; obliged the governor of Litchfield to flirrender ; and having joined his brother prince Maurice, reduced Briſtol in three days, and paffed to the relief of Newark. In 1644 he marched to relieve York, wſhere he gave the parliamentarians battle, arſd entirely defeated their right wing ; but Cromwell charged the marquis of Newcaſtle with ſuch an irreſiſtible force, that prince Rupert was entirely defeated. Atter this the prince put himſelf into Briſtol, which furrendered to Fairfax after a gallant refiſtance. The king was ſo enraged at the lofs of this city, ſo contrary to his expectation, that he recalled all prince Rupert’s commrſ-ſions, and ſent him a paſs to go out of the kingom In 1648 he went to France, was highly complimented by that court, and kindly received by king Charles II. who ſojourned there for the time. Afterward he was conſtituted admiral of the king’s navy ; inſeſted the Dutch ſhips, many of which he took ; and having engaged with De Ruyter, obliged him to fly. He died in 1682, and was interred in king Henry VII.’s chapel, Weftminfter, with great magnificence. Mr Grainger obſerves, that he poffeffed in a high degree that kind of courage which is better in an attack tl*an a defence ; and is leſs adapted to the land-ſervice than that of the ſea, wſhere precipitate valour is in its element. </hi>He ſeldom engaged but he gained the advantage, which</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>