<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>eb03-r03</title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>∙neral expreſſion of the rotatory momentum of a particle).</p><p>Draw <hi rend="italic">Em</hi>  perpendicular to P∕&gt;. If we confider P <hi rend="italic">ρ</hi>  as an axis about which a motion of rotation may be produced, it is plain that the momentum of the ■point L to produce ſuch a rotation will be A.&lt;j∕.Lhi. In like manner, its momentum for producing a rotation round « P would be A.∣j∕.Lh. In general, Its momentum for producing rotation round any axis is equal to the product ol the perpendicular force at L (that is, <hi rend="italic">A.a l)</hi>  and the diſtance of L from this axis.</p><p>In order therefore that P may be the centre of percuſſion, the ſum of all the forces <hi rend="italic">A.αllErn</hi>  muſt be equal to nothing ; that is, the -ſum of the forces <hi rend="italic">A.al.Em</hi>  on one ſide of this axis P<hi rend="italic">p</hi>  muſt be balanced by the ſum of forces A'.&lt;i AL' <hi rend="italic">m'</hi>  on the other ſide. To expreſs this in the uſual manner, we muſt have <hi rend="italic">ſA .a l.n</hi>  P — o. But <hi rend="italic">n</hi>  P <hi rend="italic">— η</hi>  O—OP. Therefore <hi rend="italic">ſ A.a l.n</hi>  O —<hi rend="italic">ſA.a</hi>  /.OP — o, and <hi rend="italic">ſ A.a l.n</hi>  O — <hi rend="italic">ſA.al.OP.</hi>  But OP is the ſame wherever the particle A is ſituated ; and becauſe G is the centre of gravity, the ſum of all the quantities <hi rend="italic">A.a l</hi>  isτn.GC, <hi rend="italic">m</hi>  being the quantity of matter of the body ; that is, <hi rend="italic">ſ A.αl~ m.GC,</hi>  and ∕ A .« Z.OP = w.GC.OP, = <hi rend="italic">ſA.al.nG.</hi>  Hence we derive the final equation</p><p><hi rend="italic">f A.a l.n</hi>  O OP=<hi rend="sup">y</hi>---.</p><p>Therefore the centre of percuſſion P of a body turning round the axis D <hi rend="italic">d</hi>  is determined by theſe conditions : I ft, It is in the plane DCG paſſing through the axis and the centre of gravity ; 2d, It is in a line <hi rend="italic">η</hi>  O paſſing through the centre oſ ofcillation, and parallel to the axis, and therefore its diſtance P<hi rend="italic">p</hi>  from the axis of</p><p>. ∕A∙A <hi rend="italic">a*</hi></p><p>rotation is--∕∖∕,- ; and, 3d, Its diſtance OP from the</p><p><hi rend="italic">m.EG    <hi rend="sup">j</hi></hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">.ſA.al.nG</hi></p><p>centre of ofcillation is-7e7s —.</p><p>fW.L-Lr.</p><p>In order therefore that the centres of ofcillation and percuſſion may coincide, or be one and the ſame, OP muſt vaniſh, or SA.a <hi rend="italic">l.n</hi>  O muſt be equal to nothing, that is, the ſum of all the quantities <hi rend="italic">A.a l.n</hi>  O on one ſide of the line CO muſt be equal to the ſum of all the quantities <hi rend="italic">A'.a' l'.n O</hi>  on the other ſide.</p><p>Let Di∕&lt;<hi rend="sup">f</hi>∆ be a plane paſſing through the axis D<hi rend="italic">d </hi>perpendicular to that other plane DCG through it, in which the centre of gravity is ſituated, and let <hi rend="italic">Cg</hi>  Z <hi rend="italic">x </hi>be a third plane paſſing through the centre of grav<hi rend="sup">1</hi>ty perpendicular to both the planes Di/M and DCG. Draw<hi rend="italic">I r</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">a *</hi>  perpendicular to <hi rend="italic">a</hi>  L, and <hi rend="italic">r</hi>  ά perpen-pendicular to <hi rend="italic">c <hi rend="sup">r</hi>,</hi>  and then draw A α, A « perpendicular to <hi rend="italic">a a</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">r «. </hi>It is evident that A <hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps">λ</hi></hi>  and Α * are reſpectively equal to <hi rend="italic">a I</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">l r,</hi>  or to <hi rend="italic">a l</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">η o ; </hi>ſo that the two factors or coriſtituents of the momentum of a particle A round the centre of percuſſion are the diſtances of the particle from the planes Di∕<hi rend="sup">fi</hi>  and κ<hi rend="italic">c g γ,</hi>  both of which are perpendicular to that plane through the axis in which the centre of gravity is placed.</p><p>We may ſee, from theſe obſervations, that the centres of ofcillation and percuſſion do not neceſſarily coincide, and the circumſtance which is neceſſary for their coincidence, viz. that/A.A«. A « is equal to O. It is of importance to keep this in mind.</p><p>There occurs here another obſervation of great im-_ portance. Since every force is balanced by an equal</p><p>force acting in the oppoſite direction, and ſince all motion progreſſive and rotatory is ſtopped by an external force applied at P in the direction &lt;yP, it follows that, if the body were at reſt, and the ſame force be applied there, it will ſet the body in rotation round the axis D7, in the oppoſite direction, with the ſame angular velocity, and without any preſſure on the pivots D and <hi rend="italic">d.</hi>  For whatever motion of the particle A, in the direction AL, was ſtopped by a part of the external force applied at P, the ſame motion will be produced by it in the quieſcent particle A in the oppoſite direction LA. And as the pivots D and <hi rend="italic">d</hi>  had no motion in the caſe of the body turning round them, they will acquire no motion, or will have-no tendency to motion, or no preſſure will be exerted on them, in the laſt caſe. Therefore when an external force is applied at P in a direction perpendicular to the line P∕&gt;, the line D <hi rend="italic">d. </hi>will become a momentary ſpontaneous axis of converſion, and the incipient motion of the body will per-ſectly reſemble the rotation of the ſame body round a fixed axis Dr∕.</p><p>There is another ſet of forces of which we have as yet taken no notice, viz. that part of each force AL which is directed along the plane DCG, and is repreſented by <hi rend="italic">l</hi>  L when the whole force is repreſented by AL, or by A∕ when the whole force is repreſented by <hi rend="italic">A a.</hi>  Theſe forces being all in the plane DCG, and in the dilection CG or GC, can have no effect on the rotation round any axis in that plane. But they tend, ſeparately, to produce rotation round any axis paſſing through this plane perpendicularly. And the momentum of A to produce a rotation round an axis perpendicular to this plane, in O for iniiance, muſt evidently be <hi rend="italic">A.Al.n</hi>  O, and round P it muſt be A.A ∕.nP, &amp;c. We ſhall have occaſion to confider theſe afterwards.</p><p>It is uſual in courſes of experimental philoſophy to illuſtrate the motions of bodies on inclined planes and curved ſurfaces by experiments with balls rolling down theſe ſurfaces. But the motions of ſuch rolling balls aie by no means juſt repreſentations of the motions they repreſent. The ball not only goes down the inclined plane by the action of gravity, but it alſo turns round an axis. Force is neqeſſary for producing this rotation ; and as there is no other ſource but the weight of the ball, part ot this weight is expended on the rotation, and the remainder only accelerates it down the plane. The point of the ball which reſts on the plane is hindered from Aiding down by friction ; and therefore the ball tumbles, as it were, over this point of contact, and is inſtantly catched by another point of contact, over which it tun.Wes in the ſame manner. A cylinder rolls down in the very ſame way; and its motion is nearly the ſame as if a fine thread had been lapped round it, and one end oſ it made faſt at the head of the inclined plane. The cylinder rolls down by unwinding this thread.</p><p>The mechaniſin of all ſuch motions (and ſome oſ them are important) may be underſtood by conſidering them as follows : Let a body of any ſhape be connected with a cylinder FCB (fig. 6.) whoſe axis paſſes through G the centre of gravity of the body. Suppoſe that body ſuſpended from a fixed point A by a thread wound round the cylinder. This body will de-Jcend by the action of gravity, and it will alſo turn round, unwinding the thread. Draw the horizontal</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>