<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>eb03-r03</title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>flowers.-— Roſa mundi (roſe of the world) or ſtriped red roſe, is a variety of the common red roſe, growing ] but three or four feet high, having large ſpreading ſemi- ∣ double red flowers, beautifully ſtriped with white—and 1 deep red.—York and Lancaſter variegated roſe, grows <hi rend="sup">, </hi>five, fix, or eight feet high, or more ; bearing variegated red flowers, conſiſting of a mixture of red and ■ white ; alſo frequently diſpoſed in elegant ſtripes, ſometimes in half of the flower, and ſometimes in ſome of the petals.—Monthly roſe, grows about four or five feet high, with green very prickly ſhoots ; producing middle-ſized, moderately double, delicate flowers, of different colours in the varieties. The varieties are, common red-flowered monthly roſe—bluſh-flowered— white-flowered—ſtriped-flowered. All of which blow both early and late, and often produce flowers ſeveral months in the year, as May, June, and July ; and frequently again in Auguſt or September, and ſometimes, in fine mild ſeaſons, continues till November or December : hence the name<hi rend="italic">monthly roſe.—</hi>Double virgin-roſe, grows five or fix feet high, having greeniſh branches with ſcarce any ſpines ; and with large double pale-red and very fragrant flowers.— Reddamaſk roſe, grows eight or ten feet high, having greeniſh branches, armed wfith ſhort aculea; and moderately-dcuble, fine ſoft-red, very fragrant flowers.—White damaſk roſe, grows eight or ten feet high, with greeniſh very prickly branches, and whitiſh-red flowers, becoming gradually of a whiter colour. — Bluſh Belgic roſe, grows three or four feet high, or more ; having greeniſh prickly branches, five or ſeven lobed leaves, and numerous, very double, bluſh-red flowers, wfith ſhort petals, evenly arranged.-—Red Belgic roſe, having greeniſh and red ſhoots and leaves, and fine double deep-red flowers.- Velvet roſe, grows three or four feet high, armed with but few prickles ; producing large velvet-red flowers, comprifing ſemi-double and double varieties, all very beautiful roſes.— Marbled roſe, grow<hi rend="sup">r</hi>s four or five feet high, having browniſh branches, wfith but few prickles ; and large, double, finely-marbled, red flow<hi rend="sup">r</hi>ers.—Red-and-yellow Auſtrian roſe, grows five or fix feet high, having llender reddiſh-branches, armed with ſhort browniſh aculea ; and with flowers of a reddiſh copper colour on one fide, the other fide yellow. This is a curious variety, and the flowers aſſume a Angularly agreeable appearance.— Yellow Auſſrian roſe, grows five or fix feet high, having reddiſh very prickly ſhoots ; and numerous bright-yellow flowers.— Double yellow roſe, grow<hi rend="sup">r</hi>s ſix or ſeven feet high ; wfith browniſh branches, armed with numerous large and ſmall yellowiſh prickles ; and large very double yellow flowers.—Frankfort roſe, grows eight or ten feet high, is a vigorous ſhooter, with browmiſh branches thinly armed with ftrong prickles ; and produces largiſh double purpliſh-red flowers, that blow irregularly, and have but little fragrance.</p><p>4. The centiſolia, or hundred-leaved red roſe, &amp;c. grows from about three or four to fix or eight feet high, in different forts, all of them hiſpid and prickly; pinnated three and five lobed leaves ; and large very double red flowers, having very numerous petals, and of different ſhades in the varieties- The varieties are, — common Dutch hundred-leaved roſe, grows three or four feet high, with erect greeniſh branches, but moderately armed with prickles ; and large remarkably double red flowers, with ſhort regularly arranged petals.</p><lb/><p>—Bluſh hundred leaved roſe, grows like the other, with</p><p>large very double pale-red flowers___Provence roſe,</p><p>grows five or ſix feet, with greeniſh-browm prickly branches, and very large double globular red flowers, with large petals folding over one another, more or leſs in the varieties.—The varieties are, common red Provence roſe, and pale Provence roſe ; both of which having larger and ſomewhat looſer petals than the following fort.—Cabbage Provence roſe ; having the petals cloſely folded over one another like cabbages— Dutch cabbage roſe, very large, and cabbages tolerably. — Childing Provence roſe—Great royal roſe, grows ſix or eight feet high, producing remarkably large, ſomewhat looſe, but very elegant flowers.—-All theſe are large double red flowers, ſomewhat globular at ſirſt blowing, becoming gradually a little ſpreading at top, and are all very ornamental fragrant roſes.—Moſs Provence roſe, ſuppoſed a variety of the common roſe ; grows erectly four or five ſeet high, having browniſh ſtalks -end branches, very cloſely armed with ſhort prickles, and double crimſon-red flowers ; having the calyx and upper part of the peduncle ſurrounded. wfith a rough moſſy-like ſubſtance, effecting a curious Angularity. This is a fine delicate roſe, of a high fragrance, which, together wfith its moſſy calyx, renders it of great eſtimation as a curioiity.</p><p>5.    The cinnamomea, or cinnamon roſe, grows five or ſix feet high, or more, with purpliſh branches thinly aculeated; pinnated five or ſeven lobed leaves, having almoſt inermous petioles, ſmooth pedunculi, and ſmooth globular germina ; with ſmall purpliſh-red cinnamon-ſcented flowers early in May. There are varieties with double flowers.</p><p><hi rend="italic">6.</hi>     The Alpina, or Alpine inermous roſe, growls five or ſix ſeet high, having ſmooth or unarmed reddiſh branches, pinnated ſeven-lobed ſmooth leaves, ſomewhat hiſpid pedunculi, oval germina, and deep-red ſingle flowers ; appearing in May. This ſpecies, as being free fron; all kind of armature common to the other forts of roſes, is eſteemed as a ſingularity ; and from this property is often called the <hi rend="italic">virgin roſe.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">q.</hi>  The Carolina, or Carolina and Virginia roſe, &amp;c. grows fix or eight ſeet high, or more, having ſmooth reddiſh branches, very thinly aculeated; pinnated ſeven-lobed ſmooth leaves, with prickly foot-ſtalks; ſomewhat hiſpid pedunculi, globoſe hiſpid germen, and fiπgle red flowers in cluſters, appearing moſtly in Auguſt and September. The varieties are, dwarf Pennſylvanian roſe, with ſingle and double red flowers—American pale-red roſe. This ſpecies and varieties grow naturally in different parts of North America; they effect a fine variety in our gardens, and are in eſtimation ſor their late-flowering property, as they often continue in blow from Auguſt until October ; and the flowers are ſucceeded by numerous red berry-like heps in autumn, cauſing a variety all winter.</p><p>8. The villoſa, or villoſe apple-bearing roſe, grows ſix or eight feet high, having ſtrong erect browniſh ſmooth branches ;. aculeated ſparſedly pinnated ſeven-lobed villoſe or hairy leaves, downy underneath, with prickly foot-ſtalks, hiſpid peduncles, a globular prickly germen ; and large ſingle red flowers, ſucceeded by large round prickly heps, as big as little apples. Thia ſpecies merits admittance into every collection as a cu-rioſity for the ſingularity of its fruit, both for variety</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>