<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>eb03-r03</title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>volve while proceeding forward, and that theſe are at right angles to each other ; and they have given the conditions which muſt be implemented in the determination of theſe axes. But they ſtill leave us exceedingly at a loſs ſor means to diſcover the poſitions of the axes of a given body which have theſe conditions.</p><p>To ſolve this problem therefore in general terms, would lead to a diſquiſition altogether diſproportioned to our work. We muſt reſtrict ourſelves to thoſe forms of body and ſituations of the point of impulſion which admit of the coincidence of the centres of ofcillation and percuſſion ; and we muſt leave out the caſes where the axis has 'a motion in the direction of its length ; that is, we ſhall always ſuppoſe the ſpontaneous axis of converſion to have no motion. Thus we ſhall comprehend the phenomena of the planetary motions, ſimilar to the preceſſion of our equinoctial point?, and all the intereſting caſes oſ practical mechanics. The ſpeculative mathematical reader will fill up the blanks of this inveſtigation by conſuking the writings of Euler and D’Alembert in the Berlin Memoirs, Friſi’s Coſmo-graphia, and the papers of Mr Landen, Mr Milner, and Mr Vince, in the Philoſophical Tranſactions. But we hope, by means of a beautiful propoſition on the com-poſition of rotatory motions, to enable every reader to diſcover the poſition oſ the axis oſ progreſſive rotation in every caſe which may intereſt him, without the previous ſolution of the intricate problem mentioned</p><p>above.</p><p>Let ABPC∕&gt;i A (fig. 13.) be a ſection of a body through its centre of gravity G, ſo formed, that the part ABPC is ſimilar, and ſimilarly placed with the part <hi rend="italic">AbpC,</hi>  ſo that the plane AC would divide it equally. Let thia body bc impelled at P in the direction HP, perpendicular to the plane AC. The axis round which it will turn will be perpendicular to G ‰ Suppoſe it at A. Then drawing AB and A <hi rend="italic">b</hi>  to ſimilar points, it is plairr that B <hi rend="italic">r, b ß</hi>  are equal and oppoſite ; theſe repreſent the forces which would raiſe or lower one end of the axis, as has been already obſerved. The axis therefore will remain perpendicular to G ‰</p><p>Let the body be ſo ſhaped, that if the parts to the right and left of the point of impulſe jγ (the impulſe is here ſuppoſed not <hi rend="italic">perpendicular</hi>  to the plane AC, but <hi rend="italic">in</hi>  this plane) are equal and ſimilarly placed ; then the momenta round AC muſt balance each other, and the axis EF will have no tendency to go out of the plane ABCZ∣ A perpendicular to the impulſe.</p><p>Any body whoſe ſhape has theſe two properties will turn round an axis perpendicular to the plane which paſſes through the centre of gravity in the direction of the impelling force. This condition is always found in the planets when dſtlurbed by the gravitation to a diſtant planet: for they are all figures of revolution. The direction of the diſturbing or impelling force is always in a plane paſſing through the axis and the diſturbing body.</p><p>With ſuch limitations therefore we propoſe the following problem</p><p>Let G (ſig. 14.) be the centre of gravity of a body in free ſpace, which is impelled by an external force <hi rend="italic">f, </hi>acting in the fine FP, which does not paſs through the centre. Ret <hi rend="italic">m</hi>  be the number of equal particles in the body, or its quantity of matter. Let the forcé <hi rend="italic">f</hi>  be</p><p>ſuch, that it would communicate to the body the velocity <hi rend="italic">v ;</hi>  that is, would cauſe the centre to move with the velocity <hi rend="italic">v.</hi>  It may be expreffed by the quantity of motion which it produces, that is, by <hi rend="italic">m v,</hi>  and it would produce the velocity <hi rend="italic">m v</hi>  on one particle. It is required to determine the whole motion, progreſſive and rotatory, which it will produce, and the ſpace which it will deſcribe during one turn round its axis.</p><p>Draw GI parallel and PGC perpendicular to FP, and let GI be taken for the meaſure of the progreſſive velocity <hi rend="italic">v.</hi></p><p>It has been demonſtrated that the centre G will proceed in the direction GI with the velocity <hi rend="italic">v,</hi>  and that the body will at the ſame time turn round an axis paſſing through G, perpendicular to the plane of the figure, every particle deſcribing circles in parallel planes round this axis, and with velocities of rotation proportional to their diſtances from it. There is therefore a certain diſtance GB, ſuch that the velocity with which a particle deſcribes its circumference is equal to the progreſſive velocity <hi rend="italic">v.</hi>  Let BCD be this circumference. When the particle deſcribing this circumference is in the line CGP, and in that part of it which lies beyond P from G, its abſolute velocity muſt be double that of the centre G ; but when it is in the oppoſite point C<hi rend="sub">9 </hi>its retrograde velocity being equal to the progreſſive velocity of the centre, it muſt be at reſt. In every poſition of the body, therefore, that point of the accompanying circumference which is at this extremity of the perpendicular drawn through the centre on the line of dire ion of the impelling force is at reſt. It is at that-initant a ſpontaneous centre of converſion, and the ſtraight line drawn through it perpendicular to the plane of the figure is then a ſpontaneous axis of converſion, and every particle is in a momentary ſtateof rotation round this axis, in directions perpendicular to the lines drawn to the axis at right angles, and with velocities proportional to theſe diſtances ; and laſtly, the body advances in the direction GI through a ſpace equal to the circumference BCD, while it makes one turn round G.</p><p>Let A be one of the particles in the plane of the figure. Join AC, AG, AP. Draw <hi rend="italic">Ab, Ac, Ad </hi>perpendicular to CP, CA, GA. The abſolute motion A <hi rend="italic">c</hi>  of A is compounded of the progreſſive motion A <hi rend="italic">h </hi>common to the whole body and equal to GI, and the motion A <hi rend="italic">d</hi>  of rotation round the . entre of gravity G. Therefore ſince A <hi rend="italic">b</hi>  is equal to &lt;υ, and A <hi rend="italic">c</hi>  is the diagonal of a parallelogram given both in ſpecies and magnitude, it is alſo given, and (as appears alſo ſrom the reaſoning in art. 85.) it is to GI as CA to CG.</p><p>By the application of the force <hi rend="italic">m v</hi>  in the direction FP, every particle of the body is dragged out of its place, and exerts a reſiſtance equal to the motion which it acquires. A part of this force, which we may call <hi rend="italic">m v,</hi>  is employed in communicating the motion A <hi rend="italic">c</hi>  tΘ A. Therefore <hi rend="italic">m v,</hi>  which we have, and, from what has been lately ſhown, CG.: CA = GI : A <hi rend="italic">c, = v</hi>  : A <hi rend="italic">c<hi rend="sub">9</hi></hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">v'CA</hi></p><p>and therefore At = ^qq^. But farther (agreeably to</p><p>what was demonſtrated in art. 16.) we have CP : C A ∙u.CA</p><p>≈ A <hi rend="italic">c : m v,</hi>  ≈ Tg^ : <hi rend="italic">m ν,</hi>  and therefore <hi rend="italic">m'v</hi>  =s</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>