<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>eb03-r03</title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ROUNDELAY, or Roundo, a fort of ancient poer∩, derived its name, according to Menage, from its form, and becauſe it ſtill turns back again to the ſirll verſe, and thus goes round. The common roundelay conſiſts ol 13 verſes, eight of which are in one rhyme and five in another. It is divided into couplets ; at the end of the ſecond and third of which the beginning of the roundelay is repeated ; and that, if poſſible, in an equivocal or punning ſenſe. The roundelay is a popular poem in Fiance, but is little known among us. Ma-rot and Voiture have ſucceeded the beſt in it. Rapin remarks, that if the roundelay be not very exquiſite, it is intolerably bad In all the ancient ones, Menage ob-ſerves, that the verſe preceding has a leſs complete ſenſe, and yet joins agreeably with that oſ the cloſe, without depending neceſſarily thereon, f his rule, well ob-ſerved, makes the roundelay more ingenious, and is one of the ſineſſts of the poem. Some of the ancient wri ters ſpeak of the roundelay or roundel as a kind of air appropriated to dancing ; and in this ſenſe the term ſeems to indicate little more than dancing in a circle with the hands joined</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">ROUND-House, a kind of p ifon for the nightly watch in London to ſecure diſorderly perſons till they can be carried before a magiftrate</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">RoVND-PLuſe,</hi>  in a ſhip, the uppermoſt room or cabin on the ſterii of a ſhip, where the mailer lies</p><p>ROUNDS, in military matters, a detachment from the main-guard, of an officer or a non-commiſſioned officer and fix men, who go round the rampart oſ a garriſon, to liſten if any thing be ſtirring without the place, and to ſee that the centinels be diligent upon their duty, and^all in order. In ſtrict garriſons the rounds go every half-hour. The centinels are to challenge at a diſtance, and to reſt their arms as the round paffes. All guards turn out, challenge, exchange the parole, and reſt their arms, &amp;c.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Rounds are ordinary and extraordinary. The ordinary rounds are three ; the town-major’s round, the grand-round, and the viſiting-round.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Manner oſ going the Rounds.</hi>  When the town-major goes his round, he comes to the main guard, and demands a ſerjeant and four or ſix men to eſcort him to the next guard ; and when it is dark, one of the men is to carry a light.</p><p>As ſoon as the ſentry at the guard perceives the round comi⅞g, he ſhall give notice to the guard, that they may be ready to turn out when order ed ; and when the round is advanced within about 20 or 30 paces of the guard, he is to challenge briſkly ; and when he is anſwered by the ſerjeant wſho attends the round, <hi rend="italic">Town major's round,</hi>  he is to ſay, <hi rend="italic">Stand round!</hi>  and reſt his arms ; after which he is to call out immediately, <hi rend="italic">Serjeant turn out the guard, towη-maj∙ Ls round. </hi>Upon the ſentry calling, the ſerjeant is to turn out the guard immediately, drawing up the men in good or der with ſhouldered arms, the officer placing himſelf at the head of it, with his arms in his hand. He then orders the ſerjeant and four or ſix men to advance toward the round, and challenge : the ſerjeant of the round is to anſwer, <hi rend="italic">Town-major's round ;</hi>  upon which the ſerjeant of the guard replies, <hi rend="italic">AHvan<hi rend="sub">l</hi>  ∣, Je&gt;jeant, with the parole !</hi>  at the ſame time ordering his men to . reſt their arms. The ſerjeant of the round advances •alone, and gives the ſerjeant of the guard the parole in his car, that nene elſe may hear it ; during which period the ſerjeant of the guard holds the ſpear of his halbert at the other’s breaſt. The ſerjeant of the round then returns to his poll, wſhilſt the ſerjeant of the guard leaving his men to keep the round from advancing, gives the parole to his officer. This being found right, the officer orders his ſerjeant to return to his men ; ſays, <hi rend="italic">Advance, town-major's round!</hi>  and orders the gμard to reſt their arms ; upon which the ſerjeant of the guard orders his men to wheel back from the centre, and form a lane, through which the town-major is to paſs (the eſcort remaining where they were), and go up to the officer and give him the parole, laying his mouth to his ear. The officer holds the ſpear of his efponton at the town major’s breaſt while he gives him the parole.</p><p>The deſign of rounds is not only to vifιt the guards, and keep the centinels alert ; but likewiſe to diſcover what pa(Γes in the outworks, and beyond them.</p><p>ROUSSILLON, a province of France, in the Pyrenees, bounded on the eaſt by the Mediterranean ſea, on the weft by Cerdagne, on the north by Lower Languedoc, and on the ſouth by Catalonia, from which it is ſeparated by the Pyrenees. It is a fertile country, about 50 miles in length, and 2t in breadth, and remarkable for its great number of olive-trees. Perpignan is the capital town.</p><p>ROUSSEAU (James), an eminent painter, was born at Paris in the year 1630, and ſtudied firſt under Swa-nevelt. who had married one of his relations ; after which he improved himſelf by travelling into Italy, practiſing ſolely in perfective, architecture, and landſcape. On his return home, he was employed at Marly. He dx-ſtingu’ſhed himſelf very much in painting buildings, and by his knowledge of, and attention to, the principles of perlpective. Louis XIV. employed him to decorate his hall of devices at St Germaine-en-Laſe, where he repreſented the operas of Lulli. But being a Proteſ-tant, he quitted France on the perſecution of his brethren, and retired to Swifferland. Louis invited him back ; he refuſed, but ſent his deſigns, and recommended a proper perſon to execute them. After a ſſiort ſtay in Swfifferland, he went to Holland ; whence he was invited over to England by Ralph duke of Montague, to adorn his new houſe in Bloomſhury, where he painted much. Some oſ his pictures, both in landſcape and architecture, are over doors at Hampton-court ; and he etched ſome of his own deſigns. His perſpectives having been moſt commonly applied to decorate courts or gardens, have ſuffered much from the weather. Such oſ them as remain are monuments of an excellent genius The colours are durable and bright, and the choice of them moſt judicious. He died in Soho-ſquare, about the year 1693, aged 63.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Rousseau (John Baptiſt), a celebrated French poet, w^as born at Paris in April 167</hi><hi rend="sup">r</hi>. His father⅛ who was a ſhoemaker in good circumſtances, made him ſtudy in the beſt colleges of Paris, wſhere he diſtinguiſhed himſelf by his abilities. He at length applied himſelf entirely to poetry, and ſoon made hιmklf known by ſeveral ſhort pieces, that were filled w<hi rend="sup">,</hi>ith lively and agreeable images which made him iought for by perlons of the ſiiſt rank, and men oſ the brighteſt genius. He was admitted in quality of<hi rend="italic">élève,</hi>  or pupil, into the academy of Inſcriptions and Belles Lettres, in 1701,</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>