<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>eb03-r03</title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>within, and reſted on a ſtrong projection on the ιnfide. Small ſhot was gradually poured in upon the floors, ſo as to ſpread uniformly over them. The plain joiſted floor broke down with 487 pounds, and the carcaſe floor with 327. The firſt broke without giving any warning ; the other gave a violent crack when 294 pounds had been poured in.</p><p>A trial had been made before, and the loads were 341 and 482. But the modelshaving been made by a leſs accurate hand, it was not thought a fair ſpecimen of the ſtrength which might be given to a carcaſe floor.</p><p>The only argument of weight which we can recollect in favour of the compound conſtruction of roofs is, that the plain method would prodigiouſly increaſe the quantity of work, would admit nothing but long timber, which would greatly add to the expence, and would make the garrets a mere thicket of planks. We admit this in its full force ; but we continue to be of the opinion that plain roofs are greatly ſuperior in point of ſtrength, and therefore ſhould be adopted in caſes where the great difficulty is to inſure this neceſſary circumſtance.</p><p>It would appear very neglectful to omit an account of the roofs put on round buildings, ſuch as domes, cupolas, and the like. They appear to be the moſt difficult taſks in the carpenter art. But the difficulty lies entirely in the mode of framing, or what the French call the <hi rend="italic">trait de charpenterie.</hi>  The view whiςh we are taking of the ſubject, as a part of mechanical ſei-ence, has little connection with this. It is plain, that whatever form of a truſs is excellent tn a ſquare building muſt be equally ſo as one of the frames of a round one; and the only difficulty is how to manage their mutual interſections at the top. Some ot them muſt be diſcontinued before they reach that length, and common ſenſe will teach us to cut them ſhort alternately, and always leave as many, that they may ſtand equally thick as at their firſt ſpringing from the bale of the dome. Thus the length of the purlins which reach from truſs to truſs will never be too great.</p><p>The truth is, that a round building which gathers in at top, like a glaſs-houſe, a potter’s kiln, or a ſpire ſteeple, inſtead of being the moſt difficult to erect with liability, is of all others the eaſieſt. Nothing can ſhow this more forcibly than daily practice, where they are run up without centres and without ſcaffoldings ; and it requires groſs blunders indeed in the choice of their outline to put them is much danger of falling from a want of equilibrium. In like manner, a dome of carpentry can hardly fall, give it what ſhape or what conſtruction you will. It <hi rend="italic">cannot</hi>  fall unlèfs ſome part of it flies out at the bottom : an iron hoop round it, or ſtraps at the joinings of the truffes and purlins, which make an equivalent to a hoop, will effectually ſecure it. And as beauty requires that a dome ſhall ſpring almoſt perpendicularly from the wall, it is evident that there is hardly any thruſt to force out the walls. The only part where this is to be guarded againſt is, where the tangent is inclined about 40 or 50 degrees to the horizon. Here it will be proper to make a courſe of firm horizontal joinings.</p><p>We doubt not but that domes βf carpentry will now be raiſed of great extent. The Halle du Bles at Paris, of 200 .feet in diameter, was.the invention of an intelligent carpenter, the Sieur Moulιneau. He was not by any means a man of ſcience, but had much more mechanical knowledge than artiſans uſually have, and was convinced that a very thin ſhell of timber might not only be ſo ſhaped as to be nearly in equilibrio, but that if hooped or firmly connected horizontally, it would have all the ſtiffneſs that was neceſſary ; and he preſented his project to the magiſtracy of Paris. The grandeur of it pleaſed them, but they doubted of its poffibility. Being a great public work, they prevailed on the Academy of Sciences to conſider it. The members, who were competent judges, were inſtantly ſtruck with the juſtneſs of Mr Moulineau’s principles, and aſtoniſhed that a thing ſo plain had not been long familiar to every houſe-carpenter. It quickly became an univerſal topic of converſation, diipute, and cabal, in the polite circles of Paris. But the Academy having given a very favourable report of their opinion, the project was immediately carried into execution, and ſoon completed, and now ſtands as one of the great exhibitions of Paris.</p><p>The conſtruction of this dome is the ſimpleſt thing that can be imagined. The circular ribs which com-poſe it conſiſt of planks nine feet long, 13 inches broad, and three inches thick ; and each rib conſiſts of three of theſe planks bolted together in ſuch a manner that two-joints meet. A rib is begun, for inſtance, with a plank of three feet long ſtanding between one of fix feet and' another of nine, and this is continued to the head of it. No machinery was neceſſary for carrying up ſuch ſmall. pieces, and the whole went up like a piece of bricklayer’s work. At various diſtances theſe ribs were con-nected horizontally by purlins and iron ſtraps, which made ſo many hoops to the whole. When the works had reached ſuch a height, that the diſtance of the ribs was two-thirds of the original diſtance, every third rib was diſcontinued, and the ſpace was left open and glazed. When carried ſe&gt; much higher that the diſtance of the ribs is one-third, of the original diſtance, every ſecond rib (now conliſting of tw<hi rend="sup">r</hi>o ribs very near each other) is in like manner diſcontinued, and the void is glazed. A little above this the heads of the ribs are framed into a circular ring of timber, which forms a wide opening in the middle ; over which is a glazed canopy or umbrella, with an opening between it and the dome for allowing the heated air to get out. All who have ſeen this dome ſay, that it is the moſt beautiful and magnificent object they have ever beheld.</p><p>The only difficulty which occurs in the conſtruction of wooden domes is, when they are unequally loaded, by caιτying a heavy lanthern or cupola in the.middle. In ſuch a caſe, if the dome were a mere ſhell, it would be cruſhed in at the trop, or the action of the wind on the lanthern might tear it out of its place. Such a dome mult therefore conſiſt of trailed frames. Mr Price has given a very good one in his plate OP, tho’ much ſtronger in the truffes than there was any oc-cafion for. This cauſes a great loſs of room, and throw's the lights of the lanthern too far up. It is evidently copied from Sir Chriſtopher Wren’s dome of St Paul’s church in London ; a model of propriety in its particular ſituation, but by no means a general model of a wooden dome. It reſts on the. brick cone within it ; and Sir Chriſtopher has very ingeniouſly made uſe of it for ſtifſening this cone, as any intelligent</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>