<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>eb03-r03</title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>der limitations that ſeme thought derogatory to her dignity, yet ſhe broke them all, aſſerted the prerogative of her anceſtors, and puniſhed the aſpiring Dolgo∏ιcki family, who had impoſed upon her limitations, v-ith a view, as it is ſaid, that they themſelves might govern. She raiſed her favourite Biron to the duchy of Cour-land ; and was obliged to give way to many ſevere executions on his account. Upon her death in 1740, John, the ſon of her niece the princeſs of Mecklenburgh, by Antony Ulric of Brunſwiq Wolfenbuttel, was, by her will, intitled to the ſucdeffion : but being no more than two years old, Biron was appointed to he adminiſtrator of the empire during h⅛ nonage. This deſtination was diſagreeable to the prir⅛eefs of Mecklenburgh and her huſhand, and unpopulaf<hi rend="sup">s</hi>samong the- Ruffians. . Count Munich was employed b⅜the princeſs of Mecklenburgh to arreſt Biron ; who was tried, and condemned to die, but was ſent in exile to Siberia.</p><p>The adminiſtration of the princeſs Anne of Mecklenburgh and her huſhand was, upon many accounts, but particularly that of her German connections, diſagreeable not only to the Ruffians, but to other powers of Europe ; and notwithſtanding a proſperous war they carried on with the Swedes, the princeſs Elizabeth, daughter by Catharine to Peter the Great, formed ſuch a party, that in one night’s time ſhe was declared and proclaimed empreſs of the Ruffias ; and the princeſs ot Mecklenburgh, her huſhand, and ſon, were made priſoners.</p><p>Elizabeth’s reign may be ſaid to have been more glo-'rious than that of any of her predeceffors, her father excepted. She aboliſhed capital puniſhments, and introduced into all civil and military proceedings a moderation till her time unknown in Ruffia : but at the ſame time ſhe puniſhed the counts Munich and Oſter-man, who had the chief management of affairs during the late adminiſtration, wiſh exile. She made peace with Sweden ; and ſettled the ſucceffion to that crown, as well as to her own dominions, upon ſhe moſt equitable foundation. Having glorioufly finiſhed a war, which had been ſtirred up againſt her with Sweden, ſhe replaced the natural order of ſucceffion in her own family, by declaring the duke of Holſtein-Gottorp, who was deſcended from her elder fiſter, to be her heir. She gave him the title of grand duke of Ruffia ; and ſoon after her acceffion to the throne, ſhe called him to her court ; where he renounced the ſucceffion to the crown of Sweden, which undoubtedly belonged to him, embraced the Greek religion, and married a princeſs of Anhalt-Zerbſt, by whom he had a ſon, who is now heir to the Ruffian empire.</p><p>Few princes have had a more uninterrupted career of glory than Elizabeth. She was completely victorious over the Swedes. Her alliance was courted by Great Britain at the expence of a large ſubfidy ; but many political, and ſome private reaſons, it is ſaid, determined her to take part with the houſe of Auſtria againft ſhe king of Pruffia in 1 756. Her arms alone gave a turn to the ſucceſs of the war, which was in disfavour of Pruffia, notwithftanding that monarch’s amazing abilities both in the field and cabinet. Her conqueſts were ſuch as portended the entire deſtruction of the Pruffian power, which was perhaps ſaved only by her critical death on January 5. 1762.</p><p>Elizabeth was Succeeded by Peter UI. grand prince</p><p>of Ruffia and duke of Holſtein ; a prince whoſe conduct has been variouſly repreſented. He mounted the throne poffeffed of an enthufiaſtic admiration of his Pruffian majeſty’s virtues ; to whom he gave peace, and whoſe principles and practices he ſeems to have adopted as the directories of his future reign. He might have ſurmounted the effects even of thoſe peculiarities, un-popular as they then were in Ruffia ; but it is ſaid, that he aimed at reformations in his dominions, which even Peter the Great durſt not attempt ; and that he even ventured to cut off the beards of his clergy. He was certainly a weak man, who had no opinions of his own, but childiſhly adopted the ſentiments of any perſon who took the trouble to teach him. His chief amuſement was buffoonery ; and he would fit for hours looking with pleaſure at a merry-andrew fi∏g-ing drunken and vulgar ſongs. He was a ſtranger to the country, its inhabitants, and their manners ; and ſuffered himſelf to be perſuaded by thoſe about him, that the Ruffians were fools and beafts unworthy of his attention, except to make them, by meanε of the Pruffian diſeipline, good fighting machines. Theſe ſentiments regulated his whole conduct, and prepared the way for that revolution which improprieties of a different kind tended to haften.</p><p>Becoming attached to one of the Vorontzoff ladies, fiſter to the princeſs Daſhkoff, he diſguſted his wife, who was then a lovely .woman in the prime of life, of great natural talents and great acquired accompliſhments ; whilſt the lady whom he preferred to her was but one degree above an idiot. The princeſs Daſhkoff, who was married to a man whoſe genius was not ſupe-rior to that of the emperor, being <hi rend="italic">dame d<hi rend="sup">,</hi>honneur </hi>and lady of the bedchamber, had of courſe much of the empreſs’s company. Similarity of ſituations knit theſe two illuſtrious perſonages in the cloſeſt friendſhip. The princeſs being a zealous admirer of the French <hi rend="italic">κconorniftcs</hi>, could make her converſation both amufing andinſtructive. She retailed all her ſtatiſtical knowledge ; and finding the empreſs a willing hearer, ſhe ſpoke of her in every company as a prodigy of knowledge, judgment, and philanthropy. Whilſt the emperor, by his buffoonery and attachment to foreign manners, was daily incurring more and more the odium of his ſubjects, the popularity of his wife was rapidly in-creaſmg ; and ſome peiſons about the court expreffed their regret, that ſo much knowledge of government, ſuch love of humanity, and ſuch ardent wiſhes for the proſperity of Ruffia, ſhould only furniſh converſations with Catharina Romanovna*. The empreſs and her favourite did not let theſe expreffions paſs unobſerved: they continued their ſtudies in concert ; and whilſt the former was employed on her famous code of laws for a great empire, the latter always reported progreſs, till the middling circles of Moſcow and St Peterſhurgh began to ſpeak familiarly of the bleffings which they might enjoy if theſe {peculations could be realized.</p><p>Meanwhile Peter III. was giving freſh cauſe of discontent.. He. had recalled from Siberia count Munich, who was indeed a ſenſible, brave, and worthy man ; hut as he. was ſmarting under the effects of Ruffian def-potifm, and had grounds of reſentment againft moſt of the great families, he did not much diſcourage the emperor’s unpopular conduct, but only tried to moderate it and give it a ſyſtem. Beter, however, was impatient.</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>