<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>eb03-r03</title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>and equal to the quantity of motion oſ the board, all motion will be ſtopped : for when the point G is ſtopped, no- reaſon can be aſſigned why one part of the board ſhall advance more than another. The ſame thing muſt happen if the board be ſtopped by a ſtraight edge put in its way, and paſſing through G : for example, in the line LGM, or y G <hi rend="italic">h.</hi>  But if this edge be ſo placed that the board ſhall meet it with the line IPK, then, becauſe this line does not divide it equally, and becauſe there is a greater quantity of motion in the part CIKC' than in the part IDD K, though the progreſſive motion may be ſtopped, the upper part will advance, and a motion of rotation will commence, of which IK will be the axis. Now ſuppoſe that the board, inſtead of having been moving along in the direction GH, every part with the ſame velocity had been fwinging round the axis CC' like a pendulum, from the poſition C <hi rend="italic">d d'</hi>  C', and that it is ſtopped by a ſtraight edge meeting it in the line LGM parallel to CO', in the moment that it has attained the vertical poſition CDD'C' ; all its motion will not be ſtopped : for, although LGM divides the board equally, there is more motion in the lower part LDD<hi rend="sup">,</hi>M than in the upper part CLMC', becauſe every particle of the lower part iβ deſeribing larger circles and moving ſwifter. Therefore when the line LGM is ſtopped, there will be a <hi rend="italic">tendency</hi>  of the lower part to advance, and the pivots C and C' of the axis will be preſſed backwards on their holes ; and if the holes were at that inſtant removed, a rotation would commence, of which LM is the axis. The board muſt therefore be ſtopped in ſome line IPK below LGM, and ſo ſituated, that the ſum of all the momenta on each ſide oſ it ſhall be equal. This alone can hinder a rotation round the axis IPK. From what has been already demonſtrated, it appears, that this will be prevented if the edge meets the board in aline ΓPK paſſing through O the centre of oſcillation, which is ſituated in the line <hi rend="italic">gGh</hi>  paſſing through the centre of gravity perpendicular to the axis CC'. This line 10 K may therefore be called the <hi rend="italic">line</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">axis</hi>  of percuſſion.</p><p>But any point of this line will not do. It is evident that if the board ∏toulc⅛meet the fixed edge in the line <hi rend="italic">g</hi>  GO <hi rend="italic">h,</hi>  all motion will be ſtopped, for the motions on each ſide arc equal, and neither can prevail. But if it be ſtopped in the line ∕&gt; P <hi rend="italic">q,</hi>  there is more motion in the part <hi rend="italic">p q</hi>  DC' than in the part <hi rend="italic">p q</hi>  DC ; and if the ſupports at C and C' were that inſtant taken away, there would commence a rotation round the axis <hi rend="italic">p q.</hi>  Con-ſequently, if the body were not ſtopped by an edge, but by a ſimple point at P, this rotation would take place. The motions above and below P would indeed balance each other, but the motions on the· right and left lides of it would not. Therefore it is not enough for determining the centre of percuſſion that we have aſcertained its diſtance <hi rend="italic">g</hi>  0 from the axis of rotation by</p><p><hi rend="italic">ſp r *    ,</hi></p><p>the equation <hi rend="italic">g</hi>  0 = <hi rend="italic">f<hi rend="sub">v</hi>~"fyp</hi>  This equation only gives</p><p>us the line IOK parallel to CC', but not the point of percuſſion. This point (ſuppoſe it P) muſt be ſuch that if any line <hi rend="italic">p</hi>  P <hi rend="italic">q</hi>  be drawn through it, and conſidered as an axis round which a rotation <hi rend="italic">may</hi>  commence, it <hi rend="italic">ſhall not</hi>  commence, becauſe the ſum of all the momenta round this axis on the right ſide is equal to the</p><p>ſum of the momenta on the left. Let us inveſtigate in what manner this condition may be ſecured.</p><p>Let there be a body in a ſtate of rotation round the axis D <hi rend="italic">d</hi>  (ſig. 5.), and let G be its centre of gravity, and CGO a line through the centre of gravity perpendicular to the axis DC <hi rend="italic">d.</hi>  At the moment under conſideration, the centre of gravity is moving in the direction GH, perpendicular to the radius vector GC, as alſo perpendicular to a plane paſſing through the lines D <hi rend="italic">d</hi>  and CG. Let O be the centre of oſcillation, Draw the line <hi rend="italic">n</hi>  O parallel to D <hi rend="italic">d.</hi>  The centre oſ percuſſion muſt be ſomewhere in this line. For the point of percuſſion, wherever it is, muſt be moving in the ſame direction with the progreſſive motion of the body, that is, in a direction parallel to GH, that is, perpendicular to the plane DCG. And its diſtance from the axis D <hi rend="italic">d</hi>  muſt be the ſame with that of the centre of oſcillation. Theſe conditions require it therefore to be in ſome point oſ <hi rend="italic">η</hi>  0. Suppoſe it at P. Draw P<hi rend="italic">p</hi>  perpendicular to D <hi rend="italic">d.</hi>  P muſt be ſo ſituated, that all the momenta tending to produce a rotation round the line <hi rend="italic">p</hi>  P may balance each other, or their ſum total be nothing.</p><p>Now let A be any particle of the body which is out of the plane DCG, in which lie all the lines CGO, <hi rend="italic">ρP, n</hi>  OP, See. Draw its radius vector A <hi rend="italic">β</hi>  perpendicular to D <hi rend="italic">a,</hi>  and draw <hi rend="italic">a n</hi>  parallel to CG, and therefore perpendicular to D <hi rend="italic">a.</hi>  The plane A <hi rend="italic">a n</hi>  is perpendicular to the plane <hi rend="italic">Dan</hi>  (Euclid, XI. 4). Draw AL perpendicular to A <hi rend="italic">a,</hi>  and AZ perpendicular to <hi rend="italic">a n.</hi>  Then, while the body is beginning to turn round D <hi rend="italic">d,</hi>  the incipient motion of the particle A is in the direction AL, perpendicular to its radius vector A <hi rend="italic">α. </hi>This motion AL may be conſidered as compounded of the motion A Z, perpendicular to the plane DCG, and the motion Z L in this plane. It is evident that it is AZ only which is oppoſed by the external force Hopping the body at P, becauſe A ∕ alone makes any part of the progreſſive motion of the centre of gravity in the direction GH,</p><p>We have hitherto taken the <hi rend="italic">radii vefiοres</hi>  for the meaſures of the velocities or motions of the particles. Therefore the quantity of motion or the moving force of A is A. An, and this is exerted in the direction AL, and may be conceived as exerted on any point in this line, and therefore on the point L- That is, the point L might be conſidered as urged in this direction with the force A.A <hi rend="italic">a,</hi>  or with the two forces of which the force A. A <hi rend="italic">a</hi>  is compounded. The force in the direction AL is to the force in the direction AZ as AL to A Z, or as <hi rend="italic">a</hi>  A to <hi rend="italic">a l,</hi>  becauſe the triangles A <hi rend="italic">l</hi>  L and <hi rend="italic">a l</hi>  A are ſimilar. Therefore, inſtead of ſuppoſing the point L urged, by the force A.A <hi rend="italic">a,</hi>  acting in the direction AL, we may ſuppoſe it impelled by the force A.αZ, acting perpendicularly to the line A ∕, or to the plane DCG, and by the force A.AZ acting in this plane, viz. in the direction L n. This laſt force has nothing to do with the percuſſion at P. Therefore we need conſider the point L as only impelled by the force A.A Z. The momentum of this force, or its power to urge the plane DCG forward in the direction GH, by turning it round D eZ, muſt be A.aZ. aL. (√V. <hi rend="italic">B, </hi>This is equal to A. A <hi rend="italic">a <hi rend="sup">2</hi>,</hi>  becauſe <hi rend="italic">a I : a</hi>  A ~ <hi rend="italic">a</hi>  A : αL<hi rend="sub">3 </hi>and.A, A <hi rend="italic">a <hi rend="sup">2</hi>,</hi>  has been ſhown long ago to be the ge-</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>