<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>eb03-r03</title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>And we deduce immediately ſrom the premiſes that this rotation is performed round an axis paſſing through the centre of gravity G : for ſince the centre deſcribes a ſtraight line, it is never either above or below the axis of rotation, and is therefore always in it. This is a fundamental theorem, and our ſubſequent inveſtigation is by this means greatly ſimplified, being thus reduced to two problems : ι. To determine in what direction the axis paſſes through the centre of gravity.</p><p>2. To determine the angular velocity of the rotation, or how far the centre muſt ’ advance while the body makes one turn round the axis. 'Γhis eſtabliſhes the relation between the progreſſive and rotatory motions. It will contribute to our better conception of both theſe problems to ſee the reſult iι⅛ the preſent ſimple caſe.</p><p>It is evident, in the firſt place, that the impreſſions made on A and B are in lines A <hi rend="italic">o,</hi>  B <hi rend="italic">b</hi>  parallel to FP and G . ; and therefore the motions of the points A, G, and B, are made in one plane, viz. the plane FPG. The axis of rotation therefore muſt be a line drawn through G, perpendicular to this plane. If we give it any other poſition, one of the points A, B, or both of them, muſt quit this plane.</p><p>In the next place, in <hi rend="italic">bα</hi>  produced take <hi rend="italic">bc~~P&gt;C. </hi>Then ſuppoſing AC to be a rigid line connected with the ſy ſtem, it is evident that if there had been no rotation, the line BC would have kept parallel to its firſt poſition, and that at the end of the moment of time C would have been at <hi rend="italic">c.</hi>  The point C therefore has had, by the rotation, a backward motion <hi rend="italic">e</hi>  C, relative to the centre G or y, and this motion is equal to the progreſſive motion Gy of the centre ; therefore if we make G <hi rend="italic">y</hi>  equal to the circumference of a circle, whoſe radius is CG, the body will make one rotation round the centre of gravity, while this centre moves along G <hi rend="italic">y ; </hi>and thus the relation is eſtabliſhed between the two motions.</p><p>But farther, the point C has, in fact, not moved out of its place. The incipient motion has therefore been ſuch, that C has become a ſpontaneous centre of converſion. It is eaſy to ſee that this muſt always be the caſe, whatever may be the form of the rigid body or ſyſtem of particles connected by inflexible and inexten-ſible lines. Since the ſyſtem both advances and turns round an axis paſſing through its centre of gravity, there muſt be ſome point in the ſyſtem, or which may eb conceived as connectedwith it by an inflexible line, which moves backward, by the rotation, as faſt as the centre advances forward. A line drawn through this point parallel to the axis muſt in this inſtant be at reſt, and therefore muſt be a ſpontaneous axis of conversion. And, in this inſtant, the combined motions of rotation round an axis paſſing through the centre of gravity and the motion of progreſſion, are equivalent to, and actually con-ſtitute, an incipient ſimple motion of rotation round another axis parallel to the former, whoſe poſition may be afcertâined. But it is neceſſary to eſtabliſh this propoſition and its converſe on clearer evidence.</p><p>Therefore let G (ſig. ιo.) be the centre of gravity of a rigid ſyſtem of particles of matter, ſuch as we ſuppoſe a ſolid body to be. Let this ſyſtem be ſuppoſed to turn round the axis G <hi rend="italic">g,</hi>  while the axis itſelf is moving forward in the direction and with the velocity GI. Let the rotation be ſuch, that a particle A has the direction ant velocity A Z<hi rend="sup">,</hi>. Letus firſt ſuppoſe the progreſſive motion GI to be perpendicular to the axis G^. Tt will therefore be parallel to the planes of the circles deſcribed round the axis by the different particles. Let C G <hi rend="italic">g</hi>  be a plane perpendicular to G I. It will cut the plane of the circle deſcribed by A in a ſtraight line <hi rend="italic">cg,</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">g </hi>will be the centre round which A is turning. Therefore A <hi rend="italic">g</hi>  will be the radius vector of A, and A <hi rend="italic">h</hi>  is perpendicular to <hi rend="italic">i∖ g.</hi>  Let A <hi rend="italic">d</hi>  be perpendicular to <hi rend="italic">c g,</hi>  and in A <hi rend="italic">d</hi>  take A <hi rend="italic">e</hi>  equal to G I or <hi rend="italic">g i.</hi>  It is evident, that the abſolute motion of A is compounded of the motions A <hi rend="italic">e</hi>  and A <hi rend="italic">h,</hi>  and is the diagonal A<hi rend="italic">ſ</hi>  of the parallelogram A <hi rend="italic">e ſ h.</hi>  In the line <hi rend="italic">g c,</hi>  which is perpendicular to G <hi rend="italic">g,</hi>  take <hi rend="italic">g c</hi>  to <hi rend="italic">g</hi>  A, as A <hi rend="italic">e</hi>  to A <hi rend="italic">h, </hi>and draw <hi rend="italic">c</hi>  C parallel to <hi rend="italic">g</hi>  G, and produce <hi rend="italic">k&gt;</hi>  A till it cut <hi rend="italic">c g</hi>  in <hi rend="italic">n.</hi>  We ſay that C <hi rend="italic">c</hi>  is in this moment a ſpontaneous axis of converſion ; ſor, becauſe A <hi rend="italic">η</hi>  is perpendicular to A^∙ and A <hi rend="italic">d</hi>  to Cy, the angle c<hi rend="sub">t</hi>y A is equal to<hi rend="italic">d An,</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">ſh</hi>  A. Therefore, ſince <hi rend="italic">εg : g</hi>  A <hi rend="italic">— ſh : h A,</hi>  the triangles <hi rend="italic">eg</hi>  A and<hi rend="italic">ſ h A</hi>  are ſimilar, and the angle <hi rend="italic">g</hi>  A <hi rend="italic">c</hi>  is equal to <hi rend="italic">h</hi>  A<hi rend="italic">ſ.</hi>  Take away the common angles A<hi rend="italic">ſ,</hi>  and the remaining angle <hi rend="italic">c</hi>  A <hi rend="italic">f</hi>  is equal to the remaining angle <hi rend="italic">h</hi>  A <hi rend="italic">g,</hi>  and Aj<hi rend="sup">r</hi>is perpendicular to A<hi rend="italic">c,</hi>  and the incipient motion of A is the ſame in reſpect of direction as if it were turning round the axis <hi rend="italic">e</hi>  C.-Moreover, A <hi rend="italic">f</hi>  is to <hi rend="italic">'fh</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">g i</hi>  as A ί to <hi rend="italic">c g.</hi>  Therefore, both the direction and velocity of the abſolute motion of A is the lame as if the body were turninground the fixed axis <hi rend="italic">cC</hi>  ; and the combined motion A <hi rend="italic">e of</hi>  proςref-ſion, and the motion A <hi rend="italic">h</hi>  of rotation round Gy, are equivalent to, and really conſtitute, a momentary ſimple motion of rotation round the axis C <hi rend="italic">c</hi>  given in poſition, that is, determinable by the ratio of A <hi rend="italic">e</hi>  to A <hi rend="italic">h.</hi></p><p>On the other hand, the converſe propoſition is, that a ſimple motion of rotation round a fixed axis Cc, ſuch that the centre G has the velocity and direction GI perpendicular to C G, is equivalent to, and produces a motion of rotation round an axis <hi rend="italic">Gg,</hi>  along with the progreſſive motion GI of this axis. This propo’ſtion is demonſtrated in the very ſame way, from the conιide-ration that, by the rotation round C <hi rend="italic">c,</hi>  we have <hi rend="italic">c</hi>  A : <hi rend="italic">eg — A.J : g ι.</hi>  From this we deduce, that A <hi rend="italic">h</hi>  is perpendicular to <hi rend="italic">Ag,</hi>  and that <hi rend="italic">ſh</hi>  : A <hi rend="italic">h — c g</hi>  : y A; and thus we rcſolve the motion .Vj<hi rend="sup">r</hi>  into a motion A<hi rend="italic">h</hi>  of rotation round G y, and a motion A <hi rend="italic">e</hi>  of progreſſion common to the whole body.</p><p>But let us not confine the progreſſive motion to the direction perpendicular to the axis G y Let us ſuppoſe that the whole body, while turning round G <hi rend="italic">g,</hi>  is carried forward in the direction and with the velocity GK. We can always conceive a plane L G C, which is perpendicular to the plane in wſhich the axis G <hi rend="italic">g</hi>  and the direction G K of the progreſſive motion are ſituated— And the motion G K may be conceived as compounded of a motion Gt perpendicular to this plane and to the axis ; and a motion of tranſlation G L, by which the axis Hides along in its own direction. It is evident, that in conſequence of the firſt motion G I, there ariſes a motion of rotation round C c. It is alſo evident, that if, while the body is turning for a moment round C <hi rend="italic">c, </hi>this line be ſlid along itſelt in the direction <hi rend="italic">c</hi>  C, a motion equal to G L vzill be induced on every particle A, and compounded with its motion of rotation A F, and that if <hi rend="italic">ft</hi>  be drawn equal and parallel to G L, &lt;p will be the ſituation of the particle A when G is in K</p><p>And thus it appears, that when the progreſſive mo-</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>