<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>eb03-r03</title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>truck of the top carriage be to tuat of another truck fixed to the ſledge, in the proportion of the velocity of the top to that of the ſledge. Let a mark be made on the rim of each ; let the man at the ſledge make a ſignal every time that the mark on the ſledge truck is up-permoft. The mark on the carriage truck ſhould be uppermoſt at the ſame inſtant ; and in this way the foreman knows the ſtate of the rope at all times without quitting his llation. Thus, in making a cable of 120 fathoms, it is ufiιal to warp the yarns l8o fathoms, and to harden them up to 140 before doling. Therefore, in the cloſing, the top muſt move 140 fathoms, and the ſledge only 20. The diameter of the carriage truck ſhould therefore be ſeven times the diameter or the ſledge truck.</p><p>We have hitherto proceeded on the ſuppofition, that the twiſt produced by the cranks is propagated freely along the ſtrands and along the cloſing rope. But this is not the cafe.. It is almoſt unavoidable that the twiſt is greater in the neighbourhood of the crank which produces it. The ſtrands are frequently of very conſiderable weight, and lie heavy on the flakes. Force is therefore neceſſary to overcome their friction, and it is only the overplus that is propagated beyond the ſtake. It is proper to lift them up from time to time, and let them fall down again, as the ſawer does with his marking line. This helps the twiſt to run along the ſtrand. But this is not enough for the cloſed rope, which is of much greater weight, and much ſtiſſer.— When the top approaches the tackle-board, the heaving at the Hedge could not can e the ſtrands immediately behind the top to dole well, without *having previouſly produced an extravagant degree of twiſt in the intermediate rope. The effort of the crank muſt therefore be aſſiſted by men ſtationed along the rope, each ſur-niihed -with a tool, called a <hi rend="italic">vaoolcter.</hi>  This is a ſtout oak flick about three feet long, having a ſtrap of ſoft rope-yarn or cordage fattened on its middle or end. The 'ſtrap is wrapped round the laid rope, and the workman works with the ſtick as a lever, twilling the rope round in the direction of the crank’s motion. The woolders ſhould keep their eye on the men at the crank, and make their motion correſpond with his. Thus they ſend forward the twiſt produced by the crank, without either increaſing or diminiſhing. it, in that part cf the rope which lies between them and the Hedge.</p><p>It is uſual before taking the rope ſtom the hooks to heave a while at the ſledge end, in order to harden the <hi rend="sup">, </hi>rope a little. They do this ſo as to take it up about ∙<hi rend="sub">δ</hi><hi rend="sup">l</hi><hi rend="sub">δ</hi>-. The propriety or Impropriety of this practice de-peπdsbentirely on the proportion which has been previouſly obſerved between tiιe hardening of the ſtrands and the twiſting of the cloſing rope. It is, in all cafes, better to adjuſt theſe preciſely, and then nothing remains to be done when the top has arrived at the upper end of the walk. The making of two ſtrand and three ſtrand line pointed out the principle which ſhould be attended to in this,caſe ; namely, that the twiſt given to the rope in laying ſhould be preciſely what a perfectly ſoſt rope would give to itſelf. We do not fee any reaſon for thinking that the proportion between the number of turns given to the ſtrands and the number of turns given to the laid line by its own elaſticity, will vary by any difference of diameter. We would therefore recommend t© the artiſts to fettle this proportion by experiment. lhe line ſhould be made of tne ſineſt, ſmalleſt, and ſofteft threads or yarn. Theſe ſhould be made into ſtrands, and the ſtrands ſhould be hardened up in the direction ’contrary to the ſpinning twiſt. The rope ſhould then be laid, hanging perpendicularly, with a ſmall weight on the top to keep it down, and a very ſmall weight at the end of the rope. The number of turns given to the ſtrands ſhould be carefully noticed', and the number of turns which the rope takes of itſelf in cloſing. T<hi rend="sup">1</hi>ne weight ſhould then be taken off, and the rope will make a dew turns more. This whole number will never exceed what is neceſſary for the equilibrium ; and we imagine it will not fall much ſhort of it. We are clearly of opinion an exact ad-juſtment of this particular will tend greatly to improve the art of rope-making, and that experiments on good' principles for aſcertaimng this proportion would be highly valuable, becauſe there is no point about which the artiſts themſelves differ more in their opinions'and practice.</p><p>The cordage, of which we have been describing the manufacture, is ſaid to be hawser-laid. It is not uncommon to make ropes of four llra'nd6. Theſe are uſed for lhrouds, and this cordage is therefore called shroud-laid cordage. A rope of the lame fize and weight mnſt be ſmoother when it has four ſtrands, be-caute the ſtrands are ſmaller : hut it is more difficult to lay cloſe. When three cylindrical ſtrands are limply laid together, they leave a vaciiity at the axis amounting to √-<hi rend="sub">g</hi>- of the ſection of a ſtrand. This is to be filled up by compreſſing the ſtrands by twiſting them. Each muſt fill up ſ of it by changing its ſhape ; and 4 of this change is made on each fide of the ſtrand. The greateſt change of ſhape therefore made on any one part of a ſtrand amounts only to <hi rend="sub">τ</hi>⅛-<hi rend="sub">5</hi>∙ of the ſection of the ſtrand. The vacuity between four cylinders is √<hi rend="sub">τ</hi> of one of them. This being divided into eight parts, is √<hi rend="sub">5</hi>- of a ilrand, and is the greateſt compreſſion which any part of it has to undergo. This is nearly five times greater than the former, and muſt be more difficult to produce. Indeed it may be ſeen by looking at the figures 11. and 12. that it will be eafier to compreſs a ſtrand into the obtuſe angle of .120 degrees than into the right angle of 90 ; and without reaſoning more about the matter, it appears that the difficulty will increaſe w<hi rend="sup">τ</hi>ith the number of ſtrands. Sixdlrands muſt touch each other, and form an arch leaving a hollow in the middle, into which one of the ſtrands will flip, and then the reſt will not completely furround it. Such a rope would be uneven on the ſurface. It would be weak ; becauſe the central ſtrand would be ſlack in compariſon of the reſt, and would not be exerting its whole force when they are juſt ready to break. We fee then that a four ſtrand rope muſt be more difficult to lay well than a hawſer-laid rope. With care, however, they may be laid well and cloſe, and are much uſed in the royal navy.</p><p>Ropes, aie made of four ſtrands, with a heart or ſtrand in the middle. This gives no additional ſtrength,: for the reaſon juſt now given. Its only uſe is to make’ the work better and more eaſy, and to ſupport all the ſtrands at the ſame diſtance from the axis of the rope. This is of great conſequence ; becauſe when they are at unequal diſtances from the axis, ſome muſt be more doping than.others, and they will not reſiſt alike. This</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>