<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>eb03-r03</title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>the moſt animated diſplay of eloquence, and in the moſt inſidious manner. In this letter he deſcribes himſelf as “ more vehement than· celebrated in his reſearches, but ſincere on the whole, even againſt himſelf ; ſimple and good, but ſenſible and weak ; often doing evil, and always loving good ; united by friendſhip, never by circumſtances, and keeping more to his opinions than to his intereſts ; requiring nothing of men, and not wiſhing to be under any obligation to them ; yielding no more to their prejudices than to their will, and preſerving his own as free as his reaſon; diſputing about religion without lſeentiouſneſs ; loving neither impiety nor fanaticiſm, but diſliking preciſe people more than bold ſpirits,” &amp;c. &amp;c. From this ſpecimen, the limitations he would appoint to this portrait may eaſily be dilcovered.</p><p>The letters of La Montaigne appeared ſoon after ; but this work, far leſs eloquent, and full of envious diſ-cuſſions on the magiſtrates and clergy of Geneva, irritated the Proteſtarit miniſters without effecting a reconciliation with the clergy of the Romiſh church. Rouſſeau had ſolemnly abjured the latter religion in 1753, and, what is ſomewhat ſtrange, had then reſolved to live^_ in France, a Catholic country. The Proteſtant clergy were not fully reconciled by this change ; and the protection oſ the king of Pruſſia, to whom the principality of Neufchatel belonged, was not ſuſſicient to reſcue him from that obloquy which the mim'ſter of Moutiers-Travers, the village to which he had retired, had excited againſt him. He preached againſt Rouſſeau, and his fermons produced an uproar among the people. On the night between the 6th and 7th September 1765, ſome fanatics, drove on by wine and the declamations of their miniſter, threw ſome ſtones at the windows of the Genevan philoſopher, who fearing new inſults, in vain fought an aſylum in the canton of Berne. As this Canton was connected with the republic of Geneva, they did not think proper to allow him to remain in their city, being proſeribed by that republic. Neither his broken ſtate of health, nor the approach of winter, could ſoften the hearts of theſe obdurate Spartans. In vain, to prevent them from the feartheyhad of the ſpreading of his opinions, did he beſeech them to ſhut him up in priſon till the ſpring ; for even this favour was denied him. Obliged to ſet out on a journey, in the beginning of a very inclement ſeaſon, he reached Straſ-bourg in a very deſtitute ſituation. He received from Marſhal de Contades, who then commanded in that place, every accommodation which could be expected from generoſity, humanity, and compaſſion. He waited there till the weather was milder, when he went to Paris, where Mr Flume then was, who determined on taking him with him to England. After having made ſome ſtay in Paris, Rouſſeau actually ſet out for London in 176b. Hume, much affected with his ſituation and his misfortunes, procured for him a very agreeable ſettlement in the country. Our Genevan philoſopher was not, however, long ſatisſied with this new place. He did not make ſuch an impreſſion on the minds of the Engliſh as he had done on the French. His free diſpoſition, his obdurate and melancholy temper, was deemed no ſingularity in England. He was there looked upon as an ordinary man, and the periodical prints were filled with ſatires againſt him. In" particular, they publiſhed a forged letter from the king of Pruſſia, holding up to ridicule the principles and •conduit of tl⅛is new Diogenes. Rouſſeau imagined there was a plot between Hume and ſome philoſophers in France to deſtroy his glory and repoſe. He lent a letter to him, filled with the moſt abuſive expreſſions, and reproaching him for his conduct towards him. From this time he looked upon Hume as a wicked and perfidious perſon, wſho had brought him to England with no other view than to expoie him to public ridicule ; which fooliſh and chimerical idea was nouriſhed by ſelſ-love and a reſtleſs diſpoſition. He imagined that the Engliſh philoſopher, amidſt all his kindneſſes, had ſomething diſagreeable in the manner of expreſſing them. The bad health of Rouſſeau, a ſtrong and melancholy imagination, a too nice ſenſibility, a jealous diſpoſition, joined with philoſophic vanity, cheriſhed by the falle informations of his governeſs, who poſſeſſed an uncommon power over him ; all theſe taken together, might tend to prepoſſeſs him with unfavourable ſentiments of ſome innocent freedoms his benefactor might have taken with him, and might render him ungrateful, wſhich he thought himſelf incapable of becoming. Meanwhile, theſe falſe conjectures and probabilities ought never to have had the weight with an honeſt mind to withdraw itſelf from its friend and benefactor. Proofs are always neceſſary in caſes of this kind; and that which Rouſſeau had was by no means a certain demonſtration. The Genevan philoſopher, however, certainly returned to France. In paſſing through Amiens, he met with M. Greſſet, who interrogated him about his misfortunes and the controverſies he had been engaged in. He only anſwered, “ You have got the art of making a parrot ſpeak ; but you are not yet poſſeſſed of the ſecret of making a bear ſpeak.” In the mean time, the magiſtratts of this city wiſhed to confer on him ſome mark of their eſteem, which he abſolutely refuſed. His diſordered imagination viewed theſe flattering civilities as nothing elſe than inſults, ſuch as were laviſhed on Sancho in the iſland of Barataria. He thought one part of the people looked upon him as like Lazarille of Tormes, who, being fixed to the bottom of a tub, with only his head out of the water, was carried from one town to another to amuſe the vulgar. But theſe wrong and whimſical ideas did not prevent him from aſpiring after a reſidence in Paris, where, without doubt, he was more looked on as a ſpectacle than in any other place whatever. On the ill July 1770, Rouſſeau appeared, for the firſt time, at the regency coffee-houſe, dreſſed in ordinary clothing, having for ſome time previous to this wore an Armenian habit. He was loaded with praiſes by the ſurrounding multitude. “ It is ſomewhat ſingular (ſays M. Sennebier) to ſee a man ſo haughty as he returning to the very place from whence he had been baniſhed ſo often. Nor is it one of the ſmalleſt inconſiſtencies of this extraordinary character, that he preferred a retreat in that place of which he had ſpoken ſo much ill.” It is as ſingular that a perſon under ſentence of impriſonment ſhould wiſh to live in ſo public a manner in the very place where his ſentence was in force againſt him. His friends procured for him, however, liberty of ſtaying, on condition that he ſhould neither write on religion nor politics : he kept his word ; ſor he wrote none at all. He was contented with living in a calm philoſophical manner, giving himſelf to the ſociety of a few tried friends, ſhunning the</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>