<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>eb03-r03</title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>cattle, ſiſh, bees, timber proper for every uſe, different kinds of wild beafts, metals, both of ſuperior as well as of inferior kind, different precious ſtones, &amp;c. This divifion is likewiſe moſt convenient for the habitation of mankind, on account of the temperature arid pleaſant-neſs of the air. The ſouth divifion has not that abundance of grain, but has the preference in different delicate kinds of fruit, quantity of fiſh, cattle, and wild animals, amongſt which there are ſeveral ſpecies different from thoſe which are found in the middle divifion. It exceeds greatly both the other divifιons in plants and roots fit for dying and for medical purpoſes, as well as for the table ; neither is it deprived of precious ſtones, as well as different metals.</p><p>The products of thoſe three diviſions conftitute the permanent and inexhauſtible riches of Ruffia ; for, befides what is neceffary ſor home conſumption, there is a great quantity of thoſe products exported yearly into foreign countries to the amount of ſeveral millions of rubles. Theſe productions are brought from different places to fairs, eſtabliſhed in different parts of Ruffia, where the merchants buy them up, and forward them to different port6, and other trading towns, for exportation into foreign kingdoms. Theſe fairs are likewiſe the places where a conſiderable quantity of goods imported from foreign kingdoms is diſpoſed of. The principal yarmankas, that iβ, fairs, are the yarmanka Makarievikaya, Korennaya, and lrbitſkaya.</p><p>The external commerce of Ruſlia may be divided into two different branches; iff, The commerce with the European nations, which is carried on by buying and felling goods either for ready money or upon credit. 2d, The commerce with the Afiatic nations, which is conducted by barter or exchange of goods.</p><p>The principal ports belonging to the firſt part of Ruffia are, on the Baltic ſea, -St Peterſhurgh, Riga, Vyborg, Revel, Narva, Frederickſham, and the Baltic port ; Archangel on the White ſea, and Kola on the Northern Ocean ; Taganrog on the ſea of Azov ; Kher-ſon, Sevaſtopole, Balaklava, Soudak,Theodofιa, Kerche, and Phanagoria on the Black ſea, befides others of ſmaller note. In theſe ports commerce iβ carried on, as well as in ſeveral trading towns ſituated on the Rentiers of Poland, Sweden, and Turkey.</p><p>The products of Ruffia exported into the different European kingdoms conſiſt chiefly in hemp, flax, different kinds of grain, tallow, hides, fail-cloth, iron, timber, linſeed, butter, hemp-oil, train-oil, wax, potaſhes, tar, tobacco, briſtles, linens, peltry, and other goods, the greateſt part of which is exported chiefly by way of St Peterſhurgh, Riga, and Archangel ; and in return from the European kingdoms they receive woollen cloths, different kinds of goods made of worlled, filk, cotton, and thread ; wines and beer, white and moiſt ſugars, filks, cotton unwrought, and yarn ; French brandy, liquors, aιrack, ſhrub, different iron tools, and toys ; gold and ſilver in bars, in foreign money, and in other things ; brilliants, pearls, galanterie goods, coffee, colours ; peltry, viz. beaver and otter fkins ; herrings, ſtock-fiſh, ſalt, tobacco, different trees, oil, horſes, china and earthen ware, <hi rend="italic">Sec.</hi>  The greateſt part of theſe goods is imported through the ports of St Peterſhurgh and Riga, but a conſiderable quantity is likewiſe admitted by land through different frontier cuſtom-houſee.</p><p>The principal goods exported into Afla are partly the products of Ruffia, and partly imported from other European kingdoms, and conſiſt of peltry and hides. The other goods are woollen cloths, bays, borax, bottles, printed linens, iron, and different kinds of ironware, calamanco«, kerſeys, glue, ifinglaſs, cochineal, indigo, laura, tinſel, gold and ſilver lace, ſoap ; all kinds of arms, as piſtols, guns, ſabres ; different kinds of linens, printed and glazed, ſtriped linen, ticking, pallock, craſh, &amp;c. From the Afiatic kingdoms they import different filk goods, raw filk, cotton, filk-wove ſtuffs, gold and ſilver in bars and in coin, cattle, horſes, &amp;c.</p><p>The mountains within Ruffia, as well as thoſe on its frontiers, abound with minerals of various kinds. Gold, filver, quickfilver, copper, lead, iron-ore, very powerful loadſtones, mountain-cryftal, amethyſt, topazes of different forts, agates, cornelian, beryl, chalcedony, onyx, porphyry, antimony, pyrites, aquamarines, cliryſolites, ophites, and lapis lazuli, hre found in them, befides marble, granite, trappe, maria or Muſcovy glaſs, of remarkable fize and clearneſs, baſaltes, and coal, &amp;c. ; and in every part of Siberia, but particularly in the plains of it, are found bones of animals uncommonly large, mammoth’s teeth (ſee Mammoth), and other foſſils.</p><p>In the Ruffian empire are many lakes of very large extent, ι. The Ladoga, anciently called <hi rend="italic">Nevo,</hi>  is the latgeſt lake in Europe, extending in length r75 and in breadth 105 verſts ; or it is 116 Engliſh miles long and near 70 broad. It lies between the governments of St Peterſhurgh, Olonetz, and Vyborg ; and communicates with the Baltic ſea by the river Neva, with the Onega lake by the river Svir, and with the Ilmen lake by the river Volkov. Several conſiderable rivers fall into it, as the Paſha, Sias, Oyat, and others. The Ladoga canal is made near this lake. 2. The Onega lake is ſituated in the government of Olonetz. Tt it above 200 verſts long, and the greateſt width of it does not exceed 80 verſts. 3. The Tchude lake, or Peipus, lies between the governments of St Peterſhurgh, Pſcov, Revel, and Riga. It is near 80 verſts' long and 60 broad. It joins to the lake of Pſcov by a large neck of water. The length of this lake is 50 and the width about 40 verſts. The river Velikaya flows into it. The river Narova comes out of the lake Peipus, which by the river Embakha communicates with the lake Wirtz-Erve, and from this latter flows the river Fellin, and runs into the bay of Riga. 4. The Ilmen lake, anciently called <hi rend="italic">Mοljk,</hi>  lies in the -government of Novogorod. Its length is 40 and width 30 verſts. The rivers Mſta, .Lovate, Shelone, and others, fall into it ; and only one liver, Volkov, runs out of it, by which it is joined with the Ladoga lake. 5. The Bielυ-Ozero, that is, the White Lake, lies in the government of Novogorod. It extends $0 verſts in length, and -about 30 in width. There are many ſmall rivers which run into it ; but only one river, Shekſna, comes out of it, and falls into the river Volga. 6. The Altin, or Altay lake, otherwiſe called the <hi rend="italic">Tel-tſk Lake,</hi>  is fituated in the government of Kolhivane. It extends in length 126 and in width about 84 verſts. The river Biya comes out of it, which being joined to the river Katounya, conftitute the river Obc. 7. The Baical Lake, otherwiſe called the <hi rend="italic">Bal-cal Sea,</hi>  and the <hi rend="italic">Holy Sea,</hi>  lies in the government of Irk-outſk. Its extent in length is 600, and in width from</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>