<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>eb03-r03</title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>will greatly 'aſſiſt our conception o'f the manner in which motion is thus produced in a diſtant particle, if we conſider the particles as ſo many little balls, connected with each other by ſlender ſpiral ſprings like cork-ſcrews. This would compoſe a maſs which would be compreſ-ſible, or which could be ſtretched, &amp;c. And if we give an impulſe to one of theſe balls, we ſhall ſet the whole aſſemblage in motion round any axis which we may ſuppoſe to ſupport it. Now any one of theſe balls is really and immediately moved by the elaſticity of the ſpiral wares which join it to its neighbours.</p><p>We are but little acquainted with the nature of theſe connecting forces. It can be learned only by the phenomena which arc their effects. Theſe are various, almoſt beyond defoliation ; but the mechanical philoſo-pher has little to do wfith this variety. '1 he diſtinctionS which are the immediate cauſes of fluidity, of hardneſs, ſoftneſs, elaſticity, ductility, are not of very difficult conception. There is one general fact which is ſuſſicient for our preſent purpoſe - the forces by which the particles of bodies act on each other are equal. This is a matter of unexcepted experience ; and no other foundation can be given to it as a law of mechanical nature.</p><p>An immediate conſequence of this law is, that wſhen two external forces A and B are in equilibrium by the intervention of a folid body (or rather w<hi rend="sup">r</hi>hen a ſolidbody fis in equilibrium betw<hi rend="sup">r</hi>een tw<hi rend="sup">r</hi>o external forces), theſe forces are equal and oppoſite ; for the force A is in factin immediate equilibrium wfith the oppoſite forces exerted by the particle to which it is applied, and is therefore equal and oppoſite to the force reſulting from the combination of all the forces which connect that particle with the ſeries of particles immediately adjoining. This reſulting force may with propriety be called tfie equivalent of the forces from the combination of which it reſults. The uſe of this term will greatly abbreviate language. This firſt ſet of connecting forces conſiſts of a number of diſtinct forces correſponding to each particle of the ſeries, and each force has an equal and oppoſite force correſponding to it : therefore the compound force by wſhich the firſt ſeries of particles acts on that to which the external force A is applied, is equal and oppoſite to the compound force which connects this ſirſt ſeries with the next ſeries. And the ſame thing muſt be ſaid of each ſucceeding ſeries of particles, till w<hi rend="sup">r</hi>e come at laſt to the particle to which the external force B is immediately applied. The force exerted by this particle is equal and oppoſite to that external force ; and it is equal to the compound force exerted by the ſecond ſeries of particles on that fide ; therefore the forces A and B are equal and oppoſite.</p><p>It reſults ſrom this propoſition, that <hi rend="italic">when any number of external forces are applied to a folid body, and it is in equilibrio between them, they are ſuch as would be in equilibrio iſ they were all applied to one point.</hi>  Let the forces «A, <hi rend="italic">b</hi>  B, cC (ſig. 2.), be applied to three particles of the folid body. Therefore <hi rend="italic">a</hi>  A is immediately in ■equilibrium with an equal and oppoſite force A a, reſulting from the compoſition of the force AD, wſhich connects the particles A and B, and the force AE ■which connects A wfith C. In like manner <hi rend="italic">b</hi>  B is immediately in equilibrio wfith B <hi rend="italic">ß,</hi>  the equivalent of the forces BF and BG j and c C is in immediate equilibrio</p><p>with the equivalent C χ of the forces CH and CI. We ſhall conceive it very clearly if we ſuppoſe the three forces A <hi rend="italic">a,</hi>  B <hi rend="italic">b,</hi>  C <hi rend="italic">c,</hi>  to be exerted by means of threads pulling at the folid body. The connecting parts be* tween A and B, as alſo between A and C, are ſtretched. The lines AB and AC may be conſidered as elaſtic threads. Each thread is equally ſtretched through its wfiιole length ; and therefore if we take AD to repreſent the force wfith which the particle A is held back by the particle B, and if we would alſo repreſent the force with wſhich B is held back by A, we muſt make BF equal to AD. Now (n<hi rend="sup">0</hi>  9.) the forces AD and BF are equal and oppoſite ; ſo are the forces AE and CI ; ſo are the forces CH and BG. Now it is evident, that if the ſix forces AD, BF, BG, CH, CI, AE, were applied to one particle, the particle would be iri equilibrio; for each force is accompanied by an equal and oppoſite force : and iſ the force A «■ were applied in place of AD, AE, the equilibrium w<hi rend="sup">r</hi>ould remain, becauſe A≈ is equivalent to AD and AE. The ſame is true of B<hi rend="italic">ß</hi>  and C χ. Therefore if the three forces A «, B <hi rend="italic">ß,</hi>  C <hi rend="sup">,</hi>, were applied to one point, they would be in equilibrio. Conſequently if the three forces a A,<hi rend="italic">b</hi>  B, <hi rend="italic">c</hi>  C, which are reſpectively equal and oppoſite to A ≈, B <hi rend="italic">ß, C</hi><hi rend="sup">x</hi>-, are ſo applied, they will be in equilibrio. It is plain that this demonſtration may be extended to any number of forces.</p><p>We may juſt remark by the bye, that if three forces are thus in equilibrio, they are acting in one plane ; and, if they are not parallel, they are really directed to one point : for any one of them muſt be equal and oppoſite to the equivalent of the other two ; and this equivalent is the diagonal of a parallelogram, of which the other two are the ſides, and the diagonal and ſides of any parallelogram are in one plane -; and ſince they are in one plane, anti any one of them is in equilibrio wfith the equivalent of the other two, it muſt paſs thro’ the ſame point wfith that equivalent, that is, through the point of concourſe of the other two. -</p><p>Theſe very limple propoſitions are the foundation of the whole theory of ſtatics, and render it a very ſimple branch of mechanical ſcience. It has been made ab-ſtruſe by our very attempts to Amplify it. Many elaborate treatiſes have been written on the fundamental property of the lever, and in them all it has been thought next to an inſuperable difficulty to clemonſtrate the equilibrium of a ſtraight lever when the parallel forces are inverſely as their diſtances from the fulcrum.</p><p>We think the demonſtrations of Archimedes, Fonſe-nex, D’Alembert, and Hamilton, extremely ingenious; but they only bring the mind into ſuch a ſtate of conception that it cannot refuſe the truth of the propoſition ; and, except Mr Hamilton’s, they labour under the diſadvantage of being applicable only to commen-ſurable tliſtances anti forces. Mr Vince’s, in the Philoſophical Tranſactions for 1794, is the moſt ingenious of them all ; and it is wmnderful that it has not occurred long ago. The difficulty in them all has ariſen from the attempt to ſimplify the matter by conſidering ∙a lever as an inflexible ſtraight line. Had it been taken out of this abſtract form, and conſidered as what it really is, a natural body, of ſome ſize, having its particles connected by equal and oppoſite forces, all «diſſi-culty would have vaniſhed.</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>