<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>eb03-r03</title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>true incipient axis of rotation, and the angular velocity, without the intricate proceſs which would otherwiſe have been neceſſary.</p><p>• If the body is of ſuch a ſhape, that the forces in the plane DCG do not balance each other, we ſhall then diſcover a momentum round an axis perpendicular to this plane. Compound this rotation in the ſame manner with the rotation round D <hi rend="italic">d.</hi></p><p>And from this ſimple view of the matter we learn (what would be difficult to diſcover in the other way), that when the centre of percuſſion does not coincide with that of rotation, the axis is in the plane DGC, though not perpendicular to PG. But when there is a momentum round an axis perpendicular to this plane, the incipient axis of rotation is neither perpendicular to PC, nor in a plane perpendicular to that paſſing through the centre in the direction of the impelling force.</p><p>We muſt content ourſelves with merely pointing out theſe tracks of inveſtigation to the curious reader, and recommending the cultivation of this moſt fruitful theorem of Father Friſi.</p><p>Theſe are by no means ſpeculations of mere curioſity, intereſting to none but mathematicians : the nobleſt art which is practiſedby man muſt receive great improvement from a complete knowledge of this ſubject. We mean the art of seamanship. A ſhip, the moſt admirable 6f machines, muſt be conſidered as a body in free ſpace, impelled by the winds and waters, and continually moved round ſpontaneous axes of converſion, and inceſſantly checked in theſe movements. The trimming of the ſails, the action of the rudder, the very diſpoſition of the loading, all affect her verſatility. An experienced ſeaman knows by habit how to produce and facilitate theſe motions, and to check or ſtop ſuch as are inconvenient. Experience, without any reflection or knowledge how and why, informs him what poſition qf the rudder produces a deviation from the courſe. A fort of common ſenſe tells him, that, in order to make the ſhip turn her head away from the wind, he muſt increaſe the ſuri'ace or the obliquity of the head ſails, and diminiſh the power of the ſails near the ſtern. A few other operations are dictated to him by this kind of common ſenſe ; but few, even of old ſeamen, can tell why a ſhip has ſuch a tendency to bring her head up in the wind, and why it is ſo neceſſary to crowd the tore part oſ the ſhip with ſails ; fewer ſtill know that a certain ſhifting of the loading will facilitate ſome motions in different caſes ; that the crew of a great ſhip running ſuddenly to a particular place ſhall enable the ſhip tcx accompliih a movement in a ſtormy ſea which could not be done otherwiſe ; and perhaps not one in ten thouſand can tell why this procedure will be ſucceſs-ful. But the mathematical inquirer will ſee all this ; and it would be a moſt valuable acquifition to the public, to have a manual of ſuch propoſitions, deduced from a careful and judicious conſideration of the circumſtances, and freed from that great complication and intricacy which only the learned can unravel, and expreffed in a familiar manner, clothed with ſuch reaſoning as will be intelligible to the unlearned ; and though not accurate, yet perſuaſive. Mr Bouguer, in his <hi rend="italic">'Traité du Navire,</hi>  and in his <hi rend="italic">Manœuvre des Paiſſeaux,</hi>  has delivered a great deal of uſeful information on this ſubject ; and Mr Bezout has made a very uſeful abſtract of theſe works in his <hi rend="italic">Cours de Mathématique.</hi>  But the ſubject iβ left by them in a form far too abſtruſe to be of any general uſe : and it is unfortunately ſo combined with or founded on a falſe theory of the action and reſiſtance of fluids, that many of the propoſitions are totally inconſiſtent with experience, and many maxims of ſea-manſhip are falſe. This has occaſioned theſe doctrines to bc neglected altogether. Few of our proſeſſional ſeamen have the preparatory knowledge neceſſary for improving the ſcience ; but it would be a work of immenſe utility, and would acquire great reputation to the perſon who ſucceſsfully proſecutes it.</p><p>We ſhall mention under the article Seamanship the chief problems, and point out the mechanical principles by wſhich they may be ſolved.</p><p>RÖTHERAM, a town in the Weft Riding of Yorkſhire, ſeated on the river Don, near which there is a handſome ſtoneſhridge. It is a well-built place, and the market is large for proviſions. W. Long. ι. io. N. Lat. 53. 25.</p><p>ROTHSAY, a town in the iſle of Bute, oſ which it is the capital. It is a well-built town of ſmall houſes, and about 200 families ;· and is within theſe few years much improved. It has a good pier, and is ſeated at the bottom of a fine bay, whoſe mouth lies exactly oppoſite to Loch Steven in Cowal. Here is a fine depth of water, a ſecure retreat, and a ready navigation down the Frith for an export trade. Magazines of goods for foreign parts might be moſt advantageouſly erected here. The women of this town ſpin yarn, the men ſupport themſelves by fiſhing. W. Long. 5.0. N. Lat. 55. 5°∙</p><p>Rothſay gives the title of Duke to the prince of Scotland, a title which was formerly accompanied with ſuitable revenues, powers, and privileges. Of the origin of this title we have the following account ſrom the pen of the learned Dr M<hi rend="sup">t</hi>Leod of Glaſgow. Some time between the 16th of March and the 26th of October 1398, John of Gaunt, who is ſtyled John duke of Aquitaine and Lancaſter, uncle to the king of England, and David, who is ſtyled earl of Carrick, eldeſt ſon of the king of Scotland, met for the purpoſe of ſettling the borders, and terminating all mattere in diſpute. At a ſubſequent interview between the ſame parties, David is ſtyled Duke of Rothſay. “ This innovation probably proceeded on an idea, to which the interview of the two princes might naturally give riſe, that it was unſuitable, and unworthy of the Scottiſh national dignity, that the princes of England ſhould enjoy a title of nobility, which was eſteemed to be of higher rank than that poffeſſed by the hereditary prince of Scotland.” And this, in the opinion of our author, was the occaſion of introducing the title of Duke into Scotland.</p><p>ROTTBŒLLIA, in botany ; a genus of the di-gynia order, belonging to the triandria claſs of plants. The rachis is jointed, roundiſh, and in many caſes filiform ; the calyx is ovate, lanceolated, flat, ſimple, or bipartite ; the florets are alteιnate on the winding rachis.</p><p>ROTONDO, or Rotundo, in architecture, an appellation given to any building that is round both within and without ; whether it be a church, a ſaloon, or the like. The moſt celebrated rotundo of the ancients is the pantheon at Rome. See Pantheon.</p><p>RO ΓTEN-stone, a mineral found in Derby (hire,</p></body></text></TEI>