<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>eb03-r03</title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>fortabîe repaſt. Both ſexes are remarkably healthy and robuſt, and accuſtom themſelves to ſleep every day after dinner.</p><p>The Ruffian women are remarkably fair, comely, ſtrong, and well-ſhaped, obedient to their lordly huſ-bands, and patient under diſcipline : they are even ſaid to be fond of correction, which they conſider as an infallible mark of their huſhand’s conjugal affection ; and they pout and pine iſ it be with-held, as if they thought themſelves treated with contempt and diſregard. Of this neglect, however, they have very little cauſe to complain ; the Ruffian huſhand being very well diſpoſed, by nature and inebriation, to exert his arbitrary power. Some writers obſerve, that, on the wedding-day, the bride preſents the bridegroom with a whip of her own making, in token of ſubmiſſion ; and this he fails not to employ as the inſtrument of his authority. Very little ceremony is here uſed in match-making, which is the work of the parents. Perhaps the bridegroom never ſees the woman till he is joined to her for life. The marriage being propoſed and agreed to, the lady is examined, ſtark· naked, by a certain number of her female relations ; and if they find any bodily defect, they endeavour to cure it by their own ſkill and experience. '1 he bride, on her wedding-day, is crowned with a garland of wormwood, implying the bitterneſs that often attends the married ſtate. When the prieſt has tied the nuptial knot at the altar, his clerk or ſexton throws upon her head a handful of hops, wiſhing that ſhe may prove as fruitful as the plant thus ſeattered. She is muffled up, and led home by a certain number of old women, the pariſh-prieſt carrying the croſs before; while one of his ſubalterns, in a rough goat-ſkin, prays all the way that ſhe may bear as many children as there are hairs on his garment. The new-married couple, being ſeated at table, are preſented with bread and ſalt ; and a chorus of boys and girls ling the epithalamium, which is always groſsly obſcene. This ceremony being performed, the bride and bridegroom are conducted to their own chamber by an old woman, who exhorts the wife to obey her huſhand, and retires. 1 hen the bridegroom deſires the lady to pull off one of his bu-ikins, giving her to underſtand, that in one of them is contained a whip, and in the other a jewel or a purſe of money. She takes her choice ; and if ſhe finds the purſe, interprets it into a good omen ; whereas ſhould ſhe light on the whip, ſhe conſtrues it into an unhappy preſage, and inſtantly receives a laſh as a ſpecimen of what ſhe has to expect. After they have remained two hours together, they are interrupted by a deputation of old women, who come to ſearch for the ſigns of her virginity : if theſe are apparent, the young lady ties up her hair, which before conſumma-tion hung looſe over her ſhoulders, and viſits her mother, of whom ſhe demands the marriage portion. It is generally agreed, that the Muſcovite huſhands are barbarous even to a proverb ; they not only adminiſter frequent and ſevere correction to their wives, but ſometimes even torture them to death, without being ſubject to any puniſhment for the murder.</p><p>The canon law of Muſcovy forbids the conjugal commerce on Mondays, Wedneſdays, and Fridays ; and whoever tranſgreſſes this law, muſt bathe himſelf before he enters thc church-porch. He that marries a ſecond wife, the firſt being alive, is not admitted farther than the church-door ; and if any man eſpouſes a third, he is excommunicated : ſo that though bigamy is tolerated, they nevertheleſs count it infamous, iſ a woman is barren, the huſhand generally perſuades her to retire into a convent : if fair means wfill not ſucceed, he is at liberty to whip her into condeſcenſion. When the czar, or emperor, has an inclination for a wife, the moſt beautiful maidens of the empire are preſented to him for his choice.</p><p>The education of the czarovitz, or prince royal, is intruſted to the care of a few perſons, by whom he is ſtrictly kept from the eyes of the vulgar, until he hath attained the 15th year of his age : then he is publicly expoſed in the market-place, that the people, by viewing him attentively, ⅛nay remember his perſon, in order to aſcertain his identity ; for they have more than once been deceived by impoſtors.</p><p>Such is the ſlavery in which the Muſcovites oſboth ſexes are kept by their parents, their patrons, and the emperor, that they are not allowed to diſpute any match that may be provided for them by theſe directors, however diſagreeable or odious it may be. Officers of the greateſt rank in the army, both natives and foreigners, have been ſaddled with wives by the ſovereign in this arbitrary manner. A great general ſome time ago deceaſed, who was a native oſ Britain, having been preſſed by the late czarina to v/ed one of her ladies, ſaved himſelf from a very diſagreeable marriage, by pretending his conſtitution was ſo unſound, that the lady would be irreparably injured by his compliance.</p><p>In Ruſſia, the authority of parents over their children is almoſt as great as it was among the ancient Romans, and is often excrciſed with equal ſeverity. Should a father, in puniſhing his ſon for a fault, be the immediate cauſe of his death, he could not be called to account' for his conduct ; he would have done nothing but what the law authorized himto do. Nor does this legal tyranny ceaſe with the minority of children ; it continues while they remain in their father’s family, and is often exerted in the moſt indecent manner. It is not uncommon, even in St Peterſhurgh, to ſee a lady of the higheſt rank, and in all the pomp and pride of youthful beauty, ſtanding in the court-yard with her back bare, expoſed to the whip of her father’s ſervants. And ſo little diſgrace is attached to this puniſhment, that the ſame lady will fit down at table with her father and his gutſts immediately after ſhe has ſuſſered her flogging, provided its ſeverity has not confined her to bed.</p><p>The Muſcovites are fond of the bagpipe, and have a kind of violin, with a large belly like that of a lute : but their muſic is very barbarous and defective. Nevertheleſs, there are public ſchools, in which the children are regularly taught to fing. The very beggars aſk alms in a whining cadence, and ridiculous fort of recitative. A Ruffian ambaſſador at the Hague, having been regaled with the beſt concert of vocal and inſtrumental muſic that could be procured, was aſked how he liked the entertainment ? he replied, “ Perfectly well : the beggars in my country ſing juſt in. the fame manner.” The warlike muſic of the Ruſſians conſiſt! in kettle-drums and trumpets : they likewiſe uſe hunt ing horns ; but they are not at all expert in the per</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>