<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>eb03-r03</title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ral books oſ the privy-council, which he had preſerved in his own poſſeſſion during the commotions which then agitated the country. Sir Orlando Bridgeman keeper oſ the great ſeal choſe him his ſecretary in 1677, an office which he enjoyed as long as Sir Orlando kept the ſeals. In 1678 he was a third time choſen member for Berwick, and a fourth time in the enſuing parliament in 1679· He was also a member of the parliament which was convened at Oxford. The different offices he had held afforded him favourable opportunities of acquiring a fortune, or at leaſt an independence ; yet, whether from negligence or prodigality, he was never poſſeſſed of wealth. Having run himſelf into debt, he was arreſted and committed to the King’s Bench pri-ſon, Southwark, where he lingered for the laſt ſix years of his life in the moſt deplorable condition. His memory and judgment were much impaired, partly by age and partly by the too frequent uſe of ſpirituous liquors. He died on the 12th of May 1690.</p><p>His “ Hiſtorical Collections of private Paſſages in State, weighty Matters in Law, remarkable Proceedings in Parliament,” were publiſhed in folio at different times. The ſirſt part, comprehending the years between 1618 and 1629, appeared in 1659. The copy had been entruſted by Oliver Cromwell to Whitelock, with inſtructions to peruſe and examine it. Upon peruſing it, he thought it neceſſary to make ſome alterations and additions. The ſecond part was publiſhed in 1680 ; the third in 1692 ; the fourth and laſt, which comes down to the year 1648, was publiſhed in 1701 ; and altogether made ſeven volumes. Theſe underwent a ſecond edition in 1721 ; and the trial of the earl of Strafford was added, which made the eighth. This work has been much applauded by thoſe who condemn the conduct of Charles I. and accuſed of partiality by thoſe who favour the cauſe of that unhappy monarch. One perſon in particular, Dr John Nelſon of Cambridge, in a Collection of the Affairs of State publiſhed by the command of Charles II. undertook to prove, “ that Ruſhworth has concealed truth, endeavoured to vindicate the prevailing detractions of the late times, as well as their barbarous actions, and with a kind of rebound to libel the government at ſecond-hand.” This accuſation ſeems to be carried too far. His principles indeed led him to ſhow the king and his adherents in an unfavourable light, and to vindicate the proceedings of parliament ; yet it cannot juſtly be affirmed that he has miſrepreſented or falsified any oſ the ſpeeches or facts which he has admitted into his collection. Perhaps he may have omitted ſome papers merely becauſe they were unfavourable to the party which he had eſpouſed ; and is therefore not to be conſidered as an impartial hiſtorian who relates the whole truth, but as an honeſt lawyer, who ſtates all his facts fairly and candidly, but paſſes over ſuch as are injurious to his client’s cauſe.</p><p>RUSSELIA, in botany : A genus of the trigynia order, belonging to the pentandria claſs of plants. The calyx is five-leaved ; the petals five above ; the capſule is one-celled and many ſeeded.</p><p>RUSSIA, a very large and powerful kingdom, partly in Europe and partly in Aſia, is bounded on the north by the Northern Ocean, or Frozen Sea ; on the eaſt it is waſhed by the Eaſtern Ocean, and is divided from America by Behring’s (formerly Anian) Straits, which are about 73 verſts @@(A) wide. From thence, towards the ſouth, it extends along the chain of the Aleoutſkie iſlands. which approach the north-weſt coaſt of America ; and from Kamtſchatka, towards the ſouth-weſt, it extends, by a chain of other iſlands, called Keurilſkie iſlands, as far as Japan ; on the ſouth it borders on the Black Sea, on the nations which dwell at the foot of the Caucaſian mountains, on a part of Perſia, the Caſpian Sea, the hordes of Kwghiſkaiſacki, on Ziungoria, Chineſe Mungalia and Daouria @@(b) ; and on the weft, on the Da-niſh and Swediſh Lapland, the Baltic Sea, Courland, Livonia, Lithuania, Poland, and Turkey in Europe.</p><p>Ruſſia occupies more than a ſeventh part of the known continent, and nearly the 26th part of the whole globe. Its greateſt extent from weft to eaſt, viz. from the 39¼ to 207¼ degree of longitude, is 168 degrees ; and if the iſlands of the Eaſtern Ocean be included, it will then be 185; ſo that the continental length of Ruſſia, viz. from Riga to Tchoukotſkoy Noſs, which is the eaſternmoſt promontory, will conſtitute about 8500 verſts. The greateſt extent of this empire from north to ſouth, that is, from the 78th to 50¼ degree of latitude, is 27¾ degrees. Hence the breadth of Ruſſia, that is, ſrom the Cape Taymour,· which is the north-eaſtern promontory, to Kiakhta, will conſtitute about 3200 verſts.</p><p>The greater part of this empire lies in the temperate zone, and a part of it, viz. that which is beyond the 66½ degree of latitude, lies in the frigid zone ; and the whole ſurface contains above 2,150,000 ſquare verſts. There therefore is not at preſent, and never has been in any period, an empire, the extent of which could be compared to that of Ruſſia. The length and breadth of this immenſe empire, taken in a ſtraight line, may be thus diſcovered. Its furthermoſt point or ſpot on the north is the Taymour Cape, which is the moſt north-eaſtern promontory in the government oſ Tobolſk, lying in the 78th degree of latitude ; its ſar-theſt point on the ſouth -is the mouth of the river Soulak, falling into the Caſpian Sea in the government of Caucaſus, lying in the 43d degree oſ latitude ; its weſternmoſt point is the iſland of Oezel in the government of Riga, in the 39¼ degree of longitude ; and the furthermoſt point of it on the eaſt is the Tchoukotſkoy Noſs, which is the moſt eaſtern cape in the government oſ Iikoutſk, lying in the 207¼ degree of longitude.</p><p>In ancient times Ruſſia was inhabited by various nations ; ſuch as Hunns, Scythians, Sarmatians, Maſſa-getes, Sclavonians, Cimbri, &amp;c. of whom an account is given under the various detached articles in this work.. The origin oſ the Ruſſians themſelves, though not prior to the ninth century, is ſtill covered with almoſt impenetrable obſcurity ; partly owing to the ignorance and barbarity oſ the people, and partly to the</p><lb/><lb/><p><hi rend="smallcaps">@@@(a)</hi>     Verſta is the uſual meaſure oſ roads in Ruſſia, 1166 yards and two feet.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">@@@(b)</hi>     Daouria is that extent of land wſhich is traverſed by the river Amour. It is ſo called on account of the Daouri, its ancient inhabitants, who were a race of the Toungooſi or Manjouri.</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>