<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>eb03-r03</title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>victorious monarch. However, in the reign of Miecz-ſlaus II. the ſucceſſor of Boleſlaus, the Ruffians again ſhook off the yoke, and a laſting peace was confirmed by the marriage of Mieczſlaus with the filler of Wolo-domir.</p><p>Jari∏aus now continued to enjoy the empire quietly, and was ſo much addicted to reading, that he devoted even a part of the night to his ſtudies. He invited men of letters to his court, and cauſed many Greek books to be tranſlated into the Ruffian language. It was he that in the year 1019, gave the people of Nowgorod ſeveral laws, under the title of <hi rend="italic">Gramota Sou-d,inaia,</hi>  to be obſerved in the courts of juſtice. Theſe are the firſt laws that were reduced to writing in Ruſſia ; and, what renders them remarkable, is the conformity they have with thoſe of the other northern nations. He founded a public ſehool at Novogorod, where he maintained and educated 300 children at his own expence. His court was the moſt brilliant of the north, and furniſhed an aſylum to unfortunate princes. He died in 1052 ; and fell into the ſame error which his father had committed, by dividing his dominions among his five fons. This produced a repetition of the bloody ſcenes which had been acted by the fons of Wolodomir ; the Poles took the advantage of the diſ-tractcd ſtate of affairs to make continual inroads and invaſions ; and the empire continued in the moſt deplorable ſituation till the year 1237, when it was totally ſubdued by the Tartars. We are not informed of any particulars of this remarkable event, farther than that innumerable multitudes of theſe barbarians, headed by their khan Batto, or Battus, after ravaging great part of Poland and Sileſia, broke ſuddenly into Ruſſia, where they committed the greateſt cruelties. Moſt of the RuſſiaH princes, among whom was the great duke George Sevoloditz, were made priſoners, and racked to death ; and, in ſhort, none found mercy but ſuch as acknowledged themſelves the ſubjects of the Tartars. The imperious conqueror impoſed upon the Ruffians every thing that is moſt mortifying in llavery ; inſiſting that they ſhould have no other princes than ſuch as he approved of ; that they ſhould pay him yearly a tribute, to be brought by the fovereigns themſelves on foot, who were to preſent it humbly to the Tartarian ambaſſador on horſeback. They were alſo to proſtrate themſelves before the haughty Tartar ; to offer him milk to drink; and, if any drops of it fell down, to lick theιq up ; a ſingular mark of ſervility, which continued near 260 years.</p><p><hi rend="sup">i</hi> George Seyolodſtz was ſucceeded by his brother Michael Sevoloditz Zernigouſki ; who oppoſed the Tartars, but was defeated by them, and loſt his life. He left three fons, Feodor, Alexander, and Andrew, whoſe wars with each other ended in the death of them all. A fon of Alexander, and of the ſame name, was then placed on the throne by the Tartqrs ; and his ſon Da-nilow, or Daniel Alexandrovitz, removed his court from Wolodimir to Moſcow, where he firſt aſſumed the title of<hi rend="italic">Great duke oſ Wolodimir and Moſcow.</hi>  Daniel Alexandrovitz left two fons, Gregory and John ; the former of whom, named <hi rend="italic">Kalita,</hi>  from a purſe he uſed always to carry about him filled with money for the poor, aſcended the throne ; but he was ſoon aſſaſſinated by another prince named <hi rend="italic">Demetri Michaelovit%,</hi>  who was himſelf put to death for it by the Tartars ; and</p><lb/><p>John, likewiſe ſurnamed <hi rend="italic">Kalita,</hi>  was then made czar. This John left three fons, John, Simon, anti Andrew ; and the eldeſt of theſe, commonly called <hi rend="italic">Ivan Ivano-vit%,</hi>  was made czar, with the approbation of the Tartars, on whom he was dependenr.</p><p>During theſe ſeveral reigns, which fill a ſpace oſ upwards of 100 years, and which all hiſtorians have paffed over for want of records concerning them, the miſeries of a foreign yoke were aggravated by all the calamities of inteſtine diſcord and war ; whilſt the knights of Livonia, or brothers of the ſhort-ſword, as they are ſometimes called, a kind of military order of religious, on one ſide, and the Poles on the other, catching at the opportunity, attacked Ruſſia, and took ſeveral of itβ<hi rend="sub">χ </hi>towns, and even ſome conſiderable countries. The Tartars and Ruffians, whoſe intereſts were in this caſe the ſame, often united to oppoſe their common enemies ; but were generally worſted. The Livonians took Pleſkow ; and the Poles made themſelves mailers of Black Ivuſſia, the Ukraine, Podolia, and the city of Kiow. Caſimir the Great, one of their kings, carried his conqueſts ſtill farther. He aſſerted his pretenſions to a part of Ruſſia, in right of his-relation to Boleſlaus duke of Halitz, who died without iſſue, and forcibly poſſeſſed himſelf of the duchies of Perzemyſlia, Halitz, and Luckow, and of the diſtricts of Sanock, Luback-zow, and Trebowla ; all which countries he made a province oſ Roland.</p><p>The newly-conquered Ruffians were ill-diſpoſed to brook the government of the Poles ; whoſe laws and cuſtoms were more contrary to their own than thoſe of the Tartars had been. They joined the latter to rid themſelves of the yoke ; and aſſembled an army numerous enough to overwhelm all Poland, but deſtitute of valour and diſcipline. Caſimir, undaunted by this deluge of barbarians, preſented himſelf at the head of a few troops on the borders of the Viſtula, and obliged his enemies to retire.</p><p>Demetrius Ivanovitz, ſon of Ivan Ivanovitz, who commanded in Moſcow, made frequent efforts to rid himſelf of the galling yoke. He defeated in ſeveral battles Maymay khan of the Tartars ; and, when conqueror, refuſed to pay them any tribute, and aſſumed the title <hi rend="italic">of great duke oſ Mulcoνy.</hi>  But the oppreſſors ol the north returned in greater numbers than before ; and Demetrius, at length overpowered, after a ſtruggle of three years, periſhed with his whole army, which, it we may credit hiſtorians, amounted to upwards of 240,oco men. .</p><p>Baſilius Demetrivitz revenged his father’s death. He attacked his enemies, drove them out of his dominions, and conquered Bulgaria. He made an alliance with the Poles, whom he could not ſubdue ; and even ceded to them a part of his country, on condition that they ſhould help him to defend the reſt againſt any new incurſions of the Tartars. But this treaty was a weak barrier againſt ambition. The Ruffians found new enemies in their allies ; and the Tartars ſoon returned.— Baſilius Demetrivitz had a ſon who was called after his name, and to whom the crown ought naturally to have deſcended. «But the father, ſuſpecting his legitimacy, left it to his own brother Gregory, a man of a ſevere and tyrannical diſpoſition, and therefore hated by the people, wlι∙o aſſerted the fon’s right, and proclaimed him their fovereign. I he Tartars took cognizance</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>