<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>eb03-r03</title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ready turning round an axis A <hi rend="italic">a</hi>  (fig. 17. J, receives an impulſe which makes it actually turn round another axis C r, there <hi rend="italic">has been propagated to each particle</hi>  a force preciſely competent to produce, not the motion, but the <hi rend="italic">change</hi>  of motion which takes place in that particle, that is, a force which, when compounded with the inherent force of its primitive motion, produces the new motion ; that is (by this theorem), a force wſhich alone would have cauſed it to turn round a third axis B <hi rend="italic">b, </hi>with a rotation making the other conſtituent of the actual rotation round C <hi rend="italic">c.</hi></p><p>This muſt be conſidered as one of the moſt important propofitions in dynamics, anti gives a great extenſion to the doctrine of the compofition of motion. We ſee that rotations are compounded in the ſame manner as other motions, and it is extremely eaſy to diſcover the compofition. We have only to ſuppoſe a ſphere deſeribed round the centre of the body ; and the equator of this ſphere correſponding to any primitive poſition of the axis of rotation gives us the direction and velocity of the particles ſituated in it. Let another great circle cut this equator in any point ; it will be the equator oſ another rotation. Set off an arch of each from the point of interſection, proportional to the angular velocity of each rotation, and complete the ſpherical parallelogram. The great circle, which is the diagonal of this parallelogram, will be the equator of the rotation, wſhich is actually compounded of the other two.</p><p>And thus may any two rotations be compounded. We have given an inſtance of this in the ſolution of the problem of the <hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps">Precession of the Equinoxes,</hi></hi>  Vol. XV. p. 463.</p><p>It appears plainly in the demonſtration of this theorem that the axis C <hi rend="italic">c</hi>  is a new line in the body. The change of rotation is not accompliſhed by a transference ' of the poles and equator of the former rotation to a new ſituation, in which they are again the poles and equator of the rotation ; for we ſee that in the rotation round the axis C <hi rend="italic">c,</hi>  the particle of the body which was formerly the pole A is deſeribing a circle round the axis C <hi rend="italic">c.</hi>  Not knowing this compofition of rotations, Newton, Walmefly, Simpſon, and other celebrated mathematicians, imagined, that the axis of the earth’s rotation remained the fame, but changed its poſition. In this they were confirmed by the conſtancy of the obſerved latitudes of places on the ſurface of the earth. But the axis of the earth’s rotation really changes its place, and the poles ſhift through different points of its ſurface ; but theſe different points are too near each other to</p><p>make the change ſenſible to the niceſt obſervation.</p><p>It would ſeem to rtſult from theſe obſervations, that it is impoſſible that the axis of rotation can change its poſition in abſolute ſpace without changing its poſition in the body, contrary to wſhat we∙ experience in a thouſand familiar inſtances ; and indeed this is impoſſible by any one change. We cannot by the impulſe of any one force make a body which is turning round the axis Aa change its poſition and turn.round the ſame material axis brought into the poſition C r. In the ſame way that a body muſt paſs through a ſeries of intermediate points, in going from one end of a line to the other, ſo it· muſt acquire an infinite ſeries of intermediate rotations (each of them momentary) before the fame material axis paſſes into another poſition, ſo as to become an. axis’ of rotation. A momentary impulſe may make a great change of the poſition of the axis of rotation, as it may make in the velocity of a rectilineal motion. Thus although the rotation round A <hi rend="italic">a</hi>  be indefinitely ſmall, if another equally ſmall rotation be impreſſed round an axis B <hi rend="italic">b</hi>  perpendicular to A <hi rend="italic">a,</hi>  the axis will at once ſhift to C <hi rend="italic">c</hi>  half way between them ; but a ſucceſſion of rotations is necefl'ary for carrying the primitive material axis into a new poſition, wſhere it is again an axis. This transference, however, is poſſible, but gradual, and muſt be accompliſhed by a <hi rend="italic">continuation </hi>of impulſes totally different from what we would at firſt ſuppoſe. In order that A may paſs from A to C, it is not enough that it gets an impulſe in the direction AC. Such an impulſe would carry it thither, if the body had not been whirling round A <hi rend="italic">a</hi>  by the mere perſeverance of matter in its ſtate of motion; but wſhen the body is already whirling round A <hi rend="italic">a,</hi>  the particles in the circle IP <hi rend="italic">i</hi>  are moving in the circumference of that circle ; and ſince that circle alſo partakes of the motion given to A, every particle in it muſt be <hi rend="italic">incejſant-ly</hi>  deflected from the path in which it is moving. The <hi rend="italic">continual</hi>  agency of a force is therefore neceſſary for this purpoſe ; and if this force be diſeontinued, the point A will immediately quit the plane of the arch AC, along which we are endeavouring to move it, and will ſtart up.</p><p>This is the theorem which we formerly ſaid would enable us to overcome the difficulties in the inveſtigation of the axis oſ rotation.</p><p>Thus we can diſcover what Mr Landen calls the evagations of the poles of rotation by the action of cen∙ , trifugal forces: For in fig. 16. the known velocity of∣ the ball A and the radius AC of its circle of rotation' will give us the centrifugal force by wſhich the balls <hi rend="italic">tend</hi>  to turn in the plane DA&lt;∕BD. This gives the, axis D <hi rend="italic">d</hi>  a tendency to move in a plane perpendicular to the plane of the figure ; and its ſeparation from the poles 1&gt; and <hi rend="italic">d</hi>  does not depend on the ſeparation of the connecting rod A B from its preſent inclination to D <hi rend="italic">d, </hi>but on the angle which the ſpiral path of the ball makes with the plane of a circle of rotation round <hi rend="italic">Dd. </hi>The diſtance of the new poles from D and <hi rend="italic">d</hi>  is an arch of a circle which meaſures the angle made by the ſpiral w<hi rend="sup">,</hi>ith the . circle of rotation, round the primitive axis. This-wall gradually increaſe, and the mathematical axis of rotation will be deſeribing a ſpiral round D and<hi rend="italic">d, </hi>gradually ſeparating from , theſe points, and again approaching them, and coinciding with them again, at the time that the balls themſelves are moſt of all removed from their primitive ſituation, namely, when A is in the place of B.</p><p>The ſame theorem·'alio, enables us to-find the inci-. pient axis of rotation in the complicated caſes which<hi rend="sup">1 </hi>are almoſt inaceeſſible by- means oſ the elementary prin-' ciples of rotation.</p><p>Thus, when the centres of oſcillation and-percuſſion do not coincide,, as we ſuppoſed in fig. 5. and 12. .Suppoſe, firſt,.that they do coincide, and find the poſition of the axis.a <hi rend="italic">b,</hi>  and the angular .velocity of the rotation. Then find the centre of percuſſion, the axis P<hi rend="italic">p,</hi>  and the momentum.round it, and the angular velocity which this momentum would produce. Thus we have obtained tw<hi rend="sup">τ</hi>o rotations round given axes, and with given angular velocities. Compound theſe rotations by this theorem, and we obtain the required poſition of the</p></body></text></TEI>