<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>eb03-r03</title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>he applied himſelf to the military art and to civil government. He had alſo a very ſingular natural defect, which, had it not been conquered, would have rendered him for ever incapable of accompliſhing what he afterwards did. This was a vehement dread of water ; which is thus accounted for. When he was about five years of age, his mother went with him in a coach, in the ſpring-ſeaſon ; and paſſing over a dam where there was a conſiderable water-fall, whilſt he lay aſleep in her lap, he was ſo ſuddenly awaked and frightened by the ruſhing of the water, that it brought a fever upon him ; and after his recovery he retained ſuch a'dread of that element, that he could not bear to ſee any ſtanding water, much leſs to hear a running ſtream. This averſion, however, he conquered by jumping into water ; and afterwards became very fond of that element.</p><p>Being aſhamed of the ignorance in which he had been brought up, he learned almoſt of himſelf, and without a maſter, enough of the High and Low Dutch languages to ſpeak and write intelligibly in both. He looked upon the Germans and Hollanders as the moſt civilized nations ; becauſe the former had already erected ſome of thoſe arts and manufactures in Moſcow, which he was deſirous of ſpreading throughout his empire ; and the latter excelled in the art of navigation, which he conſidered as more neceſſary than any other. During the adminiſtration of the princeſs Sophia, he had formed a deſign of eſtabliſhing a maritime power in Ruſſia ; which he accompliſhed by the means which we have recorded in his life.</p><p>Having reformed his array, and introduced new diſcipline among them, he led his troops againſt the Turks; ſrom whom, in 1696, he took the fortreſs of Azov, and had the ſatisfaction to ſee his fleet defeat that of the enemy. On his return to Moſcow were ſtruck the firſt medals which had ever appeared in Ruſſia. The legend was, “ Peter the first, <hi rend="italic">the auguβ emperor of Rujfia.”</hi>  On the reverſe was Azov, with theſe words, <hi rend="italic">ViSorious by fire and water.</hi>  Notwithſtanding this ſucceſs, however, Peter , was very much chagrined at having his ſhips all built by foreigners ; having beſides as great an inclination to have an harbour on the Baltic as on the Euxine Sea. Theſe conſiderations determined him to ſend ſome of the young nobility oſ his empire into foreign countries, where they might improve. In 1697 he ſent 69 young Ruffians into Italy ; moſt of them to Venice, and the reſt to Leghorn, in order to learn the method of conſtructing their galleys. Forty more were ſent out by his direction for Holland, with an intent to inſtruct themſelves in the art of building and working large ſhips : others were appointed for Germany, to ſerve in the land-forces, and to learn the military diſcipline of that nation. At laſt he reſolved to travel through different countries in perſon, that he might have the opportunity of profiting by his own obſervation and experience. Of this journey we have given a ſhort account elſewhere ; and ſhall here only add, that in executing his great deſign, he lived and worked like a common carpenter. He laboured hard at the forges, rope-yards, and at the ſeveral mills for the ſawing of timber, manufacturing of paper, wiredrawing, &amp;c. In acquiring the art of a carpenter, he began -with purchaſing a boat, to which he made a maſt himſelf, and by degree« he executed every part of the conſtruction of a ſhip·</p><p>Beſides this, Peter frequently went ſrom Sweden to Amſterdam, where he attended the lectures of the celebrated Ruyſeh on anatomy. He alſo attended the lectures of burgomaſter Witſen on natural philoſophy. From this place he went for a few days to Utrecht, in order to pay a viſit to King William III. of England ; and on his return ſent to Archangel a 60 gun ſhip, in the building of which he had aſſiſted with his own hands. In 1698 he went over to England, where he employed himſelf in the ſame manner as he had done in Holland. Here he perfected himſelf in the art of ſhip-building ; and having engaged a great number of artificers, he returned with them to Holland ; from whence he ſet out for Vienna, where he paid a viſit to the emperor; and was θn the point of ſetting out for Venice to finiſh his- improvements, when he was informed of a rebellion having broken out in his dominions. This was occaſioned by the ſuperſtition and obſtinacy of the Ruffians, who having an almoſt invincible attachment to thçir old ignorance and barbariſm, had reſolved to dethrone the Czar on account of his innovations. But Peter arriving unexpectedly at Moſcow, quickly put an end to their machinations, and took a moſt ſevere revenge on thoſe wſho had been guilty. Having then made great reformations in every part of his empire, in 1700 he entered into a league with the kings of Denmark and Poland againſt Charles XII. of Sweden. The particulars of this famous war are related under the article Sweden. Here we ſhall only obſerve, that, from the conclufion of this war, Sweden ceaſed not only to be a formidable enemy to Ruſſia, but even loſt its political conſequence in a great meaſure altogether.</p><p>Peter applied himſelf to the cultivation of commerce, arts, and ſciences, with equal aſſiduity as to the pursuits of war ; and he made ſuch acquiſitions of dominion even in Europe itſelf, that he may be ſaid, at the time of his death, to have been the moſt powerful prince of his age. He was unfortunate in the Czarovitz his eldeſt ſon, whom he contrived to get rid oſ by the forms of juſtice (ſee Peter I. note b),' and then ordered his wife Catharine to be crowned with the ſame magnificent ceremonies as if ſhe had been a Greek em-preſs, and to be recogniſed as his ſucceſſor ; which ſhe accordingly was, and mounted the Ruſſian throne upon the deceaſe of her huſhand. She died, after a glorious reign, in 1727, and was ſucceeded by Peter II. a minor, ſon toi the Czarovitz. Many domeſtſe revolutions happened in Ruſſia during the ſhort reign of this prince; but none was more remarkable than the diſgrace and exile of Prince Menzikoff, the favourite general in the two late reigns, and eſteemed the richeſt ſubject in Europe. Peter died of the ſmall-pox in 1730.</p><p>Notwithſtanding the deſpotiſm of Peter the Great and his wife, the Ruſſian ſenate and nobility, upon the death of Peter II. ventured to ſet aſide the order of ſucceſſion which they had eſtabliſhed. The male iſſue of Peter was now extinguiſhed ; and the duke of Hol-ſtein, ſon to his eldeſt daughter, was by the deſtination of the late empreſs intitled to the crown : but the Ruffians, for political reaſons, filled their throne with Anne ducheſs of Courland, ſecond daughter to John, Peter’s eldeſt brother ; though her elder fitter the ducheſs of Mecklenburgh was alive. Her reign was extremely prυfperous : and though ſhe accepted of the crown u»&lt;</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>