<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>eb03-r03</title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>company of the great, appearing to have given up all his whimſies, and affecting neither the character of a philoſopher nor a <hi rend="italic">bel eſprit.</hi>  He died of an apoplexy at Ermenon-ville, belonging to the marquis de Girardin, about ten leagues from Paris, July 2. 1778, aged 66 years. This nobleman has erected to his memory a very plain monument, in a grove of poplars, which con-ftitutes part of his heautifnl gardens. On the tomb are iaſcribed the following epitaphs :</p><p><hi rend="italic">Id repoſe</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">D </hi><hi rend="italic">Homme de la Nature Et de la Rente !</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Pit am impendere Hero *.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Hie j accent OJſa Jf. jl. Rouſſeau.</hi></p><p>The curious who go to ſee this tomb likewiſe ſee the cloak which the Genevan philoſopher wore. Above the door is inſcribed the following ſentence, which might afford matter for a whole book : “ He is truly free, who, to accompliſh his pleaſure, has no need of <hi rend="italic">the aſſiſlance of a fécond perſonl”</hi>  Rouſſeau, during his ftay in the environs of Lyons, married Mademoiselle le Vaſſeur, his governeſs, a woman who, without either beauty or talents, had gained over him a great aſcen-dancy. She waited on him in health and in ſickneſs : But as if ſhe had been jealous of poſſeſſing him alone, ſhe drove from his mind, by the moſt perfidious iniinu-ations, all thoſe who came to entertain him ; and when Rouſſeau did not diſmiſs them, ſhe prevented their return by invariably refufing them admittance. By theſe means ſhe the more eaſily led her huſhand into incon-ſiſtencies of conduct, which the originality of his character as well as of his opinions ſo much contributed to aſſiſt. Nature had perhaps but given him the embryo of his character, and art had probably united to make it more fingular. He did not incline to aſſociate with any perſon ; and as this method of thinking and living was uncommon, it procured him a name, and he difplayed a kind of fantaſticalneſs in his behaviour and his writings. Like Diogenes of old, he united Simplicity of manners with all the pride of genius ; and a large ſtock of indolence, with an extreme ſenlibility, ſerved to render his character ſtill more uncommon. “ An indolent mind (ſays he), terrified at every application, a warm, bilious, and irritable temperament, ſenſible alſo in a high degree to every thing that can affect it, appear not poſſible to be united in the ſame perſon : and yet theſe two contrarieties compoſe the chief of mine. An active life has no charms for me. I would an hundred times rather conſent to be idle than to do any thing againſt my will ; and I have an hundred times thought that I would live not amiſs in the Baſtille, provided I had nothing to do but juſt continue there. In my younger days I made ſeveral attempts to get in there ; but as they were only with the view of procuring a refuge and reſt in my old age, and, like the exertions of an indolent pa<hi rend="sup">v</hi>fon, only by fits and ftarts, they were »ever attended with the ſmalleſt ſucceſs. When misfortunes came, they afforded me a pretext of giving myſelf up to my ruling paſſion.” He often exaggerated his misfortunes to himſelf as well as to others. He endeavoured particularly to render intereſting by his description his misfortunes and his poverty, although the former were ſar leſa than he imagined, and notwith-ftanding he had certain reſources againſt the latter. In <hi rend="sup">1 </hi>other refpects he was charitable, generous, ſober, juſt, ' contenting himſelf with what was purely neceſſary, and refufing the means which might have procured him wealth and offices. He cannot, like many other ſo-phiſts, be accuſed oſ having often repeated with a ſtudied emphafis the word<hi rend="italic">Dir tue,</hi>  without inſpiring the ſentiment. When he is ſpeaking of the duties of mankind, of the principles neceſſary to our happineſs, of the duty we owe to ourſelves and to our equals, it is with a copiouſneſs, a charm, and an impetuofity, that could only proceed from the heart. He ſaid one day to M. de Buffon, “ You have aſſerted and proved before J. J. Rouſſeau that mothers ought to ſuckle their children.” “ Yes (ſays this great naturaliſt), we have all ſaid ſo ; but M. Rouſſeau alone forbids it, and cauſes himſelf to be obeyed.” Another academician ſaid, “ that the virtues of Voltaire were without heart, and thoſe of Rouſſeau without head.” He was acquainted at an early age with the works of the Greek and Roman authors ; and the republican virtues there held forth to view, the rigorous auſterity of Cato, Brutus, &amp;c. carried him beyond the limits of a ſimple eſtimation of them. Influenced by his imagination, he admired every thing in the ancients, and ſaw nothing in his contemporaries but enervated minds and degenerated bodies.</p><p>His ideas about politics were almoſt as eccentric as· his paradoxes about religion. Some reckon his <hi rend="italic">Social Compaft,</hi>  which Voltaire calls the <hi rend="italic">Unſocial Compact,</hi>  the greateſt effort his genius produced. Others find it full of contradictions, errors, and cynical paſſages, obſcure, ilharranged, and by no means worthy of his ſhining pen. There are ſeveral other ſmall pieces wrote by him, to be found.in a collection of his works publiſhed in 25 vols 8vo and 12mo, to which there is appended a very inſignificant ſupplement in 6 vols.</p><p>The moſt uſeful and moſt important truths in this collection are picked out in his Thoughts; in which the confident ſophiſt and the impious author diſappear, and nothing is offered to the reader but the eloquent writer and the contemplative moraliſt. There were found in his port-folio his Conſeſſions, in twelve books ; the firſt fix oſ-which were publiſhed. “ In the preface to theſe memoirs, which abound with characters well drawn, and written with warmth, with energy, and ſometimes with elegance, he declares (ſays M. Paliſſot), like a peeviſh miſanthrope, who boldly introduces himſelf on the ruins of the world, to declare to mankind, whom he ſuppoſes aſſembled upon theſe ruins, that in that innumerable multitude, none could dare to ſay, <hi rend="italic">I am better than that man.</hi>  This affectation of ſeeing himſelf alone in the univerſe, and of continually directing every thing to himſelf, may appear to ſome moroſe minds a fanaticiſm of pride, of which we have no examples, at leaſt ſince the time of Cardan.” But this is not the only blame which may be attached to the author of the Conſeſſions. With uneaſmeſs we ſee him, under the pretext of fin-cerity, diſſionouring the character of his benefactreſs Lady Warren. There are innuendos no leſs oſſenfive againſt obſcure and celebrated characters, which ought entirely or partly to have feeen ſuppreſſed. A lady of wit ſaid, that Rouſſeau would have been held in higher eſtimation for virtue, “ had he died without his confeſ-ſion.” The ſame opinion is entertained by M. Senne-</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>