<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>eb03-r03</title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>election oſ Sigiſmund I. a prince of a mild and peaceable diſpoſition, he ſent an army into Lithuania, and laid ſiege to Smolenſko. The place made a brave reſiſtance, till news arrived that the crown-troops of Poland were coming to their aſſiſtance, with the additional aid of 80,000 Crim Tartars ; on which the Ruffians returned home with the utmoſt precipitation. They were, however, quickly followed by the Poles, who reduced the czar, to ſubmit to ſuch terms as they pleaſed to impoſe. Baſilius remained quiet till he thought himſelf capable of revenging the injuries he had ſuſtained ; after which, pretending to ſet out upon ſome other expedition, he marched with a numerous army, and encamped in the neighbourhood of Pleſkow, where the Poles, prefuming∙ on the late treaty, received him as a friend and ally. But in the mean time the Muſeovite prieſts oſ the Greek church preached to their hearers concerning the expediency of having a fovereign of their own religion ; and brought them to ſuch a height of enthufιafm,that they murdered their magiſtrates, and opened their gates to the czar, who made them all ilaves, and ſent them away' to different parts, replacing them with Muſcovites, the better to ſecure his conqueſt. Soon after he took alſo the city of Smolenſko ; and the Swedes, alarmed at his rapid progreſs, deſired a prolongation of the truce, at that time ſub-liſting between the two ſtates, for 6o years longer. The duchy of Lithuania was the great object of the deſigns of Baſilius ; and to accompliſh his deſign, he ordered Ivan Czeladin, a man of great reſolution, and enterprifing even to raſhneſs, to march thither with 80,000 men. The army of the Poles did not exceed 35,000 men, but was commanded by a moſt experienced general. The two armies met on the oppoſite banks oſ the Dneiper, near Orſova, and the Poles paffed that river in fight of their enemies. Czeladin’s officers adviſed him to fall upon the enemy when about half of them had croſſed the river ; but that general, too confident of ſucceſs, replied, that the other half would then run away, and he was determined to gain a complete victory. The Lithuanians began the attack, but were repulſed by the Ruffians ; who imprudently following them, loſt an advantageous ſituation, and found themſelves at once expoſed to the full fire of the enemy’s artillery. The Poliſh cavalry then ruſhed in among them ſword in hand, and made dreadful havoc ; the trembling Ruffians ſcarce even attempting to defend themſelves. Thoſe who endeavoured to fly, fell into the Dneiper and'were drowned ; and all the reſt, including Czeladin himſelf, were made ſlaves.</p><p>Baſilius was at Smolenſko when he received the news of this dreadful defeat ; on which he immediately fled* to Moſcow, where his danger increaſed daily. The Crim-Tartars ravaged his dominions, and the emperor Maximilian, with whom he had been in alliance, deſerted him ; his troops, were utterly defeated in Iri-vonia, where he was obliged to ſubmirto a peace on diſhonourable terms ; but what theſe terms were hiſtorians do not inform.us. In the mean time, the king of Poland ſtirred up the Tartars to invade Ruſſia, while the Ruffian monarch in his turn endeavoured to excite them to an invaſion of Poland. Theſe barbarians, equally treacherous to both parties, firſt invaded and ravaged Podolia, a province of Poland ; and then having invaded Ruſſia and defeated the armies of the czar in the year 1521, they poured in thither in ſuch incredible multitudes, that they quickly made themſelves maſters of Moſcow. An army, which had been ſent to oppoſe their progreſs, was defeated near the riveT Occa ; and the czar’s brother Andrew, who commanded it, was the very firſt who fled. Baſilius with great difficulty made his way to Novogorod ; ſo terrified, that he hid himſelf by the way under a haycock, to avoid a ſtraggling party of the enemy. The Tartars, however, ſoon obliged him to ſign a writing, by which he acknowledged himſelf their vaſſal, and promiſed to pay, them a tribute of ſo much a head for every one of his ſubjects. Beſides this, Machmetgerei, the commander of the Tartars, cauſed his own ſtatuq to be ſet up at Moſcow, as a mark of his ſovereignty; compelled Baſilius to return to his capital, to bring thither in perſon the firſt payment of this tribute, and<hi rend="sub">i </hi>as a token of his ſubmiſſion, to proſtrate himſelf before his ſtatue. Machmetgerei then left Moſcow, and returned home with an immenſe booty, and upwards of 80,000 priſoners, who were made ſlaves, and ſold like cattle to the Turks and other enemies of the Chriſtian name. In his way back.he attempted to take the city of Rezan ; but was repulſed with conſiderable loſs by I wan Ko wen, who commanded in that place for the Ruffians. Here the Tartar general narrowly eſcaped with his life, his coat being ſhot through with a mu-ſket-ball ; andthe Muſcovites pulled down his ſtatue, and broke it to pieces as ſoon as the conquerors had left them.</p><p>The Tartars were no ſooner gone, than Baſilius began to talk in a high ſtrain of the revenge he intended to take of them ; but was never abſe to execute his threats. He died in 1533 ; and was ſucceeded by his ſon Ivan or John Baſilovitz, an infant of -five years of age.</p><p>During the minority of the young prince, his two uncles Andrew and George endeavoured to deprive him of the crown; but their attempts were defeated by the care and activity of his guardians ; and the Poles alſo immediately commenced hoſtilities, but could make little progreſs. The new czar, as ſoon a3 he entered the 19th year of his age, ſhowed an inclination ſor re-ſeuing his ſubjects out of that deſperate ſtate of ignorance and barbariſm in which they had been hitherto immerſed. Pie ſent a ſplendid embaſſy to the emperor Charles V. who was then at Augſhurg, to deſire the renewal of the treaty of friendſhip which had been concluded with his father Maximilian ; and offering to enter into a league with him againſt the Turks, as enemies to the Chriſtian religion ; for his farther information in which, particularly in regard to the doctrine and ceremonies of the Latin church, he requeſted that his ambaſſador might be allowed to ſend from Germany to Ruſſia proper prieſts to inſtruct him and his ſubjects. With theſe he likewiſe deſired to have ſome wiſe and experienced ſtateſmen, able to civilize the wild people under his government ; and alſo, the better to help to poliſh them, he requeſted that he would ſend mechanics and artiſts of every kind ; in return ſor all which he offered to furniſh two tons of gold yearly, for 20 years together, to be employed in the war againſt the Turks. The emperor readily agreed to the deſire of the czar ; and the Ruffian ambaſſador accordingly en-</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>