<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>eb03-r03</title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>the yarns muſt be exerting twice this force. Now let the ſame yarn, ſpun up to one-half, be made up in a ſtrand, and let the ſtrand be twiſted in the oppoſite direction to the ſpinning till it has acquired the ſatne elaſtſeſty fit for laying. The yarns are untwiſted. Sup-ρofe to three-fourths of the length oſ the fibres. They are now exerting only four-thirds of the force neceſlary for laying, that is, two-thirds of what they were obliged to exert in the other caſe; and thus we have ſtronger yarns when the ſtrands are equally ſtrained. But they require to be more ſtrained than the other ; which, being made of more twi 'ed yarn, ſoon,er acquire the elaſticity’' fit for laying. But ſince the elaſticſty which fits the ſtrand ſor laying does not increaſe ſo faſt as the ſtrain on the fibres of the yarn which produces it, it is plain, that when each has acquired that elaſticity which is proper for laying, the ſtrands made of the flack-twiſted yarn are the ſtrongeſt ; and the yarns are alſo the ſtrongeſt ; and being ſoſter, the rope will cloſe better.</p><p>Experience confirms all this ; and cordage, whoſe ſtrands are twiſted in the oppoſite direction to the twiſt of ſpinning, are found to be ſtronger than the others in a proportion not leſs than that of 7 to 6.</p><p>Such being the difficulty of making a large ſtrand, and its deſects when made, w<hi rend="sup">,</hi>e have fallen on a method of making great cordage by laying it tw’ſee. A haw-ſer-laid rope, flack ſpun, little hardened in the ſtrands, and flack laid, is made a ſtrand of a large rope called a <hi rend="italic">cable</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">cablet.</hi>  The advantages of this fabric are evident. The ſtrands are reduced to one-third or one-fourth of the diameter which they would have in a hawffer of the ſame ſize. Such ſtrands cannot have their yarns lying very obliquely, and the outer yarns cannot be much more ſtrained than the inner ones. There muſt therefore be a much greater equality in the whole ſubſtance of cable-laid cordage, and ſrom this we ſhould expect ſuperior ſtrength.</p><p>Accordingly, their ſuperiority is great, not leſs than in the proportion of 13 to 9, which is not far from the proportion of 4 to 3. A cable is more than a fourth part, but is not a third part, ſtronger than a hawſer of the ſame ſize or weight.</p><p>They are ſeldom made of more than three hawſers of three ſtrands each, though they are ſometimes made of three four-ſtranded hawſers, or of four three-ſtrand-ed. The ſirſt of theſe two is preferred, becauſe four ſmall ſtrands can be laid very cloſe ; whereas it is difficult to lay well four hawſers, already become very hard.</p><p>The ſuperiority of a cable-laid cordage being attributed entirely to the greater perfection of the ſtrands, and this ſeeming to ariſe entirely from their ſmallneſs, it was natural to expect ſtill better cordage by laying cables as the ſtrands of ſtill larger pieces. It has been tried, and wfith every requifite attention. But although they have always equalled, they have not decidedly excelled, common cables of the ſame weight ; and they require a great deal more work. We ſhall not therefore enter upon the manipulations of this fa- . bric.</p><p>There is only one point of the mechanical proceſs of rope-making which we have not conſidered minutely ; and it is an important one, viz. the diſtribution of the</p><p>total ſhortening of the yarns between the hardening of the ſtrands and the laying the rope. This is a point about which the artiſts are by no means agreed. There is certainly a poſition of the ſtrands of a laid rope which puts every part in equilibrio ; and this is what an elaſtic, but perfectly ſoſt rope (were ſuch a thing poſſible), would aſſume. But this cannot be diſcovered by any experiments made on large or even on firm cordage ; and it may not be thought ſuſſiciently clear that the pro-∣ portion which would be diſcovered by the careful fabri-<hi rend="sup">1 </hi>cation of a very ſmall and ſoſt line is the ſame that’ wfill fuit a cordage of any diameter. We muſt proceed <hi rend="sub">j </hi>much on conjecture ; and w;e cannot ſay that the arguments uſed by the partiſans of different proportions are very convincing.</p><p>The general practice, we believe, is to divide the whole of the intended ſhortening of the yarns, or the w'orking up into three parts, and to employ two of theſe in hardening the ſtrands, and the remaining third in cloſing the haw-ſer.</p><p>Mr Du Hamel thinks, that this repartition is injudicious, and that the yarns are too much ſtrained, and the ſtrands rendered weak. He recommends to invert this proportion, and to ſhorten one-third in the hardening of the ſtrands, and two-thirds in laying the hawſer. But if the ſtrain of the yarns only is conſidered, one ſhould think that the outſide yarn of a ſtrand will be more ſtrained in laying, in proportion to the yarn of the ſame ſtrand, that is, in the very axis of the rope. We can only ſay, that if a very ſoft line is formed in this way, it will not keep its twiſt. This ſhows that the turns in laying were more than what the elaſticity or hardening of the ſtrands required. The experiments made on ſoft lines always ſhowed a tendency to take a greater twiſt when the lines were made in the firſt manner, and a tendency to loſe their twiſt when made in Mr Du Hamel’s manner. We imagine that the true proportion is between theſe two extremes, and that we ſhall not err greatly if w’e halve the total ſhortening between the two parts of the proceſs. If working up to two-thirds be inſiſted upon, and if it be really too much, Mr Du Hamel’s repartition may be better, becauſe part of this working will quickly go off when the cordage is uſed. But it is ſurely better to be right in the main point, the total working up, and then to adjuſt the diſtribution of it ſo that the finiſhed cordage ſhall preciſely keep the form we have given to it. '</p><p>There muſt be the ſame uncertainty in the quadruple diſtribution of the working up a cable. When a cable has its yarns ſhortened to two-thirds, w<hi rend="sup">,</hi>e believe the ordinary practice has been, iff, To warp 180 fathoms; 2d, To harden up the ſtrands 30 fathoms ; 3d, To lay or cloſe up 13 fathoms ; 4th, To work up the hawſers nine fathoms ; 5th, To cloſe up eight fathoms. This leaves a cable of 120. Since Mr Du Hamel’s cxperi* ments have had an influence at Rochefort, the practice has been to warp 190, to harden up 38, to lay up 12; to work up the hawſers 1 o, and then to cloſe up fix ; andwfiιen the cable is finiſhed, to ſhorten it tw<hi rend="sup">r</hi>o fathoms . more, which our workmen call<hi rend="italic">throwing the turn well up.</hi>  This leaves a cable of 1 2 2 fathoms.</p><p>As there ſeems little doubt of the ſuperiority of cordage ſhortened one-fourth over cordage ſhortened one-third, the followfing diſtribution may be adopted : warp</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>