<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>eb03-r03</title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>is a kind of lane, known by the name of <hi rend="italic">Dlns-dykes. </hi>A circumſtance which beſel the unfortunate queen Mary, immediately after her forces were routed at the battle of Langſide, has ever ſince continued to cha-racteriſe this place with an indelible mark of opprobrium. Her majeſty, during the battle, ſtood on a riſing ground about a mile ſrom Rutherglen. She no ſooner ſaw her army defeated than ſhe took her precipitate flight to the ſouth. Dms-dykes unfortunately lay in her way. Two ruſtics, who were at that inſtant cutting graſs hard by, ſeeing her majeſty fleeing in hafte, rudely attempted to intercept her, and threatened to cut her in pieces with their ſcythes if ſhe preſumed to proceed a ſtep further. Neither beauty, nor even royalty itſelf, can at all times ſecure the unfortunate wſhen they have to do With the unfeeling or the revengeful. Relief however was at hand ; and her majeſty proceeded in her flight.</p><p>Adjoining to a lane called the <hi rend="italic">Back-row</hi>  ſtood the caſtle of Rutherglen, originally built at a period coeval, it is reported, with the foundation of the town. This ancient ſortreſs underwent ſeveral lieges during the unhappy wars in the days of king Robert Bruce, and it remained a place of ſtrength until the battle of Langſide ; ſoon after which it was deſtroyed by order of the regent, to revenge himſelf on the Hamilton family, in whole cuſtody it then was. The foundations of the buildings are now eraſed, and the ſite converted into dwelling-houſes and gardens.</p><p>The kirk of Rutherglen, an ancient building of. the Saxon· Gothic ſtyle, was rendered famous by two tranſ-nctions, in which the fate of Sir William Wallace and his country' was deeply concerned. In it a truce was concluded between Scotland and England in the year 1397 (Henry’s Life of Wallace, Book VI. verſe 862.), and in it Sir John Monteath bargained with the Engliſh to betray Wallace his friend and companion (Life of Wallace, Book XI. verſe 796)· This ancient building, having become incommodious, was, in 1794, pulled down, and one oſ a modern ſtyle was erected in its place. Buried in the area were found vaſt quantities oſ human bones, and ſome relics of antiquity.</p><p>No borough probably in Britain poffeſſes a political conſtitution or ſett more free and unembarraffed than Rutherglen. It was anciently under the. influence of a ſelf-elected magiſtracy, many oſ whom lived at a diſtance from the borough, and who continued long in office without interruption. Negligence on the one hand, and an undue exertion of power on the other, at length excited the burgeſſes, about the middle of the laſt century, to apply an effectual remedy to this evil. The community who, at that period, poſſeſſed the power of reforming the abuſes that had long prevailed in the management of the borough, were much aſſiſted in their exertions by<hi rend="sup">,</hi> a Mr David Spens town-clerk, a gentleman unbiaſſedby falſe politics, and who was animated with a high degree of true patriotiſm. Great oppoſition was at ſirſt made to the reform ; but the plan adopted by the burgeſſes was wifely laid, and was proſecuted with unremitting aſſiduity. They were proof againſt the influence and bribery of a party that ſtruggled to continue the old practice ; and having at length ſur-mounted every difficulty, they formed a new conſtitution or ſett for the borough, which, in 167 1, was approved of by<hi rend="sup">r</hi> all the inhabitants of the town, and afterwards inſerted in the records of the general convention of the royal boroughs of Scotland.</p><p>Rutherglen, in conjunction with Glaſgow, Renfrew, and Dumbarton, fonds a member to the Britiſh parliament. The fairs of this town are generally well attended, and have long been famous for a great ſliow of horſes, of the Lanarkſhire breed, which are eſteemed the beſt draught-horſes in Britain. The inhabitants of this borough ſtill retain fome cuſtoms of a very remote antiquity. One of theſe is the making of <hi rend="italic">Rutherglen four cakes.</hi>  The operation is attended with ſome peculiar rites, which lead us to conclude that the practice is of Pagan origin. An account of theſe rites is given in Ure’s Hiſtory of Rutherglen and Kilbride, p. 94. ; from whence we have taken the above account of this place, and which we do not heſitate to recommend to the attention of ſuch of our readers as are fond of natural and local hiſtory, being perſuaded that they will find it to be both an uſeful and entertaining performance.</p><p>RUTLANDSHIRE, is the leaſt county in England, it being but 40 miles in circumference ; in which are two towns, 48 pariſhes, and 3263 houſes. However, ſor quality it may be compared with any other county; the air being good, and the ſoil fertile both for tillage and paſtures ; and it not only<hi rend="sup">r</hi> affords plenty of corn, but feeds a grcat number of horned cattle and flreep. It is well watered with brooks and rivulets ; and the principal rivers are the Weland and the Waſh. It is bounded on the eaſt by Lincolnſhire ; on the· ſouth by the river Weland, which parts it from Northamptonſhire; and on the welt and north by Leiceſteiſhire. It has only two market-towns ; namely, Okeham, where the affizeâ and ſeffions are held, and Uppingham.</p><p>RUYSCH (Frederic), one oi the moſt eminent ana-tomiſts of which Holland can boaſt, was born at the Hague in 1638. After making great progreſs at home, he repaired to Leyden, and there proſecuted the ſtudy of anatomy and botany. He ſtudied next at Francker, where he obtained the degree of doctor oſ phyſic. He then returned to the Hague ; and marrying in 1661, dedicated his whole time to the ſtudy of his proſeſſion. In 1665 he publiſhed a treatiſe, entitled <hi rend="italic">Dilucidatio valvularum de variis lymphalicis et lafleis ; </hi>which raiſed his reputation ſo high, that he was choſen proſeſſor of anatomy at Amſterdam. This honour he accepted with the more pleaſure, becauſe his ſituation at Amſterdam would give him eaſy acceſs tt&gt; every requifite help for cultivating anatomy and natural hiſtory. After he ſettled in Amſterdam he was perpetually engaged in diſſecting and in examining with the moſt inquiſitive eye the various parts of the human body, tie improved the ſcience of anatomy by new diſcoveries ; in particular, he found out a way to preſerve dead bodies many years from putrefaction. His anatomical collection was curious and valuable. He had a ſeries of ſeetuſes of all ſizes, from the length of the little finger to that of a new born infant. He had alſo bodies of full grown perſons of all,ages, änd a vaſt number of animals almoſt oſ every ſpecies on the globe, befides a great many other natural cu-rioſities. Peter the Great of Ruſſia, in his tour through Holland in the year 1698, viſited Ruyſch, and was ſo chai med with his conversation, that he</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>