<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>eb03-r03</title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ether,, then parted, and have never met ſince. . The thing melted away without notice ; and the Princeſs Daſhkoſſ was handſomely given to underſtand, that her-counſeh were no longer neceſſary, and that ſhe could not do better than take the amuſements ol the tour of Europe. She was liberally ſupplied, and has ever ſince been treated with great kindneſs, but kept amuſed with ſomething very different from legillation.</p><p>In the mean time, many patriotic things were really done. Taxes were frequently remitted where they were burthenſome. Every perſon was declared free who had ſerved government without pay for two years. No man was allowed to ſend boors from -his cultivated •eſtates to his mines in Siberia, nor to any diſtant eſtates, but for the purpoſes of agriculture. Many colonies of German peaſants were in various places ſet-tled on the -crown-lands, to teach the natives the management of the dairy ; a branch of rural economy of which the Ruffians were till that period ſo completely ignorant, that there is not in their language an appropriated word for <hi rend="italic">butter,</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">cheeſe,</hi>  or even lor <hi rend="italic">cream.</hi></p><p>The Ruffians hoped to be likewiſe inſtructed in agriculture ; but the coloniſts were poor and ignorant ; and this part of the project came to nothing, like the great national ſchools. Other improvements however took place in favour of commerce ; for all barriers were removed, and goods ſuffered to paſs through the empire duty-free. The empreſs with great liberality encouraged the introduction of arts and manufactures. An academy was inſtituted of ſculptur/·, painting, and architecture, &amp;c. a magnificent and elegant building was erected for it, and mauy élevés ſupported in it at the expence of the erawn. Several very promiſing youths have been educated in that academy ; but as the Ruffians are childiſhly fond of finery, and cannot be perſuaded that any thing fine was ever done by their own countrymen, the ſtudents are all, on leaving the academy, ſuffered to ſtarve.</p><p>The empreſs, who has a very juſt taſte in architecture, has herſelf deſigned ſeveral buildings equally uſeful and ornamental to her capital (ſee Neva and Pete rsburgh) ; and while ſhe has thus diligently cultivated the arts of peace, ſhe has not neglected thole of war. She put her fleets on the moſt reſpectable footing, and procured a number of Britiſh officers to inſtruct her ſeamen in the ſcience oſ naval tactics. By land, her .ſucceſſes againſt the Turks, the Swedes, and the Poles (ſee Turkey, Sweden, and Poland), .compel us to believe, that her troops are better diſci-plined, 3∏d her generals more fl&lt;ilful, than any whom the greateſt of her predeceſſors could bring into the ■field ; and perhaps it is not too much to ſay, that the empire of Ruſſia, though the people are but juſt emer-.ging from a ſtate of barbariſm, is at thia day the moſt powerful in Europe.</p><p>Ruſſia is divided into two great parts by a range of mountains called <hi rend="italic">Ourat,</hi>  or the <hi rend="italic">Pelt,</hi>  which, through the whole breadth of it, form one continual uninterrupted barrier, dividing Siberia from the remaining Ruſſia.—-That part of Ruſſia which lies on this fide oſ the Oural mountains preſents a very extenſive plain verging weſtward by an eaſy deſcent. The vaſt extent of this plain has a great variety of different climates, foils, and products. The aoκthern past of it is very woody,</p><p>marſhy, and but little fit for cultivation, and has a ſenſible dediyity towards the White and the Frozen Seas. The other part of this vaſt plain includes the whole extent along the river Volga as far as the deſerts, extending by the Caſpian and the Azov Seas, and conſtitutea the fineſt part of Ruſſia, which in general is very rich, and fruitful, having more arable and meadow laud than wood, marſhes, or barren deſerts.</p><p>The part lying on the other ſide of the Oural moun« tains, known by the name of Siberia, is a flat tract of land of conſiderable extent, declining imperceptibly towards the Glacial Sea, and equally by imperceptible degrees riling towards the ſouth, where at laſt it forms a great range of mountains, conſtituting the borders of Ruſſia on the ſide of Chuta. Between the rivers Irtiſh, Obè, and the Altay mountains, there is a very extenſive plain, known by'the name of <hi rend="italic">liurabinſkaya Stepe<hi rend="sub">9</hi>, </hi>viz. the deſerts of Baraba, the northern part of which· is excellent for agriculture ; but the ſouthern part, on-the contrary, is a deſert full of ſands and marſhes, and very unfit for cultivation. Between the rivers Obe and Eniſſey there is more woodland than open ground ; and the other ſide of the Eniſſey is entirely covered with-impervious woods, as far as the lake Baical ; but the ſoil is fruitful everywhere ; and wherever the trouble has been taken of clearingit of the wood, and of draining it ſrom unneceffary water, it proves to be very rich, and fit for cultivation ; and the country beyond the Baical is ſurrounded by ridges of highſtony mountains. Proceeding on farther towards the eaſt, the climate of Siberia becomes by degrees more and more ſevere, the ſummer grows ſhorter, the winter longer, and the froſts prove more intenſe.</p><p>With reſpect to the variety of climates, as well as the produce of the earth, Ruſſia naturally may be divided into three regions or diviſions, viz. into the north· ern, middle, and ſouthern diviſions.</p><p>I'heſe were about <hi rend="italic">20</hi>  years ago ſubdivided into different governments, for the better adminiſtration of iu* ſtice.</p><p>The northern diviſion, beginning from the 57th degree oſ latitude, extends to the end of the Ruſſian dominions on the north, and includes the governments of St Peterſhurgh, Riga, Revel, Vyborg, Pſcov, Novogorod* Tver, Oloneti, Archangel, Vologda, Yaroſlavl, Koſtro-ma, Viatka, Ferme, and fobolſk. The middle diviſion is reckoned from the 57th to the 50th degree of latitude, and includes the governments of Moſcow» Smolenſk, Polotfl&lt;, Moghilev, Tchernigov, Novogorod-Bieverſkoy, Kharkov, Voronez, Kourſk, Orel, Kalou&lt; ga, Toola, Riazane, Vladimir, Niznei-Novogorod, Tambov, Saratov, Penza, Sinbiiſk, Kazane, Oufa, Kolhivane, and Irkoutſk. The ſouthern diviſion begins at the 50th degree of latitude, and extends to the end of Ruſſia on the ſouth, including the governments of Kiev, Ekatherinoſlav, Caucafus∙, and the province of Taurida. To this may be added the habitations of the Coffack6 of the Don.</p><p>The northern diviſion, though deficient in grain, fruit, and garden vegetables, has the preference before the other two in the abundance of animals, rare and valuable for their ſkins j in ſiſhes of particular forts, very uſeful for different purpoſes of life ; in cattle, and metals of inferior kinds, &amp;c. The middle diviſion of Ruſſia abounds in different kinds of grain, hemp, flax<hi rend="sub">ff</hi></p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>