<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:50:09Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>to Edward, who ordered Baliol to appear before him in perſon on the 25th of March 1293; but as Baliol did not obey this order, he ſummoned him again to appear on the 14th of October. In the mean time the Engliſh parliament drew up certain <hi rend="italic">ftanding orders</hi> in caſes of appeal from the king of Scots; all of which were harſh and captious. One of theſe regulations provided, “that no excuſe of abſence ſhould ever be received either from the appellant, or the king of Scotland reſpondent; but that the parties might have counſel if they demanded it.”</p><p>Though Baliol had not the courage to withſtand the ſecond ſummons of Edward, he behaved with conſiderable reſolution at the trial. The cauſe of Macduff being come on, Edward aſked Baliol what he had to offer in his own defence; to which he replied, “I am king of Scotland. To the complaint of Macduff, or to ought elſe reſpecting my kingdom, I dare not make anſwer without the advice of my people.”—Edward affected ſurpriſe at this refuſal, after the ſubmiſſions which Baliol had already made him; but the latter ſteadily replied, “In matters reſpecting my kingdom, I neither <hi rend="italic">dare</hi> nor <hi rend="italic">can</hi> anſwer in this place, without the advice of my people.” Edward then deſired him to aſk a farther adjournment, that he might adviſe with the nation. But Baliol, perceiving that his doing ſo would imply an acquieſcence in Edward’s right of requiring his perſonal attendance on the Engliſh courts, made anſwer, “That he would neither aſk a longer day, nor conſent to an adjournment.” — It was then reſolved by the parliament of England, that the king of Scotland had offered no defence; that he had made evaſive and diſreſpectful anſwers: and that he was guilty of manifeſt contempt of the court, and of open disobedience. To make recompenſe to Macduff for his impriſonment, he was ordered damages from the king of Scots, to be taxed by the court; and it was alſo determined that Edward ſhould inquire, according to the uſages of the country, whether Macduff recovered the tenements in queſtion by the judgment of the king’s court, and whether he was diſpoſſeſſed by the king of Scots. It was alſo reſolved, that the three principal caſtles of Scotland, with the towns wherein they were ſituated, and the royal juriſdiction thereof, ſhould be taken into the cuſtody of the king, and there remain until the king of Scots ſhould make ſatisfaction for his contempt and diſobedience. But, before this judgment was publicly intimated, Baliol addreſſed Edward in the following words: “My lord, I am your liege-man for the kingdom of Scotland; that, whereof you have lately treated, reſpects my people no leſs than myſelf: I therefore pray you to delay it until I have conſulted my people, left I be ſurpriſed through want of advice: They who are now with me, neither will nor dare adviſe me in abſence of the reſt of my kingdom. After I have adviſed with them, I will in your firſt parliament after Eaſter report the reſult, and do to you what I ought.”</p><p>In conſequence of this addreſs, Edward, with conſent of Macduff, ſtopped all proceedings till the day after the feaſt of Trinity 1294. But before this, term Edward was obliged to ſuſpend all proceedings againſt the Scots, by a war which broke out with France. In a parliament held this year by Edward, the king of Scotland appeared, and conſented to yield up the whole re</p><p>venues of his Engliſh eſtates for three years to aſſiſt Edward againſt his enemy. He was alſo <hi rend="italic">requested</hi> and <hi rend="italic">ordered</hi> by Edward to extend an embargo laid upon the Engliſh veſſels all over Scotland; and this embargo to endure until the king of England’s further pleaſure ſhould be known. He alſo requeſted him to ſend ſome troops for an expedition into Gaſcony, and required the preſence and aid of ſeveral of the Scottiſh barons for the ſame purpoſe. The Scots, however, eluded the commands of Edward, by pretending that they could not bring any conſiderable force into the field; and, unable to bear his tyranny any longer, they negociated an alliance with Philip king of France. Having aſſembled a parliament at Scone, they prevailed upon Baliol to diſmiſs all the Engliſhmen whom he maintained at his court. They then appointed a committee of twelve, four biſhops, four earls, and four barons, by whoſe advice every thing was to be regulated; and, if we may credit the Engliſh hiſtorians, they watched the conduct of Baliol himſelf, and detained him in a kind of honourable captivity. However, they could not prevent him from delivering up the caſtles of Berwick, Roxburgh, and Jedburgh, to the biſhop of Carliſle; in whoſe cuſtody they were to remain during the war between England and France, as a pledge of his allegiance. Notwithſtanding this, Baliol concluded the alliance with Philip; by which it was ſtipulated, that the latter ſhould give in marriage the eldeſt daughter of the count of Anjou to Baliol’s ſon; and it was alſo provided, that Baliol ſhould not marry again without the conſent of Philip. The king of Scotland engaged to aſſiſt Philip in his wars at his own expence, and with his whole power, especially if Edward invaded France; and Philip on his part engaged to aſſiſt Scotland, in cafe of an Engliſh invaſion, either by making a diverſion, or by ſending ſuccours.</p><p>Puffed up with the hopes of aſſiſtance from France, the Scots invaded Cumberland with a mighty army, and laid ſiege to Carliſle. The men abandoned the place; but the women mounted the walls, and drove the affailants from the attack. Another incurſion into Northumberland proved almoſt as diſgraceful. Their whole exploits conſiſted in burning a nunnery at Lameley, and a monaſtery at Corebridge, though dedicated to their patron St Andrew; but having attempted to ſtorm the caſtle of Harbottle, they were repulſed with loſs. In the mean time Edward, with an army equal in number to that of the Scots, but much ſuperior on account of its diſcipline, invaded the eaſt coaſt of Scotland. Berwick had either not been delivered according to promiſe, or had been reſumed by the Scots, and was now defended by a numerous garriſon. Edward aſſaulted it by ſea and land. The ſhips which began the attack were all either burnt or diſabled; but Edward having led on his army in perſon, took the place by ſtorm, and cruelly butchered the inhabitants, to the number of 8000, without diſtinction of ſex or age. In this town there was a building called the <hi rend="italic">Red-hall,</hi> which certain Flemings poſſeſſed by the tenure of defending it at all times againſt the king of England. Thirty of theſe maintained their ground for a whole day againſt the Engliſh army; but at night the building being ſet on fire, all of them periſhed in the flames. The ſame day the caſtle capitulated; the garriſon, conſiſting of 2000 men, marched out with all the honours</p></body></text></TEI>