<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:49:54Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Brought them were put to death as traitors. The king of England alſo, dreading the neighbourhood of the Norwegians, interpoſed in young Edgar’s favour, and gave Atheling the command of an army in order to reſtore his nephew. Donald prepared to oppoſe his enemies with all the forces he could raiſe; but was deſerted by the Scots, and obliged to flee: his enemies purſued him ſo cloſely, that he was ſoon taken; and being brought before Edgar, he ordered his eyes to be put out, condemning him at the ſame time to perpetual baniſhment, in which he died ſome time after.</p><p>The hiſtorians of theſe times inform us, that this revolution was owing to the interpoſition of St Cuthbert, who appeared to Edgar, informing him that he ſhould prove victorious, provided he repaired next day to his church, and received his banner from the hands of the canons; which he accordingly did, and proved ever afterwards a moſt grateful votary to his patron. During his reign a ſtrict friendſhip ſubſiſted between the courts of England and Scotland; owing to the marriage of Henry I. of England with the Princeſs Matilda, filler to Edgar. This has given occaſion to the Engliſh hiſtorians to aſſert that Edgar held the kingdom of Scotland as a feudatory of Henry; and to this purpoſe have forged certain writings, by which Edgar acknowledges “That he held the kingdom of Scotland by gift from his Lord William king of England; and with conſent of his ſaid lord, he gives to Almighty GOD, and the church of Durham, and to the glorious biſhop of St Cuthbert, and to biſhop William, and to the monks of Durham, and their ſucceſſors, the manſions of Berwick and Coldingham, with ſeveral other lands poſſeſſed by his father Malcolm: and this charter is granted in the preſence of biſhop William, and Turgot the prior; and confirmed by the croſſes of Edgar his brother, and other noblemen.” But that theſe writings are forged, appears from the non-exiſtence of the original charter, and from their being related in quite a different manner by ſome other authors. —For the ſame purpoſe a ſeal has been forged of Edgar fitting on horſeback, with a ſword in his right-hand, and a ſhield on his left arm, within a border of France. But this laſt circumſtance is a ſufficient proof of the forgery; ſince, in the ſame repoſitory in which this ſeal is kept, there are five charters of the ſame Edgar, which are undoubtedly genuine; and on the ſeals belonging to them he is repreſented ſitting on two ſwords placed acroſs, with a ſceptre in one hand, a ſword in the other, a royal diadem on his head, with this inſcription round it, <hi rend="smallcaps">Scotorum Basileus,</hi> which the beſt Engliſh antiquaries allow to have been a title denoting independency.</p><p>After a reign of nine years, Edgar died at Dundee, in the year 1107; and was ſucceeded by his brother Alexander I. ſurnamed the <hi rend="italic">Fierce</hi> from the impetuoſity of his temper. On his acceſſion to the throne, however, the Scots were ſo ignorant of his true character, on account of his appearance of piety and devotion, that the northern parts of the kingdom were ſoon filled with ravages and bloodſhed, by reaſon of the wars of the chieftains with each other. Alexander immediately raiſed an army, and marching into Moray and Roſsſhire, attacked the inſurgents ſeparately; and having ſubdued them all, he put great numbers of them to death. He then ſet himſelf to reduce the exorbitant power of the nobles, and to deliver the common people</p><p>from the oppreſſion under which they groaned. A remarkable inſtance of this appeared on his return from the expedition juſt now mentioned. In paſſing through the Mearns, he met with a widow, who complained that her huſhand and ſon had been put to death by the young earl their ſuperior. Alexander immediately alighted from his horſe, and ſwore that he would not remount him till he had inquired into the juſtice of the complaint; and, finding it to be true, the offender was hanged on the ſpot. Theſe vigorous proceedings prevented all attempts at open rebellion; but produced many conſpiracies among the profligate part of his private ſubjects, who had been accuſtomed to live under a more remiſs government. The moſt remarkable of theſe took place while the king was engaged in building the caſtle oſ Baledgar, ſo called in memory of his brother Edgar, who had laid the foundation-ſtone. It was ſituated in the Carſe of Gowrie, which, we are told, had formerly belonged to Donald Bane, but afterwards came to the crown, either by donation or forfeiture. The conſpirators bribed one of the king’s chamberlains to introduce them at night into the royal bed-chamber: but Alexander, alarmed at the noiſe, drew his ſword, and killed ſix of them; after which, by the help of a knight named <hi rend="italic">Alexander Carron,</hi> he eſcaped the danger, by fleeing into Fife. The conſpirators chiefly reſided in the Mearns, to which Alexander once more repaired at the head of an army; but the rebels retreated northwards, and croſſed the Spey. The king purſued them acroſs that river, defeated them, and brought to juſticc all that fell into his hands. In this battle, Carron diſtinguiſhed himſelf ſo eminently, that he obtained the name of <hi rend="italic">Skrimgeour</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Skrimzeour;</hi> which indeed is no other than the Engliſh word <hi rend="italic">skirmisher</hi> or <hi rend="italic">fighter.</hi></p><p>The next remarkable tranſaction of Alexander’s reign, as recorded by the Engliſh hiſtorians, was his journey into England, where he paid a vifit to Henry I. whom he found engaged in a war with the Welſh. The occaſion of it was this: Henry had planted a colony of Flemings on the borders of Wales, in order to keep that turbulent people in awe, as well as to introduce into his kingdom the manufactures for which the Flemings were famous. The Welſh, jealous of this growing colony, invaded England; where they defeated the earl of Chtſter and Gilbert Strongbow, the two moſt powerful of the Engliſh ſubjects. Alexander, in virtue of the fealty which he had ſworn for his Engliſh poſſeſſions, readily agreed to lead an army into Wales. There he defeated one of the chieftains, and reduced him to great ſtraits; but could not prevent him from eſcaping to Griffith prince oſ North Wales, with whom he was cloſely allied. Henry alſo marched agamſt the enemy, but with much worſe ſucceſs in the field than Alexander; for he loſt two-thirds of his army, with almoſt his whole baggage, by fatigue, famine, and the attacks of the Welſh. This loſs, however, he made up in ſome meaſure by his policy; for having found means to raiſe a jealouſy between the two Welſh chiefs, he induced them to conclude a peace, but not without reſtoring all his lands to the one, and paying a conſiderable ſum of money to the other. Alexander died in 1124, after a reign of ſeventeen years; and was buried at Dunfermline.</p><p>This prince, dying a bachelor, was ſucceeded by his younger brother David;  who interfered in the affairs</p></body></text></TEI>