<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:48:23Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ſoon after at Paris of a malady contracted from too intenſe application. A ſenſible obſtruction <hi rend="italic">in</hi> the right lobe of the liver had made a deciſive progreſs, which the return of ſummer, ſome ſimple medicines, a ſtrict regimen, and travelling, ſeemed to remove.</p><p>On his return into the country adjacent to Paris, his health however was ſtill doubtful; for it is well known that when the organization of one of the viſcera has been much deranged, deep traces of it will ever remain. His active mind, however, made him regardleſs of his health, and he conceived it his duty to profit by thoſe appearances of recovery which he experienced at the cloſe of the ſummer and the beginning of autumn, to put into order his travels into the iſlands of the Archipelago, intended as a continuation of his letters on Egypt. His warmth of temper was exaſperated by ſome lively criticiſms which had been made on his former productions, and he gave himſelf up to ſtudy with a degree of activity of which the conſequences were ſufficiently obvious. An obſtruction in the liver again took place, and made a new progreſs; his digeſtion became extremely languid; ſleep quite forſook him, both by night and by day; a dry and troubleſome cough came on; his face appeared bloated, and his legs more and more inflamed. The uſe of barley water and cream of tartar ſtill however promoted, in ſome degree, the urinary ſecretions, and afforded ſome little glimmering of hope. In this ſituation he returned to Paris in the beginning of the year 1788, to attend to the publication of his new work concerning the iſlands of the Archipelago, particularly the iſle of Candia. He had then all the ſymptoms of a dangerous dropſy, which became ſtill more alarming from the very exhauſted ſtate of the viſcera. The right lobe of the liver was extremely hard and ſenſible. The patient had ſhiverings without any regular returns, and his ſtrength was undermined by a hectic fever. At the ſame time ſtill more uneaſy ſymptoms took place, thoſe of a dropſy in the cheſt; but the circumſtances which deſtroyed all hope, and announced his approaching diſſolution, were a ſevere pain in the left ſide, with a very troubleſome cough, and a copious and bloody expectoration <hi rend="italic">(in hepaticis, </hi>ſays Hippocrates, <hi rend="italic">ſputum cruentum mortiferum};</hi> his reſpiration became more and more difficult; his ſtrength was exhauſted, and his death took place on the 4th of February 788, attended with every indication of the moſt copious overflowing in the cheſt, and of an abſceſs in the liver. — Thus was deſtroyed, in the vigour of his age, an author whoſe character and talents rendered him worthy of the happieſt lot.</p><p>Mr Savary’s genius was lively and well cultivated; his heart warm and benevolent; his imagination vigorous; his memory retentive. He was cheerful and open; and had ſo great a talent for telling a ſtory, that his company was not leſs agreeable than inſtructive. He did not mingle much with the world, but was ſatisfied with performing well the duties of a ſon, of a brother, and of a friend.</p><p>SAUCISSE, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Saucisson,</hi> in mining, is a long pipe or bag made of cloth well pitched, or ſometimes of leather, of about an inch and an halt diameter, filled with powder, going from the chamber of the mine to the entrance of the gallery. It is generally placed in a wooden pipe called an <hi rend="italic">aυget,</hi> to prevent its growing damp. It ſerves to give fire to mines, caſſions, bomb-cheſts, &amp;c.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Saucisson,</hi> is likewiſe a kind of faſcine, longer than the common ones; they ſerve to raiſe batteries and to repair breaches. They are alſo uſed in making epaulements, in flopping paſlages, and in making traverſes over a wet ditch, &amp;c.</p><p>SAVE, a river of Germany, which has its ſource in Upper Carniola, on the frontiers of Carinthia. — It runs through Carniola from weſt to eaſt, afterwards ſeparates Sclavonia from Croatia, Boſnia, and part of Servia, and then falls into the Danube at Belgrade.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">SAVER-krout.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">CroUte.</hi></p><p>SAVERN <hi rend="smallcaps">KE-Forest</hi> is ſituated near Marlborough in Wiltſhire, and is 12 miles in circumference, well ſtocked with deer, and delightful from the many viſtas cut through the woods and coppices with which it abounds. Eight of theſe viſtas meet, like the rays of a ſtar, in a point near the middle of the foreſt, where an octagon tower is erected to correſpond with the viſtas; through one of which is a view of Tottenham Park, Lord Aileſbury’s feat, a ſtately edifice erected after the model, and under the direction, of our modern Vitruvius, the Earl of Burlington, who to the ſtrength and convenience of the Engliſh architecture has added the elegance of the Italian.</p><p>SAVILE (Sir George), afterwards marquis of Halifax, and one of the greateſt ſtateſmen of his time, was born about the year 1630; and ſome time after his return from his travels was created a peer, in conſideration of his own and his father’s merits. He was a ſtrenuous oppoſer of the bill of excluſion; but propoſed ſuch limitations of the duke of York’s authority, as ſhould diſable him from doing any harm either in church or ſtate, as the taking out of his hands all power in eccleſiaſtical matters, the diſpoſal of the public money, and the power of making peace and war; and lodging theſe in the two houſes of parliament. After that bill was rejected in the houſe of lords, he preſſed them, though without ſucceſs, to proceed to the limitation of the duke’s power; and began with moving, that during the king’s life he might be obliged to live five hundred miles out of England. In Auguſt 1682 he was created a marquis, and ſoon after made privy-ſeal. Upon King James’s acceffion, he was made preſident of the council; but on his refuſal to conſent to the repeal of the teſt, he was diſmiſſed from all public employments. In that aſſembly of the lords which met after king James’s withdrawing himſelf the firſt time from Whitehall, the marquis was choſen their preſident; and upon the king’s return from Feverſham, he was ſent, together with the earl of Shrewſhury and lord Delamere, front the Prince of Orange, to order his majeſty to quit the palace at Whitehall. In the convention of parliament he was choſen ſpeaker of the houſe of lords, and ſtrenuouſly ſupported the motion for the vacancy of the throne, and the conjunctive ſovereignty of the prince and princeſs; upon whoſe acceſſion he was again made privy- ſeal. Yet, in 1689, he quitted the court, and became a zealous oppoſer of the meaſures of government till his death, which happened in April 1695. The rev. Mr Grainger obſerves, that “he was a perſon of unſettled principles, and of a lively imagination, which ſometimes got the better of his judgment. He would never loſe</p></body></text></TEI>