<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:49:44Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>to form any deciſive opinion concerning the tranſactions of this reign. All agree, however, that it was but ſhort; and that he was ſuccceded by Gregory the ſon of Dongal, contemporary with Alfred of England, and that both princes deſervedly acquired the name of <hi rend="italic">Great. </hi>The Danes at their departure had left the Picts in poſſeſſion of Fife. Againſt them Gregory immediately marched, and quickly drove them into the north oſ England, where their confederates were already maſters of Northumberland and York. In their way thither they threw a garriſon into the town of Berwick; but this was preſently reduced by Gregory, who put to the ſword all the Danes, but ſpared the lives of the Picts. From Berwick, Gregory purſued the Danes into Northumberland, where he defeated them; and paſſed the winter in Berwick. He then marched againſt the Cumbrians, who being moſtly Picts were in alliance with the Danes. Them he eaſily overcame, and obliged to yield up all the lands they had formerly poſſeſſed belonging to the Scots, at the ſame time that he agreed to protect them from the power of the Danes. In a ſhort time, however, Conſtantine the king of the Cumbrians violated the convention he had made, and invaded Annandale; but was defeated and killed by Gregory near Lochmaben. After this victory Gregory entirely reduced the counties of Cumberland and Weſtmoreland, which, it is ſaid, were ceded to him by Alfred the Great; and indeed the ſituation of Alſred’s affairs at this time renders ſuch a ceſſion by no means improbable.</p><p>We next find Gregory engaged in a war with the Iriſh, to ſupport Donach, an Iriſh prince, againſt two rebellious noblemen. The Iriſh were the firſt aggreſſors, and invaded Galloway; but being repulſed with great loſs, Gregory went over to Ireland in perſon, where the two chieftains, who had been enemies to each other before, now joined their forces in order to oppoſe the common enemy. The firſt engagement proved fatal to one of their chiefs named <hi rend="italic">Brian,</hi> who was killed with a great number of his followers. After this victory Gregory reduced Dundalk and Drogheda. On his way to Dublin he was oppoſed by a chieftain named <hi rend="italic">Corneil,</hi> who ſhared the fate of his confederate, being alſo killed, and his army entirely defeated. Gregory then became guardian to the young prince whom he came to aſſiſt, appointed a regency, and obliged them to ſwear that they would never admit into the country either a Dane or an Engliſhman without his conſent. Having then placed garriſons in the ſtrongeſt fortreſſes, he returned to Scotland, where he built the city of Aberdeen; and died in the year 892, at his caſtle of Dundore in the Garioch.</p><p>Gregory was ſucceeded by Donald III. the ſon of Conſtantine, who imitated the virtues of his predeceſſor. The Scots hiſtorians unanimouſly agree that Northumberland was at that time in the hands of their countrymen; while the Engliſh as unanimouſly affirm that it was ſubject to the Danes, who paid homage to Alfred. Be this as it will, however, Donald continued to live on good terms with the Engliſh monarch, and ſent him a body of forces, who proved of conſiderable advantage to him in his wars with the Danes. The reign of Donald was but ſhort; for having marched againſt ſome robbers (probably no other than the Danes) who had invaded and ravaged the counties of Murray and Roſs, he died at Forres ſoon after, having defeated and ſubdued them in the year 903. He was ſucceeded by Conſtantine III. the ſon of Eth the Swift- footed, concerning whom the moſt remarkable particular we find related is his entering into an alliance with the Danes againſt the Engliſh. The occaſion of this confederacy is ſaid to have been, that the Engliſh monarch, Edward the Elder, finding the Scots in poſſeſſion of the northern counties of England, made ſuch extravagant demands upon Conſtantine as obliged him to ally with the Danes in order to preſerve his dominions in ſecurity. However, the league ſubſiſted only for two years, after which the Danes found it more for their advantage to reſume their ancient friendſhip with the Engliſh.</p><p>As ſoon as Conſtantine had concluded the treaty with the Danes, he appointed the ρreſumptive heir to the Scottiſh crown, Malcolm, or, according to ſome, Eugene the ſon of the late king Donald, prince of the ſouthern counties, on condition of his defending them againſt the attacks of the Engliſh. The young prince had ſoon an opportunity of exerting his valour: but not behaving with the requiſite caution, he had the misfortune to be defeated, with the loſs of almoſt all his army, he himſelf being carried wounded out of the field; and in conſequence of this diſaſter, Conſtantine was obliged to do homage to Edward for the poſſeſſions he had to the ſouthward of the Scots boundary.</p><p>In the beginning of the reign of Athelſtan the ſon of Edward the Elder, the northern Danes were encouraged by ſome conſpiracies formed againſt that monarch to throw off the yoke; and their ſucceſs was ſuch, that Athelſtan thought proper to enter into a treaty with Sithric the Daniſh chief, and to give him his daughter in marriage. Sithric, however, did not long ſurvive his nuptials; and his ſon Guthred, endeavouring to throw off the Engliſh yoke, was deſeated, and obliged to fly into Scotland. This brought on a ſeries of hoſtilities between the Scots and Engliſh, which in the year 938 iſſued in a general engagement. At this time the Scots, Iriſh, Cumbrians, and Danes, were confederated againſt the Engliſh. The Scots were commanded by their king Conſtantine, the Iriſh by Anlaf the brother of Guthred the Daniſh prince, the Cumbrians by their own ſovereign, and the Danes by Froda. The generals of Athelſtan were Edmund his brother, and Tmketil his favourite. The Engliſh attacked the entrenchments of the confederates, where the chief reſiſtance they met with was from the Scots. Conſtantine was in the utmoſt danger of being killed or taken priſoner, but was reſoued by the bravery of his ſoldiers: however, after a moſt obſtinate engagement, the confederates were defeated with ſuch ſlaughter, that the ſlain are laid to have been <hi rend="italic">innumerable.</hi> The conſequence of this victory was, that the Scots were deprived of all their poſſeſſions to the ſouthward of the Forth; and Conſtantine, quite diſpirited with his misfortune, reſigned the crown to Malcolm, and retired to the monaſtery of the Culdees at St Andrew’s, where he died five years after, in 943.</p><p>The diſtreffes which the Engliſh ſuſtained in their ſubſequent wars with the Danes gave the Scots an opportunity of retrieving their affairs; and in the year 944, we find Malcolm, the ſucceſſor of Conſtantine, inveſted with the ſovereignty of Northumberland, on con-</p></body></text></TEI>