<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:48:53Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>which fell down in 1737, and the water was loſt; but in clearing away the ruins in order to rebuild the wharf, it was recovered, to the great joy of the town. The waters of Scarborough are chalybeate and purging. The two wells are both impregnated with the ſame principles, in different proportions; though the purging well is the moſt celebrated, and the water of this is uſually called the <hi rend="italic">Scarborough water.</hi> When theſe waters are poured out of one glaſs into another, they throw up a number of air-bubbles; and if they are ſhaken for ſome time in a phial cloſe flopped, and the phial be ſuddenly opened before the commotion ceaſes, they diſplode an elaſtic vapour, with an audible noiſe, which ſhows that they abound in fixed air At the fountain they have a briſk, pungent, chalybeate taſte; but the purging water taſtes bitteriſh, which is not uſually the caſe with the chalybeate one. They loſe their chalybeate virtues by expoſure and by keeping; but the purging water the ſooneſt. They both putrefy by keeping; but in time recover their ſweetneſs. Four or five half pints of the purging water drank within an hour, give two or three eaſy motions, and raiſe the ſpirits. The like quantity of the chalybeate purges leſs, but exhilarates more, and paſſes off chiefly by urine. Theſe waters have been found beneficial in hectic fevers, weakneſſes of the ſtomach, and indigeſtion; in relaxations of the ſyſtem; in nervous, hyſteric, and hypochondriacal diſorders; in the green ſickneſs, ſcurvy, rheumatiſm, and aſthmatic complaints; in gleets, the fluor albus, and other preternatural evacuations; and in habitual coſtiveneſs. Here are aſſemblies and balls in the ſame manner as at Tunbridge. It is a place of ſome trade, has a very good harbour, and fends two members to parliament. E. Long. 54. 18 N. Lat. O 3.</p><p>SCARDONA, a ſea port town of Dalmatia, ſeated on the eaſtern banks of the river Cherca, with a biſhop’s ſee. It has been taken and retaken ſeveral times by the Turks and Venetians; and theſe laſt ruined the fortifications and its principal buildings in 1537; but they have been ſince put in a ſtate of defence</p><p>“@@No veſtiges (ſays Fortis) now remain viſible of that ancient city, where the ſtates of Liburnia held their aſſembly in the times of the Romans. I however tranſcribed theſe two beautiful inſcriptions, which were diſcovered ſome years ago, and are preſerved in the houſe of the reverend Canon Mercati. It is to be hoped, that, as the population of Scardona continues increaſing, new lands will be broken up, and conſequently more frequent diſcoveries made of the precious monuments of antiquity. And it is to be wiſhed, that the few men of letters, who have a ſhare in the regulation of this reviving city, may beſtow ſome particular attention on that article, ſo that the honourable memorials of their ancient and illuſtrious country, which once held ſo eminent a rank among the Liburnian cities, may not be loſt, nor carried away. It is almoſt a ſhame, that only fix legible inſcriptions actually exiſt at Scardona; and that all the others, ſince many more certainly muſt have been dug up there, are either miſerably broken or loſt, or tranſported to Italy, where they loſe the greateſt part of their merit. Roman coins are very frequently found about Scardona, and ſeveral valuable ones were ſhown to me by that hoſpitable prelate Monſignor Treviſani, biſhop and father of the riſing ſettlement One of the principal gentlemen ot the place was ſo kind as to</p><p>give me ſeveral ſepulchral lamps, which are marked by the name of <hi rend="italic">Fortis,</hi> and by the elegant form of the letters appear to be of the beſt times. The repeated devaſtations to which Scardona has been expoſed, have left it no traces of grandeur. It is now, however, beginning to riſe again, and many merchants of Servia and Boſnia have fettled there, on account of the convenient ſituation for trade with the upper provinces of Turkey. But the city has no fortifications, notwith- ſtanding the aſſertion of P. Farlati to the contrary. ” E. Long. 17. 25. N. Lat. 43. 55. 	</p><p>SCARIFICATION, in ſurgery, the operation of making ſeveral inciſions in the ſkin by means of lances or other inſtruments, particularly the cupping inſtrument. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Surgery.</hi></p><p>SCARLET, a beautiful bright red colour.</p><p>In painting in water-colours, minium mixed with a little vermilion produces a good ſcarlet: but if a flower in a print is to be painted a ſcarlet colour, the lights as well as the ſhades ſhould be covered with minium, and the ſhaded parts finiſhed with carmine, which will produce an admirable ſcarlet.</p><p><hi rend="italic">SCARLET-Fever.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Medicine,</hi> n⁰ 230.</p><p>SCARP, in fortification, is the interior talus or ſlope of the ditch next the place, at the foot of the rampart.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Scarp,</hi> in heraldry, the ſcarf which military commanders wear for ornament. It is borne ſomewhat like a battoon ſiniſter, but is broader than it, and is continued out to the edges of the field, whereas the battoon is cut off at each end.</p><p>SCARPANTO, an iſland of the Archipelago, and one of the Sporades, lying to the ſouth-weſt of the iſle of Rhodes, and to the north-eaſt of that of Candia. It is about 22 miles in length and 8 in breadth; and there are ſeveral high mountains. It abounds in cattle and game; and there are mines of iron, quarries of marble, with ſeveral good harbours. The Turks are maſters of it, but the inhabitants are Greeks.</p><p>SC RPE, a river of the Netherlands, which has its ſource near Aubigny in Artois, where it waſhes Arras and Douay; after which it runs on the confines of Flanders and Hainault, paſſing by St Amand, and a little after falls into the Scheldt.</p><p>SCARRON (Paul), a famous burleſque writer, was the ſon of a counſellor in parliament, and was born at Paris about the end of the year 610, or in the beginning of the ſucceeding year. His father marrying a ſecond time, he was compelled to aſſume the eccleſiaſtical profeſſion At the age of 24 he viſited taly, where he freely indulged in licentious pleasures. After his return to Paris he persisted in a life of diſſipation till a long and painful diſeaſe convinced him that his conſtitution was almoſt worn out. At length when engaged in a party of pleaſure at the age of 27, he loſt <hi rend="italic">the uſe of thoſe legs which danced so gracefully and of those hands which could paint and play on the lute with ſo much elegance.</hi> In the year 1638 he was attending the carnival at Mens, of which he was a canon. Having dreſſed himſelf one day as a ſavage, his ſingular appearance excited the curioſity of the children of the town. They followed him in multitudes, and he was obliged to take ſhelter in a marſh. This wet and cold ſituation produced a numbneſs which totally deprived him of the use of his limbs; but notwithſtanding this misfortune he continued gay and cheertul. He took up his reſidence at</p><p><hi rend="italic">@@@ [mu] </hi>Travels into Dalmatia.</p></body></text></TEI>