<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:46:44Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>before the pope and what divines he chooſes @@<hi rend="smallcaps">(a).</hi> Public prayer and faſting are likewiſe preſcribed, in order to obtain light and direction from heaven. After all this long procedure, when the pope is reſolved to give his approbation, he iſſues a bull, firſt of <hi rend="italic">beatification,</hi> by which the perſon is declared <hi rend="italic">bleſſed,</hi> and afterwards another of <hi rend="italic">ſanctification,</hi> by which the name of <hi rend="italic">ſaint</hi> is given him. Theſe bulls are publiſhed in St Peter’s church with very great ſolemnity.</p><p>A perſon remarkable for holineſs of life, even before he is canonized, may be venerated as ſuch by thoſe who are perſuaded of his eminent virtue, and his prayers may be implored; but all this muſt reſt on private opinion. After his canonization, his name is inſerted in the Martyrology, or catalogue of ſaints, of which the reſpective portion is read every day in the choir at the divine office. A day is alſo appointed for an yearly commemoration of him. His name may be mentioned in the public church ſervice, and his interceſſion with God beſought. His relics may be enſhrined: he may be painted with rays of glory, and altars and churches may be dedicated to God in honour of him, and in thankſgiving to the divine goodneſs for the bleſſings beſtowed on him in life, and for the glory to which he is raiſed in heaven.</p><p>The affair of a canonization is neceſſarily very expenſive, becauſe ſo many perſons muſt be employed about it; ſo many journeys muſt be made; ſo many writings for and againſt it muſt be drawn out. The expence altogether amounts to about 25,000 Roman crowns, or L. 6000 Sterling. But it is generally contrived to canonize two or three at a time, by which means the particular expence of each is very much leſſened, the ſolemnity being common.</p><p>It often happens that the ſolicitors for a canonization are unſucceſsful. Thus the Jeſuits, even when their intereſt at Rome was greateſt, could not obtain the canonization of Bellarmine; and it is remarkable, that the objection is ſaid to have been, his having defended the indirect power of the pope over Chriſtian princes even in temporals.</p><p>Several authors have written on canonization, and particularly Proſper Lambertini, afterwards pope under the name of Benedict XIV. who had held the office of <hi rend="italic">promoter of the faith</hi> for many years. He publiſhed on it a large work in ſeveral volumes, in folio, of which there is an abridgment in French. In this learned performance there is a full hiſtory of the canonization of ſaints in general, and of all the particular proceſſes of that kind that are on record: an account is given of the manner of proceeding in theſe extraordinary trials; and it is  ſhiown, that, beſides the aſſiſtance of providence, which is implored and expected in what is ſo much connected with religion, all prudent human means are made uſe of, in order to avoid miſtakes, and to obtain all the evidence of which the matter is ſuſceptible, and which muſt appear more than ſufficent to every impartial judge. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Pope, Popery, &amp;c.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Saint-Foin,</hi> in botany, a ſpecies of the hedyſarum. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Hedysarum</hi>; and <hi rend="smallcaps">Agriculture,</hi> n<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> 180,</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Saint</hi> Januarius's Blood.<hi rend="italic"> See </hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Chemistry,</hi><hi rend="italic"> n° 800.</hi></p><p>SAINTES, an ancient and conſiderable town of France. It is the capital of Saintonge, and before the revolution was a biſhop’s ſee. It contained likewiſe ſeveral convents, a Jeſuits college, and an abbey remarkable for its ſteeple, built with ſmall ſtones, which admits the light. It is ſeated on an eminence, 37 miles ſoutheaſt of Rochelle, and 262 ſouth ſouth-weſt of Paris. W. Long. O. 34. N. Lat. 45. 45. The caſtle is ſeated on a rock, and is reckoned impregnable.</p><p>This city was a Roman colony; and thoſe conquerors of the earth, who poliſhed the nations they ſubdued, have left behind them the traces of their magnificence. In a hollow valley between two mountains, and almoſt adjoining to one of the ſuburbs, are the ruins of the amphitheatre. Though now in the laſt ſtage of decay, its appearance is auguſt and venerable. In ſome parts, ſcarce any of the arches are to be ſeen; but the eaſt end is ſtill in a great degree of preſervation. From its ſituation in a valley, and from the ruins of an aqueduct which conveyed water to the town from near three leagues diſtance, it has been ſuppoſed that Naumachae were repreſented in it; but this amounts only to conjecture. A triumphal arch, on which is an inſcription in Roman letters, merits likewiſe attention. It was erected to Germanicus, on the news of his death, ſo univerſally lamented throughout the empire. The river Charente ſurrounds this city, as the Severne does that of Shrewſhury, deſcribing the form of a horſe-ſhoe.</p><p>Except the remains of Roman grandeur yet viſible at Saintes, the place contains very Iittle to detain or amuſe a traveller. It is built with great irregularity; the ſtreets are narrow and winding, the houſes mean, and almoſt all of them are ſome centuries old. The cathedral has been repeatedly defaced and deſtroyed by Normans and Huguenots, who made war alike on every monument of art or piety. One tower only eſcaped their rage, which is ſaid to have been built as early as the year 800 by Charlemagne. It is of an enormous magnitude, both as to height and circumference. Theſe circumſtances have probably conduced more to its preſervation during the fury of war, than any veneration for the memory of its founder, or for the ſanctity of its inſtitution.</p><p>SAINTONGE, a province of France, bounded on the eaſt by Angoumois and Perigord, on the north by Poitou and the territory of Aunis, on the weſt by the ocean, and on the ſouth by Bourdelois and Giron, about 62 miles in length and 30 in breadth. The river Charente runs through the middle of it, and renders it one of the fineſt and moſt fertile provinces in France, abounding in all forts of corn and fruits; and they make the beſt ſalt here in Europe.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">The</hi> SAINTS, three leagues diſtant from Guada- loupe, are two very ſmall iſlands, which, with another yet ſmaller, form a triangle, and have a tolerable harbour. Thirty Frenchmen were ſent thither in 1648, but were foon driven away by an exceſſive drought, which dried up their only ſpring before they had time to make any reservoirs. A ſecond attempt was made in 1652,</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">@@@ a) [</hi>m<hi rend="smallcaps">]</hi> His holineſs generally appoints three conſiſtories; in the firſt of which the cardinals only aſſiſt, and give their opinion; in the ſecond, a preacher pronounces a ſpeech in praiſe of the candidate before a numerous audience; to the third, not only the cardinals, but all the biſhops who are at Rome, are invited, and all of them. give their vote by word of mouth.</p></body></text></TEI>