<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:49:17Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>weſt to the weſt of Scilly and Ireland. The major aſſigns ſtrong reaſons for the exiſtence of this current between Uſhant and Ireland, in a chart of the tracts of the Hector and Atlas, Eaſt India ſhips, in 1778 and 1787. The following remarks on the effect of this current are abridged ſrom the author’s work, which is well worthy the peruſal of all ſailors and ſhipmaſters.</p><p>1 ft, If a ſhip croſſes it obliquely, that is, in an eaſt by ſouth or more ſoutherly direction, ſhe will continue much longer in it, and of courſe be more affected by it, than if ſhe croſſed it more directly. The ſame conſequence will happen if ſhe croſſes it with light winds. 2dly, A good obſervation of latitude at noon would be thought a ſufficient warrant for running eaſtward during a long night; yet as it may be poſſible to remain in the current long enough to be carried from a parallel, which may be deemed a very ſafe one, to that of the rocks of Scilly, it would appear prudent, after experiencing a continuance of ſtrong weſterly winds in the Atlantic, and approaching the Channel with light ſoutherly winds, either to make Uſhant in time of peace, or at all events to keep in the parallel of 48⁰ 45' at the higheſt. 3dly, Ships bound to the weſtward, from the mouth of the Channel, with the wind in the ſouth-weſt quarter, ſhould prefer the larboard tack. 4thly, Major Rennel approves the deſign of removing the light- houſe of Scilly (if it be not already removed) to the ſouth-weſt part of the high rocks. 5thly, He recommends the fending a veſſel, with time-keepers on board, to examine the foundings between the parallels of Scilly and Uſhant; from the meridian of the Lizard Point as far weſt as the moderate depths extend. A ſet of timekeepers, he obſerves, will effect more in one ſummer, in ſkilful hands, than all the ſcience of Dr Halley could do in the courſe of a long life.</p><p>In time of war, the importance of theſe iſlands is ſtill more conſpicuous; and it is highly probable, that they afforded the allies a place for aſſembling their fleet, when the Britons, Danes, Scots, and Iriſh, ſailed under the command of Anlaff, to attack King Athelſtan; which convinced him of the neceſſity of adding them to his dominions. Upon the like principle, Henry VIII. when upon bad terms with his neighbours, cauſed an old fortreſs to be repaired; and Queen Elizabeth, who had more to fear, directed the conſtruction of a caſtle, which, in part at leaſt, ſtill remains. But the moſt ſingular inſtance ot the detriment that might ariſe ſrom theſe iſlands falling into other hands than our own happened in 1651, when Sir John Grenville took ſhelter in them with the remains of the Corniſh cavaliers. For the depredations committed by his frigates ſoon made it evident that Scilly was the key of the Engliſh commerce; and the clamours of the merchants thereupon roſe ſo high, that the parliament were forced to ſend a fleet of fifty ſail, with a great body of land-forces on board, under Sir George Avſcue and admiral Blake, who with great difficulty, and no inconſiderable loſs, made themſelves matters of Treſcaw and Brehar; where they erected thoſe lines and fortifications near the remains of the old fortreſs that are called <hi rend="italic">Oliver's Caſtle.</hi> But at length, finding that little was to be done in that way, they choſe to grant Sir John Grenville a moſt honourable capitulation, as the ſureſt means to recover places of ſuch conſequence: with which the parliament were very little</p><p>ſatisſied, till Mr Blake gave them his reaſons; which appeared to be ſo well founded, that they directed the articles he had concluded to be punctually carried into execution.</p><p>SCIO, or CHIO, a celebrated iſland of the Archipelago (fee <hi rend="smallcaps">Chio).</hi> It is 32 miles long and 15 broad, is a mountainous but very pleaſant country. The principal mountain, called anciently <hi rend="italic">Pelinaeus,</hi> preſents to view a long lofty range of bare rock, reflecting the fun; but the receſſes at its feet are diligently cultivated, and reward the huſbandman by their rich produce. The ſlopes are clothed with vines. The groves of lemon, orange, and citron-trees, regularly planted, at once perfume the air with the odour of their bloſſoms, and delight the eye with their golden fruit. Myrtles and jaſmines are interſperſed, with olive and palm-trees, and cypreffes. Amid theſe the tall minarees riſe, and white houſes glitter, dazzling the beholder. The inhabitants export a large quantity of pleaſant wine to the neighbouring iſlands, but their principal trade is in ſilks. They have alſo a ſmall commerce in wool<hi rend="smallcaps">,</hi> cheeſe, figs, and maſtic. The women are better bred than in other parts of the Levant; and though the dreſs is odd, yet it is very neat. The partridges are tame, being ſent every day into the fields to get their Sving, and in the evening are called back with a whiſtle. The town called <hi rend="italic">Scio</hi> is large, pleaſant, and the beſt built of any in the Levant, the houſes being beautiful and commodious, ſome of which are terraffed, and others covered with tiles. The ſtreets are paved with flint-ſtones; and the Venetians, while they had it in their poſſeſſion, made a great many alterations for the better. The caſtle is an old citadel built by the Genoeſe, in which the Turks have a garrifon of 1400 men. The harbour of Scio is the rendezvous of all ſhipping that goes to or comes from Conſtantinople, and will hold a fleet of fourſcore veſſels. They reckon there are 10,000 Turks, 100,000 Greeks, and 10,000 Latins, on this iſland. The Turks took it from the Venetians in 1695. Scio is a biſhop’s ſee, and is ſeated on the ſea-ſide, 47 miles weſt of Smyrna, and 210 ſouth-weſt of Conſtantinople.</p><p>There are but few remains of antiquity in this place. “The moſt curious of them (ſays Dr Chandler) is that which has been named without reaſon the <hi rend="italic">School of Homer.</hi> It is on the coaſt at ſome diſtance from the city northward, and appears to have been an open temple of Cybele, formed on the top of a rock. The ſhape is oval, and in the centre is the image of the goddeſs, the head and an arm wanting. She is repreſented, as uſual, fitting. The chair has a lion carved on each ſide, and on the back. The area is bounded by a low rim or  ſeat, and about five yards over, The whole is hewn out of the mountain, is rude, indiſtinct, and probable of the moſt remote antiquity. From the Hope higher up is a fine view of the rich vale of Scio, and of the channel, with its ſhining iſlands, beyond which are the mountains on the mainland of Alia. ”</p><p>SCIOPPIUS (Gaſpar), a learned German writer of the 17th century, was born at Neumark in the Upper Palatinate on the 27th of May 1576. He ſtudied at the univerſity with ſo much ſucceſs, that at the age of 16 he became an author; and publiſhed books, ſays Ferrari, which deſerved to be admired by old men. His diſpoſitions did not correſpond with his genius. Naturally paſſionate and malevolent, he aſſaulted without</p></body></text></TEI>