<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:50:36Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>river, returned with certain intelligence that the Scottiſh camp was totally deserted: which when the young king of England was certainly informed of, he burſt into tears; for the enterpriſe, which thus terminated in diſappointment and dishonour, had coſt an immenſe  ſum. Every preparation had been made for oppoſing an enemy, and auxiliaries had even been procured at a moſt enormous expence from Hainault. Theſe auxiliaries conſiſted of  heavy-armed cavalry; and they were now ſo much worn out, that they could ſcarcely move. Their horſes were all dead, or had become unſerviceable, in a campaign of three weeks; ſo that they were obliged to procure horſes to convey themselves to the ſouth of England. Edward having reſted at Durham for ſome days, marched to York, where he diſbanded his army. Barbour, a Scots historian, relates, that there Was a moraſs in the rear of the Scottiſh camp, which he calls the <hi rend="italic">two-mile mora</hi>ſ<hi rend="italic">s; </hi>that the Scots made a way over it with bruſhwood, removing it as they went along,‘that the Engliſh might not purſue them by the  ſame way. The Engliſh hiſtoriarts are filled with deſcriptions of the ſtrange appearance of the deſerted camp of the Scots. They found there a number of ſkins ſtretched between ſtakes, which ſerved for kettles to boil their meat; and for bread, each ſoldier carried along with him a bag of oatmeal, of which he made takes, toaſting them upon thin iron plates, which appear to have been part of their armour.</p><p>On the return Of Douglas and Randolph, the king led his army againſt the eastern borders, and beſieged the caſtle of Norham. However, in 1328, Edward, wearied out with continual loſſes and diſappointments, Conſented to a perpetual peace between the two kingdoms on the following conditions. 1. The ſtone on which the kings of Scotland were wont to fit at the time of their coronation, ſhall be reſtored to the Scots. 2. The king of England engages to employ his good offices at the papal court for obtaining a revocation  of all ſpiritual proceſſes depending before the holy ſee againſt the king of Scots, or againſt his kingdom or ſubjects. 3. For theſe cauſes, and in Order to make  reparation for the ravages Committed in England by  the Scots, the king of Scots ſhall pay 30,000 merks to  the king of England. 4. Reſtitution ſhall be made of the poſſeſſions belonging to eccleſiaſtics in either kingdom, whereof they may have been deprived during the war. 5. But there ſhall not be any reſtitution made of inheritances which have fallen into the hands of the  king of England or of the king of Scots, by reaſon of  the war between the two nations, or through the forfeiture of former poſſeſſors. 6. Johanna, ſiſter of the  king of England, ſhall be given in marriage to David,  the ſon and heir to the king of Scots. 7. The king  of Scots ſhall provide the princeſs Johanna in a jointure  of 2000 l. yearly, ſecured on lands and rents, according  to a reasonable eſtimation. 8. If either of the parties ſhall fail in performing theſe conditions, he ſhall pay  2000 pounds of ſilver to the papal treaſury.</p><p>This peace, ratified at Northampton, is ſtyled <hi rend="italic">ignominious </hi>by the Engliſh hiſtorians, and the marriage df the Scots prince to the king of England’s ſiſter, denominated <hi rend="italic">that baſe marriage;</hi> because at this time all pretenſions to fovereignty over Scotland were given up, they had in vain attempted to eſtabliſh them by a ruinous war of 20 years. The marriage of the infant prince was celebrated on the 12th of July 1328,</p><p>On the 7th of June 1329 died Robert Bruce, unqueſtionably the greateſt of all the Scottiſh monarchs. His death ſeems to have been occaſioned by the exceſſive fatigues of military ſervice; and his diſeafe, called by the hiſtorians of thoſe times a leproſy, was probably an inveterate scurvy, occaſioned by his way of living. He died at the age of 55. He was married to Iſabella, daughter of Donald the tenth carl of  Marr; by whom he had a daughter named Marjory, married to Walter the ſteward of Scotland; whose huſband died in 1326. The ſecond wife of Robert was Eliſabeth, the daughter of Aymer de Burgh earl of Ulſter. By her he had a ſon, David II.; a daughter named Margaret, married to William earl of Sutherland ; another, named Matilda, married to an eſquire named Thomas Iſaac; and Eliſabeth, married to Sir Walter Oliphant or Gaſk. He had alſo a natural ſon named Robert.</p><p>That king Robert I. was a man of unqueſtionable virtue and humanity, as well as unequalled in the knowledge of the military art, muſt be evident from many particulars already related. The only queſtionable part of his character is his ſevere puniſhment of a conſpiracy formed againſt him in the year 1320; a relation of which, to avoid interrupting our detail of more important matters, we have deferred till now.—The chief of the conſpirators were William de Soulis, whoſe anceſtor had been a candidate for the crown of Scotland; the counteſs of Strathern, and ſome other perſons of high rank. The counteſs diſcovered the plot; after which Soulis confeſſed the whole, and was puniſhed with perpetual impriſonment; as well as the counteſs, notwithſtanding her having made the diſcovery. Gilbert de Malyerb and John de Logie, both knights, and Richard Brown an eſquire, were put to death as traitors: but the, perſon moſt lamented was Sir David de Brechin, for his bravery ſtyled <hi rend="italic">the flοwer of chivalry. </hi>He was nephew to the king, and ſerved with great reputation againſt the Saracens. To him the conſpirators, after having exacted an oath of ſecrecy, revealed their deſigns. He condemned their undertaking, and refuſed to ſhare in it; but did not diſcover it, on account of the oath he had taken. Yet for this concealment he was tried as traitor, condemned and executed, without regard to his perſonal merit or his relation to the king. The conſpirators were tried before the parliament at Scone in 1320; and this ſeſſion, in which ſo much blood was ſhed, was long remembered by the vulgar under the name of the <hi rend="italic">black parliament.</hi> Whether there was any thing real in this conſpiracy, or whether the king only made uſe of this pretence to rid himſelf of ſuch as were obnoxious to him, cannot now be known with certainty.</p><p>After the death of Robert, the administration was aſſumed by Randolph, in conſequence of an act paſſed in 1318, by which he was appointed regent in caſe of the king's death. In his new character he behaved himſelf in a moſt exemplary manner; and by impartially diſchargiag the duties of his ſtation, and rigidly adminiſtering juſtice, he ſecured the public tranquillity in the moſt perfect manner. A ſevere exerciſe of juſtice was now rendered not only neceſſary, but indispensable.</p></body></text></TEI>