<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:51:12Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>had retired to the caſtle of Dunbar, while it was in Hepburn’s poſſeſſion, where ſhe died ſoon after. She left by her ſecond huſband three ſons; John, who in 1455 was made earl of Athol, by his uterine brother the king; James, who under the next reign, in 1469, was created earl of Buchan; and Andrew, who afterwards became biſhop of Murray. As the earl of Douglas was an enemy to the queen-dowager’s huſband, the latter retired to England, where he obtained a paſs to go abroad, with 20 in his train; but being taken at ſea by the Flemiſh pirates, he died in his confinement.</p><p>The great point between the king and Sir William Crichton, whether the latter ſhould give up the caſtle to his majeſty, remained ſtill undecided; and by the advice and direction of the earl of Douglas, who had been created lord-lieutenant of the kingdom, it had now ſuffered a nine months liege. Either the ſtrength of the caſtle, or an opinion entertained by Douglas that Crichton would be a valuable acquiſition to his party, procured better terms for the latter than he could otherwiſe have expected; for he and his followers were offered a full indemnity for all paſt offences, and a promiſe was made that he ſhould be reſtored not only to the king’s favour, but to his former poſt of chancellor. He accepted of the conditions; but refuſed to act in any public capacity till they were confirmed by a parliament, which was ſoon after held at Perth, and in which he was reſtored to his eſtate and honours. By this reconciliation between Douglas and Crichton, the former was left at full liberty to proſecute his vengeance againſt the Lord Callendar, the late governor, his friends and family. That vengeance was exerciſed with rigour. The governor himſelf, Sir James Dundas of Dundas, and Sir Robert Bruce of Clackmannan, were forced to ſave their lives by the loſs of their eſtates; but even</p><p>that could not preſerve their liberty, for they were ſent priſoners to the caſtle of Dumbarton. The fate of Alexander, the governor’s eldeſt ſon, and of two other gentlemen of his name and family, was ſtill more lamentable; for they were condemned to loſe their heads. Thoſe ſeverities being inflicted after the king had in a manner readmitted the ſufferers into his favour, ſwelled the public outcry againſt the earl of Douglas. We have in Lindſay an extract of the ſpeech which Alexander Livingſton, one of the moſt accompliſhed gentlemen of his time, made upon the ſcaffold, in which he complained, with great bitterneſs, of the cruel treatment his father, himſelf, and his friends, had undergone; and that he ſuffered by a packed jury of his enemies.</p><p>The king being now about 18 years of age, it was thought proper that a ſuitable confort ſhould be provided for him; and, after various conſultations, Mary, the daughter of Arnold duke of Gueldres, was choſen, at the recommendation of Charles king of France, though the marriage was not completed till ſome time after. This produced an immediate rupture with England. The earls of Saliſbury and Northumberland entered Scotland at the head of two ſeparate bodies. The former burnt the town of Dumfries, as the latter did that of Dunbar; while Sir John Douglas of Balveny made repriſals by plundering the county of Cumberland, and burning Alnwic. Upon the return of the Engliſh armies to their own country, additional levies were made, and a freſh invasion of Scotland was reſolved up</p><p>on under the earl of Northumberland, who had along with him a lieutenant, whom the Scots of thoſe days, from the buſhineſs and colour of his beard, called <hi rend="italic">Magnus with the red mane.</hi> He was a ſoldier of fortune, but an excellent officer, having been trained in the French wars; and he is ſaid to have demanded no other recompenſe for his ſervices from the Engliſh court, but that he ſhould enjoy all he could conquer in Scotland. The Scots, in the mean time, had raiſed an army commanded by George Douglas earl of Ormond, and under him by Wallace of Craigie, with the Lords Maxwell and Johnſton. The Engliſh having paſſed Solway Frith, ravaged all that part of the country which belonged to the Scots; but hearing that the earl of Ormond’s army was approaching, called in their parties, and fixed their camp on the banks of the river Sark. Their advanced guard was commanded by Magnus; their centre by the earl of Northumberland; and the rear, which was compoſed of Welch, by Sir John Pennington, an officer of courage and experience.</p><p>The Scots drew up in three diviſions likewiſe. Their right wing was commanded by Wallace, the centre by the earl of Ormond, and their left wing by the Lords Maxwell and Johnſton. Before the battle joined, the earl of Ormond harangued his men, and inſpired them with very high reſentment againſt the Engliſh, who, he ſaid, had treacherouſly broken the truce. The ſignal for battle being given, the Scots under Wallace ruſhed forward upon their enemies: but, as uſual, were received by ſo terrible a diſcharge from the Engliſh archers, that their impetuoſity muſt have been flopped, had not their brave leader Wallace put them in mind, that their forefathers had always been defeated in diſtant fights by the Engliſh, and that they ought to truſt to their ſwords and spears; commanding them at the ſame time to follow his example. They obeyed, and broke in upon the Engliſh commanded by Magnus, with ſuch fury, as ſoon fixed the fortune of the day on the ſide of the Scots, their valour being ſuitably ſeconded by their other two diviſions. The ſlaughter (which was the more conſiderable as both parties fought with the utmoſt animoſity) fell chiefly upon the diviſion commanded by Magnus, who was killed, performing the part of a brave officer; and all his body-guard, conſiſting of picked ſoldiers, were cut in pieces.</p><p>The battle then became general: Sir John Pennington’s diviſion, with that under the earl of Northumberland, was likewiſe routed; and the whole Engliſh army, ſtruck by the loſs of their champion, fled towards the Solway, where, the river being ſwelled by the tide, numbers of them were drowned. The loſs of the Engliſh in ſlain amounted to at leaſt 3000 men. Among the priſoners were Sir John Pennington, Sir Robert Harrington, and the earl of Northumberland’s eldeſt ſon the Lord Percy, who loſt his own liberty in forwarding his father’s eſcape. Of the Scots about 600 were killed; but none of note, excepting the brave Wallace, who died three months after of the wounds he had received in this battle. The booty that was made on this occaſion is ſaid to have been greater than any that has fallen to the Scots ſince the battle of Barunockburn.</p><p>The reſt of the hiſtory of this reign conſiſts almoſt entirely of a relation of the cabals and conſpiracies of the great men. The earl of Douglas had entered into a</p></body></text></TEI>