<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:47:51Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>to Latin and Italian poetry. His gay and facetious humour made him ſought for by all companies; but he was ſo afflicted at the news that Phillibert prince of Orange, general of the emperor’s army, had demoliſhed his country-houſe, that it threw him into an illneſs, of which he died in 1530. It is ſaid, that being informed a few days before his death, that the prince of Orange was killed in battle, he called out, “I ſhall die contented, ſince Mars has puniſhed this barbarous enemy of the Muſes.” He wrote a great number of Italian and Latin poems: among thoſe in Latin, his <hi rend="italic">De Partu Virginis</hi> and Eclogues are chiefly eſteemed; and the moſt celebrated of his Italian pieces is his <hi rend="italic">Arcadia.</hi></p><p>SANTA <hi rend="smallcaps">Cruz,</hi> a large iſland in the South Sea, and one of the moſt conſiderable of thoſe of Solomon, being about 250 miles in circumference. W. Long. 130. 0. S. Lat. 10. 21.</p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Santa</hi><hi rend="italic"> Cruz,</hi> or St <hi rend="smallcaps">Croix,</hi> a ſmall and unhealthy iſland, ſituated in about 64 degrees weſt longitude and 18 north latitude. It is about eighteen leagues in length, and from three to four in breadth. @@In 1643 it was inhabited by Dutch and Engliſh, who ſoon became enemies to each other; and in 1650 were both driven out by 1200 Spaniards, who arrived there in five ſhips. The triumph of theſe laſted but a few months. The remains of that numerous body, which were left for the defence of the iſland, ſurrendered without reſiſtance to 160 French, who had embarked in 1651, from St Chriſtopher’s, to make themſelves maſters of the iſland.</p><p>Theſe new inhabitants loſt no time in making themſelves acquainted with a country ſo much diſputed. On a ſoil, in other reſpects excellent, they found only one river of a moderate ſize, which, gliding gently almoſt on a level with the ſea through a flat country, furniſhed only a brackiſh water. Two or three ſprings, which they found in the innermoſt parts of the iſland, made but feeble amends for this defect. The wells were for the moſt part dry. The conſtruction of reſervoirs required time. Nor was the climate more inviting to the new inhabitants. The iſland being flat, and covered with old trees, ſcarce afforded an opportunity for the winds to carry off the poiſonous vapours with which its moraſſes clogged the atmoſphere. There was but one remedy for this inconvenience; which was to burn the woods. The French ſet fire to them without delay; and, getting on board their ſhips, became ſpectators from the ſea, for ſeveral months, of the conflagration they had raiſed in the iſland. As ſon as the flames were extinguiſhed, they went on ſhore again.</p><p>They found the ſoil fertile beyond belief. Tobacco, cotton, arnotto, indigo, and ſugar, flouriſhed equally in it. So rapid was the progreſs of this colony, that in 11 years from its commencement there were upon it 822 white perſons, with a proportionable number of ſlaves. It was rapidly advancing to proſperity, when ſuch obſtacles were thrown in the way of its activity as made it decline again. This decay was as ſudden as its rife. In 1696 there were no more than 147 men, with their wives and children, and 623 blacks remaining; and theſe were tranſported to St Domingo.</p><p>Some obſcure individuals, ſome writers unacquainted with the views of government, with their ſecret nego</p><p>tiations, with the character of their miniſters, with the intereſts of the protectors and the protected, who flatter themſelves that they can diſcern the reaſon of events amongſt a multitude of important or frivolous cauſes, which may have equally occaſioned them; who do not conceive, that among all theſe cauſes the moſt natural may poſſibly be the fartheſt from the truth; who after having read the news, or journal of the day, with profound attention, decide as peremptorily as if they had been placed all their lifetime at the helm of the ſtate, and had aſſiſted at the council of kings; who are never more deceived than in thoſe circumſtance in which they diſplay ſome ſhare of penetration; writers as abſurd in the praiſes as in the blame which they beſtow upon nations, in the favourable or unfavourable opinion they form of miniſterial operations: theſe idle dreamers, in a word, who think they are perſons of importance, becauſe their attention is always engaged on matters of conſequence, being convinced that courts are always governed in their deciſions by the moſt comprehenſive views of profound policy, have ſuppoſed that the court of Verſailles had neglected Santa Cruz, merely becauſe they wiſhed to abandon the ſmall iſlands in order to unite all their ſtrength, induſtry, and population, in the large ones; but this is a miſtaken notion. This determination aroſe from the farmers of the revenue, who found that the contraband trade of Santa Cruz with St Thomas was detrimental to their intereſts. The ſpirit of finance hath in all times been injurious to commerce; it hath deſtroyed the ſource from whence it ſprang. Santa Cruz continued without inhabitants, and without cultivation, till 1733, when it was sold by France to Denmark for 30,7501. Soon after the Danes built there the fortreſs of Chriſtianſtadt. Then it was that this northern power ſeemed likely to take deep root in America. Unfortunately, ſhe laid her plantations under the yoke of excluſive privileges. lnduſtrious people of all ſects, particularly Moravians, ſtrove in vain to overcome this great difficulty. Many attempts were made to reconcile the interests of the coloniſts and their oppreſſors, but without ſucceſs. The two parties kept up a continual ſtruggte of animoſity, not of induſtry. At length the government, with a moderation not to be expected from its conſtitution, purchaſed, in 1754, the privileges and effects of the company. The price was fixed at L. 412,500, part of which was paid in ready money, and the remainder in bills upon the treaſury, bearing intereſt. From this time the navigation to the iſlands was opened to all the ſubjects of the Daniſh dominions. Of 345 plantations, which were ſeen at Santa Cruz, 150 were covered with ſugar canes, and every habitation is limited to 3000 Daniſh feet in length, and 2000 in breadth. It is inhabited by 2136 white men, by 22,244 ſlaves, and by 155 freedmen.</p><p><hi rend="italic">SANTA Cruz,</hi> in Teneriff. See TENERIFF.</p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Santa</hi><hi rend="italic"> Cruz,</hi> a town of Africa, on the coaſt of Barbary, and in the province of Suez and kingdom of Morocco, with a harbour and a fort. The Moors took it from the Portugueſe in 1536. It is ſeated at the extremity of Mount Atlas, on the Cape Aguer. W. Long. 10. 7. N. Lat. 30. 38.</p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Santa</hi><hi rend="italic"> Cruz de la Sierra,</hi> a town of South America, and capital of a province of that name in Peru, and in the audience of Los Charcas, with a biſhop's</p><p>@@@ [mu] <hi rend="italic">Raynal's History of the East and West Indies, </hi>vol. 4th, p. 298.</p></body></text></TEI>