<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:49:02Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>when once his ſentiments were fixed, he adhered to them, and defended them with reſolution. Not but that he was ingenuous enough to ſuſſer himſelf to be convinced by weighty objections; as he has ſhewn that he was open to conviction.</p><p>His chemical apparatus was neither neat nor convenient; his laboratory was ſmall and confined; nor was he particular in regard to the veſſels which he employed in his experiments, as often the firſt phial which came to hand was placed in his ſand heat: ſo that we may juſtly wonder how ſuch diſcoveries, and ſuch elegant experiments, could have been made under ſuch unfavourable circumſtances. He underſtood none of the modern languages except the German and Swediſh; ſo that he had not the advantage of being benefited by the early intelligence of discoveries made by foreigners, but was forced to wait till the intelligence was conveyed to him in the flow and uncertain channel of tranſlation. The important ſervices which Scheele did to natural philoſophy entitled him to univerſal reputation; and he obtained it: his name was well known by all Europe, and he was member of ſeveral learned academies and philoſophical ſocieties.</p><p>It was often wiſhed that he would quit his retirement at Koping, and move in a larger ſphere. It was ſuggeſted to him, that a place might be procured in England, which might afford him a good income and more leiſure; and, indeed, latterly an offer was made to him of an annuity of 300l. if he would ſettle in this country. But death, alas! put an end to this project. For half a year before this melancholy event, his health had been declining, and he himſelf was ſenſible that he would not recover. On the 19th of May 1786, he was confined to his bed; on the 21ſt he bequeathed all of which he was poſſeſſed to his wife (who was the widow of his predeceſſor at Koping, and whom he had lately married); and on the ſame day he departed this life. So the world loſt, in leſs than two years, Bergman and Scheele, of whom Sweden may juſtly boaſt; two philoſophers, who were beloved and lamented by all their contemporaries, and whoſe memory poſterity will never ceaſe moſt gratefully to revere.</p><p>SCHEINER (Chriſtopher), a German mathematician, aſtronomer, and Jeſuit, eminent for being the firſt who diſcovered ſpots on the ſun, was born at Schwaben in the territory of Middleheim in 1575. He firſt diſcovered ſpots on the ſun’s diſk in 1611, and made obſervations on theſe phenomena at Rome, until at length reducing them to order, he publiſhed them in one vol. folio in 1630. He wrote alſo ſome ſmaller things relating to mathematics and philoſophy; and died in 1690.</p><p>SCHELD, a river which riſes on the confines of Picardy, and runs north-eaſt by Cambray, Valenciennes, Tournay, Oudenarde, &amp;c. and receiving the Lis at Ghent, runs eaſt by Dendermond, and then north to Antwerp: below which city it divides into two branches, one called <hi rend="italic">the Weſler-Scheld,</hi> which ſeparates Flanders from Zealand, and diſcharges itſelf into the ſea near Fluffing; and the other called <hi rend="italic">the Ofter-Scheld,</hi> which runs by Bergen op-zoom, and afterwards between the iſlands Beveland and Schowen, and a little below falls into the ſea.</p><p>SCHEMNITZ, a town of Upper Hungary, with three caſtles. It is famous for mines of ſilver and other</p><p>metals, as alſo for hot baths. Near it is a rock of a ſhining blue colour mixed with green, and ſome ſpots of yellow. E. Long. 19. 0. N. Lat. 48. 40.</p><p>SCHERARDIA, in botany; a genus of the monogynia order, belonging to the tetrandria claſs of plants. The corolla is monopetalous and funnel-ſhaped; there are two three-toothed ſeeds.</p><p>SCHETLAND. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Shetland.</hi></p><p>SCHEUCHZERIA, in botany: A genus of the trigynia order, belonging to the hexandria claſs of plants; and in the natural method ranking under the fifth order, <hi rend="italic">Triρelatoideae.</hi> The calyx is ſexpartite; there is no corolla, nor are there any ſtyles; there are three inflated and monoſpermous capſules.</p><p>SCHIECHS, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Schech,</hi> among the Arabs, is a name applied to their nobles. “Among the Bedouins, ” ſays Niebuhr, “it belongs to every noble, whether of the higheſt or the loweſt order. Their nobles are very numerous, and compoſe in a manner the whole nation; the plebeians are invariably actuated and guided by the ſchiechs, who ſuperintend and direct in every tranſaction. The ſchiechs, and their ſubjects, are born to the life of ſhepherds and ſoldiers. The greater tribes rear many camels, which they either ſell to their neighbours, or employ them in the carriage of goods, or in military expeditions. The petty tribes keep flocks of ſheep. Among thoſe tribes which apply to agriculture, the ſchiechs live always in tents, and leave the culture of their grounds to their ſubjects, whoſe dwellings are wretched huts. Schiechs always ride on horles or dromedaries, inſpecting the conduct of their ſubjects, viſiting their friends, or hunting. Traverſing the deſert, where the horizon is wide as on the ocean, they perceive travellers at a diſtance. As travellers are ſeldom to be met with in thoſe wild tracts, they eaſily diſcover ſuch as paſs that way, and are tempted to pillage them when they find their own party the ſtrongeſt. ”</p><p>SCHINUS, in botany: A genus of the decandria order, belonging to the dicecia claſs of plants; and in the natural method ranking under the 43d order, <hi rend="italic">Dumoſr. </hi>The male calyx is quinquefid; the petals five. The female flower is the ſame as in the male; the berry tricoccous.</p><p>SCHIRAS, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Schirauz,</hi> a large and famous town of Perſia, capital of Farſiſtan, is three miles in length from eaſt to weſt, but not ſo much in breadth. It is ſeated at the north-weſt end of a ſpacious plain ſurrounded with very high hills, under one of which the town ſtands. The houſes are built of bricks dried in the ſun; the roofs are flat and terraced. There are 15 handſome moſques, tiled with ſtones of a bluiſh green colour, and lined within with black poliſhed marble. There are many large and beautiful gardens, ſurrounded with walls fourteen feet high, and four thick. They contain various kinds of very fine trees, with fruits almoſt of every kind, beſides various beautiful flowers. The wines of Schiras are not only the beſt in Perſia, but, as ſome think, in the whole world. The women are much addicted to gallantry, and Schiras is called <hi rend="italic">an earthly ρaradise</hi> by ſome. The ruins of the famous Perſepolis are 30 miles to the north-eaſt of this place. E. Long. 56. 0. N. Lat. 29. 36.</p><p>SCHISM, (from the Greek, σχισμα, <hi rend="italic">cliſt, fiſſure), </hi>in its general acceptation ſignines <hi rend="italic">divisioη</hi> or <hi rend="italic">ſeparation; </hi>but is chiefly uſed in ſpeaking of ſeparations happening</p></body></text></TEI>