<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:48:10Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>with a ſand glaſs in his hand. The Greeks ſay, that the ſtory of his mutilating his father and deſtroying his children is an allegory, which ſignifies, that Time devours the part and preſent, and will alſo devour the future. The Romans, in honour of him, built a temple and celebrated a feſtival, which they called <hi rend="italic">Saturnalia.</hi> During this feſtival no buſineſſs or profeſſion was allowed to be carried on except cookery; all diſtinctions of rank ceaſed; ſlaves could ſay what they pleaſed to their maſters with impunity; they could even rally them with their faults before their faces.</p><p>SATURNALIA, in Roman antiquity, a feſtival obſerved about the middle of December, in honour of the god Saturn, whom Lucan introduces giving an account of the ceremonies obſerved on this occaſion, thus. “During my whole reign, which laſts but for one week, no public buſineſſs is done; there is nothing but drinking, ſinging, playing, creating imaginary kings, placing ſervants with their maſters at table, &amp;c. There ſhall be no diſputes, reproaches, &amp;c. but the rich and poor, maſters and ſlaves, ſhall be equal, ” &amp;c.</p><p>On this feſtival the Romans ſacrificed bare-headed, contrary to their cuſtom at other ſacrifices.</p><p>SATURNINE, an appellation given to perſons of a melancholy diſpoſition, as being ſuppoſed under the influence of the planet Saturn.</p><p>SATURNITE, a name given by Mr Kirwan to a new metallic ſubſtance, ſuppoſed to be diſcovered by M. Monnet. It was met with in ſome lead founderies at a place named <hi rend="italic">Poulla οuen</hi> in Brittany; being ſeparated from the lead ore during its torrefaction. It reſembles lead in colour, weight, ſolubility in acids and other properties, but differs from it in being more fuſible, brittle, eaſily ſcoriſied and volatilized, and likewiſe not being miſcible with lead in fuſion. Meſſieurs Haſſenfratz and Girond contended, that this ſaturnite was nothing but a compound of different ſubſtances, and accordingly gave an analyſis of it as conſiſting of lead, copper, iron, ſilver, and ſulphur; the proportions of which muſt naturally vary according to the quality of the ore put into the furnace. M. Monnet, however, infilled that the ſubſtance analyſed by them was not that which he had diſcovered; but when he again viſited the mines above- mentioned, he could meet with none of the ſubſtance there which he found before.</p><p>SATYAVRATA, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Menu,</hi> in Indian mythology, is believed by the Hindoos to have reigned over the whole world in the earlieſt age of their chronology, and to have reſided in the country of Dravira on the coaſt of the eaſtern Indian peninſula. His patronymic name was <hi rend="italic">Vaivaſwata</hi>, or <hi rend="italic">child oſ the ſun.</hi> In the <hi rend="italic">Bhagavat</hi> we are informed, that the Lord of the Univerſe, intending to preſerve him from the ſea of deſtruction, cauſed by the depravity of the age, thus told him how he was to act. “In ſeven days from the preſent time, O thou tamer of enemies, the three worlds will be plunged in an ocean of death; but, in the midſt of the deſtroying waves, a large veffel, ſent by me for thy uſe, ſhall ſtand before thee. Then ſhalt thou take all medicinal herbs, all the variety of ſeeds; and, accompanied by ſeven ſaints, encircled by pairs of all brute animals, thou ſhalt enter the ſpacious ark and continue in it, ſecure from the flood on one immenſe ocean without light, except the radiance of thy holy companions. When the ſhip ſhall be agitated by an impetuous wind, thou</p><p>ſhalt faſten it with a large ſea-ſerpent on my horn; for I will be near thee: drawing the veffel, with thee and thy attendants, I will remain on the ocean, O chief of men, until a night of Brahma ſhall be completely ended. Thou ſhalt then know my true greatneſs, rightly named the ſupreme Godhead; by my favour, all thy queſtions ſhall be anſwered, and thy mind abundantly in- ſtructed. ” All this is ſaid to have been accompliſhed; and the ſtory is evidently that of Noah diſguiſed by A- ſiatic fiction and allegory. It proves, as Sir William Jones has rightly obſerved, an ancient Indian tradition of the univerſal deluge deſcribed by Moſes; and enables us to trace the connection between the eaſtern and weſtern traditions relating to that event. The ſame learned author has ſhown it to be in the higheſt degree probable, that the <hi rend="italic">Satyavrata</hi> of India is the <hi rend="italic">Cronus</hi> of Greece and the <hi rend="italic">Saturn</hi> of Italy. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Saturn</hi>; and <hi rend="italic">Aſiatic Reſearches,</hi> Vol. I. p. 230, &amp;c.</p><p>SATYR, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Satire,</hi> in matters oſ literature, a diſcourſe or poem, expoſing the vices and follies of mankind. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Poetry,</hi> Part II. Sect. x.</p><p>The chief ſatiriſts among the ancients are, Horace, Juvenal, and Perſius: thoſe among the moderns, are, Regnier and Boileau, in French; Butler, Dryden, Ro- cheſter, Buckingham, Swift, Pope, Young, &amp;c. among the Engliſh; and Cervantes among the Spaniards.</p><p>SATYRIASIS. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Medicine,</hi> n⁰ 372.</p><p>SATYRIUM, in botany: A genus of the diandria order, belonging to the gynandria claſs of plants; and in the natural method ranking under the 42d order, <hi rend="italic">Verticillatae.</hi> The nectarium is ſcrotiform, or inflated double behind the flower.</p><p>SATYRS (in ancient mythology), a ſpecies of demi gods who dwelt in the woods. They are repreſented as monſters, half-men, and half-goats; having horns on their heads, a hairy body, with the feet and tail of a goat. They are generally in the train that follows Bacchus. As the poets ſuppoſed that they were remarkable ſor piercing eyes and keen raillery, they have placed them in the ſame pictures with the Graces, Loves, and even with Venus herſelſ.</p><p>SAVAGE (Richard), one of the moſt remarkable characters that is to be met with perhaps in all the records of biography, was the ion of Anne counteſs of Macclesſied by the earl of Rivers, according to her own confeſſion; and was born in 1698. This confeſſion of adultery was made in order to procure a ſeparation from her huſhand the earl of Macclesfield: yet, having obtained this defired end, no ſooner was her ſpurious offspring brought into the world, than, without the dread of ſhame or poverty to excuſe her, ſhe diſcovered the reſolution of diſowning him; and, as long as he lived, treated him with the moſt unnatural cruelty. She delivered him over to a poor woman to educate as her own; prevented the earl of Rivers from leaving him a legacy of L. 6000, by declaring him dead; and in effect; deprived him of another legacy which his godmother Mrs Lloyd had left him, by concealing from him his birth, and thereby rendering it impoſſible for him to proſecute his claim. She endeavoured to ſend him ſecretly to the plantations; but this plan being either laid aſide or fruſtrated, ſhe placed him apprentice with a ſhoemaker. In this ſituation, however, he did not long continue: for his nurſe dying, he went to take care of the effects of his fiippoſcd mother; and found in</p></body></text></TEI>