<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-14T17:49:35Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>engage the induſtry of theſe adventurers in hunting or in trading with the
                ſavages.</p>
            <p>This colony was yet in its infancy when the ſettlement, which has ſince become ſo
                famous under the name of <hi rend="italic">Neva England,</hi> was firſt eſtabliſhed
                in its neighbourhood. The rapid ſucceſs of the plantations in this new colony did
                not much attract the notice of the French. This kind of proſperity did not excite
                any jealouſy between the two nations. But when they began to ſuſpect that there was
                likely to be a competition for the beaver trade and furs, they endeavoured to ſecure
                to themſelves the ſole property of it, and were unfortunate enough to ſucceed.</p>
            <p>At their firſt arrival in Acadia, they had found the peninſula, as well as the
                foreſts of the neighbouring continent, peopled with ſmall ſavage nations, who went
                under the general name of <hi rend="italic">Abenakies.</hi> Though equally fond of
                war as other ſavage nations, they were more ſociable in their manners. The
                miſſionaries eaſily inſinuating themſelves among them, had ſo far inculcated their
                tenets, as to make enthuſiaſts of them. At the ſame time that they taught them their
                religion, they inſpired them with that hatred which they themſelves entertained for
                the Engliſh name. This fundamental article of their new worſhip, being that which
                made the ſtrongeſt impreſſion on their ſenſes, and the only one that favoured their
                paſſion for war, they adopted it with all the rage that was natural to them. They
                not only refuſed to make any kind of exchange with the Engliſh, but alſo frequently
                diſturbed and ravaged the frontiers of that nation.</p>
            <p>This produced perpetual hoſtilities between the New Englanders and the French
                ſettlers in Acadia, till that province was, at the peace of Utrecht, for ever ceded
                to the Engliſh, who ſeemed not for a long time to diſcover the value of their new
                acquiſition. They reſtored to it its ancient name of <hi rend="italic">Nova
                    Scotia;</hi> and having built a ſlight fortification at Port-Royal, which they
                called <hi rend="italic">Annapolis</hi> in honour of Queen Anne, they contented
                themſelves with putting a very ſmall garriſon into it. In proceſs of time, however,
                the importance of Nova Scotia to the commerce of Great Britain began to be
                perceived; and at the peace of 1749, the miniſtry offered particular advantages to
                all perſons who choſe to go over and ſettle in Acadia. Every ſoldier, ſailor, and
                workman, was to have 50 acres of land for himſelf, and ten for every perſon he
                carried over in his family. All non-commiſſioned officers were allowed 80 for
                themſelves, and 15 for their wives and children; enſigns 200; lieutenants 300;
                captains 400; and all officers of a higher rank 600; together with 30 for each of
                their dependents. The land was to be tax free for the firſt ten years, and never to
                pay above one livre two ſols ſix deniers@@* for fifty acres. Beſide this the
                government engaged to advance or reimburſe the expences of paſſage, to build houſes,
                to furniſh all the neceſſary inſtruments for fiſhery or agriculture, and to defray
                the expences of ſubſiſtence for the firſt year. Theſe encouragements determined 3750
                perſons, in the month of May 1749, to go to America, in hopes of bettering their
                fortune,</p>
            <p>Thus encouraged, the province of Nova Scotia began to flouriſh, though in 1769 it
                ſent out only 14 veſſels and 148 boats, which together amounted to 7324 tons, and
                received 22 veſſels and 120 boats, which together made up 7000 tons. They
                conſtructed three ſloops, which did not exceed no tons burden. Their exportation for
                Great Britain and for the other parts of the globe did not amount to more than 729,
                850 livres 12 ſols 9 deniers @@†. Continuing, however, true to its allegiance when
                the other colonies threw off the dominion of Great Britain, it has now become a
                place of great conſequence both to the mother-country and the Weſt Indies. Its
                ſhipping and ſeamen are rapidly increaſing, as well as its produce, which affords
                the pleaſing proſpect of being able to ſupply itſelf with all the neceſſaries of
                life. The number of perſons who have abandoned their habitations in the more
                ſouthern provinces, and ſettled either there or in Canada, cannot be eſtimated, by
                the moſt moderate calculation, at leſs than 80,000; and it is without doubt the moſt
                convenient in point of ſituation of any province in America for a maritime power of
                Europe to be poſſeſſed of.</p>
            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Scotia,</hi> in architecture, a ſemicircular cavity or channel
                between the tores in the baſes of columns.</p>
            <p>SCOTISTS, a ſect of ſchool-divines and philoſophers, thus called from their founder
                    <hi rend="italic">J. Duns Scotus,</hi> a Scottiſh cordelier, who maintained the
                immaculate conception of the virgin, or that ſhe was born without original ſin, in
                oppoſition to Thomas Aquinas and the Thomiſts.</p>
            <p>As to philoſophy, the Scotiſts were, like the Thomiſts, Peripatetics (fee <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Peripatetics)</hi>; only diſtinguiſhed by this, that in each
                being, as many different qualities as it had, ſo many different formalities did they
                diſtinguiſh; all diſtinct from the body itſelf, and making as it were ſo many
                different entities; only theſe were metaphysical, and as it were ſuperadded to the
                being. The Scotiſts and Thomiſts likewiſe diſagreed about the nature of the divine
                co-operation with the human will, the meaſure of divine grace that is neceſſary to
                ſalvation, and other abſttruſe and minute queſtions, which it is needleſs to
                enumerate.</p>
            <p>SCOTLAND, the country of the Scots, or that part of Great Britain lying to the north
                of the Tweed; is ſituated between the 54th and 59th degrees of north latitude, and
                extends in length about 278 miles, and in ſome places near 180 in breadth;
                containing an area of 27,794 miles. On the ſouth it is bounded by England; on the
                north, eaſt, and weft, by the Deucaledonian, German, and Iriſh ſeas.</p>
            <p>It is extremely difficult to give any ſatisfactory account of the origin oſ the
                appellation of <hi rend="italic">Scots,</hi> from which the country has derived its
                name. It has puzzled the </p>
            <p>most eminent antiquaries, whoſe conjectures ſerve rather to perplex than to clear up
                the difficulty. Nor is this to be wondered at, when Varro and Dionyſius could not
                agree about the etymon of <hi rend="italic">Italia,</hi> nor Plutarch and Solinus
                about that of <hi rend="italic">Rome.</hi> All that we know with any degree of
                certainty, concerning the appellation of <hi rend="italic">Scot,</hi> amounts to
                this—That it was at firſt a term of reproach, and conſequently framed by enemies,
                rather than aſſumed by the nation diſtinguiſhed by that name. The Highlanders, who
                were the genuine deſcendants of the ancient Scots, are abſolutely ſtrangers to the
                name, and have been ſo from the beginning of time. All thoſe who ſpeak the Gaelic
                language call themſelves <hi rend="italic">Albanich</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                    >Gael,</hi> and their country <hi rend="italic">Alba</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                    >Gaeldοchd.</hi></p>
            <p>The Picts, who poſſeſſed originally the northern and</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">@@@ [m]* About 18 Sterling.</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">@@@ † About L. 30,410,8 s. 10d. Sterling.</hi></p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
