<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:48:49Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>SCANTO, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Spavento,</hi> a ſudden impreſſion of horror upon the mind and body. @@ It is extremely dreaded by the inhabitants of Sicily; and the wild ideas of the vulgar part of the inhabitants reſpecting it are almoſt incredible, and their dread of a ſudden ſhock is no leſs ſurpriſing. There is ſcarce a ſymptom, diſorder, or accident, they do not think may befal the human frame in conſequence of the ſcanto. They are perſuaded that a man who has been frightened only by a dog, a viper, ſcorpion, or any other creature, which he has an antipathy to, will ſoon be ſeized with the  ſame pains he would really feel, had he been torn with their teeth, or wounded with their venomous ſting; and that nothing can remove theſe nervous imaginary pangs but a ſtrong doſe of dilena, a ſpecies of cantharides found in Sicily.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">SCAPE goat,</hi> in the Jewiſh antiquities, the goat which was ſet at liberty on the day of ſolemn expiation. For the ceremonies on this occaſion, ſee Levit, xvi. 5, 6, &amp;c.</p><p>Some ſay, that a piece of ſcarlet cloth, in form of a tongue, was tied on the forehead of the ſcape-goat. <hi rend="italic">Hoff. Lex. Univ. in voc. Lingua.</hi></p><p>Many have been the diſputes among the interpreters concerning the meaning of the word <hi rend="italic">ſcape goat; </hi>or rather of <hi rend="italic">azazel,</hi> for which <hi rend="italic">ſcape-goat</hi> is put in our verſion of the Bible.</p><p>Spencer is of opinion, that azazel is a proper name, ſignifying the devil or evil daemon. See his reaſons in his book <hi rend="italic">De leg. Hebr. ritual.</hi> Diſſert. viii. Among other things, he obſerves, that the ancient Jews uſed to ſubſtitute the name <hi rend="italic">Samaël</hi> for <hi rend="italic">Azazel;</hi> and many of them have ventured to affirm, that at the feaſt of expiation they were obliged to offer a gift to Samael to obtain his favour. Thus alſo the goat, ſent into the wildemeſs to Azazel, was underſtood to be a gift or oblation. Some Chriſtians have been of the ſame opinion. But Spencer thinks that the genuine reaſons of the ceremony were, 1. That the goat, loaded with the ſins of the people, and ſent to Azazel, might be a ſymbolical repreſentation of the miſerable condition of ſinners. 2. God ſent the goat thus loaded to the evil daemons, to ſhow that they were impure, thereby to deter the people from any converſation or familiarity with them. 3. That the goat ſent to Azazel, ſufficiently expiating all evils, the Iſraelites might the more willingly abſtain from the expiatory ſacrifices of the Gentiles.</p><p>SCAPULA, in anatomy, the ſhoulder, or ſhoulder- bone.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Scapula</hi> (John), the reputed author of a Greek lexicon, ſtudied at Lauſanne. His name is recorded in the annals of literature, neither on account of his talents nor learning, nor virtuous induſtry, but for a groſs act of diſingenuity and fraud which he committed againſt an eminent literary character of the 16th century. Being employed by Henry Stephens as a corrector to his preſs while he was publiſhing his <hi rend="italic">Theſaurus linguae Graecae,</hi> Scapula extracted thoſe words and explications which he reckoned moſt uſeful, compriſed them in one volume, and publiſhed them as an original work, with his own name.</p><p>The compilation and printing of the Theſaurus had coſt Stephens immenſe labour and expence; but it was ſo much admired by thoſe learned men to whom he had</p><p>ſhown it, and ſeemed to be of ſuch eſſential importance to the acquiſition of the Greek language, that he reaſonably hoped his labour would be crowned with honour, and the money he had expended would be repaid by a rapid and extenſive ſale. But before his work came abroad, Scapula’s abridgment appeared; which, from its ſize and price, was quickly purchaſed, while the Theſaurus itſelf lay neglected in the author’s hands. The conſequence was, a bankruptcy on the part of Stephens, while he who had occaſioned it was enjoying the fruits of his treachery. Scapula’s Lexicon was tirſt printed in 1570, in 4to. It was afterwards enlarged, and publiſhed in folio. It has gone through ſeveral editions, while the valuable work of Stephens has never been reprinted. Its ſucceſs is, however, not owing to its ſuperior merit, but to its price and more commodious ſize. Stephens charges the author with omitting a great many important articles. He accuſes him of miſunderſtanding and perverting his meaning; and of tracing out abſurd and trifling etymologies, which he himſelf had been careful to avoid. He compoſed the following epigram on Scapula:</p><p><hi rend="italic">Quidam επιτεμνων me</hi> capulo <hi rend="italic">tenus abdidit enſem AEger eram a</hi> Scapulis, <hi rend="italic">ſanus et huc redeo.</hi></p><p>Doctor Buſby, ſo much celebrated for his knowledge of the Greek language, and his ſucceſs in teaching it, would never permit his ſcholars at Weſtminſter ſchool to make uſe of Scapula.</p><p>SCAPULAR, in anatomy, the name of two pair of arteries, and as many veins.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Scapular,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Scapulary,</hi> a part of the habit of ſeveral religious orders in the church of Rome, worn over the gown as a badge of peculiar veneration for the Bleſſed Virgin. It conſiſts of two narrow flips or breadths of cloth covering the back and the breaſt, and hanging down to the feet. —The devotees of the ſcapulary celebrate its feſtival on the 10th of July</p><p>SCARABAEUS, the <hi rend="smallcaps">Beetle,</hi> in zoology, a genus of infects of the coleoptera order: the antennae of the beetles are of a clavated figure, and fiſſile longitudinally; and their legs are frequently dentated. There are 87 ſpecies; all, however, concurring in one common formation of having caſes to their wings, which are the more neceſſary to thoſe infects, as they often live under the ſurface of the earth, in holes, which they dig out by their own induſtry. The caſes prevent the various injuries their real wings might ſuſtain by rubbing or cruſhing againſt the ſides of their abode; Theſe, though they do not aſſiſt flight, yet keep the internal wings clean and even, and produce a loud buzzing noiſe when the animal riſes in the air.</p><p>It we examine the formation of all animals of the beetle kind, we ſhall find, as in ſhell fiſh, that their bones are placed externally, and their muſcles within. Theſe muſcles are formed very much like thoſe of quadrupeds; and are formed with ſuch ſurpriſing ſtrength, that, bulk for bulk, they are a thouſand times ſtronger than thoſe of a man. The ſtrength of theſe muſcles is of uſe in digging the animal’s ſubterraneous abode, whither it moſt frequently returns, even after it becomes a winged infect capable of flying.</p><p>Beſides the difference which reſults from the ſhape and colour oſ theſe animals, the ſize alſo makes a conſiderable one; ſome beetles being not larger than the</p><p><hi rend="italic">@@@ [mu] </hi>Swinburne's Travels in the two Sicilies.</p></body></text></TEI>