<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:49:39Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>productive of any ſolid or laſting advantage to the Romans; ſince we find that Agricola, inſtead of putting an end to the war by the immediate conqueſt of all Caledonia, retreated into the country of the Foreſti, commonly ſuppoſed to be Forſarſhire, though others imagine it to have been the county of Fife. Here he received hoſtages from part of the Caledonians; and ordered part of his fleet to ſail round Britain, that they might diſcover whether it was an iſland or a continent. The Romans no former had left that part of the country, than the Caledonians demoliſhed all the forts they had raiſed: and Agricola being ſoon after recalled by Domitian, the further progreſs of the Roman arms was flopped; Galgacus proving ſuperior to any of the ſucceſors of that general.</p><p>From the time of Agricola to that of Adrian, we know little of the affairs of Scotland, excepting that during this interval the Scots muſt have entirely driven the Romans out of their country, and reconquered all that tract which lay between Agricola’s chain of forts and Carliſle on the weſt, and Newcaſtle or Tinmouth- Bar on the eaſt; which Adrian, on viſiting Britain, thought proper to fix as the northern boundary of the Roman dominions. Here he built a wall of turf between the mouth of the Tine and the Solway frith, with a view to ſhut out the barbarians; which, however, did not anſwer the purpoſe, nor indeed could it be thought to do ſo, as it was only built of turf, and guarded by no more than 18,000 men, who could not be ſuppoſed a ſufficient force to defend ſuch an extent of fortification.</p><p>On the departure of Adrian, he left Julius Severus as his lieutenant: but this man, though one of the greateſt commanders of his age, did not carry his arms to the northward of Adrian’s wall; and this long interval of peace gave ſo much ſecurity to Mogold the Scottiſh monarch, that he degenerated into a tyrant, and was murdered by ſome of his noblemen. The only inſtance of his tyranny which is produced, however, is a law by which it was enacted, that the eſtates of ſuch as were condemned ſhould be forfeited to his exchequer, without any part thereof being allotted to their wives and children; an act which ſubſiſts almoſt in its full force to this day in Great Britain and the beſt regulated European governments.</p><p>In the reign of Antoninus Pius, the proprietor Lollius Urbius drove the Scots far to the northward, and repaired the chain of forts built by Agricola, which lay between the Carron on the frith of Forth and Dunglaſs on the Clyde. Theſe were joined together by turf walls, and formed a much better defence than the wall of Adrian. However, after the death of Antoninus, Commodus having recalled Calpurnius Agricola, an able commander, who kept the Scots in awe,  a more dangerous war broke out than had ever been experienced by the Romans in that quarter. The Scots having paſſed the wall, put all the Romans they could meet with to the ſword: but they were ſoon repulſed by Ulpius Marcellus, a general of conſummate abilities, whom Commodus ſent into the iſland. — In a ſhort time the tyrant alſo recalled this able commander. After his departure, the Roman diſcipline in Britain ſuffered a total relaxation; the ſoldiery grew mutinous, and great djſorders enſued: but theſe were all happily removed by the arrival, of Clodius Albinus, a perſon of great ſkill and experience in military affairs. His preſence for ſome time reſtrained the Scots within proper bounds: but a civil war breaking out between him and Severus, Albinus croſſed over to the continent with the greateſt part of the Roman forces in Britain; and meeting his antagoniſt at Lyons, a dreadful battle enſued, in which Albinus was utterly defeated, and his army cut in pieces. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Rome,</hi> n⁰ 375.</p><p>The abſence of the Roman forces gave encouragement to the Scots to renew their depredations, which they did with ſuch ſucceſs, that the emperor became apprehenſive of loſing the whole iſland; on which he determined to go in perſon and quell theſe troubleſome enemies. The army he collected upon this occaſion was far more numerous than any the Romans had ever ſent into Britain; and being commanded by ſuch an able general as Severus, it may eaſily be ſuppoſed that the Scots muſt have been very hard preſſed. The particulars of this important expedition are very imperfectly related; however, we are aſſured that Severus loſt a vaſt number of men, it is ſaid not leſs than 50,000, in his march through Scotland. Notwithſtanding, he penetrated, it is laid, to the moſt northern extremity of the iſland, and obliged the enemy to yield up their arms. On his return, he built a much ſtronger fortification to ſecure the frontiers againſt the enemy than had ever been done before, and which in ſome places coincided with Adrian’s wall, but extended farther at each end. But in the meantime, the Scots, provoked by the brutality of the emperor’s ſon Caracalla, whom he had left regent in his abſence, again, took arms: on which Severus himſelf took the field, with a deſign, as it would ſeem, to extirpate the whole nation; for he gave orders to his ſoldiers “not to ſpare even the child in the mother’s belly.” The event of his furious declaration is unknown: but in all probability the death of the emperor, which happened ſoon after, put a flop to the execution of this revenge; and it is certain that his ſon Caracalla, who ſucceeded Severus, ratified the peace with the Scots.</p><p>During all theſe important tranſactions, Scotland was governed by Donald I. who is ſaid to have been the firſt Chriſtian king of this country. From him to the time of Eugene I. no remarkable occurrence offers; but under the latter, the Roman and Fictiſh forces were united againſt the Scots. The Picts were commanded by their king, named <hi rend="italic">Hargust;</hi> and the Romans by Maximus, who murdered Valentinian III. and afterwards aſſumed the empire @@<hi rend="italic">§</hi>. The allies defeated Eugene in the county of Galioway; but Maximus being obliged to return ſouthward on account of an inſurrection, the Picts were in their turn defeated by the Scots. Next year, however, Maximus marched againſt the Scots; who being now reduced to extremity, brought into the field not only all the men capable of bearing arms, but the women alſo. In this engagement the Picts would have been utterly defeated, had not they been ſupported by the Romans; but Eugene being killed, with the greateſt part of his nobility, the Scots were defeated; and ſo well did the conquerors improve their victory, that their antagoniſts were at laſt totally driven out of the country. Some of them took refuge in the Aebudae iſlands, and ſome in Scandinavia and Ireland, from whence they made frequent deſcents upon Scotland. The Picts were at firſt mightily pleased</p><p><hi rend="italic">@@@ § See Rome, n⁰ 536.</hi></p></body></text></TEI>