<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-14T17:50:07Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>are diviſible, the eldeſt female heir has a certain prerogative, it is not ſo in a
                kingdom that is indivisible; there the neareſt heir of blood is preferable whenever
                the ſucceſſion opens. —To this Baliol replied, that the claimants were in the court
                of their lord paramount; and that he ought to give judgment in this caſe, as in the
                caſe of any other tenements, depending on his crown, that is, by the common law and
                uſage of his kingdom, and no other. That by the laws and uſages of England, the
                eldeſt female heir is preferred in the succeſſion to all inheritances, indiviſible
                as well as diviſible.</p>
            <p>3. It was urged by Bruce, that the manner of ſucceſſion to the kingdom of Scotland in
                former times, made for his claim; for that the brother, as being neareſt in degree,
                was wont to be preferred to the ſon of the deceaſed king. Thus, when Kenneth
                Macalpin died, his brother Donald was preferred to his ſon Conſtantine, and this was
                confirmed by ſeveral other authentic inſtances in the hiſtory of Scotland. — Baliol
                anſwered, that if the brother was preferred to the ſon of the king, the example
                proved againſt Bruce; for that the ſon, not the brother, was the neareſt in degree.
                He admitted, that after the death of Malcolm III. his brother uſurped the throne;
                but he contended, that the ſon of Malcolm complained to his liege lord the king of
                England, who diſpoſſeſſed the uſurper, and placed the ſon of Malcolm on the throne;
                that after the death of that ſon the brother of Malcolm III. again uſurped the
                throne; but the king of England again diſpoſſeſſed him, and raiſed Edgar, the ſecond
                ſon of Malcolm, to the ſovereignty.</p>
            <p>4. Bruce pleaded, that there are examples in other countries, particularly in Spain
                and Savoy, where the ſon of the ſecond daughter excluded the grandſon of the eldeſt
                daughter. Baliol anſwered, that examples from foreign countries are of no
                importance; for that according to the laws of England and Scotland, where kings
                reign by ſucceſſion in the direct line, and earls and barons ſucceed in like manner,
                the iſſue of the younger ſiſter, although nearer in degree, excludes not the iſſue
                of the eldeſt ſiſter, although more remote; but the ſucceſſion continues in the
                direct line.</p>
            <p>5. Bruce pleaded, that a female ought not to reign, as being incapable of governing:
                That at the death of Alexander III. the mother of Baliol was alive; and as ſhe could
                not reign, the kingdom devolved upon him, as being the neareſt male heir of the
                blood royal. But to this Baliol replied, that Bruce’s argument was inconſiſtent with
                his claim: for that if a female ought not to reign, Iſabella the mother of Bruce
                ought not, nor must Bruce himſelf claim through her. Beſides, Bruce himſelf had
                ſworn fealty to a female, the maiden of Norway.</p>
            <p>The arguments being thus ſtated on both ſides, Edward demanded an anſwer from the
                council as to the merits of the competitors. He alſo put the following queſtion to
                them: By the laws and uſages of both kingdoms, does the iſſue of the eldeſt ſiſter,
                though more remote in one degree, exclude the iſſue of the ſecond ſiſter, though
                nearer in one degree? or ought the nearer in one degree, iſſuing from the ſecond
                ſiſter, to exclude the more remote in one degree iſſuing from the eldeſt ſiſter? To
                this it was anſwered unanimouſly, That by the laws and uſages of both kingdoms, in
                every heritable ſucceffion, the more remote in one degree lienally deſcended from
                the eldeſt ſiſter, was preferable to the nearer in degree iſſuing from the ſecond
                ſiſter. In conſequence of this, Bruce was excluded from the ſucceſſion; upon which
                he entered a claim for one third of the kingdom: but being baffled in this alſo, the
                kingdom of Scotland being determined an indiviſible ſee, Edward ordered John. Baliol
                to have ſeiſin of Scotland; with this caveat, however, “That this judgment ſhould
                not impair his claim to the property of Scotland.”</p>
            <p>After ſo many diſgraceſul and humiliating conceſſions on the part of the Scots, John
                Baliol was crowned king at Scone on the 30th November 1292; and ſiniſhed the
                ceremony by doing homage to the king of England. All his ſubmiſſions, however, could
                not ſatisfy Edward, as long as the leaſt ſhadow of independence remained to
                Scotland. A citizen of Berwick appealed from a ſentence of the Scots judges
                appointed by Edward, in order to carry his cauſe into England. But this was oppoſed
                by Baliol, who pleaded a promiſe made by the Engliſh monarch, that he ſhould
                “obſerve the laws and uſages of Scotland, and not withdraw any cauſes from Scotland
                into his Engliſh courts.” Edward replied, that it belonged to him to hear the
                complaints made againſt his own miniſters; and concluded with aſſerting his right,
                not only to try Scots cauſes in England, but to ſummon the king of Scotland, if
                neceſſary, to appear before him in perſon. Baliol had not ſpirit to reſiſt; and
                therefore ſigned a moſt diſgraceful inſtrument, by which he declared, that all the
                obligations which Edward had come under were already fulfilled, and therefore that
                he diſcharged them all.</p>
            <p>Edward now thought proper to give Baliol ſome marks of his favour, the moſt
                remarkable of which was giving him ſeiſin of the Iſle of Man; but it ſoon appeared
                that he intended to exerciſe his rights of ſuperiority in the moſt provoking manner.
                The firſt inſtance was in the caſe of Malcolm earl of Fife. This nobleman had two
                ſons, Colban his heir, and another who is conſtantly mentioned in hiſtory by the
                family- name of Macduff. —It is ſaid, that Malcolm put Macduff in poſſeſſion of the
                lands of Reres and Crey. Malcolm died in 1266; Colban his ſon, in 1270; Duncan the
                ſon of Colban, in 1288. To this laſt earl, his ſon Duncan, an infant, ſucceeded.
                During the nonage of this Duncan, grand-nephew of Macduff, William biſhop of St
                Andrew’s, guardian of the earldom, diſpoſſeſſed Macduff. He complained to Edward;
                who having ordered his cauſe to be tried, reſtored him again to poſſeſſion. Matters
                were in this ſtate when Baliol held his firſt parliament at Scone, 10th February
                1292. There Macduff was cited to anſwer for having taken poffeſſion of the lands of
                Reres and Crey, which were in poſſeſſion of the king ſince the death of the laſt
                earl of Fife. As his defences did not ſatisfy the court, he was condemned to
                impriſonment; but an action was reſerved to him againſt Duncan, when he ſhould come
                of age, and againſt his heirs. In all this defence, it is ſurpriſing that Macduff
                ſhould have omitted his ſtrongeſt argument, viz. that the regents, by Edward’s
                authority, had put him in poſſeſſion, and that Baliol had ratified all things under
                Edward’s authority. However, as ſoon as he was ſet at liberty, he petitioned Baliol
                for a rehearing; but this being refuſed, he appealed</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
