<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-14T17:47:55Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>border of light freſh earth, but muſt be watered and ſhaded in hot dry weather, until
                they have taken root; after which they will require no farther care but to keep them
                clean from weeds till autumn, when they ſhould be tranſplanted where they are
                deſigned to remain: but if the ground is not ready by that time to receive them, it
                will be proper to let them remain in the border until ſpring; for if they are
                tranſplanted late in autumn, they are liable to be deſtroyed by cold in winter.</p>
            <p>SANTORINI, an iſland of the Archipelago, to the north of Candia, and to the
                ſouth-weſt of Nanphio. It is eight miles in length, and near as much in breadth, and
                almoſt covered with pumice-ſtone, whence the ſoil in general muſt be dry and barren;
                it is, however, greatly improved by the labour and in- duſtry of the inhabitants,
                who have turned it into a garden. It affords a great deal of barley, plenty of
                cotton, and large quantities of wine. Fruit is ſcarce except figs; and they have
                neither oil nor wood. The inhabitants are all Greeks, and are about 10,000 in
                number. Pyrgos is the capital town, and there are ſeveral little towns and villages.
                They have but one ſpring in the iſland, for which reaſon they preſerve the
                rain-water in ciſterns. Though ſubject to the Turks, they chooſe their own
                magiſtrates. E. Long. 25. 5. N. Lat. 39. 10.</p>
            <p>SANZIO (Raphael). See <hi rend="smallcaps">Raphael.</hi></p>
            <p>SAO, a territory, called a kingdom, of Africa, on the gold-coaſt of Guinea, hardly
                two miles in length along the ſhore. It produces abundance of Indian corn, yams,
                potatoes, palm-wine, and oil. The inhabitants are very treacherous, and there is no
                dealing with them without a great deal of caution. It contains ſeveral villages, of
                which Sabo is the principal; and the Dutch have a fort here called <hi rend="italic"
                    >Naſſau.</hi></p>
            <p>SAONE, a conſiderable river of France, which has its ſource in mount Voſgue, near
                Darney; runs through the Franche Comte, Burgundy, Beaujolois; and falls into the
                Rhone at Lyons. It paſſes by Gray, Chalons, and Maſcon.</p>
            <p>SAP, the juice found in vegetables.</p>
            <p>We obſerved, when treating of <hi rend="smallcaps">Plants,</hi> that it has been long
                diſputed whether the ſap of plants be analogous to the blood of animals, and
                circulates in the fame manner. We alſo mentioned the concluſions that Dr Halesdrew
                from his numerous experiments, which were all in oppoſition to the doctrine that the
                lap circulates. As the ſubject is curious and intereſting, and as additional light
                has been thrown upon it of late years, we wiſh to communicate it to our readers as
                fully as our limits will permit.</p>
            <p>As the vegetable economy is ſtill but imperfectly underſtood, and experiments made
                for tracing the motion of the ſap may lead to important diſcoveries, we are happy to
                find, that of late years this ſubject has been again revived. Dr Walker, profeſſor
                of Natural Hiſtory in the univerſity of Edinburgh, has publiſhed in the 1ſt volume
                of the Philoſophical Tranſactions of Edinburgh an account of a courſe of very
                accurate and ingenious experiments, accompanied with obſervations and concluſions
                made with a caution which inſpires confidence, and is indeed worthy of a diſciple of
                Bacon. He is the firſt perſon, as far as we know, who thought of comparing the
                thermometer with the motion of the ſap,</p>
            <p>It is well known that in the ſpring vegetables contain a great quantity of ſap; and
                there are ſome trees, as the birch and plane, which, if wounded, will diſcharge a
                great portion of it. Whence is this moiſture derived? Whether is it imbibed from the
                atmoſphere, or does it flow from the ſoil through the roots? Theſe are the queſtions
                which require firſt to be anſwered; and Dr Walker’s experiments enable us to anſwer
                them with confidence.</p>
            <p>He ſelected a vigorous young birch, 30 feet high and 26 inches in circumference at
                the ground. He bored a hole juſt above the ground on the 1ſt of February, and cut
                one of its branches at the extremity. He repeated this every ſecond day; but no
                moiſture appeared at either of the places till the 5th of May, when a ſmall quantity
                flowed on making an inciſion near the ground. He then cut 21 inciſions in the trunk
                of the tree, on the north side, at the diſtance of a foot from one another, and
                reaching from the ground to the height of 20 feet. The inciſions were ſolid
                triangles, each side being an inch long and an inch deep, and penetrating through
                the bark and wood. Dr Walker viſited the tree almoſt every day for two months, and
                marked exactly from which of the inciſions the ſap flowed. He obſerved that it
                flowed from the loweſt inciſion firſt, and gradually aſcended to the higheſt. The
                following table will ſhow the progreſs of the ſap upwards, and its correſpondence
                with the thermometer.</p>
            <p>The firſt column is the day of the month on which the obſervation was made; the
                ſecond expreſſes the number of inciſions from which the ſap flowed on the day of the
                month oppoſite; and the third column the degree of the thermometer at noon. Some
                days are omitted in March, as the inciſions, though made on the 5th, did not bleed
                till the 11th. Some days are alſo paſſed over in April, becauſe no obſervation was
                made on account of rain.</p>
            <table>
                <row>
                    <cell>March.</cell>
                    <cell>N of In.</cell>
                    <cell>Γher. Noon.</cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell>March.</cell>
                    <cell>N. of In.</cell>
                    <cell>Ther. Noon.</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>5</cell>
                    <cell>—</cell>
                    <cell>46</cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell>30</cell>
                    <cell>8</cell>
                    <cell>50</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>11</cell>
                    <cell>2</cell>
                    <cell>49</cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell>31</cell>
                    <cell>7</cell>
                    <cell>62</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>I2</cell>
                    <cell>2</cell>
                    <cell>49</cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>13</cell>
                    <cell>1</cell>
                    <cell>44</cell>
                    <cell>April</cell>
                    <cell>2</cell>
                    <cell>7</cell>
                    <cell>46</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>14</cell>
                    <cell>4</cell>
                    <cell>48</cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell>4</cell>
                    <cell>10</cell>
                    <cell>53</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>15</cell>
                    <cell>5</cell>
                    <cell>52</cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell>7</cell>
                    <cell>11</cell>
                    <cell>49</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>16</cell>
                    <cell>5</cell>
                    <cell>47</cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell>8</cell>
                    <cell>11</cell>
                    <cell>48</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>17</cell>
                    <cell>4</cell>
                    <cell>44</cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell>9</cell>
                    <cell>12</cell>
                    <cell>50</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>18</cell>
                    <cell>5</cell>
                    <cell>47</cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell>10</cell>
                    <cell>13</cell>
                    <cell>53</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>19</cell>
                    <cell>6</cell>
                    <cell>48</cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell>11</cell>
                    <cell>13</cell>
                    <cell>45</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>20</cell>
                    <cell>5</cell>
                    <cell>44</cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell>12</cell>
                    <cell>13</cell>
                    <cell>44</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>21</cell>
                    <cell>7</cell>
                    <cell>48</cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell>13</cell>
                    <cell>13</cell>
                    <cell>43</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>22</cell>
                    <cell>7</cell>
                    <cell>45</cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell>14</cell>
                    <cell>14</cell>
                    <cell>55</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>23</cell>
                    <cell>8</cell>
                    <cell>46</cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell>15</cell>
                    <cell>14</cell>
                    <cell>49</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>24</cell>
                    <cell>9</cell>
                    <cell>47</cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell>16</cell>
                    <cell>16</cell>
                    <cell>56</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>25</cell>
                    <cell>9</cell>
                    <cell>42</cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell>18</cell>
                    <cell>16</cell>
                    <cell>50</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>26</cell>
                    <cell>7</cell>
                    <cell>39</cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell>19</cell>
                    <cell>17</cell>
                    <cell>54</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>27</cell>
                    <cell>8</cell>
                    <cell>45</cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell>20</cell>
                    <cell>19</cell>
                    <cell>56</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>28</cell>
                    <cell>8</cell>
                    <cell>49</cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell>21</cell>
                    <cell>20</cell>
                    <cell>54</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>29</cell>
                    <cell>8</cell>
                    <cell>46</cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell>22</cell>
                    <cell>21</cell>
                    <cell>52</cell>
                </row>
            </table>
            <p>Dr Walker found that the ſap aſcends through the wood, and ſtill more copiouſly
                between the wood and the bark; but none could be perceived aſcending through the
                pith or the bark. He found alſo, that when the thermometer at noon is about 49, or
                between 46 and 50, the ſap riſes about one foot in 24 hours; that when the
                thermometer is about 45 at noon, it aſcends about</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
