<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-14T17:50:38Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>During a long courſe of war, the common people had been accustomed to plunder and
                bloodſhed; and having now no Engliſh enemies to employ them, they robbed and
                murdered one another. The methods by which Randolph repreſſed theſe crimes were much
                the ſame with thoſe which have been adopted in latter times; for he made the
                counties liable for the ſeveral robberies committed within their bounds. He even
                ordered the farmers and labourers not to houſe the tools employed by them in
                agriculture during the night-time, that the ſheriff’s officers might be the more
                vigilant in ſecuring them. He gave orders for ſeverely puniſhing all vagabonds, and
                obliged them to work for their livelihood; making proclamation, that no man ſhould
                be admitted into a town or borough who could not earn his bread by his labour. Theſe
                regulations were attended with the moſt ſalutary effects. A fellow who had ſecreted
                his own plough-irons, pretending that they were ſtolen, being detected by the
                ſheriſſ’s officers, was inſtantly hanged. A certain man having killed a prieſt, went
                to Rome, and obtained abſolution from the pope; after which he boldly returned to
                Scotland. Randolph ordered him to be tried, and, on his conviction, to be executed::
                “Becauſe,” ſaid he, “although the pope may grant abſolution from the ſpiritual
                conſequences of ſin, he cannot ſcreen offenders from civil puniſhment.”</p>
            <p>King Robert, juſt before his death, had deſired that his heart might be depoſited in
                our Saviour’s ſepulchre at Jeruſalem; and on this errand the great commander Douglas
                was employed, who ſet ſail in June 1530 with a numerous and ſplendid retinue. He
                anchored off Sluys in Flanders, the great emporium of the low countries, where he
                expected to find companions in his pilgrimage; but learning that Alphonſus XI. the
                young king of Leon and Caſtile, was engaged in a war with Oſmyn the Moor, he could
                not reſiſt the temptation of fighting againſt the enemies of Chriſtianity. He met
                with an honourable reception at the court of Spain, and readily obtained leave to
                enter into what was thought the common cauſe oſ Chriſtianity. The Spaniards first
                came in ſight of their enemy, near Theba, a caſtle on the frontiers of Andaluſia,
                towards the kingdom of Granada. The Moors were defeated; but, Douglas, giving way to
                his impetuous valour, pursued</p>
            <p>the enemy too eagerly, and throwing among them the caſket which contained the heart
                of his ſovereign, cried out, “Now paſs thou onward as thou went wont; Douglas will
                follow thee or die.” The fugitives rallied and ſurrounded Douglas; who, with a few
                of his followers, was killed in attempting to reſcue Sir Waller St Clair of Roflin.
                His body was brought back to Scotland, and interred in the church of Douglas. His
                countrymen perpetuated his memory by beſtowing upon him the epithet of th<hi
                    rend="italic">e good Sir James Douglas.</hi> He was one of the greateſt
                commanders of the age; and is ſaid to have been engaged in 70 Battles, 57 of which
                he gained, and was defeated in 13. —Of him it is reported, that meeting with an
                officer at the court of Alphonſus, who had his face quite disfigured with fears, the
                latter ſaid to him, “It aſtoniſhes me, that you, who are ſaid to have ſeen ſo much
                ſervice, ſhould have no marks of wounds on your face.” “Thank heaven,” anſwered
                Douglas, “I had always an arm to protect my face.”</p>
            <p>In 1331, Edward Baliol began to renew his pretenſions to the crown of Scotland, about
                the fame time that David II. and his conſort Johanna were crowned at Scone; which
                ceremony was performed on the 24th of November. Some hiſtorians relate, that he was
                excited to this attempt by one Twynham Lowriſon, a perſon who had been
                excommunicated for refusing to do penance for adultery, and afterwards was obliged
                to fly on account of his having way-laid the official, beat him, and extorted a ſum
                of money from him. But however this may be, it uncertain, that in this year
                differences began to ariſe with England, on the following account. It had been
                provided by an article of the treaty of Northampton, that “Thomas lord Wake of
                Ledel, Henry de Beaumont, called <hi rend="italic">earl of Buchan,</hi> and Henry de
                Percy, ſhould be reſtored to their eſtates, of which the king of Scots, by reaſon of
                the war between the two nations, had taken poſſeſſion.” This article had been
                executed with reſpect to Percy, but not to the other two; and though Edward had
                repeatedly complained of this neglect, he could not obtain any satisfaction @@<hi
                    rend="smallcaps">(g).</hi></p>
            <p>The diſinherited batons now reſolved to invade Scotland, though their force conſiſted
                of no more than 3000</p>
            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">@@@(g)</hi> As this is an important period of hiſtory, we ſhall
                here transcribe the opinion of lord Hailes concerning the cauſes of this ſtrange
                delay of executing an article ſeemingly of little importance where a nation was
                concerned. “By the treaty of Northampton," ſays she, “all the claims of the Engliſh
                Batons to inheritances in Scotland were diſregarded, excepting thoſe of Henry de
                Percy, Thomas lord Wake of Ledel, and Henry de Beaumont. Percy procured
                ſatisfaction: but the others did not.</p>
            <p>“Henry de Beaumont, in the reign of Edward II. had aſſociated himſelf with the
                ability againſt the D’Efpenſers, and on that account had ſuffered impriſonment and
                exile. He aided queen Iſabella in the invaſion which proved the cauſe of the
                depoſition, captivity, and death of her huſband. Although, under the adminiſtration
                of Mortimer, he had obtained a ſhare in the partition of the ſpoils of the
                D’Lſpeaſers, he perſiſted in oppoſing the meaſures of the new favourite; and
                although his own intereſts were ſecured by the treaty of Northampton, he boldly
                exclaimed againſt the injuſtice done to the other barons by that treaty. He joined
                the princes of the blood-royal in their attempt to reſcue the young king from the
                hands of Iſabella and her minion, and place him in their own; and, on the failure of
                that ill-adviſed conspiracy, he again took refuge in foreign parts. It appears that
                lord Wake, having followed the political opinions of Henry de Beaumont, was involved
                in like calamities and diſgrace. While the queen-dowager and Mortimer retained their
                influence, the claims of thoſe two barons were altogether overlooked: But within
                forty-eight hours after the. execution of Mortimer, a peremptory demand was made by
                Edward III. to have their inheritance reſtored.</p>
            <p>“The demand was unexpected and alarming. Made at the very moment of the fall of
                Iſabella and Mortimer, <pb n="766"> </pb>and in behalf of men who had loudly proteſted
                againſt the treaty of Northampton, it indicated a total and perilous change in the
                ſyſtem of the Engliſh.</p>
            <p>“Randolph, of late years, had beheld extraordinary viciſſitudes in England. The
                D’Eſpenſers alternately perſecuted and triumphant, and at length abaſed in the duſt:
                The fugitive Mortimer elevated to ſupreme authority, victorious over the princes of
                the bloody-royal, and then dragged to a gibbet. Hence it was natural for Randolph to
                wiſh, and even to look, for ſome new revolution, which might prove more favourable
                to the Scottiſh intereſts. Meanwhile, with great reaſon and good policy, he delayed
                the reſtitution of the inheritances claimed under the treaty of Northampton, in
                behalf of the avowed oppoſers of that treaty.</p>
            <p>Beſides, it was neceſſary for Randolph to be aſſured that the Engliſh, while they
                urged the performance of one article of that treaty, did, on their part, ſincerely
                purpoſe to perform its more important articles, by continuing to acknowledge the
                ſucceſſion in the houſe of Bruce, and the independency of the Scottiſh nation.</p>
            <p>“Of this, however, there was much reaſon to doubt. For the Engliſh king had taken
                Baliol under his protection, and had granted him a paſſport to come into England,
                with permiſſion to reſide there during a whole year, (10th October 1330). Theſe
                things had no friendly or pacific appearance.</p>
            <p>“Be this as it will, the event too fatally juſtified the apprehenſions of Randolph;
                for, while Edward III. was demanding reſtitution of the eſtates reſerved by the
                treaty of Northampton, his ſubſects were arming in violation of that treaty.</p>
            <p>“It is remarkable, that, on the 24th March 1331-2, Edward appears to have known of
                the hoſtile aſſociation of the diſinherited barons. His words are, ‘Quia ex relatu
                accepimus plurimorum, quod diverſi homines de regno noſtro, et alii (meaning Baliol
                and his attendants), pacem inter nos, et Robertum de Brus, nuper Regem Scotorum,
                initam et confirmatam infringere machinantes, diversas congregationes hominum ad
                arma indies faciunt, et, <hi rend="italic">per marchas regni nostri, dictam
                    terram</hi> Scotiae, <hi rend="italic">ad eam modo guerrino impugnandum, ingredi
                    intendunt; Foedera,</hi> T. iv. p. 511. And yet, on the 22d April following, he
                demanded reſtitution of the inheritance of lord Wake, one of the barons in arms;”
                    <hi rend="italic">Foedera,</hi> T. iv. p. 518.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
