<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-14T17:51:18Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>mortgage of the iſles of Shetland for the other 8000, The Scottiſh plenipotentiaries,
                of whom Boyd earl of Arran was one, gratified him in his requeſt; and this
                conceſſion is thought to have proved fatal to the earl. Certain it is, that his
                father was beheaded for treasonable practices alleged to have been committed long
                before, and for which he produced a parliamentary indemnity to no purpoſe: the earl
                himſelf was divorced from his wife the king’s filter, and obliged to live in
                perpetual exile, while the counteſs was married to another.</p>
            <p>In 1476, thoſe misfortunes began to come on James which afterwards terminated in his
                ruin. He had made his brother, the duke of Albany, governor of Berwick; and had
                entruſted him with very extenſive powers upon the borders, where a violent
                propenſity for the feudal law ſtill continued. The Humes and the Hepburns, then the
                moſt powerful ſubjects in thoſe parts, could not brook the duke of Albany's
                greatneſs, eſpecially after he had forced them, by virtue of a late act, to part
                with ſome of the eſtates which had been inconſiderately granted them in this and the
                preceding reign. The pretended ſcience of judicial aſtrology, by which James
                happened to be incredibly infatuated, was the eaſieſt as well as moſt effectual
                engine that could work their purpoſes. One Andrew, an infamous impoſtor in that art,
                had been brought over from Flanders by James; and he and Schevez, then archbiſhop of
                St Andrew’s, concurred in perſuading James that the Scotch lion was to be devoured
                by his own whelps; a prediction that, to a prince of James’s turn, amounted to a
                certainty.</p>
            <p>The condition to which James reduced himſelf by his belief in judicial aſtrology, was
                truly deplorable. The princes upon the continent were ſmitten with the ſame
                infatuation; and the wretches who beſieged his peribn had no ſafety but by
                continuing the deluſion in his mind. According to Lindſay, Cochran, who had ſome
                knowledge of architecture, and had been introduced to James as a maſter-maſon,
                privately procured an old woman, who pretended to be a witch, and who heightened his
                terrors by declaring that his brothers intended to murder him. James believed her;
                and the unguarded manner in which the earl of Mar treated his weakneſs, exaſpersoted
                him ſo much, that the earl giving a farther looſe to his tongue in railing againſt
                his brother’s unworthy favourites, was arreſted, and committed to the caſtle of
                Craig Miller; from whence he was brought to the Canongate, a ſuburb of Edinburgh,
                where he ſuffered death.</p>
            <p>The duke of Albany was at the caſtle of Dunbar when his brother the earl of Mar's
                tragedy was acted; and James could not be eaſy without having him like- wise in his
                power. In hopes of ſurpriſing him, he marched to Dunbar: but the duke, being
                apprized of his coming, fled to Berwick, and ordered his caſtle of Dunbar to be
                ſurrendered to the lord Evendale, though not before the garriſon had provided
                themſelves with boats and final! veſſels, in which they eſcaped to England. He
                ventured to come to Edinburgh; where James was ſo well ſerved with ſpies, that he
                was ſeized,</p>
            <p>and committed close prisoner to the caſtle, with orders that he ſhould ſpeak with
                none but in the preſſence of his keepers. The duke had probably ſuſpected and
                provided againſt this diſagreeable event; ſor we are told that he had agents, who
                every day repaired to the caſtle, as if they had come from court, and reported the
                ſtate of matters between him and the king, while his keepers were preſent, in ſo
                favourable a light, that they made no doubt of his ſoon regaining his liberty, and
                being readmitted to his brother’s favour. The ſeeming negociation, at laſt, went ſo
                proſperouſly on, that the duke gave his keepers a kind of a farewell entertainment,
                previous to his obtaining a formal deliverance; and they drank ſo immoderately, that
                being intoxicated, they gave him an opportunity of eſcaping over the caſtle wall, by
                converting the ſheets of his bed into a rope. Whoever knows the ſituation of that
                fortrefs, muſt be amazed at the boldness of this attempt; and we are told that the
                duke’s valet, the only domestic he was allowed to have, making the experiment before
                his maſter, broke his neck: upon which the duke, lengthening the rape, slid down
                unhurt; and carrying his fervant on his back to a place of ſafety, he went on board
                a ſhip which his friends had provided, and eſcaped to France.</p>
            <p>In 1482, the king began to feel the bad conſequences of taking into his favour men of
                worthleſs characters, which ſeems to have been one of this prince’s pernicious
                foibles. His great favourite at this time was, Cochran, whom he had railed to the
                dignity of earl of Mar. All hiſtorians agree that this man made a moſt infamous uſe
                of his power. He obtained at laſt a liberty of coinage, which he abused ſo much as
                to endanger an inſurrection among the poor people; ſor he iſſued a baſe coin, called
                    <hi rend="italic">black money</hi> by the common people, which they resitſed to
                take in payments. This favourite’s ſkill in architecture had ſirſt introduced him to
                James; but he maintained his power by other arts: for, knowing that his maſter’s
                predominant paſſion was the love of money, he procured it by the meaneſt and moſt
                oppreſſive methods. James, however, was inclined to have relieved his people by
                calling in Cochran's money; but he was diverted from that reſolution, by conſidering
                that it would be agreeable to his old nobility. Beſides Cochran, James had other
                favourites whoſe profeſſions rendered them ſtill leſs worthy of the royal
                countenance; James Hommil a tavlor, Leonard a blackſmith, Torsifan a dancing-maſter,
                and ſome others. The favour ſhown to theſe men gave ſo much offence to the nobility,
                that, after ſome deliberation, they reſolved to remove the king, with ſome of his
                leaſt exceptionable domeſtics (but without offering any violence to his perſon) to
                the caſtle of Edinburgh; but to hang all his worthleſs favourites over
                Lawder-bridge, the common place of execution. Their deliberation was not kept so
                ſecret as not to come to the ears of the favourites; who ſuſpecting the worſt,
                wakened James before day-break, and informed him of the meeting. He ordered Cochran
                to repair to it, and to bring him an account of its proceedings @@(L). According to
                Lind-</p>
            <p>@@@(L) Lindſay’s deſcription of this upſtart’s magnificence is very particular, and
                may serve to give the reader an idea of the finery of that age. “Cochran (says he),
                the earl of Mar, came from the king to the council <pb n="793"> </pb>(which council was
                holden in the kirk of Lawder for the time), who was well accompanied with a band of
                men of war, to the number of 300 light axes, all clad in white livery, and black
                bends thereon, that they might be known for Cochran the earl of Mar’s men. Himſelf
                was clad in a riding-pie of black velvet, with a great chain of gold about his neck,
                to the value of 500 crowns; and four blowing horns, with both the ends of gold and
                ſilk, ſet with precious ſtones. His horn was tipped with fine gold at every end, and
                a precious ſtone, called a <hi rend="italic">beryl,</hi> hanging in the midſt. This
                Cochran had his heumont borne before him, overgilt with gold; ſo were all the reſt
                of his horns; and all his pallions (pavilions or tents) were of fine canvas of fill,
                and the cords thereof fine twined ſilk; and the chains upon his pallions were double
                overgilt with gold.”</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
