<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-14T17:49:23Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>1. The <hi rend="italic">arquata,</hi> or curlew, frequents our ſea-coaſts and
                marſhes in the winter time in large flocks, walking on the open ſands; feeding on
                ſhells, frogs, crabs, and other marine infects.@@ In summer they retire to the
                mountainous and unfrequented parts of the country, where they pair and breed. Their
                eggs are of a pale olive colour, marked with irregular but diſtinct ſpots of pale
                brown. Their fleſh is very rank and fiſhy, not- withſtanding an old Engliſh proverb
                in its favour. Curlews differ much in weight and ſize; ſome weighing 37 ounces,
                others not 22: the length of the largeſt to the tip of the tail, 25 inches; the
                breadth, three feet five inches; the bill is ſeven inches long: the head, neck, and
                coverts of the wings are of a pale brown; the middle of each feather, black; the
                breaſt and belly white, marked with narrow oblong black lines: the back is white,
                ſpotted with a few black ſtrokes: the quill feathers are black, but the inner webs
                ſpotted with white; the tail is white, tinged with red, and beautifully barred with
                black; the legs are long, ſtrong, and of a bluiſh grey colour; the bottoms of the
                toes flat and broad, to enable it to walk on the ſoft mud, in ſearch of food.</p>
            <p>2 The <hi rend="italic">phaeopus,</hi> or whimbrel, is much leſs frequent on our
                ſhores than the curlew; but its haunts, food, and general appearance, are much the
                ſame. It is obſerved to viſit the neighbourhood of Spalding (where it is called the
                    <hi rend="italic">curlew knot</hi>) in vaſt flocks in April, but continues there
                no longer than May; nor is it ſeen there any other time of the year: it ſeems at
                that ſeaſon to be on its paſſage to its breeding place, which Mr Pennant ſuſpects to
                be among the Highlands of Scotland. The ſpecific difference is the ſize; this never
                exceeding the weight of 12 ounces.</p>
            <p>3. The <hi rend="italic">rusticola,</hi> or woodcock, during ſummer inhabits the Alps
                of Norway, Sweden, Poliſh Pruſſia, the march of Brandenburg, and the northern parts
                of Europe: they all retire from thoſe countries the beginning of winter, as ſoon as
                the froſts commence; which force them into milder climates, where the ground is
                open, and adapted to their manner of feeding. They live on worms and inſects, which
                they ſearch for with their long bills in ſoft grounds and moiſt woods. — Woodcocks
                generally arrive here in flocks, taking advantage of the night or a miſt: they ſoon
                ſeparate; but before they return to their native haunts, pair. They feed and fly by
                night; beginning their flight in the evening, and return the ſame way or through the
                ſame glades to their day retreat. They leave England the latter end of February, or
                beginning of March; not but they have been known to continue here accidentally.
                Theſe birds appear in Scotland firſt on the eaſtern coaſts, and make their progreſs
                from eaſt to weſt. They do not arrive in Breadalbane, a central part of the kingdom,
                till the beginning or middle of November; nor the coaſts of Nether Lorn, or of
                Roſsſhire, till December or January: they are very rare in the remote Hebrides, and
                in the Orkneys. A few ſtragglers now and then arrive there. They are equally ſcarce
                in Caithneſs. Our ſpecies of woodcock is unknown in North America: but a kind is
                found that has the general appearance of it; but is ſcarce half the ſize, and wants
                the bars on the breaſt and belly. The weight of the woodcock is uſually about 12
                ounces; the length near 14 inches; and the breadth, 26; the bill is three inches
                long, duſky towards the end, reddiſh at the baſe; tongue ſlender, long, ſharp, and
                hard at the point; the eyes large, and placed near the top of the head, that they
                may not be injured when the bird thruſts its bill into the ground; from the bill to
                the eyes is a black line; the fore-head is a reddiſh aſh colour; the crown of the
                head, the hind part of the neck, the back, the coverts of the wings, and the
                ſcapulars, are prettily barred with a ferruginous red, black, and grey; but on the
                head the black predominates: the quill-feathers are duſky, indented with red marks.
                The chin is of a pale yellow; the whole under ſide of the body is of a dirty white,
                marked with numerous tranſverſe lines of a duſky colour. The tail conſiſts of 12
                feathers, duſky or black on the one web, and marked with red on the other; the tips
                above, are aſh coloured, below white; which, when ſhooting on the ground was in
                vogue, was the ſign the fowler diſcovered the birds by. The legs and toes are livid;
                the latter divided almoſt to their very origin, having only a very ſmall web between
                the middle and interior toes; as thoſe of the two ſpecies of ſnipes found in
                England.</p>
            <p>4. The <hi rend="italic">oegocephala,</hi> or godwit, weighs 12 ounces and a half;
                the length is 16 inches; the breadth 27; the bill is four inches long, turns up a
                little, black at the end, the reſt a pale purple; from the bill to the eye is a
                broad white ſtroke; the feathers of the head, neck, and back, are of a light reddiſh
                brown, marked in the middle with a duſky ſpot; the belly and vent feathers white,
                the tail regularly barred with black and white. The ſix firſt quill-feathers are
                black; their interior edges of a reddiſh brown; the legs in ſome are duſky, in
                others of a greyiſh blue, which perhaps may be owing to different ages; the exterior
                toe is connected as far as the firſt joint of the middle toe with a ſtrong ſerrated
                membrane. The male is diſtinguiſhed from the female by ſome black lines on the
                breaſt and throat; which in the female are wanting. Theſe birds are taken in the
                fens, in the ſame ſeaſon and in the ſame manner with the ruffs and reeves @@*; and
                when fattened are eſteemed a great delicacy, and ſell for half a crown or five
                ſhillings a piece. A ſtale of the ſame ſpecies is placed in the net. They appear in
                ſmall flocks on our coaſts in September, and continue with us the whole winter; they
                walk on the open ſands like the curlew, and feed on insects.</p>
            <p>5. The <hi rend="italic">glottis, </hi>or greenſhank, is in length to the end of the
                tail, 14 inches; to that of the toes, 20; its breadth, 25. The bill is two inches
                and a half long; the upper mandible black, ſtraight, and very ſlender; the lower
                reflects a little upwards; the head and upper part of the neck are aſh-coloured,
                marked with ſmall duſky lines pointing down; over each paſſes a white line; the
                coverts, the ſcapulars, and upper part of the back, are of a browniſh aſh-colour;
                the quill-feathers duſky, but the inner webs ſpeckled with white; the breaſt, belly,
                thighs, and lower part of the back, are white; the tail is white, marked with
                undulated duſky bars: the inner coverts of the wings finely croſſed with double and
                treble rows of a duſky colour. It is a bird of an elegant ſhape, and ſmall weight in
                proportion to its dimenſions, weighing only ſix ounces. The legs are very long and
                ſlender, and bare above two inches higher than the knees he exterior toe is united
                to the middle toe, as far as the ſecond joint, by a ſtrong</p>
            <p>@@@ [mu] Plate CCCCXLV.</p>
            <p>@@@ [m] *See <hi rend="italic">Tringo</hi>.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
