<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:46:53Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>grows but to a moderate height; having yellow, very pliant, ſhoots; oval, acute, ſerrated, very ſmooth leaves, with the ſerratures cartilaginous, and with callous punctures on the footſtalks. 4. The purpurea, purple, or red willow, grows to a large height, having long, reddiſh, very pliable ſhoots, and long ſpear-ſhaped, ſerrated, ſmooth leaves, the lower ones being oppoſite. 5. The viminalis, or oſier-willow, grows but a moderate height, having ſlender rod-like branches; very long, pliant, greeniſh ſhoots; and very long, narrow, ſpear- ſhaped, acute, almoſt entire leaves, hoary, and ſilky underneath. 6. The pentandria, pentandrous, broad-leaved, ſweet-ſcented willow, grows to ſome conſiderable ſtature, having browniih-green branches; oblong, broad, ſerrated, ſmooth, ſweet-ſcented leaves, ſhining above; and pentandrous flowers. 7. The triandria, or triandrous willow, grows to a large ſtature, having numerous, erect, greyiſh-green branches, and pliant ſhoots; oblong, acute-pointed, ſerrated ſmooth, ſhining- green leaves, eared at the baſe; and triandrous flowers. 8. The fragilis, fragile or crack-willow, riſes to a middling ſtature, with browniſh, very fragile, or brittle branches, long, oval lanceolate, ſawed, ſmooth leaves of a ſhining-green on both ſides, having dentated glandular foot-ſtalks. This fort in particular being exceedingly fragile, ſo that it eaſily cracks and breaks, is unfit for culture in oſier-grounds. 9. The Babylonica, Babylonian pendulous ſalix, commonly called w<hi rend="italic">eeρing willow, </hi>grows to a largiſh ſize, having numerous, long, ſlender, pendulous branches, hanging down looſely all round in a curious manner, and long, narrow, ſpear-ſhaped, ſerrated, ſmooth leaves. This curious willow is a native of the eaſt, and is retained in our hardy plantations for ornament, and exhibits a moſt agreeable variety; particularly when diſpoſed ſingly by the verges of any piece of water, or in ſpacious openings of graſs- ground.</p><p>All the ſpecies of ſalix are of the tree kind, very hardy, remarkably faſt growers, and ſeveral of them attaining a conſiderable ſtature when permitted to run up to ſtandards. They are moſtly of the aquatic tribe, being generally the moſt abundant and of moſt proſperous growth in watery ſituations: they however will grow freely almoſt anywhere, in any common foil and expoſure; but grow conſiderably the faſteſt and ſtrong- eſt in low moiſt land, particularly in marſhy ſituations, by the verges of rivers, brooks, and other waters; likewiſe along the ſides of watery ditches, &amp;c. which places often lying waſte, may be employed to good advantage, in plantations of willows, for different purpoſes.</p><p>SAILLEE, an ancient and conſiderable town of Africa in the kingdom of Fez, with a harbour and ſeveral ports. The harbour of Sallee is one of the beſt in the country; and yet, on account of a bar that lies acroſs it, ſhips of the ſmalleſt draught are forced to unload and take out their guns before they can get into it. There are docks to build ſhips; but they are hardly ever uſed, for want of ſkill and materials. It is a large place, divided into the Old and New. Towns, by the river Guero. It has long been famous for its rovers or pirates, which make prizes of all Chriſtian ſhips that come in their way, except there is a treaty to the contrary. The town of Sallee in its preſent ſtate, though large, preſents nothing worthy the obſervation of the</p><p>traveller except a oattery of 24 pieces of cannon fronting the ſea, and a redoubt at the entrance of the river, which is about a quarter of a mile broad, and penetrates ſeveral miles into the interior country. W. Long, 6. 30. N. Lat. 34. o.</p><p>SALLET, or SALLAD<hi rend="smallcaps">,</hi> a diſh of eatable herbs, ordinarily accompanying roaſt meat; compoſed chiefly of crude, ſreſh herbage, ſeaſoned with ſalt, oil, and vinegar.</p><p>Menage derives the word from the Latin <hi rend="italic">balata;</hi> of <hi rend="italic">ſal,</hi> “ſalt; ” others from <hi rend="italic">ſalcedo;</hi> Du-Cange from <hi rend="italic">ſalgama, </hi>which is uſed in Auſonius and Columella in the ſame ſenſe.</p><p>Some add muſtard, hard eggs, and ſugar; others, pepper, and other ſpices, with orange-peel, ſaffron, &amp;c.</p><p>The principal ſallet-herbs, and thoſe which ordinarily make the baſis of our Engliſh ſallets, are lettuce, celery, endive, creſſes, radiſh, and rape; along with which, by way of furniture, or additionals, are uſed purſlane, ſpenach, ſorrel, tarragon, burnet, corn-ſallet, and chervil.</p><p>The gardeners call ſome plants <hi rend="italic">ſmall herbs</hi> in ſallets; theſe ſhould always be cut while in the ſeed-leaf: as creſſes, muſtard, radiſh, turnep, ſpinach, and lettuce; all which are raiſed from ſeeds ſown in drills, or lines, from the middle of February to the end of March, under glaſſes or frames; and thence to the middle of May, upon natural beds, warmly expoſed; and during the ſummer heats in more ſhady places; and afterwards in September, as in March, &amp;c.; and laſtly, in the rigour of the winter, in hot-beds. If they chance to be frozen in very froſty weather, putting them in ſpring-water two hours before they be uſed recovers them.</p><p>SALLO (Denis de), a French writer, famous for being the projector of literary journals, was born at Paris in 1626. He ſtudied the law, and was admitted a counſellor in the parliament of Paris in 1652. It was in 1664 he ſchemed the plan of the <hi rend="italic">Journal des Sçavans;</hi> and the year following began to publiſh it under the name of Sieur de Heronville, which was that of his valet de chambre. But he played the critic ſo ſeverely, that authors, ſurpriſed at the novelty of ſuch attacks, retorted ſo powerfully, that M. de Sallo, unable to weather the ſtorm, after he had publiſhed his third Journal, declined the undertaking, and turned it over to the abbé Gallois; who, without preſuming to criticiſe, contented himſelf merely with giving titles, and making extracts. Such was the origin of literary journals, which afterwards ſprang up in other countries under different titles; and the ſucceſs of them, under judicious management, is a clear proof of their utility. M. de Sallo died in 1669.</p><p>SALLUSTIUS (Caius Criſpus), a celebrated Roman hiſtorian, was born at Amiternum, a city of Italy, in the year of Rome 669, and before Chriſt 85. His education was liberal, and he made the beſt uſe of it. His Roman Hiſtory in fix books, from the death of Sylla to the conſpiracy of Catiline, the great work from which he chiefly derived his glory among the antients, is unfortunately loſt excepting a few fragments; but his two detached pieces of Hiſtory which happily remain entire, are ſufficient to juſtify the great encomiums he has received as a writer. —He has had the ſingular honour to be twice tranſlated by a royal hand: firſt by our Elizabeth, according to Camden;</p></body></text></TEI>