<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:48:41Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ſon Bernard obtaining the dignity of duke of Saxony from the emperor Frederic I. the name of <hi rend="italic">duchy</hi> was given to this country; and the electoral dignity having been afterwards annexed to the duchy, it acquired thereby alſo the name of the <hi rend="italic">electoral circle.</hi></p><p>The country of Saxony is remarkable for being the mother of the preſent Engliſh nation; but concerning the Saxons themſelves, previous to that period, we have very few particulars. The Saxons (ſays Mr Whitaker) have been derived by our hiſtorians from very different parts of the globe; India, the north of Aſia, and the foreſts of Germany. And their appellation has been equally referred to very different cauſes; the name of their Indian progenitor, the plundering diſpoſition of their Aſiatic lathers, and the ſhort hooked weapons of their warriors. But the real origin of the Saxons, and the genuine derivation of their name, ſeem clearly to be theſe.</p><p>In the earlier period of the Gallic hiſtory, the Celtae of Gaul croſſed the Rhine in conſiderable numbers, and planted various colonies in the regions beyond it. Thus the Volcae Tectoſages ſettled on one ſide of the Hercynian foreſt and about the banks of the Neckar, the Helvetii upon another and about the Rhine and Maine, the Boii beyond both, and the Senones in the heart of Germany. Thus alſo we ſee the Treviri, the Nervii, the Suevi, and the Marcomanni, the Quadi, the Venedi, and others, in that country; all plainly betrayed to be Gallic nations by the Gallic appellations which they bear, and all together poſſeſſing the greateſt part of it. And, even as late as the concluſion of the firſt century, we find one nation on the eaſtern fide of this great continent actually ſpeaking the language of Gaul, and another upon the northern uſing a dialect nearly related to the Britiſh. But as all the various tribes of the Germans are conſidered by Strabo to be γενησιοι ΓαλαΊαι or genuine Gauls in their origin; ſo thoſe particularly that lived immediately beyond the Rhine, and are afferted by Tacitus to be indubitably native Germans, are expreſsly denominated ΓαλαΊαι, or Gauls, by Diodorus, and as expreſsly declared by Dio to have been diſtinguiſhed by the equivalent appellation of <hi rend="italic">Celtae</hi> from the earlieſt period. And the broad line of nations, which extended along the ocean, and reached to the borders of Scythia, was all known to the learned in the days of Diodorus, by the ſame ſignificant appellation of ΓαλαΊαι or Gauls.</p><p>Of theſe, the moſt noted were the Si-Cambri and Cimbri; the former being ſeated near the channel of  the Rhine, and the latter inhabiting the peninſula of Jutland. And the denominations of both declare their original; and ſhow them to have been derived from the common ſtock of the Celtae, and to be of the ſame Celtic kindred with the Cimbri of our own Somerſetſhire, and the Cymbri or Cambrians of our own Wales. The Cimbri are accordingly denominated <hi rend="italic">Celtae </hi>by Strabo and Appian. And they are equally aſſerted to be Gauls by Diodorus; to be the deſcendants of that nation which ſacked the city of Rome, plundered the temple of Delphi, and ſubdued a great part of Europe and ſome of Aſia.</p><p>Immediately to the ſouth of theſe were the Saxons, extending from the iſthmus of the Cherſoneſus to the current of the Elbe. And they were equally Cel</p><p>tic in their origin as their neighbours, They were denominated <hi rend="italic">Ambrοnes</hi> as well as Saxons; and, as ſuch, are included by Tacitus under the general appellation of <hi rend="italic">Cimbri,</hi> and comprehended in Plutarch under the equal one of <hi rend="italic">Celtο-Scythae.</hi> And the name of <hi rend="italic">Ambrones </hi>appears particularly to have been Gallic; being common to the Saxons beyond the Elbe, and the Ligurians in Ciſalpine Gaul; as both found to their ſurpriſe, on the irruption of the former into Italy with the Cimbri. And, what is equally ſurpriſing, and has been equally unnoticed by the critics, the Welſh diſtinguiſh England by the name of <hi rend="italic">Loegr</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Liguria,</hi> even to the preſent moment. In that irruption theſe Saxons, Ambrons, or Ligurians, compoſed a body of more than 30, 000 men, and were principally concerned in cutting to pieces the large armies of Manlius and Caepio. Nor is the appellation of <hi rend="italic">Saxons</hi> leſs Celtic than the other. It was originally the ſame with the Belgic Sueſſones of Gaul; the capital of that tribe being now intitled <hi rend="italic">Soiſons</hi> by the French, and the name of the Saxons pronounced <hi rend="italic">Saiſen</hi> by the Welſh, <hi rend="italic">Saſon</hi> by the Scotch, and <hi rend="italic">Saſenach</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Saxſenach</hi> by the Triſh. And the Sueſſones or Saxones of Gaul derived their own appellation from the poſition of their metropolis on a river, the ſtream at Soiſons being now denominated the <hi rend="italic">Aiſne,</hi> and formerly the <hi rend="italic">Axon;</hi> Ueſſ-on or Axon importing only waters or a river, and S-ueſſ-on or S-ax-on the waters or the river. The Sueſſones, therefore, are actually denominated the <hi rend="italic">Ueſſones by</hi> Ptolemy; and the Saxones are actually intitled the <hi rend="italic">Axones</hi> by Lucan.</p><p>Theſe, with their brethren and allies the Cimbri, having been more formidable enemies to the Romans by land, than the Samnites, Carthaginians, Spaniards, Gauls, or Parthians, in the ſecond century applied themſelves to navigation, and became nearly as terrible by ſea. They ſoon made themſelves known to the inhabitants of the Britiſh iſles by their piracies in the northern channels, and were denominated by them <hi rend="italic">Lochlyn</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Lochlynach;</hi> lucd-lyn ſignifying the people of the wave, and the D being quieſcent in the pronunciation. They took poſſeſſion of the Orkney iſlands, which were then merely large ſhoals of fand, uncovered with woods, and overgrown with ruſhes; and they landed in the north of Ireland, and ravaged the country. Before the middle of the third century they made a ſecond deſcent upon the latter, diſembarked a conſiderable body of men, and deſigned the abſolute ſubjection of the iſland. Before the concluſion of it, they carried their naval operations to the ſouth, infeſted the Britiſh channel with their little veſſels, and made frequent deſcents upon the coaſts. And in the fourth and fifth centuries, acting in conjunction with the Picts of Caledonia and the Scots of Ireland, they ravaged all the eaſtern and ſouth-eaſtern ſhores of Britain, began the formal conqueſt of the country, and finally ſettled their victorious ſoldiery in Lancaſhire.</p><p>SAY, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Saye,</hi> in commerce, a kind of ſerge much uſed abroad for linings, and by the religious for ſhirts; with us it is uſed for aprons by ſeveral forts of artificers, being uſually died green.</p><p>SCAB. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Itch</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Medicine.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Scab</hi><hi rend="italic"> in Sheep.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Sheep.</hi></p><p>SCABIOSA, <hi rend="smallcaps">Scabious,</hi> in botany: A genus of the monogynia order, belonging to the tetrandria claſs</p></body></text></TEI>