<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-14T17:50:10Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p><hi rend="italic">of</hi> war, after having ſworn never to bear arms againſt
                England.</p>
            <p>In the mean time, Baliol, by the advice of his parliament, ſolemnly and openly
                renounced his allegiance to Edward, ſending the following declaration.</p>
            <p>“To the magnificent prince, Edward, by the grace of God, king of England; John, by
                the ſame grace, king of Scotland.</p>
            <p>“Whereas you, and others of your kingdom, you not being ignorant, or having cauſe of
                ignorance, by your violent power, have notoriouſly and frequently done grievous and
                intolerable injuries, contempts, grievances, and ſtrange damages againſt us, the
                liberties of our kingdom, and againſt God and juſtice; citing us, at your pleaſure,
                upon every flight ſuggeſtion, out of our kingdom; unduly vexing us; ſeizing our
                caſtles, lands, and poſſeſſions, in your kingdom; unjuſtly, and for no fault of
                ours, taking the goods of our ſubjects, as well by ſea as land, and carrying them
                into your kingdom; killing our merchants, and others of our kingdom; carrying away
                our ſubjects and impriſoning them: For the reformation of which things, we ſent our
                meſſengers to you, which remain not only unredreſſed, but there is every day an
                addition of worſe things to them; for now you are come with a great army upon the
                borders, for the diſinheriting us, and the inhabitants of our kingdom; and,
                proceeding, have inhumanly committed ſlaughter, burnings, and violent invaſions, as
                well by ſea as land: We not being able to ſuſtain the ſaid injuries, grievances, and
                damages any longer, nor to remain in your fealty or homage, extorted by your violent
                oppreſſion, we reſtore them to you, for ourſelf, and all the inhabitants of our
                kingdom, as well for the lands we hold of you in your kingdom, as for your pretended
                government over us.”</p>
            <p>Edward was preſented with this renunciation by the hands of the intrepid Henry abbot
                of Aberbrothwick; and as it was favourable to his political views, he received it
                rather with contempt than anger. “The fooliſh traitor,” ſaid he to the abbot, “ſince
                he will not come to us, we will go to him.” The abbot had been perſuaded by his
                enemies, of whom he had many in Scotland, to preſent this letter, in hopes that
                Edward would have put him to death; but he had addrefs enough to eſcape ſafe out of
                his hands, without receiving any other anſwer.</p>
            <p>Though this ſcheme of renunciation had been concerted ſome time before, the
                declaration was not ſent to Edward till after the taking of Berwick. The fate of
                Scotland, however, after it, was ſoon decided. The Earl of March had taken part with
                Edward, but the counteſs betrayed his caſtle of Dunbar into the hands of the Scots.
                Edward ſent a choſen body of troops to recover the place. The whole force of
                Scotland oppoſed them on the heights above Dunbar; but leaving their advantageous
                poſt, and pouring down on their enemies in confuſion, they were diſperſed and
                defeated.</p>
            <p>The caſtle of Dunbar ſurrendered at diſcretion; that of Roxburgh followed the ſame
                example; the caſtle of Edinburgh ſurrendered after a ſhort ſiege; and Stirling was
                abandoned. The Scots, in the mean time, were guilty of the greateſt extravagances.
                During the ſhort interval between the loſs of Berwick and the defeat at Dunbar, an
                order was made for expelling all the Engliſh eccleſiaſtics who held benefices in
                England; all the partizans of England, and all neutrals, were declared traitors, and
                their eſtates confiſcated. But the great ſucceſſes of Edward ſoon put an end to
                theſe impotent acts of fury. Baliol was obliged to implore the mercy, of the
                conqueror. Diverted of his royal ornaments, and bearing a white rod in his hand, he
                performed a moſt humiliating penance; confeſſing, that by evil and falſe counſel,
                and through his own ſimplicity, he had grievoufly offended his liege lord. He
                recapitulated his various tranſgreſſions, in concluding an alliance with France
                while at enmity with England; in contracting his ſon with the niece of the French
                king; in renouncing his fealty; in attacking the Engliſh territories, and in
                reſisting Edward. He acknowledged the juſtice of the Engliſh invaſion and conqueſt;
                and therefore he, of his own free conſent, reſigned Scotland, its people, and their
                homage, to his liege-lord Edward, 2d July 1296.</p>
            <p>The king of England purſued his conqueſts, the barons everywhere crowding in to ſwear
                fealty to him, and renounce their allegiance with France. His journey ended at
                Elgin, from whence he returned ſouth- ward; and, as an evidence of his having made
                an abſoute conqueſt of Scotland, he carried off from Scone the wooden chair in which
                the kings were wont to be crowned. This chair had for its bottom the fatal ſtone
                regarded as the national palladium @@<hi rend="smallcaps">(d).</hi> Some of the</p>
            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">@@@(d)</hi> " This ſtone is thus deſcribed by W. Hemingford, T.
                i. p. 37. “Apud monaſterium de Scone poſitus erat lapis pergrandis in eccleſia Dei,
                juxta magnum altare, concavus quidem <hi rend="italic">ad modum rotundae cathedrae
                    confectus,</hi> in quo futuri reges loco quaſi coronationis ponebantur ex more.
                Rege itaque novo in lapide poſito, miſſarum ſolemnia incepta peraguntur, et
                praeterquam in elevatione facri dominici corporis, semper lapidatus, manſit.” And
                again, T. i. p. 100. “In redeundo per Scone, praecepit tolli et Londoniis cariari,
                    <hi rend="italic">lapidem</hi> illum, in quo, ut supra dictum eſt, Reges
                Scotorum solebant poni loco coronationis ſuae, <hi rend="italic">et hoc in signum
                    regni conquesti et resignati.”</hi> Walfingham mentions the uſe to which Edward
                put this ſtone: “Ad Weſtmonaſterium tranſtulit illum, jubens inde fieri celebrantium
                cathedram ſacerdotum.” This account of <hi rend="italic">the fatal stone</hi> is
                here tranſcribed, that it may be compared with the appearance of the ſtone that now
                bears its name at Weſtminſter.</p>
            <p>Fordun has preſerved the ancient rhymes conerning it; L. xi. c. 25.</p>
            <p>“Hic rex ſic totam Scotiam fecit ſibi notam,</p>
            <p>Qui fine menſura tulit inde jocalia plura,</p>
            <p>Et pariter lapidem, Scotorum quem fore federn</p>
            <p>Regum decrevit fatum; quod ſic inolevit,</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Ni fallat fatum, Scoti quocunque locatum</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Invenient lapidem, regnare tenentur ibidem."</hi></p>
            <pb n="747"> </pb>
            <p>This was the ſtone which Gathelus ſent from Spain with his ſon when he invaded
                Ireland, which king Fergus won in Ireland, brought oven with him, and placed at
                Scone, As the moſt proper authority for a ſtory of this nature, ſee <hi
                    rend="italic">Acts of Sir William Wallace, by Blind Hurry,</hi> B. i. c. 4.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
