<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:50:23Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>directions for the entertainment of the queen are ſtill preſerved@@‡. She was to be conveyed to the manor of Bruſtewick; to have a waiting-woman and a maid-ſervant, advanced in life, ſedate, and of good conversation; a butler, two men-ſervants, and a foot-boy for her chamber, ſober, not riotous, to make her bed: three greyhounds when ſhe inclines to hunt; veniſon, fiſh, and the faireſt houſe in the manor. In 1308, ſhe was removed to another priſon; in 1312, ſhe was removed to Windſor caſtle, 20 ſhillings per week being allowed for her maintenance. In 1314, ſhe was committed to Rocheſter caſtle, and was not ſet at liberty till the cloſe of that year.</p><p>The only fortreſs which Bruce poſſeſſed in Scotland was the caſtle of Kildrommey; and it was ſoon beſieged  by the earls of Lancaſter and Hereford. One Oſhurn treacherouſly burnt the magazine; by which means the garriſon, deſtſtute of proviſions, was obliged to ſurrender at diſcretion. The common ſoldiers were hange; Sir Neil Bruce and the earl of Athol were ſent priſoners to Edward, who cauſed them to be hanged on a gallows 50 feet high, and then beheaded and burnt. The counteſs of Buchan, who had crowned King Robert, was taken priſoner; as was Lady Mary Bruce, the king’s filter. Some hiſtorians ſay, that Edward ordered theſe two ladies to be ſhut up in wooden cages, one to be hung over the walls of the caſtle of Roxburgh, and the other over thoſe of Berwick, as public ſpectacles: but Lord Hailes only tells us, that the counteſs of Buchan was put into cloſe confinement in the caſtle of Berwick @@<hi rend="smallcaps">(f).</hi></p><p>About this time alſo many others of Bruce’s party were put to death; among whom were Thomas and Alexander Bruce, two of the king’s brothers, and John Wallace, brother to the celebrated Sir William. Bruce himſelf, in the mean time, was in ſuch a deſpicable ſituation, that it was thought he never could give more diſturbance; and it was even reported that he was dead. All his misfortunes, however, could not intimidate him, or prevent his meditating a moſt ſevere revenge upon the deſtroyers of his family. He firſt removed to the caſtle of Dumbarton, where he was hoſpitably received and entertained by Angus lord of Kintyre; but, ſuſpecting that he was not ſafe there, he failed in three days to Rachrin, a ſmall iſland on the Iriſh coaſt, where he ſecured himſelf effectually from the purſuit of his enemies. It was during his ſtay in this iſland, that the report of his death was generally propagated. Notwithſtanding this, his party increaſed conſiderably; and, even when he landed on this iſland, he was attended by 300 men. However, after having lived for ſome time in this retreat, being apprehenſive that the report of his death might be generally credited among his friends in Scotland, it was reſolved to attempt the ſurpriſe of a fort held by the Engliſh under Sir John Haſtings, on the iſle of Arran. This was performed with ſucceſs by his two friends Douglas and Sir Robert Boyd, who put the greateſt part of the garriſon to the ſword. The king, hearing of their ſuccefs, paſſed over into Arran; but, not knowing where his people reſided, is ſaid to have found them out by blowing a horn. He then ſent a truſty ſervant, one Cuthbert, into his own country of Carrick; with orders, in caſe he found it well affected</p><p><hi rend="italic">@@@‡ </hi>Faedera, <hi rend="italic">Tom. ii. p. 1013.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">@@@(f)</hi> M. Weſtminſter, p. 455. ſays, “Capitur etiam et illa impiiſſima conjuratrix de Buchan, de qua conſultus Rex, ait, Quia gladio non percuſſit, gladio non peribit; verum, propter illicitam conjurationem quam fecit, in domicilio lapideo et ferreo, in modum coronae fabricato, firmiſſime obſtruatur, et apud Bervicum ſub dio forinſecus ſuſpendatur, ut fit data, in vita et poſt mortem, ſpeculum viatoribus, et opprobrium sempiternum.” Other Engliſh hiſtorians, copying M. Weſtminſter, have ſaid the ſame thing. We cannot, therefore, blame Abercrombie for ſaying, “She was put in a wooden cage ſhaped like a crown, and in that tormenting poſture hung out from high walls or turrets to be gazed upon and reproached by the meaneſt of the multitude:” Vol. I. p. 579. Hemingford, Vol. I. p. 221. relates the ſtory in a manner ſomewhat different. He ſays, that the earl of Buchan her huſhand fought to kill her for her treaſon; but that Edward reſtrained him, and ordered her to be confined in a wooden cage. </p><p>The intentions of Edward I. touching the durance of the counteſs of Buchan, will be more certainly learned from his own orders, than from the report of M. Weſtminſter. His orders run thus: “By letters under the privy-ſeal, be it commanded, that the chamberlain of Scotland, or his deputy at Berwick upon Tweed, do, in one of the turrets of the ſaid caſtle, and in the place which he ſhall find moſt convenient, cauſe conſtruct a cage ſtrongly latticed with wood <hi rend="italic">(de fuist,</hi> i. e. beams of timber or paliſades), croſs-barred, and ſecured with iron, in which he ſhall put the counteſs of Buchan. And that he take care that ſhe be ſo well and ſafely guarded therein, that in no fort ſhe may iſſue therefrom. And that he appoint one or more women of Berwick, of Engliſh extraction, and liable to no ſuſpicion, <hi rend="italic">who ſhall minister to the ſaid counteſs in eating and drinking, and in all things else convenient, in her said lodging place.</hi> And that he do cauſe her to be ſo well and ſtrictly guarded in the cage, that ſhe may not ſpeak with any one, man or woman, of the Scottiſh nation, or with any one elſe, having with the women who ſhall be appointed to attend her, or with the guard who ſhall have the cuſtody of her perſon. And that the cage be ſo conſtructed, <hi rend="italic">that the counteſs may have therein the convenience oſ a decent chamber</hi> (eſement de chambre courtoiſe); nevertheleſs, that all things be ſo well and ſurely ordered, that no peril ariſe touching the right cuſtody of the ſaid counteſs. And that he to whom the charge of her is committed ſhall be reſponſible, body for body; and that he be allowed his charges.” <hi rend="italic">Federa</hi> T. ii. p. 1014.</p><p>Such were the orders of Edward I. and <hi rend="italic">he</hi> ſurely was not a man who would ſuffer his orders to be diſobeyed. Here, indeed, there is a detail concerning the cuſtody of a female priſoner, which may ſeem ridiculouſly minute, but which is inconſiſtent with the ſtory related by M. Weſtminſter and other hiſtorians. To thoſe who have no notion of any cage but one for a parrot or a ſquirrel, hung out at a window, we deſpair of rendering this mandate intelligible.</p></body></text></TEI>