<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-14T17:46:59Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>taken, varied ſlightly with blue and gold: the ſide-line is ſtraight: the ſcales are
                large, and the lower edges duſky, forming ſtraight rows from head to tail: the tail
                is much forked.</p>

                <p>8. The eperlanus, or ſmelt, inhabits the ſeas of the northern parts of Europe,
                    and probably never is found as far ſouth as the Mediterranean: the Seine is one
                    of the French rivers which receive it; but whether it is found ſouth of that, we
                    have not at preſent authority to fay. If we can depend on the obſervations of
                    navigators, who generally have too much to think of to attend to the minutiae of
                    natural hiſtory, theſe fiſh are taken in the Straits of Magellan, and of a moſt
                    ſurprifing ſize, ſome meaſuring 20 inches in length and 8 in circumference. They
                    inhabit the ſeas that waſh theſe iſlands the whole year, and never go very
                    remote from ſhore except when they aſcend the rivers. It is remarked in certain
                    rivers, that they appear a long time before they ſpawn, being taken in great
                    abundance in November, December, and January, in the Thames and Dee, but in
                    others not till February; and in March and April they ſpawn; after which they
                    all return to the ſalt water, and are not ſeen in the rivers till the next
                    ſeaſon. It has been obſerved that they never come into the Merſey as long as
                    there is any ſnow-water in the river. Theſe fiſh vary greatly in ſize; but the
                    largeſt we ever heard of was 13 inches long, and weighed half a pound. They have
                    a very particular ſcent, from whence is derived one of their Engliſh names, <hi
                        rend="italic">ſmelt</hi>, i. e. ſmell it. That of <hi rend="italic"
                        >sparling,</hi> which is uſed in Wales and the north of England, is taken
                    from the French <hi rend="italic">ſperlan.</hi> There is a wonderful
                    diſagreement in the opinion of people in reſpect to the ſcent of this fiſh: ſome
                    aſſert it flavours of the violet; the Germans, for a very different rea- ſon,
                    diſtinguiſh it by the elegant title of <hi rend="italic">ſtinckfiſch,
                    </hi>—Smelts are often fold in the ſtreets of London ſplit and dried. They are
                    called <hi rend="italic">dried /partings;</hi> and are recommended as a reliſh
                    to a glaſs of wine in the morning. It is a fiſh of a very beautiful form and
                    colour; the head is tranſparent, and the ſkin in general ſo thin, that with a
                    good microſcope the blood may be obſerved to circulate. The irides are ſilvery;
                    the pupil of a full black; the under jaw is the longeſt: in the front of the
                    upper jaw are four large teeth; thoſe in the ſides of both are ſmall; in the
                    roof of the mouth are two rows of teeth; on the tongue two others of large
                    teeth. The ſcales are ſmall, and readily drop off: the tail conſiſts of 19 rays,
                    and is forked. The colour of the back is whitiſh, with a caſt of green, beneath
                    which it is varied with blue, and then ſucceeds a beautiful gloſs of a ſilvery
                    hue.</p>
                <p>9. The lavaretus, or gwiniad, is an inhabitant of ſeveral of the lakes of the
                    Alpine parts of Europe. It is found in thoſe of Switzerland, Savoy, and Italy;
                    of Norway, Sweden, Lapland, and Scotland; in thoſe of Ireland, and of
                    Cumberland; and in Wales, in that of Llyntegid, near Bala, in Merionethſhire. It
                    is the ſame with the ferra of the lake of Geneva; the ſchelly of Hulſe-water;
                    the pollen of Lough Neagh; and the vangis and juvengis of Loch Mabon. In
                    Scotland there is a tradition that it was firſt introduced there by their
                    beauteous but unfortunate queen, Mary Stuart; and as in her time the Scotch
                    court was much Frenchified, it ſeems likely that the name was derived from the
                    French <hi rend="italic">vendoiſe,</hi> a “dace; ” to which a flight obſerver might be
                tempted to compare it from the whiteneſs of its ſcales. The Britiſh name <hi
                    rend="italic">gwiniad,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">whiting,</hi> was beſtowed upon
                it for the ſame reaſon. It is a gregarious fiſh, and approaches the ſhores in vaſt
                ſhoals in ſpring and in ſummer; which proves in many places a bleſſed relief to the
                poor of inland countries, in the ſame degree as the annual return of the herring is
                to thoſe who inhabit the coaſts. Between 7000 and 8000 have been taken at one
                draught. The gwiniad is a fiſh of an inſipid taſte, and muſt be eaten ſoon, for it
                will not keep long; thoſe that chooſe to preſerve them do it with falt. They die
                very ſoon after they are taken. Their ſpawning ſeaſon in Llyntegid is in December.
                The largeſt gwiniad we ever heard of weighed between three and four pounds: the head
                is ſmall, ſmooth, and of a duſky hue: the eyes very large; the pupil of a deep blue:
                the noſe blunt at the end; the jaws of equal length: the mouth ſmall and toothleſs:
                the branchioſtegous rays nine: the covers of the gills ſilvery, powdered with black.
                The back is a little arched, and ſlightly carinated: the colour, as far as the
                lateral line, is gloſſed with deep blue and purple; but towards the lines aſſumes a
                ſilvery caſt, tinged with gold; beneath which thoſe colours entirely prevail. The
                tail is very much forked: the ſcales are large, and adhere cloſe to the body.</p>
            <p>SALMON, in ichthyology. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Salmo,</hi> n⁰ 1.</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Salmon-</hi><hi rend="italic">Fiſhery.</hi> See <hi
                    rend="italic">Salmon-FISHERY.</hi></p>
            <p>SALON, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Saloon,</hi> in architecture, a lofty, ſpacious fort
                of hall, vaulted at top, and uſually comprehending two ſtories, with two ranges of
                windows.</p>
            <p>The ſalon is a grand room in the middle of a building, or at the head of a gallery,
                &amp;c. Its faces, or ſides, are all to have a ſymmetry with each other; and as it
                uſually takes up the height of two ſtories, its ceiling, Daviler obſerves, ſhould be
                with a moderate ſweep.</p>
            <p>The ſalon is a ſtate-room much uſed in the palaces in Italy; and from thence the mode
                came to us. Am- baſſadors, and other great viſitors, are uſually received in the
                ſalon.</p>
            <p>It is ſometimes built ſquare, ſometimes round or oval, ſometimes octagonal, as at
                Marly, and ſometimes in other forms.</p>
            <p>SALONA, a ſea-port town of Dalmatia, ſeated on a bay of the gulph of Venice. It was
                formerly a very conſiderable place, and its ruins ſhow that it was 10 miles in
                circumference. It is 18 miles north of Spalatto, and ſubject to Venice. @@ It is now
                a wretched village, preſerving few diſtinguiſhable remains of its ancient ſplendor.
                Doubtleſs the two laſt ages have deſtroyed all that had eſcaped the barbarity of the
                northern nations that demoliſhed it. In a valuable MS. relation of Dalmatia, written
                by the ſenator Giam- battiſta Guiſtiniani, about the middle of the 16th century,
                there is a hint of what exiſted at that time. “The nobility, grandeur, and
                magnificence of the city of Salona, may be imagined from the vaults and arches of
                the wonderful theatre, which are ſeen at this day; from the vaſt ſtones of the
                fineſt marble, which lies ſcattered on, and buried in the fields; from the beautiful
                column of three pieces of marble, which is ſtill ſtanding in the place where they
                ſay the arſenal was, towards the ſea- ſhore; and from the many arches of ſurpriſing
                beauty.</p>
            <p>@@@ [mu] <hi rend="italic">Fortis's Travels into Dalmatia</hi></p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
