<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:46:38Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>be generally condemned in the preſent day; whilſt the learning and acuteneſs of their author will be univer- ſally acknowledged and admired by all who can diſtinguiſh merit in a friend or an adverſary.</p><p>SAGENE, a Ruffian long meaſure, 500 of which make a verſt: the ſagene is equal to ſeven Engliſh feet.</p><p>SAGINA, in botany: A genus of the tetragynia order, belonging to the tetrandria claſs of plants; and in the natural method ranking under the 22d order, <hi rend="italic">Caryioρbyllei.</hi> The calyx is tetraphyllous; the petals four; the capſule is unilocular, quadrivalved, and polyſpermous.</p><p>SAGITTARIA, <hi rend="smallcaps">arrow-head</hi>: A genus of the polyandria order, belonging to the monoeciaclaſs of plants; and in the natural method ranking under the fifth order, <hi rend="italic">Tripelatoideae. </hi>The male calyx is triphyllous; the corolla tripetalous; the filaments generally about 14; the female calyx is triphyllous; the corolla tripetalous; many piſtils; and many naked feeds. There are four ſpecies, of which the moſt remarkable is the ſagittiſolia, growing naturally in many parts of England. The root is compoſed of many ſtrong fibres, which ſtrike into the mud; the footſtalks of the leaves are in length proportionable to the depth of the water in which they grow; ſo they are ſometimes almoſt a yard long: they are thick and fungous; the leaves, which float upon the water, are ſhaped like the point of an arrow, the two ears at their baſe ſpreading wide aſunder, and are very ſharp-pointed. The flowers are produced upon long ſtalks which riſe above the leaves, ſtanding in whorls round them at the joints. They conſiſt of three broad white petals, with a cluſter of ſtamina in the middle, which have purple ſummits. There is always a bulb at the lower part of the root, growing in the ſolid earth beneath the mud. This bulb conſtitutes a conſiderable part of the food of the Chineſe; and upon that account they cultivate it. Horſes, goats, and ſwine, eat it; cows are not fond of it.</p><p>SAGITTARIUS, in aſtronomy, the name of one of the 12 ſigns of the zodiac.</p><p>SAGO, a ſimple brought from the Eaſt Indies, of conſiderable uſe in diet as a reſtorative. Tt is produced from a ſpecies of palm tree <hi rend="italic">(CYCAS circnalis,</hi> L.) growing ſpontaneouſly in the Eaſt Indies without any culture. The progreſs of its vegetation in the early ſtages is very flow. At firſt it is a mere ſhrub, thick ſet with thorns, which makes it difficult to come near it; but as ſoon as its ſtem iſ once formed, it riſes in a ſhort time to the height of 30 feet, is about ſix feet in circumference, and imperceptibly loſes its thorns. Its ligneous bark is about an inch in thickneſs, and covers a multitude of long fibres; which, being interwoven one with another, envelope a maſs of a gummy kind of meal. As ſoon as this tree is ripe, a whitiſh duſt, which tranſpires through the pores of the leaves, and adheres to their extremities, proclaims its maturity. The Malais then cut them down near the root, divide them into ſeveral ſections, which they ſplit into quarters: they then ſcoop out the maſs of mealy ſubſtance, which is enveloped by and adheres to the fibres; they dilute it in pure water, and then paſs it through a ſtraining bag of fine cloth, in order to ſeparate it from the fibres. When this paſte has loſt part of its moiſture by evaporation, the Malais throw it into a kind of earthen veſſels, of different ſhapes, where they allow it to dry and hard</p><p>en. This paſte is wholeſome nouriſhing food, and preſerves for many years. The Indians eat it diluted with water, and ſometimes baked or boiled. Through a principle of humanity, they referve the fineſt part of this meal for the aged and infirm. A jelly is ſometimes made of-it, which is white and of a delicious flavour.</p><p>SAGUM, in Roman antiquity, a military habit, open from top to bottom, and uſually faſtened on the right ſhoulder with a buckle or claſp. It was not different in ſhape from the <hi rend="italic">chlamys</hi> of the Greeks and the <hi rend="italic">paludamentum</hi> of the generals. The only difference between them was, that the paludamentum was made of a richer fluff, was generally of a purple colour, and both longer and fuller than the ſagum.</p><p>SAGUNTUM, an ancient town of Spain, now called <hi rend="italic">Morvedro,</hi> where there are ſtill the ruins of a Roman amphitheatre to be ſeen. The new town is ſeated on a river called <hi rend="italic">Mοrvedro,</hi> 15 miles to the north of Valencia, in E. Long. 0. 10. N. Lat. 39. 38. It was taken by Lord Peterborough in 17c6.</p><p>SAICK, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Saique,</hi> a Turkiſh veſſel, very common in the Levant for carrying merchandize.</p><p>SAIDE, the modern name of Sidon. See SIDON.</p><p>SAIL, in navigation, an aſſemblage of ſeveral breadths of canvas ſewed together by the lifts, and edged round with cord, faſtened to the yards of a ſhip, to make it drive before the wind. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Ship.</hi></p><p>The edges of the cloths, or pieces, of which a ſail is compoſed, are generally ſewed together with a double ſeam; and the whole is ſkirted round at the edges with a cord, called the <hi rend="italic">bolt-rope.</hi></p><p>Although the form of ſails is extremely different, they are all nevertheleſs triangular or quadrilateral figures; or, in other words, their ſurfaces are contained either between three or four ſides.</p><p>The former of theſe are ſometimes ſpread by a yard, as lateen-ſails; and otherwiſe by a ſtay, as ſtay-ſails; or by a maſt, as ſhoulder of-mutton ſails; in all which caſes the foremoſt leech or edge is attached to the ſaid yard, maſt, or ſtay, throughout its whole length. The latter, or thoſe which are four-ſided, are either extended by yards, as the principal ſails of a ſhip; or by yards and booms, as the ſtudding-ſails, drivers, ringtails, and all thoſe ſails which are ſet occaſionally; or by gaffs and booms, as the main-ſails of ſloops and brigantines.</p><p>The principal ſails of a ſhip(PlateCCCCXLIV. fig. 2.) are the courſes or lower fails a; the top-ſails <hi rend="italic">b,</hi> which are next in order above the courſes; and the top-gallant ſails<hi rend="italic"> c</hi>, which are expanded above the top-ſails.</p><p>The courſes are the main-ſail, fore-ſail, and mizen, main ſtay-ſail, fore ſtay-ſail, and mizen ſtay-ſail: but more particularly the three firſt. The main-ſtay ſail is rarely uſed except in ſmall veſſels.</p><p>In all quadrangular ſails the upper edge is called the <hi rend="italic">head</hi>; the ſides or ſkirts are called <hi rend="italic">leeches</hi>; and the bottom or lower edge is termed the <hi rend="italic">foot.</hi> If the head is parallel to the foot, the two lower corners are denominated <hi rend="italic">clues,</hi> and the upper corners earings.</p><p>In all triangular ſails, and in thoſe four-ſided ſails wherein the head is not parallel to the foot, the foremoſt corner at the foot is called the <hi rend="italic">tack,</hi> and the after lower-corner the <hi rend="italic">clue</hi>; the foremoſt perpendicular or sſoping edge is called the <hi rend="italic">fore-leech,</hi> and the hindmoſt the <hi rend="italic">after-leech.</hi></p></body></text></TEI>