<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-14T17:49:04Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>from diverſity of opinions among people of the fame religion and faith.</p>
            <p>Thus we lay the <hi rend="italic">ſchiſm</hi> of the ten tribes of Judah and
                Benjamin, the schi<hi rend="italic">ſm</hi> of the Perſians from the Turks and other
                Mahometans, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Among eccleſiaſtical authors, the great ſchiſm of the Weſt is that which happened in
                the times of Clement VII. and Urban VI. which divided the church for 40 or 50 years,
                and was at length ended by the election of Martin V. at the council of
                Conſtance.</p>
            <p>The Romaniſts number 34 ſchiſms in their church. —They beſtow the name <hi
                    rend="italic">English ſchiſm</hi> on the reformation of religion in this kingdom
                Thoſe of the church of England apply the term <hi rend="italic">ſchiſm</hi> to the
                ſeparation of the nonconformiſts, viz. the preſhyterians, independents, and
                anabaptiſts, for a further reformation.</p>
            <p>SCHISTUS, in mineralogy, a name given to ſeveral different kinds of ſtones, but more
                eſpecially to ſome of the argillaceous kind; as,</p>
            <p> 1. The bluiſh purple ſchiſtus, ſchiſtus tegularis, or common roof ſlate. This is ſo
                ſoft that it may be ſlightly ſcraped with the nail, and is of a very brittle
                lamellated texture, of the ſpeciſic gravity of 2,876. It is fuſible <hi
                    rend="italic">per se</hi> in a ſtrong heat, and runs into a black ſcoria. By a
                chemical analyſis it is found to conſiſt of 26 parts of argillaceous earth, 46 of
                ſiliceous earth, 8 of magneſia, 4 of calcareous earth, and 14 of iron. The dark-blue
                ſlate, or ſchiſtus ſcriptorius, contains more magneſia and leſs iron than the common
                purple ſchiſtus, and efferveſces more briſkly with acids. Its ſpeciſic gravity is
                2,701.</p>
            <p> 2. The pyritaceous ſchiſtus is of a grey colour, brown, blue, or black; and capable
                of more or leſs decompoſition by expoſure to the air, according to the quantity of
                pyritous matter it contains and the ſtate of the iron in it. When this laſt is in a
                ſemi-phlogiſticattd ſtate it is eaſily decompoſed; but very ſlowly, or not at all,
                if the calx is much dephlogiſticated. The aluminous ſchiſtus belongs to this
                ſpecies.</p>
            <p> 3. The bituminous ſchiſtus is generally black, and of a lamellated texture, of
                various degrees of hardneſs, not giving fire with ſteel, but emitting a ſtrong ſmell
                when heated, and ſometimes without being heated. M. Magellan mentions a ſpecimen
                which burns like coal, with a ſtrong ſmell of mineral bitumen, but of a yellowiſh
                brown, or rather dark aſh-colour, found in Yorkſhire. — This kind of ſchiſtus does
                not ſhow any white mark when ſcratched like the other ſchiſtus.</p>
            <p>SCHMIEDELIA, in botany: A genus of the digynia order, belonging to the octandria
                claſs of plants. The calyx is diphyllous; the corolla tetrapetalous; the germina
                pedicellated, and longer than the flower.</p>
            <p>SCHOENOBATES (from the Greek, σχοινͼ, a <hi rend="italic">rope;</hi> and Ϧχιω<hi
                    rend="italic">, I walk),</hi> a name which the Greeks gave to their
                rope-dancers: by the Romans called <hi rend="italic">ſunambuli. </hi>See <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Rope-dancer</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Funambulus.</hi></p>
            <p>The <hi rend="italic">ſchcenobates</hi> were ſlaves whoſe maſters made money of them,
                by entertaining the people with their feats of activity. <hi rend="italic"
                    >Mercurialis de arte gymnastica, lib.</hi> III. gives us five figures of <hi
                    rend="italic">ſchcenobates</hi> engraven after ancient ſtones</p>
            <p>SCHOENUS, in botany: A genus of the monogynia order, belonging to the triandria claſs
                of plants; and in the natural method ranking under the 3d order,</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Calamarioe.</hi> The glumes are paleaceous, univalved, and
                thickſet; there is no corolla, and only one roundiſh feed between the glumes.</p>
            <p>SCHOLASTIC, ſomething belonging to the ſchools. See <hi rend="smallcaps"
                >School.</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Scholastic</hi><hi rend="italic"> Divinity,</hi> is that
                part or ſpecies of divinity which clears and diſcuſſes queſtions by reaſon and
                arguments; in which ſenſe it ſtands, in ſome meaſure, oppoſed to <hi rend="italic"
                    >poſaive divinity,</hi> which is founded on the authority of fathers, councils
                &amp;c. The ſchool- divinity is now fallen into contempt; and is ſcarce regarded
                anywhere but in ſome of the univerſities, where they are ſtill by their charters
                obliged to teach it.</p>
            <p>SCHOLIAST, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Commentator,</hi> a grammarian who writes <hi
                    rend="italic">ſcholia,</hi> that is, notes, gloſſes, &amp;c. upon ancient
                authors who have written in the learned languages. See the next article.</p>
            <p>SCHOLIUM, a note, annotation, or remark, occaſionally made on ſome paſſage,
                propoſition, or the like. This term is much uſed in geometry and other parts of
                mathematics, where, after demonſtrating a propoſition, it is cuſtomary to point out
                how it might be done ſome other way, or to give ſome advice or precaution in order
                to prevent miſtakes, or add ſome particular uſe or application thereof.</p>
            <p>SCHOMBERG (Frederick-Armand duke of), a diſtinguiſhed officer, ſprung from an
                illuſtrious family in Germany, and the ſon of count Schomberg, by an Engliſh lady,
                daughter of lord Dudley, was born in 1608. He was initiated into the military fife
                under Frederick- Henry prince of Orange, and afterwards ſerved under his ſon William
                II. of Orange, who highly eſteemed him He then repaired to the court of France,
                where his reputation was ſo well known, that he obtained the government of
                Gravelines, of Furnes, and the ſurrounding countries. He was reckoned inferior to no
                general in that kingdom except mareſchal Turenne and the prince of Condé; men of
                such exalted eminence that it was no diſgrace to acknowledge their ſuperiority. The
                French court thinking it neceſſary to diminiſh the power of Spain, lent Schomberg
                to. the aſſiſtance of the Portugueſe, who were engaged in a war with that country
                respecting the ſucceſſion to their throne. — Schomberg’s military talents gave a
                turn to the war in favour of his allies. The court of Spain was obliged to ſolicit
                for peace in 1668, and to acknowledge the houſe of Braganza as the juſt heirs to the
                throne of Portugal. For his great ſervices he was created count Mentola in Portugal;
                and a penſion of 5000<hi rend="italic">l.</hi> was beſtowed upon him, with the
                reverſion to his heirs.</p>
            <p>In 1673 he came over to England to command the army; but the Engliſh at that time
                being, diſguſted with the French nation, Schomberg was luſpected of coining over
                with a deſign to corrupt, the army, and bring it under French diſcipline. He
                therefore found it neceſſary to return to France, which he ſoon left, and went to
                the Netherlands. In the month of June 1676, he forced the prince of Orange to raiſe
                the ſiege of Maeſtricht; and it is ſaid he was then railed to the rank of marelchal
                of France. But the French <hi rend="italic">Dictionaire Historique,</hi> whole
                information on a point of this nature ought to be authentic, ſays that he was
                inveſted with this honour the ſame year in which he took the</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
