<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-14T17:50:51Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>Some authors tell us, that at the acceſſion of Robert II. his title was diſputed by
                William earl of Douglas. If any ſuch claim was preferred, an aſſembly of the States
                ſet it aſide, and it was reſolved that Robert ſhould be crowned at Scone; and to
                take away for the future all diſputes concerning the ſucceſſion, a particular act
                was framed, by which the kingdom was ſecured to Robert and his heirs.</p>
            <p>The new king being thus eſtabliſhed on the throne, endeavoured to renew the war with
                the Engliſh, in order to recover from them the town of Berwick, and ſome other
                places on the borders. In this, however, he failed; and as 56,000 pounds of David’s
                ranſom ſtill remained unpaid, Robert bound himſelf to diſcharge it at the rate of
                4000 marks every midſummer. He then propoſed an alliance with France; but the terms
                demanded by that kingdom being, that Scotland ſhould be obliged to make war with
                England whenever France ſhould require it, Robert could not by any means be induced
                to conſent to ſuch a requiſition, which would have obliged him to break through the
                most ſolemn treaties, whenever the king of France ſhould think proper to break with
                England. A new treaty,</p>
            <p>therefore, was entered into, by which it was provided, that neither Scotland nor
                France ſhould be obliged to make war with England; and by another clauſe, that the
                diſpenſation or authority even of the pope himſelf ſhould never free the kings or
                kingdoms of France and Scotland from the obligations they lay under to aſſiſt one
                another, as often as required, in oppoſition to the kingdom of England. In cafe of a
                competition for the crown of Scotland, the king of France and his heirs were to take
                care that no Engliſh influence was uſed; but that the matter being by the greateſt
                and beſt part of the nation decided conformably to the laws and eſtabliſhment of
                Scotland, he ſhould with all his power defend and aſſiſt the perſon ſo eſtabliſhed.
                Lastly, it was agreed that no Frenchman ſhould ever henceforth ſerve for wages, or
                otherwiſe, againſt Scotland, nor any Scotſman againſt France.</p>
            <p>This laſt article occasioned a recal of all the Scots from the Engliſh armies, which
                Edward looked upon to be a prelude to an invaſion. He accordingly iſſued writs for
                aſſembling all the militia in the north of England. At this time an invincible
                hatred ſubſiſted between the neighbouring people of both nations, which</p>
            <p>“According to one account, the genealogies of their families ſtand thus:</p>
            <p>Siward earl of Northumberland*.</p>
            <p>Emma= Alan earl of Brittany. Another daughters Duncan king of Scots.</p>
            <p>Chriſtina=Walter the Stewart. Malcolm III.</p>
            <p>“Thus Walter the Stewart and Malcolm III. were couſins-german.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
