<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:47:11Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>which do not afford vaſt quantities of rock or foſſil ſalt. Mines @@<hi rend="smallcaps">(a)</hi> of it have long been diſcovered and wrought in England, Spain, Italy, Germany, Hungary, Poland, and other countries of Europe. In ſeveral parts of the world, there are huge mountains which wholly conſiſt of foſſil ſalt. Of this kind are two mountains in Ruſſia, nigh Aſtracan; ſeveral in the kingdoms of Tunis and Algiers, in Africa; and ſeveral alſo in Alia; and the whole iſland of Ormus in the Perſian gulf almoſt entirely conſiſts of foſſil ſalt. The new world is like- wiſe ſtored with treaſures of this uſeful mineral, as well as with all other kinds of ſubterranean productions. Moreover, the ſea affords ſuch vaſt plenty of common ſalt, that all mankind might thence be ſupplied with quantities ſufficient for their occaſions. There are alſo innumerable ſprings, ponds, lakes, and rivers, impregnated with common ſalt, from which the inhabitants of many countries are plentifully ſupplied therewith. In ſome countries which are remote from the ſea, and have little commerce, and which are not bleſſed with mines of ſalt or ſalt-waters, the neceſſities of the inhabitants have forced them to invent a method of extracting their common ſalt from the aſhes of vegetables. The muriatic ſalt of vegetables was deſcribed by Dr Grew under the title of <hi rend="italic">lixiviated marine ſalt.</hi> Leeuwenhoek obtained cubical cryſtals of this ſalt from a lixivium of ſoda or kelp, and alſo from a ſolution of the lixivial ſalt of carduus benedictus; of which he hath given figures in a letter to the Royal Society, publiſhed in N⁰ 173. of their Tranſactions. Dr Dagner, in <hi rend="italic">Act</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Acad. N. C.</hi> vol. v. obſ. 150. takes notice of great quantities of it which he found mixed in pot- aſhes. And the ingenious Dr Fothergill extracted plenty of it from the aſhes of fern: See <hi rend="italic">Medical Eſſays,</hi> vol. V. article 13.</p><p>The muriatic ſalt which the excellent Mr Boyle extracted from ſandiver, and ſuppoſed to be produced from the materials uſed in making glaſs, was doubtleſs ſeparated from the kelp made uſe of in that proceſs. Kunckel alſo informs us, that he took an alkaline ſalt; and after calcining it with a moderate fire, diſſolved it in pure water, and placing the ſolution in a cool cellar, obtained from it many cryſtals of a neutral ſalt. He ſuppoſes, that the alkaline ſalt was by the proceſs converted into this neutral ſalt. But it is more reaſonable to believe, that the alkaline ſalt which he applied was not pure, but mixed with the muriatic ſalt of vegetables, which by this proceſs was only ſeparated from it.</p><p>It is doubtleſs chiefly this muriatic ſalt which, in ſome of the inland parts of Aſia, they extract from the aſhes of duck-weed and of Adam’s fig-tree, and uſe for their common ſalt.</p><p>That they are able in thoſe countries to make common ſalt to profit from vegetables, ought not to be wondered at, ſince in Dehli and Agra, capitals of In- doſtan, ſalt is ſo ſcarce as uſually to be ſold for half-a- crown a pound. We may therefore give ſome credit to Marco Polo, wſhen he informs us, that in the inner parts of the ſame quarter of the world, in the province</p><p>of Caindu, lying weſt of Tebeth, the natives ufed fait inſtead of money, it being firſt made up in cakes, and ſealed with the ſtamp of their prince; and that they made great profit of this money by exchanging it with the neighbouring nations for gold and muſk. We are alſo told by Ludolfus, in his <hi rend="italic">Hiſstoria Æthiopica,</hi> that in the country of the Abyſſines there are mountains of ſalt, the which when dug out is ſoft, but ſoon grows hard; and that this ſalt ſerves them inſtead of money to buy all things. The ſame is confirmed by Ramuſio.</p><p>Mr Boyle diſcovered common ſalt in human blood and urine. “I have obferved it (ſays Mr Brownrigg), not only in human urine, but alſo in that of dogs, horſes, and black cattle. It may eaſily be diſcovered in theſe, and many other liquids impregnated with it, by certain very regular and beautiful ſtarry figures which appear in their ſurfaces after congelation. Theſe figures I firſt obſerved in the great froſt in the year 1739. The dung of ſuch animals as feed upon grafs or grain, doth alſo contain plenty of common ſalt. ”</p><p>Naturaliſts, obſerving the great variety of forms under which this ſalt appears, have thought fit to rank the ſeveral kinds of it under certain general claſſes; diſtinguiſhing it, moſt uſually, into rock or foſſil ſalt, ſea-ſalt, and brine or fountain ſalt. To which claſſes, others might be added, of thoſe muriatic ſalts which are found in vegetable and animal ſubſtances. Theſe ſeveral kinds of common ſalt often differ from each other in their outward form and appearance, or in ſuch accidental properties as they derive from the heterogeneous ſubſtances with which they are mixed. But when perfectly pure, they have all the ſame qualities; ſo that chemiſts, by the exacted inquiries, have not been able to diſcover any eſſential difference between them; for which reaſon we ſhall diſtinguiſh common ſalt after a different manner, into the three following kinds, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> into rock or native ſalt, bay ſalt, and white ſalt.</p><p>By <hi rend="italic">rock ſalt,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">native ſalt,</hi> is underſtood all ſalt dug out of the earth, which hath not undergone any artificial preparation. Under the title of <hi rend="italic">bay ſalt</hi> mav be ranked all kinds of common ſalt extracted from the water wherein it is diſſolved, by means of the ſun’s heat, and the operation of the air; whether the water from which it is extracted be ſea-water, or natural brine drawn from wells and ſprings, or ſalt water ſtagnating in ponds and lakes. Under the title of white <hi rend="italic">ſalt,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">boiled ſalt,</hi> may be included all kinds of common ſalt extracted by coction from the water whrein it is diſſolved; whether this water be ſea water, or the ſalt water of wells, fountains, lakes, or rivers; or water of any ſort impregnated with rock-ſalt, or other kinds of common ſalt.</p><p>The firſt of theſe kinds of ſalt is in ſeveral countries found ſo pure, that it ſerves for moſt domeſtic uſes, without any previous preparation (triture excepted); for of all natural ſalts rock-ſalt is the moſt abundantly furniſhed by nature in various parts of the world, being found in large maſſes, occupying great tracts of land. It is generally formed in ſtrata under the ſurface of the</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">@@@ (a)</hi> Amongſt the ſalt mines of chief note are thoſe of Northwich in Cheſhire, Altemonte in Calabria, Hall in Tyrol, Cardona in Catalonia: alſo thoſe ſtupendous mines at Wilieczka of Roland, and Soowar in Upper Hungary; of which ſee accounts in Phil. Tranſ. No 61. and 413.</p></body></text></TEI>