<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:48:34Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>full of reſpect, for the word of God, which the reformers entertained of the perfection and perſpicuity of the Holy Scriptures, and the manifeſt miſinterpretation of paſſages which they bring to ſupport that idea (for that miſinterpretation is a point which can be proved). Two or three articles ſtill raiſed ſome objections in my mind againſt the Romiſh church; to wit, Tranſubſtantiation, the adoration of the ſacrament, and the infallibility of the church. The adoration of the ſacrament I conſidered as idolatry, and, on that account, removed from her communion. But ſoon after, the Expoſition of the biſhop of Meaux, a work which can never be ſufficiently admired, and his Treatiſe concerning changes, reverted all my opinions, and rendered me an enemy to the Reformation.” It is ſaid alſo, that Saurin appealed his conſcience by reading Poiret’s <hi rend="italic">Cogitationes rationales.</hi> This book is written with a view to vindicate the church of Rome from the charge of idolatry.</p><p>If it was the love of diſtinction that induced Saurin to return to the Romiſh church, he was not diſappointed; for he there met with protection and ſupport. He was favourably received by Louis XIV. obtained a penſion from him, and was treated by the Academy of Sciences with the moſt flattering reſpect. At that time (1717), geometry formed his principal occupation. He adorned the <hi rend="italic">Journal des Savons</hi> with many excellent treatiſes; and he added to the memoirs of the Academy many intereſting papers. There are the only works which he has left behind him. He died at Paris on the 29th December 1737, in his 78th year, of a fever. He married a wife of the family of Crouſas in Switzerland, who bore him a ſon, Bernard-Jofeph, diſtinguiſhed as a writer for the theatre.</p><p>Saurin was of a bold and impetuous ſpirit. He had that lofty deportment which is generally miſtaken for pride. His philoſophy was auſtere; his opinions of men were not very favourable; and he often delivered them in their pretence: this created him many enemies. His memory was attacked after his deceaſe. A letter was printed in the <hi rend="italic">Mercure Suiſſe,</hi> ſaid to be written by Saurin from Paris, in which he acknowledges that he had committed ſeveral crimes which deſerved death. Some Calviniſt miniſters publiſhed in 1757 two or three pamphlets to prove the authenticity of that letter; but Voltaire made diligent enquiry not only at the place wſhere Saurin had been diſcharging the ſacerdotal office, but at the Deans of the clergy of that department. They all exclaimed againſt an imputation ſo opprobrious. It muſt not, however, be concealed, that Voltaire, in the defence which he has publiſhed in his general hiſtory of Saurin’s conduct, leaves ſome unfavourable impreſſions upon the reader’s mind. He inſinuates, that Saurin ſacrificed his religion to his intereſt; that he played upon Boſſuet, who believed he had converted a clergyman, when he had only given a little fortune to a philoſopher.</p><p>SAURURUS, in botany: A genus of the tetragynia order, belonging to the heptandria claſs of plants; and in the natural method ranking under the ſecond order, <hi rend="italic">Piperitae.</hi> The calyx is a catkin, with uniflorous ſcales: there is no corolla; there are four germina, and four monoſpermous berries.</p><p>SAUVAGESIA, in botany: A genus of the monogynia order, belonging to the pentandria claſs of plants; and in the natural method ranking with thoſe</p><p>of which the order is doubtful. The corolla is pentapetalous and fringed; the calyx pentaphyllous; the nectarium the ſame, having its leaves placed alternately with the petals; the capſule unilocular.</p><p>SAUVEUR (Joſeph), an eminent French mathematician, born at La Fleche in 1653. He was abfolutely dumb until he was ſeven years of age; and even then his organs of ſpeech did not diſengage themſelves  ſo freely, but that he was ever after obliged to ſpeak with great deliberation. Mathematics were the only ſtudies he had any reliſh for, and theſe he cultivated with extraordinary ſucceſs; ſo that he commenced teacher at 20 years of age, and was ſo ſoon in vogue, that he had prince Eugene for his ſcholar. He was made mathematical profeſſor in the royal college in 1686; and ten years after was admitted a member of the Academy of Sciences. He died in 1716; and his writings, which conſiſt rather of detached papers than of connected treatiſes, are all inſerted in the Memoirs of the Academy of Sciences. He was twice married; and by the laſt wife had a ſon, who, like himſelf, was dumb for the firſt ſeven years of his life.</p><p>SAW, an inſtrument which ſerves to cut into pieces  ſeveral ſolid matters; as wood, ſtone, ivory, &amp;c.</p><p>The beſt ſaws are of tempered ſteel ground bright and ſmooth: thoſe of iron are only hammer-hardened: hence the firſt, beſides their being ſtiffer, are likewiſe found ſmoother than the laſt. They are known to be well hammered by the ſtiff bending of the blade; and to be well and evenly ground, by their bending equally in a bow.</p><p><hi rend="italic">SAW-fish.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Pristis.</hi></p><p>SAXE (Maurice count of), was born the 13th October 1696. He was the natural ſon of Frederic Auguſtus II. elector of Saxony, and king of Poland, and of the counteſs of Konigſmarc, a Swediſh lady, celebrated both for her wit and beauty. He was educated along with Frederic Auguſtus the electoral prince, afterwards king of Poland. His infancy announced the future warrior. Nothing could prevail on him to apply to his ſtudies but the promiſe of being allowed, after he had finiſhed his taſk, to mount on horſeback, or exercite himſelf with arms.</p><p>He ſerved his firſt campaign in the army commanded by prince Eugene and the duke of Marlborough, when only twelve years old. He ſignalized himſelf at the ſieges of Tournay and Mons, and particularly at the battle of Malplaquet. In the evening of that memorable day, he was heard to fay, "I’m content with my day’s work.” During the campaign of 1710, prince Eugene and the duke of Marlborough made many public encomiums on his merit. Next year the young count accompanied the king of Poland to the ſiege of Stralſund, the ſtrongeſt place in Pomerania, and diſplayed the greateſt intrepidity. He ſwam acroſs the river in fight of the enemy, with a piſtol in his hand. His valour ſhone no leſs conſpicuouſly on the bloody day of Gaedelbuſck, where he commanded a regiment of cavalry. He had a horſe killed under him, after he had three times rallied his regiment, and led them on to the charge.</p><p>Soon after that campaign, his mother prevailed on him to marry the counteſs of Lubin, a lady both rich and beautiful. This union laſted but a ſhort time. In 1721, the count procured a diſſolution of the marriage;</p></body></text></TEI>