<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:49:11Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ways deſtroying the roots, and for want of ſalt-water they do not thrive in ſummer. Sometimes the roots which are bought for uſe put forth their stems and produce flowers, as they lie in the druggiſts ſhops. — This root is very nauſeous to the taſte, intenſely bitter, and ſo acrimonious, that it ulcerates the ſkin if much handled. Taken internally, it powerfully ſtimulates the ſolids, and promotes urine, ſweat, and expectoration. If the doſe is conſiderable, it proves emetic, and ſometimes purgative. The principal uſe of this medicine is where the primae viae abound with mucous matter, and the lungs are oppreſſed by tenacious phlegm. It has been recommended in hydropic caſts, taken in powder, from four to ten grains in a dole, mixed with a double quantity of nitre. The moſt commodious mode of exhibiting this root is as a bolus or pill. Liquid forms are too diſagreeable to moſt people; though this may be remedied in ſome degree by the addition of ſome aromatic diſtiſted waters. It yields the whole of its virtues to aqueous and vinous menſtrua, and likewiſe to vegetable acids.</p><p>SCILLY, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Sillev,</hi> a cluſter of ſmall iſlands and rocks, ſituated in the Atlantic Ocean, in W. Long 7⁰. N. Lat. 50⁰.</p><p>Theſe iſlands were firſt called <hi rend="italic">Caſſiterides,</hi> or the <hi rend="italic">Tin Isles,</hi> from their being rich in that metal. The common opinion is, that this is a Greek appellation; which in the moſt obvious ſenſe is true: But as the Phoenicians were familiar with the metal, and with the country that produced it, before the Greeks knew any thing of either, it is very likely they introduced the names of both from their own language. Strabo  ſays theſe iſlands were ten in number, lying cloſe together, of which only one was uninhabited: the people led an erratic life, lived upon the produce of their cattle, wore an under garment which reached down to their ankles, and over that another, both of the ſame colour, which was black, girt round a little below the breaſt with a girdle, and walked with ſtaves in their hands. The riches of theſe iſlands were tin and lead, which, with thc ſkins of their cattle, they exchanged with foreign merchants, that is, the Phoenicians from Cadiz, for earthen-ware, ſalt, and utenſils made of  braſs. An author of as great or greater antiquity, ſeems to include a part at leaſt of Cornwall amongſt  theſe iſlands; or rather he ſuggeſts, that they were not perfect iſlands except at full ſea, but that at ebb the inhabitants paſſed from one to another upon the sands, and that they even tranſported their tin in large ſquare blocks upon carriages from one iſland to another. He farther takes notice, that such as inhabited about Belerium (the Land’s End) were in their converſation with ſtrangers remarkably civil and courteous. Other ancient writers ſtyle theſe iſlands <hi rend="italic">Hesperides,</hi> from their weſtern ſituation, and <hi rend="italic">Oestrymnides,</hi> aſſerting that the land was extremely fertile, as well as full of mines; and that the people, though very brave, were entirely addicted to commerce, and boldly paſſed the ſeas in their leather boats.</p><p>The Romans were exceedingly deſirous of having a ſhare in this commerce, which the Phoenicians as carefully laboured to prevent, by concealing their navigation to theſe iſlands as much as it was in their power. At length, however, the Romans prevailed; and Publius Craſſus coming thither, was ſo well pleaſed with the</p><p>induſtry and manners of the people, that he taught them various improvements, as well in working their mines, which till that time were but ſhallow, as in carrying their own merehandiſe to different markets. There is no room to doubt that they followed the fate of the reſt of Britain, and particularly of Cornwall, in becoming ſubject to the Roman empire. We find them called in the Itinerary of Antoninus, <hi rend="italic">Sigdeles;</hi> bv Sulpitius, Sillenae<hi rend="italic">;</hi> and by Solinus they are termed- <hi rend="italic">Silures.</hi> All we know of them during this period is, that their tin trade continued, and that ſometimes ſtate- priſoners were exiled, or, to uſe the Roman phraſe, relegated hither as well as to other iſlands.</p><p>When the legions were withdrawn, and Britain with its dependencies left in the power of the natives, there  is no reaſon to queſtion that theſe iſlands ſhared the  ſame lot with the reſt. As to the appellation which from this period prevailed, the ordinary way of writing it is <hi rend="italic">Sally;</hi> in records we commonly ſind it ſpelt <hi rend="italic">Silly, Silley,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Sulley;</hi> but we are told the old Britiſh appellation was <hi rend="italic">Sulleb,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Sylleb,</hi> which ſignifies rocks conſecrated to the ſun. We have not the leaſt notice of any thing that regards them from the fifth to the tenth century. It is, however, with much appearance of truth conjectured, that ſome time within, this ſpace they were in a great meaſure deſtroyed by an earthquake, attended with a ſinking of the earth, by which moſt of their lowlands, and of courſe the greateſt part of their improvements, were covered by the ſea, and thoſe rich mines of tin which had rendered them ſo famous ſwallowed up in the deep. They have a tradition in Cornwall, that a very externſive tract of country called the <hi rend="italic">Lione</hi>ſs<hi rend="italic">,</hi> in the old Corniſh <hi rend="italic">Lethousow,</hi> ſuppoſed to lie between that country and Scilly, was loſt in that manner; and there are many concurrent circumſtances which render this probable. In reference to theſe iſlands, the caſe is ſtill ſtronger; for at low ebbs their ſtone-incloſures are ſtill viſible from almoſt all the iſles, and thereby afford an ocular demonſtration that they were formerly of far greater extent, and that in remoter ages their inhabitants muſt have been very numerous, and at the ſame time very induſtrious. This ſufficiently proves the fact, that by ſuch an earthquake they were deſtroyed; and that it happened at ſome period of time within thoſe limits that have been aſſigned, appears from our hearing nothing more of their tin trade, and from our having no notice of it at all in any of our ancient chronicles, which, if it had fallen out later, from their known attention to extraordinary events, muſt certainly have happened.</p><p>It is generally ſuppoſed, and with great appearance of truth, that king Athelitan, after having overcome a very powerful confederacy formed againſt him, and having reduced Exeter, and driven the Britons beyond the river Tamar, which he made the boundary of their Corniſh dominions, paſſed over into theſe iſlands, (then ſurely in a better ſtate than now, or they would not have been objects of his vengeance), and reduced them likewiſe. Hiltory does not inform us, that the Danes ever fixed themſelves in theſe illands; but as their method of fortifying is very well known, it has been conjectured that the Giant’s Caſtle in the iſle of St Mary was erected by them; and indeed, if we conſider the convenient ſituation of theſe iſlands, and the</p></body></text></TEI>