<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:46:50Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>cent, and well adapted to reſiſt the diſſolution of the craſis of the blood, which is ſo evident in theſe caſes. And by the ſame mucilaginous quality, it is equally efficacious in the ſtrangury and dyſury; especially in the latter, when ariſing from a venereal cauſe, becauſe the diſcharge of urine is then attended with the moſt exquiſite pain, from the ulceration about the neck of the bladder and through the courſe of the urethra. I have found it alſo an uſeful aliment for patients who labour under the ſtone or gravel. ” The ancient chemiſts appear to have entertained a very high opinion of the orchis root, as appears from the <hi rend="italic">ſecreta ſecretorum</hi> of Raymund Lully, a work dated 1765.</p><p>SALERNO, an ancient and conſiderable town of Italy, in the kingdom of Naples, and capital of the Hither Principato, with an archbiſhop’s fee, a caſtle, harbour, and an univerſity- chiefly for medicine. It is  ſeated at the bottom of a bay of the ſame name. E. Long. 14. 43. N. Lat. 40. 45<hi rend="italic">.</hi></p><p>SALET, in war, a light covering or armour for the head, anciently worn by the light-horſe, only different from the caſque in that it had no creſt and was little more than a bare cap.</p><p>SALIANT, in fortification, denotes projecting. There are two kinds of angles, the one ſaliant, which have their point outwards; the other re-entering, which have their points inwards.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Saliant, Salient,</hi> or <hi rend="smallcaps">Saillant,</hi> in heraldry, is applied to a lion, or other beaſt, when its fore-legs are raiſed in a leaping poſture.</p><p>SALIC, or <hi rend="smallcaps">salique, Law, </hi><hi rend="italic">(Lex Salica),</hi> an ancient and fundamental law of the kingdom of France, uſually ſuppoſed to have been made by Pharamond, or at leaſt by Clovis; in virtue whereof males only are to inherit.</p><p>Some, as Poſtellus, would have it to have been called <hi rend="italic">Salic,</hi> q. d. <hi rend="italic">Gallic,</hi> becauſe peculiar to the Gauls. Fer Montanus inſiſts, it was becauſe Pharamond was at firſt called <hi rend="italic">Salrcus.</hi> Others will have it to be ſo named, as having been made for the ſalic lands. Theſe were noble fiefs which their firſt kings uſed to beſtow on the ſallians, that is, the great lords of their falle or court, without any other tenure than military ſervice; and for this reaſon, ſuch fieſs were not to deſcend to women, as being by nature unfit for ſuch a tenure. Some, again, derive the origin of this word from the Salians, a tribe of Franks that ſettled in Gaul in the reign of Julian, who is ſaid to have given them lands on condition or their perſonal ſervice in war. He even paſſed the conditions into a law, which the new conquerors acquieſced in, and called it <hi rend="italic">ſalic,</hi> from the name of their former countrymen.</p><p>SALICORNIA, <hi rend="smallcaps">jointed glass-wort,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Saltwort</hi>: A genus of the monogynia order, belonging to the monandria claſs of plants; and in the natural method ranking under the 12th order, <hi rend="italic">Holoraceae.</hi> The calyx is ventricoſe, or a little ſwelling out and entire; there are no petals, and but one ſeed. There are four ſpecies, of which the rtroſt remarkable are, I. The fruticoſa, with obtuſe points, grows plentifully in moſt of the ſalt marſhes which are overflowed by the tides in many parts of England. It is an annual plant, with thick, ſucculent, jointed ſtalks, which trail upon the ground. The flowers are produced at the ends of the joints toward the extremity of the branches, which are ſmall, and ſcarce diſcernible by the naked eye. 2. The</p><p>perennis, with a ſhrubby branching ſtalk, grows naturally in Sheppey iſland. This hath a ſhrubby branching ſtalk about ſix inches long 5 the points of the articulations are acute; the ſtalks branch from the bottom, and form a kind of pyramid. They are perennial, and produce their flowers in the ſame manner as the former.</p><p>The inhabitants near the ſea-coaſts where theſe plants grow, cut them up toward the latter end of ſummer, when they are fully grown; and, after having dried them in the fun, they burn them for their aſhes, which are uſed in making of glaſs and ſoap. Theſe herbs are by the country people called <hi rend="italic">kelp,</hi> and promiſcuouſly gathered for uſe. See the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Salsola;</hi> alſo <hi rend="italic">Dyeing of LEATHER,</hi> p. 750, note A.</p><p>SALII, in Roman antiquity, prieſts of Mars, whereof there were 12, inſtituted by Numa, wearing painted, particoloured garments, and high bonnets; with a ſteel cuiraſſe on the breaſt. They were called <hi rend="italic">falii</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">, </hi>from <hi rend="italic">ſaltare</hi> “to dance;” becauſe, after aſſiſting at ſacrifices, they went dancing about the ſtreetε, with bucklers in their left-hand, and a rod in their right, ſtriking muſically with their rods on one another’s bucklers, and ſinging hymns in honour of the gods.</p><p>SALINO, one of the Lipari iſlanda, ſituated between Sicily and Italy, conſiſts of two mountains both in an high ſtate of cultivation. The one lying more towards the north than the other is rather the higheſt of the two, and is called <hi rend="italic">del Capo,</hi> “the head.” The other is called <hi rend="italic">della Foſſa felice,</hi> or “the happy valley.” One third of the extent of theſe hills from the bottom to the ſummit is one continued orchard, conſiſting of vines, olive, fig, plum, apricot, and a vaſt diverſity of other trees. The white roofs of the houſes, which are everywhere interſperſed amid this diverſity of verdure and foliage, contribute to variegate the proſpect in a very agreeable manner. The back part of almoſt all the houſes is ſhaded by an arbour of vines, ſupported, by pillars of brick, with croſs poles to ſuſtain the branches and foliage of the vines. Thoſe arbours ſhelter the houſes from the rays of the ſun, the heat of which is quite ſcorching in theſe ſouthern regions. The vines are extremely fruitful; the poles bending under the weight of the grapes.</p><p>The ſcenes in this iſland are more intereſting to the lover of natural hiſtory than to the antiquarian. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Reticulum.</hi></p><p>On the ſouth fide of the iſland, however, there are ſtill to be ſeen ſome fine ruins of an ancient bath, a Roman work. They conſiſt of a wall 10 or 11 fathoms in extent, and terminating in an arch of no great height, of which only a ſmall part now remains. The building ſeems to have been reduced to its preſent ſtate rather by the ravages of men than the injuries of time. Almoſt all the houſes in the iſland are built of materials which have belonged to ancient monuments. The ancients had, in all probability, baths of freſh as well as of ſalt water in this iſland; for whenever the preſent inhabitants have occaſion for a ſpring of freſh water, they have only to dig a pit on the  ſhore, and pure ſweet water flows in great abundance.</p><p>There were formerly mines of alum here, from which the inhabitants drew a very conſiderable yearly revenue. But whether they are exhauſted, or whatever circumſtance may have cauſed them to be given up, they are</p></body></text></TEI>