<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:50:34Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Crab, a Flemliſh engineer in the Scots ſervice. This was a kind of moveable crane, whereby great ſtones might be raiſed on high, and then let fall upon the enemy. The Engliſh made a general aſſault on the quarter towards the ſea, as well as on the land ſide; ſo that the garriſon, exhauſted by continual fatigue, could ſcarce maintain their poſts. The great engine moved on to the walls; and, though ſtones were inceſſantly diſcharged againſt it from the crane, their effect was ſo ſmall, that all hope of preſerving Berwick was lost. At length a huge ſtone ſtruck it with ſuch force, that the beams gave way, and the Scots pouring down combuſtibles upon it, it was reduced to aſhes. The Engliſh, however, ſtill continued the attack. The Steward, with a reſerve of 100 men, went from poſt to poſt, relieving thoſe who were wounded or unfit for combat. One ſoldier of the reſerve only remained with him when an alarm was given that the Engliſh had burnt a barrier at the port called <hi rend="italic">St Mary's,</hi> poſſeſſed themſelves of the draw-bridge, and fired the gate. The Steward haſtened thither, called down the guard from the rampart, ordered the gate to be ſet open, and ruſhed out upon the enemy. A deſperate combat enſued, and continued till the cloſe of the day, when the Engliſh commanders withdrew their troops.</p><p>Notwithſtanding this brave defence, it was evident that the town could not hold out long without a ſpeedy relief; and Robert could not, with any probability of fucceſs, attack the fortified camp of the Engliſh. He therefore determined to make a powerful diverſion in England, in order to oblige Edward to abandon the undertaking. By order of the king, 15,000 men entered England by the weſtern marches. They had concerted a plan for carrying off the queen of England from her <hi rend="italic">reſidence</hi> near York; but being diſappointed in this attempt, they laid waſte Yorkſhire. The arch- biſhop of York haſtily collected a numerous body of commons and eccleſiaſtics, with whom he encountered the Scots at Mitton, near Borough-bridge, in the north- riding of Yorkſhire. The Engliſh were inſtantly routed; 3000 were left dead on the field, and great part of thoſe who fled periſhed in the river Swale. In this action 300 eccleſiaſtics loſt their lives. The news of this ſucceſsful inroad alarmed the beſiegers of Berwick. The barons whoſe eſtates lay to the ſouthward remote from the Scottiſh depredations were eager for continuing the ſiege. But they were oppoſed by thoſe of the north; who were no leſs eager to abandon the enterpriſe, and return to the defence of their own country. With them the earl of Lancaſter concurred in opinion; who, underſtanding that his favourite manor of Pontefract was expoſed to the ravages of the Scots, departed with all his adherents. Edward, upon this, drew off the remainder of his army, and attempted to intercept Randolph and Douglas; but they eluded him, and returned, in ſafety to Scotland.</p><p>The unſucceſsſul event of this laſt attempt induced Edward ſerioufly to think of peace; and accordingly a truce between the two nations was concluded on the 21ſt of December 1319; which interval of tranquillity the Scots made uſe of in addreſſing a manifeſto to the pope in juſtification of their cauſe. This was drawn up in a ſpirited manner, and made a very conſiderable alteration in the councils of Rome. The pope, foreſeeing that Robert would not he terrified into ſubmiſſions, ordered Edward to make peace with him in the beſt manner he could. A negociation was accordingly ſet on foot, which ſoon terminated ineffectually; the truce was not renewed, and in 1322 a mutual invaſion took place. The Scots penetrated into Lancaſhire by the weſtern marches; and, after plundering the country, returned home with an extraordinary booty; while Edward made great preparations for an expedition into Scotland, which took place in Auguſt the ſame year. In this, however, he was not attended with ſucceſs. Robert had cauſed all the cattle to be driven off, and all the effects of any value to be removed from Lothian and the Merſe; fixing his camp at Culroſs, on the north ſide of the frith of Forth. His orders for removing the cattle were ſo punctually obeyed, that, according to common tradition, the only prey which fell into the hands of the Engliſh was a lame bull at Tranent in Eaſt Lothian. Edward, however, ſtill proceeded, and penetrated as far as Edinburgh, but without any hopes of ſubduing the kingdom. His proviſions being conſumed, many of his ſoldiers periſhed for want; and he was obliged at laſt to retire without having ſeen an enemy. On their return, his ſoldiers burnt the abbeys of Holyrood, Melroſs, Dryburgh, &amp;c. killed many of the monks, and committed other ſacrileges: but when they returned to their own country, and began again to enjoy a plentiful living, they indulged themſelves in ſuch exceſſes as were productive of mortal diſeaſes; inſomuch that, according to an Engliſh hiſtorian, almoſt one half of the great army which Edward had brought from England with him were deſtroyed either by hunger or gluttony.</p><p>No ſooner were the Engliſh retired than they were purſued by the Scots, who laid ſiege to the caſtle of Norham. Edward lay at the abbey of Biland in Yorkſhire, with a body of troops advantageouſly polled in the neighbourhood. The Scots, invited, as is ſaid, by ſome traitors about the king’s perſon, attempted to ſurpriſe him; and it was with the utmoſt difficulty that he made his eſcape to York, abandoning all his baggage and treaſure to the enemy. The Engliſh camp was ſuppoſed to be acceſſible only by a narrow paſs, but Douglas undertook to force it, and Randolph preſented himſelf as a volunteer in this dangerous ſervice under bis friend Douglas. The Highlanders and men of the Iſles climbed the precipice on which the Engliſh camp flood, and the enemy were driven out with great loſs. The Scots purſued them to the very gates of York, waſted the country without controul, and returned home unmoleſted.</p><p>Edward, diſheartened by repeated Ioffes, agreed to ceſſation of arms “with the men of Scotland who were engaged in war with him.” But the king of Scotland would not conſent to it in that form; however, he gave his conſent, on the proper form being employed, to which Edward now made no objection. This treaty was concluded on the 30th of March 1323, and was to endure until the 12th of June 1336. It was agreed, that, during the continuance of it, no new fortreſſes ſhould be erected in Cumberland, to the north of the Tyne, or in the counties of Berwick, Roxburgh, or Dumfries; and by a very ſingular article it was provided, that “Bruce and the people of Scotland might procure abſolution from the pope; but in caſe there was no peace concluded before the expiration of the</p></body></text></TEI>