<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:51:02Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>days, the 29th of March 1405, after having reigned near 15 years.</p><p>By the death of Robert, and the captivity of the prince, all the power devolved upon the duke of Albany, who was appointed regent by a convention of the ſtates aſſembled at Scone. The allegiance of the people, however, to their captive prince could not be ſhaken; ſo that the regent was obliged to raiſe an army for the purpoſe of reſcuing him. Henry ſummoned all his military tenants, and made great preparations: but, having agreed to treat of a final peace with Ireland and the lord of the Iſles, the regent laid hold oſ this as a pretence for entering into a new negociation with the Engliſh monarch; and a truce was concluded for a year, during which time all differences were to be ſettled. In conſequence of this agreement, Rotheſay, king at arms, was appointed comrniſſary-general for the king and kingdom of Scotland; and in that quality repaired to the court of England. At the time when the prince of Scotland was taken, it ſeems that there had been a truce, however ill obſerved on both ſides, ſubſiſting between the two nations. Rotheſay produced the record of this truce, which provided that the Scots ſhould have a free navigation; and in conſequence of this, he demanded juſtice of the captain and crew of the privateer who had taken the prince. Henry ordered the matter to be inquired into: but the English brought their complaints as well as the Scots; and the claims of both were ſo intricate, that the examination fell to the ground, but at the ſame time the truce was prolonged.</p><p>In the end of the year 1409, or the beginning of 1410, the war was renewed with England, and Flenry prepared to ſtrike a fatal blow which he had long meditated againſt Scotland. He had, as we have ſeen, entered into a league with the lord of the Iſles, where a conſiderable revolution then happened. Walter Leſley had ſucceeded to the eſtate and honours of the earl of Roſs, in right of his wife, who was the heir. By that marriage, he had a ſon named <hi rend="italic">Alexander,</hi> who ſucceeded him; and a daughter, Margaret, who was married to the lord of the Iſles. This Alexander had married one of the regent’s daughters; and dying young, he left behind him an only daughter, Euphane, who was deformed, and become a nun at North Berwick. Her grandfather, the regent, procured from her a reſignation of the earldom of Roſs, to which ſhe was undoubted heir, in favour oſ John earl oſ Buchan, but in prejudice of Donald lord of the Iſles, who was the ſon of Margaret, ſifter to the earl Alexander, and conſequently the neareſt heir to the eſtate after the nun. Donald applied for redreſs; but his ſuit being rejected, he, with his brother John, fled into England, where he was moſt graciouſly received by king Henry. According to the inſtructions given him by the Engliſh monarch, Donald returned to his own dominions in the Iſles, where he raiſed an army, and paſſing over into Roſsſhire, violently ſeized on the eſtate in diſpute. In a ſhort time he found himſelf at the head of 10,000 Highlanders; with whom he marched into the province of Moray, and from thence to Strathbogie and Garioch, which he laid under contribution. Advancing towards Aberdeen, with a view to pay his troops with the plunder of that city, which was then a place of conſiderable trade, he was met by the earl of Marr, whom the re</p><p>gent had employed to command againſt him, at a village called <hi rend="italic">Harlaw,</hi> in the neighbourhood of Aberdeen. A fierce engagement enſued, in which great numbers were killed on both ſides, and the victory remained uncertain: but Donald, finding himſelf in the midſt oſ an enemy’s country, where he could raiſe no recruits, began to retreat next day; and the ſhattered ſtate of the royal army preventing him from being purſued, he eſcaped to his own dominions, where in a ſhort time he ſubmitted, and ſwore allegiance to the crown of Scotland.</p><p>In the mean time, Henry continued the war with Scotland, and refuſed to renew the truce, though frequently ſolicited by the Scots. He had now, however, ſuſtained a great loſs by the defection of the earl of March, who had gone over to the Scots, though the hiſtorians have not informed us of his quarrel with the Engliſh monarch. On his return to Scotland, he had been fully reconciled to the Douglas family, and now ſtrove to diſtinguiſh himſelf in the cauſe of his country. This, with the countenance which was ſhown the Scots by the court of France, a bull publiſhed by the pope in their favour, and the vigorous behaviour of the regent himſelf, contributed to reduce Henry to reaſon; and we hear of no more hoſtilities between the two nations till after the death of the Engliſh monarch, which happened in the year 1413.</p><p>In 1415, the truce being either broken or expired, the Scots made great preparations for beſieging Berwick. The undertaking, however, came to nothing; all that was done during the campaign being the burning of Penrith by the Scots, and of Dumfries by the Engliſh. Next year a truce was agreed upon, and a treaty entered into for the ranſom of King James; which was ſo far advanced, that the Engliſh king agreed to his viſiting Scotland, provided he engaged to forfeit 100,000 pounds Sterling in caſe of his failure to return by a certain day. For reaſons now unknown, this, treaty was broken off, and vaſt preparations were made for a new invaſion of Scotland; which, however, was executed with ſo little fucceſs, that it became known among the common people of Scotland by the name of the <hi rend="italic">ſule raid,</hi> or the fooliſh expedition.</p><p>In 1420, died Robert duke of Albany, regent of Scotland, at the age of 80; and ſuch was the veneration which the Scots had for his memory, that his poſt of regent was conferred upon his eldeſt ſon Murdoch, though a perſon no way qualified for that ſtation.— The war with England was now diſcontinued; but in France Henry met with the greateſt oppoſition from the Scots auxiliaries, inſomuch, that at laſt he proclaimed all the Scots in the ſervice of the Dauphin to be rebels againſt their lawful ſovereign, and threatened to treat them as ſuch wherever he found them. It was not long before he had an opportunity of putting this menace in execution; for the town and caſtle of Melun being obliged through famine to capitulate, one of the articles of capitulation was, that all the Engliſh and Scots in the place ſhould be reſigned to the abſolute diſpoſal of the king of England; and, in conſequence of his reſolution above-mentioned, cauſed twenty Scots ſoldiers who were found in the place to be hanged as traitors. In 1421, Henry returned to England, and with him James the Scots king. On his</p></body></text></TEI>