<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:50:45Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>he had taken the place, and put the garriſon to the ſword; however, his utmoſt efforts were at laſt baffled, and he was obliged, notwithſtanding his oath, to deſiſt.</p><p>In the mean time, the regents aſſembled a parliament at Dairſy, near Cupar in Fife; but no plan of defence could be fallen upon, by reaſon of the animosities and factions which prevailed among the barons. Through the mediation of the French, ſome terms of peace were propoſed; but being rejected by the Engliſh, Edward again invaded Scotland, cruelly ravaging the country with one army, while Baliol and the earl of Warrene did the ſame with another. Soon after this invaſion, count Guy of Namur landed at Berwick with a conſiderable number of men-at-arms, in the ſervice of the Engliſh. He advanced to the neighbourhood of Edinburgh; but was defeated and taken priſoner by the earls of March and Moray, and Sir Alexander Ramſay. In this engagement, one Richard Shaw, a Scottiſh eſquire, was ſingled out by a combatant in the army of count Guy, and both pierced each other with their ſpears; the ſtranger being ſtripped, was diſcovered to be a woman. The earl of Moray treated Guy with the greateſt reſpect, not only allowing him and the remainder of his troops to depart from Scotland without moleſtation, but even attending him to the borders, accompanied by William Douglas and his brother James. On his return, William de Preſſen, warden of the caſtle and foreſt of Jedburgh, attacked and defeated his party; James Douglas was killed, the earl himſelf taken priſoner, and carried into England.</p><p>Thus was the Scottiſh nation once more reduced to the brink of ruin. Alexander de Mowbray, Geffrey de Mowbray, and ſome others, pretending powers from “the earl of Athol and Robert the Steward of Scotland,” concluded a treaty with Edward at Perth; the ſubſtance of which was, that all the Scots ſhould receive pardon, and have their fees, lands, and offices reſtored, excepting those who by <hi rend="italic">common qſſent</hi> in parliament ſhould be excluded. The liberties of the church and the ancient laws and uſages of Scotland were to remain in full force. All offices were to be filled with Scotſmen, excepting that the king ſhould appoint whom he pleaſed within his regalities.</p><p>The earl of Athol now began to perſecute with the utmoſt fury thoſe who wiſhed well to the cauſe of Scotland. With 3000 men he besieged the caſtle of Kildrommey, which had hitherto been the great refuge of king David’s party. Sir Andrew Murray of Both- well reſolved at all events to attempt the reſcue of his wife and family, who were ſhut up in this caſtle. With 1100 men he ſurpriſed Athol in the foreſt of Kilblain. The earl's men, ſeized with a panic, fled and diſperſed themſelves; on which their commander, refuſing to accept of quarter, was killed. Sir Andrew Murray then aſſembled a parliament at Dunfermline, where he was immediately appointed regent.</p><p>In 1336, the king of England perceiving that the Scots were taken under the patronage of France, reſolved to invade their country, and cruſh them at once before they could have any assiſtance from their new allies. In this expedition he penetrated as far as Inverneſs; but the Scots, commanded by Sir Andrew Murray, avoided coming to a general action; ſo that Edward could not effect any thing of conſequence.</p><p>The inhabitants of Aberdeen attacked one Thomas Roſheme, who had landed at Dunottar. They were defeated but Roſheme fell in the action. Edward chaſtiſed the vanquiſhed ſeverely for their temerity, and laid the town in aſhes. He then began to repair the caſtles whoſe fortifications had been demoliſhed by king Robert. He put in a ſtate of defence the caſtles of Dunottar, Kinclevin, Lawrieſton, Stirling, Bothwell, Edinburgh, and Roxburgh; greatly augmented the fortifications of Perth, and left a conſiderable body of troops in the place. The Scots began to reduce theſe caſtles as ſoon as Edward was departed; and in 1337, under Sir Andrew Murray, invaded Cumberland. No great exploits, however, were now performed on either ſide. Edward being employed in preparations for invading France, had little leiſure to attend to the affairs of Scotland; and the Scots, divided among themſelves, and deſtitute of thoſe leaders under whom they had acquired ſo much glory, could not now annoy their enemies as formerly. The moſt remarkable tranſaction was the ſiege of the caſtle of Dunbar, belonging to the earl of March. The Engliſh commander was the earl of Saliſhury. The earl of March was abſent; but his wife, the daughter of Randolph, from her complexion commonly called <hi rend="italic">Black Agnes,</hi> undertook to defend it in her huſhand’s abſence. The Engliſh again employed that huge machine called <hi rend="italic">a sow,</hi> formerly mentioned in our account of the ſiege of Berwick: it met with the ſame fate now as at that time; an huge ſtone, let fall upon it from the top of the walls, cruſhed it to pieces. The Engliſh, baffled in every attack, turned the ſiege into a blockade; but Sir Alexander Ramſay having; found means to enter it with 40 reſolute men, the garriſon made a ſally, and cut in pieces the advanced guard of the enemy. The Engliſh, diſheartened by ſo many misfortunes, abandoned the enterprise.</p><p>In 1338, Sir Andrew Murray the regent died, and was ſucceeded in his office by Robert the Steward of Scotland. In 1339 he reduced the town of Perth and the caſtle of Stirling; and gained over to the Scottiſh intereſt William Bullock, governor of the caſtle of Coupar: after which, having expelled the enemy from every poſt to the northward of the Forth, he employed himſelf in ſettling the affairs of the nation as well as he could.</p><p>In 1341, the caſtle of Edinburgh was ſurpriſed by a device of Sir William Bullock. According to his appointment, one Walter Currie of Dundee privately received into his ſhip the knight of Liddeſdale, with William Fraſer, Joachim of Kinbuck, and 200 reſolute men. Currie caſt anchor in Leith road, pretending to be an Engliſh ſhipmaſter, who had a cargo of wine and proviſions, with which he propoſed to furniſh the commander of the caſtle. His barrels and hampers were brought to the caſtle-gate, and ſuddenly thrown down in such a manner as to obſtruct the ſhutting of it. Currie and his men then flew the centinels; and the knight of Liddeſdale, with a party who lurked in the neighbourhood, ruffled in, overpowered the garriſon, and made themſelves maſters of the place.—On the 4th of March this year, the king and queen arrived from France, and landed at Inverbervie in Kincardineſhire.</p><p>In 1342, Sir Alexander Ramsay took the ſtrong fortreſs of Roxburgh; for which important ſervice the king beſtowed on him the charge of sheriff of Teviotdale, at</p></body></text></TEI>