<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:48:35Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>a ſtep of which he afterwards repented. The counteſs left him with regret; but this did not prevent her from marrying ſoon after. The count of Saxe was too fond of pleaſure and variety to ſubmit to the duties which marriage impoſes. In the midſt, however, of the pleaſures in which he ſometimes indulged, he never loſt ſight of his profeſſion. He carried along with him wherever he went a library of military books; and even when he ſeemed moſt taken up with his pleaſures, he never failed to ſpend an hour or two in private ſtudy.</p><p>In 1717 he went to Hungary, where the emperor had an army of 15, 000 men under the command of prince Eugene. Young count Saxe was preſent at the ſiege of Belgrade, and at a battle which the prince gained over the Turks. On his return to Poland in 1718, he was made a knight of the golden eagle.</p><p>The wars in Europe being concluded by the treaties of Utrecht and Poſſarowitz, count Saxe went to France. He had always profeſſed a partiality for that country. French, indeed, was the only foreign language which during his infancy he was willing to learn. He ſpent his whole time during the peace in ſtudying mathematics, fortification, and mechanics, ſciences which exactly ſuited his genius. The mode of exerciſing troops had ſtruck his attention when very young. At 16 he invented a new exerciſe, which was taught in Saxony with the greateſt ſucceſs. Having obtained a regiment in France in 1722, he formed it himſelf according to his new plan. From that moment the <hi rend="italic">Chevalier Follar,</hi> an excellent judge of military talents, predicted that he would be a great man.</p><p>In 1726 the States of Courland choſe him for their ſovereign. But both Poland and Ruſſia roſe in arms to oppoſe him. The Czarina wiſhed to beſtow the duchy on Menzikoff, a happy adventurer, who from a paſtry-cook’s boy became a general and a prince. Menzikoff ſent 800 Ruffians to Milan, where they beſieged the new-choſen duke in his palace. Count Saxe, who had only 60 men, defended himſelf with aſtoniſhing intrepidity. The ſiege was railed, and the Ruffians obliged to retreat. Soon after he retired to Uſmaiz, and prepared to defend his people againſt the two hoſtile nations. Here he remained with only 300 men, till the Ruffian general approached at the head of 4000 to force his retreat. That general invited the count to a conference, during which he intended to ſurpriſe him, and take him priſoner. The count, informed of the plot, reproached him for his baſeneſs, and broke up the conference. About this time he wrote to France for men and money. Mademoiſelle le Couvreur, a famous actreſs, pawned her jewels and plate, and ſent him the ſum of 40, 000 livres. This actreſs had formed his mind for the fine arts. She had made him read the greater part of the French poets, and given him a taſte for the theatre, which he retained even in the camp. The count, unable to defend himſelf againſt Ruſſia and Poland, was obliged in the year 1729 to leave his new dominions, and retire into France. It is ſaid that Anne Iwanowa, ducheſs dowager of Courland, and ſecond daughter of the czar Iwan Alexiowitz, had given him hopes of marriage, and abandoned him at that time becauſe ſhe deſpaired of fixing his wavering paſſion. — This inconſtancy loſt him not only Courland, but the throne of Ruſſia itſelf, which that Princeſs afterwards filled.</p><p>Count Saxe, thus ſtript of his territories, devoted himſelf for ſome time to the ſtudy of mathematics. He compoſed alſo, in 13 nights, and during the intervals of an ague, his <hi rend="italic">Reveries,</hi> which he corrected afterwards. This book is written in an incorrect but forcible ſtyle; it is full of remarks both new and profound, and is equally uſeful to the ſoldier and the general.</p><p>The death of the king of Poland his father, in 1733, kindled a new war in Europe. His brother, the elector of Saxony, offered him the command of all his forces, but he preferred the French ſervice, and repaired to the marechal of Berwick’s army, which was encamped on the Rhine. “Count, ” ſaid that general, who was preparing to attack the enemy’s entrnchments at Etlinghen, “I was going to ſend for 3000 men, but your arrival is of more value than theirs. ” When the attack began, the count, at the head of a regiment of grenadiers, forced the enemy’s lines, and by his bravery decided the victory. He behaved at the ſiege of Philipſburgh with no leſs intrepidity. For theſe ſervices he was, in 1734, rewarded with the rank of lieutenant- general. Peace was concluded in 1736; but the death of Charles VI. emperor of Germany kindled a new war almoſt immediately.</p><p>Prague was beſieged by the count of Saxe in 1741, near the end of November, and taken the ſame month by aſſault. The conqueſt of Egra followed that of Prague. It was taken a few days after the trenches were opened. This ſucceſs gave ſo much joy to the Emperor Charles VII. that he wrote a congratulatory  letter to the conqueror with his own hands.</p><p>In 1744 he was made marechal of France, and commanded a part of the French army in Flanders. During that campaign he diſplayed the greateſt military conduct. Though the enemy was ſuperior in number, he obſerved their motions ſo ſkillully that they could do nothing.</p><p>In January 1745, an alliance was concluded at Warſovia between the queen of Hungary, the king of England, and the States of Holland. The ambaffador of the States General, meeting marechal Saxe one day at Verſailles, aſked his opinion of that treaty. “I think (fays he), that if the king my maſter would give me an unlimited commiſſion, I would read the original at the Hague before the end of the year. ” This anſwer was not a bravado; the marechal was capable of performing it.</p><p>He went ſoon after, though exceedingly ill, to take the command of the French army in the Low Countries. A gentleman ſeeing the feeble condition in which he left Paris, aſked him how he could in that ſituation undertake ſo great an enterpriſe? “The queſtion (replied he) is not about living, but ſetting out. ”— Soon after the opening of the campaign, the battle of Fontenoy was fought. Marechal Saxe was at the point of death, yet he cauſed himſelf to be put into a litter, and carried round all the poſts. During the action he mounted on horſeback, though he was ſo very weak that his attendants dreaded every moment to ſee him expire. The victory of Fontenoy, owing entirely to his vigilance and capacity, was followed by the reduction of Tournay, Bruges, Ghent, Oudenarde, Oſtend, Ath, and Bruſſels: This laſt city was taken on the 28th February 1746; and very ſoon after the King ſent to the marechal a letter of naturalization conceived in the moſt</p></body></text></TEI>