<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-14T17:47:17Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>rit of ſalt; for neither mineral alkali nor pure ſea-ſalt are at all deliqueſcent in
                the air.</p>
            <p> 3. Vitriolated magneſia with vitriol of iron, or Epſom ſalt contaminated with
                copperas. This, according to M. Monet, is found in ſome mineral waters.</p>
            <p> 4. Native alum contaminated with copperas. This is ſometimes found in the aluminous
                ſchiſtus, and efflo- reſces in a feathery form, and is perhaps the plumoſe alum of
                the ancients.</p>
            <p>5. Native alum contaminated with ſulphur. Dr Withering informs us, that this ſalt is
                met with about Wednegburg and Belſton, two places in Staffordſhire, where the
                coal-pits are on fire. It ſublimes to the ſurface, whence it may be collected in
                conſiderable quantity during dry or froſty weather. Our author, however, does not
                certainly affirm that this is a true chemical union, but the parts, he ſays, cannot
                be diſtinguiſhed by the eye. It is kept in a deliqueſcent ſtate by an acceſs of
                vitriolic acid.</p>
            <p> 6. Native alum contaminated by vitriolated cobalt. This is found in ſome of the
                mines of Herregrund and Idria, where it ſhoots into long and ſlender filaments. M.
                Magellan ſuppoſes that this may be the <hi rend="italic">trichites</hi> of the
                Greeks. On diſſolving it in water, the preſence of the vitriolic acid is diſcovered
                by adding a ſolution of terra ponderoſa in muriatic acid; the phlogiſticated alkali
                throws down a precipitate of cobalt, which forms a blue glaſs with cobalt or
                microcoſmic ſalt.</p>
            <p> 7. Vitriol of copper with iron, the <hi rend="italic">vitrolurn ferreo-cupreum
                    cyaneum</hi> oſ Linnaeus. It is alſo called<hi rend="italic"> Vitriol of
                    Hungary,</hi> becauſe found in plenty in that country. Its colour is that of
                blue mixed with green; but ſometimes the one ſhade prevails, and ſometimes the
                other.</p>
            <p> 8. Vitriol of copper, iron, and zinc, is prepared in Sweden from the water pumped
                out of the copper mines at Dalame. The copper does not precipitate from a ſolution
                of this ſalt by rubbing it on iron, as is the caſe with the common blue vitriol.
                Large cryſtals of this ſalt are often found in the water, the copper mines from
                whence it is prepared.</p>
            <p> 9. Vitriol of copper and zinc. This is a quadruple ſalt, ſtyled by Linnaeus <hi
                    rend="italic">Vitriolum ferreo-zinceo cupreum cyaneum.</hi> Its colour is blue
                inclining to green; and it does not precipitate the copper by rubbing on iron, as
                the common blue vitriol does. It is called the blue vitriol of Goſlar. Mongez makes
                a ſeparate article of a compound ſalt mentioned by Wallerius, conſiſting alſo of a
                vitriolated copper with zinc, but whoſe cryſtals are of a fine red colour, found
                lately in the mines of Fahlun in Sweden. He adds, that the pale-blue colour of the
                former ſalt ſhows the predominancy of the copper, by which it is neceſſarily
                diſtinguiſhed from the latter, where the vitriol is over-ſaturated. M. Magellan,
                however, is of opinion, that the red colour is owing to a proper quantity of iron in
                a dephlogiſticated ſtate, which has been overlooked in that compound. To this kind
                alſo Wallerius refers the yellowiſh vitriol found in Hungary.</p>
            <p> 10. Vitriol of iron and zinc; the green vitriol from Goſlar in the Hartz; the <hi
                    rend="italic">vitreolum zinceo-ferreum viride</hi> of Linnaeus. It is of a
                pale-green colour.</p>
            <p>SALT-Mines.<hi rend="italic"> See </hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Salt.</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Rock-SALT.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Salt.</hi></p>
            <p>S<hi rend="smallcaps">alt-</hi>Water,<hi rend="italic"> or </hi>Sea-water
                (Diſstillation of).<hi rend="italic"> See SEA.</hi> Water.</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Neutral</hi>
                <hi rend="italic smallcaps">Salts.</hi> See CHEMISTRY, n⁰172, 1180, and 1331.</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">SALT-Springs.</hi> Of theſe there are great numbers in different
                parts of the world, which undoubtedly have their origin from ſome of the large
                collections of foſſil ſalt mentioned under the article <hi rend="italic">Common</hi>
                <hi rend="italic smallcaps">Salt.</hi> See that article, and likewife <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Spring.</hi></p>
            <p>SALTIER, one of the honourable ordinaries. — See <hi rend="smallcaps">Heraldry,</hi>
                p. 452, and Plate CCXXX.</p>
            <p>This, ſays G. Leigh, in his Accedence of Arms, p. 70. was anciently made of the
                height of a man, and driven full of pins, the uſe of which was to ſcale walls,
                &amp;c. Upton ſays it was an inſtrument to catch wild beaſts, whence he derives this
                word from <hi rend="italic">ſaltus,</hi> i.e. “a foreſt.” The French call this
                ordinary <hi rend="italic">ſautoir,</hi> from <hi rend="italic">ſauter</hi> "to
                leap;” becauſe it may have been uſed by ſoldiers to leap over walls of towns, which
                in former times were but low; but ſome modern authors think it is borne in imitation
                of St Andrew’s croſs.</p>
            <p>SALTING <hi rend="smallcaps">meat for the use of the navy</hi>. The following is the
                method recommended by the late admiral Sir Charles Knowles. When the ox is killed,
                let it be ſkinned and cut up into pieces fit for uſe as quick as poſſible, and
                ſalted while the meat is hot. For which purpoſe we muſt have a ſufficient quantity
                of ſaltpetre and bay-ſalt pounded together and made hot in an oven, of each equal
                parts; with this ſprinkle the meat at the rate of about two ounces to the pound;
                then lay the pieces on ſhelving boards to drain for 24 hours; which done, turn them
                and repeat the ſame operation, and let them lie for 24 hours longer. By this time
                the ſalt will be all melted, and have penetrated the meat, and the pieces be drained
                off; each piece muſt then be wiped dry with clean coarſe cloths. A ſufficient
                quantity of common felt muſt then be made hot like- wiſe in an oven, and mixed when
                taken out with about one-third of brown ſugar: then the caſks being ready, rub each
                piece well with this mixture, and pack them well down, allowing about half a pound
                of the ſalt and ſugar to each pound of meat, and it will keep good ſeveral
                years.</p>
            <p>It is beſt to proportion the caſks to the quantity uſed at one time, as the leſs it
                is expoſed to the air the better. The ſame proceſs does for pork, only a larger
                quantity of ſalt and leſs ſugar muſt be uſed; but the preſervation of both depends
                equally upon the meat being hot when firſt ſalted.</p>
            <p>One pound of beef requires two ounces of ſaltpetre and two ounces of bay-ſalt,
                becauſe it is to be ſprinkled twice; an ounce of each to a pound of beef both times.
                The ſaltpetre requiſite for 100 lb. of beef is I2 <hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi
                    rend="subscript">2</hi> lb. which at 12 d. per lb. is 12s. 6d.; and the ſame
                quantity of bay-ſalt (for 100 lb. of beef), at three half-pence per lb. is 1s. 6d.;
                of brown ſugar and common ſalt mixed together half a pound is required, the former
                in the proportion of one-third, the latter of two- thirds, to a pound of beef. The
                brown ſugar at 8d. per pound. A hundred pounds of beef will take 250 ounces of it,
                which coſts 10s. 5d. The quantity of common ſalt requiſite for 100 lb. of beef is
                533 ounces, which at 2d. per lb. amounts to 5s. 6d. The expence therefore will ſtand
                thus.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
