<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:51:00Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>traitors had previouſly poſſeſſed the prince with an apprehenſion that his life was in danger, and had persuaded him to ſeize the caſtle of St Andrew’s, and to keep poſſeſſion of it during the vacancy of that ſee. Robert had nominated one oſ his baſtard brethren, who was then deacon of St Andrew’s, to that biſhopric: but being a perſon no way fitted for ſuch a dignity, he declined the honour, and the chapter refuſed to elect any other during his lifetime; ſo that the prince had a proſpect of poſſeſſing the caſtle for ſome time. He was riding thither with a ſmall attendance, when he was arreſted between the towns of Nidi and Stratirum (according to the continuator of Fordun), and hurried to the very caſtle of which he was preparing to take poſſeſſion.</p><p>The duke of Albany, and the earl of Douglas, who was likewiſe the prince’s enemy, were then at Culroſs, waiting the event of their deteſtable conſpiracy; of which they were no ſooner informed, than they ordered a ſtrong body of ruffians to carry the royal captive from the caſtle of St Andrew’s; which they did, after clothing him in a ruſſet cloak, mounting him on a very ſorry horſe, and committing him to the cuſtody of two execrable wretches, John Selkirk and John Wright, who were ordered by the duke of Albany to ſtarve him to death. According to Buchanan, his late was for ſome time prolonged by the compaſſion of one of his keeper’s daughters, who thruſt thin oat cakes through the chinks of his priſon walls, and by a woman who, being a wet nurſe, found means to convey part of her milk to him through a ſmall tube. Both theſe charitable females were detected, and put to death; the young lady’s inhuman father being himſelf the proſecutor. The prince himſelf died a few days after, on Eaſter-eve, his hunger having impelled him to devour part of his own fleſh.</p><p>In the mean time, Robert, being yet ignorant of the murder of his ſon, had renewed, or rather conſented to renew, hoſtilities with England. On the expiration of the truce, Henry had ſent a commiſſion to the earls of Northumberland and Weſtmoreland, to offer the Scots any terms they could reaſonably deſire; but every offer of this kind being rejected, there was a neceſſity for renewing hoſtilities. The earl of March had received another penſion from Henry, on condition of his keeping on foot a certain number of light troops to act againſt the Scots. This had been done; and ſo effectually did theſe now annoy their enemies, that the earl of Douglas was obliged to take the field againſt them. By dividing his men into ſmall parties, he repreſſed the depredations of theſe invaders; and Thomas Haliburton, the commander of one of the Scottiſh parties, made incurſions into England as far as Bamborough, from whence he returned with a conſiderable booty. This encouraged another chieftain, Patrick Hepburn, to make a ſimilar attempt: but being elated with his ſucceſs, he remained too long in the enemy’s country; ſo that the earl of March had time to ſend a detachment to intercept him on his return. This produced a deſperate encounter, in which Hepburn was killed; the flower of the youth of Lothian, who had attended in this expedition, were cut off, and ſcarce a ſingle Scotſman remained unwounded.</p><p>On the news of this diſaſter, the earl of Douglas applied to the duke of Albany for aſſiſtance. He was immediately furniſhed with a conſiderable army, according to ſome, conſiſting of 10,000; according to others of 13,000; and according to the Engliſh hiſtorians, of 20,000 men. Murdoc, the ſon of the duke, attended the earl on this expedition, as did alſo the earls of Moray, Angus, Orkney, and many others of the chief nobility, with 80 knights. The Scots on this occaſion conducted themſelves with the ſame imprudence they had done before. Having penetrated too far into the country, they were intercepted by the Engliſh on their return, and obliged to engage at a place called <hi rend="italic">Homeldon,</hi> under great diſadvantages. The conſequence was, that they were utterly defeated, and almoſt the whole army either killed or taken.</p><p>Henry Hotſpur, to whom this victory was chiefly owing, reſolving to purſue the advantage he had gained, entered the ſouthern parts of the kingdom, and laid ſiege to a caſtle called <hi rend="italic">Cocklawys,</hi> on the borders of Teviotdale. The caſtle was for ſome time bravely defended: but at laſt the governor entered into a treaty, by which it was agreed to deliver up the caſtle, in caſe it was not relieved by the king or governor in ſix weeks; during which time no additional fortifications were to be made. But while the Engliſh were retiring, one of Percy’s ſoldiers pretended that the Scots had broke the capitulation, by introducing a mattock into the place. The governor, hearing of this charge, offered to fight any Engliſhman who ſhould engage to make it good. A champion was accordingly ſingled out, but was defeated by the Scotſman; and the Engliſh army retired according to agreement. The matter then being debated in the Scottiſh council, it was reſolved to ſend relief to the caſtle. Accordingly the duke of Albany, with a powerful army, ſet out for the place; but before he came there, certain news were received of the defeat and death of Hotſpur, at Shrewſhury, as related under the article <hi rend="smallcaps">England,</hi> n⁰ 182.</p><p>In the year 1404, king Henry, exceedingly deſirous of a peace with Scotland, renewed his negociations for that purpoſe. Theſe, however, not being attended with ſucceſs, hoſtilities were ſtill continued, but without any remarkable tranſaction on either side. In the mean time, king Robert was informed of the miſerable fate of his eldeſt ſon the duke of Rotheſay; but was unable to reſent it by executing juſtice on ſuch a powerful murderer. After giving himſelf up to grief, therefore, for ſome time, he reſolved to provide for the ſafety of his ſecond ſon James, by ſending him into France. This ſcheme was not communicated to the duke of Albany; and the young prince took flipping with all imaginable ſecrecy at the Baſs, under the care of the earl of Orkney. On his voyage he was taken by an Engliſh privateer off Flamborough-head, and brought before Henry. The Engliſh monarch having examined the attendants of the prince, they told him that they were carrying the prince to France for his education. "I underſtand the French tongue (replied Henry), and your countrymen ought to have been kind enough to have truſted me with their prince’s education.” He then committed the prince and his attendants cloſe priſoners to the tower of London. The news of this diſaſter arrived at the caſtle of Rotheſay in the iſle of Bute (the place of Robert’s reſidence) while the king was at ſupper. The news threw him into ſuch an agony of grief, that he died in three</p></body></text></TEI>