<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:48:04Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p><hi rend="italic">rough oſ Old Sarum,</hi> and fends two members to parliament, who are choſen by the proprietors of certain adjacent lands.</p><p>In February 1795 a ſubterraneous paſſage was diſcovered at this place, of which we have the following account in the Gentleman’s Magazine for March, in a letter dated Saliſhury, Feb. 10. “Some perſons of Saliſ</p><p>bury on Saturday laſt went to the upper verge of the fortification (the citadel), and on the right-hand, after they had reached the ſummit, diſcovered a large hole. They got a candle and lantern, and went down a flight of ſteps for more than 30 yards. It was an arched way ſeven feet wide, neatly chiſſeled out of the ſolid rock or chalk. It is probable the crown of the arch gave way from the ſudden thaw, and fell in. There is a great deal of rubbiſh at the entrance. It appears to be between ſix and ſeven feet high, and a circular arch overhead all the way. Theſe particulars I learned from the perfon who himſelf explored it; but was afraid to go farther left it might fall in again and bury him. He thinks it turns a little to the right towards Old Sarum houſe, and continues under the foſſe till it reached the outer verge, The marks of a chiſſel, he ſays, are viable on the fide. There are two large pillars of ſquare-stoneone at the entrance, which appear to have had a door at foot. They are 18 inches by 27, of good free-ſtone, and the maſon-work is extremely neat. The higheſt part of the archway is two feet below the ſurface of the ground</p><p>“It is all now again filled up by order of farmer Whitchurch, who rents the ground of Lord Camelford, and thinks curioſity would bring ſo many people there as to tread down his graſs whenever graſs ſhall be there. I went into it 30 yards, which was as far as I could get for the rubbiſh. I meaſured it with a line, and found it extend full 120 feet inwards from the two pillars ſuppoſed to be the entrance; then onwards it appeared to be filled to the roof with rubbiſh. By meaſuring with the ſame line on the ſurface of the earth, I found it muſt go under the bottom of the outer bank of the outer trench; wſhere I think the opening may be found by digging a very little way. Whether it was a Roman or a Norman work it is difficult to ſay; but it certainly was intended as a private way to go into or cut of the caſtle; and probably a fort or ſtrong caſtle was built over the outer entrance. I looked for inſcriptions or coins, but have not heard of any being found. ”</p><p>SASAFRAS. See LAURUS.</p><p>SASHES, in military dreſs, are badges of diſtinction worn by the officers of moſt nations, either round their waiſt or over their ſhoulders. Thoſe for the Britiſh army are made of crimſon ſilk: for the Imperial army crimſon and gold; for the Pruſſian army black ſilk and ſilver; the Hanoverians yellow ſilk; the Portugueſe crimſon ſilk with blue taſſels.</p><p>SASINE, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Seisin,</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Law, N</hi><hi rend="superscript smallcaps">o</hi> clxiv. 15, &amp;c.</p><p>SASSA. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Myrrh, OpocalPasum,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Bruce’s Travels,</hi> Vol. V. p. 27, &amp;c.</p><p>SAT A N, a name very common in Scripture, means the devil or chief of the fallen angels. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Devil.</hi></p><p>SATELLITE, in aſtronomy, the ſame with a ſecondary planet or moon.</p><p>SATIRE. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Satyr.</hi></p><p>SATRAPA, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Satrapes,</hi> in Perſian antiquity, denotes an admiral; but more commonly the governor of a province.</p><p>SATTIN, a gloſſy kind of ſilk ſtuff, the warp of which is very fine, and ſtands ſo as to cover the coarſer woof.</p><p>SATTINET, a ſlight thin kind of ſattin, commonly ſtriped, and ordinarily uſed by the ladies for ſummer night-gowns.</p><p>SATURANTS, in anatomy, the ſame with <hi rend="smallcaps">Absorbents.</hi></p><p>SATURATION, in chemiſtry, is the impregnating an acid with an alkali, or <hi rend="italic">vice verſa,</hi> till either will receive no more, and the mixture will then become neutral. 	</p><p>SATURDAY, the ſeventh and laſt day oſ the week, ſo called from the idol Seater, worſhipped on this day by the ancient Saxons, and thought to be the ſame as the Saturn of the Latins.</p><p>SATUREIA, <hi rend="smallcaps">savory,</hi> in botany: A genus of the gymnoſpermia order, belonging to the didynamia claſs of plants; and in the natural method ranking under the 42d order, <hi rend="italic">Verticillatae.</hi> The ſegments of the corolla are nearly equal; the ſtamina ſtanding aſunder.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Species.</hi> I. The hortenſis, or ſummer favory, is an annual plant, which grows naturally in the ſouth of France and Italy, but is cultivated in this country both for the kitchen and medicinal uſe. 2. The montana, or winter ſavory, is a perennial plant growing naturally in the ſouth of France and Italy, but is cultivated in gardens both for culinary and medicinal purpoſes.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Culture.</hi> Both kinds are propagated by ſeeds. Thoſe of the firſt kind ſhould be ſown in the beginning of April upon a bed of light earth, either where they are to remain, or for tranſplanting. If the plants are to ſtand unremoved, they ſhould be ſown thinly; but if they are to be tranſplanted, they may be ſown cloſer. The ſecond ſpecies may be ſown upon a poor dry ſoil, where the plants will endure the ſevereſt winters, though they are often killed by the froſt when planted in good ground. The plants will continue ſeveral years; but when they are old, the ſhoots will be ſhot and not ſo well furniſhed with leaves; it will therefore be proper to raiſe a ſupply of young plants every year.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Uſes.</hi> Summer ſavory is a very warm pungent aromatic; and affords in diſtillation with water a ſubtile eſſential oil, of a penetrating ſmall, and very hot acrid taſte. It yields little of its virtues by infuſion to aqueous liquors; rectified ſpirit extracts the whole oſ its taſte and ſmell, and elevates nothing in diſtillation.</p><p>SATURN, in aſtronomy, one of the planets of our ſolar ſyſtem, revolving at the diſtance of more than 900 millions of miles from the fun. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Astronomy, </hi>n⁰ 31, 104—109, 191, and 269.</p><p>Dr Herſchel, who has ſo much ſignalized himſelf by his diſcoveries in the celeſtial regions, has not omitted to make his obſervarions on this planet, which he conſi ders as one of the moſt engaging objects that aſtronomy offers to our view. His attention was firſt drawn to it in the year 1774, when he ſaw its ring reſembling in appearance a narrow line, extending on both ſides not much leſs than the diameter oſ the planet’s diſk. The obſervation was taken with a five and an half feet re-</p></body></text></TEI>