<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:51:15Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>tions they were obliged to ſupply, they left Stirling, and deſtroyed the eſtate of Sir John Douglas of Dab keſth, whom they conſidered as a double traitor, because he was a Douglas and a good ſubject. They then beſieged his caſtle: but it was ſo bravely defended by Patrick Cockburn, a gentleman of the family of Langton, that they raiſed the ſiege; which gave the royal party farther leiſure for humbling them.</p><p>All this time the unhappy country was ſuffering the moſt cruel devaſtations; for matters were now come to ſuch extremity, that it was neceſſary for every man to be a royaliſt or a rebel. The king was obliged to keep on the defenſive; and though he had ventured to leave the caſtle of Stirling, he was in no condition to face the rebels in the field. They were in poſſeſſion of all the ſtrong paſſes by which his friends were to march to his aſſiſtance; and he even conſulted with his attendants on the means of eſcaping to France, where he was ſure of an hoſpitable reception. He was diverted from that reſolution by biſhop Kennedy and the earl of Angus, who was himſelf a Douglas, and prevailed upon to wait for the event of the earl of Huntley’s attempts for his ſervice. This nobleman, who was deſcended from the Seatons, but by marriage inherited the great eſtates of the Gordons in the north, had raiſed an army for James, to whoſe family he and his anceſtors, by the Gordons as well as the Seatons, had been always remarkably devoted. James was not miſtaken in the high opinion he had of Huntley; and in the mean time he iſſued circular letters to the chief eccleſiaſtics and bodies-politic of his kingdom, ſetting forth the neceſſity he was under to proceed as he had done, and his readineſs to protect all his loyal ſubjects in their rights and privileges againſt the power of the Douglaſſes and their rebellious adherents. Before thoſe letters could have any effect, the rebels had plundered the defenceleſs houſes and eſtates of all who were not in their confederacy, and had proceeded with a fury that turned to the prejudice of their cauſe.</p><p>The indignation which the public had conceived againſt the king, for the violation of his ſafe conduct, began now to ſubſide; and the behaviour of his enemies in ſome meaſure juſtiſied what had happened, or at leaſt made the people ſuſpect that James would not have proceeded as he did without the ſtrongeſt provocation. The forces he had aſſembled being unable, as yet, to act offenſively, he reſolved to wait for the earl of Huntley, wſho by this time was at the head of a conſiderable army, and had begun his march southwards. He had been joined by the Forbeſes, Ogilvies, Leſlies, Grants, Irvings, and other relations and dependents of his family; but having advanced as far as Brechin, he was oppoſed by the earl of Crawford, the chief ally of the earl of Douglas, who commanded the people of Angus, and all the adherents of the rebels in the neighbouring counties, headed by foreign officers. The two armies joining battle on the 18th of May, victory was for ſome time in ſuſpence; till one Coloss of Bonnymoon, on whom Crawford had great dependence, but whom he had imprudently diſobliged, came over to the royaliſts with the diviſion he commanded, which was the beſt aimed part of Crawford's army, conſiſting of battle-axes, broad ſwords, and long ſpears His defection gave the fortune of the day to the earl of Huntley, as it left the centre flank of Crawford’s army en</p><p>tirely expoſed to the royaliſts. He himſelf loſt one of his brothers; and fled with another, Sir John Lindſay, to his houſe at Finhaven, where it is reported that he broke out into the following ejaculation: “That he would be content to remain ſeven years in hell, to have in ſo timely a ſeaſon done the king his mailer that ſervice the earl of Huntly had performed, and carry that applauſe and thanks he was to receive from him.”</p><p>No author informs us of the loſs of men on either fide, though all agree that it was very conſiderable upon the whole. The earl of Huntley, particularly, loſt two brothers, William and Henry; and we are told, that, to indemnify him for his good ſervices, as well as for the rewards and preſents he had made in lands and privileges to his faithful followers, the king beſtowed upon him the lands of Badenoch and Lochaher.</p><p>The battle of Brcchin was not immediately deciſive in favour of the king, but proved ſo in its conſequences. The earl of Moray, a Douglas likewiſe, took advantage of Huntley's abſence to haraſs and ravage the eſtates of all the royaliſts in the north; but Huntley returning from Brechin with his victorious army, drove his enemy into his own county of Moray, and afterwards expelled him even from thence. James was now encouraged, by the advice of his kinſman Kennedy biſhop of St Andrew’s, to whoſe ſirmneſs and prudence he was under great obligations, to proceed againſt the rebels in a legal manner, by holding a parliament at Edinburgh, to which the confederated lords were ſummoned; and upon their non-compearance, they were ſolemnly declared traitors. This proceeding ſeemed to make the rebellion rage more fiercely than ever; and at laſt, the confederates, in fact, diſowned their allegiance to James. The earls of Douglas, Crawford, Ormond, Moray, the Lord Balveny Sir James Hamilton, and others, ſigned with their own hands public manifeſtoes, which were paſted on the doors of the principal chinches, importing, “That they were reſolved never to obey command or charge, nor anſwer citation for the time coming; becauſe the king, ſo far from being a juſt maſter, was a bloodſucker, a murderer, a tranſgresſor of hoſpitality, and a ſurpriſer of the innocent.” It does not appear that thoſe and the like atrocious proceedings did any ſervice to the cauſe of the confederates. The earl of Huntley continued victorious in the north; where he and his followers, in revenge for the earl of Moray’s having burnt his caſtle of Huntley, ſeized or ravaged all that nobleman's great eſtate north of the Spey. When he came to the town of Forres, he burnt one fide of the town, becauſe it belonged to the earl, and ſpared the other, becauſe it was the property of his own friends. James thought himſelf, from the behaviour of the earl of Douglas and his adherents, now warranted to come to extremities; and marching into Annandale, he carried fire and ſword through all the eſtates of the Douglaſſes there. The earl of Crawford, on the other hand, having now recruited his ſtrength, deltroyed the lands of all the people of Angus and of all others who had abandoned him at the battle of Brechin; though there is reaſon to believe, that he had already ſecretly reſolved to throw himſelf upon the king’s mercy.</p><p>Nothing but the moſt obſtinate pride and reſentment could have prevented the earl of Douglas, at this time, from taking the advice of his friends, by returning to</p></body></text></TEI>