<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:49:41Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>with the victory they had gained over their antagoniſts; but being commanded to adopt the laws of the Romans, and to chooſe no king who was not ſent them from Rome, they began to repent of their having contributed to the expulſion of the Scots; and in the year 421, when Autulphus king of the Goths ſent over a body of exiled Scots to Britain, under Fergus, a deſcendant of the royal family of Scotland, the Picts immediately joined them againſt the common enemy. The conſequence of this was, that the Britons were puſhed to the laſt extremity; and the Romans being obliged, on account of the inundation of northern barbarians who poured in upon them, to recal their forces from Britain, the inhabitants were reduced to the moſt miſerable ſituation that can be imagined. In the time of Fergus II. they were obliged to give up all the country which lies to the north of Adrian’s wall; and in the reign of Grimus or Graham, the ſucceſſor of Fergus, they were obliged to write that remarkable letter to Rome, intitled, “The groans of the Britons @@†.” This, however, not being attended with ſucceſs, the Britons were obliged to call in the Saxons to their aſſiſtance. By theſe new allies the Scots were defeated in a great battle, and their king (Eugene) drowned in the river Humber; which put a ſtop for ſome time to theſe incurſions.</p><p>Hitherto we have ſeen the Scots very formidable enemies to the ſouthern Britons. But when the Saxons became the enemies of the Britons, the Scots joined in a ſtrict alliance with the latter; and the famous king A rthur is ſaid to have been aſſiſted by the Scots in all his battles with the Saxons: neither does it appear that this league was ever diſſolved again, though the united efforts of the Scots and Brſtons were not ſufficient to preſerve the independency of the latter.</p><p>The next remarkable event in the hiſtory of Scotland is the war with the Picts, which took place in the ninth century. The occaſion of the quarrel was, that Dongal king of Scotland pretended a right to the Pictiſh throne; which, however, was rejected by the Picts: upon which both parties had recourſe to arms; but when every thing was ready for the campaign, Dongal was drowned in croſſing the river Spey.</p><p>At this time the dominions of the Scots comprehended the weſtern iſlands, together with the counties of Argyle, Knapdale, Kyle, Kintyre, Lochaber, and a part of Breadalbane; while the Picts poſſeſſed all the reſt of Scotland, and part of Northumberland; ſo that the Picts ſeem to have been by much the moſt powerful people of the two. However, the Scots appear to have been ſuperior in military ſkill; for Alpin, the ſucceſſor of Dongal, having engaged the Pictiſh army near Forfar, after an obſtinate engagement defeated them, and killed their king, though not without the loſs of a great number of his own men. The Picts choſe Brudus, the ſon of their former king, to ſucceed him; but ſoon after depoſed and put him to death, on account of his ſtupidity and indolence. His brother Kenneth ſhared the ſame fate on account of his cowardice; till at laſt another Brudus, a brave and ſpirited prince, aſcended the throne. Having raiſed a powerful army, he began with offering terms of peace to the Scots; which, however, Alpin rejected, and inſiſted upon a total ſurrender of his crown. Brudus on  this endeavoured to procure the aſſiſtance of Edwin</p><p>king of Northumberland. Edwin accepted the money; but pretending to be engaged in other wars, he refuſed the aſſiſtance which he at firſt promiſed. Brudus, not diſmayed by this diſappointment, marched reſolutely againſt his enemies; and the two armies came to an engagement near Dundee. The ſuperior ſkill of the Scots in military affairs was about to have decided the victory in their favour, when Brudus bethought himſelf of the following ſtratagem to preſerve his army from deſtruction. He cauſed all the attendants, and even the women who attended his army, to aſſemble and ſhow themſelves at a diſtance as a powerful reinforcement coming to the Picts. This ſtruck the Scots with ſuch a panic, that all the efforts of Alpin could not recover them; and they were accordingly defeated with great ſlaughter. Alpin himſelf was taken priſoner, and ſoon after beheaded by order of the conqueror. This execution happened at a place now called <hi rend="italic">Pit-alpy,</hi> but in former times <hi rend="italic">Bas-alpin,</hi> which in the Gaelic language ſigniſies the <hi rend="italic">death of Alpin.</hi> His head was afterwards ſtuck upon a pole, and expoſed on a wall.</p><p>Alpin was ſucceeded by his ſon Kenneth II. who being a brave and enterpriſing prince, reſolved to take a moſt ſevere revenge for his father’s death. The Scots, however, were ſo diſpirited by their late defeat, that they were exceedingly averſe to any renewal of the war: while, on the other hand, the Picts were ſo much elated, that they made a law by which it became death for any man to propoſe peace with the Scots, whom they reſolved to exterminate; and ſome of the nobility were expelled the council on account of their oppoſition to this law. The conſequence of this was, that civil diffenſions took place among them, and a bloody battle was fought between the oppoſite parties, before the Scots had thought of making any farther reſiſtance.</p><p>By theſe diſtractions Brudus, wſho had in vain endeavoured to appeaſe them, was ſo much affected, that he died of grief; and was ſucceeded by his brother Druſken. —The new prince alſo failed in his endeavours to accommodate the civil differences; ſo that the Scots, by gaining ſo much reſpite, at laſt began to recover from their conſternation; and ſome of them having ventured into the Pictiſh territories, carried off Alpin’s head from the capital of their dominions, ſuppoſed to have been Abernethy. In the mean time, Kenneth ſound means to gain over the nobility to his  ſide by the following ſtratagem; which, however ridiculous, is not incredible, if we conſider the barbariſm and ſuperſtition of that age. Having invited them to an entertainment, the king introduced into the hall where they ſlept a perſhn clothed in a robe made of the ſkins of fifties, which made ſuch a luminous appearance in the dark, that he was miſtaken for an angel or ſome ſupernatural meſſenger. To add to the terror of thoſe who ſaw him, he denounced, through a ſpeaking trumpet, the moſt terrible judgments, if war was not immediately declared againſt the Picts, the murderers of the late king. In conſequence of this celeſtial admonition, war was immediately renewed with great vigour. The Picts were not deficient in their preparations, and had now procured ſome aſſiſtance from England. The firſt battle was fought near Stirling; where the Picts, being deſerted by their Engliſh auxiliaries, were utterly defeated. Druſken eſcaped by the ſwift-</p><p>@@@[m]† See England, n⁰ 27.</p></body></text></TEI>