<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:48:01Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>only by Mutianus and Theophraſtus, except that Pliny had copied it from theſe authors, and ſome of the later writers on theſe ſubjects from him. The account Matianus gives of it is, that it converted into ſtone the ſhoes of perſons buried in it, as alſo the utenſils which it was in ſome places cuſtomary to bury with the dead, particularly thoſe which the perſon while living moſt delighted in. The utenſils this author mentions, are ſuch as muſt have been made of very different materials; and hence it appears that this ſtone had a power of conſuming not only fleſh, but that its petrifying quality extended to ſubſtances of very different kinds. Whether ever it really poſſeſſed this laſt quality has been much doubted; and many, from the ſeeming improbability of it, have been afraid to record it. What has much encouraged the general diſbelieſ of it is, Mutianus's account of its taking place on ſubſtances of very different kinds and textures; but this is no real objection, and the whole account has probably truth in it. Petrifactions in thoſe early days might not be diſtinguiſhed from incruſtations of ſparry and ſtony matter on the ſurfaces of bodies only, as we find they are not with the generality of the world even to this day; the incruſtations of ſpar on moſſes and other ſubſtances in ſome of our ſprings, being at this time called by many <hi rend="italic">petrified mo</hi>ſ<hi rend="italic">s. &amp;c.</hi> and incruſtations like theſe might eaſily be formed on ſubſtances encloſed in veſſels made of this ſtone, by water paſſing through its pores, diſlodging from the common maſs of the ſtone, and carrying with it particles of ſuch ſpar as it contained; and afterwards falling in repeated drops on whatever lay in its way, it might again depoſit them on ſuch ſubſtances in form of incruſtations. By this means, things made of ever ſo different matter, which happened to be incloſed, and in the way of the paſſage of the water, would be equally incruſted with and in appearance turned into ſtone, without regard to the different configuration of their pores and parts.</p><p>The place from whence the ancients tell us they had this ſtone was Aſſos, a city of Lycia, in the neighbourhood of which it was dug; and De Boot informs us, that in that country, and in ſome parts of the Eaſt, there are alſo ſtones of this kind, which, if tied to the bodies of living perſons, would in the ſame manner conſume their fleſh. <hi rend="italic">Hill's Notes on Theοphra</hi>ſt<hi rend="italic">us,</hi></p><p>P. 14.</p><p>SARCOTICS, in ſurgery, medicines which are ſuppoſed to generate fleſh in wounds.</p><p>SARDANAPALUS, the laſt king of Aſſyria, whoſe character is one of the moſt infamous in hiſtory. He is ſaid to have ſunk ſo far in depravity, that, as far as he could, he changed his very ſex and nature. He clothed himſelf as a woman, and ſpun amidſt companies of his concubines. He painted his face, and behaved in a more lewd manner than the moſt laſcivious harlot. In ſhort, he buried himſelf in the moſt unbounded ſenſuality, quite regardleſs of ſex and the dictates of nature. Having grown odious to all his ſubjects, a rebellion was formed againſt him. by Arbaces the Mede and Belefis the Babylonian. They were attended, however, with very bad ſucceſs at firſt, being defeated with great Slaughter in three pitched battles. With great difficulty' Belefis prevailed upon his men to keep the field only five days longer; when they were joined by the Bactrinus, who had come to the aſſiſtance of Sardanapalus, but</p><p>had been prevailed upon to renounce their allegiance to him. With this reinforcement they twice defeated the troops of Sardanapalus, who ſhut himſelf up in Nineveh the capital of his empire. The city held out for three years; at the end of which, Sardanapalus finding himſelf unable to hold out any longer, and dreading to fall into the hands of an enraged enemy, retired into his palace, in a court of which be cauſed a vaſt pile of wood to be railed; and heaping upon it all his gold and filler, and royal apparel, and at the ſame time incloſing his eunuchs and concubines in an apartment within the pile, he ſet fire to it, and ſo deſtroyed himſelf and all together.</p><p>SARDINIA, an iſland of the Mediterranean, bounded by the ſtrait which divides it from Corſica on the north; by the Tulcan ſea, which flows between this iſland and Italy, on the eaſt; and by other parts of the Mediterranean ſea on the ſouth and weft. @@ It is about 140 miles in length and 70 in breadth, and contains 420, 000 inhabitants. The revenue ariſes chiefly from a duty upon ſalt, and is barely ſufficient to defray the expences of government; but it certainly might be conſiderably augmented, as the foil produces wine, corn, and oil, in abundance. Moſt of the ſalt that is exported is taken by the Danes and Swedes; the Engliſh formerly took great quantities for Newfoundland, but having found it more convenient to procure it from Spain and Portugal, they now take little or none. A profitable tunny fiſhery is carried on at the ſouth-weſt part of the iſland, but it is monopolized by the Duke de St Pierre, and a few more people, who happen to be proprietors of the adjoining land. Wild boars abound in the hilly parts of the iſland, and here are ſome few deer, not ſo large as thoſe in Britain, but in colour and make exactly the ſame. Beeves and ſheep are alſo common, as well as horſes. </p><p>The feudal ſyſtem ſtill ſubſiſts in a limited degree, and titles go with their eſtates, ſo that the purchaſer of the latter inherits the former. The regular troops ſeldom exceed 2000 men; but the militia amount to near 26, 000, of whom 11, 000 are cavalry. Their horſes are ſmall, but uncommonly active. In a charge, we ſhould beat them: but, on a march, they would be ſuperior to us. The country people are generally armed; but notwithſtanding their having been ſo long under the Spaniſh and Italian government, aſſaſſinations are by no means frequent; and yet by the laws of the country, if a man ſtabs another without premeditated malice, with in four hours after quarrelling with him, he is not liable to be hanged. On the other hand, the church affords no protection to the guilty. The Sardinians are not at all bigoted; and, next to the Spaniards, the Engliſh are their favourites. The whole iſland is ſubject to the Duke of Savoy, who enjoys the title of king of Sardinia. See <hi rend="smallcaps">CAGLIARI</hi></p><p>There is in this iſland a pleaſing variety of hills and valleys, and the foil is generally fruitful; but the inhabitants are a ſlothful generation, and cultivate but a little part of it. On the coaſt there is a fiſhery of anchovies and coral, of which they ſend large quantities to Genoa and Leghorn. This iſland is divided into two parts; the one, called <hi rend="italic">Capo-di-Cagliari </hi>lies to the ſouth; and the other <hi rend="italic">Capο-di Lugary,</hi> which is leated to the north. The principal towns are Cagliari the capital, Oriſtagno, and Saſſari.</p><p>@@@ [mu] <hi rend="italic">Sutherland's Tour up the Straits. </hi></p></body></text></TEI>