<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:50:17Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ward could not  penetrate farther; and the ſame year a truce was concluded with the Scots, to continue till Whitſunday 1301.</p><p>This year a new competitor appeared for the crown of Scotland. Boniface VIII. in a bull directed to Edward, averred, that Scotland belonged anciently, and did ſtill belong, to the holy ſee; and ſupported his extravagant claim by ſome ſtrange authorities; ſuch as, that Scotland had been miraculouſly converted by the relics of St Andrew: after which he proceeded to ſhow the futility of Edward’s pretenſions, and that Scotland never had any feudal dependence on England. He required Edward to ſet at liberty all the Scottiſh eccleſiaſtics, particularly Wiſheart biſhop of Glaſgow, and to remove his officers from the patrimony of the church: “But (added he) ſhould you have any pretenſions to the whole, or any part of Scotland, ſend your proctors to me within ſix months; I will hear and determine according to juſtice; I take the cauſe under my own peculiar cognizance.”</p><p>This interpoſition of the pope had probably been procured by Scottiſh emiſſaries at the court of Rome; but, however ridiculous his pretenſions might be, they afforded matter of very ſerious conſideration to Edward. After ſpending a whole winter in deliberations, Edward and his parliament made ſeparate anſwers to the pope. The anſwer of the parliament was to the following purpoſe: All England knows, that ever ſince the firſt eſtabliſhment of this kingdom, our kings have been liege- lords of Scotland. At no time has the kingdom of Scotland belonged to the church. In temporals, the kings of England are not amenable to the ſee of Rome. We have with one voice reſolved, that, as to temporals, the king of England is independent of Rome; that he ſhall not ſuffer his independency to be queſtioned; and therefore, that he ſhall not ſend commiſſioners to Rome. Such is, and ſuch, we truſt in God, ever will be, our opinion. We do not, we cannot, we muſt not, permit our king to follow meaſures ſubverſive of that government which we have ſworn to maintain, and which we will maintain.”</p><p>The king entered into a more full refutation of the pope’s arguments; and having, as he thought, anſwered them ſufficiently, he marched again into Scotland: but, by the mediation of France, another truce was concluded, to laſt till St Andrew’s day 1302.</p><p>After the expiration of the truce, Edward ſent an army into Scotland, under the commandof John de Segrave. This general divided his troops into three bodies; but, keeping them ſo far diſtant that they could not ſupport each other, they were all engaged and defeated in one day by the Scots; near Roſlin (ſee ROSL<hi rend="smallcaps">in).</hi> This, however, was the laſt ſucceſsful exploit of the Scots at this periods The pope deſerted them; and the king of France, concluded a peace with England, in which all mention of the Scots was induſtriouſly avoided; ſo that they were left alone to bear the whole weight of Edward’s reſentment, who now invaded their country in perſon with a mighty army. He met with no reſiſtance in his progreſs, except from the caſtle of Brechin, which was commanded by Thomas Maul, a brave and experienced officer. He held out for 20 days againſt the whole power of the Engliſh army; but at laſt, being mortally wounded, the place capitulated.</p><p>From thence he proceeded northward, according to ſome hiſtorians, as far as Caithneſs. He then returned towards the ſouth, and wintered in Dunfermline. In that place there was an abbey of the Benedictine order; a building ſo ſpacious, that, according to an Engliſh hiſtorian, three ſovereign princes with all their retinue might have been lodged conveniently within its precincts. Here the Scottiſh nobles ſometimes held their aſſemblies. The Engliſh ſoldiers utterly demoliſhed this magnificent fabric. </p><p>The only fortreſs that remained in the poſſeſſion of the Scots was the caſtle of Stirling, where Sir William Oliphant commanded. To protect this ſingle place of refuge, Cornyn aſſembled all his forces. He poſted his army on the ſouth bank of the river, in the neighbourhood of Stirling, there to make the laſt ſtand for the national liberty. The Scots fondly imagined, that Edward would attempt to force the paſſage, as the impetuous Creſſingham had attempted in circumſtances not diſſimilar. But the prudence of Edward fruſtrated their expectations. Having diſcovered a ford at ſome diſtance, he croſſed the river at the head of his wſhole cavalry. The Scots gave way, and diſperſed themſelves.</p><p>All reſources but their own courage had long failed them; that laſt reſource failed them; now, and they haſtened to conciliate the favour of the conqueror. Previous to this, Bruce had ſurrendered himſelf to John de St John, the Engliſh warden. Comyn and his followers now ſubmitted to Edward. They ſtipulated for their lives, liberties, and eſtates: reſerving always to Edward the power of inflicting pecuniary mulcts on them as he ſhould ſee fit.</p><p>From the general conditions of this capitulation, the following perſons were excepted: Wiſheart biſhop of Glaſgow, the Steward, Sir John Soulis, David de Graham, Alexander de Lindeſay, Simon Fraſer, Thomas Bois, and Wallace. With reſpect to them, it was provided, that the biſhop of Glaſgow, the Steward, and Soulis, ſhould remain in exile for two years, and ſhould not paſs to the north of Trent; that Graham and Lindeſay ſhould be baniſhed from Scotland for ſix months; that Fraſer and Bois ſhould be baniſhed for three years from all the dominions of Edward, and ſhould not be permitted, during that ſpace, to repair to the territories of France. “As for William Wallace, it is agreed, that he ſhall render himſelf up at the will and mercy of our ſovereign lord the king, if it ſhall ſeem good to him.” Theſe were all the conditions that the Scottiſh nation ſtipulated for the mam who had vanquiſhed the Engliſh at Stirling, who had expelled them from Scotland, and who had once ſet his country free!</p><p>Amid this wreck of the national liberties, Wallace ſcorned ſubmiſſion. He lived a free man: a free man he reſolved to die. Fraſer, who had too oft complied with the times, now caught the ſame heroic ſentiments. But their endeavours to rouſe their countrymen were ſh vain. The ſeaſon of reſiſtance was paſt. Wallace perceived that there remained no more hope; and ſought out a place of concealment, where, eluding the vengeance of Edward, he might ſilently lament over his fallen country.</p><p>Edward aſſembled at St Andrew’s what is called a</p></body></text></TEI>