<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:51:07Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>and diſſembled with ſo much art, that the chancellor, imagining ſhe had become a convert to his cauſe, treated her with unbounded confidence, and ſuffered her at all hours to have free acceſs to her ſon’s perſon. Pretending that ſhe had vowed a pilgrimage to the white church of Buchan, ſhe recommended the care of her ſon’s perſon, till her return, to the chancellor, in the moſt pathetic and affectionate terms; but, in the mean time, ſhe ſecretly ſent him to Leith, packed up in a clothes- cheſt; and both ſhe and James were received at Stirling by the governor before the eſcape was known. As every thing had been managed in concert with Livingſton, he immediately called together his friends; and laying before them the tyrannical behaviour of, the chancellor, it was reſolved to beſiege him in the caſtle of Edinburgh, the queen promiſing to open her own granaries for the uſe of the army. The chancellor foreſaw the ſtorm that was likely to fall upon him, and ſought to prevent it by applying to the earl of Douglas. That haughty nobleman anſwered him in the terms already mentioned, and that he was preparing to exterminate both parties. The ſiege of Edinburgh caſtle being formed, the chancellor demanded a parley, and to have a perſonal interview with the governor; which the latter, who was no ſtranger to the ſentiments of Douglas, readily agreed to. Common danger united them in a common cauſe; and the chancellor reſigning to the other the cuſtody of the caſtle and the king’s perſon, with the higheſt profeſſions of duty and loyalty, the two competitors ſwore an inviolable friendſhip for each other. Next day the king cemented their union, by confirming both of them in their reſpective charges.</p><p>The lawleſs example of the earl of Douglas encouraged the other great landholders to gratify their private animoſities, ſometimes at the expence of their honour as well as their humanity. A family-difference happened between Sir Allan Stuart of Darnley, and Thomas Boyd of Kilmarnock; but it was concluded that both parties ſhould come to a peaceable agreement at Polmaiſthorn, between Linlithgow and Falkirk, where Stuart was treacherouſly murdered by his enemy. Stuart’s death was revenged by his brother, Sir Alexander Stuart of Beilmouth, who challenged Boyd to a pitched battle, the principals being attended by a retinue which carried the reſemblance of ſmall armies. The conflict was fierce and bloody, each party retiring in its turn, and charging with freſh fury; but at laſt victory declared itſelf for Stuart, the braveſt of Boyd’s attendants being cut off in the field. About this time, the iſlanders, under two of their chieftains, Lauchlan Maclean and Murdoc Gibſon, notorious freebooters, invaded Scotland, and ravaged the province of Lenox with fire and ſword. They were oppoſed by John Colquhoun of Lrrſs, whom they ſlew, ſome ſay treacherouſly, and others, in an engagement at Lochlomond, near Inchmartin. After this, the robbers grew more outrageous than ever, not only filling all the neighbouring country with rapine, but murdering the aged, infants, and the defenceleſs of both ſexes. At laſt, all the labouring hands in the kingdom being engaged in domeſtic broils, none were left for agriculture; and a dreadful famine enſued, which was attended, as uſual, by a peſtilence. James was now about ten years of age; and the wiſeſt part of the kingdom agreed, that</p><p>the public diſtreſſes were owing to a total diſreſpect of the royal authority. The young earl of Douglas never had fewer than 1000, and ſometimes 2000 horſe in his train; ſo that none was found hardy enough to contract him. He pretended to be independent of the king and his courts of law; that he had a right of judicature upon his own large eſtates; and that he was entitled to the exerciſe of royal power. In conſequence of this he iſſued his orders, gave protections to thieves and murderers, affected to brave the king, made knights, and, according to ſome writers, even noblemen, of his own dependents, with a power of fitting in parliament.</p><p>The queen-mother was not wholly guiltleſs of thoſe abuſes. She had fallen in love with and married Sir Janies Stuart, who was commonly called the <hi rend="italic">Black Knight oſ Lorn,</hi> brother to the lord of that title, and a deſcendant of the houſe of Darnley. Affection for her huſband cauſed her to renew her political intrigues; and not finding a ready compliance in the governor, her intereſt inclined towards the party of the Douglaſſes. The governor ſought to ſtrengthen his authority by reſtoring the exerciſe of the civil power, and the reverence due to the perſon of the ſovereign.</p><p>The conduct of the lord Callendar was in many rejects not ſo dtfenſible, either as to prudence or policy. When the queen expreſſed her inclination . that her huſhand might be admitted to ſome part of the adminiſtration, the governor threw both him and his brother the lord Lorn into priſon, on a charge of indutiful practices againſt the ſtate, and abetting the earl of Douglas in his enormities. The queen, taking fire at her huſhand’s impriſonment, was herſelf confined in a mean apartment within the caſtle of Stirling; and a convention of the ſtates was called, to judge in what manner ſhe was to be proceeded againſt. The cafe was unprecedented and difficult; nor can we believe the governor would have carried matters to ſuch extremity, had he not had ſtrong evidences of her illegal behaviour. She was even obliged to diſſemble her reſentment, by making an open profeſſion before the ſtates, that ſhe had always been entirely innocent of her huſband’s practices, and that ſhe would for the future behave as a peaceable and dutiful ſubject to the laws and the ſovereign. Upon making this purgation (as Lindſay calls it), ſhe was releaſed, as alſo her huſband and his brother, being bailed by the chancellor and the lord Gordon, who became fureties for their good behaviour in the penalty of 40c0 merks. The governor was afterwards accuſed of many arbitrary and partial acts of power: and indeed, if we conſider his ſituation, and the violence of the parties which then divided Scotland, it was ahnoſt impoſſible, conſiſtentlywith his own ſafety, to have exerted the virtues either of patriotiſm or moderation.</p><p>The chancellor was exceedingly vexed at the ſmall regard which the governor paid to his perſon and dignity, and ſecretly connected himſelf with the queen-mother; but in the mean time he remained at Edinburgh. The king and his mother continued all this time at Stirling; where the governor, on pretence of conſulting the public ſafety, and that of the king’s perſon, maintained a ſtrong guard, part of which attended James in his juvenile exercises and diverſions. The queen-mother did not fail to repreſent this to her</p></body></text></TEI>