<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T21:15:58Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>an entrance pavilion serving as town hall and the richly decorated façade of the church, both dating from the 17th century.</p><p>St Amand owes its name to St Amand, bishop of Tongres, who founded a monastery here in the 7th century. The abbey was laid waste by the Normans in 882 and by the count of Hainaut in 1340. The town was captured by Mary of Burgundy in 1477, by the count of Ligne, Charles V.’s lieutenant, in 1521, and finally in 1667 by the French. In 1793 St Amand was the headquarters of General Dumouriez in revolt against the Republican government.</p><p>ST-AMAND-MONT-ROND, a town of central France, capital of an arrondissement in the department of Cher, 39 m. S. by E. of Bourges on the railway to Montluçon. Pop. (1906), 7711. The town stands at the foot of the hill of Mont-Rond on the right bank of the Cher, at its confluence with the Marmande and on the canal of Berry. A church of the period of transition from the Romanesque to Gothic style and several old houses are the more interesting buildings. The beautiful château of Meillant, built from 1500 to 1510 by the admiral Charles of Amboise, is 5½ m. from St Amand; and the abbey of Noirlac, a fine type of Cistercian abbey with a 12th-century church, is 2½ m. from the town.</p><p>The town grew up round a monastery founded by St Amand, a follower of St Columban, in the 7th century. Its ruined stronghold, on the hill of Mont-Rond, was of importance in the middle ages, and during the Fronde, when it belonged to the great Condé, was a centre of resistance to the royal troops, by whom it was taken after a siege of eleven months in 1652. It was for a time the property of Sully, who retired to it under the regency of Marie de' Medici.</p><p>SAINT-AMANT, MARC ANTOINE DE GÉRARD, <hi rend="smallcaps">Sieur de </hi>(1594-1661), French poet, was born near Rouen in the year 1594. His father was a merchant who had, according to his son’s account, been a sailor and had commanded for 22 years <hi rend="italic">une escadre de la reine Êlizabeth—</hi>a vague statement that lacks confirmation. The son obtained a patent of nobility, and attached himself to different great noblemen—the duc de Retz and the comte d’Harcourt among others. He saw military service and sojourned at different times in Italy, in England— a sojourn which provoked from him a violent poetical attack on the country, <hi rend="italic">Albion</hi> (1643)—in Poland, where he held a court appointment for two years, and elsewhere. Saint-Amant’s later years were spent in France; and he died at Paris on the 29th of December 1661.</p><p>Saint-Amant has left a not inconsiderable body of poetry. His <hi rend="italic">Albion</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Rome ridicule</hi> set the fashion of the burlesque poem, a form in which he was excelled by his follower Paul Scarron. In his later years he devoted himself to serious subjects and produced an epic, <hi rend="italic">Moïse sauvé</hi> (1653). His best work consists of Bacchan- alian songs, his <hi rend="italic">Débauche</hi> being one of the most remarkable convivial poems of its kind.</p><p>The standard edition is that in the <hi rend="italic">Bibliothèque Elzévirienne,</hi> by M. C. L. Livet (2 vols. Paris, 1855).</p><p>SAINT ANDRÉ, ANDRÉ JEANBON (1749-1813), French revolutionist, was born at Montauban (Tam-et-Garonne) on the 25th of February 1749, the son of a fuller. Although his father was a Protestant, St André was brought up by the Jesuits at Marseilles and took orders. He turned Protestant, however, and became pastor at Castras and afterwards at Montauban. The proclamation of liberty of worship made him a supporter of the Revolution, and he was sent as deputy to the Convention by the department of Lot. He sat on the Mountain, voted for the death of Louis XVI. and opposed the punishment of the authors of the September massacres. In July 1793 he was president of the Convention, entered the Committee of Public Safety the same month and was sent on mission to the Armies of the East. On the 20th of September 1793 he obtained a vote of one hundred million francs for constructing vessels, and from September 1793 to January 1794 reorganized the military harbours of Brest and Cherbourg. In May 1794 he took part with Admiral Villaret de Joyeuse in a fight with the English. Finally, after a mission in the south, which lasted from July 1794 to March 1795 and in which he showed great moderation, he was arrested on the 28th of May 1795, but was released by the amnesty of the year IV. He was then appointed consul at Algiers and Smyrna (1798), was kept prisoner by the Turks for three years, and subsequently became prefect of the department of Mont-Tonnerre (1801) and commissary-general of the three</p><p>departments on the left bank of the Rhine. He died at Mainz on the 10th of December 1813.</p><p>See Lévy-Schneider, <hi rend="italic">Le Conventionnel Jeanbon St André</hi> (Paris, 1901).</p><p>SAINT ANDRÉ. JACQUES D’ALBON, <hi rend="smallcaps">Seigneur de (</hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps">c</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">.</hi> 1505- 1562), French soldier and favourite of Henry II. of France. He was made marshal of France, governor of Lyonnais and ambassador in England. He served with great bravery against the emperor Charles V. in 1552. In 1557 he was taken prisoner at the battle of Saint Quentin, but was released the following year, and took part in negotiating the peace of Cateau-Cam- brésis. After the death of Francis II. he formed in 1561 with the constable de Montmorency and Francis, duke of Guise, an alliance known as “ the triumvirate ” against the Protestants and the queen-mother. He perished at the battle of Dreux by the hand of a private enemy.</p><p>ST ANDREWS, a city, royal burgh, university town and seaport of Fifeshire, Scotland. Pop. (1901), 7621. It is situated on a bay of the North Sea, 12½ m. S.È. of Dundee by the North British railway, via Leuchars junction. It occupies a plateau of sandstone rock about 50 ft. high, on the north breaking off in precipitous cliffs in which the sea has worn numerous caves The Eden enters St Andrews Bay to the north-west of the Links; and Kinness Burn, skirting the south side of the town, flows into the harbour. Almost the whole activity of St Andrews is centred in education and golf. There are a few small businesses, however, such as brewing, tanning, shipping and fishing. The harbour, which is somewhat difficult of access, is protected by a pier 630 ft. long. The city has been called the “ Mecca of Golf,” partly because the Royal and Ancient Golf Club, founded in 1754, is the legislative authority of the game, and partly because its beautiful links—acquired by the town in 1894 and containing three courses—rank amongst the finest in the world. For the sake of the game, the bracing air and the bathing which the sandy beach of its bay affords, visitors are attracted to St Andrews in great numbers. The chief modern buildings include the town hall, the Templars’ Hall, the Volunteer Hall, the Gibson Hospital, the Memorial Cottage Hospital, the Marine Biological Station (erected by Dr C. H. Gatty and opened in 1896), the Library and the Golf Club House, erected in 1853. The city was never surrounded by walls, and of its ancient gates the West Port only remains. The Martyrs’ Memorial, erected to the honour of Patrick Hamilton, George Wishart, and other martyrs of the Reformation epoch, stands at the west end of the Scores on a cliff overlooking the sea.</p><p>The cathedral originated partly in the priory of Canons Regular founded by Bishop Robert (1122-1159). At the end of the 17th century some of the priory buildings were still entire and considerable remains of others existed, but nearly all traces have now disappeared, except portions of the priory wall and the archways, known as the Pends. The wall is about three-quarters of a mile long, and bears turrets at intervals. The 3rd marquis of Bute undertook the restoration of the priory, but the work was interrupted by his death in 19oo. The cathedral was founded by Bishop Arnold (1159-1162), to supply more ample accommodation than was afforded by the church of St Regulus. Of this church in the Romanesque style, probably dating from the 10th century, there remain the square tower, 108 ft. in height, and the choir, of very diminutive proportions. On a plan of the town, about 153o, a chancel appears, and on seals affixed to the city and college charters there are representations of other build- ings attached. The cathedral was constructed in the form of a Latin cross, the total length inside the walls being 355 ft., the length of the nave 200 ft., of the choir and lateral aisles 62 ft. and of the lady chapel at the eastern extremity 50 ft. The width at the transepts was 166 Jt. and of the nave and choir 62 ft. The building was finished in the time of Bishop Lamberton (1297-1328), and was dedicated on the 5th of July 1318, the ceremony being witnessed by Robert Bruce. When entire it had, besides a central tower, six turrets, of which two at the east and one of the two at the west extremity, rising to a height of 100 ft., remain. The building was partly destroyed by fire in 1378, and the restoration and further embellishment were completed in 1440. It was stripped of its altars and images in 1559. It is believed that about the end of the 16th century the central tower gave way, carrying with it the north wall. Afterwards large portions of the ruins were taken away for building purposes, and nothing was done to preserve them until 1826. Since then it has been tended with scrupulous care, an interesting feature being the cutting out of the ground-plan in the turf. The principal portions extant, partly Norman and partly Early English, are the</p></body></text></TEI>