<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r03-0480-02" facs="gri_33125011196389_0486.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>ROOK</label>
in ornithology. See Corvus.</p><p>Rooks are very deſtructive of corn, eſpecially of wheat. Theyſearch out the lands where it is fown, and watching them more carefully than the owners, they perceive when the ſeed firſt begins to ſhoot up its blade ; this is the time’of their feeding on it. They will not be at the pains of ſearching for it at random in the ſown land, for that is more trouble than fo ſmall a grain will requite them for : but as ſoon as theſe blade» appear, they are by them directed, without loſs of time or pains, to the places where the grains lie ; and in three or four days time they will root up ſuch' vaſt quantities, that a good crop is oſten thus deſtroyed in embryo. After a few days the wheat continuing to grow, its blades appear green above ground ; and then the time of danger from theſe birds is over ; for then the ſeeds are fo far robbed of their mealy matter, that they are of no value to that bird, and it will no longer give itſelf the trouble to deſtroy them.</p><p>Wheat that is ſown ſo early as to ſhoot up its green blades before the harveſt is all carried in, is in no danger from theſe birds ; becauſe while it is in a ſtate worth their ſearching for, the ſcattered corn in the harveſt fields is eaſier come at, and they feed wholly on this, neglecting the ſown grain. But as this cannot always be done, the farmers, to drive away theſe ravenous and miſchievous birds, dig holes in the ground and ſtick up the feathers of rooks in them, and hang up dead rooks on ſticks in ſeveral parts of the fields : but all this is of very little uſe ; for the living rooks will tear up the ground about the feathers, and under the dead ones, to ſteal the feed3. A much better way than either is to tear ſeveral rooks to pieces, and to ſeatter the pieces over the fields ; but this laſts but a little while, for the kites and other birds of prey ſoon carry off the pieces and feed upon them. A gun is a good remedy</p>
<pb xml:id="eb03-16-r03-0481" facs="gri_33125011196389_0487.tif"/>
<p><hi rend="sup">-</hi> while the perſon who has it is preſent ; but as ſoon as he is gone, they will return with redoubled vigour to the field and tear up every thing before them.</p><p>The beſt remedy the farmer has is to watch well the time of the corn’s being in the condition in which they feed upon it ; and as this laſts only a few days, he ſhould keep a boy in conſtant pay to watch the field from day-break till the duſk of the evening. Every time they ſettle upon the ground to ſly over it, the boy is to holloa, and throw up a dead rook into the air : this will always make them riſe ; and by degrees they will be ſo tired of this conſtant diſturbance, that they will ſeek out other places of preying, and will leave the ground even before the time of the corn’s being unfit for them. The reaſon of their riling at the toſſing up of their dead fellow creature is, that they are a bird extremely apprehenſive of danger, and they are always alarmed when one of their comrades riſes. They take this for the riſing of an out-bird, and all fly off at the fignal.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>