<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r03-0541-05" facs="gri_33125011196389_0547.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>RUBENS</label>
(Sir Peter Raul), the moſt eminent of the Flemiſh painters, was born in 15 77 ; but whether at Antwerp or Cologne it is not eaſy to determine. His father, who was a counſellor in the ſenate of Antwerp, had been forced by the civil wars to ſeek refuge in Cologne, and during his reſidence there Rubens is commonly ſaid to have been born.</p><p>The genius of Rubens, wlſtch began to unfold itſelf in his earlieſt years, was cultivated with peculiar care, and embelliſhed with every branch of claſſical and polite literature.</p><p>He ſoon diſcovered a ſtrong inclination for deſigning; and uſed to amuſe himſelf with that employment in his leiſure hours, while the reſt of his time was devoted to other ſtudies. His mother, perceiving the bias of her ſon, permitted him to attend the inſtructions of Tobias· Verhaecht a painter of architecture and landſcape. He next became the pupil of Adam Van Oort, but lie ſoon found that the abilities of this maſter were inſuſſicient to anſwer his elevated ideas. His ſurly temper too was</p><p>diſguſtful to Rubens, whoſe natural diſpoſition was model! and amiable. .</p><p>Anxious to find an artiſt whoſe genius and diſpofi. tſens were congenial with his own, he became the di-ſeiple of Octavio Van Veen, generally known by the name of Otho Venius, a painter of ſingular merit, and who was not only ſldlled in the principles of his art, but alſo diſtinguiſhed for learning and other accompliſh-ments. Between the maſter and ſeholar a remarkable ſimilarſty appeared in temper and inclination ; indeed, iιι the whole turn of their »finds. It was this congeniality of ſentiments which animated Rubens with that ardent paſſion for the art of painting which at length determined him to purſue it as a proſeſſion. From this time he gave up his whole mind to it ; and ſo ſucceſsful were his exertions, that he ſoon equalled his maſter.</p><p>In order to arrive at that perfection which he already beheld in idea, it became requifite to ſtudy the productions of the moſt eminent artiſts. For this purpoſe he travelled through Italy, viſiting the moſt valuable collections of paintings and antique ſtatues with which that country abounds.</p><p>Sandrart, who was intimately acquainted with Rubens, informs us, that he was recommended in the moſt honourable manner to the duke of Mantua by the archduke Albert, who had witneſſed his talents in the finiſh-ing of ſome fine paintings deſigned for his own palace. At Mantua he was received by the duke with the moſt flattering marks of diſtinction, and had'opportunities of improving himſelf which he did not neglect. Here he carefully ſtudied the works of Julio Romano. He next viſited Rome, where he had an opportunity of examining the productions of Raphael. The paintings of Titian and Paolo Veroneſe called him to Venice, where he accompliſhed himſelf in the art of colouring.</p><p>He continued in Italy ſeven years. At length receiving intelligence that his mother was taken ill, he haſtened to Antwerp ∙. but hi's filial affection was not gratified with a light of her; ſhe died before his arrival. He married ſoon after ; but his wife dying at the end' of four years, he retired from Antwerp for ſome time,, and endeavoured to ſoothe his melancholy by a journey to Holland. At Utrecht he viſited Hurtort, for whom he had a great value. »</p><p>The tame of Rubens was now ſpread over Europe. He was invited by Mary of Medicis queen of. Henry IV. of France to Râris, where he painted the galleries in the palace of Luxemburg. Theſe form a ſeries of' paintings which delineate the hiſtory of Mary ; and af-foι d a convincing proof how well qualified he was to excel in allegorical and emblematical compo tions. While at Paris he became acquainted with the duke of Buckingham, who was-ſo taken with his great talents and accompliſhments, that he judged him well qualified to explain to Iſabella, the wife oſ Albeit the archduke, the cauſe of the nriſunderſtanding which had taken place between the courts of England and Spain. In this employment Rubens, acquitted himſelf with ſuch propriety, that Iſabella appointed him envoy' to the king oſ Spain, with a commiſſion to propoſe terms of peace, and to bring back the inſtructions of that monarch. Philip was no leſs captivated with Rubens; He conferred on him the honour of knighthood, and made him ſecretary to his privy council. Rubens</p>
<pb xml:id="eb03-16-r03-0542" facs="gri_33125011196389_0548.tif"/>
<p>returned to Bruſſels, and thence paffed over into Eng-' land in 1630 with a commiſſion from the Catholic king to negociate a peace between the two crowns. He was ſucceſsful in his negociation, and a treaty was concluded. Charles I. who then filled the Britiſh throne, could not receive Rubens in a public character on ac* count of his proſeſſion ; nevertheleſs, he treated him with every mark of reſpect. Having engaged him to paint ſome of the apartments of Whitehall, he not only gave him a handſome ſum of money, but, as an acknowledgment of his merit, created him a knight ; and the duke of Buckingham, his friend and patron, purchaſed</p><p>of him a collection of pictures, ſtatues, medals, and antiques, with the ſum of L. 10,000.</p><p>He returned to Spain, where be was magnificently honoured and rewarded for his ſervices. He was created a gentleman of ⅛the king’s bedchamber, and named ſecretary to the council of ſtate in the Netherlands. Rubens, however, did not lay aſide his proſeſſion. He returned to Antwerp, where he married a ſecond wife called <hi rend="italic">Helena Forment,</hi> who, being an eminent beauty, helped him much in the figures of his women. He died on 30th May 1640, in the 63d year of his age ; leaving vaſt riches to his children. Albert his eldeſt ſon ſucceeded him in the office of ſecretary of ſtate in Flan-ders.</p><p>As Rubens was poſſeſſed of all the ornaments and advantages that render a man worthy to be eſteemed or courted, he was always treated as a perſon of conſequence. His figure was noble, his manners engaging, and his converſation lively ; his learning was univerſal. Though his favourite ſtudy muſt have occupied him much, yet he found time to read the works of the moſt celebrated authors, and eſpecially the poets. He ſpoke ſeveral languages perfectly, and was an excellent ſtates-man.</p><p>His houſe at Antwerp was enriched with everything in the arts that was rare and valuable. It contained one ſpacious apartment, in imitation of the rotunda at Rome, adorned with a choice collection of pictures which he had purchaſed in Italy; part of which he fold to the duke of Buckingham.</p><p>His genius qualified him to excel equally in every thing that can enter into the compoſition of a picture. His invention was ſo fertile, that, if he had occaſion to paint the ſame ſubject ſeveral times, his imagination always ſupplied him with ſomething ſtriking and new. The attitudes of his figures are natural and varied, the carriage of the head is peculiarly graceful, and his ex-preffion noble and animated.</p><p>He is by all allowed to have carried the art of colouring to its higheſt pitch; he underſtood ſo thoroughly the true principles of the chiaro-ſcuro, that he gave to his figures the utmoſt harmony, and a prominence reſembling real life. His pencil is mellowed, his ſtrokes bold and eaſy, his carnation glows with life, and his drapery is ſimple, but grand, broad, and hung with much ſkill.</p><p>The great excellence of Rubens appears in his grand compoſitions; for as they are to be viewed at a diſtance, he laid on a proper body of colours with uncommon boldneſs, and fixed all his tints in their proper places ; ſo that he never impaired their luſtre by breaking or torturing them ; but touched them in ſuch a manner as to give them a laſting force, beauty, and harmony.</p><p>It is generally allowed, that Rubens wanted correct-</p><p>neſs in drawing and deſigning ; ſome of his figures being heavy and too ſhort, and the limbs in ſome parts not being juſtly ſketched in the outline. Though he had ſpent ſeven years in Italy in ſtudying thoſe antiques by which other celebrated artiſts had modelled their taſte; though he had examined them with ſuch minute attention as not only to perceive their beauties, but to be qualified to deſcribe them in a Diſſertation which he wrote on that ſubject : yet he ſeems never to have diverted htm-ielſ oſ that heavy ſtyle of painting, which, being pe-culiar to his native country, he had inſenfibly acquired. The aſtoniſhing rapidity too with which he painted, made him fall into inaccuracies, from which thoſe works that he ſiniſhed with care are entirely exempted.</p><p>Among his finiſhed pieces may be mentioned the Crucifixion of Jeſus Chriſt between the two Thieves, which was very lately to be ſeen at Antwerp·; but of all his works the. paintings in the palace^of Luxemburg beſt diſplay his genius and his ſtyle.</p><p>It is the obſervation of Algarotti, that he was more moderate in his movements than Tintoretto, and more ſoft in his chiaro-ſcuro than Carravaggio ; but not ſo rich in his compoſitions, nor ſo light in his touches, as Paolo Veroneſe ; in his carnations leſs true than Titian, and leſs delicate than Vandyck. Yet he contrived to give his colours the utmoſt tranſparency and harmony, notwithſtanding the extraordinary deepneſs of them ; and he had a ſtrength and grandeur of ſtyle entirely his own.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>