<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r03-0548-03" facs="gri_33125011196389_0554.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>RUE</label>
in. botany. See RUTA.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Rue (Charles de la), a French orator and poet, was</hi></p><p>born at Paris in 1643. He was educated at the college of the Jeſuits, where he afterwards became a proſeſſor of humanity and rhetoric. At an early age his talent for poetry diſcloſed itſelf. In 1667, when he was only 24 years old, he compoſed a Latin poem on the conquests oſ Louis XIV. which was ſo much eſteemed by</p>
<pb xml:id="eb03-16-r03-0549" facs="gri_33125011196389_0555.tif"/>
<p>the celebrated Ret er Corneille, that he tranflated it into French, preſented it to the King, and at the fame time paſſed ſo high encomiums on the ſuperior merit of the original, that the author was received into ſhe favour of that monarch, and ever after treated byſhim wiſh Angular reſpect.</p><p>De la Rue, anxious to preach the goſpel to the Canadians, requeſted leave of abſence from his ſuperiors ; bμt having deſtined him for the pulpit, they refuſed to comply wiſh his requeſt. Accordingly he commenced preacher, and became one of the moſt eminent orators .of his age. In his diſeourſes he would probably have been too laviſh of his wit, if he had not been cautioned againſt it by a judicious courtier. “ Continue (ſaid he) to preach as you do. We will hear you with pleaſure as long as you reaſon wiſh us ; but avoid wit. We value the wit contained in two verſes of a ſong more than all that is contained in moſt of the fermons in Lent.”</p><p>Relpectιng the delivery of fermons, he entertained an opinion quite oppoſite to the eſtabliſhed practice of his countrymen. In France it was cuſtomary not to read fermons from ſhe pulpit, but to recite them from τnemoιy. TTιis he conſidered as a laborious taſk not compenſated by any advantages. On the contrary, he was of opinion that reading fermons was preferable.— The preacher, wuſh his diſcourſe before him, could read it w <hi rend="sup">r</hi> ith eaſe, free from that timidity and embar-raſſment which frequently attends the act of recollection ; and he would fave a conſiderable time which is •uſually ſpent in committing it to memory. In theſe ſentiment» many will not be diſpoſed to acquieſce : but, «without pretending to determine the queſtion, it may be aſſerted, that a ſermon, whether read Or recited, if ſpoken in a ſerious manner, and with proper inflections and tones of voice, will produce all ſhe effects, for which a ſermon is calculated.</p><p>De la Rue died at Paris on ſhe 27th of May 1725, at the age of 82.</p><p>He w <hi rend="sup">r</hi> as as amiable in ſociety as he w <hi rend="sup">,</hi> as venerable in the pulpit. His converſation was pleaſant and inſtruc-tive. His taſte and know ledge enabled him to converſe .with eaſe, and to expreſs himſelf with propriety on every ſubject. He charmed his ſuperiors by his wit, and his inferiors by his affability. Though living ainidſt ſhe buſtle of the world, he was always prepared for the ſo-iitude cf the cloſet and the retreat of the cloiſter. In ſhe pulpit he poured forth the ſineſt effufions of eloquence in the moſt animated and impreſſive manner.—-He publiſhed Panegyrics, Funeral Orations, and Sermons. His beſh ſermon is ſhat intitled <hi rend="italic">Des Calamités Publiques,</hi> and his moſt admired funeral oration was compoſed on the Prince of Luxemburg. There are alſo tragedies of his wτiting, both in Latin and French, which were approved by Corneille. He was one of thoſe who publiſhed editions of the claſſics for the uſe cf the Dauphin. Virgil, which fell to his ſhare, was publiſhed with notes, and a Life oſ the Poet, in 1675, 4t0, and is a valuable and uſeful edition.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>