<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r03-0536-03" facs="gri_33125011196389_0542.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>ROWE</label>
(Nicholas), deſcended of an ancient family in Devoriſhire, was born in 1673- He acquired a complete taſte of the claſſic authors under the fa r.ous Dr Buſhy in Weſtminſter ſchool; but poetry wao his early and darling ſtudy. His father, who was a lawyct, and de’ gned him for his own proſeſſion, entered him a ſtudent in the Middle Temple He made remarkable advances in the ſtudy of the law ; but the love of the belles lettres, and of poetry in particular, ſtopt him in h’s career. His firſt tragedy, the Ambitious Stepmother, meeting with univerſal applauſe, he laid aſide all thoughts of riſing by the law. He afterward compoſed ſeveral tragedies ; but that which he valued himſelf moſt upon, was his Tame. lane. The others are, the <hi rend="italic">Fair Penitent Uiffs,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Royal Cοnv rt, Jane Shore,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Lady J .r&gt;e G' eν.</hi> He alſo wrote a poem called the <hi rend="italic">Piter,</hi> and ſeveral poems upon different ſubjects, which have been publiſhed under the title of Mifcellane0u3 Works, in one volume, as his dramatic works have been in two. Rowe is chiefly to be conſidered (Dr Johnſon ob-ſerves) in the light of a tragic writer and a tranſlator. In his attempt at comedy, he failed ſo ignominiouſly, that his Biter is not inſerted in his works ; and his oc-ca onal poems and ſhort compofitions are rarely worthy of either praiſe or cenſure, for they ſeem the ca-ſual ſports of a mind ſeek ng rather to amuſe its leiſure $han to exerciſe its powers. In the conſtruction of his dramas there is not much art ; he is not a nice obſerver of the unities. He extends time, and varies place, as his convenience requires. To vary the place is not (in the opinion oſ the learned critic from whom theſe ob-ſervations are borrowed) any violation of nature, if the change be made between the acts ; for it is no leſs eaſy for the ſpectator to ſuppoſe himſelf at Athens in the ſecond act, than at Thebes in the ſirſt ; but to change the ſcent, as is done by Rowe in the middle of an act, is to add more acts to the play, lmce an act is ſo much of the bufineſs as is tranſacted without interruption. Rowe, by this licence, eaſily extricates him-ſelt from difficulties ; as in Lady Jane Gray, when we have been terrified with all the dreadful pomp of public execution, and are wondering how the heroine or the poet will proceed, no ſooner has Jane pronounced ſome prophetic rhimes, than—paſs and be gone—the ſcene cloſes, and Pembroke and Gardiner are ruined out upon the ſtage. I know not (ſays Dr Johnſon) that there can be found in his plays any deep ſearch into nature, any accurate diſcriminations of kindred qualities, or nice diſplay of paſſion in its progreſs ; all is general and undefined. Nor does he much intereſt or affect the auditor, except in Jane Shore, who is always ſeen and heard writh pity. Alicia is a character of empty noiſe, with no reſemblairce to real ſorrow or to natural madneſs. Whence then -has Rowe his reputation ? From the rea-ſonableneſs and propriety of ſome ot his ſcenes, from the elegance of his diction, and the ſuavity of his verſe. He ſeldom moves either pity or terror, but he often elevates the ſentiment; he ſeldom pierces the breaſt, but he always delights the ear, and often improves the</p>
<pb xml:id="eb03-16-r03-0537" facs="gri_33125011196389_0543.tif"/>
<p>underſtanding. Being a great admirer of Shakeſpeare, he gave the public an edition of his plays ; to which he prefixed an account of that great man’s life. But the moſt conſiderable of Mr Rowe’s performances was a tranſlation of Lucan’s <hi rend="italic">PharſaHa,</hi> which he juſt lived to finiſh, but not to publiſh ; for it did not appear in print till r728, ten years after his death.</p><p>Meanwhile, the love of poetry and books did not make him unfit for buſineſs ; for nobody applied cloſer to it when occaſion required. The Duke of Queen ſ-berry, when ſecretary of ſtate, made him ſecretary for public affairs. After the Duke’s death, all avenues were ſtopped to his preferment ; and during the reſt of Queen Anne’s reign he paffed his time with the Muſes and his books. A ſtory, indeed, is told of him, which ſhows that he had ſome acquaintance with her miniſters. It is ſaid, that he went one day to pay his court to the lord treaſurer Oxford, whβ aſked him, “If he under-ftood Spaniſh well ?” He anſwered, “ No but thinking that his Lordſhip might intend to ſend him into Spain on ſome honourable commiſſion, he preſently added, “ that he did not doubt but he could ſhortly be able both to underſtand and to ſpeak it.” The earl approving what he ſaid, Rowe took his leave ; and, retiring a few weeks to learn the language, waited again on the Earl to acquaint him with it. His Lordſhip aſking him, “ If he was ſure he underſtood it thoroughly ?” and Rowe affirming that he did, “ How happy are you, Mr Rowe,” ſaid the Earl, “ that you can have the pleaſure of reading and underſtanding the Hiſtory of Don Quixote in the original!” On the acceſſion of George I. he was made poet laureat, and one of the land ſurveyors of the cuſtoms in the port of London. The prince of Wales conferred on him the clerkſhip of his council ; and the Lord Chancellor Parker made him his ſecretary for the preſentations. He did not enjoy theſe promotions long ; for he died Dec. 6. 1718, in his 45th year.</p><p>Mr Rowe was twice married, had a ſon by his firſt wife, and a daughter by his ſecond. He was a handſome, genteel man ; and his mind was as amiable as his perſon. He lived beloved ; and at his death had the honour to be lamented by Mr Pope, in an epitaph which is printed in Pope’s works, although it was not affixed on Mr Rowe’s monument in Weſtminſter'ab-bey, where he was interred in the poet’s corner, oppoſite to Chaucer.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Rowe (Eliſabeth), an Engliſh lady, eminent for her excellent writings both in proſe and verſe, born at Ilcheſter in Somerſetſhire in 1647, was the daughter of worthy parents, Mr Walter Singer and Mrs Eliſabeth Portnel. She received the firſt ſerious impreſſions of religion as ſoon as ſhe was capable of it. There being a great affinity between painting and poetry, this lady, who had a vein for the one, naturally had a taſte for the other. She was alſo very fond of muſic ; chiefly of the grave and ſolemn kind, as beſt ſuited to the grandeur of her ſentiments and the ſublimity of her devotion. But poetry was her favourite employment, her diſtinguiſhing excellence. So prevalent was her genius this way, that her proſe is all poetical. In 1696, a collection of her poems was publiſhed at the deſire of two friends. Pier paraphraſe on the xxxviiith chapter of Job was written at the requeſt of biſhop Ken. She had no other tutor for the French and Italian languages than the honourable Mr Thynne, who willingly</hi> took the taſk upon himſelf. Her ſhining merit, with the charms oſ her perſon and converſation, had procured her a great many admirers. Among others, it is ſaid, the famous Mr Prior made his addreſſes to her. But Mr Thomas Rowe was to be the happy man. This gentleman was honourably deſcended : and his ſuperior genius, and ſhſatiable thirſt after knowledge, were con-ſpicuous in his earlieſt years. He had formed a defm∙n to compile the lives of all the illuſtrious perſons in antiquity omitted by Plutarch ; which, indeed, he partly executed. Eight lives were publiſhed ſince his deceaſe. They were tranſlated into French by the abbs Bellen-geτ in j 734. He ſpoke with eaſe and fluency ; had a frank and benevolent temper, an inexhauſtible fund of wit, and a communicative diſpoſition. Such was the man who, charmed with the perſon, character, and writings, of our authoreſs, married her in 17 1 o, and made it his ſttidy to repay the felicity with which ſhe crowned his life. Too intenſe an application to ſtudy, beyond what the delicacy of his frame would bear, broke his health, and threw him into a conſumption, which put a period to his valuable life in May 1 715, when he was but juſt paſt the 28th year of his age. Mrs Rowe wrote a beautiful elegy on his death ; and continued to the laſt moments of her life to expreſs the higheſt veneration and affection ſor his memory. As ſoon after his deceaſe as her affairs would permit, ſhe indulged her inclination for ſolitude, by retiring to Frome, in Somerſetſhire, in the neighbourhood of which place the greateſt part of her eſtate lay. In this receſs ſt was tlιat ſhe compoſed the moſt celebrated of her works, Friendſhip in Death, and the Letters Moral and Entertaining. In 1736, ſhe publiſhed, the Hiſtory of Joſepli ; a poem which ſhe had written in her younger years. She did not long ſurvive this publication ; for ſhe died of an apoplexy, as was ſuppoſed, Feb. 20. 1736-7. In her cabinet were found letters to ſeveral of her friends, which ſhe had ordered to be delivered immediately after her deceaſe. The Rev. Dr Iſaac Wâtts, agreeably to her requeſt, reviſed and publiſhed her devotions in 1737, under the title of Devout Exerciſes oſ the Heart in Meditation and Soliloquy, Praiſe and Prayer; and, in 1739, her Miſcellaneous Works, in proſe and verſe, were publiſhed in 2 vols 8vo, with an account oſ her life and writings prefixed.</p><p>As to her perſon, ſhe was not a regular beauty, yet poſſeſſed a large ſhare of the charms of her ſex. She was of a moderate ſtature, her hair of a fine colour, her eyes of a darkiſh grey inclining ta blue, and full of fire. Her complexion was very fair, and a natural bluſh glowed in her cheeks. She ſpoke gracefully ; her voice was exceedingly ſweet and harmonious ; and ſhe had a ſoftneſs in her aſpect which inſpired love, yet not witl&gt;-out ſome mixture of that awe and veneration which di^ ſtinguiſhed ſenſe and virtue, apparent in the countenance, are wont to create.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>