<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r03-0576-05" facs="gri_33125011196389_0582.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>RUTA</label>, rue : A genus of the monogynia order, belonging to the decandria claſs of plants ; and in the natural method ranking under the 26th order, <hi rend="italic">Multifi-liqu&lt;r.</hi> The calyx is quinquepartite; the petals concave; the receptacle ſurrounded with 1 o melliferous pores ; the capſule is lobed. In ſome flowers, a fifth part of the number is excluded. There are ſeveral ſpecies ; of which the moſt remarkable is the horten fis, or common broad-leaved garden rue, which has been long cultivated for medicinal uſe. This riſes with a ſhrubby ſtalk to the height of five or ſix feet, ſending out branches on every ſide, garniſhed with decompounded leaves, whoſe ſmall lobes are wedge-ſhaped, of a grey colour, and have a ſtrong odour. The flowers are produced at the end of the branches in bunches almoſt in the form of umbels : they are compoſed of four yellow concave petals which are cut on their edges, and eight yellow ſtamina which are longer than the petals, terminated by roundiſh ſummits. The germen becomes a roundiſh capſule, with four lobes punched full of holes containing rough black ſeeds.</p><p>Rue has a ſtrong ungrateful fmell, and a bitteriſh penetrating taſte : the leaves, when full of vigour, are extremely acid, inſomuch as to inflame and bliſter the ſkin, if much handled. With regard to their medicinal virtues, they are powerfully ſtimulating, attenuating, and detergent ; and hence, in cold phlegmatic habits, they quicken the circulation, diſſolve tenacious juices, open obſtructions of the excretory glands, and promote the fluid ſecretions. The writers on the materia mεdi-ca in general have entertained a very high opinion of the virtues of this plant. Boerhaave is full of its praiſes ; particularly of the eſſential oil, aud the diſtil-led water cohobated or re-diſtilſed ſeveral times from freſh parcels of the herb. Alter extravagantly commending other waters prepared in this manner, he adds, with regard to that of rue, that the greateſt commendations he can bellow upon it fall ſhort of its merit : “ What medicine (lays he) can be more efficacious for promoting ſweat and perſpiration, for the cure of the hyſteric paſſion and of epilepſies, and for expelling poiſon ?” Whatever ſervice rue may be of in the two laſt caſes, it undoubtedly has its uſe in the others : the cohobated water, however, is not the moſt efficacious preparation of it. An extract made by rectified ſpirit contains in a ſmall compaſs the whole virtues of the rue; this menſtruum taking up by infufion all the pungency and flavour of the plant, and elevating nothing in diſtillation. With water, its peculiar flavour and warmth ariſe ; the bitterneſs, and a conſiderable ſhare of the pungency, remaining behind.</p><p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps">Ruta</hi> Baga,</hi> or Swediſh turnip. See Husbandry,</p><p>p. 761.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>