<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/>         </publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb09-20-r01-0295-03" facs="encyclopediabrit20newyrich_raw_0313.jp2" type="entry">

<p><label>RAVEN</label>
(Anglo-Saxon <hi rend="italic">Hrsefn,</hi> Icelandic <hi rend="italic">Hrafn,</hi> Danish <hi rend="italic">Ravn,</hi> Dutch <hi rend="italic">Raaf</hi> , German <hi rend="italic">Rabe),</hi> the largest of the Birds of the Order <hi rend="italic">Passeres ·,</hi> and, as already shewn <hi rend="smallcaps">(Ornithology,</hi> vol. xviii. p. 49), probably the most highly developed of all Birds.</p><p>Quick-sighted, sagacious, and bold, it must have followed the prehistoric fisher and hunter, and generally without molestation from them, to prey on the refuse of their spoils, just as it now waits, with the same intent, on the movements of their successors ; while it must have likewise attended the earliest herdsmen, who could not have regarded it with equal indifference, since its now notorious character for attacking and putting to death a weakly animal was doubtless in those days manifested. Yet the Raven is no mere dependant upon man, being always able to get a living for itself; and moreover a sentiment of veneration or superstition has from very remote ages and among many races of men attached to it—a sentiment so strong as often to overcome the feeling of distrust not to say of hatred which its deeds inspired, and, though rapidly decreasing, even to survive in some places until the present day. There is no need to dwell on the association of this bird with well-known characters of history sacred or profane—Noah or Elijah, Odin or Flokki, the last of whom by its means discovered Iceland. The Raven is even said to have played its part in the mythology of the Red Indian ; and none can wonder that all this should be so, since, wherever it occurs and more especially wherever it is numerous, as in ancient times and in thinly peopled countries it must have been, its size, appearance, and fearless habits would be sure to attract especial attention. Nor has this attention wholly ceased with the advance of enlightenment, for both in prose and verse, from the time of Shakespeare to that of Poe and Dickens, the Raven has often figured, and generally without the amount of misrepresentation which is the fate of most animals which celebrated writers condescend to notice. Notwithstanding all this, however, the Raven has now fallen upon evil days. The superstitious reverence with which it was once regarded has all but vanished and has been very generally succeeded by persecution, which in many districts has produced actual extirpation, so that it is threatened with extinction, save in the wildest and most unpeopled districts. <note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="1"> That all lovers of nature should take what steps they can to arrest this sad fate is a belief which the present writer fully holds. Without attempting to deny the loss which in some cases is inflicted upon the rearers of cattle by Ravens, it is an enormous mistake to suppose that the neighbourhood of a pair of these birds is invariably detrimental. On this point he can speak from experience. For many years he had an intimate knowledge of a pair occupying an inland locality surrounded by valuable flocks of sheep, and abounding in rabbits and game, and had ample opportunities, which he never neglected, of repeatedly examining the pellets of bones and <hi rend="italic">exuvise</hi> that these, like all other carnivorous birds, cast up. He thus found that this pair of Ravens fed almost exclusively on moles. Soon after he moved from the neighbourhood in which they lived the unreasoning zeal of a gamekeeper (against, it is believed, the orders of his master) put an end to this interesting couple—the last of their species which inhabited the county. </note></p><p>The Raven breeds very early in the year, in England resorting to its nest, which is usually an ancient if not an ancestral structure, about the middle or towards the end of January. Therein are laid from five to seven eggs of the common Corvine coloration (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Crow,</hi> vol. vi. pp. 617, 618), and the young are hatched before the end of February. In more northern countries the breeding-season is naturally delayed, but everywhere this species is almost if not quite the earliest of birds to enter upon tlie business</p>
<pb xml:id="eb09-20-r01-0296" facs="encyclopediabrit20newyrich_raw_0314.jp2"/>
<p>of perpetuating its kind. The Raven measures about 26 inches in length, and has an expanse of wing considerably exceeding a yard. Its bill and feet are black, and the same may be said of its whole plumage, but the feathers of the upper parts as well as of the breast are very glossy, reflecting a bright purple or steel-blue. <note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="2"> Pied examples are not at all uncommon in some localities and wholly white varieties are said to have been seen. </note> The species inhabits the whole of Europe, and the northern if not the central parts of Asia; but in the latter continent its southern range is not well determined. In America <note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="3"> American birds have been described as forming a distinct species under the name of <hi rend="italic">Corvus carnivarus</hi> or <hi rend="italic">C. cacolotl.</hi> </note> it is, or used to be, found from the shores of the Polar Sea to Guatemala if not to Honduras, but is said hardly to be found of late years in the eastern part of the United States. In Africa its place is taken by three allied but well-differentiated species, two of which ( <hi rend="italic">Corvus umbrvnus,</hi> readily distinguished by its brown neck, and <hi rend="italic">C. affinis,</hi> <note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="4"> Mr Sharpe <hi rend="italic">(Cat. B. Brit. Museum,</hi> iii. p. 45) separates <hi rend="italic">C. affinis</hi> as forming a distinct genus <hi rend="italic">Rhinocorax</hi> ; but it is a hard task on any reasonable ground to break up the genus <hi rend="italic">Corvus</hi> as long accepted by systematists. </note> having its superior nasal bristles upturned vertically) also occur in South-Western Asia, while the third ( <hi rend="italic">C. leptoηyx</hi> or <hi rend="italic">C. tingitanus,</hi> a smaller species characterized by several slight differences) inhabits Barbary and the Atlantic Islands. Further to the southward in the Ethiopian Region three more species appear, whose plumage is varied with white <hi rend="italic">—C. seapulatus, C. albicollis,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">C. crαssirostris—</hi> the first two of small size, but the last rivalling the real Raven in that respect. <hi rend="smallcaps">(a. n.)</hi></p>
</div></body></text></TEI>