<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/>         </publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb09-20-r01-0349-06" facs="encyclopediabrit20newyrich_raw_0367.jp2" type="entry">

<p><label>REICHENHALL</label>
a small town and watering-place of Upper Bavaria, is finely situated in an amphitheatre of lofty mountains, on the river Saale or Saalach, 1570 feet above the level of the sea and 9 miles to the south-west of Salzburg. As indicated by its name, in which the syllable <hi rend="italic">hall</hi> corresponds, according to a well-known linguistic law, to the Latin <hi rend="italic">sal,</hi> Reichenhall possesses several copious saline springs, producing upwards of 11,500 tons of salt per annum. The water of some of the springs, the sources of which are 50 feet below the surface of the soil, is so strongly saturated with salt (up to 24 per cent.) that it is at once conducted to the boiling houses, while that of the others is first submitted to a process of evaporation. Reichenhall is the centre of the four chief Bavarian saltworks, which are connected with each other by brine conduits having an aggregate length of 60 miles. The surplus brine of Berchtesgaden is conducted to Reichenhall, and thence, in increased volume, to Traunstein and Rosenheim, which possess larger supplies of timber for use as fuel in the process of boiling. Since 1846 Reichenhall has become one of the most fashionable spas in Germany, and it is now visited annually by about five thousand patients, besides many thousand passing tourists. The resident population in 1880 was 3271, almost all Roman Catholics. The saline springs are used both for drinking and bathing, and are said to be efficacious in scrofula and incipient tuberculosis. In addition to numerous large hotels, the most prominent edifices are the Romanesque church, recently restored, and the handsome and extensive buildings of the salt-works.</p><p>The brine springs of Reichenhall are mentioned in a document of the 8th century, and were perhaps known to the Romans ; but almost all trace of the antiquity of the town was destroyed by a conflagration in 1834. The brine conduit to Traunstein dates from 1618. The environs abound in numerous charming Alpine excursions.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>