<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/>         </publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb09-20-r01-0394-04" facs="encyclopediabrit20newyrich_raw_0412.jp2" type="entry">

<p><label>RENÉ I</label>
. (1409-1480), duke of Anjou, count of Provence, and titular king of Naples, was the second son of Louis II. of Aragon, king of Naples, and Yolande, daughter of John I. of Aragon, and was born 16th</p>
<pb xml:id="eb09-20-r01-0395" facs="encyclopediabrit20newyrich_raw_0413.jp2"/>
<p>January 1409. Although his father was crowned king of Naples at Avignon by Pope Clement VII. in 1384, he was unable to make good his claims. After his death Louis III., the elder son, assumed the title, and in 1423 was adopted by Johanna II. of Naples, and obtained possession of the throne. Dying 15th November 1434, he left his claims to his brother René, who was also appointed heir by Johanna II. at her death in the following year. Meantime René had been imprisoned by the count of Vaudemont for contesting his claims to the dukedom of Lorraine, and therefore appointed his wife Isabella regent in his stead. In 1437 he procured his freedom and the acknowledgment of his right to Lorraine for 400,000 florins, and in the following year landed at Naples and rejoined Isabella. Finding, however, that the task of conquering the kingdom from Alphonso of Aragon was beyond his power, he returned in 1442 to Lorraine, which he afterwards gave over to his son John, titular duke of Calabria. In 1444 he took part at Tours in the peace negotiations between England and France; and, to cement the alliance, Henry VI. espoused his daughter Margaret of Anjou. Subsequently he ceased to concern himself with politics, and devoted his chief attention to literature. He also took a special interest in painting and sculpture, although there appears to have been no foundation for the statement that he practised either of these arts. His closing years were spent in the company of his daughter the exiled queen. He died 10th July 1480.</p><p>His <hi rend="italic">Œuvres Completes,</hi> with a biography and notes by the count of Quatrebarbes, were published at Paris, 4 vols., 1844-46. See also De Villeneuve-Bargemont, <hi rend="italic">Histoire de René d'Anjou,</hi> 3 vols., Paris, 1825 ; Reriouvier, <hi rend="italic">Les peintres et les enlumineurs du roi René,</hi> 1851; and Lecoy de la Marche, <hi rend="italic">Le roi René,</hi> 2 vols., Paris, 1875.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>