<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/>         </publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb09-20-r01-0302-02" facs="encyclopediabrit20newyrich_raw_0320.jp2" type="entry">

<p><label>RAZORBILL</label>
or <hi rend="smallcaps">Razor-billed Auk,</hi> known also on many parts of the British coasts as the Marrot, Murre, Scout, Tinker, or Willock—names which it, however, shares with the <hi rend="smallcaps">Guillemot</hi> (vol. xi. p. 262), and to some extent with the <hi rend="smallcaps">Puffin</hi> (see above, p. 101)—a common sea-bird of the Northern Atlantic, <note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="1"> Schlegel <hi rend="italic">{Mus. des Pays-Bas, Urinatores,</hi> p. 14) records an example from Japan ; but this must be in error. </note> resorting in vast numbers to certain stations on rocky cliffs for the purpose of breeding, and, its object being accomplished, returning to deeper waters for the rest of the year. It is the <hi rend="italic">Alca tor da</hi> of Linnæus <note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="2"> The word <hi rend="italic">Alca</hi> is simply the Latinized form of this bird’s common Teutonic name, <hi rend="italic">Aik,</hi> of which Auk is the English modification. It must therefore be held to be the type of the Linnsean genus <hi rend="italic">Alca,</hi> though some systematists on indefensible grounds have removed it thence, making it the sole member of a genus named by Leach, after Aldrovandus ( <hi rend="italic">Ornithologia,</hi> bk. xix. chap, xlix.), <hi rend="italic">Utamania</hi> —an extraordinary word, that seems to have originated in some mistake from the no less extraordinary <hi rend="italic">Vuttamaria,</hi> given by Belon ( <hi rend="italic">Observations,</hi> i. c. xi.) as the Cretan name of some diving bird, which certainly could not have been the present species. </note> and most modern authors, congeneric with the <hi rend="smallcaps">Gare-fowl</hi> (vol. x. p. 78), if not with the true Guillemots, between which two forms it is intermediate—differing from the former in its small size and retaining the power of flight,</p><p>which that presumably extinct species has lost, and from the latter in its peculiarly-shaped bill, which is vertically enlarged, compressed, and deeply furrowed, as well as in its elongated, wedge-shaped tail. A fine white line, running on each side from the base of the culmen to the eye, is in the adult bird in breeding-apparel (with a few very rare exceptions) a further obvious characteristic. Otherwise the appearance of all these birds may be briefly described in the same words—head, bi’east, and upper parts generally of a deep glossy black, and the lower parts and tip of the secondaries of a pure white, while the various changes of plumage dependent on age or season are alike in all. In habits the Razorbill closely agrees with the true Guillemots, laying its single egg (which is not, however, subject to the same amazing variety of coloration that is pre-eminently the Guillemot’s own) on the ledges of the cliffs to which it repairs in the breeding-season, but it is said then as a rule to occupy higher elevations, and when not breeding to keep further out to sea. On the east side of the Atlantic the Razorbill has its stations on convenient parts of the coast from the North Cape to Britanny, besides several in the Baltic, while in winter it passes much further to the southward, and is sometimes numerous in the Bay of Gibraltar, occasionally entering the Mediterranean but apparently never extending to the eastward of Sicily or Malta. On the west side of the Atlantic it breeds from 70° N. lat. on the eastern shore of Baffin’s Bay to Cape Farewell, and again on the coast of America from Labrador and Newfoundland to the Bay of Fundy, while in winter it reaches Long Island, <hi rend="smallcaps">(a. n.)</hi></p>
</div></body></text></TEI>