<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/>         </publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb09-20-r01-0283-03" facs="encyclopediabrit20newyrich_raw_0301.jp2" type="entry">

<p><label>RASHBA</label>
(רשב׳׳א) stands for three rabbins of various ages and various countries.</p><p>1. R. <hi rend="smallcaps">Shime'on Ben El'azar</hi> was a Mishnic teacher of the 2d century.</p><p>2. <hi rend="smallcaps">Rabbenu Shimshon Ben Abraham</hi> of Sens wrote commentaries on various Mishnic treatises (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Mishnah,</hi> vol. xvi. p. 506).</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">3. R. Shelomoh Ben Abraham</hi> (or Ben [Ibn] Ad-dereth) was a disciple of Nachmanides, upon whom his master’s mantle had fallen (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Ramban).</hi> He became chief rabbi of Barcelona. Here so many disciples from the neighbouring provinces flocked to him as to excite emulation among the Jews in the capital of Castile, who thereupon appointed the German Rabbi Asher b. Yehiel (Rosh). At the same time religious questions poured in upon him from all Israel, so that it is a marvel how he could go through his mere clerical work.</p><p>His works extend over the whole Talmud, although not all of them are printed. But thousands of his <hi rend="italic">Responsa</hi> have been printed, while many others lie in MS. at Cambridge (Add. 500). Of his other works, the enumeration of which would occupy columns, mention can be made only of his explanations of the Agadoth of the Babylonian Talmud, containing polemic against both Christians and Moslems (MS., Univ. Camb., Add. 1567, 1). On his part in the Maimonidean controversy see Schiller-Szinessy, <hi rend="italic">Catalogue,</hi> i. 187 <hi rend="italic">sq.</hi> (S. M. S.-S.)</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>