<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0211-03"
                facs="gri_33125011196389_0217.tif" type="entry">

                <p><label>RHINOCEROS</label>, in zoology, a genus of quadrupeds belonging to the
                    order of belluæ. The name is entirely Greek ; but theſe animals were totally
                    unknown to the ancient Greeks. Ariſtotle takes no notice of them, nor any other
                    Greek writer till Strabo, nor Roman till Pliny. It is probable they did not
                    frequent that part of India into which Alexander had penetrated, ſince it was
                    near 300 years after that Pompey brought them to Europe. From this time till the
                    days of Heliogabalus, the rhinoceros was frequently exhibited in the Roman
                    ſpectacles ; and he has often been transported into Europe in more modern times
                    ; but they were long very ill repreſented, and very imperfectly de-ſcribed, till
                    ſome that arrived in London in 1739 and 1741 were inſpected, by which the errors
                    and caprices of former writers were detected.</p>
                <p>Ί here are two ſpecies of rhinoceros, the ſirſt of which is the <hi
                        rend="italic"> unicornis,</hi> the length of which, Buffon tells us, from
                    the extremity of the muzzle to the origin of the tail, is at leaſt 12 ſeet, and
                    the circumference of the body is nearly the ſame. " The rhinoceros which came to
                    London in the year 1739 was ſent from Bengal. Though not above two years of age,
                    the expence of his food and journey amounted to near L. 1000 Sterling. He was
                    fed with rice, ſugar, and hay. He had daily ſeven pounds of rice, mixed with
                    three pounds of ſugar, and divided into three portions. He had likewife hay and
                    green herbs, which laſt he preferred to hay. His drink was water, of which he
                    took large quantities at a time <note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial" n="1"> " Their food in a ſtate of nature is the groſſeſt
                        herbs, as thiſtles and thorny ſhrubs, which they prefer to bhe foft paſture
                        of the beſt meadows ; they are fond of the ſugar cane, and eat all kinds of
                        grain, but for fleſh they have no appetite.” </note>. He was of a peaceable
                    diſpoſition, and allowed all parts of his body to be touched, when hungry, or
                    ſtruck by any perſon, he became miſehievous, and in both caſes nothing appeaſed
                    him but food, when enraged, he ſprung forward, and nimbly raiſed himſelf to a
                    great height, puſhing at the ſame time his head ſuriouily againſt the walls,
                    which he performed with amazing quickneſs, notwithſtanding his heavy aſpect and
                    unwieldy maſs. I often obſerved, ſays Dr Parſons, theſe movements produced by
                    rage or impatience, eſpecially in the mornings before his rice and ſugar were
                    brought to him. The vivacity and promptitude of his movements, Dr Parſons adds,
                    led me to think, that he is altogether unconquerable, and that he could eaſily
                    overtake any man who ſhould offend him.</p>
                <p>" This rhinoceros, at the age of two years, was not taller than a young cow that
                    has never produced. But his body was very long and very thick. His head was
                    diſproportionally large. From the ears to the horn there is a concavity, the two
                    extremities of which, namely the upper end of the muzzle, and the part near the
                    ears, are conſiderably raiſed. The horn, which was not yet above an'inch high,
                    was black, ſmooth at the top, but full of wrinkles directed backward at the
                    baſe. The noſtrils are ſituated very low, being not above an inch diſtant from
                    the opening of the mouth. The under lip is pretty ſimilar to that of the ox ;
                    but the upper lip has a greater reſemblance to that of the hoiſe, with this
                    advantageous difference, that the rhinoceros can lengthen this lip, move it from
                    ſide to fide, roll it about a ſtaſſ, and ſeize with it any object he wiſhes to
                    carry to liis mouth. Tlie tongue of tliis young rhinoceros was ſoft, like that
                    of a calf. His eyes had no vivacity : In figure they reſembled thoſe of tlie
                    hog, and were ſituated lower, or nearer the noſtrils, than in any other
                    quadruped. His ears are large, thin at the extremities, and contracted at their
                    origin by a kind of annular rugoſity. I'he neck is very ſhort, and ſurronnded
                    with two large folds of ſkin. The ſhoulders aie very thick, and at their
                    juncture there is another fold oſ ſkin, whieh deſeends upon the fore legs. The
                    body of this young rhinoceros was very thick, and pretty much reſembled that oſ
                    a cow about to bring ſorth. Between the body and crupper there is another fold,
                    which deſeends upon the hind legs, Laſtly, another fold tranfverfely ſurrounds
                    the inferior part of the crupper, at ſome diſtance from the tail. The belly was
                    large, and hung near the ground, particularly its middle part. The legs are
                    round, thick, ſtrong, and</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0212" facs="gri_33125011196389_0218.tif"/>
                <p>their joint bended backwards. This joint, which, when the animal lies, is
                    covered with a remarkable fold of the ſkin, appears when he ſtands. The tail is
                    thin, and proportionally ſhort ; that of the rhinoceros ſo often mentioned,
                    exceeded not 16 or 17 inches in length. It turns a little thicker at the
                    extremity, which is garniſhed with ſome ſhort, thick, hard hairs. The form of
                    the penis is very extraordinary. It is contained in a prepuce or ſheath like
                    that of the horſe ; and the ſirſt thing that appears in the time of erection is
                    a fecond prepuce, of a ſſeſh-colour, from which there iffues a hollow tube, in
                    the form of a funnel cut and bordered fomewhat like a flower-de-luce, and
                    conſtitutes tlie glans and extremity of the penis. This anomalous glans is of à
                    paler ſſeſh-colour than the ſecond prepuce. Tn the moſt vigorous erection, tlie
                    penis extends not above eight inches out of the body ; and it is eaſily procured
                    by rubbing the animal witli a liandſul of ſtraw wlien lie lies at his eaſe. The
                    direction of this organ is not ſtraiglit, but bended backward. Hence lie throws
                    out his urine behind ; and from this circumſtance, it may be inferred that the
                    male covers not the female, but that they unite with their cruppers to each
                    other. The female organs are ſituated like thoſe of the cow ; and ſhe exactly
                    reſembles the male in ſigure and groffneſs of body. The ſkin is ſo thick and
                    impenetrable, that when a man lays hold of any of the folds, he would imagine he
                    is touching a wooden plank of half an inch thick<note anchored="true"
                        place="bottom" type="authorial" n="2"> This Mr Bruce denies to be the caſe,
                        and ſuſpects, where it does occur, that it is the effect of diſeaſe, or oſ a
                        different habit acquired by keeping. In their natural ſtate, he thinks they
                        prevent this rigidity by wallowing· in the mud. </note>. when tanned, Dr
                    Grew remarks, it is exceffively hard, and thicker than the hide of any other
                    terreſtrial animal. It is everywhere covered more or leſs with in-eruſtations in
                    the form of galls or tuberoſities, which are pretty ſmall on the top of the neck
                    and back, but become larger on the ſides. The largeſt are on the ſhoul-ders and
                    crupper, are ſtill pretty large on the thighs and legs, upon which they are
                    ſpread all round, and even on the feet. But between the folds the ſkin is
                    penetrable, delicate, and as ſoft to the touch as ſilk, while the external part
                    of the fold is equally hard with the reſt. This tender ſkin between the folds is
                    of a light fleſh-colour ; and the ſkin of the belly is nearly of the ſame colour
                    and conſiſtence. Theſe galls or tubero-ſities ſhould not be compared, as fome
                    authors have done, to ſcales. They are only ſtmple indurations of the ſkin,
                    without any regularity in their ſigure or ſymmetry in their reſpective
                    poſitions. The flexibility of the ſkin in the folds enables the rhinoceros to
                    move with facility his head, neck, and members. The whole body, except at the
                    joints, is inflexible, and reſembles a coat of mail. Dr Parſons remarks, that
                    this animal liſtened with a deep and long continued attention to any kind of
                    noiſe ; and that, though he was ſſeeping,</p>
                <p>eating, or obeying any other preffing, demands of nature, he raifed his head,
                    aud liſtened till the noiſe ceaſed.”</p>
                <p>Theſe animals never affemble or march together in troops like elephants. Being
                    of a more ſolitary and ſa-vage diſpoſition, they are more difficult to hunt and
                    to overcome. They never attack men, however, except when they are provoked, when
                    they are very furious and formidable ; but as they fee only before them, and</p>
                <p>not very ſharply, and as they turn with great difficulty, they may be eaſily
                    avoided. The ſkin of theſe animals is ſo extremely hard as to reſiſt ſabres,
                    lances, javelins, and even muſket balls, the only penetrable parts being the
                    belly, the eyes, and about the ears. Hence the hunters generally attack them
                    wlien they lie down to ſleep.— Their ſleſh is conſidered as excellent hy the
                    Indians and Africans, but eſpecially by the Hottentots ; and if they were
                    trained when young, they might be rendered, domeſtic, in which caſe they would
                    multiply more eaſtly than the elephant. They inhabit Bengal, Siam,
                    Col-chin-China, Quangſi in China, the iſles of Java and· Sumatra, Congo, Angola,
                    Ethiopia, and the country as low as the Cape. They love ſhady foreſts, the
                    neigh-bourhood of rivers, and marſhy places. They wallow in the mire like hogs,
                    and are ſaid by that means to give ſhelter in the folds of their ſkins to
                    ſcorpions, centipedes, and other infects. This is denied by Buffon and Ed-wards,
                    though the ſurgeon of the Shafteſhury had ob-ſerved in a rhinoceros, newly taken
                    after having welter-ed in the mud, ſeveral infects concealed under the ply of
                    the ſkin. This carries with it every appearance of probability ; for as the
                    creature welters in mud, it is impoffible for it to do ſo without bringing up
                    with it ſome of the infects which live in that mud ; and when this is the caſe,
                    it ſurely cannot be unnatural to ſuppoſe that they would ſhelter themſelves
                    under the plaits of the ſkin. Mr Bruce had an opportunity of examining the ſkin
                    of a rhinoceros before his muddy covering had been ſcraped off, and ſaw under it
                    ſeveral very large worms, but not of the carnivorous kind. He ſaw like-wiſe
                    ſeveral ſmaller animals reſembling car-wigs, which he took to be young
                    fcolopendræ ; and, though he ſearched no farther, we muſt certainly conſlder
                    this as a proof of what the ſurgeon of the Shafteſhury re-lated. Mr Bruce
                    ſuppoſes, too, that they welter in mire, partly in order to ſereen themſelves by
                    a caſe of mud from the attacks of that miſchievous fly which in-feſts the
                    animals of Abyffinia to filch a degree. " The time of the fly (ſays he) being in
                    the rainy ſeaſon, the whole black earth turns into mire.- In the night, when the
                    fly is at reſt, the rhinoceros chooſes a convenient place, and there, rolling
                    himſelf in tlie mud, he clothes himſelf with a kind of caſe, which defends him
                    againſt his enemy the following day. The wrinkles and plaits of his ſkin ſerve
                    to keep this muddy plaſter ſirm up-on him, all but about his hips, ſhoulders,
                    and legs,, where it cracks and falls off by motion, and leaves hime expoſed in
                    thoſe places to the attacks of the fly. The itching and pain which follow
                    occaſion him to rub him-ſelf in thoſe parts againſt the rougheſt trees ; and
                    this is at leaſt one cauſe of the puſtules or tubercles whichi we ſee upon theſe
                    places, both on the elephant and rhino-ceros.” They bring forth only one young
                    at a time,, about which they are very ſolicitous- They are ſaid to confort with
                    tygers ; a ſtory founded merely on their common attachment to the ſides of
                    rivers, by which, means they are often found near each other. Their ſkin,,
                    fleſh, hoofs, teeth, and even dung, are uſed in India medicinally. The horn,
                    eſpecially that of a virgin rhinoceros, is conſidered as an antidote againſt
                    poiſon. Every</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0213" facs="gri_33125011196389_0219.tif"/>
                <p>Born, however, has not this property; feme of them ſell-ing very cheap, while
                    others are extremely dear.</p>
                <p>Some writers are of opinion, that the rhinoceros is the unicorn of holy writ and
                    of the ancients, and that the oryx or Indian aſs of Ariſtotie, who ſays it has
                    but one horn, was the ſame, his informers comparing the clutnſy ſhape of the
                    rhinoceros to that of the aſs.— It was alſo the <hi rend="italic">bos unicornis</hi> and <hi rend="italic">fera monoceros</hi> of Pliny, both of which were
                    of India and in his account of the monoceros he exactly deſcribes the great
                    black horn and hog-like tail. The unicorn of Scripture is confidered as having
                    all the properties of the rhinoceros, as rage, untameableneſs, great ſwiftneſs,
                    and vaſt ſtrength. This opinion is moſt ably ſupported by Mr Bruce. " The
                    derivation of the Hebrew word <hi rend="italic">reem</hi> (ſays he), which in
                    our verſion is tranſlated <hi rend="italic">unicorn,</hi> both in the Hebrew
                    and the Ethiopic, ſeems to be from ereôfnefs, or handing ſtraight. This is
                    certainly no particular quality in the animal itſelf, who is not more or even ſo
                    much erect as many other quadrupeds, ſor in its knees it is rather crooked; but
                    it is from the circumſtance and manner in which itshorn is placed. The horns of
                    all other animals are inclined to ſome degree of paralleliſm with his noſe or os
                    frontis. '1 he horn of the rhinoceros is erect and perpendicular to this bone,
                    on which it ſtands at right angles, thereby poſſeſſing a greater purchaſe or
                    power, as a lever, than an horn could poffibly have in any other poſition. The
                    ſituation of the horn is very happily alluded to in Scripture ; ‘ My horn ſhalt
                    thou exalt like the horn of an unicorn.’ And the horn here alluded to is not
                    wholly figurative, but was really an ornament worn by great men in the days of
                    victory, preferment, or rejoicing, when they were anointed with new, ſweet, or
                    freſh oil ; a circumſtance which David joins with that of erecting the horn.</p>
                <p>" Some authors, for what reaſon I know not, have made the reem, or unicorn, to
                    be of the deer or antelope kind ; that is, of a genus whoſe very character is
                    fear and weaknefs, directly oppoſite to the qualities by which the reem is
                    deſcribed in Scripture : beſides, it is plain that the reem is not of the claſs
                    of clean quadru-peds ; and a late modern traveller very wllimſically takes him
                    for the leviathan, which certainly was a ſiſh. Balaam, a prieſt of Midian, and
                    ſo in the neighbourhood of the haunts of the rhinoceros, and intimately
                    connected with Ethiopia, (for they themſelves were ſhepherds of that country),
                    in a tranſport, from contemplating the ſtrength of Iſrael, whom he was brought
                    to curſe, ſays, they had, as it were, the ſtrength oſ the reem. Job makes
                    frequent alluſion to his great ſtrength, ferocity, and indocility. He aſks,
                    'Will the reem be willing to ſerve thee, or abide by thy crib ?’ that is, Will
                    lie willingly come into thy ſtable, and eat at thy manger ? And again, ‘ Canſt
                    thou bind the reem witli a band in the furrow ; and will lie harrow tlie valleys
                    ſor thee ?’— In other words, Canſt thou make him go to the plough or harrows?</p>
                <p>" The rhinoceros, in Geez, is called <hi rend="italic">A rave Harich,</hi> and
                    in the Amharic <hi rend="italic">Auraris ;</hi> both which names ſigniſy ‘ the
                    large wild beaſt with the horn.’ This would ſeem as if applied to the ſpecies
                    witli one horn. On the other hand, in the conntry of the Shangalla and in Nubia
                    he is called <hi rend="italic">Girnamgim,</hi> or ‘ horn upon horn;’ and this
                    would ſeem to denote that he had two. The Ethiopic text renders the word <hi
                        rend="italic"> reem,</hi> ‘ Arwe-Harich and this the Septuagint tianſſates <hi rend="italic">monoceros,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">unicorn.</hi> The
                    principal reaſon of tranſiating the word <hi rend="italic">unicorn</hi> rather
                    than <hi rend="italic">rhinoceros,</hi> is from ?. prejudice that he muſt have
                    had but one horn. But this is by no means ſo well founded as to be admitted the
                    only argument for eſtabliſhing tlie exiſtence of an animal, which never has
                    appeared after the ſearch of ſo many ages. Scripture ſpeaks of tlie horns of
                    tlie unicorn ; fo that even from this circumſtance tlie reem may be the
                    rhinoceros, as the Aſiatic, and part of the African rhinoceros, may be the
                    unicorn.”</p>
                <p>Tlie rhinoceros bicornis was long known in Europe merely by the double horns
                    wliich were preferved in various cabinets ; and its exiſtence, though now paſt
                    all doubt, has been frequently queſtioned. Dr Sparman, in his voyage to the Cape
                    of Good Hope, killed two of theſe animals, wliicli he diffected, and very
                    minutely deſcribes. The horns, lie ſays, in the live animal are ſo mobile and
                    looie, that wlien it walks careleſsly along, one may ſee tliem waggle about, and
                    hear them claſh and clatter againſt each other. In tlie Phil. Tranſ. ſor 1793,
                    we have a deſcription of tlie double-horned rhinoceros of Sumatra, by Mr Bell,
                    ſurgeon in the ſervice of the Eaſt India Company at Bencoolen ; and this
                    account, though it differs conſiderably from that of Sparman in ſome
                    particulars, we ſhall infert here. “ The animal (ſays· Mr Bell) herein defcribed
                    was ſhot with a leaden ball· from a muſket about ten miles from Fort
                    Marlborough.</p>
                <p>I ſaw it the day after ; it was then not in the leaſt pu-trid, and I put it into
                    the poſition from which the accompanying drawing was made. (See Plate
                    ccccxxxvm.) It was a male ; the height at the ſhoulder was 4 feet 4 inches ; at
                    the ſacrum nearly the ſame ; from the tip of the noſe to the end of the tail
                    eight feet five inches.— From the appearance of its teeth and bones it was but
                    young, and probably not near its full ſize. The ſhape of the animal was much
                    like that of the hog. The ge-neral colour was a browniſh aſh ; under the belly,
                    be-tween the legs and folds of the ſkin, a dirty ſſeſh co-lour. The head much
                    reſembled that of the Angle horned rhinoceros ; the eyes were ſmall, of a brown
                    colour j the <hi rend="italic">membrana nictitans</hi> thick and ſtrong : the
                    ſkin fur-rounding the eyes was wrinkled ; the noſtrils were wide;, the upper lip
                    was pointed, and hanging over the under.</p>
                <p>" There were fix <hi rend="italic">molares,</hi> or grinders, on each ſide of
                    the upper and lower jaw, becoming gradually larger backward, particularly in the
                    upper ; two teeth in the front of each jaw ; the tongue was quite ſmooth ; the
                    ears were ſmall and pointed, lined and edged with ſhort black hair, and ſituated
                    like thoſe of the ſingle-horned rhinoceros. The horns were black, the larger was
                    placed immediately above the noſe, pointing upwards,, and was bent a little
                    back; it was about nine inches-long. The ſmall horn was four inches long, of a
                    pyra-midal ſhape, flattened a little, and placed above the eyes, rather a little
                    more forward, ſtanding in a line with the larger-horn, immediately above it.
                    They were both firmly attached to the ſkull, nor was there any appear-ance of
                    joint or muſcles to move them<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial" n="3">Mr Bruce, however, ſays, that in the living animal
                        the horns are extremely ſenſible. He informs us, <pb/> that once at a
                        hunting match he ſaw the point of a rhinoceros’s horn broken off by a
                        muſket-ſhot; the conſequence of which was, that the creature was for a
                        moment deprived of all appearance of life.</note>. The neck was thick and
                    ſhort, the ſkin on the under ſide thrown in</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0214" facs="gri_33125011196389_0220.tif"/>
                <p>to folds, and theſe folds again wrinkled. The body was bulky and round, and from
                    the ſhoulder ran a line, or fold, as in the ſingle-horned rhinoceros, though it
                    was but faintly marked. There were ſeveral other folds and wrinkles on the body
                    and legs ; and the whole gave rather the appearance of ſoftneſs : the legs were
                    thick, ſhort, and remarkably ſtrong· ; the feet armed with three diſtinct hoofs,
                    of a blackiſh colour, which ſurrounded half the foot, one in front, the others
                    on each ſide.— The ſoles of the feet were convex, of a light colour, and the
                    cuticle on them not thicker than that on the foot of a man who is uſed to
                    walking ; the teſticles Hardly appeared externally ; the penis was bent
                    backward, and opened about 18 inches below the anus. At its origin it was as
                    thick as a man’s leg, and about two feet and a half long ; the bend in it
                    occaſions the urine to be diſcharged backwards. The glans is very ſingular ; the
                    opening of the urethra is like the mouth of a cup with its brim bending over a
                    little and is about three quarters of an inch in diameter ; the glans here is
                    about half an inch in diameter, and continues that thick-neſs for an inch and a
                    half : it is then inſerted into another cup like the firſt, but three times as
                    large ; the glans afterwards gradually becomes thicker, and at about nine inches
                    from the opening of the urethra are placed two bodies on the upper part of the
                    glans, very like the nipples of a milch-cow, and as large ; theſe become turgid
                    when the penis is erected ; the whole of this is contained in the prepuce, and
                    may be conſidered as glans. From the os pubis ariſes a ſtrong muſcle, which ſoon
                    becomes tendinous : this tendon is continued along the back or upper part of the
                    penis ; it is flattened, is about the ſize of a man’s little finger, and is
                    inſerted into the upper part of the glans, near the end. The uſe of this muſcle
                    is to ſtraiten the penis. On the under ſide of the penis there are two muſcles,
                    antagoniſts to the above ; they ariſe from the os ifchium fleſhy, run along tlie
                    lower ſide of the penis, on each ſide of the corpus ſpongioſum, and are inſerted
                    fleſhy into the lower ſide of the glans ; the action of theſe muſcles will draw
                    in the penis, and bend it. The male has two nipples, like the female, ſituated
                    between the hind legs; they are about half an inch in length, of a pyramidal
                    form, rounded at the end.</p>
                <p>" The whole ſkin of the animal is rough, and covered very thinly with ſhort
                    black hair. The ſkin was not more than one third of an inch in thickneſs at the
                    ſtrongeſt part ; under the belly it was hardly a quarter of an inch ; any part
                    of it might be cut through with eaſe by a common diſſecting knife. The animal
                    had not that appearance of armour which is obſerved in the ſingle-horned
                    rhinoceros. Since I diſſected the male, I have had an opportunity of examining a
                    female, which was more of a lead colour : it was younger than the male, and had
                    not ſo many folds or wrinkles in its ſkin; of courſe it had ſtill leſs the
                    appearance of armour. The only external mark which diſtinguiſhes it from the
                    male is the vagina, which is cloſe to the anus ; whereas in the male the opening
                    for the penis is 18 inches below the anus.”</p>
                <p>From the difference between this account and Spar-man’s, which in ſome
                    particulars is conſiderable, and from the difference of ſhape, we are diſpoſed
                    to think them varieties. Mr Bruce’s drawing of the rhinoceros bicornis is
                    unqueſtionably a deception ; the body of the animal, as there repreſented,
                    correſponds exactly with that of the unicornis except in its having two horns on
                    its head. In the muſeum of the late Dr William Hunter, the two-horned animal was
                    preſerved, agreeing exactly with the general accounts and figures we have of
                    that animal, but differing eſſentially from Mr Bruce’s. For further particulars
                    reſpecting theſe curious animals, we refer to Buffon, vol. vi. p. 92—117 ;
                    Sparman's Voyage to the Cape, vol. ii. chap. 12.; and Bruce’s Travels, vol. iv.
                    p. 296, &amp;c. and Appendix, p. 85, &amp;c.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">RHINOCEROS-Bird.</hi> See Buceros.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
