<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0324.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s03-0318-07" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SESAMUM, <hi rend="smallcaps">oily grain,</hi></label>
 in botany : A genus of plants belonging to the claſs of didynamia, and to the order of angioſpermia ; and in the natural ſystem ranging under the 20th order, <hi rend="italic">Lurida.</hi> The calyx is divided into five parts. The corolla is campanulated, the tube of which is nearly the length of the calyx ; the throat is inflated, and very large ; the border is divided into five parts, four of which are ſpreading and nearly equal ; the fifth is the loweſt and largeſt. There are four filaments, and the rudiments of a fifth. The ſtigma is lanceolated, and the capſule has four cells. There are only two ſpecies, the <hi rend="italic">orientale</hi> and <hi rend="italic">indicum.</hi> 1. The orientale has ovate, oblong, entire leaves. It is an annual, and grows naturally on the coaſt of Malabar and in the iſland of Ceylon ; riſing with an herbaceous four-cornered ſtalk, two feet high, ſending out a few ſhort ſide-branches ; the leaves are oblong, oval, a little hairy, and ſtand oppoſite. The flowers terminate the ſtalks in looſe ſpikes ; they are ſmall, of a dirty white colour, ſhaped ſomewhat like thoſe of the fox-glove. After the flowers are paid, the germen turns to an oval acute-pointed capſule with four cells, filled with oval compreſſed ſeeds, which ripen in autumn. 2. The indicum, with trifid lower leaves, grows naturally in India : this is alſo an annual plant ; the ſtalk riſes taller than that of the former ; the lower leaves are cut into three parts, which is the only difference between them.</p><p>The firſt fort is frequently cultivated in all the eaſtern countries, and alſo in Africa, as a pulſe ; and of late years the ſeeds have been introduced into Carolina by the African negroes, where they ſucceed extremely well. The inhabitants of that country make an oil from the ſeed, which will keep good many years, without having any rancid ſmell or taſte, but in two years become quite mild ; ſo that when the warm taſte of the feed, which is in the oil when firſt drawn, is worn off, they uſe it as a ſalad-oil, and for all the purpoſes of ſweet oil. The ſeeds oſ this plant are alſo uſed by the negroes for food ; which ſeeds they parch over the fire, and then mix them with water, and ſtew other ingredients with them, which makes an hearty food. Sometimes a fort of pudding is made of theſe ſeeds, in the ſame manner ,as with millet or rice, and is by ſome perſons eſteemed, but is rarely uſed for theſe purpoſes in Europe. This is called <hi rend="italic">benny</hi> or <hi rend="italic">bonny</hi> in Carolina. In England theſe plants are preſerved in botanic gardens as curiosities. Their ſeeds must be ſown in the ſpring upon a hot bed ; and when the plants are come up, they muſt be tranſplanted into a freſh hot-bed to bring them forward. After they have acquired a tolerable degree of ſtrength, they ſhould be planted into pots, and plunged into another hot-bed, managing them as hath been directed for amaranths ; for if theſe plants are not thus brought forward in the former part of the ſummer, they will not produce good ſeeds in this Country.</p><p>From nine pounds of this ſeed which came from Ca-<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0325.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s03-0319"/>
rolina, there were upwards of two quarts of oil drawn, which is as great a quantity as hath been obtained from any vegetable whatever. This might occaſion its being called the <hi rend="italic">oily grain.</hi></p></div></body></text></TEI>