<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0333.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s03-0327-01" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SEX</label>,
the property by which any animal is male or female.</p><p>Lavater has drawn the following characteriſtic distinctions between the male and female of the human ſpecies.</p><p>“ The primary matter of which women are conſtituted appears to be more flexible, irritable, and elaſtic, than that of man. They are formed to maternal mildneſs and affection ; all their organs are tender, yielding, eaſily wounded, ſenſible, and receptible. Among a thouſand females there is ſcarcely one without the generic feminine ſigns ; the flexible, the circular, and the irritable.</p><p>“ They are the counterpart of man, taken out of man, to be ſubject to man ; to comfort him like angels, and to lighten his cares. ‘ She ſhall be ſaved in childbearing, if they continue in faith, and charity, and holineſs, with ſobriety” (1 Tim. ii. 15.) This tenderneſs, this ſenſibility, this light texture of their fibres and organs, this volatility of feeling, render them ſo eaſy to conduct and to tempt ; ſo ready of ſubmiſſion to the enterpriſe and power of the man ; but more powerful through the aid of their charms than man, with all his ſtrength. The man was not firſt tempted, but the woman, afterward the man by the woman. And, not only eaſy to be tempted, ſhe is capable of being formed to the pureſt, nobleſt, moſt ſeraphic virtue ; to every thing which can deserve praiſe or affection. Highly ſenſible of purity, beauty, and symmetry, ſhe does not always take time to reflect on internal life, internal death, internal corruption. ‘ The woman ſaw that the tree was good for food, and that it was pleaſant to the eyes, and a tree to be deſired to make one wise, and ſhe took of the fruit thereof.’ (Gen. iii. 6.)</p><p>“ The female thinks not profoundly ; profound thought is the power of the man. Women feel more. Senſibility is the power of woman. They often rule more effectually, more ſovereignly, than man. They rule with tender looks, tears, and ſighs ; but not with paſſion and threats ; for if, or when, they ſo rule, they are no longer women but abortions. They are capable of the ſweeteſt ſenſibility, the moſt profound emotion, the utmoſt humility, and the exceſs of enthuſiaſm. In their countenance are the ſigns of ſanctity and inviolability, which every feeling man honours, and the effects of which are often miraculous. Therefore, by the irritability of their nerves, their incapacity for deep inquiry and firm deciſion, they may eaſily from their extreme ſenſibility become the moſt irreclaimable, the moſt rapturous enthuſiaſts. Their love, ſtrong and rooted as it is, is very changeable ; their hatred almoſt incurable, and only to be effaced by continued and artful flattery. Men are moſt profound ; women are more ſublime.</p><p>“ Men moſt embrace the whole ; women remark individually, and take more delight in ſelecting the minutiæ which form the whole, Man hears the bursting<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0334.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s03-0328"/>
thunder, views the deſtructive bolt with ſerene aſpect, and stands erect amidſt the fearful majeſty of the dreaming clouds. Woman trembles at the lightning, and the voice of diſtant thunder ; and ſhrinks into herſelf or sinks into the arms of man. Man receives a ray of light ſingle, woman delights to view it through a priſm in all its dazzling colours. She contemplates the rainbow as the promiſe of peace ; he extends his inquiring eye over the whole horizon. Woman laughs, man ſmiles ; woman weeps, man remains silent. Woman is in anguiſh when man weeps, and in deſpair when man is in anguiſh ; yet has ſhe often more faith than man. Man without religion, is a diſeaſed creature, who would perſuade himſelf he is well, and needs not a phyſician ; but woman without religion, is raging and monſtrous. A woman with a beard is not ſo diſguſting as a woman who acts the freethinker ; her ſex is formed to piety and religion ; to them Chriſt firſt appeared ; but he was obliged to prevent them from too ardently, and too haſtily, embracing him : ‘ Touch me not.’ They are prompt to receive and ſeize novelty, and become its enthuſiaſts. The whole world is forgotten in the emotion cauſed by the preſence and proximity of him they love. They sink into the moſt incurable melancholy, as they alſo riſe to the moſt enraptured heights.</p><p>“ Male ſenſation is more imagination, female more heart. When communicative, they are more communicative than man ; when ſecret, more ſecret. In general they are more patient, long-ſuffering, credulous, benevolent, and modeſt. Woman is not a foundation on which to build. She is the gold, ſilver, precious ſtones, wood, hay, ſtubble ( I Cor. iii. 12. ) ; the materials for building on the male foundation. She is the leaven, or more expreſſively the oil to the vinegar of man : the ſecond part of the book of man.</p><p>“ Man ſingly is but half man ; at leaſt but half human ; a king without a kingdom. Woman, who feels properly what ſhe is, whether ſtill or in motion, reſts upon the man ; nor is man what he may and ought to be, but in conjunction with woman : therefore, ‘ it is not good that man ſhould be alone, but that he ſhould leave father and mother, and cleave to his wife, and they two ſhall be one fleſh.”</p><p>They differ alſo in their exterior form and appearance.</p><p>“ Man is the moſt firm ; woman the moſt flexible. Man is the ſtraighteſt ; woman the moſt bending. Man ſtands ſtedfaſt ; woman gently retreats. Man ſurveys and obſerves ; woman glances and feels. Man is ſerious ; woman is gay. Man is the talleſt and broadeſt ; woman the ſmalleſt and weakeſt. Man is rough and hard ; woman ſmooth and ſoft. Man is brown ; woman is fair. Man is wrinkly ; woman is not. The hair of man is more ſtrong and ſhort ; of woman more long and pliant. The eyebrows of man are compreſſed; of woman lets frowning. Man has moſt convex lines ; woman moſt concave. Man has moſt ſtraight lines ; woman moſt curved. The countenance of man taken in profile is more ſeldom perpendicular than that of the woman. Man is moſt angular; woman moſt round.”</p><p>In determining the comparative merit of the two ſexes,<note anchored="false" n="1" place="margin" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">Fitzosborne's Letters.</hi></p></note> it is no derogation from female excellency that it differs in kind from that which diſtinguiſhes the male part of our ſpecies : and if, in general, it ſhould be found (what upon an impartial inquiry will moſt certainly be found) that women fill up their appointed circle of action with greater regularity than men, the claim of preference cannot juſtly be decided in our favour. In the prudential and economical parts of life, it is undeniable that they riſe far above us : and if true fortitude of mind is beſt discovered by a cheerful reſignation to the meaſures of Providence, we ſhall not find reaſon, perhaps, to claim that moſt lingular of the human virtues as our peculiar privilege. I here are numbers of the other sex who, from the natural delicacy of their conſtſtution, paſs through one continued ſcene of suffering from their cradles to their graves, with a firmneſs of reſolution that would deserve so many ſtatues to be erected to their memories, if heroism were not esteemed more by the ſplendor than the merit of actions.</p><p>But whatever real difference there may be between the moral or intellectual powers of the male and female mind, Nature does not ſeem to have marked the diſtinction ſo ſtrongly as our vanity is willing to imagine ; and after all, perhaps, education will be found to conſtitute the principal ſuperiority. It muſt be acknowledged, at leaſt, that in this article we have every advantage over the ſofter ſex that art and induſtry can poſſibly ſecure to us. The moſt animating examples of Greece and Rome are ſet before us, as early as we are capable of any obſervation ; and the nobleſt compoſitions of the ancients are given into our hands almoſt as ſoon as we have ſtrength to hold them ; while the employments of the other ſex, at the ſame period of life, are generally the reverſe of every thing that can open and enlarge their minds, or fill them with juſt and rational notions. I he truth of it is, female education is ſo much worſe than none, as it is better to leave the mind to its natural and uninſtructed ſuggeſtions, than to lead it into falle purſuits, and contract its views, by turning them upon the loweſt and moſt trifling objects. We ſeem, indeed, by the manner in which we ſuffer the youth of that ſex to be trained, to conſider women agreeably to the opinion of certain Mahometan doctors, and treat them as if we believed they had no fouls : why elſe are they</p><p>Bred only, and completed to the taſte</p><p>Of luſtful appetence, to fing, to dance,</p><p>To dreſs, and troul the tongue, and roll the eye.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Milton.</hi></p><p>This ſtrange neglect of cultivating the female mind can hardly be allowed as good policy, when it is considered how much the intereſt of society is concerned in the rectitude of their underſtandings. That ſeason of every man’s life which is moſt ſuſceptible of the strongeſt impreſſions, is neceſſarily under female direction ; as there are few inſtances, perhaps, in which that ſex in not one of the ſecret ſprings which regulates the moſt important movements of private or public tranſactions. What Cato obſerves of his countrymen is in one reſpect true of every nation under the fun : “ The Romans (said he) govern the world, but it is the women that govern the Romans.”</p><p>If it be true then ( as true beyond all peradventure it is) that female influence is thus extenſive, nothing certainly can be of more importance than to give it a proper tendency, by the aſſiſtance of a well-directed education. Far are we from recommending any attempts<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0335.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s03-0329"/>
to render women learned ; yet ſurely it is neceſſary they ſhould be raiſed above ignorance. Such a general tincture of the most useful ſciences as may ſerve to free the mind from vulgar prejudices, and give it a reliſh for the rational exerciſe of its powers, might very juſtly enter into a plan of female erudition. That ſex might be taught to turn the courſe of their reflections into a proper and advantageous channel, without any danger of rendering them too elevated for the feminine duties of life. In a word, they ought to be conſidered as deſigned by Providence for uſe as well as ſhow, and trained up, not only as women, but as rational creatures.</p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Sex</hi> <hi rend="italic">of Bees.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Bee.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Sex</hi> <hi rend="italic">of Plants.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Botany,</hi> p. 448. SEXAGENARY, ſomething relating to the number ſixty : thus ſexagenary or ſexageſimal arithmetic is a method of computation proceeding by ſixties ; ſuch is that uſed in the diviſion of a degree into ſixty minutes, of the minute into ſixty ſeconds, of the ſecond into ſixty thirds, &amp;c. Alſo ſexagenary tables are tables of proportional parts, ſhowing the product of two ſexagenaries that are to be multiplied, or the quotient of the two that are to be divided.</p></div></body></text></TEI>