<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="gri_33125011196363_0347.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s03-0341-04"
                xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                <p><label>SHEEP</label>, in zoology. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Ovis</hi> and <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Wool.</hi></p>
                <p>Amongſt the various animals with which Divine Providence has ſtored the world for
                    the uſe of man, none is to be found more innocent, more uſeful, or more
                    valuable, than the ſheep. The ſheep ſupplies us with food and clothing, and finds
                    ample employment for our poor at all times and ſeaſons of the year, whereby a
                    variety of manufactures of woollen cloth is carried on without interruption to
                    domeſtic comfort and loſs to friendly ſociety or injury to health, as is the
                    caſe with many other occupations. Every lock of wool that grows on its back
                    becomes the means of ſupport to ſtaplers, dyers, pickers, ſcourers, ſcriblers,
                    carders, combers, ſpinners, ſpoolers, warpers, queelers, weavers, fullers,
                    tuckers, burlers, ſhearmen, preſſers, clothiers, and packers, who, one after
                    another, tumble and toſs, and twiſt, and bake, and boil, this raw material, till
                    they have each extracted a livelihood out of it ; and then comes the merchant,
                    who, in his turn, ſhips it (in its higheſt ſtate of improvement) to all quarters
                    of the globe, from whence he brings back every kind of riches to his country, in
                    return for this valuable commodity which the ſheep affords.</p>
                <p>Beſides this, the uſeful animal, after being deprived of his coat, produces
                    another againſt the next year ; and when we are hungry, and kill him for food,
                    he gives us his ſkin to employ the fell-mongers and parchment-makers, who ſupply
                    us with a durable material for ſecuring our eſtates, rights, and poſſeſſions ;
                    and if our enemies take the field againſt us, ſupplies us with a powerful
                    inſtrument for rouſing our courage to repel their attacks. When the
                    parchment-maker has taken as much of the ſkin as he can uſe, the glue-maker
                    comes after and picks up every morſel that is left, and therewith ſupplies a
                    material for the carpenter and cabinet-maker, which they cannot do without, and
                    which is eſſentially neceſſary before we can have elegant furniture in our
                    houſes ; tables, chairs, looking-glaſſes, and a hundred other articles of
                    convenience : and when the winter nights come on, while we are deprived of the
                    cheering light of the ſun, the ſheep ſupplies us with an artificial mode of
                    light, whereby we preſerve every pleaſure of domeſtic ſociety, and with whose
                    aſſiſtance we can continue our work, or write or read, and improve our minds, or
                    enjoy the facial mirth of our tables. Another part of the ſlaughtered animal
                    ſupplies us with an ingredient necessary for making good common ſoap, a useful
                    ſtore for producing cleanlineſs in every family, rich or poor. Neither need the
                    horns be thrown away ; for they are converted by the button-makers and turners
                    into a cheap kind of buttons, tips for bows, and many uſeful ornaments. From the
                    very trotters an oil is extracted uſeful for many purpoſes, and they afford good
                    food when baked in an oven.</p>
                <p>Even the bones are uſeful alſo ; for by a late invention of Dr Higgins, they are
                    found, when reduced to aſhes, to be an uſeful and eſſential ingredient in the
                    compoſition of the fineſt artificial ſtone in ornamental work for
                    chimney-pieces, cornices of rooms, houſes, &amp;c. which renders the composition
                    more durable by effectually preventing its cracking<note anchored="true" n="1"
                        place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="smallcaps">(a)</hi> Any curious
                            perſon would be much entertained to ſee the manufactory of bone-aſh, new
                            carried on by Mr Miniſh of White chapel, New Road, wherein the bones of
                            ſheep and cows undergo many ingenious proceſſes. 1. There is a mill to
                            break them ; 2. A cauldron to extract their oil, marrow, and fat ; 3. A
                            reverberatory to heat them red-hot ; 4. An oven for thoſe bones to
                            moulder to aſhes; 5. A ſtill to collect the fumes of the burnt <pb
                                n="117"/>bones into a brown fluid, from whence hartſhorn is made ;
                            6. Furnaces for making parts thereof into Glauber's ſalts ; 7. A sand
                            heat containing twelve jars, for collecting; a cryſtallizing vapour into
                            ſal-ammoniac.</p></note>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">(a).</hi></p>
                <p>If it is objected to the meek inoffenſive creature, that<pb
                        facs="gri_33125011196363_0348.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s03-0342"/> he is
                    expenſive while living, in eating up our graſs, &amp;c. it may be anſwered that
                    it is quite the contrary ; for he can feed where every other animal has been
                    before him and grazed all they could find ; and that if he takes a little graſs
                    on our downs or in our fields, he amply repays us for every blade of graſs in
                    the richneſs of the manure which he leaves behind him. He protects the hands
                    from the cold wintry blaſt, by providing them with the ſofteſt leather gloves.
                    Every gentleman’s library is alſo indebted to him for the neat binding of his
                    books, for the ſheath of his ſword, and for cases for his inſtruments ; in
                    ſhort, not to be tedious in mentioning the various uſes of leather, there is
                    hardly any furniture or utenſil of life but the ſheep contributes to render
                    either more uſeful, convenient, or ornamental.</p>
                <p>As the ſheep is ſo valuable an animal, every piece of information concerning the
                    proper method of managing it muſt be of importance. It will not therefore be
                    uſeleſs nor unentertaining to give ſome account of the manner of managing ſheep
                    in Spain, a country famous for producing the beſt wool in the world.</p>
                <p>In Spain there are two kinds of ſheep : the coarſe- woolled ſheep, which always
                    remain in their native country, and are houſed every night in winter ; and the
                    fine-wooled ſheep, which are always in the open air, and travel every ſummer
                    from the cool mountains of the northern parts of Spain, to feed in winter on the
                    ſouthern warm plains of Andalusia, Mancha, and Eſtramadura. Of theſe latter, it
                    appears from accurate computations, that there are about five millions<note anchored="false" n="2" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>Bourgoanne's
                            Travels, vol. i. p. 53.</p></note> (<hi rend="smallcaps">b</hi>) ; and
                    that the wool and fleſh of a flock of 10,000 ſheep produce yearly about 24 reals
                    a head, or about the value of 12 Engliſh ſixpences, one of which belongs to the
                    owner, three to the king, and the other eight are allowed for the expences of
                    paſture, tythes, ſhepherds, dogs, ſalt, ſhearing, &amp;c. Ten thouſand ſheep
                    form a flock, which is divided into ten tribes, under the management of one
                    perſon, who has abſolute dominion over fifty ſhepherds and fifty dogs.</p>
                <p>M. Bourgoanne, a French gentleman, who reſided many years in Spain, and directed
                    his inquiries chiefly to the civil government, trade, and manufactures, of that
                    country, gives the following account of the wandering ſheep of Segovia. “ It is
                    (says he) in the neighbouring mountains that a part of the wandering ſheep feed
                    during the fine ſeaſon.<note anchored="true" n="3" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial"><p><hi rend="smallcaps">(b)</hi> In the 16th century the
                            travelling ſheep were eſtimated at ſeven millions : under Philip III.
                            the number was diminiſhed to two millions and a half. Uſtariz, who wrote
                            at the beginning of this century, made it amount to four millions. .The
                            general opinion is, that at preſent it does not exceed five millions. If
                            to this number the eight millions of ſtationary ſheep be added, it will
                            make nearly thirteen millions of animals, all managed contrary to the
                            true intereſts of Spain, for the advantage of a few individuals. For the
                            proprietors of ſtationary flocks alſo have privileges which greatly
                            reſemble thoſe of the members of the Meſta. According to Arriquebar,
                            Spain contains eight millions of fine-wooled ſheep, ten millions of
                            coarſe-wooled, and five hundred thouſand bulls, oxen, and
                        cows.</p></note> They leave them in the month of October, paſs over thoſe
                    which ſeparate the two Caſtiles, croſs New Caſtile, and diſperſe themſelves in
                    the plains of Eſtramadura and Andaluſia. For ſome years paſt thoſe of the two
                    Caſtiles, which are within reach of the Sierra-Morena, go thither to paſs the
                    winter ; which, in that part of Spain, is more mild : the length of their day’s
                    journey is in proportion to the paſture they meet with. They travel in flocks
                    from 1000 to 1200 in number, under the conduct of two ſhepherds ; one of whom is
                    called the <hi rend="italic">Mayoral,</hi> the other the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Zagal.</hi> When arrived at the place of their deſtination, they are
                    diſtributed in the paſtures previouſly aſſigned them. They return in the month
                    of April ; and whether it be habit or natural inſtinct that draws them towards
                    the climate, which at this ſeaſon becomes moſt proper for them, the inquietude
                    which they manifeſt might, in case of need, ſerve as an almanac to their
                    conductors.”</p>
                <p>Mr Arthur Young, in that patriotic work which he conducted with great induſtry
                    and judgment, the Annals of Agriculture, gives us a very accurate and
                    intereſting account of the Pyrenean or Catalonian ſheep.</p>
                <p>“ On the northern ridge, bearing to the west, are the paſtures of the Spaniſh
                    flocks. This ridge is not, however, the whole ; there are two other mountains,
                    quite in a different ſituation, and the ſheep travel from one to another as the
                    paſturage is ſhort or plentiful. I examined the ſoil of theſe mountain paſtures,
                    and found it in general ſtony ; what in the west of England would be called a st
                        <hi rend="italic">one brash,</hi> with ſome mixture of loam, and in a few
                    places a little peaty. The plants are many of them untouched by the ſheep ; many
                    ferns, narciſſus, violets, &amp;c. but burnet <hi rend="italic">(poterium
                        ſanguisorba}</hi> and the narrow-leaved plantain <hi rend="italic">(plantago
                        lanceοlata)</hi> were eaten, as may be ſuppoſed, cloſe. I looked for
                    trefoils, but found ſcarcely any : it was very apparent that ſoil and
                    peculiarity of herbage had little to do in rendering theſe heights proper for
                    ſheep. In the northern parts of Europe, the tops of mountains half the height of
                    theſe (for we were above ſnow in July) are bogs, all are ſo which I have ſeen in
                    our iſlands, or at leaſt the proportion of dry land is very trifling to that
                    which is extremely wet : Here they are in general very dry. Now a great range of
                    dry land, let the plants be what they may, will in every country suit ſheep. The
                    flock is brought every night to one ſpot, which is ſituated at the end of the
                    valley on the river I have mentioned, and near the port or paſſage of Picada :
                    it is a level ſpot ſheltered from all winds. The ſoil is 8 or 9 inches deep of
                    old dung, not at all incloſed : from the freedom from wood all around, it ſeems
                    to be choſen partly for ſafety againſt wolves and bears. Near it is a very large
                    ſtone, or rather rock, fallen from the mountain. This the ſhepherds have taken
                    for a ſhelter, and have built a hut againſt it ; their beds are ſheep-ſkins, and
                    their door ſa ſmall that they crawl in. I faw no place for fire ; but they have
                    it, ſince they dress here the fleſh of their ſheep,<pb
                        facs="gri_33125011196363_0349.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s03-0343"/> and in the
                    night ſometimes keep off the bears, by whirling fire-brands : four of them
                    belonging to the flock mentioned above lie here. I viewed their flock very
                    carefully, and by means of our guide and interpreter, made ſome inquiries of the
                    ſhepherds, which they anſwered readily, and very civilly. A Spaniard at
                    Venaſque, a city in the Pyrenees, gives 600 livres French (the livre is 10 ½d.
                    Engliſh) a-year for the paſturage of this flock of 2000 ſheep. In the winter he
                    ſends them into the lower parts of Catalonia, a journey of 12 or 13 days, and
                    when the ſnow is melted in the ſpring, they are conducted back again. They are
                    the whole year kept in motion, and moving from ſpot to ſpot, which is owing to
                    the great range they everywhere have of paſture. They are always in the open
                    air, never houſed or under cover, and never taſte of any food but what they can
                    find on the hills.</p>
                <p>“ Four ſhepherds, and from four to six large Spaniſh dogs, have the care of this
                    flock: the lacter are in France called of the <hi rend="italic">Pyrenees breed
                        ;</hi> they are black and white, of the ſize of a large wolf, a large head
                    and neck, armed with collars ſtuck with iron ſpikes. No wolf can ſtand againſt
                    them ; but bears are more potent adversaries : if a bear can reach a tree, he is
                    ſafe; he rises on his hind legs, with his back to the tree, and ſets the dogs at
                    defiance. In the night the ſhepherds rely entirely on their dogs ; but on
                    hearing them bark are ready with fire-arms, as the dogs rarely bark if a bear is
                    not at hand. I was ſurpriſed to find that they are fed only with bread and milk.
                    The head ſhepherd is paid 120 livres a-year wages and bread ; the others 80
                    livres and bread. But they are allowed to keep goats, of which they have many
                    which they milk every day. Their food is milk and bread, except the fleſh of
                    ſuch ſheep or lambs as accidents give them. The head ſhepherd keeps on the
                    mountain top, or an elevated ſpot, from whence he can the better see around
                    while the flock traverses the declivities. In doing this the ſheep are expoſed
                    to great danger in places that are ſtony ; for by walking among the rocks, and
                    eſpecially the goats, they move the ſtones, which, rolling down the hills,
                    acquire an accelerated force enough to knock a man down, and ſheep are often
                    killed by them ; yet we ſaw how alert they were to avoid ſuch ſtones, and
                    cautiouſly on their guard againſt them. I examined the ſheep attentively. They
                    are in general polled, but ſome have horns ; which in the rams turn backwards
                    behind the ears and project half a circle forward ; the ewes horns turn alſo
                    behind the ears, but do not project : the legs white or reddiſh ; ſpeckled
                    faces, ſome white, ſome reddiſh ; they would weigh fat, I reckon, on an average,
                    from 15 lb. to 18 lb. a quarter. Some tails ſhort, ſome left long. A few black
                    ſheep among them : ſome with a very little tuft of wool on their foreheads. On
                    the whole they reſemble thoſe on the South Downs ; their legs are as ſhort as
                    thoſe of that breed ; a point which merits obſervation, as they travel ſo much
                    and ſo well. Their ſhape is very good ; round ribs and flat ſtraight backs ; and
                    would with us be reckoned handſome ſheep ; all in good order and fleſh. In order
                    to be ſtill better acquainted with them, I deſired one of the ſhepherds to catch
                    a ram for me to feel, and examine the wool, which I found very thick and good of
                    the carding sort, as may be ſuppoſed, I took a ſpecimen of it,</p>
                <p>and also of a hoggit, or lamb of laſt year. In regard to the mellow ſoftneſs
                    under the ſkin, which, in Mr Bakewell’s opinion, is a ſtrong indication of a
                    good breed, with a diſpoſition to fatten, he had it in a much ſuperior degree to
                    many of our Engliſh breeds, to the full as much ſo as the South Downs, which are
                    for that point the beſt ſhort-woolled ſheep which I know in England. The fleece
                    was on his back, and weighed, as I gueſſed, about 8 lb. Engliſh ; but the
                    average, they ſay, of the flock is from four to five, as I calculated by
                    reducing the Catalonian pound of 12 oz. to ours of 16, and is all sold to the
                    French at 30s. the lb. French. This ram had the wool of the back part of his
                    neck tied cloſe, and the upper tuft tied a ſecond knot by way of ornament; nor
                    do they ever ſhear this part of the fleece for that reaſon : we ſaw ſeveral in
                    the flock with this ſpecies of decoration. They ſaid that this ram would ſell in
                    Catalonia for 20 livres. A circumſtance which cannot be too much commended, and
                    deferves univerſal imitation, is the extreme docility they accuſtom them to.
                    When I deſired the ſhepherd to catch one of his rams, I ſuppoſed he would do it
                    with his crook, or probably not be able to do it at all ; but he walked into the
                    flock, and ſingling out a ram and a goat, bid them follow him, which they did
                    immediately ; and he talked to them while they were obeying him, holding out his
                    hand as if to give them ſomething. By this method he brought me the ram, which I
                    caught, and held without difficulty.”</p>
                <p>The beſt sort of ſheep for fine wool are thoſe bred in Herefordſhire, Bevonſhire,
                    and Worceſterſhire ; but they are ſmall, and black-faced, and bear but a ſmall
                    quantity. Warwick, Leiceſterſhire, Buckingham, and Northamptonſhire, breed a
                    large-boned ſheep, of the beſt ſhape and deepeſt wool we have. The marſhes of
                    Lincolnſhire breed a very large kind of ſheep, but their wool is not good,
                    unleſs the breed be mended by bringing in ſheep of other counties among them,
                    which is a scheme of late very profitably followed there. In this county, it is
                    no uncommon thing to give fifty guineas for a ram, and a guinea for the
                    admiſſion of an ewe to one of theſe valuable males, or twenty guineas for the
                    uſe of it for a certain number of ewes during one ſeaſon. Suffolk alſo breeds a
                    very valuable kind of ſheep. The northern counties in general breed ſheep with
                    long but hairy wool : however, the wool which is taken from the neck and
                    ſhoulders of the Yorkſhire ſheep is uſed for mixing with Spaniſh wool in ſome of
                    their fineſt cloths.</p>
                <p>Wales bears a ſmall hardy kind of ſheep, which has the beſt taſted fleſh, but the
                    worſt wool of all. Nevertheleſs it is of more extensive uſe than the fineſt
                    Segovian fleeces ; for the benefit oſ the flannel manufacture is univerſally
                    known. The ſheep of Ireland vary like thoſe of Great Britain : thoſe of the
                    ſouth and eaſt being large and their fleſh rank : those of the north and the
                    mountainous parts ſmall and their fleſh ſweet. The fleeces in the same manner
                    differ in degrees of value. Scotland breeds a ſmall kind, and their fleeces are
                    coarſe.</p>
                <p>But the new Leiceſterſhire breed is the moſt faſhionable, and of courſe the moſt
                    profitable breed in the iſland. Joſeph Altom of Clifton, who railed himſelf from
                    a plough-boy, was the firſt who diſtinguiſhed him-<pb
                        facs="gri_33125011196363_0350.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s03-0344"/> ſelf in the
                    midland counties of England for a ſuperior breed of sheep. How he improved his
                    breed is not known ; but it was cuſtomary for eminent farmers in his time to go
                    to Clifton in ſummer to chooſe and purchaſe ram-lambs, for which they paid two
                    or three guineas. This man was ſucceeded by Mr Bakewell ; and it may reaſonably
                    be ſuppoſed that the breed, by means of Altom’s ſtock, had paſſed the firſt
                    ſtage of improvement before Mr Bakewell’s time. Still, however, it muſt be
                    acknowledged, that the Leiceſterſhire breed of ſheep owes its preſent high ſtate
                    of improvement to the ability and care of Mr Bakewell.</p>
                <p>“ The manner in which Mr Bakewell raiſed his ſheep to the degree of celebrity in
                    which they deſervedly ſtand, is, notwithſtanding the recentneſs of the
                    improvement, and its being done in the day of thouſands now living, a thing in
                    diſpute ; even among men high in the profeſſion, and living in the very diſtrict
                    in which the improvement has been carried on !</p>
                <p>“ Some are of opinion that he effected it by a croſs with the Wiltſhire breed ;
                    an improbable idea, as their form altogether contradicts it : others, that the
                    Ryeland breed were uſed for this purpoſe ; and with ſome ſhow of probability. If
                    any croſs whatever was uſed, the Ryeland breed, whether we view the form, the
                    ſize, the wool, the fleſh, or the fatting quality, is the most probable
                    instrument of improvement.</p>
                <p>“ Theſe ideas, however, are regiſtered merely as matters of opinion. It is more
                    than probable that Mr Bakewell alone is in poſſeſſion of the ſeveral minutiæ of
                    improvement ; and the public can only hope that at a proper time the facts may
                    be communicated for the direction of future improvers.</p>
                <p>“Whenever this ſhall take place, it will moſt probably come out that no croſs
                    with any alien breed whatever has been uſed ; but that the improvement has been
                    effected by ſelecting individuals from kindred breeds ; from the ſeveral breeds
                    or varieties of long-woolled ſheep, with which Mr Bakewell was ſurrounded on
                    almoſt every ſide, and by breeding, <hi rend="italic">inandin</hi><note
                        anchored="true" n="4" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>(c) <hi
                                rend="italic">Inandin</hi> is a term uſed in the midland counties of
                            England to cxpreſs breeding from the ſame family.</p></note> (c), with
                    this ſelection : ſolicitouſly ſeizing the ſuperior accidental varieties
                    produced; aſſociating theſe varieties; and ſtill continuing to ſelect, with
                    judgment, the ſuperior individuals.</p>
                <p>“ It now remains to give a deſcription of the ſuperior claſs of individuals of
                    this breed, eſpecially ewes and wedders, in full condition, but not immoderately
                    fat. The rams will require to be diſtinguiſhed afterwards.</p>
                <p>“ The head is long, ſmall, and hornleſs, with ears ſomewhat long, and standing
                    backward, and with the noſe ſhooting forward. The neck thin, and clean toward
                    the head ; but taking a conical form ; ſtanding low, and enlarging every way at
                    the baſe ; the fore-end altogether ſhort. The boſom broad, with the ſhoulders,
                    ribs, and chine extraordinary full. The loin broad, and the back level. The
                    haunches comparatively full toward the hips, but light downward ; being
                    altogether ſmall in proportion to the fore-parts. The legs, at preſent, of a
                    moderate length ; with the bone extremely fine. The bone throughout remarkably
                    light. The</p>
                <p>carcaſe, when fully fat, takes a remarkable form ; much wider than it is deep,
                    and almoſt as broad as it is long. Full on the ſhoulder, wideſt on the ribs,
                    narrowing with a regular curve towards the tail ; approaching the form of the
                    turtle nearer perhaps than any other animal. The pelt is thin, and the tail
                    ſmall. The wool is ſhorter than long wools in general, but much longer than the
                    middle wools ; the ordinary length of ſtaple five to ſeven inches, varying much
                    in fineneſs and weight.”</p>
                <p>This breed ſurpaſſes every other in beauty of form ; they are full and weighty in
                    the fore quarters ; and are remarkable for ſmallneſs of bone. Mr Marſhall, who
                    has been of ſo much benefit to agriculture and his country by his publications,
                    informs us, in his Rural Economy of the Midland Counties, that he has ſeen a rib
                    of a ſheep of this breed contraſted with one of a Norfolk ſheep : the diſparity
                    was ſtriking ; the latter nearly twice the ſize ; while the meat which covered
                    the former was three times the thickneſs ; conſequently the proportion of meat
                    to bone was in the one incomparably greater than in the other. Therefore, in
                    this point of view, the improved breed has a decided preference : for ſurely
                    while mankind continue to eat fleſh and throw away bone, the former muſt be, to
                    the confirmer at leaſt, the more valuable.</p>
                <p>The criterions of good and bad fleſh while the animal is alive differ in
                    different ſpecies, and are not properly ſettled in the ſame ſpecies. One
                    ſuperior breeder is of opinion, that if the fleſh is not looſe, it is of courſe
                    good ; holding, that the fleſh of ſheep is never found in a ſtate of hardneſs,
                    like that of ill-fleſhed cattle : while others make a fourfold diſtinction of
                    the fleſh of ſheep ; as looſeneſs, mellowness, firmneſs, hardneſs : conſidering
                    the firſt and the laſt equally exceptionable, and the second and third equally
                    deſirable ; a happy mixture of the two being deemed the point of perfection.</p>
                <p>The fleſh of ſheep, when ſlaughtered, is well known to be of various qualities.
                    Some is compoſed of large coarſe grains, interſperſed with wide empty pores like
                    a ſponge : others, of large grains, with wide pores filled with fat ; others, of
                    fine cloſe grains, with ſmaller pores filled with fat : and a fourth, of cloſe
                    grains, without any intermixture of fatneſs.</p>
                <p>The fleſh of ſheep, when dreſſed, is equally well known to poſſeſs a variety of
                    qualities : ſome mutton is coarſe, dry, and inſipid ; a dry ſponge, affording
                    little or no gravy of any colour. Another sort is ſomewhat firmer, imparting a
                    light-coloured gravy only. A third plump, ſhort, and palatable ; affording a
                    mixture of white and red gravy. A fourth likewiſe plump and well-flavoured, but
                    diſcharging red gravy, and this in various quantities.</p>
                <p>It is likewiſe obſervable, that ſome mutton, when dreſſed, appears covered with a
                    thick, tough, parchment-like integument ; others with a membrane comparatively
                    fine and flexible. But theſe, and ſome of the other qualities of mutton, may not
                    be wholly owing to breed, but in part to the age and the ſtate of fatneſs at the
                    time of daughter. Examined in this light, whe<pb
                        facs="gri_33125011196363_0351.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s03-0345"/>ther we
                    consider the degree of fatneſs, or their natural propenſity to a ſtate of
                    fatneſs, even at as early age, the improved breed of Leiceſterſhire ſheep appear
                    with many superior advantages.</p>
                <p>The degree of fatneſs to which the individuals of this breed are capable of being
                    raised, will perhaps appear incredible to thoſe who have not had an opportunity
                    of being convinced by their own obſervation. “ I have ſeen wedders (ſays Mr
                    Marſhall) of only two ſhear (two to three years old) ſo loaded with fat as to be
                    ſcarcely able to make a run ; and whoſe fat lay ſo much without the bone, it
                    ſeemed ready to be ſhaken from the ribs on the ſmalleſt agitation.</p>
                <p>" It is common for the ſheep of this breed to have ſuch a projection of fat upon
                    the ribs, immediately behind the shoulder, that it may be eaſily gathered up in
                    the hand, as the flank of a fat bullock. Hence it has gained, in technical
                    language, the name of the fore-flank { a point which a modern breeder never
                    fails to touch in judging of the quality of this breed of ſheep.</p>
                <p>“ What is, perhaps, ſtill more extraordinary, it is not rare for the rams, at
                    leaſt of this breed, to be ‘ cracked on the back ; that is, to be cloven along
                    the top of the chine, in the manner fat ſheep generally are upon the rump. This
                    mark is considered as an evidence of the beſt blood.</p>
                <p>" Extraordinary, however, as are theſe appearances while the animals are living,
                    the facts are ſtill more ſtriking after they arc ſlaughtered. At Litchfield, in
                    February 1785, I law a fore quarter of mutton, fatted by Mr Rrincep of Croxall,
                    and which meaſured upon the ribs four inches of fat. It muſt be acknowledged,
                    however, that the Leiceſterſhire breed do not produce ſo much wool as most other
                    long-woolled ſheep.”</p>
                <p>As the practice of letting rams by the ſeason is now become profitable, it may be
                    uſeful to mention the method of rearing them.</p>
                <p>“ The principal ram-breeders save annually twenty, thirty, or perhaps forty ram
                    lambs ; caſtration being ſeldom applied, in the firſt inſtance, to the produce
                    of a valuable ram, for in the choice of theſe lambs they are led more by blood,
                    or parentage, than by form ; on which, at an early age, little dependence can be
                    placed. Their treatment from the time they are weaned, in July or Auguſt, until
                    the time of ſhearing, the firſt week in June, consiſts in giving them every
                    indulgence of keep, in order to puſh them forward for the ſhow ; it being the
                    common practice to let ſuch as are fit to be let the firſt ſeason, while they
                    are yet yearlings—provincially ‘ ſharhogs.’</p>
                <p>“ Their firſt paſture, after weaning, is pretty generally,</p>
                <p>I believe, clover that has been mown early, and has got a second time into head ;
                    the heads of clover being conſidered as a moſt forcing food of ſheep. After this
                    goes off, turnips, cabbages, colewort, with hay, and (report ſays) with corn.
                    But the uſe of this, the breeders ſeverally deny, though collectively they may
                    be liable to the charge.</p>
                <p>“ Be this as it may, ſomething conſiderable depends on the art of making up, not
                    lambs only, but rams of all ages. Fat, like charity, covers a multitude of
                    faults ; and beſides, is the beſt evidence of their fatting quality wſhich their
                    owners can produce (i. e their natural propenſity to a ſtate of fatneſs), while
                    in the fatneſs of the</p>
                <p>ſharhogs is ſeen theſe degree of inclination to fat at an early age.</p>
                <p>“ Fatting quality being the one thing needful in grazing ſtock, and being found,
                    in ſome conſiderable degree at leaſt, to be hereditary, the ſattest rams are of
                    courte the beſt ; though other attachments, well or ill placed, as to form or
                    faſhionable points, will perhaps, have equal or greater weight in the minds of
                    ſome men, even in this enlightened age. Such ſhearlings as will not make up
                    ſufficiently as to form and fatneſs, are either kept on to another year to give
                    them a fair chance, or are caſtrated, or butchered while ſharhogs.”</p>
                <p>From the firſt letting, about 40 years ago, to the year 1780, the prices kept
                    gradually rising from fifteen ſhillings to a guinea, and from one to ten. In
                    1780 Mr Bakewell let ſeveral at ten guineas each ; and, what is rather
                    inexplicable, Mr Parkinſon of Quarndon let one the ſame year for twenty-five
                    guineas; a price which then aſtoniſhed the whole country.</p>
                <p>From that time to 1786 Mr Bakewell’s ſtock roſe rapidly from ten to a hundred
                    guineas ; and that year he let two thirds of one ram (reſerving one third of the
                    uſual number of ewes to himſelf) to two principal breeders, for a hundred
                    guineas each, the entire ſervices of the ram being rated at three hundred
                    guineas ! Mr Bakewell making that year, by letting twenty rams only, more than a
                    thouſand pounds !</p>
                <p>Since that time the prices have been ſtill riſing. Four hundred guineas have been
                    repeatedly given. Mr Bake- well, this year (1789) makes, ſays Mr Marſhall,
                    twelve hundred guineas by three rams (brothers, we believe); two thouſand of
                    ſeven ; and of his whole letting, full three thouſand guineas !</p>
                <p>Beſide this extraordinary ſum made by Mr Bakewell, there are six or ſeven other
                    breeders who make from five hundred to a thouſand guineas each. The whole amount
                    of monies produced that year in the Midland Counties, by letting rams of the
                    modern breed for one ſeason only, is eſtimated, by thoſe who are adequate to the
                    ſubject, at the almoſt incredible ſum of ten thouſand pounds.</p>
                <p>Rams previous to the ſeaſon are reduced from the cumbrous fat ſtate in which they
                    are ſhown. The uſual time of ſending them out is the middle of September. They
                    are conveyed in carriages of two wheels with ſprings, or hung in flings, 20 or
                    30 miles a-day, ſometimes to the diſtance of 200 or 300 miles. They are not
                    turned loose among the ewes, but kept apart in a ſmall incloſure, where a couple
                    of ewes only are admitted at once. When the ſeaſon is over every care is taken
                    to make the rams look as fat and handſome as poſſible.</p>
                <p>In the choice of ewes the breeder is led by the ſame criterions as in the choice
                    of rams. Breed is the firſt object of conſideration. Excellency, in any ſpecies
                    or variety of live-ſtock, cannot be attained with any degree of certainty, let
                    the male be ever ſo excellent, unleſs the females employed likewiſe inherit a
                    large proportion of the genuine blood, be the ſpecies or variety what it may.
                    Hence no prudent naan ventures to give the higher prices for the Diſhley rams,
                    unless his ewes are deeply tinctured with the Diſhley blood. Next to breed is
                    fleſh, fat, form, and wool.</p>
                <p>After the lambs are weaned, the ewes are kept in common feeding places, without
                    any alteration of pas<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0352.tif"
                        xml:id="eb03-17-s03-0346"/>ture, previous to their taking the ram. In winter
                    they are kept on graſs, hay, turnips, and cabbages. As the heads of the modern
                    breed are much finer than moſt others, the ewes lamb with leſs difficulty.</p>
                <p>The female lambs, on being weaned, are put to good keep, but have not ſuch high
                    indulgence ſhown them as the males, the prevailing practice being to keep them
                    from the ram the firſt autumn.</p>
                <p>At weaning time, or previouſly to the admiſſion of the ram, the ewes are culled,
                    to make room for the thaves or ſhearlings, whoſe ſuperior blood and faſhion
                    intitle them to a place in the breeding flock. In the work of culling, the
                    ram-breeder and the mere grazier go by ſomewhat different guides. The grazier’s
                    guide is principally age, ſeldom giving his ewes the ram after they are four
                    shear. The ram-breeder, on the contrary, goes chiefly by merit ; an ewe that has
                    brought him a good ram or two is continued in the flock ſo long as ſhe will
                    breed. There are inſtances of ewes having been prolific to the tenth or twelfth
                    year ; but in general the ewes of this breed go off at six or ſeven ſhear.</p>
                <p>In the practice of ſome of the principal ram-breeders, the culling ewes are never
                    ſuffered to go out of their hands until after they are ſlaughtered, the breeders
                    not only fatting them, but having them butchered, on their premiſes. There are
                    others, however, who ſell them ; and ſometimes at extraordinary prices. Three,
                    four, and even ſo high as ten, guineas each have been given for theſe
                    outcaſts.</p>
                <p>There are in the flocks of ſeveral breeders ewes that would fetch at auction
                    twenty guineas each. Mr Bakewell is in poſſeſſion of ewes which, if they were
                    now put up to be fold to the beſt bidder, would, it is eſtimated, fetch no leſs
                    than fifty each, and perhaps, through the preſent ſpirit of contention, much
                    higher prices.</p>
                <p>The following inſtructions for purchaſing ſheep, we hope, will be acceptable to
                    our country readers.— The farmer ſhould always buy his ſheep from a worſe land
                    than his own, and they ſhould be big-boned, and have a long greaſy wool, curling
                    cloſe and well. Theſe ſheep always breed the fineſt wool, and are alſo the moſt
                    approved of by the butcher ſor ſale in the market. For the choice of ſheep to
                    breed, the ram muſt be young, and his skin of the ſame colour with his wool, for
                    the lambs will be of the ſame colour with his ſkin. He ſhould have a large long
                    body ; a broad forehead, round, and well riſing ; large eyes ; and ſtraight and
                    ſhort noſtrils. The polled ſheep, that is, thoſe which have no horns, are found
                    to be the best breeders. The ewe ſhould have a broad back ; a large bending neck
                    ; ſmall, but ſhort, clean, and nimble legs ; and a thick, deep wool covering her
                    all over.</p>
                <p>To know whether they be found or not, the farmer ſhould examine the wool that
                    none of it ſhe wanting, and ſee that the gums be red, the teeth white and even,
                    and the briſket ſkin red, the wool firm, the breath ſweet, and the feet not hot.
                    Two years old is the beſt time for beginning to breed; and their firſt lambs
                    ſhould not be kept too long, to weaken them by ſuckling, but be fold as soon as
                    conveniently may be. They will breed advantageouſly till they are ſeven years
                    old. The farmers have a method, of knowing the age of a ſheep, as a horſe’s is
                    known, by the mouth. When a ſheep</p>
                <p>is one ſhear, as they expreſs it, it has two broad teeth before ; when it is two
                    ſhear, it will have four ; when three, six ; and when four, eight. After this
                    .their mouths begin to break.</p>
                <p>The difference of land makes a very great difference in the ſheep. The fat
                    paſtures breed ſtraight tall ſheep, and the barren hills and downs breed ſquare
                    ſhort ones ; woods and mountains breed tall and ſlender ſheep ; but the beſt of
                    all are thoſe bred upon new-ploughed land and dry grounds. On the contrary, all
                    wet and moist lands are bad for ſheep, eſpecially ſuch as are ſubject to be
                    overflowed, and to have sand and dirt left on them. The ſalt marſhes are,
                    however, an exception to this general rule, for their ſaltneſs makes amends for
                    their moiſture ; ſalt, by reaſon of its drying quality, being of great advantage
                    to ſheep.</p>
                <p>As to the time of putting the rams to the ewes, the farmer muſt consider at what
                    time of the ſpring his graſs will be fit to maintain them and their lambs, and
                    whether he has turnips to do it till the graſs comes ; for very often both the
                    ewes and lambs are deſtroyed by the want of food ; or if this does not happen,
                    it the lambs are only ſtinted in their growth by it, it is an accident that they
                    never recover. The ewe goes 20 weeks with lamb, and according to this it is eaſy
                    to calculate the proper time. The beſt time for them to yean is in April, unleſs
                    the owner has very forward graſs or turnips, or the ſheep are field ſheep. Where
                    you have not incloſures to keep them in, then it may be proper they ſhould yean
                    in January, that the lambs may be ſtrong by May-day, and be able to follow the
                    dam over the fallows and water-furrows ; but then the lambs that come ſo early
                    muſt have a great deal of care taken of them, and ſo indeed ſhould all other
                    lambs at their firſt falling, elſe while they are weak the crows and magpies
                    will pick their eyes out.</p>
                <p>When the ſheep are turned into fields of wheat or rye to feed, it muſt not be too
                    rank at firſt, for if it be, it generally throws them into ſcourings. Ewes that
                    are big ſhould be kept but bare, for it is very dangerous to them to be fat at
                    the time of their bringing forth their young. They may be well fed, indeed, like
                    cows, a fortnight beforehand, to put them in. heart- Mortimer’s Huſhandry, p.
                    243.</p>
                <p>The feeding ſheep with turnips is one great advantage to the farmers. When they
                    are made to eat turnips they soon fatten, but there is some difficulty in
                    bringing this about. The old ones always refuſe them at firſt, and will
                    ſometimes faſt three or four days, till almoſt famiſhed ; but the young lambs
                    fall to at oncs. The common way, in ſome places, of turning a flock of ſheep at
                    large into a field of turnips, is very diſadvantageous, for they will thus
                    deſtroy as many in a fortnight as would keep them a whole winter. There are
                    three other ways of feeding them on this food, all of which have their ſeveral
                    advantages.</p>
                <p>The firſt way is to divide the land by hurdles, and allow the ſheep to come upon
                    ſuch a portion only at a time as they can eat in one day, and ſo advance the
                    hurdles farther into the ground daily till all be eaten. This is infinitely
                    better than the former random method; but they never eat them clean even this
                    way, but leave the bottoms and outsides ſcooped in the ground : the people pull
                    up theſe indeed with iron crooks, and lay them before the ſheep again, but they
                    are common<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0353.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s03-0347"/>ly
                    ſo fouled with the creature’s dung and urine, and with the dirt from their feet,
                    that they do not care for them ; they eat but little of them, and what they do
                    eat does not nouriſh them like the freſh roots.</p>
                <p>The ſecond way is by incloſing the ſheep in hurdles, as in the former; but in
                    this they pull up all the turnips which they ſuppoſe the ſheep can eat in one
                    day, and daily remove the hurdles over the ground whence they have pulled up the
                    turnips : by this means there is no waſte, and leſs expence, for a perſon may in
                    two hours pull up all thoſe turnips ; the remaining ſhells of which would have
                    employed three or four labourers a-day to get up with their crooks out of the
                    ground trodden hard by the feet of the ſheep ; and the worſt is, that as in the
                    method of pulling up firſt, the turnips are eaten up clean ; in this way, by the
                    hook, they are waſted, the ſheep do not eat any great part of them, and when the
                    ground comes to be tilled afterwards for a crop of corn, the fragments of the
                    turnip's are ſeen in ſuch quantities on the ſurface, that half the crop at leaſt
                    ſeems to have been waſted.</p>
                <p>The third manner is to pull up the turnips, and remove them in a cart or waggon
                    to ſome other place, ſpreading them on a freſh place every day ; by this method
                    the ſheep will eat them up clean, both root and leaves. The great advantage of
                    this method is, when there is a piece land not far off which wants dung more
                    than that where the turnips grew, which perhaps is alſo too wet for the ſheep in
                    winter, and then the turnips will, by the too great moiſture and dirt of the
                    soil, ſometimes ſpoil the ſheep, and give them the rot. Yet ſuch ground will
                    often bring forth more and larger turnips than dry land, and when they are
                    carried off, and eaten by the ſheep on ploughed land, in dry weather, and on
                    green ſward in wet weather, the ſheep will ſucceed much better ; and the moiſt
                    soil where the turnips grew not being trodden by the ſheep, will be much fitter
                    for a crop of corn than if they had been fed with turnips on it. The expence of
                    hurdles, and the trouble of moving them, are ſaved in this cafe, which will
                    counterbalance at leaſt the expence of pulling the turnips and carrying them to
                    the places where they are to be eaten. They muſt always be carried off for
                    oxen.</p>
                <p>The diſeaſes to which ſheep are ſubject are theſe, rot, red-water, foot-rot and
                    hoving, ſcab, dunt, rickets, fly-ſtruck, flux, and burſting. Of each of theſe we
                    ſhall give the beſt deſcription in our power, with the moſt approved
                    remedies.</p>
                <p>The rot, which is a very pernicious diſeaſe, has of late engaged the attention of
                    ſcientific farmers. But neither its nature nor its cauſe has yet been fully
                    aſcertained. Some valuable and judicious obſervations have, however, been made
                    upon it, which ought to be circulated, as they may perhaps, in many caſes,
                    furniſh an antidote for this malignant diſtemper, or be the means of leading
                    others to ſome more efficacious remedy. Some have ſuppoſed the rot owing to the
                    quick growth of graſs or herbs that grow in wet places. Without premising, that
                    all-bounteous Providence has given to every animal its peculiar taſte, by which
                    it diſtinguiſhes the food proper tor its preſervation and support, if not
                    vitiated by fortuitous circumſtances, it ſeems very difficult to diſcover on
                    philoſophical principles why the quick growth of graſs ſhould render it noxious,
                    or why any herb ſhould at one ſeaſon produce fatal effects, by the admiſſion of
                    pure water only into its component parts, which at other times is perfectly
                    innocent, although brought to its utmoſt ſtrength and maturity by the genial
                    influence of the ſun. Beſides, the constant practice of moſt farmers in the
                    kingdom, who with the greateſt ſecurity feed their meadows in the ſpring, when
                    the graſs ſhoots quick and is full of juices, militates directly againſt this
                    opinion.</p>
                <p>Mr Arthur Young, to whom agriculture is much indebted, aſcribes this diſeaſe to
                    moiſture. In confirmation of this opinion, which has been generally adopted, we
                    are informed, in the Bath Society papers<note anchored="true" n="5" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>* Vol. I. art. xlvi.</p></note> *, by
                    a correſpondent, that there was a paddock adjoining to his park which had for
                    ſeveral years cauſed the rot in moſt of the ſheep which were put into it. In
                    1769 he drained it, and from that time his ſheep were free from this malady. But
                    there are facts which render it doubtful that moiſture is the ſole cauſe. We are
                    told, the dry limed land in Derbyſhire will produce the rot as well as water
                    meadows and stagnant marſhes ; and that in ſome wet grounds ſheep ſuſtain no
                    injury for many weeks.</p>
                <p>Without attempting to enumerate other hypotheſes which the ingenious have formed
                    on this ſubject, we ſhall purſue a different method in order to diſcover the
                    cauſe. On diſſecting ſheep that die of this diſorder, a great number of infects
                    called <hi rend="italic">flukes</hi> (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Fasciola)</hi>
                    are found in the liver. That theſe flukes are the cauſe of the rot, therefore,
                    is evident ; but to explain how they come into the liver is not ſo eaſy. It is
                    probable that they are ſwallowed by the ſheep along with their food while in the
                    egg ſtate. The eggs depoſited in the tender germ are conveyed with the food into
                    the ſtomach and inteſtines of the animals, whence they are received into the
                    lacteal veſſels, carried off in the chyle, and paſs into the blood ; nor do they
                    meet with any obſtruction until they arrive at the capillary veſſels of the
                    liver. Here, as the blood filtrates through the extreme branches, anſwering to
                    thoſe of the <hi rend="italic">vena porta</hi> in the human body, the ſecerning
                    veſſels are too minute to admit the impregnated ova, which, adhering to the
                    membrane, produce thoſe animalculæ that feed upon the liver and deſtroy the
                    ſheep. They much reſemble the flat fiſh called plaice, are ſometimes as large as
                    a silver two-pence, and are found both in the liver and in the pipe (anſwering
                    to that of the <hi rend="italic">vena cava}</hi> which conveys the blood from
                    the liver to the heart.</p>
                <p>The common and moſt obvious objection to that opinion is, that this insect is
                    never found but in the liver, or in ſome parts of the viſcera, of ſheep that are
                    diſeaſed more or leſs ; and that they muſt therefore be bred there. But this
                    objection will loſe its force, when we consider that many infects undergo
                    ſeveral changes, and exiſtunder forms extremely different from each other. Some
                    of them may therefore appear and be well known under one ſhape, and not known to
                    be the same under a ſecond or third. The fluke may be the laſt ſtate of ſome
                    aquatic animal which we at preſent very well know under one or other of its
                    previous forms.</p>
                <p>If this be admitted, it is eaſy to conceive that ſheep may, on wet ground
                    eſpecially, take multitudes of theſe ova or eggs in with their food ; and that
                    the ſtomach and viſcera of the ſheep being a proper nidus for them, they of
                    courſe hatch, and appearing in their fluke<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0354.tif"
                        xml:id="eb03-17-s03-0348"/> or laſt ſtate, feed on the liver of the animal,
                    and occasion this diſorder.</p>
                <p>It is a ſingular fact, “ that no ewe ever has the rot while ſhe has a lamb by her
                    ſide.” The reaſon of this may be, that the impregnated ovum passes into the
                    milk, and never arrives at the liver. The rot is fatal to ſheep, hares, and
                    rabbits, and ſometimes to calves ; but never infeſts animals of a larger
                    ſize.</p>
                <p>Miller says that parſley is a good remedy for the rot in ſheep. Perhaps a ſtrong
                    decoction of this plant, or the oil extracted from its ſeeds, might be of
                    ſervice. Salt is alſo a uſeful remedy. It ſeems to be an acknowledged fact that
                    ſalt marſhes never produce the rot. Salt indeed is pernicious to most infects.
                    Common ſalt and water expel worms from the human body; and ſea-weed, if laid in
                    a garden, will drive away infects ; but if the ſalt is ſeparated by ſteeping it
                    in the pureſt ſpring-water for a few days, it abounds with animalcule of various
                    ſpecies.</p>
                <p>Liſle, in his book of huſbandry, informs us of a farmer who cured his whole flock
                    of the rot by giving each ſheep a handful of Spaniſh ſalt for five or six
                    mornings ſucceſſively. The hint was probably taken from the Spaniards, who
                    frequently give their ſheep ſalt to keep them healthy. On ſome farms perhaps the
                    utmoſt caution cannot always prevent this diſorder. In wet and warm ſeaſons the
                    prudent farmer will remove his ſheep from the lands liable to rot. Thoſe who
                    have it not in their power to do this may give each ſheep a ſpoonful of common
                    ſalt, with the ſame quantity of flour, in a quarter of a pint of water, once or
                    twice a-week. When the rot is recently taken, the ſame remedy given four or five
                    mornings ſucceſſively will in all probability effect a cure. The addition of the
                    flour and water (in the opinion of Mr Price of Saliſhury, to whole excellent
                    paper in the Bath Society’s Tranſactions we own ourſelves much indebted) will
                    not only abate the pungency of the ſalt, but diſpoſe it to mix with the chyle in
                    a more gentle and efficacious manner.</p>
                <p>A farmer of a conſiderable lordſhip in Bohemia visiting the hot-wells of
                    Carlſhad, related how he preſerved his flocks of ſheep from the mortal diſtemper
                    which raged in the wet year 1769, of which ſo many periſhed. His preſervative
                    was very simple and very cheap : “ He ſed them every night, when turned under a
                    ſhed, cover, or ſtables, with haſhed fodder ſtraw ; and, by eating it greedily,
                    they all eſcaped.”</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">" Red-water</hi> is a diſorder moſt prevalent on wet grounds. I
                    have heard (says Mr Arthur Young) that it has ſomctimes been cured by tapping,
                    as for a dropſy. This operation is done on one side of the belly towards the
                    flank, just below the wool.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">“ The foot-rot</hi> and <hi rend="italic">hoving,</hi> which is
                    very common on low fenny grounds, is cured by keeping the part clean, and lying
                    at rest in a dry paſture.”</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">ſcab</hi> is a cutaneous diſeaſe owing to an impurity of
                    the blood, and is moſt prevalent in wet lands or in rainy ſeaſons. It is cured
                    by tobacco-water, brimſtone, and alum, boiled together, and then rubbed ever the
                    ſheep. If only partial, tar and greaſe may be sufficient. But the ſimpleſt and
                    moſt efficacious remedy for this diſeaſe was communicated to the Society for the
                    Encouragement of Arts, &amp;c, by Sir Joſeph Banks. " Take one pound of
                    quickſilver, half a pound of Venice turpentine, half a pint of oil of
                    turpentine, and four pounds of hogs lard<note anchored="true" n="6"
                        place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>(c) By ſome unaccountable miſtake the
                            laſt ingredient, the four pounds of hogs lard, is omitted in the receipt
                            publiſhed in the Tranſactions of the Society ; a circumſtance that might
                            be productive of bad effects.--· The leaf which contained the receipt
                            has since been cancelled, and a new one printed.</p></note> (c). Let
                    them be rubbed in a mortar till the quickſilver is thoroughly incorporated with
                    the other ingredients ; for the proper mode of doing which, it may be proper to
                    take the advice, or even the aſſiſtance, of ſome apothecary or other perſon uſed
                    to make ſuch mixtures.</p>
                <p>“ The method of uſing the ointment is this : Beginning at the head of the ſheep,
                    and proceeding from between the ears along the back to the end of the tail, the
                    wool is to be divided in a furrow till the ſkin can be touched ; and as the
                    furrow is made, the finger ſlightly dipped in the ointment is to be drawn along
                    the bottom of it, where it will leave a blue ſtain on the ſkin and adjoining
                    wool : from this furrow similar ones must be drawn down the ſhoulders and thighs
                    to the legs, as far as they are woolly ; and if the animal is much infected, two
                    more ſhould be drawn along each ſide parallel to that on the back, and one down
                    each ſide between the fore and hind legs.</p>
                <p>“ Immediately after being dreſſed, it is uſual to turn the ſheep among other
                    ſtock, without any fear of the infection being communicated ; and there is
                    ſearcely an inſtance of a ſheep ſuffering any injury from the application in a
                    few days the blotches dry up, the itching ceaſes, and the animal is completely
                    cured : it is generally, however, thought proper not to delay the operation
                    beyond Michaelmas.</p>
                <p>“ The <hi rend="italic">hippoboſca ovina,</hi> called in Lincolnshire sheep f <hi
                        rend="italic">agg,</hi> an animal well known to all ſhepherds, which lives
                    among the wool, and is hurtful to the thriving of ſheep both by the pain its
                    bite occaſions and the blood it sucks, is deſtroyed by this application, and the
                    wool is not at all injured. Our wool-buyers purchaſe the fleeces on which the
                    ſtain of the ointment is viſible, rather in preference to others, from an
                    opinion that the uſe of it having preſerved the animal from being vexed either
                    with the ſcab or faggs, the wool is leſs liable to the defects of joints or
                    knots; a fault obſerved to proceed from every ſudden flop in the thriving of the
                    animal, either from want of food or from diſeaſe.</p>
                <p>“ This mode of curing was brought into that part of Lincolnſhire where my
                    property is ſituated about 13 years ago, by Mr Stephenſon of Mareham, and is now
                    ſo generally received, that the ſcab, which uſed to be the terror of the
                    farmers, and which frequently deterred the more careful of them from taking the
                    advantage of paſturing their ſheep in the fertile and extenſive commons with
                    which that diſtrict abounds, is no longer regarded with any apprehenſion : by
                    far the moſt of them have their flock anointed in autumn, when they return from
                    the common, whether they ſhow any ſymptons of ſcab or not ; and having done ſo,
                        conclude<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0355.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s03-0349"/>
                    them ſafe for some time from either giving or receiving infection. There are
                    people who employ themſelves in the buſiness, and contract to anoint our large
                    ſheep at five ſhillings a ſcore, inſuring for that price the ſucceſs of the
                    operation ; that is, agreeing, in caſe many of the ſheep break out afreſh, to
                    repeat the operation gratis even ſome months afterwards.”</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">dunt</hi> is a diſtemper cauſed by a bladder of water
                    gathering in the head. No cure for this has yet been diſcovered.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">rickets</hi> is a hereditary diſeaſe for which no antidote
                    is known. The firſt ſymptom is a kind of light- headedneſs, which makes the
                    affected ſheep appear wilder than uſual when the ſhepherd or any perſon
                    approaches him. He bounces up ſuddenly from his lare, and runs to a diſtance, as
                    though he were purſued by dogs. In the second ſtage the principal ſymptom is the
                    ſheep’s rubbing himſelf againſt trees, &amp;c. with ſuch fury as to pull off his
                    wool and tear away his fleſh. “ The diſtreſſed animal has now a violent itching
                    in his skin, the effect of an highly inflamed blood ; but it does not appear
                    that there is ever any cutaneous eruption or ſalutary critical diſcharge. In
                    ſhort, from all circumstances, the fever appears now to be at its height.”— The
                    laſt ſtage of this diſeaſe “ ſeems only to be the progreſs of diſſolution, after
                    an unfavourable crisis. The poor animal, as condemned by Nature, appears ſtupid,
                    walks irregularly (whence probably the name <hi rend="italic">rickets),</hi>
                    generally lies, and eats little: theſe ſymptoms increaſe in degree till death,
                    which follows a general conſumption, as appears upon dissection of the carcaſe ;
                    the juices and even ſolids having ſuffered a general diſſolution.”</p>
                <p>In order to diſcover the ſeatand nature of this diseaſe, ſheep that die of it
                    ought to be diſſected. This is ſaid to have been done by one gentleman, Mr Beal
                    and he found in the brain or membranes adjoining a maggot about a quarter of an
                    inch long, and of a browniſh colour. A few experiments might eaſily determine
                    this fact.</p>
                <p>The fly-struck is cured by clipping the wool off as far as infected, and rubbing
                    the parts dry with lime or wood-aſhes ; curriers oil will heal the wounds, and
                    prevent their being ſtruck any more ; or they may be cured with care, without
                    clipping, with oil of turpentine, which will kill all the vermin where it goes ;
                    but the former is the sureſt way.</p>
                <p>The flu <hi rend="italic">x</hi> is another diſeaſe to which ſheep are ſubject.
                    The beſt remedy is ſaid to be, to houſe the ſheep immediately when this
                    diſtemper appears, to keep them very warm, and feed them on dry hay, giving them
                    frequent gliſters of warm milk and water. The cauſe of that diſtemper is either
                    their feeding on wet lands, or on graſs that is become moſſy by the lands having
                    been fed many years without being ploughed. When the farmer perceives his
                    ſheep-walks to become moſſy, or to produce bad graſs, he ſhould either plough or
                    manure with hot lime, making kilns either very near or in the ſheep walks,
                    becauſe the hotter the lime is out on, the ſweeter the graſs comes up, and that
                    early in the year.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Bursting,</hi> or as it is called in ſome places the <hi
                        rend="italic">blast,</hi> attacks ſheep when driven into freſh graſs or
                    young clover. They overeat themſelves, foam at the mouth, ſwell exceedingly,
                    breathe very quick and ſhort, then jump up, and inſtantly fall down dead. In
                    this caſe, the only chance of having their life is by ſtabbing them in the maw
                    with an instrument made for the purpoſe. The infiniment is a hollow tube, with a
                    pointed weapon paſſing through it. A hole is made with the pointed weapon ;
                    which is immediately withdrawn, and the hole is kept open by inſerting the tube
                    till the wind is diſcharged.</p>
                <p>Sheep are infeſted with worms in their noſe called aestru <hi rend="italic">s
                        oves,</hi> and produced from the egg of a large twowinged fly. The frontal
                    ſinuſes above the noſe in ſheep and other animals are the places where theſe
                    worms live and attain their full growth. Theſe ſinuſes are always full of a ſoft
                    white matter, which furniſhes theſe worms with a proper nouriſhment, and are
                    ſufficiently large for their habitation; and when they have here acquired their
                    deſtined growth, in which they are fit to undergo their changes for the
                    fly-ſtate, they leave their old habitation, and, falling to the earth, bury
                    themſelves there ; and when theſe are hatched into flies, the female, when ſhe
                    has been impregnated by the male, knows that the noſe of a ſheep or other animal
                    is the only place for her to depoſit her eggs, in older to their coming to
                    maturity. Mr Vallisnieri, to whom the world owes ſo many diſcoveries in the
                    infect claſs, is the firſt who has given any true account of the origin of theſe
                    worms. But though their true hiſtory had been till that time unknown, the
                    creatures themſelves were very early diſcovered, and many ages since were
                    eſteemed great medicines in epilepsies.</p>
                <p>The fly produced from this worm has all the time of its life a very lazy
                    diſpoſition, and does not like to make any uſe either of its legs or wings. Its
                    head and corſelet together are about as long as its body, which is composed of
                    five rings, ſtreaked on the back ; a pale yellow and brown are there diſpoſed in
                    irregular ſpots ; the belly is of the same colours, but they are there more
                    regularly diſpoſed, for the brown here makes three lines, one in the middle, and
                    one on each side, and all the intermediate ſpaces are yellow. The wings are
                    nearly of the ſame length with the body, and are a little inclined in their
                    position, ſo as to lie upon the body : they do not, however, cover it ; but a
                    naked ſpace is left between them. The ailerons or petty wings which arc found
                    under each of the wings are of a whitiſh colour, and perfectly cover the
                    balancers, so that they are not to be ſeen without lifting up theſe.</p>
                <p>The fly will live two months after it is firſt produced, but will take no
                    nouriſhment of any kind ; and possibly it may be of the same nature with the
                    butterflies, which never take any food during the whole time of their living in
                    that ſtate. Reaumur, Hiſt. Inſi vol iv. p. 552, &amp;c.</p>
                <p>To find a proper compoſition for marking ſheep is a matter of great importance,
                    as great quantities of wool are every year rendered uſeleſs by the pitch and tar
                    with which they are uſually marked. The requiſite qualities for ſuch a
                    compoſition are, that it be cheap, that the colour be ſtrong and laſting, ſo as
                    to bear the changes of weather, and not to injure the wool. Dr Lewis recommends
                    for this purpoſe melted tallow, with ſo much charcoal in fine powder ſtirred
                    into it as is ſufficient to make it of a full black colour, and of a thick
                    confidence. This mixture, being applied warm with a marking iron, on pieces of
                    flannel, quickly fixed or hardened, bore moderate rubbing, reſiſted the ſun and
                        rain.<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0356.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s03-0350"/> and
                    yet could be waſhed out freely with soap, or ley, or ſtale urine. In order to
                    render it ſtill more durable, and prevent its being rubbed off, with the tallow
                    may be melted an eighth, ſixth, or fourth, of its weight of tar, which will
                    readily waſh out along with it from the wool. Lewis’s Com. Phil. Techn. p.
                    361.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Sheep</hi><hi rend="italic">-Stealing.</hi> See <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Theft.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
