<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0262.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s03-0256-01" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SELIM I</label>
. emperor of the Turks, was the second ſon of Bajazet II. He made war upon his father, and though defeated in 1511, he at laſt dethroned him and took him priſoner, and immediately diſpatched him by poison, together with his elder brother Achmet, and his younger Korkud, an amiable and enlightened prince. Having eſtabliſhed his throne by theſe crimes, he marched againſt Carnpſon-Gaury ſovereign of Egypt, gained a great victory at Aleppo, and flew their general. But though the ſultan periſhed in that battle, the Mameluks determined to oppoſe the emperor. Selim entering their country at the head of his army, defeated the Egyptians in two battles, and ordered Toumonbai, the new elected ſultan, who had fallen into his hands, to be hung on a gibbet. He then took Cairo and Alexandria, and in a ſhort time reduced all Egypt to ſubjection. Thus ended the dominion of the Mameluks in Egypt, which had continued for more than 260 years. He confirmed the ancient privileges of the Venetians in Egypt and Syria, by which they carried on their commerce with India, and formed a league with them to deſtroy the power of the Portugueſe in that country. (See India, n⁰ 37). Selim had before this gained a great victory over the Perſians, and ſtripped them of Tauris and Keman. He was preparing to attack Chriſtendom when he was ſeized with an ulcerous fore in the back. Thinking that the air of Adrianople would reſtore his health, he ordered himſelf to be conducted thither ; but he died at Clari in Thrace on his road to that city, in the year 1520, in the very ſpot where he had poiſoned his father. He reigned 8 years, and lived 54. He was a prince of great courage, sobriety, and liberality ; he was fond of hiſtory, and wrote ſome verſes. But theſe good qualities were obſcured by the moſt abominable crimes that ever diſgraced human nature : he made his way to the throne by ſhedding the blood of his father, and ſecured it by murdering his brothers and eight nephews, and every baſhaw who had been faithful to his duty.</p></div></body></text></TEI>