<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0346.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s03-0340-02" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SHAWLS</label>,
are woollen handkerchiefs, an ell wide, and near two long. The wool is ſo fine and ſilky, that the whole handkerchief may be contained in the two hands cloſed. It is the produce of a Tibet ſheep ; but some say that no wool is employed but that of lambs torn from the belly of their mother before the time of birth. The most beautiful ſhawls come from Caſhmire : their price is from 150 livres (about fix guineas) to 1220 livres (or L. 50 Sterling.)</p><p>In the Tranſactions of the Society- for Encouraging Arts, Manufactures, &amp;c. for the year 1792, we are informed that a ſhawl counterpane, four yards ſquare, manufactured by Mr P. J. Knights of Norwich, was prefented to the society ; and that, upon examination, it appeared to be of greater breadth than any goods of equal fineneſs and texture that had ever before been presented to the society, or to their knowledge woven in this country. The ſhawls of Mr Knights’s manufacture, it is said, can ſcarcely be diſtinguished from Indian ſhawls, though they can be afforded at one-twentieth part of the price. When the ſhawl is 16 quarters ſquare, Mr Knights ſays it may be retailed at L. 2c ; if it conſiſted of 12 quarters, and embroidered as the former, it will coſt L. 15 ; if plain, with a fringe only, a ſhawl of 16 quarters ſquare may be fold at L. 8, 8 s.; if 12 quarters and fringed, at L. 6, 6 s.</p><p>Mr Knights maintains, that his counterpane of four yards ſquare is equal in beauty, and ſuperior in ſtrength, to the Indian counterpanes which are fold at 200 guineas. The principal consumption of this cloth is in train-dreſſes. for ladies ; as likewiſe for long ſcarfs, in imitation of the real Indian ſcarfs, which are fold from L. 60 to L. 80 ; whereas ſcarfs of this fabric are fold for as many ſhillings, and the ladies ſquare ſhawls in proportion.</p></div></body></text></TEI>