<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0450.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s03-0444-04" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SHORT</label>
(James), an eminent optician, was born in Edinburgh on the 10th of June, O. S. în the year 1710. At ten years of age, having lost his father and mother, and being left in a state of indigence, he was received into Heriots' Hoſpital, (see <hi rend="italic">EDINBURGH Public Buildings,</hi> n⁰ 16. ), where he ſoon diſplayed his mechanical genius in conſtructing, for himſelf, little cheſts, book- cases, and other conveniences, with ſuch tools as fell in his way. At the age of twelve he was removed from the Hoſpital to the High School, where he ſhowed a conſiderable taſte for claſſical literature, and generally kept at the head of his forms. In the year 1726 he was entered into the univerſity, where he paſſed through</p><p>the usual courſe of education, and took his maſter’s degree with great applauſe.</p><p>By his friends he was intended for the church ; but after attending a courſe of theological lectures, his mind revolted from a profeſſion which he thought little suited to his talents ; and he devoted his whole time to mathematical and mechanical purſuits. He had been fortunate enough to have the celebrated M'Laurin for his preceptor ; who having ſoon diſcovered the bent of his genius, and made a proper eſtimate of the extent of his capacity, encouraged him to proſecute thoſe ſtudies in which nature had qualified him to make the greateſt figure. Under the eye of that eminent maſter, he began in 1732 to conſtruct Gregorian teleſcopes; and, as the profeſſor obſerved in a letter to Dr Jurin, “by taking care of the figure of his ſpecula, he was enabled to give them larger apertures, and to carry them to greater perfection, than had ever been done before him.” See <hi rend="smallcaps">Optics,</hi> n⁰ 97.)</p><p>In the year 1736 Mr Short was called to London, at the deſire of Queen Caroline, to give inſtructions in mathematics to William duke of Cumberland; and immediately on his appointment to that very honourable office he was elected a fellow of the royal ſociety, and patroniſed by the earls of Morton and Macclesfield. In the year 1739 he accompanied the former of thoſe noble lords to the Orkney Iſles, where he was employed in adjuſting the geography of that part of Scotland : and happy it was for him that he was ſo employed, as he might otherwiſe have been involved in a ſcuffle which took place between the retainers of Sir James Stewart of Barra and the attendants of the earl, in which ſome of the latter were dangerouſly wounded.</p><p>Mr Short having returned to London, and finally establiſhed himſelf there in the line of his profeſſion, was in 1743 employed by lord Thomas Spencer to make for him a reflector of twelve feet focus, for which he received 600 guineas. He made ſeveral other teleſcopes of the ſame focal diſtance with greater improvements and higher magnifiers ; and in 1752 finiſhed one for the king of Spain, for which, with its whole apparatus, he received 1200 l. I his was the nobleſt inſtrument of the kind that had then been conſtructed, and perhaps it has never yet been ſurpaſſed except by the aſtoniſhing reflectors of Herſchel. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Telescope.</hi></p><p>Mr Short was wont to viſit the place of his nativity once every two or three years during his reſidence in London, and in 1766 he viſited it for the laſt time. On. the 15th of June 1768 he died, after a very ſhort illness, at Newington Butts, near London, of a mortification in his bowels, and was buried on the 22d of the ſame month, having completed, within a few days, his fifty-eighth year. He left a fortune of about 20,00cl. of which 15,000 l. was bequeathed to two nephews, and the rest in legacies to his friends. In gratitude for the ſteady patronage of the earl of Morton, he left to his daughter the Lady Mary Douglas, afterwards counted of Aboyne, 1000 l. and the reverſion of his fortune, ſhould his nephews die without iſſue ; but this reverſionary legacy the lady, at the deſire of her father, generouſly relinquished by a deed in favour of Mr Short’s brother Mr Thomas Short and his children. Mr Short's eminence as an artiſt is univerſally known, and we have often heard him ſpoken of by thoſe who had<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0451.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s03-0445"/>
known him ſrom his youth, as a man of virtue and of very amiable manners.</p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Short-H</hi> <hi rend="italic">and Writing.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Stenography.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">SHORT-jointed,</hi> in the manege. A horſe is ſaid to be ſhort-jointed that has a ſhort paſtern ; when this joint, or the paſtern is too ſhort, the horſe is ſubject to have his fore legs from the knee to the cornet all in a ſtraight line. Commonly your ſhort-jointed horſes do not manege ſo well as the long.jointed ; but out of the manege the ſhort-jointed are the beſt for travel or fatigue.</p><p><hi rend="italic">SHORT-Sightedneſs,</hi> a certain defect in viſion, by which objects cannot be diſtinctly ſeen unleſs they are very near the eye. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Optics,</hi> n⁰ 155 <hi rend="italic">.</hi></p></div></body></text></TEI>