<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0281.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s03-0275-01" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SENTENCE</label>,
in law, a judgment paſſed in court by the judge in ſome process, either civil or criminal. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Judgment.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sentence,</hi> in grammar, denotes a period ; or a ſet of words comprehending ſome perfect ſenſe or ſentiment of the mind. The buſineſs of pointing is to diſtinguiſh the ſeveral parts and members of ſentences, ſo as to render the ſenſe thereof as clear, diſtinct, and full as poſſible. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Punctuation.</hi></p><p>In every ſentence there are two parts neceſſarily required ; a noun for the ſubject, and a definite verb : whatever is found more than theſe two, affects one of them, either immediately, or by the intervention of ſome other, whereby the firſt is affected.</p><p>Again, every ſentence is either simple or compound: a simple ſentence is that conſiſting of one ſingle ſubject, and one finite verb.—A compound ſentence contains ſeveral ſubjects and finite verbs, either expreſsly or implicitly.</p><p>A simple ſentence needs no point or diſtinction ; only a period to cloſe it : as, “ A good man loves virtue for itſelf.”— In ſuch a ſentence, the ſeveral adjuncts affect either the ſubject or the verb in a different manner. Thus the word <hi rend="italic">good</hi> expresses the quality of the ſubject, <hi rend="italic">virtue</hi> the object of the action, and <hi rend="italic">for itſelf</hi> the end thereof.—Now none of theſe adjuncts can be ſeparated from the reft of the ſentence : for if one be, why ſhould not all the reſt ? and if all be, the ſentence will be minced into almoſt as many parts as there are words.</p><p>But if ſeveral adjuncts be attributed in the ſame manner either to the ſubject or the verb, the ſentence becomes compound, and is to be divided into parts.</p><p>In every compound ſentence, as many ſubjects, or as many finite verbs as there are, either expreſsly or implied, ſo many diſtinctions may there be. Thus, “ My hopes, fears, joys, pains, all centre in you.” And thus <hi rend="italic">Catilina abiit, exceſfit, evasit, erupit.</hi> The reason of which pointing is obvious ; for as many ſubjects or finite verbs as there are in a ſentence, ſo many members does it really contain. Whenever, therefore, there occur. more nouns than verbs, or contrariwiſe, they are to be conceived as equal. Since, as every ſubject requires its verbs, ſo every verb requires its ſubject, wherewith it may agree : excepting, perhaps, in ſome figurative expreſſions.</p></div></body></text></TEI>