<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0450.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s03-0444-01" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SHORE</label>
(Jane), the celebrated concubine of the licentious king Edward IV. was the wife of Mr Matthew Shore, a goldſmith in Lombard ftreet, London. Kings are ſeldom unſucceſsful in their amorous purſuits; therefore there was nothing wonderful in Mrs Shore’s removing from Lombard-ſtreet to ſhine at court as the royal favourite. Historians repreſent her as extremely beautiful, remarkably cheerful, and of moſt uncommon generoſity. The king, it is ſaid, was no leſs captivated with her temper than with her perſon : ſhe never made uſe of her influence over him to the prejudice of any perſon ; and if ever ſhe importuned him, it was in favour of the unfortunate. After the death of Edward, ſhe attached herſelf to the lord Haſtings ; and when Richard III. cut off that nobleman as an obſtacle to his ambitious ſchemes, Jane Shore was arreſted as an accomplice, on the ridiculous accuſation of witchcraft. This, however, terminated only in a public penance ; excepting that Richard rifled her of all her little property : but whatever ſeverity might have been exerciſed towards her, it appears that ſhe was alive, though ſufficiently wretched, under the reign of Henry VIII. when Sir Thomas More ſaw her poor, old, and ſhrivelled, without the leaſt trace of her former beauty. Mr Rowe, in his tragedy of Jane Shore, has adopted the popular ſtory related in the old hiſtorical ballad, of her periſhing by hunger in a ditch where Shoreditch now ſtands. But Stow aſſures us that street was ſo named before her time.</p></div></body></text></TEI>