<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="gri_33125011196363_0328.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s03-0322-01"
                xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                <p><label>SEVERUS</label> (Cornelius), an ancient Latin poet of the Auguſtan age ;
                    whoſe <hi rend="italic">Ætna,</hi> together with a fragment <hi rend="italic">De
                        morte Ciceronis,</hi> were publiſhed, with notes and a proſe interpretation,
                    by Le Clerc, 12mo, Amsterdam, 1703. They were before inſerted among the <hi
                        rend="italic">Catalecta Virgilii</hi> publiſhed by Scaliger ; whoſe notes,
                    with others, Le Clerc has received among his own.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Severus</hi> (Septimus), a Roman emperor, who has been ſo
                    much admired for his military talents, that some have called him the moſt
                    warlike of the Roman emperors. As a monarch he was cruel, and <hi rend="italic"
                        >it</hi> has been obſerved that he never did an act of humanity or forgave a
                    fault. In his diet he was temperate, and he always ſhowed himſelf an open enemy
                    to pomp and ſplendor. He loved the appellation of a man of letters, and he even
                    compoſed an hiſtory of his own reign, which ſome have praiſed for its
                    correctneſs and veracity. However cruel Severus may appear in his puniſhments
                    and in his revenge, many have endeavoured to exculpate him, and obſerved that
                    there was need of ſeverity in an empire where the morals were ſo corrupted, and
                    where no leſs than 3000 perlons were accuſed of adultery during the ſpace of 17
                    years. Of him, as of Augustus, ſome were fond to say, that it would have been
                    better for the world if he had never been born, or had never died. See <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Rome,</hi> n <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> 372.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">SEVERUS' Wall,</hi> in Britiſh topography, the fourth and laſt
                    barrier erected by the Romans againſt the incurſions of the North Britons. See
                    the articles <hi rend="smallcaps">Adrian,</hi> and A <hi rend="italic smallcaps"
                        > ntoninUS'</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">s Wall.</hi></p>
                <p>We learn from ſeveral hints in the Roman hiſtorians, that the country between the
                    walls of Hadrian and Antoninus continued to be a ſcene of perpetual war and
                    ſubject of contention between the Romans and Britons, from the beginning of the
                    reign of Commodus to the arrival of the emperor Septimius Severus in Britain, A.
                    D. 206. This laſt emperor having ſubdued the Mæatæ, and repulſed the
                    Caledonians, determined to erect a ſtronger and more impenetrable barrier than
                    any of the former, againſt their future incurſions.</p>
                <p>Though neither Dio nor Herodian make any mention of a wall built by Severus in
                    Britain for the protection of the Roman province, yet we have abundant evidence
                    from other writers of equal authority, that he really built ſuch a wall. “ He
                    fortified Britain (says Spartian) with a wall drawn croſs the iſland from sea to
                    sea ; which is the greateſt glory of his reign. After the wall was finiſhed, he
                    retired to the next ſtation (York), not only a conqueror, but the founder of an
                    eternal peace.” To the same purpoſe, Aurelius Victor and Oroſius, to ſay nothing
                    of Eutropius and Caſſiodorus : “ Having repelled the enemy in Britain, he
                    fortified the country, which was ſuited to that purpoſe, with a wall drawn croſs
                    the iſland from ſea to sea.</p>
                <p>Severus drew a great ditch, and built a ſtrong wall, fortified with ſeveral
                    turrets, from ſea to ſea, to protect that part of the iſland which he had
                    recovered from</p>
                <p>the yet unconquered nations.” As the reſidence of the emperor Severus in Britain
                    was not quite four years, it is probable that the two laſt of them were employed
                    in building this wall ; according to which account, it was begun A. D. 209, and
                    finiſhed A. D. 210.</p>
                <p>This wall of Severus was built nearly on the ſame tract with Hadrian’s rampart,
                    at the diſtance only of a few paces north. The length of this wall, from
                    Cousins’ houſe near the mouth of the river Tyne on the eaſt, to Boulneſs on the
                    Solway frith on the west, hath been found, from two actual menſurations, to be a
                    little more than 68 English miles, and a little leſs than 74 Roman miles. To the
                    north of the wall was a broad and deep ditch, the original dimenſions of which
                    cannot now be aſcertained, only it ſeems to have been larger than that of
                    Hadrian. The wall itſelf, which ſtood on the ſouth brink of the ditch, was built
                    of free-stone, and where the foundation was not good, it is built on piles of
                    oak ; the interſtices between the two faces of this wall is filled with broad
                    thin ſtones, placed not perpendicularly, but obliquely on their edges ; the
                    running mortar or cement was then poured upon them, which, by its great ſtrength
                    and tenacity, bound the whole together, and made it firm as a rock. But though
                    theſe materials are ſufficiently known, it is not eaſy to gueſs where they were
                    procured, for many parts of the wall are at a great diſtance from any quarry of
                    free ſtone ; and, though ſtone of another kind was within reach, yet it does not
                    appear to have been anywhere uſed. The height of this wall was 12 feet beſides
                    the parapet, and its breadth 8 feet, according to Bede, who lived only at a
                    ſmall diſtance from the eaſt end of it, and in whoſe time it was almoſt quite
                    entire in many places. Such was the wall erected by the command and under the
                    direction of the emperor Severus in the north of England ; and, conſidering the
                    length, breadth, height, and ſolidity, it was certainly a work of great
                    magnificence and prodigious labour. But the wall itſelf was but a part, and not
                    the moſt extraordinary part, of this work. The great number and different kinds
                    of fortreſſes which were built along the line of it for its defence, and the
                    military ways with which it was attended, are ſtill more worthy of our
                    admiration, and come now to be deſcribed.</p>
                <p>The fortreſſes which were erected along the line of Severus’s wall for its
                    defence, were of three different kinds, and three different degrees of ſtrength
                    ; and were called by three different Latin words, which may be tranſlated statio
                        <hi rend="italic">ns, castles,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">turrets.</hi> Of
                    each of theſe in their order.</p>
                <p>The st <hi rend="italic">ationes,</hi> ſtations, were ſo called from their
                    ſtability and the ſtated reſidence of garriſons. They were alſo called <hi
                        rend="italic">callra,</hi> which hath been converted into <hi rend="italic"
                        >chestres,</hi> a name which many of them ſtill bear. Theſe were by far the
                    largeſt, ſtrongeſt, and moſt magnificent of the fortreſſes which were built upon
                    the wall, and were deſigned for the head-quarters of the cohorts of troops which
                    were placed there in garriſon, and from whence detachments were ſent into the
                    adjoining caſtles and turrets. Theſe ſtations, as appears from the veſtiges of
                    them which are ſtill visible, were not all exactly of the ſame figure nor of the
                    ſame dimenſions ; ſome of them being exactly ſquares, and others oblong, and
                    ſome of them a little larger than others. Theſe variations were no doubt
                    occasioned by the difference of si-<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0329.tif"
                        xml:id="eb03-17-s03-0323"/> tuation and other circumſtances. The ſtations
                    were fortified with deep ditches and ſtrong walls, the wall itſelf coinciding
                    with and forming the north wall of each ſtation. Within the ſtations were
                    lodgings for the officers and ſoldiers in garriſon ; the ſmalleſt of them being
                    ſufficient to contain a cohort, or 600 men. Without the walls of each ſtation
                    was a town, inhabited by labourers, artificers, and others, both Romans and
                    Britons, who choſe to dwell under the protection of theſe fortreſſes. The number
                    of the ſtations upon the wall was exactly 18 ; and if they had been placed at
                    equal diſtances, the interval between every two of them would have been four
                    miles and a few paces : but the intervention of rivers, marſhes, and mountains ;
                    the conveniency of ſituations for ſtrength, proſpect, and water ; and many other
                    circumſtances to us unknown, determined them to place theſe ſtations at unequal
                    diſtances. The ſituation which was always choſen by the Romans, both here and
                    everywhere else in Britain where they could obtain it, was the gentle declivity
                    of a hill, near a river, and facing the meridian sun. Such was the ſituation of
                    the far greateſt part of the ſtations on this wall. In general, we may obſerve,
                    that the ſtations stood thickeſt near the two ends and in the middle, probably
                    becauſe the danger of invaſion was greateſt in theſe places. But the reader will
                    form a clearer idea of the number of theſe ſtations, their Latin and Engliſh
                    names, their ſituation and diſtance from one another, by inſpecting the
                    following table, than we can give him with equal brevity in any other way. The
                    firſt column contains the number of the ſtation, reckoning from eaſt to west ;
                    the ſecond contains its Latin, and the third its Engliſh name ; and the three
                    laſt its diſtance from the next ſtation to the west of it, in miles, furlongs,
                    and chains.</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell>N⁰</cell>
                        <cell>Latin Name.</cell>
                        <cell>Engliſh Name.</cell>
                        <cell>M</cell>
                        <cell>F.</cell>
                        <cell>C.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>I</cell>
                        <cell>Segedunum</cell>
                        <cell>Couſins’-houſe</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>Pons Ælii</cell>
                        <cell>Newcaſtle</cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>9</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>Condercum</cell>
                        <cell>Benwell hill</cell>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>Vindobala</cell>
                        <cell>Rutcheſter</cell>
                        <cell>7</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>3 ½</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>Hunnum</cell>
                        <cell>Halton-cheſters</cell>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>I</cell>
                        <cell>7</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                        <cell>Cilurnum</cell>
                        <cell>Walwick-cheſters</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>8</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>7</cell>
                        <cell>Procolitia</cell>
                        <cell>Carrawbrugh</cell>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>3 ½</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>8</cell>
                        <cell>Borcovicus</cell>
                        <cell>Houſeſteeds</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>8</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>9</cell>
                        <cell>Vindolana</cell>
                        <cell>Little-cheſters</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell>Æsica</cell>
                        <cell>Grcat-cheſters</cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>I</cell>
                        <cell>6 ½</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>I I</cell>
                        <cell>Magna</cell>
                        <cell>Carrvoran</cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>12</cell>
                        <cell>Amboglanna</cell>
                        <cell>Burdoswald</cell>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>8</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>13</cell>
                        <cell>Petriana</cell>
                        <cell>Cambeck</cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>14</cell>
                        <cell>Aballaba</cell>
                        <cell>Watchcroſs</cell>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>I</cell>
                        <cell>9</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>15</cell>
                        <cell>Congavata</cell>
                        <cell>Stanwix</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>16</cell>
                        <cell>Axelodunum</cell>
                        <cell>Brugh</cell>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>9</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi>7</cell>
                        <cell>Gabroſentum</cell>
                        <cell>Brumbrugh</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>I</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>18</cell>
                        <cell>Tunnocelum</cell>
                        <cell>Boulneſs</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/> 
                        <cell>Length of the wall</cell>
                        <cell>68</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">castella,</hi> or caſtles, were the ſecond kind of
                    fortifications which were built along the line of this wall for its defence.
                    Theſe caſtles were neither ſo large nor ſtrong as the ſtations, but much more
                    numerous, being no fewer than 81. The ſhape and dimenſions of the caſtles, as
                    appears from the foundations of many</p>
                <p>of them which are still viſible, were exact ſquares of 66 feet every way. They
                    were fortified on every side with thick and lofty walls, but without any ditch,
                    except on the north side ; on which the wall itſelf, raiſed much above its uſual
                    height, with the ditch attending it, formed the fortification. The caſtles were
                    ſituated in the intervals between the ſtations, at the diſtance of about ſeven
                    furlongs from each other ; though particular circumſtances ſometimes occaſioned
                    a little variation. In theſe caſtles, guards were conſtantly kept by a competent
                    number of men detached from the neareſt ſtations.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">turres,</hi> or turrets, were the third and laſt kind of
                    fortifications on the wall. Theſe were ſtill much ſmaller than the caſtles, and
                    formed only a ſquare of about 12 feet, ſtanding out of the wall on its ſouth
                    side. Being ſo ſmall, they are more entirely ruined than the ſtations and
                    caſtles, which makes it difficult to diſcover their exact number. They ſtood in
                    the intervals between the caſtles ; and from the faint veſtiges of a few of
                    them, it is conjectured that there were four of them between every two caſtles,
                    at the diſtance of about 300 yards from one another. According to this
                    conjecture, the number of the turrets amounted to 324. They were deſigned for
                    watch-towers and places for ſentinels, who, being within hearing of one another,
                    could convey an alarm or piece of intelligence to all parts of the wall in a
                    very little time.</p>
                <p>Such were the ſtations, caſtles, and turrets, on the wall of Severus ; and a very
                    conſiderable body of troops was conſtantly quartered in them for its defence.
                    The uſual complement allowed for this ſervice was as follows :</p>
                <p>1. Twelve cohorts of foot, confiding of <hi rend="smallcaps">600</hi> men each:
                    7,200</p>
                <p>2. One cohort of mariners in the ſtation at Boulneſs: 600</p>
                <p>3. One detachment of Moors, probably equal to a cohort: 600</p>
                <p>4. Four alae or wings of horſe, confiding, at the loweſt computation, of 400
                    each: 1,600</p>
                <p>10,000</p>
                <p>For the conveniency of marching theſe troops from one part of the wall to
                    another, with the greater eaſe and expedition, on any ſervice, it was attended
                    with two military ways, paved with ſquare ſtones, in the moſt ſolid and
                    beautiful manner. One of theſe ways was ſmaller, and the other larger. The
                    ſmaller military way run cloſe along the ſouth side of the wall, from turret to
                    turret, and caſtle to caſtle, for the uſe of the ſoldiers in relieving their
                    guards and centinels, and ſuch ſervices. The larger way did not keep ſo near the
                    wall, nor touch at the turrets or caſtles, but purſued the moſt direct courſe
                    from one ſtation to another, and was deſigned for the conveniency of marching
                    larger bodies of troops.</p>
                <p>It is to be regretted, that we cannot gratify the reader’s curiosity, by
                    informing him by what particular bodies of Roman troops the ſeveral parts of
                    this great work were executed ; as we were enabled to do with regard to the wall
                    of Antoninus Pius from inſcriptions. For though it is probable that there
                        were<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0330.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s03-0324"/>
                    ſtones with inſcriptions of the ſame kind, mentioning the ſeveral bodies of
                    troops, and the quantity of work performed by each of them, originally inserted
                    in the face of this wall, yet none of them are now to be found. There have
                    indeed been discovered, in or near the ruins of this wall, a great number of
                    ſmall ſquare ſtones, with very ſhort, and generally imperfect, inſcriptions upon
                    them ; mentioning particular legions, cohorts, and centuries ; but without
                    directly aſſerting that they had built any part of the wall, or naming any
                    number of paces. Of theſe inſcriptions, the reader may ſee no fewer than
                    twenty-nine among the Northumberland and Cumberland inſcriptions in Mr Horsley’s
                    Britannia Romana. As the ſtones on which theſe inſeriptions are cut are of the
                    ſame ſhape and ſize with the other facing-ſtones of this wall, it is almoſt
                    certain that they have been originally placed in the face of it. It is equally
                    certain, from the uniformity of theſe inſcriptions, that they were all intended
                    to intimate ſome one thing, and nothing ſo probable as that the adjacent wall
                    was built by the troops mentioned in them. This was, perhaps, ſo well
                    underſtood, that it was not thought neceſſary to be expreſſed ; and the diſtance
                    of theſe inſcriptions from one another ſhowed the quantity of work perlormed. If
                    this was really the cafe, we know in general, that this great work was executed
                    by the ſecond and ſixth legions, theſe being the only legions mentioned in theſe
                    inſeriptions. Now, if this prodigious wall, with all its appendages of ditches,
                    ſtations, caſtles, turrets, and military ways, was executed in the ſpace of two
                    years by two legions only, which, when moſt complete, made no more than 12,000
                    men, how greatly muſt we admire the ſkill, the induſtry, and excellent
                    diſcipline of the Roman ſoldiers, who were not only the valiant guardians of the
                    empire in times of war, but its moſt active and uſeful members in times of peace
                    ?</p>
                <p>This wall of Severus, and its fortreſſes, proved an impenetrable barrier to the
                    Roman territories for near <hi rend="italic">200</hi> years. But about the
                    beginning of the 5th century, the Roman empire being aſſaulted on all ſides, and
                    the bulk of their forces withdrawn from Britain, the Mæatæ and Caledonians, now
                    called <hi rend="italic">Scots</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Pies,</hi> became more
                    daring ; and ſome of them breaking through the wall, and others ſailing round
                    the ends of it, they carried their ravages into the very heart of Provincial
                    Britain. Theſe invaders were indeed ſeveral times repulſed after this by the
                    Roman legions ſent to the relief of the Britons. The laſt of theſe legions,
                    under the command of Gallio of Ravenna, having, with the aſſiſtance of the
                    Britons, thoroughly repaired the breaches of Severus’s wall and its fortreſſes,
                    and exhorted the Britons to make a brave defence, took their final farewell of
                    Britain. It ſoon appeared, that the ſtrongest walls and ramparts are no ſecurity
                    to an undiſciplined and daſtardly rabble, as the unhappy Britons then were. The
                    Scots and Picts met with little reſiſtance in breaking through the wall, while
                    the towns and caſtles were tamely abandoned to their deſtructive rage. In many
                    places they levelled it with the ground, that it might prove no obſtruction to
                    their future inroads.— From this time no attempts were ever made to repair this
                    noble work. Its beauty and grandeur procured it no reſpect in the dark and
                    taſteleſs ages which ſucceeded. It became the common quarry for more than
                    thouſand years, out of which all the towns and villages around were built ; and
                    is now ſo entirely ruined, that the penetrating eyes of the moſt poring and
                    patient antiquarian, can hardly trace its vaniſhing foundations.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
