<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0269.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s03-0263-02" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SENATE</label>,
in general, is an aſſembly or council of senators ; that is, of the principal inhabitants of a ſtate, who have a ſhare in the government.</p><p>The ſenate of ancient Rome is of all others the moſt celebrated. It exerciſed no contentious juriſdiction ; but appointed judges, either from among the ſenators or knights, to determine proceſſes : it alſo appointed governors of provinces, and diſpoſed of the revenues of the commonwealth, &amp;c. Yet did not the whole ſovereign power reſide in the ſenate, ſince it could not elect magiſtrates, make laws, or decide of war and peace ; in all which caſes the ſenate was obliged to conſult the people.</p><p>The ſenate, when firſt inſtituted by Romulus, conſiſted of l00 members ; to whom he afterwards added the ſame number when the Sabines had migrated to Rome. Tarquin the ancient made the ſenate conſiſt of 300, and this number remained fixed for a long time ; but afterwards it fluctuated greatly, and was increaſed firſt to 700, and afterwards to 900 by J. Caesar, who filled the ſenate with men of every rank and order. Under Auguſt us the ſenators amounted to 1000, but this number was reduced, and fixed to 600. The place of a ſenator was always beſtowed upon merit: the monarchs had the privilege of chooſing the members ; and after the expulſion of the Tarquſhs, it was one of the rights of the conſuls, till the election of the cenſors, who from their office ſeemed moſt capable of making choice of men whoſe character was irreproachable, whoſe morals were pure, and relations honourable. Only particular families were admitted into the ſenate; and when the plebeians were permitted to ſhare the honours of the ſtate, it was then required that they ſhould be born of free citizens. It was also required that the candidates ſhould be knights</p><p>before their admiſſion into the ſenate. They were to be above the age of 25 <hi rend="italic">,</hi> and to have previouſly paſſed through the inferior offices of quaestor, tribune of the people, edile, pretor, and conſul.</p><p>The ſenate always met of courſe on the 1st of January, for the inauguration of the new consuls ; and in all months, univerſally, there were three days, viz. the kalends, nones, and ides, on which it regularly met : but it always met on extraordinary occaſions, when called together by conſul, tribune, or dictator.</p><p>To render their decrees valid and authentic, a certain number of members was requiſite, and ſuch as were abſent without ſome proper cauſe were always fined. In the reign of Auguſtus, 400 ſenators were requiſite to make a ſenate. Nothing was tranſacted before ſun-rise or after ſun-ſet. In their office the ſenators were the guardians of religion, they diſpoſed of the provinces as they pleaſed, they prorogued the aſſemblies of the people, they appointed thankſgivings, nominated their ambaſſadors, diſtributed the public money, and in ſhort had the management of every thing political or civil in the republic, except the creating of magiſtrates, the enacting of laws, and the declarations of war or peace, which were confined to the aſſemblies of the people.</p></div></body></text></TEI>