<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0365.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s03-0359-01" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SHERIFF</label>,
an officer, in each county in England, nominated by the king, inveſted with a judicial and miniſterial power, and who takes place of every nobleman in the county during the time of his office.</p><p>The ſheriff is an officer of very great antiquity in this kingdom, his name being derived from two Saxon words, ſignifying the <hi rend="italic">reeve, bailiff,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">officer</hi> of the ſhire He is called in Latin <hi rend="italic">vice-cοmes,</hi> as being the deputy of the earl or <hi rend="italic">cοmes,</hi> to whom the cuſtody of</p><p>the ſhire is ſaid to have been committed at the firſt diviſion of this kingdom into counties. But the earls, in proceſs of time, by reaſon of their high employments and attendance on the king’s perſon, not being able to tranſact the buſineſs of the county, were delivered of that burden ; reſerving to themſelves the honour, but the labour was laid on the ſheriff. So that now the ſheriff does all the king’s buſineſs in the county ; and tho’ he be ſtill called <hi rend="italic">vice-cοmes,</hi> yet he is entirely independent of, and not ſubject to, the earl ; the king, by his letters patent, committing <hi rend="italic">custodian comitatus</hi> to the ſheriff, and to him alone.</p><p>Sheriffs were formerly choſen by the inhabitants of the ſeveral counties. In confirmation of which it was ordained, by ſtatute 28 Edw. I. c. 8. that the people ſhould have an election of ſheriffs in every ſhire where the ſhrievalty is not of inheritance. For anciently in ſome counties the ſheriffs were hereditary ; as we apprehend they were in Scotland till the ſtatute 20 Geo. II. c. 43; and ſtill continue in the county of Weſtmoreland to this day ; the city of London having alſo the inheritance of the ſhrievalty of Middleſex veſted in their body by charter. The reaſon of theſe popular elections is aſſigned in the ſame ſtatute, c. 13. “ that the commons might chooſe ſuch as would not be a burden to them.” And herein appears plainly a ſtrong trace of the democratical part of our conſtitution ; in which form of government it is an indiſpenſable requiſite, that the people ſhould chooſe their own magiſtrates. This election was in all probability not abſolutely veſted in the commons, but required the royal approbation. For in the Gothic conſtitution, the judges of their county-courts (which office is executed by the ſheriff) were elected by the people, but confirmed by the king : and the form of their election was thus managed ; the people, or <hi rend="italic">incolae territorii,</hi> choſe twelve electors, and they nominated three perſons, <hi rend="italic">ex quibus rex unum confirmabat.</hi> But, with us in England, theſe popular elections, growing tumultuous, were put an end to by the ſtatute 9 Edw. IL ft. 2. which enacted, that the ſheriffs ſhould from thenceforth be aſſigned by the chancellor, treaſurer, and the judges ; as being perſons in whom the ſame truſt might with confidence be repoſed. By ſtatutes 14 Edw. III. c. 7. 23 Hen. VI. c. 8. and 21 Hen. VIII. c. 20. the chancellor, treaſurer, preſident of the king’s council, chief juſtices, and chief baron, are to make this election ; and that on the morrow of All Souls, in the exchequer. And the king’s letters patent, appointing the new ſheriffs, uſed commonly to bear date the sixth day of November. The ſtatute of Cambridge, 12 Ric. II. c. 2. ordains, that the chancellor, treaſurer, keeper of the privy ſeal, ſteward of the king’s houſe, the king’s chamberlain, clerk of the rolls, the juſtices of the one bench and the other, barons of the exchequer, and all other that ſhall be called to ordain, name, or make juſtices of the peace, ſheriffs, and other officers of the king, ſhall be ſworn to act indifferently, and to name no man that ſueth to be put in office, but ſuch only as they ſhall judge to be the beſt and moſt ſufficient. And the cuſtom now is (and has been at leaſt ever ſince the time of Forteſcue, who was chief justice and chancellor to Henry the ſixth), that all the judges, together with the other great officers, meet in the exchequer chamber on the morrow of All Souls yearly, (which day is now altered to the morrow<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0366.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s03-0360"/>
of St Martin by the laſt act for abbreviating Michaelmas term), and then and there propoſe three perſons to the king, who afterwards appoints one of them to be ſheriff. This cuſtom of the twelve judges proposing three perſons ſeems borrowed from the Gothic conſtitution before-mentioned : with this difference, that among the Goths the 12 nominors were firſt elected by the people themselves. And this usage of ours, at its firſt introduction, there is reaſon to believe, waa founded upon ſome ſtatute, though not now to be found among our printed laws ; firſt, becauſe it is materially different from the direction of all the ſtatutes before- mentioned ; which it is hard to conceive that the judges would have countenanced by their concurrence, or that Forteſcue would have inſerted in his book, unleſs by the authority of ſome ſtatute ; and also, becauſe a ſtatute is expreſsly referred to in the record, which Sir Edward Coke tells us he tranſcribed from the council-book of 3d March, 34 Hen. VI. and which is in ſubſtance as follows. The king had of his own authority appointed a man ſheriff of Lincolnſhire, which office he refuſed to take upon him ; whereupon the opinions of the judges were taken, what ſhould be done in this behalf. And the two chief juſtices, Sir John Forteſcue and Sir John Priſot, delivered the unanimous opinion of them all ; “ that the king did an error when he made a perſon ſheriff that was not choſen and preſented to him according to the ſtatute ; that the perſon refuſing was liable to no fine for diſobedience, as if he had been one of the three perſons choſen according to the tenor of the ſtatute ; that they would adviſe the king to have recourſe to the three perſons that were choſen according to the ſtatute, or that ſome other thrifty man be intreated to occupy the office for this year ; and that, the next year, to eſchew ſuch inconveniences, the order of the statute in this behalf made be obſerved.” But, notwithſtanding this unanimous reſolution of all the judges of England, thus entered in the council-book,and the ſtatute 34 and 35 Hen. VIII. c. 26. * 61. which expreſsly recognizes this to be the law of the land, ſome of our writers have affirmed, that the king, by his prerogative, may name whom he pleaſes to be ſheriff, whether choſen by the judges or not. This is grounded on a very particular caſe in the fifth year of queen Elizabeth, when, by reaſon of the plague, there was no Michaelmas term kept at Weſtminſter ; ſo that the judges could not meet there in crastino animarum to nominate the ſheriffs : whereupon the queen named them herſelf, without ſuch previous aſſembly, appointing for the most part one of two remaining in the laſt year’s lift. And this caſe, thus circumſtanced, is the only authority in our books for the making theſe extraordinary ſheriffs. It is true, the reporter adds, that it was held that the queen by her prerogative might make a ſheriff without the election of the judges, non obstante aliquo statuto in contrarium ; but the doctrine of non obstante, which lets the prerogative above the laws, was effectually demoliſhed by the bill of rights at the revolution, and abdicated Weſtminſter-hall when king James abdicated the kingdom. However, it muſt be acknowledged, that the practice of occaſionally naming what are called pocket-sheriffs, by the ſole authority of the crown, hath uniformly continued to the reign of his preſent majeſty ; in which, it is believed, few (if any) inſtances have occurred.</p><p>Sheriffs, by virtue of ſeveral old ſtatutes, are to con</p><p>tinue in their office no longer than one year ; and yet it hath been said that a ſheriff may be appointed durante bene placito, or during the king's pleasure; and ſo is the form of the royal writ. Therefore, till a new ſheriff be named, his office cannot be determined, unleſs by his own death, or the demiſe of the king ; in which laſt caſe it was uſual for the ſucceſſor to send a new writ to the old ſheriff; but now, by ſtatute I Anne st. 1. c. 8. all officers appointed by the preceding king may hold their offices for six months after the king’s demiſe, unleſs sooner diſplaced by the ſucceſſor. We may farther obſerve, that by ſtatute 1 Ric. 11. c. 11. no man that has ſerved the office of ſheriff for one year can he compelled to ſerve the same again within three years after.</p><p>We ſhall find it is of the utmoſt importance to have the ſheriff appointed according to law, when we conſider his power and duty. Theſe are either as a judge, as the keeper of the king’s peace, as a miniſterial officer of the ſuperior courts of juſtice, or as the king's bailiff</p><p>In his judicial capacity he is to hear and determine all cauſes of 40 shillings value and under, in his court : and he has also a judicial power in divers other civil cases. He is likewiſe to decide the elections of knights of the ſhire, (ſubject to the controul of the Houſe of Commons), of coroners, and of verderors;to judge of the qualification of voters, and to return ſuch as he ſhall determine to be duly elected.</p><p>As the keepers of the king’s peace, both by common law and ſpecial commission, he is the firſt man in the county, and ſuperior in rank to any nobleman therein, during his office. He may apprehend, and commit to priſon, all perſons who break the peace, or attempt to break it ; and may bind,any one in a recognizance to keep the king’s peace. He may, and is bound, ex officio, to pursue and take all traitors, murderers, felons, and other miſdoers, and commit them to gaol for safe custody. He is also to defend his county againſt any of the king’s enemies when they come into the land ; and for this purpoſe, as well as for keeping the peace and purſuing felons, he may command all the people of his county to attend him ; which is called the poſſe comitatus, or power of the county ;which ſummons, every perſon above 15 years old, and under the degree of a peer, is bound to attend upon warning, under pain of fine and imprisonment. But though the ſheriff is thus the principal conſervator of the peace in his county, yet, by the expreſs directions of the great charter, he, together with the conſtable, coroner, and certain other officers of the king, are forbidden to hold any pleas of the crown, or, in other words, to try any criminal offence. For it would be highly unbecoming, that the executioners of juſtice ſhould be alſo the judges ; ſhould impoſe, as well as levy, fines and amercements ; ſhould one day condemn a man to death, and personally execute him the next. Neither may he act as an ordinary juſtice of the peace during the time of his office ; for this would be equally inconsiſtent, he being in many respects the servant of the juſtices.</p><p>In his miniſterial capacity, the ſheriff is bound to execute all proceſs iſſuing from the king’s courts of justice, In the commencement of civil cauſes, he is to ſerve the writ, to arrest, and to take bail ; when the cauſe comes to trial, he muſt ſummon and return the jury ; when it is determined, he muſt ſee the judgment<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0367.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s03-0361"/>
of the court carried into execution. In criminal matters, he alſo arreſts and impriſons, he returns the jury, he has the Cuſtody of the delinquent, and he executes the ſentence of the court, though it extend to death itſelf.</p><p>As the king’s bailiff, it is his buſineſs to preſerve the rights of the king within his bailiwick ; for ſo his county is frequently called in the writs : a word introduced by the princes of the Norman line ; in imitation of the French, whoſe territory is divided into bailiwicks, as that of England into counties. He muſt ſeize to the king’s uſe all lands devolved to the crown by attainder or eſcheat ; muſt levy all fines and forfeitures, muſt ſeize and keep all waifs, wrecks, eſtrays, and the like, unleſs they be granted to ſome ſubject ; and muſt alſo collect the king’s rents within his bailiwick, if commanded by</p><p>proceſs from the exchequer.</p><p>To execute theſe various offices, the ſheriff has under him many inferior officers ; an under-ſheriff, bailiffs, and gaolers, who muſt neither buy, ſell, nor farm their offices, on forfeiture of 500 l.</p><p>The under-ſheriff uſually performs all the duties of the office ; a very few only excepted, where the perſonal preſence of the high-ſheriff is necessary. But no under-ſheriff ſhall abide in his office above one year ; and if he does, by statute 23 Hen. VI. c. 8. he forfeits 200l. a very large penalty in thoſe early days. And no under-ſheriff or ſheriff’s-officer ſhall practiſe as an attorney during the time he continues in ſuch office : for this would be a great inlet to partiality and oppreſſion. But theſe ſalutary regulations are ſhame fully evaded, by practising in the names of other attorneys, and putting in ſham deputies by way of nominal under-ſheriffs : by reaſon of which, ſays Dalton, the under-ſheriffs and bailiffs do grow ſo cunning in their ſeveral places, that they are able to deceive, and it may well be feared that many of them do deceive, both the king, the high-ſheriff, and the county.</p><p>Sheriff, in Scotland. See Law, Part iii. ſect. 3.</p></div></body></text></TEI>