<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0356.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s03-0350-04" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SHEFFIELD</label>,
a town in the west riding of Yorkſhire, about 162 miles from London, is a large, thriving, populous town on the borders of Derbyſhire; has a fine ſtone bridge over the Don, and another over the Sheaf, and a church built in the reign of Henry I.</p><p>It had a caſtle built in the reign of Henry III. in which, or elſe in the manor-houſe of the Park, Mary Queen of Scots was priſoner 16 or 17 years ; but after the death of Charles I. it was, with ſeveral others, by order of parliament demoliſhed. In 1673 an hoſpital was erected here, and endowed with 2001. a-year. There is a charity-ſchool for 30 boys, and another for 30 girls. This town has been noted ſeveral hundred years for cutlers and ſmiths manufactures, which were encouraged and advanced by the neighbouring mines of iron, particularly for files and knives, or whittles ; for the laſt of which eſpecially it has been a ſtaple for above 300 years ; and it is reputed to excel Birmingham in theſe wares, as much as it is ſurpaſſed by it in locks, hinges, nails, and poliſhed ſteel. The firſt mills in England for turning grindſtones were also ſet up here. The houſes look black from the continual ſmoke of the forges. Here are 600 maſter cutlers, incorporated by the ſtyle of the <hi rend="italic">Cutlers of Hallamſhire</hi> (of which this is reckoned the chief town), who employ not leſs than 40,000 perſons in the iron manufactures ; and each of the maſters gives a particular ſtamp to his wares. There is a large market on Tueſday for many commodities, but eſpecially for corn, which is bought up here for the whole West Riding, Derbyſhire, and Nottinghamſhire. It has fairs on Tueſday after Trinity-Sunday, and November 28. In the new market-place, erected by the Duke of Norfolk, the ſhambles are built upon a moſt excellent plan, and ſtrongly incloſed. There are ſeveral other new good buildings, ſuch as a large and elegant octagon chapel belonging to the hoſpital or almshouſes ; likewise a good aſſembly-room and theatre. We muſt not omit the large ſteam-engine, lately finiſhed, for the purpoſe of poliſhing and grinding the various forts of hardware. The pariſh being very large, as well as populous, Mary I. incorporated 12 of the chief inhabitants, and their ſucceſſors for ever, by the ſtyle of the <hi rend="italic">Twelve Capital Burgesses of Sheffield,</hi> empowering them to elect and ordain three priests to aſſiſt the vicar, who were to be paid out of certain lands and rents which ſhe gave out of the crown ; and ſince this ſettlement two more chapels have been built in two hamlets of this pariſh, which are ſerved by two of the aſſiſtants, while the third, in his turn, helps the vicar in his pariſh-church. James I. founded a free grammar-ſchool here, and appointed 13 ſchool burgeſſes to manage the revenue, and appoint the maſter and uſher. A new chapel was built lately by the contributions of the people of the town and of the neighbouring nobility and gentry. Water is conveyed by pipes into Sheffield, whoſe inhabitants pay but a moderate rent for it. In the neighbourhood there are ſome mines of alum. The remains of the Roman fortification between this town and Rotheram, which is six miles lower down the river, are ſtill visible ; and here is alſo the famous trench of five miles long, by ſome called <hi rend="italic">Devil’s</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Dane’s Bank,</hi> and by others <hi rend="italic">Kemp Bank</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Temple’s Bank.</hi> W. Long. 1. 29. N, Lat. 53. 20.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sheffield</hi> (John), duke of Buckinghamſhire, an eminent writer of the laſt and preſent century, of great perſonal bravery, and an able miniſter of ſtate, was born about 1650. He loſt his father at nine years of age ; and his mother marrying lord Oſſulſton, the care of his education was left entirely to a governor, who did not greatly improve him in his studies. Finding that he was deficient in many parts<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0357.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s03-0351"/>
of literature, he reſolved to devote a certain number of hours every day to his ſtudies ; and thereby improved himſelf to the degree of learning he afterwards attained. Though poſſeſſed of a good eſtate, he did not abandon himſelf to pleaſure and indolence, but entered a volunteer in the ſecond Dutch war ; and accordingly was in that famous naval engagement where the duke of York commanded as admiral : on which occaſion his lordſhip behaved ſo gallantly, that he was appointed commander of the Royal Catharine. He afterward made a campaign in the French ſervice under M. de Turenne. As Tangier was in danger of being taken by the Moors, he offered to head the forces which were ſent to defend it ; and accordingly was appointed to command them. He was then earl of Mulgrave, and one of the lords of the bed-chamber to king Charles II. The Moors retired on the approach of his majeſty’s forces ; and the reſult of the expedition was the blowing up of Tangier. He continued in ſeveral great poſts during the ſhort reign of king James II. till that unfortunate prince was dethroned. Lord Mulgrave, though he paid his reſpects to king William before he was advanced to the throne, yet did not accept of any poſt in the government till ſome years after. In the ſixth year of William and Mary he was created marquis of Normanby in the county of Lincoln. He was one of the moſt active and zealous oppoſers of the bill which took away Sir John Fenwick’s life ; and exerted the utmoſt vigour in carrying through the Treaſon Bill, and the bill for Triennial Parliaments. He enjoyed ſome conſiderable poſts under king William, and enjoyed much of his favour and confidence. In 1702 he was ſworn lord privy-ſeal ; and in the ſame year was appointed one of the commiſſioners to treat of an union between England and Scotland. In 1703 he was created duke of Normanby, and ſoon after duke of Buckinghamſhire. In 1711 he was made ſteward of her majeſty’s houſehold, and preſident of the council. During queen Anne’s reign he was but once out of employment ; and then he voluntarily reſigned, being attached to what were called the <hi rend="italic">Tory principles.</hi> Her majeſty offered to make him lord-chancellor ; but he declined the office. He was inſtrumental in the change of the miniſtry in 1710. A circumſtance that reflects the higheſt honour on him is, the vigour with which he acted in favour of the unhappy Catalans, who afterward were ſo inhumanly ſacrificed. He was furvived by only one legitimate son (who died at Rome in 1735) ; but left ſeveral natural children. His worst enemies allow that he lived on very good terms with his laſt wife, natural daughter to king James II. the late ducheſs of Buckingham, a lady who always behaved with a dignity suitable to the daughter of a king. He died in 1721. He was admired by the poets of his age ; by Dryden, Prior, and Garth. His Eſſay on Poetry was applauded by Addiſon, and his Rehearſal is ſtill read with pleaſure. His writings were ſplendidly printed in 1723, in two volumes 4t0 ; and have ſince been reprinted in 1729, in two vols 8vo. The firſt contains his poems on various ſubjects : the ſecond, his proſe works ; which conſiſt of hiſtorical memoirs, ſpeeches in parliament, characters, dialogues, critical obſervations, eſſays, and letters. It may be proper to obſerve, that the edition of 1729 is eaſtrated ; ſome particulars relating to the revolution in that of 1723 having given offence.</p></div></body></text></TEI>