<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>translated from HTML to TEI</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-23-r03-0297-02"
                facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0320.jp2" type="entry">

                <p><label>RICHARD, HENRY</label> (1812-1888), Welsh politician, was the son of the
                    Rev. Ebenezer Richard (1781-1837), a Calvinistic Methodist minister, and was
                    born on the 3rd of April 1812. Educated at Llangeitho grammar school, he also
                    studied at a college at Highbury, and in 1835 he became minister of a
                    Congregational church in the Old Kent Road, London, a position which he retained
                    for fifteen years. Richard is chiefly known as an advocate of peace and
                    international arbitration. In 1848 he became secretary of the Peace Society, and
                    in this capacity he helped to organize a series of congresses in the capitals of
                    Europe, and was partly instrumental in securing the insertion of a declaration
                    in favour of arbitration in the treaty of Paris in 1856. He resigned this post
                    in 1885. In 1868 Richard was elected member of parliament for the Merthyr
                    boroughs, and he remained in the House of Commons until his death at Treborth,
                    near Bangor, on the 20th of August 1888. In parliament he was a leading member
                    of the party which advocated the removal of Nonconformist grievances and the
                    disestablishment of the church in Wales; in 1877 he was chairman of the
                    Congregational Union of England and Wales. Among Richard’s writings may be
                    mentioned: <hi rend="italic">Defensive War</hi> (1846, and again 1890); <hi
                        rend="italic">Memoirs of Joseph Sturge</hi> (1864); <hi rend="italic"
                        >Letters on the Social and Political Condition of the Principality of
                        Wales</hi> (1866, and again 1884); and <hi rend="italic">The Recent Progress
                        of International Arbitration</hi> (1884). He also prepared some of the
                    material for the fife of his friend and associate, Richard Cobden, which was
                    written by Mr John, now Lord, Morley; and he did some journalistic work in the
                        <hi rend="italic">Morning Star</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Evening
                        Star.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>See C. S. Miall, <hi rend="italic">Henry Richard, M.P.</hi> (1889); U. Appleton,
                        <hi rend="italic">Memoirs of Henry Richard</hi> (1889); and articles in <hi
                        rend="italic">Cymru Fydd</hi> for 1888.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
