<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>translated from HTML to TEI</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-23-r03-0399-03"
                facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0422.jp2" type="entry">
               <p>                   <label>ROBERT II.</label> (c. 970-1031), king of France, was a son of Hugh
                    Capet, and was born at Orleans. He was educated at Reims under Gerbert,
                    afterwards Pope Silvester II. As the ideal of medieval Christianity he won his
                    surname of “ Pious ” by his humility and charity, but he also possessed some of
                    the qualities of a soldier and a statesman. His father associated him with
                    himself in the government of France, and he was crowned in December 987,
                    becoming sole king on Hugh’s death in October 996. Robert’s reign is chiefly
                    remembered for its dramatic side. In 988 he had married Rosala, or Susanna,
                    widow of Arnold IL, count of Flanders. This lady, however, was much older than
                    Robert, who repudiated her in 989, fixing his affections upon Bertha, daughter
                    of Conrad the Peaceful, king of Burgundy, or Arles, and wife of Eudes L, count
                    of Blois; and although the pair were related, and the king had been godfather to
                    one of Bertha’s children, they were married in 996, a year after the death of
                    Eudes. Pope Gregory V., whose favour Robert vainly sought to win by allowing
                    Arnulf, the imprisoned archbishop, to return to his see of Reims and forcing
                    Gerbert to flee to the court of the emperor Otto III., excommunicated the king,
                    and a council at Rome imposed a seven years’ penance upon him. For five years
                    the king braved all anathemas, but about 1002 he gave up Bertha and married
                    Constance, daughter of a certain Count William, an intriguing and ambitious
                    woman, who made life miserable for her husband, while the court was disturbed by
                    quarrels between the partisans of the two queens. Still attached to Bertha,
                    Robert took this lady with him to Rome in 1010, but the pope refused to
                    recognize their marriage, and the king was forced to return to Constance. By
                    this wife Robert had four sons, and in 1017, the eldest of these, Hugh,
                    (1007-1025), was crowned as his father’s colleague and successor. After Hugh’s
                    death the king procured the coronation of his second son, Henry, duke of
                    Burgundy, afterwards king of France, a proceeding which displeased Constance,
                    who wished her third son, Robert (d. 1075), afterwards duke of Burgundy, to
                    receive the crown. Robert’s concluding days were troubled by a rising on the
                    part of these two sons, and after a short war, in which he was worsted, the king
                    died at Melun on the 20th of July 1031. The notable gain to France during this
                    reign was the duchy of Burgundy, which Robert claimed on the death of his uncle,
                    Duke Henry, in 1001. The other claimant, however, Otto William, count of upper
                    Burgundy, or Franche Comté, offered so stubborn a resistance that it was not
                    until 1015 that the king secured the duchy, which he gave as an apanage to his
                    son Henry. Nevertheless, Robert himself kept a close oversight over its
                    government, and this was one reason which led to the revolt of his sons in 1030.
                    Owing to family quarrels, he could not prevent the kingdom of Burgundy, or
                    Arles, from passing into the hands of the emperor Conrad II., and no serious
                    results followed his interference in Flanders or in Lorraine. Robert added to
                    the royal domains, and was greatly aided by the support of Richard II. and
                    Richard III., dukes of Normandy, the latter of whom was his son-in-law.</p>               <p>His life was written by his chaplain, Helgaud, and this panegyric, <hi
                        rend="italic">Epitoma vitae Roberti regis,</hi> is published by J. P. Mign»
                    in the <hi rend="italic">Patrologia Latina,</hi> tome cxli. (Paris, 1844). See
                    also C. Pfister, <hi rend="italic">Études sur le règne de Robert le Pieux</hi>
                    (Paris, 1885); and E. Lavisse, <hi rend="italic">Histoire de France,</hi> tome
                    ii. (Paris, 1901).</p>            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
