<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>translated from HTML to TEI</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-23-r03-0319-01"
                facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0342.jp2" type="entry">

                <p><label>RIDINGS</label> are the three districts into which from ancient times
                    Yorkshire has been divided for administrative purposes.</p>
               <p>Formerly there were similar districts in Lindsey in Lincolnshire. The word
                    riding was originally Written as <hi rend="italic">thrithing</hi> or <hi
                        rend="italic">thriding,</hi> but the initial <hi rend="italic">th</hi> has
                    been absorbed in the final <hi rend="italic">th</hi> or <hi rend="italic">t</hi>
                    of the words north, south, east and west, by which it was normally preceded.
                    Ridings are Scandinavian institutions. In Iceland the third part of a <hi
                        rend="italic">thing</hi> which corresponds roughly to an English county was
                    called <hi rend="italic">thrithjungr,</hi> in Norway, however, the <hi
                        rend="italic">thrithjungr</hi> seems to have been an ecclesiastical
                    division. According to the 12th-century compilation known as the “ laws of
                    Edward the Confessor,” the riding was the third part of a county <hi
                        rend="italic">(provincia),</hi> to it causes were brought which could not be
                    determined in the wapentake, and a matter which could not be determined in the
                    riding was brought into the court of the shire. There is abundant evidence that
                    riding courts were held after the Norman Conquest. A charter which Henry I.
                    granted to the Church of St Peter’s at York mentions wapentacmot, tridingmot and
                    shircsmot, and exemptions from suit to the thriding or riding may be noticed
                    frequently in the charters of the Norman kings. As yet, however, the
                    jurisdiction and functions of these courts have not been ascertained. It seems
                    probable from the silence of the records that they had already fallen into
                    disuse early in the 13th century.</p>
               <p>Each of the ridings of Yorkshire has its own lord lieutenant and commission of
                    the peace, and under the Local Government Act of 1888 forms a separate
                    administrative county. They are distinguished as the north, east and west
                    ridings, but the ancient</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-23-r03-0320" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0343.jp2"/>
               <p>divisions of Lindsey were known as the north, south and west ridings
                    respectively.</p>
               <p>See Felix Liebermann, <hi rend="italic">Die Gesetze der Angelsachsen</hi>
                    (Halle, 1888-89); William Stubbs, <hi rend="italic">Constitutional History of
                        England',</hi> Richard Cleasby, <hi rend="italic">Icelandic Dictionary; New
                        English Dictionary',</hi> and William Dugdale, <hi rend="italic">Monasticon
                        Anglicanum</hi> vol. vi., edited by John Caley and others (1846). (G. J. T.)
               </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
