<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>544) considers that this is only the case in the earlier ’ part of the season, and that later the females greatly outnumber the males. It remains to say that the moral characteristics of the Ruff exceed even anything that might be inferred from what has been already stated. By no one have they been more happily described than by Wolley, in a communication to Hewitson <hi rend="italic">{Eggs of Brit. Birds,</hi>  3d ed., p. 346), as follows : —</p><p>“The Ruff, like other fine gentlemen, takes much more trouble with his courtship than with his duties as a husband. Whilst the Reeves are sitting on their eggs, scattered about the swamps, he is to be seen far away flitting about in flocks, and on the ground dancing and sparring with his companions. Before they are confined to their nests, it is wonderful with what devotion the females are attended by their gay followers, who seem to be each trying to be more attentive than the rest. Nothing can be more expressive of humility and ardent love than some of the actions of the Ruff. He throws himself prostrate on the ground, with every feather on his body standing up and quivering ; but he seems as if he were afraid of coming too near his mistress. If she flies off, he starts up in an instant to arrive before her at the next place of alighting, and all his actions are full of life and spirit. But none of his spirit is expended in care for his family. He never comes to see after an enemy. In the [Lapland] marshes, a Reeve now and then flies near with a scarcely audible <hi rend="italic">ka-ka-kuk</hi>  ; but she seems a dull bird, and makes no noisy attack on an invader.”</p><p>Want of space forbids a fuller account of this extremely interesting species. Its breeding-grounds extend from Great Britain@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi> across northern Europe and Asia ; but the birds become less numerous towards the east. They winter in India, reaching even Ceylon, and Africa as far as the Cape of Good Hope. The Ruff also occasionally visits Iceland, and there are several well-authenticated records of its occurrence on the eastern coast of the United States, while an example is stated<hi rend="italic">{Ibis,</hi>  1875, p. 332) to have been received from the northern part of South America.    <hi rend="smallcaps">(a. n.)</hi></p><p>RUFINUS, <hi rend="smallcaps">Tykannius (Turkanius, Toranus),</hi>  the well-known contemporary of Jerome, was born at or near Aquileia about the year 345. In early life he studied rhetoric, and while still comparatively young he entered the cloister as a catechumen, receiving baptism about 370. About the same time a casual visit of Jerome to Aquileia led to the formation of a close and intimate friendship between the two students, and shortly after Jerome’s departure for the East Rufinus also was drawn thither (in 372 or 373) by his interest in its theology and monasticism. He first settled in Egypt, hearing the lectures of Didymus, the Origenistic teacher at Alexandria, and also cultivating friendly relations with Macarius and other ascetics in the desert. In Egypt, if not even before leaving Italy, he had become intimately acquainted with Melania, a wealthy and devout Roman matron, who since the death of her husband had devoted all her means to religious and charitable works ; and when she removed to Palestine, taking with her a number of clergy and monks on whom the persecutions of Valens had borne heavily, Rufinus ultimately (about 378) followed her. While his patroness lived in a convent of her own in Jerusalem, Rufinus, in close cooperation with her and at her expense, gathered together a number of monks in a monastery on the Mount of Olives, devoting himself at the same time with much ardour to the study of Greek theology. When Jerome came to reside at Bethlehem in 386 the friendship formed at AquiIeia was renewed. Another of the intimates of Rufinus was John, bishop of Jerusalem, and formerly a Nitrian monk, by whom he was ordained to the priesthood in 390. In 394, in consequence of the attack upon the doctrines of Origen made by Epiphanius of Salamis during a visit to Jerusalem, a fierce quarrel broke out, which found Rufinus <hi rend="underline">and Jerome ranged on different</hi>  sides; and, though three</p><p>@@@ In England of late years it has been known to breed only in one locality, the name or situation of which it is not desirable to publish.</p><p>years afterwards a formal reconciliation was brought about between Jerome and John through the intervention of third parties, the breach between Jerome and Rufinus remained unhealed.</p><p>In the autumn of 397 Rufinus embarked for Rome, where, finding that the theological controversies of the East were exciting much interest and curiosity, he published a Latin translation of the <hi rend="italic">Apology</hi>  of Pamphilus for Origen, and also (398-399) a somewhat free rendering of the 7rept αρχών of that author himself. In the preface to the latter work he had referred to Jerome as an admirer of Origen, and as having already translated some of his works ; this allusion proved very annoying to the subject of it, who was now exceedingly sensitive as to his reputation for orthodoxy, and the consequence was a bitter pamphlet war, very wonderful to the modern onlooker, who finds it difficult to see anything discreditable in the accusation against a Biblical scholar that he had once thought well of Origen, or in the countercharge against a translator that he had avowedly exercised editorial functions as well. Some time during the pontificate of Anastasius (398-402) Rufinus was summoned from Aquileia to Rome to vindicate his orthodoxy, but he excused himself from personal attendance in a written <hi rend="italic">Apologia pro fide sua</hi>  ; the pope in his reply expressly condemned Origen, but leniently left the question of Rufinus’s orthodoxy to his own conscience. In 408 we find Rufinus at the monastery of Pinetum (in the Campagna?); thence he was driven by the arrival of Alaric to Sicily, being accompanied by Melania in his flight. In Sicily he was engaged in translating the <hi rend="italic">Homilies</hi>  of Origen when he died in 410.</p><p>The original works of Rufinus are—(1) <hi rend="italic">De Adulterations Librorum Origenis—</hi>an appendix to his' translation of the <hi rend="italic">Apology </hi>of Pamphilus, and intended to show that many of the features iu Origens teaching which were then held to be objectionable arise from interpolations and falsifications of the genuine text ; (2) <hi rend="italic">De Benedietionibus XII Patriarcharum Libri II,—</hi>an exposition of Gen. xlix. ; (3) <hi rend="italic">Apologia s. Inveetivarum in Hieronymum Libri II</hi>  ; (4) <hi rend="italic">Apologia pro Fide Sua ad Anastasium Pontifieem</hi>  ; (5) <hi rend="italic">HistOria Eremitiea-</hi>consisting of the lives of thirty-three monks of the Nitrian desert ; (6) <hi rend="italic">Expositio Symbolk</hi>  The <hi rend="italic">Historise Eeclesiasticx Libri XI</hi>  of Rufinus consist partly of a free translation of Eusebius (10 books in 9) and partly of a continuation (bks. x. and xi. ) down to the time of Theodosius the Great. The other translations of Rufinus are—(1) the <hi rend="italic">Instituta Monaehorum</hi>  and some of the <hi rend="italic">Homilies</hi>  of Basil ; (2) the <hi rend="italic">Apology</hi>  of Pamphilus, referred to above ; (3) Origen’s <hi rend="italic">Principia</hi>  ; (4) Origen’s <hi rend="italic">Hornilies</hi>  (Gen.-Kings, also Cant, and Rom.) ; (5) <hi rend="italic">Opusnda</hi>  of Gregory of Nazianzus ; (6) the <hi rend="italic">Sententiæ</hi>  of Sixtus, an unknown Greek philosopher ; (7) the <hi rend="italic">Sententiæ</hi>  of Evagrius ; (8) the <hi rend="italic">Clementine Recognitions</hi>  (the only form in which that work is now extant) ; (9) the <hi rend="italic">Canon Pasehalis </hi>of Anatolius Alexandrinus.</p><p>Vallarsfs uncompleted edition of Ruflnus (vol. i., fol., Verona, 1745) contains the <hi rend="italic">De Benedictionibus,</hi>  the <hi rend="italic">Apologies,</hi>  the <hi rend="italic">Expositio Syrnboli,</hi>  the <hi rend="italic">Historia Erernitiea,</hi>  and the two original books of the <hi rend="italic">Hist. Eeel.</hi>  Sec also Migne, <hi rend="italic">Patrol. </hi>(vol. xxi. of the Latin series). For the translations, see the various editions of Origen, Eusebius, &amp;c.</p><p>RUGBY, a market-town of Warwickshire, is finely situated on a table-land rising from the southern bank of the Avon, at the junction of several railway lines, and near the Grand Junction Canal, 30 miles E.S.E. of Birmingham, and 20 S.S.W. of Leicester. It is a well-built town, with a large number of modern houses erected for private residences. It occupies C, gravel site, is well drained, and has a good supply of water. It owes its importance to the grammar school, built and endowed by Laurence Sheriff, a merchant grocer and servant to Queen Elizabeth, and a native of the neighbouring village of Brownsover. The endowment consisted of the parsonage of Brownsover, Sheriff’s mansion house in Rugby, and one-third (8 acres) of his estate in Middlesex, near the Foundling Hospital, London, which, being let on building leases, gradually increased to about £5000 a year. The full endowment was obtained in 1653. The school originally stood opposite the parish church, and was removed to its</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>