<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>in either that of property or that of obligation. The rise and progress of the military testament has already been explained. The testament of the common law was still ostensibly that <hi rend="italic">per aes et libram</hi>  ; but the practice of granting <hi rend="italic">bonorum possessio secundum tabulas</hi>  to the persons named as heirs in any testamentary instrument that bore outside the requisite number of seals led, from the time of Marcus Aurelius, to the frequent neglect of the time-honoured formalities of the <hi rend="italic">familiae mandpatio</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">nuncupatio testamenti. </hi>It was a rescript of his, declaring that an heir-at-law should no longer be entitled to dispute the last wishes of a testator on the technical ground of non-compliance with the purely formal requirements of the law, that practically introduced what Justinian calls the praetorian testament.</p><p>One of the commonest provisions in the testaments of the period was the <hi rend="italic">fideicommissum,—</hi>a request by the testator to his heir to enter to the inheritance and thereafter denude wholly or partially in favour of a third party. It was introduced in the time of Augustus by (it is said) a testator who had married a peregrin wife, and desired thus indirectly to give to his peregrin children the succession which, as not being citizens, they could neither take <hi rend="italic">ab intestato</hi>  nor as his direct testamentary heirs.@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi>  The practice soon gained ground, and became thoroughly established once the emperor, shocked at the perfidy of a trustee who had failed to comply with the request of his testator, indicated his approval of the new institution by remitting the matter to the consuls of the day, with instructions to do in the circumstances what they thought just. So quickly did it establish itself in public favour, and so numerous did the questions become as to the construction and fulfilment of testamentary trusts, that before long it was found necessary to institute a court specially charged with their determination, —that of the<hi rend="italic">praetor fideicommissarius.</hi></p><p>The employment of a trust as a means of benefiting those who were under disqualifications as heirs or legatees, as, for example, persons who had no <hi rend="italic">testamenti factio,</hi>  women incapacitated by the Voconian law, unmarried and married but childless persons incapacitated by the Julian and Papia-Poppsean law, and so on, was in time prohibited by statute ; but that did not affect its general popularity. For, whether what was contemplated was a transfer of the universal <hi rend="italic">hereditas</hi>  or a part of it to the beneficiary <hi rend="italic">{fideicommissum hereditatis),</hi>  or only of some particular thing <hi rend="italic">{fideicommissum rei singula r is),</hi>  a testamentary trust had various advantages over either a direct institution or a direct bequest <hi rend="italic">{legatum).</hi>  In theory the imposition upon the heir of a trust in favour of a beneficiary, whether it required him to denude of the whole or only a part of the inheritance, did not deprive him of his character of heir or relieve him of the responsibilities of the position ; and at common law therefore he was entitled to decline the succession, often to the great prejudice of the beneficiary. In order to avoid such a mischance, and at the same time to regulate their relations <hi rend="italic">inter se</hi>  and towards debtors and creditors of the testator’s, it became the practice for the parties to enter into stipulatory arrangements about the matter ; but these were to some extent rendered superfluous by two senatusconsults, the Trebellian in the time of Nero and the Pegasian in that of Vespasian, which at once secured the beneficiary against the trustee’s <hi rend="italic">{i.e.,</hi>  the heir’s) repudiation of the inheritance, protected the latter from all risk of loss where he was trustee and nothing more, and enabled the former to treat directly with debtors and creditors of the testator’s and himself ingather the corporeal items of the inheritance.</p><p>It was one of the advantages of a trust-bequest, whether universal or singular, that it might be conferred in a codicil, even though unconfirmed by any relative testament. The codicil <hi rend="italic">{codiciUi),</hi>  also an invention of the time of Augustus, was a deed of a very simple nature. It was inappropriate either for disherison of <hi rend="italic">sui</hi>  or institution of an heir; but if confirmed by testament it might contain direct bequests, manumissions, nominations of tutors, and the like, and whether confirmed or unconfirmed might, as stated, be utilized as a vehicle for trust-gifts. Latterly it was held operative even in the absence of a testament, the trusts contained in it being regarded as burdens on the heir-at-law.</p><p>The most important changes in the law of intestate succession during the period were those accomplished by the Tertullian and Orphitian senatusconsults, fruits of that respect for the precepts of natural law which in so many directions was modifying the doctrines of the <hi rend="italic">pis civile.</hi>  The first was passed in the reign of Hadrian, the second in the year 178, under Marcus Aurelius. Down to the time of the Tertullian senatusconsult a mother and her child by a marriage that was unaccompanied with <hi rend="italic">manus</hi>  stood related to each other only as cognates, being in law members of different families ; consequently their chance of succession to each other was remote, being postponed to that of their respective agnates to the sixth or seventh degree. The purpose of the senatusconsult was to prefer a mother to all agnates of her deceased child except father and brother and sister; father and brother excluded her ; but with a sister of the deceased, and in the absence of father or brother, she shared equally. While there can be little doubt that it was natural considerations that dictated this amendment, yet its authors were too timid to justify it on the abstract principle of common humanity, lest thereby they should seem to impugn the wisdom of <hi rend="italic">thejus civile, </hi>and so they confined its application to women who had thejus <hi rend="italic">liber-orum, i.e.,</hi>  to women of free birth who were mothers of three children and freedwomen who were mothers of four, thus making it ostensibly a reward of fertility. The Orphitian senatusconsult was the counterpart of the Tertullian. It gave children, whether legitimate or illegitimate, a right of succession to their mother in preference to all her agnates; and subsequent constitutions extended the principle, admitting children to the inheritance not only of their maternal grandparents but also to that of their paternal grandmother.</p><p>III. Judicial Procedure.</p><p><hi rend="italic">The Formular System</hi>@@<hi rend="italic">2
                </hi>The ordinary procedure of the first three centuries of the empire was still two-staged ; it commenced before the prsetor <hi rend="italic">{in jure)</hi>  and was concluded before a <hi rend="italic">judex {in judicio). </hi>But the <hi rend="italic">legis actiones</hi>  had given place to praetorian <hi rend="italic">formulae.</hi>  Under the older system parties, and particularly the plaintiff, had themselves to formulate in statutory or traditional words of style the matter in controversy between them ; and as they formulated, so did it go for trial to centumviral court or <hi rend="italic">judex</hi>  or arbiters, with the not infrequent result that it was then all too late discovered that the real point in the case had been missed. Under the formular system parties were free to represent their plaint and defence to the praetor in any words they pleased, the plaintiff asking for a <hi rend="italic">formula</hi>  and usually indicating the style on the <hi rend="italic">album</hi>  that he thought would suit his purpose, and the defendant demanding when necessary an exception, <hi rend="italic">i.e.,</hi>  a plea in defence, either praetorian or statutory, that, without traversing the facts or law of the plaintiffs case, avoided his demand on grounds of equity or public policy. It was for the praetor to consider and determine whether the action or exception should or should not be granted, and, if granted, whether it should be according to the style exhibited on the <hi rend="italic">album</hi>  or according to a modification of it. The result he embodied in a written and signed appointment to a judge, whom he instructed what he had to try, and empowered to pronounce a finding either condemning or acquitting the defendant. This writing was the <hi rend="italic">formula.</hi></p><p>Although it was not until the early empire that this system of procedure attained its full development, yet it had its commencement two centuries before the fall of the republic. Gaius ascribes its introduction and definitive establishment to the <hi rend="italic">Lex Aebutia </hi>(probably of the second decade of the sixth century of the city) and two judiciary laws of the time of Augustus <hi rend="italic">{supra,</hi>  pp. 696, 704). The JEbutian law, of which unfortunately w<hi rend="sup">r</hi>e know very little, is generally supposed to have empowered the praetors (1) to devise a simpler form of procedure for causes already cognizable<hi rend="italic">per legis actionem,</hi>  (2) to devise forms of action to meet cases not cognizable under the older system, and (3) themselves to formulate the issue and reduce it to writing. It was by no means so radical a change as is sometimes supposed. There were <hi rend="italic">formulae</hi>  employed by the praetor both in the procedure <hi rend="italic">per judicis postulationem</hi>  and in that <hi rend="italic">p&gt;er condictionem.</hi>  The difference between them and the <hi rend="italic">formulae</hi>  of the jEbutian system was that the former were in part mere echoes of the statutory words of style uttered by the plaintiff, and that they were not written but spoken in the hearing of witnesses.</p><p>A large proportion of the personal actions of the formular system were evolved out of the <hi rend="italic">legis actio per condictionem.</hi>  The sequence of operations may have been something like this. Taking the simplest form of it, the action for <hi rend="italic">certa pecunia</hi>  under the Silian law, the first step was to drop the formal <hi rend="italic">condictio</hi>  from which it derived its character of <hi rend="italic">legis actio,</hi>  thus avoiding a delay of thirty days ; the plaintiff stated his demand in informal words, and, if the defendant denied indebtedness, the prsetor straightway formulated a written appointment of and instruction to a judge, embodying in it the issue in terms substantially the same as those he would have employed under the earlier procedure:—“Titius be judge. Should it appear that N. N. ought to pay <hi rend="italic">{dare oportere)</hi>  50,000 sesterces to A. A., in that sum condemn N. N. to A. A.@@<hi rend="sup">3</hi>  should it not so appear, acquit him. ” This was no longer the<hi rend="italic">legis actio per condictionem,</hi>  because what had made it <hi rend="italic">legis actio</hi>  was gone, but the <hi rend="italic">certi condictio</hi>  of the formular system. The <hi rend="italic">condictio triti-caria</hi>  of the same system ran on the same lines : “ Titius be judge. Should it appear that N. N. ought to give A. A. the slave Stichus, then, whatever be the value of the slave, in that condemn N. N. to A. A.,” and so on. In both of these examples the <hi rend="italic">formula</hi>  included only two of the four clauses that might find place in it@@<hi rend="sup">4</hi>—an “ in-</p><p>@@@They could not even have a claim as cognates under the praetorian rules ; for the praetors followed the rule of the<hi rend="italic">jus civile</hi>  to this extent, that they did not grant <hi rend="italic">bonorum possessio</hi>  to a person who had not <hi rend="italic">testamenti factio</hi>  with him whose succession was in question.</p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">2</hi> See Keller (as on p. 681, note 1), §§ 23-43 ; Bethmann-Hollweg (as in same note), vol. ii. §§ 81-87 ; Bekker (as in same note), vol. i. chaps. 4-7, vol. ii. chaps. 15, 19, 20; Baron,<hi rend="italic">Gesch. d. rom. Rechts,</hi>  Berlin, 1884, vol. i. §§ 202-215.</p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">3</hi> In the typical Roman styles of actions the plaintiff was usually called Aulus Agerius and the defendant Numerius Negidius.</p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">4 </hi>Gaius enumerates them as the<hi rend="italic">Aemonstratio, intentio, adjudicatio,</hi>  and<hi rend="italic">condemnatio,</hi>  and describes their several functions in iv. §§ 39-43. Besides these <hi rend="italic">&amp; formula</hi>  might be preceded by a <hi rend="italic">praescriptio</hi>  (Gai., iv. §§ 130-137), and have incorporated in it fictions (§§ 32-38), exceptions (§§ 115-125), and replications, duplications, &amp;c. &lt;§§ 126-129).</p></body></text></TEI>