<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>of the long struggle had come at last. The Carthaginian government, despairing of
                being able to send further aid to their troops in Sicily, authorized Hamilcar to
                treat for peace. His proposals were accepted by Catulus, and the terms agreed upon
                between them were confirmed in all essential points by the commissioners sent out
                from Rome. The Carthaginians agreed to evacuate Sicily and the adjoining islands, to
                restore all prisoners, and to pay an indemnity of 2300 talents.</p>
            <p>In its duration and its severity the First Punic War is justly ranked by Polybius
                above all other wars of his own and preceding times, though neither in the military
                talent displayed nor in the importance of its results can it be compared with the
                war that followed. It was distinguished by no military achievement comparable
                with Hannibal’s invasion of Italy, and with the single exception of Hamilcar it
                produced no general of the calibre of Hannibal or Scipio. It was in fact a struggle
                in which both Rome and Carthage were serving an apprenticeship in a warfare the
                conditions of which were unfamiliar to both. The Roman legions were foes very unlike
                any against which the Carthaginian leaders had ever led their motley array of
                mercenaries, while Rome was called upon for the first time to fight a war across the
                sea, and to fight with ships against the greatest naval power of the age. The
                novelty of these conditions accounts for much of the vacillating and uncertain
                action observable on both sides, and their effect in this direction was increased by
                the evident doubts felt by both antagonists as to the lengths to which the quarrel
                should be pushed. It is possible that Hamilcar had already made up his mind that
                Rome must be attacked and crushed in Italy, but his government attempted nothing
                more than raids upon the coast. There are indications also that some in the Roman
                senate saw no end to the struggle but in the destruction of Carthage; yet an
                invasion of Africa was only once seriously attempted, and then only a halfhearted
                support was given to the expedition. But these peculiarities in the war served to
                bring out in the clearest relief the strength and the weakness of the two contending
                states. The chief dangers for Carthage lay obviously in the jealousy exhibited at
                home of her officers abroad, in the difficulty of controlling her mercenary troops,
                and in the ever-present possibility of disaffection among her subjects in
                Libya,—dangers which even the genius of Hannibal failed finally to surmount. Rome,
                on the other hand, was strong in the public spirit of her citizens, the fidelity
                of her allies, the valour and discipline of her legions. What she needed was a
                system which should make a better use of her splendid materials than one under which
                her plans were shaped from day to day by a divided senate, and executed by officers
                who were changed every year, and by soldiers most of whom returned home at the close
                of each summer’s campaign.</p>
            <p>The interval between the First and Second Punic Wars was employed by both Rome and
                Carthage in strengthening their respective positions. Of the islands lying off
                the coast of Italy, the most important, Sicily, had fallen to Rome as the prize of
                the recent war. The eastern end of the island was still left under the rule of King
                Hiero as the ally of Rome, but the larger western portion became directly subject to
                Rome, and a temporary arrangement seems to have been made for its government, either
                by one of the two prætors, or possibly by a quæstor.@@<hi rend="sup">1 </hi>Sardinia
                and Corsica had not been surrendered to Rome by the treaty of 241, but three years
                later (238), on the invitation of the Carthaginian mercenaries stationed in the
                islands, a Roman force occupied them ; Carthage pro-</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>tested, but, on the Romans threatening war, she gave way, and Sardinia and Corsica
                were formally ceded to Rome, though it was some seven or eight years before all
                resistance on the part of the natives themselves was crushed, ln 227, however, the
                senate considered matters ripe for the establishment of a separate and settled
                government, not only in Sardinia and Corsica, but also in Sicily. In that year two
                additional prætors were elected ; to one was assigned the charge of western Sicily,
                to the other that of Sardinia and Corsica,@@<hi rend="sup">2</hi> and thus the first
                stones of the Roman provincial system were laid. Of at least equal importance for
                the security of the peninsula was the subjugation of the Celtic tribes in the valley
                of the Po. These, headed by the Boii and Insubres and assisted by levies from the
                Celts to the westward, had in 225 alarmed the whole of Italy by invading Etruria and
                penetrating to Clusium, only three days’ journey from Rome. Here, however, their
                courage seems to have failed them. They retreated northward along the Etruscan
                coast, until at Telamon their way was barred by the Roman legions, returning from
                Sardinia to the defence of Rome, while a second consular army hung upon their rear.
                Thus hemmed in, the Celts fought desperately, but were completely defeated and the
                flower of their tribesmen slain. The Romans followed up their success by invading
                the Celtic territory. The Boii were easily reduced to submission. The Insubres,
                north of the Po, resisted more obstinately, but by 222 the war was over, and all
                the tribes in the rich Po valley acknowledged the supremacy of Rome. The conquered
                Celts were not enrolled among the Italian allies of Rome, but were treated as
                subjects beyond the frontier. Three colonies were founded to hold them in
                check—Placentia and Cremona in the territory ol the Insubres, Mutina in that of the
                Boii ; and the great northern road (Via Flaminia) was completed as far as the Celtic
                border at Ariminum.</p>
            <p>On the Adriatic coast, where there was no Carthage tc be feared, and no important
                adjacent islands to be annexed, the immediate interests of Rome were limited to
                rendering the sea safe for Italian trade. It was with this object that, in 229, the
                first Roman expedition crossed the Adriatic, and inflicted severe chastisement on
                the Illyriac pirates of the opposite coast.@@<hi rend="sup">3</hi> But the results
                of the expedition did not end here, for it was the means of establishing for the
                first time direct political relations between Rome and the states of Greece proper,
                to many of which the suppression of piracy in the Adriatic was of as much importance
                as to Rome herself. Alliances were concluded with Corcyra, Epidamnus, and Apollonia
                ; and embassies explaining the reasons which had brought Roman troops into Greece
                were sent to the Ætolians, the Achæans, and even to Athens and Corinth. Everywhere
                they were well received, and the admission of the Romans to the Isthmian games@@<hi
                    rend="sup">4</hi> (228) formally acknowledged them as the natural allies of the
                free Greek states against both barbarian tribes and foreign despots, a relationship
                which was destined to prove as useful to Rome in the East as it had already proved
                itself to be in the West.</p>
            <p>While Rome was thus fortifying herself on all sides, Carthage had acquired a
                possession which promised to compensate her for the loss of Sicily, Sardinia, and
                Corsica. The genius of her greatest citizen and soldier, Hamilcar Barca, had
                appreciated the enormous value of the Spanish peninsula, and conceived the scheme of
                founding there a Carthaginian dominion which should not only add to the wealth of
                Carthage, but supply her with troops, and with a base of operations for that war of
                revenge with Rome on which his heart was set. The conquest of southern and eastern
                Spain, begun by Hamilcar (236-228), and carried</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>@@@Marquardt,<hi rend="italic">Rom. Staatsver.,</hi> i. 92; Mommsen, <hi
                    rend="italic">Ji. G.,</hi> i. 543 ; Appian, <hi rend="italic">Sie., 2.</hi></p>
            <lb/>
            <p>@@@ Livy,<hi rend="italic">Epit.</hi> xx.</p>
            <p>@@@<hi rend="sup">3</hi> Polyb., ii. 8.</p>
            <p>@@@<hi rend="italic"> </hi> Polyb., ii. 12.</p>
            <lb/>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
