<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>which stood on the Comitium. On the other slab the emperor is seated on the rostra (this part is broken), while in front a crowd of citizens are bringing tablets and piling them in a heap to be burnt. This records the remission by Trajan of some arrears of debt due to the imperial treasury (Spartian, 7). The background here represents again the Basilica Julia, with (on the right) the Ionic temple of Saturn and the Corinthian temple of Vespasian. Between them is an arch, which may be that of Tiberius. On the left the fig-tree and the statue of Marsyas are repeated. Other explanations of these reliefs have been given, but the above appears the most probable.@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi> Towards the other end of the Forum are remains of a large concrete pedestal. This is usually called the base of the equestrian statue of Domitian (Statius,<hi rend="italic">Silv.,</hi>  i. 22), which stood in front of the Ædes Julii ; but its brick facing shows that it is much later than Domitian’s time, and, moreover, Domitian’s statue was destroyed immediately after his death.</p><p>The seven cubical brick and concrete structures, once faced with marble, which line the Sacra Via, are not earlier than the time of Constantine.@@<hi rend="sup">2</hi> They are probably the pedestals of honorary columns, such as those shown in the relief on Constantine’s arch, mentioned above. The column erected in honour of the tyrant Phocas by Smaragdus in the eleventh year of his exarchate (608) is still standing. It is a fine marble Corinthian column, stolen from some earlier building ; it stands on rude steps of marble and tufa. The name of Phocas is erased from the inscription ; but the date shows that this monument was to his honour. Remains of other small marble structures are shown in Plate VII., but what they are is not known. In the 4th century a long brick and concrete building faced with marble was built along the whole south-east end of the Forum, probably a row of shops. They were destroyed by Comm. Rosa’s order a few years ago. Countless fragments of other buildings, reliefs, and statues are strewn all over the Forum. Many of these are of great interest ; pieces of large granite columns which probably stood on the seven pedestals mentioned above are lying in various places ; some of these appear to have been decorated with bronze reliefs, the iron fastenings of which, run with lead, still exist.@@<hi rend="sup">3</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Palatine HiU or Palatium.</hi></p><p>In addition to the walls of Roma Quadrata (see above), a few remains only now exist earlier in date than the later years of the republic; these are mostly grouped near the Scalæ Caci (see No. 11 in fig. 17) and consist of small cellæ and other structures of unknown use.@@<hi rend="sup">4</hi> They are partly built of the soft tufa used in the wall of Romulus and partly of the hard tufa which resembles peperino. Various names, such as the “hut of Faustulus” and the “ Auguratorium,” have been given to these very ancient remains, but with little reason. One thing is certain, that the buildings ιvere respected and preserved even under the empire and were probably regarded as sacred relics of the earliest times. Remains of more than one temple, probably of the early republican period, exist near this ιvest angle of the Palatine ; these had peristyles with Tuscan columns of tufa stuccoed and painted. The larger of these (see 14 in fig. 17) has been called Conjecturally the temple of Jupiter Victor (Liv., x. 29 ; Ov.,<hi rend="italic">Fast.,</hi>  iv. 621). It stands on a levelled platform of tufa rock, the Ioiver part of which is excavated into quarry chambers, used in later times as water reservoirs. Two ancient ιvell-shafts lined ιvith tufa communicate ιvith these subterranean IioIIoavs. Another extensive building of hard tufa of the republican period exists in the valley afterwards covered by the Flavian palace ; part of this can be seen under the so-called Accademia (21 in fig. 17). Not far from the top of the Scalæ Caci are the massive remains of some large cella, nothing of which noιv exists except the concrete core made of alternate layers of tufa and</p><p>f peperino. It was probably once lined ιvith marble. By it a noble colossal seated figure of a goddess ιvas found, in Greek marble, ιvell modelled, a ιvork of the 1st century a.d. The head and arms are missing, but the figure is probably rightly called a statue of Cybele ; and from it her name has been Conjecturally given to this temple. Augustus in the <hi rend="italic">Monumcnturn A ncyranum</hi>  records AEDEM. MATRIS. MAGNÆ . IN . PALATI0 . FECI ; but it is more probable that his temple to Cybele formed part of the magnificent group of buildings in the area of Apollo (see below). Some interesting early</p><p>architectural fragments are lying near this temple ; they consist of drums and capitals of Corinthian columns, and part of the cornice of the pediment, cut in peperino, and thickly coated with hard white stucco to imitate marble. Betiveen this and the temple (so called) of Jupiter Victor are extensive remains of a large sort of porticus, with tufa Avails and travertine piers, also republican in date. The use and name of this building are unknown. The temple of Jupiter Stator, traditionally voιved by Romulus during his repulse by the Sabines (Liv., i. 12), stood near the Porta Mugionis, and therefore near the road leading up to the Palatine Sacra A ia.@@<hi rend="sup">5 </hi>This has been identified with the ruined concrete podium (40 in fig. 17), the position of which suits the above indications ; but the admixture of travertine, brick, and even marble with the tufa of the concrete shoιvs that no trace here remains of any early building. On the tufa blocks of a shaft leading down to a large drain by the side of these remains are incised in large letters—</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">FILOCRatγ DIOCLe<hi rend="sup">a l</hi>-</hi></p><p>—possibly the names of Greek stone-masons (Diodes, Philocrates) ; the form of the letters shows that this inscription is as early as the 2d or even 3d century B. c.</p><p>Remains of extensive lines of buildings in early opus reticulatum exist on the upper slopes of the Palatine, all along the Velabrum side, and on the south-west side as far as the so-called Domus Gelotiana. These buildings are constructed on the ruins of the Avail of Romulus, a great part of which has been cut away to make room for them ; their base is at the foot of the ancient wall, on the shelf cut midway in the side of the hill ; their top reached originally above the upper level of the summit. They are of various dates and cannot be identified with any known buildings. Part is apparently of the time of the emperor Tiberius, and no doubt belongs to the Domus Tiberiana mentioned by Suetonius <hi rend="italic">(Tib.,</hi>  5 ; comp. Tac., <hi rend="italic">Hist.,</hi>  i. 27, and iii. 71) ; this palace covered a great part of the Avest corner of the hill. Of about the same date is a very interesting and well-preserved private house built wholly of opus reticulatum ; it is usually called the house of Livia. It has a small atrium, out of which open the triclinium and the tablinum with a room (α∕α) on each side, all handsomely decorated with good paintings of mythological and domestic scenes, probably the work of Greek artists, as inscriptions in Greek occur,—<hi rend="italic">c.g.</hi>, EPMHC, under the figure of Hermes, in a picture representing his deliverance of Io from Argus.@@<hi rend="sup">6</hi>  The back part of this house was three stories high, and is divided into a great number of very small rooms, mostly bedrooms. The house is built in a sort of hole against the side of an elevation, so that the upper floor behind is level with an ancient paved road. The dampness caused by this is counteracted and kept off the paintings by a lining of flange-tiles over the external Avails, under the stucco, thus forming an air-cavity all over the surface. From the back of the house, at the upper level, a long subterranean passage leads towards the Flavian palace, and then, turning at right angles and passing by the foundations of the so-called temple of Jupiter Victor, issues in the ancient tufa building mentioned above (20 in fig. 17). Another crypto-porticus starts near this house and communicates with the long semi-subterranean passage by which the palaces of Caligula and Domitian are connected (19 in fig. 17). It is ornamented with very beautiful stucco reliefs of cupids, beasts, and foliage, once painted and gilt. This private house is probably that of Germani-cus, into which the soldiers who killed Caligula in the long crypto-porticus escaped, as described by Josephus<hi rend="italic">(Ant. Jud.,</hi>  xix. 1 ; see also Suet., <hi rend="italic">Cal.,</hi>  58). Some inscribed lead pipes were found in this house ; some pieces bear the inscription IVLIAE . AVG., probably the daughter of Titus.</p><p>The palace of Augustus and the Area Apollinis@@<hi rend="sup">7</hi> occupied a great portion of the central part of the Palatine (see 47 and 48 in fig. 17) ; the splendour of its architecture and the countless works of art in gold, silver, ivory, bronze, and marble, mostly the production of the best Greek artists, which adorned this magnificent group of buildings must have made it the chief glory of this splendid city. It was approached from a road leading out of the Summa Sacra Via along the line of the present Via di S. Bonaven-tura ; the entrance, probably the Arcus of Pliny<hi rend="italic">(H.N.,</hi>  xxxvi. 4, 10), led through lofty propylæa into a very extensive peristyle or porticus, with (at least) fifty-two fluted columns of Numidian giallo ; the rest was of white Luna and Athenian marble. In the centre of this enclosure stood the great octostyle peripteral temple of Apollo Palatinus, so called to distinguish it from another temple of Apollo outside the Porta Carmentalis, remains of which exist</p><p>@@@1    See Brizio, <hi rend="italic">Ann. lnst.,</hi>  1872, p. 309 ; Henzen, <hi rend="italic">Bull. Inst.,</hi>  1872, p. 81 ; and Jordan, <hi rend="italic">MarsyasaufdemForum,</hi>  Berlin, 1883.</p><p>@@@2    It is probable that these occupy the line of the Tabemæ Veteres.</p><p>@@@3    <hi rend="italic">Authorities on the Forum.—</hi>Nichols, <hi rend="italic">Roman Forum,</hi>  London, 1877 (very useful from its collection of passages in ancient authors) ; Jordan, <hi rend="italic">Capitol, Forum, £c.,</hi>  Berlin, 1881, and <hi rend="italic">Topographie Roms,</hi>  vol. i., 1878 ; Nibby, <hi rend="italic">Il Foro Romano, </hi>1819 ; Angelini and Fea, <hi rend="italic">Il Foro Romano,</hi>  1837 ; Tocco, <hi rend="italic">Ripristinazione del Foro, </hi>1858 ; Ravioli and Montiroli, <hi rend="italic">Foro Romano,</hi>  1859 ; Michelet, <hi rend="italic">DasForum Romanum, </hi>Berlin, 1877; JIarucchi, <hi rend="italic">Il Foro Romano,</hi>  ISSl ; Dutert, Le <hi rend="italic">Forum Romain,</hi>  Paris, 1876 (very handsomely illustrated, but more fanciful than trustworthy) ; Canina, <hi rend="italic">U Foro Romano,</hi>  1845 (open to the same criticism as the work of Dutert, and wholly stultified by later discoA<hi rend="sup">r</hi>eries). For inscriptions found in the Forum, see Jordan, “ Sylloge Inscrip. Fori Rom.,” in the<hi rend="italic">Fphem. Epigraph., </hi>iii. p. 24S <hi rend="italic">sq.</hi>  Some of the more recent excavations are described by Lanciani, “ Scavi del Foro,” in <hi rend="italic">Notizie degli Seavi</hi>  for 1882.</p><p>@@@    JIany masons’ marks exist on the tufa blocks of the most primitive buildings near the Scalæ Caci (see fig. 10).</p><p>@@@5    Dionys., ii. 50; see also Plut., Cic., 16; Ov., <hi rend="italic">Fast.,</hi>  vi. 793, and <hi rend="italic">Trist.,</hi>  iii. 127. Near this temple, and also near the Porta JIugonia, was the house of Tarquinius Priscus (Liv., i. 41 ; Sol., <hi rend="italic">Polyhist.,</hi>  i. 24). Owing to the strength of its position this temple ιvas more than once selected during troubled times as a safe meeting-place for the Senate; it was here, as being a “locus ιnuni-tissimus,” that Cicero delivered his <hi rend="italic">First Catiline Oration</hi>  (see Cic., <hi rend="italic">In Cat.,</hi>  i. 1).</p><p>@@@6    See <hi rend="italic">Μon. Inst.,</hi>  xi., pis. xxii., xxiii. ; Renier, <hi rend="italic">Les Peintures du Palatin,</hi></p><p>Paris, 1870.    .    ,</p><p>@@@7    See Lanciani's paper in <hi rend="italic">Bull. Comm. Arch. Roma,</hi>  iv., 1883.</p></body></text></TEI>