<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>the Later English style with embattled parapet. There are a mechanics’ institute and a working men’s club. Coal and stone are obtained in the neighbourhood, and the town possesses match works and rope and twine factories. The population of the urban sanitary district (area 3302 acres) in 1871 was 3733, and in 1881 it was 5105.</p><p>ROTIFERA. The <hi rend="italic">Rotifera</hi>  (or <hi rend="italic">Rotatoria)</hi>  form a small, in many respects well-defined, but somewhat isolated class of the animal kingdom. They are here treated of separately, partly on account of the difficulty of placing them in one of the large phyla, partly on account of their special interest to microscopists.</p><p>Now familiarly known as “ wheel animalcules ” from the wheel-like motion produced by the rings of cilia which generally occur in the head region, the so-called rotatory organs, they were first discovered by Leeuwenhoek (I),@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi> to whom we also owe the discovery of<hi rend="italic">Bacteria</hi>  and ciliate <hi rend="italic">Infusoria.</hi>  Leeuwenhoek described the <hi rend="italic">Rotifer vulgams</hi>  in 1702, and he subsequently described <hi rend="italic">Melicerta mngens</hi>  and other species. A great variety of forms were described by other observers, but they were not separated as a class from the unicellular organisms <hi rend="italic">(Protozoa)</hi>  with which they usually occur until the appearance of Ehrenberg’s great monograph (2), which contained a mass of detail regarding their structure. The classification there put forward by Ehrenberg is still widely adopted, but numerous observers have since added to our knowledge of the anatomy of the group (3). At the present day few groups of the animal kingdom are so well known to the micro-scopist, few groups present more interesting affinities to the morphologist, and few multicellular animals such a low physiological condition.</p><p><hi rend="italic">General Anatomy.—</hi>The <hi rend="italic">Rotifera</hi>  are multicellular animals of microscopic size which present a coelom. They are bilaterally symmetrical and present no true metameric segmentation. A head region is generally well marked, and most forms present a definite tail region. This tail region has been termed the “pseudopodium.” Itvaries very much in the extent to which it is developed. It attains its highest development in forms like <hi rend="italic">Philodina, </hi>which affect a Ieech-Iike method of progression and use it as a means of attachment. We may pass from this through a series of forms where it becomes less and less highly developed. In such forms as <hi rend="italic">Brachionus</hi>  it serves as a directive organ in swimming, while in a large number of other forms it is only represented by a pair of terminal styles or flaps. In the sessile forms it becomes a contractile pedicle with a suctorial extremity. A pseudopodium is entirely absent in <hi rend="italic">Asplanxhna, Tmarthra, Polyarthra,</hi>  and a few other genera. The pseudopodium, when well developed, is a very muscular organ, and it may contain a pair of glands (fig. 2, <hi rend="smallcaps">a, </hi><hi rend="italic">gl)</hi>  which secrete an adhesive material.</p><p>The surface of thebody is covered by a firm homogeneous structureless cuticle. This cuticle may become hardened by a further development of chitin, but no calcareous deposits ever take place in it. The cuticle remains softest in those forms which live in tubes. Among the free-living forms the degree of hardening varies considerably. In some cases contraction of the body merely throws the cuticle into wrinkles <hi rend="italic">(Notornmata, Asjdanchna)</hi>  ; in others definite ring-like joints are produced which telescope into one another during contraction ; while in others again it becomes quite firm and rigid and resembles the carapace of one of the <hi rend="italic">Entomostraxa</hi>  ; it is then termed a “ Iorica. ” The Iorica may be prolonged at various points into spines, which may attain a considerable length. The surface may be variously modified, being in some cases smooth, in others</p><lb/><p>@@@ These numbers refer to the bibliography at p. 8.</p><lb/><p>marked, dotted, ridged, or sculptured in various ways (fig. 1, κ). The curved spines of <hi rend="italic">Philodina aculeata</hi>  (fig. 1, <hi rend="smallcaps">g) </hi>and the long rigid spines of <hi rend="italic">Tmarthra</hi>  are further developments in this direction. The so-called setæ of <hi rend="italic">Polyarthra</hi>  on the other hand are more complex in nature, and are moved by muscles, and thus approach the “ limbs ” of <hi rend="italic">Pedalion.</hi></p><p>Several genera present an external casing or sheath or tube which is termed an “ urceolus.” In <hi rend="italic">Eloscularia</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">Stejohanxceros</hi>  the urceolus is gelatinous and perfectly hyaline ; in <hi rend="italic">Conocfiilus</hi>  numerous individuals live in such a hyaline urceolus arranged in a radiating manner. The urceolus, which is secreted by the animal itself, may become covered with foreign particles, and in one species, the well-known <hi rend="italic">Melicerta mngens,</hi>  the animal builds up its urceolus with pellets which it manufactures from foreign</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>