<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p><hi rend="italic">nata);</hi>  but how they were dealt with when the debtor made default is by no means clear.</p><p>f <hi rend="italic">Changes in the Law of Succession.—</hi>The two forms of testament of the regal period <hi rend="italic">(supra,</hi>  p. 674) still remained in use in the early republic ; but in course of time they were displaced by the general adoption of that executed with the copper and the scales <hi rend="italic">(testamentum per aes et libram).</hi>  It seems to be the general opinion that it was to the first two that the words applied which stood in the forefront of the provisions of the XII. Tables about inheritance,—“uti legassit suae rei, ita jus esto.” Whether resort was to the comitia or to the army, the testator’s own will in the matter was henceforth to be supreme. There was to be no more reference to the pontiffs as to the expediency of the testament in view of the interests of the family <hi rend="italic">sacra</hi>  and of creditors of the testator’s; from legislators, sanctioning a departure from the ordinary rules of succession, the assembled Quirites became merely witnesses,—recipients of the oral declaration of the testator’s will in regard to his inheritance.</p><p>The testament with the copper and the scales is depicted by Gaius as a written instrument. But he presents it in what was apparently the third stage of its history. Its probable origin has been explained in describing the result of the Servian reforms upon the private law. It was then not a testament but only a makeshift for one. A plebeian was not qualified in the regal period to make a testament in the comitia; so, instead, he transferred his estate to a friend on whom he could rely with instructions how to distribute it on his death. The transferee was called <hi rend="italic">familiae emptor,</hi>  because the conveyance was in form a mancipation for a nominal price.</p><p>It is not at all unlikely that the same device may occasionally have been resorted to by a patrician who had neglected to make a regular testament, and was seized with mortal illness before he had an opportunity of appealing to the curies. But such a disposition was not a testament, and may not have been so called. A testament was the nomination of a person as the testator’s heir,—sometimes the substitution of an individual of the testator’s choice for the heir assigned to him by law, sometimes the acceptance of the latter but in the character of testamentary heir, so that the testator might be able to impose upon him what burdens he pleased as the tacit condition of heirship. It made the person instituted as fully the representative of the testator after his death as his heir-at-law would have been had he died intestate. The <hi rend="italic">mortis causa</hi>  mancipation that opened the way for the testament <hi rend="italic">per aes et libram </hi>conferred upon the <hi rend="italic">familiae emptor</hi>  no such character. Gaius says that he stood in place of an heir <hi rend="italic">ifieredis loco),</hi>  inasmuch as he had such of an heir’s rights and duties as the <hi rend="italic">familiae venditor</hi>  had it in his power to confer and impose ; but the transaction was but a conveyance of estate, -with a limitation of the right of the grantee. It has been argued that, as the law did not recognize conditional mancipation, the conveyance must have operated as a complete and immediate divestiture of the grantee. But this does not follow. For it was quite competent for a man, in transferring property by mancipation, to reserve to himself a life interest; and apparently it was equally competent for him to postpone delivery of possession, without infringing the rule that the mancipation itself could not be «c <hi rend="italic">cerlo tempore.</hi>  So far as one can see, therefore, there was nothing to prevent the grantee of the conveyance (or quasi-testator) bargaining that he was to retain the possession till his death ; and, as the/aww'Zia was an aggregate of estate <hi rend="italic">(universitas rerum)</hi>  which retained its identity notwithstanding any change in its component elements, he must in such case have been as free to operate on it while he survived as if he had never conveyed it by mancipation.</p><p>Cicero incidentally remarks—what indeed the nature of the business of itself very distinctly suggests—that the true testament with the copper and the scales had its statutory warrant, not in the <hi rend="italic">uti legassit suae rei</hi>  of the XII. Tables, but in the provision contained in the words,—“ cum nexum faciet mancipiumque, uti lingua nuncupassit, ita jus esto.” Reflexion on the import and comprehensiveness of these words led the interpreters to the conclusion that there was nothing in them to prevent the direct institution of an heir in the course of the <hi rend="italic">verba nuncupata</hi>  engrafted on a mancipation. From the moment this view was adopted</p><p>and put in practice the <hi rend="italic">familiae mancipatio</hi>  ceased to be a transfer of the testator’s estate to the <hi rend="italic">familiae emptor; </hi>the latter’s purchase was now for form’s sake only, though still an indispensable form, since it was it alone that, according to the letter of the statute, imparted efficacy to the <hi rend="italic">nuncupatio.</hi>  But it was the <hi rend="italic">nuncupatio—</hi>the oral declaration addressed to the witnesses—that really contained the testamentary disposition, <hi rend="italic">i.e.,</hi>  the institution of an heir, with such other provisions as the testator thought fit to embody in it. This was the second stage in the history of the testament <hi rend="italic">per aes et libram.</hi>  The third was marked by the introduction of tablets in which the testamentary provisions were set out in writing, and which the testator displayed to the witnesses, folded and tied up in the usual manner, declaring that they contained the record of his last will.</p><p>Gaius narrates the words spoken by the <hi rend="italic">familiae emptor</hi>  and addressed to the testator as follows :—“Your estate and belongings <hi rend="italic">(familia pecuniaque tua),</hi>  be they mine by purchase with this bit of copper and these copper scales, subject to your instructions, but in my keeping, that so you may lawfully make your testament according to the statute <hi rend="italic">{quo tujure testamentum faccrepossis secundum legem publicam). ” </hi>The meaning of the words “ in my keeping <hi rend="italic">{endo custodelam meam)</hi>  ” is not quite obvious ; they may have been remnants of an older style, or may be due to a clerical error of the writer of the Verona MS. Certain it is that they no more imported a real custody than a real property in the <hi rend="italic">familiae emptor</hi>  ; for the testator remained so entirely master of his estate that the very next day if he pleased he might mancipate it anew to a different purchaser, and nuncupate fresh testamentary writings. The nuncupation was in these terms : “ As is written in these tablets so do I give, so do I legate, so do I declare my will; therefore, Quirites, grant me your testimony ” ; and, adds Gaius, “ whatever the testator had set down in detail in his testamentary tablets he was regarded as declaring and confirming by this general statement. ” To the appeal of the testator the witnesses responded by giving their testimony in words which unfortunately are not preserved ; and then the testament was sealed by testator, officials, and witnesses, the seals being outside according to the early fashion.</p><p>Although this testament with the copper and the scales was justified in the first instance by the provision of the XII. Tables as to the effect of nuncupative words annexed to a mancipation, yet in course of time it came to be subordinated to that other one which dealt directly with testamentary dispositions, —<hi rend="italic">uti legassit suae rei, ita jus esto.</hi>  Upon the words <hi rend="italic">riti legassit</hi>  the widest possible meaning was put by the interpreters : not only was a testator held entitled on the strength of them to appoint tutors to wife and children, to enfranchise slaves, and make bequests to legatees, but he might even disinherit his proper heir <hi rend="italic">{suus heres)</hi>  in favour of a stranger, so long as he did so in express terms. Institution of a stranger without mention of the proper heir, however, was fatal, at least if the latter was a son ; for without express disherison <hi rend="italic">{exheredatio) </hi>his father could not deprive him of the interest he had in the family property as in a manner one of its joint owners. It can hardly be supposed that disherison was contemplated by the compilers of the Tables: it was foreign to the traditional conception of the family and the family estate. But it was a right whose concession could not be resisted when claimed as embraced in the <hi rend="italic">uti legassit,</hi>  although generally discountenanced, and as far as possible restrained by the strictness of the rules imposed on its exercise.</p><p>In the absence of a testament, or on its failure from any cause, the succession opened to the heirs <hi rend="italic">ab intestato. </hi>So notoriously were the <hi rend="italic">sui heredes</hi>  entitled to the first place—and that not so much in the character of heirs as of persons now entering upon the active exercise of rights hitherto existing, though in a manner dormant—that the compilers of the XII. Tables thought it superfluous expressly to declare it. “ If a man die intestate, leaving no <hi rend="italic">suus heres,</hi>  his nearest agnate shall have his estate. If the agnate also fail, his gentiles shall have it.” It has been pointed out, in dealing with the tutory of agnates, that the notion of agnation, as a bond distinct from that which connected the gentile members of a clan, was due to the decemvirs. They had to devise a law of intestate tutory and succession suitable alike to the patricians who had <hi rend="italic">gentes </hi>and to the plebeians who had none. To put the latter in exactly the same position as the former was beyond their power <hi rend="italic">; for</hi>  the fact had to be faced that the plebeians had no gentile institutions, and to create them was impossible.</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>