<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Cosmati,@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi> seven members of which, for four generations, were skilful architects, sculptors, and mosaicists.</p><p>The following are the names and dates known from existing inscriptions :—</p><p>Their principal works in Rome are :—ambones of S. Maria in Ara Cceli (Lorenzo) ; door of S. Saba, 1205, anti door with mosaics of S. Tommaso in Formis (Jacopo) ; chapel of the Sancta Sanctorum, by the Lateran (Cosimo) ; pavement of S. Jacopoalla Lungara, and (probably) the magnificent episcopal throne and choir-screen in S. Lorenzo fuori Ie Mura, of 1254 (Jacopo the younger) ;@@<hi rend="sup">2</hi> baldacchino of the Lateran and of S. Maria in Cosmedin, c. 1294 (Adeodato) ; tombs in S. Maria sopra Minerva (c. 1296), in S. Maria Maggiore, and in S. Balbina (Giovanni), A large number of other works by members and pupils of the same family, but unsigned, exist in Rome. These are mainly altars and baldacchini, choir-screens, paschal candlesticks, ambones, tombs, and the like, all enriched with sculpture and glass mosaic of great brilliance and decorative effect.</p><p>Besides the more mechanical sort of work, such as mosaic patterns and architectural decoration, they also produced mosaic pictures and sculpture of very high merit, especially the recumbent effigies, with angels standing at the head and foot, in the tombs of Ara Cceli, S. Maria Maggiore, anti elsewhere. One of their finest works is in S. Cesareo ; this is a marble altar richly decorateel with mosaic in sculptured panels, and (below) two angels drawing back a curtain (all in marble) so as to expose the open grating of the confessio. The magnificent cloisters of S. Paolo fuori Ie Mura, built about 1285 by Giovanni, the youngest of the Cosmati, are one of the most beautiful works of this school. The baldacchino of the same basilica is a signed work of the Florentine Arnolfo del Cambio, 1285, “cum suo socio Petro,” probably a pupil of the Cosmati. Other works of Arnolfo, such as the Braye tomb at Ohvieto (g<hi rend="sup">,</hi>.v.), show an intimate artistic alliance between him and the Cosmati. The equally magnificent cloisters of the Lateran, of about the same date, are very similar in design ; both these triumphs of the sculptor-architect’s and    mosaicist’s    work have    slender marble    columns,</p><p>twisted or straight, richly    inlaid with    bands of glass    mosaic in</p><p>delicate and brilliant patterns. The shrine of the Confessor at AVestminster is    a work of    this school,    executed about    1268 (see</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mosaic). The    general style of works    of the Cosmati    school is</hi></p><p>Gothic in its main lines, especially in the elaborate altar-canopies, with their pierced geometrical tracery. In detail, however, they differ widely from the purer Gothic of northern countries. The richness of effect which the English or French architect obtained by elaborate and carefully worked mouldings was produced in Italy by the beauty of polished marbles and jewel-like mosaics,—the details being mostly rather coarse and often carelessly executed.</p><p>Chiefly to the 13th century belong the large number of beautiful campanili, which are the most conspicuous relics of the mediæval period in Rome. The finest of these are attached to the churches of S. AIaria Nuova, SS. Giovanni e Paolo, and S. Maria Maggiore. Others belong to the basilicas of S. Lorenzo fuori and S. Croce in Gerusalemme, and to S. Giorgio in Velabro, S. Maria in Cosmedin, S. Alessio, S. Giovanni ad Portam Latinam, S. Cecilia, S. Crisogono, and S. Pudentiana. They occupy various positions with regard to the church, being all later additions ; that of SS. Giovanni e Paolo stands at some distance from it. In design they are very similar, consisting of many stages, divided by brick and marble cornices ; in the upper stories are from two to four windows on each side, with round arches supported on slender marble columns. They are decorated with brilliantly coloured <hi rend="italic">eiotole</hi>  or disks of earthenware, enamelled and painted in green or turquoise blue, among the earliest existing specimens of the so-called majolica (see Pottery, vol. xix. p. 624 <hi rend="italic">sq.).</hi>  Sometimes disks or crosses made of red or green porphyry are inlaid in the walls. In most cases on one face of the top story is a projecting canopied niche, which once contained a statue or mosaic picture. The walls are built of fine neat brickwork. One campanile (that of S. Maria Maggiore), the largest and once the handsomest of all, has string-courses of enamelled and coloured terra-cotta. The slender columns of the windows have often proved insufficient to support the weight, and so many of the arches are built up.@@<hi rend="sup">3</hi></p><p>Though but little used for churches, the Gothic style, in its modified Italian form, was almost Universallv employed for domestic</p><p>architecture in Rome during the 13th and 14th centuries. Tufa@@<hi rend="sup">4 </hi><hi rend="italic">or</hi>  brick was used for the main walls, the lowest story being often supported on an arcade of pointed arches and marble columns. The windows were usually formed of large marble slabs with trefoilshaped heads or cusped arches. As a rule the upper stories projected slightly over the lower wall, and were supported on small ornamental machicolations. The top story frequently had an open loggia, with rows of pointed arches. AVhen vaulting was used it also was of the pointed form, usually in simple quadripartite bays, with slightly moulded groin-ribs. The finest existing specimen ol this style is the palace built about 1300 by Boniface VIIL (Gaetanc family), enclosing the tomb of Cecilia AIetella on the Via Appia, with a graceful little chapel within the precincts of the castle. This building is very worthy of study ; the remaining part is well preserved. Many houses of this period, though generally much injured by alterations, still exist in Rome. They are mostly in out-of-the-way alleys, and, not being mentioned in any books, are seldom examined. The Ghetto and the quarter near the Ponte Rotto contain many of these interesting buildings, as well as some of the most crowded parts of the Trastevere district ; all are rapidly disappearing under the wholesale destruction of old streets now in progress. Among those which may possibly escape for a while is the 13th-century house -where Giulio Romano lived, near the Palazzo di Venezia, and the Albergo del Orso, at the end of the Via di Tordi-nona, of the same period, which was an inn in the 16th century and is one still ; this has remains of a fine upper loggia, with rich cornices in moulded terra-cotta ; the lowest story has pointed vaulting resting on many pillars. Another graceful but less stately house exists, though sadly mutilated, opposite the entrance to the atrium of S. Cecilia in Trastevere.@@<hi rend="sup">5</hi>  Very few now remain of the once numerous lofty towers built by the turbulent Roman barons for purposes of defence. The finest, the Torre della AIilizia on the Viminal, was built in the 13th century by the sons of Petrus Alexius ; of about the same date is the Torre dei Conti, near the forum oi Augustus, built by AIarchione of Arezzo ; both these were once much higher than they are now ; they are very simple and noble in design, with massive walls faced with neat brickwork, much resembling that of the 2d century.</p><p>Till the 14th century the Lateran was the usual residence of the pope ; this was once a very extensive building, covering four times its present area. The original house is<hi rend="sub">ι</hi>said to have belonged to the senator Plautius Lateranus in the reign of Nero ; but the existing part on the line of the Aurelian wall is of the 3d century. This house, which had become the property of the emperors, was given by Constantine as a residence for S. Sylvester ; it was very much enlarged at many periods during the next ten centuries ; in 1308 a great part was burnt, and in 1586 the ancient palace was completely destroyed by Sixtus V., and the present palace built by Domenico Fontana. The Cappella Sancta Sanctorum (see list of Cosmati works) is the only relic of the older palace.@@<hi rend="sup">6 </hi>The present palace has never been used as a papal residence ; in the 18th century it was an orphan asylum, and is now a museum of classical sculpture and early Christian remains.</p><p>The Vatican palace also appears to have originated in a house which existed in the time of Constantine. This was rebuilt by Innocent III. (c. 1200) and enlarged by Nicholas III. (1277-80). It did not, however, become the fixed residence of the popes till after the return from Avignon in 1377. In 1415 John XXIIL connected the Vatican and the castle of S. Angelo by a covered passage carried on arches. But little of the existing palace is older than the 15th century ; Nicholas V. in 1447 began its reconstruction on a magnificent scale, and this was earned on by Sixtus IV. (Sistine chapel), Alexander VI. (Appartamenti Borgia), Julius II. and Leo X. (Bramante’s cortile and paintings by Raphael), and Paul III. (Sala Regia and Cappella Paolina by Antonio da Sangallo). Sixtus V. and his successors built the lofty part of the palace on the east of Bramante’s cortile. The Scala Regia was built by Bernini for Urban VIII., the Aluseo Pio-Clementino under ClementXIV. and Pius VI., the Braccio Nuovo under Pius A<hi rend="sup">r</hi>IL, and lastly the grand stairs up to the cortile were added by Pius IX.</p><p>The Quirinal palace, now occupied by the king of Italy, is devoid of architectural merit. It stands on the highest part of the hill, on the site of part of thé baths of Constantine. This palace was begun in 1574, under Gregory XIII., by Flaminio Ponzio, and was completed by Fontana and AIaderna under subsequent popes.</p><p>@@@1    An excellent account of the Cosmati is given by Boito, <hi rend="italic">Architettura del Medio Evo,</hi>  Milan, 1880, pp. 117-182.</p><p>@@@    The chief signed works of Jacopo and his brother Luca are at Anagni and Subiaco.</p><p>@@@3    See De Montault, <hi rend="italic">Les Cloches de Rome,</hi>  Arras, 1874.</p><p>@@@4    For many centuries wall-facing of small tufa stones was used, <hi rend="italic">e.g.,</hi>  in the mediæval part of the Capitol; this was called “opera Saracinesca” from its supposed adoption from the Saracens ; it is largely employed in the walls and towers of the Leonine city, built by Leo IV. (848-852) to defend the Vatican basilica and palace against the inroads of the Moslem invaders. The greater part of this wall is now destroyed and built over, but a long piece with massive circular towers well preserved exists in the gardens of the Vatican.</p><p>@@@5    The house of Crescentius, popularly called the “ house of Rienzi,” near the</p><p>Ponte Rotto, is perhaps the sole relic of the domestic architecture of an earlier period,—the Ilth century. Its architectural decorations are an extraordinary mixture of marble fragments of the most miscellaneous sort, all taken from classical buildings ; it has a long but somewhat unintelligible inscription over the doorway.    <hi rend="sub">-</hi>    ,    » <hi rend="sub">i</hi>, ,    . . .</p><p>@@@6    The great mosaic in the adjacent apse is a modem copy of that which once decorated the triclinium of Leo III. (795-816).</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>