<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>OrJer II.—Bdelloida.</p><p>Forms which swim and creep like a leech ; foot retractile, jointed, telescopic, termination furcate.</p><p>Fam. 3. Philodixadze. <hi rend="italic">Philodina, Rotifer, Callidiua.</hi></p><p>Order III.—Ploima.</p><p>Forms which swim only.</p><p>Grade A. Illoricata.</p><p>Fam. 4. Hydatinadæ. <hi rend="italic">Hydatina, Rhinops.</hi></p><p>Fam. 5. Synchætadæ. <hi rend="italic">Synchxta, Polyarthra.</hi></p><p>Fam. 6. Notommatadæ. <hi rend="italic">Kotommata, Digleua, Furcularia,</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Scaridium, Pleurotrocha, Distemma.</hi></p><p>Fam. 7. Triarthradæ. <hi rend="italic">Tmarthra.</hi></p><p>Fam. 8. Asplancunadj;. <hi rend="italic">Asplanchna.</hi></p><p>Grade B. Loricata.</p><p>Fam. 9. Brachionidæ. <hi rend="italic">Brachiouus, Koteus, Auurxa, Sac-cul us.</hi></p><p>Fam. 10. Pterodinλd.e. <hi rend="italic">Pterodina, Pompholyx.</hi></p><p>Fam. 11. Ecchlanidæ. <hi rend="italic">Euehlanis, Salpina, Diplax, Mono-</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">stylα, ColUmis, Monura, Metopodia, Stephanops, Monoeerca,</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Mastigocerea, Dinoeharis.</hi></p><p>Order IV.—Scirtopoda.</p><p>Forms which swim with their ciliary wreath, and skip by means of hollow limbs with internal locomotor muscles.</p><p>Fam. 12. Pedalionidæ. <hi rend="italic">Peilalion.</hi></p><p>The above list includes only the principal genera. There are,</p><p>however, a number of forms which could not be placed in any of the above families.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Aberrant Forms.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Troehosphxra Xquatorinlis</hi>  (fig. 6, g), found by Semper in the Philippine Islands, closely resembles a Uionotrochal polychætous</p><p>Fiο. 6.—Vnvions aberrant forms. A, <hi rend="italic">Jialatro ealrus</hi>  (after Claparbde) : <hi rend="italic">a.</hi>  mastax. B. <hi rend="italic">Seiton nebalix</hi>  (after Claus) : <hi rend="italic">in.</hi>  mouth ; <hi rend="italic">vd,</hi>  position of the aperture of the vas deferens. C, <hi rend="italic">Lindia toru'osa : a,</hi>  ciliated processes at the sides of the head representiιιjr Cephalotroch : <hi rend="italic">oc,</hi>  eye-spots. D, Ε, and F, <hi rend="italic">ApsiIvs Ientiformis </hi>(after Mecznikow). D, adult female with expanded proboscis : <hi rend="italic">m.</hi>  position of the mouth ; <hi rend="italic">s,</hi>  lateral sense-organs. E, young free-swimming female. F, adult male. G, <hi rend="italic">Troehosphiera Xguatorialis</hi>  (after Semper) : m, mouth; <hi rend="italic">g,</hi>  ganglion ; <hi rend="italic">a,</hi>  anus ; <hi rend="italic">b,</hi>  velum ; <hi rend="italic">oc,</hi>  eye-spot ; <hi rend="italic">c,</hi>  muscles.</p><p>Ian a while PossessingundoubtedlyRotiferal characters. Mecznikow has described a remarkable form, <hi rend="italic">Apsilus Ientifonuis</hi>  (fig. 6, D, E, and F), the adult female of which is entirely devoid of cilia but possesses a sort of retractile hood ; the young female and the males are not thus modified. Claparède discovered fixed to the bodies of small Oligochretes a curious nou-ciliated form, <hi rend="italic">Balatro calvus</hi>  (fig. 6, a), which has a worm-like very contractile body and a well-developed mastax. As mentioned above, the ciliation is reduced to a minimum in the curious worm-like form <hi rend="italic">Liudia</hi>  (fig. 6, c). <hi rend="italic">Seison nebaliæ</hi>  (fig. 6, b), living on the surface of <hi rend="italic">Kebalix,</hi>  which was described originally by Grube, is the same form as the <hi rend="italic">Saccobddla nebaliæ,</hi>  which was supposed by Van Beneden and Hesse to be a leech. It has been shown by Claus to be merely an aberrant Rotifer.</p><p>Of the curious aquatic forms <hi rend="italic">Icthydium, Chxtonotus, Turbanella,</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Dasyditis, Cephalidium, Chxtura,</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">Hemidasys,</hi>  which Mecznikow and Claparède included under the name <hi rend="italic">Gastrotmcha,</hi>  no further account can be given here. They are possibly allied to the <hi rend="italic">Rotifera, </hi>but are devoid of mastax and trochal disk.</p><p>The following are some of the more Important memoirs, Ac., on the <hi rend="italic">Jiotifera</hi></p><p>(1) Leeuwenhoek, <hi rend="italic">Phil. Τranι.,</hi>  1701-1704. (2) Ehrenberg. <hi rend="italic">Die Jnftisionsthierchen alt vollkommene Organismen.</hi>  1838. (3) M. F. Dujardin, <hi rend="italic">JJist. Jfai. des Zoophytes : Jn/titoires,</hi>  1841. (4) W, C. Williamson, “On <hi rend="italic">Melicerta ringens,” Quart. Jour. Μ&gt;er. Sei.,</hi>  1853. (5) Ph. H. Gosse, “On <hi rend="italic">Melicerta ringens," Quart. Jour. Mier. &gt;Sei.,</hi>  1853. (6) T. H. Huxley, “On <hi rend="italic">Laeinutaria socialisé’ Trans. Mier. Soe.,</hi>  1853. (7) Fr. Leydig, “ Ueber den BauunddieeystematischeStellung dcrRaderthiere" <hi rend="italic">Zeit./, te. Zool.,</hi>  vi., 1854. (8) Ph. H. Gosse, <hi rend="italic">Phil. Trans.,</hi>  1856. (9) F. Cohn, <hi rend="italic">Zeit f. te. Zool,,</hi>  vil., ix., and xii. (10) Ph. H. Gosse, <hi rend="italic">Phil. Trans.,</hi>  1858. (11) Pritchard <hi rend="italic">Jnfusoria,</hi>  1861. (12, 13. 14) C. T. Hudson, "On <hi rend="italic">PedaIionp Quart. Jour. Mier. </hi>∣S&gt;ι., 1872, and <hi rend="italic">Monthly Mtcr. Jour.,</hi>  1871 and 1872. (15) E. Ray Lankcster. <hi rend="sup">it</hi>On <hi rend="italic">Pedalionp Quart. Jour. Mier. Sci.,</hi>  1872. (16) El. Mecznikow, "On <hi rend="italic">Apsilut Ienti-</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">formiιp Zeit. f. te. Zool.,</hi>  1872. (17) C. Semper, “On <hi rend="italic">Troehosphxrap Zeit. f. te. Zool.,</hi>  xxii. 1872. (18) K. Eckstein, “ Die Rotutorien der Umgegend vonGiessen, " <hi rend="italic">Zeit./, ιe. Zool.,</hi>  1883. (19) C. T. Hudson, “ On an Attempt to reclassify Rotifers," <hi rend="italic">Quart. Jour. Mier. Sci.,</hi>  1884.    (A. G. B.)</p><p>ROTROU, <hi rend="smallcaps">Jean de</hi>  (1609-1650), the greatest tragic poet of France before Corneille, was born on August 21, 1609 at Dreux in Normandy, and died of the plague at the same place on the 28th June 1650. His family was of small means but of not inconsiderable station, and seems to have had a kind of hereditary connexion with the magistracy of the town of Dreux. He himself was “ lieutenant particulier et civil, ” a post not easy to translate, but apparently possessing some affinity to a Scotch sheriffship substitute. Rotrou, however, went very early to Paris, and, though three years younger than Corneille, with whom he was intimately acquainted, began play-writing before him. With few exceptions the only events recorded of his life are the successive appearances of his plays and his enrolment in the band of five poets who had the not very honourable or congenial duty of turning Richelieu’s dramatic ideas into shape. Rotrou’s own first piece, <hi rend="italic">HHypocondriaque,,</hi>  appeared when he was only seventeen. His second, <hi rend="italic">La Bague de VOubli,</hi>  an adaptation in part from Lope de Vega, was much better, much more suggestive, and much more characteristic. It is the first of several plays in which Rotrou, following or striking out for himself a way which did not lead to much for the time but which was again entered at the Romantic revival, endeavoured to naturalize in France the romantic comedy which had flourished in Spain and England instead of the classical tragedy of Seneca and the classical comedy of Terence. Corneille, as is known to readers of his early work, had considerable leanings in the same direction, and yielded but slowly and unwillingly to the pressure of critical opinion and the public taste. Rotrou’s brilliant but hasty and unequal work showed throughout marks of a stronger adhesion to the Spanish (it is needless to say that neither writer is likely to have known the English) model. <hi rend="italic">Cleagenor et Doristee, Diane, Les Occasions Perdues, HHeureuse Constance,</hi>  pieces which succeeded each other very rapidly, were all in the Spanish style. Then the author changed his school, and, in 1632, imitated very closely the <hi rend="italic">Mensechrni</hi>  of Plautus and the <hi rend="italic">Hercules Œtæus </hi>of Seneca. A crowd of comedies and tragi-comedies followed, and by the time he was twenty-eight (when documents exist showing the sale of two batches of them to the bookseller Quinet for the sum of 220 livres tournois) Rotrou had written nearly a score of plays. He was married in 1640, and had three children, a son and two daughters (none of vzhom, however, continued the name), and it seems that he went to live at Dreux. Previously, vague and anecdotic tradition describes him as having led rather a wild life in Paris, and especially as having been much addicted to gambling. Among his pieces written before his marriage were a translation of the <hi rend="italic">Amphitryon</hi>  under the title of <hi rend="italic">Les Deux Sosies,</hi>  which was not useless to Molière, <hi rend="italic">Antigone,</hi>  which was not useless to Racine, and <hi rend="italic">Laure Persecutee</hi>  (in the opposite style to these classical pieces), which has much merit. These were followed by others until, in 1646 and 1647, Rotrou produced his three masterpieces, <hi rend="italic">Saint Genest,</hi>  a story of Christian martyrdom containing some amusing by-play, one noble speech, and a good deal of dignified action ; <hi rend="italic">Don Bertrand de Cabrère,</hi>  a comedy of merit ; and <hi rend="italic">Ven-ceslas,</hi>  which is considered in France his masterpiece, and which in a manner kept the stage till our own times. The subject (in which a father, being constrained to choose between his duty as king and his parental affection, pardons his son for a murder he has committed, but immediately abdicates as feeling himself unworthy to reign) was taken from Francisco de Rojas; the execution,</p></body></text></TEI>