<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="chi.28490924-1526168109_Page_0101.jpf" type="entry" xml:id="eb07-20-s02-0086-03" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SELTERS</label>,
or <hi rend="smallcaps">Seltzers,</hi> a village of the principality of Nassau, in Germany, about ten miles from Coblentz. The name of the mineral spring here is celebrated in every part of Europe. Seltzer water is brought to this country in stone bottles, which are closely corked and sealed, and contain about three pints each ; and when they are well secured, it keeps unchanged for a considerable time. Seltzer water, according to the analysis of Bergman, contains, in an English wine pint,</p><p>Grains.</p><p>Carbonate of lime 3</p><p>Ditto of magnesia 5</p><p>Ditto of soda 4</p><p>Muriate of soda 17∙5</p><p>29∙5</p><p>The same quantity of water also yields seventeen cubic inches of a gaseous substance, which is found to be almost entirely pure carbonic acid gas. This water has been long in high repute on account of its medicinal virtues, and we have no doubt that it may be used with considerable benefit in many of those complaints which arise from a deranged state of the stomach and bowels. The usual dose of this water is from half a pint to a pint ; but in most cases it may be drunk freely. From its agreeable taste, and its exhilarating effects on the spirits, it is extensively employed at table as a common drink in Germany and Holland. In this country also both the real and the artificial Seltzer water is largely used for the same purpose. Seltzer water may be artificially imitated, by adding the ingredients discoverable by analysis, and in the same proportion.</p></div></body></text></TEI>