<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>But in the Middle Ages this was removed and replaced by the turrets which remain still. Contemporaneously with the arch was built the beautiful bridge over the Marecchia, the only other ancient monument to be found in Rimini, since of the amphitheatre scarcely a stone is left.</p><p>During the AIiddle Ages the history of Rimini has no importance. Alternately captured by Byzantines and Goths, it was rigorously besieged by the latter in 538 A.D. They were, however, compelled to retreat before the reinforcements sent by Belisarius and Narses ; thus the Byzantines, after various vicissitudes, became masters of the town, appointed a duke as its governor, and included it in the exarchate of Ravenna. It afterwards fell into the power of the Longobards, and then of the Franks, who yielded it to the pope, for whom it was governed by counts to the end of the lθth century. Soon after this period the imperial power became dominant in Rimini. In 1157 Frederick I. gave it, by imperial patent, the privilege of coining money and the right of self-government ; and in the 13 th century we find Rimini an independent commune waging war on the neighbouring cities. But throughout these times the main feature of its history is its alternate subjection to pope and emperor. And, weak as the sway of either was, it was strong enough to prevent any genuine local prosperity. During the continued struggle between church and empire, the withdrawal of the one was the signal for the other to advance, and these speedy mutations gave the commune no chance of achieving independence. This state of things went on until the rise of the despots, who, for similar reasons, were powerless to establish themselves on a firm and independent footing. Such indeed was the fate of nearly every city of Romagna excepting Bologna.</p><p>In the year 1216 Rimini, being worsted by Cesena, adopted the desperate plan of granting citizenship to two members of the powerful Malatesta tribe, Giovanni and Malatesta, for the sake of their aid and that of their vassals in the defence of the state and the conduct of the war. This family quickly struck root in the town and gave birth to future tyrants; for in 1237 Giovanni was named podestà, and this office was the first step towards the sovereign power afterwards assumed by his descendants. Meanwhile Rimini was torn by the feuds of Guelf and Ghibelline. The latter were the dominant party in the days of Frederick IL, although very unpopular on account of the grievous taxes imposed by the empire. Accordingly the majority of the urban nobles joined the Guelfs and were driven into exile. But before long, as the Swabian power declined in Italy, the Guelf party was again predominant.</p><p>Then followed a long period of confusion in which, by means of conspiracies and crimes of every kind, the Malatesta succeeded in becoming masters and tyrants of Rimini. And, albeit this string of events is of no historic value, it may serve nevertheless to give an idea of what was occurring throughout Romagna at that time. Giovanni Malatesta had died in 1247 and been succeeded by his son Malatesta, born in 1212, and surnamed Malatesta da Verrucchio. This chieftain, who lived to be a hundred years old, had ample time to mature his ambitious designs, and was the real founder of his house. Seizing the first suitable moment, he placed himself at the head of the exiled Guelfs and restored them to Rimini. Then, as the empire acquired fresh strength in Italy, he quietly bided his time and, on the descent of the Angevins, again assumed the leadership of the Guelfs, who now had the upper hand for a long time. Being repeatedly elected podestà for lengthy terms of office, he at last became the virtual master of Rimini. Nor was he checked by Rome. Pope Boniface VΠL was fully aware of the rights and traditional pretensions of the Holy See, but preferred to keep on good terms with one who had so largely contributed to the triumph of the Guelfs in Romagna. Accordingly he not only left Malatesta unmolested, but in 1299 conferred on him fresh honours and estates, so that his power went on increasing to the day of his death in 1312.</p><p>Four sons had been born to Malatesta—Malatestino, Giovanni the Lame, Paolo the Handsome, and Pandolfo ; but only the oldest and youngest survived him. Giovanni the Lame <hi rend="italic">^Sciancato),</hi>  a man of a daring impetuosity only equalled by his ugliness, had proved so useful a general to Giovanni da Polenta of Ravenna as to win in reward the hand of that potentate’s beautiful daughter, known to history as Francesca da Rimini. But her heart had been won by the handsome Paolo, her brother-in-law ; and the two lovers, being surprised by Giovanni, were murdered by him on the spot (1285). This episode of the story of the Malatesta has been immortalized in Dante’s <hi rend="italic">Inferno. </hi>Giovanni died in 1304. Thus in 1312 Malatestino became lord of Rimini, and on his decease in 1317 bequeathed the power to his brother Pandolfo. Even in his father’s lifetime the new lord had helped to extend the dominions of his house in Pesaro, Fano, Sinigaglia, and Fossombrone. He quickly perceived that, however willing Boniface VIII. might have been to tolerate the increased power of a chief who, like Malatesta da Verrucchio, had rendered such excellent service to the Holy See, it could not be expected that the papacy would really sanction the establishment of a strong and independent state in Romagna. He accordingly turned to the empire, and, siding with Louis the Bavarian, won that monarch’s favour for himself and his sons, who in 1342 were appointed imperial vicars.</p><p>Pandolfo died in 1326, leaving two heirs, Malatesta and Galeotto. The former was nicknamed Guastafamiglia, because, although at first willing to let his brother share his power, he rid himself by violence and treachery of other kinsmen who claimed their just rights to a portion of the state. His intent was to become sole lord and to aggrandize his tiny principality. But the reigning pope Innocent VI. despatched the terrible Cardinal Albornoz to Romagna and it was speedily reduced by fire and sword. In 1355 the Malatesta shared the fate of the other potentates of the land. Nevertheless it was the cardinal’s policy to let existing Governments stand, provided they promised to act in subordination to the papal see. Thus, he granted the Malatesta brothers the investiture of Rimini, Pesaro, Fano, and Fossombrone, and they arranged a division of the state. Guastafamiglia took Pesaro, which was held by his descendants down to the brothers Carlo and Galeazzo. The former of these, who died in 1439, was father to the Parisina beheaded in Ferrara, whose tragic love story has been sung by Byron. The latter won the title of “ ΓInetto ” (the Incapable) by the foolish sale of his rights over Pesaro to the Sforza in 1447.</p><p>Galeotto, on the other hand, retained the lordship of Rimini, ruling tranquilly and on good terms with the popes, who allowed him to add Cervia, Cesena, and Bertinoro to his states. Dying in 1385 at the age of eighty, he left two sons—Carlo, who became lord of Rimini, and Pandolfo, who had Fano for his share. Carlo (1364-1429) was energetic, valiant, and a friend of the popes, who named him vicar of the church in Romagna. He was a patron of letters and the arts, and during his reign his court began to be renowned for its splendour. As he left no issue, his inheritance was added to that of his brother Pandolfo, and Fano was once more united to Rimini. Pandolfo (1370-1427) had led the life of a</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>