<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p><hi rend="italic">confiovσnt</hi>  (comp, <hi rend="italic">fioviom ; fiuvidus,</hi>  Lucretius), <hi rend="italic">sοvo, suvo,</hi>  suo, <hi rend="italic">iηgeηuvae, elovacas.</hi>  Comp. Umb. tover and <hi rend="italic">tuer,</hi>  tui; Osc. <hi rend="italic">suvad,</hi>  &amp;c. It reappears in Petronius, urceatim <hi rend="italic">plovebat,</hi>  and in Ital. <hi rend="italic">ρibvere, rovιna, védova, Gènova, Mantova, chiavica,</hi>  Span. <hi rend="italic">llovér,</hi>  Fr. <hi rend="italic">pleuvoir.</hi></p><p>9.    In <hi rend="italic">qu</hi>  the <hi rend="italic">u</hi>  after <hi rend="italic">q</hi>  was only a lip glide, defined by the grammarians as “neither vowel nor consonant,” as it did not count in the metre. It was therefore easily dropped altogether, as in <hi rend="italic">Cinti</hi>  for Quincti in an old inscription. This was especially peculiar to Etruscan Latin, as in the very old <hi rend="italic">Aeeetiai</hi>  Aequitiae, <hi rend="italic">Tarena,</hi>  Etrus. <hi rend="italic">Tarχnas,</hi>  Tarquinius. Instances occur later everywhere, as <hi rend="italic">eoeus</hi>  for <hi rend="italic">eoqwus, eottidie</hi>  (Lex Julia), &amp;c. ; L. Lat. <hi rend="italic">cinque, einquaginta</hi>  (Edict. Diocl., 301); Ital. <hi rend="italic">chi</hi>  qui, <hi rend="italic">ehe</hi>  quid, <hi rend="italic">eubcere </hi>coquere, <hi rend="italic">eueina =</hi>  vulg. Lat. coquina ( = culina), <hi rend="italic">cinque,</hi>  &amp;c. But generally Italian retains <hi rend="italic">qu</hi>  with the old sound, <hi rend="italic">quinto, quanto, </hi>Span, <hi rend="italic">euaηto,</hi>  but <hi rend="italic">que, quinto {-k),</hi>  Fr. <hi rend="italic">qu = k.</hi></p><p>10.    The Old Romans, having no aspirates in their own speech,</p><p>, could not pronounce the Greek <hi rend="italic">φ, χ, θ,</hi>  but generally turned them</p><p>into <hi rend="italic">ρ, e, t,</hi>  as <hi rend="italic">Rilippus Φίλιπποί, Prune Φρύνη, cοlapus, Bacanal. </hi>In some words the old popular pronunciation continued later, as class, <hi rend="italic">ampulla, purpura ; </hi>Silver Age, <hi rend="italic">percolopabant</hi>  (Petron.) ; Mediæval, <hi rend="italic">colopus, eolpus,</hi>  I tai. <hi rend="italic">colριo,</hi>  Fr. <hi rend="italic">coup ; sρ&gt;aera,</hi>  Old I tai. <hi rend="italic">spera</hi>  (Dante), Early Eng. <hi rend="italic">spere</hi>  (Chaucer), vulg. Eng. <hi rend="italic">spear, </hi>“sphere”; <hi rend="italic">Josepus,</hi>  Ital. <hi rend="italic">Giuseppe ; Step&lt;vnus,</hi>  Span. <hi rend="italic">Estéban,</hi>  Slav. <hi rend="italic">Stepan.</hi></p><p>11.    Greek initial <hi rend="italic">π</hi>  was often rendered <hi rend="italic">b,</hi>  as <hi rend="italic">Βurrus Xlvphbi,</hi>  also adj., <hi rend="italic">“burrum</hi>  antiqui quod nunc dicimus rufum” (Fest.) ; hence, through <hi rend="italic">burtfi)eus,</hi>  Ital. <hi rend="italic">bujo,</hi>  “dark”; likewise <hi rend="italic">burns πυξ6s,</hi>  Ital. <hi rend="italic">busso, bosso,</hi>  Fr. <hi rend="italic">buis,</hi>  “box tree”; from <hi rend="italic">πυξis,</hi>  class, <hi rend="italic">pyxis,</hi>  popular and L. Lat. <hi rend="italic">buxis, buxida,</hi>  Fr. <hi rend="italic">boîte.</hi></p><p>12.    <hi rend="italic">F</hi>  after vowels is rare in Latin, but frequent in Umbro-Oscan, as Umb. <hi rend="italic">prufie</hi>  probe, Osc. <hi rend="italic">ampmιfid</hi>  improbe, <hi rend="italic">Safinim</hi>  Samnium (*Sabinium), corresponding in cognate words to Greek aspirates where Latin commonly had <hi rend="italic">b</hi>  : Lat. <hi rend="italic">vafier,</hi>  “sly,” orig. “varius”; comp, <hi rend="italic">vabmt,m</hi>  “varium” (Gloss. Isid.), Umb. vufru. The relation between Lat. <hi rend="italic">rufus,</hi>  Umb. rofu and Lat. <hi rend="italic">ruber</hi>  is very like that between <hi rend="italic">nasus</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">ηrnres,</hi>  or that between <hi rend="italic">veho</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">lingo, ligurio</hi>  as representing Gr. <hi rend="italic">χ.</hi>  We may suppose that /is the older and stronger common Italic form, sometimes retained in old popular Latin speech, partly by provincial influence. We find <hi rend="italic">sifilare</hi>  for <hi rend="italic">sibilare</hi>  mentioned as archaic by Nonius, as vulgar in the appendix to Probus, Ital. <hi rend="italic">zufiolare,</hi>  Fr. <hi rend="italic">siffler. F</hi>  is preserved in many provincial names, as <hi rend="italic">Safinius</hi>  (Petron. ) and <hi rend="italic">Tifernum,</hi>  Ital. <hi rend="italic">Tifierno. </hi>We find this /again in the Italian <hi rend="italic">tafiano</hi>  tabanus, <hi rend="italic">bûfolo</hi>  bubalus, Eng. buffalo. The Neapolitan <hi rend="italic">attmιfie, “</hi>  October,” has a very Oscan appearance.</p><p>13.    Old Latin often prefers short <hi rend="italic">e,</hi>  especially original and unaccented, to <hi rend="italic">i,</hi>  as in <hi rend="italic">dedxt, fiuxt</hi>  (T. Scip.), <hi rend="italic">eepet, refecet</hi>  (Col. Rostr. ), <hi rend="italic">velet</hi>  (Bacch.), <hi rend="italic">Crnuietios</hi>  (inscr.), <hi rend="italic">acetare = agetare</hi>  (Fest.), <hi rend="italic">dubenτιs </hi>dominus (Fest. ), <hi rend="italic">componeto</hi>  (Cato), <hi rend="italic">gcnetmx, mereto, ealecare</hi>  (inscr. ), <hi rend="italic">fiamelia, magester</hi>  (Quint. ). It stands for radical i, mostly orig. <hi rend="italic">e, </hi>as in <hi rend="italic">en, endo-Cχ. </hi><hi rend="italic">lv, </hi><hi rend="italic">semul</hi>  (Plaut.)—comp. Ital. insieme, Fr. ensemble; <hi rend="italic">Menerva</hi>  (inscr., and mentioned by Quintilian). Sometimes it stands even for original <hi rend="italic">i,</hi>  as <hi rend="italic">tempestatebus, aidiles</hi>  (T. Scip. ), <hi rend="italic">nαvebos, ηavaled,</hi>  but <hi rend="italic">marid</hi>  (Col. Rostr.), <hi rend="italic">sei ques,</hi>  si quis (Bacch.). This is quite Umbrian; comp, kanetu canito, urfetam orbitam, fratreks “fratricus,” ∕αfβ∕eZe = L. Lat. <hi rend="italic">fiaxibilis,</hi>  Old Fr. <hi rend="italic">fesible </hi>feasible, famedias familiae (nom. plur.), kvêstretie quaestura, formed like Lat. <hi rend="italic">segnities.</hi>  In North Latin we find Etrus. Lat. <hi rend="italic">Aeeetiai</hi>  Aequitiae ; Umb. Lat. <hi rend="italic">Publeee, menesterium,</hi>  (T. Pis.) <hi rend="italic">Apoleηei, dede, Komefiia)</hi>  ; Mars, <hi rend="italic">dedet, mereto</hi>  ; and rustic “rustici etiam nunc quoque viam <hi rend="italic">veham</hi>  appellant ” (Varro). <hi rend="italic">E,</hi>  being more subject to be obscured than <hi rend="italic">i,</hi>  is not unfrequently dropped, as in <hi rend="italic">eante</hi>  for <hi rend="italic">*eanete,</hi>  class, <hi rend="italic">αrnιte</hi>  (Carm. Sali.), <hi rend="italic">Nurntoriai</hi>  (inscr. c. 290 B.c.), <hi rend="italic">oinvorsei</hi>  (Bacch.), <hi rend="italic">unversum</hi>  (Lucretius), <hi rend="italic">caldus</hi>  (Cato), <hi rend="italic">ardus, frigdaria</hi>  (Lucilius) ; always <hi rend="italic">fieri, fierte=φιρeτe.</hi>  Popular Latin here approached the North dialect, where such syncopes were constant : comp. Umb. <hi rend="italic">ηοrnnc</hi>  nomine, <hi rend="italic">termnu</hi>  termino, <hi rend="italic">postro </hi>postero ; they were still more violent in Etruscan, as <hi rend="italic">Elχsentre </hi>Alexander, <hi rend="italic">Sehtmnal</hi>  Septimienâ nata, <hi rend="italic">Tarχnas</hi>  Tarquinius ; Pis. Lat. efe&lt;⅛o(Q dederunt, <hi rend="italic">Lebro</hi>  Liberum ; Umb. Lat. <hi rend="italic">eedre</hi>  cedere, &amp;c. South Latin, on the contrary, favoured <hi rend="italic">i</hi>  (see below).</p><p>14.    Of long <hi rend="italic">i</hi>  Lucilius distinguishes two kinds—close (i tenue), as in <hi rend="italic">pila, “</hi>  mortar,” and open (i ρingue), approaching to <hi rend="italic">e,</hi>  written <hi rend="italic">ei, </hi>as in <hi rend="italic">peilum,</hi>  “ spear,” <hi rend="italic">media,</hi>  “thousands ” ; he might have added <hi rend="italic">fieilius,</hi>  “son,” comp, <hi rend="italic">fielare, 6ηλτf∣.</hi>  There was an original diphthong <hi rend="italic">eι,</hi>  as in <hi rend="italic">deicere,</hi>  Osc. <hi rend="italic">deicum,</hi>  Gr. <hi rend="italic">5eικvbvαn,</hi>  which was early contracted into this middle sound, exactly like Eng. <hi rend="italic">ey</hi>  in <hi rend="italic">money </hi>from Old Fr. <hi rend="italic">rnaneix.</hi>  This too is quite Umbrian, spelt <hi rend="italic">ei</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">ee, e,</hi>  as enetu inito, Arch. Lat. eneito, feliuf filios, <hi rend="italic">screihtor, screhto </hi>scripti, <hi rend="italic">ρreve</hi>  privus, <hi rend="italic">Ioveine= Ij ovine,</hi>  Iguvini; comp, the datives</p><p><hi rend="italic">Juve paire, mchs, tefie</hi>  (tibi), Ose. <hi rend="italic">Diuve*, ρatere*</hi>  ; also Umb. Lat. ∕eZ = filius, and Pis. <hi rend="italic">Lebro.</hi>  In North Latin datives in <hi rend="italic">e</hi>  are generally constant <hi rend="italic">(Apolenei,</hi>  Pis., uncontracted), as <hi rend="italic">Junone matre, Jove, ρatre, Marte,</hi>  &amp;c., extending sometimes even farther south ; and Gallo-Lat. <hi rend="italic">nise</hi>  (Lex Rubr. de Gall. Cisalp.). Livy used <hi rend="italic">sibe</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">quase</hi>  (originally -ei). This exactly agrees with the rustic pronunciation <hi rend="italic">νella, speca</hi>  recorded by Varro, <hi rend="italic">leber</hi>  by Festus—“ab antiquis et <hi rend="italic">ameci</hi>  et <hi rend="italic">amecae</hi>  per e litteram efferebantur” (Fest.). And this again surprisingly agrees with the Modern Emilian (Romagnuolo) pronunciation, as Bolognese <hi rend="italic">mega</hi>  mica, <hi rend="italic">dég</hi>  dico, <hi rend="italic">méll</hi>  mille, plur. τneZα=Ital. mila, <hi rend="italic">véta</hi>  vita, <hi rend="italic">maré</hi>  marito, <hi rend="italic">prém </hi>primo. Thus this old rustic sound seems to have extended northwards, but later to have been driven from its old home by the classic close <hi rend="italic">i,</hi>  which penetrated everywhere else, and is generally represented in all the Romance languages.</p><p>15.    Old Latin often prefers short <hi rend="italic">o,</hi>  especially original and un</p><p>accented, to <hi rend="italic">u,</hi>  as in <hi rend="italic">consol</hi>  (T. Scip.), <hi rend="italic">tabola</hi>  (Bacch.), <hi rend="italic">pocolom </hi>(many old inscr.), <hi rend="italic">popolum</hi>  (Tab. Bantina), <hi rend="italic">cpistola = </hi><hi rend="italic">iπισrολn, </hi><hi rend="italic">Patricoles, Hereοles, eolpa</hi>  (Prise. ), <hi rend="italic">Voleanom</hi>  (inscr. 3d century b.c.), <hi rend="italic">volgo</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">volt, &amp;c,c.</hi>  (Plaut. ; <hi rend="italic">o</hi>  after <hi rend="italic">v</hi>  continued in the classical age), <hi rend="italic">sont</hi>  sunt, <hi rend="italic">eosentiont</hi>  (T. Scip.), <hi rend="italic">deηοηtiari</hi>  (Tab. Bant.); in terminations— <hi rend="italic">Venos, ορos, robose, filios,</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">Luciom,</hi>  &amp;c. (T. Scip.); in Umb acc. <hi rend="italic">ρoplo, salvo, tertio</hi>  ; even for orig. <hi rend="italic">u—aseriato eest,</hi>  observa-tum ibit ; radical—mo‰multa, “ fine,” <hi rend="italic">onse</hi>  (h)umero, I tai. <hi rend="italic">0mero, </hi>Span, <hi rend="italic">ombro, somo</hi>  summo (orig. sup-mo), Ital. <hi rend="italic">s6mmο</hi>  ; in North Latin <hi rend="italic">moltaticod</hi>  (T. Piceu. ) ; in Fal. <hi rend="italic">maxomo, zenatuo</hi>  ; and in Ligurian Latin <hi rend="italic">fioviom, infiumo, suso</hi>  (bronze tablet near Genoa, 117 b.c.).    <hi rend="italic">0</hi>  reappears in Late Latin and Italian <hi rend="italic">m6lto, d6lee,</hi>  &amp;c.</p><p>Medial <hi rend="italic">o</hi>  is often dropped before <hi rend="italic">l,</hi>  as in <hi rend="italic">οrnmpoplo</hi>  (Plaut. Pseud.), <hi rend="italic">teglarius</hi>  (inscr.), <hi rend="italic">Fostlus</hi>  (Faustulus, 114 b.c. ), <hi rend="italic">Herele</hi>  (Plaut. ), <hi rend="italic">singlariter</hi>  (Lucr. )—comp. Fr. <hi rend="italic">sanglier,</hi>  I tai. <hi rend="italic">einghiale—eoplata </hi>(Lucr.) ; in some cases, as <hi rend="italic">poclum, periclum,</hi>  the contraction does not appear till the empire ; at Pompeii <hi rend="italic">aηglata, subla,</hi>  &amp;c. As Umbrian always has contraction, <hi rend="italic">pihaelom, anglom, Treblaηir, vitlu, katlu, stiplo,</hi>  whilst Oscan distinguishes diminutive forms like <hi rend="italic">zicolom, zicelei, ziculud</hi>  from such forms as <hi rend="italic">sakaraklom, pestlerm, </hi>the strongest impulse must have come from the north, although there must have been a pretty general tendency to syncope everywhere. In Italian contraction is the rule in popular words, as <hi rend="italic">veechio</hi>  for <hi rend="italic">vet'lus,</hi>  Late <hi rend="italic">veelus, ocehio</hi>  oc’lus, &amp;c. In <hi rend="italic">pbpolo, tdvola, isola,</hi>  &amp;c., and diminutives like <hi rend="italic">rivolo</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">g6ndola,</hi>  the original vowel has remained throughout. South Latin favoured <hi rend="italic">u</hi>  (see below).</p><p>16.    The use of <hi rend="italic">o</hi>  for <hi rend="italic">e</hi>  after <hi rend="italic">v</hi>  is shown by Old Lat. <hi rend="italic">oinvorsei, vortere;</hi>  in <hi rend="italic">vostrum</hi>  (Plaut., Ambrosian palimpsest), the original sound (from <hi rend="italic">vos)</hi>  occurs, which must have been universal in popular speech, since it reappears in Late Latin and all the Romance languages—Ital. <hi rend="italic">vostro,</hi>  Fr. <hi rend="italic">votre,</hi>  &amp;c. There was a tradition that Scipio Africanus had been the first to spell these words with <hi rend="italic">e</hi>  (Quint.,</p><p>i. 7, 25). Here Umbrian distinguished between <hi rend="italic">e</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">o,</hi>  as in <hi rend="italic">vestra, eoιxrtu</hi>  (pres.), but <hi rend="italic">covortzιs</hi>  (perf.); Lat. <hi rend="italic">vorsare</hi>  is perhaps Span. <hi rend="italic">vosar, bosar,</hi>  “to vomit”; in other words <hi rend="italic">e</hi>  is now universal.</p><p>17.    <hi rend="italic">U</hi>  occurred for <hi rend="italic">i</hi>  before labials ; but the old <hi rend="italic">optumo</hi>  has scarcely left any trace, yet Ital. has <hi rend="italic">menοmo</hi>  besides <hi rend="italic">minimo. </hi>Later <hi rend="italic">u</hi>  was pronounced with the sound of <hi rend="italic">ii,</hi>  Gr. <hi rend="italic">υ,</hi>  Fr. <hi rend="italic">u,,</hi>  which at last was turned into <hi rend="italic">i,</hi>  as in <hi rend="italic">optimus,</hi>  Ital. <hi rend="italic">ottimx.</hi>  But in some few words the old popular form has survived—<hi rend="italic">stupula,</hi>  Ital. <hi rend="italic">st6ppia, </hi>Fr. <hi rend="italic">étouble,</hi>  “stubble,” <hi rend="italic">dissupare,</hi>  Ital. <hi rend="italic">sciupare.</hi></p><p>18.    <hi rend="italic">U</hi>  stands for <hi rend="italic">o—“ Frundes, fiuntes</hi>  vetustissimi ; quae tarnen a primoribus repudiata sunt, quasi rustico more dicta” (Prise.)— contrary to the general rule (see 15). Spellings like <hi rend="italic">muns, muntem, fiuntem</hi>  abound in Late Latin, as <hi rend="italic">puntifiex</hi>  (already in 98 a.d.), <hi rend="italic">∑eπτοpουvτιιρ</hi>  (Plut., <hi rend="italic">e.</hi>  100) ; whence Old Fr. and Old Eng. <hi rend="italic">muηt, </hi>“mount,” Ital. <hi rend="italic">m6nte, p6nte, fi6nte</hi>  with close <hi rend="italic">o.</hi>  In Sienese we have even <hi rend="italic">pognxre, poηto,</hi>  Ital. and Florentine <hi rend="italic">pugnere, punto </hi>(pungere, pùnctum) ; the connexion, however, of <hi rend="italic">ό</hi>  with Old Latm <hi rend="italic">u</hi>  is doubtful.</p><p>19.    Greek u was pronounced <hi rend="italic">u,</hi>  as in <hi rend="italic">Bruges Φρbyes, Rurrus, purpmra, gubernum, gιdernare, (nιpressus,—</hi>the last four also classical ; otherwise the classical age adopted the Greek sound <hi rend="italic">y,</hi>  as in <hi rend="italic">Cyprus.</hi>  In popular Latin the old sound remained, and <hi rend="italic">u</hi>  was sometimes (before <hi rend="italic">r,</hi>  as in <hi rend="italic">fiore)</hi>  even changed into <hi rend="italic">o,</hi>  as in <hi rend="italic">storαx </hi>(Ter.), <hi rend="italic">aneora</hi>  (Nævius). In Low Latin n is frequent: <hi rend="italic">cuprum, </hi>“copper,” for which Pliny used <hi rend="italic">Cyρriurn</hi>  (αes) ; comp, <hi rend="italic">bursa,</hi>  Ital. bôrsa, Fr. bourse, <hi rend="italic">crupta,</hi>  Ital. grotta, <hi rend="italic">tumba,</hi>  Ital. tomba, &amp;c.</p><p>In popular Latin there was a general tendency to contract the old diphthongs, in accordance with Umbrian and North Latin.</p><p>20.    <hi rend="italic">Au</hi>  in North Latin began very early to be contracted into long openo, as <hi rend="italic">Rola</hi>  (inscr. Picen., 218 B.c.). In Umbrian this is a constant law—<hi rend="italic">ote</hi>  aut, Ital. <hi rend="italic">b,</hi>  Umb. Zorιt tauros, Ital. <hi rend="italic">tbro,</hi>  &amp;c. The only form of the oldest Roman Latin was <hi rend="italic">au,</hi>  as <hi rend="italic">Taurasia, CP)aulla</hi>  (T. Scip.), <hi rend="italic">Claudi</hi>  (Bacch.). When the Umbrian poet whose provincial name was Plot(u)s settled in Rome in the latter half of the 3d century B.c. his name was Latinized into Plautus. Meanwhile the North Latin ô began to penetrate into Latium as rustic, vulgar, and familiar; Cato and Varro often use it in their books <hi rend="italic">De Re Rustieα,</hi>  as <hi rend="italic">coles</hi>  (Cato), <hi rend="italic">colis, orata</hi>  (Varro) : “ <hi rend="italic">Orata </hi>genus piscis appellatur a colore auri, quod rustici <hi rend="italic">orum</hi>  dicebant, ut auriculas, <hi rend="italic">amendas”</hi>  (Fest.). But in the classical age there was a good deal of reaction against this vulgarism, and there is a well-known anecdote of Mestrius Floras warning the emperor Vespasian against saying <hi rend="italic">plostra,</hi>  and being next day facetiously greeted by the emperor as <hi rend="italic">Flaurus</hi>  (Suet., <hi rend="italic">Vesρ.,</hi>  22). At Pompeii</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>