<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>to see” ; and Ritter recognizes the “union of the acutest observation of topographical and local conditions with much preparatory study.” He was gifted with great practical sense and unusual accuracy of observation ; but hewas extreme in his criticism of the local legends of the Holy Land, and not sufficiently skilled in historic criticism. Although great progress has been made in Biblical geography in the last quarter of this century, yet the work of Robinson is still classical.</p><p>See <hi rend="italic">The Life, Writings, and Character of Edward Robinson,</hi>  by Henry B. Smith and Boswell D. Hitchcock (New York, 1863), and <hi rend="italic">Services in Adam Chapel at the Dedication of the New Buildings of Union Theological Seminary </hi>(New York, 1885).</p><p>ROBINSON, John (1575-1625), one of the founders of Independency in England (see vol. xii. p. 725), was born most probably near Scrooby in Nottinghamshire in 1575. He was entered of Corpus Christi College, Cambridge, in 1592, and graduated in ordinary course, becoming a fellow in 1599. Having taken orders he officiated for some time in the neighbourhood of Norwich, but his Puritan leanings soon caused his suspension by the bishop. After having ministered for some time to a congregation of sympathizers in Norwich he resigned his fellowship in 1604, and, proceeding to Gainsborough in Lincolnshire, he there joined a company who had bound themselves by covenant before God “to walk in all His ways made known or to be made known unto them, according to their best endeavours, whatever it should cost them.” In 1606 he became minister at Scrooby, but the increasing hostility of the authorities towards nonconformity soon forced him and his people to think of flight, and, not without difficulty, they succeeded in making their escape in detachments to Hol-land. Robinson settled in Amsterdam in 1608, but in the following year removed to Leyden, and ministered there to members of his former congregation. In 1620 a considerable minority of these sailed for England in the “ Speed-well,” and ultimately crossed the Atlantic in the “ Mayflower ” ; it was Robinson’s intention to follow as soon as practicable along with the rest of his flock, but he died before the plan could be carried out, on 1st March 1625.</p><p>Besides preaching to his congregation, and, during his later years, corresponding with those of his people who had settled in New England, Robinson devoted himself to theological study, and became a member of the university of Leyden. Amongst his other publications may be mentioned <hi rend="italic">Justification of Separation from the Church</hi>  (1610), <hi rend="italic">Apologia Brownistarum</hi>  (1619), <hi rend="italic">A Defence of the Doctrine propounded by the Synod of Dort</hi>  (1624), and a volume of <hi rend="italic">Essays, or Observations Divine and Moral,</hi>  printed in 1628. His <hi rend="italic">Works,</hi>  with a memoir by R. Ashton, were reprinted in 3 vols, in 1851.</p><p>ROBINSON, John Thomas Romney (1792-1882), the inventor of the cup-anemometer, was born in Dublin on 23d April 1792. He studied at Trinity College and obtained a fellowship in 1814 ; for some years he was deputy professor of natural philosophy, until he relinquished his fellowship in 1821 on obtaining the college living of Enniskillen. In 1823 he was appointed astronomer of the Armagh observatory (see Observatory), with which he (from 1824) combined the living of Carrickmacross, but he always resided at the observatory, engaged in re-searches connected with astronomy and physics, until his death on 28th February 1882.</p><p>Robinson wrote a number of papers in scientific journals and transactions, and the Armagh catalogue of stars (<hi rend="italic">Places of 5345 Stars observed from 1828 to 1854 at the Armagh Observatory,</hi>  Dublin, 1859), but he is best known as the inventor of the cup-anemometer for registering the velocity of the wind. This instrument (which he erected at the Armagh observatory in 1846 and which has since come into general use) consists of four light arms forming a horizontal cross, carrying four hemispherical cups and turning freely about a vertical axis. By an endless screw attached to the axis a system of wheelwork is set going, and the velocity of the wind is indicated by one or more dials, or it may be registered continuously by a pencil drawn by clockwork along a dial or drum turned by the anemometer, or (as in the modification now generally used) by a metallic screw of only one thread, which leaves a tracing on a sheet of metallic paper folded round a drum revolving by clockwork. It has been found by elaborate experiments by Dr Robinson ( <hi rend="italic">Trans. R. Irish Academy,</hi>  vol. xxii. ; <hi rend="italic">Phil. Trans.,</hi>  1878 and 1880) and others that the centre of each cup moves with a velocity very nearly equal to one-third of that of the wind.</p><p>ROB ROY <hi rend="italic">(c.</hi>  1660-1734), the popular designation of a famous Highland outlaw whose prowess is the theme of one of Sir Walter Scott’s novels, was by descent a Macgregor, being the younger son of Donald Macgregor of Glengyle, who had attained the rank of lieutenant-colonel in the army of James II., by his wife, a daughter of William Campbell of Glenfalloch. He received the name Roy from the red hair which clustered in thick curls over his brow, and latterly adopted Campbell as his surname on account of the Acts proscribing the name of his clan. Though in stature not much above the middle height, he was so muscular and thickly set that few were his equals in feats of strength, while the unusual length of his arms gave him an extraordinary advantage in the use of the sword. His eyes were remarkably keen and piercing, and his whole expression indicated a mental prowess forming an appropriate complement to his powerful physical frame. He inherited a small property on the Braes of Balquhidder, and at first devoted himself to the rearing of cattle. Having formed a band of armed clansmen, he obtained, after the accession of William III., a commission from James II. to levy war on all who refused to acknowledge him as king, and in the autumn of 1691 made a descent on Stirlingshire to carry off the cattle of Lord Livingstone, when, being opposed by the villagers of Kippen, he also seized the cattle from all the byres of the village. Shortly afterwards he married Mary, daughter of Macgregor of Comar. On the death of Gregor Macgregor, the chief of the clan, in 1693 he managed, though not the nearest heir, to get himself acknowledged chief, obtaining control of the lands stretching from the Braes of Balquhidder to the shores of Loch Lomond, and situated between the possessions of Argyll and those of Montrose. To assist in carrying on his trade as cattle-dealer he borrowed money from the duke of Montrose, and, being on account of losses unable to repay it, he was in 1712 evicted from his property and declared an outlaw. Taking refuge in the more inaccessible Highlands, Rob Roy from this time forward supported himself chiefly by depredations committed in the most daring manner on the duke and his tenants, all attempts to capture him being unsuccessful. During the rebellion of 1715, though nominally siding with the Pretender, he did not take an active part in the battle of Sheriffmuir except in plundering the dead on both sides. He was included in the Act of Attainder ; but, having for some time enjoyed the friendship of the duke of Arygll, he obtained, on making his submission at Inveraray, a promise of protection. He now established his residence at Craigroyston near Loch Lomond, whence for some time he levied black mail as formerly upon Montrose, escaping by his wonderful address and activity every effort of the English garrison stationed at Inversnaid to bring him to justice. In his later years he was, through the mediation of Argyll, reconciled to Montrose. According to a notice in the <hi rend="italic">Caledonian Mercury</hi>  he died at Balquhidder on 28th December 1734. He was buried in Balquhidder churchyard.</p><p>K. Macleay, <hi rend="italic">Historical Memoirs of Rob Roy</hi>  (1818 ; new ed. 1881 ) ; Sir Walter Scott, <hi rend="italic">Highland Clans</hi>  ; A. H. Miller, <hi rend="italic">Story of Rob Roy </hi>(1883).</p><p>ROBUSTI, Jacopo (1518-1594), commonly called Il Tintoretto or Tintoret, one of the greatest painters of the Venetian or of any school, was born in Venice in 1518, though most accounts say in 1512. His father, Battista Robusti, was a dyer, or “ tintore ” ; hence the son got the nickname of “ Tintoretto,” little dyer, or dyer’s boy. In childhood Jacopo, a born painter, began daubing on the dyer’s walls ; his father, noticing his bent, took him round, still in boyhood, to the studio of Titian,</p><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>