<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p><hi rend="italic">στάσα δpικi∣.</hi>  The distinction between justice and equity (τJ δίκαιον aud τδ <hi rend="italic">ιπιtικls)</hi>  is noticed. Equity is “a kind of justice, but goes beyond the written law,” as in the <hi rend="italic">Ethics</hi>  (v. 10) equity is said to be a corrective of the law, where the latter fails through generality,—i. <hi rend="italic">e.,</hi>  through the lawmaker’s inability to frame a general rule which should precisely fit the circumstances of every particular case. True to his conception of a method, Aristotle next applies “the topic of degree” to injustice,—as, in an earlier chapter <hi rend="italic">(Rhet.,</hi>  i. 7) he had applied it to the idea of “ good. ”</p><p>The analysis of the three branches of rhetoric—deliberative, epideictic, forensic—is now finished. In the closing chapter of his first book, Aristotle briefly considers and dismisses the “ inartificial proofs,”—the means of persuasion, that is, which arise from matters external to the art itself, though the art uses them. These, having regard to the actual circumstances of his time and country, lie declares to be five : (1) laws ; (2) witnesses ; (3) evidence given under torture—<hi rend="italic">β0σavos ; </hi>(4) documents ; (5) oaths, meaning chiefly treaties between states. With regard to (3) it may be remarked that the rhetorical theory of torture in the ancient world was, that a person uuder torture will tell the truth because it is his interest to do so. This is stated, <hi rend="italic">e.g.,</hi>  in the <hi rend="italic">Rhetorica ad Alexandnιm,</hi>  XV. § 1. Among the Attic orators, Isæus gives his emphatic adhesion to this view (Or., viii. § 12). On the other hand, the common-sense view of the matter is very well put by another Attic orator, Antiphon, in his speech <hi rend="italic">De Cæde Herodis </hi>(§§31-33), when he remarks that “in the torturers is the hope of the tortured.” “So long, then,” Antiphon proceeds, “as the slave felt that his prospects in slandering λvere hopeful, he was obstinate in the calumny ; but, when he saw that he was to die, then at last he told the truth, and said that he had been persuaded by the persecutors to slander me.” It would have been interesting if Aristotle had given some indication of his view on this, his third, ⅛τ∈χvos πiστσ ; but he simply accepts it as a fact of his day, and, taking it along with the rest, gives a number of general arguments which may be used on either side, according as the particular Sτ∈χvos τriστts is for us or against us. Here the first book ends.</p><p>At the beginning of the second book, Aristotle returns to the “artificial proofs” (evτ∈χvoi <hi rend="italic">πiσταs)—</hi>those which rhetoric itself provides. Of these, the logical proof has already been in part discussed (i. 2). He therefore turns to the “ ethical ” proof. The speaker’s character may be so indicated by his speech as to prepossess the hearers ; and this result depends chiefly on three things. He should make them feel that he possesses (1) <hi rend="italic">φρόνησα </hi>—intelligence ; (2) <hi rend="italic">ipeτi∣—</hi>virtue ; and (3) eυvotα—good-will to them. Aristotle then proceeds to furnish the speaker with the materials for seeming intelligent and good, referring for these to his previous analysis of the virtues (i. 9). As to the means of seeming friendly, these will be furnished by an analysis of the affections <hi rend="italic">(πάθη).</hi>  Here we are already on the boundary line between the “ethical proof” and the third of the <hi rend="italic">evτeχvοι πiστeα, </hi>the “emotional proof.” In regard to each affection (παθos), we have to see (1) what it is ; (2) what things predispose men to it ; (3) the objects and conditions of its manifestation. The next ten chapters of the second book (2-11) are accordingly devoted to an analysis of those emotions which it is most important for the rhetorician to understand :—viz. (1) anger, and its opposite, mildness ; (2) love and hatred ; (3) fear and boldness ; (4) compassion, envy, emulation ; (5) shame and shamelessness ; (6) gratitude (χαpts) ; (7) righteous indignation (ve<hi rend="sub">i</hi>ueσts). But, in appealing to these various emotions, the speaker must have regard to the general character of his audience, according,<hi rend="italic">e.g.,</hi>  as they are young or old, rich or poor, &amp;c. Hence it is necessary to know the characteristics of the various periods and conditions of life. Aristotle therefore delineates the chief traits of the young, of the old, and of men in their prime ; of the well-born, the rich, and the powerful. With regard to the well-born, he makes a remark which seems equally true of the rich : “ the possessor of good birth is the more ambitious ; for all men, when they have got anything, are wont to add to the heap” (ch. 12-17). The analysis of the “ethical” and the ‘ ‘ emotional ” proof is now finished.</p><p>After a concise retrospect, Aristotle passes to the treatment of a subject barely indicated in the first book (ch. 2). The <hi rend="italic">κοινοί τόποι, </hi>or “universal commonplaces,” applicable to all materials, are mainly four :—(1) <hi rend="italic">τό δυνατόν</hi>  and τό <hi rend="italic">αδύνατον—</hi>possibility and impossibility ; (2) τό <hi rend="italic">yeγοv0i</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">τb μiλλοv—</hi>past and future ;</p><p>(3)    τό <hi rend="italic">αtiξeιv κal μeιουv</hi>  (or <hi rend="italic">μeyeθοs</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">μικροτηs)—</hi>great and small ;</p><p>(4)    τό <hi rend="italic">μάλλον καί ήττον—</hi>greater and less. Aristotle means that all subjects whatsoever admit of arguments into which these ideas enter. The first comes into play when we argue, “since this is possible, that must be so also ” ; the second, when we say, “ if this has been, that has been also,” or “if this is to happen, that will happen also.” For the third and fourth of the <hi rend="italic">κοινοί τόποι, </hi>magnitude and degree, we are referred back to bk. i. ch. 7 and 8, where they have already been handled. The second book is completed by a sort of appendix, intended to supplement the sketch of the “logical proof” given in bk. i. ch. 2. The “example," or rhetorical induction, had been rather cursorily treated there, and is now illustrated more fully (ii. 20). There are two kinds of “example”—the historical (τδ <hi rend="italic">πρayμaτa λiytιv)</hi>  and the artificial (τό <hi rend="italic">αυτόν ποιeιv).</hi>  The artificial example, again, has two species— —(1) comparison, <hi rend="italic">παραβολή,—</hi>as when Socrates said that magistrates ought not to be chosen by lot, for this is like choosing athletes by lot, rather than for athletic power ; (2) fiction, or fable in the special sense—<hi rend="italic">λοyοι</hi>  ; as when Stesichorus warned the people of Himera against establishing a despot by telling them the fable of the horse who asked the man to help him against a deer. If you have no arguments of a logical kind (enthymemes), says Aristotle, the “ example ” must do duty as proof ; if you have enthymemes, it can serve as illustration.</p><p>The use of <hi rend="italic">yvωμaι,</hi>  or general moral sentiments, next claims attention (ch. 21). These are of two classes—those which are self-evident, and those which, not being so obviously true, require some confirmatory comment <hi rend="italic">(eπιλοyοi),</hi>  as when Medea says that no sensible man should allow his children to be exquisitely educated, because it makes them fastidious and unpopular. Such maxims with an “epilogue” are, in fact, virtually enthymemes. Apropos of yrω<hi rend="sub">j</hi>uαt, Aristotle remarks that spurious generalization is particularly useful in the utterance of bitter complaint (e.g., “ frailty, thy name is woman ”). Then it is often effective to controvert received maxims,<hi rend="italic">e.g.,</hi>  “It is not well to ‘know oneself’ ; for if this man had known himself, he would never have become a general” (ch. 21).</p><p>Some precepts on the enthymeme follow. The rhetorical reasoner must not have too many links in the chain of his argument ; and he must omit those propositions which his hearers can easily supply. Also, it is highly important to know the special topics (∈fδr∕) from which enthymemes can be drawn in each subject. The enthymeme is either (1) <hi rend="italic">δeικτ∣κ0v,</hi>  demonstrative, establishing a point, or (2) <hi rend="italic">tλeyκτικ0v,</hi>  refutative, destroying a position by a comparison of conflicting statements (τό <hi rend="italic">τa avομολοyουμeva συva-yeιv).</hi>  Aristotle now gives (ii. 23) an enumeration of classes or heads of argument <hi rend="italic">(evθυμημaτικοl τόποι)</hi>  from which enthymemes can be constructed. These apply nominally to all three branches of rhetoric, but in fact chiefly to the deliberative and the forensic. The demonstrative enthymeme is almost exclusively treated, since the refutative form can, of course, be inferred from the other. A chapter (24), answering to the treatise on fallacies in logic (π∈pl <hi rend="italic">σοφιστικών eλeyχωv),</hi>  is devoted to the fallacious <hi rend="italic">(φaιv0μevοv) </hi>enthymeme, of which ten “topics” are explained and illustrated. Another chapter is given to the two general types of <hi rend="italic">λύσα,</hi>  or refutation (ch. 25), viz., (1) direct counter-argument-(τδ <hi rend="italic">avτισυλ∙ λοyιζισθaι),</hi>  opposing one enthymeme to another ; (2) objection to a particular point in the adversary’s case (τό <hi rend="italic">όνίστασθαι).</hi>  The second book then concludes with some supplementary remarks, meant, seemingly, to correct errors made by previous writers on rhetoric (ch. 26).</p><p>In his first two books Aristotle has thus dealt with invention <hi rend="italic">(eυpeσa)—</hi>the discovery of means of persuasion. In the third book he deals with expression and arrangement (λe'ξιs and <hi rend="italic">τaξιs).</hi>  The subject is prepared by some remarks on the art of delivery <hi rend="italic">(ύπόκρισa), </hi>which Aristotle defines as the management of the voice. “ It is the art of knowing how to use the voice for the expression of each feeling, of knowing when it should be loud, low, or moderate, of managing its pitch—shrill, deep, or middle—and of adapting the cadences to the theme.” Aristotle says nothing on gesture or play of feature, which Cicero and Quintilian recognize as important. He includes them by implication, however, in saying that the art of delivery, whenever it is reduced to method, “ will perform the function of the actor's art,” adding that “the dramatic faculty is less a matter of art than of nature.</p><p>But verbal expression, at least, is clearly in the province of art, and to that he now turns. He deals first with diction <hi rend="italic">(λόξα)</hi>  in the proper sense, as concerned with the choice of words and phrases. The first excellence of diction is clearness <hi rend="italic">(σaφhveιa),</hi>  which is attained by using words in their proper sense <hi rend="italic">(κύρια).</hi>  Next, the diction must be “neither too low nor too grand, but suitable to the subject.” In prose <hi rend="italic">Gv τοls ψιλο7s λόγοα)</hi>  there is less scope for ornament than in poetry, though in the latter, too, much depends on the speaker or the theme. And here Aristotle remarks that Euripides was the first poet who produced a happy illusion by taking his words from the language of daily life (e<hi rend="sup">,</hi>κ<hi rend="italic">τηs eιωθυias διaλtκτου). </hi>With a view to adorning prose, and giving it “distinction” (the term which best represents Aristotle’s phrase <hi rend="italic">ξtvοv</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">ξevικbv ποιtιv), </hi>nothing is more important than the judicious use of metaphor. Aristotle admits that “the art of metaphor cannot be taught” ; but he gives some sensible hints on the subject, and on the use of epithets. The poet Simonides, he tells us, when the winner of a mule race offered him a small fee, declined to write an ode on “halfasses,” but, when the price was raised, sang “Hail, daughters of windswift steeds." Tno perceptions which made the best Greek prose so good are illustrated by Aristotle’s next chapter (iii. 3) on ψυχρά, “frigidities,” “faults of style.” He traces these to four</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>