<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Latin into the foreground, barbarism quite made away with literary Latin. Latin was not only dead but forgotten. The old sounds and forms had been lost, and the scribes, ignorant of classical grammar, tried nevertheless to make a show of learning by putting Latin forms at random. This makes the language look much more barbarous than it really was. It is sometimes very hard to find out the living popular form under the Latin varnish, and harder still to find out what is proper to each country, as Low Latin is very much the same everywhere. The following were some of the chief peculiarities.</p><p>1.    Old Latin forms reappeared, especially in Italy. Final consonants, especially <hi rend="italic">m, t, s,</hi>  were dropped or wrongly put. In Italy the nom. <hi rend="italic">annus</hi>  (-os), the ace. <hi rend="italic">annum {-om),</hi>  the dat. abl. <hi rend="italic">anno, </hi>the ace. plur. <hi rend="italic">anιws,</hi>  coalesced in <hi rend="italic">anno</hi>  ; as this was the real pronunciation, the scribes confounded the Latin forms. There being no longer any difference between <hi rend="italic">in locum</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">in loco,</hi>  both were confounded ; even <hi rend="italic">in locus, per locus,</hi>  Ac., were written. The prevalence of the type <hi rend="italic">anno</hi>  on the one hand and the growing use of the preposition <hi rend="italic">de</hi>  for the genitive on the other made the genitive <hi rend="italic">anni</hi>  disappear, and <hi rend="italic">anni</hi>  (with which <hi rend="italic">annis</hi>  coalesced) was used solely for the plural, likewise <hi rend="italic">fiori, month</hi>  Sometimes, as in Old French, the objective form <hi rend="italic">anno,</hi>  Old Fr. <hi rend="italic">an,</hi>  was used as a genitive, of which <hi rend="italic">Hôtel-Dieu</hi>  is still a remnant. In the same way Ital. <hi rend="italic">rosa</hi>  became the common singular, <hi rend="italic">rose</hi>  the common plural form. Out of Italy, final s being retained, the plural form was <hi rend="italic">annos, rosas, flores,</hi>  which is the Spanish (a»os) and Portuguese form, and partly the French, as <hi rend="italic">roses,</hi>  with <hi rend="italic">fleurs</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">ans</hi>  as accusatives. In Provençal and Old French <hi rend="italic">s</hi>  was kept in the nom. sing, masc., <hi rend="italic">ans, </hi>but in the nom. plur. the oldest form was <hi rend="italic">i,</hi>  retained in some Old French monosyllables—<hi rend="italic">li</hi>  illi, <hi rend="italic">did, trei, tuit</hi>  from <hi rend="italic">tutti,</hi>  used in the Gloss, of Cassel ; in polysyllables this <hi rend="italic">i</hi>  was lost, and <hi rend="italic">an</hi>  remained, likewise<hi rend="italic">fior Cfiori;</hi>  comp, <hi rend="italic">sapienti,</hi>  Gloss. Cass.), <hi rend="italic">munt.</hi>  The verbs <hi rend="italic">canto, cantos, cantat</hi>  in Spanish only lost <hi rend="italic">t</hi>  ; in Ital. <hi rend="italic">cantαs</hi>  through <hi rend="italic">eaηtis</hi>  (caused by the affinity of <hi rend="italic">s</hi>  to i) became <hi rend="italic">eanti.</hi>  In French both s and <hi rend="italic">t</hi>  were kept—<hi rend="italic">chante, chantes ; chaηtet,</hi>  later <hi rend="italic">chante ; est, vit, vient,</hi>  and from the analogy of these Mod. Fr. <hi rend="italic">aime -t -il, chante-t-il.</hi>  Many old tenses were lost, as &lt;mα(ι⅝)rαnι, which even in Latin sometimes had the sense of the simple past (see Latin), only in the oldest Fr. <hi rend="italic">rovéret,</hi>  roga(ve)rat = rogavit. <hi rend="italic">Ama(fi)i</hi>  became Ital. <hi rend="italic">amah</hi>  Fr. <hi rend="italic">aimai,</hi>  and was used as simple past (perfectum historicum) ; the praesens perfectum was expressed by a new tense, as <hi rend="italic">habeo amatum</hi>  (of which early germs are found), Ital. <hi rend="italic">ho amato, </hi>Span, <hi rend="italic">he amαdο,</hi>  Fr. <hi rend="italic">fiai aimé.</hi>  The old future was destroyed and a new future formed out of <hi rend="italic">aman habeo</hi>  (of which early traces are found), Old Ital. <hi rend="italic">ameraggio,</hi>  Mod. I tai. awierô, Span, <hi rend="italic">amuré,</hi>  Fr. <hi rend="italic">j’aimerai,</hi>  Ac. In consequence of the general loss of body, short words dwindled down so much that they became unfit for use, and were superseded by fuller words or reinforced by composition ; this is especially the case in pronouns and particles. As αcZ became <hi rend="italic">a, </hi>Lat. <hi rend="italic">a, ab</hi>  could no longer keep its ground, and was replaced by <hi rend="italic">de,</hi>  likewise <hi rend="italic">vis</hi>  by <hi rend="italic">fortia,</hi>  Ac. (see Latin). <hi rend="italic">Hie</hi>  disappeared and was replaced by <hi rend="italic">iste,</hi>  which remained uncomposed in Span, <hi rend="italic">este, </hi>and in the others was composed with <hi rend="italic">ecce, cecum</hi>  (see above). <hi rend="italic">Abαnte,</hi>  Mod. Ital. <hi rend="italic">avanti,</hi>  Fr. <hi rend="italic">avant,</hi>  occurs in a pagan inscription. Lat. <hi rend="italic">unde</hi>  became <hi rend="italic">de unde,</hi>  Ital. <hi rend="italic">donate</hi>  ; in Spanish this was further composed with <hi rend="italic">αd,</hi>  as <hi rend="italic">adonde,</hi>  and as this in time came to mean “where” a new <hi rend="italic">de</hi>  had to be added,—<hi rend="italic">de adonde, he.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">2.    C</hi>  became assibilated before single <hi rend="italic">e, i.</hi>  That during all the preceding periods c had the sound of <hi rend="italic">k</hi>  is proved by Old Latin spellings like <hi rend="italic">dekem</hi>  ; by Greek transcriptions, as <hi rend="italic">'F.ικlρων, Kαισαρ ; </hi>by the German renderings <hi rend="italic">Kaiser</hi>  (Old Eng. <hi rend="italic">cdsere}, Keller, “</hi>  cellar,” <hi rend="italic">Kirsche,</hi>  “ cherry,” Ac., and by the use of <hi rend="italic">c</hi>  for <hi rend="italic">k</hi>  in Old English, as in <hi rend="italic">cynne,</hi>  “kin,” <hi rend="italic">cennan,</hi>  “ken”; by late Latin spellings like <hi rend="italic">ques-quenti,</hi>  quiescenti, <hi rend="italic">pαche</hi>  (Rome, 408), <hi rend="italic">chingxit</hi>  (Gaul, 676), <hi rend="italic">vachis </hi>(Lucca, 722)—in Italian still <hi rend="italic">ch=k,</hi>  as <hi rend="italic">chi</hi>  quis, <hi rend="italic">ehe</hi>  quid ; and lastly <hi rend="italic">dulkisrna</hi>  (Pisaur., 410), <hi rend="italic">ofikina</hi>  (Gallic vase, end of 6th century; see <hi rend="italic">Romania,</hi>  xiii. 485). Yet c before <hi rend="italic">e, i</hi>  must early have had a more palatal sound than before <hi rend="italic">a, o, u,</hi>  something like the old-fashioned English pronunciation <hi rend="italic">kyard</hi>  for <hi rend="italic">card.</hi>  But it was not until very late that the difference became so marked as to be expressed by different letters : the palatal sound began to be assibilated into something like Italian <hi rend="italic">ce, ci,</hi>  Eng. <hi rend="italic">ch</hi>  (as in <hi rend="italic">child</hi>  from Old Eng. <hi rend="italic">cild},</hi>  about the 6th century, although perhaps not equally early everywhere. We find <hi rend="italic">κeιτανe</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">tzitane</hi>  (Ravenna charter, 591), and <hi rend="italic">paze</hi>  (inscr. about the same time). Ital. c = Eng. <hi rend="italic">eh</hi>  in <hi rend="italic">pace, dieci</hi>  (in Central Italy mostly pronounced <hi rend="italic">sh∖ cielo ; </hi>Span, <hi rend="italic">paz, diez, cielo</hi>  (lisping <hi rend="italic">s</hi>  from <hi rend="italic">ts) ;</hi>  Fr. <hi rend="italic">cixl</hi>  (Old <hi rend="italic">ts,</hi>  Mod. s).</p><p>1    3. <hi rend="italic">E</hi>  for accented ï became frequent. As original î and ï were no</p><p>longer different in quantity, they had to be distinguished by quality ; accordingly <hi rend="italic">rnnum</hi>  became Ital. <hi rend="italic">vino, minus {minus,</hi>  open i), Ital. <hi rend="italic">meno,</hi>  with the same vowel as in <hi rend="italic">véna</hi>  from <hi rend="italic">vena</hi>  ; thus Latin <hi rend="italic">ï</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">e</hi>  coalesced ; likewise we have <hi rend="italic">serivo</hi>  scribo, <hi rend="italic">bevo</hi>  bïbo, <hi rend="italic">sévo</hi>  sébum, <hi rend="italic">fido</hi>  fidus, <hi rend="italic">féde</hi>  fïdes, <hi rend="italic">eréde</hi>  crédit, <hi rend="italic">scritto</hi>  scriptum, <hi rend="italic">dette</hi>  dictum.</p><p>We find traces of this in the Pomp, <hi rend="italic">veces,</hi>  Ital. vece. In Low Latin <hi rend="italic">menus, fedes,</hi>  Ac., are constant. But many who had a little more learning retained the Latin spelling <hi rend="italic">minus,</hi>  pronouncing <hi rend="italic">meno{s),</hi>  and by this were induced to write constantly <hi rend="italic">i</hi>  for close <hi rend="italic">e, </hi>especially accented, as <hi rend="italic">habire, vedire,</hi>  crπ∕cre= Ital. avéré, vedére, crédere; <hi rend="italic">vindere, stüla</hi>=véndere, stëlla, Ital. véndere, stélla, Piedm. esteila, Old Fr. esteile, Fr. étoile. In some few instances this may represent a provincial <hi rend="italic">i,</hi>  as in Sicil. <hi rend="italic">aviri,</hi>  or special cases like Fr. <hi rend="italic">tenir, plaisir, merci.</hi></p><p>4.    Unaccented <hi rend="italic">e</hi>  for <hi rend="italic">ï,</hi>  which is frequent in Old Latin and not unfrequent in the post-classical age, returns in Low Latin with redoubled force. Thus we find <hi rend="italic">fedelis</hi>  (404), later <hi rend="italic">Damenecus, sej&gt;temus, decemus, ancma, deposeta, genetor, capete, soledοs</hi>  ; in the Ravenna charters <hi rend="italic">vecedomeno, vendecare, ordenαta,</hi>  Ac.; in Frankish charters <hi rend="italic">decemo,</hi>  Fr. dime, <hi rend="italic">Domeneeus, venerabelis, nobelis, lacrema, cantate, veretate, femena, ρlacetus,</hi>  Ac. This penetrated even into Central Italy, as in the Tuscan Latin of the 8th century, <hi rend="italic">dedet, placetum, homenis, inviolavelis.</hi>  In Middle Italian <hi rend="italic">uοrneni,</hi>  in Modern Italian <hi rend="italic">DomenedJte, ospedale,</hi>  are rare remnants of the earlier form. Generally classical <hi rend="italic">i</hi>  has prevailed in Florentine and Italian, as «mi»!, <hi rend="italic">femmina, anima, asino, online, spirite.</hi>  In the Sienese dialect <hi rend="italic">e</hi>  has remained, as <hi rend="italic">ordenare, cardenale,</hi>  and in North Italian — Venet. <hi rend="italic">δmeni, fèrnena, menèstra, brdene, dseno;</hi>  Lomb. <hi rend="italic">innen, asen, ordendri,</hi>  Ac. In Spanish it is not unfrequent—<hi rend="italic">ôrden, ûmedo, nove-ddd, corredôr</hi>  ; comp. Prov. <hi rend="italic">lagrema, semenar, conoissedor,</hi>  and Old Fr. <hi rend="italic">aneme,</hi>  pronounced <hi rend="italic">dnme</hi>  (the spelling points to an older stage).</p><p>5.    Unaccented medial <hi rend="italic">e</hi>  was often dropped, though less in Italian, except in the north, as in L. Lat. <hi rend="italic">dulkisrna,</hi>  dulcissima (Pisaur., 410), answering to modern Bomagnu∂lo forms like <hi rend="sup">,</hi>sZrissm=illus-trissimo ; generally L. Lat.<hi rend="italic">domnus, domna—ltA. donna,</hi>  “lady,” “woman.” In French all proparoxytones are contracted ; for instance, Old Fr. (asinum, *as<hi rend="sup">,</hi>no)<hi rend="italic">asne</hi>  âne, (anima, *an<hi rend="sup">,</hi>ma)<hi rend="italic">anmx </hi>âme, (hominem, *hom<hi rend="sup">,</hi>ne)<hi rend="italic">homme,</hi>  (femina, *fem<hi rend="sup">,</hi>na), ∕ewυne.</p><p>6.    Accented <hi rend="italic">o</hi>  for m, not unfrequent in the preceding period, was constant in Low Latin. While Lat. <hi rend="italic">lücem</hi>  became Ital. <hi rend="italic">luce,</hi>  Lat. <hi rend="italic">crucem, nucem {nucem,</hi>  open <hi rend="italic">u)</hi>  became <hi rend="italic">crôee, noce,</hi>  like <hi rend="italic">voce</hi>  from <hi rend="italic">vδcem</hi>  ; comp, <hi rend="italic">jùstus,</hi>  Ital. giusto, Fr. juste, but <hi rend="italic">augüstus,</hi>  Ital. agôsto, Fr. août. This caused many to write <hi rend="italic">u</hi>  for close <hi rend="italic">o,</hi>  as oicwrβ uxore, <hi rend="italic">geneture</hi>  genitorem, although this may partly represent a provincial <hi rend="italic">u,</hi>  as in Sicil. <hi rend="italic">amuri.</hi>  In Old Fr. we have <hi rend="italic">honour, favour,</hi>  and still <hi rend="italic">amour,</hi>  and in L. Lat. <hi rend="italic">curte</hi>=cohortem, *corte, Ital. corte, Fr. cour, Eng. court.</p><p>7.    Unaccented o for <hi rend="italic">ü</hi>  as in Old Latin is frequent, as in L. Lat. <hi rend="italic">tubola, popolo, secolom, ηgola, volontate,</hi>  Ital. <hi rend="italic">tdvola, popοlo,</hi>  Ac. ; even for original <hi rend="italic">u,</hi>  as <hi rend="italic">mano, spirite.</hi></p><p>8.    Unaccented medial <hi rend="italic">o</hi>  was often dropped before <hi rend="italic">l,</hi>  in which case the unfamiliar group <hi rend="italic">t’l</hi>  was changed into <hi rend="italic">el,</hi>  as in L. Lat. <hi rend="italic">oclus </hi>oculus, Ital. <hi rend="italic">6cchio,</hi>  Span, <hi rend="italic">ojo,</hi>  Fr. ceil ; <hi rend="italic">veelus</hi>  vetulus, Ital. <hi rend="italic">vecchio </hi>(Old Ital. <hi rend="italic">veglio∖</hi>  Span, vièjo, Fr. vieil, vieux ; also L. Lat. <hi rend="italic">tabla — </hi>Span, tabla, <hi rend="italic">poplom=</hi>Span, puéblo. In French syncope is a law— <hi rend="italic">table, peuple, sangle</hi>  cingulum, Ac.</p><p>9.    Final unaccented vowels in Italian on the whole obey the general laws. By the loss of the Latin final consonants all words end in a vowel, except such as <hi rend="italic">per, con, non, in, un bel giorno, buon giomo.</hi>  In South Italian <hi rend="italic">i, u</hi>  stand for <hi rend="italic">e, o.</hi>  In Spanish <hi rend="italic">e</hi>  is sometimes dropped, as <hi rend="italic">sed</hi>  sitim, Ital. séte ; <hi rend="italic">pared</hi>  parietem, Ital. paréte ; <hi rend="italic">fdcil, 6rden.</hi>  In Portuguese <hi rend="italic">o</hi>  is pronounced <hi rend="italic">u,</hi>  but often only whispered ; <hi rend="italic">e</hi>  is nearly always whispered or mute. In North Italian, Ladino, Catalan, Provençal, and French all final vowels are generally dropped, except <hi rend="italic">a,</hi>  which remains in Provençal, as <hi rend="italic">port,</hi>  but <hi rend="italic">porta </hi>(Mod. <hi rend="italic">pδrte∖</hi>  In Catalan <hi rend="italic">a</hi>  is mostly pronounced as open <hi rend="italic">e</hi>  ; in French this becomes obscure <hi rend="italic">e,</hi>  which in modern French is mute except in such cases as <hi rend="italic">table ronde.</hi></p><p>10.    Accented <hi rend="italic">ie</hi>  stands for <hi rend="italic">é, uo</hi>  for <hi rend="italic">8.</hi>  As ë and ë, <hi rend="italic">δ</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">δ</hi>  were levelled in quantity, they were already distinguished in quality, as in Ital. <hi rend="italic">bène</hi>  bêne, <hi rend="italic">véne</hi>  vënae ; Portuguese has got no further than this. But generally this was not distinct enough for the wants of the speakers, and unconsciously <hi rend="italic">è</hi>  (in which <hi rend="italic">è</hi>  from Lat. <hi rend="italic">ae</hi>  was included) became <hi rend="italic">iè,</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">δ</hi>  (in which <hi rend="italic">i&gt;</hi>  from Lat. <hi rend="italic">an</hi>  was <hi rend="italic">not </hi>included) became <hi rend="italic">uδ,</hi>  both diphthongs being generally accented on the last vowel—Ital. and Span, <hi rend="italic">viène,</hi>  Fr. <hi rend="italic">vient</hi>  venit ; Ital. <hi rend="italic">buδno, </hi>Span, <hi rend="italic">budnο</hi>  ; Ital. <hi rend="italic">suδιw,</hi>  Span, <hi rend="italic">sueno</hi>  (generally <hi rend="italic">sonido}</hi>  sonus, different from Ital. <hi rend="italic">sδno</hi>  sunt, Span. <hi rend="italic">son.</hi>  This change must be very old, as it is found in nearly all the Romance languages. In Spanish, Provençal, and French <hi rend="italic">ui&gt;</hi>  was changed into <hi rend="italic">ué,</hi>  and this in Modern French to <hi rend="italic">eu, œu,</hi>  contracted into the sound of <hi rend="italic">o.</hi>  In Spanish the use of diphthongs is extended to position—<hi rend="italic">tiémpo, siete </hi>septem, Ital. sètte, <hi rend="italic">hiérro,</hi>  Ital. fèrro, <hi rend="italic">ciiérpo,</hi>  Ital. cδrpo, <hi rend="italic">iiiuérte, </hi>Ital. morte. Mark the displacement of stress in popular Latin— <hi rend="italic">pariétem</hi>  for parietem, Ital. paréte, Span, pared, Fr. paroi ; <hi rend="italic">filiδlus </hi>for filiδlus, Ital. figliuδlo, Span, hijuélo, Fr. filleul.</p><p>11.    Of <hi rend="italic">mediae</hi>  (voiced stops) for <hi rend="italic">tenues</hi>  (voiceless stops), especially between vowels, we find some few earlier instances, as <hi rend="italic">grassus</hi>  for <hi rend="italic">crassus,</hi>  Ital. grasso, Fr. gras. This is generally rare in Italian Latin, as <hi rend="italic">gubitus,</hi>  cubitus, Ital. gomito, and is still comparatively rare in Italian. Yet it occurs in some of the most familiar words, as <hi rend="italic">ago</hi>  acus, <hi rend="italic">lago, luogo, segare,pagare</hi>  (pacare, “to satisfy,”</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>