<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>and <hi rend="italic">Frédéric de Sicile</hi>  (1680) are a connecting link between the romance of De Scudéry and the modern historical novel.</p><p>After the invention of printing England produced few original contributions to the literature of chivalric romance. There was a large number of translations of the old French works, and, in addition to these, a rich store of romantic ballads, which formed the customary literature of the people. The yeoman and the outlaw had succeeded the steel-clad knight in public favour. Robin Hood and his merry men appealed to a wider range of sympathies than did Arthur and his companions, and such tales as the <hi rend="italic">Exploits of Robin Hood, Tom a Lincoln, George a Green the Pinder of Wakefield,</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">Thomas of Reading</hi>  retained their vogue in abbreviated shape as chapbooks down to the end of the 18th century. The stage monopolized the chief forces of imaginative narration during the Elizabethan and Jacobean periods, and the next specimen of a native romance is to be found in the <hi rend="italic">Euphues</hi>  (1579-80) of John Lyly, who drew largely from Spanish sources. Euphuism gave rise to the <hi rend="italic">Philo-timus</hi>  (1583) of Brian Melbanck, to Lodge’s <hi rend="italic">Rosalynde </hi>(1590), to Greene’s <hi rend="italic">Dοrastus and Fawnia</hi>  (1588), which was the foundation of Shakespeare’s <hi rend="italic">Winter’s Tale,</hi>  and to <hi rend="italic">Philomela</hi>  (1592) by the same writer. Sir Philip Sidney’s <hi rend="italic">The Countess of Pembroke's Arcadia,</hi>  which appeared in 1590, after the author’s death, is the most brilliant prose fiction in English of the century, and a genuine pastoral and heroic romance. We should not forget <hi rend="italic">Parismus, Prince of Bohemia</hi>  (1598), based upon Palmerin de Oliva, and <hi rend="italic">Ornatus and Artesia</hi>  (1607), both by Emanuel Ford ; <hi rend="italic">Pheander, a Maiden Knight</hi>  (1595), by Henry Roberts; and <hi rend="italic">The Miseries of Malvillia</hi>  (1606), by Breton. Such compilations as Painter’s <hi rend="italic">Palace of Pleasure</hi>  (1566), Whetstone’s <hi rend="italic">Heptameron</hi>  (1582), <hi rend="italic">Westward for Smelts</hi>  (1620), and Goulart’s <hi rend="italic">Admirable Histories</hi>  (1607) are composed of translations or imitations of Italian and French tales. Boccaccio, Giraldi Cinthio, Apuleius, Heliodorus, and Montemayor appeared in English in the latter half of the 16th century, and to the laborious Munday we owe versions of <hi rend="italic">Amadis</hi>  (1592) and <hi rend="italic">Palmervn of England</hi>  (1602) through the French. In the 17th century La Calprenède, Scudéry, Gombauld, and other romancists were translated, and Mrs. Behn, Lee, Lord Orrery, Settle, Banks, and Dryden adapted their works for the stage. Barclay’s <hi rend="italic">Argenis,</hi>  a politico-heroic romance with characters representative of real and historical personages, first came out in Latin in 1622; Bishop Hall’s <hi rend="italic">Mundus alter et idem </hi>(1607) is an imitation of Rabelais. <hi rend="italic">Eliana</hi>  (1661) is a caricature of all the absurdities of the contemporary French school. The last of the English romances is the <hi rend="italic">Partheηissa </hi>(1665) of Roger Boyle, earl of Orrery, which, although prolix and incongruous, has literary merit and a certain narrative interest.</p><p>The last of the Spanish romances is <hi rend="italic">Ρolicisne de Roeeia</hi>  (1602) by Juan de Silva. They received their death-blow in Spain at the hands of <hi rend="italic">Don Quixote</hi>  in 1605, and even those of the greatest merit and popularity almost entirely ceased to be reprinted after that date. Although the pastoral romance of <hi rend="italic">Diana</hi>  (1560) by Montemayor does not really belong to the present subject, it should be mentioned as forming a distinct school of fiction with a family of successors scarcely less numerous than the lineage of Amadis. It was continued by Gil Polo, and in it, as in the <hi rend="italic">Galatea</hi>  (1584) of Cervantes, figure real persons and incidents. The earliest representative of the <hi rend="italic">picaresque</hi>  tale is to be found in <hi rend="italic">Lazamllο de Termes</hi>  (1554).</p><p>The heroic romance never became thoroughly naturalized in Portugal, and the narrative class chiefly found its way through Spain. The romancists Rodriguez Lobo, Eloi de Sa Sotomayor, and Pires de Rebello may be mentioned. The <hi rend="italic">Menina e Moςa</hi>  (1554) of Bernardim Ribeiro is the earliest specimen of the pastoral style in the Portuguese language.</p><p>Although the <hi rend="italic">Pastorαlia</hi>  of Longus is to be considered as the remote prototype of the modern works, <hi rend="italic">Arcadia</hi>  (1502), the Italian poem of Sannazaro, undoubtedly influenced the <hi rend="italic">Diana</hi>  of Montemayor, and through it inspired the <hi rend="italic">Arcadia</hi>  of Sir Philip Sidney. A few translations and weak imitations of foreign romances were printed in Italy in the 16th and 17th centuries, but <hi rend="italic">nουelle</hi>  or short tales formed the staple of the uatioual prose fiction during that period.</p><p>French romance—translations of <hi rend="italic">Amadis</hi>  in the 16th and the writings of Mademoiselle de Scudéry and her compeers in the 17th century—exercised a supreme influence in Germany, where the pastoral romance was represented by innumerable “Schäfereien.” <hi rend="italic">Herkules und Valisea</hi>  (1659) of A. II. Bucholz is a specimen of the voluminous and tiresome heroic romance of the period. <hi rend="italic">Simplicis-simus</hi>  (1669) by Hans Jakob von Grimmelshausen, in which the hero traverses the scenes of the Thirty Years’ War, is less a romance than the first national novel. C. W. Hagdorn’s <hi rend="italic">Acquαn, oder der grosse Mogul</hi>  (1670) is an adaptation of La Calprenède's <hi rend="italic">Cassaηdrc, </hi>and E. W. HappeΓs <hi rend="italic">Der insulanisehe Mandorell</hi>  (1682) is a kind of foreshadowing of <hi rend="italic">Robinson Crusoe.</hi>  Two of the most admired fictions of the time were the <hi rend="italic">Asiatische Banise</hi>  (1688) of H. Anselm von Ziegler und Klipphausen and the <hi rend="italic">Arminius und Thusnelda </hi>(1689) of D. K. von Lohenstein. Historical tales and love stories were the chief favourites at the end of the 17th and “ Robin-sonad⅛n" or imitations of Defoe in the second quarter of the 18th century.</p><p>In Holland the French heroic school was mirrored in the works of Johan van Heemskerk, Hendrik Zoeteboom, and Lambertus Bos, published in the middle of the 17th century.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">General Literature of Mediæval Romance.—Modern critical editions of the </hi><hi rend="italic">chansons</hi>  and romances invariably contain literary introductions. Most of these have been already referred to. For the general history of the subject, see [Bp. R. Hurd] <hi rend="italic">Letters on Chivalry arul Romance,</hi>  1762; Clara Reeve, <hi rend="italic">The Progress</hi>  o∕Romance,Colchester,1785,2 vols. ; J. Moore, “ View of the Commencement and Progress of Romance ” (preface to <hi rend="italic">Works of T.</hi>  Smollett, 1797, 8 vols.) ; J. Ritson, “ Diss, on Romances and Minstrelsy” (vol. i. of <hi rend="italic">Ancient Μetr. Rom., </hi>1SO2, 3 vols.) ; W. J. Thoms, <hi rend="italic">Coll, of Early English Prose Romances,</hi>  London, 1828, 3 vols., new ed. 1858; T. Warton, “Origin of Romantic Fiction in Europe" <hi rend="italic">(History of Eng. Poetry,</hi>  London, 1840, 3 vols.) ; G. Ellis, <hi rend="italic">Specimens of Early Eng. Μetr. Romances,</hi>  new ed. by Halliwell, 1848, 8vo ; J. Dunlop, <hi rend="italic">History of Fiction, </hi>1816, 3 vols., and London, 1S45, roy. 8vo, still the best general history of the subject, and not very much improved in the German translation by F. Liebrecht, Berlin, 1851, roy. 8vo ; J. Nigroni, <hi rend="italic">Diss, de lectione libb. amatoriorum,</hi>  Louvain, 1624 ; Langlois (Fancan), <hi rend="italic">Le tombeau des romans,</hi>  1626 ; P. D. Huet, <hi rend="italic">De l’origine des romans,</hi>  1711; <hi rend="italic">Histoire littéraire de la France,</hi>  1733-1881, 28 vols. 4to ; [N. Lenglet Dufresnoy], <hi rend="italic">De l’usage des romans, avec une bibl. des romans,</hi>  Amsterdam, 1734, 2 vols. 12mo, and <hi rend="italic">L’histoire justifiée contre les romans,</hi>  Amsterdam, 1735 ; [Jacquin], <hi rend="italic">Entretiens sur les romans,</hi>  1755 ; [Boucher de la Richarderie], <hi rend="italic">Lettre sur les romans,</hi>  1762 ; Lacurne de Ste Palaye, “ Mém. concernant la lecture des anciens romans" <hi rend="italic">(Hist, et Mém. de l’Acad. des Inscr.,</hi>  vol. xvii.) ; J. Chapelain, <hi rend="italic">De la lecture des vieux romans,</hi>  ed. Feillet, 1870 ; <hi rend="italic">Bibliothèque universelle des romans,</hi>  1775-89, 112 vols. 12mo, containing analyses of most of the romances, over 40 vols, being edited by De Paulmy, the remainder by Le Grand d’Aussy, Tressan, &amp;c.,—the new edition by Bastide (Paris, 1782, 4to) stopped in the middle of the third volume ; <hi rend="italic">Nouvelle Bibliothèque,</hi>  1798-1805, 56 vols. 12mo ; De Paulmy and Contant d’Orville, <hi rend="italic">Mélanges tirés d'une grande bibliothèque, </hi>1779-88, 69 vols. 8vo,—Le Grand d’Aussy helped in this work, which contains many analyses and a bibliography ; Tressan, <hi rend="italic">Corps d'extraits de romans de chevalerie,</hi>  1782, 4 vols. 12mo ; C. de Caylus, “ Sur l’origine de l’ancienne chevalerie et des anciens romans ” <hi rend="italic">(Hist, et Mém. de l’Acad. des Inscr.,</hi>  vol. xxiii.) ; L. Dutens, <hi rend="italic">Tables généalogiques des héros de romans,</hi>  1796, 4to ; J. Michelet, “Sur les épopées du Moyen Âge" (in <hi rend="italic">Rev. des D. M.,</hi>  July 1831); A. P. Paris, <hi rend="italic">Réponse à M. Michelet,</hi>  1831 ; J. J. Ampère, <hi rend="italic">Histoire littéraire de la France,</hi>  1839-40, 3 vols. ; A. Ch. Gidel, <hi rend="italic">Étude sur la littérature grecque moderne et nos romans de chevalerie,</hi>  1846; A. P. Paris, “Romans” (Lacroix, Le <hi rend="italic">Moyen fige et la Renaissance,</hi>  vol. ii., 1849); E. du Méril, <hi rend="italic">Poésies populaires latines antérieures au XIle siècle,</hi>  1843 ; L. Gantier, <hi rend="italic">Hist, des proses jusqu'à la fin du Xlle siècle,</hi>  1858 ; A. Maury, <hi rend="italic">Croyances et légendes de l’antiquité,</hi>  1863 ; L. Moland, <hi rend="italic">Origines littéraires de la France,</hi>  1863 ; A. Delvau, <hi rend="italic">Coll, de romans de chevalerie,</hi>  1869, 4 vols, (abridgments) ; Fr. H. von der Hagen, <hi rend="italic">Heldenbilder aus d. Sagenkreisen,</hi>  Breslau, 1823, 3 vols. ; J. G. T. Graesse, <hi rend="italic">Die grossen Sagenkreise des Mittelalters,</hi>  Dresden, 1842, bibliographical and literary, but showing extraordinary industry and grasp of the materials; F. Diez, <hi rend="italic">Altromanische Sprachdenkmäler,</hi>  Bonn, 1846; O. L. B. wolff, <hi rend="italic">Allg. Geschichte des Romans,</hi>  Jena, 1850 ; F. W. Val. Schmidt, <hi rend="italic">Les romans en prose des cycles de la Table Ronde et de Charlemagne,</hi>  trans, by F. de Roisin, St Omer, 1845; K. Goedeke, <hi rend="italic">Deutsche Dichtung im Mittelalter,</hi>  Dresden, 1871 ; F. Henrion, <hi rend="italic">Istoria de’ Romanzi di Cavalleria,</hi>  Florence, 1794 ; G. Ferrario, <hi rend="italic">Storia ed Analisi degli Antichi Romami d'Italia,</hi>  Milan, 1828-29, 4 vols. 8vo ; A. de Gubernatis, <hi rend="italic">Storia della I.etteratura</hi>  (ix.-x., Romanzo), 2 vols. sm. 8vo, 1883 ; see also numerous articles in <hi rend="italic">Jahrbücher für romanische u. engl. Litteratur, Anglia, Revue Celtique, Romania, Revue des langues romanes, &amp;c.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Arthurian Cycle.—Lady Ch. Guest, </hi><hi rend="italic">The Mabinogion,</hi>  1838-50, 3 vols. ; Th. Hersart de la Villeinarqué, <hi rend="italic">Contes pop. de la Bretagne</hi>  (1846, 2 vols.), Les <hi rend="italic">Bardes Bretons</hi>  (1S6O), <hi rend="italic">Les Romans de la Table Ronde</hi>  (1861), and <hi rend="italic">Myrdhinn, ou l'Enchanteur Merlin</hi>  (1862); San Marte [A. Schulz), <hi rend="italic">Die Sagen von Merlin</hi>  (Halle, 1853), and <hi rend="italic">Parceval-Studien</hi>  (Berlin, 1861-62, 3 pts.); [F. Zambrini], <hi rend="italic">DelΓ Illustre Historia di Lancillotto del Lago,</hi>  Bologna, Î862 ; “ La Tavola Ritonda, o ΓHistoria di Tristano" (Acad. Bologna, R. Com., 1863); E. F. Leith, <hi rend="italic">The Legend of Tristan,</hi>  1868 ; A. P. Paris, Les <hi rend="italic">romans de la Table Ronde,</hi>  1868-77, 5 vols. ; Skene, <hi rend="italic">Four Anc. Books of Wales,</hi>  1868, 2 vols. ; J. S. Stuart Glennie, <hi rend="italic">Arthurian Localities,</hi>  1869 ; F. G. Bergmann, <hi rend="italic">The San Great,</hi>  1870 ; G. E. R., <hi rend="italic">The Story of Merlin and Vivien,</hi>  [1879] ; E. F. ∙F. Hucher, <hi rend="italic">Sur les représen tations de Tristan et d’Yseult dans les monuments,</hi>  1871, and Le <hi rend="italic">Saint Gral,</hi>  Le Mans, 1874-77, 3 vols.; W. B. Odgers, <hi rend="italic">King Arthur and the Arthurian Romances,</hi>  [1872]; A. Birch-Hirschfeld, <hi rend="italic">Die Sage vom Graal,</hi>  Leipsic, 1877 ; C. Domanig, <hi rend="italic">l’ardval-Studien,</hi>  1878 ; L. Kraussold, <hi rend="italic">Die Sage vom Heil. Gral,</hi>  1878 ; E. Martin, <hi rend="italic">Zur Gndsage,</hi>  1880.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Charlemagne Cycle.—J. C. v. Aretin, </hi><hi rend="italic">Aelteste Sage über die Geburt . . . Karls d. Gr.,</hi>  Munich, 1803 ; L. Uhland, “Ueber das altfranzösische Epos” (in Fouqué’s <hi rend="italic">Musen,</hi>  1812, pt. 3) ; F. W. Val. Schmidt, <hi rend="italic">Ueber die italienischen Heldengedichte aus d. Sagenkreis Karls des Gr.,</hi>  Berlin, 1820; E. Aignan, <hi rend="italic">Ro. mances tirées des anciennes hist, des 12 Pairs</hi>  (vol. iii. of <hi rend="italic">Bibliothèque Etrangère, </hi>Paris, 1823) ; <hi rend="italic">Romans des douze pairs de France,</hi>  Paris, 1832-42, 9 vols. ; A. P. Paris, “Sur les romans des douze pairs” (pref. to <hi rend="italic">Berte aux grans piés,</hi>  1832),</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>