<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>“pay”), <hi rend="italic">pregare, budello, parentado, contadο</hi>  (comitatus), <hi rend="italic">contrada, spada, strada; p</hi>  from <hi rend="italic">b</hi>  becomes <hi rend="italic">v,</hi>  as in <hi rend="italic">riva, riviera, povero, savio; </hi>before <hi rend="italic">r—padre, madre, segreto, lebbra.</hi>  This recalls similar changes in Umbrian, and was perhaps originally North Italian and from thence penetrated into Tuscany. In Spanish the voiced sounds are the general rule, as <hi rend="italic">fuégo,</hi>  Ital. fuòco, <hi rend="italic">amigo,</hi>  Ital. amico, <hi rend="italic">amado, finido,</hi>  Ital. amato, finito, <hi rend="italic">sabér,</hi>  Ital. sapére, &amp;c., yet there are some exceptions, such as <hi rend="italic">poco</hi>  (paucum). In Old French the soft sound is the constant law, but this mostly disappears later, as in <hi rend="italic">aimé, aimée</hi>  (see France, vol. ix. p. 632 <hi rend="italic">sq. ). </hi>A general Romance case is placitum, Old Ital. <hi rend="italic">ρiaitο,</hi>  Ital. <hi rend="italic">piato,</hi>  Span. <hi rend="italic">pleito,</hi>  Old Fr. <hi rend="italic">plaid,</hi>  through *plagito, *plajeto, which is singularly like the Umbrian <hi rend="italic">feitu, feetu</hi>  for <hi rend="italic">façitu.</hi>  A limited case is that of such words as Fr. <hi rend="italic">raison,</hi>  Ital. <hi rend="italic">ragione</hi>  from <hi rend="italic">rationem,</hi>  probably first changed to <hi rend="italic">ratsió, *radsióne,</hi>  thence to <hi rend="italic">rasione,</hi>  which sometimes occurs in Late Latin, and often in Early Italian, Span, <hi rend="italic">razon</hi>; comp. Ital. <hi rend="italic">cagione</hi>  occasionem.</p><p>12.    <hi rend="italic">I</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">e</hi>  unaccented before vowels, especially post-tonic, became <hi rend="italic">j, </hi>as<hi rend="italic">  filjus</hi>  (Plautus), <hi rend="italic">olium</hi>  pron. <hi rend="italic">οljo. J</hi>  coalesced with the preceding consonant, making it palatal, as in Ital. <hi rend="italic">figlio, oglio, figlia, maraviglia</hi>  (mirabilia), <hi rend="italic">battaglia</hi>; Span, <hi rend="italic">maraυilla, batalla; </hi>Fr. <hi rend="italic">fille, merveille, bataille</hi>  (in North French the palatal sound is replaced by <hi rend="italic">i</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">j),</hi>  &amp;c. <hi rend="italic">N</hi>—Ital. <hi rend="italic">vigna</hi>  vinea, <hi rend="italic">Spagna</hi>  Hispania, <hi rend="italic">ingegno, castagna, campagna, bagnο</hi>  balneum; Span. <hi rend="italic">Espana, campa na;</hi>  Fr. <hi rend="italic">vigne, champagne.</hi>  In some cases <hi rend="italic">j</hi>  was assibilated, as Span. <hi rend="italic">granja, estranjero,</hi>  Fr. <hi rend="italic">songe, grange, étrange.</hi></p><p>13.    Sometimes attraction takes place, <hi rend="italic">i</hi>  being transposed to the radical syllable, especially in French, as <hi rend="italic">huile, bain, témoin, Antoine, gloire, histoire.</hi>  Before and after <hi rend="italic">r</hi>  peculiar forms appear—Ital. <hi rend="italic">primaio</hi>  (-70); <hi rend="italic">muojo</hi>  morior; Ital. <hi rend="italic">primiero, cavaliere, </hi>from<hi rend="italic">  primario, </hi>probably assimilated into *<hi rend="italic">primer(i)o</hi>  (Dr Thomsen). Forms like <hi rend="italic">pαner, sorcerus</hi>  are found as early as the 8th century.</p><p>14.    <hi rend="italic">Vocabulary. —</hi>During this period the Roman world, after being conquered by the Germanic nations, adopted many words from their conquerors. The German influence was strongest in France; hence we find Germanic expressions for many of the most common words except form-words, though the stock of the language remains Latin. A curious instance, characteristic of the Middle Ages, is <hi rend="italic">rauba, </hi>which from “robbery, ” “prey, ” came to mean “property, ” Ital. <hi rend="italic">roba </hi>(<hi rend="italic">robba</hi>)<hi rend="italic">,</hi>  “things in general, ” Span, <hi rend="italic">ropa,</hi>  “linen, ” “stuff, ” Fr. <hi rend="italic">robe,</hi>  “gown. ” In Rumonsch we have <hi rend="italic">la rauba c'aud a mi,</hi>  “the property that belongs to me. ” The German <hi rend="italic">h,</hi>  as in <hi rend="italic">haïr</hi>, old <hi rend="italic">hadir </hi>= “hate, ” is peculiar to French, and is still sounded in Normandy. Some Germanic sounds had to be modified, as <hi rend="italic">w</hi>  to <hi rend="italic">gu</hi>, for instance, <hi rend="italic">guerra</hi>  from <hi rend="italic">werra,</hi>  “war”; <hi rend="italic">guanto,</hi>  Old Fr. <hi rend="italic">guant,</hi>  Fr. <hi rend="italic">gant,</hi>  from <hi rend="italic">want,</hi>  Dan. <hi rend="italic">Vante</hi>; in North French <hi rend="italic">w</hi>  remained, whence Eng. <hi rend="italic">war,</hi>  &amp;c. Among the <hi rend="italic">leges barbarae,</hi>  the Lex Salica is perhaps the most remarkable as a document of Low Latin. It has sentences and words like—hoc sunt <hi rend="italic">pariculas causas=ce</hi>  sont pareilles choses; si in dominica <hi rend="italic">ambactia</hi>  fuerit occupatus, Ital. ambasciata, Fr. ambassade; si quis alterum voluerit occidere et <hi rend="italic">colpus</hi>  praeter <hi rend="italic">fallierit,</hi>  Ital. se il colpo fallisce; si quis alterum <hi rend="italic">de</hi>  sagitta toxicata percutere voluerit et praeter <hi rend="italic">sclupaverit</hi>  (see <hi rend="italic">stloppsιs,</hi>  p. 665); si quis <hi rend="italic">cabαllum</hi>  extra consilium domini sui <hi rend="italic">caballixaverit,</hi>  Ital. caval-care, Fr. chevaucher; si quis per mal0 ingenio in <hi rend="italic">curie</hi>  (Ital. corte, Fr. cour) alterius aut in <hi rend="italic">casa</hi>  (Ital. <hi rend="italic">casa,</hi>  “house”) aliquid de furtzzτn miserit; <hi rend="italic">eompanium,</hi>  Ital. compagnia; <hi rend="italic">bare, baronis,</hi>  “a free man, ” Old Fr. nom. <hi rend="italic">ber,</hi>  obj. <hi rend="italic">baruη,</hi>  “hero, ” “baron”; <hi rend="italic">diffaeere,</hi>  Ital. disfare, Fr. défaire; <hi rend="italic">exeortieare,</hi>  Ital. scorticare, Fr. écorcher. From other laws we have—<hi rend="italic">-fortia,</hi>  Ital. forza, Fr. force; <hi rend="italic">hostis</hi>  exercitus, Eng. host; <hi rend="italic">vassus</hi>  (Celtic), “a vassal”; <hi rend="italic">auca,</hi>  Ital. δca, Fr. oie (from <hi rend="italic">avixa); troppus,</hi>  grex (from Germ, <hi rend="italic">thorp∖</hi>  Ital. truppa, Fr. troupe, and also Ital. <hi rend="italic">troppo,</hi>  “too much, ” Fr. <hi rend="italic">trop; forestis</hi>  (from <hi rend="italic">foris), “</hi>  foreign, ” Ital. forestiere; <hi rend="italic">marea</hi>  (Germ. ), “ border, ” whence <hi rend="italic">mαrehensis,</hi>  Ital. marchese, Fr. marquis; <hi rend="italic">tornare</hi>  (Greek; also Dacian Latin@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi>). Gregory of Tours (6th century) has<hi rend="italic">ρageηsis, </hi>Ital. paése, Fr. pays. Gregory the Great has mercea, “mercy ”; <hi rend="italic">fiasco,</hi>  Ital. fiasco, “a flask. ” Coripγus (Afr., c. 570): <hi rend="italic">eara,</hi>  ‘‘face ” (Gr. <hi rend="italic">κάρα,</hi>  “head”), Span, <hi rend="italic">cara,</hi>  Old Fr. <hi rend="italic">chixre,</hi>  whence <hi rend="italic">bonne chère, </hi>“ good cheer ” (originally the kind, hospitable countenance of the entertainer). Venantius Fortunatus (c. 580): <hi rend="italic">eofea,</hi>  “coif”; <hi rend="italic">crema,</hi>  “cream”; <hi rend="italic">viaticum,</hi>  Ital. viaggio, Fr. voyage. Other sources: <hi rend="italic">eamiηus,</hi>  “ road ” (Spanish Latin, 7th century; probably Celtic), Ital. cammino, Fr. chemin; <hi rend="italic">directum,</hi>  jus (Italian Latin, 551), Ital. diritto, Fr. droit. The late agrimensores: circαre, Ital. cercare, Fr. chercher. Old glosses (7th and 8th centuries): <hi rend="italic">αeiarium,</hi>  Ital. acciaio, Fr. acier; <hi rend="italic">cosinus,</hi>  consobrinus, Ital. cugino, Fr. cousin; <hi rend="italic">gamba,</hi>  Ital. gamba, Fr. jambe (Gloss. Cass. ). Isidore: <hi rend="italic">trudα,</hi>  Fr. truite, Eng. trout; <hi rend="italic">cama,</hi>  Span, <hi rend="italic">eama,</hi>  “bed”; <hi rend="italic">fieatum, </hi>“liver” (properly <hi rend="italic">jeeurfixαtum,</hi>  liver of geese fed with figs), Ital. fégato, Span, higado, Fr. foie; and <hi rend="italic">eusire,</hi>  consuere, Ital. cuscire, cucire, Span, coser, Fr. coudre (Gloss. Isid. ); <hi rend="italic">selvatieus,</hi>  Ital. sel-vaggio, Fr. sauvage; <hi rend="italic">formaticum,</hi>  Ital. formaggio, Fr. fromage.</p><lb/><p>VI. <hi rend="italic">Sixth (Last) Period.</hi></p><p>For the sixth and last period—that is, for the history and distinctive traits of the great modern Romance languages —the reader is referred to the separate articles.</p><p>1.    <hi rend="italic">Italian</hi>  is distinguished by its harmonious form, its vocalic endings, and the rich fulness of its tones.</p><p>2.    <hi rend="italic">Spanish</hi>  is distinguished by its regularity, by its short, distinct sounds and its fixed tones, and by many Arabic words. Certain “thick” sounds, as the <hi rend="italic">j</hi>  (like Dutch and South German <hi rend="italic">ch,</hi>  though in the south of Spain much weaker, almost Λ) and the lisping c, <hi rend="italic">z</hi>  seem to be rather modern developments than due to direct Arabic influence.</p><p>3.    <hi rend="italic">Portuguese</hi>  is, with <hi rend="italic">Gallego</hi>  (the dialect of Galicia), the western dialect of Spanish, and has almost the same words, but a very different pronunciation ; in sound it approaches somewhat to French, as in the nasal vowels (which, however, are less purely vocalic than in French) and the voiced sounds of s, 2, and <hi rend="italic">j.</hi>  It has partly retained the Old Spanish form, as in <hi rend="italic">filho</hi>  for Span, <hi rend="italic">hijo,</hi>  and partly it has a character of its own owing to its many obscured vowels and contractions, as <hi rend="italic">boa</hi>  for <hi rend="italic">bona, dor</hi>  for <hi rend="italic">dolor.</hi></p><p>4.    <hi rend="italic">Provençal</hi>  in many respects represents the earliest form of French; in others it has peculiar developments (see Provençal). <hi rend="italic">Catalan</hi>  is the southern dialect of Provençal.</p><p>5.    <hi rend="italic">French</hi>  makes up for the want of the full forms and tones of Italian by its grace and delicacy. It has more of a history than the other Romance languages, Old French being very different from Modern.</p><p>6.    <hi rend="italic">Ladino (Rumonsch,</hi>@@<hi rend="italic"><hi rend="sup">2</hi></hi>  Germ. <hi rend="italic">Churwαlsch,</hi>  from the town of Chur) or <hi rend="italic">Central Romance</hi>  extends from the Grisons to Friuli on the Adriatic. It is not uniform, being only an agglomeration of cognate dialects ; and it is scarcely more Latin than any other Romance language. It has chiefly been elucidated by Ascoli.</p><p>7.    <hi rend="italic">Roumanian</hi>  has probably not survived from the old Roman colonists of Dacia, but been imported from Istria (which has a cognate dialect) or Northern Italy. It has been greatly mixed up with Slavonic words and sounds (such as the “ mixed ” vowels), and has some distinctive marks, such as the post-positive article, <hi rend="italic">Romunul =</hi>  Romanus ille ; compare the similar phenomenon in the Slavonic dialect of Bulgaria and in the Albanian language.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Literature.—</hi>The real founder of scientific Romance philology and linguistics is Friedrich Diez, in his <hi rend="italic">Grammatik der romanischen Sprachen,</hi>  3 vols., Bonn, 1836-42, and <hi rend="italic">Etymologisches Wörterbuch der romanischen Sprachen,</hi>  2 vols., 1852. He also published <hi rend="italic">Altro∙ manische Sprachdenkmäler,</hi>  1846 ; <hi rend="italic">Zwei altromanischc Gedichte, </hi>1852 ; and <hi rend="italic">AUromanisehe Glossare,</hi>  1865. Pott contributed several articles on the Low Latin of the <hi rend="italic">leges barbarae</hi>  in the <hi rend="italic">Zeitschriften </hi>of Hofer and Kuhn. Other authorities on various branches of the subject are—Ducange, <hi rend="italic">Glossarium mediæ et infirnæ latinitαtis,</hi>  7 vols. ; Marini, <hi rend="italic">Papiri diplomatiei</hi>  ; Muratori, <hi rend="italic">Antiquitates Italieæ-, </hi>Schuchardt, <hi rend="italic">Der Voealismus des Vulgärlateins,</hi>  3 vols., 1866-68 (a valuable collection of materials), also several minor works by the same author ; and Gaston Paris, <hi rend="italic">Étude sur le Rôle de l'Accent Latin dans la Längste Française,</hi>  Paris, 1862, and <hi rend="italic">La Vie de St Alexis </hi>(a poem of 11th century), 1872. The principal magazines devoted to the subject are—<hi rend="italic">Jahrbuch für romanische und englische Literatur </hi>(ed. Wolff, Ebert, and Lembcke), later only <hi rend="italic">für romanische Literatur ; Archiv für das Studium der neueren Sprachen</hi>  (ed. Herrig), of a more popular character ; <hi rend="italic">Romania</hi>  (a quarterly, cd. Gaston Paris and Paul Meyer, since 1872), contains articles of the most eminent Romanists; <hi rend="italic">Revue des Langues Romanes</hi>  (Montpellier, from 1870 onwards), chiefly devoted to Provençal ; <hi rend="italic">Romanische Studien </hi>(ed. Boehmer) ; <hi rend="italic">Zeitschrift für romanische Philologie</hi>  (ed. Gröber, since 1877) ; and <hi rend="italic">Romanische Forschungen</hi>  (ed. Vollmöller, since 1884). Mussafia has written many articles and treatises, chiefly in the <hi rend="italic">Transadions</hi>  of the Vienna Academy of Sciences. Ascoli, author of <hi rend="italic">Studi Critici,</hi>  has edited since 1873 the <hi rend="italic">Archivio Glottologieo, </hi>which has articles by Flecchia. The <hi rend="italic">Rivista di Filologia Romαnza </hi>(ed. Manzoni, Monaci, and Stengel, 1873) in 1878 became <hi rend="italic">Giornαle di Filologia Romαnza</hi>  (ed. Monaci). For the etymological dictionaries of the separate languages see the special articles.    (J. ST.*)</p><lb/><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi>  The Greek historians Theophylact (c. 600) and Theophanes relate that the Dacian soldiers said in their native tongue<hi rend="italic">τi&gt;ρvα, τt&gt;pva, φpaτρe, htτbpva. </hi>This has been called by some the earliest trace of Roumanian.</p><lb/><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">2</hi>  Rumonsch is properly the dialect of the upper Rhine valley, Ladino that of the Engadine. Ascoli includes all varieties under the common name of Ladino.</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>