<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>(inscr. biling.), <hi rend="italic">Setume, Setimi,</hi>  Septimius, Umb. <hi rend="italic">scrcihtor, serehto, </hi>Ital. <hi rend="italic">Settimo, Xettuno, atto</hi>  aptus, <hi rend="italic">cattivo, scritto.</hi></p><p>3.    <hi rend="italic">Tt</hi>  takes the place of <hi rend="italic">et,</hi>  as in <hi rend="italic">Beneditus</hi>  (204), <hi rend="italic">lattuea</hi>  (Edict. Diocl., 301). This too came from the north ; <hi rend="italic">Vitoria</hi>  occurs on an ancient mirror, probably Etruscan. Comp. Umb. subahtu and <hi rend="italic">subator,</hi>  formally = su bacti, <hi rend="italic">rehte</hi>  recte, where/;, originally sounded, had become mute or nearly so, which is further proved by the spellings <hi rend="italic">anibrehtu, ambretu,</hi>  ambito, &amp;c. ; comp, <hi rend="italic">tettvrn{e),</hi>  probably = Ital. <hi rend="italic">tetto</hi>  tectum, just as Ital. <hi rend="italic">retto</hi>  rectus, <hi rend="italic">atto</hi>  actus, <hi rend="italic">otto</hi>  octo, <hi rend="italic">notte</hi>  noctem. This change was restricted to Italy ; elsewhere <hi rend="italic">et </hi>became <hi rend="italic">it,</hi>  as Fr. <hi rend="italic">fait</hi>  factum, Port, <hi rend="italic">feito,</hi>  Span, <hi rend="italic">hecho</hi>  ( = *feitjo). Likewise <hi rend="italic">cs (x)</hi>  became in Italy ss, as in Lat. <hi rend="italic">eossim, vissit,</hi>  elsewhere <hi rend="italic">is,</hi>  as Span, and Port, <hi rend="italic">seis,</hi>  Fr. <hi rend="italic">cuisse, laisser.</hi></p><p>4.    <hi rend="italic">G</hi>  before a single <hi rend="italic">e, i</hi>  becomes palatal (like the old-fashioned Eng. <hi rend="italic">gyarden,</hi>  &amp;c.) or nearly y (Eng. <hi rend="italic">y</hi>  in <hi rend="italic">yσu∖</hi>  so that both are confounded—<hi rend="italic">magestati</hi>  (inscr. before 243) ; <hi rend="italic">cogiugi,</hi>  conjugi. The sign for <hi rend="italic">J</hi>  in the Gothic alphabet, taken from Latin <hi rend="italic">G,</hi>  shows the pronunciation of the 4th century.</p><p>5.    <hi rend="italic">Xgη</hi>  for <hi rend="italic">gη,</hi>  as <hi rend="italic">eongnato, singno,</hi>  belongs perhaps to this period—<hi rend="italic">connate,</hi>  &amp;c., is also found—E. Ital. <hi rend="italic">seng no,</hi>  now spelt <hi rend="italic">segno,</hi>  with palatal <hi rend="italic">n, degno</hi>  dignus, <hi rend="italic">regno</hi>  regnum, &amp;c., Fr. <hi rend="italic">digue, </hi>&amp;c. ; sometimes n(τι), as in <hi rend="italic">eonôseere,</hi>  Fr. <hi rend="italic">connaître.</hi>  There are traces of some other transitions that appear to have been completed only in the next period.</p><p>6.    <hi rend="italic">Vocabulary.—</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Apuleius has </hi><hi rend="italic">sapidus,</hi>  “savoury” (comp, insipidus), Old Fr. <hi rend="italic">sadx,</hi>  whence Fr. <hi rend="italic">maτcssade</hi>  (mal-sade) ; <hi rend="italic">rnarsicare </hi>= Ital. ; <hi rend="italic">follicare,</hi>  “breathe” (like a bellows), Port, <hi rend="italic">folgar,</hi>  J3pan. <hi rend="italic">holgar,</hi>  “rest,” “lounge”; <hi rend="italic">masticare,</hi>  Ital. masticare, Fr. mâcher; <hi rend="italic">minari</hi>  (equunι baculis), “threaten,” hence “drive,” Ital. menare, Fr. mener ; <hi rend="italic">cambiare</hi>  (better than <hi rend="italic">eambire),</hi>  Ital. cambiare, Fr. changer; <hi rend="italic">victηαlis</hi>  adj., in the 6th century subst. <hi rend="italic">vietualia</hi>  (nom. plur. ), Old Fr. and E. Eng. <hi rend="italic">vitaille,</hi>  Eng. <hi rend="italic">vittles,</hi>  spelt etymologically <hi rend="italic">victuals ; aucilla, aueella</hi>  for <hi rend="italic">avieella,</hi>  the existence of which had been denied by Varro, L. Lat. <hi rend="italic">aueellus,</hi>  Ital. <hi rend="italic">uecello,</hi>  poet, <hi rend="italic">augello, </hi>Prov. <hi rend="italic">auzels,</hi>  Old Fr. <hi rend="italic">οisel,</hi>  Mod. Fr. <hi rend="italic">oiseau. </hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Cælius Aurelianus (2d or 3d century) has </hi><hi rend="italic">testa,</hi>  “skull,” frequent in the 4th century, I tai. <hi rend="italic">testa,</hi>  “head,” Fr. tête. Lampridius (c. 250): <hi rend="italic">ρapilio = </hi>pavilion, ∕w∕∕icmMS, Ital. pulcino, Fr. poussin; <hi rend="italic">pipio,</hi>  “pigeon”; <hi rend="italic">]datea,</hi>  “place.” Tertullian, first Christian author: <hi rend="italic">rememorare, </hi>“remember,” <hi rend="italic">aeternalie,</hi>  “eternal,” <hi rend="italic">eompassio, “</hi>  compassion,” and many other modernisms, such as <hi rend="italic">plus miser=</hi>I tai. piu misero, Fr. plus miserable. Diocletian : <hi rend="italic">fata,</hi>  parca, Ital. fata, Fr. fée. Solinus (c. 3d century): <hi rend="italic">repatriare,</hi>  “to repair (to).” Apicius (c. 3d century) : <hi rend="italic">exealdare,</hi>  I tai. scaldare, Fr. échauder ; <hi rend="italic">spatula, </hi>ltal. spalla, Span, espalda, Fr. épaule.</p><p>IV. <hi rend="italic">Fourth Period</hi>  : 300 (350) <hi rend="italic">to</hi>  500 (550).</p><p>This period extends from the introduction of Christianity to the Middle Ages and the great migrations. Christianity marks an important epoch in the history of the Romance languages. Pagan literature was abhorred, and classical traditions lost. Popular speech got the upper hand ; the gospel was preached to the people in the people’s own language, and the New Testament translated into vulgar Latin. Several phonetic changes which formerly had been wavering and uncertain became rapidly fixed and decided. The whole language was revolutionized.</p><p>1.    Palatal <hi rend="italic">g οrj</hi>  was developed into <hi rend="italic">dj</hi>  (like <hi rend="italic">gy</hi>  in Hung. <hi rend="italic">Magyar </hi>=palatal <hi rend="italic">d</hi>  + Eng. <hi rend="italic">y)</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">dzh</hi>  (Eng. j), sometimes <hi rend="italic">dz,</hi>  and was confounded with original <hi rend="italic">di—Zerax,</hi>  Hierax (Cumæ, 202); Zoυλιoe (pagan inscr.), comp. <hi rend="italic">Diuliali</hi>  (568), <hi rend="italic">Madias</hi>  (364), also <hi rend="italic">Mazas = </hi>majas, <hi rend="italic">Gianuaria</hi>  (503), also <hi rend="italic">Zanuari,</hi>  &amp;c. Italian still retains the sound of <hi rend="italic">dzh</hi>  in <hi rend="italic">giungere</hi>  jüngere, <hi rend="italic">Giove</hi>  Jovem, <hi rend="italic">gènere, giacére, </hi>&amp;c. Original <hi rend="italic">di</hi>  in <hi rend="italic">Aziabenico</hi>  (Afr., 195), <hi rend="italic">niedius,</hi>  pronounced <hi rend="italic">medsius</hi>  according to Servius (4th century) and Consentius (5th century), Ital. <hi rend="italic">mezzo,</hi>  pronounced <hi rend="italic">med∙zo</hi>  (but <hi rend="italic">giorno</hi>  from <hi rend="italic">diurnus).</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">2.    Ti was</hi>  assibilated before vowels ; there are no certain pre-Christian instances. In the 4th century the Gothic <hi rend="italic">laiktjδ= </hi>lectio shows that the change had only begun ; <hi rend="italic">ci</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">ti</hi>  were sometimes confounded, as in κdλτtos calceus (Plut., c. 100 ; Ed. Diocl., 301), <hi rend="italic">ocio</hi>  (Rome, 389) ; we have <hi rend="italic">ti</hi>  for <hi rend="italic">si</hi>  in <hi rend="italic">aecletiae </hi>(early Christ, inscr.). In the 5th century the change appears as fully accomplished ; the grammarian Pompeius (probably a Mauretanian) expressly teaches the pronunciation <hi rend="italic">Titius</hi>  as <hi rend="italic">Titsius,</hi>  and Consentius (a Gaul) <hi rend="italic">etiam</hi>  as <hi rend="italic">eziam, i.e., etsiam.</hi>  In the 6th century we have the Gothic <hi rend="italic">kavtsjoη,</hi>  cautionem. It is probable that this change too originally came from the north, especially from Etruria, where it was very old : we have Etrus. <hi rend="italic">Ventia Venza, Arηθia Arηza,</hi>  Etrus. Lat. <hi rend="italic">Vencsi, Vensius, Arnzius</hi>  (while Umbrian has <hi rend="italic">tertio, Martie,</hi>  &amp;c. ), Mars. Lat. <hi rend="italic">Martses,</hi>  evidently the source of the Latin <hi rend="italic">Marsi.</hi>  At length this pronunciation reached the capital and became general, mostly expressed by <hi rend="italic">c,</hi>  as in <hi rend="italic">eciarn, ter· eins, milieia, justieia, staeio, ηacioηem,</hi>  &amp;c. The pronunciation <hi rend="italic">ts</hi>  is confirmed for Spain by Isidore in the 7th century. This sound is still preserved by Italian in words like <hi rend="italic">piazza, grazia, naziωιe, giustιzia,</hi>  likewise by Old French, as <hi rend="italic">naeium, place,</hi>  whereas in Spanish <hi rend="italic">ts</hi>  has coalesced into a lisped <hi rend="italic">s,</hi>  as in <hi rend="italic">gracia, nation,</hi>  and in Portuguese, Provençal, and Modern French it has been assimilated into a hard (voiceless) <hi rend="italic">s,</hi>  as in <hi rend="italic">plαςa, plαssα, place.</hi></p><p>3.    <hi rend="italic">Ci</hi>  was assibilated before vowels. In the 4th century we have the Gothic <hi rend="italic">faskja,</hi>  which shows no change. Schuchardt is probably right in supposing that <hi rend="italic">ci</hi>  was assibilated a good deal later than <hi rend="italic">ti, </hi>—an inference from the comparative rarity of instances of change, and from the silence of the grammarians. From instances like <hi rend="italic">ocio</hi>  (see 2) it would appear that <hi rend="italic">ci</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">ti</hi>  had the same sound, but this cannot have been the case, as Italian still keeps up a difference, as in <hi rend="italic">piaeeia</hi>  placeat, <hi rend="italic">piazza</hi>  platea. Yet there may have been a beginning of a palatal affection, making the two sounds somewhat like each other. In the 6th century we have the Gothic <hi rend="italic">unkjane </hi>(unciarum) and <hi rend="italic">οvvκια</hi>  in the Ravenna charters, but on the other hand <hi rend="italic">πpcκαω=preeio</hi>  for <hi rend="italic">pretiο, Urbitcηιs</hi>  (533, which, however, may be a miscorrection, <hi rend="italic">c</hi>  being added instead of substituted for ∕), <hi rend="italic">Mauriscius</hi>  on a Gaulish coin, from the same period,—making it probable that the assibilation had been accomplished. In the 7th and 8th centuries spellings like <hi rend="italic">οnzia</hi>  for <hi rend="italic">uncia</hi>  are quite common.</p><p>4.    The most important change of all was the victory of stress over quantity and tones. The popular songs of the classical period show a decided prevalence of accent. In the soldiers’ songs from the end of the 3d century stress has quite superseded quantity and is the ruling principle of the metre :—</p><p>“ Unus Λ&lt;⅛ι.o mille, mille, mille decollavimus.</p><p>Tantum vini nemo Λtiδei quantum fudit sanguinis.”</p><p>This is just like the metre of early Christian hymns—<hi rend="italic">“Dies</hi>  irae, <hi rend="italic">dies</hi>  ilia,” and “O Rex aeterne, <hi rend="italic">Démine,” tzc.</hi>  The old quantities had been levelled. St Augustine (354-430) says that in his time only a few grammarians had kept up the distinction between <hi rend="italic">rnδrae </hi>and <hi rend="italic">more,</hi>  and that the Africans confounded <hi rend="italic">tis</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">os.</hi>  Servius (4th century) could only find out quantity from stress in words like <hi rend="italic">impius, amicus.</hi>  Consentius says that some, especially Africans, said <hi rend="italic">piper</hi>  for <hi rend="italic">piper</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">δrator</hi>  for <hi rend="italic">orator.</hi>  This does not necessarily mean that all short accented vowels before single consonants had become long ; probably both short and long coalesced to a medial quantity, rather short than long, and there was no very marked difference of quantity between accented and unaccented vowels. This appears plainly from the nature of Romance poetry, where stress has only a moderate importance—namely, in the most prominent parts of the verse — while the chief principle is the number of syllables. In Italian, especially in the Tuscan dialect, we may hear <hi rend="italic">bambino</hi>  with short accented <hi rend="italic">i,</hi>  the unaccented <hi rend="italic">o</hi>  being rather longer than the accented <hi rend="italic">i,</hi>  just as Eng. <hi rend="italic">y</hi>  in <hi rend="italic">pity,</hi>  when emphatic, is longer than <hi rend="italic">i.</hi>  In Spanish words like <hi rend="italic">mΑno, primêro, senôra</hi>  the accented vowel is generally as short as the unaccented or even shorter, which does not prevent the Spaniards from counting it as “ <hi rend="italic">dos tiempos ”</hi>  (duas moras) ; the unaccented final syllables are often rather longer, as in Eng. <hi rend="italic">pity.</hi>  In Italian the longest syllables are those containing two or more consonants after the accented vowel, as <hi rend="italic">tèmpo, paziènza, bôcca, gatto</hi>  ; the chief difference between <hi rend="italic">fdtto</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">fdto</hi>  is the length of the <hi rend="italic">t</hi>  in the former. In Spanish and French even long consonants are shortened, as Span. <hi rend="italic">bοca, gato,</hi>  Fr. <hi rend="italic">chatte·, jette</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">achète</hi>  are equally short; vowels are generally short or medial, as <hi rend="italic">une belle ville</hi>  (not like wα∕, as the English make it), and are long only by compensation, as in <hi rend="italic">ane, chante</hi>  (where the nasal is absorbed by the vowel). The old distinction of tone necessarily disappeared with these, the acute or high even <hi rend="italic">iR,oma)</hi>  and the circumflex or high falling tone (A5wα) being dependent on the quantities.</p><p>5.    <hi rend="italic">Vocabulary.—</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Ausonius (Burdigala, 309-392) : </hi><hi rend="italic">burrαe,</hi>  nugae, Ital. burla, “joke." Arnobius (Afr.,c. 330): <hi rend="italic">coquina,</hi>  I tai. cucina, Fr. cuisine. Firmicus Maternus (c. 340 ?) : <hi rend="italic">compti,tτιs,</hi>  Ital. conto, Fr. compte. Palladius (c. 350): <hi rend="italic">e&amp;tus,</hi>  “cat”; <hi rend="italic">species=Εv.</hi>  épices. Ammianus Marcellinus (end of 4th century) : <hi rend="italic">molina,</hi>  Ital. molino, Fr. moulin; <hi rend="italic">impedieare</hi>  empêcher ; pi∕αrβ=expilare, Fr. piller, Ital. pigliare ; <hi rend="italic">proba,</hi>  preuve. Vegetius (end of 4th century): <hi rend="italic">burgus,</hi>  castellum parvum, Ital. borgo, Fr. bourg. Jerome (331-420) : <hi rend="italic">eamisia</hi>  (Celtic), Ital. camicia, Span, camisa, Fr. chemise; <hi rend="italic">earrieare,</hi>  I tai. caricare, Span, cargar, Fr. charger; <hi rend="italic">impostor</hi>  = Eng.; <hi rend="italic">rancor,</hi>  “rancour.” The Vulgate: <hi rend="italic">grossus,</hi>  Ital. grosso, Fr. gros (see also Latin). Servius (c. 390) : <hi rend="italic">falco,</hi>  Ital. falcone, Fr. faucon. Lactantius (d. c. 330) : <hi rend="italic">meridionalis. </hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Augustine (354-430) : </hi><hi rend="italic">combina™ ; vanitare</hi>  vanter. Codex Theodos. (438) : <hi rend="italic">exagium,</hi>  Ital. saggio, Fr. essai; <hi rend="italic">paraveredus,</hi>  L. Lat. palafredus, I tai. palafreno, Fr. palefroi ; <hi rend="italic">aeueula,</hi>  aiguille. Cassiodorus (beginning of 6th century): <hi rend="italic">modernus,</hi>  “modern.” Codex Justinian. (527-565) : <hi rend="italic">amicabilis,</hi>  “ am iable. ”</p><p>V. <hi rend="italic">Fifth Period·.</hi>  500 (550) <hi rend="italic">to c.</hi>  900 (1000).</p><p>This period, which extends from the migrations to the first appearance of the modern Romance languages, is the age of Low or barbarous Latin, as written especially in charters and laws. While Christianity had brought vulgar</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>