<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>emolument, and its occupant was invested with a jurisdiction over the youth of Athens similar to that of the vice-chancellor in a modern university. Thus it is said of Theodotus, the first holder of the chair of sophistic as constituted by Marcus Aurelius, <hi rend="italic">πρoiστη</hi>  δe <hi rend="italic">καί της των Αθηναίων veoτητoς πρώτος</hi>  (Philostr., <hi rend="italic">Vit. Soph.,</hi>  II. Π. ρ. 566). The Antonines further encouraged rhetoric by granting immunities to its teachers. Three “ sophists ” in each of the smaller towns, and five in the larger, were exempted from taxation <hi rend="italic">{Dig.,</hi>  xxvii. 1, 6, § 2). The wealthier sophists affected much personal splendour. One of them, Polemon (c. 130 a.d.), was attended on his journeys by an enormous retinue—slaves, beasts of burden, horses, and hounds—while he himself drove in a costly equipage. Another, Adrian of Tyre (c. 170 a.d.), was drawn to his lectures by horses “ with silver bits,” wore the richest attire and the rarest jewels, and endeared himself to the Athenian students by the entertainments which he provided for them. In all this foppery there was calculation. The aim of the sophist was to impress the multitude. Popular applause was the breath of life to him. His whole stock in trade was style, and this was directed to astonishing by <hi rend="italic">tours de force.</hi>  The scholastic declamations were chiefly of two classes. (1) The <hi rend="italic">suasoriæ</hi>  were usually on historical or legendary subjects, in which some course of action was commended or censured ; thus Juvenal, alluding to his school-days, cries—</p><p>“ I, too, have counselled Sulla to resign,</p><p>And taste those joys for which dictators pine.”</p><p>These <hi rend="italic">suasoriæ</hi>  belonged to deliberative rhetoric (the <hi rend="italic">βοvλevτLκοv ycvος, deliberativum genus).</hi>  (2) The <hi rend="italic">controversies</hi>  turned especially on legal issues, and represented the forensic rhetoric <hi rend="italic">{8eκαvLκοv γevος, judiciale genus). </hi>But it was the general characteristic of this period that all subjects, though formally “ deliberative ” or “ forensic,” were treated in the style and spirit of that third branch which Aristotle distinguished, the rhetoric of e7rιδ∈tfιs or “display.” The oratory produced by the age of the academic sophists can be estimated from a large extant literature. It is shown under various aspects, and presumably at its best, by such writers as Dion Chrysostom at the end of the 1st century, Ælius Aristides in the 2d, Themistius, Himerius, and Libanius in the 4th. It would be unjust to deny that, amid much which is tawdry or vapid, these writings occasionally present passages of true literary beauty, while they constantly offer matter of the highest interest to the student of the past.</p><p>In the mediæval system of academic studies, grammar, logic, and rhetoric were the subjects of the trivium, or course followed during the four years of undergraduateship. Music, arithmetic, geometry, and astronomy constituted the quadrivium, or course for the three years from the B.A. to the M. A. degree. These were the seven liberal arts. According to Hallam <hi rend="italic">{Lit. Eur.,</hi>  vol. i.), the idea of a trivium and quadrivium dates from the 6th century. The well-known memorial couplet can be traced to <hi rend="italic">c.</hi>  1420 a.d. :—</p><p><hi rend="italic">Gram,</hi>  loquitur, <hi rend="italic">Dia.</hi>  vera docet, <hi rend="italic">Rhet.</hi>  verba colorât :</p><p><hi rend="italic">Mus.</hi>  canit, <hi rend="italic">Ar.</hi>  numerat. <hi rend="italic">Geo.</hi>  pondérât, <hi rend="italic">As.</hi>  colit astra.</p><p>A shorter formula was—“ lingua, tropus, ratio ; numerus, tonus, angulus, astra.” In the Middle Ages the chief authorities on rhetoric were the latest Latin epitomists, such as Martianus Capella (5th century), Cassiodorus (5th century), or Isidorus (7th century).</p><p>After the revival of learning, the better Roman and Greek writers gradually returned into use. Some new treatises were also produced. Leonard Cox (died 1549) wrote <hi rend="italic">The Art or Craft of Rhetoryke,</hi>  partly compiled, partly original, which was reprinted in Latin at Cracow.</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">Art of Rhétorique</hi>  by Thomas Wilson (1553), afterwards secretary of state, embodied rules chiefly from Aristotle, with help from Cicero and Quintilian. About the same time, treatises on rhetoric were published in France by Tonquelin (1555) and Courcelles (1557). The general aim at this period was to revive and popularize the best teaching of the ancients on rhetoric. The subject was regularly taught at the universities, and was, indeed, important. At Cambridge in 1570 the study of rhetoric was based on Quintilian, Hermogenes, and the speeches of Cicero viewed as works of art. An Oxford statute of 1588 shows that the same books were used there. In 1620 George Herbert was delivering lectures on rhetoric at Cambridge, where he held the office of public orator. The decay of rhetoric as a formal study at the universities set in during the 18th century. In 1712 Steele regrets that Oxford and Cambridge have “ grown dumb in the study of eloquence.” The function of the rhetoric lecturer passed over into that of correcting written themes ; but his title remained long after his office had lost its primary meaning If the theory of rhetoric fell into neglect, the practice however, was encouraged by the public exercises (“acts’ and “ opponencies ”) in the schools. The college prizes fo “ declamations ” served the same purpose.</p><p>The fortunes of rhetoric in the modern world, as briefly sketched above, may suffice to suggest why few modern writers of ability have given their attention to the subject. Perhaps one of the most notable modern contributions to the art is the collection of commonplaces framed (in Latin) by Bacon, “ to be so many spools from which the threads can be drawn out as occasion serves,” a truly curious work of that acute and fertile mind. He called them “Antitheta.” A specimen is subjoined :—</p><table><row><cell cols="2" rows="1"><p>Uxor et Liberi.</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>For.</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Against.</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>“Attachment to the state</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="2"><p>“ He who marries, and has children, has given hostages to fortune. ”</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>begins from the family.”</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>“Wife and children are a dis</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>“ The immortality of brutes is</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>cipline in humanity. Bachelors</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>in their progeny ; of men, in</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>are morose and austere. ”</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>their fame, services, and institutions. ”</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>“The only advantage of celi</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>“Regard for the family too</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>bacy and childlessness is in case</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>often overrides regard for the</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>of exile.”</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>state. ”</p></cell></row></table><p>This is quite in the spirit of Aristotle’s treatise. The popularity enjoyed by Blair’s <hi rend="italic">Rhetoric</hi>  in the latter part of the 18th and the earlier part of the present century was merited rather by the form than by the matter. Campbell’s <hi rend="italic">Philosophy of Rhetoric,</hi>  which found less wide acceptance than its predecessor, was superior to it in depth, though often marred by an imperfect comprehension of logic. But undoubtedly the best modern book on the subject is Whately’s <hi rend="italic">Elements of Rhetoric.</hi>  Starting from Aristotle’s view, that rhetoric is “an offshoot from logic,” Whately treats it as the art of “ argumentative composition.” He considers it under four heads :—(1) the address to the understanding ( = Aristotle’s <hi rend="italic">λoyiκη πiστ∣s)</hi>  ; (2) the address to the will, or persuasion ( = Aristotle’s <hi rend="italic">ηθeκη</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">παθητική πiστις)</hi>  ; (3) style ; (4) elocution, or delivery. At the outset he makes some judicious remarks on the popular objections to the art. “It has been truly observed that ‘genius begins where rules end.’ But to infer from this, as some seem disposed to do, that, in any department wherein genius can be displayed, rules must be useless, or useless to those who possess genius, is a very rash conclusion. What I have observed elsewhere concerning logic, that ‘a knowledge of it serves to save a waste of ingenuity,’ holds good in many other departments also.” “A drayman, we are told, will taunt a comrade by saying, ‘ you ’re a pretty fellow,’ without</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>