<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>which gives its Portuguese name to a northern province of Brazil, rises in the Serra dos Cairiris-Novos, passes Natal, the capital of the province, and falls into the sea to the south of Sào Roque. (3) Rio Grande do Sul, the outlet of the Lagδa dos Patos, wrongly supposed by the early explorers to be the mouth of a great river, gives its name to a city and province of Brazil (see below). (4) Rio Grande, a river of Western Africa, enters the sea opposite the Bissagos Archipelago (see Senegambia).</p><p>RIO GRANDE DO SUL, or in full Säo Pedro do Rio Grande do Sul, a city of Brazil, in the province of the same name, near the mouth of the estuary of Rio Grande. Including the suburbs it is a place of from 30,000 to 35,000 inhabitants (1880), with a considerable trade and various manufactures. The bar at the mouth of the “ Rio ” does not admit vessels of full 10-feet draught ; but dredging operations undertaken by the Government in 1882 are considerably increasing the depth. In 1881-84 a railway was constructed from Rio Grande do Sul to Bage, 125 miles inland. The average annual value of the imports in the six official years ending June 30, 1882, was about £589,043, reckoning the milreis at 2s. In 1881 651 vessels (133,779 tons) crossed the bar inwards, and 555 (133,276) outwards. Among the foreign vessels the British are most numerous. The imports are very various, to supply the colonies of Germans, Italians, &amp;c., settled throughout the province; the exports on the other hand are mainly hides, skins, bones, hair, tallow, &amp;c.</p><p>Rio Grande do Sul was a long time the chief town of the captaincy of El Rei (which included both the present province of Rio Grande do Sul and that of Santa Catharina). It was first founded as an encampment of Portuguese troops in 1737 on the south side of the Rio Grande. The settlement was removed to its present site by Gomes Ereire d’Andrade in 174δ. The Spaniards occupied this part of the country from 1763 to 1776. In 1807 the two districts of Sào Pedro and Santa Catharina were united and erected into a province with Sào José de Porto Alegre for its chief town ; and, though Rio Grande was declared a city in 1809, Porto Alegre retained its position even after the separation into two comarcas in 1812. The name of the province has been rendered familiar in Europe through the remarkable success which has attended the establishment of German and Italian agricultural colonies. In 1872 there were 36,458 foreigners in the province to 330,564 freeborn Brazilians and 67,791 slaves ; and by 1882 it was estimated that the German population alone amounted to 102,000, while the Italians, who began to immigrate in 1875, were rapidly approaching 50,000. The first German settlement was that of Sào Leopoldo on the Rio do Sino, founded by Dorn Pedro I. in 1825. By 1830 the inhabitants numbered 5000, and in 1854 the town was made a municipium. Others of the same nationality are Novo Mundo (1850), Nova Petropolis (1858), Santa Maria da Soledade, Marato, Sào Benedicto, Sào Salvador, Montenegro, Feliz, Teutonia (1858), Estrella (1856), Santa Cruz (1849), Mont Alverne, Germania, Sào Lorenzo (1858), Santa Clara, Säo Silvano, Domingos, &amp;c. The principal Italian colonies are Caxias, Conde d’Eu, Donna Isabel, and Sil viera Martins, which in 1884 had respectively 13,680, 6287, 9595, and 6000 inhabitants. The success of these colonies is one of the most important elements in the development of the Brazilian empire.</p><p>See works by Hörmeyer (Coblentz, 1854); Mulhall (London, 1873); Cantatt (Berlin, 1877); H. Lange (Leipsic, 1881); Richard Dilthey (Berlin, 1882); for the Italian colonies, Breitenbach’s paper in <hi rend="italic">Globus</hi>  (1885) ; and, for the Lagoa dos Patos, Ihering in <hi rend="italic">Deutsche geogr. Blätter</hi>  (Bremen, 1885).</p><p>RIOM, a town of France, with 9590 inhabitants, at the head of an arrondissement in the department of Puy-de-Dôme, 8 miles north of Clermont-Ferrand on the railway to Paris, occupies an eminence on the left bank of the Ambène (a left-hand tributary of the Allier) rising above the fertile plain of Limagne. It is surrounded with boulevards and has wide streets, but the houses, being built of black lava, have a rather sombre appearance. Some date from the 15th and 16th centuries, with turrets and ancient carved work. The church of St Amable goes back to the 12th century, but has suffered by repeated restorations. The old ducal palace (now occupied by the court of appeal, etc.) has a collection of portraits of Auvergne celebrities. A feature in the town is the fountains, of which some are of the Renaissance period. Riom trades in the products of Limagne—grain, wine, hemp, preserved fruits, and especially a conserve of apricots—and has a tobacco manufactory.</p><p>Riom <hi rend="italic">{Rieomagus</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">Rieomum</hi>  of the Romans) was long the rival of Clermont. Along with Auvergne it was seized for the crown by Philip Augustus, and it was the capital of this province under the dukes of Berri and Bourbon. During the religious wars it long held with the League. Its courts of law, always famous, are associated with the memory of D’Aguesseau.</p><p>RIONERO IN VOLTURE, a city of Italy, in the province of Potenza, 4 miles from Atelia, is pleasantly situated at the foot of Monte Voiture, has the repute of being the best built and best kept of the towns of the Basilicata, and has long been distinguished by the industrious character of its inhabitants (11,383 in 1881). It does not seem to be older than the first half of the 17th century. In 1851 it suffered severely from the earthquake.</p><p>RIOT is “an unlawful assembly which has actually begun to execute the purpose for which it assembled by a breach of the peace and to the terror of the public. A lawful assembly may become a riot if the persons assembled form and proceed to execute an unlawful purpose to the terror of the people, although they had not that purpose when they assembled ” (Stephen, <hi rend="italic">Digest of the Criminal Law,</hi>  art. 73). The above is the definition of a riot at common law in England. The offence is the most grave kind of breach of the peace known to the law, short of treason. In its previous stages it may be an affray, an unlawful assembly, or a riot, according to circumstances, and it may, if carried far enough, become treason. An affray is the fighting of two or more persons in the public street. An unlawful assembly is an assembly of three or more persons λvith intent to commit a crime by force or carry out a common purpose, lawful or unlawful, in such a way as to give reasonable grounds for fearing a breach of the peace. A rout is an unlawful assembly which has made a motion towards the execution of its common purpose. If the unlawful assembly should begin to demolish a particular inclosure, that would be a riot ; if it should proceed to pull down all inclosures, that would be treason. It was considered as early as the 14th century that the common law gave an insufficient remedy against riot. In 1360 the statute of 34 Edw. III. c. 1 gave jurisdiction to justices to restrain, arrest, and imprison rioters. In 1393 the statute of 17 Rie. II. c. 8 conferred similar powers on the sheriff and <hi rend="italic">posse comitαtus.</hi>  Numerous other Acts extending the common law were passed, especially in the Tudor reigns (see Stephen, <hi rend="italic">History of the Criminal Law,</hi>  vol. i. p. 202). The effect of existing legislation is to constitute certain statutory offences similar to riot at common law. The earliest Act now in force is one commonly called the Riot Act, 1 Geo. I. st. 2, c. 5. That Act makes it the duty of a justice, sheriff, mayor, or other authority, wherever twelve persons or more are unlawfully, riotously, and tumultuously assembled together to the disturbance of the public peace, to resort to the place of such assembly and read the following proclamation :—“ Our Sovereign Lady the Queen chargeth and commandeth all persons being assembled immediately to disperse themselves, and peaceably to depart to their habitations or to their lawful business, upon the pains contained in the Act made in the first year of King George for preventing tumultuous and riotous assemblies. God save the Queen.” It is a felony punishable with penal servitude for life to obstruct the reading of the proclamation or to remain or continue together unlawfully, riotously, and tumultuously for one hour after the proclamation was made or for one hour after it would have been made but for being hindered. The Act requires the justices to seize and apprehend all persons continuing after the hour, and indemnifies them</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>