<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>(Louvre), must for ever remain amongst the masterpieces of French art. Rigaud, although the great successes to which he owed his fame were won without exception in portrait painting, persisted in pressing the Academy to admit him as an historical painter. This delayed his reception, and it was not until January 2, 1700, that he succeeded in obtaining his desire. He presented as his diploma works a St Andrew (Louvre) and the portrait of Desjardins already mentioned, exhibited at the salon of 1704, and fdled in turn all the various posts of academical distinction. Having attained a professional position of unsurpassed eminence, Rigaud died at the age of eighty-four on 27th December 1743, having never recovered from the shock of losing his wife in the year previous. He had many pupils, and his numerous works had the good fortune to be reproduced by the greatest of French engravers — Edelinck, Drevet, Wille, Audran, and others.</p><p>RIGGING. See Seamanship.</p><p>RIGHT, Petition of. See Petition, vol. xviii. p. 705.</p><p>RIGHTS, Bill of. On the 13th February 1688-89 the Declaration of Right was delivered by the Lords and Commons to the prince and princess of Orange. In October 1689 the rights claimed by the declaration were enacted with some alterations by the Bill of Rights, 1 Will, and M., sess. 2, c. 2, next to Magna Charta the greatest landmark in the constitutional history of England and the nearest approach to the written constitutions of other countries. The Act (the full name of which is “ An Act declaring the Rights and Liberties of the Subject, and settling the Succession of the Crown ”), after reciting the unconstitutional proceedings of James II., the abdication of that king, the consequent vacancy of the crown, and the summons of the convention parliament, declared, on the part of the Lords and Commons, “ for the vindicating and asserting their ancient rights and liberties—</p><p>“ 1. That the pretended power of suspending of laws or the execution of laws by regal authority without consent of parliament is illegal. 2. That the pretended power of dispensing with laws or the execution of laws by regal authority, as it hath been assumed and exercised of late, is illegal. 3. That the commission for erecting the late court of commissioners for ecclesiastical causes, and all other commissions and courts of like nature, are illegal and pernicious. 4. That levying money for or to the use of the crown, by pretence of prerogative, without grant of parliament, for longer time or in other manner than the same is or shall be granted, is illegal. 5. That it is the right of the subjects to petition the king, and all commitments and prosecutions for such petitioning are illegal. 6. That the raising or keeping a standing army within the kingdom in time of peace, unless it be with consent of parliament, is against law. 7. That the subjects which are Protestants may have arms for their defence suitable to their conditions, and as allowed by law. 8. That elections of members of parliament ought to be free. 9. That the freedom of speech, and debates or proceedings in parliament, ought not to be impeached or questioned in any court or place out of parliament. 10. That excessive bail ought not to be required, nor excessive fines imposed, nor cruel and unusual punishments inflicted. 11. That jurors ought to be duly impanelled and returned, and j urors which pass upon men in trials for high treason ought to be freeholders. 12. That all grants and promises of fines and forfeitures of particular persons before conviction are illegal and void. 13. And that for redress of all grievances, and for the amending, strengthening, and preserving of the laws, parliament ought to be held frequently. And they do claim, demand, and insist upon all and singular the premises, as their undoubted rights and liberties. ”</p><p>The further provisions of the Act were concerned with the settlement of the crown upon the prince and princess of Orange, with the exception of § 12, which negatived the right of dispensation by <hi rend="italic">non obstante</hi>  to or of any statute or any part thereof, unless a dispensation be allowed in the statute itself or by bill or bills to be passed during the then session of parliament. An example of an Act giving a dispensing power is 7 &amp; 8 Will. III., c. 37, by which the crown is empowered to grant licences to hold in mortmain <hi rend="italic">non obstante</hi>  the Mortmain Acts.</p><p>It is to be noticed that the Declaration of Right and the Bill of Rights introduced no new principle into the English constitution. In the words of Lord Macaulay, “ the Declaration of Right, though it made nothing law which had not been law before, contained the germ of every good law which has been passed during more than a century and a half, of every good law which may hereafter in the course of ages be found necessary to promote the public weal, and to satisfy the demands of public opinion” <hi rend="italic">(History of England,</hi>  vol. ii. p. 396). In the United States, the main provisions of the Bill of Rights, so far as they are applicable, have been adopted both in the constitution of the United States and in the State constitutions.</p><p>RIMINI. The city of Rimini is bounded on three sides by water. It faces the Adriatic to the north, has the torrent Aprusa, now called Ausa, on the east, and has the river Marecchia, the Arimnum of the ancients and later known as the Ariminum, on the west. It stands in a fertile plain, which on the southern side soon swells into pleasant slopes backed by the jagged peaks of the Umbrian Apennines. The foremost foothill of the range is the steep crag of Mons Titanus crowned by the towers of San Marino. This oldest and smallest of republics commands a prospect of almost unrivalled beauty over hill and plain—to Ravenna on one side, Pesaro on the other, the mountains of Montefeltro, Rimini and its rivers, and across the Adriatic to the Dalmatian coast.</p><p>Of the foundation of Rimini nothing certain is known. It was first inhabited by the Umbrians, then by the Etruscans for many centuries. In the 4th century B.c. it was invaded by the Senones, who advanced as far as Sinigaglia. Brenn us established himself in Rimini, and marched thence upon Rome, which he destroyed by fire in 390 B.c. After more than a century of dominion the Senones were expelled by the Romans, who founded a military colony in Rimini and made it the seat of the prætor governing the province designated as Ariminumιor Gallia Togata. Owing to its position, Rimini rose to increased importance under its new masters. The Romans reopened the mint formerly established by the Gauls, which had issued the “ æs grave,” the heaviest Italic coin that has been preserved. Rimini was the starting point of the Flaminian Way leading to Rome, and of the Emilian Way to Piacenza. Later, 134 b.c., the Popilian Way leading as far as Venice was made. In 82 b.c. Rimini was withdrawn from the province of Gaul and included in Italy, of which the frontier was now extended from the Esino to the Rubicon, about ten miles from Rimini near Cesena. This added to the city’s importance. We find continual mention of it in the wars of Marius and Sulla, and by the latter it was afterwards sacked. In 49 b.c. Julius Cæsar crossed the Rubicon with the 13th legion, entered Rimini, and harangued his troops in the great square that still bears his name. A pillar marks the spot on which, according to tradition, he delivered his address.@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi>  From Rimini, after having assembled the tribunes of the people and summoned the other legions, he went forth on the great expedition that was to lead to the battle of Pharsalia and ultimately to the foundation of the empire.</p><p>Rimini was highly favoured under Augustus. That emperor restored the Flaminian Way, and the senate decreed the erection in his honour of the famous arch that is still one of the grandest of ancient monuments. It seems that this arch was originally crowned by a statue of Augustus mounted on a triumphal car <hi rend="italic">(quadriga).</hi></p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi> A stone originally stood there, mentioned by 15th-century writers as <hi rend="sup">t</hi> ‘ the big stone<hi rend="italic">{petτoηe),</hi>  on which he (Cæsar) stood to make his speech.” But this stone, <hi rend="italic">vetustate cοllapsum</hi>  was replaced in 1555 by the existing column.</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>