<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>XVIII. to whom it fell to sign the treaty of 1815. A pension of 50,000 francs, voted to him by the two chambers, he bestowed on the public charities of Bordeaux.</p><p>RICHERUS, a chronicler of the 10th century, son of Rodulf, a trusty councillor and captain of Louis IV., studied at Rheims under Gerbert, afterwards Pope Silvester II. His intimacy with this famous man gave him many opportunities of knowing the history of his time, and when Gerbert became archbishop of Rheims he charged Richerus with the task of writing a history of the Gauls. This history in four books begins with Charles the Fat and Eudes, and goes down to the year 995. From 969 onwards Richerus had no earlier history before him, and his work is the chief source for the period when the Capets superseded the Carlovingians. It was first edited in Pertz’s <hi rend="italic">Monumenta Germaniæ,</hi>  vol. iii., and there have since been several separate editions.</p><p>RICHMOND, a town of Surrey, is situated on the south bank of the Thames, here crossed by a stone bridge of five arches, 8∣ miles west of Hyde Park Corner by road, and 9f from the Waterloo station of the South-Western Railway. The town, anciently called <hi rend="italic">Syeηes</hi>  and afterwards <hi rend="italic">Schene</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">Sheen,</hi>  until the name was in 1500 changed to Richmond by command of Henry VII., grew up round the royal manor house, which became a frequent residence of different sovereigns, but of which nothing more than a gateway now remains. Edward I. received the Scotch commissioners at his manor of Sheen in 1300. The palace was rebuilt by Edward III., who died there in 1377. It was frequently resided in by Richard IL, and here his wife Anne of Bohemia died, upon which he cursed the place and “caused it to be thrown down and defaced.” By Henry V. it was, however, rebuilt, and a great tournament was held at it in 1492 by Henry VII., who after its destruction by fire in 1499 restored it and named it Richmond. Henry VIII. gave it to Wolsey to reside in, after the latter presented him with the new palace of Hampton Court. James I. settled it on his son Henry, prince of Wales, who restored and embellished it at great expense. Charles I. added to it the new deer park generally known as Richmond Park, 2253 acres in extent, which is surrounded by a wall 11 miles in length. After the execution of the king, .the parliament presented the park to the citizens of London, who again presented it to Charles II. at the Restoration. Though partly dismantled, the palace was the residence of the queen dowager till 1665, and by J âmes II. it was used as a nursery for the young prince ; but, gradually falling into decay, it was, about 1720, parcelled into tenements. In the old deer park extending northwards from the site of the palace towards Kew an observatory was erected in 1769, occupying the site of a Carthusian convent founded by Henry V., and a dwelling house in which Swift for some time resided. To the south-east of the town, at the entrance to Richmond Park, is Richmond Hill, from which is the famous view of the Thames with the surrounding country to the west. The White Lodge in Richmond Park is usually the residence of some member of the royal family. The town itself is without special interest, and consists chiefiy of one long and irregular street running north and south. The church of St Mary Magdalen is of considerable antiquity, but has been almost entirely rebuilt ; it contains a large number of monuments to celebrated persons. The theatre, first established in 1719, was during his later years leased by Edmund Kean. The town has a Wesleyan theological college founded in 1834, a free public library, and public baths. The population of the urban sanitary district (area 1210 acres) in 1871 was 15,113, and in 1881 it was 19,066.</p><p>RICHMOND, a borough in the North Riding of Yorkshire, is finely situated on the Swale, at the terminus of the Richmond branch of the North-Eastern Railway, 44 miles north-west of York and 15 south-west of Darlington. The interest of the town centres in the castle, said to have been founded by Alan Rufus, son of Hoel, count of Bretagne, who is also said to have rebuilt the town on his obtaining the estates of the Saxon Earl Edwin, embracing two hundred manors of Richmond and extending over nearly a third of the North Riding. When Henry VII. came to the throne these possessions reverted to the crown. Henry VIII. gave it to his son Henry by a daughter of Sir John Blount, and Charles II. bestowed the title of duke of Richmond on his son by the duchess of Portsmouth. The castle is situated on a perpendicular rock rising about 100 feet above the Swale, and from its great strength was considered inaccessible. Originally it covered an area of 5 acres, but the only portions of it now remaining are the Norman keep, with pinnacled tower and walls 100 feet high by 11 feet thick, and some other smaller towers. A portion of it is now occupied by the North York Rifles militia. The old church of St Mary, chiefly in the Gothic style, though with some traces of Norman, has been restored under the direction of Sir Gilbert Scott. For the free grammar school founded by Elizabeth a Gothic building was erected in 1850, in memory of the Rev. James Tate, a former master. The tower of the Franciscan abbey founded in 1258 still remains. The chief modern buildings are the town-hall, the masonic hall, and the workmen’s hall. The principal trade is in agricultural produce, but there are a paper mill and an iron and brass foundry. The town received its first charter from Elizabeth. Under the Municipal Corporations Act it is governed by a mayor, four aldermen, and tw<hi rend="sup">r</hi>elve councillors. Up to 1885, when it ceased to be separately represented, Richmond was a parliamentary borough, returning two members till 1868, and one after that date. The population of the municipal borough (area 2520 acres) in 1871 was 4443, and in 1881 it was 4502.</p><p>RICHMOND, a city of the United States, the county seat of Wayne county, Indiana, is situated in a fine agricultural region on the east branch of the White Water River (a sub-tributary of the Ohio), 68 miles east of Indianapolis. It is an important railway junction, has a city park 135 acres in extent, manufactures machinery, agricultural implements, &amp;c., and contains a public library (15,000 volumes), a museum, two theatres, and two educational institutions (Earlham College, 1859) belonging to the Society of Friends, which is strongly represented in the city. The population was 9445 in 1870, and 12,742 in 1880. The city obtained its charter in 1845.</p><p>RICHMOND, a city of the United States, the capital of Virginia, is situated in Henrico county, on the north side of the James River, at the point where the lower falls (100 feet in 6 miles) mark the limit of the tide ascending from Chesapeake Bay. On the other side of the river, and in the county of Chesterfield, but connected with Richmond by bridges, is Manchester. By rail the city is 116 miles south-south-west of Washington. At mean high tides vessels drawing 14 feet of water can come up to Rocketts, as the lower district is called. The town proper occupies a group of hills—Gamble’s Hill, Shockoe Hill, Church Hill, &amp;c.—and looks down over the river, from which it is separated by a strip of flat ground. Main Street is a typical street after the old Southern style, the large portion burned in 1865 having been rebuilt in keeping with the remnant that escaped. By far the most conspicuous edifice in the city is the Capitol, on the summit of Shockoe Hill, designed by Thomas Jefferson, after the Maison Carrée of Nîmes. Beneath the dome of</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>