<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>chief sources,—the use of tawdry or ungainly compounds (διπλά <hi rend="italic">ονόματα),</hi>  the use of rare or obsolete words (γλώτται), and infelicity of epithet or metaphor.</p><p>A simile <hi rend="italic">(εlκc!&gt;v)</hi>  is a metaphor with an explanation (λόγο?): <hi rend="italic">e.g., </hi>in speaking of Achilles, “ he sprang on them like a lion ” is simile ; “ the lion sprang on them ” is metaphor. Simile is less available than metaphor for prose, being more poetical. The “ proportional ” metaphor mentioned here requires a passing comment. Aristotle used the term “ metaphor ” <hi rend="italic">(μεταφορά)</hi>  in a larger sense than ours. He meant by it “ any transference of a word to a sense different from its proper sense.” Thus he can distinguish <hi rend="italic">(Poet.,</hi>  c. 21) four classes of metaphor:—(1) “from genus to species,” as when “vessel” means “ship”; (2) from species to genus, as when “the lilies of the field” stand for “flowers” generally. These two kinds are not what we call “metaphors,” but are examples of the figure which was afterwards named “ synecdoche.” Aristotle’s third class of metaphor is (3) “from species to species,” under which head come almost all familiar metaphors, as to “ scent a plot,”—the generic notion, “ find out,” being common to the special terms, “scent” and “detect”; (4) then lastly there is the “proportional” metaphor (⅞ άνάλογον), when A is not simply compared with B (on the strength of something obviously common to both), but A’s relation to C is compared with B’s relation to D. To call old age “ the evening of life ” implies that old age is to life as the evening to the day. Obviously a “ proportion ” of this kind is implicit in the metaphors of Aristotle’s third class ; but in the fourth class proportion is expressly indicated by the mention of the second term (“life” in our example).</p><p>The first four chapters having thus dealt with expression in the narrower sense of diction (λε<hi rend="sup">,</hi>ξts proper), Aristotle devotes the next eight (iii. 5-12) to composition, which would be properly called <hi rend="italic">σvvθεσις. -</hi>  After remarks on the first requisites—grammatical correctness, and purity of idiom (τδ eλλτ,∙vif∈ιv)—we have some hints on “dignity” of style (uγκos). “ Propriety” (&lt;rδ <hi rend="italic">πpεποv)</hi>  is defined as depending chiefly on three qualities :—(1) expression of the feelings which it is desired to move in the hearer ; (2) fitness to the character and position of the speaker ; and (3) congruity with the level of the subject. A certain “rhythm” <hi rend="italic">(ρυθμός),</hi>  or harmonious movement, should be sought in prose ; but this must not be so precise as to give the effect of metre. The elements of rhythm are “times,” i.e., in writing, long or short syllables, the short syllable being the unit. Here, following the early writers on music (comp. Plato, <hi rend="italic">Rep.,</hi>  400 B), Aristotle recognizes three “rhythms” : (1) the</p><p>“ heroic ” or dactylic,---which is in the ratio of equality,</p><p>since — =    or 1 <hi rend="sup">;</hi>1 j (2) the iambic or trochaic (■—■— or</p><p>— —∙ ), which has the ratio of 2 to 1 ; (3) the pæonic, — which has the ratio of 3 : 2. Of these, the heroic is too grand for prose ; the iambic is too commonplace, being the very cadence of ordinary talk <hi rend="italic">(αυτή εστιv ή λεξις των πολλών)</hi>  ; the trochee is too comic. The pæon remains. It is the best rhythm for prose, since it will not, by itself, produce a metrical effect (μάλλον λαvθdv∈t). The “first” pæon (-— — is most suitable to the beginning of sentences, the “ fourth ” pæon ( ———— ) to the close. Rhythm having been attained, a framework is supplied by the period (πepioδos). A “compact” or periodic style <hi rend="italic">(κατεστραμμένη λεξtς)</hi>  is so called in contrast with that “running” style <hi rend="italic">(εipομεvη λεξις)</hi>  which simply strings clause to clause, “ having no necessary end until the thought is finished,” and is unpleasing because it is unlimited ; “for all men wish to descry the end.” The periodic style pleases for the opposite reason, because the nearer always fancies that he has grasped something and has got something defined. The period may consist of several parts or members <hi rend="italic">(κωλa),</hi>  or it may be “simple,” forming a unit <hi rend="italic">(αφελής, μοvοκωKοs).</hi>  The rhetorical use of antithesis is then noticed in its application to the period. Two kindred figures are also mentioned,—<hi rend="italic">parisosis,</hi>  a parallelism of structure between clauses of equal length, —and <hi rend="italic">paromoiosis,</hi>  a resemblance in sound, when the last (or first) word of one clause has an echo, as it were, in the same place of the next clause.</p><p>Two chapters (10, 11) are now given to the sources of vivacity in speaking. Those “smart sayings” (τα α&lt;rτ∈Γα) which win applause “ must be invented by the clever or practised man ; the business of this treatise is to point out their use.” They come chiefly from (1) metaphor, (2) antithesis, and (3) vividness—ι,e., placing the thing described “before the eyes of the hearer” (τδ <hi rend="italic">προ ομμάτων</hi>  πoιe7v). This is called by Aristotle <hi rend="italic">εvεpyειa,</hi>  “actuality” (which must be carefully distinguished from <hi rend="italic">εv0pyειa,</hi>  another term for “ vividness ”), since things are represented not merely in their potentiality (δυvαμιs), but as living and moving. One of the most effective kinds of point (says Aristotle) is “a metaphor with a surprise,” i.e., with the disclosure of a likeness not perceived before, the source of the pleasure being the same as in riddles.</p><p>The whole subject of expression is concluded by a chapter on the general types of style, in their relation to the three branches of rhetoric (ch. 12). There is a literary style <hi rend="italic">(ypaφικ⅛ λdξις)</hi>  and a style suited to oral contest or debate <hi rend="italic">(αγωνιστική).</hi>  The literary style is that which admits of the highest finish <hi rend="italic">(ακριβέστατη),</hi>  and is best suited to the epideictic branch of rhetoric, since the latter is properly addressed to readers. The other, or “agonistic,” style is best adapted to delivery <hi rend="italic">(ΰποκριτικωτάτη).</hi>  It is so mainly through two things—adaptation to the character of speaker and hearer, and skilful appeals to feeling. Forensic and deliberative rhetoric both use it ; but the forensic branch admits of higher finish, and so far approximates to the literary style. Deliberative rhetoric, on the other hand, is like drawing in light and shade (without colours), <hi rend="italic">σκιαγραφία—</hi>like scene-painting, we should rather say, ι.e., it is meant to produce its effects at a distance, and will not bear looking at too closely.</p><p>From expression we now pass to the other subject announced at the opening of the third book, arrangement (ταξjs), which occupies the last seven chapters (13-19). The received system, which had been popularized, if not originated, by Isocrates, recognised four divisions of a speech : (1) exordium (or proem), <hi rend="italic">πpοοiμιοv</hi>  ; (2) narrative, <hi rend="italic">διήγησις</hi>  ; (3) proof, <hi rend="italic">πiστεις ;</hi>  (4) peroration, <hi rend="italic">επίλογος. </hi>Aristotle adopts this fourfold partition as his basis,—with the preliminary remark, however, that only two elements are necessarily present in every case, viz., “statement” of one’s subject, <hi rend="italic">πp6θεσιs,</hi>  and “argument” in its support, <hi rend="italic">πiστεις.</hi>  He then takes the four divisions in order. The contents of the proem usually come under one of two heads—(1) exciting or allaying prejudice ; (2) amplifying or detracting. In epideictic rhetoric the connexion of proem with sequel may be comparatively loose ; it is like a flute-player’s prelude <hi rend="italic">(προαύλιον),</hi>  which he deftly links on to the keynote <hi rend="italic">(ενδόσιμου)</hi>  of his principal theme. The forensic proem, on the other hand, may be likened to the prologue of an epic or a tragedy (ch. 14, 15). Narrative is least needed in deliberative speaking, since this deals chiefly with the future. In forensic narrative, the object must be to bring out clearly the issues on which accuser or accused relies, with an effective colouring of ethos and pathos. In the epideictic branch, the narrative should not form a continuous whole, but should be divided and varied by comments (ch. 16). The rhetorician’s proofs <hi rend="italic">(πιστειs)</hi>  will, in the forensic branch, be relevant to one of four issues :—(1) fact : was the alleged act done, or not ? (2) damage : if done, was it hurtful ? (3) criminality : if hurtful, was the hurt justifiable ? (4) quantity or degree. Aristotle’s four “issues ” <hi rend="italic">(αμφισβητήσεις)</hi>  here correspond with the <hi rend="italic">στάσεις,</hi>  “positions” or “questions,” usually three, of later legists and rhetoricians: (1) <hi rend="italic">στάσις στοχαστική, status eonjeeturalis,</hi>  the question of fact; (2) <hi rend="italic">στάσις όρική, statics definitivus, nomen,</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">finitio,</hi>  the question of legal definition ; (3) <hi rend="italic">στάσις ποιότητος status qualitatis</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">juridieialis,</hi>  the question of justice or injustice. Thus Cicero says, “res (controversiam facit) aut de vero (1), aut de recto (3), aut de nomine” (2), <hi rend="italic">Orat.,</hi>  xxxiv. 121. In deliberative rhetoric, the four “issues” can be applied to the future, since, if a speaker anticipates certain results from a course of a policy, his adversary can deny their (1) probability, (2) expediency, (3) justice, or (4) importance. The enthymeme is most useful in the deliberative branch, as the “example,” or rhetorical induction, is most useful in the forensic. The “ethical” proof from the speaker’s indicated character is always a most important adjunct to the logical proof (ch. 17). A chapter is now given to one special resource by which a proof can often be enforced, viz., interrogation of the adversary <hi rend="italic">(ερωτησιs),</hi>  which has usually one of two objects—</p><p>(1)    <hi rend="italic">reductio ad absurdum,</hi>  or (2) to entrap him into a fatal admission (ch. 18). The last chapter of the book, and of the treatise, deals with the peroration or “epilogue” <hi rend="italic">(επίλογος).</hi>  This aims usually at one of four things :—(1) to conciliate the hearers ;</p><p>(2)    to magnify or lower the importance of topics already treated ;</p><p>(3)    to excite emotion in the hearers ; (4) to refresh their memories by a short recapitulation. Remarking that asyndeton gives force to the close of an epilogue, Aristotle ends his rhetoric with the last words (not quite accurately quoted) of the great speech in which Lysias denounced Eratosthenes—<hi rend="italic">παΰσομαι κατήγορων. άκηκόατε, εωράκατε, πεπόνθατε, εχετε, δικάζετε.</hi></p><p>Aristotle’s <hi rend="italic">Rhetoric</hi>  is incomparably the most scientific work which exists on the subject. It may also be regarded as having determined the main lines on which the subject was treated by nearly all subsequent writers. The extant treatise on rhetoric entitled <hi rend="italic">Wgτopuκp</hi>  7rpos *Aλ∈'ξαvδpov was undoubtedly by Anaximenes of Lampsacus, and was probably composed about 340-330 b.c., a few years before Aristotle’s work. The introductory letter prefixed to it is a late forgery. If the treatise of Anaximenes is compared with that of Aristotle the distinctive place of the latter in this field becomes clearer. Anaximenes, who knew the treatise of Isocrates, and could profit by all the preceding Greek “arts,” is, for us, the sole representative of <hi rend="italic">technical </hi>rhetoric before Aristotle, and probably represents it at its best. We miss the intellectual power, the grasp of principles, and the subtle discrimination which belong to</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>