<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="chi.12945678-1526170221_Page_0019.jpf" type="entry" xml:id="eb07-21-s06-0008-01" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SUSSEX</label>,
an English maritime county, bounded on the east by Kent, on the north by that county and Surrey, on ; the west by Hampshire, and on the south by the British Channel. It is of an oblong shape, being about seventy miles in length from east to west, and nowhere more than twenty-six miles in breadth from north to south. Its area is 1463 square miles, or 936,320 statute acres. It is divided into six portions, provincially called <hi rend="italic">rapes,</hi> which are again divided into sixty-five hundreds, and contain 313 parishes. The greater part of the county is within the diocese of Chichester ; but the deaneries of Pagham and South Malling, and All-Saints in Chichester, form a part of the peculiar of the archbishop of Canterbury.</p><p>The population of this county at the four decennial periods of enumeration amounted, in 1801 to 59,311, in 1811 to 190,083, in 1821 to 233,019, and in 1831 to 272,800.</p><p>At the last period the distribution of the inhabitants was, Occupiers of land employing labourers 3,160</p><p>Occupiers not employing labourers 1,330</p><p>Labourers employed in agriculture 26,125</p><p>Labourers employed in manufactures 109</p><p>Labourers in retail trade and handicraft. 19,208</p><p>Capitalists, bankers, &amp;c 3,094</p><p>Labourers not agricultural 8,151<pb facs="chi.12945678-1526170221_Page_0021.jpf" xml:id="eb07-21-s06-0010"/>
Description of Kent and Sussex ; Gilpin’s Observations ; Pennant’s Journey from London to the Isle of Wight ; Beauties of England and Wales.</p></div></body></text></TEI>