<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T17:36:44Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>dations of water, from the corruption of the air, or from the falling of the superincumbent masses under which the work is carried on ; 2d, with meteorology, from the influence of the atmosphere on the soil ; from the variation of the di mate, according to the altitude, and the varieties of the vegetable tribes which are found at different heights, all which are important facts in the statistics of every country ; and, 3d, with zoology, from the necessity of ascertaining the different breeds of the domestic animals, and their qualities, and how far they can be made subservient to the purposes of man. How curious it is to contemplate the varieties of these animals in different climates and countries : how in Asia the elephant, whose gigantic strength could crush its masters in the dust, is yet, by the ingenuity of man, reduced to one of the humblest of his drudges ; the camel in like manner to be a pattern of patient service; and the swift dromedary, and the wild ass, with its indomitable spirit, bro ken to the yoke, though in the eastern countries still retaining its native fire; while in Europe man depends upon an entirely different class of animals, whose properties are of the highest importance in reference to the various duties to which they are appointed, and form, therefore, the proper subject of statistical inquiries, to which zoology contributes its aid.</p><p>The moral and religious condition of the people is a subject of still greater importance, which cannot be under stood without knowing the nature and extent of the religious establishments and seminaries of education ; the funds that are appropriated for these purposes, and their efficiency for their proposed ends ; from what source they are derived ; whether they are large or small ; the number of churches and schools, as compared with the population ; the nature of the different seminaries ; what are the sciences taught ; the pay of the teachers, civil as well as religious ; the different sects ; the number of each ; the proportion of those teachers who are paid by the state to those who depend on the voluntary contributions of their flocks. All these facts are necessary to be known in order to decide on the great questions which will ever agitate the world on the subject of religion, namely, whether any particular form ought to be encouraged by the state ; whether it is not the better policy to leave religion to its own native and divine strength ; to give protection to all, but encouragement to none ; a fair field and no favour ; whether religion is more effectually promoted by a largely endowed ministry, or by one more humble and industrious, depending for their subsistence on the good will of their people ; whether large pay may not be a source of corruption and a bribe to indolence ; or whether such a class of luxurious priests may not be necessary to propagate religion among the rich. It is by inquiries into facts such as we have enumerated that these important questions can be best eluci dated ; and it is to these objects, therefore, of which we have given an imperfect enumeration, that the statistical in quirer ought to direct his attention, with a view of clearing away all obstructions from the paths of science.</p><p>The study of statistics has only been of late years systematically prosecuted. It makes no part of the early history of nations. The glare of battles, and of political commotions which fix the destiny of nations, alone attracts the no tice of the historian ; and for these, the more precious details of domestic history are thrown into the shade, and finally lost. It is only, therefore, that portion of human affairs, which, though more striking, is the least valuable, that his tory embalms, while it casts aside as useless those import ant facts which illustrate the progress of society, in arts, in literature, and in science; in wealth also, in population, and in commerce, by new and more ingenious modes of indus try, which shew the changes of manners that follow increased wealth, the state of the public revenue, with various other topics equally interesting to the statesman as well as the</p><p>philosopher. The ancient history of Greece and Rome is eminently deficient in those details. The writers of those times appear to be extremely loose in their facts ; and they very seldom refer to the authority of any original document. In the ancient republics of Greece and Rome, every thing was subservient to war ; and the accounts that were from time to time taken of the male population, were with a view to ascertain the military strength of the state. But little reliance can even be placed on these accounts. The ancient historians were rather intent on general description, often vigorous and eloquent, than in any accurate appeal to facts. There was no accurate census of the Ro man empire after it had attained to the height of its power ; and the Roman historian, admitting that the number of subjects cannot now be fixed “ with such a degree of accuracy as the importance of the object would deserve,” is reduced to little better than conjecture, when he estimates the number of persons under the imperial sway at 120 millions ; “ a degree of populousness,” he adds, “ which possibly exceeds that of modern Europe ;’ the vague manner of his expres sion truly intimating the imperfect data with which he was furnished. In other departments the statistics of Rome are still more deficient in facts. The relative proportions of births, deaths, and marriages, are never so much as pointed at in any historical work ; and the accounts that remain of the state of commerce and manufactures are meagre in the extreme. A list is no doubt given of articles of luxury im ported into Rome, and of the trade to India and Arabia ; in which Pliny complains of the unfavourable exchange, a modern complaint, also, in this country, and of the drain of gold which it occasioned, there being no other equivalent with which the rare luxuries of those countries could be purchased. (See the article <hi rend="smallcaps">κrαβια.)</hi> But we have no account of the state of wages, of the value of the exports or imports, nor any very accurate account of the currency, or of the public revenue. The modern historians of Rome, gleaning a few scattered facts which shed an incidental light, from the works of the classical writers, are reduced, by the help of their own conjectures, to form them into a specious, but often doubtful hypothesis. What a meagre account, accordingly, does the illustrious Gibbon, not less noted for eloquence and fancy, than for accurate research, give of the revenues of Rome. He begins with lamenting the want of any authentic document. “ History,” he observes, “ has ne ver perhaps suffered a greater or more irreparable injury than in the loss of the curious register bequeathed by Augustus to the senate, in which that experienced prince so accurately balanced the revenues and expenses of the Roman empire.” And when groping his way, by the imperfect light which history supplies, he estimates that 20,000 pounds weight of gold were annually received from the provinces of Austria, Gallicia, and Lusitania, he adds, “ we want both leisure and materials to pursue this curious inquiry through the many potent states that were annihilated in the Roman empire.” After stating the incidental circumstance of Augustus having once received a petition from the inhabitants of Gyarus, a solitary and desolate isle, for a remission of their annual duties, which only amounted in value to L.5 sterling, and naturally inferring, if such severe attention was directed to the abodes of sterility, that much larger contributions would be levied in the seats of population and of wealth, he adds, “ from the faint glimmerings of such doubtful and scattered lights, we should be inclined to believe, that with every fair allowance of times and circumstances, the general income of the Roman provinces could seldom amount to less than L. 15,000,000 or L.20,000,000  of our money.” Such is all the information which the most diligent research could collect from any extant record concerning the revenues of Rome. What a contrast does this present to the enlighten ed science of modern times, and to the more accurate documents prepared by authority in the great states of Europe,</p></body></text></TEI>