<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T17:34:27Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>and solder of three. It is the mixture of copper in the solder that makes raised plate come always cheaper than flat.</p><p>SOLDIER, a military man enlisted to serve a prince or state in consideration of a certain daily pay. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Αrμυ.</hi></p><p>SOLDIN, a town of the government of Frankfurt on the Oder in Prussia. It is the capital of a circle of the same name, which extends over 404 square miles, and contains 26,600 inhabitants. The town, which is near the Soldin lake, is surrounded with walls, and contains 434 houses, with 2860 inhabitants.</p><p>SOLECISM in <hi rend="italic">Grammar,</hi> a false manner of speak- ing, contrary to the rules of grammar, either in respect of declension, conjugation, or syntax. The word is Greek,  σoλoικισμὸς, derived from the <hi rend="italic">Soli,</hi> a people of Attica, who being transplanted to Cilicia, lost the purity of their ancient tongue, and became ridiculous to the Athenians for the improprieties into which they fell.</p><p>SOLEURE. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Solothurn.</hi></p><p>SOLFA, <hi rend="italic">(Ital.)</hi> a musical exercise for the voice when learning to sing, in which the syllables <hi rend="italic">do, re, mi,fα, sol, la, si,</hi> are applied to their respective notes in the exercise.</p><p>SOLFAING, (Fr. <hi rend="italic">Solfler,</hi> Ital. <hi rend="italic">Sοlfeggiare,)</hi> means the performance of such an exercise ; and also the singing of a piece of music at sight with these syllables. On this subject consult the large work on singing, published for the use of the French Conservatory of Music.</p><p>SOLFATARA, a lake in the Campagna of Rome, near to Tivoli. It is of small extent, but is remarkable for containing several floating islets formed of matted sedge and herbage, with a soil of dust and sand blown from the adjacent country, and cemented by the bitumen and sulphur with which the water of the lake is impregnated. Some of these islands are more than forty feet long, and will bear five or six persons, who, by means of a pole, may move to different parts of the lake. From this lake there issues a whitish stream, emitting a sulphureous vapour, until it reaches the small river Teverone, which discharges itself into the Tiber. The water of that rivulet is of a petrifying quality, which increases in strength the farther it flows from the lake. Fish are only to be found in the Teverone before it receives this impure stream.</p><p>SOLFATERRA, a mountain of Italy in the kingdom of Naples and Terra di Lavorro. This mountain appears evi- dently to have been a volcano in ancient times; and the soil is yet so hot, that the workmen employed there in making alum need nothing else besides the heat of the ground for evaporating their liquids.</p><p>SOLICITOR, a person employed to take care of and manage suits depending in the courts of law or equity. There is also a great officer of the law, next to the attorney-general, who is styled the king or queen’s solicitor-general ; who holds his office by patent during the sovereign’s pleasure, assists the attorney in managing the law business of the crown, and has fees for pleading, besides other fees arising by patents, &amp;c. He attends on the privy-council ; and the attorney-general and he were anciently reckoned among the officers of the Exchequer. They have their audience, and come within the bar in all the courts.</p><p>SOLID, in <hi rend="italic">Philosophy,</hi> a bo&lt;ly whose parts are so firmly connected together, as not easily to give way or slip from each other; in which sense <hi rend="italic">solid</hi> stands opposed to <hi rend="italic">fluid. </hi>Geometricians define a solid to be the third species of magnitude, or that which has three dimensions, viz. length, breadth, and thickness or depth. Solids are commonly di- vided into regular and irregular. The regular solids are those terminated by regular and equal planes, and are only five in number, vie. the tetrahedron, which consists of four equal triangles; the cube or hexahedron, of six equal squares; the octahedron, of eight equal triangles; the dodecahedron, of twelve; and the icosahedron, of twenty equal triangles. The irregular solids are almost infinite, comprehending all such as do not come under the definition of regular solids;</p><p>as the sphere, cylinder, cone, parallelogram, prism, parallelopiped, &amp;c.</p><p>SOLIDITY, that property of matter, or body, by which it excludes all other bodies from the place which itself possesses ; and as it would be absurd to suppose that two bodies could possess one and the same place at the same time, it follows, that the softest bodies are equally solid with the hardest.</p><p>Among geometricians, the solidity of a body denotes the quantity or space contained in it, and is called also its solid content. The solidity of a cube, prism, cylinder, or paral- lelopiped is had by multiplying its basis into its height. The solidity of a pyramid or cone is had by multiplying either the whole base into a third part of the height, or the whole height into a third part of the base.</p><p>SOLILOQUY, a reasoning or discourse which a man holds with himself ; or, more properly, according to one ac- count, it is a discourse by way of answer to a question which a man proposes to himself.</p><p>SOLIMAN II. emperor of the Turks, surnamed the <hi rend="italic">Magnificent,</hi> was the only son of Selim I., whom he succeeded in 1520. He was educated in a manner very differ- ent from the Ottoman princes in general ; for he was in- structed in the maxims of politics and the secrets of go- vernment. He began his reign by restoring those persons their possessions whom his father had unjustly plundered. He re-established the authority of the tribunals, which was almost annihilated, and bestowed the government of pro- vinces upon none but persons of wealth and probity. “ I would have my viceroys,” he used to say, “ resemble those rivers that fertilize the field through which they pass, not those torrents which sweep every thing before them.” After concluding a truce with Ishmael Sophy of Persia, and subduing Gozeli Bey, who had raised a rebellion in Syria, he turned his arms against Europe. Belgrade was taken in 1522, and Rhodes fell into his hands the year following, af- ter an obstinate and enthusiastic defence. In 1526 he defeated and slew the king of Hungary in the famous battle of Mohatz. Three years afterwards he conquered Buda, and immediately laid siege to Vienna ; but after continuing twenty days before that city, and assaulting it twenty times, he was obliged to retreat with the loss of 80,000 men. Some time after he was defeated by the Persians, and disappointed in his hopes of taking Malta. He succeeded, however, in dispossessing the Genoese of Chio, an island which had belonged to that republic for more than two hundred years. He died at the age of seventy-six, while he was besieging Sigeth, a town in Hungary, on the 30th August 1566.</p><p>SOLINGEN, a town of the Prussian government of Cleves, the capital of a circle of the same name. It has been long celebrated for the excellent temper of the sword blades and other cutting instruments fabricated in the town and district. The circle is small, including only forty-two square miles, but it contains 28,500 inhabitants, of whom about four thousand reside within the town. Lat. 51.12.31. Long. 7. 2. 20. E.</p><p>SOLIS, <hi rend="smallcaps">Αντονιο de</hi> a Spanish writer, of an ancient and illustrious family, was born at Placentia, in Old Castile, on the 18th of July 1610. He was intended for the law ; but his inclination toward poetry prevailed, and he culti- vated it with great success. Philip IV. of Spain made him one of his secretaries ; and after the king’s death, the queen-regent appointed him historiographer of the Indies, a place of great profit and honour. His history of the conquest of Mexico, shows that she could not have named a fitter person. “ Historia de la Conquista de Mexico." Madrid, 1684, fol. He is better known by this history, than by his poetry and dramatic writings, though in these he was also distinguished. At the age of fifty-six he took orders. He died at Madrid on the 19th of April 1686.</p></body></text></TEI>