<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T17:35:44Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>astonishing experiments, from which a suspicion arose, that these animals must have a new sense, as it appeared to Spallanzani that the other known senses could not compen sate for the want of sight ; but he was afterwards inclined to think, in consequence of Professor Jurin’s experiments on the organ of hearing in bats, that in this particular in stance the sense of hearing might possibly supply the want of sight.</p><p>He published many other works, which we cannot here enumerate.@@' He had nearly finished an account of his voyage to Constantinople, and had collected many valuable materials for a history of the sea, when his life and labours were brought to a termination. He was seized with a retention of urine, on the 30th of February 1799, and next morning was so far deprived of the use of his faculties, that he only enjoyed a sound mind during very short intervals. Tourdes and Scarpa did every thing to save him, which could be produced by the joint exertions of genius, expe rience, and friendship, but in vain. He died on the twelfth of the same month, after having completed the seventieth year of his age. His works have been translated into a great variety of languages, and he was enrolled as a member of many foreign academies.</p><p>SPALMADORI, a small island situated between the continent of Asia Minor and the island of Scio. Long. 26. 7. E. Lat. 38. 36. N.</p><p>SPAN, a measure taken from the space between the thumb and the tip of the little finger when both are stretched out The span is estimated at three hands breadths, or nine inches.</p><p>SPANDAU, a town of Prussia, in the government of Potsdam. It is a strongly fortified place, and is the chief arsenal of the kingdom. It stands on a peninsula, formed by the junction of the river Spree with the Havel. There are manufactures of all descriptions of arms, for the use of the government, and some private establishments for making silk goods, together with several breweries and distilleries. In the fortress is the state-prison ; and there are institutions for the punishment of offenders, by keeping them to hard labour. The town contains 540 houses, with 6750 inhabitants. Lat. 53. 33.7. Long. 13. 36. 40. E.</p><p>SPANDRELL, the solid work on each haunch of an arch, to keep it from spreading.</p><p>SPANHEIM, <hi rend="smallcaps">Ezekiel,</hi> a very learned writer, was bom at Geneva on the 7th of December 1629. His father, Frederic Spanheim, a distinguished theologian, was successively professor of divinity at Geneva and Leyden. The son accompanied him to the latter university, and there distinguished himself by his proficiency in solid learning. His early reputation procured him the professorship of eloquence at Geneva. He took possession of this chair in 1651 ; but he only retained it for a few months, the elector palatine Charles Louis having appointed him tutor to his only son. This task he discharged to the entire satisfaction of the elector, by whom he was also employed in divers negociations at foreign courts. In 1677 he entered into the service of the elector of Brandenburg, who in 1680 sent him as envoy extraordinary to the court of France, and soon after made him a minister of state. After the peace of Ryswyck, be was again sent on an embassy to France, where he continued from the year 1697 to 1702. The elector of Brandenburg having during that interval assumed the title of king of Prussia, conferred on him the title and dignity of a baron. In 1702 he left France, and was sent as ambassador to England, which he had previously visited on more than one occasion. He died in London on the 7th of November 1710, at the age of eighty-one. It is surprising, that in discharging the duties of a public minister with so</p><p>much exactness, and amidst so many different journeys, he could find sufficient time to write the various books which he published. It may be said of him, that he acquitted himself in his negociations like a person who had nothing else in his thoughts ; and that he wrote like a man who had spent his whole time in his study. His works display a very pro found and variegated erudition. The most elaborate of them is entitled, “ Dissertationes de Praestantia et Usu Numismatum antiquorum,” first printed at Rome in quarto in the year 1664. The best edition, extending to two volumes folio, was printed at London in 1706—17. Another valuable work is his “ Orbis Romanus,” of which the best edition is that of London, 1704, 4to. He translated the Cæsars of Julian into French, and illustrated them with annotations. He likewise contributed notes on Aristophanes, Callimachus, and some other Greek writers, of whom he did not himself publish editions.</p><p>SPAR, in <hi rend="italic">Mineralogy,</hi> a name given chiefly to some of the crystallized combinations of lime, as the carbonate and the fluate ; the former being called simply lime spar, the latter fluor spar, or Derbyshire spar, from the name of the place where it is found in greatest abundance.</p><p>SPARTA, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Lacedæmon,</hi> the capital of the country of Laconia in Greece, an ancient and most renowned state, the inhabitants of which have been in all ages celebrated for the singularity of their laws and character. The his tory of Sparta for many ages is entirely fabulous ; and the authentic accounts commence only with the celebrated lawgiver Lycurgus, who flourished about 870 <hi rend="smallcaps">b. c.</hi></p><p>After his death, the first important transaction which we find mentioned in the Spartan history is the Messenian war, which commenced in the year 752 <hi rend="smallcaps">b. c.,</hi> and ended in the total reduction of the Messenian territory. During this period, according to some authors, a great change took place in the government of Sparta. This was the creation of the ephori, which is ascribed to one of the kings named Theopompus. Perceiving that there was a necessity for leaving magistrates to execute the laws, when the kings were obliged to be in the field, he appointed the magistrates above mentioned, who afterwards made so great a figure in the state. One great privilege of the ephori was, that they did not, like all other magistrates, rise up at the presence of the kings : another was, that if the kings offended against the laws, the ephori took cognizance of the offence, and inflicted a suitable punishment. From the first election of the ephori the year was denominated, as at Athens from the first election of the archons.</p><p>The conquest of Messenia gave Sparta the superiority over the rest of the states, excepting only that of Athens, which for a long time continued to be a very troublesome rival ; but the contests between these two rival states have been so fully related under the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Attica,</hi> that no thing more is requisite to be added in this place. In the time of the Persian war, Leonidas as the Spartan king, distinguished himself an such a manner, as to become the ad miration not only of that but of every succeeding age. It being resolved in a general council to defend the straits of Thermopylae against the Persians, 7000 foot were put un der the command of Leonidas ; of whom, however, only 200 were Spartans. Leonidas did not think it practicable to defend the pass against such multitudes as the Persian king commanded ; and therefore privately told his friends, that his design was to devote himself to death for his coun try. Xerxes advancing near the straits, was strangely surprised to find that the Greeks were resolved to dispute his passage ; for he had always flattered himself, that on his approach they would betake themselves to flight, and not attempt to oppose his innumerable forces. Still however</p><p><hi rend="superscript">@@@,</hi> Biographie Universelle, tom. xliii. p. 246, where a catalogue of Spallanzani's works may be found.</p></body></text></TEI>