<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T17:36:38Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>broke Hall. At a very early age, he published “ Aelian’s Various Histories, translated into English.” Lond. 1665, 8vo.</p><p>STANNARIES, the mines and works where tin is dug and purified ; as in Cornwall, Devonshire, &amp;c.</p><p>STANNARY Courts, in Devonshire and Cornwall, for the administration of justice among the tinners. They are held before the lord-warden and his substitutes, by virtue of a privilege granted to the workers in the tin mines there, to sue and be sued only in their own courts, that they may not be drawn from their business, which is highly profitable to the public, by attending their lawsuits in other courts.</p><p>STANOVOI, a chain of mountains in Astatic Russia, forming a part of the great northern chain which crosses the breadth of that continent. It is of considerable height, and continues uninterrupted, though with some diminution of magnitude, to Cape Tchontchi, at the northeastern <hi rend="italic">extremity of</hi> Asia ; and the Aleutian and Fox Islands may be considered as in some degree a continuation of it. This chain turns to the north near the source of the Aldane, whence it runs parallel to the eastern sea or gulf of Ok hotsk, a narrow plain only intervening. Granite and porphyry are the chief materials of which these mountains con sist, though there are some of green jasper.</p><p>STANSTEAD, a town in the hundred of Braughen, and county of Hertford, sixteen miles from London. It stands in a valley near the river Lea, two miles from Hoddesdon. ln this parish is the Ryehouse, remarkable for the suppos ed plot in the reign of Charles the Second, for the assassination of that monarch. The population was, in 1801, 861 ; in 1811, 832; in 1821, 950; and in 1831, 966.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Stanstead-Mountfitchet,</hi> a small town in the county of Essex and hundred of Uttlesford, thirty-four miles from London. It derives its name from an ancient castle, built on an artificial mount about a quarter of a mile from the church, some relics of which are still visible. The hamlet of Bentfield is comprehended in the parish, and their united population was, in 1801, 1285; in 1811, 1334; in 1821, 1518; and in 1831, 1560.</p><p>STANZA, in <hi rend="italic">Poetry.,</hi> a number of lines regularly ad justed to each other; so much of a poem as contains every variation of measure or relation of rhyme used in that poem.</p><p>STAPLE primarily signifies a public place or market, whither merchants, &amp;c. are obliged to bring their goods to be bought by the people. The merchants of England were formerly obliged to carry their wool, cloth, lead, and other like staple commodities of this realm, in order to expose them by wholesale ; and these staples were appointed to be constantly kept at York, Lincoln, Newcastle upon-Tyne, Norwich, Westminster, Canterbury, Chichester, Winches ter, Exeter, and Bristol ; in each of which a public mart was appointed to be kept, and each of them had a court of the mayor of the staple, for deciding differences, held according to the lawmerchant, in a summary way.</p><p>STAR, in <hi rend="italic">Astronomy,</hi> a general name for all the heavenly bodies, which, like so many brilliant studs, are dispersed throughout the whole heavens. The stars are distinguished, from the phenomena of their motion, &amp;c., into fixed, and erratic or wandering stars. These last are again distinguished into the greater luminaries, viz. the sun and moon ; the planets, or wandering stars, properly so called, and the comets ; which have been all fully considered and explained under the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Αsτrονομυ.</hi> As to the fixed stars, they are so called, because they seem to be fixed, or perfectly at rest, and consequently appear always at the same distance from each other.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Palling </hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Stars</hi><hi rend="italic">,</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Meteorology,</hi> fiery meteors which dart through the sky in the form of a star.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Star</hi>, in <hi rend="italic">Fortification,</hi> denotes a small fort, having five or more points, or salient and reentering angles, flanking one another, and their faces ninety or a hundred feet long.</p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Star-Chamber</hi><hi rend="italic">, Court of, (Camera Stellata),</hi> a famous, or rather infamous, English tribunal, said to have been so called either from a Saxon word signifying to <hi rend="italic">steer</hi> or govern ; or from its punishing the <hi rend="italic">crimen stellionatus,</hi> or cosenage ; or because the room in which it sat, the old coun cil-chamber of the palace of Westminster, was full of win dows ; or, (to which Sir Edward Coke, 4 Inst. 66. accedes), because <hi rend="italic">haply</hi> the roof thereof was at the first garnished with gilded <hi rend="italic">stars.</hi> This was a court of very ancient original ; but newmodelled by statutes 3 Henry VII. c. 1, and 21 Henry VIII. c. 20, consisting of divers lords spiritual and temporal, being privy-councillors, together with two judges of the courts of common law, without the intervention of any jury. Their jurisdiction extended legally over riots, perjury, misbehaviour of sheriffs, and other notorious misdemeanours, contrary to the laws of the land. Yet this was afterwards, as Lord Clarendon informs us, stretched “ to the asserting of all proclamations and orders of state ; to the vindicating of illegal commissions and grants of monopolies ; holding for honourable that which pleased, and for just that which profited ; and becoming both a court of law to determine civil rights, and a court of revenue to en rich the treasury : the council-table by proclamations en joining to the people that which was not enjoined by the laws, and prohibiting that which was not prohibited ; and the star-chamber, which consisted of the same persons in different rooms, censuring the breach and disobedience to those proclamations by very great fines, imprisonments, and corporal severities : so that any disrespect to any acts of state, or to the persons of statesmen, was in no time more penal, and the foundations of right never more in danger to be destroyed.” For these reasons, it was finally abolished by statute 16 Car. I. c. 10, to the general joy of the whole nation.</p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Star-Board</hi><hi rend="italic">,</hi> the right side of the ship when the eye of the spectator is directed forward.</p><p><hi rend="italic">SτARshot,</hi> a gelatinous substance frequently found in fields, and supposed by the vulgar to have been produced from the meteor called a <hi rend="italic">falling-star ;</hi> but, in reality, it is the half-digested food of herons, seamews, and the like birds ; for these birds have been found, when newly shot, to disgorge a substance of the same kind.</p><p>STARAJA-RUSSA, a city of Russia in the province of Moscow and government of Novogorod, the capital of a circle of the same name. It is 206 miles from Petersburg, on the river Polesta. lt is an ill-built place, containing 1048 houses, many of them of wood, and 6200 inhabitants. There is a copious brine spring, from which about 100,000 bushels of culinary salt are annually made, and this is the chief trade of the place. Lat. 57. 51. Long. 32. 54. 25. E.</p><p>STARCH, a fecula or sediment, found at the bottom of vessels in which wheat has been steeped in water. Of this fecula, after separating the bran from it, by passing it through sieves, they form a kind of loaves, which being dried in the sun or an oven, is afterwards cut into little pieces, and so sold. The best starch is white, soft, and friable, and easily broken into powder. Such as require fine starch, do not content themselves, like the starchmen, with refuse wheat, but use the finest grain. The process is as follows. The grain, being well cleaned, is left to ferment in vessels full of water, which they expose to the sun while in its greatest heat ; changing the water twice aday, for the space of eight or twelves days, according to the season. When the grain bursts easily under the finger, they judge it sufficiently fermented. The fermentation being perfected, and the gram thus softened, it is put, handful by handful, into a canvas-bag, to separate the flour from the husks ; which is done by rubbing and beating it on a plank laid across the mouth of an empty vessel that is to receive the flour. As the vessels are filled with this liquid flour, there is seen swimming at top a reddish water, which is to be carefully skimmed off</p></body></text></TEI>