<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-03-26T17:33:57Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>From that time, however, a change, introduced by the literary taste of Pisistratus,
                had gradually prepared the way for establishing a school of philosophy at
                    Athens.@@<hi rend="superscript">1</hi> Pericles, too, had given a great stimulus
                to the literary spirit by his own fondness for intellectual pursuits, and the
                society of intellectual men. In the midst of his active political life, he could
                find time and thought for the elaborate disquisitions of the ingenious persons whom
                he invited to him. He could spend a whole day in disputing with Protagoras on so
                subtile a question as the theory of causation;@@<hi rend="superscript">3</hi> such
                was the intense interest which he displayed in every thing tending to the
                development of mental energy, and such the encouragement he gave to the change of
                taste then in progress by his own example. In the person of Socrates was found the
                genius formed to preside over the growing taste for literary and philosophical
                refinement, and to give it the form of an established institution. What, therefore,
                were merely indefinite fears at the time of the exhibition of “ The Clouds,” assumed
                a more distinct character of alarm to ancient prejudices within a quarter of a
                century afterwards. The rapidity and violence of several successive revolutions of
                the government during the latter part of that interval, further prepared the minds
                of the people for any sudden outbreaks of party spirit, and made every man an object
                of suspicion to his neighbour. A democracy of an hundred years’ existence@@’ had
                been overthrown, and first an oligarchy of four hundred, then a tyranny of thirty,
                established by foreign arms, in its place. Nor, as it had not been without fraud and
                bloodshed that the people had been spoiled of their “ ancient liberty,”@@* were they
                disposed to surrender it in quiet; or were those who seized on the government able
                to retain it long on the same footing. A struggle ensued ; in which the individuals
                of contending parties only sought to provide, each for his own aggrandizement and
                interest, or at least his own safety, under the constant expectation of some
                    counter-revolution.@@<hi rend="superscript">5</hi> The people had found that
                some of those very pcrsons who would never have been suspected of oligarchical
                views, had in the late changes taken part against the popular government, so that
                they knew not, at last, whom to trust even of themselves.@@® We are not to wonder
                that an accusation of Socrates should have succeeded before an Athenian jury at this
                period of morbid sensitiveness of the public mind.</p>
            <p>An accusation of impiety was, we must remember, too, an accusation of a political
                offence. A change of the popular religion was a change of the fundamental
                constitution of a Greek state. And as in the absolute rule of a single despot, so in
                the tyranny of a multitude, the reputation of zeal for religion is studiously
                maintained from policy, if from no higher motive, to throw around its arbitrary acts
                the reverence and fear due to the religious character. The teaching of Socrates was
                indeed eminently religious, but it differed from what the state regarded as such. He
                proved the existence of an invisible divine power, wisely designing and governing
                all things, and inculcated the duties of piety and morality as flowing from the
                belief of such an agency. Such clearly was not the state-religion.@@<hi
                    rend="superscript">7</hi> This was no system of truth or morality. It was
                tradition and legend, and immemorial usage, and ritual observance.@@<hi
                    rend="superscript">8</hi> And it was enough for a charge of impiety that
                Socrates rested religion on other</p>
            <p>grounds. A pious Athenian, and yet not pious after the manner of the Athenians, was,
                in their view, an introducer of new gods. He might well be believed to be a
                worshipper of the clouds and the air, when he pointed out to them, that the gods
                would not receive the sacrifice offered by wicked men,@@<hi rend="superscript">3
                </hi>that even their silent counsels were not concealed from the divine cognizance,
                and that justice was an indispensable duty of the worshipper of the gods.@@<hi
                    rend="superscript">10</hi></p>
            <p>That the accusation further should be credible, as brought in this form, is not
                strange, when it is known that, during the Peloponnesian war, the worship of new
                gods had been introduced into the city; as at Rome during the depression of its
                fortunes in the first years of the second Punic war. So greatly had the vicissitudes
                of fortune influenced the minds of men, observes Livy, describing this effect,—so
                great was the influx of religion, and that chiefly foreign, into the state,—that
                either the men or the gods appeared to have suddenly become different.@@<hi
                    rend="superscript">11</hi> So at Athens, it appears, the forms of superstition
                had been multiplied, under the pressure of civil and domestic calamity acting on the
                fears and credulity of the people. The strong reproof which Euripides puts into the
                mouth of Theseus, of the austere life of Hippolytus, would seem to point at some
                ascetic devotees among the Athenians themselves, practising a more refined and
                scrupulous religion, distinct from that of the vulgar ;</p>
            <p>"Ηδη rt⅛ <hi rend="italic">aυ%eι, xa∣ iι</hi> ά·ψό;/οο <hi rend="italic">βog3,i
                </hi>2iτB∕ς xαtr⅞λευ, <hi rend="italic">t)ξf&gt;ιa</hi> r âraxr’ sχu&gt;r,</p>
            <p>Baxjrrvs, τολλϊν <hi rend="italic">γgaμψMm&gt; npΛt</hi> ζασνούί·@@<hi
                    rend="superscript">12</hi></p>
            <p>In Aristophanes@@<hi rend="superscript">13</hi> we find still more evident allusion
                to the introduction of new objects of worship, new fanatical rites, in which the
                women chiefly officiated, and in which a gross licentiousness mingled with the gloom
                and solemnities of barbaric superstition.</p>
            <p>Again, education was intimately connected with politics in a Grecian state. The state
                took in hand its youthful citizens, and trained them according to its peculiar
                institutions, and in its own spirit. At least, in all the early constitutions, great
                attention was paid to education. Lycurgus made Sparta a constant school of war to
                his citizens. So too Solon, though he had, with greater knowledge of human nature
                than Lycurgus, adapted his institutions to the people for whom he legislated,
                provided that the people should be trained to the system of laws prescribed to them.
                But this care of the early legislators had begun to be lost sight of in
                    practice.@@<hi rend="superscript">H</hi> In Aristotle’s day it had disappeared
                    everywhere.@@<hi rend="superscript">15 </hi>In Sparta it was still nominally
                reverenced. In Athens, an entire relaxation of the educational discipline had taken
                place already in the time of Socrates. Pericles, flattering the democratic spirit of
                the Athenians of his day, could boast of their ease from labours and the obligation
                of exercises, and congratulate them on the courage which they could display at the
                time of action, without being inured beforehand by a course of hardy
                    discipline.@@<hi rend="superscript">10</hi> But now, whilst the state was remiss
                in not enforcing education according to its ancient system, a new system had grown
                up, the offspring of the luxury and refinement of its days of imperial greatness.
                This new and unauthorized education was diffused throughout the mass of the
                inhabitants beyond the pale of the citizens. Solon’s law imposed the duties of</p>
            <p><hi rend="superscript">@@@I</hi> Aul. Gell. vi. 17. Libros Athenis disciplinarum
                liberalium publice ad legendum præbendos primus posuisse dicitur Pisistratus
                tyrannus, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>@@@• Plutarch iu Pericl. Op. i. p. 665.</p>
            <p>@@@» Thucyd. viii. 68.</p>
            <p>@@@* Thucyd. viii. 71, 72. </p>
            <p>@@@’ Thucyd. iii. 82. <hi rend="italic superscript">ι</hi><hi rend="italic">rarrωr
                    i'aùrùn</hi> a'rar, x.r.λ. </p>
            <p><hi rend="superscript">@@@β</hi> Thucyd. viii. 66.</p>
            <p>@@@’ Aristotle, Pol. v. 9. </p>
            <p>@@@’ Cic. de Legib. ii. 16. </p>
            <p>@@@<hi rend="superscript">9</hi> Xenoph. Mem. i. 3. </p>
            <p>@@@<hi rend="superscript">10</hi> Xenoph. i. 6.</p>
            <p><hi rend="superscript">@@@II</hi> Liv. XXV. I. Quo diutius trahebatur bellum et
                variabant secundæ adversæq. res non fortunam magis quam animos hominum; tanta
                religio, et ea magna ex parte externa, civitatem incessit, ut aut homines aut Dii
                repente alii viderentur facti, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>@@@&gt;· Euripid. Hippolyt. 952. </p>
            <p><hi rend="superscript">@@@15</hi> See Pax. 410, 428. Lysist. 389.</p>
            <p><hi rend="superscript">@@@14</hi> Lysimachus, in the Laches, complains of their
                fathers having neglected their education, &lt;iπ <hi rend="italic">i&gt;fuit
                    ∕∙&lt;∙&lt;&gt; t"ut rζvφS.,</hi> p. 182. See this dialogue of Plato throughout,
                on the subject of Athenian education.</p>
            <p><hi rend="superscript">@@@15</hi> Aristot. Pol. v. 7. Jλ&lt;yaP∙5v∕ τaim(. </p>
            <p><hi rend="superscript">@@@16</hi> Thucyd. ii. 39.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
