<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T17:35:33Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>the mountains of Cuenza. The wild animals of the southern part of Spain are very similar to those of the north of Africa.</p><p>Spain has long been celebrated for its richness in minerals, and large veins of various metals are still found in several parts of the country. Gold and silver mines were formerly worked; but they have been given up, although grains of these metals are still found. Lead is found in considerable quantities ; the principal veins, as the lead-glance veins of Sinares, are found in granite. The colossal deposit of galena, which yielded 600,000 quintals of lead in 1829, lies in irregular masses in a limestone formation. The principal mines are near Tortoza in Catalonia ; nt Zoma, Benasques, and Plan in Aragon ; in Estremadura, in Murcia, in Old Castille, in Seville ; and at the district of Linares, in Jaen. Mercury is also found, and at Almaden there is a rich mine of this valuable mineral, which is wrought in the clay slate. Iron ore occurs in very large quantities, principally in the northern provinces. In the Pays Basque, the lias formation is very rich in iron ore ; and at Solomostro, near Bilboa, enormous deposits of carbonated iron are found. Veins of copper, antimony, and sulphur, are occasionally discovered, but not in such quantities as to be worth working. Coal also exists in considerable quantities in many provinces ; and this mineral is gaining in importance every year, from other fuel becoming scarce.</p><p>Although Spain possesses all the advantages of climate, and the soil is generally fertile, the agriculture of the country is in a state of deplorable backwardness. A variety of causes has been assigned for this, but the principal cause is what has been appropriately termed the curse of the Mesta. This is a privilege granted to the proprietors of flocks to conduct their sheep into different provinces for the sake of pasturage. In their progress the sheep commit considerable depredations on the crops. The law of entail, which exists in Spain in its worst form, is also supposed to hinder improvement in agriculture ; but perhaps the most serious obstacle to improvement is the want of internal communication, and the indolence of the rural population. The farms are generally small, and the farmers of a district live together in villages. There is no rotation of crops, and the wheat, after a slight ploughing, is sown at the commencement of the rains. The operation of thrashing and cleaning the grain is performed in the open air, and the grain is left in the fields or concealed in caves till sold. Implements of husbandry are of the rudest description ; fanners are un known except about the seacoast, and the spade is still in use in some of the mountainous parts of the country. The most careful cultivation is to be found in the <hi rend="italic">huertas of </hi>Granada, Murcia, and Valencia, which are well irrigated by the waters of the Xenil, Segura, and Xucar. Rice is produced in Valencia, and a mild red pepper is the chief vegetable cultivated in Murcia. These three provinces are considered as the gardens of Spain, and annually yield three and four crops of vegetables, maize, and a mild red pep per. In spite of this fertility, however, it is calculated that the entire lands of Spain do not yield more than from one and a half to two per cent. to the proprietors. Some improvements have recently been introduced, but even now scarcely a fourth of the surface of the country is applied to any profitable use. A far greater extent of land is devoted to pasturage than is required for the maintenance of the cattle; and only about a twelfth of the superficies is occupied by wood. In Biscay, agriculture has made many improvements ; and in spite of the disadvantages of soil, the population of this district is more numerous, and grain cheaper, than in the fertile plains to the south and east of Seville ; which, if properly cultivated, might supply all Spain. “ The kingdoms of Old Castille and Leon,” says a writer in the Foreign Quarterly Review, vol. v. “ are justly considered the granaries of Spain. They have their outlets in</p><p>the north by various ports from Gijon to St Sebastian, the principal being Santander and Bilboa. The provinces of Burgos and Palencia are the nearest points from which these ports get any considerable supply ; the distance being from 130 to 140 English miles from each. The elevated and rich <hi rend="italic">campos</hi> which extend from Logroño to Burgos, and thence on each side of the Arlanza and Pisuerga, and along the Cauvion, and numerous other streams which water the provinces of Palencia, Valladolid, and Zamora, yield immense quantities of wheat ; and further to the west, and on the south side of the Douro, the provinces of Toro and Salamanca may be considered as forming a portion of the richest wheat country in Spain, or perhaps in the world. The crop is often so abundant for a series of years, that the produce of the fields at a distance from the villages is some times allowed to rot on the ground, the expense of conveying it home being considered beyond its value. It was calculated that the accumulated surplus of four or five successive years, in the <hi rend="italic">silos</hi> and granaries of these plains, amount ed at the close of the harvest of 1828 to 6,000,000 of fane gas, or 1,200,000 Winchester quarters. The ordinary cost of carriage does not exceed seven or eight shillings for every hundred miles ; but the means of transport are so defective and so badly organized, that when any extraordinary demand for exportation takes place, the rates advance accordingly. Thus, in September 1828, the usual price was seven or eight shillings ; but in consequence of extensive demands from France and England, it rose two months after to fourteen shillings and sixteen shillings per quarter. The grain of Spain is of the finest quality, that of Andalusia bearing a price tcn or fifteen per cent. higher than that of any foreign grain brought to the markets of Cadiz. In spite of her facilities for agriculture, it is remarkable that Spain regularly imports, upon an average, 400,000 quarters of grain. This may arise from the want of proper means of transporting grain from one province to another, and not from any deficiency in the produce of the country.” Several of the provinces, such as Galicia, Asturias, part of Leon, Santander, Biscay, and the kingdom of Navarre, barely produce sufficient for the consumption of their inhabitants. Catalonia does little more than maintain the half of its in habitants; Valencia exports rice, but both it and Murcia import wheat ; Cuenza, Guadalaxara, Segovia, Avila, and Madrid, produce less than their consumption. The pro vinces of Old Castille, part of Leon, Estremadura, part of Andalusia and Toledo, produce such an abundance that they might supply all the deficiencies of the other parts of Spain, and also export to foreign countries in seasons of plenty. Miñano calculates the gross amount of agricultural produce in 1826 at L.76,965,000, and the net produce at L.28,403,666. The same authority estimates the number of cattle, &amp;c. in the kingdom in 1826 as follows : horned beasts, 2,944,885; horses, 400,495; mules, 223,646 ; sheep, 18,687,159; goats, 5,187,668; asses, 641,788; swine, 2,728,283 ; beehives, 1,697,593.</p><p>The manufactures of Spain are in a very depressed state, although some thriving manufactories exist, principally on the seacoast. The manufacture of silk was formerly the grand staple of trade, and although now much depre ciated, it is calculated to furnish employment for nearly 16,000 persons. Numerous manufactures of various kinds have been established in Catalonia within the last twenty years ; those of silk and cotton are the most extensive, and are in a thriving state. The looms of Valencia are calculated to employ at the present day nearly 3000 persons, and produce tissues, gauzes, and ribbands, equal to the French manufactories. The silk manufacture of Talavera de la Reyna and Saragossa are still in high repute. The latter province also produces cloth, which is much in request. Galicia annually imports 20,000 hundredweight of flax, which is conveyed to Santiago, and distributed throughout</p></body></text></TEI>