<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T17:34:30Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>birth.@@<hi rend="superscript">1</hi> According to Laertius, he died at the age of eighty ; but Lucian extends his life to one hundred years. Of the poems of Solon, an elaborate edition has recently been published by Bach, under the title of “ Solonis Atheniensis Carminum quæ supersunt.” Bonnæ, 1825, 8vo.</p><p>SOLOON, a small island in the Eastern seas, twenty- five miles from the island of Samar. Long. 125. 42. E. Lat. 10. 55. N.</p><p>SOLOR <hi rend="smallcaps">Isle,</hi> an island in the Eastern seas, separated from the island of Floris by the straits of Floris. It is about thirty miles in length, by fifteen in average breadth.</p><p>SOLOTHURN, a canton of Switzerland. It is bounded on the north by France and by Basel, on the east by Basel and Zurich, and on the south and west by Berne. It extends over two hundred and fifty-eight square miles, com- prising two cities, one market-town, and one hundred and thirty-seven villages, with 59,122 inhabitants, of whom 54,000 are catholics, and the remainder protestants. The revenues amount to 180,000 francs, and the yearly expen- diture to 164,000. It is bound to contribute 904 men, and 1365 francs to the general confederation. The mountains are a continuation of the Jura range, and none of them exceeds 3900 feet in height. The river Aar receives the smaller streams. There are no extensive lakes. The cli- mate is temperate, and the soil produces good com, hemp, flax, fruit, and wine. The chief employment is agriculture and cutting the extensive woods, which supply some fuel and building timber for exportation.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Solothurn,</hi> a city of Switzerland, the capital of the canton of that name. It stands at the foot of the Jura moun- tains, on both sides of the river Aar. It is surrounded with walls and defended by bastions, is well, but irregularly built, and contains 560 houses, with 4470 inhabitants. It has a college with five professors and a good public lib- rary. Solothurn contains several manufactories for making and printing cotton, and some other goods. Lat. 47. 12. Long. 7. 26. E.</p><p>SOLOTONOSCHA, a town of Russia, the capital of a circle of the same name, in the province of Pultowa, 947 miles from Petersburg. It stands at the point where the Solontschia falls into the Dneiper. It contains three churches, two monasteries, eight hundred houses, and 5650 inhabi- tants, chiefly employed in agriculture. Lat. 49∙58. Long. 31.58. E.</p><p>SOLSTICE, in <hi rend="italic">Astronomy,</hi> the time when the sun is in one of the solstitial points ; that is, when he is at his greatest distance from the equator ; thus called because he then appears to stand still, and not to change his distance from the equator for some time ; an appearance owing to the obliquity of our sphere, and to which those living un- der the equator are strangers.</p><p>The solstices are two in each year ; the æstival or summer solstice, and the hyemal or winter solstice. The summer solstice is when the sun seems to describe the tropic of cancer, which is on June 22, when he makes the longest day : the winter solstice is when the sun enters the first degree, or seems to describe the tropic of capricorn, which is on December 22, when he makes the shortest day. This is to be understood as in our northern hemisphere ; for in the southern, the sun’s entrance into capricorn makes the summer solstice, and that into cancer the winter solstice. The two points of the ecliptic, at which the sun’s greatest ascent above the equator, and his descent below it, are terminated, are called the <hi rend="italic">solstitial points ;</hi> and a circle, supposed to pass through the poles of the world and these points, is called the <hi rend="italic">solstitial colure.</hi> The summer solstitial point is in the beginning of the first degree of cancer, and is called the <hi rend="italic">æstival</hi> or <hi rend="italic">summer point;</hi> and the winter solstitial point is in the beginning of the first</p><p>degree of capricorn, and is called the <hi rend="italic">winter point.</hi> These two points are diametrically opposite to each other.</p><p>SOLYMANIA, called also Shehr Zaur, a town of Kur- distan, the residence of the Pacha. The town had fallen into decay, but was rebuilt by Solyman the Pacha, who, in 1810, having taken up arms against the Pacha of Bagdad, defeated him and put him to death. Population, 6000 ; fifty-four miles east of Kerkook.</p><p>SOMALPET, a town of Hindustan in the Nizam’s pro- vince of Nandere, fifty-two miles N.N.E. from the town of Nandere.</p><p>SOMBOR, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Ζομβοr,</hi> a city of the kingdom of Hungary, in the province of the hither Danube, in the circle of Kozep Jaras. It contains 2980 houses, with 14,860 inhabitants, whose chief trade is in corn and cattle. Lat. 48. 8. 32. Long. 21. 10. 33. E.</p><p>SOMERS, <hi rend="smallcaps">John</hi> Lord, high chancellor of England, was born at Worcester in 1652. He was educated at Oxford, and afterwards entered himself at the Middle-Temple, where he studied the law with great vigour. In 1688 he was one of the counsel for the seven bishops at their trial, and argued with great learning and eloquence against the dispensing power. In the convention which met by the prince of Orange’s summons, January 22, 1689, he repre- sented Worcester; and was one of the managers for the House of Commons, at a conference with the House of Lords upon the word <hi rend="italic">abdicated.</hi> Soon after the accession of William and Mary to the throne, he was appointed so- licitor-general, and received the honour of knighthood. In 1692 he was made attorney-general, and in 1693 advanced to the post of lord-keeper of the great seal of England. In 1695 he proposed an expedient to prevent the practice of clipping the coin. In 1697 he was created Lord Somers, baron of Evesham, and made lord high chancellor of Eng- land. In the beginning of 1700 he was removed from his post of lord chancellor, and the year after was impeached of high crimes and misdemeanours by the House of Commons, of which he was acquitted upon trial by the House of Lords. He then retired to a studious course of life, and was chosen president of the Royal Society. In 1706 he proposed a bill for the regulation of the law ; and the same year was one of the principal managers for the union be- tween England and Scotland. In 1708 he was made lord president of the council ; from which post he was removed in 1710, upon the change of the ministry. In the latter end of Queen Anne’s reign his lordship grew very infirm in his health ; which is supposed to be the reason that he held no other post than a seat at the council-table, after the accession of King George I. He died of an apoplectic fit in 1716. Mr. Addison has drawn his character very beauti- fully in the Freeholder.</p><p>SOMERSETSHIRE, a maritime county of England, lying in a crescent-like form on the Bristol Channel, to which its north-western side is turned. It is bounded to the north-east by Gloucestershire, on the east by Wilt- shire, on the south by Dorsetshire and part of Devonshire, and on the west by the latter county. Its greatest length, from east to west, is sixty-five miles, and its greatest breadth, from north to south, forty-five miles. Its bound- ary line has several considerable indentations. The whole area comprehends 1642 square statute miles, or 1,050,880 English acres ; being in extent the seventh in the list of the English counties. The acreable value of the land, ac- cording to the late returns under the property-tax, exceed- ed that of any other county except Leicestershire, being, including the tithes, L.876 per square mile, or about 27s. per acre.</p><p>The civil divisions of this county are denominated the eastern and the western. The eastern division contains</p><p><hi rend="superscript">@@@1</hi> Clinton’s Fasti Hellenici, vol. ii. p. 301.</p></body></text></TEI>