<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T17:36:30Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>with the book kept below, the distances, as for instance in the cave :</p><p>“ No. 1, in the book below, was called from the water to the foot of the first pillar in the book above ; No. 1 gave 36 feet 8 inches, the highest of that ascent, which was corn posed of broken pillars.</p><p>“ No. 1. Pillar at the west corner of Fingal's cave.</p><p>Feet In.</p><p>1.	From the water to the foot of the pillar, 12 10</p><p>2.	Height of the pillar, .	.	37 3</p><p>3.	Stratum above the pillar, .	66 9</p><p>“ No. 2. Fingal’s cave.</p><p>1.	From the water to the foot of the pillar,	36 8</p><p>2.	Height of the pillar, .	.	39 6</p><p>9. From the top of the pillar to the top of the</p><p>arcb, .	.	.	31 4</p><p>4.	Thickness of the stratum above, .	34 4</p><p>By adding together the three first measure</p><p>ments, we got the height of the arch</p><p>from the water,	.	.	117 6</p><p>“ No. 3. Corner pillar to the westward of Fingal’s cave.</p><p>Stratum below the pillar of lava-like matter, 11 0 Length of pillar,	.	.	54 0</p><p>Stratum above the pillar, .	61 6</p><p>“ No. 5. Another part to the westward.</p><p>Stratum below the pillar,	.	17	1</p><p>Height of the pillar,	.	.	50 0</p><p>Stratum above,	.	.	51	1</p><p>“ No. 5. Another pillar farther to the west ward.</p><p>Stratum below tne pillar, .	.	19 8</p><p>Height of the pillar, .	.	<hi rend="italic">55</hi>	1</p><p>Stratum above, .	.	.	54 7</p><p>“ The stratum above the pillars, which is here mention ed, is uniformly the same, consisting of numberless small pillars, bending and inclining in all directions, sometimes so irregular that the stones can only be said to have an incli nation to assume a columnar form ; in others more regular, but never breaking into or disturbing the stratum of large pillars, whose tops everywhere keep an uniform and regular line.</p><p>“ Proceeding now along the shore round the north end of the island, you arrive at <hi rend="italic">0ua na scarce,</hi> or the Corvorant’s Cave. Here the stratum under the pillars is lifted up very high ; the pillars above are considerably less than those at the northwest end of the island, but still very considerable. Beyond is a bay, which cuts deep into the island, rendering it in that place not more than a quarter of a mile over. On the sides of this bay, especially beyond a little valley, which almost cuts the island into two, are two stages of pillars, but small ; however, having a stratum between them exactly the same as that above them, formed of innumerable little pillars, shaken out of their places, and leaning in all directions.</p><p>“ Having passed this bay, the pillars totally cease ; the rock is of a dark-brown stone, and no signs of regularity occur till you have passed round the southeast end of the island, (a space almost as large as that occupied by the pil lars), which you meet again on the west side, beginning to form themselves irregularly, as if the stratum had an inclination to that form, and soon arrive at the bending pillars where I began.</p><p>“ The stone of which the pillars are formed, is a coarse kind of basaltes, very much resembling the Giant’s Cause way in Ireland, though none of them are near so neat as the specimens of the latter which I have seen at the British Museum, owing chiefly to the colour, which in ours is a dirty brown, in the Irish a fine black ; indeed the whole production seems very much to resemble the Giant’s Causeway.”</p><p>Views of Fingal's Cave are given in plates CCCLXIV and CCCLXV, under the head <hi rend="smallcaps">Minerology</hi>.</p><p>STAFFORD, the county town of Staffordshire, is 135 miles from London. It consists of two parishes, and returns two members to Parliament. It stands on the river Sow, and was once fortified. It is now well built. The principal buildings are the assize hall, the county jail, and the infirmary. It has a good free-school, several almshouses, and on Saturday a good market, well attended. The cabal encourages some trade ; but the chief occupation of the inhabitants is making shoes, and some cloth is also made. The population was in 1801, 3927 ; in 1811, 4898 ; in 1821, 5775; and in 1831, 6998.</p><p>STAFFORDSHIRE, an inland English county of an oblong form. Its greatest length from northeast to southwest is about sixty, and its greatest breadth about thirty eight, miles. It contains 1148 statute square miles, or 734,720 acres. It is bounded on the north by Cheshire, west by Shropshire, south by Worcester and Warwickshire, and east by Derbyshire. The great divisions are five hundreds ; but as each of these is subdivided into the north and south portions, there are effectively ten hundreds. These contain one hundred and eighty-one parishes, twenty-three market towns, and one city. The whole of the county, with the exception of two parishes, is within the diocese of Lich field, and comprehended within the archdeaconry of Stafford.</p><p>The population of this county at the four decennial periods of enumeration, was found to be as follow: in 1801, 239,153; in 1811, 295,153; in 1821, 341,040; and in 1831, 410,400.</p><p>In 1831, the occupiers of land employing 1a</p><p>bourers were	 3,781</p><p>The occupiers not employing labourers		3,649</p><p>Labourers employed in agriculture	 16,812</p><p>Labourers employed in manufactures	 26,755</p><p>Labourers employed in retail trade or handi craft	 24,766</p><p>Capitalists, bankers, &amp;c	 3,569</p><p>Labourers not agricultural	 22,690</p><p>Other labourers under twenty years of age... 4,245</p><p>Males at and above twenty years	101,632</p><p>Male servants	 1,959</p><p>Female servants	 12,739</p><p>In the same year, the number of families, chiefly employ ed in agriculture, was found to be 18,156; of those chiefly employed in trade, manufactures, and handicraft, 43,646 ; and of those not comprised in either of the preceding classes, 21,789. The number of inhabited houses was 78,049, occupied by 83,593 families. The uninhabited houses were 4088, and those building 573. The annual value of the real property of the county, as assessed for the purposes of the property tax in the year 1813, was L.1,150,285.</p><p>The towns and townships within this county, and their population in 1831, were as follows, but some of them may be better described as large villages than towns.</p><p>Wolverhampton	 48,184	Wednesbury	 8437</p><p>Stoke-upon-Trent... 37,220	Newcastle-under-Lyne 8196</p><p>Sedgley	 20,577	Stone	 6918</p><p>West Bromwick	 15,066	Stafford	 6998</p><p>Kingswinford......... 15,156	Darlaston	 6647</p><p>Walsall	 15,066	Lichfield (city)		6499</p><p>Tipton	 14,951	Handsworth	 4944</p><p>Burslem	 11,250	Uttoxeter	 4864</p><p>Wolstanton	 10,853	Eccleshall	 4471</p><p>Leek, the town	 4,374	Burton-on-Trent	 4399</p><p>but the parish	 10,780	Penkridge	 2991</p><p>The middle and southern portions are generally level, but interspersed with gentle eminences. The northern division</p></body></text></TEI>