<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T17:35:13Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>The condition to which it was now reduced was pitiable. The army and navy were in a state of utter disorganization ; the walls of towns and fortresses were in ruins ; the public revenues had dwindled to little more than a nobleman’s in come ; and trade, manufactures, and commerce, had all but ceased to exist. Another such reign as that of Charles II. would have dissolved the bonds of society.</p><p>Charles II. was succeeded by Philip V. duke of Anjou, grandson to Louis XIV. of France. He was the eldest son of Maria Teresa, eldest daughter of Philip IV., consequently the most legitimate sovereign ; for Charles left no issue, and before his death he had subscribed an instrument, declaring Philip his successor. The foreign events of this reign demand our first attention. The transactions of the war which was soon declared against France and Spain, by England, Holland, and the empire, assisted by Savoy, Por tugal, and Prussia, have been already related under the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Βritian.</hi> The chief objects of the alliance were to obtain satisfaction for the Austrian claims on Spain, the emperor Leopold being not only descended from Fernando, brother of Charles V., but whose mother was the daughter of Philip III. ; to rescue the Netherlands from France ; to prevent the union of the French and Spanish crowns ; and to exclude subjects of the former from the Spanish possessions in the West Indies. The treaty of Utrecht, which terminated the differences between the principal contending powers, was signed in 1713 ; and in 1715 a permanent peace was concluded between Spain and Portugal. By the celebrated treaty of 1713, Spain was stripped of half her European possessions. Philip was indeed acknowledged king of Spain and the Indies ; but Sicily was ceded to the duke of Savoy ; Milan, Naples, Sardinia, and the Nether lands, to the emperor ; and Gibraltar and Minorca to the English. The Catalans, who had revolted and joined the allies, were likewise guaranteed a general amnesty, but without any stipulations for the preservation of their ancient fueros or privileges, which they had justly forfeited. Philip also renounced, both for himself and his successors, all claims to the French crown. In return for this renunciation, he forced rather than persuaded his council to introduce a measure to which subsequent events in the history of Spain gave great importance. This was to alter the order of succession, and establish a sort of Salic law, by which the most distant male of the family would be called to the inheritance in preference to the nearest female. The innovation was regarded with discontent. By the ancient law, which, in default of direct male issue, called females to the throne, the monarchy had been formed. By it Catalonia had been united with Aragon, and the latter with Castille ; and by it Philip himself had inherited the crown.</p><p>Philip made an unsuccessful attempt to recover Sicily, Sardinia, and Naples; for he had now rendered both his navy and his army formidable alike by discipline and num bers. His fleet, however, was totally destroyed off the coast of Sicily, by our Admiral Byng, in the year 1718.</p><p>By a new treaty in 1720, Sardinia was given to the duke of Savoy, and Sicily to the emperor ; and by the treaty of Seville, concluded in 1729, the duchies of Tuscany, Parma, and Placentia, were ceded to Spain. In 1731, the Spanish king invaded Naples, took possession of that kingdom, and conferred it on his son Don Carlos, in consequence of which war was declared between Spain and the empire in 1733. At the end of that year the palace of Madrid was consumed by fire, and all the archives relating to the Indies perished in the flames. In 1739, hostilities were renewed between Spain and Britain ; but the only successes obtained by the latter power were the capture of Porto Bello by Admiral Vernon, and that of the Manilla galeon by Commodore Anson. Philip’s long and turbulent reign was now drawing to a close. In July 1746, he was hurried to the grave by an attack of apoplexy. One memorable event of his</p><p>reign remains to be noticed. In imitation of the emperor, he resigned the cares of royalty into the hands of his son in 1724; but finding seclusion irksome, he resumed them again in a very short time. Whatever might be the weak nesses of this prince, he had a sincere desire for the good of Spain, and retrieved it from hopeless ruin by several judicious measures which he introduced, so that the country attained a degree of positive prosperity unknown since the days of the second Philip.</p><p>Ferdinand VI. a mild, prudent, and beneficent prince, reformed abuses in the administration of justice and management of the finances. He revived commerce, established manufactures, and promoted the prosperity of his kingdom.</p><p>Charles III. succeeded Ferdinand in 1759. The famous family compact was concluded at Versailles in 1761, among the four kings of the house of Bourbon. The English, alarmed by the naval preparations of Spain, declared war in 1762, and took Havannah in the island of Cuba, and Manilla in the East Indies. Notwithstanding this success, peace was hastily concluded at Fontainebleau, in Novem ber, by which the Havannah was restored. In 1767 the Jesuits were expelled from Spain. An unsuccessful <hi rend="italic">expedition</hi> was concerted against Algiers in 1775, the particulars of which it is unnecessary to detail. In the war between Great Britain and her American colonies, Spain, by the intrigues of the French court, was instigated to take up arms in support of the latter. At the conclusion of that calamitous war, Great Britain, in a treaty with Spain, ceded to this power East and West Florida, and the island of Minorca. Charles died in 1788, and was succeeded by his second son Charles Anthony, prince of Asturias, the eld est having been declared incapable of inheriting the crown.</p><p>Charles IV. had not long been seated on the throne be fore the portentous revolution in France involved Europe in a general scene of political and military contest. The king of Spain joined the general confederacy against the new republic, and in consequence was numbered among the objects of its resentment, by a declaration of war in 1793. The military operations of Spain, however, were extremely languid ; and after two campaigns, in which she might be said to carry on rather a defensive than an offensive war against the republican armies, she was compelled to conclude a treaty of peace, which was signed at Basel on the 22d July 1795. By this treaty the French republic restored to the king of Spain all the conquests which she had made from him since the commencement of hostilities, and received in exchange all right and property in the Spanish part of St Domingo.</p><p>This treaty was soon followed by <hi rend="italic">a</hi> rupture with Great Britain. On 5th October 1796, the court of Spain having published a manifesto against this country, the court of London made a spirited reply ; and about the same time was published a treaty of offensive and defensive alliance, which had been concluded about two months before, between the king of Spain and the French republic. In the war which followed between Spain and Great Britain, his Catholic majesty could boast of but little honour or success ; and the French republic gained little from its new ally but the contributions of money which it from time to time compelled him to advance. On the l4th of February 1797, a Spanish fleet of twenty-seven sail of the line was defeated by Sir John Jervis off Cape St Vincent, and four of the Spanish line-of-battle ships were left in the hands of the victors. From this time till the temporary cessation of hostilities by the peace of Amiens in 1802, there is nothing remarkable in the transactions of Spain.</p><p>On the renewal of the war in 1803, Spain was again compelled, by the overbearing power of France, to take an active part against Great Britain, and fitted out a formidable fleet, which was united to a considerable naval force belong</p></body></text></TEI>