<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T17:35:23Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ed from him, not only when he was in the agonies of expected death, but under false misrepresentations that all Spain demanded it, and that the inviolability of the monarchy required it ; whereas it had only been desired by an ambitious and unscrupulous faction, and was opposed to the fundamental laws of the kingdom. A more liberal minis try was formed, and some liberal measures were adopted ; high expectations were raised that milder times were at hand, and the funds in Madrid rose ten per cent. Early in 1883, Ferdinand was able to resume the reins of govern ment. On the 20th of June he assembled the Cortes to swear allegiance to his daughter, and do homage to her as their future sovereign. This solemnity was performed with great pomp in the church of the royal monastery of St Jerome. Don Carlos refused to take the oath ; but previously to this he had taken up his residence in Portugal, where his nephew was playing the same desperate game which he himself was about to undertake. Ferdinand survived the ceremony of <hi rend="italic">the jura</hi> only a few months. He <hi rend="italic">expired</hi> on the 29th of September 1833, leaving a will, in which he appointed his daughter Isabella heir to the crown, and her mother regent during her minority.</p><p>No sooner was Isabella II. proclaimed queen, than Don Carlos announced his claim to the throne, and the flames of civil war burst out in the northern provinces, where his par tisans, assembled in great numbers, stood ready armed for the contest. Of the bloody and protracted struggle for the throne which ensued, we can afford room for few details ; indeed, an account of the numerous battles, skirmishes, sieges, and other warlike operations, would prove a very uninteresting and monotonous portion of the modem his tory of Spain. IsabeIla was acknowledged without opposition throughout all the provinces of Spain, and by the leading powers of Europe. The question of the Spanish suc cession, apart altogether from the bloody war to which it gave rise, has been keenly agitated in this and many other countries. It may be briefly stated as follows. Carlos’s right rests upon the Salic law, which had never the force of law in Spain. The Salic law was not the ancient rule of succession ; it was first introduced by the Bourbon Philip V., the greatgrandfather of Don Carlos. Females could always succeed in Castille, Leon, and Portugal. It was by marriage with the heiress of Navarre that a king of France obtained a claim to that kingdom; and although females were excluded in Aragon, yet it was through a princess that its inheritance passed to the counts of Catalonia. It was by the right of female succession that the house of Austria reigned in Spain ; it was by the same right that the Bourbons themselves occupied the throne. It formed a part of the Partidas, or system of constitutional law, which Philip swore to observe on his succession to the throne. The Salic law, on which Carlos grounds his claim, could only be established in two ways ; by the old forms of the constitution, or by the despotic will of the sovereign. If the advocates of Don Carlos take their stand on the former ground, the answer is, that the forms as well as the sub stance of the constitution were violated when Philip V. established his law of succession ; and that, conscious of its in validity, he did not register it in the form usual with similar acts ; while again, if we pass over the Cortes of 1789 as secret and irregular, we have the Cortes of Cadiz in 1812, which abolished the decree of Philip, and restored the ancient law of the Partidas. But Ferdinand having annulled the proceedings of this body, its reestablishment of the right of female succession must fall to the ground with its other decrees. There is however Ferdinand’s own de cree, constituting his daughter his successor, which was just as regularly sanctioned by the Cortes as Philip’s law of succession. If, on the other hand, the sovereign is to be regarded as despotic in Spain, the question is at an end ; for even Carlos must acknowledge that Ferdinand had a right</p><p>to regulate the succession according to his own royal plea sure. This view seemed to have been taken by the king’s confessor, and his minister Calomarde,, when, during his dangerous illness at La Granja in 1832, they induced him to sign a new will, settling the crown on Don Carlos. Ferdinand’s recovery disconcerted their plan ; but their effort plainly shows that the partisans of Don Carlos at that time felt that the Salic law was a very weak support to their favourite’s claims. The transaction by which Ferdinand (supposed to be on his deathbed) transferred the crown to his brother, is admitted by the Carlists to have been a perfectly legal proceeding. Can the subsequent transaction, by which, under exactly similar circumstances, the king ap pointed his daughter his successor, be considered otherwise than as an equally legal proceeding ? If the constitution be referred to, the question is decided against Don Carlos ; the will of the sovereign is against his claim ; and, what is of yet more consequence, as the event has shown, the will of the majority of the nation is against him.</p><p>It was in the northern provinces, in Navarre, Guipuscoa, Biscay, and Alava, that the strength of Don Carlos lay. Here he was immediately proclaimed in several towns by the title of Charles V., and bands of Carlist guerillas assembled to maintain his right to the throne. He himself still hovered a fugitive on the frontiers of Portugal, his movements being closely watched by a royal force under General Rodil. Another strong division of the queen’s army, under General Sarsfield, marched against the disaffected provinces. The Carlists retired before him ; Bilboa and other towns were occupied and garrisoned; the constitutional party was restored in several places where it had lost ground ; and the insurrection seemed at first to have been happily put down without much loss. But early in 1834 the affairs of the Carlists assumed altogether a new aspect. Hitherto their operations were carried on in an unconnected manner ; this system was now exchanged for one of steady unity of design. Indeed so numerous were the adherents of Don Carlos in the north, that there was only required a firm hand to seize the reins, control local jealousies, and direct aright the energies of the provinces. Such a man was Thomas Zumalacarreguy, who now assumed the chief command of the Carlists. He was admirably skilled in the desultory warfare of these provinces, and well acquainted with the country and with the charac ter of the inhabitants. By his activity and enterprise he repeatedly inflicted severe blows upon the forces of the queen, or the Christinos, as they were generally called. His method of fighting was to surprise the enemy in an unprotected position, and cut off as many of them as he could before they recovered from their panic. His troops would then suddenly separate and fly, but only to unite again at a predetermined point some miles in the rear. By this mode of warfare he caused great loss to the Christinos, while his own small band suffered little. The Christino army under General Rodil, who had now obtained the chief command, might amount to 20,000 men, and was thus sufficiently strong at least to have confined Zumalacarreguy to the mountains ; but it was greatly reduced by several thousand troops having been distributed among a number of petty fortresses, most of which, one after the other, fell a prey to the Carlist chieftain. It was further weakened by being divided into different corps and scattered over the country. Rodil found it necessary to resign the command, which now devolved upon Mina, from whom much was ex pected. Nor did he disappoint the hopes which were formed of him. Just before his appointment, Generals O’Doyle and Asina had severally been defeated with great loss by Zumalacarreguy, which occasioned much alarm at Madrid, and loud outcries against the ministry. But the old war rior, though broken by sickness and infirmities, restored confidence by making head against the hitherto victori</p></body></text></TEI>