<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T17:36:31Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>is of an opposite character, the surface being for the most part bleak and hilly. The general elevation of this district above the southern part of the county is about two or three hundred feet ; but some points rise to the height of from 1200 to 1500. Of those the most elevated are Bunster and the Weever Hills. In the valleys on the banks of the rivers are some tracks of country equal to the most beautiful parts of the island. Among these, the district betwixt Lichfield and Stone, and the picturesque banks of the Dove, especially at Ham, are very remarkable.</p><p>The soil is various, but the strong clays are the most pre dominant ; next in extent is the sandy soil, chiefly to the south of the Trent. There is no chalk, and only a small district is calcareous. The meadows, especially on the banks of the Trent, are most rich and luxuriant ; and, though on some spots there is much inert peat, yet, when it is properly drained, it becomes valuable pasture and meadow land. The climate is generally raw and moist: the rain that falls on an average of several years is about thirty-six inches. The quantity of snow, in the winter on the moorlands, is very great, which may contribute to the general coldness of the district.</p><p>The Trent, the third river in England, is the principal stream of the county. It rises at Newpool on the confines of Cheshire, and enters Derbyshire below Burton, after having formed a junction with the Dove. Through the whole of its course in this county, it is a clear and rather rapid stream. The Dove is celebrated for the picturesque scenery through which it flows. In its course it receives the Mani fold and the Hamps, two streams which are lost in subterraneous channels, but again emerge at the distance of some miles, and rejoin it. The smaller rivers are the Tame, the Blythe, the Sow, and the Penk, all of which empty them selves into the Trent. No part of Great Britain is so intersected with navigable canals as Staftbrdshire, and in no county have their beneficial effects been so extensively <hi rend="italic">experienced.</hi> The Grand Trunk was planned and executed by Mr. Brindley, the most eminent engineer that ever exerted talent in this peculiar branch of inland navigation. This canal is about ninety-one miles in length. The fall of water to the north is 326 feet, and to the south 316 feet. It is twenty-nine feet wide at the top, and about four feet deep. It unites by navigation the internal trade of the great marts of London, Liverpool, Hull, and Bristol. The branches that extend from it in every direction are very numerous, and serve to connect the great shipping ports with all those districts, in the centre of the kingdom, which produce those heavy commodities of which the weight would make them almost worthless without the means of cheap conveyance to distant markets</p><p>That great work, the railroad from Liverpool to Birmingham, has been completed. In proceeding northward it enters this county about a mile from Birmingham, and con tinues in it for the distance of forty-five miles, when it enters Cheshire. The whole distance of ninety-seven miles is commonly performed in four hours and a half, including stop pages. The towns which, though not on the immediate line of the road, are in communication with it, and at only a few miles distance, are, in this county, West Bromwick, Walsall, Wolverhampton, Stafford, Stone, Eccleshall, Utto exeter, Newcastle-under-Lyne, Stoke-upon-Trent, and the Potteries. After passing through Cheshire and entering Lancashire, it separates into two branches at Newton, the right proceeding to Manchester, and the left to Liverpool, at the distance of ten miles from each of these towns.</p><p>The chief mineral productions of the county are iron and coal, and these arc so copious that they appear to be almost inexhaustible. Upwards of 50,000 acres have been already ascertained to have beneath them beds of coal ; and not withstanding the length of time, and the extent to which they have been worked, it is calculated that not one-tenth</p><p>of their contents has been yet consumed. The strata of this mineral, in the mines already worked, vary in thick ness from twenty-four to thirty-six feet. Every portion of the coal district abounds in iron ore ; and the strata of that mineral are generally found beneath a stratum of coal. Copper and lead are also raised, but not to an extent nearly approaching that of iron. Limestone, freestone, alabaster, marble, ochre, gypsum, and clays of various descriptions, applicable to the purposes of the potteries, are most abundantly extracted from the bowels of the earth. Though salt springs are both copious and richly impregnated with that mineral, no rock salt has yet been discovered ; but it is supposed there are some abundant repositories of it be neath the surface.</p><p>The relative proportion of the employment of the several families shows the great preponderance of manufacturing labour in this county. The whole of the southern part is occupied in the different working of metals. Wolverhampton is the chief seat of the manufacture of locks, keys, hinges, bolts, and the heavier kinds of iron ware. Walsall furnishes buckles, bitts, stirrups, spurs, and all the kinds of hardware used by saddlers. Wednesbury supplies guns, iron axle-trees, saws, trowels, hammers, edge tools, and cast iron work of every kind. Almost all the villages in the vicinity of these towns contribute in a greater or less degree to supply part of the work for which the town nearest to them is the great mart.</p><p>The northern part of Staffordshire is celebrated for the excellence of its earthenware, with which it supplies the consumption of the greater portion of the civilized world. The great extension of this manufacture has been owing to the scientific skill and persevering energy of one distinguished individual, the late Mr. Wedgew∞d ; whose combinations of the different earths, and study of the arts of design, have given a value to that which before was almost worthless, and increased to a most wonderful extent the wealth of his neighbourhood, and the number and comfort of its inhabitants. By means of the canals, the pipeclay from Dorsetshire and Devonshire, and the flints from Kent, are brought to the spots where the clays and coal abound ; and the finished goods, by the same means, are conveyed to the great shipping ports, from whence they are distributed to all parts of the globe. Salt is made from natural springs at Shirleyweck, and of late, at Lord Talbot’s works at Ingestrie, to such an extent as to supply all those parts of the middle of the kingdom which are not in more close connection with the refineries of Northwich or Droitwich. There are some respectable establishments at Cheadle for making brass and copper goods. Shoes are manufactured on an ex tensive scale at Stafford and at Newcastle. At Tamworth are great works for printing calicoes. Burton has ale-breweries of great celebrity, with manufactures of hats, and of several kinds of cotton goods. At Leek there are large and flourishing establishments for ribbons, handkerchiefs, ferrets, galloons, and other kinds of silk goods.</p><p>In order to exhibit the proportion of employment in the several branches of industry, we extract the notices from the returns under the population of 11 Geo. IV., cap. 30.	“ Eastward of West Bromwich, 1000 males</p><p>are employed in the further preparation of iron for the forges and workshops; 2200 are employed at Tipton, 1200 at Walsall, 740 at Willenhall, 157 at Wednesfield, 444 at Wednesbury, and 200 at Rowley Regis, in making guns and other firearms, gas-tubes, chains, spades, locks and keys, &amp;c. &amp;c. &amp;c. ; and in producing the more various and complex aids of human industry, which are comprehended under the name of machinery. At the villages of Smith wick and Handworth, near to Birmingham, 150 men are similarly occupied. Wolverhampton contains 2000 men, who, in addition to articles before mentioned, are employed in making domestic fire-irons, and turned and japanned iron</p></body></text></TEI>