<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T17:34:40Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>tragedies, of which seven only have escaped the ravages of time. Having testified his love of his country by refusing to leave it, though invited by many kings, and having en joyed the uninterrupted esteem and affection of his fellow citizens, which neither the gallant actions and sublime genius of Æschylus, nor the tender spirit and philosophic virtue of Euripides, could secure to them, he died in the beginning of the year 405, at the very advanced age of ninety.@@<hi rend="superscript">1</hi> The burial-place of his ancestors was at Decelia, which the'La cedæmonians had at that time seized and fortified : but Lysander, the Spartan chief, permitted the Athenians to inter their deceased poet ; and they paid him all the honours due to his love of his country, integrity of life, and high poetic excellence. Æschylus had at once seized the highest post of honour in the field of poetry, the true sublime : to that eminence his claim could not be disputed. Sophocles had a noble elevation of mind, but tempered with so fine a taste, and so chastened a judgment, that he never passed the bounds of propriety. Under his conduct the tragic muse appeared with the chaste dignity of some noble matron at a religious solemnity ; harmony is in her voice, and grace in all her motions. From him the theatre received some additional embellishments ; but his distinguished excellence is in the judicious disposition of the fable, and so nice a connection and dependence of the parts on each other, that they all conduce to make the event not only probable, but even necessary. This is peculiarly admirable in his King OEdipus ; and in this important point he is far superior to every other dramatic writer of antiquity.</p><p>The ingratitude of the children of Sophocles is well known. They wished to become immediate masters of their father’s possessions, and therefore, tired of his long life, they accus ed him before the Areopagus of insanity. The only defence the poet made, was to read his tragedy of Œdipus at Colo nos, which he had lately finished ; and he then asked his judges, whether the author of such a performance could be charged with insanity. The father upon this was acquitted, and the children returned home covered with shame and confusion.</p><p>The editions of Sophocles are very numerous, and some of them very elaborate, but we can only enumerate the more conspicuous. The <hi rend="italic">editio princeps</hi> was published by Aldus, Venet. 1502, 8vo. This was followed by an edition published by the heirs of P. Junta, Florent. 1522, 4to; and another published by B. Junta, Florent. 1547, 4to. The text of Aldus was the basis of all the editions which preceded that of Tumebus, Paris. 1553, 4to. This is among the best of the early editions. We must not omit those of H. Stephanus, Paris. 1568, 4to, and of Canter, Antverp. 1579, 12mo. The text of Tumebus was chiefly adopted in all the succeeding editions till that of Brunck, Argent. 1786, 2 tom. 4to. This is a very elaborate as well as splendid edition, and strikingly displays the editor’s acute ness and learning. The same able critic published two octavo editions, each in two volumes. We now descend to the edition of Erfurdt, Lips. 180211, 8 tom. 8vo. The tragedies of Sophocles have been translated into many different languages. An English version, which was favour ably received, was published by Dr Francklin, Greek professor at Cambridge, Lond. 1759, 2 vols. 4to. Another was subsequently published by Mr Potter, Lond. 1788, 4to.</p><p>SOPING, a district or principality of the island of Cele bes, formerly one of the most extensive in the country. In 1775 it was governed by its own king.</p><p>SOPRA, a river of Hindustan, which rises in the province of Malwah, and joins the Gilly Sinde river, after which their united streams fall into the Chumbul.</p><p>SORA, a city of Italy, in the Neapolitan province of Terra di Lavoro, the capital of a district of its own name.</p><p>It stands on the banks of the river Garigliano, is the seat of a bishop, and, besides the cathedral, has five churches, and 7950 inhabitants.</p><p>SORAU, a circle of Prussia, in the government of Frankfurt, which extends over 513 square miles, with 46,400 inhabitants. The capital is the town of the same name. It stands on a large plain, is well built, and contains 430 houses, with 4060 inhabitants, who manufacture large quantities of cotton goods.</p><p>SORBONNE, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Sorbon,</hi> the house or college of the faculty of theology established in the old university of Paris. It was founded in 1252, by St Louis, or rather by Robert de Sorbon his confessor and almoner, first canon of Cambray, and afterwards of the cathedral of Paris ; who gave his own name to it, which he himself took from the village of Sorbon or Serbon, near Sens, where he was born. The foundation was laid in 1250; Queen Blanche, in the absence of her husband, furnishing him with a house which had formerly been the palace of Julian the apostate. The king afterwards gave him all the houses he had in the same place, in exchange for some others. The college was magnificently rebuilt by the Cardinal de Richelieu. The institution was designed for the use of poor students in divinity.</p><p>SORBONNE was also used in general for the whole faculty of theology at Paris, as the assemblies of the whole body were held in the house of the Sorbonne, and the bachelors of the other houses of the faculty came hither to hold their <hi rend="italic">sοrbonnique,</hi> or act for being admitted doctor of divinity.</p><p>SORCERY, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Magic,</hi> the power which some persons were formerly supposed to possess, of commanding the devil and the infernal spirits, by skill in charms and invocations, and of soothing them by fumigations. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Magic</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Ap </hi>PARITIONS.</p><p>SORIA, one of the four departments into which the pro vince of Old Castille, in Spain, is divided. Its extent is 341 square leagues, and its population amounts to 257,537 souls. It is in general a hilly district, and in some parts very mountainous. The plains are fertile, especially that of Rioja, and yield abundance of wheat and barley, and in some years it has a surplus of both these productions. Its wine is good, but not abundant ; and it is deficient in a supply of oil, which is procured from the more southern provinces. This province furnishes to commerce a great proportion of the fine wool of the merinos. That of Soria is not equal in fineness to what is produced in Segovia, but is however of a good quality ; and the quantity annually sent away amounts to about 2,250,000 pounds.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Soria</hi>, a city of Spain, in New Castille, the capital of the department of that name. It is situated on the north bank of the river Duero, but too near its source to derive any benefit as to navigation. In the vicinity there are excellent pastures for sheep, with houses of various kinds to shelter them when the weather is more than usually inclement, or when they are shorn. It is not a large city, nor are the public buildings of a nature to merit a detailed description ; but the extensive ruins of the ancient Numantia invite the notice of every lover of Roman antiquities. Soria contains thirteen churches, eleven monasteries, four hospitals, and 6000 inhabitants. The manufacture of silk stockings employs eightytwo looms. Some of the inhabitants are employed in soapboiling, tanning, and in the manufacture of cloth. Lat. 4L 48. N.</p><p>SORIANG, a river of Celebes, on the west coast, which falls into the sea.</p><p>SORITES, in <hi rend="italic">Logic,</hi> a species of reasoning, in which a great number of propositions are so linked together, that the predicate of the one becomes continually the subject of the next following, till at last a conclusion is formed by bringing together the subject of the first proposition and</p><p><hi rend="superscript">@@@,</hi> Clinton's Fasti Hellenici, vol. ii. p. 23, 57, 83.</p></body></text></TEI>