<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T17:34:28Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>SOLITARIES, a denomination of nuns of St. Peter of Alcantara, instituted in 1676. The design of the institution was to imitate the severe penitent life of that saint. Thus they were to keep a continual silence ; never to open their mouths to a stranger; to employ their time wholly in spiritual exercises, and leave their temporal concerns to a number of maids, who had a particular superior in a sepa- rate part of the monastery. They were always to go barefooted, without sandals ; gird themselves with a thick cord, and wear no linen.</p><p>SOLITARY <hi rend="smallcaps">Island,</hi> in the South Pacific ocean, disco- vered by Mendana in 1595. It is low, and surrounded with rocks. Long. 178. 20. W. Lat. 10. 4. S.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Solitary</hi> <hi rend="italic">Islands,</hi> a cluster of small islands near the east coast of New Holland. Lat. 30. 8. S.</p><p>SOLO, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Saura-Corta,</hi> an inland town of Java, the capital of a district, and the residence of an emperor. It is large and populous, intersected with broad and shaded avenues or streets, running at right angles. The emperor’s palace is very spacious, and comprises several palaces in its area. The European town and port are very neat. The resident’s house is also a large and handsome building. A fine river, which flows near the town, and falls into the harbour of Grepie, affords in the rainy season a ready con- veyance for the various productions of a large tract of coun- try, in exchange for commodities which are sent up in boats from the coast.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Solo, </hi><hi rend="italic">(Ital.)</hi> a term used in musical compositions of se- veral parts, to mark those voices or instruments that are to perform alone or in a more prominent manner ; as, <hi rend="italic">sofrano solo, violino solo, See.</hi> The plural is used when two or more voices or instruments of the same name are to per- form alone. <hi rend="italic">Solo</hi> is also a name given to a composition written for a single instrument, such as a violin, an oboe, a flute, &amp;c., which is accompanied by a bass for the violon- cello, or a thorough-bass for the pianoforte.</p><p>SOLOFRA, a city of Italy, in the Neapolitan province Ulteriore. It contains three churches and 6050 inhabi- tants, who are manufacturers of gold and silver articles, of leather and parchment, and are celebrated for their salted hams and bacon.</p><p>SOLLER, a town in Majorca, one of the Balearic islands in the Mediterranean, belonging to Spain. The valley in which it stands is productive of olives and oranges. It is situated in Lat. 39∙ 61., and contains 5614 inhabitants.</p><p>SOLOMBO, GREAT, a small island in the Eastern seas, of a moderate height. Long. 114. 45. E. Lat. 5. 36. S. Little Solombo is near the north-east coast of Great So- 1ombo.</p><p>SOLOMON, the son of David king of Israel, renowned in Scripture for his wisdom, riches, and magnificent temple and other buildings. Towards the end of his life he sullied his former glory by his apostacy from God ; from which cause vengeance was denounced against his house and nation. He died about 977 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Solomon's </hi><hi rend="italic">Islands.</hi> This group is in the South Pacific ocean, situated chiefly between long. 155° and 160° E. lat. 5° and 12° S. Little is known of the precise situation or number of these islands. The longest are Ysabel, Gua- dalcanar, San Cristoval, and an island called New Georgia. The first two are affirmed by the Spaniards to be very large islands ; the latter nearly seventy miles in extent. Geor- gia is still larger, and San Cristoval is not less than sixty. These islands were discovered in 1567.</p><p>SOLON, one of the seven wise men of Greece, was born at Salamis, of Athenian parente, who were descended from Codrus. His father leaving little patrimony, he had recourse to merchandise for his subsistence. He had, how- ever, a greater thirst after knowledge and fame than after riches, and made his mercantile voyages subservient to the increase of his intellectual treasures. He very early cultivated</p><p>the art of poetry, and applied himself to the study of moral and civil wisdom. When the Athenians, tired out with a long and troublesome war with the Megarensians, for the recovery of the isle of Salamis, prohibited any one, under pain of death, to propose the renewal of their claim to that island, Solon thinking the prohibition dishonourable to the state, and finding many of the younger citizens de- sirous to revive the war, feigned himself mad, and took care to have the report of his insanity spread through the city. In the mean time he composed an elegy adapted to the state of public affairs, and committed it to memory. Every thing being thus prepared, he sallied forth into the market-place with the kind of cap on his head which was commonly worn by sick persons, and ascending the herald’s stand, he delivered, to a numerous crowd, his lamentation for the desertion of Salamis. The verses were heard with general applause; Pisistratus seconded his advice, and urged the people to renew the war. The decree was immediately repealed ; the claim to Salamis was resumed ; and the conduct of the war was committed to Solon and Pisistratus, who by means of a stratagem defeated the Megarensians and recovered the island.</p><p>His popularity was extended through Greece in consequence of a successful alliance which he formed among the states in defence of the temple at Delphi against the Cirrhæans. When dissensions had arisen at Athens be- tween the rich creditors and their poor debtors, Solon was created archon, with the united power of supreme legislator and magistrate. He soon restored harmony between the rich and poor. He cancelled the debts which had proved the occasion of so much oppression ; and ordained that in future no creditor should be allowed to seize the body of the debtor for his security. He made a new distribution of the people, instituted new courts of judicature, and fram- ed a judicious code of laws, which afterwards became the basis of the laws of the twelve Tables in Rome. Among his criminal laws are many wise and excellent regulations ; but the code is necessarily defective with respect to those prin- ciples which must be derived from the knowledge of the true God, and of pure morality, as the certain foundations of national happiness. Two of them in particular were very exceptionable ; the permission of a voluntary exile to per- sons that had been guilty of premeditated murder, and the appointment of a less severe punishment for a rape than for seduction. Those who wish to see accurately stated the comparative excellence of the laws of Moses, of Lycurgus, and Solon, may consult the prize Dissertations relative to natural and revealed religion, published by the Teylerian Society of Haarlem, vol. ix.</p><p>The interview which Solon is said to have had with Crœsus king of Lydia ; the solid remarks of the sage after surveying the monarch’s wealth ; the recollection of those remarks by Crœsus when doomed to die, and the noble conduct of Cyrus on that occasion, are known to every school- boy. Solon died in the island of Cyprus at a very advan- ced age. Statues were erected to his memory both at Athens and in Salamis. His thirst after knowledge con- tinued to the last : “ I grow old,’’ said he, “ learning many things.” Among the apophthegms and precepts which have been ascribed to Solon, are the following : Laws are like cobwebs, that entangle the weak, but are broken by the strong. He who has learned to obey, will know how to command. In all things let reason be your guide. Dili- gently contemplate excellent things. In every thing that you do, consider the end.</p><p>The chronology of his life is involved in no small obscurity. His legislation may, with some degree of con- fidence, be referred to the year 594 before Christ ; but, as a very learned and able chronologer has remarked, since both his age and the time of his death are doubtful, nothing can be with certainty affirmed of the year of his</p></body></text></TEI>