<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/>         </publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb09-21-r04-0066-01" facs="encyclopediabrit21newyrich_raw_0078.jp2" type="entry">

<p><label>RUSSELL</label>
John Scott (1808-1882), was born in 1808 near Glasgow, a “son of the manse,” and was at first destined for the ministry. But this intention on his father’s part was changed in consequence of the boy’s early leanings towards practical science. He attended in succession the universities of St Andrews, Edinburgh, and Glasgow,— taking his degree in the last-named at the age of sixteen. After spending a couple of years in workshops, he settled in Edinburgh as a lecturer on science, and soon collected large classes. In 1832-33 he was engaged to give the natural philosophy course at the university, the chair having] become vacant by the death of Leslie. In the following year he began that remarkable series of observations on waves whose results, besides being of very great scientific importance, were the chief determining factor of his subsequent practical career. Having been consulted as to the possibility of applying steam-navigation to the Edinburgh and Glasgow Canal, he replied that the question could not be answered without experiments, and that ho was willing to undertake such if a portion of the canal were placed at his disposal. The results of this inquiry are to be found in the <hi rend="italic">Transactions of the Royal Society of Edinburgh</hi> (vol. xiv.), and in the <hi rend="italic">British Association Reports</hi> (seventh meeting). We need not say more than that the existence of the <hi rend="italic">long wave,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">wave of translation,</hi> as well as many of its most important features, were here first recognized, and (to give one very simple idea of the value of the investigation) that it was clearly pointed out <hi rend="italic">why</hi> there is a special rate, depending on the depth of the water, at which a canal-boat can be towed at the least expenditure of effort by the horse. The elementary mathematical theory of the long wave is very simple, and was soon supplied by commentators on Scott Russell’s work ; a more complete investigation has been since given by Stokes ; and the subject may be considered äs certainly devoid of any special mystery. Russell held an opposite opinion, and it led him to many extraordinary and groundless speculations, some of which have been published in a posthumous volume, <hi rend="italic">The Wave of Translation</hi> (1885). His observations led him to propose and experiment on a new system of shaping vessels, which is known as the w <hi rend="italic">ave system.</hi> This culminated in the building of the enormous and unique “Great Eastern,” of which it has been recently remarked by a competent authority that “ it is probable that, if a new ‘ Great Eastern ’ were now to be built, the system of construction employed by Mr Scott Russell would be followed exactly.”</p><p>Though his fame will rest chiefly on the two great steps we have just mentioned, Scott Russell’s activity and ingenuity displayed themselves in many other fields,— steam-coaches for roads, improvements in boilers and in marine engines, the immense iron dome of the Vienna exhibition, cellular double bottoms for iron ships, Ac. Along with Mr Stafford Northcote (now Lord Iddesleigh), he was joint secretary of the Great Exhibition of 1851 ; and he was one of the chief founders of the Institution of Naval Architects, from the twenty-third volume of whose <hi rend="italic">Transactions</hi> we have extracted much of what is stated above. Russell contributed the articles Steam, Steam-Engine, Steam Navigation, &amp;c., to the 7th edition of the <hi rend="italic">Encyclopædia Britannica.</hi> He died at Ventnor. June 8, 1882.</p>
<pb xml:id="eb09-21-r04-0067" facs="encyclopediabrit21newyrich_raw_0083.jp2"/>

</div></body></text></TEI>