<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/>         </publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb09-21-r03-0028-02" facs="encyclopediabrit21newyrich_raw_0040.jp2" type="entry">

<p><label>ROVEREDO</label>
(in German sometimes <hi rend="italic">Rofreit),</hi> one of the chief industrial cities in South Tyrol, and, after Trent, the chief seat of the Tyrolese silk industry, is situated on the left bank of the Adige (Etsch), in the fertile Val Lagarina, 35 miles north of Verona and IOO miles south of Innsbruck. Though there are several open places within the town, the streets, except in the newer quarters, are narrow, crooked, and uneven. Of the two parish churches, S. Marco dates from the 15th century and Sta Maria del Carmine from 1678. The only other interesting building is the quaint old castle known as Castell Junk. As an active trading town and administrative centre Roveredo is well equipped with commercial, judicial, educational, and benevolent institutions. Though the district between Trent and Verona yields about 120,000 lb of silk annually, the silk industry of Roveredo, introduced in the 16th century, has declined during the last fifty years. The establishments id which the cocoons are unwound <hi rend="italic">(Jilande)</hi> are distinct from those in which the silk is spun <hi rend="italic">(Jilatoje).</hi> The silk is not woven at Roveredo. Paper and leather are the other chief manufactures of the place ; and a brisk trade in southern fruits and red wine is carried on. The population is 8864.</p><p>The origin of Roveredo is probably to be traced to the founding of the castle by William of Castelbarco-Lizzauaabout 1300. Later it passed to the emperor Frederick of the Empty Pockets, who sold it to Venice in 1413. The treaty of Cambray transferred it from Venice to the emperor Maximilian in 1510, since which time it has shared the fate of southern Tyrol, finally passing to Austria in 1814. In September 1709 the French under Massena won a victory over the Austrians near Roveredo. Near the neighbouring village of St Marco are the traces of a destructive landslip in 883, described in the <hi rend="italic">Inferno</hi> (xii. 4-9) by Dante, who spent part of his exile in 1302 in a castle near Lizzana.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>