<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>some man ; and his mind was as amiable as his person. He lived beloved ; and at his death he had the honour to be lamented by Pope, in an epitaph which is printed in Pope’s works, although it was not affixed on Mr Rowe’s monument in Westminster Abbey, where he was interred, in the poets’ corner, opposite to Chaucer.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Rowe, </hi><hi rend="italic">Elizabeth,</hi>  an English lady, eminent for her writings both in prose and verse, was bom at Ilchester, in Somersetshire, in 1674, being the daughter of worthy parents, Mr Walter Singer and Mrs Elizabeth Portnel. There being a great affinity between painting and poetry, this lady, who had a vein for the one, naturally had a taste for the other. She was also very fond of music, chiefly of the grave and solemn kind, as best suited the grandeur of her sentiments and the sublimity of her devotion. But poetry was her favourite employment, her distinguishing excellence ; and so prevalent was her genius this way, that her prose is all poetical. In 1696, a collection of her poems was published at the desire of two friends. Her paraphrase on the thirty-eighth chapter of Job w<hi rend="sup">r</hi>as written at the request of Bishop Ken. She had no other tutor for the French and Italian languages than Mr Thynne, who willingly took the trouble upon himself. Her shining merit, with the charms of her person and conversation, had procured her many admirers. Amongst others, it is said, the famous Mr Prior made his addresses to her ; but Mr Thomas Rowe was destined to be the happy man. This gentleman was honourably descended ; and his superior genius, and insatiable thirst after knowledge, were conspicuous in his earliest years. He had formed a design to compile the lives of all the illustrious persons in antiquity omitted by Plutarch ; which, indeed, he partly executed, and eight lives were published after his decease. They were translated into French by the Abbé Bellenger in 1734. He spoke with ease and fluency, and had a trank and benevolent temper, an inexhaustible fund of wit, and a communicative disposition. Such was the man who, charmed with the person, character, and writings of our authoress, married her in 1710, and made it his study to repay the felicity with which she crowned his life. But too intense an application to study, beyond what the delicacy of his frame would bear, broke his health, and threw him into a consumption, which put a period to his life in May 1715, when he had but just passed the twenty-eighth year of his age. Mrs Rowe wrote a beautiful elegy on his death ; and continued to the last moments of her life to express the highest veneration and affection for his memory. As soon after his decease as her affairs would permit, she indulged her inclination for solitude by retiring to Frome, in Somersetshire, in the neighbourhood of which place lay the greatest part of her estate. In this recess it was that she composed the most celebrated of her works, Friendship in Death, and the Letters Moral and Entertaining. In 1736, she published the History of Joseph, a poem which she had written in her younger years. But she did not long survive this publication ; for she died of an apoplexy, as was supposed, on the 20th ofFebruary 1736-1737. In her cabinet were found letters to several of her friends, which she had ordered to be delivered immediately after her decease. Dr Isaac Watts, agreeably to her request, revised and published, in 1737, her devotions, under the title of Devout Exercises of the Heart in Meditation and Soliloquy, Praise and Prayer ; and, in 1739, her Miscellaneous Works, in prose and verse, were published in two volumes 8vo, with an account of her life and writings prefixed.</p><p>ROWEL, amongst farriers, a kind of issue, answering to what in surgery is called a seton.</p><p>ROWLEY, a monk who is said to have flourished at Bristol in the fifteenth century. Of the poems attributed to him various opinions have been entertained, which we have noticed under the article on Chatterton.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Rowley, </hi><hi rend="italic">William,</hi>  who stands in the third class of dramatic writers, lived in the reign of King Charles I. and received his education at the University of Cambridge ; but whether he took any degree there, is not evident, there beng but few particulars preserved in regard to him, except his close intimacy and connection with all the principal wits and poetical geniuses of that age, by whom he was well beloved, and with some of whom he joined in their writings. Wood styles him “ the ornament, for wit and ingenuity, of Pembroke Hall in Cambridge.” In a word, he was a very great benefactor to the English stage, having, exclusively of his aid lent to Middleton, Day, Heywood, Webster, and others, left us five plays of his own composition, and one in which even the immortal Shakspeare afforded him some assistance.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Rowley Regis, a town of the parish of Dudley, in Worcestershire, although within the hundred of Seisdon, in Staffordshire, and chiefly inhabited by nail-makers and other workers in iron. The population amounted in 1901 to 5027, in 1811 to 4974, in 1821 to 6062, and in 1831 to 7438.</hi></p><p>ROWNING, John, an English mathematician and philosopher of considerable ingenuity, was fellow of Magdalen College, Cambridge, and afterwards rector of Anderby in Lincolnshire, in the gift of that society. He constantly attended the meetings of the Spalding Society, and was a man of an extraordinary philosophical habit of mind, whilst at the same time his dispositions were social and cheerful. His genius was peculiarly fitted for mechanical contrivances or inventions. He published a compendious system of Natural Philosophy at Cambridge, in the year 1738, in two volumes 8vo; a work of much ingenuity, which has gone through several editions. He likewise inserted two pieces in the Philosophical Transactions, namely, a description of a barometer, wherein the scale of variation may be increased at pleasure (vol. xxxviii. p. 39); and directions for making a machine for finding the roots of equations universally, together with the manner in which it should be used (vol. lx. p. 240). He died at his lodgings in Carey Street, near Lincoln’s-Inn Fields, in the end of November 1771, in the seventy-second year of his age. Though a man both ingenious and pleasant, his external appearance was rather forbidding, being tall, and low in the shoulders, with his countenance down-looking and sallow.</p><p>ROXBURGHSHIRE, a county in Scotland, on its south-eastern extremity, where it joins England, situated between 55. 6. and 55. 43. north latitude, and between 2. 12. and 3. 7. west longitude from Greenwich. It is sometimes called Teviotdale, from its principal river the Teviot, but improperly, as it also includes a tract called Liddesdale on the south-west, which is unconnected with the Teviot. Its boundaries are Berwickshire, from which it is separated in part by the river Tweed on the north, Selkirkshire and Dumfriesshire on the west and south-west, and the English counties of Cumberland and Northumberland on the south-east and east. Between Berwickshire and Selkirkshire a small tract touches the county of Mid-Lothian; on the south, between Dumfriesshire and Cumberland, the county terminates almost in a point; on the west it in some places surrounds small portions of Selkirkshire, and in others projects into that county; and it has the Cheviot Hills on the east, the outline being exceedingly irregular on all sides. Its greatest length is nearly forty-one miles, and its greatest breadth about thirty miles. According to the latest authorities, its area is 715 square miles, or 457,600 English acres, containing thirty-two entire parishes, and part of other four, which properly belong to the counties adjoining. In an agricultural view, it may be considered as divided into arable land and hilly pasture ; the pasture land, estimated at about three fifths of the whole, occupying the eastern, southern, and western quarters, and surrounding, in a circular form, the arable, which lies on the north and north-east sides of the county. The arable, pasture, and</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>