<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>peasants who dwelt on the noblemen’s estates, were almost ' completely slaves, and transferable with the land on which they dwelt. An attempt to annul this barbarous vassalage had been made, both by Boris and by Schuiskoy ; but, from the opposition of the nobles, it was abandoned.</p><p>The laws then in force consisted partly of the municipal laws drawn up for the state of Novgorod by Yaroslaf, and partly of an amended code, called <hi rend="italic">Sudebnih,</hi>  promulgated by Ivan Vasiliivitch II. By this Sudebnik the administration of the laws was made uniform throughout the empire, and particular magistrates were appointed in the several towns and districts, all subject to the czar as their chief. The Sudebnik consisted of ninety-seven articles, all containing civil laws; as the penal statutes are only briefly mentioned in some articles, so as to appear either connected with the civil, or as serving to illustrate them. The criminal laws were contained in a separate code, called <hi rend="italic">Gubnaia Gramota,</hi>  which is now lost, but is referred to in the civil code. In neither of these codes is there any mention of ecclesiastical affairs ; but these were regulated by a set of canons drawn up in 1542, under the inspection of Ivan Vasiliivitch, in a grand council held at Moscow. In the civil statutes of the Sudebnik, theft was punished in the first instance by restitution ; or, if the thief were unable to restore the property stolen, he became the slave of the injured party till by his labour he had made sufficient compensation. Of murder nothing is said, except where the person slain was a lord or master, when the murderer was to be punished with death. There is no mention of torture, except in cases of theft.</p><p>Before the accession of the house of Romanof, the commercial intercourse which the cities of Novgorod and Pscov, formerly held with the Hanse Towns, had entirely ceased ; but this was in some degree compensated by the newly established trade between Russia and England, the centre of which was Archangel. This trade had been lately increased by the products derived from the acquisition of Siberia, in exchange for which the English principally supplied the Russians with broad cloth. In 1568, an English counting-house was established at Moscow, and about the same time the Russian Company was incorporated. Previously to the fifteenth century, the trade of the Russians had been carried on merely by barter; but during that century the coinage of money commenced at Novgorod and Pscov; and from this time their commerce was placed on an equal footing with that of the other European nations.</p><p>Except in the article of commerce, the Russians were deplorably behind the rest of Europe; and though attempts had been made by Ivan <hi rend="italic">L,</hi>  Ivan Vasiliivitch II., and Boris, to cultivate their manners and to improve the state of their arts and manufactures, these attempts had failed of success. @@<hi rend="sup">1</hi></p><p>At the accession of Mikhail, who was crowned in June 1613, the Swedes and Poles were in possession of several parts of the empire ; and to dislodge these intruders was<hi rend="sup">1 </hi>the first object of the new czar. Aware of the difficulty of) contending at once with both these formidable enemies, hei began by negotiating a treaty of peace with Sweden. This was not effected without considerable sacrifices. Mikhail agreed to give up Ingria and Karelia, and to evacuate Es-thonia and Livonia. Thus freed from his most dangerous enemy, he prepared to oppose the Poles, of whom a numerous body had entered Russia, to support the claims of their king’s son Vladislaf. Mikhail proceeded, however, in a very wary manner, and instead of opposing the invaders in the open field, he entrapped them by ambuscades, or allured them into districts already desolated, where they suffered so much from cold and hunger, that in 1619 they agreed to a cessation of hostilities for fourteen years and a half, on condition that the Russians should cede to Poland the government of Smolensk.</p><p>Thus freed from external enemies on terms which, though not very honourable, were the best that the posture of his affairs admitted, Mikhail applied himself to arranging the internal economy of his empire. He began by placing his father at the head of the church, by conferring on him the dignity of patriarch, which had become vacant. The counsels of this venerable man were of great advantage to the emperor, and contributed to preserve that peace and tranquillity by which his reign was in general distinguished. His next step was to form treaties of alliance with the principal commercial states of Europe. He accordingly sent ambassadors into England, Denmark, Holland, and the German empire ; and Russia, which had hitherto been considered rather as an Asiatic than a European power, became so respectable in the eyes of her northern neighbours, that they vied with each other in their eagerness for establishing with her commercial relations.</p><p>Mikhail also commenced those improvements of the laws which we shall presently see more fully executed by his son and successor; but the tide of party ran so high, that he could effect only a very imperfect reformation. He was also obliged to put his frontiers in a state of defence, by providing for the expiration of the truce with Poland, which now drew nigh ; and as no permanent peace had been established, both parties began to prepare for a renewal of hostilities. Indeed the armistice was broken by the Russians, who, on the death of Sigismund, king of Poland, appeared before Smolensk, justifying the infringement of the treaty, on the pretence that it was concluded with Sigismund, and not</p><p>@@@ Tooke furnishes the following characteristic features of the state of Russia in the sixteenth century.</p><p>The houses were in general of timber, and badly constructed, except that in Moscow and other great town3 there were a few built of brick.</p><p>That contempt for the female sex which is invariably a characteristic of defective civilization, was conspicuous among the Russians. The women were kept in a state of perfect bondage, and it was thought a great instance of liberality if a stranger were but permitted to see them. They were scarcely ever allowed to quit the house, even for the purpose of going to church, though attendance on divine worship was considered of the highest importance.</p><p>The men of the middle ranks always repaired about noon to the market, where they transacted business, conversed about public affairs, and attended the courts of judicature to hear the causes that were going forward. In agreements and bargains the highest asseveration was, “ If I keep not my word, may it turn to my infamy;” a custom extremely honourable to the nation, as they held the disgrace of having forfeited their word to be the deepest degradation.</p><p>If the wife was so dependent on her husband, the child was still more dependent on his father; for parents were allowed to sell their children. Masters and servants entered into a mutual contract respecting the terms of their connection; and a written copy of this agreement was deposited in the proper court, where, if either party broke the contract, the other might lodge his complaint.</p><p>Single combat still continued to be the last resource in deciding a cause ; and to this the judge resorted in cases which he knew not otherwise how to determine. But duels out of court were strictly prohibited ; and when these took place, and either party fell, the survivor was regarded as a murderer, and punished accordingly. Personal vengeance was forbidden, under the strictest penalty. The nobles were universally soldiers, and were obliged to appear when summoned, to assist the prince in his wars. Till the end of the sixteenth century the boor was not bound to any particular master. He tilled the ground of a nobleman for a certain time on stated conditions. Thus he either received part of the harvest or of the cattle, a portion of wood, hay, &amp;c.; or he worked five days for the master, and on the sixth was at liberty to till a piece of ground set apart for his use. At tie expiration of the term agreed on, either party might give up the contract; the boor might remove to another master, and the master dismiss the boor that did not suit him.</p></body></text></TEI>