<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Baltic Sea. Thus, then, there is an easy transport of goods insured from the remotest governments of the empire to  the Caspian Sea, and thence to the Transcaucasian territory. There is also on the other side a communication by the Black Sea, but it does not present so many advantages as that by the Caspian. Our space, however, will not allow us to pursue the subject further.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Islands in the Polar and Eastern Oceans.</hi></p><p>In the Polar Ocean are the groups of New Siberia and of the Bear’s Island. The first consists of four large and many smaller islands. They are covered with snow during the greater part of the year ; their surface is generally rocky, and on some of them there are marks of volcanoes. They are chiefly remarkable for the bones and teeth of the mammoth, rhinoceros, buffalo, and other animals, which are found upon and beneath the surface of the ground. It was the search for this ivory which originally induced the Russians to visit these islands ; and their first expedition for exploring them was equipped in 1820. These islands do not appear to be inhabited, though traces of human beings have been occasionally discovered by the Russians engaged in the fisheries. The Bear’s Island group consists of six small islands, with several kinds of plants and shrubs on them, but no trees, although their shores are found to be covered with large drift-wood. The southernmost point of these islands is in latitude 69° 5', and they extend to latitude 76° 20'. Their longitude is between 154° and 183° 50' east from Greenwich.</p><p>In the Eastern Ocean the islands are thus classed :</p><p><hi rend="italic">1 st,</hi>  The islands of Gevosbewy and Nelken, in Behring’s Straits, in latitude 65° 4', with about 400 people.</p><p><hi rend="italic">2d,</hi>  St Lawrence, latitude 63° 40<hi rend="sup">z</hi>, and longitude 190° 26', and three smaller islands on the south-east of it.</p><p><hi rend="italic">3d,</hi>  St Mathew’s, in latitude 60°, in the Sea of Kamts-chatka, consisting of three islands, one of which was named by some early British navigators Pinnacle Island.</p><p><hi rend="italic">4th</hi>, The Prebelow Islands, in latitude 57°. Two of them have been named St Paul and St George. The former is about twenty-eight miles long and twenty broad, and both are well stocked with animals whose furs are valuable.</p><p><hi rend="italic">5th,</hi>  The Aleutian Islands. This is a chain of islands extending from the peninsula of Kamtschatka to the American peninsula of Alaschka, between 51° and 55° 10' north latitude, and 167° and 197° east longitude. (See Aleutian Islands.)</p><p><hi rend="italic">6tlι,</hi>  The Kurile Islands. This chain extends from north latitude43<hi rend="sup">0</hi>  48' to 50<hi rend="sup">o</hi>56', and from longitude 145° 5'to 156° 30' east. They are evidently of volcanic origin. In some of them good water is found, but others arc utterly destitute of it. The few inhabitants are of Japanese origin. Many of these islands have hitherto obtained no European names ; but nineteen of the most considerable have been named by the Russians.</p><p><hi rend="italic">American Russia.</hi></p><p>Russian America comprehends the north-west angle of the North American continent, as far as the 141st degree of longitude west from London, with a narrow stripe of coast reaching as far south as 55½° of north latitude. It occupies a surface of about 500,000 square miles, of which the useful soil forms but a very small proportion. Thick fogs continually brood over these shores. Some parts of the country, bristling with mountains of difficult access, present at every step impenetrable forests and extensive morasses ; others, wholly without vegetation, offer to the eye nothing but sterile rocks. In short, the nature of the climate, and that of the soil itself, equally oppose prodigious obstacles to agriculture. The Russians have therefore been obliged to imitate the aborigines, in renouncing all attempts to form permanent establishments in the interior, and in fixing their abode upon the borders of the sea ; it being there only that the chase, fishing, and trade, could furnish them with the means of subsistence.</p><p>The Russians who inhabit this remote part of the empire consist either of officers in the imperial navy or civil <hi rend="italic">employés,</hi>  who again quit these shores after a service of five years ; or else of mechanics and workmen sent by the American Company. These latter, whose engagement is for seven years, also return home upon that term having expired ; and even during the time of their sojourn in the colonies their names still remain upon the registers of their district, and the class to which they originally belonged. Exempted only from the conscription, they still continue to pay taxes ; in short, the place of their birth is still regarded as their legal abode. The aborigines of the continent, with the exception of three tribes, are exempted from taxes ; but they show a great reluctance to come under the restraints of civilization. On several of the numerous islands, as well as along the shores of the mainland, the Russian Company have hunting and fishing stations. The otter chase is the chief occupation in summer, together with the pursuit of aquatic birds and sea-calves. In winter, snares are laid for the white foxes ; and dogs regularly trained for the purpose track the zizel to its subterranean abodes.</p><p>Novo Arkhangelsk or New Archangel, situated in latitude 57° 3' and longitude 135° 20', is the head establishment. It has a fortress with a small garrison and forty pieces of cannon. Hospitals and schools are established at the company’s expense, which also takes upon itself the maintenance of the orphans and children of those among the tribes whose family is numerous. In these schools the children are taught reading, writing, arithmetic, and the precepts of religion. The priests attached to the churches of these colonies occasionally traverse the remotest regions, for the purpose of making converts ; but, as may well be believed, their success is not in proportion to their zeal. On the 1st of January 1836 there were in American Russia 711 Russians, 1110 Creoles, 9101 Aleutians, and 99 Kuriles, being 11,021 inhabitants in the various settlements.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">(r. r. r.)</hi></p><p>RUSSOOA, a village of Thibet, on the northern face of the Himalaya Mountains, which marks the frontier of the Nepaul dominions in this direction. Long. 85. 40. E. Lat. 28. 3. N.</p><p>RUSSOOLPOOR, a town of Hindustan, belonging to the nabob of Oude, in the province of Allahabad, forty miles north-west from the city and fortress of Allahabad. Long. 81. 25. E. Lat. 25. 57. N.</p><p>RUST, the calx or oxide of a metal, iron, for instance, formed by exposure to the air, or by corroding and dissolving its superficial parts by some menstruum. Water is the great instrument or agent in producing rust ; and hence oils and other fatty bodies secure metals from rust, water being no menstruum for oil, and therefore not able to make its way through it. Almost all metals are liable to rust. The rust of iron is not merely an oxide of that metal ; it contains, besides, a portion of carbonate.</p><p>RUSTIC, in <hi rend="italic">Architecture,</hi>  implies a manner of building in imitation of nature, rather than according to the rules of art.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Rustic Gods, or </hi><hi rend="italic">dii rustici,</hi>  in <hi rend="italic">Antiquity,</hi>  were the gods of the country, or those who presided over agriculture. Varro invokes the tw<hi rend="sup">,</hi>elve<hi rend="italic">dii consentes,</hi>  as the principal amongst the rustic gods, viz. Jupiter, Tellus<hi rend="sub">1</hi>  the Sun, Moon, Ceres, Bacchus, Rubigus, Flora, Minerva, Venus, Lympha, and Good Luck. Besides these twelve arch-</p></body></text></TEI>