<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>violent storm. Pitcaime wanting amusement, inquired at the hostess if she could procure any agreeable companion to bear him company at dinner. She replied, that the schoolmaster, though young, was said to be learned, and, though modest, she was sure he could talk. Pitcairne was delighted with the conversation and learning of his new companion, invited him to Edinburgh, and promised him his patronage.</p><p>When Ruddiman arrived in Edinburgh, the Advocates Library, which had been founded eighteen years before by Sir George Mackenzie, attracted his curiosity and attention, and he was soon afterwards appointed assistant-keeper under Mr Spottiswoode the principal librarian. His salary for executing this laborious office was L.8. 6s. 8d. He had, besides, a small honorary present from those who were admitted advocates, for correcting their theses ; and he was also paid for copying manuscripts for the use of the library. The faculty, however, before he had held the office two years, were so highly pleased with his conduct, that they made him a present of fifty pounds Scotch, or L.4. 3s. 4d. sterling.</p><p>During the sitting of the Court of Session he attended the library from ten till three. But this confinement did not prevent him from engaging in other laborious duties. A part of his time was occupied in teaching young gentlemen the Latin language. Some he attended at their lodgings, some waited upon him, and some resided in his own house. An exact list of the names of those who attended him, expressing the date of their entry, and the sums which he was to receive from each, has been found in his pocketbook, a curious relic, which is still preserved.</p><p>When Ruddiman’s merit as a scholar became better known, his assistance was anxiously solicited by those who were engaged in literary publications. Freebairne, a respectable bookseller of that period, prevailed upon him to correct and prepare for the press Sir Robert Sibbald’s <hi rend="italic">Introductio ad historiam rerum a Romanis gestarum in ea Borealis Britannia parte qua ultra murum Picticum est. </hi>For his labour he received L.3 sterling. At the request of Mr Spottiswoode, librarian, he contributed for L.5 sterling his aid to the publication of Sir Robert Spottiswoode’s Practiques of the Laws of Scotland.</p><p>In 1707 he commenced auctioneer, an employment not very suitable to the dignified character of a man of letters. But to this occupation he was probably impelled by necessity ; for upon balancing his accounts at the end of the preceding year, the whole surplus was L.28. 2s. with prospects of L.236. 7s. 6d. Scotch. Ruddiman had a family, and seems to have been a stranger to that foolish pride which has seduced some literary men into the opinion, that it is more honourable to starve than have recourse to an occupation which men of rank and opulence are accustomed to despise. The same year he published an edition of <hi rend="italic">Voluseni de Animi Tranquillitate Diatogus,</hi>  to which he prefixed the life of Volusenus. Volusenus or Wilson was a learned Scotchman, and had the honour to be patronized by Cardinal Wolsey. In 1709 he published <hi rend="italic">Johnstoni Cantici Solomonis Paraphrasis Poetica,</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">Johnstoni Cantica</hi>  with notes, which he dedicated in verse to his friend and patron Dr Pitcairne. The edition consisted of two hundred copies. The expense of printing amounted to L.5. 10s. sterling, and he sold them at a shilling each copy.</p><p>The philological talents of Ruddiman were next directed to a more important object, in which they became more conspicuous and useful. Freebairne the bookseller proposed to publish a new edition of the Scottish translation of  Virgil's Æneid by Gawin Douglas, bishop of Dunkeld. Of the contributions which some eminent characters of the age presented, the most valuable were supplied by Ruddiman. Freebairne acknowledged in general terms this obligation, but has not done him the justice to inform the reader what</p><p>these valuable contributions were, and Ruddiman’s modesty restrained him from publicly asserting his claim. From the pocket-book which has been already mentioned, it appears that Ruddiman corrected the work and wrote the glossary; and there is strong reason to believe that he was the author of the forty-two general rules for assisting the reader to understand the language of Douglas. To those who wish to be acquainted with the ancient language of this island, the glossary will be a treasure, as it forms a compendious dictionary of the Anglo-Saxon. For this elaborate work Ruddiman was allowed L.8. 6s. 8d. sterling.</p><p>The reputation of Ruddiman had now extended to a distance. He was invited by the magistrates of Dundee to be rector of the grammar-school of that town ; but the faculty of advocates, anxious to retain him, augmented his salary to L.30. 6s. 8d. sterling, and he declined the offer.</p><p>In 1711 he assisted Bishop Sage in publishing Drummond of Ilawthornden’s works ; and performed the same favour to Dr Abercrombie, who was then preparing for the press his Martial Achievements. In 1713 he was deprived of his friend Dr Pitcairne. On this occasion he testified all the respect which friendship could inspire to the memory of his deceased patron and surviving family. He composed Pitcairne’s epitaph, and conducted the sale of his library, which was disposed of to Peter the Great of Russia.</p><p>In 1714 the Rudiments of the Latin Tongue were published. Eighteen or nineteen Latin grammars, composed by Scotchmen, had appeared before this period ; yet such is the intrinsic value of this little treatise, that it soon superseded all other books on the subject, and is now taught in all the grammar-schools in Scotland. It has also been translated into other languages.</p><p>He was next called upon to publish the works of Buchanan. The value of these he enhanced by an elaborate preface, his <hi rend="italic">Tabula Regum Scotiæ Chronologica</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">Propriorum Nominum Interpretatio.</hi>  The interpretation of proper names was highly requisite ; for Buchanan has so disguised them in the Roman dress, that the original name is scarcely discernible ; and the preface puts the reader on his guard against the chronological errors and factious spirit of the history. Ruddiman also added a learned dissertation, entitled <hi rend="italic">De Metris Buchananais Libellus,</hi>  and subjoined annotations critical and political on the History of Scotland. As he espoused the cause of Queen Mary, he raised against himself a host of enemies, and gave occasion to that celebrated controversy which has been carried on with much keenness and animosity, and with little intermission, even to the present times. For this work Ruddiman was promised L.40 sterling.</p><p>He had now been so long accustomed to superintend the press, that he was led to form the plan of erecting a printing-office himself. Accordingly, in the year 1715, he commenced printer in partnership with his brother Walter, who had been regularly bred to the business; and some years afterwards he was appointed printer to the university, along with James Davidson, bookseller.</p><p>The first literary society formed in Scotland was instituted in the year 1718. It probably derived its origin from the factious and turbulent spirit of the times. The learned, anxious perhaps to find some respite from the political dissensions of the day, endeavoured to procure it in elegant amusement; for one of the fundamental articles of the new association was, that the “ affairs of church and state should not be introduced.” Ruddiman and the masters of the high school had the honour to found this society. They were afterwards joined by Lord Karnes.</p><p>In 1725 was published the first part of his <hi rend="italic">Grammatica Latina Institutiones,</hi>  which treated of etymology. The second part, which explained the nature and principles of syntax, appeared in 1731. He also wrote a third part on prosody, which is said to be more copious and correct than</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>