<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>father’s death, attempted by assassination, or force of arms, to take possession of the neighbouring principalities, determined to resist him in his encroachments. Collecting an army of Novgorodians, he, in 1016, drove Sviatopolk from Kief, and forced him to seek an asylum with his father-in-law, Boleslas, duke of Poland. Boleslas, easily persuaded to engage in the cause of his son-in-law, accompanied Sviatopolk into Russia with an army, retook Kief, and obliged the Novgorodian prince to retire with precipitation. Whilst he was endeavouring to collect fresh forces to renew the war with Boleslas and Sviatopolk, the latter, by the treachery and perfidy with which he treated his Polish allies, contributed to his own downfall. He caused great numbers of the Poles to be secretly massacred, a transaction by which Boleslas was so incensed, that he plundered Kief, made himself master of several places on the Russian frontiers, and then left, his perfidious son-in-law to shift for himself. Sviatopolk now sought assistance from the Petchenegans, and with an army of these auxiliaries offered battle to Ya-roslaf, not far from the place where he had, four years before, caused one of his brothers to be murdered. The contest was long and bloody, but terminated in favour of Yaros-laf. Sviatopolk was put to flight, and died soon afterwards.</p><p>By this victory Yaroslaf acquired possession of the greater part of his father’s dominions, and testified his gratitude for the assistance given him by the Novgorodians, by the attention which he paid to the particular improvement of that state. He drew up for it a code of laws, which are still known by the appellation of the municipal law of Novgorod. He also exerted himself for the welfare of other towns, and of the country at large.</p><p>Yaroslaf did not neglect the advancement of the Christian religion. He established a metropolitan in Kief, and thus gave to the Russian clergy a head, who might watch over the morals of the inferior pastors, and provide for the general dissemination of the Christian doctrine. He collected several books on the Greek religion, and caused many of them to be translated into the Russian language.</p><p>This monarch is supposed to have died in 1054, and to have reigned thirty-five years. He followed the example of his father, in dividing his territories amongst his sons, though he endeavoured to prevent the dissensions which he himself had witnessed from such a partition, by exhorting them on his death-bed to the most intimate concord, and endeavouring to convince them that they would be respected by their subjects, and feared by their enemies, only whilst they continued to act with unanimity.</p><p>We know little of the proceedings of Yaroslaf’s successors, except that Isiaslaf, his eldest son, who until 1078 reigned as grand prince of Kief, had frequent disputes with his brothers, in which he was assisted by the Poles, and supported by the influence of the Roman pontiff.</p><p>From the death of Isiaslaf to the beginning of the thirteenth century, the history of Russia comprises little else than a continued series of intestine commotions and petty wars with the neighbouring states. The same system of dismemberment was continued by the succeeding princes, and was attended with the same result. There were during this period not fewer than seventeen independent principalities, though these were at length reduced to seven, viz. those of Kief, Novgorod, Smolensk, Vladimir, Tver, Halitcb, and Moskva or Moscow. Of these, Kief and Novgorod long continued to be the most powerful, though they could not always maintain their superiority over the others; and towards the latter end of the period which we have mentioned, the district of Vladimir erected itself into a grand principality, and became at least as powerful as Kief and Novgorod. @@<hi rend="sup">1</hi></p><p>During the intestine broils that attended the dismemberment of the Russian monarchy, the ambition of its neighbours, with the folly of the contending princes, who solicited foreign aid against their rivals, contributed to diminish the strength and resources of the empire. In particular, the Poles and the Hungarians availed themselves of these circumstances. By ravaging the towns and villages, carrying off the captives into slavery, and making a prey of whatever appeared most useful, they quickly recompensed themselves for their assistance. The Poles seem to have been the most successful in their depredations, and to have fully revenged themselves for their former humiliation.</p><p>A state of anarchy and confusion, such as we have described, held out a strong temptation to powerful states in the vicinity. In the neighbourhood of the Sea of Aral, not far from the confines of Vladimir and Kief, the wandering hordes of Mongols, or Mongol Tartars, had taken up their residence. They were perhaps descended from the ancient Scythians, and long dwelt on the confines of China. Hence they gradually marched westward, and about the year 1228 arrived on the shores of the Sea of Aral, under the conduct of Tuschi, son of the famous Tschinghis Khan, chief of the Mogul empire. From the Aral, Tuschi conducted his horde along the shores of the Caspian Sea, and gradually approached the Dnieper. In his course he attacked and overcame the Tscherkasses, or Circassians, who on his approach had joined with the Polovtzes to resist the terrible enemy. The defeated Polovtzes gave notice to their neighbours the Russians, of the approaching storm, and invited them to form a common cause against the enemy. In the mean time the Tartars had sent ambassadors to the Russians, hoping to prevent their alliance with the Polovtzes, and thus the more easily to subdue the disunited nations. For this time, however, the Russians were true to their own interest. In concert with the Polovtzes they assembled an army, and prepared to resist the incursions of the Tartars. Both parties</p><lb/><p>@@@ In the supremacy of these three great principalities, we may trace the division of European Russia into Great, Little, and White Russia ; a distinction which long maintained its ground, and in later times gave to the sovereign of this empire the title of monarch or emperor of all the Russias. Great Russia comprehended the principality of Novgorod, and extended northward to the White Sea, eastward to the river Dvina, and the entrance of the Petchora into the Ural Mountains ; whilst to the south it bordered on the district of Vladimir, as far as the Volga and the mouth of the Medveditza, and to the west on Lithuania and Prussia, including the tributary tribes on the Baltic, as far as Memel. Its capital was Novgorod. Little Russia extended on the north along the river Agcr to White Russia, on the east above the Donetz and the Oka to the Polovtzes and the Petchenegans« whilst to the south it stretched as far as the Tauric Chersonesus, or the Crimea, and to the west along the banks of the river Goryn. This was the principality of Kief, and in that city was the seat of government. The principality of Vladimir received the name of White Russia. It extended northward along the Volga, to the southern boundary of Great Russia; to the east it bordered on the possessions of the Ugres, and the territory of the Mordvines, stretching down the Volga to the mouth of the Oka ; and to the south it extended along the Oka to the principality of Riazan, and the Bulgarian territory. The metropolis of this division was at first Shuja, and afterwards in succession Rostof, Susdal, and Vladimir, till at length the seat of government was transferred to Moscow.</p><p>The principality of Novgorod appears, during this interval, to have been the most respect able for its commercial intercourse with the neighbouring nations, and for the independent spirit of its internal government. This, though nominally monarchical, seems to have possessed much of a republican character. The princes were evidently dependent on the people, and some ludicrous instances of this dependence are related by the old historians. One of the grand princes had so much displeased his people, that they refused to pay him their usual obedience. As the prince seems to have been aware of the little influence which he possessed in the state, he employed the metropolitan of the principality to negotiate a reconciliation. This prelate, accordingly, by a letter addressed to the Novgorodians, interceded for the sovereign, and pledged himself as surety for his good behaviour.</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>