<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>with his successors. Nothing of consequence, however, was then executed ; and the Russian commander, after having lain there in perfect indolence, with an army of fifty thousand men, for two years, at length raised the siege. Mikhail attempted to engage the Swedes in an alliance with him against Poland ; but failing in this negotiation, he concluded a new treaty, which continued unbroken till his death. This event happened in 1645.</p><p>Mikhail was succeeded by his son Alexei ; but as the young prince was only fifteen years of age at the time of his father’s death, a nobleman named Morosof had been appointed his governor and regent of the empire. This man possessed all the ambition of Boris, without his prudence and address ; and in attempting to raise himself and his adherents to the highest posts in the state, he incurred the hatred of all ranks of the people. Though, by properly organizing the army, he provided for the defence of the empire against external enemies, he shamefully neglected internal policy, and connived at the most flagrant enormities in the administration of justice. These abuses went so far that the populace once stopped the czar as he was returning from church to his palace, calling aloud for righteous judges. Although Alexei promised to make strict inquiry into the nature and extent of their grievances, and to inflict deserved punishment on the guilty, the people had not the patience to await this tardy process, and proceeded to plunder the houses of those nobles who were most obnoxious to them. They were at length pacified, however, on condition that the author of their oppression should be brought to condign punishment. One of the most nefarious judges was executed ; and the principal magistrate of Moscow was killed in a tumult. The life of Morosof was spared at the earnest entreaty of the czar, who engaged for his future good behaviour.</p><p>Similar disturbances had broken out at Novgorod and Pscov ; but they were happily terminated, chiefly through the exertions of the metropolitan Nicon, a man of low birth, who, by his reputation for extraordinary piety and holiness, had raised himself to the patriarchal dignity, and was high in favour with Alexei. The pacific conduct of the neighbouring states did not long continue, though indeed we may attribute the renewal of hostilities to the ambition of the czar.</p><p>The war with Poland was occasioned by Alexei’s supporting the Kozaks, a military horde, who had left the north-• ern shores of the Dnieper, and retired further to the south. Here they had established a military democracy, and during the dominion of the Tartars in Russia had been subject to the kliaa of those tribes ; but after the expulsion or subjugation of the Tartars, the Kozaks had put themselves under the guardianship of Poland, to which kingdom they formerly belonged. As the Polish clergy, however, attempted to impose on them the Greek faith, they threw off their allegiance to the king of Poland, and claimed the patronage of Russia. Alexei, who seems to havα sought a pretext for a rupture with that state, gladly received them as his subjects, hoping, by their assistance, to recover the territories which had been ceded to Poland by his father. He began by negotiation, and sent an embassy to the king of Poland, complaining of some Polish publications, in which reflections had been cast on the honour of his father, and demanding that, by way of compensation, the Russian territories formerly ceded should be restored. The king of Poland of course refused so arrogant a demand, and both parties prepared for war. The Russians, assisted by the Kozaks, were so successful in this contest, that the king of Sweden became jealous of Alexei’s good fortune, and apprehensive of an attack. He therefore determined to take a very active part in the war, especially as the Lithuanians, who were extremely averse to the Russian dominion, had sought his protection. The war with Sweden commenced in 1656, and lasted for two years, without any important</p><lb/><p>advantage being gained by either party. A truce was concluded in 1658 for three years, and at the termination of this period a solid peace was established. In the mean time the war with Poland continued, but was at length terminated by an armistice, which was prolonged from time to time during the remainder of Alexei’s life.</p><p>The reign of this monarch is as remarkable for turbulence as that of his predecessor had been for tranquillity. No sooner was peace established with the neighbouring states than fresh commotions shook the empire from within. The Don Kozaks, who now formed a part of the Russian population, felt themselves aggrieved by the rigour with which one of their officers had been treated, and, placing at their head Radzin, the brother of the deceased, broke out into open rebellion. Allured by the spirit of licentiousness and the hopes of plunder, vast numbers, both of Kozaks and inferior Russians, flocked to the standard of Radzin, and formed an army of nearly two hundred thousand men. This force, however, ill armed and quite undisciplined, was formidable merely from its numbers. Radzin himself seems to have placed no reliance on the courage or fidelity of his followers, and eagerly embraced the first opportunity of procuring a pardon by submission. Having been deceived into a belief that this pardon would be granted on his surrendering himself to the mercy of the czar, he set out for Moscow, accompanied by his brother ; but when he had arrived within a short distance of the capital, whither notice had been sent of his approach, he was met by a cart containing a gallows, on which he was immediately hanged. His followers, who had assembled at Astracan, were surrounded by the czar’s troops, taken prisoners, and twelve thousand of them hung on the gibbets in the highways.</p><p>The authority which Alexei had obtained over the Don- &lt; skoi Kozaks excited the jealousy of the Sublime Porte,<hi rend="sup">1 </hi>which justly dreaded the extension of the Russian territo-1 ry on the side of the Crimea, a peninsula at that time belonging to Turkey. After a successful attempt on the frontiers of Poland, a Turkish army entered the Ukraine, and the Russians made preparations to oppose them. Alexei endeavoured to form a confederacy against the infidels among the Christian potentates of Europe ; but the age of crusading chivalry was over, and the czar was obliged to make head against the Turks, with no assistance but that of the king of Poland. The Turkish arms were for some years victorious, especially on the side of Poland ; but at length a check was given to their successes by the Polish general Sobieski, who afterwards ascended the throne of that kingdom. Hostilities between the Turks and Russians were not, however, terminated during the reign of Alexei, and the czar left to his successor the prosecution of the war.</p><p>The reign of Alexei is most remarkable for the improve-. ments introduced by him into the Russian laws. Before' his time the <hi rend="italic">Emannoy Ukases,</hi>  or personal orders of the so-' vereign, were almost the only laws of the country. These edicts were as various as the opinions, prejudices, and passions of men ; and before the days of Alexei they produced endless contentions. To remedy this evil, he made a selection, from all the edicts of his predecessors, of such as had been current for a hundred years, presuming that these either were founded in natural justice, or during so long a currency had formed the minds of the people to consider them as just. This digest, which he declared to be the common law of Russia, and which is prefaced by a sort of institute, is known by the title of the <hi rend="italic">Uloshenic</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">Selection. </hi>It was long the standard law-book, all edicts prior thereto being declared to be obsolete. He soon made his new code, however, more bulky than even the Selection ; and the additions of his successors are beyond enumeration. This was undoubtedly a great and useful work ; but Alexei performed another still greater.</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>