<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>at all, such as choristers and sacristans, who, strictly speak-' ing, do not belong to the clerical order, but merely discharge the duties of attendants.</p><p>It has been justly remarked, that the members of the religious fraternities are here of more importance, compared with the other clergy, than in the west of Europe, since from them alone are the highest functionaries of the church selected. They are divided into ecclesiastical functionaries of the highest class, such as metropolitans, archbishops, and bishops ; heads of religious bodies, such as archimandrites (abbots), and igumen (priors); and monks. Whoever aims at the honour of being a bishop, &amp;c. must of necessity become a monk. On account of their higher learning and more correct life, the monks are held in much greater estimation than the secular clergy. They live a life of abstinence and strict self-denial. Many of them are men of profound learning and undoubted piety ; but it is to be feared that the greater bulk of the lower orders of ecclesiastics are among the most degraded that ever assumed the priestly habit in Europe. Many of them are as ignorant as the boors with whom they associate, drinking, playing, and going to market with them like unsophisticated serfs. The general state of morals in the Greek Church, compared with those of Protestants in Russia, may be inferred from the tables of births in St Petersburg, published by the holy synod. From these it appears, that out of 8663 births, the number which took place in the year 1834, in families of the Greek Church not fewer than 1589 were illegitimate ; whilst in the Protestant congregations, of 1031 infants who were baptized, only seventy-six were illegitimate. @@<hi rend="sup">1</hi></p><p>The Catholic Church comprehends eighteen different orders, who possess 113 cloisters, in which there are 2200 monks. They support sixteen circuit and thirty-one parochial schools, at which 3012 scholars receive instruction. There are 666 nuns, belonging to ten different orders, and inhabiting fifty-two nunneries. They support thirty-three female schools, fifteen hospitals for the sick, and twelve poor-houses for the aged and infirm. These educational and benevolent institutions are attached to the cloisters. The Catholic secular priesthood, comprising about two thousand individuals, superintend a number of such establishments. There are in all thirteen seminaries of a higher order, 201 parochial schools, with 7688 pupils, and 566 poor-houses, with 4449 inmates. This enumeration is exclusive of Poland, in which, in 1830, there were 1917 clergymen, 309 chapels of ease, 2369 secular priests, 156 monasteries with 1783 monks, and twenty-nine nunneries with 354 nuns. At the head of the clergy were one archbishop, eight bishops, with a chapter of 276 dignitaries, canons, and the like. The collective number of Catholic ecclesiastics in Russia and Poland is estimated at 10,772.</p><p>The Protestants, consisting of Lutherans and some other sects, are divided into two synods and eight consistories,  to which belong 865 places of devotion. Each of the consistories has a bishop as its president. The Razkolniks or Apostates, that is, dissenters from the Greek Church, do not compose a distinct ecclesiastical body, but exist in separate congregations, independently of one another, and each having some distinctive shade of difference from all the rest. They have a consecrated clergy, but of course no common synod or consistory. Another sect, called the Duchoborzy, differing still more widely from the Greek Church than the former, have taken refuge in the steppes beyond the Don, w’here they still profess their creed, but</p><p>without the aid of either churches or a priesthood.</p><p>The Mahommedans have 4785 mosques in Russia, of which 2466 are head mosques. They have colleges, mullahs, and muftis, who regulate the religious affairs of the sect.</p><p>The worshippers of the Grand Lama have their principal religious establishment at Darsan, in the province of Udinsk. They have a numerous priesthood, who are said to be very successful in making converts amongst the wandering tribes.</p><p>The principal institution for the dissemination of the Holy Scriptures amongst the various tribes of the empire, in their native languages, is established at St Petersburg, and is in connection with the British and Foreign Bible Society of London. It consists of fifty-eight sections and 289 auxiliary societies, situated in Moscow, Jaroslav, Dor-pat, Mittau, Revel, Riga, Orenburg, Tobolsk, Irkutsk, and other places. From the period of its institution in 1813 until June 1823, it had issued 184,851 complete Bibles, 315,928 New Testaments, and 204,052 Old Testaments, in forty-one different languages and dialects. Its further usefulness was greatly promoted by an arrangement made in 1826, by which the sale of Bibles was for the future permitted. There is always a large supply of Bibles at Moscow, where those condemned to exile in Siberia may have a copy, if they desire one, as they pass through this city on their way to their place of banishment. It is well known that all the exiles, in whatever part of the country they may have received sentence, must take Moscow in their route to Siberia.</p><p>As early as the eleventh century, public schools were founded at several places in Russia; but Peter the Great, to whom Russia is indebted for her civilization and present standing, was the first to plan a regular system of public education. Elementary schools were established throughout the country; a naval and engineering school at St Petersburg ; mathematical and navigation schools at Moscow and other places ; ecclesiastical schools in the bishoprics ; and Latin and Greek schools were also founded in different towns of the empire. Shortly after the demise of Peter, the St Petersburg Academy of Sciences was opened; but the military schools were those which throve best under the Empresses Anne and Elizabeth. @@<hi rend="sup">2</hi> This last sovereign, however, founded in 1755 an university at Moscow, and two years afterwards an academy of the fine arts at St Petersburg. Inferior public schools were not regularly organized until the year 1786, under the reign of the Empress Catherine II. Boarding schools were established by her authority in all the different governments of the empire. But a more important measure was the institution of a central authority, intrusted with the care of disseminating education. This organization underwent a complete reform under the Emperor Alexander, who substituted, for the special commission of the former reign, a minister of public instruction with more extensive powers. This sovereign re-organized the university of Wilna, and founded those of Dorpat, St Petersburg, Kazan, and Kharkov. He also established a gymnasium in the capital of every government, and district schools in every district. But on the accession of Nicholas the system underwent a total change. A few immaterial forms were preserved, but the spirit had departed. His object was to render the system of instruction religious, monarchical, and national; but as the two first terms are evidently auxiliaries of the last, we must fuse the whole into two words,<hi rend="italic">strictly national,</hi>  a term of profound import, as we shall presently see. Until the year 1835, all the civil schools of the empire throughout the se-</p><lb/><p>@@@1 Bremner’s Excursions in the Interior of Russia, voi. ii. p. 133.</p><p><hi rend="italic">@@@2 Precis du Système, des Progrès, et de l'Etat de l'Instruction Publique en Russie, redigi d'après des documents officiels.</hi>  Par Alexandre de Krusenstern, Chambellan de S. M. l’Empereur de Russie. Warsaw, 1837, in 8vo.</p></body></text></TEI>