<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>empire, Oleg prepared to carry into effect his ambitious designs against Constantinople. Leaving Igor at Kief, he himself embarked on the Dnieper with eighty-thousand warriors, on board of not fewer than two thousand vessels. Their passage down the river met with no obstruction, till they came to that part where its course is embarrassed for nearly fifteen leagues by seven rocks ; and here began a series of perils, labours, and fatigues, which none but barbarians could have overcome. They were obliged to unload their barks, and convey them over the rocks ; and, in particular, at the fourth rock, they carried their baggage for above six thousand paces, exposed to the perpetual risk of attack from the neighbouring nations with whom they were at war, while thus hampered and encumbered. Having at length reached the mouth of the Dnieper, Oleg drew together his scattered vessels to be repaired, and waited for a favourable wind to carry him across the Black Sea to the mouth of the Dniester. Here the vessels were again refitted, and hence the expedition, coasting along the shores of the Euxine, soon arrived at the Strait of Constantinople.</p><p>The inhabitants of the imperial city, on discovering the approach of the barbarians, had drawn a massy chain across the harbour, thus hoping to prevent their landing. In this hope, however, they were deceived. The invaders drew ashore their barks, fitted wheels to their flat bottoms, and converted them into carriages, which by the help of sails they forced along the roads that led to the city, and thus arrived under the walls of Constantinople. In their route they ravaged the whole country, and pillaged and demolished the houses ; loaded the inhabitants with irons, and committed other enormities which generally attend the incursions of a barbarous enemy. The weak Leo, who then swayed the sceptre of the Grecian empire, instead of making a manly resistance, is said to have attempted carrying off his enemy by poison ; but this not succeeding, he was obliged to purchase from the conqueror an ignominious peace. Oleg on his return made his entrance into Kief laden with the wealth acquired by his victory; and the people, dazzled with such splendid objects, imagined their prince to be endowed with supernatural powers, and looked up to him with a reverence approaching to adoration.</p><p>Soon after his return to his own dominions, the Russian monarch despatched deputies to Constantinople with the articles of a treaty, which he required the Greek emperor to sign. This treaty, which is preserved in the Chronicles of Nestor, is extremely curious ; and we learn from it many important particulars respecting the internal policy of the Russians at the beginning of the tenth century. Several articles of it show that the Russian laws laid great stress on oaths ; that they pronounced the sentence of death against the murderer, instead of inflicting on him only a pecuniary fine, and thus allowing the rich to commit assassination with impunity ; that the punishment of offences did not extend to the entire confiscation of goods, and hence the widow and orphan did not suffer for a crime of which they were innocent ; that robbery, which attacks only property, was punished by the privation of property ; that the citizens, secure in their possessions, were under no apprehension that the sovereign would seize on their heritage, and might even dispose of their effects in favour of friends.</p><p>Oleg maintained the sovereign power for thirty-three years; nor does it appear that Igor, even after he attained the age of majority, had any share in the administration, till the death of his guardian, in 913, left him in full possession of the throne.</p><p>Igor had reached his fortieth year before he entered upon the government. He soon discovered marks of the same warlike spirit which had actuated his predeccssor. Among the nations that had been subjugated by Oleg, several, on the accession of the new sovereign, attempted to regain their independence ; the Drevlians, who dwelt on the banks of</p><p>the Uscha, in the present district of Vrutsch, being the first to revolt. They were, however, soon quelled, and punished ' by the imposition of an increased tribute.</p><p>Igor had next to contend with more formidable enemies. The Petchenegans, a nation hitherto unknown, quitted their settlements on the Yaik and the Volga, and made incursions into the Russian territory. These people appear to have been at least as powerful and warlike as the Varages; and Igor, finding himself unable to cope with them, concluded a treaty of alliance. About five years afterwards, disputes arose between the new allies, and both had recourse to arms. It appears that the Russians were finally victorious, and the Petchenegans were for some time disabled from giving further molestation.</p><p>The Russian monarch, in imitation of his guardian, soon turned his attention towards the Grecian empire, where depredations might apparently be made with impunity. He equipped an immense armament, consisting, if we may credit the improbable tale of the Russian annals, of ten thousand barks, each carrying forty men, thus forming an array of four hundred thousand warriors. He set sail for Constantinople, without any previous declaration of war, and without any ostensible motive for thus infringing the treaty which had been concluded some years before between Oleg and Leo. In his route he overran and ravaged the provinces of Paphlagonia, Pontus, and Bithynia, plundering the towns, and butchering the inhabitants. For some time the barbarians met with no opposition, as the imperial troops were engaged in distant provinces ; but the government of the empire was now in very different hands from those w’hich had held it during the former invasion. The Grecian forces were well appointed, and commanded by two generals of approved ability and courage. These were Theophanes and Phocas, of whom the former commanded the fleet, and the latter the army. The Russians had soon cause to repent their temerity. Theophanes attacked them on board their ships, within sight of the Pharos, and throwing among them the unquenchable Grecian fire, with the effects of which they were wholly unacquainted, produced such confusion, that many plunged into the sea in order to avoid the flames that threatened and pursued them. Their vessels were dispersed, shattered, or burned, and great numbers of their crews perished. The remainder reached the shores of Bithynia; but before they could recover from their consternation, they were met by Phocas, who fell upon them with his troops, and made prodigious slaughter. So great were the losses sustained by Igor in this unfortunate expedition, that he carried back with him scarcely a third of his army. This second naval expedition of the Russians against Constantinople took place in 941.</p><p>Though discouraged by the ill success which had attended his first invasion of the Grecian empire, Igor was too much stimulated by the desire of plunder, not to risk a second attempt. Three years afterwards, he collected new forces, took into pay many of the Petchenegans, and again set out for Greece ; but before he had advanced beyond the Tau-rican Chersonesus, the emperor Romanus, informed of his approach, anil not choosing to hazard the result of an engagement, sent deputies to the Russian leader, offering to pay him the same tribute which had been given to his predecessor. With this offer Igor complied, and once more retired with his army.</p><p>Igor was now far advanced in years ; but the insatiable rapacity of his officers, ever craving for fresh spoils from vanquished nations, impelled him to turn his arms against the Drevlians, for the purpose of obtaining from them an increase of their yearly tribute. In this unjust attack he was at first successful, and returned loaded with the contributions which he had levied from that people ; but having dismissed great part of his troops with the spoils of the vanquished, and marching with the remainder too far into the</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>