<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>who founded the empire. It underwent various changes along with the empire itself, the Scandinavian, Mongolian, Tartar, and German, also the Polish and French languages, being all by degrees incorporated with it to a greater or less extent. This improvement is continually advancing by means of the national literature. 2. The Sclavonian language, or that of the Sclavonian Bible. It was fixed by the translation of the Holy Scriptures, and so settled that it has since experienced but few alterations. From the combination of these two a mixed language arose, which was used in sermons, rhetorical prose, and the higher species of poetry. The following extract presents a concise view of the way in which the Russian language began to assume its present form. “ From the thirteenth to the fourteenth century,” says the celebrated Karamsin, “ our language generally became more pure and more correct. Our scrupulous authors gave up the use of the Russian language, as yet too rude, in order to attach themselves more strongly to that which had been employed in composing the books of our church, namely, the ancient Servian, in which our Bible is written. They followed its rules, not only in the declensions and conjugations, but even in the pronunciation and orthography 5 nevertheless, as may be seen in Nestor, the force of habit made them often recur to their natural idioms, a circumstance which ha3 introduced into our literature a mixture consecrated by antiquity, and so deeply rooted amongst us, that often in the same book, and in the same page, we write <hi rend="italic">zlato</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">zoloto</hi>  (gold), <hi rend="italic">glad</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">golod</hi>  (hunger), <hi rend="italic">mladost </hi>and <hi rend="italic">molodost</hi>  (youth). The time had not yet arrived for giving to the Russian language that energy, that flexibility, that grace and delicacy, which in the days of peace and prosperity are coupled with the rapid progress of the intellectual faculties, with richness of ideas, and variety of knowledge, as well as with the formation of taste and the sense of the beautiful. We see, however, that our ancestors endeavoured to express their thoughts with more distinctness; that they sought to soften the still too rude sound of words, and to give less stiffness to their style. In short, putting aside all national pride, we may say that though, compared with other Europeans, the Russians might appear very ignorant, they were nevertheless far from having lost all the fruits of civilization ; they proved how much force it has to resist the rudest assaults of barbarism.” @@<hi rend="sup">1</hi>  The study of the Russian language is extremely difficult; and from the fact of its not yet being in a state which would entitle it to be called fixed, it is an arduous study, even for the natives.</p><p>The accounts of the Russian character in the works of those who have resided or travelled in the country, are extremely conflicting. He who impartially weighs the evidence of Coxe, Tooke, Clarke, Porter, Wilson, Cochrane, Holman, Londonderry, Bremner, and others, will arrive at the conclusion, which might have been suspected before the investigation began, that whilst there are not a few dark stains on the national character, many of them are attributable to the peculiar political system under which the people live, to their general ignorance hitherto, and to the low character and unclerical behaviour of the secular clergy; and that under a proper system of government, instruction, and religious discipline, the Russians would not be far behind some of their continental neighbours who hold a much higher place in the scale of civilization and morals. The opinion which generally prevails in this country regarding the Russians as a people does them injustice. If, as Dr Lyall asserts, they are “ insinuating and cunning, deceitful and perfidious, sensual and immoral,” it must not be forgotten, that any natural tendency to these vices not only remains unchecked by proper secular and religious instruction, but is fostered, as in a hot-bed, by a state of slavery,</p><lb/><p>or semi-vassalage, which is little better. Amongst all the nations of Europe, in Russia alone is one half of the population a marketable commodity, or something not very far removed from it. But we question much if the natural bias to the crimes and vices mentioned by Dr Lyall and others be very strong. From circumstances, however, they have received a powerful development; and from the statements of more recent travellers, it would seem that they are gradually becoming less conspicuous. They are fond of novelties, amusements, and gambling, particularly of cardplaying. They are extremely partial to singing, and their talents for imitation and the acquisition of languages are universally allowed to be remarkable. With regard to the former, Dr Clarke observes, “ their surprising powers of imitation exceed all that has been hitherto known.”</p><p>The foregoing observations apply to the bulk of the community. With regard to the Russian nobles, it may be briefly stated, that the style of living of the wealthy greatly resembles that of the higher ranks in other parts of Europe. With the exception of a few traits of a national cast, there is little distinction between the majority of the Russian nobility and those who move in the polite circles in Paris or in London. French and German are spoken with as much facility as the Russian language. French is the court language, and in spite of the invasion of 1812, and the loss of Moscow, the manners and literature of France are held in universal esteem. The wealthy nobles expend enormous sums on their entertainments, and many a goodly estate is mortgaged to gratify this passion for display.</p><p>The national dress of Russia consists of a long coat reach- ] ing to the calves of the legs, with numerous tucks at the bottom of the waist; a waistcoat of coloured linen, having the neck bare; and thin boots and shoes of the bark of the linden tree. In winter a sheep-skin pelisse is substituted for the coat. The dress of the higher ranks is now formed studiously on the European model, though no other part of Europe can rival the gorgeous robes worn by the nobles and bishops on public occasions, or the profusion of diamonds which emblazon their persons. The national amusements are chiefly those afforded by the ice. A favourite diversion is the ice-hill, or mountain, as the Russians call it, on whose sides are formed steep inclined planes, down which the adventurer throws himself, seated on a machine, which he guides with surprising skill. Swinging is another Russian diversion ; to which may be added the common ones of dancing, and of a national music, which, with the songs and ballads to which it is sung, is very plaintive and pleasing.</p><p>There are ten orders of knighthood or of merit in this; empire, three of which were established by Peter the Great, the parent of Russian civilization. They are both of a civil and military description ; and many of them are divided into several classes, some having five, others three and four. But the indiscriminate manner in which these marks of distinction arc bestowed greatly lessens their value. Even private soldiers have frequently half a dozen bits of ribbon strung in a line across the breast, and common policemen are sometimes bedecked in the same manner. A general officer in the Russian service is usually covered with orders of one kind or another. It is a fact worthy of remark, that the calendar has not yet been reformed in Russia. The reason assigned by the Russians for thus remaining twelve days in arrear of all other nations, is partly the fear which the emperor has of any serious innovations giving offence to his nobles, and partly the unwillingness of the clergy to accede to any change which would so materially disarrange the present order of their numerous feasts or saints’ days. Without the sanction of the priesthood, such</p><lb/><p><hi rend="italic">@@@ 1 Histoire de l' Empire de Russie,</hi>  par M Karamsin, traduite par MM. St Thomas et Jauffret, tome v. Paris, 1819-1826.     </p><lb/></body></text></TEI>