<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>has a rough and long-continued winter, especially in the ' eastern territory. This district is the largest and wealthiest portion of the empire, and forms broad, open, undulating plains, over which, as far as the declivities of the Ural chain upon the east, only slight elevations break the monotonous level. The northern district, from 57° to 67°, in European Russia, has a much milder climate than the same parallels in Asia. With the exception of the w’ooded mountains of Finland on the west, it is, as far as the Urals, a continuation of the former flat land, upon which forests, meadows, marshes, and moor-ground, alternate with one another. The poor, meagre soil, only insures the husbandman a return as far as the sixtieth parallel. The winter here is long and severe, there being six or seven months in which travelling is prosecuted on sledges. Mercury freezes in the winter, and the autumn is foggy. Here only slow-growing wood succeeds, and beyond 67° is confined to dry, stunted shrubs. From 64° the rearing of cattle is always difficult, and agriculture is limited to roots. Under the parallel of 66° the sun does not set on the 21st of June, nor rise above the horizon on the 21st of December. According to observations by the Imperial Russian Academy of Sciences, extending over twenty years, from 1777 to 1797, the duration of winter in St Petersburg extends from the end of September to the beginning of May. Snow and ice set in about the 9th of October, and continue to the beginning of May. Upon an average, 230 days of the 365 are reckoned as belonging to winter. For 160 of these, that is, from the 27th of November till the 19th of April, the waters are bound fast with ice. In winter the east wind prevails for 113 days, and the west sixty-eight days. In summer the westerly wind prevails for 110 days, and the easterly for eighty-four days. The quantity of rain which falls is firom ten to eleven French inches; the number of rainy days is reckoned at about eighty. In 1774 there were reckoned forty-eight appearances of the northern lights ; but since 1782 their number has decreased in a remarkable degree, especially within the last fifteen years. In the arctic or hyperborean region, extending from 67° to 74°, the rigours of the climate tell upon man and other animals, as well as upon vegetation; for neither attain the full size nor the complete development of their members. In Archangel the sun rises on the 11th of December at twenty-three minutes past ten, and sets about our mid-day, thirty-seven minutes past one ; whilst on the 10th of June it rises thirty-seven minutes past one in the morning, and does not disappear below the horizon until twenty-three minutes past ten in the evening. But beyond 67° the climate is one long summer day and long winter night. The summer, how'ever, is much overcast with vapours, which obscure, and sometimes wholly conceal, the sun. The dark and dreary reign of winter is greatly alleviated by clear moonlight and the brilliant apparition of the aurora borealis. Trees cease entirely about 67°, only hardy shrubs being able to endure the intense cold of the climate. In St Petersburg in 1732 the cold was 33° below zero, and in Tornea 37° On the 12th of January 1809, quicksilver froze into a solid mass in Moscow', and was extended with a hammer like lead. As this metal becomes solid about 33°, we may reckon the degree of cold in this case as about 35° below zero. Earthquakes were almost unknown in this country till the 17th of November 1821, when Kief and other places were visited by one, which shook the buildings with violence, but did no material damage.</p><p>From the vast extent of this empire, and the great range of its temperature, it is not surprising that the productions of every clime are found, or may be successfully cultivated, in some parts of its wide-spread surface. On the east, the great chain of the Urals separates by a bold line the northern European from the northern Asiatic botany; and over this vast expanse winter reigns with excessive severity, while the almost tropical temperature of the brief summer brings the productions of the vegetable kingdom to sudden maturity; and this rapid growth is followed by as rapid a decay in autumn.</p><p>The forests of Russia are in several respects an important feature of the country; firstly, as a physical characteristic, from their overspreading such enormous tracts of country ; secondly, in a commercial point of view, from the timber, tar, pitch, potash, and turpentine, which they afford, forming important items of trade ; and, thirdly, from their supplying fuel in a country nearly destitute of coal. An able writer thus describes them: “ Estimating the surface of European Russia,” says M. Schnitzler, @@<hi rend="sup">1</hi> “ at 402,100,552 dessaitines, 156,000,000 of this number are occupied by forests; 178,000,000 by uncultivated land, water, houses, and roads; 61,500,000 dessaitines by arable, and a little more than 6,000,000 by meadow-land. On this general view of the surface, we may compute that a dessaitine of wood occurs for every two and five-ninth dessaitines without it. The forests, indeed, constitute a source of riches which may long continue inexhaustible, and which might be indefinitely increased by strict regulations for their economy and management. Seventy-six millions of dessaitines are still completely covered with pines, firs, and other cone-bearing trees, without counting the oaks, maples, beeches, poplars, and elms, which are by no means rare in the latitudes within the 52d degree, and the birch, which grow’s in still more northern districts....The governments of Novgorod and Tver, in particular, are studded with forests; that of Volkonskoi, which extends to the Valdai Hills, is one of the largest known. In the government of Perm, out of 18,000,000 of dessaitines, 17,000,000 are forest. These immense tracts, covered with w'ood, are a great blessing in so inclement a climate, as they form a shelter against the wfinds from the icy seas. The provinces to the south have not the same necessity for them, and are so destitute of wood as to occasion the burning of grass and dung for fuel.” The trees furnish the inhabitants with fir-timber of the finest and most durable quality, for building, household furniture, and utensils; and for these purposes it is largely used in the interior. The same tree supplies the peasantry with torches, which they use instead of candles. The brushwood, which covers a vast extent of forest country, consists almost entirely of the hazel, dwarf birch, alder, willow, and juniper. In other places the surface of the earth is covered with wild bilberry, and the cranberry, which is extensively exported.</p><p>Russia is as yet chiefly an agricultural country. It is so extensive, and in many parts yields such abundant crops of grain, that enough is produced not only for home con-<hi rend="sup"/>sumption, but for exportation in considerable quantities. On an average of five years, the annual production of grain amounts to 180,965,000 chetwerts, or about 134,818,920 English quarters, of which quantity 50,335,864 chetwerts were reserved for seed, leaving 119,498,213 chetwerts for home consumption or exportation. The price of grain varies exceedingly in different governments. Rye-meal in 1818 was, in Revel and Mittau, twenty-six and twenty-seven roubles per chetwert, while in Viatka and Simpero-pol it was only about the one half. St Petersburg, Moscow, Archangel, Vologda, and Perm are the only governments that consume more than they raise; all the others produce more than they require. The grains most commonly cultivated are rye and oats. The best wheat is produced in Southern Russia, where also, along with millet, a little rice</p><lb/><p>@@@<hi rend="italic"> La Russie, la Pologne, et la Finlande,</hi>  Paris and St Petersburg, 1835. This is a valuable work on the statistics of Russia.</p></body></text></TEI>