<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>wards the Caspian, without coming into contact on the east with the mountain systems of Asia. It is called at different points the Orenburg, Baschkir, and Kirghis Urals, and sends out an offshoot on the south-west, between the rivers Ural and Samara, the Obschtschei-Syrt, which stretches to the banks of the Volga. The Sok Mountains form a part of this spur of tire Urals. There are seven defiles or passes through this great range, the most practicable of which are the roads from Perm and Orenburg into Asia. Between the southern declivities of the Urals and the Caspian Sea and Aral, there is an opening of about two hundred and eighty miles in breadth, through which, more than once, the hordes of Asia in former times have poured like a flood over Europe.</p><p>Steppes, or plains, are an important feature of the geography of Russia, as well as of that of Tartary, with which the term is more frequently associated. The most important of these are the following: 1. The Steppe of Petchora, which stretches along both sides of the rivers Dvina and Petchora, from the Icy Ocean and White Sea, to the northern part of the government of Vologda. It is called Tundra, and consists of turf-moor covered with moss. In the north it is destitute of wood; in the south it is thickly wooded, and has many small fresh-water lakes. 2. The little Jaroslav Steppe, situated between Koslov and Tambov, a plain rich in flowers, and fifty versts @@<hi rend="sup">1</hi> in diameter. In connection with it may be mentioned the great steppe between Tambov and Kopersk, which is plentifully supplied with water, very fruitful, and rich in vegetables and pasture. 3. The Steppe of the Don, belonging to the Don Cossacks. This immense plain, wholly destitute of hills, is about 57,600 geographical square miles in extent; in some parts it is fruitful, but in general the soil is barren and uncultivated. 4. The Kuban Steppe, extending from Kuban to the Manitch. The soil is very unproductive, and rests on a bed of sandy limestone. 5. The Steppe of Azof, which extends on both sides of the Lower Manitch, to the Sea of Azof and the Lower Don ; but it is as worthless as the former. 6. The Steppe of Taurida, a gentle declivity of the northerly and easterly mountains of Taurida, inclining towards Kertsch and the Bosphorus, the Putrid Sea (a branch of the Sea of Azof), and the Straits of Perekop. The soil near the mountains is poor and unproductive ; but farther down it becomes clayey and fruitful, and towards the sea is impregnated with salt. Similar to the Steppe of Taurida are those of Vosnesenks and Otcha-kof. 7. The Steppe of Nogais on the Black Sea and the Sea of Azof, from the Lower Don to the Lower Dnieper. It is a dry unwooded tract, of some value to the wandering tribes, but nearly useless to the settled countryman. 8. The</p><p>Steppe of Astracan, stretching between the Don, the Volga, and the Caucasus; and, 9. the Steppe of Kalmytz. According to Pallas, both of these immense plains must at one time have been covered with the waters of the Caspian Sea. But, in fact, the whole country appears at some period of remote antiquity to have lain beneath the tide of the ocean. Two large oases must be noticed as occurring in the midst of these steppes ; they form the country of the Little Russians, and that of the Don Cossacks.</p><p>M. Huot, in his new edition of Malte-Brun’s great geographical work, thus mentions the rivers of Russia. “ The soil of Russia is so slightly undulated, that to consider the spaces traversed by its rivers as true basins, would be an abuse of terms; notwithstanding that it contains the most important water-courses in Europe. It would not perhaps be more exact to apply the same name to the Black, Caspian, and Baltic Seas, or to the Icy Ocean, in one or other of which all its waters disembogue. I prefer designating by the denomination of declivities the inclination of the. soil to these several seas, and hence shall term them the Tauric, Caspian, Icy, and Baltic declivities. The Tau-ric, to which I give the name because all the water-courses which descend on this side have their embouchures around the peninsula of Taurida, is watered by the Dniester, the Dnieper, the Bog, and the Don; the Caspian, the waters of which fall into the sea of that name, is furrowed by the Terek, the Volga, and the Ural; the Icy declivity, formed by the tracts which incline towards the White Sea and Icy or Frozen Ocean, is watered by the Petchora, the Mezen, and the Northern Dvina; lastly, the Baltic comprehends all the streams which fall into the Baltic, the most important being the Torneo or Tornea, the Neva, the Southern Dvina or the Dvina, and the Niemen.” Some eminent German geographers have also adopted this plan of classifying the rivers according to the seas into which they discharge themselves ; and as it has several advantages over the usual method of describing the streams of a country in the order of their size and importance, we shall follow it.</p><p>In the declivity which slopes to the Black Sea and the Sea of Azof, there is, 1. the Danube, whose northern arm forms part of the southern boundary between Russia and Turkey. Below Galatz it receives its last tributary the Pruth, which descends from the mountains of Gallicia or Austrian Poland, and separates Bessarabia in Russia from Moldavia in Turkey. 2. The Dniester, which rises also in Gallicia, and flows with many serpentine windings towards Russia. Below Chotzim it is broken by rapids, so that near Bender boat-navigation is interrupted, and without receiving any tributaries of importance it falls into the Black Sea at the broad but shallow estuary or Lake of Ovidovo. 3. The Dnieper, which has its source in the government of Smolen-sko, on the southern slope of the Volkouski Wood, and empties itself into the Black Sea below Kerson. This noble stream receives many tributaries, amongst which, on .the right, flow in the Berezina, the Priepetz, and the Bug, and on the left the Soj, the Desna, the Sem, Sula, Psiol, Vorskla, and others. This river is the ancient Borystlienes. It is connected by canals with the Dvina and the Niemen. 4. The Don, which originates in the small lake of Ivanovsko, in the government of Riasan. After intersecting the Cossack territory to which it gives name, it discharges itself below Tcherkask into the Sea of Azof, by several mouths. In summer it is shallow; in spring it overflows its low banks to a great extent, and forms unhealthy morasses. By means of navigable canals it is connected with the rivers Shat, Upa, Oka, and Volga. Its principal affluents on the right are the Sosna and Donetz, and on the left the Voronej (on which stream Peter the Great built his ships for the Black Sea), the Khoper, Medveditsa, anti the Manitch. 5. The Kuban, which descends from the northern side of Elburz in the Caucasus, flows first north and then west, upon the boundary between Asia and Europe. It separates into two main branches, the northern of which falls into the Sea of Azof, and the southern into the Black Sea.</p><p>@@@ As we shall have frequent occasion to mention Russian weights anil measures, we here present a table, to which the reader can refer, in order to understand what the calculations are equivalent to in English.</p><p>A verst is 3520 English feet; consequently three versts are equal to two English miles.</p><p>A dessaitine is equal to 2<hi rend="sub">T</hi>’<hi rend="sub">3</hi>ths English acres nearly.</p><p>A chetwert is equal to 5-952 Winchester bushels; consequently 100 chetwerts are equivalent to 74-4 English quarters.</p><p>A vedro is equal to 3Jth English wine gallons.</p><p>A rouble, that is, a paper rouble, the only basis of commercial calculations, is equal to lOJd., which is very nearly the value of a French franc. But the rouble fluctuates with the exchange.</p><p>A pood or poud is always reckoned in commerce as equal to thirty-six pounds English.</p></body></text></TEI>