<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>been laid down ; but if it be supposed to extend in the form of a circle between the promontories of Nikolskoi and Winter, the area would amount to 83,271 τ¾¾, English square miles. Thus the whole superficial extent of the Russian empire is about 7,028,561-⅛C English square miles, of which l,364,815¼y<hi rend="sub">j</hi>j lie within the frozen, and 5,663,745¼¼⅛ within the temperate zone.” According to an estimate previously made by Kraft, Russia has a superficies of 7,023,252 English square miles, including 571,858 miles of steppes possessed by the Kirghises, which however are omitted by M. Sernoff. We are inclined to adopt the computation of the latter writer as the nearest approximation to the truth ; for perfect accuracy is not to be expected where so many liabilities to error exist. In the statistical account of this great empire, we shall describe the European and the Asiatic possessions of Russia separately; its American territory, and the islands in the Polar and Eastern Oceans, coming under the latter head.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Russia in Europe.</hi></p><p>Russia in Europe is bounded on the south by the Caucasus and the Black Sea ; on the north by the Arctic Ocean, especially by its great gulf the White Sea ; on the east by the river Kara Baigarama, the Ural chain of mountains, the river Ural to its embouchure in the Caspian, and thence by the shores of this sea to the eastern extremity of the Caucasus ; and on the west by the principality of Moldavia, Austria, Prussia, the Baltic Sea, and the dominions of Sweden. Excluding Nova Zembla and the archipelago of Spitzbergen, but including the part of Poland which has been absorbed by this vast empire, European Russia lies between 18° 20<hi rend="sup">,</hi> 15<hi rend="sup">l</hi>* and 64° 20' 15” of east longitude, and between 40° and 70° of north latitude. Its extreme length, from the northern declivities of the Caucasian range, near the sources of the river Samour, to the banks of the Muo-nio, near Ekontekis in East Bothnia, is 1840 miles of sixty to a degree ; and its breadth, from the west side of the Ural chain, near the sources of the Sylva, in the government of Perm, to the western limits of Vollhynia, on a line with Loutsk, is 1300 miles. In comparison with its size, Russia has less sea-coast than any other great European power. Its line of coast on the Frozen Ocean is about 920 miles in length, on the Baltic Sea about 1230, and on the Black Sea and the Sea of Azof about 1280 ; forming altogether a district of sea-coast about 3430 miles in length. Thus a greatly preponderating part of the country is cut off from all maritime intercourse and influence, except by means of navigable rivers and canals, which at best are but an indifferent substitute for the ocean. Owing to this circumstance, and the interruptions occasioned by the ice in the Arctic Sea, and in a considerable portion of the Baltic for the greater part of the year, Russia has made less progress in commerce and civilization than other nations of Europe more favourably situated.</p><p>European Russia, together with Poland, belongs entirely to that immense level plain which begins in the north of Germany, and extends over the whole east of Europe. From the Carpathian to the Ural range, a distance of five hundred leagues, all is one immense undulating plain, without a mountain to break the monotonous level of the horizon, or oppose a barrier to the winds. A great portion of it, in the south especially, consists of those immense levels called <hi rend="italic">steppes,</hi>  that, like the pampas of South America, present to the eye only a dead flat for many hundreds of miles. Here and there indeed the surface is diversified by some large ancient tumuli, supposed to be the burial-places of the ancient Scythians, and in a few places there are small tablelands ; but the latter swell so gently above the surrounding level as scarcely to be perceptible. Of these, the most worthy of notice are the Valdai Hills and the forest of Vol-konskoï, situated in the governments of St Petersburg,</p><p>Moscow, Tver, and Tula, the loftiest summit of which, lying between the villages of Poloschva and Mosti, and the towns of Ostasckov and Valdai, is only 1064 French feet in height. No part of the forest of Volkonskoi is very rugged ; on the contrary, it is a gently sloping plain. But the rivers and the deeply-indented lakes are encompassed by steep banks of slate, gypsum, and limestone mixed with shells. Masses and blocks of granite are scattered on the surface. This ridge, or rather plateau, is rich in iron, sulphur pyrites, vitriol, alum-earth, a species of coal, petrifactions, salt springs, and lime and gypsum quarries. Here are situated, within the distance of a hundred miles, the sources of the rivers Volga, Dvina, Dnieper, Don, Oka, Volchow, Lowat, Pola, Kolp, and others less distinguished. To the north-east, the land gradually slopes to the almost flat shores of the Baltic Sea, and is for the most part covered with immense forests, marshes, and turf-moors. Between this ocean inlet and the White Sea, on the north-northwest, lies a tract of country which is richer in water than any other in Europe. Here a multitude of lakes, large and small, are united together like a network of water, and between them extend those rocky ridges which, on the northwest, rise into the inferior Finnish chain of hills. These, however, sink again towards the lake Enara and the river Tana, without joining the Scandinavian system of mountains. Proceeding south-west from the interior hills of Voldai, the land also gradually sinks, and becomes encumbered by immense marshes, situated between Minsk and Volhynia. Through these the river Priepetz, the great feeder of the Dnieper, takes its way, constituting their drain or outlet. The northern declivities of the Carpathian Mountains only in a few places cross the borders of the Austrian territory, and enter Russia, but not as hills of any height. Near the sources of the Oder, they proceed towards the Vistula, and along this stream, as a plateau eight hundred feet in height, which, eastwards between Pilica and the above river, rises into groups of mountains, which extend, in five parallel chains, having a breadth of about fifty miles, for a distance of ninety miles. In two places they reach about two thousand feet in height, which are the loftiest points in Poland. Upon the other side, in the east, the declivities of the Carpathian range extend as a broad plateau across the whole of Southern Russia. It thus separates the low land of the interior from the maritime country of the Black Sea. Unlike the table-land of Volkonskoi, which bears on its broad surface lakes and fens, this southern plateau consists of large steppes, penetrated by the rivers Dniester, Dnieper, and Don, which here form cataracts. , Between the last-named stream and the Volga it rises as a continuation of the Lower Volgarange<hi rend="sub">1</hi> which, under the name of the Irgeni Hills, extends southwards to the Caucasus. On the peninsula of Crimea, a wholly insulated chain of mountains rises to a considerable height, and runs from east to west nearly a hundred and twenty miles, close to the coast of the Black Sea. In one part it attains an elevation of 4740 feet, and in another 4600 feet. Along the eastern boundary of European Russia, the Ural mountain chain extends from the shores of the Frozen Ocean southwards towards the Caspian Sea, for a distance of nearly 1500 miles, unconnected with any other mountain system of Europe. The northern portion of the Ural chain, from the Straits of Waygats to the sources of the Petchora, consists of rough, naked, limestone rocks, which in one place, Padwinski, are 6500 feet in height. This part of the country is comparatively little known. The middle portion of the chain, as far as the sources of the Oufa, called the Verchoturic Urals, forms a broad tableland of moderate elevation, overspread with morasses. Further to the south the Urals rise again in height, and become thickly wooded, whilst in the government of Orenburg they expand in broad ramifications on both sides of the river Ural. The chain, with all its branches,sinks tα-</p></body></text></TEI>