<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>only four thousand men, that composed the wing which he commanded, pursued the flying enemy, amounting to fifty thousand, to the river Narva. Here the bridge broke down with the weight of the fugitives, and the river was filled with their bodies. Great numbers returned in despair to their camp, where they defended themselves for a short time, but were at last obliged to surrender. In this battle, thirty thousand were killed in the intrenchments and the pursuit, or drowned in the river ; twenty thousand surrendered at discretion, and were dismissed unarmed, while the rest were totally dispersed. Λ hundred and fifty pieces of cannon, twenty-eight mortars, a hundred and fifty-one pairs of colours, twenty standards, and all the Russian baggage, fell into the hands of the Swedes ; and the Duke de Croy, the Prince of Georgia, and seven otller generals, were made prisoners. Charles behaved with the greatest generosity to the conquered. Being informed that the tradesmen of Narva had refused credit to the officers whom he detained prisoners, he sent a thousand ducats to the Duke de Croy, and to every other officer a proportional sum.</p><p>Peter was advancing with forty thousand men to surround the Swedes, when he received intelligence of the dreadful defeat at Narva. He was greatly chagrined ; but comforting himself with the hopes that the Swedes would in time teach the Russians to beat them, he returned to his own dominions, where he applied himself with the utmost diligence to the raising of another army. He evacuated all the provinces which he had invaded, and for a time abandoned all his great projects, thus leaving Charles at liberty to prosecute the war against Poland.</p><p>As Augustus had expected an attack, he endeavoured to draw the czar into a close alliance with him. The two monarchs had an interview at Birzen, where it was agreed that Augustus should lend the czar fifty thousand German soldiers, to be paid by Russia ; that the czar should send an equal number of his troops to be trained up to the art of war in Poland ; and that he should pay the king three millions of rix-dollars in the space of two years. Of this treaty Charles had notice, and, by means of his minister Count Piper, entirely frustrated the scheme.</p><p>After the battle of Narva, Charles became confident and negligent, while the activity of Peter increased with his losses. He supplied his want of artillery by melting down the bells of the churches, and constructed numerous small vessels on the lake of Ladoga to oppose the entrance of the Swedes into his dominions. He took every advantage of Charles’s negligence, and engaged in frequent skirmishes, in which, though often beaten, he was sometimes victorious. He contrived to make himself master of the river Neva, and captured Nyenschantz<hi rend="sub">1</hi> a fortress at the mouth of that river. Here he laid the foundation of that city which he had long projected, and which was to become the metropolis of his empire. At length, in 1704∙, he became master of Ingria, and appointed his favourite Prince Menzikoff to be viceroy of that province, with strict orders to make the building of the new city his principal business. Here edifices were already rising in every quarter, and navigation and commerce were increasing in vigour and extent.</p><p>In the mean time Augustus king of Poland, though treat-• ing with Charles for the surrender of his dominions, was obliged to keep up the appearance of war, which he had neither ability nor inclination to conduct. He had been lately joined by Prince Menzikoff with thirty thousand Russians ; and this obliged him, contrary to his inclination, to hazard an engagement with Meyerfeldt, who commanded ten thousand men, one half of whom were Swedes. As at tnis time no disparity of numbers whatever was reckoned an equivalent to the valour of the Swedes, Meyerfeldt did not decline the combat, though the army of the enemy was four times as numerous as his own. With his own countrymen he defeated the enemy’s first line, and was on the point of defeating the second, when Stanislas, with the Poles and Lithuanians, gave way. Meyerfeldt then perceived that the battle was lost ; but he fought desperately, that he might avoid the disgrace of a defeat. At last, however, he was oppressed by numbers, and forced to surrender ; suffering the Swedes for the first time to be conquered by their enemies. The whole army were taken prisoners excepting Major-general Krassau, who having repeatedly rallied a body of horse formed into a brigade, at last broke through the enemy, and escaped to Posnania. Augustus had scarcely sung <hi rend="italic">Te Deum </hi>for this victory, when his plenipotentiary returned from Saxony with the articles of the treaty, by which he was to renounce all claim to the crown of Poland in favour of his rival Stanislas. The king hesitated and scrupled, but at last signed them ; after which he set out for Saxony, glad at any expense to be freed from such an enemy as the king of Sweden, and from such allies as the Russians.</p><p>The czar Peter was no sooner informed of this extraordinary treaty, than he learned also the cruel fate of his plenipotentiary Patkul, a Livonian emigrant, whom Charles claiming as a subject, seized and executed. Peter immediately sent letters to every court in Christendom, complaining of this breach of the law of nations. He entreated the emperor, the queen of Britain, and the states-general, to revenge this insult on humanity. He stigmatized the compliance of Augustus with the opprobrious name of pusillanimity ; and exhorted them not to guarantee a treaty so unjust, but to despise the menaces of the Swedish bully. So well, however, was the prowess of the king of Sweden known, that none of the allies thought proper to irritate him, by refusing to guarantee any treaty which he thought proper to accept. At first, Peter thought of revenging PatkuPs death by massacring the Swedish prisoners at Moscow ; but from this he was deterred, by remembering that Charles had many more Russian prisoners than he himself had of Swedes. In the year 1707, however, he entered Poland at the head of sixty thousand men, and, assembling a diet, solemnly deposed Stanislas, with the same ceremonies which had been used with regard to Augustus. The appearance of a Swedish army under King Stanislas and General Lewenhaupt put a stop to this invasion, and the czar retired into Lithuania, giving out as the cause of his retreat, that the country could not supply him with the provisions and forage necessary for so great an army.</p><p>During these transactions Charles had taken up his residence in Saxony, where he gave laws to the court of Vienna, and in a manner intimidated all Europe. At last, satiated with the glory of having dethroned one king, set up another, and struck all Europe with terror and admiration, he began to evacuate Saxony in pursuit of his great plan, the dethroning the czar Peter, and conquering the vast empire of Russia. While the army was on full march in the neighbourhood of Dresden, he took the extraordinary resolution of visiting King Augustus with no more than five attendants. Although he had no reason to imagine that Augustus either did or could entertain any friendship for him, he was not uneasy at the consequences of thus putting himself entirely in his power. He reached the palace door of Augustus before it was known that he was in the city ; and he entered the elector’s chamber in his boots before the latter had time to recover from his surprise. He breakfasted with him in a friendly manner, and then expressed a desire of viewing the fortifications. While he was walking round them, a Livonian, who had formerly been condemned in Sweden, and served in the troops of Saxony, thought he could never have a more favourable opportunity of obtaining pardon. He therefore begged of King Augustus to intercede for him, being fully assured that his majesty could not refuse so small a favour to a prince in whose power he then was. Augustus accordingly made the request, but Charles refused</p></body></text></TEI>