<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>soon obliged, however, to postpone the completion of this design, on receiving intelligence that his old enemies the Petchenegans had assembled in great numbers, ravaged the Kievian territory, and laid siege to the capital, within the walls of which were shut up his mother and his sons. He hastened to the relief of his family, but before he reached home, the Petchenegans had been induced to raise the siege by an artifice of the Kievian general. Sviatoslaf on his arrival pursued the enemy, defeated them, and obliged them to sue for peace.</p><p>He now resumed his design of establishing himself on the banks of the Danube, and divided his hereditary dominions among his children. He gave Kief to Yaropolk, the Drevlian territory to Oleg, and on Vladimir, a natural son, born to him by one of the attendants of Olga, he bestowed the government of Novgorod. On his return to Bulgaria, indeed, he found that his affairs had assumed a very different aspect ; for the Bulgarians, taking advantage of his absence with his troops, had recovered most of their towns, and seemed well prepared to resist the encroachments of a foreign power. Sviatoslaf, however, soon regained all that he had lost.</p><p>During these transactions the Emperor Nicephorus had been assassinated, and John Zimisces, his murderer, had succeeded to the imperial diadem. The new emperor sent ambassadors to the Russian monarch, requiring him to comply with the stipulations of his treaty with Nicephorus, and evacuate Bulgaria, which he had agreed to occupy as an ally, but not as a master. Sviatoslaf refused to give up his newly-acquired possessions, and prepared to decide the contest by force of arms. The particulars of this campaign, and the numbers of the contending armies, are very differently related by the Russian annalists, and the historians of the Grecian empire ; the former stating that Sviatoslaf had not more than ten thousand men, and yet was victorious over the troops of Zimisces ; while the Grecian historians affirm that the Russians amounted to three hundred thousand, but were defeated, and compelled to abandon Bulgaria. As far as respects the issue of the war, the Grecian writers are probably correct ; for it is certain that Sviatoslaf retreated towards Russia with the shattered remains of his army. He did not, however, live to reach the capital ; for having, contrary to the advice of his most experienced officers, attempted to return to Kief by the dangerous navigation of the Dnieper, he was intercepted by the Petchenegans near the cataracts of that river. After remaining upon the defensive during winter, exposed to all the horrors of famine and disease, he, on the return of spring, attempted to force his way through the ranks of the enemy ; but his troops were defeated, and himself killed in the battle.</p><p>Yaropolk, the sovereign of Kief, may be considered as the successor of Sviatoslaf upon the Russian throne; but his reign was short and turbulent. A war took place between him and his brother Oleg, on account of a base assassination committed by the latter upon the son of his father’s friend and privy councillor Svenald. Oleg was defeated and slain, and the other brother, Vladimir, dreading the increased power and ambitious disposition of Yaropolk, abandoned his dominions, which were quickly seized on by the Kievian prince. Vladimir had retired among the Va-ragians, from whom he soon procured such succours as enabled him to make effectual head against the usurper. While his natural courage was thus increased, his enmity against Yaropolk received an additional spur from an affront inflicted on him by a lady whom he had sought in marriage, but who, despising the meanness of his birth, as being the son of a slave, had rejected his proposals, and offered her hand to Yaropolk. The vindictive Vladimir, on being informed of this insult, attacked the possessions of the lady’s father, put both him and his two sons to the sword, and obliged the princess to accept his hand, yet reeking with her parent’s blood. He now advanced towards Kief, where Yaropolk was by no means prepared to oppose him. The Kievian prince had indeed been lulled into security by the treacherous report of one of his voyvodes, who was in the interest of Vladimir, and who not only prevented Yaropolk from taking effectual measures for his safety, but found means to raise suspicions in his breast against the inhabitants of his capital, which he thus induced him to abandon. The Kievians, left without a leader, opened their gates to Vladimir; and the wretched Yaropolk, still misled by the treachery of his adviser, determined to throw himself on the mercy of his brother. It is probable that this would have availed him little, as Vladimir seems to have determined on his death ; but before he could reach the arms of his revengeful brother, Yaropolk was assassinated by some of his Varagian followers.</p><p>By this murder the conqueror acquired the undivided possession of his father’s territories, and maintained the sovereignty during a long reign, respected at home, and feared abroad. Indeed, had not the commencement of his reign been stained with the blood of his father-in-law and his brother, we might place him among the most distinguished monarchs of the age in which he lived, as he not only extended and enriched his empire, but was the means of establishing in his dominions, upon a firm and lasting basis, the Christian religion, which, though introduced by Olga, appears hitherto to have made but a very trifling progress.</p><p>The commencement of Vladimir’s reign formed but a continuation of those enormities which had conducted him to the throne. He began with removing Blude, the treacherous voyvode by whom his brother had been betrayed into his power, and to whom he had promised the highest honours and dignities. Accordingly, for three days he suffered Blude to live in all the splendour of a prince. At the end of that period he thus addressed him : “ I have fulfilled my promise; I have treated thee as my friend ; the honours thou hast received exceed thy most sanguine wishes. Today, as the judge of crimes and the executor of justice, I condemn the traitor, and punish the assassin of his prince.” Having uttered these words, he caused Blude to be put to death. He displayed still more the perfidiousness of his character in his behaviour towards the Varagians, who had assisted in placing him on the throne of his ancestors ; for on their requesting permission to go and seek their fortune in Greece, he granted their request, but privately advertised the emperor of their approach, and caused them to be arrested and secured.</p><p>Vladimir engaged in numerous wars, and subjected several of the neighbouring states to his dominion. He seized on part of the Polish territories, and compelled the Bulgarians who dwelt in the districts that now form the government of Kazan to do him homage. He subjected the Petchenegans and Khazares, who lay in the immediate neighbourhood of the Kievian state ; he reduced to his authority Halitsch and Vladimir, countries which are now called Gallicia and Lubomiria ; he conquered Lithuania as far as Memel, and took possession of a great part of the modern Livonia.</p><p>His conduct after these successes by no means prognosticated his future zeal for the Christian religion. None of the Russian monarchs appears to have been more devout in the adoration of their heathen deities. It was usual for him to return thanks to the gods for the success which they had granted to his arms, and to show his gratitude by offering on their altars a part of the prisoners he had taken in war. Upon one occasion his piety extended so far, that he resolved on selecting one of his own subjects as the object of his sacrifice, thinking that he should thus more worthily testify his gratitude for the signal favours he had received from heaven. His choice fell upon a young Vara-</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>