<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>in furs of the nomade races. But in estimating the receipts and expenditure of government, allowance must be made for numerous and large sums never carried to the account of either income or expenditure, because they are either appropriated to local purposes, or are discharged in kind by various portions of the population. This is the case with the rent of the fisheries on the Ural, which either serves as pay for specific services, or is assigned in perpetuity to certain classes of the community, so that it makes no appearance amongst the public receipts. In some districts the capitation tax is commuted, either wholly or in Tirt, for labour or military service. According to Schubert's reckoning, the income of the Russian empire for 1836 amounted to 354,268,000 paper roubles, or about L.14,200,000 sterling. To the above may be added six millions of roubles as the produce of the gold and platina mines, The national debt, which in many other countries swallows up so much of the revenue, here absorbs but a comparatively small part of it. On the 1st of January 1834, the debt of the Russian government amounted to 933,871,673 roubles, a sum which two years and a half of revenue would pay up. It has been materially reduced since the above date, and, it is believed, will in a few years be altogether extinguished. Every year a large sum is appropriated to this purpose. In the course of 1835, there were consigned to the commission for the extinction of the national debt no less than 66,529,080 roubles 96 kopecks. For a long period the currency of the country was in a very equivocal state, from government having issued paper roubles or assignats at a gradually increasing depreciation. The assignats, or bank-notes, of Russia were established by an imperial ukase in 1768, and issued in the following year. Of course they were at first equivalent in value to silver roubles, or very nearly so, and were issued to the amount of 40,000, in notes of the value of a hundred, seventy-five, fifty, and twenty-five roubles a piece. In 1786 these assignats were exchanged for new ones, and their quantity increased to the sum of 60,000,000 roubles. Their number went on augmenting till the death of Catherine II., when the sum in circulation amounted to 157,000,000 roubles. A natural consequence of the increased issue was their proportional fall; so that, at the above-mentioned epoch, the value of a hundred roubles in assignats was equal to seventy in silver. During the reign of the Emperor Paul I. the quantity of assignats was increased by 55,000,000 more; and during the reign of Alexander the issues were carried to such an extent, that in 1817 their whole quantity amounted to 836,000,000, and their value fell in proportion to their over-issue. The Russian treasury then adopted measures for diminishing the number of its assignats; and from that year till 1822, assignats to the amount of 236,077,650 roubles were withdrawn from circulation and destroyed. In 1819 the old assignats were exchanged for new ones, issued in a much improved shape, and in notes of two hundred, one hundred, fifty, twenty-five, ten, and five. According to the report of the minister of finance on the 20th of August 1835, the whole amount of assignats in circulation was 595,776,310 roubles, and their relative value to the metallic money was as a hundred to twenty-seven. There is little gold to be seen; and the only silver coin is the rouble, @@<hi rend="sup">1</hi> and its aliquot parts of halves, quarters, tenths, and twentieths. There is an immense copper circulation of kopecks, one hundred of which equal a paper rouble. Indeed the only true metallic currency may be said to be copper. A coinage of platina was made at the mint, but it is more rarely seen than even gold.</p><p>The amount of the Russian army in time of peace is nominally 612,332 men, of which the imperial guard contains 41,200. The most correct enumeration of the various corps of this enormous force appears to be that of Marshal Marmont. He says that “ the imperial guard are six divisions, three of infantry and three of cavalry, making sixteen battalions in all. The grenadier corps has three divisions of infantry, made up of twelve regiments, and a division of light cavalry, made up of four regiments ; also two batteries of horse artillery and fifteen of foot. The regiments of guards consist of three battalions of infantry and seven squadrons of cavalry. The six corps of the line are composed each of a division of light cavalry (made up of four regiments), and three divisions of infantry, each of four regiments; in all twelve regiments; besides two battalions of foot and two of horse artillery. The total six corps of the line are seventy-two regiments of infantry and twenty-four of cavalry, twelve batteries of horse and ninety of foot artillery. The corps of cavalry reserve has two divisions, each of four regiments, making a total of twenty-four regiments, and twelve batteries of artillery. The reserve of the line are three divisions, composed of twenty-four battalions. There is, in addition, the corps of the Caucasus, Siberia, and Finland; the troops of the interior, fifty battalions of horse militia, and one hundred and forty-six regiments of Cossacks.” The expense of this vast force is very small; the articles for their equipment, provisioning, and arming, being of the cheapest and coarsest kind, and the pay of both officers and men being low. @@<hi rend="sup">2</hi> See the article Army.</p><p>The naval force of Russia, for a long time inferior both in point of numbers and character, is now placed upon a highly respectable footing. The present emperor, when he ascended the throne, resolving to render Russia a first-rate naval as well as military power, made great, exertions to realize his wishes. The Baltic fleet, in 1838, consisted of the following vessels ; one three-decker of a hundred and twenty guns, three three-deckers of a hundred and ten guns, seven ships of eighty-four guns, and nineteen ships of seventy-four guns ; thus making in all thirty heavy line-of-battle ships. To these must be added one razee of fifty-six guns, three frigates of fifty-two guns, and eighteen frigates of forty-four guns, besides corvettes and small craft. The whole is manned by a force of 33,000 men. The fleet in the Black Sea consists of sixteen heavy ships of the line, besides a number of frigates, smaller vessels, gun-boats, &amp;c. On the Caspian Sea there are also several ships of very considerable size, and more are in rapid progress at the building-yards recently established at favourable points. Russia possesses at least sixty steam-boats of one kind or another. This is a formidable armament, and it is admitted by unprejudiced individuals, that the navy of Russia was never in such high condition as it is at the present time. But it is quite preposterous to look upon it in the light of a rival to that of</p><p>@@@ Whenever the word rouble is used in any work relative to Russia, as well as throughout this article, the paper rouble (10 Ad.) is meant. The silver rouble is never made the basis of calculations of any kind, nor have the Russians any higher denomination corresponding to our pound sterling. Kopecks and roubles constitute the only practical elements of the currency throughout the whole empire, with the exception of Poland.</p><p>@@@2 “ The military conscription in Russia,’’ says the British and Foreign Review, October 1838, “is the most horrible thing that can be imagined. The levy of recruits is ordered almost every year, and each community is compelled to furnish one, two, three, or more recruits from every five hundred males, or, as they are officially called, <hi rend="italic">touls.</hi>  The choice of recruits is entirely left amongst peasants to their masters, and amongst the burghers to the elders of the community ; and it may be easily imagined to how many abuses such a mode of levying is liable. We shall not enter into the disgusting details by which the levy of recruits is accompanied in Russia ; we shall only add, that the condition of a Russian soldier is considered so wretched and so hopeless, that there are many instances of individuals, who have not only mutilated, but even destroyed themselves, in order to escape military service.”</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>