<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>fully kept, though it cannot be averred to have been for the benefit of the empire ; since, in consequence of it, the number of malefactors who deserved to die was every day increasing, insomuch that even the clergy requested the empress to retract her vow, at the same time urging proofs that they could release her from it. All the arguments they could use, however, were of no avail to move the conscientious monarch ; she would not give effect to any sentence of death, although the commanders in the army particularly would have been glad that her conscience had yielded a little on that point. They declared that the soldiers were not to be restrained from their excesses by the severest corporal punishments they could employ ; whereas such was their dread of a solemn execution, that a few examples of that nature would have effectually kept them in awe.</p><p>“ Commerce and literature, arts, manufactures, handi-<hi rend="sup">3</hi>crafts, and the other means of livelihood, which had been fostered by the former sovereigns, continued their course under Elizabeth with increasing prosperity. The country products were obtained and wrought up in greater quantities, and several branches of profit were more zealously carried on. The sum appointed for the support of the Academy of Sciences founded by Peter I. at St Petersburg, was considerably augmented by Elizabeth ; and she moreover established, in 1758, the academy still subsisting for the arts of painting and sculpture, in which a number of young persons are brought up as painters, engravers, statuaries, architects, &amp;c. At Moscow she endowed a university and two gymnasia.</p><p>“ The Empress Elizabeth herself having a good voice, music, which Anne had already much encouraged, found under her administration a perpetual accession of disciples and admirers ; so that even numbers of persons of distinction at St Petersburg became excellent performers. The art of acting plays was now also more general among the Russians. Formerly none but French or Italian pieces were performed on the stage of St Petersburg, whereas now Sumarokof obtained celebrity as a dramatic poet in his native language, and, in 1756, Elizabeth laid the foundation of a Russian theatre in her residence. Architecture likewise found a great admirer and patroness in her, St Petersburg and its vicinity being indebted to her for great embellishments and numerous structures.</p><p>“ The magnificence which had prevailed under Anne at the court of St Petersburg was not diminished during her reign, and the court establishment therefore amounted to extraordinary sums. Elizabeth, indeed, in this respect did not imitate her great father ; and accordingly in the Seven Years’ War the want of a well-stored treasury was already very sensibly felt.</p><p>“ The population of the empire was considerably increased under her reign ; and so early as 1752, according to the statement in an account published by an official person, it was augmented by one fifth.</p><p>“ Elizabeth continued the practice of her predecessors in encouraging foreigners to come to settle in her empire. Emigrant Servians cultivated a considerable tract of land, till then almost entirely uninhabited, on the borders of Turkey, where they built the town of Elizabetllgorod, and multiplied so fast, that in the year 1764 a particular district was formed of these improvements, under the name of New Servia. Only the Jews Elizabeth was no less resolute not to tolerate than her father had been ; insomuch that, so early in her reign as 1743, they were ordered to quit the country on pain of death.</p><p>“ The army was augmented under Elizabeth, but certainly not improved. There were now no longer at the head of it such men as the foreigners Munnich, Keith, or Loevendal, who, besides their personal courage and intrepidity, possessed the soundest principles of the art of war ;</p><p>and, what is of no less consequence in a commander, kept up a strict discipline, and took care that the laws of su⅛or-dination were punctually observed. The excessive license which the regiments of guards, particularly the life company of the Preobajerskoy guards, presumed to exercise, under the very eyes of the empress in St Petersburg, afforded no good example to the rest of the army ; and Elizabeth, in appointing those soldiers of that life company who had been most guilty of flagrant disorders, and the basest conduct, to be officers in the marching regiments, gives us no very high idea of what was required in an officer, but rather serves easily to explain whence it arose that such frequent complaints were made of insubordination. A great number of excellent regulations that had been introduced into the army, and always enforced by foreigners, especially by Mun-nich, were suffered by the Russian generals to fall into total disuse. The bad effects of this negligence were very soon perceived ; and it was undoubtedly a circumstance highly favourable to the Russian troops, that for several years successively in the war which we have had occasion so often to mention, they had to engage with such a master in the military art as the king of Prussia, and by their conflicts with him, as well as by their connection with the Austrians, and in the sequel with the Prussian soldiery, had an opportunity of learning so many things, and of forming themselves into regular combatants.</p><p>“ Elizabeth tarnished her reign, however, by the institution of a political court of inquisition, under the name of a secret state chancery, empowered to examine into and punish all such charges as related to the expression of any kind of displeasure against the measures of government. This, as is usual in such cases, opened a door to the vilest practices. The lowest and most profligate of mankind were now employed as spies and informers, and were rewarded for their denunciations and calumnies against the most virtuous characters, if these happened by a look, a shrug of the shoulders, or a few harmless words, to signify their disapprobation of the proceedings of the sovereign.”</p><p>The grand duke ascended the throne by the name of Peter III. This prince’s conduct has been variously represented. He entered on the government possessed of an enthusiastic admiration of the virtues of the king of Prussia, with whom he immediately made peace, and whose principles and practice he seems to have adopted as patterns for his imitation. He<hi rend="sup">,</hi> might have surmounted the effects even of these peculiarities, unpopular as they then were in Russia ; but it is said that he aimed at reforms in his dominions which Peter the Great durst not attempt ; and that he even ventured to cut off the beards of his clergy. He was certainly a weak man, who had no opinions of his own, but childishly adopted the sentiments of any person who took the trouble to teach him. His chief amusement was buffoonery ; and he would sit for hours looking with pleasure at a merry-andrew singing drunken and vulgar songs. He was a stranger to the country, its inhabitants, and their manners ; and suffered himself to be persuaded by those about him, that the Russians were fools and beasts unworthy of his attention, except to make them, by means of the Prussian discipline, good fighting machines. These opinions regulated his whole conduct, and prepared the way for that revolution which faults of a different kind tended to hasten.</p><p>Becoming attached to a lady of the noble family of Vo-rontzoff, he disgusted his wife, who was then a beautiful wo-' man in the prime of life, of great natural talents and great acquired accomplishments ; whilst the lady whom he preferred to her was but one degree above an idiot. The Princess Dashkoff, the favourite’s sister, who was married to a man whose genius was not superior to that of the emperor, being <hi rend="italic">dame d'honneur</hi>  and lady of the bed-chamber, had of course much of the empress’s company. Similarity of situations knit these two illustrious personages in the</p></body></text></TEI>