<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>RUSS, a small island in the Eastern Seas, near the west coast of Nassau. Long. 99. 48. E. Lat. 2. 53. S.</p><p>RUSSELL, William, a very popular historian, the eldest son of Alexander Russell and Christian Ballantyne, was born in the year 1741 at Windydoors, a farm-house in the parish of Stowe and county of Selkirk. Most of the parish is within the limits of the county of Edinburgh. At an early age he was sent to school in the neighbouring village of Inverleithen, well known as a delightful place of summer resort. Here he acquired an elementary knowledge of the Greek and Latin languages ; and private study afterwards enabled him to supply many of the deficiencies of his early education. In 1756 he was removed to Edinburgh, in order to be instructed in writing and arithmetic ; and after having attended to these branches for about ten months, he was bound an apprentice to the bookselling and printing business for the term of five years. While engaged in this occupation, he discovered the utmost ardour in literary pursuits ; nor was his situation unfavourable to the acquisition of useful and elegant knowledge.</p><p>After the completion of his apprenticeship, he published a select collection of modern poems, which was favourably received. The first edition we have not seen ; the second bears the subsequent title: “ The select Poems of our most celebrated contemporary British Poets : viz. Dr Akenside, Mr Gray, Mr Mason, W. Shenstone, Esq. Mr W. Collins, Lord Lyttelton, Mess. Wartons, Mr Blacklock, Mr Beattie, Mr Ogilvie, etc. Vol.I. Second edition, with additions.” Edinb. 1764, 12mo. He afterwards congratulated himself on having contributed to extend the popularity of Gray and Shenstone in the northern part of the kingdom. It may be mentioned as a proof of his classical taste, that at this early period of life he entertained the highest admiration for the sublime odes of Gray, which he was accustomed to recite in a wild and enthusiastic manner. In the year 1763, while employed as a journeyman printer, he became a member of a literary association, denominated the Miscellaneous Society, which was composed of students and other young men anxious to exercise their talents and to improve their taste. This juvenile society included other individuals who afterwards rose to distinction. Among these we find Sir Robert Liston, who was employed in several important embassies, and Mr Dalzel, who became professor of Greek in this university.</p><p>About the same period he made an attempt to adapt Crebillon’s <hi rend="italic">Rhadamisthe el Zenobie</hi>  to the English stage. The manuscript was submitted to the inspection of his two friends Liston and Dalzel; who, after a very careful perusal, stated not a few objections to particular passages, though they do not appear to have condemned the entire performance. This tragedy was at length offered to Garrick: but Murphy’s Zenobia was at that time in rehearsal; and if the merit of Russell’s play had been more conspicuous, it probably would not have been accepted. In 1764, he issued proposals for publishing a second volume of his collection of poems, which however did not make its appearance. With the view of arranging his materials, he now retired to the country, and about this period of his life he maintained an epistolary correspondence with Lord Elibank, Dr Ogilvie, and Mr Dalzel, by all of whom he seems to have been regarded as a young man of promising talents. In the course of the ensuing year, Lord Elibank, who was himself a man of literature, invited him to his seat in the county of Haddington, where he spent the greater part of the autumn, and had an opportunity of conversing with many distinguished individuals. To this nobleman he seems to have looked for favour and protection. The hope of obtaining preferment through his influence, had induced him to relinquish his original employment; and in the mean time he continued to prosecute his studies, particularly in the departments of history and polite literature.</p><lb/><p>Having resided with his father till the month of May 1767, he proceeded to London in quest of honour and emolument. But his high hopes were speedily blasted; and after having in vain waited for advancement through the influence of Mr Hume, Lord Elibank, General Murray, and Governor Johnstone, he was under the necessity of contracting his views, and engaging himself as a corrector of the press in the great office of William Strahan, afterwards printer to his majesty. To find himself thus placed in a situation so inadequate to his expectations, must have cast a temporary gloom over his mind ; but the freshness of youth, added to the natural vivacity of his mind, would have enabled him to support even greater disappointments. In some brief notices found among his papers after his death, he mentions his expectations of preferment through the interest of these individuals; but he does not aver that his hopes were founded on their promises. The disappointments of human life may very frequently be traced to the unreasonableness of our expectations.</p><p>In the year 1769 he quitted the employment of Mr Strahan, and was engaged as overseer of the printing office of Brown and Adlard. During the same year he published an “ Ode to Fortitude,” which was immediately reprinted at Edinburgh by his former masters, Martin and Wotherspoon. His “ Sentimental Tales” appeared in 1770; and from this time he contributed to the periodical publications many essays in prose as well as verse. In 1772 he published a collection of “Fables, Moral and Sentimental,” and “An Essay on the Character, Manners, and Genius of Women, from the French of M. Thomas.” In 1774 he produced an octavo volume under the title of “ Julia, a Poetical Romance.” Of this work, which is founded on the <hi rend="italic">Nouvelle Heloise</hi>  of Rousseau, neither the plan nor the execution can be commended. In the estimate of his literary character Russell dissented from the public opinion : his historical works, which have met with a very favourable reception, he considered as greatly inferior to his poetical works, which have been totally neglected. But his friends certainly had no reason to regret that the collective edition of his poems, which he long meditated, never made its appearance. On the death of Hume he produced an elegy which occasioned a sarcastic effusion from another poet. Mickle, who abhorred the scepticism of Hume, and who believed himself to have been materially injured by Smith, concludes his verses with this stanza:</p><p>For him shall Russell rant and rave</p><p>In hobbling rumbling lays ;</p><p>And Smith in barbarous sleepy prose</p><p>Shall grunt and croak his praise.</p><p>Russell is the author of the verses on the death of Dr Armstrong, subscribed W. R. and dated from Gray’s Inn, Sept. 10, 1779, which are commonly printed with the poems of that classical writer. Before this period he had apparently relinquished his connexion with the printing-office, and had entirely devoted himself to the pursuits of literature. His “ History of America,” published in numbers, was completed in the course of the same year. This work was received with some degree of favour ; hut the splendid merit of Dr Robertson’s history precluded all competition. During the same year, 1779, he likewise published, in octavo, the first two volumes of“ The History of Modern Europe; with an account of the Decline and Fall of the Roman Empire, and a View of the Progress of Society from the fifth to the eighteenth century. In a Series of Letters from a Nobleman to his Son.” Their reception was so favourable as to exceed his most sanguine expectations. His studies experienced a temporary interruption in 1780, when he embarked for Jamaica in order to recover some money, due to him as the heir of his brother James, who, after a residence of several years, had died in that island. He after-</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>