<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>1794. Kosciuszko was recalled from Italy, and arrived at Cracow, where the Poles received him as their deliverer. .Here he was joined by some other officers, and took the <hi rend="sub">1</hi> command of his little army, consisting of about three thousand infantry and twelve hundred cavalry. On the 24th of March was published the manifesto of the patriots, in which they declared the motives for their insurrection, and called on their countrymen to unite in the glorious attempt to free the republic from a foreign yoke. Kosciuszko was soon joined by three hundred peasants armed with scythes, and some other small reinforcements gradually came in. A body of seven thousand Russians had collected to oppose the movements of this little army, and a battle took place, in which the patriots were successful.</p><p>While the insurrection had thus auspiciously commenced on the frontiers, the confederates of the capital were nearly crushed by the exertions of the Russian general. Hearing at Warsaw of the success of Kosciuszko, Igelstrom caused all those whom he suspected of having any concern in the insurrection to be arrested; but these measures served only to irritate the conspirators. On the 18 th of April they openly avowed their confederacy with the patriots of the frontiers, and proceeded in great numbers to attack the Russian garrison. Two thousand Russians were put to the sword, and the general, being besieged in his house, proposed a capitulation ; but, profiting by the .delay that had been granted him, he escaped to the Prussian camp, which lay at a little distance from Warsaw.</p><p>Wilna, the capital of Lithuania, followed the example of Warsaw ; but the triumph of the insurgents was there less terrible, as Colonel Yasinsky, who headed the patriots, conducted himself with so much skill, that he made all the Russians prisoners without bloodshed. The inhabitants of the cantons of Chelm and Lublin also declared themselves in a state of insurrection, and three Polish regiments who were employed in the service of Russia espoused the cause of their country. Some of the principal partisans of Russia were arrested, and sentenced to be hanged.</p><p>Kosciuszko exerted himself to the utmost to augment his army. He procured recruits among the peasants, and to inspire them with the more emulation, he adopted their dress, ate with them, and distributed rewards among such as appeared most to merit encouragement. All his attempts to inspire the lower orders of the Poles with the ardour of patriotism were, however, unavailing. A mutual distrust prevailed between the nobles and the peasants, and this was fomented by the arts of Stanislas and the other partisans of Russia.</p><p>The empress had sent into Poland two of her best generals, Suwaroff and Fersen. For some time Kosciuszko succeeded in preventing the junction of these commanders, and several engagements took place between the Russians and patriots, in which the former were generally successful. At length, on the 4th of October, the fate of Poland was decided by a sanguinary conflict between Kosciuszko and Fersen, at Macieyovitch, a small town of Little Poland, about sixty miles from Warsaw. The talents, valour, and desperation of Kosciuszko could not prevent the Poles from yielding to superior numbers. Almost the whole of his army was either cut in pieces or compelled to surrender at discretion, and the hero himself, covered with wounds, fell senseless on the field of battle, and was made prisoner.</p><p>The small number that escaped fled to Warsaw, and shut themselves up in the suburb of Praga. Hither they were pursued by Suwaroff, who immediately laid siege to the suburb, and prepared to carry it by storm. On the 2d of November he gave the assault, and having made himself master of the place, put to the sword both the soldiers and the peaceable inhabitants, without distinction of age or sex. It is computed that twenty thousand persons fell victims to the savage ferocity of the Russian general ; and, covered with the blood of the slaughtered inhabitants, the barbarian entered Warsaw in triumph.</p><p>Thus terminated the feeble resistance of the Polish patriots. The partition of the remaining provinces was soon effected, and Stanislas Augustus, who had long enjoyed merely the appearance of royalty, and had degraded himself by becoming the instrument of Russian usurpation, retired to Grodno, there to pass the remainder of his days, on a pension granted him by the empress.</p><p>1795. On the 18th of February, a treaty of defensive alliance between the empress of Russia and his Britannic majesty was signed at St Petersburg. The ostensible object of this treaty was to maintain the general tranquillity of Europe, and more especially of the north ; and by it Russia agreed to furnish Great Britain with ten thousand infantry and two thousand horse in case of invasion ; while Great Britain was, under similar circumstances, to send her imperial majesty a squadron consisting of two ships of seventy-four guns, six of sixty, and four of fifty, with a complement of four thousand five hundred and sixty men. On the 18th of March was signed the act by which the duchy of Courland, together with the circle of Pilten, all of which had lately belonged to the Duke of Courland, but had long retained only the shadow of independence, submitted themselves to the Russian dominion.</p><p>In this year there took place between the courts of St Petersburg and Stockholm a dispute which threatened to terminate in a war. Gustavus III. had been assassinated<hi rend="sup">1 </hi>by Ankerstroem at a masquerade, on the 15th of March 1791 ; and the young king GustavusAdolphus being still a minor, the Duke of Sudermania, his uncle, had been appointed regent of the kingdom. The regent had determined to effect a marriage between his nephew and a princess of the house of Mecklenburg ; but Catherine publicly declared that the late king had betrothed his son to one of her grand-daughters. The misunderstanding hence originating was increased by the rude and indecorous behaviour of the Baron von Budberg, the Russian minister at Stockholm ; and matters seemed tending to an open rupture, when, in the year 1796, a French emigrant named Christin effected a reconciliation, and General Budberg, the baron’s uncle, was sent as ambassador to Stockholm from the Russian court. In consequence of this reconciliation, the young king, attended by the regent, and a numerous train of Swedish courtiers, set out on a visit to St Petersburg, where they arrived on the 24th of August, and an interview took place between the empress and her royal visiters, for the purpose of finally adjusting the projected matrimonial alliance. Gustavus Adolphus was much pleased with the appearance of the Grand Duchess Alexandra, but informed the empress, that by the fundamental laws of Sweden he could not sign the marriage-contract before the princess had abjured the Greek religion ; and as neither the solicitations nor the flatteries of Catherine could prevail on the young monarch to depart from the received custom of his country, the negotiation ended, and the next day Gustavus and his retinue quitted St Petersburg.</p><p>The last transaction of importance in the reign of Catherine was her invasion of the Persian territories, undertaken for the purpose of acquiring certain possessions on the shores of the Caspian. A Russian army entered Daghestan, and made itself master of Derbent, but was afterwards defeated by the Persians under Aga Mahmoud. The death of the empress took place, as we have elsewhere stated, on the 9th of November of this year ; and the Grand Duke Paul Pe-trovitch ascended the throne under the title of Paul I.</p><p>Paul Petrovitch had attained his forty-second year before the death of his mother placed him on the imperial throne ; but for many years before her death he had lived in a state of comparative obscurity and retirement, and had apparently been considered by the empress as incapable of taking</p></body></text></TEI>