<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>it suffered still more by the imprisonment of all the German merchants, and the confiscation of their effects, with the abolition of the old municipal franchises. Indeed from this period Novgorod never recovered its former splendour.</p><p>After his reduction of this city, Ivan invaded the territories of Livonia and Esthonia, in consequence, as we are told, of an affront offered to him by the inhabitants of Revel. Here, however, he met with a stout resistance, and does not seem to have made much progress. Towards the conclusion of his reign, the Razanian Tartars, who, though humbled, had continued to inhabit that district, made a hard struggle to shake off the Russian yoke that had been imposed on them ; but Ivan had established his authority too firmly for them to accomplish their purpose during his life. He died in 1505, and was succeeded by his son Vasilii Ivanovitch, commonly called Basilius III.</p><p>The Tartars of Kazan were still suffered to maintain a show of independency, by electing their own khans ; but a Russian noble, under the denomination of voyvode, was associated with the khan in the government, and took care that the administration should be conducted in such a manner as to secure the interests of his master. About fourteen years after the death of Ivan, however, the Tartars resolved to overturn so humiliating an administration. They murdered the Russian voyvode, expelled their nominal khan, and united themselves with their brethren of the Crimea. With their assistance they assembled a mighty force, entered the Russian dominions, and carried their arms even to the gates of Moscow. The grand prince Vasilii found himself at that time unable to resist the barbarians ; and therefore purchased an exemption from general pillage by great presents, and a promise of renewed allegiance. The Tartars retired, but carried off immense booty, and nearly three hundred thousand prisoners, the greater part of whom they sent to Theodosia in the Crimea, and sold to the Turks. This humiliation of Vasilii did not, however, long continue; and he was soon enabled to make head against the Tartars, and to recover possession of the city Kazan, and of Pscove, a city which had been built by the Princess Olga, and was the great rival of Novgorod in wealth and commercial importance. Under this prince all the principalities of Russia were once more united, and they have remained ever since under the dominion of one sovereign.</p><p>It was under the son and successor of Vasilii, Ivan IV., or, as he is styled by the Russian historians, Ivan Vasilii-vitch II., that Russia completely emancipated herself from her subjection to the Tartars, and acquired a vast accession of territory, which extended her empire into the northeast of Asia, and rendered her for the first time superior in extent to any state that had appeared since the Roman empire. Vasilii died in 1533, having reigned twenty-eight years, and lived fifty-five. His son Ivan was only three years old when he succeeded to the throne ; and during his minority the state became a prey to anarchy and confusion. But when he attained his seventeenth year, he was able to assume the reins of government without opposition ; and, from the important transactions in which he immediately engaged, he must have been possessed of considerable resources.</p><p>In taking into his own hands the administration of the state, Ivan displayed so much prudence and manly fortitude as soon raised him very high in the estimation of his subjects. At the same time he showed marks of a tyrannical disposition and irritability of temper, which made him rather feared than admired by his friends, whilst they rendered him an object of terror to his neighbours and his enemies. He saw himself surrounded on all sides by contending factions, and to suppress these was the first object of his care. In the choice of means for effecting this, he does not seem to have been very scrupulous, provided they tended to the accomplishment of his end ; and in punishing the offences of those who opposed his purpose, his violence of temper not unfrequently led him to confound the innocent with the guilty. He was successful, however, in his great design ; and having secured the domestic tranquillity of his dominions, he had leisure to direct his attention to the more remote but not less predominant objects of his ambition. He resolved to attempt liberating his country for ever from the dominion of the Tartars; and he succeeded. In the year 1551 he marched an army in the depth of winter into the district of Kazan, and laid siege to the capital, checking by severe punishments the murmurs of his troops, who loudly and openly expressed their dislike to this expedition.</p><p>Before entering seriously on the siege of Kazan, he built several forts on the frontiers of the Tartar territories, by which he hoped to awe these barbarians, and to prevent them from disturbing the peace of his dominions. He then invested Kazan, and, in the year 1552, made himself master of it by the new, and, to the Tartars, unheard-of method of springing a mine below the walls. The inhabitants that escaped slaughter were offered mercy on condition that they should embrace the Christian faith. By this important conquest, the dominion of the Tartars, who had oppressed the Russians for more than three centuries, was completely and permanently overthrown.</p><p>About two years later Ivan extended his conquests eastward to the shores of the Caspian, and took possession of the territory that lay on the right bank of the Volga, round the city of Astracan, which was also inhabited by the Tartar hordes.</p><p>Ivan, as well as his grandfather, had found it necessary to chastise the inhabitants of Novgorod. But, in the year 1570, this city, being suspected Offormingaplot for delivering itself and the surrounding territory into the hands of the king of Poland, felt still more severely the effects of his vengeance. All who had been in any degree implicated in the conspiracy, to the number of twenty-five thousand, suffered by the hands of the executioner. The city of Pscove was threatened with a similar proscription ; but Ivan, on theiι voluntary submission, contented himself with the execution of a few monks, and the confiscation of the property of the most opulent inhabitants. It is not surprising that acts like these should have given to this prince the names of <hi rend="italic">Ierriblt </hi>and <hi rend="italic">tyrant,</hi>  by which historians have occasionally distinguished him ; though it is not a little extraordinary that he should have retained so much interest in the affections of his subjects, that when, to try their attachment, he, in 1575, abdicated the government, and retained only the title of Prince of Moscow, the majority of the nation loudly expressed their wish for him to resume the administration of affairs. We can account for this only by considering the measures which he had adopted for the improvement and the civilization of his people. These were of such a nature as in a great measure to obliterate the remembrance of his cruelty and oppression. He promulgated a new code of laws, composed partly of such ancient statutes as were still in force, and were capable of improvement, and partly of new regulations, which he either contrived himself, or adopted from the neighbouring states. He found it necessary, however, to render many of these laws extremely severe ; though their execution was most frequently exemplified in the persons of his nobles, whose proud obstinacy seemed unconquerable by more lenient measures.</p><p>Ivan cultivated an intercourse with several of the European states, especially with Germany. In 1547, he sent a splendid embassy to the Emperor Charles V., requesting him to permit a number of German artists, mechanics, and literary men, to establish themselves in Russia. Charles readily complied with his request, and several hundred volunteers were collected and assembled at Lubeck, whence they were to proceed through Livonia to Moscow. The Lubeck-</p></body></text></TEI>