<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ers, however, afraid lest the improvement of the Russians in arts and manufactures might render them independent of their neighbours, and diminish the commercial intercourse that had long subsisted between their city and the principal towns of Russia, arrested the Germans on their route ; and, in concert with the merchants of Revel and Riga, sent a petition to Charles, requesting him to recall the permission he had granted. In consequence of these measures, many of the German artists returned home; but several of them escaped the vigilance of the Lubeckers, and reached Moscow by a circuitous journey. Ivan endeavoured to revenge himself on the Livonians by invading their country, which was strenuously defended by the Teutonic knights; and these champions, finding at last that they were unable to maintain their ground, put the territory under the protection of Poland.</p><p>The Swedes also received a share of the Livonian territories ; and this circumstance gave rise to a war between them and the Russians. Ivan invaded Finland; but that ’country was bravely defended by William of Furstenberg, grand-master of the Livonian knights, with the assistance of the troops of Gustavus Vasa; and it does not appear that Ivan gained much in this expedition, though we are told that the Livonian grand-master ended his life in a Russian prison.</p><p>In 1553, an event happened which first led to an intercourse between Russia and England. Some Englishmen, who were at that time on a voyage of discovery, landed on the shores of the White Sea, where soon after was built the port of Archangel. They were hospitably received by the natives ; and intimation of the circumstance being conveyed to Ivan, he sent for the strangers, and was so much pleased with their abilities and deportment, that he resolved to give every encouragement to the English commerce, and thus open a new channel of intercourse with a highly polished nation, by which his subjects might obtain fresh incitements to activity and industry. He expressed the highest esteem for Queen Elizabeth, and requested by his ambassador, that if the ingratitude of his subjects should ever compel him to quit Russia (a circumstance by no means improbable), she would grant him an asylum in her dominions. It was in consequence of this accidental communication between the Russians and the English that England first engaged in a trade to Russia, and promoted this new commerce by the establishment of a company of Russian merchants in London.</p><p>About twenty years after Astracán had been annexed to the Russian empire, a new acquisition of territory accrued to it from the conquests of a private adventurer, in the unknown regions of Siberia. The steps that led to the acquisition of this immense tract of the Asiatic continent are thus related by Tooke.</p><p>“ The grand prince, Ivan III. had already sent out a body of men, who penetrated across the Ingrian Mountains, and traversed all the districts as far as the river Oby. But, amidst the urgent affairs of government, the discoveries they made insensibly fell into oblivion. Some years afterwards, a merchant named Stroganof, who was proprietor of some salt-works on the confines of Siberia, was curious to gain a farther knowledge of that country, which was likewise inhabited by Tartars, whose khan resided in the capital Sibir. Perceiving, among the persons who came to him on affairs of trade, men who belonged to no nation with which he was acquainted, he put several inquiries to them concerning the place whence they came, and once sent a few of his people with them back to their country. These people brought with them, at their return from the regions they had now explored, and which proved to be this very Siberia, a great quantity of valuable furs, and thus opened to their master a new road to wealth. However, not sc covetous as to wish to keep this treasure to himself, he sent information of it to the court, and the attention of government was once more directed to this country. But the conquest of it, and its conjunction with Russia, was reserved foi an adventurer named Timoseyef Yermak. This Yermak, at the head of a gang of Don Kozaks, had made it his practice to rob and plunder the caravans and passengers that occasionally frequented the roads, as well as the inhabitants, wherever he came, and was so fortunate as to escape the search of the Russian troops that had been sent out against him and his band, which consisted of not fewer than six thousand men. On their flight, he and his people accidentally came to the dwelling of Stroganof, where, hearing much talk about Siberia, and being persons who had nothing to lose, and therefore might put all to the hazard, they soon formed a plan to penetrate farther into that country, and there seek at once their safety and their fortune. After numerous struggles and conflicts with the natives, which greatly reduced their numbers, they at length conquered the capital, and shortly after the whole country. Yermak now presented the fruit of his toilsome and perilous victories to his Czar, @@<hi rend="sup">1 </hi>Ivan, in hopes of obtaining thereby a pardon of his former depredations, which was granted him accordingly; and by the building of several towns, and the constructing a number of forts, the possession of this country was soon permanently secured. The less and the greater Kabardey were also added to Russia in the reign of Ivan. This Czar, however, not only enlarged the circumference of his empire, partly by force of arms and partly by accident, but he resolved to reform his people, to render them more polished, more skilful, and more industrious ; but this he found to be the most arduous enterprise he could possibly have undertaken. The insuperable impediments which threw themselves in the way of the execution of this grand work, were the principal incitements to those frequent acts of cruelty and despotism which have covered his memory with so deep a stain.”</p><p>Towards the close of Ivan’s reign, a prodigious army of Tartars entered Russia, with a design to subdue the whole country. But Zerebrinoff, the Czar’s general, having attacked them in a defile, put them to flight with considerable slaughter. They then retired towards the mouth of the Volga, where they expected a considerable reinforcement; but being closely pursued by the Russians, and the Tartars in alliance with them, they were again defeated, and forced to fly towards Azof, where their army was almost annihilated.</p><p>From this time the empire of Russia became so formidable that none of the neighbouring nations could hope to make a total conquest of it. The Poles and Swedes indeed continued to be very formidable enemies; and, by the instigation of the former, the Crim Tartars, in 1571, again invaded the country with an army of seventy thousand men, which totally defeated the Russians in a battle fought within eighteen miles of the city of Moscow. The Czar retired with his most valuable effects to a well-fortified cloister; upon which the Tartars entered the city, plundered it, and set fire to several churches. A violent storm which happened at the same time soon spread the flames all over the city, which was entirely reduced to ashes in six hours. The fire likewise communicated itself to a powder magazine at some distance from the city; an accident by which upwards of fifty</p><p>@@@1 Previous to the reign of Vasilii, the predecessor of the monarch whose transactions we are now relating, the Russian sovereigns held the title of Velikn Kniaz, which has been translated Grand Duke, though it more properly denotes Grand Prince ; and by this latter appellation we have accordingly distinguished the preceding monarchs. Vasilii, near the conclusion of his reign, adopted the title of Czar or Emperor ; but this title was not fully established till the successes and increasing power of his son Ivan enabled the latter to confirm it both at home and abroad ; and since his time it has been universally acknowledged.</p></body></text></TEI>