<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>11. <hi rend="italic">Kamschats.—</hi>This is another polar people, consisting of six races and 48,000 souls.</p><p>12.    <hi rend="italic">Esquimaux.—</hi>This northern race is estimated at 20,000.</p><p>13.    <hi rend="italic">Indians.—</hi>There are three races of Indians, estimated at 30,000 souls in all.</p><p>There are, besides, in the Russian empire, 25,000 Greeks, 10,000 gypsies, 15,000 Persians, and 6000 Arabians on the river Kama. There are likewise in the empire Hindus, Osman Turks, and in the cities and towns mercantile people belonging to England, France, Italy, and other countries.</p><p>It appears from the researches of De Jonnes in the <hi rend="italic">Revue Encyclopédique</hi>  for August 1833, that the mortality of Russia and Poland has remained stationary for a great number of years. The ratio of deaths to the population is one in forty-four, the annual mortality in each million of the inhabitants being 22,700. This differs somewhat from the statements of Herrmann, from whose elaborate researches concerning the progress of population in Russia the following conclusions have been drawn, viz. 1. The proportion of births to the number of inhabitants is one to twenty-five for the whole empire. 2. The proportion of deaths to the total population is one in forty. @@<hi rend="sup">1</hi>  3. The general proportion of births to deaths in the whole empire is sixteen to ten. 4. The proportion of male to female births is forty-four to forty. The following table is of a more recent date than the researches of Herrmann. It is formed from the reports published by the synod (which, however, includes only the members of the orthodox Greek church), and shows the rate of the progressive increase of the population, as far as relates to that most numerous body of the people.</p><table><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"/><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>1806.</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>1810.</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>1816.</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>1820.</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Marriages</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>299,057</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>320,389</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>329,683</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>317,805 @@<hi rend="sup">2</hi></p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Births</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>1,361,286</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>1,374,926</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>1,457,606</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>1,570,399 @@<hi rend="sup">3</hi></p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Deaths</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>818,585</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>903,380</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>820,383</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>9l7,680 @@<hi rend="sup">4</hi></p></cell></row><row><cell cols="2" rows="1"><p>Deaths of per- </p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"/><cell cols="1" rows="1"/><cell cols="1" rows="1"/></row><row><cell cols="2" rows="1"><p>sons above a hundred </p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>350</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>689</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>807</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="2" rows="1"><p>years old </p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"/><cell cols="1" rows="1"/><cell cols="1" rows="1"/></row></table><p>The increase of population in Russia appears to be equal to that of any European country. It is indeed not a little remarkable, that in places where neither nature nor fortune have been lavish of their bounties, the inhabitants live one half longer than those who enjoy the sunny skies and lovely landscapes of Italy, and exactly twice as long as those who people the capital of Austria ; yet very recent and elaborate investigations have proved this to be the fact. The instances of longevity in Russia are astonishing. In 1821 the deaths were reckoned at 945,088 ; and of these, 221 were above 105 years of age, 120 above 110 ditto, seventy-eight above 115 ditto, forty-nine above 120 ditto, sixteen above 125 ditto, five above 130 ditto ; one obtained to the great age of between 145 and 150 ditto; and another had tenaciously adhered to life till he had reached the almost antediluvian term of existence, 155 years.</p><p>The government of Russia is that of an absolute hereditary monarchy, where the will of the sovereign is the supreme law of the empire. No restraint can be imposed on it ; but the emperors themselves have endeavoured in some degree to qualify this unlimited power, which is likewise somwehat moderated by the rights and privileges enjoyed through long-established usage by many bodies of people in different provinces, and which claims it would be dangerous to the monarch to infringe. The emperors of the house of Holstein have more than once declared that they would wish to follow fixed laws in whatever appertains to the rights of individuals and corporations. Arbitrary enactments are partly abolished ; indeed they are only enforced against the great, or courtiers less solicitous about liberty than personal aggrandisement. The highest department of government is the council of the empire, which was established in 1810, to render the laws and the administration less liable to change. In 1811 it was completely organized, and consisted of thirty-five members and four presidents. It is divided into four departments, viz. law or legislation, the supreme court of judicature in spiritual and civil affairs ; war ; civil and church affairs ; and internal political economy, or administration of the public revenue. The emperor himself is president, and, in his absence, one of the members whom he formally appoints president every year takes his place. Each department has its president, and the whole together have a common secretary, who is principal director of chancery, and the organ through which the council of the empire makes known its decisions to the monarch. He is also the person who bears the commands of the sovereign to the directing council of the empire, or makes them known to individual departments ; he expedites all the orders of the above council to the respective authorities who are to execute them ; and he receives all petitions, and the like, directed to the emperor in person. Each department has its state secretary. The ministers are members of the council of the empire, but they are disqualified from being presidents of the departments. The introduction of the members to the departments takes place half yearly. The original outline, or sketch of every law, ordinance, or regulation, is laid before the council of the empire, who examine it ; but the sovereign power alone can give it efficiency. There are three commissions in connection with the council of the empire ; these are, commissions of law, petitions, and the chancery of the empire. Alexander gave new activity to the law commission, by which about 70,000 ukases relative to civil rights were rescued from oblivion, and arranged in proper order. The archives of the chancery of the empire contain a collection of accurate accounts of state affairs of former years ; complete accounts of the present situation of the government, the protocols of the council of the empire, and the imperial decisions. Each commission has a director, and is divided into several sections, over which a head presides. Such is the constitution of the Russian council of the empire.</p><p>The directing senate is one over which the emperor also presides. It is the supreme tribunal in all affairs of a home or internal description, as distinguished from those of a foreign nature. As guardian of the law, the sovereign watches over the administration of justice, superintends the management of the income and expenditure of the state, as well as looks after the means of national instruction, the preservation of public security, and the abolition of every illegal proceeding. The minister of justice is at the same time general procurator ; but the remaining members are undefined, partly consisting of the ministers, who have likewise seats in the council of the empire. The directing senate is divided into eight departments, five of which have their constant seat at St Petersburg, and three at Moscow. These two bodies being composed of individuals either directly or indirectly</p><p>@@@ The annual mortality has diminished in some localities since Herrmann drew up his tables, which in some measure accounts for the discrepancy here observable.</p><p>@@@ <hi rend="sup">2</hi> It appears that the marriages in 1820 were fewer by 22,470 than in the year 1819.</p><p>@@@ <hi rend="sup">3</hi> The births of 1820 exceeded those of 1819 by 48,288.</p><p>@@@ <hi rend="sup">4</hi> The deaths of 1820 were fewer than those of 1819 by 1429.</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>