<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>move from home without his master’s leave, which is some-</p><p>times obtained for a certain annual sum, called <hi rend="italic">obroh,</hi>  in lieu of service. As a general rule, he has a house and a portion of land, for which he pays rent in labour instead of money. He works three days in the week for his master, and has the remainder of his time at his own disposal. A day’s labour of a man includes that of his wife and his horse when requisite. These peasants, who are for the most part in a state of the grossest ignorance, are perfect predestinarians, or fatalists ; and this doctrine serves as an excuse on all occasions for their habitual improvidence and want of forethought. Yet, though ignorant, superstitious, and a slave, the serf seems in general happy and contented, and bears about him no signs of oppression ; his desires are few and easily satisfied ; though his fare is coarse and poor, he seldom suffers from cold or hunger, and he is naturally gay, good-humoured, and light-hearted.” The situation of domestic servants is much worse than that of the peasant, whose great dread is the conscription, and a serious evil it is when it visits him. The peasant cannot legally be sold or transferred from one master to another, excepting with the whole of his family ; but this law is often broken or evaded. “ There are few landed proprietors who do not carry on a manufactory of some kind or other. The riches of the Russian gentleman lie in the labour of his serfs, which it is his study to turn to good account ; and he is the more urged to this, since the law which compels the peasant to work for him, requires him to maintain the peasant ; if the latter is found begging, the former is liable to a fine. He is therefore a master who must always keep a certain number of workmen, whether they are useful to him or not ; and as every kind of agricultural and out-doors employment is at a stand during the winter, he naturally turns to the establishment of a manufactory as a means of employing his peasants, and as a source of profit to himself. In some cases the manufactory is at work only during the winter, and the people are employed in the summer in agriculture. The alternate employment of the same man in the field and in the factory, which would be attempted in most countries with little success, is here rendered practicable and easy by the versatile genius of the Russian peasant, one of whose leading national characteristics is a general capability of turning his hand to any kind of work which he may be required to undertake.” Not only are the Russian nobles manufacturers, but they carry on the business in every branch ; and from the privileges which they enjoy, they have great advantages over the other classes who are not allowed to possess serfs. In almost every house some art is carried on, useful or ornamental ; and women are employed in spinning, weaving, knitting, carpet-making, and the like. Mr Bremner informs us that seven shillings and sixpence a week is the general pay of a labourer in the field, and that the best hands in the manufactories can only earn nine shillings and sixpence a week. Hence no people in Europe are so plainly or coarsely fed as the Russians. Their daily fare consists of pickled cucumbers, cabbages, and mushrooms, with a piece of black bread. Fish and butcher-meat are great rarities amongst the poor ; they live upon the wretched articles which we have specified.</p><p>The established religion of Russia is that of the Greek Church, to which the great bulk of the population belongs, although all others are tolerated, no civil or political disabilities attaching to those who profess other creeds. In regard to the doctrines of this church, it may be briefly stated, that they differ in several essential particulars from those of the Roman Catholics, although there is a general accordance. The first of these particulars is, that it holds the necessity of complete submersion of the whole body at baptism ; the second, that whilst it admits the doctrine of tran-substantiation in regard to the eucharist, it affirms that the bread must be leavened and the wine mixed with water, and they allow both elements to be distributed to every communicant, even to children before they have any correct idea of sin ; and a third important distinction relates to the marriage of the clergy, all secular or parish priests being bound to marry. The Greek Church further differs from the Roman Catholic by rejecting purgatory, predestination, works of supererogation, indulgences, and dispensations. Catechising and preaching are scarcely practised ; and mass forms the chief part of the public worship. No instrumental music is allowed, but vocal music is much cultivated. Fast days are numerous, and they are kept with great strictness. In addition to the Wednesday and Friday of every week, there are four principal fasts in the year, and several festivals which are celebrated with eastern pomp and splendour. This church rejects all round or solid images of the Saviour, or of saints, as idolatrous ; but pictures, mosaics, bas-reliefs, in short, whatever is represented on a flat surface, they do not consider as violations of the law which says, “ Thou shalt not make unto thee any graven image.” The state of religion amongst the lower orders is in general deplorable. The most important parts of public worship are, first, to pronounce distinctly and fluently the two words <hi rend="italic">Gospodi pomilui,</hi>  which mean, “ God be merciful ;” secondly, to make the sign of the cross on the breast a countless number of times ; and, thirdly, to bow the head to the ground repeatedly. The common people have a firm belief in good and bad angels. Evil spirits are the tempters and betrayers of men, and they believe that the sign of the cross, which they are very fond of making, will not only drive them away, but avert every kind of misfortune. There are comparatively few sectarians in Russia. The following is as near an approximation as can be arrived at, of the religious diversities of the Russian empire.</p><table><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Members of the Russo-Greek Church...........</p><p>Dissenters from the church, called <hi rend="italic">Razholniks,</hi>  or Heretics.......................................</p><p>Roman Catholics, including the united Greeks and the united Armenians.....................</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>.45,000,000     350,000</p><p>3,500,000</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Armenians not united..............................</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>..    250,000</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Members of the Confession of Augsburg (Pro- </p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="2"><p>2,000,000</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>testants...........................................</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Members of the Reformed Church...............</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>54,000</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Moravians 10,000, and Mennonites 6000........</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>16,000</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Mahommedans........................................</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>. 2,500,000</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Jews....................................................</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>.. 600,000</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Worshippers of the Grand Lama.................</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>,.    300,000</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Indians, devotees of Fetichism....................</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>,. 600,000</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Idolaters................................................</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>.    170,000</p></cell></row></table><p>The whole spirituality of the Greek Church is divided into priests belonging to some religious order, and secular priests. For the management of church affairs there are at present thirty-six eparchies of three different classes, only four being of the highest class, those of St Petersburg, Moscow, Novgorod, and Kief. There are nine metropolitans, thirteen archbishops, and twenty-nine bishops. All aspiring to these dignities must be members of some monastery, and unmarried. By a statement published a short time since, the number of monasteries throughout the empire would appear to be 350, with 5330 monks. There are ninety-eight nunneries, containing 4162 nuns ; all of them belong to the strict order of St Basil. There are 483 cathedrals, and 28,200 parish churches (of which 853 are situated in Bessarabia), with 218,418 ecclesiastics of the orthodox Greek ritual, and 7311 ecclesiastics of the united Greek ritual. The Russian clergy may be divided into three classes ; those who are in full orders, including “ pro-topapi,” or inferior priests, and “ papi,” or common priests ; those who are only in what may be called half orders, such as deacons and readers, who are not allowed to administer the sacrament ; and those who have received no ordination</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>