<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>people in favour of Otrepief. The courtiers of the usurper, who had long been jealous of his elevation, pretended to believe his assertions ; whilst those who were persuaded that the young prince had been murdered by order of tile present Czar, regarded this event as a judgment from heaven. The greater part of the nation appear to have been persuaded that the pretender was the real Dmitri ; and as they believed that he had been miraculously preserved, they piously resolved to concur with the hand of Providence in assisting him to recover his just rights. Thus, before he had set foot in Russia, a numerous party was formed in his behalf. He soon made his appearance on the frontiers with a regiment of Polish troops, and a body of Kozaks. Boris sent an army to oppose him ; but though the number of these troops greatly exceeded the small force of the invaders, the latter were so animated by the eloquence of their leader, and the intrepidity and personal bravery which he displayed in the field of battle, that, after a bloody conflict, the army of Boris was defeated, and the pretended Dmitri remained master of the field.</p><p>This victory served still further to strengthen the belief that Dmitri was favoured by heaven, and consequently could not be an impostor. To confirm the good opinion which he had evidently acquired, the victor treated his prisoners with great kindness ; caused the dead to be decently interred ; and gave strict injunctions to his troops to behave with humanity in the towns through which he passed. This gentle behaviour, when contrasted with the horrible excesses committed by the soldiers of Boris, wherever the people appeared to show any inclination towards the cause of the invader, gained Dmitri more adherents than even the persuasion that he was the lawful sovereign of the country. Unluckily for Boris, likewise, the superstition of the Russians was about this time directed against him, by the appearance of a comet, and by the more than usual coruscations of the aurora borealis, phenomena which were immediately regarded as manifest demonstrations that the Almighty was pouring out his phials of wrath on the devoted country. Boris, unable to resist the torrent of public opinion in favour of his rival, is said to have taken poison, and thus hastened that fate which he foresaw awaited him if he should fall into the hands of his enemies.</p><p>The death of Boris took place in the year 1605; and though the principal nobility at Moscow placed his son Feodor on the throne, the party of Dmitri was now so strong, that Feodor was dethroned and sent to prison with his mother and sister, within six weeks after his accession.</p><p>The successful monk had now attained the summit of his ambitious hopes, and made his entry into Moscow with the utmost magnificence. Not deeming himself secure, however, whilst the son of Boris remained alive, he is said to have caused him to be strangled, together with one of his sisters. The new Czar, though he evidently possessed great abilities, seems to have been deficient in point of prudence. Instead of conciliating the favour of his subjects, he openly displayed his predilection for the Poles, conferring on them high posts and dignities, and even conniving at the extravagance and enormities which they committed. This impolitic conduct, together with his partiality for the Catholic religion ; his marked indifference towards the public worship of the national church, and his want of reverence for the Greek clergy ; his marrying a Polish lady ; his affectation of Polish manners ; his inordinate voluptuousness, and the contempt with which he treated the principal nobility ; so exasperated the Russians, Shat discontents and insurrections arose in every quarter of the empire. The populace of the capital were at length roused to fury, by a rumour that a timber fort which he had caused to be constructed before Moscow, was intended to serve as an engine of destruction, and that at a martial spectacle which the Czar was preparing for the entertainment of his bride, the</p><p>Poles, and other foreigners that composed hie body guard, were from this building to cast firebrands into the city, and then slaughter the inhabitants. The people were still further incensed by the clergy, who declaimed against Dmitri as a heretic, and by Schuiskoy, a nobleman who had been condemned to death by the Czar, but had afterwards been pardoned. This nobleman put himself at the head of the enraged mob, and led them to attack the palace. They entered it by assault, put to the sword all the Poles whom they found within its walls, and afterwards extended their massacre to such as were discovered in other parts of the city. Dmitri himself, in attempting to escape, was over taken by his pursuers, and thrust through with a spear ; and his dead body, being brought back into the city, lay for three days before the palace, exposed to every outrage that malice could invent or rage inflict. His father-in-law and his wife escaped with their lives, but were detained as prisoners, and the Czarina was confined at Yaroslaf.</p><p>Schuiskoy, who had pretended to be actuated by no other motives than those of the purest patriotism, now aspired to the vacant throne, and had sufficient interest to carry his election. His reign was short and uninteresting, and indeed from tllis time till the accession of the house of Rom-anof in 1613, the affairs of Russia have little to gratify our curiosity. Schuiskoy’s reign was disturbed by the pretensions of two fictitious Dmitris, who successively started up, and declared themselves to be either the late Czar, or the prince whom he had personated ; and his neighbours the Swedes and Poles, taking advantage of the internal dissensions in the empire, made many successful incursions into Russia, set fire to Moscow’, and massacred above a hundred thousand of the people. The Russians, dissatisfied with the reigning prince, treated with several of the neighbouring potentates for the disposal of the imperial crown. They offered it to Vladislaf, or Uladislas, son of Sigismund<hi rend="sub">1</hi> king of Poland, on condition that he should adopt the Greek persuasion ; but as he rejected this preliminary, they turned their eyes first on a son of Charles IX. of Sweden, and then on a young native Russian, Mikhail Feodorovitch, of the house of Romanof, a family which was distantly related to their ancient Czars, and of which the head was then metropolitan of Rostof, and as such held in great estimation. The influence of the clergy, who exerted themselves for Mikhail, both by personal intrigues and by the dissemination of pretended revelations from heaven, silenced the supporters of the other claimants ; and after a long series of confusion and disaster, there ascended the Russian throne a new family, whose descendants have raised the empire to a state of grandeur and importance unequalled in any former period.</p><p>Having traced Russia through the obscurer stages of its history, we are now to witness its sudden elevation amongst the powers of Europe, and to accompany it in its hasty strides towards that importance which it has lately assumed. But before ¼<hi rend="sup">r</hi>e enter on the transactions that have enriched the pages of the Russian annals since the accession of the house of Romanof, it may not be uninteresting to take a general view of the state of the empire at the beginning of the seventeenth century.</p><p>At this period the government of Russia may be considered as a pure aristocracy, since the supreme power rested in the hands of the nobles and the superior clergy. In particular, the boyars, or chief officers of the army, who were also the privy counsellors of the prince, possessed a very considerable share of authority. The election of the late princes Boris, Dmitri, and Schuiskoy, had been conducted principally by them, in concert with the inhabitants of Mosoow, where was then held the seat of government. The common people, especially those of the inferior towns, though nominally free, had no share in the government or in the election of the chief ruler. The boors, or those</p></body></text></TEI>