<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>to merit on the occasion, it must be allowed that the innovation showed an uncommon combination of courage with talent and good sense ; and the accurate description of the disease that he has given us fully establishes his claim to the character of an accurate nosologist.</p><p>22.    On the Symptoms and Cure of Dropsy, and especially of Water in the Head. 1793.</p><p>23.    An Account of the Influenza of Philadelphia in 1789, 1790, 1791.</p><p>24.    Observations on the State of the Body and Mind in Old Age. 1794.</p><p>25.    Observations on the Nature and Cure of Gout and Hydrophobia. 1797.</p><p>26.    Inquiry into the Cause and Cure of the Cholera Infantum. 1797.</p><p>27.    Observations on Cynanche Trachealis. 1797.</p><p>28.    Introductory Lectures. 1801. Ed. 2, 1811; with ten new introductory lectures, and two lectures on the Pleasures of the Senses and of the Mind.</p><p>29.    In 1809 he published the works of Sydenham and of Cleghorn, with Notes, and in 1810 those of Pringle and Hilary.</p><p>30.    On Diseases of the Mind, 8vo, 1812; an elaborate work, which had long been impatiently expected.</p><p>31.    A letter on Hydrophobia, 1813; addressed to Dr Hosack, and containing additional reasons for believing the seat of the disease to be chiefly in the blood-vessels ; an opinion which, in all probability, has at least tended to shorten the sufferings of several individuals on whom the experiment of profuse depletion has been tried.</p><p>Dr Rush’s numerous publications obtained him many marks of respect from his contemporaries, and procured him admission, as an honorary member, into the most distinguished literary and philosophical societies of Europe. His name was familiar to the medical world as the Sydenham of America. His accurate observations and correct discrimination of epidemic diseases well entitled him to this distinction ; while, in the original energy of his reasoning, he far excelled his prototype. His literary and professional character, indeed, appears to have been greatly influenced by the moral and political sentiments which were prevalent in his day. A love of innovation led him to that proud defiance of established authority which is just as likely to be pernicious as to be salutary.· The study of the learned languages he depreciated, in one of his early essays, as unfit for a republican education ; and this was the first step to the true Jacobin doctrine, that it was unrepublican and aristocratical to have received any education whatever. In physic, his rejection of the prejudices of antiquity was somewhat more consistent with moderation, and the reform that he attempted was occasionally more successful than his literary speculations ; nor can it be denied that there are a multitude of original suggestions in his works, which may very probably be found capable of affording valuable hints to the lovers of medical experiments.</p><p>Hosack and Francis in the <hi rend="italic">American Med. Philos. Register ;</hi>  Chalmers’s <hi rend="italic">Biographical Dictionary,</hi>  xxv. London, 1816, 8vo.    (l. l.)</p><p>RUSHWORTH, <hi rend="smallcaps">John</hi>, the compiler of some very useful historical collections, was born in Northumberland about the year 1607, being descended of honourable ancestors. After attending the university of Oxford for some time, he removed to Lincoln’s Inn ; but the study of the law not suiting his genius, he soon deserted it, in order to seek a situation where he might more easily gratify his love for political information. He frequently attended the meetings of parliament, and wrote down the speeches both of the king and members. During the space of eleven years from 1630 to 1640, when no parliament was held, he was an attentive observer of the great transactions of state in the star-chamber, the court of honour, and exchequer chamber, when all the judges of England assembled there on cases of great emergency. Nor did he neglect to observe with a watchful eye those events which happened at a distance from the capital. He visited the camp at Berwick, and was present at the battle of Newborn, at the treaty of Ripon, and at the great council of York.</p><p>In 1640 he was appointed assistant to Henry Elsynge, clerk to the House of Commons, and thus had the best opportunities of being acquainted with their debates and proceedings. The Commons considered him as a person worthy of confidence ; and, in particular, they trusted him with carrying their messages to the king whilst he remained at York. And when the parliament created Sir Thomas Fairfax their general, Rushworth was appointed his secretary, and discharged the office much to the advantage of his master. When Fairfax resigned his commission, his secretary returned to Lincoln’s Inn, and was soon afterwards (in 1651-52) chosen one of the committee that was appointed to deliberate concerning the propriety and means of altering or new-modelling the common law. He was elected one of the representatives for Berwick-upon-Tweed to the parliament which Richard Cromwell assembled in 1658, and was re-elected by the same town to the parliament which restored Charles II. to the crown.</p><p>After the Restoration, he delivered to the king several books of the privy-council, which he had preserved in his own possession during the commotions which then agitated the country. Sir Orlando Bridgeman, keeper of the great seal, chose him his secretary in the year 1677, an office which he enjoyed as long as Sir Orlando kept the seals. In 1678 he was a third time chosen member for Berwick, and a fourth time in the ensuing parliament in 1679. He was also a member of the parliament which was convened at Oxford. The different offices he had held afforded him favourable opportunities of acquiring a fortune, or at least an indcpen-denee ; yet, whether from negligence or prodigality, he was never possessed of wealth. Having run himself into debt, he was arrested and committed to the King’s Bench prison, Southwark, where he lingered for the last six years of his life in the most deplorable condition. His memory and judgment were much impaired, partly by age and partly by the too frequent use of spirituous liquors. He died on the l2th of May 1690.</p><p>His Historical Collections of private Passages in State, weighty Matters in Law, and remarkable Proceedings in Parliament, were published in folio at different times. The first part, comprehending the years between 1618 and 1629, appeared in 1659. The copy had been intrusted by Oliver Cromwell to Whitelock, with instructions to peruse and examine it. Upon perusing it, he thought it necessary to make some alterations and additions. The second part was published in 1680 ; the third in 1692 ; the fourth and last, which comes down to the year 1648, was published in 1701 ; and altogether they made seven volumes. These underwent a second edition in 1721 ; and the trial of the Earl of Strafford was added, which made the eighth. This work has been much applauded by those who condemn the conduct of Charles I., and accused of partiality by those who favour the cause of that unhappy monarch. One person in particular, Dr John Nelson of Cambridge, in a Collection of the Affairs of State, published by the command of Charles II., undertook to prove that Rushworth has concealed truth, endeavoured to vindicate the prevailing detractions of the times, as well as their barbarous actions, and with a kind of rebound to libel the government at second hand. But this accusation seems to be carried too far. His principles indeed led him to show the king and his adherents in an unfavourable light, and to vindicate the proceedings of parliament ; yet it cannot justly be affirmed that he has misrepresented or falsified any of the speeches or facts which he has admitted into his collection.</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>