<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Though there were many courts of judicature in this ’ widely-extended empire, the emperor was always lord paramount, and could take a cause from any court immediately before himself. But as several of the old nobles had the remains of principalities in their families, and held their own courts, the sovereign or his ministers, at a distance up the country, frequently found it difficult to bring a culprit out of one of these hereditary feudal jurisdictions, and to try him by the laws of the empire. This was a very dangerous limitation of imperial power, and the more so that some families claimed even a right of replevance. A fortunate opportunity soon offered of settling the dispute, and Alexei embraced it with great ability.</p><p>Some families on the old frontiers were taxed with their defence, for which they were obliged to maintain regiments ; and as they were but scantily indemnified by the state, it sometimes required the exertion of authority to make them keep up their levies. When, by the conquest of Kazan, the frontiers were far extended, these nobles found the regiments no longer burdensome, because, by the help of false musters, the formerly scanty allowance much more than reimbursed them for the expense of the establishment. The consequence was, that disputes arose among them about the right of guarding certain districts, and lawsuits were necessary to settle their respective claims. These were tedious and intricate. The emperor ordered all the family archives to be brought to Moscow, and all documents on both sides to be collected. A time was fixed for the examination ; a fine wooden court-house was built ; every paper was lodged under a guard ; and the day was appointed when the court should be opened and the claims heard. But on that morning the house, with all its contents, was in two hours consumed by fire. The emperor then said, “ Gentlemen, henceforward your rank, your privileges, and your courts, are the nation’s, and the nation will guard itself. Your archives are unfortunately lost, but those of the nation remain. I am the keeper, and it is my duty to administer justice for all and to all. Your rank is not private, but national, attached to the services you are actually performing. Henceforward Colonel Buturlin (a private gentleman) ranks before Captain Viazemsky (an old prince).”</p><p>The Russians owe more to this prince than some of their historians seem willing to acknowledge ; and there appears to be no doubt that several of the improvements attributed to Peter the Great were at least projected by his father. Under Alexei a considerable trade was opened with China, from which country silks, and other rich stuffs, were brought into Russia, and exchanged for the Siberian furs. The exportation of Russian products to other countries was also increased ; and we are assured that Alexei had even projected the formation of a navy, and would have executed the design, had he not been perpetually occupied in foreign wars and domestic troubles.</p><p>Alexei died in 1676, leaving three sons and six daughters. Two of the sons, Feodor and Ivan, were by a first marriage; the third, Peter, by a second. The two former? particularly Ivan, were of a delicate constitution, and some attempts were made by the relations of Peter to set them aside. These attempts, however, proved unsuccessful, and Feodor became the successor of Alexei.</p><p>The reign of this prince was short, and distinguished rather for the happiness which the nation then experienced, than for the importance of the transactions which took place. He continued the war with the Turks for four years after his father’s death, and at length brought it to an honourable conclusion, by a truce for twenty years, after the Turks had acknowledged the Russian right of sovereignty over the Kozaks. Feodor died in 1682, but before his death nominated his half-brother Peter his successor.</p><p>The succession of Peter, though appointed by their fa</p><p>vourite czar Feodor, was by no means pleasing to the majority of the Russian nobles, and it was particularly opposed by Galitzin, the prime minister of the late czar. This able man had espoused the interest of Sophia, the sister of, Feodor and Ivan, a young woman of eminent abilities and<hi rend="sub">1 </hi>the most insinuating address. Sophia, upon pretence of asserting the claims of her brother Ivan, who, though of a feeble body and weak intellect, was considered as the lawful heir of the crown, had really formed a design of securing the succession to herself ; and with that view, had not only insinuated herself into the confidence and good graces of Galitzin, but had brought over to her interests the Stre-Iitzes, who were the body-guard of the czars, and at this time were about fourteen thousand in number. These licentious soldiers assembled for the purpose, as was pretended, of placing on the throne Prince Ivan, whom they proclaimed czar by acclamation. During three days they roved about the city of Moscow, committing the greatest excesses, and putting to death several of the chief officers of state who were suspected of being hostile to the designs of Sophia. Their employer did not, however, entirely gain her point ; for as the new czar entertained a sincere affection for his half-brother Peter, he insisted that this prince should share with him the imperial dignity. This was at length agreed to ; and on the 6th of May 1682, Ivan and Peter were solemnly crowned joint emperors of all the Russias, while the Princess Sophia was nominated their copartner in the go-vernment-</p><p>From the imbecility of Ivan and the youth of Peter, who was now only ten years of age, the whole power of the government rested with Sophia and her minister Galitzin, although till the year 1687 the names of Ivan and Peter only were annexed to the imperial decrees. Scarcely had Sophia established her authority when she was threatened with deposition, from an alarming insurrection of the Stre-litzes. This was excited by their commander Prince Ko-vanskoi, who had demanded of Sophia that she should marry one of her sisters to his son, but had met with a mortifying refusal. In consequence of this insurrection, which threw the whole city of Moscow into terror and consternation, Sophia and the two young czars took refuge in a monastery about twelve leagues from the capital ; and before the Strelitzes could follow them thither, a considerable body of soldiers, principally foreigners, was assembled in their defence. Kovanskoi was taken prisoner, and instantly beheaded ; and though his followers at first threatened dreadful vengeance on his executioners, they soon found themselves obliged to submit. From every regiment was selected the tenth man, who was to suffer as an atonement for the rest ; but this cruel punishment was remitted, and only the most guilty among the ringleaders suffered death.</p><p>The quelling of these disturbances gave leisure to the friends of Peter to pursue the plans which they had formed for subverting the authority of Sophia ; and about this time a favourable opportunity offered, in consequence of a rupture with Turkey. The Porte was now engaged in a war with Poland and the German empire, and both these latter powers had solicited the assistance of Russia against the common enemy. Sophia and her party were averse to the alliance ; but as there w<hi rend="sup">τ</hi>ere in the council many secret friends of Peter, these had sufficient influence to persuade the majority that a Turkish war would be of advantage to the state. They even prevailed on Galitzin to put himself at the head of the army, and thus removed their principal opponent. It is difficult to conceive how a man, so able in the cabinet as Galitzin, could have suffered his vanity so far to get the better of his good sense, as to accept a military command, for which he certainly had no talents. Assembling an army of nearly three hundred thousand men, he marched towards the confines of Turkey, and there consumed two campaigns in marches and countermarches, and</p></body></text></TEI>