<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/>         </publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb09-20-r03-0856-02" facs="encyclopediabrit20newyrich_raw_0890.jp2" type="entry">

<p><label>ROSSELLINO</label>
<hi rend="smallcaps">Antonio (1427-c.</hi> 1479), one of the most skilful of Florentine sculptors, was the son of Matteo di Domenico Gamberelli, and had four brothers, who all practised some branch of the fine arts. Almost nothing is known about the life of Antonio, but many of his works</p><p>still exist, and are of the highest beauty, full of strong religious sentiment, and executed with the utmost delicacy' of touch and technical skill. The style of Antonio and his brother (see below) is a development of that of Donatello and Ghiberti ; it possesses all the refinement and soft sweetness of the earlier masters, but is not equal to them either in vigour or originality. Antonio’s chief work, still in perfect preservation, is the very lovely tomb of a young cardinal prince of Portugal, who died in 1459, aged only twenty-six. It occupies one side of a small chapel on the north of the nave of San Miniato. <note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="1"> Illustrated by Gonnelli, <hi rend="italic">Mon. Sepol. della Toscana,</hi> Florence, 1819, plate xxiii. </note> The recumbent effigy of the cardinal is very remarkable for the grace of its pose and the beauty of the portrait face. It rests on a handsome sarcophagus, and over it, under the arch which frames the whole, is a beautiful relief of the Madonna between two flying angels. The tomb was begun in 1461 and finished in 1466 ; Antonio received four hundred and twenty-five gold florins for it. A reproduction of this tomb with slight alterations, and of course a different effigy, was made by Antonio for the wife of Antonio Piccolomini, duke of Amalfi, in the church of S. Maria del Monte at Naples, where it still exists. For the same church he also executed some delicate reliefs, which perhaps err in being too pictorial in style, especially in the treatment of the backgrounds. A fine medallion relief by him is preserved in the Bargello at Florence (see fig.), and the original terra cotta model for this is in the possession of Mr Drury Fortnum ; in some small matters of</p>
<pb xml:id="eb09-20-r03-0857" facs="encyclopediabrit20newyrich_raw_0891.jp2"/>
<p>detail the original terra cotta is superior to the finished marble, especially in the treatment of the infant Christ.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>