<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/>         </publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb09-20-r03-0851-04" facs="encyclopediabrit20newyrich_raw_0885.jp2" type="entry">

<p><label>ROSEWOOD</label>
. Under this name several distinct kinds of ornamental timber are more or less known. That, however, so called in the United Kingdom is Brazilian rosewood, the <hi rend="italic">palissandre</hi> of the French, the finest qualities of which, coming from the provinces of Rio de Janeiro and Bahia, are believed to be the produce principally of <hi rend="italic">Dalbergia nigra,</hi> a Leguminous tree of large dimensions, called <hi rend="italic">cabiuna</hi> and <hi rend="italic">jacaranda</hi> by the Brazilians. The same name, jacaranda, is applied to several species of <hi rend="italic">Machxrvum,</hi> also trees belonging to the natural order <hi rend="italic">Legti-minosæ</hi> ; and there can be no doubt that a certain proportion of the rosewood of commerce is drawn from these sources. Formerly Brazilian rosewood was said, on the authority of the French botanist and traveller Guillemin, to be the produce of a species of <hi rend="italic">Triptolomæa,</hi> but that genus has now been constituted a section of <hi rend="italic">Dalbergia.</hi> Rosewood comes to the United Kingdom from Rio, Bahia, Jamaica, and Honduras. The heartwood attains large dimensions, but as it begins to decay before the tree arrives at maturity it is always faulty and hollow in the centre. On this account squared logs or planks of rose-</p>
<pb xml:id="eb09-20-r03-0852" facs="encyclopediabrit20newyrich_raw_0886.jp2"/>
<p>wood are never seen, the wood being imported in half round flitches 10 to 20 feet in length and from 5 to 12 inches in their thickest part. Owing to its irregular form the wood is sold by weight, and its value varies within wide limits according to the richness of colour. Rosewood has a deep ruddy brown colour, richly streaked and grained with black resinous layers. It takes a fine polish, but on account of its resinous nature it is somewhat difficult to work. The wood is very much in demand both by cabinetmakers and pianoforte-makers, by whom it is used both solid and in veneer.</p><p>The wood of <hi rend="italic">Dalbergia Iatifolia,</hi> a native of the East Indies used for ornamental furniture and carvings under the name of black wood, is frequently termed East Indian Rosewood, as is also the allied tree of Madras, <hi rend="italic">Dalbergia sissoides.</hi> The <hi rend="italic">Bois de Rose</hi> of the French, the Portuguese <hi rend="italic">Pao de Rosa,</hi> and the German <hi rend="italic">RoseaJiolz,</hi> is a Brazilian wood, the produce of <hi rend="italic">Physoealymma fioribunda,</hi> called in the United Kingdom tulip wood, and very highly esteemed on account of its beautiful rose colour and grain. African rosewood is from <hi rend="italic">Pteroearpus erinaceus,</hi> Dominican from <hi rend="italic">Cordia Geraseanthus,</hi> and in New South Wales the wood of <hi rend="italic">Synoum glaηdulosum</hi> locally receives the same name.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>