<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/>         </publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb09-20-r03-0857-01" facs="encyclopediabrit20newyrich_raw_0891.jp2" type="entry">

<p><label>ROSSELLINO</label>
<hi rend="smallcaps">Bernardo</hi> (1409-1464), was no less able as a sculptor than his younger brother (see above), and was also a very distinguished architect. His finest piece of sculpture is the tomb, in the Florentine Santa Croce, of Leonardo Bruni of Arezzo, the historian of Florence ; the recumbent effigy is a work of great merit. The inner cathedral pulpit at Prato, circular in form on a tall slender stem, was partly the work of Mino da Fiesole and partly by Bernardo Rossellino. The latter executed the very minute reliefs of St Stephen and the Assumption of the Virgin. For his part in the work he received sixty-six gold florins. The South Kensington Museum possesses a relief by Bernardo, signed and dated (1456). It is a fine portrait of the physician Giovanni da S. Miniato. <note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="1"> See Perkins, <hi rend="italic">Italian Sculptors,</hi> 1864, i. p. 207 ; also Id., <hi rend="italic">Tuscan Sculptors,</hi> p. 202, and <hi rend="italic">Historical Handbook of Italian Sculpture,</hi> 1883, p. 121. </note> Bernardo’s works as an architect were very numerous and important, and he was also very skilful as a military engineer. He restored the church of S. Francis at Assisi, and designed several fine buildings at Civita Vecchia, Orvieto, and elsewhere. He also built fortresses and city walls at Spoleto, Orvieto, and Civita Castellana. He was largely employed by Nicholas V. and Pius II. for restorations in nearly all the great basilicas of Rome, but at present little trace of his work remains, owing to the sweeping alterations which were made during the tasteless 17th and 18th centuries. Between the years 1461 and 1464 (the date of his death) he occupied the important post of <hi rend="italic">capo-maestro</hi> to the Florentine duomo. A number of buildings at Pienza, executed for Pius II., are attributed to him ; the Vatican registers mention the architect of these as MBernardo di Fiorenza, but this indication is too slight to make it certain that the elder Rossellino is referred to (see Vasari, ed. Milanesi, iii. 93 <hi rend="italic">sq.</hi> <hi rend="italic">∖</hi></p>
</div></body></text></TEI>