<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/>         </publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb09-21-r03-0058-02" facs="encyclopediabrit21newyrich_raw_0070.jp2" type="entry">

    <p><label>RULHIÈRE</label>
or <hi rend="smallcaps">RulhiLres, Claude Carloman de</hi> (1735-1791), poet and historian, was born at Bondy in 1735, and died at Paris in 1791. He was for a time a soldier, and served under Richelieu in Germany. But at twenty-five he accompanied Breteuil to St Petersburg as secretary of legation. Here he actually saw the revolution which seated Catherine IL on the throne, and thus obtained the facts of his best-known and best work, the short sketch called <hi rend="italic">Anecdotes sur la Revolution de Russie en 1762.</hi> It was not published till after the empress’s death. The later years of Rulhière’s life were spent either in Paris, where he held an appointment in the foreign office and went much into society, or else in travelling over Germany and Poland. The distracted affairs of this latter country gave him the subject of his longest work, <hi rend="italic">Histoire de FAnarchix de Pologne</hi> (1807), which was never finished, and which the patriotism of its latest editor, M. Ostrowski, has rather unjustifiably rebaptized <hi rend="italic">Revolutions de Pologne.</hi> Rulhière was made an Academician in 1787.</p><p>Besides the historical works mentioned, he wrote one on the Revocation of the Edict of Nantes (1788).</p><p>Rulbiere as an historian has much merit of style and arrangement, and the short sketch of the Russian revolution is justly ranked among the masterpieces of the kind in French. Of the larger <hi rend="italic">Polaiui</hi> Carlyle, as justly, complains that its allowance of fact is too small in proportion to its bulk. The author was also a fertile writer of <hi rend="italic">vers de société,</hi> short satires, epigrams, Ac., which show much point and polish, and he had a considerable reputation among the witty and ill-natured group also containing Chamfort, Rivarol, Champcenetz, Ac. On the other hand he has the credit of being long and disinterestedly assiduous in caring for J. J. Rousseau in his morose old age, until Rousseau as usual quarrelled with him.</p><p>Kulhifere <hi rend="sup">-</hi> S woιks were published by Anguis in 1819 (Paris, 6 vols. 8vo). The <hi rend="italic">Rtusian Revolution</hi> may be found in the <hi rend="italic">Chefs-d'œuvre Historiques</hi> of the Collection Didot, and the <hi rend="italic">Poland,</hi> with title altered as above, in the same Collection.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>