<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T17:51:42Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>The sultan was now completely humbled ; and after various delays and negociations with Russia, a treaty was finally concluded, which ceded the dominion of Syria to Mehemet Ali.</p><p>Syria has been ruled by Mehemet Ali with the most tyrannical cruelty. The conscriptions both for the army and for his military works have been enforced with the most unheard-of brutality. At Damascus the houses were surrounded in the night by troops, and every man capable of bearing arms was carried off. Still greater outrages t∞k place at Beirout, where the inhabitants, Turks, Jews, and Christians, were seized or knocked down in the streets ; the housesbroken open, and all dragged indiscriminately to prison, and there plundered and otherwise maltreated. His conscriptions and rigorous exactions produced insurrection in various quarters of the country. These were soon suppressed, and were followed by severe vengeance. The Druses were decimated, and their villages burned. The Ansaries, who were driven to resistance by oppression, were indiscriminately slaughtered, though they implored forgiveness. Towards the close of 1837, the Druses again rose in arms to resist the intolerable cruelty of Mehemet Ali. They gained a signal victory over a force of 20,000 troops under Achmet Pacha, who was driven back with great loss by the Druses, advantageously posted on the mountains. But new armies being sent, the Druses were finally defeated, and compelled to seek refuge in the recesses of the mountains.</p><p>In the mean time the Porte, stung by recent humiliation and the loss of Syria, was preparing for a new war ; to which the hesitation of Mehemet Ali in paying his tribute, and his threatened declarations of independence, afforded a sufficient motive. Mehemet Ali on his part reinforced his armies ; and although the European powers, namely, Great Britain, Russia, France, and Austria, interposed to maintain peace, the armies at length encountered, when victory again declared in favour of Mehemet Ali, whose way was now open to Constantinople, when the vigorous interposition of the European powers enforced an armistice, with a view to establish a lasting peace. Since this period the combined influence of the same powers has been exerted to settle these eastern disputes, and, as is understood, to maintain the integrity of the Turkish empire by the cession of Syria to the Porte. Mehemet Ali refuses to yield the hereditary sovereignty of this country, the fruit of victory and his right by conquest. Thc European powers are engaged in anxious discussions to effect a settlement of these disputes, and numerous fleets are assembled in the Mediterranean to give weight to their interference.</p><p>How far the interest or honour of those powers, and more especially of Great Britain, is so directly concerned in the integrity of Turkey as to warrant such actual interference, and the maintenance of expensive armaments, may well be questioned. The Turkish empire has been long verging to decay ; and can no longer maintain supreme rule over its subordinate governors, who, taking advantage of its weakness, assume independent power. This is a necessary step in the natural progress of decay which no foreign aid can avert ; nor is it easy to perceive any rational ground for the interference of Great Britain, by means of expensive armaments, in those distant disputes, the result of which cannot affect her safety. The rise of an independent power in the east, such as Egypt, cannot possibly be prejudicial to European interests ; and for what purpose therefore set in motion such expensive political machinery to arrest the natural progress of events? Even if Turkey were to fall under the extending sway of Russia, of which there is no immediate prospect, it is doubtful whether this accession of territory would add to her solid strength; whether it would render her a more formidable enemy, held aS it would be by the uncertain tenure of recent conquest ; and whether therefore it is not the wiser policy to remain quiet, watching the course of events, than to provide by expensive preparations against dangers which may only exist in the fancies of speculative politicians. It is this system of watchful anticipation, and of chimerical anxiety about the balance of power, which has plunged Great Britain into so many useless wars, and has overwhelmed her with debt ; and thc danger is, that the same course followed in a season of profound peace will increase her burdens, until she sink at last under the accumulating load.	<hi rend="smallcaps">(f.)</hi></p><p>SYRIAM, a town of the Birman empire, in the province of Pegu, on the banks of the Appoo river, where were formerly situated several factories of the Europeans. The British factory was destroyed during the wars between the Birmans and the Peguers. Long. 96. 17. E. Lat. 16. 49. N.</p><p>SYRINGE, a well-known instrument, serving to imbibe or suck in a quantity of fluid, and to squirt or expel the same with violence. The word is formed from the Greek <hi rend="italic">συϑιγξ</hi>, <hi rend="italic">a pipe.</hi> A syringe is only a single pump, and the water ascends in it on the same principle as in the common sucking-pump.</p><p>SYSTEM, in general, denotes an assemblage or chain of principles and conclusions, or thc whole of any doctrine, the several parts of which are bound together, and follow or depend on each other ; in which sense we say a system of philosophy, a system of divinity, &amp;c. The word is formed from the Greek <hi rend="italic">συστημα, composition.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">System,</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Music,</hi> signifies an exposition of all the sounds employed in composition, considered theoretically and practically, melodically and harmonically. The ancient Greek melodic system was divided into tetrachords; the modem melodic and harmonic system is divided into octaves. The Guidonian system was divided into hexachords. The most modem system of harmony, which originated in the sixteenth, seventeenth, and eighteenth centuries, is founded upon a system of tonality different from that employed prior to these periods, as will be shown under the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Tonality</hi>. For some account of harmonic systems, see <hi rend="smallcaps">Music</hi>.</p><p>SYSTYLE, in <hi rend="italic">Architecture,</hi> that manner of placing columns where the space between the two shafts consists of two diameters or four modules.</p><p>SYZYGY, <hi rend="smallcaps">Syzygia,</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Astronomy,</hi> a term equally used for the conjunction and opposition of a planet with the sun. The word is formed from the Greek <hi rend="italic">συζυγι</hi>α, which properly signifies <hi rend="italic">conjunctio.</hi> On the phenomena and circumstances of the syzygies a great part of the lunar theory depends. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Astronomy.</hi></p><p>SZARVAS, a large town of the Austrian kingdom of Hungary, of the circle of the Farther Theiss, and the district of Bekesch. It stands on the river Koros. It is chiefly inhabited by the Saxon race, who have there a Lutheran church, and several institutions for education, chiefly on subjects relating to the knowledge and promotion of arts, manufactures, and agriculture. It contains 820 houses, with 8600 inhabitants. Long. 20. 26. 19. E. Lat. 46. 52. 30. N.</p><p>SZEGEDIN, a large city of the kingdom of Hungary, in the province of the Farther Theiss, and circle of Song- rab, of which it is the capital. It stands on the river Theiss, where that stream is joined by the Maros. It is well built and strongly fortified, is the scat of a Greek propope, of a Piarist college, and of a Catholic gymnasium.</p></body></text></TEI>