<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T17:50:47Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>were to take a part in the same cause, he could scarcely hope to succeed in his enterprise. The king stopped a while, and appeared to hesitate. A serjeant of the guards overheard their discourse, and cried aloud, “ It shall succeed. Long live Gustavus!” His majesty immediately said, “ Then I will venture;” and stepping forward to the soldiers, he addressed them in terms nearly similar to those which he had employed to the officers, and with the same success. They answered him with loud acclamations. One voice only said, No ; but it excited no attention.</p><p>In the mean time some of the king’s emissaries had spread a report about the town that his majesty was arrested. This drew' the populace to the palace in great numbers, where they arrived as he had concluded his harangue to the guards. They testified by reiterated shouts their joy at seeing him safe ; a joy which promised the happiest conclusion to the business of the day. The senators were now immediately secured. They had from the window of the council-chamber beheld what was going forward on the parade before the palace ; and, at a loss to know the meaning of the shouts which they heard, were coming down to inquire into the cause of them, when thirty grenadiers, with their bayonets fixed, informed them it was his majesty’s pleasure they should continue where they were. They began to speak in a high tone, but were only answered by having the door shut and locked upon them. The moment the secret committee heard that the senate was arrested, they separated of themselves, each individual providing for his own safety. The king then mounting his horse, followed by his officers with their swords drawn, a large body of soldiers, and numbers of the populace, went to the other quarters of the town where the soldiers whom he had ordered to be assembled were posted. He found them all equally willing to support his cause, and to take to him an oath of fidelity. As he passed through the streets, he declared to the people, that he only meant to defend them, and save his country ; and that if they would not confide in him, he would lay down his sceptre, and surrender up his kingdom. So much was the king beloved, that some of the people even fell on their knees, and many more, with tears in their eyes, implored his majesty not to abandon them.</p><p>The king proceeded in his course, and in less than an hour made himself master of all the military force in Stockholm. In the mean time the heralds, by proclamation in the several quarters of the city, summoned an assembly of the states for the ensuing morning, and declared all members traitors to their country who should not appear. Thither his majesty repaired in all the pomp of royalty, surrounded by his guards, and holding in his hand the silver sceptre of Gustavus Adolphus. In a very forcible speech, he lamented the unhappy state to which the country was reduced by the conduct of a party ready to sacrifice every thing to its ambition, and reproached the states with adapting their actions to the views of foreign courts, from which they received the wages of perfidy. “ If any one dare contradict this, let him rise and speak.” Conviction, or fear, kept the assembly silent, and the secretary read the new form of government, which the king submitted to the approbation of the states. It consisted of fifty-seven articles ; of which the five following were the chief. 1. The king has the entire power of convoking and dissolving the assembly of the states as often as he thinks proper. 2. His majesty alone has the command of the army, fleet, and finances, and the disposal of all offices civil and military. 3. In case of an invasion, or of any pressing necessity, tile king may impose taxes, without waiting for the assembly of the states. 4. The diet can deliberate on no other subjects than those proposed by the king. 5. The king shall not carry on an offensive war without the consent of the states. When all the articles were recited, the king de</p><p>manded if the states approved of them, and was answered by a general acclamation. He then dismissed all the senators from their employments, adding, that in a few days he would appoint others; and concluded this extraordinary scene by drawing out of his pocket a small psalm-book, from which, after taking off the crown, he gave out <hi rend="italic">Te Deum. </hi>All the members very devoutly added their voices to his, and the hall resounded with thanksgiving.</p><p>The power which he had thus obtained, he employed for the good of his subjects. He took care that the law should be administered with impartiality to the richest noble and the poorest peasant, making a severe example of such judges as were proved to have made justice venal. He gave particular attention and encouragement to commerce ; and being himself a man of letters, was a liberal and enlightened patron of literature and science. He strenuously laboured to introduce into his kingdom the most valuable improvements in agriculture that had been made in foreign countries.</p><p>But while thus active in promoting the arts of peace, he was not inattentive to the art of war. The fleet, which he found decayed and feeble, he in a few years restored to a respectable footing ; and, besides changing the regulations of the navy, he raised a new corps of sailors, and formed them to the service by continual exercise. The army, which, like the navy, had been neglected during the aristocracy, was next to be reformed. The king began by giving cloaks, tents, and new arms to all the regiments. Afterwards, under the direction of Field-marshal Count de Hessenstein, a new exercise was introduced, and several camps were formed, in which the soldiery were manoeuvred by the king himself. The sale of military offices, which had been permitted for many years, was entirely suppressed ; and the king provided not only for the re-establishment of discipline and good order in the army, but for the future welfare of the individuals who composed it. These warlike preparations were necessary to a plan which he had formed for entirely abolishing the power of the aristocracy, and freeing Sweden from the factions which had long been formed in it by the court of St Petersburg. The change which he had introduced was very inimical to the intrigues of that court ; and the Russian ambassador exerted himself openly to bring about a rupture between the king and the discontented nobles. Gustavus ordered him to quit the kingdom in eight days, and immediately prepared for war with Russia. To this apparently rash enterprise he was incited by the Ottoman Porte, at that time unable to oppose the armies of the two empires ; and his own ambition, together with the internal state of his kingdom, powerfully concurred to make him lend every assistance to his ancient ally. It is needless for us to enter into a detail of the particulars of that war, the principal circumstances of which have already been noticed under <hi rend="smallcaps">Russia</hi>. Suffice it to say, that neither Gustavus Adolphus nor Charles XII. gave greater proofs of undaunted courage and military conduct in their long and bloody wars than were given by Gustavus III. from the end of the year 1787 to 1790, when peace was restored between the courts of St Petersburg and Stockholm. When the court of Copenhagen was compelled, by the means of England and Prussia, to withdraw its troops from the territories of Sweden, the king attacked Russia with such vigour both by sea and land, displayed such address in retrieving his affairs when apparently reduced to the last extremity, and renewed his attacks with such pertinacious courage, that the empress lowered the haughtiness of her tone, and was glad to treat with Gustavus as an equal and independent sovereign.</p><p>Sweden now enjoyed peace ; but the nobles continued discontented, and a conspiracy was planned against Gustavus under his own roof. He had entered into the alliance that was formed against the revolutionary government of France; and in order to raise an army, which he was to</p></body></text></TEI>