<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T17:50:52Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>effect is of course more rapid and powerful as we advance to the north.</p><p>The inhabitants consist of Swedes, Lapons or Laps, and Finns. The Swedes are a branch of the same family as the Danes and Norwegians, and speak a dialect of the same language, considerably modified, however, by the consequences of the long political separation and international enmity of the two nations. Books are translated from the one language to the other ; but the vulgar tongue, the language of the peasantry in Sweden and Norway, differs not much more than broad Scotch from Cockney English. The roots of words, construction, and idioms are the same in both, or have a common origin.</p><p>In 1751 the population of Sweden amounted to 1,785,727, in 1800 to 2,347,303, and in 1830 to 2,888,082. Norway in 1825 contained 1,051,318 inhabitants, and in 1836 the population was 1,200,000, showing an increase of nearly 150,000 during the preceding ten years. In Sweden the annual number of births is one to twenty-eight of the population, in Norway one to thirty-four. In Sweden the marriages are one in 112, in Norway one in 130; but in Sweden the mortality is one in thirty-four and a half, and in Norway only one in forty-eight. The standing army amounts to 33,000 ; but in the time of war it may be raised by conscription to 240,000. In 1825 the inhabitants of the towns of Sweden amounted to 279,645, or about one tenth of the population. Stockholm had then a population of 97,183, Gottenburg 26,702, Carlserona 11,943. All the other towns are little better than villages.</p><p>The Swedes are represented to be a brave, hardy, generous, and enterprising people, distinguished by a happy union of courage and steadiness, fine genius, and natural probity of disposition. They are said, however, to be greatly addicted to drunkenness ; and this unfortunate habit is the fruitful source of many evils, both moral and physical.@@<hi rend="superscript">1</hi> In 1835 one person out of every 114 of the population was accused, and one out of every 140 convicted, of some criminal offence.</p><p>With the exception of a few congregations in Stockholm and other principal towns, the Swedes are all Lutherans, and Lutheranism is the established religion of the state. Other sects are now allowed the free exercise of worship ; but Catholics and all other dissenters are excluded from the diet and higher offices of state. In the whole kingdom there are 2490 congregations, viz, 1147 country parishes, and 129 town charges, with 1214 annexed chapels in the larger parishes. The whole personal establishment consists of 3193 clergy, and 3753 sextons or parish-clerks, organists, and church servants. The hierarchy consists of one archbishop of Upsala, and eleven bishops, viz. of Lund, Gottenburg, Wexio, Calmar, Linkioping, Skara, Carlstadt, Wisby, Westeraas, Strangnæs, and Hernosand ; seventy archdeacons, and 192 probsts (provosts or deans). The archbishop’s income is rated at about L.2000 sterling a year, the bishops at more than L.600 each, and the archdeacons and probsts from L.400 to L.700 each. None of the inferior clergy has less than L.120, while many have as much as L.300, besides parsonage-houses and glebe-lands. The clergy, as a body, have been always distinguished for piety and morality, and yet among their people religious feeling and moral purity are at a very low ebb ; their religion indeed has become little better than a system of rites and ceremonies. There is, however, a spirit of religious enthusiasm spreading in the north of Sweden, especially among the new colonists or squatters in Lapland ; but this spirit the clergy attempt to extinguish. These religionists are called Læseren, or readers, from their reading the scriptures; but they do not form a sect having internal</p><p>communion and regulations. They are however numerous ; their numbers are said to be increasing, and their meetings for preaching are attended by people from great distances. The Catholics throughout the kingdom do not amount to 2000, the greater part of whom reside in the capital, and the whole are foreigners. The Swedenborgians, the only sect which the country has produced, are also comparatively few. The Jews scarcely exceed 1000 individuals, and have four synagogues, at Stockholm, Gottenburg, Norrkoping, and Carlscrona.</p><p>Of the whole population, including even the Laps, it is reckoned that the proportion of grown persons unable to read is less than one in a thousand. This general diffusion of elementary education is ascribed to the zeal of King Gustaf-Wasa (Gustavus Vasa, 1523-1560), and his immediate successors. John III., in 1574, ordered that the nobleman who had no knowledge of book-learning should forfeit his nobility ; Charles XI., in 1684, required the clergy to have every Swedish subject taught to read ; and made it a law that no marriage should be celebrated unless the parties had previously taken the Lord’s Supper; and that none should be admitted to the communion-table who could not read, and was not instructed in religion. Parish schools, however, are only found where there happen to have been lands or rents bequeathed for their endowment ; and these in some parishes are ambulatory, in others fixed. It is supposed that more than half of all the parishes have no schools ; but the deficiency is supplied by the people themselves, who teach their children at home in the leisure hours of their long winters. The king, however, in his speech at the opening of the present diet, 1840, has recommended the establishment of a primary sch∞l in every parish. In the provincial towns there are gymnasia, or high schools, which prepare youth for the universities. They are under the care of the bishops, and, besides the higher branches of Greek and Roman literature, their course often embraces the oriental languages, and the leading doctrines of theology. There are two universities, one at Upsala, and the other at Lund. In these the teachers may be divided into three classes: 1. professors ; 2. adjuncts, or privileged teachers in different sciences, who give instruction privately or publicly to the students, and who are expectants of professorships; and 3. the masters in modern languages, exercises, and other inferior branches. Of the theological faculty there are four professors at Upsala, and four at Lund ; of the juridical faculty, two at each ; of the medical and surgical, five at each ; of the philosophical and literary, fourteen at Upsala, and ten at Lund.</p><p>The constitution is of a mixed character, in which the executive and administrative departments are managed by a hereditary king and his ministers, while the legislative is vested conjointly in the king and a diet of four chambers, elected by the nobles, clergy, burghers, and peasants. The noble families are reckoned at about 2400. The head of each is by right a member of the diet, but seldom more than 400 take any part in its proceedings. The clergy have sixty representatives, including the archbishop and bishops, of whom the primate is always president The burghers are elected by eighty-five cities and towns; Stockholm returning ten, Gottenburg three, Norrkoping two, and each of the rest one. The peasantry have between 140 and 150 representatives, chosen by districts ; and these, as well as the burghers, are required to possess a certain amount of qualification in property ; and each of their chambers has a president, appointed by the king. During the session each member of the last three orders receives a small pecuniary compensation, paid by his constituents, the amount of which is voluntary. The diet meets at intervale of five years, and</p><p><hi rend="superscript">@@@i</hi> Laing’s Travels in Sweden, p. 110.</p></body></text></TEI>