<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T17:51:32Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>darts, slings, and bows, to drive the besieged from the ramparts, which on one side were washed by the sea, and to facilitate the approach to the walls. But a machine of Marcellus’s own invention, called a <hi rend="italic">sambuca,</hi> was that on which he placed his chief reliance. The consul’s design was to bring his sambuca to the f∞t of the walls of Acra- dina ; but while it was at a considerable distance (and it advanced very slowly, being moved only by two ranks of rowers), Archimedes discharged from one of his engines a vast stone, weighing, according to Plutarch’s account, 1250 pounds, then a second, and immediately after a third, all which, falling upon the sambuca with a dreadful noise, broke its supports, and gave the galleys upon which it stood such a violent shock that they parted, and the machine which Marcellus had raised upon them with immense labour and expense was battered to pieces. At the same time, several other machines, which were not visible without the walls, and consequently did not lessen the confidence of the Romans in the assault, played incessantly upon their ships, and overwhelmed them with showers of stones, rafters, and beams pointed with iron, insomuch that Marcellus found it necessary to retire with all possible haste, and sent orders to his land forces to do the same; for the attack on the land side was attended with no better success, the ranks being broken and thrown into the utmost confusion by the stones and darts, which flew with such noise, force, and rapidity, that they struck the Romans with terror, and dashed all to pieces before them.</p><p>Marcellus, surprised, though not discouraged, at this artificial storm, which he did not expect, held a council of war, in which it was resolved, the next day before sunrise, to advance close to the wall, and remain there. They were in hopes by this means to secure themselves against the terrible storm of stones and darts which fell on the ships when at a distance ; but Archimedes had prepared engines which were adapted to all contingencies. When the Romans therefore had brought their ships close under the wall, and thought themselves well covered, they were unexpectedly overwhelmed with a new shower of darts and stones, which fell perpendicularly on their heads, and obliged them to retire with great precipitation. But they had no sooner removed to some distance, than a new shower of darts overtook them, which made a dreadful havock of the men, while stones of an immense weight, discharged from other machines, either disabled or broke in pieces most of their galleys. This loss they sustained without being able to revenge it on the enemy ; for Archimedes had placed most of his engines behind the walls, and not only out of the reach, but even out of the sight, of the enemy ; so that the Romans were repulsed witli a dreadful slaughter, without seeing the hand that occasioned it. What most harassed them in the attack by sea, was a sort of crow with iron claws, fastened to a long chain, which was let down by a lever. The weight of the iron made it fall with great violence, and drove it into the planks of the galleys. Then the besieged, by a great weight of lead at the other end of the lever, weighed it down, and consequently raised up the iron of the crow in proportion, and with it the prow of the galley to which it was fastened, sinking the poop at the same time into the water. After this the crow letting go its hold all of a sudden, the prow of the galley fell with such force into the sea, that the whole vessel was filled with water, and sunk. At other times, the machines, dragging ships to the shore by hooks, dashed them to pieces against the points of the rocks which projected under the walls. Other vessels were quite lifted up into the air, there whirled about with incredible rapidity, and then let fall into the sea, and sunk, with all that they contained. How these stupendous works were effected, few, if any, have hitherto been able to comprehend.</p><p>The troops under the command of Appius suffered no less than the fleet in this second attack. In the whole space of ground which the army occupied when formed, the last files as well as the first were overwhelmed with showers of darts and flints, against which they could not possibly defend themselves. When they had with infinite trouble brought the mantlets and covered galleries, under which they were to work the rams, near the foot of the wall, Archimedes discharged such large beams and stones upon them as crushed them to pieces. If any brave Roman ventured to draw too near the wall, iron hooks were immediately let down from above, which, taking hold of his clothes or some part of his body, lifted him up in the air and dashed out his brains with the fall. Marcellus, though at a loss how to proceed, could not however forbear expressing himself with pleasantry. Shall we persist, said he to his workmen, in making war upon this Briareus, upon this giant with an hundred hands? But the soldiers, if they saw upon the walls only a small cord, or the least piece of wood, were so terrified, that they immediately turned their backs and fled, crying out that Archimedes was going to discharge some dreadful machine upon them.</p><p>The consuls, finding themselves thus defeated in every attempt, turned the siege into a blockade, reduced most of the other places in the island, and defeated the forces which were sent against them ; and at last Marcellus made himself master of Syracuse itself. He took the opportunity of a festival, when the soldiers and citizens had drunk plentifully, to make a detachment scale the walls of Tyche, in that part of it which was nearest to Epipolæ, and which was ill guarded. He speedily possessed himself of Epipolæ ; and the inhabitants of Neapolis, as well as Tyche, then sent deputies to offer their submission. Marcellus granted life and liberty to all of free condition, but gave up those quarters of the city to be plundered. . The soldiers had orders to spare the lives of the citizens ; but they were cruel in their avarice, slew many of them, and among the rest the incomparable Archimedes. He was very intent on a demonstration in geometry, and calmly drawing his lines, when a soldier entered the room, and applied a sword to his throat. “ Hold!" said Archimedes, “ one moment, and my demonstration will be finished.” But the soldier, equally regardless of his prayer and his demonstration, instantly put him to death. Of the manner of his death there are different accounts, but all agree that Marcellus regretted it extremely, and showed a singular favour to his relations for his sake.</p><p>The city of Syracuse continued subject to the western empire till its declension, when the island of Sicily being ravaged by different barbarians, the capital also underwent various revolutions, till at last, in the ninth century, it was so destroyed by the Saracens that very few traces of its ancient grandeur are now to be seen. The ancient city of Syracuse was of a triangular form, and consisted of five parts or divisions. The circuit, according to Strabo, amounted to 180 stadia, or twenty-two English miles and four furlongs. This account Mr Swinburne once suspected of exaggeration ; but after spending two days in tracing the ruins, and making reasonable allowances for the encroachments of thc sea, he was convinced of the exactness of Strabo’s measurement.</p><p>The modem city is the capital of an intendancy of its own name. It is situated on a noble harbour, with an excellent bottom, and a plentiful supply of fresh water; but though well adapted for a naval station, or for an extended commercial port, it is only visited by a few polaccas or other small coasting vessels. Lord Nelson, when in pursuit of the French expedition in 1798, was here enabled to water and provide his fleet with fresh meat in five days. The city is now  fortified, and has a strong citadel. The streets are confined and narrow; the public buildings, though numerous, have little to recommend them. There is a museum and a public library, as well as some private cabinets. The country around, being abundantly irrigated, is highly fertile, produ-</p></body></text></TEI>