<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T17:50:50Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>the example given in his own person and that of his followers had contributed to destroy some of the old illusions as to birth and hereditary honours, and had prepared men’s minds for great innovations. It was thus that the son of a French peasant, who began his career as a common soldier, was raised to the Swedish throne by the spontaneous choice of a body of nobles, proud of their birth and ancestry.</p><p>The appearance of Bernadotte in the Swedish capital was followed by numerous feasts and spectacles. He received congratulations from all the public bodies ; and though not immediately called to the throne, was, from the king’s infirmities, intrusted with the entire conduct of the government. One of his first acts was to recommend to the diet the introduction of a conscription law like that of France, a measure which certainly hazarded his popularity. It was however adopted ; and on this occasion he prevailed with the nobles to make a voluntary surrender of their ancient privilege of exemption from military service, as well as from taxation. Pressed by France and Russia, Sweden, in November 1810, professed her adherence to the continental system, and declared war against Britain. The war however was only nominal, and the British cruisers returned in most cases their captures untouched. This state of things continued till Bonaparte was preparing for his great Russian campaign, when the Swedish government, solicited by both parties, and tempted by great offers, at length signed treaties of alliance with Russia and Britain in 1812 and 1813. By these treaties, the two powers mentioned engaged to assist the king in conquering Norway from Denmark. The French, for the purpose of intimidation, had previously seized Pomerania. Bernadotte carried over an army of 30,000 Swedes to Germany in 1813; and being joined by several large bodies of Prussian and German troops, he was encountered by Marshal Ney between Berlin and Leipzig on the 6th September, and, after an obstinate engagement, drove back the French army with the loss of 16,000 men. In the battle of Leipzig, fought on the 18th October, he likewise bore a conspicuous share. After the victory, he continued to act against Marshal Davoust's corps, and against the Danes, till he reduced the latter to the necessity of capitulating. He lost no time in improving this advantage ; and by a treaty concluded at Kiel on the 14th January 1814, compelled Denmark to cede Norway, on surrendering to her the possession of Pomerania, and thus securing a great advantage by the exchange of territory. He now advanced to the Rhine ; but, satisfied with reducing Napoleon’s power, and, from views of interest, most probably adverse to ruining him, he was thought to be rather dilatory in improving his advantages. The success of the allies at length left him at liberty to secure Norway, the prize for which he had fought As the Norwegians announced their intention of resisting, he crossed the frontier with an army in July, and, by judicious manœuvres, which placed the Norwegian force in his power, he obliged them to capitulate, and obtained possession of the country almost without bloodshed ; Norway preserving its ancient constitution, and having states of its own. On the death of Charles XIII. in 1818, Bernadotte mounted the throne ; and being still on good terms with most of the surrounding powers, has every chance to preserve his situation, and transmit the crown to his posterity.</p><p>STATISTICS.</p><p>Sweden and Norway form together one geographical region, situated between 4° and 32° E. Long., and 55<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> and 71° N. Lat. The greatest length, from Falsterbo in the province of Malmo, to Cape Nordkun in Finmark, exceeds 1000 geographical miles, and the superficial area is about 292,700 English square miles, of which 170,150 are in Sweden. Throughout the length of the peninsula, from the Varangerfiord in the north-east to the Scagerack in the south-west, a line of lofty and rugged mountains, hills, and table-lands extends for 1110 miles, forming the water-shed between the shores of the ocean and the basin of the Baltic Sea. Numerous rivers, which have their source at the base of this range, empty themselves into the Gulf of Bothnia. The principal of these are the Tomea, which, with its affluent the Muonio, forms the boundary between Swedish and Russian Lapmark ; the Kalix, the Ranea, the Lulea, the Pitea, the Sildut or Skellestia, the Unea, and Windel ; the Gildea, the Angerman, the Indals, the Ljusne, and Dahl. The Gotha is the outlet of Lake Wenner, and runs into the Cattegat at Gottenburg.</p><p>The lakes of Sweden are numerous, and cover a large space of the surface of the country. The principal of these are the Wenner, which, after those of Ladoga and Onega, is the largest in Europe ; it is ninety miles in length by thirty- six at its greatest breadth, and covers an area of 2136 square miles. The Wetter measures eighty-two miles in length by sixteen at its greatest breadth ; but is generally much narrower, and only contains 830 square miles. The Malar extends from Stockholm, nearly seventy miles in length ; it is crowded with islands, and presents throughout the greatest variety of beautiful scenery. At Stockholm it communicates, by a narrow strait, with an arm of the Baltic Sea, forming a very intricate navigation of sixty miles between the open sea and the capital.</p><p>Sweden is not more fortunate in its soil than in its climate. It cannot boast of any of those deep rich alluvial deposits which elsewhere usually occupy a large portion of low and well-watered countries. Coarse sand or gravel, but partially covered over with a thin layer of fertile soil, forms in general the champaign country ; and, besides the woods, which occupy more than three fourths of its surface, a large portion is covered with lakes, morasses, rivers, and with inconceivable numbers of boulder-stones or isolated rocks of every size. The surface has been thus numerically represented in square miles: Woods, 137,420; lakes, marshes, &amp;c., 11,900; meadows, pastures, &amp;c., 7350; arable land, 3480; total, 170,150 square miles. The soil of Norway is of much the same character as that of Sweden, in both the vegetation being abridged by the length and the severity of the winter : thc soil remains always poor ; and the paucity of alluvial tracts, with the prevalence of rock, seldom far beneath, and often forming the surface, materially detract from the quality as well as the quantity of the soil. In some parts however it is very rich, and the valleys in particular are celebrated for their luxuriant fertility ; but even there much of the soil is thin, and obstructed by rocky knobs rising above its surface.</p><p>In the most favoured situations of Sweden, as at Lund in Schonen, the mean temperature of the year does not exceed 45° Fahr., while at the North Cape it is at the freezing point ; the extreme cold, however, is modified by the elevations of the land, and its proximity to the sea. At North Cape, lat. 70° N., potatoes, broccoli, and gooseberries, are raised with some difficulty ; one degree farther south a little barley makes its appearance. In lat. 68° 20', at Enonte- keis, the crops of barley yield a remunerating harvest once in the three years. Rye and hemp cannot be successfully cultivated beyond 66°, nor oats beyond 64° ; this latter is also the general limit of garden cultivation. The cherry-tree, alder, and maple cease to thrive beyond 63° ; the ash and willow beyond 62° ; the elm, lime, and oak beyond 61° ; and the natural beech-woods do not extend beyond 57°. The mulberry, the chestnut, and the walnut arrive at perfection in Schonen, 54°. In the southern parts of the country an elevation of 500 feet above the level of the sea is found to have the same effect on the climate and vegetation as 175 miles of north latitude, a thousand feet as 300 miles, and two thousand feet as 630 miles ; but the</p></body></text></TEI>