<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T17:50:35Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Gustavus kept the port and citadel of Mcmel, the harbour of Pillau, the towns of Elbing, Brunsberg, and all that he had conquered in Livonia.</p><p>Gustavus having thus brought the war with Poland to an honourable conclusion, began to think of resenting the conduct of the emperor in assisting his enemies and oppressing the protestant states. Before embarking in such an important undertaking, it was necessary that he should consult the diet. Here the propriety of engaging in a war with Germany was warmly debated ; but, after much altercation, the king, in a very noble speech, determined the matter, having declared in such strong terms the virtuous motives by which he was actuated, that the whole assembly wept, and every thing was granted which he could require.</p><p>It was not difficult for him to begin his expedition. His troops amounted to 60,000 men, hardened by a succession of severe campaigns in Russia, Finland, Livonia, and Prussia. His fleet exceeded seventy sail, carrying from twenty to forty guns, and manned with 6000 scamen. Embarking his troops, he landed at Usedom on the 24th of June 1630, the Imperialists having evacuated all the fortresses which they there possessed ; and the isle of Rugen had been before reduced by General Lesley, in order to secure a retreat if fortune should prove unfavourable. Passing the strait, Gustavus stormed Wolgast, and another strong fortress in the neighbourhood, leaving a garrison for the defence of these conquests. He then proceeded to Stettin, which consented to receive a Swedish garrison, and the king persuaded the duke of Pomerania to enter into an alliance with him. In consequence of this the Swedish troops were received into several towns of Pomerania; and the most bitter enmity took place between the Imperialists and Pomeranians.</p><p>These successes of Gustavus struck the empire with consternation ; for, being already overwhelmed with civil dissensions, they were in no condition to resist so impetuous an enemy. At last Count Tilly was invested with the dignity of field-marshal. In the mean time, the king, being reinforced by a considerable body of troops in Finland and Livonia under the conduct of Gustavus Horn, defeated the Imperialists before Griffenhagen, and soon afterwards took the place by assault. By this and some other conquests, he opened a passage into Lusatia and Silesia ; but in the mean time Tilly cut off 2000 Swedes at New Brandenburg. This advantage, however, was soon overbalanced by the conquest of Frankfurt on the Oder, which Gustavus took by assault, making the whole garrison prisoners. Thus he commanded the rivers Elbe and Oder on both sides, and had a fair passage, not only to the countries already mentioned, but also to Saxony and the hereditary dominions of the house of Austria. He soon afterwards laid siege to Landsberg, which be took by assault.</p><p>About this time the protestant princes held a diet at Leipzig, to which Gustavus sent deputies, and conducted his negociations with such address as tended greatly to promote his interests. Immediately after this he reduced Greifswald, and with it all Pomerania. Having then marched to Gustrow, he restored the dukes of Mecklenburg to their dominions.</p><p>All this time Tilly was employed in the siege of Magdeburg ; but being alarmed at the repeated successes of the Swedes, he now left Pappenheim with part of the army before that city, while he marched with the rest into Thuringia, to attack the landgrave of Hesse-Cassel and the elector of Saxony. After a most obstinate defence, Magdeburg fell into the hands of Pappenheim, who committed all imaginable cruelties. The king formed a plan of recovering the city ; but was obliged to abandon it, by Pappenheim’s throwing himself into the place with his whole army, and by the progress which Tilly was making in Thuringia. Relinquishing this enterprise, he ordered an attack on Havelsburg ; which was conducted with such resolution, that the place was forced in a few hours, and all the garrison made prisoners. Werben was next obliged to submit after an obstinate conflict, in which many fell on botli sides. These successes obliged Tilly to attempt in person to check the progress of the Swedes. He detached the vanguard of his army, composed of the flower of the Imperial cavalry, within a few miles of the Swedish camp. An action ensued, in which Bernstein the Imperial general was defeated and killed, with 1500 of his men. Gustavus, after this advantage, placed himself in a situation so much superior to that of his enemies, that Tilly was fired with indignation, and marched up to the Swedish lines to give him battle. The king kept within his works, and Tilly attacked his camp, though almost impregnably fortified, and maintained a most terrible fire from a battery of thirty-two pieces of cannon ; which, however, produced no other effect than obliging the Swedish monarch to draw up his army behind the walls of Werben. Tilly had placed his chief hopes in being able to spike the enemy’s cannon, or set fire to their camp ; after which he proposed making his grand attack. With this view he bribed some prisoners ; but they betrayed him, and communicated his design to Gustavus. The king ordered fires to be lighted in different parts of his camp, and his soldiers to imitate the noise of a tumultuous disorderly rabble. This had the desired effect. The count led his army to the breach made by the cannon, where he was received with such a volley of grape-shot as cut off the first line, and put the whole body in disorder, so that they could never be brought back to the charge. In this confusion the Imperial army was attacked, and after an obstinate conflict obliged to quit the field.</p><p>Soon after this action the queen arrived at the camp with a reinforcement of 8000 men ; at the same time a treaty was concluded with Charles I. of England, by which that monarch allowed the marquis of Hamilton to raise 6000 men for the service of Gustavus. These auxiliaries were to be conducted to the main army by a body of 4000 Swedes ; and were in every thing to obey the king while he was personally present, but in his absence were to be subject to the orders of the marquis. With these troops the king had resolved to make a diversion in Bremen ; but the marquis finding it impossible to effect a junction with the Swedish army, resolved, without debarking his troops, to steer his course for the Oder, and land at Usedom. Gustavus was very much displeased at finding his project thus disconcerted ; but making the best of the present circumstances, he commanded the British troops to act on the Oder instead of the Weser. The number of this little army was magnified exceedingly by report, insomuch that Tilly had some thoughts of marching against them with his whole force ; but on the departure of the marquis for Silesia, he reinforced the army in that country with a large detachment, which was thought to contribute not a little to the defeat which he soon after received.</p><p>Since the late action Gustavus had kept within his in- trenchments, where his army was well supplied with provisions and stores. Tilly made several attempts to surprise or draw him to an engagement; but finding all his endeavours fruitless, he marched into Saxony, and laid siege to Leipzig. This precipitate measure proved highly advantageous to the Swedish monarch. A treaty offensive and defensive was immediately concluded with Gustavus ; and the elector willingly promised every thing that was required of him. Tilly, in the mean time, carried fire and sword into the electorate. At the head of an army of 44,000 veterans, he summoned the city of Leipzig to surrender ; denouncing, in case of a refusal, the same vengeance against it as had been executed on Magdeburg. The governor was so much intimidated, that he instantly submitted ; and he also surrendered the castle of Passenberg, which was in a</p></body></text></TEI>