<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T17:51:20Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>time their household occupation ; sometimes working in their gardens, and contributing in turns their assistance in the cultivation of their fields, and the labour of agriculture in general. The quality and neatness of the articles produced are evidently rendered inferior by this custom ; but, on the other hand, it is more economical, and during a slackness of trade the workman who possesses a garden and a little ground suffers less. In almost every part of Switzerland, with the exception of those mountain heights which are incapable of cultivation, agricultural labour affords resources when wages fall or markets are glutted, so that the pressure of want is generally light and temporary.</p><p>The working classes in Switzerland are divided into four different sections, viz. manufacturers, weavers, winders, and embroiderers. There are manufacturers of every order and description, from the individual who only manufactures the quantity which himself and his family can weave, up to those who employ a hundred weavers or embroiderers ; for the manufacturer who employs embroiderers does not engage in weaving. These manufacturers, who either sell their goods unbleached to the traders at home, or bleached to foreigners, breakfast upon coffee and milk, butter, honey, or green cheese. Their dinner is composed of soup and bouilli, potatoes, or porridge. Their beverage is cider or milk. Many of them sup upon coffee, and they seldom drink wine. This class is in general very economical. They take a great interest in public affairs, and pride themselves particularly upon their probity and honour. They furnish the greatest number of magistrates, and from among them are principally chosen all the parochial authorities.</p><p>The weaver, as soon as it is possible for him to do so, purchases a piece of ground, or at least a small house ; and very frequently the manufacturer furnishes him with the means. The acquisition of landed property is greatly promoted in Switzerland, by the facility with which money may be borrowed upon mortgage. This class of working proprietors forms the great mass of voters in the popular assemblies.</p><p>All the weavers in Switzerland make use of coffee, milk, oatmeal, and potatoes, which compose their principal food. They work from thirteen to fourteen hours a day. They earn from 1s. 10d. to 9s. 2d. a week ; but the greatest number only earn from 3s. 8d. to 5s. per week. The winders, many of whom are old people of both sexes, earn from 1d. to 3d. sterling a day. The embroiderers, who are generally women or young lads, earn on an average about 6<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">2</hi>d. a day. In Neuchâtel the ordinary rate of wages is, for male domestics, from L.8 to L.12 sterling, and for females, from L.4 to L.6 sterling, per annum. The average wages of agricultural labourers are from ls. ld. to ls. 8d. per day. The wages of artisans vary extremely, the lowest being about 9d. and the highest 11d. per day. The wages of watchmakers may be calculated at from L.55. 10s. to L.83. 5s. per annum; but workmen are generally paid by the job.</p><p>Provisions are very cheap in Switzerland. In the canton of Appenzell, a pound of bread weighing 20 ounces is worth 4 kreutzers, rather less than 1<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">2</hi>d. In Neuchâtel, the loaf of white bread is from 2d. to 2<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">2</hi>d. ; meat, from 4d. to 5<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">4</hi>d. ; butter, from 9<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">2</hi>d. to 10d. the pound of 17 ounces. The measure of potatoes weighing from 33 to 34 pounds, is worth from 10d. to 1s. 1<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">4</hi>d. ; milk, l<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">4</hi>d. ; and wine from 3d. to 6d. the bottle.</p><p>In Switzerland the clergy are supported by the state. The cost of the church establishment in Zürich is L.8000 per annum, being 9d. for each individual. The clergy amount to 271. In Neuchâtel the maximum salary of a clergyman is L.121, the minimum L.72, and the average L.83. There are 34 clergymen in this canton, which gives one to every 1647 persons. The Protestant religion is professed by the cantons of Basel, Berne, Vaud, Schaffhausen, Zürich, Geneva, and Neuchâtel. Soleure, Freyburg, Lucerne, Zug, Schwytz, Unterwalden, Uri, Ticino, and Valais, have continued Romanists. The cantons of Aargau, Glaris, Thurgau, St Gall, Appenzell, and the Grisons, contain a mixture of Romanists and Protestants.</p><p>Education is very generally diffused throughout Switzerland. In Appenzell every one is instructed ; and for many years past the law does not allow any person to be admitted to the sacrament who cannot read ; and the greater part of the population can also write, and have acquired the rudiments of arithmetic and singing. In Neuchâtel a considerable sum is paid by the state for the purpose of education. Every commune is required to provide a schoolmaster, and education is made obligatory throughout the principality. There is no person under the age of forty who is unable to read and write ; and it is extremely difficult to find a person who does not also know how to calculate, and who is not well acquainted with his civil and political rights. To religious instruction much attention is paid. Before being admitted to the sacrament, the young men are obliged to attend for a certain number of years on the public ordinances, as well as to receive private lessons from their own pastors. In Basel both the primary and superior schools are good ; and for many years the poor have been obliged to send their children to school for a course of elementary instruction, which occupies them until their tenth or twelfth year. The means for educating them are furnished by the poor-fund. In this manner children are prevented from entering too young into the factories, or from being employed in too laborious occupations.</p><p>At Hofwyl, in the canton of Berne, the establishments of Mr de Fellenberg for the maintenance and education of poor children, and his institution for the instruction of schoolmasters, have been attended with that success which might have been expected from efforts prompted by pure benevolence and guided by sound judgment.</p><p>In Aargau every district of 120 children must have at least one primary and one superior sch∞l. In every circle, the population being from 15,000 to 20,000 souls, there are from five to six secondary schools, and in the capital a gymnasium and a school of art. Besides this, there is a normal school for the instruction of teachers. The cost of these establishments is paid partly by the communes, and partly from the state funds. In Thurgau, every child, on reaching the age of five years, must be sent to school. Of the whole proceeds of the land-tax, two fifths have been applied to the purposes of education. A model-school for the education of teachers, established at Krutzlingen in 1833, under the superintendence of Mr Wehrlea, a pupil of Fellenberg, has had great success. Funds are cheerfully and liberally voted by the legislature. In 1834 more than one fifth of the whole population was attending the schools.</p><p>The poor in Switzerland are supported by a poor-law, greatly assisted however by voluntary contributions. The general law is that each parish shall take care of its own poor, but the arrangements in the different parishes respecting paupers are very various.</p><p>The administration of justice in Switzerland is prompt and economical. In Neuchâtel, for example, a verdict obtained in the Court of First Instance, might be pressed through all its stages, even to the confiscation of property to any amount, at a cost of less than 6s. 8d. sterling, and with a delay of only three weeks, there being three stages of appeal, each one allowing of a week for appearance and answer. While the cost to suitors is small, the cost to the public is equally so. In the district of Valangin, consisting of 6104 souls, the expenses for the administration of civil justice for 1834 amounted to less than five sixths of a farthing per individual ; yet there are 122 trusteeships of minors, lunatics, &amp;c., committed to the charge of the civil tribunals. There are on an average seventy causes per</p></body></text></TEI>