<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T17:50:29Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>and the senate, instead of taking proper measures to oppose the enemy, spent their time in idle debates. Christiern in the mean time advanced into the heart of the kingdom, destroying every thing with fire and sword ; but on his arrival at Stragnez, he granted a suspension of arms, on condition that they would elect him king. To this condition they submitted, and Christiern proved one of the most bloody tyrants that ever sat on the throne of any kingdom. Immediately after his coronation, he gave grand entertainments for three days ; during which time he projected the diabolical design of extirpating at once all the Swedish nobility, and thus for ever preventing the people from revolting, by depriving them of their proper leaders. As the tyrant had signed articles, by which he promised indemnity to all who had borne arms against him, it became necessary to invent some cause of offence against those whom he intended to destroy. To accomplish his purpose, Gustavus Trolle, formerly archbishop of Upsala, but who had been degraded from that dignity, in an oration before his majesty lamented the demolition of Stecka, his place of residence, and the losses sustained by the see of Upsala, amounting to a very large sum of money. He then proceeded in a bitter accusation against the widow and the son-in-law of Sture, the late regent, comprehending in the same accusation about fifteen of the principal nobility, the whole senate, and the burghers of Stockholm. In consequence of this, about sixty of the principal nobility and people of first rank in Sweden were hanged as traitors. Innumerable other cruelties were committed, part of which are owned by the Danish historians, and the whole are minutely related by those of Sweden. At last he departed for Denmark, ordering gibbets to be erected, and causing the peasants to be hanged on them for the slightest offences.</p><p>This monstrous cruelty, instead of securing him on the throne, exasperated the whole nation against him. It has already been mentioned, that Gustavus Ericson, or, as he is commonly called, <hi rend="italic">Gustavus Vasa, </hi>was among the number of the hostages whom Christiern had perfidiously carried to Denmark in 1519. Large promises had been made in order to reconcile him to Christiern, and all means had been employed, but in vain. Secret orders were given to strangle him in prison ; but the officer to whom the assassination was committed remonstrated to the king about the consequences of it, and prevailed on him to change the sentence of death into close confinement in the castle of Copenhagen. Some of the hostages perished in consequence of the rigorous treatment to which they were subjected ; but Gustavus witlistood all hardships. At last one Banner, a Danish nobleman, prevailed on the king to place him in his hands, in order to try whether or not he could prevail on him to change his sentiments. The king however told Banner that he must pay 6000 crowns if the prisoner should make his escape. Banner generously consented ; and having brought the noble prisoner to his fortress of Calo in Jutland, soon allowed him all the liberty he could desire, and otherwise heaped favours on him. All this however could not extinguish his remembrance of the cruelties of Christiern, and his desire of being serviceable to his country. He therefore determined to make his escape ; and the liberty which he enjoyed soon enabled him to accomplish his design. Having one day mounted his horse, under pretence of hunting as usual in the forest, when he got to a proper distance he changed his dress to the habit of a peasant, and quitting his horse, travelled for two days on foot through by-paths, and over wilds almost impassable, arriving on the third at Flensburg. Here no one was admitted without a passport ; and Gustavus dreaded presenting himself to the governor or the officer on guard, for fear of being discovered. He hired himself to a cattle-merchant, and in this disguise escaped out of the Danish territories, and arrived at Lübeck.</p><p>Banner was no sooner acquainted with his escape, than he set out after him with the utmost diligence, found him at Lubeck, and reproached him with great warmth as ungrateful and treacherous ; but he was soon appeased by the arguments urged by Gustavus, and especially by a promise of indemnifying him in the loss of his ransom. On this Banner returned home, and pretended that he could not find his prisoner. Christiern was enraged at his escape, apprehending that he might reverse all his designs in Sweden ; and gave orders to Otho his general to make the strictest search, and leave no means untried to arrest him. Gustavus applied to the regency for a ship to convey him to Sweden, where he hoped he should be able to form a party against the Danes. He likewise endeavoured to draw the regency of Lübeck into his measures ; and reasoned with so much zeal and ability, that Nicholas Gemins, first consul, was entirely gained ; but the regency could never be prevailed upon to declare for a party without friends, arms, money, or credit. Before his departure, however, the consul gave him assurances, that if he could raise a force sufficient to make head against the enemy in the field, he might depend on the services of the republic, and that the regency would immediately declare for him. Gustavus desired to be landed at Stockholm ; but thc captain of the ship, either having secret orders to the contrary, or business elsewhere, steered a different course, and put him on shore near Calmar, a city then garrisoned by the troops of Christiana, widow of the regent. In fact, the governor held this place for his own purposes, and only waited to make the best terms he could with the Danes. When Gustavus arrived, he made himself known to him and the principal officers of the garrison, who were mostly Germans, and his fellow-soldiers in the late administrator’s army ; but the mercenary band, seeing him without troops and without attendants, regarded him as a desperate person devoted to destruction, refused to embrace his proposals, and even threatened to kill or betray him if he did not instantly quit the city.</p><p>Disappointed in his expectations, Gustavus departed ; and his arrival being now publicly known, he was again forced to have recourse to his peasant’s disguise to conceal him from the Danish emissaries dispersed over the country to search for him. In a waggon loaded with hay, he passed through the Danish army, and at last repaired to an old family castle in Sudermania. Hence he wrote to his friends, intimating his return to Swedcn, and beseeching them to assemble all their forces in order to break through the enemy’s army into Stockholm, at that time besieged ; but they refused to embark in so hazardous and desperate an attempt.</p><p>Gustavus next applied himself to the peasants ; but they answered that they enjoyed salt and herrings under the government of the king of Denmark ; and that any attempts to bring about a revolution would be attended with certain ruin, without the prospect of bettering their condition ; for peasants they were, and peasants they should remain, whoever was king. At length, after several attempts to throw himself into Stockholm, after that city was surrendered to the king, after the horrid massacre of the senate, and after running a thousand dangers, and undergoing hardships and fatigues scarcely to be supported by human nature, he formed the resolution of trying the courage and affection of the Dalecarlians. While he was in the deepest obscurity, and plunged in almost insurmountable adversity, he never relinquished his designs nor his hopes. The news of the massacre had, however, nearly sunk him into despondency, as by it he lost all his friends, relations, and connections, and indeed almost every prospect of safety to himself, or deliverance to his country. This suggested the thought of going to Dalecarlia, where he might live with more security in the high mountains and thick woods of</p></body></text></TEI>