<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0734.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0728-01" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>STAR</label>-
shot, a gelatinous ſubſtance frequently found in fields, and ſuppoſed by the vulgar to have been produced from the meteor called a <hi rend="italic">falling star :</hi> but, in reality, is the half-digeſted food of herons, ſea-mews, and the like birds ; for theſe birds have been found, when newly ſhot, to diſgorge a ſubſtance of the ſame kind.</p><p><hi rend="italic">STAR-Stone,</hi> in natural hiſtory, a name given to certain extraneous foſſil ſtones, in form of ſhort, and commonly ſomewhat crooked, columns compoſed of ſeveral joints, each reſembling the figure of a radiated ſtar, with a greater or ſmaller number of rays in the different ſpecies : they are uſually found of about an inch in length, and of the thickneſs of a gooſe-quill. Some of them have five angles or rays, and others only four ; and in ſome the angles are equidiſtant, while in others they are irregularly ſo : in ſome alſo they are ſhort and blunt, while in others they are long, narrow, and pointed ; and ſome have their angles very ſhort and obtuſe. The ſeveral joints in the ſame ſpecimen are uſually all of the ſame thickneſs ; this, however, is not always the caſe : but in ſome they are larger at one end, and in others at the middle, than in any other part of the body ; and ſome ſpecies have one of the rays bifid, ſo as to emulate the appearance of a six-rayed kind.</p><p><hi rend="italic">STAR-Thistle,</hi> in botany. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Centaurea.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">STAR-Wort,</hi> in botany. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Aster.</hi></p></div></body></text></TEI>