<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0790.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0784-03" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>STELLARIA, <hi rend="smallcaps">Stichwort,</hi></label>
 in botany : A genus of plants belonging to the claſs of <hi rend="italic">decandria,</hi> and order of <hi rend="italic">trigynia ;</hi> and in the natural ſyſtem arranged under the 22d order, <hi rend="italic">Caryophyllea.</hi> The calyx is pentaphyllous and ſpreading. There are five petals, each divided into two ſegments. The capſuſe is oval, unilocular, and polyſpermous. There are nine ſpecies, the nemorum, dichotoma, radians, holostea, graminea, ceraſtoides, undulata, biflora, and arenaria. Three of theſe are Britiſh plants, 1. <hi rend="italic">Nemorum,</hi> broad-leaved ſtichwort. The stalks are about a foot or eighteen inches high, and branched in a panicle at the top. The leaves are heart- ſhaped, and of a paler green on the under than on the upper side ; the lower ones being ſupported by foot- ſtalks which are hairy and channelled ; the upper ones are ſeſſile. The calyx is erect, ſomewhat hairy and white on the margins. The petals are bifid almoſt to the baſe. There is a ſmall nectarium between the longer ſtamina and the calyx. — 2. <hi rend="italic">Holoβea,</hi> greater ſtichwort. The ſtalks are about two feet long ; the petals are nearly twice the length of the calyx, and divided half-way to the baſe. It is common in woods end hedges. —3. <hi rend="italic">Graminea,</hi> leſs ſtichwort. The ſtem is near a foot high. The leaves are linear and entire, and the flowers grow in looſe panicles. It is frequent in dry paſtures. There is a variety of this ſpecies called <hi rend="italic">bog stichwort,</hi> with ſmooth, oval, ſeſſile leaves, and few leaves, which grows often in wet marshy places. The ſtalk is quadrangular ; the petals ſcarcely longer than the calyx, and bifid to the baſe.</p></div></body></text></TEI>