<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-12T18:12:08Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>acquired a considerable celebrity in shipbuilding ; and a powerful French baron had a ship specially built at Inverness in 1249 to convey him and his vassals to the Holy Land. The principal shipowners at this period were the clergy, who embarked the wealth of their religious houses in commercial enterprises. Definite statements regarding the number and tonnage of shipping are, however, lacking till the 18th century. From two reports printed by the Scottish Burgh Record Society in 1881, it appears that the number of vessels belonging to the principal ports—Leith, Dundee, Glasgow, Kirkcaldy, and Montrose—in 1656 was 58, the tonnage being 3140, and that by 1692 they had increased to 97 of 5905 tons. These figures only represent a portion of the total shipping of the kingdom. At the time of the Union in 1707 the number of vessels was 215 of 14,485 tons. The following table (XIX.) gives the numbers for various years from 1850 :—</p><table><row><cell/><cell cols="2">1850.</cell><cell cols="2">I860.</cell><cell cols="2">1870.</cell><cell cols="2">1884.</cell></row><row><cell/><cell>No.</cell><cell>Tons.</cell><cell>No.</cell><cell>Tons.</cell><cell>No.</cell><cell>Tons.</cell><cell>No.</cell><cell>Tons.</cell></row><row><cell>Sailing vessels</cell><cell>3432</cell><cell>491,395</cell><cell>3172</cell><cell>552,212</cell><cell>2715</cell><cell>727,942</cell><cell>1 2065</cell><cell>827,295</cell></row><row><cell>Steam vessels</cell><cell>169</cell><cell>30,827</cell><cell>314</cell><cell>71,579</cell><cell>582</cell><cell>209,142</cell><cell>1403</cell><cell>866,780</cell></row><row><cell>Total ....</cell><cell>3601</cell><cell>522,222</cell><cell>3486</cell><cell>623,791</cell><cell>3297</cell><cell>937,084</cell><cell>346S</cell><cell>1,694,075</cell></row></table><p>Table XX. shows the progress of the coasting and foreign trade since 1855:—</p><table><row><cell>Year.</cell><cell cols="2">Coasting.</cell><cell cols="2">Colonial and Foreign.</cell><cell cols="2">Total.</cell></row><row><cell/><cell>Entered.</cell><cell>Cleared.</cell><cell>Entered.</cell><cell>Cleared.</cell><cell>Entered.</cell><cell>Cleared.</cell></row><row><cell>1855</cell><cell>1,963,552</cell><cell>2,057,936</cell><cell>668,078</cell><cell>840,150</cell><cell>3,631,630</cell><cell>2,898,0S6</cell></row><row><cell>1880</cell><cell>6,628,853</cell><cell><p>5,691,136</p><p>6,098,938</p></cell><cell>2,700,915</cell><cell>3,001,897</cell><cell>9,329,768</cell><cell>8,693,033</cell></row><row><cell>1884</cell><cell>7,167,230</cell><cell/><cell>3,073,561</cell><cell>3,638,423</cell><cell>10,240,791</cell><cell>9,737,361</cell></row></table><p>Table XXI. shows the great expansion of the foreign and colonial trade since 1755:—</p><table><row><cell>Year.</cell><cell>Imports.</cell><cell>Exports.</cell><cell>Year.</cell><cell>Imports.</cell><cell>Exports.</cell></row><row><cell>1755</cell><cell>£464,411</cell><cell>£535,576</cell><cell>1825</cell><cell>£4,994,304</cell><cell>£5,842,296</cell></row><row><cell>1790</cell><cell>1,688,337</cell><cell>1,235,405</cell><cell>1851</cell><cell>8,921,10S</cell><cell>5,016,116</cell></row><row><cell>1795</cell><cell>1,268,520</cell><cell>976,791</cell><cell>1874</cell><cell>31,012,750</cell><cell>17,912,932</cell></row><row><cell>1800</cell><cell>2,212,790</cell><cell>2,340,069</cell><cell>1880</cell><cell><p>34,997,652</p><p>30,600,258</p></cell><cell>18,243,078</cell></row><row><cell>1815</cell><cell>3,447,853</cell><cell>6,997,709</cell><cell>1884</cell><cell/><cell>20,322,355</cell></row></table><p>The value of the imports into Scotland is only about a tenth of that of England, but this does not represent the proper proportion of foreign imports used or consumed in Scotland, as large quantities find their way to Scotland from England by rail,—nearly all the tea, for example, consumed in Great Britain being imported into London, while various other ports have almost a monopoly of certain other imports. Reckoning by the combined value of their imports and exports, the principal ports of Scotland are Glasgow, Leith, Greenock, Dundee, Grangemouth, and Aberdeen, in the order named, but for particulars regarding the trade of these and other ports reference must be made to the articles on the several towns.</p><p>For many of the most important improvements in the construction of ships, especially steam vessels, Great Britain is indebted to the enterprise and skill of the Clyde shipbuilders. From the time of the construction by Mr Robert Napier of the steamers for the Cunard line, formed in 1840, the shipbuilders on the Clyde have enjoyed an unrivalled reputation for the construction of large ocean steamers, both as regards mechanical appliances and the beauty and convenience of the internal arrangements. Shipbuilding is also carried on to a considerable extent at Dundee, Leith, and Aberdeen, and to a certain degree at most of the ports of the king</p><p>dom, but within recent years the industry has been in a very fluctuating condition, the tonnage of the vessels constructed annually varying between 1880 and 1885 from a little over 100,000 to nearly 300,000.</p><p><hi rend="italic">National Wealth.—</hi>The immense increase in the wealth of Scotland within the last 200 years is sufficiently proved by the fact that, while in 1674 the valued rent was only £3,656,408 Scots or £304,700 sterling, the gross annual value of the land according to the estimate in the return of 1873 was £18,698,804, or more than sixty times as much, and about fifteen times as great as the proportional increase of population. This increase is of course partly due to agricultural improvements and partly to the discovery and development of the mineral wealth in coal and iron, but it may also be accounted for by the smaller representative value of money, and by the fictitious increase in rents in towns, which does not represent an increase in absolute value. The annual value of real property assessed for income-tax under schedule A in 1843 was £9,481,000 ; the average value for the three years ending 5th April 1883 was £16,995,718, and for the year ending 5th April 1884 the value was £17,066,705. For the year ending 5th April 1857 the amount of property and income charged with duty was £22,563,238 ; and during the following twenty-five years it was more than doubled, the average amount for the three years ending 5th April 1883 being £48,069,765, and for the year ending 5th April 1884 £49,600,348. This is less than a tenth of that for the United Kingdom. The total amount of money lying in deposit in savings banks in 1884 was £7,709,471,—about a seventh part of the whole amount deposited in the savings banks of the United Kingdom. Notice of the rise and progress of banking in Scotland will be found under <hi rend="smallcaps">Banking</hi> (vol. iii. pp. 332-336). The total paid-up capital of the Scottish banks at the dates of balance in 1885 was £9,052,000 and their total liabilities £107,882,595.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Education.—</hi>Notices of the existence of schools in the principal towns occur as early as the 13th century. They were under the supervision of the chancellor of each diocese and were chiefly devoted to studies preparatory for the church. Previous to the Reformation schools for general education were attached to many religious houses. In the <hi rend="italic">First Book of Discipline,</hi> 1560, a comprehensive scheme of general education was propounded, but neither this proposal nor an Act passed in 1616 by the privy council for the establishment of a school in every parish was carried into effect ; and the system of parochial schools which prevailed till the passing of the Education Act of 1872 really dates from the Act of William and Mary in 1696 providing for the maintenance of a school in every parish at the cost of the heritors. The various religious secessions in Scotland led to the founding of a large number of denominational and subscription schools, and at the Disruption in 1843 the Free Church made provision for the supply of secular education as well as religious instruction to its adherents. The Education Act of 1872 abolished the old management of the parish schools, and provided for the creation of districts under the management of school boards elected for three years by the ratepayers, male and female. These boards have the power to levy rates for the maintenance and erection of schools for primary instruction, elect the teachers, and enforce the clause in regard to compulsory attendance. The maintenance of schools is also aided by a Government grant, and the salary of the teacher is paid partly by school fees and partly by a grant dependent upon the result of the examination of the scholars by the Government inspector, the school board having the power, however, to make their own terms with the teacher. Denominational schools are permitted to receive a Government grant. The following table (XXII.) shows the proportion of persons in the receipt of education in Scotland in 1861, 1871, and 1881 :—</p><table><row><cell>Year.</cell><cell cols="4">Population at different Ages.</cell><cell cols="4">Persons in Receipt of Education.</cell><cell cols="2">Percentages to the</cell><cell cols="2">Population at each Age.</cell></row><row><cell/><cell>0-5 years.</cell><cell>5-15 years.</cell><cell>15 and above.</cell><cell>Total.</cell><cell>0-5 years.</cell><cell>5-15 years.</cell><cell>15 and above.</cell><cell>Total.</cell><cell>0-5 years.</cell><cell>5-15 years.</cell><cell>15 and above.</cell><cell>Total.</cell></row><row><cell>1861</cell><cell>417,259</cell><cell>685,912</cell><cell>1,959,123</cell><cell>3,052,294</cell><cell>8,666</cell><cell>439,388</cell><cell>19,002</cell><cell>467,056</cell><cell>2∙08</cell><cell>64·05</cell><cell>0·96</cell><cell>15∙25</cell></row><row><cell>1871</cell><cell>455,620</cell><cell>776,871</cell><cell>2,127,527</cell><cell>3,360,018</cell><cell>10,025</cell><cell>541,995</cell><cell>22,101</cell><cell>574,121</cell><cell>2∙19</cell><cell>69·77</cell><cell>1·04</cell><cell>17·09</cell></row><row><cell>1881</cell><cell>510,591</cell><cell>855,015</cell><cell>2,369,967</cell><cell>3,735,573</cell><cell>14,152</cell><cell>675,314</cell><cell>30,633</cell><cell>720,099</cell><cell>2∙77</cell><cell>78·98</cell><cell>1·29</cell><cell>19·28</cell></row></table><p>Particulars in regard to schools under school board management are given in the following table (XXIII.) :—</p><table><row><cell/><cell>M 2 w g</cell><cell>o · s</cell><cell>School</cell><cell>≈ . ss</cell><cell>d ft .Λ u o a; £</cell><cell><p>t- .</p><p>£ ® 2-2 J5 .g τ&gt; o</p></cell><cell><p>•s „·</p><p>■5 fe</p></cell><cell>S ≈</cell><cell><p>£</p><p>¾2</p></cell></row><row><cell>$</cell><cell><p>5’S</p><p>êi,</p></cell><cell><hi rend="italic">~z</hi> ο <hi rend="italic">■ Λ &amp;</hi></cell><cell>Places.</cell><cell>∣ &amp; 0Q</cell><cell><p>Expe</p><p>ture</p><p>Schol</p><p>Aveι</p><p>Atteιι∣</p></cell><cell><p>C ∈	·—</p><p>=&gt; X	-</p><p>κ</p></cell><cell>So ■£ 5 «3 <hi rend="superscript">h</hi></cell><cell><p>.2'S</p><p>•z <hi rend="superscript">ri</hi></p><p>&lt; -</p></cell><cell><p>Ä ?</p><p>H</p></cell></row><row><cell>1875</cell><cell>£551,140</cell><cell>314,164</cell><cell>391,538</cell><cell>2730</cell><cell>£1 15 91</cell><cell>12,958</cell><cell>3811</cell><cell>129</cell><cell>4262</cell></row><row><cell>1884</cell><cell>938,223</cell><cell>458,121</cell><cell>655,672</cell><cell>3131</cell><cell>2 1 5∣</cell><cell>61,429</cell><cell>6220</cell><cell>1012</cell><cell>3629</cell></row></table><p>All the training colleges for teachers in board schools are connected with religious denominations—three with the Established Church, three with the Free Church, and one with the Episcopal Church.</p><p>As early as the 14th century some of the burghs had grammar- schools partly under the control of the magistrates. In 1496 an</p><p>Act was passed enjoining the attendance at the schools of the eldest sons of barons and freeholders until “ they be founded in perfect Latin, and thereafter to remain at the schools of arts and law ” (where ecclesiastics were trained). The grammar or burgh schools enjoyed a monopoly of teaching certain branches, and private schools were frequently prohibited as interfering with their rights. Grammar-schools were chiefly devoted to instruction in Latin, and the course usually extended to five years. According to the report of the education commissioners, the number of burgh schools in 1867 was twenty-six. By the Act of 1872 their management was transferred to the school board, but they were excluded from participation in the school fund, and no provision was made for their inspection. The Act of 1878 authorized certain grunts of money, and contained certain provisions for inspection, which, however, have been practically inoperative. The Educational Endowments Act of 1882 provides for a more comprehensive scheme for the</p></body></text></TEI>