<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-12T18:08:28Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>an unsolved problem which receives satisfaction only in the practical, the
                individualizing activity. The practical, again, taken in conjunction with the
                theoretical, forces on the question of the reconciliation between the free conscious
                organization of thought and the apparently necessitated and unconscious mechanism of
                the objective world. In the notion of a teleological connexion and in that which for
                spirit is its subjective expression, viz., art and genius, the subjective and
                objective find their point of union.</p>
            <p>(2) Nature and spirit, <hi rend="italic">Naturphilosophie</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                    >Transcendentalρhilo- sοphie,</hi> thus stand as two relatively complete, but
                complementary parts of the whole. It was impossible for Schelling, the animating
                principle of whose thought was ever the reconciliation of differences, not to take
                and to take speedily the step towards the conception of the uniting basis of which
                nature and spirit are manifestations, forms, or consequences. For this common basis,
                however, he did not succeed at first in finding any other than the merely negative
                expression of indifference. The identity, the absolute, which underlay all
                difference, all the relative, is to be characterized simply as <hi rend="italic"
                    >neutrum</hi>, as absolute undifferentiated self-equivalence. It lay in the very
                nature of this thought that Spinoza should now offer himself to Schelling as the
                thinker whose form of presentation came nearest to his new problem. The <hi
                    rend="italic">Darstellung meines Systems, </hi>and the more expanded and more
                careful treatment contained in the lectures on <hi rend="italic">System der
                    gesummten Philosophie und der Naturphilosophie insbesondere</hi> given in
                Würzburg, 1804 (published only in the <hi rend="italic">Sämmtliche Werke,</hi> vol.
                vi. p. 131-576), are thoroughly Spinozistic in form, and to a large extent in
                substance. They are not without value, indeed, as extended commentary on Spinoza.
                With all his efforts, Schelling does not succeed in bringing his conceptions of
                nature and spirit into any vital connexion with the primal identity, the absolute
                indifference of reason. No true solution •could be achieved by resort to the mere
                absence of distinguishing, differencing feature. The absolute was left with no other
                function than that of removing all the differences on which thought turns. The
                criticisms of Fichte, and more particularly of Hegel (in the “Vorrede” to the <hi
                    rend="italic">Phänomenologie des Geistes),</hi> point to the fatal defect in the
                conception of the absolute as mere featureless identity.</p>
            <p>(3) Along two distinct lines Schelling is to be found in all his later writings
                striving to amend the conception, to which he remained true, of absolute reason as
                the ultimate ground of reality. It was necessary, in the first place, to give to
                this absolute a <hi rend="italic">character,</hi> to make of it something more than
                empty sameness ; it was necessary, in the second place, to clear up in some way the
                relation in which the actuality or apparent actuality of nature and spirit stood to
                the ultimate real. Schelling had already (in the <hi rend="italic">System der ges.
                    Phil.</hi> ) begun to endeavour after an amalgamation of the Spinozistic
                conception of substance with the Platonic view of an ideal realm, and to find
                therein the means of enriching the bareness of absolute reason. In <hi rend="italic"
                    >Bruno,</hi> and in <hi rend="italic">Philos. u. Religion,</hi> the same thought
                finds expression. In the realm of ideas the absolute finds itself, has its own
                nature over against itself as objective over against subjective, and thus is in the
                way of overcoming its abstractness, of becoming concrete. This conception of a
                difference, of an internal structure in the absolute, finds other and not less
                obscure expressions in the mystical contributions of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Menschliche Freiheit</hi> and in the scholastic speculations of the Berlin
                lectures on mythology. At the same time it connects itself with the second problem,
                how to attain in conjunction with the abstractly rational character of the absolute
                an explanation of actuality. Things,—nature and spirit,—have an actual being. They
                exist not merely as logical consequence or development of the absolute, but have a
                stubbornness of being in them, an antagonistic feature which in all times
                philosophers have been driven to recognize, and which they have described in varied
                fashion. The actuality of things is a defection from the absolute, and their
                existence compels a reconsideration of our conception of God. There must be
                recognized in God as a completed actuality, a dim, obscure ground or basis, which
                can only be described as not yet being, but as containing in itself the impulse to
                externalization, to existence. It is through this ground of Being in God Himself
                that we must find explanation of that independence which things assert over against
                God. And it is easy to see how from this position Schelling was led on to the
                further statements that not in the rational conception of God is an explanation of
                existence to be found, nay, that all rational conception extends but to the form,
                and touches not the real,—that God is to be conceived as act, as will, as something
                over and above the rational conception of the divine. Hence the stress laid on will
                as the realizing factor, in opposition to thought, a view through which Schelling
                connects himself with Schopenhauer and Von Hartmann, and on the ground of which he
                has been recognized by the latter as the reconciler of idealism and realism.
                Finally, then, there emerges the opposition of negative, i.e., merely rational
                philosophy, and positive, of which the content is the real evolution of the divine
                as it has taken place in fact and in history and as it is recorded in the varied
                mythologies and religions of mankind. Not much satisfaction can be felt with the
                exposition of either as it appears in the volumes of Berlin lectures.</p>
            <p>Schelling’s works were collected and published by his sons, in 14 vols., 1856-61. For
                the life good materials are to be found in the three vols., <hi rend="italic">Aus
                    Schelliηg's Leben in Briefen,</hi> 1869-70, in which a biographic sketch of the
                philosopher's early life is given by his son, and in Waitz, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Karοline,</hi> 2 vols., 1871 An interesting little work is Klaiber, <hi
                    rend="italic">Hölderlin, Hegel, u. Schelling in ihren Schwäbischen
                    Jugendjahren,</hi> 1877. The biography in Kuno Fischer's volume is complete and
                admirable. Apart from the expositions in the larger histories of modern philosophy,
                in Michelet, Erdmann, Willm, and Kuno Fischer, and in Haym’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Romantische Schule,</hi> valuable studies are—Rosenkranz, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Schelling,</hi> 1843 ; Noack, <hi rend="italic">Schelling und die Philosophie
                    der Romantik,</hi> 2 vols., 1859 ; Frantz, <hi rend="italic">Schelling's
                    positive Philosophie,</hi> 3 vols., 1879-80; Watson, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Schelling's Transcendental Idealism,</hi> 1882. (R. AD.)</p>
            <p>SCHEMNITZ (Hung. <hi rend="italic">Selmeczbánya),</hi> a mining town in the
                Cis-Danubian county of Hont, Hungary, lies about 65 miles north from Budapest, in
                48° 27' N. lat., 18° 52' E. long., on an elevated site, 2300 feet above the level of
                the sea. Its institutions include a Roman Catholic and a Protestant gymnasium, a
                high school for girls, a court of justice, a hospital, and several benevolent and
                scientific societies. Schemnitz owes its chief importance to the fact of its being
                the mining centre of the kingdom. Connected with this local industry are important
                Government institutions, such as various mining superintendencies, a chemical
                analytical laboratory, and an excellent academy of mining and forestry (with a
                meteorological observatory and a remarkable collection of minerals), attended by
                pupils from all countries of Europe and also from America. The mines are chiefly the
                property of the state and the corporation ; the average yield annually is— gold, 232
                lb; silver, 45,000 lb ; lead, 11,600 cwt.; copper, 180 cwt. Iron, arsenic, &amp;c.,
                to the value of about £150,000 are also produced. There are also flourishing
                potteries where well-known tobacco pipes are manufactured. With Schemnitz is
                conjoined the town of Bélabánya ; their united population in 1884 was 15,265,
                chiefly Slovaks, of whom nearly 3000 were engaged in mining.</p>
            <p>Schemnitz, which was already noted for its mines in the time of the Romans, has
                played considerable part in the history of Hungary. The archives of the town contain
                many interesting documents. After the Tartar invasion in the 12th century it was
                colonized by Germans, but had become quite Slavonized before the academy of mining
                was founded by Maria Theresa (1760). The school of forestry was added in 1809. The
                corporation is wealthy, having received special commercial privileges from the crown
                in consideration of pecuniary aid afforded in times of emergency.</p>
            <p>SCHENECTADY, a city of the United States, county seat of Schenectady county, New
                York, in the valley of the Mohawk river, 17 miles by rail north-west of Albany, with
                which it is also connected by the Erie Canal. It is best known as the seat of Union
                College, an institution founded in 1795 by a union of several religious sects, and
                now possessed of large endowments, extensive buildings, and a valuable library, and
                along with the Albany medical and law schools, &amp;c., forming the Union
                University. Besides manufacturing locomotives, iron bridges, and agricultural
                implements, Schenectady has shawl, hosiery, carriage, and varnish factories. The
                population was 9579 in 1860, 11,026 in 1870, and 13,655 in 1880.</p>
            <p>Occupying the site of one of the council grounds of the Mohawks, Schenectady was
                chosen as a Dutch trading post in 1620, was chartered in 1684, and became a borough
                in 1765 and a city in 1798. In 1691 it was burned by the French and Indians, and
                sixty-three of its inhabitants massacred.</p>
            <p>SCHETKY, <hi rend="smallcaps">John Alexander</hi> (1785-1824), a younger brother of
                J. C. Schetky (see below), studied medicine in Edinburgh university and drawing in
                the Trustees’ Academy. As a military surgeon he served with distinction under Lord
                Beresford in Portugal. He contributed excellent works to the exhibitions of the
                Royal Academy and of the Water-Colour Society, and executed some of the
                illustrations in Sir W. Scott’s <hi rend="italic">Provincial Antiquities.</hi> He
                died at Cape Coast Castle, 5th September 1824, when preparing to follow Mungo Park’s
                route of exploration.</p>
            <p>SCHETKY, <hi rend="smallcaps">John Christian</hi> (1778-1874), marine painter,
                descended from an old Transylvanian family, was born in Edinburgh on the 11th of
                August 1778. He studied art under Alexander Nasmyth, and after having</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
