<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-12T18:11:01Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>bration of this marriage Livingstone, now chamberlain, with many of his kindred and
                friends, was suddenly arrested and tried before a parliament at Edinburgh ; two were
                executed, and the others, including the chamberlain, attainted and placed in strict
                ward in Dumbarton. Douglas and Crichton received part of the forfeited estates.
                James was chiefly advised at this period by Bishop Kennedy, whose counsel was the
                old one of “ divide et impera.” He now determined to do to the more powerful Douglas
                as he had done to the Livingstones. The earl had shown no moderation in prosperity.
                His revenue and retainers equalled those of the king : 1000 horsemen were his
                ordinary train, and he attended the king’s marriage with five times that number. His
                courts on the borders were almost parliaments. In the year of jubilee (1450) he went
                to Rome with a large suite. On his return he visited the new king of England, Edward
                IV. At the parliament of Edinburgh (1451) he submitted to the king’s mercy, and at
                the request of the queen and estates received a regrant of his lands and honours. He
                was already suspected of treason, and had in fact renewed a secret bond with the
                earls of Crawford and Ross, the most powerful nobles in the north, which threatened
                the royal authority. James felt a crisis had come and summoned Douglas to Stirling
                at Shrovetide. There the young king, in violation of hospitality and a safe conduct
                which he had given the earl, when Douglas refused to break the bond with the other
                earls, struck him with his knife and killed him (21st February 1452). @@<hi
                    rend="superscript">1</hi> An appeal to arms necessarily followed. Douglas’s
                brother James, the ninth earl, came to Stirling and burnt great part of the town.
                But the clergy and commons and other nobles, some even of Douglas’s own kin, not
                sorry at the fall of one who overtopped them, stood by the king. Parliament
                sanctioned James’s act and declared Douglas had deserved death. At length, after
                repeated struggles, Crawford was defeated at the Muir of Brechin and Douglas fled to
                England. His estates were of course forfeited. The lordship of Douglas was granted
                to Angus. Ettrick Forest and Galloway were annexed to the crown. Some years later
                Douglas made another desperate effort against James, but after wasting Merse was
                totally defeated by Angus (1458). @@<hi rend="superscript">2</hi> The energy of
                James in visiting all parts of his kingdom was conspicuous during the last period of
                his reign. The good relations with the French and other Continental courts
                continued. With England—one brief interruption excepted— peace had been preserved
                during the reign of Henry VI. Henry even agreed to restore Roxburgh and Berwick to
                Scotland in return for assistance against the duke of York. When Henry was taken
                prisoner at Northampton, his queen and her young son fled to Scotland, and James was
                called on to fulfil his engagements. He laid siege to Roxburgh, which for more than
                a century had defied his predecessors, and after a stout resistance it was taken ;
                but James did not live to enjoy the triumph. When inspecting the discharge of a new
                gun it burst, and he was killed (3d August 1460). He had not reached his thirtieth
                year.</p>
            <p>His reign had been singularly fortunate, for he succeeded (where his father failed)
                in restoring the royal authority and reducing the power of the nobles. This may have
                been partly due to the counsels of Kennedy, bishop of St Andrews, and Crichton; but James
                showed skill in government and vigour in war, though the murder of Douglas has left
                a stain on his character. The crown was richer at his death than it had been since
                the time of Alexander III., by many forfeitures secured from alienation by the Act
                of Annexation (1455, c. 41). The royal prerogative was strengthened by the first
                statute defining treason (1449, c. 25). Provision was made for the execution of
                criminal justice by the king, his justiciar, and sheriffs, and of civil justice by
                the session. Stringent rules were laid down against violent spoliation of lands and
                goods (1449, c. 30). The coinage was regulated, an attempt made to preserve its
                standard, and to prohibit export of gold and silver (1451, c. 23). Towards the end
                of the reign, when war with England was impending, statutes were passed for the
                defence of the borders, giving the king more direct control, and declaring that the
                office of warden should not be hereditary. The progress of agriculture was furthered
                by the famous Act for the encouragement of feu farm, an existing form of tenure
                becoming more common, and another giving fixity of tenure to leases until the expiry
                of their terms notwithstanding alienation of the lands. There were also many minor
                laws which had for their object the welfare of the people. Though the legislation of
                James II. was not so large, it was perhaps as important as that of James I.</p>
            <p>On the Sunday after his father’s death James III. (1460-88) was crowned at Kelso. A
                regency was formed consisting of the queen, Kennedy, and others. A parliament
                followed at Edinburgh, which was blamed by the nobles for leaving so much power in
                the hands of a woman ; but there was a full appointment to the offices of state,
                and, though Mary of Guelders aimed at more than the guardianship of her son, it does
                not appear that she really exercised royal authority. After the defeat of Towton
                (29th March 1461), Henry VI. and his queen took refuge in Scotland. In return for
                their reception and in hope of further aid, Henry surrendered Berwick (23d April) to
                the Scottish king, in whose hands it remained till its final annexation to England
                at the close of the reign. Edward IV. retaliated by a treaty (13th February 1462)
                with the banished earl of Douglas, the earl of Ross, lord of the Isles, and Donald
                Balloch, by which Douglas was to be restored to his estates, and the whole country
                north of the Forth divided between the two Highland chiefs. George, earl of Angus,
                who had risen on the ruins of the house of Douglas, made a counter-league with Henry
                VI., by which he was promised an English dukedom and valuable lands between Trent
                and Humber, but was to preserve his allegiance to the Scottish king. These were
                paper promises, and all that came of them were an ineffectual rising in the north
                and the relief of Alnwick, which had been besieged by the Yorkists. Next year the
                Lancastrian cause having received a fatal blow by the defeat of Hexham, a singular
                offer by Edward IV. to marry the queen dowager of Scotland—one of the many schemes
                of the king-maker, earl of Warwick—was frustrated by her death or perhaps by the
                discovery of an intrigue with Adam Hepburn of Hales, whose wife was alive. Kennedy,
                who had the chief control of Scottish affairs, negotiated the release of Alexander,
                the king’s brother, who had been taken by an English cruiser, and secured a truce
                between England and Scotland for fifteen years. He understood the nature of his
                countrymen better than any man, and was always ready to give counsel in parliament,
                while his learning, especially in the civil law, made him respected by foreign
                powers. When he died the country wept for him as for a parent.</p>
            <p>Before his death a plot had been formed which threw the young king into different
                hands. Amongst the barons</p>
            <p><hi rend="superscript">@@@1</hi> The origin of two great families dates from the fall
                of Douglas. Sir James Hamilton of Cadzow deserted his kinsman for the king and
                received large grants of land and the king’s daughter as wife. Sir Walter Scott of
                Kirkurd and Buccleuch, a border chief, was similarly rewarded. These were the
                ancestors of the dukes of Hamilton and Buccleuch.</p>
            <p><hi rend="superscript">@@@2</hi> In the next reign along with the king’s banished
                brother, Albany, he made a daring raid on Lochmaben, but being taken prisoner he
                ended his days as a monk at Lindores. A saying attributed to him, “ If a man cannot
                better be, he may be a monk,” was a sign of the change of times since Celtic kings
                were proud to assume the cowl.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
