<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-12T18:09:34Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Gentile da Fabriano worked in the purely religious and richly decorative style that characterized Fra Angelico at Perugia. Fiorenzo di Lorenzo (see fig. 11) and Bonfigli prepared the way for Perugino (see fig. 12) and his pupils Pinturicchio. Raphael, Lo Spagna, and others. Timoteo Viti was another Umbrian painter of great ability, whose portrait by Raphael in black and red chalk is one of the most beautiful of the drawings in the Print Room of the British Museum.</p><p>The Paduan school is chiefly remarkable for the great name of Andrea Mantegna, the pupil of Squarcione ; his firm and sculpturesque draw</p><p>ing is combined with great</p><p>beauty of colour and vigor</p><p>ous expression (see fig. 13).</p><p>His pupil Montagna also</p><p>studied under Gian. Bellini</p><p>at Venice. Andrea Mantegna</p><p>influenced and was influenced</p><p>by the Venetian school ; to</p><p>him are attributed many of</p><p>the early paintings of his</p><p>brother-in-law Gian. Bellini,</p><p>such as the Vatican Pietà, and</p><p>other works more remarkable</p><p>for vigour than for grace.</p><p>The school of Arezzo was early in its development.</p><p>Margaritone, who is absurdly overpraised by his fellow- townsman Vasari, was an artist of the most feeble abilities. In the 14th century Arezzo produced such able painters as Spinello di Luca, Niccolo di Gerini, and Lorenzo di Bicci. In the 15th century it possessed no native school worth recording.</p><p>Venice did not come into prominence till the 15th century ; the Vivarini family of Murano were at work about the middle of it, and</p><p>were perhaps influ</p><p>enced by the Ger</p><p>man style of a con</p><p>temporary painter</p><p>from Cologne, known</p><p>as Johannes Aleman-</p><p>nus, who had settled</p><p>in Venice. Some</p><p>years later the tech</p><p>nical methods of</p><p>Flanders were intro</p><p>duced by Antonello</p><p>of Messina, who is</p><p>said to have learnt</p><p>the secret of an oil</p><p>medium from the</p><p>Van Eycks. @@<hi rend="superscript">1</hi> Cri-</p><p>velli, an able though</p><p>mannered painter of</p><p>the second half of</p><p>the 15th century,</p><p>adhered to an earlier type than his contemporaries (see fig. 14). Gian. Bellini is one of the chief glories of</p><p>the Venetian school (see fig. 15); as are also in a secondary degree his brother Gentile and his pupil Vittore</p><p>Carpaccio. @@<hi rend="superscript">2</hi> In the following century Venice possessed a school which for glory of colour and technical power has never been rivalled,</p><p>though it soon lost</p><p>the sweet religious</p><p>sentiment of the ear</p><p>lier Venetians. The</p><p>chief names of this</p><p>epoch are Palma</p><p>Vecchio, Giorgione,</p><p>Titian (see fig. 16),</p><p>and Lorenzo Lotto,</p><p>—the last a magnifi</p><p>cent portrait painter,</p><p>a branch of art in</p><p>which Venice occu</p><p>pied the highest</p><p>rank. In the 16th</p><p>century Tintoretto</p><p>and Paul Veronese</p><p>were supreme (see</p><p>fig. 17). In the 17th</p><p>and 18th centuries</p><p>Venice produced</p><p>some fairly good</p><p>work.</p><p>The Brescian school has bequeathed two very illustrious names,—Moretto and his pupil Moroni, both portrait painters of extraordinary power during the 16th century (see fig. 18). Mo</p><p>retto also painted</p><p>some fine large</p><p>altar-pieces, remark</p><p>able for their deli</p><p>cate silver - grey</p><p>tones and refined</p><p>modelling. Ro-</p><p>manino was an ex</p><p>tremely able painter</p><p>of frescos as well as</p><p>of easel pictures.</p><p>The school of Verona, which existed from the 13th to the 17th century, contains few names of highest importance; except that of Pisanello, the chief were painters of the end of the 15th and the early part of the 16th century, as Domenico and Francesco Morone, Bonsignori, Girolamo dai Libri, and Cavaz-</p><p><hi rend="superscript">@@@1</hi> Antonello certainly possessed technical knowledge beyond that of his contemporaries in Venice, namely, that of glazing in transparent oil colours over a tempera ground, and he must either in Italy or in Flanders have come in contact with some painter of the Flemish school ; many of the chief Flemish painters visited Italy in the 15th century.</p><p><hi rend="superscript">@@@2</hi> It should be noted that there are a large number of forged signatures of Gian. Bellini, many of them attached to their own pictures by his pupils, such as Catena and Kondiuelli.</p></body></text></TEI>