<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-12T18:09:31Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>at Florence ; chief among them were Simone di Martino, Lippo Memmi, and especially Ambrogio Lorenzetti, a</p><p>painter of both panels and large frescos, which show rich and noble imaginative power and much technical skill. It is important to</p><p>note that Ambrogio</p><p>and probably other</p><p>painters of his time</p><p>were, like the ear</p><p>lier Pisan Niccola,</p><p>beginning to study</p><p>the then rare ex</p><p>amples of classical</p><p>sculpture. Ghiberti, </p><p>in his <hi rend="italic">Commentary,</hi></p><p>speaks with enthu-.</p><p>siasm of the beauty</p><p>of an antique statue</p><p>which he knew only</p><p>from a drawing by Ambrogio Lorenzetti. In the second half of the 14th century Siena produced a large</p><p>number of more mediocre painters ; but these were succeeded by an abler generation, among whom the chief were</p><p>perhaps Sano di Pietro and Matteo di Giovanni, whose grand altarpiece (No. 1155), recently acquired, is one of</p><p>the glories of the English National Gallery. Many excellent masters were working at Siena throughout the 15th century and even later; the last names of any real note are those of Peruzzi and Beccafumi. Sodoma, though he settled in Siena in 1501, does not belong to the school of Siena ; his early life was passed at Milan, chiefly under the influence of Da Vinci. His talent was developed at Rome among the followers of Raphael.</p><p>On the whole the Florentine school surpasses in importance all others throughout Italy. Cimabue, though he</p><p>did not emancipate himself from the Byzantine manner, was a painter of real genius (see fig. 2).</p><p>Giotto is perhaps the most important painter in the history of the development of art, for during the whole of the 14th century the painters of Florence may be said to have been his pupils and imitators (see fig. 3). Orcagna alone developed rather a different line, more richly decorative in style and brighter in colour,— a link between the art of Giotto and that of Siena. In the 15th century Florence reached its period of highest artistic splendour and developed an almost</p></body></text></TEI>