<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-12T18:11:55Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>or other softer rock between them, it offers conditions peculiarly favourable for the
                formation of escarpments. In the wide basalt plateaus of the Inner Hebrides these
                conditions have been manifested on a great scale. The Carboniferous lavas of the
                Campsie and Fintry Hills and of the south of Dumfriesshire and Roxburghshire
                likewise rise in lines of bold escarpment.</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Lakes.—</hi>These important features in the landscapes of Scotland
                present the general characters of the water-basins so profusely scattered over the
                northern parts of Europe and North America. They may be classified in four groups,
                each of which has its own peculiar scenery and a distinct mode of origin—(1) glen
                lakes, (2) rock-tarns, (3) moraine-tarns, (4) lakes of the plains.</p>
            <p>(1) Glen lakes are those which occupy portions of glens. They are depressions in the
                valleys, not due to mere local heaping up of detritus, but true rock-basins, often
                of great depth. Much discussion has arisen as to their mode of origin. They have
                been regarded as caused by special subsidence of their areas, open fissures of the
                ground, general depression of the central part of each mountain district from which
                they radiate, and by the erosive action of glacier ice. That they are not open
                fissures and cannot be explained by any general subsidence of a neighbouring region
                is now generally admitted. That glaciers have occupied the glens where these lakes
                exist and have worn down the rocks along the sides and bottom cannot be doubted, but
                whether the ice would be capable of eroding hollows so deep as many of these lakes
                is a question which has been answered with equal confidence affirmatively and
                negatively. On the other hand, to suppose that each of these hollows has been caused
                by a special local subsidence would involve a complex series of subterranean
                disturbances, for which some better evidence than the mere existence of the basins
                is required. Under any circumstances it is quite certain that the lakes must be of
                recent geological date. Any such basins belonging to the time of the plication of
                the crystalline schists would have been filled up and effaced long ago. So rapid is
                the infilling by the torrents which sweep down detritus from the surrounding heights
                that the present lakes are being visibly diminished, and they cannot, therefore, be
                of high geological antiquity. It is worthy of remark that the glen lakes are almost
                wholly confined to the western half of the Highlands, where they form the largest
                sheets of fresh water. Hardly any lakes are to be seen east of a line drawn from
                Inverness to Perth. West of that line, however, they abound in both the longitudinal
                and the transverse valleys. The most remarkable line of them is that which fills up
                so much of the Great Glen. Loch Ness, the largest, is upwards of 20 miles long,
                about 1<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">2</hi> miles broad, and
                not less than 774 feet deep in the deepest part. This great depression exceeds the
                general depth reached by the floor of the North Sea between Great Britain and the
                opposite shores of the Continent. Other important longitudinal lakes are Lochs Tay,
                Awe, Ericht, and Shiel. The most picturesque glen lakes, however, lie in transverse
                valleys, which being cut across the strike of the rocks present greater variety, and
                usually also more abruptness of outline. Lochs Lomond, Katrine, and Lubnaig in the
                southern Highlands, and Lochs Maree and More in the north, are conspicuous
                examples.</p>
            <p>(2) Rock-tarns are small lakes lying in rock-basins on the sides of mountains or the
                summits of ridges, and on rocky plateaus or plains. Unlike the glen lakes, they have
                no necessary dependence upon lines of valley. On the contrary, they are scattered as
                it were broadcast over the districts in which they occur, and are by far the most
                abundant of all tire lakes of the country. Dispersed over all parts of the western
                Highlands, they are most numerous in the north-west, especially in the Outer
                Hebrides and in the west of Ross-shire and Sutherland. The surface of the Archæan
                gneiss is so thickly sprinkled with them that many tracts consist almost as much of
                water as of land. They almost invariably lie on strongly ice-worn platforms of rock.
                Their sides and the rocky islets which diversify their surface have been powerfully
                glaciated. They cannot be due to either fracture or subsidence, but are obviously
                hollows produced by erosion. They have accordingly with much probability been
                assigned to the gouging action of the sheets of land-ice by which the general
                glaciation of the country was effected. In the southern uplands, owing probably to
                the greater softness and uniformity of texture among the rocks, rock-tarns are
                comparatively infrequent, except in Galloway, where the protrusion of granite and
                its associated metamorphism have given rise to conditions of rock-structure more
                like those of the Highlands. Over the rocky hill-ranges of the central Lowlands
                rock-tarns occasionally make their appearance.</p>
            <p>(3) Moraine-tarns—small sheets of water ponded back by some of the last moraines shed
                by the retreating glaciers—are confined to the more mountainous tracts. Among the
                southern uplands many beautiful examples may be seen, probably the best known and
                certainly one of the most picturesque being the wild lonely Loch Skene lying in a
                recess of Whitecoomb at the head of the Moffat Water. Others are sprinkled over the
                higher parts of the valleys in Galloway. None occur in the central Lowlands. In the
                Highlands they may be counted by hundreds, nestling in the bottoms of the corries.
                In the north-western counties, where theglaciers continued longest to descend to the
                sea-level, lakes retained by moraine-barriers may be found very little above the
                sea.</p>
            <p>(4) The lakes of the plains lie in hollows of the glacial detritus which is strewn so
                thickly over the lower grounds. As these hollows were caused by original irregular
                deposition rather than by erosion, they have no intimate relation to the present
                drainagelines of the country. The lakes vary in size from mere pools up to wide
                sheets of water several square miles in area. As a rule they are shallow in
                proportion to their extent of surface. Though still sufficiently numerous in the
                Lowlands, they were once greatly more so, for, partly from natural causes and partly
                by artificial means, they have been made to disappear. The largest sheets of fresh
                water in the midland valley are of this class, as Loch Leven and the Lake of
                Menteith.</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Coast-Line.—</hi>The eastern and western seaboards of Scotland
                present a singular contrast. The former is indented by a series of broad arms of the
                sea, but is otherwise tolerably unbroken. The land slopes gently down to the margin
                of the sea or to the edge of cliffs that have been cut back by the waves. The shores
                are for the most part low, with few islands in front of them, and cultivation comes
                down to the tide-line. The western side of the country, on the contrary, is from end
                to end intersected with long narrow sea lochs or fjords. The land shelves down
                rapidly into the sea and is fronted by chains and groups of islands. This contrast
                has sometimes been erroneously referred to greater erosion by the waves on the
                western than on the eastern coast. The true explanation, however, must be sought in
                the geological structure of the land. The west side of Scotland, as we have seen,
                has been more deeply eroded than the eastern. The glens are more numerous there and
                on the whole deeper and narrower. Many of them are prolonged under the sea ; in
                other words, the narrow deep fjords which wind so far into the land are seaward
                continuations of the glens which emerge from their upper ends. The presence of the
                sea in these fjords is an accident. If they could be raised out of the sea they
                would become glens, with lakes filling up their deeper portions. That this has
                really been their history can hardly admit of question. They are submerged
                land-valleys, and as they run down the whole western coast they show that side of
                the country to have subsided to a considerable depth beneath its former level. The
                Scottish sea lochs must be viewed in connexion with those of western Ireland and of
                Norway. The whole of this north-western coast-line of Europe bears witness to recent
                submergence. The bed of the North Sea, which at no distant date in geological
                history was a land surface across which plants and animals migrated freely into
                Great Britain, sank beneath the sea-level, while the Atlantic advanced upon the
                western margin of the continent and filled the seaward ends of what had previously
                been valleys open to the sun. Not improbably the amount of subsidence was greater
                towards the west.</p>
            <p>Nearly the whole coast-line of Scotland is rocky. On the east side of the country,
                indeed, the shores of the estuaries are generally low, but the land between the
                mouths of these inlets is more or less precipitous. On the west side the coast is
                for the most part either a steep rocky declivity or a sea-wall, though strips of
                lower ground are found in the bays. The sea-cliffs everywhere vary in their
                characters according to the nature of the rock out of which they have been carved.
                At Cape Wrath precipices nearly 300 feet high have been cut out of the Archæan
                gneiss. The varying texture of this rock, its irregular foliation and jointing, and
                its ramifying veins of pegmatite conspire to give it very unequal powers of
                resistance in different parts of its mass. Consequently it projects in irregular
                bastions and buttresses and retires into deep recesses and tunnels, showing
                everywhere a ruggedness of aspect which is eminently characteristic. In striking
                contrast to these precipices are those of the Cambrian red sandstone a few miles to
                the east. Vast vertical walls of rock shoot up from the waves to a height of 600
                feet, cut by their perpendicular joints into quadrangular piers and projections,
                some of which even stand out alone as cathedrallike islets in front of the main
                cliff. The sombre colouring is relieved by lines of vegetation along the edges of
                the nearly flat beds which project like vast cornices and serve as nesting-places
                for crowds of sea-fowl. On the west side of the country the most notable cliffs
                south from those of Cape Wrath and the Cambrian sandstones of Sutherland are to be
                found among the basaltic islands, particularly in Skye, where a magnificent range of
                precipices rising to 1000 feet bounds the western coast-line. The highest cliffs in
                the country are found among the Shetland and Orkney Islands. The sea-wall of Foula,
                one of the Shetland group, and the western front of Hoy in Orkney rise like walls to
                heights of 1100 or 1200 feet above the waves that tunnel their base. Caithness is
                one wide moor, terminating almost everywhere in a range of sea-precipices of Old Red
                Sandstone. Along the eastern coast-line most of the cliffs are formed of rocks
                belonging to the same formation. Beginning at Stonehaven, an almost unbroken line of
                precipice varying up to 200 feet in height runs southwards to the mouth of the
                estuary of the Tay. The southern uplands plunge abruptly into the sea near St Abb’s
                Head in a noble range of precipices 300 to 500 feet in height, and on the western
                side the same high grounds</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
