<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:54:35Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>guſted with an exercise of power which deſpiſed every boundary of moderation and juſtice. The prediction of Mr Wiſhart, ſuggeſted by the general odium which attended the cardinal, was conſidered by the disciples of this martyr as the effuſion of a prophet; and perhaps gave occaſion to the aſſaſſination that followed, Their complaints were attended to by Norman Leſly, the eldeſt ſon of the earl of Rothes, whom the cardinal had treated with indignity, though he had profited by his ſervices. He conſented to be their leader. The cardinal was in his caſtle at St Andrew’s, which he was fortifying after the ſtrongeſt faſhion of that age. The conſpirators, at different times, early in the morning, entered into it. The gates were ſecured; and appointing a guard, that no intimation of their proceedings might go to the cardinal, they diſmiſſed from the caſtle all his workmen ſeparately, to the number of 100, and all his domeſtics, who amounted to no fewer than 50 perſons. The eldeſt ſon of the earl of Arran, whom he kept as an hoſtage for his father’s behaviour, was alone detained by them. The prelate, alarmed with their noiſe, looked from his window, and was informed that his caſtle was taken by Norman Lesly. It was in vain that he endeavoured to ſecure the door of his chamber by bolts and cheſts. The conſpirators brought fire, and were ready to apply it, when, admitting them into his preſence, he implored their mercy. Two of them ſtruck him haſtily with their ſwords. But James Melvil, rebuking their paſſion, told them, that this work and judgment of God, though ſecret, ought to be done with gravity. He reminded the cardinal, in general terms, of the enormity of his ſins, and reproached him in a more particular manner with the death of Mr Wiſhart. He ſwore, that no hopes of his riches, no dread of his power, and no hatred to his perſon, were any motives which actuated him; but that he was moved to accompliſh his deſtruction, by the obſtinacy and zeal maniſeſted by him againſt Chriſt Jeſus and his holy goſpel. Waiting for no anſwer to his harangue, he thruſt the cardinal three times through the body with his dagger, on the 29th of May 1546,</p><p>The rumour that the caſtle was taken giving an alarm to the inhabitants of St Andrew’s, they came in crowds to gratify their curioſity, and to offer their aſſiſtance, according to the ſentiments they entertained. The adherents and dependents of the cardinal were clamorous to ſee him; and the conſpirators, carrying his dead body to the very place from which he had beheld the ſuſſerings of Mr Wiſhart, expoſed it to their view.</p><p>The truce, in the mean time, which had been concluded with England was frequently interrupted; but no memorable battles were fought. Mutual depredations kept alive the hoſtile ſpirit of the two kingdoms; and while the regent was making military preparations, which gave the promiſe of important events, a treaty of peace was finiſhed between England and France, in which Francis I. took care to comprehend the Scottiſh nation. In this treaty it was ſtipulated by Henry, that he was not to wage war againſt Scotland, unleſs he  ſhould be provoked by new and juſt cauſes of hoſtility.</p><p>But the murderers of cardinal Beaton, apprehenſive of their ſafety, had diſpatched meſſengers into England, with applications to Henry for assiſtance; and being mined by more than 120 of their friends, they took the reſolution oſ keeping the caſtle, and of defending</p><p>themſelves. Henry, notwithstanding his treaty with France, reſolved to embrace this opportunity of augmenting the diſturbances of Scotland. He haſtened to collect troops; and the regent and his counſellors preſſed France for ſupplies in men and money, and military ſtores and artillery.</p><p>The high places which the cardinal occupied were filled up immediately upon his death. John Hamilton abbot of Paiſley was elected archbiſhop of St Andrew’s, and George earl of Huntley was promoted to be chancellor. By theſe officers the regent was urged to proceed with vigour againſt the conſpirators; and it was a matter of the greatcſt anxiety to him to recover his eldeſt ſon, whom they detained in cuſtody, The clergy had, in the moſt ſolernn manner, pronounced them to be accurſed; and agreed to furniſh, ſor four months, a monthly ſubſidy of 3000 l. to defray the expence of reducing them to obedience. The queen dowager and the French faction were eager, at the same time, to concur in avenging the aſſaſſination of a man to whoſe counſels and ſervices they were ſo greatly indebted. — And that no dangerous uſe might be made of the eldeſt ſon of the earl of Arran, who, after his father, was the heir of the monarchy, an act of parliament was paſſed, excluding him ſrom his birthright white he remained in the poſſeſſion of the enemies of his country, and ſubſtituting his brothers in his place, according to their ſeniority. The dark politics of Henry ſuggeſted the neceſſity of this expedient; and in its meaning and tendency there may be remarked the ſpirit and greatneſs of a free people.</p><p>A powerful army laid ſiege to the caſtle of St Andrew’s, and continued their operations during four months; but no ſucceſs attended the aſſailants. The fortifications were ſtrong; and a communication with the beſieged was open by ſea to the king of England, who ſupplied them with arms and proviſions. The garriſon received his pay, and the principal conſpirators had penſions from him. In return for his generoſity, they were engaged to promote the marriage of his ſon with the young queen; to advance the reformation; and to keep in cuſtody the eldeſt ſon of the regent. Negociation fucceeded to hoſtility; and as the regent expected aſſiſtance from France, and the conſpirators had the proſpect of ſupport from an Engliſh army, both parties were difpoſed to gaiu time. A treaty was entered into and tranſacted, in which the regent engaged to procure from Rome an abſolution to the conſpirators, and to obtain to them from the three eſtates an exemption from proſecutions of every kind. Upon the part of the beſieged, it was ſtipulated, that when theſe conditions were fulfilled, the caſtle ſhould be ſurrendered, and the regent's son be delivered up to him. In the mean time Henry VIII. died; and a few weeks after Francis I, alſo paid his debt to nature. But the former, before his death, had recommended the proſecution of the Scottiſh war; and Henry II. the ſucceſſor of Francis, was eager to ſhow his attention to the ancient ally of his nation. When the abſolution arrived from Rome, the conſpirators refilled to conſider it as valid; and an expreſſion uſed by the pope, implying an abſurdity, furniſhed an apology for their conduct. They knew that the counſellors of Edward VI. were making vigorous preparations to invade Scotland; they were confident of their preſent ability to defend themſelves; and the</p></body></text></TEI>