<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:59:26Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>are lieutenants, the other enſigns: exclusive is a ſtaff, of adjutant and ſurgeon. The black non-commiſſioned officers anſwer to our ſerjeants and corporals, and are called <hi rend="italic">havildars</hi> and <hi rend="italic">naigues.</hi> There is alſo to each corps an Engliſh ſerjeant-major, drill and ſtore ſerjeant; to each battalion is a band of drums and fifes, and to each a pair of colours. A captain commands the whole.</p><p>Their jackets, which are made entirely after the European faſhion, are of a red colour with yellow facings (as worn by all the infantry of the company on the Coromandel coaſt), The remaining part of their attire reſembles more the country or Indian habit, and conſiſts of a dark blue turban, broad and round at top, deſcending deep to the bottom, the fides of which, of a concave form, are croſſed by a white band, running in front, faſtened under a roſe above. As an under garment, they have a jacket of linen. A dark blue ſaſh girding, to anſwer the turban, goes round their middle. On the thighs they have ſhort drawers, faſtened by a ſcolloped band. Their legs are bare, which renders them more ready for action or ſervice. Their arms are a firelock and bayonet; their accoutrements or croſs belts black leather, with pouches the ſame.</p><p>A battalion drawn out cannot but ſtrike the ſpectators with a lively and fanciful military impreſſion, as they unite in their exterior traits reſpectively Indian and European.</p><p>They are brought to the utmoſt exactneſs of diſcipline; go through their evolutions and manœuvres with a regularity and preciſion equal to, and not ſurpaſſed by, European troops. In action they are brave and ſteady, and have been known to ſtand where Europeans have given way.</p><p>Their diſcipline puts them on a footing with European troops, with whom they are always ready to act in concert.</p><p>Their utility and ſervices are evident: they ſecure to the company the internal good order and preſervation of their territorial diſtricts, which, though poſſible to be enforced with a ſtrong hand by Europeans, requires numbers, and can only be conducted with that eaſe and addreſs peculiar to the native forces of the country.</p><p>They are conſidered with reſpect in the eyes of the other natives, though they ſufficiently, and with a good grace, feel and aſſert their own conſequence. In large garriſons, where the duty is great, as Madras, Pondicherry, Trichinopoly, Vellore, &amp;c. two or three battalions might be preſent together, excluſive of Europeans. If ſent ſingly up the country, they are liable to be detached, ſometimes by one or more companies being ſent to a ſtation dependent on the chief garriſon or headquarters, otherwiſe they are diſperſed through the diſtricts, four or five together, with a non-commiſſioned officer (this is a part of the ſervice which is called <hi rend="italic">going on command),</hi> on hills, or in villages, to preſerve order, convey intelligence, and aſſiſt the taſildar, renter, or cutwall of the place, in caſes of emergency. They alſo enforce the police, and prevent in ſuch caſes the country from being infeſted with thieves, which otherwiſe have combined, forming a banditti, to rob paſſengers and plunder cattle, of which there are ſo many inſtances upon record. As for ſuch Britiſh officers in the company’s ſervice as are attached to battalions, they are obliged to follow the fortunes and deſtinations of their</p><p>men, with their reſpective corps, leading a life replete with adventures of a peculiar nature. An individual in ſuch caſes is frequently ſecluded from thoſe, of his own colour when up the country, or detached upon command, where in a frontier garriſon or hill fort in the interior parts of India none but natives are to be found. Here he might live as he pleaſes, being perfectly abſolute within his juriſdiction. Such ſtations being lucrative, with management may produce great fortunes. Neither is the condition hard to a perſon converſant in the language of the country, or that of the Seapoys called <hi rend="italic">Moors</hi> (which moſt officers in the company’s ſervice acquire); otherwiſe the loſs of ſociety is not recompenſed by other advantages, as you forget your own language, grow melancholy, and paſs your days without comfort.</p><p>The peace eſtabliſhment at Madras conſiſts of 30 Seapoy battalions, but in time of war is augmented as occaſion requires; or frequently each corps is ſtrengthened by the addition of two companies, which are reduced again in time of peace, the officers remaining ſuper- numeraries in the ſervice. In garriſon they are quartered in barracks: they live agreeably to the uſage of the country, ſleep on the ground on a mat or thin carpet. In their perſons they are cleanly, but appear to beſt advantage in their uniform. Off duty they go as the other natives in poor circumſtances; and have only a cloth round their middle and over their ſhoulders. As to the different calls, the Moormen or Muſſulmen aſſert pre-eminence, as coming into the country by conqueſt. In their perſons they are rather robuſt, and in their tempers vindictive. Their religion and dreſs is diſtinct from the Hindoos, who are mild and paſſive in their temper, faithful, ſteady, and good ſoldiers. The Pariars are inferior to the others, live under different circumſtances, dwell in huts, and aſſociate not on equal terms with the reſt; they do all menial offices, are ſervants to Europeans, and think themſelves happy when by them employed, though they are equally good Seapoys. </p><p>Having thus treated of the company’s Seapoys, we ſhall obſerve that they are kindly attentive to their officers when often in circumſtances requiring their aſſiſtance; are guilty of few vices; and have a ſtrong attachment for thoſe who have commanded them. That acute hiſtorian Dr Robertſon has remarked, as a proof that the ingenuity of man has recourſe in ſimilar ſituations to the ſame expedients that the European powers have, in forming the eſtabliſhment oſ theſe native troops, adopted the ſame maxims, and, probably without knowing it, have modelled their battalions of Seapoys upon the ſame principles as Alexander the Great did his phalanx of Perſians.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">SEARCH-warrant,</hi> in law, a kind of general warrant iſſued by juſtices of peace or magiſtrates of towns for ſearching all ſuſpected places for ſtolen goods. In Scotland this was often done formerly; and in ſome Engliſh law-books there are precedents requiring the conſtable to ſearch all ſuch ſuſpected places as he and the party complaining ſhall think convenient; but ſuch practice is condemned by Lord Hale, Mr Hawkins, and the beſt authorities both among the Engliſh and Scotch lawyers. However, in caſe of a complaint, and oath made of goods ſtolen, and that the party ſuſpects that thoſe goods are in a particular houſe, and ſhows the</p></body></text></TEI>