<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:54:07Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>during the minority of her ſon. For a remedy of preſent evils, one year’s truce and a day longer was yielded unto; in which time he had leiſure to proſecute his deſigns againſt France, without fear of being diſturbed or diverted by the incurſions and inroads of the Scots upon his borders.”</p><p>Thus far Drummond: but though Henry might grant this time to his ſiſter’s intreaty, yet it certainly did not become a national meaſure; for it appears by a letter dated two years after, from the Scots council to the king of France, publiſhed by Rymer, that the Scots never had deſired a truce. So far from that, the French influence, joined to a deſire of revenge, remained ſo ſtrong in the kingdom, that after the meeting of the parliament, ſome of the members were ſo violent as to propoſe a renewal of the war. This motion was indeed over-ruled by the more moderate part of the aſſembly: but they could not be brought to make any advances towards Henry for a peace; and every day was now big with public calamity, which ſeems to have gathered ſtrength while the queen was in child-bed. The archbiſhopric of St Andrew’s being vacant, it was offered by univerſal conſent to Elphinſton biſhop of Aberdeen; but being now old and infirm, he declined it. Three competitors for that high dignity then appeared. The firſt was Gawin Douglas, who was then abbot of Aberbrothwic, to which he was preſented by the queen upon her recovery (having been brought to bed of a ſon) the very day before her marriage with his nephew the earl of Angus: and upon the death of biſhop Elphinſton in November following, ſhe preſented him likewiſe to the archbiſhopric of St Andrew’s. The ſecond competitor was John Hepburn, prior of St Andrew’s; a bold, avaricious, reſtleſs, but  ſhrewd and ſenſible prieſt. By his office he had received the rents of the ſee during its vacancy; and having prevailed with the canons, on pretence of ancient privileges, to elect him archbiſhop, without regard to the nomination either of the queen or pope, he drove Douglas’s ſervants from the caſtle of St Andrew’s, of which they had taken poſſeſſion. The third and moſt powerful competitor was Forman biſhop of Moray in Scotland, and archbiſhop of Bourges in France, a dignity to which he had been raiſed for his public ſervices. He had in his intereſt not only the duke of Albany (ſon to the traitor duke) firſt prince of the blood, but alſo the court of Rome itſelf; and having received the pope’s bull and nomination to the dignity, he was conſidered by the Scotch clergy in general, and by the principal tenants and dependents upon the ſee, as the legal archbiſhop.</p><p>The preference given to Forman diſcouraged Douglas from purſuing his pretenſions; but Hepburn, being supported by the clan of his own name and by the Humes, made ſo formidable a head againſt his rivals, that none could be found daring enough to publiſh the papal bull in favour of Forman. The friends of the latter, however, having intimated to the earl of Hume, that his credit at the court of Rome could eaſily procure the rich abbey of Coldingham for his younger brother, the earl put himſelf at the head of his followers, and, notwithſtanding all the oppoſition given by the Hepburns, he proclaimed the pope’s bull over the croſs of Edinburgh. This daring action plainly proved that the earl of Hume had more power than</p><p>the queen-regent herſelf; but Hepburn s reſolution, and the greatneſs of his friends, obliged Forman to agree to a compromiſe. Hepburn was advanced to the ſee of Moray, without accounting for the revenues of the archbiſhopric, which he had received during its vacancy; and he gave Forman a preſent of three thouſand crowns, to be divided among his friends and followers.</p><p>In April 1514, the poſthumous ſon, of whom the queen had been delivered in Stirling caſtle, was by the biſhop of Caithneſs baptized Alexander. On the 6th of Auguſt this year ſhe was married to the earl of Angus; than which nothing could be accounted more impolitic. She had neither conſulted her brother nor the ſtates of Scotland in the match; and by her having accepted of a huſband, ſhe in fact reſigned all claim to the regency under the late king’s will. The Douglaffes did not diſpute her having diveſted herſelf of the regency: but they affirmed, that the ſtates might lawfully reinſtate her in it; and that the peace of the kingdom required it, as it was the only meaſure that could preſerve the happy tranquillity which then ſubſiſted between Scotland and England. The earl of Hume put himſelf at the head of the oppoſition to this proposal. He knew that he had enemies, and he dreaded that the farther aggrandizement of Angus muſt weaken his intereſt on the borders. He was joined by a number of the young nobility, who, though otherwiſe divided, united againſt Angus. In ſhort, the general opinion was, that the Douglaſſes were already too great; and that ſhould the queen be reinſtated in the regency, they muſt be abſolute within the kingdom, and engroſs all places oſ power and profit. It was added by the earl of Hume, that he had, out of reſpectto 'the late king’s memory, ſubmitted to the queen’s government; and that, now ſhe had made a voluntary abdication of it by her marriage, it ought not to be renewed.</p><p>After ſome deliberations, the duke of Albany was choſen regent. He was a man poſſeſſed of all the qualities requiſite for a good governor; nor did he deceive the expectations of the public. On his arrival at Glaſgow, he took upon him the titles of earl of March, Marr, Garioch, lord of Annandale, and of the iſle of Man, regent and protector of the kingdom of Scotland. On his arrival at Edinburgh he was received in form by the three eſtates of the kingdom, and the queen had met him at ſome diſtance from the town. The parliament then reſumed its ſeſſion, and the three eſtates took an oath of obedience, till the king, then an infant of four years old, ſhould arrive at the years of maturity.</p><p>The firſt thing at which the regent aimed, was the conciliating the differences amongſt the various contending families in the kingdom; at the ſame time that he ſuppreſſed ſome daring robbers, one oſ whom is ſaid to have had no fewer than 800 attendants in his infamous proſeſſion. So great was his love of good order and decency, that he puniſhed the lord Drummond with the loſs of his eſtate for having ſtruck Lyon king at arms, whoſe perſon, as the firſt herald in Scotland, ought to have been held ſacred. Nay, it was at the eameſt felicitation of Lyon himſelf. and many of the chief nobility, that a greater puniſhment was not inflicted. However, the forfeiture was afterwards</p></body></text></TEI>