<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-14T17:56:42Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>fully ſhewn that all theſe diverſities may be accounted for by natural cauſes. It has
                been reckoned a great difficulty to explain how foſſil ſhells were introduced into
                the bowels of the earth; but the deluge explains this fact better than all the
                romantic theories of philoſophers. It is impoſſible to account for the origin of
                ſuch a variety of languages in a more ſatisfactory manner than is done in the
                account of the confuſion of tongues which took place at Babel. It would be no eaſy
                matter to ſhew why the ſea of Sodom is ſo different from every other ſea on the
                globe which has yet been explored, if we had not poſſeſſed the ſcriptural account of
                the miraculous deſtructiou of Sodom and Gomorrah. It is ſaturated with bitumen and
                ſalt, and contains no fiſhes. Theſe are very Angular facts, which have been fully
                eſtabliſhed by late travellers. The book of Geneſis, too, has been treated with
                contempt, becauſe it makes the world leſs ancient than is neceſſary to ſupport the
                theories of modern philoſophers, and becauſe it is difficult to reconcile the
                chronologies of ſeveral nations with the opinion that the world is not above 6000 or
                7000 years old. The Chaldeans, in the time of Cicero, reckoned up 470,000 years. The
                Egyptians pretend that they have records extending 50,000 years back; and the
                Hindoos go beyond all bounds of probability, carrying back their chronology,
                according to Halhed, more than 7,000,000 of years.</p>
            <p>An attempt has been made by M. Bailly, lately mayor of Paris, to reconcile theſe
                magnified calculations with the chronology of the Septuagint, which is juſtly
                preferred to the Hebrew. (See <hi rend="smallcaps">Septuagint.) </hi>He informs us,
                that the Hindoos, as well as the Chaldeans and Egyptians, had years of arbitrary
                determination. They had months of 15 days, and years of 60 days, or two months. A
                month is a night and day of the patriarchs; a year is a night and day of the gods;
                four thouſand years of the gods are as many hundred years of men. By attention to
                ſuch modes of computation, the age of the world will be found very nearly the ſame
                in the writings of Moſes, and in the calculations and traditions of the Bramins.
                With theſe alſo we have a remarkable coincidence with the Perſian chronology. Bailly
                has eſtabliſhed theſe remarkable epochas from the Creation to the Deluge.</p>
            <p>The Septuagint gives 2256 years.</p>
            <p>The Chaldeans: 2222</p>
            <p>The Egyptians: 2340</p>
            <p>The Perſians: 2000</p>
            <p>The Hindoos: 2000</p>
            <p>The Chineſe: 2300</p>
            <p>The ſame author has alſo ſhewn the Angular coincidence of the age of the world as
                given by four diſtinct and diſtantly ſituated people.</p>
            <p>The ancient Egyptians: 5544 years.</p>
            <p>The Hindoos: 5502</p>
            <p>The Perſians: 5501</p>
            <p>The Jews, according to Joſephus: 5555</p>
            <p>Having made theſe few remarks, to ſhew that the facts recorded in Geneſis are not
                inconſiſtent with truth, we ſhall now, by a few obſervations, confirm the evidence,
                from teſtimony, that Moſes was the author, and anſwer the objections that ſeem
                ſtrongeſt.</p>
            <p>There ariſes a great probability, from the book of Geneſis itſelf, that the author
                lived near the time of Joſeph; for as we advance towards the end of that book,</p>
            <p>the facts gradually become more minute. The materials of the antediluvian hiſtory are
                very ſcanty. The account of Abraham is more complete; but the hiſtory of Jacob and
                his family is ſtill more fully detailed. This is indeed the caſe with every hiſtory.
                In the early part, the relation is very ſhort and general; but when the hiſtorian
                approaches his own time, his materials accumulate. It is certain, too, that the book
                of Geneſis muſt have been written before the reſt of the Pentateuch; for the
                alluſions in the laſt four books to the hiſtory of Abraham, of Iſaac, and Jacob, are
                very frequent. The ſimplicity of the ſtyle ſhows it to be one of the moſt ancient of
                the ſacred books; and perhaps its ſimilarity to the ſtyle of Moſes would determine a
                critic to aſcribe it to him. It will be allowed, that no man was better qualified
                than Moſes to compoſe the hiſtory of his anceſtors. He was learned in all the wiſdom
                of the Egyptians, the moſt enlightened nation of his time, and he had the beſt
                opportunities of obtaining accurate information. The ſhort account of the
                antediluvian world could eaſily be remembered by Abraham, who might obtain it from
                Shem, who was his contemporary. To Shem it might be conveyed by Methufelah, who was
                340 years old when Adam died. From Abraham to Moſes, the interval was leſs than 400
                years. The ſplendid promiſes made to that patriarch would certainly be carefully
                communicated to each generation, with the concomitant facts: and thus the hiſtory
                might be conveyed to Moſes by the moſt diſtinguiſhed perſons. The accounts
                reſpecting Jacob and his ſon Joſeph might be given to Moſes by his grandfather
                Kohath, who muſt have been born long before the deſcent to Egypt; and Kohath might
                have heard all the facts reſpecting Abraham and Iſaac from Jacob himſelf. Thus we
                can eaſily point out how Moſes might derive the materials of the book of Geneſis,
                and eſpecially of the laſt 38 chapters, from the moſt authentic ſource.</p>
            <p>It will now be neceſſary to conſider very ſhortly the objections that have been
                ſuppoſed to prove that Geneſis could not have been written by Moſes. 1. It is
                objected, that the author of the firſt chapters of Geneſis muſt have lived in
                Meſopotamia, as he diſcovers a knowledge of the rivera that watered Paradiſe, of the
                cities Babylon, Erech, Reſen, and Calneh; of the gold of Piſon; of the bdellium and
                onyx ſtore. But if he could not derive this knowledge from the wiſdom of the
                Egyptians, which is far from being improbable, he might ſurely obtain it by
                tradition from Abraham, who was born and brought up beyond the Euphrates. 2<hi
                    rend="italic">.</hi> In Geneſis xiv. 14. it is ſaid, Abraham pursued the four
                confederate kings to Dan, yet that name was not given till after the conqueſt of
                Paleſtine@@*. We anſwer, this might be inſerted by a tranſcriber. But ſuch a
                ſuppoſition is not neceſſary; for though we are told in the book of Judges that a
                city originally called Laiſh received then the name of Dan, this does not prove that
                Laiſh was the ſame city with the Dan which is mentioned in Geneſis. The ſame anſwer
                may be given to the objection which is brought from Geneſis xxxv. 21. where the
                tower of Edar is mentioned, which the objectors ſay was the name of a tower over one
                of the gates of Jeruſalem. But the tower of Edar ſignifies the tower of the flocks,
                which in the paſtoral country of Canaan might be a very common name. 3. The moſt
                formidable objection is derived from theſe two paſſages, Gen. xii. 6.</p>
            <p>@@@ [m]* Judges chap. xviii. 22.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
