<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:55:51Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>lizabeth, proteſted that he never meant to depart from the fidelity which he owed to her; and that it was his fixed reſolution to have applied for her conſent to his marriage with the queen of Scots. In return, ſhe ordered him to repair to her court at Windſor; and, as he appeared to be irreſolute, a meſſenger was diſpatched to take him into cuſtody. He was firſt confined to the houſe of Paul Wentworth, at Burnham, in the neighbourhood of Windſor, and then committed to the Tower. The earls of Pembroke and Arundel, the lord Lumley, Sir Nicholas Throgmorton, and the biſhop of Roſs, were alſo apprehended and confined.</p><p>Elizabeth, amidſt the ferment of her inquietudes, forgot not to gratify her revenge by inſulting the queen of Scots. The name of Mary was ſufficient to convulſe her with anger. The earl of Huntingdon, who affected to have pretenſions to the crown of England that were preferable to thoſe of the Scottiſh princeſs, was joined with the earl of Shrewſhury in the office of guarding her. His inſtructions were rigorous, and he was diſpoſed to exceed them. The earl of Shrewſbury conſidered it as an indignity to have an aſſociate who was a declared enemy to his charge, who had an intereſt in her death, and who was remarkable for a natural ferocity of diſpoſition. Mary exclaimed againſt the indelicacy and rudeneſs of Elizabeth, and proteſted that all her intentions were commendable and innocent. Huntingdon took a delight in her ſufferings. He ranſacked her coffers with a view of making diſcoveries; but her prudence had induced her to deſtroy all the evidences of her tranſactions with the duke of Norfolk; and the officious aſſiduity of this jailor was only rewarded with two cyphers which he could not comprehend. The domeſtics whom ſhe favoured were ſuſpected and diſmiſſed. Her train of attendants was diminiſhed. An unrelenting watch was kept upon her. No couriers were allowed to carry her diſpatches. No meſſengers were admitted to her preſence; and all the letters from her friends were ordered to be intercepted, and to be conveyed to the queen of England.</p><p>The proceedings of the convention at Perth were afflicting to Elizabeth, to Mary, and to the duke of Norfolk. In the former they created ſuſpicions of the regent; and they were a certain annunciation to the latter, that he was reſolved to ſupport himſelf in the government of Scotland. Uncertain rumours had reached Elizabeth of the interviews he had held with Norfolk in the buſineſs of the marriage. Her ſurpriſe and indignation were infinite. Mr Wood, who brought from the regent his anſwer to her letter, was treated with diſreſpect. Secretary Cecil diſpatched inſtructions to the lord Hunſdon, the governor of Berwick, to watch his operations with a jealous eye. Elizabeth, by a ſpecial envoy, required from him an explanation of his ambiguous carriage. The regent, true to his intereſts, apologized to her for his connections with the duke of Norfolk, by laying open the deſign of that nobleman to cut him off, in his way to Scotland, by a full communication of whatever had paſſed between them in relation to Mary, and by offers of an unlimited ſubmiſſion and obedience.</p><p>While the duke of Norfolk was carrying on his intrigues with Mary, the ſcheme of an inſurrection for her deliverance was advancing under the direction of the earls of Northumberland and Weſtmoreland. Motives of religion were the chief foundation of this conſpiracy; and the more zealous Catholics over England were concerned in it. Mary, however, by the advice of the duke of Norfolk, who was afraid of her matching with a foreign prince, did not enter into it with cordiality. It advanced notwithſtanding; and the agents of the pope were laviſh of exhortations and donatives. The duke of Alva, by the order of his maſter the king of Spain, encouraged the conſpirators with the offer of 20,000 men from the Netherlands; and, under the pretence of adjuſting commercial diſputes, he ſent into England Chiapini Vitelli marquis of Celona, an officer of ability, that he might be at hand, and prepare to take the command of them.—- The report of an inſurrection was univerſal. Elizabeth kept an army of 15,000 men near her perſon. The queen of Scots was removed to Coventry, a place of great ſtrength; and if a ſuperior and commanding force ſhould appear before it, her ferocious keeper, it is ſaid, had orders to aſſaſſinate her. Repeated commands were ſent to the earls of Northumberland and Weſtmoreland, to repair to court. But the impriſonment of the duke of Norfolk and his friends had ſtruck a panic into them. They conceived that their conſpiracy was diſcovered; and putting themſelves at the head of their followers, they iſſued their manifeſto. The reſtoration of Popery, the eſtabliſhment of the titles of Mary to the Engliſh crown, and the reformation of abuſes in the commonwealth, were the avowed objects of their enterpriſe. But they had embarked in a buſineſs for which they were altogether unequal. Their efforts were feeble and deſultory. The duke of Alva forgot his promiſes. Wherever the peace was diſturbed by inſurgents, there were troops to oppoſe them. The vigilance of Elizabeth diſconcerted with eaſe the operations of men whom no reſources or popularity could have conducted to greatneſs, and who could neither conquer nor die. The earl of Weſtmoreland, after concealing himſelf for ſome time in Scotland, effected an eſcape into Flanders, where he paſſed a miſerable and uſeleſs exiſtence; and the earl of Northumberland being taken by the regent, was impriſoned in the caſtle of Lochleven.</p><p>As the fury of Elizabeth abated, her reſentment to the duke of Norfolk loſt its power; and ſhe failed not to diſtinguiſh between the intrigues of an honourable ambition, and the practices of an obſtinate ſuperſtition. It was the reſult of the examination of this nobleman, and of the confeſſions of the other priſoners, that Lethington had ſchemed the buſineſs of the marriage, and that the earl of Murray had encouraged it; that her conſent was underſtood to be neceſſary to its completion; and that Mary herſelf had warmly recommended the expedient of conſulting her pleaſure. Upon receiving proper admonitions, the earls of Pembroke, Arundel, the lord Lumley, Sir Nicholas Throgmorton, and the biſhop of Roſs, were releaſed from confinement; and, after a more tedious impriſonment, the duke of Norfolk himſelf was admitted to his liberty. This favour, however, was not extended to him till he had not only ſubmiſſively acknowledged his preſumption in the buſineſs of the marriage; but had fully revealed whatever had paſſed between Mary and him, and ſolemnly engaged himſelf never more to think of this al-</p></body></text></TEI>