<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:54:50Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ſummon Leith to ſurrender; but meeting with defiance inſtead of ſubmiſſion, it was reſolved to take the town by ſcalade. "For this ſervice ladders were framed in the church of St Giles; a buſineſs which, interrupting the preachers in the exerciſe of public worſhip, made them prognoſticate misfortune and miſearriage to the Congregation. In the diſpleaſure of the preachers, the common people found a ſource of complaint; and the emiſſaries of the queen-dowager acting with indefatigable induſtry to divide her adverſaries, and to ſpread chagrin and diſſatisfaction among them, diſcontent, animoſity, and terror, came to prevail to a great degree. The duke of Chatelherault diſcouraged many by his example. Defection from the Proteſtants added ſtrength to the queen-dowager. The moſt ſecret deliberations of the confederated lords were revealed to her. The ſoldiery were clamorous for pay; and it was very difficult, to procure money to ſatisfy their claims. Attempts to ſoothe and appeaſe them, diſcovering their conſequence, engendered mutinies. They put to death a domeſtic of the earl of Argyle, who endeavoured to compoſe them to order: they inſulted ſeveral perſons of rank who diſcovered a solicitude to pacify them; and they even ventured to declare, that, for a proper reward, they were ready to ſuppreſs the reformation, and to re-eſtabliſh the maſs.</p><p>It was abſolutely neceſſary to give ſatisfaction to the Proteſtant ſoldiers. The lords and gentlemen of the Congregation collected a conſiderable ſum among them; but it was not equal to the preſent exigency. The avarice of many taught them to withhold what they could afford, and the poverty of others did not permit them to indulge their generoſity. It was reſolved, that each nobleman ſhould ſurrender his ſilver- plate to be ſtruck into money. By the addreſs, however, of the queen-dowager, the officers of the mint were bribed to conceal, or to convey to a diſtance, the ſtamps and inſtruments of coinage. A gloomy deſpair gave diſquiet to the Congregation, and threatened their ruin. Queen Elizabeth, with whole miniſters the confederated lords maintained a correſpondence at this time, had frequently promiſed them her aſſiſtance; but they could not now wait the event of a deputation to the court of England. In an extremity ſo preſſing, they therefore applied for a ſum of money to Sir Ralph Sadler and Sir James Croft, the governors of Berwick; and Cockburn of Ormiſton, who was entruſted with this commiſſion, obtaincd from them an aid of 4000 crowns. Traitors, however, in the councils of the Congregation, having informed the queen-dowager of his errand and expedition, the earl of Bothwel, by her order, intercepted him upon his return, diſcomfited his retinue, and made a prize of the Engliſh ſubſidy.</p><p>To rouſe the ſpirit of the party, an attack was projected upon Leith, and ſome pieces of artillery were planted againſt it. But before any charge could be made, the French ſoldiers ſallied out to give battle to the troops of the Congregation, poſſeſſed themſelves of their cannon, and drove them back to Edinburgh. A report that the victors had entered this city with the fugitives, filled it with diſorder and diſmay. The earl, of Argyle and his Highlanders haſtened to recover the honour of the day, and haraſſed the French in their retreat. This petty conflict, while it elated the queen-dowager, ſerved to augment the deſpondence of the Proteſtants.</p><p>Vain of their proweſs, the French made a new ſally from Leith, with a view to intercept a ſupply of proviſions and ſtores for the Congregation. The earl of Arran and the lord James Stuart advanced to attack them, and obliged them to retire. But purſuing them with too much heat, a freſh body of French troops made its appearance. It was prudent to retreat, but difficult. An obſtinate reſiſtance was made. It was the object of the French to cut off the ſoldiery of the Congregation from Edinburgh, and by theſe means to divide the ſtrength of that ſtation. The earl of Arran and the lord James Stuart had occaſion for all their addreſs and courage. Though they were able, however, to effect their eſcape, their loſs was conſiderable, and the victory was manifeſtly on the ſide of their adverſaries.</p><p>About this time "William Maitland of Lethington, ſecretary to the queen-dowager, withdrew ſecretly from Leith, and joined himſelf to the confederated nobles. He had been diſguſted with the jealouſies of the French counſellors, and was expoſed to danger from having embraced the doctrines of the reformed. His reception was cordial, and correſponded to the opinion entertained of his wiſdom and experience. He was ſkilled in buſineſs, adorned with literature, and accuſtomed to reflection. But as yet it was not known, that his want of integrity was in proportion to the greatneſs of his talents.</p><p>The acceſſion of this ſtateſman to their party could not conſole the lords of the Congregation for the un- promiſing aſpect of their affairs. The two diſcomfitures they had received ſunk deeply into the minds of their followers. Thoſe who affected prudence, retired privately from a cauſe which they accounted to be deſperate; and the timorous fled with precipitation. The wailings and diſtruſt of the brethren were melancholy and infectious; and by exciting the ridicule and ſcorn of the partiſans of the queen-dowager, were augmented the more. A diſtreſs not to be comforted ſeemed to have invaded the Proteſtants; and the aſſociated nobles conſented to abandon the capital. A little after midnight, they retired from Edinburgh; and ſo great was the panic which prevailed, that they marched to Stirling without any ſtop or intermiſſion.</p><p>John Knox, who had accompanied the Congregation to Stirling, anxious to recover their unanimity and courage, addreſſed them from the pulpit. He repreſented their misfortunes as the conſequences of their ſins; and intreating them to remember the goodneſs of their cauſe, aſſured them in the end of joy, honour, and victory. His popular eloquence correſponding to all their warmeſt wiſhes, diffuſed ſatisfaction and cheerfulneſs. They paſſed from deſpair to hope. A council was held, in which the confederated nobles determined to ſolicit, by a formal embaſſy, the aid of queen Elizabeth. Maitland of Lethington, and Robert Melvil, were choſen to negociate this important tranſaction; and they received the fulleſt inſtructions concerning the ſtate and difficulties of the Congregation, the tyrannical deſigns of the queen-dowager, and the danger which threatened England from the union of Scotland with France.</p><p>The queen of England having maturely conſidered</p></body></text></TEI>