<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:54:34Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>and then ſet fire to them. A cruel devaſtation enſued in the ſurrounding villages and country, and an immenſe booty was conveyed on board the Engliſh fleet. But, while an extreme terror was everywhere excited, the earl of Hartford re-imbarked a part of his troops, and ordered the remainder to march with expedition to the frontiers of England.</p><p>The regent, aſſiſted by cardinal Beaton and the earls of Huntley, Argyle, Bothwell, and Murray, was active, in the mean time, to collect an army, and to provide for the ſecurity of the kingdom. He felt, therefore, the greateſt ſurpriſe on being relieved ſo unexpectedly from the moſt imminent danger; and an expedition, conducted with ſo little diſcernment, did not advance the meaſures of Henry VIII. To accompliſh the marriage of the young queen with the prince of Wales, to poſſeſs himſelf of her perſon, or to achieve a conqueſt over Scotland, were all circumſtances apparently within the reach of the Engliſh commander: and yet, in the moment of victory, he neglected to proſecute his advantages; and having inflamed the animoſities of the Scottiſh nation, by a diſplay of the paſſions and cruelty of his maſter, left them to recover from their diſaſter, and to improve in their reſources.</p><p>The earl of Lenox, taking the opportunity of the Engliſh fleet, went to conſult with Henry VIII. upon the deſperate ſtate of his affairs. He renewed his engagements with this monarch; and received in marriage the lady Margaret Douglas, with poſſeſſions in England Soon after, he arrived in the frith of Clyde, with 18 ſhips and 600 ſoldiers, that he might ſecure the caſtle of Dumbarton, and employ himſelf in plundering and devaſtation. But George Stirling, to whom the caſtle was intruſted, refuſed to ſurrender it; and even obliged him to reimbark his troops. After engaging in a few petty incurſions and ſkirmiſhes, he returned to England.</p><p>In 1544, Henry conſented to a truce; and Scotland, after having ſuffered the miſeries of war, was subjected to the horrors of perſecution. The regent had procured an act of parliament for the perſecution of the reformed; and the cardinal, to draw to himſelf an additional ſplendour and power, had obtained from the pope the dignity of legate <hi rend="italic">à latere.</hi> A viſitation of his own dioceſe appeared to him the moſt proper method of commencing the propoſed extirpation of hereſy; and he carried with him in his train the regent, and many perſons of diſtinction, to aſſiſt in his judicatories, and to ſhare in his diſgrace.</p><p>In the town of Perth a great many perſons were accuſed and condemned. The moſt trifling offences were regarded as atrocious crimes, and made the ſubjects of proſecution and puniſhment. Robert Lamb was hanged for affirming that the invocation of faints had no merit to fave. William Anderſon, James Reynold, and James Finlayſon, ſuffered the fame death, for having abuſed an image of St Francis, by putting horns upon his head. James Hunter, having kept their company, was found to be equally guilty, and puniſhed in the fame manner. Helen Stirke, having refuſed, when in labour, to invoke the aſſiſtance of the Virgin, was drowned in a pool of water. Many of the burgesses of Perth, being ſuſpected of hereſy, were ſent into baniſhment; and the lord Ruthven, the provoſt, was upon the ſame account diſmiſſed from his office.</p><p>The cardinal was ſtrenuous in perſecuting hereſy in other parts of his dioceſe. But the diſcontents and clamour attending the executions of men of inferior ſtation were now loſt in the fame of the martyrdom of George Wiſhart; a perſon who, while he was reſpectable by his birth, was highly eminent from the opinion entertained of his capacity and endowments. The hiſtorians of the Proteſtant perſuaſion have ſpoken of this reformer in terms of the higheſt admiration. They extol his learning as extenſive, inſiſt on the extreme candour of his diſpoſition, and aſcribe to him the utmost purity of morals. But while the ſtrain of their panegyric is expoſed to ſuſpicion from its exceſs, they have ventured to impute to him the ſpirit of prophecy; ſo that we must neceſſarily receive their eulogiums with ſome abatement. It may be ſufficient to affirm, that Mr Wiſhart was the moſt eminent preacher who had hitherto appeared in Scotland. His mind was certainly cultivated by reflection and ſtudy, and he was amply poſſeſſed of thoſe abilities and qualifications which awaken and agitate the paſſions of the people. His miniſtry had been attended with the moſt flattering ſucceſs; and his courage to encounter danger grew with his reputation. The day before he was apprehended, he ſaid to John Knox, who attended him; “I amt weary of the world, since I perceive that men are weary of God.” He had already reconciled himſelf to that terrible death which awaited him. He was found in the houſe of Cockburn of Ormiſton, in Eaſt Lothian; who refuſing to deliver him to the ſervants of the regent, the earl of Bothwell, the ſheriff of the county, required that he ſhould be intruſted to his care, and promiſed that no injury ſhould be done to him But the authority of the regent and his counſellors obliged the earl to ſurrender his charge. He was conveyed to the cardinal’s caſtle at St Andrew’s, and his trial was hurried on with precipitation. The cardinal and the clergy proceeding in it without the concurrence of the ſecular power, adjudged him to be burnt alive. In the circumſtances of his execution there appears a deliberate and moſt barbarous cruelty. When led out to the  ſtake, he was met by prieſts, who, mocking his condition, called upon him to pray to the virgin, that ſhe might intercede with her Son for mercy to him. “Forbear to tempt me, my brethern,” was his mild reply to them. A black coat of linen was put upon him by one executioner, and bags of powder were faſtened to his body by another. Some pieces of ordnance were pointed to the place of execution. He ſpoke to the ſpectators, intreating them to remember that he was to die for the true goſpel of Chriſt. Fire was communicated to the faggots. From a balcony in a tower of his caſtle, which was hung with tapeſtry, the cardinal and the prelates, reclining upon rich cuſhions, beheld the inhuman ſcene. This inſolent triumph, more than all his afflictions, affected the magnanimity of the ſufferer. He exclaimed, that the enemy, who ſo proudly ſolaced himſelf, would periſh in a few days, and be expoſed ignominiouſly in the place which he now occupied.</p><p>Cardinal Beaton took a pleaſure in receiving the congratulations of the clergy upon a deed, which, it was thought, would fill the enemies of the church with terror. But the indignation of the people was more excited than their fears. All ranks of men were dis-</p></body></text></TEI>