<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:55:41Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>verbal obedience of the people had enſued, and a ſteady adminiſtration of juſtice had taken place: that certain perſons, however, envious of the public order and peace, had brought her out of priſon, and had engaged to ſubvert the government; that they had been diſappointed in their wicked attempts; and that it was moſt juſt and equitable, that the king and the regent ſhould be ſupported in power, in oppoſition to a rebellious and turbulent faction.</p><p>This apology, ſo imperfect, ſo impudent, and ſo irreconcileable with hiſtory, received a complete confutation from the deputies of the queen of Scots. To take arms againſt her becauſe Bothwel had her favour, was, they ſaid, a lame juſtiſication of the earl of Murray and his friends; ſince it had never been properly manifeſted to her that he was the murderer of her huſband. He had indeed been ſuſpected of this crime; but had been tried by his peers, and acquitted. His acquittal had been ratified in parliament, and had obtained the expreſs approbation of the party who were now ſo loud in accuſing him, and who had conſpired againſt her authority. Theſe rebels had even urged her to accompliſh her marriage with him, had recommended him as the fitteſt perſon to govern the realm, and had ſubſcribed a bond aſſerting his innocence, and binding themſelves to challenge and puniſh all his adverſaries and opponents. They had never, either before or after the marriage, like true ſubjects, advertiſed the queen of his guilt, till, having experience of their ſtrength, they ſecretly took arms, and inveſted her in Borthwick caſtle. The firſt mark of their diſplealure was the ſound of a trumpet in hoſtility, and the diſplay of warlike banners. She made her eſcape to Dunbar; and they returning to Edinburgh, levied troops, iſſued proclamations, took the field againſt her, under the pretence of delivering her from his tyranny, and got poſſeſſion of her perſen. She was willing to prevent the effuſion of blood, and was very far from preferring his impunity to her honour. Kirkaldy of Grange, in obedience to inſtructions from them, deſired her to cauſe him to retire, and invited her to paſs to them under the promiſe of being ſerved and obeyed as their ſovereign. She conſented, and Kirkaldy taking Bothwel by the hand, recommended it to him to depart, and aſſured him that no man would purſue him. It was by their own contrivance that he fled; and it was in their power to have taken him; but they ſhowed not the ſmalleſt deſire to make him their priſoner. He remained, too, for ſome time in the kingdom, and was unmoleſted by them; and it was not till he was upon the ſeas that they affected to go in ſearch of him. When ſhe ſurrendered herſelf in the fight of their army, the earl of Morton ratified the ſtipulations of Kirkaldy, made obeiſance to her, in their names, and promiſed her all the ſervice and honour which had ever been paid to any of her predeceſſors. They were not ſlaves, however, to their engagements. They carried her to Edinburgh, but did not lodge her in her palace. She was committed to the houſe of a burgeſs, and treated with the vileſt indignities. She indeed broke out into menaces, and threatened them; nor was. this a matter either of blame or of wonder. But it was utterly falſe that ſhe had ever made any offer to give away her crown, if ſhe might poſſeſs Bothwel. In the midſt of her ſufferings, ſhe had even required them by ſecretary Maitland to ſpecify their complaints, and beſought them to allow her to appear in parliament, and to join and aſſiſt in ſeeking a remedy to them from the wiſdom of the three eſtates This overture, however, ſo ſalutary and ſubmiſſive, they abſolutely rejected.— They were animated by purpoſes of ambition, and had not in view a relief from grievances. They forced her from her capital in the night, and impriſoned her in Lochleven; and there, they affirm, being exhauſted with the toils of government and the languors of ſickneſs, ſhe, without conſtraint or ſolicitation, reſigned her crown to her ſon, and appointed the earl of Murray to be regent during his minority. This indeed was to aſſume an unlimited power over facts; but the truth could neither be concealed, nor overturned, nor palliated. She was in the vigour of youth, unaſſailed by maladies, and without any infirmity that could induce her to ſurrender the government of her kingdom. Nor was it unknown to them that the earl of Athol and the barons Tullibardin and Lethington, principal men of their council, diſpatched Sir Robert Melvil to her with a ring and preſents, with a recommendation to ſubſcribe whatever papers ſhould be laid before her, as the only means in her power to ſave her life, and with an aſſurance that what ſhe did under captivity could not operate any injury to her. Melvil, too, communicated to her an intimation in writing from Sir Nicholas  Throgmorton, which gave her the ſame advice and the ſame aſſurance. To Sir Nicholas Throgmorton ſhe ſent an anſwer, informing him that ſhe would follow his counſel; and enjoining him to declare to his miſtreſs her hapleſs ſtate and that her reſignation of her crown was conſtrained. Nor did this ambaſſador neglect her commiſſion; and it was a popular perſuaſion that Elizabeth would have marched an army to her relief, if ſhe had not been intimidated by the threat of the rebels, that the blood of the queen of Scots would be the wages of her ſoldiers. It was alſo not to be contradicted, that when the lord Lindſay preſented to his ſovereign the inſtruments of reſignation, he menaced her with a cloſer priſon and a ſpeedy death if ſhe ſhould refuſe to ſubſeribe them. It was under an extreme terror, and with many tears, that ſhe put her name to them. She did not conſider them as her deeds; did not read them; and proteſted, that when ſhe was at liberty, ſhe would diſavow ſubſcriptions which had been extorted from her. Even Douglas, the keeper of Lochleven, could not endure to be a witneſs of the violence employed againſt her. He departed out of her preſence, that he might not ſee her ſurrender her rights againſt her will; and he fought and obtained from her a certificate, that he was not acceſſory to this compulſion and outrage. Nor did it conſiſt with the ſlighteſt probability or reaſon, that ſhe would, of her own will and accord, execute a reſignation of her royal eſtate, and retain no proviſion for her future maintenance. Yet by theſe extraordinary deeds, the condition to which ſhe was reduced was moſt miſerable and wretched. For no portion whatever of her revenue was referred to her, and no ſecurity of any kind was granted either for her liberty or her life. As to the coronation of the prince, it could have no validity, as being founded in a pretended and forced reſignation. It was alſo defective in its form; for there were in Scotland more than an hundred earls, biſhops, and lords; and of theſe the whole, or at leaſt the major part, ought</p></body></text></TEI>