<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:55:03Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>heir to the crown of England, and Elizabeth preſſed Mary to confirm the treaty of Edinburgh. With thi3 the latter could not comply, as it would in fact have been renouncing for ever the title to that crown for which ſhe was ſo earneſtly contending. Endleſs negociations were the conſequence, and the hatred of Elizabeth to Mary continually increaſed. This year the queen of Scotland amuſed herſelf by making a circuit through part of her dominions. From Edinburgh ſhe proceeded to Stirling; from thence to Perth, Dundee, and St Andrew’s. Though received everywhere with the greateſt acclamations and marks of affection, ſhe could not but remark the rooted aversion which had univerſally taken place againſt Popery; and upon her return to Edinburgh, her attention was called to an exertion of this zeal, which may be conſidered as highly characteriſtic of the times. The magiſtrates of this city, after their election, enacted rules, according to cuſtom, for the government of their borough. By one of theſe acts, which they publiſhed by proclamation, they commanded all monks, friars, and prieſts, together with all adulterers and fornicators, to depart from the town and its limits within 24 hours, under the pains of correction and puniſhment. Mary, juſtly interpreting this exertion of power to be an uſurpation of the royal authority, and a violation of order, displaced the magiſtrates, commanded the citizens to elect others in their room, and granted by proclamation a plenary indulgence to all her ſubjects not convicted of any crime, to repair to and remain in her capital at their pleaſure.</p><p>Beſides theſe diſturbances on account of religion, the kingdom was now in confuſion on another account. The long continuance of civil wars had left a proneneſs to tumults and inſurrections everywhere; and thefts, rapine, and licentiouſneſs of every kind, threatened to ſubvert the foundations of civil ſociety. Mary made conſiderable preparations for the ſuppreſſion of theſe diſorders, and appointed the lord James Stuart her chief juſtſeiar and lieutenant. He was to hold two criminal courts, the one at Jedburgh, and the other at Dumfries. To aſſiſt his operations againſt the banditti, who who were armed, and often aſſociated into bodies, a military force was neceſſary; but as there were at preſent neither Handing army nor regular troops in the kingdom, the county of Edinburgh, and ten others, were commanded to have their ſtrength in readineſs to aſſiſt him. The feudal tenants, and the allodial or free proprietors of theſe diſtricts, in complete armour, and with proviſions for 20 days, were appointed to be ſubſervient to the purpoſes of his commiſſion, and to obey his orders in eſtabliſhing the public tranquillity. In this expedition he was attended with his uſual ſucceſs. He deſtroyed many of the ſtrong-holds of the banditti; hanged 20 of the moſt notorious offenders; and ordered 50 more to be carried to Edinburgh, there to ſuffer the penalties of law on account of their rebellious behaviour. He entered into terms with the lord Grey and Sir John Foſter, the wardens of the Engliſh borders, for the mutual benefit of the two nations; and he commanded the chiefs of the diſorderly clans to ſubmit to the queen, and to obey her orders with regard to the ſecuring of the peace, and preventing inſurrections and depredations for the future.</p><p>In the mean time the queen was in a very diſagreeable ſituation, being ſuſpected and diſtruſted by both parties. From the conceſſions ſhe had made to the Proteſtants, the Papiſts ſuppoſed that ſhe had a deſign of renouncing their religion altogether; while, on the other hand, the Proteſtants could ſcarcely allow themselves to believe that they owed any allegiance to an idolater. Diſquiets of another kind alſo now took place. The duke of Chatelherault, having left the Catholics to join the oppoſite party, was neglected by his ſovereign. Being afraid of ſome danger to himſelf, he fortified the caſtle of Dumbarton, which he reſolved to defend; and in caſe of neceſſity to put himſelf under the protection of the queen of England.—The earl of Arran was a man of very ſlender abilities, but of boundleſs ambition. The queen’s beauty had made an impreſſion on his heart, and his ambition made him fancy himſelf the fitteſt perſon in the kingdom for her huſband. But his fanaticiſm, and the violence with which he had oppoſed the maſs, diſguſted her. He bore her diſlike with an uneaſineſs that preyed upon his intellects and diſordered them. It was even ſuppoſed that he had concerted a ſcheme to poſſeſs himſelf of her perſon by armed retainers; and the lords of her court were commanded to be in readineſs to defeat any project of this fort. The earl of Bothwel was diſtinguiſhed chiefly by his prodigalities and the licentiouneſs of his manners. The earl of Mariſchal had every thing that was honourable in his intentions, but was overwary and ſlow. The earl of Morton poſſeſſed penetration and ability, but was attached to no party or meaſures from any principles of rectitude: His own advantage and interdis were the motives which governed him. The earl of Huntley the lord chancellor, was unquiet, variable, and vindictive: His paſſions, now fermenting with violence, were ſoon to break forth in the moſt dangerous practices. The earls of Glencairn and Menteith were deeply tinctured with fanaticiſm; and their inordinate zeal for the new opinions, not leſs than their poverty, recommended them to queen Elizabeth. Her ambaſſador Randolph, adviſed her to ſecure them ſervice, by addreſſing herſelf to their neceſſities. Among courtiers of this deſcription, it was difficult for Mary to make a ſelection of miniſters in whom to confide. The conſequence and popularity of the lord James Stuart, and of Maitland of Lethington, had early pointed them out to this diſtinction; and hitherto they had acted to her ſatisfaction. They were each of eminent capacity: but the former was ſuſpected of aiming at the ſovereignty; the latter was prone to refinement and duplicity; and both were more connected with Elizabeth than became them as the miniſters and ſubjects of another ſovereign.</p><p>Beſide the policy of employing and truſting ſtateſmen who were Proteſtants, and the precaution of maintaining a firm peace with England, Mary had it alſo at heart to enrich the crown with the revenues of the ancient church. A convention of eſtates was aſſembled to deliberate upon this meaſure. The biſhops were alarmed with their perilous ſituation. It was made known to them, that the charge of the queen’s houſe- hold required an augmentation; and that as the rents of the church had flowed chiefly from the crown, it was expedient that a proper proportion of them ſhould now be reſumed to uphold its ſplendour. After long conſultations, the prelates and eſtate eccleſiaſtical, conſider-</p></body></text></TEI>