<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:54:10Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>he at laſt conſented to a prolongation of the truce for a year.</p><p>In 1517, the affairs of the regent requiring his preſence in France, he reſolved, before his departure, to remove the earl of Hume, who, as we have ſeen, alone continued to diſturb the public tranquillity. Under pretence of ſettling ſome differences which ſtill remained with England, he called a convention of the nobility; and ſent ſpecial letters to the earl of Hume and his brother to attend, on account of their great knowledge in Engliſh affairs. Both of them imprudently obeyed the ſummons, and were ſeized and executed as ſoon as they arrived at Edinburgh. But whatever occaſion there might be for this ſeverity, it loſt the affections of the people to ſuch a degree, that the regent could ſcarce get the place filled up which Lord Hume had poſſeſſed. That of lord warden of the marches he at laſt gave to his French favourite La Beaute, called by hiſtorians Sir Anthony D’Arcy. The poſt of lord chamberlain was given to Lord Fleming. Soon after this, the regent levied an army, on pretence of repreſsing ſome diſturbances on the borders. Theſe being ſpeedily quelled, he ſeized on his return upon the earl of Lenox, and forced him to deliver up his caſtle of Dumbarton; not chooſing to leave it, during his intended abſence in France, in the cuſtody of a nobleman of ſuſpected fidelity; and from ſimilar motives, he afterwards took him along with him on his departure for the continent. He then procured himſelf to be nominated ambaſſador to France, in which character he left the kingdom; having committed the government to the archbiſhops of St Andrew’s and Glaſgow, the earls of Arran, Angus, Huntley, and Argyle, with the warden D’Arcy, on whom was his chief dependence.</p><p>On the departure of the regent, the queen-mother left the Engliſh court; and arrived with a noble retinue at Berwick, on purpoſe to viſit her ſon. Here ſhe was received by her huſband; for whom ſhe had contracted an invincible aversion, either on account of his infidelities to her bed, or becauſe he had deſerted her in the manner already related. However, ſhe ſuppreſſed her reſentment for the preſent, and accompanied him to Edinburgh. Here, in conſequence of the pro- poſals made by the regent, ſhe demanded acceſs to her ſon; but was refuſed by D’Arcy. Lord Erſkine, however, who was one of thoſe to whom the care of the young king was committed, conveyed him to the caſtle of Craigmillar (where D’Arcy had no juriſdiction), on pretence that the plague was in Edinburgh; and there the queen was admitted; but this gave ſuch offence to D’Arcy, that Lord Erſkine was obliged to carry back the king to the caſtle of Edinburgh, where all further acceſs was denied to his mother. In ſhort, the behaviour of this favourite was on all occaſions ſo haughty and violent, that he rendered himſelf univerſally odious; and was at laſt murdered, with all his attendants, in his way to Dunſe, where he propoſed to hold a court of juſtice.—His death was very little regretted; yet his murderers were proſecuted with the utmoſt ſeverity, and ſeveral perſons of diſtinction declared rebels on that account.</p><p>Meanwhile, the regent was treated with high marks of diſtinction in France. The king ſhowed him the greateſt reſpect, promiſed to aſſiſt in eſtabliſhing his</p><p>authority in Scotland, and ſolemnly confirmed the ancient league between the two kingdoms. Soon after, the earl of Lenox arrived from France, with aſſurances of protection and aſſiſtance from the king, who was highly pleaſed at the zeal of the governors in puniſhing D’Arcy’s murderers; and 500 ſoldiers arrived with him, to reinforce the garriſons, eſpecially that of Dunbar.</p><p>All this time the queen-mother continued at Edinburgh, employing herſelf in attempts to procure a divorce from her huſband, under pretence of his having been previouſly contracted to another. The affairs of the kingdom again began to fall into confuſion, and many murders and commotions happened in different parts of the country. The earl of Arrah had the chief direction in the ſtate; but the earl of Angus, notwithſtanding the difference with his wife, had ſtill great intereſt, and waited every opportunity to oppoſe him. This emulation produced an encounter at Edinburgh; in which victory declared for Angus, and 72 of the routed party were killed. This ſkirmiſh was fought on the 30th of April 1519, and has been known in Scot3 hiſtory by the name of <hi rend="italic">Cleanſe the Cauſeway.</hi></p><p>On the 19th of November 1521, the regent returned from France. He found the kingdom in great diſorder. The earl of Ahgus domineered in the field, but his antagoniſts outvoted his party in the parliament. The queen-mother, who had fixed her affections on a third huſhand, hated all parties almoſt equally; but joined the duke of Albany, in hopes of his depriving the other two of their power. This happened according to her expectation; and ſhe was with the regent when he made a kind of triumphal entry into Edinburgh, attended by a number of perſens of the firſt rank.—The carl of Angus was now ſummoned to appear as a criminal; but his wife interceded for him, not out of any remains of affection, but becauſe he gave her no oppoſition in the proceſs of divorce which was depending between them.—In the mean time, Henry VIII. of England, perceiving that the Scots were entirely devoted to the French intereſt, ſent a letter full of accuſations againſt the regent, and threats againſt the whole nation, if they did not renounce that alliance. No regard being paid to theſe requiſitions, lord Dacres was ordered to proclaim upon the borders, that the Scots muſt ſtand to their peril if they did not fall in with his meaſures by the firſt of March 1522. This producing no effect, Henry ſeized the effects of all the Scots reſiding in England, and baniſhed them his dominions, after marking them, according to biſhop Leſley, with a croſs, to diſtinguiſh them from his other ſubjects. A war was the unavoidable conſequence of theſe proceedings; and, on the 30th of April, the earl of Shrewsbury, Henry’s ſteward of the houſehold, and knight of the garter, was appointed commander in chief of the army that was to act againſt the Scots; and, in the mean time, Lord Dacres made an inroad as far as Kelſo, plundering and burning wherever he came.</p><p>The regent ordered his army to rendezvous at Roſlin; but the Scots, remembering the diſaſter at Eloddon, ſhowed an extreme averſion to the war, and even told the regent to his face, that though they would defend themſelves in caſe they were attacked, they would not engage in a French quarrel. The regent remon-</p></body></text></TEI>