<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:54:56Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>vince. The houſe of Guiſe was encompaſſed with difficulties, and trembling with apprehenſions, ſo that they could not think of perſiſting in their views of diſtant conqueſts. It was neceſſary that they ſhould abandon for a time all the proud projects they had formed for the extenſion of the French monarchy. It was chiefly in the exemption from foreign wars that they could hope to ſupport their own greatneſs, and apply a remedy to the domeſtic diſturbances of France.</p><p>It appeared to Francis and Mary, that they could not treat in a direct method with the Congregation, whom they affected to conſider as rebellious ſubjects,  without derogating from their royal dignity. In negociating a peace, they therefore addreſſed themſelves to queen Elizabeth. It was by her offices and interference that they projected a reconciliation with the confederated lords, and that they meant to extinguiſh the animoſities which, with ſo much violence, had agitated the Scottiſh nation. They granted their commiſſion to John Monluc biſhop of Valence, Nicholas Pelleve biſhop of Amiens, Jacques de la Broſſe, Henry Clentin ſieur d’Oyſel, and Charles de la Rochefaucault ſieur de Randan; authoriſing them in a body, or by two of their number, to enter into accords and agreements with the queen of England. The Engliſh commiſſioners were Sir William Cecil principal ſecretary of ſtate, Nicolas Wotton dean of Canterbury and York, Sir Ralph Sadler, Sir Henry Percy, and Sir Peter Crew; and the powers of treaty were to be exerciſed by them all in conjunction, or by four, three, or two of them.</p><p>The plenipotentiaries of France, though empowered only to treat with England, were yet, by a ſeparate commiſſion, entruſted to aſſure the Congregation, that, notwithſtanding the heinous guilt incurred by them, Francis and Mary were inclined to receive them into favour, upon their repentance and return to obedience; and to abſtain for ever from all inquiry into their conduct. They had full authority, at the ſame time, by this new deed, to hear, in conjunction with the commiſſioners of Elizabeth, the complaints of the Congregation, and to grant, with their conſent, the relief which appeared to them to be the moſt proper and ſalutary.</p><p>The nobility and people of Scotland, chooſing for their repreſentatives the lord James Stuart, the lord Ruthven, and Maitland of Lethington, expreſſed their willingneſs to concur in reaſonable meaſures for the re- eſtabliſhment of the public union and tranquillity. By the mode of a formal petition, they enumerated their grievances, laid claim to a redreſs of them, and beſought an uniform protection to their conſtitution and laws. To this petition the interceſſion of queen Elizabeth effected the friendly attention of Francis and Mary; and upon a foundation concerted with ſo much propriety, Monluc and Randan, Cecil and Wotton, the acting plenipotentiaries of England and France, drew up and authenticated the celebrated deed of relief and conceſſion which does ſo much honour to the ſpirit, perſeverance, and magnanimity of the Scottiſh nation.</p><p>By this accord and agreement, Francis and Mary ſtipulated and conſented, that no French ſoldiers and no foreign troops ſhould ever be introduced into Scotland without the counſel and advice of the three eſtates. They concurred in the opinion, that the French mercenaries ſhould be ſent back into France, and that the</p><p>fortifications of Leith ſhould be demoliſhed. They agreed that commiſſioners ſhould be appointed to vint Dunbar, and to point out the works there which ought to be deſtroyed; and they bound and engaged themſelves to build no new fortreſs or place of ſtrength within the kingdom, and to repair no old one, without a parliamentary authority and fonction. They conſented to extinguiſh all debts which had been contracted for the maintenance of the French and Scotch ſoldiery in their ſervice. They appointed the eſtates of the realm to hold a parliament for the diſcuſſion of affairs of ſtate; and they obliged themſelves to conſider the acts of this aſſembly as valid and effectual in every reſpect. They confirmed the ancient law of the country, which prohibited the princes of Scotland from making peace and war without the advice of the three eſtates. It was accorded and agreed by them, that the three eſtates, in concurrence with the queen, ſhould elect a council for the adminiſtration of affairs during her majeſty’s abſence. They became bound to employ the natives of Scotland in the management of juſtice both civil and criminal, in the offices of chancellor, keeper of the ſeals, treaſurer, comptroller, and in other ſtations of a ſimilar nature; and to abſtain from the promotion of all foreigners to places of truſt and honour, and from inveſting any clergyman in the charge of affairs of the revenue. They determined to eſtabliſh an act of oblivion, and to forget and bury for ever the memory of all the late tranſactions of war and offence. It was concluded by them, that a general peace and reconciliation ſhould take place among all parties. They expreſſed their determination, that no pretence ſhould be aſſumed by them, from the late contentions, to deprive any of their ſubjects of their eſtates or offices. And they referred the reparation which might be proper to compeniate the injuries that had been ſuſtained by biſhops and eccleſiaſtics, to the judgment of the three eſtates in parliament.</p><p>Upon the ſubject of the reformation, the plenipotentiaries of England and France did not chooſe to deliberate and decide, although articles with regard to it had been preſented to them by the nobles and the people. They referred this delicate topic to the enſuing meeting of the parliament; and the leaders of the Congregation engaged, that deputies from the three eſtates ſhould repair to the king and queen, to know their intention concerning matters of ſuch high importance.</p><p>After having granted theſe conceſſions to the nobility and the people of Scotland, upon the part of their reſpective courts, Monluc and Randan, Cecil and Wotton, concluded another deed of treaty and agreement. By this convention it was determined, that the Engliſh and French troops ſhould depart out of Scotland; that all warlike preparations ſhould ceaſe ; that the fort of Eymouth ſhould be razed to the ground, in terms of∣ the treaty of Cambray; that Francis and Mary ſhould abſtain from bearing the title and arms of England or Ireland; that it ſhould be conſidered, whether a farther compenlation ſhould be made to Elizabeth for the injuries committed againſt her; and that the king and queen of Scots ſhould be fully and ſincerely reconciled to the nobility and the people of their kingdom. The intereſts of England and France were the particular objects of this agreement. But though the conceſſions to the Proteſtants were not inſerted in it at full length, an</p></body></text></TEI>