<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-14T17:58:15Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>In the twelfth chapter, by the woman bearing a man- child is to be underſtood the
                Chriſtian church; by the great red dragon, the heathen Roman empire; by the
                man-child whom the woman bore, Conſtantine the Great; and by the war in heaven, the
                conteſts between the Chriſtian and Heathen religions.</p>
            <p>In the thirteenth chapter, by the beaſt with ſeven heads and ten horns, unto whom the
                dragon gave his power, feat, and great authority, is to be underſtood, net Pagan but
                Chriſtian, not imperial but papal Rome; in ſubmitting to whole religion, the world
                did in effect ſubmit again to the religion of the dragon. The ten-horned beaſt
                therefore repreſents the Romiſh church and ſtate in general: but the beaſt with two
                horns like a lambis the Roman clergy; and that image of the ten-horned beaſt, which
                the two-horned beaſt cauſed to be made, and inſpired with life, is the pope; whoſe
                number is 666, according to the numerical powers of the letters conſtituting the
                Roman name <hi rend="italic">Latinus,</hi></p>
            <p>or its equivalent in <hi rend="italic">Hebrew;</hi> דומ׳׳ח <hi rend="italic"
                    >Romiith.</hi></p>
            <table>
                <row>
                    <cell>Λ 30</cell>
                    <cell>200 ד</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>A 1</cell>
                    <cell>6 ו</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>T 300</cell>
                    <cell>40 מ</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>E 5</cell>
                    <cell>10 ׳</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>I 10</cell>
                    <cell>10 ׳</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>N 50</cell>
                    <cell>400 ת</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>O 70</cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Σ 200</cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>666</cell>
                    <cell>666</cell>
                </row>
            </table>
            <p>Chapter xiv. By the lamb on mount Sion is meant Jeſus; by the hundred forty and four
                thouſand, his church and followers; by the angel preaching the ever- laſting goſpel,
                the firſt principal effort made towards a reformation by that public oppoſition
                formed againſt the worſhip of ſaints and images by emperors and biſhops in the
                eighth and ninth centuries; by the angel crying, “Babylon is fallen,” the Waldenſes
                and Albigenſes, who pronounced the church of Rome to be the Apocalyptic Babylon, and
                denounced her deſtruction; and by the third angel, Martin Luther and his fellow
                reformers, who proteſted againſt all the corruptions of the church of Rome, as
                deſtructive to ſalvation. For an account of the doctrines and precepts contained in
                the Scriptures, ſee <hi rend="smallcaps">Theology.</hi> For proofs of their divine
                origin, ſee <hi rend="smallcaps">Religion, Prophecy,</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Miracles.</hi></p>
            <p>SCRIVENER, one who draws contracts, or whoſe buſineſs it is to place money at
                intereſt. If a ſcrivener is entruſted with a bond, he may receive the intereſt; and
                if he fails, the obligee ſhall bear the loſs: and ſo it is if he receive the
                principal and deliver up the bond; for being entruſted with the ſecurity itſelf, it
                muſt be preſumed that he is truſted with power to receive intereſt or principal; and
                the giving up the bond on payment of the money ſhall be a diſcharge thereof. But if
                a ſcrivener ſhall be entrusted with a mortgage-deed, he hath only authority to
                receive the intereſt, not the principal; the giving up the deed in this caſe not
                being ſufficient to reſtore the eſlate, but there muſt be a reconveyance, &amp;c. It
                is held, where a ſcrivener puts out his client’s money on a bad ſecurity, which upon
                inquiry might have been eaſily found ſo, yet he cannot in equity be charged to
                anſwer for the money; for it is</p>
            <p>here ſaid, no one would venture to put out money of another upon a ſecurity, if he
                were obliged to warrant and make it good in caſe a loſs ſhould happen, without any
                fraud in him.</p>
            <p>SCROBICULUS <hi rend="smallcaps">cordis,</hi> the ſame as <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >AnticardIUM.</hi></p>
            <p>SCROFANELLO, in ichthyology, a name by which ſome have called a ſmall fiſh of the
                Mediterranean, more uſually known by the name of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >ſcorpaena.</hi></p>
            <p>SCROLL, in HERALDRY. See that article, chap. iv, ſect. 9. When the motto relates to
                the creſt, the ſcroll is properly placed above the atchievement; otherwiſe it ſhould
                be annexed to the eſcutcheon. Thoſe of the order of knighthood are generally placed
                round ſhields.</p>
            <p>SCROPHULA, the <hi rend="smallcaps">king’s evil.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Medicine, </hi>n° 349.</p>
            <p>SCROPHULARIA, <hi rend="smallcaps">Figwort,</hi> in botany: A genus of the
                angioſpermia order, belonging to the didynamia claſs of plants; and in the natural
                method ranking under the 40th order, <hi rend="italic">Perſonatae.</hi> The calyx is
                quinqueſid; the corolla almoſt globoſe, and reſupinated; the capſule bilocular.
                There are ſeveral ſpecies, of which the moſt remarkable are, 1. <hi rend="italic"
                    >Nodosa,</hi> or the common figwort, which grows in woods and hedges. The root
                is tuberous; the ſtalks are four or five feet high, and branched towards the top;
                the leaves are heart- ſhaped, ſerrated, and acute. The flowers are of a dark red
                colour, ſhaped like a cap or helmet; the lower lip greeniſh: they grow in looſe
                dichotomous ſpikes or <hi rend="italic">racemi</hi> at the top of the branches. The
                leaves have a fetid ſmell and bitter taſte. A decoction of them is ſaid to cure hogs
                of the meaſles. An ointment made of the root was formerly uſed to cure the piles and
                ſcrophulous sores, but is at preſent out of practice. 2. <hi rend="italic"
                    >Aquatica,</hi> water-figwort, or betony. The root is fibrous; ſtem erect,
                ſquare, about four feet high. The leaves are oppoſite, elliptical, pointed, ſlightly
                ſcalloped, on decurrent footſtalks. Flowers purple, in looſe naked ſpikes. It grows
                on the ſides of rivulets and other wet places, and has a fetid ſmell, though not ſo
                ſtrong as the preceding. The leaves are uſed in medicine as a corrector of ſena, and
                in powder to promote ſneezing. 3. <hi rend="italic">Scorodonia,</hi> or balm-leaved
                figwort. The ſtem is erect, ſquare, about two feet high. The leaves are oppoſite,
                doubly ſerrated. The flowers are duſky purple, in compoſite bunches. It grows on the
                banks of rivulets, &amp;c. in Cornwall. 4. V<hi rend="italic">ernalis,</hi> or
                yellow fig- wort. The ſtalks are ſquare, hairy, brown, about two feet high. The
                leaves are heart-ſhaped, roundiſh, hairy, indented, oppoſite. The flowers are
                yellow, on ſingle forked footſtalks from the alæ of the leaves. It grows in hedges
                in Surry.</p>
            <p>SCROTUM. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Anatomy,</hi> n⁰ 107.</p>
            <p>SCRUPI, in natural hiſtory, the name of a claſs of foſſils, formed in detached
                maſſes, without any crufts; of no determinate figure or regular ſtructure; and
                compoſed of a cryſtalline or ſparry matter, debaſed by an admixture of earth in
                various proportions. Under this claſs are comprehended, 1. The <hi rend="italic"
                    >telaugia.</hi> 2. The petri<hi rend="italic">dia.</hi> 3. The lit<hi
                    rend="italic">hozugia.</hi> 4.The<hi rend="italic"> jaſpides</hi> or
                jaſpers.</p>
            <p>SCRUPLE, <hi rend="smallcaps">Scrupulus,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Scrupulum,</hi>
                the leaſt of the weights uſed by the ancients, which amongſt the Romans was the 24th
                part of an ounce, or the 3d part of a dram. The ſcruple is ſtill a weight among</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
