<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-14T17:55:28Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>guinity. By both courts their marriage was decided to be void; and thus two ſentences
                of divorce were pronounced.</p>
            <p>Bothwel now conducted the queen from Dunbar to her capital. But inſtead of attending
                her to her palace of Holyrood houſe, his jealouſy and apprehenſions induced him to
                lodge her in the caſtle of Edinburgh, where he could hold her in ſecurity againſt
                any attempt of his enemies. To give ſatisfaction, however, to her people, and to
                convince them that ſhe was no longer a priſoner, a public declaration upon her part
                appeared to be a meaſure of expediency. She preſented herſelf, therefore, in the
                court of ſeſſion; the lords chancellor and preſident, the judges, and other perlons
                of diſtinction, being preſent. After obſerving that ſome ſtop had been put to the
                adminiſtration of juſtice upon account of her being detained at Dunbar againſt her
                will by the lord Bothwel, ſhe declared, that though ſhe had been highly offended
                with the outrage offered to her, ſhe was yet inclined to forget it. His
                courteouſneſs, the ſenſe ſhe entertained of his paſt ſervices to the ſtate, and the
                hope with which ſhe was impreſſed of his zeal and activity for the future, compelled
                her to give him and his accomplices in her impriſonment a full and complete pardon.
                She at the ſame time deſired them to take notice, that ſhe was now at her freedom
                and liberty; and that ſhe propoſed, in conſideration of his merits, to take an early
                opportunity of promoting him to new and diſtinguiſhed honours.</p>
            <p>It was underſtood that the queen was immediately to advance him to be her huſband.
                The order was given for the proclamation of the banns; and Mr John Craig, one of the
                miniſters of Edinburgh, was deſired to perform this buſineſs. But though the order
                was ſubſcribed by the queen, he refuſed abſolutely his compliance without the
                authority of the church. The brethren, after long reaſonings, granted him permiſſion
                to diſcharge this duty. His ſcruples, notwithſtanding, and delicacy, were not yet
                removed. He proteſted, that, in obeying their deſire, he ſhould be allowed to ſpeak
                his own ſentiments concerning the marriage, and that his publiſhing the banns ſhould
                infer no obligation in him to officiate in the ſolemnſty. In his congregation,
                accordingly, before a crowded audience, and in the preſence of ſeveral noblemen and
                privy counſellors, he declared that the marriage of the queen and the earl of
                Bothwel was unlawful, and that he was prepared to give his reaſons for this opinion
                to the parties themſelves. He added, that if leave to do this was denied Him, he
                would either abſtain altogether from proclaiming the banns, or take the liberty,
                after proclaiming them, to inform his people of the cauſes of his diſapprobation of
                the marriage. He was carried before the lords of the privy-council ; and the earl of
                Bothwel called upon him to explain his behaviour. He anſwered, that the church had
                prohibited the marriage of perſons ſeparated for adultery; and that the divorce
                between him and his wife muſt have been owing to colluſion; ſince the ſentence had
                been given with precipitation, and ſince his new contract was ſo ſudden; and he
                objected to him the abduction and raviſhment <hi rend="italic">of</hi> the queen,
                and the ſuſpicion of his guilt in the king’s murder. This bold language drew no
                reply from Bothwel that was ſatislactory to Mr Craig, or that could intimidate him.
                He proclaimed in his church the banns of the marriage; but he told the congregation,
                that he diſcharged the ſuggeſtions of his conference in pronouncing it to be a
                deteſtable and ſcandalous engagement. He expreſſed the ſorrow he felt for the
                conduct of the nobility, who ſeemed to approve it from their flattery or ſilence;
                and addreſſing himſelf to the faithful, he beſought them to pray to the Almighty
                that he would turn a reſolution intended againſt law, reaſon, and religion, into a
                comfort and benefit to the church and the kingdom. Theſe freedoms were too great to
                paſs unnoticed. Mr Craig was ordered anew to attend the privy-council; and he was
                reprimanded with ſeverity for exceeding the bounds of his commiſſion. He had the
                courage to defend himſelf. His commiſſion, he ſaid, was founded in the word oſ God,
                poſitive law, and natural reaſon; and upon the foundation of theſe topics he was
                about to prove that the marriage muſt be univerſally foul and odious, when the earl
                of Bothwel commanded him to be filent. The privy-council, ſtruck with the vigour of
                the man, and apprehenſive of the public diſeontents, did not dare to inflict any
                puniſhment upon him; and this victory, over Bothwel, while it heightened all the
                ſuſpicions againſt him, ſerved to encourage the enemies of the queen, and to
                undermine the reſpect of her ſubjects.</p>
            <p>Mary, before ſhe rendered her hand to Bothwel, created him duke of Orkney. The
                ceremony was performed in a private manner, after the rules of the Popiſh church;
                but, to gratify the people, it was likewiſe ſolemnized publicly according to the
                Proteſtant rites by Adam Bothwel biſhop of Orkney, an eccleſiaſtic who had renounced
                the Epiſeopal order, for the reformation. It was celebrated with little pomp and
                feſtivity. Many of the nobles had retired to their feats in the country; and thoſe
                who attended were thoughtful and ſad. Du Croc, the French ambaſſador, ſenſιble that
                the match would be diſpleaſing to his court, refuſed to give his countenance to the
                lolemnity. There were no acclamations of the common people. Mary herſelf was not
                inconſcious of the imprudence of the choice ſhe had made, and looked back with
                ſtupriſe and ſorrow to the train of circumſtances which had conducted her to this
                fatal event. Forſaken by her nobles, arid impriſoned at Dunbar, ſhe was in ſo
                perilous a ſituation that no remedy could ſave her honour but death. Her marriage
                was the immediate and neceſſary conſequence of that ſituation @@(s). It was the</p>
            <p>@@@(s) "The queen (ſays Melvil) could not but marry him; feeing he had raviſhed her
                and lain with her againſt her will.’’ Memoirs, p. 159. In the following paſſage,
                from a writer of great authority, in our hiſtory, this topic is touched with no leſs
                exactneſs, but with greater delicacy. After Mary had remained a fortnight under the
                power of a daring profligate adventurer, ſays Lord Haſtes, few foreign princes would
                have ſolicited her<pb n="61"></pb> hand. Some of her ſubjects might ſtill have
                ſought that honour; but her compliance would have been humiliating beyond meaſure.
                It would have left her at the mercy of a capricious huſhand; it would have expoſed
                her to the diſgrace of being reproached, in ſome ſullen hour, for the adventure at
                Dunbar. Mary was ſo ſituated, at this critical period, that ſhe was reduced to this
                horrid alternative, either to remain in a friendleſs and hazardous celibacy, or to
                yield her hand to Bothweh” Remarks on the Hiſtory of Scotland, p. 204.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
