<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:56:10Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>miniſters was exerted to multiply the ſubſcriptions to a bond or league which was to prepare the way, and to be a foundation for accompliſhing the full deſtruction and ruin of the Scottiſh queen.</p><p>A combination ſo reſolute and ſo fierce, which pointed to the death of Mary, which threatened her titles to the crown of England, and which might defeat the ſucceſſion of her ſon, could not fail to excite in her boſom the bittereſt anxieties and perturbation. Weary of her ſad and long captivity, broken down with calamities, dreading afflictions ſtill more cruel, and willing to take away ſrom Elizabeth every poſſible pretence of ſeverity, ſhe now framed a ſcheme of accommodation, to which no decent or reaſonable objection could be made. By Naw, her ſecretary, ſhe preſented it to Elizabeth and her privy-council. She proteſted in it, that if her liberty ſhould be granted to her, ſhe would enter into the cloſeſt amity with Elizabeth, and pay an obſervance to her above every other prince of Chriſten- dom; that ſhe would forget all the injuries with which ſhe had been loaded, acknowledge Elizabeth to be the rightful queen of England, abſtain from any claim to her crown during her life, renounce the title and arms of England, which ſhe had uſurped by the command of her huſband the king of France, and reprobate the bull from Rome which had depoſed the Engliſh queen. She likewiſe proteſted, that ſhe would enter into the aſſociation which had been formed for the ſecurity of Elizabeth; and that ſhe would conclude a defenſive league with her, provided that it ſhould not be prejudicial to the ancient alliance between Scotland and France; and that nothing ſhould be done during the life of the Engliſh queen, or after her death, which ſhould invalidate her titles to the crown of England, or thoſe of her ſon. As a confirmation of theſe articles, ſhe profeſſed that ſhe would conſent to ſtay in England for ſome time as an hoſtage; and that if ſhe was permitted to retire from the dominions of Elizabeth, ſhe would ſurrender proper and acceptable perſons as  ſureties. She alſo proteſted, that ſhe would make no alterations in Scotland; and that, upon the repeal of what had been enacted there to her diſgrace, ſhe would bury in oblivion all the injuries ſhe had received from her ſubjects: that ſhe would recommend to the king her ſon thoſe counſellors who were moſt attached to England, and that ſhe would employ herſelf to reconcile him to the fugitive nobles: that ſhe would take no ſteps about his marriage without acquainting the queen of England; and that, to give the greater firmneſs to the propoſed accommodation, it was her deſire that he ſhould be called as a party to it: and, in fine, ſhe affirmed, that ſhe would procure the king of France and the princes of Lorraine to be guarantees for the performance of her engagements. Elizabeth, who was ſkilful in hypocriſy, diſcovered the moſt deciſive ſymptoms of ſatisfaction and joy when theſe overtures were communicated to her. She made no advances, however, to conclude an accommodation with Mary; and her miniſters and courtiers exclaimed againſt lenient and pacific meaſures. It was loudly inſiſted, that the liberty of Mary would be the death of Elizabeth; that her aſſociation with her ſon would be the ruin both of England and Scotland; and that her elevation to power would extend the empire of Popery, and give a deadly blow to the doctrines of the reformation.</p><p>In the mean time, an act of attainder had paſſed againſt the fugitive nobles, and their eſtates and honours were forfeited to the king; who, not ſatisſied with this, ſent Patrick maſter of Gray to demand a ſurrender of their perſons from the queen of England. As this ambaſſador had reſided ſome time in France, and been intimate with the duke of Guiſe, he was recommended to Mary: but being a man of no principles, he eaſily ſuffered himſelf to be corrupted by Elizabeth; and while he pretended friendſhip to the unfortunate queen, he diſcovered all that he knew of the intentions of her and her ſon. The moſt ſcandalous falſehoods were forged againſt Mary; and the leſs ſhe was apparently able to execute, the more ſhe was ſaid to deſign. That an unhappy woman, confined and guarded with the utmoſt vigilance, who had not for many years ſufficient intereſt to procure a decent treatment for herſelf, ſhould be able to carry on ſuch cloſe and powerful negociations with different princes as were imputed to her, is an abſurdity which it muſt for ever be impoſſible to reconcile. That ſhe had an amour with her keeper the earl of Shrewſhury, as was now reported, might be; though of this there is no proof. This, however, could ſcarce be treaſon againſt Elizabeth @@(x): yet, on account of this, Mary was committed to the charge of Sir Amias Paulet and Sir Drue Drury, zealous puritans, and who, it was hoped, would treat her with ſuch ſeverity as might drive her to deſpair, and induce her to commit ſome raſh action. — The earl of Leiceſter, ſaid to be Elizabeth’s paramour, even ventured to ſend aſſaſſins, on purpoſe, by the murder of Mary, at once to deliver his miſtreſs from her fears. But the new keepers of the caſtle, though religious bigots, were men of ſtrict probity, and rejected with ſcorn ſuch an infamous tranſaction. In 1585, Mary began to feel all the rigours of a ſevere impriſonment. She had been removed from Sheffield to the caſtle of Tutbury; and under her new keepers ſhe experienced a treatment which was in the higheſt degree unjuſt, diſreſpectful, and acrimonious. Two apartments or chambers only were allotted to her, and they were ſmall and inconvenient, meanly furniſhed, and ſo full of apertures and chinks, that they could not protect her againſt the inclemencies of the weather. The liberty of going abroad for pleaſure or exerciſe was de-</p><p>@@@(x) Amidſt the infamous calumnies which this princeſs was ſolicitous to fix upon the queen of Scots, it muſt excite the higheſt indignation to conſider her own contempt of chaſtity, and the unprincipled licentiouſneſs of her private life. See Haynes’s Collect. of State Papers, p. 99, &amp;c. Even when palſied with age, ſhe was yet burning with unquenchable deſires; and vain of her haggard and cadaverous form, ſought to allure to her many lovers. See Murdin, p. 558, 560, 657, 718, 719. and the diſcoveries of a writer, whoſe pen, elegant, poignant, inquiſitive, and polite, improves and embelliſhes every topic that it canvaſſes; Walpole, Catalogue of royal and  noble Authors, vol. i. p. 126. [Stuart, vol. ii. p. 282, note.]</p></body></text></TEI>