<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:58:36Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>atic origin cannot, we think, be queſtioned; and as Perſia was peopled at a very early period, it may not improbably have been their parent country: but when our author contends that their empire had ſubſiſted for more than 1500 years before Ninus the founder of the Aſſyrian monarchy, and that it extended from Egypt to the Ganges, and from the Perſian gulf and Indian ſea to the Caſpian, we cannot help thinking that his prejudices againſt the Celts, and his deſire to do honour to his favourite Goths, have made him advance a paradox inconſiſtent with the moſt authentic records of antiquity. His diſſertation however is ingenious, and replete with a variety of curious learning.</p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Scythian</hi><hi rend="italic"> Lamb,</hi> in natural hiſtory. See <hi rend="italic">Scythian LAMB.</hi></p><p>SCYTHROPS, a genetical name given by Mr Latham to a bird of which hitherto but one ſpecies has been obſerved. It is about the ſize of a crow, and two feet three inches in length. The bill is large, convex, furrowed on the ſides, and bent at the tip; the noſtrils are placed at the baſe of it, and the tongue is cloven at the end. The general colour of the plumage is a browniſh aſh, but the tip of each feather of the back, wings, and tail, is black. The tail has each feather banded with black at the end, and the tip itſelf white; but the inner webs of the feather are marked with black and white bands. The toes are placed two forwards and two backwards, as in the parrot genus. This curious bird is a native of New Holland, and we believe in that part of the world is not uncommon, but its manners are as yet quite unknown. We are happy in being able to preſent our readers with an engraving of it from an excellent drawing with which we were lately favoured. See plate CCCCXLIX.</p><p>SEA, in a ſtrict ſenſe, ſignifies a large portion of water almoſt ſurrounded by land, as the Baltic and Mediterranean ſeas; but it is frequently uſed for that vaſt body of water which encompaſſes the whole earth.</p><p>What proportion the ſuperficies of the ſea bears to that of the land cannot eaſily be aſcertained. Buffon has ſuppoſed that the ſurface of our globe is equally divided between land and water, and has accordingly calculated the ſuperficies of the ſea to be 85,490,506 ſquare miles. But it is now well known that the ocean covers much more than the half of the earth’s ſurface. Buffon believed the exiſtence of a vaſt ſouthern continent, which Captain Cook has ſhown to be viſionary. It was this circumſtance which miſſed him. According to the moſt accurate obſervations hitherto made, the ſurface of the ſea is to the land as three to one; the ocean therefore extends over 128,235,759 ſquare miles, ſuppoſing the ſuperficies of the whole globe to be 170,981,012 ſquare miles. To aſcertain the depth of the ſea is ſtill more difficult than its ſuperficies, both on account of the numerous experiments which it would be neceſſary to make, and the want of proper inſtruments for that purpoſe. Beyond a certain depth the ſea has hitherto been found unfathomable; and though ſeveral methods have been contrived to obviate this difficulty, none of them has completely anſwered the purpoſe. We know in general that the depth of the ſea increaſes gradually as we leave the ſhore; but if this continued beyond a certain diſtance, the depth in the middle of the ocean would be prodigious. Indeed the numerous iſlands everywhere ſcattered in the ſea demonſtrate the contrary, by ſhowing us that the bottom of the water is unequal like the land, and that ſo far from uniformly  ſinking, it ſometimes riſes into lofty mountains. If the depth of the ſea be in proportion to the elevation of the land, as has generally been ſuppoſed, its greateſt depth will not exceed five or ſix miles, for there is no mountain ſix miles perpendicular above the level of the ſea. The ſea has never been actually founded to a greater depth than a mile and 66 feet; every thing beyond that therefore reſts entirely upon conjecture and analogical reaſoning, wſhich ought never to be admitted to determine a ſingle point that can be aſcertained by experiment, becauſe, when admitted, they have too often led to falſe concluſions. Along the coaſts, where the depth of the ſea is in general well known, it has always been found proportioned to the height of the ſhore; when the coaſt is high and mountainous, the ſea that waſhes it is deep; when, on the contrary, the coaſt is low, the water is ſhallow. Whether this analogy holds at a diſtance from the ſhore, experiments alone can determine.</p><p>To calculate the quantity of water contained in the ſea, while its depth is unknown, is impoſſible. But if we ſuppoſe with Buffon that its medium depth is the fourth part of a mile, the ocean, if its ſuperficies be 128,235,759 ſquare miles, will contain 32,058,939.75 cubic miles of water.</p><p>Let us now endeavour to compute the quantity of water which is conſtantly diſcharged into the ſea. For this purpoſe let us take a river whoſe velocity and quantity of water is known, the Po, for inſtance, which according to Riccioli is 1000 feet (or 100 perches of Boulogne) broad, 10 feet deep, and runs at the rate of four miles in an hour; eonſequently that river diſcharges into the ſea 200,000 cubic perches of water in an hour, or 4,800,000 in a day. A cubic mile contains 125,000,000 cubic perches; the Po therefore will take 26 days to diſcharge a cubic mile of water into the ſea. Let us now ſuppoſe, what is perhaps not very far from the truth, that the quantity of water which the ſea receives from the rivers in any country is proportioned to the extent of that country. The Po from its origin to its mouth traverſes a country 380 miles long, and the rivers which fall into it on every  ſide riſe from ſources about ſixty miles diſtant from it. The Po, therefore, and the rivers which it receives, water a country of 45,600 ſquare miles. Now ſince the wſhole ſuperficies of the dry land is about 42,745,253. ſquare miles, it follows, from our ſuppoſition, that the quantity of water diſcharged by all the rivers in the world, in one day, is 36 cubic miles, and in a year 13,140. If therefore the ſea contains 32,058,939 cubic miles of water, it would take all the rivers in the world 2439 years to diſcharge an equal quantity.</p><p>It may ſeem ſurpriſing that the ſea, ſince it is continually receiving ſuch an immenſe ſupply of water, does not viſibly increaſe, and at laſt cover the whole earth. But our ſurpriſe will ceaſe, if we conſider that the rivers themſelves are ſupplied from the ſea, and that they do nothing more than carry back thoſe waters which the ocean is continually laviſhing upon the earth. Dr Halley, has demonſtrated that the vapours raiſed from the ſea and tranſported upon land are ſufficient to maintain all the rivers in the world. The ſimplicity of this great proceſs is aſtonifhing; the ſea not only connects</p></body></text></TEI>