<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:55:23Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>majeſty ſhould enter by the one, he ſhould be conſtrained to go out by the other.</p><p>While he reſided at Stirling, the king chiefly confined himſelf to his chamber. His ſtrange behaviour to the queen did not give the public any favourable idea of him; and as the earl of Murray and his faction took care to augment the general odium, no court was paid to him by foreign ambaſſadors. His ſituation, therefore, was exceedingly uncomfortable; but though he muſt have been conſcious of his imprudence and folly, he did not alter his conduct. In a ſullen humour he left Stirling, and proceeded to Glaſgow. Here he fell ſick, with ſuch ſymptoms as ſeemed to indicate poiſon. He was tormented with violent pains, and his body was all covered over with puſtules of a bluiſh colour; ſo that his death was daily expected. Mary did not repay his coldneſs to her by negligence. She ſet out immediately for Glaſgow, and waited on him with all the aſſiduity of an affectionate wife, until he recovered: after which ſhe returned with him to Edinburgh; and as the low ſituation of the palace of Holyroodhouſe  was thought to render it unhealthy, the king was lodged in a houſe which had been appointed for the ſuperior of the church, called <hi rend="italic">St Mary's in the Fields. </hi>This houſe ſtood upon an high ground, and in a ſalubrious air; and here ſhe ſtaid with him ſome days. — Here the conſpirators thought proper to finiſh their plot in the moil execrable manner. On the 10th of February 1567, about two o’clock in the morning, the houſe where the king reſided was blown up by gunpowder. The exploſion alarming the inhabitants, excited a general curioſity, and brought multitudes to the place from whence it proceeded. The king was found dead and naked in an adjoining field, with a fervant who uſed to ſleep in the ſame apartment with him. On neither was there any mark of fire or other external injury.</p><p>The queen was in the palace of Holyroodhouſe, taking the diverſion of a walked ball, which was given to honour the marriage of a favourite domeſtic, when the news of the king’s death was brought to her. She ſhowed the utmoſt grief, and appeared exaſperated to the laſt degree againſt the perpetrators of a deed at once ſo ſhocking and barbarous. The moil expreſs and peremptory orders were given to inquire after the perpetrators by every poſſible method. A proclamation was iſſued by the privy-council, aſſuring the people, that the queen and nobility would leave nothing undone to diſcover the murderers of the king. It offered the firm of 2000 l. and an annuity for life, to any perſon who ſhould give information of the deviſers, counſellors, and perpetrators of the murder; and it held out this reward, and the promiſe of a full pardon, to the conſpirator who ſhould make a free confeſſion of his own guilt, and that of the confederates. On the fourth day after this proclamation was publiſhed, a placard was affixed to the gate of the city-priſon, affirming, that the earl of Bothwel, James Balfour, David Chalmers, and black John Spence, were the murderers. No name, however, was ſubſcribed to this intelligence, nor was any demand made for the proffered reward; ſo that it was difficult to know whether this advertiſement had been dictated by a ſpirit of calumny or the love <hi rend="italic">of</hi> juſtice.</p><p>In the mean time, the earl of Murray conducted</p><p>himſelf with his uſual circumſpection and artifice. Upon a pretence that his wife was dangerouſly ſick at his caſtle in Fife, he, the day before the murder, obtained the queen’s permiſſion to pay a viſit to her. By this means he propoſed to prevent all ſuſpicion whatever of his guilt. He was ſo full, however, of the intended project, that while he was proceeding on his journey, he obſerved to the perſen who accompanied him, “This night, before morning, the lord Darnley ſhall loſe his life.” When the blow was ſtruck, he returned to Edinburgh to carry on his practices. Among foreign nations<hi rend="subscript">i</hi> the domeſtic disputes of the queen and her huſband being fully known, it was with the greater eaſe that reports could be propagated to her diſadvantage. To France letters were diſpatched, expreſſing, in fervent terms, her participation in the murder. In England, the miniſters and courtiers of Elizabeth could not flatter that princeſs more agreeably, than by induſtriouſly detracting from the honour and the virtue of the Scottiſh queen. Within her own dominions a ſimilar ſpirit of outrage exerted itſelſ, and not without ſucceſs. As her reconciliation with her huſband could not be unknown to her own ſubjects, it was interpreted to be diſſimulation and treachery. The Proteſtant clergy, who were her moſt determined enemies, poſſeſſed a leading direction among the populace; and they were the friends and the partizans of the earl of Murray. Open declamations from the pulpit were made againſt Bothwel, and ſtrong inſinuations and biting ſurmiſes were thrown out againſt the queen. Papers were diſperſed, making her a party with Bothwel in the murder. Every art was employed to provoke the frenzy of the people. Voices, interrupting the ſilence of the night, proclaimed the infamy of Bothwel; and portraits of the regicides were circulated over the kingdom.</p><p>The queen’s determination, however, to ſcrutinize into the matter was unabated; and to the earl of Lennox, the king’s father, ſhe paid an attention which he could only have expected from her upon an emergency of this kind. Having preſſed her by letter to the moſt diligent inquiry after the regicides, ſhe returned an anſwer ſo completely to his wiſhes, that he: was fully convinced of the ſincerity and rigour with which ſhe intended to proceed againſt them: and he urged her to aſſemble the three eſtates, that their advice might direct the order and manner of their trial. She wrote to him, that an aſſembly of the eſtates was already proclaimed; and that it was her earneſt and determined will and purpoſe, that no ſtep ſhould be neglected that could conduce to the advancement and execution of juſtice. Yielding to his anxieties, he addreſſed her anew, intreating that the trial might not be delayed; obſerving, that it was not a matter of parliamentary inquiry; adviſing, that it would be more proper to proceed to it with the greateſt expedition and urging her to commit to priſon all the perſons who had been named and deſcribed in the papers and placards which had been ſet up in the public places of the city. The queen informed him, that although ſhe had thought it expedient to call a meeting of the parliament at this juncture, it was not her meaning that the proceedings againſt the regicides ſhould be delayed till it was actually aſſembled. As to the placards and papers to which he alluded, they were ſo numerous and contradictory,</p></body></text></TEI>