<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:54:58Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ed, that ""they would believe as their fathers had done before them.” The biſhops and the eſtate ecclesiaſtical, from a conſciouſneſs of the weakneſs of popery, ſeemed to have lost all power of ſpeech. No diſſent, no vote, was given by them. “It is long (ſaid the earl Mariſchal), ſince I entertained a jealouſy of the Romiſh faith, and an affection to the reformed doctrines. But this day has afforded me the completeſt conviction, of the falſehood of the one, and the truth of the other. The biſhops, who do not conceive themſelves to be deficient in learning, and whoſe zeal for the maintenance of the hierarchy cannot be doubted, have abandoned their religion, and their intereſt in it, as objects which admit of no defence or juſtification.” All the other conſtituent members of this great council were zealous for the eſtabliſhment of the reformation, and affirmed the propriety of its doctrines. Thus the high court of parliament, with great deliberation and ſolemnity, examined, voted, and ratified the confeſſion of the reformed faith.</p><p>A few days after the eſtabliſhment of the Conſeſſion of Faith, the parliament paſſed an act againſt the maſs and the exerciſe of the Romiſh worſhip. And it ſcrupled not to ordain, that all perſons ſaying or hearing maſs ſhould, for the firſt offence, be expoſed to the confiſcation of their eſtates, and to a corporal chaſtiſement, at the diſcretion of the magiſtrate; that for the ſecond offence, they ſhould be baniſhed out of the kingdom; and that for the third offence they ſhould incur and ſuffer the pains of death. This fierceneſs, it is to be acknowledged, did not ſuit the generoſity of victory; and while an excuſe is ſought for it in the perſidiouſneſs oſ the Romiſh prieſthood, it escapes not the obſervation of the moſt ſuperficial hiſtorians, that theſe ſeverities were exactly thoſe of which the Proteſtants had complained ſo loudly, and with ſo much juſtice. By another ordination, the parliament, after having declared, that the pope, or biſhop of Rome, had inflicted a deep wound and a humiliating injury upon the ſovereignty and government of Scotland, by his frequent interferences and claims of power, commanded and decreed, that, for the future, his juriſdiction and authority ſhould be dead and extinct; and that all perſons maintaining the ſmalleſt connection with him, or with his ſect, ſhould be liable to the loſs of honour and offices, proſcription, and baniſhment.</p><p>Theſe memorable and deciſive ſtatutes produced the overthrow of the Romiſh religion. To obtain to theſe proceedings, and to its other ordinances, the approbation of Francis and Mary was an object of the greateſt anxiety, and of infinite moment to the three eſtates. Sir James Sandilands lord St John was therefore appointed to go to France, and to expreſs to the king and queen the affection and allegiance of their ſubjects, to explain what had been done in conſequence of the late conceſſions and treaty, and to ſolicit their royal ratification of the tranſactions of the parliament. The ſpirited behaviour of the Congregation had, however, exceeded all the expectations of the princes of Lorraine; and the buſineſs of the embaſſy, and the ambaffador himſelf, though a man of character and probity, were treated not only with ridicule, but with inſult and contumely. He. returned accordingly without any anſwer to his commiſſion. Inſtead of ſubmitting the heads</p><p>and topics of a reformation to Francis and Mary, by a petition or a narrative, the parliament had voted them into laws; and from this informality the validity of its proceedings has been ſuſpected. But it is obſervable of the Proteſtants, that they had not concealed their views with regard to religion and the abolition of Popery; that in the grant of redreſs and conceſſion, and in the deed of treaty, no actual prohibition was made to bar the eſtabliſhment of the reformation; that a general authority was given to the parliament to decide in affairs of ſtate; and that Francis and Mary were ſolemnly bound to authenticate its tranſactions. Though a formality was invaded, the ſpirit of the treaties was yet reſpected and maintained. The nation, of conſequence, imputed the conduct of Francis and Mary to political reaſons ſuggeſted by the princes of Lorraine, and to the artifices of the Popiſh clergy; and as Elizabeth did not refuſe, upon her part, the ratification of the agreements, and ſolicited and preſſed the French court in vain to adopt the ſame meaſure, a ſtrength and force were thence communicated to this concluſion.</p><p>When the three eſtates diſpatched Sir James Sandilands to France, they inſtructed the earls of Morton and Glencairn, with Maitland of Lethington, to repair to the court of England. By theſe ambaſſadors they preſented to Elizabeth their ſincere and reſpectful thanks, for the attention ſhown by her to Scotland, in her late moſt important ſervices. And while they ſolicited the continuance of her favour and protection, intreated, in an earned: manner, that her majeſty, for the eſtabliſhment of a perpetual peace and amity, would be pleaſed to take in marriage the earl of Arran, the next heir after his father to the Scottiſh monarchy. The queen made new and fervent proteſtations of her regard and attachment; and gave the promise of her warmeſt aid when it ſhould be neceffary, in their juſt defence, upon any future occaſion. She ſpoke in obliging terms of the earl of Arran; but as ſhe found in herſelf no preſent diſpoſition to marriage, ſhe deſired that he might conſult his happineſs in another alliance. She expreſſed a favourable opinion of the Scottiſh nobility; and as a demonſtration of her affection and eſteem, ſhe took the liberty to remind them of the practices which had been employed to overturn their independency, and begged them to confider the unanimity and concord of their order as a neceſſary guard againſt the ambition and the artifice of the enemies of their nation.</p><p>The ſucceſs of the Congregation, though great and illuſtrious, was not yet completely deciſive. The refuſal of Francis and Mary to ratify their proceedings opened a ſource of bitterneſs and inquietude. The Popiſh party, though humbled, was not annihilated. Under the royal protection it would ſoon be formidable. Political conſiderations might ariſe, not only to cool the amity of England, but even to provoke its reſentment. And France, though it could now tranſport no army againſt Scotland, might ſoon be able to adopt that expedient. Cruel diſtractions and ſevere calamities were ſtill to be dreaded. In the narrowneſs of their own reſources they could find no ſolid and permanent ſecurity againſt the rage and weight of domeſtic faction, and the ſtrenuous exertions of an extenſive kingdom. All their fair atchievements might</p></body></text></TEI>