<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-14T17:57:32Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>as Chriſt himſelf has done in ſaying, 'Ye alſo ſhall bear witneſs, becauſe ye have
                been with me from the beginning@@*. And no one that attempts to convince an
                unbeliever of the truth of Chriſtianity, would begin his dernonſtration by
                preſuppoſing a doctrine which his adverſary denies, but would ground his arguments
                on the credibility of the evangeliſts as human hiſtorians, for the truth of the
                miracles, the death, and the reſurrection of Chriſt. Even thoſe who examine the
                grounds of their faith for their own private conviction, muſt treat the evangeliſts
                as human evidence; ſince it would be arguing in a circle to conclude that the facts
                recorded in the goſpels are true, becauſe they are inſpired, when we conclude the
                Scriptures to be inſpired in conſequence of their contents. In theſe caſes, then, we
                are obliged to conſider the evangeliſts as human evidence; and it would be no
                detriment to the Chriſtian cauſe to conſider them at all times as ſuch in matters of
                hiſtorical fact. We find it nowhere expreſsly recorded that the public tranſactions
                which the apoſtles knew by their own experience, and of which St Luke informed
                himſelf by diligent inquiry, ſhould be particular objects of divine inſpiration. We
                ſhould even be conſiderable gainers, in adjuſting the harmony of the goſpels, if we
                were permitted to ſuppoſe that ſome one of the evangeliſts had committed an
                immaterial error, and that St John has rectified ſome trifling miſtakes in the
                preceding goſpels. The moſt dangerous objections which can be made to the truth of
                our religion, and ſuch as are moſt difficult to anſwer, are thoſe drawn from the
                different relations of the four evangeliſts.”</p>
            <p>Before any inquiry is made reſpecting the inſpiration of the books of the New
                Teſtament, it is neceſſary to determine the meaning of the term; for theologians
                have given to it a variety of ſignifications. Moſt of the German divines make it to
                consiſt in an infusion of words as well as ideas. Luther, Beza, and Salmaſius,
                reſtrict it to ideas alone. Doddridge underſtands by it an intervention of the
                Deity, by which the natural faculties of the mind were directed to the diſcovery of
                truth. Warburton and Law think it was a negative intervention to preſerve the ſacred
                writers from eſſential errors. Some believe every circumſtance was dictated by the
                Holy Ghoſt; others ſuppoſe that no ſupernatural aſſiſtance was granted except in the
                epiſtolary writings. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Inspiration.</hi></p>
            <p>As there is an evident diſtinction between inſpiration and revelation, and as the
                origin of the Chriſtian religion may be ſtill proved divine, even though it were
                denied that thoſe who record its facts and doctrines were inſpired in the act of
                writing, it will be moſt judicious and ſafe to employ the word <hi rend="italic"
                    >inſpiration</hi> in that ſenſe which can be moſt eaſily defended and ſupported.
                By doing this much may be gained and nothing loſt. It is difficult to prove to a
                deiſt that the words of Scripture are divine, becauſe he ſees that every writer has
                words and phraſes peculiar to himſelf. It is difficult alſo to prove that the ideas
                were infuſed into the mind of the authors while they were engaged in the act of
                writing; becauſe concerning facts they appeal not to divine inſpiration, but declare
                    <hi rend="italic">what they have ſeen and heard.</hi> In reaſoning they add
                their own ſentiments to what they had received from the Lord, and ſubjoin,
                eſpecially in their epiſtles, things not connected with religion. The definition
                which Doddridge gives, ſeems</p>
            <p>applicable to ordinary gifts or the uſual endowments of rational creatures, rather
                than to the extraordinary gifts of the Holy Spirit, which were beſtowed on the
                apoſtles. Thoſe who maintain that every fact or circumſtance was ſuggeſted by divine
                inſpiration, will find it no eaſy matter to prove their poſition. The opinion of
                Warburton and Law, with proper explanations, ſeems moſt probable. The opinion of
                Grotius, that only the epiſtles were inſpired, may be eaſily refuted.</p>
            <p>The proof of the authenticity of the New Teſtament depends on human teſtimony: The
                proof of its inſpiration is derived from the declaration of inſpired perſons.</p>
            <p>In proving that the New Teſtament is inſpired, we preſuppoſe its authenticity that
                the ſacred books were written by the apoſtles whoſe names they bear, and that they
                have been conveyed to us pure and uncorrupted. This we have already attempted to
                prove, and we hope with ſucceſs. The evidence of inſpiration is the teſtimony of
                Chriſt and his apoſtles, which we receive as credible, becauſe they confirmed their
                doctrines by miracles. From the important miſſion of Chriſt and his apoſtles, we
                infer that every power was beſtowed which divine wiſdom thought expedient; and from
                their conduct we conclude, that it is morally impoſſible that they could lay claim
                to any powers which they did not poſſeſs. It is proper therefore to inquire into the
                declarations of Chriſt and his apoſtles concerning the nature, degree, and extent,
                of the inſpiration beſtowed upon the writers of the ſacred books.</p>
            <p>If we conſider Chriſt’s more immediate promiſes of inſpiration to the apoſtles, we
                ſhall find that he has given them, in the moſt proper ſenſe of the word, at three
                ſeveral periods, 1ſt, When he ſent the apoſtles to preach the goſpel @@†; 2dly, In
                holding a public diſcourſe relating to the goſpel, at which were preſent a
                conſiderable multitude; 3dly, In his prophecy of the deſtruction of Jeruſalem @@‡.
                When he ſent the apoſtles to preach the goſpel, he thus addreſſed them: “When they
                deliver you up, take no thought how or what ye ſhall ſpeak, tor it ſlrall be given
                you in that ſame hour what ye ſhall ſpeak; for it is not you that ſpeak, but the
                ſpirit of your Father that ſpeaketh in you.” The ſame promiſe was made almoſt in the
                ſame words in the preſence of an immenſe multitude (Luke xii. 11, 12.) From theſe
                paſſages it has been urged, that if the apoſtles were to be inſpired in the preſence
                of magiſtrates in delivering ſpeeches, which were ſoon to be forgotten, it is ſurely
                reaſonable to conclude that they would be inſpired when they were to compoſe a
                ſtandard of faith for the uſe of all future generations of Chriſtians. If this
                concluſion be fairly deduced, it would follow that the writings of the New Teſtament
                are the dictates of inſpiration, not only in the doctrines and precepts, but in the
                very words. But it is a concluſion to which ſincere Chriſtians have made objections;
                for, ſay they, though Chriſt promiſes to aſſiſt his apoſtles in caſes of great
                emergency, where their own prudence and fortitude could not be ſufficient, it does
                not follow that he would dictate to them thoſe facts which they knew already, or
                thoſe reaſonings which their own calm reflection might ſupply. Beſides, ſay they, if
                the New Testament was dictated by the Holy Spirit, and only penned by the apoſtles,
                what reaſon can be given for the care with which Chriſt inſtructed them both during
                his</p>
            <p>@@@[m]* John xv.</p>
            <p>@@@[m]† Matt. I. 19, 20.</p>
            <p>@@@[m]‡ Mark xiii. II; Luke xxi. 14, 15.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
