<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:55:38Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>of the caſtle, they immediately entered a boat which waited for them; and being rowed acroſs the lake, the lord Seton received the queen with a choſen band of horſemen in complete armour. That night he conveyed her to his houſe of Niddrie in Weſt Lothian; where having reſted a few hours, ſhe ſet out for Hamilton.</p><p>The eſcape of the queen threw her enemies into the greateſt conſternation. Many forſook the regent openly; arid ſtill more made their ſubmiſſions privately, or concealed themſelves. He did not, however, deſpond; but reſolved to defend himſelf by force of arms. The queen ſoon found herſelf at the head of 6000 men, and the regent oppoſed her with 4000. Mary, however, did not think it proper to riſk a battle; knowing the capacity of the regent as a general, and that his officers were all men of approved valour and experience. But in this prudent reſolution ſhe was over-ruled by the impetuoſity of her troops. A battle was fought on the 13th of May 1568, at Langſide near Glaſgow in which Mary’s army was defeated, and her laſt hopes blaſted. The unfortunate queen fled towards Kirkcudbright; wſhere finding a place of ſafety, ſhe deliberated on the plan ſhe ſhould afterwards follow. The reſult of her deliberations, as frequently happens in cafes of perplexity, led her to take the worſt ſtep poſſible. Not- withſtanding all the perfidy which ſhe had found in Elizabeth, Mary could not think that ſhe would now refuſe to afford her a refuge in her dominions; and therefore determined to retire into England. To this ſhe had been ſolicited by Elizabeth herſelf during her confinement in Lochleven caſtle; and ſhe now reſolved, in oppoſition to the advice of her moſt faithful counſellors, to make the fatal experiment.</p><p>In obedience to her order, the lord Herries addreſſed a letter to Mr Lauder, the deputy-commander at Carliſle; and after detailing her defeat at Langſide, deſired to know if ſhe might truſt herſelf upon Engliſh ground. This officer wrote inſtantly an anſwer, in which he ſaid, that the lord Scroop the warden of the frontiers being abſent, he could not of his private authority give a formal aſſurance in a matter which concerned the ſtate of a queen: but that he would ſend by poſt to his court to know the pleaſure of his ſovereign; and that if in the mean time any neceſſity ſhould force Mary to Carliſle, he would receive her with joy, and protect her againſt her enemies. Mary, however, before the meſſenger could return, had embarked in a fiſhing boat with ſixteen attendants. In a few hours ſhe landed at Wirkington in Cumberland; and from thence ſhe proceeded to Cockerrnouth, where ſhe continued till Mr Lauder, having aſſembled the gentlemen of the country, conducted her with the greateſt reſpect to the caſtle of Carliſle.</p><p>To Elizabeth ſhe announced her arrival in a diſpatch, which deſcribed her late misfortunes in general and pathetic terms, and in which ſhe expreſſed an earneſt ſolicitude to pay her a viſit at her court, and the deep ſenſe ſhe entertained of her friendſhip and generoſity. The queen of England, by obliging and polite letters, condoled with her upon her ſituation, and gave her aſſurances of all the favour and protection that were due to the juſtice of her cauſe. But as they were not accompanied with an invitation to London, Mary took the alarm. She thought it expedient to inftruct lord</p><p>Fleming to repair to France; and ſhe instructed lord Herries with a moſt preſſing remonſtrance to Elizabeth. Her anxiety for an interview in order to vindicate her conduct, her ability to do ſo in the moſt ſatisſactory manner, and her power to explain the ingratitude, the crimes, and the perfidy of her enemies, were urged to this princeſs. A delay in the ſtate of her affairs was repreſented as nearly equivalent to abſolute deſtruction. An immediate proof was therefore requeſted from Elizabeth of the ſincerity of her profeffions. If ſhe was unwilling to admit into her preſencfe a queen, a relation, and a friend, ſhe was reminded, that as Mary’s entrance into her dominions had been voluntary, her departure ought to be equally free and unreſtrained. She valued the protection of the queen of England above that of every other potentate upon earth; but if it could not be granted, ſhe would ſolicit the amity, and implore the aid, of powers who would commiſerate her afflictions, and be forward to relieve them. Amidſt remonſtrances, however, which were ſo juſt and ſo natural, Mary failed not to give thanks to Elizabeth for the courteſy with which ſhe had hitherto been treated in the caſtle of Carliſle. She took the opportunity alſo to beg of this princeſs to avert the cruelty of the regent from her adherents, and to engage him not to waſte her kingdom with hostility and</p><p>ravages; and ſhe had the prudence to pay her compliments in an affectionate letter to ſecretary Cecil, and to court his kind offices in extricating her from her difficulties and troubles.</p><p>But the queen of England was not to be moved by remonſtrances. The voluntary offer of Mary to plead her cauſe in the preſence of Elizabeth, and to ſatisfy all her ſcruples, was rejected. Her diſaſters were rather a matter of exultation than of pity. The deliberations of the Engliſh queen, and thoſe of her ſtateſmen, were not directed by maxims of equity, of compaſſion, or of generoſity. They conſidered the flight of Mary into England as an incident that was fortunate and favourable to them; and they were ſolicitous to adopt thoſe meaſures which would enable them to draw from it the greateſt profit and advantage. If the queen of Scots were allowed to rcturn to her own dominions, it was probable that ſhe would ſoon be in a condition to deſtroy the earl of Murray and his faction, who were the friends of England. The houſe of Hamilton, who were now zealous in the intereſts of France, would riſe into conſideration änd povver. England would be kept in perpetual turmoils upon the frontiers; Ireland would receive moleſtation from the Scots, and its diſturbances grow important and dangerous. Mary would renew with redoubled ardour her deſigns againſt the Proteſtant religion; and a French army would again be introduced into Scotland. For theſe reaſons, Elizabeth and her miniſters determining not to reſtore the queen of Scots to her throne, conſidered what would be the probable conſequences of permitting her to remain at liberty in England. In this ſituation, ſhe would augment the number of her partizans, ſend to every quarter her emiſſaries, and inculcate her title to the crown. Foreign ambaſſadors would afford her aid, and take a ſhare in her intrigues; and Scotland, where there was ſo high an object to be gained, would enter with cordiality into her views. This plan being alſo hazardous, it was deliberated whether the</p></body></text></TEI>