<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:55:53Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>liance, and never more to take any concern whatsoever in her affairs.</p><p>The regent, in the meanwhile, was very anxious to recover the good opinion of Elizabeth. Her treatment of Mr Wood, and her diſcovery of his practices, had excited his apprehenſions. He therefore aſſembled at Stirling a convention of the eſtates; and taking her letters a ſecond time into conſideration, returned her a reply to them by Robert Pitcairn abbot of Dunfermline, in a ſtyle ſuited to her temper and jealouſies, and from which ſhe could deciſively infer, that no favour of any kind would be ſhown to the queen of Scots. But this baſe condeſcenſion, though aſſiſted by his treachery to the duke of Norfolk, not being ſufficient, in his opinion, to draw completely to him the cordiality of the queen of England, he was preparing to gratify her with another ſacrifice. The partiality of Maitland to Mary, and his intrigues with Norfolk and the Engliſh malcontents, had rendered him uncommonly obnoxious to Elizabeth and her miniſtry. The late commotions had been chiefly aſcribed to his arts; and it was natural to dread new calamities and tumults from the fruitful ſpring of his invention. Under the pretence of employing his ſervice in diſpatches to England, the regent invited him to Stirling. He was then with the earl of Athol at Perth; and ſuſpecting ſome improper device, he obeyed the ſummons with reluctance. When he took his place in the privy-council, Captain Crawford, the minion of the earl of Lenox, who had diſtinguiſhed himſelf in the trial of Mary, accuſed him, in direct terms, of being a party in the murder of the late king. The regent affected aſtoniſhment, but permitted him to be taken into cuſtody. He was ſoon after lent to Edinburgh under a guard, and admoniſhed to prepare for his trial. Upon ſimilar charges, the lord Seton and Sir James Balfour were ſeized upon and impriſoned.</p><p>Kirkaldy of Grange, the governor of the caſtle of f Edinburgh, who was warmly attached to Maitland, after having remonſtrated in vain with the regent on the violence of his conduct, employed addreſs and ſtratagem in the ſervice of his friend. Under the cover of night, he went with a guard of ſoldiers to the lodgeing where Maitland was confined; and ſhowing a forged warrant for taking his perſon into keeping, got poſſeſſion of him. Kirkaldy had now in his cattle the duke of Chatelherault, the lord Herries, and Maitland. The regent ſent for him to a conference; but he refuſed to obey his meſſage. He put himſelf and his fortreſs under the direction of his priſoners. The regent, condeſcending to pay him a viſit, was more laviſh than uſual of his promiſes and kindneſs. His arts, however, only excited the diſdain of this generous ſoldier. Since he could not lead out Maitland to the block, he inſtituted a proceſs of treaſon againſt him, in order to forfeit his eſtates. Kirkaldy, by the mouth of a trumpeter, deſired him to commence ſimilar actions againſt the earl of Morton and Mr Archibald Douglas, as it was notorious that they were parties to the king’s murder. This meſſenger was like- wiſe charged with delivering a challenge from him to Mr Archibald Douglas, and another from the lord Herries to the earl of Morton. This diſappointment, and theſe indignities, made a deep impreſſion upon the regent; and, in a thoughtful diſſatisſied. humour, a</p><p>bout this time, he made a ſhort progreſs towards the Engliſh border, courting popularity, and deſerving it, by an attention to order and juſtice.</p><p>Elizabeth, flattered by his ſubmiſſive advances, and pleaſed with his ambition, was now diſpoſed to gratify his fulleſt wiſhes; and ſhe perceived, that by delivering to him the queen of Scots, ſhe would effectually relieve herſelf of a priſoner whoſe vigour and intrigues were a conſtant interruption to her repoſe. A treaty for this purpoſe was entered into and concluded. The regent was to march an army to the Engliſh frontiers, and to receive from her his ſovereign into her own dominions, the victim of his power, and the ſport of his paſſions. No hoſtages and no ſecurity were ſtipulated for her entertainment and good uſage. His authority over her was to be without any limits. Upon his part, he was to deliver to Elizabeth the young prince, to put her in poſſeſſion of the principal forts of Scotland, and to aſſiſt her with troops in the event of a war with France. This treaty, ſo fatal to Mary, and ſo ruinous to the independence of Scotland, eſcaped not the vigilance of the biſhop of Roſs. He complained of it in the ſtrongeſt terms to Elizabeth; and declared it to be equivalent to a ſentence of death againſt his miſtreſs. The ambaſſadors of France and Spain were alſo ſtrenuous in their remonſtrances to her upon this ſubject. All reſiſtance, however, was unavailing; and the execution of the treaty ſeemed inevitable. Yet how vain are the loftieſt ſehemes of human pride! The career of the regent was haſtening to its termination; and the hand of an aſſaſſin put a period to his dream of royalty. Scotland did not loſe its liberties; but Mary continued to be unfortunate.</p><p>James Hamilton of Bothwelhaugh, who had been taken a priſoner at the battle of Langſide, obtained his liberty and life; but his eſtates were forfeited. — His wife, the heireſs of Woodhouſlie, retired upon this emergency to her paternal inheritance, in the hope that it might eſcape the rapacity of the regent. He had, however, given it away in a gift to one of his favourites, Sir James Ballenden; and the inſtruments of his power having the inhumanity to ſtrip her of her garments, and to turn her naked out of her houſe, in a cold and dark night, ſhe became diſtracted before the morning. Hamilton vowed revenge; and the regent made a mockery of his threats. This contempt inſpirited his paſſions; and the humiliation of the houſe of Hamilton, to which he was nearly allied, foſtered the eagerneſs of his diſcontents. The madneſs of party fermented in him with the atroc;ouſneſs of rage. His mind reconciled itſelf to aſſaſſination. After watching for ſome time a proper opportunity to commit his horrible purpoſe, he found it at Linlithgow. The regent was to paſs through this town in his way from Stirling to Edinburgh. Intimations reached him that Hamilton was now to perpetrate his deſign: and he unaccountably neglected them. The affaſſin, in a houſe that belonged to the archbiſhop of St Andrew’s, waited deliberately his approach; and firing his muſket from a window, ſhot him through the body. The wound, when examine, was not judged to be mortal; but the regent finding its pain to increaſe, prepared himſelf for death; and in a few hours after he expired. A fleet horſe of the abbot of Arbroath’s carried the affaſſin to the palace of Hamilton; and</p></body></text></TEI>