<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-14T17:56:03Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>other inferior prelates preſcnted to benefices, ſhould be examined by the biſhop or
                ſuperintendant of the dioceſe or precinct where the preferment was ſituated; and
                that their fitneſs to repreſent the church in parliament ſhould be duly inquired
                into. It was judged that the king and the regent ſhould recommend qualified perſons
                to vacant biſhoprics, and that the elections of them ſhould be made by the chapters
                of the reſpective cathedrals. It was ordered that all benefices with cure under
                prelacies ſhould only be diſpoſed of to officiating miniſters; that every miniſter
                ſhould receive ordination from the biſhop of the dioceſe, or the ſuperintendant of
                the province; and that the biſhops and ſuperintendants, upon the ordination of
                miniſters, ſhould exact an oath from them to recognize the authority of the king,
                and to pay canonical obedience to their ordinary in all things that were lawful.</p>
            <p>By thefe artful regulations the earl of Morton did not mean ſolely to conſult his own
                rapacity or that of the nobles. The exaltation of the Proteſtant church to be one of
                the three eſtates was a conſequence of them; and the clergy being the ſtrenuous
                enemies of Mary, he might by their means ſecure a decided influence in parliament.
                The earl of Marre, as regent, giving his ſanction to the proceedings of the
                commiſſion, they were carried into practice. The deluſive expectation of wealth,
                which this revival of Epiſcopacy held out to the miniſtry, was flattering to them;
                and they bore with tolerable patience this ſevere blow that was ſtruck againſt the
                religious policy of Geneva. Mr John Douglas was deſired to give a ſpecimen of his
                gifts in preaching; and his election took effect, not- withſtanding the oppoſition
                that was made to it by John Knox and other eccleſiaſtics, who flood up for the rules
                and forms which had been eſtabliſhed at the reformation. He was inaugurated in his
                office by the biſhop of Caithneſs, Mr John Spotſwood ſuperintendant of Lothian, and
                Mr David Lindſay, who violating the book of diſcipline, communicated to him his
                character and admiſſion by the impoſition of hands. This was a ſingular triumph to
                Epiſcopacy; and thc exaltation of Douglas included other peculiarities remarkable
                and offenſive. He denied that he had made any ſimoniacal agreement with the earl of
                Morton; yet it was known that the revenues of the archbiſhopric were almoſt wholly
                ingroſſed by that nobleman, he had promiſed to relign, upon his inſtalment, the
                office of rector which he held in the univerſity of St Andrew’s: yet he refuſed to
                execute this engagement. He was in a very advanced age; and his mental
                qualifications, which had never been eminent, were in a ſtate of decay.</p>
            <p>A general aſſembly, which was holden at St Andrew’s, conſidering the high moment of
                the new regulations introduced into the church, appointed commiſſioners to go to
                John Knox, who was at this time indiſpoſed, and to conſult with him deliberately in
                his houſe, whether they were agreeable to the word of God. But from the arts of the
                nobles, or from the ſickneſs of Knox, it happened that this conference was not
                carried into execution. In a general aſſembly, however, which met at Perth, the new
                polity was reported and examined. The names of archbiſhop, dean, arch-deacon,
                chancellor, and chapter, were excepted againſt as Popiſh diſtinctions, and as
                ſlanderous to the ears of pious Chriſtians. A wiſh was expreſſed that they might</p>
            <p>be exchanged for titles leſs profane and ſuperſtitious; and an unanimous proteſtation
                was made, that the new polity was merely a temporary expedient, and ſhould only
                continue and prevail till a more perfect order ſhould be obtained from the king, the
                regent, and the nobility. This tolerating reſolution left the new polity in its full
                force; and a colourable foundation was now eſtabliſhed for the laity to partake in
                the profits of biſhoprics. The ſimoniacal paction of Morton and Douglas was not long
                a matter of ſingularity. Mr James Boyd was appointed to the archbiſhopric of
                Glaſgow, Mr James Paton to the b;ſhopric of Dunkeld, and Mr Andrew Graham to the ſee
                of Dumblain; and theſe compromiſing eccleſiaſtics, upon being allowed competencies
                to themſelves, gratified their noble friends with the greateſt proportion of their
                revenues. The virtue of the common people approved not this ſpirit of traffic; and
                the biſhops of the new polity were treated openly with reproach or with
                ridicule.</p>
            <p>The year 1572 is alſo remarkable for the death of John Knox, whoſe miſtaken zeal had
                contributed not a little to bring upon the queen thoſe misfortunes with which ſhe
                was now oppreſſed. Neither by his death, however, nor by the change of the regency,
                could ſhe now be relieved. The earl of Morton was ſo much devoted to Elizabeth, that
                he received particular inſtructions from her how to guide the young king. His
                elevation, indeed, gave the finiſhing ſtroke to the queen’s affairs. He employed
                himſelf with ſucceſs in dividing her party among themſelves, and by his means the
                duke of Chatelherault and the earl of Huntley were induced to forſake her. As for
                Elizabeth, ſhe was bent on putting Mary to death; but as no crime could be alleged
                againſt her in England, ſhe thought it proper that ſhe ſhould be carried back to
                ſuffer death in her own dominions. This propofol, however, was rejected; and the
                friends who remained true to Mary once more began to indulge themſelves in hopes of
                ſuccours from France. New misfortunes, however, awaited them.— The caſtle of
                Edinburgh, which had hitherto been held for the queen by Kirkaldy of Grange, was
                obliged to ſurrender to an Engliſh army commanded by Sir William Drury. Kirkaldy was
                ſolemnly aſſured by the Englilh commander of his life and liberty; but Elizabeth
                violated this capitulation, and commanded him to be delivered up to the regent. An
                hundred of his relations offered to become vaſſals to Morton, and to pay him 3000
                merks yearly, if he would ſpare his life; but in vain: Kirkaldy and his brother Sir
                James were hanged at Edinburgh. Maitland of Lethington, who was taken at the ſame
                time, was poiſoned in the priſon houſe of Leith.</p>
            <p>The jealouſy of Elizabeth did not diminiſh with the decline of Mary’s cauſe. She now
                treated her with more rigour than ever, and patroniſed Morton in all the enormities
                which he committed againſt her friends. Leſly biſhop of Roſs had been long
                impriſoned in England, on account of his concern in the duke of Norfolk’s
                conſpiracy. Morton earneſtly ſolicited the queen to deliver him up, and would
                undoubtedly have put him to death; but as he had acted in the character of
                ambaſſador from Mary, this was judged impolitic, and the prelate was ſuffered to
                depart for France. When he arrived there, he endeavoured in vain to ſtir up the
                emperor, the pope, and the duke of Alva, to exert them-</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
