<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:54:25Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>wiſhing that all the princes of Chriſtendom would unite their arms againſt their common enemy the Turks, He hinted, very juſtly, that his Imperial majeſty had offered more than he could perform, becauſe his couſin, Mary of England, was not at his diſpoſal. The ambaſſador replied, that his maſter, it perſuaſions failed, would compel Henry by force of arms to reſign her. James anſwered this ridiculous declaration by obſerving, that the emperor then would be guilty of a breach of all laws both divine and human; that it would be impolitic to give a preference to any of the three princeſſes, all of them being ſo illuſtrious and deſerving; but, to ſhow how much he valued an alliance with his Imperial majeſty, he would become a ſuppliant to that prince for his niece, daughter to Chriſtſern king of Denmark, to become his bride. The ambaſſador’s anſwer to this unexpected requeſt was, that ſhe was already betrothed to the count palatine, and that before that time the marriage was probably conſummated;</p><p>But whether the Imperial ambaſſador had any right to offer the Engliſh princeſs or not, it is agreed by moſt hiſtorians, that he was offered either Mary or Elizabeth by their father Henry himſelf. To Mary of Bourbon, the daughter of the duke of Vendoſme, he is ſaid to have been contracted; but for ſome reaſon or other all theſe matches were broken off; and the king at laſt went to France, where he married Magdalen the eldeſt daughter of Francis. The nuptials were celebrated at Paris in the year 1537, with great magnificence; and among other things ſerved up by way of deſert at the mariage-feaſt, were a number of covered cups filled with pieces of gold and gold-dull, the native product of Scotland, which James distributed among the gueſts. This gold was found in the mines of Crawford-moor, which were then worked by the Germans. In the beginning of May, the royal pair embarked for Leith, under convoy of four large ſhips of war, and landed on the 28th of the fame month. The joy of the Scots was inexpreſſible, but it was of ſhort continuance; for the young queen died of a fever on the 22d of July the ſame year.</p><p>King James did not long remain a widower; for the ſame year he ſent Beaton abbot of Arbroath, to treat of his ſecond marriage with a French lady, Mary of Guiſe, ducheſs-dowager of Longueville. In this he was rivalled by his uncle Henry VIII. but not before James had been contracted to her. But this was nothing to Henry; for he not only inſiſted upon having this lady for his wife, but threw out ſome menaces againſt Francis, becauſe he would not comply with this unjuſtifiable requeſt. In January 1538, ſhe was married to James, and eſcorted to Scotland by the admiral of France with a conſiderable ſquadron; both James and Francis being ſuſpicious that Henry would make ſome attempt to intercept the royal bride. But nothing of this kind happened, and ſhe landed ſafely at Fifeneſs; from whence ſhe was conducted to the king at St Andrew’s.</p><p>But while James appeared thus to be giving himſelf up to the pleaſures of love, he was in other reſpects ſhowing himſelf a bloody tyrant. Some differences ſubſiſted between the families of Gordon and Forbes in the north. The heir of the houſe laſt-mentioned had been educated in a looſe diſſipated manner, and kept</p><p>company with a worthleſs fellow named <hi rend="italic">Strahan.</hi> Having refuſed this favourite ſomething he had aſked, the latter attached himſelf to Gordon earl of Huntley, who, it is ſaid, aſſiſted him in forming a charge of treaſon againſt Forbes. He was accuſed of intending to reſtore the Douglaſſes to their forfeited eſtates and honours; which improbable ſtory being ſupported by ſome venal evidences, the unhappy young man was condemned and executed as a traitor. The king could not but ſee the injuſtice of this execution; and, in order to make ſome amends for it, baniſhed Strahan the kingdom. The following execution, which happened a few days after, was much more inhuman, inſomuch that it would have ſtained the annals even of the moſt deſpotic tyrants. The earl of Angus, finding that he could not regain the favour of the king, had recourſe to the method uſual in thoſe days, viz. the committing of depredations on the borders. This crime was ſufficient with James to occaſion the death of his innocent ſiſter, the dowager- lady of Glamis. She had been courted by one Lyon, whom ſhe had rejected in favour of a gentleman of the name of <hi rend="italic">Campbell.</hi> Lyon, exaſperated at his repulſe, found means of admittance to James, whom he filled with the greateſt terrors on account of the practices of the family of Angus; and at laſt charged the lady, her huſband, and an old prieſt, with a deſign of poiſoning the king in order to reſtore Angus. The parties were all remarkable for the quiet and innocent lives they led; and even this circumſtance was by their diabolical accuſer turned to their prejudice, by repreſenting it as the effect of cunning or caution. In this reign an accuſation of treaſon was always followed by condemnation. However, the evidence againſt the lady appeared ſo abſurd and contradictory, that ſome of the judges were for dropping the proſecution, and others for recommending her caſe to the king: but the majority prevailed to have it determined by a jury, who brought her in guilty; and ſhe was condemned to be burnt alive in the Caſtle-hill of Edinburgh. The defence ſhe made would have done honour to the ableſt orator, and undeniably proved her innocence; but tho’ it was reported to James, it was ſo far from mitigating her ſenterce, that it was aggravated by her huſband being obliged to behold her execution. The unhappy husband himſelf endeavoured to make his way over the caſtle-wall of Edinburgh; but the rope proving too ſhort, he was daſhed in pieces: and lord Glands her ſon, though but a child, was impriſoned during the remainder of this reign. The old prieſt, though put to the torture, confeſſed nothing, and was freed. Lyon, like the other acculer already mentioned, was baniſhed the kingdom.</p><p>Whether theſe and other cruelties had affected the king’s conſcience, or whether his brain had been touched by the diffractions of the different parties, is unknown; but it is certain, that, in the year 1540, he began to live retired: his palace appeared like the cloiſtered retreat of monks; his ſleep was haunted by the moſt frightful dreams, which he conſtrued into apparitions; and the body of Sir James Hamilton, whole execution has already been mentioned, ſeemed continually preſent to his eyes. Perhaps the loſs of his two ſons, who died on the ſame day that Sir James was executed, might have contributed to bring this man more remark-</p></body></text></TEI>