<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:54:22Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>and the moſt open profligacy of manners. In connection with theſe defects, he poſſeſſed a perſevering obſtinacy in purſuing his meaſures, the ability to perceive and to practiſe all the arts which were neceſſary to advance them, and the allurements of oſtentation and prodigality.</p><p>He was ſcarcely inveſted in the primacy, when he exhibited an example of his taſte for magnificence, and of his averſion to the reformed. He proceeded to St Andrew’s with an uncommon pomp and parade. The earls of Huntley, Arran, Mariſchal, and Montroſe, with the lords Fleming, Lindſey, Erſkine, and Seton, honoured him with their attendance; and there appeared in his train, Gavin archbiſhop of Glaſgow and lord high chancellor, four biſhops, ſix abbots, a great many private gentlemen, and a vaſt multitude of the inferior clergy. In the cathedral church of St Andrew’s, from a throne erected by his command, he harangued concerning the ſtate of religion and the church, to this company, and to a crowd of other auditors. Hc lamented the increaſe of heretics; he inſiſted upon their audacity and contempt of order; he ſaid, that even in the court of the ſovereign too much attention was ſhown to them; and he urged the ſtrong neceſſity of acting againſt them with the greateſt rigour. He informed this aſſembly, that he had cited Sir John Borthwick to appear before it, for maintaining tenets of faith hoſtile to the church, and for diſperſing heretical books; and he deſired that he might be aſſiſted in bringing him to juſtice. The articles of accuſation @@(o) were accordingly read againſt him; but he neither appeared in his. own perſon, nor by any agent or deputy. He was found, notwithſtanding, to be guilty; and the cardinal, with a ſolemnity calculated to ſtrike with awe and terror, pronounced ſentence againſt him. His goods and eſtate were confiſcated; a painted repreſentation of him was burned publicly, in teſtimony of the malediction of the church, and as a memorial of his obſtinacy and condemnation. It was ordained, that in the event of his being apprehended, he ſhould ſuffer as a heretic, without hope of grace or mercy. All Chriſtians, whether men or women, and of whatever degree or condition, were prohibited from affording him any harbour or ſuſtenance. It was declared, that every office of humanity, comfort, and ſolacement, extended to him, ſhould be conſidered as criminal, and be paniſhed with conſifcations and forfeitures.</p><p>Sir John Borthwick having been appriſed of his danger, fled into England; where he was kindly received by Henry VII1. who employed him in negociations with the Proteſtant princes of Germany. Cardinal Beaton perceived with concern that this act of ſeverity did not terrify the people. New defections from the church were announced to him. Andrew Cunningham ſon to the maſter of Glencairn, James Hamilton brother to Patrick Hamilton the martyr, and the celebrated George Buchanan the hiſtorian, were impriſoned upon ſuſpicions of hereſy; and, if they had not found means to eſcape, mult have died at the ſtake. In this declining condition of Popery, the cardinal held many mournful conſultations with the biſhops. All their intrigues and wiſdom were employed to deviſe methods to ſupport themſelves. The project of an inquiſitorial court was conceived, and exhibited a diſtant view of the extirpation of heretics. To erect this tribunal, they allured James V. with the hopes of the confiſcation and ſpoils, which might enrich him, from the perſecution and puniſhment of the reformed. He yielded himſelf to their ſolicitations, and gave them the ſanction of his authority.</p><p>A formal commiſſion was granted, conſtituting a court of inquiry after heretics, and nominating for its preſident Sir James Hamilton of Fennard, natural brother to the earl of Arran. The officious aſſiduity of this man, his ambition, and his thirſt of blood, were acceptable in a high degree to the clergy; and to this bad eminence their recommendation had promoted him. Upon the ſlighteſt ſuſpicion he was allowed to call any perſon before him, to ſcrutinize into his creed, and to abſolve or to condemn him. A tribunal ſo dreadful could not have found a director more ſuited to it. He was in haſte to fill the priſons of the kingdom with culprits, and was marking down in lifts the names of all thoſe to whom hereſy was imputed by popular report, and whom the arts of malicious men had repreſented as the objects of correction and puniſhment. But, while he was brood-</p><p>@@@(o) They are preſerved by archbiſhop Spotiſwood, and diſplay great liberality of mind, in a period when philoſophy may be ſaid to have been unknown in Scotland. They are thus detailed by this judicious writer.</p><p>I. “That he held the pope to have no greater authority over Chriſtians than any other biſhop or prelate had. 2. That indulgences and pardons granted by the pope were of no force nor effect, but deviſed to abuſe people, and deceive poor ignorant ſouls.</p><p>3. “That biſhops, prieſts, and other clergymen, may lawfully marry.</p><p>4. “That the hereſies, commonly called <hi rend="italic">heresies of England,</hi> and their new liturgy, were commendable, and to  ſee embraped of all Chriſtians.</p><p>5. “That the people of Scotland are blinded by their clergy, and profeſſed not the true faith.</p><p>6. "That churchmen ought not to enjoy temporalties.</p><p>7. “That the king ought to convert the rents of the church into other pious uſes.</p><p>8. “That the church of Scotland ought to be governed after the manner of the Engliſh.</p><p>9. “That the canons and decrees of the church were of no force, as being contrary to the law of God.</p><p>10. “That the orders of the friars and monks ſhould be aboliſhed, as had been done in England.</p><p>11. “That he did openly call the pope<hi rend="italic"> simoniac,</hi> for that he fold ſpiritual things.</p><p>12. “That he did read heretical books, and the New Teſtament in Engliſh, and ſome other treatiſes written by Melancthon, Oecolampadius, and Eraſmus, which he gave likewiſe unto others.</p><p>13. “The laſt and greateſt point was, that he refuſed to acknowledge the authority of the Roman ſee, or be ſubject thereunto.” Hist. of t<hi rend="italic">he Church,</hi> p. 70.</p></body></text></TEI>