<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-14T17:57:15Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>The 12th, 13th, and 14th chapters contain prophecies which refer entirely to the
                Chriſtian dispenlation; the circumſtances attending which he deſcribes with a
                clearneſs which indicated their near approach.</p>
            <p>The ſtyle of Zechariah is ſo ſimilar to that of Jeremiah, that the Jews were
                accuſtomed to remark that the ſpirit of Jeremiah had paſſed into him. He is
                generally proſaic till towards the concluſion of his work, when he becomes more
                elevated and poetical. The whole is beautifully connected by eaſy tranſitions, and
                preſent and future ſcenes are blended with the greateſt delicacy.</p>
            <p>Malachi was the laſt prophet that flouriſhed under the Jewiſh diſpenſation; but
                neither the time in which he lived, nor any particulars of his hiſtory, can now be
                aſcertained. It is even uncertain whether the word Malachi be a proper name, or
                denote, as the Septuagint have rendered it, h<hi rend="italic">is angel @@</hi><hi
                    rend="smallcaps">(r),</hi> that is, “the angel of the Lord.” Origen ſuppoſed,
                that Malachi was an angel incarnate, and not a man. The ancient Hebrews, the Chaldee
                paraphraſt, and St Jerome, are of opinion he was the ſame perſon with Ezra: but if
                this was the caſe, they ought to have aſſigned ſome reaſon for giving two different
                names to the ſame perſon.</p>
            <p>As it appears from the concurring teſtimony of all the ancient Jewiſh and Chriſtian
                writers, that the light of prophecy expired in Malachi, we may ſuppoſe that the
                termination of his miniſtry coincided with the accompliſhment of the firſt ſeven
                weeks of Daniel’s prophecy, which was the period appointed for ſealing the viſion
                and prophecy. This, according to Prideaux’s account, took place in A. M. 3595; but,
                according to the calculations of Biſhop Lloyd, to A. M. 3607, twelve years later.
                Whatever reckoning we prefer, it muſt be allowed that Malachi completed the canon of
                the Old Teſtament about 400 years before the birth of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>It appears certain that Malachi propheſied under Nehemiah, and after Haggai and
                Zechariah, at a time when great diſorders reigned among the prieſts and people of
                Judah, which are reproved by Malachi. He inveighs againſt the prieſts (i. 6, &amp;c.
                ii. 1, 2, &amp;c.); he reproaches the people with having taken ſtrange wive3 (ii.
                11.); he reproves them for their inhumanity towards their brethren (ii. 10. iii.
                5.); their too frequently divorcing their wives; their neglect of paying their
                tithes and firſt-fruits (Mal. iii. 13.). He ſeems to allude to the covenant that
                Nehemiah renewed with the Lord (iii. 10. and ii. 4, 5, &amp;c.), aſſiſted by the
                prieſts and the chief of the nation. He ſpeaks of the ſacriſice of the new law, and
                of the abolition of thoſe of the old, in theſe words (i. 10, 11, 12, 13.): “I have
                no pleaſure in you, faith the Lord of hoſts, neither will I accept an offering at
                your hand. For from the riſing of the ſun, even unto the going down of the ſame, my
                name ſhall be great among the Gentiles, and in every place incenſe ſhall be offered
                unto my name, and a pure offering: for my name ſhall be great among the Heathen,
                ſaith the Lord of hoſts.” He declares that the Lord was weary with the impiety of
                Iſrael; and aſſures them, that the Lord whom they fought</p>
            <p>ſhould ſuddenly come to his temple preceded by the meſſenger of the covenant, who was
                to prepare his way; that the Lord when he appeared ſhould purify the ſons of Levi
                from their unrighteouſneſs, and refine them as metal from the droſs; and that then
                the offering of Judah, the ſpiritual ſacriſice of the heart, ſhould be pleaſant to
                the Lord. The prophet, like one who was delivering a laſt meſſage, denounces
                deſtruction againſt the impenitent in emphatic and alarming words. He encourages
                thoſe who feared the name of the Lord with the animating promiſe, that the “Sun of
                righteouineſs ſhould ariſe with ſalvation in his rays,” and render them triumphant
                over the wicked. And now that prophecy was to ceaſe, and miracles were no more to be
                performed till the coming of the Meſſiah; now that the Jews were to be left to the
                guidance of their own reaſon, and the written inſtructions of their prophets—Malachi
                exhorts them to remember the law of Moſes, which the Lord had revealed from Horeb
                for the ſake of all Iſrael. At length he ſeals up the prophecies of the Old
                Teſtament, by predicting the commencement of the new diſpenſation, which ſhould be
                uſhered in by John the Baptiſt with the power and ſpirit of Elijah; who ſhould turn
                the hearts of fathers and children to repentance; but if his admonitions ſhould be
                rejected, that the Lord would ſmite the land with a curſe.</p>
            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">The</hi> collection of writings compoſed after the aſcenſion of
                Chriſt, and acknowledged by his followers to be, divine, is known in general by the
                name of χαινη διαθηχη.This title, though neither given by divine command, nor
                applied to theſe writings by the apoſtles, was adopted in a very early age, though
                the preciſe time of its introduction is uncertain, it Being juſtiſied by ſeveral
                paſſages in Scripture @@†, and warranted by the authority of St Paul in particular,
                who calls the ſacred books before the time of Chriſt ωαλαιαδιαθηαη @@‡. Even long
                before that period, either the whole of the Old Teſtament, or the five books of
                Moſes, were entitled βιϐλιον, or book of the covenant @@§.</p>
            <p>As the word διαθηχη admits of a two-fold interpretation, we may tranſlate this title
                either the <hi rend="italic">New Covenant</hi> or the <hi rend="italic">New
                    Te</hi>ſt<hi rend="italic">ament.</hi> The former tranſlation muſt be adopted,
                if reſpect be had to the texts of Scripture, from which the name is borrowed, ſince
                thoſe paſſages evidently convey the idea of a covenant; and, beſides, a being
                incapable of death can neither have made an old nor make a new teſtament. It is
                likewiſe probable, that the earlieſt Greek diſciples, who made uſe of this
                expreſſion, had no other notion in view than that of covenant. We, on the contrary,
                are accuſtomed to give this ſacred collection the name of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Te</hi>ſt<hi rend="italic">ament;</hi> and ſince it would be not only improper,
                but even abſurd, to ſpeak of the Teſtament of God, we commonly underſtand the
                Teſtament of Chriſt; an explanation which removes but half the difficulty, ſince the
                new only, and not the old, had Chriſt for its teſtator.</p>
            <p>In ſtating the evidence for the truth of Chriſtianity, there is nothing more worthy
                of conſideration than the authenticity of the books of the New Teſtament. This is
                the foundation on which all other arguments reſt;</p>
            <p>@@@[m]† Matth. xxvi. 28. Gal. iii. 17. Heb. viii. 8. ix. 15-20.</p>
            <p>@@@[m]‡ 2 Cor. iii. 14.</p>
            <p>@@@[m]§ 1. Mac. i. 57.</p>
            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">@@@(r) סלאכ׳</hi>
                <hi rend="italic">Malachi</hi> ſignifies properly my <hi rend="italic"
                >angel.</hi></p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
