<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:55:15Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>reſtraint, there would be no ſecurity for the fitneſs of the incumbent; and if no trials or examinations of miniſters took place, the church would be filled with miſrule and ignorance. Nor was it right or juſt that her majeſty ſhould retain to herſelf any part of the revenue of benefices; as it ought to be all employed to the uſes of the clergy, for the purpoſes of education, and for the ſupport of the poor. And as to her opinion, that a ſuitable aſſignment ſhould be made for them, they could not but thank her with reverence: but they begged to ſolicit and importune her to condeſcend upon the particulars of a proper ſcheme for this end, and to carry it into execution; and that, taking into a due conſideration the other articles of their demands, ſhe would ſtudy to comply with them, and to do juſtice to the religious eſtabliſhment of her people.</p><p>From the fears of the people about their religion, diſturbances and inſurrections were unavoidable; and before Mary had given her anſwer to the petitions or addreſs of the clergy, the Proteſtants, to a formidable number, had marched to St Leonard’s Craig; and, dividing themſelves into companies, had choſen captains to command them. But the leaders of this tumult being apprehended and committed to cloſe cuſtody, it ſubſided by degrees; and the queen, upon the interceſſion of the magiſtrates of Edinburgh, inſtead of bringing them to trial, gave them a free pardon. To quiet, at the ſame time, the apprehenſions which had gone abroad, and to controvert the inſidious reports which had been induſtriouſly ſpread of her inclination to overturn the reformed doctrines, ſhe repeatedly iſſued proclamations, aſſuring her ſubjects, that it was her fixed determination not to moleſt or diſturb any perſon whatſoever upon account of his religion or conference; and that ſhe had never preſumed even to think of any innovation that might endanger the tranquillity, or do a prejudice to the happineſs of the commonwealth.</p><p>While Mary was conducting her affairs with diſcernment and ability, the earl of Murray and his confederates continued their conſultations and their intrigues. After their diſappointment in the conſpiracy againſt the queen and the lord Darnley, they perceived that their only hope of ſucceſs or ſecurity depended upon Elizabeth; and as Randolph had promiſed them her protection and aſſiſtance, they ſcrupled not to addreſs a letter  to her, explaining their views and ſituation. The pretences of their hoſtility to their ſovereign upon which they affected to inſiſt, were her ſettled deſign to overturn the Proteſtant religion, and her rooted deſire to break all correſpondence and amity with England. To prevent the accompliſhment of theſe purpoſes, they ſaid, was the object of their confederacy; and with her ſupport and aid they did not doubt of being able to advance effectually the emolument and advantage of the two kingdoms. In the preſent ſtate of their affairs, they applied not, however, for any ſupply of her troops. An aid from her treaſury was now only neceſſary to them; and they engaged to beſtow her bounty in the manner the moil agreeable to her inclinations and her intereſts. The pleaſure with which Elizabeth received their application was equal to the averſion ſhe had conceived againſt the queen of Scots. She not only granted to them the relief they requeſted, but aſſured them by Randolph of her eſteem and favour while they ſhould continue to uphold the reformed religion and the</p><p>connection of the two nations Flattered by her aſſurances and generoſity, they were ſtrenuous to gain partizans, and to diſunite the friends of their ſovereign; and while they were ſecretly preparing for rebellion, and for trying their ſtrength in the field, they diſſeminated among the people the tenets, That a Papiſt could not legally be their king; that the queen was not at liberty of herſelf to make the choice of a huſband; and that, in a matter ſo weighty, ſhe ought to be entirely directed by the determination of the three eſtates aſſembled in parliament.</p><p>Elizabeth, at the ſame time, carrying her diſſimulation to the moſt criminal extremity, commanded Ran dolph to aſk an audience of Mary; and to counſel her to nouriſh no ſuſpicions of the earl of Murray and his friends; to open her eyes to their ſincerity and honour; and to call to mind, that as their lervices had hitherto preſerved her kingdom in repoſe, her jealouſies of them might kindle it into combuſtion, make the blood of her nobles to flow, and caſt into hazard her perſon and her crown. Full of aſtoniſhment at a meſſage ſo rude and ſo improper, the queen of Scots deſired him to inform his miſtreſs, that ſhe required not her inſtructions to diſtinguiſh between patriotiſm and treachery; that ſhe was fully ſenſible when her will or purpoſe was reſiſted or obeyed; and that ſhe poſſeſſed a power which was more than ſufficient to repreſs and to puniſh the enormities and the crimes of her ſubjects. The Engliſh reſident went now to the earl of Lenox and the lord Darnley, and charged them to return to England. The former expreſſed an apprehenſion of the ſeverity of his queen, and ſought an aſſurance of her favour before he could venture to viſit her dominions. The latter, exerting greater foritude, told him, that he acknowledged no duty or obedience but to the queen of Scots. The reſident treating this anſwer as diſreſpectful to Elizabeth, turned his back upon the lord Darnley, and retired without making any reverence, or bidding him an adieu.</p><p>The behaviour of Elizabeth, ſo fierce and ſo perfidious, was well calculated to confirm all the intentions of Mary; and this, doubtleſs, was one of the motives with which ſhe was actuated. But while the queen of Scots was eager to accompliſh her marriage, ſhe was not inattentive to the riſing troubles of her country. The parliament which ſhe had appointed could not now be held: it was therefore prorogued to a more diſtant day; and the violence of the times did not then permit it to aſſemble. By letters ſhe invited to her, with all their retainers, the moſt powerful and the moſt eminent of her ſubjects. Bothwel was recalled anew from France; and by general proclamations ſhe ſummoned to her ſtandard the united force of her kingdom. The caſtle of Edinburgh was likewiſe provided amply with ſtores and ammunition, that, in the event of misfortunes, it might afford her a retreat and defence. The alacrity with which her ſubjects flocked to her from every quarter, informed her of her power and popularity; and while it ſtruck Murray and his adherents with the danger to which they were expoſed, it declared to them the opinion entertained by the nation of the iniquity and the ſelfiſhneſs of their proceedings.</p><p>On the 29th of July 1565, the ceremony of marriage between the queen and lord Darnley was performed. The latter had been previouſly created duke of</p></body></text></TEI>