<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:59:27Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>cauſe of ſuch ſuſpicion, the juſtice may grant a warrant to ſearch not only that houſe but other ſuſpected places; and to attach the goods, and the party in whoſe cuſtody they are found, and bring them before him or ſome other juſtice, to give an account how he came by them, and to abide ſuch order as to law ſhall appertain; which warrant ſhould be directed to the conſtable or other public officer, who may enter a ſuſpected houſe and make ſearch.</p><p>SEARCHER, an officer in the cuſtoms, whoſe buſineſs it is to ſearch and examine ſhips outward bound, if they have any prohibited goods on board, &amp;c. (12 Car. II.) There are alſo ſearchers of leather, &amp;c. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Alnager.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Searcher,</hi> in ordnance, is an iron ſocket with branches, from four to eight in number, a little bent outwards, with ſmall points at their ends; to this ſocket is fixed a wooden handle, from eight to twelve feet long, of about an inch and a quarter diameter. After the gun has been fired, this ſearcher is introduced into it, and turned round, in order to diſcover the cavities within. The diſtances of theſe cavities, if any be found, are then marked on the outſide with chalk, when another ſearcher that has only one point, about which a mixture of wax and tallow is put, is introduced to take the impreſſion of the holes; and if there be any hole, a quarter of an inch deep, or of any conſiderable length, the gun is rejected as unſerviceable.</p><p>SEARCLOTH, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Cerecloth,</hi> in ſurgery, a form of external remedy ſomewhat harder than an unguent, yet ſofter than an emplaſter, though it is frequently uſed both for the one and the other. The cerecloth is always ſuppoſed to have wax in its compoſition, which diſtinguiſhes and even denominates it. In effect, when a liniment or unguent has wax enough in it, it does not differ from a cerecloth.</p><p>SEASIN, in a ſhip, the name of a rope by which the boat rides by the ſhip’s ſide when in harbour, &amp;e.</p><p>@@SEASONING, the firſt illneſs to which perſons habituated to colder climates are ſubject on their arrival in the Weſt Indies. This ſeaſoning, unleſs they live very temperately, or are in a proper habit of body (tho' ſome people are unmoleſted for many months), ſeldom ſuffers them to remain long before it makes its appearance in ſome mode or other; particularly if at firſt they expoſe themſelves in a ſhower of rain, or too long in the ſun, or in the night-air; or when the body is much heated, if they drink large draughts of cold liquors, br bathe in cold water; or uſe much exerciſe; or commit exceſs in drinking wine or ſpirits; or by heating the body and inflaming the blood; or by ſubjecting themſelves to any cauſe that may ſuddenly check perſpiration, which at firſt is generally exceſſive.</p><p>Some people, from a favourable ſtate of body, have no ſeaſoning. Thin people, and very young people, are moſt likely to eſcape it. Women generally do from their temperance, and perhaps their menſtruation contributes to their ſecurity; indeed hot climates are favourable to the delicacy of their habits, and ſuitable to their modes of life. Some eſcape by great regularity of living; ſome, by the breaking out of the raſh, called the <hi rend="italic">prickly heat;</hi> ſome by a great degree of perſpiration; and ſome by obſervſing a cooling regimen. The disorders are various that conſtitute this ſeaſoning of <hi rend="italic">new-comers</hi> as they are called; depending on age, conſtitution, and habit of body. But all ſeaſoning diieaſes are of the inflammatory kind; and yield to antiphlogiſtic treatment proportioned to their violence. When all precaution to guard againſt ſickneſs has failed, and prudence proved abortive to new-comers, they will have this comfort at leaſt for their pains, that their diſorders will ſeldom be ſevere or expenſive, and will generally have a ſpeedy termination; and that their ſeaſoning, as it is emphatically called, will be removed by bleeding, a doſe of ſalts, reſt, and a cooling regimen.</p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Seasoning</hi><hi rend="italic"> of Timber.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Timber.</hi></p><p>SEASONS, in coſmography, certain portions or quarters of the year, diſtinguiſhed by the ſigns which the sun then enters, or by the meridian altitudes of the ſun; conſequent on which are different temperatures of the air, different works in tillage, &amp;c. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Weather.</hi></p><p>The year is divided into four ſeaſons, ſpring, ſummer, autumn, and winter. The beginnings and endings of each whereof, see under its proper article. It is to be obſerved, the ſeaſons anciently began differently from what they now do: witneſs the old verſes,</p><p><hi rend="italic">Dat Clemens hyemem; dot Petrus ver cathedratus;</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Æstuat Urbanus; autumnat Bartholomaus.</hi></p><p>SEAT, in the manege, is the poſture or ſituation of a horſeman upon the ſaddle.</p><p>SEATON, a ſmall fiſhing town on the ſouth coaſt of Devon, between Lyme and Sidmouth. Rildon ſays “our learned antiquarians would have it to be that <hi rend="italic">Maridunum</hi> whereof Antonine ſpake, placed between Dunnovaria and Iſca; for <hi rend="italic">Maridunum</hi> in Britiſh is the ſame with <hi rend="italic">Seaton</hi> in Engliſh, ‘a town upon a-hill by the ſea-ſide.” This place is memorable for the Daniſh princes landing there in the year 937.</p><p>SEBACIC <hi rend="smallcaps">acid,</hi> the acid procured from fat. To obtain it, let ſome ſuet be melted in a ſkillet over the fire, along with ſome quicklime in fine powder, and conſtantly ſtirred, raiſing the fire towards the end of the operation, and taking care to avoid the vapours, which are very offenſive. By this proceſs the ſebacic acid unites with the lime into a ſebat of lime, which is difficultly ſoluble in water; it is, however, ſeparated from the fatty matters with which it is mixed by ſolution in a large quantity of boiling water. From this the neutral ſalt is ſeparated by evaporation; and, to render it pure, is calcined, rediſſolved, and again cryſtallized. After this we pour on a proper quantity of ſulphuric acid, and the ſebacic acid paſſes over by diſtillation. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Fat,</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Chemistry-Index. [</hi></p><p>ST SEBASTIAΝ, a handſome, populous, and ſtrong town of Spain, in the province of Guipuſcoa, with a good and well frequented harbour. It is ſeated at the foot of a mountain; and the harbour ſecured by two moles, and a narrow entrance for the ſhips. The town is ſurrourrded with a double wall, and to the ſea-ſide is fortified with baſtions and half moons. The ſtreets are long, broad, and ſtraight, and paved with white flag- ſtones. At the top of the mountain is a citadel, with a garriſon well ſurniſhed with cannon. The town carries on a conſiderable trade, the greateſt part of which conſiſts of iron and ſteel, which ſome reckon to be the beſt in Europe. They alſo deal in wool, which comes</p><p>@@@ [mu] Moseley on Tropical Diseases.</p></body></text></TEI>