<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:54:54Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>that in ſo advanced a ſtage of their affairs, they might exhibit the determined firmneſs of their reſolutions, and bind to them by an indiſſoluble tie the earl of Huntley and the other perſons who had joined them in conſequence of the Engliſh alliance, they thought of the aſſurance and ſtability of a <hi rend="italic">new league and covenant,</hi> more ſolemn, expreſſive, and reſolute, than any which they had yet entered into and ſubſcribed.</p><p>The nobles, barons, and inferior perſons, who were parties to this bond and aſſociation, bound themſelves in the preſence of Almighty God, as a ſociety, and as individuals, to advance and ſet forward the reformation of religion, and to procure, by every poſſible means, the true preaching of the goſpel, with the proper adminiſtration of the ſacraments, and the other ordinances in connection with it. Deeply affected, at the ſame time, with the miſconduct of the French ſtateſmen, who had been promoted to high offices; with the oppreſſions of the French mercenaries, whom the queen- dowager kept up and maintained under the colour of authority; with the tyranny of their captains; and with the manifeſt danger of conqueſt to which the country was expoſed, by different fortifications upon the ſea-coaſt, and by other dangerous innovations; they promiſed and engaged, generally and individually, to join with the queen of England’s army, and to concur in an honeſt, plain, and unreſerved reſolution to expel all foreigners from the realm, as oppreſſors of public liberty; that, by recovering the ancient rights, privileges, and freedom of their nation, they might live for the future under the due obedience of their king and queen, be ruled by the laws and cuſtoms of the country, and by officers and ſtateſmen born and educated among them. It was likewiſe contracted and agreed by</p><p>the ſubſcribers to this bond and covenant, that no private intelligence by writing or meſſage, or communication of any kind, ſhould be kept up with their adverſaries; and that all perſons who reſiſted the godly enterprise in which they were united, ſhould be regarded as their enemies, and reduced to ſubjection and obedience.</p><p>When the ſtrong and fervid ſentiment and expreſſion of this new aſſociation were communicated to the queen-dowager, ſhe reſigned herſelf to ſorrow. Her mind, inclined to deſpondence by the increaſe of her malady, felt the more intenſely the cruel diffractions and diſquiets into which the kingdom had been driven by the ambition of France, her own doating affection for the princes of Lorraine, and the vain prognoſtſeations of flatterers and courtiers. In the agony of paſſion, ſhe beſought the malediction and curſe of God to alight upon all thoſe who had counſelled her to perſecute the preachers, and to refuſe the petitions of the moſt honourable portion of her ſubjects.</p><p>In the mean time the ſiege of Leith was proſecuted. But the ſtrength of the garriſon amounting to more than 4000 ſoldiers, the operations of the beſiegers were flow and languid. An accidental fire in the town, which deſtroyed many houſes and a great part of the public granary, afforded them an opportunity of playing their artillery with ſome advantage; and a few days aſter they made a general aſſault. But the ſcaling- ladders which were applied to the walls being too ſhort, and Sir James Croft, who had been gained to the queen- dowager, having acted a treacherous part, the attempt</p><p>failed of ſucceſs, and 1000 men were deſtroyed. The combined armies, however, did not loſe their reſolution or their hopes. The Engliſh and Scots animated the conſtancy of one another; and in the ratification of the treaty of Berwick, which was now made, a new ſource of cordiality opened itſelf. Letters alſo had come from the duke of Norfolk, promiſing a powerful reinforcement, giving the expectation of his taking upon him the command of the troops in perſon, and ordering his pavilion to be erected in the camp. Leith began to feel the miſery of famine, and the French to give themſelves to deſpair. The beſiegers abounded in every thing; and the arrival of 2000 men, the expected reinforcement from England, gave them the moſt deciſive ſuperiorſty over their adverſaries. Frequent ſallies were made by the garriſon, and they were always unſucceſsful. Diſcouraged by defeats, depreſſed with the want of proviſions, and languiſhing under the negligence of France, they were ready to ſubmit themſelves to the mercy of the Congregation.</p><p>Amidſt this diſtreſs the queen-dowager, wafted with a lingering diſtemper and with grief, expired in the caſtle of Edinburgh. A few days before her death, ſhe invited to her the duke of Chatelherault, the lord James Stuart, and the earls of Argyle, Glencairn, and Mariſchal, to bid them a laſt adieu. She expreſſed to them her ſorrow for the troubles of Scotland, and made it her earneſt ſuit, that they would conſult their conſtitutional liberties, by diſmiſſing the French and Engliſh from their country; and that they would preſerve a dutiful obedience to the queen their ſovereign. She profeſſed an unlimited forgiveneſs of all the injuries which had been done to her; and entreated their pardon for the offences ſhe had committed againſt them. In token of her kindneſs and charity, ſhe then embraced them by turns; and, while the tear ſtarted in her eye, preſented to them a cheerful and ſmiling aſpect. After this interview, the ſhort portion of life which remained to her was dedicated to religion; and that ſhe might allure the Congregation to be compaſſionate to her Popiſh ſubjects and her French adherents, ſhe flattered them, by calling John Willocks, one of the moſt popular of their preachers, to aſſiſt and comfort her by his exhortations and prayers. He made long diſcourſes to her about the abominations of the maſs; but ſhe appears to have died in the communion of the Romiſh church; and her body being tranſported to France, was depoſited in the monaſtery of St Peter, at Rheims, in Champagne, where her sister Renée was an abbeſs.</p><p>The death of the queen-dowager, at a period ſo critical, broke altogether the ſpirit of the French troops. They were blocked up ſo completely, that it was almoſt impoſſible for any ſupplies to reach them either by ſea or land; and France had delayed ſo long to fulfil its magnificent promiſes, that it was no longer in a capacity to take any ſteps towards their accompliſhment. Its internal diſtreſs and diſquiets were multiplying. The nobility, impoveriſhed by wars, were courting the rewards of ſervice, and ſtruggling in hoſtility. The clergy were avaricious, ignorant, and vindictive. The populace, knowing no trade but arms, offered their ſwords to the factious. Francis II. the huſhand of Mary, was. without dignity or underſtanding. Catharine de Medicis his mother was full of artifice and falſehood. Inſurrections were dreaded in every pro-</p></body></text></TEI>