<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-14T17:57:44Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>by Montſaucon. That they are found too in the <hi rend="italic">Codex Vaticanus,</hi>
                though not frequently, is related by Birch in his <hi rend="italic"
                    >Prolegomena,</hi> p. 14.</p>
            <p>As the fact has not been generally known, that the ancients pointed their
                manuscripts, and as it is an important and intereſting fact, we ſhall preſent our
                readers with the firſt ſix lines of St John’s Goſpel, as they are pointed in the
                Alexandrine manuſcript:</p>
            <p>ΕΝΑΡΧΗΝΟΛΟΓΟΣΚΑΙΟΛΟΓΟΣΗΝ</p>
            <p>ΠΡΟΣΤΟΝΘΝ ΚΑΙΘΣΗΝΟΛΟΓΟΣ·</p>
            <p>ΟϓΤΟΣΗΝΕΝΑΡΧΗΠΡΟΣΤΟΝΘΝ</p>
            <p>ΠΑΝϓΑΔΙΑϓΤΟϓΕΓΟ·ΚΑΙΧΩ</p>
            <p>ΡΕΙΣΑϓΤΟϓΕΓΕΝΕΤΟΟϓΔΕΕΝ·</p>
            <p>ΟΓΕΓΟΝΕΝΕΝΑϓΤΩΖΩΗΗΝ·</p>
            <p>Whether any points for marking the ſenſe were uſed by the apoſtles, cannot be
                determined; but the points now in uſe have been invented ſince.</p>
            <p>In the fourth century, Jerome began to add the comma and colon to the Latin verſion;
                and they were then inſerted in many more ancient manuſcripts. In the fifth century,
                Euthalius a deacon of Alexandria divided the New Teſtament into lines. This diviſion
                was regulated by the ſenſe, ſo that each line ended where ſome pauſe was to be made
                in ſpeaking. And when a copyiſt was diſpoſed to contract his ſpace, and therefore
                crowded the lines into each other, he then placed a point where Euthalius had
                terminated the line. In the eighth century, the ſtroke was invented which we call a
                comma. In the Latin manuſcripts, Jerome’s points were introduced by Paul Warnfried
                and Alcuin, at the command of Charlemagne. In the ninth century, the Greek note of
                interrogation(;) was firſt uſed. At the invention of printing the editors placed the
                points arbitrarily, probably without beſtowing the neceſſary attention; and
                Stephens, in particular, varied his points in every edition @@<hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >(d).</hi></p>
            <p>The meaning of many paſſages in the Scripture has been altered by falſe pointing. We
                ſhall produce one inſtance of this: Mat. v. 34. is commonly pointed in this manner,
                εγω δε λεγω υμιν, μη ομοσαι ολως· μητε εν τω ϱραχω<hi rend="italic">, </hi>and
                conſequently tranſlated, “But I ſay unto you, ſwear not at all.” But if, inſtead of
                the colon placed after ολως we ſubſtitute a comma, the tranſlation will be, “But I
                ſay to you that you ought by no means to ſwear, either by heaven, for it is his
                throne, or by earth, for it is his footſtool.” The command of Chriſt therefore
                applies particularly to the abuſe of oaths among the Phariſees, who on every trivial
                occaſion ſwore by the heaven, the earth, the temple, the head, &amp;c. but it
                implies no prohibition to take an oath in the name of the Deity on ſolemn and
                important occaſions.</p>
            <p>The ancients divided the New Teſtament into two kinds of chapters, ſome longer and
                ſome ſhorter. This method appears to be more ancient than St Jerome, for be expunged
                a paſſage from the New Teſtament which makes an entire chapter. The longer kind of
                chapters were called <hi rend="italic">breves,</hi> the ſhorter <hi rend="italic"
                    >capitula.</hi> St Mat</p>
            <p>thew contained, according to Jerome, 68 breves; Mark contained 48; Luke 83; and John
                18. All the evangeliſts together conſiſted of 217 breves and 1126 capitula. The
                inventor of our modern diviſion into chapters was Hugo de S. Caro, a French
                Dominican friar who lived in the 13th century.</p>
            <p>The ancients had two kinds of verſes, one of which they called ςιχοι, and the other
                ρηματα. The r<hi rend="italic">emata </hi>were lines which contained a certain
                number of letters, like our printed books, and therefore often broke off in the
                middle of a word. Joſephus’s 20 books of Antiquities contained 60,000 of them,
                though in Ittiquis’s edition there are only 40,000 broken lines.</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Stichi</hi> were lines meaſured by the ſenſe: according to an
                ancient written lift mentioned by Father Simin, there were in the New Teſtament
                18,612 of theſe.</p>
            <p>The verſes into which the New Teſtament is now divided are more modern, and an
                imitation of the diviſion of the Old Teſtament. Robert Stephens, the firſt inventor,
                introduced them in his edition in the year 1551. He made this diviſion on a journey
                from Lyons to Paris; and, as his ſon Henry, tells us in the preface to the
                Concordance of the New Teſtament, he made it <hi rend="italic">inter
                    equitandum.</hi> This phraſe probably means, that when he was weary of riding,
                he amuſed himſelf with this work at his inn.</p>
            <p>This invention of the learned printer was ſoon introduced into all the editions of
                the New Teſtament; and it muſt be confeſſed, that in conſulting and quoting the
                Scriptures, and in framing concordances for them, a ſubdiviſion into minute parts is
                of the greateſt utility. But all the purpoſes of utility could ſurely have been
                gained, without adopting the haſty and indigeſted diviſion of Stephens, which often
                breaks the ſenſe in pieces, renders plain paſſages obſcure, and difficult paſſages
                unintelligible. To the injudicious diviſion of Stephens we may aſcribe a great part
                of the difficulties which attend the interpretation of the New Teſtament, and a
                great many of thoſe abſurd opinions which have diſgraced the ages of the
                Reformation. For as ſeparate verſes appear to the eyes of the learned, and to the
                minds of the unlearned, as ſo many detached ſentences, they have been ſuppoſed to
                contain complete ſenſe, and they have accordingly been explained without any regard
                to the context, and often in direct oppoſition to it. Were any modern hiſtory or
                continued diſcourſe divided into fragments with as little regard to the ſenſe, we
                ſhould ſoon find, that as many oppoſite meanings could be forced upon them as have
                been forced upon the books of the New Teſtament. The diviſion into verſes has been
                ſtill more injurious to the Epiſtles than to the Goſpels, for there is a cloſe
                connection between the different parts of the Epiſtles, which the verſes entirely
                diſſolve. It is therefore to be wiſhed that this diviſion into verſes were laid
                aſide. The Scriptures ought to be divided into paragraphs, according to the ſenſe;
                and the figures ought to be thrown into the margin. In this way, the figures will
                retain their utility</p>
            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">@@@(d)</hi> The reader will perceive that the account of the
                origin of points is different from that given under <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Punctuation.</hi> But the beſt authors differ upon this ſubject. We ſhall
                perhaps reconcile the difference, by ſuppoſing that points were invented at the time
                here mentioned, but were not in general uſe till the time mentioned under the
                article <hi rend="smallcaps">Punctuation.</hi></p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
