<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-14T17:58:44Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>ſecond and third of theſe claſſes, and even ſome referred to the firſt, are not
                vegetables, but animals, or the productions of animals. See <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Corallina, Madrepora, Spongia.</hi> Sea-plants, then, properly ſpeaking, belong
                to the claſs of cryptogamia, and the order of algae; and, according to Bomare, are
                all comprehended under the genus of fucus. We may alſo add ſeveral ſpecies of the
                ulva and conferva and the ſargazo. The fuci and marine ulvæ are immerſed in the ſea,
                are ſeſſile, and without root. The marine confervæ are either ſeſſile or floating.
                The ſargazo grows beyond ſoundings.</p>
            <p>As ſome ſpecies of the fucus, when dried and preſerved, are extermely beautiful, the
                curious, and eſpecially thoſe who proſecute the ſtudy of botany, muſt be anxious to
                know the beſt method of preſerving them, without deſtroying their colour and beauty.
                The following method is recommended by M. Mauduyt. Take a ſheet of paper, or rather
                of paſteboard, and cover it with varniſh on both ſides; and having rowed in a boat
                to the rock where the fucus abounds, plunge your varniſhed paper into the water,
                and, detaching the fucus, receive it upon the paper. Agitate the paper gently in the
                water, that the plant may be properly ſpread over it; and lift them up together
                ſoftly out of the water: then fix down with pins the ſtrong ſtalks, that they may
                not be diſplaced, and leave the plant lying upon the varniſhed paper to dry in the
                open air. When it is fully dry, the different parts will retain their poſition, and
                the plant may be preſerved within the leaves of a book. If you wiſh to free it from
                the ſlime and ſalt which adheres to it, it may be waſhed gently in freſh water,
                after being removed from the rock on which it grew.</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">SEA-Serpent,</hi> a monſtrous creature, ſaid to inhabit the
                northern ſeas about Greenland and the coaſts of Norway. The following marvellous
                account of this monſter is given by Guthrie. “In 1756, one of them was ſhot by a
                maſter of a ſhip: its head reſembled that of a horſe; the mouth was large and black,
                as were the eyes, a white mane hanging from its neck: it floated on the ſurface of
                the water, and held its head at leaſt two feet out of the ſea: between the head and
                neck were ſeven or eight folds, which were very thick; and the length of this ſnake
                was more than 100 yards, ſome ſay fathoms. They have a remarkable averſion to the
                ſmell of caſtor; for which reaſon, ſhip, boat, and bark matters provide themſelves
                with quantities of that drug, to prevent being overſet, the ſerpent’s olfactory
                nerves being remarkably exquiſite. The particularities related of this animal would
                be incredible, were they not atteſted upon oath Egede, a very reputable author,
                ſays, that on the 6th day of July 1734, a large and frightful ſeamon er raiſed
                itſelf ſo high out of the water, that its head reached above the main-top-maſt of
                the ſhip; that it</p>
            <p>had a long ſharp ſnout, broad paws, and ſpouted water like a whale; that the body
                ſeemed to be covered with ſcales; the ſkin was uneven and wrinkled, and the lower
                part was formed like a ſnake. The body of this monſter is ſaid to be as thick as a
                hogſhead; his ſkin is variegated like a tortoiſe ſhell; and his excrement, which
                floats upon the ſurface of the water, is corroſive.” Not- withſtanding the belief of
                Guthrie, and the teſtimony which he produces, we cannot help doubting of the
                exiſtence of the ſea-ſerpent. Its bulk is ſaid to be ſo disproportionate to all the
                known animals of our globe, that it requires more than ordinary evidence to render
                    <hi rend="italic">it </hi>credible; but the evidence which is offered is ſo very
                feeble and unſatisfactory, that no man of ſound judgement would think it ſufficient
                to eſtabliſh the truth of an extraordinary fact.</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">SEA-Sickneſs,</hi> a diſorder incident to moſt perſons on their
                firſt going to ſea, occaſioned by the agitation of the veſſel. In voyages,
                ſea-ſickneſs, though it continues in general only for the firſt day or two, is
                extremely haraſſing to ſome people at intervals, eſpecially on any increaſed motion
                of the veſſel. Sometimes, by long continuance, it cauſes fever, headach, quick
                pulſe, thirſt, white tongue, and a total deprivation of the retention of the
                ſtomach; evils which are always difficult to remove, and frequently terminate only
                with the voyage.</p>
            <p>This indiſpoſition is conſiderably alleviated by a ſmall tea ſpoonful of ether, taken
                now and then in a glaſs of water, and applying ſome of it to the temples and
                noſtrils. The ancient writers recommend acid fruits, bread and vegetables ſoaked in
                vinegar, after the ſtomach has been cleanſed by vomiting; but not to attempt to
                ſuppreſs the vomiting until that end was obtained. An old remedy for ſea-ſickneſs,
                and a very common one among ſailors, is a draught or two of ſea water; which,
                though, a diſguſting medicine at ſuch a time, yet where the firſt paſſages are foul
                and loaded, generally produces the deſired effect when the perturbation it occaſions
                ceaſes.</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Sea-</hi><hi rend="italic">Star.</hi> See <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">AsterIas.</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">SEA-Urchine.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Echinus.</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Sea-</hi><hi rend="italic">Water,</hi> the ſalt water of
                the ſea. The principal ſalts contained in ſea-water are, 1ſt, Common marine or
                culinary ſalt, compounded of foſſil alkali or ſoda and marine acid; 2dly, A ſalt
                formed by the union of the ſame acid with magneſian earth; and, laſtly, A ſmall
                quantity of ſelenite. The quantity of ſaline matter contained in a pint of
                ſea-water, in the Britiſh ſeas, is, according to Neumann, about one ounce in each
                pint @@<hi rend="smallcaps">(a).</hi></p>
            <p>The ſaltneſs of this water is judged to ariſe from great multitudes both of mines and
                mountains of ſalt diſperſed here and there in the depths of the ſea. Dr Halley
                ſuppoſes that it is probable the greateſt part of the ſea-ſalt, and of all ſalt
                lakes, as the Caſpian Sea, the Dead Sea, the Lake of Mexico, and the Titicaca</p>
            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">@@@(a) </hi>In Sir Torbern Bergman’s analyſis of ſea-water taken
                up in the beginning of June 1776, about the latitude of the Canaries, from the depth
                of 60 fathoms, the ſolid contents of a pint of the water were,</p>
            <p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell></cell>
                        <cell>Grs. </cell>
                        <cell></cell>
                        <cell></cell>
                        <cell></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Of common ſalt</cell>
                        <cell>253 <hi rend="superscript">6</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">11</hi></cell>
                        <cell></cell>
                        <cell></cell>
                        <cell></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Salited magneſia</cell>
                        <cell>69<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">11</hi></cell>
                        <cell>3.</cell>
                        <cell>϶</cell>
                        <cell>Grs.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Gypſum</cell>
                        <cell>8<hi rend="superscript">2</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">11</hi></cell>
                        <cell>or 5.</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>10<hi rend="superscript">9</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">11</hi></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Total</cell>
                        <cell>330<hi rend="superscript">9</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">11</hi></cell>
                        <cell></cell>
                        <cell></cell>
                        <cell></cell>
                    </row>
                </table></p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
