<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-14T17:58:42Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>feet, and in ſome places even more. The tide generally riſes higher in the evening
                than in the morning: on the coaſt of Britain this holds in winter, but in ſummer the
                morning tides are higheſt. In ſome ſeas it is ſaid that there are no tides. This
                cannot be owing to their being ſurrounded by land, becauſe there is a tide in the
                lakes of North America. For an explanation of theſe and other phenomena we refer to
                the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Tide.</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Sea-</hi><hi rend="italic">Air,</hi> that part of the
                atmoſphere which is above the ſea.</p>
            <p>Sea-air has been found ſalubrious and remarkably beneficial in ſome diſtempers. This
                may be owing to its containing a greater portion of oxigenous gas or vital air, and
                being leſs impregnated with noxious vapours than the land. Dr Ingenhouſz made
                ſeveral experiments to aſcertain the ſalubrity of ſea-air. By mixing equal meaſures
                of common air and nitrous air, he found, that at Graveſend, they occupied about 104,
                or one meaſure, and <hi rend="superscript">4</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">100</hi> of a
                meaſure: whereas on ſea, about three miles from the mouth of the Thames, two
                meaſures of air (one of common and one of nitrous air) occupied from 0.91 to 0.94.
                He attempted a ſimilar experiment on the middle of the channel between the Engliſh
                coaſt and Oſtend; but the motion of the ſhip rendered it impracticable. He found
                that in rainy and windy weather the ſea-air contained a ſmaller quantity of vital
                air than when the weather was calm. On the ſea-ſhore at Oſtend it occupied from
                    94<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">2</hi> to 97; at Bruges he
                found it at 105; and at Antwerp 109<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi
                    rend="subscript">2</hi>. Dr Ingenhouſz thus concludes his paper:</p>
            <p>It appears, from theſe experiments, that the air at ſea and cloſe to it is in general
                purer and fitter for animal life than the air on the land, though it ſeems to be
                ſubject to the ſame inconſtancy in its degree of purity with that of the land; ſo
                that we may now with more confidence ſend our patients, labouring under conſumptive
                diſorders, to the ſea, or at leaſt to places ſituated cloſe to the ſea, which have
                no marſhes in their neighbourhood. It ſeems alſo probable, that the air will be
                found in general much purer far from the land than near the ſhore, the former being
                never ſubject to be mixed with land air.</p>
            <p>Dr Damman, an eminent phyſician and profeſſor royal of midwifery at Ghent, told Dr
                Ingenhouſz, that when he was formerly a practitioner at Oſtend, during ſeven years,
                he found the people there remarkably healthy; that nothing was rarer there than to
                ſee a patient labouring under a conſumption or aſthma, a malignant, putrid, or
                ſpotted fever; that the diſeaſe to which they are the moſt ſubject, is a regular
                intermittent fever in autumn, when ſudden tranſitions from hot to cold weather
                happen.</p>
            <p>People are in general very healthy at Gibraltar, though there are very few trees near
                that place; which Dr Ingenhouſz thinks is owing to the purity of the air, ariſing
                from the neighbourhood of the ſea.</p>
            <p>Moſt ſmall iſlands are very healthy.</p>
            <p>At Malta people are little ſubject to diſeaſes, and live to a very advanced age.</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">SEA-Anemony.</hi> See ANIMAL-Flower.</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">SEA-Bear and SEA-Calf: See PHOCA.</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sea-Cow.</hi><hi rend="italic"> See </hi><hi
                    rend="italic smallcaps">Trichecus.</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">SEA-Crow, MIRE-Crow,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Pewit,</hi> See <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Larus.</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">SEA-Dead,</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Asphaltites.</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">SEA-Devil.</hi> See LOPHIUS.</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">SEA-Dragοn,</hi> a monſter of a very ſingular nature. In the
                Gentleman’s Magazine for the year 1749, we have the account of a ſeadragon which was
                ſaid to be taken between Orford and Southwould, on the coaſt of Suffolk, and
                afterwards carried round the country as a curioſity by the fiſherman who caught
                it.</p>
            <p>“Its head and tail (ſays the writer) reſemble thoſe of an alligator; it has two large
                fins, which ſerve it both to ſwim and to fly; and though they were ſo dried that I
                could not extend them, yet they appear, by the folds, to be ſhaped like thoſe which
                painters have given to dragons and other winged monſters that ſerve as ſupporters to
                coats of arms. Its body is covered with impenetrable ſcales; its legs have two
                joints, and its feet are hoofed like thoſe of an aſs: it has five rows of very white
                and ſharp teeth in each jaw, and is in length about four feet, though it was longer
                when alive, it having ſhrunk as it became dry.</p>
            <p>“It was caught in a net with mackerel; and being dragged on ſhore, was knocked down
                with a ſtretcher or boat-hook. The net being opened, it ſuddenly ſprung up, and flew
                above 50 yards: the man who firſt ſeized it had ſeveral of his fingers bitten off;
                and the wound mortifying, he died. It afterwards faſtened on the man’s arm who ſhows
                it, and lacerated it ſo much, that the muſcles are ſhrunk, and the hand and fingers
                diſtorted; the wound is not yet healed, and is thought to be incurable. It is ſaid
                by ſome to have been deſcribed by naturaliſts under the name of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Sea- dragοn."</hi> See Plate CCCCXLIX.</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">SEA-Gage.</hi> See <hi rend="italic">Sea-GAGE. </hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Sea-</hi><hi rend="italic">Hare.</hi> See <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">LaplysiA.</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">SEA-Horse,</hi> in ichthyology, the Engliſh name of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Hippocamus.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Syngnathus.</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="italic smallcaps">SEA-</hi><hi rend="italic">Lemon.</hi> See <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Doris.</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">SEA-Liοn.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Phoca.</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">SEA-Mall,</hi> or <hi rend="italic smallcaps">Sea-Mew.</hi> See <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Larus.</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sea-</hi>Man.<hi rend="italic"> See </hi><hi
                    rend="italic smallcaps">Mermaid.</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">SEA-Marks.</hi> The erection of beacons, light-houſes, and
                ſea-marks, is a branch of the royal <hi rend="smallcaps">prerogative. </hi>By 8
                Eliz. 13. the corporation of the Trinity-houſe are empowered to ſet up any beacons
                or ſea-marks wherever they ſhall think them neceſſary; and if the owner of the land
                or any other perſon ſhall deſtroy them, or take down any ſteeple, tree, or other
                known ſea-mark, he ſhall forfeit 100 l. Sterling; or, in caſe of inability to pay
                it, he ſhall be <hi rend="italic">ip</hi>ſo f<hi rend="italic">acto</hi>
                outlawed.</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">SEA-Needle, Gar fish.</hi> See Esox.</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">SEA-Nettle.</hi> See <hi rend="italic smallcaps">Animal-</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Flower.</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Sea-Pie,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Oyster-Catcher.</hi>
                See <hi rend="smallcaps">HæmAtopUs.</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Sea-</hi><hi rend="italic">Plants,</hi> are thoſe
                vegetables that grow in ſalt-water within the ſhores of the ſea. The old botaniſts
                divided theſe into three claſſes. 1. The firſt claſs, according to their
                arrangement, contained the <hi rend="italic">Algae,</hi> the s<hi rend="italic"
                    >uci,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">ſea-moſſes</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                    >confervas,</hi> and the different ſpecies of ſponges. 2. The ſecond contained
                ſubſtances of a hard texture, like ſtone or horn, which ſeem to have been of the
                ſame nature with what we call zoophyta<hi rend="italic">, </hi>with this difference,
                that we refer ſponges to this claſs and not to the firſt. The third claſs was the
                ſame with our <hi rend="italic">lithophyta,</hi> comprehending <hi rend="italic"
                    >corals, mandrepora,</hi> &amp;c. It is now well known that the genera belonging
                to the</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
