<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-14T17:55:29Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>point for which her enemies had laboured with a wicked and relentleſs policy.</p>
            <p>Mary was unfortunate in her ſecond marriage, but much more ſo in her third. Bothwel
                had neither talents for buſineſs nor affection for his wife. Ambitious and jealous
                to the laſt degree, he ſought only to eſtabliſh himſelf in power, while his fears
                and jealouſies made him take the moſt improper means. The marriage had already
                thrown the nation into a ferment; and the leaſt improper exerciſe of power, or
                indeed an appearance of it, even on the part of the queen, would be ſufficient to
                ruin them both for ever. Perhaps the only thing which at this juncture could have
                pacified the people, would have been the total abolition of Popery, which they had
                often required. But this was not thought of. Inſtead of taking any ſtep to pleaſe
                the people, Bothwel endeavoured to force the earl of Marre to deliver up the young
                prince to his cuſtody.— This was ſuſſicient to make the flame, which had hitherto
                been ſmothered, break out with all its violence. It was univerſally believed that
                Bothwel, who had been the murderer of the father, deſigned to take away the life of
                the ſon alſo, and the queen was thought to participate in all his crimes. The earl
                of Murray now took advantage of the queen’s unfortunate ſituation to aggrandize
                himſelf and effect her ruin. After having viſited the Engliſh court, he proceeded to
                France, where he aſſiduouſly diſſeminated all the reports againſt the queen which
                were injurious to her reputation; and where, without being expoſed to ſuſpicion, he
                was able to maintain a cloſe correſpondence with his friends Morton and Lethington,
                and to inſpirit their machinations. His aſſociates, true to his ambition and their
                own, had promoted all the ſchemes of Bothwel upon the queen with a power and
                influence which had inſured their ſucceſs. In confederacy with the earl of Murray
                himſelf, they had conſpired with him to murder the king. Aſſiſted with the weight of
                the earl of Murray, they had managed his trial, and operated the verdict which
                acquitted him. By the ſame arts, and with the ſame views, they had joined with him
                to procure the bond of the nobles recommending him to the queen as a huſband,
                aſſerting his integrity and innocence, recounting his noble qualities, expreſſing an
                unalterable reſolution to ſupport the marriage againſt every oppoſer and adversary,
                and recording a wiſh that a defection from its objects and purpoſes ſhould be
                branded with everlaſting ignominy, and held out as a moſt faithleſs and perjured
                treachery. When the end, however, was accompliſhed for which they had been ſo
                zealous, and when the marriage of the queen was actually celebrated, they laid aſide
                the pretence of frſendſhip, and were in haſte to entitle themſelves to the ignominy
                which they had invited to fall upon them. The murder of the king, the guilt of
                Bothwel, his acquittal, his divorce, and his marriage, became the topics of their
                complaints and declamation. Upon the foundation of this hated</p>
            <p>marriage, they even ventured privately to infer the privity of the queen to all his
                iniquity and tranſactions; and this ſtep ſeemed doubtleſs, to the maſs of her own
                ſubjects and to more diſtant obſervers, a ſtrong confirmation of all the former
                ſuſpicions to her ſhame which had been circulated with ſo much artifice. Their
                imputations and devices excited againſt her, both at home and abroad, the moſt
                indignant and humiliating odium. Amidſt the ruins of her fame, they thought to bury
                for ever her tranquillity and peace; and in the convuiſions they had meditated, they
                already were anticipating the downfal of Bothwel, and ſnatching at the crown that
                tottered on her head.</p>
            <p>But while this cabal were proſecuting their private ends, ſeveral noblemen, not leſs
                remarkable for their virtue than their rank, were eager to vindicate the national
                integrity and honour. The earl of Athol, upon the king’s murder, had retired ſrom
                the court, and was waiting for a proper ſeaſon to take revenge upon the regicides.
                The earl of Marre, uneaſy under the charge of the young prince, was ſolicitous to
                make himſelf ſtrong, that he might guard him from injury. Motives ſo patriotic and.
                honourable drew applauſe and partizans. It was ſufficient to mention them. By
                private conference and debate, an association was inſenſibly formed to puniſh the
                murderers of the king, and to protect the perſon of the prince. Morton and
                Lethington encouraged and promoted a combination from which they might derive ſo
                much advantage. A convention accordingly was appointed at Stirling, for the purpoſe
                oſ conſulting upon the meaſures which it was moſt expedient to purſue, They agreed
                to take an early opportunity to appear in the field; and when they ſeparated, it was
                to collect their retainers, and to inſpirit their paſſions.</p>
            <p>Of this confederacy, the leading men were the earls of Argylc, Athol, Morton, Marre,
                and Glencairn; the lords Hume, Semple, and Lindſay; the barons Kirkaldy of Grange,
                Murray of Tullibardin, and Maitland oſ Lethington. The earl of Bothwel was ſenſible,
                that if he was to ſit upon a throne, he muſt wade to it through blood. By his
                advice, two proclamations were iſſued in the name of the queen, under the pretence
                of ſuppreſſing inſurrections and depredations upon the borders. By the former, ſhe
                called together in arms, upon an early day, the earls, barons, and freeholders of
                the diſtricts of Forfar and Perth, Strathern and Menteith, Clackmannan, Kinroſs, and
                Fife. By the latter ſhe charged the greater and leſſer baronage, with all the
                inferior proprietors oſ the ſhires of Linlithgow and Edinburgh, and the conſtabulary
                of Haddington and Berwick, to prepare immediately for war, and to kecp themſelves in
                readineſs to march upon her order. Theſe military preparations admoniſhed the
                aſſociation to be firm and active, and added to the public, inquietudes and
                diſeontents. The rumours againſt the queen were moſt violent and lourd. It was ſaid,
                that ſhe meant to</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
