<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:54:38Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>had aſked permiſſion from the protector to treat of peace, and the earl of Warwick was appointed to wait for them at Berwick; but none were ever ſent on the part of Scotland. It was not long, therefore, before hostilities were recommenced by the Engliſh. Lord Gray led an army into Scotland, fortified the town of Haddington, took the caſtles of Yeſter and Dalkeitſh, laid waſte the Merſe, and the counties of Eaſt and Mid Lothian. On the other hand, in June 1548, Monſieur de Deſſe, a French officer of great reputation, landed at Leith with 6000 ſoldiers, and a formidable train of artillery.</p><p>In the mean time, the regent was in diſgrace on account of the diſaſter at Pinkey; and the queen-dowager being diſpoſed to ſuperſede his authority, attempted to improve this circumſtance to her own advantage. As ſhe perceived that her power and intereſt could beſt be ſupported by France, ſhe reſolved to enter into the ſtricteſt alliance with that kingdom. It had been propoſed that the dauphin of France ſhould marry the queen of Scotland; and this propoſal now met with many partizans, the hoſtilities of the Engliſh having loſt a great number of friends to the cauſe of that country. It was reſolved to ſend the queen immediately to France, which would remove the cauſe of the preſent contentions, and her ſubſequent marriage with the dauphin would in the fulleſt manner confirm the friendſhip betwixt the two nations. The French government alſo entered deeply into the ſcheme; and in order to promote it made preſents of great value to many of the Scottiſh nobility. The regent himſelf was gained over by a penſion of 12,000 livres, and the title of duke of Chatelherault. Monſieur de Villegagnon, who commanded four galleys in the harbour of Leith, making a feint as if he intended to proceed inſtantly to France, tacked about to the north, and, ſailing round the iſles, received the queen at Dumbarton; whence he conveyed her to France, and delivered her to her uncles the princes of Lorraine, in the month of July 1548.</p><p>Theſe tranſactions did not put an end to the military operations. The ſiege of Haddington had been undertaken as ſoon as the French auxiliaries arrived, and was now conducted with vigour. To reinforce the garriſon, 1500 horſe advanced from Berwick; but an ambuſcade being laid for them, they were intercepted, and almoſt totally deſtroyed. Another body of Engliſh troops, however, which amounted only to 300 perſons, was more ſucceſsful. Eluding the vigilance of the Scots and the French, they were able to enter Haddington, and to ſupply the beſieged with ammunition and proviſions. The lord Seymour, high admiral of England, made a deſcent upon Fife with 1200 men, and ſome pieces of artillery; but was driven back to his ſhips with great ſlaughter by James Stuart, natural brother to the young queen, who oppoſed him at the head of the militia of the county. A ſecond deſcent was made by him at Montroſe; but being equally unſucceſsful there, he was obliged to leave Scotland without performing any important or memorable achievement.</p><p>Having collected an army of 17,000 men, and adding to it 3000 German Proteſtants, the protector put it under the direction of the earl of Shrewſhury. Upon the approach of the Engliſh, Deſſe, though he had</p><p>been reinforced with 15,000 Scots, thought it more prudent to retreat than to hazard a deciſive battle. He raiſed the ſiege of Haddington, and marched to Edinburgh. The earl of Shrewſhury did not follow him to force an engagement; jealouſies had ariſen between the Scots and the French. The inſolence and vanity of the latter, encouraged by their ſuperior ſkill in military arts, had offended the quick and impatient ſpirit of the former. The fretfulneſs of the Scots was augmented by the calamities inſeparable from war; and after the conveyance of the young queen to France, the efficacious and peculiar advantage conferred upon that kingdom by this tranſaction was fully underſtood, and appeared to them to be highly diſgraceful and impolitic. In this ſtate of their humour, Deſſe found not at Edinburgh the reception he expected. The quartering of his ſoldiers produced diſputes, which ended in an inſurrection of the inhabitants. The French fired among the citizens. Several perſons of diſtinction fell, and among theſe were the provoſt of Edinburgh and his ſon. The national diſcontents and inquietudes were driven, by this event, to the moſt dangerous extremity; and Deſſe, who was a man of ability, thought of giving, employment to his troops, and of flattering the people by the ſplendour of ſome martial exploit.</p><p>The earl of Shrewſhury, after ſupplying Haddington with troops, proviſions, and military ſtores, retired with his army into England. Its garriſon, in the enjoyment oſ ſecurity, and unſuſpicious of danger, might be ſurpriſed and overpowered. Marching in the night, Deſſe reached this important poſt; and deſtroying a fort of obſervation, prepared to ſtorm the main gates of the city, when the garriſon took the alarm. A French deſerter pointing a double cannon to the thickeſt ranks of the aſſailants, the ſhot was incredibly deſtructive, and threw them into confusion. In the height of their conſternation, a vigorous ſally was made by the beſieged. Deſſe renewed the aſſault in the morning, and was again diſcomfited. He now turned his arms againſt Broughty caſtle; and, though unable to reduce it, he yet recovered the neighbouring town of Dundee, which had fallen into the poſſeſſion of the enemy. Flume caſtle was retaken by ſtratagem. Deſſe entered Jedburgh, and put its garriſon to the ſword. Encouraged by this ſucceſs, he ravaged the Engliſh borders in different incurſions, and obtained ſeveral petty victories. Leith, which from a ſmall village had grown into a town, was fortified by him; and the iſland of Inchkeith, which is nearly oppoſite to that harbour, being occupied by Engliſh troops, he undertook to expel them, and made them priſoners after a briſk encounter.</p><p>His activity and valour could not, however, compoſe the diſcontents of the Scottiſh nation; and the queen-dowager having written to Henry II. to recal him, he was ſucceeded in his command by Monſieur de Thermes, who was accompanied into Scotland by Monluc biſhop of Valence, a perſon highly eſteemed for his addreſs and ability. This eccleſiaſtic was deſigned to ſupply the loſs of cardinal Beaton, and to diſcharge the office of lord high chancellor of Scotland. But the jealouſies of the nation increaſing, and the queen-dowager herſelf ſuſpecting his ambition and turbulence, he attained not this dignity, and ſoon returned to his own country.</p></body></text></TEI>