<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-14T17:54:01Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>SCOTLAND CONTD <hi rend="smallcaps">James</hi> could never forgive Henry for the loſs
                of his brave officer. He ſent to demand ſatisfaction; but all the anſwer he received
                was, that Barton and his crews were lawleſs pirates, and that what had been done
                againſt them ought never to have been reſented amongſt ſovereign princes. James
                aſſerted, that Barton was no pirate, becauſe he bore his commiſſion; and that he
                ought to have been convicted of piratical acts before he was treated as being guilty
                of them. Henry intimated to James, that he was willing to accommodate the affair by
                way of negociation; but James thought himſelf affronted by the propoſal.</p>
            <p>Various negociations took place concerning this and other affairs till the year 1513;
                when James, though he had for ſome time before been fully reſolved upon a war with
                England, thought it highly neceſſary that it ſhould have the ſanction of his
                parliament, which he aſſembled for that purpoſe. The young nobility were not only
                inſpired with the ſentiments of James, but had been won over by the French; and the
                majority of them, as well as of the clergy (which was ſomewhat extraordinary, as
                James was, in effect, to fight againſt the pope and his allies), were keen for a war
                with England. The old counſellors, on the other hand, who ſaw the flouriſhing ſtate
                of Scotland, ariſing from a long peace and their commerce, which was protected by a
                fleet, dreaded the ruinous conſequences of the war. The queen naturally headed this
                party; and ſhe was joined by the earl oſ Angus and the wiſeſt part of the nobility.
                Their arguments made no impreſſion upon James, who had received a preſent from Louis
                of four ſhips laden with wine and flour, and two ſhips of war completely equipped,
                one of them carrying 34 pieces of braſs ordnance. He promiſed to the French queen,
                upon his honour, that he would take the field againſt the Engliſh; and ſhe had ſent
                him a freſh letter, gently reproaching him for want of gallantry, and for not being
                ſo good as his word. In ſhort, the reaſonings of the wiſeſt and beſt part oſ the
                nobility were over ruled, and the expedition againſt England was reſolved on.</p>
            <p>The earl of Hume, who was chamberlain of Scotland, was, at this juncture, at the head
                of 7000 or 8000 men, with whom he committed prodigious de</p>
            <p>vaſtations on the Engliſh borders. Henry’s queen, Catharine of Spain, whom he had
                left regent of his dominions, iſſued a commiſſion of array, directed to Sir Thomas
                Lovel, knight of the garter, for aſſembling the militia of the counties of
                Nottingham, Derby, Warwick, Leiceſter, Stafford, Rutland, Northampton, and Lincoln.
                The management of the war, however, was chiefly committed to the earl of Surry, who
                aſſembled the militia of Cheſter, Lancaſter, Northumberland, Weſtmoreland,
                Cumberland, and the biſhopric of Durham. The earl of Hume had by this time laid
                great part of Northumberland waſte; and his men were returning home laden with
                booty. The earl of Surry, reſolving to intercept them, ordered Sir William Bul∙ mer
                to form an ambuſh with 1000 archers, at a place called <hi rend="italic"
                    >Broomhou</hi>ſ<hi rend="italic">e,</hi> which was extremely convenient for that
                purpoſe, as the Scots were obliged to paſs that way. As the latter expected nothing
                of that kind, Bulmer executed his orders with great ſucceſs. The archers aſſaulted
                the Scots all at once, and made ſo good uſe of their arrows, that their main body
                was put to flight, 500 were killed, and 400 taken, with the Lord Hume’s ſtandard,
                which he left on the field of battle; the greateſt part of the plunder being
                recovered at the fame time. The commonalty of Scotland termed this expedition of the
                Lord Hume’s the <hi rend="italic">Ill road.</hi></p>
            <p>James was more exaſperated than ever by this defeat, and continued his preparations
                for invading England with additional vigour. His queen did all that became a wiſe
                and prudent wife to divert him. from his fatal purpoſe. She endeavoured to work upon
                his ſuperſtition, by recounting to him her ominous dreams and boding apprehenſions.
                James treating theſe as mere illuſions and fictions of the brain, ſhe had recourſe
                to other arts. While James was waiting at Linlithgow for the arrival of his army
                from the north and the Highlands, he aſſiſted one afternoon at the veſpers in the
                church of St Michael. Being placed in one of the canon’s ſeats, a venerable, comely
                man oſ about 52 years of age, entered, drefſed in a long garment of an azure colour,
                and girded round with a towel or roll of linen, his forehead bald, and his yellow
                locks hanging down his ſhoulders; in ſhort, he was drefſed and</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
