<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-14T17:55:16Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>Albany. The day before the marriage, a proclamation was publiſhed, commanding him to
                be ſtyled <hi rend="italic">king of the realm,</hi> and that all letters after their
                marriage ſhould be directed in the names of her huſband and herſelf. The day alter
                it, a new proclamation was iſsued confirming this act: he was pronounced king by the
                ſound of trumpets, and aſſociated with the queen in her government. This meafure
                ſeems to have been the effect of the extreme love the queen had for her huſband,
                which did not permit her to ſee that it was an infringement of the conſtitution of
                the kingdom; though perhaps ſhe might alſo be urged to it by the preſſing eagerneſs
                of lord Darnley himſelf, and the partial counſels of David Rizzio. The earl of
                Murray made loud complaints, remonſtrated, that a king was impoſed upon the nation
                without the conſent of the three eſtates, and called upon the nation to arm againſt
                the beginnings of tyranny. The malcontents accordingly were immediately in arms; but
                their ſucceſs was not anſwerable to their wiſhes. The bulk of the nation were
                ſatisfied with the good intentions of their ſovereign, and ſhe herſelf took the
                earlieſt opportunity of cruſhing the rebellion in its infancy. The earl of Murray
                was declared a traitor; and ſimilar ſteps were taken with others of the chiefs of
                the rebels. She then took the field againſt them at the head of a conſiderable army:
                and having driven them from place to place, obliged them at laſt to take refuge in
                England. Queen Elizabeth received them with that duplicity for which her conduct was
                ſo remarkable. Though ſhe herſelf had countenanced, and even excited them to revolt,
                ſhe refilled to give an audience to their deputies. Nay, ſhe even cauſed them to
                emit a public declaration, that neither ſhe, nor any perſon in her name, had ever
                excited them to their rebellious practices. Yet, while the public behaviour of
                Elizabeth was ſo acrimonious, ſhe afforded them a ſecure tetreat in her kingdom,
                treated the earl of Murray in private with reſpect and kindneſs, and commanded the
                earl of Bedford to ſupply him with money. Mary, however, reſolved to proceed againſt
                the rebels with an exemplary rigour. The ſubmiſſions of the duke of Chatel- herault
                alone, who had been leſs criminal than the rest, were attended to. But even the
                favour which he obtained was precarious and uncertain; for he was commanded to uſe
                the pretence of ſickneſs, and to paſs for ſome time into foreign countries. A
                parliament was called; and a ſummons of treaſon being executed againſt the earls of
                Argyle, Glencairn, and Rothes, with others</p>
            <p>of the principal rebels, they were commanded to appear before the three eſtates; in
                default of which their lives and eſtates were declared to be forfeited.</p>
            <p>In the mean time Throgmorton the Engliſh ambaſſador ſolicited the pardon of the
                rebels; which Mary was at firſt inclined to grant. However, by the perſuaſion of the
                court of France, ſhe was not only induced to proceed againſt them with rigour, but
                acceded to the treaty of Bayonne, by which the deſtruction of the Proteſtants was
                determined. This meaſure filled the whole court with terror and diſmay. The rebels
                were acquainted with the danger of their ſituation; and being now driven deſperate,
                they were ready to engage in the moſt atrocious deſigns. Unhappily, the ſituation of
                affairs in Scotland rendered the accompliſhment of their purpoſes but too eaſy.
                Violent diſguſts had taken place between the queen and her huſband. Her fondneſs had
                been exceſſive; but ſhe ſoon perceived that the qualities of his mind were not
                proportioned to his perſonal accompliſhments. He was proud, diſdainful, and
                ſuſpicious. No perſuaſions could correct his wilfulneſs; and he was at the ſame time
                giddy and obſtinate, inſolent and mean. The queen in conſequence began to ſhow an
                indifference towards him; which he took care to augment, by ſhowing the like
                indifference towards her, and engaging in low intrigues and amours, indulging
                himſelf in diſſipation and riot, &amp;c. However, the deſire of dominion was his
                ruling paſſion; and. the queen, finding his total incapacity for exerciſing his
                power to any good purpoſe, had excluded him from it altogether. He was therefore at
                preſent a proper object for the machinations of the rebels, and readily entered into
                an agreement with them to depoſe the queen; vainly thinking by that means that he
                ſhould ſecure the crown to himſelf. However, as the parliament was ſoon to aſſemble,
                in which the rebels had every reaſon to believe that they would be condemned for
                high treaſon, it was neceſſary that the kingdom ſhould be thrown into diſorder
                before that time came, otherwiſe their fate was inevitable. Practiſing on the
                imbecillity of Darnley, they perſuaded him that a criminal correſpondence ſubſiſted
                between the queen and David Rizzio @@<hi rend="smallcaps">(r).</hi> For this reaſon
                the king reſolved upon his deſtruction; and the conſpirators hoped thereby not only
                to get an indemnity to themſelves, but to effect a total revolution at court, and
                the entire humiliation of Bothwel, Huntley, and Athol, who were the aſſociates of
                Rizzio. However, in order to ſave them-</p>
            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">@@@(r)</hi> That there ſubſiſted a criminal intercourſe between
                Mary and Rizzio is a ſcandal wſhrch is now given up by her enemies. It ſeems to reft
                on the authority of Buchanan and Knox; and their evidence in this cafe is clearly of
                no weight, not only from their being the ſtrenuous partizans of her adverſaries, but
                from the multitude of ſalſehoods which they anxiouſly detail to calumniate her. The
                love ſhe felt for Darnley was extreme, and their acquaintance commenced a month or
                two after the appointment of Rizzio to be her ſecretary for French affairs. She
                became pregnant ſoon after her marriage; and it was during her pregnancy that Rizzio
                was aſſaſſinated. There are ſtriking preſumptions in her favour. And what ſeems to
                put her innocence out of all queſtion, is the ſilence of the ſpies and reſidents of
                Elizabeth with regard to this amour; for, if there had been any thing real in it,
                they could not have made their court to their queen more effectually than by
                declaring to her its peculiarities; and their want of delicacy, ſo obſervable in
                other circumſtances, would have induced them upon this occaſion to give the greateſt
                foulnels and deformity to their information.</p>
            <p>It appears that Rizzio was ill-favoured, and of a diſagreeable form. Buchanan ſays of
                him, "Non faciem cultus hor.eſtabat, ſed facies cultum deſtruebat. Hiſt. Scot. lib.
                xvii. This expreſſion is very ſtrong; but it would have little weight if other
                authors had not concurred in giving a ſimilar deſcription of Rizzio. In a book <pb
                    n="53"> </pb>intitled, “Le Livre de la Morte de la Reyne d’Ecoſſe,” and printed
                in the year 1587, he is ſaid to be “diſgracie de corps.” Cauſſin, ap. Jebb, p. 37.
                This work, too, while it records the unkindneſs of nature to his perſon, has
                obſerved, that he was in his old age when he made a figure in the court of Mary.
                “Elle traittoit ordinairement avec David Rſecio ſon ſecretaire, homme aagé et
                prudent, qui poſſedoit ſon oreille.” Ibid. And other authors give their teſtimonies
                to the ſame purpoſe.</p>
            <p>It is probable that the panegyriſts of Mary exaggerate ſomewhat the imperfections as
                well as the good qualities of Rizzio. But there ſeems in general to be no reaſon to
                doubt his fidelity and talents, any more than his uglineſs and ſenility. He had
                therefore a better title to be her ſecretary than her lover. It is an abſurdity to
                think that a queen ſo young and beautiful would yield herſelf to deformity and old
                age. A common proſtitute muſt be brought to endure this misfortune. The capacity of
                the man was a recommendation to him; and as he owed every thing to her bounty, and
                was a ſtranger, ſhe had the greateſt reaſon to rely upon his faithfulneſs. The
                perſidiouſneſs and duplicity of her courtiers drew cloſer the tie of their
                connection; and as Rizzio was ſtudious to make himſelf agreeable, and was ſkilful in
                games of hazard, he was always ready to be a party with her in thoſe innocent
                amuſements which fill up the liſtleſs intervals of life. Keith. Append, p. 124.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
