<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:56:09Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>by the heralds, Mr Robert Pont miniſter of St Cuthbert’s, and one of the ſenators of the court of ſeſſion, with Mr Walter Balcanqual, proteſted formally in the name of the church, that it diſſented from them, and that they were conſequently invalid. Having made this proteſtation, they inſtantly fled, and were proclaimed traitors. By letters and pamphlets, which were artfully ſpread among the people, their paſſions were rouzed againſt the king and his council. The miniſters of Edinburgh took the reſolution to forſake their flocks, and to retire to England. And in an apology circulated by their management, they anxiouſly endeavoured to awaken commiſeration and pity. They magnified the dangers which threatened them; and they held out, in vindication of their conduct, the example of the prophets, the apoſtles, the martyrs, and of Chriſt himſtlf, who all concurred, they ſaid, in oppoſing the ordinations of men, when contradictory to the will of heaven, and in declining the rage of the enemies of God, The king appointed his own chaplains and the archbiſhop of St Andrew’s to perform the miniſterial functions in his capital. The clergy over Scotland were commanded to ſubscribe a declaration, which imported the ſupremacy of the king over the church, and their ſubmiſſion to the authority of the biſhops. Tire national ferments ſtill increaſed in violence. Many miniſters refuſed to ſubſcribe this declaration, and were deprived of their livings. It was contended, that to make the king ſupreme over the church was no better than to ſet up a new pope, and to commit treaſon againſt Jeſus Chriſt. It was urged, that to overthrow aſſemblies and preſhyteries, and to give dominion to biſhops, was not only to overſet the eſtabliſhed polity of the church, but to deſtroy religion itſelf, For the biſhops were the ſlaves of the court, were ſchiſmatical in their opinions, and depraved in their lives. It was affirmed, that hereſy, atheiſm, and popery, would ſtrike a deep root, and grow into ſtrength,, And the people were taught to believe, that the biſhops would corrupt the nation into a reſemblance with themſelves; and that there everywhere prevailed diſſimulation and blaſphemy, perſecution and obſcenity, the profanation of the ſcriptures, and the breach of faith, covetouſneſs, perjury, and ſacrilege. It was reported abroad, that the miniſters alone were entruſted with eccleſiaſtical functions, and with the ſword of the word; and that it was moſt wicked and profane to imagine, that Jeſus Chriſt had ever committed the keys of the kingdom of heaven to civil magiſtrates and their ſervants or deputies.</p><p>While the clergy were thus impotently venting their wrath, Elizabeth, alarmed beyond meaſure at this hidden revolution, and terrified by a confeſſion extorted by the rack from one Francis 'Throgmorton, concerning a combination of the Catholic princes to invade England, began to treat with Mary in a more ſincere manner than uſual; but having gained over to her ſide the earl of Arran, the only man of activity in Scotland, ſhe reſolved to proceed to extremities with the queen of Scots, The Roman Catholics, both at home and abroad, were inflamed againſt her with a boundleſs and implacable rage. There prevailed many rumours of plots and conſpiracies againſt her kingdom and her life. Books were publiſhed, which detailed her cruelties and injuſtice to Mary in the moſt indignant lan</p><p>guage of reproach, and which recommended her assassination as a moſt meritorious act, The earl of Arran had explained to her the practices of the queen of Scots with her ſon, and had diſcovered the intrigues of the Catholic princes to gain him to their views. While her ſenſibilities and fears were ſeverely excruciating to her, circumſtances happened which confirmed them in their ſtrength, and provoked her to give the fulleſt ſcope to the malignity of her paſſions. Crichton, a Scottiſh Jeſuit, paſſing into his own country, was taken by Netherland pirates; and ſorne papers which he had torn in pieces and thrown into the ſea being recovered, were tranſmitted to England. Sir William Wade put them together with dexterity; and they demonſtrated beyond a doubt, that the invaſion of England was concerted by the Pope, the king of Spain, and the duke of Guiſe. About this time, too, a remarkable letter was intercepted from Mary to Sir Francis Englefield. She complained in it that ſhe could have no reliance upon the integrity of Elizabeth, and that she expected no happy iſſue to any treaty which might be opened for her reſtoration and liberty. She urged the advancement of the "great plot;” she intimated, that the prince her ſon was favourable to the “deſignment," and diſpoſed to be directed by her advice; ſhe intreated, that every delicacy with regard to her own ſtate and condition ſhould be laid aſide without ſcruple; and ſhe aſſured him, that ſhe would moſt willingly ſuffer perils and dangers, and even death itſelf, to give relief to the oppreſſed children of the church. Theſe diſcoveries, ſo exaſperating to the inquietudes and ditresses of Elisabeth, were followed by a deep and general conſternation, The terror of an invaſion ſpread itſelf with rapidity over England; and the Proteſtants, while they trembled for the life of their champion, were ſtill more alarmed with the dangers which threatened their religion.</p><p>In this ſtate of perplexity and diſtraction, the counſellors of Elizabeth did not forget that they had been her inſtruments in perſecuting the queen of Scots, and of the ſeventies with which ſhe had treated the Roman Catholics. They were fully ſenſible, that her greatneſs and ſafety were intimately connected with their own; and they concurred in indulging her fears, jealouſies, and reſentment. It was reſolved that Mary ſhould ρeriſh, An aſſociation was formed, to which perſons <hi rend="italic">of</hi> every condition and degree were invited, The profeſſed buſineſs of this aſſociation or ſoeiety was the preſervation of the life of Elizabeth, which it was affirmed was in danger, from a conſpiracv to advance ſorne pretended title to the crown; and its members vowed and proteſted, by the majeſty of God, to employ their whole power, their bodies, lives, and goods, in her ſervice; to withſtand, as well by force of arms as by other methods of revenge, all perſons, of whatſoever nation or rank, who ſhould attempt in any form to invade and injure her ſafety or her life, and never to deſiſt from the forcible purſuit of them till they ſhould be completely exterminated. They alſo vowed and proteſted, in the preſence of the eternal God, to proſecute to deſtruction any pretended ſucceſſor by whom, or for whom, the deteſtable deed of the aſſaſſination of Elizabeth ſhould be attempted or committed, The earl of Leiceſter was in a particular manner the patron of this aſſociation; and the whole influence of Elizabeth and her</p></body></text></TEI>