<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:56:23Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>and ſaid, "In thee, O Lord! do I truſt, let me never be confounded.” She covered her eyes with a linen handkerchief in which the eucharrſt had been incloſed; and ſtretching forth her body with great tranquillity, and fitting her neck for the fatal ſtroke, ſhe called out, “Into thy hands, O God! I commit my ſpirit.” The executioner, from deſign, from unſkilfulneſs, or from  inquietude, ſtruck three blows before he ſeparated her head from her body. He held it up mangled with wounds, and ſtreaming with blood; and her hair being diſcompoſed, was diſcovered to be already grey with afflictions and anxieties. The dean of Peterborough alone cried out, “So let the enemies of Elizabeth periſh.” The earl of Kent alone, in a low voice, anſwered, “Amen.” All the other ſpectators were melted into the tendereſt ſympathy and ſorrow.</p><p>Her women haſtened to protect her dead body from the curioſity of the ſpectators; and ſolaced themſelves with the thoughts of mourning over it undiſturbed when they ſhould retire, and of laying it out in its funeral garb. But the two earls prohibited them from diſcharging theſe melancholy yet pleaſing offices to their departed miſtreſs, and drove them from the hall with indignity. Bourgoin her phyſician applied to them that he might be permitted to take out her heart for the purpoſe or preſerving it, arid of carrying it with him to France. But they refuſed his intreaty with diſdain and anger. Her remains were touched by the rude hands of the executioners, who carried them into an adjoining apartment; and who, tearing a cloth from an old billiard-table, covered that form, once ſo beautiful. The block, the cuſhion, the ſcaffold, and the garments, which were ſtained with her blood, were conſumed with fire. Her body, after being embalmed and committed to a leaden coffin, was buried with royal ſplendour and pomp in the cathedral of Peterborough. Elizabeth, who had treated her like a criminal while she lived, ſeemed diſpoſed to acknowledge her for a queen when ſhe was dead.</p><p>On the death of his mother, the full government of the kingdom devolved on James her ſon. Elizabeth, apprehenſive of his reſentment for her treatment of his mother, wrote him a letter, in which ſhe diſclaimed all knowledge of the fact. James had received intelligence of the murder before the arrival of this letter, which was ſent by one Cary. The meſſenger was flopped at Berwick by an order from the king, telling him, that, if Mary had been executed, he ſhould proceed at his peril. James ſhut himſelf up in Dalkeith caſtle, in order to indulge himſelf in grief; but the natural levity and imbecility of his mind prevented him from acting in any degree as became him. Inſtead of reſolutely adhering to his firſt determination of not allowing Cary to ſet foot in Scotland, he in a few days pave his conſent that he ſhould be admitted to an audience of certain members of his privy-council, who took a journey to the borders on purpoſe to wait upon him. In this conference, Cary demanded that the league of amity between the two kingdoms ſhould be inviolably obſerved. He ſaid that his miſtreſs was grieved at the death of Mary, which had happene without her conſent; and, in Elizabeth’s name, offered any ſatisfaction that James could demand. The Scots commiſſioners treated Cary’s ſpeech and propoſal with becoming diſdain. They obvſſerved, that they amounted to no more than know whether James was diſpoſed to fell his mother’s blood; adding, that the Scottiſh nobility and people were determined to revenge it, and to intereſt in their quarrel the other princes of Europe. Upon this Cary delivered to them the letter from Elizabeth, together with a declaration of his own concerning the murder of the queen; and it does not appear that he proceeded farther.</p><p>This reception of her ambalſador threw Elizabeth into the utmoſt conſternation. She was apprehenſive that James would join his force to that of Spain, and entirely overwhelm her; and had the reſentment or the ſpirit of the king been equal to that of the nation, it is probable that the haughty Engliſh princeſs would have been made ſeverely to repent her perfidy and cruelty. It doth not, however, appear, that James had any ſerious intention of calling Elizabeth to an account for the murder of his mother; for which, perhaps, his natural imbecility maybe urged as an excuſe, though it is more probable that his own neceſſity for money had ſwallowed up every other conſideration. By the league formerly concluded with England, it had been agreed that Elizabeth ſhould pay an annual penſion to the king of Scotland. James had neither economy to make his own revenue anſwer his purpoſes, nor addreſs to get it increaſed. He was therefore always in want; and as Elizabeth had plenty to ſpare, her friendſhip became a valuable acquiſition. To this conſideration, joined to his view of aſcending the Engliſh throne, muſt chiefly be aſcribed the little reſentment ſhown by him to the atrocious conduct of Elizabeth.</p><p>Elizabeth was not wanting in the arts of diſſimulation and treachery now more than formerly. She proſecuted and fined ſecretary Davidſon and lord Burleigh for the active part they had taken in Mary’s death. Their puniſhment was indeed much leſs than they deſerved, but they certainly did not merit ſuch treatment at her hands. Walſingham, though equally guilty, yet efcaped by pretending indiſpoſition, or perhaps eſcaped becauſe the queen had now occaſion for his ſervices. By her command he drew up a long letter addreſſed to lord Thirlſton, king James’s prime miniſter; in which he ſhowed the neceſſity of putting Mary to death, and the folly of attempting to revenge it. He boaſted of the ſuperior force of England to that of Scotland; ſhewed James that he would for ever ruin his pretenſions to the Engliſh crown, by involving the two nations in a war; that he ought not to truſt to foreign alliances; that the Roman Catholic party were ſo divided among themſelves, that he could receive little or no aſſiſtance from them, even ſuppofing him ſo ill adviſed as to change his own religion ſor Popery, and that they would not truſt his ſincerity. Laſtly, he attempted to ſhow, that James had already diſcharged all the duty towards his mother and his own reputation that could be expected from an affectionate ſon and a wife king; that his interceding for her with a concern ſo becoming nature, had endeared him to the kingdom of England; but that it. would be madneſs to puſh his reſentment farther.</p><p>This letter had all the effect that could be deſired. James gave an audience to the Engliſh ambaſſador; and being aſſured that his blood was <hi rend="italic">not tainted</hi> by the execution of his mother for treaſon againſt Elizabeth, but</p></body></text></TEI>