<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r03-0549-05" facs="gri_33125011196389_0555.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>RUFINUS</label>
was born about ſhe middle of the fourth century at Concordia, au inconfiderable town, in Italy. At firſt lie applied himſelf to the belles lettres, and particularly to the ſtudy of eloquence. To accompliſh himſelf in this elegant art, he removed to Aquileia, a town at that time ſo celebrated that it was called a ſecond Rome. Having made himſelf acquainted with the“ polite literature of the age, he withdrew into a mona-ltery, where he devoted himſelf to the ſtudy of theology . While ſhus occupied, St Jerome happened to paſs through Aquileia. Rufinus formed an intimate friend-ſhip wiſh him; but to his iuexpreſſible grief was ſoon deprived of the company of his new friend, who continued bis travels through France and Germany, and then ſet out for the eaſt. Rufinus, unable to bear his abſence,. reſolved to follow him. Accordingly he embarked for Egypt ; and having vifited ſhe hermits who inhabit the deſerts of that country, he repaired to Alexandria to hear ſhe renowned Didymus. Here he w <hi rend="sup">r</hi> as gratified with a light of St Melania, of whoſe virtue and charity he had heard much. The ſanctity of his manners ſoon obtained ſhe confidence of St Melania, which continued without interruption during their refidence in the eaſt, a period of 30 years. The Arians, who ſwayed the ecclefiaſtical ſceptre in the reign of Valens, perſecuted Rufinus wiſh great cruelty. They threw him into a dungeon, loaded him with chains, and after almoſt ltarving him to death, baniſhed him to the deſerts oſ Paleltine. From this exile he was relieved by the pecuniary aid of St. Melania, who employed her wealth in ranſeming thoſe</p>
<pb xml:id="eb03-16-r03-0550" facs="gri_33125011196389_0556.tif"/>
<p>conſeſſors who had been condemried to priſon or baniſh-ment.</p><p>St Jerome, ſuppoſing that -Ruſinus would immediately proceed to Jeruſalem, wrote to one of his friends there, congratulating him on the proſpect of ſo illuſtrious a viſitor. To Jeruſalem he went, and having built a monaſtery on the Mount of Olives, he there aſſembled a great number of hermits, whom he animated to virtue by his exhortations. He converted many to the Chriſtian faith, and perſuaded more than 400 hermits who had taken part in the ſchiſm of Antioch to return to the church. He prevailed on many Macedonians and Arians to renounce their errors.</p><p>His attachment to the opinions of Origen ſet him at variance with St Jerome, who, being of a temper peculiarly irritable, not only retracted all the praiſes which he had laviſhed upon him, but loaded him with ſevere reproaches. Their diſputes, which were carried to a very indecent height, tended to injure Chriſtianity in the èyes of the weak. Theophilus, their mutual friend, fettled their differences ; but the reconciliation was of -ſhort continuance. Ruſinus having publiſhed a tranſlation of the principles of Origen at Rome, was ſum-ηιoned to appear before Pope Anaſtaſius. But he made a ſpecious apology for not appearing, and ſent a vindication of his work, in which he attempted to prove that certain errors, of which Origen had been accuſed, were perfectly conſiſtent with the opinions of the orthodox. St Jerome attacked Ruſinus’s tranſlation. Rufi-nus compoſed an eloquent reply, in which lie declared •that he was only the tranſlator of Origen, and did not confider himſelf bound .to fonction all his errors. Moſt occleſiaſtical hiſtorians ſay that Ruſinus was excommunicated by Pope Anaſtaſius ; but for this no good evidence has been brought. In 407, he returned to Rome ; but the year aſter, that city being threatened by Alaric,.he retired to Sicily, where he died in 410.</p><p>His works are, 1. À Tranſlation of Joſephus;</p><p>2. A Tranſlation of ſeveral works of Origen ; 3· A Latin Verſion of Ten Diſeourſes of Gregory Nazian-.z,en, and Eight of Baſil’s ; 4. Chromatius of Aquileia prevailed on him to undertake a Tranſlation of the Ec-cleſiaſtical Hiſtory of Euſebius, which engaged him almoſt ten years. He made many additions to the body of the work, and continued the hiſtory from the 2cth year of Conſtantine to the death of Theodoſius the Great. Many parts of this work are negligently written, many things are recorded as facts without any authority but common report, and many things of great importance are entirely omitted. 5. A Vindication of Origen. 6. Two Apologies addreſſed to St Jerome. 7. Commentaries on the prophets Hoſea, Joel, and Amo?. 8. Lives of the Hermits. 9. rtn Explanation of the Creed.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>