<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r03-0529-05"
                facs="gri_33125011196389_0535.tif" type="entry">

                <p><label>ROUSSEAU</label> (James), an eminent painter, was born at Paris in the
                    year 1630, and ſtudied firſt under Swa-nevelt. who had married one of his
                    relations ; after which he improved himſelf by travelling into Italy, practiſing
                    ſolely in perfective, architecture, and landſcape. On his return home, he was
                    employed at Marly. He dx-ſtingu’ſhed himſelf very much in painting buildings,
                    and by his knowledge of, and attention to, the principles of perlpective. Louis
                    XIV. employed him to decorate his hall of devices at St Germaine-en-Laſe, where
                    he repreſented the operas of Lulli. But being a Proteſ-tant, he quitted France
                    on the perſecution of his brethren, and retired to Swifferland. Louis invited
                    him back ; he refuſed, but ſent his deſigns, and recommended a proper perſon to
                    execute them. After a ſſiort ſtay in Swfifferland, he went to Holland ; whence
                    he was invited over to England by Ralph duke of Montague, to adorn his new houſe
                    in Bloomſhury, where he painted much. Some oſ his pictures, both in landſcape
                    and architecture, are over doors at Hampton-court ; and he etched ſome of his
                    own deſigns. His perſpectives having been moſt commonly applied to decorate
                    courts or gardens, have ſuffered much from the weather. Such oſ them as remain
                    are monuments of an excellent genius The colours are durable and bright, and the
                    choice of them moſt judicious. He died in Soho-ſquare, about the year 1693, aged
                    63.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Rousseau (John Baptiſt), a celebrated French poet, w^as
                        born at Paris in April 167</hi> <hi rend="sup">r</hi> . His father⅛ who was a ſhoemaker in good circumſtances,
                    made him ſtudy in the beſt colleges of Paris, where he diſtinguiſhed himſelf by
                    his abilities. He at length applied himſelf entirely to poetry, and ſoon made
                    hιmklf known by ſeveral ſhort pieces, that were filled w <hi rend="sup">,</hi> ith lively and agreeable images which made him iought for by perlons of the
                    ſiiſt rank, and men oſ the brighteſt genius. He was admitted in quality of <hi
                        rend="italic"> élève,</hi> or pupil, into the academy of Inſcriptions and
                    Belles Lettres, in 1701,</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r03-0530" facs="gri_33125011196389_0536.tif"/>
                <p>and almoſt all the reſt of his life attached himſelf to ſome of the great lords,
                    He attended marſhal Tallard into England, in quality of ſecretary, and here
                    contracted a ſriendſhip with St Evremond. At his return to Paris, he was
                    admitted into the politeſt company, lived among the courtiers, and ſeemed
                    perfectly ſatisſied with his ſituation ; when, in 1708, he was proſe-cuted for
                    being the author of ſome couplets, in which the characters of ſeveral perſons of
                    wit and merit were blackened by the moſt atrocious calumnies. This pro-ſecution
                    made much noife ; and Rouſſeau was baniſhed in 1712 out of the kingdom, to which
                    he was never more to return, by a decree of the parliament of Paris, However, he
                    always ſteadily denied, and even on his death-bed, his being the author of theſe
                    couplets.— From the date of this ſentence he lived in foreign countries, where
                    he found illuſtrious protectors. The count de Luc, ambaſſador of France, in
                    Swiſſerland, took him into his family, and ſtudied to render his life agreeable.
                    He took him with him to the treaty of Baden in</p>
                <p>1714, where he was one of the plenipotentiaries, and preſented him to prince
                    Eugene, who entertaining a particular eſteem'for him, took him to Vienna, and
                    introduced him to the emperor’s court. Rouſſeau lived about three years with
                    prince Eugene ; but having loſt his favour by ſatiriſing one of his miltreſſes,
                    he retired to Bruſſels, where he afterwards uſually reſided, and where he met
                    with much attention and much generoſity, as we ſhall ſoon mention.— It was here
                    that his diſputes with Voltaireeommenced,with whom he had become acquainted at
                    the college of Louis the Great, who then much admired his turn for poetry. At
                    that time Voltaire aſ-ſiduouſly cultivated the acquaintance of Rouſſeau, and
                    made him a preſent of all his works ; and Rouſſeau, flattered by his reſpect,
                    announced him as a man who would one day be a glory to the age. The author of
                    the Henriad continued to conſult him about his productions, and to laviſh on him
                    the higheſt encomiums, while their friendſhip daily increaſed. When they again
                    met at Bruſſels, however, they harboured the blackeſt malice againſt one
                    another. The cauſe of this enmity, as Rouſſeau and his friends tell the ſtory,
                    was a lecture which he had compoſed from his Epiſtie to Julia, new Urania. This
                    piece frightened Voltaire, as it plainly diſcovered his rage againſt him. The
                    young man, vexed at theſe calumnies, underſtood the whole as thrown out againſt
                    him. This is what Rouſſeau aſſerts. But his adverſaries, and the friends of the
                    poet whom he cried down, ſuſpected him, perhaps rather raſhly, of having
                    employed ſarcaſms, becauſe he thought that his own reputation was in danger of
                    being eclipſed by that of his rival. What is very ſingular, theſe two celebrated
                    characters endeavoured each of them to prepoſſcſs the public with a bad opinion
                    of the other, which they themſelves never entertained in reality, and to ſmother
                    in their breaſt that eſteem for each other which, in de</p>
                <p>fiance of all their exertions, ſtill held its place. Rouſſeau, from the period
                    of this diſpute, always repre-fented Voltaire as a buffoon, as a writer
                    poſſelfing neither taſte nor judgment, who owed all his ſucceſs to a particular
                    mode which he purſued. As a poet he confi-dered him as inferior to Lucan, and
                    little ſuperior to Pradon. Voltaire treated him ſtill worſe. Rouſſeau, according
                    to him, was nothing better than a plagiariſt, who could make ſhiſt to rhime, but
                    could not make any reflections ; that he had nothing but the talent of arranging
                    words, and that he had even loſt that in foreign countries. He thus addreſſes
                    him, in a piece little known :</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Aυffitδt le Dieu qui rrfinſpire T <hi rend="sup">,</hi> arracha le luth et la lyre lpu’avoient cléjhonorés tes mains ;</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Tu n’es plus qu’un reptile immonde,</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Rebut du Pamojſe et du monde</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Enſeveli dans tes venins.</hi></p>
                <p>In conſequence of the little eſteem in which Rouſſeau was held at Bruſſels, he
                    could never forget Paris. The grand-prior of Vendôme, and the baron de
                    Breteuil&gt; ſolicited the regent duke of Orleans to allow him to return ;
                    which favour was obtained. But our poet, before he would make uſe of the <hi
                        rend="italic"> lettres de rapel</hi> iſſued in his favour, demanded a
                    review of his proceſs, which he wiſhed to be repealed, not as a matter of
                    favour, but by a ſolemn judgment of court ; but his petition was refuſed. He
                    then came over, in 1721, to England, where he printed <hi rend="italic">A
                        Collection oſ his Works,</hi> in 2 vols ι 2mo, at London. This edition,
                    publiſhed in 1723, brouglu him near 10,000 crowns, the wholeof which he placed
                    in the hands of the Oſtend company. The affairs of this company, however, ſoon
                    getting into contuſion, all thoſe who had any money in their hands loſt the
                    whoſe of it, by which unfortunate event Rouſſeau, when arrived at that age when
                    he ſtood moſt in need of the comforts of fortune, had nothing to depend upon but
                    the generoſity of ſome tnends. Boutet, public notary in Paris, was peculiarly
                    generous and attentive to him. He found a ſtill greater aſylum in the Duke
                    d’Arem-berg, whoſe table was open to him at all times ; who being obliged in
                    1733 to go into the army in Germany, ſettled on him a penſion of 1500 livres.
                    But unfortunately he ſoon loſt his good opinion, having been-Jm-prudent enough
                    to publiſh in a Journal (of which Voltaire accuſed him), that the duke
                    d’Aremberg was the author of thoſe verſes for which he himſelf had been baniſhed
                    France. He was therefore diſmiſſed from his table, and his pride would not allow
                    him to accept of the penſion after this rupture. Bruſſels now became
                    inſupportable to him ; and the count du Luc, and M. de Senozan, receiver-general
                    of the church revenue, being informed of his difappointments,. invited him to
                    come privately to Paris, in the hopes of procuring a diminution of the period of
                    his baniſhment. Some time previous to this Rouſſeau had publiſhed two new
                    letters ; one to P. Brumoi, on tragedy ; the other to Rollin, on hiſtory. It is
                    laid, he expected from his letter to Brumoi to get the favour of all the Jeſuits
                    ;</p>
                <p>aud from the one to Rollin, the patronage of the Jan-ſeniſts. He had likewiſe
                    written an Ode, in praiſe of Cardinal de Fleury, on Peace, which met with a
                    favourable reception, although it was not equal to ſome of his former pieces. He
                    imagined his return to Paris would be found no difficult matter. He attempted
                    it, and found he could not obtain a paſs for a ſingle year. Some ſay, that
                    Rouſſeau had irritated ſome perſons in power, by an allegory, called <hi
                        rend="italic"> The Judgment of Pluto ;</hi> in which piece he deſeribes one
                    of the principal judges,</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r03-0531" facs="gri_33125011196389_0537.tif"/>
                <p>whoſe ſkin Pluto had cauſed to be taken off, and ſtretched out on the ſeat in
                    the bench. This ſatirej joined to the ſecret machinations of enemies, rendered
                    all the attempts of his friends to procure his return abortive. After having
                    ſtaid three months at Paris, he returned to Bruſſels in February 1740, at which
                    olace he died March 1*7. 174t, ſtrongly impreſſed with religious ſen-timents.
                    Immedir.tely before he received the viaticum, he proteſted he was not the author
                    of thoſe horrid verſes which had ſo much embittered his life ; and this
                    declaration, in the opinion of the virtuous part of mankind, wſll be conſidered
                    as a ſuſſicient proof of his innocence. Borne have ſaid that Rouſſeau was
                    profane, troubleſome, capricious, forward, vindictive, envious, a flatterer, and
                    a ſatiriſt. Others again repreſent him as a man full of candour and openneſs, a
                    faithful and grateful friend, and as a Chriſtian affected with a ſenſe of
                    religion.— Amidſt ſuch widely varied accounts it is difficult to form an opinion
                    of his character. Such of our readers as wiſh to know <hi rend="sup">7</hi> more of this great poet may conſult the Dictionary of M. Chatipepié, written
                    with as much preciſion as impartiality, who endeavours to give a juſt idea of
                    his character. From what he ſays, it does not appear that Rouſſeau can be
                    cleared ſrom the accuſation brought againſt him of having attacked his
                    benefactors. We believe he may be much more eaſily freed ſrom the imputation
                    brought againſt him by ſome of having diſ-owned his father : for what occaſion
                    had Rouſſeau to conceal the obſeurity of his birth ? It exalted his own merit.</p>
                <p>, M. Seguy, in concert with M. the prince of la</p>
                <p>Tour Taſſis, has given a very beautiful edition of his works, agreeable to the
                    poet’s laſt corrections. It was publiſhed in 1743, at Paris, in 3 vols. 4t0, and
                    in 4 vols. 12mo, containing nothing but what was acknowledged by the author as
                    his own. It contains, 1. Four Books of Odes, of which the firſt are ſacred odes,
                    ta-keu from the Pſalms. “ Rouſſeau (ſays Freron) unites in himſelf Pindar,
                    Horace, Anacreon, and Malherbe. What fire, what genius, what flights of
                    imagination, what rapidity of deſcription, what variety of affecting ſtrokes,
                    what a crowd of brilliant companions, what richneſs of rhymes, what happy
                    verſifi--cation ; but eſpecially what inimitable expreſſion ! His verſes are
                    finiſhed in the higheſt ſtyle of perfection that French verſe is capable of
                    aſſuming.” The lyric compoſitions of Rouſſeau are, in general, above mediocrity.
                    All his odes are not, however, of equal merit. The moſt beautiful are thoſe
                    which he has addreſſed to count du Luc, to Malherbe, to prince Eugene, to
                    Vendôme, to the Chriſtian princes ; his Odes on the death of the prince de
                    Conti, on the battle of Peterwara-din ; and the Ode to Fortune, altho’ there are
                    certainly ſome few weak ſtanzas to be met with in it. There is conſiderable
                    neatneſs in the compoſition of the Ode to a Widow, in his ſtanzas to the Abbé de
                    Chaulieu, in his addreſſes to Roſſignol, in his Odes to count de
                    Bi&gt;nne-val, to M. Duche, and to count de Sinzindorf ; and it is to be
                    lamented that he wrote ſo few pieces oſ this kind, from which his genius ſeemed
                    to ſead him with difficulty. 2. Two books of Epiſtles, in verſe. Although theſe
                    do not wafιt their beauties, yet there prevails too much of a miſanthropic
                    ſpirit in them, which takes away greatly from their excellence. He makes too
                    frequent mention of his enemies and his miſe fortunes ; he diſplays thoſe
                    principles which are flip-ported leſs on the bafis of truth than on thoſe
                    various paſſions which ruled his mind at the time. He puts forth his anger in
                    paradoxes. If he be reckoned equal to Horace in his odes, he is far inferior in
                    his epiſtles. 'Γhere is much more philoſophy in the Roman poet than in him. 3. <hi rend="italic">Cantatas,</hi> hie is the father of this ſpecies of
                    poetry, in which he ſtands unrivalled. His pieces of this fort breathe that
                    poetical expreſſion, that pic-tureſque ſtyle, thoſe happy turns, and thoſe eaſy
                    graces, which conſtitute the true oharacter of this kind of writing. He is as
                    lively and impetuous as he is mild and affecting, adapting himſelf to the
                    paſſions of thoſe perſons whom he makes to ſpeak. “ I confeſs (ſays M. de la
                    Harpe) that 1 find the cantatas of Rouſſeau more purely lyric than his odes,
                    although he riſes to greater heights in theſe. I ſee nothing in his cantatas but
                    bold and agreeable images. He always addreſſes himſelf to the imagination, and
                    he never becomes either too verboſe or too prolix. On the contrary, in ſome of
                    the beſt of his odes, we find ſome languiſh-ing ſtanzas, ideas too long delayed,
                    and verſes of inex-cuſable meanneſs.” 4. <hi rend="italic">Allegories,</hi> the moſt of which are happy, but ſome of them appear forced. 5. <hi
                        rend="italic"> Epigrams,</hi> after the manner of Martial and Marot. He has
                    taken care to leave out of this edition thoſe pieces which li-centiouſneſs and
                    debauchery inſpired. They bear, indeed, as well as his other pieces, the marks
                    of genius ; but ſuch productions are calculated only to diſ-honour their
                    authors, and corrupt the heart of thoſe who read them, 5. A book of <hi
                        rend="italic"> Poems on Various Subjects,</hi> which ſometimes want both
                    eaſe and delicacy. The moſt diſtinguiſhed are two eclogues, imitated from
                    Virgil. 6. Four comedies in verſe ; the <hi rend="italic">Flatterer,</hi> whoſe character is well ſupported ; the <hi rend="italic">Imaginary
                        Forefathers,</hi> a piece which had much leſs ſucceſs, although it affords
                    ſuſſiciently good ſentiment ; the <hi rend="italic">Capricious Man,</hi> and
                    the <hi rend="italic">Dupe oſ Herſelſ,</hi> pieces of very inconſi-derable
                    merit. 7. Three comedies in proſe ; the <hi rend="italic">Ccf-ſee-houſe,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Magic Girdle,</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Madragore,</hi> which are little better than his other theatrical pieces. The theatre was
                    by no means his forte; he had a genius more ſuited for ſatire than comedy, more
                    akin to Boileau’s than Moliere’s. 8. A <hi rend="italic">Galleaioη oſ Letters,</hi> in proſe. In this edition he has ſelected the moſt intereſting.— There is
                    a larger collection in y volumes. This laſt has done at the ſame time both
                    injury and honour to his memory. Rouſſeau in it ſpeaks both in favour of and
                    againſt the very ſame perſons. He appears too haſty in tearing to pieces the
                    characters of thoſe who dil-pleaſed him. We behold in them a man of a ſteady
                    character and an elevated mind, who wiſhes to return to his native country only
                    that he might be enabled completely to juſtify his reputation. We ſee him again
                    correſponding with perſons of great merit and uncommon integrity, with the Abbé
                    d’Olivet, Racine the ſon, the poets La Foſſe andDuche, the celebrated Rol-lin,
                    M. le Franc de Pompignan, &amp;c. &amp;c. We meet alſo with ſome
                    anecdotes and exact judgments of ſeveral writers. A bookſeller in Holland has
                    publiſhed his port-folio, which does him no honour. There are, indeed, ſome
                    pieces in this wretched collection which did come from the pen of Rouſſeau ; but
                    he is leſs to be blamed for them than they are who have drawn theſe works from
                    that oblivion to which our great poet had</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r03-0532" facs="gri_33125011196389_0538.tif"/>
                <p>configned them. A pretty good edition of his <hi rend="italic">Select Pieces</hi> appeared at Paris in 1741, in a ſmall 12mo volume. His portrait, engraved
                    by the celebrated Aved, his old friend, made its appearance in 1778, with the
                    following motto from Martial :</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Certior in ηoβro carmine vultus grit.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Rousseau (John-James), was born at Geneva June 28. 17 12.
                        Plis father was by prdfeſſion a clock and watch maker. At his birth, which,
                        he ſays, was the firſt of his misfortunes, he endangered the life of his
                        mother, and he himſelf was for a long time after in a very weak and
                        languiſhing ſtate of health ; but as his bodily' ſtrength increaſed, his
                        mental powers gradually opened, and afforded the happſeſt preſages of future
                        greatnefs. His father, who was a citizen of Geneva, was a well-informed
                        tradeſman ; and in the place where he wrought he kept a Plutarch and a
                        Tacitus, and theſe authors of courſe ſoon became familiar to his ſon. A raſh
                        juvenile ſtep occaſioned his leaving his father’s houſe. “ Finding himſelf a
                        fugitive, in a ſtrange country, and without money or friends, he changed
                        (ſays he himſelf) his religion, in order to procure a ſubſiſtence.” Bornex,
                        biſhop of Anneci, from whom he fought an aſylum, committed the care of his
                        education to Madame de Warrens, an ingenious and amiable lady, who hſtd in
                        1726 left part of her wealth, and the Proteſtant religion, in order to throw
                        herſelf into the boſom of the church. This generous lady ſerved in the
                        triple capacity of a mother, a friend, and a lover, to the new proſelyte,
                        whom ſhe regarded as her ſon. Hie neceſſity of procuring for himſelf ſome
                        ſettlement, however, or perhaps his unſettled diſ-poſition, obliged Rouffeau
                        often to leave this tendhr mother.</hi></p>
                <p>He poffeffed more than ordinary talents for muſic ; and the Abbé Blanchard
                    flattered his hopes with a place in the royal chapel, which he, however, failed
                    in obtaining for him ; he was therefore under the neceſſity of teaching muſic at
                    Chamberi. He remained in this place till 1741, in which year he went to Paris,
                    where he w <hi rend="sup">r</hi> as long in very deſtitute circumſtances.
                    Writing to a friend in 1743, he thus exprefſes himſelf: * <hi rend="sup">,</hi> Every thing is dear here, but eſpecially bread.” What an expreſſion ; and
                    to what may not genius be reduced ! Meanwhile he now began to emerge from that
                    obſcurity in which he had hitherto been buried. His friends placed him with M.
                    de Montaigu, ambaſe ſador from France to Venice. According to his own
                    confeſſion, a proud miſanthropy and a peculiar contempt of the riches and
                    pleaſures of this world, conſtituted the chief traits in his character, and a
                    miſun-derſtanding ſoon took place between him and the am-baffador. The place of
                    depute, under M. Dupin, farmer-general, a man of conſiderable parts, gave him
                    ſome temporary relief, and enabled him to be of ſome benefit to Madam de Warrens
                    his former benefactreſs. lhe year 17 ςo was the commencement of his literary
                    career. The academy of Dijon had propoſed the following queſtion : “ Whether the <hi rend="italic">∣ evival</hi> of the arts and ſciences has contributed
                    to the refinement of manners?” Rouffeau at fiiſt inclined to ſupport the
                    affirmative. « This is the <hi rend="italic">pons aβ'dorum</hi> (ſays a
                    phιlυlopher, at that time a friend of his), take the negative fide of∖the
                    queſtion, and I’ll promiſe you the greateſt ſucceſs,”</p>
                <p>His diſcourſe againſt the ſciences, accordingly, having been found to be the
                    beſt written, and replete with the dcepeſt reaſoning, was publicly crowned with
                    the approbation of that learned body. Never was a paradox ſupported with more
                    eloquence ; it was not however a,nt- one; but he enriched it with all the
                    advantages which either knowledge or genius could confer on it. Immediately
                    after its appearance, he met with ſeveral opponents of <hi rend="sup">z</hi> his tenets, which he de-fended ; and from one diſpute to another, he found
                    himſelf involved in a formidable train of correſpon-deπce, without having ever
                    almoſt dreamed of ſuch oppoſition. From that period he decreaſed in happineſs as
                    he increaſed in celebrity. His “ Diſcourſe on the cauſes of inequality among
                    mankind, and on the origin of ſocial compacts,” a work full of almoſt
                    unintelligible maxims and wild ideas, was written with a view to prove that
                    mankind are equal ; that they were born to live apart from each other ; and that
                    they have perverted the order of nature in forming ſocieties. He bellows the
                    higheſt praiie on the ſtate of nature, and depreciates the idea of every ſocial
                    compact. This dilcourſe, and eſpecially the dedication of <hi rend="italic">it
                        to</hi> the republic of Geneva, are the <hi rend="italic">chef-Lœuvres</hi> of that kind of eloquence of which the ancients alone had given us any
                    idea. By preſenting this performance to the ma-giſtrates, he was received again
                    into his native country, and reinſtated in all the privileges and rights of a
                    citizen, after having with much difficulty prevailed on himſelf to abjure the
                    Catholic religion. He ſoon, however, returned to France, and lived for ſome time
                    in Paris. He afterwards gave himſelf up to retirement, to eſeape the ſhafts of
                    criticiſm, and follow after the regimen which the ſtrangury, with which he was
                    tormented, demanded of him. This is an important epoch in the hiilory of his
                    life, as it is owing to this circum-ftance, perhaps, that we have the moſt
                    elegant works that have come from his pen. His “ Letter to M. d’Alembert” on the
                    deſign of erecting a theatre at Geneva, written in his retirement, and publiſhed
                    in‘ 1757, contains, along with ſome paradoxes, ſome very important and
                    well-handled truths. This letter firſt drew down upon him the envy of Voltaire,
                    and was the cauſe of thoſe indignities with which that author never ceaſed to
                    load him. What is fingular in him, is, that althouglι ſo great an enemy to
                    theatrical reprefen--tations himſelf, he cauſed a comedy to be printed, and in
                    1752 gave to the theatre a paſtoral (The Village Conjuror), of which he compoſed
                    both the poetry and muſic, both of them abounding with ſentiment and elegance,
                    and full of innocent and rural ſimplicity. What renders the Village Conjuror
                    highly delightful to perſons of taſte, is that perfect harmony of words and
                    muſic which everywhere pervades it ; that proper connection among the parties
                    who compoſe it ; and its being perfectly correct from beginning to end. The
                    muſician hath ſpoken, hath thought, and felt like a poet. Everything in it is
                    agreeable, interefting, and far ſuperior to thole common affected and inſipid
                    productions of our modern petit-oramas. His Dictionary of Muſic affords ſeveral
                    excellent articles; ſome of them, however, are very inaccurate. “ This work
                    (ſays M. la Borde), in his Effay on Muſic, has need to be written over again, to
                    fave much trouble to thoſe who wiſh to ſtudy it, arid prevent them from falling
                    into errors, which</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r03-0533" facs="gri_33125011196389_0539.tif"/>
                <p>it is difficult to avoid, from the engaging manner in which Rouſſeau drags along
                    his readers.” The paſe ſages in it which have any reference to literature may
                    be eaſily diſtinguiſhed, as they are treated with the agreeableneſs of a man of
                    wit and *he exactneſs of a nian of taſte. Rouſſeau, ſoon after the rapid ſucceſs
                    of his Village Conjuror, publiſhed a Letter <hi rend="italic">on</hi> French
                    Muſic, or rather <hi rend="italic">againfi</hi> French muſic, written with as
                    much freedom as livelineſs. The exaſperated partiſans of French comedy treated
                    him with as much ſury as if he had conſpired againſt the ſtate. A crowd of
                    inſigni-ficant enthuſiaſts ſpent their ſtrength in outcries againſt him. He was
                    iniulted, menaced, and lampooned. Harmonic fanaticiſm went even to hang him up
                    in effigy.</p>
                <p>That intereſting and tender ſtyle, which is ſo conſpicuous throughout the
                    Village Conjuror, animates ſeveral letters in the New Heloiſa, in ſix parts,
                    publiſhed 176x, in I2mo. This epiſtolary romance, of which the plot is
                    ill-managed, and the arrangement bad, like all other works of genius, has its
                    beauties as well as its faults. More truth in his characters and more preciſion
                    in his details were to have been wiſhed. The characters, as well as their ſtyle,
                    have too much ſameneſs, and their language is too affected and exaggerated. Some
                    of the letters are indeed admirable, from the force and warmth of expreſſion,
                    from an eſſerveſcence of ſenti-ments, ſrom the irregularity of ideas which
                    always cha-racteriſe a paſſion carried to its height. But why is ſo affecting a
                    letter ſo often accompanied with an unimportant digreſſion, an inſipid
                    criticiſm, or a ſelf contradicting paradox ? Why, after having (hone in all the
                    energy of ſentiment, does he on a hidden turn unaffecting ? It is becauſe none
                    of the perſonages are truly intereſting. That of St Preux is weak, and often
                    forced Julia is ad affemblage of tenderneſs and pity, of elevation of foul and
                    of coquetry, of natural parts and pedantry. Wolmar is a violent man, and almoſt
                    beyond the limits of nature. In fine, when he wiſhcs to change his ſtyle, and
                    adopt that of the ſpeaker, it may eaſily be obſerved that he docs not long
                    ſupport it, and every attempt em-barraffes the author and cools the reader. In
                    the He-loiſa, Rouſſeau’s unlucky talent of rendering every thing problematical,
                    appears very conſpicuous; as in his arguments in favour of and againſt duelling,
                    which afford an apology for ſuicide, and a juſt condemnation of it : in his
                    facility in palliating the crime of adultery, and his very ſtrong reaſons to
                    make it abhorred : on the one hand, in declamations againſt ſocial happi-neſs ;
                    on.the other, intranſports in favour of humanity : here, in violent rhapſodies
                    againſt philoſophers ; there, •by a rage for adopting their opinions : the
                    exiſtence of God attacked by ſophiſtry, and Atheiſts confuted by the moſt
                    irrefragable arguments ; the Chriſtian religion combated by the moſt ſpecious
                    objections, and celebrated wfith the moſt ſublime eulogies.</p>
                <p>His Emilia afterwards made more noiſe than .the new Helofia. This moral romance,
                    which was publiſhed in' 176 &gt;, in four vols ιzmo, treats chiefly of
                    education. Rouſſeau wiſhed to follow nature in every thing ; and though his
                    ſyſtem in ſeveral places differs from received ideas, it delerves in many
                    reſpects to be put in practice, and with ſome neceſſary modifications it has
                    been ſo. His precepts are expreſſed with the force and dignity of a mind full oſ
                    the leading truths of morality. 7f he has not always been virtuous? no body at
                    leaſt</p>
                <p>has ſelt ſt more, or made it appear to more advantage. Every thing which he ſays
                    againſt luxury ſhows the vices and conceited opinions of his age, and is worthy
                    at once of Plato or of Tacitus. His ſtyle is peculiar to himſelf. He ſometimes,
                    however, appears, by a kind of affected rudeneſs and aſperity, to ape at the
                    mode of Montaigne, of whom he is a great admirer, and whoſe ſentiments and
                    expreſſions he often clothes in a new drtſſs. What is moſt to be lamented L,
                    that in wiſhing to educate a young man as a Chriſtian he has filled his third
                    volume with objections againſt Chriſtianity. He has, it muſt be confeſſed, given
                    a very ſublime eulogium on the goſpel, and an affecting portrait of its divine
                    Author : but the miracles, and the prophecies which ſerve to eſtabliſh his
                    miſſion, he attacks without the leaſt reſerve. Admitting only natural religion,
                    he weighs every thing in the balance of reaſon; and this reaſon being falſe,
                    leads him into dilemmas veιy unfavourable to his own hepoſe and happineſs.</p>
                <p>He dwelt from 1754 in a ſmall houſe in the country near Montmorenci ; a retreat
                    which he owed to the generoſity of a farmer-general. The cauſe oſ his love for
                    this retirement was, according to himſelf, “ that invincible ſpirit of liberty
                    which nothing could conquer, and in competition with which honours, fortune, and
                    reputation, could not ſtand. It is true, this defire of liberty has occaſioned
                    leſs pride than lazineſs ; but this indolence is inconceivable. Every thing
                    ſtartlesit; the moſt inconſiderable reciprocalities of ſocial life are to it
                    inſupportable. A word to ſpeak, a letter to write, a viſit to pay, things
                    neceſſary to be done, are to me pu-niſhments. Hear my reaſons. Although the
                    ordinary intercourſe between mankind be odious to me, intimate friendſhip
                    appears to me very dear ; becauſe there are no mere ceremonies due to it ; it
                    agrees with the heart, and all is accompliſhed. Hear, again, why I have always
                    ſhunned kindneſſes ſo much ; becauſe every act of kindneſs requires a grateful
                    mind, and I find my heart ungrateful, ſrom this alone, that gratitude is a duty.
                    Laſtly, that kind of felicity which is neceſſary for me, is not ſo much to do
                    that which I wiſh, as not to do what I wiſh, not to do.” Rouſſeau enjoyed this
                    felicity which he ſo much wiſhed in his retirement. Without entirely adopting
                    that too rigorous mode of life purſued by the ancient Cynics, he deprived
                    himſelf of every thing that could in any meaſure 'add fuel to this wiſhed-for
                    luxury, which is ever the companion of riches, and which inverts even cuſtom
                    itſelf. He might have been happy in this retreat, if he could have forgot this
                    public which he affected to deſpiſe ; but his deſire after a great name got the
                    better of his ſelf love, and it was this thirſt after reputation which made him
                    introduce ſo many dangerous paragraphs in his Emilia.</p>
                <p>The French parliament condemned this book in. 1762, and entered into a criminal
                    proſecution againſt the author, which forced him to make a precipitate retreat.
                    He dire&lt;cted his ſteps towards his native country, which ſhut its gates
                    upon him. Proſeribed in the place where he firſt drew breath, he ſought an
                    aſylum in Switzerland, and found one in the principality of Neufchatel. His
                    firſt care was to défend his Emilia againſt the mandate of the archbiſhop of
                    Paris, by whom it had been anathematiſed. In 1763 he publiſhed a letter, in
                    which he re-exhibits all his errors, let off with</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r03-0534" facs="gri_33125011196389_0540.tif"/>
                <p>the moſt animated diſplay of eloquence, and in the moſt inſidious manner. In
                    this letter he deſcribes himſelf as “ more vehement than· celebrated in his
                    reſearches, but ſincere on the whole, even againſt himſelf ; ſimple and good,
                    but ſenſible and weak ; often doing evil, and always loving good ; united by
                    friendſhip, never by circumſtances, and keeping more to his opinions than to his
                    intereſts ; requiring nothing of men, and not wiſhing to be under any obligation
                    to them ; yielding no more to their prejudices than to their will, and
                    preſerving his own as free as his reaſon; diſputing about religion without
                    lſeentiouſneſs ; loving neither impiety nor fanaticiſm, but diſliking preciſe
                    people more than bold ſpirits,” &amp;c. &amp;c. From this ſpecimen, the
                    limitations he would appoint to this portrait may eaſily be dilcovered.</p>
                <p>The letters of La Montaigne appeared ſoon after ; but this work, far leſs
                    eloquent, and full of envious diſ-cuſſions on the magiſtrates and clergy of
                    Geneva, irritated the Proteſtarit miniſters without effecting a reconciliation
                    with the clergy of the Romiſh church. Rouſſeau had ſolemnly abjured the latter
                    religion in 1753, and, what is ſomewhat ſtrange, had then reſolved to live^_ in
                    France, a Catholic country. The Proteſtant clergy were not fully reconciled by
                    this change ; and the protection oſ the king of Pruſſia, to whom the
                    principality of Neufchatel belonged, was not ſuſſicient to reſcue him from that
                    obloquy which the mim'ſter of Moutiers-Travers, the village to which he had
                    retired, had excited againſt him. He preached againſt Rouſſeau, and his fermons
                    produced an uproar among the people. On the night between the 6th and 7th
                    September 1765, ſome fanatics, drove on by wine and the declamations of their
                    miniſter, threw ſome ſtones at the windows of the Genevan philoſopher, who
                    fearing new inſults, in vain fought an aſylum in the canton of Berne. As this
                    Canton was connected with the republic of Geneva, they did not think proper to
                    allow him to remain in their city, being proſeribed by that republic. Neither
                    his broken ſtate of health, nor the approach of winter, could ſoften the hearts
                    of theſe obdurate Spartans. In vain, to prevent them from the feartheyhad of the
                    ſpreading of his opinions, did he beſeech them to ſhut him up in priſon till the
                    ſpring ; for even this favour was denied him. Obliged to ſet out on a journey,
                    in the beginning of a very inclement ſeaſon, he reached Straſ-bourg in a very
                    deſtitute ſituation. He received from Marſhal de Contades, who then commanded in
                    that place, every accommodation which could be expected from generoſity,
                    humanity, and compaſſion. He waited there till the weather was milder, when he
                    went to Paris, where Mr Flume then was, who determined on taking him with him to
                    England. After having made ſome ſtay in Paris, Rouſſeau actually ſet out for
                    London in 176b. Hume, much affected with his ſituation and his misfortunes,
                    procured for him a very agreeable ſettlement in the country. Our Genevan
                    philoſopher was not, however, long ſatisſied with this new place. He did not
                    make ſuch an impreſſion on the minds of the Engliſh as he had done on the
                    French. His free diſpoſition, his obdurate and melancholy temper, was deemed no
                    ſingularity in England. He was there looked upon as an ordinary man, and the
                    periodical prints were filled with ſatires againſt him. In" particular, they
                    publiſhed a forged letter from the king of Pruſſia, holding up to ridicule the
                    principles and •conduit of tl⅛is new Diogenes. Rouſſeau imagined there was a
                    plot between Hume and ſome philoſophers in France to deſtroy his glory and
                    repoſe. He lent a letter to him, filled with the moſt abuſive expreſſions, and
                    reproaching him for his conduct towards him. From this time he looked upon Hume
                    as a wicked and perfidious perſon, who had brought him to England with no other
                    view than to expoie him to public ridicule ; which fooliſh and chimerical idea
                    was nouriſhed by ſelſ-love and a reſtleſs diſpoſition. He imagined that the
                    Engliſh philoſopher, amidſt all his kindneſſes, had ſomething diſagreeable in
                    the manner of expreſſing them. The bad health of Rouſſeau, a ſtrong and
                    melancholy imagination, a too nice ſenſibility, a jealous diſpoſition, joined
                    with philoſophic vanity, cheriſhed by the falle informations of his governeſs,
                    who poſſeſſed an uncommon power over him ; all theſe taken together, might tend
                    to prepoſſeſs him with unfavourable ſentiments of ſome innocent freedoms his
                    benefactor might have taken with him, and might render him ungrateful, which he
                    thought himſelf incapable of becoming. Meanwhile, theſe falſe conjectures and
                    probabilities ought never to have had the weight with an honeſt mind to withdraw
                    itſelf from its friend and benefactor. Proofs are always neceſſary in caſes of
                    this kind; and that which Rouſſeau had was by no means a certain demonſtration.
                    The Genevan philoſopher, however, certainly returned to France. In paſſing
                    through Amiens, he met with M. Greſſet, who interrogated him about his
                    misfortunes and the controverſies he had been engaged in. He only anſwered, “
                    You have got the art of making a parrot ſpeak ; but you are not yet poſſeſſed of
                    the ſecret of making a bear ſpeak.” In the mean time, the magiſtratts of this
                    city wiſhed to confer on him ſome mark of their eſteem, which he abſolutely
                    refuſed. His diſordered imagination viewed theſe flattering civilities as
                    nothing elſe than inſults, ſuch as were laviſhed on Sancho in the iſland of
                    Barataria. He thought one part of the people looked upon him as like Lazarille
                    of Tormes, who, being fixed to the bottom of a tub, with only his head out of
                    the water, was carried from one town to another to amuſe the vulgar. But theſe
                    wrong and whimſical ideas did not prevent him from aſpiring after a reſidence in
                    Paris, where, without doubt, he was more looked on as a ſpectacle than in any
                    other place whatever. On the ill July 1770, Rouſſeau appeared, for the firſt
                    time, at the regency coffee-houſe, dreſſed in ordinary clothing, having for ſome
                    time previous to this wore an Armenian habit. He was loaded with praiſes by the
                    ſurrounding multitude. “ It is ſomewhat ſingular (ſays M. Sennebier) to ſee a
                    man ſo haughty as he returning to the very place from whence he had been
                    baniſhed ſo often. Nor is it one of the ſmalleſt inconſiſtencies of this
                    extraordinary character, that he preferred a retreat in that place of which he
                    had ſpoken ſo much ill.” It is as ſingular that a perſon under ſentence of
                    impriſonment ſhould wiſh to live in ſo public a manner in the very place where
                    his ſentence was in force againſt him. His friends procured for him, however,
                    liberty of ſtaying, on condition that he ſhould neither write on religion nor
                    politics : he kept his word ; ſor he wrote none at all. He was contented with
                    living in a calm philoſophical manner, giving himſelf to the ſociety of a few
                    tried friends, ſhunning the</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r03-0535" facs="gri_33125011196389_0541.tif"/>
                <p>company of the great, appearing to have given up all his whimſies, and affecting
                    neither the character of a philoſopher nor a <hi rend="italic">bel eſprit.</hi> He died of an apoplexy at Ermenon-ville, belonging to the marquis de
                    Girardin, about ten leagues from Paris, July 2. 1778, aged 66 years. This
                    nobleman has erected to his memory a very plain monument, in a grove of poplars,
                    which conftitutes part of his heautifnl gardens. On the tomb are iaſcribed the
                    following epitaphs :</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Ici repoſe</hi></p>
              <p>                <hi rend="italic">L'Homme de la Nature</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Et de la Verite!</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Vitam impendere Vero<note anchored="true" place="margin" type="authorial">His motto.</note>.</hi>
              </p>                <p><hi rend="italic">Hic jacent Ossa J. J. Rouſſeau.</hi></p>
                <p>The curious who go to ſee this tomb likewiſe ſee the cloak which the Genevan
                    philoſopher wore. Above the door is inſcribed the following ſentence, which
                    might afford matter for a whole book : “ He is truly free, who, to accompliſh
                    his pleaſure, has no need of <hi rend="italic">the aſſiſlance of a fécond
                        perſon”</hi> Rouſſeau, during his ftay in the environs of Lyons, married
                    Mademoiselle le Vaſſeur, his governeſs, a woman who, without either beauty or
                    talents, had gained over him a great aſcen-dancy. She waited on him in health
                    and in ſickneſs : But as if ſhe had been jealous of poſſeſſing him alone, ſhe
                    drove from his mind, by the moſt perfidious iniinu-ations, all thoſe who came to
                    entertain him ; and when Rouſſeau did not diſmiſs them, ſhe prevented their
                    return by invariably refufing them admittance. By theſe means ſhe the more
                    eaſily led her huſhand into incon-ſiſtencies of conduct, which the originality
                    of his character as well as of his opinions ſo much contributed to aſſiſt.
                    Nature had perhaps but given him the embryo of his character, and art had
                    probably united to make it more fingular. He did not incline to aſſociate with
                    any perſon ; and as this method of thinking and living was uncommon, it procured
                    him a name, and he difplayed a kind of fantaſticalneſs in his behaviour and his
                    writings. Like Diogenes of old, he united Simplicity of manners with all the
                    pride of genius ; and a large ſtock of indolence, with an extreme ſenlibility,
                    ſerved to render his character ſtill more uncommon. “ An indolent mind (ſays
                    he), terrified at every application, a warm, bilious, and irritable temperament,
                    ſenſible alſo in a high degree to every thing that can affect it, appear not
                    poſſible to be united in the ſame perſon : and yet theſe two contrarieties
                    compoſe the chief of mine. An active life has no charms for me. I would an
                    hundred times rather conſent to be idle than to do any thing againſt my will ;
                    and I have an hundred times thought that I would live not amiſs in the Baſtille,
                    provided I had nothing to do but juſt continue there. In my younger days I made
                    ſeveral attempts to get in there ; but as they were only with the view of
                    procuring a refuge and reſt in my old age, and, like the exertions of an
                    indolent pa <hi rend="sup">v</hi> fon, only by fits and ftarts, they were
                    »ever attended with the ſmalleſt ſucceſs. When misfortunes came, they afforded
                    me a pretext of giving myſelf up to my ruling paſſion.” He often exaggerated his
                    misfortunes to himſelf as well as to others. He endeavoured particularly to
                    render intereſting by his description his misfortunes and his poverty, although
                    the former were ſar leſa than he imagined, and notwith-ftanding he had certain
                    reſources againſt the latter. In <hi rend="sup">1</hi> other refpects he was
                    charitable, generous, ſober, juſt, ' contenting himſelf with what was purely
                    neceſſary, and refufing the means which might have procured him wealth and
                    offices. He cannot, like many other ſo-phiſts, be accuſed oſ having often
                    repeated with a ſtudied emphafis the word <hi rend="italic">Dir tue,</hi> without inſpiring the ſentiment. When he is ſpeaking of the duties of mankind,
                    of the principles neceſſary to our happineſs, of the duty we owe to ourſelves
                    and to our equals, it is with a copiouſneſs, a charm, and an impetuofity, that
                    could only proceed from the heart. He ſaid one day to M. de Buffon, “ You have
                    aſſerted and proved before J. J. Rouſſeau that mothers ought to ſuckle their
                    children.” “ Yes (ſays this great naturaliſt), we have all ſaid ſo ; but M.
                    Rouſſeau alone forbids it, and cauſes himſelf to be obeyed.” Another academician
                    ſaid, “ that the virtues of Voltaire were without heart, and thoſe of Rouſſeau
                    without head.” He was acquainted at an early age with the works of the Greek and
                    Roman authors ; and the republican virtues there held forth to view, the
                    rigorous auſterity of Cato, Brutus, &amp;c. carried him beyond the limits of
                    a ſimple eſtimation of them. Influenced by his imagination, he admired every
                    thing in the ancients, and ſaw nothing in his contemporaries but enervated minds
                    and degenerated bodies.</p>
                <p>His ideas about politics were almoſt as eccentric as· his paradoxes about
                    religion. Some reckon his <hi rend="italic">Social Compaft,</hi> which
                    Voltaire calls the <hi rend="italic">Unſocial Compact,</hi> the greateſt
                    effort his genius produced. Others find it full of contradictions, errors, and
                    cynical paſſages, obſcure, ilharranged, and by no means worthy of his ſhining
                    pen. There are ſeveral other ſmall pieces wrote by him, to be found.in a
                    collection of his works publiſhed in 25 vols 8vo and 12mo, to which there is
                    appended a very inſignificant ſupplement in 6 vols.</p>
                <p>The moſt uſeful and moſt important truths in this collection are picked out in
                    his Thoughts; in which the confident ſophiſt and the impious author diſappear,
                    and nothing is offered to the reader but the eloquent writer and the
                    contemplative moraliſt. There were found in his port-folio his Conſeſſions, in
                    twelve books ; the firſt fix oſ-which were publiſhed. “ In the preface to theſe
                    memoirs, which abound with characters well drawn, and written with warmth, with
                    energy, and ſometimes with elegance, he declares (ſays M. Paliſſot), like a
                    peeviſh miſanthrope, who boldly introduces himſelf on the ruins of the world, to
                    declare to mankind, whom he ſuppoſes aſſembled upon theſe ruins, that in that
                    innumerable multitude, none could dare to ſay, <hi rend="italic">I am better
                        than that man.</hi> This affectation of ſeeing himſelf alone in the
                    univerſe, and of continually directing every thing to himſelf, may appear to
                    ſome moroſe minds a fanaticiſm of pride, of which we have no examples, at leaſt
                    ſince the time of Cardan.” But this is not the only blame which may be attached
                    to the author of the Conſeſſions. With uneaſmeſs we ſee him, under the pretext
                    of fin-cerity, diſſionouring the character of his benefactreſs Lady Warren.
                    There are innuendos no leſs oſſenfive againſt obſcure and celebrated characters,
                    which ought entirely or partly to have feeen ſuppreſſed. A lady of wit ſaid,
                    that Rouſſeau would have been held in higher eſtimation for virtue, “ had he
                    died without his confeſ-ſion.” The ſame opinion is entertained by M. Senne-</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r03-0536" facs="gri_33125011196389_0542.tif"/>
                <p>bier, author of the Literary Hiſtory of Geneva : “ His confeſſions (ſays he)
                    appear to me to be a very dangerous book, and paint Rouſſeau in ſuch colours as
                    we would never have ventured to apply to him. The excellent analyſes which we
                    meet with of ſome ſentiments, and the delicate anatomy which he makes of ſome
                    actions, are not ſuſſicient to counterbalance the deteftable matter which is
                    found in them, and the unceaſing obloquies everywhere to be met with.” It is
                    certain, that if Rouſſeau has given a faithful delineation of ſome perſons, he
                    has viewed others through a cloud, which formed in his mind perpetual
                    ſuſpſeions. He imagined he thought juſtly and ſpoke truly ; but the ſimpleſt
                    thing in nature, ſays M. Serv mt, if diſtilled throu⅛ his violent and ſuſpſeious
                    head, might becom poiſom Rouſſeau, in what he fays of himſelf, makes ſuch
                    acknowledgments as certainly prove that there were better men than he, at leaſt
                    if we may judge him from the ſirſt ſix books of his memoirs, where nothing
                    appears but his vices. They ought not perhaps to be ſeparated from the ſix laſt
                    books, where he ſptaks of the virtues which make reparation ſor them ; or rather
                    the work ought not to have been publiſhed at all, iſ it be truc (which there can
                    be little doubt of) that in his conſeſ-ſions hς injured the public manners, both
                    by the baſe-neſs of the vices be diſcloſed, and by the manner in which he united
                    them ith the virtues. The other pieces which we find in this new edition oſ his
                    works are, I. <hi rend="italic">The Reveries oſ a Solitary ÏV .ndeιer,</hi> being a journal of the latter part of his life. In this he confeſſes, that he
                    liked better to ſend his children into hofpitals deſtined ſor orphans, than to
                    take upon himſelf the charge of their maintenance and education ; and endeavours
                    to palliate this error, which nothing can exculpate. 2. <hi rend="italic">Cοηfιderations upon the Government oſ Poland.</hi> 3. <hi rend="italic">The Adventures of l ord Ed ∙tυ rd,</hi> a novel, being a kind of ſupplement
                    to the new Heloiſa. 4· <hi rend="italic">Famous Memoirs and Eugitive Pieces,</hi> with a great number of letters, ſome of which are very long, and written
                    with too much ſtudy, but containing ſome eloquent paſſages and ſome deep
                    thought. 5. <hi rend="italic">Emilia and Sophia.</hi> 6. <hi rend="italic">The Levite of Ephraim,</hi> a poem in proſe, in 4 cantos ; written in a
                    truly ancient ſtyle oſ ſimplicity. 7. <hi rend="italic">l</hi> <hi rend="italic">Mers to Sara.</hi> 8. <hi rend="italic">An Opera and a
                        Comedy.</hi> 9. <hi rend="italic">Tranβations of thefrfl book oſ Tacitus’s
                        Hiβory, oſ the Epiſode of Olinda and Sophrοnia, taken from Taff),</hi> &amp;c. &amp;c. Like all the other writings of Rouſſeau, we find in
                    theſe poſthumous pieces many admirable and ſome uſeful things ; but they alſo
                    abound with contradictions, paradoxes, and ideas very unfavourable to religion.
                    In his letters eſpecially we ſee a man chagrined at misfortunes, which he never
                    attributes to himſelf, ſuſpſeious of every body about him, calling and believing
                    himſelf a lamb in the midſt of wohes ; in one word, as like Paſcal in the
                    ſtrength of his genius, as in his fancy of always feeing a precipice about him.
                    This is the reflection oſ M. Servant, who knew him, aſſiſted him, and careſſed
                    him during his retreat at Grenoble in 768. This magiſtrate having been very
                    attentive in obſerving his character, ought the rather to be believed, as he
                    inſpected it without either malice, envy, or reſcntment, and only from the
                    concern he had for this philoſopher. whom he loved and admired.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
