<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r03-0501-02" facs="gri_33125011196389_0507.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>ROSS</label>
in Herefordſhire, in England, 119 miles; from London, is a fine old town, with a good trade, on the river Wye. It was made a free borough by’ Henry III. It is a populous place, famous ior cyder,, anti was noted in Camden’s time for a manufacture of iron-wares. There are in it two charity-ſchools, which lately have been enriched by a legacy of 200 1. <hi rend="italic">per annum.</hi> from Mr Scott, in Dec. 1786, a ſecond <hi rend="italic">Man oſ Ro∕s.</hi> And its market and fairs are well ſtored with cattle and other provifions. At the well end of it there is a fine broad cauſeway, conſtructed by Mr John Kyrle, the celebrated <hi rend="italic">Man of R∩fs,</hi> who allô raiſed the ſpire upward of 100 feet, and incloſed a piece of ground with a ſtone wall, and funk a reſervoir in its centre, for-the uſe of the inhabitants of the town. He died in x714, aged 90, with the bleſſing of all who knew him, both rich and poor. There cannot be a pleaſanter country than the banks of the Wye, between this town and Monmouth. W. Long. 2. 25, N. Lat. 5 1. 56.</p><p>Ross, a county of Scotland, including Tayne and Cromarty, ſtretching 80 miles in length, and 78 in breadth, is bounded on the well by the weſtern fea <hi rend="sub">ik</hi> and part of the iſle of Sky ; by Inverneſs, on the ſouthj Strathnavern and Sutherland, on the north and north-, eaſt ; and by Cromarty and the Murray-Frith ôn the eaſt. 'Γayne includes the greater part of Roſs, with the iſles of Sky, Lewis, and Harries. Cromarty lies on the other fide of the Murray-Frith, to the northward of In-» verneſs, extending but 12 miles in length, bounded on the ſouth and eaſt by part of Roſs and the Frith of Murray, and by the Frith of Cromarty on the north&gt; 'Γhe flιire of Roſs takes up the whole breadth of the iſland ; and being much indented with bays and inlets from both ſeas, appears of a very irregular form.— Theſe bays afford ſafe harbours for ſhipping, eſpecially that of Cromarty, which is capacious enough to contain all the fleets of Europe, being land-locked on every fide, and is in all reſpects one of the beſt harbours in the known world. The Frith of Tayne, on the eaſt fide of the ſhire, runs up 25 miles ſrom the ſea, as far as the Cape Tarbat, dividing Roſs from Sutherland : it is about ſeven miles broad at the mouth, but, on account of quick∙fands, unſafe for navigation. The country of Roſs is encumbered with huge mountains,, on which the ſnow lies for the greateſt part of the year; theſe, however, yield good pafture ; but on the eaſtern fide, next the German ocean, the country admits of agriculture, and produces good crops of corn. The valleys are fertilized by ſeveral rivers, among which we reckon the Okcl, the Charron, and the Braan ; be. ſides a number of freſh-water lakes, which indeed ar⅛⅜</p>
<pb xml:id="eb03-16-r03-0502" facs="gri_33125011196389_0508.tif"/>
<p>found in every part of this country. The valleys, or ſtraths, are generally covered with wood ; and near Al-frag there are foreſts of fir ιy ôr 20 miles in length, well ſtocked with deer and game of all forts. Great numbers of black cattle, horſes flιeep, and goats, are fed upon the mountains ; and the ſea, rivers, and lakes, teem with fiſh and fowl. The lochs on the weſtern coaſt abound with herrings in the ſeaſon, particularly Loch Eu, about nine miles long, and three in breadth ; one part of this is formed by a bay, or inlet of the ſea ; and the other is a lake of freſh water. The Tides of it are covered with wood, where formerly abundance of iron was ſmelted. Though the middle part of Roſs, called <hi rend="italic">Ardroſs,</hi> is mountainous and ſcarce inhabited, the north-eaſt parts on the rivers Okel, Charron, and Frith of Tayne, are fruitful, and abound with villages. Coygach and Aſsgut, two northerly diſtricts, are bare and hilly ; yet they abound with deer and black cattle; and we ſee ſeveral good houſes towards the coaſt, where there are alſo promontories, and huge r0ck3 of marble. Ardmeanach part of the peninſula betwixt the bays cf Cromarty and Murray, is a barony, which of old be owed a title on the king of Scotland’s ſecond ſon. The di rict of Glen-elchig, on the ſouth-we ‘, as the paternal e '.ate of the earl of Seafo th, chief of the clan of Mackenzie : but the la I earl of that name, having riſen in rebellion, was in the year 1719 defeated at Glen-ihiel, in th∣s very quarter, together with a ſmall body of Spaniards by whom he had been joined. His auxiliaries were taken ; and though he himſelf, with ſome of his friends, eſeaped to the continent, his e <hi rend="sup">ι</hi> ate and honours were forfeited. At the ſame time, the king’s troops, who obtained this victory, diſmantled the caſtle of Yion donnen, ſituated on an iſland in a bay that fronts the ifle of Sky. It belonged to the crown ; but the office of hereditary governor was <hi rend="italic">ve'</hi> ed in the earl of Seaforth, and here he had erected his magazine. Roſs is chiefly peopled by the Mackenzies and Fraſers, two warlike clans, who ſpeak Erſe, and live in the Highland faſhion. There are fiſheries carried on along the coa <hi rend="sup">ι</hi> ' ; but their chief traffic is with ſſieep and black cattle. The chief towns of Roſs are Channerie, Dingwall, Tayne, and Fortroſe.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>