<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r03-0553-05" facs="gri_33125011196389_0559.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>RUSHWORTH</label>
(John), the compiler of ſome uſeful collections reſpecting the affairs of ſtate, was born in Northumberland about the year 1607, and was de-ſcended of honourable anceſtors. After attending the univerſity of Oxford for ſome time, he removed to Lincoln’s Inn ; but the ſtudy of law not ſuiting his genius, he ſoon deſerted it, in order to ſeek a ſituation where he might more eaſily gratify his love for political information. He frequented the meetings of parliament, and wrote down the ſpeeches both of the king and members. During the ſpace of 11 years, From 1630 to 1640, when no parliament was held, he was an attentive obſerver of the great tranſactions of ſtate in the ſtar-chamber, the court of honour, and exchequer chamber, when all the judges of England aſſembled there on caſes of great emergency. Nor did he neglect to obſerve with a watchful eye thoſe events which happened at a diſtance from the capital. He vilited the camp at Berwick, was preſent at the battle of Newborn, at the treaty of Rippon, and at the great council of York.</p><p>In 1640 he was appointed aſſiſtant to Henry Elſynge clerk to the houſe of commons, and thus had the beſt opportunities of being acquainted with their debates and proceedings. The commons conſidered him as a perſon worthy of confidence. In particular, they truſted him with carrying their meffages to the king while he remained at York. And when the parliament created Sir Thomas Fairfax their general, Ruſhworth was appointed his ſecretary, and diſcharged the office much to the advantage of his maſter. When Fairfax reſign-ed his commiſſion, his ſecretary returned to Lincoln’s Inn, and was ſoon after (in 1651-2) choſen one of the committee that was appointed to deliberate concerning the propriety and means oſ altering or new-modelling the common law. He was elected one of the repre-fentatives for Berwick upon Tweed to the parliament which Richard Cromwell aſſembled in 1658, and was re-elected by the ſame town to the parliament which reſtored Charles II. to the crown.</p><p>Aſter the Reſtoration, he delivered to the king ſeve-</p>
<pb xml:id="eb03-16-r03-0554" facs="gri_33125011196389_0560.tif"/>
<p>ral books oſ the privy-council, which he had preſerved in his own poſſeſſion during the commotions which then agitated the country. Sir Orlando Bridgeman keeper oſ the great ſeal choſe him his ſecretary in 1677, an office which he enjoyed as long as Sir Orlando kept the ſeals. In 1678 he was a third time choſen member for Berwick, and a fourth time in the enſuing parliament in 1679· He was also a member of the parliament which was convened at Oxford. The different offices he had held afforded him favourable opportunities of acquiring a fortune, or at leaſt an independence ; yet, whether from negligence or prodigality, he was never poſſeſſed of wealth. Having run himſelf into debt, he was arreſted and committed to the King’s Bench pri-ſon, Southwark, where he lingered for the laſt ſix years of his life in the moſt deplorable condition. His memory and judgment were much impaired, partly by age and partly by the too frequent uſe of ſpirituous liquors. He died on the 12th of May 1690.</p><p>His “ Hiſtorical Collections of private Paſſages in State, weighty Matters in Law, remarkable Proceedings in Parliament,” were publiſhed in folio at different times. The ſirſt part, comprehending the years between 1618 and 1629, appeared in 1659. The copy had been entruſted by Oliver Cromwell to Whitelock, with inſtructions to peruſe and examine it. Upon peruſing it, he thought it neceſſary to make ſome alterations and additions. The ſecond part was publiſhed in 1680 ; the third in 1692 ; the fourth and laſt, which comes down to the year 1648, was publiſhed in 1701 ; and altogether made ſeven volumes. Theſe underwent a ſecond edition in 1721 ; and the trial of the earl of Strafford was added, which made the eighth. This work has been much applauded by thoſe who condemn the conduct of Charles I. and accuſed of partiality by thoſe who favour the cauſe of that unhappy monarch. One perſon in particular, Dr John Nelſon of Cambridge, in a Collection of the Affairs of State publiſhed by the command of Charles II. undertook to prove, “ that Ruſhworth has concealed truth, endeavoured to vindicate the prevailing detractions of the late times, as well as their barbarous actions, and with a kind of rebound to libel the government at ſecond-hand.” This accuſation ſeems to be carried too far. His principles indeed led him to ſhow the king and his adherents in an unfavourable light, and to vindicate the proceedings of parliament ; yet it cannot juſtly be affirmed that he has miſrepreſented or falsified any oſ the ſpeeches or facts which he has admitted into his collection. Perhaps he may have omitted ſome papers merely becauſe they were unfavourable to the party which he had eſpouſed ; and is therefore not to be conſidered as an impartial hiſtorian who relates the whole truth, but as an honeſt lawyer, who ſtates all his facts fairly and candidly, but paſſes over ſuch as are injurious to his client’s cauſe.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>