<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r03-0497-08" facs="gri_33125011196389_0503.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>ROSCOMMON</label>
(Wentworth Dillon, earl of), a celebrated poet of the 17th century, was the ſon of James Dillon earl of Roſcommon ; and was born in Ireland, under the adminiſtration of the firſt earl of Strafford, who was his uncle, and from whom he received the name of <hi rend="italic">Wentworth</hi> at his baptiſm. He paffed his infancy in Ireland ; after which the earl of Strafford ſent for him into England, and placed him at his own ſeat in Yorkſhire, under the tuition of Dr Hall, afterwards biſhop of Norwich, who inſtructed him in Latin, without teaching him the common rules of grammar, which he could never retain in his memory, and yet he learnt to write in that language with claffical elegance and propriety. On the earl of Strafford’s being impeached, he went to complete his education at Caen in Normandy ; and after ſome years travelled to Rome, where he became acquainted with the moſt valuable remains of antiquity, and in particular was well ſkilled in medals, and learned to ſpeak Italian with ſuch grace and fluency, that he was frequently taken for a native. He returned to England ſoon after the Relloration, and was made captain of the band of penſioners ; but a diſ-pute with the lord privy-ſeal, about a part of his eſtate, obliged him to reſign his poſt, and reviſit his native country, where the duke of Ormond appointed him captain oſ the guards. He was unhappily very fond of gaming ; and as he was returning to his lodgings from a gaming-table in Dublin, he was attacked in the dark by three ruffians, who were employed to aſſaſſinate him.</p>
<pb xml:id="eb03-16-r03-0498" facs="gri_33125011196389_0504.tif"/>
<p>The earl defended himſelf with ſuch reſolution, that he had diſpatched one of the aggreſſors, when a gentleman paſſing that way took his part, and diſarmed another, on which the third ſought his ſafety in flight. This generous aſſiſtant was a diſhanded officer of good family and fair reputation, bpt reduced to poverty ; and his lordihip rewarded his bravery by refigning to him his poſt of captain of the guards. He at length returned to London ; when he was made matter of the horſe to the ducheſs of York, and married the lady Frances, eldeſt daughter of Richard earl of Burlington, who had been the wife of Colonel Courtney. He here diſtinguiſhed himſelf by his writings : and in imitation of thoſe learned and polite aſſtmblies with which he had been acquainted abroad, began to form a ſo-,ciety ſor refining and fixing the ſtandard of the Engliſh language, in which his great friend Mr Dryden was a principal aſſiſtant. This ſcheme was entirely defeated by the religious commotions which enſued on king James’s acceſſion to the throne. In 1683 he was ſeized with the gout ; and being too impatient of pain, he permitted a bold French empiric to apply a repelling medicine, in order to give him preſent relief; which drove the diſtemper into his bowels, and in a ſhort time put a period to his life, in January 1684. He was buried with great pomp in Weſtrmnſter-abbey.</p><p>His poems, which are not numerous, are in the body of Engliſh poetry collected by Dr Johnſon. His * <hi rend="sup">t</hi> Eſſay on Tranſlated Verſe,” and his tranſlation of <hi rend="sup">te</hi> Horace’s Art of Poetry,” have great merit. Waller addreſſed a poem to his lordſhip upon the latter, when he was 73 years of age. “ in the writings of this nobleman we view (fays Fenton) the image of a mind naturally ſerious and folid ; richly furniſhed and adorned with all the ornaments of art and ſcience ; and thoſe ornaments unaffectedly diſpoſed in the moſt regular and elegant order. His imagination might probably have been more fruitful and ſprightly, if his judgement had been leſs ſevere ; but that ſeverity (delivered in a maſculine, clear, ſuccinct ftyle) contributed to make him ſo eminent in the didactical manner, that no man, with juſtice, can affirm he was ever equalled by any of our nation, without confeſſing at the ſame time that he is inferior to none. In ſome other kinds of writing his genius ſeems to have wanted fire to attain the point of perfection ; but who can attain it ? He was a man of an amiable diſpoſition, as well as a good poet ; as Pope, in his * Eſſay on Criticifm, <hi rend="sup">,</hi> hath teſti-fied in the following lines :</p><p>--Roſcommon not more learn’d than good,</p><p>With manners generous as his noble blood ;</p><p>To him the wit of Greece and Rome was known,</p><p>And every author’s merit but his own.”</p><p>We muſt allow of Roſcommon, what Fenton has not mentioned ſo diſtinctly as he ought, and, what is yet very much to his honour, that he is perhaps the only correct writer in verſe before Addiſon ; and that, if there are not ſo many or ſo great beauties in his com-poſitions as in thoſe of ſome contemporaries, there are at leaſt fewer faults. Nor is this his higheſt praiſe ; for Pope has celebrated him as the only moral writer of King Charles’s reign :</p><p>Unhappy Dryden ! in all Charles’s days,</p><p>Roſcommon only boaſts uaſpotted lays.</p><p>Of Roſcommon’s woιks, the judgment of the public ſeems to be right. He is elegant, but not great ; he never labours after exquiſite beauties, and he ſeldom falls into groſs faults. Hrs verſi cation is ſmooth, but rarely vigorous, and his rhymes are remarkably exact. He improved taſte, if he did not enlarge knowledge, and may be numbered among the benefactors to Engliſh literature.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>