<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r03-0551-04" facs="gri_33125011196389_0557.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>RUMEX</label>
dock, in botany : A genus of the trigy-nia order, belonging to the hexandria claſs of plants j and in the natural method ranking under the 12th order, <hi rend="italic">Holorαce&lt;t.</hi> The calyx is- triphyllous ; there are three connivent petals, and one triquetrous ſeed. There are 27 ſpecies ; of which the moſt remarkable are,</p><p>1. The patientia, commonly called <hi rend="italic">patience rhubarb.</hi> This was formerly much more cultivated in the Britiſh gardens than at preſent: the.roots of this have been generally uſed for the monk’s rhubarb, and has even been thought to be the true kind ; but others ſuppoſe the ſecond fort ſhould be uſed as ſuch. The root rs large, and divides into many thick fibres ; their outer cover is brown, but they are yellow within, with ſome reddiſh veins; the leaves are broad, long, and acute-pointed; their footſtalks are of a reddiſh colour ; the ſtalks riſe ſix or ſeven ſeet high, aud divide towards the top into ſeveral erect branches garniſhed with a few narrowdeaves terminating with looſe ſpikes oſ large ſtaminous flowers. Theſe appear in June, and are ſucceeded by pretty large three-cornered ſeeds, whoſe coverings are entire, which ripen, i« autumn.</p><p>2. The alpinus, or monk’s rhubarb, grows naturally on the Alps, but has ∙long been cultivated in the gardens of this country. This hath large roots which ſpread and multiply by their offsets : they are ſhorter and thicker than the former, are of a very dark brown on the outſide, and yellow within. The leaves are of the round heart-ſhape, ſtanding upon long footſtalks. The ſtalks riſe from two to three feet high ; they are thick, and have a few ſmall roundiſh leaves:on the lower part;· but the upper part is cloſely garniſhed with ſpikes of white flowers ſtanding erect cloſe to the ſtalks. Theſe appear in the latter end of May, and are ſucceeded by large triangular ſeeds which ripen in Auguſt.</p><p>3. The aquaticus, or water-dock, grows naturally inponds, ditches, and ſtanding waters, in many parts of' Britain. It is ſuppoſed- to be the herba Britannica of the ancients. It hath large roots which ſtrike deep' into the looſe mud, ſending out leaves which are above» two feet long. The ſtalks riſe five or ſix feet high when the plants grow in water, but in dry land fel- <hi rend="sup">,</hi> dom mere than three ; theſe are garniſhed with narrow</p>
<pb xml:id="eb03-16-r03-0552" facs="gri_33125011196389_0558.tif"/>
<p>t leaves among the ſpikes of flowcrs to the top. The flowers ſtand upon ſlender footſtalks, which are reflexed; tſhey are of an herbaceous colour, appear in June, and the feeds ripen in autumn.</p><p>4. The acutus, or ſharnpointed dock, (the oxyla-pâthum of the ſhops) ; but the markets are ſupplied with roots of the common docks which are indifferently gathered by thoſe who collect them in the fields, where the kind commonly called <hi rend="italic">butter dock</hi> (from its leaves being uſed to wrap up butter) is much more common than this. The roots of this are ſlender, and run downright, ſending Out a few ſmall fibres ; the ſtalks riſe about two feet high, garniſhed at bottom with leaves four inches long, and one and an half broad in the middle. They are rounded at their baſe, where'they -are ſlightly indented, but end in acute points. From the joints of the ſtalks come out alternately long foot-ſtalks, which ſuſtain the ſpikes of flowers, which grow in ſmall whorls round the ſtalks, at about an inch diftant.</p><p>Theſe plants are but ſeldom cultivated ; and ſo eaſily multiply by their numerous ſeeds, that they ſoon become troubleſome weeds where they once get an entrance.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>