<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r03-0548-01" facs="gri_33125011196389_0554.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>RUDESHEIM</label>
a rich village of the Rhinegan, ſituated about five miles from the city of Mentz, contains about 2500 inhabitants. The wine of this place is looked upon as without compariſon the beſt of the Rhinegau, and conſequently of all Germany. Baron Rieſheck ſays, he found it much more fiery than that of Hochheim but that for pleaſantneſs of taſte there is no compariſon betwixt them. The beſt Rudeſheim, like the beſt Hochheimer, ſells upon the ſpot far three guilders the bottle. “ You can (ſays our author) have no tolerable wine here for one guilder, nor any very good for two ; at leaſt I ſhould prefer the worſt Burgundy I ever tailed to any Rudeſheimer I met with either here or at Mentz for theſe prices. Indeed the wine of our hoſt (a rich eccleſiaſtic) was far better than any we could get at the inn. It ſtands to reaſon, that the fame vintage furniſhes grapes of very different degrees of goodneſs ; but beſides this, it is in the Rhinegau as every where elſe. The beſt wines are generally ſent abroad by the poor and middling inhabitants, and the worſt kept for internal conſumption ; for the expence of the carriage being the ſame in both caſes, ſtrangers had much rather pay a double price for the good than have the bad. It is only rich people, ſuch as our hoſt was, who can afford to keep the produce of their land for their own drinking. Upon this principle, I have eaten much better Swiſs cheeſes out of Switzerland than in it, and have drank much better Rheniſh in the inns of the northern parts of Germany than in the «country where the wine grows. The poſition of the country alſo contributes to render the wine dearer than it would otherwiſe be. As the beſt wine grows in its more northern parts, the eaſy tranſport by the Rhine to Holland, and all parts of the world, raiſes its price above its real value. The place where the flower of the Rudeſheim wine grows is preciſely the neck of the land, formed by the winding of the Rhine to the north, after it has run to the weſtward from Mentz hither. This neck, which is a rock almoſt perpendicular, enjoys the ſirſt rays of the riſing and the laſt of the ſetting ſun. It is divided into ſmall low terraces, which are carried up to the utmoſt top oſ the hill like ſteep ſtairs ; theſe are guarded by ſmall walls and earthen mounds, which are often waſhed away by the rain. The firſt vine was brought hither from France, and they ſtill call the beſt grape the Orleannois. They plant the vine ſtocks very low, ſcarce ever more than four or five ſeet high. This way of planting the vine is favourable to the production oſ a great deal of wine but not to its goodneſs, as the phlegmatic and harſh parts oſ it would certainly evaporate more, if the ſap was refined through higher and more numerous canals. This is undoubtedly the reaſon why every kind of Rheniſh has ſomething in it that is harſh, four, and watery. The harveſt of the beſt vineyards, which are the lower ones, in the above-mentioned neck of land, is often bought before-hand, at the advanced price of ſome ducats, by Dutch and other merchants. It muſt be a very rich ſtock to yield above four meaſures of wine.— You may eaſily imagine, that the cultivation of vineyards muſt be very expenſive in this country, as the dung, which is extremely dear, muſt be carried up to the top of the mountains on the peaſants ſhoulders ”</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>