<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r03-0538-01"
                facs="gri_33125011196389_0544.tif" type="entry">

              <p>               <label>ROXBURGH<hi rend="smallcaps">-shire</hi></label>, or Teviotdale, a county
                    of Scotland, deriving its name from the town of Roxburgh, which is now
                    deſtroyed, and the river Teviot, that runs through the ſhire into the Tweed, is
                    divided into the three diſtricts of <hi rend="italic">Teviotdale, Liddisdale,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Eusdale,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Euſdale,</hi> ſo called from their refpective rivers, Teviot, IAddal, and Eſk. It is bounded
                    on the eaſt and ſouth-eaſt by Northumberland and Cumberland, on the ſouth and
                    ſouth-weſt by Annandale, on the weſt by Tweeddale, on the north by the Merſe and
                    Lauderdale; extending about 30 miles from eaſt to weſt, and about 15 in breadth
                    from the border of England to the Blue Cairn in Lauder-moor. The ſhire exhibits
                    a rough irregular appearance of hills, moffes, and mountains, interſperſed,
                    however, with narrow valleys, and watered with delightful ſtreams. Though the
                    face of the country is bare of woods, the valleys yield plenty of corn, and the
                    hills abound with paſture for ſheep and black cattle. The principal mountains of
                    this country are known by the name of <hi rend="italic">Cockraw :</hi> from
                    whence a range of very high hills runs weſtward, dividing Scotland from England.
                    On the confines of this ſhire are the debateable lands ; the property of which
                    was formerly diſputed by the Scots and Engliſh borderers, but adjudged to the
                    Scots at the union of the crowns.— Roxburghſhiie yields plenty of lime and
                    freeſtone, which in former times was freely uſed by the inhabitants in building
                    cattles to defend them from the invafions of their Engliſh neighbours. The moſt
                    diſtinguiſhed families in this county are the Scots and Kers, who raiſed
                    themſelves to wealth and honours by their bravery and ſucceſs in a fort of
                    predatory war with their enemies of South Britain. The ſhire is very populous ;
                    and the people are ſtout and valiant. They were formerly inured to military
                    diſeipline and all the dangers of war, by living on dry marches contiguous to
                    thoſe of England ; being ſo numerous and alert, that this and the neighbouring
                    ſhire of Berwick could in 24 hours produce 10,000 men on horſeback, well armed
                    and accoutred. In the ſhire of Roxburgh we ſtill meet with a great number of old
                    caſtles and ſeats belonging to private gentlemen, whoſe anceſtors fignalized
                    themſelves in this manner ; and we find the remains of old encampments, and a
                    Roman military way, vulgarly called the <hi rend="italic">cauſewny,</hi> rιmning from Haunυm to the Tweed. The principal town, called <hi rend="italic">Roxburgh,</hi> giving the title of <hi rend="italic">duke</hi> to the
                    chief of the Kers, was anciently a royal borough, containing divers pariſhes,
                    large and fiouriſhing, defended by a ſtrong citadel, which was often alternately
                    reduced by the Engliſh and Scotch adventurers. It was in befieging this caſtle
                    that James II. of Scotland loſt his life by the burſting of a cannon. In
                    conſequence of the almoſt continual wars between the two. nations, this fortreſs
                    was razed, the town ruined, and its royalty tranflated to Jedburgh, which is now
                    a royal borough, ſituated between the Tefy and Jed.</p>            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
