<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r03-0501-01" facs="gri_33125011196389_0507.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>ROSMARINUS</label>
rosemary, in botany: A genus of the monogynia order, belonging to the diandria claſs of plants, and in the natural method ranking under the 42d order, <hi rend="italic">Pertiιillatee.</hi> The corolla is unequal, with its upper lip bipartite ; the filaments are long, curved, and ſimple, each having a ſmall dent. There are two ſpecies, the anguſtifolia anti latifolia, or narrow and broad leaved roſemary ; of which the ſecond has larger flowers and a ſtronger ſcent than the other. There are two varieties ; one oſ the ſirſt fort with ſtriped leaves, called the <hi rend="italic">ſilver roſemary ;</hi> and the other with yellow, whence it is called the <hi rend="italic">goldſlriped roſematy.</hi> Theſe plants grow naturally in the ſouthern parts of France, Spain, and Italy ; where, upon dry rocky ſoils near the ſea, they thrive prodigiouſly, and perfume the air in ſuch a manner as to be ſmelt at a great diſtance from the land.— However, they are hardy enough to bear the cold of our ordinary winters, provided they be planted upon a poor, dry, gravelly ſoil, on which they will endure the cold much better than in a richer ground, where, growing more vigorouſly in ſummer, they are more apt to be injured by froſt in winter ; nor wfill they have ſuch a ſtrong aromatic ſcent as thoſe on a dry and barren ſoil. They are to be propagated either by flips or cuttings.</p><p>Roſemary has a fragrant ſmell, and a warm pungent bitteriſh taſte, approaching to thoſe of lavender : the leaves and tender tops are ſtrongeſt ; next to thoſe, the cup of the flower ; the flowers themſelves are conhder-ably the weakeſt, but moſt pleaſant. Aqueous liquors extract great ſliare of the virtues-of roſemary leaves by infuſion, and elevate them in eiiſtillation ; along with· the water ariſes a conſiderable quantity of eſſential oil, of an agreeable ſtrong penetrating ſmell. Pure ſpirit extracts in great perfection the whole aromatic flavour of the roſemary, and elevates very little of it in diſtillation ; hence the reſinous maſs, left upon extracting the ſpirit, proves an elegant aromatic, very rich in the peculiar qualities of the plant. The flowers of roſemary' give over great part of their flavour in diſtillation with pure ſpirit ; by watery liquors, their fragrance is much injured ; by beating, deſtroyed.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>