<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r03-0499-01" facs="gri_33125011196389_0505.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>ROSETTO</label>
a town of Africa, in Egypt, is plea-ſantly ſituated on the welt ſide of that branch of the Nile called by the ancients <hi rend="italic">Bolbιtinum,</hi> affirmed by Herodotus to have been formed by art ; the town and caſtle being on the right hand as you enter that river. Any one that iees the hills about Roſetto would judge that they had been the ancient barriers of the ſea, and conclude that the ſea has not loſt more ground than the /pace between the hills and the water.</p><p>Roſetto is eſteemed one of the pleafanteſt places in Egypt ; it is about two miles long, and conſiſts only of two or three ſtreets. The country about it is moſt delightful and fertile, as is all the whole Delta on the other ſide of the Nile, exhibiting the moſt plea-ſant profpect of gardens, orchards, and corn-fie!ds, excellently well cultivated. The caſtle ſtands about two miles north of the town, on the weft ſide of the river. It is a ſquare building, with round towers at the four corners, mounted with ſome pieces of braſs cannon. The walls are of brick, caſed with ftone, ſuppoſed to have been built in the time of the holy war, though ſince repaired by Cheyk Begh. At a little diſtance lower, on the other ſide of the river, is a platform, mounted with ſome guns, and to the eaſt of it are the fait lakes, out of which they gather great quantities of that commodity. At ſome farther diſtance, Tailing up the river, we ſee a high mountain, on which ſtands an old building that ſerves for a w <hi rend="sup">r</hi> atch-tower. From this eminence is diſeovered a large and deep gulph, in form of a creſcent, which appears to have been the work of art, though it be now filled up, and diſcovers nothing but its ancient bed. Roſetto is grown a conſiderable place for commerce, and hath ſome good manufactures in the linen and cotton way ; but its chief bufineſs is the carriage of goods to Cairo, all the European merchandiſe being brought thither from Alexandria by ſea, and carried in other boats to that capital ; as thoſe that are brought down from it on the Nile are there ſhipped off for Alexandria ; on which account the Europeans have here their vice-conſulsand factors to tranſact their bufineſs ; and the government maintains a beigh, a cuſtomhouſe, and a garriſon, to keep all ſafe and quiet.</p><p>In the country to the north of Roſetto are delightful gardens, full of orange, lemon, and citron trees, and almoſt all forts of fruits, with a variety of groves of palm-trees ; and when the fields are green with rice, it adds greatly to the beauty of the country. It is about 25 miles north-eaſt of Alexandria, and 100 north-weſt of Cairo. E. Long. 30. 45. N. Lat. 31. 30.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>