<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r03-0502-01"
                facs="gri_33125011196389_0508.tif" type="entry">

                <p><label>ROSSANO</label> a ſtrong town of Italy, in the kingdom βf Naples, and in
                    the Hither Calabria, with an archbi-ſhop’s ſee, and the title of a principality.
                    It is pretty large, well peopled, and ſeated on an eminence ſurrounded with
                    rocks. There is nothing in this archiepiſcopal city that claims much notice ;
                    the buildings are mean, the ſtreets vilely paved and contrived. The number of
                    inhabitants does not exceed 6000, who ſubſiſt by the ſale of their oil, the
                    principal object of their attention, though the territory produces a great deal
                    of good wine and corn.</p>
                <p>Roffano probably owes its origin to the Roman emperors, who conſidered it as a
                    poll equally valuable for ſtrength and convenience of traffic. The Marfans, a
                    family of French extraction, poffeffed this territory, with the title of prince,
                    from the time of Charles II. to that of Alphonſus II. when the laſt male heir
                    was, by that prince’s order, put to death in Iſchia, where he</p>
                <p>was confined for treaſon. It afterwards belonged to Bona, queen of Poland, in
                    right of her mother Iſabella, daughter to Alphonſus II. and at her deceaſe
                    returned to the crown. It was next in the poſſeſſion of the Aldobrandini, from
                    whom the Borgheſi inherited it. So late as the 16th century, the inhabitants of
                    this city ſpoke the Greek language, and followed the rites of the eaſtern
                    church. Here was formerly the moſt celebrated rendezvous of the Bafilian monks
                    in Magna Graecia. E. Long. 16. 52. N. Lat. 39. 45.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
