<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r03-0497-03" facs="gri_33125011196389_0503.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>ROSAMOND</label>
daughter of Walter Lord Clifford, was a young lady of exquiſite beauty, fine accomplilh-ments, and bleſſed with a moſt engaging wit and ſweetneſs of temper. She had been educated, according to the cuſtom of the times, in the nunnery of Godſtow ; and the popular ſtory of her is as follows: Henry II. ſaw her, loved her, declared his paſſion, and triumphed over her honour. To avoid the jealouſy of his queen Elinor, he kept her in a wonderful labyrinth at Wood-ſtock, and by his connection with her had William Longſword earl of Saliſhury, and Geoffrey biſhop of Lincoln. O,n Henry’s abſence in France, however, on account of a rebellion in that country, the queen found mea∏6 to diſcover her, and though ſtruck with her beauty, ſhe recalled ſufficient reſentment to poiſon her. The queen, it is ſaid, diſeovered her apartment by a thread of ſilk ; but how ſhe came by it is differently related. This popular ſtory is not however ſupported by hiſtory ; ſeveral writers mention no more of her, than that the queen ſo vented her ſpleen on Roſamond as that the lady lived not long after. Other writers aſſert that ſhe died a natural death; and the ſtory of her being poiſoned is thought to have ariſen from the figure of a cup on her tomb. She was buried in the church of Godſtow, oppoſite to the high altar, where her body remained till it was ordered to be removed with every mark ol diſgrace by Hugh biſhop of Lincoln, in 1191. She was, however, by many conſidered as a faint after her death, as appears from an inſcription on a crois which Leland ſays ſtood near Godſtow :</p><p><hi rend="italic">Slut meat hac oret, ſignumſalutis adοret,</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Utque Jlbi detur veniam. Rοfamunda precetur.</hi></p><p>And alſo by the following ſtory : Roſamond, during her reſidence at. her bower, made ſeveral viſits to God-ffo,' ; where being frequently reproved for the life ſhe led, and threatened with the conſequences in a future ,ate, ſhe always anſwered, that ſhe knew ſhe ſhould be</p><p>ſaved ; and as a token to them, ſhowed a tree which ſhe ſaid would be turned into a ſtone when ſhe was with the ſaints in heaven. Soon after her death this wonderful metamorphoiis happened, and the ſtone was . ſhown to ſtrangers at Godſtow till the time of the diſſo-lution.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>