<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:55:48Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ſupport he had received from the earl of Murray. By the advice and influence of Sir Nicholas Throgmorton, he engaged in his behalf the earl of Leiceſter; and this nobleman imparted the matter to the earls of Pembroke and Arundel. The duke himſelf was able to conciliate the favour of the earls of Derby, Bedford, Shrewſhury, Southampton, Northampton, Northumberland, Weſtmoreland, and Suſſex. In the mean time, he was eagerly preſſing Mary herſelf with his ſuit and importunities; and had mutually exchanged the tokens of a conſtant and ſincere love. It was in this forward ſtate of the match, that the biſhop of Roſs drew up the ſchedule of articles for the accommodation of the rival queens.</p><p>At the deſire of Elizabeth, her privy-council conferred with the biſhop upon theſe articles at different times; and they expreſſed themſelves to be highly pleaſed with their general import and meaning. Little doubt was entertained of their ſucceſs; and the earl of Leiceſter, in order to complete the bufineſs, and to ſerve the duke of Norfolk, undertook to give them a more ſpecial force, and to improve them by the introduction of a ſtipulation about the marriage of the queen of Scots. According to his ſcheme of agreement, it was required of Mary, that ſhe ſhould be a party to no attempt againſt the rights and titles of the queen of England, or her heirs; that ſhe ſhould conſent to a perpetual league, offenſive and defenſive, between the two kingdoms; that ſhe ſhould finally eſtabliſh the Proteſtant religion in Scotland; that ſhe ſhould admit to her favour thoſe of her ſubjects who had appeared againſt her; that if ſhe had made any aſſignment of her kingdom to the duke of Anjou, in the expectation of a marriage to be contracted between, them, it ſhould be diſſolved; and that inſtead of looking to a foreign prince, whoſe alliance would be dangerous, not only to the religion but to the liberty of the two realms, ſhe would agree to marry the duke of Norfolk, the firſt peer of England. Theſe articles being communicated to the biſhop of Roſs, he was deſired to tranſmit them to Mary; but, as they touched upon ſome points concerning which he had no inſtructions, he declined this office, and recommended the propriety of their employing a ſpecial meſſenger of their own in a commiſſion of ſuch high importance. They accordingly appointed Mr Candiſh to go with them to the queen of Scots, and, in a formal diſpatch, they extolled the merits of the duke of Norfolk; aſſured her of the general favour and ſupport of the Engliſh nobility, if ſhe ſhould approve of his love: and intimated their belief that Elizabeth would not be averſe from a marriage which gave the certain promiſe of tranquillity and happineſs to the two kingdoms. This diſpatch was in the handwriting of Leiceſter; and it was ſubſcribed by this nobleman, and the earls of Arundel and Pembroke, and the lord Lumley.</p><p>Mary, in the ſolitude of her priſon, received this application with pleaſure. By the lord Boyd ſhe returned a very favourable anſwer to it; but took the liberty to admoniſh them of the neceſſity of their ſecuring the good-will of Elizabeth, left her diſlike of the treaty of the marriage ſhould excite new diſaſters and misfortunes, and involve the duke of Norfolk in inconveniency and danger. This advice, the ſuggeſtion of her delicacy and, prudence, did not draw ſufficiently</p><p>their attention. The duke of Norfolk was now impatient to conclude this great tranſaction, in which he had engaged himſelf; and admitted into his councils many nobles whom he had hitherto neglected to court, and many gentlemen who were conſiderabk from their diſtinction and fortunes. The countenance and conſent of the kings of France and Spain were thought neceſſary to the meaſures in agitation, and were ſolicited and obtained. In the univerſality of the applauſe with which they were honoured, it was ſuppoſed that Elizabeth would be allured into a cordial acknowledgment of their propriety, or be compelled to afford them a reluctant approbation; and ſo ardent a belief prevailed of their fortunate termination, that the marriage-contract was actually intruſted to the keeping of M. Fenelon the French ambaſſador.</p><p>The activity of the duke of Norfolk with the Engliſh nobles did not ſo much engroſs his attention as to make him forget the regent. He kept up with him a cloſe correſpondence in conſequence of the concert into which they had entered, and received the moſt ample aſſurances of his fidelity and ſervice. The moſt ſanguine and ſeducing hopes elated him. The regent, while he ſtipulated for terms of favour and ſecurity to himſelf and his faction, appeared to be full of the marriage, as a meaſure from which the greateſt advantages would ariſe to the two kingdoms, to the two queens, and to the true religion. The match, in the meanwhile, was anxiouſly concealed from Elizabeth; but ſhe was zealouſly preſſed to conclude an accommodation with Mary, on the foundation of the ſchedule of agreement preſented by the biſhop of Roſs. After having had many conferences with her privy-council, ſhe ſeemed inclined to treat definitively for the reſtoration of the queen of Scots, and actually agreed to open the tranſaction to the regent. The lord Boyd was ſent into Scotland upon this bufineſs; and while he carried her letters, he was intruſted with diſpatches from Mary, the duke of Norfolk, and Sir Nicholas Throgmorton.</p><p>As the regent was returning from his northern expedition, he was ſaluted at Elgin by the lord Boyd, who immediately laid before him the diſpatches and inſtructions with which he had been charged. The queen of England, in her letters, made three propoſitions in behalf of Mary, and intimated a deſire that one of them ſhould be accepted. The queen of Scots, ſhe ſaid, might be reſtored fully and abſolutely to her royal eſtate: ſhe might be aſſociated in the government with her ſon, have the title of <hi rend="italic">queen,</hi> and, till the prince ſhould attain the age of 17 years, the adminiſtration might continue in the regent; or ſhe might be permitted to return to Scotland in a. private ſtation, and have an honourable appointment to maintain her in a ſafe and happy obſcurity. The diſpatches from Mary to the regent deſired, that judges might immediately be allowed to inquire into the legality of her marriage with Bothwel: and that, if it was found to have been concluded in oppoſition to the laws, it ſhould be declared void, and that the liberty be granted to her of entering anew into a matrimonial engagement. The duke of Norfolk expreſſed to the regent the gratitude he felt for his friendſhip; promiſed him the command of the fulleſt exertions of his conſequence and power; intreated him to proceed expeditiouſly in</p></body></text></TEI>