<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:55:01Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ciſed. The churches and religious houſes were everywhere defaced, or pulled to the ground; and their furniture, utenſils, and decorations, became the prizes and the property of the invader. Even the ſepulchres of the dead were ranſacked and violated. The libraries of the eccleſiaſtics, and the regiſters kept by them of their own tranſactions and of civil affairs, were gathered into heaps, and committed to the flames. Religious antipathy, the fonction of law, the exhortation of the clergy, the hope of ſpoil, and, above all, the ardour to put the laſt hand to the reformation, concurred to drive the rage of the people to its wildeſt fury; and, in the midſt of havock and calamity, the new eſtabliſhment ſurveyed its importance and its power.</p><p>The death of Francis IL having left his queen, Mary, in a very diſagreeable ſituation while ſhe remained in France, it now became neceſſary for her to think on returning to her own country. To this ſhe was ſolicited both by the Proteſtants and Papiſts; the former, that they might gain her over to their party; and the latter, hoping that, as Mary was of their own perſuaſion, Popery might once more be eſtabliſhed in Scotland. For this deputation, the Proteſtants choſe lord James Stuart, natural brother to the queen; and the Papiſts, John Leſly, official and vicar-general of the dioceſe of Aberdeen. The latter got the ſtart of the Proteſtant ambaſſador, and thus had the opportunity of firſt delivering his meſſage. He adviſed her ſtrongly to beware of the lord James Stuart, whom he repreſented as a man of unbounded ambition, who had eſpouſed the Proteſtant cauſe for no other reaſon than that he might advance himſelf to the higheſt employments in the ſtate; nay, that he had already fixed his mind on the crown itſelf. For theſe reaſons he adviſed that the lord James Stuart ſhould be confined in France till the government of Scotland could be completely eſtabliſhed. But if the queen was averſe to this meaſure, he adviſed her to land in ſome of the northern diſtricts of Scotland, where her friends were moſt numerous; in which caſe an army of 20,000 men would accompany her to Edinburgh, to reſtore the Popiſh religion, and to overawe her enemies. The next day the lord James Stuart waited upon her, and gave an advice very different from that of Leſly. The ſureſt method of preventing inſurrections, he ſaid, was the eſtabliſhment of the Proteſtant religion; that a ſtanding army and foreign troops would certainly loſe the affections of her ſubjects; for which reaſon he adviſed her to viſit Scotland without guards and without ſoldiers, and he became ſolemnly bound to ſecure their obedience to her. To this advice Mary, though ſhe diſtruſted its author, liſtened with attention; and lord James, imagining that ſhe was prejudiced in his favour, took care to improve the favourable opportunity; by which means he obtained a promiſe of the earldom of Marre.</p><p>Before Mary ſet out from France, ſhe received an embaffy from queen Elizabeth, preſſing her to ratify the treaty of Edinburgh, in which ſhe had taken care to get a clauſe inſerted, that Francis and Mary ſhould <hi rend="italic">for ever</hi> abſtain from aſſuming the title and arms of England and Ireland. But this was declined by the queen of Scotland, who, in her conference with the Engliſh ambaſſador, gave an eminent proof of her political abilities @@*. Her refusal greatly augmented the</p><p>jealouſies which already prevailed between her and Elizabeth, inſomuch that the latter refuſed her a ſafe paſſage through her dominions into Scotland. This was conſidered by Mary as a high indignity; ſhe returned a very ſpirited anſwer, informing her rival, that ſhe could return to her own dominions without any aſſiſtance from her, or indeed whether ſhe would or not. In the month of Auguſt 1561, Mary ſet ſail from Calais for Scotland. She left France with much regret; and at night ordered her couch to be brought upon deck, deſiring the pilot to awaken her in the morning if the coaſt of France ſhould be in view. The night proved calm, ſo that the queen had an opportunity once more of indulging herſelf with a fight of that beloved country. A favourable wind now ſprung up, and a thick fog coming on, ſhe eſcaped a ſquadron of men of war which Elizabeth had ſet out to intercept her; and on the 20th of the month ſhe landed ſafely at Leith.</p><p>But though the Scots received their queen with the greateſt demonſtrations of joy, it was not long before an irreconcileable quarrel began to take place. The Proteſtant religion was now eſtabliſhed all over the kingdom; and its profeſſors had ſo far deviated from their own principles, or what ought to have been their principles, that they would grant no toleration to the oppoſite party, not even to the ſovereign herſelf. In conſequence of this, when the queen attempted to celebrate maſs in her own chapel of Holyroodhouſe, a violent mob aſſembled, and it was with the utmoſt difficulty that the lord James Stuart and ſome other perſons of high diſtinction could appeaſe the tumult. Mary attempted to allay theſe ferments by a proclamation, in which ſhe promiſed to take the advice of the ſtates in religious matters; and, in the mean time, declared it to be death for any perſon to attempt an innovation or alteration of the religion which ſhe found generally eſtabliſhed upon her arrival in Scotland. Againſt this proclamation the earl of Arran proteſted, and formally told the herald, the queen’s proclamation ſhould not protect her attendants and ſervants if they preſumed to commit idolatry and to ſay maſs. John Knox declared from the pulpit, that one maſs was more terrible to him than if 10,000 armed enemies had landed in any part of the kingdom to re-eſtablilh Popery. The preachers everywhere declaimed againſt idolatry and the maſs; keeping up, by their miſtaken zeal, a ſpirit of diſcontent and ſedition throughout the whole kingdom. John Knox was called before the queen to anſwer for the freedom of his ſpeeches; but his unbounded boldneſs when there gave Mary much diſquiet, as not knowing in what manner to deal with him. The freedoms, however, which were taken with the queen, could not induce her to depart from that plan of government which ſhe had laid down in France. To the Proteſtants ſhe reſolved to pay the greateſt attention; from among them ſhe choſe her privy-council, and heaped favours upon the lord James Stuart, who for his activity in promoting the reformation was the moſt popular man in the kingdom; while to her courtiers of the Roman Catholic perſuaſion ſhe behaved with a diſtant formality.</p><p>In the mean time, the difference between the two rival queens became every day greater. The queen of Scotland preſſed Elizabeth to declare her the neareſt</p><p>@@@ [m] *See <hi rend="italic">Robertson of Dalmeny's History of Mary Queen of Scotland.</hi></p></body></text></TEI>