<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:55:57Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>her, and remain in England for three years; that the caſtles of Dumbarton and Plume ſhould be in her poſſeſſion during the ſame period; and as to the article  concerning the delivery of the prince into her cuſtody, he obſerved, that it would be required from the regent,  the queen of Scots not having the power of its performance. The deputies of Mary, ſurpriſed with this language, intreated the Engliſh delegates to reflect, that their queen, if deprived of the moſt faithful of her nobles, and oſher ſtrongeſt ſorts, could have little deſire or ambition to return to her own kingdom; for ſhe would thus be unable to protect herſelf againſt the turbulence of her ſubjects, and be a ſovereign without friends, and without ſtrength. They were inclined, they ſaid, to put their commiſſion and powers to the fulleſt ſtretch, in order to gratify Elizabeth 5 and they would agree, that two earls and two barons ſhould be ſurrendered for two years, as hoſtages of the fidelity of their ſovereign; under the reſtriction, that they might be exchanged every ſix months for perſons of an equal condition, if they ſhould be deſirous of returning to their  own country. As to the giving up of any forts or caſtles, they would not agree to it, becauſe among the other inconveniences of this meaſure, ſimilar claims would be competent to the king of France, by the ſpirit of the treaty of Edinburgh, which ſtipulated, that no French or Engliſh troops ſhould be admitted into Scotland. The lord keeper Bacon, reſuming his diſcourſe, told them, that the whole realm of Scotland, its prince, nobles, and caſtles, were an inadequate pledge to the queen of England; and that, if his advice would be followed, the queen of Scots ſhould not obtain her liberty upon any kind of ſecurity which could be granted by the Scottiſh nation. In all public treaties, ſaid the delegates of Mary, no further aſſurance can be required from a ſovereign than what conſiſts with his ſafety; and when exactions are preſſed from a contracting party in a league which are ruinous and impoſſible, it is underſtood that a foundation is fought to break off the negociation. The Engliſh commiſſioners, now interfering in a body, declared upon their honour, that it was the meaning of Elizabeth to agree to the reſtoration of the queen of Scots to her crown and realm upon receiving ſufficient aſſurances for the articles of the accommodation; that the ſecurity offered for her acceptance, ſhould be ſubmitted to her deliberation; and that they would immediately proceed to confer with the deputies for the king of Scots.</p><p>The Engliſh commiſſioners were not unacquainted with the ſentiments of the earl of Morton and his colleagues; and it was from this quarter that they expected a reſolute and definitive interruption to the treaty. Nor did theſe delegates diſappoint the expectations conceived of them. After affecting to take a comprehenſive view of the articles under debate, they declared, that their commiſſion gave them authority to treat about the amity of the two kingdoms, and the maintenance of the true religion; but that it conferred upon them no power to receive their queen into Scotland, or to ſurrender to Elizabeth the perſon of their king. They therefore begged not to be urged to accede to a league which, in ſome future period, might expoſe them to a charge of high treaſon.</p><p>This Angular declaration was conſidered to be ſolid and weighty by the Engliſh commiſſioners; and, in a</p><p>new conference, it was communicated by them to the deputies of Mary. The biſhop of Roſs and his aſſoiates were diſguſted with this formal impertinence. They did not heſitate to pronounce the plea of an inſufficient commiſſion from the king to his delegates to be an unworthy and moſt frivolous ſubterfuge. The authors, they ſaid, of the depoſition of their ſovereign did not need any authority but their own to ſet her at liberty; the prince was not yet five years of age, and could give them no inſtructions: and the regent was wholly dependent upon the will and pleaſure of the queen of England. It was repreſented in return by the Engliſh delegates, that the commiſſion of king James to his deputies, having been peruſed by Elizabeth, was accounted by her to be inſufficient; and that it was her opinion, that the earl of Morton ſhould return to Scotland to hold a parliament for obtaining new powers. The biſhop of Roſs exclaimed, that the queen of Scots had been amuſed with deceitful promiſes, that the prudence of Elizabeth had been corrupted by partial counſels, and that the allegations and pretences held out for interrupting the negociation were affected and unreal. The inſtructions, he ſaid, from his ſovereign to her commiſſioners, were to negociate and to conclude, and not to trifle; and they would not by any means conſent to protract, by artificial delays, a treaty which the queen of England, if her intentions were ſincere and right, could immediately terminate upon reaſonable and honourable terms. His ſpeech and his demeanour he acknowledged to be free and open; and he beſought them to excuſe him, ſince, having been made an inſtrument to abuſe his miſtreſs with falſe hopes, he could not but reſent the indignity, and expreſs what he knew and what he felt. The Engliſh deputies, addreſſing him and his colleagues, obſerved, that as the friends of Mary, and thoſe of the king her ſon, could not come to an agreement, and as their queen was refuſed the aſſurance ſhe expected, they held their commiſſion to be at an end, and were no longer at liberty to negociate.</p><p>The inſincerity of Elizabeth, and the failure of the league or agreement, filled Mary with reſentment and complaints. Her animoſities, and thoſe of Elizabeth, were increaſed and fortified. She was in haſte to communicate to her allies the unworthy treatment ſhe had received; and ſhe ſent her commands to her adherents in Scotland to riſe up in arms, to repoſe no truſt in truces which were prejudicial and treacherous, and to employ all their reſources and ſtrength in the humiliation of the regent and his faction. Elizabeth, who by this time apprehended no enterpriſe or danger from Charles IX. or the duke of Alva, reſolved, on the other hand, to give a ſtrong and effectual ſupport to the king’s friends, and to diſunite by ſtratagem, and oppreſs by power, the partizans of the Scottiſh princeſs. The zeal of the biſhop of Roſs having railed her anger, ſhe commanded him to depart from London; and Mary, in contempt of her mandate, ordered him to remain there under the privilege of her ambaffador. The high and unbroken ſpirit of the Scottiſh queen, in the midſt of her misfortunes, never once awakened the generous admiration, of Elizabeth. While it uniformly inflamed her rage, it ſeems alſo to have excited her terror. With a puſillanimous meanneſs, ſhe ſent a diſpatch to the earl of Shrewſbury, inſtructing him to keep his charge in the</p></body></text></TEI>