<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:54:15Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>tion, but at the ſame time to carry along with him the king. This reſolution being made known to the queen- mother, ſhe was ſo much concerned for the ſafety of her ſon, that the whole party diſbanded themſelves; and thus the authority of the earl of Angus ſeemed to be more eſtabliſhed than ever. Nothing, indeed, was now wanting to render him deſpotic but the poſſeſſion of the great ſeal, which the archbiſhop of St Andrew’s had carried with him to Dunfermline. As no deed of any conſequence could be executed without this, he prevailed upon the king to demand it by a ſpecial message; in conſequence of which, the archbiſhop was obliged to give it up. About this time the divorce which had been ſo long in agitation between the queen-mother and the earl of Angus actually took place; which, no doubt, increaſed the diſlike of James to his confinement, while the imprudence of Angus gave every day freſh matter of diſguſt. As Angus knew that he had no firm ſupport but in the attachment of his followers to his perſon, he ſuffered them to rob and plunder the eſtates of his opponents without mercy. Theſe, again, did not fail to make repriſals; ſo that, towards the end of the year 1526, there was ſcarcely any appearance of civil government in Scotland. Thus the court became almoſt totally deſerted; every nobleman being obliged to go home to defend his own eſtate. Even Angus himſelſ ſhared in the common calamity, and hence was frequently obliged to leave the king to the cuſtody of Lenox. To this nobleman the king now made the molt grievous complaints, and charged him to contrive ſome plan for his eſcape. Lenox accordingly recommended to him the baron of Buccleugh, who was very powerful in the ſouthern parts, and a violent enemy to Angus and the whole family of Douglas. To him he gave orders to foment the diſorders in the ſouthern parts to ſuch a degree as to require the king’s perſonal preſence to compoſe them. Bucclcugh was then to attack the party, and take the king by force from the Douglaſſes. This ſcheme was put in execution, but Buccleugh had the misfortune to be defeated; ſo that the attempt proved abortive, and James found himſelf in a worſe ſituation than ever. After this attempt, however, as the earl of Angus could not but know that Lenox had been acceſſory to it, the former behaved towards him with ſuch viſible indifference, that Lenox openly declared againſt him, and adviſed the king to form a friendſhip with the archbiſhop of St Andrew’s, in order to effect his liberty. This was accordingly done; but the intereſt of the archbiſhop and Lenox was overbalanced by that of Arran and the Hamilton family, whom the earl of Angus now drew over to his party. However, the earl of Lenox, having received powers from the king for that purpoſe, ſuddenly retired from court; and publiſhed a manifeſto, inviting all loyal ſubjects to aſſiſt him in delivering the king from confinement. In conſequence of this he was ſoon joined by a numerous army, with whom he advanced towards Edinburgh. Angus did not fail to aſſemble his adherents; and ſent orders to the inhabitants of Edinburgh to take the field, with the king at their head. The citizens immediately put themſelves under arms; but James, pretending to be indiſpofed, Sir George Douglas, brother to the earl of Angus, made him the following ſpeech: “Sir, rather than our enemies ſhould take you from us, we will lay hold of your perfon </p><p>and ſhould you be torn in pieces in the ſtruggle, we will carry off part of your oody.” Upon this ſpeech, which James never forgot, he mounted his horſe and ſet forward to Linlithgow, but with a very ſlow pace; inſomuch that Sir George Douglas, afraid of not coming in time to ſuccour his brother, made uſe of many indecent expreſſions and actions to puſh James on to the field of battle. Three expreſſes arrived from the earl of Angus; the firſt informing his brother that he was about to engage with a ſuperior army; the ſecond, that Angus was engaged with a diviſion of Lenox’s army, commanded by the earl of Glencatrn; and that Lenox himſelf was engaged with the Hamiltons. The third informed him that Lenox, if not actually debated, was on the point of being ſo. Upon receiving this laſt news, James haſtened to the field of battle, that he might ſave Lenox, and put an end to the bloodſhed.— But he came too late: for the royal party was already defeated with great ſlaughter; and Lenox himſelf, after being wounded and taken priſoner, was murdered by Sir James Hamilton.</p><p>On the night of the battle, the king was removed to Linlithgow; and though he was under the greateſt grief for the fate of Lenox, the behaviour of the Dou- glaffes ſtruck him with ſuch terror that he diſſembled his ſentiments. The earl of Angus led his victorious troops into Fife, in hopes of ſurpriſing the queen and the archbiſhop of St Andrew’s. The queen, on the news of his approach, fled, with her new huſband Henry Stuart, brother to lord Evandale, to Edinburgh, and both were admitted into the caſtle. The archbiſhop fled to the mountains, where he was obliged to keep cattle as a ſhepherd. Angus, after having plundered the caſe tle of St Andrew’s and the abbey of Dunfermline, returned in triumph to Edinburgh, where he prepared to beſiege the caſtle; but the queen, hearing that her ſon was among the number of the beſiegers, ordered the gates of the caſtle to be thrown open, and ſurrendered herſelf and her huſband priſoners to James, who was adviſed to confine them to the caſtle. After theſe repeated ſucceſſes, the earl of Angus eſtabliſhed a kind of court of juſtice, in which he proſecuted thoſe who had oppoſed him, among whom was the earl of Caſſils. He was offered by Sir James Hamilton, natural ſon to the earl of Arran, the ſame who had murdered Lenox, an indemnity if he would own himſelf a vaſſal of that houſe; but this condition was rejected. Being called to his trial, and accuſed of having taken arms againſt the king, a gentleman of his name and family, who was his advocate, denied the charge, and offered to produce a letter under James’s own hand, deſiring him to aſſiſt in delivering him from his gaolers. This ſtriking evidence confounded the profecutor fo much, that the earl was acquitted; but on his return home he was way-laid and murdered by one Hugh Campbell, at the inſtigation of Sir James Hamilton.</p><p>During theſe transactions in the ſouth, many of the Highland clans were perpetrating the moſt horrid ſcenes of rapine and murder, which in ſome places reigned alſo in the Lowlands. The ſtate of the borders was little better than that of the Highlands; but it engaged the attention of Angus more, as he had great intereſt in theſe parts. Marching, therefore, againſt the banditti which infeſted theſe parts, he ſoon reduced them to reaſon. His power ſeemed now to be firmly eſtabliſhed,</p></body></text></TEI>