<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:56:32Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>der Moſes: but their name does not appear till under the judges. It is ſaid, that in the wars of Barak againſt Siſera, "out of Machir came down governors, and out of Zebulun they that handle the pen of the writer.” (Judges V. 14). Others think that David firſt inſtituted them, when he eſtabliſhed the ſeveral claſſes of the prieſts and Levites. The ſcribes were of the tribe of Levi; and at the time that David is ſaid to have made the regulations in that tribe, we read that 6000 men of them were conſtituted officers and judges (1 Chr. xxii. 4.); among whom it is reaſonable to think the ſcribes were included. For in 2 Chr. xxiv. 6. we read of Shemaiah the ſcribe, one of the Levſtes; and in 2. Chr. xxxiv. 13. we find it written, “Of the Levites that were ſcribes and officers.”</p><p>The ſcribes and doctors of the law, in the ſcripture phraſe, mean the fame thing; and he that in Mat. xxii. 35. is called a <hi rend="italic">doctor of the law,</hi> or a <hi rend="italic">lawyer,</hi> in Mark xii. 28. is named a <hi rend="italic">ſcribe,</hi> or one <hi rend="italic">of the ſcribes.</hi> And as the whole religion of the Jews at that time chiefly conſiſted in phariſaical traditions, and in the uſe that was made of them to explain the ſcripture; the greateſt number of the doctors of the law, or of the ſcribes, were phariſees; and we almoſt always find them joined together in ſcripture. Each of them valued themſelves  upon their knowledge of the law, upon their ſtudying and teaching it (Mat. xxii. 52.): they had the key of  knowledge, and ſat in Moſes’s chair (Mat. xxiii. 2). Epiphanius, and the author of the <hi rend="italic">Recognitions</hi> imputed to St Clement, reckon the ſcribes among the ſects of the Jews; but it is certain they made no ſect by themſelves; they were only diſtinguiſhed by their ſtudy of the law.</p><p>SCRIBONIUS (Largus), an ancient phyſician in the reign of Auguſtus or Tiberius, was the author of ſeveral works; the beſt edition of which is that of John Rhodius.</p><p>SCRIMZEOR or <hi rend="smallcaps">Scrimgeour</hi> (Henry), an eminent reſtorer of learning, was born at Dundee in the year 1506. He traced his deſcent from the ancient family of the Scrimzeours of Didupe, who obtained the office of hereditary ſtandard-bearers to the kings of Scotland in 1057.</p><p>At the grammar ſchool of Dundee our author acquired the Greek and Latin languages to an uncommon degree of perfection, and that in a ſhorter ſpace of time than many ſcholars before him. At the univerſity of  St Andrew’s his ſucceſsful application to philoſophy gained him great applauſe. The next ſcene of his ſtudies was the univerſity of Paris, and their more particular object the civil law. Two of the moſt famous civilians of that age, Eguinard Baron and Francis Duaren @@<hi rend="smallcaps">(a),</hi> were then giving their lectures to crowded circles at Bourges. The fame of theſe profeſſors occaſioned his removal from Paris; and for a conſiderable time he proſecuted his ſtudies under their direction.</p><p>At Bourges he had an opportunity of becoming acquainted with the celebrated James Amiot, Greek profeſſor in that city, well known in the learned world by his tranſlation of Plutarch’s Lives, and diſtinguiſhed afterwards by his advancement to great honours in the church, and finally to the rank of cardinal.</p><p>Through the recommendation of this eminent perſon, Mr Scrimzeor engaged in the education of two young gentlemen of the name of Bucherel, whom he inſtructed in the belles lettres, and other branches of literature, calculated to accompliſh them for their ſtation in life.</p><p>This connection introduced him to Bernard Bornetel biſhop of Rennes, a perſon famed in the political world for having ſerved the ſtate in many honourable embaſſies. Accepting an invitation from this prelate to accompany him to Italy, Mr Scrimzeor greatly enlarged the ſphere of his literary acquaintance, by his converſation and connection with moſt of the diſtinguiſhed ſcholars of that country. The death of Francis Spira @@<hi rend="smallcaps">(b)</hi> happened during his viſit at Padua; and as the character and conduct of this remarkable perſon at that time engaged the attention of the world, Mr Scrimzeor is ſaid to have collected memoirs of him in a publication entitled, “The Life of Francis Spira, by Henry of Scotland.” This performance, however, does not appear in the catalogue of his works.</p><p>After he had ſtored his mind with the literature of foreign countries, and ſatisfied his curioſity as a travel-</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">@@@(a)</hi> “Francis Duaren was the firſt of the French civilians who purged the chair in the civil law ſchools from the barbariſms of the Gloſſaries, in order to introduce the pure ſources of the ancient jurisprudence. As he did not deſire to ſhare that glory with any one, he looked with an envious eye on the reputation of his colleague Eguinard Baron, who alſo mixed good literature with the knowledge of the law. This jealouſy put him upon compoſing a work, wherein he endeavoured to leſſen the eſteem that people had for his colleague The maxim, "<hi rend="italic">Paſcitur in vivis livor; post ſata quieſcit,"</hi> was verified remarkably in him; for after the death of Baron, he ſhowed himſelf moſt zealous to eternize his memory, and was at the expence of a monument to the honour of the deceaſed.” From the Tranſlation of Bayle’s Dict. of 1710, p. 1143-4.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">@@@(b)</hi> Francis Spira was a lawyer of great reputation at Cistadella in the Venetian ſtate, at the beginning of the 10th century. He had imbibed the principles of the Reformation, and was accuſed before John de la Caſa, archbiſhop of Benevento, the pope’s nuncio at Venice. He made ſome conceſſions, and aſked pardon of the papal miniſter for his errors. But the nuncio infilled upon a public recantation. Spira was exceedingly averſe to this meaſure; but at the preſſing inſtances of his wife and his friends, who repreſented to him that he muſt loſe his practice and ruin his affairs by perſiſting againſt it, he at laſt complied. Shortly after he fell into a deep melancholy, loſt his health, and was removed to Padua for the advice of phyſicians and divines; but his diſorders augmented. The recantation, which he ſaid he had made from cowardice and intereſt, filled his mind with continual horror and remorſe; inſomuch that he ſometimes imagined that he felt the torments of the damned. No means being found to reſtore either his health or his peace of mind, in 1548 he fell a victim to his miſerable ſituation. See Collyer’s Dict.—Spira.</p></body></text></TEI>