<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:54:48Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>gregation aſſumed to themſelves the ruling power of the kingdom, appointed preachers in all the churches, and ſeized the mint, with all the inſtruments of coining. The queen-regent, unable to diſpute the matter in the field, publiſhed a manifeſto, in which ſhe ſet forth their ſeditious behaviour, commanding them to leave Edinburgh within ſix hours, and enjoining her fubjects to avoid their ſociety under the pain of treaſon. The Congregation having already loſt ſomewhat of their popularity by their violent proceedings, were now incapable of coping with government. As they had not eſtabliſhed themſelves in any regular body, or provided a fund for their ſupport, they felt their ſtrength decay, and multitudes of them returned to their habitations. Thoſe who remained found themſelves obliged to vindicate their conduct; and, in an addreſs to the regent, to diſclaim all treaſonable intentions. Negociations again took place, which ended as uſual; the queen-regent, who had taken this opportunity of collecting her forces, marched againſt the Congregation on the 23d of July 1559. The Proteſtants now found themſelves incapable of making head againſt their enemies; and therefore entered into a negociation, by which all differences were for the preſent accommodated. The terms of this treaty were, that the town of Edinburgh ſhould be open to the queen-dowager and her attendants; that the palace of Holyroodhouſe and the mint ſhould be delivered up to her; that the Proteſtants ſhould be ſubject to the laws, and abſtain from moleſting the Roman Catholics in the exerciſe of their religion. On the queen’s part, it was agreed, that the Proteſtants ſhould have the free exerciſe of their religion, and that no foreign troops ſhould enter the city of Edinburgh.</p><p>Notwithſtanding this treaty, however, the reformed had no confidence in the queen’s ſincerity. Having heard of the death of Henry II. of France, and the acceſſion of Francis II. and Mary to that kingdom, they ſeem to have apprehended more danger than ever. They now entered into a third covenant; in which they engaged themſelves to refuſe attendance to the queen- dowager, in caſe of any meſſage or letter; and that immediately on the receipt of any notice from her to any of their number, it ſhould be. communicated without reſerve, and be made a common ſubject of ſcrutiny and deliberation. It was not long before they had occaſion for all their conſtancy and ſtrength. The queen-regent repented of the favourable terms ſhe had granted the reformed; and being denied the favour which ſhe requeſted of ſaying maſs in the high-church of Edinburgh, ſhe ordered them to be everywhere diſturbed in the exerciſe of their religion.</p><p>In this imprudent meaſure, the queen-regent was confirmed by letters which now came from Francis and Mary, promiſing a powerful army to ſupport her intereſts. The envoy who brought theſe diſpatches alſo carried letters to the lord James Stuart, now the principal leader of the Proteſtants, and natural brother to the queen. The letters were filled with reproaches and menaces, mixed with intreaties; and along with them the envoy delivered a verbal meſſage, that the king his maller was reſolved rather to expend all the treaſures of France than net to be revenged on the rebellious nobles who had diſturbed the peace of Scotland. The lord James Stuart was not to be frightened by theſe mena</p><p>ces, He returned a cool and deliberate anſwer, apologizing for the Proteſtants, and vindicating them from the charge of rebellion; but at the fame time intimating his full reſolution of continuing to head the reformed as he had already done.</p><p>The letters of Francis and Mary were ſoon followed by 1000 French ſoldiers, with money and military flores; and the commander was immediately diſpatched again to France, to ſolicit the aſſiſtance of as many more ſoldiers, with four ſhips of war, and 100 men- at-arms. But before he could ſet out, La Broſſe, another French commander, arrived with 2000 infantry; and that the Congregation might be defeated not only by arms but in diſputation, the ſame ſhip brought three doctors of the Sorbonne, to ſhow the pernicious tendency of the new doctrines. Thus matters were puſhed on beyond all hopes of reconciliation. The nation was univerſally alarmed on account of the introduction of French troops, to which they ſaw no end. The queen-regent attemptcd to quiet the minds of the public by a proclamation; but their fears increaſed the more. The Congregation aſſembled at Stirling, where they were joined by the earl of Arran, and ſoon after by his father the duke of Chatelherault. They next deliberated on the meaſures to be followed with the queen-regent; and the reſult of their conſultations was, that an expoſtulatory letter ſhould be addreſſed to her. This was accordingly done; but as the queen behaved with her uſual duplicity, the nobles called the people to arms. Mutual manifeſtos were now publiſhed; and both parties prepared to decide the conteſt by the ſword. The Congregation having ſeized Broughty caſtle, marched from thence to Edinburgh. The queen-regent retired to Leith, which ſhe had fortified and filled with French troops. Thither the nobles ſent their laſt meſſage to her, charging her with a deſign to overthrow the civil liberties of the kingdom. They requeſted her to command her Frenchmen and mercenaries to depart from Leith, and to make that place open and patent, not only to the inhabitants who had been diſpoſſeſſed of their houſes, but to all the inhabitants of Scotland. They declared, that her denial of this requeſt ſhould be conſidered by them as a proof of her intention to reduce the kingdom to ſlavery; in which caſe, they were determined to employ their utmoſt power to preſerve its independency. Two days after this meſſage, the queen-regent ſent to them the lord Lyon, whom ſhe enjoined to tell them, that ſhe conſidered their demand not only as preſumptuous, but as an encroachment on the royal authority; that it was an indignity to her to be dictated to by ſubjects; that Frenchmen were not to be treated as foreigners, being entitled to the ſame privileges with Scotſmen; and that ſhe would neither diſhand her troops, nor command the town of Leith to be made open and patent. The lord Lyon then, in the name of the queen- regent, commanded the lords of the Congregation to depart from Edinburgh, and diſperſe themſelves, under the pain of high treaſon. The Proteſtants, irritated by this anſwer, after ſome deliberation degraded the queen-regent; and to this purpoſe the nobility, barons, and burgeſſes, all agreed in ſubſcribing an edict, which was ſent to the principal cities in Scotland, and publiſhed in them.</p><p>The next ſtep taken by the Congregation was to</p></body></text></TEI>