<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:56:27Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>into the ſea below Dundee. Spay, or Spey, iſſues from a lake of the ſame name in Badenoch; and, running a north-eaſterly courſe, falls into the German ocean, at Speymouth. Some of the freſh-water lakes are beautiful pieces of water, incredibly deep, and ſurpriſingly extended. There are ſeveral large foreſts of fir in Scotland, and a great number of woods; which, however, produce very little timber of any conſequence: but the country, in general, is rather bare of trees; and in many places neither tree, ſhrub, nor any kind of plantation, is to be seen. The case has been otherwise of old; for huge trunks of trees are often dug from under ground in almost every part of the kingdom. In the North of Scotland, the day at midsummer is lengthened out to 18 hours and 5 minutes; so that the shortest night does not exceed 5 hours and 55 minutes; the night and day, in winter, are in the same proportion. The air of this kingdom is generally moist and temperate, except upon the tops of high mountains covered with eternal snow, where it is cold, keen, and piercing. In other parts it is tempered by warm vapours from the sea, which environs it on three sides, and runs far up into the land by friths, inlets, and indentations. This neighborhood of the sea, and the frequency of the hills and mountains, produce a constant undulation in the air, and many hard gales, that purify the climate, which is for the most part agreeable and healthy. Scotland affords a great variaty of soil in different parts of the country, which, being hilly, is in general well adapted to pasturage: not but that the Lowlands are as fertile, and, when properly enclosed and manured, yield as good crops of wheat as any grounds in the iſland of Great Britain. The water in Scotland is remarkably pure, light, and agreeable to the ſtomach: but, over and above that which is uſed for the ordinary purpoſes of life, here are many medicinal ſprings of great note.</p><p>Scotland abounds with quarries of ſree-ſtone eaſily worked, which enable the people to build elegant houſes, both in town and country, at a ſmall expence, eſpecially as they have plenty of lime-ſtone, and labour very cheap. The eaſt, weſt, and northern parts of the country produce excellent coal; and where this is wanting, the natives burn turf and peat for fuel. Cryſtals, variegated pebbles, and precious ſtones, are found in many parts of Scotland; talc, flint, and ſea ſhells, fuller’s earth, potter’s clay, and metals in great plenty. The country produces iron and copper ore, a prodigious quantity of lead, mixed with a large proportion of ſilver; and in ſome places little bits of ſolid gold are gathered in brooks immediately after torrents.</p><p>The Lowlands of Scotland, as has been obſerved when duly cultivated, yield rich harveſts of wheat; and indeed it muſt be owned that many parts of this kingdom rival the beſt ſpots of England in agriculture: but theſe improvements have not yet advanced into the weſtern and northern extremities of the iſland, where we ſee nothing but ſcanty harveſts of oats, rye, and barley. The Highlands are ſo defective even in theſe, that it is neceſſary to import ſupphes of oatmeal from Ireland and Liverpool. This ſcarcity, however, we muſt not impute to the barrenness of the ſoil, ſo much as to the ſloth and poverty of the tenants, oppreſſed by rapacious landlords, who refuſe to grant ſuch leaſes as would encourage the huſbandman to improve his farm</p><p>and make himſelf better acquainted with the ſcience of agriculture. This is perfectly well underſtood in the Lothians, where we ſee ſubſtantial incloſures, plantations, meadows for hay and paſture, wide extended fields of wheat, the fruits of ſkill and induſtry, and meet with farmers who rent lands to the amount of 400 l. or 500 l a-year. Of plants this country produces an immenſe variety, growing wild, excluſive of thoſe that are railed by the hands of the huſbandman and gardener. Their farm-grounds are well flocked with wheat, rye, barley, oats, hemp, and flax: their gardens produce great plenty of kitchen-roots, ſalads, and greens; among which laſt we reckon thc colewort, known by the name of <hi rend="italic">Scotch kail:</hi> their orchards bear a variety of apples, pears, cherries, plums, ſtrawberries, gooſeberries, raſpberries, and currants: here alſo apricots, nectarines, peaches, and ſometimes grapes, are brought to maturity. In a word, there is nothing, whether ſhrub, fruit, or flower, that grows in any part of South Britain, which may not, with a little pains, be brought to the ſame perfection in the middle of Scotland. Among the trees and ſhrubs which are the national growth of this country, we may reckon the oak, the fir, the birch, the poplar, the alder, willow, elder, hazle, mountain-aſh, crab-tree, and juniper; which laſt abounds to ſuch a degree in ſome parts of the Highlands, that in the ſpace of a few miles many tons of the berries might be yearly gathered: beſides theſe, we find the hawthorn, the ſloe, the dog-role, furze, broom, fern, and whole tracts  of land and mountains covered with ſtrong heath. This affords ſhelter for the myrtillis, the fruit of which, called <hi rend="italic">bilberries,</hi> is here found in great abundance, as well as the brambleberry, cranberry, and wild ſtrawberry. The aſh, the elm, the ſycamore, lime and walnut-tree, are chiefly planted about the houſes of gentlemen; but even the incloſures of quickſet appear naked for want of Inch hedge-rows as adorn the country of England. Indeed, great part of this kingdom lies naked and expoſed like a common; and other parts have no other incloſure than a paltry wall huddled up of looſe ſtones, which yields a bleak and mean proſpect, and ſerves no other purpoſe than that of keeping out the cattle. All the ſea-coaſt is covered with alga marina, dulſe, and other marine plants.</p><p>The Highlands are well ſtocked with red deer, and the ſmaller ſpecies called the <hi rend="italic">roe-buck,</hi> as well as with hares, rabbits, foxes, wild eats, and badgers; and they abound with all forts of game. The rivers and lakes pour forth a profuſion of ſalmon, trout, jack, and eels; the ſea-coaſt ſwarms with all the productions of the ocean. The hills and mountains are covered with ſheep- and black cattle for exportation, as well as domeſtic uſe. Theſe are of ſmall ſize, as are alſo the horſes bred in the Highlands; but the Lowlanders uſe the large breed, which came originally from England.</p><p><hi rend="italic">New </hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Scotland.</hi> See <hi rend="italic">Nova </hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Scotia.</hi></p><p>SCOTOMIA, in medicine, a vertigo accompanied: with dimneſs of fight, frequently the forerunner of an apoplexy.</p><p>SCOTT (John), an eminent Engliſh divine, was born in 1638, and became miniſter of St Thomas’s in Southwark. In 1684 he was collated to a prebend in the cathedral of St Paul’s. Dr Hiekes tells us, that, after the revolution, “ he firſt refuſed the biſhopric of Cheſter, becauſe he would not take the oath of ho-</p></body></text></TEI>