<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-14T17:57:51Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>of the Lord; one the ſon of the Creator, and another the Chriſt, from the
                ſuperceleſtial abodes who deſcended upon Jeſus, the ſon of the Creator, but remained
                impaſſible, and afterwards fled back into his own pleroma or fulneſs.” As Irenæus is
                the moſt ancient author who has written upon this ſubject, many appeals have been
                made to his authority. The authority of Irenæus is certainly respectable, and we
                have often referred to his teſtimony with confidence; but we think it neceſſary to
                make a diſtinction between receiving his teſtimony to a matter of fact, and
                implicitly adopting his opinion. He does not tell us, that he derived his
                information from any preceding writer, or indeed from any perſon at all. Nay, he
                ſeems to have believed that John wrote againſt theſe hereſies by a prophetic ſpirit;
                for he ſays in another place, chap. xx. 30. “As John the diſciple of our Lord
                aſſures us, laying, But theſe are written, that ye might believe that Jeſus is the
                Chriſt, the Son of God, and that believing ye might have life through his name; <hi
                    rend="italic smallcaps">foreseeing</hi><hi rend="italic"> theſe blaſphemous
                    notions that divide the Lord, ſo far as it is in their power.”</hi></p>
            <p>Indeed it ſeems very improbable that an apoſtle ſhould write a hiſtory of our Lord on
                purpoſe to confute the wild opinions of Cerinthus or any other heretic. Had John
                conſidered ſuch a confutation neceſſary, it is more likely that he would introduce
                it into an epiſtle than blend it with the actions of his venerable Maſter. But were
                the opinion of Irenæus well- founded, we ſhould ſurely diſcover ſome traces of it in
                the goſpel of John; yet except in the introduction, there is nothing that can with
                the leaſt ſhadow of probability be applied to the opinions of Cerinthus; and few, we
                preſume, will affirm, that the goſpel of John was compoſed merely for the ſake of
                the firſt eighteen" verſes.</p>
            <p>The intention of John in writing his goſpel was far more extenſive and important than
                to refute the opinions of a few men who were to ſink into oblivion in the courſe of
                a few centuries. It was evidently (according to the opinion of Clemens of
                Alexandria) to ſupply the omiſſions of the other evangeliſts: It was to exhibit the
                evidences of the Chriſtian religion in a diſtinct and perſpicuous manner: It was, as
                he himſelf in the concluſion of his goſpel aſſures us, to convince his readers, <hi
                    rend="italic">that Jeſus is the Messiah, the Son oſ God, and that believing they
                    might have life through his name @@*. </hi>Now it will appear to any perſon who
                reads this goſpel with attention, that he has executed his plan with aſtoniſhing
                ability, and has given the moſt circumſtantial and ſatisfactory evidence that Jeſus
                was the Meſſiah the Son of God. After declaring the pre-exiſtence of Jeſus, he
                proceeds to deliver the teſtimony of John the Baptiſt, and ſelects ſome of the
                greateſt miracles of Jeſus to prove his divine million. In the fifth chapter he
                preſents us with a difcourſe which our Saviour delivered in the temple in the
                preſence of the Jews, wherein he ſtates in a very diſtinct manner the proofs of his
                miſſion from, 1. The teſtimony of John; 2. His own miracles; 3. The declaration of
                the Father at his baptiſm;</p>
            <p>4. The Jewriſh Scriptures. Indeed the concluſion that Jeſus was the Meſſiah the Son
                of God, naturally ariſes from almoſt every miracle which our Saviour is ſaid to have
                performed and from every diſcourſe that he delivered. This declaration is very often
                made by our Saviour himſelf; particularly to the woman of Samaria, to Nicodemus, and
                to the bhnd man whom he had cured.</p>
            <p>It muſt be evident to every reader, that John ſtudiouſly paſſes over thoſe paſſages
                in our Lord’s hiſtory and teaching which had been treated at large by the other
                evangeliſts, or if he mentions them at all he mentions them ſlightly. This confirms
                the teſtimony of ancient writers, that the firſt three goſpels were written and
                publiſhed before John compoſed his goſpel. Except the relation of our Saviour’s
                trial, death, and reſurrection, almoſt every thing which occurs in this book is
                new.@@ The account of our Saviour’s nativity, of his baptiſm, and of his temptation
                in the wilderneſs, is omitted; nor is any notice taken of the calling of the twelve
                apoſtles, or of their miſſion during our Saviour’s life. It is remarkable, too, that
                not one parable is mentioned, nor any of the predictions relating to the deſtruction
                of Jeruſalem. All the miracles recorded by the other evangeliſts are paſſed over,
                except the miraculous ſupply of proviſion, by which five thouſand were fed: and it
                is probable that this miracle was related for the ſake of the diſcourſe to which it
                gave birth. The other miracles which are mentioned are few in number, but in general
                they are minutely detailed. They conſiſt of theſe: the turning of water into wine at
                Cana; the cure oſ the diſeaſed man at the pool of Betheſda; the cure of the man that
                had been blind from his birth; the reſtoring of Lazarus to life; and the healing of
                the ſervant’s ear which Peter had cut off. But valuable would this goſpel be, though
                it had only recorded the conſolation of Jeſus to his diſciples previous to his
                departure; which exhibits a moſt admirable view of our Saviour’s character, of his
                care and tender regard for his diſciples. Having opened every ſource of comfort to
                their deſponding minds; exhorted them to mutual love, and to the obedience of his
                Father’s precepts; having warned them of the impending dangers and ſorrows—our
                Saviour concludes with a prayer, in the true ſpirit of piety and benevolence; ardent
                without enthuſiaſm, ſober and rational without lukewarmneſs.</p>
            <p>The time in which this goſpel was written has not been fixed with any preciſion.
                Irenæus informs us, that it was written at Epheſus, but leaves us to conjecture
                wſhether it was written before or after John’s return from Patmos. He was baniſhed
                to Patmos by Domitian, who reigned 15 years, and according to the beſt computation
                died A. D. 96. The persecution which occaſioned the exile of John commenced in the
                14th year of Domitian’s reign. If John wrote his goſpel after his return to Epheſus,
                which is affirmed by Epiphanius to have been the caſe, we may fix the date of it
                about the year 97 @@<hi rend="smallcaps">(f).</hi></p>
            <p>This goſpel is evidently the production of an illite-</p>
            <p>@@@(F) It has been argued ſrom a paſſage in this goſpel, that it muſt have been
                written before the deſtruction of Jeruſalem. In ſpeaking of the pool of Bethſaida,
                John uſes the preſent tenſe; His words are, “There <hi rend="italic">is</hi>
                <pb n="159"></pb>at Jeruſalem.” Now if theſe words had been written after the
                deſtruction of Jeruſalem, it is urged the paſt tenſe would have been uſed, and not
                the preſent. This argument is more ſpecious than forcible. Though Jeruſalem was
                demoliſhed, does it follow that the pool of Bethſaida was dried up?</p>
            <p>@@@[m]* John xv. 31. </p>
            <p>@@@[mu] Dr. Campbell's Preface to John's Gospel.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
