<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:56:17Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>mentaries. As to the copies of the diſpatches which are ſaid to have been written by my direction to Mendoza, the lord Paget, Charles Paget, the archbiſhop of Glaſgow, and Sir Francis Ingleſield, they are moſt unprofitable forgeries. For they tend only to ſhow that I was employed in encouraging my friends to invade England. Now, if I ſhould allow that theſe diſpatches were genuine, it could not be inferred from them that I had conſpired the death of Elizabeth. I will even conſeſs, that I have yielded to the ſtrong impulſes of nature; and that, like a human creature, encompaſſed with dangers and inſulted with wrongs, I have exerted  myſelf to recover my greatneſs and my liberty. The efforts I have made can excite no bluſhes in me; for the voice of mankind muſt applaud them. Religion, in her ſterneſt moments of ſeverity, cannot look to them with reproach; and to conſider them as crimes, is to deſpiſe the ſanctimonious reverence of humanity, and to give way to the ſuſpicious wretchedneſs of deſpotiſm. I have ſought by every art of conceſſion and friendſhip to engage my ſiſter to put a period to my ſufferings. Invited by her ſmiles, I ventured into her kingdom, in the pride and gaiety of my youth; and, under her anger and the miſeries of captivity, I have grown into age. During a calamitous confinement of 20 years, my youth, my health, my happineſs, are for ever gone. To her tenderneſs and generoſity I have been indebted as little as to her juſtice: and, oppreſſed and agonizing with unmerited afflictions and hardſhips, I ſcrupled not to beſeech the princes my allies to employ their armies to relieve me. Nor will I deny, that I have endeavoured to promote the advantage and intereſt of the perſecuted Catholics of England. My intreaties in their behalf have been even offered with earneſtneſs to queen Elizabeth herſelf. But the attainment of my kingdom, the recovery of my liberty, and the advancement of that religion which I love, could not induce me to ſtain myſelf with the crimes that are objected to me. I would diſdain to purchaſe a crown by the aſſaſſination of the meaneſt of the human race. To accuſe me of ſcheming the death of the queen my ſiſter, is to brand me with the infamy which I abhor moſt. It is my nature to employ the devotions of Either, and not the ſword of Judith. Elizabeth herſelf will atteſt, that I have often admoniſhed her not to draw upon her head the reſentment of my friends by the enormity of her cruelties to me. My innocence cannot ſincerely be doubted; and it is known to the Almighty God, that I could not poſſibly think to forego his mercy, and to ruin my ſoul, in order to compaſs a tranſgreſſion ſo horrible as that of her murder. But amidſt the inclement and unprincipled pretences which my adverſaries are pleaſed to invent to overwhelm me with calamities and anguiſh, I can trace and diſcover with eaſe the real cauſes of their hoſtility and provocation. My crimes are, my birth, the injuries I have been compelled to endure, and my religion. I am proud of the firſt; I can forgive the ſecond; and the third is a ſource to me of ſuch comfort and hope, that for its glory I will be contented that my blood ſhall flow upon the ſcaffold.”</p><p>To the defence of Mary, no returns were made beſide flout and unſupported affirmations of the truth of the evidence produced to her prejudice. In the courſe of the trial, however, there occurred ſome incidents which deſerve to be related. My lord Burleigh, who</p><p>was willing to diſcompoſe her, charged her with a fixed reſolution of conveying her claims and titles to England to the king of Spain. But though, in a diſcontented humour with her ſon, ſhe had threatened to diſinherit him, and had even correſponded on the ſubject with her ſelect friends, it appears that this project is to be conſidered as only a tranſient effect of reſentment and paſſion. She indeed acknowledged, that the Spaniard profeſſed to have pretenſions to the kingdom of England, and that a book in juſtification of them had been communicated to her. She declared, however, that ſhe had incurred the diſpleaſure of many by diſapproving of this book; and that no conveyance of her titles to the Spaniard had been ever executed.</p><p>The trial continued during the ſpace of two days; but ſhe commiſſioners avoided to deliver their opinions. My lord Burleigh, in whoſe management Elizabeth chiefly confided, and whom the Scottiſh queen diſcompoſed in no common degree by her ability and vigour, being eager to conclude the buſineſs, demanded to know if ſhe had any thing to add to what ſhe had urged in her defence. She informed him, that ſhe would be infinitely pleaſed and gratified, if it ſhould be permitted to her to be heard in her juſtification before a full meeting of the parliament, or before the queen and her privy-council. This intimation was unexpected; and the requeſt implied in it was rejected. The court, in conſequence of previous inſtructions from Elizabeth, adjourned to a farther day, and appointed that the place of its convention ſhould be the ſtar-chamber at Weſtminſter. It accordingly aſſembled there; and Naw and Curl, who had not been produced at Fotherſhgay- caſtle, were now called before the commiſſioners. An oath to declare the truth was put to them; and they definitely affirmed and proteſted that the declaration they had ſubſcribed was in every reſpect juſt and faithful. Nothing farther remained but to pronounce ſentence againſt Mary. The commiſſioners unanimouſly concurred in delivering it as their verdict or judgment, that ſhe “was a party to the conſpiracy of Babington; and that ſhe had compaſſed and imagined matters within the realm of England tending to the hurt, death, and deſtruction, of the royal perſon of Elizabeth, in oppoſition to the ſtatute framed for her protection.” Upon the ſame day in which this extraordinary ſentence was given, the commiſſioners and the judges of England iſſued a declaration, which imported, that it was not to derogate in any degree from the titles and honour of the king of Scots.</p><p>The ſentence againſt Mary was very ſoon afterwards ratified by the Engliſh parliament. King James was ſtruck with horror at hearing of the execution of his mother; but that ſpiritleſs prince could ſhow his reſentment no farther than by unavailing embaſſies and re- monſtrances. France interpoſed in the ſame ineffectual manner; and on the 6th of December 1586, Elizabeth cauſed the ſentence of the commiſſioners againſt her to be proclaimed. After this ſhe was made acquainted with her fate, and received the news with the greateſt compoſure, and even apparent ſatisfaction. Her keepers now refuſed to treat her with any reverence or reſpect. They entered her apartment with their heads covered, and made no obeiſance to her. They took down her canopy of ſtate, and deprived her of all the badges of royalty. By theſe intuiting mortifications</p></body></text></TEI>