<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-14T17:57:16Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>and if it is ſolid, the Chriſtian religion is fully eſtabliſhed. The proofs for the
                authenticity of the New Teſtament have this peculiar advantage, that they are plain
                and ſimple, and involve no metaphyſical ſubtilties.— Every man who can diſtinguiſh
                truth from falſehood muſt see their force; and if there are any so blinded by
                prejudice, or corrupted by licentiouſneſs, as to attempt by ſophiſtry to elude them,
                their ſophiſtry will be eaſily detected by every man of common underſtanding, who
                has read the hiſtorical evidence with candour and attention. Inſtead, therefore, of
                declaiming againſt the infidel, we ſolicit his attention to this ſubject, convinced,
                that where truth reſides, it will ſhine with ſo conſtant and clear a light, that the
                combined ingenuity of all the deiſts ſince the beginning of the world will never be
                able to extinguiſh or to obſcure it. If the books of the New Teſtament are really
                genuine, oppoſition will incite the Chriſtian to bring forward the evidence; and
                thus by the united efforts of the deiſt and the Chriſtins, the arguments will be
                ſtated with all the clearneſs and accuracy of which they are ſuſceptible in ſo
                remarkable a degree.</p>
            <p>It is ſurpriſing that the adverſaries of Chriſtianity have not always made their
                firſt attacks in this quarter; for if they admit that the writings of the New
                Teſtament are as ancient as we affirm, and compoſed by the perſons to whom they are
                aſcribed, they muſt allow, if they reaſon fairly, that the Chriſtian religion is
                true.</p>
            <p>The apoſtles allude frequently in their epiſtles to the gift of miracles, which they
                had communicated to the Chriſtian converts by the impoſition of hands, in
                confirmation of the doctrine delivered in their ſpeeches and writings, and ſometimes
                to miracles which they themſelves had performed.@@ Now if theſe epiſtles are really
                genuine, it is hardly poſſible to deny thoſe miracles to be true. The caſe is here
                entirely different from that of an hiſtorian, who relates extraordinary events in
                the courſe of his narrative, ſince either credulity or an actual intention to
                deceive may induce him to deſcribe as true a ſeries of falſehoods reſpecting a
                foreign land or diſtant period. Even to the Evangeliſts might an adverſary of the
                Chriſtian religion make this objection: but to write to perſons with whom we ſtand
                in the reareſt connection, “I have not only performed miracles in your preſence, but
                have likewiſe communicated to you the ſame extraordinary endowments,” to write in
                this manner, if nothing of the kind had ever happened, would require ſuch an
                incredible degree of effrontery, that he who poſſeſſed it would not only expoſe
                himſelf to the utmoſt ridicule, but by giving his adverſaries the faireſt
                opportunity to detect his impoſture, would ruin the cauſe which he attempted to
                ſupport.</p>
            <p>St Paul’s Firſt Epiſtle to the Theſſalonians is addreſſed to a community to which he
                had preached the goſpel only three Sabbath days, when he was forced to quit it by
                the perſecution of the populace. In this epiſtle he appeals to the miracles which he
                had performed, and to the gifts of the Holy Spirit which he had communicated. Now,
                is it poſſible, without forfeiting all pretenſions to common ſenſe, that, in writing
                to a community which he had lately eſtabliſhed, he could ſpeak of miracles
                performed, and gifts of the Holy Ghoſt communicated, if no member of the ſociety had
                ſeen the one, or received the other?</p>
            <p>To ſuppoſe that an impoſtor could write to the couverts or adverſaries of the new
                religion ſuch epiſtles as theſe, with a degree of triumph over his opponents, and
                yet maintain his authority, implies ignorance and ſtupidity hardly to be believed,
                Credulous as the Chriſtians have been in later ages, and even ſo early as the third
                century, no leſs ſevere were they in their inquiries, and guarded againſt deception,
                at the introduction of Chriſtianity. This character is given them even by Lucian, a
                writer of the ſecond century, who vented his ſatire not only againſt certain
                Chriſtians @@*, who had ſupplied Peregrinus with the means of ſubſiſtence, but alſo
                againſt heathen oracles and pretended wonders. He relates of his impoſtor
                (Pſeudomantis), that he attempted nothing ſupernatural in the preſence of the
                Chriſtians and Epicureans. This Pſeudomantis exclaims before the whole aſſembly,
                “Away with the Chriſtians, away with the Epicureans, and let thoſe only remain who
                believe in the Deity!" (ωιϛευντεϛ τωϴεω) upon which the populace took up ſtones to
                drive away the ſuſpicious; while the other philoſophers, Pythagoreans, Platoniſts,
                and Stoics, as credulous friends and protectors of the cauſe, were permitted to
                remain @@§.</p>
            <p>It is readily acknowledged, that the arguments drawn from the authenticity of the New
                Teſtament only eſtabliſh the truth of the miracles performed by the apoſtles, and
                are not applicable to the miracles of our Saviour; yet, if we admit the three firſt
                goſpels to be genuine, the truth of the Chriſtian religion will be proved from the
                prophecies of Jeſus. For if theſe goſpels were compoſed by Matthew, Mark, and Luke,
                at the time in which all the primitive Chriſtians affirm, that is, previous to the
                deſtruction of Jeruſalem, they muſt be inſpired; for they contain a circumſtantial
                prophecy of the deſtruction of Jeruſalem, and determine the period at which it was
                accompliſhed. Now it was impoſſible that human ſagacity could foreſee that event;
                for when it was predicted nothing was more improbable. The Jews were reſolved to
                avoid an open rebellion, well knowing the greatneſs of their danger, and ſubmitted
                to the oppreſſions of their governors in the hope of obtaining redreſs from the
                court of Rome.— The circumſtance which gave birth to theſe misfortunes is ſo
                trifling in itſelf, that, independent of its conſequences, it would not deſerve to
                be recorded. In the narrow entrance to a ſynagogue in Caeſarea, ſome perſon had made
                an offering of birds merely with a view to irritate the Jews. The inſult excited
                their indignation, and occaſioned the ſhedding of blood. Without this trifling
                accident, which no human wiſdom could foreſee even the day before it happened, it is
                poſſible that the prophecy of Jeſus would never have been fulfilled. But Florus, who
                was then procurator of Judea, converted this private quarrel into public
                hoſtilities, and Compelled the Jewiſh nation to rebel contrary to its wiſh and
                reſolution, in order to avoid what the Jews had threatened, an impeachment before
                the Roman emperor for his exceſſive cruelties. But even after this rebellion had
                broken out, the deſtruction of the temple was a very improbable event. It was not
                the practice of the Romans to deſtroy the magnificent</p>
            <p>@@@[mu] Michaelis's Introduction to the New Testament.</p>
            <p>@@@[m]* De Morte Peregrini, § 12. 13. 16. Ed. Reitz, Tom. 111. p. 334-338, 341.</p>
            <p>@@@[m]§ Alexander seu Pseudomantis, 25. 28. Tom. 11. p. 232, 233-244, 245. </p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
