<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:56:11Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>med to her. She was aſſailed by rheumatiſms and other maladies; and her phyſician would not undertake to effect a cure, or even to procure her any eaſe, unleſs ſhe ſhould be removed to a more commodious dwelling. Applications for this purpoſe were frequently made, and uniformly rejected. Here, however, her own afflictions did not extinguiſh in her mind her ſenſibility for the misfortunes of others; and ſhe often indulged herſelf in the ſatisfaction of employing a ſervant to go through the village of Tutbury in ſearch of objects of diſtreſs, to whom ſhe might deal out her charity. But her inhuman keepers, envying her this pleaſure, commanded her to abſtain from it. Imputing their rigour to a ſuſpicious fidelity, ſhe deſired that her fervant might, on theſe occaſions, be accompanied by one of the ſoldiers of their guard, or by the conſtable of the village. But they would not alter their prohibition. They refuſed to her the exerciſe of the Chriſtian duty of diſpenfing an alms; and they would not allow her the ſoft conſolation of moiſtening her eye with ſorrows not her own. To inſult her the more, the caſtle of Tutbury was converted into a common jail. A young man, whoſe crime was the profeſſion of the Romiſh religion, was committed to a chamber which was oppoſite to her window, in order that he might be perſecuted in her fight with a peſtilent cruelty. Notwithſtanding his cries and reſiſtance, he was dragged every morning to hear prayers, and to join in the Proteſtant worſhip; and after enduring ſeveral weeks this extraordinary violence to his conſcience, he was unmercifully ſtrangled without any form of law or juſtice. Mary remonſtrated with warmth to Elizabeth againſt indignities ſo ſhocking and ſo horrible; but inſtead of obtaining conſolation or relief, ſhe was involved more deeply in wo, and expoſed to ſtill harder inventions of malice and of anger.</p><p>In the midſt of her misfortunes, Mary had ſtill ſolaced herſelf with hope; and from the exertions of her ſon ſhe naturally expected a ſuperlative advantage. He had hitherto behaved with a becoming cordiality; and in the negociation which ſhe had opened with him for her aſſociation in the government, he had been ſtudious to pleaſe and flatter her. He had informed her by a particular diſpatch, that he found the greateſt comfort in her maternal tenderneſs, and that he would accompliſh her commands with humility and expedition; that he would not fail to ratify her union and aſſociation with him in the government; that it would be his moſt earneſt endeavour to reconcile their common ſubjects to that meaſure; and that ſhe might expect from him, during his life, every ſatisfaction and duty which a good mother could promiſe to herſelf from an affectionate and obedient ſon. But theſe fair bloſſoms of kindneſs and love were all blaſted by the treacherous arts of Elizabeth. By the maſter of Gray, who had obtained an aſcendant over James, ſhe turned from Mary his affections. He delayed to ratify her aſſociation in the government; and he even appeared to be unwilling to preſs Elizabeth on the ſubject of her liberty. The maſter of Gray had convinced him, that if any favour was ſhown to Mary by the queen of England, it would terminate in his humiliation. He aſſured him, that if his mother were again to mount the Scottiſh throne, her zeal for Popery would induce her to ſeek a huſband in the houſe of Auſtria: that ſhe would diſſolve his aſſociation with her in the government, on the pretence of his attachment to the reformed doctrines; and that he would not only loſe the glory of his preſent power, but endanger his proſpects of ſucceſſion. Mary expoſtulated with him by letter upon the timidity and coldneſs of his behaviour; and he returned her an anſwer full of diſreſpect, in which he intimated his reſolution to conſider her in no other character than as queen-mother. Her amazement, indignation, and grief, were infinite. She wrote to Caſtelnau the French ambaſſador to inform him of her inquietudes and anguiſh. “My ſon (ſaid ſhe) is ungrateful; and I deſire that the king your maſter ſhall conſider him no longer as a ſovereign. In your future diſpatches, abſtain from giving him the title of king. I am his queen and his ſovereign; and while I live, and continue at variance with him, he can at the beſt be but an uſurper. From him I derive no luſtre; and without me he could only have been lord Darnley or the earl of Lenox; for I raiſed his father from being my ſubject to be my huſband. I aſk from him nothing that is his; what I claim is my own; and if he perſiſts in his courſe of impiety and ingratitude, I will beſtow upon him my malediction, and deprive him not only of all right to Scotland, but of all the dignity and grandeur to which he may ſucceed through me. My enemies ſhall not enjoy the advantages they expect from him. For to the king of Spain I will convey, in the ampleſt form, my claims, titles, and greatneſs.”</p><p>Elizabeth having thus found means to ſow diſſenſion between the queen of Scots and her ſon, did not fail to make the beſt uſe ſhe could of the quarrel for her own advantage. The Pope, the duke of Guiſe, and the king of Spain, had concluded an alliance, called the <hi rend="italic">holy league,</hi> for the extirpation of the Proteſtant religion all over Europe. Elizabeth was thrown into the greateſt conſternation on this account; and the idea of a counter aſſociation among the Proteſtant princes of Europe immediately ſuggeſted itſelf. Sir Edward Wotton was deputed to Scotland; and ſo completely gained upon the imbecility of James, that he concluded a firm alliance with Elizabeth, without making any ſtipulation in favour of his mother. Nay, ſo far was he the dupe of this ambaſſador and his miſtreſs, that he allowed himſelf to be perſuaded to take into his favour Mr Archibald Douglas, one of the murderers of Lord Darnley; and, as if all this had not been ſuſſicient, he appointed this aſſaſſin to be his ambaſſador for England.</p><p>Mary, thus abandoned by all the world, in the hands of her moſt inveterate and cruel enemy, fell a victim to her reſentment and treachery in the year 1587. A plot of aſſaſſination had been formed in the ſpring of the year 1586 againſt the Engliſh queen; partly with a view to reſcue the Scottiſh princeſs; but chiefly from a motive to ſerve the intereſts of the Roman Catholic religion. This conſpiracy, which originated with Roman Catholic prieſts and perſons of little note, was ſoon imparted to Mr Babington, a perſon of great fortune, of many accompliſhments, and who had before that time diſcovered himſelf to be a zealous friend of queen Mary. That ſhe had correſponded with Babington there is no doubt; but it was ſome years previous to the formation of the plot. A long ſilence had taken place between them; and Morgan,</p></body></text></TEI>