<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-14T17:56:36Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>guiſh them from other books; which, being of no authority, were kept as it were out
                of ſight, and therefore ſtyled <hi rend="italic">apocryphal @@</hi><hi
                    rend="smallcaps">(a).</hi></p>
            <p>The authenticity of the Old Teſtament may be pro ved from the character of the Jews,
                from internal evidence, and from teſtimony.</p>
            <p>I. The character of the Jews affords a ſtrong preſumptive evidence that they have not
                forged or corrupted the Old Teſtament. Were a perſon brought before a court of
                juſtice on a ſuſpicion of forgery, and yet no preſumption or poſitive evidence of
                his guilt could be produced, it would be allowed by all that he ought to be
                acquitted. But farther, if the forgery alleged were inconſiſtent with the character
                of the accuſed; if it tended to expoſe to diſgrace and reproach his general
                principles and conduct; or if we were aſſured that be conſidered forgery as an
                impious and abominable crime—it would require very ſtrong teſtimony to eſtabliſh his
                guilt. The cafe now mentioned correſponds exactly with the character and ſituation
                of the Jews. If a Jew had forged any book of the Old Teſtament, he muſt have been
                impelled to ſo bold and dangerous an enterpriſe by ſome very powerful motive. It
                could not be national pride, for there is ſcarcely one of there books which does not
                ſeverely cenſure the national manners. It could not be the love of fame; for that
                paſſion would have taught him to flatter and extol the national character; and the
                puniſhment, if detected, would have been infamy and death. The love of wealth could
                not produce ſuch a forgery; for no wealth was to be gained.</p>
            <p>The Jews were ſelected from the other nations of the world, and preſerved a diſtinct
                people from the time of their emigration from Egypt to the Babyloniſh captivity, a
                period of 892 years. The principal purpoſes for which they were ſelected was to
                preſerve in a world running headlong into idolatry the knowledge and worſhip of the
                one true God, and to be the guardians of thoſe ſacred books that contained the
                prophecies which were to prove to future ages the divine miſſion of the Redeemer of
                mankind. To fit them for theſe important trufts, the ſpirit of their laws and the
                rites of their religion had the ſtrongeſt tendency. Miracles were openly performed,
                to convince them that the God of Iſrael was the God of all the earth, and that he
                alone was to be worſhipped. Public calamities always befel them when they became
                apoſtates to their God; yet they continued violently attached to idolatry till their
                captivity in Babylon made them for ever renounce it.</p>
            <p>The Jews then had two oppoſite characters at different periods of their hiſtory: At
                firſt they were addicted to idolatry; afterwards they acquired a ſtrong antipathy
                againſt it.</p>
            <p>Had any books of the Old Teſtament been forged before the Babyloniſh captivity, when
                the Jews were devoted to idolatry, is it to be conceived that the impoſtor would
                have inveighed ſo ſtrongly againſt this vice, and ſo often imputed to it the
                calamities of the ſtate; ſince by ſuch conduct he knew that he would render himſelf
                obnoxious to the people and to thoſe idolatrous monarchs who perſecuted the
                prophets?</p>
            <p>But it may next be ſuppoſed, that “the ſacred books were forged after the Babyloniſh
                captivity, when the principles of the Jews would lead them to inveigh againſt the
                worſhip of idols. But theſe principles would ſurely never lead them to expoſe the
                character of their anceſtors, and to detail their follies and their crimes. Never
                had any people more national pride, or a higher veneration for their anceſtors, than
                the Jews. Miracles and prophecies ceaſed ſoon after their return to Jeruſalem; and
                from that period their reſpect for the ſacred books approached to ſuperſtition. They
                preſerved them with pious care, they read them often in their ſynagogues, and they
                conſidered every attempt to alter the text as an act of ſacrilege. Is it poſſible
                that ſuch men could be guilty of forgery, or could falſe "writings be eaſily impoſed
                on them?</p>
            <p>2. There is an internal evidence in the books of the Old Teſtament that proves them
                to have been written by different perſons, and at diſtant periods; and enables us
                with preciſion to aſcertain a time at or before which they muſt have been compoſed.
                It is an undeniable fact that Hebrew ceaſed to be the living language of the Jews
                during the Babyloniſh captivity, and that the Jewiſh productions after that period
                were in general written either in Chaldee or in Greek. The Jews of Paleſtine, ſome
                ages before the coming of our Saviour, were unable, without the aſſiſtance of a
                Chaldee para- phraſe, to underſtand the Hebrew original. It neceſſarily follows,
                therefore, that every book which is written in pure Hebrew was compoſed either
                before or about the time of the Babyloniſh captivity. This being admitted, we may
                advance a ſtep farther, and contend that the period which elapſed between the
                compoſition of the moſt ancient and the moſt modern book of the Old Teſtament was
                very conſiderable; or, in other words, that the moſt ancient books of the Old
                Teſtament were written many ages before the Babyloniſh captivity.</p>
            <p>No language continues ſtationary; and the Hebrew, like other tongues, paſſed through
                the ſeveral ſtages of infancy, youth, manhood, and old age. If therefore, on
                compariſon, the ſeveral parts of the Hebrew Bible are found to differ not only in
                regard to ſtyle, but alſo in regard to character and cultivation, we have ſtrong
                internal marks that they were compoſed at different and diſtant periods. No
                claſſical ſcholar would believe, independent of the Grecian hiſtory, that the poems
                aſcribed to Homer were written in the age of Demoſthenes, the Orations of
                Demoſthenes in the time of Origen, or the Commentaries of Origen in the time of
                Daſcaris and Chryſhloras. For the very ſarne reaſon, it is certain that the five
                books which arc aſcribed to Moſes were not written in the time of David, the Pſalins
                of David in the age of Iſaiah, nor the prophecies of Iſaiah in the time of Malachi;
                and ſince the Hebrew became a dead language about the time of the Babyloniſh
                captivity, the book of Malachi could not have been written much later. Before that
                period there- fore were written the prophecies of lſaiah, ſtill earlier the Pſalms
                of David, and much earlier than theſe the books which are aſcribed to Moſes.</p>
            <p>@@@<hi rend="italic smallcaps">(a)</hi><hi rend="italic"> From αποχϱυπΊω,</hi> to put
                out of sight.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
