<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:55:37Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>papers ſhe had ſubſcribed; and ſurrendered the ſword, ſceptre, and royal crown. After the papers were read, the earls of Morton, Athol, Glencairn, Marre, and Menteith, with the maſter of Graham, the lord Hume, and Bothwel biſhop of Orkney, received the queen’s reſignation in favour of her ſon in the name of the three eſtates. After this formality, the earl of Morton, bending his body, and laying his hand upon the Scriptures, took the coronation oath for the prince, engaging that he ſhould rule according to the laws, and root  out all heretics and enemies to the word of God. Adam Bothwel then anointed the prince king of Scotland; a ceremony with which John Knox was diſpleaſed, as believing it to be of Jewiſh invention. This prelate next delivered to him the ſword and the ſceptre, and finally put the crown upon his head. In the proceſſion to the caſtle from the church, where the inauguration was performed, and where John Knox preached the inauguration ſermon, the earl of Athol carried the crown, Morton the ſceptre, Glencairn the ſword, and the earl of Marre carried the prince in his arms. Theſe ſolemnities received no countenance from Elizabeth; and Throgmorton, by her expreſs command, was not preſent at them.</p><p>Soon after this ceremony, the earl of Murray returned from France; and his preſence gave ſuch a ſtrength and firmneſs to his faction, that very little oppoſition could be given by the partiſans of Mary, who were unſettled and deſponding for want of a leader. A little time after his arrival, this monſtrous hypocrite and traitor waited upon his diſtreſſed and inſulted ſovereign at Lochleven. His deſign was to get her to deſire him to accept of the regency, which he otherwiſe pretended to decline. The queen, unſuſpicious of the deepneſs of his arts, conſcious of the gratitude he owed to her, and truſting to his natural affection, and their tie of a common father, received him with a tender welcome. She was in haſte to pour forth her foul to him; and with tears and lamentations related her condition and her ſufferings. He heard her with attention: and turned occaſionallyhis diſcourſe to the topics which might lead her to open to him her mind without diſguiſe in thoſe ſituations in which he was moſt anxious to obſerve it. His eye and his penetration were fully employed; but her diſtreſs awakened not his tenderneſs. He ſeemed to be in ſuſpenſe; and from the guardedneſs of his converſation ſhe could gather neither hope nor fear. She begged him to be free with her, as he was her only friend. He yielded to her intreaties as if with pain and reluctance; and taking a comprehensive ſurvey of her conduct, deſcribed it with all the ſeverity that could affect her moſt. He could diſcover no apology for her miſ-government and diſorders; and, with a mortifying plainneſs, he preſſed upon her conſcience and her honour. At times ſhe wept bitterly. Some errors ſhe confeſſed; and againſt, calumnies ſhe warmly vindicated herſelf. But all ſhe could urge in her behalf made no impreſſion upon him; and he ſpoke to her of the mercy of God as her chief refuge. She was torn with apprehenſions, and nearly diſtracted with deſpair. He dropped ſome words of conſolation; and after expreſſing an attachment to her intereſts, gave her his promiſe to employ all his conſequence to ſecure her life. As to her liberty, he told her, that to atchieve it was beyond all his efforts; and that it was not good for her</p><p>to deſire it. Starting from her ſeat, ſhe took, him in. her arms, and kiſſing him as her deliverer from the ſcaffold, ſolicited his immediate acceptance of the regency. He declared he had many reaſons to refuſe the regency. She implored and conjured him not to abandon her in the extremity of her wretchedneſs. There was no other method, ſhe ſaid, by which ſhe herſelf could be ſaved, her ſon protected, and her realm rightly governed. He gave way to her anxiety and ſolicitations. She beſought him to make the moſt unbounded uſe of her name and authority, defined him to keep for her the jewels that yet remained with her, and. recommended it to him to get an early poſſeſſion of all the forts of her kingdom. He now took his leave of her, and embracing anew this pious traitor, ſhe ſent her bleſſing with him to the prince her ſon.</p><p>In the mean time the wretched earl of Bothwel was ſtruggling with the greateſt difficulties. Sir William Murray and Kirkaldy of Grange had put to ſea in ſearch of him. He had been obliged to exerciſe piracy in order to ſubſiſt himſelf and his followers. His purſuers came upon him unexpectedly at the Orkney iſlands, and took three of his ſhips; but he himſelf made his eſcape. Soon after, having ſeized a Turkiſh trader on the coaſt of Norway, two ſhips of war belonging to the king of Denmark gave chace to him as a pirate. An engagement enſued, in, which Bothwel was taken. His officers and mariners were hanged in Denmark; but Bothwel himſelf, being known by ſome Scottiſh merchants, had his life ſpared. He was thrown,  however, into a dungeon, where he remained ten years; and at laſt died melancholy and diſtracted. The regent ſent commiſſioners to the king of Denmark to demand him as a priſoner; but that prince, conſidemng him as a traitor and uſurper, totally diſregarded his requeſt.</p><p>The dreadful fate of Bothwel did not make any alteration in the ſituation of the queen. Her enemies, bent on calumniating her, produced letters, which they ſaid were written and ſent by her to that licentious nobleman during the life of the king. Theſe letters are now univerſally admitted to have been forged by the rebels themſelves, who practiſed likewiſe upon ſome ſervants of Bothwel to accuſe the queen of the murder of her huſband. The letters for ſome time gained credit; but the conſeſſions of the ſervants were all in her favour. When on the ſcaffold, they addreſſed themſelves to the people; and after having ſolemnly declared the innocence of the queen, they proteſted before God and his angels, that the earl of Bothwel had informed them that the earls of Murray and Morton were the contrivers <hi rend="italic">of</hi> the king’s murder.</p><p>It was impoſſible that ſuch tranſactions as theſe could advance the popularity of the regent. His unbounded ambition and cruelty to his ſovereign began at laſt to open the eyes of the nation; and a party was forming itſelf in favour of the queen. She herſelf had been often meditating her eſcape from her priſon; and ſhe at laſt effected it by means of a young gentleman Georgy Douglas, brother to her keeper, who had fallen in love with her. On the 2d day of May 1568, about ſeven o’clock in the evening, when her keeper was at ſupper with hi<hi rend="smallcaps">s</hi> family, George Douglas, poſſeſſing himſelf of the keys of the caſtle, haſtened to her apartment, and conducted her out of priſon. Having locked the gates</p></body></text></TEI>