<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:54:40Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>De Thermes brought with him from France a reinforcement of 1000 foot, 2000 horſe, and 100 men- at-arms. He erected a fort at Aberlady, to diſtreſs the garriſon of Haddington, and to intercept its ſupplies of proviſion. At Coldingham he deſtroyed a troop of Spaniards in the Engliſh pay. Faſt-caſtle was regained by ſurpriſe. Diſtractions in the Engliſh court did not permit the protector to act vigorouſly in the war. The earl of Warwick was diverted from marching an army into Scotland. An infectious diſtemper had broke out in the garriſon at Haddington; and an apprehenſion prevailed, that it could not hold out for any length of time againſt the Scots, The earl of Rutland, therefore, with a body of troops, entered the town; and after ſetting fire to it, conducted the garriſon and artillery to Berwick. The regent, in the poſſeſſion of Haddington, was solicitous to recover the other places which were yet in the power of the Engliſh. De Thermes laid ſiege to Broughty caſtle, and took it. He then beſieged Lawder; and the garriſon was about to ſurrender at diſcretion, when the news arrived that a peace was concluded between France, England, and Scotland.</p><p>By this treaty Henry IT. obtained the reſtitution of Boulogne and its dependencies, which had been taken from him by the king of England, and for which he paid 400,000 crowns, No oppoſition was to be given to the marriage of the queen of Scotland with the dauphin: the fortreſſes of Lawder and Douglas were to be reſtored to the Scots, and the Engliſh were to deſtroy the caſtles of Roxburgh and Eymouth. After the ratification of the articles, the queen-dowager embarked with Leon Strozzi for France, attended by many of the nobility. Having arrived there, ſhe communicated to the king her deſign of affirming the government of Scotland, and he promiſed to aſſiſt her to the utmost of his power. But the jealouſy which prevailed between the Scots and French rendered the accompliſhment of this deſign very difficult. To remove the regent by an act of power might endanger the ſcheme altogether; but it might be poſſible to perſuade him to reſign his office voluntarily. For this purpoſe intrigues were immediately commenced; and indeed the regent himſelf contributed to promote their ſchemes by his violent perſecution oſ the reformed. The peace was hardly proclaimed, when he provoked the public reſentment by an action of ſanguinary inſolence. Adam  Wallace, a man of ſimple manners, but of great zeal for the reformation, was accuſed of hereſy, and brought to trial in the church of the Black Friars at Edinburgh. In the preſence of the regent, the earls of Angus, Huntley, Glencaim, and other perſons of diſtinction and rank, he was charged with preaching without any authority of law, with baptizing one of his own children, and with denying the doctrine of purgatory; and it was ftrenuouſly objected to him, that he accounted prayers to the faints and the dead to be an uleleſs ſuperſtition, that he had pronounced the maſs to be an idolatrous ſervice, and that he had affirmed that the bread and wine in the ſacrament of the altar, after the words of the conſecration, do not change their nature, but continue to be bread and wine. Theſe offences were eſteemed too terrible to admit of any pardon.— The earl of Glencairn alone proteſted againſt his puniſhment. The pious ſufferer bore with reſignation the</p><p>contumelious inſults of the clergy; and by his courage and patience at the ſtake gave a fonction to the opinions he had embraced.</p><p>Other acts of atrocity and violence ſtained the adminiſtration of the regent. In his own palace, William Crichton, a man of family and reputation, was aſſaſſinanated by the lord Semple. No attempt was made to puniſh the murderer. His daughter was the concubine of the archbiſhop of St Andrew’s, and her tears and intreaties were more powerful than juſtice. John Melvil, a perſon reſpectable by his birth and his fortune, had written to an Engliſh gentleman, recommending to his care a friend who at that time was a captive in England. This letter contained no improper information in matters of ſtate, and no ſuſpicion of any crime againſt Melvil could be inferred from it. Yet the regent brought him to trial upon a charge of high treaſon; and, for an act of humanity and friendſhip, he was condemned to loſe his head. The eſtate of Melvil, forfeited to his family, was given to David the youngeſt ſoil of the regent.</p><p>Amidſt the pleaſures and amuſements of the French court, the queen-dowager was not inattentive to the ſcheme of ambition which ſhe had projected. The earls of Huntley and Sutherland, Mariſchal and Caſſilis, with the lord Maxwell, and other perſons of eminence who had accompanied her to France, were gained over to her intereſts, Robert Carnegie of Kinnaird, David Panter biſhop of Rofs, and Gavin Hamilton commendator of Kilwinning, being alſo at this time in that kingdom, and having the greateſt weight with the regent, were treated with a moſt punctilious reſpect. Henry declared to them his earneſt wiſh that the queen-dowager might attain the government of Scotland. In cafe the regent ſhould conſent to this meaſure, he expreſſed a firm intention that no detriment ſhould happen to his conſequence and affairs; and he deſired them to inform him, that he had already confirmed his title of <hi rend="italic">duke oſ Chatelherault,</hi> had advanced his ſon to be captain oſ the Scots gendarmes in France, and was ready to tender other marks of favour to his family and relations. Upon this buſineſs, and with this meſſage, Mr Carnegie was diſpatched to Scotland; and a few days after, he was followed by the biſhop of Roſs. The biſhop being a man of eloquence and authority, obtained, though with great difficulty, a promiſe from the regent to reſign his high office; and for this ſervice he received, as a recompenſe, an abbey in Poitou.</p><p>The queen-dowager, full of hopes, now prepared to return to Scotland, and in her way thither made uſe of a safe-conduct obtained from Edward VI. by the king of France, The Engliſh monarch, however, had not yet forgot the beautiful queen of Scotland; and did not fail to urge his ſuperiority of claim to her over the dauphin. The queen-dowager did not ſeriouſly enter upon the buſineſs; only in general terms complained of the hoſtilities committed by the Engliſh; and two days after this converſation, ſhe proceeded towards Scotland, where ſhe was conducted by the earl of Bothwel, lord Hume, and ſome other noblemen, to Edinburgh, amidſt the acclamations of the people. She had not long been returned to the capital, when the bad conduct of the regent afforded her an opportunity of exerting her influence and addreſs to the advantage of her project. The regent having propoſed a judicial circuit through</p></body></text></TEI>