<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:54:31Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ſhould be inſerred againſt any perſon ſor having them in his poſſeſſion, or for making uſe of them. The regent and the three eſtates acknowleged the propriety of this propoſal. Gavin Dunbar archbiſhop of Glaſgow, and chancellor of Scotland, proteſted, indeed, for himſelf and for the church, that no act on this ſubject ſhould paſs and be effectual, till a provincial council of all the clergy of the kingdom ſhould conſider and determine, whether there was a neceſſity that the people ſhould conſult and ſtudy the ſcriptures in the vulgar tongue. But his prateſtation being disregarded, the bill of the lord Maxwell was carried into a law, and the regent made it generally known by a proclamation.</p><p>From this period copies of the Bible were imported in great numbers from England; and men, allured by an appeal ſo flattering to their reaſon, were proud to recover from the ſupine ignorance in which they had been kept by an artful prieſthocd. To read became a common accompliſhment: and books were multiplied in every quarter, which diſcloſed the pride, the tyranny, and the abſurdities of the Romiſh church and iuperſtitions.</p><p>The death of James V. proved very favourable to the ambitious deſigns of Henry. He now propoſed an union of the two kingdoms by the marriage of his ſon Edward VI. with Mary the young queen of Scotland. To promote this, he releaſed the noblemen who had been taken priſoners at Solway, after having engaged them on oath, not only to concur in promoting the alliance, but to endeavour to procure him the charge and cuſtody of the young queen, with the government of her kingdom, and the poſſeſſion of her caſtles. The earl of Angus and his brother, who had been fifteen years in exile, accompanied them to Scotland, and brought letters from Henry recommending them to the reſtitution of their honours and eſtates. The regent was inclined to favour the demands of perſons of ſuch eminent ſtation; but though the ſtates were inclined to the marriage, they refuſed to permit the removal of the queen into England, and treated with contempt the idea of giving the government of Scotland and the care of the caſtles to the king of England. Sir Ralph Sadler, the Engliſh ambaſtador, exerted all his endeavours to induce the regent to comply with the requiſitions of his maſter; but all his intrigues were unſucceſsful; and Henry perceiving that he muſt depart from ſuch extravagant conditions, at laſt authoriſed the commiſſioners to conſent to treaties of amity and marriage, on the moſt favourable terms that could be procured. In conſequence of theſe powers given to the eommiſſioners, it was agreed that a firm peace and alliance ſhould take place between the two nations, and that they ſhould mutually defend and protect one another in caſe of an invaſion. The queen was to remain within her own dominions till ſhe was ten years of age; and Henry was not to claim any ſhare in the government. Six nobles, or their apparent heirs, were to be ſurrendered to him in ſecurity for the conveyance of the young queen into England, and for her marriage with prince Edward, as ſoon as ſhe was ten years of age. It was alſo ſtipulated, that though the queen ſhould have iſſue by Edward, Scotland ſhould retain not only its name, but its laws and liberties.</p><p>Theſe conditions, however advantageous to Scotland, yet did not give entire ſatisfaction Cardinal</p><p>Beaton, who had been impriſoned on pretence of treaſonable ſchemes, and was now releaſed from his confine, ment by the influence of the queen-dowager, took all opportunities of exclaiming againſt the alliance, as tending to deſtroy the independency of the kingdom. He pointed out to the churchmen the dangers which aroſe from the prevalence of hereſy, and urged them to unanimity and zeal. Awakening all their fears and ſelfiſhneſs, they granted him a large ſum of money with which he might gain partizans; the friars were instructed to preach againſt the treaties with England; and fanatical men were inſtructed to diſplay their rage in offering indignities to Sir Ralph Sadler.</p><p>Cardinal Beaton was not the only antagoniſt the regent had to deal with. The Earls of Argyle, Hunt- ley, Bothwel, and Murray, concurred in the oppoſition; and having collected ſome troops, and poſſeſſed themſelves of the queen’s perſon, they affirmed all the authority. They were joined by the earl of Lenox, who was made to hope that he might eſpouſe the queen- dowager and obtain the regency. He was also inclined to oppoſe the earl oſ Arran, from an ancient quarrel which had ſubſiſted between their two families; and from a claim he had to ſuperſede him, not only in the enjoyment of his perſonal eſtates, but in the ſucceſſion to the crown. The regent, alarmed at ſuch a powerful combination againſt him, inclined to attend to ſome advances which were made him by the queen- dowager and cardinal. To refuſe to confirm the treaties, after he had brought them to a concluſion, was, however, a ſtep ſo repugnant to probity, that he could not be prevailed upon to adopt it. He therefore, in a ſolemn manner, ratified them in the abbey-church of Holyroodhouſe, and commanded the great ſeal of Scotland to be appended to them. The fame day he went to St Andrew’s, and iſſued a mandate to the cardinal, requiring him to return to his allegiance. To this the prelate refuſed to pay any attention, or to move ſrom his caſtle; upon which the regent denounced him a rebel, and threatened to compel him to ſubmiſſion by military force. But in a few days after, the puſillammous regent meeting with Beaton, forſook the intereſt of Henry VIII. and embraced that of the queen-dowager and of France. Being in haſte alſo to reconcile himſelf to the church of Rome, he renounced publicly, at Stirling, the opinions of the reformed, and received abſolution from the hands of the cardinal.</p><p>By this mean-ſpirited conduct the regent expoſed himſelf to univerſal contempt, while cardinal Beaton usurped the wſhole authority. The earl of Lenox, finding that he had no hopes of ſucceſs in his ſuit to the queen dowager, engaged in negociations with Henry, to place himſelf at the head of the Scottiſh lords who were in the Engliſh intereſt, and to aſſert the cauſe of the reformation. The conſequence of all this was a rupture with England. Henry not only delayed to ratify the treaties on his part, but ordered all the Scottiſh ſhips in the harbours oſ England to be taken and confiſcated. This violent proceeding inflamed the national diſguſts againſt the Engliſh alliance; and the party of the cardinal and queen-dowager thus obtained an increaſe of popularity. Henry himſelf, however, was ſo much accuſtomed to acts of outrage and violence, that he ſeemed to think the ſtep he had juſt now takena matter of no moment; and therefore he de-</p></body></text></TEI>