<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-14T17:56:48Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>adding it to the other, which he found ready compoſed to his hand, he made it a
                complete hiſtory of the Jewiſh reſtoration.</p>
            <p>This book 13 written in Chaldee from chap. iv. 8. to chap. vii. 27. As this part of
                the work chiefly contains letters, converſations, and decrees expreſſed in that
                language, the fidelity of the hiſtorian has probably induced him to take down the
                very words which were uſed. The people, too, had been accuſtomed to the Chaldee
                during the captivity, and probably underſtood it better than Hebrew; for it appears
                from Nehemiah’s account, chap. viii. 2, 8. that all could not underſtand the
                law.</p>
            <p>The book of Nehemiah, as has been already obſerved, bears, in the Latin bibles, the
                title of the <hi rend="italic">ſecond book</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Eſdras;</hi>
                the ancient canons likewiſe give it the ſame name, becauſe, perhaps, it was
                conſidered as a ſequel to the book of Ezra. In the Hebrew bibles it has the name of
                    <hi rend="italic">Nehemiah</hi> prefixed to it; which name is retained in the
                Engliſh bible. But though that chief is by the writer of the ſecond book of
                Maccabees affirmed to have been the author of it, there cannot, we think, be a doubt
                but that either it was written at a later period, or had additions made to it after
                Nehemiah’s death.</p>
            <p>With the book of Nehemiah the hiſtory of the Old Teſtament concludes. This is
                ſuppoſed to have taken place about A. M. 3574- A. C. 434. But Prideaux with more
                probablity has fixed it at A. M. 3595. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Nehemiah.</hi></p>
            <p>It is uncertain who was the author of the book of Eſther. <hi rend="italic"
                    >Clement</hi> of Alexandria, and many commentators, have aſcribed it to
                Mordecai; and the book itſelf ſeems to favour this opinion; for we are told in chap.
                ix. 20. that “Mordecai wrote theſe things.” Others have ſuppoſed that Ezra was the
                author; but the more probable opinion of the Talmudiſts is, that the great ſynagogue
                (ſee <hi rend="smallcaps">Synagogue),</hi> to perpetuate the memory of the
                deliverance of the Jews from the conſpiracy of Hainan, and to account for the origin
                of the feaſt of Purim, ordered this book to be compoled, very likely of materials
                left by Mordecai, and afterwards approved and admitted it into the ſacred canon. The
                time when the events which it relates happened, is ſuppoſed by ſome to have been in
                the reign of Artaxerxes Longimanus, and by others in that of Darius the ſon of
                Hyſtaſpes, called by the ſacred penman <hi rend="italic">Ahaſuerus.</hi></p>
            <p>Concerning the author of the book of Job there are many different opinions. Some have
                ſuppoſed that Job himſelf wrote it in <hi rend="italic">Syriac</hi> or <hi
                    rend="italic">Arabic,</hi> and that it was afterwards tranſlated by Moſes.
                Others have thought that El<hi rend="italic">ihu</hi> wrote it; and by others it is
                aſcribed to Moſes, to Solomon, to Iſaiah, and to Ezra. To give even an abridgment of
                the arguments brought in ſupport of theſe various opinions would fill a volume, and
                at laſt leave the reader in his preſent uncertainty. He who has leiſure and
                inclination to weigh them may ſtudy the ſecond ſection of the ſixth book of
                Warburton’s Divine Legation of Moſes, together with the ſeveral works there referred
                to; but the queſtion at iſſue is of very little importance to us. The book of job,
                by whomſoever it was written, and whether it be a real hiſtory, or a dramatical poem
                founded on hiſtory, has been always eſteemed a portion of canonical ſcripture, and
                is one of the moſt ſublime compoſitions in the ſacred volume.</p>
            <p>The book of Job appears to ſtand ſingle and unparalleled in the ſacred volume. It
                ſeems to have little connection with the other writings of the Hebrews, and no
                relation whatever to the affairs of the Iſraelites. The ſcene is laid in Iduaea
                @@(H); the hiſtory of an inhabitant of that country is the baſis of the
                narrative;</p>
            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">@@@(h</hi>) “The information which the learned have endeavoured
                to collect from the writings and geography of the Greeks concerning the country and
                reſidence of Job and his friends, appears to me (lays Dr Lowth) ſo very
                inconcluſive, that I am inclined to take a quite different method for the ſolution
                of this queſtion, by applying ſolely to the Sacred Writings: the hints with which
                they have furniſhed me towards the illuſtration of this ſubject, I ſhall explain as
                briefly as poſſible.</p>
            <p>“The land of <hi rend="italic">Uz,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Gnutz,</hi> is evidently
                    <hi rend="italic">Idumae,</hi> as appears from Lam. iv. 21. <hi rend="italic"
                    >Uz</hi> was the grandſon of Seir the Horite, Gen. xxxvi. 20, 21, 28. 1. Chron.
                i. 38, 42. Seir inhabited that mountainous tract which was called by his name
                antecedent to the time of Abraham; but his poſterity being expelled, it was occupied
                by the Idumaeans: Gen. xiv. 6. Deut. ii. 12. Two other men are mentioned of the name
                    <hi rend="italic">Uz;</hi> one the grandſon of Shem, the other the ſon of
                Nachυr, the brother of Abraham; but whether any diſtrict was called after their name
                is not clear. Idumæa is a part of Arabia Petræa, ſituated on the ſouthern extremity
                of the tribe of Judah: Numb, xxxiv. 3. Joſh. xv. 1, 21. The land of Uz therefore
                appears to have been between Egypt and Philiſtia, Jer. xxv. 20. where the order of
                the places ſeems to have been accurately obſerved in reviewing the different nations
                from Egypt to Babylon; and the ſame people ſeem again to be deſcribed in exactly the
                ſame ſituations, Jer. xlvi—1.</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">“Children of the East,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Eastern
                    people,</hi> ſeems to have been the general appellation for that mingled race of
                people (as they are called, Jer. xxv. 20.) who inhabited between Egypt and the
                Euphrates, bordering upon judea from the ſouth to the call; the Idumaeans, the
                Amalekites, the Midianites, the Moabites, the Ammonites. See Judges vi. 3. and Iſa.
                xi. 14. Of theſe the Idumaeans and Amalekites certainly poſſeſſed the ſouthern
                parts. See Numb. xxxiv. 3, xiii. 29. 1 Sam. xxvii. 8, 10. This appears to be the
                true ſtate of the cale: The whole region between Egypt and Euphrates was called the
                Eaſt, at firſt in reſpect to Egypt (where the learned Joſ. Mede thinks the
                Iſraelites acquired this mode ofſpeaking. Mede’s <hi rend="italic">Works,</hi> p.
                580.), and afterwards abſolutely and without any relation to ſituation or
                circumſtances. Abraham is ſaid to have ſent the ſons of his concubines, Hagar and
                Keturah, “eaſtward, to the country which is commonly called the Eaſt." Gen. xxv. 6.
                where the name of the region ſeems to have been derived from the ſame ſituation.
                Solomon is reported “to have excelled in wiſdom all the Eaſtern people, and all
                Egypt,” 1 Kings iv. 30.; that is, all the neighbouring people on that quarter: for
                    <pb n="116"></pb>there were people beyond the boundaries of Egypt, and
                bordering on the ſouth of Judea, who were famous for wiſdom, namely, the Idumaeans
                (ſee Jer. xlix. 7. Ob, 8.), to whom we may well believe this paſſage might have ſome
                relation. Thus Jehovah addreſſes the Babylonians; “Ariſe, aſcend unto Kedar, and lay
                waſte the children of the Eaſt,” (Jer. xlix. 28). notwithſtanding theſe were really
                ſituated to the weſt of Babylon. Although Job, therefore, be accounted one of the
                orientals, it by no means follows that his reſidence muſt be in Arabia Deſerta.</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">“Eliphaz</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Temanite</hi> was the ſon of
                Eſau, and Teman the ſon of Eliphaz, (Gen. xxxvi. 10, 11.), The Eliphaz of Job was
                without a doubt of this race. Teman is certainly a city of Idumaea, (Jer. xlix, 7,
                20. Ezek. XXV. 13. Amos i. 11, 12. Ob. 8, 9.).</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">“Bildad the Shuhite: Shuah</hi> was one of the ſons of Abraham by
                Keturah, whoſe poſterity were numbered among the people of the Eaſt, and his
                ſituation was probably contiguous to that of his brother Midian, and of his nephews
                Shebah and Dedan, (ſee Gen. xxv. 2, and 3.) Dedan is a city of Idumaea (Jer. xlix.
                8.), and ſeems to have been ſituated on the eaſtern side, as Teman was on the west,
                (Ezek. xxv. 13.). From Sheba originated the Sabaeans in the paſſage from Arabia
                Felix to the Red Sea: Sheba is united to Midian (Iſa. lx. 6.); it is in the ſame
                region however with Midian, and not far from Mount Horeb, (Exod. ii. 15. iii.
                1.)</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">“Zophar</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Naamathite:</hi> among the
                cities which by lot fell to the tribe of Judah, in the neighbourhood of Idumaea,
                Naama is enumerated, (Joſh. xv. 21, 41.) Nor does this name elſewhere occur; this
                probably was the country of Zophar.</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">“Elihu</hi> the Buz<hi rend="italic">ite:</hi> Buz occurs but once
                as the name of a place or country (Jer. xxv. 23.), where it is mentioned along with
                Dedan and Thema: Dedan, as was juſt now demonſtrated, is a city of Idumæa; Thema
                belonged to the children of Iſhmael, who are ſaid to have inhabited from Havilah,
                even to Shur, which is in the diſtrict of Egypt, (Gen. xxv. 15. 18.) Saul, however,
                is ſaid to have ſmitten the Amalekites from Havilah even to Shur, which is in the
                diſtrict of Egypt, (I Sam. xv. 7.) Havilah cannot, therefore, be very far from the
                boundaries of the Amalekites; but the Amalekites never exceeded the boundaries of
                Arabia Petraea. (See Reland Palaestin. lib. i. c. xiv.) Thema, therefore, lay
                ſomewhere between Havilah and the deſert of Shur, to the ſouthward of Judea. Thema
                is alſo mentioned in connection with Sheba, (Job vi. 19.)</p>
            <p>“Upon a fair review of theſe facts, I think we may venture to conclude, ſtill with
                that modeſty which ſuch a queſtion demands, that Job was an inhabitant of Arabia
                Petraea, as well as his friends, or at leaſt of that neighbourhood. To this ſolution
                one objection may be raided: it may be aſked, How the Chaldeans, who lived on the
                borders of the Euphrates, could make depredations on the camels of Job, who lived in
                Idumaea at ſo great a diſtance? This too is thought a ſufficient cauſe for aſſigning
                Job a ſituation in Arabia Deſerta, and not far from the Euphrates. But what ſhould
                prevent the Chaldeans, as well as the Sabaeans, a people addicted to rapine, and
                roving about at immenſe diſtances for the ſake of plunder, from wandering through
                theſe defenceleſs regions, which were divided into tribes and families rather than
                into nations, and pervading from Euphrates even to Egypt? Further, I would aſk on
                the other hand, whether it be probable that all the friends of Job who lived in
                Idumaea and its neighbourhood, ſhould inſtantly be informed of all that could happen
                to Job in the deſert of Arabia and on the confines of Chaldea, and immediately
                repair thither ? Or whether it be reaſonable to think, that, ſome of them being
                inhabitants of Arabia Deſerta, it ſhould be concerted among them to meet at the
                reſidence of Job; ſince it is evident, that Eliphaz lived at Theman, in the extreme
                parts of Idumaea? With reſpect to the <hi rend="italic">Aisitas </hi>of Ptolemy (for
                ſo it is written, and not <hi rend="italic">Ausitas)</hi> it has no agreement, not
                ſo much as in a ſingle letter with the Hebrew Gnutz The LXX indeed call that country
                by the name <hi rend="italic">Ausitida,</hi> but they deſcribe it as ſituated in
                Idumaea; and they account Job himſelf an Idumaean, and a deſcendant of Eſau.” See
                the Appendix of the L<hi rend="smallcaps">XX</hi> to the book of Job, and <hi
                    rend="italic">Hyde Not.</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Peritzol.</hi> chap. xi. <hi
                    rend="italic">Lowth on Hebrew Poetry.</hi></p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
