<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:58:33Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>interſecting the plumb-lines by horizontal ones. This recourſe has, nevertheleſs, its inconveniences, ſince the ſquares formed by tranſverſal lines, that are at a diſtance from the figure (though they be exactly equal), yet repreſent the parts of the figure as greater or ſmaller, according as they are more or leſs removed from our poſition or point of view. But, notwithſtanding theſe inconveniences, the method now under conſideration is certainly the beſt that has hitherto been employed: it is</p><p>more practicable and ſure than any other we know, though it appears, from the remarks we have now been making, that it does not exhibit a ſure and univerſal criterion to a ſculptor who executes after a model.</p><p>To poliſh the ſtatue, or make the parts of it ſmooth and ſleek, they uſe pumice-ſtone and ſmelt; then tripoli; and when a ſtill greater luſtre is required, they uſe burnt ſtraw. For the <hi rend="italic">Casting of Statues,</hi> ſee <hi rend="smallcaps">FounderY</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">PLASTER oſ Paris.</hi></p><p>SCUM, properly denotes the impurities which a liquor, by boiling, caſts up to the ſurface. The term <hi rend="italic">ſcum</hi> is alſo uſed for what is more properly called the ſcoria of metals.</p><p>SCUPPERS, in a ſhip, are certain channels cut through the water-ways and ſides of a ſhip, at proper diſtances, and lined with plated lead, in order to carry the water off from the deck into the ſea. The ſcuppets of the lower deck of a ſhip of war are uſually furniſhed with a leathern pipe, called the <hi rend="italic">ſcupper-ho</hi>ſ<hi rend="italic">e,</hi> which hangs downward from the mouth or opening of the ſcupper. The intent of this is to prevent the water from entering when the ſhip inclines under a weight of  ſail.</p><p>SCURVY, in medicine, ſee that article, n⁰ 351, where we have given an account of the ſymptoms, cauſes, and modes of prevention and cure, according to ſome of the moſt eminent writers in medicine. We have here only to add, that, in the opinion oſ Dr Beddoes, the mineral acids, eſpecially the nitric and vitriolic, may be employed in the prevention or cure of this dreadful diſeaſe with as much ſucceſs as the vegetable acids.— But of all the ſubſtances that can at once be cheaply procured and long preſerved, he thinks the concrete acid of tartar by far the moſt promiſing. It is very grateful, and comes near to the citric acid. In tropical countries the ſcurvy is ſeldom known.</p><p><hi rend="italic">ScURVY-graſs,</hi> in botany. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Cochlearea.</hi></p><p>The officinalis, or common officinal ſcurvy-graſs, grows upon rocks on the ſea coaſt, and on the Highland mountains, abundantly. It has an acrid, bitter, and acid taſte, and is highly recommended for the ſcurvy. There are inſtances of a whole ſhip’s crew having been cured of that diſtemper by it; and as it abounds with acid ſalts, there can be no doubt but that it is a great reſiſter of putrefaction. The beſt way of taking it is raw in a ſalad. It is alſo diuretic, and uſeful in dropſies. The Highlanders eſteem it as a good ſtomachic.</p><p>The coronopus, another ſpecies, was ſome years ago rendered famous, the aſhes of it being an ingredient in Mrs Joanna Stephens’s celebrated medicine for the ſtone and gravel; but, unfortunately for thoſe afflicted with that excruciating complaint, it has not been able to ſupport its credit. It is acrid, and taſtes like garden creſs.</p><p>SCUTAGE <hi rend="italic">(ſcutagium,</hi> Sax. s<hi rend="italic">cildpening),</hi> was a tax or contribution raiſed by thoſe that held lands by knights ſervice, towards furniſhing the king’s army, at one, two, or three merks for every knight’s fee. Henry III. for his voyage to the Holy Land, had a tenth granted by the clergy, and <hi rend="italic">ſcutage</hi> three merks of every</p><p>knight’s ſee by the <hi rend="italic">laity.</hi> This was alſo levied by Henry II. Richard I. and King John. See <hi rend="italic smallcaps">Knight </hi><hi rend="italic">Service.</hi></p><p>SCUTE <hi rend="italic">(ſcuturn),</hi> a French gold coin of 3s. 4d. in the reign of king Henry V. Catharine queen of England had an aſſurance made her of ſundry caſtles, manors, lands, &amp;c. valued at the ſum of 40,000 ſc<hi rend="italic">utes, </hi>every two whereof were worth a noble. <hi rend="italic">Rot. Parl.</hi> 1, <hi rend="italic">Hen.</hi> VI.</p><p>SCUTELLARIA, <hi rend="smallcaps">Skull-cap,</hi> in botany: A genus of the gymnoſpermia order, belonging to the didynamia claſs of plants; and in the natural method ranking under the 40th order, <hi rend="italic">Personatae.</hi> The calyx is ſhort, tubulated, has the mouth entire, and dole after flowering. There are two ſpecies in Britain, the <hi rend="italic">galericulata</hi> and <hi rend="italic">minor.</hi> 1. The <hi rend="italic">Galericulata, Blue Skull-cap,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Hooded Willow-herb.</hi> The ſtems are weak, branched, and above a foot high; the leaves are heart-ſhaped, narrow-pointed, on ſhort foot-ſtalks, and ſcalloped; the flowers are blue, in pairs, on pedicles from the alae of the leaves, and pendulous. It grows on the banks of rivers and lakes, is bitter, and has a garlic ſmell. 2. <hi rend="italic">Minor, little red Skull-cap,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Willow-herb.</hi> The ſtalks are about eight inches high; the leaves are heart-ſhaped, oval; the flowers are purple. It grows in fens, and on the ſides of lakes.</p><p>SCUTTLES, in a ſhip, ſquare holes cut in the deck, big enough to let down the body of a man, and which ſerve upon ſome occaſions to let the people down into any room below, or from one deck to another.</p><p>SCYLAX, a celebrated mathematician and geographer of Caria, flouriſhed under the reign of Darius Hyſtaſpes, about 558 B. C. Some have attributed to him the invention of geographical tables. We have under his name a geographical work publiſhed by Hoeſchelius; but it is wirkten by a much later author, and is perhaps only an abridgment oſ Scylax’s Ancient Geography.</p><p>SCYLLA (anc. geog.), a rock in the Fretum Siculum, near the coaſt of Italy, dangerous to ſhipping, oppoſite to Charybdis, a whirlpool on the coaſt of Sicily; both of them famous in mythology.</p><p>Scylla and Charybdis have been almoſt ſubdued by the repeated convulſions of this part of the earth, and by the violence of the current, which is continually in- creaſing the breadth of the Straits. If proper allowance be made for theſe circumſtances, we ſhall acquit the ancients of any exaggeration, notwithſtanding the very dreadful colours in which they have painted this paffage. It is formed by a low peninſula, called <hi rend="italic">Cape Pelorus,</hi> ſtretching to the eaſtward on the Sicilian ſide,</p></body></text></TEI>