<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-14T17:58:38Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>diſtant countries, and renders it eaſy to tranſport the commodities of one nation to
                another, but its waters riſing in the air deſcend in ſhowers to fertiliſe the earth
                and nouriſh the vegetable kingdom, and collecting into rivers flow onwards, bringing
                fertility and wealth and commerce along with them, and again return to the ſea to
                repeat the fame round.</p>
            <p>The knowledge of this proceſs of nature might, one would think, have convinced
                philoſophers that the proportion between ſea and land continued always nearly the
                ſame. Philoſophers however have formed different theories about this as well as moſt
                other ſubjects, maintaining on the one hand that the ſea is continually encroaching
                on the land, and on the other that the land is conſtantly gaining on the ſea. Both
                ſides have ſupported their theories by arguments, demonſtrations, and
                uncontrovertible facts!</p>
            <p>The height of the mountains, ſay the philoſophers who ſupport the encroachments of
                the ſea, is continually diminiſhing; expoſed to the violence of every ſtorm, the
                hardeſt rocks muſt at laſt give way and tumble down. The rivers are continually
                ſweeping along with them particles of earth which they depoſite in the bottom of the
                ſea. Both the depth of the ocean then and the height of the dry land muſt be always
                decreaſing; the waters therefore muſt, unleſs a part of them were annihilated,
                ſpread over a greater extent of ſurface in proportion as theſe cauſes operate. This
                reaſoning, convincing as it is, might be confirmed by a great number of facts: it
                will be sufficient however to mention one or two. In the reign of Auguſtus the iſle
                of Wight made a part of Britain, ſo that the Engliſh croſſed over to it at low water
                with cart loads of tin; yet that iſland is at preſent ſeparated from Britain by a
                channel half a mile wide. The Godwin ſands on the eaſtern ſhore of England were
                formerly the fertile eſtate of earl Godwin. Nor are the encroachments of the ſea
                confined to Britain. In the bay of Baiæ near Naples there are remains of houſes and
                ſtreets ſtill viſible below the preſent level of the ſea. The ſea therefore is
                making continued encroachments upon the land; and the time will come, ſay they, when
                the waters will again cover the ſurface of the earth.</p>
            <p>Such are the arguments of thoſe philoſophers who maintain the continual encroachments
                of the ſea. Thoſe who maintain the oppoſite theory, that the land is gradually
                gaining on the ſea, though they pretend not to deny the facts advanced by their
                opponents, affirm that they are altogether inſufficient to eſtabliſh the hypotheſis
                which they were brought forward to ſupport. Though the rivers carry down particles
                of earth into the ſea, theſe, ſay they, are either accumulated on other ſhores, or,
                collecting in the bottom of the ocean, harden into ſtone, which being poſſeſſed of a
                vegetative power riſes by degrees above the ſurface of the ſea and form rocks, and
                mountains, and iſlands. The vegetative nature of ſtone indeed is ſufficient, of
                itſelf, to convince us that the quantity of earth muſt be daily accumulating, arid
                conſequently that the ſurface of the ſea is diminiſhing in extent. Celſius, a
                Swediſh philoſopher (for this diſpute has been carried on in Sweden with the
                greateſt keenneſs), has endeavoured to build this</p>
            <p>theory with more ſolid materials than vegetable ſtone. In a curious memoir, pubiſſhed
                in 1743, he aſſerts that the Baltic and the Atlantic, at leaſt that part of it which
                waſhes Norway, is conſtantly diminiſhing; and he proves this by the teſtimony of a
                great many aged pilots and fiſhermen, who affirmed that the ſea was become much
                ſhallower in many places than it had been during their youth: that many rocks
                formerly covered with water were now ſeveral feet above the ſurface of the ſea: that
                loaded veſſels uſed formerly to ride in many places where pinnaces and barks could
                now with difficulty ſwim. He produces inſtances of ancient ſea-port towns now
                ſeveral leagues from the ſhore, and of anchors and wrecks of veſſels found far
                within the country. He mentions a particular rock which 168 years before was at the
                bottom of the ſea, but was then raiſed eight feet above its ſurface. In another
                place where the water 50 years before had reached to the knee there was then none.
                Several rocks, too, which during the infancy of ſome old pilots had been two feet
                under water, were then three feet above it. From all theſe obſervations M. Celſius
                concludes, that the water of the Baltic decreaſes in height 4<hi rend="superscript"
                    >1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">2</hi> lines in a year, 4 inches 5 lines in 18
                years, 4 feet 5 inches in a hundred years, and in a thouſand years 45 feet.
                Conſcious, however, that theſe facts, how concluſive ſoever as far as relates to the
                Baltic, can never determine the general queſtion, M. Celſius advances another
                argument in ſupport of his theory. All that quantity of moiſture, ſays he, which is
                imbibed by plants is loſt to the general maſs of water, being converted into earth
                by the putrefaction of vegetables. This notion had been mentioned by Newton, and was
                adopted by Van Helmont: if granted, it follows as a conſequence that the earth is
                continually increaſing and the water diminiſhing in a very rapid degree.</p>
            <p>Such are the arguments advanced in ſupport of both theories; for it is needleſs to
                mention a notion of Linnaeus that the whole earth was formerly covered with water
                except a ſingle mountain. When fairly weighed, they amount to nothing more than
                this, that the ſea has encroached upon the land in ſome places, and retired in
                others; a concluſion which we are very willing to allow. What was advanced by thoſe
                philoſophers, who maintain that the ſea is continually encroaching on the land,
                about the depth of the ſea conſtantly diminiſhing, muſt remain a mere aſſertion till
                they prove by experiments, either that this is really the caſe, or that nature has
                no way of reſtoring thoſe particles of earth which are waſhed down by the rivers.
                Nor have they any good reaſon to affirm that the height of the mountains is
                decreaſing. Can a ſingle uncontrovertible inſtance be produced of this? Are the Alps
                or the Apennines, or Taurus, or Caucaſus, leſs lofty now than they were a thouſand
                years ago? We mean not to deny that the rain actually waſhes down particles of earth
                from the mountains, nor to affirm that the hardeſt rocks are able to refill
                continual ſtorms, nor that many mountains have ſuffered, and continue to ſuffer
                daily, from a thouſand accidents. But the effects produced by all theſe cauſes are
                ſo trifling as to be altogether imperceptible @@<hi rend="smallcaps">(a).</hi>
                Nature has aſſiduouſly guarded againſt ſuch accidents; ſhe has formed the mountains
                of the moſt dura-</p>
            <p>@@@(A). M. Gensanne pretends that the Pyrenean mountains become an inch lower every
                ten years. But even ac<pb n="191"> </pb>cording to his own calculation, it would
                require a million of years to level theſe mountains with the plain, though they
                continued to decreaſe at the ſame rate; and philoſophers tell us that this rate is
                conſtantly diminiſhing!</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
