<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:55:35Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>her ſubjects, The device of a letter from her to Bothwel completed the amazement of the queen. So unprincipled a contempt of every thing that is moſt ſacred, ſo barbarous a perſeverance in perſidiouſneſs and injuſtice, extinguiſhed every ſentiment of hope in her boſom. She conceived that ſhe was doomed to inevitable deſtruction, and ſunk under a pang of unutterable anguiſh.</p><p>The Lords Ruthven and Lindſay arrived in this paroxyſm of her diſtreſs, to inform her, that they were commanded to put in execution the order for her commitment. They charged her women to take from her all her ornaments and her royal attire. A mean dreſs was put upon her; and in this diſguiſe they conveyed her with precipitation to the priſon appointed for her. The Lords Seton, Yeſter, and Borthwick, endeavoured to reſcue her, but failed in the attempt. She was delivered over to William Douglas the governor of the caſtle of Lochleven, who had married the mother of the earl of Murray, and was himſelf nearly related to the earl of Morton. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Mary.</hi></p><p>Upon the ſame day on which the nobles ſubſcribed the order for the impriſonment of the queen, they entered into a bond of concurrence or confederacy. By this deed they bound and cemented themſelves into a body for the ſtrenuous proſecution of their quarrel; and it detailed the purpoſes which they were to forward and purſue. They propoſed to puniſh the murderers of the king, to examine into the queen’s rape, to diſſolve her marriage, to preſerve her from the bondage of Bothwel, to protect the perſon of the prince, and to reſtore juſtice to the realm. The fonction of a moſt ſolemn oath confirmed their reliance upon one another; and in advancing their meaſures, they engaged to expoſe and employ their lives, kindred, and fortunes.</p><p>It is eaſy to ſee, notwithſtanding all the pretended patriotiſm of the rebels, that nothing was farther from their intentions than to proſecute Bothwel and reſtore the queen to her dignity. They had already treated her in the vileſt manner, and allowed Bothwel to eſcape when they might eaſily have apprehended and brought him to any trial they thought proper. To exalt themſelves was their only aim. Eleven days alter the capitulation at Carberry hill, they held a convention, in which they very properly aſſumed the name of <hi rend="italic">lords oſ the ſecret council,</hi> and iſſued a proclamation for apprehending Bothwel as the murderer of the king; offering a reward of loco crowns to any perſon who ſhould bring him to Edinburgh. A ſearch had been made for the murderers of the king that very night in which the queen was confined in Lochleven caſtle. One Sebaſtian a Frenchman, and captain Blackader, were then apprehended; and ſoon after James Edmondſtone, John Blackader, and Mynart Fraſer, were taken up and impriſoned. The people expected full and ſatisfactory proofs of the guilt of Bothwel, but were diſappointed. The affirmation of the nobles, that they were poſſeſſed of evidence which could condemn him, appeared to be no better than a pretence or artifice. Sebaſtian found means to eſcape; the other perſons were put to the torture, and ſuſtained it without making any confeſſion that the nobles could publiſh. They were condemned, however, and executed, as being concerned in the murder, in their dying moments they proteſted their innocence.</p><p>A ſanguine hope was entertained that captain Blackader would reveal the whole ſecret at the place of execution, and a vaſt multitude of ſpectators were preſent. No information, however, could be derived from what he ſaid with regard to the regicides; but while he ſolemnly proteſted that his life was unjuſtly taken away, he averred it as his belief that the earls of Murray and Morton were the contrivers of the king’s murder.</p><p>The lords of the ſecret council now proceeded to the greateſt enormities. They robbed the palace of Holyroodhouſe of its furniture and decorations; converted the queen’s plate into coin; and poſſeſſed themſelves of her jewels, which were of great value; and while the faction at large committed theſe acts of robbery, the earl of Glencairn with ſolemn hypocriſy demoliſhed the altar in the queen’s chapel, and defaced and deſtroyed all its pictures and ornaments. Theſe exceſſive outrages, however, loſt them the favour of the people, and an aſſociation was formed in favour of the queen. The court of France, as ſoon as the news of Mary’s impriſonment arrived, diſpatched M. de Villeroy to condole with her upon her misfortunes: but the lords of the ſecret council would not admit him to ſee her, upon which he immediately returned to his own country. The earl of Murray, however, was at this time in France; and to the promiſes of this ambitious and treacherous wretch the king truſted, imagining him to be a ſteady friend to the unfortunate queen. Elizabeth alſo pretended friendſhip, and threatened the aſſociated lords; but as they had every reaſon to doubt her ſincerity, they paid no regard to her threats, and even refilled to admit her ambaſſador to Mary’s preſence.</p><p>From all theſe appearances of friendſhip Mary neither did nor could derive any real aſſiſtance. On the 24th of July 1567, the lord Lindſay, whoſe imperious behaviour, fays Dr Stuart, approached to inſanity, was ordered by the lords to wait upon the queen at Lochleven. He carried with him three deeds or inſtruments, and was inſtructed not to be ſparing in rudeneſs and menaces in order to compel her to ſubſcribe them. By the firſt, ſhe was to reſign her crown to her infant-ſon; by the ſecond, ſhe appointed the earl of Murray regent of Scotland; and by the third, ſhe conſtituted a council to direct the prince till this nobleman ſhould arrive in Scotland, or in the event of his death or refuſal of the office. On the part of the queen all reſiſtance was vain. Sir Robert Melvil aſſured her, that her belt friends were of opinion, that what ſhe did by compulſion, and in a priſon, could have no power to bind her; and of this ſhe was alſo aſſured by Throgmorton, the Engliſh ambaſſador, in a letter which Sir Robert Melvil brought in the ſcabbard of his ſword. Mary therefore, forlorn and helpleſs, could not reſiſt the barbarous rudeneſs with which Lindſay preſſed the ſubſcription of the papers, though ſhe would not read them. Five days after, the lords of the ſecret council met at Stirling, for the coronation of the young prince, and conſidered themſelves as repreſenting the three eſtates of the kingdom. A proteſtation was made in the name of the duke of Chatelherault, that this ſolemnity ſhould neither prejudge his rights of ſucceſſion nor thoſe of the other princes of the blood. The young prince being preſented to them, the lords Lindſay and Ruthven appeared, and in the name of the queen renounced in his favour her right and title to the crown, gave up the</p></body></text></TEI>