<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:54:13Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>with his wife, and to co-operate with the earl of Arran, who now acted as prime miniſter, as long as he ſhould oppoſe the French party. On his return, however, he found himſelf excluded from all ſhare in the government, but ſoon found means to form a ſtrong party in oppoſition to Arrau. In the mean time, ambaſſadors were ſent to the court of England, in order to treat of a perpetual peace between the two nations. At the ſame time a match was propoſed between the young king of Scotland and Henry’s daughter. This had originally been a ſcheme of Henry himſelf; but the emperor Charles V. had reſolved to outbid him, by offering James a princeſs of his own family, with an immenſe treaſure. The ambaſſadors arrived at London on the 19th of December, and found Henry very much diſpoſed both to the peace and to the match. Commiſſioners were appointed to treat of both; but they were inſtructed to demand by way of preliminary, that the Scots ſhould abſolutely renounce their league with France, and that James ſhould be ſent for education to England till he ſhould be of a proper age for marriage. The Scottiſh commiſſioners declared, that they had no inſtructions on theſe points: but one of them, the earl of Caſſils, offered to return to Scotland, and bring a definitive anſwer from the three ſtates; and in the mean time the truce was prolonged to the 15th of May 1525. On his arrival at Edinburgh, he found the earl of Angus the leading man in parliament; by whoſe influence it was determined that the Scots ſhould renounce their league with France, and ſubſtitute in place of it a ſimilar league with England; and that the king ſhould be brought up at the Engliſh court till he was of an age proper for marriage: but at the ſame time they required of Henry to break off all engagements with Charles V. who was the bitter enemy of Francis, and at that time detained him priſoner. To this the Engliſh monarch returned but a cold anſwer, being then engaged in a number of treaties with the emperor, among which one was concerning the marriage of the princeſs Mary with his imperial majeſty himſelf; however, before Caſſils returned, a truce of two years and a half was concluded between England and Scotland.</p><p>But now the queen-mother, though ſhe had always been a warm advocate for an alliance between the two nations, yet diſliked the means of bringing it about.— She ſaw her huſband’s party increaſing every day in power; ſo that now ſhe had no other reſource than in keeping poſſeſſion of the king’s perſon, whom ſhe removed to the caſtle of Edinburgh. Being now under the neceſſity of convening a parliament, it was reſolved to hold it within the caſtle; which, being an un- conſtitutional meaſure, gave a great handle to the earl of Arran and his party to complain of the innovation. They began with remonſtrances; but finding them ineffectual, they Formed a blockade of the caſtle with 2000 men, and cut off all communication with the town by means of trenches. As no proviſions could thus be got into the caſtle, the queen ordered ſome of the cannon to be turned againſt the town, in order to force the citizens to put an end to the blockade. Several ſhot were fired: but when all things appeared ready for a civil war, matters were compromiſed, though in ſuch an imperfect manner as left very little room to hope for perfect tranquillity. It was agreed, that the king ſhould remove out of the caſtle of Edinburgh to the palace of Holy-roodhouſe; from whence he ſhould repair with all poſſible magnificence to his parliament, in the houſe where it was commonly held; and there a finiſhing hand was to be put to all differences. This agreement was ſigned on the 25th of February 1526. The parliament accordingly met, and the king’s marriage with the princeſs of England was confirmed; but no mention was made of the king’s being ſent for his education into that country; on the contrary, he was committed to the care of eight lords of parliament. Theſe were to have the cuſtody of the king’s perſon, every one his month ſucceſſively, and the whole to ſtand for the government of the ſtate; yet with this limitation, “that the king, by their counſel, ſhould not ordain or determine any thing in great affairs to which the queen, as princeſs and dowager, did not give her conſent.” This partition of power, by giving the queen a negative in all public matters, ſoon threw every thing into confuſion. The earl of Angus, by leading the king into various ſcenes of pleaſure and diſſipation, ſo gained the aſcendency over him, that he became in a manner totally guided by him. The queen-mother, perceiving that ſhe could not have acceſs to her ſon, without at the ſame time being in company with her huſband, whom ſhe hated, retired ſuddenly with her domeſtics to Stirling. Thus the king was left under the ſole tuition of the earl of Angus, who made a very bad uſe of his power, engroſſing into his own hands, or thoſe of his friends, all the places of honour or profit. The archbiſhop of St Andrew’s, having now joined the king’s party, adviſed her to make a formal demand upon her huſhand, that the order of government which had been ſettled laſt parliament ſhould take place, and that under a penalty he ſhould ſet the king at liberty. To this the earl anſwered by a kind of manifeſto drawn up by his brother; in which he declared, that “the earl of Angus having been ſo highly favoured by his good uncle the king of England, and that James himſelf being under great obligations to him, neither the queen nor the other lords need be in any pain about him, as he choſe to ſpend his time with the earl of Angus rather than with any lord in the kingdom.” James himſelf, however, had diſcernment ſuſſicient to perceive, that, notwithſtanding all the fair pretences of the earl of Angus, he was in fact no better than his priſoner; and reſolved to attempt the recovery of his liberty. The earls of Argyle and Arran had for ſome time retired from court, where they had no ſhare in the adminiſtration, and were living on their own eſtates; but the earl of Lenox diſſembled his∙ ſentiments ſo well, that he was neither ſuſpected by the earl of Angus, nor any of the Douglas family, who were his partiſans. The king being gained upon by his inſinuating behaviour, opened his mind to him, and requeſted his aſſiſtance againſt his treacherous keepers. At the ſame time he ſent letters to his mother, and the heads of her party, by ſome of his domeſtics whom Lenox had pointed out, intreating them to remove him from the carl, and not ſuffer him any longer to remain under his imperious juriſdiction; adding, that if this could not be done by any other means, they ſhould uſe force of arms.</p><p>On receiving this letter, the queen and her party aſſembled their forces at Stirling, and without loſs of time began their march for Edinburgh. Angus, on the other hand, prepared to give them a warm recep-</p></body></text></TEI>