<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-14T17:57:01Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>bol for deſtruction by war. The <hi rend="italic">aſcent of ſmoke</hi> from any thing
                burning for ever, denotes the continuance of a people under ſlavery. <hi
                    rend="italic">Riding in the clouds,</hi> ſignifies reigning over many ſubjects.
                    <hi rend="italic">Tempestuous winds,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">motion of the
                    clouds,</hi> denote wars. <hi rend="italic">Thunder</hi> denotes the noiſe of
                multitudes. <hi rend="italic">Fountains oſ waters</hi> expreſs cities, <hi
                    rend="italic">Mountains and islands,</hi> cities with the territories belonging
                to them. <hi rend="italic">Houſes and ſhips</hi> ſtand for families, aſſemblies, and
                towns. A <hi rend="italic">forest</hi> is put for a kingdom. A <hi rend="italic"
                    >wilderneſs</hi> for a nation much diminiſhed in its numbers.</p>
            <p>Animals, as a <hi rend="italic">lion, bear, leopard, goat,</hi> are put for kingdoms
                or political communities correſponding to their reſpective characters. When a man or
                beaſt is put for a kingdom, the head repreſents thoſe who govern; the tail thoſe who
                are governed; the <hi rend="italic">horns</hi> denote the number of military powers
                or ſtates that riſe from the head. <hi rend="italic">Seeing</hi> ſignifies
                underſtanding; <hi rend="italic">eyes</hi> men of underſtanding; the <hi
                    rend="italic">mouth</hi> denotes a lawgiver; the <hi rend="italic">arm oſ a
                    man</hi> is put for power, or for the people by whoſe ſtrength his power is
                exerciſed; fe<hi rend="italic">et</hi> repreſent the loweſt of the people.</p>
            <p>Such is the preciſion and regularity of the prophetic language, which we learn to
                interpret by comparing prophecies which are accompliſhed with the facts to which
                they correſpond. So far is the ſtudy of it carried already, that a dictionary has
                been compoſed to explain it; and it is probable, that in a ſhort time it may be ſo
                fully underſtood, that we ſhall find little difficulty in explaining any prophecy.
                But let us not from this expect, that the prophecies will enable us to penetrate the
                dark clouds of futurity: No! The difficulty of applying prophecies to their
                correſponding events, before completion, will ſtill remain unſurmountable. Thoſe
                men, therefore, however pious and well- meaning they may be, who attempt to explain
                and apply prophecies which are not yet accompliſhed, and who delude the credulous
                multitude by their own romantic conjectures, cannot be acquitted of raſhneſs and
                preſumption.</p>
            <p>The predictions of the prophets, according to the opinion of Dr Lowth, are written in
                a poetic ſtyle. They poſſeſs indeed all the characteriſtics of Hebrew poetry, with
                the ſingle exception, that none of them are alphabetical or acroſtic, which is an
                artificial ar</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">rangement utterly repugnant to the nature of prophecy.</hi></p>
            <p>The other arguments, however, ought to be particularly adverted to upon this ſubject:
                the poetic dialect, for inſtance, the diction ſo totally different from the language
                oſ common life, and other ſimilar circumſtances, which an attentive reader will
                eaſily diſcover, but which cannot be explained by a few examples; for circumſtances
                which, taken ſeparately, appear but of ſmall account, are in a united view
                frequently of the greateſt importance. To theſe we may add the artificial
                conformation of the ſentences; which are a neceſſary concomitant of metrical
                compoſition, the only one indeed which is now apparent, as it has always appeared to
                us.</p>
            <p>The order in which the books of the minor prophets are placed is not the fame in the
                Septuagint as in the Hebrew @@*. According to the latter, they ſtand as in our
                tranſlation; but in the Greek, the ſeries is altered as to the ſix firſt, to the
                following arrangement: Hoſea, Amos, Micah, Joel, Obadiah, Jonah. This change,
                however, is of no conſequence, ſince neither in the original, nor in the Septuagint,
                are they placed with exact regard to the time in which their ſacred authors
                reſpectively flouriſhed.</p>
            <p>The order in which they ſhould ſtand, if chronologically arranged, is by Blair and
                others ſuppoſed to be as follows: Jonah, Amos, Hoſea, Micah, Nahum, Joel, Zephaniah,
                Habbakuk, Obadiah, Haggai, Zechariah, Malachi. And this order will he found to be
                generally conſiſtent with the periods to which the Prophets will be reſpectively
                aſſigned in the following pages, except in the inſtance of Joel, who probably
                flouriſhed rather earlier than he is placed by theſe chronologers. The preciſe
                period of this prophet, however, cannot be aſcertained; and ſome diſputes might be
                maintained concerning the priority of others alſo, when they were nearly
                contemporaries, as Amos and Hoſea; and when the firſt prophecies of a later prophet
                were delivered at the ſame time with, or previous to, thoſe of a prophet who was
                called earlier to the ſacred office. The following ſcheme, however, in which alſo
                the greater prophets will be introduced, may enable the reader more accurately to
                comprehend the actual and relative periods in which they ſeverally propheſied.</p>
            <p>The <hi rend="smallcaps">Prophets</hi> in their ſuppoſed Order of Time, arranged
                according to Blair’s Tables@@* with but little Variation.</p>
            <table>
                <row>
                    <cell></cell>
                    <cell>Before Chriſt.</cell>
                    <cell>Kings of Judah.</cell>
                    <cell>Kings of Iſrael.</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Jonah,</cell>
                    <cell>Between 856 and 784.</cell>
                    <cell></cell>
                    <cell>Jehu, and Jehoahaz, according to Lloyd; but Joaſh and Jeroboam the Second
                        according to Blair.</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Amos,</cell>
                    <cell>Between 810 and 785,</cell>
                    <cell>Uzziah, ch. i. 1.</cell>
                    <cell>Jeroboam the Second, chap. i. 1.</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell> Hoſea,</cell>
                    <cell>Between 810 and 725.</cell>
                    <cell>Uzziah, Jotham, Ahaz, the third year of Hezekiah.</cell>
                    <cell>Jeroboam the Second, chap. i. 1.</cell>
                </row>
            </table>
            <p>@@@[m]* Chronology of the Prophets.</p>
            <p>@@@[m]* Bishop Newcomb's Version of Minor Prophets, Preface, p. 43.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
