<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:54:12Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ſtrated, but without effect; and as the malcontents continued obſtinate, he was in danger of being left by himſelf, when the queen-mother interpoſed, and prevailed upon Lord Dacres to agree to a conference, the event of which was a renewal of the negociations for peace.</p><p>The regent perceiving, by the diſgrace of this expedition, that he had loſt his former popularity, determined to revenge himſelf; and therefore told thoſe whom he could truſt, that he was about to return to France, from whence he ſhould bring ſuch a force by ſea and land, as ſhould render it unneceſſary for him to aſk leave of the Scots any more to invade England. Accordingly he embarked for France on the 25th of October, but publicly gave out that he would return the enſuing Auguſt.</p><p>On the regent’s arrival in France, he made a demand of 10,000 foot and 5000 horſe for carrying on the war againſt England; but the ſituation of King Francis did not then allow him to ſpare ſo many at once, though he was daily ſending over ſhips with men, ammunition, and money, for the French garriſons in Scotland. At laſt it was publicly known in England that the regent was about to return with a ſtrong fleet, and 4000 of the beſt troops in France; upon which Henry determined, if poſſible, to intercept him. Sir William Fitz-Williams, with 36 large ſhips, was ordered to block up the French ſquadron in the harbour of Finhead; Sir Anthony Poyntz cruized with another in the weſtern ſeas, as Sir Chriſtopher Dow and Sir Henry Shireburn did in the northern with a third ſquadron. The duke of Albany, being unable to cope with Fitz-Williams, was obliged to ſet out from another port with I 2 ſhips, having ſome troops on board. They fell in with Fitz-Williams’s ſquadron; two of their ſhips were ſunk, and the reſt driven back to Dieppe. Fitz-Williams then made a deſeent at Treport, where he burnt 18 French ſhips, and returned to his ſtation off Finhead. By this time the French had given the duke ſuch a reinforcement as made him an overmatch for the Engliſh admiral, had the men been equally good; but the regent had no dependence upon French ſailors when put in competition with the Engliſh. Inſtead of coming to an engagement, therefore, as ſoon as Fitz-Williams appeared, he diſembarked his ſoldiers, as if he had intended to delay his expedition for that year; but a ſtorm ſoon ariſing, which obliged the Engliſh fleet to return to the Downs, the regent took that opportunity of reimbarking his men, and failing by the weſtern coaſts, arrived ſafe in Scotland.</p><p>All this time the earl of Surry had been carrying on the moſt cruel and deſtructive war againſt Scotland; inſomuch that, according to Cardinal Wolſey, “there was left neither houſe, ſortreſs, village, tree, cattle, corn, nor other ſnccour for man,” in the countries of Tweed- dale and March. The regent’s return did not immediately put a ſtop to theſe devaſtations; for the inteſtine diviſions in Scotland prevented him from taking the field. His party was weakened by his long abſence, and the queen-mother had been very active ſtrengthening the Engliſh intereſt. A parliament was called in 1521, where it was debated, Whether peace or war with England ſhould be reſolved on? and the  determinations of this parliament were evidently on the worſt fide of the queſtion. Henry was at this time ſo</p><p>well dispoſed to cultivate a friendſhip with Scotland, that he offered to James his eldeſt filter Mary in marriage; but the Scots, animated by the appearance of their French auxiliaries, and corrupted by their gold, rejected all terms, and reſolved upon war. However, when the army was aſſembled, and had advanced to the borders, he found the ſame difficulty he had formerly experienced; for they flatly refuſed to enter England With great difficulty he prevailed upon part of the army to paſs the Tweed; but not meeting with ſucceſs, he was obliged to return to Scotland, which at this time was divided into four factions. One of theſe was headed by the regent, another by the queen, a third by the earl of Arran, and a fourth by the earl of Angus, who had lived as an exile under Henry’s protection. Had it been poſſible for the earl of Angus and his wife to have been reconciled to each other, it would have been much for the intereſt of the kingdom; but all the art even of Cardinal Wolſey could not effect this. At laſt, the duke of Albany, finding all parties united againſt him, reſigned his office of regent of Scotland. On the 14th of March that year, he went on board one of his own ſhips for France, from whence he never returned to Scotland. He did not indeed make a formal abdication of his government; ſo far from that, he requeſted the nobility, whom he convened for that purpoſe, to enter into no alliance with England during his abſence, which he ſaid would continue no longer than the firſt of September following; to make no alteration in the government; and to keep the king at Stirling.</p><p>The nobility, who were impatient for the abſence of the regent, readily promiſed whatever he required, but without any intention of performing it: nor, indeed, was it in their power to comply; for it had been previouſly determined that James himſelf ſhould now take the adminiſtration into his own hands. According to Buchanan, the regent had no ſooner returned to France than Scotland relapſed into all the miſeries of anarchy. The queen-dowager had the management of public affairs, but her power was limited. The earl of Arran, apprehending danger from the Engliſh, entered into the views of the French party. The queen-mother’s diſlike to her huſband continued as great as ever, which prevented an union among thoſe who were in the Engliſh intereſt; and Wolſey took that opportunity of reſtoring the earl of Angus to all his importance in Scotland.— The queen-mother, therefore, had no other way left to keep herſelf in power, but to bring James himſelf into action. On the 29th of July, therefore, he removed from Stirling to the abbey of Holyroodhouſe; where he took upon himſelf the exerciſe of government, by convoking the nobility, and obliging them to ſwear allegiance to his perſon a ſecond time. The truce with England was now prolonged, and the queen’s party carried all before them. On the very day in which the laſt truce was ſigned with England, the carl of Angus entered Scotland. He had been invited from his exile in France into England, where he was careſſed by Henry, who diſregarded all his ſiſter’s intreaties to lend him back to France, and now reſolved to ſupport him in Scotland. Yet, though his declared intention in ſending the earl to Scotland was, that the latter might balance the French party there, the king enjoined him to ſue, in the moſt humble manner, for a reconciliation</p></body></text></TEI>