<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:55:10Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>into him other sentiments than gratitude and reverence, He could not behold her charms without feeling their power: and inſtead of ſtifling in its birth the moſt dangerous of all the paſſions, he encouraged its growth. In an unhappy moment, he entered her apartment; and, concealing himſelf under her bed, waited the approach of night. While the queen was undreſſing, her maids diſcovered his ſituation, and gave her the alarm. Chatelard was diſmiſſed with diſgrace; but ſoon after received her pardon. The frenzy, however, of his love compelling him to repeat his crime, it was no longer proper to ſhow any compaſſion to him. The delicate ſituation of Mary, the noiſe of theſe adventures, which had gone abroad, and the rude ſuſpicions of her ſubjects, required that he ſhould be tried for his offences and puniſhed. This imprudent man was accordingly condemned to loſe his head; and the ſentence was put in execution.</p><p>The diſagreeable circumſtances in which Mary found herſelf involved by reaſon of her quarrel with Elizabeth, the exceſſive bigotry and overbearing ſpirit of her Proteſtant ſubjects, together with the adventure of Chatelard, and the calumnies propagated in conſequence of it, determined her to think of a ſecond marriage. Her beauty and expectations of the crown of England, joined to the kingdom which ſhe already poſſeſſed, brought her many ſuitors. She was addreſſed by the king of Sweden, the king of Navarre, the prince of Conde, the duke of Ferrara, Don Carlos of Spain, the arch-duke Charles of Auſtria, and the duke of Anjou. Her own inclination was to give the preference, among theſe illuſtrious lovers, to the prince of Spain; but her determination, from the firſt moment, was to make her wiſhes bend to other conſiderations, and to render her deciſion upon this important point as agreeable as poſſible to queen Elizabeth, to the Engliſh nation, and to the Proteſtants in both kingdoms. Her ſucceſſion to the crown of England was the object neareſt her heart; and Elizabeth, who wiſhed to prevent her from marrying altogether, contrived to impreſs upon her mind an opinion that any foreign alliance would greatly obſtruct that much deſired event. She therefore pitched upon two of her own ſubjects, whom ſhe ſucceſſively recommended as fit matches for the queen of Scots; and ſhe promiſed, that upon her acceptance of either of them, her right of inheritance ſhould be inquired into and declared. Lord Robert Dudley, afterwards earl of Leiceſter, was the firſt perſon propoſed; and except a manly face and fine figure he had not one quality that could recommend him to the Scottiſh princeſs. Whilſt Mary received this ſuitor with ſome degree of compoſure, ſhe did not altogether repreſs her ſcorn. “She had heard good accounts (ſhe owned) of the gentleman; but as queen Elizabeth had ſaid, that in propoſing a huſband to her, ſhe would conſult her honour, ſhe aſked what honour there could be in marrying a ſubject The Engliſh queen then brought under the eye of Mary another ſuitor, left her thoughts ſhould return to a foreign alliance. This was lord Darnley, of the houſe of Stuart itſelf, whoſe birth was alrnoſt equal to her own, and whom the Scottiſh princeſs was induced to accept as a huſband by motives which we have detailed elſewhere.</p><p>(ſee <hi rend="smallcaps">Mary.)</hi> Elizabeth however was not more ſincere in this propoſal than in the former; for after permitting Darnley and his father the earl of Lenox to viſit Scotland merely with the view of diverting the attention of the Queen from the continent, ſhe threw every obſtacle in the way of the marriage which art and violence could contrive. When ſhe found Mary ſo much entangled, that ſhe could hardly draw back, or make any other choice than that of Darnley, Elizabeth attempted to prevent her from going farther on; and now intimated her diſapprobation of that marriage, which ſhe herſelf had not only originally planned, but, in theſe latter ſtages, had forwarded by every means in her power. The whole council of Elizabeth declared againſt the marriage. Even from her own ſubjects Mary met with conſiderable oppoſition. An inveterate enmity had taken place between the duke of Chatelherault and the earl of Lenox, in conſequencc of which the former deſerted the court, and very few of the Hamiltons repaired to it. The lord James Stuart, now earl of Murray, fought to promote the match with lord Dudley, In conſequencc of this he was treated openly with diſreſpect by the earl of Lenox; lie loſt the favour of his ſovereign, and Darnley threatened him with his vengeance when he ſhould be married to the queen. John Knox in the mean time behaved in the moſt furious manner, forgetting not only the meek and peaceable behaviour of a Chriſtian, but the allegiance of a ſubject. This preacher even interfered with the marriage of his ſovereign. He warned the nobility, that if they allowed a Papiſt or an infidel to obtain her perſon and the government of Scotland, they would be guilty, to the full extent of their power, of baniſhing Jeſus Chriſt from the kingdom, of bringing down upon it the vengeance of God, of being a curſe to themſelves, and of depriving their queen of all comfort and conſolation. As Darnley was a Papiſt, he was of conſequence execrated by the whole body of Proteſtants, laity as well as clergy; while, on the other hand, he was ſupported by the earls of Athol and Caithneſs, the lords Ruthven and Hume, and the whole Popiſh faction.</p><p>It was exceedingly unfortunate for the queen, that neither lord Darnley himſelf, nor his father the earl of Lenox, had any talents for buſineſs; and as they naturally had the direction of the queen’s affairs, it is no wonder that they were very ill managed. But a ſource of oppoſition, more violent than any imperfections of their own, roſe up to them in the attachment which they diſcovered to a perſon upon whom the queen had of late beſtowed her favour with an imprudent prodigality. David Rizzio from a mean origin raiſed himſelf to a diſtinguiſhed eminence. He was born at Turin, where his father earned a ſubſiſtence as a muſician. Varieties of ſituation and adventure, poverty, and misfortunes, had taught him experience. In the train of the count de Morette, the ambaſſador from the duke of Savoy, he had arrived in Scotland. The queen, deſirous to complete her band of muſic, admitted him into her ſervice. In this humble ſtation he had the dexterity to attract her attention; and her French ſecretary falling into diſgrace, from negligence and incapacity, he was promoted to diſcharge the duties of his office. A neceſſary and frequent admiſſion to her company afforded him now the fulleſt opportunity to recommend himſelf to her; and while ſhe approved his manners, ſhe was ſenſible of his fidelity and his talents. His mind, however, was not ſufficiently vigorous to bear with ſucceſs and proſperity. Ambition grew upon him with preferment. He</p></body></text></TEI>