<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:54:03Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>formed to appear like St Andrew, the apoſtle of Scotland, as he is repreſented in painting and ſculpture. The church being crowded, this perfſonage, with ſome difficulty, made his way to the king’s ſeat; and leaning over it, he ſpoke to the following purpoſe: “Sir (ſaid he), I am ſent hither to intreat you for this time to delay your expedition, and to proceed no farther in your intended journey: for if you do, you ſhall not proſper in your enterpriſe, nor any of your followers. I am further charged to warn you, if ye be ſo refractory as to go forward, not to uſe the acquaintance, company, or counſel of women, as ye tender your honour, life, and eſtate.” After delivering thoſe words, he retired through the crowd, and was no more ſeen, though, when the ſervice was ended, James earneſtly inquired after him.</p><p>That this ſcene was acted, ſeems to be paſt diſpute; for Sir David Lindſay, who was then a young man, and preſent in the church, reported it both to Buchanan and Lindſay the hiſtorian. It is, however, equally certain, that the whole was a contrivance of the queen, to whoſe other afflictions the ſtings of jealouſy were now added. In one of the Scotch inroads into England, one Heron, the proprietor of the caſtle of Ford, had been taken priſoner, and ſent to Scotland; where he was detained on a charge of murder, of which he ſeems to have been innocent. The Engliſh hiſtorians mention this as having paſſed after James entered England: but from the latter part of the ſuppoſed phantom’s ſpeech, it is probable that it happened before; and that Heron’s wife and beautiful daughter had been for ſome time ſoliciting James for his deliverance. Be that as it may, it is too probable that James was ſmitten with the charms of the daughter; and that her mother, who was a moſt artful woman, knew how to avail herſelf of the conqueſt. Pretending that ſhe had intereſt enough to procure the releaſe of the lord Johnſton and Alexander Home, who were priſoners in England, ſhe was permitted by James to keep a conſtant correſpondence with the earl of Surry, to whom ſhe is ſaid to have betrayed all James’s ſecrets and meaſures. The rendezvous of James’s army was at the Burrowmoor, to which James repaired; and having given orders for the march of his artillery, he lodged at the abbey of Holyroodhouſe. While he was there, another attempt was made to divert him from his purpoſe of invading England: but James, deaf to all the ſolicitations and inventions of his queen, muſtered his army; and on the 22d of Auguſt he paſſed the Tweed, encamping that night near the banks of the Twiſſel. On his arrival at Twiſſelhaugh on the 14th, he called an aſſembly of his lords together, and made a declaration, that the heirs of all ſuch as ſhould die in the army, or be killed by the enemy during his flay in England, ſhould have their wards, relief, and marriages of the king; who, upon that account, diſpenſed with their age. This is ſaid to have been the criſis of that prince’s fate. Abandoned to his paſſion for his Engliſh miſtreſs, ſhe prevailed with him, at her mother’s inſtigation, to trifle away his time for ſome days; during which internal, the junction of the Engliſh army was formed. The earl of Surry, the Engliſh general, was then at Pomfret: but ordered the landholders of the neighbouring counties to certify to him in writing what number of men each could furniſh, charging them to</p><p>be ready at an hour’s warning; and he laid his plan ſo, as not to bring his army into the field till James had advanced ſo ſar into England as to render it very difficult for him to retire without a general battle. This precaution aſſiſted the lady Ford (as ſhe is called) in perſuading James that there was no danger in the delay, becauſe the Engliſh had not the face of an army in the field.</p><p>In the mean time, the earl of Surry ordered the governors of Berwick and Norham, the two ſtrongeſt places on the frontiers of England, to prepare for a vigorous reſiſtance in caſe they were attacked; and directed them to certify how long they could hold out, in hopes, that if they made a reſolute defence, James would march on; and leave them in his rear, The governor of Norham’s anſwer was, that his caſtle was ſo well provided, as to leave him no doubt, in caſe of a ſiege, to be able to defend it till king Henry ſhould return from abroad, and relieve it in perſon. James, however, beſieged it on the 25th of Auguſt, and battered it ſo furiouſly, that he took it by capitulation the ſixth day after. James then proceeded to the caſtle of Etal belonging to the family of Manners (now duke of Rutland); which he took and demoliihed likewiſe, as he alſo did Wark, and arrived before the caſtle of Ford. The Scotch army is generally allowed to have conſiſted of at leaſt 50,000 men when it paſſed the Tweed. At this time it was encamped on the heights of Cheviot, in the heart of a country naturally barren, and now deſolate through the precautions taken by the Engliſh general. Being obliged to extend their quarters for the benefit of ſubſiſtence, the mercenary part of them had acquired a conſiderable plunder, with which, as uſual, they retired to their own country, as many more did for want of ſubfiſtence. The earl of Surry knew their ſituation, and ordered the rendezvous of his army, firſt at Newcaſtle, and then near Norham, having certain intelligence of the vaſt deſertions daily happening in the Scotch army, which had reduced it greatly. The wetneſs of the ſeaſon rendered his march, eſpecially that of the artillery, extremely difficult; but being joined by ſeveral perſons of diſtinction, he marched on the 3d of September to Alnwic, where he was reinforeed by 5000 hardy veteran troops, ſent from the Engliſh army on the continent, under the command of his ſon the lord admiral of England; ſo that the Engliſh authors admit his army to have conſiſted of 26,000 men, all completely armed and provided for the field. James having, in the manifeſto which he diſperſed on his entering England, given the death of Barton as one of the cauſes of his invaſion, the lord-admiral had prevailed with Henry to ſend him upon this ſervice; and he informed James by a letter, that he intended to juſtify the death of that pirate in the front of the Engliſh army.</p><p>By this time the army of James was, by deſertion and other cauſes, reduced to leſs than half its numbers; but the chief misfortune attending it was his own conduct. His indolence and inactivity, joined to the ſcandalous examples of his amours, at ſuch a ſeaſon, had diſguſted ſeveral of his greateſt men and beſt friends; and ſome of them more than ſuſpected a correſpondence between the Engliſh lady and the earl of Surry. James was deaf to all their remonſtrances; and the earl of Angus declared, that he was reſolved to return home, as he ſoreſaw that the ruin of the army was inevitable</p></body></text></TEI>