<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:55:22Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>clamations were therefore iſſued by the queen to call her ſubjects to arms; and ſhe proceeded to Jedburgh, to hold juſtice-courts, and to puniſh traitors and diſorderly perſons. In the courſe of this journey ſhe was taken dangerouſly ill; inſomuch that, believing her death to be at hand, ſhe called for the biſhop of Roſs, telling him to bear witneſs, that ſhe had perſevered in that religion in which ſhe had been nouriſhed and brought up; taking the promiſe of her nobles, that after her death they would open her laſt will and teſtament, and pay the reſpect to it that conſiſted with the laws; recommending to them the rights of her infant ſon, and the charge of educating him in ſuch a manner as might enable him to rule the kingdom of his anceſtors with honour; and intreating them to abſtain from all cruelty and perſecution of her Roman Catholic ſubjects. Not- withſtanding her apprehenſions, however, and the extreme violence of her diſtemper, the queen at laſt recovered perfect health. As ſoon as ſhe was able to travel, ſhe viſited Kelſo, Werk caille, Hume, Langton, and Wedderburn. The licentious borderers, on the firſt news of her recovery, laid down their arms. Being deſirous to take a view of Berwick, the queen advanced to it with an attendance of 1000 horſe. Sir John Forſter, the deputy warden of the Engliſh marches, came forth with a numerous retinue, and conducted her to the moſt proper ſtation for ſurveying it, and paid her all the honours in his power, by a full diſcharge of the artillery, and other demonſtrations of joy. Continuing her journey, ſhe paſſed to Eymouth, Dunbar, and Tantallon; proceeding thence to Craigmillar caſtle, where ſhe propoſed to remain till the time of the baptiſm of the prince, which was ſoon to be celebrated at Stirling.</p><p>During the ſevere ſickneſs of the queen, her huſband kept himſelf at a diſtance: but when ſhe was ſo far recovered as to be out of danger, he made his appearance; and being received with ſome coldneſs and formality, he retired ſuddenly to Stirling. This cruel neglect was a moſt ſenſible mortification to her; and while ſhe ſuffered from his ingratitude and haughtineſs, ſhe was not without ſuſpicions that he was attempting to diſturb the tranquillity of her government. She was ſeized with a ſettled melancholy; and, in her anguiſh, often wiſhed for death to put a period to her exiſtence. Her nobles, who were caballing againſt her, remarked her condition, and took advantage of it. Bothwel, who had already recommended himſelf by his ſervſees, redoubled his efforts to heighten the favour which theſe ſervices had induced her to conceive for him. At this time, it is probable, he ſought to gain the affection of the queen, with a view to marry her himſelf, providing a divorce from her huſband could be obtained, which was now become the ſubject of conſultation by Murray and his aſſociates. After much deliberation, the queen herſelf was acquainted with this project; and it was told her, that provided ſhe would pardon the earl of Morton and his aſſociates, the means ſhould be found of effectuating the divorce. This was urged as a matter of ſtate by the earls of Murray, Lethington, Argyle, and Huntley; and the queen was invited to conſider it as an affair which might be managed without any interference on her part. The queen replied, that ſhe would liſten to them, upon condition that the divorce could be ob</p><p>tained according to the laws, and that it ſhould not be any way prejudicial to her ſon: but if they meant to operate their purpoſe by a diſregard to theſe points, they muſt not think any more of it; for rather than conſent to their views, ſhe would endure all the torments, and abide by all the perils, to which her ſituation expoſed her.</p><p>Lethington upon this, in the name of the reſt, engaged to make her quit of her huſband, without prejudice to her ſon; words which could not be underſtood otherwiſe than as pointing at murder. Lord Murray (added he), who is here preſent, ſcrupulous as he is, will connive; and behold our proceedings without opening his lips. The queen immediately made anſwer, “I deſire that you will do nothing from which any ſtain may be fixed upon my honour or conſcience; and I therefore require the matter to reſt as it is, till God of his goodneſs ſend relief: What you think to be of ſervice to me may turn out to my diſpleafure and harm.”</p><p>It appears, however, that from this moment a plot was formed by Murray, Bothwel, and Lethington, againſt the life of Darnley, and by ſome of them probably againſt the queen herſelf; and that Morton, who with the other conſpirators againſt Rizzio had received a pardon, was cloſely aſſociated with them in their nefarious deſigns. That profligate peer was, in his way to Scotland, met at Whittingham by Bothwel and the ſecretary. They propoſed to him the murder of the king, and required his aſſiſtance, alleging that the queen herſelf conſented to the deed; to which Mot ton by his own account replied, that he was diſpoſed to concur, provided he were ſure of acting under any authority from her; but Bothwel and Lethington having returned to Edinburgh, on purpoſe to obtain ſuch an authority, ſent him back a meſſage, That the queen would not permit any conversation upon that matter.</p><p>In the mean time, preparations were made for the baptiſm of the young prince; to aſſiſt at which the queen left Craigmillar and went to Stirling. The ceremony was performed on the 17th of December 1566. After the baptiſmal rites were performed, the name and titles of the prince were three times proclaimed by the heralds to the found of trumpets. He was called and deſigned, Charles James, James Charles, prince and Steward of Scotland, duke of Rotheſay, earl of Carrick, lord of the Iſles, and baron of Renfrew. Amidſt the ſcenes of joy diſplayed on this occaſion, the king ſhowed his folly more than he had done before. As Elizabeth did not mean to acknowledge him in his ſovereign capacity, it was neither conſiſtent with the dignity of the queen, nor his own, that he ſhould be preſent at the baptiſm. He did not indeed preſent himſelf either at the ceremony or the entertainments and maſquerades with which it was accompanied. At this juncture, however, though he had often kept at a greater diſtance before, he took up his residence at Stirling, as if he had meant to offend the queen, and to expoſe their quarrels to the world. Du Croc, who was inclined to be favourable to him, was ſo ſtruck with the impropriety of his behaviour, that he affected to have inſtructions from France to avoid all intercourſe with him: and when the king propoſed to pay him a viſit, he took the liberty to inform him, that there were two paſſages in his chamber; and that if his</p></body></text></TEI>