<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:55:39Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>queen of Scots might not be allowed to take a voyage into France. But all the pretenſions which had hitherto threatened the crown of Elizabeth would in this caſe be revived. A ſtrong reſentment to her would even urge Mary and Charles IX. to the boldeſt and moſt deſperate enterpriſes. The party of the queen of Scots in England, ſtrong from motives of religion and affection, and from diſcontents and the love of change, would ſtimulate their anger and ambition. England had now no territories in France. A war with that country and with Scotland would involve the greateſt dangers. Upon revolving theſe meaſures and topics, Elizabeth and her counſellors were induced to conclude, that it was by far the wiſeſt expedient to keep the queen of Scots in confinement, to invent methods to augment her diſtreſs, to give countenance to the regent, and to hold her kingdom in dependence and ſubjection.</p><p>In conſequence of this cruel and unjuſt reſolution, Mary was acquainted, that ſhe could not be admitted into Elizabeth’s preſence till ſhe had clearcd herſelf of the crimes imputed to her; ſhe was warned not to think of introducing French troops into Scotland; and it was hinted, that for the more ſecurity ſhe ought to be removed farther from the frontier. This meſſage at once ſhowed Mary the imprudence of her conduct in truſting herſelf to Elizabeth. But the error could not now be remedied. She was watched to prevent her eſcape, and all her remonſtrances were vain. The earl of Murray had offered to accuſe her; and it was at laſt concluded that Elizabeth could not, conſiſtently with her own honour and the tranquillity of her government, ſuffer the queen of Scots to come into her preſence, to depart out of England, or to be reſtored to her dignity, till her cauſe ſhould be tried, and decided. An order was given to remove her from Carliſle caille to a place of ſtrength at a greater diſtance from the borders, to confine her more cloſely, and to guard againſt all poſſibility of an eſcape.</p><p>In conſequence of theſe extraordinary tranſactions, a trial took place, perhaps the moſt remarkable for its injuſtice and partiality of any recorded in hiſtory. Mary, confined and apprehenſive, ſubmitted to be tried as they thought proper. The regent, who was to be the accuſer, was ſummoned. into England, and commiſſioners were appointed on both ſides. On the 4th of October, the commiſſioners met at York; and four  days after, the deputies of the queen of Scots were called to make known their complaints. They related the moſt material circumſtances of the cruel uſage ſhe had received. Their accuſations were an alarming introduction to the buſineſs in which the regent had embarked; and notwithſtanding the encouragement ſhown to him by Elizabeth, he was aſſaulted by apprehenſions. The artifices of Maitland added to his alarms. Inſtead of proceeding inſtantly to defend himſelf, or to accuſe the queen, he fought permiſſion to relate his doubts and ſcruples to the Engliſh commiſſioners. In his own name, and with the concurrence of his aſſociates, he demanded to know whether they had ſufficient authority from Elizabeth to pronounce, in the caſe of the murder, Guilty or not guilty, according to the evidence that ſhould be laid before them; whether they would actually exerciſe this power; whether, in the event of her criminality, their ſovereign ſhould be deli</p><p>vered to him and his friends, or detained in England in ſuch a way as that no danger ſhould enſue from her activity; and whether, upon her conviction, the queen of England would allow his proceedings, and thoſe of his party, to be proper, maintain the government of the young king, and ſupport him in the regency in the terms of the act of parliament which had confirmed him in that office. To theſe requiſitions, it was anſwered, upon the part of the Engliſh deputies, that their commiſſion was ſo ample, that they could enter into and proceed with the controverſy; and that they had liberty to declare, that their ſovereign would not reſtore the queen of Scots to her crown, if ſatisfactory proofs of her crime ſhould be produced; but that they knew not, and were not inſtructed to ſay, in what manner ſhe would finally conduct herſelf as to her perſon and puniſhment. With regard to the ſovereignty of the prince, and the regency of the earl of Murray, they were points, they obſerved, which might be canvaſſed in a futurer period. Theſe replies did not pleaſe the regent and his affociaties; and they requeſted the Engliſh commiſſioners to tranſmit their doubts and ſcruples to be examined and anſwered by Elizabeth.</p><p>But while the regent diſcovered in this manner his apprehenſions, he yet affirmed that he was able to anſwer the charges imputed to him and his faction; and this being in a great meaſure a diſtinct matter from the controverſy of the murder, he was deſired to proceed in it. It was contended, that Bothwel, who had the chief concern in the murder of lord Darnley, poſſeſſed ſuch credit with the queen, that within three months after that horrible event, he ſeized her perſon and led her captive to Dunbar, obtained a divorce from his wife, and married her: that the nobility, being moved with his crimes, did confederate to puniſh him; to relieve her from the tyranny of a man who had raviſhed her, and who could not be her huſband; and to preſerve the life of the prince: that having taken arms for theſe purpoſes, the earl marched againſt them; but that, propoſing to decide the quarrel by ſingle combat, his challenge was accepted: that he declined, notwithſtanding, to enter the lifts, and fled: that, the queen, preferring his impunity to her own. honour, favoured his eſcape by going over to the nobility: that they conducted her to Edinburgh, where they informed her of the motives of their proceedings, requeſted her to take the proper ſteps againſt him and the other regicides, and intreated her to diſſolve her pretended marriage, to take care of her ſon, and to conſult the tranquillity of her realm: that this treatment being offenſive to her, ſhe menaced them with vengeance, and offered to ſurrender her crown if they would permit her to poſſeſs the murderer of her huſband: that her inflexible mind, and the neceſſities of the ſtate, compelled. them to keep her at a diſtance from him, and out of the way of a communication with his adherents: that during her confinement, finding herſelf fatigued with the troubles of royalty, and unfit for them from vexation of ſpirit and the. weakneſs of her body and intellect, ſhe freely and of her, own will reſigned her crown to her ſon, and conſtituted the earl of Murray to the regency; that the king accordingly had been crowned, and Murray admitted to the regency; that the fonction of the three eſtates aſſembled in parliament having confirmed theſe appointments, an uni-</p></body></text></TEI>