<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:56:26Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Marre, Sir Thomas Erſkine afterwards earl of Kellie, and Sir John Ramſey who was likewiſe ennobled; and though Gowrie and his brother fell in the ſtruggle, they were attainted by an act of parliament, which decerned their name, memory, and dignity, to be extinguiſhed; their arms to be cancelled; their whole eſtates to be forfeited and annexed to the crown; the name of Ruthven to be aboliſhed; and their poſterity and ſurviving brethren to be incapable of ſucceeding to, or of holding, any offices, honours, or poſſeſſions.</p><p>The moſt memorable tranſaction of James’s reign, and that moſt to his honour, is the civilizing of the weſtern iſlanders. For this purpoſe, he inſtituted a company of gentlemen adventurers, to whom he gave large privileges for reforming them. The method he propoſed was to tranſport numbers of them to his low countries in Scotland, and to give their iſlands, which were very improveable, in ſee to his lowland ſubjects  who ſhould chooſe to reſide in the iſlands. The experiment was to be made upon the Lewes, a long range of the Ebudae; from whence the adventurers expelled Murdoch Macleod, the tyrant of the inhabitants. Macleod, however, kept the ſea; and intercepting a ſhip which carried one of the chief adventurers, he lent him priſoner to Orkney, alter putting the crew to the ſword. Macleod was loon after betrayed by his own brother, and hanged at St Andrew’s The hiſtory of this new undertaking is rather dark; and the ſettlers themſelves ſeem to have been defective in the arts of civilization. The arrangements they made were conſidered by the inhabitants as very oppreſſive; and one Norman, of the Macleod family, attacked and ſubdued them ſo effectually, that they not only conſented to yield the property ot the iſlands to him, but engaged to obtain the king’s pardon for what he had done.</p><p>In 1603 James was called to the throne of England by the death of Elizabeth, and the ſame year took a final leave of Scotland @@<hi rend="smallcaps">(a)</hi> From this period the hiſtory of Scotland, being blended with that of England, is included in the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Britain ; </hi>to which therefore we refer the reader, and ſhall proceed to give a general account of the country.</p><p>The firſt and great diviſion of Scotland is into the Highlands and Lowlands. The former engroſs more than one half of Scotland; extending from Dumbartonſhire to the moſt northern part of the iſland, a ſpace of 200 miles in length, and in breadth from 50 to 100. This tract, however, includes ſeveral extenſive diſtricts of low, fruitful ground, inhabited by people who are in all reſpects different from the mountaineers. Nothing can be more ſavage and tremendous to the eye of a ſtranger, than the appearance of the Highlands, compoſed of blue rocks and duſky mountains heaped upon one another even above the clouds, their interſtices rendered impaſſable by bogs, their ſides embrowned with heath, and their ſummits covered with ſnow, which lies all the year unthawed, pouring from their jagged ſides a thouſand torrents and roaring cataracts</p><p>that fall into gloomy vales or glens below, ſome of them ſo narrow, deep, and diſmal, as to be altogether impenetrable by the rays of the ſun; yet even theſe mountains are in ſome places ſloped into agreeable green hills fit for paſture, and ſkirted or interſperſed with pleaſant ſtraths or valleys capable of cultivation. It may be unneceſſary to obſerve, that the Lowlanders of Scotland ſpeak an ancient dialect of the Engliſh language, interlarded with many terms and idioms which they borrowed immediately from France, in a long courſe of correſpondence with that kingdom: they likewiſe copy their ſouthern neighbours in their houſes, equipage, habit, induſtry, and application to commerce. As to the inhabitants of the mountains, ſee the article <hi rend="smallcaps">High-landers.</hi> They are, all, however, comprehended under the name of <hi rend="italic">Scots</hi> governed by the ſame laws, and tried by the ſame judges; and, whatever may be their diſſenſions at home, they always, when abroad, acknowledge and aſſiſt one another as friends and countrymen. Some authors have divided Scotland into that part which lies to the ſouthward of the Frith, and that  which lies to the northward; but the true diviſion is, like that of England, into ſhires, counties, ſtewart- ries or bailiwicks, of which there are above 40 within the kingdom of Scotland.</p><p>The lace of this country exhibits a very mountainous appearance, eſpecially to the weſt and northward; but, at the ſame time, it diſplays many large and long tracts of plain ground fit for all the purpoſes of agriculture. It is divided from eaſt to weſt by a chain of huge mountains, known by the name of <hi rend="italic">Grant's bain </hi>or the <hi rend="italic">Grampian hills.</hi> There is another chain called the <hi rend="italic">Pentland hills,</hi> which run through Lothian, and join the mountains of Tweeddale; a third, called <hi rend="italic">Lammer-muir,</hi> riſing near the eaſtern coaſt, runs weſtward through the Merſe: but beſides these, there is a vaſt number of detached hills and mountains, remarkable ſor their ſtupendous height and ſteepneſs. There is no country in the world better ſupplied than Scotland with rivers, lakes, rivulets, and fountains. Over and above the principal rivers of Tweed, Forth, Clyde, Tay, and Spey, there is an infinity of ſmaller ſtreams that contribute to the beauty, convenience, and advantage of the kingdom. Tweed takes its riſe from the borders of Annandale; ſerves as a boundary between Scotland and England; and, after a long ſerpentine courſe, diſcharges itſelf into the ſea at Berwick. Forth riſes in Monteith near Callendar, paſſes by Stirling, and after a courſe of 25 leagues, runs into the arm of the ſea called the <hi rend="italic">Frith of Forth,</hi> which divides the coaſt of Lothian from File. Clyde takes its riſe from Errick hill, in the ſhire of Lanerk; traverſes the ſhire of Clydeſdale, to which it gives name; waſhes the city of Glaſgow, widens in its paſſage to the caille of Dumbarton, and forms the frith of Clyde adjoining to the Iriſh ſea. Tay, the largeſt river in Scotland, derives its ſource from Loch-Tay in. Breadalbane; and, after a ſouth-eaſt courſe, diſcharges itſelf</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">@@@(a)</hi> In 1589 James was married to Anne princeſs of Denmark, ſor whom he made a voyage on purpoſe to that country. This princeſs ſeems to have intermeddled very little with ſtate-affairs, ſince we find her ſcarce ever mentioned either by Scots or Engliſh hiſtorians. In lier private conduct ſhe is ſaid to have been unprincipled, vindictive, and unfaithful to her huſband.</p></body></text></TEI>