<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>translated from HTML to TEI</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-23-r04-0694-02"
                facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0741.jp2" type="entry">

                <p><label>RÖNTGEN RAYS</label>, W. K. Röntgen discovered in 1895 <hi rend="italic"
                        >(Wied. Ann.</hi> 64, p. 1) that when the electric discharge passes through
                    a tube exhausted so that the glass of the tube is brightly phosphorescent,
                    phosphorescent substances such as potassium platinocyanide became luminous when
                    brought near to the tube. He found that if a thick piece of metal, a coin for
                    example, were placed between the tube and a plate covered with the
                    phosphorescent substance a sharp shadow of the metal was cast upon the plate;
                    pieces of wood or thin plates of aluminium cast, however, only partial shadows,
                    thus showing that the agent which produced the phosphorescence could traverse
                    with considerable freedom bodies opaque to ordinary light. He found that as a
                    general rule the greater the density of the substance the greater its opacity to
                    this agent. Thus while this effect could pass through the flesh it was stopped
                    by the bones, so that if the hand were held between the discharge tube and a
                    phosphorescent screen the outline of the bones was distinctly visible as a
                    shadow cast upon the screen, or if a purse containing coins were placed between
                    the tube and the screen the purse itself cast but little shadow while the coins
                    cast a very dark one. Röntgen showed that the cause of the phosphorescence, now
                    called Röntgen rays, is propagated in straight lines starting from places where
                    the cathode rays strike against a solid obstacle, and the direction of
                    propagation is not bent when the rays pass from one medium to another, <hi
                        rend="italic">i.e.</hi> there is no refraction of the rays. These rays,
                    unlike cathode rays or <hi rend="italic">Canalstrahlen,</hi> are not deflected
                    by magnetic force; Röntgen could not detect any deflection with the strongest
                    magnets at his disposal, and later experiments made with stronger magnetic
                    fields have failed to reveal any effect of the magnet on the rays. The rays
                    affect a photographic plate as well as a phosphorescent screen, and shadow
                    photographs can be readily taken. The time of exposure required depends upon the
                    intensity of the rays, and this depends upon the state of the tube, and the
                    electric current going through it, as well as upon the substances traversed by
                    the rays on their journey to the photographic plate. In some cases an exposure
                    of a few seconds is sufficient, in others hours may be required. The rays coming
                    from different discharge tubes have very different powers of penetration. If the
                    pressure in the tube is fairly high, so that the potential difference between
                    its electrodes is small, and the velocity of the cathode rays-in consequence
                    small, the Röntgen rays coming from the tube will be very easily absorbed; such
                    rays are called “ soft rays.” If the exhaustion of the tube is carried further,
                    so that there is a considerable increase* in the potential differences between
                    the cathode and the anode in the tube and- therefore in the velocity of the
                    cathode rays, the Röntgen rays have much greater penetrating power and aie
                    called “ hard rays.” With a highly exhausted tube and a powerful induction coil
                    it is possible to get appreciable effects trom rays which have passed through
                    sheets of brass or iron several millimetres thick. The penetrating power of the
                    rays thus varies with the pressure in the tube; as this pressure gradually
                    diminishes when the discharge is kept running through the tube, the type of
                    Röntgen ray coming from the tube is continually changing. The lowering of
                    pressure due to the current through the tube finally leads to such a high degree
                    of exhaustion that the discharge has great difficulty in passing, and the
                    emission of the rays becomes very irregular. Heating the walls of the tube
                    causes some gas to come off the sides, and by thus increasing the pressure
                    creates a temporary improvement. A thin-walled platinum tube is sometimes fused
                    on to the discharge tube to remedy this defect; red-hot platinum allows hydrogen
                    to pass through it, so that if the platinum tube is heated, hydrogen from the
                    flame will pass into the discharge tube and increase the pressure. In this way
                    hydrogen may be introduced into the tube when the pressure gets too low. When
                    liquid air is available the pressure in the tube may be kept constant by fusing
                    on to the discharge tube a tube containing charcoal; this dips into a vessel
                    containing liquid air, and the charcoal is saturated with air at the pressure
                    which it is desired to maintain in the tube. Not only do bulbs emit different
                    types of rays at different times, but the same bulb emits at the same time rays
                    of different kinds. The property by which it is most convenient to identify a
                    ray is the absorption it suffers when it passes through a given thickness of
                    aluminium or tin-foil. Experiments made by McClelland and Sir J. J. Thomson on
                    the absorption of the rays produced by sheets of tin-foil showed that the
                    absorption by the first sheets of tin-foil traversed by -the rays was much
                    greater than that by the same number of sheets when the rays had already passed
                    through several sheets of the foil. The effect is just what would occur if some
                    of the rays were much more readily absorbed by the tin-foil than others, for the
                    first few layers would stop all the easily absorbable rays while the ones left
                    would be those that were but little absorbed by tin-foil.</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-23-r04-0695" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0742.jp2"/>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>Element.</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>Atomic weight.</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>λ.</p>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>Chromium</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>. . . . 52</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>367</p>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>Iron .</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>• · . 55·9</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>239</p>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>Cobalt</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>. 59·0</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>193.2</p>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>Nickel</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>. . . 58·7? <hi rend="smallcaps">(6i</hi> · <hi rend="smallcaps"
                                    >3)</hi>
                           </p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>159.5</p>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>Copper</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>. . . . 63-6</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>128.9</p>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>Zinc .</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>. 65·4</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>106.3</p>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>Arsenic .</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>. 75·0</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>60.7</p>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>Selenium .</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>• 79·2</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>51.0</p>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>Strontium</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>. 87·6</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>35.2</p>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>Molybdenum</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>. . . . 96·0</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>12.7</p>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>Rhodium</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>. 103·0</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>8.44</p>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>Silver .</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>. 107·9</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>6.75</p>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>Tin . .</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>. 119·0</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>4.33</p>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
               <p>The fact that the rays when they pass through a gas ionize it and make it a
                    conductor of electricity furnishes the best means of measuring their intensity,
                    as the measurement of the amount of conductivity they produce in a gas is both
                    more accurate and more convenient than measurements of photographic or
                    phosphorescent effects. Röntgen rays when they pass through matter produce—as
                    Perrin <hi rend="italic">{Comptes rendus,</hi> 124, ρ. 455), Sagnac <hi
                        rend="italic">(Jour, de Phys.,</hi> 1899, (3), 8, and J. Townsend <hi
                        rend="italic">(Proc. Camb. Phil. Soc.,</hi> 1899, 10, p. 217, have
                    shown—secondary Röntgen rays as. well as cathodic rays. A very complete
                    investigation of this subject has been made by BarkIa and Sadler (Barkla, <hi
                        rend="italic">Phil. Mag.,</hi> June 1906, pp. 812-828; Barkla and Sadler,
                        <hi rend="italic">Phil. Mag.,</hi> October 1908, pp. 550-504; Sadler, <hi
                        rend="italic">Phil. Mag.,</hi> July 1909, p. 107; Sadler, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Phil. Mag.,</hi> March 1910, p. 337). They have shown that the secondary
                    Röntgen rays are of two kinds: one kind is of the same type as the primary
                    incident ray and may be regarded as scattered primary rays, the other kind,
                    depends only on the matter struck by the rays—their quality is independent of
                    that of the incident ray. When the atomic weight of the element exposed to the
                    primary rays was less than that of calcium, Barkla and Sadler could only detect
                    the first type of ray, <hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi> the secondary radiation
                    consisted entirely of scattered primary radiation; elements with atomic weights
                    greater than that of calcium gave out, in addition to the scattered primary
                    radiation, Röntgen rays characteristic of the element and independent of the
                    quality of the primary rays. The higher the atomic weight of the metal the more
                    penetrating are the characteristic rays it gives out. This is shown in the
                    table, which gives for the different elements the reciprocal of the distance,
                    measured in centimetres, through Which the rays from the element can pass
                    through aluminium before their energy sinks to ½*7 of the value it had when
                    entering the aluminium; this quantity is denoted in the table by λ.</p>
               <p>The radiation from chromium cannot pass through more than a few centimetres of
                    air without being absorbed, while that from tin is as penetrating as that given
                    out by a fairly efficient Röntgen tube. Barkla and Sadler found that the
                    radiation characteristic of the metal is not excited .unless the primary
                    radiation is more penetrating than the characteristic radiation. Thus the
                    characteristic radiation from silver can excite the characteristic radiation,
                    from iron, but. the characteristic radiation from iron cannot excite that from
                    silver. We may compare this result with Stokes’s rule for phosphorescence, that
                    the phosphorescent light is of longer wave-length than the light which excites
                    it.</p>
               <p>The discovery that each element gives out a characteristic radiation (or, as
                    still more recent work indicates, a line spectrum of characteristic radiation)
                    is one of the utmost importance. It gives us, for example, the means of getting
                    homogeneous Röntgen radiation of a perfectly definite type: it is also of
                    fundamental importance in connexion with any theory of the Röntgen rays. We have
                    seen that there is no evidence of refraction of the Röntgen rays ; it would be
                    interesting to try if this were the case when the rays passing through the
                    refracting substance are those characteristic of the substance.</p>
               <p>                    <hi rend="italic">Secondary Cathodic Rays.—</hi> The incidence of Röntgen rays
                    on matter causes the matter to emit cathodic rays. The velocity of these rays is
                    independent of the intensity of the primary Röntgen rays, but depends upon the
                    “hardness” of the rays; it seems also to be independent of the nature of the
                    matter exposed to the primary rays. The velocity of the cathodic rays increases
                    as the hardness of the primary Röntgen rays increases. Innes <hi rend="italic"
                        >(Proc. Roy. Soc.</hi> 79, p. .442) measured the velocity of the cathodic
                    radiation excited by the rays from Röntgen tubes, and found velocities varying
                    from 6-2 X io’cm./sec. to 8·3X10’ cm./sec. according to the hardness of the rays
                    given out by the tube. The cathodic rays given out under the action of the
                    homogeneous secondary Roptgen radiation characteristic of the different elements
                    have been studied by Sadler <hi rend="italic">(Phil. Mag.,</hi> March 1910) and
                    Beatty <hi rend="italic">(Phil. Mag.,</hi> August 1910). The following table
                    giving the properties of the cathode rays excited by the radiation from various
                    elements is taken from Beatty’s paper; Z <hi rend="sub">1</hi> is the thickness
                    of air at atmospheric pressure and</p>
               <p>temperature required to absorb one-half of the energy of the cathode particles,
                    Z <hi rend="sub">2</hi> is the corresponding quantity for hydrogen.</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>Radiator.</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>Zi</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>Z <hi rend="sub">2</hi>
                           </p>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>Iron</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>. 00804</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>•0410</p>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>Copper.</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>..... .0135</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>•0733</p>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>Zinc</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>..... .0164</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>•0909</p>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>Arsenic.</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>..... .0255</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>Tin . .</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>..... .1672</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                           <p>1.37</p>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
               <p>The properties of the cathode rays excited by the radiation from tin correspond
                    very closely with those produced in a discharge tube when the potential
                    difference between the anode and cathode is about 30,000 volts. When Röntgen
                    rays pass through a thin plate the cathodic radiation on the side the rays
                    emerge is more intense than on the side they enter. Kaye <hi rend="italic"
                        >(Phil. Trans. 209,</hi> p. 123) has shown that when cathode rays fall upon
                    a metal two kinds of Röntgen rays are excited, one being the characteristic
                    radiation of the metal and the other a kind independent of the nature of the
                    metal and dependent only upon the velocity of the cathode rays. The faster the
                    cathode rays the harder the Röntgen rays they produce. It would be interesting
                    to see if there is any connexion between the velocity of the cathode rays
                    required to excite Röntgen rays as hard as those given out say by tin and the
                    velocity of the cathode rays which the radiation from tin produces when it falls
                    upon any metal. Sadler has shown that metals can give off cathodic radiation
                    even when the incident Röntgen rays are too soft to excite the characteristic
                    Röntgen radiation of the metal, but that there is a large increase in the
                    cathodic radiation as soon as the characteristic Röntgen radiation is excited.
                    It is possible that the shock produced by the emission of these cathode
                    particles starts the vibrations which give rise to the characteristic rays; the
                    cathode particles emitted when the incident rays arc too soft to excite the
                    characteristic radiation coming from a different source from those tapped by the
                    hard rays.</p>
               <p>                    <hi rend="italic">Absorption of Ronlgen Rays.—</hi> The wide variations in the
                    penetrating power of Röntgen rays from different sources is shown by the above
                    table of the penetrating power of the characteristic rays of the different
                    elements. Many experiments have been made on the penetration of the same rays
                    for different substances. It is a rule to which there is no well-established
                    exception that the greater the density of the substance the greater is its power
                    of absorbing the rays. The connexion, however, between the absorption and the
                    density of the substance is not in general a simple one, though there is
                    evidence that for exceedingly hard rays the absorption is proportional to the
                    density.</p>
               <p>The power of any material to absorb rays is usually measured by a coefficient λ,
                    the definition of which is that a plate i/X centimetres thick reduces the energy
                    of the rays when they pass through it normally to <hi rend="italic">i/e</hi> of
                    their original value, where <hi rend="italic">e</hi> is the base of the
                    Napierian logarithms and equal to 2·7128. It has been shown that however the
                    physical state of a substance may alter,—if, for example, it changes from the
                    liquid to the gaseous,—λ/D, where <hi rend="italic">D</hi> is the density of the
                    substance, remains constant. It has also been shown that if we have a mass <hi
                        rend="italic">M</hi> made up of masses Mi, M <hi rend="sub">2</hi> , M <hi
                        rend="sub">1</hi> , . . . of substances having coefficients, of absorption
                    λι, X <hi rend="sub">2</hi> , Xj, . . . and densities Di, D <hi rend="sub"
                        >2</hi> , D <hi rend="sub">8</hi> , . . . then if λ/D for the mixture is
                    given by the equation</p>
               <p>Mλ/D = M <hi rend="sub">1</hi> λ <hi rend="sub">1</hi> /D <hi rend="sub">1</hi>
                    +M <hi rend="sub">2</hi> λ <hi rend="sub">2</hi> /D <hi rend="sub">2</hi> +M <hi
                        rend="sub">3</hi> λ <hi rend="sub">3</hi> /D <hi rend="sub">3</hi> + . . .
                    this equation is true whether the substances are chemically combined or
                    chemically mixed. From this equation, when we know λ/D for a binary compound and
                    for one of its constituents, we can find the value of λ/D for the other
                    constituent. By the use of this principle we can find the value of λ/D for the
                    elements which cannot be obtained in a .free state. Benoist <hi rend="italic"
                        >(Jour, de Phys.</hi> (7), 28, p. 289) has shown that if the values of λ/D
                    are plotted against the atomic weight we get a smooth curve; if we draw this
                    curve it is evident that we have the means of determining the atomic weight of
                    an element by measuring its transparency to Röntgen rays when in combination
                    with elements whose transparency is known. Benoist has applied this method to
                    determine the atomic weight of indium.</p>
               <p>The value of λ/D for any one substance depends upon the type of ray used, and
                    the ratio of the values of λ/D for two substances may vary very greatly with the
                    type of ray; this is especially the case when one of the substances is hydrogen.
                    Thus Crowther <hi rend="italic">(Proc. Roy. Soc.,</hi> March 1909) has shown
                    that the ratio of X for air to X for hydrogen varied from 100 for rays given out
                    by a Röntgen tube at a comparatively high pressure when the rays were very soft
                    to 5*56 when the pressure in the bulb was very low and the rays very hard.
                    Beatty <hi rend="italic">(Phil. Mag.,</hi> August 1910) found that this ratio
                    was as large as 175 for the characteristic rays given out by iron, copper, zinc
                    and arsenic, but fell to 25-0 for the rays from tin.</p>
                <div>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Polarization of Ronlgen Rays.—</hi>
                        A great deal of attention has been paid to a phenomenon
                        called the polarization of the </head>
                </div>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-23-r04-0696" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0743.jp2"/>
                <div>
                   <p>Röntgen rays. The nature of this effect may be illustrated by fig. i.
                        Suppose that AB is a stream of cathode rays striking against a solid
                        obstacle B and giving rise to Röntgen rays, let these rays impinge on a
                        small body P, P under these conditions will emit secondary rays in all
                        directions. Barkla <hi rend="italic">(Phil. Trans.</hi> , 1905, A, 204, p.
                        467; <hi rend="italic">Proc. Roy. Soc. p,</hi> p. 247) found that the
                        intensity of the secondary rays, tested by the ionization they produced in
                        air, was less intense in the plane ABP than in a plane through PB at right
                        angles to this plane, the distances from P being the same in the two cases;
                        the difference in the intensities amounting to about 15%. Haga <hi
                            rend="italic">(Ann. d. Phys.</hi> 28, p. 439), who tried a similar
                        experiment hut used a photographic method to measure the intensity of the
                        secondary rays, could not detect any difference of intensity in the two
                        planes, but experiments by Bassler (<hi rend="italic">Ann. der Phys.</hi>
                        28, p. 808) and Vegard <hi rend="italic">(Proc. Roy. Soc.</hi> 83, p. 379)
                        have confirmed Barkla’s original observations.</p>
                   <p>The “ polarization ” is much more marked if instead of exciting the
                        secondary radiation in P by the Röntgen rays from a discharge tube we do so
                        by means of secondary rays. If, for example, in the case illustrated by fig.
                        1 we allow a beam of Röntgen rays to fall upon B instead of the cathode
                        rays, the difference between the intensities in the plane ABP and in the
                        plane at right angles to it are very much increased. _ It is only the
                        scattered secondaiy radiation which shows this “polarization”; the
                        characteristic secondary radiation emitted by the body at P is quite
                        unpolarized. The existence of this effect has a very important bearing on
                        the nature of Röntgen rays. Whether Röntgen rays are or are not a form of
                        light, <hi rend="italic">t.e.</hi> are some form of electromagnetic
                        disturbance propagated through the aether, is a question on which opinion is
                        not unanimous. They resemble light in their rectilinear propagation; they
                        affect a photographic plate and, Brandes and Dorn have shown, they produce
                        an effect, though a small one, on the retina, .giving rise to a very faint
                        illumination of the whole field of view. They resemble light in not being
                        deflected by either electric or magnetic forces, while the characteristic
                        secondary radiation may be compared with the phosphorescence produced by
                        ultra-violet light, and the cathodic secondary rays with the photo-electric
                        effect. . The absence of refraction is not an argument against the rays
                        being a kind of light, for all theories of refraction make this property
                        depend upon the relation • between the natural time of vibration T of the
                        refracting substance and the period Z of the light vibrations, the
                        refraction vanishing when Z/T is very small. Thus there would be no
                        refraction for light of a very small period, and this would also be true if
                        instead of regular periodic undulations we had a pulse of electromagnetic
                        disturbance, provided the time taken by the light to travel over the
                        thickness of the pulse is small compared with the periods of vibration of
                        the molecules of the refracting substance. Experiments on the diffraction of
                        Röntgen rays are very difficult, for, in addition to the difficulties caused
                        by the smallness .of the wavelength or the thinness of the pulse, the
                        secondary radiation produced when the rays strike against a photographic
                        plate or pass, through air might give rise to what might easily be mistaken
                        for diffraction effects. Röntgen has never succeeded in observing effects
                        which prove the existence of diffraction. Fomm <hi rend="italic">(Wied.
                            Ann.</hi> 59, p. 50) observed in the photograph of a narrow slit light
                        and dark bands which looked like diffraction bands; but observation with
                        slits of different sizes showed that they were not of this nature, and Haga
                        and Wind <hi rend="italic">(Wied. Ann.</hi> 68, p. 884) have explained them
                        as contrast effects. These observers, however, noticed with a very narrow
                        wedge-shaped slit a broadening of the image, of the narrow part which they
                        are satisfied could not be explained by the causes. Walter and Pohl <hi
                            rend="italic">(Ann. der Phys.</hi> 29, p. 331) could not observe any
                        diffraction effects, though their arrangement would have enabled them to do
                        so if the wave-length had not been smaller than 1·5×10-<hi rend="sup"
                            >9</hi> cm. Sir George Stokes <hi rend="italic">(Proc. Manchester Lit.
                            and Phil. Soc.,</hi> 1898) put forward the view that the disturbances
                        which constitute the rays are not regular periodic undulations but very thin
                        pulses. Thomson <hi rend="italic">(Phil. Mag.</hi> 45, p. 172) has shown
                        that when charged particles are suddenly stopped, pulses of very intense
                        electric and magnetic disturbances are started. As the cathode rays consist
                        of negatively electrified particles, the impact of these on a solid would
                        give rise to these intense pulses. The electromagnetic theory therefore
                        shows that effects resembling light, inasmuch as they are electromagnetic
                        disturbances propagated through the aether, must be produced when the
                        cathode rays strike against an obstacle. Since under these circumstances
                        Röntgen rays are produced, it seems natural, unless direct evidence to the
                        contrary is obtained, to connect the Röntgen rays with these pulses. This
                        view explains very simply the “ polarization” of the rays; for, suppose the
                        cathode particle moving from A to B were stopped at its first impact with
                        the plate B (fig. 1), the electric force transmitted along BP would be in
                        the plane ABP at right angles to BP. When this electric force reached the
                        body at P it would accelerate any electrified particles in that body, the.
                        acceleration being parallel to AB. Each of these accelerated particles
                        would, start electric waves. The theory of such waves shows that their
                        intensity vanishes along a line through the particle parallel to the
                        direction of acceleration, while it is a maximum at right angles to this
                        line; thus the intensity of the rays along a horizontal line through P would
                        vanish, while it would be a maximum in the plane at right angles to this
                        line. In this case there would be complete polarization. In reality the
                        cathode particle is not. stopped at its first encounter, but makes many
                        collisions, changing its direction between each; and these collisions will
                        send out electric disturbances which when they fall on P are able to excite
                        waves which send some energy along PC. The polarization will therefore be
                        only partial and will be of the kind found by Barkla.</p>
                   <p>The velocity with which the waves travel has not yet been definitely
                        settled. Marx <hi rend="italic">(Ann. der Phys.</hi> 20, p. 677) by an
                        ingenious but elaborate method came to the conclusion that they travelled
                        with the velocity of light; his interpretation of his experiments has,
                        however, been criticized by Franck and Pohl <hi rend="italic">(Verh. d. D.
                            Physik Ges.</hi> 10, p. 489).</p>
                   <p>Another view of the nafure of Röntgen rays has been advocated by Bragg <hi
                            rend="italic">(Phil. Mag..</hi> 14, p. 429); he regards them as neutral
                        electric doublets consisting of a negative and a positive charge of
                        electricity which are usually held together by the attraction between them,
                        but which may be knocked asunder when the rays strike against matter and
                        turned into cathodic rays. On this view when the rays pass through a gas
                        only a few of the molecules of the gas are struck by the rays and so we can
                        easily understand why so few of the molecules are ionized. On the ordinary
                        view of an electric wave all the molecules would be affected by the wave
                        when it passed through a gas, and to explain the small fraction ionized we
                        must either suppose that systems sensitive to the Röntgen rays are at any
                        time present only in a very small fraction of the molecule or else that the
                        front of an electric or light wave is not continuous but that the energy is
                        concentrated in patches which only occupy a fraction of the wave front.</p>
                   <p>                        <hi rend="italic">Apparatus for producing Röntgen Rays.—</hi> The tube now
                        used most frequently for producing Röntgen rays is of the kind introduced by
                        Porter and known as a focus tube (fig. 2). The cathode is a portion of a
                        hollow sphere,</p>
                   <p>and the cathode rays come</p>
                   <p>to a point on or near a</p>
                   <p>metal plate A, called the</p>
                   <p>anti-cathode, connected</p>
                   <p>with the anode; this plate</p>
                   <p>is the source of the rays.</p>
                   <p>This ought to be made of</p>
                   <p>a very unfusible metal</p>
                   <p>such as platinum or, still</p>
                   <p>better, tantalum, and kept</p>
                   <p>cool by a water-cooling</p>
                   <p>arrangement. The anti-cathode is generally set at an angle of 45° to the
                        rays; it is probable. that the 'action of the tube would be improved by
                        putting the anti-cathode at right angles to the cathode rays. The walls of
                        the tube get strongly electrified. This electrification affects the working
                        of the tube, and the production of rays can often be improved by having an
                        earth-connected piece of tin-foil on the outside, of the bulb, and moving it
                        about until the best position is attained. . To produce the discharge an
                        induction coil is generally employed with a mercury interrupter. Excellent
                        results have been obtained by using an electrostatic induction machine to
                        produce the current, the emission of rays is more uniform than when an
                        induction coil is.used. The rays are emitted pretty uniformly in all
                        directions until the plane of the anti-cathode is approached; in the
                        neighbourhood of this plane there is a rapid falling off in the intensity of
                        the rays. After long use the glass of the bulb often becomes distinctly
                        purple. This is believed to be due to the presence of manganese compounds in
                        the glass. (J. J. T.)</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
