<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>translated from HTML to TEI</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-23-r04-0684-03"
                facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0731.jp2" type="entry">

                <p><label>ROME</label> a city of Oneida county, New York, U.S.A., on the Mohawk
                    river and Wood Creek, and the Erie and the Black river canals, 14 m. W.N.W. of
                    Utica. Pop. (1890) 14,991; (1900) 15,343, of whom 2527 were foreign-born; (1910,
                    census) 20,497. Rome is served by the New York Central &amp; Hudson River,
                    the Rome, Watertown &amp; Ogdensburg (controlled by the New York Central),
                    the New York, Ontario &amp; Western, and the Utica &amp; Mohawk Valley
                    (electric) railways. It is about 450 ft. above sea-level. The city is the seat
                    of the Academy of the Holy Names (opened in 1865 as St Peter’s Academy), of the
                    State Custodial Asylum for unteachable idiots, of the Central New York
                    Institution for Deaf Mutes (1875), and of the Oneida County Home. The Jervis
                    Public Library (1895), founded by John Bloomfield Jervis (1795-1885), a famous
                    railway engineer, had in 1909 about 15,000 volumes. The surrounding country is
                    devoted largely to farming, especially vegetable gardening, and to dairying.
                    Among the manufactures are brass and copper work, wire for electrical uses,
                    foundry and machine-shop products, locomotives, knit goods, tin cans and canned
                    goods (especially vegetables). In 1905 the value of the factory products was
                    $8,631,427 (55-6% more than in 1900).</p>
               <p>The portage at this place between the Mohawk river and Wood Creek, which are
                    about 1 m. apart, gave the site its Indian name, De-o-wain-sta, “ place where
                    canoes are carried from one stream to another,” and its earliest English name,
                    “The Great (or Oneida) Carrying-Plate,” and gave it strategic value as a key
                    between the Mohawk Valley and Lake Ontario. About 1725 there were built, to
                    protect the carrying-place here, Fort Bull, on Wood Creek, which was surprised
                    and taken by French and Indians in March 1756, and Fort Williams, on the Mohawk,
                    which, like Fort Craven, also on the Mohawk, was destroyed by Colonel Daniel
                    Webb after the reduction of Oswego by the French</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-23-r04-0685" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0732.jp2"/>
               <p>in August 1756. General John Stanwix built Fort Stanwix here at an expense of
                    £60,000, and the first permanent settlement dates from about this time. In
                    October-November 1768, Sir William Johnson and representatives of Virginia and
                    Pennsylvania met 3200 Indians of the Six Nations here and made a treaty with
                    them, under which, for £10,460 in money and provisions, they surrendered to the
                    crown their claims to what is now Kentucky and West Virginia and the western
                    part of Pennsylvania. Of this cession the part which lay in Pennsylvania was
                    secured by purchase from the Indians for the proprietors Richard and Thomas Penn
                    (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Pittsburg).</hi> The fort was* dismantled immediately
                    afterward. After 1776, when it was partly repaired by Colonel Elias Dayton, it
                    was called by the continentals Fort Schuyler, in honour of General Philip
                    Schuyler, and so is sometimes confused with (old) Fort Schuyler at Utica. The
                    third regiment of the New York line under Colonel Peter Gansevoort occupied the
                    fort in April 1777 and completed the repairs begun in 1776; on the 3rd of August
                    in the same year (one month before the official announcement by Congress of the
                    design of the flag) the first flag of the United States, made according to the
                    enactment of the 14th of June and used in battle, was raised here: it was made
                    from various pieces of cloth. On the 2nd of August an advance party of Colonel
                    Barry St Leger’s forces coming from the west arrived before the fort, and the
                    main body (altogether about 650 whites, including loyalists—the Royal
                    Greens—under Sir John Johnson, and more than 800 Indians, some led by Joseph
                    Brant) arrived soon afterwards. The fort then contained about 750 men under
                    Colonel Gansevoort, with Lieut.-Colonel Marinus Willett as second in command.
                    The danger to the fort roused General Nicholas Herkimer to gather a force of
                    between 700 and 1000 men (including some „Oneida Indians), who during their
                    advance on the 6th of August were ambuscaded in a ravine near Oriskany <hi
                        rend="italic">(q.v.),</hi> about 8 m. E. of the fort; after heavy losses to
                    both sides, about 250 men from the fort under Willett attacked the camp of the
                    Indians who were supporting St Leger, thus relieved Herkimer through the falling
                    back of the British and Indians to save their supplies, captured five ensigns of
                    the Royal Greens, and seized large quantities of stores from the enemy’s camp.
                    The siege now lost force, the Indians straggled away after the loss of their
                    camp supplies, and on the 23rd of August, St Leger, hearing exaggerated reports
                    of the immediate approach of large reinforcements under General Benedict Arnold,
                    withdrew, abandoning his camp and stores. The successful resistance here to St
                    Leger contributed greatly to the American success at Saratoga. Fort Stanwix was
                    the headquarters of Colonel Gozen Van Schaick (1736-1789) in 1779 when he
                    destroyed the Onondaga villages. At the fort, on the 22nd of October 1784, a
                    treaty was made by Oliver Wolcott, Richard Butler and Arthur Lee, commissioners
                    for the United States, with the chiefs of the Six Nations. In 1796 a canal was
                    built across the old portage between Wood Creek and the Mohawk river. In 1796
                    the township of Rome was formed, receiving its name, says Schoolcraft, “ from
                    the heroic defence of the republic made here.” The village of Rome, in the
                    centre of the township, was incorporated in 1819; and Rome was chartered as a
                    city in 1870.</p>
               <p>See Pomroy Jones, <hi rend="italic">Annals and Recollections of Oneida
                        County</hi> (Rome, 1851); W. M. Willett, <hi rend="italic">A Narrative of
                        the Military Actions of Col. Marinus Willett</hi> (New York, 1831); and <hi
                        rend="italic">Orderly Book of Sir John Johnson during the Oriskany
                        Campaign</hi> (Albany, 1882), with notes by W. L. Stone and J W. de Peyster.
               </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
