<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>translated from HTML to TEI</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-23-r04-0754-02"
                facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0807.jp2" type="entry">
               <p>                   <label>ROSTAND, EDMOND</label> (1869- ), French dramatist, was</p>               <p>born on the ist of April 1869, the son of Joseph Eugène Herbert Rostand (b.
                    1843), a prominent journalist and economist of Marseilles. His first play, a
                    burlesque, <hi rend="italic">Les romanesques,</hi> was produced on the 21st of
                    May 1894 at the Théâtre Français. He’took the motive of his second piece, <hi
                        rend="italic">La Princesse lointaine</hi> (Théâtre de la Renaissance, 5th
                    April 1895), from the story of the troubadour Rudel and the Lady of Tripoli. The
                    part of Mélissande was created by Sarah Bernhardt, who also was the original
                    Photine of <hi rend="italic">La Samaritaine</hi> (Théâtre de la Renaissance,
                    14th April 1897), a Biblical drama in three scenes taken from the gospel story
                    of the woman of Samaria. The production of his “ heroic comedy ” of <hi
                        rend="italic">Cyrano de Bergerac</hi> (28th December 1807, Théâtre de la
                    Porte Saint-Martin), with Coquelin in the title-rôle, was a triumph. No such
                    enthusiasm for a drama in verse had been known since the days of Hugo's <hi
                        rend="italic">Hernani.</hi> The play was quickly translated into English,
                    German, Russian and other European languages. For his hero he had drawn on
                    French 17th-century history; in <hi rend="italic">U Aiglon</hi> he chose a
                    subject from Napoleoqjc legend, suggested probably by Henri Welsch-inger’s <hi
                        rend="italic">Roi de Rome, 1811-32</hi> (1897), which contained much new
                    information about the unhappy life of the duke of Reichstadt, son of Napoleon I.
                    and Marie Louise, under the surveillance of Metternich at the palace of
                    Schönbrunn. <hi rend="italic">L'Aiglon,</hi> in six acts and in verse, was
                    produced (15th March 1900) by Sarah Bernhardt at her own theatre, she herself
                    undertaking the part of the duke of Reichstadt. In 1902 Rostand was elected to
                    the French Academy. His <hi rend="italic">Chantecler,</hi> produced in February
                    1910, was awaited with an interest (enhanced by considerable delay in the
                    production) hardly equalled by the enthusiasm of its reception. Lucien Guitry
                    was in the title-rôle and Mme. Simone played the part of the pheasant, the play
                    being a fantasy of bird and animal life, and the characters denizens of the
                    farmyard and the woods. Rostand’s wife, <hi rend="italic">née</hi> Rosemonde
                    Êtienette Gérard, published in 1890 <hi rend="italic">Les Pipeaux,</hi> a volume
                    of verse crowned by the Academy.</p>               <p>See a notice by Henry James in vol. 84, pp. 477 seq. of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Cornhill Magazine.</hi>
               </p>            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
