<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>translated from HTML to TEI</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-23-r04-0684-01"
                facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0731.jp2" type="entry">

                <p>ROME, a province of modern Italy, co-extensive with the <hi
                        rend="italic">compartimento</hi> of Lazio, but really covering a
                    considerably larger area than the ancient Latium, even including Latium
                    adjectum. On the S.E. and E. alone it does not extend so far, the boundary being
                    that between the former papal states and the kingdom of Naples, running from a
                    point S.E. of Ter-racina along the eastern, edge of the Volscian mountains to
                    Coprano, and thence along the Liris valley. It then runs N.E. through the
                    mountains to Carsoli, being conterminous with the Abruzzi; it then includes part
                    of the ancient Sabine country, reaching the Tiber near the railway station of
                    Fara Sabina, 25 m. N. of Rome. It follows the river for some distance, where it
                    is conterminous with Umbria, and then runs S.W. to the coast, where it is
                    conterminous with the province of Grosseto (Tuscany), thus including a
                    considerable portion of the ancient Etruria. The resident population in 1901 was
                    estimated at 1,196,909 (including Rome itself, 520,196), and the floating
                    population, Italian and foreign, 54,383. In 1907 the total number was calculated
                    at 1,278,000. In 1871 the aggregate population was only 836,704. Emigration rose
                    from 2222 in 1896 to 18,507 in 1906, there being a great rise in 1905, as over
                    all Italy. The economic crisis in the United States in 1907, led, however, to a
                    set-back, many emigrants being obliged to return to Italy for lack of work. Alum
                    is extracted from the mines principally near Tolfa. At Filettino above Subiaco
                    asphaltic rock is obtained, and salt from a rocksalt mine near Cometo Tarquinia.
                    Chemical fertilizers are manufactured by several firms. The main industries of
                    the district are, however, agricultural (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Latium).</hi>
               </p>            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
