<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="encyclopediabrit21newyrich_raw_0287.jp2" type="entry" xml:id="eb09-21-s01-0267-01" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SAN MARTIN DE JOSÉ</label>
(1778-1850), Chilian general, was born at Yapeyú, on the Uruguay river, February 25, 1778. In his eighth or ninth year he accompanied his own family to Spain for his education, and being intended for the military profession was admitted into the college of nobles at Madrid. He saw active service and gained distinction in the war of independence, and had risen to the rank of lieutenant-colonel when in 1811 he returned to La Plata. Entering the service of the insurgents there he was entrusted with raising a troop of cavalry, and afterwards was appointed to the chief command of the army acting in Upper Peru against the forces of the viceroy of Lima. After re-establishing his health at Cordova in 1814, he proceeded in 1815 to take command of Cuyo, where he organized an expedition for the liberation of Chili (see vol. v. p. 618). He crossed the mountains early in 1817, and, after gaining a brilliant victory at Chacabuco on 12th February, was pressed by the people of Chili to take the supreme command, and gained a still more brilliant victory at Maypú, 5th April 1818. After organizing the govern</p><p>ment of Chili he sailed with the squadron under Lord Cochrane for Peru, 21st August 1820, and, capturing Lima, drove the Spaniards from the coast and assumed the title of “Protector” of Peru in 1821, but resigned it a year afterwards, and, sailing secretly for Europe, spent the remainder of his life in absolute seclusion near Paris. He died at Boulogne, 17th August 1850.</p><p>See <hi rend="italic">Biographical Sketch</hi> of General San Martin attached to <hi rend="italic">Peruvian Pamphlet, being an exposition of the Administrative Labours of the Peruvian Government,</hi> 1823.</p></div></body></text></TEI>