<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="encyclopediabrit21newyrich_raw_0217.jp2" type="entry" xml:id="eb09-21-s01-0197-02" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>ST SERVAN</label>,
a cantonal town of France, in the department of Ille-et-Vilaine, on the right bank of the Rance to the south of St Malo, from which it is separated by a creek at least a mile wide (see <hi rend="smallcaps">St Malo).</hi> In population (10,691 inhabitants in 1881; 12,867 in the commune) St Servan is slightly the smaller town of the two. It is not enclosed by walls, and with its new houses, straight wide streets, and numerous gardens forms quite a contrast to its neighbour. In summer it attracts a number of seaside visitors. The floating dock will when finished have an area of 27 acres and one mile of quays. The creek on which it opens is dry at low water, but at high water is 30 to 40 feet deep. Another port on the Rance, to the south-west of the town at the foot of the tower of Solidor, is used by the local guard-ship. This tower, erected in the close of the 14th century by Duke John IV. for the purpose of contesting the claims of Josselin de Rohan, bishop of St Malo, to the temporal sovereignty of the town, consists of three distinct towers formed into a triangle by loop-holed and machicolated curtains. At the north-west point of St Servan stands the “ city fort ” and near by are the ruins of the cathedral of St Peter of Aleth, the seat of a bishopric from the 6th to the 12th century. The church is modern (1742-1842).</p><p>The northern quarter of St Servan, called “the City,” occupies the site of the city of Aleth, which at the close of the Roman empire supplanted Corseul as the capital of the Curiosolites. Aleth was a bulwark of Druidism in those regions and was not Christianized till the 6th century, when St Malo became its first bishop. On the removal of the bishopric to St Malo Aleth declined ; but the houses that remained standing became the nucleus of a new community, which placed itself under the patronage of St Servan, apostle of the Orkneys. In 1758 the place was occupied by Marlborough. It was not till 1789 that St Servan became a separate commune from St Malo with a municipality and police of its own.</p></div></body></text></TEI>