<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb09-21-s01-0120-03" facs="encyclopediabrit21newyrich_raw_0138.jp2" type="entry"><p><label>SAADIA</label>, or Saadias (Heb. <hi rend="italic">Se'adyah,</hi> Arab. <hi rend="italic">Sa'îd</hi><note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="1"> He signs himself םציך acrostically in his <hi rend="italic">Azharoth (Ḳobeṣ,</hi> pp. 52, 53 ; see note 4 on next page). </note> <hi rend="italic">1),</hi> was the most accomplished, learned, and noble gaon (head of the academy) of Sūrā (see Rab). Mar Rab Se'adyah b. Yoseph<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="2"> Mas'údí, a contemporary, calls the father Ya'aḳob ; but see Fürst, <hi rend="italic">Literaturblatt d. Orients,</hi> vi. col. 140. </note> was born in the Fayyûm, Upper Egypt, in 892 and died at Sūrā in 942. Of his teachers only the Jew Abú Kethír is positively known by name,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="3"> Mas'údí (De Sacy, <hi rend="italic">Chrest. Ar.,</hi> 2d ed., i. 350, 351). </note> but he must have had at least three more . teachers of considerable learning, one a Karaite,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="4"> The late learned and ingenious Rabbi S. L. Rapoport rolled here, </note> one a Mohammedan, and one a Christian, as his acquaintance with the literature of these four religious bodies testifies. His pre-eminence over his</p><p>as in many other places, the stone of Sisyphus (“ Toledoth Rahhenu Se'adyah Gaon,” in <hi rend="italic">Bikkure Ha'ittim,</hi> Vienna, 1828, note 31). Perhaps, after all, the Karaites may be right in asserting that Salmon b. Yeruḥam was Rah Se'adyah’s teacher.</p><pb xml:id="eb09-21-s01-0121" facs="encyclopediabrit21newyrich_raw_0139.jp2"/><p>contemporaries is indicated in the fact that he was the only gaon who had not been educated and then advanced by degrees in the academy, to the highest dignity of which he was called from a far-off country, but best appears in the excellence of his many works, which extend over most branches of learning known in his time. And his learning was exceeded by his manifold virtues. His love of truth and justice was made more conspicuous by the darkness of the corruption amid which he lived. When the rēsh gāluthā (“prince of the captivity,” the highest dignitary of the Jews in Babylonia, and to some extent of those of the whole world) attempted to wrest judgment in a certain case, and first asked, then requested, and finally demanded the signature<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="5"> To make the legal decisions of therēsh gāluthā more respected, the signatures of the geonim of Sūrā and Pumbadithā were desirable. A specimen of a legal decision by David b. Zakkai signed on the authority of Rab Se'adyah Gaon is to be found in Frankel-Grätz, <hi rend="italic">Monatsschrift,</hi> xxxi. pp. 167-170. </note> of the gaon of Sūrā in a threatening manner, Se'adyah refused it, fearless of consequences. David b. Zakkai, the rēsh gāluthā, deposed him and chose another gaon in his stead. A reconciliation took place some years afterwards, and Se'adyah was reinstated in his old dignity. And, although his health had been fatally undermined by the behaviour of the rēsh gāluthā and his son, Se'adyah, when his former opponent died, was indefatigable in his endeavours to have this very son of his once mortal enemy placed on the throne of his fathers. But the new prince of the captivity enjoyed his dignity for little more than half a year. He left behind him a boy, twelve years of age, whom Se'adyah took into his own house and treated in every respect as his own child. This learning and these virtues endeared Se'adyah not merely to his contemporaries but also to the best men of succeeding ages. Behayye b. Yoseph (the author of the <hi rend="italic">Hoboth Hallebaboth),</hi> Rashi, Se'adyah (the author of the commentary on Daniel in the Rabbinic Bible), David Kimḥi, Behayye b. Asher (the author of <hi rend="italic">Kad Haḳḳemah),</hi> all appeal to him as an authority not to be questioned. Even Ibn 'Ezra defers more to him than to any other authority. To this day Jewish and Christian scholars alike express for him the highest admiration.</p><p>The numerous works which are ascribed to him may be conveniently divided into four classes.</p><p>I. <hi rend="italic">Genuine and still extant Works.—</hi> (1) Arabic translations of, and in part commentaries<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="6"> If we may argue from the known to the unknown, Se'adyah’s translations, whether they were called <hi rend="italic">tafsír</hi> or <hi rend="italic">sharh,</hi> contained more than a mere translation. From Ibn 'Ezra’s preface to his commentary on the Pentateuch and from the Arabic comm. on the Psalms published in excerpt by Ewald we see that Rab Se'adyah was in the habit of explaining in addition to translating. Compare also Munk, “Notice sur Saadia,” in Cahen, <hi rend="italic">La Bible</hi> (Isaïe), Paris, 1838, 8vo, p. 77, note 1. </note> on, books of the Bible : (a) the Pentateuch (printed in Hebrew characters, Constantinople, 1546, fob, and in Arabic characters in the Paris and London polyglotte) ; (δ) Isaiah (printed in Arabic characters from Hebrew letters of the Bodleian MS. Uri 156,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="7"> In the copyist’s subscription to this MS. the actual reading is not צבראת (Rapoport), but צבארת; this should be צבארת, as Munk prints it (“ Notice,” p. 108). The Bodleian MSS. are referred to in this article from personal inspection. </note> by Paulus, Jena, 1790-91, 8vo) ; (c) Psalms (Ewald, <hi rend="italic">Ueber die arabisch geschriebenen Werke jüdischer Sprachgelehrten,</hi> Stuttgart, 1844, 8vo) ; (<hi rend="italic">d</hi>) Proverbs (Bodleian MS. Uri 15) ; (<hi rend="italic">e</hi>) Job (Uri 45) ; (<hi rend="italic">f</hi>) Canticles (Merx, <hi rend="italic">Die Saadjanische Ueber-setzung des Hohen Liedes ins Arabische,</hi> Heidelberg, 1882, 8vo). (2) Hebrew Lexicography : Seventy (90 or 91) <hi rend="italic">ἅπαξ λεγόμεvα</hi> to be found in the Bible, published from the Bodl. MS. Hunt. 573, by Dukes (Z. <hi rend="italic">K. M.,</hi> v. 6) and by Benjacob <hi rend="italic">(Debarim Attikim,</hi> i., Leipsic, 1844). (3) Talmudic Literature : (a) Decisions (incorporated in <hi rend="italic">'Ittur,</hi> Venice, 1608, fol. ; and in the book of <hi rend="italic">Responsa, Sha'are Sedek,</hi> Salonica, 1792, 4to) ; (δ) On the laws of inheritance (Bodl. MS. Hunt. 630). (4) Liturgy, both in prose and poetry :</p><p>(a) <hi rend="italic">Siddur</hi> (Bodleian MS. Uri 261);<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="8"> The original codex on brownish paper, in square characters of Babylonian handwriting (14th cent.), is defective at beginning and end. The supplement at the beginning, containing also later matter, </note> (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) <hi rend="italic">Arabischer Midrasch (!)</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">zu den Zehn Geboten,</hi> in Hebrew letters (MS. Jellinek of Vienna, with Hebrew and German translation by W. Eisenstadter, Vienna, 1868, 8vo). (5) Religious Philosophy: (a) Commentary on the</p><p><hi rend="italic">Sepher Yesirah,</hi> MS. Uri 370 <hi rend="italic">{Opp. Add.,</hi> 4to, 89), contains the earlier part of a Heb. trans, in a modern hand ; (δ) <hi rend="italic">Kitab al-Amânât wa'l-I'tiqâdât</hi> (Landauer, Leyden, 1880, 8vo), translated into Hebrew by Yehudah Ibn Tibbon (<hi rend="italic">editio princeps,</hi> Constantinople, 1562, 4to), and by R. Berekhyah Hannakdan, author of the <hi rend="italic">Mishele Shu'alim</hi> (printed only in part ; see Dukes, <hi rend="italic">Beiträge,</hi> pp. 20, 22) ; nine chapters have been translated into German (Fürst, Leipsic, 1845, 12mo), and parts into English <hi rend="italic">(Two Treatises,</hi> by P. Allix, London, 1707, 8vo).</p><p>II. <hi rend="italic">Works now lost, but the existence of which is testified to by</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">contemporary and later authors.—</hi> (1) An Arabic translation of, and in part commentary on, most, if not all, the other books of the Bible.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="9"> is in S. Arabian handwriting. The well-known “Ten reasons for Sounding the Trumpet on the Day of Memorial ” are not found in this Siddur (against Rapoport, <hi rend="italic">ut supra,</hi> note 21). The three poetical pieces published as five by Rosenberg <hi rend="italic">{Kobes,</hi> ii., Berlin, 1856) form an integral part of the <hi rend="italic">Siddur,</hi> but bear on the surface marks of having been taken from a second-hand, if not a third-hand, copy, as the editor admits with regard to the “second petition.” The “Two Petitions” must have served Ibn Gebirol (Avicebkon) as a model for the latter </note> (2) Lexical Treatises : Book of Interpretations (<hi rend="italic">Sepher Pithronim,</hi> or Collection (<hi rend="italic">Iggeron).</hi><note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="10"> or liturgical part of his מלכות בתר , just as he and others after him silently utilized Se'adyah’s philosophy. </note> <hi rend="italic"/>(3) Grammatical Treatises : (a) Elegancy of the Hebrew Tongue—(a) Treatise on the Changes, <hi rend="italic">(ß)</hi> Treatise on the Combinations, (γ) Treatise on <hi rend="italic">Dagesh</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Rapheh,</hi> (δ) Treatise on the Letters צ, Π, H, K<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="11"> See <hi rend="italic">Hoboth Hallebaboth</hi> (preface) and <hi rend="italic">Sibbub</hi> (Travels) of R. Peth-ahyah of Ratisbon (London, 1861, 8vo, p. 22). </note>; (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) Treatise on Punctuation<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="12"> <hi rend="italic">L.-B. d. Orients,</hi> x. coll. 516, 541, 684. </note>; (c) Treatise on Right Reading<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="13"> <hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi> coll. 516, 518. </note>;—it is not impossible that the first four constituted one work and the last two another work. (4) Talmudic Literature : (a) Translation of the <hi rend="italic">Mishnah</hi><note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="14"> See Rashi on Psalm xlv. 10. </note> <hi rend="italic"/>; (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) Methodology of the (Babylonian) Talmud<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="15"> <hi rend="italic"/><hi rend="italic">L.-B. d. Or.,</hi> x. 518. </note>; (c) Treatise on Bills<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="16"> <hi rend="italic"/><hi rend="italic">Sibbub</hi> (as in note 5 above). </note>; (<hi rend="italic">d)</hi> Treatise on Deposits<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="17"> See <hi rend="italic">Shem Haggedolini</hi> (Vilna, 1852, 8vo), ii. leaf 16a, col. 2. </note>; (<hi rend="italic">e)</hi> Treatise on Oaths<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="18"> See <hi rend="italic">Sha'are Sedek (ut supra),</hi> leaf 17b. </note>; (<hi rend="italic">f)</hi> Treatise on Prohibited Degrees<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="19"> See R. Menahem b. Shelomoh Iebeth Meir (commonly called Meiri) on <hi rend="italic">Aboth</hi> (Vienna, 1854, 8vo, Introduction, p. 17). </note>; (<hi rend="italic">g</hi>) Treatise on <hi rend="italic">Impura et Pura,</hi> including <hi rend="italic">Hilekhoth Niddah</hi><note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="20"> See Rapoport, <hi rend="italic">l.c.,</hi> note 20. </note> <hi rend="italic"/>;—it is very possible that those marked <hi rend="italic">c</hi> to <hi rend="italic">f</hi> constituted one book, just as the treatise marked <hi rend="italic">g</hi> constituted one book. (5) Calendaric Literature : <hi rend="italic">Sepher Hdibbur</hi> (Treatise on Intercalation).<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="21"> See Pinsker, <hi rend="italic">Likkute Kadmoniyyoth</hi> (Vienna, 1860, p. 174, note </note> (6) Apologetics : Treatise on Investigations.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="22"> See Rapoport, <hi rend="italic">l.c.,</hi> note 19. </note> (7) Polemics : <hi rend="italic">(a)</hi> against Karaism—(a) 'Anan,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="23"> See <hi rend="italic">L.-B. d. Or.,</hi> xii. coll. 101, 102. </note> <hi rend="italic">(β)</hi> Ibn Sakkawiyyah,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="24"> See <hi rend="italic">Sion</hi> (Frankfort-on-Main, 1842-43, 8vo), ii. p. 137. </note> (γ) Ibn Zitta (or Zutta)<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="25"> See Pinsker <hi rend="italic">(ut supra),</hi> p. 103. </note>; (δ) against the Rabbanite Hivvi al-Balkhi<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="26"> <hi rend="italic">Sion</hi> (as before). </note>; (c) against the Karaite Ben Asher (the completer of the <hi rend="italic">Massoreth</hi>; see <hi rend="italic">L.-B. d. Or.,</hi> x. 684). (8) The nature of the <hi rend="italic">Sepher</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Haggalui</hi> cited by Babad II. and Ab. b. Hiyya in his <hi rend="italic">Sepher Hdibbur</hi> is not clear.</p><p>III. <hi rend="italic">Works ascribed to Se'adyah the authorship of which is not sufficiently proven.</hi> —(1) The commentary on Canticles edited by Yishak Ibn 'Akrish (Constantinople, 1577, 4to), and that published by L. Margaliyyoth at Frankfort-on-Oder, 1777<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="27"> On this commentator see Ibn 'Ezra on Exodus xxi. 24. From this passage we learn that Se'adyah and Ben Zitta were contemporaries, and even had oral controversies with one another. </note>. (2) The well-known piece of didactic poetry which gives account of all the letters of the Bible, how many times they occur, &amp;amp;c. <hi rend="italic">(editio princeps,</hi> Venice, 1538, at the end of Elias Levita’s <hi rend="italic">Massoreth Hammass.).</hi></p><p>IV. <hi rend="italic">Works ascribed to Se'adyah by mistake.—</hi> (1) The Commentary</p><p>on Daniel commonly found in the Rabbinic Bibles belongs to another Rab Se'adyah, who lived at least two hundred years later, and was a native either of France or the south of Germany. (2) The Commentary on the <hi rend="italic">Sepher Yesirah,</hi> printed with the text and three other commentaries at Mantua in 1562, 4to. (3) The Book on Lots <hi rend="italic">(Sepher Haggoraloth),</hi> often printed separately and in conjunction with similar works. (4) <hi rend="italic">Eben Happilosophim (Lapis Philosophorum),</hi> ascribed to him by R. Mosheh Butrial (Mantua edition of the <hi rend="italic">Sepher Yesirah</hi> as above). (S. M. S. - S. )</p><p>1, in <hi rend="italic">Nispahim).</hi></p><pb xml:id="eb09-21-s01-0122" facs="encyclopediabrit21newyrich_raw_0140.jp2"/>

</div></body></text></TEI>