<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="encyclopediabrit21newyrich_raw_0140.jp2" type="entry" xml:id="eb09-21-s01-0122-05" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SAAVEDRA, <hi rend="smallcaps">Angel de</hi></label>
, <hi rend="smallcaps">Duke of Rivas</hi> (1791-1865), Spanish poet and politician, was born at Cordova in 1791, and fought with bravery in the Spanish War of Independence. From 1813 to 1820 he lived in retirement in An- dalucia, but in the latter year he sided actively with the revolutionary party, and in consequence had to go into exile in 1823. He lived successively in England, Malta, and France until 1834, when he received permission to return to Spain, shortly afterwards succeeding his brother as duke of Rivas. In 1836 he became minister of the interior under Isturiz, and along with his chief had again to leave the country. Having returned with Maria Christina in 1844, he again held a portfolio for a short time in 1854 ; and during the last two decades of his life he was ambassador at Naples, Paris, and Florence for considerable periods. He died in 1865.</p><p>In 1813 he published <hi rend="italic">Ensayos poeticos,</hi> and between that date and his first exile several tragedies of his composition <hi rend="italic">[Aliatar,</hi> 1814 ; <hi rend="italic">El Duque d' Aquitania,</hi> 1814 ; <hi rend="italic">Lanuza,</hi> 1822) were put upon the stage. <hi rend="italic">Tanto vales quanto ticncs,</hi> a comedy, appeared in 1834, <hi rend="italic">Don Alvaro,</hi> a tragedy, in 1835, and two other dramatic compositions in 1842. Saavedra was also the author of <hi rend="italic">El Moro Exposito,</hi> a narrative poem in ballad metre (two volumes), and <hi rend="italic">Florinda,</hi> an epic romance.</p></div></body></text></TEI>