<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>to be situated in the depths of Guiana. He returned to England the same year, and soon afterwards published an account of his expedition. In the following year he was one of the admirals in the successful expedition against Cadiz, under the command of Howard and the Earl of Essex : and in 1597 he sailed with the same commanders against the /Yzores. Soon after these expeditions we find him assiduously engaged in parliamentary business. His speeches evince a knowledge of political economy far superior to any man of his time. In 1600 he was sent on a joint embassy with Lord Cobham to Flanders, and on his return made governor of Jersey.</p><p>Queen Elizabeth died in the beginning of the year 1603 ; and with her Raleigh’s glory and felicity sunk, never to rise again. Upon the accession of James, Sir Walter lost his interest at court, was stripped of his preferments, and accused of a plot against the king. He was arraigned at Winchester, and, on his trial, insulted with the most shocking brutality by the famous Coke, attorney-general, who influenced the jury to convict him without any legal proof of his guilt. After a month’s imprisonment, however, in daily expectation of his execution, he was reprieved and sent to the Tower; and his estates were given to Car, earl of Somerset, the king’s favourite. During this confinement he wrote many of his most valuable pieces, particularly his History of the World. In March 1615, after sixteen years’ imprisonment, he obtained his liberty, and immediately began to prepare for another voyage to Guiana, which proved equally abortive and ruinous. In the year 1618, he returned from this fatal voyage to England, where he was soon afterwards seized, imprisoned, and beheaded. He was sacrificed by the pusillanimous monarch to appease the Spaniards, who, whilst Raleigh lived, thought every part of their dominions in danger. He was executed in Old Palace Yard, and buried in St Margaret’s adjoining, in the sixty-sixth year of his age. His behaviour on the scaffold was manly, unaffected, cheerful, and easy. Being asked by the executioner which way he would lay his head, he answered, “ So the heart be right, it is no matter which way the head lies.” He was a man of admirable parts, extensive knowledge, undaunted resolution, and perhaps the best prose writer of his age. His great work, the History of the World, is a truly remarkable performance, both for matter and for style. It has often been reprinted in folio. An edition of his whole works was published at Oxford in 1829, in eight volumes octavo.</p><p>RALPH, James, an ingenious historical and political writer, of whose birth and country nothing has been ascertained. He was first known as a schoolmaster in Philadelphia, in North America. He came to England about the beginning of the reign of George I. and wrote some things in the dramatic way, which were not received with great applause ; but though he did not succeed as a poet, he was a very ingenious prose-writer. He wrote a History of England, commencing with the Stuarts, which is much esteemed; and so also were his political essays and pamphlets, some of which were looked upon as masterpieces. His last publication, the Case of Authors by Profession, is an excellent and entertaining performance. He died in 1762.</p><p>RAMA, or Ramla, a considerable town of Palestine, situated in one of the most fertile and extensive districts of the Holy Land ; though at the time when Dr Clarke visited the country it was almost deserted, in consequence of the ravages of the plague. It seems doubtful, however, whether this was the ancient city described in Scripture. Some ascribe its origin to the Moslems ; yet this can scarcely have been the case, as it is distinctly mentioned by St Jerome. Rama was a splendid city, well fortified, exceedingly populous, adorned with stately buildings, and abounding in all the luxuries of the East, during the time of the Crusaders. It was one of the first cities that fell into the hands of the Crusaders. In its neighbourhood many ancient ruins arc</p><p>RAM</p><p>still to be seen. It is twenty-five miles west-north-west from Jerusalem.</p><p>RAMAGIRY, a town and fortress of the south of India, and province of Mysore. The fort is situated upon a rock, and is of considerable strength, although it surrendered to the British in 1791 without any resistance. The country in the vicinity is very wild, being overrun with woods, deep jungle, and dreadfully infested with tigers. There is but little cultivation, the peasants being chiefly employed in the breeding of cattle. In this hilly tract there is a very mild race of men, who subsist on game, wild roots, herbs and fruits, and a little grain, which they purchase from the farmers in exchange for drugs, honey, and wax. It is fifty-miles north-east from Seringapatam. Long. 77. 33. E. Lat. 12. 44. N.</p><p>RAMBERT, Sτ, a tow-n of France, in the department of the Loire, and arrondissement of Montbrison. It is situated on the river Loire, near to its source, but where it is navigable. It has a hospital, and contains 430 houses, with 2600 inhabitants. It has a very extensive trade in wine : and in the vicinity there are several extensive iron forges. There is another town of the same name in the department of the Ain, and arrondissement of Belley. It is situated in a valley between two mountains, portions of the Jura range, on the river Albarine, and contains 390 houses, with 2430 inhabitants, w<hi rend="sup">,</hi>ho carry on considerable trade in hempen cloth.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">RAMBERVILLERs, a large market-town of France, in the department of the Vosges, and the arrondissement of Epinal. It stands on a mountain, at the foot of which runs the river Mortagne. It has a considerable number of iron forges in the vicinity, and much woollen and linen cloth is manufactured ; and there are mills for making paper. In 1836 its population amounted to 4990. Long. 7. 5. 18. E. Lat. 48. 20. 43. N.</hi></p><p>RAMBOUILLET, an arrondissement of the department of the Seine and Oise, in France, extending over 518 square miles. It is divided into five cantons, and these into 119 communes, containing 66,514 inhabitants. The capital, of the same name, is situated between two woods, has a royal palace and park, and in 1836 contained 3066 inhabitants. There is here a large farm celebrated for breeding sheep with the finest wool.</p><p>RAMAZZINI, Bernardin, an Italian physician, born at Carpi, near Modena, in 1633. He was professor of physic in the university of Modena during eighteen years ; in 1700 he accepted an invitation from Padua, where he was made rector of the college; andin 1714hedied. His works were collected and published in London in 1716; and of these, his treatise <hi rend="italic">De Morbis Artiflcum,</hi>  or on the maladies peculiar to artificers, will always be esteemed curious and useful.</p><p>RAMDROOG, a hill-fortress of Hindustan, in the province of Bejapoor, situated on the north side of the Mal-purba river. It was taken from the Mahrattas<hi rend="sub">1</hi> in 1785, by Tippoo Sultan, but w&gt;as restored to them after the war of 1793.</p><p>RAMERGH, a town of Hindustan, in the province of Hyderabad, belonging to the Nizam. Long. 79. 32. E. Lat. 18. 31. N.</p><p>RAMESES, in <hi rend="italic">Ancient Geography,</hi>  a tow-n built by the Israelites during their bondage in Egypt, and whence the Exodus took place. It must have been towards and not far from the Arabian Gulf, seeing that in their third station the Israelites arrived on its shore.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Rameses, king of Lower Egypt when Jacob went thither with his family, in the 1706th year before file Christian era. Ancient authors mention several other kings of Egypt of the same name ; and it is believed that one of these princes erected, in the temple of the Sun at Thebes, the magnificent obelisk which the Emperor Constantine caused to be removed to Alexandria in the year 334. After the death</hi></p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>