<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>development of her story. On the contrary, she selected a species of machinery afforded her by the most vulgar conceptions entertained of the Catholic religion, when established in its paramount superiority ; and instead of contemplating it calmly as reflected in the glass of history, she adopted all the conventional and ready-made horrors that came in her way; and had thus at her disposal the usual apparatus of monks, spies, dungeons, the mute obedience of the familiars of the Inquisition, and the dark, domineering spirit of the crafty emissaries of Rome. “ This fortunate adoption,” as Sir Walter Scott calls it, “ placed in the hands of the authoress, a set of agents powerful enough to act forcibly on imaginations in which they were associated with all imaginable kinds of atrocity and wickedness, and furnished at once the means of producing a strong effect, without the trouble of inventing new characters, or creating original combinations. But it may be questioned whether such agents, with all their conventional attributes, were suited to the purposes for which they were employed, or whether, evcn by their instrumentality, any tinge of probability could be imparted to those parts of the story which are most at variance with the ordinary course of human actions and events.” The <hi rend="italic">Italian,</hi>  however, was well received by the public, to whom delineations which flatter their religious prideorhatred are always welcome; and after its publication in 1797, the world were not favoured with any more of Mrs. Radcliffe’s works. “ Like an actress in full possession of applauded powers, she chose to retire from the stage in the very blaze of her fame ; and, for more than twenty years, an imagination naturally so prolific, was, for reasons which we are left in vain to conjecture, condemned to inaction and sterility.”</p><p>The tenor of Mrs. Radcliffe’s domestic life seems to have been peculiarly calm and sequestered. She appears to have declined the notoriety which, in London society, usually attaches to persons of literary distinction ; and perhaps no author whose works were so universally read and admired, was so little known personally, even to the most bustling of that class who rest their pretensions to fashion upon the selection of literary society. She no doubt consulted her own feelings, happy in equally avoiding the stare of the curious or the scrutiny of the malignant. Nor did it at all disturb her domestic comforts, although many of her admirers believed, that from brooding over imaginary terrors, her reason had at length been overcome, and that the gifted author of the <hi rend="italic">Mysteries of Udolpho</hi>  existed only as the inmate of a private madhouse. For this belief, however, there neither was, nor ever had been the most distant foundation ; although the rumour on which it was founded had been generally spread, and confidently repeated in print as well as in conversation. During the last twelve years of her life, Mrs. Radcliffe suffered from a spasmodic asthma, which considerably affected both her health and her spirits. This chronic disorder, however, at length took a more fatal turn, on the 9th of January 1823, and on the 7th of February ensuing, it terminated the life of this ingenious and gifted woman, at her own house in London.</p><p>Mrs. Radcliffe, considered as an author, is fully entitled to take her place amongst those who have been distinguished as the founders of a class or school. She led the way in a species of composition, which has since been attempted by many, but in which no one has attained, or even approached the excellencies of the original inventor. The species of romance which she introduced bears nearly the same relation to the novel that a melodrame does to the legitimate drama. It does not appeal to the judgment, by searching delineations of human feeling, nor stir the passions by scenes of deep pathos, nor awaken the fancy, by tracing out the higher marks of life and manners, nor excite mirth, by strong representations of the ludicrous or the humorous. It attains its interest neither by the path of comedy nor by</p><p>that of tragedy ; and yet it has, notwithstanding, a deep, decided, and powerful effect, gained by means independent of both ; in other words, by an appeal to the passion of fear, whether excited by natural dangers, or by the suggestions of superstition. The force of the production consists in the delineation of external incidents, whilst the character of the agents are entirely subordinate to the scenes in which they are placed, and only distinguished by such outlines as to make them seem appropriate to their respective situations. The persons introduced bear the features, not of individuals, but of the class to which they belong ; and if they be dressed in the proper costume, and converse in language sufficiently appropriate to their stations and qualities, nothing more is required. The primary object is the generation of awe and terror, and everything ministers to the production of this effect. It is enough if the characters be truly and forcibly sketched in outline ; they are accessaries rather than principals, and for the most part rather passive than active, so that in throwing upon them and their actions just enough of that dubious light which mystery requires, Mrs. Radcliffe does all that is requisite for the accomplishment of her object. It were easy to find fault with a proceeding like this, which, dispensing with scenes of passion such as those of Richardson, or delineations of life and manners, as in the pages of Fielding and Smollett, carries us back to the fare of the nursery, and gorges us with the wild and improbable fictions of an overheated imagination. And there might be some truth in this, if it were only predicated of the crowd of copyists who came forward as imitators of Mrs. Radcliffe, and assumed her wand, without having the power of wielding it with the same magical effect. But no author can be arraigned for the deficiencies of servile imitators, who present an obscure, distorted, and indistinct outline of what is in itself clear, precise, and distinct ; nor can it be truly said that the applause with which the romances of Mrs. Radcliffe were received, argued a great and increasing degradation of the public taste, the corruption of which is almost never the consequence of pow<hi rend="sup">ι</hi>er and originality ; whilst the inferiority of the servile race is much more likely to put the style theyimitate out of fashion, than to engraft its peculiarities upon that of a nation. [See Sir Walter Scott’s <hi rend="italic">Biographical Notice of Mrs Ann Radcliffe.]    </hi><hi rend="smallcaps">(a.)</hi></p><p>RADCLIFFE, Db. John, an English physician of great eminence in his time, was born at Wakefield in Yorkshire in 1650. He was educated at Oxford, and enrolled himself in the physical line; but it was remarked that he recommended himself much more by his ready wit and vivacity, than by any extraordinary acquisitions in learning. He began to practise at Oxford in 1675, but never paid any regard to established rules, which he censured whenever he thought fit, with great freedom and acrimony ; and as this drew all the old practitioners upon him, he lived in a state of continual hostility with them. He died in 1714 ; and if he never attempted to write any thing himself, he has perpetuated his memory by founding a fine library at Oxford, to preserve the writings of other men.</p><p>RADE, sometimes called Bade by the Forest, a city of the Prussian government of Cleves, in the circle of Len-nep. It is fortified, and having been burned down in 1802, has since been regularly built. It contains 510 houses, with 4950 inhabitants, diligently employed in manufactures of cloths, hosiery, serges, and hardware.</p><p>RADICAL, in general, something that serves as a basis or foundation. Hence physicians talk much of a radical moisture. In grammar, the appellation of <hi rend="italic">radical</hi>  is applied to primitives, in contradistinction to compounds and derivatives. Algebraists also speak of the radical sign of quantities, which is the character expressing their roots.</p><p>RADICLE, that part of the seeds of all plants which upon vegetating becomes their root, and is discoverable by the microscope.</p></body></text></TEI>