<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p><hi rend="italic">false meshes</hi>  equidistantly, then twenty rows of <hi rend="italic">dead</hi>  netting, then a row with five <hi rend="italic">false meshes ;</hi>  repeat this manœuvre ; then net thirty-six rows of <hi rend="italic">dead</hi>  netting, and the next row in <hi rend="italic">double</hi>  twine ; thus you have an upper and a lower row, as shown in fig. 5, the dotted lines representing the lower row. Cut off the thread which has worked the <hi rend="italic">upper</hi>  row, leaving an end ; empty your needle, and wind on it the thread that proceeds from the <hi rend="italic">lower</hi>  row, and work on with the single twine as follows, taking care, however, to pick up only the loops of the <hi rend="italic">lower</hi>  row as you go round. Net on the same spool fourteen rows of <hi rend="italic">dead</hi>  netting, then at equal distances in the circumference of the fifteenth row set in eight <hi rend="italic">stole </hi>meshes, then net two rows of <hi rend="italic">dead</hi>  netting, in the next row eight stole meshes in a line with the others ; repeat this action three times more. After you have for the fifth time set in your <hi rend="italic">stole</hi>  meshes, net a row of plain netting ; lay aside the two-inch spool, and take a twelve-inch and net one row. The <hi rend="italic">valve</hi>  is now finished, and must be reflected inwards to gain its right position. You now take your needle, charged with single twine, and join on to that end which was left at the upper row where the valve issued from the <hi rend="italic">body</hi>  of the engine ; with the two-inch spool net eleven rows of dead netting. In the next row set in five <hi rend="italic">false meshes</hi>  at equal distances each from the other, and continue to set in these at every third row eleven times in the same line. This done, make seven rows of <hi rend="italic">dead</hi>  netting, then one row on a four-inch spool in <hi rend="italic">double</hi>  twine. Through this last row a pliant stick is passed, about six feet long, and bent into a <hi rend="italic">bow</hi>  (BBB, fig. S) ; a piece of cord keeps the extremities in place, answering to the string of the archer’s bow ; the lower meshes of the net’s mouth are strung on this cord, see fig. 8. A weight is generally attached to the <hi rend="italic">bow</hi>  at its extremities, somew'here towards BB. Four hoops are lashed round the net at HHHH, to prevent its collapsing ; these are larger as they proceed from the point to the mouth, and are made of slighter wood than the bow, the smallest being about one foot three inches diameter, and the largest two feet.</p><p>Some <hi rend="italic">hoop-nets</hi>  have more tnan one <hi rend="italic">valve.</hi>  In that case the hoops must always be placed at the entrance of the <hi rend="italic">valves,</hi>  and many netters make a row of <hi rend="italic">double</hi>  twine at those parts, to give additional strength where there is most strain on the netting. The large loops at the bottom of the <hi rend="italic">funnel</hi>  are tied together, in <hi rend="italic">fasces</hi>  of equal number of loops, to four lines, and these are made fast to another line which is threaded through the last row of meshes belonging to the point of the <hi rend="italic">body,</hi>  and which, being drawn tight, closes up the entrance at that part. All the lines are then tied to a support at P, and thus the net is kept extended. The principle of this engine is analogous to that of the common mouse-trap. When there is only one valve (as in fig. 8, V), the fisherman withdraws the fish by loosing the line that closes the body of the engine at P ; but when there are more than one valve, he makes a <hi rend="italic">regard</hi>  in the <hi rend="italic">body </hi>between each hoop. A <hi rend="italic">regard</hi>  is thus made : Net round and round, and when arrived at the part wherein you wish to put a <hi rend="italic">regard, return on your worh ;</hi>  and when you again come to the place where you altered your mode of netting, return again ; and thus continue until you have made the <hi rend="italic">regard</hi>  of sufficient length, then work round and round as before.</p><p>A <hi rend="italic">tunnel</hi>  for partridges is made like the hoop-net, but without valves.</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">trawl</hi>  is a very large and rapacious net, and much discussion has been held as to whether it should be permitted. It would seem, however, upon a careful examination of evidence, that, under proper restrictions, it is not detrimental to the fisheries. This engine is composed of two separate pieces, called the <hi rend="italic">upper</hi>  and the <hi rend="italic">lower leaf ; </hi>the meshes are about two inches square. For the <hi rend="italic">under leaf</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">blade,</hi>  net 160 loops in <hi rend="italic">double</hi>  twine, two rows, then with single twine net a plain row ; in the next, set in a <hi rend="italic">stole </hi>mesh at about the sixth mesh from the beginning, and another at about the sixth mesh from the end of the row ; net three rows of <hi rend="italic">dead</hi>  netting, then set in <hi rend="italic">stole</hi>  meshes as before; repeat this once again, afterwards go on setting in <hi rend="italic">stole meshes</hi>  less frequently, t. <hi rend="italic">e.</hi>  leave five rows of dead netting between, until the width of the <hi rend="italic">blade</hi>  is reduced to thirty-six meshes, then net about five feet for the <hi rend="italic">hose</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">tail</hi>  H, fig. 9. The <hi rend="italic">wings</hi>  are now to be set on to this <hi rend="italic">leaf. </hi>For this purpose you must begin working at the other extremity, or top of the <hi rend="italic">leaf,</hi>  as at T or <hi rend="italic">t ;</hi>  net fifty-six loops and stop ; return on your work ; net again to the end of your row (the third), and here, quite at the extremity, set in a <hi rend="italic">false</hi>  mesh ; but when, in the course of netting row after row, you come to the <hi rend="italic">false</hi>  meshes, do <hi rend="italic">not</hi>  take them up, but let them <hi rend="italic">hang,</hi>  as is shown in fig. 9 at B and B of the <hi rend="italic">wings</hi>  W and W. At the <hi rend="italic">commencement</hi>  of every row which alternates with those to which you add a <hi rend="italic">false </hi>mesh, at about three loops from the beginning, set in a <hi rend="italic">stole </hi>mesh ; thus <hi rend="italic">the false</hi>  meshes will always be on one side, and the <hi rend="italic">stole</hi>  meshes on the other side of the <hi rend="italic">wing,</hi>  which will thus be diminished at last to eighteen meshes. When this is effected, net two rows in <hi rend="italic">double</hi>  twine, not adding or diminishing. Thus one <hi rend="italic">wing</hi>  is done ; net the other in the same way, and take care that the one is exactly the same as the other. The <hi rend="italic">under</hi>  leaf being now finished, we pass on to the structure of the <hi rend="italic">upper blade,</hi>  fig. 10. Net 180 <hi rend="italic">loops </hi>in <hi rend="italic">double</hi>  twine, two rows ; then with single twine forty rows of <hi rend="italic">dead</hi>  netting; diminish evenly and gradually from 180 to 160 meshes, taking notice that this reduction must be made before you come to a level with the <hi rend="italic">double</hi>  rows whence the <hi rend="italic">wings</hi>  rose in the other <hi rend="italic">blade.</hi>  Diminish from 160 to thirty-six, as you did when working down the <hi rend="italic">lower leaf,</hi>  making the <hi rend="italic">hose</hi>  as before. The <hi rend="italic">blades</hi>  being now finished, must be joined together down their sides, as the sides of a sack are ; and a rope, acting as a binding along the seams, is sewn on, in the same way as the <hi rend="italic">head-rope</hi>  of the <hi rend="italic">trammel.</hi>  Round the top of the <hi rend="italic">upper blade</hi>  a rope is strung through the meshes, and carried round the <hi rend="italic">bosom </hi>BBB, fig. 9, being sewn to, and not threaded through, the <hi rend="italic">hanging false loops</hi>  of the <hi rend="italic">wings</hi>  W, W. The two blades are then sewn together at certain parts to form <hi rend="italic">pockets,</hi>  in the direction of A, A, A, A, A, A; <hi rend="italic">oooooo,</hi>  being the orifice of the pockets. At L, L, loops of rope are bent, to which lines are hitched for hauling the net out of the sea into the boat. The two <hi rend="italic">blades</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">leaves</hi>  must be <hi rend="italic">exactly </hi>of the same length ; for, when joined, the top row of the <hi rend="italic">wings</hi>  must be even with the top row of the back of the net or <hi rend="italic">upper blade,</hi>  and the <hi rend="italic">hose</hi>  should meet no less accurately at the bottom. When the <hi rend="italic">trawl</hi>  is in the sea, a long beam of about thirty feet in length and seven inches in circumference is lashed to the top of the net, keeping the <hi rend="italic">wings</hi>  and back extended from point to point. This beam is let into irons, called <hi rend="italic">trawl-heads,</hi>  at each extremity, which serve to sink it. A heavy rope, usually made of old netting, tightly twisted and bound round with strong twine, is lashed along the bosom of the net. Thus <hi rend="italic">mounted,</hi>  the engine is lowered into the sea, being <hi rend="italic">trailed</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">trawled</hi>  along the bottom by means of a rope attached to the boat’s mast, and communicating with each end of the <hi rend="italic">beam</hi>  by a <hi rend="italic">bridle.</hi>  The <hi rend="italic">bosom</hi>  touches the ground, and the <hi rend="italic">upper blade</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">beam </hi>floats over it ; the <hi rend="italic">bosom’s</hi>  rope disturbs the fish at the bottom ; they are, however, stopped from escaping, by striking against the <hi rend="italic">upper blade,</hi>  which extends over the <hi rend="italic">bosom,</hi>  so they swim down the <hi rend="italic">trawl</hi>  to the hose; but this is tied up, so they next attempt to return towards the mouth of the net ; but in their way they fall into the pockets, which only open inwards towards the <hi rend="italic">hose,</hi>  and thus are secured. <hi rend="italic">Λ </hi><hi rend="italic">day-net</hi>  is used for catching larks from 14th September to 14th November; after that, until 25th February, the <hi rend="italic">trammel.</hi>  The reason of this is, that during the latter division of</p></body></text></TEI>