<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p><hi rend="italic">bis,</hi>  which they often bear, was bestowed upon them by an error of Seba’s, who, misconstruing a passage in Margrave, applied to these reptiles the designation of a tribe of people.</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">first subdivision</hi>  of the genus contains the Monitors <hi rend="italic">properly so called</hi>  (genus Varanus, Dum.), @@<hi rend="sup">1</hi>  distinguished by small and numerous scales on the head, limbs, beneath the abdomen, and around the tail, the last-named portion being surmounted by a kind of keel formed by a double range of projecting scales. The thighs want the peculiar range of pores observable among several other groups of saurians. The species are confined exclusively to the ancient world, although Seba, and in later years Daudin, have stated the contrary. Travellers report that they prey on the eggs of water-fowl and on those of crocodiles, and that chameleons, young turtles, and fishes, have been found in their stomachs. M. Leschenault de Latour even states that they combine together on the banks of lakes and rivers for the purpose of attacking such quadrupeds as come to assuage their thirst, and that he has seen them attempt to drown a young stag which was trying to cross a river. He moreover found the thigh-bone of a sheep in one which he dissected.</p><p>The monitor of the Nile (A. <hi rend="italic">Nilοtica,</hi>  Linn. <hi rend="italic">Varanus Niloticus,</hi>  Dum.), called <hi rend="italic">Ouaran</hi>  by the Arabs, has the teeth strong and conical, the posterior becoming rounded by age. The general colour is brown, with paler and darker points, forming various compartments, among which are transverse rows of large oceliated spots, which on the tail become ring-like. The tail is rounded at the base, and surmounted by a keel throughout its whole length. This species grows to the length of five or six feet A vulgar belief prevails among the Egyptians, that it is a young crocodile hatched in drier earth than usual. Its figure is engraved on the ancient monuments of Egypt, probably in connection with the fact of its preying on the eggs of the crocodile. To the monitors also belong the animal called scink (A. <hi rend="italic">sciηcus,</hi>  Merr., but not of Linn., <hi rend="italic">Var. arenarius, </hi>Dum.), a small species, very abundant in Libya, Syria, Egypt, and Arabia, where it frequents rather dry and sandy soils. It is called <hi rend="italic">Ouaran el hard</hi>  by the Arabs. Its teeth are compressed, cutting, and pointed, the tail almost without ridge, and a great part of it rounded. Its habits are more terrestrial than those of the preceding, and it may be regarded as identical with the land-crocodile of Herodotus. The jugglers of Cairo pluck out its teeth, and then employ it in the performance of tricks. Many other monitors are found both in Africa and India. @@<hi rend="sup">2</hi></p><p>The <hi rend="italic">second subdivision</hi>  of Baron Cuvier’s monitors consists of such as have angular plates upon the head, and large rectangular scales beneath the abdomen and around the tail. The skin of the throat is clothed with small scales, and forms a couple of transverse folds. There is a row of pores upon the thighs.</p><p>This subdivision corresponds to the genus Teyus of Merrem, and several minor groups may be indicated in it. For example, those called Dracænæ by Lacépède have the scales raised up into ridges, as among the crocodile tribe, and forming crests along the tail, which is compressed. An eatable species (<hi rend="italic">Mon. crocodilinus,</hi>  Merr.) occurs in Guiana, where it inhabits holes in the vicinity of marshes. It is said to swim with difficulty, to run rather swiftly, to climb trees with facility, and to bite severely. It attains the length of six feet and is characterized by some scattered ridges of scales upon the back. Another and much smaller species <hi rend="italic">(Drαc. bicurinαtα.)</hi>  likewise inhabits South America. (See Plate CCCCXXXI. fig. 1.) The little group of safeguards <hi rend="italic">(Sauvegardes,</hi>  Cuv. the restricted genus <hi rend="italic">Monitor</hi>  of Fitzinger) have all the scales of the back and tail without ridges. Their teeth are dentated, although those of the back part of the mouth become rounded by use or age. Some have the tail more or less compressed, and the scales of the abdomen longer than broad. They dwell by the banks of rivers. Such is the very large variegated lizard <hi rend="italic">(L. tequixin),</hi>  well represented by Madame Me-rian at the end of her work on the insects of Surinam. It inhabits Brazil, Guiana, &amp;c. where it attains the length of six feet. It runs rapidly, and plunges into the water when pursued, although it can scarcely be said to swim. It feeds on insects, reptiles, the eggs of poultry and of other birds, and is itself useful as an article of food. Others, distinguished by the name of <hi rend="italic">Ameiva,</hi>  scarcely differ from the preceding sections of the genus Teyus, except in the tail being rounded, and no way compressed, and furnished, as well as the abdomen, with transverse rows of square scales. The scales of the abdomen are rather broader than long. The species of this little group may be regarded as the <hi rend="italic">lizards</hi>  of America, that is, as representing in the new world the reptiles which we so designate in the old ; but they differ in wanting the molar teeth, the majority have no collar, and all the scales upon the throat are small. Their heads also are more pyramidal, and they want the osseous plate above the orbits. Several different species have been confounded under the title of <hi rend="italic">Laccrta ameiva.</hi>  The most generally distributed is that named <hi rend="italic">Teyus ameiva</hi>  by Spix. (See Plate CCCCXXXI. fig. 2.) It is of a green colour, with vertical rows of white ocelli, bordered with black upon the flanks.</p><p>The genus Lacerta, Cuv., or lizards properly so called, forms the second principal group of the Lacertine family. They have the back part of the palate armed with two rows of teeth, and are further distinguished from the Ameivas and Safeguards by a collar beneath the neck, formed by a transverse row of broad scales, separated from those of the abdomen by a space, on which there are only minute scales, as on the throat. A portion also of the bones of the cranium projects over the orbits and temples, so that all the upper part of the head is provided with a bony buckler.</p><p>Lizards are remarkable for their lively movements, and light and elegant forms. Their colours are also often brilliant. They pass the winter in a state of torpidity, and are always active and vivacious in proportion to the power of the solar heat. They are often seen stretching themselves on rocks or stones, however heated, and brandishing from time to time their forked tongues, a motion which in some countries has induced the belief of their being venomous, an unfounded idea, we need scarccly say, no creatures being more innocent. They are by no means difficult to tame, but in a state of nature we have usually found them very timorous, although M. Bory St Vincent regards them as being as bold as they are beautiful. “ Nous en avons vu plusieurs saisir bravement au museau des chiens d’arrêt qui les avaient surpris dans quelque pelouse sèche, et ne pas lâcher prise malgré les secouses violentes et les efforts que faisaient ces chiens pour se delivrent.” They are by no means devoid of intelligence, and, though shy and fearful, are decidedly inquisitive in regard to what takes place around them. When raising themselves as high as their little limbs permit, in order to enlarge their “ visible diurnal sphere,” they often exhibit themselves to a quiet and concealed spectator in attitudes of great beauty. They frequently show themselves more alarmed for birds and quadrupeds than for the human race, and they will even acquire a certain degree of tameness when domiciled near</p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi> The term<hi rend="italic">Monitor</hi>  is somewhat injudiciously app lied to this restricted group, in as far as it does not contain the species originally so named, that is, the <hi rend="italic">grande sauvegarde d'Amérique,—Lacerta tequixin</hi>  of I.inn. and Shaw.</p><p>@@@ <hi rend="sup">2</hi> The genera<hi rend="italic">Varanus</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">HeMerma</hi>  form a distinct family ( <hi rend="italic">Varnniens)</hi>  in the system of MM. Dumeril and Bibron. Of the former genus, four are Asiatic, two are from New Holland, one is from the Papous, one from Timor, and three are of African origin. <hi rend="italic">Heluderma horridum</hi>  (the sole species) is the only American member of the family.</p></body></text></TEI>