<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>lingness to permit the performance of any of its duties which might be irksome to him by a deputy.</p><p>From this period Sir Joshua never painted more. The last effort of his pencil was the portrait of Charles James Fox, which was executed in his best style, and shows that his fancy, his imagination, and his other great powers in the art which he professed, remained unabated to the end of his life. When the last touches were given to this picture,</p><p>The hand of Reynolds fell, to rise no more.</p><p>On Thursday the 23d of February 1792, the world was deprived of this amiable man and excellent artist, at the age of sixty-eight years ; a man than whom no one, according to Johnson, had passed through life with more observation of men and manners. The following character of him is said to be the production of Mr Burke.</p><p>“ His illness was long, but borne with a mild and cheerful fortitude, without the least mixture of anything irritable or querulous, agreeably to the placid and even tenor of his whole life. He had from the beginning of his malady a distinct view of his dissolution, which he contemplated with that entire cotnposure which nothing but the innocence, integrity, and usefulness of his life, and an unaffected submission to the will of Providence, could bestow. In this situation he had every consolation from family tenderness, which his tenderness to his family had always merited.</p><p>“ Sir Joshua Reynolds was, on very many accounts, one of the most memorable men of his time ; he was the first Englishman who added the praise of the elegant arts to the other glories of his country. In taste, in grace, in facility, in happy invention, and in the richness and harmony of colouring, he was equal to the great masters of the renowned ages. In portrait he went beyond them ; for he communicated to that description of the art in which English artists are the most engaged, a variety, a fancy, and a dignity, derived from the higher branches, which even those who professed them in a superior manner did not always preserve when they delineated individual nature. His portraits remind the spectator of the invention of history and the amenity of landscape. In painting portraits he appears not to be raised upon that platform, but to descend to it from a higher sphere. His paintings illustrate his lessons, and his lessons seem to be derived from his paintings.</p><p>“ He possessed the theory as perfectly as the practice of his art. To be such a painter, he was a profound and penetrating philosopher.</p><p>“ In full happiness of foreign and domestic fame, admired by the expert in art, and by the learned in science, courted by the great, caressed by sovereign powers, and celebrated by distinguished poets, his native humility, modesty, and candour never forsook him, even on surprise or provocation ; nor was the least degree of arrogance or assumption visible to the scrutinizing eye in any part of his conduct or discourse.</p><p>“ His talents of every kind, powerful from nature, and not meanly cultivated in letters, his social virtues in all the relations and all the habitudes of life, rendered him the centre of a very great and unparalleled variety of agreeable societies, which will be dissipated by his death. He had too much merit not to excite some jealousy, too much innocence to provoke any enmity. The loss of no man of his time can be felt with more sincere, general, and unmixed sorrow.” See Painting.</p><p>REZΛT, a circle of the kingdom of Bavaria, formed out of the ancient Southern Franconia, in the principality of Ans-pach, out of Bavarian Unterland, and the territories of the former free states of Nuremberg, Rottenburg, Windsheim, and Weissenbourg. It extends over 3052 square miles, and is bounded on the north-west by the circle of the Lower Maine, and on the north-east by that of the Upper Maine, on the east by that of the Regen, on the south by that of the Upper Maine, and on the west by the territory of the kingdom of Wirtemberg. The circle is divided into forty-one bailiwicks, which comprehend forty-two cities or towns once walled, fifty-five market-towns, and 2004 villages, with 530,726 inhabitants, of whom the far greater part are Lutherans, and most of the rest still adhere to the Catholic church. It is generally a level or undulating district, whose waters are partly conveyed by the smaller rivers to the Danube, but the greater portion by the Maine to the Rhine. It is the best cultivated, the most populous, and the most productive division of the kingdom. It yields abundance of corn and cattle, some wine, and all the various kinds of common fruits. Its manufactures also are extensive, especially near Nuremberg, but having little water communication, the chief commodities are conveyed by land-carriage.</p><p>RHABDOLOGY, or Rabdology, in arithmetic, a name given by Napier of Merchiston, the inventor of logarithms, to a method of performing some of the more difficult operations of numbers by means of square little rods. Upon these are inscribed the simple numbers ; then, by shifting them according to certain rules, those operations are performed by simply adding or subtracting the numbers as they stand upon the rods.</p><p>RHADAMANTHUS, a severe judge, and king of Lydia. The poets make him one of the three judges of hell.</p><p>RHADEN, a town of the Prussian province of Westphalia, in the government of Minden, and the capital of the circle of the same name, which extends over 180 square miles, inhabited by 30,000 persons. The town is on the new canal, and contains 390 houses, with 2680 inhabitants, who make large quantities of linen and of woollen yam.</p><p>RHAMA, or Rama, an incarnate deity of the first rank, in Indian mythology. Sir William Jones believes he was the Dionysos of the Greeks, whom they named <hi rend="italic">Bromius, </hi>without knowing why ; and <hi rend="italic">Bugenes</hi>  when they represented him <hi rend="italic">honied,</hi>  as well as <hi rend="italic">Lyaois</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">Eleutherios</hi>  the deliverer, and <hi rend="italic">Tryarnbos</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">Dithyrambos</hi>  the triumphant. “ Most of those titles,” says Sir William, “ were adopted by the Romans, by whom he was called <hi rend="italic">Bruma, Tauriformis, Liber,</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">Triumphus ;</hi>  and both nations had records or traditionary accounts of his giving laws to men and deciding their contests, of his improving navigation and commerce, and, what may appear yet more observable, of his conquering India and other countries with an army of satyrs, commanded by no less a personage than Pan ; whom Lil-Hus Gyraldus, on what authority I know not, asserts to have resided in Iberia, ‘ when he had returned,’ says the learned mythologist, ‘ from the Indian war, in which he accompanied Bacchus.’ It were superfluous in a mere essay to run any length in the parallel between this European god and tlle sovereign of Ayodhya, whom the Hindus believe to have been an appearance on earth of the preserving power ; to have been a conqueror of the highest renown, and the deliverer of nations from tyrants, as well as of his consort Sita from the giant Ravan king of Lanca ; and to have commanded in chief a numerous and intrepid race of those large monkeys, which our naturalists, or some of them, have denominated Indian satyrs. This general, the prince of satyrs, was named <hi rend="italic">Hanurnat,</hi>  or ‘ with high cheek-bones ;’ and with workmen of such agility, he soon raised a bridge of rocks over the sea, part of which, say the Hindus, yet remains ; and it is probably the series of rocks to which the Mussulmans or Portuguese have given the foolish name of <hi rend="italic">Adam’s,</hi>  or, as it should be called, <hi rend="italic">Rama’s</hi>  Bridge. Might not this army of satyrs have been only a race of mountaineers, whom Rama, if such a monarch ever existed, had civilized? However that may be, the large breed of Indian apes is at this moment held in high veneration by the Hindus, and fed with devotion by the Brahmins, who seem in two or three places on the banks of the Ganges to have a regular endowment for the support of them ; they live in</p></body></text></TEI>