<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>There still remain two other true crocodiles, described by M. Graves, @@<hi rend="sup">1</hi> and which he regards as new ; the<hi rend="italic">C. Gra-vesii</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">Jtmrnei</hi>  of Bory de St Vincent. Both of them are in the Bordeaux museum. The habitat of the former is believed to be the Congo, and of the latter America. All the bones of the <hi rend="italic">Gravesii</hi>  are as if pierced with small holes, a character they possess in common with some of the alligators. Its head is of the shape of a slender isosceles triangle ; the extremity of the snout is rounded, and its surface covered with great obtuse tubercles, having no regular arrangement. The ninth, tenth, and eleventh teeth of the lower jaw are received into a furrow, as well as the fourth. The colour of the upper part is a dark deep brown, that of the lower a dull yellow. The snout of the <hi rend="italic">Journei </hi>is very slender, approaching to that of the gavials ; it is convex as well as long, and near its extremity is almost cylindrical. The back of this species is of a deep yellowish green ; the flanks are yellowish, and the belly yellow.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Genus Alligator, Cuv. The alligators are by far the most common representatives of this group in the new world ; although, as we have already seen, there are true crocodiles in St Domingo, and probably in many other localities. In most parts of America they are known by the title of cayman, a name apparently of African origin, and applied by the negroes, not to the alligators only, but indifferently to every species of the group. It does not seem to be yet ascertained whether any true caymans are found in the old world. Adanson thought he discovered one in the Senegal ; M. de Beauvais states that he saw one in Guinea ; and Cuvier thinks it most probable that they have their representatives in our hemisphere. They possess all the power and ferocity of the true crocodiles, and in many places are found in astonishing numbers.</hi></p><p>The head of the alligators is not so oblong as that of the true crocodiles ; the snout is broad and obtuse ; the teeth are somewhat unequal, the number ranging from nineteen to twenty-two on each side of each jaw ; the fourth of the under jaw is received, not into a lateral furrow of the upper one, but into a distinct foramen. Their feet are only semi-palmated, and are not denticulated.</p><p><hi rend="italic">A. lucius,</hi>  Cuv.; <hi rend="italic">Croc. Cuvieri,</hi>  Leach. <hi rend="italic">Pike-muzzled alligator.</hi>  This is peculiarly the alligator of the southern parts of North America, including Carolina, the Floridas, and Louisiana. In the Mississippi it ascends as far as the thirty-second degree north, a higher latitude than any species reaches in the old world. In these countries they frequent the muddy banks, and quite bury themselves in the cold season, falling into a lethargic state before the setting in of the frost. @@<hi rend="sup">2</hi>  This sleep is so profound that they may be almost cut to pieces without manifesting any sign of life ; when the warm weather returns, they are soon roused into activity. According to Bosc, their eggs are white, and not larger than those of the turkey. They are good eating, and are prized by the natives, though they partake of the musky smell of the animal. As soon as they escape, the young betake themselves to the water ; but the vast majority become the prey of turtles, fish, and amphibious animals, not excluding the older of their own species. During the first year they feed upon insects and very young fish. Bosc states that he preserved a brood of fifteen. They ate only living insects ; and never captured them except when moving, upon which they darted at them with great velocity. They appeared quite gentle when he took them in his hand. At the end of the first year they are still very feeble creatures; during the second they acquire their formidable teeth. The duration of their existence is not precisely ascertained, but is supposed to equal</p><p>that of man. They never cast their skin ; and on acquiring their full size, few animals can injure them. They can fast long. They live on frogs, fish, aquatic birds, on dogs, hogs, cattle, and any animal they can catch ; when these go to the river to drink, they seize them by the muzzle or leg, and draw them into the water to drown them. “ I used often,” adds the traveller last named, “ to amuse myself, bringing them from their retreats by making my dog bark. Sometimes I used to advance and strike them with my stick, at which they were little disturbed. They never thought of attacking me, and deliberately retired when they found their hunting promised no success.” Though slow on land, they swim with great velocity. In Carolina they make deep burrows, where they pass the whole winter, and even the entire day in summer. Though usually met with on the edges of rivers and lakes, they are sometimes also found in ponds in woods. Bosc often attempted to take them with every kind of strong snare ; but these were invariably broken to pieces. They are commonly taken with a strong hook bated with a bird or small quadruped, and connected by a chain to a tree. The Indians eat the tail only. At the time of reproduction they fight furiously with each other, and bellow as loud as bulls. They avoid the salt water and proximity to the sea, because they are there exposed to the attacks of sharks and the great turtle. In very warm districts in the Floridas, the rivers are sometimes quite crowded w'ith them, so that they almost interrupt the navigation.</p><p>The specific characters of the pike-headed alligator are a flat snout, the sides of which are nearly parallel, uniting in front in a regular curve. There are eighteen transverse rows of scales on the back. The colour above is a deep greenish brown, beneath white tinged with green, and the flanks are regularly striated with the two colours. Catesby has seen them fourteen feet long. Its hide, except at particular spots, resists a musket ball ; it is most vulnerable at the inferior part of the belly, and round the eye.</p><p>The great alligator of North America certainly forms one of the most remarkable features in the zoology of the United States. Whatever may be said of the African or South American species, this huge reptile is usually neither shy nor dangerous. Its ordinary motion on land is slow and sluggish, a kind of laboured crawling, which leaves the track of a lengthened trail upon the mud, like the keel of a small vessel. When met with at any distance from the water, it immediately squats, that is, lies as flat as it can, with its nose upon the ground, and staring around with rolling eyes. “ Should a man approach them,” says that accurate and admirable describcr Audubon, “ they do not attempt either to make away or attack, but merely raise their body from the ground for an instant, swelling themselves, and issuing a dull blowing sound, not unlike that of a blacksmith’s bellows. Not the least danger need be apprehended ; you either kill them with ease, or leave them.” As if conscious of their incapacity of self-defence, they seldom travel except during the night, being then less subject to disturbance, besides “ having a better chance to surprise a litter of pigs, or of land-tortoises, for prey.” “ In Louisiana,’’ Mr Audubon observes, “ all our lagoons, bayous, creeks, ponds, lakes, and rivers, are well stocked with them ; they are found wherever there is a sufficient quantity of water to hide them, or to furnish them with food ; and they continue thus in great numbers as high as the mouth of the Arkansas river, extending east to North Carolina, and as far west as I have penetrated. On the Red River, before it was navigated by steam-vessels, they were so extremely abundant, that to see hundreds at a sight along the shores, or on the immense rafts of floating or stranded timber, was</p><lb/><p>@@@<hi rend="italic"> Ann. Gin, des Seien. Physiques,</hi>  t. ii. p. 343.</p><p>@@@ An individual, however, was observed by Messrs Dunbar and Hunter ⅛ latitude 32 1/2° north, in the month of December, while the weather was very cold.</p></body></text></TEI>