<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>horrid execrations, and always insisted that he did the fact from his own motive, and that he could accuse nobody. On the day of his execution, after he had made the <hi rend="italic">amende</hi>  before the church of Nôtre Dame, he was carried to the Grève ; and, being placed upon a scaffold, was tied to a wooden engine in the shape of a St Andrew’s cross. The knife with which he did the murder being fastened in his right hand, it was first burned in a slow fire ; then the fleshy parts of his body were torn with red-hot pincers, and melted lead, oil, pitch, and rosin poured into the wounds. The people refused to ray for him ; and when, according to the sentence that had een pronounced upon him, he came to be dragged to pieces by four horses, one of those that were brought appearing to be but weak, a spectator offered his own, with which the criminal was much moved. He was very earnest for absolution, which his confessor refused, unless he would reveal his accomplices. “ Give it me,” said he, “ upon condition that I have told the truth ;” which the priest eventually did. His body was so robust that it resisted the force of the horses ; and the executioner was at length obliged to cut him into quarters, which the people dragged through the streets. Such was the miserable fate of this fanatical assassin, who deprived France of one of her best and greatest kings. He was believed by the populace to have been set on by the Jesuits, although, whilst suffering the most horrible torments, he declared that he had no accomplices, and had done the deed from motives of his own.</p><p>RAVELIN, in <hi rend="italic">Fortflcation,</hi>  was anciently a flat bastion placed in the middle of a curtain ; but it is now a detached work, composed only of two faces, which form a salient angle without any flanks, and are raised before the counterscarp of the place. See Fortification.</p><p>RAVENNA, a delegation of the States of the Church, in Italy, in the northern part of the ancient Romagna. It is 935 square miles in extent, and contains four cities, eight market-towns, many villages, and 123,760 inhabitants. It is a level district on the sea-coast, with numerous saline lakes, but towards the west there are some gentle undulations. It is moderately fertile, and is drained by the rivers La-mone, Lanterno, and their tributary streams. The capital is the city of the same name, which is of high antiquity. It was formerly on the sea-shore, but, by the recession of the water, is now three miles from it. It is in a marshy situation, surrounded by walls of no great strength. It is the see of a bishop, has a cathedral, twenty-one parish churches, twelve monasteries, five nunneries, a public library, an hospital, and some schools. It contains in the city 16,000 inhabitants, but, including the suburbs and some adjacent villages, the population amounts to 23,930. It was formerly the capital of the kingdom of the Ostrogoths, and, in later times, of an exarchate. There are now to be seen the remains of some old Gothic castles. Long. 12. 5.31. E. Lat. 44. 25. 5. N.</p><p>RAVENSBURG, a city of the kingdom of Wirtemberg<hi rend="sub">1 </hi>in tile circle of the Danube, and the capital of a bailiwick of the same name. It stands on the river Schussen, and is surrounded with walls, defended by several ancient towers. It contains 870 houses, with 3760 inhabitants, one half Catholics and the other Protestants. It has several sawmills, and manufactories of cottons, hosiery, iron and wood ware ; and it grows good wine. Long. 9.32. E. Lat. 47.46. 55. N.</p><p>RAVEY, the ancient Hydraotes, a celebrated river of Hindustan, and the third river of the Punjab. It rises in the eastern mountains of Cashmere, near a famous place of Hindu worship, not far from the sources of the Sutulege, the Chunaub, and the Beyah rivers. It afterwards runs in a south-westerly direction until it passes the city of Lahore, sixty miles above which it is 120 yards broad, and extremely rapid, yet navigable during the rains for boats of a considerable size. It flows in the same direction after passing the city of Lahore, and it is joined about twenty-eight miles above the city of Moultan by the Jhylum and the Chunaub rivers, forming a stream in some places several miles in breadth, and scarcely inferior to the Indus itself. Immediately after their junction it is one mile, one furlong, and eighty-five yards, but lower down the stream is contracted in its breadth to less than 350 yards. Seventy miles below Moultan the Ravey joins the Indus after a course, including its windings, of 500 miles. The water is light and wholesome.</p><p>RAVILPANDY, a large and populous town of Hindustan, in the district of the Punjab, situated about half way between the Indus and the Hydaspes rivers. The houses are flat-roofed, and the surrounding country is open and well cultivated. This place was visited by Mr Elphinstone in 1809. It belonged to Jewun Sing, a Sikh chief.</p><p>RAVREE, a town of Hindustan, in the Western Ghauts, and province of Bejapoor. It was the first stronghold seized by Sevajee, the great founder of the Mahratta power. It is forty-five miles south-south-west from Poonah. Long. 73. 32. E. Lat. 18. 2. N.</p><p>RAWAAD, a small town of Hindustan, in the province of Lahore, in the Sikh territories, 120 miles north-west from the city of Lahore. Long. 72. 12. E. Lat. 33. 5. N.</p><p>RAWAK Isle, a small island in the Eastern Seas, off the north coast of Waygiou, with which it forms a harbour. The channel is here a mile broad, with a depth of from ten to fifteen fathoms, and a mud bottom. Sago, in cakes, is sold here in large quantities. Fish and turtle may also be had. Long. 131. 15. E. Lat. O. 3. N.</p><p>RAWANKRAD, a celebrated lake in the mountains of Thibet, on the north of the great Himalayah range. It is the source of the river Sutulege, and is connected with the lake Mansarowar. The lake is long and narrow, and is divided by an island. It derives its supplies from several small rivers that flow from the mountains, and also from the melting of the snows. The situation is about the thirty-first degree of north latitude, and near it may be seen Mount Cailas, a well-known scene of Hindu fable, covered with perpetual snow.</p><p>RAWCLIFFE, a town of the west riding of Yorkshire, in the parish of Snaith<hi rend="sub">1</hi> and wapentake of Osgoldcross, 176 miles from London. It has some trade by the river Aire, which is navigable beyond it. The population amounted in 1801 to 920, in 1811 to 1143, in 1821 to 1496, and in 1831 to 1450.</p><p>RAWICZ, or Rawitsch, a city of the Prussian province of Posen, in the circle of Kobben. It is surrounded with walls, is well built and paved, and, including the suburbs, contains 1100 houses, with 8640 inhabitants, who are occupied in making linen, woollen, and cotton goods, mostly by machinery, and in tanning and currying leather. Of the inhabitants, 1500 are Jews.</p><p>RAY, John, a celebrated naturalist, and the son of Mr Roger Ray, a blacksmith, was born at Black Notly, in Essex, in 1628. He received the rudiments of learning at the grammar-school of Braintree ; and in 1644 was admitted into Catharine Hall, Cambridge, whence he afterwards removed to Trinity College in that university. He took the degree of master of arts, and became at length a senior fellow of the college ; but his intense application to his studies having injured his health, he was obliged at his leisure hours to exercise himself by riding or walking in the fields, which led him to the study of plants. He noted from Johnson, Parkinson, and the <hi rend="italic">Phytologia Britannica, </hi>the places where curious plants grew ; and in 1658 he rode from Cambridge to the city of Chester, whence he proceeded to North Wales, visiting many places, and amongst others the famous hill of Snowdon, and returning by Shrewsbury and Gloucester. In 1660 he published his <hi rend="italic">Catalogus Plantorurn circa Cnutabrigiam nascentium,</hi>  and the same</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>