<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>other inherent in himself, founded on the abstract nature and the over-cautious, captious spirit, of the legal arguments which in most courts form the greater part of the ordinary practice, and which, as we see in everyday experience, disqualify most lawyers, by various defects (and most of all by want of apparent candour), from success as popular speakers. For success in pulpit-oratory, this instrument of persuasion is absolutely and without exception indispensable. The hearer’s confidence in the speaker’s understanding requires scarcely any illustrative remark but this ; that it must not be a confidence in his oratorical skill, which has an inevitable tendency to check belief : but it may advantageously extend to an unlimited admiration of his general intelligence, and of the profundity of his acquaintance with the matter of the address ; with this restriction, however, that the display of these qualities will lose all their force, if, by exhibiting a want of modesty, they draw the speaker into a violation of the first section of the rule. The hearer’s confidence in the speaker’s good-will is as essential as the rest, and the want of this confidence is the main obstacle which makes a speaker on political questions almost inevitably unable to make an impression on men belonging to an opposite faction.</p><p>We have now reached the Third Ground of Belief ; that which the writer or speaker produces by exciting, in the minds of those whom he addresses, such an Emotion, or series of Emotions, as for a time excludes the application of their discursive faculties to the arguments regarding the question discussed. The operation which Eloquence here effects on the mind is, it must be observed, complex. The faculty primarily excited is the Imagination ; but the agency of this faculty is merely instrumental ; for the office which it is made to discharge is, that of calling up images which are adequate objects of the Emotions, and are calculated to arouse them. But, further, these objects of the imagination and the feelings, so far as they are useful towards the Production of Belief, are either themselves conclusions presented to the Reason to be pronounced by it true or false, or they are at least steps leading towards such conclusions. This appeal to the Reason, however, is the very last stage of the process : and if the discourse has effected its end, the operation of judgment is instantaneous, and as it were instinctive : the conclusion is admitted by the mind, not as the result of a train of argument, but as an element, so to speak, of the mind’s own experience or consciousness.</p><p>This is the true analysis of all animated and passionate eloquence; and yet, when so represented, this process, in which the art gains its highest triumphs, and without which it would be quite powerless as an instrument for persuading the mass of mankind, may at first sight appear more open to the charge of unfairness than any other means which literature and oratory employ. But the objection is unsound. This, like every other element of eloquence, is a neutral power, which may be made to ally itself either with good or evil, being, however, always most willing to serve truth and rectitude. We shall be enabled to discern its real position, by examining two of its most usual applications.</p><p>The first case is that in which the aim of the discourse is to determine the hearers or readers to a certain course of action, of whose abstract justice and propriety they are convinced by a simple statement of its principles, but towards which neither the abstract statement, nor their previous feelings on the subject, tend strongly enough to prompt them ; in other words, a case in which persuasion (in the strict sense of the word), not conviction, is the proper aim. The mere conviction would clearly not lead to the result required ; because men act not from convictions, but from motives ; not from simple belief of truth, reposing ultimately in the understanding, nor even from a belief superinduced on this, that the truth is also an object adequate to the gra</p><p>tification of one or more of the active powers of the mind,— but from the suggestions of these active faculties themselves, aroused to energy, and directed to the truths in question as their fittest or only objects. Eloquence strives to communicate the impulse thus needed. The most important truth stated abstractly and barely, and the same truth set forth with the adornment of eloquence, often bear to each other, in respect of their comparative value for mankind, the same relation which the skeleton-hull in the building-yard bears to the gallant ship at sea, armed, manned, and in full sail.</p><p>We next take a case which brings us nearer to the disputable ground ; being one in which we attempt, by the excitement of emotion, to lead men to a conclusion in which they would not have acquiesced but for such excitement. There is nothing to prevent us from assuming, that the conclusion which we maintain in the case supposed is true, although it may seem to those whom we address to be either positively false, or exceedingly problematical. Now this belief or doubt of theirs, adverse at once to the truth and to the end of the discourse, may arise in their minds in a variety of ways, all of these, however, being reducible to two ; for it must either be founded on an antecedent process of pure reasoning which has gone on in their minds, or it must rest on some other antecedent mental process, in which the discursive faculties are either not at all, or not alone, active. The former class of wrong conclusions arise much seldomer from any defect in the process of reasoning which has conducted to them, than from the assumption of erroneous premises ; and this makes it the more difficult to combat them directly by argument. The latter class, however, is that to which belong the great mass of common prejudices ; opinions often resulting from an inextricable combination of shallow reflection, hasty observation, ruling passion, imperfect views of moral duty, and personal or local affections and dislikes ; prepossessions on which arguments can take no hold, but which are often quickly displaced by other notions suggested without argument : just as, in a siege, the shot and shells rebound without effect from the masonry of a casemated bastion, which a storming party, if they can once enter the trenches, will carry at the first assault If we undertake to instruct or convince minds engrossed by false opinions of either class, we have only two alternatives : either a direct attack on the reason by argument, which will meet with an inevitable and signal repulse, or a well-directed appeal to other principles of the mind, which will often insure a gratifying success. No doubt it would be better if truth could be protected and disseminated without the use of these indirect methods : no doubt we can conceive, and ardently desire to witness, an advancement of human knowledge, a purification of human desires and affections, an elevation of the standard of conscience as well as intellect, which should make a simple presentation of truth to the reason always adequate for the dislodgement of error : but our mortal nature does not stand on this height, and will never rise so high till it has put on immortality ; and the aspirant after eloquence, like the philosopher and the man of business, must, in his endeavours to act on the minds of others, be contented to take their condition as he finds it. This is all that Aristotle has said, or intended to say, in a passage which has been strangely cited as expressing an opinion, that all the appeals of eloquence to the passions are wrong and illegitimate ; we say strangely, when the assertion is made as to a writer who placed so much weight on this instrument of the art, that he devoted a large proportion of his rhetorical work to an analysis of the most common passions, although, according to his own view of the province of rhetoric, the subject lies beyond its limits.</p><p>The Aristotle of modern times has at once beautiftιliy illustrated and convincingly defended the operation of elo-</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>