<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>every other town throughout the whole tract of country, the inhabitants of which could avail themselves of the benefits of the railway, therefore, in using our figure, we must make the outer boundary lines (A), respectively curve right or left as the line of railway departs in either of those directions from the straight line (A). The values of (|i) may then be found and marked ready for use, as nearly as can be judged, by seeing where the stations would, it is presumed,be ultimately placed; then having ascertained the values of (<hi rend="italic">p</hi>) and (/() from the stamp-oflice returns, or any other equally authentic document, they may in each case be marked against the roads for all the towns which we may see fit to calculate upon for putting or not into the traffic returns, according as their inhabitants would gain or not by using the railway.</p><p>It will, on a very slight inspection, be self-evident, that for perhaps three-fourths of the whole space included within the lines (/&gt;) and (A), there will be no need of any calculation, ex-cept to shew the quantity of saving. In the earlier stages, therefore, if it is merely required to know the amount of traffic ; but only the doubtful places need be computed, and the rest may be deferred till it is desirable to complete the whole table. It must also be noted, that although a place may be actually without the boundary lines, yet there may not be a conveyance from it to either of the termini, as the case may be, and that the inhabitants, in order to be enabled to travel thither, may have to come to a place within the lines. They are then to be tried for as if they were themselves situated w-ithin-the lines, and, of course, all towns beyond the termini must benefit, when travelling towards the opposite end of the line.</p><p>The effect of railways will be this: They can only be made upon main lines, because such lines will alone pay; the stage coaches will go off these lines when the railway has been a short time in operation, but the same coaches will be employed on cross country roads to feed the railway; and it is a curious fact, that through this operation one more coach was licensed at Liverpool and Manchester the year after the railway opened than there was the year before.</p><p>If the above rules be attended to, a tolerably correct knowledge of the traffic to be expected may be obtained, and it is sure notto be an exaggerated one. Whilst this has been going on, the engineer will have been employed in looking at the general features of the country preparatory to surveying and levelling it; and in most cases a man of a practised eye at this kind of work will be able at once to decide on all the principal points along which the line should go. During the same time the solicitor will have been feeling his way amongst the landowners and the occupiers, so that w here much dissent is manifested, that property may if possible be avoided. Landholders have been proverbially hostile to railways, and enormous in their demands for compensation, yet they have invariably found that their property has been benefited instead of being injured ; and when more land has been required from them, they have asked a higher price on account of that very railw ay running through their property, whose existence theyhadin the first instance declared to bea nuisance. This state of things cannot last much longer; but whilst it does, it must be met as far as possible in the above manner.</p><p>There are many things to be taken into consideration before definitely fixing on the precise line in which a railroad is to run. Borings should be largely taken to obtain a correct geological knowledge of the various strata. A considerable subsequent expenditure may often be saved in this way. It is of no use to put a penny on our eyes to hinder us from seeing a guinea. Borings may be carried to any depth by sinking a well part of the way, and without this they have been worked to a depth of760 feet. The nature of the traffic must also be taken into consideration, so that when all other things are equal, the line may be run so as to include particular towns. The population of all the adjacent places should be ascertained and marked on a map; the nature of the various markets and fairs should be examined' into and the state of trade; the wants of persons connected with it ought also to be taken into account; the quantity and quality of the existing goods traffic, its nature, and the demands on it with reference to any probable increase ; and the capabilities of harbours, if any are w ithin reach of the line, their draught of water, the nature of the protection they afford, their present trade, and the effect of the railroad on that trade. In this, as well as in all other cases, the results of a transition from peace to w<hi rend="sup">r</hi>ar, and<hi rend="italic">vice versa</hi>, should be well considered, together w ith the effect of any future line of railway which may become a partially competing one.</p><p>The more effectually these inquiries are made, and the more fully their results are honestly put before the proprietors, together with separate estimates for the engineering department and the managing department, so will their confidence in the undertaking increase; and it is a most essential point to place this confidence on a sure basis, so that if any little mishap, which none can avoid, take place, the shares may not be suddenly thrown on the market at a ruinous sacrifice, and the undertaking abandoned, through the projectors not having had the necessary information, to enable them to see that the result of their labours would be a profitable speculation, notwithstanding any trifling losses arising from causes against which perhaps no human foresight could provide.</p><p>Railways with two lines of rails in very favourable si'ua-1 tions have been completed for L.10,000 per mile in Eng-i land. This however must be taken as the exception, and not the rule. Under very unfavourable circumstances they have cost L.50,000 per mile; and of course there will be found an expense per mile at all differences between these two, which may fairly be taken as the extreme limits. Now it is certain, that with a line 80 miles in length, a traffic of 75 tons of goods per day from each end, or 120 passengers per day each way, or with 35 tons of goods and 60 passengers per day each way, the railway, if even constructed for L.12,000 per mile, which will rarely happen, would not afford a dividend of more than a quarter per cent, and (outnumbers throughout meaning daily each way) it would require 100 tons of goods, or 160 passengers, or 50 tons of goods and 80 passengers, to pay 1 per cent.; 125 tons of goods, or 200 passengers, or 62 tons of goods and 100 passengers, would but little exceed If percent.; and it would take 200 tons of goods, or 320 passengers, or 100 tons of goods with 160 passengers, to pay 4j- per cent.</p><p>The Americans have such facilities for these constructions, that 1600 miles of railroad have been made in that country (a good deal of it, however, being only single line) at an average cost of only L.5081 per mile; whereas in England the mere permanent way alone would amount to L.4400 per mile, if the rails were 45 lbs. to the yard, and laid upon longitudinal timbers ; L.4900 per mile, with rails 42 lbs. per yard, having chairs and cast-iron supports between them, on longitudinal timbers ; L.5300 per mile, with rails 42 lbs. per yard, on blocks 3 feet apart; L.4800 per mile, with the same sized rails on wooden sleepers; L.5600 per mile for 62 lb. rails, on blocks 4 feet apart, and L.5100 for the same rails on wooden sleepers ; L.6000 per mile for rails of 75 lb. per yard on blocks 5 feet apart, and L.5500 per mile for the same on sleepers. These prices do not include laying the way, ballasting, and draining. Thus we see that the mere cost of the permanent way in the country, averaging L.5200 per mile, exceeds that of the whole expense of a complete railway in America; and 75 pound rails on blocksand sleepers, including laying, ballasting, sidings, turn-plates, and every expense, has exceeded L.8000 per mile.</p><p>The mean receipts forfive years on theLiverpool amlMan-chester line give the following proportions: Revenue 100,expenses 55, profits 45 ; and the expenses have been as high,</p></body></text></TEI>