<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>the crane fixes that of the ash pit and coke store. The ’passengers alighting get down from the west side of the carriages, and go out from the west side of the railway. The passengers who are getting up, do so on the east side of the carriages, and come to the carriages from the east side of the railway.</p><p>The horses and carriages which are to leave the train, must, of course, be at the end of it. These, when detached, are to be run back, or to the northward, where a tumplate should be fixed to take them up by the cross line, to the spot where they are to be landed. This spot, which should be a third line of rails farther east, should be so far to the northward of the station house, that a siding can be run from the third or extra line of rails into the main east line, so as to beclearof the end of the train; andon this Sidingshould be the embarked carriages which are to join the train. On the west side of the railway, there should be another addi-' tional line of rails, with a cross line from it to the place where thecarriages areembarked. Alongthis line the goods may be brought. It will be readily seen that all the required objects will be effected by this arrangement.</p><p>For the western line, the water crane should be sufficiently to the north of the station, to allow the centre of an average train to be opposite the station-house, when the tender is under the crane. The ash-pit and coke-store are, as in the previous case, regulated by the position of the crane. The passengers w'ho are leaving the train, get out on the eastern side of the carriages, and leave the railway also on the eastern side. The passengers who are to join the train are waiting on the western side, and get into the carriages on that side. The horses and carriages which are to leave the train, are run back to the southward, past the siding from the west additional line by which those come on which are joining it, and are brought back to that siding, when clear of the carriages joining the train. By the siding they get on to the west additional line, and going to the northward, are taken across as soon as the train has left, and are disembarked at the proper spot.</p><p>Goods joining or leaving the train arc managed exactly in the same way. Those which are to leave it being run back on the main line, till past the Sidingbywhich those comeinto the main line which are to join the train ; and when these are clear, those which left the train a.re to be brought to the siding, and run into the goods’ station. Proper waiting rooms for the passengers should, of course, be provided on each side of the railway, and their exit and entrance will be by stairs, either up or down, as the station is situated on an embarkment or in a cutting. A foot-bridge may sometimes be thrown across with advantage.</p><p>There is such a decided convenience in having all stations on a level, that we should strongly recommend them to be placed so wherever it is at all practicable, even if there is some little sacrificed in another point of view ; but this is a matter which will, in general, be so completely governed by the localities, that it may not be possible, in many cases, to attain it. When this happens, however, great care must be taken to make the approaches wide, and of a gentle slope.</p><p>As the works proceed towards completion, so many causes will arise to engage the engineers and directors, even without the occurrence of any particularly great accidents, that on all the leading questions time should be taken by the forelock. Springs of water, rock, and quicksands, will be met with where least expected perhaps, and the constant exertion of every talent will be required towards the close of the works. Good drainage will be most wanted when least at command ; and work done with wet materials will be always slipping. Many times have embankments made of wet clayey earth slipped at all kinds of slopes ; and although hundreds of cubic yards of dry material have been tipped on to them, they have been swallowed up and totally dis</p><p>appeared, whilst, at last, the only remedy to be found was weighting the slip itself with a sufficient quantity of earth to enable it to bear the embankment above.</p><p>When rock occurs at any height up the sides of an excavation, advantage may sometimes be taken of it to decrease the expense, by cutting only a sufficient width for the railway, and having no slope to the earth below the rock, but building up retaining walls from the railway below when bottomed out to the rock above, or w<hi rend="sup">τ</hi>hat is called undersetting, an example of which may be seen at the great Blis-worth cutting on the London and Birmingham railway. (See Plate CCCCXXVL figs. 2, 3, 4.)</p><p>It will often happen that many parts of the permanent way are laid prior to its being possible to open either end of the line for traffic. These had better be kept in repair by the contractor ; but when the line is once opened, or any part of it, for the purpose of travelling, it will be much the best way for the company themselves to keep it in order, taking especial care that the contractor repays them a proper price for so doing. The consequences of any accident by the engine or carriages getting thrown off the rails are so frightful, that no attention and expense can be thought too great which can prevent such an occurrence. We have seen instances in which carriages have undergone so complete a smash, that not a square foot of plank could be picked up anywhere.</p><p>A set of plate-layers consists of nine men for tumplates ; twelve for laying rails ; five for repairing the way ; and six for laying in points and crossings.</p><p>To each set, the following tools will be required :—</p><p>2 chissel-ended crowbars for drawing spikes.</p><p>1 point-ended crowbar for moving rails, the point being put in the ground.</p><p>1 claw-ended crowbar.</p><p>1 cuddy or three-legged stand for the levers, so called from the name of the inventor. (Fig. 19·)</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>