<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>been beyond the means employed. The distinguished abilities of Dr Carey succeeded beyond all reasonable expectation in the translation of the Scriptures into the languages of the East. The education conferred by the Se-rampore missionaries, by means of the circle of schools under their superintendence, was superior in kind to the education given to European children in the same condition in life, and was more favourably received by the natives, though there was a natural want of perseverance on their part, in availing themselves of the benefit to the utmost.</p><p>It is more difficult to judge both with respect to the number of converts and the influence which Christianity exercises over their lives. Neither at home nor abroad, at this present moment, have we reason to suppose that Christianity is enjoying a season of spiritual prosperity. It is rather a time of outward progression than of internal renovation ; and a review of what has been done, both here and in distant countries, may more wisely lead us to place our trust in the Divine arm, which will never desert his own cause, than to form any very lofty and exaggerated notions of our present acquisitions. In some instances we have the encouragement to perceive that the success is far beyond the means. Amiable as the character was, and great as were the talents, of Henry Martyn, they are not sufficient to account for the striking and lasting impression which he produced on the Persians ; and his short residence in Persia produced more fruit than a long life might have done, even with many prosperous circumstances attending it. Those who are last and least upon the missionary field have yet made a beginning ; they have got what Archimedes required in order to move the world, a place where to stand and to erect their moral machinery, some influence over the native mind, and increased facilities for introducing new improvements and additional labourers from Europe.</p><p>Success in general will be proportioned to the means employed, and the efficacy of the means will depend upon the method of using them. The first efforts in all undertakings must be expected to be merely tentative. Resources are few, and there is a want of experience, in order to employ the scanty means to the uttermost. What was defective in the commencement is often unnecessarily prolonged, from the dislike of change ; and the very proposal of improvements often appears to imply the censure of previous mismanagement.</p><p>In most instances it is the governed who force improvements upon their governors ; but in religious enterprises the contributors are too well satisfied with having paid their subscriptions, to give themselves any farther trouble or thought as to the mode in which these contributions are expended. Yet on no subject is thought more required. The first requisite to lasting success is to act upon a system, and to be provided with a plan. Circumstances must modify that plan ; but they who act upon a large scale, and through a considerable tract of time, will at last modify circumstances to their own purposes, and ultimately turn what might seem hindrances into helps.</p><p>The first object is to understand the nature of the country and of the people on whom a missionary society is intended to operate. The Americans afford excellent examples of missionary pioneers, previously exploring the country in which they intend to settle ; weighing the advantages and the obstacles which present themselves, exhibiting a rare union of prudence and determination, and, whilst strictly acting up to their own principles, succeeding, at least for a time, in conciliating the minds of others ; though it is not to be expected that this transient favour can last long, for it must be dissipated by the first success on the part of the foreign missionaries. These missionary travels are of double service, creating and deepening an interest at home, which is the true way to enlarge the re-</p><p>VOL. xιx.</p><p>sources of missionary operations, and at the same time discovering how these resources are to be best economized, by preventing fruitless expenditure, and by pointing out and discovering the true points of attack by which the country to be entered is assailable. Those, however, who have done such service as explorers, should continue their good offices as superintendents ; and in many cases there might be an advantage in separating between the council and the executive, between those who laid down the plan and were watching the progress of its being carried into execution, and those who were filling up the outline, and engaged in the details. Many reports and evil surmises will arise against missionaries, which, being engaged in more important occupations, they little hear of and less heed, and which, even if they were desirous to do so, they could ill ward off ; but these might easily be removed by one w ho was friendly to the mission, and yet not a party implicated in each of its transactions.</p><p>If a physician in Mahommedan countries should make the first survey, and propose the original plan, by his influence with the governors he would obtain a more favourable opening for a missionary enterprise, and then watch over its prosperity, without being identified with all its proceedings. He would also have greater facilities, by the access which his profession gives him, both to governors and families of influence, to secure and extend favour and assistance from the ruling powers, and to remove the more speedily any obstacles or stumbling-blocks that might be cast in the way. The employment of physicians as missionaries, which has only very lately and very partially been practised, has been attended, on the limited scale on which it has been tried, with yet happier results than could reasonably have been anticipated. It has opened a new fountain of humanity in the hard and selfish breasts of distant nations, to see the strange spectacle of a man, in imitation of his Saviour, “ going about doing good,” and healing the sick. Those who are insensible to the diseases of the mind, feel with sufficient acuteness the sufferings of their bodies; and though missionaries may complain of the want of listeners, a missionary-physician has no reason to complain of the want of patients ; nor has he reason to lament the want of success in treating the cases that are submitted to him. The healing art transported to a distance appears to assume new powers ; and the reason is plain. Here medicine has to contend with inveterate debility, and can only hope, by the most successful treatment, to prolong a sickly existence. There the more rigorous life has already swept away those who were not possessed of the stamina of a vigorous constitution, and the physician has chiefly to attend to the cases where nature is ready to second his efforts, where disease is not inveterate, but accidental ; not to mention, that our usual remedies come to distant lands with the advantage of new discoveries, and seem to resume the efficacy which they possessed when first invented, and before the body, like that of Mithridates, seasoned to drugs, and therefore blunted to their operation, had lost the sensibility which it possessed on their first and hitherto untried exhibition. Novelty also greatly augments the power of not the least potent of medicines, faith and hope.</p><p>What interest would the residence of an intelligent physician possess at Jerusalem ; of one who was a physician indeed in the largest sense of the term, and wise in the knowledge of nature ? We need such a commentator even for the Scriptures, an intelligent and resident spectator, to view and to record again the same natural appearances w<hi rend="sup">,</hi>hich were viewed by the sacred writers of old, that we may stand again in their position, see, anew the same objects, and affix the same significance to their terms. What a benefactor he might be to the weary and superstitious pilgrims from distant lands, who might return home with prolonged life, and carrying with them the words of that</p><p>p</p></body></text></TEI>