<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>regret. “ Talis quum sis, utinam noster esses.” “ Seeing they are such, would they were ours.” The Jesuits alone understood the power of education ; but it shows the spirit of the body, how differently they used that mighty instrument in Europe, and in the countries that were beyond the range of Christendom. Where they had to contend with the reformed, they raised up disciples not unequal to the contest ; but where this motive was withdrawn, they soon showed they had no great liking to education for its own sake, for all their arts were employed to train submissive, not enlightened disciples ; and this is an error which Protestants as well as Papists may fall into. All men, good as well as bad, are fond of power, and they naturally, if there is no check over them, retain their disciples longer than is necessary in the state of pupillage. How different would have been the resources of the Jesuits, and how much greater the renown they have justly acquired, had they taken the same pains to instruct their Asiatic and American, that thev did for their European scholars ; and how different would have been the condition, at this day, of their missions throughout the world.</p><p>The Reformation, of all religious revivals, least abounded in missionary efforts ; the cause of which, though obvious, has not yet been sufficiently attended to and pointed out. Other changes of religious opinion were owing to the personal exertions of missionaries. The Reformation was spread chiefly by means of writings ; nor otherwise, with the ecclesiastical and secular power united against it, could it so rapidly have penetrated the different countries of Europe. It was the first great manifestation of the power of printing, and, being an unexpected attack, no defences whatever were prepared, as in after-times, against its inroads. The use of so new and mighty an engine seemed to supersede for a time all other exertions ; and the general mind, already stirring and awake, hailed with eagerness the new dawn of civil and religious freedom. Unfortunately the Reformation, necessarily controversial in its origin, continued, and almost ended, in controversy ; and, immersed in disputes with the Church of Rome, and in dangers from the civil power, and in domestic strifes about standards of orthodoxy, lost first the spirit, and then the form, of sound doctrine, and its followers became equally unable and unwilling to proclaim that truth to others which they were forsaking themselves.</p><p>The revivals amongst the reformed, and their returns to the primitive doctrine and spirit, were local and sectional, and their efforts, of course, were feeble and circumscribed; but they were operated by personal exertion and fervent preaching, and therefore possessed more of a missionary character than the Reformation itself ; and though much less powerful at their centre, spread to a wider circumference, and exerted a remoter influence. The Danes deserve the praise of being amongst the earliest and most persevering of the Protestant nations in planting Christianity in foreign lands. But the plant has too much the air of an exotic still ; it does not fully take root and imbibe its nourishment from the soil ; it wants the strongest symptom of vitality, growth. No cause can prosper that is chiefly dependent upon foreign aid. External force may prop up a stationary and a sinking cause ; but whatever spreads and flourishes must have an interior principle of life.</p><p>How numerous were the converts of the Dutch, if we might believe the reports that were given of them ; but when the Dutch dominion was withdrawn, how suddenly did numbers of the Dutch converts disappear. The Dutch, like the Jesuits, were doubtless contented in many instances with an outward conformity to Christianity ; yet still it is striking how slight a hold even the practice of outward rites had upon multitudes, who quietly relapsed into the profession of Paganism. It is evident that primitive Christianity proceeded upon adifferentplan. Itcollecteditsconverts into free societies, who were instructed by native teachers, trained to rely upon their own resources, not only in furnishing their own funds, but also in supplying the wants of others, and who, in assuming the form of a church, assumed at the same time the model of a missionary society, and became themselves the new centres from which light and civilization proceeded to still remoter regions.</p><p>The zeal, devotion, and activity of the primitive Christians seemed revived in the Moravians, who, scarcely escaped from persecution themselves, proceeded without delay to subject themselves to new trials, and, like the forlorn hope of Christianity, chose the most desperate situations and the most degraded tribes to exemplify what Christianity might be enabled to do in more favourable circumstances, when it had succeeded where all things seemed to be against it.</p><p>The Wesleyans, after Christianizing the abandoned districts of England, and encountering the rage of their own savage countrymen, often backed by their civil or religious guides, the neighbouring magistrate or clergyman, have carried the same zeal, dexterity, and success, to the slaves of the West Indies, more docile than their masters ; and to the savages of the remotest countries and islands, less infuriated and dangerous than the rude agricultural population of England.</p><p>In the Serampore Mission we might produce equal if not superior names to any of which the Jesuits can boast ; superior to them even in the arts of education when applied to a half-civilized people, and incomparably above them in extending information amongst the general population of the country, and in the most important of all operations, the raising up of native labourers, and creating resources for their maintenance, in part at least, in the country itself.</p><p>The London Missionary Society, distinguished for its catholic spirit, and the largeness of its undertakings, has achieved one of the most visible triumphs of Christianity, in bringing so many islands into subjection to the mild law of the gospel ; and the Episcopal Church of England, so long eminent for the numerous lights it has given to science, to knowledge, and to morals, is preparing to transplant that learning to the banks of the Ganges ; and the Church of Scotland, after originating a national system of education at home, is laying the commencement of an admirable plan of instruction for the learned region of the East. In addition to the different religious denominations, each able from its own resources, if concentrated in any direction, for producing a wide and lasting effect, several single congregations, without extrinsic aid, and with a self-devotion worthy of the apostolic days, send out their own missionary or missionaries, supported by their private funds, and strengthened by their fervent prayers.</p><p>Independently of what Britain can effect, with resources far greater than any other nation has yet possessed, a new empire has come into the conflict, with all the energy of youth and freedom, and exulting in the consciousness of ever-growing strength. The Americans are eminently fitted for missionaries. The maxim is scarcely true when applied to them, that of all animals, man is the most rooted in the soil. They move over America as if they were already masters of that great continent, and revisit Europe as another home, and their original birthplace. They bring with them ardent hopes from the land where, in spite of many disappointments, hopes are most speedily and abundantly realized ; and, accustomed to overcome the obstacles of nature, they engage with no less alacrity in the more stubborn contest with the perversity and prejudices of mankind. Their plans are admirably conceived, and in the course of being ably executed ; and they are already receiving their due applause in the dread and detestation of the corrupt priesthood of the East, who deeply feel and sincerely express with what dangerous enemies they have now to deal.</p></body></text></TEI>