<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>cult task, of discovering what propositions are likely to be received as truths, by minds affected by all the incongruous influences of imagination, passion, self-love, and ill-instructed conscience. The proof of a proposition from considerations of moral duty may appear weak to a man in whom some strong passion rebels against the principle ; but it may yet be possible for us to combat his scepticism by arguments of other kinds, drawing their topics, perhaps, from self-love, or from other passions to which we know him to be subject. 3. The necessity of watching the operations of the active powers of the mind, before we determine on the form and arrangement of arguments, may be sufficiently illustrated for the purpose here in view, by tracing the example last given for one step farther. Our proof of a proposition from ethical principles, although, in the case supposed, it would probably be met by incredulity or ridicule if stated at the outset, may gain a very different reception after we have cut a path for it by arguments addressed to the personal feelings of the auditor. When we have convinced him, that the truth on which we insist is conducive to his interest, and that, if it opposes one of his strongest passions, it is favourable to another, we have prepared his understanding for receiving attentively, and without prejudice, that argument from morality on which the proof of the proposition truly rests.</p><p>Those applications of the principles of eloquence which have been last before us, lead to the consideration of the second question that was proposed as to the connection of this branch of philosophy with others :—what is the relation which eloquence bears to poetry ? Both endeavour to arouse the imagination and the feelings ; the latter indeed always aiming at this effect, but the former too striving to attain it on those occasions when it puts forth all its strength : what, then, is it that distinguishes the one art from the other? The answer is not hard to find. Both arts, in attempting to excite the fancy and the feelings, are only using means, which each applies to its own peculiar end ; and the ends which the two propose to reach are essentially dissimilar. The dissertation on poetry in this work has correctly stated the end of that art to be “ the creation of intellectual pleasure we have here considered the end of eloquence to be “ the production of belief.” Poetry, like the other fine arts, appeals to the taste ; its compositions attain their proper and final result in the pleasure of contemplation ; and the truth or falsehood of their representations, and, in short, their agreement or disagreement with all the laws of the mental system, are qualities which enter into our conception of the essence of poetry only so far as they are subservient to that one peculiar result. The mathematician who complained that the Paradise Lost proved nothing, stated accurately the principle which separates poetry from eloquence and science.</p><p>Indeed the principle of distinction, when thus broadly enunciated, is something very like a palpable truism ; but it is one of those truths, unfortunately common in the affairs of real life as well as in the field of speculation, which are in theory universally acknowledged, and in practice very frequently forgotten : and no age can more pressingly need to be reminded of this truth than one like our own, in which what is called poetical prose has gained such general favour. We are in constant danger of being led astray by the fact, that eloquence, in addressing itself to cultivated minds (which is the only application of its powers that entitles it to be called an art, or to be investigated either philosophically or critically), does always include the gratification of taste as one of its purposes. We forget that this purpose is altogether a subordinate one, and that, if it ever comes in competition with the proper and principal purpose of the art, it ought to be unhesitatingly sacrificed. The authority of Aristotle will once more support our view, to which indeed his reasoning has conducted us. It is one of the earliest</p><lb/><p>and most valuable propositions in his treatise, that the arguments and other instruments tending to produce belief constitute the essence of eloquence, and that everything else is merely accessory.</p><p>Our review leads us, in the next place, to consider two objections, which are very often urged against the study of the subject. The first of these is chiefly directed against the practical application of eloquence, the second against the science or art which undertakes to expound its laws.</p><p>First, it is said that rhetoric is a dishonest art, which, so far as it is supposed to have any practical uses, is designed to qualify its students for inculcating falsehood as readily as truth. In answering this cavil, we must, if we would not altogether lose sight of the real principle, face boldly the difficulty which it suggests. We cheerfully admit that rhetoric directs the student to search, not for such propositions as are absolutely true, but merely for such as are likely to <hi rend="italic">seem</hi>  true to those whom he wishes to convince or persuade. But, in the first place, it does not follow that it directs him to search for falsehoods, or that these are the propositions which will best serve his purpose. The very reverse is the fact. The highest of all authorities on the subject lays it down most justly, as at once an essential principle of human nature, and a warning to the aspirant after eloquence, that mankind have a natural love and predisposition towards truth, and seldom fail in finding it out. Eloquence may doubtless be abused by being applied to wrong purposes ; but so may every science, mental and physical, which admits of any practical application at all, with the single exception of the science of morals, which, unlike all other branches of inquiry, has moral good for its object, and, if it has discovered the truths which it seeks, has thereby secured itself against all misuse of its investigations. Eloquence may be used for disseminating falsehood or heresy, as it may be for teaching truth and recommending genuine religion ; and the most important discoveries in physics may be turned to purposes of destruction, or made to promote the comfort and happiness of mankind. But, it must be once again repeated, he who attempts to apply this art, or any other which uses for its materials the principles of moral belief, to ends adverse to the cause of truth and morality, will speedily discover that he is misusing his instrument, by the imperfection of the results which he will usually produce. In the second place, however, rhetoric, assuming it to be capable of fulfilling the promise which it holds out, is not merely harmless, but positively beneficial, and is in fact necessary for the protection of truth and goodness. The argumentative writer or speaker, in the legitimate exercise of his art, addressing himself with the view of expounding or proving valuable truths to men in general, who possess but fragmentary knowledge, and are unaccustomed to discussions in scientific form, knows that he cannot convince the understanding, unless he at the same time engages the attention and conciliates the affections ; and also that he possesses no media of proof by which he can arouse the discursive faculties of those whom he addresses, except the knowledge and opinions which are already fixed in their minds. A felicitous image presented to the fancy, a gentle dealing with angry passions, an avoidance of collision with a rooted prejudice, may, without the slightest violation of truth or moral rectitude, open the minds of an assembly or a nation to receive with honest conviction a system of knowledge, religious, ethical, or political, which philosophical reasoning or uncompromising dogmatism might have striven for ages to force upon them, and striven in vain. But skill in rhetoric admits of another application. It may and will enable one to detect and expose sophistry and empty declamation. The art does unquestionably aid those who wish to mislead ; but it is on</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>