<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>1 RECIPROCAL, in general, is something that is mutual, or which ls returned equally on both sides, or affects both parties alike.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">. Reciprocal, in </hi><hi rend="italic">Mathematics,</hi>  is applied to quantities which, multiplied together, make unity. Thus - and <hi rend="italic">x, y</hi></p><p>and -, are reciprocal quantities. Likewise - is said to be <hi rend="italic">y    %</hi></p><p>reciprocal of <hi rend="italic">x,</hi>  which is again the reciprocal of X</p><p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps">Reciprocal Figures,</hi></hi>  in <hi rend="italic">Geometry,</hi>  those which have the antecedents and consequents of the same ratio in both figures.</p><p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps">Reciprocal Proportion</hi></hi>  is when, in four numbers, the fourth is less than the second by as much as the third is greater than the first, and <hi rend="italic">vice versa.</hi>  Great use is made of this reciprocal proportion by Sir Isaac Newton and others, in demonstrating the laws of motion.</p><p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps">Reciprocal Terms,</hi></hi>  amongst logicians, are those which have the same signification, and consequently are convertible, or may be used for each other.</p><p>RECITATIVO, or Recitative, in <hi rend="italic">Music,</hi>  a kind of singing, that differs but little from ordinary pronunciation ; such as that in which the several parts of the liturgy are rehearsed in cathedrals ; or that in which the actors commonly deliver themselves on the theatre at the opera, when they are to express some action or passion, relate some event, or reveal some design.</p><p>RECKLINGHAUSEN, a city of the Prussian province fo Westphalia, in the government of Munster, and the capital of a circle of the same name, which extends over 265 square miles, and contains 38,300 inhabitants. The city contains two churches, a convent, 420 houses, and 2500 inhabitants, but has very little trade. Long. <hi rend="sup">l</hi>7. 4. 57. E. Lat. 51. 37. 25. N.</p><p>RECKONING, or a <hi rend="italic">Ship's Reckoning,</hi>  in <hi rend="italic">Navigation, </hi>is the account by which at any time it may be known where the ship is, and on what course or courses she is to steer, in order to gain her port; and that account, when taken from the log-board, is called the <hi rend="italic">dead reckoning.</hi></p><p>RECLAIMING, or Reclaming, in our ancient customs, a lord’s pursuing, prosecuting, and recalling his vassal, who had gone to live in another place without his permission.</p><p>Reclaiming is also used for the demanding of a person or thing, to be delivered up to the prince or state to which it properly belongs, when, by any irregular means, it has passed into the possession of another.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Reclaiming, in </hi><hi rend="italic">Falconry,</hi>  is taming a hawk, and making her gentle and familiar.</p><p>A partridge is said to reclaim when she calls her young ones together, upon their scattering too much from her.</p><p>RECOGNIZANCE, in <hi rend="italic">Law,</hi>  is an obligation of record, which a man enters into before some court of record or magistrate, duly authorized, with condition to do some particular act, as to appear at the assizes, to keep the peace, to pay a debt, or the like.</p><p>RECOIL, or Rebound, the starting backwards of a firearm after an explosion. Mersenne tells us, that a cannon twelve feet in length, weighing 6400lbs. gives a ball of 24lbs. an uniform velocity of 640 feet per second. Putting, therefore, W = 6400, ia = 14, V = 640, and <hi rend="italic">ν</hi>  = the velocity with which the cannon recoils ; because the momentums of the cannon and ball are equal, we shall have W <hi rend="italic">v — w</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">tv V</hi>  24* x 64?</p><p>V ; and so <hi rend="italic">v</hi>  = <hi rend="sup">-</hi>ξγ^- '    <hi rend="sup">=</hi>  2∙4; that is, it would</p><p>recoil at the rate of 2<hi rend="sub">1</hi>⅞ feet per second, if free to move.</p><p>RECOLLECTION, a mode of thinking, by which ideas sought after by the mind are found and brought to view. See the article Metaphysics.</p><p>RECONNOITRE, in military affairs, implies to view and examine the state of things, in order to make a report thereon.</p><p>RECORDE, Robert, a physician and mathematician, was descended of a respectable family in Wales, and lived in the time of Henry VIII. Edward VI. and Mary of England. The time of his birth is not exactly known, but it must have been about the beginning of the sixteenth century ; for he was entered of the university of Oxford about 1525, and was elected fellow of All-Souls College in 1531. As he made physic his profession, he went to Cambridge, where he was honoured with the degree of doctor in that faculty in 1545, and was very much esteemed by all who were acquainted with him, for his extensive knowledge of many of the arts and sciences. ■  He afterwards returned to Oxford, where he publicly taught arithmetic and mathematics, as he had done prior to his going to Cambridge, and that with great applause. It appears that he afterwards went to London, and acted as physician to Edward VI. and to Queen Mary, to whom some of his books are dedicated ; yet he died in the King<hi rend="sup">,</hi>s-Bench prison, Southwark, where he was confined for debt in the year 1558, at a very immature age.</p><p>He published several works upon mathematical subjects, chiefly in the form of dialogue between master and scholar. Of these the following is a list, viz. 1. The Pathway to Knowledge, containing the first principles of geometry, as they may moste aptly be applied unto practice, bothe for the use of Instrumentes Geometricall and Astronomicall, and also for projection of Plattes, much necessary for all sortes of men, London, 1551, 4to ; 2. The Ground of Arts, teaching the perfect worke and practice of Arithmeticke, both in whole numbers and fractions, after a more easie and exact forme then in former time hath been set furth, 1552, 8vo ; 3. The Castle of Knowledge, containing the Explication of the Sphere both Celestiall and Materiall, and divers other things incident thereto, with sundry pleasaunt proofes and certaine newe demonstrations not written before in any vulgare woorkes, London, 1556, folio; 4. The Whetstone of Witte, which is the second part of Arithmetike, containing the extraction of rootes, the Cossike practice, with the rules of equation, and the woorkes of surde numbers, London, 1557, 4to.</p><p>Wood says that he was the author of several pieces on physic, anatomy, politics, and divinity ; but it is uncertain whether these were ever published. Sherburne states that he also published <hi rend="italic">Cosrnographiw Isagoge ;</hi>  that he wrote a book, <hi rend="italic">De Artc faciendi Horologium,</hi>  and another <hi rend="italic">De usu Globorum, et de statu Temporurn.</hi></p><p>RECORDER, a person whom the mayor and other magistrates of a city or corporation associate to themselves for their bettcr direction in matters of justice and proceedings in law ; on which account this person is generally a counsellor, or other person well skilled in the law.</p><p>RECOVERY, in English law, a species of assurance by matter of record, concerning the original of which it must be remarked, that common recoveries were invented by the ecclesiastics to elude the statutes of mortmain ; and afterwards they ιvere encouraged by the finesse of the courts of law in 12 Edward IV., in order to put an end to all fettered inheritances, and bar not only estates-tail, but also all remainders and reversions expectant thereon.</p><p>RECREATION Island, a fertile island in the Southern Pacific Ocean, discovered by Roggewein in the year 1722. It is about twelve leagues in circuit. The inhabitants are warlike and robust. Long. 148. W. Lat. 18. S.</p><p>RECTANGLE, in <hi rend="italic">Geometry,</hi>  is the same with a right-angled parallelogram.</p><p>RECTIFICATION, in <hi rend="italic">Chemistry,</hi>  is nothing but the repetition several times of a distillation or sublimation, in order to render the substance purer, finer, and freer from aqueous and earthy parts.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Rectification, in </hi><hi rend="italic">Geometry,</hi>  is the method of finding a</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>