<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>in lists according to the several counties in England and Wales, and entered in a book, with a careful annotation of any particulars applicable to their state or custody,” they were “ submitted to the inspection of the board, by whom the question as to their admissibility was discussed and recorded ; and in every instance the chairman, or the commissioner representing the chairman, authenticated such inspection and examination, by affixing his initials to the first and last entry in each register ; or if some parts of the register appeared to be copies, or not to bear marks of authenticity, he affixed his initials to such parts only as were deemed original or authentic.” With respect to all such registers as have thus been examined and deemed authentic, wholly or in part, the commissioners recommend, “ that they be kept together in some secure place of deposit, under the care of the Registrar-General, or of some other officer to be appointed for that purpose, that, under certain conditions, they be receivable in evidence in all courts of justice:” that the authorized custos of these registers shall permit searches, and grant certified extracts, on payment of moderate fees ; and that on payment of a reasonable fee he shall produce any original register deposited with him, on <hi rend="italic">Subpeena</hi>  or order of a competent tribunal : “ that all criminal proceedings shall be by production of the original : that in all other cases, copies or extracts, certified by the officer having custody of the original, shall, after notice, be receivable as evidence of the birth, baptism, marriage, death, or burial to which it relates, subject to the following regulations : that in courts of law, or at quarter-sessions, any party intending to use any certified extract from any register before mentioned, in evidence, on the trial of any cause, or hearing of any appeal, shall give notice in writing to the opposite party, his attorney or agent, of his intention to use such certified extract as evidence at such trial or hearing, and at the same time shall deliver to him a copy of the extract, and of the certificate thereof, in order that there may be a full opportunity to ascertain whether the authenticity, genuineness, or correctness of the entry may be liable to objection ; and in proof of such notice and delivery, or on admission of the receipt of such notice and copy, such certified extract shall be received in evidence at the trial or hearing, provided the judge or court shall be of opinion that such service had been made a reasonable time before such trial : that in case any party, instead of making proof by certified extract, intends to produce any original register in evidence, he shall nevertheless, within a reasonable time, give to the opposite party notice of his intention, together with a copy of a certified extract of the entry which he intends to offer in evidence.” The recommendations respecting the admission of registers, or certified extracts, in courts of equity, and in ecclesiastical courts, are: similar in character, containing only such variations as the different practice of those courts requires.</p><p>The registration of births, and deaths, and marriages in <hi rend="italic">France</hi>  is conducted under the provisions of the: <hi rend="italic">Code Civil</hi>  of Napoleon. The <hi rend="italic">maire</hi>  of each <hi rend="italic">commune,</hi>  of which there are about 37,300 in France, is the registering officer charged with the duty of registering, in books provided for the purpose, all births, deaths, and marriages, occurring within his commune. Births and deaths are registered in duplicate, the former upon information, in the presence of two witnesses, and are signed in duplicate by the informant, the two witnesses, and the registering officer ; in the case of deaths, one of the witnesses may be also the informant. Marriages are registered in the presence of four witnesses, and signed by the parties, the witnesses, and the registering officer. The register of births records the year, day, hour, and place of birth ; the sex and name of the child ; the names, surnames, professions, and residences of parents, witnesses, and informant ; the date of registration, and the name and quality of the registering officer ; and must be signed by him, by the witnesses, and by the informant. When the child is illegitimate, the name of the father cannot be given except by the authority of the father himself.</p><p>The register of deaths records the year, day, hour, and place of death ; the name, surname, age, profession, and residence of the deceased person ; the names, surnames, ages, professions, and residences of the parents of the deceased, and of the witnesses ; and the name and surname of the husband or wife, if the deceased was married ; also the date of registration, and the name and quality of the registering officer.</p><p>The register of marriages records the names, surnames, ages, professions, places of birth, and residences of the parties ; the names, surnames, professions, and residences of their respective parents, and of the four witnesses, with the relation in which they stand to the parties ; the consent of the parents ; whether the marriage has been opposed ; time and place of solemnization and registration ; and the name and quality of the registering officer.</p><p>Registration of births is secured by a provision, which requires, under pain of fine and imprisonment, from the father of the child, or, in default of the father, from some person present and assisting at the birth, a declaration thereof, within three days afterwards, to the registering officer, to whom the child must also be shown.</p><p>The registration of deaths is secured by a provision rendering it penal for a burial to take place without the registering officer having first seen the body and registered the death.</p><p>The registers are closed at the end of every year, with formalities which preclude interpolation. Alphabetical indexes are annually formed in duplicate for each. One of the duplicate registers, with its index, remains in the commune to which it belongs ; the other is transmitted to the tribunal of the district, where it is examined and placed under the superintendence of the <hi rend="italic">procureur du roi,</hi>  or the local officer of the c∙<hi rend="sup">,</hi>awn. Abstracts are made by the registering officer of each commune, a copy of which is transmitted to the sub-prefevt, who from thence frames an abstract for his arrondissement, a copy of which he sends to the prefect ; he also from the abstracts of the arrondissement makes an abstract for his department ; and copies of such abstracts are sent by the prefects of departments to be deposited in a central office at Paris.</p><p>The system of registration observed in France was introduced into Belgium, Geneva, and the Rhenish provinces of Prussia when under the dominion of France, and is still retained in those countries.</p><p>In Austria, registers of births, deaths, and marriages are kept by each minister of the church for his parish, and also by the Jewish rabbin for those of their own persuasion.</p><p>The register of births records the year, month, and day of birth ; the number of the house in which the birth occurred ; the name of the child and its sex, and whether it be born in wedlock or illegitimate; the names and surnames of the parents ; their religion ; and the names, and surnames, and condition of the sponsors. In the case of illegitimate children, the name of the father cannot be entered unless he acknowledges the paternity.</p><p>The register of deaths records the year, month, and day of death ; the number of the house in which it occurred ; the name, religion, sex, and stated age of the deceased ; and, when the information of a physician or surgeon can be supplied, the name of the fatal disease. For this purpose medical men are required to inform the minister, in writing, of the cause of death of such patients as they have attended.</p><p>The register of marriages records the year, month, and day of the marriage ; the place of solemnization ; the names and surnames of the parties ; their religion, age, and whether single or widowed ; and the names, and surnames, and condition of the witnesses.</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>