<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>since it occurred. This part of Rio is connected with the south-western quarter, or Bairro de Mato-porcos, by the bridge of St Diogo, thrown over a salt-water inlet. Between the old and new town is situated a large plain, nearly surrounded by an amphitheatre of mountains, clothed at their bases with the richest verdure, and terminating by belts of forest-trees of immense growth, and of every variety. One of these elevations is called the Corcovado, or Broken Back, an appellation which it acquired from its extraordinary and fantastical shape. The plain thus environed is enclosed with houses so as to form an enormous quadrangle, perhaps the largest square in the world. Here are erected the senate-house, the museum, the camera or town-hall, and other public buildings. One of the most striking features of the Brazilian capital is the number of its churches and monasteries, which not only abound in the city, but are seen crowning almost all the surrounding eminences.</p><p>Near the centre of the quay, which has already been mentioned, there is a large square, surrounded on three of its sides with buildings, but having its fourth open to the bay. In this square the palace or imperial residence is situated ; but although extensive in its dimensions, and commodious and even splendid in its internal arrangements, there is nothing magnificent or striking in its architecture. The public library occupies a suite of rooms in this quarter. It contains sixty or seventy thousand volumes in all languages, ancient and modern, and is considered a very admirable establishment. It is particularly distinguished for its collection of Bibles, said to be one of the most extensive in the world. On the quay, in front of the square, is a very beautiful fountain for supplying water to this part of the city, and to the shipping in the harbour. It is fed by a splendid stone aqueduct leading from the Corcovado Mountain, not more striking for the magnificent singularity of its appearance than for its importance and utility. This great work, which is called Arcos de Cariaco, extends across a deep valley, resting on a double tier of lofty arches placed one above the other to the height of eighty palms, and the water is conducted to the reservoir by a succession of stone troughs, laid on the top of this bridge, under an arched covering of brick-work. Each tier comprises forty-two arches, the upper one extending one hundred and forty fathoms. The whole of this splendid superstructure is highly ornamental to the city, as well as of the greatest utility to it. The following is the provision made for education : a military academy ; a naval academy ; a surgical and medical academy ; an academy of the fine arts, in connection with which we may mention a national museum ; and, lastly, two ecclesiastical seminaries, where the ancient and modern languages are taught, as well as divinity and the sciences. There are attached to it about twelve professors, for whose salaries eleven millions of reis are annually allowed by government. Besides these, there are several schools on Lancaster’s principle, and a primary school in almost every street of the city. In short, there seems to be ample provision made for the education of the people in Rio, and it is perfectly free to all classes, in which respect half-civilized Brazil is in advance of Great Britain herself. In periodicals, gazettes, and newspapers, the city is by no means deficient, and book-printing is carried on, although not extensively. Government has a printing establishment. There is a public walk and a botanic garden in the city, and another much more extensive at some distance from it. There is a bishop of Rio, who has under him the usual train of ecclesiastical functionaries. The Roman Catholic religion is that patronized by the state, but Protestants are permitted to exercise their own peculiar form of worship.</p><p>Rio is the grand emporium of Brazilian commerce ; but we need not enter into particulars in this place, as an account of the exports and imports will be found in the article Brazil, to which the reader is referred. Its coasting trade is immense, centring in itself that of all southern Brazil. The goods which it receives from foreign countries it distributes all over this vast region, obtaining the pro- ductions of each district in return. The manufactures of this city are unimportant. The shops are generally large and commodious, and well supplied with English goods, and other kinds of merchandise. Chinese goods may also be purchased here very reasonably. There is a number of English and North American merchants in the city, who monopolize no inconsiderable portion of the export trade.</p><p>The climate of Rio is considered as favourable to health, comfort, and even longevity, as that of any other place between the tropics. The sun is nearly vertical for a few weeks in December, when the heat is oppressive ; but a refreshing sea-breeze sets in every morning, and modifies the temperature. During the summer months, which may be reckoned as extending from October to April, heavy rains fall ; but, on the whole, few places possess a more beautiful climate than this celebrated city. At certain seasons it may be unhealthy to strangers, but the danger is averted by adopting the Brazilian mode of living, and by avoiding the night dews, exposure to the sun, and all excesses in eating and drinking. It is among the happy immunities of the country, that it is exempt from the accidents which occur in a similar latitude on the opposite side of the continent. Earthquakes are here unknown. The population consists of a singular mixture of coloure and nations. About two thirds are negroes, mulattoes, and other people of the darker shades. Among the whites are seen English, French, Germans, Italians, Dutch, and North Americans. Much disparity exists amongst the statements of writers regarding the exact number of the inhabitants. It is supposed to be about 200,000, of whom a very great number are slaves. The city lies in lat. 22.53. S. and long. 43. 12. W.</p><p>The bay of Rio was discovered on the 1st of January 1531, by Martin Alphonso de Sousa, a Portuguese navigator. The natives had given to this tranquil basin the significant appellation of Nitherohy, that is, hidden water; but he, supposing it the estuary of some great river like the Orinoco, called it the Rio de Janeiro, after the day on which it had been discovered. It. remained many years unnoticed or unoccupied by the Portuguese, but in the mean time was taken possession of by France, and became an asylum for the persecuted Huguenots. These were subsequently expelled by the Portuguese, who, in 1567, founded the city of Rio. In 1676 it was erected into a bishopric, and its riches soon rendered it an object of cupidity to other European powers. But the few attempts made to wrest it from Portugal were unsuccessful. It steadily advanced in riches and importance, so that in the year 1763, Dom Joseph was induced to transfer hither the vice-regal residence from Bahia, hitherto the capital of the province of Brazil. In 1803 it became the residence of the Portuguese court, and in 1822 was constituted the capital of the independent empire of Brazil. In 1831 it was the theatre of a revolution, in which 6000 armed citizens were joined by the troops of the line in their opposition to the government, and in consequence of which Dom Pedro abdicated the throne in favour of his son Pedro II.</p><p>According to the census of 1823, the last that has been made public, the population of the whole province of Rio de Janeiro was 589,650.    (r. r. r.)</p><p>RI0M, an arrondissement of the department of Puy de Dome, in France, extending over 893 square miles. It comprehends thirteen cantons, divided into 130 communes, and in 1336 contained 151,456 inhabitants. The capital is the city of the same name, situated on the river Limagne. It is well buih, with broad streets, and is surrounded by five</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>