<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>injunction was issued similar to that of 1597, with the important addition of a clause, appointing that the ancient registers, so far as they could be procured, but especially since the beginning of the reign of Elizabeth, should be copied into a parchment-book, to be provided by every parish ; after which, nothing more appears to have emanated, either from the ecclesiastical or civil authorities, on this subject, till the time of the Long Parliament, when the following entry in the Journal of the House of Commons gives evidence of attention to the importance of registration.</p><p>“ Anno 1644, Dec. 6. Ordered, that it be referred to the committee for bringing in the ordinance for the establishing the directory, to bring in a clause in that ordinance, for registering the time of baptizing of children, and their parents’ names, and for registering of burials.” In the same year an ordinance was made, directing, that in every parish or chapelry in England and Wales, the minister and other church-officers should keep a register of birth and baptism, of marriage, and of burial ; and that all persons reasonably desiring it might search therein and obtain copies.</p><p>In August 1653, in pursuance of the recommendations of a law-reform committee appointed in the preceding year, and including many eminent persons, an act was passed, which directed that in every parish a register-book shall be provided for registering all marriages, births, and burials in the parish ; and that the custody of such book, and the duty of registration, shall be given to a person, to be called the parish registrar, appointed by the parishioners chargeable to the poor, and approved by a justice of the peace. It was also enacted, that extra-parochial places, or small parishes, might be united, for the purposes of registration, to other parishes, by the justices at their sessions ; and that all existing register-books should be kept by the registering officers appointed under that act.</p><p>This act was not confirmed at the Restoration, and the business of registration reverted to the clergy of the established church. During the reigns of Charles II. and James II. nothing was done with respect to registers, except that, by a clause in the act of 30 Car. II. c. 3, entitled “ an act for burying in woollen,” it was enacted that all clergymen “ do, within their respective parishes, precincts, and places, take an exact account, and keep a register, of all and every person or persons buried in his or their respective parishes or precincts, or in such common burial-places as their respective parishioners are usually buried.”</p><p>In the reign of William III. registration was rendered a source of revenue. The act of 6 and 7 William III. c. 6, granted duties on births, marriages, and burials, and compelled the clergy, under a penalty of L.100, to keep an exact register of all persons born, christened, married, or buried in their respective parishes, to which register the collector of the tax, and all persons concerned, might have free access without fee. It thus imposed on the clergyman the onerous duty of acting gratuitously as a civil functionary, and collecting information of all births within his parish, without distinction of sect, and irrespective of baptism, a duty the difficulty of which was rendered greater by the attempts of the parents to conceal the birth, in order to elude the payment of the tax. With a view to obviate this objection, an act was passed in the following year (7 and 8 William III. c. 35), which provided that parents should, within five days after birth, give notice of the day of the birth to the clergyman, under a penalty of forty shillings, and that the clergyman should, under a like penalty, register such birth, for which the parents were to pay sixpence ; and by the 4th of Anne, c. 12, the clergy were relieved from the ruinous penalties incurred under the act of 6 and 7 William III. c. 6, in all cases where the duties ha&lt;¼ been really paid.</p><p>The 26th Geo. II. c. 33, an act “ to prevent clandestine</p><p>marriages,” directed the church-wardens of every parish to provide books of vellum, or good and durable paper, for the registration of marriages. By the 23d of Geo. III. c. 67, a stamp-duty of threepence was imposed upon every registered entry of burial, marriage, birth, or christening, to be demanded by the clergyman from the undertaker, or from the parties married, or from the parents of the child whose birth or christening had been registered. By 25 Geo. III. c. 75, the provisions of that act were extended to dissenting ministers. These measures excited much objection, and were repealed in 1794.</p><p>The next legislative measure affecting registers was the 52d Geo. III. c. 146, entitled “ an act for the better regulating and preserving parish and other registers of births, baptisms, marriages, and burials, in England.” After reciting that “ the amending the manner and form of keeping and of preserving registers of baptisms, marriages, and burials of his majesty’s subjects in the several parishes and places in England, will greatly facilitate the proof of pedigrees of persons claiming to be entitled to real or personal estates, and be otherwise of great public benefit and advantage,” it enacts, that, after the 31st of December 1812, registers of baptisms, marriages, and burials, according to the rites of the established church, shall be made and kept by the officiating minister of every parish and chapelry, in books to be provided by the king’s printer, at the expense of the respective parishes, according to the forms contained in schedules annexed to that act. These schedules contain the following particulars : In case of <hi rend="italic">baptism,—</hi>when baptized ; child’s Christian name ; parents’ Christian names and surnames ; abode ; quality, trade, or profession ; by whom the ceremony was performed. In case of <hi rend="italic">marriage,—</hi>the name and parish of the man ; the same of the woman ; when married ; whether by banns or license ; whether by consent of parents or guardians ; when ; by whom ; signature of officiating minister of the parties married, and of two witnesses. In case of <hi rend="italic">burial,—</hi>the name ; abode; when buried; age ; by whom the ceremony was performed.</p><p>The registers of baptism, marriage, and burial were to be kept in separate books, and signed within seven days after each ceremony had been performed. Annual copies were to be made, verified, and signed by the officiating minister, and attested by the church-wardens, and transmitted by them yearly to the registrar of the diocese ; which registrar must report thereon to his bishop ; must deposit such copies in a safe receptacle, arranged for reference; and cause alphabetical lists of persons and places to be made, kept, and opened for search.</p><p>It is to be observed that this act, which referred in its title to registers of births, made no provision for recording the date of birth. Neither did it provide a record of the date of death. It only provided records of the performance of the religious ceremonies of baptism, marriage, and burial, according to the rites of the Established Church. It therefore afforded an insufficient register, even for members of the Established Church, whilst for those who dissented from the Established Church, and therefore did not avail themselves of its ordinances for baptism or burial, it provided no register at all.</p><p>The inadequacy of this system, even if frllly carried into effect, and the insufficient manner in which it was complied with, called loudly for investigation and remedy, and became the subject of inquiry before a select committee of the House of Commons, appointed in March 1833, who, having, as they state, received evidence on registration “ from clergymen of the established church, and from parish-clerks; from gentlemen of the legal profession ; from authors devoted to antiquarian research ; from persons of different religious denominations, including Catholics, Dissenters, Jews, and Quakers ; from gentlemen eminently scientific, and attached to statistical inquiries ; from medical audio-</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>