<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>demy could not be measured with sufficient precision (being only observed <hi rend="italic">en passani)</hi>  for ascertaining its relation to the velocity. Du Buat attempted it in his experiments, but without success. This must evidently make a part of the resistance in all velocities: and it still remains an undecided question, “ What relation it bears to the velocities ?" When the solid body is wholly buried in the fluid this accumulation does not take place, or at least not in the same way ; it may, however, be observed. Every person may recollect, that in a very swift running stream a large stone at the bottom will produce a small swell above it ; unless it lies very deep, a nice eye may still observe it. The water, on arriving at the obstacle, glides past it in every direction, and is deflected on all sides ; and therefore what passes over it is also deflected upwards, and causes the water over it to rise above its level. The nearer that the body is to the surface, the greater will be the perpendlcular rise of the water, but it will be less diffused ; and it is uncertain whether the <hi rend="italic">whole</hi>  elevation will be greater or less. By the whole elevation we mean the area of a perpendicular section of the elevation by a plane perpendicular to the direction of the stream. We are rather disposed to think that this area will be greatest when the body is near the surface. D’Ulloa has attempted to consider this subject theoretically, and is of a very different opinion, which he confirms by the single experiment to be mentioned by and by. Meantime it is evident, that if the water which glides past the body cannot fall in behind it with sufficient velocity to fill up the space behind, there must be a void there ; and thus a hydrostatic pressure must be superadded to the resistance arising from the inertia of the water. All must have observed, that if the end of a stick held in the hand be drawn slowly through the water, the water will fill the place left by the stick, and there will be no curled wave ; but if the motion be very rapid, a hollow trough or gutter is left behind, and is not filled up till at some distance from the stick, and the wave which forms its sides is very much broken and curled. The writer of this article has often looked into the water from the poop of a second-rate man-of-war when she was sailing eleven miles per hour, which is a velocity of sixteen feet per second nearly ; and he not only observed that the back of the rudder was naked for about two feet below the load water-line, but also that the trough or wake made by the ship was filled up with water which was broken and foaming to a considerable depth, and to a considerable distance from the vessel ; there must therefore have been a void. He never saw the wake perfectly transparent (and therefore completely filled with water) when the velocity exceeded nine or ten feet per second. While this broken water is observed, there can be no doubt that there is a void and an additional resistance. But even when the space left by the body, or the space behind a still body exposed to a stream, is completely filled, it may not be filled sufficiently fast, and there may be (and certainly is, as we shall afterwards see) a quantity of water behind the body, which is moving more slowly away than the rest, and therefore hangs in some shape by the body, and is dragged by it, increasing the resistance. The quantity of this must depend partly on the velocity of the body or stream, and partly on the rapidity with which the surrounding water comes in behind. This last must depend on the pressure of the surrounding water. It would appear that when this adjoining pressure is very great, as must happen when the depth is great, the augmentation of resistance now spoken of would be less. Accordingly this appears in Newton’s experiments, where the balls were less retarded as they were deeper under water.</p><p>These experiments are so simple in their nature, and were made with such care, and by a person so able to detect and appreciate every circumstance, that they deserve great credit, and the conclusions <hi rend="italic">legitimately</hi>  drawn from them deserve to be considered as physical laws. We think that the present deduction is unexceptionable ; for in the motion of balls which hardly descended, their preponde-rancy being hardly sensible, the effect of depth must have borne a very great proportion to the whole resistanoe, and must have greatly influenced their motions ; yet they were observed to fall as if tile resistance had in no way depended on the depth.</p><p>The same thing appears in Borda’s experiments, where a sphere which was deeply immersed in the water was less resisted than one that moved with the same velocity near the surface ; and this was very constant and regular in a course of experiments. D’Ulloa, however, affirms the contrary ; he says that the resistance of a board, which was a foot broad, immersed one foot in a stream moving two feet per second, was 15½ lbs. and the resistance to the same board, when immersed two feet in a stream moving 1⅙ foot per second (in which case the surface was two feet), was 26¼ pounds.@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi></p><p>We have been more minute on this subject, because it is the leading proposition in the theory of the action of fluids. Newton’s demonstration of it takes no notice of the manner in which the various particles of the fluid are put in motion, or the motion which cach in particular acquires. He only shows, that if there be nothing concerned in the communication but pure inertia, the sum total of the motions of the particles, estimated in the direction of the motion of the body, or that of the stream, will be in the duplicate ratio of the velocity. It was therefore of importance to show that this part of the theory was just.</p><p>2.    It appears from a comparison of all the experiments, that the impulses and resistances are very nearly in the proportion of the surfaces. They appear, however, to increase somewhat faster than the surfaces. Borda found that the resistance, with the same velocity, to a surface of</p><p>9 inches ∖     <hi rend="italic">l</hi>    9 λ    Z    9</p><p><hi rend="sup">16</hi>    I    J    17,535 (    .    .    ,    <hi rend="sub">r</hi>    J 16</p><p>36    f <hi rend="sup">was</hi>S    42,750 f    <hi rend="sup">,nstead of</hi>    5 36</p><p>81    )    I 104,737 J    (    81</p><p>The deviation in these experiments from the theory increases with the surface, and is probably much greater in the extensive surfaces of the sails of ships and wind-mills, and the hulls of ships.</p><p>3.    The resistances by no means vary in the duplicate ratio of the sines of the angles of incidence.</p><p>As this is a circumstance of great importance, inasmuch as the whole theory of the construction and working of ships, and the action of water on our most important machines, depends upon it, it merits a very particular consideration. We cannot do a greater service than by rendering more generally known the excellent experiments of the French academy.</p><p>Fifteen boxes or vessels were constructed, w hich were two feet wide, two feet deep, and four feet long. One of them was a parallelopiped of these dimensions ; the others had prows of a wedge form, the angle of the wedge varying by 12° from 12° to 180°; so that the angle of incidence increased by 6° from one box to another. These boxes were dragged across a very large basin of smooth water, in which they were immersed two feet, by means of a line passing over a wheel connected with a cylinder, from which the moving weight was suspended. The motion soon became perfectly uniform ; and the time of passing over ninety-</p><p>@@@ There is something very unaccountable in these experiments. The resistances are much greater than any other author has observed.</p></body></text></TEI>