<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>consider the prow as composed of a number of parts, each of which is affected as if it were detached from all the rest.</p><p>As the very nature of naval architecture seems to require curvilineal forms in order to give the necessary strength, it seemed of importance to examine more particularly the deviations of the resistances of such prows from the resistances assigned by the theory. The academicians therefore made vessels with prows of a cylindrical shape ; one of these was a half cylinder, and the other was one third of a cylinder, both having the same breadth, viz. two feet, the same depth, also two feet, and the same length, four feet. The resistance of the half cylinder was to the resistance of the perpendicular prow in the proportion of 13 to 25, instead of being as 13 to 19∙5. Borda found nearly the same ratio of the resistances of the half cylinder, and the plane of its diameter when moved in air. He also compared the resistances of two prisms or wedges of the same breadth and height. The first had its sides plane, inclined to the base in angles of 60° : the second had its sides portions of cylinders, of which the planes were the chords, that is, their sections were arcs of circles of 60°. Their resistances were as 133 to 100, instead of being as 133 to 220, as required by the theory ; and as the resistance of the first was greater in proportion to that of the base than the theory allows, the resistance of the last was less.</p><p>Mr Robins found the resistance of a sphere moving in air to be to the resistance of its great circle as 1 to 2∙27, whereas theory requires them to be as 1 to 2. He found, at the same time, that the absolute resistance was greater than the weight of a cylinder of air of the same diameter, and having the height necessary for acquiring the velocity. It was greater in the proportion of 49 to 40 nearly.</p><p>Borda found the resistance of the sphere moving in water to be to that of its great circle as 1000 to 2503, and it was one ninth greater than the weight of the column of water whose height was that necessary for producing the velocity. He also found that the resistance of air to the sphere was to its resistance to its great circle as 1 to 2∙45.</p><p>It appears, therefore, on the whole, that the theory gives the resistance of oblique plane surfaces too small, and that of curved surfaces too great ; and that it is quite unfit for ascertaining the modifications of resistance arising from the figure of the body. The most prominent part of the prow changes the action of the fluid on the succeeding parts, rendering it totally different from what it would be were that part detached from the rest, and exposed to the stream with the same obliquity. It is of no consequence, therefore, to deduce any formula from the valuable experiments of the French academy. The experiments themselves are of great importance, because they give us the impulses on plane surfaces with every obliquity. They therefore put it in our power to select the most proper obliquity in a thousand important cases. By appealing to them, we can tell what is the proper angle of the sail for producing the greatest impulse in the direction of the ship’s course ; or the best inclination of the sail of a windmill, or the best inclination of the float of a water-wheel, &amp;c. &amp;c. We see also, that the deviation from the simple theory is not very considerable till the obliquity is great ; and that, in the inclinations which other circumstances would induce us to give to the floats of water-wheels, the sails of windmills, and the like, the results of the theory are sufficiently in accordance with experiment, for rendering this theory of very great use in the construction of machines. Its great defect is in the impulsions on curved surfaces, which puts a stop to our improvement of the science of naval architecture, and the w orking of ships.</p><p>Having thus pointed out the defects of the Newtonian theory by a comparison with experiment, we now proceed</p><p>to consider the circumstances which cause the great discrepancy. It has already been stated that Newton, in order to explain the phenomena of oblique impulse, assumed the distances between the particles of his hypothetical fluid to be infinitely great in comparison of their diameters, so that each particle might have room to escape, after making its stroke, without affecting the motions of the other particles, and consequently, that the actions of the particles might be regarded as so many separate collisions. But this assumption does not represent the real state of the case. The rare fluid introduced by Newton for the purpose now mentioned, either does not exist in nature, or does not act in the manner we have stated, namely, the particles making their impulse, and then escaping through among the rest w'ithout affecting their motion. We cannot indeed say what may be the proportion between the diameter and the distance of the particles. The first may be incomparably smaller than the second, even in mercury, the densest fluid which we are familiarly acquainted with ; but although they do not touch each other, they act nearly as if they did, in consequence of their mutual attractions and repulsions. We have seen air a thousand times rarer in some experiments than in others, and therefore the distance of the particles at least ten times greater than their diameters ; and yet, in this rare state, it propagates all pressures or impulses made on any part of it to a great distance, almost in an instant. It cannot be, therefore, that fluids act on bodies by impulse. It is very possible to conceive a fluid advancing with a flat surface against the flat surface of a solid. The very first and superficial particles may make an impulse ; and if they were annihilated, the next might do the same ; and if the velocity were double, these impulses would be double, and would be withstood by a double force, and not a quadruple, as is observed ; and this very circumstance that a quadruple force is necessary, should have made us conclude that it was not to impulse that this force was opposed. The first particles having made their stroke, and not being annihilated, must escape laterally. In their escaping they effectually prevent every farther impulse, because they come in the way of those filaments which would have struck the body. The whole process seems to be somewhat as follows :</p><p>When the particles of the fluid come into contact with the plane surface AB (fig. 6), perpendicular to the direction DC of their motion, they must deflect to both sides equally, and in equal portions, because no reason can be assigned why more should go to either side. By this means the filament EF, which would have struck the surface in G, is deflected <hi rend="italic">before it arrives at</hi>  the surface, and describes a curved path EFIHK, continuing its rectilineal motion to I, where it is intercepted by a filament immediately adjoining to EF, on the side of the middle filament DC. The different particles of DC may be supposed to impinge in succession at C, and to be deflected at right angles ; and, gliding along CB, to escape at B. Each filament in succession, outwards from DC, is deflected in its turn ; and being hindered from even touching the surface CB, it glides off in a direction parallel to it ; and thus EF is deflected in I, moves parallel to CB from I to H, and is again deflected at right angles, and describes HK parallel to DC. The same thing may be supposed to happen on the other side of DC. Thus it would appear, that except two filaments immediately adjoining to the line DC, which bisects the surface at right angles, no part of the fluid makes any impulse on the surface AB. All the other filaments are merely pressed against it by the lateral filaments without</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>