<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>of Rome was but faint and ambiguous before the Diet of Augsburg. Prior to that period, however, it appears, from undoubted testimony, that the doctrine of Luther had made a considerable, though probably secret, progress throughout Spain, Hungary, Bohemia, Britain, Poland, and Ithe Netherlands ; and had in all these countries gained many friends, of whom several repaired to Wittenberg, in order to enlarge their knowledge by means of Luther’s conversation. Some of these countries threw off entirely the yoke of Rome, and in others a prodigious number of families embraced the principles of the reformed religion. It is certain, indeed, and some Roman Catholics themselves acknowledge it without hesitation, that the papal doctrines and authority would at once have fallen into ruin in all parts of the world, had not the force of the secular arm been employed to support the tottering edifice. In the Netherlands particularly, the most grievous persecutions took place, so that by the Emperor Charles V. upwards of a hundred thousand were destroyed, whilst still greater cruelties were exercised upon the people by his son Philip II. The revolt of the United Provinces, however, and motives of real policy,, at last put a stop to these furious proceedings ; and although, in many provinces of the Netherlands, the establishment: of the Catholic religion was still continued, the Protestants have been long free from the danger of persecution on account of their principles.</p><p>The Reformation mad? considerable progress in Spain and Italy soon after the rupture between Luther and the Roman pontiff’. In all the provinces of Italy, but more especially in the territories of Venice, Tuscany, and Naples, the superstition of Rome lost ground, and great numbers of people of all ranks expressed an aversion to the papal yoke. In the year 1546, this occasioned violent and dangerous commotions in the kingdom of Naples ; which, however, were at last quelled by the united forces of Charles V., and his viceroy Don Pedro di Toledo. In several places the pope put a stop to the progress of the Reformation, by letting loose the inquisitors, who spread dreadful marks of their barbarity throughout the greater part of Italy. These formidable ministers of persecution put so many to death, and perpetrated such horrid acts of cruelty and oppression, that most of the reformed consulted their safety by a voluntary exile, whilst others returned to the religion of Rome, at least in external appearance. But the inquisition, which frightened into the profession of Popery several Protestants in other parts of Italy, could never make its way into the kingdom of Naples ; nor could either the authority or the entreaties of the pope engage the Neapolitans to admit even visiting inquisitors.</p><p>In Spain, several persons embraced the Protestant religion, not only from the controversies of Luther, but even from those divines whom Charles V. had brought with him into Germany in order to refute the doctrines of the Reformer. For these doctors had imbibed the pretended heresy instead of refuting it, and propagated it more or less on their return home. But the inquisition, w’hich could obtain no footing in Naples, reigned triumphant in Spain, and by the most dreadful methods frightened the people back into Popery, and suppressed the desire of exchanging their superstition for a more rational plan of religion. It was indeed presumed that Charles himself died a Protestant ; and it seems to be certain, that when the approach of death had dissipated those schemes of ambition and grandeur which had so long blinded him, his sentiments became much more rational and agreeable to Christianity than they had ever been before. All the ecclesiastics who had attended him, as soon as he expired, were sent to the inquisition, and committed to the flames, or put to death by some other met hod equally terrible. Such was the fate of Augustin Casal, the emperor’s preacher ; of Constantius Pontius, his confessor ; of Egidius, whom he had named to the bishopric of Tortosa ;</p><p>of Bartolomeo de Caranza<hi rend="sub">1</hi> a Dominican, who had been confessor to Philip and Mary ; besides twenty others of less note.</p><p>In England, the principles of the Reformation began to be adopted as soon as an account of Luther’s doctrines could be conveyed thither. In that kingdom there were still remains of the sect called Lollards, whose doctrine resembled that of Luther ; and amongst whom, consequently, the sentiments of the Reformer gained great credit. Henry VIII., king of England, was at that time a violent partisan of the Church of Rome, and had a particular veneration for the writings of St Thomas Aquinas. Being informed that Luther spoke of his favourite author with contempt, he conceived a violent prejudice against the Reformer, and even wrote against him, as we have already mentioned. Luther did not hesitate about writing against his majesty, overcame him in argument, and treated him with very little ceremony. The first step towards public reformation, how-ever, was not taken until the year 1529. Great complaints had been made in England, from a very early period, respecting the usurpations of the clergy ; and the prevalence of the Lutheran opinions rendered these complaints more loud and general than before. The House of Commons, finding the occasion favourable, passed several bills restraining the impositions of the clergy ; but what threatened the ecclesiastical order with the greatest danger, were the severe reproaches throw n out in the house, almost without opposition, against the dissolute lives, ambition, and avarice of the priests, and their continual encroachments on the privileges of the laity. The bills for regulating the clergy met with opposition in the House of Lords ; and Bishop Fisher imputed them to want of faith in the Commons, and to a formed design, proceeding from heretical and Lutheran principles, of robbing the church of her patrimony, and overturning the national religion. The Commons, however, complained to the king, by their Speaker Sir Thomas Audley, of these reflections thrown out against them ; and the bishop was obliged to retract his words.</p><p>Though Henry had not the least idea of rejecting any, even of the most absurd observances of the Catholic Church, yet as the oppressions of the clergy w ere very ill suited to the violence of his own temper, he was pleased with every opportunity of lessening their power. In the parliament of 1531, he showed his design of humbling the clergy in the most effectual manner. An obsolete statute w<hi rend="sup">,</hi>as revived, from which it was pretended, that to submit to the legatine power which had been exercised by Cardinal Wolsey was criminal. By this stroke the whole body of clergy was at once declared guilty. They were too well acquainted with Henry’s disposition, however, to reply, that their ruin would have been the certain consequence of their not submitting to Wolsey’s commission, which had been given by royal authority. Instead of making any defence of this kind, they chose to throw themselves on the mercy of their sovereign ; which, however, it cost them L.118,840 to procure. A confession was likewise extorted from them, that the king was protector and supreme head of the Church of England ; though some of them had the dexterity to get a clause inserted, which invalidated the whole submission, namely, “ in as far as is permitted by the law of Christ.”</p><p>The king having thus begun to reduce the power of the clergy, kept no bounds with them afterwards. He did not indeed attempt any reformation in religious matters ; nay, he persecuted most violently such as did in the least degree attempt anything of the kind. Indeed the most essential article of his creed seems to have been his own supremacy ; for whoever denied this, whether Protestant or Papist, was sure to suffer the most severe penalties.</p><p>He died in the year 1547, and was succeeded by his only son, Edward VI. This amiable prince gave new spirit and vigour to the Protestant cause, and was its brightest ornament;</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>