<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>to be kept fixed by some exterior cause, in a fluid which strikes against it. The filaments, on encountering the obstacle, bend themselves in different directions, and the portion of fluid which covers the anterior part of the body remains stagnant to a certain distance. Now the pressure sustained by the obstacle, or the resistance which it opposes to the fluid, is produced by the loss of velocity which the particles undergo ; for one body acts on another only by communicating, or tending to communicate, to it a part of its own motion. He then shows that the question reduces itself to find the velocity of the particles which glide past the surface of the body (which he determines in two different ways) ; and this velocity being found, we have the rigorous formulæ for the pressure. It then only remains, theoretically speaking, to compute the formula: in order to obtain results applicable in practice. But this is what we can scarcely hope to accomplish without restricting their generality, and neglecting some of the conditions which essentially belong to the question. So inadequate are our mathematical theories to cope with the difficulty, that even D’Alembert has not been able to exemplify the application of the equation to the simplest case which can be proposed, namely, the direct impulse on a plane surface wholly immersed in the fluid. All that he is enabled to do, is to apply it (by some modifications and substitutions which take it out of its state of extreme generality) to the direct impulse of a vein of fluid on a plane which deflects it wholly, and thus to show its conformity to the solution given by Daniel Bernoulli, and to observation and experience. He shows, that this impulse (independent of the deficiency arising from the plane not being of infinite extent) is somewhat less than the weight of a column whose base is the section of the vein, and whose height is twice the fall necessary for communicating the velocity. This great philosopher and geometer concludes by saying, that he does not believe that any method can be found for solving this problem that is more direct and simple ; and imagines, that if the deductions from it shall be found not to agree with experiment, we must give up all hopes of determining the resistance of fluids by theory.@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi></p><p>In the present state of the theory of hydrodynamics, it would be of great importance to multiply experiments on the resistance of bodies. Those of the French academy arc undoubtedly of much value, and will always be appealed to ; but there are circumstances in those experiments which render them more complicated than is proper for a general theory, and which therefore limit the conclusions which we wish to draw from them. The bodies were floating on the surface. This greatly modifies the deflections of the filaments of water, causing some to deflect laterally which would otherwise have remained in one vertical plane ; and this circumstance also necessarily produced what the academicians called the <hi rend="italic">remow</hi>  or accumulation on the anterior part of the body, and depression behind it. This produced an additional resistance, which was measured with great difficulty and uncertainty. The effect of adhesion must also have been very considerable, and very different in the different cases ; and it is of difficult calculation. It cannot perhaps be totally removed in any experiment, and it is necessary to consider it as making part of the resistance in the most important practical cases, viz. the motion of ships. Here we see that its effect is very great. Every seaman knows that the speed even of a copper-sheathed ship is <hi rend="italic">greatly </hi>increased by greasing her bottom. The difference is too remarkable to admit of a doubt : nor should we be surprised at this, when we attend to the diminution of the motion of water in long pipes. A smooth pipe four and a half inches diameter and 500 yards long yields but one fifth of the quantity which it ought to do independently of friction. But adhesion produces a great effect, which cannot be com-ared with friction. We see that water flowing through a ole in a thin plate will be increased in quantity fully one third by adding a little tube whose length is about twice the diameter of the hole. The adhesion therefore will greatly modify the action of the filaments both on the solid body and on each other, and will change both the forms of the curves and the velocities in different points.</p><p>The form of these experiments of the academy is ill suited to the examination of the resistance of bodies wholly immersed in the fluid. The form of experiment adopted by Robins for the resistance of air, and afterwards by the Chevalier Borda for water, is free from these inconveniences, and is susceptible of equal accuracy. The great advantage of both is the exact knowledge which they give us of the velocity of the motion ; a circumstance essentially necessary, and but imperfectly known in the experiments of Mariotte and others, who examined quiescent bodies exposed to the action of a stream. It is extremely difficult to measure the velocity of a stream, which is also very different in its different parts. It is swiftest of all in the middle superficial filament, and diminishes as we recede from this towards the sides or bottom, and the rate of diminution is not precisely known.</p><p>It were greatly to be wished that some more palpable argument could be found for the existence of a quantity of stagnant fluid at the anterior and posterior parts of the body. The one already given, derived from the consideration that no motion changes either its velocity or direction by finite quantities in an instant, is unexceptionable, but gives us little information. But surely there are circumstances which rigorously determine the extent of this stagnant fluid. And it appears, without doubt, that if there were no cohesion or friction, this space will have a determined ratio to the size of the body (the figures of the bodies being supposed similar). Suppose a plane surface AB, as in fig. 10, there can be no doubt but that the figure AaDèB will in every case be similar. But if we suppose an adhesion or tenacity which is constant, this may make a change both in its extent and its form : for its constancy of form depends on the disturbing forces being always as the squares of the velocity ; and this ratio of the disturbing forces is preserved, while the inertia of the fluid is the only agent and patient in the process. But when we add to this the constant (that is, invariable) disturbing force of tenacity, a change of form and dimensions must happen. In like manner, the friction, or something analogous to friction, which produces an effect proportional to the velocity, must alter this necessary ratio of the whole disturbing forces. We may conclude, that the effect of both these circumstances will be to diminish the quantity of this stagnant fluid, by licking it away externally ; and to this we must ascribe the fact, that the part ADB is never perfectly stagnant, but is generally disturbed with a whirling motion. We may also conclude, that this stagnant fluid will be more</p><p>@@@ The rigorous equations of the motions of fluids, whether incompressible or elastic, were first given by D’Alembert in his<hi rend="italic">Essai d'une E<hi rend="sup">r</hi>OuvclIe Théorie sur lu Résistance des Fluides,</hi>  1752 ; but the analytical theory was greatly simplified, and the formulæ, which are expressed by equations of partial differences, rendered completely general, by Euler (Berlin Memoirs, 1/50). The general equations of motion have been still further simplified by Lagrange, and if it were possible to integrate them, we should be enabled to determine completely, in every case, all the circumstances of the action of a fluid put in motion by any forces whatever. But the dif-ficulty Of effecting the integrations has hitherto proved insuperable, and mathematicians have hitherto been obliged, even in the solution of the simplest problems, to have recourse to particular methods, grounded on restricted hypotheses. See Fourth Preliminary Dissertation, sect. 2.</p></body></text></TEI>