<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>in the hundred of its own name, thirty-eight miles fan London, on the high road to Bath and Bristol. It is situated on the right bank of the Thames, where it is joined by the Kennet, in a fine situation rising gradually from the river, and is one of the most cheerful and well-built towns of its size in England. It has three parish churches, and various chapels for dissenters. The county sessions are held at it, and there is a house of correction. The chief trade is what is carried on by the rivers, which unite here, and into which several canals lead. There are some manufactures of silk ribbons, of sail-cloth, and blanketing ; and some barge-building. It has a corporation, consisting of a mayor, three aldermen, and seventeen councillors, and returns two members to the House of Commons. There are markets on Wednesday and on Saturday, which are well supplied , and the place is well situated for the flour trade. The population amounted in 1801 to 9742, in 1811 to 10,788, in 1821 to 12,867, and in 1831 to 15,595.</p><p>RE-AGGRAVATION, in the Roman ecclesiastical law, the last monitory, published after three admonitions, and before the final excommunication. Previous to fulminating the last excommunication, they publish an aggravation and a re-aggravation. Fevret observes, that in France the minister is not allowed to come to re-aggravation, without the permission of the bishop or official, as well as that of the lay judge.</p><p>REALISTS, a sect of scholastic philosophers formed in opposition to the Nominalists. Under the realists are included the Scotists, Thomists, and all excepting the followers of Ocham. Their distinguishing tenet is, that uni-versals are realities, and have an actual existence out of idea or imagination, or, as they express it in the schools, a <hi rend="italic">parte rei ;</hi>  whereas the nominalists contend that they exist only in the mind, and are merely ideas, or manners of conceiving things. Odo, or Oudard, a native of Orleans, afterwards abbot of St Martin de Tournay, was the chief of the sect of the Realists. He wrote three books of dialectics, in which, on the principles of Boethius and the ancients, he maintained that the object of that art was things, not words, and hence the sect took its rise and name.</p><p>REALITY, in the schools, a diminutive of <hi rend="italic">res,</hi>  thing, was first used by the Scotists, to denote a thing which may exist of itself ; or which has a full and absolute being of itself, and is not considered as a part of any other.</p><p>REALM, a country which gives its head or governor the denomination of a <hi rend="italic">hing.</hi></p><p>RE-ANIMATION means the reviving or restoring to life those who are apparently dead. Sudden death is dreaded by every human being, and it is one of those evils against which the Church of England prays in her litany. Accidents, however, cannot always be prevented ; but, after they have happened, it is often possible to prevent their effects. By the establishment of what has with great propriety been called the <hi rend="italic">Humane Society,</hi>  this has been abundantly proved ; for, in the course of twelve years immediately after its institution, it was the means of saving the lives of 850 persons, who otherwise would in all human probability have been lost to the community. Since that period it has saved many more ; and various persons, even in the most distant parts of the kingdom, have done the same by following the directions prescribed. To preserve one human being from premature death, we must consider as of the utmost consequence, both as citizens and Christians ; and how much more the preservation of thousands ? It appears from the writings of Mead, Winslow, Bruhier, Fothergill, Haller, Lecat, Tissot, Van Engelen, Gummer, and others, that they had prepared the way for institutions similar to the Humane Society ; for in their works they have elucidated the principles on which such institutions proceed, and furnished directions for the practice they favour.</p><p>REAR, a term frequently used in composition to denote something behind or backwards in respect of another. It is used in opposition to <hi rend="italic">van.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps">Rear of an Army</hi></hi>  signifies, in general, the hindmost part of an army, battalion, regiment, or squadron ; and also the ground behind either.</p><p><hi rend="italic">REAR-Guard</hi>  is that body of an army which marches after the main body. The march of an army is always composed of an advanced guard, a main body, and a rearguard ; the first and last commanded by a general.</p><p><hi rend="italic">REAR Half-files</hi>  are the three hindmost ranks of the battalion when it is drawn up six deep.</p><p><hi rend="italic">REAR-Line</hi>  of an army encamped, is always twelve hundred feet at least from the centre line, both of which run parallel to the front line, as also to the reserve.</p><p><hi rend="italic">REAR-Ranh</hi>  is the last rank of a battalion when drawn up, and generally sixteen or eighteen feet from the centre line when drawn up in order.</p><p>REASON, a faculty or power of the mind. See the article Metaphysics.</p><p>REASONING, Ratiocination, the exercise of that faculty of the mind which is called <hi rend="italic">reason ;</hi>  or it is an act or operation of the mind, deducing some unknown proposition from other previous ones that are evident and known. See the article Logic.</p><p>REAUMUR, Rene Antoine Ferchaolt, Sieor de, a person distinguished for his laborious researches in natural science, was born at Rochelle in 1683, being descended of a family belonging to the law. After having finished his early studies in the place of his birth, he began a course of philosophy at Poitiers, and one of civil law at Bourges ; but he soon relinquished the latter to apply himself to mathematics, physics, and natural history. Having come to Paris, he was received into the Academy of Sciences in 1708. From that hour he was wholly employed in natural history, to which his inclination particularly led him ; and his inquiries were not confined to any one part of the subject. His memoirs, his observations, his discoveries on the formation of shells, spiders, muscles, the marine flea, the berry which affords the purple colour, and on the cause of the numbness of the torpedo, excited the curiosity of the public, and early procured our author the character of an able, curious, and entertaining naturalist. Filled with zeal for the welfare and advantage of society, and for the progress and perfection of arts, he endeavoured in all his researches to promote the public good. The public were indebted to him for the discovery of the turquois mines in Languedoc. He also foιmd out a substance, now used to give false stones a colour, which is obtained from a certain fish called in the French <hi rend="italic">able</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">ablete</hi>  on account of its whiteness, and which is the <hi rend="italic">bleak</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">blay</hi>  of our writers. His experiments on the art of turning iron into steel obtained him a pension of twelve thousand livres ; and this reward was to be continued to the Academy to support the expense which might accrue in this art.</p><p>He continued his inquiries on the art of making tin and porcelain, and endeavoured to render our thermometers more useful than those of former times. He composed a curious history of rivers where gold-dust is found in France ; and he gave so simple and so easy a detail of the art of gathering this dust, that persons have been employed for that purpose. He also made curious and important observations on the nature of flints ; on the banks of fossil shells, whence is obtained in Touraine an excellent manure for land ; and likewise on birds and their preservation, on their method of building nests, on insects, and a great number <hi rend="italic">of</hi>  other subjects, not less curious than useful.</p><p>He at first imagined that a certain varnish would keep eggs fresh ; but the waste of time and money showed him the inconvenience of such a process. He afterwards adopted the method practised from time immemorial in Greece and the islands of the Archipelago, which is to steep or im-</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>