<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>of this prince, his son Constantius had the obelisk transported from Alexandria to Rome in 352, where it was erected in the circus maximus. Its height exceeded 130 feet. When the Goths sacked the city of Rome in 409, they overthrew the obelisk, which continued buried in the sand till the time of Sixtus V. in 1587, when it was found broken in three pieces ; but these being joined together, it was set up in the square of St John Lateran.</p><p>RAMGERRY, a town and fortress of the south of India, in the province of Malabar, situated on the Paniany river, and taken by the British in 1782.</p><p>RAMGHAUT, a town of Hindustan, in the province of Delhi, pleasantly situated on the western bank of the Ganges, and carrying on a considerable traffic. Long. 78. <hi rend="italic">22.</hi>  E. Lat. 28. 12. N.</p><p>RAMGONGA, a river of Hindustan, which rises in the mountains of Thibet, and falls into the Ganges ten miles north of the ancient city of Canonge. In some places it is fordable ; but from quagmires and quicksands the fords are dangerous.</p><p>RAMGUNGE, a town of Hindustan, in the nabob of Oude’s territories, twenty· five miles south-west from Lucknow. Long. 80. 35. E. Lat. 26. 37. N.</p><p>RAMGÜR, an extensive district and town of Hindustan, in the province of Bahar. The district is situated about the 24th degree of north latitude, and is one of the most unproductive in India. Its boundaries on the north are the district of Bahar proper ; on the south, Nagpoor and Pachete ; on the east, Monghir and Pachete ; and on the west, Pa-lamow. Other limits, however, are assigned to the modern district, which comprehends a much greater space, and may be considered as belonging to the ancient province of Gund-wana. A great part of the territory is mountainous, the soil is of rock, and a considerable portion of it is overrun with impenetrable woods. The chief produce is a coarse rice. All the hills abound with iron, which is fused by the natives in large quantities, and sold. The chief rivers are the Dum-moodah and the Burrahkur ; and the principal towns are Ramgur, Chittra, and Muckundgunge. Agreat part of the population consists of Hindus, though it was conquered by the Mahommedans in the middle of the sixteenth century. The capital, of the same name, is situated on the northern bank of the Dummoodah river, and formerly possessed a strong fortress. It is 910 miles north-west from Calcutta. Long. 84. 35. E. Lat- 20. 38. N.</p><p>RAMGURRY, one of the innumerable hill-forts with which the face of the country in India is in many parts studded. It is situated in the province of Mysore, on a very steep rock, and is well fortified by art. It is twenty miles south-west of Chitteldroog.</p><p>RAMILLIES, a small village of Brabant, in the Netherlands, twelve miles north of Namur, and twenty-two southeast of Brussels. Long. 4.48. E. Lat. 50.51. N. Itisfamous for the battle fought by the allies commanded by the Duke of Marlborough and M. d’Auverquerque, against that of the two crowns, commanded by the Duke of Bavaria and Marshal Villeroi, on the 22d of May 1706.</p><p>RAMKEWRA, a town of Hindustan, belonging to the peshwa of the Mahrattas, in the province of Bejapore, twenty-seven miles north-east from Poonah. Long. 74. 20. E. Lat. 18.41. N.</p><p>RAMLEAH, the name of a ridge of mountains in Arabia, crossing the division of Nedsjed, extending 250 miles from south-west to north-east, and terminating within eighty miles of Kalaat el Moilah.</p><p>RAMMlSSER, a tow<hi rend="sup">τ</hi>n of Hindustan, in the province of Khandeish, belonging to the Mahrattas, and situated at the confluence of the rivers Ghirah and Tuptee. Long. 75. 21. E. Lat. 21. 4. N.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">RaMMISSERAM Isle, an island situated in the straits between the island of Ceylon and the continent ; it is eleven</hi></p><p>VOL. XIX.</p><p>miles in length, by six in breadth, and separated from the latter by a narrow strait. It is low, sandy, and uncultivated, and is of little value, except as a seat of Hindu superstition. It possesses a celebrated pagoda, the entrance to which is through a lofty gateway, about a hundred feet in height, covered with carved work to the summit. It contains a town called Panban ; but its chief value is derived from a celebrated temple, which is about six hundred feet square, and is one of the finest pieces of architecture in India. The entrance into this temple is by a door forty-six feet in height, placed perpendicularly, with others crossing, and in massiveness of workmanship resembling the Egyptian style of architecture. None is permitted to enter into the inner temples except the attendants of Brahmins, who live in the town, and have their share of the offerings. The expenses of the rajah of Tanjore at this place usually amounted to 60,000 pagodas. No water is used except what is brought all the way from the Ganges, and is poured over the deity every morning, and then sold to the devout, by which a considerable revenue accrues to the temple. The capital is about nine miles distant from the great temple.</p><p>RAMNAD, a town and capital of a district of the same name, in the south of India, and province of Marawar. This pollam or zemindary was granted to the ancestors of the present family, on condition of their granting protection to the pilgrims on their road to Rammisseram, and for which protection they were also to pay a tax. The ruler is a lady, styled the rannee, who has a clear revenue of 90,000 pagodas a year, of which she pays one half to the Company, reserving 45,000 for herself. Here is a fort built many years ago by the rannee’s ancestors, but never completed. The palace adjoins it, and is a gloomy building, with lofty walls, and no window on the outside. Near it is the tomb of the rannee’s deceased husband, and a Protestant church of very neat architecture. Betel-nut from Ceylon, and red silk cloths from Bengal, constitute the chief imports ; and the exports are piece-goods, cotton, and conch-shells.</p><p>RAMNAGUR, a town of Hindustan, in the province of Allahabad, and district of Benares, which stands on the eastern bank of the Ganges, opposite the city of Benares, and is esteemed one of the neatest towns of its size in India ; the houses are of stone, and the streets of a good breadth. It contains also the palace of the rajah, and a very handsome small temple, covered with figures in alto-relievo, having in front an extensive reservoir, and surrounded by gardens. It was the favourite residence of Cheyt Sing. Long. 83. 1. E. Lat. 25. 30. N.</p><p>RAMNODE, a town of Hindustan, in the Mahratta territories, and province of Mahvah<hi rend="sub">1</hi> forty miles south-east from Narwar. Long. 78. 5. E. Lat. 25. 6. N.</p><p>RAMPANT, in <hi rend="italic">Heraldry,</hi>  a term applied to a lion, leopard, or other beast that stands on its hind-legs, and rears up his fore-feet in the posture of climbing, thus showing only half his face. It is different from salient, in which the beast seems springing forward as if making a sally.</p><p>RAMPART, in <hi rend="italic">Fortiflxation,</hi>  is an elevation of the earth thrown out of a ditch round a place, and capable of resisting the cannon of an enemy. It is formed into bastions, curtains, and other defences</p><p>RAMPOOR, a town of Hindustan, in the Mahratta province of Malwah, thirteen miles east from Bopal. Long. 77. 42. E. Lat. 23. 15. N.</p><p>RAMPOOR, a town and district of Hindustan, province of Delhi, in the district of Bareily, situated on the banks of the Corilla river. This town and district was, by the peace of Lahdong, in 1774, secured to Fyzoola Khan, a Rohilla chief. His eldest son succeeded at his death. He was afterwards assassinated by his second son, who seized the throne ; but the latter was soon afterwards expelled by a British force under Sir Ralph Abercromby, and his treasures seized, amounting in value to L.640,000, and delivered</p><p>ι</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>