<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Life of Rowe, he says, “ The character of Lothario seems to have been expanded by Richardson into that of Lovelace ; but he has excelled his original in the moral effect of the fiction. Lothario, with gaiety which cannot be hated, and bravery which cannot be despised, retains too much of the spectator’s kindness. It was in the power of Richardson alone to teach us at once esteem and detestation ; to make virtuous resentment overpower all the benevolence which wit, and elegance, and courage, naturally excite ; and to lose at lathe hero in the villain.” Dr Young has remarked, that Richardson, with the mere advantages of nature, improved by a very moderate progress in education, struck out at once, and of his own accord, into a new province of writing, in which he succeeded to admiration. And, what is more remarkable, he not only began, but finished, the plan on which he set out, leaving no room for any one after him to render it more complete ; and not one of the various writers that have ever since attempted to imitate him, have in any respect equalled, or at all approached near him. This kind of romance is peculiarly his own ; and “ I consider him,” he continues, “ as a truly great natural ge-thus ; as great and supereminent in his way as Shakspeare and Milton were in theirs.”</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Richabdson, </hi><hi rend="italic">Jonathan,</hi>  a celebrated painter of heads, was bom about the year 1665, and against his inclination was placed by his father-in-law apprentice to a scrivener, with whom he lived six years. Having obtained his freedom by the death of his master, he followed the bent of his disposition, and at the age of twenty became the disciple of Riley, with whom he lived four years, whose niece he married, and of whose manner he acquired enough to maintain a solid and lasting reputation, even during the lives of Kneller and Dahl, and to remain at the head of the profession when they no longer continued to exercise it.</p><p>There is strength, roundness, and boldness in his colouring ; but his men want dignity, and his women grace. The good sense of the nation is characterised in his portraits. We perceive that he lived in an age when neither enthusiasm nor servility was predominant. Yet with a pencil so firm, possessed of a numerous and excellent collection of drawings, full of the theory, and profound in reflections on his art, he drew nothing well below the head, and was void of imagination. His attitudes, draperies, and back-grounds, are totally insipid and unmeaning ; so ill did he apply to his own practice the sagacious rules and hints which he bestowed on others. Though he wrote with fire and judgment, his paintings owed little to either. No man dived deeper into the inexhaustible stores of Raphael, or was more smitten with the native lustre of Vandyck. Yet though capable of relishing the elevation of the one and the elegance of the other, he could never contrive to see with their eyes when he was to copy nature himself. One wonders that he could comment on their works so well, and imitate them so little.</p><p>He quitted business some years before his death ; but his temperance and virtue contributed to protract his life to a great length in the full enjoyment of his understanding, and in the felicity of domestic friendship. He had a paralytic stroke that affected his arm, yet never disabled him from his customary walks and exercise. He had been in St James’s Park, and died suddenly at his house in Queen’s-square on his return home, on the 28th of May 1745, when he had passed the eightieth year of his age. He left a son and four daughters ; one of whom was married to his disciple Mr Hudson, and another to Mr Grigson, an attorney. The taste and learniβg of the son, and the harmony in which he lived with his father, are visible in the joint works which they composed. In 1719 the father published two discourses : 1. An Essay on the whole Art of Criticism as it relates to Painting ; 2. An Argument in behalf of the Science of a Connoisseur. In 1722 came forth</p><p>“ An Account of some of the Statues, Bas-reliefs, Drawings, and Pictures, in Italy, &amp;c. with Remarks by Mr Richardson, senior and junior.” The son made the journey ; and from his notes, letters, and observations, they both at his return compiled this valuable work. As the father was a formal man, with a slow but loud and sonorous voice, and, in truth, with some affectation in his manner, and as there is much singularity in his style and expression, these peculiarities, for they were scarcely foibles, struck superficial readers, and between the laughers and the envious the book was much ridiculed. Yet both this and the former are full of matter, good sense, and instruction ; and the very quaintness of some expressions, and their laboured novelty, shew the difficulty which the author experienced in his attempts to convey mere visible ideas through the medium of language. If these authors were censured when they confined themselves within their own circle, it was not to be expected that they would be treated with milder indulgence when they ventured into a sister region. In 1734, they published a very thick octavo, containing explanatory notes and remarks on Milton’s Paradise Lost, with the life of the author, and a discourse on the poem. Again were the good sense, the judicious criticisms, and the sentiments that broke forth in this work, forgotten in the singularities by which it is distinguished. The father having said, in apology for being little conversant in ancient literature, that he had looked into the classics through his son, Hogarth, whom a quibble could furnish with wit, drew the father peeping through the nether end of a telescope, with which his son was perforated, at a Virgil placed on a high shelf. Richardson, indeed, was as incapable of reaching the sublime or harmonious in poetry, as he was in painting, though so capable of illustrating both. Some specimens of verse that he has given us here and there in his works excite no curiosity for more, though he informs us in his Milton, that if painting was his wife, poetry had been his secret concubine.</p><p>RICHELET, Cæsar Peter, a French writer, born in 1631, at Chemin in Champagne, was the friend of Patru and Albancourt ; and like them applied himself to the study of the French language with success. He compiled a dictionary of that language, full of new and useful remarks ; but exceptionable, as containing many satirical reflections and obscenities. The best edition is that of Lyon, 1728, three volumes folio. He also collected a small dictionary of rhymes, and composed some other pieces in the grammatical and critical department. He died in 1698.</p><p>RICHELIEU, John Armand du Plessis de, cardinal of Richelieu and Fronsac, bishop of Lucon, &amp;c. was born at Paris in 1585. He was possessed of excellent parts ; and at the age of twenty-two he had the address to obtain a dispensation to enjoy the bishopric of Lucon. He applied himself in a particular manner to the function of preaching; and his reputation procured him the office of almoner to the queen Mary de’ Medicis. His abilities in the management of affairs advanced him to be secretary of state in 1616; and the king soon gave him the preference to all his other secretaries. The death of the marquis d’Ancre having produced a revolution in state affairs, Richelieu retired to Avignon, where he employed himself in composing books of controversy and piety. The king having recalled him to court, he was made a cardinal in 1622 ; and, two years after, first minister of state, and grand-master of the navigation. In 1626, the Isle of Rhee was preserved by his care ; and in 1628 Rochelle was taken, the haven having been enclosed by the famous dyke which he ordered to be raised. He accompanied the king to the siege of Cazal, and contributed not a little to the raising of it in 1629. He also obliged the Huguenots to the peace at Alets, which proved the ruin of that party. He took Pamerol, and succoured Cazal, besieged by Spinola. In the mean time the</p></body></text></TEI>