<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>glide without impediment over land and sea. The operations of the Tract Society are one of the wonders of our times. Their little works are showered down upon every shore, if not quite as eloquent as the words of Ulysses, yet, like his, they fall thick as the winter snows, and no barrier has yet been found that can effectually repress the effect of these missiles. There is no tongue or speech in which their voices are not heard, nor does there seem any limit to their operations, except that which circumscribes all human endeavours, the “ alte terminus hærens,” the limitation of funds.</p><p>Another great instrument for diffusing civilization and Christianity, is the spread of the English tongue. It is to be regretted that many natives are more anxious to Iearn English than the missionaries are to teach them, from the fear, it appears, by some missionary accounts, that these natives, when instructed, would only employ their knowledge of English in the pursuit of gain. It might probably so happen in several instances at first ; but the demand for those who have a superficial acquaintance with English is not unlimited, the market would soon be supplied, and the premium lowered. Then the advantages of teaching English would remain when the disadvantages were removed. The Romans understood the art of governing rather better than the English, and met the desire of the provincials to be instructed in the Roman tongue. With them it might be matter of amusement, not of scorn or rejection, that even remote barbarians had some aspirations after Italian refinement or Grecian eloquence :—</p><p>De conducendo rhetore jam loquitur Thule.</p><p>Still remoter regions from Rome than the farthest Thule are now desirous of an acquaintance with English, and, if the English were wise, would be encouraged in this attainment, for with the spread of their language they would extend their glory and their commerce.</p><p>The true end of missionary societies, it must never be lost sight of, is to raise up native teachers and preachers. Until this point be gained, the foreign missionaries must address the natives “ with stammering lips, and another tongue ;” for though the words may be native, the idiom is sure to be foreign ; and the missionaries will certainly continue to think in English, even when they are pronouncing the words of another language. This plain and obvious truth does not seem to have hitherto been sufficiently considered. Yet to perceive the difficulty, we have only to imagine a number of French apostles endeavouring, in broken English, to recall a heathen multitude of Britons to a sense of Solemnitjq and trying to infuse into their minds, through so distorting a medium, some knowledge of the truths of the Gospel. The actual engagement of a certain number of native teachers may serve indeed as an excuse, but not as a complete justification, for this important and obvious principle not having been carried more fully into effect.</p><p>The employment of well-educated native preachers supposes, in some degree, the erection of higher schools and colleges, and therefore presents the difficulty of finding sufficient funds and suitable teachers. But the employment of native teachers is itself a source of economy, tending to diminish the number, and of course the expenditure, of European labourers, whilst it would increase the efficiency of those who are actually sent. And the knowledge to be taught must in the first place be elementary, and suitable teachers for the elements might readily be found. The Kirk of Scotland affords a good example of scholastic instruction ; the Church of England possesses a college on a large and liberal scale ; and the plan of Serampore was marked by great ingenuity and intelligence. What is desirable is, that these beginnings should be pursued and extended; and that other denominations should make equal</p><p>efforts for training up a body of native missionaries, pos- <hi rend="sup">τ </hi>sessed of the acquirements of Europe, and having greater opportunities than Europeans can possibly obtain, of familiar intercourse and ready sympathy amongst their own countrymen.</p><p>But if missionary societies do not raise up native teachers in abundance, without any one’s instruction or assistance native heretics will rise up of themselves. Light and darkness are intermingling together, and new and foreign opinions, from casual intercourse with Europeans, will combine with old prejudices, and produce a new set of errors. Thus Gnosticism arose from the first dawn of Christianity in the East ; and thus Manes united the Persian doctrine with the true principles and the purer tenets of Revelation. Thus the Sikhs in India have remodelled the opinions of the Hindus, in part, upon the more warlike creed of their Moslem conquerors, and have adopted the half of the Moslem religion, which consists of the Koran and the sword, rejecting the Koran, but worshipping the “ All-Steel.” The overflow of the English race from either side of the Atlantic would augment the confusion and destruction of the ancient systems, alike by their profligacy or their piety; even the outcasts, throwing contempt upon the idols, prepare the way for the reception of a new system of belief ; for in many instances the native savages only wait for an example of their idols being despised with impunity, to cast them aside, and admit the superiority of that Power which has instructed the white strangers in so many arts of which they themselves are ignorant. The enterprise and rivalry of Europeans naturally tend to embroil the most distant nations in their quarrels, and shake the thrones of the native princes, already crumbling from their antiquity. Every new invention shortens the period which will make the whole world European ; and, considering onlj' human means, steam alone has brought us a hundred years nearer to the conversion of the world.</p><p>The advantages of missions are obvious, both to those who send missionaries and to those who receive them. The contributors to missions have the double advantage both of saving and of giving. Every step of progress that the world has made firom the lowest scale of barbarism, is by saving ; by preferring the future to the present ; by making the acquisitions of the day <hi rend="italic">go</hi>  farther than the day itself; and by rendering the surplus of the gain of the former generation a bequest to the generation which is to succeed it. But this noble attainment often proceeds from an unworthy cause. The love of money often injures the individual as much as it benefits his species. In giving to missionary societies, the saving is not only profitable, but the motive is generous and ennobling. It solves the question of Who is our neighbour, in the manner pointed out by the Saviour, and brings into a nearness of affection those who are distant in place. It restores the dormant affinity of our common species, and embraces the whole family of man in a new and still more elevated brotherhood. Some objects chiefly warm the affections, and others enlighten the understanding ; but the cause of missions at once accomplishes both. The labourer who, from his hard earnings, spares a portion for the greater spiritual need of that distant brother whom he never saw, not only feels his heart warmed towards him whom he intends to benefit, but listens with an interest, unfelt before, to all the information he may receive concerning him. Curiosity becomes a loftier feeling, which exists after novelty is ended ; and the head and the heart are alike actively employed in devising means to ameliorate the most distant tribes of the family of man, and in affording the resources which are to carry these plans into execution. If missionary efforts were attended with no other advantages, the benefits they confer upon the contributors were well w<hi rend="sup">,</hi>orth all the sums that have been expended upon them. But they are “ twice blessed.” Every</p></body></text></TEI>