<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>the two rows must be accurately placed one upon the other, by folding the net over on itself ; then proceed as before. Sea-nets, such as those for herrings and mackerel, which are made in <hi rend="italic">rands</hi>  or breadths, are joined rand to rand lengthways, or along the <hi rend="italic">selvages.</hi>  The former are composed of three breadths, each thirty-two yards long by fifty loops deep, on a spool three inches in circumference. At the close of each year the lowest rand, which goes deepest into the sea, is removed, and a new one joined on at the top of the net ; so that the rand which was uppermost now becomes second, and that which was second is now the lowest. This latter is removed at the end of the next season, when the same rule is observed in replacing it, and so on every year ; thus the whole of the original net is renewed every three years. This operation is called by net-makers, giving the net a <hi rend="italic">new jacket.</hi>  Another mode of joining, and when performed carefully it is the neatest, is by uniting the two nets, or the two margins of one net, in the same way as the last row of the new piece is joined to the meshes of the old net in <hi rend="italic">mending.</hi>  The first-made side of the <hi rend="italic">inserted</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">joining work</hi>  must be twice as long as the rest, as also the last side of the suture ; for they, in fact, are equivalent to <hi rend="italic">two</hi>  sides of a mesh. The following description of specific nets will serve to furnish examples of the foregoing rules, and of the mode of <hi rend="italic">mounting</hi>  nets, which yet remains to be noticed.</p><p><hi rend="italic">The casting-net</hi>  (fig. 7) is netted round and round (see No. 7 in this article) ; the number of the loops for the <hi rend="italic">lever</hi>  vary, as well as their size, according as it is intended for <hi rend="italic">gudgeons,</hi>  &amp;c. or <hi rend="italic">minnows ;</hi>  in either case, it would be a great loss of labour if the whole net were made on one spool so small as it is necessary the lower part of this engine should be. Spools therefore of different circumferences are used, diminishing gradually from the largest for the top, to the smallest for the <hi rend="italic">tuck.</hi>  The following will form a good-sized net for <hi rend="italic">gudgeons</hi>  and larger fish. Fill the needle with double twine, net four rounds with a spool two inches and a half circumference, on a <hi rend="italic">lever</hi>  of thirty-six loops ; then use single twine, and in the fifth row set in twelve <hi rend="italic">false meshes ;</hi>  net two rounds dead netting, and then set i<hi rend="italic">n false meshes</hi>  in the same line with the others, having taken care to set in the <hi rend="italic">quarterings</hi>  of the fifth row so as to divide the circle into equal parts. Net two feet down on the first spool, then one foot down on each of seven other spools, each spool being an eighth of an inch less than the preceding one. Continue to set in <hi rend="italic">quarterings</hi>  in their proper places, and at the commencement of the <hi rend="italic">eighth foot</hi>  set m four additional <hi rend="italic">false meshes</hi>  equidistantly between the <hi rend="italic">original quarterings,</hi>  and continue putting in the <hi rend="italic">accrues </hi>until you have netted a foot and a half more, having taken to your <hi rend="italic">eighth spool</hi>  at the beginning of the <hi rend="italic">ninth foot; </hi>then net four rows <hi rend="italic">dead</hi>  netting in <hi rend="italic">double</hi>  twine ; take your <hi rend="italic">ninth spool,</hi>  and net two feet six inches of <hi rend="italic">dead</hi>  netting for the <hi rend="italic">tuck,</hi>  the last two rounds in <hi rend="italic">double</hi>  twine. Have a stout line with leaden bullets threaded on it, and sew this line, with running stitches, through each mesh, along the lowest row of the net, the interval between each <hi rend="italic">lead</hi>  being two inches. This weighted margin is then turned upwards and inwards, and made fast to the <hi rend="italic">double twine-work above the tuck,</hi>  at about every foot of the circumference, by means of ratlines three inches long. The <hi rend="italic">lead-line</hi>  should be about a foot less in length than the row of the <hi rend="italic">tuck</hi>  to which it is sewn. The leads are made fast to the line by being tied at each end to prevent slipping, and the holes should be bored as near the size of the line as possible. In fig. 7, the lines <hi rend="italic">a, a, a,</hi>  show the seams formed by the <hi rend="italic">accrues</hi>  running down tile net ; <hi rend="italic">d, d, d, d,</hi>  are the <hi rend="italic">ratlines</hi>  by which the tuck is suspended from the rows of <hi rend="italic">double</hi>  meshes, marked by dots ; <hi rend="italic">be, be,</hi>  indicate the <hi rend="italic">tuck</hi>  which forms a series of pockets, or rather one continuous pocket, inside the net, into which the fish fall. Fig. 7* shows a portion</p><lb/><p>of the <hi rend="italic">lead-line l, l,</hi>  sewn on to the last row of the <hi rend="italic">tuck ;</hi>  L is the bullet ; <hi rend="italic">s, s, s, s, s, s, s,</hi>  the course of the twine, simply run through the meshes and round the lead-line ; <hi rend="italic">t, t, </hi>the <hi rend="italic">tie</hi>  which holds the mesh on each side the bullet L first; v, v<hi rend="sup">,</hi>,<hi rend="italic">V,</hi>  the twine which sews the line to the meshes, passing over the bullet, being threaded through the loops which extend along the length of the bullet. The <hi rend="italic">trammel</hi>  consists of three separate layers of nettings, and derives its name from its conformation (<hi rend="italic">trois mailles,</hi>  French), because it ensnares by <hi rend="italic">threefold meshes.</hi>  The three parts consist Of two <hi rend="italic">out-wallings</hi>  and the <hi rend="italic">lint;</hi>  this latter is suspended loosely between the two former, it being made twice their length and twice their depth. The two <hi rend="italic">out-wallings</hi>  are to be of the same size.</p><p>The length and depth of this engine varies according to the service it is intended to perform, either in fishing or fowling ; the same may be said of the size of the meshes ; those of the <hi rend="italic">out-wallings,</hi>  however, are generally five times larger from knot to knot than those of the <hi rend="italic">lint.</hi>  All the parts should be netted <hi rend="italic">four square</hi>  (as <hi rend="italic">oblong</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">square </hi>netting is sometimes called, see No. 6 in this article), the <hi rend="italic">lint</hi>  in twine as fine as may be consistent with the required strength, and the <hi rend="italic">out-wallings</hi>  with much stouter material in proportion. These, when finished, are to be <hi rend="italic">mounted. </hi>Fix each of the four corners of one <hi rend="italic">out-walling</hi>  to four pegs driven into the ground, which should be cleared of rubbish, &amp;c. The <hi rend="italic">out-walling</hi>  is to be stretched tight. Pass all round the <hi rend="italic">lint,</hi>  through each mesh, a stout line of twine, as thick as that of which the <hi rend="italic">out-wallings are</hi>  made. This line, and likewise the <hi rend="italic">lint</hi>  at its four corners, is made fast to the four pegs ; the former is drawn tight from peg to peg, but the latter, being longer and wider, hangs loosely. The meshes of the <hi rend="italic">lint</hi>  should be as equally distributed along the line as is possible. Over the <hi rend="italic">lint</hi>  is applied the other <hi rend="italic">out-walling,</hi>  the four corners of which are to be fastened to the four pegs. If the engine is intended for fishing, a stout cord must be threaded with round flat corks two inches diameter, and half an inch thick, more or less. This cord is to be fixed along the <hi rend="italic">head</hi>  of the net by means of pieces of twine whipped two or three times round, and embracing the line of the <hi rend="italic">lint</hi>, the margins of each out<hi rend="italic">-</hi><hi rend="italic">walling,</hi>  and tile <hi rend="italic">cord</hi>  itself. The twine is tied into a firm knot at those points where the cord meets the angles of the <hi rend="italic">out-walling's</hi>  meshes. The floats are placed about six inches apart, and are pierced, so as to embrace the <hi rend="italic">heud-rope</hi>  firmly. This last is made fast down <hi rend="italic">each side of</hi>  the net, at the angles of the meshes of the <hi rend="italic">out-wallings ;</hi>  but it has here no floats ; it is extended along the bottom of the net, where it is called the <hi rend="italic">foot-rope,</hi>  and is weighted with small plates of lead rolled and beaten round it with a hammer, as a tag is fixed round a boot-lace, at about every three inches.</p><p>The cord that thus surrounds the net must be bent into a loop at each end of the top of the net, for to these is to be made fast a <hi rend="italic">draw-rope</hi>  when the net is <hi rend="italic">shot.</hi>  Some net-makers also tie the three layers of net together at each angle of the meshes of the <hi rend="italic">out-wallings</hi>  throughout the area of the net, to give additional strength, and to prevent the <hi rend="italic">lint</hi>  getting <hi rend="italic">huddled</hi>  together at the bottom when suspended in the water or drawn along the ground. This engine acts thus : The fish or fowl passes through the large mesh <hi rend="italic">of</hi>  the out-walling, strikes against the <hi rend="italic">lint,</hi>  which, hanging loosely, yields, and protrudes through the corresponding mesh of the other <hi rend="italic">out-walling,</hi>  and thus forms a <hi rend="italic">cœcum, </hi>into which the animal falls, and is entangled. The <hi rend="italic">hoop-net</hi>  consists of two parts ; the <hi rend="italic">body,</hi>  and the <hi rend="italic">valve, funnel, </hi>or <hi rend="italic">gullet,</hi>  which are united in the manner hereafter to be described. Begin with the <hi rend="italic">body</hi>  at its lower or pointed end (see fig. 8), and work up to its entrance, thus : Net thirty-seven loops round on a spool four inches circumference, one row. Take a spool two inches circumference and net twenty rows of <hi rend="italic">dead</hi>  netting. In the next row set in five</p></body></text></TEI>