<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>that account the more necessary that an instrument so powerful should not be abandoned to dangerous hands. A mischievous boy in a steam-vessel may, by the simple pressure of his foot, cause an explosion that shall destroy the ship’s whole company ; but the danger should induce us, instead of undervaluing or discarding this wonderful combination of machinery, to study means which make it difficult or impossible to effect the mischief. This is really the result which such risks of abuse have produced in all the powerful applications of mechanical science ; and it is the result which ought to be produced in those far more important cases where the materials of the art are seated in the mind, and the evils which may be derived from them extend over the moral world.</p><p>The second objection frequently taken to the art of rhetoric is, that it is useless. The objectors of this class are not by any means agreed as to the ground on which their allegation is to be defended ; but the only section of them whose argument is plausible enough to deserve refutation, are those who, while they admit that practice and the study of models are necessary for the production of eloquent compositions, deny the utility of attempts to investigate the principles of eloquence systematically and philosophically. In this shape the opinion is very far from being uncommon ; and, like all other common prejudices, it appears on analysis to contain a mixture of truth along with its errors. The discussion of it will bring us yet nearer to the point which, in all these general observations, it is our wish to reach.</p><p>In the first place, then, the objection, in whatever shape it is put, assumes the fact, of which also the objectors make much use in maintaining their argument, that the laws of eloquence are inherent in every intelligent mind, and are put in daily practice by those who are quite guiltless of rhetorical studies. Now this is the fact which lies at the root of all philosophical discussions on the subject, and of all rules which can be fairly deduced from the investigations. “ All men,” says Aristotle, “ in some sort practise both dialectics and rhetoric ; for all to a certain extent endeavour both to discover arguments and to maintain them, to accuse and to defend. Accordingly, of people in general, some, in the performance of these tasks, obey merely the impulses of their own minds, without having present to their thoughts any rule or general principle ; while others avail themselves of all the principles and precepts which they have been able to gather from experience and practice. Now, since the end which men thus speaking have in view, can be reached both in the one way and in the other, it is manifest that both classes must act upon the same principles, and that these, since they at the same time form legitimate subjects of speculation, and are capable of being put to practical uses, may be combined so as to form a system of rules which will be universally admitted to deserve the name of an art.” Those, if there are any such, who go so far as to maintain that the natural powers are sufficient for the production of eloquence without training of any sort, are contradicted by notorious and invariable facts. And those who maintain or conceive that practice and the study of models are in themselves sufficient aids, must be reminded that, so far as their Success exceeds that of the unlearned speaker, it is gained for them by this circumstance, that, whether they are conscious of it or not, they obey more closely than he does those principles which are common to them with him. If we suppose that the practised speaker who decries rhetoric is a perfect orator, he may be safely assured that no sound system of rhetoric which he may condescend to study, will expound to him a single principle which he has not already reduced to practice ; and even if we suppose him more moderately skilled in the art, he may be told with equal truth, that the system will not contradict any principle which he has used in practice, and found effectual for his end.</p><p>If, then, a student of eloquence, who declines to listen to a rhetorical exposition of the principles of his art, attempts to justify his refusal by maintaining, as an universal <hi rend="sub"/>proposition, that, in every art, a systematic acquaintance, with the principles is useless or injurious to one who wishes, to practise it, his assertion, contradicted by common sense and immemorial experience, deserves no serious answer. But if he maintains that this particular art forms an exception to the general rule, and that in regard to it his proposition is true, he will find that the arguments by which his position may be most plausibly supported are two. He may allege, either, first, that the experience of modern Europe has shown rhetorical studies to be useless for the end at which they profess to aim, or, secondly, that rhetoric has failed in furnishing such a systematic view of principles as can be considered either complete or useful. These arguments lead us to consider a difference, to which we have not yet adverted, between the ancient and the modern methods of studying eloquence.</p><p>We have already fully admitted, or rather we have laid it formally down as an element in the view which we take of the subject treated in these pages, that the philosophical principles, or (which in certain respects is the same thing) the preceptive rules, of rhetoric, are not by themselves sufficient even for that negative purpose which, as we have also said, all schemes of mental training have most prominently in view. A critical examination of models in oratory, and the other branches of literature, is an indispensable part of the task which the rhetorical student is bound to perform. Now, of these two divisions, or modes of studying eloquence, the former is emphatically the ancient, and the latter the modem method.</p><p>Aristotle’s treatise is strictly and wholly didactic : his criticisms are short, infrequent, and closely limited to the immediate purpose of explaining his argument; and although he strenuously recommends the study of the historical and other branches of literature as a means of collecting the materials of eloquence, we cannot with certainty gather from any part of his work a distinct advice to the prosecution of these studies, as furnishing models of composition. From the temper of the great philosopher’s mind, it may not be rash to suspect that, even if he had been unfettered in his method of dealing with his subject, he might perhaps have placed a higher value than most men will do on the systematic precepts of the art, and have too much neglected its critical portion ; but there are certain reasons which deprive us of the right to infer positively that this was really his view of the matter. His main purpose was the formation of a system of precepts for spoken eloquence, written composition being adverted to but occasionally, and by way of digression ; but, down to his time, the only high specimens of spoken oratory were the harangues of his Attic contemporaries ; and for him, the tutor of Alexander, and the pensioner of Philip, the orations of Demosthenes (if the best of these were composed before the treatise on rhetoric, which is a doubtful point) were no safe themes of criticism or commendation After Aristotle’s time, it is true, criticism became more prominent in the manuals of eloquence : the best works which remain to us of some of its most renowned teachers, such as Dionysius of Halicarnassus, are purely critical ; and in the writings of some others, which are principally preceptive, by far the most valuable portions are critical analyses of literary works, examples of this latter sort being the spirited and refined dissertations of Cicero, the judicious and liberal remarks of Quinctilian, and the severe but often very instructive criticisms of the boy-philosopher Hermogenes. But although criticism grew as the models of excellence accumulated, the tendency to theorize and systematize kept equal pace with its increase ; and in the latest and worst days of ancient rhetoric, criticism, which, if not</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>