<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>which would have suggested itself to one whose feelings or imagination were at the time highly active : the Interrogation, the Apostrophe, the Exclamation, and similar rhetorical figures, may be cited as instances. There is at least one practical inference deducible from the distinction ; namely, that the Trope proper may sometimes be safely used by rule, while the Figure proper will always be ridiculous unless prompted by genuine emotion. The former may have place in all the degrees of style, from the calmest to the most animated ; the latter is appropriate to eloquence of a highly passionate or imaginative cast, and is indeed much more rarely admissible in written prose composition than in poetry or in spoken oratory.</p><p>Perspicuity and Vivacity are qualities of style, which minister directly to the great purpose of eloquence, and which, indeed, language must possess before it can reach its rhetorical end by both of its two leading paths ; the former being essential for the conviction of the understanding, and the latter for the awakening of the fancy and the feelings. The same thing cannot be said, at least not without qualification, as to the third quality of style, namely, Beauty or Elegance, whose immediate purpose is the gratification of taste. Either in this place, or at a former stage of the inquiry, there might have been room for some curious speculations as to the functions which taste really exercises as an oratorical instrument of belief ; but the practical inferences, on which alone it is proper to enter, are very plain, and may be very briefly stated. If it is found that the gratification of the taste of those whom we address is likely to impede our progress towards impressing on their minds the truth which we wish to teach, we should at once abandon all attempts to furnish such gratification, and pursue our principal end by means of clearness and animation. But if it is found, as it most usually will be, that our purpose may be promoted by gratifying the sense of beauty in our hearers, either through the general elegance of our composition, or even through longer and more sustained addresses to the imagination, not issuing in the excitement of passion, but resting ultimately in the mere pleasure of contemplation,— we shall be bound to use, so far as we are able, this lawful means of persuasion ; taking care however to recollect, that, as soon as we have reason to believe the minds of the hearers in danger of being tempted towards such a lively attention to those incidental ornaments of our discourse as will exclude from their thoughts the main subject of it, we have thus evidence that it is time to discard the assistant, which, like a spoiled domestic servant, has begun to play the part of the master.</p><p>III.</p><p>The last division of the three, in which we undertook to treat the subject of this paper, embraces what may be called the Criticism of Rhetoric.</p><p>This branch, as it must present itself to the student, should engage him in an examination of the most celebrated efforts of eloquence which have been given to the world, either by speech or by writing, in ancient as well as in modern times ; the philosophical principles of the art being assumed throughout as the standard, and the analysis of the works being instituted for the purpose of discovering the extent and particulars of their obedience to those fundamental laws, or their departure from them. In reflecting, however, on the limits within which the plan of this work necessarily and properly restricts our contribution to it, we have more than once, convinced of the inadequacy of all that could be here performed, towards aiding the student in this interesting and valuable department of his training, felt strongly inclined to content ourselves with a brief though earnest exhortation to this branch of rhetorical stu -dies, as indispensable for all who would derive full advantage from a systematic acquaintance with the principles. But there is one consideration which imperatively forbids this. We would not willingly, it is true, be suspected <hi rend="italic">of </hi>hoping that we shall be able to convert to the orthodox doctrine any who remain incredulous after perusing the higher and more elaborate works on rhetoric ; but our outline may fall into the hands of some who either have not studied the subject at all, or have not derived their notions of it from the best sources. To such readers, indeed, our illustrations are particularly addressed ; and we shall have failed altogether in our purpose, if our mode of treating the subject should lead to a radical misapprehension of the relative importance belonging to the several branches into which the study of rhetoric divides itself; a result which would be not unlikely to happen, if one essential department were dismissed with a simple recommendation, however warm.</p><p>But the plan adopted in our systematic section, resembling that of a map, in which the chief cities of an empire are laid down in their relative bearings, is inapplicable to the present division, in which, as we assume the office of topographers, we must select one or two narrow districts as the scene of our labours. The province from which our very few specimens will be exclusively selected, is that of Political Oratory, which offers to the student of eloquence peculiar advantages, arising chiefly from the universally acknowledged excellence of the ancient masterpieces, from the high merit, as well as interest, of many works of the kind in our own country, and from the immense variety which the compositions display, both in matter and in form.</p><p>In many of the qualities essential to eloquent composition, the historical writings of the moderns, and some of their philosophical works, will, at least, suffer no dishonour by comparison with those of the ancients ; although on a close and comprehensive parallel they cannot, with respect to the mere manner of delivery, be fairly said to equal the philosophy and history of the heathen world. But, in Public Speaking, the Eloquence of the Ancients has left modern oratory at an immeasureable distance ; and in this field the Greeks are even farther superior to the Romans, than these are to the nations of Christian Europe.</p><p>The great age of the Grecian Orators embraces scarcely three generations, and the most celebrated names are to be found about the middle of the period, all within the petty district of Attica. The critics of the Alexandrian school, when they issued in a later time that sovereign decree, which declared certain authors and no others, in every department of literature, to be classical and worthy of study, admitted into their approved list ten Attic orators, of each of whom, excepting Hyperides, we possess some remains. Antiphon, Andocides, Lycurgus, and Dinarchus, must not here detain us ; and Lysias, Isocrates, and Isæus, can scarcely receive more attention, although their works are far from being undeserving of study as models of eloquence, and are singularly instructive as illustrating, in many varied cases of private litigation, points which bear upon the merits and character of the two great orators, and which present themselves less prominently in the political, and even the judicial harangues which have been bequeathed to us by these latter. Lysias, one of the simplest and purest of Attic writers, is especially commended by the ancient critics for his skill in the introductory and narrative parts of his orations ; and Dionysius of Halicarnassus considers Isæus as closely resembling him, with less real eloquence and less nature. Isocrates, who merely composed discourses to be delivered by others, and was the teacher of all the most celebrated orators who succeeded him, is one of the greatest masters of style whom Grecian literature possesses; while he unites this quality</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>