<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>in a lathe, and are also done by being passed through a cutting knife; but by whatever process they are brought to the required shape, regard should in all cases be had to the grain of the wood, which should in every instance be completely followed. The most usual way of contracting for these is, at so much per thousand, stating the place of delivery ; but if a steam-engine be used to make wooden keys, it can also work lathes for the treenails, which, in that case, will be no cost, except for labour, as, in cutting up planks for the wedges, plenty of waste pieces will be found to make the treenails A plan has grown into use on some rai lways, of dropping the treenails loose into the hole of the block, and then driving the spike in and splitting them; but this is not so good as driving them in tight. Oak spikes have formerly been much used, and have been known to last twenty years; we should not, however, recommend them, with the rate of speed that has now been attained.</p><p>The best form of chair is a subject requiring deep consideration, and on which engineers of eminence are by no means decided; we have, therefore, given several drawings of those which are most approved. The leading distinctions are, whether the rails have been keyed in by iron or by wood. The latter method, indeed, is almost indispensable when the rails have lower webs; for, as it would by no means do to have the chair following the shape of the rail, as in that case it must always be detached from the block whenever it is required to take the rail out of it, this consequence ensues, namely, that the opening in the chair must be as large as the lower web of the rail. A chair of this kind, with its wooden key, is shewn in fig. 12.</p><p>In every mode of keying it must always be remembered, that the intention is merely to keep the rail down in the chair, and not to attempt to confine it from longitudinal motion. The right way of making these wedges is an essential thing, and should be done by the company. The original mode was to purchase oak plank, thoroughly seasoned, and of the thickness required. If it be not seasoned in the most complete manner, it will not answer; but this process may be hastened by steaming it in a tank, with a pressure of about 12 lbs. on the square inch. When it is thoroughly seasoned it should be removed into a drying-house, having hot air flues under the floor, made of iron pipes, where all moisture must be extracted; and when thoroughly dry, it is cut into the proper scantling, and into thirteen-inch lengths, each of which when complete is cut into two for joint chairs, or three for intermediate chairs. They are first prepared by joiners to the right shape for going through the cutters; a joiner will prepare about 100 in a day. The cutters are composed of four blocks of iron, fixed one over the other, with openings between each of about one inch, sloping downwards. In the centre of the three lower blocks are steel cutters, the lower one being exactly the shape of the key, and the others above gradually larger. The key is put in at the top, and forced through by a lever about • seventeen feet in length, brought down by a chain and crab winch, with eighty teeth in the wheel and ten in the pinion. Three men will work this, and in ten hours will cut 500 pieces, thirteen inches long, to the required shape. The shavings come through the spaces between the iron blocks, and by the gradual cutting, each one taking off a part, the knots in the wood go through without breaking, and the key comes out perfectly smooth.</p><p>The next process is compressing them, which is done by</p><p>VOL. XIX.</p><p>forcing them through an iron block, ten inches thick, with twelve holes in it, 3-l6ths of an inch smaller than the key at the lower part, and tapering to the top to admit the key. They are forced through by the ram of an hydraulic press, worked by two pumps, one of an inch and-a-half in diameter, the other of one inch, the diameter of the ram being nine inches, and the safety valve loaded to about nine hundred tons. Four men work the large pump, and two the small. They will get through 900 per day. A little rough grease is first rubbed over them. They are then cut into two or three, or more, in the proper proportion, according to the relative number of joints to intermediate chairs, and packed up in bags, care being taken to keep them in a dry place.</p><p>This method of manufacture has been much improved by the erection of an engine on the London and Birmingham railway, by which circular saws, running from 900 to 1100 revolutions per minute, rip the plank into scantling, and afterwards cross-cut the thirteen-inch lengths. Two more cutters were adapted on the top of the other four, but gradually larger. These took in the thirteen-inch lengths without their going into the hands of the joiner ; and the key was forced through by a plunger working up and down, by a guide and parallel motion on the end of an iron beam. A similar plunger force them through the compressing box; and 1100 were completed in ten hours. A part of the power may also be applied to drill the stone blocks for the permanent way. The cost of the whole, with the necessary shops, amounted to aboutL.1500; but the keys may be made for L.8 per thousand, if a cheap pattern be adopted. The circular saws also cut up the waste wood into treenails, which were bored by a lathe adapted to that purpose, the whole being worked by steam. It is found to save the labour of fifteen men. When this sort ofchair is used, it will occasion a great saving of time and trouble, if all the chairs are either made by one contractor, or every one gaged before it is received ; for if there be the least difference in the size, it requires a different set of cutters, and a different compresssing block for each sort, besides giving a great deal of trouble to the men employed in laying the way. The same remark applies to the rails. The best way is to take plenty of time, by beginning early. Find a respectable man, and let him have the whole job, at a sum varying with the price of iron.</p><p>In iron keys there are many more ways of shaping them. The accompanying drawing (fig. 13.) shews a very good one, where the rail has a web on one side of the bottom only, and the other side of the chair is notched to receive an iron pin. The only objection ever urged against iron pins is, that they are apt to get loose. This might be obviated by splitting the end which enters first, and opening it when driven home. If this be done, the other end should have a head, so that a clawed crowbar could be applied in order to draw it out.</p><p>The annexed drawing (fig. 14.) shews another good form, invented by Mr. Robert Stephenson, where the rail is confined by two bolts having angular ends, which enter a small score in the rail, and are keyed home by iron keys with split ends ; the key hole in the chair, and that in the bolts, being so proportioned, that the effect of keying up is to press the end of the bolt against the rail. In these chairs there is a moveable piece of iron, the bottom of which is circular, and the top flat, laid in a properly-formed receptacle in the bottom of the chair; and on this the rails rest, so as to give perfect ease to any motion produced by flexure.</p></body></text></TEI>