<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0469.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0463-05" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SIERRA <hi rend="smallcaps">Leona,</hi></label>
 a large country on the west coaſt of Africa, which ſome extend from the Grain Coaſt</p><p>on the ſouth eaſt to Cape Verga or Vega on the north- west, i <hi rend="italic">. e.</hi> between 7⁰ and 10⁰ N. Lat. Others, however, confine the country between Cape Verga and Cape Tagrin. There runs through it a great river of the ſame name, of which the ſource is unknown, but the mouth is in longitude 12. 30. west, lat. 8. 5. north, and is nine miles wide. The climate and soil of this tract ot country appear to be, on both sides of the river, among the beſt in Africa, or at leaſt the moſt favourable to European conſtitutions. The heat is much the same as that of the West Indies ; but on the higher grounds there is a cool ſea breeze, and in the mountainous parts the air is very temperate. According to Lieutenant Matthew, “ Sierra Leona, if properly cleared and cultivated, would be equal in ſalubrity and ſuperior in produce to any of the iſlands in the Weft Indies ;” and others have affirmed, that “ the air is better for a man’s health than in many places of Europe.” ſheſe advantages of climate induced the Engliſh to eſtabliſh a factory at Sierra Leona ; but they chose not the moſt healthful situation. For the benefit of a ſpring of good water they fixed their residence in a low valley, which is often overspread with miſts and noiſome vapours, while the air is clear and ſerene on the ſummits of the hills, to which water from the well might be eaſily carried.</p><p>The animal productions of this country are lions, from which it has its name ; leopards, hyænas, muſk cats, and many kinds of weaſels ; the japanzee or chimpanzee, a species of ſimia, which has a ſtill more striking reſemblance to the human figure than. even the ouran outang ; porcupines, wild hogs, squirrels, and antelopes. Beſides theſe, which are natives of the country, oxen thrive in it, and even grow fat ; asses too are employed in labour, and do not ſuffer by the climate ; but sheep ſuffer much from the heat, change their wool into hair, grow lean and increaſe very lithe; while the hardy goat is here as prolific and large as in any other country. Of the birds which frequent the woods of Sierra Leona we can give no perfect account. A species of crane is mentioned as eaſily tamed ; common poultry multiply fast ; ducks thrive well, but geeſe and turkeys ſeem not to agree with the climate. Turtles of all kinds are very common, and ſometimes of a large ſize. Crocodiles or alligators of a non-deſcript species have been found ten or twelve feet in length, and lizards of six different species. Snakes, which are almoſt innumerable, haunt the houſes in the night in ſearch ”of poultry ; and one was obſerved which meaſured 18 feet, but was happily found not to be venomous. Fiſhes are in great variety both in the ſea and in the rivers. Beſides the whale, the ſhark, flinging ray, and porpoiſe, there are eels, horſe-mackarel, tarpoons, cavillos, mullets, ſnappers, yellow-tails, old-maids, ten- pounders, and ſome other fiſhes ; all of which, except the eels and ten-pounders, are eſteemed fine eating. Oyſters are found in great abundance, and another ſhell- fiſh, which the natives eat. Among the zoophites, none is more worthy of notice than the common ſponge, which covers all the ſandy beaches of the river, particularly on the Bullom ſhore, and would fetch a high price in Great Britain.</p><p>Of the numerous vegetable productions of Sierra Leona, our limits will permit us only to mention the following. Rice, which is the plant chiefly cultivated, as the natives ſubſiſt almoſt entirely upon it, grows both<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0470.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0464"/>
in the high and low grounds. It proſpers indeed beſt in swamps, though the grain is better in a drier soil. Next to rice the cassada conſtitutes the chief food oſ the inhabitants, and is cultivated with great care. The country likewiſe produces yams, various kinds of potatoes, eddoes, or the <hi rend="italic">arum eſculentum.</hi> Oil-palm, plantains, and bananas ; papaw, guava, oranges and limes; pompions, melons, and cucumbers ; pine-apples, pigeon- peas, which dressed like Engliſh peas are a good pulſe ; maize or Indian corn ; millet, cocoa-nut trees ; ockra ; the tallow-tree ; a great variety of tamarinds ; different kinds of fig-trees and plums ; a kind of fruit reſembling grapes, but more acid and acrid ; cherries reſembling a fine nectarine in taſte ; a ſpecies of the bread fruit-tree; the cream fruit, ſo called becauſe when wounded it yields a fine white juice reſembling ſugar or the beſt milk, of which the natives are very fond ; the mala- guetta pepper, or grains of paradiſe ; a new ſpecies of nutmeg, but whether ſo good as the common fort has not yet been aſcertained ; a new ſpecies of the Peruvian bark, which it is hoped will prove as uſeful as the other ; and cola, a fruit highly eſteemed by the natives for the same virtues with that bark; the ricinus, caſſia, dye- stuffs, and gums, of great value ; cotton, tobacco, and sugar-canes, which, it is thought, would thrive exceedingly well under proper cultivation.</p><p>Considering the ardour of the maritime nations of Europe for settling colonies in diſtant regions of the globe, it is ſomewhat ſurprising that a climate ſo temperate and a soil ſo productive as that of Sierra Leona did not long ago attract their notice. But it was left to be colonized for a better purpoſe than that which firſt drew the natives of Europe to the West Indies and the American continent. Being thinly inhabited, Sierra Leona appeared to ſome benevolent gentlemen in England a place where, without incommoding the natives, a ſufficient quantity of ground might be bought on which to settle a great number of free negroes, who in 1786 swarmed in London in idleneſs and want. About 400 of theſe wretches, together with 60 whites, mostly women of bad character and in ill health, were accordingly ſent out, at the charge of government, to Sierra Leona. Neceſſity, it was hoped, would make them induſtrious and orderly ; and Captain Thomſon of the navy, who conducted them, obtained, for their use, a grant of land to his majeſty from king Tom, the neighbouring chief, and afterwards from Naimbanna, the king of the country. The colony, however, ſoon went to ruin; but the land which they occupied being about 20 miles ſquare, his majeſty was enabled to grant by act of parliament to another colony founded on better principles and for a ſtill nobler purpoſe.</p><p>The moſt intelligent members of that ſociety, which has laboured ſo ſtrenuouſly to procure an abolition of the ſlave-trade, juſtly concluding that the natives of Guinea would reap very little benefit from the attainment of their object, unleſs they ſhould be taught the principles of religion and the arts of civil life, which alone can render them really free, conceived the plan of a colony at Sierra Leona to be ſettled for the truly generous purpoſe of civilizing the Aſricans by maintaining with them a friendly intercourſe, and a commerce in every thing but men. This plan could not be carried into effect but at a very great expence. Subſcriptions were therefore opened upon rational and equitable terms, and a sum deemed ſufficient was ſpeedily raiſed.</p><p>An act of parliament was paſſed in favour of the ſubscribers, by which they were incorporated by the denomination of the <hi rend="italic">Sierra Leona Company ;</hi> and in pursuance of that act they held their firſt meeting at London on the 19th of October 1791, when the following gentlemen wore choſen directors for that year</p><p>“Henry Thornton, Esq; M.P. chairman-Philip Charles Middleton, Bart.—Sir George Young, Knt. William Wilberforce, Eſq; M. P.-Rev. Thomas Clarkſon, A. M. -Joſeph Hardcaſtle, Esq; -John Kingston, Esq;-Samuel Parker, Eſq;-Granville Sharp, Eſq;-William Sandford, Esq;- Vickeris Taylor, Eſq;—George Wolf, Esq."</p><p>The directors having ſtated the natural advantages of Sierra Leona, and its present miserable condition, obſerved, that they had not merely to eſtabliſh a commercial factory, but that, to introduce civilization, cultivation, and a ſafe trade, the company must provide or the ſecurity of the perſons and property of the colonists. The directors therefore reſolved, that three or four veſſels ſhould sail at once, with ſuch a number of people as would be able to protect and aſſist each other; with goods both for trade and for the ſupply of the colony Accordingly ſeveral veſſels ſailed, having on board a council for the government of the colony and the management of the company’s affairs ; a number of artificers and other ſervants of the company ; ſome ſoldiers, and a very few Engliſh ſettlers. The directors were laudably cautious in the choice of coloniſts. They admitted into the ſociety no white man of bad character, or who was not a declared enemy to the ſlave-trade; and as the chief object of their enterpriſe was the civilization of the natives, it was with great propriety that they choſe more than three-fourths of their ſettlers from the <hi rend="italic">free</hi> negroes in Nova Scotia, who had borne arms for the Britiſh government during the American war. The Superintendant and council were particularly inſtructed to ſecure to all blacks and people of colour, at Sierra Leona, equal rights and equal treatment, in all reſpects, with whites. They were to be tried by jury, as well as others ; and the council was deſired to allot to the blacks employments ſuited to their preſent abilities, and to afford them every opportunity of cultivating their talents. All practicable means of maintaining ſubordination were directed to be uſed ; and the council was eſpecially instructed to promote religion and morals, by ſupporting public worſhip and the due obſervance of the Sabbath, and by the inſtruction of the people, and the education of children. But no perſon was to be prevented from performing or attending religious worſhip in whatever place, time, or manner, he might think fit, or from peaceably inculcating his own religious opinions. Orders were given in chooſing the scite of a town, to conſider health as the firſt object ; and the firſt town was directed to be called <hi rend="italic">Free-Town.</hi> Articles for building and cultivation were ſent out, beſides the cargoes for proſecuting the company’s commerce; and schools for reading, writing, and accounts, were ordered to be set up for the purpose of inſtructing the children of ſuch natives as ſhould be willing to put them under the company’s care.</p><p>The leading object of the company was to ſubſtitute, for that diſgraceful traffic which has too long ſubſiſted,<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0471.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0465"/>
a fair commerce with Africa, and all the bleſſings which might be expected to attend it. Conſiderable advantages appeared hereby likely to reſult to Great Britain, not only from our obtaining ſeveral commodities cheaper, but alſo from opening a market for Britiſh manufactures, to the increaſing demands of which it is difficult to aſſign a limit. From this connection, Africa was likely to derive the ſtill more important benefits of religion, morality, and civilization. To accompliſh theſe purpoſes, it was neceſſary for the company to poſſeſs a tract of land, as a repoſitory for their goods, and which the Africans might cultivate in peace, ſecure from the ravages of the ſlave-trade. It had been aſcertained, beyond a doubt, that the climate and soil of Africa were admirably ſuited to the growth of ſugar, ſpices, coffee, cotton, indigo, rice, and every other ſpecies of tropical produce. The company propoſed to inſtruct the natives to raise theſe articles, and to ſet them the example, by a ſpirited cultivation, on its own account. Directions were given to the company’s commercial agent to puſh forward a trade, in a mode preſcribed, in the preſent produce of Africa. Meaſures were taken for cultivating, on the company’s account, the moſt profitable tropical produce ; and in particular, a perſon of long experience in the West Indies was ordered to begin a ſugar plantation. A mineralogiſt and botaniſt were likewiſe engaged to go out and explore the country for new articles of commerce.</p><p>Every thing being thus ſettled upon the moſt equitable and benevolent principles, the ſhips sailed with the Britiſh coloniſts, to whom, in March 1792, were added 1131 blacks from Nova Scotia. The native chiefs being reconciled to the plan, and made to underſtand its beneficent tendency towards their people, the colony proceeded to build <hi rend="italic">Free-Town,</hi> on a dry and rather elevated ſpot on the ſouth ſide of the river. It occupied between 70 and 80 acres, its length being about one- third of a mile, and its breadth nearly the ſame ; and it contained near 400 houſes, each having one-twelfth of an acre annexed, on which a few vegetables were raised. There were nine ſtreets running from north-west to ſouth- eaſt, and three cross ſtreets, all 80 feet wide, except one of 160 feet, in the middle of which were all the public buildings. Theſe conſiſted of a governor’s houſe and offices ; a large ſtore-houſe ; a large hoſpital ; six or eight other houſes, offices, and shops, occupied by the company’s ſervants ; and a church capable oſ containing 800 people. The coloniſts at firſt ſuffered much from the rainy ſeaſon, againſt which it was not in their power to provide ſufficient protection ; but at the end of it they recovered in a great meaſure their health and ſpirits, and proceeded with alacrity to execute the various purpoſes of their ſettlement. To excite emulation in culture, the government gave premiums to those coloniſts who raiſed the greateſt quantities of rice, yams, eddoes, cabbages, Indian corn, and cotton, reſpectively. To limit the exceſſes of the ſlave-trade, and gain the favour of the neighbouring chiefs, the directors inſtructed the governor and council to redeem any native from the neighbourhood, who ſhould be unjuſtly sold either to or by a Britiſh ſubject. The ſervants of the company conducted themſelves with the utmoſt propriety, being ſober, moral, and exemplary ; and from the labours of the clergymen were derived ſervices highly important in every point of view. Before the end of two years</p><p>from the inſtitution of the colony, order and induſtry had begun to ſhow their effects in an increaſing proſperity. The woods had been cut down to the diſtance of about three Engliſh miles all round the town. By theſe means the climate had become healthier, and ſickneſs had diminiſhed. The fame of the colony had spread not only along the whole weſtern coaſt of Africa,but alſo to parts far diſtant from the coaſt ; embaſſies had been received of the moſt friendly nature from kings and princes ſeveral hundred miles diſtant ; and the native chiefs had begun to send their children to the colony, with full confidence, to be taught reading, writing, and accounts, and to be brought up in the Chriſtian religion. In a word, it was not without grounds that the directors looked forward to that joyful period when, by the influence of the company’s meaſures, the continent of Africa ſhould be reſcued from her preſent ſtate of darkneſs and miſery, and exhibit a delightful ſcene of light and knowledge, of civilization and order, of peaceful induſtry and domeſtic comfort. On their beneficent exertions they hoped with confidence for the bleſſing of Providence ; they were countenanced and ſupported by the Britiſh government ; and upon the breaking out of the preſent war, the French Convention authoriſed one of their agents to write to the directors, requeſting a full account of the deſign of the inſtitution, and the names of the ſhips employed in their ſervice, and aſſuring them of the good wiſhes of the French government to ſo noble an undertaking. How completely that government fulfilled its promiſe is very generally known. Having vindicated the rights of man in Europe by the violation of every principle of truth and juſtice, they determined by the ſame means to give light and liberty to the Africans ; and that they have fully carried their determination into effect will be ſeen by the following extract of a letter from Mr Afzelius, the company’s botaniſt, dated Sierra Leona, 15th November 1794. “The French have been here and have ruined us. They arrived on the 28th of September laſt, early in the morning, with a fleet conſiſting of one large ſhip, two frigates, two armed brigs, and one cutter, together with two large armed merchant ſhips, taken by them at the Isles de Loss, an Engliſh ſlave factory to the north of our colony, and which they have alſo deſtroyed and burnt. So well had they concealed their nation, that we took them at firſt for Engliſh. They had Engliſh- built veſſels, which were rigged in the Engliſh way. They ſhowed the Engliſh flag, and had their ſailors, at leaſt thoſe we ſaw on deck, dreſſed like Engliſh. In ſhort, we did not perceive our miſtake till we obſerved them pointing their guns. We had not ſtrength ſufficient to resist, and therefore our governor gave orders, that as ſoon as they ſhould begin to fire, the Britilh flag ſhould be ſtruck, and a flag of truce hoiſted. Accordingly this was done, but ſtill they continued firing, and did much damage, both within and without the town . They killed two people and wounded three or four. But, as we did not underſtand the meaning of this proceeding, we asked them for an explanation ; and they anſwered us, that we ſhould diſplay the flag of liberty, as a proof of our ſubmiſſion. We aſſured them that it ſhould already have been done, if we had had any, which terminated the hoſtilities from the ſhips. In the mean time, moſt of the inhabitants had fled from the the town, having taken with them as much of their<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0472.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0466"/>
property as they conveniently could in ſuch a hurry. I was with the governor, together with a number of others ; but as ſoon as I was certain they were enemies, I went towards my own houſe with a view to ſave as much as poſſible of my property and natural collections; but was received in ſuch manner, that I could not venture to proceed. My houſe was situated near the ſhore, and unfortunately just oppoſite the frigate which fired.</p><p>I ſaw the balls paſſing through the houſe, and heard them whizzing about my ears. I ſaw that I ſhould loſe all my property ; but life was dearer to me, and I haſtened to the woods.</p><p>“In the afternoon the enemy landed, finding the town almoſt deſtitute of people, but rich in provisions, clothing, and other ſtores. They began immediately to break open the houſes and to plunder. What they did not want, they deſtroyed, burnt, or threw into the river. They killed all the cattle and animals they found in the fields or ſtreets, yards, or elſewhere, not sparing even aſſes, dogs, and cats. Theſe proceedings they continued the whole ſucceeding week, till they had entirely ruined our beautiful and proſpering colony ; and when they found nothing more worth plundering, they ſet fire to the public buildings and all the houſes belonging to the Europeans ; and burnt, as they ſaid, by mistake nine or ten houſes of the coloniſts. In the mean time, they were not leſs active on the water. They ſent three of their veſſels to Bance iſland, an Engliſh ſlave factory higher up the river, which they plundered and burnt, together with ſome ſlave ſhips lying there. They took besides about 10 or 12 prizes, including the company’s veſſels. Moſt of theſe they unloaded and burnt. They took along with them alſo two of our armed veſſels, one of which was a large ſhip, laden with provisions, and which had been long expected ; but ſhe unfortunately arrived a few days too ſoon, and was taken with her whole cargo. We expected at leaſt to receive our private letters, but even this was refuſed, and they were thrown overboard. At laſt, after inflicting on us every hardship we could ſuffer, only ſparing our lives and the houſes of the coloniſts, they ſailed on the 13th of October laſt, at noon, proceeding downwards to the Gold Coaſt, and left us in the moſt dreadful situation, without provisions, medicines, clothes, houſes, or furniture, &amp; c. &amp; c. and I fear much, that moſt of us ſhould have periſhed, had not our friends in the neighbourhood, both natives and Europeans, who were so happy as to eſcape the enemy, been so kind as to send us what they could ſpare. In the mean time, moſt of us have either been, or ſtill are, very sick, and many have died for want of proper food and medicine. The worſt, however, is now past. At leaſt we are not in any want of proviſion, although of the coarſeſt kind, but are deſtitute of the moſt necessary articles and utenſils for the houſe, the table, and the kitchen.”</p><p>It was thus that the Convention executed their purpoſe of s <hi rend="italic">preading light and liberty through the world.</hi> The Sierra Leona colony was eſtabliſhed for no other end than to aboliſh the slave-trade, to enlighten the Africans, and to render them virtuous, rational, free, and happy ; and thoſe powerful patrons of the rights of man deſtroyed that colony with many circumſtances of the moſt wanton cruelty. Though Mr Afzelius is a Swede, and ought therefore to have been protected by the laws of neutrality, they burnt his houſe with the</p><p>reſt ; deprived him of his trunks, his clothes, and his bed ; deſtroyed the natural curiosities which he had collected at the hazard of his life ; and carried away the inſtruments by means of which only he could collect more. It is with pleaſure, however, that we learn from the proceedings oſ the general court held on the 25th of February 1795, that the directors do not yet deſpair of the colony ; and that they have adopted the moſt prudent meaſures to avert all ſuch calamities in future. That their benevolent labours may be finally crowned with ſucceſs is our earneſt prayer, in which we ſhall, doubtleſs, be joined by every good Chriſtian.</p></div></body></text></TEI>