<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title/>
    <author/>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <p/>
   </publicationStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>
   <div facs="gri_33125011196363_0519.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0513-02"
    xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <p><label>SISYMBRIUM, <hi rend="smallcaps">water-cresses,</hi></label> in botany : A genus of
     plants belonging to the claſs of <hi rend="italic">tetradynamia,</hi> and to the order of <hi
      rend="italic">ſiliquoſa ;</hi> and in the natural ſyſtem ranged under the 39th order, <hi
      rend="italic">Siliquoſa.</hi> The ſiliqua, or pod, opens with valves ſomewhat ſtraight. The
     calyx and corolla are expanded. There are 29 species, of which eight are natives of Britain ;
     the naſturtium, or common water-creſs ; ſylveſtre, water-rocket ; amphibium, water-radiſh ;
     terreſtre, annual water-radiſh ; monenſe ; ſophia, flixweed ; irio, broad-leaved hedge-
     muſtard.</p>
    <p>1 .The naſturtium grows on the brinks of rivulets and water ditches. The leaves have from 6
     to 8 pair of ſmooth ſucculent and ſeſſile pinnæ ; the flowers are ſmall and white, and grow in
     ſhort spikes or tufts. The leaves of water-creſſes have a moderately pungent taſte, emit a
     quick penetrating ſmell, like that of muſtard ſeed, but much weaker. Their pungent matter is
     taken up both by watery and ſpirituous menſtrua, and accompanies the aqueous juice, which
     iſſues copiouſly upon expreſſion.<note anchored="true" n="1" place="bottom" type="authorial"
       ><p>[mu] L <gap/> ie's Materia Medica. </p></note>It is very volatile, ſo as to ariſe in
     great part in diſtillation with rectified ſpirit, as well as with water, and almoſt totally to
     exhale in drying the leaves, or in- ſpiſſating by the gentleſt heat to the conſiſtence of an
     extract, either the expreſſed juice, or the watery or ſpirituous tinctures. Both the
     inſpiſſated juice, and the watery extract, diſcover to the taſte a ſaline impregnation, and in
     keeping throw up cryſtalline effloreſcences to the ſurface. On diſtilling conſiderable
     quantities of the herb with water, a ſmall proportion of a ſubtile volatile very pungent oil is
     obtained.</p>
    <p>Water-creſſes obtain a place in the Materia Medica for their antiſcorbutic qualities, which
     have been long very generally acknowledged by physicians.<note anchored="false" n="2" place="margin" type="authorial"><p><gap/> elville's Medical Botany, p. 135.
     </p></note>They are alſo ſuppoſed to purify the blood and humours, and to open viſceral
     obſtructions. They are nearly allied to ſcurvy-graſs, but are more mild and pleaſant, and for
     this reason are frequently eaten as ſalad. In the pharmacopoeias the juice of this plant is
     directed with that of ſcurvy-graſs and Seville oranges : and Dr Cullen has remarked, that the
     addition of acids renders the juices of the plantæ siliquoſae more certainly effectual, by
     determining them more powerfully to an aceſcent fermentation.</p>
    <p>2. Silveſtre, or water-rocket.<note anchored="true" n="3" place="bottom" type="authorial"
       ><p>[mu] Berkenbout's Synopsis of Natural History.</p></note> The ſtem is weak, branched, and
     above a foot high. The leaves are pinnated ; the pinnæ lance-ſhaped, and ſerrated ; the flowers
     ſmall, and yellow ; and grow frequently in ſhallow water.</p>
    <p>3. Amphibium, or water-radiſh. The ſtem is firm, erect, and two or three feet high ; the
     leaves are pinnatiſtd, and ſerrated ; the flowers are yellow, and in ſpikes ; the pods are
     ſomewhat oval, and ſhort. It grows in water.</p>
    <p>4. Terreſtre, or land-rocket. The leaves are pinnatiſid ; the pods are filled with ſeed ; the
     root is annual, and white ; the ſtem is angular, red-green, and ſmooth.</p>
    <p>5. Murale, or wall-rocket. The ſtems are rough, and about eight inches high ; the leaves grow
     on foot-ſtalks, lance-ſhaped, ſmooth, ſinuated, and ſerrated; the flowers are yellow ; the pods
     a little compreſſed, and slightly carinated. It grows on ſandy ground in the North, Angleſea, &amp;c.</p>
    <p>6. Monenſe, or yellow rocket. The ſtem is ſmooth, and about 6 or 8 inches high ; the leaves
     are pinnatifid; the pinnæ remote, generally 7 pair ; the flower is yellow ; the petals entire ;
     the calyx is cloſed. It grows in the Iſle of Man.</p>
    <p>7. Irio, broad leaved rocket, or hedge muſtard ; the ſtem is ſmooth, and about two feet high
     ; the leaves are broad, naked, pinnated, and halberd ſhaped at the end ; the flowers are
     yellow, and the pods erect. It grows on waſte ground.</p>
    <p>8. Sophia, flixweed. The ſtem is firm, branched, and two or three feet high ; the leaves are
     multifid ; the ſegments are narrow ; the flowers are yellow ; the petals much leſs than the
     calyx ; the pods are long, ſtiff, curved, without ſtyle, and erect ; the ſeeds are minute, and
     yellow. It grows on walls, waſte ground, &amp;c.</p>
   </div>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
