<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0457.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0451-04" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SIBERIA</label>,
a large country, comprehending the moſt northerly parts of the Russian empire in Asia. It is bounded on the eaſt by the eaſtem ocean ; on the ſouth by Great Tartary ; on the west by Ruſſia ; and on the north by the Frozen Ocean. It is about 2000 miles in length from eaſt to west, and 750 miles in breadth from north to south.</p><p>At what time this country was firſt inhabited, or by whom it was peopled, we are entirely ignorant ; but writings have been found in it when it was diſcovered, which ſhows that it muſt have been early known to a civilized people<note anchored="true" n="1" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>* Bell's Travels.</p></note> *. The Ruffians, from whom we have received our knowledge, knew nothing of it before the middle of the 16th century. In the reign of John Bafilowitz I. indeed, an incursion had been made into Siberia,<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0458.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0452"/>
and ſome Tartar tribes ſubdued: but these conqueſts were not permanent ; and we hear of no further communication between Ruſſia and Siberia till the time of John Baſilowitz II. It was opened again at that time by means of one Anika Strogonoſſ, a Russian merchant who had eſtabliſhed ſome ſalt-works at a town in the government of Archangel. This man carried on a trade with the inhabitants of the north-west parts of Siberia, who brought every year to the town above- mentioned large quantities of the fineſt furs. Thus he acquired a very conſiderable fortune in a ſhort time ; when at laſt the czar, perceiving the advantages which would accrue to his ſubjects from having a regular intercourſe with Siberia, determined to enlarge the communication which was already opened. With this view he ſent into Siberia a body of troops, which croſſed the Yugorian mountains, that form part of the north- eaſtern boundary of Europe. They ſeem, however, not to have paſſed the Irtiſh, or to have penetrated farther than the weſtern branch of the river Oby. Some Tartar tribes were laid under contribution, and a chief named <hi rend="italic">Tediger</hi> conſented to pay an annual tribute of 1000 fables. But this produced no laſting advantage to Ruſſia ; for, ſoon after, Yediger was defeated and taken priſoner by Kutchum Khan, a deſcendant of the great Jenghiz Khan : and thus the allegiance of this country to Ruſſia was diſſolved.</p><p>For ſome time we hear of no further attempts made by the Russians on Siberia; but in 1577 the foundation of a permanent conqueſt was laid by one Yermac Temofeeff, a Coſſack of the Don. This man was at firſt the head of a party of banditti who infeſted the Ruffians in the province of Caſan ; but being defeated by the troops of the czar, he retired with 6000 of his followers into the interior parts of that province. Continuing his courſe ſtill eaſtward, he came to Orel, the moſt eaſterly of all the Ruffian settlements. Here he took up his winter-quarters : but his reſtleſs genius did not ſuffer him to continue for any length of time in a ſtate of inactivity ; and from the intelligence he procured concerning the ſituation of the neighbouring Tartars of Siberia, he turned his arms towards that quarter.</p><p>Siberia was at that time partly divided among a number of ſeparate princes, and partly inhabited by the various tribes of independent Tartars. Of the former Kutchum Khan was the moſt powerful ſovereign. His dominions conſiſted of that tract of coun</p><p>try which now forms the ſouth-weſtern part of thc province of Tobolſk ; and ſtretched from the banks of the Irtiſh and Oby to thoſe of the Tobol and Tura. His principal reſidence was at Sibir, a ſmall fortreſs upon the river Irtiſh, not far from the preſent town of Tobolſk, and of which ſome ruins are ſtill to be ſeen. After a courſe of unremitted fatigue, and a ſeries of victories which almoſt exceed belief, but of which we have not room to give the detail, our intrepid adventurer diſpoſſeſſed this prince of his dominions, and ſeated himſelf on the throne of Sibir. The number of his followers, however, being greatly reduced, and perceiving he could not depend on the affection oſ his new ſubjects, he had recourſe to the czar of Muſcovy, and made a tender of his new acquiſitions to that monarch, upon condition of receiving immediate and effectual ſupport. This propoſal was received with the greateſt ſatisfaction by the czar ; who granted him a pardon for all former offences, and ſent him the required ſuccours. Yermac, however, being ſoon after drowned in an unſucceſsful excursion, the Russians began to lose their footing in the country. But freſh reinforcements being ſeaſonably ſent, they not only recovered their ground, but puſhed their conqueſts far and wide ; wherever they appeared, the Tartars were either reduced or exterminated. New towns were built, and colonies were planted on all ſides. Before a century had well elapſed, all that vaſt tract of country now called <hi rend="italic">Siberia,</hi> which ſtretches from the confines of Europe to the Eaſtern Ocean, and from the Frozen Sea to the preſent frontiers of China, was annexed to the Russian dominions.</p><p>The air of Siberia is, in general, extremely piercing, the cold there being more ſevere than in any other part of the Ruffian dominions. The Siberian rivers are frozen very early, and it is late in the ſpring before the ice is thawed<note anchored="true" n="2" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="smallcaps">(a)</hi> M. Gmelin, M. Muller, and two other philoſophers, ſet out in the year 1733 to explore the dreary regions of Siberia, by deſire of the empreſs Anne of Ruſſia. After ſpending nine years and a half in obſerving every thing that was remarkable, they returned to Peterſburgh, ; and an account of this journey was publiſhed by M. Gmelin. In order to examine how far the froſt had penetrated into the ground, M. Gmelin, on the 18th of June, at a place called Jacutia, ordered the earth to be dug in high ground ; they found mould to the depth of 11 inches, under which they met with looſe fand to two feet and a half further, after which it grew harder, and at half a foot deeper ſo hard as ſcarce to give way to the tools ; ſo that the ground ſtill remained unthawed at not leſs than the depth of four feet. He made the ſame experiment in a lower ſituation ; the ſoil was 10 inches deep, after that a looſe sand for two feet and ten inches, below which all was frozen and hard. At Jacutia the inhabitants preſerve in cellars ſeveral forts of berries, which they reckon among their dainties, perfectly good and freſh the whole year, though these cellars are ſcarce a fathom deep. At the fortreſs of Argun, in little more than 50 degrees of latitude, the inhabitants relate that, the earth in many places is never thawed above a yard and half, and that the internal cold of the earth will ſcarce permit a well to be dug, of which they bring an inſtance that happened not long before the author’s arrival at that place. They deſigned to ſink a well near a houſe at <pb n="453"> </pb> ſome diſtance from the river Argun, for which purpoſe they thawed the earth by degrees, and dug ſome fathoms till they had penetrated a fathom and half below the level of the river, but found no ſpring. Hence perhaps we may venture to affert, that beſides the great elevation of the earth in theſe countries, there is another cauſe, perhaps latent in the earth itſelf, of this extraordinary cold, naturally ſuggeſted to us by considering the cavity of an old ſilver mine at Argun, which being exhauſted of its ore, now ſerves the inhabitants in ſummer time for a cellar to keep their proviſions: this place is ſo extremely cold as to preſerve fleſh meats from putrefaction in the hotteſt ſummers, and to ſink the mercury in de Liſle’s thermometer to 146 and 147. The author travelling from Nerſchoi towards Argun, to viſit the works of the ſilver mines in that place, Auguſt 1735, <hi rend="superscript"> came</hi> to the river Orkija, near Soloniſchaia, on July the 1st, from whence he arrived a little before dark at the village of Seventua, diſtant from the river 27 leagues. In this journey he and his fellow travellers for more than four leagues felt it vaſtly cold ; ſoon after they came into a warm air, which continued ſome leagues ; after which the cold returned ; and thus are travellers ſubjected to perpetual viciſſitudes of warmth and cold. But it is obſerved, in general, that the eaſtern parts are colder than the weitem, though ſituated in the same latitude ; for as in thoſe eaſtern regions ſome tracts of land are much colder than the rest, their effects muſt be felt by the neighbouring parts. And this conjecture is favoured by the thermometrical obſervations made with M. de L’Iſle’s inſtrument in all parts of Siberia, in which the mercury was depreſted to the 226th degree, even in thoſe parts that lie very much towards the ſouth, as in the territory of Selinga, which ſaid degree anſwers in Fahrenheit’s thermometer to about.5 below 0, but the ſame thermometer ſometimes indicated, a much greater cold. At the fort of Kiringa, on Feb. 10. 1738, at 8 in the morning, the mercury ſtood at 240, which anſwers nearly to 72 below 0 in Fahrenheit’s. On the 23d off the ſame month it was a degree lower. At the ſame place, December 11. at three in the afternoon, it ſtood at 254 in De Liſle’s thermometer, and very near 90 in Fahrenheit’s ; on December 29. at four in the afternoon; at 263 ; on November 27. at noon, at 270 ; January 9. at 275, which ſeveral depreſſions anſwer in Fahrenheit’s to 99.44, 107.73, and 113.65; on January 5. at 5 in the morning, at 262, an hour after at 281, but at eight o’clock it returned to 250, and there remained till 6 in the afternoon, and then roſe by degrees till an hour before midnight, when it ſtood at 202. So that the greateſt depreſſion of the mercury anſwers in Fahrenheit’s thermometer to 120.76 degrees below 0, which is indeed very ſurpriſing, and what no body ever imagined before. While this cold laſted at Jenisea, the ſparrows and magpies fell to the ground, ſtruck dead, as it were, with the froſt, but revived if they were ſoon brought into a warm room. The author was told alſo that numbers of wild beaſts were found in the woods dead and ſtiff with the froſt, and ſeveral travellers had their blood and juices quite frozen in their veſſels. The air itſelf at that time was ſo dismal, that you would think it changed to ice, as it was a thick fog, which was not diſſipable by any exhalations, as in the ſpring and autumn, and the author could ſcarce ſtand three minutes in the porch of his houſe for the cold.</p></note> <hi rend="smallcaps">(a).</hi> If the corn does not ripen in Auguſt, there is little hope of a harveſt in this country ; and in the province of Jeniſeiſk it is ſometimes covered with ſnow before the peaſants can reap it. To defend the inhabitants againſt this extreme ſeverity of the climate, Providence ſeems more liberally to have dealt out to them wood for fuel and furs for clothing. As the winter’s day in the north parts of Siberia laſt but a few hours, and the ſtorms and flakes of ſnow darken the air ſo much, that the inhabitants, even at noon, cannot ſee to do any thing without artificial lights, they sleep away the greateſt part of that ſeaſon.<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0459.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0453"/>
Theſe ſevere winters are rapidly ſuceeeded by ſummers, in which the heat is ſo intenſe that the Tunguſians, who live in the province of Jakutſk, go almoſt naked. Here is ſcarcely any night during that ſeaſon ; and towards the Frozen Ocean the ſun appears continually above the horizon. The vegetables and fruits of the earth are here extremely quick in their growth.</p><p>The whole track of land beyond the 60th degree of north latitude is a barren waſte ; for the north part of Siberia yields neither corn nor fruits ; though barley is known frequently to come to perfection in Jakutſk.— For this reaſon, the inhabitants of the northern parts are obliged to live on fiſh and fleſh, but the Russians are ſupplied with corn from the ſouthern parts of Siberia, where the soil is ſurpriſingly fertile. The countries beyond the lake of Baikal, especially towards the eaſt, as far as the river Argun, are remarkably fruitful and pleaſant ; but ſuch is the indolence of the inhabitants, that ſeveral fine tracts of land, which would make ample returns to the peaſant for cultivating them, lie neglected. The paſtures are excellent in this country, which abounds in fine horned cattle, horses, goats, &amp; c. on which the Tartars chiefly depend for ſubſiſtence. How</p><p>ever, there are ſeveral ſteppes, or barren waſtes, and unimprovable tracts in theſe parts ; and not a single fruit tree is to be ſeen. There is great variety of vegetables, and in ſeveral places, particularly near Kraſnaia Sloboda, the ground is in a manner overrun with aſparagus of an extraordinary height and delicious flavour. The bulbs of the Turkiſh bundes, and other forts of lilies, are much uſed by the Tartars inſtead of bread. This want of fruit and corn is richly compenſated by the great quantities of wild and tame beaſts, and fowls, and the infinite variety of fine fiſh which the country affords<note anchored="true" n="3" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="smallcaps">(b)</hi> The oak, though frequent in Ruſſia, it is ſaid, is not to be found through this vaſt region nearer than, the banks of the Argun and Amur, in the dominions of China. The white poplar, the aspen, the black poplar, the common ſallow, and ſeveral ſpecies of the willow, are very common. The Norway and ſilver fir form great foreſts ; but the former does not grow beyond the 60th degree of north latitude, and the latter not beyond 5.8 degrees. To this dreary region of Siberia, Europe is indebted for that excellent ſpecies of oats called Av <hi rend="italic">ena Sibirica,</hi> and our gardens are enlivened with the gay and brilliant flowers brought from the same country.</p></note> <hi rend="smallcaps">(b.)</hi></p><p>In that part of Siberia which lies near the Ice Sea, as well as in ſeveral other places, are woods of pine, larch, and other trees ; beſides which, a conſiderable quantity of wood is thrown aſhore by the waves of the Ice Sea; but whence it comes is not yet aſcertained.</p><p>Beſides the wild fowl with which Siberia abounds, there is a prodigious number of quadrupeds, ſome of which are eatable, and others valuable for their ſkins or furs.</p><p>The animals moſt valued for their ſkins are the black<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0460.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0454"/>
<hi rend="italic">fox,</hi> the fable, the hyaena, the ermine, the ſquirrel, the beaver, and the lynx. The ſkin of a real black fox is more eſteemed than even that of a fable. In the country near the Frozen Ocean are alſo blue and white foxes. The fineſt fables come from Nertſhinſk and Jakutsk, the inhabitants of which places catch them in the mountains of Stannowoi Krebet. The tributary nations were formerly obliged to pay their taxes in the ſkins of foxes and fables only. But now the ſkins of ſquirrels, bears, rein-deer, &amp; c. and ſometimes money, are received by way of tribute ; and this not only from thoſe who live near the Lena, but alſo in the governments of Ilinſk, Irkutzk, Selenginſk, and Nertſhinſk. When the Tartars firſt became tributary to Ruſſia, they brought their furs indiſcriminately as they caught them, and among them were often fables of extraordinary value ; and formerly, if any trader brought with him an iron kettle, they gave him in exchange for it as many fables as it would hold. But they are now better acquainted with their value. They fell their fables to smugglers at a very high price, and pay only a ruble inſtead of a ſkin to the revenue officers, who now receive more ready money than fables, by way of tribute. The ſubjects plead the ſcarcity of furs, and indeed not without ſome appearance of truth.</p><p>Siberia has ſtill other and more valuable treaſures than thoſe we have yet mentioned. The ſilver mines of Argun are extremely rich ; the ſilver they produce yield ſome gold, and both of theſe are found among the copper ore of Koliwan. This country is alſo particularly rich in copper and iron ore. The former lies even upon the ſurface of the earth ; and conſiderable mines of it are found in the mountains of Pictow, Koliwan, Ploſkau, Woſkereſenſk, Kufwi, Alepaik, and ſeveral others, and in the government of Kraſnoiarſk<note anchored="true" n="4" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>(C) The copper mines of Koliwan, from which gold and silver are extracted, employ above 40,000 people. The silver mines of Nertshinsk, beyond lake Baikal, employ above 14,000. The whole revenue arising from these mines, according to Mr. Coxe, is not less than L. 679,182, 138.</p></note> (c). Iron is ſtill more plentiful in all theſe places, and very good ; but that of Kamenſki is reckoned the beſt. Several hundred thouſand puds of theſe metals are annually exported from the ſmelting houſes, which belong partly to the crown, and partly to private perſons. Most of them lie in the government of Catharinenburg. The Tartars alſo extract a great quantity of iron from the ore.</p><p>The topazes of Siberia have a fine luſtre, and in open ſandy places, near the river Argun, as well as on the banks of other rivers and lakes, are found single small pieces of agate. Here are alſo cornelians and green jaſper with red veins. The latter is chiefly met with in the deſerts of Gobiſkoi.</p><p>The famous marienglas, or lapis ſpecularis, great quantities of which are dug up in Siberia, is by ſome called Muſeovy or Russian glaſs ; and by others, though with leſs propriety, isinglaſs. It is a particular species of tranſparent ſtone, lying in strata like ſo marry ſheets of paper. The matrix, or ſtone in which it is found, is partly a light yellow quartz, or marcaſſia, and partly a brown indurated fluid ; and this ſtone contains in it all the ſpecies of the marienglas. To render the marienglas fit for uſe, it ia ſplit with a thin two-edged knife ; but care is taken that the lamina: be not too thin. It is uſed for windows and lanterns all over Siberia, and indeed in every part of the Ruſſian empire, and looks very beautiful ; its luſtre and clearneſs ſurpaſſing that of the fineſt glaſs, to which it is particularly preferable for windows and lanterns of ſhips, as it will stand the exploſion of cannon. It is found in the greateſt plenty near the river Witim.</p><p>Siberia affords magnets of an extraordinary size, and even whole mountains of loadſtone. Pit-coal is alſo dug up in the northern parts of this country. The kamennoe maſlo, a yellowiſh kind of alum, unctuous and ſmooth to the touch, like tophus, is found in the mountains of Kraſnoiarſk, Ural, Altaiſh, Jeniſea, Baikal, Bargusik, Lena, and ſeveral others in Siberia.</p><p>In this country are not only a great number of freſh water lakes, but likewiſe ſeveral whoſe waters are ſalt ; and theſe reciprocally change their nature, the ſalt ſometimes becoming freſh, and the freſh changing into ſaline. Some lakes also dry up, and others appear where none were ever ſeen before. The ſalt lake of Yamuſha, in the province of Tobolſk, is the moſt remarkable of all, for it Contains a ſalt as white as ſnow, conſiſting entirely of cubic cryſtals. One finds alſo in Siberia ſaline ſprings, ſalt water brooks, and a hill of ſalt.</p><p>Siberia affords many other things which deſerve notice. That uſeful root called rhubarb grows in vaſt quantities near the city of Seleginſk. The curious marouth’s bones and horns, as they are called, which are found along the banks of the Oby, Jeneſei, Lena, and Irtiſh, are unqueſtionably the teeth and bones of elephants. But whether theſe elephants teeth and bones were conveyed to theſe northern regions by the general deluge, or by any other inundation, and were by degrees covered with earth, is a point which might lead us into long and very fruitless diſquisitions ; we ſhall therefore only obſerve, that ſuch bones have likewiſe been found in Ruſſia, and even in ſeveral parts of Germany. A kind of bones of a ſtill larger size than theſe have alſo been dug up in Siberia, and ſeem to have belonged to an animal of the ox kind. The horn of the whale called <hi rend="italic">narwhal</hi> has been found in the earth near the rivers Indigirka and Anadir ; and the teeth of another species of whales, called Wolroſs, about Anadirſkoi. The latter are larger than the common fort, which are brought from Greenland, Archangel, and Kola.</p><p>The chain of Siberian mountains reaches from that of Werchoturie towards the ſouth as far as the neighbourhood of the city of Orienburg, in a continued ridge, under the name of the Uralian mountains ; but from thence it alters its direction weſtward. Theſe mountains are a kind of boundary between Ruſſia Proper and Siberia. Another chain of hills divides Siberia from the country of the Calmucks and Mongalians. —Theſe mountains, between the rivers Irtiſh and Oby, are called the Attaic or Golden Mountains, which name they afterwards loſe, particularly between the river Jeneſei and the Baikal lake, where they are called the Sayanian mountains.<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0461.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0455"/>
The inhabitants of Siberia conſiſt of the Aborigines or ancient inhabitants, the Tartars, and Russians,"</p><p>Some of theſe nations have no other religion but that of nature ; others are Pagans or Mahometans, and ſome of them have been converted to Chriſtianity, or rather only baptiſed by the Ruffian miſſionaries.</p></div></body></text></TEI>