<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0574.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0568-03" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SOCAGE</label>,
in its moſt general and extenſive ſignification, ſeems to denote a tenure by any certain and determinate ſervice.<note anchored="false" n="1" place="margin" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">Blackft. Comment.</hi> vol. ii.</p></note> And in this ſenſe it is by our ancient writer s conſtantly put in oppoſition to chivalry or knight-ſervice, where the render was precarious and uncertain. The ſervice muſt therefore be certain, in order to denominate it ſocage ; as to hold by fealty and 20 s. rent ; or, by homage, fealty, and 20 s. rent ; or, by homage and fealty without rent ; or, by fealty and certain corporal ſervice, as ploughing the lord’s land for three days ; or, by fealty only without any other ſervice : for all theſe are tenures in ſocage.</p><p>Socage is of two sorts : free-socage, where the ſervices are not only certain but honourable ; and <hi rend="italic">villein-</hi> ſoeage, where the ſervices, though certain, are of a baſer nature (ſee <hi rend="smallcaps">Villenage).</hi> Such as hold by the former tenure are called, in Glanvil and other ſubſequent authors, by the name of <hi rend="italic">liberi sοkemanni,</hi> or tenants in free- ſocage. The word is derived from the Saxon appellation soc <hi rend="italic">,</hi> which ſignifies liberty or privilege ; and, being joined to an uſual termination, is called <hi rend="italic">ſocage,</hi> in Latin socagium <hi rend="italic">;</hi> ſignifying thereby a free or privileged tenure.</p><p>It ſeems probable that the ſocage-tenures were the relics of Saxon liberty; retained by ſuch perſons as had neither,forfeited them to the king, nor been obliged to exchange their tenure for the more honourable, as it was called, but at the ſame time more burthenſome, te</p><p>nure of knight-ſervice. This is peculiarly remarkable in the tenure which prevails in Kent, called <hi rend="italic">gavelkind,</hi> which is generally acknowledged to be a ſpecies of focage-tenure ; the preſervation whereof inviolate from the innovations of the Norman conqueror is a fact univerſally known. And thoſe who thus preſerved their liberties were ſaid to hold in free and common ſocage.</p><p>As therefore the grand criterion and distinguiſhing mark of this ſpecies of tenure are the having its renders or ſervices aſcertained, it will include under it all other methods of holding free lands by certain and invariable rents and duties ; and in particular, <hi rend="italic">Petit</hi> <hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Serjeanty,</hi> <hi rend="italic">Tenure in</hi> <hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Burgage,</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Gavelkind.</hi> See theſe articles.</p></div></body></text></TEI>