<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0544.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0538-03" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SLOANE</label>
(Sir Hans), baronet, eminently diſtinguiſhed as a physician and a naturaliſt, was of Scotch extraction, his father Alexander Sloane being at the head of that colony oſ Scots which King James I. ſettled in the north of Ireland, where our author was born, at Killieagh, on the 16th of April 1660. At a very early period, he diſplayed a ſtrong inclination for natural hiſtory ; and this propenſity being encouraged by a ſuitable education, he employed thoſe hours which young people generally loſe by purſuing low and trifling amuſements, in the ſtudy of nature, and contemplating her works. When about ſixteen, he was attacked by a ſpitting of blood, which threatened to be attended with conſiderable danger, and which interrupted the regular courſe of his application for three years ; he had, however, already learned enough of phyſic to know that a malady of this kind was not to be removed ſuddenly, and he prudently abſtained from wine and other liquors that were likely to increaſe it.</p><p>By ſtrictly obſerving this ſevere regimen, which in ſome meaſure he continued ever after, he was enabled to prolong his life beyond the ordinary bounds ; being an example of the truth of his own favourite maxim, that ſobriety, temperance, and moderation, are the beſt and moſt powerful preſervatives that nature has granted to mankind.</p><p>As ſoon as he recovered from this infirmity, he re</p><p>ſolved to perfect himſelf in the different branches of phyſic, which was the profeſſion he had made choice of ; and with this view he repaired to London, where he hoped to receive that aſſiſtance which he could not find in his own country.</p><p>On his arrival in the metropolis, he entered himſelf as a pupil to the great Stafforth, an excellent chemiſt, bred under the illuſtrious Stahl ; and by his inſtructions he gained a perfect knowledge of the compoſition and preparation of the different kinds oſ medicines then in uſe. At the ſame time, he ſtudied botany at the celebrated garden at Chelſea, aſſiduouſly attended the public lectures of anatomy and phyſic, and in short neglected nothing that he thought likely to prove ſerviceable to him in his future practice. His principal merit, however, was his knowledge of natural hiſtory ; and it was this part of his character which introduced him early to the acquaintance of Mr Boyle and Mr Ray, two of the moſt eminent naturaliſts of that age. His intimacy with theſe diſtinguiſhed characters continued as long as they lived ; and as he was careful to communicate to them every object of curioſity that attracted his attention, the obſervations which he occaſionally made often excited their admiration and obtained their applauſe.</p><p>After ſtudying four years at London with unremitting ſeverity, Mr Sloane determined to viſit foreign countries for farther improvement. In this view he ſet out for France in the company of two other ſtudents, and having croſſed to Dieppe, proceeded to Paris. In the way thither they were elegantly entertained by the famous M. Lemery the elder ; and in return Mr Sloane presented that eminent chemiſt with a ſpecimen of four different kinds of phoſphorus, of which, upon the credit of other writers, M. Lemery had treated in his book of chemiſtry, though he had never ſeen any of them.</p><p>At Paris Mr Sloane lived as he had done in London. He attended the hoſpitals, heard the lectures of Tournefort, De Verney, and other eminent masters ; viſited all the literati, who received him with particular marks of eſteem, and employed himſelf wholly in ſtudy.</p><p>From Paris Mr Sloane went to Montpelier ; and, being furniſhed with letters of recommendation from M. Tournesort to M. Chirac, then chancellor of that university, he found eaſy acceſs, through his means, to all the learned men of the province, particulaιly to M. Magnol, whom he always accompanied in his botanical excurſions in the environs of that city, where he beheld with pleaſure and admiration the ſpontaneous productions of nature, and learned under his inſtructions to claſs them in a proper manner.</p><p>Having here found an ample field for contemplation, which was entirely ſuited to his taſte, he took leave of his two companions, whom a curioſity of a different kind led into Italy.</p><p>After ſpending a whole year in collecting plants, he travelled through Languedoc with the ſame design ; and paſſing through Thoulouſe and Bourdeaux, returned to Paris, where he made a ſhort ſtay. About the end of the year 1684 he ſet out for England, with an intention of settling there as a physician. On his arrival in London, he made it his firſt buſineſs to viſit his two illuſtrious friends Mr Ray and Mr Boyle, in order<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0545.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0539"/>
to communicate to them the diſcoveries he had made in his travels. The latter he found at home, but the former had retired to Essex ; to which place Mr Sloane tranſmitted a great variety of plants and ſeeds, which Mr Ray has deſcribed in his Hiſtory of Plants, and for which he makes a proper acknowledgment.</p><p>About the year 1706 our author became acquainted with the celebrated Sydenham ; who ſoon contracted ſo warm an affection for him that he took him into his houſe, and recommended him in the ſtrongeſt manner to his patients. He had not been long in London before he was propoſed by Dr Martin Lister as a candidate to be admitted a member of the Royal Society, on the 26th of November 1684 ; and being approved, he was elected on the 21st of January following.</p><p>In 1685 he communicated ſome curioſities to the Society ; and in July the ſame year he was a candidate for the office of their aſſiſtant ſecretary, but without ſucceſs, as he was obliged to give way to the ſuperior intereſt of his competitor Dr Halley. On the 12th of April 1687, he was choſen a fellow of the college of phyſicians in London ; and the ſame year his friend and fellow traveller Dr Tancred Robinſon, having mentioned to the Society the plant called the sta <hi rend="italic">r of the earth,</hi> as a remedy newly diſcovered for the bite of a mad dog, Dr Sloane acquainted them that this virtue of the plant was to be found in a book called <hi rend="italic">De Grey’s Farriery ;</hi> and that he knew a man who had cured with it twenty couple oſ dogs. This obſervation he made on the 13th of July, and on the 12th of September following he embarked at Portſmouth for Jamaica with the duke of Albemarle, who had been appointed governor of that iſland. The doctor attended his grace in quality of phyſician, and arrived at Jamaica on the 19th of December following.</p><p>Here a new field was opened for freſh diſcoverſes in natural productions ; but the world would have been deprived of the fruits of them, had not our author, by incredible application, converted, as we may say, his minutes into hours. The duke of Albemarle died ſoon after he landed, and the ducheſs determined to return to England whenever an anſwer ſhould be received to the letter ſhe had ſent to court on that melancholy occaſion. As Dr Sloane could not think oſ leaving her grace in her diſtreſs, whilſt the reſt of her retinue were preparing for their departure he improved it in making collections of natural curioſities ; ſo that though his whole ſtay at Jamaica was not above fifteen months, he brought together ſuch a prodigious number of plants, that on his return to England Mr Ray was aſtoniſhed that one man could procure in one iſland, and in ſo ſhort a ſpace, ſo vaſt a variety.</p><p>On his arrival in London he applied himſelf to the practice of his profeſſion ; and ſoon became ſo eminent, that he was choſen phyſician to Christ’s Hoſpital on the 17th of October 1694 : and this office he held till the year 1730, when, on account of his great age and infirmities, he found it necessary to reſign. It is ſomewhat ſingular, and redounds much to the Doctor’s honour, that though he received the emoluments of his office punctually, becauſe he would not lay down a precedent which might hurt his ſucceſſors, yet he conſtantly applied the money to the relief of thoſe who were the greateſt objects of compaſſion in the hoſpital, that it might never be ſaid he enriched himſelf by giving</p><p>health to the poor. He had been elected ſecretary to the Royal Society on the 30 th of November 1693 ; and upon this occaſion he revived the publication of the Philoſophſeal Tranſactions, which had been omitted for ſome time. He continued to be the editor of this work till the year 1712; and the volumes which appeared during that period are monuments of his induſtry and ingenuity, many of the pieces contained in them being written by himſelf.</p><p>In the mean time he publiſhed <hi rend="italic">Catalogus Plantarum quae in Inſula Jamaica ſponte proveniunt,</hi> &amp; c. <hi rend="italic">Seu Prodromi Historia Naturalis pars prima,</hi> which he dedicated to the Royal Society and College of Phyſicians. About the ſame time he formed the plan of a diſpenſary, where the poor might be furniſhed at prime coſt with ſuch medicines as their ſeveral maladies might require ; which he afterwards carried into execution, with the aſſiſtance of the preſident and other members of the college of phyſicians.</p><p>Our author’s thirſt for natural knowledge ſeems to have been born with him, ſo that his cabinet of curioſities may be ſaid to have commenced with his being. He was continually enriching and enlarging it ; and the fame which, in the courſe of a few years, it had acquired, brought every thing that was curious in art or nature to be firſt offered to him for purchaſe. Theſe acquiſitions, however, increaſed it but very ſlowly in compariſon of the augmentation it received in 1701 by the death of William Courten, Eſq; a gentleman who had employed all his time, and the greater part of his fortune, in collecting rarities, and who bequeathed the whole to Dr Sloane, on condition of his paying certain debts and legacies with which he had charged it. Theſe terms our author accepted, and he executed the will of the donor with the moſt ſcrupulous exactneſs ; on which account ſome people have ſaid, that he purchaſed Mr Courten’s curioſities at a dear rate.</p><p>In 1707 the firſt volume of Dr Sloane’s Natural Hiſtory of Jamaica appeared in folio, though the publication of the ſecond was delayed till 1725. By this very uſeful as well as magnificent work the materia medica was enriched with a great number of excellent drugs not before known. In 1708 the Doctor was elected a foreign member of the Royal Academy of Sciences at Paris, in the room of Mr Tſchirnaus ; an honour ſo much the greater, as we were then at war with France, and the queen’s expreſs conſent was neceſſary before he could accept it. In proportion as his credit roſe among the learned, his practice increaſed among the people of rank : Queen Anne herſelf frequently conſulted him, and in her laſt illneſs was blooded by him.</p><p>On the advancement of George I to the throne, that prince, on the 3d of April 1716, created the Doctor a baronet, an hereditary title of honour to which no Engliſh phyſician had before attained ; and at the ſame time made him phyſician general to the army, in which ſtation he continued till 1727, when he was appointed phyſician in ordinary to George II. He attended the royal family till his death ; and was particularly favoured by Queen Caroline, who placed the greateſt confidence in his preſcriptions. In the mean time he had been unanimonſly choſen one of the elects of the college of phyſicians June 1. 1716, and he was elected preſident of the ſame body on September 30. 1719, an office which he held for ſixteen years. Du-<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0546.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0540"/>
ring that period he not only gave the higheſt proofs of his zeal and aſſiduity in the diſcharge of his duty, but in 1721 made a preſent to that ſociety of L. 100 ; and ſo far remitted a very conſiderable debt, which the corporation owed him, as to accept it in ſuch ſmall sums as were leaſt inconvenient to the ſtate of their affairs. Sir Hans was no leſs liberal to other learned bodies. He had no sooner purchaſed the manor of Chelſea, than he gave the company of apothecaries the entire freehold of their botanical garden there, upon condition only that they ſhould preſent yearly to the Royal Society fifty new plants, till the number ſhould amount to 2000<note anchored="true" n="1" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="smallcaps">(a)</hi> This garden was firſt eſtabliſhed by the company in 1673 ; and having after that period been stocked by them with a great variety of plants, for the improvement of botany, Sir Hans, in order to encourage ſo ſerviceable an undertaking, granted to the company the inheritance of it, being part of his eſtate and manor of Chelſea, on condition that it ſhould be for ever preſerved as a physic garden. As a proof of its being ſo maintained, he obliged the company, in conſideration of the ſaid grant, to preſent yearly to the Royal Society, in one of their weekly meetings, fifty ſpecimens of plants that had grown in the garden the preceding year, and which were all to be specifically diſtinct from each other, until the number of two thouſand ſhould be completed. This number was completed in the year 1761. In 1733 the company erected a marble ſtatue of Sir Hans, executed by Ryſbrac, which is placed upon a pedeſtal in the centre of the garden, with a Latin inſcription, expreſſing his donation, and the deſign, and advantages of it.</p></note> (A). He gave beſides ſeveral other conſiderable donations for the improvement of this garden ; the ſituation of which, on the banks of the Thames, and in the neighbourhood of the capital, was ſuch as to render it uſeful in two reſpects : Firſt, by producing the moſt rare medicinal plants ; and, ſecondly, by ſerving as an excellent ſchool for young botaniſts ; an advantage which he himſelf had derived from it in the early part of his life.</p><p>The death of Sir Iſaac Newton, which happened in 1727, made way for the advancement of Sir Hans to the preſidency of the Royal Society. He had been vice-preſident, and frequently sat in the chair for that great man ; and by his long connection with this learned body he had contracted ſo ſtrong an affection for it, that he made them a preſent of an hundred guineas, cauſed a curious buſt of King Charles II. its founder, to be erected in the great hall where it met, and, as is ſaid, was very inſtrumental in procuring Sir Godfrey Copley’s benefaction of a medal of the value of five guineas, to be annually given as an honorary mark of diſtinction to the perſon who communicates the beſt experiments to the Society.</p><p>On his being raiſed to the chair, Sir Hans laid aſide all thoughts of further promotion, and applied himſelf wholly to the faithful diſcharge of the duties of the offices which he enjoyed. In this laudable occupation he employed his time from 1727 to 1740, when, at the age of fourſcore, he formed a reſolution of quitting the ſervice of the public, and of living for himſelf. With this view he reſigned the preſidency of the Royal Society much againſt the inclination of that reſpectable body, who choſe Martin Folkes, Eſq; to ſucceed him, and in a public assembly thanked him for the great and eminent ſervices he had rendered them. In the month of January 1741, he began to remove his library, and his cabinet of rarities, from his houſe in Bloomſbury to that at Chelſea ; and on the 12th of March following, having ſettled all his affairs, he retired thither himſelf, to enjoy in peaceful tranquillity the remains of a well-ſpent</p><p>life. He did not, however, bury himſelf in that ſolitude which excludes men from ſociety. He received at Chelſea, as he had done in London, the viſits of people of diſtinction, of all learned foreigners, and of the royal family, who fometimes did him the honour to wait on him ; but, what was ſtill more to his praiſe, he never refuſed admittance or advice to rich or poor who came to conſult him concerning their health. Not contented with this contracted method of doing good, he now, during his retreat, preſented to the public ſuch uſeful remedies as ſucceſs had warranted, during the courſe of a long continued practice. Among theſe is the efficacious redeipt for diſtempers in the eyes, and his remedy for the bite of a mad dog.</p><p>During the whole courſe of his life, Sir Hans had lived with ſo much temperance, as had preſerved him from feeling the infirmities of old age ; but in his 90th. year he began to complain of pains, and to be ſenſible of an univerſal decay. He was often heard to say, that the approach of death brought no terrors along with it ; that he had long expected the ſtroke ; and that he was prepared to receive it whenever the great Author of his being ſhould think fit. After a ſhort illneſs of three days, he died on the 11th of January 1752, and was interred on the 18th at Chelſea, in the ſame vault with his lady, the ſolemnity being attended with the greateſt concourſe of people, of all ranks and conditions, that had ever been ſeen before on the like occasion.</p><p>Sir Hans being extremely ſolicitous left his cabinet of curioſities, which he had taken ſo much pains to collect, ſhould be again diſſipated at his death, and being at the ſame time unwilling that ſo large a portion of his fortune ſhould be loſt to his children, he bequeathed it to the public, on condition that L. 20,000 ſhould be made good by parliament to his family. This ſum, though large in appearance, was ſcarcely more than the intrinſic value of the gold and ſilver medals, the ores and precious ſtones that were found in it ; for in his laſt will he declares, that the firſt coſt of the whole amounted at leaſt to L. 50,000. Beſides his library, conſiſting of more than 50,000 volumes, 347 of which were illuſtrated with cuts finely engraven and coloured from nature, there were 3560 manuſcripts, and an infinite number of rare and curious works of every kind. The parliament accepted the legacy, and fulfilled the conditions.</p></div></body></text></TEI>