<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0562.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0556-02" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SMOLLET</label>
(Dr Tobias), an author whoſe writings will transmit his name with honour to poſterity, was born in the year 1720 at a ſmall village within two miles of Cameron, on the banks of the river Leven. He appears to have received a claſſical education, and was bred to the practice of phyſic and ſurgery ; and in the early part of his life ſerved as a ſurgeon’s mate in the navy.</p><p>The incidents that beſel him during his continuance in this capacity ſerved as a foundation for Roderic Random, one of the moſt entertaining novels in the Engliſh tongue. He was preſent at the siege of Carthagena ; and in the before-mentioned novel he has given a faithful, though not very pleaſing, account of the management of that ill-conducted expedition, which he cenſures in the warmeſt terms, and from circumſtances which fell under his own particular obſervation.</p><p>His connection with the ſea ſeems not to have been of long continuance ; and it is probable that he wrote ſeveral pieces before he became known to the public by his capital productions. The firſt piece we know of with certainty is a Satire in two parts, printed firſt in the years 1746 and 1747, and reprinted in a Collection of his Plays and Poems in 1777. About this period, or ſome time before, he wrote for Mr Rich an opera intitled Alceſte, which has never been performed nor printed.</p><p>At the age of 18 he wrote a tragedy intitled The Regicide, founded on the ſtory of the aſſaſſination of James I. of Scotland. In the preface to this piece, publiſhed by ſubſcription in the year 1749, he bitterly exclaimed againſt falſe patrons, and the duplicity of theatrical managers. The warmth and impetuoſity of his temper hurried him, on this occaſion, into unjuſt reflections againſt the late George Lord Lyttleon and Mr Garrick ; the character of the former he characteriſed in the novel of Peregrine Pickle, and he added a burleſque of the Monody written by that nobleman on the death of his lady. Againſt Mr Garrick he made illiberal ill-founded criticiſms ; and in his novel of Roderic Random gave a very unfair representation of his treatment of him reſpecting this tragedy. Of this conduct he afterwards repented, and acknowledged his errors ; though in the ſubſequent editions of the novel the paſſages which were the haſty effuſions of disappointment are not omitted.</p><p>However, in giving a sketch of the liberal arts in his Hiſtory of England, he afterwards remarked, “ the exhibitions of the ſtage were improved to the moſt exquiſite entertainment by the talents and management of Garrick, who greatly ſurpaſſed all his predeceſſors of this and perhaps every other nation, in his genius for acting, in the ſweetneſs and variety of his tones, the irreſiſtible magic of his eye, the fire and vivacity of his action, the eloquence of attitude, and the whole pathos of expreſſion.</p><p>“ Candidates for literary fame appeared even in the higher ſphere of life, embelliſhed by the nervous ſenſe and extenſive erudition of a Corke; by the delicate taſte, the poliſhed muſe, and the tender feelings, of a Lyttleton.”</p><p>Not ſatisfied with this public declaration, he wrote an apology to Mr Garrick in ſtill ſtronger terms. With theſe simple conceſſions, Mr Garrick was completely ſatisfied ; ſo that in 1757, when Dr Smollet’s comedy of the Reprisals, an afterpiece of two acts, was performed at Drury Lane theatre, the latter acknowledged himſelf highly obliged for the friendly care of Mr Garrick exerted in preparing it for the ſtage ; and ſtill more for his acting the part of Luſignan in Zara for his benefit, on the ſixth inſtead of the ninth night, to which he was only intitled by the cuſtom of the theatre.</p><p>The Adventuresof Roderic Random, publiſhed in 1748,</p><p>2 vols 12mo, a book which ſtill continues to have a moſt<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0563.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0557"/>
extenſive ſale, firſt eſtabliſhed the Doctor’s reputation. All the firſt volume and the beginning of the ſecond appears to conſiſt of real incident and character, tho’ certainly a good deal heightened and diſguiſed. The Judge his grandfather, Crab and Potion the two apothecaries, and Squire Gawky, were characters well known in that part of the kingdom where the ſcene was laid. Captains Oakhum and Whiſſie, Doctors Mackſhane and Morgan, were alſo ſaid to be real perſonages ; but their names we have either never learned or have now forgotten. A bookbinder and barber long eagerly contended for being ſhadowed under the name of <hi rend="italic">Strap.</hi> The Doctor ſeems to have enjoyed a peculiar felicity in deſcribing ſea-characters, particularly the officers and ſailors of the navy. His Trunnion, Hatchway, and Pipes, are highly finiſhed originals ; but what exceeds them all, and perhaps equals any character that has yet been painted by the happieſt genius of ancient or modern times, is his Lieutenant Bowling. This is indeed nature itſelf ; original, <hi rend="italic">unique,</hi> and sui <hi rend="italic">generis.</hi></p><p>By the publication of this work the Doctor had acquired ſo great a reputation, that henceforth a certain degree of ſucceſs was inſured to every thing known or ſuspected to proceed from his hand. In the courſe of a few years, the Adventures of Peregrine Pickle appeared ; a work of great ingenuity and contrivance in the compoſition, and in which an uncommon degree of erudition is diſplayed, particularly in the deſcription of the entertainment given by the Republican Doctor, after the manner of the ancients. Under this personage the late Dr Akenſide, author oſ The Pleaſures of Imagination, is ſuppoſed to be typified ; and it would be difficult to determine whether profound learning or genuine humour predominate moſt in this epiſode. Another epiſode of The Adventures <hi rend="italic">of</hi> a Lady of Quality, likewiſe inſerted in this work, contributed greatly to its ſucceſs, and is indeed admirably executed; the materials, it is ſaid, the lady herſelf (the celebrated lady <hi rend="italic">Pane)</hi> furniſhed.</p><p>Theſe were not the only original compoſitions of this stamp with which the Doctor has favoured the public. Ferdinand Count Fathom, and Sir Launcelot Greaves, are ſtill in the list of what may be called <hi rend="italic">reading novels,</hi> and have gone through ſeveral editions ; but there is no injuſtice in placing them in a rank far below the former. No doubt invention, character, compoſition, and contrivance, are to be found in both ; but then ſituations are deſcribed which are hardly poſſible, and characters are painted which, iſ not altogether unexampled, are at leaſt incompatible with modern manners ; and which ought not to be, as the scenes are laid in modern times.</p><p>The laſt work which we believe the Doctor publiſhed was of much the ſame ſpecies, but caſt into a different form—The Expedition of Humphrey Clinker. It conſiſts of a ſeries of letters, written by different perſons to their reſpective correſpondents. He has here carefully avoided the faults which may be juſtly charged to his two former productions. Here are no extravagant characters nor unnatural ſituations. On the contrary, an admirable knowledge of life and manners is diſplayed ; and moſt uſeful leſſons are given applicable to intereſting but to very common ſituations.</p><p>We know not whether the remark has been made,</p><p>but there is certainly a very obvious ſimilitude between the characters of the three heroes of the Doctor’s chief productions. Roderic Random, Peregrine Pickle, and Matthew Bramble, are all brothers of the ſame family. The ſame ſatirical, cynical, diſpoſition, the ſame generoſity and benevolence, are the diſtinguiſhing and characteriſtical features of all three ; but they are far from being ſervile copies or imitations of each other. They differ as much as the Ajax, Diomed, and Achilles of Homer. This was undoubtedly a great effort of genius ; and the Doctor ſeems to have deſcribed his own character at the different ſtages and ſituations of his life.</p><p>Before he took a houſe at Chelſea, he attempted to ſettle as practitioner of phyſic at Bath ; and with that view wrote a treatiſe on the waters ; but was unſucceſsful, chiefly becauſe he could not render himſelf agreeable to the women, whoſe favour is certainly of great conſequence to all candidates for eminence, whether in medicine or divinity. This, however, was a little extraordinary ; for thoſe who remembered Dr Smollet at that time, cannot but acknowledge that he was as graceful and handſome a man as any of the age he lived in ; beſides, there was a certain dignity in his air and manner which could not but inſpire reſpect wherever he appeared. Perhaps he was too ſoon diſcouraged ; in all probability, had he perſevered, a man of his great learning, profound ſagacity, and intenſe application, beſides being endued with every other external as well as internal accompliſhment, muſt have at laſt ſucceeded, and, had he attained to common old age, been at the head of his profession.</p><p>Abandoning phyſic altogether as a profeſſion, he fixed his reſidence at Chelſea, and turned his thoughts entirely to writing. Yet, as an author, he was not near ſo ſucceſsful as his happy genius and acknowledged merit certainly deſerved. He never acquired a patron among the great, who by his favour or beneficence relieved him from the necessity of writing for a ſubſiſtence. The truth is, Dr Smollet poffeſſed a loftiness and elevation of ſentiment and character which appears to have diſqualiſied him for paying court to thoſe who were capable of conferring favours. It would be wrong to call this diſpoſition pride or haughtineſs ; for to his equals and inferiors he was ever polite, friendly, and generous. Bookſellers may therefore be ſaid to have been, his only patrons ; and from them he had constant employment in tranſlating, compiling, and reviewing. He translated Gil Bias and Don Quixote, both ſo happily, that all the former tranſlations of theſe excellent productions of genius have been almoſt ſuperſeded by his. His name likewiſe appears to a tranſlation of Voltaire’s Proſe Works : but little of it was done by his own hand ; he only reviſed it, and added a few notes. He was concerned in a great variety of compilations. His Hiſtory of England was the principal work of that kind. It had a moſt extenſive ſale ; and the Doctor is ſaid to have received L. 2000 for writing it and the continuation.</p><p>In 1755 he ſet on foot the Critical Review, and continued the principal manager of it till he went abroad for the firſt time in the year 1763. He was perhaps too acrimonious ſometimes in the conduct of that work; and at the ſame time diſplayed too much ſensibility<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0564.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0558"/>
when any of the unfortunate authors attempted to retaliate whoſe works he had perhaps juſtly cenſured.</p><p>Among other controverſies in which his engagements in this publication involved him, the moſt material in its conſequences was that occaſioned by his remarks on a pamphlet publiſhed by Admiral Knowles. That gentleman, in defence of his conduct on the expedition to Rochfort, publiſhed a vindication of himſelf ; which falling under the Doctor’s examination, produced ſome very ſevere ſtrictures both on the performance and on the character of the writer. The admiral immediately commenced a proſecution againſt the printer ; declaring at the ſame time that he deſired only to be informed who the writer was, that if he proved to be a gentleman he might obtain the ſatisſaction of one from him. In this affair the Doctor behaved both with prudence and with ſpirit. Deſirous of compromiſing the diſpute with the admiral in an amicable manner, he applied to his friend Mr Wilkes to interpoſe his good offices with his opponent. The admiral, however, was inflexible ; and juſt as ſentence was going to be pronounced againſt the printer, the Doctor came into court, avowed himſelf the author of the Strictures, and declared himſelf ready to give Mr Knowles any ſatisſaction he choſe. The admiral immediately commenced a freſh action againſt the Doctor, who was found guilty, fined L.100, and condemned to three months impriſonment in the King’s Bench. It is there he is ſaid to have written The Adventures of Sir Launcelot Greaves, in which he has deſcribed ſome remarkable characters, then his fellow-priſoners.</p><p>When Lord Bute was called to the chief adminiſtration of affairs, he was prevailed upon to write in defence of that nobleman’s meaſures ; which he did in a weekly paper called the <hi rend="italic">Briton.</hi> This gave riſe to the famous North Briton ; wherein, according to the opinion of the public, he was rather baffled. The truth is, the Doctor did not ſeem to poſſeſs the talents neceſſary for political altercation. He wanted temper and coolneſs ; and his friends accuſed his patron of having denied him the neceſſary information, and even neglected the fulfilling of ſome of his other engagements with him. Be that as it will, the Doctor is ſaid not to have forgotten him in his ſubſequent performances.</p><p>Beſides the Briton, Dr Smollet is ſuppoſed to have written other pieces in ſupport of the cauſe he eſpouſed. The Adventures of an Atom, in two volumes, are known to be his production.</p><p>His conſtitution being at laſt greatly impaired by a ſedentary life and aſſiduous application to ſtudy, he went abroad for his health in June 1763, and continued in France and Italy two years. He wrote an account of his travels in a series of letters to ſome friends, which were afterwards publiſhed in two volumes octavo, 1766. During all that time he appears to have laboured under a conſtant fit of chagrin. A very slight peruſal of theſe letters will ſufficiently evince that this obſervation is founded in fact, and is indeed a melancholy inſtance of the influence of bodily diſtemper over the beſt diſpoſition.</p><p>His relation of his travels is actually cynical ; for which Storne, in his Sentimental Journey, has animadverted on him under the character of Smelfungus. The Doctor lived to return to his native country: but his</p><p>health continuing to decline, and meeting with freſh mortifications and diſappnintments, he went back to Italy, where he died in October,21. 1771. He was employed, during the laſt years of his life, in abridging the Modern Univerſal Hiſtory, great part of which he had originally written himſelf, particularly the hiſtories of France, Italy, and Germany.</p><p>He certainly met with many mortifications and diſappointments ; which, in a letter to Mr Garrick, he thus feelingly expreſſes : “ I am old enough to have ſeen and obſerved, that we are all playthings of Fortune ; and that it depends upon ſomething as inſignificant and precarious as the toſſing up of a halfpenny, whether a man riſes to affluence and honours, or continues to his dying day ſtruggling with the difficulties and diſgraces of life.”</p><p>It would be needleſs to expatiate on the character of a man ſo well known as Dr Smollet, who has, beſides, given ſo many ſtrictures of his own character and manner of living in his writings, particularly in Humphrey Clinker ; where he appears under the appellation of <hi rend="italic">Mr Serle,</hi> and has an interview with Mr Bramble; and his manner of living is described in another letter, where young Melford is ſuppoſed to dine with him at his houſe in Chelſea. No doubt he made money by his connections with the bookſellers ; and had he been a rigid economiſt, or endued with the gift of retention (an expreſſion of his own), he might have lived and died very independent. However, to do juſtice to his memory, his difficulties, whatever they were, proceeded not from extravagance or want of economy. He was hoſpitable, but not oſtentatiouſly so ; and his table was plentiful, but not extravagant. No doubt he had his failings ; but ſtill it would be difficult to name a man who was ſo reſpectable for the qualities of his head, or more amicable for the virtues of his heart.</p><p>Since his death a monument has been erected to his memory near Leghorn, on which is inſcribed an epitaph written in Latin by his friend Dr Armſtrong, author of The Art of Preſerving Health, and many other excellent pieces. An inscription written in Latin was likewiſe inſcribed on a pillar erected to his memory on the banks of the Leven, by one of his relations.</p><p>To theſe memoirs we are extremely sorry to add, that so late as 1785 the widow of Dr Smollet was reſiding in indigent circumſtances at Leghorn. On this account the tragedy of Venice Preſerved was acted for her benefit at Edinburgh on the 5th of March, and an excellent prologue ſpoken on that occaſion.</p><p>The pieces inſerted in the poſthumous collection of Dr Smollet’s plays and poems are, The Regicide, a tragedy: The Repriſal, a comedy; Advice and Reproof, two ſatires ; The Tears of Scotland ; Verſes on a Young Lady; a Love Elegy, in imitation of Tibullus; two Songs ; a Burleſque Ode ; Odes to Mirth, to Sleep, to Leven Water, to Blue-ey’d Ann, and to Independence.</p></div></body></text></TEI>