<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0610.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0604-05" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SONATA</label>,
in muſic, a piece or compoſition, intend</p><p>ed to be performed by inſtruments only; in which ſenſe it ſtands oppoſed to <hi rend="italic">cantata,</hi> or a piece deſigned for the voice. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Cantata.</hi></p><p>The ſonata then, is properly a grand, free, humorous compoſition, diverſified with a great variety of motions and expreſſions, extraordinary and bold ſtrokes, figures, &amp; e. And all this purely according to the fancy of the compoſer ; who, without confining himſelf to any general rules of counterpoint, or to any fixed number or meaſure, gives a looſe to his genius, and runs from one mode, meaſure, &amp; c. to another, as he thinks fit. This ſpecies of compoſition had its rise about the middle of the 17th century ; thoſe who have moſt excelled in it were Baſſani and Corelli. We have ſonatas of i, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, and even 8 parts, but uſually they are performed by a ſingle violin, or with two violins, and a thorough baſs for the harpſichord ; and frequently a more figured baſs for the bais viol, &amp; c.</p><p>There are a thouſand different ſpecies of ſonatas ; but the Italians usually reduce them to two kinds. <hi rend="italic">Suοnate de chiesa,</hi> that is, ſonatas proper for church muſic, which uſually begin with a grave ſolemn motion, suitable to the dignity and ſanctity of the place and the ſervice, after which they ſtrike into a briſker, gayer, and richer manner. Theſe are what they more peculiarly call ſonatas. S <hi rend="italic">uοnate de camera,</hi> or ſonatas for the chamber, are properly ſerieſes of ſeveral little pieces, for dancing, only compoſed to the fame tune. They usually begin with a prelude or little ſonata, ſerving as an introduction to all the rest : afterwards come the allemand, pavane, courant, and other ſerious dances ; then jigs, gavotε, minuets, chacons, passecailles, and other gayer airs : the whole compoſed in the ſame tune or mode.</p></div></body></text></TEI>