<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0571.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0565-01" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SNUFF</label>,
a powder chiefly made of tobacco, the uſe of which is too well known to need any deſcription here.</p><p>Tobacco is uſually the baſis of ſnuff ; other matters being only added to give it a more agreeable ſcent, &amp; c. The kinds of ſnuff, and their ſeveral names, are infinite, and new ones are daily invented ; ſo that it would be difficult, not to ſay impoſſible, to give a detail of them. We ſhall only ſay, that there are three principal ſorts: the firſt granulated ; the ſecond an impalpable powder ; and the third the bran, or coarſe part remaining alter ſiſting the ſecond sort.</p><p>“ Every profeſſed, inveterate, and incurable ſnuſſ- taker (ſays Lord Stanhope), at a moderate computation, takes one pinch in ten minutes. Every pinch, with the agreeable ceremony of blowing and wiping the noſe and other incidental circumſtances, conſumes a minute and a half. One minute and a half out of every ten, allowing 16 hours to a snuff-taking day, amounts to two hours and 24 minutes out of every natural day, or one day out of every ten. One day out of every 10 amounts to 36 days and a half in a year. Hence if we ſuppoſe the practice to be persiſted in 40 years, two entire years of the ſnuff-taker’s life will be dedicated to tickling his noſe, and two more to blowing it. The expence of ſnuff, ſnuff-boxes, and handkerchiefs, will be the subject of a ſecond eſſay ; in which it will appear, that this luxury encroaches as much on the income of the ſnuff-taker as it does on his time ; and that by a proper application of the time and money thus lost to the public, a fund might be conſtituted for the diſcharge of the national debt.” See <hi rend="smallcaps">Nicotiana.</hi></p></div></body></text></TEI>