<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0623.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0617-02" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SOUTHERN</label>
(Thomas), an eminent dramatic writer, was born at Dublin in 1660, and received his education in the univerſity there. He came young to London to ſtudy law; but inſtead of that devoted himſelf to poetry and the writing of plays. His Perſian Prince, or Loyal Brother, was introduced in 1682, wſhen the Tory intereſt was triumphant in England ; and the character of the loyal brother being intended to compliment James duke of York, he rewarded the author when he came to the throne with a commiſſion in the army. On the Revolution taking place, he retired to his ſtudies, and wrote ſeveral plays, from which he is ſuppoſed to have derived a very handſome ſubſiſtence, being the firſt who raiſed the advantage of play-writing to a ſecond and third night. The moſt finiſhed of all his plays is Oroonoko, or the Royal Slave, which is built on a true ſtory related in one of Mrs Behn’s novels. Mr Southern died in 1746, in the 86th year of his age; the latter part of which he ſpent in a peaceful ſerenity, having, by his commiſſion as a ſoldier, and the profits of his dramatic works, acquired a handſome fortune ; and being an exact economiſt, he improved what fortune he gained to the beſt advantage. He enjoyed the longeſt life of all our poets ; and died the richeſt of them, a very few excepted. His plays are printed in two vols 12mo.</p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Southern</hi> <hi rend="italic">Continent.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">America,</hi> n⁰3—24. and <hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Terra</hi> <hi rend="italic">Australis.</hi></p></div></body></text></TEI>