<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Iiſhed, the Châtelet, being the Γecond court in that city, was retained for the purpoſe of trying thoſe per-fons who had become moſt obnoxious by their attach-ment to the royal cauſe. This court had the lpirit to acquit the Baron de Bezenval, Marſhal Broglio, and the Prince de Lambeſq. But having incurred much popular odium c∙n this account, they were guilty of the unworthy meanneſs of condemning to death the Marquis de Favres, for a pretended conſpiracy (of which no tolerable proof was ever brought) to maffacre La Fayette, Bailly, and Neckar, and to convey the King to Peronne.</p><p>During the whole of this winter the King had been very ſtrictly watched by numerous guards placed around his palace, infomuch that the other nations of Europe conſidered him as in a ſtate of captivity. To do away this impreffion, if poffible, and to make their king appear a voluntary agent in the meaſures that had lately been adopted, was now regarded as a matter of ſome importance. Every effort was therefore made to prevail with him to come to the Affembly ſuddenly, and, as it were, of his own voluntary motion, there to declare his adherence to the meafures which had lately been adopted. For ſome time he refilled this propo-ſal ; but at length, on the 4tl1 of February, he did ſuddenly appear in the National Affembly, where he complained of the attempts that had been made to ſhake the new conſtitution. He declared his wiſh " that it ſhould be univerſally known that the monarch and the reprefentatives of the nation were united, and their wiſhes were the fame ; that he would defend the conſtitutional liberty of the ſtate; that, in conjunction with the Queen, he would early form the ſentiments of his foil fυι that new order of things which the circumſtan-ces of the empire had introduced.” This declaration diſpirited the ariſtocratic party in no ſmall degree, and increaſed that unhappy tendency of looking for aid from foreign countries which they had always been too apt to indulge.</p><p>Ο11 the 13th of February, monaſtic eſtabhſhments were ſuppreffed, and their lands conſiſcated ; but the preſent friars and nuns were allowed penſtons for their ſubſtſtenee, and to continue the obſervance of their mo-naſtic vows, if they thought fit. we may obſerve here, that, in conſequence of the evacuation of the monaſte-ries, it is probable that about this time the <hi rend="italic">Breton</hi>  committee began to affume the appellation of the <hi rend="italic">(facobiη Club,</hi>  from the hall belonging to the Jacobin friars at Paris, in which their meetings were now held.</p><p>An event occurred at this time which tended in no ſmall degree to increafe the odium under which the old government already laboured. This was the publication of the <hi rend="italic">Red Book,</hi>  or-lift of penſions and donations granted by the crown. In conſequence of the moſt preffing inftances, it had been communicated by M. Neckar to a committee of the Affembly, after many intreaties, and the moſt ſolemn promiſes of ſecrecy. ft aſtorded, however, too ſtriking an advantage to thc popular party not to be made uſe of, and in a few days M. Neckar, to his no ſmall ſurpriſe, ſaw this regiſter publicly fold by every bookſeller in Paris. He ought not, indeed, to have been ſurpriſed ; and the giving up of this lift is one of the many proofs which the tranſactions of that period afford of his great unfitneſs for the office which he held, with much indignation, however, he demanded why the committee had publiſhed it without the permiſſion of the Affembly or the King ? But he was told by the committee, that " as to the Affembly, they were ſufe of its approbation ; and as to the King, they were not his reprefentatives.” To give an idea of ~ħ the effect of this publication, it is only neceſſiiry to re-P? mark, that, under the ſhort adminiſtration of M. Ca-lonne, thc two brothers of the King had received from the public treaſury, independent of their legitimate in-come, nearly two millions ſteiling, and that L. 600,000 had been granted to an individual, becauie he was the liuſhand of Madame de Polignac. M. Neckar’s oppoſition to this publication tended in no ſmall degree to injure his popularity, and the reft of the miniſtry began to lofe the confidence of the public. Indeed, at this time, fertile cauſes of alarm prevailed on all ſides. T&lt;he clergy were attempting to revive in the provinces the ancient animoſities between the Roman Catholics and the Protεftants, aſcribing the late decrees of the Affembly to the latter. The German Princes who poſ-ſtffed property in the north of France were complaining loudly of the violation oſ their rights by the aboli-tiυn of the feudal ſyſtem, although the National Affembly had voted to them a compenſation. The moſt melancholy intelligence was received from their colonies in the well Indies. In regulating theſe, the Affembly had not recognized the right of the free negroes to enjoy the fame privileges with other citizens ; at the fame time, they did not go the length of denying theſe privileges. This uncertain conduct produced infinite calamities. The whites contended with thoſe commonly called <hi rend="italic">people oſ colour.</hi>  Theſe again ſometimes Hood in oppoſition to the free negroes, or to the ſiaves ; and hence it ſometimes happened that no leſs than three ho-ſtile affemblies were held at the fame time in the fame colony, which made war upon each other with the moſt</p><p>inveterate fury. Each party found protectors in the National Affembly of the parent ſtate. Thoſe who favoured or oppoſed the exiſtence of diſtinctions at home, in general followed out the fame principle with regard to the colonies.</p><p>Οη the 14th of May, M. de Montmorency communicated to the National Affembly the preparations for war in which England and Spain were engaged. This brought forward the conſtitutional queſtion, “ who ought to poffeſs the power of declaring peace and war ? The Count Clermont Tonnerre, Meffrs<hi rend="sup">,</hi>&lt;de Serent,VÎ-rieu, and Dupont, ſupported the royal prerogative ; while on the other fide, the excluſive right of the legiſia-tive body to exerciſe this important prerogative was ſupported by Meſtrs d’Aiguillon, Garatjun. Freteau, Jellot, Charles Lameth, Sillery, Pction, Robeſpierre, &amp;c. M. Petion propoſed a decree “ that the French nation renounced for ever all idea of conqueſt, and confined itſelf entirely to defenſive war;” which was paffed with univerſal acclamation. The Count de Mirabeau at length ſucceſsfully propoſed that peace and war ſhould. be declared by the king and the legiſlative body in conjunction ; and the decree that was paffed on the ſubject is a ſtrange farrago of contradictions and abſurdities. It enjoined the King· to " guard the Rate from external attacks.” But how could this be done, without repelling any attack that might be made upon it ? This, however, he could not do, without previouſly informing the National Affembly j ⅛nd if th»t body chanced.</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>