<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>tſoua ln the eauſe of republicaniſm. No regard, how-<hi rend="sup">1</hi>  ever, has been paid to it by theconvention, which has declared itſelf permanent, nor indeed does it ſeem poſ-ſible to carry it into execution.</p><p>we have mentioned that Condé was inveſted from the beginning of April. It did not yield till thc loth of July, when the garriſon was ſo much reduced by famine and diſeafe, that out of 4000 men, of which it originally conſiſted, only 1500 were ſit for ſervice. The eyes of all Europe were in the mean time ſaxed upon the ſiege of Valenciennes. Colonel Moncrieff had contended, that batteries ought immediately to be placed under the walls without approaching it by regular pa-rallels ; but the Imperial engineer Mr Ferraris afferted, that the work of the great Vanban muſt be treated with more reſpect ; and his opinion was adopted by the council of war. The trenches were opened on the 14th of June. Few ſallies were attempted by the gar-riſon, on account of the ſmallneſs of their number. The inhabitants at ſirſt wiſhed to furrender ; but the violence of the bombardment prevented their affem-bling or giving much trouble on that head to General Ferrand the governor. Much of the labour of the ſiege conſiſted of mines and countermines. Some of theſe having been ſucceſsfully ſprung by the allies, tlie town was ſurrendered on the 27th of July by capitula-tion to the Duke of York, wlio took poſſeffion of it in behalf of the emperor of Germany. The ſiege of Mentz was at the ſame time going on. It ſuſſered much from famine. At laſſ, after an unſucceſsful at-tempt by the French army on the Rhine for its relief, Mentz ſurrendered on the 2 2d of July.</p><p>At the termination of the ſiege of Valenciennes it is ſaid that the allied powers were at a loſs how to pro-ceed next. The Auſtrian commanders are faid to have preſented two plans : The ſirſt was to penetrate to Pa-ris by the affiſtance of the rivers which fall into the Seine ; the other was to take advantage of the conſter-nation occaſioned·by the ſurrender of Valenciennes, and with 50,000 light troops to penetrate ſuddenly to Paris, while a debarkation ſhould be made ©n the coaſt of Brittany to affiſt thc royaliſts. The propoſal of the Britiſh miniſtry was, however, adopted, which was, to divide the grand army, and to attack weſt Flanders, beginning with the ſiege of Dunkirk. This determination proved ruinous to the allies. The French found means to vanquiſh in detail that army, which they <hi rend="sup">1</hi>  could not encounter when united.</p><p>It is ſaid that the Duke of York was in fecret cor-reſpondence with Omeron the governor of Dunkirk ; but he was removed before any advantage could be taken of his treachery. On the 24th of Auguſt the Duke of York attacked and drove the French outpoſts into the town, after an action in which the Auſtrian General Dalton was killed. A naval armament was expected from Great Britain to co-operate in the ſiege, but ſt did not arrive. In the mean time, a ſtrong re-publican force menaced the covering army of the allies, wliich was commanded by General Freytag. He was foon attacked and totally routed. The ſiege was raiſed. The Britiſh loſt their heavy cannon and baggage, with ſeveral thouſand men; and the convention, belie-ving that their General Houchard could have cut off the Duke of York’s retreat, tried and executed him for this neglect of duty,</p><p>Prince Cobourg and General Clairfait in the mean time unſucceſsſully attempted to beſiege Cambray and Boucliain. (Queſnoy was, however, taken by General Clairfait on the 1 ith of September ; and here finally terminated for the preſent campaign the ſucceſs of the allies in the Netherlands.</p><p>A conſiderable part of the French army of the north took a ſtrong poſition near Manbeuge, where they were blockaded by Prince Cobourg v but upon the 15th and 16th of October he was repeatedly at-tacked by the French troops under General Jourdan, who ſucceeded Houchard. 'I he French had now re-covered their vigour. They brought into the held a formidable train of artillery, in which were many 24 pounders. Commiffioners from the convention harangued the ſoldiers, threatened the fearful, and applauded the brave. Crowds of women, without conſuſion, went through the ranks, diſtributing ſpirituous li-quors in abundance, and carrying off the wounded, 'i'he attacks were repeated and terrible on both ſides ; but the Auſtrians had conſiderably the diſadvantage, and Prince Cobourg retired during the night. 3 he French now menaced maritime Flanders. They took Furnes and beſieged Nieuport. A detachment of Britiſh troops ready to fail to the weſt Indies were haſtily ſent to Oſtesd, and prevented for the preſent the farther progreſs of the French.</p><p>Such was the multiplicity of the events that now oc-curred in France, that it is difficult to ſtate the out-lines of them with any tolerable perſpicuity. we have already mentioned the extenſive diſſenſions that occurred throughout the republic in conſequence of the tri-umph of the Mountain party on the 3 iſt of May. The department of Calvades was ſirſt inarms againſt the convention under the command of General Felix wimp-fen ; but before the end of July the infurrection was quieted, after a few flight ſkirmiſhes. But the fœdera-liſm of the cities of Marfeilles, Lyons, and Toulon, ſtill remained. Lyons was attacked on the 8th oſ Auguſt by the conventional troops. Several actions followed, which were attended with great loſs both on the part of the affailants and of the beſieged. The city was re-duced almoſt to ruins ; but it held out during the whole month of September. The beſieging General Kellerman was removed from his command, on account of his ſuppoſed inactivity ; and the city ſurrendered on the 8th of October to General Doppet, a man who had lately been a phylieian. Such was the rage of party zeal at this time, that the walls and public buildings of Lyons were ordered to be deſtroyed, and its name changed to that of <hi rend="italic">Ville Affranchie.</hi>  Many hundreds of its citizens were dragged to the ſcaffold 011 account of their alleged treaſonable reſiftance to the convention. The victorious party, wearied by the flow operation of the <hi rend="italic">guillotine,</hi>  at laſt deſtroyed their priſoners in multitudes, by firing grape-ſhot upon them. Such indeed was the unrelenting character of the Mountain at this time, not only here but through the whole republic, that tliey tliemſelves pretended not to excuſe it, but declared that terror was with them <hi rend="italic">the order of the day.</hi></p><p>In the end of July General Cartaux was ſent againſt Marfeilles. In the beginning of Auguſt he gained ſome ſucceffes over the advanced fœderalift troops. On the 24th he took the town of Aix, and the Marſellois</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>