<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>together, gradually expanding themſelves, having thick foot-ſtalks ; and grow from one to two feet high, or more, in length and breadth, ſpreading all round : 'amidſt them rife the flower-ſtems, which are garniſhed at each joint by one leaf, and are of ſtrong and expeditious .growth, attaining their full height in June, when they flower ; and are ſucceeded by large triangular ſeeds, ripening in Auguſt. Some plants of each fort merit cub ture in gardens for variety ; they will effect a ſingula-rity with their luxuriant foliage, ſpikes, and flowers : and as medical plants, they demand culture both for private and public uſe.</p><p>They are generally propagated by ſeeds ſowed ſu au-tumn ſoon after they are ripe, or early in the ſpring, in any open bed of light deep earth ; remarking, thoſe intended for medical ufe ſhould generally be ſowed where they are to remain, that the roots, being not diſturbed by removal, may grow large. Scatter the ſeeds thinly, either by broad-caſt all over the· ſurface, and raked well in ; or in ſhallow drills a foot and half diſtance, covering them near an inch deep. The plants will rife in the fpring, but not flower till the ſecond or third year : when they, however, are come up two or three inches high, thin them to eight or ten inches, and clear out all weeds ; though thoſe deſſgned always to ſtand ſhould afterwards be hoed out to a foot and a half or two ſeet diſtance : obſerving, if any arc required ſor the pleaſure ground, &amp;c. for variety, they ſhould be transplanted where they are to remain in autumn, when their leaves decay, or early in ſpring, before they ſhoot: the others remaining where ſowed, muſt have the ground kept clean between them ; and in autumn, when the leaves and ſtalks decay, cut them down, and ſſightly dig the ground between the rows of plants^ repeating the ſame work every year.. The roots remaining, they increaſe in ſize annually : and in the fécond or third veal-many of them will ſhoot up ſtalks, flower, and perfect ſeeds ; and in three or four years tile roots will be arrived to a large ſize ; though older roots are generally preferable for medical uſe. .</p><p>In Mr Bell’s Travels we have an account of ſome curious particulars relating to the culture of rhubarb. He tells us, that the beſt rhubarb grows in that part of Eaſtern Tartary called <hi rend="italic">Mongalia,</hi>  which now ſerves as a boundary between Ruffia and China. The marmots contribute greatly to the culture of the rhubarb, wherever you ſee io or 20 plants growing, you are ſure of finding ſeveral burrows under the ſhades of their broad-ſp reading leaves. Perhaps they may fometimes eat the leaves and roots of this plant ; however, it is probable the manure they leave about the roots contributes not a little to its increaſe ; and their caſting up the earth, makes it ſhoot out young buds and multiply. This plant does not run, and ſpread itſelf, like clocks and others of the ſame ſpecies ; but grows in tufts, at uncertain diſtances, as if the feeds had been dropped with defign. It appears that thc Mon-gals never accounted it worth cultivating ; but that the world is obliged to tlie marmots for the quantities ſcattered, at random, in many parts of this coun-try : for whatever part of tile ripe ſeed happens to be blown among the thick graſs, can very ſeldom reach the ground, but muſt there wither and die ; whereas, Should it ſall among the looſe earth thrown up by the marmots, it immediately takes root, and produces a new plant.</p><p>After digging and gathering the rhubarb, the Mon-gals cut the large roots into ſmall pieces, in order to make them dry more readily. In the middle of every piece they ſcoop a hole, through which a cord is drawn, in order to ſufpend them in any convenient place. They hang them for the moſt part about their tents, and fometimes on the horns of their ſheep. This is a moſt pernicious cuſtom, as it deſtroys ſome of the beſt part or the root : ſor all about the hole is rotten and uſeleſs; whereas, were people rightly informed how to dig and dry this plant, there would not be one pound of refuſe in an hundred ; which would ſave a great deal of trouble and expence, that much diminiſh the profits on this commodity.. At preſent, the dealers in this article think theſe improvements not worthy of their attention, as their gains are more conſiderable on this than on any other branch of trade. Perhaps the government may hereafter think it proper to make ſome regulations with regard to this matter.</p><p>Two forts of rhubarb are met with in the ſhops. ſſ he ſirſt is imported from Turkey and Ruffia, in roundiſh pieces freed from the bark,-with a hole through the middle of each ; they are externally of a yellowiſh colour, and on cutting appear variegated with lively reddiſh ſtreaks. 1 he other, which is leſs eſteemed, comes immediately from the Eaſt Indies, in longiſh pieces, harder, heavier, and more compact than the foregoing. The firſt ſort, unleſs kept very dry, is apt to grow mouldy and worm-eaten ; the ſecond is lefs ſubject· to theſe inconveniences. Some of the more mduſtrious artiſts are ſaid to fill up the worm-holes with certain mixtures, and to colour the outfide of the damaged pieces with powder of the finer ſorts of rhubarb, and ſometimes wlth cheaper materials : this is often ſo nicely done, as effectually to impoſe upon the buyer, unleſs he very carefully examines each piece. The marks of good rhubarb are, that it be firm and ſolid, but not flinty ; that it be eaſtly pulverable, and appear, when powdered, of a fine bright yellow colour j that, upon being chewed, it impart to the fpittle a ſaffron tinge, without proving ſiimy or mucilaginous m the mouth. Its taſte is ſubacrid, bitteriih, and fomewhat aſtringent ; the ſmell lightly aromatic.</p><p>Rhubarb is a mild cathartic, which operates without violence or irritation, and may be given with ſafety even to pregnant women and children. - .Beſides its purgative quality, it is celebrated for an aſtringent one, by which it ſtrengthens the tone of the ſtomach and mteſtines, and proves ufeful in diarrhoeas and diſorders proceeding from a laxity of the ſibres. Rhubarb in ſubſtance operates more powerfully as a cathartic than any of the preparations of it. watery tinctures purge more than the ſpirituous ones; whilſt the latter contain in greater perfection the aromatic, aſtringent, and corro-borating virtues of the rhubarb. The doſe, when intended as a purgative, is from a ſcruple to a dram or more.</p><p>The Turkey rhubarb is, among ns,, univerſally preferred to the Eaſt India fort, though this laſt is for lome purpoſes at leaſt equal to the others lt ls mani-ſeſtly more aſtringent, but has fomewhat Ieſs of an aromatic flavour. Tinctures drawn from both with.· rectified ſpirit have nearly the fame taſte ; on diſtilling</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>