<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>to proceed with the utmoſt circumfpection : and after all, ſeldom it happens that ſpeculations of that kind afford any fatisfaction. Luckily, in the preſent caſe, our ſpeculations are ſupported by facts and ſolid argument. Firſt, a -ſmall object of one ſpecies oppoſed to a great object of another, produces not, in any degree, that deception which is ſo remarkable when both ob-jects are of the ſame ſpecies. The greateſt diſparity between objects of different kinds, is ſo common as to be obferved with perfect indifference ; but ſuch diſpa-rity between the objects of the fame kind being uncommon, never fails to produce ſurpriſe : and may we not fairly conclude, that ſurpriſe, in the latter caſe, is what occafions the deception, when we ſind no deception in the former ? In the npxt place, if ſurpriſe be the ſole cauſe of the deception, it follows neceffarily that the deception will vaniſh as ſoon as the objects compared become familiar. This holds ſo unerringly, as to leave no reaſonable doubt that ſurpriſe is the prime mover: our ſurpriſe is great, the ſirſt time a ſmall lapdog is ſeen with a large maſtiff ; but when two ſuch animals are conſtantly together, there is no furprife, and it makes no difference whether they be viewed feparately or in company. We ſet no bounds to the riches of- a man who has recently made his fortune ; the ſurpriſing diſproportion between his preſent and his paſt ſituation being carried to an extreme : but with regard to a family that for many generations hath enjoyed great wealth, the ſame falſe reckoning is not made. It is equally remarkable, that a trite ſimile has no effect : a lover compared to a moth ſcorching itfelf at the flame of a candle, originally a ſprightly ſimile, has by frequent ule loft all force ; love cannot now be compared to ſire, without ſome degree of diſguft. It has been juftly obſerved againft Homer, that the lion is too often introduced into his ſimiles ; all the variety he is able to throw into them not being ſufficient to keep alive the reader’s ſurpriſe.</p><p>To explain the influence of compariſon upon the mind, we have choſen the ſimpleft caſe, viz. the ſirſt ſight of two animals of the fame kind, differing in ſize only ; but to complete the theory, other circumſtances muſt be taken in. And the next ſuppoſition we make, is where both animals, feparately familiar to the ſpectator, are brought together for the ſirſt time. In that cafe, the effect of magnifying and dimiiiiſtſing is found remarkably greater than in that ſirſt mentioned ; and the reaſon will appear upon analyſing the operation.; the ſtrft feeling we have is of ſurpriſe at the uncommon difference of two creatures of the ſame ſpecies ; we are next ſenfible, that the one appears leſs, the other larger, than they did formerly ; and that new circumſtance increaſingour ſurpriſe, makes us imagine a ſtill greater oppoſition between the animals, than if we had formed no notion of them beforehand.</p><p>Let us make one other ſuppoſition, that the ſpectator was acquainted beforehand with one of the animals only ; the lapdog, for example. This new circumſtance will vary the effect ; for, inſtead of widening the natural difference, by enlarging in appearance the one animal, and diminifhing the other in proportion, the whole apparent alteration will reft upon the lapdog : the ſurpriſe to ſind it leſs than it appeared formerly, directs to it our whole attention, and makes us conceive it to be a moſt diminutive creature : the maſtiff</p><lb/><p>in the mean time is quite overlooked. To illuſtrate this effect by a familiar example. Take a piece of pa-per or of linen tolerably white, and compare it with a pure white of thc ſame kind : the judgment we formed of the ſirſt object is inſtantly varied ; and the ſurpriſe occafioned by finding it leſs white than was thought, produceth a haſty conviction that it is much leſs white than it is in reality : withdrawing now the pure white, and putting in its place a deep black, the furpriſe occaſioned by that new circumſtance carries us to the other extreme, and makes us conceive the object ſirſt mentioned to be a pure white : and thus experience compels us to acknowledge, that our emotions have an influence even upon our eye-light. 1 his experiment leads to a general obſervation, that whatever is found more ſtrange and beautiful than was expected, is judged to be more ſtrange and beautiful than it is in reality. Hence a common artifice, to depreciate beforehand what we wiih to make a figure in the opinion of others.</p><p>The companions employed by poets and orators are of the kind laſt mentioned; for it is always a known object that is to be magnified or lefleπed∙ The former is effected by likening it to ſome grand object, or by contrafting it with one of an oppoſite character. To effectuate the. latter, the method muſt be reverfed ⅛ the object muſt be contraſted with fomething ſuperior to it, or likened to ſomething inferior. The whole effect is produced upon the principal object ; which by that means is elevated above its rank, or depreffed below it.</p><p>In accounting for the effect that any unufual reſemblance or diffimilſtude hath upon the mind, no canſe has been mentioned but ſurpriſe ; and to prevent confuſion, it was proper to diſcuſs that caufe ſirſt. But ſurpriſe is not the only cauſe of the effect deſcribed ; another occurs, which operates perhaps not leſs powerfully, viz. a principle in human nature that lies ſtill in obſcurity, not having been unfolded by any writer, , though its effects are extenſive : and as it is not diſtinguiſhed by a proper name, the reader muſt be ſatisſied with the following deſcription. Every man who ſtu-dies himſelf or others, muſt be ſenſible of a tendency or propenſity in the mind to complete every work that is begun, and to carry things to their full perfection. There is little opportunity to diſplay that propenſity upon natural operations, which are ſeldom left imperfect ; but in the operations of art it hath great ſcope : it impels us to perſevere in our own work, and to wiſli for the completion of what another is doing : we feel a ſenſible pleaſure when the work is brought to perfection ; and our pain is not leſs fenſible when we are difappointed. Hence our uneaſineſs when an intereſting ſtory is broke off in the middle, when a piece of muſic ends without a cloſe, or when a building or garden is left unſiniihed. The ſame propenſity operates in making collections ; ſuch as the whole works, good and bad, oſ any author. A certain perſon attempted to collect prints of all the capital paintings, and fuc-ceeded except as to a few. La Bruyere remarks, that an anxious ſearch was made for theſe ; not for their value, but to complete the ſet.</p><p>The final cauſe of the propenſity is an additional proof of its exiſtence. Human works are of no ſigni-ſicancy till they be completed ; and reaſon is not always a ſufficient counterbalance to indolence : ſome prin-</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>