<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ed by the titles of <hi rend="italic">Captain oſ the queen's guards,</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">Lieutenant general oſ Cornwall.</hi>  From this period to the year 1594, he was continually engaged in projecting new expeditions, fending ſuccours to colonies abroad, defending the kingdom from the inſults of the Spani-ards, and tranſacting parliamentary buſineſs, with equal ability and refolution. whilſt thus employed, he was publicly charged, in a libel written by the infamous Jeſuit Parlous, with being an Atheiſt ; a groundleſs and ridiculous imputation. In 1594, he obtained from the queen a grant of the manor of Sherborne in Dor-ſetſhire, where he built a magnificent houſe : but Sir waiter fell under the queen’s diſpleaſure on account of an intrigue with the daughter of Sir Nicholas Throg-morton, one of the maids of honour ; however, he married the lady, and lived with her in great conjugal har-mony. During his diſgrace at court, he projected the conqueſt of Guiana in South America, and in 1595 failed ſor that country ; of which having taken poſſeſſion, after defeating the Spaniards who were ſettled there, he returned to England the ſame year, and ſoon after publiſhed an account <hi rend="sub">k</hi>of his expedition. In the following year he was one of the admirals in the ſucceſs-ful expedition againſt Cadiz, under the command of Howard and the earl of Eſſex ; and in 1597 he failed with the ſame commanders againſt the Azores. Soon after theſe expeditions, we find him aſſiduouſly engaged in parliamentary buſineſs, [and a diſtinguiſhed perſonage in jouſts and tournaments. In 1600 he was ſent on a joint embaſſy with Lord Cobham to Flanders, and at his return made governor of Jerſey.</p><p>Queen Eliſabeth died in the beginning of the year 1603 ; and with her Raleigh’s glory and felicity funk, never to riſe again. Upon the acceſſion of James, Sir walter loſt his intereſt at court, was ſtripped of his preferments, and accuſed of a plot againſt the king. He was arraigned at wincheſter, and, on his trial, inſulted by the moſt ſhockmg brutality by the famous Coke, attorney-general, whoſe ſophiſtical vociferation influen-ced the jury to convict him without the leaſt proof of guilt. After a month’s impriſonment, however, in daily expectation of his execution, he was reprieved, and ſent to the Tower ; and his eſtat es were given to Car, earl of Somerſet, the king’s favourite. During this confine-ment, he wrote many of his moſt valuable pieces, parti-cularly his Hiſtory of the world. In March 1615, after 16 years impriionment, he obtained his liberty, and immediately began to prepare·for another voyage to Guiana. In Auguſt 161 6, the king granted him a very ample commiflion for that purpoſe ; and in July the year following, he failed from Plymouth : but, ſtrange as it may appear, it is moſt certain that the whole ſcheme was revealed to the Spaniards by the king himſelf, and thus neceſſarily rendered abortive.</p><p>He returned to England in 1618, where he was foon after ſeized, imprifoned, and beheaded ; not for any pre-tended miſdemeanor on the late expedition, but in conſequence of his former attainder. The truth of the matter is, he was ſacrificed by the ptiſillanimous monarch to appeaſe the Spaniards ; who, whilſt Raleigh lived, thought every part of their dominions in danger. He was executed in old Palace Yard, and buried in St Margaret’s adjoining, in the ∙66th year of his age. His behaviour on the ſcaſſold was manly, unaffected, cheer-ful, and eaſy. Being aſked by the executioner which</p><p>be right, it is no matter which way the head lies.” He was a man of admirable parts, extenfive knowledge, un- ' daunted reſſoIution, and ſtrict honour and honeſty. He was the author oſ a great many works, ſome of which have not been printed.</p><p>RALLUS, the Rail, in ornithology ; a genus be-longing to the order of grallæ. The beak is thickeſt at the baſe, compreffed, equal, acute, and ſomewhat ſharp on the back near the point ; the noſtriis are oval ; thc feet have four toes, without any web ; and the body is compreffed. Mr Latham, in his <hi rend="italic">Index Ornithologicus, </hi>enumerates 24 ſpecies, befides ſome varieties. They are chiefly diſtinguiſhed by their colour. " Theſe birds (ſays Buffon) conſtitute a large family, and their ha-bits are different from thoſe of the other ſhore-birds, which reſide on ſands and gravel. The rails, on the contrary, inhabit only the ſlimy margins of pools and rivers, eſpecially low grounds covered with flags and other large marſh plants. This mode of living is habitual and common to all the ſpecies of water-rails. The land rail frequents meadows, and from the diſagreeable cry, or rather rattling in the throat of this bird, is de-rived the generic name. In all the rails, the body is ſlender, and ſhrunk at the ſides ; the tail extremely ſhort ; the head ſmall ; the bill pretty like that ©f the gallinaceous kind, though much longer, and not ſo thick ; a portion of the leg above the knee is bare ; the three fore-toes without membranes, and very long : they do not, like other birds, draw their feet under their bel-ly in flying, but allow them to hang down : their wings are ſmall and very concave, and their flight is ſhort.— They ſeem to be more diffuſed than varied ; and nature has produced or tranſported them over the moſt diſtant lands. Captain Cook found them at the Straits of Ma-gellan ; in different iſlands of the fouthern hcmiſphere, at Anamoka, at Tanna, and at the iſle of Norfolk. In the Society Iſlands there are two ſpecies of rails ; a little black ſpotted one, <hi rend="italic">(pooa-ηee},</hi>  and a little red-eyed one <hi rend="italic">(mai-ho}.</hi>  It appears that the two acolins of Fernandez, which he denominates <hi rend="italic">water-quails,</hi>  are of a ſpecies of rails peculiar to the great lake of Mexico.— The colins, which might be confounded with theſe, are a kind of partridges.” The principal are,</p><p>1. The aquaticus, or water-rail, is a bird of a long ſlender body, with ſhort concave wings. It delights leſs in flying than running : which it does very ſwiftly along the edges of brooks covered with buſhes : as it runs, it every now and then flirts up its tail, and in flying hangs down its legs ; actions it has in common with the water-hen. Its weight is four ounces and a half. The length to the end of the tail is 12 inches ; the breadth 16. The bill is ſlender, ſlightly incurvated, one inch three quarters long : the upper mandible black, edged with red ; the lower, orange-coloured : the head, hind part of the neck, the back, and coverts of the wings and tail, are black, edged with an olive brown ; the throat, breaſt, and upper part of the belly, are aſh-coloured : the ſides under the wings as far as the rump, finely varied with black and white bars. The tail is veι*y ſhort, conſiſts of 12 black feathers ; the ends of the two middle tipt with ruſt colour ; the fea-thers immediately beneath the tail white. The legs are placed far behind, and are of a duſky fleſh-colour. The toes very - long, and divided to their very origin ; though the feet are not webbed, it takes the water.; will f∞im ∩n it with mnrh f<hi rend="sup">,</hi>afp. but i.&lt;s r&gt;ftpn nbſerued</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>