<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>line of battle, to lead the convoys and ſquadrons of ſhips of war in action, and in general to fuit the different ex-igencies of the naval ſervice.</p><p>The fourth-rates may be employed on the fame occaſions as the third-rates, and may be alfo deſtined a-mongſt the foreign colonies, or on expeditions of great diſtance; ſince theſe veſſels are uſually excellent for keeping and ſuſtaining the ſea.</p><p>veſſels of the fifth rate are too weak to ſuffer the •ſhock of a line of battle ; but they may be deſtined to lead the convoys of merchant ſhips, to protect the commerce in the colonies, to cruize in different ſtations, to accompany ſquadrons, or be ſent expreſs with neceſſary intelligence and.orders. The ſame may be obſerved of the ſixth rates.</p><p>The frigates, which mount from 28 to 38 guns upon one deck, with the quarter-deck, are extremely proper for cruizing againſt privateers, or for ſhort expeditions, being "light, long, and uſually excellent ſailors.</p><p>RATEE.N, or Ratten, in commerce, a thick woollen ſtuff, quilled, woven on a loom with four treddles, like ſerges and other ſtuifs that have the whale or quilling. There are ſome rateens dreſſed and prepared like cloths.; others left ſimply in the hair, and others where the hair or knap is ſrized. Rateens aie chiefly manufactured in France, Holland, and Italy, and are moſtly uſed in linings. The frize is a fort of coarfe 1 ateen, and the drugget is a rateen half linen half woollen.</p><p>RATIFICATION, an act approving of and confirming ſomething done by another iu our name.</p><p>RÂTIO, in arithmetic and geometry, is that relation of homogeneous things which determines the , quantity of one from the quantity of another, without the intervention of a third.</p><p>Two numbers, lines, or quantities, A and B, being propoſed, their relation one to another may be conſidered under one of tbeſe two heads : 1. How much A ex-ceeds B, or B exceeds A ? And this is found by taking A from B, or B from A, and is called <hi rend="italic">arithmetic rea-f,,<hi rend="sub">n</hi>,</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">ratio.</hi>  2. Ογ how many times, and parts of a time, A contains B, or B contains A ? And this is called <hi rend="italic">geometric reaſon</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">ratio</hi>  ; (or, as Euclid defines it, it is the <hi rend="italic">mutual habitude,</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">reſpect,</hi>  of two magnitudes of the ſame kind, according to quantity ; that is, as to how often the one contains, or is contained in, the other) ; and is found by dividing A by B, or B by A. And here note, that that quantity which is referred to another quantity is called the <hi rend="italic">antecedent of tho ratio ; </hi>and that to which the other is referred is called the <hi rend="italic">con</hi><hi rend="italic">fie </hi><hi rend="italic">queηt of the ratio.i</hi>  as, in the ratio of A. to B, A is ’the antecedent, and B the ctnſequent. Therefore any quantity, as antecedent, divided by any quantity as a conſequent, gives the ratio of that antecedent to the conſequent.</p><p>'Γhus the ratio oſ A to B is ~, ſhut the ratio of B Jo</p><p>to A is —; and, in numbers, the ratio of 12 to 4 is A</p><p>—=3, or triple ; but the ratio of 4 to 12 is --- — -» or fubtriple.</p><p>And here note, that thc quantifies thus compared</p><lb/><p>muſt be of thc fame kind ; that is, ſuch as by nmltiρli-cation may be made to exceed one the other, or as theſc quantities are ſaid to have a ratio between them, which, being multiplied, may be made to exceed one another. Thus a line, how ſhoit foever, may be multiplied, that is, produced fo long as to exceed any given right line ; and conſequently theſe may be compared together, and the ratio expreſſed : but as a line can never, by any multiplication whatever, be made to have ſhreadth, that is, to be made equal to a fuperficies, how ſmall foever ; theſe can therefore never be compared together, and conſequently have no ratio or reſpect one to another, according to quantity ; that is, as to how often the one contains, or is contained in, the other. See Quantity, RATI0C1NAT10N, the act of reafoning. See Reason ing.</p><p>RA ΓΙΟΝ, or Ratian, in the army, a portion of ammunition, bread, drink, and forage, diſtributed to each ſoldier in the army, for his daily fubſiſtence, &amp;c. The horſe have rations of hay and oats when they cannot go out to forage. The rations of bread are regulated by weight. The ordinary ration of a foot ſoldier is a pound and a half of bread per day. The officers have ſeveral rations according to their quality and the number of attendants they are obliged to keep.— when the ration is augmented on occaſions of rejoicing, it is called a <hi rend="italic">double ration.</hi>  The ſhip’s crews have alfo their ratiofts or allowances of biſket, pulie, and water, proportioned according to their ſtock.</p><p>RATIONALE, a folution or account of the principles of fome opinion, action, hypbtheſis, phenomenon, or the like.</p><p>RATIBOR, a town of Germany, in Sileſia, and capital of a duchy of the ſame name, with a caſtle. It has been twice taken by the Swedes, and is ſeated on the river oder, in a country fertile in corn and fruits, 15 miles north-eaſt of Troppaw, and 142 eaſt of Prague. E. Long. 22. 24. N. Lat. 50. 14.</p><p>RATISB0N, an ancient, large, rich, handfome, and ſtrong city of Germany, in Bavaria, free and imperial, with a biſhop’s fee, whoſe biſhop is a prince of the empire, lt is called by the Germans Regenſhurg, from the river Regens, which runs under a line ſtone bridge, and throws itſelf into the Danube below the city ; and the rivers Luber and Nab mix with it above the city. The French call it Ratiſbon, in imitation of the Latins ; it hath formerly been ſubject to the kings of Bavai ia, who made it the place of their reſidence ; but it was declared free by the emperor Frederick 1. which does not however hinder the dukes of Bavaria from •dividing the toll with the citizens, according to an agreement between them. Th¢fe princes have alfo the criminal juriidiction, for which the magiſtrates of the city pay them homage, lt is the firſt city of the bench of Suabia, and contains at prefent within its walls five different free ſtates of the empire ; namely, the biſhop, the abbot of St Emmeran, the abbeſſes of the Low and High Munſter, and the city. The inhabitants of Ratifoon have the privilege not to be cited before other tribunals, unleſs for actions above 400 florins. The ſenate is compoſed of 17 members, and there is a council of 10, which is charged with the government of the ſtate. The citizens have a right to elect a chief, who judges of the affairs of police. The catholics have the exercife of their religion in the cathedral church, and others, and</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>