<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>other ; is leſs eaſily calcinable, and much leſs volatile. Its calx is grey, and more or leſs brown ; and whcn fu-ſed with vitrifiable matters, it changes into a beautiful blue glaſs called <hi rend="italic">fmah.</hi>  This calx, then, is one of thoſe which preſerve always a part of their inflammable prin-ciple. lſt is foluble in acids, as the regulus is. This regulus is foluble in vitriolic, marine, nitrous acids, and in aqua-regia, to all which it communicates colours. The ſolution in vitriolic acid is reddiſh ; the folution in marine acid is of a fine bluiſh-green when hot, and its colour is almoſt totally effaced when cold, but is eaſily recoverable by heating it, without being obliged to uncork the bottle containing it. This folution of the calx of regulus of cobalt is the baſis of the ſympa-thetic ink ; for without marine acid this ink cannot be made. All the ſolutions of regulus of cobalt may be precipitated by alkalis ; and theſe precipitates are blue, which colour they retain when vitriſied with the ſtrong-eſt fire.</p><p>Not only ſympathetic ink, but alſo regulus of cobalt, may be made from the ∙zaffre commonly fold ; which is nothing elſe than the calx of regulus of cobalt mixed with more or leſs pulveriſed flints. For this purpofe we muſt ſeparate as well as we can the powder of flints from it, by waſhing, as M. Beaumé docs, and then reduce it with black flux and ſea-falt. Regulus of cobalt ſeems incapable of uniting with ſulphur : but it eaſily unites with liver of ſulphur ; and the union it forms is ſo intimate, that M. Beaumé could not ſepa-rate theſe two fubſtances otherwiſe than by precipita-tion with an acid.</p><p>Many curious and intereſting remarks are ſtili to be diſcovered concerning this ſingular ſemimetal, and we may hope to receive further information from the en-deavours of chemiſts who have undertaken the exami-nation of it. M. Beaumé particularly has made conſiderable experiments on this ſubject, part of which he communicates to the public in his Courſe of Chemiſtry, and from whom we have borrowed the moſt of the above obſervations. See C⅛hemistry, n<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 1294, &amp;c.</p><p>REHEARSAL, in muſic and the drama, an effay βr experiment of ſome compoſition, generally made in private, previous to its repreſentation or performance in public, in order to render the actors and performers more perfect in their parts.</p><p>REICHENBERG, in Bohemia, 95 miles weſt of Prague, 205 north-weſt of vienaa, N. Lat. 50. 2. E. Long. 12. 25. is only remarkable as the place where the Pruffian army defeated the Auſtrians on the 2iſt of April 1757. The Auſtrian army, commanded by Count Konigfeck, was ported near Reichenberg, and was attacked by the Pruſſians under the command of the prince of Brunſwick Bevern. The Pruſſians were 20,000, and the Auſtrians 28,000 : the action began at half after ſix in the morning, when the Pruſſian lines were formed, and attacked the Auſtrian cavalry, which was ranged in three lines of 30 fquadrons, and their two wings fuſtained by the infantry, which was poſted among felled trees and intrenchments. The Auſtrians had a village on their right, and a wood on their left, where they were intrenched. The Pruffian dragoons and grenadiers cleared the intrenchment and wood, and entirely routed the Auſtrian cavalry ; at the fame time, the redoubts that covered Reichenberg were taken by General Leſtewitz ; and the Auſtrians were entirely defeated. The Pruffiιns had feven officers and 100 men killed; 14 officers and 150 men wounded. The Auſtrians had 1000 men killed and wounded ; 20 of their officers and 400 men taken priſoners. The action ended at eleven.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">REIN-dber, or </hi><hi rend="italic">Tarandus.</hi>  See Cervus, n<hi rend="sup">0</hi>  4.</p><p>REINS, in anatomy, the ſame with Kidneys. See Anatomy, n<hi rend="sup">o</hi> ιοί.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Reins </hi><hi rend="italic">of a Bridle,</hi>  are two long flips of leather, faſtened on each ſide of a curb or fnaflle, which the rider holds in his hand, to keep the horſe in fubjection.</p><p>There ia alfo what is called <hi rend="italic">falfe reins ;</hi>  which is a lath of leather, paſſed fometim,εs through the arch of the banquet, to bend the horſc’s neck.</p><p>REJOINDER, in law, is the defendant’s anſwer to the plaintiff’s replication or reply. Thus, in the court of chancery, the defendant puts in an anſwer to the plaintiff’s bill, which is ſometimes alſo called an <hi rend="italic">exception ;</hi>  the plaintlſſ’s anfwer to that is called a <hi rend="italic">replication,</hi>  and the defendant’s anfwer to that a <hi rend="italic">rejoindre.</hi></p><p>RELAND (Adrian), an eminent orientaliſt, born at Ryp, in North Holland, in 1676. During three years ſtudy under Surenhuſius, he made an uncommon progreſs in the Hebrew, Syriac, Chaldee, and Arabic languages ; and theſe languages were always his fa-vourite ſtudy. In 1701, he was, by the recommendation of King william, appointed profeffor of oriental languages and eccleſiaſtical· antiquities in the univerſity of Utrecht ; and died of the fmall-pox in 1718. Hc was diſtinguifiied by his modeſty, humanity, and learning ; and carried on a correſpondence with the moſt eminent ſcholars of his time. His principal works are, I. An excellent defcription of Paleſtine. 2. Five diſ-ſertations on the Medals of the ancient Hebrews, and feveral other differtations on different ſubjects. 3. Au Introduction to the Hebrew Grammar. 4. The An-tiqιιities of the ancient Hebrews. 5. Οη the Mahometan Religion. Thefe works are all written in Latin.</p><p>RELATION, the mutual refpect of two things, or what each is with regard to the other. See Metaphysics, n<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 93, &amp;c. and 128, &amp;c.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Relation, in geometry. See Ratio.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Relation, is alfo uſed for analogy. See Ανλ-logy, and Metaphysics, p. 529, &amp;c.</hi></p><p>RELATIVE, ſomefhing relating to or reſpectſhg another.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Rrlative, in muſic. See Mode.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">RεLAτtvε-Terms,</hi>  in logic,· are words which impIy relation : ſuch are maſter and ſervant, huſhand and wife, &amp;c.</p><p>In. grammar, relative words are thoſe which anſwer to fome other word foregoſhg, called the <hi rend="italic">antecedent ; </hi>ſuch are the relative pronouns <hi rend="italic">qui, qux, quod,</hi>  &amp;c. and in Engliſh, <hi rend="italic">who, whom, which,</hi>  &amp;c. The word an-ſwering to theſe relatives is often underſtood, as, " I know whom you mean,” for " I know the perſon whom you mean.”</p><p>RELAXATION, in medicine, the act of looſenſhg or flackening ; or the looſeneſs or flackneſs of the fibres, nerves, muſcles, &amp;c.</p><p>RELAY, a ſupply of horſes, placed on the road, and appointed to be ready for a traveller to change, in order to make the greater expedition.</p><p>RELEASE, in law, is a diſcharge or conveyance oſ a man’s right in lands or tenements, to another that</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>