<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>hath ſome former eſtate in poffeffion. The words generally uſed therein are " remiſed, releaſed, and for ever quit-claimed.” And theſe releaſes may enure, either, I. By way of <hi rend="italic">enlarging an eflate,</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">enlarger l'efiate :</hi>  as, if there be tenant for life or years, re-mainder to another in fee, and he in remainder releaſes all his right to the particular tenant and his heirs, this gives him the eſtate in fee. But in this caſe the releſſee mult be in <hi rend="italic">pofieffion</hi>  of ſome eſtate, for the releaſe to work upon ; for if there be leſſee for years, and, before he enters and is in poffeffion, the leſſor releaſes to him all his right in the reverſion, ſuch releaſe is void ſor want of poffeffion in the releſſee. 2. By way of <hi rend="italic">pfifing an efiate,</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">mitter l<hi rend="sup">,</hi>eβate :</hi>  as, when one of two coparceners rcleaſeth all his right to the other, this paſſeth the fee-ſimple of the whole. And, in both theſe caſes, there muſt be a privity of eſtate between the releſſor and releſſee ; that is, one of their eſtates muſt be ſo related to the other, as to make but one and the ſame eſtate in law. 3. By way of <hi rend="italic">pa[fiηg a right,</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">mitter le droit :</hi>  as if a man be diſſeifed, and releafeth to his diſſeifor all his right ; hereby the diſſeifor acquires a new right, which changes the quality of his eſtate, and renders that lawful which before was tortious. 4. By way of <hi rend="italic">extinguiſhment : </hi>as if my tenant for life makes a leaſe to A for life, re-mainder to B and his heirs, and I releaſe to A ; this extinguiſhes my right to the reverſion, and ſhall enure to the advantage of B’s remainder as well as of A’s particular eſtate. 5. By way of <hi rend="italic">entry and feoffment : </hi>as if there be two joint diſſeifors, and the diſſeiſee releaſes to one of them, he ſhall be fole feiſed, and ſhall keep out his former companion ; which is the ſame in effect as if the diſſeiſee had entered, and thereby put an end to the diſſeiſin, and afterwards had enfeoffed one of the diſſeifors in fee. And hereupon we may obſerve, that when a man has in himſelf the poſſeſſion of lands, he muſt at the common law convey the free-hold by feoffment and livery ; which makes a noto-riεty in the country : but if a man has only a right or a future intereſt, he may convey that right or intereſt by a mere releaſe to him that is in poſſeſſion of the land : for the occupancy of the releſſee is a matter of lufficient notoriety already.</p><p>RELEVANCY, in Scots law. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Law,</hi>  N<hi rend="sup">o </hi>clxxxvi. 48.</p><p>RELICS, in the Romiſh church, the remains of the bodies or clothes of ſaints or martyrs, and the in-ſtruments by which they were put to death, devoutly preſerved, in honour to their memory ; kiſſed, revered, and carried in proceſſion.</p><p>The reſpect which was juſtly due to the martyrs and teachers of the Chriſtian faith, in a few ages increaſed almoſt to adoration ; and at length adoration was really paid both to departed ſaints and to relics of holy men or holy things.. The abuſes of the church of Rome, with reſpect to relics, are very flagrant and notorious. For ſuch was the rage for them at one time, that, as F. Mabillon a Benedictine juſtly complains, the altars were loaded with ſuſpected relics ; numerous ſpurious ones being everywhere offered to the piety and devotion of the faithful. He adds, too, that bones are often conſecrated, which, ſo far from belonging to ſaints, probably do not belong to Chriſtians. From the catacombs numerous relics have been taken,, and yet it is</p><p>not known who were the perſons interred therein. In the nth century, relics were tried by fire, and thofe which did not conſume were reckoned genuine, and the reſt not. Relics were, and ſtill are, preſerved on the altars whereon maſs is celebrated ; a ſquare hole being made in the middle of the altar, big enough to re-ceive the hand, and herein is the relic depoſited, be-ing firſt wrapped in red ſilk, and incloſed in a leaden box.</p><p>The Romaniſts plead antiquity in behalf of relics : For the Manichees, out of hatred to the fleſh, which they conſidered as an evil principle, refuſed to,honour the relics of ſaints ; which is reckoned a kind of proof that the Catholics did it in thc firſt ages.</p><p>we know, indeed, that the touching of linen cloths on relics, from an opinion of ſome extraordinary virtue derived therefrom, was as ancient as th¢ firſt ages, there being a hole made in the coffins of the 40 martyrs at Conſtantinople expreſsly for this purpoſe. The honouring the relics of ſaints, on which the church of Rome afterwards founded her ſuperſtitious and lucrative uſe of them, as objects of devotion, as a kind of charms or amulets, and as inſtruments of pretended miracles, appears to have originated in a very ancient cuſtom, that prevailed among Chriſtians, of affembling at the cemeteries or burying-places of the martyrs, for the purpoſe of commemorating them, and of performing divine worſhip. when the profeffion of Chriſtianity obtained the protection of the civil government, under Conſtantine the Great, ſtately churches were erected over their ſepulchres, and their names and memories were treated with every poffible token of affection and reſpect. This reverence, however, gradually exceeded all reaſonable bounds ; and thoſe prayers and religious ſervices were thought to have a peculiar ſanctity and virtue, which were performed over their tombs. Hence the practice which afterwards obtained, of depofiting relics of ſaints and martyrs under the altars in all churches. This practice was then thought of ſuch importance, that St Ambroſe would not conſecrate a-church becauſe it had no relics ; and the council of Conſtantinople in Trullo ordained, that thoſe altars· ſhonld be demoliſhed under which there were found no relics. The rage of procuring relics for this and other purpoſes of a ſimilar nature, became ſo exceffive, that in 386 the emperor Theodofius the Great was obliged to paſs a law, forbidding the pcople to dig up the bo-dies of the martyrs, and to traffic in their relics.</p><p>Such was the origin of that reſpect for ſacred relics», which afterwards was perverted into a formal worſhip of them, and became the occafion of innumerable pro-ceffions, pilgrimages, and miracles, from which the church of Rome hath derived incredible advantage.— In the end of the ninth century, it was not ſufficient to reverence departed ſaints, and to confide in their inter-ceffions and ſuccours, to clothe them with an imaginary power of healing diſeaſes, working miracles, and delivering from all forts of calamities and dangers ; their bones, their clothes, the apparel and furniture they had poffeffed during their lives, the very ground which they had touched, or in which their putrified carcaſes were laid, were treated with a ſtupid veneration, and ſuppoſed to retain the marvellous virtue of healing all diſorders both of body and mind, and of defending ſuch as pof-ſeffed them againſt all the aſſaults and devices of the de-</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>