<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>to batter down the walls of bcſieged places. See <hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps">Battering Ram.</hi></hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">RAM s Head,</hi>  in a ſhip, is a great block belonging to the fore and main haulyards. It has three ſhives in it, in which the haulyards are put ; and in a hole at the end are reeved the ties,</p><p>RAMADAN, a ſolemn ſeaſon of faſting among the Mahometans, See Mahometanism.</p><p>RAMAH (anc. geog.), a town of Benjamin, near θibea, (Judges) ; called <hi rend="italic">Rama oſ Saul</hi>  (i Sam. xxii.), ſix raiies from Jeruſalem to the north ; memorable for tlιe ſtory oſ the Levite and his concubine : Taken and τortιfied by Baaſa king of Iſrael, m order to annoy the Kingdom of Judah. This Rama is mentioned lia. x. jer. xxxi. and Matth, ii. and is to be diſtinguiſhed from <hi rend="italic">Rama oſ i&gt;amnsl,</hi>  ι Sam. xix. called alio <hi rend="italic">Ramatha,</hi>  ι Sam. ι. ιy. and <hi rend="italic">Ramathaim Z,oρhtm,</hi>  ibid. i. ι. which lay a great way to the weſt, towards Joppa, near Lydda, I Ivlaccab. ii. the birth-place of Samuel ; adjoining to the mountains of Ephraim, and the place of his reſidence, I bam. xv. &amp;c. (Joſephus). Called <hi rend="italic">Ramula</hi>  in the lower <hi rend="sup">a</hi>ff<hi rend="sup">e</hi>j (Gul. 1 yrius.) There is here a convent of the Fa-tneιsol the Holy Land, inhabited only by Portugueſe, Spaniards, and Italians.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">RAMATH-mi'zpe, (Joſhua xiii.); </hi><hi rend="italic">Ramoth-Maſphe, </hi>(Septuagint, vulgate) ; <hi rend="italic">Ramoth in Gilead,</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">Rernmath Galaaa,</hi>  (Seventy) ; a town in that tract of Gilead called <hi rend="italic">Maſpha,</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">itiiι∙zpe,</hi>  one of the cities of refuge.</p><p>RAMAZZINI (Bernardin), an Italian phyſician, born at Carpi near Modena in 1633. He was profeffor of phyſic in the univerſity of Modena for 18 years; and in 1700 accepted an invitation ſrom Padua, where he was made ; rector of the college; and died in 1714. His works were collected and publiſhed in London, 1716; of which, his treatiſe <hi rend="italic">De Mοrbis Artificurn,</hi>  " of the peculiar maladies of artificers,” will always be eſteemed uſeful and curious.</p><p>RAMEKINS, a fortrefs of the United Netherlands, on the fouth coaſt ot the iſland of whlchevin, in the province of Zelaι∙ιd. Οηε of the cautionary towns given to Queen Elizabeth for the repayment of the charges ſhe had been at for the defence of this republic in its infancy, hour miles eaſt of Fluſhing ; in N. Lat. ∫ι. 34. E. Long. 4. 24.</p><p>RAMESES, (anc. geog.) ; a town built by the Iſraelites during their bondage in Egypt, and from which the Exodus took place, and which muſt have been to· waids and not far from the Arabian Gulph, feeing in the third ſtation the Iſraelites arrived on its ſhore.</p><p>RAMESES, king of the Lower Egypt when Jacob went thither with his family, in the 1706th year before the Chriſtian era. Ancient authors mention ſeveral other kings of Egypt oſ the ſame name ; and it is thought that one of thofe princes erected in the temple of the fun at Thebes, the magnificent obeliſk which the emperor Conſtantine cauſed to be removed to Alexandria in the year 334; and that prince dying, his ſon Conſtaptius had the obeliſk tranipoιted ſiom Alexandria to Rome in 352, where it was erected in the grand Circus. Its height was 132 ſeet. when the Goths ſacked the city of Rome in 409, they overthrew this obeliſk, which continued buried in the ſand till the time of Sixtus V. in 1587, when it was found broken in three pieces ; which being joined together, it was fet up in the ſquare oſ St John de Lateran. Οη the four fides of this wonderful obeblk are a number of figures aud hl?-roglyphical characters, which, according to the explication of Ammianus Marcellinus, contain the praiſes of Rameſes.</p><p>RAMIFICATION, the production of boughs or branches, or of figures reſembling branches.</p><p>RAMILLIES, a imall village of Brabant, in the Auſtrian Low Countries, 12 milts north of Namur, and 22 ſouth-eaſt of Bruſſels. Lat. 50. 51. Long. 4. 48. hamous tor the battle fought by the allies commanded by the duke of Marlborough and M. D’Auverquirque, againſt that of the two crowns, commanded by the Duke of Bavaria and Marſhal villeroy, the 22d of May 1706. See Britain, n<hi rend="sup">0</hi> 357.</p><p>I he troops deſtined to compoſe the army of the allies being joined at the camp of Borchloon the 20th of May, baited the 2 iſt. Ο11 the 2 2d the army marched from Borchloon in four columns, and poſted itſelf the ſame day, with thc right towards the Mill of Quorem, extending with the left towards Blehen: from this camp was diſcovered the army of the two crowns, which wd⅛ encamped with the left at over-Eſpen, and the right towards the wood of Chapiaraux, Heyliſſem in their iront, and 1 ιrlemont in their rear. It was reſolved tire ſame day to march the next morning towards the plain of Meerdorp or Mierdau, to view, the poſture of the enemies, and determine what would be the moſt proper means of attacking them according to the movement they ſhould make. 1 o this end, an advanced guard of 600 horſe and all the quarter-maſters of the army were lent forward on the <hi rend="italic">2</hi>3d at break of day.</p><p>Γhe ſame morning about four, the army marched in eight columns towards the aforeſaid plain. The advan-ced guard and the quarter-maſters arrived about eight at the height of Meerdorp or Mierdau ; ſrom whence the army of the enemy was ſeen in motion : a little after it was perceived that the enemy was marching through the plain of Mount St Andrew in four columns, of which information was given to the duke of Maιlbo-rough and M. D’Auverquirque, who immediately repaired to the ſaid height ; and by the time theſe gene-rals were arrived there, the head of the enemy’s army already appeared at the tomb of ottomont upon the cauleway, near the Mehaigne : whereupon the Duke of Marlborough and M. D’Auverquirque made the army advance with all expedition.</p><p>T he enemy, as faſt as they advanced, ranged in order of battle, with their right towards the tomb of ottomont upon the Mehaigne, extending with their left to Autr’Eglile ; having Tranquiers in front of their right, into which they had thrown ſeveral battalions of infan-try and 14 ſquadrons of dragoons, who had diſmounted their horſes to ſupport them. They had placed many ot their infantry and a confiderable part of their artillery in the village of Ramillies, which fronted the right oi their main body, as well as into the village of oſſuz, which fronted the left of their infantry, and into the village of Autr’Egliſe, quite on their left. The front between the village of Ramillies and Autr’Egliſe was covered by a imall ſtream of water, which rendered the meadows in ſome places marſhes, and alſo by ſeveral roads covered with hedges ; which difficulties prevent-ed our cavalry ot the right wing from coming to action. As faſt as the army of the allies arrived it was ranged in Order of battle ; with the left towards</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>