<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>with Pruffia; you anſwered, on the icth, that 50,000 Pruffians were marching againſt us, and that you gave notice to the legiſlative body of the formal acts of the pending hoſtilities, in conformity to the conſtitution. —what have you to anſwer ?”</p><p><hi rend="italic">Louis.</hi>  “ It was only at that period I had know-ledge of it : all the correſpondence paſſed with the mi-ni ſters.”</p><p><hi rend="italic">Prof.</hi>  “ You entruſted Dabancourt, the nephew oſ Calbnne, with the department oſ war ; and ſuch has been the ſucceſs oſ your conſpiracy, that the poſts oſ Longwy and Verdun were ſurrendered to the enemy at the moment oſ their appearance.—what have you to anſwer ?”</p><p><hi rend="italic">Louis.</hi>  " I did not know that Dabancourt was M. Calonne’s nephew. I have not diveſted the poſts. I would not have permitted myſelſ ſuch a thing. I know nothing of it, iſ ſt has been ſo.”</p><p><hi rend="italic">Preſ.</hi>  " You have deſtroyed our navy - a vaſt num-ber oſ officers belonging to that corps had cmigrated ;; there ſcarcely remained any to do duty in the harbours ; meanwhile Bertrand was granting paffports every day ; and when the legiſſative body repreſented to you his criminal conduct on the 8th oſ March, you anſwered, that you were ſatisſied with his ſervices.— what have you to anſwer ?”</p><p><hi rend="italic">Louis.</hi>  “ I have done all I could to retain the officers. As to M. Bertrand, ſince the legiſſative affembly preſented no complaint againſt him that might have put him in a ſtate oſ accuſation, I did not think proper to turn him out oſ office.”</p><p><hi rend="italic">Prof.</hi>  " You have favoured the maintenance oſ abſolute government in the colonies ; your agents ſoment-ed troubles and counter-revolutions throughout them, which took place at the ſame epoch when it was to-have' been brought about in France, which indicates plainly that your hand laid this plot.—what have you. to anſwer ?”</p><p><hi rend="italic">Louis.</hi>  " If there are any oſ my agents in the co-lonies, they have not ſpoken the truth ; 1 had nothing to do with what you have juſt mentioned.”</p><p><hi rend="italic">Preof </hi><hi rend="sup">a</hi>  The interior oſ the ſtate was convulſed by fanatics ; you avowed yourſelf their protector, in mani-feſting your evident intention of recovering by them your ancient power.—what have you to anſwer ?”</p><p><hi rend="italic">Louis.</hi>  “ I cannot anſwer to this ; I know nothing of ſuch a project.”</p><p><hi rend="italic">Preof</hi>  " The legiſſative body had paſſed a decree on the 29th of January againſt the factious prieſts ; you ſuſpended its execution.—what have you to an-ſwer ?”</p><p><hi rend="italic">Louis.</hi>  “ The conſtitution referved to me the free ripht to refuſe my ſanction of the decrees.”</p><p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="sup">C</hi>'Preof</hi>  " The troubles had increafed ; the miniſter declared, that he knew no means in the laws extant to arraign the guilty. The legiſſative body enacted a freſh decree, which you likewiſe ſuſpended.—what have you to ſay to this ?”</p><p>[Louis replied in the ſame manner as in tlie preced-ing charge. J</p><p><hi rend="italic">Pre/</hi>  " The uncitizen-like conduct of the guards whom the conſtitution had granted you, had rendered it neceffary to diſhand them. The day after, you ſent them a letter expreffive of your ſatisfaction, and con</p><lb/><p>tinued their pay. This fact is proved by the trea-ſurer of the civil liſt.—what have you to anſwer ?”</p><p><hi rend="italic">Louis.</hi>  " I only continued them in pay till freſh ones could be raiſed, according to the tenor of the decree.”</p><p><hi rend="italic">Prefi</hi>  “ You kept near your perſon the Swiſa-guards : the conſtitution forbade you this, aud the legiſlative affembly had expreſsly ordained their departure.—· what have you to anſwer ?”</p><p><hi rend="italic">Louis.</hi>  " I have executed all the decrees that have been enacted in this reſpect.”</p><p><hi rend="italic">Preof </hi>“ You had private companies at Paris, char-ged to operate movements uſeful to your projects oſ a counter-revolution. Dangremont and Gilles were two of your agents, who had ſalaries from the civil lift. The receipts of G illes, who was ordered to raiſe a company of 60 men, ſhall be preſented to you.—what have you to anfwer ?”</p><p><hi rend="italic">Louis. “ I</hi>  have no knowledge whatever of the pre-jects Taid to their charge : the idea of a counter-revolu· tion never entered into my mind.”</p><p><hi rend="italic">Preof</hi>  - " You wiſhed to ſuborn, with conſſderable ſums, ſeveral members oſ the legiſſative and conſtituent· affemblies. Letters from St Leon and others evince the reality of theſe deeds.—what have you to anſwer ?”</p><p><hi rend="italic">Louis. </hi>“ Several perſons preſented themfelves with ſſmilar decrees, but I have waved them ”</p><p><hi rend="italic">Preof</hi>  “ who are they that preſented you with thoſe projects ?”</p><p><hi rend="italic">Louis.</hi>  “ The plans were ſo vague that I do not recollect them now.”</p><p><hi rend="italic">Preof <hi rend="sup">i(</hi></hi>  who are thoſe to whom you gave money?’<hi rend="sup">5</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Louis.</hi>  " I gave money to nobody.”</p><p><hi rend="italic">Preof</hi>  " You ſuffered the French name to be reviled in Germany, Italy, and Spain, fince you omitted to demand ſatisfaction for the bad treatment which the French ſuffered in thoſe countries.·—what have you to anſwer ? ’</p><p><hi rend="italic">Louis.</hi>  " The diplomatical correſpondence will prove the contrary ; beſides, this was a concern of the miniſters.”</p><p><hi rend="italic">Preof</hi>  “ You reviewed the Swiſs on thé 10th of Auguſt at ſive o’clock in the morning ; and the Swifs were the ſirſt who fired upon the citizens.”</p><p><hi rend="italic">Louis.</hi>  I'went on that day to review all the troops that were aſſembled about me ; the conſſſtuted authori-ties were with me, the department, the mayor, and municipality ; I had even invited thither a deputation of the national aſſembly, and- I aſterwards repaired into the midſt of them with my family.”</p><p><hi rend="italic">Preof</hi>  “ why did you draw troops to the caſtle ?”</p><p><hi rend="italic">Louis.</hi>  “ All the conſtituted authorities ſaw that the caſtle was threatened ; and as I was a conſtituted authority, I had a right to defend myfelf.”</p><p><hi rend="italic">Preof</hi>  " why did you ſummon the mayor of Paris in the night between the 9th and 1 oth of Auguſt to the caſtle ?”</p><p><hi rend="italic">Louis.</hi>  " On account of the reports that were circulated.”</p><p><hi rend="italic">Preſ.</hi>  " You have cauſed the blood of the French to be ſhed.”</p><p><hi rend="italic">Louis.</hi>  " No, Sir, not I.”</p><p><hi rend="italic">Preof</hi>  “ You authorized Septeuil to carry on a ;</p></body></text></TEI>