<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>overturned the French monarchy. Almoſt all the men of property in the kingdom concurred with the miniſtry in thinking a war with France neceſſary for the pur-poſe of ſecuring the conſtitution at home. After the loth of Auguſt the Britiſh miniſter had been recalled ; but the new republic ſtill ſuffered the former ambaſſa-dor from France, M. Chauvelin, to remain in England.</p><p>The oftenſible grounds of quarrel on the part of Great Britain were chiefly two ; the decree oſ the 15th of November 1792, by which it was truly obſerved that encouragement to rebellion was held out to tlie ſubjects of every ftate, and that war was thereby waged againſt every eſtabliſhed government. Of this decree the French executive council gave explanations, denying tlie fairneſs of the interpretation put upon it, and alleging, that the intention of the convention was only to give aid to fuch countries as <hi rend="italic">had already</hi>  acquired their freedom, and by a declaration of the general will requeſted aid for its preſervation. But this explanation cannot be admitted. The decree expreſsly ſays, that the French nation will <hi rend="italic">grant coffiftancedo all who wifh to procure liberty ;</hi>  and when it is conſidered what their notions of liberty are, it cannot be doubted but that their intention was to excite rebellion in foreign nations. The ſecond point of diſpute referred to the opening of the Scheldt. This river runs from Brabant through the Dutch territory to the ſea. The Dutch had ſhut up the mouth of it, and prevented any maritime commerce from being carried on by the people of Brabant by means of the river. To render themfelves popular in Brabant, ;he French had declared, that they would open the navigation of the Scheldt. But Great Britain had ſome time before bound herſelf by treaty with the Dutch to affiſt them in obſtructing this nayigation, and now declared to the French, that the project of opening the Scheldt mnſt be renounced if peace with Great Britain was to remain. The French alleged, that by the law of nations navigable rivers ought to be' open to all who reſide on their banks ; but that the point was of no importance either to France or England, and even of very little importance to Holland ; that if the people of Brabant themſelves choſe to give it up, they would make no objection. It has been thought remarkable, that the Dutch gave themſelves no trouble about the matter. They did not aſk the aſſlſtance of England ; and with that coolneſs which is peculiar to their character, the merchants in-dividually declared, tliat if the Scheldt was opened, they could manage tlieir commerce as well at Antwerp as at Amſterdam. But in all this there is nothing ſtrange. Among tlic Dutch were many republicans, wlio wiſhed for the downfal of the ſtadtholder. Tlieſe rejoiced at every thing wliich diſtreſſed him, or had a tendency to render his office uſeleſs in the eyes of the people. Others, who thought diſſerently, were afraid to ſpeak their ſentiments,, as Dumourier was in their neighbourhood with a victorious army. The reſult of the whole was, that M. Chauvelin was commanded by the Brſtiſh government to leave this country. The French executive council gave powers to another mini-ſter, M. Maret, to negociate, and requeſted a paſſport for him ; but he was not ſuſſered to land. The haughty republicans having thus ſar humbled themſelves before the Britiſh government, at laſt, on the iſt of February 1793, on the motion of Briſſot, the national convention decreed, among other articles, that " George king of England had never ceaſed ſince the revolution</p><lb/><p>of the 10th of Auguſt 1792 from giving to the French nation proofs of his attachment to the concert of crowned heads ; that he had drawn into the ſame lake the ſtadtholder of the United Provinces ; that, contrary to the treaty of 1783, the Engliſh miniſtry had granted protection to the emigrants and others who have openly appeared in arms againſt France; that they have committed an outrage againſt the French repnb-lic, by ordering the ambaſſador of France to quit Great Britain ; that the Engliſh have ſtopped divers boats and veſſels laden with corn for France, whilſt, at tlie ſame time, contrary to the tieaty of 1786, they con-tinue the exportation of it to other foreign countries ; that to thwart more efficaciouſiy the commercial tranſ-actions of the republic with England, they have by an act of parliament prohibited the cmculation of aſſignats. The convention therefore <hi rend="italic">declare,</hi>  that in conſequence of tliefe acts of hoſtility and aggreffion, the French republic is at war with the king of England and tlie ſtadtholder of the United Provinces.”</p><p>The abſurdity of pretending tliat any treaty with France made in 1783 could be violated hy protecting the emigrants who fled from the fury of tlie convention, muſt be obvious to every reader. The convention was itſelf a rebellious uſurpation of tlie government with which ſuch a treaty was made. The prohibition of affignats was certainly contrary to no law, and was ſanc-tioned by every motive oſ expediency, unleſs tlie convention could prove that all nations were bound by the law of nature to riſk their own credit upon tlie credit of the Frencll republic.</p><p>About a fortnight after this abſurd declaration againſt Britain, war was likewiſe declared againſt Spain ; and in tlie courſe of tlie ſummer France was at war with all Europe, excepting only Swiſſerland, Sweden, Den* mark, and Turkey.</p><p>In the mean time General Dumourier, who was proceeding agreeably to his orders, made an attack upon Holland ; but in doing this he diſperſed his troops in ſucli a manner as to expoſe them much to any attack on the ſide of Germany. He commanded General Mi-randa to inveſt Maeſtricht, while he advanced to block up Breda and Bergen-op-zoom. The ſirſt of theſe places, viz. Breda,ſurrendered on the 24th of February; Klundert was taken on the 26th ; and Gertruydenberg on the 4th of March. But here tlie triumphs of Dumourier ended. The ſieges of williamſtadt and Bergen-op-zoom were vigorouſty but unſucceſsſully preſſed. On tbe iſt of March General Clairfait having paſſed the Roer, attacked the French poſts, and compelled them to retreat with tlie loſs of 2000 men.</p><p>The following day the archduke attacked them anew with conſiderable ſucceſs. On the 3d the French were driven from Aix-la-Chapelie, with the loſs of 4000 men killed and 1600 taken priſoners.</p><p>The ſiege of Maeſtricht was now raiſed, and the French retreated to Tongres, where they were alſo at-tacked and forced to retreat to St Tron. Dumourier here joined them, but did not bring his army along with him from the attack upon Holland. After ſome ſkirmiſhes a general engagement took place at Neer-winden. It was fought on the part of the French with great obſtinacy ; but they were at length over-? powered by the number of their enemies, and perhaps alfo by the treachery of their commander. This de-feat was fatal. The French loſt 3000 men, and <hi rend="italic">6oz&gt;o</hi></p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>