<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>proportion to the depth under the ſurface. For 57 : 73r=32 : 41 very nearly. He therefore eſtimates the non-preffure to be of the height of the water above the orifice.</p><p>we are difpoſed to think that the ingenious author has not reaſoned accurately from the experiment. In the firſt place, the force indicated by the experiment, whatever be its origin, is certainly double of what he fuppofes ; for it muſt be meaſured by the ſum of the riſe of the water in one leg, and its depreſſion in the «ther, the weight of the air in the bend of the ſyphon being neglected. It is preciſely analogous to the force acting on the water oſeillatmg in a fyphon, which is acknowledged to be the ſum of the elevation and de-preſſion. The force indicated by the experiment therefore is ∙i-⅛⅜ θf the height of the water above the orifice. The force exhibited in this experiment bears a ſtill greater proportion to the productive height ; ſor it is certain that the water <hi rend="italic">did not</hi>  iffue with the velo--*'city acquired by the fall from the ſurface, and probably did not exceed -J oſ it. The effect of contraction muſt have been confiderable and uncertain. The velocity ſhould have been meaſured both by the amplitude of the jet and by the quantity oſ water diſcharged. In the next place, we apprehend that much oſ the effect is produced by the tenacity oſ the water, which drags along with it the water which would have ſlowly iffued from the fyphon, had the other end not dipped into the water of the veffel. we know, that if the hori-zontal part of the ſyphon had been continued far enough, and if no retardation were occafioned by fric-tion, the column of water in the upright leg would have accelerated like any heavy body ; and when the laft of it had arrived at the bottom of that leg, the whole in the horizontal part would be moving with the velocity acquiredby falling from the ſurface. The water of the vef-ſel which iiΓues through the ſurrounding ring very quickly acquires a much greater velocity than what the water deſcending in the ſyphon would acquire in the ſame time, and it drags this laſt water along with it both by tenacity and friction, and it drags it out till its action is oppoſed by the want of equilibrium produced in the ſyphon, by the elevation in the one leg and the depreſſion in the other. We imagine that little can be concluded from the experiment with reſpect to the real non-preffure. Nay, if the ſides of the ſyphon be ſuppoſed infinitely thin, ſo that there would be no curvature of the fila-ments of the ſurrounding water at the mouth of the ſyphon, we do not very diſtinctly fee any fouree of non-preffure : For we are not altogether fatisfièd with the proof which Mr Buat offers for this meaſure of the preffure of a ffream of fluid gliding along a ſurface, <hi rend="italic">and οbβructed by friction or any other caufe.·</hi>  we imagine that the paſſing water in the preſent experiment would be a little retarded by accelerating continually the water de-ſcending in the ſyphon, and renewed a-top, ſuppofing tlie upper end open; becauſe this water would not of it-ſelf acquire more than half this velocity. It however drags it out, till it not only refiſts with a force equal to the weight of the whole vertical column, but even ex-ceeds it by <hi rend="sub">τ</hi>⅛⅛∙. This it is able to do, becauſe the whole preffure by which the water iffues from an orifice has been ſhown (by Daniel Bernoulli) to be equal to twice this weight, we therefore confider this beauti-Sil experiment as chiefly valuable, by giving us a mea-</p><p>ſure of the tenacity of the water; and we wiſh that it were repeated in a variety of depths, in order to diſco-ver what relation the force exerted bears to the depth. It would ſeem that the tenacity, being a certain deter-minate thing, the proportion of 100 to 112 would not be conſtant; and that the obſerved ratio would be made up of two parts, one of them conſtant, and the other proportional to the depth under the ſurface.</p><p>But ſtill this experiment is intimately connected with the matter in hand ; and this apparent non-preſ-ſure'on the hinder part of a body expofed to a ſtream, from whatever cauſes it proceeds, does operate in the action of water on this hinder part, and mult be taken into the account.</p><p>_ we muſt therefore follow the Chevalier de Buat in his diſcuſſions on this ſubject. A priſmatic body, ha-ving its prow and poop equal and parallel ſurfaces,. and plunged horizontally into a fluid, will require a force to keep it firm in the direction of its axis preciſely equal to the difference between the real preffures exerted on its prow and poop. If the fluid is at reſt, this difference will be nothing, becauſe the oppofite dead preffures of the fluid will be equal : but in a ſtream, there is ſuperadded to the dead preffure on the prow the active preffure ariſing from the deflections of the filaments-of this fluid.</p><p>If the dead preffure on the poop remained in its full intenſity by the perfect ſtagnation of the water be-hind it, the whole fenſible preffure on the body would be the active preffure only on the prow, repreſented by <hi rend="italic">m h.</hi>  If, on the other hand, we could ſuppoſe that the water behind the body moved continually away from it ( being renewed laterally ) with the velocity of the ftream, the dead preffure would be entirely removed from its poop, and the whole ſenfible preffure, or what muff be oppoſed by ſome external force, would be <hi rend="italic">m h</hi>  -j- <hi rend="italic">h. </hi>Neither of theſe can happen ; and the real ſtate of the caſe muſt be between thefo extremes.·</p><p>The following experiments were tried : The perfo-rated box with its vertical tube was expofed to the ſtream, the braſs plate being turned down the ſtream. The velocity was again 36 inches per ſecond.</p><p>The central hole A alone being opened, gave a non-preffure of _    -    .    1<hi rend="sub">3</hi>  lines..</p><p>A hole B, ⅜ of an inch from the edge; gave    -    -    15</p><p>A hole C, near the ſurfaee    -    <hi rend="sup">1</hi>5&gt;7</p><p>A hole D, at the lower angle - 1y,j</p><p>Here it appears that there is a very confiderable non-preffure, increafing from the centre to the border.. This increaſe undoubtedly-proceeds from the greater la-teral velocity with which the water is gliding in from the ſides. The water behind was by no means ſtag-nant, although moving off with a much fmaller velocity than that of the paſſing ſtream, and it was viſtbly removed from the fides, and gradually licked away at its further extremity.</p><p>Another box, having a great number of holes, all open, indicated a medium off non-preffure equal to 13,i lines.</p><p>A nother of larger dimenfions, but having fewer holes, indicated a non-preffure of 12⅛.</p><p>But the moſt remarkable,, and the moſt important phenomena, were the following :</p><p>The ſirſt box wa<hi rend="sub">l</hi>s fixed to the ſide of another box,</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>