<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>.with great force : but as to fire, light, and electricity, our experiments fail; nay, the ſuppoſition of a repulſtve power among the particles of the electric fluid is incon-ſiſtent with the phenomena, as has been demonſtrated under the article Electricity, Sect. V. and VI. E-ven in thofe fluids, air and ſteam, wherc a repulſtve power moſt manifeſtly exiſts, it is demonſtrable that the repulſion cannot be a <hi rend="italic">primary</hi>  quality, ſince it can be increaſed to a great degree by heat, and diminiſhed by cold : but it is impoſſible that a <hi rend="italic">primary</hi>  quality ol matter can be increaſed or diminiſhed by any external circumſtances whatever; for whatever property depends upon external circumftances, is not a primary but a ſe-condary one.—The repulſion of electrified bodies is explained under the article Electricity : that of others ⅛ leſs ſubject to inveſtigation ; and the moſt that can be ſaid concerning it is, that in many caſes it ſeems to ■be the conſequence of a modi; cation ot dire, and in others of electricity.</p><p>REPUTATION means credit, honour, or the character of good ; and ſince we are deſtined to live in ſociety, is neceſſary and uſeful more or leſs to every human being. There is no man, except one who is overgrown with pride and ſelf-conceit, or whoſe actions are bad, but pays attention to his reputation, and wiſhes to poſſeſs the good opinion of his neighbours or the world. The love of reputation and of fame are moſt powerful ſprings of action ; but though they proceed .from the ſame principle, the means of attaining them, and the effects of them, are not altogether the fame.</p><p>Many means indeed ſerve equally to ſupport the refutation and to increaſe the fame, differing only in degrees; others, however, bel-mg peculiarly either to the one -or to the other. An honeſt reputation is within the reach -of the bulk of mankind; it is obtained by the ſocial virtues and the conſtant practice of the common duties of life. This kind of reputation indeed is neither extensive nor brilliant, but it is ften the moſt uſeful in point of happinefs. Wit, talents, and genius, are the neceffary requiſttes for fame ; but thoſe advantages are perhaps leſs real in their conſequences than thoſe aiding from a good reputation, what is of real uſe coils little ; things rare and fplendid require the greateſt la-hour to procure, and yield perhaps a more ideal happineſs.</p><p>Fame can be poſſeſſed, comparatively ſpeaking, but •by few individuals ; as it requires either very ſuperior abilities, ſupported by great efforts, or very fortunate circumſtances. It is conſtituted by the applauſe of mankind, or at leaſt by that of a. ſingle nation ; whilſt reputation is of much leſs extent, and ariſes from different circumftances. I hat reputation which is founded on deceit and artifice is never ſolid ; and the moſt honourable will always be found to be the moſt uſeful. Every one may ſafely, and indeed ought to, afpire to the conſideration and praiſe due to his condition and merit ; bur hc who aſpires to moi e, or who ſeeks it by diſhoneſt means, will at length meet with contempt.</p><p>REQUEST, in law, a ſupplication or petition pre-ferred to a prince, or to a court of juſtice ; begging relief in ſome conſcionable cafes where the common law grants no immediate redreſs..</p><p><hi rend="italic">Court of Rescuesrs (curia requifιtionum)</hi>  was a court of equity, of the ſame nature with the court of chancery, but inferior to it ; principally inſtituted for the relief of ſuch petitioners as in conſcionable caſes addreſ-</p><lb/><p>ſed themfelves by feιpplication to his majeſty. Οί this court the lord privy-leal was chief judge, aſſiſted by the maſters of requeſts ; and it had beginning about the 9 Hen. VII. according to Sir Julius Cæfar’s tractate upon this ſubject : though Mr Gwγn, in his preface to his Readings, faith it began from a commiſſion firſt grant-ed by king Henry VIII. - This court, having aſſumed great power to itfelf, ſo that it became burthenſome, <hi rend="italic">Mich,</hi>  anno 40 and 41 <hi rend="italic">F,Hz.</hi>  in the court of common-pleas it was adjudged upon ſolemn argument, that the court of requeſts was no court of judica-ture, &amp;c. and by flat. 16 &amp; 17 Car I. c. 10. it was taken away.</p><p>'Γhere are ſtill courts of requeſts, or courts of conſcience, conſtituted in London and other trading and populous diſtricts for the recovery of ſmall debts. The firſt of theſe was eſtabliſhed in London ſo early as the reign of Henry VIII. by an act of their common council ; which however was certainly inſuſſicient ſor that purpoſe, and illegal, till confirmed by ſtatute 3 Jac. I. c. 15. which lias fince been explained and amended by ſtatute 14 Geo II. c. 10. The conſtitution is this: two aldermen and four commoners fit twice a week to hear all cauſes oſ debt not exceeding the value oſ forty ſhillings ; which they examine in a ſummary way, by the oath oſ the parties or other witneffes, and make ſuch order therein as is conſonant to equity and good conſcience. 1 he time and expence of obtaining this ſummary redreſs are very inconfiderable, which make it a great benefit to trade ; and thereupon divers trading towns and other diſtricts have obtained acts oſ parlia-ment ſor eſtabliſhing in them courts oſ conſcience upon nearly the ſame plan as that in the city oſ London.</p><p>By 25 Geo. III. c. 45. (which is confined to proſe-cutions in courts oſ conſcience in London, Middleſex, and the borough oſ Southwark), and by 26 Geo. III. c. 38. (which extends the proviſions oſ the former act to all other courts inſtituted ſor rhe recovery oſ ſmall debts), <hi rend="sup">,</hi>t is enacted, that after the firſt day oſ Septem-ber 1786, no perſon who.fcever, being a debtor or de-fendant, and who has been or ſhall be committed to any gaol or prifon by order oſ any court or commiſſioners authoriſed by any act or acts oſ parliament for conſtitu-tiπg or regulating any court or courts for the recovery ot ſmall debts, where the debt does not exceed twenty ſhillings, ſhall be kept or continued in cuſtody, on any pretence whatfoever, more than twenty days ſrom the commencement oſ the laſt mentioned act ; or ſrom the time oſ his, her, or their commitment to prifon : and where the original debt does not amount to or exceed the ſum oſ forty ſhillings, more than forty days ſrom the commencement oſ the ſaid act, or from the time of his, her, or their commitment as aforefaid ; and all gaolers are thereby required to diſcharge ſuch perſons accordingly. And by fect. 2. if it ſhall be proved to the fatisfaction of the court, that any ſuch debtoι has money or goods which he has wilfully and fraudulently concealed ; in that caſe the court ſhall have power to enlarge the aforeſaid times of imprifonment for debts un-der twenty ſhillings, to any time not exceeding thirty days, and for debts under forty ſhillings, to any time not exceeding fixty days ; which laid ground of farther detention ſhall be ſpecified in the faid commitment. And that (by ſect. 3.) at the expiration of the laid refpec<hi rend="sub">r </hi>‘ tive times of imprifonment, every ſuch perſon ſhall im</p><p>mediately be diſ¢harged, without paying any ſum of</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>