<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>aII the infirmities of age. Yet he obtained a canonry in the church of Chartres, with other benefices ; and died in 1613. There is a neat EIzevir edition of his works, 12mo, 1652, Leyden; but the moſt elegant is that with notes by M. Broſiette, 4t0, 1729, London.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Regnier des Makets (Seraphin), a French poet, born at Paris in 1632. He diſtinguiſhed himſelf early by his poetical talents, and in 1684 was made perpetual fecretary to the French academy on the death ofMe-zeray : it was he who drew up all thoſe papers in the name of the academy againſt Furetiere : the king gave him the priory of Grammont, and he had alſo an ab-bey. He died in ⅛ 713, and his works are, French, I-talian, Spaniſh, and Latin poems, 2 vols ; a French grammar; and an Italian tranſlation of Anacreon’s odes, with ſome t&gt;ther tranſlations.</hi></p><p>REGNUM (anc. geog.), a town of the Regni, a people in Britain, next the Cantii, now Surry, Suſſex, and the coaſt of Hampſhire, (Camden) ; a town ſituated, by the Itinerary numbers, on the confines of the Belgæ, in a place now called <hi rend="italic">Ringwood,</hi>  in Hampſhire, on the rivulet Avon, running down from Saliſhury, and about ten miles or more diſtant from the ſea.</p><p>REGRATOR, ſignifies him who buys and fells any wares or victuals in the <hi rend="italic">fame</hi>  market or fair : and regra-tυrs are particularly deſcribed to be thoſe who buy, or get into their hands, in fairs or markets, any grain, fiſh, butter, cheeſe, ſheep, lambs, calves, ſwine, pigs, geeſe, capons, hens, chickens, pigeons, conies, or other dead victuals whatſoever, brought to a fair or market to be fold there, and do fell the ſame again in the ſame fair, market, or place, or in ſome other within four miles thereof.</p><p>Regrating is a kind of <hi rend="italic">huckftry,</hi>  by which victuals are made dearer ; for every feller will gain ſomething, which mnſt of conſequence enhance the price. And, in ancient times, both the engroſſer and regrator were comprehended under the word <hi rend="italic">fοreβαller.</hi>  Regrators are puniſhable by loſs and forfeiture of goods, and impriſonment, according to the firſt, ſecond, or third offence, &amp;c.</p><p>REGENSBERG, a handſome, though ſmall town of Swiſſerland, in the canton of Zurich, and capital of a bailiwick of the fame name, with a ſtrong caſtle ; ſeat-cd on a hill, which is part of Mount Jura. There is a well ſunk through a rock, 36 fathoms deep.</p><p>REGULAR, denotes any thing that is agreeable to the rules of art : thus we ſay, a regular building, verb, &amp;c.</p><p>A regular figure, in geometry, is one whoſe ſides, and conſequently angles, are equal ; and a regular figure with three or four ſides is commonly termed an <hi rend="italic">equilateral triangle</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">ſquare,</hi>  as all others with more ſides are called <hi rend="italic">regular polygons.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Regular, in a monaſtery, a perſon who has taken the vows ; becaufe he is bound to obſerve the rules of the order he has embraced.</hi></p><p>REGULATION, a rule or order preſcribed by a ſuperior, for the proper management of ſome affair.</p><p>REGULATOR <hi rend="italic">of a </hi><hi rend="smallcaps">watch, the ſmall ſpring belonging to the balance ; ferving to adjuſt its motions, and make it go faſter or flower. See watch.</hi></p><p>REGULBIUM, or Regulvium, (Notitia Impe-rii) ; mentioned nowhere elſe more early: a town of the Cantii, in Britain, Now Reculver, a village on the</p><p>coaſt, near the iſland Tſhanet, towards the Thames, to thc north of Canterbury, (Camden).</p><p>REGULUS (M. Attilius), a conful during the firſt Punic war. He reduced Brunduſium, and in his ſecond conſulſhip he took 64 and funk 30 galleys of the-Carthaginian fleet, on the coaſts of Sicily.* Afterwards he landed in Africa 5 and fo rapid was his ſucceſs, that in a ſhort time he made himſelf maſter of about 200 places of conſequence on the coaſt. The Carthaginians ſued for peace, but the conqueror refuſed to grant it ; and ſoon after he was defeated in a battle by Xanthip-pus, and 30,000 of his men were left on the field of battle, and 15,000 taken priſoners. Regulus was in the number of the captives, and he was carried in triumph to Carthage. He was ſent by the enemy to Rome, to propoſe an accommodation and an exchange of priſoners ; and if his commiffiôn was unſucceſsful, he was bound by the moſt ſolemn oaths to return to Car-thage without delay, when he came to Rome, Regulus diſſuaded his countrymen from accepting the· terms which the enemy propoſed ; and when his opi-nion had had due influence on the ſenate, Regulus reti-red to Carthage agreeable to his engagements. The Carthaginians were told that their offers of peace had been rcjected at Rome by the means of Regulus ; and therefore they prepared to puniſh him with the greateſt ſeverity. His eye-brows were cut, and he was expofed’ for ſome days to the exceſſive heat of the meridian ſun, and afterwards confined in a barrel, whoſe fides were everywhere filled with large iron ſpikes, till he died in the greateſt agonies. His ſufferings were heard of at Rome ; and the ſenate permitted his widow to inflict-whatever puniſhment ſhe pleaſed on ſome of the moſt illuſtrious captives of Carthage which were in their hands. She confined them alſo in preſſes filled with ſharp iron points ; and was ſo exquifite in her cruelty, ' that the ſenate interfered, and ſtopped the barbarity of her puniſhment. Regulus died about 251 years before Chriſt.—Memmius, a Roman, made governor of Greece by Caligula, while Regulus was in his province, the emperor wiſhed to bring thç celebrated ſtatue of Jupiter olympius by Phidias to Rome, but this was ſupernatu-rally prevented ; and according to ancient authors, the ſhip which was to convey it was deſtroyed by lightning, and the workmen who attempted to remove the ſtatue</p><p>were terrified away by ſudden noiſes__A man who</p><p>condemned Sejanus.—Roſcius, a man who held the con-ſulſhip but for one day, in the reign of vſtellius.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Regulus, in chemiſtry, an imperfect metallic ſtib-ſhance that falls to the bottom of the crucible, in thc melting oſ ores or impure metallic fubſtances. It ia the ſineſt or pureſt part of the metal j and, according, to the alchemiſts, is denominated </hi><hi rend="italic">regulus,</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">little king, </hi>as being the ſirſtſhorn of the royal metallic blood. Ac-cording to them, it is really a ſon, but not a perfect man ; <hi rend="italic">i. e.</hi>  not yet a perfect metal, for want of time and proper nouriſhment. To procure the regulus oΓ mercurial parts of metals, &amp;c. flux powders are commonly uſed ; as nitre, tartar, &amp;c. which purge the ſul-phureous part adhering to the metal, hy attracting and abſorbing it to themſelves.</p><p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps">Regulus of Antimony.</hi></hi>  See Chemistry,, n<hi rend="sup">0</hi>  1252 —1257 ; and fee<hi rend="italic">Index</hi>  there, at <hi rend="italic">Antimony.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps">Regulus of Arfenic.</hi></hi>  See Chemistry, n<hi rend="sup">o</hi>  1267, &amp;c*and 1285—1294. The ancient proceſs for making re-</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>