<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>thread in a hundred coarſer than the guide-fcrew H. The wheels on the guide-fcrew arbor H, and that on the ſteel E, on which the fcrew was to be cut, were proportioned to each other to produce that effect, by giving the wheel L 198 teeth, and the wheel 200. Theſe wheels communicated with each other by means of the intermediate wheel R, which alſo ſerved to give the threads on the two ſcrews the ſame direction.</p><p>" The ſaddle-piece P is confined on the bar A by means of the pieces (g), and may be made to Aide with a proper degree of tightneſs by the ſcrews (n).”</p><p>For Ramſden’s equatorial or portable obſervatorv, ſee Optics, n<hi rend="sup">0</hi> 102. and Astronomy, n<hi rend="sup">0</hi> 504. See alfo a long account of an equatorial inſtrument made by Mr Ramſden by the direction of Sir George Shuck-burgh in the Philofophical Tranſactions for r 793, art. x. p. 67. In this inſtrument the circle of declinations is four feet in diameter, and may be obſerved nearly to a fccond. The glaſs is placed between ſix pillars, which form the axis of the machine, and turn round by two pivots placed on two blocks of ſtone. See aſſo Barometer.</p><p>RAMSEY, a town of Huntingdonſhire, 68 miles north of London, and 12 north-eaſt of Huntingdon. It is ſituated as it were in an iſland, being everywhere .encompaffed with fens, except on the weſt, where it is ſeparated from the <hi rend="italic">terra firma</hi>  by a cauſey for two ■miles. The neighbouring meers of Ramſey and whitle-ſey, which are formed by the river Nyne, abound with fowl and fiſh, efpecially eel and large pikes. It was once famous for a very rich abbey, part of the gatehoufe of which is ſtill ſtanding, and a neglected ſtatue of Ail-win ; the epitaph of whoſe tomb, which is reckoned one of the oldeſt pieces of Engliſh ſculpture extant, ftylεs him " kinſman of the famous King Edward, alderman of all England, and the miraculous founder of this abbey.” It was dedicated to St Duriſtan, and its abbots were mitred, and fat in parliament ; and ſo ■many kings of England were benefactors to it, that its yearly rents, ſays Camden, were 70001. The town was then called <hi rend="italic">Ramſey the Rich ;</hi>  but by the diſſolution of the abbey it foon became poor, and even loſt its market for many years, till about 185 years ago it recovered it. It is held on Saturday, and is reckoned one of the moſt plentiful and cheapeſt in England. In the year 1721 a great number of Roman coins was found here, ſuppoſed to have been hid by the monks on. ſome incurſion of the Danes. There is a charity ſchool in the town for poor girls. W. Long. o. 19. N. Lat. 52. 26.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Ramsey, an iſland of ſouth wales, on the coaſt of Pembrokeſhire, about two miles in length, and a mile and a half broad. Near it are ſeveral ſmall ones, known by the name of the </hi><hi rend="italic">biſhop and his clerks.</hi>  It is four miles weſt of St David’s, and 17 north-weſt of Mil-ford haven. It belongs to the biſhopric of St Da-vid’s, and was in the laſt age, ſays Camden, famous for the death of one Juſtinian, a moſt holy man, who retiring hither from Britanny, in that age rich in ſaints, and devoting himſelf entirely to God, lived a long while in ſolitude, and being at laſt murdered by his fervant was enrolled among the martyrs. W. Long. 5. 20. N. Lat. 51. 55.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Ramsey, in the Iſle of Man, to the north, a moſt </hi>noted and ſpaclous haven, in which the grcat¢ſt fleet may ride at anchor with ſafety enough from all winds but the north eaſt, and in that caſe they need not be embayed. This town ſtanding upon a beach of looſe fand, or ſhingle, is in danger, if not timely prevented, of being waſhed away by the fea.</p><p>RAMSGATE, a ſea-port town of Kent, in the iſle of Thanet, five miles from Margate, where a very fine pier has been lately built for the ſecurity of ſhips that come into the harbour, being ſeated near the Downs, between the north and fouth Foreland, 10 miles north-ea∙ft of Canterbury. The town is ſituated in the cove of a chalky cliff. It was formerly but an obfcure fiſh-ing village, but ſince the year 1688 has been improved and enlarged by a ſuccefsful trade to Ruſſia and the eaſt country. But what renders it moſt worthy of notice, and attracts multitudes of ſtrangers, is the new harbour, which is one of the moſt capacious in England, if not in Europe. It was begun in the year 1750, but delayed by various interruptions. It con-ſiſts of two piers ; that to the eaſt is built wholly of Purbeck ſtone, and extends itfelf into the ocean near 800 feet before it forms an angle ; its breadth on the top is 26 feet, including a ſtrong parapet wall, which runs along the outſide of it. The other to the weſt is conſtructed of wood as far as the low-water mark, but the reſt is of ſtone. The angles, of which there are five in each pier, conſiſt of 160 feet each, with octa-gons at the end of 60 feet diameter, leaving an en-trance of 200 feet into the harbour, the depth of which admits of a gradual increaſe of 18 to 36 feet. E. Long, i- 50. N. Lat. 51. 22.</p><p>RAMTRUT, a deity worſhipped by the Ranazins of Hindoſtan, where he has a celebrated temple at Οποί·. He is repreſented as more reſembling a mon-key than a man.</p><p>RAMUS, in general, denotes a branch of any thing, as of a tree, an artery, &amp;c. Tn the anatomy of plants it means the ſirſt or lateral branches, which go off from the petiolum, or middle rib of a leaf. Tne ſubdiviſions of thefe are called <hi rend="italic">ſurculi ;</hi>  and the final diviſions into the moſt minute of ail, are by ſome called <hi rend="italic">capiUamεηta ;</hi>  but both kinds are generally denominated <hi rend="italic">ſurculus.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Ramus (Peter), was one of the moſt famous pro* feſſors of the 16th century. He was born in Picardy in 1515. A thirſt tor learning prompted him to go to Paris when very young, and he was admitted a ſervant in the college of Navarre. Spending the day in waiting on his maſters, and the greateſt part of the night in ſtudy, he made ſuch ſurpriſing progreſs, that, when he took his maſter of arts degree, he offered to maintain a quite oppoſite doctrine to that of Ariſtotle. This raifed him many enemies ; and the two firſt books he publiſhed, </hi><hi rend="italic">Inβitutiones Dialectic#,</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">Arifio-telic&lt;e Aaimadverfiοnes,</hi>  occaſioned great diſturbances in the univerſity of Paris : and the oppoſition againſt him was not a little heightened by his deſerting the Romiſh religion, and profeſſing that of the Reformed. Beiκg thus forced to retire from Paris, he viſited the univtr-ſities of Germany, and received great honours wſhere-ever he came. He returned to France in 157r, and ioſt his life miſerably in the horrid maffacre of St Bartholomew’s day. He was a great orator, a man°of ur.i-verſal learning, and endowed with very fine moral quad-</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>