<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>the weight of the column of fluid, having twice the productive height for its height. How it is juft one-half, ihall be our next inquiry.</p><p>And here we muſt return to the labours of Sir Iſaac Newton. After many beautiful obſervations on the na-ture and mechanifm of continued fluids, he ſays, that the reſiftance which they occaſion is but one-half of that occaſioned by the rare fluid which had been the ſubject of his former propoſition ; " which truth,” (ſays he, with his uſual caution andmυdefty), " I ihall endeavour to {how.”</p><p>He then enters into another, as novel and as difficult an inveftigation, viz. the laws of hydraulics, and endeavours to aſcertain the motion of fluids through orifices when urged by preffures of any kind. He endeavours to afoertain the velocity with which a ſiuid eſcapes through a horizontal oriſice in the bottom of a veſſel, by the action of its weight, and the preſſure which this vein of fluid will exert on a little circle which occupies part of the oriſice. To obtain this, he employs a kind of approximation and trial, of which it would be extremely difficult to give an extract ; and then, by increafing the diameter oſ the veſſcl and oi the hole to infinity, he accommodates his reaſoning to the caſe of a plane ſurface expofed to an indeſinitely extended ftream of fluid; and laftly, giving to the little circular furface-the motion which he had before aſcrſhed to the fluid, he fays, that the reſiftance to a plane ſurface -moving through au unelaftic continuous fluid, is equal to the weight of a column of the ſiuid whoſe height is one-half of that neceſſary for acquiring the velocity ; and he ſays, that· the reſiſtance of a globe is, in this caſe, the ſame with that of a cylinder of the ſame diameter. The reſiſſance, therefore, of the cylinder or circle is four times leſs,’ and that of the globe is twice leſs than their reſiſtances on a rare elaſtic medium.</p><p>But this determination, though founded on principles or aſſumptions, which are much nearer to the real Hate of things, is liable to great objections. It depends on his method for afcertaining the velocity of the iſſuing fluid ; a method extremely ingenious, but defective. The cataract, which he ſuppoſes, cannot ex-ift as he ſuppoſes, deſcending by the full action off gravity, and ſurrounded by a funnel of ftagnant fluid. For, in ſuch circumftances, there is nothing to balance the hydroſtatical preſſure of this ſurrounding fluid ; be-cauſe the whole preſſure of the central cataract is exn-ployed in producing its own deſcent. In the next place, the preſſure which he determines is beyond all doubt only half of what is obſerved on a plane ſurface in all our experiments. And, in the third place, it is repugnant to all our experience, that the reſiftance of <hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps">sl</hi></hi>  globe or of a pointed body is as great as that of its circular baſe. His reafons are by no means convincing. He ſuppoſes them placed in a tube or canal ; and ſince they are ſuppoſed of the ſame diameter, and therefore leave equal ſpaces at their ſides, he concludes, that be-cauſe the water eſcapes by their ſides with the ſame <hi rend="italic">velocity,</hi>  they will have the ſame reſiſtance. But this is by no means a neeeſſary conſequence. Even if the water ſſiould be allowed to exert equal preſſures on them, the preſſures being perpendicular to their ſurfaces, and theſe ſurfaces being inclined to the axis, while in the caſe of the baſe of a cylinder it is in tl⅜e direction of the axis, there muſt be a difference in</p><lb/><p>the accumulated or compound preſſure in the direction of the axis. He indeed ſays, that in the caſe of the cylinder or the circle obſtructing the canal, a quantity of water remains ſtagnant on its upper ſurface ; viz. all the water whoſe motion would not contribute to the moſt ready paſſage of the ſiuid between the cy-liuder and the ſides of the canal or tube ; and that this water may be conſidered as frozen. If this be the caſe, it is indifferent what is the form of the body that is covered with this maſs of frozen or ſtagnant water. It may be a bemiſphere or a cone ; the reſiſtance will be the ſame. -But Newton by no means aſſigns, ei-ther with preciſion or with diſtinct evidence, the form and magnitude of this ſtagnant water, ſo as to give con-ſidence in the reſults. He contents himſelf with iay-ing, that it is that water whoſe motion is not neceſſary or cannot contribute to the moſt eaſy paſſage of the water.</p><p>i here remains, therefore, many imperfections in this theory. But notwithſtanding theſe defects, we cannot but admire the efforts and ſagacity of this great philoſopher, who, after having difcovered ſo many ſublime truths of mechanical nature, ventured to trace out a path for the folution of a pr⅛blem which no perſon had yet attempted to bring within the range of mathematical inveſtigation. And his folution, though inac-curate, ihines throughout with that inventive genius and that fertility of refource, which no man ever poſ-ſeſſed in ſo eminent a degree.</p><p>Tlroſe who have attacked the folution of Sir Iſaac Newton have not been more ſucceſsful. Moſt of them, inſtead of principles, have given a great deal of calculus’; and the chief merit which any of them can claim, is that of having deduced ſome ſingle propoſition whiclt. happens to quadrate with fome <hi rend="sup">l</hi>- ſingle caſe of experiment, while their general theories are either inapplicable, from difficulty and obfcurity, or are diſcordant with more general obfervation.</p><p>we muſt, however, except from this number Daniel Bernoulli, who was not only a great geometer, but one of the ſirſt philoſophers of the age. He poſſeſſed all the talents, and was free from the faults of that celebrated family ; and while he was the mathematician of Europe who penetrated fartheſt in the inveftigation of this great problem, he was the only perfon who felt, or at leaſt who acknowledged, its great difficulty.</p><p>In the 2d volume of the <hi rend="italic">Comment. Petropol.</hi>  1727, he propoſes a formula for the reſiſtance of fluids, de-duced from conſiderations quite different from thoſe on which Newton founded his folution. But he delivers it with modeſt diffidence; becauſe he found that it gave a reſiſtance four times greater than experiment. In the ſame differtation he determines the reſiſtance of a ſphere to be one half of that of its great circle. But in his ſubiequent theory . of Hydrodynamics (a work which muſt ever rank among the ſirſt productions of the age, and is equally eminent for refined and elegant mathematics, and ingenious and original thoughts in dynamics), he calls this determination in queſtion. It is indeed founded on the fame hypothetical principles which have been unſkilfully detached from the reſt of Newton’s phyſics, and made the ground-work of all the ſubſequent theories on this ſubject.</p><p>In 1741 Mr Daniel Bernoulli publiſhed another diſ-</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>