<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>cd to the king, by their ſpeaker Sir Thomas Audley, of thele reflections thrown out againſt them ; and the. biſhop was obliged to retract his words.</p><p>Though Henry had not the leaſt idea of rejecting any, even of the moſt abſurd Romiſh ſuperſtitions, yet as the oppreſſions of the clergy ſuited very ill with the violence of his own temper, he was pleaſed with every opportunity of leffening their power. In the parliament of 1531, he ſhowed his deſign of humbling the clergy in the moſt effectual manner. An obſolete ſtatute was revived, from which it was pretended that it was criminal to ſubmit to the legatine power which had been exerciſed by cardinal wolſey. By this ftroke the whole body of clergy was declared guilty at once. They were too well acquainted with Henry’s diſpoſition, however, to reply, that their ruin would have been the certain conſequence of their not ſubmitting to wolſey’s commiſſion which had been given by royal authority. Inſtead of making any defence of this kind, they choſe to throw themſelves on the mercy of their ſovereign ; whieh, however, it coil them 118,8401. to procure. A confeſſion was likewife extorted from them, that the king was protector and ſupreme head of the church of England ; though ſome of them had the dexterity to get a clauſe inferted, which invalidated the whole ſubmiſſion, viz. <hi rend="italic">in Jo far as is permitted by the law of Chrifl.</hi></p><p>The king, having thus begun to reduce the power of the clergy, kept no bounds with them,afterwards. He did not indeed attempt any reformation in religious matters ; nay, he perſecuted moſt violently ſuch as did attempt this in the leaſt. Indeed, the moſt effential article of his creed ſeems to have been his own ſupre-macy ; for whoever denied this, was ſure to ſuffer the moſt ſevere penalties, whether Proteſtant or Papiſt. But an account of the abſurd and cruel conduct of this prince, and of his final quarrel with the pope on aecount of his refuſing a diſpenſation to marry Anne Bo-leyn, is given under the article England, n<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 253— 292.</p><p>He died in 1547, aud was ſucceeded by his only ſon Edward VI. This amiable prince, whofe early youth was crowned with that wiſdom, ſagacity, and virtue, that would have done honour to advanced years, ,gave new ſpirit and vigour to the Proteſtant cauſe, and was its brighteſt ornament, as weſt as its moſt effectual ſupport. He encouraged learned and pious men cf foreign countries to fettle in England, and addreſ-ſed a particular invitation to Martin Bucer and Paul Fagius, whoſe moderation added a luſtre to their other virtues, that, by the miniſtry and labours of theſe eminent men, in concert with thoſe of the friends of the Reformation in England, he might purge his domi-nions from the fordid fictions of popery, and eſtabliſh the pure doctrines of Chriſtianity in their place. For this purpoſe, he iffued out the wiſeſt orders for the reſtoration of true religion; but his reign was too ſhort to accompliſh fully ſuch a glorious purpoſe. In the year 1553, he was taken from hrs loving and afflicted -ſubjects, whoſe ſorrow was inexpreſſihle, and ſuited to their loſs. His filter Mary (the daughter of Catharine of Arragon, from whom Henry had been ſeparated by the famous divorce), a furious bigot to the elιurch of Rome, and a prîncefs whoſe natural character, like the ſpirit of her religion, was deſpotic and cruel, ſucceeded him on the Britiſh throne, and impoſed anew the arbitrary laws and the tyrannical yoke of Rome upon the people of England. Nor were the methods ſhe employed in the eauſe of ſuperſtition better than the cauſe itſelf', or tempered by any ſentiments of equity or com-. paſſion. Barbarous tortures and death, in the moſt ſhocking forms, awaited thoſe who oppofed her will, or made the leaſt ſtand againſt the reſtoration of Popery. And among many other victims, the learned and pious Cranmer, archbi(hop of Canterbury, who had been one <hi rend="italic">ot</hi>  the moſt iſtuſtrious inſtruments of the Reformation in England, fell a ſacriſice to her ſury. This odious ſcene of perſecution was happily concluded in the year 1558, by the death of the queen, who left no iffιιe ; and, as ſoon as her ſucceiſor the lady Elizabeth aſcended the throne, all things affumed a new and a plealin-∕ afpect. This iſtuſtrious princeſs, whoſe fentiments°, counſels, and projects, breathed a ſpirit ſuperior to the natural ſoftneſs and delicacy of her ſex, exerted this vigorous and manly ſpirit in the defence of oppreffed conſcience and expiring liberty, broke anew the de-ſpotic yoke of Papal authority and ſuperſtition, and, delivering her people from the bondage of Rome, eſtabliſhed that form of religious doctrine and eccleſiaſtical government which ſtill ſubſiſts in England. This religious eſtabliſhment differs, in ſome reſpects, from the plan that had been formed by thoſe whom Edward VI. had employed for promoting the cauſe of the Reforma-<hi rend="sub">v</hi></p><p>tion, and approaches nearer to the rites and diſcipline " of former.times ; though it is widely different, and, in the moſt important points, entirely oppoſite to the principles of the Roman hierarchy. See England, n<hi rend="sup">0</hi> 293., &amp;c.</p><p>The cauſe of the reformation underwent in Ireland the ſame viciſſitudes and revolutions that had attended it in England, when Henry VHL after the abolition of tlie Papal authority, was declared ſupreme head upon eaιtiι of the church of England, George Brown, a native of England, and a monk of the Auguſtine order, whom that monarch had created, in the year 1535, archbiſhop of Dublin, began to act with the utmoſt vigour in conſequence of this change in the hierarchy. He purged the churches of his dioceſe from ſuperſtition in all its various forms, pulled down images, deſtroyed relics, aboliſhed abſurd and idolatrous rites, and, by the influence as weſt as authority he had in Ireland, cauſed the king’s ſupremacy to be acknowledged in that nation. Henry ſhowed, ſoon after, that this ſupremacy was not a vain title ; for he baniſhed the monks out of that kingdom, connſcated their revenues, and deſtroyed their couvents. In the reign of Edward VI. ſtſtl farther progreſs was made in the removal of Popiſh ſuperſtitions, by the. zealous labours of biſhop Brown, and the aufpicious encouragement he granted to all who exerted themſelves in the cauſe of the Reformation. But the death of this excellent prince, and the acceſſion of queen Mary, had like to have changed the face of affairs in Ireland as much as in, England ; but her deligns were difappointed by a very curious adventure, of which the following account has been copied from the papers of Richard earl of Cυrke.</p><p>" Queen Mary having dealt ſeverely with the Proteſtants in England, about the latter end of her reign ſigned a commiſſion for to take the ſame courſe with them in Ireland ; and to execute the fame with greater force, ſhe nominates Dr Cole one of the commiſſioners. This Doctor coming, with the commiſſion, to Cheſter</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>