<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>people incapable of inſtruction, and ripe for the greateſt</p><p>miſeries in which we may be involved.</p><p>REVULSION, in medicine, turning a flux of humours from one part to another by bleeding, cupping, friction, ſinapiſms, bliſters, fomentations, bathings, iſſues, fetons, ſtrong purging of the bowels, &amp;c.</p><p>REYN (Jan de), an eminent hiſtory and portrait painter, born at Dunkirk in 1610. He had the good fortune to be a diſciple of Vandyke, was the ſirſt performer, in his ſohool, and was ſo attached to his mailer that he followed him to London, where it is thought he continued as long as he lived. In fheſe ^kingdoms he is moſtly known by the name of <hi rend="italic">Lang Jan.</hi>  He died in 1678 : and it is imagined that the ſcarcity of his works is occaſioned by ſo many of them being imputed to Vandyke ; a circumſtance which, .if true, is beyond any tiling that could be ſaid in his •praiſe.</p><p>REYNOLDS (Sir Joſhua), the celebrated painter, was, on July the 16th 1723, bom at Plympton, a fmall town in Devonſhire. His father was miniſter of the pariſh, and alſo maſter of the grammar ſchool ; and being a man of learning and philanthropy, he was be-ſoved and reſpected by all to whom he was known.— Such a man, it will naturally be ſuppofed, was affiduous in the cultivation of the minds of his children, among whom his ſon Joſhua ſhonc conſpicuous, by displaying at a very early period a ſuperiority of genius, and the rudiments of a correct taſte. Unlike other boys, who generally content themſelves with giving a literal explanation of their author, regardleſs of his beauties or his faults, young Reynolds attended to both theſe, difplaying a happy knowledge of what he read^ and entering with ardour into the ſpirit of his author. He diſcovered likewiſe talents for compoſition, and a natural propenſity to drawing, in which his friends and intimates thought him qualified to excel. Emulation was a diſtinguiſhing feature in his mind, wliich his father perceived with the delight natural to a parent ; and deſigning him for the church, in which he hoped that his talents might raife him to eminence, he ſent him to one of the univerſities.</p><p>Soon after this period he grew paffionately fond of painting ; and, by the peruſal of Richardſon’s theory of that art, was determined to make it his profeffion through life. At his own earneſt requeſt, therefore, he was removed to London ; and about the year 1742 be-came a pupil to Mr Hudſon, who, though not himſelf an eminent painter was preceptor to ſeverals who afterwards excelled in the art. One of the ſirſt advices which he gave to Mr Reynolds was to copy carefully Guercino’s drawings. This was done with ſuch ſkill,</p><p>that many of the copies are ſaid to be now preſerved in the cabinets of the curious as the originals of that very great maſter.</p><p>About the year 174.9, Mr IReynolds went to Italy -under the auſpices, and in the company, of the late JLord (then Commodore) Keppel, who was appointed to the command of the .Britiſh ſquadron in the Medi-terranean. in this garden of the world, this magic feat of the arts, he failed not to viſit the fchools of the great maſters, to ſtudy the productions of different ages, and to contemplate with unwearied attention the various beauties which are characteriſtic <hi rend="italic">ei</hi>  each. His labour here, as has been obſerved of another painter, was " the labour of love, not the taſk of the hireling and how much he profited by it is .known to all Europe.</p><p>Having remained about two years in Italy, and ſta-died the language as well as the arts of the country with great ſucceſs, he returned to England, improved by travel and refined bÿ education. On the road to London from the port where he landed, he accidentally found in the inn where he lodged Johnſon’s life oſ Sa-vage ; and was ſo taken with the charms of compoſi-tion, and the maſterly delineation of character diſplay--ed in that performance, that, having begun tp read it while leaning with his arm on the chimney-piece, he continued in that attitude inſenſible of pain till he was hardly able to raiſe his hand to his head. The admiration of the work naturaliy led him to ſeek the acquaintance of its author·, who continued one of his ſincereſt admirers and warmeſt friends, till 1784, when they were ſeparated by the ſtroke of death.</p><p>The firſt thing that diſtinguiſhed him aſter his return to his native country, was a full length portrait of Commodore Keppel ; which in the polite circles was ſpoken of in terms of the higheſt encomium, and tef-tified to what a degree of eminence he had arrived in his profeffion. This was followed by a portrait of Lord Edgecombe, and a few others, which at once introduced him to the firſt buſineſs in portrait painting » and that branch of the art he cultivated with ſuch ſuccefs as will for ever eſtabliſh his fame with all deſcrip-tions of reſined ſociety. Having painted ſome of the ſirſt-rate beauties of the age, the polite world flocked to ſee the graces and the charms of his pencil ; and he ſoon became the moſt faſhionable painter, not only ſu England, but in all Europe. He has indeed preſerved the refemblance of ſo many illuſtrious characters, that we feel the leſs regret for his having left behind him ſo ſc<hi rend="sub">w </hi>hiſtorical paintings ; though what he has done in that way ſhows @@(a) him to have been qualified to excel in both departments. The only landſcape, perhaps, which</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">@@@(a) As the lovers of painting may wiſh to have a catalogue of this great maſter’s hiſtorical pieces, we ſubjoin the following from the European Magazine, which we have good reaſon to believe accurate, as the editors of that mifcellany grudge neither trouble nor expence to procure authentic information. Sir Joſhua’s principal hi-ſtorical pieces, then, are the following : Hope nttrſing Love ; Venus chaſtiſing Cupid for having learned to caſt accounts; Count Ugolino in the dungeon ; the calling of Samuel; Ariadne; a Captain of banditti; Beggar Boy ; a Lady in the character of St /Agnes; Thais; Dionyſius the Areopagite; an infant Jupiter; Maſter Crewe in the character of Henry VIII ; the death of Dido ; a Child aſleep ; Cupid ſſeeping ; Covent Garden Cupid ; Cupid in the Clouds; Cupids painting ; Boy laughing.; Maſter Herbert in the character of Bacchus ; Hebe ; Miſs Meyer in the character ef Hebe ; Madona, a head ; the Black-guard Mercury ; a little boy (Sa-spuel) praying j and old Man reading ; Love looſing the zonç ef Beauty ; the Children in the Wood j Cleo-</hi></p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>