<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>his dominion®. But with his ſucceſſor it was otherwiſe ; for he, convinced that Luther’s doctrine muſt ſoon be totally deſtroyed and ſuppreſſed unleſs it received a ſpeedy and effectual ſupport, ordered Luther and Melancthon to draw up a body of laws relating to the form of eccleſiaſtical government, the method of public worſhip, &amp;c. which was to be proclaimed by heralds throughout his dominions. This example was followed by all the -princes and ſtates of Germany who renounced tlie papal ſupremacy ; and a like form of worſhip, diſcipline, and government, was thus introduced into all the churches ’which di(Γented from that of Rome. This open renun-ciation of the Romiſh juriſdiction ſoon changed the face of affairs ; and the patrons of Popery ſoon intimated, in a manner not at all ambiguous, that they intended to make war on th¢ Lutheran party ; which would certainly have been put in execution, had not the trou-bles that took place in Europe diſconcerted their mea-fures. Οη the other hand, the Lutherans, apprized of theſe hoſtile intentions, began alſo to deliberate on a proper plan of defence againſt that fuperſtitious violence with which they were in danger of being aſſailed. The diet of the empire aſſembled at Spire, in the year 1526; where the emperor’s ambaſſadors were deſired to uſe their utmoſt endeavours to ſuppreſs all diſputes about religion, and to inſiſt upon the rigorous execution of the ientence which had been pronounced againſt Luther and his followers at worms. The greateſt part of the German princes oppoſed this motion with the ut-moſt refolution, declaring that they could not cxecute that ſentence, nor come to any determination with regard to the doctrines by which it had been occaſioned, Before the whole matter was ſubmitted to the decifion of a council lawfully aſſembled ; alleging farther, that tke deciſion of controverſies of this nature belonged properly to it, and to it alone. This opinion, after long and very warm debates, was adopted by a great majority, and at length confented to by the whole aſſembly: for it was unanimouſly agreed to preſent a ſolemn ad-tlrefs to the emperor, intreating him to aſſemble, without delay, a free and general council ; while in the mean time it was alſo agreed, that the princes of the empire ſhould, in their reſpective dominions, be at liberty to manage eccleſiaſtical affairs in the manner they ſhould think moſt proper ; yet ſo as to be able to give to God and the emperor a proper account of their adminiſtra-tion when it ſhould be required of them.</p><p>Theſe reſolutions proved extremely favourable to the cauſe of reformation ; neither had the emperor any lei-ſure for fome time to give diſturbance to the reformed. The war, which at this time enſued between him and the pope, gave the greateſt advantage to the friends of the reformed, and conſiderably augmented their number. Several princes, whom the fear of perſecution and puniſhment had hitherto prevented from lending their affiſtance, publicly renounced the Romiſh ſuperſtſtion, and introduced among their ſubjects the ſame forms of religious worſhip, and the ſame lyſtem of doctrine, that had been received in Saxony, others, though placed in ſuch circumſtances as diſcouraged them from acting in an open manner againſt the intereſts of the Roman pontiff, were, however, far from diſcovering the ſmalleſt oppoſition to thoſe who withdrew the people from his deſpotic yoke ; nor did they moleſt the private aſſem-blies of thoſe who had ſeparated themſelves from the</p><lb/><p>church of Rome. And in general, all the Germans who, before theſe 1efolutions of the diet of Spire, had rejected the papal difcipline and doctrine, were now, in conſequencc of the libcrty they enjoyed, wholly employed in bringing their fchemes and plans to a certain de-gree of confidence, and in adding vigour and firmneſs to the cauſe in which they were engaged. But this tranquillity and liberty was of no long duration. In 1529, a new diet was aſſembled at the ſame place by the emperor, after he had quieted the troubles in various parts of his dominions, and concluded a peace with the pope. The power which had been granted to princes of managing eccleſiaſtical affairs till the meeting of a general council, was now revoked by a majority of votes ; and every change declared unlawful that ſhould be introduced into the doctrine, diſcipline, or worſhip of the eſtabliſhed religion, before the determination of the approaching council was known. This decree was conſidered as iniquitous and intolerable by the elector of Saxony, the landgrave of Heſſe, and other members oſ the diet, who were perſuaded of the neceffity of a reformation. The promiſe of ſpeedily aſſembling a <hi rend="italic">general</hi>  council, they looked upon to be an artifice of the church of Rome ; well knowing, that a free and lawful council would be the Iaſt thing to which the pope would conſent. when, therefore, they found that all their arguments and remonſtrances made no impreffion upon Ferdinand the emperor’s brother, who preſided in the diet, Charles himſelf being then at Barcelona, they entered a ſolcmn proteſt againſt this decree on the 19th of April, and appealed to the emperor and a future council. Hence aroſe the denomination of <hi rend="italic">Protfiαnts, </hi>which from this period has been given to thoſe who ſeparate from the communion of the church of Rome. The princes of the empire who entered this proteſt were, John elector of Saxony; George elector of Bran-denburg ; Erneſt and Francis dukes of Lunenburgh ; the landgrave of Heſſe ; and the prince of Anhalt. Theſe were ſeconded by 13 imperial towns, viz. Straf-burg, U'lm, Nuremberg, Conſtance, Rottingen, wind-ſeim, Memmiπgen, Nortlingen, Lindaw, Kempton, Htilbron, wiſſemburg, and St Gall.</p><p>The diſſenting princes, who were the protectors and heads of the reformed churches, had no ſooner entered their proteſt, than they fent proper perfons to the em-peror, who was then upon h13 paſſage from Spain to Italy, to acquaint him with their proceedings irf this matter. The miniſters employed in this commiſſion executed it with the greateſt intrepidity and prefence of mind ; but the emperor, exaſperated at the audacity of thoſe who prefumed to differ from him, cauſed the ambaſſadors to be arreſted. The news of this violent ſtep made the Proteſtant princes conclude, that their perſon-al ſafety, and the ſuccefs of their cauſe, depended entirely upon their own courage and union. They de-termined, therefore, to enter into a ſolemn confederacy: ſor which purpoſe they held ſeveral meetings at Rot, Nuremberg, Smalcald, and other places : but ſo different were their opinions and views, that they could determine upon nothing.</p><p>o∏e great obſtacle to the intended confederacy was the diſpute which had anſen between Luther and Zuinglius concerning the real preſence of Chriſt in the Lord’s Supper. To terminate this difpute, if poſſible, Philip, landgrave of Heffe, invited, in the year 1529, tβ</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>