<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ſtegc of L andre cies; 15,000 Britiſh and 15,000 Auſtri-ans, commanded by the duke of York and general Otto, encamped towards Cambray. The emperor and the prince of Saxe-Cobourg, at the head of 60,000 Auf-trians, were advanced as ſar as Guiſe ; 12,000 Heffi-ans and Auſtrians under general worms were ſtationed near Douay and Bouchain ; Count Kaunitz with 15,000 Auſtrians defended the Sambre and the quarter near Maubeuge ; and, laſtly, general Clairfait, with 40,000 Auſtrians and Hanoverians, protected Flanders from Tournay to the ſea ; 60,000 Pruffians, for whom a ſubſidy had been paid by Great Britain, were expect-ed in addition to thefe, but they never arrived.</p><p>The French now commenced their active operations. On the morning of the 26th of April they attacked the duke of York near Cateau in great force. After a ſevere conflict they were repulſed, and their general Chapuy was taken priſoner. At the ſame time they attacked the troops under his Imperial majeſty, but were there alſo repulſed in a ſimilar manner; loſing in all 57 pieces of cannon. On the ſame day, however, general Pichegru advanced from Liſſe, attacked and defeated general Clairfait, took 32 pieces of cannon; and, in the conrſe of a few days, made himſelf maſter of Warwick, Menin, and Courtray, On the 29th of April, the garrifon of Landrecies ſurrendered to the allies. when this event was known in the convention,</p><p>. it excited a conſiderable degree of alarm. It was, however, the laſt effectual piece of ſucceſs enjoyed by the allies during this diſaſtrous campaign. General Clairfait was again completely defeated by Pichegru in a general engagement ; and it was found neceffary to ſend the duke of York to his affiſtance. This move-ment was no doubt unavoidable ; but the effect of it was, that it ſplit down tlie allied army into a variety of portions, capable of carrying on a defultory war-fare, but unfit ſor the vigorous objects of conqueſt. On tlie 10th the duke of York was attacked near Tournay by a body of tlie enemy, whom he repulſed ; but he was unable to join Clairfaſt, upon whoſe de-ſtruction the French were chiefly bent : for at thc ſame time that the duke of York was occupied by the attack upon himſeff, Pichegru fell upon Clairfait with filch irreſiſtible impetuoſity, that he was compelled to retreat in confuſion, and a part of his army appears to have fled to the neighbourhood of Bruges, while Pichegru was thus advancing ſucceſsſully in weſt Flan-dere, general jourdan advanced in Eaſt Elanders from Maubeuge, croſſed the Sambre, and forced general Kaunitz to retreat. On the 18th, however, general Kaunitz ſucceedfed in repuiſing the enemy in his turn, and they re-croſſed the Sambre with conſiderable loſs.</p><p>The allies now found that no progreſs could be made in France while general Pichegru was advancing ſuccefs-fully and occupying weft Flanders in their rear. The emperor, therefore, withdrew the greater part of his army to the neighbourhood of Tournay, and reſolved to make a grand effort to cut oſſ the communication between Courtray and Liſle, thus to prevent complete-ly the retreat of Pichegru. On the night of the 16th, the army moved forwards in five columns for this purpoſe. Clairfait was at the ſame time directed, to crofs the Lys, to effect a general junction, if poffible, and complete the plan. The attempt during that evening Äeemed to promiſe ſucceſs ; but, in the courſe of ncxt</p><p>day, the diviſion under the duke of York was Over-powered by numbers and defeated. The progreſs of the reſt of the columns was ſtopped, and Clairfaſt completely defeated. In the confuſion of the day, when attempting to rally the different parts of the di-viſion which he commanded, the duke of York was ſeparated from his own troops by a party of the enemy’s cavalry, and only eſcaped being made priſoner by the ſwiftnefs of his horſe. The plan of the allies being thus fruſtrated, their army withdrew to the neighbour« hood of Tournay.</p><p>Pichegru ſpeedily attempted to retaliate againſt the allies. On the 22d of May he brought down at day break his whole force againſt them. The attack was commenced by a heavy ſire of artillery, and all the ad-vanced poſts were forced. The engagement ſoon became general; the attacks were repeatedly renewed on both ſides ; the whole day was ſpent in a ſucceſ-ſion of obſtinate battles. All that military /kill could do was performed on both ſides. The French and the allied ſoldiers fought with equal courage and equal diſcipline. At nine o’clock in tlie evening the French at laſt reluctantly withdrew from the attack.</p><p>Ί he day on which a vanquiſhed enemy flies from the field is not âlways that on which the victory is won. In this engagement the French were unſucceſsſul in their immediate objects; but the weight of their ſire, their ſteady difcipline, and their violent obſtinacy of attack, raiſed their military character high in the eſti-mation of the officers and ſoldiers of the allied army. It was ſoon perceived, that in addition to theſe they poſſeſſed other advantages. Their numbers were im-menſe ; they implicitly obeyed their generals ; who,</p><p>being men newly raiſed from the rank of ſubalterns, as implicitly ſubmitted to the directions of the com-mitte of public ſafety. A combination of efforts was thus produced whoſe operation vvas not retarded by divided counſels. On the other ſide, the numbers of the allies were daily declining ; them leaders were independent princes or powerful men, whoſe ſentiments and intereſts were often very hoſtile to each other, and their exertions were conſequently diſunited.</p><p>Ou the 24th the French again croſſed the Sambre, but were driven back with much loſs. On the 27th an attempt was made to beſiege Charleroi, but the prince of Orange on the 3d of June compelled them to raiſe the liege. On the 12th a ſimilar attempt was made, and they were again repulſed. In weft Flanders, however, Pichegru was ſufficiently ſlrong to com* mence the liege of Ypres. He was ſoon attacked by general Clairfait for the purpoſe of relieving it, but without ſucceſs.—Ypres was garrifoned by 7000 men ; reinforcements were therefore daily ſent from the grand army to Clairfait for the purpoſe of relieving it. It is unneceſſary to, mention the bloody conteſts ſu which that unfortunate general was daily engaged with thc French ; it is fufficient to ſay, that they were uni-forraly unſucceſsful, and were the means of wafting, in a great degree, the armies of the allies. Ypres held out till the 17th of June, when it capitulated: and ſuch was the difcipline of the French army at this time, that no notice could be obtained, for ſeveral days, of that event. In conſequence of it and of other events, the duke of York found it neceffary to retreat to Oude-narde j for Jourdan, after ftorming the Auſtrian camp</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>