<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>which its occaſional inflexions, either above or below, may in ſome refpect9 be conceived to have a reference, like that which common muſic has to its key-note. Yet there is this difference between the two kinds of modulation, that whereas the ſirſt always concludes in the key-note, the other frequently concludes a tittle below it (f). This key-note, in fpeaking, is generally the found given at the outſet of every complete ſentence or period; and it may be obſerved on ſome occa-ſions to vary its pitch through the limits of a muſical interval of a conſiderable magnitude. The tones, that fall a little lower than the key at the cloſe of a ſentence or period, are called <hi rend="italic">cadenies.</hi>  Theſe cadences, if we are accurate in our diſtinctions, will, with reſpect to their offices, be found of two kinds ; though they meet ſo frequently together, that ſt may be beſt to conceive them only as anſwerihg a double purpoſe. Οηε of theſe offices is to aſſiſt the fenſe, and the other to decorate the modulation. An account of the firſt may be ſeen in the ſection on <hi rend="italic">Pauſes ;</hi>  and the latter will be found "to ſhow itſelf pretty frequently in every thing grave and plaintive, or in poetic deſcription and other highly ornamented language, where the mind is by its influ-ence brought to feel a placid kind of dignity and ſatisſaction. Thefe two cadences, therefore, may be conveniently diſtinguiſhed by applying to them reſpective-ly the epithets<hi rend="italic">fignficaηt</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">ornamental.</hi></p><p>we have already obſerved, that reading ſhould in ſome things differ from ſpeaking ; and the particular under conſideration ſeems to be one rvhich ought to va-ry a little in theſe arts. For,</p><p>Modulation in reading ſerves a'twofold purpoſe. At the ſame time that it gives pleaſure to the ear on the principles of harmony, it contributes through that medium to preferve the attention. And ſince written lan-guage (when not purely dramatical) is in general more elegant in its conſtruction, and muſical in its periods, than the oral one ; and ſince many intereſting particulars are wanting in reading, which are preſent in ſpeak-ing, that contribute greatly to fix the regard oſ the hearer ; it ſeems reaſonable, in order to do juſtice to the language, and in part to ſupply the incitements oſ attention juſt alluded to, that in the former of theſe two articles a modulation ſhould be uſed ſomething more harmonious and artificial than in the latter. Agreeably to this reaſoniug, it is believed, we ſhall find every reader, on a narrow examination, adopt more or leſs a mo-dulation thus ornamented : though, aſter all, it muſt be acknowledged there arc better grounds to believe, that the practice has been hitherto directed intuitively by nature, than that it was diſcovered by the inductions of reaſon. we ſhall conclude this head with a rule for mo-.dulation in reading. “ In every thing dramatic, colloquial, or of ſimple narrative, let your modulation be the ſame as in ſpeaking ; but when the ſubject is flowery, ſolemn, or dignified, add ſomething to its harmony,</p><p>diverſify the Jcey-note, and increaſc the frequency of cadences in proportion to the merit of the compofi tion.”</p><p>It will readily be ſeen, that the precepts here drawn from a compariſon between ſpeaking and reading, would be very inadequate, were they left deſtitute ol the aſſiſtance of <hi rend="italic">tafie,</hi>  and the opportunity of <hi rend="italic">frequently hearing and imitating mafierly readers.</hi>  And indeed, to theſe two great auxiliaries we might very properly have referred the whole matter at once, as capable of giving ſufficient directions, had we not remembered that our plan required us to found ſeveral of our rules as much on the principles of a philofophical analyſis, as on thoſe more familiar ones which will be found of greater efficacy in real practice.</p><p>IV. <hi rend="italic">Expreſfion.</hi>  i. There is no compoſition in muſic, however perfect as to key and melody, but, in order to do juſtice to the fubject and ideas of the author, will require, in the performing, ſomething more than an exact adherence to <hi rend="italic">tune</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">time.</hi>  This ſomething is of a nature, too, which perhaps can never be ade-quately pointed out by any thing graphic, and reſults entirely from the taſte and feeling of the performer. It is that which chiefly gives muſic its power over the paſſions, and characteriſes its notes with what we mean by the words <hi rend="italic">ſweet, harſh, dull, lively, plaintive, joyous,</hi>  &amp;c. for it is evident every found, conſidered ab-ſtractedly, without any regard to the movement, or high and low, may be thus modified. Tn practical muſic, this commanding particular is called <hi rend="italic">Exprejfioη ;</hi>  and as we ſind certain tones analogous to it frequently coa-leſcing with the modulation of the voice, which indi-eate our paffions and affections (thereby more particu-larly pointing out the meaning of what we ſay), the term is uſually applied in the fame fenſe to ſpeaking and reading.</p><p>Theſe tones are not altogether peculiar to man.— Every animal, that is not dumb, has a power of making ſeveral of them. And from their being able, un-affiſted by words, to manifeſt and raife their kindred emotions, they conſtitute a kind of language of them-ſelves. In this language of the heart man is eminently converſant ; for we not only underſtand it in one another, but alſo in many of the inferior creatures ſubject-ed by providence to our fervice.</p><p>The expreffion here illuſtrated is one of the moſt eſſential articles in good reading, ſince it not only gives a ſiniſhing to the ſenſe, but, on the principles of ſympa-thy and antipathy, has alſo a peculiar efficacy in intereſting the heart. It is likewiſe an article of moſt difficult attainment ; as it appears from what follows, that a maſterly reader ought not only to be able to incorporate it with the modulation properly as to <hi rend="italic">quality, </hi>but in any degree as to <hi rend="italic">quantity.</hi></p><p>Every thing written being a proper imitation of ſpeech, expreſſive reading muſt occafionally partake of</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">(f)</hi>  As muſical founds have always an harmonica! reference to a key or fundamental note, and to which the mind is ſtill ſecretly attending, no piece of muſic would appear perfect, that did not cloie in it, and ſo naturally put an end to expectation. But as the tones uſed in ſpeech are not muſical, and therefore cannot refer harmonically to any other found, there can be no neceffity that this terminating found (and which we immediately below term the <hi rend="italic">cadence)</hi>  ſhould either be uſed at all, or follow any particular law as to form, &amp;c. farther than what</p><p>impoſcd by taſte and cuſtom.</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>