<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>mnndhig his freight in a furly tone, and an uxorious monarch, are objects too familiar and ludicrous not to degrade the dignity of thoſe awful ſcenes which are repreſented as the manſions of the dead, and to prevent them from making a deep enough impreffion on the imagination. The actions and qualities, too, for which departed fpirits were admitted into Elyſium, or doomed to the regions of fijſſering, were not always of ſuch a nature as under a well-regulated government on earth would have been thought to merit reward, or to be worthy of puniſhment. It was not always virtue or wiſdom which conducted to the Elyſian fields, or gained admiſſion into the fociety of the immortal gods.— Ganimede was for a very different reaſon promoted to be the cup-bearer oſ Jove ; and Hercules and Bacchus could not finely plead that any merits of that kind entitled them to feats in the council, and at the banquets of the immortals. That doctrine, likewife, which repreſented mortals ns hurried by fate to the commiſſion of crimes, which they could no more abſtain from committing than the ſword can avoid to obey the impulſe of a powerful and furious arm plunging it into the breaſt of an unreſiſting antagυnift, could not but produce effects unfavourable to virtue ; and it afforded a ready excuſe for the moſt extravagant crimes.</p><p>Ύ ct, after all, he who attentively conſiders the ideas of the Greeks and Romans concerning the moral government of the world and a future ſtate of rewards and puniſhments, will probably acknowledge, that their general influence muſt have been favourable to virtue and moral order. Allow them to have been incorrect and daſhed with abſurdity ; ſtill they repreſent puniſhments prepared for ſuch qualities and actions as were injurious to the welfare of ſociety ; whilſt, for thoſe qualities which rendered men eminently ufefùl in the world, they hold forth a reward. Though incorrect, their ideas concerning a future ſtate were exceedingly diſtinct ; they were not vague or general, but ſuch as might be readi-Iy conceived by the imagination, in all their circumftances, as really exiſting. when a man is told that for ſuch a deed he will be put to death, he may ſhud--&lt;ier and be alarmed, and think of the deed as what he jrtuſt by no means commit ; but place before him the ſcene and the apparatus for his execution, call him to behold ſome other criminal mounting the ſcaffold, ad-βheffing his laſt words in a wild ſcream of defpair to the ſurrounding ſpectators, and then launching into eternity—his horror of the crime, and his dread of the puniſhment, will now be much more powerfully excited. In the ſame manner, to encourage the ſoldier marching cut te battle, or the mariner fetting ſail under the proſpect of a ſtorm, promiſ¢ not, merely in general terms, a liberal reward ; be ſure to ſpecify the nature of the reward which you mean to beſtow; deſcribe it ſo as that it may take hold on the imagination, and may riſe in oppoſition to the images of death and danger with which his courage is to be aſſailed.</p><p>If thefe phenomena of die human mind are fairly ftated, if it be true that general ideas produce no very powerful effects oa the fentimentβ and diſpoſitions of the human heart, it muſt then be granted, that though the ſcenes of future reward and puniſhment, which the heathens conſidered as prepared for the righteous and the wicked, were of a ſomewhat motley complexion ; yet ſtill, as they were diſtinct and even minute draughts,</p><p>they muſt have been favbtιrable to virtue, and contribu-ted in no inconfiderable degree to the fupport of civil order.</p><p>Another thing of which we may take notice under this head, is the vaſt multiplicity of deities with which the Greek and Roman mythology peopled all the <hi rend="italic">regions</hi>  of nature. Flocks and fields, and woods and oaks, and flowers, and many much more minute objects, had all their guardian deities. Tlieſe were ſomewhat capricious at times, it is true, and expected to have attention paid them. But yet the faithful ſhepherd, and the induſtrious farmer, knew generally how to acquire their friendſhip ; and in the idea of deities enjoying the ſame ſimple pleaſures, partaking in the ſame labours, protecting their poſſeſſions, and bringing forward the fruits of the year, there could not but be fomething of a very pleating nature, highly favourable to induſtry, which would animate the labours, and cheer the feſtivals, of the good people who entertained ſuch a notion ; nay, would diſſuſe a new charm over all the fcene6 of the country, even in the gayeſt months of the year.</p><p>From all of theſe particular obfervations, we think ourſelves warranted to conclude, that notwithſtanding the mixed characters of the deities who were adored by the celebrated nations of antiquity ; though they are in many inſtances repreſented as conſpicuous for vices and frolics ; however vain, abfurd, and morally criminal, ſome of the rites by which they were worſhipped may have been, and however incorrect the notions of the heathens concerning the moral government of the univerſe and a future ſtate of retribution ; yet ſtill, after making a juſt allowance for all theſe imperfections, the general influence of their religious ſyſtem was rather favourable thaπ unfavourable to virtue and to the order and happineſs of fociety.</p><p>It was not without good reaſon that the earlieſt legiſlators generally endeavoured to eſtabliſh their laws and conſtitutions on the baſis of religion ; government needs the ſupport of opinion ; the governed muſt be im-preſſed with a belief that the particular eſtabliſhment to whieh they are required to ſubmit, is tbe beſt calculated for their ſecurity and happineſs, or is ſupported on ſome ſuch ſolid foundation, that it muſt prove,im-poſſible for them to overturn it, or is connected with ſome awful ſanction, which it would hc the moſt heinous impiety to oppoſe. Οί thefe feveral notions, the laſt will ever operate on moſt men with the moſt ſteady influence. AVe are frequently blind to our own intereſt ; even when eager for the attainment of happineſs, we often refuſc to take the wiſeſt meaſures for that end. The great bulk of the people in every community are ſo little capable of reafoning and foreſight, that the public miniſter who ſhall moſt ſteadily direct his views to the public good will often be the moſt unpopular. Thoſe laws, and that ſyſtem of government, which arc the moſt beneficial, will often excite the ſtrongeſt popular diſcontents. Again, it is not always eaſy to perſuade people that your power is ſuperior to theirs, when it is not really fo. No one man will ever be able to perſuade a thouſand that he is ſtronger than they all together ; and therefore, in order to perſuade one part of his fub-jects or army that it is abſolutely neceſſary for them to ſubmit to him, becauſe any attempts to reſiſt his power</p><p>would prove ineffectual, a monarch or general muſt take care ſirſt to perſuade another part that it is ſor their in-</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>