<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>attend to onc half, and we ſhall conſider theſe as in a ſtate of permanency.</p><p>No body changes either its direction or velocity otherwiſe than by inſenſible degrees : therefore the particle which is moving in the axis will not reach the vertex A of the body, where it behoved to deflect inſtantane-ouſly at right angles. It will therefore begin to be de-flected at ſome point F a head of the body, and will de-ſcribe a curve FM, -touching the axis in F, and the body in M ; and then, gliding along the body, will quit it at ſome point L, deſcribing a tangent curve, which will join the axis again (touching it) in R; and thus there will be a quantity of ſtagnant water FAM before or a head of the body, and another LCR behind ©r aſtern of it.</p><p>Let <hi rend="italic">a</hi>  be the velocity of a particle of the fluid in any inſtant, and <hi rend="italic">a'</hi>  its velocity in the next inſtant. The velocity <hi rend="italic">a</hi>  may be conſidered as compounded of ct and <hi rend="italic">a".</hi>  If the particles tended to move with the velocities α<hi rend="sup">,</hi>'only, the whole fluid would be in equiiibrio (general principle), and the preffure of the fluid would be the fame as if all were itagnant, and each particle were urged by a force —, <hi rend="italic">t<hi rend="sup">,</hi></hi>  expreſſing an. indefinitely ſmall β<hi rend="sup">,</hi>'</p><p>moment of time. <hi rend="italic">(N. B. —</hi>  is the proper expreſſion of</p><p>the accelerating force, which, by acting during the moment ∕∙, would generate the velocity λ"; and «" is ſuppoſed an indeterminate quantity, different perhaps for each particle). Now let <hi rend="italic">a</hi>  be ſuppofed conſtant, or <hi rend="italic">a ~ ct.</hi>  In this caſe <hi rend="italic">d' — o.</hi>  That is to ſay, no preſſure whatever will be exerted on the ſolid body unleſs there happen changes fin the velocities or directions of the particles.</p><p>Let <hi rend="italic">a</hi>  and a' then be the motions of the particles in two conſecutive inſtants. They would be in equilibrio <hi rend="italic">.    a"</hi></p><p>if urged only by the forces —. Therefore if <hi rend="italic">y</hi>  be the</p><p>point where the particles which deſcribe the curve FM begin to change their velocity, the preffure in D would be equal to the preffure which the fluid contained in the canal <hi rend="italic">y</hi>  FMD would exert, if each particle were folicited by its force —, The queſtion is therefore reduced to the finding the curvature in the canal <hi rend="italic">γ</hi>  FMD, and the ac-celerating forces — in its different parts.</p><p>It appears, in the firſt place, that no preffure is ex-erted by any of the particles along the curve FM : for ſuppoſe that the particle <hi rend="italic">a</hi>  (fig. 17.) deſcribes the in-definitely ſmall ftraight line <hi rend="italic">a b</hi>  in the firff inſtant, and <hi rend="italic">I c</hi>  in the fecond inſtant ; produce <hi rend="italic">a b</hi>  till <hi rend="italic">b d — a b,</hi>  and joining <hi rend="italic">dc,</hi>  the motion <hi rend="italic">ab</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">b d</hi>  may be confidered as compoſed of <hi rend="italic">b c,</hi>  which the particle really takes in the next inſtant, and a motion <hi rend="italic">d c</hi>  which ſhould be deſtroyed. Draw <hi rend="italic">b i</hi>  parallel to <hi rend="italic">d c,</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">i t</hi>  perpendicular to <hi rend="italic">b c. </hi>It is plain that the particle <hi rend="italic">b,</hi>  ſolicited by the forces <hi rend="italic">be, ei</hi>  (equivalent to <hi rend="italic">dc}</hi>  ſhould be in equilibrio. This-being eſtabliſhed,<hi rend="italic">.b e</hi>  muſt be = o, that is, there will be. no accelerating or retarding force at <hi rend="italic">b ;</hi>  for if there be, draw <hi rend="italic">b m</hi>  (fig.. 18.) perpendicular to <hi rend="italic">b</hi>  F, and the parallel <hi rend="italic">n q</hi>  infinitely near it. The part <hi rend="italic">b n</hi>  of the fluid contained in the canal <hi rend="italic">bn qm</hi>  would ſuſtain ſome preſ-</p><p>ſure from <hi rend="italic">b</hi>  towards <hi rend="italic">n,</hi>  or from « towards <hi rend="italic">b.</hi>  Therefore ſince the fluid in this ſtagnant canal ſhould be in equilibrio, there muſt alſo be ſome action, at leaſt in one of the parts <hi rend="italic">b m, m q, qn,</hi>  to counterbalance the action on the partez/. But the fluid is ſtagnant in the ſpace FAM (in conſequence of the law of continuity). Therefore there is no force which can act on <hi rend="italic">b m, τnq, ^ q n;</hi>  and the preffure in the canal in the direction <hi rend="italic">b n</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">« b</hi>  is nothing, or the force <hi rend="italic">b e = 0,</hi>  and the force &lt; <hi rend="italic">e</hi>  is perpendicular to the canal ; and there is therefore no preffure in the canal FM, except what proceeds from the part <hi rend="italic">γ</hi>  F, or from the force &lt;∙z ; which laft being perpendicular to the canal, there can be no force exerted on the point M, but what is propagated from the part <hi rend="italic">y</hi>  F.</p><p>The velocity therefore in the canal FM is confient if finite, or infinitely ſmall if variable : for, in the firſt caſe, the force <hi rend="italic">b e</hi>  would be abſolutely nothing ; and Tn the ſecond caſe, it would be an infiniteſimal of the ſe-coπd order, and may be conſidered as nothing in com-pariſon with the velocity, which is of the ſirſt order. λVe ſhall ſee by and by that the laſt is the real ſtate of the caſe. Therefore the ſiuid, before it begins to-change its direction in F, begins to change its velocity in ſome point <hi rend="italic">y</hi>  a-head of F, and by the time that it reaches F its velocity is as it were annihilated.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Cor.</hi>  i. Therefore the preffure in any point D ariſes both from the retardations in the part <hi rend="italic">y</hi>  F, and from the particles which are in the canal MD : as theſe laſt.</p><p><hi rend="italic">a "</hi></p><p>move along the ſurface of the body, the force —&gt; de~</p><p>ftroyed in every particle, is compounded of two others<hi rend="sub">r </hi>one in the direction of the ſurface, and the other per-pendicular to it ; call theſe<hi rend="italic">p</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">p'.</hi>  The point D ia preffed perpendicularly to the ſurface MD ; iſt, by all the forces <hi rend="italic">p</hi>  in the curve MD ; 2d, by the force <hi rend="italic">ρ'</hi>  acting on the ſingle point D. This may be neglected in compariſon of the indefinite number of the others : therefore taking in the arch MD, an infinitely fmaît portion· N <hi rend="italic">m, — s,</hi>  the preffure on D, perpendicular to the ſurface of the body, will be ≈s yQ&gt; and this fluent muſt be ſo taken as to be — <hi rend="italic">0</hi>  in the point M.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Cor.</hi>  2. Therefore, to find the preffure on D, we muſt find the force <hi rend="italic">p</hi>  on any point N. Let <hi rend="italic">u</hi>  be the velocity of the particle N, in the direction N <hi rend="italic">m</hi>  in any inſtant, and a + <hi rend="italic">u</hi>  its velocity in the following inſtant ; we muſt have <hi rend="italic">p —</hi>    Therefore the whole queſtion</p><p>is reduced to finding the velocity <hi rend="italic">u</hi>  in every pcſint N, in the direction N w.</p><p>And this is the aim of a ſeries of propoſitions which follow, in which the author diſplays the moſt accurate and preciſe conception of the ſubject, and great addrefs and elegance in his mathematical analyſis. He at length brings out an equation which expreffes the preffure on the body in the moſt general and unexceptionable manner. we cannot give an abſtract, becauſe the train of reaſoning is already conciſe in the extreme : nor can we even exhibit the final equation ; for it is conceived in the moſt refined and abſtruſe form of indeterminate, functions, in order to embrace every poſſible circum-ſtance. But we can affure our readers, that it truly expreffes the folution of the problem. But, alas ! it is of</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>