<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>the Hebrew <hi rend="italic">jod</hi>  being convertible into the Greek υ or the Roman<hi rend="italic">y;</hi>  but the words <hi rend="italic">Cane, Chan, Kan,</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">Khan, </hi>which are often diverſiſied into <hi rend="italic">hen, Kyn, Cohen, Cahan, </hi>.ſignifying <hi rend="italic">Head, Chief, Prince, King,</hi>  &amp;c. are diffuſed through a great part of Aſia and Europe, lu the Chineſe language <hi rend="italic">Sfgirι,</hi>  which ſigniſies a <hi rend="italic">King,</hi>  is ſo ſi-milar to the word <hi rend="italic">Chiun</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">Khiun</hi>  under'conſideration, that no etymologiſt will hefitate&lt; to pronounce them of the ſame original and the ſame import. I he word <hi rend="italic">Kan</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">Khan</hi>  is univerſally known to be an honorary ■title in Tartary ; and <hi rend="italic">Kaian</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">Kain,</hi>  which is manifeſtly cognate of the word <hi rend="italic">Chiun</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">Kiun,</hi>  is, in the <hi rend="italic">Pihevi </hi>or old Peiſian language, the epithet applied to the dy-naſty of princes which fucceeded Cyrus the Great. Among the Scythians or ancient Tartars, <hi rend="italic">Ghiun</hi>  ſigniſies the <hi rend="italic">Sun</hi>  and likewiſe the <hi rend="italic">day ;</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">Kung, Kinung, Kun,</hi>  runs through all the -dialects of the Gothic .tongue, every where denoting a <hi rend="italic">chief</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">fovereign.</hi>  In .the Syrian dialect, <hi rend="italic">Kon</hi>  ſignifies a prince ; and hence the Almighty is ſtyled (Gen. xiv. 19.) <hi rend="italic">Konah,</hi>  which is tranſlated <hi rend="italic">poffeffor,</hi>  but might have, &gt;with perhaps more propriety, been rendered <hi rend="italic">Sovereign</hi>  of heaven and earth. In Hebrew, the word <hi rend="italic">Kahan</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">Kahen,</hi>  which λs the very fame with <hi rend="italic">Khan</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">Kan,</hi>  ſignifies either a <hi rend="italic">prieft</hi>  or a <hi rend="italic">prince ;</hi>  and in Egypt <hi rend="italic">Kon</hi>  -was the name of the firſt Hercules or the <hi rend="italic">fun.</hi>  Hence the fame word in compofition denotes greatnefs, as <hi rend="italic">Can-obus</hi>  the great .ſerpent ; <hi rend="italic">Can-athoth,</hi>  the .great <hi rend="italic">Tkoth</hi>  or Mercury; <hi rend="italic">Can-pfiris,</hi>  the great <hi rend="italic">Oftris.</hi></p><p>From tills deduction ∙ we would conclude, that the word, which is found in fo many tongues, and always .denotes <hi rend="italic">Chief, Prince, Sovereign,</hi>  is the very word <hi rend="italic">Chiun </hi>which the Egyptians and Hebrews applied to <hi rend="italic">Sothis,</hi>  as Being, in their conceptions, the chief or fovereign of aſl the ſtars. This will appear ſtill more probable, when Λve have afcertained the import of the word <hi rend="italic">Remphan, </hi>•or, as the LXX have it, <hi rend="italic">Raiphan.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Phan,</hi>  the latter part of this word, is unqueſtionably the ſame with <hi rend="italic">Pan,</hi>  the moſt ancient of the Egyptian gods (fee Pan). It is likewiſe a cognate of the Hebrew <hi rend="italic">Phanah,</hi>  conſpexit, ſpectavit, vidit ; and the radical word ſeems to be ph ah, which fignifies ſome-times the countenance, and ſometimes <hi rend="italic">tight.</hi>  Hence <hi rend="italic">Phaethon,</hi>  which is compounded of <hi rend="italic">ph a</hi>  light, <hi rend="italic">eth</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">eft: </hi>fire, and <hi rend="italic">on</hi>  ſtrength, came to be one of the names of the fun. <hi rend="italic">Rai,</hi>  which we commonly write <hi rend="italic">Rajah,</hi>  has long .dignified, among the Indians, a ſiſhordinate prince ; and we know, that between India and Egypt there was a very early intercourfe. <hi rend="italic">Raiphan,</hi>  therefore, may be either the <hi rend="italic">royal tight</hi>  or the <hi rend="italic">bright prince,</hi>  ſubordinate to . Oſiris ; and in either ſenſe, it was a very proper epithet of <hi rend="italic">Sothis</hi>  in the Egyptian kalendar. The w<hi rend="sup">r</hi>ord<hi rend="italic">Rem </hi>or <hi rend="italic">Rom,</hi>  again (for it is fometimes written Remphan, and ſometimes Rompha), is no other than the Hebrew an <hi rend="italic">Rum</hi>  “ high, exalted.” Hence Remphan is the <hi rend="italic">high </hi>or <hi rend="italic">exalted tight,</hi>  which Sothis certainly was.</p><p>For this etymological diſquiſition we are indebted to Dr Doig, the learned author of <hi rend="italic">Letters on the Savage State,</hi>  who has written a differtation on <hi rend="italic">Chiun</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">Remphan,</hi>  of ſuch value that we hope it will not be much longer with-held from the public. The afcertaining the identity of thoſe names, and the god to which they belonged, is the leaft of its merit; for it will be found to throw much light upon many paffages in the üld Teſtament. what confirms his interpretation is, that the</p><lb/><p>idol conſecrated by the Egyptians to <hi rend="italic">Sothis</hi>  or the dog-ſtar, was a female figure with a ſtar on her head; and hence the prophet upbraids his - countrymen with having borne the <hi rend="italic">Star</hi>  of their deity.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Action of REMOVING, in Scots law. See -Law, N clxvii. 18.</hi></p><p>REMURIA, feſtivals eſtabliſhed at Rome by Romulus to appeaſe the manes of his brother Remus. They were afterwards called <hi rend="italic">Lemuria,</hi>  and celebrated yearly.</p><p>-REMUS, the brother of Romulus, was expofed together with his brother -by the cruelty of his grandfather. In the conteſt which happened between the two brothers about building a city, Romulus obtained the preference, and Remus, for ridiculing the riling walls, was put to death by bis brother’s orders, or by Romulus himſelf (ſee Romulus). The Romans were afflicted with a plague after this murder; upon which the oracle was conſulted, and the manes of Remus appeaſed by the inſtitution of the Remuria.</p><p>RENAL, ſomething belonging to the reins or Kidneys.</p><p>RENCOUNTER, in the military art, the encounter of two little bodies or parties of forces. In which fenſe <hi rend="italic">rencounter</hi>  is uſed in oppoſition to a pitched battle.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Rencounter, in ſingle combats, is uſed by way of contradiſtinction to duel.—when two perſons fall put and ſigbt on the fpot without having premeditated the combat, it is called a </hi><hi rend="italic">rencounter.</hi></p><p>RENDEZVOUS, or RendEvous, a place appoint-ed to meet in at a certain day and hour.</p><p>RENE AI.MI A, in botany ; a genus of the mono-gynia order, belonging to the monandria claſs of plants. The corolla is trifid ; the nectarſhm oblong ; the calyx monophyllous ; the anthera ſeffile, oppoſite to the nec-tarium ; the berry is ſleffiy. There is only one ſpecies, which is a native of Surinam.</p><p>RENEGADE, or Renegado, a perſon who has apoſtatized or renounced the Chriſtian faith, to embrace ſome other religion, particularly Mahometaniſm.</p><p>RENFREW, the county-town of Renfrewffiire, ſtanding ©n the ſmall river Cathcart, which flows into the Clyde at the diſtance of five miles from Glaſgow, is a fmall but ancient royal borough, the feat of the ſheriff’s court and of a preſhytery. The town is neat-ly built, and the inhabitants enjoy a tolerable ſhare of commerce.—Renfrew was originally joined to Lanerk, but wa9 made an independent iheriffdom by Robert II. who had a palace here. W. Long. 4. 26. N.Lat.55. 51.</p><p>RENFREWSHIRE, a county of Scotland, ſtyled by way of eminence the <hi rend="italic">barony,</hi>  becauſe it was the ancient inheritance of the Stuarts, is a ſmall county, extending about 20 miles from north to fouth, and 13 from eaſt to weſt, parted from Dumbartonſhire by the river Clyde on the weſt, bordering on the eaſt with La-nerkſhire, and on the north with Cunningham. The face of the country is varied with hill and vale, wood and ſtream ; crowded with populous villages, and a-dorπed with the feats of gentlemen. The foil is in general fertile, producing rye, barley, oats, peaſe, beans, ſiax-, and ſome wheat : it likewiſe yields plenty of coal, and turf for fuel: and affords abundance of pafturage for ſheep and cattle. The inhabitants are Lowlanderδ and Preſhyterians ; wealthy and induftrious, addicted to traffic, and particularly expert in the linen manufacture.</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>