<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>works were printed at Amſterdam in <hi rend="italic">17ii<hi rend="sub">i</hi></hi>  in J vol§ 12 mo, and the next year a pompous edition was printed in 2 vols quarto,</p><p>RACING, the riding heats for a plate, or other premium. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Plate.</hi>  The amuſement of horſe-racing, which is now ſo common, was not unknown among the great nations of antiquity, nor wholly un-practiſed by our anceſtors in Britain, as we have al-ready mentioned in the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Race.</hi>  In 1599, pri= vate matches between gentlemen, who were their own jockies and riders, were very common ; and, in the reign of James I. public races wcre eſtabliſhed at various pla-ces, when the diſcipline, and mode of preparing the horſes for running, &amp;c. were much the ſame as they are now. The moſt celebrated races of that time were called be’l-courſes, the prize of the conqueror being a bell: hence, perhaps, the phraſe of <hi rend="italic">bearing the bell,</hi>  when applied to excellence, is derived In the latter end of Charles I.’s reign, races were performed in Hyde-Park. Newmarket was alfo a place for the ſame purpoſe, though it was ſirſt uſed for hunting. Racing was re-vived ſoon after the Reſtoration, and much encouraged by Charles II. who appointed races for his own amuſe-mcnt at Datchet Mead, when he reſided at windſor. Newmarket, however, now became the principal place. The king attended in perſon, eſtabliſhed a houfe for his own acconſmodation, and kept and entered horſes in his own name. Inſtead ©f bells, he gave a filver bowl or cup value 100 guineas ; on which prize the exploits and pedigree of the fucceſsful horſe were generally en-graved. Inſtead of the cup or bowl, the royal gift is now a hundred guineas, william III. not only added to the plates, but even founded an academy for riding ; and Queen Anne continued the bounty of her anceſ-tors, adding ſeveral plates herfelf. George I. towards the end of his reign, diſcontinued the plates, and gave in their room a hundred guineas. An act was paſſed in the 13th year of the reign of George II. for ſup-</p><p>iireffing races by poneys and other ſmall and weak ιorfes, &amp;c. by which all matches for any prize under the value of 50 1. are prohibited, under a penalty of 2.00 1. to be paid by the owner of each horſe running, and 100 1. by ſuch as advertiſe the plate ; and by which each horſe entered to run, if five years old, is obliged to carry ten ſtones ; if ſix, eleven ; and if ſeven, twelve. It is alſo ordained, that no perſon ſhall run any horſe at a courſe, unleſs it be his own, nor enter more than one horſe ſor the ſame plate, upon pain of forfeiting the horſes ; and alfo every horſe-race muſt be begun and ended in the ſame day. Horſes may run for the value of 50 1. with any weight, and at anyplace. 13 Geo. II. cap. 19. 18 George II. cap. 34. Pennant’s Britiſh Zoology, vol. i. p. 6, &amp;c. Berenger’s Hiſtory and Art of Horſemanſhip, vol. i. p. 185, &amp;c. At New-market there are two courſes, the long and the round : the firſt is exactly four miles and about 380 yards, <hi rend="italic">i. e. </hi>7420 yards. The ſecond is 6640 yards. Childers, the ſwifteſt horſe ever known, has run the firſt courſe in ſeven minutes and a half, and the ſecond in ſix mi-nutes forty ſeconds ; which is at the rate of more than forty-nine feet in a fecond. But all other horſes take up at leaſt ſeven minutes and fifty ſeconds in completing the firſt and longeſt courſe, and ſeven minutes only in the ſhorteſt, which is at the rate of more than forty, <hi rend="italic">feven,</hi>  feet in a fécond. And it is commonly ſuppoſed that thefe <hi rend="smallcaps">&lt;khh⅛&gt;jj</hi>  cover, at every bound, a fpaee of ground in length about twenty-four Engliſh feet. Race-hprſea have becn for ſome time an object of taxation.</p><p>RACHITIS, the <hi rend="smallcaps">Rickets.</hi>  SeeMEuιciNE, n<hi rend="sup">0</hi>347.</p><p>RACK (Edmund), a perſon well known in the literary world by his attachment to, and promotion of, agricultural knowledge ; he was a native of Norfolk, a Quaker. His education was common, and he was ap-prenticed originally to a ſhopkeeper : his ſociety was ſelect in this ſituation, and by improving himſelf in learning, his converſation was enjoyed by a reſpectable acquaintance. He wrote many eſſays, poems, and letters, and ſome few controverſial tracts. At length he ſettled, about his 40th ye&amp;r, at Bath in 1775, and was ſoon introduced to the molt eminent literati of that place, among whom Dr wilſon and Mrs Macaulay highly eſteemed him for his integrity and abilities. In 1777 hc publiſhed <hi rend="italic">Msator<hi rend="sup">,</hi>s Letters,</hi>  a moral work, which has run through many editions. But this year he gained great celebrity by his plan of an agricultural ſociety, which was ſoon adopted by four counties. He ſtill further advanced his fame by his papers in the Far-, mer’s Magazine, and his communications in the Bath So-ciety’s papers ; a work remarkable for its ingenuity and' ſpirit. His laſt engagement was in the Hiſtory of So-merſetſhire, where the topographical parochial furveys were his. Thia work, in 3 vols 4to, was publiſhed in 1791, by his colleague the Reverend Mr Collinſon.—. Mr Rack died of an aſthma in February 1787, aged 52.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Rack,</hi>  an engine of torture, furniſhed with pulleys, cords, &amp;c. for extorting confeffion from criminals.— The trial by rack is utterly unknown to the law of England ; though once, when the dukes of Exeter and SuffoIk, and other miniſters of Henry VL had laid a deſign to introduce the civil law into this kingdom as the rule of government ; for a beginning thereof they erected a rack for torture, which was caffed in deriſion the duke of Exeter’s daughter, and ſtill remains in the I ower of London, where it was occafionally ufed aa an engine of ſtate, not of law, more than once in the reign of Queen Elizabeth. But when, upon the aſſaf-ſination orVilliers duke of Buckingham, by Felton, it was propoſed in the privy council to put the aſſaffin to the rack, in order to diſcover his acccomplices} the judges, being conſulted, declared unanimouſly, to their own honour and the honour of the EngIiſh law, that no ſuch proceeding was allowable by the laws of Eng-land, it ſeems aſtoniſhing that this ufage of admink ſtering the torture ſhould be ſaid to ariſe from a tenderneſs to the lives of men ; and yet this is the reaſon given for its introduction in the civil lav/, and its ſubſequent, adoption by the French and other foreign na» tions, viz. becauſe the laws cannot endure that any man ſhould die upon the evidence of a falſe, or even a ſingle witnef⅛, and therefore contrived this method that inno-cence ſhould manifeſt itſelf by a ſtout denial, or guilt by a plain confeffion : thus rating a man's virtue by the hardineſs of his conſtitution, and his guilt by the ſenſi-bility of his nerves, The Marquis Beccaria, in an ex-quifite. piece of raillery, has propoſed this problem, with a gravity and precifion that are truly mathematical :</p><p>" The force of the muſcles and the ſenſibility oif the. nerves of an innocent perſon being given ; it is reqni-red to find the degree of pain aecetΓary to make him</p></body></text></TEI>