<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>years. The tenant muſt alſo be made liable to be puniſhed for committing waſte ; and the uſual rent muſt be reſerved, or, where there has uſually been no rent, one-third of the clear yearly value. The misfor-'tune is, that this act was made too late, after almoſt every valuable poffeffion of the crown had been granted away for ever, or elfe upon very long leafes ; but may be of benefit to poſterity, when thoſe leaſes come to expire.</p><p>6. Hither might have been referred the advantages which were uſed to ariſe to the king from the profits of his military tenures, to which moſt lands in the kingdom were ſubject, till the ſtatute 12 Car. II. c. 24. which in great meaſure aboliſhed them all. Hither al-ſo might have been referred the profitable prerogative of purveyance and pre-emption : which was a right en-joyed by the crown of buying up proviſions and other fteceſſaries, by the intervention of the king’s purveyors, for the uſe of his royal houſehold, at an appraiſed va-luation, in preference to all others, and even without conſent of the owner : and alſo of forcibly impreſſing the carriages and horſes of the ſubject, to do the king’s buſinefs on the public roads, in the conveyance of tim-ber, baggage, and the like, however inconvenient to the proprietor, upon paying him a fettled price. A prerogative which prevailed pretty generally thrβugh-out Europe during the ſcarcity of gold and filver, and the high valuation of money confequential thereupon. In thoſe early times, the king’s houſehold (as well as thoſe of inferior lords) were ſupported by fpecific ren-ders of corn, and other victuals, from the tenants of the reſpective demeſnes; and there was alſo a continual market kept at the palace-gate to furniſh viands for the royal ufe. And this anſwered allpurpoſes, in thoſe ages of ſimplicity, fo long as the king’s court conti-nued in any certain place. But when it removed from one part of the kingdom to another (as was formerly very frequently done), it was found neceſſary to fend purveyors beforehand, to get together a ſufficient quantity of proviſions and other neceſſaries for the houſehold: and, leſt the unuſual demand ſhould raiſe them to an exorbitant price, the powers beforementioned were veſted in 'theſe purveyors ; who in proceſs of time very greatly abuſed their authority, and became a great oppreſſion to the ſubject, though of little advantage to the crown ; ready money in open market (when the royal reſidence was more permanent, and fpecie began to be plenty) being found upon experience to be the beſt proveditor of any. wherefore, by degrees, the powers of purveyance have declined, in foreign coun-tries as well as our own : and particularly were aboliſh-ed in Sweden by Guſtavus Adolphus, towards the be-ginningof the laſt century. And, with us in England, having fallen into diſuſe during the fuſpenſion of monarchy, King Charles, at his refloration, conſented, by the lame ſtatute, to reſign entirely thoſe branches of his revenue and power: and tb.e parliament, in part of recompenfe, fettled on him, his heirs, and ſucceſſcrs, for ever, the hereditary exciſe of 15d. per barrel on all beer and ale fold in the kingdom, and a proportionable ſum for certain Other liquors. So that this hereditary txcife now forms the ſixth branch of his majeſty’s or-dinary revenue.</p><p>7. A ſeventh branch might alſo be computed to have</p><lb/><p>arifen from wine-Iicences ; or the rents payable to the crown by ſuch perfems.as are licenſed to fell wine by retail throughout Britain, except in a few privileged places. Thefe were firſt fettled on the crown by die ſtatute 12 Car. II. c. 25. and, together with the hereditary exciſe, made up the equivalent in value for the loſs ſuſtaſhed by the prerogative in the abolition of the military tenures, and the right of pre-emption and purveyance : but this revenue was aboliſhed by the ſta-tute 30 Geo. II. c. 19∙ and an annual ſum of upwards of L. 7000 <hi rend="italic">per annum,</hi>  iſſuing out of the ncw ſtamo-duties impofed on wine-licences, was fettled on the crown in its ſtead.</p><p>8.    An eighth branch of the king’s ordinary revenus is uſually reckoned to conſiſt in the profits ariſing ſrom his foreſts. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Forest.</hi>  Theſe conſiſt principally in the amercements or fines levied for offences againſt the foreſhlaws. But as few, if any, courts of this kind for levying amercements have been held fince 1632, 8 Char. I. and as, from the accounts given of the pro-ceedings in that court by our hiſtories and law-books, nobody would wiſh to ſee them again revived, it is need-leſs to purſue this inquiry any farther.</p><p>9.    The profits ariſing from the king’s ordinary courts of juſtice make a ninth branch of his revenue. And theſe conſiſt not only in fines impoſed upon offenders, forfeitures of recognizances, and amercements levied upon defaulters ; but alſo in certain fees due to the crown in a variety of legal matters, as, for ſetting the great feal to charters, original writs, and other forenſic proceedings, and for permitting fines to be levied of lands in order to bar entails, or otherwiſe to inſure their title. . As none of thefe can be done without the immediate intervention of the king, by himſelf or his officers, the law allows him certain perquiſites and pro-fits, as a recompenfe for the trouble he undertakes for tlie public. Theſe, in proceſs of time, have been al-moſt all granted out to private perſons, or elſe appropriated to certain particular ufes : ſo that, thouoſh our law proceedings are ſtill loaded with their pΓy-ment, very little of them is now returned into the king s exchequer ; for a part of whofe royal maintenance they were originally intended. All future grants of them, however, by the ſtatute 1 Ann. ft. 2. c. 7. are to endure for no longer time than the prince’s life who grants them.</p><p>10.    A tenth branch of the king's ordinary revenue, ſaid to be grounded on the conſideration of his guard, ing and protecting the feas. from pirates and robbers, is the right to <hi rend="italic">royalfifih,</hi>  which are whale andſturgeon: and theſe, when either thrown aſhore, or caught near the coaſts, are the property of the king, on account of their fuperior excellence. Indeed, our anceſtors feem to have entertained a very high notion of the im-portance of this right ; it being the prerogative of the kings of Denmark and the dukes of Normandy j and from one of theſe it was probably derived to our princes.</p><p>11.    Another maritime revenue, and founded partly upon the ſame reaſon, is that of <hi rend="smallcaps">shipwrecks.</hi>  See <hi rend="smallcaps">wreck.</hi></p><p>12.    A twelfth branch of the royal revenue, the right to mines, has its original from the king’s prerogative of coinage, in order to ſupply him with materials ; and</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>