<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>with Antigonus, and affiſt him in his wars againſt all ſtates and princes except Ptolemy king of Egypt ; and that,Tor the effectual performance of the articles ſtipu-lated between them, they ſhould deliver ioo hoſtages, ſuch as Demetrius ſhould make choice of, except thoſe who bore any public employment.</p><p>Thus was the ſiege raiſed, after it had continued a whole year ; and the Rhodians amply rewarded all thoſe who had diſtinguiſhed themſelves in the ſervice of their country. They alſo ſet up ſtatues to Ptolemy, Caffander, and Lyſimachus ; to all of whom they paid the higheſt honours, eſpecially to the ſirſt, whom they worſhipped as a god. Demetrius at his departure preſented them with the helepolis, and all the other machines which he had employed in battering the city ; from the ſale of which, with ſome additional ſums of their own, they erected the famous coloffus. After this they applied themfelves entirely to trade and navigation ; by which means they became quite maſters of the ſea, and much more opulent than any of the neigh-bouring nations. As far as lay in their power, they endeavoured to preſerve a neutrality with regard to the jarring nations of the eaſt. However, they could not avoid a war with the Byzantines, the occaſion oſ which was as follows : The Byzantines being obliged to pay a yearly tribute of 80 talents to the Gauls, in order to raife this ſum, they came to a refolution of laying a toll on all ſhips that traded to the Pontic ſea. This reſolu-tion provoked the Rhodians, who were a trading nation, above all the reſt. For this reafon they immedi-ately diſpatched ambaſſadors to the Byzantines, complaining of the new tax ; but as the Byzantines had no other method of ſatisfying the Gauls, they perfiſted in their reſolution. The Rhodians now declared war, and prevailed upon Pruſſas king of Bithynia, and Attalus king of Pergamus, to affiſt them ; by which confederacy the Byzantines were ſo intimidated, that they agreed to exact no toll from ſhips trading to the Pontic ſea, the demand which had been the occaſion of the war.</p><p>About this time happened a dreadful earthquake, which threw down the coloſſus, the arſenal, and great part of the city-walls of Rhodes <hi rend="italic">y</hi>  which calamity the Rhodians improved to their advantage, ſending ambaſſadors to all the Grecian princes and ſtates, to whom their loſſes were ſo much exaggerated, that their countrymen obtained immenſe ſums of money under pretence of repairing them. Hiero king of Syracuſe preſented them with 100 talents ; and, beſides, exempted from all tolls and duties ſuch as traded to Rhodes. Ptolemy king of Egypt gave them ico talents, a million of mea-fures of wheat, materials for building 20 quinqueremes and the like number of triremes ; and, beſides, ſent them 100 architects, 300 workmen, and materials for tepairing their public buildings, to a great value, pay-ing them moreover 14 talents a-year for the mainte-nance of the workmen whom he ſent them. Antig©-Bus gave them 100 talents of ſilver, with 10,000 pieces of timber, each piece being 16 cubits long ; 7000 planks ; 3000 pounds of iron, as many of pitch and re-Jin, and 1000 meaſures of tar. Chryſeis, a woman of diftinction, ſent them 100,000 meaſures of wheat, and 3000 pounds of lead. Antiochus exempted from all taxes and duties the Rhodian ſhips trading to his do-ttinioas i preſented them with 10 galley s, and 200,000</p><p>meafures of c®rn, with many other things of great value. Pruſias, Mithridates, and all the princes then reigning in Aſia, made them proportionable preſents : in ſhort, all the Greek towns and nations, all the princes of Europe and Aſia, contributed, according to their ability, to the relief ©f the Rhodians on that occa« ſion ; inſomuch that their city not only ſoon rofe from its ruins, but attained to an higher pitch of ſplendor than ever.</p><p>In the year 203 B. C. the Rhodians engaged in a war with Philip of Macedon. This monarch had invaded the territories of Attalus king of Pergamus ; and becauſe the Rhodians ſeemed to favour their ancient friend, ſent one Heraclides, by birth a Tarentine, to ſet ſirc to their fleet ; at the ſame time that he diſpatch-ed ambaffadors into Crete, in order to ſtir up the Cretans againſt the Rhodians, and prevent them from ſending any affiſtance to Attalus. Upon this war was im-mediately proclaimed. Philip at ſiril gained an incon-ſiderable advantage in a naval engagement ; but the next year was defeated with the lofs of 11,000 men, while the Rhodians loſt but 60 men and Attalus 70. After this he carefully avoided coming to an engagement at ſea either with Attalus or the Rhodians. The combined fleet, in the mean time, faffed towards the iſland of Ægina in hopes of intercepting him : but having failed in their purpoſe, they failed to Athens, where they concluded a treaty with that people ; and,, on their return, drew all the Cyclades into a confederacy againſt Philip. But while tlie allies were thus-walling xheir time in négociations, Philip, having divided his forces into two bodies, ſent one, under the cum· rhand of Philocles, to ravage the Athenian territories £ and put the other aboard his fleet, with orders to ſail to Meronea·, a city on the north ſide of Thrace. He then marched towards that city himſelf with a body of forces, took it by affault, and reduced a great many others ; ſo that the confederates would, in all pro-bability, have had little reaſon to boaſt of their ſuc-ceſs, had not the Romans come to their afliftance, by whoſe help the war was foon terminated to their advantage. In the war which took place between the Romans and Antiochus the Great king of Syria, the Rhodians were very uſeful allies to the former. The beſt part of their fleet was indeed delhoyed by a trea-cherous contrivance of Polyxeniades the Syrian admi-ral ; but they ſoon fitted out another, and defeated a. Syrian iquudron commanded by the celebrated Hannibal, the Carthaginian commander ; after which, in con-junction with the Romans, they utterly defeated the whole Syrian fleet commanded by Polyxeniades ; which, together with the lofs of the battle of Magneſia, ſo di-ſpirited Antiochus, that he ſubmitted to whatever eon-ditions the Romans pleaſed.</p><p>For theſe ſerviees the Rhodians were rewarded with the provinces oſ Lycia and Cana ; but tyrannizing over the people in a terrible manner, the Lycians applied to the Romans for protection. This was readily granted ; but the Rhodians were ſo much diſpleaſed with their interfering in this matter, that they ſecretly favoured Perſes in the war which broke out between him and the Roman republic. For this offence the two provinces above-mentioned were taken ſrom them ; but the Rhodians, having baniſhed or put death thoſe who had favoured Perſes, were again admitted into ſa-VOUTj</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>