<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>often diſpoſed to regard vice with a no leſs favourable eye than virtue, and who, though there be an eſtabliſhed order by which virtue is diſcriminated from vice, and right from wrong, yet ſcruple not to violate that order in their own conduct ; you cannot expect: them to require in you a degree of rectitude of which they themſelves appear incapable. A Mercury will not diſ-courage the thieviſh arts of the trader ; a Bacchus and a venus cannot frown upon debauchery ; Mars will behold with ſavage delight all the cruelties of war. The Thracians indeed, one of the moſt barbarous nations of antiquity, whoſe ferocity was little if at all inferior to that of the Indians who have been diſtinguiſhed as ca-nibals, was the favourite nation of Mars ; among whom ſtood his palace, to whieh he repaired when about to mount his chariot, and arm himſelf for battle. Even Jupiter, who had been guilty of ſo many acts of tyrannical caprice, had been engaged in fuch a multitude of amorous intrigues, and ſeemed to owe his elevated ſtation as monarch of the ſky, not to fuperior goodnefs or wifdom, but merely to a ſuperior degree of brutal force, could not be feared as the avenger of crimes, or revered as the impartial rewarder of virtues.</p><p>That this ſyſtem had a pernicious effect on morals, and that, as compared with.pure theiſm, it was injurious to ſociety, cannot be denied ; but yet, when contraſted with atheiſm, it was not without its favourable effects. It was ſo connected with the order of fociety, that, without its ſupport, that order could fcarce have been maintained. The young rake might perhaps juſtify himſelf by the example of Jupiter, or Apollo, or ſome other amorous divinity ; the frail virgin or matron might complain of Cupid, or boaſt of imitating venus ; and the thief might practiſe his craft under the patronage of Mercury : But if we take the whole fyſtem together, if we conſider with what views thoſe deities were publicly worſhipped, what temples were raiſed, wlιat rites inſtituted, what ſacrifices offered, and what <hi rend="italic">feri&lt;ε</hi>  conſecrated ; we ſhall perhaps find it neeeffary to acknowledge that the general effects even of that mixed and incoherent ſyftem of polytheiſm whieh prevailed among the Greeks and Romans were favourable to fociety. To ſtate a particular inſtance ; the <hi rend="italic">ancilia</hi>  of Mars and the fire of Veſta were thought to ſecure the perpetuity of the Roman empire. As long as the ſacred <hi rend="italic">andle,</hi>  which had been dropped from heaven for that benevolent purpoſe, was ſafely preſerved in thoſe holy archives in which it had been depoſited ; and as long as the ſacred fire of Veſta was kept burning, without being once extinguiſhed, or at leaſt ſuffered to remain for an inſtant in that ſtate ; fo long was Rome to ſubſiſt and flouriſh. And, however ſimple and abfurd the idea which connected the profperity of a nation with the preſervation of a piece of wood in a certain place, or with the conſtant blazing of a flame upon an hearth ; yet no fact can be more certain, than that the patriotifm and enthuſiaſtic valour of the Romans, which we ſo much extol and admire, were, in many inſtances, owing in no inconfiderable degree to the veneration which they entertained for the <hi rend="italic">ancilia</hi>  and the veſtal ſire.</p><p>A numerous ſeries of facts occur in the Roman, hiſtory, which ſhow the happy effects of their religious: opinions and ceremonies on their ſentiments concerning ſocial order and the public welfare. How powerful</p><lb/><p>was the influence of the <hi rend="italic">ſacramentum</hi>  adminiſtered to the ſoldiers when they enliſted in the ſervice of their country ? The promiſes made, the idea of the powers invoked, and the rites performed on that occaſion, pro-duced ſo deep and ſo awful an impreffion on their minds, that no danger, nor diſtreſs, nor difcontent, could prompt thcm to violate their engagements. The re-ſponſes of the oracles, too, thougſh the dictates of deceit and impoſture, were often of ſingular ſervice to thoſe to whom they were uttered ; when they inſpiretj the warrior, as he marched out to battle, with the con-fide∏ce of fucceſs, they communicated to him new vi-gour<hi rend="sub">i</hi>  and more heroic valour, by which he was actu-ally enabled to gain, or at leaſt to deſerve, the fucceſs which they prornifed. Again, when in times of pub. lic diſtrefs, the augur and the prieſt directed ſome games to be celebrated, certain facriſices to be offered, or ſome other ſolemnities to be performed, in order to appeaſe tbe wrath of the offended deities ; it is plain that the means were not at all ſuited to accompliſh the end pro-poſed by them ; yet ſtill they were highly bénéficiai* when the attention of the whole people was turned en-tirely to thoſe ſolemnities by which the wrath of hea-ven was to be averted, they were rouſed from that de-fpondency under which the ſenſe of the public diſtrei’s or danger might have otherwiſe cauſed them to ſink : the public union was at the ſame time more cloſely cemented, and the hearts of the people knit together ; and when perſuaded, that by propitiating the gods they had removed the cauſe of their diſtreſs, they acquired ſuch calmneſs and ſtrength of mind as enabled them to take more direct and proper meaſures for the fofetyof the ſtate.</p><p>Could we view the ancient Greeks and Romans acting in public or in private life under the influence of that ſyſtem of ſuperſtition which prevailed among them ; could we perceive how much it contributed to the maintenance of civil order; could we behold Numa and Lycurgus eſtabliſhing their laws, which would otherwiſe have met with a very different reception under the fonction of divinities ; could we obſerve all the beneficial effects which aroſe to communities from the ce-lebration of religious ceremonies - we ſhould no longer hefitate to acknowledge, that thofe principles in the hu-man heart by which we are fuceptible<hi rend="sup">,</hi> of religious fentiments, are ſo eminently calculated to promote the hap-pineſs of mankind, that even when· perverted and abuſed, their influence is ſtill favourable.</p><p>The ideas which prevailed among the nations of the heathen world concerning a future ſtate of retribution were, it muſt be confeffed,. not very correct. Some of the poets, we believe, have repreſented them in no unfair light : both Homer and virgil have conducted their heroes through the realms of Pluto, and have taken occaſion to unfold to us the ſecrets of thoſe dreary abodes-The ſcenes are wild and fanciful ; the rewards of the juſt and virtuous are of no very reſined or dignified nature : and of the puniſhments- inflicted on. the guilty, it. is often hard to ſay for what ends they could be inflicted ; whether to correct and improve, or for the gratification of revenge or whim : they are often ſo whim-ſical and unfuitable, that they cannot with any degree of propriety be afcribed to any cauſe but blind chance or wanton caprice. A great dog with three tongues, a peevilh old boat-man with a. leaky ferry-boat, de-</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>