<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>except a tint of yellowiſh on thc great quills of the wing and of the tail. Edwards ſuppoſes, that the whiteneſs is produced by the cold climate of Hudſon’s Bay, from which he received it, and that they reſume their brown feathers during the ſummer. It appears that ſeveral ſpecies of this bird have ſpread further into A-merica, and have even reached the fouthern provinces : for Sloane found our third ſpecies in Jamaica ; and Fernandez ſeems to indicate two of them in New Spain, by the names <hi rend="italic">chiquatototl</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">elototαtl ;</hi>  the former being like our woodcock, and the latter lodging under the ſtalks of maize.</p><p>A bird of this kind, Mr Latham ſays, was ſent ſrom Hudſon’s Bay, and from the figure, has every appear-ance of an avoſet : however, in Edwards’s plate, the toes appear cloven to the bottom ; a circumſtance ſeeming to overturn the fuppoſition, and only to be authen-ticated when other ſpecimens ſhall have come under the eye of the well-informed naturaliſt.</p><p>RECUSANTS, ſuch perſons as acknow!edge the pope to be the ſupreme head of the church, and re-fuſe to acknowledge the king’s ſupremacy ; who are hence called <hi rend="italic">Popiſh recufants.</hi>  The penal laws againſt Papiſts are now aboliſhed in Britain and in Ireland ; and in all probability they will quickly be allowed the am· pleſt privileges.</p><p>RED, one of the colours called <hi rend="italic">fimple</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">primary : </hi>being one of the ſhades into which the light naturally divides itſelfwhen refracted through a priſm. See C <hi rend="smallcaps">h ro-matics∙</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Red,</hi>  in dyeing, ſee that article.—Some reckon ſix kinds or caſts of red, viz. fcarlet-rcd, crimſon-red, mad-der-red, half-grain red, lively orange-red, and ſcarlet of cochineal : but it is eaſy to ſee that there can be but one proper ſpecies of red ; namely, the reflection of the light exactly in ſuch a manner as it is refracted by the priſin ; all other ſhades being adulterations of that pure colour, with yellow, brown, &amp;c.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Red,</hi>  in heraldry. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Gules.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">RKn-Bird.</hi>  See <hi rend="smallcaps">Muscicapa,</hi>  n<hi rend="sup">0</hi>  7.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Rρ∏-Breafi,</hi>  in ornithology. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Motacilla.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">RED-Sοok</hi>  of the exchequer, an ancient record or manuſcript volume, in the keeping of the king’s re-membrancer, containing divers miſcellany treatiſes re-lating to the times before the conqueſt.</p><p><hi rend="italic">RKû-Lead.</hi>  See <hi rend="smallcaps">Chemistry,</hi>  n<hi rend="sup">o</hi>  1213.</p><p><hi rend="italic">RED Precipitate of Mercury.</hi>  See <hi rend="smallcaps">Chemistry,</hi>  n<hi rend="sup">o </hi>764·</p><p><hi rend="italic">REι&gt;-Ruffa,</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">Little Rujfia,</hi>  a province of Poland, bounded on the weſt by Upper Poland, on the north by Lithuania, on the eaſt by the country of the Little Tartars, and on the ſouth by Moldavia, Tranſylvania, and a part of Hungary. It comprehends Ruſſia pro-perly ſo called, volhinia, and Podolia. lt is about 650 miles in length, and from 150 to 250 in breadth. It conſiſts chiefly of large fields, but little cultivated on account of the frequent inroads of the Tartars, and becauſe there is no water-carriage. It had the name of <hi rend="italic">Red Rujfia,</hi>  from the colour of the hair of its inha-bitants. Ruffιa<hi rend="sub">r</hi>  properly ſo called, comprehends the three palatinates of Leopol or Lemburg, Belſko, and Chelm.</p><p><hi rend="italic">RED Sea,</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">Arabic Gulph,</hi>  ſo much celebrated in ſa-cred hiſtory, ſeparates Arabia from Upper Ethiopia and part of Egypt. This ſea is 350 leagues in length</p><lb/><p>and 40 in breadth. As no river falls into it of ſuffi-cient force to counteract the influence of the tide, it is more affected by the motions of the great ocean than any oſ the inland ſeas nearly in the ſame latitude. It is not much expofed to tempeſts : the winds uſually blow from north to ſouth, and being periodical, like the monſoons of India, invariably determine the feafon of foiling into or out of this ſea. It is divided into two gulphs ; that to the eaſt was called the <hi rend="italic">Ælanitic gulph, </hi>from the city Ælana at the north end of it ; and that to the weſt the <hi rend="italic">Heroopolitic,</hi>  from the city of Heroopo-lis ; the former of which belongs to Arabia, and the latter to Egypt.</p><p>Mr Bruce has made many obſervations on this ſea, which are worthy of notice.—with regard to the name, he fays ſt was certainly derived from Edom or Efou the ſon of Jacob ; though in another place he fays, he wonders that writers have not rather fuppoſed it to have got the epithet of <hi rend="italic">Red,</hi>  from the colour of the fond on its coaſts, than for other reaſons they have alleged. w ith regard to any redneſs in the water itſelf, or in the bottom, which ſome have aſſerted, our travel-ler aſſures us that there is no ſuch thing. It is more difficult to aſſign a reafon for the Hebrew name of <hi rend="italic">it, </hi>which ſignifies the <hi rend="italic">Sea of Weeds ;</hi>  as he never faw a weed throughout the whole extent of it. " Indeed, (ſays he) upon the ſlighteſt conſideration, it will occur to any one, that a narrow gulph, under the immediate influence of the monſoons, blowing from contrary points ſix months each year, would have too much agi-tation to produce ſuch vegetables, ſeldom found but in ſtagnant waters, and ſeldom, if ever, found in folt ones. My opinion then is, that it is from the large trees or plants of white coral, ſpread everywhere over the bottom of the Red Sea, perfectly in imitation of plants on land, that the fea has obtained this name.—I ſaw one of theſe, which, from a root nearly central, threw out ramifications of an almoſt circular form, meaſuring 26 feet every way.”</p><p>our author has alſo made many uſeful obſervations on the navigation of this ſea. " All the weſtern ſhore (he fays) is bold, and has more depth of water than the eaſt; but on this fide there is neither anchoring ground nor ſhoals. It is rocky, with a conſiderable depth of water everywhere ; and there are a number of ſunken rocks, which, though not viſible, are ſufficiently near the ſurface to deſtroy a large ſhip.” The cauſe of this, in Mr Bruce’s opinion, is, that the mountains on the ſide of Abyſſinia and Egypt are all of hard ſtone, porphyry, many different kinds of marble, granite, ala-baſter, and baſaltes. Thefe being all compoſed of ſo-lid materials, therefore, can part with very little duſt or fond, which might otherwiſe be blown from them into the ſea. Οη the oppoſite coaſt, viz. that of He-jaz and Tahamah, on thc Arabian ſide, the whole con-ſiſts of moving fonds ; a large quantity of which is blown from the ſouth-eaſt by the dry winter monſoons; which being lodged among the rocks on that ſide, and confined there by the north-eaſt or ſummer monſoon, which is in a contrary direction, hinders them from coming over to the Egyptian fide. Hence the weſtern coaſt is full of funk rocks for want of fond to cover them, with which they would otherwiſe become iſlands. They are naked and bare all round, with ſharp points like ſpears ; while, on the eaſt-ſide, every rock becomes</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>