<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p><hi rend="italic">Lower Circle of the Rhine,</hi>  conſiſts of the palatinate of the Rhine, and the three eccleſiaſtical electorates, viz. thoſe of Cologne, Mentz, and Triers.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Upper Circle of the Rhine,</hi>  conſiſted of the landgravi-ates of Alſace and Heſſe, comprehending the AVeteraw; but now only Heſſe can be accounted a part of Germa-ny, Alſace being long ago .united to France.</p><p>’ RHINEBERG, a town of Germany, in the circle of the Lower Rhine, and dioceſe of Cologne. It was in the poſſeffion of the French, but reſtored to the archbiſhop of Cologne by the treaty of Utrecht. It is ſeated on the Rhine, in E. Long. 6. 39. N. Lat.</p><p>RHINECK, a town of Germany, in the archbi-ſhopric of Cologne, ſeated on the Rhine, E. Long. 7. ς3. N. Lat. 50. 27.—There is another town of the ſame name in Swiſſerland, capital of Rhinthal, ſeated on the Rhine, near the lake of Conſtance, with a good caſtle. E. Long. 9. 53. N. Lat. 47. 38,</p><p>RHINFELD, a ſmall but ſtrong town of Germany, in tbe circle of Suabia, and the beſt oſ the four foreſt-towns belonging to the houſe of Auſtria. It has been often taken and retaken in the German wars ; and is ſeated on tbe Rhine, over which there is a handfome bridge. E. Long. 7. 53· N. Lat. 47. 40.</p><p>RHINEGAU, a beautiful diſtrict of the electorate of Mentz, is ſituated on the Rhine, about three miles from the clty of Mentz, and is fo populous that lt looks like one entire town intermixed with gardens and vineyards. The Rhine here grows aſtoniſhingly wide, and forms a kmd of ſea, near a mſle bioad, in wſuch are ſeveral well wooded little lſiands. I lie Rhmegau forms an amphitheatre, tlie beauties of whicli are beyond all deſeriptlon. At walluf, the very high hills come nearly down to the river ſide ; from thence they recede agam mto tlie country, formmg a kmd of half circle, the otlier end of which is'15 miles off at Rude-ſheim’ θη the banks of the Rhine. ſhe banks of the river, the hills wliicli form the circles, and the ſlopes oſ tlie great mountams, are thick ſown with vil lages and hamlets. The white appearance of the buildings, and the ſine blue ſlated roofs of the houſes playing amidſt the various green of the landſeape, have an admirable effect. In the ſpace of every mile, as you ſail down the river, you meet with a village which in any other place would paſs for a town, blany of the νιί-lages contain from 300 to 400 families ; and there are 36 of them in a ſpace of 15 miles long and ſtx miles broad, which ls the width of this heautiful amphitheatre. The declivities of all the hills and mountains are planted thick with vineyards and fruit trees, and the thick wooded tops of the hills caſt a gloomy horror over the otherwiſe cheerful landſeape. Every now and then a row of rugged hills run directly down to the ſhore, and dommeer majcſtically over the leffer hills un-der them. On one of theſe great mountains, juſt about the middle of the Rhinegau, you meet with <hi rend="italic">Johannis-Berg,</hi>  a village which produces ſome of the beſt Rhe-niſm Before this village is a pretty little riling, and near the banks oſ the river there is a very ſine old caſtle, which gives unſpeakable majeſty to the whole landſeape. Indeed, in every village, you meet with ſome or other large building, which contributes very much to the de-coration of the whole. This country is indebted for its riches to this ſemicirci/ar hill, which protects it from the cold winds of the eaſt and north, at the ſame time that it leaves room enough for the ſun to exerciſe his benign influences. The groves and higher Hopes of the hills make excellent paſtures, and produce large quantities of dung, which, in a country of this fort, is of ineſtimable value.</p><p>The bank of the Rhine, oppoſite to tbe Rhinegau, is exceedingly barren, and heightens tbe beauty of the proſpect on the other ſide by the contraſt it exhibits ; on this ſide, you hardly meet above three or four villages, and theſe are ſar diſtant from each other. The great interval between them is occupied by heaths and mea-dows, only here and there a thick buſh affords ſome ſhade, and a few corn fields among the viliages enliven the gloomy landſcape. The back ground of this coun-try is the moſt pictureſque part of it. It is formed by a narrow gullet of mountains, which diminiſh in perſpective between Rudeſheim and Bingen. Perpendicular mountains and rocks hang over the Rhine in this place, and ſeem to make it the dominion of eternal night. At a diſtance, the Rhine ſeems to come out of this land-ſeape through a hole under ground ; and it appears to run tediouſſy, in order to enjoy its courſe through a pleaſant country the longer. Amidſt the darkneſs which covers this back ground, the celebrated Monſe tower ſeems to fwim upon the river. In a word, there is not any thing in this whole tract that does not contribute ſomething to the beauty and magnificence of the whole ; or, if I may be permitted the expreffion, to make the paradiſe more welcome. As you ſail along the Rhine, between Mentz and Bingen, the banks ©f the river form an oval amphitheatre, which makes one of the richeſt and moſt pictureſquc landſcapes to be ſeen in Europe. The inhabitants of theſe regions arer ſome of them extremely rich, and ſome extremely poor. The happy middle ſtate is not for countries the chief product of which is wine ; ſor, beſides that the culti-vation of the vineyard is inſinitely more troubleſoma and expenſive than agriculture, it is ſubjected to revolutions, which in an inſtant reduce the holder of land to the condition of a day-labourer. It is a great miſ-fortune for this country, that, though reſtrained by law,, the nobility are, through connivance of the Elector, allowed to purchaſe as much land as they pleaſe. The peaſant generally begins by running in debt for his vineyard ; ſo that if it does not turn out well, he is reduced to day-labour, and the rich man extends his poſ-ſeffions to the great detriment of the conntry. There are ſeveral peaſants here, who having incomes of 30, 50, or ιοο,οοο guilders a-year, have laid aſide the pea-ſant, and affumed the wine-merchant ; but, ſplendid as their ſituation is, it does not compenſatb, in the eyes of the humane man, for the ſight of ſo many poor people with which the villages ſwarm. In order to render a country of this kind proſperous, the ſtate ſhould ap-propriate a fund to the purpoſe of maintaining the pea-ſant in bad years, and giving him the aſſiſtance which his neceffities, and his want of ready money, may from time to time make convenient.</p><p>The inhabitants of the Rhinegau are a handſome and uncommonly ſtrong race of men. You ſee at the very ſirſt aſpect that their wine gives them merry hearts and ſound bodies. They have a great deal of natural wit, and a vivacity and jocoſeneſs, which diſtinguiſhes them</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>