<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>and afterwards tbe head. As to the body of the worm from which theſe pieces were ſeparated, it lived as well as before, and ſeemed indeed to ſuffer nothing by the loſs, the head-part being immediately uſed as if thfe head was thereon, boring the creature’s way into the mud. There are, beſides this, two other points in which the reproduction will not take place ; the one of theſe is about the fifth or ſixth ring from the head, and the other at the ſame diſtance from the tail ; and in all pro-bability the condition of the great artery in theſe parts is the cauſe of this.</p><p>what is ſaid of the want of the reproductive power of theſe parts relates only to the head and tail ends ; for as to the body, it feels very little inconvenience from the loſs of what is taken off, and very ſpeedily reproduces thoſe parts, where then does the principle of life reſide in fuch worms, which, after having their heads cut off, will have not only the ſame motions, but even the inclinations, that they had before? and yet this difficulty is very ſmall, compared to ſeveral others which at the ſame time offer themſelves to our reaſon. Is this wonderful reproduction of parts only a natural conſe-quence of the laws of motion ? or is there lodged in the body of the creature a chain of minute buds or ſhoots, a fort of little embryos, already formed and placed in £uch part3 where the reproductions are to begin ? Are thefe worms only mere machines? or are they, like more perfect animals, a fort of compound, the ſprings of whoſe motions are actuated or regulated by a fort of foul ? And if they have themſelves ſuch a principle, how is it that this principle is multiplied, and is found in every ſeparate piece ? Is it to be granted, that there are in theſe worms, not a ſingle ſoul (if it is to be ſo call-ed) in each, but that each contains as many fouls as there are pieces capable of reproducing perfect animals ? Are we to believe with Malpighi, that theſe forts of worms are all heart and brain from one end to the other! This may be ; but yet if we knew that it was ſo, we ſhould know in reality but very little the more for knowing it: and it ſeems, after all, that in caſes of this kind we are only to admire the works of the great Creator, and ſit down in ſilence.</p><p>The nice ſenſe of feeling in ſpiders has been much talked of by naturalifts ; but it appears that thefe worms have yet ſomewhat more ſurpriſing in them in regard to this particular. If a piece of ſtick, or any other ſubſtance, be brought near them, they do not ſtay tor its touching them, but begin to leap and friſk about as ſoon as it comes towards them. There want, however, ſome farther experiments to aſcertain whether this be really owing to feeling or to ſight ; for though we can diſcover no diſtinct organs of tight in theſe creatures, yet they ſeem affected by the light of the ſun or a candle, and always friſk about it in the ſame manner at the approach of either ; nay, even the moon-light has ſome effect upon them.</p><p>A twig of willow, poplar, or many other trees, be-ιng planted in the earth, takes root, and becomes a tree, every piece of which will in the ſame manner pro-duce other trees. The caſe is the ſame with theſe worms: they are cut to pieces, and theſe ſeveral pieces become perfect animals ; and each of theſe may be again cut into a number of pieces, each of which will in the ſame manner produce an animal. It had been ſuppoſed by ſome that theſe worms were ovipaζous t but Mr Bo-</p><lb/><p>nett, on cutting one of them to pieces, having obſerved a ſiender ſubftance, reſembling a ſmall filament, to move at the end of one of the pieces, ſeparated it ; and on examining it with glaffes, found it to be a perfect worm, of the ſame form with its parent, which lived and grew larger in a veffel of water into which he put it. Theſe ſmall bodies are eafily divided, and very readily complete themſelves again, a day uſually ſerving for the produc-tion of a head to the part that wants one ; and, in <hi rend="italic">general,</hi>  the ſmaller and ilenderer the worms are, the ſooner they complete themſelves after this operation, when, the bodies of the large worms are examined by the microſcope, it is very eaſy to ſee the appearance of the young worms alive, and moving about within them : but it requires great precifion and exactneſs to be certain of this ; lince the ramifications of the great artery have very much the appearance of young worms, and they are kept in a fort of continual motion by the ſyſtolea. and diaftoles of the ſeveral portions of the artery, which ſerve as ſo many hearts. It is very certain, that what we force in regard to theſe animals by our operations, is done alſo naturally every day in the brooks and ditches where they live. A curious obſerver will find in theſe places many of them without heads or tails, and ſome without either; as alſo other fragments of various kinds, aſl which are then in the act of completing them-ſelves : but whether accidents have reduced them to this ſtate, or they thus purpoſely throw off parts of their own body for the reproduction of more animals, it is not eaſy to determine. They are plainly liable to many accidents, by which they loſe the ſeveral parts of their body, and mnſt periſh very early if they had not a power of reproducing what was loſt : they often are broken into two pieces, by the refiſtance of feme hard piece of mud which they enter ; and they are ſubject to a diſeaſe, a kind of gangrene, rotting off the ſeveral parts of their bodies, and mnſt inevitably periſh by it,.. had they not this ſurprifing property.</p><p>This worm was a ſecond inſtance, after the polype, of the ſurpriſtng power in an animal of recovering its moſt effential parts when loſt. But Nature does not ſeem to have limited her beneficence in this reſpect to theſe two creatures. Mr Bonett tried the ſame expe-rimeπts on another ſpecies of water-worm, differing from the former in being much.thicker. This kind of worm, when divided in the ſummer-ſeaſon, very often ſhows the fame property: ſor if it be cut into three or four pieces, the pieces wiſl lie like dead for a long time, but afterwards will move about again ; and wiſl be found iu this ftate of reſt to have recovered a head, or a tail, or both·. After recovering their parts, they move very little⅝ and, according to this gentleman’s experiments, ſeldom ſlve more than a month.</p><p>it ſhould ſeem, that the more difficult luccefs of this laſt kind of worm, after cutting, and the long time it takes to recover the loſt parts, iſ it do recover them at aſl, is owing to its thickneſs ; fince we always find in that ſpecies of worms which ſucceeds beſt of all, that thoſe which are thinneſt always recover their parts much ſooner than the others.</p><p>The water-inſects alſo are not the only creatures which have this power of recovering their loſt parts. Tlie earth affords us ſome already diſcovered to grow in this manner from their cuttings, and theſe not leſs deferring our admiration than thoſe of the water : the</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>