<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>rannical than this was never made by an eaſtern deſpot ; and when it was ſirſt publiſhed, foreigners were at a loſs whether to regard it as a ſublime effort of a power-ful government, or as a wild project whicli could pro-duce nothing but confuſion. The effects of it, how-ever, have been truly terrible, we have already men-tioned ſome of them in the bloody conteſt wliicli oc-curred upon the Rhine, and Europe was foon deſtined to bear witneſs to ſtill more extraordinary events.</p><p>In the end of July, general Cuſtine was brought to trial, and executed, in conſequence of a variety of ac-cuſations of infidelity to his truſt and diſreſpect to the convention. The queen was next brought to trial be-fore the revolutionary tribunal, on the 15th of Octo-ber. Tlie charges againſt her were very various ; but the chief tendency of them was to prove that ſhe had always been hoſtile to the revolution, and liad excited all the efforts that had been made by the court againſt it. On the 16th of October, this beautiful woman, whom fortune once placed ſo high, ended her days on a ſcaffold, after a mock trial, in which no regard was paid either to juſtice or decency. She behaved with much dignity and compoſure, and appeared deeply impreſſed with a fenſe of religion. The members of the <hi rend="sup">1</hi> convention who had been at the head of the Girondiſt party, and had either been detained in priſon ſince the 3iſt of May, or ſeized in the departments to which they had retired, were afterwards brought to trial. On the 30th of October, 2 1 of them were executed, viz. Briffot, Vergniaud, Genſonne, Duprat, Lehardi, D ucos, Fonfrede, Boileau, Gardien, Duchatel, Sillery, Fauchet, Dufriche, Duperret, La Source, Carra, Beau-vais, Mainville, Antiboul, Vigée, and Lacaze. Seventy-one were ſtill detained in confinement. The duke of Orleans was afterwards condemned, on a cliarge of having aſpired to the ſovereignty from the beginning of the revolution. His execution gave ſatisfaction to all parties. His vote for the puniſhment of death upon the trial of the late king had done him little honour even in the opinion of the Mountain, and had rendered him odious to all the reſt of mankind.</p><p>The executions of perſons of all ranks, particularly of prieſts and nobles, became now ſo common, that it would be in vain to attempt to give any detail of them. Every perſon brought before the revolutionary tribunal was condemned as a matter of courſe. The Jacobins ſeemed inſatiable in their thirſt after blood, and the people at large appeared to regard their conduct with unaccountable indifference.</p><p>: when the human mind is once rouſed, its activity extends to every object. At this time a new table of weights and meaſures was eſtabliſhed by the convention, in which the decimal arithmetic alone is employed. The court of Spain had the liberality, notwith-ſtanding the war, to ſuffer M. Mechain to proceed in his operations for meaſuring a degree of the meridian in that country. He carried on his ſeries of triangles from Barcelona to Perpignan ; and from this place the menſuration was continued to Paris. M. de Lambre, and his pupil M. le Francois, alſo meaſured a degree of latitude in the vicinity of the metropolis. In all, 12 degrees of the meridian were meaſured ; of which the mean is 57027 toifes, and by this the univerſal ſtandard of meaſure is calculated. M. M. de Borde and Caffini determined the length of a pendulum that ſwings ſe</p><p>conds, <hi rend="italic">in vacuo</hi>  and in a mean temperature at Paris, to be 3 ſeet and 8,06 lines. Μ. M. Lavoiſier and Hauy ſound that a cubic foot of diſtilled water at the freezing point weighs <hi rend="italic">in vacuo</hi>  70 pounds and 60 gros French weight, we ſhall infert a table of the meaſures and weights now eſtabliſhed.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Long Meaſure.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Metres.    „    French Toiffs.</hi></p><p>10,000,000 = a quadrant of the meri</p><p>dian which is the prin-ciple on which the new meaſure is founded - 5132430</p><p>100,000 = an hundredth part of a quadrant, ordecimal de-gree of the meridian <hi rend="italic">-    5<hi rend="sup">I</hi>3^4-</hi></p><p>I ooo = a <hi rend="italic">milliare,</hi>  or mile -    513</p><p>100 = a ſtadium") Agrarian £51-3243</p><p>10 = a perch J meaſure, £ 5.13243 <hi rend="italic">Feet. Inch. Lines.</hi></p><p>I = a <hi rend="italic">metre,</hi>  or rectilineal</p><p>unit -    -    30    11.44</p><p>vg· or O.i = a <hi rend="italic">decimetre,</hi>  or palm o 3    8.344.</p><p>or 0.01 = a <hi rend="italic">centremetre,</hi>  or di-</p><p>git -    00    4.434</p><p><hi rend="sup">or</hi> 0.001 = a<hi rend="italic">millemetre</hi>  -    00</p><p><hi rend="italic">Superficial Meaſure.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Sq. Metres.    Sq. Feet.</hi></p><p>ΐο,οοο = an <hi rend="italic">are,</hi>  or ſuperſicial unit, being</p><p>a fquare the fide of which is 100</p><p>metres in length    -    -    94831</p><p>1000 a <hi rend="italic">declare,</hi>  or tenth of an <hi rend="italic">are ;</hi>  a ſuperficies an hundred metres long, and ten broad    -    9483.1</p><p>ioo = a centiare    -    -    94.8.31</p><p><hi rend="italic">Meaſures of Capacity.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Cub. decimetres    Paris Pints. Paris Buff.</hi></p><p>1000 = the cubic <hi rend="italic">metre,</hi>  or cade</p><p>or tun -    -    1051£    78.9</p><p>IOO <hi rend="italic">= dedicade,</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">Jeder</hi>     Ιθ5τ 7.89</p><p>IO <hi rend="italic">= centicade,</hi>  or buſhel    ιο^·    .789</p><p>I = cubic <hi rend="italic">decimetre,</hi>  or pint    l<hi rend="sub">T</hi>’g·    .0789</p><p><hi rend="italic">Cub. decimetres    <hi rend="sup">e</hi>'<hi rend="sup">l{&gt; jis</hi>'    <hi rend="sub">Γ</hi> .</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">of water.    &lt; French Pounds.</hi></p><p>1000 = the weight of a cubic <hi rend="italic">metre,</hi>  or</p><p>cade of water, is called a <hi rend="italic">bar</hi>  or</p><p><hi rend="italic">milder</hi>     -    2044.4</p><p>100 = Vo of a <hi rend="italic">h<hi rend="sup">ar</hi>·,</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">decibar,</hi>  or quintal 204.44 10 — of a <hi rend="italic">bar,</hi>  or centibar, or <hi rend="italic">decal</hi>  20.444</p><p><hi rend="italic">lb. oz. gros, grains.</hi></p><p>I = the weight of a cu-bic decimetre of wa-ter is called a <hi rend="italic">grave, </hi>or pound -    <hi rend="italic">2</hi>    8    5    49</p><p>.1 = τ’θ of a <hi rend="italic">grave,</hi>  or</p><p><hi rend="italic">decigrave,</hi>  or ounce    o 3 2    12. t</p><p>.01 = <hi rend="sub">T</hi>4n °ſ<hi rend="italic">grave,</hi>  or</p><p>centigrave, or dram o ö 2 44.4t</p><p>ι,οοί = the weight of a cubic <hi rend="italic">centimetre</hi>  of wa-ter, is named a <hi rend="italic">gravet,</hi>  or maille - ο ο o 18.841</p><p>.0001 = <hi rend="italic">decigravet,</hi>  or grain ooo 1.8841 .0000 ί <hi rend="italic">= centigravet - </hi>ooo 0.18841</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>