<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>judices on the altar of their country. He concluded an animated addrefs with theſe words, “ Let all who hold in equal deteſtation a republic and two chambers, and who wiſh to maintain the conſtitution as it is, rife!” The words were ſcarcely pronounced when the whole aſſembly ſtarted from their feats. Men of all parties ſolemnly embraced each other, and proteſted their adherence to the conſtitution. A deputation announced this happy event to the king ; who immediately came and congratulated them in a ſhort ſpeech, which was leceived with infinite app’auſe. The only good effect, however, produced by this temporary agreement was, that the ſeſtival of the 14th of July, which was celebrated with the ufual magnificence, paſſed over in tranquillity.</p><p>On the 25th of July, the duke of Brunfwick iſſued at Coblentz his celebrated manifeſto. It declared the purpoſe of the intended invaſion of France to be the reſtoration of the French king to full authority. It de-clared the national guard of France reſponfible for the preſervation of tranquillity; and threatened with the pu-niſhment of death, as rebels to their king, thoſe who ſhould appear in arms againſt the allied powers. All men holding offices, civil or military, were threatened in the ſame manner, as well as the inhabitants of all cities. The city of Paris in particular, and the national aſſembly, were declared reſponſible for every inſult which might be offered to the royal family. It was declared, that if they were not immediately placed in ſafety, the allies were reſolved to inflict " on thoſe who ſhould deſerve it the moſt exemplary and ever memorable avenging puniſhments, by giving up the city of Paris to military execution, and expoſing it to total deſtruction ; and the rebels who ſhould be guilty of illegal reſlſtance ſhould ſuffer the puniſhments which they ſhould have deſerved.” This ſanguinary and imprudent manifeſto operated as a warrant for the deſtruction of the unfortunate Louis XVI. It left no middle party in the na-tion. All who wiſhed to preferve freedom in any form, and all who loved the independence of their country, were inſtantly united. At the ſame time, the reproach-es caſt on the king by the Jacobins now gained univer-ſal credit. The kings of Pruffia and of Hungary told the French nation, that their monarch was ſecretly hof-tile to the conſtitution ; and the reſtoration of him and his family to deſpotic power was made the ſole pre-tence for a bloody and dangerous war.</p><p>The republican party faw the advantage which they had now gained, and refolved upon the depoſition of the king. The chief engine which they meant to employ in this ſervice conſiſted of about 1500 men, who had come to Paris at the period of the confederation on the 14th of July, and therefore called <hi rend="italic">faderes,</hi>  and who were alfo fometimes denominated <hi rend="italic">Marfiillms,</hi>  from the place from which the greater number of them came. Next to theſe, dependence was placed in the populace of the ſuburbs of the capital. Thc deſigns of the republicans were not unknown to the court, and both parties were forming plans of operation. It is ſaid that the royal party intended that the king and his family ſhould fuddenly lea^e the capital, and proceed to as great a diſtance as the conſtitution permitted. The republicans are ſaid to have intended to ſeize the perfon of the king, and to confine him in the caſtle of Vin-cennes till a national convention ſhould decide upon his fate. Both allegations are probably true. Every motive which can influence the mind of man muſt have induced Louis to wiſh to be at a diſtance from the factious and ſanguinary capital. And the ſubſequent conduct of the republicans authoriſe us to believe them capable of the worſt crime that was laid to their charge.</p><p>Various charges had been brought forward in the affembly againſt La Fayette, and the 8th of Auguſt was appointed for their ducuffion. In the mean time, on the 3d of Auguſt, Petion the mayor, at the head of a deputation from the ſections of Paris, appeared at the bar, and in a ſolemn ſpeech demanded the depoſition of the king. The diſcuſlion of the accuſation againſt La Fayette was conſidered as a trial of ſtrength between the parties : he was acquitted, however, by a majority of nearly 200 ; and the republican party, deſpairing oſ carrying their point by a vote ©f the national aſſembly, •reſolved to have recourſe to infurrection and force.</p><p>On the evening of the 9th of Auguſt, about 1500 gentlemen, officers of the army, and others, repaired to the palace, reſolved to protect the royal family or to die in their defence : added to thefe were 70© Swifs guards, with a body of cavalry amounting to about I ooo. Mandat, the commander of the national guards, a man who was firmly attached to the conſtitution, had procured 2400 of that body and 12 pieces of cannon, with ſuch a force, it has been generally thought that, by vigorous and ſteady councils, the palace, which is a kind of caſtle, might have been ſucceſsfully defended ; and what is now called a revolution might have born the name of a rebellion. Meanwhile the aſſembly de-clared its fittings permanent. Petion was at the palace late on the evening of the 9th. Some apprehenſions were entertained, or pretended tobe entertained, forhia ſafety (for the whole of this buſineſs was, on the part of the republicans, the moſt infernal plot), and a deputation from the aſſembly brought him away. At mid-night the toçlin or alarm bell was founded, and thc drums beat to arms through the city. At this inſtant a number of the moſt active leaders of the republican party aſſembled, and elected a new common council or <hi rend="italic">commune.</hi>  The perſons thus irregularly choſen inſſantly took poſſeffion of the common hall, and drove out tlie lawful members ; who, with that weakneſs with wliich men are apt to ſhrink from ſtations of reſponſibility in pe-rilous times, readily gave place to tlie uſurpers. The new commune ſent repeated meſſages to M. Mandat, requiring liis attendance upon important buſineſs. He was occupied in arranging the troops in the beft order a-round tlie palace ; but ſuſpecting nothing, he went to the common Lall, and was there aſtoniſhed to ſind a different affembly from what he expected. He was a-bruptly accuſed of a plot to maffacre the people, and ordered to priſon ; but as he deſeended tbe ſtairs, lie was ſhot with a piſtol, and Santerre was appointed in his ſtead to command the national guard.</p><p>On this eventful night no perfon in the palace went to bed. About ſix o’clock in the morning of the 10th the king deſeended into the gardens to review tlie troops. He was received with ſhouts of <hi rend="italic">Vive le roi</hi>  excepting from the artillery, who ſhouted <hi rend="italic">Vive la nation. </hi>The king returned to the palace, and the multitude continued to collect. The national guard ſeemed undetermined about what they were to do, as they aſſembled in diviſions near thc palace ; and had a ſteady re-</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>