<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ciple over and above is neceffary to excite our induſtry, and to prevent our ſtopping ſhort in the middle of the courſe.</p><p>V7e need not loſe time to defcribe the co-operation of the foregoing propenſity with ſnrpriſe, in producing the effect that follows any unuſual reſemblance or diſ-ſimilitude. Surpriſe firſt operates, and carries our opinion of the reſemblance or diſſimilitude beyond truth. The propenfity we have been deſcribing carries us ſtill farther ; for i.t forces upon the mind a conviction, that the reſemblance or diſſimilitude is complete. λVe need no better illuſtration, than the reſemblance that is fancied in ſome pebbles to a tree or an infect ; which reſemblance, however faint in reality, is conceived to be wonderfully perfect. The tendency to complete a reſemblance acting jointly with ſurpriſe, carries the mind ſometimes ſo far, as even to preſume upon future events. In the Greek tragedy entitled <hi rend="italic">Phimides,</hi>  thoſe unhappy women feeing the place where it was intended they fhould be ſlain, cried out with anguiſh, " They now faw their cruel deſtiny bad condemned them to die in that place, being the fame where they had been expo-fed in their infancy.”</p><p>The propenfity to advance every thing to its perfection, not only co-operates with ſurpriſe to deceive the mind, but of itſelf is able to produce that effect, of this we ſee many iuſtances where there is no place for ſurpriſe ; and the firſt we ſhall give is of reſem-blance. <hi rend="italic">Unumquodque eodem modo dijſolvitur quo colh-gatum eβ,</hi>  is a maxim in the Roman law that has no foundation in truth ; for tying and loôfing, building and demoliſhſhg, are acts oppofite to each other, and are performed by oppofite means : but when tbeſe acts are connected by their relation to the fame ſubject, their connection leads us to imagine a fort of reſem-blance between them, which by tbe foregoing propen-ſity is conceived to be as complete as poſſible. The next inſtance ſhall be of contraſt. Addiſon obferves, " That the paleſt features look the moſt agreeable in white ; that a face which is oveiſtuſhed appears to advantage in the deepeſt ſcarlet ; and that a dark complexion is not a little alleviated by a black hood.” The foregoing propenfity ſerves to account for theſe appearances ; to make this evident, one of the caſes ſhall ſuſſice. A complexion, however dark, never ap-proaches to black : when thefe colours appear together, their oppofition ſtrikes us; and the. propenfity we have to complete the oppofition, makes the dark-neſs of complexion vaniſh out of fight.</p><p>The operation of this propenfity, even where there ' is no ground for furpriſe, is not confined to opinion or conviction : fo powerful it is, as to make us fometimes proceed to action, in orde¢ to complete a reſemblance or diſſimilitude. If this appear obſcure, it will be made clear by the following inſtance. Upon what principle is the <hi rend="italic">lex talionis</hi>  founded, other than to make the puniſhment referable the miſchief? Reafon dic-tates, that there ought to be a conformity or refem-blance between a crime and its puniſhment ; and the foregoing propenfity impels us to make the reſemblance as complete as poſſible. Titus Livſhs J∣, under the influence of that propenfity, accounts for a certain puniſhment by a reſemblance between it and the crime, too ſubtile for common apprehcnſion. Speaking of</p><p>Mettus Fuffetius, the Alban general, who, for treachery to the Romans his alliés, was ſentenced to be torn to pieces by horſes, he puts the following ſpeech in the mouth of Tullus Hoſtilius, who decreed the puniſhment. <hi rend="italic">" Mette Fuffeû, inquit, ſi ipſe dijeere p<hi rend="sup">r</hi>ffβs ~, fidem ac fœdera ſervare, vivo tibi ea diſciplina a me adhibita effet. Nunc, quoniam tuum infanabile ingenium eβ, at tu tno fupplicio doce humanum genus ea fan id a credere, qux a te violata ſunt. Ut igitur paulo ante animum inter Fi-denatem Romanamque rem ancipιtem geβffβi, itajam corpus -paffim d'βrahendum dabis.”</hi>  By the ſame influence, the ſentence is often executed upon the very fpot where the crime was committed. In the <hi rend="italic">Plectra</hi>  of Sophocles, Egiſtheus is dragged from the theatre into an inner room of the ſuppofed palace, to fuffer death where he murdered Agamemnon. Shakeſpeare, whoſe knowledge of nature is not leſs profound than extenfive, has not overlooked this propenfity :</p><p><hi rend="italic">" Othello.</hi>  Get me ſome poiſon, Iago, this night. I’ll not expoſtulate with her, leſt her body and her beauty unprovide my mind again. This night, Iago.”</p><p><hi rend="italic">" Iago.</hi>  Do it not with poiſon ; ſtrangle her in her bed, even in the bed ſhe hath contaminated.”</p><p><hi rend="italic">“ Othello.</hi>  Good, good : the juſtice of it pleafes : very good.”    <hi rend="italic">Othello, act A<hi rend="sub">t</hi>∙fc∙ ξ.</hi></p><p>Perſons in their laſt moments are generally ſeized with an anxiety to be buried with their relations. In the <hi rend="italic">Amynta</hi>  of Taffo, the lover, hearing that his miſtreſs was torn to pieces by a wolf, expreffes a deſire to die tbe ſame death.</p><p>Upon the ſubject in general we have two remarks to add. Tlie firſt. concerns reſemblance, which, when too entire, hath no effect, however different in kind the things compared may be. The remark is applicable to works of art only ; for natural objects of different kinds have ſcarce ever an entire reſemblance. To give an example in a work of art : Marble is a fort of matter very different ſrom what compoſes an animal ; and marble cut into a human figure, produces great plea-ſure by the reſemblance : but if a marble ſtatue be co-loured like a picture, the reſemblance is ſo entire as at a diftance to make the ſtatue appear a real perſon : we diſcover the miſtake when we approach ; and no other emotion is raiſed, but ſurpriſe occaſioned by thc de-ception : the figure ſtill appears a real perſon, rather than an imitation ; and we muſt uſe reflection to correct the miſtake. This cannot happen in a picture ; for the reſemblance can never be ſo entire as to diſguiſe the imitation.</p><p>The other remark belongs to contraſt. Emotion3 make the greateſt figure when contraſted in ſucceſſion ; but then the ſucceſſion ought neither to be rapid, nor immoderately flow : if too flow, the effect of contraſt becomes faint by the diſtance of the emotions ; and if rapid, no ſtngle emotion has room to expand itſelf to . its full fize, but is ſtiſted, as it were, in the birth by a ſucceeding emotion. The funeral oration of the biſhop of Meux upon the ducheſs of Qrleans, is a perfect hodge-podge of cheerful and melancholy reprefeπ-tations, following each other in the quickeſt ſucceſſion : oppofite emotions are belt felt in ſucceſſion ; but each emotion feparately ſſiould be raiſed to its due pitch, before another be introduced..</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>