<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Bonnef, and the right towards Folz, and every thing was diſpoſed in order to attack. To this end, four battalions were detached to attack the village of Fran-quenies, and twelve battalions to attack the village of Ramillies, which were to be ſupported by the whole in-fantry.</p><p>Gur artillery began to cannonade the enemy at one ; at about two, the attack began with the poſt of Fran-quenies, where our infantry had the good fortune to drive the enemy from the hedges, where they were ad-vantageouſly poſted, and at the ſame time all the caval-ry of our left wing advanced to attack that of the enemy’s right ; ſoon aſter aſl was in action. whilſt the cavalry were engaged, the village of Ramillies was likewiſe attacked, and forced after a vigorous reſiſtance.</p><p>The battle laſted about two hours, and was pretty obſtinate; butfo ſoon as our cavalry had gained ground enough to attack the enemy in flank, they began to give way ; at the ſame time all their infantry were put in diforder, ſo that the whole retreated in great cofiſu-ſion. The cavalry of their leſt wing formed a little upon the high ground, between oſſuz and Mount St Andrew, to favour their retreat : but after the infantry and cavalry of our right wing had filed off between the bottom of the village of Ramillies and oſſuz, the whole army marched in feveral columns to attack the enemy anew ; but they gave way before we could come up with them, and retired in great confuſion, ſome towards the defile of the Abbey De La Ramée and towards Dongelberge, others towards Judogne, and others again towards Hougarde. They were purſued aſl night ſo cloſely that they were obliged to abandon all their artillery and baggage, part of which was found at Judog-ne and at Hougarde, with their cheſts of ammunition.</p><p>The enemy loſt above 30,000 men, 60 cannon, 8 mortars, ſtandards, colours, baggage, &amp;c. ; we about 3000. The reſt of the campaign was ſpent in the ſie-ges of oſtend, Menin, and Aeth. In fourteen days the Duke defeated and diſperſed the beſt appointed ar~ my the Fçench ever had, and recovered all Spaniſh Brabant, the marquifate of the holy Roman empire. The army of the enemy conſiſted of 76 battalions and 142 ſquadrons, including the king’s houſhold troops <hi rend="italic">(La </hi><hi rend="italic">Maifon du Roi);</hi>  and the army of the allies was 74 bat-talions and 123 ſquadrons. Conſidering the import-ance of the victory, the loſs of the allies was very ſmaſl, not above 1100 being killed, and 2600 wounded.</p><p>RAMLA, the modern name of Arimathea. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Arimathea.</hi></p><p>RAMMER, an inſtrument uſed ſor driving down ſtones ©r piles into the ground; or for beating the earth, m order to render it more ſolid for a foundation.</p><p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps">Rammer oſ </hi></hi><hi rend="italic">a </hi><hi rend="italic">Gun,</hi>  the <hi rend="italic">Gm-βiek</hi>  ; a rod uſed in charging of a gun, to drive home the powder, as alſo the ſhot, and the wad which keeps the ſhot from roſling out.</p><p>RAMPANT, in heraldry, a term applied to a lion, leopard, or other beaſt that ffu,nds on its hind legs, and rears up his fore-feet in the poſture of climbing, ſhowing only half his face, as one eye, &amp;c. It is diffe-rent from ſaliant, in which the beaſt ſeems ſpringing forward as if making a ſally.</p><p>RAMPART, in fortification, is an elevation of earth round a place capable of reſiſting the cannon of an enemy ; and formed into baſtions, curtins, &amp;c.</p><p>RAMPHASTOS, the <hi rend="smallcaps">Toucan,</hi>  in ornithology. See Rhamphastos.</p><p>RAMSAY (Allan), the Scots paſtoral poet, was a barber in Edinburgh in the early part of the preſent century. His taſte in poetry, however, has juſtly raiſed him to a degree of fame that may in ſomc meafure be conſidered as a recompenſe for the frowns of fortune. His ſongs are in univerſal eſteem ; as is alſo the only dramatic performance attributed to him, viz. <hi rend="italic">Patte and R-)ger,</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">The Gentle Shepherd,</hi>  a Scots pa-ſtoral. He died in 1743 ; and was father to the ingenious Mr Ramſay, a celebrated painter of the preſent age, and who has likewiſe diſtinguiſhed himſelf by ſomc well-written tracts ©n various branches of polite literature, particularly the <hi rend="italic">Invelligator.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Ramsay (Andrew Michael), generally known bv the name of the </hi><hi rend="italic">Chevalier Ramſay,</hi>  was a polite Scots writer, born of a good family at Ayr in 1686. His good parts and learning recommended him to be tutor t® the ſon of the earl of wemyſs ; after which, concei-. ving a diſguſt at the religion in which he had been edu-cated, he in the ſame ill humour reviewed other Chriſtian churches ; and, finding none to his liking, reſted for a while in Deifm. while he was in this uncertain ſtate of mind, he went to Leyden ; where, falling into the company of one Poiret a royſtic divine, he received the infection of myſticifm : which prompted him to con-ſult M. Fenelon, the celebrated archbiſhop of Cambrav, who had imbibed principles of the ſame nature ; and who gained him over to the Catholic religion in 1709. The ſubſequent courſe of his life received its direction from his friendſhip and connections with this prelate ; and being appointed, governor to the duke de Chateau Thierry, and the prince de Turenne, he was madc a knight of the order of St Lazarus, He was ſent for to Rome by the chevalier de St George, to undertake the education of his children ; but he found ſo many intrigues and diſſenſions on his arrival there in 1724, that he obtained the Chevalier’s leave to return to Pa-ris. He died in 1743, <hi rend="sup">1</hi>'<hi rend="sup">n</hi>  the °fſi<hi rend="sup">ce θ</hi>f intendant to the duke of Bouillon, prince de Turenne. The .moſt ca-pital work of his writing is the<hi rend="italic">Travels of Cyrus,</hi>  which has been ſeveral times printed in Engliſh.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Ramsay (the Reverend James), ſo juſtly celebrated for his philanthropy, was, on the 25th of Ju-ly </hi><hi rend="sup">1</hi>733&gt; born at Fraferſhurgh, a ſmall town in the county of Aberdeen, North Britain. His defcent w<hi rend="sup">,</hi>as honourable, being, through his father, from the Ramſays of Melroſe in Banffshire, and through his mother, from the ogilvies of Purie in Angus. Hi⅜-parents were of characters the moſt reſpectable, but in circumſtances by no means affluent. From his earlieſt years he difcovered a ſerious diſpoſition, and a ſtrong thirſt for knowledge ; and aſter paſſing through the courſe of a Scotch grammar ſchool education, he was inclined to purſue the ſtudies requiſite to ſit him for the profeffion of a clergyman ; an inclination with which the wiſhes of his mother, a woman of eminent piety, powerfully concurred. Several circumſtances, however, conſpired to divert him for a time from his favourite purſuit.</p><p>He was educated in the epiſcopal perſuaſion ; and ha-ving been unhappy enough to loſe his father while yet very young, he found, upon his advancing towards the ſtate of manhood, that the joint fortunes of himſelf and..</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>