<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>certain butterflies diſcharged from them as they were high up in the air. But it ſeems a very wild conjec-ture, as we know of no butterfly whoſe excrements or eggs are of ſuch a colour, or whoſe abode is ſo high, or their flocks ſo numerous, as to be the occaſion of this.</p><p>It is moſt probable that theſe bloody waters were never ſeen falling ; but that people feeing the ſtanding ■waters b∙lood∙ coloured, were affured, from their not knowing how it ſhould elfe happen, that it had rained blood into them. A very memorable inſtance of this there was at the Hague in the year 1670. Swammerdam, who relates it, tells us, that one morning the whole town was in an uproar on finding their lakes and ditches full of blood, as they thought ; and having been certainly full of water the night before, they agreed it muſt have rained blood in the night : but a certain phy-ſician went down to one of the canals, and taking home a quantity of this blood-coloured water, he examined it by the microfcope, and found that the water was water ſtill, and had not at all changed its colour ; but that it was full of prodigious ſwarms of ſmall red animals, all alive, and very nimble in their motions, whoſe colour and prodigious number gave a red tinge to the whole body of the water they lived in, on a leſs accurate in-ſpection. The certainty that this was the caſe, did not however perſuade the Hollanders to part with the mi-racle : they prudently concluded, that the ſudden ap-pearancε of ſuch a number of animals was as great a prodigy as the raining of blood would have been ; and are aſſured to this day, that this portent foretold the ſcene of war and deſtruction which Louis XIV. afterwards brought into that country, which had before enjoyed 40 years uninterrupted peace.</p><p>The animals which thus colour the water of lakes and ponds are the <hi rend="italic">pulices arboreſcentes</hi>  of Swammerdam, or the water-fleas with branched horns. Thefe creatures are of a reddiſh-yellow cr flame colour : they live about the ſides of ditches, under weeds, and among the mud. ; and are therefore the leſs viſible, except at a certain time, which is in the end or beginning of June : it is at this time that theſe little animals leave their receſſes to float looſe about the water, to meet for the propagation of their ſpecies, and by that means become viſible in the colour they give the water. This is viſible, more or leſs, in one part or other of almoſt all ſtanding waters at this feafon ; and it is always at this ſeaſon that the bloody waters have alarmed the ignorant. See <hi rend="italic">Pυ-IEX Moηocιιlus.</hi></p><p>The raining of <hi rend="italic">frogs</hi>  is a thing not leſs wonderful in the accounts of authors who love the marvellous, than thoſe of blood or ſtones ; and this is ſuppofed to hap-pen ſo often, that there are multitudes who pretend to have been eye-witneſſes of it. Theſe rains of frogs always happen after very dry ſeaſons, and are much more frequent in the hotter countries than in the cold ones. In Italy they are very frequent ; and it is not uncommon to ſee the ſtreets of Rome ſwaiming both with young frogs and toads in an inſtant in a ſhower of rain ; they hopping everywhere between the people’s legs as they walk, though there was not the leaſt appearance of them before. Nay, they have been feen to fall through the air down upon the pavements. This ſeems a ſtrong circumſtance in favour of their being raincd down from the clouds ; but, when ſtrictly examined, it comes to nothing : for theſe frogs that are ſeen to fall, are always found dead, lamed, or bruiſed by the fall, and never hop about as the reſt; and they are never ſeen to fall, except cloſe under the walls of houſes, from the roofs and gutter of which they have accidentally flipped down. Some people, who love to add to ſtrange things yet ſtranger, affirm that they have had the young frogs fall into their hats in the midſt of an open field ; but this is idle, and wholly falſe.</p><p>others, who cannot agree to their falling from the clouds, have tried to ſolve the difficulty of their ſud-den appearance, by ſuppoſing them hatched out of the egg, or ſpawn, by theſe rains. Nay, fome have ſuppo-ſed them made immediatelyout of the duſt : but there are unanſwerable arguments againſt all theſe ſuppoſitions. Equivocal generation, or the fpontaneous production of animals out of duſt, is now wholly exploded. The fall from the clouds muſt deſtroy and kill thefe tender and ſoft-bodied animals : and they cannot be at this time hatched immediately out of eggs ; becauſe the young frog does not make its appearance from the egg in form, but has its hinder legs enveloped in a fl&lt;in, and is what we call a <hi rend="italic">tadpole ;</hi>  and the young frogs are at leaſt 100 times larger at the time of their appearance, than the egg from which they ſhould be hatched.</p><p>It is beyond a doubt, that the frogs which make their appearance at this time, were hatched and in being long before : but that the dry feaſons had injured them, and kept them ſluggiſhly in holes or coverts ; and that all the rain does, is the enlivening them, giving them new ſpirits, and calling them forth to ſeek new habitations, and enjoy the element they were deſtined in great part to live in. Theophraſtus, the greateſt of all the naturaliſts of antiquity, has affirmed the fame thing, we find that the error of ſuppoſing theſe creatures to fall from the clouds was as early as that author’s time ; and alſo that the truth, in regard to their appearance, was as early known ; though, in the ages ſince, authors have taken care to conceal the truth, and to hand down to us the error, we find this venerable ſage, in a fragment of his on the generation of animals which appear on a ſudden, bantering the opinion, and aſſerting that they were hatched and living long before. The world owes, however, to the accurate Signior Redi the great proof of this truth, which Theophraſtus only has affirmed : for this gentleman, diſſecting ſome of thefe new-appearing frogs, found in their ſtomachs herbs and other half-di-geſted food ; and, openly ſhowing this to his credulous countrymen, aſked them whether they thought that na-ture, which engendered, according to their opinion, theſe animals in the clouds, had alfo been ſo provident as to engendcr grais there for their food and nouriſh-rnent ?</p><p>To the raining of frogs we ought to add the raining of <hi rend="italic">grajshοpι ers</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">locυjis,</hi>  which have ſometimes appeared in prodigious numbers, and devoured the fruits of the earth. There has not been the leaſt pretence for the luppoſing that theie animals defcended from the clouds, but that they appeared on a fudden in prodigious numbers. The naturaliſt, who knows the many ac-ciden∙ts attending the eggs of theie and other the like animals, cannot but know that ſome ſeafons will prove particularly favourable to the hatching them, and the prodigious number of eggs that many infects lay could not but every year bring us ſuch abundance of the young, were they not liable to many accidents, and had not provident nature taken care, as in many plants, to continue</p></body></text></TEI>