<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>For, when GH repreſents the direct impulfe of a particle, GI is the abfolute oblique impulſe, and GO is the effective impulſe in the direction G Ο : Now GI is to GO as radius to the fine of G10, and G10 is the complement of IG0, and is therefore equal to CG0, "the angle of obliquity.</p><p>Therefore <hi rend="italic">f</hi>  : &lt;r~R : Sin. 0.</p><p>But F : <hi rend="italic">ſ~</hi>  R<hi rend="sup">1</hi>  : Sin.*z'</p><p>Therefore F : τ = R<hi rend="sup">3</hi> : Sir∣.<hi rend="sup">,</hi>i × Sin.0. and</p><p><hi rend="italic">'φ</hi>  ~F × Sin.<hi rend="sup">5</hi>/ × Sin. O.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Cor.—</hi>The direct impulſe on any ſurface is to the effective oblique impiſtfe in the direction of the ftream, as the cube of radius to the cube of the fine of incidence. For draw I Q^and GP perpendicular'to GH, and IP perpendicular to GP ; then the abſolute im-pulſe GI is equivalent to the impulſe GQJ∏ the direc-tion ol the ſtream, and GP, which may be called the tranfverſe impulfe. The angle G I QJs evidently equal to the angle GHI, or FGC, the angle of incidence.</p><p>Therefore ∕ : <hi rend="sub">p</hi> =GI : GQ<hi rend="sub">j</hi> = R : Sin.<hi rend="italic">i.</hi></p><p>"But F : <hi rend="italic">ſ ~</hi>     R’    : Sin.’/.</p><p>Therefore F : <hi rend="italic">&lt;P —    </hi>R ’ : Sin.<hi rend="sup">3</hi><hi rend="italic">i.</hi></p><p>And ¢ — F × Sin.’/.</p><p>Before we proceed further, we ſhall conſider the im-pulſe on a ſuiface which is alſo in motion. This is evidently a frequent and an important cafe. It is perhaps the moſt frequent and important : It is the caſe of a ſhip under fail, and of a wind or water-mill at work.</p><p>Tlιerefore, let a ſtream of ſiuid, moving with the direction and velocity DE, meet a plane BC, (fig. I. <hi rend="sup">l</hi>∙ n<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 2. ), which is moving parallel to itſelf in the direction and with the velocity DF : It is required to determine</p><p>the impulſe ?</p><p>Nothing is more eaſy : The mutual actions of bodies depend on their relative motions only. The motion DE of thc fluid relative to BC, which is alſo in motion, is compounded of the real motion of the fluid and the oppofite to the real motion of the body. There-fore produce FD till D ∕~E&gt;F, and complete the pa-'rallelogram D <hi rend="italic">f e</hi>  E, and draw the diagonal D <hi rend="italic">e.</hi>  The ⅛∏pulfe on the plane is the ſame as if the plane were at reſt, and evcιy particle of the fluid impelled it in the direction and with the velocity D <hi rend="italic">e</hi>  ; and may therefore be determined by the foregoing propoſition. This pro-pofition applies to every poſſible caſe ; and we ſhall not beſtow more time on it, but reſerve the important mo-dification of the general propofition for the caſes which ſhall occur in thc practical applications of the whole doctrine of the impulſe and refiſtance of fluids.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Prop. IV. The direct impulſe of a ſtream of fluid, whoſe breadth is given, is to its oblique effective impulfe in the direction of the ſtream, as the ſquare of radius to the ſquare of the fine of the angle of incidence.</hi></p><p>For the number of filaments which occupy the ob-lique plane BC, would occupy the portion NC of a perpendicular plane, and therefore we have only to compare the perpendicular impulfe on any point V with the effective impulſe made by the ſame filament FV on the oblique plane at G. Now GH fepreſents the impulſe which this filament would make at V ; and G Q~ is the effective impulſe oſ the ſame filament at G, eſtimated in the direction G H of the ſtream ; and G H is tβ GQ as G H<hi rend="sup">i</hi>  to GΣ<hi rend="sup">1</hi>, that is, as rad.<hi rend="sup">i</hi>  to fin/fi</p><p><hi rend="italic">Cor.</hi>  I. The effective impulſe in the direction oſ the ſtream on any plane ſurface BC, is to the direct impulfe on its baſe BR or SE, as the ſquare of the fine of the angle of incidence to the fquare of the radius.</p><p>2. If an ifoſceles wedge ACB (fig. 2.) be expofed to a ſtream of fluid moving in the direction of its 'height CD, the impulſe on the fides is to the direct impulfe on the baſe as the ſquare of half the bafe AD to the ſquare of the fide AC, or as the fquare of the fine of half the angle of the wedge to the ſquare of the radius. For it is evident, that in this caſe the two tranſverſe impulſes, ſuch as GP in fig. ι, balance each other, and the only impulſe which can be obferved is the ſum of the two impulfes, luch as GQjff ſig. ι, which are to be compared with the impulſes on the two halves AD, DB of the baſe. Now AC : AB ≈ rad. : fin. ACD, and ACD is equal to the angle of incidence.</p><p>Therefore, if the angle ACB is a right angle, and ACD is half a right angle, the ſquare of AC is twice the ſquare of AD, ’ and the impulſe on the ſides of a rectangular wedge is half the impulſe on its baſe.</p><p>Alſo, if a cube ACBE (ſig. 3.) be expofed to a ſtream moving in a direction perpendicular to one of its ſides, and then to a ſtream moving in a direction perpendicular to one of its diagonal planes, the impulſe in the ſirſt caſe will be to the irapulſe in the ſecond as */ ?, to i. Call the perpendicular impulſe on a ſide F, and the perpendicular impulſe on its diagonal plane <hi rend="italic">f<hi rend="sub">t</hi></hi>  and the effective oblique impulſe on its ſides <hi rend="italic">&lt;p</hi>  ;—we have</p><p>F :/= AC : AB ≈ 1 : V<hi rend="sup">z</hi>2, and</p><p>/: f = AChAD<hi rend="sup">,</hi>= 2:1. Therefore</p><p>E : ;&gt; —    2 : √<hi rend="sup">,</hi>2, = √2 : 1, or</p><p>very nearly as 10 to 7.</p><p>The ſame reaſoning will apply to a pyramid whoſe baſe is a regular polygon, and whofe axis is perpendicu-lar to the bafe. If ſuch a pyramid is expofed to a ſtream of fluid moving in the direction of the axis, the direct impulſe on the baſe is to the effective impulſe on the pyramid, as the ſquare of the radius to the fquare of the fine of the angle which the axis makes with the ſides of the pyramid. *</p><p>And, in like manner, the direct impulſion on the baſe of a right cone is to the effective impulſion on the conical ſurface, as the ſquare of the radius to the ſquare of the fine of half the angle at the vertex of the cone. This is demonitrated, by ſuppoſing the cone to be a pyramid of an infinite number of ſides.</p><p>we may in this manner compare the impulſe on any polygonal ſurface with the impulſe on its baſe, by comparing apart the impulſes on each plane with thoſe in their correfponding bales, and taking their ſum.</p><p>And we may compare the impulſe on a curved fur-face with that on its baſe, by reſolving the curved ſurface into, elementary planes, each of which is impelled by an elementary filament of the ftream.</p><p>The following beautiful propofition, given by Le Seur and Jaquier, in their Commentary on the ſecond Book of Newton’s Principia, with a few examples of its application, will ſuſſice for any further account of this theory.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Prop.</hi>  V.—Let ADB (fig. 4.) be the ſection of a ſurface of fimple curvature, ſuch as is the fnrface of a cylinder. Let this be expofed to the action of a ſtuid moving in the direction AC. Let BC be the</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>