<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>fioners therein named ſhould be impowered to accept fo much of any future loan as they ſhould have caſh be-longing to the public to pay for. This, he ſaid, would relieve that diſtreſs the country would otherwiſe be under, when, on account of a war, it might be ncceſſary to raiſe a new Ioan : whenever that ſhoiſid be the caſe, his opinion was, that the miniſter ſhould not only raiſe taxes ſufficiently productive to pay the intereſt of the· loan, but alſo ſufficient to make good to the finking, fund whatſoever had been taken from it.</p><p>If, therefore, for inſtance, at any future period a loan of fix millions was propoſed, and there was at that time one million in the hands of the commiſſioners, in fuch caſe they ſhould take a million of the loan, and the <hi rend="italic">bonus</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">douceur</hi>  thereupon ſhould be received by them for the public. Thus government would only have five millions to borrow inſtead of fix ; and from ſueh a mode of proceeding, he ſaid, it was evident great benefit would ariſe to the public.</p><p>This claule was received by Mr Pitt with the ſtrcngeſt marks of approbation, as was likewiſe another, moved by Mr Pulteney, enabling the commiſſioners named in the bill to continue purchafing ſtock for the public when· it is above par, unleſs otherwiſe directed by parliament, with theſe additional clauſes the bill was read a third-time on the 15th of May, and carried up to the Lords, where it alfo paſſed without meeting with any material oppoſition, and afterwards received the royal aſſent.</p><p><hi rend="sup">r</hi>Γhe operation of this bill ſurpaſſed perhaps the mi-niſter’s moſt ſanguine expectation. The fund was ably managed, and judiciouſly applied ; and in 1793 the commiſſioners had extinguiſhed ſome millions of■ the public debt. The war, however, into which the nation was that year involved, and of which there is yet no cer-tain proſpect of a near end, has made it neceſlary to bor-row additional ſums, ſo large, that .many years of peace muſt elapſe before the operation of the fund can contribute ſenſibly. to the relief of the people. The clear produce of the taxes raiſed on the people of this.country was, in the year; 1792, very near L.. 17,000,oco ; and it muſt henceforth, from the accumulation of the debt, and the enormous expence of the prefent war, be neceſſarily rendered greater.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Revenue,</hi>  in hunting, a fleſhy lump formed chiefly by a cluſter of whitiſh worms on the head of the deer, ſuppoſed to occafion the caſting of their horns by gnaw-ing them at the root.</p><p>REVERBERATION, in phyſics, the act of a body repelling or reflecting another after its impinging thereon.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Reverberation,</hi>  in chemiſtry, denotes a kind of circulation of the flame by means of a reverberatory furnace.</p><p>REVERBERATORY, or <hi rend="italic">REfΕREERA<hi rend="sup">t</hi>∏NG Furnace.</hi>  See <hi rend="smallcaps">Chf.mis </hi><hi rend="italic">τκ∖-Iηdex zt Furnace,</hi>  and <hi rend="smallcaps">Furnace;</hi></p><p>REVEREND, a title of refpect given to eccleτ fiaſtics.—The religious abroad are called <hi rend="italic">reverend fathers,</hi>  and abbeſſes, prioreſſes, &amp;c« <hi rend="italic">reverend mothers.</hi>  In England, biſhops are <hi rend="italic">right reverend,</hi>  and archbiſhops <hi rend="italic">τnofi reverend.</hi>  In France, before the Revolution, their biſhops, archbiſhopa, and abbots, were .all alike <hi rend="italic">mofi reverend.</hi>  In Scotland the clergy individually are <hi rend="italic">reverend,</hi>  a ſynod is <hi rend="italic">very reverend,</hi>  .and the general affembly is <hi rend="italic">venerable.</hi></p><p>REVERIE, the ſame with delirium, raving, or diffraction. It is uſed alſo for any ridiculous, extra</p><p>vagant imagination, action, or propoſition, a chimera, or viſion. But the moſt ordinary uſe of the word among Engliſh writers, is for a deep diſorderly muſing or meditation.</p><p>REVERSAL <hi rend="italic">oſ </hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Judgment,</hi>  inlaw. A judgment may be falſiſied, reverſed, or voided, in the firſt place; <hi rend="italic">without a writ of error,</hi>  for matters foreign fo or <hi rend="italic">dehors </hi>the record, that is, not apparent upon the face of it ; ſo that they cannot be affigned for error in the ſuperior court, which can only judge from what appears in the record itſelf ; and therefore, if the whole record be not certified, or not truly certified, by the inferior court, the party injured thereby (in both civil and criminal cafes) may allege a diminution of the record, and cauſe it to be rectified. Thus, if any judgment whatever be given by perſons who had no good commiſſion to pro-ceed againſt the perſon condemned, it is void ; and may be falfified by ſhewing the ſpecial matter, without writ of error. As, where a commiſſion iffues to A and B, and twelve others, or any two of them, of which A or B ſhall be one, to take and try indictments ; and any of the other twelve proceed without the interpoſition or preſence of either A or B : in this cafe all proceedings, trials, convictions, and judgments, are void for want of a proper authority in the commiſſioners, and may be falſiſied upon bare inſpection, without the trouble of a writ of error ; it being a high miſdemeanour in the judges fo proceeding, and little (if any thing) ſhort of murder in them all, in caſe the perſon ſo attainted be executed and ſuffer death. So likewiſe if a man pur*</p><p>chafes land of another ; and afterwards the vender is<hi rend="sub">i </hi>either by outlawry or his own confeſſion, convicted and attainted of treaſon or felony previous to the ſale or alienation ; whereby ſuch land becomes liable to forfeit-ure or eſcheat : now, upon any trial, the purchaſer is at liberty, without bringing any writ of error, to falſify not only the time of the felony or treaſon ſuppofed, but the very point of the felony or treafon itſelf ; and is not concluded by the confeffion or the outlawry of the vender, though the vender himſelf is concluded, and not ſuffered now to deny the fact, which he has by confeſſion or flight acknowledged. But if ſuch attainder of the vender was by verdict, on the oath of his peers, the alienee cannot be received to falſify or contradict the<hi rend="italic">fact </hi>of the crime committed ; though he is at liberty to prove a miſtake in <hi rend="italic">time,οx</hi>  that the offence was committed after the alienation, and not before..</p><p>Secondly, a judgment may be reverfed, <hi rend="italic">by writ of error,</hi>  which lies from all inferior criminal juriſdictions to the court of king’s-bench, and from the king’s-bench to the hαufe of peers ; ,and may be brought for notorious miſtakes in the judgment or other parts of the record : as where a man is found guilty of perjury, and receives the judgment of felony, or for other leſs palpable errors ; fuch as any irregularity, omiffion, or want of form in the proceſs of outlawry, or proclama-tions ; the want of a proper addition to the defendant’s name, according to the ſtatute of additions ; for not properly naming the ſheriff or other officer of the court, or not duly deſcribing where his county-court was held: for laying an offence, committed in the time of the late king, to be done againſt the peace of the preſent ; and for many other ſimilar. causes, which (though allowed out of tenderneſs to life and liberty) are not much to the credit or advanv⅛meffΓ of the national juſtice.—-Theſe writs of error, i⅛ reverſe judgments in caſe of.</p><p>4</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>