<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Γ.    IL    ∏L    IV,</p><p>x8a    ΙΟΟΟΟ    IOOOQ    ο</p><p>1&lt;58    9⅜<hi rend="sup">0</hi>    9<hi rend="sup">s</hi>93    ÷3</p><p>156    95<hi rend="sup">68</hi>    9578    ÷iQ</p><p>144    9045    9°<hi rend="sup">s</hi>4    +39</p><p>132    8346    8446    ÷ wo</p><p>J3Q    7500    77iQ    4-210</p><p>jo8    6545    6925    4-380</p><p>96    5523    6148    +625</p><p>84    4478    543J    +955</p><p>72    3455    4800    +1345</p><p>60    2500    4404    +<hi rend="sup">1</hi>9<hi rend="sup">o</hi>4</p><p>48    1654    4240    -j-2586</p><p>36    955    4142    ÷3<hi rend="sup">l8</hi>7</p><p>24    43 g    4063    + 3<hi rend="smallcaps"><hi rend="sup">6</hi>3<hi rend="sup">i</hi></hi></p><p>12    109    3999    4-3890</p><p>The reſiſtance to 1 ſquare foot, French meaſure, moving with the velocity of 2,56 feet pci ſecond, was ve-ry nearly 7,625 pounds French.</p><p>Reducing theſe to Engliſh meaſures, we have the ſuiface = l√363 feet, the velocity of the motion equal to 2,7263 feet per ſecond, and the reſiſtance equal to 8,234 pounds avoirdupois. The weight of a column of ireſh water of this baſe, and having for its height the fall neceffary for communicating this velocity, is 8,264 pounds avoirdupois. TlTe reſiſtances to other velocities were accurately proportional to the ſquares of the velocities.</p><p>There is great diverſity in the value which different authors have deduced for the abſolute reſiſtance of wa-ter from their experiments. In the value now given nothing is taken into account but the inertia of the water. The accumulation againſt the forepart of the boχ was carefully noted, and the ſtatical preffure backwards, ariſing from this cauſe, was ſubtracted from the whole reſiſtance to the drag. There had not been a ſufficient variety of experiments for diſeovering the ſhare which tenacity and friction produced ; fo that the number of pounds ſet down here may be conſidered as fomewhat ſuperior to the mere effects of the inertia of the water, we think, upon the whole, that it is the moſt accurate determination yet given of the reſiſtance to a body in motion : but we ſhall afterwards ſee reafons for belie -ving, that the impulſe of a running ſtream having the ſame velocity is ſomewhat greater ; and this is the form in which moſt of the experiments have been made.</p><p>Alſo obſerve, that the refiſtance here given is that to a veffel two feet broad and deep and four feet long. The refiſtance to a plane of two feet broad and deep would probably have exceeded this in the proportion of 15,22 to 14,54, for reafons we ſhall ſee afterwards.</p><p>From the experiments of Chevalier Buat, it appears that a body of one foot ſquare, French meaſure, and two feet long, having its centre 15 inches under water, moving three French feet per ſecond, fuſtained a preffure of 14,54 French pounds, or 15,63 Engliſh. This redu-ced in the proportion of 3<hi rend="sup">1</hi> to 2,56<hi rend="sup">i</hi> gives 11,43 pounds, conſiderably exceeding the 8,24.</p><p>Mr Bouguer, in his <hi rend="italic">Manœuvre des Vajſeaux,</hi>  fays, that he found the reſiſtance of ſea-water to a velocity of one foot to be 23 ounces <hi rend="italic">poids des Marc.</hi></p><p>The Chevalier Borda found the reſiſtance of ſea-water to the face of a cubic foot, moving againſt the water one foot per ſecond, to be 21 ounces nearly. But this experiment iβ complicated ; the wave wag net de. ducted ; and it was not a plane, but a cube.</p><p>Don George d’Ulloa found the impulfe of a ſtream of fea-water, running two feet per fecond on a foot ſquare, to be 15Î pounds Engliſh meaſure. This greatly exceeds all the values given by others.</p><p>From theſe experiments we learn, in the firſt place, that the direct refiſtance to a motion of a plane furface through water, is very nearly equal to the weight of a column of water having that ſurface for its baſc, and for its height the fall producing the velocity of the motion. This is but one half of the refiſtance determined by the preceding theory. It agrees, however, very well with the beſt experiments made by other philoſo-phers on bodies totally immerfed or ſurrounded by the fluid ; and ſuſſiciently ſhows, that there muſt be ſome fallacy in the principles or reaſoning by which this re-ſult of the theory is ſuppoſed to be deduced. We ſhall have occafion to return to this again.</p><p>But we ſee that the effects of the obliquity of inci-dence deviate enormouſly from the theory, and thafc this deviation increaſes rapidly as the acuteneſs of the prow increaſes. In the prow of 6o<hi rend="sup">0</hi> the deviation is nearly equal to the whole refiſtance pointed out by the theory, and in the prow of 12<hi rend="sup">0</hi> it is nearly 40 times greater than the theoretical refiſtance.</p><p>The refiſtance of the prow of 90<hi rend="sup">o</hi> ſhould be one half the reſtſtance of the baſe. we have not fitch a prow ; but the medium between the reſiſtance of the prow of 96 and 84 is 5790, inſtead of 500.</p><p>Theſe experiments are very conform to thoſe of other authors on plane ſurfaces. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Robins found the re-ſiſtance of the air to a pyramid of 45<hi rend="sup">0</hi>, with its apex foremoſt, was to that of its bafe as 1000 to 1411, in-ſtead of-O∏e to two. Chevalier Borda found the refiſtance of a cube, moving in water in the direction of the fide, was to the oblique refiſtance, when it was moved in the direction of the diagonal, in the proportion of 5∣∙ to 7 ; whereas it ſhould have been that of √2 to 1, or of 10 to 7 nearly. He alſo found, that a wedge whoſe angle was 90°, moving in air, gave for the proportion of the reſiſtances of the edge and baſe 7281 : 10000, inſtead of 5000 : 10000, Alfo when the angle of the wedge was 60<hi rend="sup">0</hi>, the refiſtances of the edge and baſe were 52 and 100, inſtead of 25 and 100.</p><p>In ſhort, in all the cafes oſ oblique plane ſurfaces, the reſiſtances were greater than thoſe which are affigned by the theory. The theoretical law agrees tolerably with obſervation in large angles of incidence, that is, in incidences not differing very far from the perpendicular ; but in more acute prows the reſiſtances are more nearly proportional to the fines of incidence than to their ſquares.</p><p>The academicians deduced from theſe experiments an expreſſion of the general value of the refiſtance, which correſponds tolerably well with obſervation. Thus let <hi rend="italic">x</hi>  be the complement of the half angle of the prow, and let P be the direct preffure or reſiftance, with an incidence of 90<hi rend="sup">o</hi>, and<hi rend="italic">p</hi>  the effective oblique preffure : then <hi rend="italic">p ~</hi>  P × coſine <hi rend="sup">,</hi>  * + 3,t53    ‘ This</p><p>gives for a prow of 12<hi rend="sup">0</hi> an error in defect about <hi rend="sub">τ</hi>⅛, and in larger angles it is much nearer the truth ;and this is exact enough for aβ!y practice.</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>