<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>to pay attention to the ſame duties. He likewiſe en-jυins works of beneficence, deſires the prieſt to relieve the diſtreſſed, and to build houſes for the accommodation of ſtrangers of whatever religion ; and ſays, it is a diſgrace for Pagans to difregard thoſe of their own religion, while Chriſtians do kind offices to ſtrangers and enemies. This is indeed an eminent inſtance of the happy influence of Chriſtianity even on the ſentiments and manners of thoſe who regarded the Chriſtian name with abhorrence.</p><p>Upon the whole then, may we not, from the parti-ciſlars here exhibited concerning the influence of this religion on the manners and happineſs of men in ſociety, conclude that Chriſtianity is infinitely ſuperior to the ſuperſtitions of Paganiſm ? as being in its tendency unifoιraly favourable to the virtue and the happinefs of mankind, and even to the ſyſtem of religion and laws delivered by Moſes to the children of Iſrael : becauſe, while the religion of the Jews was calculated only for one particular nation, and it may almoſt be ſaid for one particular ſtage in the progreſs of ſociety, Chriſtiani-ty is an univerſal religion, formed to exert its happy influence in all ages and among all nations ; and has a tendency to diſpel the ſhades of barliariſm and ignorance, to promote the cultivation of the powers of the human underſtanding, and to encourage every virtuous refinement of manners.</p><p>V. Another religion, which has made and ſtill makes a conſpicuous figure in the world remains yet to be examined. The religion of Mahomet is that which we here allude to. whether we conſider through what an extenſive part of the globe that religion prevails, the political importance of the nations among whom it is profeſſed, or the ſtriking peculiarity of cha-racter by which it is diſtinguiſhed from all other religious ſyſtems—it is for all theſe reafons well worthy of particular notice. Like the Jewiſh religion, it is not barely a ſyſtem oſ religious doctrines and general moral precepts ; it forms both the civil legiſlature and. the religious ſyſtem of thofe nations among whom it is profeſſed ; and, like it too, it would appear to be calcula-t⅛d rather for one particular period in the progreſs of mankind from rudenefs to refinement, than for all ages and all ſtates of fociety.</p><p>The hiſtory of its origin is pretty well known, and we have had occaſion to enlarge upon it under a former article (fée Mahomet and&lt; Mahometanism). ∖Ve are not here to trace the impoſtures of the prophet, or to conſider the arts by which, he io ſuccefsfully accompliſhed his deſigns ; but merely to eonſider the morality of his religion, and its influence on civil order and the happineſs of fociety.</p><p>If we view the ſtate of the- nations among whom it is eſtabliſhed, we cannot hefitate a moment to declare if friendly to . ignorance, to deſpotiſm, and to impurity of manners- The Turks, the Perfians, and the Malays, are all Mahometans ; and in reviewing their hiſtory aud confidering their preſent ſtate, we might find a ſufficient nnmhër of facts to juſtify the above aflertion and we muſt not neglect to obſerve, that, as thoſe nations are not known to have ever been ſince their con-verfion to Mâhometanifm under a much happier government, or in a much more civilized ſtate than at preſent, it cannot be, with any degree of fairnefs, argued, with refpect to Mahometaniſen as with reſpect to Chriitiani-.</p><p>ty, that it is only when its influence is ſo oppoſed by other cauſes as to prevent it from producing its full effects, that it does not conduct thoſe ſocieties among which it is eftabliſhed to an high ſtate of civilization and refinement.</p><p>Οηε, and that by no means an inconfiderable, part of the Koran, was occafionally invented to ſolve ſome difficulty with which the prophet found himſelf at the time perplexed, or to help him to the gratification of his ruling paſſions, luſt and ambition, when he and his followers were, at any time, unſucceſsful in thoſe wars by which he fought to propagate his religion, to prevent them from falling away into unbelief, or finking into deſpondency, he took care to inform them that God ſuſſered ſuch misfortunes to befal believers, as a pυniflιment for their fins, and to try their faith. The doctrine of predeſtination, which he affiduouſly inculcated, had an happy effect to perfuade his followers to ruſh boldly into the midſt of death and danger at his command. He prevailed with Zeyd to put away his -wife, married her himſelf, and pretended that his crime had the approbation of heaven ; and, in the Koran, he introduces the Deity approving of this marriage. Being repulſed from the fiege of Mecca, he made a league with the inhabitants ; but on the very next year, finding it convenient to ſurprife the city, by violating this treaty, he juſtified his perfidy by teaching his followers to difregard promiſes or leagues made with infidels. In ſome inſtances again, we find abſurd prohibitions en-joined for fimilar reafons : his officers, having on ſome occafion drunk to exceſs, excited much riot and confufion in the camp, he prohibited the uſe of wine and other inebriating liquors among his followers in future* Now, though it muſt be acknowledged that many evils ariſe from the uſe of theſe liquors, yet we cannot but think that, when uſed in moderation, they are in many cafés beneficial to men ; and certainly as much allowed by God as. opium, which the Mahometans have ſubſti-tuted in their place.</p><p>Mahomet· is allowed to have copied from the Chrb ſtian and the Jewiſh religions, as well as from the ido-latrous fiiperſtitions which prevailed through Arabia, and thus to have formed a motley mixture of reafon and abſurdity, of pure theiſm and wild ſuperſtition. He coniidered alfo the circumftances of his country, and the prejudices of his countrymen, when he attended to the former, he was generally judicious enough to fuit his doctrines and decifions to them with ſufficient ſkill ; the latter he alſo managed with the greateſt'art : but he entered into accommodation with them in in-ſtauces when a true prophet or a wiſe ;and upright le-gi∏ator would ſurely have oppofed them with decifive vigour. . where the prophet indulges his own fancy, <hi rend="sub">7 </hi>or borrows from the ſuperſtitions of hie countrymen, nothing can be more ridiculous than that.rhapſody of lies, contradictions, and extravagant fables, which he delivers to his followers.' Amazing are the abſurdities which he relates concerning the patriarchs, concerning . Solomon, and concerning- the&gt; animals that were affuιr bled in Noah’s ark.</p><p>But in the whole tiſſue cf abfurdities of which his ſyſtem confiſts, there is nothing mere abſurd, or more happily calculated to promote impurity of manners, than his deſcriptions of heaven and hell ; the ideas of future rewards and puniſhments which he fought to imprefe</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>