<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>adequate ideas and notions of every object in which they were intereſted, brought all their organs, external and internal, at once to their utmoſt poſſible ſtate of perfection ; taught them inſtantaneouſly the laws of reaſon-ing ; and, in one word, ſtored their minds with every branch of uſeful knowledge ? This is indeed our own opinion ; and it is perfectly agreeable to what we are taught by the Hebrew lawgiver. when God had formed Adam and Eve, Moſes does not ſay that he leſt them to acquire by flow degrees the ufe of their ſenfes and reaſoning powers, and to diſtinguiſh as they could fruits that were ſalutary from thoſe that were poiſonous. No : he placed them in a garden where every tree but one bore fruit fit for food ; he warned them particulaιly againſt the fruit of that tree; he brought before them the various animals which roamed through the garden ; he arranged theſe animals into their proper genera and ſpeciee ; and by teaching Adam to give them names, he communicated to the firſt pair the elements of language. This condeſcenſion appears in every reſpect worthy of perfect benevolence ; and indeed without it the helpleſs man and woman could not have lived one whole week. But it cannot be ſup-poſed, that amidſt ſo much uſeful inſtruction the gra-cious Creator would neglect to communicate to his rational creatures the knowledge of himſelf ; to inform them of their own origin, and the relation in which they ſtood to him ; and to ſtate in the plaineſt terms the duties incumbent on them in return for fo much goodnefs.</p><p>In what manner all this knowledge was communica-±ed, cannot be certainly known. It may have been in either of the following ways conceivable by us, or in others of which we can form no conception. God may have miraculouſly ſtored the minds of the ſirſt pair with adequate ideas and notions of ſenſible and intellectual objects ; and then by an internal operation of his own Spirit have enabled them to exert at once their rational faculties ſo as to difcover his exiſtence and attributes, together with the relation in which as creatures they ſtood to him their Almighty Creator. Ον, after rendering them capable of diſtinguiſhing objects by means of their ſenſes, of comparing their ideas, and underſtand-ing a language, he may have exhibited himtelt under ſome ſenſible emblem, and conducted them by degrees from one branch of knowledge to another, as a tehool-maſter conducts his pupilβ, till they were ſufficiently acquainted with every thing relating to their own happinefs and duty as rational, moral, and religious, creatures. In determining the queſtion before us, it is of no importance whether infinite wiſdom adopted either of theſe methods, or fome other different from them, both which we cannot conceive. The ordinary proceſs in which men acquire knowledge is, by the laws of their nature, extremely tedious. They cannot reafon before their minds be ſtored with ideas and notions ; and they cannot acquire theſe but through the medium of their ſenſes long exerciſed on external objects.</p><p>The progenitors of the human race, left to inform themſelves by this proceſs, muſt have inevitably periſhed before they had acquired one diſtinct notion ; and it is the fame thing with reſpect to the origin of religion, whether God preferved them from deſtruction by aa <hi rend="italic">internal</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">external</hi>  revelation. If he ſtored their minds at once with the rudiments of all uſeful knowledge, and</p><p>rendered them capable of exerting thcir rational faculties, ſo as, by tracing effects to their cauſes, to diſcover his being and attributes, he <hi rend="italic">revealed</hi>  himſelf to them as certainly as he did afterwards to Moſes, when to him he condeſcended to fpeak face to face.</p><p>If this reaſoning be admitted as fair and concluſive, and wc apprehend that thc principles on which it proceeds cannot be conſidered as ill-founded, we have advanced ſo far as to prove that mankind muſt have been originally enlightened by a revelation. But it is ſcarce neceſſary to obſerve, that this revelation mnſt have been handed down through ſucceeding generations. It could not fail to reach the era of the deluge. It is not abfurd to ſuppoſe, that he who ſpake from heaven to Adam, ſpake alſo to Noah. And both the revelation which had been handed down to the poſtdeluvian patriarch by tradition, and that which was communicated immediately to himſelf, would be by him made known to his deſcendants. Thus it appears almoſt impoſſible that ſome part of the religious ſentiments of mankind ſhould not have been derived from revelation ; and that not of the religious ſentiments of one particular family or tribe, but of almoſt all the nations of the earth.</p><p>This concluſion, which we have deduced by fair rea-ſoning from the benevolence of God and the nature of man, is confirmed by the authority of the Jewiſh and Chriſtian Scriptures, which are entitled to more implicit credit than all the other records of ancient hiſ-tory.</p><p>when we review the internal and external evidence of the authenticity of thefe ſacred books, we cannot for a moment hefitate to receive them as the genuine <hi rend="italic">word oſ God.</hi>  If we examine their internal character, they everywhere appear to be indeed the voice of Heaven. The creation of the world—-the manner in which this globe was ſirſt peopled—the deluge which ſwept away its inhabitants—the ſucceeding views of the ſtate of mankind in the next ages after the deluge—the calling of Abraham—the legiſlation of Moſes—the whole fe-ries of events which befel the Jewiſh nation—the prophecies—the appearance of Jeſus Chriſt, and the promulgation of his goſpel, as explained to us in the Scrip-tureβ—form one ſeries, which is, in the higheſt degree, illuſtrative of the power, wiſdom, and goodnefs of the Supreme Being.</p><p>while it muſt be allowed that the human mind is ever prone to debate the ſublime principles of true religion by enthuſiaſm and ſnperſtition, reaſon and can-dour will not for a moment heſitate to acknowledge, that the whole ſyſtem of revelation repretents the Supreme Being in the moſt fublime and amiable light : that, in it, religion appears effentially connected with morality : that the legiilative code of Motes was ſuch as no legiſ-lator ever formed and eſtabliſhed among a people e-qually rude and uncultivated : that the manners and morals of the Jews, vicious and ſavage as they may in ſome inſtances appear, yet merit a much higher character than thoſe either of their neighbours, or of almoſt any other nation, whofe circumſtances and character were in other reſpects ſimilar to theirs : that there is an infinite difference between the Scripture prophecies and the oracles and predictions which prevailed among hea-then nations : and that the miracles recorded in thofe writings which we eſteem ſacred were attended with circumſtances which entitle them to be ranked in a very</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>