<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>the ſpecies by a very numerous ſtock of fe :ds, of which perhaps not one in 500 need take root in order to continue an equal numbcr of plants. As it is thus alſo in regard to infects, it cannot but happen, that if a favourable ſeaſon encourage the hatching of all thofe eggs, a very ſmall number of which alone were neceſſiry to continue the ſpecies, we muſt, in ſuch ſeaſons, have a proportionate abundance oſ them. There appeared a-.bout 50 years ago, in London, fuch a prodigious lwarm of the little beetle we call the <hi rend="italic">lady-cow,</hi>  that the very .poſts in the ſtreets were eveιγwhere covered with them. But thanks to the progreſs of philoſophy among us, we had no body to affert that it rained cow-ladies, but con-tented ourſelves with faying that it had been a favour-able ſeaſon for their eggs. The prodigious number of a fort of grub which did vaſt miſchief about the ſame period among the corn and graſs by-eating off their roots, might alſo have been ſuppoſed to proceed from its having rained grubs by people fond of making every thing a prodigy. ; but our knowledge in natural hiſtory aſſured us, that theſe were only the hexapode worms of the. common hedge-beetle called the <hi rend="italic">cock-chafer.</hi></p><p>' The raining of <hi rend="italic">fiſhes</hi>  has been a prodigy alfo much talked of in.France, where the ſtreets of a town at ſome diſtance from Paris, after a terrible hurricane in the night, which tore up trees, blew down houfes, &amp;c. were found in a manner covered with fiſhes of various ſizes. Nobody here made any doubt of theſe having fallen from the clouds ; nor did the abſurdity of fiſh, of five or fix inches long, being generated in the air, at all ſtartle the</p><p>i&gt;eople, or ſhake their belief in the miracle, till they bund, upon inquiry, that a very well-ſtocked fiſh-pond, which ſtood on an eminence in the neighbourhood, had been blown dry by the hurricane, and only the great fiſh left at the bottom of it, all the ſmaller fry having been .toffed into their ſtreets.</p><p>Upon the whole, all the ſuppoſed marvellous rains have been owing to ſubſtances naturally produced on the -earth, and either never having been in the air at all, or only carried thither by accident.</p><p>In Slleſia, after a great dearth of wheat in that country, there happened a violent ſtorm of wind and rain, and the earth was afterwards covered, in many places, with ſmall round feeds. The vulgar cried out that Pro-vidence had ſent them food, and that it had rained <hi rend="italic">m'd-let :</hi>  but theſe were, in reality, only the feeds of a ſpe-cies of veronica, or fpeed-well, very common in that country ; and whoſe feeds being juſt ripe at that time, the wind had diſlodged them from their capſules, and ſcattered them about. In our own country, we have hiſtories of rains of this marvellous kind, but all fabu-lous. It was once faid to rain <hi rend="italic">wheat</hi>  in wiltſhire ; and the people were all alarmed at it as a miracle, till Mr Dole ſhowed them, that what they took for wheat was .only the feeds or kernels of the berries of ivy, which being then fully ripe, the wind had diſlodged from the fides oſ houfes, and trunks of trees, on which the ivy that produced them crept.</p><p>And we even once had a raining of fiſhes near the coaſt of Kent in a terrible hurricane, with thunder and lightning. The people who ſaw ſmall ſprats ſtrewed all about afterwards, would have it that they had fallen from the clouds ; but thoſe who confidered how far the high winds have been known to carry the ſea-water, did not wonder that they ſhould be able to carry ſmall fifh with it ſo ſmall a part of the way.</p><p>In the Philofophical Tranfactions for 1782 we have the following account of a preternatural kind of rain by Count de Gioeni : “ The morning of the 24th inſtant there appeared here a moſt ſingular phenomenon. Every place expofed to the air was found wet with a coloured cretaceous grey water, which, after evapoia-ting and filtrating away, left every place covered with it to the height of two or three lines ; and all the ironwork that was touched by it became ruſty.</p><p>" The public, inclined to the marvellous, fancied va--τious cauſes of this rain, and began to fear for the ani-mals and vegetables.    *►</p><p>" In places where rain-water was uſed, they abſtain-ed from it : ſome ſufpecting vitriolic principles to be mixed with it, and others predicting ſome epidemical diforder.</p><p>" Thoſe who had obſerved the exploſions of Etna 20 days and more before, were inclined to believe it origi-nated from one of them.</p><p>" The ſhower extended from N.⅞N.E. to S.4S.W. ov¢r the fields, about 70 miles in a right line from the vertex of Etna.</p><p>" There is nothing new in volcanos having thrown up ſand, and alſo ſtones, by the violent expanſive force generated within them, which ſand has been carried by the wind to diſtant regions.</p><p>“ But the colour and ſubtilty of the matter occaſion-ed doubts concerning its origin ; which increafed from the remarkable circumſtance of the water in which it came incorporated ; for which reaſons ſome other principle or origin was ſuſpected.</p><p>“ It became, therefore, neceſſary by all means to aſ-certain the nature of this matter, in order to be con-vinced of its origin, and of the effects it might produce. This could not be done without the help of a chemical analyſis. To do this then with certainty, I endeavour-ed to collect this rain ſrom places where it was moſt probable no heterogeneous matter would be mixed with it. . I therefore chofe the plant called <hi rend="italic">brajfica capitata, </hi>which having large and turned-up leaves, they contain-ed enough of this coloured water : many of thefe I emptied into a veffel, and left the contents to fettle till the water became clear.</p><p>" This being ſeparated into another veſſel, I tried it with vegetable alkaline liquors and mineral acids ; but could obferve no decompoſition by either. I then evaporated the water in order to reunite the ſubſtances that might be in ſolution ; and touching it again with the aforeſaid liquors, it ſhowed a flight eſſerveſcence with the acids, when tried with the ſyrup of violets, this became a pale green ; ſo that I was perſuaded it contained a calcareous ſalt. with the decoction of galls no precipitation was produced.</p><p>" The matter being afterwards dried in the ſhade, it appeared a very ſubtile fine earth, of a cretaceous co-lυur, but inert, from having been diluted by the rain.</p><p>" I next thought of calcining it with a flow fire, and it aſſumed the colour of a brick. A portion of this being put into a crucible, I applied to it a ſtronger heat; by which it loſt almoſt all its acquired colour. Again, I expofed a portion of this for a longer time to a very violent heat (from which a vitrification might be</p></body></text></TEI>