<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>tented myſelf with opening its mouth, and ſlightly in-ſpecting it.</p><p>" You may imagine, that a toad, generally deteſted, (although one of the moſt inoffenſive of all animals), ſo much taken notice of and befriended, excited the curioſity of all comers to the houſe, who all deſired to ſee it fed ; ſo that even ladies ſo far conquered the hor-rors inſtilled into them by nurſes, as to deſire to ſee it. This produced innumerable and improbable reports, making it as large as the crown of a hat, &amp;c. &amp;c.”</p><p>The following are anſwers from the ſame gentleman to fome queries propoſed by Mr Pennant.</p><p><hi rend="italic">" Firfi,</hi>  I cannot ſay how long my father had been acquainted with the toad before I knew it ; but when I firſt was acquainted with it, he uſcd to mention it as the old toad I’ve known ſo many years ; I can anſwer for 36 years.</p><p><hi rend="italic">" Secondly,</hi>  No toads that I ever ſaw appeared in the winter ſeaſon. The old toad made its appearance as ſoon as the warm weather came, and I always con-cluded it retired to ſome dry bank to repoſe till the ſpring. AVhen we new-lay<hi rend="sup">,</hi>d the ſteps, I had two holes made in every third ſtep, with a hollow of more than a yard long for it, in which I imagine it ſlept, as it came from thence at its firſt appearance.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Thirdly,</hi>  It was ſeldom provoked: neither that toad, nor the multitudes I have ſeen tormented with great cruelty, ever ſhowed the leaſt deſire of revenge, by ſpitting or emitting any juice from their pimples.— Sometimes, upon taking it up, it would let out a great quantity of clear water, which, as I have often feen it do the ſame upon the ſteps when quite quiet, was certainly its urine, and no more than a natural evacuation.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Fourthly,</hi>  A toad has no particular enmity for the ſpider ; he uſed to eat five or fix with his millepedes (which I take to be its chief food) that I generally provided for it before I found out that fleſh maggots, by their continual motion, was the moſt tempting bait ;</p><p>but, when offered, it eat blowing flies and humble bees that come from the rat-tailed maggot in gutters, or in ſhort any inſect that moved. I imagine, if a bee was to be put before a toad, it would certainly eat it to its coſt ; but as bees are ſeldom ſtirring at the ſame time that toads are, they can ſeldom come in their way, as they ſeldom appear after ſun-riſing or before ſun-ſct. In the heat of the day they will come to the mouth of their hole, I believe, for air. I once from my parlour window obſerved a large toad I had in the bank of a bowling-green, about 12 at noon, a very hot day, very buſy and active upon the grafs ; ſo uncommon an appearance made me go out to ſee what it was, when I found an innumerable fwarm of winged ants had drop-ped round his hole, which temptation was as irreſiſtible as a turtle would be to a luxurious alderman.</p><p><hi rend="italic">" Fifthly,</hi>  whether our toad ever propagated its fpecies, I knφw not ; rather think not, as it always ap-peared well, and not leſſened in bulk, which it muſt have done, I ſhould think, if it had diſcharged ſo large a quantity of ſpawn as toads generally do. Tlie femalcs that are to propagate in the ſpring, I imagine, inſtead of retiring to dry holes, go into the bottom of ponds, and lie torpid among the weeds : for to my great furprife, in the middle of the winter, having for amufe-ment put a long pole into my pond, and twiſted it till it had gathered a large volume of weed, on taking it off I found many toads ; and having cut ſome aſunder with my knife, by accident, to get off the weed, found them full of ſpawn not thoroughly formed. I am not pofitive, but think there were a few males in March ; I know there are 30 males (b) to one female, 12 or 14 of whom I have ſeen clinging round a female : I have often diſengaged her, and put her to a ſolitary male, to fee with what eagerneſs he would ſeize her. They impregnate the ſpawn as it is drawn (c) out in long ſtrings, like a necklace, many yards long, not in a large quantity of jelly, like frogs fpawn.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">(b)</hi>     Mr John Hunter has aſſured me, that during his reſidence at Belleiſle, he diſſected ſome hundreds of toads, yet never met with a ſingle female among them.</p><p>(c)    I was incredulous as to the <hi rend="italic">obfietrical</hi>  offices of the male toad; but fince the end is ſo well accounted for, and the fact eſtabliſhed by ſuch good authority, belief muſt take place.</p><p>Mr Demours, in the Memoirs of the French Academy, as tranſlated by Dr Templeman, vol. i. p. 371, has been very particular in refpect to the male toad as acting the part of an <hi rend="italic">accoucheur :</hi>  His account is curious, and claims a place here.</p><p>" In the evening of one of the long days in fummer, Mr Demours, being in the king’s garden, perceived two toads <hi rend="italic">coupled together</hi>  at the edge of an hole, which was formed in part by a great ſtone at the top.</p><p>“ Curioſity drew him to ſee what was the occaſion of the motions he obſerved, wheβ<hi rend="sub">1</hi>two facts equally new ſurpriſed him. The<hi rend="italic">firfi</hi>  was the extreme difficulty the female had in laying her eggs, inſomuch that ſhe did not ſeem capable of being delivered of them without ſome aſſiſtance. The <hi rend="italic">fecond</hi>  was, that the male was mounted on the back of the female, and exerted all his ſtrength with his hinder feet in puffing out the eggs, whilſt his forefeet embraced her breaſt.</p><p>“ In order to apprehend the manner of his working in the delivery of the female, the reader muſt obſerve, that the paws of theſe animals, as well thoſe of the fore-feet as of the hinder, are divided into ſeveral toes, which can perform the office of fingers.</p><p>" It muft<hi rend="sup">t</hi>be remarked likewiſe, that the eggs of this ſpecies of toads are included each in a membranous coat that is very firm, in which: is contained the embryo ; and that theſe eggs, which are oblong and about two lines in length, being faſtened one to another by a ſhort but very ſtrong cord, form a kind of chaplet, the beads of which are diſtant from each other about the half of their length, lt is by drawing this cord with his paw that the male pcrforms the function of a midwife, and acquits himſelf in it with a dexterity that one would not expect from fo Jumpiſh an animal.</p><p>" The preſence of the obſerver did not a little diſcompoſe the male : ſor ſome time he ſtopped ſhort, and threw</p></body></text></TEI>