<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>queen or prîncefs dowager, or any defcεndant of king George If. reſiding in this kingdom ; — to be guardian and regent till the ſucceffor attains ſuch age, aſſiſted by √ι council of regency ; the powers of them all being expreſsly defined and ſet down.in the ſeveral acts.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Regent alſo ſignifies a profeffor of arts and ſciences iu a college, having pupils under his care ; but it is generally reſtrained to the lower claffes, as to rhetoric, logic, &amp;c. thoſe of philoſophy being called    In</hi></p><p>the Engliſh univerſities it is applied to Mailers of Arts under five years ſtanding, and to Doctors under two, as non-regent is to thoſe above that ſtanding.</p><p>REGGI0, an ancient and conſiderable town of Italy, in the kingdom of Naples, and in the Farther Calabria, with an archbiſhop’s ſee, and a woollen manufactory. It is · ſeated in a delightful country, which produces plenty of oranges, and all their kindred fruits. The olives are exquiſite, and high-flavoured· The town, however, can boaſt oſ neither beautiful buildings nor ſtrong fortifications. 01' its edifices the Gothic cathedral is the only ſtriking one, but it affords nothing curious in architecture. The citadel is far from formidable, according to the preſent ſyſtem of tactics : nor could the city walls make a long reiiſtance againſt any enemy but Barbary corſairs ; and even tbeſe they have not always been able to repel, for in 1543 it was laid in aſhes by Barbaroffa. Muſtapha ſacked it 15 years after, and the deſolation was renewed in 1593 by another ſet of Turks. Its expofed ſituation, on the very threſhold of Italy, and fronting Sicily, has from the earlieſt period rendered it liable to attacks and devaſtation. The Chal-cidians ſcized upon it, or, according to the uſual Greek phraſe, founded it, aud called the colony <hi rend="italic">Rhegion,</hi>  from a word that means a break or crack, alluding to its poſt-tion on the point where Sicily broke off from the continent. Anaxilas oppreffed its liberties. Dionyſius the Elder took it, and put many of the principal citizens to death, in revenge for their having refufed his alliance.. The Campanian legion, ſent to protect the Rhegians, turned its ſword againſt them, maffacred many inhabitants, and tyrannized over the remainder, till the Roman ſenate thought proper to puniſh theſe traitors with exemplary ſeverity, though at the ſame time it entered into kagιιe with the revolted garrifon of Meſſina. This union with a ſet of villains, guilty of the ſame crime, proved that no love of juſtice, but political reaſons alone, drew down its vengeance on the Campanians.— It is about 12 miles S.<hi rend="sub">j</hi>E. of Meſſina, and 190 S. by E. of Naples. E. Long. 16. ο. N. Lat. 38. 4.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Reggio, an ancient, handfome, and ſtrong town of Italy, in the duchy of Modena, with a ſtrong citadel, and a biſhop’s fee. It has been ruined ſeveral times by the Goths, and other nations. In the cathedral are paintings by the greateſt maſters ; and in the ſquare is the ſtatue of Brennus, chief of the Gauls. The inhabitants are about 22,</hi>coo, who carry on a great trade in ſilk. It was taken by prince Eugene in 1706, and by the king cf Sardinia in 1742. It is ſeated in a fertile country to the fouth of the Apennines, and to the north of a lpacious plain, 15 miles north-weft of Modena, and 80 ſouth-eaſt of Milan. E. Long. 11. 5. N. Lat. 44. 43. —The duchy of this name is bounded on the weſt by that of Modena, and produces a great deal of ſilk, and belongs to the duke of Modena, except the marquifate cf St Martin, which belongs to a prince of that name.</p><p>REGIAM majestatem. See Law, n<hi rend="sup">5</hi> civ. 3. REGICIDE, king-killer, a word chiefly uſed</p><p>with us in ſpeaking of the perſons concerned in the trial, condemnation, and execution, of king Charles I.</p><p>REG1FUGJUM was a feaſt celebrated at Rome on the 24th of February, in commemoration of the expυl-ſion of <hi rend="italic">Tcirquinius Snperbm,</hi>  and tlie abolition ot regal power. It was alio performed on the 26th of May, when the king of the iacrifices, or <hi rend="italic">Rex Sacrorι∩n<hi rend="sub">i</hi></hi>  offered bean flour and bacon, in the place where the affemblies were held. The ſacrifice being over, the people hailed away with all ſpeed, to denote the precipitate flight of King Tarquin.</p><p>REGIMEN, the regulation of diet, and, in a more general fenle, of all the non-naturals, with a view to preſerve or reſtore health. See Abstinence, Aliment, Food, Diet, Drink, and Medicine.</p><p>The viciſſitude of excrciſe and reſt forms alſo a neceffary part of regimen. See Exercise.</p><p>it is beneficial to be at reſt now and then, ’ but more ſo frequently to uſe exerciſe ; becauſe inaction renders the body weak and liſtleſs, and labour ſtrengthens it. But a medium is to be obſerved in all things, and too much fatigue is to be avoided : for frequent and violent exerciſe overpowers the nat ural ſtrength, and waſtes thc body ; but moderate exerciſe ought always to be uſed before meals. Now, of all kinds of exerciſe, riding on horfeback is the molt convenient : or if the perſon be too weak to bear it, riding in a coach, or at leaſt in a litter : next follow fencing, playing at ball, running, walking. But it is one of the inconveniences of old age, that there, is ſeldom ſuſſicient ſtrength for uſing bodily exerciſe, though it be extremely requiſtte for health:. wherefore frictions with the fleſh-bruſh are neceffary at this time of life ; which ſhould be performed by the perfon himſelf, if poſſible ; if not, by his ſervants.</p><p>Sleep is the ſweet ſoother of cares, and reſtorer of ſtreifbth ; as it repairs and replaces the waſtes that are made by the labours and exerciſes of the day. But exceſſive ſleep has its inconveniences ; for it blunts the ſenſes, and renders them leſs fit for the duties of life. The proper time for ſleep is the night, when darknefi&gt;-and filence invite and bring it on : day-ſleep is leſs re·· freſhing ; which rule if it be proper ſor the multitude to obſerve, much more is the obſervance of it neceffary for perſons addicted to literary ſtudies, whofe minds and bodies are more fiιfcept⅛le oſ injuries.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Regimen, in grammar, that part of ſyntax, or conſtruction, which regulates the dependency of words, and the alterations which one occaiions in another.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps">Regimen for Seamen.</hi></hi>  See Seamen.</p><p>REGIMENT, is a body of men, either horſe, foot, or artillery, commanded by a colonel, lieutenant-colonel, and major. Each regiment of foot is divided into companies ; but the number of companies differs : though in Britain our regiments are generally 10 companies, one of which is always grenadiers, excluſive of the two independent companies. Regiments of horfe are commonly ſix troops, but there are fome of nine. Dragoon regiments are generally in war-time 8 troops, and in time of peace but 6. Each regiment has a chaplain, quarter-maſter, adjutant, and ſurgeon. Some German regiments conſiſt of 2000 foot ; and the regiment of Picardy in France confiſted of 6000, being 120 companies, of 50 men in each company.</p><p>7</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>