<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>marlcabfy dry till the latter part oſ harveſt, when there fell a conſiderable, though by no means unuſual, quan-tity of rain. Towards the end of December a ſevere froſt bound up the whole of the rivers and lakes of Holland. The waal was frozen over in the beginning of January; a circumſtance which had not occurred for 14 years paſt. Taking advantage ef this, the French croſſed that river, and with little oppoſition ſeized the important pafs of Bommell, which at other ſcafons is ſo ſtrong by its inundations. The allied army had been joined by 17,000 Auſtrians, and had received ordcrs to defend Holland to the laſt. They did fo, and were ſuccefsſul in repulſing the French for ſome days between the waal and the Leck ; but the republican army, amounting to 70,000 men, having at laſt advanced in full force, the allied troops were compelied to retire acroſs the Yſſel into weſtphalia^ In the courſe of their march throughthis deſert country, in the midſt of ſevere froſt and a deep ſuow, they arc ſaid to have ſuſſered incredible hardſhips, and to have loſt a very great number of men. The French, in the mean time, advanced rapidly acrofs the country to the Zuyder fea, to prevent the in-habitants ſrom flying, and carrying oſſ their property. On the 16th of January 1795, a party of horſe, without jreflſtance, took poſſeffion of Amſterdam. The other towns furrendered at diſcretion. In confeqnence of an. order from the States General, the ſlrong ſortreſſes of Bergen-op-zoon, wiliiamftadt, Breda, &amp;c. opened their gates to the French. The fleet and the ſhipping were fixed by the intenſe froſt in their Rations, and fell a prey to the enemy; who thus, with little effort, made a complete conqueſt of this populous and once powerful country. The French were well received by the people at large. The power of the Stadtholder had been ſupport-ed among them merely by the influence of Pruffia and England. Through hatred to this officc, which had now become odious chiefly to the mercantile ariſtocracy of Holland, they were little attached to their allies, and gave them, during the preſent war, as little ſupport as poſſible. The Stadtholder and his family now fled to England. Tlie French declared, that they did not mean to make ſubjects but allies of the Dutch, and invited them to call together popular aſſemblies for ſettling their own government, under the protection of the French republic.</p><p>Thus terminated a campaign, the moſt aſtoniſhing, perhaps, that has been known in the hiſtory of mankind. In the courſe cf it, even before the conqueſt of Holland, the French had taken 2000 pieces of cannon and 60,000 priſoners. Aſter that event, the conquered ter-ritories added to them a population of nearly 14 millions of people. Luxembourg and Mentz were the only places on this ſide of the Rhine that reſiſted them. The former was cloftly blockaded, for the purpoſe of compelling it to ſurrender the latter was ſeveral times aſ-faulted,, but ſucceſsfully held out.</p><p>Europe was now weary of this bloody ſtrife. The German Diet of Ratiſhon declared its reſolution to take meafures for procuring peace. Tile Grand Duke of Tuſcany concluded a treaty with thc French republic. France itſelſ, exhauſted by maſſacrea, emigrations, and the terrible efforts which it had made, wiſhed for tranquillity ; and the Convention found it neceſſary to declare that they were willing to treat for peace with any of the powers of Europe, upon honourable terms.</p><p>The frequent changes, however, which have with aſtoniſhing rapidity taken place in the mode oſ conduct-ing French affairs, and the different principles diſplay-ed by the different factions as they ſucceffively got into power, have produced in Great Britain and Auſtria a very general perſuaſion that no peace concluded with the preſent Convention could either be honourable or per-manent ; and therefore theſe two mighty nations have reſolved to continue the war with redoubled vigour.— In ſupport oſ the wiſdom oſ this reſolutſon, it has been obſerved, that the hatred oſ the Mountain to the Gi-rondiſts was Inch, that it would have violated any treaty which had been concluded with thAa ; that when Robeſpierre beoame all powerful, and terror was the order oſ the day, all former meaſures were changed, and peace or war made wholly ſubſervient to the ambitious views of that relentteſa tyrant ; that Taliien, having orig'nally belonged to the Mountain, introduced the preſent ſyſtem of moderation, not from principle, but only to reconcile the people to his uſurped authority, and the faſt of his bloody predeceſſor ; that he may ſuddenly change his meaſures, or be denounced and executed hy the influence of ſome more daring demagogue, who would again introduce the fyſtem of terror; and that in ſuch a ſtate of uncertainty, the only confe-qnence to be expected from making peace at preſent is, that it would furniſh the next faction which may gain, the aſeendancy in France with an opportunity of attacking the allies when leſs prepared to receive them.. Such reafoning as this has been admitted in the Britiih. parliament, where a loan of ſix millions Sterling has. been voted to the Emperor, to enable him to begin the enſuing campaign with an army of 2-00,000 men. In what manner the war ought to be conducted, it is not for ns to ſay. The Britiſh nation feems to reſt its hopes on its ſuperiority at ſea ; and the greateſt exertions are making to augment and man the navy. But we are here under the neceffity of dropping this ſubject, with-out being able completely to fulfil the promiſe which we made to our readers at the end of the article France, There is as little appearance at preſent of peace, and a ſteady government being foon reſtored to that diſtracted eountry, as there was at the beginning of the troubles ; and there is not the ſmalleſt probab;-lity that the republican conſtitution, framed by the Convention, will laſt one year after the diſſolution of that aſſembly.</p><p>In tracing the origin and progrefs of this wonderful revolution, we have conſulted every work from which we had reaſon to look ſor information, aad we have confined ourſelves to a ſimple narration of facts, ſeldom giving way to the reflections which they ſuggeſted. Our facts, too, have been generally ſtated from writers who are ſuppoſed to be not unfriendly to democracy, that they may gain the fuller credit with our own reformers ; lor in the moſt favourable point of view in which thoſe facts can be placed, they furniſh the ſtrongeſt objection poffible to all their propoſed reformations of the Britiſh conſtitution. If the horrible deeds of darknefs which have been acted on the theatre of France cannot make us contented with the government under which we live, and which has been brought to its preſent ſtate of perfection, not by the metaphyſical ſpeculations of recluſe philofophers, but by obfervation and the practical experience of ages, wc ſhall be confidered by poſterity as a</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>