<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>chap, <hi rend="italic">v!,</hi>  and <hi rend="smallcaps">Theology,</hi>  n<hi rend="sup">0</hi>  8, 9.) But ſurely itwould be raſh to infer, either that every truth for which, when it is known, the ingenuity of man can frame a demonſtration, is therefore <hi rend="italic">diſcover able</hi>  by human ſagacity, or that all the truths which have been diſcovered by a <hi rend="italic">Newton</hi>  or a <hi rend="italic">Lot he</hi>  might therefore have been diſcovered by untaught barbarians. In mathematical foiençe, there are few demonſtrations of ea-fier comprehenſion than that given by Euclid, of the theorem of which Pythagoras is the reputed author ; yet no man ever dreamed that a boy capable of being made to undeιſtand that theorem, muſt therefore have ſagacity equal to the fagc of Samos; or that ſuch a boy, having never heard of the relation between the hypo-then uſe and other two ſides of a right angled triangle, would be likely to <hi rend="italic">diſcover</hi>  that the ſquare ot the former js preciſely equal to the ſum of the ſquares of the latter. Juſt fo it feems to be with the fundamental truths of theology. There can hardly be conceived a demonſtration lefs intricate, or more concluſive, than that which the man of ſcience employs to prove the exiſtence of at leaſt one God, poſſeſſed of boundleſs power and perfect wiſdom. And could we ſuppoſe that the human race had remained without any knowledge oſ God in the world, till certain lucky individuals had by ſome means or other made themſelves maſters oſ the rules oſ logic, and the philoſophy of cauſes, there can be no doubt but that theſe individuals might have diſcovered the exiſtence of ſuperior powers, and communicated their diſcovery to their aiſociates and followers. But this iuppofitιon cannot be admitted, as it is contradicted by the evidence of all hiſtory. No nation or tribe has ever been found, in which there is not reafon to believe that fome notions were entertained of fuperior and inviſible powers, upon which depends the happinefs or mifery of mankind : and from the moſt authentic records cf antiquity, it is apparent that very pure principles of theiſm prevailed in ſome nations long before the rules of logic, and the philoſophy of cauſes, were thought of by any people under heaven.</p><p>The ſuppoſition before us is inadmiſſible upon other accounts. Some modern philoſophers have fancied that the original progenitors of mankind were left entirely to themſelves from the moment ot their creation; that they wandered about for ages without the uſe of ipeech and in the loweſt ſtate of ſavagiſin ; but that they gradually civilized themſelves, and at laſt ſtumbled upon the contrivance of making articulate founds ſignificant of ideas, which was followed by the invention of arts and ſciences, with all the bleſſings of religion and legiſlation in their train. But this is a wild reverie, inconſiſtent with the phenomena of human nature.</p><p>It is a well known fact, that a man blind from his birth, and fuddeπly made to ſee, would not by means <hi rend="sup">,</hi>cf his newly acquired ſenſe diſcern either the magnitude or figure or diſtance of objects, but would conceive every thing which communicated to him viſible ſenſations as inſeparably united to his eye or his mind (See Me-taphysics, n° 49—53)· How long his ienle of ſight would remain in ſuch an imperfect ſtate, we cannot poſitively fay ; but from attending to the viſible ſenſations of infants, we are confident that weeks, if not months, elapſe before they can diſtinguiſh one thing from another. we have indeed been told, that Cheſelden’a famous patient, though he was at ſirſt in the ſtate which we have deſcribed, learned to diſtinguiſh objects by ſight in the courſe of a few hours, or at the moſt of a few days ; but admitting this to a certain extent to be true, it may eaſily be accounted for. The diſeaſe call-ed a <hi rend="italic">cataract</hi>  foldυm occaſions total blindneſs ; but let us iuppoie the eyes of this man to have been ſo completely dimmed as to communicate no ſenſation whatever upon being expofed to the rays of light; ſtill we muſt remember that he had long poſſeſſed the power of loco-motion and all his other ſenſes in perfection. He was therefore well acquainted with the real, <hi rend="italic">i. e,</hi>  the tangible magnitude, figure, and diſtance of many υb-jects ; and having been often told that the tilings which he touched would, upon his acquiſition oſ ſight, com-municate new ſeniations to his mind, differing ſrom each other according to the diſtance, figure, and magnitude of the objects by which they were occaſioned, he would foon learn to infer the one ſrom the other, and to diſtinguiſh near objects by means oſ his ſight.</p><p>Ί he progenitors oſ the human race, however, iſ leſt to themielves from the moment oſ their creation, had not the ſame advantages. when they ſirſt opened their eyes, they had neither moved, nor handled, nor heard, nor ſinelled, nor tailed, nor had a ſingle idea or notion treaſured up in their memories ; but were in alI theſe reſpects in the ſtate oi new-born infants. Now we ſhould be glad to be informed by thoſe ſages who have conducted mankind through many generations in which they were <hi rend="italic">mutum et turpe pecus</hi>  to that happy pe-ricd when they invented language, how the ſirſt men were taught to diſtinguiſh objects by their ſenſe of ſight, and how they contrived to <hi rend="italic">live</hi>  till this moſt ne-ceiſary faculty was acquired ? It does not appear that men are like brutes, provided with a number oſ inilinct⅛ which guide them blindfold and without experience to whatever is neceſſary ſor their own preſervation (ſee Instinct) : Ο11 the contrary, all voyagers tell us that,, in ſtrange and uninhabited countries, they dare not venture to taſte unknown fruits unleſs they perceive that theſe fruits are eaten by the fowls of the air. But with-out the aid of inſtinct, or of ſome other guide equally to be depended upon, it is not in our power to conceive how men dropt from the hands of their Creator, and left from that inſtant wholly to themſelvcs, could move a ſingle ſtep without the moſt imminent danger, or even ſtretch out their hands to lay hold of that food which we may ſuppoſe to have been placed within their reach. They could not, for mauy days, diſtinguiſh a precipice from a plane, a rock from a pit, or a ■river from the meadows through which it rolled. And in ſuch circumſtances, how could they pofſibly exiſt, till their ſenſe of ſight had acquired ftιch perfection as to be a ſuſſicient guide to all their neceſlary motions <hi rend="italic">ί </hi>Can any conſiſtent theiſt ſuppoſe that the God whoſe goodneis is lo conſpicuouſiy diſplayed in all his works, would leave his nobleſt creature on earth, a creature ſor whole comfort alone many other creatures ſeem to have been formed, in a ſituation io forlorn as this, where his immediate deſtruction appears to be inevitable ? No ! This ſuppoſition cannot be formed, becauſe mankind ſtiil exiſt.</p><p>WÜ1 it then be ſaid, that when God formed the ſirſt men, he not only gave them organs of ſenſation, and fouls capable of arriving by diſcipline at the exerciſe of reaιυn, but that he alſo impreiſed upon their minds</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>