<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>tisfaction is the moſt powerful check to honeſt induſtry ; and diffatisfaction and idleneſs muſt be the effect of the wanderings of ſuch men in the labyrinths of politics ; which, for uncultivated minds efpεcially,paves the wayfor every ſpecies of vice, and gradually ripens them for any wickedneſs, however atrocious. For the truth of theſe re-marks, we appeal to the hiftory of mankind from theCrea∙ tion to the preſent time : and we would ſeriouſly requeſt the <hi rend="italic">fiber friends of reform,</hi>  and many ſuch, we doubt not, there are, to reflect, that in the preſent day we have more to fear from licentiouſneſs than from deſpotiſm ; from reform carried to an extreme than from the pretended attempts either of kings or miniſters to annihilate our real liberty (ſee Revolution).</p><p>It may alſo be worth their while to conſider, that times of public danger are not generally the beſt adapted to attempt changes of government ; becauſe what might ſatisfy one party would probably be thought too little by another, and diviſions at ſuch a period are moſt dangerous, when, therefore, attempts are made for reform which appear to be inconſiſtent with the ſafety of the ſtate, reftriétions muſt be uſed, which may by ſpecu-lative men be thought ſevere and unneceffary, but of which they themſelves are the caufes. Theſe re-ſtrictions too will be patiently ſubmitted to by the wiſer part of the community, when in more peaceable times they would neither have been thought of nor allowed.</p><p>Speculative reaſoners may ſpeak as much as they will of enlightening the minds of men, and of reform-ing government by the dictates of a refined and diΓ-paſſionate philoſophy ; but when they come to apply their notions to practice, they will either find their re-preſentations little better than empty founds, and therefore ineffectual ; or, as is more generally found to be the caſe, thoſe ſchemes which in theory appeared to be perfect, 'will in practice, when combined with the malignant and ambitious paſſions of men, lead to ruin and diſorder. The ſirſt inſtitution of government, except among the Jews, was unqueſtionably the effect of paſſion and intereft combined ; and this paſſion and this intereſt, reſtrained within due bounds, is productive of much happineſs. That government, we believe, too, will be beſt ſupported, and moſt productive of happineſs, in which the mutual paſſions and intereſts of the individuals who compoſe it are ſo equally poiſed as to ſupport one another, and to promote each the ends and ſucceſs of the other : and this by the ableſt reaſoners and the beſt men has been thought to be the caſe with the Britiſh conſtitution. If the modern favourers of reform ſhould think this an unſtable ſupport, if they will conſider the world as it ever has been, and as it is<hi rend="sub">r </hi>they will ſind it the only one we have, except religion ; and they will thence be inclined to make the beſt of it. If, after all, however, they ſhould be diſpofed to doubt the poſition, we have only further to requeſt them, with the ſincerity of men and of Chriſtians, to conſult their own breaſts, and ſerioufly to conſider the probable motives of thoſe who act with them. They will then perhaps ſee, and they ſurely ought to acknowledge, that few men have acted more according to the impulſe of paſſion, intereſt, and ambition, than thofe who have for ſome time paſt founded the toczin of reform.</p><p>REFORMATION, in general, an act of reforming or correcting an error or abuſe in religion, diſci-</p><p>pline, or the like. By way of eminence the word is uſed for that great alteration and reformation in the corrupted ſyſtem of Chriſtianity, begun by Luther in the year 1517.</p><p>Under the article History (fect. ii.), the various corruptions in religion, the oppreſſions and uſurpations of the clergy, and the extreme inſolence of the popes, have been ſo fully treated of, that any further detail here is unneceffary. It is ſuſſicient to obſerve, that, before the period of the Reformation, the Pope had in the moft audacious manner declared himſelf the ſovereign of the whole world. All the parts of it which were inhabited by thoſe who were not Chriſtians, he accounted to be inhabited by <hi rend="italic">no-body</hi>  ; and if Chriſtians took it into their heads to po∏efs any of thoſe countries, he gave them fuff liberty to make war upon the inhabitants without any provocation, and to treat them with no more humanity than they would have treated wild beaſts. The countries, if conquered, were to be parcelled out according to the pope’s pleaſure ; and dread-ful was the ſituation of that prince who refuſed to obey the will of the holy pontiff, of which many inftances' will occur to the reader in the various hiſtorical articles of this work. In conſequence of this extraordinary authority which the pope had affumed, he at laſt: granted to the king of Portugal all the countries to the eaſt-ward of Cape Non in Africa, and to the king of Spain all the countries to the weſtward of it. In this, according to the opinions of ſome, was completed in his perſon the character of <hi rend="italic">Aηtichrifi fitting in tbe temple oſ God, andſhewing himfidſ as God</hi>  *. He had long before, ſay they, affumed the fupremacy belonging to the Deity himſelf in ſpiritιιal matters ; and now he affumed the ſame ſupremacy in worldly matters alſo, giving the extreme regions of the earth to whom he pleaſed. The Reformation, therefore, they confider as the immediate effect of divine power taking vengeance on this and all other deviations from the ſyſtem of truth while others conſider it merely as an effect of natural cauſes, and which might have been foreſeen and prevented, without abridging the papal power in any confiderable degree.</p><p>Be this as it will, however, the above-mentioned partition was the laſt piece of inſolence which the pope ever had, or in all probability ever will have, in his power to exerciſe, in the way of parcelling out the globe to his adherents. Every thing was quiet, every heretic exterminated, and the whole Chriſtian world fupinely acquieſced in the enormous abſurdities which were inculcated upon them ; when, in 1517, the empire,of iuper-ſtition began to decline, and has continued to do ſo ever ſince. The perfon who made the firſt attack on the extravagant ſuperſtitions then prevailing was Martin Luther ; the occafion of which is fully related under tlie article Luther. By ſome it is pretended, that the Only motive which Luther had m beginning the Reformation was his enmity to the Dominican friars, who had excluded his order (the Auguſtins) from all ſhare in the gainful traffic of indulgences. But this does not ſeem at all probable, if we conſider that fuch a motive would not naturally have led him to deny the virtue cf indulgences, as ſuch conduct could not but exclude him forever from any chance of a ſhare in the traffic, which otherwiſe perhaps he might have obtained. Beſides, the extreme contrariety of this traffic to the common principles of reaſon and honeſty was ſo great, that we</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>