<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>therefore thoſe mines which are properly royal, and to which the king is entitled when found, are ^nly thoſe of ſilver and gold. See Mine.</p><p>13.    To the fame original may in part be reſerrcdthe revenue of treaſure-trove. See <hi rend="italic">TKKΛsuRK-Trove.</hi></p><p>14.    waifs. See waif.</p><p>15.    Eſtrays. See Estray.</p><p>Beſides the particular reafons, given in the different articles, why the king ſhould have the ſeveral revenues of royal fiſh, ſhipwrecks, treaſure-trove, waifs, and eſtrays, there is alfo onc general reaſon which holds for them all ; and that is, becauſe they are <hi rend="italic">bona vacantia,</hi>  or goods in which no one elſe can claim a property. And, therefore, by the law of nature, they be-longed to the firſt occupant or finder; and ſo continued under the imperial law. But, in ſettling the modern eonſtſtutions of moſt of the governments in Europe, it was thought proper (to prevent that ſtrife and contention which the mere title of occupancy is apt to create and continue, and to provide for the ſupport of public authority in a manner the leaſt burdenſome to individuals) that theſe rights ſhould be annexed to the ſu-preme power by the pofitive laws of the ſtate. And io it came to paſs, that, as Bracton expreſſes it, " hæc, " quæ nullius in bonis ſunt, et olim fuerunt inventons " de jure naturali, jam efficiuntur principis de jure gen-" tium.”</p><p>16.    The next branch of the king’s ordinary revenue conſiſts in forfeitures of lands and goods for offences ; <hi rend="italic">bona confiſcata,</hi>  as they are called by the civilians, be-caufe they belonged to the<hi rend="italic">fiβus</hi>  or imperial treaſury ; or, as our lawyers term them,ybrh <hi rend="italic">ſacta,</hi>  that is, ſuch whereof the property is gone away or departed from the owner. The true reaſon and only ſubſtantial ground oſ any forfeiture for crimes, conſiſt in this ; that all property is derived from ſociety, being one of thofe civil rights which are conferred upon individuals, in ex-change for that degree of natural freedom which every man muſt ſacrifice when he enters into ſocial communities. If, therefore, a member of any national community violates the fundamental contract of his affirmation, by tranfgreſſing the municipal law, he forfeits his right to ſuch privileges as he claims by that con-tract ; and the ſtate may very juſtly reſume that portion of property, or any part of it, which the laws have before affigned him. Henςe, in every offence of an atrocious kind, the laws of England have exacted a total confifcation of the moveables or perſonal eſtate ; and, in many caſes, a perpetual, in others only a temporary, lpfs of the offender’s immoveables or landed property ; and have veiled them both in the king, who is the perſon ſuppoſed to be offended, being the one viſible magiſtrate in whom the majeſty of the public re-ſides. See Forfeiture and Deodand.</p><p>17.    Another branch of the king’s ordinary revenue arifes from eſcheats of lands, which happen upon the defect of heirs to ſucceed to the inheritance ; where-upon they in general revert to and veſt in the king, who is eſteemed, in the eye of the law, the original pro-prietor of all lands in the kingdom.</p><p>18.    The laſt branch of the king’s ordinary revenue, conſiſts in the cuſtody of idiots, from whence we ſhall be naturally led to cυnlider alſo the cuſtody of lunatics. See Idiot and Lunatic.</p><p>This may ſuffice for a ſhort view of the king’s <hi rend="italic">ordi</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">nary</hi>  revenue, or the proper patrimony of the crown j which was very large formerly, and capable of being increaſed to a magnitude truly formidable : for there are very few eſtates in the kingdom that have not, at ſome period or other ſince the Norman conqueſt, been veſted in the hands of the king, by forfeiture, eſcheat, or otherwiſe. But, fortunately for the liberty of the ſubject, this hereditary landed revenue, by a ſeries of improvident management, is funk almoſt to nothing ; and the caſual profits, ariſing from the other branches of the <hi rend="italic">cenfus regalis,</hi>  are likewiſe almoſt all of them alienated from the crown. In order to ſupply the deficiencies of which, we are now obliged to have recourfe to new methods of railing money, unknown to our early anceſtors ; which methods conſtitute.</p><p>„ II. The king’s <hi rend="italic">extraordinary</hi>  revenue. For, the public patrimony being got into the hands of private ſubjects, it is but reaſonable that private contributions ſhonld ſupply the public ſervice. which, though it may perhaps fall harder upon ſome individuals, whoſe anceſtors have had no ſhare in the general plunder, than upon others, yet, taking the nation .throughout, it amounts to nearly the ſame ; provided the gain by the extraordinary ſhould appear to be no greater than the loſs by the ordinary revenue. And perhaps, if every gentleman in the kingdom was to be ſtripped of ſuch of his lands as were formerly the property of the crown, was to be again ſubject to the inconveniences of purveyance and pre-emption, the oppreſſion of fo∙ reſt-laws, and the ſlavery of <hi rend="sup">,</hi>feodal-tenures ; and was to reſign into the king’s hands all his royal franchiſes of waifs, wrecks, eſtrays, treaſure-trove, mines, deo-dands, forfeitures, and the like ; he would find himſelf a greater loſer than by paying his<hi rend="italic">quota</hi>  to ſuch taxes as are neceſſary to the ſupport oſ government. The thing, therefore, to be wiſhed and aimed at in a land of liberty, is by no means the total abolition of taxes, which would draw after it very pernicious con-ſequences, and the very fuppoſition of which is the height of political abfurdity. For as the true idea of government and magiſtracy will be found to conſiſt in this, that ſome few men are deputed by many others to preſide over public affairs, ſo that individuals may the better be enabled to attend their private concerns ∙, it is neceſſary that thoſe individuals ſhould be bound to contribute a portion of their private gains, in order to ſupport that government, and reward that magiſtracy, which protects them in the enjoyment of their reſpective properties. But the things to be aimed at are wiſdom and moderation, not only in granting, but alfo in the method of raiſing, the neceſſary fiιpplies j by contriving to do both in ſuch a manner as may be moſt coducive to the national welfare, and at the ſame time moſt conſiſtent with economy and the liberty of the ſubject ; who, when properly taxed, contributes only, as was before obſerved, ſome part of his property in order to enjoy the reſt.</p><p>Theſe extaordinary grants are ufually called by the ſynonymous names of <hi rend="italic">aids, fubfidies,</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">ſupplies ;</hi>  and are granted by the commons of Great Britain, in par-liament aſſembled. See Parliament and Tax.</p><p>The clear nett produce of the ſeveral branches of the revenue, after all charges of collecting and ma-nagement paid, amounted in the year 1786 to about L. I5&gt;397&gt;∞Q Sterling, whſte the expcnditure was.</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>