<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>a conference at Marpurg, Luther and Zuinglius, toge-ther with ſeveral other of the more eminent doctors who adhered to the reſpective parties of theſe contending chiefs : but this meaſure was not attended with the ſa-lutary effects which were expected from it. The divines diſputed for four days in preſence of the landgrave. Lu-ther attacked oecolampadius, and Zuinglius was attack-ed by Melancthon. Zuinglius was accuſed of hereſy, not only on account of his explanation of the nature aud deſign of the Lord’s Supper, but alfo in confequence of the falfe notions he was fuppoſed to have adopted concerning the divinity of Chriſt, the efficacy of the divine -word, original fin, and ſome other parts of the Chriſtian doctrine. This illuſtrious reformer, however, cleared himfelf from the greateſt part of thefe charges whh the moſt triumphant evidence, and in fuch a manner as appeared fatisfactory even to Luther himfelf : but their diſſenſion concerning the manner of Chriſt’s preſence in the euchariſt ſtill remained ; nor could either of the contending parties be perſuaded to abandon, or even to modify, their opinions on that matter. The only advantage, therefore, which reſulted from the meeting was, that the jarring doctors formed a kind of truce, by agreeing to a mutual toleration of their fentiments, and leaving to the diſpoſal of Providence the cure of their diviſions.</p><p>In the mean time news were received that the emperor deſigned to come into Germany, with a view to terminate all religious differences at the approaching diet of Augſhurg. Having foreſeen fome of the conſequences of thoſe diſputes, and, beſides, taken the advice of men of wiſdom, ſagacity, and experience, he became at certain times more cool in his proceedings, and more impartial in his opinions both of the contending parties and the merits of the cauſe. He, therefore, in an interview with the pope at Bologna, inſiſted, in the moſt ſerious and urgent manner, on the neceſſity of a general council. His remonſtrances and expo-ſtulations, however, could not move the pontiff ; who maintained with zeal the papal prerogatives, reproached the emperor with an ill-judged clemency, and alleged that it was the duty of that prince to ſupport the church, and to execute ſpeedy vengeance upon that obitinate heretical faction who dared to call in queſtion the au-thority of Rome and its pontiff. To this diſcourſe the emperor paid no regard ; looking upon it as a moſt iniquitous thing, and a meaſure directly oppoſite to the laws of the empire, to condemn unheard a ſet of men who had always approved themfelves good citizens, and deſerved well of their country in ſeveral reſpects. Hitherto indeed it was not eaſy for the emperor to form a clear idea of the matters in debate, ſince there was no regular ſyſtem as yet compoſed, by which it might be known with certainty what were the true cauſes of Luther's oppoſition to the pope. The elector of Saxony, therefore, ordered Luther, and other eminent divines, to commit to writing the chief articles of their religious ſyſtem, and the principal points in which they differed from the church of Rome. Luther, in compliance with</p><p>this order, delivered to the elector at Torgaw 17 articles which had been agreed upon in a conference at Sultzbach in 1529 ; from whence theſe received the name of <hi rend="italic">the articles oſ Torgaw.</hi>  But though theſe were deemed by Luther a ſufficient declaration of the ſenti-jκιents of the reformers, yet it was judged proper to en</p><lb/><p>large them, J∏ order to give perſpicuity to their arguments, and ſtrength to their cauſe. In this work Melancthon was employed ; in which he ſhowcd a proper deference to the counſels of Luther, and expreſſed his fentiments and doctrine with the greateſt elegance and perſpicuity ; and thus came forth to view the famous <hi rend="italic">Confeffion oſ Augsburg.</hi></p><p>Οη the 15th of June 1530, Charles arrived at Augſ. burg, and the diet was opened live days after. The Proteſtants received a formal permiſſion to preſent an account of their tenets to the diet on the 25th of the ſame month ; in conſequence of which, at the time ap-pointed, Chriſtian Bayer, chancellor of Saxony, read, in the German language, before the emperor and the princes affembled, the confeſſion of Augſhurg above-mentioned. It contained 28 chapters, of which <hi rend="italic">21 </hi>were employed in repreſenting the religious opinions of the Proteſtants, and the other feven in pointing out the errors and fuperſtitions of the church of Rome. The princes heard it with the deepeſt attention and recollection of mind : it confirmed ſome in the principles they had embraced ; ſurpriſed others ; and many, who be-fore this time had little or no idea of the religious ſentiments of Luther, were now not only convinced of their innocence, but delighted with thcir purity and fimplicity. The copies of this Confeſſion, which after being read were delivered to the emperor, were ſigned by John elector of Saxony, George marquis of Bran-denburg, Erneſt duke of Lunenburg, Philip landgrave of Heife, Wolfgang prince of Anhalt, and by the im-perial cities of Nuremberg and Reutlingen.</p><p>The creatures of the church of Rome who were pre* fent at this diet employed John Faber, afterw<hi rend="sup">τ</hi>ards biſhop of vienna, together with Eckius, and another doctor named<hi rend="italic">Cockdœus,</hi>  to draw up a refutation of the Protef-tant confeſſion : which refutation having been publicly read, the emperor required the Proteſtant members to acquiefce in it, and put an end to tbe religious diſputes by an unlimited ſubmiſſion to the opinions and doctrines contained in this anſwer. But this demand was far from being complied with. The Proteſtants declared on the contrary, that they were by no means ſatisfied with the reply of their adverſaries ; and earneſtly defired a copy of it, that they might more fully demonſtrate its extreme infufficiency and weakneſs. But this reaſonable requeſt was refuſed by the emperor ; who interpoſed his ſupreme authority to prevent any farther proceedings in this matter, and ſolemnly prohibited the publication of any new writings or declarations that might contribute to lengthen out theſe religious debates. This, however, did not reduce the Proteſtants to ſilence. The divines of that communion, who had been preſent at the diet, endeavoured to recollect the arguments and objections employed by Faber, and had again recourſe to the pen of Melancthon, who refuted them in an ample and ſa-tisfactory manner in a piece which was preſented to thc emperor on the 2 2d of September, but which Charles refnſed to receive. This anſwer was afterwards enlarged by Melancthon, when he had obtained a copy of Faber’s reply ; and was publiſhed in the year 1531, with the other pieces that related to the doctrine and difeipline of the Lutheran church, under the title of <hi rend="italic">A Defence of the Cοnfijfiοn oſ Augsburg.</hi></p><p>Matters now began to draw towards a criſis. There were only three ways of bringing to a coacluſion theſe</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>