<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>hàff to contend with regular military bodies, and not with undifciplined multitudes, as they expected.</p><p>The duke of Brunſwick encamped his army at La Lun, near the camp of Dumourier. And here the Pruffians began to be in extreme dlſtrefs both from ſickneſs and famine. No temptation could induce the inhabitants of the country to carry proviſions to the hoſtile camp, while at the fame time the French army was abundantly ſupplied.</p><p>Bournonville, with a body of 4000 men, intercepted ſeveral droves of cattle and other convoys of proviſions deſtined for the Pruffians. The rain fell in torrents, and the roads were uncommonly deep. Expoſed to the cold, the moiſture, and want of proviſions, the Pruffians raſhly ate great quantities of the grapes of Champagne. The conſequence of this was, that an epidemical diſtem-per commenced and ſpread through the army to ſuch an extent, that 10,000 men at one time were unfit for duty. The duke of Brunſwick, however, ſtill commanded a force much more numerous than that of Dumourier ; and he has been much cenſured for not attacking his camp, and forcing him to engage. It has been laid, that the veteran and numerous force which he com-manded would have marched to certain victory a-gainſt the raw troops that oppoſed them ; that, having defeated Dumourier’s army, there was nothing to oppoſe their march to Paris. But the duke ot Brunſwick had entered France upon the ſuppoſition, that in its preſent diſtracted ſtate no regular army could be brought into the field againſt him, and that the people at large were hoſtile to the ruling faction. ſſ he contrary of ail this had turned out to be true. He found himſelf in the midſt of an hoſtile people, and op-poſed by ſkilful military chiefs. A defeat in ſuch a ſituation would have brought certain ruin to his army ; and even the loſs ſnſtained in the acquiſition of a victory might have proved equally fatal. ſſ he remains of the French army would not fail to hang upon his rear 5 and from the diſpoſition of the people it appeared impoffible to aſcertain to what amount that army might be ſuddenly increaſed. After propoſing a truce, there-fore, which laſted eight days, he commenced his retreat towards Grandpré, and no advantage v/as gained over him in the courſe of it. Verdun was retaken by the French on the 12th of October, and Longwy on the 18 th; the ſiege of Thionville was at the ſame time raiſed. That ſmall, but ſtrong fortreſs, under the command of general Felix wimpfen, had held in check an army of 15,000 men.</p><p>while the Pruffians were advancing from the north-eaſt, the Auſtrians under the duke of Saxe Tefchen laid ſiege to Liſie. The council-general of the commune anfwered tlte ſummons of the beſiegers thus, "we have juſt renewed our oath to be faithful to the nation,, and to maintain liberty and equality, or to die at our poſt. we wili not perjure ourſelves.” Such was the cant of theſe men who had already perjured themſelves by contributing to overturn the conſtitution which they had repeatedly fworn to defend. The Auſtrian batte-ries began to play upon the town on the 29th, and were chieflydirected againſt that quarter which was inhabi-ted by the lowcr claſs of citizens, for the purpoſe of making them mutinous and ſeditious. This procedure was ill judged. The lower claſtes of mankind are always much accuſtomed to hardſhips, and they go fartheſt in ſupport of any enthuſiaſtic principle they have been perſuaded to adopt. Accordingly, though a great part of the ciry was reduced to a heap of ruins, the citizens of Liſie became daily more obſtinate. They received each other into the houſes that were ſtill ſtanding, and every vault and cellar was occupied. Although up-wards of 30,000 red-hot balls and 6000 bombs were thrown into the city, beſides the efforts made by an im-menſe battering train of artillery, yet the loſs both to the garriſon and people did not exceed 500 pet ſons, moſt of whom were women and children. Aſter a fortnight of fruitlefs labour the Auſtrians raiſed the ſiege.</p><p>war had been declared againſt the king of Sardinia on account of the threatening appearances exhibited in that quarter. On the 20th of September general Montefquieu entered the territories of Savoy, and was received at Chambery and throughout the whole country with marks of unbounded welcome. On the 29th general Anſelm, with another body of troops, took poffeffion of Nice and the conntry around it. On the 30th general Cuſtine advanced to Spires, when he found the Auſtrians drawn up in order of battle. Hc attacked and drove them through the city, taking 3000 of them priſoners. The capture of worms ſucceeded that of Spires; Mentz ſurrendered by capitulation; and Franckfort fell into the hands of the French on the 23d. Out of this laſt place, however, they were afterwards driven on the 2d of December.</p><p>On the 20th of September the French <hi rend="italic">National Convention</hi>  affembled. It was found to contain men of all characters, orders, and ranks. Many diſtinguiſhed members of the <hi rend="italic">Conftituting</hi>  Affembly were elected into it, and alſo ſeveral that had belonged to the <hi rend="italic">Legflalive </hi>Aſſembly ; even foreigners were invited to become French lcgiſſators. The famous Thomas Paine and Dr Prieſtley of England were elected by certain depart-ments ; but the latter declined accepting. Clouts a Pruffian, whom we formerly noticed as bringing a de-putation to the bar of the conſtituent affembly, conſi ſt-ing of perſons repreſenting all the nations of the earth, was alſo choſen. The general aſpect of the new convention ſhowed that the republican party liad acquired a de-cided ſuperiority. On the ſirſt day oſcrneeting M. Collot D’Herbois, who had formerly been an actor, aſcendcd the tribune, and propoſed <hi rend="italic">the eternal abolition of royalty in France.</hi>  The queſtion was carried by acclamation, and the houſe adjourned. Meffages were ſent to all parts of the country to intimate the decree, and by the influence of the Jacobins they were everywhere re-ceived with applauſe. It was next day decreed, that all public acts ſhould be dated by the year of the French republic ; and all citizens were declared eligible to all the vacant offices and places. The rage of republica-niſm ſoon went ſo far, that the ordinary titles of Mon-ſieur and Madame were aboliſhed, and the appellation of <hi rend="italic">Citizen</hi>  ſubſtituted in their ſtead, as more ſuitable to the principles of liberty and equality.— It may be re«= marked, that in this laſt trifling circumſtance an attachment to the form of ſpeech to which they had been accuſtomed appears even in its abolition : For, al-though the Roman orators addreffed their countrymen when affembled by the honourable appellation of <hi rend="italic">Citizens,</hi>  yet they never, in accoſting an individual, called him Citizen Cato, or Citizen Cæfar, according to the mode now adopted in France.</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>