<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ſtanee be reduced to <hi rend="sub">τ</hi>J<hi rend="sub">5</hi>∙ part of a revolution, or twoſeconds and a half ; and theſe errors or inequalities of the teeth were equally diſtributed round the wheel at the diſtance of nine teeth from each other. Now, as the fcrew in ratching had continually hold of ſeveral teeth at the ſame time, and, theſe conſtantly changing, the above-mentioned inequalities ſoon corrected them· ſelves, and the teeth were reduced to a perfect equality. The piece of braſs which carries the wire was how taken away, and the cutting ſcrew was alſo removed, and a plain one (hereafter deſcribed) put in its place : on one end of the ſcrew is a fmall braſs circle, having its edge divided into 60 equal parts, and numbered at every ſixth diviſion, as before-mentioned. Οη the other end of the ſcrew is a ratchet-wheel C, having 60 teeth, covered by the hollowed circle (d), which carries two clicks that catch upon the oppoſite ſides of the ratchet when the ſcrew is to be moved forwards. The cylinder S turns on a ſtrong ſteel aιbor F, which paſſes through and is firmly ſcrewed to the piece Y : this piece, for greater firmneſs, is aftached to the ſcrew-frame G by the braces (v) : a ſpiral groove or thread is cut on the outſide of the cylinder S, which ſerves both for holding the firing, and alſo giving motion to the lever J on its centre by means of a ſteel tooth (n), that works between the threads of the ſpiral. I o the lever is attached a ſtrong ſteel pin(m), on which a braſs ſocket (r) turns : this focket paſſes through a flit in the piece (p), and may be tightened in any part of the flit by the finger-nut (f) : this piece ſerves to regu-late the number of revolutions of the ſcrew for each tread of the treadle R.</p><p>" T is a braſs box containing a ſpiral ſpring ; a ſtrong gut is faſtened and turned tnree or four times round the crrcumference of this box ; the gut then paſſes ſeveral times round the cylinder S, and from thence down to the treadle R. Now, when the treadle is preſſed down, the ſtring pulls the cylinder S round its axis, and the clicks catching hold of the teeth on the ratchet carry the ſcrew round with it, till, by the tooth (n) working in the ſpiral groove, the lever J is brought near the wheel (d), and the cylinder ſtopped by the ſcrew-head (x) ſtriking ©n the top of the lever J ; at the ſame time the ſpring is wound up by the other end of the gut paſſing round the box T. Now, when the foot is taken off the treadle, the ſpring unbending itſelf pulls back the cylinder, the clicks leaving the ratchet and ſcrew at reſt till the piece (t) ſtrikes on the end of the piece (p) : the number of revolutions of the fcrew at each tread is limited by the number of revolutions the cylinder is allowed to turn back before the ſtop ſtrikes on the piece (p).</p><p>“ When the endleſs ſcrew was moved round its axis with a confiderable velocity, it would continue that motion a little after the cylinder S was ſtopped : to</p><p>■    prevent this, the angular leγer « was made ; that when the lever J comes near to ſtop the ſcrew (x), it, by a ſmall chamfer, preſſes down the piece χ of the angular lever ; this brings the other end ⅛" of the ſame lever forwards, and ſtops the endleſs ſcrew by the ſteel pin μ ſtriking upon the top oſ it : the foot of the lever is raiſed again by a ſmall ſpring preſſing on the biace (v).</p><p>“ D, two clamps, connected by the piece «, ſlide</p><p>■    one on each arm of the frame L, and may be fixed at</p><lb/><p>pleaſure by the four finger-fςrcws <hi rend="sup">r</hi>, which preſs againſt ſteel ſprings to avoid ſpoiljng the arms : the pieçe (q) is made to turn without ſhake between two conical pointed ſcrews (f), which are prevented ſrom untura-ing by tightening the finger-nuts N.</p><p>“ The piece M is made to turn on the piece (q), byp^ the conical pointed ſcrews (ſ) reſting in the hollow cen-ters (e).</p><p>“ As there is frequent occaſion to cut diviſions on inclined planes, for that purpoſe the piece ?, in which the tracer is fixed, has a conical axis at [each end, which turn in half holes : when the tracer is ſet to any inclination, it may be fixed there by tightening the ſteel ſcrews 6.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Deſcription oſ the Engine by which the endleſs ſcrew sſ thÿ Dividing Engine was cut.</hi></p><p><hi rend="sup">ti</hi> Fig. 9. repreſents this engine of its full dimen, fions feen from one fide.</p><p>“ Fig. 8. the upper fide of the ſame as ſeen from above.</p><p>“ A repreſents a triangular bar of ſteel, to which the triangular holes in the pieces B and C are accurately fitted, and may be fixed on any part of the bar by the ſcrews D∙</p><p>" E is a piece of ſteel whereon the ſcrew is intended to be cut ; which, after being hardened and tempered, has its pivots turned in the form of two fruſtums of c9nes, as repreſented in the drawings of the dividing engine (fig. ç.). Theſe pivots were exactly fitted to the half holes F and T, which were kept together by the ſcrews Z.</p><p>" H repreſents a ſcrew of untempered ſteel, having a pivot I, which turns in the hole K. At the other end of the ſcrew is a hollow centre, which receives the hardened conical point of the ſteel pin M. when this point is fufficiently preſſed againſt the ſcrew, to prevent its ſhaking, the ſteel pin may be fixed by tightening the ſcrews Y.</p><p>" N is a cylindric nut, moveable on the ſcrew H 5 which, to prevent any ſhake, may be tightened by the ſcrews O. This nut is connected with the ſaddle-piece P by means of the intermediate univerſal joint W, through which the arbor of the ſcrew H paſſes. A front view of this piece, with a ſection acroſs the ſcrew arbor, is repreſented at X. This joint is connected with the nut by means of two ſteel flips S, which turn on pins between the cheeks T on the nut N. Thc other ends of theſe flips S turn in like manner on pin&lt;</p><p>(a)    . Οηε axis of this joint turns in a hole in the cock</p><p>(b)    , which is fixed to the ſaddle-piece ; and the other turns in a hole (d), made for that purpoſe in the ſame piece on which the cock (b) is fixed. By this means, when the ſcrew is turned round, the ſaddle-piece will ſlide uniformly along the triangular bar A.</p><p>" K is a ſmall triangular bar of well-tempered ſteel, which Aides in a groove of the fame form on the ſaddle-piece P. The point of this bar or cutter is formed to the ſhape of the thread intended to be cut on the endleſs ſcrew. when the cutter is ſet to take proper hold of the intended fcrew, it may be fixed by tightening the fcrew (e), which preſs the two pieces of braſs G upon it.</p><p>“ Having meaſured the circumference of the divi-ding-wheel, I found it would require a ſcrew about one</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>