<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>RANA,the frog, in zoology; a genus belongingto the order of amphibia reptilia. The body is naked, furniſhed with four feet, and without any tail. Therc are 17 ſpecics. The moſt remarkable are,</p><p>i. The temporaria, or common frog. This is an animal ſo well known, that it needs no defcription; but ſome of its properties are veιy ſingular.</p><p>Its fpring, or power of taking large leaps, is re-markably great, and it is the beſt ſwimmer of all four-footed animals. Nature hath finely adapted its parts for thofe ends, the fore members of 'the body being very lightly made, the hind legs and thighs very long, and furniſhed with very ſtrong mufcles.</p><p>while in a tadpole ſtate, it is entirely a water animal ; the work of generation is performed in that ele-χr&gt;ent, as may be ſeen in every pond during ſpring, when the female remains oppreſſed by the male for a number of days.</p><p>The work of propagation is extremely ſingular, it be-ing certain that the frog has not a <hi rend="italic">penis intrans.</hi>  There appears a ſtrong analogy in this caſe between a certain claſs of the vegetable kingdom and thoſe animals ; for it is well known, that when the female frog depofits its ſpawn, the male inſtantaneouſly impregnates it with what we may call a <hi rend="italic">ſarina f∑cundcms,</hi>  in the ſame manner as the palm-tree conveys fructification to the flowers of the female, which would otherwiſe be barren.</p><p>As ſoon as the frogs are releaſed from their tadpole ſtate, they immediately take to land ; and if the weather has been hot, and there fall any reſreihing ſhowers, you may fee the ground for a confiderable ſpace perfectly blackened by myriads of theſe animalcules, ſeek-ing ſor ſome ſecure lurking places. Some philoſo-phers, not giving themſelves time to examine into this phenomenon, imagined them to have been generated in the clouds, and ſhowered on the earth ; but had they, like our Derham, but traced them to the next pool, they would have found a better folution of the difficulty. See <hi rend="italic">Preternatural RAiNs.</hi></p><p>As frogs adhere cloſely to the backs of their own fpecies, ſo we know they will do the ſame by fiſh.— walton mentions a ſtrange ſtory of their deſtroying pike ; but that they will injure, if not entirely kill carp, is a fact ⅛difputable, ſrom the following rela-tion. Not many years ago, on fiſhing a pond belong-ing to Mr Pitt of Encomb, Dorſetſhire, great numbers of the carp were found each with a frog mounted on it, the hind legs clinging to the back, and the fore legs fixed in the corner of each eye of the fiſh, which were thin and greatly wafted, teized by carrying ſo diſagrce-able a load. 1 heſe frogs Mr Pennant ſuppoſes to lιave been males diſapppointed of a mate.</p><p>The croaking of frogs is well known ; and from that in fenny countries they are diſtinguiſhed by ludicrous titles : thus they are ſtyled <hi rend="italic">Dutch nightingales,</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">Boſ-ton waites.</hi></p><p>Yet there is a time of the year when they become mute, neither croaking nor opening their mouths for a whole month : this happens in the hot ſeaſon, and that is in many places known to the country people by tbe name of the <hi rend="italic">paddock moon.</hi>  It is ſaid, that during that period their mouths are ſo cloſed, that no force (without killing the animal) will be capable of opening them.</p><p>Thefe, as well as other reptiles, feed but a final! ſpace of the year. The food of this genus is flies, in-ſects, and fnails. Toads are ſaid to feed alſo on bees, and to do great injury to thoſe uſeful infects.</p><p>During winter, frogs and toads remain in a torpid ſtate : the laſt of which will dig into the earth, and cover themſelves with almoſt the ſame agility as the mole. See Physiology, n<hi rend="sup">0</hi>48 and note (b), and ſh 52.</p><p>2.    The eſculenta, or edible frog, differs from the former, in having a high protuberance in the middle of the back, forming a very ſharp angle. Its colours are alſo more vivid, and its marks more diſtinct ; the ground colour being a pale or yellowiſh green, marked with rows of black ſpots from the head to the rump.—. This, and (Mr Pennant thinks) the former, are eaten. He has feen in the markets at Paris whole hampers full, which the venders were preparing for the tab!e, by fkinning and cutting off the fore-parts, the loins and legs only being kept ; but his ſtrong diſlike to theſc reptiles prevented a cloſe exanſhiatioa into the ſpecies,</p><p>3.    In the country of Pennſylvania, and fome other parts of North America, there is a very large ſpecies of frogs called the <hi rend="italic">bullfrog,</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">rana ocellatd.</hi>  Their irides arc of a duſky red, ſurrounded with a yellow ring. The auricles are covered with a thin circular ſkin, which forms a ſpot behind each eye. They have four toes on the fore-feet, and five palmated toes behind. Their co-lour is a duſky brown, mixed with yellowiſh green, and fpotted with black. The belly is yellowiſh, and faintly fpotted. Theſe make a monſtrous roaring noiſe like a bull, only ſomewhat ſhore hoarſe. Their fize is ſuperior to that of any other of the genus, and they can ſpring forward three yards at a leap. By this means they will equal in fpecd a very good horſe in its ſwiſteſt couiſſe. Their places of abode are ponds, or bogs with ſtagnant water ; but they never frequent ſtreams. when many</p></body></text></TEI>