<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>with ſhouts from the immenſe concourſe of ſpectators of " Vive le Roi et vive l’affemble nationale,” <hi rend="italic">Long live the king and the national aſſembly.</hi>  M. Bailly was choſen preſident for four days only, Meſſrs Camus and Piſon de Galand fεcrctaries, and the aſſembly proceeded to bu∙ fineſs.</p><p>Its firſt acts were deciſively expreſſive of its own ſo-vereignty. All taxes impoſed without the conſent of the reprefentatives of the people were declared to be null and void ; but a temporary fonction was given to the preſent taxes, although illegal, till the diſſolution of the aſſembly and no longer. It was added, that " as ſoon as, in concert with his majeſty, the aſſembly ſhould be able to fix the principles of national regeneration, it would take into conſiderat ion the <hi rend="italic">national debt,</hi>  placing from the prefent moment the creditors of the ſtate un-der the fofeguard and honour of the French <hi rend="italic">nation.”</hi></p><p>The popular caufe now gained ground fo faſt, that on the 19th of June a majority of the clergy voted for the verification of their powers in common with the national aſſembly, and they reſolved to unite with them on the following day.</p><p>Affairs were now come to a crifis, and the nobleβ perceived that they muſt inſtantly make a decifive ſtand, or yield up their cauſe as finally loft. Such was their alarm, that M. d’Eſpremenil propoſed, at one of the fittings of their order, to addreſs the king, intreating him to diſſolve the ſtates-generah Hi-therto that prince had gone along with M. Neckar in favouring the popular cauſe in oppoſition to the ariſto' cracy. But every art was now uſed to alarm his mind upon the ſubject of the late aſſumptions of power on the part of the commons, and theſe arts were at length ſucceſsful. Repeated counſels were held ; M. Neckar was abſent attending a dying fiſter, and the king was prevailed upon to act agreeably to the advice of the leaders of the nobles. But the firſt meafure which they adopted was fo ill conducted as to afford little proſpect of final ſucceſs to their cauſe. Οη the 20th of June,, when the preſident and members were about to enter as uſual into their own hall, they found it unexpectedly ſurrounded by a detachment of the guards, who refuſed them admiffion, while the heralds at the ſame time pro-claimed a royal ſeſſion. Alarmed by this unforeſeen event, the meaning of which they knew not, but ap-prehending that an immediate diſſolution of the aſſembly was deſigned, they inſtantly retired to a neighbouring tennis-court, where, in the vehemence of their enthu-iiaſm, they took a folemn oath " never to feparate till the conſtitution of their country ſhould be completed.”</p><p>Οη the 22d a new proclamation intimated that the royal ſeſſion, was deferred till the following day. It was now found that the aſſembly had been excluded from their hall merely becaufe the workmen were oc-cupied in preparing it for the intended ſolemnity. This information was ill calculated to excite favourable expectations of the meaſures about to be adopted at a royal ſeffion, uſhered in by ſuch circumſtances of mark-ed diſreſpect for the reprefentatives of the people. The aſſembly, after wandering about in ſearch of a place of meeting, at length entered the church of St Louis, and were immediately joined by the majority of the clergy, with their preſident, the archbiſhop of vienne, at their head. Two nobles of Dauphiné, the marquis de Blacon and. the count d’Agoult, preſcnted. their cou∖-</p><p>miſſions at the ſame time. Encouraged by theſe events, and by the applauſes of fiμroundiιιg multitudes, the aſſembly now expected with firmneſs the meaſures about to be adopted.</p><p>The royal'ſeffion was held in the moſt fplendid form,D but altogether in the ſtyle of the ancient deſpotiſm. Soldiers ſurrounded the hall. The two ſuperior orders were ſeated, while the reprefentatives of the people, left ſtanding a full hour in the rain, were in no humour, when at laſt admitted, to receive with much compla-cency the commands of their fovereign. The king read a diſcourſe, in which he declared null and void the reſolutions of the r7tl1, but at the ſame time preſented the plan of a conſtitution for France. It contained many good and patriotic principles, but preſerved the diſtinction of orders, and the exerciſe of <hi rend="italic">lettres de cachet ;</hi>  it foid nothing about any active ſhare in the le-giſlative power to be poſſeſſed by the ſtates-general, and was ſilent both about the reſponſibility of miniſters and the liberty of the prefs. The king concluded by commanding the deputies immediately to retire, and to aſ-ſemble again on the following day. He then withdrew, and was followed by all the nobles and a part of the clergy. The commons remained in gloomy ſilence on their feats. It was interrupted by the grand maſter of the ceremonies, who reminded the preſident of the intentions of the king. Inſtantly the vehement count de Mirabeau, ſtarting from his feat, exclaimed with indignation, " ſ'he commons of France have determined to debate, we have heard the intentions that have been ſuggeſted to the king ; and you, who cannot be his agent with the ſtates-general, you who have here neither feat nor voice, nor a right to ſpeak, are not the perfon to remind us of his ipeech. Go tell your maſter, that we are here by the power , of the people, and that nothing ſhall expel us but the bayonet.” '1 he applauſe of the aſſembly ſeconded the enthuſiaſm oſ the orator, and the maſter of the ceremonies withdrew in filence.</p><p>M. Camus then roſe ; and in a violent ſpeech indignantly ſtigmatiſed the royal ſeffion by the obnoxious appellation of a <hi rend="italic">bed oſjufiice ;</hi>  he concluded by moving that the aſſembly ſhould declare their unqualified adhe-rence to their former decrees. This motion was fol» lowed by another, pronouncing the perſons of the de-puties inviolable. Both were iuppoιted by Meſſrs Pc’ tion, Barnave, Glaizen, the Abbés Gregoire, Sieyes, and many others, and were unanimouſly decreed. The aſſembly therefore continued their fittings in the uſual form. Οη the following day the majority of the clergy attended as mcmbers ; and on the 25th the duke of ûrleans, along with 49 of the deputies belonging to the order of nobles, joined them alſo. The remaining nobles, as well as the fmall minority of the clergy, now found themſelves aukwardly ſituated. whether on this account, or becauſe their leaders had by.this time formed a plan for carrying their point not by peaceable means but by the aid of a military force, the king, on the 27th, invited by a preffing letter both orders to join the commons. This requeſt was immediately complied with, although many of the nobility difoppro-ved of the raeaſure.</p><p>The ſituation of France was now become truly alarming, when the king retired from the aſſembly after the royal ſeffion, he was followed by more than 6000</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>