<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>whieh ſenſe it is the ſame with <hi rend="italic">ſcoria, frees,</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">excre</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">ments.</hi></p><p>RECRIMINATION, in law, an accuſation brought by the accuſed againſt the accuſer upon the fame fact.</p><p>RECRUITS, in military affairs, new-raifed foldier3 deſigned to ſupply the place of thoſe who have loſt their live3 in the ſervice, or who are diſabled by age or _ wounds.</p><p>RECTANGLE, in geometry, the ſame with a right-angled parallelogram. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Geometry.</hi></p><p>RECTIFICATION, in chemiſtry, is nothing but the repetition of a diſtillation or ſublimation ſeveral times, in order to render the ſubſtance purer, finer, and freer from aqueous and earthy parts.</p><p><hi rend="italic">RεcτifιcAτιoN oſSpirits.</hi>  See <hi rend="smallcaps">Distillation.</hi></p><p>RECTIFIER, in navigation, an inſtrument conſiſt-ing of two parts, which are two circles, either laid one upon, or let into the other, and ſo faſtened together in their centres, that they repreſent two compaffes, one fixed, the other moveable ; each of them divided into the 32 points of the compaſs, and 360<hi rend="sup">o</hi>, and numbered both ways, from the north and the ſouth, ending at the eaſt and weſt, in 90<hi rend="sup">c</hi>.</p><p>The fixed compaſs repreſents the horizon, in which the north and all the other points of the compaſs are fixed and immoveable.</p><p>The moveable compaſs repreſents the mariner’s com-paſs ; in which- the north and all other points are liable to variation.</p><p>In the centre of the moveable compaſs is faſtened.a filk thread, long enough to reach the outfide of the fixed compaſs. But if the inſtrument be made of wood, there is an index inſtead of the thread.</p><p>Its uſe is to find the variation of the compafs, to rectify the courſe at ſea ; having the amplitude or azi-muth given.</p><p>RECTIFYING the <hi rend="smallcaps">Globe.</hi>  See <hi rend="smallcaps">Geography, </hi>p. 656.</p><p>RECTILINEAR, in geometry, right-lined; thus figures whoſe perimeter conſiſts of right lines, are ſaid to be rectilinear.</p><p>RECTITUDE, in philoſophy, refers either to the act of judging or of willing ; and therefore whatever comes under the denomination of rectitude, is either what is true or what is good, theſe being the only objects about which the mind exerciſes its two faculties &lt;ff judging and willing.</p><p>Moral rectitude, or 'uprightnefs, is the chooſing and purſuing thoſe things which the mind, upon due inqui-ry and attention, clearly perceives to be good ; and avoiding thoſe that are evil. See <hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps">Moral Philoſophy.</hi></hi></p><p>RECTOR, a term applied to ſeveral perſons whoſe offices are very different : as, 1. The rector of a pariſh is a clergyman that has the charge and cure of a pariſh, and poſſeſſes all the tithes, &amp;c.    2. The ſame name is</p><p>alfo given to the chief elective officer in ſeveral foreign univerſities, particularly in that of Paris, and alſo. in thoſe of Scotland. It is alſo applied to the head maſ-ter of large ſichools in Seotland, as in the high ſchool of Edinburgh. 3. Rector is alſo uſed in ſeveral convents for the ſuperior officer who governs the houſe : ιind the Jeſuits give this name to the ſuperiors of ſuch of their houſes as are either ſeminaries or colleges.</p><p>RECTORY, a pariſh-church, parſonage, or ſpiritual living, with all its rights, tithes, and glebes.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Rectory is alſo ſometimes uſed for the rector*» manſion or parſonage-houſe.</hi></p><p>RECTUM, in anatomy, the third and laſt of the large inteſtincs or guts. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Anatomy,</hi>  n<hi rend="sup">c</hi>' 93.</p><p>RECTUS, in anatomy, a name common to ſeveral pairs of mufcles, ſo called on account of the ſtraightneſs of their fibres.</p><p>RECUPERATORES, among the Romans, were commiſſioners appointed to take cognizance of private matters in diſpute, between the ſubjects of the ſtate and foreigners, and to take care that the former had juſtice done them. It came at laſt to be uſed ſor com-rniſſioners, to whom the prætor referred the determi-nation of any affair between one fubject and another.</p><p>RECURRENTS, in anatomy, a name given to ſe-veral large branches of nerves ſent out by the par va-gum from the upper part of the thorax to the larynx,</p><p>RECURVIROSTRA, in ornithology ; a genus belonging to the order of grallæ of Linnaeus, and that of palmipedes of Pennant and Latham. The bill is long, ſubulated, bent back, ſharp and flexible at the point. The feet are webbed, and furniſhed with three toes forwards, and a ſhort one behind. Mr Latham notes of this genus three fpecies, viz. the Avofetta, or the one commonly known, the Americana, and the Alba. This laſt, it is probable, has ſome affinity to the -Americana. The recurviroſtra avoſetta is about the ſize of a lapwing in body, but has very long legs. The fubſtance of the bill is foft, and almoſt membranous at its tip ; it is thin, weak, ſlender, compreffed horizontally, and incapable of defence or effort. Thefe birds are variegated with black and white, and during the win-ter are frequent on the eaſtern ſhores of Great Britain. They viſit alſo the Severn, and ſometimes the pools of Shropſhire. They feed on worms and infects, which they ſcoop out of the fand with their bills. They lay two eggs, white, with a greeniſh hue, and large ſpots of black ; theſe eggs are about the ſize of a pigeon’s.— They are found alſo in various parts of the continent of Europe, in Ruſſia, Denmark, and Sweden, but they are not numerous. They are alſo found in Siberia, but oftener about the ſalt lakes of the Tartarian deſert, and about<hi rend="sup">r</hi> the Caſpian ſea. They are found likewiſe on the coaſts of Picardy in France in April and November, and at orleans, but rarely. In breeding-time they are very plentiful on the coaſts of Bas Poictou. They do not appear to wander farther ſouth in Europe than</p><p>Italy, whether from timidity or addreſs, the avoſet ſhuns ſnares, and is not eaſily taken. The American avoſet is rather larger and longer than the laſt. The bill is ſimilar, and its colour black : the forehead is duſky white : the head, neck, and upper part of the breaſt, arc of a deep cream-colour : the lower parts of the neck behind white : the back is black, and the uιf-der parts from the breaſt pure white : the wings are partly black, partly white, and partly aſh-coloured. Theſe birds inhabit North America, and were found by Dampier in Shark’s Bay, on the coaſt of New Holland. See Plate CCCCXXXV.</p><p>Tlie recurviroſtra, or ſcolopax alba, is about 14 inches and a quarter long, its colour white, the inferior coverts of its wings duſkiſh, its bill orange, its legs brown. Edwards remarks, that the bill of this bird is bent upwards, as in the avoſet ; its bill black at the tip, and orange the reſt of its length ; all the plumage is white,</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>