<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>peheve that eur naval architects are not diflpoſed to grant that they have profited much by all the labours of the mathematicians. But the ancients had not made any great progreſs in the phyſicomathematical ſciences, which conſiſt chiefly in thc application of calculus to the phenomena of nature. In this branch they could make none, becaufe they had not the means of inveſtigation. A knowledge of the motions and actions of fluids is acceſſible only to thoſe who are familiarly acquainted with the fluχionary mathematics; and with-out this key there is no admittance. Even when poffeffed of this guide, our progreſs has been very flow, heſitating, and devious ; and we have not yet been able to eſtabliſti any ſet of doctrines which are ſuſceptible of an eafy and confident application to the arts of life. If we have advanced farther than the ancients, it is becauſe we have come after them, and have proſited by their labours, and even by their miſtakes.</p><p>Sir Ifaac Newton was the firſt (as far as we can recollect) who attempted to make the motions and ac-tions of fluids the ſubject of mathematical diſcuſſion. Ηe had invented the method of fluxions long before he engaged in his phyfical reſearches ; and he proceeded in theſe <hi rend="italic">ſua mαthfi facem pr¢ſerente.</hi>  Yet even with this guide he was often obliged to grope his way, and to try various bye-paths, in the hopes of obtaining a legitimate theory. Having exerted all his powers in eſtabliſhing a theory of the lunar motions, he was obliged to reſt contented with an approximation inſtead oſ a perfect folution of the problem which aſcer-tains the motions of three bodies mutually acting on each other. This convinced him that it was in vain to expect an accurate inveſtigation of the motions and actions of fluids, where millions of unfeen particles combine their influence. He therefore caſt about to ſind ſome particular caſe of the problem which would admit of an accurate determination, and at the ſame time furniſh circumftances of analogy or reſemblance ſuſſiciently numerous for giving limiting caſes, which ſhould include between them thoſe other caſes that did not admit of this accurate inveſtigation. And thus, by knowing the limit to which the cafe propoſed did approximate, and the circumſtance which regulated the approximation, many uſeful propoſitions might be deduced for directing us in the application of theſe doc-trines to the arts of life.</p><p>He therefore figured to himſelf a hypothetical collection of matter which poffeffed the characteriſtic pro-perty of fluidity, viz. the <hi rend="italic">quaqudverfum</hi>  propagation of preffure, and the moſt perfect intermobility (pardon the uncouth term) of parts, and which formed a phy. ſical whole or aggregate, whoſe parts were connected by mechanical forces, determined both in degree and in direction, and ſuch as rendered the determination of certain important circumſtances of their motion ſuſceptible of preciſe inveſtigation. And he conςluded, that the laws which he ſhould difcover in theſe motions muſt have a great analogy with the laws of the motions of real fluids : And from this hypotheſis he deduced a ſe-rιes of propoiitions, which form the baſis of almoſt all the theories of the impulfe and reſiftance of fluids which have been offered to the public ſince his time.</p><p>It muſt be acknowledged, that the reſults of this theory agree but ill with experiment, and that, <hi rend="italic">in the way in which it has been zealouſly proj'ecuted by ſubſequent mathematicians,</hi>  it proceeds on principles or aſſumptions which are not only gratuitous, but even falſe. But it affords ſuch a beautiful appl ication of geometry and calculus, that mathematicians have been as it were faf-cinated by it, and have publiſhed ſyſtems ſo elegant and ſo extenſively applicable, that one cannot help lamenting that the foundation is ſo flimſy. John Bernoulli’s theory, in his differtation on the communica-' tion of motion, and Bouguer’s in his <hi rend="italic">Traité du Navire, </hi>and in his <hi rend="italic">Theoriedu Manœuvre et delà Mâture des k<hi rend="sup">r</hi>aif-feau ∖,</hi>  muſt ever be conſidered as among the fineſt ſpecimens of phyſicomathematical ſcience which the world has ſeen. And, with all its imperfections, this theory ſtill furniſhes (as w’as expected by its illuſtrious author) many propoſitions of immenfe practical uſe, they being the limits to which the real phenomena of the impulſe and refiſtance of fluids really approximate. So that when the law by which th'e phenomena deviate from the theory is once determined by a well choſen ſeries of experiments, this hypothetical theory becomes almoſt as valuable as a true one. And we may add, that although Mr d’Alembert, by treading warily in the ſteps oi Sir lſaac Newton in another route, has diſcovered a genuine and unexceptionable theory, the proceſs of inveſtigation is ſo intricate, requiring every fineffe of the moſt abſtruſe analyfis, and the final equations aie ſo complicated, that even their moſt expert author has not been able to deduce more than one-fimple propofition (which too was diſcovered by Daniel Bernoulli by a more fimple proceſs) which can be applied to any uſe. The hypothetical theory of Newton, therefore, continues to be the groundwork of all our practical knowledge of the ſubject.</p><p>we ſhall therefore lay before our readers a very ſhort view of the theory, and the manner of applying it. we ihall then ſhow its defects (all of which were pointed out by its great author), and give an hiſtorical account of the many attempts which have been made to amend it or to ſubſtitute another: in all which we think it our duty to ſhow, that Sir Iſaac Newton took the lead, and pointed out every path which others have taken, if we except Daniel Bernoulli and d’Alembert ; and we ſhall give an account of the chief ſets of experiments which’ have been made on this important ſubject, in the hopes of eſtabliſhing an empirical theory, which may be employed with confidence in the arts of life.</p><p>we know by experience that force muſt be applied to a body in order that it may move through a fluid, ſuch as air or water ; and that a body projected with any velocity is gradually retarded in its motion, and generally brought to reſt. The analogy of nature makes us imagine that there is a force acting in the oppofite direction, or oppofing the motion, and that this force relides in, or is exerted by, the fluid. And the phenomena referable thoſe which accompany the known refiſtance of active beings, ſuch as animals. Therefore we give to this ſuppoſed force the metaphorical name of Resistance, <hi rend="sup">,</hi>we alſh know that a fluid in-motion will hurry a ſolid body along with the ſtream, and that it requires force to maintain it in its place. A fimilar analogy makes us ſuppoſe that the fluid exerts force, in the ſame manner as when an active being impels the body before him ; therefore we call this the <hi rend="italic">IMPULSION of a Fluid.</hi>  And as our knowledge of nature inlorms∙ us that the mutual actions of bodies are in-</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>