<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="chi.28490924-1526168109_Page_0432.jpf" type="entry" xml:id="eb07-20-s03-0369-04" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SIR</label>,
the title of a knight or baronet, which, for distinction’s sake, as it is now given indiscriminately to all men, is always prefixed to the knight’s Christian name, either in speaking or in writing to him.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir Charles Hardy’s</hi> island, in the Southern Pacific Ocean, discovered by Captain Carteret in the year 1767. Long. 154. 6. E. Lat-4. 38. S.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir Charles</hi> H <hi rend="smallcaps">ardy’s Islands,</hi> a cluster of small islands in the South Pacific Ocean, discovered by Captain Cook in 1770. Long. 217. W. Lat. 11. 55. S.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir Charles Saunders’ Island,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Tapooamanhoo,</hi> in the Southern Pacific Ocean, discovered by Captain Wallis in 1765. It is about six miles in length. Long. 150. 40. W. Lat. 17. 28. S.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir Ηενrυ Martin's Island,</hi> in the Pacific Ocean, discovered by Lieutenant Hergest in 1792, and the most fertile and considerable of the group to which it belongs. Long. 220. 19. E. Lat. 80. 51. S.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir Isaac Ροιντ,</hi> a cape on the south coast of New Hol- land. Long. 135. 10. E. Lat. 34. 27. S.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir Joseph Banks’ Group,</hi> a cluster of small islands in Spencer’s Gulf, on the south coast of New Holland.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir Roger Curtis' Isles,</hi> an island, with two smaller ones near it, on the south coast of New Holland, twenty-two miles south-east of Wilson’s promontory.</p></div></body></text></TEI>