<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r02-0326-01" facs="gri_33125011196389_0332.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>ROMANO</label>
(Giulio), a famous painter, was the diſciple of Raphael, who had ſuch an affection for him, that he appointed him, with John Francis Penni, his heir. His conceptions were more extraordinary and more elevated than even thoſe of his maſter, but not ſo natural. He was wonderful in the choice of attitudes ; but did not perfectly underſtand the lights and ſhades, and is frequently harſh and ungraceful. The folds of his draperies, ſays Du Freſnoy, are neither beautiful nor great, eaſy nor natural, but all extravagant, like the fantaſtical habits of comedians. He was, however, ſuperior to moſt painters, by his profound knowledge of antiquity ; and, by converging with the works of the moſt excellent poets, particularly Homer, he made himſelf maſter of the qualifications neceſſarily required in a great deſigner. Julio Romano was alſo well ſhilled in architecture. He was employed by cardinal de Medicis, who was afterwards pope under the name of <hi rend="italic">Clement</hi> VII.; and afterwards went to Mantua, whither he was invited by Frederic Gonzaga, marquis of that city, in order to avoid his being juſtly puniſhed for his having drawn at Rome the deſigns of 20 ob-ſcene plates, engraved by Mark Antony, to which A-retine added the ſame number of ſonnets. Julio Romano embelliſhed the city of Mantua with many of his performances both in painting and architecture ; and died in that city in 1545, at 54 years of age, much regretted by the marquis, who had an extraordinary friendſhip ſor him.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>