<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r02-0462-02"
                facs="gri_33125011196389_0468.tif" type="entry">

                <p><label>ROOF</label> expreſſes the covering of a houſe or building, by which its
                    inhabitants or contents are protected ſrom the injuries of the weather. It is
                    perhaps the eſſential part of a houſe, and is frequently uſed to expreſs the
                    whole. To <hi rend="italic">come under a perſon’'s roof,</hi> is to enjoy his
                    protection and ſociety, to dwell with him. <hi rend="italic">Tectum</hi> was
                    uſed in the ſame ſenſe by the Romans. To be within our walls rather expreſſes
                    the being in our poſſeſſion : a roof therefore is not only an eſſential part of
                    a houſe, but it even ſeems to be its characteriſtic feature. The Greeks, who
                    have perhaps excelled all nations in taſte, and who have given the moſt perfect
                    model of architectonic ordonnance within a certain limit, never erected a
                    building which did not exhibit this part in the diſtincteſt manner ; and though
                    they borrowed much of their model from the orientals, as will be evident to any
                    who compares their architecture with the ruins of Perſepolis, and of the tombs
                    in the mountains of Sciras, they added that form of roof which their own climate
                    taught them was neceſſary for ſheltering them from the rains. The roofs in
                    Perſia and Arabia are flat, but thoſe of Greece are without exception doping. It
                    ſeems therefore a groſs violation of the true principles of taſte in
                    architecture (at leaſt in the regions of Europe), to take away or to hide the
                    roof of a houſe ; and it muſt be aſeribed to that rage for novelty which is ſo
                    powerful in the minds of the rich. Our anceſtors ſeemed to be of a very
                    different opinion, and turned their attention to the ornamenting of their roofs
                    as much as any other part of a building. They ſhowed them in the moſt
                    conſpicuous manner, running them up to a great height, broke them into a
                    thouſand fanciful ſhapes, and ſtuck them full of highly dreſſed windows. We
                    laugh at this, and call it Gothic and clumſy ; and our great architects, not to
                    offend any more in this way, conceal the roof altogether by parapets,
                    baluſtrades, and other contrivances. Our forefathers certainly did offend
                    againſt the maxims of true taſte, when they enriched a part of a houſe with
                    marks of elegant habitation, which every ſpectator muſt know to be a cumberſome
                    garret : but their ſucceſſors no leſs offend, who take off the cover of the
                    houſe altogether, and make it impoſſible to know whether it is not a mere ikreen
                    or colonnade we are looking at.</p>
                <p>We cannot help thinking that Sir Chriſtopher Wren erred when he ſo induſtriouily
                    concealed the roof of St Paul’s church in London. The whole of the upper order
                    is a mere ſcreen. Such a quantity of wall would have been intolerably offenſive,
                    had he not given it ſome appearance of habitation by the mock windows or niches.
                    Even in this ſtate it is gloomy, and it is odd, and is a puzzle to every
                    ſpectator—There ſhould be nd puzzle in the deſign of a building any more than in
                    a diſcourſe. It has been ſaid that the double roof of our great churches which
                    have aiſles is an incongruity, looking like a houſe ſtanding on the top of
                    another houſe. But there is not the leaſt occaſion for ſuch a thought. We know
                    that the aiſle is a ſhed, a cloiſter. Suppoſe only that the lower roof or ſhed
                    is hidden by .a baluſtrade, it then becomes a portico, againſt which the
                    cennoiſſeur has no objection : yet there is no difference ; ſor the portico muſt
                    have a cover, otherwiſe it is neither a ſhed, cloiſter, nor portico, any more
                    than a building without a roof is a houſe. A houſe without a viſible roof is
                    like a mah abroad without his hat ; and we may add, that the whim of concealing
                    the chimneys, now ſo faſhionable, changes a houſe to a barn or ſtore-houſe. A
                    houſe ſhould not be a copy of any thing. It has a title to be an original ; and
                    a ſcreen like houſe and a pillar-like candleſtick are ſimilar ſoleciſms in
                    taſte.</p>
                <p>The architect is anxious to preſent a fine object, and a very ſimple outline
                    diſcuſſes all his concerns with the roof. He leaves it to the carpenter, whom he
                    frequently puzzles (by his arrangements) with coverings almoſt impoſſible to
                    execute. Indeed it is ſeldom that the idea of a roof is admitted by him into his
                    great compoſitions; or if he does introduce it, it is from mere affectation, and
                    we may ſay pedantry. A pediment is frequently ſtuck up in the middle of a grand
                    front, in a ſituation where a roof cannot perform its office ; for the rain that
                    is ſuppoſed to flow down its ſides muſt be received on the top of the level
                    buildings which flank it. This is a manifeſt incongruity. The tops of dreſſed
                    windows, trifling porches, and ſometimes a projecting portico, are the only
                    ſituations in which we ſee the figure of a roof correſpond with its office.
                    Having thus loſt ſight of the principle, it is not ſurpriſing that the
                    draughtſman (for he ſhould not be called architect) runs into every whim : and
                    we ſee pediment within pediment, a round pediment, a hollow pediment, and the
                    greateſt of all abſurdities, a broken pediment. Nothing could ever reconcile us
                    to the ſight of a man with a hat without its crown, becauſe we cannot overlook
                    the uſe of a hat.</p>
                <p>But when one builds a houſe, ornament alone will not do. We muſt have a cover ;
                    and the enormous ex-pence and other great inconveniences which attend the
                    concealment of this cover by parapets, baluſtrades, and ſcreens, have obliged
                    architects to conſider the pent roof as admiſſible, and to regulate its form.
                    Any man of ſenſe, not under the influence of prejudice, would be determined in
                    this by its ſitneſs for anſwering its purpoſe. A high pitched roof will
                    undoubtedly ſhoot off the rains and ſnows better than one of a lower pitch. The
                    wind will not ſo eaſily blow the dropping rain in between the ſlates, nor will
                    it have ſo much power to ſtrip them off. A high pitched roof will exert a
                    ſmaller thruſt on the walls, both becauſe its ſtrain is leſs horizontal, and
                    becauſe it will admit of lighter covering. But it is more expenſive, becauſe
                    there is more of it. It requires a greater ſize of timbers to make it equally
                    ſtrong, and it expoſes a greater ſurface to the wind.</p>
                <p>There have been great changes in the pitch of roofs : our forefathers made them
                    very high, and we make them very low. It does not, however, appear, that this
                    change has been altogether the effect of principle. In the ſimple unadorned
                    habitations of private perſons, every thing conies to be adjuſted by an
                    experience of inconveniences which have reſulted from too low pitched rcofs ;
                    and their pitch will always be nearly ſuch as ſuits the climate änd covering.
                    Our architects, however, go to work oh different principles. Their pro-feſſed
                    aim is to make a beautiful object. The ſources of the pleaſures ariſing from
                    what we call <hi rend="italic">tafle</hi> are ſo various, ſo complicated, and
                    even ſo whimſical, that it</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r02-0463" facs="gri_33125011196389_0469.tif"/>
                <p>is almoſt in vain to look for principle in the rules adopted by our profeſſed
                    architects. We cannot help thinking, that much of their practice reſults from a <hi rend="italic">pedantic</hi> veneration for the beautiſul productions
                    of Grecian architecture. Such architects as have written on the principles of
                    the art in reſpect of proportions, or what they call the ordonnance, are very
                    much puzzled to make a chain of reaſoning ; and the moſt that they have made of
                    the Greek architecture is, that it exhibits a nice adjuſtment of ſtrength and
                    ſtrain. But when we conſider the extent of this adjuſtment, we find that it is
                    wonderfully limited. The whole of it conſiſts of a baſcment, a column, and an
                    entablature ; and the entablature, it is true, exhibits ſomething of a
                    connection with the framework and roof of a wooden building ; and we believe
                    that it really originated from this in the hands of the orientals, from whom the
                    Greeks certainly borrowed their forms and their combinations. We could eaſily
                    ſhow in the ruins of Perſepolis, and among the tombs in the mountains (which
                    were long prior to the Greek architecture), the fluted column, the baſe, the
                    Ionic and Corinthian capital, and the Doric arrangement of lintels, beams, and
                    rafters, all derived from unqueſtionable principle. The only addition made by
                    the Greeks was the pent roof ; and the changes made by them in the ſubordinate
                    forms of things are ſuch as we ſhould expect ſrom their exquiſite judgment of
                    beauty.</p>
                <p>But the whole of this is very limited ; and the Greeks, after making the roof a
                    chief feature of a houſe, went no farther, and contented themſelves with giving
                    it a ſlope ſuited to their climate. This we have followed, becauſe in the milder
                    parts of Europe we have no cogent reaſon for deviating from it ; and if any
                    architect ſhould deviate greatly in a building where the outline is exhibited as
                    beautiful, we ſhould be diſguſted ; but the diſguſt, though felt by almoſt every
                    ſpectator, has its origin in nothing but habit.. In the profeiſed architect or
                    man of education, the diſguſt ariſes from pedantry: for there is not ſuch a
                    cloſe connection between the form and uſes of a roof as ſhall give precife
                    determinations ; and the mere form is a matter of indifference.</p>
                <p>We ſhould not therefore reprobate the high-pitched roofs of our anceſtors,
                    particularly on the continent. It is there where we ſee them in all the
                    extremity of the faſhion, and the taſte is by no means exploded as it is with
                    us. A baronial caſtle in Germany and France is ſeldom rebuilt in the pure Greek
                    ſtyle, or even like the modern houſes in Britain ; the high-pitched roofs are
                    retained. We ſhould not call them Gothic, and ugly becauſe Gothic, till we ſhow
                    their principle to be falſe or taſteleſs. Now we apprehend that it will be found
                    quite the reverſe ; and that though we cannot bring ourſelves to think them
                    beautiful, we ought to think them ſo. The conſtruction of the Greek architecture
                    is a transference of the practices that are neceſſary in a wooden building to a
                    building of ſtone. To this the Greeks have adhered, in ſpite of innumerable
                    difficulties. Their marble quarries, however, put it in their power to retain
                    the proportions which habit had rendered agreeable. But it is next to impoſſible
                    to adhere to theſe proportions with freeſtone or brick, when the order is of
                    magnificent dimenſions. Sir Chriſtopher Wren ſaw this; for his mechanical
                    knowledge was equal to his taſte. He compoſed the front of St Paul’s church in
                    London of two orders, and he coupled his columns ; and ſtill the lintels which
                    form the architrave are of ſuch length that they could carry no additional
                    weight, and he was obliged to truſs them behind. Had he made but one order, the
                    architrave could not have carried its own weight. It is impoſſible to execute a
                    Doric entablature of this ſize in brick. It is attempted in a very noble front,
                    the Academy of Arts in St Peterſhurgh. But the architect was obliged to make the
                    mutules and other projecting members of the corniche of granite, and many of
                    them broke down by their own weight.</p>
                <p>Here is ſurely an error in principle. Since ſtone is the chief material of our
                    buildings, ought not the members Qf ornamented architecture to be refinements on
                    the eſſential and unaffected parts of a ſimple ſtone-.building. There is almoſt
                    as much propriety in the architecture of India, where a dome is made in
                    imita-tation of a lilly or other flower inverted, as in the Greek imitation of a
                    wooden building. The principles of maſonry, and not of carpentry, ſhould be ſeen
                    in our architecture, if we would have it according to the rules of juſt taſte.
                    Now we affirm that this is the characteriſtic feature of what is called the
                    Gothic architecture. In this no dependence is had on the tranſverſe ſtrength of
                    ſtone·. No lintels are to be ſeen ; no extravagant projections. Every ſtone is
                    preſſed to its neighbours, and none is expoſed to a tranſverſe ſtrain. The
                    Greeks were enabled to execute their coloſſal buildings only by uſing immenſe
                    blocks of the hardeſt materials. The Norman maſon could raiſe a building to the
                    ikies without uſing a ſtone which a labourer could not carry to the top on his
                    back. Their architects ſtudied the principles of equilibrium j <hi rend="sub">x</hi> and having attained a wonderful knowledge of it, they indulged themſelves
                    in exhibiting remarkable inſtances. We call this falſe taſte, and ſay that the
                    appearance of inſecurity is the greateſt fault. But this is owing to our habits
                    : our thoughts may be ſaid to run in a∙ wooden train, and certain ſimple maxims
                    of carpentry are familiar to our imagination ; and in the careful adherence to
                    theſe conſiſts the beauty and ſymmetry of the Greek architecture. Had we been as
                    much habituated to the equilibrium of preſſure, this apparent inſecurity would
                    not have met our eye : we would have perceived the ſtrength, and we ſhould have
                    reliſhed the ingenuity.</p>
                <p>The Gothic architecture is perhaps intitled to the name of rational
                    architecture, and its beauty is founded on the characteriſtic diſtinction of our
                    ſpecies. It deſerves cultivation : not the pitiful, ſervile, and un-ſkilled
                    copying of the monuments ; this will produce incongruities and abſurdities equal
                    to any that have crept into the Greek architecture : but let us examine with
                    attention the nice diſpoſition of the groins and ſpaundrels ; let us ſtudy the
                    tracery and knots, not as ornaments, but as uſeful members ; let us obſerve how
                    they have made their walls like honey-combs, and admire their ingenuity as we
                    pretend to admire the inſtinct infuſed by the great architect into the bee. All
                    this cannot be underſtood without mechanical knowledge ; a thing which few of
                    our profeſſional architects have any ſhare of. Thus would architectonic taſte be
                    a mark of ſkill ; and the perſon who preſents the deſign of a building would
                    know how to excite it, without committing it entirely to the maſon and
                    carpenter.</p>
                <p>Theſe obſervations are not a digreſſion from our ſub-</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r02-0464" facs="gri_33125011196389_0470.tif"/>
                <p>ject. The fame principles of mutual preſſure and equilibrium have a place in
                    roofs and many wooden edifices; and if they had been as much ſtudied as the
                    Normans and Saracens ſeem to have ſtudied ſuch of them as were applicable to
                    their purpoſes, we might have produced wooden buildings as ſar ſuperior to what
                    we are familiarly acquainted with, as the bold and wonderful churches ſtill
                    remaining in Europe are ſuperior to the timid productions of our ſtone
                    architecture. The cein-tres uſed in building the bridge of Orleans and the
                    corn-market ⅜f Paris, are late inſtances of what may be done in this way. The
                    laſt mentioned is a dome of 200 feet diameter, built of fir planks ; and there
                    is not a piece of timber in it more than nine feet long, a foot broad, and three
                    inches thick.</p>
                <p>The Norman architects frequently roofed with ſtone. Their wooden roofs were in
                    general very fimple, and their profeſſed aim was to diſpenſe with them
                    altogether. Fond of their own ſcience, they copied nothing from a wooden
                    building, and ran into a ſimilar fault with the ancient Greeks. The parts of
                    their buildings which were neceſſarily of timber were made to imitate
                    ſtone-buildings; and Gothic ornament conſiſts in cramming every thing full of
                    arches and ſpaundrels. Nothing elſe is to be ſeen in their timber works, nay
                    even in their ſculpture. Took at any of the maces or ſceptres ſtill to be found
                    about the old cathedrals; they are ſilver ſteeples.</p>
                <p>But there appears to have been a rivalſhip in old times between the maſons and
                    the carpenters. Many of the baronial halls are of prodigious width, and are
                    roofed with timber : and the carpenters appeared to have borrowed much knowledge
                    from the maſons of thoſe times, and their wide roofs are frequently conſtructed
                    with great ingenuity. Their aim, like the maſons, was to throw a roof over a
                    very wide building without employing great logs of timber. We have ſeen roofs 6o
                    ſeet wide, without having a piece of timber in it above io ſeet long and 4
                    inches ſquare. The Parliament Houſe and Tron-Church of Edinburgh, the great hall
                    of Tarnaway caſtle near Elgin, are ſpecimens of thoſe roofs. They are very
                    numerous on the continent. Indeed Britain retains few monuments of private
                    magnificence. Ariſtocratic ſtate never was ſo great with us ; and the rancour of
                    our civil wars gave moſt of the performances of the carpenter to the flames.
                    Weſtminſter-hall exhibits a ſpecimen of the falſe taſte of the Norman roofs. It
                    contains the eſſential parts indeed, very properly diſpoſed ; but they are
                    hidden, or intentionally covered, with what is conceived to be ornamental ; and
                    this is an imitation of ſtone arches, crammed in between ſlender pillars which
                    hang down from the principal frames, truſſes, or rafters. In a pure Norman roof,
                    ſuch as Tarnaway hall, the eſſential parts are exhibited as things underſtood,
                    and therefore reliſhed. They are refined and ornamented ; and it is here that
                    the inferior kind of taſte or the want of it may appear. And here we do not mean
                    to defend all the whims of our anceſtors ; but we aſſert that it is no more
                    neceſſary to conſider the members of a roof as things to be concealed like a
                    ganet or privy, than the members of a ceiling, which form the moſt beautiſul
                    part of the Greek architecture. Should it be ſaid that a roof is only a thing to
                    keep off the rain, it may be anſwered,</p>
                <p>that a ceiling is only to keep off the duſt, or the floor to be trodden
                    underfoot, and that we ſhould have neither copartments in the one nor inlaid
                    work or carpets on the other. The ſtructure of a roof may therefore be exhibited
                    with propriety, and made an ornamental feature. This has been done even in
                    Italy. The church of St Maria Maggiore in Rome and ſeveral others are ſpecimens:
                    but it muſt be acknowledged, that the forms of the principal ſrames of theſe
                    roofs, which reſemble thoſe of our modern buildings, are very unfit for
                    agreeable ornament. As we have already obſerved, our imaginations have not been
                    made ſufficiently familiar with the principles, and we are rather alarmed than
                    pleaſed with the appearance of the immenſe logs of timber which form the couples
                    of theſe roofs, and hang over our heads with every appearance of weight and
                    danger. It is quite otherwiſe with the ingenious roofs of the German and Norman
                    architects. Slender timbers, interlaced with great ſymmetry, and thrown by
                    neceſſity into figures which are naturally pretty, form altogether an object
                    which no carpenter can view without pleaſure. And why ſhould the gentleman
                    refuſe himſelf the ſame pleaſure of beholding ſcientific ingenuity ?</p>
                <p>The roof is in fact the part of the building which requires the greateſt degree
                    of fl∙cill, and where ſcience will be of more ſervice than in any other part.
                    The architect ſeldom knows much of the matter, and leaves the taſlc to the
                    carpenter. The carpenter conſiders the framing of a great roof as the touchſtone
                    of his art; and nothing indeed tends ſo much to ſhow his judgment and his
                    fertility of reſource.</p>
                <p>It muſt therefore be very acceptable to the artiſt to have a clear view of the
                    principles by which this difficult problem may be folved in the beſt manner, ſo
                    that the roof may have all the ſtrength and ſecurity that can be wiſhed for,
                    without an extravagant expence of timber and iron. We have ſaid that mechanical
                    ſcience can give great aſſiſtance in this matter. We may add that the framing of
                    carpentry, whether for roofs, floors, or any other purpoſe, affords one of the
                    moſt elegant and moſt ſatisfactory applications which can be made of mechanical
                    ſcience to the arts&gt;of common liſe. Unfortunately the practical artiſt is
                    ſeldom poſſefl'ed even of the ſmall portion of ſcience which would almoſt inſure
                    his practice from all riſh of failure ; and even our moſt experienced carpenters
                    have ſeldom any more knowledge than what ariſes from their experience and
                    natural ſagacity. The moſt approved author in our language is Price in his
                    Britiſh Carpenter. Mathurin Jouſſe is in like manner the author moſt in repute
                    in France ; and the publications of both theſe authors are void of every
                    appearance of principle. It is not uncommon to ſee the works of carpenters of
                    the greateſt reputation tumble down., in conſequence of miſtakes from which the
                    moſt elementary knowledge would have ſaved them.</p>
                <p>We ſhall attempt, in this artide, to give an account of the leading principles
                    of this art in a manner ſo familiar and palpâble, that any perſon who know <hi
                        rend="sup"> ,</hi> sthecommon properties of the lever, and <hi rend="sup">x</hi> the Oompoſition of motion, ſhall ſo far underſtand them as to be
                    able, on every occaſion, ſo to diſpoſe his materials, with reſpect to the
                    ſtrains to which they are to be expoſed, that he ſhall always know the effective
                    ſtrain on every piece, and</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r02-0465" facs="gri_33125011196389_0471.tif"/>
                <p>ſhall, in moſt caſes, be able to make the diſpoſition ſuch as to derive the
                    greateſt poſſible advantage from the materials which he employs.</p>
                <p>It is evident that the whole muſt depend on the principles which regulate the
                    ſtrength of the materials, relative to the manner in which this ſtrength is
                    exerted, and the manner in which the ſtrain is laid on the piece of matter. With
                    reſpect to the firſt, this is not the proper place ſor conſidering it, and we
                    muſt refer the reader to the article <hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps"> Strength of Materials in Mechanics.</hi></hi> We (hall juſt borrow from that article two or three propoſitions ſuited to
                    our purpoſe.</p>
                <p>The force with which the materials of our edifices, roofs, floors, machines, and
                    framings of every kind, reſiſt being broken or cruſhed, or pulled aſunder, is,
                    immediately or ultimately, the coheſion of their particles. When a weight hangs
                    by a rope, it tends either immediately to break all the fibres, overcoming the
                    coheſion among the particles of each, or it tends to pull one parcel of them
                    from among the reſt, with which they are joined. This union of the fibres is
                    brought about by ſome kind of gluten, or by twiſting, which cauſes them to bind
                    each other ſo hard that any one will break rather than come out, ſo much is it
                    withheld by friction. The ultimate reſiſtance is therefore the coheſion of the
                    fibre ; the force or ſtrength of all fibrous materials, ſuch as timber, is
                    exerted in much the fame manner. The fibres are either broken or pulled out from
                    among the reſt. Metals, ſtone, glaſs, and the like, reſiſt being pulled aſunder
                    by the ſimple coheſion of their parts.</p>
                <p>The force which is neceſſary for breaking a rope or wire is a proper meaſure of
                    its ſtrength. In like manner, the force neceſſary for tearing directly aſunder
                    any rod of wood or metal, breaking all its fibres, or tearing them from among
                    each other, is a proper meaſure of the united ſtrength of all theſe fibres. And
                    it is the limpleſt ſtrain to which they can be expoſed, being juſt equal to the
                    ſum of the forces neceſſary for breaking or diſengagſhg each fibre. And, if the
                    body is not of a fibrous ſtructure, which is the caſe with metals, ſtones,
                    glaſs, and many other ſub-ſtances, this force is ſtill equal to the ſimple ſum
                    of the coheſive forces of each particle which is ſeparated by the fracture. Let
                    us diſtinguiſh this mode of exertion of the coheſion of the body by the name of
                    its Ab* solute Strength.</p>
                <p>When ſolid bodies are, on the contrary, expoſed to great compreſſion, they can
                    reſiſt only to a certain degree. A piece of clay or lead will be ſqueezed out ;
                    a piece of freeſtone will be cruſhed to powder ; a beam of wood will be
                    crippled, ſwelling out in the middle, and its fibres loſe their mutual coheſion,
                    after which it is eaſily cruſhed by the load. A notion may be formed of the
                    manner in which theſe ſtrains are reſiſted by conceiving a cylindrical pipe
                    filled with ſmall ſhot, well ſhaken together, ſo that each ſphericle is lying in
                    the cloſeſt manner poſſible, that is, in contact with ſix others in the ſame
                    vertical plane (this being the poſition in which the ſhot will take the leaſt
                    room). Thus each touches the reſt in fix points : Now ſuppoſe them all united,
                    in theſe ſix points only, by ſome cement. This aſſemblage will flick together
                    and form a cylindrical pillar, which may be taken out of its mould. Sup</p>
                <p>poſe this pillar ſtanding upright, and loaded above. The ſupports ariſing ſrom
                    the cement act obliquely, and the load tends either to force them aſunder
                    laterally, or to make Jſhem Aide on each other : either of theſe things
                    happening, the whole is cruſhed to pieces. The reſiſtance of fibrous materials
                    to ſuch a ſtrain is a little more intricate, but may be explained in a way very
                    ſimilar.</p>
                <p>A piece of matter of any kind may alſo be deſtroyed by wrenching or twiſting it.
                    We can eaſily form a notion of its reſiſtance to this kind of ſtrain by
                    confi-dering what would happen to the cylinder of ſmall ſhot if treated in this
                    way.</p>
                <p>And laſtly, a beam, or a bar of metal, or a piece of ſtone or other matter, may
                    be broken tranſverſely. This will happen to a rafter or joiſt ſupported at the,
                    ends when overloaded, or to a beam having one end ſtuck faſt in a wall and a
                    load laid on its projecting part. This is the ſtrain to which materials are moſt
                    commonly expoſed in roofs; and, unfortunately, it is . the ſtrain which they are
                    the leaſt able to bear ; or rather it is the manner of application which cauſes
                    an ex-ternal force to excite the greateſt poſſible immediate ſtrain on the
                    particles. It is againſt this that the carpenter muſt chiefly guard, avoiding it
                    when i∣ι his power, and, in every caſe, diminiſhing it as much as poſſible. It
                    is neceſſary to give the reader a clear notion of the great weakneſs of
                    materials in relation to this tranſverſe ſtrain. But we ſhall do nothing more,
                    referring him to the articles Strain, Stress, Strength.</p>
                <p>Let ACBD (fig. i.) repreſent the ſide of a beam projecting horizontally from a
                    wall in which it is firmly fixed, and let it be loaded with a weight W appended
                    to its extremity. This tends to break it;· and the leaſt reflection will
                    convince any perſon that if the beam is equally ſtrong throughout, it will break
                    in the line CD, even with the ſurface of the wall. It will open at D, while C
                    will ſerve as a ſort of joint, round which it will turn. The croſs ſection
                    through the line CD is, for this reaſon, called the <hi rend="italic">ſeaion of
                        frαcture,</hi> and the horizontal line, drawn through C on its under
                    ſurſace, is called the <hi rend="italic">axis offrα8ure.</hi> The fracture is
                    made by tearing aſunder the fibres, ſuch as DE or FG. Let us ſuppoſe a real
                    joint at C, and that the beam is really ſawed through along CD, and that in
                    place of its natural fibres threads are ſubſtituted all over the ſection of
                    fracture. The weight now tends to break theſe threads ; and it is our buſineſs
                    to find the force neceſſary for this purpoſe.</p>
                <p>It is evident that DCA may be conſidered as a bended lever, of which C is the
                    fulcrum. If /be the force which will juſt balance the coheſion of a thread when
                    hung on it ſo that the ſmalleſt addition will break it, we may find the weight
                    which will be ſufficient for this purpoſe when hung on at A, by ſaying, AC : CD <hi rend="italic">—j</hi> : ?, and <hi rend="italic">φ</hi> will be the
                    weight which will juſt break the thread, by hanging <hi rend="italic">φ</hi> by the point A. This gives</p>
                <p>CD</p>
                <p>us pZ× <hi rend="sup">-</hi> ζjyγ∙ U the weight be hung on at <hi
                        rend="italic"> a,</hi> the force</p>
                <p>juſt ſufficient for breaking the ſame thread will be CD.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">— ffff</hi> lik <hi rend="sup">,e</hi> manner the force
                    $&gt;, w <hi rend="sup">,</hi> hich muſt be hung on at A in order to break
                    an equally ſtrong or as</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r02-0466" facs="gri_33125011196389_0472.tif"/>
                <p>CF</p>
                <p>equally reſiſting fibre at F, muſt be ≈=∕× ς∙^r. And ſo on of all the reſt.</p>
                <p>If we ſuppoſe all the fibres to exert equal reſiſtances at the inſtant of
                    fracture, we know, from the ſimpleſt elements of mechanics, that the reſiſtance
                    of all the particles in the line CD, each acting equally in its own place, is
                    the ſame as if all the individual reſiſtances were united in the middle point <hi rend="italic">g.</hi> Now this total reſiſtance is the reſiſtance or
                    ſtrength <hi rend="italic">ſ</hi> of each particle, multiplied by the number
                    of particles. This number may be expreſſed by the line CD, becauſe we have no
                    reaſon to ſuppoſe that they are at unequal diſtances. Therefore, in comparing
                    different ſections together, the number of particles in each are as the ſections
                    themſelves. Therefore DC may repreſent the number of particles in the line DC'.
                    Let us call this line the depth of the beam, and expreſs it by the ſymbol <hi
                        rend="italic"> ci.</hi> And ſince we are at preſent treating of roofs whole
                    rafters and other parts are commonly of uniform breadth, let us call AH or BI
                    the breadth of the beam, and expreſs it by <hi rend="italic">b,</hi> and let
                    CA be called its length, <hi rend="italic">l.</hi> We may now expreſs the
                    ſtrength of the whole line CD by <hi rend="italic">f~&gt;id,</hi> and we
                    may ſuppoſe it all concentrated in the middle point <hi rend="italic">g.</hi> Its mechanical energy, therefore, by which it reſiſts the energy of the weight <hi rend="italic">vυ,</hi> applied at the diſtance ∕, is <hi rend="italic"
                        > ſ.</hi> CD. Cy, while the momentum of <hi rend="italic">w</hi> is <hi
                        rend="italic"> w.</hi> CA. We muſt therefore have <hi rend="italic">ſ.</hi> CD. Cy=∞. CA, or <hi rend="italic">fd.fd z= nv.</hi> ∕, and <hi
                        rend="italic"> fd : <hi rend="sup">r</hi> w~ I</hi> or <hi rend="italic">ſd '. <hi rend="sup">r</hi> w~ 2l : &lt;l.</hi> That is, twice the
                    length of the beam is to its depth as the abſolute ſtrength of one of its
                    vertical planes to its relative ſtrength, or its pow <hi rend="sup">,</hi> er
                    of reſiſting this tranſverſe fracture.</p>
                <p>It is evident, that what has been now demonſtrated of the reſiſtance exerted in
                    the line CD, is equally true of every line parallel to CD in the thickneſs or
                    breadth of the beam. The abſolute ſtrength of the whole ſection of fracture is
                    properly repreſented by <hi rend="italic">f. d. b <hi rend="sub">i</hi></hi> and we ſtill have 2/ : <hi rend="italic">d—ſdb</hi> : ⅛&gt;.,∙ or
                    twice the length of the beam is to its depth as the abſolute ſtrength to the
                    relative ſtrength. Suppoſe the beam 12 feet long and one foot deep ; then
                    whatever is its abſolute ſtrength, the 24th part of this will break it if hung
                    at its extremity.</p>
                <p>But even this is too favourable a ſtatement ; all the fibres are ſuppoſed to
                    meet alike in the inſtant of fracture. But this is not true. At the inſtant that
                    the fibre at D breaks, it is ſtretched to the utmoſt, and is exerting its whole
                    force. But at this inſtant the fibre at <hi rend="italic">g</hi> is not ſo
                    much ſtretched, and it is not then exerting its utmoſt force. If we ſuppoſe the
                    extenſion of the fibres to be as their diſtance from C, and the actual exertion,
                    of each to be as their extenſions, it may eaſily be ſhown (ſee Strength and
                    Strain), that the whole reſiſtance is the ſame as if the full force of all the
                    fibres were united at a point <hi rend="italic">r</hi> diſtant from C by one
                    third of CD. In this caſe we muſt ſay, that the abſolute ſtrength is to the
                    relative ſtrength as three times the length to the depth ; ſo that the beam is
                    wêaker than by the former ſtatement in the proportion of two to three.</p>
                <p>Even this is more ſtrength than experiment juſtiſies ; and we can ſee an evident
                    reaſon for it. When the beam is ſtrained, not only are the upper fibres
                    ſtretched, but the lower fibres are compreſſed. This is</p>
                <p>very diſtinctly ſeen, if we attempt to break a piece oſ cork cut into the ſhape
                    of a beam : this being the caſe,</p>
                <p>C is not the centre of fracture. There is ſome point <hi rend="italic">c</hi> which lies between the fibres which are ſtretched and thoſe that are compreſſed.
                    This fibre is neither ſtretched nor ſqueezed ; and this point is the real centre
                    of fracture : and the lever by which a fibre D reſiſts, is not DC, but a ſhorter
                    one Dr; and the energy of the whole reſiſtances muſt be leſs than by the ſecond
                    ſtatement. Till we know the proportion between the dilatability and
                    compreſſibility of the parts, apd the relation between the dilatations of the
                    fibres and the reſiſtances which they exert in this ſtate of dilatation, we
                    cannot poſitively ſay where the point <hi rend="italic">c</hi> is ſituated,
                    nor what is the ſum of the actual reſiſtances, or the point where their action
                    may be ſuppoſed concentrated. The firmer w <hi rend="sup">,</hi> oods, ſuch as
                    oak and cheſnut, may be ſuppoſed to be but ffightly compreſſible ; we know that
                    willow and other ſoft woods are very comprejſible. Theſe laſt muſt therefore be
                    weaker : for it is evident, that the fibres which are in a ſtate of compreſſion
                    do nqt reſiſt the fracture. It is well known, that a beam of willow may be cut
                    through from C to <hi rend="italic">g</hi> without weakening it in the leaſt,
                    if the cut be filled up by a wedge of hard wood ſtuck in</p>
                <p>We can only ſay, that very ſound oak and red fir have the centre of effort ſo
                    ſituated, that the abſolute ſtrength is to the relative ſtrength in a proportion
                    not leſs than that of three and a half times the length of the beam to its
                    depth. .-∖ ſquare inch of found oak will carry about 8000 pounds. If this bar be
                    firmly fixed in a wall, and project 12 inches, and be loaded at the extremity
                    with 200 pounds, it will be broken. It will juſt bear 190, its relative ſtrength
                    being - <hi rend="sub">3</hi> ∙ <hi rend="sup">,</hi> - <hi rend="sub">r</hi> of its abſolute ſtrength ; and this is the caſe only with the ſineſt
                    pieces, ſo placed that their annual plates or layers are in a vertical poſition.
                    A larger log is not fo ſtrong tranſverſely, becauſe its plates lie in various
                    directions round the heart.</p>
                <p>Theſe obſervations are enough to give us a diſtinct notion of the vaſt
                    diminution of the ſtrength of timber when the ſtrain is acroſs it ; and w <hi
                        rend="sup"> ,</hi> e ſee the juſtice of the maxim which we inculcated, that
                    the carpenter, in framing roofs, ſhould avoid as much as poſſible the ex-poſing
                    his timbers to tranſverſe ſtrains. But this cannot be avoided in all caſes. Nay,
                    the ultimate ſtrain, ariſing ſrom the very nature of a roof, is tranſverſe. The
                    rafters muſt carry their own weight, and this tends to break them acroſs : an
                    oak beam a foot deep will not carry its own weight if it project more than 60
                    ſeet. Beſides this, the rafters muſt carry the lead, tyling, or fiâtes. We muſt
                    therefore conſider this tranſverſe ſtrain a little more particularly, ſo as to
                    know what ſtrain will be laid on any part by an unavoidable load, laid on either
                    at that part or at any other.</p>
                <p>We have hitherto ſuppoſed, that the beam had one of its ends fixed in a wall,
                    and that it was loaded at the other end. This is not an uſual arrangement, and
                    was taken merely as affording a ſimple application of the mechanical principles.
                    It is much more uſual to have the beam ſupported at the ends, and loaded in the
                    middle. Let the beam FEGH (ſig. 2.) reſt on the props E and G, and be loaded at
                    its middle point C with a weight W. It is required to determine t he ſtrain at
                    the ſection CD ? It is plain that the beam will</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r02-0467" facs="gri_33125011196389_0473.tif"/>
                <p>receive the ſame ſupport, and ſuffer the fame ſtrain, if, inſtead of the blocks
                    E and G, we ſubſtſtute the ropes E <hi rend="italic">f e,</hi> G <hi
                        rend="italic"> hg,</hi> going over the pulleys <hi rend="italic">f</hi> andy, and loaded with proper weights <hi rend="italic">e</hi> and <hi
                        rend="italic"> g.</hi> The weight <hi rend="italic">e</hi> is equal to
                    the ſupport given by the block E ; and <hi rend="italic">g</hi> is equal to
                    the ſupport given by G. The ſum of <hi rend="italic">e</hi> and y is equal to
                    W ; and, on whatever point W is hung, the weights <hi rend="italic">e</hi> and
                    y are to W in the proportion of Γ)G and DE to GE. Now, in this ſtate of things,
                    it appears that the ſtrain on the ſection CD ariſes immediately from the upward
                    action of the ropes F <hi rend="italic">f</hi> and H <hi rend="italic">h,</hi> or the upward preſſions of the blocks E and G ; and that the office of the
                    weight W is to oblige the beam to oppoſe this ſtrain. Things are in the ſame
                    ſtate in reſpect of ſtrain as if a block were ſubſtituted at D for the weight W,
                    and the weights <hi rend="italic">e</hi> and <hi rend="italic">g</hi> were
                    hung on at E and G ; only the directions will be oppoſite. The beam tends to
                    break in the ſection CD, becauſe the ropes pull it upwards at E and G, while a
                    weight W holds it down at C. It tends to open at D, and C becomes the centre of
                    fracture. The ſtrain therefore is the ſame as if the half ED were fixed in the
                    wall, and a weight equal to <hi rend="italic">g,</hi> that is, to the half of
                    W, were hung on at G.</p>
                <p>Hence we conclude, that a beam ſupported at both ends, but not fixed there, and
                    loaded in the middle, will carry twice as much weight as it can carry at its
                    extremity, when the other extremity is faſt in a wall.</p>
                <p>The ſtrain occaſioned at any point L by a weight W, hung on at any other point
                    D, is — W ×</p>
                <p>DE _ <hi rend="sub">τ</hi> , <hi rend="sub">τ</hi> , <hi rend="sub">z</hi> , . <hi rend="sub">τττ</hi> ,</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">j7q × LG. For EG is to ED as W to the preſſure</hi></p>
                <p>occaſioned at G. This would be balanced by ſome weight ç acting over the pulley <hi rend="italic">h ;</hi> and this tends to break the beam at L, by
                    acting on the lever GL. The</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">BE</hi></p>
                <p>preſſure at G is and therefore the ſtrain at L</p>
                <p>is W. jF~√∙ LG.</p>
                <p>In like manner, the ſtrain occaſioned at the point DE</p>
                <p>D by the weight W hung on there, is W X DG ;</p>
                <p>which is therefore equal to ⅜ W, when D is the middle point.</p>
                <p>Hence we ſee, that the general ſtrain on the beam ariſing from one weight, is
                    proportionable to the rec-</p>
                <p>, <hi rend="sub">r</hi> , <hi rend="sub">r</hi> , „ W.DE.DG .</p>
                <p>tangle of the parts of the beam, (for---is as</p>
                <p>DE.DG,, and is greateſt when the load is laid on the middle of the beam.</p>
                <p>We alſo ſee, that the ſti ain at L, by a load at D, is equal to the ſtrain at D
                    by the ſame load at L. And the ſtrain at L, from a load at D, is to the ſtrain
                    by the ſame load at L as DE to LE. Theſe are all very obvious corollaries ; and
                    they ſufficiently inform us concerning the ſtrains which are produced on any
                    part of the timber by a load laid on any other part.</p>
                <p>If we now ſuppoſe the beam to be ſixed at the two ends, that is, firmly framed,
                    or held down by blocks at I and K, placed beyond E and G, or framed into poſts,
                    it will cany twice as much as when its ends were free. For ſuppoſe it ſawn
                    through at CD ; the weight λ⅞ hung on there will be juſt ſufficient to break it
                    at E and G. Now reſtore the connection of the ſec</p>
                <p>tion CD, it will require another weight W to break it there at the ſame time.</p>
                <p>Therefore, when a rafter, or any piece of timber, ia firmly connected with three
                    fixed points G, E, I, it will bear a greater load between any two of them than
                    if its connection with the remote point were removed ; and if it be faſtened in
                    four points, G, E, I, K, it will be twice as ſtrong in the middle part as
                    without the two remote connections.</p>
                <p>One is apt to expect from this that the joiſt of a floor will be nauch
                    ſtrengthened by being firmly built in the wall. It is a little ſtrengthened ;
                    but the hold which can thus be given it is much too ſhort to be of any ſenſible
                    ſervice ; and it tends greatly to ſhatter the wall, becauſe, when it is bent
                    down by a load, it forces up the wail with the momentum of a long lever.
                    Judicious buildeιs therefore take care not to bind the joiſts tight in the wall.
                    But when the joiſt3 of adjoining rooms lie in the ſame direction, it is a great
                    advantage to make them of one piece. They are then twice as ſtrong as when made
                    in two lengths.</p>
                <p>It is eaſy to deduce from theſe premiſſes the ſtrain on any point which ariſes
                    from the weight of the beam it-felt; or from any load which is uniformly
                    diſſuſed over the whole or any part. We may always conſider thé whole of the
                    weight which is thus uniformly diſſuſed over any part as united in the middle
                    point of that part ; and if the load is not uniformly diſſuſed, we may ſtill
                    ſuppoſe it united at its centre of gravity. Thus, to know the ſtrain at L
                    ariſing from the weight of the whole beam, we may ſuppoſe the whole weight accu-
                    . mulated in its middle point D. Alſo the ſtrain at L <hi rend="sub">t</hi> ariſing from the weight of the part ED, is the ſame as if this weight were
                    accumulated in the middle point <hi rend="italic">ci</hi> of ED ; and it is
                    the ſame as if half the weight of ED were hung on at D. For the real ſtrain at L
                    is the upward preſſure at G, acting by the lever GL. Now call the weight of the
                    part DE <hi rend="italic">e</hi> ; this upward preſſure</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="sub"> ι</hi> e×</hi> √ E ί ſ × DE will be J£G ’ ° <hi rend="sup"
                        > r</hi> EG .</p>
                <p>Therefore the ſtrain on the middle of a beam, ari≈ fing from its own weight, or
                    from any uniform load, it</p>
                <p>• , ED</p>
                <p>the weight of the beam or its load × ∣τθ × DG; that</p>
                <p><hi rend="sup">1</hi> s, half the weight of the ſheam or load multiplied or
                    acting by the lever DG ; for ED . <hi rend="sub">ι</hi></p>
                <p>E G <hi rend="sup">1S</hi></p>
                <p>Alſo the ſtrain at L, ariſing from the weight of the beam, or the unifoim load,
                    is { the weight of the beam or load acting by the lever LG. It is therefore
                    proportional to LG, and is greateſt of all at D. Therefore a beam of uniform
                    ſtrength throughout, uniformly loaded, will bιeak in the middle.</p>
                <p>It is of importance to know the relation between the ſtrains ariſing from the
                    weights of the beams, or from any uniformly diſſuſed load, and the relative
                    ſtrength. We have already ſeen, that the relative</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">. rdb.d</hi></p>
                <p>ſtrength is y^ <hi rend="italic">fiſſt</hi> where <hi rend="italic">m</hi> is a number to be diſcovered by experiment for every different ſpecies of
                    materials. Leaving out every circumſtance but what depends on the dimenſions of
                    tlie beam, viz. <hi rend="italic">d, b,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">l,</hi> we</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">. . ‘ d'b</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">ſee</hi> that the relative ſtrength is in the proportion of</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r02-0468" facs="gri_33125011196389_0474.tif"/>
                <p>that is, as the breadth and the ſquare of the depth directly and the length
                    inverſely.</p>
                <p>Now, to conſider firſt the ſtrain ariſing from the weight of the beam itſelf, it
                    is evident that this weight increaſes in the ſame proportion with the depth, the
                    breadth, and the length of the beam. Therefore its power of reſiſting this
                    ſtrain muſt be as its depth directly, and the ſquare of its length inverſely. To
                    conſider this in a more popular manner, it is plain that the increaſe of breadth
                    makes no change in the power of reſiſting the actual ſtrain, becauſe the load
                    and the abſolute ſtrength increaſe in the ſame proportion with the breadth. But
                    by increaſing the depth, we increaſe the reſiſting ſection in the ſame
                    proportion, and therefore the number of reſiſting fibres and the abfolute
                    ſtrength: but we alſo increaſe the weight in the ſame proportion. This makes a
                    compenſation, and the relative ſtrength is yet the ſame. But by increaſing the
                    depth, we have not only increaſed the abſolute ſtrength, but alſo its mechanical
                    energy : For the reſiſtance to fracture is the ſame as if the full ſtrength of
                    each fibre was exerted at the point which we called the centre of effort ; and
                    we ſhowed, that the diſtance of this from the underſide of the beam was a
                    certain portion (a half, a third, a fourth, &amp;c.) of the whole depth of
                    the beam. This diſtance is the arm of the lever by which the coheſion of the
                    wood may be ſuppoſed to act. Therefore this arm of the lever, and conſequently
                    the energy of the reſiſtance, increaſes in the proportion of the depth of the
                    beam, and this remains uncompenſated by any increaſe of the ſtrain. On the
                    whole, therefore, the power of the beam to ſuſtain its own weight increaſes in
                    the proportion of its depth. But, on the other hand, the power of withſtanding a
                    given ſtrain applied at its extremity, or to any aliquot part of its length, is
                    diminiſhed as the length increaſes, or is inverſely as the length ; and the
                    ſtrain ariſing from the weight of the beam alſo increaſes as the length.
                    Therefore the power of reſiſting the ſtrain actually exerted on it by the weight
                    of the beam is inverſely as the ſquare of the length. On the whole,'therefore,
                    the power of a beam to carry its own weight, varies in the proportion of its
                    depth directly and the ſquare of its length inverſely.</p>
                <p>As this ſtrain is frequently a conſiderable part of the whole, it is proper to
                    conſider it apart, and then to reckon only on what remains for the ſupport of
                    any extraneous load.</p>
                <p>In the next place, the power of a beam to carry any load which is uniformly
                    diſſuſed over its length, muſt be inverſely as the ſquare of the length : for
                    the power of withſtanding <hi rend="italic">any</hi> ſtrain applied to an
                    aliquot part of the length (which is the caſe here, becauſe the load may be
                    conceived as accumulated at it3 centre of gravity, the middle point of the beam)
                    is inverſely as the length ; and the <hi rend="italic">aitual</hi> ſtrain is
                    as the length, and therefore its momentum is as the ſquare of the length.
                    Therefore the power of a beam to carry a weight uniformly diffuſed over it, is
                    inverſely as the ſquare of the length. <hi rend="italic">N. B.</hi> It is here
                    underſtood, that the uniform load is of ſome determined quantity for every foot
                    of the length, ſo that a beam of double length carries a double load.</p>
                <p>We have hitherto ſuppoſed that the forces which tend to break a beam
                    tranſverſely, are acting in a direction perpendicular to the beam. This is
                    always the caſe in level floors loaded in any manner ; but in roofs, thte action
                    of the load tending to break the rafters is oblique, becauſe gravity always acts
                    in vertical lines. It may alſo frequently happen, that a beam is ſtrained by a
                    force acting obliquely. This modification of the ſtrain is eaſily diſcuſſed.
                    Suppoſe that the external force, which is meaſured by the weight W in fig. ι.
                    acts in the direction A <hi rend="italic">w'</hi> inſtead of AW. Draw C <hi
                        rend="italic"> a</hi> perpendicular to A w. Then the momentum of this
                    external force is not to be meaſured by W × AC, but by W × <hi rend="italic">ά</hi> C. The ſtrain therefore by which the fibres in the ſection of fracture DC
                    are torn aſunder, is diminiſhed hr the proportion of CA to C 0, that is, in the
                    proportion of radius to the fine of the angle CA&lt;i, which the beam makes
                    with the direction of the external force.</p>
                <p>To apply this to our purpoſe in the moſt familiar manner, let AB (fig. 3.) be an
                    oblique rafter of a building, loaded with a weight W ſuſpended to any point C,
                    and thereby occaſioning a ſtrain in ſome part D. We have already ſeen, that the
                    immediate cauſe of the ſtrain on D is the reaction of the ſupport which is given
                    to the point B. The rafter may at preſent be conſidered as a lever, ſupported at <hi rend="italic">A</hi> , and pulled down by the line CW. This occaſions
                    a preſſure on B, and the ſupport acts in the oppoſite direction to the action of
                    the lever, that is, in the direction B <hi rend="italic">b,</hi> perpendicular
                    to BA. This tends to break the beam in every part. The preſſure exerted at B is
                    , AE being a horizontal line. Therefore the ſtrain at D will be W×AE _ <hi
                        rend="sub"> ττ</hi></p>
                <p>AB × BD. Had the beam been lying horizontally, the ſtrain at D, from the weight
                    W ſuſpended at W,</p>
                <p>C, would have been —× BD. It is therefore di miniſhed in the proportion of AC to
                    AE, that is, in the proportion of radius to the coſine of the elevation, or in
                    the proportion of the ſecant of elevation to the radius.</p>
                <p>It is evident, that this law of diminution of the ſtrain is the ſame whether the
                    ſtrain ariſes from a load on any part of the rafter, or from the weight of the
                    rafter itſelf, or from any load uniformly diſſuſed over its length, provided
                    only that theſe loads act in vertical lines.</p>
                <p>We can now compare the ſtrength of roofs which have different elevations.
                    Suppoſing the width of the building to be given, and that the weight of a ſquare
                    yard of covering is alſo given. Then, becauſe the load on the rafter will
                    increaſe in the ſame proportion with its length, the load on the flant∙fide BA
                    of the roof will be to the load of a ſimilar covering on the half AF of the flat
                    roof, of the ſame width, as AB to AF. But the tranſverſe action of any load on
                    AB, by which it tends to break it, is to that of the ſame load on AF as AF to
                    AB. The tranſverſe ſtrain therefore is the ſame on both, the increaſe of real
                    load on AB being compenſated by the obliquity of its action. But the ſtrengths
                    of beams to reſiſt equal ſtrains, applied to ſimilar points, or uniformly
                    diffuſed over them, are inverſely as their lengths, becauſe the momentum or
                    energy of the ſtrain is proportional to the length. There-</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r02-0469" facs="gri_33125011196389_0475.tif"/>
                <p>fore the power of AB to withſtand the ſtrain to which it is really expoſed, is
                    to the power of AF to reſiſt its ſtrain as AF to AB. If, therefore, a rafter AG
                    of a certain ſcantling is juſt able to carry the roofing laid on it, a rafter AB
                    of the ſame ſcantling, but more elevated, will be too weak in the proportion of
                    AG to AB. Therefore ſteeper roofs require ſtouter rafters, in order that they
                    may be equally able to carry a roofing of equal weight per ſquare yard. To be
                    equally ſtrong, they muſt be made broader, or placed nearer to each other, in
                    the proportion of their greater length, or they muſt be made deeper in the
                    fubd&lt; plicate proportion of their length. The following eaſy conſtruction
                    will enable the artiſt not ſamiliar with computation to proportion the depth of
                    the rafter to the ſlope of the roof.</p>
                <p>Let the horizontal line <hi rend="italic">aſ</hi> (fig. 4.) be the proper
                    depth of a beam whoſe length is half the width of the building ; that is, ſuch
                    as would make it fit for carrying the intended tiling laid on a flat roof. Draw
                    the vertical line <hi rend="italic">ſ b,</hi> and the line a <hi rend="italic"
                        > b</hi> having the elevation of the rafter; make <hi rend="italic">a g</hi> equal to <hi rend="italic">aſ,</hi> and deſcribe the ſe-jnicircle <hi
                        rend="italic"> b dg</hi> ; draw <hi rend="italic">a d</hi> perpendicular
                    to <hi rend="italic">a b, a d</hi> is the required depth. The demonſtration is
                    evident.</p>
                <p>We have now treated in ſufficient detail what relates to the chief ſtrain on the
                    component parts of a roof, namely, what' tends to break them tranſverſely ; and
                    we have enlarged more on the ſubject than what the preſent occaſion
                    indiſpenſably required, becauſe the propoſitions which we have demonſtrated are
                    equally applicable, to all framings of carpentry, and are even of greater moment
                    in many caſes, particularly in the conſtruction of machines. Theſe conſiſt of
                    levers in various forms, which are ſtrained tranſverſely ; and ſimilar ſtrains
                    frequently occur in many of the ſupporting and connecting parts. We ſhall give
                    in the article Timber an account of the experiments which have been made by
                    different naturaliſts, in order to aſeertain the abfolute ſtrength of ſome of
                    the materials which are moſt generally framed together in buildings and engines.
                    The houſe-carpenter will draw from them abſolute numbers, which he can apply to
                    his particular purpoſes by means of the propoſitions which we have now
                    eſtabliſhed.</p>
                <p>We proceed, in the next place, to conſider the other ſtrains to which the parts
                    of roofs are expoſed, in conſequence of the ſupport which they mutually give
                    each other, and the preiſures (or <hi rend="italic">thruſts</hi> as they are
                    called in the language of the houſe carpenter) which they exert on each other,
                    and on the walls or piers of the building.</p>
                <p>Let a beam or piece of timber AB (fig. 5.) be ſuſpended by two lines AC, BD ; or
                    let it be ſupported by two props AE, BF, which are perfectly moveable round
                    their remote extremities E,F, or let it reſt on the two poliſhed plains KAH,
                    LBM. Moreover, let G be the centre of gravity of the beam, and let GN be a line
                    through the centre of gravity perpendicular to the horizon. The beam will not be
                    in equilibrio unleſs the vertical line GN either paſſes through P, the point in
                    which the directions of the two lines AC, BD, or the directions of the two props
                    EA, FD, or the perpendiculars to the two planes KAH, LBM interſect each other,
                    or is parallel to theſe directions. For the ſupports given by the lines or props
                    are unqueſtionably exerted in the direction of their lengths ; and it is as well</p>
                <p>known in mechanics that the ſupports given by planes are exerted in a direction
                    perpendicular to thoſe planes in the points of contact ; and we know that the
                    weight of the beam acts in the ſame manner as if it were all accumulated in its
                    centre of gravity G, and that it acts in the direction GN perpendicular to the
                    horizon. Moreover, when a body is in equilibrio between three forces, they are
                    acting in one plane, and their directions are either parallel or they paſs
                    through one point.</p>
                <p>The ſupport given to the beam is therefore the ſame as if it were ſuſpended by
                    two lines which are attached to the ſingle point P. We may alſo infer, that the
                    points of ſuſpenſion C, D, the.points of ſupport E, F, the points of contact A,
                    B, and the centre of gravity G, are all, in one vertical plane.</p>
                <p>When this poſition of the beam is diſturbed by any external force, there muſt
                    either be a motion of the points A and B round the centres of ſuſpenſion C and
                    D, or of the props round theſe points of ſupport E and F, or a Aiding of the
                    ends of the beam along the poliſhed planes GH and IK ; and in conſequence of
                    theſe motions the centre of gravity G will go out of its place* and the vertical
                    line GN will no longer paſs through the point where the directions of the
                    ſupports interſect each other. If the centre of gravity riſes by this motion,
                    the body will have a tendency to recover its former poſition, and it will
                    require force to keep it away from it. In this caſe the equilibrium may be ſaid
                    to be <hi rend="italic">stable,</hi> or the body to have <hi rend="italic">stability.</hi> But if the centre of gravity deſcends when the body is
                    moved ſrom the poſition of equilibrium, it will tend to move ſtill farther;, and
                    lo ſar will it be from recovering its former poſition, that it will now fall.
                    This equilibrium may be called a <hi rend="italic">tottering equilibrium.</hi> Theſe accidents depend on the ſituations of the points A, B, C, D, E, F ; and
                    they may be determined by conſidering the ſubject geometrically. It does not
                    much intereſt us at preſent ; it is. rarely that the equilibrium of ſuſpenſion
                    is tottering, or that of props is ſtable. It is evident, that if the beam were
                    ſuſpended by lines from the point P, it would have ſtability, for it would ſwing
                    like a pendulum round P, and therefore would always tend towards the poſition of
                    equilibrium. The intersection of the lines of ſupport would ſtill be at P, and
                    the vertical line drawn through the centre of gravity, when in any other
                    ſituation, would be on that ſide of P towards which this centre has been moved.
                    Therefore, by the rules of pendulous bodies, it tends to come back. This would
                    be more remarkably the caſe if the points of ſuſpenſion C and D be on the ſame
                    ſide of the point P with the points of attachment A and B ; ſor in this caſe the
                    new point of interſection of the lines of ſupport would ſhift to the oppoſite
                    ſide, and be ſtill farther from the vertical line through the new poſition of
                    the centre of gravity. But if the points of ſuſpenſion and of attachment are on
                    oppoſite ſides of P, the new point of interſection may ſhift to the ſame ſide
                    with the centre of gravity, and lie beyond the vertical line ; in this caſe the
                    equilibrium is tottering. It is eaſy to perceive, too, that if the equilibrium
                    of ſuſpenſion from the points C and D be ſtable, the equilibrium on the props AE
                    and BF muſt be tottering. It is not neceſſary for our preſent purpoſe to engage
                    more particularly in this diſcuſſion.</p>
                <p>It is plain that, with reſpect to the mere momentary equilibrium, there is no
                    difference in the ſupport, by</p>

                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r03-0470" facs="gri_33125011196389_0476.tif"/>
                <p>threads, or props, of planes, and we may ſubſtitute the one for the other. We
                    ſhall find this ſubſtſtution extremely uſeful, becauſe we eaſily conceive
                    diſtinct notions of the ſupport of a body by ſtrings.</p>
                <p>Obſerve farther, that if the whole figure be inverted, and ſtrings be
                    ſubſtituted for props, and props for ſtrings, the equilibrium will ſtill obtain
                    : for by comparing fig. 5. with fig. 6. we ſee that the vertical line through
                    the centre of gravity will paſe through the in-terſection of the two ſtrings or
                    props.; and this is all that is lſeceſſary for the equilibrium : only it muſt be
                    obſerved in the ſubſtſtution of props for threads, and of threads for props,
                    that it it be done without inverting the whole figure, a ſtable equilibrium
                    becomes a tottering one, and <hi rend="italic">vice verſa.</hi></p>
                <p>This is a moſt uſeſul propoſition, eſpecially to the unlettered artiſan, and
                    enables him to make a practical life of problems which the greateſt mechanical
                    geniuſes have found no eaſy taſk to ſolve. An inſtance will ſhow the extent and
                    utility of it. Suppoſe it were required to make a manſard or kirb roof whoſe
                    width is AB (fig. 7.), and conſiſting of the four equal rafters AC, CD, DE, EB.
                    There can be no doubt but that its beſt form is that which will put all the
                    parts in equilibrio, ſo that no ties or ſtays may be neceſſary for oppoſing the
                    unbalanced thruſt of any part of it. Make a chain <hi rend="italic">a c d e b</hi> (fig. 8.) of four equal pieces, looſely connected by pin-joints, round
                    which the parts are perfectly moveable. Suſpend this from two pins <hi
                        rend="italic"> a, b,</hi> fixed in a horizontal line. This chain or feſtoon
                    will arrange itſelf in ſuch a form that its parts are in equilibrio. Then we
                    know that if the figure be inverted, it will compoſe the frame or truſs of a
                    kirb-roof <hi rend="italic">α</hi> <hi rend="italic">γ</hi> ς <hi rend="italic">b,</hi> which is alſo in
                    equilibrio, the thruſts of the pieces balancing each other in the ſame manner
                    that the mutual pulls of the hanging feſtoon <hi rend="italic">a c d e b</hi> did. If the proportion of the height <hi rend="italic">d f</hi> to the width <hi rend="italic">a, b</hi> is not ſuch as pleaſes, let the pins <hi
                        rend="italic"> a,</hi> <hi rend="italic">b</hi> be placed nearer or more diſtant, till a proportion
                    between the width and height is obtained which pleaſes, and then make the figure
                    ACDEB fig. 7. ſimilar to it. It is evident that this propoſition will apply in
                    the ſame manner to the determination of the form of an arch of a bridge ; but
                    this is not a proper place for a farther diſcuſſion.</p>
                <p>We are now able to compute all the thruſts and other preſſures which are exerted
                    by the parts of a roof on each other and on the walls. Let AB (fig. 9.) be a
                    beam ſtanding anyhow obliquely, and G its centre of gravity. Let us ſuppoſe that
                    the ends of it are ſup-ported in any directions AC, BD, by ſtrings, props, or
                    planes. Let theſe directions meet in the point P of the vertical line PG paſſing
                    through its centre of gravity. Through G draw lines G <hi rend="italic">a</hi> , <hi rend="italic">G</hi> <hi rend="italic">b</hi> parallel to PB, PA. Then</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                            <p>The weight of the beam</p>
                            <p>The preſſure or thruſt at A are proportional to -</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                            <p>PG</p>
                            <p>P <hi rend="italic">a</hi></p>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                            <p>The preſſure at B</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                            <p>P <hi rend="italic">b</hi></p>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>For when a body is in equilibrio between three forces, theſe forces are
                    proportional to the ſides of a triangle which have their directions.</p>
                <p>In like manner, if A g be drawn parallel to P <hi rend="italic">b <hi
                            rend="sub"> i</hi></hi> we ſhall have</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                            <p>Weight of the beam</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                            <p>P <hi rend="italic">g</hi></p>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                            <p>Thruſt on A proportional to</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                            <p>PA</p>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                            <p>Thruſt on B</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                            <p>B <hi rend="italic">g</hi></p>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>Or, drawing B <hi rend="sub">y</hi> parallel to P <hi rend="italic">a</hi></p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                            <p>Weight of beam</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                            <p><hi rend="sup">Py</hi></p>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                            <p>Thruſt at A</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                            <p>are proportional to B <hi rend="italic">y</hi></p>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                            <p>Thruſt at B</p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1">
                            <p>PB</p>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>It cannot be diſputed that, if ſtrength alone be conſidered, the proper form of
                    a roof is that which puts the whole in equilibrio, ſo that it would remain in
                    that ſhape although all the joints were perfectly looſe or flexible. If it has
                    any other ſhape, additional ties or braces are neceſſary for preſerving it, and
                    the parts are unneceſſarily ſtrained. When this equilibrium is obtained, the
                    rafters which compoſe the roof are all acting on each other in the direction of
                    their lengths ; and by this action, combined with their weights, they ſuſtain no
                    ſtrain but that of compreſſion, the ſtrain of all others that they are the moſt
                    able to reſiſt. We may conſider them as ſo many inflexible lines having their
                    weights accumulated in their centres of gravity. But it will allow an eaſier
                    inveſtigation of the ſubject, if we ſuppoſe the weights to be at the joints,
                    equal to the real vertical preſſures which are exerted on theſe points. Theſe
                    are very easily computed: for it is plain, that the weight of the beam AB (fig.
                    9.) is to the part of this weight that is ſupported at B as AB to AG. Therefore,
                    if W repreſent the weight of the beam, the vertical preſ-</p>
                <p>AG</p>
                <p>ſure at B will be W X AB, and the vertical preſſure BG</p>
                <p>at A will be W × AB∙ In like manner, the prop BF</p>
                <p>being conſidered as another beam, and <hi rend="italic">f</hi> as its centre
                    of gravity and <hi rend="italic">w</hi> as its weight, a part of this weight,
                    equal to <hi rend="italic">w</hi> is ſupported at B, and the whole vertical</p>
                <p>AG <hi rend="italic">f</hi> F</p>
                <p>preſſure at B is W X -+ <hi rend="italic">w</hi> ×BF∙ And thus we greatly
                    Amplify the conduction of the mutual thruſts of roof frames. We need hardly
                    obſerve, that although theſe preſſures by which the parts of a frame ſupport
                    each other in oppoſition to the vertical action of gravity, are always exerted
                    in the direction of the pieces, they may be reſolved into preſſures acting in
                    any other direction which may engage our attention.</p>
                <p>All that we propoſe to deliver on this ſubject at preſent may be included in the
                    following propoſition.</p>
                <p>Let ABCDE (fig· 10.) be an aſſemblage of rafters in a vertical plane, retting on
                    two fixed points A and E in a horizontal line, and perfectly moveable round all
                    the joints A, B, C, D, E ; and let it be ſuppoſed to be in equilibrio, and let
                    us inveſtigate what adjuſtment of the different circumſtances of weight and
                    inclination of its different parts is neceſſary for producing this equilibrium.</p>
                <p>Let F, G, H, I, be the centres of gravity of the diſſerent rafters, and let
                    theſe letters expreſs the weights of each. Then (by what has been ſaid above)
                    the weight</p>
                <p>AF</p>
                <p>which preſſes B directly downwards is F X + G X</p>
                <p>CG BG</p>
                <p>The weight on C is in like manner G X BC+</p>
                <p>DH CH El H × and that on D is H X CD + I ×DE∙</p>
                <p>Let A <hi rend="italic">b e</hi> JE be the figure ABCDE inverted, in the
                    manner already deſcribed. It may be conceived as a thread faſtened at A and E,
                    and loaded at <hi rend="italic">b. c <hi rend="sub">i</hi></hi> and</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r03-0471" facs="gri_33125011196389_0477.tif"/>
                <p><hi rend="italic">d</hi> with the weights which are really preſſing on B, C,
                    and D. It will arrange itſelf into ſuch a form that all will be in equilibrio.
                    We may diſcover this form by means of this Angle conſideration, that any part <hi rend="italic">b c</hi> of the thread is equally ſtretched throughout
                    in the direction of its length. Let us therefore inveſtigate the proportion
                    between the weight A which we ſuppoſe to be pulling the point <hi rend="italic">b</hi> in the vertical direction <hi rend="italic">b P&gt;</hi> to
                    the •weight «Γ, which is pulling down the point <hi rend="italic">d</hi> in a
                    ſimilar manner. It is evident, that ſince ÂE is a horizontal line, and the
                    figures A <hi rend="italic">b c d</hi> E and ABCDE equal and ſimilar, the
                    lines B <hi rend="italic">b,</hi> C <hi rend="italic">c,</hi> D <hi
                        rend="italic"> d,</hi> are vertical. Take <hi rend="italic">b f</hi> to
                    repreſent the weight hanging at <hi rend="italic">b.</hi> By ſtretching the
                    threads <hi rend="italic">b</hi> A and <hi rend="italic">b c</hi> it is ſet
                    in oppoſition to the contractile powers of the threads, acting in the directions <hi rend="italic">t&gt;</hi> A and <hi rend="italic">b c,</hi> and
                    it is in immediate equilibrio with the equivalent of theſe two contractile
                    forces. Therefore make <hi rend="italic">bg</hi> equal to <hi rend="italic">bſ,</hi> and make it the diagonal of a parallelogram <hi rend="italic">h b
                        ig.</hi> It is evident that <hi rend="italic">b /?, bi,</hi> are the
                    forces exerted by the threads <hi rend="italic">b A,b c·.</hi> Then, feeing
                    that the thread <hi rend="italic">b c</hi> is equally ſtretched in both
                    directions, make <hi rend="italic">c k</hi> equal to <hi rend="italic">b i ;
                        c k</hi> is the contractile force which is excited at by the weight which
                    is hanging there. Draw <hi rend="italic">k I</hi> parallel to <hi
                        rend="italic"> c d,</hi> and ∕ <hi rend="italic">m</hi> parallel to <hi
                        rend="italic"> b c.</hi> The force <hi rend="italic">l c</hi> is the
                    equivalent of the contractile forces <hi rend="italic">ck,cm</hi> and is
                    therefore equal and oppoſite to the force of gravity acting at C. In like
                    manner, make <hi rend="italic">dn—c rn,</hi> and complete the parallelogram <hi rend="italic">n dp o,</hi> having the vertical line <hi rend="italic">o d</hi> for its diagonal. Then <hi rend="italic">dη</hi> and <hi
                        rend="italic"> dp</hi> are the contractile forces excited at <hi
                        rend="italic"> d,</hi> and the weight hanging there mull be equal to <hi
                        rend="italic"> ο d.</hi></p>
                <p>Therefore, the load at <hi rend="italic">b</hi> i&amp; to the load at <hi
                        rend="italic"> d</hi> as <hi rend="italic">bg</hi> to <hi rend="italic">d o</hi> But we have ſeen that the oompreſſing forces at B, C, D may be
                    ſubſtituted <hi rend="italic">for</hi> the extending forces at <hi
                        rend="italic"> b, c, d.</hi> Therefore the weights at B, C, D which produce
                    the compreſſions, are equal to the weights at A, <hi rend="italic">c, d,</hi> which produce the extenſions. Therefore <hi rend="italic">bg : da —</hi> <hi rend="sub">r</hi> AF CG <hi rend="sub">ττ</hi> CH <hi rend="sub">τ</hi> El</p>
                <p><hi rend="sup">F x</hi> AB ÷ <hi rend="sup">GX</hi> BC <hi rend="sup">:HX</hi> CD + <hi rend="sup">x</hi> DE <hi rend="sup">,</hi></p>
                <p>Let us enquire what relation there is between this proportion of the loads upon
                    the joints at B and D, and the angles which the rafters make at theſe joints
                    with each other, and with the horizon or the plumb lines. Produce AB till it cut
                    the vertical Cr in Qj draw BR parallel to CD, and BS parallel to DE. The
                    ſimilarity of the figures ABCDE and <hi rend="italic">A.bed'E.,</hi> and the
                    ſimilarity of their poſition with reſpect to the horizontal and plumb lines,
                    ſhow, without any further demonſtra-tion, that the triangles QCB and <hi
                        rend="sub"> ι</hi> g&lt;¼ are ſimilar, and that QB : BC <hi
                        rend="italic"> — g i : t b. — h b : i b.</hi> Therefore QB is to BC as the
                    contractile force exerted by the thread A <hi rend="italic">b</hi> to that
                    exerted by A ; and therefore QB is to BC as the compreſſion of BA to the
                    compreſſion on BC <note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="1">
                        This proportion might have been ſhown directly without any uſe of the
                        inverted figure or conſideration of contractile forces ; but this
                        ſubſtitution gives diſtinct notions of the mode of acting even to perſons
                        not -much converſant in ſuch diſquiſitions ; and we wiſh to make it familiar
                        to the mind, becauſe it gives an eaſy ſoluiion of the moſt complicated
                        problems, and.furniſhes the practical carpenter, who has little icιence,
                        with foutions of the moſt difficult cales by experiment. A ſeſtoon, as we
                        called it, may eaſily be made ; and we are certain, that the forms into
                        which it will arrange itſelf are models of perfect frames. </note> Then,
                    becauſe <hi rend="italic">b i</hi> is equal to <hi rend="italic">ek,</hi> and the triangles CBR and <hi rend="italic">c k I</hi> are ſimilar, CB : BR =
                    H ∕, = <hi rend="italic">c k</hi> : r <hi rend="italic">m,</hi> and CB is to
                    BR as the compreſſion on CB to the compreſſion on CD. And, in like manner,
                    becauſe <hi rend="italic">cm = dn,</hi> we have BR to BS as the compreſſion on
                    DC to the compreſſion on DE. Alſo BR : RS =s <hi rend="italic">ηd∙. do,</hi> that is, as the compreſſion on DC to the load on D. Finally, combining all theſe
                    ratios</p>
                <p>QC : CB <hi rend="italic">= gb∙.bi, = gb∙.kc</hi></p>
                <p>CB:BR = ^:i/, <hi rend="italic">-kczdn</hi></p>
                <p>BR : BS <hi rend="italic">— nd∙. no — dn∖ no</hi></p>
                <p>BS : RS <hi rend="italic">— no·, do — no z do,</hi> we have finally</p>
                <p>QC ; RS = <hi rend="italic">g b : β d —</hi> Load at B : Load at D.-ι</p>
                <p>Now</p>
                <p>QC : BC =∕, QBC :/, BQC, = ∕, ABC :/, AB <hi rend="italic">b</hi></p>
                <p>BC : BR = <hi rend="italic">ſ,</hi> BRC :/, BCR <hi rend="sub">i</hi> = /CD <hi rend="italic">dzf <hi rend="sub">i</hi> b</hi> BC</p>
                <p>BR : RS =∕, BSR : ∕, RBS =∕, JDE :/, CDE « Therefore</p>
                <p>QC : RS <hi rend="italic">-ſ,</hi> ABC./, CD √.∕, <hi rend="italic">d</hi> DE :∕,CDE.∕, AB <hi rend="italic">R</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">∕3bc.</hi></p>
                <p>Or</p>
                <p>OC ∙ RS - -√T- <hi rend="smallcaps"><hi rend="sup"> b</hi> ^- .</hi> — <hi rend="smallcaps">^</hi> <hi rend="sup">cde</hi> &lt;≈ ' -∕, AB i./CB <hi rend="italic">b ■ r, d</hi> DC. ∕, &lt;ZDE∙</p>
                <p>That is, the loads on the different joints are as the fines of the angles at
                    theſe joints directly, and as the products of the fines of the angles which the
                    rafters make with the plumb-lines inverſely.</p>
                <p>Or, the loads are as the fines of the angles of the joints directly, and as the
                    products of the coſines of the elevations of the rafters jointly.</p>
                <p>Or, the loads at the joints are as the fines of the angles at the joints, and as
                    the products of the ſecants of elevation of the rafters jointly : for the
                    ſecants of angles are inverſely as the coſines.</p>
                <p>Draw the horizontal line BT. It is evident, that if this be conſidered as the
                    radius of a circle, the lines BQ, BC, BR, BS are the ſecants of the angles which
                    theſe lines make with the horizon. And they are alſo as the thruſts of thoſe
                    rafters to which they are parallel. Therefore, the thruſt which any rafter makes
                    in its own direction is as the ſecant of its elevation.</p>
                <p>The horizontal thruſt is the ſame at all the angles. For <hi rend="italic">i I
                        — k <hi rend="sup">κ</hi> &gt; = m *■&gt; — n &gt;&gt; ≈ ρ
                        *∙</hi> Therefore both walls are equally preſſed out by the weight of the
                    roof. We can find its quantity by comparing it with the load on one of the
                    joints :</p>
                <p>Thus, QC : CB =∕, ABC :/, AB <hi rend="italic">b</hi></p>
                <p>BC:BT = Rad. :√, BCT, = Rad. : ∕, CB <hi rend="italic">b</hi></p>
                <p>Therefore,QC : BT = Rad. ×∕ ABC :∕, <hi rend="italic">b</hi> BA×∕, £BC</p>
                <p>It deſerves remark, that the lengths of the beams do not afſect either the
                    proportion of the load at the different joints, nor the poſition of the rafters.
                    This depends merely on the weights at the angles. If a change of length affects
                    the weight, this indeed affects the form alſo ; and this is generally the caſe.
                    For it ſeldom happens, indeed it never ſhould happen, that the weight on rafters
                    of longer bearing are not greater. The covering alone increaſes nearly in the
                    proportion of the length of the rafter.</p>
                <p>If the proportion of the weights at B, C, and D</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r03-0472" facs="gri_33125011196389_0478.tif"/>
                <p>tire given, as alſo the poſition of any two of the lines, the poſition of all
                    the reſt is determined.</p>
                <p>If the horizontal diſtances between the angles are all equal, the forces on the
                    different angles are proportional to the verticals drawn on the lines through
                    theſe angles from the adjoining angle, and the thruſts from the adjoining angles
                    are as the lines which connect them.</p>
                <p>If the rafters themſelves arc of equal lengths, the weights at the different
                    angles are as theſe verticals and as the ſecants of the elevation of the rafters
                    jointly.</p>
                <p>This propoſition is very fruitful in its practical conſequences. It is eaſy to
                    perceive that it contains the whole theory of the conſtruction of arches ; for
                    each ſtont of an arch may be conſidered as one of the rafters of this piece of
                    carpentry, ſince all is kept up by its mere equilibrium. We may have an
                    opportunity in ſome future article of exhibiting ſome very elegant and ſimple
                    ſolutions of the moſt difficult cafes of this important problem ; and we now
                    proceed to make uſe of the knowledge we have acquired for the conſtruc</p>
                <p>tion of roofs.</p>
                <p>We mentioned by the bye a problem which is not unfrequent in practice, to
                    determine the beſt form of a kirb-roof. Mr Couplet of the Royal Academy of Paris
                    has given a ſolution of it in an elaborate memoir in 1726, occupying ſeveral
                    lemmas and theorems.</p>
                <p>Let AE (fig. ιι.) be the width, and CF the height; it is required to conſtruct a
                    roof ABCDE whoſe rafters AB, BC, CD, DÉ, are all equal, and which ſhall be in
                    equilibrio.</p>
                <p>D raw CE, and biſect it perpendicularly in H by the line DHG, cutting the
                    horizontal line AE in G. A-bout the centre G, with the diſtance GE, deſcribe the
                    circle EDC. It muſt paſs through C, becauſe CH is equal to HE and the angles at
                    H are equal. Draw HK parallel to FE, cutting the circumference in K. Draw CK,
                    cutting GH in D. Join CD, ED ; theſe lines are the rafters of half of the roof
                    required.·</p>
                <p>' We prove this by ſhowing, that the loads in the angles C and D are equal. For
                    this is the proportion which reſults from the equality of the rafters, and the
                    extent of ſurſece of the uniform roofing which they are ſuppoſed to ſupport.
                    Therefore produce ED till it •meet the vertical FC in N ; and having made the
                    fide CBA ſimilar to CDE, complete the parallelogram BCDP, and draw DB, which
                    will biſect CP in R, as the horizontal line K H, biſects CF in Draw KF, which is
                    evidently parallel to DP. Make CS perpendicular to CF, and equal to FG; and
                    about S, with the radius SF, deſcribe the circle FKW. It muſtpaſs through K,
                    becauſe SF is equal to C G, and C Qj= OF. Draw W K, W S, and produce B C,
                    cutting ND in O.</p>
                <p>The angle WKF at the circumference is one-half of the angle W S F at the centre,
                    and is therefore equal to WSC, or CGF. It is therefore double of the angle CEF
                    or ECS. But ECS is equal to ECD and DCS, and ECD is one-half of NDC, and DCS is
                    one-half of DCO, or C D P. Therefore the angle W K F is equal to NDP, and WK is
                    parallel to ND, and CF is to CW as CP to CN ; and CN is equal to CP. But it has
                    been ſhown above, that C N and C P are as the loads upon D and C. Theſe are
                    therefore equal, and the frame ABCDE is in equilibrio,</p>
                <p>A companion of this ſolution with that of Mr Couplet will ſliow its great
                    advantage in reſpect of ſimplicity and perſpicuity. And the intelligent reader
                    can eaſily adapt the conſtruction to any proportion between the rafters A B and
                    B C, which other circumſtances, ſuch as garret-room, &amp;c. may <hi
                        rend="sup"> r</hi> render convenient. The conſtruction muſt be ſucli that
                    NC may be to CP as CD to CD+DE.</p>
                <p>Whatever proportion of AB to BC is</p>
                <p>aſſumed, the point D'will be found in the circumference of a ſemicircle H' D'
                    Z∣', whoſe centre is in the line C E, and having A B : B C = C H' : H E , = <hi
                        rend="italic"> cP ; h'</hi> E. — The reſt of the conſtruction is ſimple,</p>
                <p>In buildings which are rooſed with ſlate, tyle, or ſhingles, the circumſtance
                    which is moſt likely to limit the conſtruction is the ſlope of the upper rafters
                    C B, CD. This muſt be ſuſſicient to prevent the penetration of rain, and the
                    ſtripping by the winds. The only circumſtance left in our choice in this caſe is
                    the pro* portion of the rafters AB and BC. Nothing is eaſier than making NC to
                    CP in any delired proportion when the angle BCD is given.</p>
                <p>We need not repeat that it is always a deſirable thing to form a truſs for a
                    roof in ſuch a manner that it ſhallbe in equilibrio. When this is done, the
                    whole force of the ſtruts and braces which are added to it is employed in
                    preſerving this form, and no part is expended in un∙ neceſſary ſtrains. For we
                    muſt now obſerve, that the equilibrium of which we have been treating is always
                    of that kind which we called the tottering, and the roof requires ſtays, braces,
                    or hanging timbers, to give it ſtiffneſs, or keep it in ſhape. We have alſo ſaid
                    enough to enable any reader, acquainted with the moſt elementary geometry and
                    mechanics, to compute the tranſverſe ſtrains and the thruſts to which the
                    component parts of all roofs are expoſed.</p>
                <p>It only remains now to ſhow the general maxims by which all roofs muſt be
                    conſtructed, and the circumſtances which determine their excellence. In doing
                    this we ſhall be exceedingly brief, and almoſt content our-ſelves with
                    exhibiting the principal forms, of which the endleſs variety of roofs are only
                    flight modifications.— We ſhall not trouble the reader with any account of ſuch
                    roofs as receive part of their ſupport from the interior walls, but confine
                    ourſelves to the more difficult problem of throwing a roof over a wide building,
                    without any intermediate ſupport ; becauſe when ſuch roofs are conſtructed in
                    the beſt manner, that is, deriving the greateſt poſſible ſtrength from the
                    materials employed, the beſt conſtruction of the others is neceſſarily included.
                    For all ſuch roofs as reſt on the middle walls are roofs of ſmaller bearing. The
                    only exception deſerving notice is the roofs of churches, which have aiſles
                    ſeparated from the nave by columns. The roof muſt rife on theſe. But if it is of
                    an arched form internally, the horizontal thruſts muſt be nicely balanced, that
                    they may not puſh the columns aſide.</p>
                <p>The ſimpleſt notion of a roof-frame is, that it conſiſts of two rafters A B and
                    B C (fig. 12.), meeting in the ridge B.</p>
                <p>Even this ſimple form is ſuſceptible of better and</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r03-0473" facs="gri_33125011196389_0479.tif"/>
                <p>worfe. We have already ſeen, that when the weight of a ſquare yard of covering
                    is given, a ſteeper roof requires ſtronger rafters, and that when the ſeantling
                    of ■the timbers is alſo given, tlιe relative ſtrength of a rafter is inverſely
                    as its length. But there is now another circumſtance to be taken into the
                    account, viz. the ſupport which one rafter leg gives to the other. The beſt form
                    of a rafter will therefore be that in which the relative ■ſtrength of the legs,
                    and their mutual ſupport, give the greateſt product. Mr Muller, in his <hi
                        rend="italic"> Military Engineer,</hi> gives a determination of the beſt
                    pitch of a roof, which has conſiderable ingenuity, and has been copied into many
                    books of military education both in this iſland and on the continent. Deſcribe
                    on the width A C, ſig. 13. the ſemicircle AFC, and biſect it by the radius F D.
                    Produce the rafter A B to the circumference in E, join EC, and draw the
                    perpendicular E G.—</p>
                <p>Now A B : AD = A C : A E, and AE = Λ¾Δ <hi rend="sup">c</hi> ,A 13</p>
                <p>and AE is inverſely as AB, and may therefore repre-ſent its ſtrength in relation
                    to the weight actually lying «η it.' Alſo the ſupport which CB gives to AB is as
                    CE, becauſe CE is perpendicular to AB. Therefore the form which renders A E × E
                    C a maximum ſeems to be that which has the greateſt ſtrength. But A C :</p>
                <p>AE E C</p>
                <p>A E = E C : E G, and E G=—~ſſlg—» <hi rend="sup">an</hi> ^ is therefore
                    proportional to AE.EC. Now E G is a maximum when B is in F, and a ſquare pitch
                    is in this reſpect the ſtrongeſt. But it is very doubtful whether this
                    conſtruction is deduced from juſt principles. There is another ſtrain to which
                    the leg A B is expoſed, which is not taken into the account. This ariſes from
                    the curvature which it unavoidably acquires by the tranſverſe preſſure of its
                    load. In this ſtate it is preſſed in its own direction by the abutment and load
                    of the other leg. The relation between this ſtrain and the reſiſtance of the
                    piece is not very diſtinctly known. Euler has given a diſſertation on this
                    ſubject (which is of great importance, becauſe it affects poſts and pillars of
                    all kinds ; and it is very well known that a poſt of ten feet long and fix
                    inches ſquare will bear with great ſafety a weight which would cruſh a poſt of
                    the ſame ſeantling and 20 feet long in a minute) ; but his determination has not
                    been acquieſced in by the firſt mathematicians. Now it is in relation to theſe
                    two ſtrains that the ſtrength of the rafter ſhould be adjuſted. The ſineneſs of
                    the ſupport given by the other leg is of no conſequence, if its own ſtrength is
                    inferior to the ſtrain. The force which tends to cruſh the leg A B, by
                    compreſſing it in its curved ſtate, is to its weight as A B to B D, as is eaſily
                    ſeen by the compoſition of forces; and its incurvation by this force has a
                    relation to it, which is of intricate determination. It is contained in the
                    properties demonſtrated by Bernoulli of the elaſtic curve. This determination
                    alſo includes the relation between the curvature and the length of the piece.
                    But the whole of this ſeemingly ſimple problem is of much more difficult
                    inveſtigation than Mr Muller was aware of ; and his rules for the pitch of a
                    roof, and for the ſally of a dock gate, which depends on the ſame principles,
                    are of no value. He is, however, the firſt author who attempted to ſolve either
                    of theſe problems on mechanical principles ſuſceptible of preciſe reaſoning.
                    Belidor’s ſolu-⅞ions, in his <hi rend="italic">Architecture Hydraulique <hi
                            rend="sub"> t</hi></hi> are below notice.</p>
                <p>Reaſqns of ’economy have made carpenters prefer a low pitch ; and although this
                    does diminiſh the ſup-port given by the oppoſite leg falter than it increaſes
                    the relative ſtrength of the other, this is not 9f material conſequence, becauſe
                    the ſtrength remaining in the oppoſite leg is ſtill very great ; for the
                    ſupporting leg is acting againſt compreſſion, in which caſe it is vaſtly
                    ſtronger than the ſupported leg acting againſt a tranſverſe ſtrain.</p>
                <p>But a roof of this ſimplicity will not do in moſt caſes. There is no notice
                    taken in its conſtruction of the thruſt which it exerts on the walls. Now this
                    is the ſtrain which is the moſt hazardous of all. Our ordinary walls, inſtead of
                    being able to reſiſt any conſiderable ſtrain preſſing them outwards, require, in
                    general, ſome ties to keep them on foot. When a perſon thinks of the thinneſs
                    and height of the walls of even a ſtrong houſe, he will be ſurpriſed that they
                    are uot blown down by any ſtrong puff of wund. A wall of three feet thick, and
                    60 feet high, could not withſtand a wind blowing at the rate of 30 feet <hi
                        rend="italic"> per</hi> ſecond (in which caſe it acts with a force
                    conſiderably exceeding two pounds on every ſquare foot), if it were not
                    ſtiſſened by croſs walls, joiſts, and roof, which all help to tie the different
                    parts of the building together.</p>
                <p>A carpenter is therefore exceedingly careful to avoid every horizontal thruſt,
                    or to oppoſe them by other <hi rend="sup">i</hi> forces. And this introduces
                    another eſſential part into the conſtruction of a roof, namely the <hi
                        rend="italic"> tie</hi> or <hi rend="italic">beam</hi> A C, ( <hi
                        rend="sup"> fi</hi> ff∙ 14.), laid from wall to wall, binding the feet A
                    and C of the rafters together. This is the ſole office qf the beam ; and it
                    ſhould be conſidered in no other light than as a firing to prevent the roof from
                    puffing out the walls. It is indeed uſed for carrying the ceiling of the
                    apartments under it ; and it is even made to ſupporta flooring. But, conſidered
                    as making part of a roof, it is merely a ſtring ; and the ſtrain which it w <hi
                        rend="sup"> ,</hi> ithftandp tends to tear its parts aſunder. It therefore
                    acts with its whole abſolute force, and a very ſmall ſeantling would ſuffice if
                    we could contrive to faſten it firmly enough to the foot of the rafter. If it is
                    of oak, we may ſafely ſubject it to a ſtrain of three tons for every ſquare inch
                    of its ſection. And fir will ſafely bear a ſtrain of two tons for every ſquare
                    inch. But we are obliged to give the tie-beam much larger dimenſions, that we
                    may be able to connect it with the foot of the rafter by a mor-tiſe and tenon.
                    Iron ſtraps are alſo frequently added. By attending to this office of the
                    tie-beam, the judicious carpenter is directed to the proper form of the mor-tiſe
                    and tenon and of the ſtrap. We ſhall eonſider both of theſe in a proper place,
                    after we become acquainted with the various ſtrains at the joints of a roof.</p>
                <p>Theſe large dimenſions of the tie-beam allow us to load it with the ceilings
                    without any riſk, and even to lay floors on it with moderation and caution. But
                    when it has a great bearing or ſpan, it is very apt to bend downwards in the
                    middle, or, as the workmen term it, to ſway or ſwag ; and it requires a ſupport.
                    The queſtion is, where to find this ſupport ? What fixed points can we find with
                    which to connect the middle of the tie-beam ? Some ingenious carpenter thought
                    of ſuſpending it from the ridge by a piece of timber B D (fig. 15.), called by
                    our carpenters the <hi rend="italic">kiηg-poft.</hi> It muſt be acknowledged
                    that there was great ingenuity in this thought. It was alſo perfectly juſt. For
                    the weight of the rafters B A, BC tends to make them fly</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r03-0474" facs="gri_33125011196389_0480.tif"/>
                <p>out at the foot. This is prevented by the tie-beam, and this excites a preſſure,
                    by which they tend to compreſs each other. Suppoſe them without weight, and that
                    a great weight is laid on the ridge B. This can be ſupported only by the butting
                    of the rafters in their own directions A B and C B, and the weight tends to
                    compreſs them in the oppoſite directions, and, through their intervention,, to
                    ſtretch the tie-beam. If neither the rafters can be compreſſed, nor the tie-beam
                    ſtretched, it is plain that the triangle ABC muſt retain its ſhape, and that B
                    becomes a fixed point, very proper to be uſed as a point of ſuſpenſion. To this
                    point, therefore, is the tie-beam ſuſpended by means of the king-poſt. A common
                    ſpectator, unacquainted with carpentry, view's it very differently, and the
                    tie-beam appears to him to carry the roof. The king-poſt appears a pillar
                    reſting on the beam, wdιereas it is really a ſtring ; and an iron-rod of
                    one-ſixteenth of the ſize would have done juſt as well. The king-poſt is
                    ſometimes mortiſed into the tie-beam, and pins put through the joint, which
                    gives it more the look of a pillar with the roof reſting on it. This does well
                    enough in many cafes. But the beſt method is to connect them by an iron ſtrap,
                    like a ſtirrup, which is bolted at its upper ends into the king-poſt, and paſſes
                    round the tie-beam. In this way a ſpace is commonly left between the end of the
                    king-poſt and the upper ſide of the tie-beam. Here the beam plainly appears
                    hanging in the ſtirrup ; and this method allows us to reſtore the beam to an
                    exact level, when it has funk by the unavoidable compreſſion or other yielding
                    of the parts. The holes in the ſides of the iron ſtrap are made oblong inſtead
                    of round ; and the bolt which is drawn through all is made to taper on the under
                    fide; ſo that driving it farther draws the 'tie-beam upwards. A notion of this
                    may be formed by looking at fig. 16. which is a ſection of the poſt and beam.</p>
                <p>It requires conſiderable attention, however, to make this ſuſpenſion of the
                    tie-beam ſuſſiciently firm. The top of the king-poſt is cut into the form of the
                    arch-ſtone of a bridge, and the heads of the rafters are firm-'ly mortiſed into
                    this projecting part. Theſe projections are called joggles, and are formed by
                    working the king-poſt out of a much larger piece of timber, and cutting off the
                    unneceffary wood from the two ſides ; and, left all this ſhould not be
                    ſuſſicient, it is uſual in great works to add an iron-plate or ſtrap of three
                    branches, which are bolted into the heads of the king-poſt and rafters.</p>
                <p>The rafters, though not ſo long as the beam, ſeem to ſtand as much in need of
                    ſomething to prevent their bending, for they carry the weight of the covering.—
                    This cannot be done by ſuſpenſion, for we have no fixed points above them : But
                    we have now got a very firm point of ſupport at the foot of the king-poſt.— <hi
                        rend="italic"> Braces,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">firuts,</hi> ED, ED,
                    (fig. 17.), are put under the" middle of the rafters, where they are ſlightly
                    mortiſed, and their lower ends are firmly mortiſed into joggles formed on the
                    foot of the king-poſt. As theſe braces are very powerful in their reſiſtance to
                    compreſe ſion, and the king-poſt equally ſo to refill extenſion, the points E
                    and F may be conſidered as fixed ; and the rafters being thus reduced to half
                    their former length, have now four times their former relative ſtrength.</p>
                <p>Roofs do not always conſiſt of two ſloping ſides meeting in a ridge. They have
                    ſometimes a flat on the top, with two ſloping ſides. They are ſometimes formed
                    with a double ſlope, and are called <hi rend="italic">kirb</hi> or <hi
                        rend="italic"> manſarde roofs.</hi> They ſometimes have a valley in the
                    middle, and are then called M roofs. Such roofs require another piece which may
                    be called the <hi rend="italic">trufs beam</hi> becauſe all ſuch frames are
                    called <hi rend="italic">truffes,</hi> probably from the French word <hi
                        rend="italic"> trouſfe,</hi> becauſe ſuch roofs are like portions of plain
                    roofs, <hi rend="italic">trouſſes</hi> or ſhortened.</p>
                <p>A flat-topped roof is thus conſtructed. Suppoſe the three rafters AB, BC, CD
                    (fig. 18.) of which AB and CD are equal, and BC horizontal. It is plain that
                    they will be in equilibrio, and the roof have no tendency to go to either fide.
                    The tie-beam AD withſtands the horizontal thruſts of the whole frame, and the
                    two rafters AB and CD are each preſſed in their own directions in conſequence of
                    their butting with the middle rafter or truſs-beam BC. It lies between them like
                    the keyſtone of an arch. They lean towards it, and it reſts on them. The
                    preſſure which the truſs-beam and its load excites on the two rafters is the
                    very ſame as if the rafters were produced till they meet in G, and a weight were
                    laid on theſe equal to that of BC and its load. If therefore the truſs-beam is
                    of a ſcantling ſuſſicient for carrying its own load, and withſtanding the
                    compreſſion from the two rafters, the roof will be equally ſtrong (while it
                    keeps its ſhape) as the plain roof AGD furniſhed with king-poſt and braces. We
                    may conceive this another way. Suppoſe a plain roof AGD, without braces to
                    ſupport the middle B and C of the rafters. Then let a beam BC be put in between
                    the rafters, butting upon little notches cut in the rafters. It is evident that
                    this muſt prevent the rafters from bending dowm-wards, becauſe the points B and
                    C cannot deſcend, moving round the centres A and D, without ſhortening the
                    diſtance BC between them. This cannot be without compreſſing the beam BC. It is
                    plain that B C may be wedged in, or wedges driven in between its ends B and C
                    and the notches in which it is lodged. Theſe wedges may be driven in till they
                    even force out the rafters GA and GD. Whenever thi3 happens, all the mutual
                    preſſure of the heads of theſe rafters at G is taken away, and the parts GB and
                    GC may be cut away, and the roof ABCD will be as ſtrong as the roof AGD
                    furniſhed with the king-poſt and braces, becauſe the truſs-beam gives a ſupport
                    of the ſame kind at B and C as the brace would have done.</p>
                <p>But this roof ABCD would have no firmneſs of ſhape. Any addition of weight on
                    one ſide would de* ſtroy the equilibrium at the angle, would depreſs that angle,
                    and cauſe the oppoſite one to riſe. To give it ſtiffneſs, it muſt either have
                    ties or braces, or ſomething partaking of the nature of both. The uſual method
                    of framing is to make the heads of the rafters butt on the joggles of two
                    ſide-poſts BE and CF, while the truſs-beam, or ſtrut as it is generally termed
                    by the carpenters, is mortiſed ſquare into the inſide of the heads. The lower
                    ends E and F of the ſide-poſts are connected with the tie-beam either by
                    mortiſes or ſtraps.</p>
                <p>This conſtruction gives firmneſs to the frame ; for the angle B cannot deſcend
                    in conſequence of any inequality of preſſure, without forcing the other angle C
                    to riſe. This it cannot do, being held down by the poſt CF. And the ſame
                    conſtruction fortifies the tie-beam, which is now ſuſpended at the points E and
                    F</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r03-0475" facs="gri_33125011196389_0481.tif"/>
                <p>from the points B and C, whoſe ſirmneſs we havejuſt now ſhown.</p>
                <p>But although this roof may be made abundantly ſtrong, it is not quite ſo ſtrong
                    as the plain roof AGD of the ſame ſcantling. The compreffion which BC muſt
                    ſuſtain in order to give the ſame ſupport to the rafters at B and C that was
                    given by braces properly placed, is conſiderably greater than the compreſſion of
                    the braces. And this ſtrain is an addition to the tranſverſe ſtrain which BC
                    gets from its own load. Alſo this form neceſſarily expoſes the tie-beam to croſs
                    ftrains. If BE is mortiſed into the tie-beam, then the ſtrain which tends to
                    depreſs the angle ABC preſſes on the tie-beam at E tranſverſely, while a
                    contrary ſtrain acts on F, pulling it upwards. Theſe ftrains however are ſmall ;
                    and this conſtruction is frequently uſed, being ſuſceptible of ſufficient
                    ſtrength, without much increaſe of the dimenſibns of the timbers ; and it has
                    the great advantage of giving free room in the garrets. Were it not for this,
                    there is a much more perfect form repreſented in fig. 19. Here the two poſts BE,
                    CF are united below. All tranſverſe action on the tie-beam is now entirely
                    removed. We are almoſt diſpoſed to ſay that this is the ſtrongeſt roof of the
                    ſame width and ilope : for if the iron ſtrap which connects the pieces BE, CF
                    with the tie-beam have a large bolt G through it, confining it to one point of
                    the beam, there are five points A, B, C, D, G, which cannot change their places,
                    and there is no tranſverſe ſtrain in any of the connections.</p>
                <p>When the dimenſions of the building are very great, ſo that the pieces AB, BC,
                    CD, would be thought too weak for withſtanding the croſs ftrains, braces may be
                    added as is expreſſed in fig. 18. by the dotted lines. The reader will obſerve
                    that it is not meant to leave the top flat externally : it muſt be raiſed a
                    little in the middle to ſhoot off the rain. But this muſt not be done by
                    incurvating the beam BC. This would ſoon be cruſhed, and ſpring upwards. The
                    ſlopes muſt be given by pieces of timber added above the ſtrutting beam.</p>
                <p>And thus we have completed a frame of a roof. It conſiſts of theſe principal
                    members : The rafters, which are immediately loaded with the covering; the
                    tie-beam, which withſtands the horizontal thruſt by which the roof tends to fly
                    out below and puſh out the walls ; the king-pofts, which hang from fixed points
                    and ferve to uphold the tie-beam, and alſo to afford other fixed points on
                    which we may reft the braces which ſupport the middle of the rafters ; and
                    laſtly the truſs or ſtrut-ting-beam, which ſerves to give mutual abutment to the
                    different parts which are at a diſtance from each either. The rafters, braces,
                    and truſſes are expoſed to compreffion, and muſt therefore have not only
                    coheſion but ſtiſſneſs. For if they bend, the prodigious compreſſions to which
                    they are ſubjected would quickly cruſh them in this bended ſtate. The tie-beams
                    and king-pofts, if performing no other office but ſupport-ing the roof, do not
                    require ſtiſſneſs, and their places might be ſupplied by ropes, or by rods of
                    iron of one-tenth part of the lection that even the ſmalleſt oak ſtretcher
                    requires. Theſe members require no greater dimenſions than what is neceſſary for
                    giving ſufficient joints, and any more is a needleſs expence and k&gt;ad.
                    All roofs, however complicated, conſiſt of theſe eſſential parts, and if pieces
                    of timber are to be ſeea which perform none of theſe offices, they muſt be pro·
                    nounced uſeleſs, and they are frequently hurtful, by producing croſs ftrains in
                    i’ome other piece. In a rool properly conſtructed there ſhould be no ſuch
                    ſtrains. All the timbers, except thoſe which immediately carry the covering,
                    ſhould be either puſhed or drawn in the direction of their length. And this is
                    the rule by which a roof ſhould alw <hi rend="sup">r</hi> ays be examined.</p>
                <p>Theſe eſſential parts are ſuſceptible of numberleſs combinations and varieties.
                    But it is a prudent maxim to make the conſtruction as ſimple, and conſiſtſhg of
                    as few parts, as poſſible. We areleſs expoſed to the imperfections of
                    workmanſhip, ſuch as looſe joints, &amp;c. Another eſſential harm ariſes
                    from many pieces, by the compreſſion and the ſhrinking of the timber in the
                    croſs direction of the libres. The effect of this is equivalent to the
                    ſhortening of the piece which butts on the joint. This alters the proportions of
                    the lides of the triangle on which the lhape of the whole depends. Now in a roof
                    ſuch as fig. 18. there is twice as much of this as in the plain pent roof,
                    becauſe there are tw <hi rend="sup">τ</hi> o poſts. And when the direction of
                    the butting pieces is very oblique to the action of the load, a ſmall ſhrinking
                    permits a great change of ſhape. Thus in a roof of what is called pediment
                    pitch, where the rafters make an angle of 30 degrees with the horizon, half an
                    inch compreſſion of the king-poſt will produce a fagging of an inch, and
                    occaſion a great ſtrain on the tie-beam if the poſts are mortiſed into it. In
                    fig. 2. of the roofs in the article Architecture, half an inch ſhrinking of each
                    of the two poſts will allow the middle to ſagg above five inches. Fig. ι. of the
                    ſame plate is faulty in this reſpect, by cutting the ſtrutting-beam in the
                    middle. <hi rend="sup">r</hi> Γhe ſtrutting-beam is thus ſhortened by three
                    ſhrinkings, while there is but one to ſhorten the rafters. The conſequence is,
                    that the truſs which is included within the rafters will ſagg away from them,
                    and then they muſt bend in the middle till they again reft on this included
                    truſs. This roof is, however, conſtructed on the whole on good principles, and
                    we adduce it only tα ſhow the advantages of ſimplicity. This cutting of the
                    truſſing-beam is unavoidable, if we would preſerve the king-poſt. But we are in
                    doubt whether the ſervice performed by it in this caſe will balance the
                    inconvenience. It is employed only to ſupport the middle of the upper half of
                    each rafter, which it does but imperfectly, becauſe the braces and ſtrut muſt be
                    cut hall through at their croſſing : if theſe joints are made tight, as a
                    workman would wiſh to do, the ſettling of the roof will cauſe them to work on
                    each other croſſwiſe with inſuperable force, and will undoubtedly ſtrain them
                    exceedingly.</p>
                <p>This method of including a truſs within the rafters of a pent roof is a very
                    conſiderable addition to the ai t of carpentry. But to inſure its full effect,
                    it ſhould always be executed in the manner repreſented in fig. 1. Plate XLVIII.
                    with butting rafters under the principal ones, butting on joggles in the heads
                    of the poſts. Without this the ſtrut-Seam is hardly of any ſervice. We would
                    therefore recommend fig. 20. as a proper conſtruction of a truſſed roof, and the
                    king-poſt which is placed in it may be employed to ſupport the upper part of the
                    rafters, and alſo for preventing the ſtrut-beam from bending in either-direction
                    in conſequence of its great compreſſion. It will alſo give a ſuſpenlion for the
                    great burdens which are ſometimes neceſſary in</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r03-0476" facs="gri_33125011196389_0482.tif"/>
                <p>a theatre. The machinery has no other firm points to •which it can be attached ;
                    and the portion of the Angle rafters which carry this king-poſt are but ſhort,
                    and therefore may be conſiderably loaded with ſafety.</p>
                <p>We obſerve in the drawings which we ſometimes have of Chineſe buildings, that
                    the truſſing of roofs is underſtood by them. Indeed they muſt be very
                    experienced carpenters. We ſee wooden buildings run up to a great height, which
                    can be ſupported only by ſuch truſſing. One of theſe is ſketched in ſig. 21.
                    There are ſome very excellent ſpecimens to be ſeen in the buildings at Deptford,
                    belonging to the victualling-office, uſually called the <hi rend="italic">Red
                        Houſe,</hi> which were erected about the year 1788, and we believe are the
                    performance of Mr James Arrow of the Board of Works, one of the moſt intelligent
                    artiſts in this kingdom.</p>
                <p>Thus have we given an elementary, but a rational or Scientific, account of this
                    important part of the art of carpentry. It is ſuch, that any practitioner, with
                    the troubleof a little reflection, may always proceed with confidence, and
                    without reſting any part of his practice on the vague notions which habit may
                    have given him of the ſtrength and ſupports of timbers, and of their manner of
                    acting. That theſe frequently miſlead, is proved by the mutual criticiſms which
                    are frequently publiſhed by the rivals in the proſeſſion. They have frequently
                    ſagacity enough (for it can ſeldom be called ſcſence ) to point out glaring
                    blunders ; and any perſon who will look at ſome of the performances of Mr Price,
                    Mr Wyatt, Mr Arrow, and others of acknowdedged reputation, will readily ſee them
                    diſtinguiſhable from the works of inferior artiſts by ſimplicity alone. A man
                    without principles is apt to conſider an intricate conſtruction as ingenious and
                    effectual ; and ſuch roofs ſometimes fail merely by being ingeniouſly loaded
                    with timber, but more frequently ſtill by the wrong action of ſome uſeleſs
                    piece, which produces ſtrains that are tranſverſe to other pieces, or which, by
                    rendering ſome points too firm, cauſe them to be deſerted by the reſt in the
                    general fubſiding of the whole. Inſtances of this kind are pointed out by Price
                    in his Britiſh Carpenter. Nothing ihows the ſkill of a carpenter more than the
                    diſtinctneſs with which he can foreſee the changes of ſhape which muſt take
                    place in a ſhort time in every roof. A knowledge of this will often correct a
                    conſtruction which the mere mathematician thinks unexceptionable, becauſe he
                    does not reckon on the actual compreſſion which muſt obtain, and imagines that
                    his triangles, which ſuſtain no croſs ſtrains, invariably retain their ſhape
                    till the pieces break. The ſagacity of the experienced carpenter is not,
                    however, enough without fci-ence for perfecting the art. But when he knows how
                    much a particular piece will yield to compreſſion in one caſe, ſcience will tell
                    him, and nothing but ſcience can do it, what will be the compreſſion of the ſame
                    piece in another very different caſe. Thus he learns how far it will now yield,
                    and then he proportions the parts ſo to each other, that when all have yielded
                    according to their ſtrains, the whole is of the ſhape he wiſhed to produce, and
                    every joint is in a ſtate of firmneſs. It is here that we obſerve the greateſt
                    number of improprieties. The iron ſtraps are frequently in poſitions not ſuited
                    to the actual ſtrain on them, and they are in a ſtate of violent twiſt, which
                    both tends ſtrongly to</p>
                <p>break the ſtrap, and to cripple the pieces which they ſurround. *</p>
                <p>In like manner, we frequently ſee joints or mortiſes in a ſtate of violent
                    ſtrain on the tenons, or on the heels and ſhoulders. The joints were perhaps
                    properly ſhaped to the primitive form of the truſs ; but by its ſettling, the
                    bearing on the puſh is changed : the brace, for example, in a very low pitched
                    roof, comes to preſs with the upper part of the ſhoulder, and, acting as a
                    powerful lever on the tenon, breaks it. In like manner, the lower end of the
                    brace, which at firſt butted firmly and ſquarely on the joggle of the king-poſt,
                    now preſſes with one corner with prodigious force, and ſeldom fails to ſplinter
                    off on that fide. We cannot help recommending a maxim of Mr Perronet the
                    celebrated hydraulic architect of France, as a golden rule, viz. to make all the
                    ſhoulders of butting pieces in the form of an arch of a circle, having the
                    oppoſite end of the piece for its centre. Thus, in ſig. 18. if the joggle-joint
                    B be of this form, having A for its centre, the ſagging of the roof will make no
                    partial bearing at the joint ; for in the ſagging of the roof, the piece AB
                    turns or bends round the centre A, and the counter-preſſure of the joggle is
                    ſtill directed to A, as it ought to be. We have juſt now ſaid <hi rend="italic">bends</hi> round A. This is too frequently the caſe, and it is always very
                    difficult to give the tenon and mortiſe in this place a true and invariable
                    bearing. The rafter puſhes in the direction BA, and the beam reſiſts in the
                    direction AD. The abutment ſhould be perpendicular to neither of theſe but in an
                    intermediate direction, and it ought alſo to be of a curved ſhape. But the
                    carpenters perhaps think that this would weaken the beam too much to give it
                    this ſhape in the ſhoulder ; they do not even aim at it in the heel of the
                    tenon. The ſhoulder is commonly even with the ſurface of the beam. When the
                    bearing therefore is on this ſhoulder, it cauſes the foot of the rafter to Aide
                    along the beam till the heel of the tenon bears againſt the outer end of the
                    mortiſe (See Price’s <hi rend="italic">Bri-tilh Carpenter,</hi> Plate C. fig.
                    I K). This abutment is perpendicular to the beam in Price’s book, but it is more
                    generally pointed a little outwards below, to make it more ſecure againſt
                    ſtarting. The conſequence of this conſtruction is, that when the roof ſettles,
                    the ſhoulder comes to bear at the inner end of the mortiſe, and it riſes at the
                    outer, and the tenon taking hold of the wood beyond it, either tears ſt out or
                    is itſelf broken. This joint therefore is ſeldom trailed to the ſtrength of the
                    mortiſe and tenon, and is uſually ſecu-red by an iron ſtrap, which lies
                    obliquely to the beam, to which it is bolted by a large bolt quite through, and
                    then embraces the outſide of the rafter foot. Very frequently this ſtrap is not
                    made ſuſſiciently oblique, and we have ſeen ſome made almoſt ſquare with the
                    beam. When this is the caſe, it not only keeps the foot of the rafter from
                    flying out, but it binds it down. In this caſe, the rafter acts as a powerful
                    lever, whoſe fu}crum is the inner angle of the ſhoulder, and then the ſtrap
                    never fails to cripple the rafter at the point. All this can be prevented only
                    by making the ſtrap very long and very oblique, and by making its outer end (the
                    ſtirrup part) ſquare with its length, and making a notch in the rafter foot to
                    receive it. It cannot now cripple the rafter, for it will riſe along with it,
                    turning round</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r03-0477" facs="gri_33125011196389_0483.tif"/>
                <p>the bolt at its inner end. We have been thus particular on this joint, becauſe
                    it is here that the ultimate ſtrain of the whole roof is exerted, and its
                    ſituation will not allow the excavation neceſſary for making it a good mortiſe
                    and tenon.</p>
                <p>Similar attention muft be paid to ſome other ſtraps, ſuch as thoſe which embrace
                    the middle of the rafter, and connect it with the poſt or truſs below it. We
                    muſt attend to the change of ſhape produced by the ſagging of the roof, and
                    place the ſtrap in ſuch a manner as to yield to it by turning round its bolt,
                    but ſo as not to become looſe, and far leſs to make a fulcrum for any thing
                    acting as a lever. The ſtrains ariſing from ſuch actions, in framings of
                    carpentry which change their ſhape by ſagging, are enormous, and nothing can
                    reſiſt them.</p>
                <p>We ſhall cloſe this part of the ſubject with a Ample ï method, by which any
                    carpenter, without mathematical ſcience, may calculate with ſuſſicient preciſion
                    the ſtrains or thruſts which are produced on any point of</p>
                <p>his work, whatever be the obliquity of the pieces.</p>
                <p>Let it be required to find the horizontal thruſt acting on the tie-beam AD of
                    fig. 18. This will be the ſame as if the weight of the whole roof were laid at G
                    on the two rafters GA and GD. Draw the vertical linc GH. Then, having calculated
                    the weight of the whole roof that is ſupported by this ſingle frame ABCD,
                    including the weight of the pieces AB, BC, CD, BE, CF themſelves, take the
                    number of pounds, tons, &amp;c. which expreſſes it from any ſcale of equal
                    parts, and ſet it from G to H. Draw HK, HL parallel to GD, GA, and draw the line
                    KL, which will be horizontal when the two ſides of the roof have the ſame ſlope.
                    Then ML meaſured on the ſame ſcale will give the horizontal thruſt, by which the
                    ſtrength of the tie-beam is to be regulated. GL will give the thruſt which tends
                    to cruſh the rafters, and LM will alio give the force which tends to cruſh the
                    ſtrut-beam BC.</p>
                <p>In like manner, to find the ſtrain on the king-poſt BD of fig. 17. confider that
                    each brace is preſſed by half the weight of the roofing laid on BA or BC, and
                    this preſſure, or at leaſt its hurtful effect, is diminiſhed in the proportion
                    of BA to DA, becauſe the action of gravity is vertical, and the effect which we
                    want to counteract by the braces is in a direction E <hi rend="italic">e</hi> perpendicular to BA or BC. But as this is to be reſiſted by the brace ∕E acting
                    in the direction/E, we muſt draw <hi rend="italic">ſe</hi> perpendicular to E <hi rend="italic">e,</hi> and ſuppoſe the ſtrain augmented in the
                    proportion of E <hi rend="italic">e</hi> to Ey <hi rend="sup">r</hi> .</p>
                <p>Having thus obtained in tons, pounds, or other mea-ſures, the ſtrains which muſt
                    be balanced at /by the co-heſion of the king-poſt, take this meaſure fιom the
                    ſcale of equal parts, and ſet it off in the directions of the braces to G and H,
                    and complete the parallelogram G/HK; and ∕K meaſured on the ſame ſcale will be
                    the ſtrain on the king-poſt.</p>
                <p>The artiſt may then examine the ſtrength of his ■ truſs upon this principle,
                    that every ſquare inch of oak will bear at an average 7000 pounds compreſſing or
                    ſtretching it, and may be ſafely loaded with 3j00 for any length of time ; and
                    that a ſquare inch of fir will in like manner ſecurely bear 2500. And, becauſe
                    ſtraps are uſed to reſiſt ſome of theſe ſtrains, a ſquare inch of well wrought
                    tough iron may be ſafely ſtrained by 50,000 pounds. But the artiſt will always
                    recollect, that we cannot have the ſame confidence in iron as in timber. The
                    faults of this laſt are much more eafily perceived ; and when timber is too
                    weak, it gives us warning of its failure, by yielding ſenſibly before it breaks.
                    This is not the caſe with iron ; and much of its ſervice depends on the honeſty
                    of the blacſk-ſmith.</p>
                <p>In this way may any deſign of a roof be examined. We ſhall here give the reader
                    a ſketch of two or three truffed roofs, which have been executed in the chief
                    varieties of circumſtances which occur in common practice.</p>
                <p>Fig. 22. is the roof of St Paul’s Church, Covent Garden, London, the work of
                    Inigo Jones. Its conſtruction is ſingular. Tlιe roof extends to a conſiderable
                    diſtance beyond the building, and the ends of the tie-beams ſupport the Tuſean
                    corniche, appearing like the nιu-tules of the Doric order. Such a- roof could
                    not reft on the tie-beam. Inigo Jones has therefore ſupported it by a truſs
                    below it ; and the height has allowed him to make this extremely ſtrong with
                    very little timber. It is accounted the higheſt roof of its width in London. But
                    this was not difficult, by reaſon of the great height which its extreme width
                    allowed him to employ without hurting the beauty of it by too high a pitch. The
                    ſupports, however, are diſpoſed with judgment.</p>
                <p>Fig. 23. is a kirb or manſaid roof by Price, and ſuppoſed to be of large
                    dimenſions, having braces to carry the middle of the rafters.</p>
                <p>It will ſerve exceedingly well for a church having pillars. The middle part of
                    the tie-beam being taken away, the ſtrains are very well balanced, ſo that there
                    is no riſk of its puſhing alide the pillars on which it reſts.</p>
                <p>Fig. 24. is the celebrated roof of the theatre of the univerſityof Oxford, by
                    Sir Chriſtopher Wren. The ſpan between the walls is 75 feet. This is accounted a
                    very ingenious, and is a ſingular performance. The middle part of it is almoſt
                    unchangeable in its form; but from this· circumſtance it does not diſtribute the
                    horizontal thruſt with the ſame regularity as the uſual conſtruction. The
                    horizontal thruſt on the tie-beam is about twice the weight of the roof, and is
                    withſtood by an iron ſtrap below the beam, which ſtretches the whole width of
                    the building in the form of a rope, making part of the ornament of the ceiling.</p>
                <p>In all the roofs which we have conſidered hitherto the thruſt is diſcharged
                    entirely from the walls by the tie-beam. But this cannot always be done. We
                    frequently want great elevation within, and arched ceilings. In ſuch caſes, it
                    is a much more difficult matter to keep the walls free of all preſſure outwards,
                    and there are few buildings where it is completely done. Yet this is the
                    greateſt fault of a roof. We ſhall juſt point out the methods which may be molt
                    ſueceſsfully adopted.</p>
                <p>We have ſaid that a tie-beam juſt perſorms the office of a ſtring. We have ſaid
                    the ſame of the king-poſt. Now ſuppoſe two rafters AB, BC (fig. 25.} moveable
                    about the joint B, and reſting on the top of the walls. If the line BD be
                    ſuſpended from B, and the two lines DA, DC be faſtened to the feet of the
                    rafters, and if theſe lines be incapable of extenſion, it is plain that all
                    thruſt is removed from the walls as ef-</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r03-0478" facs="gri_33125011196389_0484.tif"/>
                <p>fectually as by a common tie-beam. A nd by ſhorten·· ing BD to B√, we gain a
                    greater infide height, and more room for an arched ceiling. Now if we
                    ſubfti-∙tute a king-poſt BD (fig. 26.) and two ſtretchers or hammer-beams DA, DC
                    for the other ſtrings, and connect them firmly by means of iron ſtraps, we
                    obtain our purpoſe.</p>
                <p>Let us compare this roof with a tie-beam roof in point of ſtrain and ſtrength.
                    Recur to fig. 25. and complete the parallelogram ABCF, and draw the diagonals
                    AC, BF croſſing in E. Draw BG perpendicular to CD. We have ſeen that the weight
                    of the root (which we may callW) is to the horizontal thruſt at C as B F to EC ;
                    and if we expreſs this thruſt by</p>
                <p>W × EC</p>
                <p>T, we have T = —p-p—. We may at preſent con-</p>
                <p>ſider BC as a lever moveable round the joint B, and pulled at C in the direction
                    EC by the horizontal thruſt, and held back by the ſtring pulling in the
                    direction CD. Suppoſe that the forces in the directions EC and CD are in
                    equihbrio, and let us find the force S by which the ſtring CD is ſtrained. Theſe
                    forces muſt (by the property of the lever) be inverſely as the perpendiculars
                    drawn from the centre of motion on the lines of their direction. Therefore BG :
                    BE = T : S,</p>
                <p><hi rend="sub">1</hi> _ „ BE <hi rend="sub">t</hi> BE.EC.</p>
                <p>and S _ Γ × <hi rend="sub">bg</hi> , _ W X <hi rend="sub">brbg</hi></p>
                <p>Therefore the ſtrain upon each of the ties DA and DC is always greater than the
                    horizontal thruſt or the ſtrain on a fimple tie-beam. This would be no great
                    inconvenience, becauſe the ſmalleſt dimenſions that we could give to theſe ties,
                    ſo as to procure ſufficient fixtures to the adjoining pieces, are always
                    ſufficient to wſthſtand this ſtrain. But although the ſame may be ſaid of the
                    iron ſtraps which make the ultimate connections, there is always ſome hazard of
                    imperfect work, cracks or flaws, which are not perceived. We can judge with
                    tolerable certainty of the ſoundneſs of a piece of timber, but cannot ſay ſo
                    much of a piece of iron. Moreover, there is a prodigious ſtrain excited on the
                    king-poſt, when BG is very ſhort in compariſon of BE, namely, the force
                    compounded of the two ſtrains 8 and S on the ties DA and DC.</p>
                <p>But there is another defect from which the ſtraight tie-beam is entirely free.
                    All roofs fettle a little.— When this roof ſettles, and the points B and D
                    de-ſcend, the legs BA, BC muſt ſpread further out, and thus a preſſure outwards
                    is excited on the walls. It is ieldom therefore that this kind of roof can be
                    executed in this ſimple form, and other contrivances are neceſſary for
                    counteracting this ſupervening action on the walls. Fig. 27. is one of the beſt
                    which we have ſeen, and is executed with great ſucceſs in the circus or
                    equeſtrian theatre in Edinburgh, the width being 60 feet. The pieces EF and ED
                    help to take off ſome of the weight, and by their greater uprightneſs they exert
                    a ſmaller thruſt on the walls. The beam D <hi rend="italic">d</hi> is alſo a
                    fort of truſs-beam, having fomething of the ſame effect. Mr Price has given
                    another very judicious one of this kind, Britiſh Carpenter, Plate IK, fig. C,
                    from which the tie-beam may be taken away, and there will remain very little
                    thruſt on the walls. Thoſe which he has given in the following Plate K are, in
                    our opinion, very faulty. The whole ſtrain in theſe laſt roofs tends to Break
                    the rafters and ties tranſverſely, and the fixtures-of the ties are alſo not
                    well calculated to refill the ſtrain to which the pieces are expoſed. W e
                    hardly think that theſe roofs could be executed.</p>
                <p>It is ſcarcely neceſſary to remind the reader, that in all that we have
                    delivered on this ſubject, we have at-1 tended only to the conſtruction of the
                    principal rafters or truſſes. In ſmall buildings all the rafters are of one kind
                    ; but in great buildings the whole weight of the covering is made to reſt on a
                    few principal rafters, which are connected by beams placed horizontally, and
                    either mortiſed into them or ſcarfed on them. Theſe are called <hi rend="italic"
                        > purlins.</hi> Small rafters are laid from purlin to purlin ; and on theſe
                    the laths for tiles, or the ſkirting-boards for liâtes, are nailed. Thus the
                    covering does not immediately reſt on the principal frames This allows ſome more
                    liberty in their conſtruction, becauſe the garrets can be ſo divided that the
                    principal rafters ſhall be in the partitions and the reſt left unincumbered.
                    This conſtruction is ſo ſar analogous to that of ſtoots which are conſtructed
                    with girders, binding, and bridge-ing joiſts.</p>
                <p>It may appear preſuming in us to queſtion the propriety of this practice. There
                    are ſituations in which it is unavoidable, as in the roofs of churches, which
                    can be allowed to reſt on ſome pillars. In other ſituations, where partition-w <hi rend="sup">,</hi> alls intervene at a diſtance not too great for a
                    ſtout purlin, no principal rafters are neceſſary, and the whole may be roofed
                    with ſhort rafters of very ſlender ſcantling. But in a great uniform roof, which
                    has no intermediate ſupports, it requires at leaſt ſome reafons for preferring
                    this method of carcaſe-roofing to the ſimpler method of making all the rafters
                    alike. The method of carcaſe-rooſing requires the {election of the greateſt logs
                    of timber, which are ſeldom of equal ſtrength and ſoundneſs with thinner
                    rafters. In theſe the outſide planks can be taken off, and the beſt part alone
                    worked up. It alſo expoſes to all the defects of workmanſhip in. the mortiſing
                    of pur-lins, and the weakening of the rafters by this very mortiſing ; and it
                    brings an additional load of purlins and ſhort rafters. A roof thus conſtructed
                    may ſurely be compared with a floor of limilar conſtruction. Here there is not a
                    ſhadow of doubt, that if the girders were ſawed into planks, and theſe planks
                    laid as joiſts ſuſſici-ently near for carrying the flooring boards, they will
                    have the ſame ſtrength as before, except ſo much as is taken out of the timber
                    by the ſaw. This will not amount to one-tenrh part of the timber in the binding,
                    bridging, and ceiling joiſts, which are an additional load ; and all the
                    mortiſes and other joinings are fo many diminutions of the ſtrength of the
                    girders ; and as no part of a carpenter’s w <hi rend="sup">τ</hi> ork requires
                    more ſkill and accuracy of execution, we are expoſed to many chances of
                    imperfection. But, not to reſt on theſe confidera-tions, however reafonable they
                    may appear, we ſhall relate an experiment made by one on whoſe judgment and
                    exactneſs we can depend.</p>
                <p>Two models of floors were made 18 inches ſquare of the ſineſt uniform deal,
                    which had been long lealoned. The one confiſted of ſimple joiſts, and the other
                    was framed with girders, binding, bridging, and ceiling joiſts. The plain joiſts
                    of the one contained the ſame quantity of tirA&gt;er with the girders alone
                    of the other, and both were made by a moſt accurate workman. They were placed in
                    wooden trunks 18 inches ſquare</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r03-0479" facs="gri_33125011196389_0485.tif"/>
                <p>within, and reſted on a ſtrong projection on the ιnfide. Small ſhot was
                    gradually poured in upon the floors, ſo as to ſpread uniformly over them. The
                    plain joiſted floor broke down with 487 pounds, and the carcaſe floor with 327.
                    The firſt broke without giving any warning ; the other gave a violent crack when
                    294 pounds had been poured in.</p>
                <p>A trial had been made before, and the loads were 341 and 482. But the
                    modelshaving been made by a leſs accurate hand, it was not thought a fair
                    ſpecimen of the ſtrength which might be given to a carcaſe floor.</p>
                <p>The only argument of weight which we can recollect in favour of the compound
                    conſtruction of roofs is, that the plain method would prodigiouſly increaſe the
                    quantity of work, would admit nothing but long timber, which would greatly add
                    to the expence, and would make the garrets a mere thicket of planks. We admit
                    this in its full force ; but we continue to be of the opinion that plain roofs
                    are greatly ſuperior in point of ſtrength, and therefore ſhould be adopted in
                    caſes where the great difficulty is to inſure this neceſſary circumſtance.</p>
                <p>It would appear very neglectful to omit an account of the roofs put on round
                    buildings, ſuch as domes, cupolas, and the like. They appear to be the moſt
                    difficult taſks in the carpenter art. But the difficulty lies entirely in the
                    mode of framing, or what the French call the <hi rend="italic">trait de
                        charpenterie.</hi> The view whiςh we are taking of the ſubject, as a part
                    of mechanical ſei-ence, has little connection with this. It is plain, that
                    whatever form of a truſs is excellent tn a ſquare building muſt be equally ſo as
                    one of the frames of a round one; and the only difficulty is how to manage their
                    mutual interſections at the top. Some ot them muſt be diſcontinued before they
                    reach that length, and common ſenſe will teach us to cut them ſhort alternately,
                    and always leave as many, that they may ſtand equally thick as at their firſt
                    ſpringing from the bale of the dome. Thus the length of the purlins which reach
                    from truſs to truſs will never be too great.</p>
                <p>The truth is, that a round building which gathers in at top, like a glaſs-houſe,
                    a potter’s kiln, or a ſpire ſteeple, inſtead of being the moſt difficult to
                    erect with liability, is of all others the eaſieſt. Nothing can ſhow this more
                    forcibly than daily practice, where they are run up without centres and without
                    ſcaffoldings ; and it requires groſs blunders indeed in the choice of their
                    outline to put them is much danger of falling from a want of equilibrium. In
                    like manner, a dome of carpentry can hardly fall, give it what ſhape or what
                    conſtruction you will. It <hi rend="italic">cannot</hi> fall unlèfs ſome part
                    of it flies out at the bottom : an iron hoop round it, or ſtraps at the joinings
                    of the truffes and purlins, which make an equivalent to a hoop, will effectually
                    ſecure it. And as beauty requires that a dome ſhall ſpring almoſt
                    perpendicularly from the wall, it is evident that there is hardly any thruſt to
                    force out the walls. The only part where this is to be guarded againſt is, where
                    the tangent is inclined about 40 or 50 degrees to the horizon. Here it will be
                    proper to make a courſe of firm horizontal joinings.</p>
                <p>We doubt not but that domes βf carpentry will now be raiſed of great extent. The
                    Halle du Bles at Paris, of 200 .feet in diameter, was.the invention of an
                    intelligent carpenter, the Sieur Moulιneau. He was not by any means a man of
                    ſcience, but had much more mechanical knowledge than artiſans uſually have, and
                    was convinced that a very thin ſhell of timber might not only be ſo ſhaped as to
                    be nearly in equilibrio, but that if hooped or firmly connected horizontally, it
                    would have all the ſtiffneſs that was neceſſary ; and he preſented his project
                    to the magiſtracy of Paris. The grandeur of it pleaſed them, but they doubted of
                    its poffibility. Being a great public work, they prevailed on the Academy of
                    Sciences to conſider it. The members, who were competent judges, were inſtantly
                    ſtruck with the juſtneſs of Mr Moulineau’s principles, and aſtoniſhed that a
                    thing ſo plain had not been long familiar to every houſe-carpenter. It quickly
                    became an univerſal topic of converſation, diipute, and cabal, in the polite
                    circles of Paris. But the Academy having given a very favourable report of their
                    opinion, the project was immediately carried into execution, and ſoon completed,
                    and now ſtands as one of the great exhibitions of Paris.</p>
                <p>The conſtruction of this dome is the ſimpleſt thing that can be imagined. The
                    circular ribs which com-poſe it conſiſt of planks nine feet long, 13 inches
                    broad, and three inches thick ; and each rib conſiſts of three of theſe planks
                    bolted together in ſuch a manner that two-joints meet. A rib is begun, for
                    inſtance, with a plank of three feet long ſtanding between one of fix feet and'
                    another of nine, and this is continued to the head of it. No machinery was
                    neceſſary for carrying up ſuch ſmall. pieces, and the whole went up like a piece
                    of bricklayer’s work. At various diſtances theſe ribs were con-nected
                    horizontally by purlins and iron ſtraps, which made ſo many hoops to the whole.
                    When the works had reached ſuch a height, that the diſtance of the ribs was
                    two-thirds of the original diſtance, every third rib was diſcontinued, and the
                    ſpace was left open and glazed. When carried ſe&gt; much higher that the
                    diſtance of the ribs is one-third, of the original diſtance, every ſecond rib
                    (now conliſting of tw <hi rend="sup">r</hi> o ribs very near each other) is in
                    like manner diſcontinued, and the void is glazed. A little above this the heads
                    of the ribs are framed into a circular ring of timber, which forms a wide
                    opening in the middle ; over which is a glazed canopy or umbrella, with an
                    opening between it and the dome for allowing the heated air to get out. All who
                    have ſeen this dome ſay, that it is the moſt beautiful and magnificent object
                    they have ever beheld.</p>
                <p>The only difficulty which occurs in the conſtruction of wooden domes is, when
                    they are unequally loaded, by caιτying a heavy lanthern or cupola in the.middle.
                    In ſuch a caſe, if the dome were a mere ſhell, it would be cruſhed in at the
                    trop, or the action of the wind on the lanthern might tear it out of its place.
                    Such a dome mult therefore conſiſt of trailed frames. Mr Price has given a very
                    good one in his plate OP, tho’ much ſtronger in the truffes than there was any
                    oc-cafion for. This cauſes a great loſs of room, and throw's the lights of the
                    lanthern too far up. It is evidently copied from Sir Chriſtopher Wren’s dome of
                    St Paul’s church in London ; a model of propriety in its particular ſituation,
                    but by no means a general model of a wooden dome. It reſts on the. brick cone
                    within it ; and Sir Chriſtopher has very ingeniouſly made uſe of it for
                    ſtifſening this cone, as any intelligent</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r03-0480" facs="gri_33125011196389_0486.tif"/>
                <p>perſon will perceive by attending to its conſtruction {See <hi rend="italic">Price,</hi> Plate OP).</p>
                <p>Fig. 28. repreſents a dome executed irι the Regiſter Office in Edinburgh by
                    James and Robert Adams, and is very agreeable to mechanical principles. The ſpan
                    is 50 feet clear, and the thickneſs is only 4⅛.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">We cannot take leave of the ſubject without taking ſome
                        notice of wlιat we have already ſpoken of with commendation by the name of</hi> <hi rend="italic">Norman roofs.</hi> We called them <hi rend="italic">Norman,</hi> becauſe they were frequently executed by that people ſoon after their
                    eſtabliſhment in Italy and other parts of the ſouth of Europe, and became the
                    prevailing taſte in all the great baronial caſ-tles. Their architects were
                    rivals to the Saracens and Moors, who about that time built many Chriſtiari
                    churches ; and the architecture which we now call Gothic ſeems to have ariſen
                    from their joint labours.</p>
                <p>The principle of a Norman roof is extremely ſimple. The rafters all butted on
                    joggled king-poſts AF, BG, CH, &amp;c. (fig. 29.), and braces or ties were
                    then diſpoſed in the intervals. In the middle of the roof HB and HD are
                    evidently ties in a ſtate of extenſion, while the poſt CH is compreſſed by them.
                    Towards the walls on each ſide, as between B and F, and between F and L, they
                    are braces, and are compreſſed. The ends of the poſts were generally ornamented
                    with knots of flowers, emboſſed globes, and the like, and the whole texture of
                    the truſs was exhibited and dreſſed out.</p>
                <p>This conſtruction admits of employing very ſhort timbers; and this very
                    circumſtance gives greater ſtrength to the truſs, becauſe the angle which the
                    brace or tie makes with the rafter is more open. We may alſo perceive that all
                    thruſt may be taken off the walls. If the pieces AF, BF, LF, be removed, all the
                    remaining diagonal pieces act as ties, and the pieces directed to the centre act
                    as ſtruts ; and it may alſo be obſerved, that the principle will apply equally
                    to a ſtraight or flat roof or to a floor. A floor ſuch as <hi rend="italic">a
                        be,</hi> having the joint in two pieces <hi rend="italic">a b, be,</hi> with a ſtrut <hi rend="italic">bd,</hi> and two ties, will require a much
                    greater weight to break it than if it had a continued joiſt <hi rend="italic">a
                        c</hi> of the ſame ſcantling. And, laſtly, a piece of timber acting as a
                    tie is much ſtronger than the ſame piece acting as a ſtrut : for in the latter
                    ſituation it is expoſed to bending, and when bent it is much leſs able to
                    withſtand a very great ſtrain. It muſt be acknowledged, however, that this
                    advantage is balanced by the great inferiority of the joints in point of
                    ſtrength. The joint of a tie depends wholly on the pins ; for this reaſon ties
                    are never uſed in heavy works without ſtrapping the joints with iron. In the
                    roofs we are now deſcribing the diagonal pieces of the middle part only act
                    purely as ties, while thoſe towards the ſides act as ſtruts or braces. Indeed
                    they are ſeldom of ſo very ſimple conſtruction as we have deſcribed, and are
                    more generally conſtructed like the ſketch in ſig. 30. having two ſets of
                    rafters AB, <hi rend="italic">a b,</hi> and the angles are filled up with thin
                    planks, which give great ſtiffneſs and ſtrength. They have alſo a doublé ſet of
                    purlins, which connect the different truffes. The roof being thus divided into
                    ſquares, other purlins run between the middle points E of the rafters. The
                    rafter is ſupported at E by a check put between it and the under rafter. The
                    middle point of each ſquare of the roof is ſupported and ſtiffened by four
                    braces, one of which ſprings from <hi rend="italic">e,</hi> and its oppoſite
                    from the ſi-milar part of the adjoining truſs. The other two braces ſpring from
                    the middle points of the lower purlins, which go horizontally from <hi
                        rend="italic"> a</hi> and <hi rend="italic">b</hi> to the next truſs, and
                    are ſupported by planks in the ſame manner as the rafters. By this contrivance
                    the whole becomes very ſtiff and ſtrong.</p>
                <p>We hope that the reader will not be diſpleaſed with &lt; our having taken
                    ſome notice of what was the pride of our anceſtors, and conſtitnted a great part
                    of the finery of the grand hall, where the feudal lord aſſembled his vaffals and
                    diſplayed his magnificence. The intelligent mechanic will ſee much to commend ;
                    and all who look at theſe roofs admire their apparent flimſy lightneſs, and
                    wonder at their duration. We have ſeen a hall of 57 feet wide, the roof of which
                    Was in four diviſions, like a kirb roof, and the truffes were about 1 <hi
                        rend="italic"> 6</hi> feet aſunder. They were ſingle rafters, as in fig.
                    30. and their dimenſions were only eight inches by fix. The roof appeared
                    perfectly found, and had been ſtanding ever ſince the year 1425.</p>
                <p>Much of what has been ſaid on this ſubject may be applied to the conſtruction of
                    wooden bridges and the centres for turning the arches of ſtone-bridges. But the
                    farther diſcuſſion of this muſt be the employment of another article.</p>

            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
