<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r02-0315-02" facs="gri_33125011196389_0321.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>ROCK</label>
a large maſs or block of hard ſtone rooted</p><p>in the ground. See Mountain, Petrifaction, and Stone.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Rock, in ornithology, a ſpecies of Vulture.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps"> Rock Baſons</hi></hi> are cavities or artificial baſons of diffe</p><p>rent ſizes, from ſix feet to a few inches diameter, cut in the ſurface <hi rend="italic">of</hi> the rocks for the purpoſe, as is ſuppoſed, of collecting the dew and rain pure as it de-ſcended ſrom the heavens, for the uſe of ablutions and purifications, preſcribed in the druidieal religion; theſe, eſpecially the dew, being deemed the pureſt of all</p>
<pb xml:id="eb03-16-r02-0316" facs="gri_33125011196389_0322.tif"/>
<p>fluids. There are two ſorts of theſe baſons, one with lips pr communications between the different baſons, the other ſimple cavities. The lips as low as the bottom of the baſons, which are horizontal, and communicate with one ſomewhat lower, ſo contrived that the contents ſell by a gradual deſcent through a ſucceſſion of baſons either to the ground, or into a veiſel ſet to receive it. The baſons without lips might be intended for reſervoirs to preſerve the rain or dew in its original purity without touching any other veſſel, and was perhaps uſed for the druid to drink, or waſh his hands, previous to officiating at any high ceremony, or elſe to mix with their miſletoe.</p><p>Some of theſe baſons are ſo formed as to receive the head and part of the human body ; one of this kind is found on a rock called king Arthur’s bed, in the pariſh of North Hall in Cornwall, where are alſo others, called by the country people Arthur’s troughs, in which they ſay he uſed to feed his dogs.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Rocκ-Cryſtal,</hi> in natural hiſtory, otherwiſe called <hi rend="italic">ſprig-cryſtal,</hi> a name given to the third order of cryſtals, from their being affixed to a rock or other ſolid body. •See Crystal.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Rock Salt.</hi> See Salt.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Rock-Oil.</hi> See Petroleum.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Rocκ-Fiſh.</hi> See Gobius.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>