<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r02-0323-02" facs="gri_33125011196389_0329.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>ROLLO</label>
the conqueror of Normandy, was a Norwegian duke, baniſhed from his country by Harold Harfagre, who conquered Norway in 870, on account -of the piracies he exerciſed. He firſt retired with his fleet among the iſlands of the Hebrides to the north-weſt of Scotland, whither the flower of the Norwegian nöbility had fled for refuge «ver ſince Harold had become maſter of the whole kingdom. He was there received with open arms by thoſe warriors, who, eager for conq,ueft and revenge, waited only for a chief to undertake ſome glorious enterpriſe. Rollo ſetting himſelf at their head, and ſeeing his power formidable, ſailed towards England, which had been long as it were a field open on all ſides ito the violence of the northern nations. But the great Alfred had ſome years before eſtabliſhed ſuch order in his part of the iſland, that Rollo, after ſeveral fruitleſs attempts, de-ſpaired of forming there ſuch a ſettlement as ſhould make him amends for the loſs of his own country. He pretended, therefore, to have had a ſupematural dream, which promiſed him a glorious fortune in France, and which ſerved at leaſt to ſupport the ardour of his followers. The weakntſs of die government in that; kingdom, and the confuſion in which it was involved, were ſtill moιe perſuaſive reaſons to inſure them of ſucceſs. Having therefore failed up the Seine to Rouen, he immediately took that capital of the province, then called <hi rend="italic">Neu/lria,</hi> and making it his magazine of arms, he advanced up to Paris, to which he laid ſiege in form. This war at length ended in the entire cefiiαn of Neuſtria, which Charles the Simple was obliged to give up to Rollo and his Normans in order to purchaſe a peace. Rollo received it in perpetuity to himſelf and his poſterity, as a feudal duchy dependant on the crown of France. A deſcription of the interview between Charles and this new duke gives us a curious picture of the manners of theſe Normans (as they were called by foreigners) ; for the latter would not take the oath of fealty to his ſovereign lord any other way than by placing his hands within thoſe of the king ; and abſolutely refiiſed to kiſs his feet, as cuſtom then required. It was with great difficulty he was prevailed on to let one of his warriors perform this ceremony in his ſtead ; but the officer to whom Rollo deputed, this ſervice, ſuddenl.y raiſed the king’s foot ſo high, that he overturned him on his back ; a piece of rudeneſs which was only laughed at; to ſuch a degree were the Normans feared, and Charles deſpiſed.</p><p>Soon after* Rollo was perſuaded to embrace Chriſti-anity, and hc was baptized with much ceremony by the archbiſhop of Rouen in the cathedral of that city. As foθH as he ſaw himſelf in full poſſeſſion of Normandy, he exhibited ſuch virtues as rendered the province happy, and deſerved to make his former outrages forgotten. Religious, wiſe, and liberal, this captain of pirates became, after Alfred, the greateſt and moſt humane prince of his time- ' <hi rend="sub">;</hi></p>
</div></body></text></TEI>