<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r02-0311-01" facs="gri_33125011196389_0317.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>ROBINSON</label>
(the moſt Rev. Sir Richard), archbiſhop of Armagh and Lord Rokeby, was immediately deſeended from the Robinſons of Rokeby in the North Riding of the county of York, and was born in 1709. He was educated at Weſtminſter ſchool, from whence he was elected to Chriſt-Church, Oxford, in 1726. After continuing his ſtudies there the uſual time, Doctor Blackburne, archbiſhop of York, appointed him his. chaplain, and collated him firſt to the rectory of Elton, in the Eaſt Riding of Yorkſhire, and next to the prebend of Grindal, in the cathedral of York. In 1751 he attended the Duke of Dorſet, lord-lieutenant of Ireland, to that kingdom, as his firſt chaplain, and the ſame year was promoted to the biſhopric of Killala. A. family connection with the Earl of Holderneffe, who was ſecretary of ſtate that year, with the Earl of Sandwich and other noblemen related to him, opened the faireſt proſpects of attaining to the firſt dignity in the Iriſh church. Accordingly in 1759 he was tranſlated to the united fees of Leighlin and Ferns, and in 1761 to Kildare. The Duke of Northumberland being appointed to the lieutenancy of Ireland in 1765, he was advanced to the primacy of Armagh, made lord-almoner, and vice-chancellor of the univerlity of Dublin. When Lord Harcourt was lord-lieutenant of Ireland in 1777, the king was phaſed by privy-ſeal at St James’s, February 6th, and by patent at Dublin the 26th of the ſame month, to create him Baron Rokeby of Armagh, with remainder to Matthew Robinſon of Weil Layton, Eſq; and in j 783 he was appointed prelate to the moſt illuſtrious order of St Patrick. On the death of the Duke of Rutland lord-lieutenant of Ireland in 1787, he was nominated one of the lords-juſtices of that kingdom. Sir William Robinſon, his brother, dying in 1785, the primate ſucceeded to the title of baronet, and is the ſurvivor in the direct male, line of the Robinſons of Rokeby, being the 8th in de-ſeent from William of Kendal. His grace died at Clifton near Briſtol in the end of October 1794.</p><p>No primate ever ſat in the ſee of Armagh who watched more carefully over the intereſt of the church of Ireland, as the ſtatute-book evinces. The act of the</p>
<pb xml:id="eb03-16-r02-0312" facs="gri_33125011196389_0318.tif"/>
<p>I τtil and 12th of his preſent majeſty, which ſecures to biſhops and eccleſiaſtical perſons repayment by their ſuc-ceſſors of expenditures in purchaſing glebes and houſes, or building new houſes, originated from this excellent man, and muſt ever endear his name to the clergy. The other acts for repairing churches, and facilitating the recovery of eccleſiaſtical dues, were among the many happy exertions of the primate.</p><p>But it was at Armagh, the ancient ſeat of the primacy, that he diſplayed a princely munificence. A very elegant palace, 90 feet by 60, and 40 high, adorns that town ; it is light and pleaſing, without the addi-tion*of wings or leſſer parts; which too frequently wanting a ſufficient uniformity with the body of the edifice, are unconnected with it in effect, and divide thé attention. Large and ample offices are conveniently placed behind a plantation at a ſmall diſtance. Around the palace is a large lawn, which ſpreads on every ſide over the hills, ſhirted by young plantations, in one of which is a terrace, which commands a moſt beautiful view of cultivated hill and dale ; this view from the palace is much improved by the barracks, the ſchool, and a new church at a diſtance ; all which are ſo placed as to be exceedingly ornamental to the whole country’.</p><p>The barracks were erected under the primate’s direction, and form a large and handſome edifice. The ſchool is a building of conſiderable extent, and admirably adapted for the purpoſe ; a more beautiful or better contrived one is nowhere to be ſeen ; there are apartments for a maſter, a ſchool-room 56 feet by 28, a large dining room and ſpacious airy dormitories, with every other neceſſary, and a ſpacious play-ground walled in ; the whole forming a handſome fιont : and attention being paid to the reſidence of the maſter (the ſalary is 400l. a year), the ſchool flouriſhes, and muſt prove one of the greateſt advantages to the country. This edifice was built entirely at the primate’s expence. The church is erected of white ſtone, and having a tall ſpire, makes a very agreeable object, in a country where churches and ſpires do not abound. The primate built three other churches, and made conſiderable reparations to the cathedral ; he was alſo the means of erecting a public infirmary, contributing amply to it himſelf : he likewiſe conſtructed a public library at his own coſt, endowed it, and gave it a large collection of books ; -the room is 45 feet by 25, and 20 high, with a gallery and apartments for the librarian. - The town he ornamented with a mai ket-houſe and ſhambles, and was the direct means, by giving leaſes upon that condition, of 'almoſt new-building the whole place. He found it a neſt of mud cabins, and he left it a well-built city of ſtone and date. Theſe are noble and ſpirited works, in which the primate expended not leſs than L. 30,0c0. Had this ſum been laid out in improving a paternal eſtate, even then they would be deſerving great praiſe ; but it is not for his poſterity but the public good that his grace was ſo munificest. A medal was ſtruck by the ingenious William Moſſop of Dublin, which has on one ſide the head of the primate, inſcribed “ Richard Robinſon, Baron Rokeby, Lord Pιimate of all Ireland.” And on the reverſe, the ſouth front of the obſervatory at Armagh, erected by his grace, with this admirable motto, “ The Heavens declare the glory of God.” MDCCLXXXIX.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Robinson (Robert), a diſſenting miniſter of conſi</hi></p><p>derable note, was born on the 8th of October I7 35 at Swaffham in Norfolk. His father died when he was young ; and his maternal grandfather Robert Wilkin, of Milden-hall, Suffolk, gent, who had ever been diſſa-tisſied with his daughter’s marriage, deprived him of bis maternal inheritance, cutting him off with half-a-guinea. His uncle, however, who was a ſubſtantial farmer, in ſome meaſure ſupplied this loſs. He took Mr Robinſon home, and placed him under the Rev. Joſeph Brett, at Seaming ſchool in Norfolk, with a view to the miniſtry of the church of England ; where he had for one of his ſchool-ſellows the lord chancellor Thurlow. When about the age of 1 ç or 16, h»e imbibed the notions of George Whitfield ; on which account he was diſcarded by his uncle, and again expoſed to poverty and want. He firſt directed his thoughts towards the miniſtry in the year 1754, and commenced preacher in the following year at the age of 20; preaching his firſt ſermon to a congregation of poor people at Milden-hall. He continued for a year or two as one of Mr Whitfield’s preachers, and during that period he married. In the year 1758, however, he determined to ſeparate from the Methodiſts ; after which he ſettled at Norwich with a ſmall congregation formed chiefly of his methodiſtic friends, being at that time an Independent. In the year 1759 he was invited to Cambridge, and for two years preached on trial to a congregation conſiſting of no more than 34 people, and ſo poor that they could only raiſe L. 3 : 6 : o a quarter for his ſub-ſiſtence. In June 1761 he ſettled as their paſtor, and was ordained in the uſual manner; at which time we are told he exerciſed the office of a barber. In 1774, his congregation had ſo much increaſed as to conſiſt of 1000 ſouls, including children and ſervants.</p><p>In Cambridge Mr Robinſon’s talents ſoon attracted notice, and he quickly ſet up a Sunday evening lecture, which was well attended. His preaching was altogether without notes ; a method in which he was peculiarly happy : not by trufting to his memory entirely, nor by working himſelf up to a degree of warmth and paſſion, to which the preachers among whom he firſt appeared commonly owe their ready utterance ; but by thoroughly ſtudying and making himſelf perfectly maſter of his ſubject, and a certain faculty of expreſſion which is never at a loſs for ſuitable and proper words. In ſhort, his manner was admirably adapted to enlighten the underſtanding, and to affect and reform the heart. He had ſuch a plainneſs of ſpeech, ſuch an eaſy and apparent method in dividing a diſcourſe, and ſuch a familiär way of reaſoning, as diſcovered an heart filled with the tendereſt concern for the meaneſt of his hearers ; and yet there was a decency, propriety, and juſt-neſs, that the moſt judicious could not but approve. Several gentlemen of the univerlity, eminent for character and abilities, we are told, were his conſtant hearers.</p><p>The circumſtances which loſt him his uncle’s patronage paved the way for the future events of his liſe. The incident which made him diſcard the common ſentiments· on the ſeſhject of baptiſm, at once marked the turn of his mind, and ſhows what apparently flight cauſes frequently determine the lot and uſefuln-eſs of our lives. He was invited to the baptiſm of a child ; the miniſter who was to perform the ſervice keeping the company in long expectation of his appearance, ſome</p>
<pb xml:id="eb03-16-r02-0313" facs="gri_33125011196389_0319.tif"/>
<p>one ſuggeſted, that ſuppoſing the child were not baptized at all, he ſaw not how it could affect his happi-neſs. Though the converſation was not purſued, the hint ſtruck Mr Robinſon’s mind ; and he immediately determined to read the New Teſtament with this particular view, to examine what it ſaid concerning the baptiſm of infants. He accordingly began with the Goſpel of Matthew ; and, in ſucceſſion, peruſed the hiſtorical and epiſtolary books ; in expectation that he ſſiould find in every following part what he had not met with in the preceding parts of the ſacred volume ; namely, paſſages recommending and urging this rite. But obſerving, on the whole, a total ſilence about it, he thought it his duty to relinquiſh the practice, as without foundation in the rule of our faith ; which appeared to him to ſpeak only of the baptiſm of believers.</p><p>This change of his ſentiments was more unfavourable than the former alterations in his religious judgment to bis worldly views ; and having married very early in life from pure affection, he was involved in great difficulties for near 12 years after his ſettlement in Cambridge ; as, in that courſe of time, his family became numerous, and the ſupport of an aged mother, as well as of a wife and ten children, depended upon him. But unexpected ſupplies, from quarters of which he was ignorant, frequently relieved his neceſſities, and confirmed his truſt in Providence : yet the ſituation of his family muſt, it is eaſy to conceive, have much affected his mind. For he appears to have poſſeſſed great tenderneſs and ſenſibility, and to have regarded with peculiar endearment his domeſtic connections.</p><p>It may be reckoned a circumſtance worthy of mention, that the ſphere of Mr Robinſon’s miniſtry was the ſame in which his great-grandfather Mr Shelly, of Jeſus College, and vicar of All-Saints, had, with others, diſſuſed the principles of the Puritans, about the beginning of the laſt century. The reputation of the Diffen-ters in the univerſity and neighbourhood had for almoſt a century been linking into contempt, when Mr Robinſon ſettled with the baptiſt church at Stone-Yard. <hi rend="sup">z</hi> His abilities and aſſiduity, however, raiſed their reputation. The place in which his people aſſembled, which was at firſt a barn, afterwards a ſtable and granary, and then a meeting-houſe, but ſtill a damp, dark, and ruinous place, ſoon became too ſmall for the audience ; and ſeveral of the new auditors being men of fortune, they purchaſed the fite, and erected at their own expence a new houſe in the year 1764.</p><p>His labours as a preacher were not limited to the town of Cambridge ; but ſoon after bis coming there, he ſet up ſeveral lectures in the adjacent villages. His lectures were either annual or occaſional, or ſtated on fixed days. The uſual time was half an hour after fix in the evening ; and ſometimes at five in the morning ; and now and then in the ſummer at two in the afternoon, for the ſake of thoſe who came from a diſtance.</p><p>He died on the 9th of June 1790, at the houſe of William Ruſſel,Eſq;of Showell green near Birmingham. He had laboured under an alarming diſorder for ſome time before; but on the Sunday preceding his death he preached a charity ſermon. On Monday he was ſeized with a fit ; on Tueſday he recovered and went to bed tolerably well, and was found dead next morning.</p><p>The abilities of Mr Robinſon were very conſiderable, as appears from his numerous works ; and he poſſeſſed</p><p>the quality of expreſſing his thoughts in an eaſy and a forcible manner. But he appears to have been of an unſteady temper, and, in our opinion, acquires but little credit either from the frequency with which he changed his religious creed (for we have reaſon to believe he died a Socinian), or from the fooliſh and undeſerved acrimony with which he treated the Church of England. His Plan of Lectures on the Principles of Nonconformity, for the Inſtruction of Catechumens, is a piece of the moſt unjuſt and illiberal abuſe that we have ever ſeen, and would have diſgraced the moſt high flying Puritan of the laſt century.</p><p>Mr Robinſon’s largeſt work, the Hiſtory of Baptiſm and of the Baptiſts, was publiſhed ſince his death, and is written in the ſame ſtyle and with the ſame confidence as his other works. Yet, as we have heard it remarked by a learned and liberal profeſſor of Theology in the church which he oppoſed, it is not a little remarkable that there is in it no argument or fact againſt infant baptiſm which was not anſwered by Dr Wall nearly 100 years ago, of whoſe arguments Mr Robinſon however takes no notice.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>