<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r02-0314-02" facs="gri_33125011196389_0320.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>ROCHELLE</label>
a celebrated city of France, capital of the territory of Aunis, with a very commodious and ſale harbour, which, though it does not admit veſſels of any conſiderable burden, is yet well calculated for trade. <hi rend="sup">il</hi> It may be divided (ſays Mr Wraxal) into three parts ; the baſon, which is the innermoſt of theſe, is only a quarter of a mile in circumference ; and at the entrance are two very noble Gothic towers, called the Tower de St Nicholas, and the Tour de la Chaîne. They are now in a ſtate of decay, but were anciently deſigned to protect the town and harbour. Without theſe towers is the Avant Port, extending more than a league, and bounded by two points of land to the north and ſouth. Beyond all is the road where the largeſt ſhips uſually anchor, protected from the ſouth-weſt winds by the iſlands of Re, Oleron, and Aix.” The celebrated mound erected by Richlieu extends from ſide to ſide acroſs the whole harbour, nearly an Engliſh mile in length, and when the ſea retires is ſtill vilible. “ I walked out upon it (ſays Mr Wraxal) above 300 feet. Its breadth is at this time more than 150 ſeet, and it. widens continually towards the baſe. No effort of art or power can poſſibly impreſs the mind with ſo vaſt and lublime an idea of the genius of Richlieu, as does this bulwark againſt the ſea. While I ſtood upon it, in the middle of the port, between the waves which rolled on either ſide, and contemplated its extent and ſtrength, I was almoſt inclined to ſuppoſe this aſtoniſhing work to be ſuperior to human power, and the production rather of a deity than of a mortal. A ſmall opening of about 200 ſeet was left by Pompey Targon, the architect who conſtructed it, to give entrance to veſſels, and ſhut up by chains fixed acroſs it. A tower was likewiſe erect-ed at each end, no remains of which are now to be ſeen. Neither the duke'of Buckingham, nor the earl of Lindſey, who were ſucceſſively ſent from England to the aid of the beſieged by Charles the Firſt, dared to attack this formidable barrier : they retired, and left Rochelle to its fate. In all probability, a thouſand years, aided by ſtorms and all the fury of the ſea, will make little or no impreſſion on this mound, which is deſigned to endure as long as the fame of the Cardinal, its author.”</p><p>Before the revolution, Rochelle was a biſhop’s ſee, and contained a college of humanities, an academy, a ſchool for medicine, anatomy, and botany, and a mint. It cannot lay claim to any remote antiquity, being merely a little collection of houſes on the ſhore, inhabited by fiſhermen, when William IX. laſt count of Poictou, rendered himſelf maſter of it in 1139. From this Prince it deſeended to his only daughter Eleanor, afterwards queen of Henry II. of England ; and her charter incorporating the town is ſtill preſerved in the • regiſters of the city. In the year 1540, Rochelle was the grand aſylum of the Proteſtants ; and the maſſacre at Paris was ſoon followed by the ſiege of Rochelle, which began in November 1572, and was raiſed in June 1573; but in 1628, after a moſt obſtinate reſiſtance, ∣uιd a ſiege of 13 months, it ſurrendered to</p>
<pb xml:id="eb03-16-r02-0315" facs="gri_33125011196389_0321.tif"/>
<p>the mercy of Louis XIII.. At the beginning of the firſt ſiege, the number of inhabitants in the city amounted to 72,000 ; in the ſecond they diminiſhed to 28,000 ; and they were, when Mr Wraxal was there, between 17 and 18,000, of which ſcarce 2000 were Huguenots. The houſes of this city are fine, and ſupported with piazzas, under which perſons may walk in all weathers ; and the ſtreets in general are as ſtraight as a line. There ate ſeveral handſome churches, and other ſtructures, beſides a remarkable pump in the ſquare of Dauphiny, which throws out the water through ſeveral pipes. There are no remains of the old fortifications, except on the ſide of the harbour, where there are bulwarks and ſtrong towers to defend the entrance. The new fortifications are in the manner of Vauban. Before Canada was ceded to England·, and New Orleans to Spain, the trade of Rochelle was very lucrative. It revived about the year 1773, and, beſide that to the coaſt of Guinea and the Eaſt Indies, the inhabitants carried on a conſiderable trade in wines, brandy, fait, paper, linen cloth, and ſerge. It is ſeated on the ocean, in W. Long. 1. it. N. Lat. 46. 10.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>