<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r02-0235-01" facs="gri_33125011196389_0241.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>RICHLIEU</label>
(John Armand du Pleſſis de), cardinal of Richlieu and Fronſac, biſhop of Lucon, &amp;c. was born at Paris in 1585. He was of excellent parts ; and at the age of 2 2 had the addref3 to obtain a diſpen ∙ ſation to enjoy the biſhopric of Lucon in 1607. Returning into France, he applied himſelf in a particular manner to the function of preaching ; and his reputation this way procured him the office of almoner to the queen Mary de Medicis. His abilities in the management of affairs advanced him to be ſecretary of ſtate in 1616 ; aftd the king ſoon gave him the preference to all his other ſecretaries. The death of the marquis d’Ancre having produced a revolution in ſtate affairs, Richlieu retired to Avignon ; where he employed himſelf in compoſing books of controverſy and piety. The king having recalled him to court, he was made a cardinal in 1622 ; and, two years after, firſt miniſter of ſtate, and grand maſter of the navigation. In 1626, the iſle of Rhée was preſerved by his care, and Rochelle taken, having ſtopped up the haven by that famous dyke which he ordered to be made there. He accompanied the king to the ſiege of Cazal, and contributed not a little to the raiſing of it in 1629. He alſo obliged the Huguenots to the peace at Akts, which proved the ruin of that party ; he took Pamerol, and ſuccoured Cazal be-ſieged by Spinola. In the mean time the nobles found fault with his conduct, and perſuaded the king to diſ-card him. The cardinal, for his part, was unmoved with it ; and by his reaſonings overthrew what was thought to be determined againſt him ; ſo that, inſtead of being diſgraced, he from that moment became more powerful than ever. He puniſhed all his enemies in the ſame manner as they would have had him ſuffer ; and the day which produced this event, ſo glorious to cardinal Richlieu, was called the <hi rend="italic">day of dupes.</hi> This able miniſter had from thenceforwards an aſcendancy over the king’s mind ; and he now reſolved to humble the exceſſive pride of the houſe of Auſtria. For that purpoſe he concluded a treaty with Guſtaphus Adolphus king of Sweden, for carrying the war into the heart of Germany. He alſo entered into a league with the duke of Bavaria ; ſecured Lorrain ; railed a part of the princes of the empire againſt the emperor ; treated with the Dutch to continue the war againſt Spain ; favoured the Catalans and Portugueſe till they ſhook off the Spaniſh yoke ; and, in ſhort, took ſo many different meaſures, that he accompliſhed his deſign ; and after having carried on the war with ſucceſs, was thinking of concluding it by a peace, when he died at Paris on the 4th of December 1642, aged 58. He was interred in the Sorbonne, where a magnificent mauſoleum is erected to his memory. This great politician made the arts and ſciences flouriſh; formed the botanical garden at Paris, called the <hi rend="italic">kings garden ;</hi> founded the French academy ; eſtabliſh-ed the royal printingſhouſe ; erected the palace afterwards called <hi rend="italic">Le Palais Royal,</hi> which he preſented to the king; and rebuilt the Sorbonne with a magnificence that appears truly royal. Beſides his books of controverſy and piety, there go under the name of this miniſter, A Journal, in 2 vols 12mo ; and a Political Teſtament, in 12mo ; all treating of politics and ſtate affairs. Cardi∙</p>
<pb xml:id="eb03-16-r02-0236" facs="gri_33125011196389_0242.tif"/>
<p>nal Mazarine purſued Richlieu’s plan, and completed many of the ſchemes which he had begun, but left unfi-niſhed.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>