<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r02-0248-08" facs="gri_33125011196389_0254.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>RIOT</label>
in law. The riotous aſſembling of 12 perſons, or more, and not diſperfing upon proclamation, w <hi rend="sup">,</hi> as ſir ſt made high treaſon by ſtatute 3' &amp; 4 Edw∖ VI. c. 5. when the king was a minor, and a change of religion to be effected.: but that ſtatute was repealed by ſtatute I Mar. c. 1. among the other treaſens created ſince the 25 Edw, III. ; though the prohibition was in ſubſtance re-enacted, with an inferior degree of puniſh-ment, by ſtatute 1 Mar. ſt. 2. c. 12. which made the ſame offence a ſingle felony. Theſe ſtatutes ſpecified and particularized the nature of the riots they were meant to ſuppreſs ; as, for example, ſuch as were ſet on foot with intention to offer violence to the privy-council, or to change the laws of the kingdom, or for certain other ſpecific purpeſes ; in which caſes, if the perſons were commanded by proclamation to diſperſe, and they did not, it was by the ſtatute of Mary made ſelony, but within the benefit of clergy ; and alſo the act indemnified the peace-officers and their affiliants, if they killed any of the mob in endeavouring to ſuppreſs ſuch riot. This was thought a neceſſary ſecurity in that ſanguinary reign, when popery was intended to be re-eſtabliſhed, which was like to produce great diicontents : but at firſt it was made only ſor a year, and w <hi rend="sup">,</hi> as afterwards continued for that queen’s life. And, by ſtatute 1 Eliz. c. 16. when a reformation in religion was to be once more attempted, it w <hi rend="sup">,</hi> as revived and continued during her life alſo ; and then expired. From the acceſſion of James I. to the death of Queen Anne, it was never once thought expedient to ιevive it ; but, in the firſt year of George I. it was judged neceſſary, in order to ſupport the execution of the act of ſettlement, to renew it, and at one ſtroke to make it perpetual, with large additions. For, whereas the former acts expreſsly defined and ſpecified what ſhould be accounted a riot, the ſtatute 1 Geo. I. c. 5. enacts, generally, that if any 12 perſons are unlawfully aſſembled to the diſtutbance of the peace, and any one juſtice of the peace, ſheriff, under ſheriff, or mayor of a town, ſhall think proper to command them by proclamation to diſperſe, if they contemn his orders and continue together for one hour afterw <hi rend="sup">τ</hi> ards, ſuch contempt ſhall be felony without benefit of clergy. And farther, if the reading of the proclamation be by force oppoſed, or the reader be in any manner wilfully</p>
<pb xml:id="eb03-16-r02-0249" facs="gri_33125011196389_0255.tif"/>
<p>hindered from the reading of it, ſuch opρofers and hin-derers are felons without benefit of clergy ; and all perſons to whom ſuch proclamation <hi rend="italic">ought to have been made,</hi> and knowing of ſuch hindrance, and not diſ-perſing, are felons without benefit of clergy. There is the like indemnifying clauſe, in caſe any of the mob be unfortunately killed in the endeavour to diſperſe them ; being copied ſrom the act of queen Mary. And by a fubſequent clauſe of the new act, if any perſon, ſo riotouſly aſſembled, begin even before proclamation to pull down any church, chapel, meeting-houſe, dwell-ing-houſe, or out-houſes, they ſhall be felons without benefit of clergy.</p><p>Riots, routs, and unlawful aſſemblies, muſt have three perſons at leaſt to conſtitute them. An <hi rend="italic">unlawful af-ſembly</hi> is, when three, or more, do aſſemble themſelves together to do an unlawful act, as to pull down incloſures, to deſtroy a warren or the game therein ; and part without doing it, or making any motion towards it. A <hi rend="italic">rout</hi> is where three or more meet to do an unlawful act upon a common quarrel, as forcibly breaking down fences upon a right claimed of common, or of way, and make ſome advances towards it. A <hi rend="italic">riot</hi> is where three or more actually do an unlawful act of violence, either with or without a common cauſe or quarrel ; as if they beat a man ; or hunt and kill game in another’s park, chaſe, warren, or liberty ; or do any other unlawful act with force and violence ; or even do a lawful act, as removing a nuiſance, in a violent and tumultuous manner. The puniſhment of unlawful aſſemblies, if to the number of 12, we have juſt now ſeen, may be capital, according to the circumſtances that attend it ; but, ſrom the number of three to eleven, is by fine and impriſonment only. The ſame is the caſe in riots and routs by the common law ; to which the pillory in very enormous caſes has been ſometimes ſu-peradded. And by the ſtatute 13 Hen. IV. c. 7. any two juſtices, together with the ſheriff or under-ſheriff of the county, may come with the <hi rend="italic">po[fe cornitatus,</hi> if need be, and ſuppreſs any ſuch riot, aſſembly, or rout, arreſt the rioters, and record upon the ſpot the nature and circumſtances of the whole tranſaction ; which record alone ſhall be a ſufficient conviction of the offenders. In the interpretation of which ſtatute it hath been holden, that all perſons, noblemen and others, except women, clergymen, perſons decrepit, and infants under 15, are bound to attend the juſtices in ſup-preſſing a riot, upon pain of fine and impriſonment; and that any battery, wounding, or killing the rioters, that may happen in ſuppreſſing the riot, is juſtiſiable. So that our ancient law, previous to the modern riot-act, ſeems pretty well to have guarded againſt any violent breach of the public peace ; eſpecially as any riotous aſſembly on a public or general account, as to re-dreſs grievances or pull down all 1nclofure3, and alſo re-ſiſting the king’s forces if ſent to keep the peace, may amount to overt acts of high treaſon, by levying war againſt the king.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>