<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r02-0234-02" facs="gri_33125011196389_0240.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>RICHES</label>
a word uſed always in the plural number, means wealth, money, poſſeſſion, or a ſplendid ſump-tuous appearance. When uſed to expreſs the fortune of private perſons, whether patrimonial or acquired, it lignifies <hi rend="italic">opulencea ;</hi> term which expreſſes not the enjoyment, but the poſſeſſion, of numerous ſuperfluities.— The riches of a ſtate or kingdom expreſſes the produce of induſtry, of commerce, of different incorporated bodies, of the internal and external adminiſtration of the principal members of which the ſociety is compoſed, &amp;c.</p><p>Our Saviour ſays, that it is more eaſy ſor a camel to go through the eye of a needle, than for a rich man to enter the kingdom of heaven ; and we find, in fact, that riches frequently bring along with them a degree of inattention, lukewarmneſs, and irréligion, ſuch as ſuffici-ently confirms the divine aſſertion ; which is merely a general truth, and which by no means aſſerts the abſo-lute impoſſibility of being virtuous and rich at the ſame time. For as the ancient philoſophers wiſely taught, riches, conſidered in themſelves, and abſtractedly from the bad purpoſes to which they may be applied, are not neceſſarily incompatible with virtue and wiſdom. They are indeed abſolutely indifferent ; in good hands they will be uſeful, and promote the cauſe of truth, virtue, and humanity; and in bad hands they are the ſource of much miſchief ; on the one band they confer the power of doing much good, and on the other they are equally powerful in doing ill.</p><p>To men, however, whoſe principles of virtue are not ſufficiently founded, riches are unqueſtionably a dangerous and ſeducing bait ; and as the ancients rightly taught, they are to the greateſt number of men, in an</p>
<pb xml:id="eb03-16-r02-0235" facs="gri_33125011196389_0241.tif"/>
<p>infinite variety of circumſtances, a powerful obſtacle to the practice of moral virtues, to the progreſs of truth, and a weight which prevents them from riſing to that degree of knowledge and perfection of which human nature is capable. They multiply without ceaſing the occaſions of vice, by the facility which they give to ſa-tisfy a multitude of irregular paſſions, and to turn at length thoſe who are attached to them from the road of virtue, and from the deſire of inquiring after truth.</p><p>It is this which Seneca means to expreſs, when he ſays, “ that riches in a vaſt number of caſes have been a great obſtacle to philoſophy ; and that, to enjoy freedom of mind neceſſary for ſtudy, a man muſt live in poverty, or as if he were poor. Everyman (adds he) who wiſhes to lead a pleaſant, tranquil, and ſecure life, muſt avoid, as much as poſſible, the deceitfulneſs of riches, which are a bait with which we allow ourſelves to be taken as in a ſnare, without afterwards having the power to extricate ourſelves, being ſo much the more unhappy, that we believe we poſſeſs them, while, on the contrary, they tyrrannize over us.” <hi rend="italic">Senec. Epiſt. 17.</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Epiſt.</hi> 8.</p><p>“ The wiſe man (ſays the ſame author in another place) does not love riches to exceſs, but he would not .choofe wholly to diveſt himſelf of them ; he does not receive them into his ſoul, but into his houſe ; he is careful of them, and employs them for the purpoſe of opening a wide field for virtue, and of making it appear in all its ſplendor. Who can doubt that a wiſe man has not more occaſions of diſplaying the elevation and greatneſs of his mind when he is poſſeſſed of riches than when he labours under indigence, ſince, in the laſt condition, he can exerciſe only one virtue, namely, resignation ; whereas, riches give him an opportunity of diſplaying, in their greateſt luſtre, the virtues of temperance, liberality, diligence, regularity, and magnificence. There is no occaſion, then, to prohibit philosophers from the uſe of wealth, or to condemn wiſdom to poverty. The philoſopher may poſſeſs the greateſt riches, provided he has not employed force or ſhed blood in acquiring them ; provided he has not gained them by unjuſt or illegal means ; in a word, provided the uſe which he makes of them be as pure as the ſource from which they were derived, and no perſon (the envious excepted) regretting his poſſeſſion ; he will not refuſe the kindneſsof fortune, and will enjoy, without ſhame or pride, the wealth acquired by honeſt means ; he will have more reaſon to glory, if, after ex-poſinghis riches to the view of the whole world, he can deſire any perſon to carry away the reward of treachery or the fruits of oppreſſion. If, after theſe words, his riches continue undiminiſhed, this man is truly great, and worthy to be rich. If he has not allowed to enter into his poſſeſſion the ſinalleſt piece of money gained by unwarrantable means, neither will he refuſe the greateſt riches, which are the bleſſings of fortune, and the huit of virtue : if he can be rich, he will chooſe to be ſo, and he ſhall have riches ; but he will regard them as bleſſings of uncertain poſſeſſion, and of which he may be every moment deprived ; he will not permit them to be a load to himſelf or to others ; he will give them to the good, or to thoſe whom he would make good ; but he will give them with the niceſt wiſ-dom, taking care always to diſtribute them to the moil worthy, and to thoſe who remember that they muſt give an account, as well of the wealth which they receive from heaven, as of the purpoſes to which it is ap∙ plied.” <hi rend="italic">Senec. de Vita Beata.,</hi> cap. 21, 22, &amp; 23.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>