<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r02-0228-03" facs="gri_33125011196389_0234.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>RHUS</label>
sumach, in botany : A genus of the tri-g∙ynia order, belonging to the pentandria claſs of plants; and in the natural method ranking under the 43d order, <hi rend="italic">Dumoſ</hi> <hi rend="italic">æ</hi> <hi rend="italic">.</hi> The calyx is quinquepartite; the petals five; the berry monoſpermous. There are 24 ſpecies, of which the moſt remarkable are,</p><p>1. The coriaria, or elm-leaved ſumach, grows naturally in Italy, Spain, Turkey, Syria, and Paleſtine. The branches of this tree are uſed inſtead of oak-bark for tanning of leather ; and it is ſaid that the Turkey leather is all tanned with this ſhrub. It has a ligneous ftalk, which divides at bottom into many irregular branches, riling to the height of eight or ten feet ; the bark is hairy, of an herbaceous brown colour; the leaves are winged, compoſed of ſeven or eight pair of lobes, terminated by an odd one, bluntly ſawed on their edges, hairy on their under ſide, of a yellowiſh-green colour, and placed alternately on the branches; the flowers grow in looſe panicles on the end of the branches, which are of a vchitiſh herbaceous colour, each panicle being compoſed of ſeveral ſpikes of flowers fitting cloſe to the footſtalks. The leaves and feeds of this ſort are uſed in medicine, and are eſteemed very reſtringent and ftiptic.</p><p>2. The typhinum, Virginian ſumach, or vinegar plant, grows naturally in almoſt every part of North America. This hath a woody ſtem, with many irregular branches, which are generally crooked and deformed. The young branches are covered with a ſoft velvet-like down, re-ſembling greatly that of a young flag’s horn, both in colour and texture, from whence the common people have given it the appellation of <hi rend="italic">ſtag's horn ;</hi> the leaves are winged, compoſed of fix or ſeven pair of oblong heart-ſhaped lobes, terminated by an odd one, ending in acute points, hairy on their underſide, as is alſo the midrib. The flowers are produced in cloſe tufts at the end of the branches, and are ſucceeded by feeds, inclo-ſed in purple woolly ſucculent covers ; ſo that the bunches are of a beautiful purple colour in autumn ; and the leaves, before they fall in autumn, change to a purpliſh colour at firſt, and before they fall to a feuille-mort. This plant, originally a native of North America, has been long cultivated in the north of Germany, and is lately introduced into Ruſſia. It has got the name of the <hi rend="italic">vinegar plant</hi> from the double reaſon of the young germen of its fruit, when fermented, producing either new or adding to the ſtrength of old weak vinegar, whilſt its ripe berries afford an agreeable acid, which might ſupply the place when neceſſary of the citric acid. The powerful aſtringency of this plant in all its parts recommends it as uſeful in ſeveral of the arts. As for example, the ripe berries boiled with alum make a good dye for hats. The plant in all its parts may be uſed as a ſuccedaneum for oak-bark in tanning, eſpecially the white glove leather. It will likewiſe anſwer to prepare a dye for black, green, and yellow colours ; and with martial vitriol it makes a good ink. The milky juice</p><p>that flows from inciſions made in the trunk or branches, makes when dried the baſis of a varniſh little inferior to the Chineſe. Bees are remarkably fond of its flowers; and it affords more honey than any of the flowering ſlrrubs, ſo that it may prove a uſeful branch of economy, where rearing tlieſe infects is an object. The natives of America uſe the dried leaves as tobacco.</p><p>3. The glabrum, with winged leaves, grows naturally in many parts of North America ; this is commonly titled by the gardeners <hi rend="italic">New England ſumach.</hi> The ſtem of this is ſtronger and riſes higher than that of the former ; the branches ſpread more horizontally ; they are not quite ſo downy as thoſe of the laſt, and the down is of a browniſh colour ; the leaves are compoſed of many more pair of lobes, which are ſmooth on both ſides ; the flowers are diſpoſed in looſe panicles, which are of an herbaceous colour.</p><p>4. The Carolinian um, with ſawedwinged leaves, grows naturally in Carolina ; the feeds of this were brought from thence by the late Mr Cateſhy, who has given a figure of the plant in his Natural Hiſtory of Carolina. This is by the gardeners called the <hi rend="italic">ſcarlet Carolina ſu-mach ;</hi> it riſes commonly to the height of ſeven or eight feet, dividing into many irregular branches, which are ſmooth, of a purple colour, and pounced over with a greyiſh powder, as are alſo the footſtalks of the leaves. The leaves are compoſed of ſeven or eight pair of lobes, terminated by an odd one ; theſe are not always placed exactly oppoſite on the midrib, but are ſometimes alternate. The upper ſide of the lobes are of a dark green, and their under hoary,, but ſmooth. The flowers are produced at the end of the branches in very cloſe panicles, which are large, and of a bright red colour.</p><p>5. The Canadenſe, with winged ſpear-ſhaped leaves, grows naturally in Canada, Maryland, and ſeveral other parts of North America. This hath ſmooth branches of a purple colour, covered with a grey pounce. The leaves are compoſed of ſeven or eight pair of lobes, terminated by an odd one ; the lobes are ſpear-ſhaped, ſawed on their edges, of a lucid green on their upper ſurface, but hoary on their under, and are ſmooth. The flowers are produced at the end of the branches in large panicles, which are compoſed of ſeveral ſmaller, each ſtanding upon ſeparate footſtalks ; they are of a deep red colour, and the whole panicle is covered with a grey pounce, as if it had been ſcattered over them.</p><p>6. The copallinum, or narrow-leaved ſumach, grows naturally in moſt parts of North America, where it is known by the title of <hi rend="italic">beach ſumach,</hi> probably from the place where it grows. This is of humbler growth than either, of the former, ſeldom riſing more than four or five feet high in Britain, dividing into many ſpreading branches, which are ſmooth, of a light brown colour, cloſely garniſhed with winged leaves, compoſed of four or five pair of narrow lobes, terminated by an odd one; they are of a light green on both ſides, and in autumn change purpliſh. The midrib, which ſuſtains the lobes, has on each ſide a winged or leafy border, which runs from one pair of lobes to another, ending in joints at each pair, by which it is eaſily diſtinguiſhed from the other ſorts. The flowers are produced in looſe panicles at the end of the branches, of a yellowiſh herbaceous colour.</p>
<pb xml:id="eb03-16-r02-0229" facs="gri_33125011196389_0235.tif"/>
<p>Theſe ſix ſorts are hardy plants, and will thrive in the open air here. The firſt and fourth ſorts are not quite ſo hardy as the others, ſo muſt have a better fi-tuation, ptherwiſe their branches will be injured by ſe-vere froſt in the winter. They arc eaſily propagated by ſeeds, which if ſown in autumn the plants will come up the following ſpring ; but if they are ſown in ſpring, they will not come up till the next ſpring ; they may be either ſown in pots, or the full ground. If they are ſown in pots in autumn, the pots ſhould be placed under a common frame in winter, where the ſeeds may be protected from hard froſt ; and in the ſpring, if the pots are plunged into a very moderate hot-bed, the plants will ſoon riſe, and have thereby more time to get ſtrength before winter. When the plants come up, they muſt be gradually hardened to bear the open air, into which they ſhould be removed as ſoon as the weather is favourable, placing them where they may have the morning ſun ; in the ſummer, they muſt be kept clean from weeds, and in dry weather watered. Toward autumn it will be proper to ſtint their growth by keeping them dry, that the extremity of their ſhoots may harden ; for if they are replete with moiſture, the early froſts in autumn will pinch them, which will cauſe their ſhoots to decay almoſt to the bottom if the plants are not ſcreened from them. If the pots are put under a common frame in autumn, it will ſecure the plants from injury : for while they are young and the ſhoots ſoft, they will be in danger of ſuffering, if the winter proves very ſevere ; but in mild weather they muſt always enjoy the open air, therefore ſhould never be covered but in froſt. The ſpring following, juſt before the plants begin to ſhoot, they ſhould be ſhaken out of the pots, and carefully ſeparated, ſo as not to tear the roots ; and tranſplanted into a nurſery, in rows three feet aſunder, and one foot diſtance in the rows. In this nurſery they may Hand two years to get·ſtrength, and then may be tranſplanted where they are to remain.</p><p>7. Beſides theſe, Linnæus has included in this genus the toxicodendron or poiſon-tree, under the name of <hi rend="italic">rhus vernix</hi> or <hi rend="italic">poiſon-aſh.</hi> This grows naturally in Virginia, Penſylvania, New .England, Carolina, and Japan, riſing with a ſtrong woody ſtalk to the height of 20 feet and upwards ; though in this country it is ſeldom ſeen above 12, by reaſon of the plants being extremely tender. The bark is brown, inclining to grey ; the branches are garniſhed with winged leaves compoſed of three or four pair of lobes terminated by an odd one. The lobes vary greatly in their ſhape, but for the moſt part they are oval and ſpear-ſhaped. The footſtalks become of a bright purple towards the latter part of ſummer, and in autumn all the leaves are of a beautiful purple before they fall off.</p><p>All the ſpecies of ſumach abound with an acrid milky juice, which is reckoned poiſonous; but this property is moſt remarkable in the vernix. The moſt diſtinct account of it is to be found in Proſeſſor Kalm’s Travels in North America. “ An inciſion (ſays he) being made into the tree, a whitiſh yellow juice, which lias a nauſeous ſmell, comes out between the bark and the wood. This tree is not known for its good qualities, but greatly ſo for the effect of its poiſon ; which, tho’ it is noxious to ſome people, yet does not in the leaſt affect others. And therefore one perſon can handle the tree as he pleaſes, cut it, peel off its bark, rub it or</p><p>the wood upon his hands, ſmell at it, ſpread the juice upon his ſkin, and make more experiments, with no in. convenience to himſelf : another perſon, on the contrary, dares not meddle with the tree while its wood is freſh ; nor can he venture to touch a hand which has handled it, nor even to expoſe himſelf to the ſtnoke of a fire which is made with this wood, without ſoon feel, ing its bad effects ; for the face, the hands, and frequently the whole body, ſwclls exceſſively, and is af* fected with a very acute pain. Sometimes bladders or bliſters ariſe in great plenty, and make the fiεk perſon look as if he was infected by a leprofy. In ſome people the external thin ſhin, or cuticle, peels off in a <hi rend="italic">fενι</hi> days, as is the caſe when a perſen has ſcalded or burnt any part of his body. Nay, the nature of ſome perſons will not even allow them to approach the place where the tree grows, or to expoſe themſelves to the wind when it carries the effluvia or exhalations of this tree with it, without letting them feel the inconvenience of the ſwelling which I have juſt now deſcribed. Their eyes are ſometimes ſhut up for one, or two, or more days together, by the ſwelling. 1 know two brothers, one of whom could without danger handle this tree in what manner he pleaſed, whereas the other could not come near it without ſwelling. A perſon ſometimes does not know that he has touched this poiſonous plant, or that he has been near it, before his face and hands ſhow it by their ſwelling. I have known old people who were more afraid of this tree than of a viper ; and I was acquainted w <hi rend="sub">j</hi> ith a perſon who, merely by the noxious exhalations of it, was ſwelled to ſuch a degree, that he was as ſtiff as a log of wood, and could only be turned about in ſheets.</p><p>“ I have tried experiments of every kind with the poifon-tree on myſelf. I have ſpread its juice upon my hands, cut and broke its branches, peeled off its bark, and rubbed my hands with it, ſmelt at it, carried pieces' of it in my bare hands, and repeated all this frequently, without feeling the baneful effects ſo commonly annexed to it ; but I, however, once cxperienced, that the' poiſon of the ſumach was not entirely without effect upon me. Oil a hot day in ſummer, as I was in ſome degree of peiſpiration, I cut a branch of the tree, anſh carried it in my hand for about half an hour together, and ſmelt at it now and then. I felt nq effects from it in the evening. But next morning I awoke with a-violent itching of my eye-lids and the parts thereabouts; and this was ſo painful, that I could hardly keep my hands from it. It ceaſed after I had waſhed my eyes for a while with very cold water. But my eye-lids were very ſtiff all that day. At night the itching returned ; and in the morning when I awoke, I felt it as ill as the morning before, and I uſed the ſame remedy againſt it. However, it continued almoſt for a whole week together ; and my eyes were very red, and my eye-lids were with difficulty moved during all that time. My pain ceaſed entirely afterwards. About the fame time I had ſpread the juice of the tree very thick upon my hand. Three days after, they occaſtoned bliſters, which ſoon went off without affecting me much. I have not experienced any thing more of the effects of this plant, nor had I any deſire ſo to do. However, I found that it could not exert its power upon me when-I was not perſpiring.</p><p>I have never heard that the poiſon of this ſumach</p>
<pb xml:id="eb03-16-r02-0230" facs="gri_33125011196389_0236.tif"/>
<p>has been mortal, but the pain ceaſes after a few days duration. The natives formerly made their flutes of this tree, becauſe it has a great deal of pith. Some people aſſured me, that a perſon ſuffering from its noi-ſome exhalations, would eaſily recover by ſpreading a mixture of the wood burnt to charcoal, and hog’s lard, upon the ſwelled parts. Some aſſerted, that they had really tried this remedy. In ſome places this tree is rooted out, on purpoſe that its poiſon may not affect the workmen.”</p><p>The natives are ſaid to diſtinguiſh this tree in the dark by its extreme coldneſs to the touch. The juice of ſome kinds of ſumach, when expoſed to the heat of the ſun, becomes ſo thick and clammy, that it is uſed for bird-lime, and the inſpiſſated juice of the poiſon-aſh is ſaid to be the fine varniſh of Japan. A cataplaſm made with the freſh juice of the poiſon-aſh, applied to the feet, is ſaid by Hughes, in his Natural Hiſtory of Barbadoes, to kill the vermin called by the Weft Indians <hi rend="italic">chigers.</hi> Very good vinegar is made from an in-fuſion of the fruit of an American ſumach, which for that reaſon is called the <hi rend="italic">vinegar-tree.</hi> The reſin called <hi rend="italic">gum copal</hi> is from the rhus copallinum. See Copal.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>