<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T20:03:32Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>bloody serum occurs ſrom the integuments ; and, if a real mortification do not take place, the ſkin cracks in different parts ; and the artery being now deprived of the uſual resistance, the blood burſts out with ſuch force as to occasion the almoſt immediate death of the patient. Thus the diſeaſe teιminates in the large cavities of the body; but in the extremities we can, by means of the tourniquet, prevent the hidden termination of the diſeaſe.</p><p>When affections of this kind happen in the larger arteries, the effects produced upon the neighbouring parts are often ſurpriſing : the soft parts not only yield to a great extent, but even the bones frequently undergo a great degree of derangement.</p><p>The f<hi rend="italic">alſe</hi> or <hi rend="italic">diffuſed</hi> aneuriſm conſiſts in a wound or rupture in an artery, producing, by the blood thrown out of it, a ſwelling in the contiguous parts. It is moſt frequently produced by a wound made directly into the artery.</p><p>The following is the uſual progreſs of the diſorder. A tumor, about the size of a horſe bean, generally rises at the orifice in the artery ſoon after the diſcharge of the blood has been stopped by compreſſion. At firſt it is ſoft, has a strong degree of puliation, and yields a little to preſſure, but cannot be made entirely to diſappear ; ſor here the. blood forming the tumor being at rest, begins to coagulate. If not improperly treated by much preſſure, it generally remains nearly of the ſame ſize for ſeveral weeks. The enlargement however proceeds more rapidly in some caſes than in others. Inſtances have occurred of the blood being diffuſed over the whole arm in the ſpace of a few hours ; while, on the contrary, ſwellings of this kind have been many months, nay even years, in arriving at any conſiderable ſize.</p><p>As the tumor becomes larger, it does not, like the true aneuriſm, grow much mote prominent, but rather ſpreads and diffuſes itſelf into the ſurrounding parts. By degrees it acquires a firm conſiſtence ; and the pulſation, which was at firſt conſiderable, gradually diminiſhes, till it is ſometimes ſcarcely perceptible. If the blood at firſt thrown out proceed from an artery deeply ſeated, the ſkin preſerves its natural appearance till the diſorder is far advanced : but when the blood gets at firſt into contact with the ſkin, the parts become inſtantly livid, indicating the approach of mortification ; and a real ſphacelus has ſometimes been induced. The tumor at firſt produces little uneaſineſs ; but as it increaſes in ſize, the patient complains of ſevere pain, stiffneſs, numbneſs, and immobility of the whole joint ; and theſe ſymptoms continuing to augment, if the artery be large, and aſſiſtance not given, the teguments at laſt burst, and death muſt enſue.</p><p>When an artery is punctured through a vein, as in bloodletting at the arm, the blood generally ruſhes into the yielding cellular ſubſtance, and there ſpreads ſo as to ſhut the ſides of the vein together. But in ſome inſtances where the artery happens to be in contact with the vein, the communication opened has been preſerved; and the vein not being ſufficiently ſtrong for refilling the impulſe of the artery, muſt conſequently be dilated. This is a varicoſe aneuriſm. It was firſt accurately deſcribed by Dr Hunter, and since that time has been frequently obſerved by different practitioners. Here the ſwelling is entirely confined to the veins. Soon after the injury the vein immediately communicating with the artery begins to swell, and enlarge gradually. If there be any conſiderable communications in the neighbourhood, the veins which form them are alſo enlarged. The tumor diſappears upon preſſure, the blood contained in it being chiefly pushed forwards in its courſe towards the heart ; and when the tumor is large, there is a singular tremulous motion, attended with a perpetual hiſſing noise, as if air was passing into it through a ſmall aperture.</p><p>If a ligature be applied upon the limb immediately below the ſwelling, tight enough to ſtop the pulſe in the under part of the member, the swelling diſappears by preſſure, but returns immediately upon the preſſure being removed. If, after the ſwelling is removed by pressure, the finger be placed upon the orifice in the artery, the veins remain perfectly flaccid till the preſſure is taken off. If the trunk of the artery be compreſſed above the orifice ſo as effectually to ſtop the circulation, the tremulous motion and hiſſing immediately ceaſe ; and if the veins be now emptied by pressure, they remain so till the compreſſion upon the artery be removed. If the vein be compreſſed a little above, as well as below the tumor, all the blood may generally, though not always, be puſhed through the orifice into the artery ; from whence it immediately returns on the preſſure being diſontinued.</p><p>When the diſeaſe has continued long, and the dilatation of the veins has become conſiderable, the trunk of the artery above the orifice generally becomes greatly enlarged, while that below becomes proportionably small ; of consequence the pulse in the under part of the member is always more feeble than in the sound limb of the oppoſite ſide.</p><p>The cauſes producing aneuriſms, in general, are a natural, diſeaſe of the arteries. Thus a partial debility of their coats may readily produce the diſeaſe ; or they may ariſe, eſpecially in the internal parts of the body, from great bodily exertions. They are likewiſe produced by wounds of the coats of the arteries, as now and then happens in bloodletting at the arm ; or from acrid matter contained in a neighbouring ſore ; or from the deſtruction of ſurrounding parts, by which the natural ſupport is removed.</p><p>Aneuriſms have frequently been miſtaken ſor abſceſſes and other collections of matter, and have been laid open by inciſion ; on which account great attention is sometimes required to make the proper diſtinction. In the commencement of the diſeaſe the pulſation in the tumor is commonly ſo ſtrong, and other concomitant circumſtances so evidently point out the nature of the diſorder, that little or no doubt reſpecting it can ever take place ; but in the more advanced ſtages of the diſeaſe, when the ſwelling has become large and has lost its pulsation, nothing but a minute attention to the previous hiſtory of the caſe can enable the practitioner to form a judgment of its nature.</p><p>Aneuriſms may be confounded with ſoft encyſted tumors, ſcrophulous ſwellings, and abſcesses ſituated so near to an artery as to be affected by its puliation. But one ſymptom, when connected with ſtrong pulſation, may always lead to a certain determination that the ſwelling is of the aneurismal kind, viz. the contents of the tumor being made eaſily to diſappear upon preſſure, and their returning on the compreſſion being removed. The want of this circumſtance, however, ought not to convince us that it is not of that nature ; for it frequently happens, eſpecially in the advanced ſtages of aneuriſms, that their contents become ſo firm that no effect is produced upon them by preſſure. Hence the propriety, in doubtful cases, of proceeding as if the diſease was clearly of the aneuriſmal kind.</p><p>In the prognoſis, three circumſtances are chiefly to be attended to ; the manner in which the diſeaſe appears to have been produced, the part of the body in which the ſwelling is situated, and the age and habit of the body of the patient.</p><p>If an aneuriſm has come forward in a gradual manner,  without any apparent injury done to the part, and not ſucceeding any violent bodily exertion, there will be reason to</p></body></text></TEI>