<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T20:01:23Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>val of Hannibal was ſlain in a ſkirmiſh. E. Long, 17. 26. N. Lat. 39. 20.</p><p>STRONTITES, or STRONTIAN <hi rend="smallcaps">earth,</hi> a new ſpecies of earth lately diſcovered at Strontian in Scotland.</p><p>Who the diſcoverer of this earth was we have not learned ; but Dr Kirwan ſays, the first information he received of it was from Dr Crawford in the year 1790. In the Miners Journal for February 1791 a good deſcription of its external appearance, with ſome account of its chemical properties, was publiſhed from the obſervations of Mr Sulzer. Dr Kirwan examined it in October 1793, and found it to be a new earth between the barytic and common limeſtone. Dr Hope, who is now joint profeſſor of chemiſtry with Dr Black in the univerſity of Edinburgh, read a paper on the 4th November 1793 before the Royal Society of Edinburgh, intitled “ An Aβcount of a Mineral from Strontian, and of a peculiar Species of Earth which it contains ;” an abridgment of which is publiſhed in the third volume of the Edinburgh Philoſophical Tranſactions. Mr Schmeiſſer read a paper on the ſame ſubject before the Royal Society of London in May 1794, which is publiſhed in their Tranſactions for that year, p. 418, &amp;c.</p><p>@@Its external characters are theſe : Its colour is whitiſh or light green ; its luſtre common ; its transparency intermediate between the ſemitranſparent and opaque ; its fracture ſtriated, preſenting oblong diſtinct concretions, ſomewhat uneven and bent; its hardneſſs moderate, being eaſily ſcratched, but not ſcraped. It is very brittle ; and its ſpecific gravity from 3,4 to 3,644.</p><p>For a full account of its chemical qualities we muſt refer to the books already mentioned, as all the accounts of it which we have ſeen are too long to insert here, and as we do not conſider the circumſtance of its being a newly discovered earth a ſufficient reaſon for running into a tedious detail till its utility be aſcertained. We ſhall, however, mention ſome of its moſt remarkable qualities. It requires 180 times its weight of water at a low temperature to diſſolve it. When diſſolved in boiling water, and allowed to cool, it depoſits tranſparent cryſtals, which when expoſed to the air become white and powdery. It is not affected by the ſulphuric acid ; but when diluted, 10,000 parts of it will diſſolve one of ſtrontites. Diluted nitric acid dissolves it rapidly. The muriatic acid, whether diluted or oxygenated, diſſolves it in a ſimilar manner.</p><p>Strontites has a ſtrong reſemblance to barytes, but eſſentially differs from it. Its ſpeciſic gravity is leſs; it parts with its carbonic acid when urged by heat ſomewhat more readily, and without ſuffering fuſion@@; when calcined, it imbibes moiſture with vaſtly greater avidity, ſwelling and cracking with more heat and noiſe. Strontites diſſolves much more abundantly in hot water than barytes ; and the form of the cryſtals of theſe pure earths is very diſſimilar. The compounds generated by ſtrontites differ from thoſe of barytes. It will ſuffice to mention the nitrate and muriate. This earth, united to nitric and muriatic acid, forms salts  that ſuffer changes from expoſure to air, which do not happen to the nitrate and muriate of barytes. They are likewiſe much more ſoluble in water, and have cryſtals of a peculiar figure. The combinations of ſtrontites with acids are not, like thoſe of barytes, decompoſed by pruſſiate of lime or of potaſh. Strontites and its compounds tinge flame, which barytes does not. Laſtly, theſe earths diſagree in the order of their attractions. From theſe conſiderations it is concluded, that the mineral is not aerated barytes.</p><p>It alſo is diſtinguiſhed from calcareous ſpar or limeſtone : for it is much heavier, and retains its fixed air with more obſtinacy in the fire. The incomparably greater ſolubility of the pure earth in hot than in cold water, and the cryſtalline form it aſſumes, ſufficiently diſtinguiſh it from lime, which the diſpoſition of the nitrate and muriate to cryſtallize no leſs tends to do.</p><p>The moſt remarkable quality of ſtrontites is that of tinging flame of a red colour, The muriate has it in the moſt eminent degree, and its effects are well exhibited by putting a portion of the salt on the wick of a candle, which is thereby made to burn with a very beautiful blood-red flame. The nitrate ſtands next, then cryſtallized ſtrontites, and after it the acetite. A hundred parts of ſtrontites are compoſed of 61.21 of earth, 30.20 of carbonic acid, and 8.59 of water.</p><p>STROPHE, in ancient poetry, a certain number of verſes, including a perfect ſenſe, and making the firſt part of an ode. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Poetry,</hi> n⁰ 130.</p><p>STRUMÆ, ſcrophulous tumors ariſing on the neck and throat, conſtituting what is commonly called the <hi rend="italic">king's evil. </hi>See <hi rend="smallcaps">Medicine,</hi> n⁰ 349.</p><p>STRUMPFIA, in botany ; a genus of plants belonging to the claſs of s<hi rend="italic">yngynesia,</hi> and to the order of <hi rend="italic">monogamia. </hi>The calyx is quinquedentate and iuperior ; the corolla is pentapetalous ; and the berry monoſpermous. There is only one ſpecies, the maritima.</p><p>STRUTHIO, in natural hiſtory ; a genus of birds belonging to the order of <hi rend="italic">grallae</hi> of Linnaeus ; but, according to the new claſſification of Dr Latham, it forms, along with the dodo, caſſuarius, and rhea, a ſeparate order under the name of st<hi rend="italic">ruthiοus.</hi> As the dodo or didus, and rhea, have been already deſcribed in their proper place, we will now give ſome account of the oſtrich and caſſowary.</p><p>I. @@The <hi rend="smallcaps">Ostrich</hi> (the <hi rend="italic">Camelus</hi> of Linnasus) has a bill ſomewhat conical ; the wings are ſo ſhort as to be unfit for flying ; the thighs and sides of the body are naked ; the feet are formed for running, having two toes, one only of which is furniſhed with a nail. In this respect it differs entirely from the caſſowary, which has three toes complete. The oſtrich is without doubt the largeſt of all birds : it is nearly eight feet in length, and when ſtanding upright from six to eight feet in height. We are told in the Gentleman’s Magazine@@*, that two oſtriches were ſhown in London in the year 1750, and that the male was 10 feet in height, and weighed three hundred weight and a quarter. The head and bill ſomewhat reſemble those of a duck ; and the neck may be likened to that of a ſwan, but that it is much longer; the legs and thighs reſemble thoſe of an hen; though the whole appearance bears a ſtrong reſemblance to that of a camel. But though uſually ſeven feet high from the top of the head to the ground, from the back it is only four ; ſo that the head and neck are above three feet long. From the top of the head to the rump, when the neck is ſtretched out in a right line, it is six feet long, and the tail is about a foot more. One of the wings, without the feathers, is a foot and an half; and being ſtretched out, with the feathers, is three feet.</p><p>The plumage is much alike in all; that is, generally black and white; though ſome of them are ſaid to be grey. There are no feathers on the ſides, nor yet on the thighs, nor under the wings. The lower part of the neck, about half way, is covered with ſtill ſmaller feathers than thoſe on the belly and back ; and thoſe alſo are of different colours.</p><p>All theſe feathers are of the ſame kind, and peculiar to the oſtrich ; for other birds have ſeveral forts, some of which are ſoft and downy, and others hard and ſtrong. Oſtrich-feathers are almoſt all as ſoft as down, being utterly unfit to ſerve the animal for flying, and ſtill leſs adapted to be a proper defence against external injury. The feathers</p><p>@@@[mu] Transactions of the Irish Academy, vol. v.</p><p>@@@[mu] Transactions of the Royal Society of Edinburgh, vol. iii. </p><p>@@@[mu] Plate CCCCLXXXVI.</p><p>@@@[m] Vol xx. p. 536.</p></body></text></TEI>