<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T20:02:37Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Till the days of Hippocrates we know very little of what was the practice of the Greek ſurgeons. From him, however, we learn, that the practice of blood-letting, cupping, and ſcarification, was known to them ; alſo the uſe of warm and emollient fomentations, issues made with hot irons, peſſaries, injections, fumigations, &amp;c. Hippocrates alſo gives directions with regard to fractures, luxations, ulcers, siſtulas. He directs the extenſion, reduction, bandages, and ſplints, proper to be uſed in fractures and luxations of different bones, with ſeveral machines to increaſe the extenſion when neceſſary. He directs the laxity and tightneſs of the bandages ; the intervals for unlooſing and binding them on again ; the position and repoſe of the fractured member, and the proper regimen ; and he mentions the time when a callus is uſually formed. He treats alſo of fractures of the ſkull, and the method of applying the trepan. In his treatment of ulcers, he ſpeaks of reducing fungous fleſh by means of eſcharotics, ſome of which are alum, nitre, verdigriſe, quicklime, &amp;c.</p><p>In the time of Ptolemy Philopater of Egypt, medicine, all the branches of which had hitherto been practiſed by the ſame perſon, was now divided into three, viz. the dietetic, pharmaceutic, and ſurgical ; from which time to the preſent, ſurgery has continued to be reckoned a diſtinct profeſſion from medicine, though very improperly, in the opinion of the best authors.</p><p>Surgery appears not to have exiſted in Rome, notwithſtanding the warlike genius of the people, for more than 500 years. Archagathus, a Greek, was the firſt profeſſor of that art in the city; and ſo frequently employed the knife, hot irons, and other cruel methods of cure, that he was branded with the opprobrious title of <hi rend="italic">carnifex,</hi> and expelled the city, where no phyſician or ſurgeon of eminence again made his appearance for 180 years. At this time Aſclepiades undertook the profeſſion of medicine ; but ſeems to have dealt little in ſurgery. Neither have we any thing of importance on that ſubject till the time of Celſus, who flouriſhed during the reigns of Auguſtus and Tiberius.— In his ſurgery, all the improvements from Hippocrates to his own days are collected ; the moſt minute and trifling diſeaſes are not omitted. An eminent ſurgeon, of the moderns, emphatically exhorts every perſon in that profeſſion “ to keep Celſus in his hands by day and by night.” He describes the signs of a fractured ſkull, the method of examining for the fracture, of laying the ſkull bare by an incision in the form of the letter X, and afterwards of cutting away the angles, and of applying the trepan, with the ſigns of danger and of recovery. He obſerved, that sometimes, though very rarely, a fatal concuſſion of the brain might happen, the blood- vessels within the ſkull being burſt, yet the bone remaining entire. After the operation of the trepan, ſponges and cloths wetted with vinegar, and ſeveral other applications, were made to the head ; and, throughout, ſevere abſtinence was enjoined. In violent fractures of the ribs, he ordered veneſection ; low diet ; to guard againſt all agitation of the mind, loud speaking, motion, and every thing that might excite coughing or ſneezing. Cloths wetted with wine, roſes and oil, and other applications, were laid over the fracture. The cure of fractures, in the upper and lower extremities, he ſaid were nearly alike ; that fractures differ in degree of violence and danger, in being ſimple or compound, that is, with or without a wound of the fleſh, and in being near to the joint. He directs the extenſion of the member by aſſiſtants ; the reduction, by the ſurgeon’s hands, of the fractured bones into their natural ſituation ; and to bind the fractured part with bandages of different lengths, previouſly dipped in wine and oil : on the third day freſh bandages are to be applied, and the fractured member fomented with warm vapour, eſpecially during the inflammation. Splinte, if necessary, are to be applied, to retain the bones in a fixed position. The fractured arm is to be ſuſpended in a broad sling hung round the neck : the fractured leg is to be incloſed in a kind of caſe, reaching above the ham, and accommodated likewiſe with a ſupport to the foot, and with straps at the side, to keep the leg ſteady : in the fractured thigh-bone, the caſe is to extend from the top of the hip to the foot. He deſcribes the method of treating compound fractures, and of removing ſmall fragments of splinters of bones ; and the manner of extracting darts. In luxations of the ſhoulder, he mentions ſeveral methods of giving force to the extenſion, and of replacing the diſlocated bone, One method ſimilar to that of Hippocrates was, to ſuſpend the patient by the arm ; the fore part of the ſhoulder, at the ſame time, reſting upon the top of a door, or any other ſuch firm fulcrum. Another method was to lay the patient ſupine, ſome aſſiſtants retaining the body in a fixed position, and others expending the arm in the contrary direction ; the ſurgeon, in the mean time, attempting, by his hands, forcibly to reduce the bone into its former place.</p><p>If a large inflammation was expected to ensue after a wound, it was ſuffered to bleed for ſome time, and blood was drawn from the arm. To wounds accompanied with conſiderable hæinorrhagy, he applied a ſponge wet in vinegar, and constant pressure : If necessary, on account of the violence of the hæmorrhagy, ligatures were made round the veſſels, and ſometimes the bleeding orifice was feared up with the point of a hot iron. On the third day freſh dreſſings were applied. In conſiderable contuſions, with a ſmall wound of the fleſh, if neither blood-veſſels nor nerves prevented, the wound was to be enlarged. Abſtinence and low diet, upon all ſuch accidents, were preſcribed; cloths wet with vinegar, and ſeveral other applications, were to be applied to the inflamed part. He obſerves, that freſh wounds may be healed without compound applications. In external gangrene, he cut into the found fleſh; and when the diſeaſe, in ſpite of every effort, spread, he adviſed amputation of the member. After cutting to the bone, the fleſh was then ſeparated from it, and drawn back, in order to ſave as much fleſh as poſſible to cover the extremity of the bone. Celſus, though extremely diffuſe. in the deſcription of ſurgical diſeaſes, and of various remedies and external applications, treats slightly of the method of amputating ; from which, comparing his treatiſe with the modern ſyſtems, we might infer that the operation was then ſeldomer practiſed than at preſent. He deſcribes the ſymptoms of that dangerous inflammation the carbuncle, and directs, immediately to burn, or to corrode the gangrened part. To promote the ſuppuration of abſceſſes, he orders poultices of barley-meal, or of marſhmallows, or the seeds of linſeed and fenugreek. He alſo mentions the compoſitions of ſeveral repellent cataplaſms. In the <hi rend="italic">erysipelas,</hi> he applies ceruſe, mixed with the juice of ſolanum or nightſhade. Sal ammoniac was ſometimes mixed with his plaſters.</p><p>He is very minute in deſcribing diſeaſes of the eyes, ears, and teeth, and in preſcribing a multitude of remedies and applications. In inflammation of the eyes, he enjoined abſtinence and low diet, rest, and a dark room: if the inflammation was violent, with great pain, he ordered veneſection, and a purgative ; a ſmall poultice of fine flower, ſaffron, and the white of an egg, to be laid to the forehead to ſuppreſs the flow of pituita ; the ſoſe inside of warm wheat bread dipped in wine, to be laid to the eye ; poppy and roſes were alſo added to his collyriums, and various ingredients too tedious to enumerate. In chronic watery deflu-</p></body></text></TEI>