<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T20:04:06Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>heal, as the ſides of it will be frequently ſeparated by the action of deglutition. On this account as great a degree of abſtinence as poſſible is to be advised ; and nothing but nouriſhing liquids, in ſmall quantities, are to be allowed. The patient ſhould be prevented from moving his neck; and the wound is to be healed as ſoon as poſſible by the ſame methods which are uſed with wounds in other parts of the body. On the other hand, if the operation has been done for the purpoſe of conveying nouriſhment into the ſtomach, when the patient was diſtressed by a tumor either in the oeſopſhagus itſelf or in ſome of the neighbouring parts, it will be neceſſary to keep the wound open during the continuance of the tumor, or the life of the patient.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Chap.</hi> XX. <hi rend="italic">Of Sore Nipples.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Women</hi> are more generally affected with ſore nipples in suckling their firſt child than at any period afterwards. This may, in ſome meaſure, be owing to the ſmallneſs of the nipples ; but very often it ariſes ſrom their being unaccuſtomed to the irritation of ſucking. In ſome caſes, the nipples are ſo flat, and ſo much sunk in the breaſt, as to render it difficult for the child to lay hold of them. Here aſſiſtance can ſometimes be given, by the mother preſſing back the prominent part of the breaſt, ſo as to make the nipple project between two of ſher fingers. Should this be inſufficient, the nipple may be made to project by applying to it a ſtout child ſeveral months old : but when this cannot be done, breaſt-glasses, ſuch äs fig. 68. may anſwer the ſame purpoſe. By applying theſe to the nipple, and ſucking out the air, the child will commonly be enabled to lay hold of it.</p><p>The nipples at this time are liable to excoriations, cracks, or chops ; which, though not attended with a formidable appearance, are frequently more diſtreſſing than large ulcers. Mild, aſtringent, and drying applications are moſt to be depended upon in ſuch complaints ; as port wine, brandy properly diluted, or lime-water ; all of which ought to be applied warm. After bathing the parts with any of theſe, the nipple ſhould be covered with unguentum nutritum, or Goulard’s cerate ; the firſt of which is conſidered as beſt. Even a little ſoft pomatum frequently rubbed upon the part, and covered with a ſoft linen rag, is ſometimes found to give considerable relief. But the nipple ſhould be perfectly cleared of theſe applications before the child is laid to the breaſt ; and this may be done with a little port wine, or equal parts of brandy and vinegar. If proper attention be paid to theſe remedies, they will commonly be found to have the desired effect ; but if the contrary ſhould happen, another remains to be mentioned, which, in different inſtances, has given great relief : it conſiſts in the application of a thin ſkin to the nipple, as the neck and part of the body of a ſwine’s bladder with an aperture in it ; which, being properly moiſtened and fixed to the breaſt, will completely protect <hi rend="italic">it</hi> in the time of ſucking. As long as the nipples remain any way affected, ſmall cups of glaſs or tin are uſeful for retaining the dreſſings, defending the nipples from the friction of the clothes, and receiving any milk which may fall from the breaſt.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Chap.</hi> XXI.	<hi rend="italic">Of Paracentesis of the Thorax.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">When</hi> either the action of the heart or of the lungs is impeded by fluids collected in the cavity of the pleura, a diſcharge of theſe fluids by a perforation is the only chance the patient has for relief. The fluids which collect in the pleura are, ſerum, blood, air, or pus. A collection of water or ſerum is frequently found in the thorax, combined with dropſy in other parts of the body ; but the affection is often local, and it is then chiefly that advantage is to be derived from an operation. Beſides, in the two great cavities of the thorax, collections of water are frequently met with in the pericardium, and are ſaid to be ſometimes diſcovered between the layers of the anterior mediaſtinum. The diſeaſe is marked by the following ſymptoms : There is a ſenſe of weight or oppreſſion in the thorax, and difficulty of breathing ; the patient has frequently a more uneaſy ſenſation in one ſide than in the other ; has ſudden ſtartings during ſleep, with a ſenſe of ſuffocation ; is troubled with a frequent dry cough ; the pulſe is ſmall and irregular ; the ſkin dry, and the urine ſcanty.</p><p>With theſe ſymptoms there are commonly other marks of dropſy ; and the patient ſometimes, upon any ſudden motion, is ſenſible of an undulation within the cheſt ; and when the quantity of water is conſiderable, the undulation will even be heard by the byſtanders, if the body be ſmartly agitated. For this purpoſe, the patient’s body ſhould be uncovered while under examination ; and the ſurgeon ſhould place his hand upon the breaſt near the ſternum ; then an aſſiſtant ought to raiſe the patient ſuddenly from an horizontal to an erect poſture, or to ſtand behind the patient and make ſudden jerks ; when, if water be preſent, the undulation will be felt ; but it is neceſſary to guard againſt being deceived by the noiſe ſometimes made by the contents of the ſtomach.</p><p>When the water is collected in one side only, if the diſeaſe be of long standing, for the moſt part that ſide is more prominent than the other. If the water be in the pericardium, the ſymptoms are nearly the ſame as thoſe above enumerated, with this difference, that the pain is generally felt behind, and to the left ſide of the ſternum ; and the ſtroke of the heart is as if buried in water, while an undulatory motion has been ſaid to be felt oppoſite to the anterior extremities of the third, fourth, and fifth ribs.</p><p>In the treatment of this diſeaſe, little advantage can be derived from internal remedies. Squills, cream of tartar, mercury, and digitalis, are upon ſome occaſions attended with advantage ; but the only method ſrom which we can expect any decree of ſucceſs is the removing of the water by an operation, which ſhould be performed as ſoon as there is reaſon to expect that danger may ariſe from delaying it longer. The operation is done in the ſame way as ſhall be afterwards deſcribed in the caſe of empyema.</p><p>Blood collected in the thorax is always extravaſated thro’ ſome wound or rupture of the veſſels of the lungs or thorax. The breathing becomes oppreſsed, the motion of the heart and arteries feeble and irregular, and all theſe ſymptoms are more diſtreſſing than collections of other fluids. As it frequently happens, in caſes of this kind, that ſome of the veſſels of the lungs are injured, part of the blood is thrown up by coughing ; which, when conſiderable, gives a temporary relief to the lungs and heart ; and while this is the caſe, no operation is neceſſary ; but whenever the action of theſe parts becomes much impeded by a great accumulation of blood, a perforation ought to be made to diſcharge it. When the extravaſated blood is too firmly coagulated to paſs off by a perforation, the wound ought to be made considerably larger ; and if this be inſufficient, injections of warm water ought to be thrown in, and allowed to remain for ſome time, to promote the diſſolution of the maſs, which is afterwards to be evacuated. If the extravaſation has been occaſioned by a wound in the lower part of the thorax, a new perforation will be unneceſſary ; an enlargement of the wound will be quite ſufficient. But if it be ſituated in the upper part of the cavity, a perforation in the</p></body></text></TEI>