<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T20:03:35Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>is to be expected from it, though it may be productive of miſchief.</p><p>In the early stages of encyſted aneuriſm, while the blood can be yet preſſed entirely out of the ſac into the artery, it often happens, by the uſe of a bandage of ſoft and ſomewhat elaſtic materials, properly fitted to the part, that much may be done in preventing the ſwelling from receiving any degree of increaſe; and on ſome occaſions, by the continued ſupport thus given to the weakened artery, complete cures have been at laſt obtained. In all ſuch caſes, therefore, particularly in every inſtance of the varicoſe aneuriſm, much advantage may be expected from moderate pressure.</p><p>But preſſure, even in encyſted aneuriſm, ought never to be carried to any great length ; for tight bandages, by producing an immoderate degree of reaction in the containing parts to which they are applied, inſtead of anſwering the purpoſe for which they were intended, have evidently the contrary effect. Indeed the greateſt length to which preſſure in ſuch caſes ought to go, ſhould be to ſerve as an eaſy ſupport to the parts affected, and no farther.</p><p>In performing the operation for aneuriſm, the firſt ſtep ought to be to obtain a full command of the circulation in the inferior part of the member by means of the tourniquet. This being done, the patient ſhould be ſo placed, that the diſeaſed limb, on being ſtretched on a table, is found to be of a proper height for the ſurgeon ; who, as the operation is generally tedious, ought to be ſeated. The limb being properly ſecured by an aſſiſtant, the operator is now with the ſcalpel, Plate CCCCLXXXVII. fig. 18. to make an inciſion through the ſkin and cellular ſubſtance along the whole courſe of the tumor ; and as freedom in the remaining parts of the operation is here a matter of much importance, it is even of uſe to carry this external inciſion half an inch or ſo both above and below the fartheſt extremities of the ſwelling.</p><p>All the effuſed blood ought then to be wiped off by means of a ſponge ; and the ſofteſt part of the tumor being diſcovered, an opening ought there to be made into it with the lancet, Plate CCCCLXXXVII. fig. 19. large enough ſor admitting a finger of the operator’s left-hand. This being done, and the finger introduced into the cavity of the tumor, it is now to be laid open from one extremity to the other, by running a blunt-pointed biſtoury, Plate CCCCLXXXVII. fig. 20. along the finger from below upwards, and afterwards from above downwards, ſo as to lay the whole cavity fairly open.</p><p>The cavity of the tumor being thus laid freely open, all the coagulated blood is to be taken out by the fingers of the operator, together with a number of tough membranous filaments commonly found here. The cavity of the tumor is now to be rendered quite dry, and free from the blood which, on the firſt opening of the ſwelling, is diſcharged into it ſrom the veins in the inferior part of the member : the tourniquet is then to be ſlackened to diſcover, not only the artery itſelf, but the opening into it, from whence the blood collected in the tumor has been all along diſcharged. This being done, the next point to be determined is the manner of ſecuring this opening into the artery, ſo as to prevent in future any farther effuſion of blood. Various means have been propoſed for accompliſhing this ; but the effects of all of them may be comprehended under the three following heads.</p><p>1.	The effects of ligature upon a large artery having on ſome occaſions proved fatal to the inferior part of the member, it was long ago propoſed, that ſo ſoon as the opening into the artery has been diſcovered, inſtead of applying a Ligature round it, which for certain is to obliterate its cavity entirely, a piece of agaric, vitriol, alum, or any other aſtringent ſubſtance, ſhould be applied to the orifice, in order if poſſible to produce a reunion of its ſides.</p><p>2.	Upon the ſame principle with the preceding, viz. that of ſtill preſerving the circulation in the artery, it was ſeveral years ago propoſed by an eminent ſurgeon of Newcaſtle, Mr Lambert, that the orifice in the artery ſhould be ſecured by means of the twiſted suture. A ſmall needle being puſhed through the edges of the wound, they are then directed to be drawn together by a thread properly twiſted round the needle, as was formerly directed when treating of sutures.</p><p>Strong objections, however, occur to both of theſe methods. In the firſt place, no aſtringent application with which we are acquainted is posseſſed of ſuch powers as to deserve much confidence. In almoſt every inſtance in which they have been uſed, the hemorrhagy has recurred again and again, ſo as to prove very diſtreſſing, not only to the patient, but to the practitioner in attendance ; little or no attention is therefore to be paid to remedies of this kind in ordinary practice.</p><p>Mr Lambert’s method of ſtitching the orifice in the artery is certainly a very ingenious propoſal ; and would in all probability, at leaſt in moſt inſtances, prove an effectual ſtop to all farther diſcharge of blood : but as we have yet only one inſtance of its ſucceſs, little can be ſaid about it. Two material objections, however, ſeem to occur to this practice. One is, that in the operation for the aneuriſm, in almoſt every inſtance, a very few only excepted, the artery lies at the back-part of the tumor; ſo that when all the collected blood is removed, there is ſuch a depth of wound, that it muſt be always a very difficult matter, and on many occaſions quite impracticable, to perform this nice operation upon the artery with that attention and exactneſs which, in order to ensure ſucceſs, it certainly requires. But there is another very material objection. By introducing a needle through the ſides of the orifice, and drawing theſe together by a ligature, the cavity of the artery muſt undoubtedly be at that point much diminiſhed. Indeed Mr Lambert, in his account of the caſe in which this operation was performed, acknowledges that the diameter of the artery was thereby diminiſhed. Now the paſſage of the blood being thus contracted at one point, the impulſe upon that particular part muſt be very conſiderable : So that the very remedy employed for the cure of one ſpecies of aneuriſm, will in all probability prove a very powerful agent in inducing another ; for the blood being thus obſtructed in its uſual courſe, there will be no ſmall danger incurred of a dilatation being produced immediately above this preternatural ſtricture.</p><p>3.	Neither of the methods we have yet been conſidering being found eligible for ſecuring the orifice in the artery, we ſhall now proceed to deſcribe the ordinary manner of performing this operation ; which conſiſts in obliterating the arterial cavity entirely by means oſ ligatures.</p><p>The artery being laid bare in the manner directed, and all the coagulated blood being carefully removed from the cavity of the tumor, on the tourniquet being now ſlackened  ſo as to bring the orifice in the artery into view, a ſmall probe curved at the extremity is to be introduced at the opening, in order to raiſe the artery from the neighbouring parts, ſo as that the ſurgeon may be enabled with certainty to paſs a ligature round it, without comprehending the contiguous nerves, which in general run very near to the large blood-veſſels of a limb. By this precaution the nerves may be always avoided ; and by doing ſo, a great deal of miſchief may be prevented, which otherwiſe might ſupervene. When the diſorder is ſituated either in the ham, or in the uſual part of blood-letting in the arm, bending the joints of</p></body></text></TEI>