<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T20:03:42Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ſleep is much diſturbed, neither natural ſleep nor that procured by opiates affording him relief ; the pulſe is hard and quick ; the face is fluſhed ; the eyes inflamed, and unable to bear an expoſure to much light. Sometimes, where a wound of the head accompanies theſe ſymptoms, its edges become hard and ſwelled, and an eryſipelatows inflammation ſpreads quickly over the whole head, and eſpecially towards the forehead and eyelids, which frequently ſwell to ſuch a degree as to ſhut up the eyes entirely. This ſwelling is ſoft and painful to the touch ; it receives the impreſſion of the finger, and frequently originates merely from the external wound ; on which account the attending ſymptoms are commonly eaſily removed by the means beſt ſuited to eryſipelas of the parts. In a few inſtances, however, this symptom is likewiſe connected with, and ſeems to originate from, ſome affection of the dura mater. Its tendency is then of the moſt dangerous kind, and therefore requires the greateſt attention. Soon after theſe ſymptoms become formidable, the part which received the blow begins to put on a diſeaſed appearance. If the bone has been expoſed by the accident, it now loses its natural complexion, becomes pale, white, and dry, either over its whole ſurface or in particular ſpots : but when the bone has not been denuded, nor the ſofter parts divided, but merely contuſed, they now ſwell, become puffy, and painful to the touch ; and when the head is shaved, the skin over the part affected is redder than the reſt of the ſcalp ; and if the ſwelled part be laid open, the pericranium will probably be found to be detached from the ſkull, and a little bloody fetid ichor will be obſerved between this membrane and the bone, which will be found diſcoloured in nearly the ſame manner as if it had been laid bare from the beginning.</p><p>By the application of proper remedies theſe ſymptoms are frequently entirely removed ; but when neglected, or when they do not yield to the means employed, they conſtantly become worſe. Delirium enſues ; the patient becomes extremely hot ; and is at times ſeized with slight ſhiverings, which continue to increaſe and are attended with ſome degree of coma or ſtupor. The former ſymptoms now in a great meaſure diſappear ; palſy of one ſide is ſoon followed by deep coma ; the pupils are dilated ; the urine and fæces are paſſed involuntarily ; ſubſultus tendinum and other convulsions enſue ; and death certainly follows, if the patient be not ſpeedily relieved.</p><p>Of the above ſymptoms, the firſt ſet point out the inflammatory, the other the ſuppurative, ſtage of the diſease. The remedies which are uſeful in the one are highly improper in the other. During the inflammatory ſtage, blood-letting is the principal remedy ; but this is improper after the suppurative ſymptoms appear, for then the trepan is the only thing that can give relief.</p><p>The indications of cure are ; 1. To employ the moſt effectual means for preventing inflammation. 2. To endeavour to procure the reſolution of inflammation by general and topical remedies. 3. When the inflammation cannot be removed by reſolution, and when ſuppuration has taken place, to give a free vent to the matter. 4. If the affected parts be attacked with gangrene, to endeavour to remove it and obviate its effects.</p><p>To anſwer the firſt indication, when the contuſion is conſiderable, blood-letting, both general and topical, ought to be employed, and to a conſiderable extent ; the bowels ought to be kept open by the uſe of laxatives ; a watery ſolution of ſaccharum ſaturni ſhould be applied to the part affected, and a low diet, with a total abſtinence from exercite, ought to be enjoined : but if theſe means fail, or, as frequently happens, the practitioner has not been called in ſoon enough for their proper application, and if inflammation have actually commenced, the second indication ought then to be attended to. For this purpoſe, blood-letting, not from the feet according to the advice of old practitioners, but as near as poſſible to the part affected, is to be performed, by leeching, cupping, or scarifying with a lancet or ſcalpel,</p><p>When, inſtead of this, general blood-letting is thought more adviſable, it is commonly reckoned beſt to open the external jugular vein, or the temporal artery ; and the rule, with regard to the quantity to be evacuated, ought to be, to draw blood as long as the pulſe continues firm ; so that, in violent caſes, taking away from 20 to 25 ounces at once will be found to anſwer the purpoſe better than to extract even a larger quantity, but at different intervals. A few hours afterwards, if the ſymptoms continue violent, it may be proper to diſcharge an additional quantity ; but this muſt depend upon the ſtrength of the patient and the fulneſs of the pulſe.</p><p>Along with the liberal uſe of blood-letting, brisk purgatives ſhould be given. The bowels ſhould not merely be kept open ; but in order to receive full advantage from the practice, a ſmart purging ſhould be kept up by repeated doſes of calomel, jalap, or ſome other neutral ſalt. Where the patient cannot ſwallow in ſufficient quantity, ſtimulating injections ſhould be frequently exhibited.</p><p>A moiſt ſtate of the skin is uſeful in every caſe of inflammation, and ought therefore to be here particularly attended to. In general a mild perſpiration may be induced by applying warm fomentations to the feet and legs, and by laying the patient in blankets inſtead of linen. But when theſe means are insufficient, diaphoretics or even ſudorifics may be given.</p><p>When much pain or reſtlessneſs takes place, opiates ſhould be adminiſtered freely, which are now found to be attended with real advantage.</p><p>With reſpect to the external treatment of this diſorder, attention ſhould be paid to thoſe means which may moſt readily induce a free diſcharge of purulent matter from the seat of the injury. With this view, if the original accident be attended with a wound or diviſion of the integuments, as the lips of the ſore are commonly obſerved to be hard, painful, and dry, it ſhould be covered with pledgets ſpread with an emollient ointment, and warm emollient poultices laid over the whole ; by which means, and eſpecially by a frequent renewal of the poultices, a free diſcharge of matter will commonly be induced, and the bad ſymptoms will generally be much mitigated, or entirely removed.</p><p>In caſes unattended with a diviſion of the integuments, as ſoon as it is ſuſpected that bad ſymptoms may ſupervene, the tumor ſhould be divided down to the pericranium ; and if that membrane be found ſeparated from the bone, it ought likewiſe to be divided ; and by inducing a ſuppuration in the way already mentioned, the inflammatory ſymptoms will probably be removed. As matter formed here is commonly of an acrid nature, and therefore apt to affect the bone, and by communication of veſſels the membranes under it, inſtead of wailing time till fluctuation be distinctly perceived, a free inciſion ſhould be made as ſoon as a tumor is obſervable. But this would be extremely improper in the treatment of tumors which immediately ſucceed to external injuries ; for it often happens that ſuch tumors diſappear ſpontaneously, or by the uſe of aſtringent applications. It is only when a tumor attended with pain appears at a diſtant period upon the ſpot where the injury was received, that it ought to be opened as ſoon as perceived.</p><p>The next part of the practice regards the remedies to be</p></body></text></TEI>