<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T20:01:35Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>STUD, in the manege, a collection of breeding horſes and mares.</p><p>STUDDlNG-SAILS, certain light ſails extended, in moderate and steady breezes, beyond the ſkirts of the principal sails, where they appear as wings upon the yard-arms.</p><p>STUFF, in commerce, a general name for all kinds of ſabrics of gold, ſilver, ſilk, wool, hair, cotton, or thread, manufactured on the loom ; of which number are velvets, brocades, mohairs, ſatins, taffetas, cloths, ſerges, &amp;c.</p><p>STUKELY (Dr William), a celebrated antiquarian, descended from an ancient family in Lincolnſhire, was born at Holbech in 1687, and educated in Bennet college, Cambridge. While an under-graduate, he often indulged a strong propenſity to drawing and deſigning ; but made phyſic his principal ſtudy, and firſt began to practiſe at Boſton in his native country. In 1717 he removed to London, where, on the recommendation of Dr Mead, he was ſoon after elected a fellow of the Royal Society ; he was one of the firſt who revived that of the antiquarians in 1718, and was their ſecretary for many years during his reſidence in town. In 1729 he took holy orders by the encouragement of archbishop Wake ; and was ſoon after presented by lord-chancellor King with thc living of All Saints in Stamford. In 1741 he became one of the founders of the Egyptian ſociety, which brought him acquainted with the benevolent duke of Montague, one of the members ; who prevailed on him to leave Stamford, and preſented him to the living of St George the Martyr, Queen Square. He died of a ſtroke of the palſy in 1765. In his phyſical capacity, his Diſſertation on the Spleen was well received ; and his <hi rend="italic">Itinerarium Curioſum,</hi> the firſt fruit of his juvenile excurſions, was a good specimen of what was to be expected from his riper age. His great learning, and profound researches into the dark remains of antiquity, enabled him to publiſh many elaborate and curious works : his friends uſed to call him the <hi rend="italic">arch-druid</hi> of his age. His diſcourſes, intitled <hi rend="italic">Palaeographica Sacra,</hi> on the vegetable creation, beſpeak him a botaniſt, philoſopher, and divine.</p><p>STUM, in the wine-trade, denotes the unfermented juice of the grape after it has been ſeveral times racked off and ſeparated from its ſediment. The caſks are for this purpoſe well matched or fumigated with brimſtone every time, to prevent the liquor from fermenting, as it would otherwiſe readily do, and become wine. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Must.</hi></p><p>STUPIDITY. The Greek word μωροτης correſponds moſt with our Engliſh word stu<hi rend="italic">pidity</hi> or <hi rend="italic">fooliſhneſs,</hi> when uſed to express that ſtate of mind in which the intellects are defective. The immediate cauſes are ſaid to be, a deficiency of vital heat, or a defect in the brain. Stupid children ſometimes become ſprightly youths ; but if ſtupidity continues to the age of puberty, it is hardly ever removed. If ſtupidity follows upon a violent paſſion, an injury done to the head, or other evident cauſe, and if it continues long, it becomes incurable. But the ſtupidity which conſiſts in a loſs of memory, and ſucceeds a lethargy, ſpontaneouſly ceases when the lethargy is cured.</p><p>STUPOR, a numbneſs in any part of the body, whether occaſioned by ligatures obstructing the blood’s motion, by the palſy, or the like.</p><p>STUPPA, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Stupe,</hi> in medicine, is a piece of cloth dipped in ſome proper liquor, and applied to an affected part.</p><p>STURDY, a diſtemper to which cattle are ſubject, called alſo the <hi rend="italic">turning evil.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Farriery.</hi></p><p>STURGEON. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Accipenser.</hi></p><p>STURMIUS (John), a learned philologer and rhetorician, was born at Sleida in Eiſel near Cologne in 1507. He studied at firſt in his native country with the ſons of count de Manderscheid, whoſe receiver his father was. He afterward purſued his ſtudy at Liege in the college of St Jerom, and then went to Louvain in 1524. Five years he spent there, three in learning and two in teaching. He ſet up a printing-press with Rudger Reſcius profeſſor of the Greek tongue, and printed ſeveral Greek authors. He went to Paris in 1529, where he was highly eſteemed, and read public lectures on the Greek and Latin writers, and on logic. He married there, and kept a great number of boarders : but as he liked what were called the <hi rend="italic">new opinions, </hi>he was more than once in danger ; and this undoubtedly was the reaſon why he removed to Straſburg in 1537, in order to take poſſeſſion of the place offered him by the magiſtrates. The year following he opened a ſchool, which became famous, and by his means obtained of Maximilian IL the title of an univerſity in 1566. He was very well ſkilled in polite literature, wrote Latin with great purity, and was a good teacher. His talents were not confined to the ſchool ; for he was frequently intruſted with deputations in Germany and foreign countries, and diſcharged theſe employments with great honour and diligence. He ſhowed extreme charity to the refugees on account of religion : He not only laboured to aſſiſt them by his advice and recommendations ; but he even impoveriſhed himſelf for them. He died in his 82d year, after he had been for ſome time blind. He published many books ; the principal of which are, 1. <hi rend="italic">Partitiones Dialectica.</hi> 2. <hi rend="italic">De Educatione Principum, 3. De Nobilitate Anglicana.</hi> 4. <hi rend="italic">Lingua Latinae resolvendae Ratio. 5.</hi> Excellent Notes on Ariſtotle’s and Hermogenes’s Rhetoric, &amp;c.</p><p>He ought not to be confounded with <hi rend="italic">John Sturmius,</hi> a native of Mechlin, and phyſician and proſeſſor of mathematics at Louvain, who alſo wrote ſeveral works.</p><p>STURNUS, the <hi rend="smallcaps">Starling</hi> ; agenus of birds belonging to the order of <hi rend="italic">paſſeres.</hi> The beak is ſubulated, depressed, and ſomewhat blunt ; the superior mandible is entire, and ſomewhat open at the edges ; the noſtrils are marginated above ; and the tongue is ſharp and emarginated. There are 15 ſpecies according to Dr Latham ; the vulgaris, capenſis, ludovicianus, militaris, cellaris, carunculatus, gallinaceus, ſericeus, viridis, olivaceus, moritanicus, loyca, dauuricus, junceti, and mexicanus.</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">vulgaris,</hi> or common ſtarling, is the only ſpecies of the ſturnus that is indigenous. The weight of the male of this ſpecies is about three ounces ; that of the female rather leſs. The length is eight inches three quarters: the bill is brown or yellow, but in old birds generally yellow@@. The whole plumage is black, very reſplendent, with changeable blue, purple, and copper : each feather marked with a pale yellow ſpot. The lesser coverts are edged with yellow, and ſlightly gloſſed with green. The quill-feathers and tail duſky : the former edged with yellow on the exterior side ; the last with dirty white. The legs of a reddiſh brown.</p><p>The ſtare breeds in hollow trees, eaves of houſes, towers, ruins, cliffs, and often in high rocks over the ſea, ſuch as that of the iſle of Wight. It lays four or five eggs, of a pale- greeniſh aſh-colour ; and makes its neſt of ſtraw, ſmall fibres of roots, and the like. In winter, ſtares aſſemble in vast flocks : they collect in myriads in the fens of Lincolnſhire, and do great damage to the fen-men, by rootling on the reeds, and breaking them down by their weight ; for reeds are the thatch of the country, and are laid up in harveſt with great care. Theſe birds feed on worms and infects ; and it is ſaid that they will get into pigeon-houſes, for the ſake of ſucking the eggs. Their fleſh is ſo bitter as to be ſcarce eatable. They are fond of following oxen and other large cattle as they feed in the meadows, attracted, it is ſaid, by the infects which flutter round them, or by thoſe, perhaps,</p><p>@@@[mu] Latham's Synopsis, vol. iii. </p></body></text></TEI>