<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T20:03:02Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>made moſt frequently are thoſe of compound fractures, and the breaſt : but the latter do offener well without dilatation than the former ; though it muſt be performed in both, if practicable, the whole length of the abſeeſs, when after ſome trial the matter does not lessen in quantity, and the ſides of it grow thinner ; and if the ſinuſes be ſiſtulous, no cure need be expected without dilatation.</p><p>When an ulcer with looſe rotten fleſh diſcharges more than the ſize of it ſhould yield, and the diſcharge is oily and ſtinking, in all probability the bone is carious ; which may easily be diſtinguiſhed by running the probe through the fleſh : and if ſo, it is called a <hi rend="italic">carious ulcer.</hi> The cure oſ theſe ulcers depends principally upon the removal of the rotten part of the bone, without which it cannot heal. Thoſe caries which happen from the matter of abscesses lying too long upon the bone, are moſt likely to recover : thoſe of lues venerea very often do well, becauſe that diſtemper fixes ordinarily upon the middle and outſide of the denſeſt bones, which admit of exfoliation ; but thoſe produced by ſcrophula, where the whole extremities of the ſpongy parts of the bone are affected, are exceedingly dangerous. All enlarged bones are not neceffarily carious ; and there are ulcers ſometimes on the ſkin which covers them, which do not communicate with the bone, and conſequently do well without exfoliation ; nay, it ſometimes happens, though the caſe be rare, that, in young ſubjects particularly, the bones will be carious to ſuch a degree, as to admit a probe almoſt through the whole ſubſtance of them ; and yet afterwards admit of a cure, without any notable exfoliation.</p><p>The method of treating an ulcer with caries, is by applying a cauſtic of the ſize of the ſcale of the bone which is to be exfoliated ; and after having laid it bare, to wait till the carious part can without violence be ſeparated, and then heal the wound. In order to quicken the exfoliation, there have been ſeveral applications deviſed ; but that which has been moſt uſed in all ages, is the actual cautery, with which ſurgeons burn the naked bone every day, or every other day, to dry up, as they ſay, the moiſture, and by that means procure the ſeparation : but as this practice is never of great ſervice, and always cruel and painful, it is now pretty much exploded. Indeed, from conſidering the appearance of a wound, when a ſeale of bone is taken out of it, there is little doubt that burning retards rather than haftens the ſeparation ; ſor as every ſeale of a carious bone is flung off by new fleſh generated between it and the found bone, whatever would prevent the growth of theſe granulations would alſo in a degree prevent the exfoliation ; which muſt certainly be the effect of a red-hot iron applied ſo cloſe to it.</p><p>Some caries of the bones are ſo very ſhallow, that they crumble inſenſibly away, and the wound fills up ; but when the bone will neither exfoliate nor admit of granulations, it will be proper to ſcrape it with a rugine, or perforate it in many points with a convenient instrument down to the quick. In ſcrophulous caſes, the bones of the carpus and tarſus are often affected ; and from their ſpongineſs they are ſeldom cured : ſo that when theſe, or indeed the extremities of any of the bones, are carious through their ſubſtance, it is adviſable to amputate ; though there are inſtances in the ſcrophula, but more eſpecially in critical abscesses, where, after long dreſſing down, the ſplinters, and ſometimes the whole ſubſtance, of the ſmall bones, have worked away, and a healthy habit of body coming on, the ulcer has healed ; but theſe are ſo rare, that no great dependence is to be laid on ſuch an event. The dreſſings of carious bones, if they are ſtinking, may be doſſils dipped in the tincture of myrrh ; otherwiſe thoſe oſ dry lint are eaſieſt, and keep down the cdges of the ulcer better than any other gentle applications.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sect.</hi> II. <hi rend="italic">Of  White Swellings.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">There</hi> are two ſpecies of white ſwellings, Mr Benjamin Bell obſerves; the one of a mild nature, and frequently admitting of a cure ; which the other never does. The former, named by our author the <hi rend="italic">rheumatic</hi> ſpecies of white swelling, begins with an acute pain, ſeemingly diffuſed over the whole joint, and frequently extending along the tendinous aponeu- roſes of the muscles which communicate with it. There is, from the beginning, an uniform ſwelling of the whole ſurrounding integuments. Great tenſion generally prevails; but at firſt there is ſeldom any external change of colour. From the commencement of the diſeaſe the motion of the joint is attended with exquiſite pain, and the patient keeps it conſtantly in a relaxed poſture, finding that the eaſieſt. Hence the tendons become extremely ſtiff and rigid, till at laſt the joints have the appearance of complete and real anchyloſes. The ſwelling now begins to augment, till the joint has acquired three or four times its natural ſize ; the cuticular veins become turgid and varicoſe ; at the ſame time that the muſcular ſubſtance of the limb below decays, though it frequently acquires an equality in ſize by becoming cedematous ; the pain becomes intolerable, eſpecially when the perſon is warm in bed or otherwiſe heated ; abſcesses form in different parts, which, either breaking of themſelves, or by being laid open, diſcharge conſiderable quantities of matter, but without any remarkable effect in reducing the ſize of the ſwelling. The pus diſeharged from theſe is at firſt of a tolerably good consiſtence, but ſoon degenerates into a thin ill-conditioned ſanies. However, the orifices ſrom whence it flows ſoon heal up, unleſs they are kept open by art ; and new collections breaking out, they burſt and heal up as before ; ſo that in long-continued dilorders of this kind, the ſurrounding integuments are often entirely covered with cicatrices.</p><p>In the mean time, the health of the patient gradually declines, from the violence of the pain, and the abſorption of matter into the ſyſtem, which takes place in ſome degree ſrom its ſirſt formation in the different abſeeffes ; but which never appears ſo evidently till the different abſeeffes have been laid open ; after which a quick pulſe, night-ſweats, and a weakening diarrhoea, are ſure to occur, which generally carry off the patient, if the member is not either amputated, or the diſeaſe cured ſome other way.</p><p>On diſſecting limbs which have been amputated for white ſwellings, the original diſeaſe appears to have been a morbid thickening of the ſurrounding ligaments, without any other affection of the joint whatever ; the bones and cartilages always remaining perfectly found, as likewiſe the synovia both in quantity and conliſtence. In the more advanced stages of the diſorder, the thickneſs of the ligaments is more conſiderable, and is generally attended with an effusion, into the ſurrounding cellular ſubſtance, of a thick glairy matter, which gives to ſwellings of this kind an elaſtic ſpringy feel, independent of the collections of matter the fluctuation of which may also be perceived. Through this glairy matter the collections of pus run in various directions, without ſeeming, however, to mix with it. In ſome inſtances alio a great many ſmall hydatides are obſerved ; all which form a confuſed maſs, incapable of further diffec- tion.</p><p>All the above-mentioned appearances have been obſerved without any affection of the bones or cartilages. But when, by a very long continuance of the diſorder the ligaments come to be corroded by the different collections of</p></body></text></TEI>