<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T20:02:54Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>year ; as the cure of them, when opened, very often proves extremely troubleſome ; and as their being opened cannot contribute any thing towards their cure.</p><p>Where the inflammation is but beginning, and the ſymptoms are not ſo violent as to affect the general ſyſtem, topical remedies, with a due attention to regimen, often answer in reſolving them. The firſt thing to be attended to in the caſe of every inflammation, is the removal of the exciting cauſes, which either have brought on the inflammation originally, or which may continue it after it is begun. Such are extraneous bodies in wounds, pieces of fractured bones, luxations, &amp;c. Of all the various applications for an inflamed part, thoſe of a ſedative nature are chiefly to be depended upon ; and, next to theſe, emollients. Of the former kind we may conſider all the different preparations of lead dissolved in vinegar; together with vinegar itſelf, which generally acts alſo as a ſedative. Among the latter we may place the mild expreſſed oils, as alſo the ſoft ointments made with theſe oils and pure wax.</p><p>When we speak of ſedative medicines, however, it muſt not be underſtood that all of that claſs are to be uſed indiſcriminately. Thus opium, though one of the moſt powerful of all ſedatives, yet as its application, externally, to the human body, is always attended with ſome degree of irritation, however uſeful it may at times be found in ſome particular ſpecies of inflammatory diſorders, will never, probably, as an external application, become of general uſe in theſe caſes. Warm emollient fomentations alſo, though powerful ſedatives, as tending more effectually to remove tenſion and pain than perhaps any other remedy, are conſtantly found to be improper where a reſolution is to be wiſhed for. Their constant effect is, either to bring the ſwelling to a ſuppuration, or to relax the parts in ſuch a manner as to render the removal of the diſorder always exceedingly tedious.</p><p>Mr Bell recommends the preparations of lead as proper applications, in caſes of external inflammation, where we wiſh for a reſolution. The beſt method of applying it, he ſays, is in the form of a watery ſolution ; and he gives the following formula: “ R. Sacchar. ſaturn. 3fs. ; ſolve in acet. pur. 3iv. ; et adde aq. ſontan. diſtillat. lbij. The addition of vinegar renders the ſolution much more complete than it otherwiſe would be ; and without it indeed a very conſiderable proportion of the lead generally ſeparates and falls to the bottom.</p><p>In making uſe of this ſolution in caſes of inflammation, as it is of conſequence to have the parts affected kept constantly moiſt with it, cataplaſms prepared with it and crumb of bread in general anſwer that intention exceedingly well. But when the inflamed part is ſo tender and painful as not eaſily to bear the weight of a poultice, which is frequently the caſe, pieces of ſoft linen moiſtened with the ſolution answer the purpoſe tolerably well. Both ſhould be applied cold, or at leaſt with no greater warmth than is merely neceſſary for preventing pain or uneaſineſs to the patient : they ſhould be kept almoſt conſtantly at the part, and renewed always before turning ſtiff or hard.</p><p>When the tenſion and irritation on the skin are conſiderable, emollients are often attended with very great advantage : the parts affected being, in ſuch a ſtate of the diſorder, gently rubbed over with any of the mild expreſſed oils two or three times a-day, the tenſion, irritation, and pain are often very much relieved, and the diſcuſſion of the tu, mor thereby greatly promoted.</p><p>In every caſe of inflammation, indeed, emollient applications would afford ſome relief. But as the preparations of lead, already recommended, prove in all ſuch diſorders ſtill more advantageous ; and as unguents of every kind tend conſiderably to blunt the action of lead ; theſe two ſets of remedies ſhould as ſeldom as poſſible be allowed to interfere with one another ; and emollients ſhould accordingly never be preſcribed, but when the circumſtances already mentioned, of irritation, tenſion, and pain, are ſo conſiderable as to render their application altogether neceſſary.</p><p>When the part affected with inflammation is not very tender, or lies deep, applications of vinegar are often had recourſe to with conſiderable advantage : the moſt effectual form of uſing it ſeems to be by way of cataplaſm, made with the ſtrongeſt vinegar and crumb of bread. In such caſes, an alternate uſe of this remedy, with the ſaturnine ſolution, has produced more beneficial effects than are commonly obſerved from a continued courſe of any one of them.</p><p>At the ſame time that theſe applications are continued, blooding with leeches, or cupping and ſcarifying, as near as poſſible to the part affected, is generally of very great ſervice ; and in no caſe of local inflammation ſhould ever be omitted. In all ſuch caſes, the whole body, but more eſpecially the diſeaſed part, ſhould be preſerved as free as poſſible from every kind of motion ; and, for the ſame reaſon, the neceſſity of a low cooling diet, in every inflammatory diſorder, appears obvious, as does alſo a total abſtinence from spirituous and fermented liquors.</p><p>In slight caſes of inflammation, a due perſeverance of the ſeveral articles taken notice of will, in general, be found ſufficient for every purpoſe. But when there is likewiſe a full, hard, or quick pulſe, with other ſymptoms of fever, general blood-letting becomes neceſſary; the quantity of blood taken away being always to be determined by the violence oſ the diſorder, and by the age and ſtrength of the patient. Evacuation, however, ſhould never be carried to a greater height than what is merely neceſſary for moderating the febrile ſymptoms ; for if ſuppuration ſhould take place after the ſyſtem is too much reduced, its progreſs is thereby rendered much more slow and uncertain, nor will the patient be ſo able to bear the diſcharge that muſt enſue upon opening the abſceſs. The uſe of gentle laxatives, together with cooling diaphoretic medicines, are alſo attended with very good effects.</p><p>Theſe different evacuations being premiſed, the next object of conſequence is to procure eaſe and quietneſs to the patient ; which is often, in inflammatory cases, of more real ſervice than any other circumſtance whatever. The moſt effectual remedy for this purpoſe is opium ; which, when pain and irritation are conſiderable, as in extenſive inflammations very frequently happens, ſhould never be omitted. In large wounds, eſpecially after amputations and other capital operations, alſo in punctures of all kinds, large doſes of opium are always attended with remarkable good effects. In all ſuch caſes, however, opium, in order to have a proper influence, ſhould, as was obſerved, be adminiſtered in very large doſes ; otherwiſe, inſtead of proving ſerviceable, it ſeems rather to have the contrary effect ; a circumſtance which is perhaps the chief reaſon for opiates in general having been very unjuſtly condemned in every caſe of inflammation.</p><p>By a proper attention to the different circumſtances taken notice of, in the courſe of three or four days, and ſometimes in a ſhorter ſpace of time, reſolution of the tumor will in general begin to take place ; at leaſt before the end of that period it may, for the moſt part, be known how the diſorder is to terminate. If the heat, pain, and other attending ſymptoms abate, and eſpecially if the tumor begins to decreaſe, without the occcurrence of any gangrenous appearances, we may then be almoſt certain that by a continuance of the ſame plan a total reſolution will in time be effected.</p><p>But, on the contrary, if all the different ſymptoms rather</p></body></text></TEI>