<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T20:04:04Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>touching the part with lunar cauſtic ; but this will ſeldom be neceſſary.</p><p>When a ligature is to be employed, it may be readily done according to the method recommended in the extirpation of polypi. A double canula with a ligature may be paſſed through the noſe, or the ligature may be applied according to Cheſelden’s method in extirpation of the tonſils.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sect.</hi> XI. <hi rend="italic">Of ſcarifying and fomenting the Throat.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">In</hi> inflammatory affections of the throat, the means commonly employed are gargles, fomentations, ſcarification, or top-bleeding. Gargles are uſeful ſor cleaning the fauces from thick mucus or other ſordes ; they may likewiſe be uſeful in caſes of ulceration. In relaxation of the parts, they are employed to advantage when made of aſtringent materials. Fomentations may be of ſome uſe when externally applied ; but the steam of water, &amp;c. drawn into the throat, by means of Mudge’s inhaler (fig. 58.), is preferable. Sometimes it is neceſſary to draw blood from the part affected. Here recourſe may be had to ſcarifying with a common lancet, the tongue being depreſſed with a spatula. It may be ſtill more readily done by the ſcarificator (fig. 59). After a ſufficient number of punctures have been made, the flow of blood may be promoted by the patient’s frequently applying warm water to the punctures. When abſeeſs forms, notwithſtanding the uſe of theſe remedies, the matter may be discharged with the ſcarificator already mentioned.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Chap.</hi> XVII. <hi rend="italic">Of Diſeaſes of the Ear, and Operations performed upon it.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sometimes</hi> a thin membrane is ſpread over the mouth of the external paſſage, while at other times a conſiderable part of the paſſage is filled up with a fleſhy looking ſubſtance, occaſioning deafneſs. When the firſt circumſtance occurs, the ſkin is eaſily divided by a simple inciſion, and the accretion of its ſides may be prevented by a doſſil of lint or a bit of bougie inſerted between the edges of the wound, and daily cleaned and returned till the part be rendered callous.</p><p>When the other cauſe is preſent, the inciſion muſt be continued conſiderably deeper, till the reſiſtance be removed, or till the inſtrument reach near to the membrane of the tympanum, when the operator ſhould deſiſt, leſt the membrane ſhould be wounded ; then the ſame kind of treatment may be followed as in the former caſe. The proper time for performing the operation is when children uſually begin to ſpeak ; for previous to this the patient may be too weakly to bear it, and after this ſpeech would be impeded.</p><p>Sometimes the meatus externus is entirely wanting, in the temporal bone. For this an opening through the maſtoid proceſs has been propoſed ; but the operation, has not been performed, at leaſt in this country.</p><p>Children ſometimes puſh hard bodies into their ear, or different kinds of inſects occaſionally creep into it, ſo as to cauſe conſiderable uneasineſs. Subſtances lying near the outer end of the paſſage may generally be extracted by the ſmall forceps repreſented in (fig. 60.) ; but round, hard bodies ſituated deeper in the paſſage are more readily removed by a crooked probe. When inſects are deep ſeated in the ear, they ought firſt to be killed, by filling the passage with oil, or any other fluid which proves noxious to them, without hurting the tympanum. They may then be waſhed out by injecting warm water frequently by means of a ſyringe.</p><p>Wax is one of the moſt frequent cauſes of deafneſs, and it may be readily detected by looking into the ear in a clear ſunſhine.</p><p>Various methods have been propoſed for removing wax from the ear ; but one, not inferior to any, is to throw in frequently, by means of a ſyringe (fig. 61.), warm milk and water, or water in which a little ſoap has been diſſolved. Aſſiſtance may likewiſe be given here, by uſing along with the injection a blunt probe or fine hair pencil, by which the bottom of the paſſage may be cleared out. After the wax is removed, the patient ought to guard againſt the effects of cold by introducing a little wool for ſome time into the meatus. When deafneſs is owing to a deficiency of wax in the ear, a little oil of almonds, or even oils of a hotter nature, or ſoap, or galbanum &amp;c. have been of ſervice.</p><p>Purulent matter is now and then formed in the ears of adults, but oftener in thoſe oſ children. Sometimes it is produced by ulcers ſituated in the lining of the meatus, or upon the membrane oſ the tympanum. It ſeems to be merely a local affection, and does not, as many have ſuppoſed, originate from morbid humours of the ſyſtem. The remedies beſt calculated for removing it are ſuch as are of a moderately aſtringent nature, as a weak ſolution of ſaccharum ſaturni. A little of this may be dropped in two or three times a-day, but it is ſtill better to uſe a ſyringe. If the diſcharge has continued long, it may be proper, in addition to the other applications, to keep open a ſmall bliſter for ſome time in the neck, arm, or wherever it may be thought moſt convenient.</p><p>It ſometimes happens, particularly in old people, that, from expoſure to a ſtream of cold air, the tympanum becomes affected, and a noiſe is heard by the patient like the ruſhing of water. In other caſes the patient is incapable of accurately diſtinguishing the words of ſome persons ſpeaking in a'loud tone of voice ; or, in mixed companies, he hears only a confuſion of ſounds. Complaints of this kind frequently originate from a relaxation of the ſoft parts of the tympanum ; and though a complete cure is not very frequently performed, yet conſiderable advantage is ſometimes derived from the uſe of hot ſtimulating oils, and from keeping the part warm at the ſame time with a little wool. When deafneſs ariſes from affections of this nature, ſome aſſiſtance may be derived from collecting the ſound, ſo as to make a ſtronger impreſſion upon the internal ear. A variety of inſtruments have been invented for this purpoſe. Some uſe a convoluted tube as is repreſented in fig. 62, (ſee <hi rend="smallcaps">Trumpet);</hi> others a sort of cup, fig. 63. which is concealed under the hair, and fixed to the head with ſtraps.</p><p>In ſcrophulous habits, ſuppurations ſometimes occur in the neighbourhood of the ear, and penetrate into the external paſſage, or into the tympanum itſelf; after which it is not unuſual for the ſmall bones of the ear to loſe their connecting membrane, and to be discharged along with the matter, and for caries to enſue in the tympanum ; in conſequence of which a high degree of deafness is produced, which can never be removed. In ſuch a ſituation little elſe can be attempted than to preſerve the parts clean and free from ſmell, which is readily done by injecting a little warm milk and water morning and evening by means of a ſyringe. If this be neglected, the matter from the carious bones is apt to become offenſive ; and it commonly continues till the diſeaſed parts are either diſſolved and discharged, or probably during the life of the patient.</p><p>Beſides the affections which may ariſe in the meatus externus, and may be the cauſe of deafneſs, others may occur in or about the meatus internus or euſtachian tube, which may have in part the ſame effect, though by no mean in the ſame degree. Inflammation and its conſequences may</p></body></text></TEI>