<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T20:02:46Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ral or vegetable acids, ought to be the only drink ; motion of every kind, particularly of the part affected, ſhould be guarded againſt ; and the wound being gently covered with ſoft charpie, ought to be tied up with a bandage ſo applied as to produce a moderate degree of preſſure on the extremities of the divided parts.</p><p>As ſoon as a sufficient quantity of blood has been diſcharged, the wound being dreſſed, and the patient laid to reſt, a doſe of opium proportioned to the violence of the ſymptoms ought to be immediately exhibited. It ought to be remarked, however, that in all ſuch circumſtances, much larger doſes of the remedy are neceſſary than in ordinary caſes requiring the uſe of opiates. Small doſes, inſtead of answering any good purpoſe, ſeem frequently rather to aggravate the various ſymptoms ; ſo that whenever they are here had recourſe to, they ought always to be given in quantities ſufficient for the intended effect.</p><p>But hæmorrhagies of this nature happen much more frequently in relaxed enfeebled habits, where the ſolids have loſt part of their natural firmneſs, and the fluids have acquired a morbid tenuity. In this caſe a moderate uſe of generous wine ought to be immediately prescribed ; for nothing tends ſo much, in ſuch circumſtances, to reſtrain hæmorrhagies, as a well directed uſe of proper cordials. By tending to invigorate and brace the ſolids, they enable the arterial ſyſtem to give a due reſiſtance to the contained fluids ; and have alſo a conſiderable influence in reſtoring to the fluids that viſcidity of texture, of which in all ſuch inſtances we ſuppoſe them to be deprived.</p><p>A nouriſhing diet alſo becomes proper ; the patient ought to be kept cool ; and the mineral acids, from their known utility in every ſpecies of hæmorrhagy, ought alſo to be prescribed. Reſt of body is here alſo proper ; and opiates, when indicated either by pain or ſpaſmodic affections of the muſcles, ought never to be omitted.</p><p>Together with theſe remedies adapted to the general ſyſtem, particular dreſſings, appropriated to the ſtate of the parts to which they are to be applied, have been found very beneficial. In healthy conſtitutions, ſoon after the diſcharge of blood is over, the parts are covered with a viſcid coagulable effuſion from the mouths of the now retracted arteries ; but in conſtitutions of an oppoſite nature, where the solids are much relaxed, the blood in general is found in ſuch an attenuated ſtate as to afford no ſecretion of this nature.</p><p>To ſupply as much as poſſible the deficiency of this natural balſam, different artificial applications have been invented. Duſting the part with ſtarch or wheat-flour has ſometimes been ſound of uſe, and gum arabic in fine powder has been known to anſwer when theſe failed.</p><p>Applications of this kind, indeed, have been uſed with ſucceſs in all ſuch hæmorrhagies, with whatever habit of body they happen to be connected ; but they have always proved more particularly ſerviceable in relaxed conſtitutions, attended with an attenuated ſtate of the blood and an enfeebled muſcular ſyſtem. Alcohol, or any other ardent ſpirits, impregnated with as great a quantity as they can diſſolve of mirrh, or any other of the heating viſcid gums, may be here uſed with freedom, though in conſtitutions of an oppoſite nature they ought never to be employed. The balsamum traumaticum of the shops, a remedy of this nature, has long been famous for its influence in ſuch caſes: but that indiſcriminate uſe of this and ſimilar applications which has long prevailed with ſome practitioners, has undoubtedly done much harm ; for as they are all poſſeſſed of very ſtimulating powers, they of courſe tend to aggravate every ſymptom in wounds connected with a tenſe ſtate of fibres, when much pain, and eſpecially when ſpaſmodic muſcular affections prevail.</p><p>By a due perſeverance in one or other of the plans here pointed out, it will ſeldom happen that hæmorrhagies of this nature are not at laſt put a ſtop to : but when the contrary does occur, when, notwithstanding the uſe of the remedies recommended, a diſcharge of blood ſtill continues; together with the means already adviſed, an equal moderate pressure ought to be applied over the whole ſurface of the sore, to be continued as long as the neceſſity of the caſe ſeems to indicate.</p><p>In finiſhing the dreſſings of ſuch wounds, after the charpie and compreſſes have been applied, a bandage properly adapted to the part ought to conclude the whole, and in ſuch a manner as to produce as equal a degree of pressure over the ſurface of the sore as poſſible. But it now and then happens that no bandage whatever can be ſo applied as to produce the desired effect ; and in ſuch caſes the hand of an aſſiſtant is the only reſource ; which being firmly applied over the dreſſings, ſo as to produce a very equal degree of preſſure, will commonly ſucceed when no other remedy is found to have much influence.</p><p>Wounds of the nerves, tendons, and ligaments, are attended with much more violent ſymptoms than thoſe where even conſiderable arteries are divided, and frequently reſiſt every method of cure propoſed by the moſt ſkilful practitioners. In the simple proceſs of blood-letting, it frequently happens that the tendinous expanſion called the <hi rend="italic">aponeuroſis</hi> of the biceps muſcle is wounded, or even the tendon of that muſcle itſelf is punctured, by the point of the lancet ; or ſometimes a nerve which happens to lie in the neighbourhood is partially divided. Any one of theſe wounds, though they are the smalleſt we can well ſuppoſe to be given, are frequently very dangerous and difficult of cure. It ſometimes immediately happens on the introduction of the lancet, that the patient complains of a moſt exquiſite degree of pain ; and when this occurs, we may reſt aſſured that either a nerve or tendon has been wounded. On ſome occaſions, by proper management, ſuch as evacuating a conſiderable quantity of blood at the orifice newly made, by keeping the part at perfect reſt, and preſerving the patient in as cool a ſtate as poſſible, the pain at firſt complained of will gradually abate, and at laſt go off entirely, without any bad conſequence whatever. At other times, however, this pain which occurs inſtantaneouſly on the introduction of the lancet, inſtead of abating, begins ſoon to increaſe ; a fullneſs, or ſmall degree of ſwelling, takes place in the parts contiguous to the wound ; the lips of the sore become ſomewhat hard and inflamed ; and, in the courſe of 24 hours or ſo from the operation, a thin watery ferum begins to be diſcharged at the orifice.</p><p>If, by the means employed, relief is not ſoon obtained, theſe ſymptoms generally continue in nearly the same ſtate for two or perhaps three days longer. At this time the violent pain which at firſt took place becomes ſtill more distreſſing ; but inſtead of being ſharp and acute as before, it is now attended with the ſenſation of a burning heat, which ſtill goes on to increaſe, and proves, during the whole courſe of the ailment, a ſource of constant diſtreſs to the patient. The fullneſs and hardneſs in the lips of the wound begin to increaſe, and the ſwelling in the neighbouring parts gradually extends over the whole members. The parts at laſt become exceedingly tenſe and hard; an eryſipelatous inflammatory colour frequently appears over the whole member ; the pulſe by this time has generally become very hard and quick ; the pain is now intense, the patient exceedingly reſtleſs ; twitchings of the tendons oc</p></body></text></TEI>