<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T20:03:59Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>are moſt effectual in allaying irritation ; as opiates, bliſters, and eſpecially warm-bathing. When theſe fail, cutting the gum by means of a sleme (fig. 48.), over the approaching tooth, is frequently found to remove every ſymptom ; but this ought to be done earlier than it commonly is to have the full effect. Whenever the ſymptoms give reaſon to think that a tooth is approaching, the gums ſhould be cut freely over that part where the teeth may be first expected. When the ſymptoms recur, the operation ſhould be repeated. A crucial inciſion is attended with ſtill more effect ; and the bleeding which afterwards takes place is of conſiderable ſervice. The inciſion ſhould always be carried as far as the tooth, which ought to be ſomewhat expoſed ; and when properly done, is frequently followed with immediate relief Sometimes the ſame kind of ſymptoms attend the cutting of the second ſet, particularly of the dentes sapientiae. When this is owing to the thickneſs of the gums, ſcarifying gives the greateſt relief; but ſometimes it is for want of room in the jaw, and then the tooth ſhould be drawn.</p><p>Derangement of the teeth happens more frequently in the ſecond than in the firſt ſet, and more commonly in the sore than in the back teeth. This may be owing to the firſt ſet remaining in the jaw after the ſecond have appeared. Another cauſe is a waſte of ſpace in the jaw ; and a third is a mal-conformation of the teeth, where they are too large in proportion to the jaw, and therefore overlope each other. The remedy is the ſame in each of theſe caſes, viz. to extract the teeth which ſtand in the way of the reſt, to allow thoſe which are out of their place to come into the row, and put on a more uniform appearance.</p><p>The uſual method of moving teeth which are out of the row is, by fixing them with a ligature to the neareſt teeth ; or the ſame thing is done by metalline plates or pieces of wire. But theſe methods have not been found fully to answer the purpoſe intended, though in ſome caſes they may be uſeful. When one or more front teeth are accidentally drawn out of the jaw, they ought to be immediately replaced. When the teeth are broken over or otherwiſe injured, they may be ſupplied with others tranſplanted from the jaws of another person; but this can only be done when the sockets have been newly emptied, for after inflammation comes on it is impracticable. In theſe caſes the inflammation muſt be allowed to ſubſide, and then artificial teeth can be readily adapted.</p><p>When the teeth are looſened by external violence, by falls and blows, or by improper uſe of inſtruments in pulling diſeaſed teeth in the neighbourhood of ſound ones, they may again be made tolerably faſt by preſſing them as firmly as poſſible into their ſockets, and preserving them ſo with ligatures of catgut, Indian weed, or waxed ſilk, and keeping the patient upon ſpoon-meat till they are firm. When looſe teeth are owing to tartar, nothing will faſten them till the cauſe be removed ; and this ought to be done early, otherwiſe it will have no effect. Frequently the teeth become looſe from a ſpongineſs in the gums, often, but improperly, attributed to ſcurvy. The beſt remedy is ſcarifying the gums deeply, and allowing them to bleed freely ; this ſhould be repeated till they are fully fattened. Mild aſtringents, as tincture of bark, are here attended with good effects, tho’ thoſe of a ſtrong nature will certainly do harm. The mouth ſhould be frequently waſhed with cold water ſtrongly impregnated with theſe, and the patient ſhould not uſe the teeth which have been looſe till they become firm again. The looſening of the teeth in old age cannot be remedied, as it is owing to a waiting of their ſockets, from which the teeth loſe their ſupport.</p><p>The teeth ſometimes become yellow or black without any adventitious matter being obſerved in them ; at other times they become foul, and give a taint to the breath, in conſequence of the natural mucus of the mouth, of part of the food remaining too long about them. The moſt frequent cauſe of foul teeth is the ſubſtance called <hi rend="italic">tartar,</hi> which ſeems to be a depoſition from the ſaliva, and with which the teeth are often almoſt entirely incruſted. When this ſubſtance is allowed to remain, it inſinuates itſelf between the gums and the teeth, and then gets down upon the jaw in such a manner as frequently to looſen the teeth. This indeed is by far the moſt common cauſe of looſe teeth, and when they have been long covered with this or with any other matter, it is ſeldom they can be cleaned without the aſſiſtance of inſtruments. But when once they are cleaned, they may generally be kept ſo by rubbing them with a thin piece of ſoft wood made into a kind of bruſh, and dipped into white-wine vinegar ; after which the mouth is to be waſhed with common water.</p><p>When the teeth are to be cleaned by inſtruments, the operator ought, with a linen cloth or with a glove, to preſs againſt the points of the teeth, ſo as to keep them firm in their ſockets, with the fingers of the one hand, while he cleans them with the neceſſary inſtruments, fig. 51. n⁰ 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, held in the other; taking care not to ſcrape them ſo hard as to looſen them, or to rub off the enamel. This being done, the teeth ſhould be rubbed over with a ſmall bruſh, or a piece of ſponge dipped in a mixture of cream of tartar and Peruvian bark. The ſame application may be made to the teeth for a few days, after which they may be kept clean as already directed.</p><p>The teeth are ſometimes covered over with a thin dark coloured ſcurf, which has by ſome been miſtaken for a waiting of the enamel, but which is only an extraneous matter covering it. By perſeverance this may be cleaned off as completely as where the teeth are covered with tartar ; but it is apt, after ſome time, to appear again. When this is obſerved, the ſame operation muſt be repeated.</p><p>For the purpoſe of applying powders or waſhes to the teeth, a bruſh or a ſponge is commonly employed ; the latter is certainly preferable, as being leſs in danger of wearing down the enamel, or of ſeparating the teeth.</p><p>The cauſes producing toothach may be, expoſure of the nerve of a tooth, by breaking or wasting of the enamel, inflammation in or about the tooth, or from ſympathy when diſtant parts are affected, as the eye, the ear, the ſtomach, or the uterus, as in time of geſtation. After toothach has once been produced and removed, it is apt to return by expoſure to cold, by taking hot liquids, by hard bodies preſſed againſt the nerve in the time of chewing, by the uſe of a pick-tooth, &amp;c.</p><p>With reſpect to the cure of this diſeaſe, no rule can be laid down which will anſwer with certainty upon all occaſions. No remedy has yet been diſcovered which will at all times even moderate the pain ; relief, however, is frequently obtained from acrid ſubſtances applied to the tooth, ſo as to deſtroy the irritability of the nerves, ſuch as opium, ſpirit of wine, camphire, and eſſential aromatic oils. When theſe fail, bliſters behind the ear, or deſtroying the nerve by the cautious uſe of ſtrong acids, or by a red hot wire frequently applied to the part, have been attended with advantage.</p><p>When a black or mortified ſpot appears on a tooth, it it be quite superficial, it may be removed ; but if it go through the thickneſs of the enamel, it will be more adviſable to let it remain.</p><p>When a ſmall hole breaks out in a tooth, particular attention ſhould be paid to prevent the admiſſion of air. Tin, lead, or gold-leaf, commonly employed for this purpoſe, ſometimes give relief for many months, or even years ; but</p></body></text></TEI>