<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T20:02:44Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>at the ſame time, inſtead of laudable pus, a thin ill-coloured and fetid ichor is diſcharged. In this caſe the lips of the wound loſe their beautiful pearl colour, and become callous and white, nor does the cicatrizing of the wound at all advance. When this happens in a healthy patient, it generally proceeds from ſome improper management, especially the making uſe of too many emollient and relaxing medicines, an immoderate uſe of balſams and ointments. Frequently nothing more is requisite for taking down this fungus than dreſſing with dry lint ; at other times deſiccative powders, ſuch as calamine, tutty, calcined alum, &amp;c. will be necessary ; and ſometimes red precipitate mercury muſt be uſed. This laſt, however, is apt to give great pain, if ſprinkled in its dry ſtate upon the wound ; it is therefore moſt proper to grind it with ſome yellow baſilicon ointment, which makes a much more gentle, though at the ſame time an efficacious escharotic. Touching the overgrown parts with blue vitriol is alſo found very effectual.</p><p>Hitherto we have conſidered the wounded patient as otherwiſe in a ſtate of perfect health ; but it muſt be obſerved, that a large wound is capable of diſordering the ſyſtem to a great degree, and inducing dangerous diſeaſes which did not before exiſt.— If the patient is ſtrong and vigorous, and the pain and inflammation of the wound great, a conſiderable degree of fever may ariſe, which it will be neceſſary to check by bleeding, low diet, and other parts of the antiphlogiſtſe regimen, at the ſame that the inflamed lips of the wound and parts adjacent are to be treated with emollient fomentations or cataplaſms till the pain and swelling abate. On the other hand, it may happen, when the patient is of a weak and lax habit, that the vis vitæ may not be ſufficient to excite ſuch an inflammation in the wound as is abſolutely necessary for its cure. In this caſe, the edges of the wound look pale and soft ; the wound itſelf ichorous and bloody, without any ſigns of fleshy granulations ; or if any new fleſh shoots up, it is of the fungous glassy kind above-mentioned. To ſuch wounds all external applications are vain ; it is neceſſary to ſtrengthen the patient by proper internal remedies, among which the bark has a principal place, until the wound begins to alter its appearance. In ſuch persons, too, there is ſome danger of a hectic fever by the abſorption of matter into the body when the wound is large ; and this will take place during the courſe of the cure, even when the appearances have been at firſt as favourable as could be wiſhed. This happens generally when the wound is large, and a great quantity of matter formed : for by this diſcharge the patient is weakened ; ſo that the pus is no ſooner formed, than it is by the abſorbent veſſels re-conveyed into the body, and feveriſh heats immediately affect the patient. For this the beſt remedy is to exhibit the bark copiouſly, at the ſame time ſupporting the patient by proper cordials and nouriſhing diet. Indeed, in general, it will be found, that, in the caſe of wounds of any conſiderable magnitude, a more full and nouriſhing regimen is required than the patient, even in health, has been accuſtomed to ; for the diſcharge of pus alone, where the quantity is conſiderable, proves very debilitating, if the patient is not ſtrengthened by proper diet. And it is conſtantly found, that the cure of inch sores goes on much more eaſily when the patient is kept in his usual habit of body, than when his ſyſtem is much emaciated by a very low allowance ; and, for the ſame reaſon, purgatives, and whatever elſe tends to weaken the conſtitution, are improper in the cure of wounds.</p><p>Hæmorrhagies very frequently happen in wounds, either from a diviſion of one large artery, or of a number of shall ones. In this caſe, the firſt ſtep to be taken by the ſurgeon is to effect a temporary ſtoppage of the blood by means of compreſſion. He is then to tie up all the veſſels in the manner to be afterwards deſcribed.</p><p>When the principal arteries of a wound have been tied, and a little blood continues to be diſcharged, but appears to come from sundry ſmall veſſels only, an experienced ſurgeon is induced to think, that the neceſſary compreſſion of the bandages will in all probability effect a total ſtoppage of the hæmorrhagy. In a general oozing of a ſmall quantity of blood from the whole ſurface of a sore, and when no particular veſſel can be diſtinguiſhed, there is a neceſſity for truſting to this remedy; but whenever an artery can be discovered, of whatever ſize it may be, it ought unqueſtionably to be ſecured by a ligature. But it frequently happens, that conſiderable quantities of blood are diſcharged, not from any particular veſſel, but from all the ſmall arteries over the ſurface of the ſore. In wounds of great extent, particularly after the extirpation of cancerous breaſts, and in other operations where extensive sores are left, this ſpecies of hæmorrhagy often proves very troubleſome by being exceedingly difficult to ſuppreſs.</p><p>Bleedings oſ this kind seem evidently to proceed from two very different and oppoſite cauſes. F<hi rend="italic">irst,</hi> Either from too great a quantity of blood contained in the veſſels, or from an over degree oſ tone in the veſſels themſelves; or, perhaps, from a combination of both theſe cauſes. But, <hi rend="italic">ſecondly,</hi> Such evacuations undoubtedly happen moſt frequently in ſuch conſtitutions as are very relaxed and debilitated ; either from a particular ſtate of the blood, or from a want of tone in the containing veſſels, or, in ſome inſtances, from a concurrence of both.</p><p>In conſtitutions perfectly healthy, on the occurrence of wounds even of the moſt extenſive nature, as ſoon as the larger arteries are ſecured, all the ſmall vessels which have been divided are diminiſhed, not only in their diameters, but alſo in their length; in conſequence of which, they recede conſiderably within the ſurface of the ſurrounding parts. This cauſe oſ itſelf would probably, in the greateſt number of inſtances, prove ſufficient for reſtraining all loſs of blood from the smaller arteries. Another very powerful agent however is provided by nature for producing the same effect. From the extremities of the divided veſſels which at firſt diſcharged red blood only, there now, in their contracted ſtate, oozes out a more thin, though viſcid fluid, containing a great proportion of the coagulable parts of the blood; and this being equally diſtributed over the ſurface of the wound, by its balsamic agglutinating powers has a very conſiderable influence in reſtraining all ſuch hæmorrhagies.</p><p>When a tedious oozing occurs in a patient young and vigorous, and where the tone of the muſcular fibres is evidently great, the moſt effectual means of putting a stop to the diſcharge is to relax the vascular ſyſtem, either by opening a vein in ſome other part, or, what gives ſtill more immediate relief, by untying the ligature on one of the principal arteries of the part, ſo as to allow it to bleed freely : thoſe violent ſpasſmodic twitchings too, ſo frequent after operations on any of the extremities, when they do not depend on a nerve being included in the ligature with the artery, are in this manner more effectually relieved than by any other means.</p><p>By the ſame means the patient, from being in a febrile heat and much confused, ſoon becomes very tranquil : the violent puliation of the heart and larger arteries abates, and the blood not being propelled with ſuch impetuoſity into the smaller veſſels of the part, they are thereby left at more liberty to retract. In the mean time the patient ought to be kept exceedingly cool ; wine and other cordials ſhould be rigidly avoided ; cold water, acidulated either with the mine</p></body></text></TEI>