<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T20:03:17Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>With reſpect to the treatment.·—As long as they remain ſtationary, they are not to be touched ; but when they continue to grow, we ought to uſe aſtringent remedies, eſpecially a ſtrong ſolution of alum, a decoction of oak bark, vinegar, ardent ſpirits, &amp;c. The ſofter kinds of polypi may frequently be prevented for a long time from increaſing in ſize, and ſometimes they even become conſiderably ſmaller. Mercury has been found rather to make them worſe ; cauſtic and other corroding applications have been of uſe in the ſofter kind, though they have not produced a cure. Setons have likewiſe been uſed with little advantage. It is therefore found neceſſary to have recourſe to a more effectual practice; and with this view the knife, ſciſſars, forceps, or ligature, are more generally recommended. The knife and ſciſſars may be uſed when the roots of the tumor can be readily come at ; but polypi are ſeldom ſo ſituated as to render exciſion practicable ; and even when they are, the hemorrhagy may be attended with conſiderable danger. The removal of a polypus by tearing or twitting it with the forceps, Plate CCCCLXXXVΠ. fig. 4. is occaſionally practiſed; but as ligatures are leſs painful, and fully as effectual, they are now more generally employed. The ligatures conſiſt of wire, catgut, ſilk cord, &amp;c. Different methods have been employed for paſſing theſe over polypi, according to their different ſituations.</p><p>When the ligature is to be applied, it is to be passed double over the tumor, and conducted to the root of it by means of the fingers or by ſlit probes, as in Plate CCCCLXXXVII. fig. 5. or rings, Plate CCCCLXXXVII. fig. 6. as may be beſt ſuited to the ſhape and ſize of the paſſage. The ends of the ligature are then to be introduced into a ſingle or double canula, as in Plate CCCCLXXXVII. fig. 7. which is to be puſhed along the oppoſite side of the polypus till the end of the canula teach the root of it, when the ligature is to be drawn ſomewhat tight, and fastened to the canula which is to be left in the paſſage. The ligature is to be daily tightened till the tumor drop off. In this manner the largeſt polypus may be removed equally well with thoſe of a ſmaller ſize. Should any part of it remain, it may be destroyed by cauſtic, and different inſtruments are contrived ſor conducting this to the root of the tumor.</p><p>What has been ſaid of the treatment of polypi in general, readily applies to thoſe ſeated in the noſe, outer paſſage of the ear, the rectum, and the vagina. It likewiſe applies to thoſe in the throat ; only that inſtead of paſſing the ligature through the mouth, it is to be passed through one of the noſtrils. The operator is then to introduce one or two of his fingers into the mouth, and open the doubling of the ligature, which he is to paſs over the polypus, and having pressed it down to the root of it, to proceed as before directed.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Chap.</hi> VII. <hi rend="italic">Of Diſeaſes of the Bones.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">The</hi> bones, as well as the ſofter parts, are liable to be swelled, either throughout their whole length, or to have tumors formed on particular parts of them.</p><p>Exoſtoſis is one ſpecies of tumor of the bone. According to Mr Bromefield, no ſwelling ſhould be called ſo, but an excrescence continued from a bone, like a branch from the trunk of a tree. Under this head therefore is ranked the <hi rend="italic">benign node,</hi> which may be produced by external injury, ſuch as contuſions and fractures : it can hardly be called a diſeaſe, as pain ſeldom ſucceeds, but rather a deformity.</p><p>There are riſings or tumors observable on the bones which are often the conſequents of venereal virus, and are termed <hi rend="italic">tophi, gummi,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">nodes.—</hi>Tophus is a ſoft tumor in the bone; and ſeems to be formed of a chalky ſubſtance, that is intermediate between the offeous fibres. Theſe cretaceous extravaſations are ſometimes found on the ligaments and tendons, as well as on the bone ; and may ſometimes be taken out by the knife. We have many inſtances where chalk ſtones in gouty people make their way out through the skin of the fingers and toes.</p><p>Gummi is a ſoft tumor on the ſurface of the bone, between it and the perioſteum ; and its contents resemble gum ſoftened, from whence it has taken its name. Poſſibly, by obstruction in the nutrient veſſels of the bone, a rupture of ſome of them occaſions the ſerous liquor to eſcape, which, by making its way between the fibres of the bone, arrives at its ſurface ; and being detained by the reſistance of the perioſteum, its moſt liquid parts being evaporated, and the remainder condenſed by the inflammation, and conſequently this inelaſtic covering being ſtretched, it becomes inſpissated, and forms this ſpecies of exostosis<hi rend="italic">,</hi> as it is generally called. When this is the cauſe, and the indiſpoſition of the habit in general got the better of, pressure by a ſteel infiniment, adapted to the part affected, is the proper cure.</p><p>The confirmed venereal node has the appearance of a divarication of the oſſeous fibres, probably from ſome inſpiſſated humour obſtructing the nutrient veſſels, but not extravaſated ; this occaſioning an extenſion of the perioſteum, produces a violent pain, which, when nocturnal, is the characteriſtic of a venereal cauſe. When the perioſteum is thickened, but the bone not affected, a courſe of mercury, by attenuating the obſtructed humour, and fitting it to be carried out of the body by the proper outlets, will often produce a perfect cure : but when the bone itſelf is diseased, this method will fail. But here the diviſion of the extended perioſteum has been known to give perfect eaſe.</p><p>The uſual method, formerly, was to apply a cauſtic equal to the extent of the node, which being laid bare, required exfoliation before it could be cicatrized. If the inciſion is made early, that is, before matter be formed under the inveſting membrane, it ſeldom requires exfoliation ; and, as we often find that the bone itſelf is not affected, but only the perioſteum thickened, we may be deceived even after a careful examination : it is therefore proper that the patient ſhould be pretty far advanced in a courſe of mercurial unction before even the inciſion is made ; for, ſhould the tumor decreaſe, and the pain abate during the courſe, chirurgical aſſiſtance, with the knife, moſt likely may become unneceſſary.</p><p>A bone may become carious firſt in its internal parts ; and that from external injury, as well as from a vitiated ſtate of the animal-fluids. Authors ſeem not to agree as to the technical term for this kind of diſeaſe of the bones ; ſome calling it <hi rend="italic">cancer</hi> or <hi rend="italic">gangraena ossis ;</hi> others, <hi rend="italic">ſpina ventosa,</hi> from the pointed extuberances uſually attendant on this diſorder of the bone ; and ſome again <hi rend="italic">teredo,</hi> from the appearance of the carious bone, like wood that is worm-eaten.</p><p>It is univerſally allowed, that this diſeaſe takes its riſe from matter being formed either in the diploe, or in the marrow : whenever obſtruction is begun in the veſſels expanded on, or terminating in, the medullary cyſts, the conſequence will be inflammation, and, if not early removed, matter will form ; for this reaſon this caſe may be called <hi rend="italic">abscessus in medulla.</hi> Whenever, then, a patient complains of dull heavy pain, deeply ſituated in the bone, poſſibly conſequent to a violent blow received on the part ſome time before, though the integuments appear perfectly ſound, and the bone itſelf not in the leaſt injured, we have great reaſon to ſuſpect an abſceſſus in the medulla. Children of a bad habit of body, though they have not ſuffered any external injury, will often become lame, and complain of the limb being remarkably heavy ; and though not attended with acute</p></body></text></TEI>