<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T20:03:15Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>be adviſable to attempt extirpation, and that the patient ſhould rather trust to the common palliative treatment. When the tumor, however, is not much increaſed, if other remedies have failed, and the diſeaſe is advancing, a surgeon might be warranted in attempting its extirpation.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sect.</hi> VI. <hi rend="italic">Of Navi Materni, Corns, and Warts.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Nævi materni</hi> are thoſe marks which frequently appear upon the bodies of children at birth, and which are suppoſed to originate from impreſſions made on the mind of the mother during pregnancy. They are of various forms ; their colour is likewiſe various ; though moſt frequently reſembling that of claret or red port-wine. Many of theſe marks are perfectly flat, and never rise above the level of the ſkin : theſe do not require the aſſiſtance of ſurgery ; but in ſome caſes they appear in the form of ſmall protuberances, which frequently increaſe to a great ſize in the courſe of a few months. They appear to be sum and fleſhy. They ſometimes hang by ſlender attachments to the contiguous parts, but more generally they are fixed by broad baſes. They may be removed with as little danger as any other tumor of the ſarcomatous kind. They are ſupplied indeed more plentifully with blood than moſt other tumors are ; and even ſometimes they appear to be entirely formed by a congeries of ſmall blood-veſſels ; but the arteries which ſupply them may, for the moſt part, eaſily be ſecured by ligature. The operation ſhould never be long delayed ; for as the ſize of the veſſels corresponds with that of the tumor, they ſometimes are ſo large as to throw out a good deal of blood before they can be ſecured. In performing it, the tumor is to be cut out, the arteries taken up, and the remaining ſkin brought as well together as the nature of the part will allow, and kept ſo by adheſive plaſter or future. When the tumor is pendulous, and connected only by a narrow neck, it ſhould be extirpated by ligature.</p><p>Corns are ſmall hard tubercles, commonly ſituated on the toes or other parts of the feet, and ſometimes on the hands. They are of a horny nature. They proceed ſrom a diſeaſed ſtate of the cuticle, occaſioned by pressure. The part becomes hard and thickened, with a ſmall white ſubſtance in the centre, which has a dispoſition to become prominent. It likewiſe forms a depreſſion in the ſubjacent cutis vera, and ſometimes is ſaid to penetrate it. When corns are ſituated on parts much exposed to preſſure, they irritate the ſkin, and produce an increaſed ſenſibility of the part, and thus occaſion much pain. The beſt preventative of corns is the wearing of wide ſhoes, and avoiding every kind of preſſure ; and unleſs this be attended to, it will be found difficult to keep free from them. Various remedies are recommended ſor the cure or removal of corns. One is to bathe the part about half an hour in warm water, then to pare as much off them as poſſible without giving pain, and to apply over them any emollient ointment. If this treatment be frequently repeated, while preſſure from ſhoes is prevented, they generally fall off, and do not return if preſſure be afterwards avoided. Another method is to allow them to grow to ſome length through pieces of perforated leather, properly ſecured by plaſter or by any other means, and afterwards to cut round their root, by which they may for the moſt part be eaſily turned out. Or if ſuch irritating ſubſtances be applied to them as will raiſe a bliſter by ſeparating the cuticle from the cutis, the corn will be raised along with the cuticle, and may then be readily removed by a ſcalpel or ſcissars. The ſurface of the cutis being now expoſed, is to be healed like any other part that has been bliſtered.</p><p>Warts are ſmall, hard, indolent tumors, with a rough ſurface, appearing on different parts of the body, chiefly the hands and face, and more commonly in young people, When they appear in advanced life they are apt to degenerate into cancer, eſpecially when of a livid colour and with a ſmooth surface. If they do not prove troubleſome, nothing ſhould be done to them, as they generaly either fall off or waſte gradually away. When from their ſize or ſituation they require to be removed, this, if they are pendulous or have narrow necks, is eaſily done by ligature ; but if their baſes be broad, the ſcalpel or eſcharotic applications will be neceſſary. As few, however, will ſubmit to the former, the latter are generally employed. Eſcharotics of a mild nature give leaſt pain, and are leaſt apt to excite inflammation, which in theſe caſes it is difficult to remove, and are found to be quite ſufficient for the purpoſe. One of the beſt of theſe is crude sal ammoniac: it ſhould firſt be moiſtened in water, and then well rubbed upon the warts two or three times a-day. Liquid ſalt of tartar, and sometimes spirit of hartſhorn, has anſwered the ſame purpoſe : ſome recommend alſo the juice of onions.</p><p>Warts appearing on the penis as a ſymptom of venereal infection, are of the ſame nature, and to be cured by the ſame means. Mercury is of no advantage here, and commonly indeed does harm. When every other part of the diſeaſe is eradicated, the warts may generally be removed by waſhing them morning and evening in lime-water, or in a weak ſolution of ſaccharum ſaturni. They may be removed alſo by the knife, and the parts from whence they are cut afterwards touched with lunar cauſtic, to prevent them from returning : but when this method is practiſed, the operator ought to be certain that he has removed the wart entirely, for where part has been left the moſt formidable ſymptoms have ſometimes enſued.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sect.</hi> VII. <hi rend="italic">Of Polypi.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Polypi</hi> are pendulous, fleſhy, indolent tumors, ſo called from their ſuppoſed reſemblance to the animal of that name. They may be found in different cavities of the body, and originate from the lining membrane ; but thoſe which come under ſurgical treatment are found in the noſe, mouth, throat, and outer paſſage of the ear, and in the vagina and rectum. They are divided into two claſſes ; the one ſoft and compreſſible, the other extremely firm. Both of them bleed on being fretted or roughly handled. The ſoft kind ſhrivels and contracts in a dry atmoſphere, (this is particularly the caſe with thoſe of the noſe) ; but the firm are not affected by the influence of the weather. Their colour is commonly pale and tranſparent, and ſometimes a deep red.</p><p>The pain at the commencement of the diſorder is always inconſiderable ; but increaſes in thoſe of a hard nature as they increaſe in ſize. Sometimes polypi of this kind become unequal, and form ulcers over the whole ſurface, diſcharging fetid matter in conſiderable quantity. They are apt at this time, unleſs extirpated, to degenerate into cancer.</p><p>Moſt frequently they ariſe from local injury, or whatever tends to produce and ſupport an inflamed ſtate of the part. Scrophula and lues venerea, though conſidered by ſome authors as frequently giving riſe to them, ſeem only to be exciting cauſes ; for in lues venerea in particular, polypi when preſent remain after the diſeaſe is cured.</p><p>The prognoſis muſt depend much upon their ſituation and their conſiſtence. The ſoft kind being ſeldom painful, may be removed at any period with little danger; but the hard kind are generally not only painful, but more apt to degenerate into cancer, or to return after being removed. The ſoft kind therefore may be removed in general with ſucceſs; but when polypi of a harder nature exiſt, the prognoſis will be much more unfavourable.</p></body></text></TEI>