<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T20:03:03Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>matter, the cartilages and in conſequence thereof the bones, ſoon begin to ſuffer. The tendons of the flexor muscles, though very ſtiff and contracted, do not, upon diſſection, ſhow any ſigns of diſeaſe.</p><p>The above is an hiſtory of the mildeſt ſpecies of white ſwelling ; the more inveterate kind our author names the <hi rend="italic">ſcrophulous white ſwelling.</hi> In this the pain is commonly very violent ; more acute than in the former ; and, inſtead of being diffuſed, is confined to a particular ſpot, commonly the very middle of the joint. The ſwelling is commonly inconſiderable at firſt ; inſomuch that, on ſome occaſions, even when the pain has been very violent, little difference in point of ſize could be obſerved between the diſeaſed and the sound joint. The motion of the joint is attended with very great pain, and the tendons become ſtiff. As the diſorder advances, the pain becomes more violent, and the ſwelling incrcaſes, with an evident enlargement of the ends of the bones. The ſame elaſtic feel, together with ſimilar abſcesses, occur in this as in the laſt : but upon opening them they commonly diſcharge a thin fetid stuff ; the bones are found to be carious, and pieces of them are frequently diſcharged at the openings.</p><p>By the continuance of the diſorder, the conſtitution ſuffers, as in the first ſpecies of the diſeaſe ; and a diarrhoea with night-ſweats commencing, the patient is ſoon reduced to little more than ſkin and bone.</p><p>Upon ſuch joints being dissected in the firſt ſtages of the diſorder, the ſoft parts ſeem very little affected : but there is conſtantly obſerved an enlargement either of the whole ends of the bones, or of their epiphyſes ; frequently of thoſe on one side of the joint only ; in others, again, the bones on both ſides have been affected.</p><p>This enlargement ſometimes occurs without any other evident diſeaſe : but in general, and always in a more advanced ſtate of the complaint, the ſoft ſpongy parts of ſuch bones appear diſſolved into a thin, fluid, fetid matter ; and that too, in ſome caſes, without the cartilages which ſurround them ſeeming much affected. In process of time the cartilages are likewiſe diſſolved ; and then the matter of the bones and ſofter parts mixing together, ſuch ſwellings exhibit in that ſtate a ſtill more confuſed collection than is generally obſerved even in the worſt ſtages of the other ſpecies of the diſorder.</p><p>In the farther progreſs of this diſeaſe the ſurrounding ſoft parts likewiſe ſuffer : The ligaments become thickened, and the contiguous cellular membrane is fluffed with the viſcid glairy matter obſerved in the other ſpecies of the diſorder.</p><p>We come now to the conſideration of the different cauſes which tend to produce this diſeaſe. That the ligaments of the joints only are firſt affected in this disorder is rendered evident by diſſection. The thick glairy effuſions into the cellular membrane are probably occaſioned by an exudation ſrom the veſſels of thoſe ligaments that have been originally inflamed, as ſuch parts never furniſh a proper fluid for the formation of purulent matter : In the courte of the diſeaſe, indeed, abſcesses containing real pus always appear ; but never till inflammation has been communicated to the ſurrounding parts. We may conclude, therefore, that the firſt ſpecies of white ſwelling is always occaſioned by an <hi rend="italic">inflammatory</hi> or <hi rend="italic">rheumatic affection</hi> of the ligaments of ſuch joints as it attacks, from whatever cauſe ſuch inflammation may originally have proceeded.</p><p>The other ſpecies of the diſorder ſeems to be orignally an affection oſ the bones ; the ſurrounding ſoft parts coming only to ſuffer in the progreſs of the diſeaſe from their connection with and vincinity to theſe. This laſt ſpecies of white ſwelling generally begins without the patient being in the leaſt able to account ſor it : and from the effects which it produces on the bones attacked, appears to be a ſpecies of <hi rend="italic">ſpina ventoſa ;</hi> a diſeaſe of the bones probably of the ſame nature as ſcrophula is of the ſoft parts. Indeed, the appearances of the two diſorders, after making allowance for their different ſituations, are exceedingly ſimilar : they both begin with conſiderable enlargements or ſwellings of the parts, which generally end in ulcerations ; they both likewiſe frequently occur in the ſame perſon at the ſame time. This ſpecies of white ſwelling is generally either attended with other evident ſymptoms of ſcrophula ; or the patient, in an early period of life, has been ſubject to that diſeaſe ; or, which is nearly the ſame, he is deſcended ſrom ſcrophulous parents, and probably has the ſeeds of that diſeaſe lurking in his conſtitution. From all theſe circumſtances, it may with probability be concluded, that this ſpecies of white ſwelling is of a ſcrophulous nature: and since the other ſpecies of the diſorder is to be conſidered as an inflammatory affection, a thorough diſtinction between them is of very great importance ; it will not be improper therefore to give a ſhort enumeration of the ſeveral diagnoſtic er moſt characteriſtſe ſymptoms oſ each.</p><p>The pain in the firſt ſpecies is always, from the beginning, diffuſed over the whole joint, and ſometimes extends a conſiderable way along the muſcles that are attached to it : in the other ſpecies it is always at firſt, and ſometimes even when the complaint has been of conſiderable standing, confined to a very ſmall circumscribed ſpace. In the former, the ſwelling is always confined to the ſoft parts, and is from the beginning exceedingly evident : but in the latter, it is generally for ſome time hardly perceptible ; and when it appears the bones are the parts chiefly affected, the ſurrounding teguments coming only to ſuffer on a farther progreſs of the diſeaſe. Theſe are the chief local differences of the two ſpecies of this diſorder ; but ſome aſſiſtance in the diſtinction may likewiſe be obtained from the general habit oſ the patient, and from the manner in which the complaint may ſeem to have been produced. Thus, when ſuch ſwellings occur in young, ſtrong, plethoric, people, eſpecially in ſuch as have formerly been subject to rheumatiſm,they moſt probably will always prove of the mildeſt or rheumatic ſpecies of the diſorder: But when they appear in patients of ſcrophulous diſpoſitions, we need be under very little doubt in concluding them to be of a ſcrophulous nature.</p><p>The great utility of properly diſtinguiſhing the two different ſpecies of white ſwellings appears in no circumſtance ſo evident as in the treatment. In the one, there being ſome chance, by proper remedies, of being ſerviceable to the patient ; whereas in the other, viz. the ſcrophulous, it is not probable that art will ever be able to afford much aſſiſtance.</p><p>In the rheumatic white ſwelling, as it is always at firſt evidently of an inflammatory nature, conſiderable advantages are commonly obtained by a due attention to a proper cooling courſe. The firſt remedy which, with this view, ſhould be put in practice, is blood-letting immediately ſrom the part affected. Cupping and ſcarifying is here a principal remedy. The inſtrument ſhould be applied to each side of the diſeaſed joint ; on each side of the rotuula, for inſtance, when the knee is the part affected, and at leaſt eight or ten ounces of blood diſcharged ; and this to be repeated at proper intervals, once, twice, or oftener, according to the violence of the ſymptoms and ſtate of the patient’s ſtrength at the time.</p><p>Cupping is, in theſe caſes, much ſuperior to leeches, becauſe it is more expeditious, and becauſe of the ſwelling occaſioned by the application of any conſiderable number of</p></body></text></TEI>