<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>eb03-r03</title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ed by gentle degrees, and the diſtillation continued till 30 pounds of water are come over, which is generally done in about four or five hours ; this roſe-water is to be poured again on a freſſi quantity (40 pounds) of roſes, and from 15 to 20 pounds of water are to be drawn by diſtillation, following the ſame proceſs as before. The roſe-water thus made and cohobated will be found, if the roſes were good and freſh, and the diſtillation carefully performed, highly ſcented with the roſes. It is then poured into pans either of earthen ware or of tinned metal, and left expoſed to the freſh air for the night. The ottar or effence will be found in the morning congealed, and ſwimming on the top of the water ; this is to be carefully ſeparated and collected either with a thin ſhell or a ſkimmer, and poured into a vial. When a certain quantity has thus been obtained, the water and feces muſt be ſeparated from the clear effence, which, with reſpect to the firſt, will not be difficult to do, as the effence congeals with a flight cold, and the water may then be made to run off. If, after that, the effence is kept fluid by heat, the feces will ſubſide, and may be ſeparated ; but if the operation has been neatly performed, theſe will be little or rone. The feces are as highly perfumed as the effence, and muſt be kept, after as much of the effence has been ſkimmed from the roſe-water as could be. The remaining water ſhould be uſed for freſh diſtil-lations, inſtead of common water, at leaſt as far as it will go.</p><p>The above is the whole proceſs, as given in the Afia-tic Reſearches by lieutenant-colonel Polier ∙, of making genuine otter of roſes. But attempts (he ſays) are often made to augment the quantity, though at the ex-pence of the quality. Thus the raſpinga of ſandal-wood, which contain a deal of effential oil, are uſed ; but the impoſition is eaſily diſeovered, both by the ſinell, and becauſe the effential oil of ſandal-wood will not congeal in common cold. In other places they adulterate the otter by diſtiſting with the roſes a ſweet-ſcented graſs, wſhich colours it of a high clear green. This does not congeal in a flight cold. There are numerous other modes, far more palpable, of adulteration. The quantity of effential oil to be obtained from roſes is very precarious, depending on the ſkill of the diſtil. 1er, on the quality of the roſes, and the favourableneſs of the ſeaſon. The colour of the otter is no criterion of its goodneſs, quality, or country The calyxes by no means diminiſh the quality of otter, nor do they impart any green colour to it. They indeed augment the quantity, but the trouble neccffary to ſtrip them is ſuch as to prevent their being often uſed.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Ross,-Nobιe,</hi>  an ancient Engliſh gold coin, firſt ftruck in the reign of Edward III. It was formerly current at 6s. 8 cl. and ſo called becauſe ſtamped with a roſe. See Money.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Rosκ Wood.</hi>  See Aspalathus.</p><p>ROSETTO, a town of Africa, in Egypt, is plea-ſantly ſituated on the welt ſide of that branch of the Nile called by the ancients <hi rend="italic">Bolbιtinum,</hi>  affirmed by Herodotus to have been formed by art ; the town and caſtle being on the right hand as you enter that river. Any one that iees the hills about Roſetto would judge that they had been the ancient barriers of the ſea, and conclude that the ſea has not loſt more ground than the /pace between the hills and the water.</p><p>Roſetto is eſteemed one of the pleafanteſt places in Egypt ; it is about two miles long, and conſiſts only of two or three ſtreets. The country about it is moſt delightful and fertile, as is all the whole Delta on the other ſide of the Nile, exhibiting the moſt plea-ſant profpect of gardens, orchards, and corn-fie!ds, excellently well cultivated. The caſtle ſtands about two miles north of the town, on the weft ſide of the river. It is a ſquare building, with round towers at the four corners, mounted with ſome pieces of braſs cannon. The walls are of brick, caſed with ftone, ſuppoſed to have been built in the time of the holy war, though ſince repaired by Cheyk Begh. At a little diſtance lower, on the other ſide of the river, is a platform, mounted with ſome guns, and to the eaſt of it are the fait lakes, out of which they gather great quantities of that commodity. At ſome farther diſtance, Tailing up the river, we ſee a high mountain, on which ſtands an old building that ſerves for a w<hi rend="sup">r</hi>atch-tower. From this eminence is diſeovered a large and deep gulph, in form of a creſcent, which appears to have been the work of art, though it be now filled up, and diſcovers nothing but its ancient bed. Roſetto is grown a conſiderable place for commerce, and hath ſome good manufactures in the linen and cotton way ; but its chief bufineſs is the carriage of goods to Cairo, all the European merchandiſe being brought thither from Alexandria by ſea, and carried in other boats to that capital ; as thoſe that are brought down from it on the Nile are there ſhipped off for Alexandria ; on which account the Europeans have here their vice-conſulsand factors to tranſact their bufineſs ; and the government maintains a beigh, a cuſtomhouſe, and a garriſon, to keep all ſafe and quiet.</p><p>In the country to the north of Roſetto are delightful gardens, full of orange, lemon, and citron trees, and almoſt all forts of fruits, with a variety of groves of palm-trees ; and when the fields are green with rice, it adds greatly to the beauty of the country. It is about 25 miles north-eaſt of Alexandria, and 100 north-weſt of Cairo. E. Long. 30. 45. N. Lat. 31. 30.</p><p>ROSICRUCIANS, a name affumed by a ſect or cabal of hermetical philoſophers ; wſho aroſe, as it has been ſaid, or at leaſt became firſt taken notice of, in Germany, in the beginning of the fourteenth century. They bound themſelves together by a ſolemn ſecret, which they all ſwore inviolably to preſerve ; and obliged themſelves, at their admiſſion into the order, to a ſtrict obſervance of certain eſtabliſhed rules. They pretended to know all ſciences, and chiefly medicine ; whereof they publiſhed themſelves the reſtorers. - They pretended to be maſters of abundance of important ſecrets, and, among others, that of the philoſopher’s ftυne ; all which they affirmed to have received by tradition from the ancient Egyptians, Chaldeans, the Magi, and Gymnoſo-phiſts. '1 hey have been diſtinguiſhed by ſeveral names, accommodated to the ſeveral branches of their doctrine. Becauſe they pretend to protract the period of human life, by means of certain noſtrums, and even to reſtore youth, they were called <hi rend="italic">Immortales</hi>  ; as they pretended to know all things, they have been called <hi rend="italic">Iliuminati ; </hi>and becauſe they have made no appearance for ſeveral years, unlefβ the ſect of Illuminated which lately ſtarted up on the continent derives its origin from them, they have been called the <hi rend="italic">invijible brothers.</hi>  Their ſociety i$</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>