<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>eb03-r03</title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>paffed whole days wiſh him ; and when the hour of departure came, he left him with regret. He ſet ſo high a value on Ruyſeh’s cabinet of curioſities, that when he returned to Holland in 1717, he purchaſed it for 30,000 florins, and ſent it to Peterſhurgh.</p><p>In 1685 he was made profeffor of medicine, an office which he diſcharged wiſh great ability. In 1728 he got his tlu'gh-bone broken by a fall <hi rend="italic">in</hi>  his chamber. The year before this misfortune happened he had been deprived of his ſon Henry, a youth of talents, and well ſkiiled in anatomy and botany. He had been created a doctor of phyſic, and was ſuppoſed to have aſſiſted bis father in his diſcoveries and publications. Ruyſeh’s family now confiſted only of his youngeſt daughter. This lady had been early inſpired wiſh a paſſion for anatomy, the favourite ſeience of her father and brother, and had ſtudied it with ſucceſs. She was therefore well qualified to aſſiſt her father in forming a ſecond collection of curioſities in natural hiſtory and anatomy, which he began to make after the emperor of Ruſſia had purchaſed the ſirſt. Ruyſch is ſaid to have been of ſo healthy a conſtitution, that though he lived to the age of 93, yet during that long period he did not labour under the infirmities of diſeaſe above a month. From the time he broke his thigh he was indeed diſabled from walking without a ſupport ; yet he retained his vigour both of mind and body without any ſenſible alteration, till in 1731 his ſtrength at once deſerted him. He died on the 2 2d of February the ſame year. His anatomical works are printed in 4 vols 4t0.</p><p>The ſtyle of his writings is ſimple and conciſe, but ſometimes inaccurate. Inſtruction, and not oſtentation, ſeems to be his only aim. In anatomy he undoubtedly made many diſcoveries ; but from not being ſuſſiciently converſant in the writings of other anatomiſts, he publiſhed as diſcoveries wſhat had been known before. The academy of ſciences at Paris in 1727 elected him a member in place of Sir Iſaac Newton, who was lately deceaſed. He was alſo a member of ſhe Royal Society of London.</p><p>RUYTER (Michael Adrian), a diſtinguiſhed naval officer, was born at Fleſſingue, a town oſ Zealand, in 1607. He entered on a ſea-faring life when he was only 11 years old, and w<hi rend="sup">,</hi>as ſirſt a cabin-boy. While he advanced ſucceſſively to ſhe rank of mate, maſter, and captain, he acquitted himſelf wfith ability and honour in all theſe employments. He repulfed the Iriſh, wſho attempted to take Dublin out of the hands of' the Eng-liſh. He made eight voyages to the Weſt Indies and ten to Brazil. He was then promoted to the rank of rear-admiral, and ſent to aſſiſt the Portugueſe againſt the Spaniards. When the enemy came in fight, he advanced boldly to meet them, and gave ſuch unqueſtionable proofs of valour as drew from ſhe Portugueſe monarch the warmeſt applauſe. His gallantry was ſtill more conſpicuous before Salee, a towm of Barbary. Wiſh one ſingle veffel he ſailed through the roads of that place in defiance of five Algerine Corſairs wſho came to attack him.</p><p>In 1Ç53 a ſquadron qf ſeventy veſſels was diſpatched againſt the Engliſh under the command of Van Tromp. Ruyter, who accompanied the admiral in this expedition, ſeconded him with great ſkill and bravery in the three battles wſhich the Engliſh ſo glorioufly won. He was afterwards ſtationed in the Mediterranean, where</p><p>he captured* ſeveral Turkiſh veſſels. In 1659 lie received a commiſſion to join the king of Denmark in his war with the Swedes; and he not only maintained his former reputation, but even raiſed it higher. As the reward of his ſervices, the king of Denmark ennobled him and gave him a penſion. In 1661 he run aſhore a veffel belonging to Tunis, releaſed 40 Chriſtian flaves, made a treaty with the Tιιnilians, and reduced the Algerine corſairs to ſubmiſſion. FI is country, as a teiti-mony of her gratitude for ſuch illuſtrious ſervices, raiſed him to ſhe rank of vice-admiral and commander in chief. To the latter dignity, the higheſt that could be conferred upon him, he was well intitled by the ſignal victory which he obtained over the combined fleets of France and Spain. This battle was fought in 1672 about the. time oſ the conqueſt of Holland. The fight w<hi rend="sup">r</hi>as maintained between the Engliſh and Dutch with the ob∙-ſtinate bravery of nations which were accuſtomed to diſpute the empire of the main. Ruyter having thus made himſelf maſter of the ſea, conducted a fleet of Indiamen ſafely into the Texel 4 thus defending and enriching his country, while it was become the prey of hoſtile invaders. The next year he had three engagements wiſh the fleets of France and England, in which,, if poſſible, his bravery was ſtill more diſtinguiſhed than, ever. D’Eſtrees the French vice-admiral wrote to Colbert in theſe words : “ I would purchaſe with my life the glory of De Ruyter.” But he did not long enjoy the triumphs which he had ſo honourably won. Inara engagement with the French fleet off the coaſt of Sicily, he loſt the day, and received a mortal wound, which put an end to hi? life in a few days. His corpſe was carried to Amſterdam, and a magnificent monument was there erected by ſhe command of the ſtates-general. The Spaniſh council beſtowed on him the title of duke, and tranſmitted a patent inveſting him with that dignity ; but he died before it arrived.</p><p>When ſome perſon was congratulating Louis XIV, upon De Ruyter’s death, telling him he had now got rid of one dangerous enemy ; he replied, “ Every one muſt be lorry at the death of ſo great a man.”</p><p>RYE, in botany. See Secale.</p><p><hi rend="italic">RTE Graſs.</hi>  See <hi rend="smallcaps">Agriculture, n</hi><hi rend="sup">0</hi>  179.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Rye, a town in Suſſex, with two markets on Wed-neſdays and Saturdays, but no fair. It is. one of the cinque-ports; is a handſome w</hi><hi rend="sup">r</hi>elkbuilt place, governed by a mayor and jurats, and ſends two members to parliament. It has a church built with ſtone, and a town-hall ; and conſiſts of three ſtreets, paved with ſtone. One ſide of ſhe town has been walled in, and the other is guarded by the ſea. It has two gates, and is a place of conſiderable trade in the ſhipping way. From thence large quantities of corn are exported, and many of the inhabitants are ſiſhermen. It is 34 miles ſouth-eaſt by ſouth of Tunbridge, and 64 on the ſame point from London. The mouth off the harbour is of late choaked up wfith fand ; but if well opened, it would be a good ſtation for privateers that cruize againſt the French. E. Long. o. 50. N. Lat. 51. o.</p><p>RYMER (Thomas I, Eſq; the author of the <hi rend="italic">Fader a, </hi>was born in ſhe north of England, and educated at the grammar-ſchool of Northallerton. He was admitted a ſeholar at Cambridge, then became a member of Gray’s Inn, and at length w<hi rend="sup">,</hi>as appointed hιitoriographer to King William in place of Mr Shadwell. He wrote A</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>