<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>eb03-r03</title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>perſon will perceive by attending to its conſtruction {See <hi rend="italic">Price,</hi>  Plate OP).</p><p>Fig. 28. repreſents a dome executed irι the Regiſter Office in Edinburgh by James and Robert Adams, and is very agreeable to mechanical principles. The ſpan is 50 feet clear, and the thickneſs is only 4⅛.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">We cannot take leave of the ſubject without taking ſome notice of wlιat we have already ſpoken of with commendation by the name of </hi><hi rend="italic">Norman roofs.</hi>  We called them <hi rend="italic">Norman,</hi>  becauſe they were frequently executed by that people ſoon after their eſtabliſhment in Italy and other parts of the ſouth of Europe, and became the prevailing taſte in all the great baronial caſ-tles. Their architects were rivals to the Saracens and Moors, who about that time built many Chriſtiari churches ; and the architecture which we now call Gothic ſeems to have ariſen from their joint labours.</p><p>The principle of a Norman roof is extremely ſimple. The rafters all butted on joggled king-poſts AF, BG, CH, &amp;c. (fig. 29.), and braces or ties were then diſpoſed in the intervals. In the middle of the roof HB and HD are evidently ties in a ſtate of extenſion, while the poſt CH is compreſſed by them. Towards the walls on each ſide, as between B and F, and between F and L, they are braces, and are compreſſed. The ends of the poſts were generally ornamented with knots of flowers, emboſſed globes, and the like, and the whole texture of the truſs was exhibited and dreſſed out.</p><p>This conſtruction admits of employing very ſhort timbers; and this very circumſtance gives greater ſtrength to the truſs, becauſe the angle which the brace or tie makes with the rafter is more open. We may alſo perceive that all thruſt may be taken off the walls. If the pieces AF, BF, LF, be removed, all the remaining diagonal pieces act as ties, and the pieces directed to the centre act as ſtruts ; and it may alſo be obſerved, that the principle will apply equally to a ſtraight or flat roof or to a floor. A floor ſuch as <hi rend="italic">a be,</hi>  having the joint in two pieces <hi rend="italic">a b, be,</hi>  with a ſtrut <hi rend="italic">bd,</hi>  and two ties, will require a much greater weight to break it than if it had a continued joiſt <hi rend="italic">a c</hi>  of the ſame ſcantling. And, laſtly, a piece of timber acting as a tie is much ſtronger than the ſame piece acting as a ſtrut : for in the latter ſituation it is expoſed to bending, and when bent it is much leſs able to withſtand a very great ſtrain. It muſt be acknowledged, however, that this advantage is balanced by the great inferiority of the joints in point of ſtrength. The joint of a tie depends wholly on the pins ; for this reaſon ties are never uſed in heavy works without ſtrapping the joints with iron. In the roofs we are now deſcribing the diagonal pieces of the middle part only act purely as ties, while thoſe towards the ſides act as ſtruts or braces. Indeed they are ſeldom of ſo very ſimple conſtruction as we have deſcribed, and are more generally conſtructed like the ſketch in ſig. 30. having two ſets of rafters AB, <hi rend="italic">a b, </hi>and the angles are filled up with thin planks, which give great ſtiffneſs and ſtrength. They have alſo a doublé ſet of purlins, which connect the different truffes. The roof being thus divided into ſquares, other purlins run between the middle points E of the rafters. The rafter is ſupported at E by a check put between it and the under rafter. The middle point of each ſquare of the roof is ſupported and ſtiffened by four braces, one of which ſprings from <hi rend="italic">e,</hi>  and its oppoſite from the ſi-milar part of the adjoining truſs. The other two braces ſpring from the middle points of the lower purlins, wſhich go horizontally from <hi rend="italic">a</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">b</hi>  to the next truſs, and are ſupported by planks in the ſame manner as the rafters. By this contrivance the whole becomes very ſtiff and ſtrong.</p><p>We hope that the reader will not be diſpleaſed with &lt; our having taken ſome notice of what was the pride of our anceſtors, and conſtitnted a great part of the finery of the grand hall, where the feudal lord aſſembled his vaffals and diſplayed his magnificence. The intelligent mechanic will ſee much to commend ; and all who look at theſe roofs admire their apparent flimſy lightneſs, and wonder at their duration. We have ſeen a hall of 57 feet wide, the roof of which Was in four diviſions, like a kirb roof, and the truffes were about 1<hi rend="italic">6</hi>  feet aſun-der. They were ſingle rafters, as in fig. 30. and their dimenſions were only eight inches by fix. The roof appeared perfectly found, and had been ſtanding ever ſince the year 1425.</p><p>Much of what has been ſaid on this ſubject may be applied to the conſtruction of wooden bridges and the centres for turning the arches of ſtone-bridges. But the farther diſcuſſion of this muſt be the employment of another article.</p><p>ROOFING, the materials of which the roof of a houſe is compoſed. See the foregoing article.</p><p>ROOK, in ornithology. See Corvus.</p><p>Rooks are very deſtructive of corn, eſpecially of wheat. Theyſearch out the lands where it is fown, and watching them more carefully than the owners, they perceive when the ſeed firſt begins to ſhoot up its blade ; this is the time’of their feeding on it. They will not be at the pains of ſearching for it at random in the ſown land, for that is more trouble than fo ſmall a grain will requite them for : but as ſoon as theſe blade» appear, they are by them directed, without loſs of time or pains, to the places where the grains lie ; and in three or four days time they will root up ſuch' vaſt quantities, that a good crop is oſten thus deſtroyed in embryo. After a few days the wheat continuing to grow, its blades appear green above ground ; and then the time of danger from theſe birds is over ; for then the ſeeds are fo far robbed of their mealy matter, that they are of no value to that bird, and it will no longer give itſelf the trouble to deſtroy them.</p><p>Wheat that is ſown ſo early as to ſhoot up its green blades before the harveſt is all carried in, is in no danger from theſe birds ; becauſe while it is in a ſtate worth their ſearching for, the ſcattered corn in the harveſt fields is eaſier come at, and they feed wholly on this, neglecting the ſown grain. But as this cannot always be done, the farmers, to drive away theſe ravenous and miſchievous birds, dig holes in the ground and ſtick up the feathers of rooks in them, and hang up dead rooks on ſticks in ſeveral parts of the fields : but all this is of very little uſe ; for the living rooks will tear up the ground about the feathers, and under the dead ones, to ſteal the feed3. A much better way than either is to tear ſeveral rooks to pieces, and to ſeatter the pieces over the fields ; but this laſts but a little while, for the kites and other birds of prey ſoon carry off the pieces and feed upon them. A gun is a good remedy</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>