<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>eb03-r03</title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>The earl defended himſelf with ſuch reſolution, that he had diſpatched one of the aggreſſors, when a gentleman paſſing that way took his part, and diſarmed another, on which the third ſought his ſafety in flight. This generous aſſiſtant was a diſhanded officer of good family and fair reputation, bpt reduced to poverty ; and his lordihip rewarded his bravery by refigning to him his poſt of captain of the guards. He at length returned to London ; when he was made matter of the horſe to the ducheſs of York, and married the lady Frances, eldeſt daughter of Richard earl of Burlington, who had been the wife of Colonel Courtney. He here diſtinguiſhed himſelf by his writings : and in imitation of thoſe learned and polite aſſtmblies with which he had been acquainted abroad, began to form a ſo-,ciety ſor refining and fixing the ſtandard of the Engliſh language, in which his great friend Mr Dryden was a principal aſſiſtant. This ſcheme was entirely defeated by the religious commotions which enſued on king James’s acceſſion to the throne. In 1683 he was ſeized with the gout ; and being too impatient of pain, he permitted a bold French empiric to apply a repelling medicine, in order to give him preſent relief; which drove the diſtemper into his bowels, and in a ſhort time put a period to his life, in January 1684. He was buried with great pomp in Weſtrmnſter-abbey.</p><p>His poems, which are not numerous, are in the body of Engliſh poetry collected by Dr Johnſon. His *<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Eſſay on Tranſlated Verſe,” and his tranſlation of <hi rend="sup">te</hi> Horace’s Art of Poetry,” have great merit. Waller addreſſed a poem to his lordſhip upon the latter, when he was 73 years of age. “ in the writings of this nobleman we view (fays Fenton) the image of a mind naturally ſerious and folid ; richly furniſhed and adorned with all the ornaments of art and ſcience ; and thoſe ornaments unaffectedly diſpoſed in the moſt regular and elegant order. His imagination might probably have been more fruitful and ſprightly, if his judgement had been leſs ſevere ; but that ſeverity (delivered in a maſculine, clear, ſuccinct ftyle) contributed to make him ſo eminent in the didactical manner, that no man, with juſtice, can affirm he was ever equalled by any of our nation, without confeſſing at the ſame time that he is inferior to none. In ſome other kinds of writing his genius ſeems to have wanted fire to attain the point of perfection ; but who can attain it ? He was a man of an amiable diſpoſition, as well as a good poet ; as Pope, in his * Eſſay on Criticifm,<hi rend="sup">,</hi> hath teſti-fied in the following lines :</p><p>--Roſcommon not more learn’d than good,</p><p>With manners generous as his noble blood ;</p><p>To him the wit of Greece and Rome was known,</p><p>And every author’s merit but his own.”</p><p>We muſt allow of Roſcommon, what Fenton has not mentioned ſo diſtinctly as he ought, and, what is yet very much to his honour, that he is perhaps the only correct writer in verſe before Addiſon ; and that, if there are not ſo many or ſo great beauties in his com-poſitions as in thoſe of ſome contemporaries, there are at leaſt fewer faults. Nor is this his higheſt praiſe ; for Pope has celebrated him as the only moral writer of King Charles’s reign :</p><p>Unhappy Dryden ! in all Charles’s days,</p><p>Roſcommon only boaſts uaſpotted lays.</p><p>Of Roſcommon’s woιks, the judgment of the public ſeems to be right. He is elegant, but not great ; he never labours after exquiſite beauties, and he ſeldom falls into groſs faults. Hrs verſi cation is ſmooth, but rarely vigorous, and his rhymes are remarkably exact. He improved taſte, if he did not enlarge knowledge, and may be numbered among the benefactors to Engliſh literature.</p><p>ROSE, in botany. See Rosa.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Eſſence oſ Rosis.</hi>  See <hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps">Poses Otter.</hi></hi></p><p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps">Rose</hi></hi><hi rend="italic">  oſ Jericho,</hi>  ſo called becauſe it grows in the plain of Jericho, though it did not originally grow there. It has perhaps been ſo named by travelers who did not know that it was brought from Arabia Petræa. Roſe buſhes are frequently found in the fields about Jericho; but they are of a ſpecies much inferior to thoſe ſo much extolled in Scripture, the flowers of which ſome naturaliſts pretend to have in their cabinets.</p><p>“ The roſe ſhrub of Jericho (ſays Mariti) is a ſmall<hi rend="sup">, </hi>plant, with a buſhy root, about an inch and a half in' length. It has a number of Items which diverge from' the earth : they are covered with few leaves ; but it is loaded with flowers, which appear red when in bud, turn paler as they expand, and at length become white entirely. Theſe flowers appear to me to have a great reſemblaace to thoſe of the elder-tree ; with this difference, that they are entirely deſtitute of ſmell. The ſtems never riſe more than four or five inches from the ground. This ſhrub ſheds its leaves and its flowers as it withers. Its branches then bend in the middle, and becoming entwined with each other to the top, form a kind of globe. This happens during the great heats ; but during moiſt and rainy weather they again open and expand.</p><p>“ In this country of ignorance and ſuperſtſtſhn, people do not judge with a philoſophical eye of the alternate ſhutting and opening of this plant : it appears to them to be a periodical miracle, which heaven operates in order to make known the events of this world. The inhabitants of the neighbouring cantons come and examine theſe ſhrubs when they are about to undertake a journey, to form an alliance, to conclude any affair of importance, or on the birth of a ſon. If the ſtems of the plants are open, they do not doubt of fuc-ceſs ; but they account it a bad omen to ſee them ſhut, and therefore renounce their project if it be not too late.</p><p>“ This plant is neither ſubject to rot nor to wither. It will bear to be tranſplanted ; and thrives without degenerating in any kind of ſoil whatever.”</p><p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps">Roses Otter</hi></hi>  (or eſſential oil of), is obtained from roſes by ſimple diſtillation, and may be made in the following manner : A quantity of freſh roſes, for example 40 pounds, are put in a ſtill with 60 pounds of water, the roſes being left as they are with their calyxes, but with the ſtems cut cloſe. The maſs is then well mixed together with the hands, and a gentle fire is made under the ſtill ; when the water begins to grow hot, and fumes to riſe, the cap of the ſtill is put on, and the pipe fixed ; the chinks are then well luted with paſte, and cold water put on the refrigeratory at top ; the receiver is alſo adapted at thè end of the pipe ; and the fire is continued under the ſtill, neither too violent nor too weak. When the impregnated water begins to come over, aud the ſtill is very hot, the fire is leſſen-</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>