<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>eb03-r03</title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ment, to which he ſubjoined an abſtract of his pro-</p><p>ſody.</p><p>Ruddiman next engaged in the management of a newſpaper, an employment for which his genius and in-duſtry ſeemed to render him well qualified. But thoſe 'who ſhould expect either much information or amuſe-ment from this publication, would perhaps be greatly diſappointed. The newſpaper wſhich he conducted was the Caledonian Mercury, and was eſtabliſhed in 1720 by William Rolland a lawyer^ Ruddiman acted only in 'the capacity of printer for five years ; but upon the death of Mr Rolland in 1729, the property was tranf-'ferred to him, or to his brother Walter and him con· 'junctly. This paper continued in the family of Ruddi-^man till the year 1772, when it was ſold by the truſ-■tees of his grandchildren to Mr John Robertſon.</p><p>The Caledonian Mercury was at firſt printed three times a week, on Monday, ſueſday, and Thurſday, in a ſmall 4t0 of four pages, with two columns in each page, and 50 lines in each column ; ſo that the whole paper contained only 400 lines. It now contains in its folio ſize 2480 lines.</p><p>Mr Ruddiman, after the death of Mr Spottiſwoode librarian, remained for ſome time in his former ſtation ; but was at length appointed keeper of the library, tho’ without any increaſe oſ ſalary; and ſome years after Mr Goodal, the defender of Queen Mary, ſucceeded him in the office of ſub-librarian.</p><p>The aſſiduous application of Ruddiman, ſupported by ſuch learning, was intitled to wealth, which now indeed flowed upon him in what was at that period deemed great abundance. On the iſt of October i735, it appeared from an exact ſtatement oſ his affairs, that he was worth L. 1882 : 5 : 2 Sterling ; and on the 20th ■of May, the enſuing year, his wealth had increaſed to L. 1985 : 6 : 3 Sterling. In 1710 he valued his effects at L. 24 : 14 : 9 Sterling.</p><p>In 1737 the ſchoolmaſters and teachers in Edinburgh formed themſelves into a ſociety, in order to eſtabliſh a fund for the ſupport of their wives and children. Of this ſcheme Ruddiman was an active promoter, and was choſen treaſurer. Perhaps it was this aſſociation which in 1742 gave the idea to the Scots clergy of forming their widows fund.</p><p>In 1739 he publiſhed <hi rend="italic">Seleftus Diplomatum et Num'f-inatum Scotiæ Theſaurus.</hi>  This work was projected and begun by Anderſon (hence called <hi rend="italic">Anderſon’s Diploma-ta),</hi>  but was finiſhed by Ruddiman. The preface, which is an excellent commentary on Anderſon’s performance, was written by Ruddiman, and diſplays a greater extent of knowledge than any of his other productions.</p><p>As Ruddiman had imbibed from his father thoſe political principles which attached him to the family of Stuart, he probably did not remain an unconcerned ſpectator of the civil commotions which in τ 745 agitated Scotland. He did not, however, take any active part in the rebellion. His principles, he has been heard to ſay, induced him to be a quiet ſubject and a good citizen. He retired to the country during the ſummer of 1745" ; and while his fellow-citizens were ſpilling each ethers blood, he was more happily engaged in writing Critical Obſervations on Burman’s Commentaries on Lucan’s Pharſalia. The Caledonian Mercury was in the mean time marked with a jealous eye. His ſon, who had for ſome time been the principal manager of that newſpaper, having copied a paragraph which was reckoned ſeditious from an Engliſh paper, was impri∙ ſoned. The ſolicitation of his father procured his re-leaſe : but it was too late ; for the unhappy young man had contracted a diſtemper in the tolbooth of Edinburgh which brought him to his grave.</p><p>During the laſt ſeventeen years of his life Ruddiman was almoſt inceſſantly engaged in controverſy. To this he w<hi rend="sup">τ</hi>as in ſome meaſure compelled by the violent attacks which ſome critics of the times had ſucceſſively made upon his works. He was firſt called upon by Benſon, auditor in the exchequer, to determine the comparative merit of Buchanan and Johnſton as poets. He gave a decided preference to Buchanan in perſpi-cuity, purity, and variety of ſtyle ;■ but, like a candid critic, allowed Johnſton to be ſuperior in the harmony of his numbers. His next antagoniſt was Logan, one of the miniſters of Edinburgh, a weak illiterate man, but an obſtinate polemic. The ſubject of conteſt was, whether the crown of Scotland was ſtrictly hereditary, and whether the birth of Robert III. was legitimate ? Ruddiman maintained the affirmative in both pointe, and certainly far ſurpaſſed his antagoniſt in the powers of reaſoning. He proved the legitimacy of Robert by the public records of the kingdom with a force of argument which admits of no reply ; but in diſcuſſing the firſt queſtion (by which he was led to confider the conteſt between Bruce and Baliol) he was not ſo ſucceſsful : for there are many inſtances in the hiſtory of Scotland in whjch the brother ſucceeded to the crown in preference to the ſon. He ſhowed, however, that the Scottiſh crown was at no period properly elective; and that, according to the old licentious conſtitution of the kingdom, the right of Bruce, who was the neareſt in blood to the royal ſtock, was preferable to the claim of Baliol though deſcended ſrom the eldeſt daughter.</p><p>But the labours of Ruddiman did not end when the pen dropt from the feeble hand of Logan. He was ſoon called upon to repel the attacks of Love ſchool-maſter of Dalkeith, who maintained, in oppoſition to him, that Buchanan had neither repented of his treatment oſ Queen Mary, nor had been guilty of ingratitude to that prmceſs. That Buchanan ever repented there is reaſon to doubt. Whether he was guilty of ingratitude, let the unbiaſſed determine, when they are aſſu-red by authentic records that Mary conferred on him a penſion for life of 500 pounds.Scots.</p><p>When Ruddiman had arrived at his eightieth year, and was almoſt blind, he was aſſailed by James Man, mailer of an hoſpital at Aberdeen, with a degree of rancour and virulence, united with ſome learning and ability, which muſt have touched him in a ſenſible manner, and alarmed his fears for his reputation after his deceaſe. He was called a <hi rend="italic">fimjhed pedant,</hi>  a <hi rend="italic">furious calumniator,</hi>  and a <hi rend="italic">corrupter of Buchanan's works.</hi>  The venerable old man again put on his armour, entered the lifts, and gained a complete victory. Man, with all his acuteneſs, could only point out twenty errors in two folio volμmes. Some of theſe were typographical, ſome trifling, and ſome doubtful. Ruddiman, with much pleaſantry, drew up againſt Man an account of 469 errors, conſiſting of 14 articles, of wſhich two or three may<hi rend="sup">r</hi>  be produced as a ſpecimen. 1. Falſehoods and prevarications,20.    2. Abſurdities, 69.    3. Paflages from</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>