<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>eb03-r03</title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>gaged upwards of 300 German artiſts, who were directed to repair to Lubec, in order to proceed from thence to Livonia, But the Lubeckers, who were very powerful at that time, and aimed at nothing leſs than the engroſſing of the whole commerce of the north, ſtopped them, and repreſented ſtrongly to the emperor, in the name of all the merchants in Livonia, the dangerous conſequence oſ thus affording inſtructions to the Ruſſians, who would ſoon avail themſelves of it to ruin their trade, and diſtreſs the ſubjects of his imperial majeſty. The workmen and others intended for Ruſſia were eaſily prevailed upon to return to their re-ſpective homes; and the czar’s ambaſſador was arreſted upon his arrival at Lubec, and impriſoned there at the fuit of the Livonians : however, he made his eſcape ſhortly after ; and the czar, though provoked to the laſt degree at the behaviour of the Lubeckers, was obliged for ſome time to ſuſpend his reſentment.</p><p>The firſt enterpriſe oſ Baſilovitz now was againſt the Tartars of Caſan, who had hitherto been ſuch formidable enemies. In this he was attended with great ſucceſs ; the whole territory was conquered in ſeven years ; but the capital, named alſo <hi rend="italic">Caſan,</hi>  being well fortified and bravely defended, made ſuch reſiſtance as quite diſheartened the beſiegers, and made them think of abandoning their enterpriſe.<hi rend="sup">i</hi>  Baſilovitz being informed of this, haſtened to them with a conſiderable reinforcement, endeavoured to revive their drooping courage, and exhorted them to puſh the ſiege with redoubled vigour. However, the greater part, deaf to all his remonſtrances, after loudly inſiſting upon a peace with the Tartars, and leave to return home, proceeded to mutiny, and fell upon their comrades who were for continuing the war. Baſilovitz, alarmed at this event, ruſhed in among the combatants, and with great difficulty parted them : but neither menaces nor intreaties, nor even a promiſe of giving them the whole plunder of the city if they took it, could prevail on them to continue the war. Their rage at laſt prompted them to threaten the life of their ſovereign ; who, to provide for his own ſafety, was obliged to make the beſt of his way to Moſcow ; and the mutineers, no longer regarding any command, inſtantly returned thither.</p><p>Baſilovitz, though juſtly incenſed at this inſolence, took a method of puniſhing it which does honour to his humanity. Having ſelected a guard of 2c00 of his beſt troops, he ordered a great feaſt, to which he invited his principal nobles and officers, to each of whom, according to the Ruffian cuſtom, he gave very rich garments. The chief of the ſeditious were clothed in black velvet ; and after the dinner was over, he made a ſpeech to the whole company, ſetting forth the behaviour of his troops before Caſan, their contempt of his commands, and their conſpiracy to take away his life : to which he added, that he was doubly ſorry to find the inſtigators of ſuch wickedneſs among thoſe who were ſtyled, and who ought to be, his faithful counſellors ; and that thoſe who knew themſelves to be guilty of ſuch atrocious wickedneſs could not do better than voluntarily to ſubmit themſelves to his mercy. Upon this, moſt of them immediately threw themſelves at his ſeet, and implored his pardon. Some -of the moſt criminal were executed, but the reſt were only impriſoned.</p><p>Immediately after this puniſhmeut of the rebels, Baſilovitz inarched with a freſh army to re-inveſt Ca* ſan before the Tartars had time to recover themſelves. The beſieged ſtill made an obſtinate defence, and the Ruſſians again began to be cliſpirited ; upon which the czar ordered his pioneers to undermine the walls of the citadel, a practice then quite unknown to the Tartars. This work being completed, he directed his prieſts to read a ſolemn maſs to the whole army, at the head of which he afterwards ſpent ſome time in private prayer, and then ordered fire to be ſet to the powder, which acted ſo effectually, that great part of the foundation was immediately blown up, and the Muſcovites ruſhing into the city, ſlaughtered all before them ; while the aſtoniſhed Tartars, crowding out at the oppoſite gate, croſſed the river Caſanka, and fled into the. foreſts. Among the priſoners taken on this occaſion were Simeon king of Caſan with his queen; both of whom were ſent to Moſcow, where they were treated with the utmoſt civility and reſpect.</p><p>Encouraged by this ſucceſs, Baſilovitz invaded the country of Aſtracan, the capital of which he ſoon reduced ; after which he prepared to revenge himſelf on the Livonians for their behaviour in flopping the German artiſts. John Baſilovitz I. had concluded a truce with this people for 50 years ; which being now expired, Iodocus, archbiſhop of Dorpt and canon of Munſter in Weſtphalia, ſenlible of the danger to which he was expoſed by the vicinity of the Ruſſians, requeſted the czar to give him a prolongation of the truce. .Baſilovitz deſired him to chooſe whether he would have a truce for five years longer, on condition that all the inhabitants of his archbiſhopric ſhould pay to him the annual tribute of a fifth part of a ducat for each perſon, which the people of Γ)orpt had formerly agreed to pay to the grand-dukes of Pleſkow ; or, for 20 years, on this farther condition that he and the Livonians ſhould rebuild all the Ruffian churches which had been demoliſhed in their territories at the time of the reformation, and allow his ſubjects the free exerciſe of their religion. Iodocus evaded an anſwer as long as he could : but finding at laſt that the affair grew ſerious, he levied a conſiderable ſum from his ſubjects, and fled with it to Munſter, where he re· ſigned his prebend and married a wife. His ſucceſlbr, whoſe name was <hi rend="italic">Herman,</hi>  and the deputies from Livonia, accepted of the conditions, and ſwore to obſerve them ; with this additional clauſe, that the prieſts of the Romiſh communion ſhould be exempted from paying tribute.</p><p>But though the Livonians ſwore to the obſervation of theſe terms, they were at that very time in treaty with GuſtavuS Vaſa, king of Sweden, to join them in attacking Ruſſia. <hi rend="sup">r</hi>Γhe king of Sweden very readily complied with their deſires ; upon which Balilowitz invaded Finland. Guſtavus advanced againſt him with a powerful army ; but as neither the Poles nor Livonians gave him any aſſiſtance, he was obliged to conclude a treaty with the czar, and ſoon after to evacuate the country. Finland was at this time governed by William of Furſtenberg grand-maſter of the Livonian knights, and the archbiſhop of Riga, with ſome other prelates ; between whom a quarrel happened about this time, which ſoon facilitated the deſigns of Baſilovitz on the country. The archbiſhop, after at</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>