<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>eb03-r03</title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>it is difficult to avoid, from the engaging manner in which Rouſſeau drags along his readers.” The paſe ſages in it wſhich have any reference to literature may be eaſily diſtinguiſhed, as they are treated with the agreeableneſs of a man of wit and *he exactneſs of a nian of taſte. Rouſſeau, ſoon after the rapid ſucceſs of his Village Conjuror, publiſhed a Letter <hi rend="italic">on</hi>  French Muſic, or rather <hi rend="italic">againfi</hi>  French muſic, written with as much freedom as livelineſs. The exaſperated partiſans of French comedy treated him with as much ſury as if he had conſpired againſt the ſtate. A crowd of inſigni-ficant enthuſiaſts ſpent their ſtrength in outcries againſt him. He was iniulted, menaced, and lampooned. Harmonic fanaticiſm went even to hang him up in effigy.</p><p>That intereſting and tender ſtyle, which is ſo conſpicuous throughout the Village Conjuror, animates ſeveral letters in the New Heloiſa, in ſix parts, publiſhed 176x, in I2mo. This epiſtolary romance, of which the plot is ill-managed, and the arrangement bad, like all other works of genius, has its beauties as well as its faults. More truth in his characters and more preciſion in his details were to have been wiſhed. The characters, as well as their ſtyle, have too much ſameneſs, and their language is too affected and exaggerated. Some of the letters are indeed admirable, from the force and warmth of expreſſion, from an eſſerveſcence of ſenti-ments, ſrom the irregularity of ideas which always cha-racteriſe a paſſion carried to its height. But why is ſo affecting a letter ſo often accompanied with an unimportant digreſſion, an inſipid criticiſm, or a ſelf contradicting paradox ? Why, after having (hone in all the energy of ſentiment, does he on a hidden turn unaffecting ? It is becauſe none of the perſonages are truly intereſting. That of St Preux is weak, and often forced Julia is ad affemblage of tenderneſs and pity, of elevation of foul and of coquetry, of natural parts and pedantry. Wolmar is a violent man, and almoſt beyond the limits of nature. In fine, when he wiſhcs to change his ſtyle, and adopt that of the ſpeaker, it may eaſily be obſerved that he docs not long ſupport it, and every attempt em-barraffes the author and cools the reader. In the He-loiſa, Rouſſeau’s unlucky talent of rendering every thing problematical, appears very conſpicuous; as in his arguments in favour of and againſt duelling, which afford an apology for ſuicide, and a juſt condemnation of it : in his facility in palliating the crime of adultery, and his very ſtrong reaſons to make it abhorred : on the one hand, in declamations againſt ſocial happi-neſs ; on.the other, intranſports in favour of humanity : here, in violent rhapſodies againſt philoſophers ; there, •by a rage for adopting their opinions : the exiſtence of God attacked by ſophiſtry, and Atheiſts confuted by the moſt irrefragable arguments ; the Chriſtian religion combated by the moſt ſpecious objections, and celebrated wfith the moſt ſublime eulogies.</p><p>His Emilia afterwards made more noiſe than .the new Helofia. This moral romance, which was publiſhed in' 176 &gt;, in four vols ιzmo, treats chiefly of education. Rouſſeau wiſhed to follow nature in every thing ; and though his ſyſtem in ſeveral places differs from received ideas, it delerves in many reſpects to be put in practice, and with ſome neceſſary modifications it has been ſo. His precepts are expreſſed with the force and dignity of a mind full oſ the leading truths of morality. 7f he has not always been virtuous? no body at leaſt</p><p>has ſelt ſt more, or made it appear to more advantage. Every thing which he ſays againſt luxury ſhows the vices and conceited opinions of his age, and is worthy at once of Plato or of Tacitus. His ſtyle is peculiar to himſelf. He ſometimes, however, appears, by a kind of affected rudeneſs and aſperity, to ape at the mode of Montaigne, of whom he is a great admirer, and whoſe ſentiments and expreſſions he often clothes in a new drtſſs. What is moſt to be lamented L, that in wiſhing to educate a young man as a Chriſtian he has filled his third volume with objections againſt Chriſtianity. He has, it muſt be confeſſed, given a very ſublime eulogium on the goſpel, and an affecting portrait of its divine Author : but the miracles, and the prophecies which ſerve to eſtabliſh his miſſion, he attacks without the leaſt reſerve. Admitting only natural religion, he weighs every thing in the balance of reaſon; and this reaſon being falſe, leads him into dilemmas veιy unfavourable to his own hepoſe and happineſs.</p><p>He dwelt from 1754 in a ſmall houſe in the country near Montmorenci ; a retreat which he owed to the generoſity of a farmer-general. The cauſe oſ his love for this retirement was, according to himſelf, “ that invincible ſpirit of liberty which nothing could conquer, and in competition with which honours, fortune, and reputation, could not ſtand. It is true, this defire of liberty has occaſioned leſs pride than lazineſs ; but this indolence is inconceivable. Every thing ſtartlesit; the moſt inconſiderable reciprocalities of ſocial life are to it inſupportable. A word to ſpeak, a letter to write, a viſit to pay, things neceſſary to be done, are to me pu-niſhments. Hear my reaſons. Although the ordinary intercourſe between mankind be odious to me, intimate friendſhip appears to me very dear ; becauſe there are no mere ceremonies due to it ; it agrees with the heart, and all is accompliſhed. Hear, again, why I have always ſhunned kindneſſes ſo much ; becauſe every act of kindneſs requires a grateful mind, and I find my heart ungrateful, ſrom this alone, that gratitude is a duty. Laſtly, that kind of felicity which is neceſſary for me, is not ſo much to do that which I wiſh, as not to do what I wiſh, not to do.” Rouſſeau enjoyed this felicity wſhich he ſo much wiſhed in his retirement. Without entirely adopting that too rigorous mode of life purſued by the ancient Cynics, he deprived himſelf of every thing that could in any meaſure 'add fuel to this wiſhed-for luxury, which is ever the companion of riches, and which inverts even cuſtom itſelf. He might have been happy in this retreat, if he could have forgot this public which he affected to deſpiſe ; but his deſire after a great name got the better of his ſelf love, and it was this thirſt after reputation which made him introduce ſo many dangerous paragraphs in his Emilia.</p><p>The French parliament condemned this book in. 1762, and entered into a criminal proſecution againſt the author, which forced him to make a precipitate retreat. He dire&lt;cted his ſteps towards his native country, which ſhut its gates upon him. Proſeribed in the place where he firſt drew breath, he ſought an aſylum in Switzerland, and found one in the principality of Neufchatel. His firſt care was to défend his Emilia againſt the mandate of the archbiſhop of Paris, by whom it had been anathematiſed. In 1763 he publiſhed a letter, in which he re-exhibits all his errors, let off with</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>