<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>eb03-r03</title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>the bolt at its inner end. We have been thus particular on this joint, becauſe it is here that the ultimate ſtrain of the whole roof is exerted, and its ſituation will not allow the excavation neceſſary for making it a good mortiſe and tenon.</p><p>Similar attention muft be paid to ſome other ſtraps, ſuch as thoſe which embrace the middle of the rafter, and connect it with the poſt or truſs below it. We muſt attend to the change of ſhape produced by the ſagging of the roof, and place the ſtrap in ſuch a manner as to yield to it by turning round its bolt, but ſo as not to become looſe, and far leſs to make a fulcrum for any thing acting as a lever. The ſtrains ariſing from ſuch actions, in framings of carpentry which change their ſhape by ſagging, are enormous, and nothing can reſiſt them.</p><p>We ſhall cloſe this part of the ſubject with a Ample ï method, by which any carpenter, without mathematical ſcience, may calculate with ſuſſicient preciſion the ſtrains or thruſts which are produced on any point of</p><p>his work, whatever be the obliquity of the pieces.</p><p>Let it be required to find the horizontal thruſt acting on the tie-beam AD of fig. 18. This will be the ſame as if the weight of the whole roof were laid at G on the two rafters GA and GD. Draw the vertical linc GH. Then, having calculated the weight of the whole roof that is ſupported by this ſingle frame ABCD, including the weight of the pieces AB, BC, CD, BE, CF themſelves, take the number of pounds, tons, &amp;c. which expreſſes it from any ſcale of equal parts, and ſet it from G to H. Draw HK, HL parallel to GD, GA, and draw the line KL, which will be horizontal when the two ſides of the roof have the ſame ſlope. Then ML meaſured on the ſame ſcale will give the horizontal thruſt, by which the ſtrength of the tie-beam is to be regulated. GL will give the thruſt which tends to cruſh the rafters, and LM will alio give the force which tends to cruſh the ſtrut-beam BC.</p><p>In like manner, to find the ſtrain on the king-poſt BD of fig. 17. confider that each brace is preſſed by half the weight of the roofing laid on BA or BC, and this preſſure, or at leaſt its hurtful effect, is diminiſhed in the proportion of BA to DA, becauſe the action of gravity is vertical, and the effect which we want to counteract by the braces is in a direction E <hi rend="italic">e</hi>  perpendicular to BA or BC. But as this is to be reſiſted by the brace ∕E acting in the direction/E, we muſt draw<hi rend="italic">ſe</hi>  perpendicular to E <hi rend="italic">e,</hi>  and ſuppoſe the ſtrain augmented in the proportion of E <hi rend="italic">e</hi>  to Ey<hi rend="sup">r</hi>.</p><p>Having thus obtained in tons, pounds, or other mea-ſures, the ſtrains which muſt be balanced at /by the co-heſion of the king-poſt, take this meaſure fιom the ſcale of equal parts, and ſet it off in the directions of the braces to G and H, and complete the parallelogram G/HK; and ∕K meaſured on the ſame ſcale will be the ſtrain on the king-poſt.</p><p>The artiſt may then examine the ſtrength of his ■ truſs upon this principle, that every ſquare inch of oak will bear at an average 7000 pounds compreſſing or ſtretching it, and may be ſafely loaded with 3j00 for any length of time ; and that a ſquare inch of fir will in like manner ſecurely bear 2500. And, becauſe ſtraps are uſed to reſiſt ſome of theſe ſtrains, a ſquare inch of well wrought tough iron may be ſafely ſtrained by 50,000 pounds. But the artiſt will always recollect, that we cannot have the ſame confidence in iron as in timber. The faults of this laſt are much more eafily perceived ; and when timber is too weak, it gives us warning of its failure, by yielding ſenſibly before it breaks. This is not the caſe with iron ; and much of its ſervice depends on the honeſty of the blacſk-ſmith.</p><p>In this way may any deſign of a roof be examined. We ſhall here give the reader a ſketch of two or three truffed roofs, which have been executed in the chief varieties of circumſtances which occur in common practice.</p><p>Fig. 22. is the roof of St Paul’s Church, Covent Garden, London, the work of Inigo Jones. Its conſtruction is ſingular. Tlιe roof extends to a conſiderable diſtance beyond the building, and the ends of the tie-beams ſupport the Tuſean corniche, appearing like the nιu-tules of the Doric order. Such a- roof could not reft on the tie-beam. Inigo Jones has therefore ſupported it by a truſs below it ; and the height has allowed him to make this extremely ſtrong with very little timber. It is accounted the higheſt roof of its width in London. But this was not difficult, by reaſon of the great height which its extreme width allowed him to employ without hurting the beauty of it by too high a pitch. The ſupports, however, are diſpoſed with judgment.</p><p>Fig. 23. is a kirb or manſaid roof by Price, and ſuppoſed to be of large dimenſions, having braces to carry the middle of the rafters.</p><p>It will ſerve exceedingly well for a church having pillars. The middle part of the tie-beam being taken away, the ſtrains are very well balanced, ſo that there is no riſk of its puſhing alide the pillars on which it reſts.</p><p>Fig. 24. is the celebrated roof of the theatre of the univerſityof Oxford, by Sir Chriſtopher Wren. The ſpan between the walls is 75 feet. This is accounted a very ingenious, and is a ſingular performance. The middle part of it is almoſt unchangeable in its form; but from this· circumſtance it does not diſtribute the horizontal thruſt with the ſame regularity as the uſual conſtruction. The horizontal thruſt on the tie-beam is about twice the weight of the roof, and is withſtood by an iron ſtrap below the beam, which ſtretches the whole width of the building in the form of a rope, making part of the ornament of the ceiling.</p><p>In all the roofs which we have conſidered hitherto the thruſt is diſcharged entirely from the walls by the tie-beam. But this cannot always be done. We frequently want great elevation within, and arched ceilings. In ſuch caſes, it is a much more difficult matter to keep the walls free of all preſſure outwards, and there are few buildings where it is completely done. Yet this is the greateſt fault of a roof. We ſhall juſt point out the methods which may be molt ſueceſsfully adopted.</p><p>We have ſaid that a tie-beam juſt perſorms the office of a ſtring. We have ſaid the ſame of the king-poſt. Now ſuppoſe two rafters AB, BC (fig. 25.} moveable about the joint B, and reſting on the top of the walls. If the line BD be ſuſpended from B, and the two lines DA, DC be faſtened to the feet of the rafters, and if theſe lines be incapable of extenſion, it is plain that all thruſt is removed from the walls as ef-</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>