<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>eb03-r03</title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>and almoſt all the reſt of his life attached himſelf to ſome of the great lords, He attended marſhal Tallard into England, in quality of ſecretary, and here contracted a ſriendſhip with St Evremond. At his return to Paris, he was admitted into the politeſt company, lived among the courtiers, and ſeemed perfectly ſatisſied with his ſituation ; when, in 1708, he was proſe-cuted for being the author of ſome couplets, in which the characters of ſeveral perſons of wit and merit were blackened by the moſt atrocious calumnies. This pro-ſecution made much noife ; and Rouſſeau was baniſhed in 1712 out of the kingdom, to which he was never more to return, by a decree of the parliament of Paris, However, he always ſteadily denied, and even on his death-bed, his being the author of theſe couplets.— From the date of this ſentence he lived in foreign countries, where he found illuſtrious protectors. The count de Luc, ambaſſador of France, in Swiſſerland, took him into his family, and ſtudied to render his life agreeable. He took him with him to the treaty of Baden in</p><p>1714, where he was one of the plenipotentiaries, and preſented him to prince Eugene, who entertaining a particular eſteem'for him, took him to Vienna, and introduced him to the emperor’s court. Rouſſeau lived about three years with prince Eugene ; but having loſt his favour by ſatiriſing one of his miltreſſes, he retired to Bruſſels, where he afterwards uſually reſided, and where he met with much attention and much generoſity, as we ſhall ſoon mention.— It was here that his diſputes with Voltaireeommenced,with whom he had become acquainted at the college of Louis the Great, who then much admired his turn for poetry. At that time Voltaire aſ-ſiduouſly cultivated the acquaintance of Rouſſeau, and made him a preſent of all his works ; and Rouſſeau, flattered by his reſpect, announced him as a man who would one day be a glory to the age. The author of the Henriad continued to conſult him about his productions, and to laviſh on him the higheſt encomiums, while their friendſhip daily increaſed. When they again met at Bruſſels, however, they harboured the blackeſt malice againſt one another. The cauſe of this enmity, as Rouſſeau and his friends tell the ſtory, was a lecture which he had compoſed from his Epiſtie to Julia, new Urania. This piece frightened Voltaire, as it plainly diſcovered his rage againſt him. The young man, vexed at theſe calumnies, underſtood the whole as thrown out againſt him. This is what Rouſſeau aſſerts. But his adverſaries, and the friends of the poet whom he cried down, ſuſpected him, perhaps rather raſhly, of having employed ſarcaſms, becauſe he thought that his own reputation was in danger of being eclipſed by that of his rival. What is very ſingular, theſe two celebrated characters endeavoured each of them to prepoſſcſs the public with a bad opinion of the other, which they themſelves never entertained in reality, and to ſmother in their breaſt that eſteem for each other which, in de</p><p>fiance of all their exertions, ſtill held its place. Rouſſeau, from the period of this diſpute, always repre-fented Voltaire as a buffoon, as a writer poſſelfing neither taſte nor judgment, who owed all his ſucceſs to a particular mode which he purſued. As a poet he confi-dered him as inferior to Lucan, and little ſuperior to Pradon. Voltaire treated him ſtill worſe. Rouſſeau, according to him, was nothing better than a plagiariſt, who could make ſhiſt to rhime, but could not make any reflections ; that he had nothing but the talent of arranging words, and that he had even loſt that in foreign countries. He thus addreſſes him, in a piece little known :</p><p><hi rend="italic">Aυffitδt le Dieu qui rrfinſpire T<hi rend="sup">,</hi>arracha le luth et la lyre lpu’avoient cléjhonorés tes mains ;</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Tu n’es plus qu’un reptile immonde,</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Rebut du Pamojſe et du monde</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Enſeveli dans tes venins.</hi></p><p>In conſequence of the little eſteem in which Rouſſeau was held at Bruſſels, he could never forget Paris. The grand-prior of Vendôme, and the baron de Breteuil&gt; ſolicited the regent duke of Orleans to allow him t© return ; which favour was obtained. But our poet, before he would make uſe of the <hi rend="italic">lettres de rapel</hi>  iſſued in his favour, demanded a review of his proceſs, which he wiſhed to be repealed, not as a matter of favour, but by a ſolemn judgment of court ; but his petition was refuſed. He then came over, in 1721, to England, where he printed <hi rend="italic">A Collection oſ his Works,</hi>  in 2 vols ι 2mo, at London. This edition, publiſhed in 1723, brouglu him near 10,000 crowns, the wholeof which he placed in the hands of the Oſtend company. The affairs of this company, however, ſoon getting into contuſion, all thoſe who had any money in their hands loſt the whoſe of it, by wſhich unfortunate event Rouſſeau, when arrived at that age when he ſtood moſt in need of the comforts of fortune, had nothing to depend upon but the generoſity of ſome tnends. Boutet, public notary in Paris, was peculiarly generous and attentive to him. He found a ſtill greater aſylum in the Duke d’Arem-berg, whoſe table was open to him at all times ; who being obliged in 1733 to go into the army in Germany, ſettled on him a penſion of 1500 livres. But unfortunately he ſoon loſt his good opinion, having been-Jm-prudent enough to publiſh in a Journal (of which Voltaire accuſed him), that the duke d’Aremberg was the author of thoſe verſes for which he himſelf had been baniſhed France. He was therefore diſmiſſed from his table, and his pride would not allow him to accept of the penſion after this rupture. Bruſſels now became inſupportable to him ; and the count du Luc, and M. de Senozan, receiver-general of the church revenue, being informed of his difappointments,. invited him to come privately to Paris, in the hopes of procuring a diminution of the period of his baniſhment. Some time previous to this Rouſſeau had publiſhed two new letters ; one to P. Brumoi, on tragedy ; the other to Rollin, on hiſtory. It is laid, he expected from his letter to Brumoi to get the favour of all the Jeſuits ;</p><p>aud from the one to Rollin, the patronage of the Jan-ſeniſts. He had likewiſe written an Ode, in praiſe of Cardinal de Fleury, on Peace, which met with a favourable reception, although it was not equal to ſome of his former pieces. He imagined his return to Paris would be found no difficult matter. He attempted it, and found he could not obtain a paſs for a ſingle year. Some ſay, that Rouſſeau had irritated ſome perſons in power, by an allegory, called <hi rend="italic">The Judgment of Pluto ; </hi>in which piece he deſeribes one of the principal judges,</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>