<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>eb03-r03</title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>line OGC- ït will paſs through the point of conta -' C of the thread and cylinder, and C is the point round which it <hi rend="italic">begins</hi>  to turn in deſcending. Let G be its centre of oſcillation correſponding to the momentary centre oſ rotation C. It will begin to deſeend in the ſame manner as jf all its matter were collected in O: for<hi rend="sup">-</hi>  it may be conſidered, in this inſtant, as a pendulum ſuſpended at C. But in this caſe O will deſeend in the ſame manner as if the body were falling freely. Therefore the velocity of G (that is, the velocity of de-ſcent) will be to the velocity with which a heavy body would fall as CG to CO. Now ſince the points C, G, o, are always in a horizontal line, and the radius CG is given'; as alſo CO (n<hi rend="sup">0</hi>48.) the velocity of a body falling· freely, and of the body unwinding from this thread, will always be in the ſame proportion of CO to CG, and ſo will the ſpaces deſeribed in any given time. And thus we can compare their motions in every caſe when we know the place of the centre of oſcillation.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Cor</hi>  I. The weight of the defeending body will be to the tenſion of the thread as CO to GO : for the ten ſion of the thread is the difference between the momentum of thé rolling body and that of the body falling freely.</p><p>Obſerve, that this proportion between the weight of the body and the tenſion of the thread will be always the ſame; for it has been demonſtrated already, n<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 42. that if C be in the circumference of a circle whoſe centre is G, O will be in the circumference of another circle round the ſame centre, and therefore the ratio of CG to CO is conſtantl</p><p>v <hi rend="italic">Cor.</hi>  2. If a circular body TCB roll down an inclined plane by unfolding a thread, or by friction which prevents all Aiding, the ſpace deſeribed will be to that which the body would deſcribe freely as CG to CO ; for the tendency down the inclined plane is a determined proportion of the weight of the body. The motion of rotation in theſe caſes, both progreſſive and whirling, is uniformly accelerated.</p><p>Something of the ſame kind obtains in common pendulous bodies. A ball hung by a thread not only oſcillates, but alſo makes part of a rotation ; and for this reaſon its oſcillations differ from thoſe of a heavy point hanging by the ſame thread, and the centre of oſcillation is a little below the centre of the ball. A ball hung by a thread, and oſeillating between cycloidal cheeks, does not ofcillate like a body in a cycloid, becauſe its centre of oſcillation is continually ſhiſting its place. Huyghens avoided this by ſuſpending his pendulous body from two points, ſo that it did not change its attitude during its oſcillation. If ourſpring-carriages w<hi rend="sup">r</hi>ere hung in this manner, having the four lower ſtaples to wſhich the ſtraps are fixed as far aſun-rier as the four upper ſtaples at the ends of the ſprings, the body of the carriage would perform its oſcillations without kicking up and down in the diſagreeable manner they now do, by which we are frequently in danger oſ ſtriking the glaſſes with our heads. The ſwings would indeed be greater, but incomparably eaſeer; and we could hold things almoſt as ſteadily in our hand as if the carriage were not fwinging at all.</p><p>This will ſuſſice for an account of the rotation round fixed axes, as the foundation for a theory of machines actually performing work. The limits oſ our under</p><p>taking will not .allow us to do any more than juſt point out the method of applying it.</p><p>Let there be any machine of the rotatory kind, <hi rend="italic">i. e. </hi>compoſed of levers or wheels, and let its conſtruction be ſuch, that the velocity of the point to wſhich the power is applied (which we ſhall call the <hi rend="italic">impelled point)</hi>  is to the velocity of the working point in the ratio of <hi rend="italic">vι</hi>  to <hi rend="italic">n.</hi>  It is well known that the energy of this machine will be the ſame with that of an axis in peritrochio, of which the radii are <hi rend="italic">m</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">n.</hi></p><p>Let <hi rend="italic">ρ</hi>  expreſs the actual preſſure exerted on the impelled point by the moving power, and let <hi rend="italic">r</hi>  be the actual preſſure or reſiſtance exerted on the working point by the work to be performed. Let <hi rend="italic">χ</hi>  be the inertia of the power, or the quantity of dead matter which muſt move with the velocity of the impelled point in order that the moving power may act. Thus the moving power may be <hi rend="italic">the weight</hi>  of a bucket of water in a water-wheel ; then <hi rend="italic">x</hi>  is the quantity of matter in this bucket of water. Let <hi rend="italic">y</hi>  in like manner be the inertia of the w<hi rend="sup">τ</hi>ork, or matter which muſt be moved with the velocity oſ the working-point, in order that the work may be performed. Thus<hi rend="italic">y</hi>  may be a quantity of water which muſt be continually puſhed along a pipe. This is quite different from the weight of the water, though it is proportional to it, and may be meafured by it.</p><p>Let <hi rend="italic">ſ</hi>  be a preſſure giving the ſame reſiſtance when applied at the w'orking-point with the friction of the machine, and let <hi rend="italic">aη<hi rend="sup">i</hi></hi>  be the momentum of the machine’s inertia, viz. the fame as if a proper quantity of matter <hi rend="italic">a</hi>  were attached to the working-point, or to any point at the fame diſtance from the axis.</p><p>This ſtate of things may- be repreſented by the wſheel and axle PQS (ſig. 7.) wſhere <hi rend="italic">x</hi>  and y and <hi rend="italic">a</hi>  are repreſented by weights acting by lines. P is the impelled point, and R the working-point; CP is <hi rend="italic">m</hi>  and CR is«. 'Ihe moving force is repreſented by PA, the reſiſtance by RB, and the friction by BF.</p><p>It is evident that the momentum of the inertia of <hi rend="italic">x, y,</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">a</hi>  are the ſame as if they were for -a moment attached to the points P and R.</p><p>Hence we derive the following expreſſions,</p><p>1.    The angular velocity <hi rend="italic">zz —-</hi>—<hi rend="italic">—.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">xm<hi rend="sup">1</hi></hi>  -J-y -j- αn<hi rend="sup">x</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">p↑nn —r +f"'</hi></p><p>2.    Velocity oſ the working-point =    ,—≈--—'</p><p><hi rend="sup">3</hi>    ° *    _ *W*+J+tfn<hi rend="sup">,</hi></p><p>,<hi rend="sub">τr</hi> √ r<hi rend="italic">,    i&gt;mηr—rJf.f<hi rend="sub">η</hi><hi rend="sup">ι</hi>r</hi></p><p>3.    Work performed = —---- -_—    For the</p><p><hi rend="italic">x m<hi rend="sup">2</hi>-↑-y</hi>  -{-<hi rend="sub">i</hi>zβ<hi rend="sup">1</hi>∙</p><p>work is proportional to the product of the reſiſtance and the. velocity with which it is overcome.</p><p>We ſhall give a very ſimple example of the utility of theſe formulæ. Let us ſuppoſe that water is to be raiſed in a bucket by the deſeent of a weight, and that the machine is a ſimple pulley. Such a machine is deſeribed by Deſaguliers *, who ſays he found it preferable to all other machines. The bucket dipped itſelf in the ciſtern. A chain from it went over a pulley,' and at its extremity was a ſtage on which a man could ſtep from the head of a ſtair His preponderance brought down the ſtage and raiſed the bucket, which diſcharged its water into another ciſtern. The man quitted the ſtage, and walked up flairs, and there he found</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>