<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>eb03-r03</title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>JO to 50 verſts, and in the wideſt places as far as 70 verſts. 8. The Tchani Lake lies in the deſerts of Ba-raba, between the rivers Obè and lrtiſh. It joins with a great many ſmaller lakes, occupies a vaſt tract of land, and abounds very much in ſiſh. 9. Between the Gulf of Finland and the White Sea there are ſeveral lakes which extend from 50 to 70 verſts in length ; and befides theſe there are many other ſalt lakes in different parts of Ruſſia, ſuch as the Ozero, that is, the lake El-tonſkoye, Bogdo, Inderſkoye, Ebele, Koryakovſkoye, Yamiſhevſkoye, Borovye, and others ; and the fait which is got from them ſerves for the uſe of the greateſt part of the empire. To theſe may be added the Caſpian, which, though called a ſea, is more properly a lake, as it has no communication with the ocean either viſible or ſubterraneous. See <hi rend="italic">CASPiAN-Sea,</hi>  and Pneumatics, n<hi rend="sup">0</hi>277.</p><p>Ruſſia boaſts likewiſe of a conſiderable number of large and famous rivers. Of the Dvina or Dwina, the Neva, Dnieper or Nieper, the Don, the Volga, the Trtis, the Onega, the Oby, and the Lena, the reader of this work will find ſome account under their reſpective names ; but in this vaſt empire there are many other rivers worthy of notice, tho’ not perhaps of ſuch minute deſcription. Among theſe the <hi rend="italic">Bong,</hi>  or, as it is ſometimes written, <hi rend="italic">Bog,</hi>  riſes in Poland ; then directing its courſe to the ſouth-eaſt, it divides the government of Ecatherinoſlav from the deſerts of Otchakov, now belonging to Ruſſia, and falle into the Liman, which communicates with the Black ſea.</p><p>The Kubane conſiſts of many ſprings or rivulets running out of the Caucaſian mountains, and divides itſelf into two branches, the one of which falls into the Azov Sea, and the other into the Black ſea. This river, from its ſource to the end of it, conſtitutes the frontier of Ruſſia.</p><p>The Oural, formerly Yaik, takes its riſe in the Oural mountains, in the government of Oufa, which it divides from that of Caucaſus, and extends its courſe about 3000 verſts. It receives many rivers, the principal of which are the Or, Sakmara, Yleck, and Terkool.— The Kouma riſes in the Caucaſian mountains, and runs through the plains between Terek and Volga, and at laſt lofes itſelf in the ſands, before it comes to the Caſpian ſea. The Terek originates in the Caucaſian mountains, runs between them, and then coming out, extends its courſe to the Caſpian Sea, and receives ſeveral rivers, as the Malka, Soonja, Bakſan, and Ack-ſay.</p><p>The Bolſhaya Petchora, that is, the great Petchora, riſes in the Oural mountains, in the government of Vologda, runs acroſs the whole breadth of the government of Archangel, and falls into the Icy ſea. It receives in its courſe ſeveral rivers, the principal of which are the Outcha and the Elma. The Eniſſey is formed by the junction of two rivers, the Oulookema and the Baykema, which riſe in the Altay mountains in Mun-galia. It runs through the whole extent of Siberia, and falls into the Icy Sea. The extent of the Eniſſey is about 2500 verſts. It receives in its courſe ſeveral rivers, the principal of which are the Abakan, Elogooy, Podkamennaya Tungouſka, Niznyaya Tungouſka, and Tourookhan. The Yana, the Indighirka, and the Kolhima, are likewiſe no inconſiderable rivers in the government of Iikoutſk. The ſirſt riſes in the mountains which overſhadow the banks of the river Lena on the right hand, and extends its courſe 800 verſts. The two laſt take their ſources in the mountains which extend on the coaſts of the Eaſtern ſea. The length of the In-dighirka is 1200 and that of Kolhima 1500 verſts.— The laſt, near its mouth, is divided into two branches, and receives the rivers Omolon and Onooy. The Anadir is the eaſternmoſt of all the rivers in Siberia. It- riſes out of the lake Ioanko, in the diſtrict of Okhotſk, and runs through the eaſtern part of it, and then falls into the Eaſtern ocean The Amour is formed by the junction of two conſiderable rivers, the Shilka and Argoonya, which are joined juſt by the frontiers of China. It runs through the Chineſe dominions, and at laſt falls into the Eaſtern ocean. The Kamtſchatka runs through the peninſula oi the ſame name, extending its courſe from the Verkhney to Nizney Oſtrog, that is, from the upper to the lower fort, and falls into the Eaſtern ocean. The Penjina riſes in the Yablonnoy ridge of mountains, and falls into the Penjinſkaya Gooba, that is, the gulf or the ſea of Penjina.</p><p>In ſuch a vaſt extent of country, ſtretching from the temperate ſo far into the frigid zone, the climate muſt vary conſiderably in different places. In the ſouthern parts of the Ruffian empire, the longeſt day does not exceed fifteen hours and a half ; whereas in the moſt northern, the ſun in ſummer is ſeen two months above the horizon. The country in general, though lying under different climates, is exceſſively cold in the winter. Towards the north, the country is covered near three quarters of the year with ſnow and ice ; and by the ſeverity of the cold many unfortunate perſons are maimed, or periſh. This fort of weather commonly ſets in about the latter end of Auguſt, and continues till the month of May ; in which interval the rivers arc frozen to the depth of four or five feet. Water thrown up into the air will fall down in icicles ; birds are frozen in their flight, and travellers in their ſledges. In ſome provinces the heats of ſummer are as ſcorching as the winter colds are rigorous.</p><p>The ſoil of Muſcovy varies ſtill more than the climate, according to the influence of the ſun and the ſituation of the country. In the warmer provinces, thc proceſs of vegetation is ſo rapid, that corn is commonly reaped in two months after it begins to appear above the ſurface of the ground. Hence the great variety of muſhrooms produced ſpontaneouſly in Ruſſia, which may be conſidered as a comfortable relief to the poor, while they appear as delicacies at the tables of the rich. Above 1000 waggon-loads of them uſed to be fold annually in Moſcow. Perhaps it is on account of the ſcar-city of proviſions that ſuch a number of faſts are inſti-tuted in the Muſcovite religion.</p><p>Beſide^ tire productions already mentioned as peculiar to each of the three great natural diviſions of the empire, Muſcovy yields rhubarb, flax, hemp, paſture for cattle, wax, and honey. Among other vegetables, we find in Ruſſia a particular kind of rice called <hi rend="italic">[ſyntha, </hi>plenty of excellent melons, and in the neighbourhood of Aſtracan the famous zoophyton, or animal plant, which the Mulcovites call <hi rend="italic">bonnaret,</hi>  or lambkin, from its reſemblance to a larnb. See the article <hi rend="italic">Scythian LAMB.</hi></p><p>Agriculture in general is but little underſtood, and leſs proſecuted in this country. The moſt conſiderable articles in the oeconomy of a Ruffian farm are wax and</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>