<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>eb03-r03</title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>he generally loſt by purſuing it too far. He was better qualified to ftorm a citadel, or even to mount a breach, than patiently to ſuſtain a fiege ; and would have furniſhed an excellent hand to a general of a cooler head. This prince is celebrated for the invention of prints in mezzotinto, of wſhich he is ſaid to have taken the hint from a ſoldier’s ſcraping his ruſty fufil. The firſt print of this kind ever publiſhed was done by his highneſs, and may be ſeen in the firſt edition oſ Evelyn’s Sculptra. The ſecret is ſaid to have been ſoon after diſeovered by Sherwin an engraver, who made uſe of a loaded file for laying the ground. The prince, upon ſeeing one of his prints, ſuſpected that his ſervant had lent him his tool, which was a channeled roller ; but upon receiving full ſatisfaction to the contrary, he made him a preſent of it. The roller was afterwards laid aſide ; and an inſtrument with a crenelled edge, ſhaped like a ſhoemaker’s cutting-knife, was uſed inſtead of it. He alſo invented a metal called by his name, in which guns weι e caſt ; and contrived an excellent method of boring them, for which purpoſe a water-mill was erected at Hackney-marſh, to the great detriment of the undertaker, as the ſecret died with the illuſtrious inventor.</p><p><hi rend="italic">RUPERPs Drops,</hi>  a fort of glaſs-drops with long and ſlender tails, which burſt to pieces on the breaking off thoſe tails in any part ; ſaid to have been invented by prince Rupert, and therefore called by his name. Concerning the cauſe of this ſurpriſing phenomenon ſcarce any thing that bears the leaſt appearance of probability has been offered. Their exploſion is attended in the dark with a flaſh of light ; and by being boiled in oil, the drops are deprived of their exploſive quality.</p><p>RUPIN, or Rap in, a town of Germany, in the marquiſate of Brandenburg, and capital of a duchy .of the ſame name. It is divided into the Old and the New. The Old was nothing but an ancient caſtle, very well furniſhed, the late king of Pruſſia, before his father’s death, reliding there. New Rupin is ſeated on a lake, and become a conſiderable place of trade, with a manufactory of cloth. It is alſo noted for brewers. E. Long. 13. 23. N. Lat. 53. o.</p><p>RUPPI A, in botany : A genus of the tetragynia order, belonging to the tetrandria claſs of plants; and in the natural method ranking under the 15th order, <hi rend="italic">Inundate. </hi>There is neither calyx nor corolla ; but four pedicellated ſeeds.</p><p>RUSCUS, KNEE-HOLLY, or <hi rend="italic">Butcher’s Broom :</hi>  A genus of the ſyngeneſia order, belonging to the dioecia claſs of plants ; and in the natural method ranking under the 11th order, <hi rend="italic">Sarmentactte.</hi>  The male calyx is hexaphyllous ; there is no corolla ; the ncctarium is central, ovate, and perforated at the top. The female calyx, corolla, and nectarium, are the ſame as in the male; there is one ſtyle, with a trilocular two-ſeeded berry.</p><p>The moſt remarkable ſpecies is the aculeatus, or common butcher’s broom, common in the woods in many parts of England. It has roots compoſed of many thick fibres which twine about eaβh other ; from which ariſe ſeveral ſtiff green ſtalks about three feet high, lending out from their ſides ſeveral ſhort branches, gar-niſhed with ſtiff, oval, heart-ſhaped leaves, placed alternately on every part of the ſtalk, ending with ſharp prickly points. The flowers are produced in the middle, on the upper fide of the leaves ; they are ſmall, and cut into ſix parts ; of a purple colour, fitting cloſe to the midrib. They appear in June ; and the female flowers are ſucceeded by benies as large as cherries, of a ſweetiſh taſte, which ripen in winter j when they are of a beautiful red colour. As this plant grows wild in moſt parts of England, it is rarely admitted into gardens ; but if ſome of the roots are planted under tall trees in large plantations, they will ſpread into large clumps ; and as they retain their leaves in winter, at that ſeaſon they will have a good effect. The ſeeds of this plant generally lie a year in the ground before they vegetate ; and the plants ſo raiſed are long before they arrive at a fize big enough to make any figure, and therefore it is much better to tranſplant the roots.— The root of this plant is accounted aperient, and in this intention is ſometimes made an ingredient in apozems and diet-drinks, ſor opening flight obſtructions of the viſcera and promoting the fluid ſecretions. This plant is uſed by the butchers for beſoms to ſweep their blocks. Huckſters place the boughs round their bacon and cheeſe to defend them from the mice ; for they cannot make their way through the prickly leaves.</p><p>RUSH, in botany. See Juncus.</p><p><hi rend="italic">R usH-Candles.</hi>  See <hi rend="italic">Riſh-CANDLES.</hi></p><p>RUSHWORTH (John), the compiler of ſome uſeful collections reſpecting the affairs of ſtate, was born in Northumberland about the year 1607, and was de-ſcended of honourable anceſtors. After attending the univerſity of Oxford for ſome time, he removed to Lincoln’s Inn ; but the ſtudy of law not ſuiting his genius, he ſoon deſerted it, in order to ſeek a ſituation where he might more eaſily gratify his love for political information. He frequented the meetings of parliament, and wrote down the ſpeeches both of the king and members. During the ſpace of 11 years, From 1630 to 1640, when no parliament was held, he was an attentive obſerver of the great tranſactions of ſtate in the ſtar-chamber, the court of honour, and exchequer chamber, when all the judges of England aſſembled there on caſes of great emergency. Nor did he neglect to obſerve with a watchful eye thoſe events which happened at a diſtance from the capital. He vilited the camp at Berwick, was preſent at the battle of Newborn, at the treaty of Rippon, and at the great council of York.</p><p>In 1640 he was appointed aſſiſtant to Henry Elſynge clerk to the houſe of commons, and thus had the beſt opportunities of being acquainted with their debates and proceedings. The commons conſidered him as a perſon worthy of confidence. In particular, they truſted him with carrying their meffages to the king while he remained at York. And when the parliament created Sir Thomas Fairfax their general, Ruſhworth was appointed his ſecretary, and diſcharged the office much to the advantage of his maſter. When Fairfax reſign-ed his commiſſion, his ſecretary returned to Lincoln’s Inn, and was ſoon after (in 1651-2) choſen one of the committee that was appointed to deliberate concerning the propriety and means oſ altering or new-modelling the common law. He was elected one of the repre-fentatives for Berwick upon Tweed to the parliament which Richard Cromwell aſſembled in 1658, and was re-elected by the ſame town to the parliament which reſtored Charles II. to the crown.</p><p>Aſter the Reſtoration, he delivered to the king ſeve-</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>