<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>eb03-r03</title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>miſtaken policy which yet prevails in the nation, of ſuppreſſing all accounts of their origin, and inquiries into their ancient ſtate and ſituation ; of which we have a remarkable inſtance in the ſuppreſſion of a work by profeffor Muller, intitled <hi rend="italic">De Originlbus Gentis et Nominis Rufforum.</hi></p><p>According to ſeveral authors of credit, the Ruffians derived their origin from the Slavi or Slavonians, corruptly called the <hi rend="italic">Sclavonians,</hi>  who fettled ſirſt along the banks of the Volga, and afterwards near the Danube, in the countries named <hi rend="italic">Bulgaria</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">Hungary; </hi>but being driven from thence by the Romans (whom the Ruffians call <hi rend="italic">Wolochers,</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">Wolotaners'),</hi>  they firſt removed to the river Boryſthenes, or Dneiper, then •over-ran Poland, and, as is reported, built the city of Kiow. Afterwards they extended their colonies farther north, to the rivers which run into the <hi rend="italic">Ilmen</hi>  lake, and laid the foundation of the city of Novogorod. The towns,of Smolenſk and Tſernikow appear alſo to have been built by them, though the dares-of theſe events . cannot be aſcertained. The moſt ancient inhabitants, not only of Ruſſia, but all over Siberia, quite to the borders of China, are called <hi rend="italic">TJhucli ;</hi>  for profeffor Muller, on inquiring in thoſe parts by whom the ancient buildings and ſepulchral monuments he ſaw there, were erected, was everywhere anſwered, that they were the works of the Tſhudi, who in ancient times had lived in that country.</p><p>In the ninth century, the Scandinavians., that is, the Danes, Norwegians, and Swedes, emigrated from the north, and, crofling the Baltic^ went to ſeek habitations in Ruſſia. They firſt ſubdued the Courlanders, Livonians, and Eſthonians ; and, extending their conqueils ftill ſarther, they exacted tribute from the Novogorodi-ans, ſettled kings over them, and traded as far as Kiow, and even to Greece. Theſe new invaders were called <hi rend="italic">Waregers ;</hi>  which, according to profeffor Muller, fignifies “ ſea-faring people or, it derived from the old northern word <hi rend="italic">war,</hi>  it fignifies “ warlike men.” To theſe Waregers the name of <hi rend="italic">Ruffles, or Ruffians,</hi>  is thought by the moſt eminent authors to owe its origin ; but the etymology of the word itſelf is entirely uncertain.</p><p>In the dark ages of which we are ſpeaking, it is ! pretty certain that Ruſſia was divided among a great -number of petty princes, who made war upon each ' other with the ferocity and cruelty of wild beaſts ; ſo that the whole country was reduced to the utmoſt ml-ſery ; when Goſtomiſel, a chief of the Novogorodians, pitying the unhappy fate of his countrymen, and ſeeing no other method of remedying their calamities, adviſed them to offer the government of their country to the Waregers. The propoſal was readily accepted, and three princes of great abilities and valour were ſent to govern them ; namely, Ruric, Sineus, and Truwor, generally ſuppoſed to have been brothers. The firſt took up his refidence at Ladoga, in the principality of Great Novogorod ; the ſecond at Bielo Oſero, or the White Lake ; and the third kept his court at Iſhorſk, or, according to others, at a ſmall town, then called <hi rend="italic">Twcrizog,</hi>  in the principality of Pleſkow. The three brothers reigned amicably, and made conſiderable additions to-their dominions ; all of which at length devolved to Ruric by the death of Sineus and Truwor j but what</p><lb/><p>the conqueſts of the two brothers were, we have no records to inform us of.</p><p>Ruric, to his honour, became zealous for the ſtrict adminiſtration of juſtice ; and iffued a command to all: the boyars who poffeffed territories under him, to exer-i ciſe it in an exact and uniform manner. To this end, it was neceffary there ſhould be general laws. And this naturally leads us to conjecture, that letters were not entirely unknown in his dominions.</p><p>The Ruffian empire continued to flouriſh till the end ^ of the reign of Wolodomir, who aſcended the throne in the year 976. Having ſettled the affairs of his empire in peace, he demanded in marriage the princeſs Anne, fiſter to the Greek emperor Bafιlius Porphyro-genitus. His fuit w<hi rend="sup">,</hi>as granted, on condition that he ſhould embrace Chriſtianity. With this the Ruffian monarch complied ; and that vaſt empire was thenceforward conſidered as belonging to the patriarchate of Conſtantinople. Wolodomir received the name of<hi rend="italic">Ba-ltlius</hi>  on the day on which he was baptized ; and, according to the Ruffian annals, zo,ooo of his ſubjects were baptized the ſame day. Michael Syra, or Cyrus, a Greek, ſent by Photius the patriarch of Conſtantinople, was accepted as metropolitan of the whole country. At the ſame time, Wolodomir put away all his former wives and concubines, of whom he had upwards of 800, and by whom he had 12 Tons, who were baptized on the ſame day with himſelf. The idols of pa-ganiſm were now thrown down ; churches and mona-lteries were erected, towns built, and the arts began to flouriſh. The Sclavonian letters were now firſt introduced into Ruſſia ; and Wolodomir ſent miflionaries to convert the Bulgarians ; but only three or four of their princes came to him and were baptized. Theſe events happened in the year 987.</p><p>Wolodomir called the arts from Greece, cultivated them in the peaceable periods of his reign, and rewarded their proſeffors with generality, that he might dif-pel the clouds of ignorance which enveloped his country, call forth the genius of his countrymen, and render them happy. He alſo founded public ſchools, and enacted a law concerning the methods of inſtructing youth, and directing the conduct of the maſters appointed to inftruct them. He died in 1008, and, contrary to all rules of found policy and prudence, divided his empire among his 12 fons. The conſequence was, that they fell to making war and deſtroying one another as ſoon as their father was dead. 8uantepolk, one of the brothers, having deſtroyed and ſeized upon the dominions of two others, was himſelf driven out by Ja-riſlaus, and obliged to fly to Boleſlaus king of Poland. This brought on a dreadful war betwixt the Poles and Ruffians ; in which the former were victorious, and the latter loſt a great part of their dominions, as has been related under the article Poland.</p><p>Jariilaus finding himſelf unable to oppoſe the king of Poland, now turned his arms againſt the reſt of his brothers, all of whom he diſpoſſeffed of their dominions, and ſeized them for himſelf. He next attacked the Coſ-ſacks, over w<hi rend="sup">,</hi>hom he gained ſeveral advantages. After which he ventured once more to try his fortune with Boleſlaus : but in this ſecond expedition he was attended with worſe ſucceſs than before ; being now reduced «to the· condition oſ a vaffal and tributary to the</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>