<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>eb03-r03</title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>defray all expences in their refpective governments, and ſend a certain yearly ſum to the great treaſury. In a word, they enjoyed abſolute power in every thing but what related to the regular troops, which, though quartered in their juriſdiction, were neither paid nor directed by them, but received their orders immediately from the czar or his generals.</p><p>In 1775 the preſent empreſs made a complete new-modelling of the internal government in a form of great ſimplicity and uniformity. By that reglement ſhe divided the whole empire into 43 governments, as we have already mentioned, placing over each, or where they are of leſs extent, over two contiguous governments, a governor-general with very conſiderable powers. She ſubdivided each government into provinces and diſtricts; and for the better adminiſtration of juſtice erected in them various courts of law, civil, criminal, and commercial, analogous to thoſe which are found in other countries. She eſtabliſhed likewiſe in every government, if not in every province, a tribunal of con-fcience, and in every diſtrict a chamber for the protection of orphans. Amidſt ſo many wiſe inſtitutions a chamber for the adminiſtration of her imperial majeſe ſty’s revenues was not forgotten to be eſtabliſhed in each government, nor a tribunal of police in each diſtrict. The duty of the governor-general, who is not properly a judge, but the guardian of the laws, is to take care that the various tribunals in his government diſcharge their refpective duties, to protect the oppreſ-ſed, to enforce the adminiſtration of the laws ; and when any tribunal ſhall appear to have pronounced an irregular ſentence, to ſtop the execution till he make a report to the ſenate and receive her majeſty’s orders : It is his bufineſs likewiſe to ſee that the taxes be regularly paid ; and, on the frontiers of the empire, that the proper number of troops be kept up, and that they be attentive to their duty.</p><p>This reglement contains other inſtitutions, as well as many directions for the conducting of law-ſuits in the different courts, and the adminiſtration of juſtice, which do her majeſty the higheſt honour ; but the general want of morals, and wſhat we call a ſenſe oſ honour, in every order of men through this vaſt empire, muſt make the wiſeſt regulations of little avail. Ruſſia is perhaps the only nation in Europe where the law is not an incorporated proſeſſion. There are no ſemina-ries where a practitioner muſt be educated. Any man wſho will pay the fees of office may become an attorney, and any man wſho can find a client may plead at the bar. The judges are not more learned than the pleaders. They are not fitted for their offices by any kind ef education ; nor are they neceſſarily choſen from thoſe who have frequented courts and been· in the practice of pleading. A general, from a ſucceſsſul or an equivocal campaign, may be inſtantly ſet at the head of a court of juſtice ; and in the abſence of the imperial court from St Peterſhurgh, the commanding officer in that city, whoever he may be, prelides <hi rend="italic">ex officio</hi>  in the high court of juſtice. The other courts generally change their prefidents every year. Many inconveniences muſt ariſe from this fingular conſtitution ; but fewer,, perhaps, than we are apt to imagine. The appointment to ſo many interior governments makes the Ruffian nobility acquainted with the groſs of the ordinary bιιli-neſs of law-courts ; and a ſtatute or imperial edict is law in every caſe. The great obſtacles to the admi-niſtration of juſtice are the contrariety of the laws and the venality of the judges. From inferior to ſuperior courts there are two appeals ; and in a great proportion of the cauſes the reverlal of the ſentence of the inferior court ſubjects its judges to a heavy fine, unleſs they can produce an edict in full point in ſupport of their decilion. This indeed they ſeldom find any difficulty to do ; for there is hardly a cafe ſo fimple but that edicts may be found clear and preciſe ſor both parties ; and therefore the judges, ſenſible of their ſafety, arc very ſeldom incorruptible. To the principle of honour, which often guides the conduct of judges in other nations, they are ſuch abſolute ſtrangers, that an officer has been ſeen fitting in ſtate and diſtributing juſtice from a bench to which he was chained by an iron collar round his neck, ſor having the day before been detected in conniving at ſmuggling. This man ſeemed not to be aſhamed of the crime, nor did any one avoid, his company in the evening.</p><p>Few crimes are capital in Ruſſia : murder may be atoned by paying a ſum of money ; nay, the civil ma-giitrate takes no cognizance of murder, without having previouſty received information at the fuit of ſome individuals. Criminals were puniſhed with torture and the moſt cruel deaths till the reign of the illuſtrious Catharine I. when a more merciful ſyſtem took place, and which the preſent empreſs has ſince confirmed by lawn See the articles <hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps">Catharine L oſ Ruffiιa</hi></hi><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="sub">r</hi></hi>  and <hi rend="italic">L-LiZABETH Petrowna.</hi></p><p>We have already mentioned the traffic of the Ruffians with the different nations both of Aſia and Europe, and ſpecified iron as one of the articles wſhich they export. We may here add, that in 1792 there were in the government oſ Parma alone<hi rend="sub">τ</hi> which lies in the northern divifion of the empire, 88- copper and iron works belonging to the government and private perſons, and tlπee gold works. The metals ex-tracted in theſe works are chiefly conveyed to St Peterſ-bιιrgh by water-carriage on the river Tchuſovaya, w<hi rend="sup">τ</hi>hich falls into the Kama. With reſpect to the revenue of Ruflia, it continually fluctuates, according to the increaſe of commerce or the pleaſure of the czar, wſho-has all the wealth of the empire at his diſpoſal. He monopolizes all the beſt furs, mines, minerals, and the trade by land to the Eaſt Indies ; he farms out all the tobacco, wine<hi rend="sub">r</hi> brandy, beer, mead, and other liquors; the inns, taverns, public houſes, bath, and fw<hi rend="sup">r</hi>eating-houſes. The cuſtoms upon merchandize, the impoſts upon corn, and toll exacted from cities, tow<hi rend="sup">r</hi>ns, and villages, are very conſiderable. He poffeffes demeſnes to a very great value ;. inherits the effects of all thoſe that die inteſtate, or under accuſation of capital crimes; derives a duty front all- law-ſuits ; and to ſum up the whole, can command the fortunes of all his∙fiιbjects. All theſe articles produce a large revenue, which w<hi rend="sup">r</hi>as three years ago eſtimated at upwards- of 40,000,000 rubles, or L. 6,333,333 : 6 : 8 Sterling; but then the intrinfic value of money is at leaſt. three, times greater in Ruſſia than in Britain. The expences in time of peace never exceed 38,000,000 rubles : the remainder is not treaſeired up, but is employed by her imperial majeſty in eonſtructing public edifices, making harbours, canals, roads, and other uſeful works, for the glory of the empire and the benefit ot her ſubjects.</p><p>The Handing army of Ruſſia is computed at <hi rend="italic">250,000 </hi>men g befides theſe,. the Ruffians can aſſemble a body</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>