<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>eb03-r03</title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>as moveable round the point G by mean« of a pin at right angles to the axis. Suppoſe the balls paſſing through the ſituations A and B ; their centrifugal forces urge them at the ſame time in the directions CA and OB, which impulſions conſpire to make the connecting rod recede from both ends of the axis D <hi rend="italic">d.</hi>  And thus the balls, inſtead of deſeribing parallel circles round this axis, will deſcribe parallel ſpirals, gradually opening the angles DGA, <hi rend="italic">d</hi>  GB more and more, till the balls acquire the poſition « <hi rend="italic">ß</hi>  at right angles to the axis. They will not ſtop there, for tach came into that poſition v⅜h an oblique motion. They will paſs it ; and were it not for the reſiſtance of the air and the friction of the joint at G, they would go on till the ball A came to deſcribe the circle BHK, and the ball B to deſcribe the circle AEF. The centrifugal forces will now have exhauſted by oppoſition all the motions wſhich they had acquired during their paſſage from the poſition AB to the poſition <hi rend="italic"><hi rend="sup">x</hi>  IL</hi>  and now they will again deſcribe ſpirals gradually opening, and then contracting, till the balls arrive at their original poſition AB, when the proceſs will begin again. Thus they will continue a kind of oſeillating rotation.</p><p>Thus the axis is continually changing with reſpect to the ſyſtem of balls ; but it is fixed in reſpect to abſolute ſpace, becauſe the axis D <hi rend="italic">d</hi>  is ſupported. It does not yet appear that it has any tendency to change its poſition, becauſe the centrifugal tendency of the balls is completely yielded to by the joint at G. The material axis has indeed ſuftained no change ; but the real axis, or mathematical line round which the rotation was going on every moment, has been continually ſhiſting its place. This is not ſo obvious, and requires a more attentive conſideration. To ſhow accurately the gradual change of poſition of the real axis of rotation would require a long diſcuſſion We ſhall content ourſelves wn’tſh exhibiting a caſe where the poſition of the momentary axis is unqueſtionably different from <hi rend="italic">Dd,</hi>  which we may ſuppoſe horizontal.</p><p>Take the balls in the poſition « <hi rend="italic">β∙</hi>  They came into this poſition with a ſpiral motion, and therefore each of them was moving obliquely to <hi rend="sup">t</hi>he tangents<hi rend="italic">*r,βγ </hi>to the circle <hi rend="italic">afβt,</hi>  ſuppoſe in the directions <hi rend="italic">a6,βκ, </hi>They are therefore moving round the centre G in a plane <hi rend="italic">0aβκ,</hi>  inclined to the plane <hi rend="italic">&lt;t<hi rend="sup">i</hi>&lt;*-βy</hi>  of the circle <hi rend="italic">aSβι.</hi>  The momentary axis of rotation is therefore perpendicular to this oblique plane, and therefore does not coincide with D <hi rend="italic">d.</hi></p><p>We cannot enter upon the inveſtigation oſ this eva-gation of the axis, although the ſubject is both curious and important to the ſpeculative mathematicians.</p><p>A knowledge of it is abſolutely neceffary to a <hi rend="italic">complete </hi>ſolution of the great ' problem of the preceſſion. But when treating that article, we contented ourſelves with ſhowing that the evagation which obtains in this natural phenomenon is ſo exceedingly minute, that although multiplied many thouſands of times, it would eſeape the niceft obſervations of modern aſtronomers; and that it is a thing which does not accumulate beyond a certain limit, much too ſmall for obſervation, and then , diminiſhes again, and is periodical. Euler, D’Alembert, Frifi, and De la Grange, have ſhown the momentary poſition of the real variable axis correſponding to any given time ; and Landen has with great ingenuity and elegance connected theſe momentary pofi∙</p><lb/><p>fitιons, and given the whole paths of evagation. Mr Segnor was, we believe, the firſt who ſhowed (in a Diſſertation <hi rend="italic">De Mοtu Turbinuιn<hi rend="sub">t</hi></hi>  Halle, 1755)» that in every body there were at leaſt three lines paſſing through the centre of gravity at right angles to each other, forming the ſolid angle of a cube, round which the centrifugal forces were accurately balanced, and therefore a rotation begun round either of theſe three lines would be continued, and they are permanent axes of rotation. Albert Euler gave the firſt de-monſtration in 1760, and ſince that time the inveſtigation of theſe axes has been extended and improved by the different authors already named. It is an exceedingly difficult ſubject; and w<hi rend="sup">r</hi>e recommend the ſyn-thetical inveſtigation by Frifi in his<hi rend="italic">Coſmographia</hi>  as the fitteſt for inſtructing a curious reader to whom the ſubject is new. We ſhall conclude this diſſertation with a beautiful theorem, the enunciation of which we owe to P. Frifi, which has amazingly improved the whole theory, and gives eaſy and elegant ſolutions of the moſt difficult problems. It is analogous to Qιe great theorem of the compofition of motions and forces.</p><p>If a body turns round an axis AGa (fig. 17.) paſſing through its centre of gravity G with the angular velocity α, while this axis is carried round another axis BGi with the angular velocity <hi rend="italic">b,</hi>  and if GD be taken to GK as <hi rend="italic">a</hi>  to <hi rend="italic">b</hi>  (the points B and E being taken on that fide of the centre wſhere they are moving towards the ſame fide of the plane of the figure), and the line DE be drawn, though the whole and every particle of the body will be in a ſtate of rotation round a third axis CGf, lying in the plane of the other two, and parallel to DE, and the angular velocity <hi rend="italic">c</hi>  round this axis will be to <hi rend="italic">a</hi>  and to <hi rend="italic">b</hi>  as DE is to GD and to GE.</p><p>For, let P be any particle oſ the body, and ſuppoſe a ſpherical ſurface to be deſeribed round G paſſing through P. Draw PR perpendicular to the plane of the figure. It is evident that PR is the common ſection of the circle of rotation IP/’ round the axis A <hi rend="italic">a, </hi>and the circle KPZ of rotation round the axis Bi. Let I ∕, Ki be the diameters of theſe circles of rotation, F and G their centres. Draw the radii PF and PO, and the tangents PM and PN. Theſe tangents are in a plane MPN which touches the ſphere in P, and cuts the plane of the axis in a line MN, to wſhich a line drawn from the .centre G of the ſphere through the point R is perpendicular. Let PN repreſent the velocity oſ rotation of the point P round the axis Bi, and P<hi rend="italic">ſ</hi>  its velocity of rotation round Am Complete the parallelogram PNi∕. Then Pi is the direction and velocity of motion reſulting from the compofition of PN and <hi rend="italic">Pſ. Pt</hi>  is in the plane MPN, becauſe the diagonal of a parallelogram is in the plane oſ its lides PN and <hi rend="italic">Pſ.</hi></p><p>Let perpendiculars∕F, zT, be drawn to the plane of the axes, and the parallelogram PN(∕^will be orthθτ graphically projected on that plane, its projection being a parallelogram RNTF. ( F here falls on the centre by acci-, dent). Draw the diagonal RT. It is evident that the plane PR/T is perpendicular to the plane of the two axes, becauſe PR is ſo. Therefore the compound motion Pi is in the plane of a circle of revolution round ſome axis ſituated in the plane of the other two. Therefore produce TR, and draw GC cutting it aſ right</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>