<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>eb03-r03</title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>in reſpect to the great church, that the tower which leaned on one ſide was ſet up ſtraight in the year ι6y^, as appears by the inſcription engraved on brais at the bottom of the tower withinſide. In the choir of this church are celebrated, with no ſmall ſolemnity, the promotions made in the Latin ſchools. Beſides, there are two Engliſh churches, one for thoſe of the church of England and the other for the Preſhyterians ; and one Scotch church ; as likewiſe one Lutheran, two Armi-nian, two Anabaptiſt, four Roman Catholic chapels, and one Jewiſh ſynagogue.</p><p>Though the public buildings here are not ſo ſtately as thoſe of Amſterdam and ſome other cities, yet there are ſeveral of them well worth ſeeing. The great church of St Laurence is a good old building, where tire many ſtately monuments of their old admirals. ■From the top of this church one may ſee the Hague, Delft, Leyden, Dort, and moſt of the towns of ſouth Holland. There are ſeveral fine market-places, as three fiſh-markets, the great·market, the new-market, and the hogs-market. The Stadthouſe is an old building, but the chambers large and finely adorned. The magazines for fitting out their ſhips are very good ftructüres. The Exchange is a noble building, begun in the year 1720, and finiſhed in 1736. Upon the Great Bridge in the market-place there is a fine braſs ſtatue erected to the great Eraſmus, who was born in this city in 1467, and died at Baſil in Switzerland. He is repreſented in a furred gown, and a round cap, with a book in his hand. The ſtatue is on a pedeſtal of marble, rfurrounded with rails of iron. Juſt by, one may ſee the houſe where this great man was born, which is a very ſmall one, and has the following diſtich written on * the door :</p><p><hi rend="italic">Æ dibus his ortus<hi rend="sub">i</hi> munclum decoravit, Eraſmus,</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Artibus, ingeηiο, religione,ſde.</hi></p><p>Rotterdam and the whole of the United Provinces ■are now in the poſſeſſion of the French Republic. See Revolution and <hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps">United Provinces.</hi></hi></p><p>ROTULA, in anatomy, the ſmall bone of the knee, called alſo <hi rend="italic">patella.</hi></p><p>ROTUNDUS, in anatomy, a name given to ſeveral muſcles otherwiſe called <hi rend="italic">teres.</hi></p><p>ROUAD∙ See Aradus.</p><p>ROUANE, or Roane, an ancient and conſiderable town of France, in Lower Forez, with the title of a duchy ; ſeated on the river Loire, at the place where it begins to be navigable for boats. E. Long. 4. 9. N. Lat. 46. 2.</p><p>ROUCOU, in dyeing, the ſame with Anotta and Bixa.</p><p>ROUEN, a city of France, and capital of Normandy, had an archbiſhop’s ſee, a parliament, a mint, a handſome college, an academy, two abbeys, and an old caſtle. It is ſeven miles in circumference, and ſurround-cd with fix ſuburbs ; and contained before the revolution 3$ pariſhes, and 24 convents for men and women. The metropolitan church has a very handſome,front, on which are two loſty ſteeples, whence there is a fine view of the town and Country. The great bell is 13 feet high and 11 in diameter. The church of the Be-nedictne abbey is much admired by travellers. The parliament-houſe is adorned with beautiful tapeſtry and fine pictures. There ure a great number of foun</p><lb/><p>tains, though the houſes are ordinary ; but the walk upon the quay is very pleaſant, and there are 13 gates from thence into the city. The number of the inhabitants are about 60,000, and they have ſeveral woollen manufactures. It is ſeated on the river Seine ; and the tide riſes ſo high, that veſſels of 2oo tons may come up to the quay : but one of the greateſt curiofι-ties is the bridge, of 270 paces in length, ſupported by boats, and conſequently is higher or lower according to the tide. It is paved, and there are ways for foot-paſſengers on each ſide, with benches to fit upon ; and coaches may paſs over it at any hour of the day or night. It is often called <hi rend="italic">Roan</hi>  by Engliſh hiſtorians ; and is 50 miles ſouth-weft of Amiens, and 70 north-weft of Paris.</p><p>Though large, and enriched by commerce, Rouen 19 not an elegant place. The ſtreets are alinoſt all narrow, crooked, and dirty ; the buildings old and irregular. It was fortified by St Louis in 1253, but the walls are now demoliſhed. The environs, more peculiarly the hills which overlook the Seine, are wonderfully agreeable, and covered with magnificent villas. E» Long. ί. 10. N. Lat. 49. 26.</p><p>ROVE RE, or Rover edo, a ſtrong town of the Tyrol, on the confines of the republic of Venice; ſeated on the river Adige, at the foot of a mountain, and on the ſide of a ſtream, over which there is a bridge, defended by two large towers and a ſtrong caſtle, 1 o miles ſouth of Trent. The town is tolerably well built, and governed by a chief magiſtrate, ſtyled a <hi rend="italic">Podeſat.</hi>  There are ſeveral churches and cofivents, that contain nothing worthy of notice. The moſt remarkable thing, and what they call the great <hi rend="italic">wonder oſ Roveredo,</hi>  is its ſpinning-houſe for a manufacture of ſilk, in which they have a great trade here to the fairs of Bolzano. They have alſo a very good trade in wine Betwixt Trent and Roveredo is the ſtrong fort of Belem, belonging to the houſe of Auſtria. It is ſituated on a rock, and commands the roads at the foot of the mountain. E. Long. ιι. I. N. Lat. 46. 12.</p><p>ROUERGUE, a province oſ France, in the government of Guienne ; bounded on the eaſt by the Cevennes and Gevaudan, on the weft by Querci, on the north by the ſame and Auvergne, and on the ſouth by Languedoc. It is 75 miles in length, and 50 in breadth ; not very fertile, but ſeeds a number of cattle, and has mines of copper, iron, alum, vitriol, and ſulphur. It is divided into a county, and the upper and lower marche. Rhodez is the capital town.</p><p>ROVIGNO, a populous town of Italy, in Iſtria, with two good harbours, and quarries of fine ſtone. It is ſeated in a territory which produces excellent wine, in a peninſula on the weſtern coaſt. E. Long. 13. 53. N. Lat. 45. 14.</p><p>ROVIGO, is a town of Italy, in the territory of Venice, and capital of the Poleſin di Rovigo, in E. Long. 12. 25. N. Lat. 45. 6. It is a ſmall place, poorly inhabited, and encompaſſed with ruinous walls. Formerly it belonged to the duke of Ferrara, but has been ſubject to the Venetians ſince 1500, and is famous for being the birth-place of that learned man Coelius Rhodogſhus. It was built upon the ruins oſ Adria, anciently a noble harbour one mile from Rovigo, that gave name to the gulph, but now a half-drowned village, inhabited by a few ſiſhermen.</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>