<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>eb03-r03</title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>forces are really concerned in giving motion to the different particles.</p><p>Suppoſe the external force to act immediately on the external particle F. The line FC connecting this particle with the axis in C is either ſtretched or compreſſed by the effort of giving motion to a remote particle A. It is plain that, in the circumſlances rtpreſented in the figure, the line FC is compreſſed, and the axis is puſhed by it againſt its ſupports in the direction C<hi rend="sup">z</hi>  ; and the body muff, on this account, reſiſt in the oppoſite direction F∕. The particle A is dragged out of its poſition, and made to begin its motion in the direction AL perpendicular to AC. This cannot be, unleſs by the connection of the two lines AC, AF. A refills by its inertia, and therefore both AC and AF are ſtretched by dragging it into motion. By this reſiſtance the line AC tends to contract itſelf again, and it pulls C in the direction Cr, and A in the direction A<hi rend="italic">a ;</hi>  and if we take Cc to repreſent the action on C, A <hi rend="italic">a</hi>  muſt be taken equal to it. In like manner AF is ſtretched and tends to contract, pulling F in the direction Fø  and A in the direction A « with equal forces. Thus the particle A is pulled in the directions Aa and A<hi rend="sup">α</hi>  ; the particle F is pulled in the direction Fø,and puſhed in the direction F<hi rend="italic">ſ; </hi>and C is pulled in the direction C<hi rend="italic">c</hi>, and puſhed in the direction C×. A<hi rend="italic">a</hi>  and A<hi rend="sup">α</hi>  have produced their equivalent AL, by which A is dragged into motion ; F<hi rend="italic">f </hi>and Fø produce their equivalent F<hi rend="italic">g</hi>, by which the external force is refilled, and Fg is equal and oppoſite to <hi rend="italic">m</hi>.Gi; the forces <hi rend="italic">Cc</hi>  and C× produce their equivalent C<hi rend="italic">d</hi>  by which the axis is preſſed on its ſupports, and this is refilled by an equal and oppoſite reaction of the ſupports in the direction <hi rend="italic">d</hi>  C. The forces therefore which excite in the body the motion A.AL are both external, viz. the impelling force <hi rend="italic">g</hi>  F, and the ſupporting force  <hi rend="italic">d</hi>C. AL therefore is no<hi rend="sub">z</hi>t only the immediate equivalent of Aa and Aα, but alſo the remote equivalent of <hi rend="italic">g</hi>  F and <hi rend="italic">cl C.</hi>  We may therefore aſcertain the proportion of <hi rend="italic">g</hi>  F (that is, of <hi rend="italic">m</hi>.G<hi rend="italic">i</hi>) to AL (that is, of A. AC), independent of the property of the lever. y F is to AL in the ratio compounded of the ratios <hi rend="italic">of £</hi>  F to F<hi rend="sub">i</hi>&gt; or Aj, and of A« to AL. But we ſhall obtain it more eaſily by conſidering<hi rend="italic">g</hi>  F as the equivalent of AL andi∕C. By what has been demonſtrated above, the directions of the three forces <hi rend="italic">g</hi>  F, AL, and <hi rend="italic">d</hi>  C muſt meet in one point E, and <hi rend="italic">g</hi>F muſt be equal to the diagonal <hi rend="italic">t</hi>  E of the parallelogram <hi rend="italic">Eet,</hi>  of which the  ſides Ef, Ef are reſpectively equal to AL and <hi rend="italic">dC. </hi>Now zE is to Ee as the fine of the angle <hi rend="italic">t e</hi>  E to the fine of the angle Eze, that is, as the fine of CFA, to the fine of CEP, that is, as C A toCP, as we have already demonſtrated by the property of the lever. We preferred that demonſtration as the ſhorteſt, and as abundantly familiar, and as congenial with the general mechaniſm of rotatory motions. And the intelligent reader will ob-ſerve, that this other demonſtration is nothing but the demonſtration by the lever expanded into its own elements. Having once made all our readers ſenfible of this internal proceſs of the excitement and operation of the forces which connect the particles, we ſhall not again have recourſe to it.</p><p>It is evident that the ſum of all the forces <hi rend="italic">g</hi>F, or <hi rend="italic">m.</hi>G<hi rend="italic">i</hi>  muſt be equal to the whole moving force m.Gl. that <hi rend="italic">m</hi>.P<hi rend="italic">p</hi>  may be = <hi rend="italic">m.Gl.</hi>  That is, we muſt have</p><p>/Ά CA<hi rend="sup">z</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">m.Gl=J</hi>—cp—; or, becauſe CP is given when the</p><p>poſition of the line FP is given, we muſt have <hi rend="italic">m.Gl</hi></p><p>∕A CA</p><p>= —c*p <hi rend="sup">-</hi>, where both A and CA are variable quantities.</p><p>This equation gives us <hi rend="italic">m</hi>.GI.CP—∕A.CA<hi rend="sup">1</hi>. Now we learn in mechanics that the energy of any force applied to a lever, or its power of producing a motion round the fulcrum, in oppoſition to any reſiſtance whatever, is expreſſed by the product of the force by the perpendicular drawn from the fulcrum on the line of its direction. Therefore we may call w.GI.CP the momentum @@(b), energy, or rotatory effort, of the force vz.GI. And in like manner/A .CA<hi rend="sup">,</hi>  is the ſum of the momenta of all the particles of the body in actual rotation ; and as this rotation required the momentum nz.GΣ.CP to produce it, this momentum balances, and therefore may expreſs the energy of all the reſiſt-ances made by the inertia of the particles to this motion of rotation. Or∕A.CA<hi rend="sup">i</hi>  may expreſs it. Or, take<hi rend="italic">p</hi>  to repreſent the quantity of matter in an« particle, and <hi rend="italic">r</hi>  to repreſent its radiu3 vector, or diſtance from the axis of rotation, <hi rend="italic">fp.r<hi rend="sup">x</hi></hi>  will expreſs the momentum of inertia, and the equilibrium between the momentum of the external force <hi rend="italic">m.Gl,</hi>  acting in the direction FP, and the combined momenta of the inertia of all the particles of the whirling body, is expreſſed by the equation <hi rend="italic">ni.</hi>  G I. CP =∕A. CA<hi rend="sup">1</hi>, = <hi rend="italic">Jpr<hi rend="sup">x</hi>.</hi>The uſual way of ſtudying elementary mechanics gives us the habit of aſſociating the word equilibrium with ad⅛ate of reft ; and this has made our knowledge fo imperfect. But there is the ſame equilibrium of the actual immediate preſſures when motion enſues from the action. When a weight A deſcending raiſes a ſmaller weight B by means of a thread paſſing over a pulley, the thread is equally ſtretched between the acting and reſiſting weights. The ſtrain on this thread is undoubtedly the immediate moving force acting on B,, and the immediate reſiſting force acting on A.</p><p><hi rend="italic">'fp.ι^</hi></p><p>The ſame equation gives us GI =</p><p>Now GI:CG =^^ptCG, = ∕∕.r<hi rend="sup">,</hi><hi rend="sub">1</hi>m.CP</p><p>. CG ; but CG repreſents the velocity of the centre. Hence we derive this fundamental propofition <hi rend="italic">ſ p ■ r*</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">@@@(b) The word </hi><hi rend="italic">momentum</hi>  is very careleſsly uſed by our mechanical writers. It is frequently employed to expreſs the product of the quantity of matter and velocity, that is, the quantity of motion ; and it is alſo uſed (with ſtrict propriety of language) to expreſs the power, energy, or efficacy of a force to produce motion in the circumstances in which it acts. We wiſh to confine it to this uſe alone. Sir Iſaac Newton adhered rigidly to this employment of the term (indeed no man exceeds him in preciſion of expreſſion), even when he uſed it to expreſs the quantity of motion : for in theſe inſtances the energy of this quantity of motion, as modified by the. circumſtances of its action, was always in the ratio of the quantity of motion.</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>