<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>eb03-r03</title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>which ſeldom ripen in England. For the manner of its cultivation and preparation for the uſe of dyers, ſee the article Madder.</p><p>Madder-root is uſed in medicine. The virtues attributed to it are thoſe of a detergent and aperient ; whence it has been uſually ranked among the opening roots, and recommended in obſtructions of the viſcera, particularly ol the kidneys, in coagulations of the blood from falls or bruiſes, in the jaundice, and beginning dropfies. It is an ingredient in the icteric decoction of the Edinburgh pharmacopoeia.</p><p>It is obſervable, that this root, taken internally, tinges the urine of a deep red colour ; and in the Phi-loſophieal Tranſactions we have an account of its producing a like effect upon the bones of animals who had it mixed with their food : all the bones, particularly the more ſolid ones, w<hi rend="sup">r</hi>ere ſaid to be changed, both externally and internally, to a deep red; but neither the fleſhy or cartilaginous parts ſuffered any alterations : ſome of theſe bones macerated in water for many weeks together, and afterwards ſteeped and boiled in ſpirit of wine, loſt none of their colour, nor communicated any tinge to the liquors. This root, therefore, was concluded to be poſſeſſed of great ſubtilty of parts, and its medical virtues hence to deſerve inquiry. The ſame trials, however, made by others, have not been found to produce the ſame efi'ects as thoſe above-mentioned.— Of late the root has come into great reputation as an emmenagogue.</p><p>RUBININSKA, one of the northern provinces of Ruſſia, bounded by the province of Dwina on the north, by Syrianes on the eaſt, by Belozera on the ſouth, and by the lake Onega on the weſt.</p><p>RUBRIC, in the canon law, fignifies a title or article in certain- ancient law-books ; thus called becauſe written, as the titles of the chapters in our ancient bibles are, in red letters.</p><p>RUBUS, the Bramble, or <hi rend="italic">Raſpberry bufl&gt; :</hi>  A genus of the polygamia order, belonging to the icoſan-dria claſs of plants ; and in the natural order ranking under the 35th order, <hi rend="italic">Senticoſe.</hi>  The calyx is quin-quefid, the petals five ; the berry confiſting of mono-ſpermous acini or pulpy grains. The principal ſpecies is the common raſpberry, which, with its varieties, demands culture in every garden for their fruit ; particularly the common red kind, white fort, and twice-bearing raſpberry ; all of which are great bearers : but for the general plantations, we chooſe principally the common red and the wſhite kind, as being generally the greateſt bearers oſ all ; planting alſo a ſhare of the ^vice-bearing fort, both as a curioſity and for the ſake of its autumnal crops of fruit, which in favourable ſeaſons ripen in tolerable perfection ; obſerving to allow all the forts ſome open expoſure in the kitchen garden, though they will proſper in almoſt any ſituation.</p><p>The other ſpecies are confidered as plants of variety, for hardy plantations in the ſhrubbery. Some of them are alſo very ornamental flowering plants ; particularly the Virginian flowering raſpberry, and the double-bloſſomed bramble, which have great merit as furniture for ornamental compartments ; and the white-berried bramble, wſhich is a great curioſity. All the other ſpecies and varieties ſerve to diverfify large collections.</p><p>RUBY, a genus of precious ſtones of various colours ; as, I. Of a deep red colour inclining a little to purple ; the <hi rend="italic">carbuncle</hi>  of Pliny. 2. The ſpinell, of the colour of a bright corn poppy flower. 3. The balaſs or pale red inclining to violet ; ſuppoſed to be the mother of rubies. 4. The rubicell, of a reddiſh yellow. According to Cronſtedt, the ruby cryſtallifes into an oc-toedral form, as well as the diamond, from wſhich it differs very little in hardneſs and w<hi rend="sup">τ</hi>eight, whence he concludes that they are both of the ſame nature ; but ſome late experiments have ſhown that the diamond differs exceſſively from all other gems, in being diſſipable by a ſſrong fire, which the ethers refill. Tavernier and Dutens inform us, that in the Eaſt Indies all coloured, gems are named<hi rend="italic">rubies,</hi>  without regard to what their colours may be ; and that the particular colour is added to the name of each in order to diſtinguiſh them from one another. There are, however, ſome ſoft ſtones of this kind wſhich they call <hi rend="italic">Lacan;</hi>  and it is certain, that the hard and brilliant rubies named <hi rend="italic">oriental,</hi>  as well as the ſapphires and topazes, are all the ſame, excepting only the circumſtance of colour. Some are partly red and partly blue, yellow, and ſome quite colourleſs. The ſpinell rubies are about half the value of diamonds of the ſame weight ; the balaſs is va lued at 30 ſhill.ings per carat. Tavernier mentions 108 rubies in the throne of the great Mogul, from 100 to 200 carats, and of a round one almoſt 2⅜ ounces: there is alſo mention made by other travellers of rubies exceeding 200 carats in weight. According to Dutens, a perfect ruby, if it w<hi rend="sup">r</hi>eighs more than 3⅜ carats, is of greater value than a diamond of the ſame weight. If it weighs one carat, it is worth 40 guineas; if two carats, 40 guineas ; three carats, 150 gui* neas ; if fix carats, upwards of 1000 guineas.</p><p>According to the experiments of Bergman and A-chard, the texture of the ruby is foliated' like that of diamonds ; it is ſufible with borax in a ſtrong and long continued heat, running into a tranſparent glaſs of a pale green colour : the ſame effect is produced by mi-crocoſmſe ſalt ; but with ſedative ſalt, or mineral or vegetable alkali, the glaſs is opaque and differently co* loured. From the experiments oſM. d’Arcct, it appears that the ruby does not loſe its colour in the greateſt fire ; but Henckel ſays, that, by means of a burning glaſs, he ſoftened it in ſuch a manner as to receive the impreſſion of a’ſeal of jaſper. It becomes electric by being rubbed. Its ſpecific gravity, according to Bergman, is from 3,180 to 4,240 ; but Briſſon tells us that it is 4,283. The ſpecific gravity of the ſpinell is 3,760, of the Brafilian ruby 3,53 1.</p><p>Rubies are met with in the Capelan mountains of Pegu in the Eaſt Indies ; and at Caos, ∆va, Bifnagâr, Calicut, Cananor, Ceilan, and Brafil. They are found in the ſands of rivers of a red colour, in an argillaceous earth of an hard texture and greeniſh colour : ſome* times they adhere to red rocks. The ſpinell rubies are met with in Hungary, Silefia, Bohemia, and Bra-fil. The balaſs comes principally from Braſil, though ſome are alſo brought from the Eaſt Indies. The ru--bicell comes alſo from Braſil, but are ſaid to loſe their colour in the fire. A variety of this gem, but of a ſoft quality, is found in great plenty on the ſea-ſhore near Ely in Fifeſhire, Scotland. There is alſo a ſtone</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>