<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>eb03-r03</title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>armed and moſtly ſoldiers, had greatly the advantage ; however, they were on the point of being op preſſed by numbers, when they fell upon the moſt cruel method of enſuring their ſucceſs that could be deviſed. This was by ſetting fire to the city in ſeveral places } and wſhile the diſtreſſed Ruſſians ran to ſave their families, the Poles fell upon them ſword in hand. In this confuſion upwards of iσo,ooo peop⅛ periſhed; but the event was, that the Roles were finally driven oüt, and loſt all footing in Ruffià.</p><p>The expnllion of the Poles was ſucceeded by the election of Tſheodorovitz Romanov, a young nobleman of 17 years of age, whoſe poſterity, till the acceſſion of the preſent Empreſs, continued to enjoy the fo-vereignty. He died in 1646, and was ſucceeded by his ſon Alexis ; whoſe reign was a continued ſcene of tumult and confuſion, being haraſſcd on all ſides by external enemies, and having his empire perpetually diſ-turbed by internal commotions.</p><p>The ſources of theſe commotions were found in the multiplicity and inconſiſtency of the laws at that period, and in the jarring claims of the nobles on the borders. An <hi rend="italic">emann∙y ukaſe,</hi>  or personal order, which is an edict of the ſovereign, ſigned with his own hand, is the only law oſ Ruſſia. Theſe edicts are as various as the opinions, prejudices, paſſion-s, or whims of men ; and in the days of Alexis they produced endleſs contentions. To remedy this evil, he made a Election, from all the edicts of his predeceſſiors, of ſuch as had been familiarly current ſor a hundred years ; prtſuming that thoſe either were founded in natural juſtice, or during ſo long a currency had formed the minds of the people to conſider them as juſt. This digeſt, w hich he declared to be the common law of Ruſſia, and which is prefaced by a fort of inſtitute, is the ſtandard law-book at this day known by the title of the <hi rend="italic">Ulogeniè</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">Selection; </hi>and all edicts prior to it were declared to be obſolete. He ſoon made his <hi rend="italic">novella,</hi>  however, more bulky than tſhe Ulogeniè ; and the additions by his ſucceſſors are beyond enumeration. This was undoubtedly a great and uſe-ful work ; but Alexis performed another ſtill greater.</p><p>Though there are many courts of judicature in this widely extended empire, the emperor has always been lord paramount, and could take a cauſe from any court immediately before himſelf. But as ſeveral of the old nobles had the remains of principalities in their families, and held their own courts, the ſovereign or his mini-fters, at a diſtance up the country, frequently found it difficult to bring a culprit out of one of theſe hereditary feudal juriſdictions, and try him by the laws of the empire. This was a very diſagreeable limitation of imperial power; and the more ſo, that ſome families claimed even a right to repledge. A lucky opportunity offered of ſettling this diſpute } and Alexis embraced it with great ability.</p><p>Some families on the old frontiers were taxed with their defence, for which they were obliged to keep regiments on foot ; and as they were but lcantily indemnified by the ſtate, it ſometimes required the exertion ©f authority to make them keep up their levies. When the frontiers, by the conqueſt of Caſan, were ſar extended, thoſe gentlemen found the regiments no longer bur-denſome, becauſe by the help of falſe muſters, the former ſcanty allowance much more than reimburſed (them for the exnence of the eſtabliſhment, The conſe-</p><p>quence was, that diſputes aroſe among them about the right of guarding certain diſtricts, and law-ſuits were neceſſary to fettle their reſpective claims. Theſe were tedious and intricate. One claimant ſhowed the order of the court, iſſued a century or two back, to his an·· "ceſtor for the marching of his men, aâ a proof that thc right was then in his family. His opponent proved; that his anceſtors had been the real lords of the marches; but that, on account of their negligence, the court had iſſued an <hi rend="italic">emmansy ukaſe</hi>  to the other, only at that particular period. The emperor ordered all the family archives to be brought to Moſcow; and all documents όή both ſides to be collected. A time was ſet for the examination; a fine wooden court-houſe was built ; every paper was lodged under a good guard ; the day was appointed when the court ſhould be opened and the claims heard ; but that morning the houſe, with all its contents, was in two hours conſumed by fire. The emperor then ſaid, “ Gentlemen, henceforward your-ranks, your privileges, and your courts, are thc nation’s, and the nation will guard itſelf. Your archives are unfortunately loſt, but thoſe of the nation remain. I am the keeper, and it is my duty to ad-miniſter juſtice ſor all and to all. Your ranks are not private, but national ; attached to the ſervices you are actually performing. Henceforward Colonel Buturlin (a private gentleman) ranks before Captain Viazemſky (an old prince).”</p><p>This conſtitution, which eſtabliſhed the different ranks of Ruſſia as they remain to this day, is by Voltaire aſcribed to Peter :. but it was the work of Alexis ; who, when the ſituation of himſelf and his country is conſidered, muſt be allowed to have been a great and a good man. He died in 1676, and was ſucceeded by his ſon Theodore Alexiovit⅜} who after an excellent reign, during the whole of which he exerted himſelf to the utmoſt for the good of his ſubjects, diedin 1682, having appointed his brother Peter I. commonly called <hi rend="italic">Peter the Great,</hi>  his ſucceſſor. See PetEr I.</p><p>Theodore had another brother named <hi rend="italic">John ;</hi>  but as he was ſubject to the fallſhg-ſickneſs, the Czar had preferred Peter, though very young, to the ſucceſſion. But through the intrigues of the princeſs Sophia, fiſter to Theodore, a ſtrong party was formed in favour of John; and ſoon after both John and Peter were proclaimed ſovereigns of Ruſſia under the adminiſtration of Soph⅛ herſelf, who was declared regent. However, this adminiſtration did not continue long; for the princeſs regent having conſpired againſt Peter, and having the misfortune to be diſcovered, was confined for life in a convent. From this time alſo John continued to be only a nominal ſovereign till his death, which happened in 1696, Peter continuing to engroſs all the power.</p><p>It is to this emperor that Ruſſia is univerſally allowed to owe the whole of her preſent greatneſs. The private character of Peter himſelf ſeems to have been but very- indifferent. Though he had been married in his eighteenth year to a young and beautiful princeſs, he was not ſuſſiciently reſtrained by the ſolemn ties of wedlock ; and he was befides fo much addicted to Railing and drunkenneſs, the prevailing vice of his country, that nobody could have imagined him capable of effecting the reformation upon his ſubjects which he actually accompliſhed. In ſpite of all diſad vantages, however.</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>