<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>eb03-r03</title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ι&gt;.C.V <hi rend="sub">n</hi>-, <hi rend="sub">r</hi></p><p>CG∙CP Therefore the whole force employed in communicating to each particle the motion it really acquires,</p><p>,    , <hi rend="sub">n</hi> c ,    ∙    *<hi rend="sup">,</hi>∙CA*</p><p>or <hi rend="italic">m v,</hi>  is equal to the fluent or the quant 1ty-^^y7-θ</p><p>τ.∕CA<hi rend="sup">a</hi></p><p>or <hi rend="italic">mv=z </hi>ξιp (-Q-, and m.CP.CG =∕CA% which by</p><p>art. 23. is equal to ∕GA<hi rend="sup">2</hi>4-w.CG<hi rend="sup">1</hi>. Therefore we hare <hi rend="sub">w</hi>.CP.CG-w.CG.CG = ∕'GA<hi rend="sup">2</hi>, or rn.GP.CG</p><p>∕<hi rend="sup">-</hi>GA≈</p><p>~∕GA<hi rend="sup">1</hi>, and finally, CG<hi rend="italic"><hi rend="sup">=</hi>  ~ςpp.</hi></p><p>Now the form of the body gives us <hi rend="italic">ſG</hi><hi rend="sup">λ 2</hi>, and the poſition of the impelling force gives us w.GP∙ Therefore we can compute the value of CG ; and if be the periphery of a circle whoſe radius is unity, we have r.CG equal to the ſpace which the body muſt deſcribe in the direction GI, while it makes one rotation round its axis.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Cor.</hi>  I. The angular velocity, that is, the number of turns or the number of degrees which one of the radii will make in a given time, is proportional to the impelling force : for the length of CG depends only on the form of the body and.the ſituation of the point of impuliion ; while the time of deſeribing <hi rend="sub">π</hi>  times this length is inverſely as the force.</p><p>2.    The angular velocity with any given force is as GP : for CG, and conſequently the circumference %.CG, deſeribed during one turn, is inverſely as GP.</p><p>∕PA<hi rend="sup">i</hi></p><p>3.    PC is equal to ∕ θ p  : for we have ∕PA<hi rend="sup">i</hi>  =</p><p>∕*PA<hi rend="sup">a</hi> ∕GA≈<hi rend="italic">ſ G</hi>  A<hi rend="sup">2</hi>  +<hi rend="italic">rn</hi>  . G P ≈. Therefore <hi rend="italic">∖fefeξγ = </hi>—£p + ⅜⅛<hi rend="smallcaps"><hi rend="sup">1</hi>T&gt; = ∞ + <hi rend="sup">gp</hi>&gt; = <hi rend="sup">cp</hi>∙</hi></p><p>4.    If the point C is the centre of impuliion of the ſame body, P will be a ſpontaneous centre of conver-ſion (ſee art. 4' )∙</p><p>y. A force equal and oppoſite to <hi rend="italic">m v,</hi>  or to ∕, applied at G, will ſtop the progreſſive motion, but will make no change in the rotation ; but if it be applied at P, it will ſtop all motion both progreſſive and rotatory. If applied between P and G, it will ſtop the progreſſive motion, but will leave ſome motion of rotation. If applied beyond P it will leave a rotation in the oppoſite direction. If applied beyond G, or between G and C, it will increaſe the rotation. All this will be eaſily conceived by reflecting on its effect on the body at reſt.</p><p>6. A whirling body which has no progreſſive motion cannot have been brought into this ſtate by the action of a ſingle force It may have been put into this condition by the fimultaneous operation of two equal and oppofιte forces. The equality and oppoſition oſ the forces is neceffary for flopping all progreſſive motion. If one of them has acted, at the centre, the rotatory motion has been the effect of the other only. If they have acted on oppoſite fides, they conſpired with each other in producing the rotation ; but have oppoſed each other if they acted on oppoſite fides.</p><p>In like manner, it is plain that a motion of rotation, together with a progreſſive motion of the centre in the direction of the axis, could not have been produced by the action of a ſingle force.</p><p>7. When the ſpace S which a body deſcribes during one rotation has been obſerved, we can diſcover the point of impulſe by which a fingle force may have acted in producing both the motions of progreſſion</p><p>and rotation: for CG = -, and GP    —</p><p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="sup">π</hi>    nιΛ~G</hi></p><p>VGA<hi rend="sup">2</hi></p><p>WZ.S</p><p>In this manner we can tell the diſtances from the centre at which the fun and planets may have received the fingle impulſes which gave them both their motions oſ revolution in their orbits and rotation round their axes.</p><p>It was found (art. 40. ∕) that the diſtance OG of the centre of oſcillation or percuſſion of a ſphere fwinging round the fixed point C from its centre G, is J of the third proportional to CG, and the radius</p><p>, RG<hi rend="sup">2</hi></p><p>of the ſphere, or that OG~∣ ~CC~<hi rend="sup">,</hi> Suppofing the</p><p>planets to be homogeneous and ſpherical, and callin'·»· the radius oſ the planet r, and the radius oſ its orbit R, the time of a rotation round its axis <hi rend="italic">t,</hi>  and the time of a revolution in its orbit T, and making 1 : » the ratio of radius to the periphery of a circle, we ſhall have Jr R for the circumference of the orbit, and <hi rend="sup">5r</hi>  R y&lt; for</p><p>the arch of this circumference deſeribed during one rotation round the axis. This is S in the above-mentioned formula. 'Γhen, diminiſhing this in the ratio of the circumference to radius, we obtain CG = R ψ&gt;</p><p>r<hi rend="sup">2</hi>    Tr<hi rend="sup">1</hi></p><p>and OG = γ qg&gt; <hi rend="smallcaps"><hi rend="sup">=</hi></hi><hi rend="italic">τ</hi>     Th'<hi rend="sup">3</hi>  i<hi rend="sup">s e</hi>fi<hi rend="sup">u</hi>^<hi rend="sup">va</hi>l<hi rend="sup">en</hi>t to</p><p>*∕GA<hi rend="sup">2</hi></p><p>•-3— and eafier obtained.</p><p><hi rend="italic">n&gt;.o &gt;</hi></p><p>This gives us G <hi rend="italic">v</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">r</hi></p><p>For the Earth —--</p><p><hi rend="sup">1</hi>57</p><p>Moon --</p><p>555</p><p><hi rend="italic">r</hi></p><p>Mars    --l&gt; nearly.</p><p>195 f</p><p>Jupiter--∣</p><p><hi rend="sup">j j</hi>    2,8125</p><p>Saturn --—</p><p>2,588</p><p>We have not data for determining this for the fun. -But the very circumſtance of his having a rotation in 27<hi rend="sup">j</hi> 7<hi rend="sup">h</hi> 47<hi rend="sup">,</hi> makes it very probable that he, with all his attending planets, is alſo moving forward in the cele-ſtial ſpaces, perhaps round ſome centre of ſtill more general and extenfive gravitation : for the perfect oppoſition and equality oſ two forces, neceffary for giving a rotation without a progreſſive motion, has the odds againſt it of infinity to unity. This corroborates the conjectures of philoſophers, and the obſervations. of Herſehel and other aſtronomers, who think that the ſo-lar ſyſtem is approaching to that quarter of the heavens in which the conſtellation Aquila is ſituated.</p><p>8. As in the communication of progreſſive motion among bodies, the ſame quantity of motion is preſerved before and after colliſion, ſo in the communication of 1 o-</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>