<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>eb03-r03</title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>of the ſphere, had it acted in a direction paſſing through its centre ; and let us ſuppoſe that this force acted on the equatorial point A at right angleβ to AC : Its momentum is <hi rend="italic">mu a,</hi>  and this is equal to <hi rend="italic">v</hi>  χ <hi rend="sub">τ</hi><hi rend="sup">4</hi><hi rend="sub">τ</hi><hi rend="italic">a<hi rend="sup">4</hi>.</hi>  Alſo, we know that <hi rend="italic">m </hi>— ∙fo A Therefore we have <hi rend="italic">u . ∙} * a<hi rend="sup">4</hi>  —v</hi><hi rend="sub">τ</hi><hi rend="sup">4</hi><hi rend="sub">r</hi>  r rt<hi rend="sup">4</hi>, y « ≈ τ⅛∙<hi rend="italic">ν&gt;</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">v == ⅜ u.</hi></p><p>Let EPQ^p be an oblate ſpheroid whoſe ſemi-axis PC is rt, and equatorial radius EC is <hi rend="italic">b,</hi>  and let <hi rend="italic">v</hi>  be the velocity on the equator of the inſctibed ſphere. Then ſince the momentum of the whirling circle DD is</p><p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="sup">9</hi>ν<hi rend="sup">7f</hi>    ∙    ∙</hi></p><p>•——, the momenta of the ſphere and ſpheroid are in</p><p>tire quadruplicate ratio of their equatorial radii ; and therefore that of the whole ſpheroid is ≠<hi rend="sub">r τ</hi><hi rend="italic">b<hi rend="sup">4</hi>  v.</hi>  And if <hi rend="italic">ιυ</hi>  be the velocity at E correſponding to the velocity</p><p><hi rend="italic">b .</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">v</hi>  at A, ſo that w — — <hi rend="sup">ι</hi>u, we have the momentum oi</p><p>the ſpheroid, expreſſed in terms of the equatorial velocity at the ſurface, <hi rend="italic">ſſ b<hi rend="sup">i</hi>  aw. «</hi></p><p>If the ſame force <hi rend="italic">m u</hi>  be made to act in the ſame manner at E, its momentum <hi rend="italic">m u b</hi>  is — ⅜∙<hi rend="sub">5</hi>    « w, and</p><p>I <hi rend="italic">c rn u    .    . . <hi rend="sup">c</hi>v <hi rend="sup">ria</hi></hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">∙ω —</hi>     . Therefore the angular velocities —, ^y &gt;</p><p>4 <hi rend="italic">* D a    <hi rend="sup">a</hi>    a<hi rend="sup">i</hi>  b</hi></p><p>which the ſame force <hi rend="italic">mu</hi>  acting at A or E will produce</p><p><hi rend="italic">,    lζmu tζ&gt;nu</hi></p><p>in the ſphere and the ſpheroid, are as <hi rend="italic">ſſſfſ-Γ    <hi rend="sub">il</hi><hi rend="sup">t</hi></hi></p><p>that is, in the triplicate ratio of the equatorial diameter <hi rend="italic">b</hi>  to the polar axis <hi rend="italic">a</hi></p><p>Laſtly, if the oblate ſpheroid is made to turn round an equatorial diameter paſſing through C perpendicular to the plane of the figure, it is plain that every ſection parallel to the meridian EPQ__/&gt; is an ellipſe ſimilar to this meridian. If this ellipſe differs very little from the inſcribed circle, as is the caſe of the earth in the problem <hi rend="sub">e</hi>&gt;f the preceſſion of the equinoxes, the momentum of each ellipſe may be conſidered as equal to that of a circle of the ſame area, or whoſe diameter is a mean proportional between the equatorial and polar diameters of the ſpheroid. This radius is to the radius of the circum-ſcribed circle as √3<hi rend="italic">a</hi>  to <hi rend="italic">b.</hi>  Therefore the momenta of the ſection of the ſpheroid and oſ the circumſeribed ſphere are in the conſtant ratio of <hi rend="italic">b<hi rend="sup">2</hi>  α<hi rend="sup">l</hi></hi>  to <hi rend="italic"><hi rend="sup">b</hi>4<hi rend="sub">i</hi></hi>  or of <hi rend="italic">a<hi rend="sup">t </hi></hi>to <hi rend="italic">b<hi rend="sup">2</hi>.</hi>  And if the velocity in the equator of this cir-cumſcribed ſphere be called w, the momentum of the ſphere <hi rend="italic">is b<hi rend="sup">4</hi>  wi</hi>  and therefore that of the ſpheroid j<hi rend="sub">s</hi><hi rend="italic">τr h<hi rend="sup">2</hi><hi rend="sub">a</hi><hi rend="sup">1</hi>  w,</hi>  agreeably to what was aſſumed in the article Precession, n<hi rend="sup">0</hi>  33.</p><p>This value of the momentum of a ſpheroid round an equatorial diameter is only a very eaſy approximation ; ⅛n exact value may be obtained by an infinite ſeries. The whole matter of the ſpheroid may be conſidered as uniformly diſtributed on the ſurface of a ſimilar ſpheroid whoſe diameter is = √4 of the diameter of the ſpheroid. It will have the ſame momentum, becauſe a triangle in one of the ellipſes, having an elementary arch of the circumference for its baſe, and the centre of the ellipſe for its vertex, has its centre of gyration diſtant from the vertex √⅜ the length of the radius of the ellipſe, and the problem is reduced to the finding the ſum of theſe lines. But even when the ſeries for this ſum involves the 3d power of the eccentricity, it is not more exact than the above approximation.</p><p>A ſimilar propoſition may be obtained ſor a prolate ſpheroid vibrating round an equatorial diameter, and</p><p>applied to the conjectural ſhape of the moon, for ex</p><p>plaining her oſcillations.</p><p>The reader muſt have obſerved that the preceding diſquiſitions refer to thoſe motions only which reſiſtt from the action of external forces and to the ſtate of incipient motion. All circular motions, ſuch as thoſe of rotation, are accompanied by centrifugal forces. A central force is neceſſary .for retaining every particle in its circular path ; ſuch forces muſt therefore be excited in the body, and can ariſe only from the forces of co-heſion by which its particles are held, together. Theſe forces are mutual, equal, and oppoſite ; and as much as a particle A (fig. 5.) is retained by a force in the direction A <hi rend="italic">a</hi>  of the line which connects it with the fix, ed axis D <hi rend="italic">d<hi rend="sub">y</hi></hi>  or in the direction AG (fig. 10.), which, connects it with the progreſſive axis; ſo much muſt the point <hi rend="italic">a of</hi>  the axis <hi rend="italic">Dd</hi>  be urged in the oppoſite direction <hi rend="italic">a</hi>  A, or ſo much muſt the whole body be urged in the direction GA. Every point therefore of the axis D √, or of the axis through G in ſig. 10. is carried in a variety of directions perpendicular to itſelf. Theſe forces may or may not balance each other. If this balance obtains with reſpect to the fixed axis, its ſupports will ſuſtain no preſſure but wſhat ariſes from the external force; if not, one ſupport will be more preſſed than the other; and <hi rend="italic">iſ</hi>  both were removed, the axis would change its poſition. The ſame muſt be affirmed of the axis through G in ſig. 10. This, having no ſupport, muſt change its poſition.</p><p>And thus it may happen, that the axis of rotation paſſing through G which has been determined by the preceding diſquiſitions, is not permanent either in reſpect oſ the body, or in reſpect of abſolute ſpace. Theſe two rotations are eſſentially different. The way to conceive both is this. Suppoſe a ſpherical ſurface deſcri-bed round the body, having its centra in the centre of gravity; and ſuppoſe this ſurface to revolve and to proceed forward along with the body : in ſhort, let it be conceived as an immaterial ſm face attached to the body. The axis of rotation will paſs through this ſurface in two points which we ſhall call its poles. Now, we ſay that the axis is permanent with reſpect to the body when it has always the ſame poles in this ſpherical ſurface. Suppoſe another ſpherical ſurface dcſcribed round the ſame centre, and that this ſurface alſo accompanies the body in all its progreſſive motion, but does not turn with it. The axis is permanent with reſpect to abſolute ſpace when it has always the ſame poles in this ſurface : it is evident that theſe two facts are not inſepa-rable. A boy’s top ſpins on the ſame point and the ſame corporeal axis, while, towards the end of its motion, we obſerve it directing this round and round to different quarters of the room. And when we make an egg or a lemon ſpin with great rapidity on its fide on a level table, we ſee it gradually riſe up, till it ſtand quite on end, ſpinning all the while round an axis pointing to the zenith.</p><p>This change in the poſition of the axis is produced by the unbalanced actions of the centrifugal forces exerted by the particles. Suppoſe two equal balls A and B (fig. 16.) connected by an inflexible rod whoſe middle point is G, the centre of gravity of the balls. This ſyſtem may be made to turn round the material axis D⅛ A deſcribing the circle AEF A, and B deſcribing the circle BHKB. The rod AB may alſo be conceived</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>