<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>eb03-r03</title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Mr Du Hamel ſays, that it is decided by experi-<hi rend="sub">t</hi> ence, I. That white cordage in continual ſervice is one-third more durable than tarred. 2. That it retains its force much longer while kept in ſtore. 3. That it refills</p><p>the ordinary injuries of the weather one-fourth longer.</p><p>We know this one remarkable fact. In 1758 the ſhrowds and Hays of the Sheer hulk at Portſmouth dockyard were overhawled, and when the worming and ſervice were taken off, they were found to be of white cordage. On examining the ftorekeeper’s books, they were found to have been formerly the ſhrowds and rigging of the Royal William, of no guns, built in 1715, and rigged in 1716. She was thought top-heavy and unfit for ſea, and unrigged and her flores laid up. Some few years afterwards, her ſhrowds and Hays were fitted on the Sheer hulk, where they remained in confiant and very hard ſervice for about 30 years, while every tarred rope about her had been repeatedly renewed. This information we received from Mr Brown, boat-ſwain of the Royal William during the war 1758, &amp;c.</p><p>Why then do we tar cordage ? We thus render it more unpliant, weaker, and leſs durable. It is chiefly ſerviceable for cables and ground tackle, which muff be continually wetted and even ſoaked. The reſult of careful obſervation is, I. That white cordage, expoſed to be alternately very wet and dry, is weaker than tarred cordage. 2. That cordage which is ſuperficially tarred is conſtantly ſtronger than what is tarred throughout, and it refills better the alternatives of wet and dry. <hi rend="italic">N. B.</hi>  The ſhrouds of the Sheer hulk werc well tarred and blacked, ſo that it was not known that they were of white cordage.</p><p>Tar is a curious ſubſtance, miſcible completely with water. Attempts were made to anoint cordage with oils and fats which do not mix with water. This was expected to defend them from its pernicious effects. But it was diſtinctly found that theſe matters made the fibres of hemp glide ſo eaſily on each other, that it was hardly poſſible to twiſt them permanently. Before they graſped each other ſo hard that they could not be drawn, they were ſtrained almoſt to breaking.</p><p>Attempts have been made to increaſe the ſtrength of cordage by tanning. But although it remains a conſtant practice in the manufacture of nets, it does not appear that much addition, either of ſtrength or durability, can be given to cordage by this means. The trial has been made with great care, and by per-ſons fully able to conduct the proceſs with propriety. But it is found that the yarns take ſo long time in drying, and are ſo much hurt by drying flowly, that the room required for a conſiderable rope-work would be immenſe ; and the improvement of the cordage is but trifling, and even equivocal. Indeed tanning is a chemical proceſs, and its effect depends entirely on the nature of the materials to which the tan is applied. It unqueſtionably condenſes, and even ſtrengthens, the fibre of leather : but for any thing that we know <hi rend="italic">à priori, </hi>it may deſtroy the coheſion of hemp and flax ; and experiment alone could decide the queſtion. The reſult has been unfavourable ; but it does not follow from this that a tan cannot be found which ſhall produce on the texture of vegetables effects ſimilar to what oak-bark and other aſtringents produce on the animal fibre or membrane. It is well known that ſome dyes increaſe the</p><p>ſtrength of flax and cotton, notwithſtanding the corro-ſion which we know to be produced by ſome of the ingredients. This is a ſubject highly worth the attention of the chemiſt and the patriot.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Ropε-Dancer.</hi>  See <hi rend="italic">Rope-DANCER.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps">Rop</hi></hi><hi rend="italic">E-Yarn,</hi>  among ſailors, is the yarn of any rope untwiſted, but commonly made up of junk ; its uſe is to make ſinnet, matts, &amp;c.</p><p>ROQUET. See Rocket.</p><p>RORIDULA, in botany : A genus of the monσ-gynia order, belonging to the pentandria claſs of plants. The corolla 13 pentapetalous ; the calyx peπ-taphyllous ; the capſule trivalved ; the antheræ ſcroti-form at the baſe.</p><p>ROSA, the Rose : A genus of the polygamia order, belonging to the icoſandria claſs of plants ; and in the natural method ranking under the 35th order, <hi rend="italic">Sen-tocoſx.</hi>  There are five petals ; the calyx is urceolated, quinquefid, cornous, and ſtraitened at the neck. The ſeeds are numerous, hiſpid, and affixed to the inſide of the calyx.</p><p>The forts of roſes are very numerous ; and the bo-taniſts find it very difficult to determine with accuracy which are ſpecies and which are varieties, as well as which are varieties of the reſpective ſpecies. On this account Linnæus, and ſome other eminent authors, arc inclined to think that there is only one real ſpecies of roſe, which is the <hi rend="italic">roſa canina,</hi>  or “ dog-roſe of the hedges,” &amp;c. and that all the other forts are accidental varieties of it. However, according to the preſent Linnæan arrangement, they ſtand divided into 14 ſuppoſed ſpecies, each comprehending varieties, which in ſome forts are but few, in others numerous.</p><p>The ſuppoſed ſpecies and their varieties, according to the arrangement of modern botaniſts, are as follow :</p><p>I. The canina, canine roſe, wild dog-roſe of the hedges, or hep-tree, grows five or fix feet high, having prickly-ſtalks and branches, pinnated, five or ſeven-lobed leaves, with aculeated foot-ſtalks, ſmooth pedunculi, oval ſmooth germina, and ſmall ſingle flowers. There are two varieties, red-flowered and wſhite-flow-ered. They grow wild in hedges abundantly all over the kingdom ; and are ſometimes admitted into gardens, a few to increaſe the variety of the ſhrubbery col</p><p>lection.</p><p>2.    The alba, or common white-roſe, grows five or fix feet high, having a green item and branches, armed with prickles, hiſpid pedunculi, oval ſmooth germina, and large white flowers. The varieties are,—large double white roſe—dwarf ſingle white roſe—maidens-bluſh white roſe, being large, produced in cluſters, and of a white and bluſh-red colour.</p><p>3.    The Gallica, or Gallican roſe, &amp;c. grows from about three or four to eight or* ten feet high, in different varieties; with pinnated, three, five, or ſeven-lobed leaves, and large red and other coloured flowers in different forts. This ſpecies is very extenſive in ſuppoſed varieties, bearing the above ſpeciſic diſtinction, ſeveral of wſhich have been formerly conſidered as diſtinct ſpecies, but are now ranged among the varieties of the Gallican roſe, conſiſting of the following noted varieties.</p><p>Common red officinal roſe, grows erect, about three or four feet high, having ſmall branches, with but few prickles, and large ſpreading half-double deep-red</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>