<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>eb03-r03</title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>heart is made of inferior fluff, flack laid,· and of a ſize juſt equal to the ſpace it is to fill. When a rope of ' this fabric has been long uſed and become unſerviceable, and is opened out, the heart is always found cut and chaffed to pieces, like very ſhort oakum. This happens as follows ; When the rope is violently ſtrained, it ſtretches greatly .; becauſe the ſtrands ſui round the axis obliquely, and the ſtrain draws them into a poſition more parallel to the axis. But the heart has not the obliquity of parts, and cannot ſtretch ſo much ; at the ſame time, its yarns are firmly graſped by the hard ſtrands which ſurround them ; they muſt therefore be rtorn into ſhort pieces.</p><p>The proceſs for laying a rope with a heart is not veιy different from that already deſcribed. The top has a hole pierçed through it, in the direction of the axis. The ſkain or ſtrand intended for the heart paſſes through this hole, and is ſtretched along the walk. A boy attends it, holding it tight as it is taken into the cloſing rope. But a little attention to what has been ſaid will ſhow this method to be defective. The wick will have no more turns than the laid rope ; and as it lies in the very axis, its yarns will be much ſtraighter than the ſtrands. Therefore when the rope is ſtrained and ſtretched, the wick cannot ctretch as much as the laid ſtrands ; and being firmly graſped by them, it muſt break into ſhort pieces, and the ſtrands, having loſt their ſupport in thoſe places, will fink in, and the cordage grow looſe. We ſhould endeavour to enable all to ſtretch alike. The wick therefore ſhould fee twiſted in the ſame manner as the ſtrands, perhaps even a little more. It will thus communicate part of its ſtrength to the rope. Indeed it will not be ſo uniformly ſolid, and may chance to have three ſpiral vacuities. But that this does no harm, is quite evident from the ſuperior ſtrength of cable-laid cordage, to be deſcribed preſently, which have the ſame vacuities. In this way are the main and fore ſtays made for ſhips of the line. They are thought ſtronger than hawſer-laid ropes, but unfit for running rigging; becauſe their ſtrands are apt to get out of their places when the rope is drawn into loops. Tt is alſo thought that the heart retains water, rots, and communicates its putrefaction to the ſurrounding ſtrands.</p><p>■ Such is the general and eſſential proceſs of rope-making. The fibres of hemp are twiſted into yarns, that they may make a line of any length, and ſtick among each other with a force equal to their own coheſion. Thfe yarns are made into cords of permanent twiſt by laying them ; and, that we may have a rope of any degree of ſtrength, many yarns are united in one ſtrand, for the ſame reaſon that many fibres were united in one yarn ; and in the courſe of this proceſs it is in our power to give the rope a ſolidity and hardneſs which makes it leſs penetrable by water, which would rot it in a ſhor while.. Somç of theſe purpoſes are inconſiſtent with others : and the ſkill of a rope-maker lies in making the beſt compenſation ; ſo that the rope may on the whole be the beſt in point of ſtrength, pliancy, and duration, that the quantity of hemp in it can produce.</p><p>There is another ſpecies of cordage in very general uſe. A rope o<hi rend="sup">i</hi>  two or more ſtrands may be uſed as a ſtr?nd, in order to compoſe a ſtill larger rope ; and in this manner are cables and other ground tackle com</p><p>monly made ; for this reaſon ſuch cordage is called cable-laid cordage.</p><p>The proceſs of cable-laying hardly differs from that oſ hawſer-laying. Three ropes, in their ſtate of permanent twiſt, may be twiſted together ; but they will not hold it, like fine thread, becauſe they are ſtiff and elaiſic. They muſt therefore be treated like ſtrands for a hawſer. We muſt give them an <hi rend="italic">additional</hi>  twfiſt, which will diſpoſe them to lay or cloſe tllemſeives ; and this diſpoſition muſt be aided by the workmen at the ſledge. We ſay the twiſt ſhould be an addition to their twiſt as a rope. A twiſt in the oppoſite direction will indeed give them a diſpoſition to cloſe behind the top ; but this will be very ſmall, and the ropes (now ſtrands) will be exceedingly open, and will become more open in laying. The twiſt is therefore given in the direction of their twiſt as a rope, or oppoſite to that of the ριimary ſtrands, of which the ropes are compoſed. Theſe primary ſtrands are therefore partly untwiſted in cable-laying a rope, in the ſame manner as the yarns are untwiſted in the uſual proceſs of rope-making.</p><p>We need not infill farther on this part-of the manufacture. The reader muſt be ſenſible that the hawſers intended for ſtrands of a cable muſt not be ſo much twiſted as thoſe intended to remain hawſers ; for the twiſt given to a ſiniſhed hawſer is preſumed to be that which renders it moſt perfect, and it muſt be injured by any addition. The preciſe proportion, and the diftri-butionof the working up between the hardening of the ſtrands and cloſing the cable, is a ſubject about which the artiſts are no better agreed than in the caſe of haw-ſer-laid cordage. We did not enter on this ſubject while deſcribing the proceſs, -becauſe the introduction of reaſonings and principles would have hurt the ſim-plicity of the defcription.∙ The reader being now acquainted with the different parts of the manipulation, and knowing what can be done on any occaſion, will now be able to judge of the propriety oſ the whole, when he learns the principle on which the ſtrength of a rope depends.</p><p>We have already ſaid, that a rope-yarn ſhould be twiſted till a fibre will break rather than be pulled out from among the reſt, and that all twiſting beyond this is injurious to the ſtrength of the yarn : And we advanced this maxim upon this plain coniideration, that it is need-leſs to bind them cloſer together, for they will already break rather than come out ; and becauſe this cloſer binding is produced only by forcibly wrapping the outer fibres round the inner, and drawing the outer ones tight. Thus theſe fibres are on the ſtretch, and are ſtrained as if a weight were hung on each of them. The proceſs of laying lines, of a permanent twiſt, ſhows that we muſt do a little more. We muſt give the yarn a degree of elaſtic contractility, which will make it lay itſelf and form a line or cord which will retain its twiſt. This muſt leave the fibres of the yarns in a ſtate of greater compreſſion than iβ neceſſary for juſt keeping them together. But more than this ſeems to be need-leſs and hurtful. The ſame maxim muſt direct us in forming a rope conſiſting of ſtrands, containing more than one yarn. A needleſs exceſs of twiſt leaves them ſtrained, and leſs able to perform their office in the rope.</p><p>It not unſrequently happens, that the workman, in order to make his rope ſolid and. firm, hardens up</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>