<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>eb03-r03</title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p><hi rend="sup">-</hi> while the perſon who has it is preſent ; but as ſoon as he is gone, they will return with redoubled vigour to the field and tear up every thing before them.</p><p>The beſt remedy the farmer has is to watch well the time of the corn’s being in the condition in which they feed upon it ; and as this laſts only a few days, he ſhould keep a boy in conſtant pay to watch the field from day-break till the duſk of the evening. Every time they ſettle upon the ground to ſly over it, the boy is to holloa, and throw up a dead rook into the air : this will always make them riſe ; and by degrees they will be ſo tired of this conſtant diſturbance, that they will ſeek out other places of preying, and will leave the ground even before the time of the corn’s being unfit for them. The reaſon of their riling at the toſſing up of their dead fellow creature is, that they are a bird extremely apprehenſive of danger, and they are always alarmed when one of their comrades riſes. They take this for the riſing of an out-bird, and all fly off at the fignal.</p><p>ROOKE (Sir George), a gallant naval commander, born of an ancient and honourable family in Kent, in 1650. His merit raiſed him by regular ſteps to be vice-admiral of the blue: in which ſtation he ſerved in the-battle of La Hogue, on the 22d of May 1692 ; when it was owing to his vigorous behaviour, that the laſt ſtroke was given on that important day, which threw the French entirely into confulion. But the next day he obtained ſtill more glory ; for he had orders to go into La Hogue, and burn the enemy’s ſhips as they lay there. There were 13 large men of war, which had crowded as far up as poſſible ; and the tranſports, tenders, and ammunition ſhips, were diſpoſed in ſuch a manner that it was thought impoſſible to burn them. Beſides, the French camp was in fight, with all the French and Iriſh troops that were to have been employed in the invaſion of England; and ſeveral batteries were raiſed on the coaſt, well provided with heavy artillery. The vice-admiral made the neceſſary preparations for obeying his orders, but found it impoſſible to carry in the ſhips of hisſtquadron : he therefore ordered his light 'frigates to ply in cjoſe to the ihore ; and having manned out all his boats, went himſelf to give directions for the attack, burnt that very night fix three-deck-ſhips, and the next day ſix more, from 76 to 60 guns, together with moſt of the tranſports and ammunition veſſels ; and this under the fire of all the batteries iuſt mentioned, and in light of all the French and Iriſh troops : yet this bold action colt the lives of no more than ten men. The vice-admiral’s behaviour on this occaſſion appeared ſo great to King William, that having no opportunity at that time of promoting him, he fettled a penſion of 1000 l. per annum on him for life ; and afterwards going to Portſmouth to view the fleet, went on board Mr Rooke’s ſhip, dined with him, and then conferred on him the honour of knighthood, he having a little before made him vice-admiral of the red.</p><p>In conſequer.ce of other ſervices he was in 1694 raiſed to the rank of admiral of the blue : towards the cloſe of the next year, he was admiral of the white ; and was alſo appointed admiral and commander in chief in the Mediterranean.</p><p>During King William’s reign, Sir George was twice elected member for Portſmouth ; and upon the acceſ-ſion of Queen Anne in 1702, he was conſtituted vice-admiral and lieutenant of the admiralty of England, as alſo lieutenant of the fleets and ſeas of this kingdom.<hi rend="sub"> </hi>Upon the declaration of war againſt France, he was ordered to command a fleet ſent againſt Cadiz, the duke of Ormond having the command of the land forces. On his paſſage home, receiving an account that the galleons, under the eſcort of a ſtrong French ſquadron, were got into the harbour of Vigo, he reſolved to attack them ; and on the 11th of October came before the harbour of Rondondello, where the French commander had neglected nothing neceſſary for putting the place into the beſt poſture of defence. But not-withſtanding this, a detachment of 15 Engliſh and 10 Dutch men of war, of the line of battle, with all the fire-ſhips, were ordered in ; the frigates and bomb-veſſels followed ; the great ſhips moved after ahem, and the army landed near Rondondello. The whole ſervice was performed under Sir George’s directions, with admirable conduct and bravery; for, in ſhort, all the ſhips were deſtroyed or taken, prodigious damage done to the enemy, and vaſt wealth acquired by the allies. For this action Sir George received the thanks of the Houſe of Commons, a day of thankſgiving was appointed both by the queen and the ſtates-general, and Sir George was promoted to a ſeat in the privy-council ; yet, not-withſtanding this, the Houſe of Lords reſolved to inquire into his conduct at Cadiz. But he ſo fully juſtiſied himſelf, that a vote was paſſed, approving his behaviour.</p><p>In the ſpring of the year 1704, Sir George commanded the ſhips of war which convoyed King Cha. III. of Spain to Liſhon. In July, he attacked Gibraltar ; when, by the bravery of the Engliſh ſeamen, the place was taken on the 24th, though the town was extremely ſtrong, well furniſhed with ammunition, and had 100 guns mounted, all facing the ſea and the narrow paſſes to the land: An action which was conceived and executed in leſs than a week ; though it has fince endured ſieges of many months continuance, and more than once baffled the united forces of France and Spain. This brave officer being at laſt obliged, by the prevalence of party-ſpirit, to quit the ſervice of his country, retired to his ſeat in Kent ; where he ſpent the remainder of his days as a private gentleman.</p><p>He was thrice married ; and by his ſecond lady Mrs Luttrell left one ſon. He died January 24. 1708-9, in his 58th year, and was buried in Canterbury cathedral, where a monument is erected to his memory. In his private life he was a good huſhand and a kind maſter, lived hoſpitably towards his neighbours, and left behind him a moderate fortune; ſo moderate, that when he came to make his will, it ſurpriſed thoſe who were preſent : but Sir George aſſigned the reaſon in a few words, “ I do not leave much (ſaid he), but what I leave was honeſtly gotten ; it never coſt a ſailor a tear, or the nation a farthing.”</p><p>ROOM, a chamber, parlour, or other apartment in a houſe. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Architecture</hi>  and <hi rend="smallcaps">Ventilation.</hi></p><p>ROOT, among botaniſts, denotes that part of a plant which imbibes the nutritious juices of the earth, and tranſmits them to the other parts. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Plant</hi>  and <hi rend="smallcaps">Radix.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Colours extracted, from ROOTS.</hi>  See <hi rend="italic">COLOUR-Making,<hi rend="sub"/></hi>n<hi rend="sup">o </hi>41.</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>