<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>eb03-r03</title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>direction of an external force which is exerted on the point of impulſion of a body not connected with any fixed axis, and of the diſpoſition of all the parts of this body with reſpect to this point of impulſion, will furniſh us with the mathematical circumſtances which determine the poſition of the ſpontaneous axis of converſion, and therefore determine the poſition of the axis through the centre (parallel to the ſpontaneous axis of converſion), round which the body will whirl, while it3 centre proceeds in the direction of the external force.</p><p>The proceſs, therefore, for determining the axis of progreſſive rotation is juſt the converſe of the proceſs for determining the centre of percuſſion.</p><p>John Bernoulli was the firſt who conſidered the motion of free bodies impelled by forces whoſe line of direction did not paſs through their centre of gravity ; and lie takes it for granted, that ſince the body both advances and turns round an axis paſſing through the centre of gravity, this axis is perpendicular to the plane paſſing through the direction of the force, and through the point of impulſion and the centre of gravity. Other authors of the firſt name, ſuch as Huyghens, Leibnitz, Roberval, &amp;c. have thought themſelvee -obliged to de-monſtrate this. Their demonſtration is as follows :</p><p>Let a body whoſe centre of gravity is G (ſig. II.) be impelled at the point P by a force acting in the direction P Q not paſſing through the centre. The inertia of the whole body wfill reſiſt in the ſame manner as if the whole matter were collected in G, and therefore the reſiſtance will be propagated to the point P in the direction. GP. The particle P, therefore, is impelled in the direction P and reiiſted in the direction P A, and muſt therefore begin t© move in ſome direction PB, which makes the diagonal of a parallelogram of which the ſides have the directions P Q__and P A. The diagonal and ſides of a parallelogram are in one plane. P is therefore moving in the plane APQB or GPQ^, and it is turning round an axis which paſſes through G.— Therefore this axis <hi rend="italic">muſl</hi>  be perpendicular to the plane</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">gpq.</hi></p><p>It would require a ſeries of difficult proportions to ſhow the fallacy of this reaſoning in general terms, and to determine the poſition oſ the axis through G. We ſhall content ourſelves with a very limple caſe, where there can be no heſitation. Let A and B (ſig. 12.) be two equal balls connected wfith thc axis <hi rend="italic">a b</hi>  by inflexible lines A <hi rend="italic">a,</hi>  B <hi rend="italic">b,</hi>  perpendicular to <hi rend="italic">a b.</hi>  Let A <hi rend="italic">a</hi>  be 1, and B <hi rend="italic">b</hi>  2. The centre of gravity G wfill evidently be in the line cG parallel to Art and B/?, and in the middle of <hi rend="italic">a b,</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">c</hi>  G is ιfi- Let O be the centre of</p><p>A . A <hi rend="italic">a<hi rend="sup">2</hi></hi>  + B . B <hi rend="italic">D</hi></p><p>oſciBation. ,0 &gt;3 =    - = t—</p><p>Draw A w, B <hi rend="italic">n</hi>  perpendicular to <hi rend="italic">c</hi>  G, and ſuppoſe the balls transferred to <hi rend="italic">m</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">n.</hi>  Their centre of oſcillation will be ſtill at O ; and we ſee that if the ſyſtem in this form were ſtopped at 0, all would be in equilibrio. For the force with which the ball A arrives (by Bringing round thé axis)’at <hi rend="italic">rn,</hi>  is as its quantity of matter and velocity jointly, that is, A . A <hi rend="italic">a,</hi>  or ι. That of B arriving at <hi rend="italic">n</hi>  is B . B <hi rend="italic">b,</hi>  or 2. The arm <hi rend="italic">m</hi>  0 of the lever turning round 0 is -∣∙, and the arm <hi rend="italic">n</hi>  O is -j-. The forces, therefore, are reciprocally as the arms of the lever on which they act, and their momenta, or powers to turn the line <hi rend="italic">rn n</hi>  round O, are equal and oppoſite, and therefore balance each other ; and therefore, at the</p><p>mitant of flopping, no preſſure is exerted at <hi rend="italic">c.</hi>  Therefore, if any impulſe is made at O, the balls at <hi rend="italic">m</hi>  and « will be put in motion with velocities 1 and 2, and <hi rend="italic">c</hi>  will be a ſpontaneous centre of converſion. Let ue ſee whether this will be the caſe when the halls are in their natural places A and B, or whether there will be any tendency to a rotation round the axis <hi rend="italic">c</hi>  0. The momentum of A, by which it tends to produce a rotation round <hi rend="italic">c</hi>  O is A . A <hi rend="italic">a .</hi>  A ot, = 1 × A ot. That of B is B.B zLBn, — 2×Bπ. Aot and B <hi rend="italic">n</hi>  are equal, and therefore the momentum of B is double that of A, and there is a tendency of the ſyſtem to turn round <hi rend="italic">c</hi>  O; and if, at the inſtant of ſtoppage, the ſupports oſ the axis <hi rend="italic">ab</hi>  were removed, this rotation round <hi rend="italic">c</hi>  O would take place, and the point <hi rend="italic">b</hi>  would advance, and <hi rend="italic">a</hi>  would recede, <hi rend="italic">c</hi>  only remaining at reſt. Therefore, if an impulſe were made at O, <hi rend="italic">a b</hi>  w<hi rend="sup">,</hi>ould not become a ſpontaneous momentary axis of converſion, and 0 is not the centre of percuſſion. This centre muſt be ſomewhere in the line OP parallel to<hi rend="italic">a b,</hi>  as at P, and ſo ſituated that the momenta A . A <hi rend="italic">a</hi>  . A « and B . B <hi rend="italic">β</hi>  . B <hi rend="italic">β</hi>  may be equal, or that A <hi rend="sup">a</hi>- may be double of B<hi rend="sub">j</hi>g,or <hi rend="italic">ap </hi>double of <hi rend="italic">bp.</hi>  If an impulſe be now made at P, the balls A B will be urged by forces as 1 and 2, and therefore will move as if round the axis <hi rend="italic">a b,</hi>  and there will be no preſſures produced at <hi rend="italic">a</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">b,</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">a b</hi>  will really become a momentary ſpontaneous axis of converſion.</p><p>Now join G and P. Here then it is evident, that a body or ſyſtem A,B, receiving an impulſe at P perpendicular to the plane <hi rend="italic">a c</hi>  G, acquires to itſelf a ſpontaneous axis of converſion which is not perpendicular to the line joining the point of impreſſion and the centre of gravity. And we have ſhown, in art. 84. that this motion round <hi rend="italic">a b</hi>  is compounded of a progreſſive motion of the whole body in the direction of the centre, and a rotation round an axis paſſing through the centre <hi rend="italic">parallel to α b.</hi>  Therefore, in this ſyſtem of free bodies, the axis of rotation is not perpendicular to the plane paſſing through the centre of gravity in the direction of the. impelling force.</p><p>As w<hi rend="sup">f</hi>e have already obſerved, it would be a laborious •taſk to aſcertain in general terms the poſition of the &lt; progreſſive axis of rotation. Although the proceſs is’ the inverſe of that for determining the centre of per- j cuſſion when the axis of rotation is given, it is a moſt , intricate bufineſs to convert the ſteps of this proceſs. The general method is this : The momentum of a particleA (fig. 5.) by which it tends to change the poſx-tion of the axis D <hi rend="italic">cl,</hi>  has for its factors A <hi rend="italic">a</hi>  A ∕, and A ≈, which are its diſtances from three planes DT<hi rend="sup">t</hi>  z, DCO<hi rend="italic">n,</hi>  and C<hi rend="sub">ι</hi>5<hi rend="sup">r</hi>χκ, given in poſition. The ſum of all theſe muſt be equal to nothing,-by the compenſa-tion oſ poſitive and negative quantities. We muſt find three other planes (of which only one is in ſome meaſure determined in poſition, being perpendicular to DCO »), ſo ſituated that the ſums of ſimilar products of the diſtances of the particles from them may in like manner be equal to nothing. This is a very intricate problem ; ſo intricate, that mathematicians have long doubted and diſputed about the certainty of the ſolu-tions. Euler, d’Alembert, Erifi, Landen, and others, have at laſt proved, that every body, however irregular its ſhape, has at leaſt three axes paſſing through its centre of gravity., round which it will continue to re-</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>