<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>eb03-r03</title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>of 40,000 irregulars, Calmucks, Coſſacks, and other Tartars, who live under their dominion. But the number may be doubled on any emergency. 1 he czarina has likewiſe a conſiderable fleet in the Baltic, and a great number of formidable galleys, frigates, fire-ſhips, and bomb-ketches.</p><p>RUST, the flower or calx of any metal, procured by corroding and diſſolving its fuperficial parts by ſome menſtruum. ' Water is the great inſtrument or agent in producing ruſt : and hence oils, and other ſatty bodies, ſecure metals from ruſt ; water being no menſtruum for oil, and therefore not able to make its way through it. All metals except gold are liable to ruſt ; and even this alſo if expoſed to the fumes of ſea-ſalt. For remedies againſt ruſt, ſee Iron, <hi rend="italic">par. ult.</hi></p><p>RUSTIC, in architecture, implies a manner of budding in imitation of nature, rather than according to the rules of art. See Architecture.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Rusτιc Gods, dii rufilιci,</hi>  in antiquity, were the gods of the country, or thoſe who preſided over agriculture, &amp;c. Varro invokes the 12 <hi rend="italic">dît confiâtes,</hi>  as the principal among the ruſtic gods ; viz. Jupiter, Tellus, the Sun, Moon, Ceres, Bacchus, Rubigus, Flora, Minerva, Venus, Lympha, and Good Luck. Beſides theſe 12 aich-ruſtic gods, there were an infinity of leſſer ones ; as Pales, Vertumnus, Tutelina<hi rend="sub">5</hi>  Fulgor, Stercu-lius, Mellona, Jugatinus, Collinus, Vallonia, Terminus, Sylvanus, and Priapus. Struvius adds the Satyrs, Fauns, Sileni, Nymphs, and even Tritons ; and gives the empire over all the ruſtic gods to the god Pan.</p><p><hi rend="italic">R υsτ!C Order,</hi>  that decorated with ruſtic quoins, ruſtic work, &amp;e.</p><p><hi rend="italic">RUsτ∣c Work,</hi>  is where the ſtones in the face, &amp;c. of a building, inſtead of being ſmooth, are hatched, or picked with the point of a hammer.</p><p>RUSTRE, in heraldry, a bearing of a diamond ſhape, pierced through in the middle with a round hole. See Heraldry.</p><p>RUT, in hunting, the venery or copulation of deer.</p><p>RUT A, rue : A genus of the monogynia order, belonging to the decandria claſs of plants ; and in the natural method ranking under the 26th order, <hi rend="italic">Multifi-liqu&lt;r.</hi>  The calyx is quinquepartite; the petals concave; the receptacle ſurrounded with 1 o melliferous pores ; the capſule is lobed. In ſome flowers, a fifth part of the number is excluded. There are ſeveral ſpecies ; of which the moſt remarkable is the horten fis, or common broad-leaved garden rue, which has been long cultivated for medicinal uſe. This riſes with a ſhrubby ſtalk to the height of five or ſix feet, ſending out branches on every ſide, garniſhed with decompounded leaves, whoſe ſmall lobes are wedge-ſhaped, of a grey colour, and have a ſtrong odour. The flowers are produced at the end of the branches in bunches almoſt in the form of umbels : they are compoſed of four yellow concave petals which are cut on their edges, and eight yellow ſtamina which are longer than the petals, terminated by roundiſh ſummits. The germen becomes a roundiſh capſule, with four lobes punched full of holes containing rough black ſeeds.</p><p>Rue has a ſtrong ungrateful fmell, and a bitteriſh penetrating taſte : the leaves, when full of vigour, are extremely acid, inſomuch as to inflame and bliſter the ſkin, if much handled. With regard to their medicinal virtues, they are powerfully ſtimulating, attenuating, and detergent ; and hence, in cold phlegmatic habits, they quicken the circulation, diſſolve tenacious juices, open obſtructions of the excretory glands, and promote the fluid ſecretions. The writers on the materia mεdi-ca in general have entertained a very high opinion of the virtues of this plant. Boerhaave is full of its praiſes ; particularly of the eſſential oil, aud the diſtil-led water cohobated or re-diſtilſed ſeveral times from freſh parcels of the herb. Alter extravagantly commending other waters prepared in this manner, he adds, with regard to that of rue, that the greateſt commendations he can bellow upon it fall ſhort of its merit : “ What medicine (lays he) can be more efficacious for promoting ſweat and perſpiration, for the cure of the hyſteric paſſion and of epilepſies, and for expelling poiſon ?” Whatever ſervice rue may be of in the two laſt caſes, it undoubtedly has its uſe in the others : the cohobated water, however, is not the moſt efficacious preparation of it. An extract made by rectified ſpirit contains in a ſmall compaſs the whole virtues of the rue; this menſtruum taking up by infufion all the pungency and flavour of the plant, and elevating nothing in diſtillation. With water, its peculiar flavour and warmth ariſe ; the bitterneſs, and a conſiderable ſhare of the pungency, remaining behind.</p><p><hi rend="italic">RUTH Baga,</hi>  or Swediſh turnip. See Husbandry,</p><p>p. 761.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Book of RUTH, a canonical book of the Old Te-ſtament ; being a kind of appendix to the book of Judges, and an introduction to thoſe σf Samuel; and having its title from the perſon whoſe ſtory is here principally related. In this ſtory are obſervable the ancient rights of kindred and redemption ; and the manner of buying the inheritance of the deceaſed, with other particulars of great note and antiquity. The ca-nonicalneſs of this book was never diſputed ; but the learned are not agreed about the epocha of the hiſtory it relates. Ruth the Moabiteſs is found in the genealogy of our Saviour. Matth, i. 5.</hi></p><p>RUTILUS. See Cvprinus, n<hi rend="sup">θ</hi> 6.</p><p>RUTHERGLEN, or by contraction Ruglen, the head borough of the netherward of Lanarkſhire in Scotland, is ſituated in N. Lat. 55<hi rend="sup">0</hi> yι', and W. Long. 4<hi rend="sup">c</hi> 13' ; about two miles ſouth-eaſt of Glaſgow, and nine weſt of Hamilton. Few towns in Scotland can lay greater claim to antiquity than Rutherglen. Maitland, in his Hiſtory of the Antiquities of Scotland, vol. i. p. 92. tells us, that it was founded by a king Reuther, from whom it derived its name ; and a tradition of the ſame import prevails among the inhabitants. But without laying any ſtreſs on the authority of tradition, which is often falſe and always doubtful, we find, from ſeveral original charters ſtill preſerved, that it was erected into a royal borough by king David I. about the year 1126.</p><p>The territory under the juriſdiction of the borough was extenſive, and the inhabitants enjoyed many diſtin-guiſhed privileges, which were however gradually wreſted from them, by political influence, in favour of Glaſgow, which in latter times roſe into conſequence by trade and manufactures. The ancient dimenſions oſ the place are now unknown ; but in the fields and gardens towards the eaſt the foundations of houſes are occaſion-ally diſeovered. It is now of a very reduced ſize, conſiſting but of one principal ſtreet and a few lanes, and containing about 1 63 ι inhabitants.</p><p>About 150 yar&lt;⅛ to the ſouth of.the main ſtreet</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>