<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>eb03-r03</title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>He publicly ridiculed the exerciſe and evolutions of the Ruffian troops ; and haſtily adopting the Pruſſian diſcipline, without digeſting and fitting it for the conſtitution of his own forces, he completely ruined himſelf by diſguſting the army.</p><p>What he loſt was ſoon and eaſily gained by the emiſſaries of Catharine. Four regiments of guards, amounting to 8ooo men, were inſtantly brought over by the three brothers Orloff, who had contrived to ingratiate themſelves with their officers. The people at large were in a ſtate of indifference, out of which they were rouſed by the following means. A little manuſcript was handed about, containing principles of legiſlation for Ruſſia, founded on natural rights, and on the claims of the different claſſes of people which had inſenfibly been formed, and become ſo familiar as to appear natural. In that performance was propoſed a convention of deputies ſrom all thc claſſes, and from every part of the empire, to converſe, but without authority, on the ſubjects of which it treated, and to inform the ſenate of thc reſult of their deliberations. It paſſed for the work of her majeſty and was much admired.</p><p>While Catharine was thus high in the public eſteem and affection, the emperor took the alarm at her popularity, and in a few days came to the reſolution of confining her for life, and then of marrying his favourite. The ſervants of that favourite betrayed her to her filter, who imparted the intelligence to the empreſs. Catherine ſaw her danger, and inſtantly formed her reſolution. She muſt either tamely ſubmit to perpetual impriſonment, and perhaps a cruel and ignominious death, or contrive to hurl her huſhand from his throne. No other alternative was left her ; and the conſequence was what undoubtedly was expected. The proper ſteps were taken ; folly fell before abilities and addreſs, and in three days the revolution was accompliſhed.</p><p>When the emperor ſaw that all was loſt, he attempted to enter Cronſtadt ſrom Oranienbaum, a town on the gulph of Finland, 39 verſts, or near 26 miles from Peterſburgh. The ſentinels at the harbour preſented their muſkets at the barge ; and though they were not loaded, and the men had no cartridges, he drew back. The Engliſh ſailors called from ſhip to ſhip for ſome perſon to head them, declaring that they would take him in and defend him ; but he precipitately withdrew. Munich received him again at Oranienbaum, and exhorted him to mount his horſe and head his guards, ſwearing to live and die with him. He ſaid, “ No : I ſee it cannot be done without ſhedding much of the blood of my brave Holſteinians. I am not worthy of the ſacrifice.” The revolution was ſettled, and Catharine declared <hi rend="italic">autocratrix.</hi>  The crown was ſaid to be preſſed upon her, and her ſon was proclaimed <hi rend="italic">her</hi>  heir, and <hi rend="italic">as </hi><hi rend="italic">ſuch</hi>  great duke of all the Ruſſias.</p><p>She behaved with magnanimity and moderation ; retained Munich; even pardoned counteſs Vorontzoſſ the emperor’s favourite ; and afterwards, on her marriage with Mr Raulotſky, made a handſome· ſettlement on them. She allowed the expectations of golden days and a philoſophical government to become the ſubject of faſhionable conversation ; and the princeſs Daſhkoff@@(c) was completely happy. The convention of deputies was even reſolved on; and as they were not to be elected by the people, except here and there for the ſhow, Prince Galitzin and Count Panin, whom ſhe had completely gained over, and who had the greateſt abilities of any Ruſſians about court, were at immenſe pains in appointing a proper ſet. In the mean time, a great number of ſhowy patriotic projects were begun. A grave Engliſh clergyman was invited over to ſuperintend the inſtitution of ſchools for civil and moral education; and the empreſs was moſt liberal in her appointments. This inſtitution failed, however, to produce the effects expected from it. The clergyman appointed, though a moſt excellent character and real philan-thropiſt, had views too contracted for the ſphere in which he was placed ; and Mr Betſkoy, the Ruffian <hi rend="italic">Mecaenas,</hi>  to whom the empreſs referred him for inſtructions, preferred déclamation, and ſtage-playing, and ballets, to all other accompliſhments.</p><p>In the mean time, elegance of all kinds was introduced before the people were taught the principles of morals. The nobles were ſent a travelling ; and as the Ruſſians more eaſily acquire foreign languages than the people of moſt other nations, have great vivacity without flippancy, and in general underſtand play, theſe travellers were everywhere well received, eſpecially at Paris, where reaſons of ſtate contributed not a little to procure to them that attention with which they were treated. They were raviſhed with the manners of foreign courts, and imported faſhions and fineries without bounds. The ſovereign turned all this to her own account, by encouraging a diſſipation which rendered court favours neceſſary, and made the people about her forget their Utopian dreams.</p><p>The convention of deputies at laſt aſſembled in the capital. The empreſs’s book of inſtructions @@(d) came forth; and by ſome great things were doubtleſs expected. The moſt conſequential of the deputies were privately inſtructed to be very cautious, and informed that carriages and guards were ready for Siberia. There was a grand proceſſion at their preſentation. Each had the honour of kiſſing her majeſty’s hand and receiving a gold medal. They met in form to recogniſe one an-</p><p>@@@(c)    This lady, during the progreſs of the revolution, certainly acted either from the moſt difintereſted patriotiſm or the ∙moſt generous friendſhip. She might have taken part with the emperor, and directed the counſels of the empire ; for her ſiſter, on whom he doated, acknowledged her ſuperiority, and wanted nothing  but pleaſure. Between them they could eaſily have governed ſuch a man as Peter III. but Catharine Romanovna was a theoretical enthufiaſt, who loved the empreſs becauſe ſhe thought her a philoſopher and philanthropiſt ; and perhaps ſhe might entertain hopes of directing the conduct of Catharine II. as ſhe had formerly aſſiſted her in her patriotic ſtudies.</p><p>@@@(d)    It is intitled, <hi rend="italic">Inſtructions for the Deputies to conſult about a New Code of Laws,</hi>  &amp;c. and is a very reſpectable work, which does honour to the empreſs, by whom it was undoubtedly compoſed.</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>