<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>eb03-r03</title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p><hi rend="italic">5⅛0</hi>  miles in extent, had long thought themſelves ill uſed by the Lithuanians on account of their religion, ∙wlιich was that of the Greek church ; and wanted to -withdraw from their*(objection to Poland, and put themſelves under the protection of Ruſſia. The following accident afforded them the wiſhed-for pretence. Their envoys arriving at Wilna, deſired admittance to the king’s preſence : which being refuſed, one of them endeavoured to force his way in ; but the porter ſhut the door rudely againſt him, and in ſo doing broke one -cf his fingers. The ſervant was immediately put to .--death for this offence : but the Servians, by no means ſatisfied with that, returned home in great fury, and prevailed upon their countrymen to ſubmit themſelves and their country to the Muſcovites. Cafimir made ; ſeveral attempts to recall them, but to no purpoſe.</p><p>Matthias king of Hungary dying about this time, two of his ſons, Uladiflaιi6, then king of Bohemia, and i John Albert, contended for the vacant crown. Cafimir -wanted to give it to,the latter, whom he accordingly aſſiſted to the utmoſt of his power ; and to enable him the better ſo to do, though he was in great want of money as well as men, he purchaſed a renewal of the truce with the Ruffians, and thereby gave John Bafi∙ lovitz time to eſtabliſh himſelf in his new acquiſi-tions.</p><p>Cafimir died in the year 1492, and was ſucceeded on the throne of Poland by his ſon John Albert, w ho, totally diſregarding the Ruffians, involved himſelf un-neceffarily in a war with the brave Stephen duke of Moldavia : and though he had at the ſame time both the Tartars and Tufks againſt him, his propenſity to pleaſure, and his laſeivious diſpofition, rendered him ſo indolent, that he not only did not ſo much as attempt to moleſt Bafilowitz in any of his poffeſſions, but concluded a peace with him on terms very advantageous tp the latter ; and even entered into a treaty, by which he ſtipulated not to aſſiſt the Lithuanians, though they had choſen his brother Alexander for their duke, in caſe the Ruffians ſhould attack them, as it was ſuppoſed they would. Alexander thinking to parry the inconveniences of this agreement, and to guard againſt the deſigns of his enemies, demanded in marriage Ba-ſilowitz’s daughter, Helena, by his ſecond wife Sophia, and obtained her. The Lithuanians then flattered themſelves with a profpect of tranquillity : but the ambitious <hi rend="italic">czar,</hi>  for Bafilovitz had affumed that title ſince bis conqueſt of Caſan, aiming only at the increaſe of dominion, ſoon found a pretence to break with his new allies, by alleging, that Poliſh Ruſſia, as far as the ri-∙,ver Berezina, had formerly belonged to his anceſtors, --and therefore ſhould be his ; and that Alexander, by his marriage-contract, had engaged to build a Greek church at Wilna for his Ruffian conſort, which he had not done, but on the contrary endeavoured to force the Poliſh Ruffians to embrace the religion of the church of Rome. In conſequence of this plea, he ſent into the territories of his ſon-in-law, by different ways, i three armies, which reduced ſeveral places, deſtroyed the country about Smojenſko, and defeated the Lithu∙ .anian ſield-marſhal Oſtroſky near the river Wedr'alch, where he fell unawares into an ambuſh cf the Ruffians. Alexander raiſed a new army of Sijeſians, Bohemians, and Moravians ; but they came too late, the Ruffians having retired with their plunder. Elated by their ſucceſs againſt the Lithuanians, they invaded Livonia -in the year 1502, with 130,000 men : but Walter Von Plettenberg, grand-maſter of the knights of the croſs, with only 12,000 men, gave them a total overthrow ; -killing 10,000 of his enemies, with ſcarce any lofs on his own fide. Bafilovitz diipirited by this defeat, and being then engaged in a war with the Tartars, the Poles, and the city of Pleſkow; immediately diſpatched an embaffy to Plettenberg, and concluded a truce with him for 50 years. At the ſame time he begged of that general to ſend to Moſcow, that he might ſee him, one of the <hi rend="italic">iron-dragoons,</hi>  as he called them, wſho had performed wonders iια the late engagement. Von Plettenberg readily complied ; and the czar, ſtruck with admiration, rewarded the cuiraſſier’s accompliſhments with conſiderable honours and preſents.</p><p>Alexander had been elected king of Poland upon the death of his brother John Albert, which happened in the beginning of this year : but the Poles refuſed to crown his confort Helena, becauſe ſhe adhered to the Greek religion. Provoked at this affront, and probably ſtill more ſtimulated by ambition, Bafilovitz reſolved again to try his fortune with them; and accordingly ordered his ſon Demetrius, now the eldeſt, to march againſt Smolenſko, and reduce that city. The young prince did all that could be done : but the vigorous refiſtance of the belieged, and the arrival of the king of Poland with a numerous army, obliged the Ruffians to raiſe the fiege and return home ; and the czar was glad to make a freſh truce with the Poles for fix years, upon the eaſy terms of only returning the priſoners he had taken. Some writers ſay, that flying into a violent paſſion with his ſon the moment he ſaw him, and imputing the miſcarriage oſ this expedition to his want of courage or conduct, he gave him a blow which laid him dead at his feet ; to which is added, that remorſe for this raſſi action carried his father to his grave: but this account is not confirmed by authors whoſe authority can be relied on. Certain it is, however, that neither of them long furvived this event; and that Demetrius died firſt : for Sophia, who had gained an abſolute aſcendant over her huſhand, and wanted to give the ſovereignty to her own children, perfiιaded him by various artful infinuations to ſet afide and im-priſon his grandſon Demetrius, the only child of the late John, whom he had by his firſt wife Maria, and declare her then eldeſt ſon, Gabriel, his ſucceffor. Age and infirmities had rendered the czar ſo weak, that he blindly followed the iniquitous advice ; but ſhortly after finding his end approach, he ſent for young Demetrius, expreffed great repentance for his barbarity towards him, and on his death-bed declared him his lawful ſucceffor. He died in November 1 705, after a reign of 55 years; leaving behind him an immenſe territory, chiefly of his own acquiring.</p><p>The czar was no ſooner dead, than his ſon Gabriel Ivanovitz, at the ^inftigation of his mother Sophia, put an end to,the life of the young Demetrius, by confining him in priſon, wſhere heperiſhed with hunger and cold; alter wſhich Gabriel was crowned by the name of <hi rend="italic">Baſllius,</hi>  and took the title of <hi rend="italic">cz,ar,</hi>  as well as all the other titles belonging to the ſovereignty. On his acceſſion to the throne he expected that the Poles would be in confuſion about the election of a new ſovereign ; but his expectations, being defeated by their unanimous</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>