<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>eb03-r03</title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>fectually as by a common tie-beam. A nd by ſhorten·· ing BD to B√, we gain a greater infide height, and more room for an arched ceiling. Now if we ſubfti-∙tute a king-poſt BD (fig. 26.) and two ſtretchers or hammer-beams DA, DC for the other ſtrings, and connect them firmly by means of iron ſtraps, we obtain our purpoſe.</p><p>Let us compare this roof with a tie-beam roof in point of ſtrain and ſtrength. Recur to fig. 25. and complete the parallelogram ABCF, and draw the diagonals AC, BF croſſing in E. Draw BG perpendicular to CD. We have ſeen that the weight of the root (which we may callW) is to the horizontal thruſt at C as B F to EC ; and if we expreſs this thruſt by</p><p>W × EC</p><p>T, we have T = —p-p—. We may at preſent con-</p><p>ſider BC as a lever moveable round the joint B, and pulled at C in the direction EC by the horizontal thruſt, and held back by the ſtring pulling in the direction CD. Suppoſe that the forces in the directions EC and CD are in equihbrio, and let us find the force S by which the ſtring CD is ſtrained. Theſe forces muſt (by the property of the lever) be inverſely as the perpendiculars drawn from the centre of motion on the lines of their direction. Therefore BG : BE = T : S,</p><p><hi rend="sub">1</hi> _    „ BE <hi rend="sub">t</hi> BE.EC.</p><p>and S _ Γ × <hi rend="sub">bg</hi>, _ W X <hi rend="sub">brbg</hi></p><p>Therefore the ſtrain upon each of the ties DA and DC is always greater than the horizontal thruſt or the ſtrain on a fimple tie-beam. This would be no great inconvenience, becauſe the ſmalleſt dimenſions that we could give to theſe ties, ſo as to procure ſufficient fixtures to the adjoining pieces, are always ſufficient to wſthſtand this ſtrain. But although the ſame may be ſaid of the iron ſtraps which make the ultimate connections, there is always ſome hazard of imperfect work, cracks or flaws, which are not perceived. We can judge with tolerable certainty of the ſoundneſs of a piece of timber, but cannot ſay ſo much of a piece of iron. Moreover, there is a prodigious ſtrain excited on the king-poſt, when BG is very ſhort in compariſon of BE, namely, the force compounded of the two ſtrains 8 and S on the ties DA and DC.</p><p>But there is another defect from which the ſtraight tie-beam is entirely free. All roofs fettle a little.— When this roof ſettles, and the points B and D de-ſcend, the legs BA, BC muſt ſpread further out, and thus a preſſure outwards is excited on the walls. It is ieldom therefore that this kind of roof can be executed in this ſimple form, and other contrivances are neceſſary for counteracting this ſupervening action on the walls. Fig. 27. is one of the beſt wſhich we have ſeen, and is executed with great ſucceſs in the circus or equeſtrian theatre in Edinburgh, the width being 60 feet. The pieces EF and ED help to take off ſome of the weight, and by their greater uprightneſs they exert a ſmaller thruſt on the walls. The beam D <hi rend="italic">d</hi>  is alſo a fort of truſs-beam, having fomething of the ſame effect. Mr Price has given another very judicious one of this kind, Britiſh Carpenter, Plate IK, fig. C, from which the tie-beam may be taken away, and there will remain very little thruſt on the walls. Thoſe which he has given in the following Plate K are, in our opinion, very faulty. The whole ſtrain in theſe laſt roofs tends to Break the rafters and ties tranſverſely, and the fixtures-of the ties are alſo not well calculated to refill the ſtrain to wſhich the pieces are expoſed. W e hardly think that theſe roofs could be executed.</p><p>It is ſcarcely neceſſary to remind the reader, that in all that we have delivered on this ſubject, we have at-1 tended only to the conſtruction of the principal rafters or truſſes. In ſmall buildings all the rafters are of one kind ; but in great buildings the whole weight of the covering is made to reſt on a few principal rafters, which are connected by beams placed horizontally, and either mortiſed into them or ſcarfed on them. Theſe are called <hi rend="italic">purlins.</hi>  Small rafters are laid from purlin to purlin ; and on theſe the laths for tiles, or the ſkirting-boards for liâtes, are nailed. Thus the covering does not immediately reſt on the principal frames This allows ſome more liberty in their conſtruction, becauſe the garrets can be ſo divided that the principal rafters ſhall be in the partitions and the reſt left unincumbered. This conſtruction is ſo ſar analogous to that of ſtoots which are conſtructed with girders, binding, and bridge-ing joiſts.</p><p>It may appear preſuming in us to queſtion the propriety of this practice. There are ſituations in which it is unavoidable, as in the roofs of churches, which can be allowed to reſt on ſome pillars. In other ſituations, where partition-w<hi rend="sup">,</hi>alls intervene at a diſtance not too great for a ſtout purlin, no principal rafters are neceſſary, and the whole may be roofed with ſhort rafters of very ſlender ſcantling. But in a great uniform roof, which has no intermediate ſupports, it requires at leaſt ſome reafons for preferring this method of carcaſe-roofing to the ſimpler method of making all the rafters alike. The method of carcaſe-rooſing requires the {election of the greateſt logs of timber, which are ſeldom of equal ſtrength and ſoundneſs with thinner rafters. In theſe the outſide planks can be taken off, and the beſt part alone worked up. It alſo expoſes to all the defects of workmanſhip in. the mortiſing of pur-lins, and the weakening of the rafters by this very mortiſing ; and it brings an additional load of purlins and ſhort rafters. A roof thus conſtructed may ſurely be compared with a floor of limilar conſtruction. Here there is not a ſhadow of doubt, that if the girders were ſawed into planks, and theſe planks laid as joiſts ſuſſici-ently near for carrying the flooring boards, they will have the ſame ſtrength as before, except ſo much as is taken out of the timber by the ſaw. This will not amount to one-tenrh part of the timber in the binding, bridging, and ceiling joiſts, which are an additional load ; and all the mortiſes and other joinings are fo many diminutions of the ſtrength of the girders ; and as no part of a carpenter’s w<hi rend="sup">τ</hi>ork requires more ſkill and accuracy of execution, we are expoſed to many chances of imperfection. But, not to reſt on theſe confidera-tions, however reafonable they may appear, we ſhall relate an experiment made by one on whoſe judgment and exactneſs we can depend.</p><p>Two models of floors were made 18 inches ſquare of the ſineſt uniform deal, wſhich had been long lealoned. The one confiſted of ſimple joiſts, and the other was framed with girders, binding, bridging, and ceiling joiſts. The plain joiſts of the one contained the ſame quantity of tirA&gt;er with the girders alone of the other, and both were made by a moſt accurate workman. They were placed in wooden trunks 18 inches ſquare</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>