<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>eb03-r03</title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>That we may apply theſe proportions to explain the motion of rotation, we muſt recollect an unqueſtionable propoſition in dynamics, that the force which produces any motion is equal and oppoſite to the force which would prevent it, when applied in the fame place and in the fame line, or which would extinguiſh it in the fame time in which we ſuppoſe it to be produced. Therefore the force which is excited and made to act on any particle of a body, by the action of an external force on another particle, ſo as to cauſe it to move round an axis, is equal and oppoſite to the force which, when applied to that particle in the oppoſite direction, would be in equilibrio with the external force.</p><p>The only diſtinct notion we can form of the magnitude of any moving force is the quantity of motion which it can produce by acting uniformly during ſome given time. This will be had by knowing the velocity which it will produce in a body of known bulk. Thus we know that the weight of ten pounds of matter acting on it for a ſecond will cauſe it to fall 16 feet with an uniformly accelerated motion, and will leave it in a ſtate ſuch that it wotſld move on for ever at the rate of 32 feet in a ſecond ; which we call communicating the velocity of 3 2 feet per ſecond. In the ſame manner, the belt way of acquiring a diſtinct conception of the rotatory effort of a moving force, is to determine the quantity of rotatory motion which it can produce by acting uniformly during ſome known time.</p><p>Let a ſolid body turn round an axis palling through the point C (fig. 3.) perpendicular to the plane of this figure. Let this rotation be ſuppoſed to be produced by an external force acting in the direction FP. Let this force be ſuch, that if the body were free, that is, unconnected with any axis ſupported by fixed points, it would, by acting uniformly during a ſmall moment of time, cauſe its centre of gravity G @@(a) to deſcribe a line of a certain length parallel to FP. This we know to be the effect of a moving force acting on any ſolid body in free ſpace. The centre of gravity will always deſcribe a ſtraight line. Other particles may chance to move differently, if the body, befides its progreſſive motion, has alſo a motion of rotation, as is generally the cafe. Draw GI parallel to FP, and make GI to GC as the velocity which the external force would communicate to the centre of the body (if moving freely, unconnected with a ſupported axis), to the velocity which it communicates to it in the ſame time round the axis</p><p>C <hi rend="italic">c.</hi>  Alſo let <hi rend="italic">m</hi>  be the number of equal particles, or the quantity of matter in the body. Then <hi rend="italic">m. GI</hi>  will expreſs the quantity of motion produced by this force, and is a proper meaſure of it as a moving force ; for GI is twice the ſpace deſcribed during the given time with an uniformly accelerated motion.</p><p>But ſince the body cannot move any way but round the axis paſſing through C, the centre G will begin to move with the velocity, and in the direction, GH perpendicular to the line CG (n<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 2.) And any particle A can only move in the direction AL, perpendicular to CA. Moreover, the velocities of the different particles are as their radii vectores ; and CG is actually equal to the line GH, which expreſſes the velocity of a particle in G. Therefore CA will in like manner expreſs the velocity of the particle A. If A expreſs its quantity of matter, A<hi rend="sup">,</hi>CA will expreſs its quantity of motion, and will repreſent the force which would produce it by acting uniformly during the moment of time.</p><p>We expreſſed the external moving force by <hi rend="italic">m</hi>.GI. Part of it is employed in exciting the force A<hi rend="sup">,</hi>CA, which urges the particle A. In order to diſcover what part of the external force is neceſſary for this purpoſe, draw CP perpendicular to FP. The preceding obſer-vations ſhow us, that the force wanted at A is equal to the force which, when applied at P in the direction FP, would balance the force A<hi rend="sup">-</hi>CA applied to A in the direction LA. Therefore (by the property of the lever ACP, which is impelled at right angles at A and P) we muſt have CP to CA as the force A*CA to the balancing preſſure, which muſt be exerted at P, or at any point in the line FP. This preſſure is therefore</p><p>A∙CA∙CA A∙CA<hi rend="sup">l</hi><hi rend="sub">λ</hi>    ,    ,    ,</p><p>-C^p--or —Qp—. As we took <hi rend="italic">m</hi>.GI for the</p><p>meaſure of the whole external force, GI being the velocity which it would communicate to the whole body moving in free ſpace, we may take G<hi rend="italic">i</hi>  for the velocity which would be communicated to the whole body by</p><p>A<hi rend="sup">,</hi>CA<hi rend="sup">s</hi></p><p>the preſſure —çp<hi rend="sup">-</hi>’    <hi rend="sup">t</hi>^<hi rend="sup">l</hi>*<hi rend="sup">s</hi> P<hi rend="sup">re</hi>^<hi rend="sup">ure</hi></p><p>properly expreſſed by w.Gi. In like manner, <hi rend="italic">n&gt;.i k</hi>  may expreſs the portion of the external force employed in communicating to another particle B the motion which it acquires ; and ſo on with reſpect to all the particles of the body.</p><p>It muſt be deſirable to fee the manner in which the</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">@@@(a) We take this term in its uſual ſenſe, as expreſſing that point where the ſum of the </hi><hi rend="italic">equal</hi>  gravitations of each particle may be ſuppoſed united. It is by no means (though commonly ſuppoſed) the point where the equivalent of the real gravitations of the particles may be ſuppoſed to act, and to produce the ſame motion as wſhen acting on each particle ſeparately. It is this point only when all the particles gravitate alike, and in parallel directions. If the body were near the centre of the earth for inſtance, the gravitations of the different particles would neither be nearly equal nor in parallel lines ; and the place of its real centre of gravity, on which the equivalent of its whole gravitation may be ſuppoſed to act, would be very different from G. Were we to denominate the point G, as uſually determined, by its mathematical properties, we would call it the centre of position ; becauſe its diſtance from any plane, or its poſition with reſpect to any plane, is the average diſtance and poſition of all the particles. The true deſignation of G is “ the point through which if <hi rend="italic">any plane whatever </hi>be made to paſs, and if perpendiculars to this plane be drawn from every particle, the ſum of all the perpendiculars on one fide of this plane is equal to the ſum of all the perpendiculars on the other fide.”</p><p>It we were to denominate G by its mechanical properties, we would call it the centre of inertia ; for this is equal in every particle, and in the ſame direction : and it is not in conſequence of gravity, but of inertia, that the body deſcribes with the point G a line parallel to FP. We wiſh this remark to be kept in mind.</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>