<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>eb03-r03</title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>takes up in his hand ſuch as are flack,- and draws them tight, keeping them ſo till he reaches the upper end, where he cuts the yarns to a length, again adjuſts their tightneſs, and joins them all .together in a knot, to which he fixes the hook of a tackle, the other block of which is fixed to a firm poft, called the <hi rend="italic">vυarping-ρofl.</hi>  The ſkain is well ſtretched by this tackle, and then ſeparated into its different ſtrands. Each of theſe is knotted a-part at both ends. The knots at their upper ends are made faſt to the hooks of the cranks in the tackle-board, and thoſe at their lower ends are faſtened to the cranks in the fledge. The fledge itſelf is kept in its place by a tackle, by which the ſtrands are again ſtretched in their places, and every thing adjuſted, ſo that the fledge ſtands ſquare on the walk, and then a proper weight is laid on it. The tackle is now cut off, and the cranks are turned at both ends, in the contrary direction to the twiſt of the yarns. (In feme kinds of cordage the cranks are turned the ſame way with the ſpinning twiſt). By this the ſtrands are twiſted and hardened up ; and as they contract by this operation, the fledge is dragged up the walk. When the foreman thinks the ſtrands ſuſſiciently hardened, which he eſtimates by the motion of the fledge, he orders the heavers at the cranks to ſtop. The middle ſtrand at the ſledge is taken off from the crank. This crank is taken out, and a ſtronger one put in its place at D, fig. 9. The other ſtrands are taken off from their cranks, and all are joined on the hook which is now in the middle hole. The top is then placed between the ſtrands, and, being preſe-ed home to the point of their union, the car riage is placed under it, and it is firmly fixed down. Some weight is taken off the ſledge. The heavers now begin to turn at both ends. Thoſe at the tackle-board continue to turn as they did before ; but the heavers at the fledge turn in the oppoſite direction to their former motion, ſo that the cranks at both ends are now turning one way. By the motion of the ſledge crank the top is forced away from the knot, and the rope begins to cloſe. The heaving at the upper end reltores to the ſtrand the twiſt which they are conſtantly loling by the laying of the rope. '1 he workmen judge of this by making a chalk mark on intermediate points of the ſtrands, where they lie on the ſtakes which are let up along the walk for their ſupport. If the twfiſt of the ſtrands is diminiſhed by the motion of doling, they will ling then, and the chalk mark will move away from the tackle board : but if the twiſt increaſes by turning the crank-s at the tackle-board, the ſtrands will ſhorten, and the mark will come nearer to it.</p><p>As the doling of the rope advances, the whole ſhortens, and the ſledge is dragged up the walk. The top moves faſter, and at· laſt reaches the upper end of the walk, the rope being now laid. In the mean time, the fledge has moved ſeveral fathoms from the place where it was when the laying began.</p><p>Theſe motιor13 of the ſledge and top muſt be exactly adjuſted to each other. The rope muſt be of a certain length. Therefore the ſledge muſt ſtop at a certain place. At that moment the rope ſhould be laid ; that is, the top ſhould be at the tackle board. In this conſiſts the addrcſs of the foreman. He has his attention directed both ways. He looks at the ſtrands, and when he ſecs any oſ them hanging flacker betw<hi rend="sup">,</hi>een the flakes than the others, he calls to the heavers at the tackle· board to heave more upon that ſtrand. He finds it more difficult to regulate the motion of the top. It requires a conſiderable force to keep it in the angle oſ the ſtrands, and it is always diſpoſed to ſtart forward. Tc&gt; prevent or check this, ſome ſtraps of ſoſt rope are brought round the ſtaff of the top, and then wrapped ſeveral times round the rope behind the top, and kept firmly down by a lanyard or bandage, as is ſhown in the figure. This both holds back the top and greatly aſſiſts the laying of the rope, cauling the ſtrands to fall into their places, and keep cloſe to each other. This is ſometimes very difficult, eſpecially in ropes compoſed of more than three ſtrands. It will greatly improve the laying the rope, if the top have a ſharp, ſmooth, tapſering pin of hard wood, pointed at the end, projecting ſo far from the middle of its ſmaller end, that it gets in between the ſtrands which are cloſing. This ſupports them, and makes their cloſing more gradual and regular. The top, its notches, the pin, and the warp or ſtrap, which is lapped round the rope, are all ſmeared wſith greaſe or ſoap to aſſiſt the cloſing. The foreman judges of the progreſs of cloſing chiefly by his acquaintance with the w∙alk, knowing that when the fledge is abreaſt of a certain ſtake the top ſhould be a-breaſt of a certain other 'lake. When he finds the top too far down the walk, he flackens the motion at the tackle board, and makes the men turn briſkly at the fledge. By this the top is forced up the walk, and the laying of the rope accelerates, while the fledge remains in the lame place, becauſe the ſtrands are loſing their twill, and are lengthening, wſhile the cloſed rope is ſhortening. When, on the other hand, he thinks the top too far advanced, and fears that it will be at the head oſ the walk before the fledge has got to its proper place, he makes the men heave briſkly on the ſtrands, and the heavers at the fledge crank to work ſoftly.—-This quickens the motion of the .ſledge by ſhortening the ſtrands ; and by thus compenſating what has been overdone, the ſledge and top come to their places at once, and the work appears to anſwer the intention.</p><p>But this is a bad manner of proceeding, lt is evident, that if the I! rands be kept to one degree of hard-neſs throughout, and the heaving at the fledge be uniformly continued, the rope will be uniform. It may be a little longer or ſhorter than was intended, and the laying may be too hard in proportion to the twiſt of the ſtrands, in which caſe it will not keep it ; or it may be too flack, and the rope will tend to twi more. Either oſ theſe faults are diſcoverable by flackening the rope before it come off the hooks, and it may then be corrected. But if the error in one place be compenſated by that in another, this will not be eaſily ſeen before taking off the hooks ; and if it is a large and Iliff rope, it will hardly ever come to an equable ſtate in its different parts, but wall be apt to run into loops during ſervice.</p><p>It is, therefore,-of importance to preſerve the uniformity throughout the w hole. Mr Du Hamel, in his great work on rope-making, propoſes a method which is very exact, but requires an apparatus which is cumbersome, and which would be much in the way of the workmen. We .think that the following method would be extremely eaſy, embarraſs no one, and is perfectly exact. Having determined the proportion between the velocity of the top and fledge, let the diameter of the</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>