<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>eb03-r03</title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>whoſe ſkin Pluto had cauſed to be taken off, and ſtretched out on the ſeat in the bench. This ſatirej joined to the ſecret machinations of enemies, rendered all the attempts of his friends to procure his return abortive. After having ſtaid three months at Paris, he returned to Bruſſels in February 1740, at which olace he died March 1*7. 174t, ſtrongly impreſſed with religious ſen-timents. Immedir.tely before he received the viaticum, he proteſted he was not the author of thoſe horrid verſes which had ſo much embittered his life ; and this declaration, in the opinion of the virtuous part of mankind, wſll be conſidered as a ſuſſicient proof of his innocence. Borne have ſaid that Rouſſeau was profane, troubleſome, capricious, forward, vindictive, envious, a flatterer, and a ſatiriſt. Others again repreſent him as a man full of candour and openneſs, a faithful and grateful friend, and as a Chriſtian affected with a ſenſe of religion.— Amidſt ſuch widely varied accounts it is difficult to form an opinion of his character. Such of our readers as wiſh to know<hi rend="sup">7</hi> more of this great poet may conſult the Dictionary of M. Chatipepié, written with as much preciſion as impartiality, who endeavours to give a juſt idea of his character. From what he ſays, it does not appear that Rouſſeau can be cleared ſrom the accuſation brought againſt him of having attacked his benefactors. We believe he may be much more eaſily freed ſrom the imputation brought againſt him by ſome of having diſ-owned his father : for what occaſion had Rouſſeau to conceal the obſeurity of his birth ? It exalted his own merit.</p><p>, M. Seguy, in concert with M. the prince of la</p><p>Tour Taſſis, has given a very beautiful edition of his works, agreeable to the poet’s laſt corrections. It was publiſhed in 1743, at Paris, in 3 vols. 4t0, and in 4 vols. 12mo, containing nothing but what was acknowledged by the author as his own. It contains, 1. Four Books of Odes, of which the firſt are ſacred odes, ta-keu from the Pſalms. “ Rouſſeau (ſays Freron) unites in himſelf Pindar, Horace, Anacreon, and Malherbe. What fire, what genius, what flights of imagination, what rapidity of deſcription, what variety of affecting ſtrokes, what a crowd of brilliant companions, what richneſs of rhymes, what happy verſifi--cation ; but eſpecially what inimitable expreſſion ! His verſes are finiſhed in the higheſt ſtyle of perfection that French verſe is capable of aſſuming.” The lyric compoſitions of Rouſſeau are, in general, above mediocrity. All his odes are not, however, of equal merit. The moſt beautiful are thoſe which he has addreſſed to count du Luc, to Malherbe, to prince Eugene, to Vendôme, to the Chriſtian princes ; his Odes on the death of the prince de Conti, on the battle of Peterwara-din ; and the Ode to Fortune, altho’ there are certainly ſome few weak ſtanzas to be met with in it. There is conſiderable neatneſs in the compoſition of the Ode to a Widow, in his ſtanzas to the Abbé de Chaulieu, in his addreſſes to Roſſignol, in his Odes to count de Bi&gt;nne-val, to M. Duche, and to count de Sinzindorf ; and it is to be lamented that he wrote ſo few pieces oſ this kind, from which his genius ſeemed to ſead him with difficulty. 2. Two books of Epiſtles, in verſe. Although theſe do not wafιt their beauties, yet there prevails too much of a miſanthropic ſpirit in them, which takes away greatly from their excellence. He makes too frequent mention of his enemies and his miſe fortunes ; he diſplays thoſe principles which are flip-ported leſs on the bafis of truth than on thoſe various paſſions which ruled his mind at the time. He puts forth his anger in paradoxes. If he be reckoned equal to Horace in his odes, he is far inferior in his epiſtles. 'Γhere is much more philoſophy in the Roman poet than in him. 3. <hi rend="italic">Cantatas,</hi>  hie is the father of this ſpecies of poetry, in which he ſtands unrivalled. His pieces of this fort breathe that poetical expreſſion, that pic-tureſque ſtyle, thoſe happy turns, and thoſe eaſy graces, which conſtitute the true oharacter of this kind of writing. He is as lively and impetuous as he is mild and affecting, adapting himſelf to the paſſions of thoſe perſons whom he makes to ſpeak. “ I confeſs (ſays M. de la Harpe) that 1 find the cantatas of Rouſſeau more purely lyric than his odes, although he riſes to greater heights in theſe. I ſee nothing in his cantatas but bold and agreeable images. He always addreſſes himſelf to the imagination, and he never becomes either too verboſe or too prolix. On the contrary, in ſome of the beſt of his odes, we find ſome languiſh-ing ſtanzas, ideas too long delayed, and verſes of inex-cuſable meanneſs.” 4. <hi rend="italic">Allegories,</hi>  the moſt of which are happy, but ſome of them appear forced. 5. <hi rend="italic">Epigrams, </hi>after the manner of Martial and Marot. He has taken care to leave out of this edition thoſe pieces which li-centiouſneſs and debauchery inſpired. They bear, indeed, as well as his other pieces, the marks of genius ; but ſuch productions are calculated only to diſ-honour their authors, and corrupt the heart of thoſe who read them, 5. A book of <hi rend="italic">Poems on Various Subjects,</hi>  which ſometimes want both eaſe and delicacy. The moſt diſtinguiſhed are two eclogues, imitated from Virgil. 6. Four comedies in verſe ; the <hi rend="italic">Flatterer, </hi>whoſe character is well ſupported ; the <hi rend="italic">Imaginary Forefathers,</hi>  a piece which had much leſs ſucceſs, although it affords ſuſſiciently good ſentiment ; the <hi rend="italic">Capricious Man,</hi>  and the <hi rend="italic">Dupe oſ Herſelſ,</hi>  pieces of very inconſi-derable merit. 7. Three comedies in proſe ; the <hi rend="italic">Ccf-ſee-houſe,</hi>  the <hi rend="italic">Magic Girdle,</hi>  and the <hi rend="italic">Madragore,</hi>  which are little better than his other theatrical pieces. The theatre was by no means his forte; he had a genius more ſuited for ſatire than comedy, more akin to Boileau’s than Moliere’s. 8. A <hi rend="italic">Galleaioη oſ Letters,</hi>  in proſe. In this edition he has ſelected the moſt intereſting.— There is a larger collection in y volumes. This laſt has done at the ſame time both injury and honour to his memory. Rouſſeau in it ſpeaks both in favour of and againſt the very ſame perſons. He appears too haſty in tearing to pieces the characters of thoſe who dil-pleaſed him. We behold in them a man of a ſteady character and an elevated mind, who wiſhes to return to his native country only that he might be enabled completely to juſtify his reputation. We ſee him again correſponding with perſons of great merit and uncommon integrity, with the Abbé d’Olivet, Racine the ſon, the poets La Foſſe andDuche, the celebrated Rol-lin, M. le Franc de Pompignan, &amp;c. &amp;c. We meet alſo with ſome anecdotes and exact judgments of ſeveral writers. A bookſeller in Holland has publiſhed his port-folio, which does him no honour. There are, indeed, ſome pieces in this wretched collection which did come from the pen of Rouſſeau ; but he is leſs to be blamed for them than they are who have drawn theſe works from that oblivion to which our great poet had</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>