<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-04-20T21:26:00Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>der the wretched materials which more ancient dictionaries could furniſh, if we conſider the ſize and perfection of the work, and the immenſe labour and learning which muſt have been employed in the compilation. This work had been carried on at a greater expence than he could well bear. He expected to be reimburſed by the ſale of the book, but he was unfortunately diſappointed. John Scapula, one of his own ſervants, extracted from it whatever he thought would be moſt ſerviceable to ſtudents, and publiſhed it beforehand in 4t0. By this act of treachery Henry was reduced to poverty.</p><p>About this time he was much beloved by Henry III. of France, who treated him ſo kindly, and made him ſuch flattering promiſes, that he reſided frequently at Court. But theſe promiſes were never fulfilled, owing to the civil wars which ſoon after distracted France, and the unfortunate death of king Henry himſelf. During the remainder of his life his ſituation was very unſettled. We find him ſometimes at Paris, ſometimes in Geneva, in Germany, and even in Hungary. He died at Lyons in 1598, at the age of 70. He was fond of poetry from his very infancy. It was a cuſtom of his to compoſe verſes on horſeback, and even to write them, though he generally rode a very mettleſome ſteed. His <hi rend="italic">Thesaurus</hi> was his great work, but he was alſo the authorof ſeveral other treatiſes. His poems are numerous. His Apology for Herodotus is a witty ſatire on the Roman Catholics. His Concordance to the New Teſtament muſt have been a laborious  work, and has deſervedly endeared him to every Chriſtian who wiſhes to acquire a rational and critical knowledge of the Scriptures. The number of books which he publiſhed, though fewer than his father, was great, and ſuperior in elegance to any thing which the world had then ſeen. A great proportion of them were Greek ; he was the editor, however, of many Roman and even of ſome eaſtern writings. His Greek claſſics are remarkably correct ; the principal of them are Homer, Anacreon, Æschylus, Maximus Tyrius, Diodorus Siculus, Pindar, Xenophon, Thucydides, Herodotus, Sophocles, Diogenes Laertius, Plutarch, Plato, Apollonius Rhodius, Æschynes, Lyſias, Callimachus, Theocritus, Herodian, Dionyſius Hallicarnaſſenſis, Dion Caſſius, Isocrates, Appian, Xiphilin, &amp;c. His temper in the latter part of his life is repreſented as haughty and ſevere, owing probably to his diſappointments. He left behind him a ſon and two daughters, one of whom was married to the learned Isaac Caſaubon,</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Paul Stephens,</hi> the ſon of Henry, continued his father’s profeſſion at Geneva. He was a man of learning, and wrote tranſtations of ſeveral books, and publiſhed a conſiderable number of the ancient claſſics ; but his editions poſſeſs little of his father’s elegance. He died in 1627, at the age of 60, after felling his types to one Chouet a printer.—His ſon <hi rend="smallcaps">Antony,</hi> the laſt printer of the family, abandoned the Proteſtant religion, and returned to France, the country of his anceſtors. He received letters of naturalization in 1612, and was made printer to the king ; but managing his affairs ill, he was reduced to poverty, and obliged to retire into an hoſpital, where he died in 1674, miſerable and blind, at the age of 8c.</p><p><hi rend="italic">STEPHEN'S Medicine for the Stone,</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Alkali, </hi>n⁰ 17.</p><p>STERCORARIANS, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Stercoranistæ,</hi> formed from st<hi rend="italic">ercus</hi> “ dung,” a name which thoſe of the Romiſh church anciently gave to ſuch as held that the host was liable to digeſtion, and all its conſequences, like other food.</p><p>STERCULIA, in botany : A genus of plants belonging to the claſs of <hi rend="italic">monœcia,</hi> and order of <hi rend="italic">monodelphia; </hi>and in the natural ſyſtem under the 38th order, <hi rend="italic">tricocceæ. </hi>The male calyx is quinquepartite ; there is no corolla, but there are 15 filaments. The female calyx is quinquepartite ; there is no corolla ; the germen is placed on a pillar, and the capſule is quinquelocular, and many- ſeeded. There are three ſpecies, the balanghas, foetida, and platanifolium, all foreign plants.</p><p>STEREOGRAPHIC <hi rend="smallcaps">projection,</hi> is the projection of the circles of the ſphere on the plane of ſome one great circle, the eye being placed in the pole of that circle. See <hi rend="italic smallcaps">Projection</hi><hi rend="italic"> of the Sphere.</hi></p><p>STEREOMETRY, Στεφεομετρια formed of ςερε <hi rend="italic">ς ſolid,</hi> and μετρον<hi rend="italic"> meaſure,</hi> that part of geometry which teaches how to meaſure ſolid bodies, <hi rend="italic">i. e.</hi> to find the ſolidity or ſolid contents of bodies ; as globes, cylinders, cubes, veſſels, ſhips, &amp;c.</p><p>STEREOTOMY, formed from ςερεος and τομη, sect<hi rend="italic">ion,</hi> the art or act of cutting ſolids, or making ſections thereof ; as walls and other membranes in the profiles of architecture.</p><p>STERILITY, barrenneſs, in opposition to fertility. It has been aſſerted by many authors, that all monſters produced by a mixture of different ſpecies of animals, ſuch as mules, are barren ; but this does not hold universally, even with the mule, which is the inſtance moſt generally adduced. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Mule.</hi></p><p>Sterility in women ſometimes happens from a miſcarriage, or violent labour injuring ſome of the genital parts ; but one of the moſt frequent cauſes is the ſuppreſſion of the menstrual flux.—There are other cauſes ariſing from various diſeaſes incident to thoſe parts ; by which the uterus may be unfit to receive or retain the male ſeed ;—from the tubæ fallopianæ being too ſhort, or having loſt their erective power ; in either of which caſes no conception can take place ;—from univerſal debility and relaxation ; or a local debility of the genital ſyſtem ; by which means, the parts having lost their tone or contractile power, the fernen is thrown off immediately <hi rend="italic">post coitum ;—</hi>from imperforation of the vagina, the uterus, or the <hi rend="italic">tubae,</hi> or from diſeaſed ovas, &amp;c. Hence medical treatment can only’ avail in caſes ariſing from topical or univerſal debility ; in correcting irregularities of the menſtrual flux, or in removing tumors, cicatrices, or conſtrictions of the paſſage, by the art of ſurgery.</p><p>STERIS, in botany : A genus of plants belonging to the claſs of <hi rend="italic">pentandria,</hi> and order of <hi rend="italic">digynia.</hi> The calyx is quinquepartite ; the corolla wheel-ſhaped ; the berry is unilocular, and many ſeeded. There is only one ſpecies, the javana, a foreign plant.</p><p>STERLING, an epithet by which genuine Engliſh money is diſtinguiſhed. It is unneceſſary to mention the various conjectures of antiquaries about the origin and meaning of this appellation@@. The moſt probable opinion ſeems to be this, that ſome artiſts from Germany, who were called <hi rend="italic">Esterlings,</hi> from the ſituation of their country, had been employed in fabricating our</p><p>@@@[mu] Henry's History of Great Britain, vol. iii. p. 541.</p></body></text></TEI>