<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-04-20T21:22:35Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>obtuſe. The teeth are diſpoſed in six rows, compreſſed, ſhort, and triangular, having a notch on each side of their baſes. The eyes are sunk ; the iris is of a copper colour, and the pupil is black and oblong. The fins of the back are almoſt ſquare ; the caudal fin is divided into two lobes, and the lateral line is parallel to the back. The upper part of the body is of a reddiſh aſh- colour, with blackiſh ſpots diſpoſed irregularly. The under part is of a dirty white hue. This ſpecies is found near New Zealand, and is about 2½ feet long.</p><p>2.	<hi rend="italic">Canicula,</hi> greater dog-fiſh, or ſpotted ſhark, is diſtinguiſhed by large noſtrils, which are covered by a lobe and warm-ſhaped flap, or by the poſition of the anal fin, which is at an equal distance from the anus and tail. The body is ſpotted ; the head is ſmall, with a ſhort ſnout ; the eyes are oblong ; the iris whitiſh ; the mouth is large and oblong, armed with three rows of teeth ; the tongue is cartilaginous ; the anus is before the middle of the body ; the first dorſal fin is behind the ventral fins ; the other, which is leſs, is almost oppoſite the anal fin ; the caudal fin is narrow and marginated. This ſpecies is found in almost every sea, is about four feet long, extremely voracious, generally feeding on fifties, and is long lived. The skin, which is ſpotted like a leopard’s, is uſed when dried for various purpoſes.</p><p>3.	<hi rend="italic">Catulus,</hi> ſmaller dog fiſh, has a large head ; the pupil of the eyes is black ; the iris white ; the ſnout is of a bright hue ; the mouth, which is large, is situated between the noſtrils, and is armed with four rows of teeth, ſerrated with three points bent inwards ; thoſe in the middle between the two mandibles are longer than the rest. The tongue is broad and ſmooth ; the ſpiracles are five ; the back is tapering and yellowiſh ; the sides are ſomewhat compreſſed ; the tail longer than the body, and the caudal fin is narrow and marginated ; the anterior anal and dorſal fins are behind the ventral ; the posterior dorſal fin is oppoſite to the anal. It inhabits the Mediterranean, Northern, and Indian Ocean, and is two or three feet long.</p><p>4.	<hi rend="italic">Stellaris,</hi> or greater cat fiſh. The head is marked with points ; the abdominal fins are united and ſharp at the apex ; the dorſal fins extend almost to the tail ; the ſkin is reddiſh, marked with black ſpots of different ſizes, and is of a dirty aſh colour below. It is from two to six feet long ; reſembles the canicula, but distinguiſhed by larger and fewer ſpots, by a ſnout ſomewhat longer, a tail ſomewhat ſhorter, and noſtrils almost ſhut. It brings forth 19 or 20 young at a time. It inhabits the European ſeas, living chiefly on ſhell fiſh, molluscæ, and other ſmall fiſhes. The dorſal fins are equal ; the anterior one being behind the middle of the body, and the posterior one being a little behind the anal.</p><p>5.	<hi rend="italic">Tigrinus,</hi> or tigre, is about 15 feet long; the body is long, of unequal thickneſs, black, interſperſed with white stripes and ſpots, irregularly and tranſverſely.— The head is large ; the mouth low and tranſverſe, the upper jaw having two curls ; the upper lip is thick and prominent ; there are five ſpiracles on each side, the two last being united ſo as to give the appearance only of four ; the mandibles are armed with very ſmall pointed teeth ; the tongue is ſhort and thick ; the eyes ſmall and oblong ; the pupil azure coloured ; the iris black. The abdomen is broad ; the pectoral fins are broad, and rounded at the extremity. The anterior dorſal is oppoſite to the ventral fins, and the posterior dorſal fin to the anal. The tail is compreſſed on both sides, and the fin which terminates it is hollow. The tigrinus is found in the Indian Ocean, and lives chiefly on ſhell fiſh. See Plate CCCCLXXVI. fig. 1.</p><p>7.	<hi rend="italic">Zygaena, marteau,</hi> or balance-fiſh, is frequently six feet long, and weighs 500 lbs. The head is elongated on each side ; the fore part is bent back, and convex both above and below. At the extremities of the elongated part are the eyes, which are large, prominent, and directed downwards ; the iris is of a golden colour ; the mouth is arched, and near the beginning of the trunk. It has a horrible appearance from the teeth, which are arranged in three or four rows, and are broad, pointed, and ſerrated on both sides. The tongue is thick, broad, and like a man’s. The trunk is long and tapering : the fins are ſemicircular on the margin, and black at the baſis ; the ventral fins are ſeparate ; the anal and poſterior dorſal fins are ſmall ; the anterior dorſal fin is large, and near the head ; the caudal is long.— This ſpecies inhabits the Mediterranean Sea and the Indian Ocean. It is one of the moſt voracious of the whole tribe. See fig. 2.</p><p>8.	<hi rend="italic">Vulpes,</hi> or ſea-fox, is moſt remarkable for the great length of its tail, the body being about ſeven feet and the tail six feet long. The head is ſhort and conical ; the eyes are large ; the jaws are armed in a dreadful manner with three rows of triangular, compreſſed, and pointed teeth ; the tongue is blunt ; the lateral line is straight. The anterior dorſal fin is placed about the middle of the back ; the poſterior, which consists of two pointed lobes, is oppoſite to the anal fin ; the ventral fins are very near one another ; the anal is acuminated ; the inferior lobe of the tail is about a foot long ; the upper, which is shaped like a ſcythe, is five times longer. This ſpecies inhabits the Mediterranean, the coast of Scotland and England. It is covered with ſmall ſcales ; its back is aſh-coloured, belly whitiſh. It is extremely voracious. The ancients styled this fiſh αλωπηζ and <hi rend="italic">vulpes,</hi> from its ſuppoſed cunning. They believed, that when it had the misfortune to have taken a bait, it ſwallowed the hook till it got at the cord, which it bit off, and ſo eſcaped.</p><p>9.	<hi rend="italic">Glaucus,</hi> or blue ſhark, is about ſeven feet long. The colour of the back is a fine blue ; the belly a ſilvery white ; the head is flat ; the eyes ſmall and roundiſh ; the teeth are almoſt triangular, elongated, and pointed, but not ſerrated. The anus is very near the tail ; the anterior dorſal fin is situated before the ventral fins, about the middle of the body, and is almoſt triangular ; the poſterior dorſal fin is equal to the anal fin, and is placed nearer the tail ; the pectoral fins are large, long, and marginated ; and the ventral are blue above and white below ; the caudal is blue, divided into two lobes, of which the ſuperior is much longer than the inferior lobe. This ſpecies is frequent in every ſea, and is fierce, but not very destructive in our ſeas.</p><p>10.	The <hi rend="italic">maximus,</hi> balking ſhark, or the ſun-fiſh of the Iriſh. This ſpecies has been long known to the inhabitants of the ſouth and west of Ireland and Scotland, and thoſe of Caernarvonſhire and Angleſea ; but having never been considered in any other than a commercial view, is deſcribed by no Engliſh writer except Mr Pennant ; and, what is worſe, mistaken for and confounded with the luna of Rondeletius, the same</p></body></text></TEI>