<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-04-20T21:23:01Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>borne as a ſignal for the joining together of the ſeveral troops belonging to the ſame body.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Standard,</hi> in commerce, the original of a weight, meaſure, or coin, committed to the keeping oſ a magistrate, or depoſited in ſome public place, to regulate, adjust, and try the weights uſed by particular perſons in traffic. See MONEY.</p><p>STANHOPE (Philip Dormer, earl of Cheſterſield), was born in 1695, and educated in Trinity-hall, Cambridge ; which place he left in 1714, when, by his own account, he was an abſolute pedant. In this character he went abroad, where a familiarity with good company ſoon convinced him he was totally miſtaken in almost all his notions : and an attentive ſtudy of the air, manner, and addreſs of people of faſhion, ſoon poliſhed a man whoſe predominant desire was to pleaſe ; and who, as it afterward appeared, valued exterior accompliſhments beyond any other human acquirement. While Lord Stanhope, he got an early ſeat in parliament ; and in 1722, ſucceeded to his father’s eſtate and titles. In 1728, and in 1745, he was appointed ambaſſador extraordinary and plenipotentiary to Idolland : which high character he ſupported with the greateſt dignity ; ſerving his own country, and gaining the eſteem of the states-general. Upon his return from Holland, he was ſent lord-lieutenant of Ireland ; and during his adminiſtration there, gave general ſatisfaction to all parties. He leſt Dublin in 1746, and in October ſucceeded the earl of Harrington as ſecretary of ſtate, in which post he officiated until February 6th 1748. Being ſeized with a deafneſs in 1752 that incapacitated him for the pleaſures of ſociety, he from that time led a private and retired life, amuſing himſelf with books and his pen ; in particular, he engaged largely as a volunteer in a periodical miscellaneous paper called <hi rend="italic">The World,</hi> in which his contributions have a distinguiſhed degree of excellence. He died in 1773, leaving a character for wit and abilities that had few equals. He diſtinguiſhed himſelf by his eloquence in parliament on many important occaſions ; of which we have a characteristic inſtance, of his own relating. He was an active promoter of the bill for altering the ſtyle ; on which occaſion, as he himſelf writes in one of his letters to his son, he made ſo eloquent a ſpeech in the houſe, that every one was pleaſed, and ſaid he had made the whole very clear to them ; “ when (ſays he), God knows, I had not even attempted it. I could just as ſoon have talked Celtic or Sclavonian to them, as astronomy ; and they would have understood me full as well.” Lord Macclesfield, one of the greateſt mathematicians in Europe, and who had a principal hand in framing the bill, ſpoke afterwards, with all the clearneſs that a thorough knowledge of the ſubject could dictate ; but not having a flow of words equal to Lord Cheſterfield, the latter gained the applauſe from the former, to the equal credit of the speaker and the auditors. The high character Lord Cheſterſield ſupported during life, received no ſmall injury ſoon after his death, from a fuller diſplay of it by his own hand. He left no iſſue by his lady, but had a natural ſon, Philip Stanhope, Eſq; whoſe education was tor many years a cloſe object of his attention, and who was afterward envoy extraordinary at the court of Dreſden, but died before him. When Lord Chesterfield died, Mr Stanhope’s widow publiſhed a courſe of letters, written by the father to the ſon, filled with inſtructions ſuitable to the different gradations of the young man’s life to whom they were addreſſed. Theſe letters contain many fine obſervatious on mankind, and rules of conduct : but it is obſervable that he lays a greater streſs on exterior accomplishments and addreſs, than on intellectual qualifications and ſincerity ; and allows greater latitude to faſhionable pleaſures than good morals will juſtify, eſpecally in paternal inſtructions. Hence it is that a celebrated writer @@§, and of manners ſomewhat different from thoſe of the polite earl of Chesterfield, is ſaid to have obſerved of theſe letters that “ they inculcate only the morals of a whore, with the manners of a dancing-master.”</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Stanhope</hi> (Dr George), an eminent divine, was born at Hertiſhorn in Derbyſhire, in the year 1660. His father was rector of that place, vicar of St Margaret’s church in Leiceſter, and chaplain to the earls of Cheſterſield and Clare. His grandfather Dr George Stanhope was chaplain to James I. and Charles I. ; had the chancellorſhip of York, where he was alſo a canon reſidentiary, held a prebend, and was rector of Weldrake in that county. He was for his loyalty driven from his home with eleven children ; and died in 1644. Our author was ſent to ſchool, first at Uppingham in Rutland, then at Leiceſter ; afterwards removed to Eaton ; and thence choſen to King’s college in Cambridge, in the place of W. Cleaver. He took the degree of B. A. in 1681 ; Μ. A. 1658 ; was elected one of the ſyndics for the university of Cambridge, in the busineſs of Alban Francis, 1687 ; miniſter of Quoi near Cambridge, and vice-proctor, 1688 ; was that year preferred to the rectory of Tring in Hertfordſhire, which after ſome time he quitted. He was in 1689 preſented to the vicarage of Lewiſham in Kent by Lord Dartmouth, to whom he had been chaplain, and tutor to his ſon. He was alſo appointed chaplain to King William and Queen Mary, and continued to enjoy that honour under Queen Anne. He commenced D. D. July 5th 1697, performing all the offices required to that degree publicly and with great applauſe. He was made vicar of Deptford in 1703 ; ſucceeded Dr Hooper as dean oſ Canterbury the ſame year ; and was thrice choſen prolocutor of the lower houſe of convocation. His uncommon diligence and induſtry, aſſiſted by his excellent parts, enriched him with a large stock of polite, ſolid, and uſeful learning. His diſcourſes from the pulpit were equally pleaſing and profitable ; a beautiful intermixture of the cleareſt reasoning with the purest diction, attended with all the graces of a just elocution. The good Christian, the ſolid divine, and the fine gentleman, in him were happily united. His converſation was polite and delicate, grave without preciſeneſs, facetious without levity. His piety was real and rational, his charity great and univerſal, fruitful in acts of mercy, and in all good works. He died March 18th 1728, aged 68 years ; and was buried in the chancel of the church at Lewiſham. The dean was twice married : I. to Olivia Cotton, by whom he had one ſon and four daughters. His second lady, who was sister to Sir Charles Wager, ſurvived him, dying October 1st 1730, aged about 54. One of the dean’s daughters was married to a ſon of biſhop Burnet. Biſhop Moore of Ely died the day before Queen Anne ; who, it has been ſaid, deſigned our dean for that</p><p>@@@[m]§ Dr. Johnson. </p></body></text></TEI>