<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-04-20T21:22:59Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>hexaphyllous ; the corolla consiſts of four or of six petals : the receptacle is fleſhy, and ſomewhat ſquare ſhaped ; the filaments about 30. In the hermaphrodite flower the st<hi rend="italic">ylus</hi> is ſhort, thick, and erect ; the fruit is a berry of a globular ſhape, unilocular, and crowned with the st<hi rend="italic">ylus</hi> and st<hi rend="italic">igma :</hi> they contain three oblong jointed triangular ſeeds. Of this there is only one ſpecies, viz. the <hi rend="italic">Cambogioides,</hi> a native of the East Indies and of the warmer parts of America. From this plant is obtained the gutta cambogia, or gum gamboge of the ſhops. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Gamboge.</hi></p><p>Till very lately botaniſts were at a loſs for the true nature of the plant which yields this gum. Koenig, a native of Ireland, and an excellent botanist, travelled over a great part of India, and collected a great number of new plants, and among the rest the stalagmitis. Theſe he bequeathed to Sir Joſeph Banks preſident of the Royal Society.</p><p>STALE, among ſportſmen, a living fowl put in a place to allure ad bring others where they may be taken. For want of theſe, a bird shot, his entrails taken out, and dried in an oven in his feathers, with a stick thrust through to keep it in a convenient poſture, may ſerve as well as a live one.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Stale</hi> is alſo a name for the urine of cattle.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Animated</hi> STALK. This remarkable animal was found by Mr Ives at Cuddalore : and he mentions ſeveral kinds of it ; ſome appearing like dry straws tied together, others like graſs ; ſome have bodies much larger than others, with the addition of two ſcaly imperfect wings ; their neck is no bigger than a pin, but twice as long as their bodies ; their heads are like thoſe of an hare and their eyes vertical and very briſk. They live upon flies, and catch theſe infects very dexterouſly with the two fore-feet, which they keep doubled up in three parts cloſe to their head, and dart out very quick on the approach of their prey ; and when they have caught it, they eat it very voraciouſly, holding it in the ſame manner as a ſquirrel does its food. On the outer joints of the fore-feet are ſeveral very sharp hooks for the easier catching and holding of their prey ; while, with the other feet, which are four in number, they take hold of trees or any other thing, the better to ſurpriſe whatever they lie in wait for. They drink like a horſe, putting their mouths into the water. Their excrements, which are very white, are almost as large as the body of the animal, and as the natives ſay, dangerous to the eyes.</p><p>STALLION, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Stone-horse,</hi> in the manege, an horſe deſigned for the covering of mares, in order to propagate the ſpecies. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Equus.</hi></p><p>STAMFORD, an ancient town of Lincolnshire in England ; ſeated on the river Welland, on the edge of Northamptonſhire. It is a large handſome place, containing six pariſh-churches, ſeveral good streets, and fine buildings. It had formerly a college, the students of which removed to Brazen-Noſe college in Oxford. It has no considerable manufactories, but deals chiefly in malt. W. Long. 0. 31. N. Lat. 52. 42.</p><p>STAMINA, in botany, are thoſe upright filaments which, on opening a flower, we find within the corolla ſurrounding the pistillum. According to Linnæus, they are the male organs of generation, whoſe office it is to prepare the pollen. Each stamen consists of two distinct parts, viz. the <hi rend="smallcaps">filamentum</hi> and the AN<hi rend="smallcaps">thera.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Stamina,</hi> in the animal body, are defined to be thoſe simple original parts which existed firſt in the embryo or even in the feed ; and by whoſe diſtinction, augmentation, and accretion by additional juices, the animal body at its utmost bulk is ſuppoſed to be formed.</p><p>ST<hi rend="smallcaps">AMP-duties,</hi> a branch of the perpetual revenue. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Revenue.</hi></p><p>In Great Britain there is a tax impoſed upon all parchment and paper, whereon any legal proceedings or private inſtruments of almost any nature whatſoever are written ; and alſo upon licences for retailing wines, of all denominations ; upon all almanacs, newspapers, advertiſements, cards, dice, &amp;c. Theſe impoſts are very various ; being higher or lower, not ſo much according to the value of the property transferred, as according to the nature of the deed.@@ The highest do not exceed six pounds upon every sheet of paper or ſkin of parchment ; and theſe high duties fall chiefly upon grants from the crown, and upon certain law proceedings, without any regard to the value of the ſubject. There are in Great Britain no duties on the registration of deeds or writings, except the fees of the officers who keep the regiſter ; and theſe are ſeldom more than a reaſonable recompenſe for their labour. The crown derives no revenue from them.</p><p>The ſtamp-duties constitute a tax which, though in ſome inſtances it may be heavily felt, by greatly increaſing the expence of all mercantile as well as legal proceedings, yet (if moderately impoſed) is of ſervice to the public in general, by authenticating inſtruments, and rendering it much more difficult than formerly to forge deeds of any standing ; ſince, as the officers of this branch of the revenue vary their stamps frequently, by marks perceptible to none but themſelves, a man that would forge a deed of King William’s time, muſt know and be able to counterfeit the stamp of that date alſo. In France and ſome other countries the duty is laid on the contract itſelf, not on the instrument in which it is contained; as, with us too in England (beſides the stamps on the indentures), a tax is laid, by statute 8 Ann. c. 9. on every apprentice-fee; of 6d in the pound if it be 50l. or under, and is in the pound if a greater ſum : but this tends to draw the ſubject into a thouſand nice disquisitions and diſputes concerning the nature of his contract, and whether taxable or not ; in which the farmers of the tevenue are ſure to have the advantage. Our general method anſwers the purpoſes of the state as well, and conſults the ease of the ſubject much better. The first inſtitution of the ſtamp- duties was by statute 5 and 6 W. and M. c. 21. and they have since, in many inſtances, been increaſed to five times their original amount.</p><p>STANCHION, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Stanchions,</hi> a fort of ſmall pillars of wood or iron uſed tor various purpoſes in a ship ; as to ſupport the decks, the quarter-rails, the nettings, the awnings, &amp;c. The first of theſe are two ranges of ſmall columns fixed under the beams, throughout the ſhip’s length between decks ; one range being on the starboard and the other on the larboard side of the hatchways. They are chiefly intended to ſupport the weight of the artillery.</p><p>STAND, in commerce, a weight from two hundred and an half to three hundred of pitch.</p><p>STANDARD, in war, a fort of banner or flag,</p><p>@@@[mu] Smith's Wealth of Nations, vol. iii.</p></body></text></TEI>