<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-04-20T21:23:12Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>copies of all its proceſs, may alſo be found in 18 Rym. Foed. 192, &amp;c.</p><p><hi rend="italic">STAR-Board,</hi> the right side of the ſhip when the eye of the ſpectator is directed forward.</p><p><hi rend="italic">STAR-Fish.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Asterias.</hi></p><p>STAR-shot, a gelatinous ſubſtance frequently found in fields, and ſuppoſed by the vulgar to have been produced from the meteor called a <hi rend="italic">falling star :</hi> but, in reality, is the half-digeſted food of herons, ſea-mews, and the like birds ; for theſe birds have been found, when newly ſhot, to diſgorge a ſubſtance of the ſame kind.</p><p><hi rend="italic">STAR-Stone,</hi> in natural hiſtory, a name given to certain extraneous foſſil ſtones, in form of ſhort, and commonly ſomewhat crooked, columns compoſed of ſeveral joints, each reſembling the figure of a radiated ſtar, with a greater or ſmaller number of rays in the different ſpecies : they are uſually found of about an inch in length, and of the thickneſs of a gooſe-quill. Some of them have five angles or rays, and others only four ; and in ſome the angles are equidiſtant, while in others they are irregularly ſo : in ſome alſo they are ſhort and blunt, while in others they are long, narrow, and pointed ; and ſome have their angles very ſhort and obtuſe. The ſeveral joints in the ſame ſpecimen are uſually all of the ſame thickneſs ; this, however, is not always the caſe : but in ſome they are larger at one end, and in others at the middle, than in any other part of the body ; and ſome ſpecies have one of the rays bifid, ſo as to emulate the appearance of a six-rayed kind.</p><p><hi rend="italic">STAR-Thistle,</hi> in botany. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Centaurea.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">STAR-Wort,</hi> in botany. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Aster.</hi></p><p>STARCH, a fecula or ſediment, found at the bottom of veſſels wherein wheat has been ſteeped in water, of which fecula, after ſeparating the bran from it, by paſſing it through fieves, they form a kind of loaves, which being dried in the fun or an oven, is afterwards cut into little pieces, and ſo sold. The best ſtarch is white, ſoft, and friable, and eaſily broken into powder. Such as require fine ſtarch, do not content themſelves, like the ſtarchmen, with refuſe wheat, but uſe the fineſt grain. The proceſs is as follows : The grain, being well cleaned, is put to ferment in veſſels full of water, which they expoſe to the sun while in its greateſt heat ; changing the water twice a-day, for the ſpace of eight or twelve days, according to the ſeaſon. When the grain burſts eaſily under the finger, they judge it ſufficiently fermented. The fermentation perfected, and the grain thus ſoftened, it is put, handful by handful, into a canvas-bag, to ſeparate the flour from the huſks ; which is done by rubbing and beating it on a plank laid acroſs the mouth of an empty veſſel that is to receive the flour.</p><p>As the veſſels are filled with this liquid flour, there is ſeen ſwimming at top a reddiſh water, which is to be carefully ſcummed off from time to time, and clean water is to be put in its place, which, after ſtirring the whole together, is alſo to be ſtrained through a cloth or ſieve, and what is left behind put into the veſſel with new water, and expoſed to the sun for ſome time. As the ſediment thickens at the bottom, they drain off the water four or five times, by inclining the veſſel, but without paſſing it through the sieve. What remains at bottom is the ſtarch, which they cut in pieces to get out, and leave it to dry in the ſun. When dry, it is laid up for uſe.</p><p>STARK (Dr William), known to the public by a volume containing <hi rend="italic">Clinical and Anatomical Obſervations, </hi>with ſome curious <hi rend="italic">Experiments on Diet,</hi> was born at Mancheſter in the month of July 1740; but the family from which he ſprang was Scotch, and reſpectable for its antiquity. His grandfather John Stark of Killermont was a covenanter ; and having appeared in arms againſt his ſovereign at the battle of Bothwell bridge in the year 1679, became obnoxious to the government, and to conceal himſelf, withdrew into Ireland. There is reason to believe that he had not imbibed either the extravagant zeal or the ſavage manners of the political and religious party to which he adhered ; for after reſiding a few years in the country which he had choſen for the ſcene of his baniſhment, he married Elizabeth daughter of Thomas Stewart Eſq; of Balydrene in the north of Ireland ; who, being deſcended of the noble family of Galloway, would not probably have matched his daughter to ſuch an exile as a ruthleſs fanatic of the laſt century. By this lady Mr Stark had ſeveral children ; and his ſecond ſon Thomas, who settled at Mancheſter as a wholeſale linen-draper, and married Margaret Stirling, daughter of William Stirling, Eſq; of Northwoodſide, in the neighbourhood of Glaſgow, was the father of the ſubject of this article. Another of his ſons, the reverend John Stark, was miniſter of Lecropt in Perthshire ; and it was under the care of this gentleman that our author received the rudiments of his education, which, when we conſider the character of the maſter, and reflect on the relation between him and his pupil, we may preſume was calculated to ſtore the mind of Dr Stark with thoſe virtuous principles which influenced his conduct through life.</p><p>From Lecropt young Stark was sent to the univerſity of Glaſgow, where, under the tuition of the Doctors Smith and Black, with other eminent maſters, he learned the rudiments of ſcience, and acquired that mathematical accuracy, that logical preciſion, and that contempt of hypotheſes, with which he proſecuted all his future ſtudies. Having choſen phyſic for his profeſſion, he removed from the univerſity of Glaſgow to that of Edinburgh, where he was ſoon diſtinguiſhed, and honoured with the friendſhip of the late Dr Cullen ; a man who was not more eminently conſpicuous for the superiority of his own genius, than quick-ſighted in perceiving, and liberal in encouraging, genius in his pupils. Having finiſhed his ſtudies at Edinburgh, though he took there no degree, Mr Stark, in the year 1765, went to London, and devoted himſelf entirely to the ſtudy of phyſic and the elements of ſurgery ; and looking upon anatomy as one of the principal pillars of both theſe arts, he endeavoured to complete with Dr Hunter what he had begun with Dr Monro ; and under theſe two eminent profeſſors he appears to have acquired a high degree of anatomical knowledge. He likewiſe entered himſelf about this time a pupil at St George’s hoſpital ; for being diſguſted, as he often confeſſed, with the inaccuracy or want of candour obſervable in the generality of practical writers, he determined to obtain an acquaintance with diſeaſes at a better ſchool and from an abler maſter ; and to have from his own experience a ſtandard, by which he might judge of the ex-</p></body></text></TEI>