<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-04-20T21:21:07Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>tice that he ſhould ſoon die and that the ſhip ſhould be taken in the mouth of the Channel by the French. Next morning the captain called his firſt mate, told him his dream, which he believed was prophetic, and delivered his papers, that he might take proper care of them aſter his deceaſe. Every thing happened exactly as the dream had foretold ; the captain died, and the veſſel was taken by a French man of war in the mouth of the Channel. This dream, wonderful as it appears, is eaſily explained. In the voyage out to India, nothing was more natural than that the captain ſhould ſometimes be thinking that amidſt the various chances of war, the port to which he was bound might be taken ; perhaps it was a place of conſequence, which the French might be eager to poſſeſs. The captain being accuſtomed to revolve theſe thoughts in the day-times they would naturally return at night ; the regret which he felt for the loſs of a faithful ſervant might mingle with his apprehenſions, and thus produce the dream. Perhaps the advice was ſuch as John would have given had he been alive. It is equally eaſy to explain the cauſe of the dream in the paſſage home. The captain, we are told, was very ill, and thought himſelf dying, at the very time he had the ſecond dream, and therefore did not expect to reach England. This part of the dream, then, was only his own thoughts, delivered by his ſervant. As to the other part, that his ſhip ſhould be taken in the mouth of the Channel, it may be thought unaccountable how the very place ſhould be foreſeen. But we muſt recollect, that the mouth of the Channel, being over againſt the coaſt of France, was by far the moſt dangerous place in the whole paſſage ; and that, therefore, the captain had more reaſon to be afraid of losing his ſhip there than in any other place. The uſe which we mean to make of this ſtory is this : Had the captain been a man of a Weak mind, he would certainly have considered the dream as a reality, and believed, that inſtead of having dreamed of the things on which his imagination had dwelled, he had actually ſeen his ſervant return from the dead, and heard him deliver the meſſage. But, on the other hand, the captain, though he believed the dream was prophetic, mentioned it without any ſigns of fear ; and no man of courage and reflection ever ſees an apparition. This fight is reſerved for the weak, the timid, and ſuperſtitious. Of this many inſtances might be mentioned.</p><p>3.	Spectres are ſometimes alſo occasioned by opium. Gaſſendi the philoſopher found a number of people going to put a man to death for having intercourſe with the devil ; a crime which the poor wretch readily acknowledged. Gaſſendi begged of the people that they would permit him firſt to examine the wizard before putting him to death. They did ſo ; and Gaſſendi, upon examination, found that the man firmly believed himſelf guilty of this impoſſible crime. He even offered to Gaſſendi to introduce him to the devil. The philoſopher agreed ; and when midnight came, the man gave him a pill, which he ſaid it was neceſſary to ſwallow before ſetting off. Gaſſendi took the pill, but gave it to his dog. The man having ſwallowed his, fell into a profound ſleep ; during which he ſeemed much agitated by dreams. The dog was affected in a ſimilar manner. When the man awoke, he congratulated Gaſſendi on the favourable reception he had met with from his fable highneſs. It was with difficulty Gaſſendi convinced him that the whole was a dream, the effect of ſoporific medicines, and that he had never ſtirred from one ſpot during the whole night.</p><p>4.	That diſeaſes, eſpecially the night mare, the hypochondria, hyſteric paſſion, and madneſs, are another source of ſpcteres, we have the ſtrongeſt reaſon to affirm, Perſons ſubject to the night-mare often imagine that they ſee ſpectres. This is ſtill more the cafe with hypochondriac and hyſteric perſons, and thoſe who are in any degree deranged in their intellects. A fact which fell within the obſervation of the writer of this article will both prove and illuſtrate this aſſertion. In a village in one of the midland counties of Scotland, lived a widow diſtinguiſhed among her neighbours for decency of manners, integrity, and reſpect for religion. She affirmed, that for ſeveral nights together ſhe had heard a ſupernatural voice exclaiming aloud, <hi rend="italic">Murder ! murder!</hi> This was immediately reported through the neighbourhood ; all were alarmed, and looked around them with ſolicitude for the detection of the murder which they ſuppoſed to have been committed ; and it was not long till a diſcovery ſeemed actually to be made. It was reported, that a gentleman, who had relations at no great diſtance, and had been residing in the West Indies, had lately arrived with a considerable fortune ; that he had lodged in an inn about three miles off ; and that he had afterwards been ſeen entering a houſe in the village where the widow lived, from which he had never returned. It was next affirmed, that a tradeſman paſſing the church-yard about twelve at midnight had ſeen four men carry a dead corpſe into that cemetery. Theſe three facts being joined together ſeemed perfectly to agree and to confirm one another, and all believed ſome horrible murder had been committed. The relations of the gentleman thought they were called upon to make inquiry into the truth of theſe allegations : they accordingly came firſt to the church-yard, where, in company with the ſexton, they examined all the graves with great care, in order to diſcover whether any of them had been lately dug, or had the appearance of containing more than one coffin. But this ſearch was to no purpoſe, for no alteration had been made upon the graves. It was next reported that the murdered man had been buried in a plantation about a mile distant from the village. As the alarm was now very general, a number of the inhabitants propoſed of their own accord to explore it. They accordingly ſpread themſelves over the wood, and ſearched it with care, but no grave nor new dug earth was found. The writer of this article, who was then a boy at ſchool, was along with them. The matter did not rest here : The perſon who was ſaid to have ſeen four men carry a dead corpſe into the church-yard at midnight was ſummoned to appear before a meeting of the juſtices of the peace. Upon examination he denied any knowledge of the affair, but referred the court to another perſon from whom he had received his information. This perſon was examined, and the reſult was the ſame as the former. In ſhort, one perſon had heard it from another, who had received it from a third, who had heard it from a fourth ; but it had received a little embellishment from every perſon who</p></body></text></TEI>