<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-04-20T21:22:19Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>rocks on the top of the Highland mountains, as on Ben-Lomond, and in the Iſle of Sky, and elſewhere. This differs little from the preceding, and perhaps is no more than a variety. The filaments are about an inch high. The leaves oval-acute, not ſo lanceolate and bearded as the other. The apophyſis, and the anthera at the top of it, form together nearly an oval figure, not unlike an acorn in its cup, the apophyſis being tranlverſely ſemi-oval, and of a blood-red colour, the anthera ſhort and conical. The calyptra is the ſame as that of the other. The operculum is ſhort and obtuse, and the rim of the anthera has eight large horizontal cilia. The anthera of the other is alſo ciliated, but not ſo diſtinctly. It is an elegant moſs, and very diſtinguiſhable on account of its orange-coloured filaments and dark-red capſules.</p><p>SPLEEN, in anatomy. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Anatomy,</hi> n<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> 99. <hi rend="italic">SPLEEN-Wort.</hi> See ASPLENIUM.</p><p>SPLENETIC, a perſon afflicted with an obſtruction of the ſpleen.</p><p>SPLENT, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Splint,</hi> among farriers, a callous insensible excreſcence, breeding on the ſhank-bone of horses. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Farriery,</hi> Sect. xxxi.</p><p>SPLICING, in the ſea-language, is the untwiſting the ends of two cables or ropes, and working the ſeveral ſtrands into one another by a fidd, ſo that they become as ſtrong as if they were but one rope.</p><p>SPOILS, whatever is taken from the enemy in time of war. Among the ancient Greeks, the ſpoils were divided among the whole army ; only the general’s ſhare was largeſt : but among the Romans, the ſpoils belonged to the republic.</p><p>SPOLETTO, a duchy of Italy, bounded on the north by the Marquiſate of Ancona and duchy of Urbino, on the east by Farther Abruzzo, on the ſouth by Sabina and the patrimony of St Peter, and on the west by Orvietano and Perugino. It is about 55 miles in length and 40 in breadth. It was anciently a part of Umbria, and now belongs to the Pope.—The name of the capital city is alſo <hi rend="italic">Spοlettο.</hi> It was formerly a large place, but in 1703 was ruined by an earthquake ; from whence it has never recovered itſelf.</p><p>SPOLIATION, in eccleſiaſtical law, is an injury done by one clerk or incumbent to another, in taking the fruits of his benefice without any right thereunto, but under a pretended title. It is remedied by a decree to account for the profits ſo taken. This injury, when the jus <hi rend="italic">patronatus,</hi> or right of advowſon, doth not come in debate, is cognizable in the ſpiritual court ; as if a patron firſt preſents A to a benefice, who is inſtituted and inducted thereto ; and then, upon pretence of a vacancy, the ſame patron preſents B to the same living, and he alſo obtains inſtitution and induction. Now if A diſputes the fact of the vacancy, then that clerk who is kept out of the profits of the living, whichever it be, may ſue the other in the ſpiritual court for ſpoliation, or taking the profits of his benefice. And it ſhall there be tried, whether the living were or were not vacant ; upon which the validity of the second clerk’s pretentions muſt depend. But if the right of patronage comes at all into diſpute, as if one patron preſented A, and another patron preſented B, there the eccleſiaſtical court hath no cognizance, provided the tithes ſued for amount to a fourth part of the value of the living, but may be prohibited at the inſtance of the patron by the king’s writ of <hi rend="italic">indicavit,</hi> So alio iſ a clerk, without any colour of title, ejects another from his parſonage, this injury muſt be redreſſed in the temporal courts : for it depends upon no queſtion determinable by the ſpiritual law (as plurality of benefices or no plurality, vacancy or no vacancy), but is merely a civil injury.</p><p>SPONDEE, in ancient poetry, a foot conſiſting of two long ſyllables, as <hi rend="italic">omnes.</hi></p><p>SPONDIAS, <hi rend="smallcaps">Brasilian</hi> or <hi rend="smallcaps">Jamaica Plum,</hi> in botany ; a genus of plants belonging to the claſs of <hi rend="italic">decandria,</hi> and order of p<hi rend="italic">entagynia.</hi> The calyx is quinquedentate. The corolla pentapetalous. The fruit contains a quinquelocular kernel. There are only two ſpecies, the mombin and myrobalanus, which appear ſo much confounded in the deſcriptions of different botaniſts, that we do not venture to preſent them to our readers.</p><p>SPONGIA, <hi rend="smallcaps">Sponge,</hi> in natural hiſtory ; a genus of animals belonging to the claſs of	and order of</p><p><hi rend="italic">voophyta.</hi> It is fixed, flexible, and very torpid, growing in a variety of forms, compoſed either of reticulated fibres, or maſſes of ſmall ſpines interwoven together, and clothed with a living gelatinous fleſh, full of ſmall mouths or holes on its ſurface, by which it ſucks in and throws out the water. Fifty ſpecies have already been diſcovered, of which 10 belong to the Britiſh coaſts.</p><p>1.	<hi rend="italic">Oculata,</hi> or branched ſponge, is delicately ſoft and very much branched ; the branches are a little compreſſed, grow erect, and often united together. They have rows of cells on each margin, that project a little. This ſpecies is of a pale yellow colour, from five to ten inches high. The fibres are reticulated, and the fleſh or gelatinous part is ſo tender, that when it is taken out of the water it ſoon dries away. It is very common round the ſea-coaſt of Britain and Ireland. This deſcription will be better underſtood by Plate <hi rend="smallcaps">cccclxxv. </hi>fig. I. At <hi rend="italic">b, b,</hi> along the edges and on the ſurface of the branches, are rows of ſmall papillary holes, through which the animal receives its nouriſhment.</p><p>2.	<hi rend="italic">Cristata,</hi> or cock’s comb ſponge, is flat, erect, and ſoft, growing in the ſhape of cock’s combs, with rows of little holes along the tops, which project a little. It abounds on the rocks to the eaſtward of Hastings in Suſſex, where it may be ſeen at low-water. It is commonly about three inches long, and two inches high, and of a pale yellowiſh colour. When put into a glaſs vessel of ſea-water, it has been obſerved to ſuck in and ſquirt out the water through little mouths along the tops, giving evident signs of life.</p><p>3.	<hi rend="italic">Stupοsa,</hi> tow-ſponge, or downy branched ſponge, is ſoft like tow, with round branches, and covered with fine pointed hairs. It is of a pale yellow colour, and about three inches high. It is frequently thrown on the ſhore at Haſtings in Suſſex. Fig. 2. repreſents this ſponge ; but it is ſo cloſely covered with a fine down, that the numerous ſmall holes in its ſurface are not diſcernible.</p><p>4.	<hi rend="italic">Dichοtoma,</hi> dichotomous or forked ſponge, is ſtiff, branched, with round, upright, elaſtic branches, covered with minute hairs. It is found on the coaſt of Norway, and alſo, according to Berkenhout, on the Corniſh and Yorkſhire coaſts. It is of a pale yellow colour, and full of very minute pores, guarded by minute ſpines.</p></body></text></TEI>