<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-04-20T21:26:26Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>to the fortifications in the reign of queen Anne. Formerly they reached no farther than the old gate, upon which the flag-ſtaff now stands : but in that reign they were considerably enlarged upon the side towards the town ; and barracks, which are bomb proof, with ſeveral other conveniences for a ſiege, were erected.</p><p>Upon the ſouth side of the caſtle lies a park incloſed with a ſtone-wall, called the <hi rend="italic">king's park,</hi> and near to the foot of the rock on which the caſtle ſtands, lay the royal gardens; veſtiges of the walks and parterres, with a few ſtumps of fruit-trees, are ſtill viſible ; but by long neglect, and the natural wetneſs of the soil, the place is now little better than a marſh. In the gardens is a mount of earth in form of a table, with benches of earth around it, where, according to tradition, the court sometimes held <hi rend="italic">fetes-champetres.</hi> In the caſtle- hill is an hollow, comprehending about an acre of ground, and having all the appearance of an artificial work, which was uſed for jouſts, tournaments, and other feats of chivalry.</p><p>Northward of the caſtle lies the Govan, or perhaps more properly the <hi rend="italic">Gowling</hi> hill @@<hi rend="smallcaps">(a) ; </hi>in the middle of which is a ſmall mount called <hi rend="italic">Hurly Haaky,</hi> upon which duke Murdoch and his two sons were executed for treaſonable practices in the reign of James I.</p><p>The proſpect from the caſtle is moſt delightful, as well as extenſive, being greatly beautified, eſpecially upon the eaſt, by the windings of the Forth; which are ſo many, that though the diſtance by land from Stirling to Alloa is, in a ſtraight line, not quite six miles, it is ſaid to be 24 by water. As this river generally runs upon plain ground, it rolls its ſtream in so slow and silent a manner, that what Silius Italicus faith of the Ticinus is applicable to it, if, inſtead of <hi rend="italic">lucenti</hi> in that poet, we ſhould for once read <hi rend="italic">lutoſo ;</hi> for the claybanks, together with the tide, which flows above Stirling, render the Forth perpetually muddy :</p><p><hi rend="italic">Vix credas labi, ripis tam mitis opacis</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Somniferam ducit lutoso gurgite lympham.</hi></p><p>The lordſhip and caſtle of Stirling were a part of the uſual dowry of the queens of Scotland, at leaſt after the family of Stuart came to the throne, in which they were inveſted at their marriage.</p><p>Robert lord Erſkine was appointed governor of the caſtle by king David II. and the office continued in that family till 1715.</p><p>This fortreſs hath been the ſcene of many tranſactions. Being by <hi rend="italic">its</hi> ſituation considered as a key to the northern parts of the kingdom, the poſſeſſion of it hath been always eſteemed of great importance to thoſe who fought to be maſters of Scotland. It was undoubtedly a place of ſtrength when the art of war by ordnance was in its infancy; but though it reſiſted the utmoſt efforts of the rebels in 1746, it could not now hold out three days if beſieged by an army of a few thouſand men conducted by an engineer of knowledge and integrity.</p><p>STIRLINGSHIRE, a county of Scotland, of which Stirling is the capital. It extends 20 miles in length and 12 in breadth ; being bounded on the west by part of Lennox and Clydeſdale ; on the eaſt, by Clackmannanſhire, the river Forth, and part of Lothian ; on the ſouth-eaſt, by Lothian ; and on the north, by Monteith. The face of the country is open and agreeable, diverſified by hill and dale, well watered with ſtreams and rivers ; the principal of which is the Forth, riſing in the neighbourhood of a high mountain called <hi rend="italic">Ben-Lomond,</hi> and, running eaſtward, forms the frith of Edinburgh. The southern part is hilly, affording plenty of game, and paſturage for ſheep, horſes, and black cattle. The eaſtern part is fertile, producing plentiful harvests of corn, and great abundance of coal. Lead-ore is found in different parts of the ſhire ; and the rivers abound with pike, trout, and falmon.</p><p>STIRRUP, in the manege, a reſt or ſupport for the horſeman’s foot, for enabling him to mount and for keeping him firm in his ſeat.</p><p>Stirrups were unknown to the ancients. The want of them in getting upon horſeback was ſupplied by agility or art. Some horſes were taught to ſtoop to take their riders up; but the riders often leapt up by the help of their spears, or were aſſiſted by their ſlaves, or made uſe of ladders for the purpoſe. Gracchus filled the highways with ſtones, which were intended to anſwer the ſame end. The ſame was alſo required of the ſurveyors of the roads in Greece as part of their duty.</p><p>Menage obſerves, that St Jerome is the firſt author who mentions them. But the passage alluded to is not to be found in his epiſtles ; and if it were there, it would prove nothing, becauſe St Jerome lived at a time when ſtirrups are ſuppoſed to have been invented, and after the uſe of ſaddles. Montfaucon denies the authenticity of this passage ; and, in order to account for the ignorance of the ancients with regard to an inſtrument ſo uſeful and ſo eaſy of invention,@@ he obſerves, that while cloths and houſings only were laid upon the horſes backs, on which the riders were to sit, ſtirrups could not have been uſed, becauſe they could not have been faſtened with the ſame ſecurity as upon a ſaddle. But it is more probable, that in this inſtance, as in many others, the progreſs of human genius and invention is uncertain and flow, depending frequently upon accidental cauſes.</p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Stirrup</hi><hi rend="italic"> of a Ship,</hi> a piece of timber put upon a ſhip’s keel, when ſome of her keel happens to be beaten off, and they cannot come conveniently to put or fit in a new piece ; then they patch in a piece of timber, and bind it on with an iron, which goes under the ſhip’s keel, and comes up on each side of the ſhip, where it is nailed ſtrongly with ſpikes ; and this they call a ſtirrup.</p><p>STOBÆUS (John), a laborious Greek writer, who lived at the end of the fourth century, compoſed many works, of which there are only his Collections remaining, and even theſe are not as he compoſed them; many things being inſerted by later authors. This work contains many important ſentiments collected from the ancient writers, poets, and philoſophers.</p><p>STOCK, in gardening, &amp;c. the ſtem or trunk of a tree. What ſtock is moſt proper for each kind of fruit, ought as well to be conſidered and known, as what soil</p><p>@@@[mu] Berenger's History and Art of Horsemanship, vol. i. p 65.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">@@@(a)</hi> So called from the wailings and lamentations (in Scotch <hi rend="italic">gowlings)</hi> that were made for Duke Murdoch.</p></body></text></TEI>