<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-04-20T21:27:25Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><table><row><cell>Numb.</cell><cell>Brought over</cell><cell><p>Feet.</p><p>138</p></cell><cell><p>Inch.</p><p>0</p></cell></row><row><cell>18 <hi rend="smallcaps">Bind</hi></cell><cell>» - -</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>19 <hi rend="smallcaps">Stone</hi></cell><cell>-</cell><cell>20</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>20 <hi rend="smallcaps">Bind</hi></cell><cell/><cell>16</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>21 <hi rend="smallcaps">Coal</hi></cell><cell/><cell>7</cell><cell>4</cell></row><row><cell/><cell/><cell>184</cell><cell>4</cell></row></table><table><row><cell cols="5"><hi rend="italic">A </hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps">TaBle</hi><hi rend="italic"> of the </hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Strata</hi><hi rend="italic"> at </hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps">West HalIam.</hi></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Numb.</cell><cell/><cell>Feet.</cell><cell>Inch.</cell></row><row><cell>I</cell><cell><hi rend="smallcaps">Clay</hi></cell><cell>-</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>2</cell><cell><hi rend="smallcaps">Bind</hi></cell><cell>-</cell><cell>48</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>3</cell><cell><hi rend="smallcaps">Smutt</hi></cell><cell>- ■</cell><cell>I</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>4</cell><cell>C<hi rend="smallcaps">lunCh, </hi><hi rend="italic">or indurated clay</hi></cell><cell>-</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>5</cell><cell><hi rend="smallcaps">Bind</hi></cell><cell>-</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>6</cell><cell><hi rend="smallcaps">Stone</hi></cell><cell>-</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>3</cell></row><row><cell>7</cell><cell><hi rend="smallcaps">Bind</hi></cell><cell>-</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>8</cell><cell><hi rend="smallcaps">Stone</hi></cell><cell>-</cell><cell>I</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>9</cell><cell><hi rend="smallcaps">Bind</hi></cell><cell>-</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>10</cell><cell><hi rend="smallcaps">Stone</hi></cell><cell>-</cell><cell>I</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>11</cell><cell><hi rend="smallcaps">Bind</hi></cell><cell>-</cell><cell>16</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>12</cell><cell><hi rend="smallcaps">Shale</hi></cell><cell>-</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>13</cell><cell><hi rend="smallcaps">Bind</hi></cell><cell>-</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell><hi rend="smallcaps">14</hi></cell><cell><hi rend="smallcaps">Shale</hi></cell><cell>-</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell><hi rend="smallcaps">15</hi></cell><cell><hi rend="smallcaps">Clunch, stone </hi><hi rend="italic">and ſometimes cank</hi></cell><cell>-</cell><cell>54</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>16</cell><cell><hi rend="smallcaps">Soft Coal</hi></cell><cell/><cell>4</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>17</cell><cell><hi rend="smallcaps">Clay</hi></cell><cell>-</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>18</cell><cell><hi rend="smallcaps">Soft Coal</hi></cell><cell>-</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>19</cell><cell><hi rend="smallcaps">Clunch </hi><hi rend="italic">and </hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Bind</hi></cell><cell/><cell>21</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>20</cell><cell><hi rend="smallcaps">Coal</hi></cell><cell>-</cell><cell>I</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>21</cell><cell><hi rend="smallcaps">Bind</hi></cell><cell>-</cell><cell>I</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>22</cell><cell><hi rend="italic">Strong, broad </hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Bind</hi></cell><cell>-</cell><cell>25</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>23</cell><cell><hi rend="smallcaps">Coal</hi></cell><cell>-</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell/><cell/><cell/><cell>222</cell><cell>3</cell></row></table><p>Mr Forſter has given an account of ſome of the ſtrata of the South-Sea iſtands, the ſubſtance oſ which may be seen in the following table.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">South Georgia.</hi></p><p>1.	No soil, except in a few crevices of the rocks.</p><p>2.	Ponderous ſtate, with ſome irony particles, in horizontal ſtrata, perpendicularly intersected with veins of quartz.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Southern Isle of  </hi><hi rend="smallcaps">New Zealand.</hi></p><p>1.	Fine light black mould, in ſome places nine inches deep, but generally not ſo much.</p><p>2.	An argillaceous ſubſtance, nearly related to the claſs oſ <hi rend="smallcaps">Talcons,</hi> turned into earth by the action of the air.</p><p>3.	The ſame ſubſtance farther indurated, in oblique ſtrata, generally dipping to the south.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Easter Island.</hi></p><p>1.	Reddiſh-brown duſty mould, looking as if it had been burnt.</p><p>2. Burnt rocks, reſembling flags or droſs and other volcanic matters.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Marquesas.</hi></p><p>1.	Clay mixed with mould.</p><p>2.	An earthy argillaceous ſubſtance mixed with tarras</p><p>and puzzolana.</p><p><hi rend="italic">OTAHEITE.</hi></p><p>The ſhores are coral rock, extending from the reef encircling theſe iſles to the very high water-mark. There begins the sand, formed in ſome places from ſmall ſhells and rubbed pieces of coral ; but in others the ſhores are covered with blackiſh sand, conſiſting of the former sort mixed with black, ſometimes glittering, particles of mica, and here and there ſome particles of the refractory iron ores called in England <hi rend="smallcaps">Skim,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">ferrum micaceum</hi> of Linnaeus, and <hi rend="smallcaps">Kall</hi> the <hi rend="italic">molybdaenum spuma lupi</hi> of the ſame author. The plains from the ſhores to the foot of the hills are covered with a very fine thick ſtratum of black mould, mixed with the above-mentioned sand, which the natives manure with ſhells. The firſt and lower range of hills are formed of a red octιreous earth, ſometimes ſo intenſely red, that the natives uſe it to paint their canoes and cloth. The higher hills consiſt of a hard, compact, and ſtiff clayey ſubſtance, hardening into ſtone when out of the reach of the sun and air. At the top of the valleys, along the banks of the rivers, are large maſſes of coarſe granite ſtones of various mixtures ; in one place are pillars oſ a grey, ſolid baſaltes ; and, in ſeveral others, fragments of black baſaltes.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Friendly Islands</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">New Hebrides. </hi>The ſame with the above.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mallicollo.</hi></p><p>Yellowiſh clay mixed with common sand.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Tanna, </hi><hi rend="italic">a Polcanic Island.</hi></p><p>The chief ſtrata here are clay mixed with aluminous earth, interſperſed with lumps of pure chalk. The ſtrata of the clay are about six inches, deviating very- little from the horizontal line.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">New Caledonia</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">adjacent Isles.</hi></p><p>The ſhores conflit of ſhell-ſand, and particles of quartz; the soil in the plains a black mould mixed with this sand. The ſides of the hills compoſed of a yellow ochreous clay, richly ſpangled with ſmall particles of cat-ſilver, or a whitiſh kind of daze, the <hi rend="italic">mica argenteae</hi> of Linnæus. The higher parts of the hills conſist of a ſtone called by the German miners <hi rend="italic">gestelstein,</hi> compoſed of quartz and great lumps of the above cat- ſilver. The latter is ſometimes of an intenſely red or orange colour, by means of an iron ochre.</p><p>“ From the above account, “ ſays Mr Forſter,” it appears, I think, evidently, that all the high tropical isles of the South Sea have been ſubject to the action of volcanoes. Pyritical and ſulphureous ſubſtances, together with a few iron-ſtones, and ſome veſtiges of copper, are no doubt found in ſeveral of them : but the mountains of New Caledonia are the moſt likely to contain the richeſt metallic veins ; and the ſame opinion, I ſuſpect, may be formed of the mountains in New Zealand.”</p><p>In the city of Modena in Italy, and for ſome miles round that place, there is the moſt ſingular arrangement of ſtrata perhaps in the whole world. From the ſurface of the ground to the depth of 14 ſeet, they meet with nothing but the ruins of an ancient city. Being come to that depth, they find paved ſtreets, artificers ſhops, floors of houſes, and ſeveral pieces of inlaid work. After theſe ruins they find a very solid earth, which one would think had never been removed ; but a little lower they find it black and marſhy, and full of briars. Signior Ramazzini in one place found a heap of wheat entire at the depth of 24 feet ; in another, he found</p></body></text></TEI>