<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-04-20T21:26:28Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>is moſt ſuitable to trees; for on theſe two things the future vigour of trees, and the goodneſs of fruit, equally depend. The beſt way for thoſe who intend to plant, is to raiſe their own stocks, by which they will be better assured of what they do ; but if they ſhould buy their trees of nurserymen, they ſhould diligently inquire upon what stocks they were propagated. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Grafting.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Stock,</hi> in trade. See <hi rend="italic smallcaps">Capital</hi><hi rend="italic"> Slock. STOCK-Broker.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Broker</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Stocks.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Stock-</hi><hi rend="italic">Dove,</hi> in zoology. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Columba.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Stock-</hi><hi rend="italic">Jobbing,</hi> the art or myſtery of trafficking in the public ſtocks or funds. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Fund</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Stock-JOBBING.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Stock</hi><hi rend="italic"> Gilly-flower,</hi> in botany. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Cheriranthus.</hi></p><p>STOCKHOLM, the capital oſ Sweden, is ſituated in the province of Upland, in E. Long. 19. 30. and N. Lat. 59. 20. Its foundation is by the beſt Swediſh writers generally attributed to Birger Jarl, regent of the kingdom about the middle of the 13th century during the minority of his ſon Waldemar, who had been raiſed to the throne by the states of the kingdom ; but it was not before the last century that the royal reſidence was transferred from Upſala to this city.</p><p>This capital, which is very long and irregular, occupies, beside two peninſulas, ſeven ſmall rocky iſlands, ſcattered in the Mæler, in the streams which issue from that lake, and in a bay of the gull of Bothnia. A variety of contraſted and enchanting views are formed by numberleſs rocks of granite rising boldly from the ſurface of the water; partly bare and craggy, partly dotted with houſes, or feathered with wood. The harbour is an inlet oſ the Baltic : the water is clear as cryſtal, and of ſuch depth that ſhips of the largeſt burthen can approach the quay, which is of conſiderable breadth, and lined with ſpacious buildings and ware houſes. At the extremity of the harbour ſeveral streets riſe one above another in the form of an amphitheatre; and the palace, a magnificent building, crowns the ſummit. Towards the ſea, about two or three miles from the town, the harbour is contracted into a narrow ſtrait, and, winding among high rocks, diſappears from the sight ; and the proſpect is terminated by diſtant hills, overſpread with forest: It is far beyond the power of words, or of the pencil, to delineate theſe Angular views. The central iſland, from which the city derives its name, and the Ritterholm, are the handſomeſt parts of the town. Excepting in the ſuburbs, where the houſes are of wood painted red, the generality of the buildings are of stone, or brick stuccoed white. The royal palace, which stands in the centre of Stockholm, and upon the higheſt ſpot of ground, was begun by Charles XI. : it is a large quadrangular stone edifice, and the style of architecture is both elegant and magnificent.</p><p>It is the habitation not only of the royal family, but alſo of the greater part of the officers belonging to the household. It likewiſe comprehends the national or ſupreme court of justice, the colleges of war, chancery, treaſury, and commerce ; a chapel, armoury, library, and office for the public records ; but the greater number of inferior officers and ſervants belonging to the court, are, with the foot guards, quartered on the burghers. The caſtle, and all the ſtately edifices in the kingdom, are covered with copper. The palace of the nobility, in which this order sits during the ſeſſion</p><p>of the diet, is an elegant building adorned on the outſide with marble ſtatues and columns, and on the inside with painting and sculpture. This and three other palaces stand on the banks of the lake, and are built on the same model, ſo as to compoſe an uniform piece of architecture. The bank, built at the expence of the city, is a noble edifice, and joins with many ſumptuous houses belonging to the nobility in exhibiting a splendid appearance. The houſes of the burghers are generally built of brick in the city ; but in the ſuburbs they are commonly made up of timber, and therefore very ſubject to conflagrations. Theſe houſes are often framed in Finland, according to the plan and dimensions preſcribed ; whence they are tranſported in pieces to Stockholm by water, and there set up by the carpenters. Theſe wooden habitations, if kept in proper repair, will laſt 30 or 40 years, and are deemed wanner, neater, and more healthy, than thoſe of brick or ſtone. To prevent the danger of conflagrations, the city is divided into 12 wards. In each of theſe there is a maſter and four aſſiſtants, who forthwith repair to the place where the fire breaks out; and all porters and labourers are obliged to range themſelves under the maſter of the ward to which they belong. A fire-watch patroles the ſtreets by night, to give warning or assistance as it may be wanted ; and a centinel is maintained in the ſteeple of every church, to toll the bell on the firſt appearance of any ſuch accident. The police of Stockholm is entirely ſubjected to the regulations of the grand governor, assisted by a deputy and bailiff of the caſtle. This city is the ſtaple of Sweden, to which all the commodities of the kingdom are brought for exportation, and where almoſt all the imports ſrom abroad are deposited. The port or haven formed by the lake Mæler is large enough to contain 1000 ſail of shipping ; and furniſhed with a key or wharf about an Engliſh mile in length, to which the vessels may lie with their broadſides. The greateſt inconveniences attending this ſituation are, the diſtance from the ſea, which is not within leſs than 10 miles of the town ; the want of tides ; and the winding of the river, which is remarkably crooked. It opens into the Baltic; and the entrance, which is dangerous and rocky, the Swedes have ſecured with two ſmall forts : within, it is perfectly ſafe and commodious. The northern ſuburbs are remarkable for the king’s gardens, and for the great number of artiſans who have choſen their habitations in this quarter. In the southern ſuburbs the Muſcovite commodities are sold ; and here is a magnificent exchange where the merchants daily assemble.</p><p>STOCKING, that part of the clothing of the leg and foot which immediately covers and ſcreens them from the rigour of the cold. Anciently, the only flockings in uſe were made of cloth, or of milled fluffs ſewed together ; but ſince the invention of knitting and weaving flockings of silk, wool, cotton, thread, &amp;c. the uſe of cloth flockings is quite diſcontinued. Dr Howel, in his Hiſtory or the World (vol. ii. p. 222.) relates, that queen Elizabeth, in 1501, was preſented with a pair of black knit ſilk flockings by her ſilk-woman, and thenceforth ſhe never wore cloth ones any more. The ſame author adds, that king Henry VIII. ordinarily wore cloth hoſe, except there came from Spain, by great chance, a pair of ſilk stockings. His ſon, king Edward VI. was preſented with a pair of long Spanish ſilk stockings by Sir Thomas Greſham,</p></body></text></TEI>