<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-04-20T21:21:18Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p><hi rend="italic">re-prove, di-stinct</hi> ; however, this rule is found sometimes to fail ; for though <hi rend="italic">gn</hi> begins a word, as <hi rend="italic">gnaw, gnat,</hi> &amp;c. yet it must be divided in ſpelling, as in <hi rend="italic">cog- ni-zance, ma-lig-ni-ty, &amp;.C.</hi>	4. Thoſe conſonants which</p><p>cannot begin a word muſt be divided, as <hi rend="italic">ld</hi> in s<hi rend="italic">eldom, It </hi>in <hi rend="italic">mul-ti-tude, mp</hi> in <hi rend="italic">tem-per, rd in ar-dent</hi> ; but in final ſyllables there are exceptions, as <hi rend="italic">tl</hi> in <hi rend="italic">ti-tle, dl</hi> in <hi rend="italic">handle,</hi> &amp;c.	5. When two vowels come together, and are</p><p>both of them diſtinctly founded, they must be ſeparated in ſpelling, as in <hi rend="italic">co-e-val, mu-tu-al,</hi> &amp;c.	6. The gram</p><p>matical terminations or endings muſt be ſeparated in ſpelling, as <hi rend="italic">ed</hi> in w<hi rend="italic">ing-ed, edst</hi> in <hi rend="italic">de-li-ver-edst, ing </hi>in <hi rend="italic">bear-ing, once</hi> in <hi rend="italic">de-li-ver-ance,</hi> &amp;c.	7. Compound words muſt be reſolved into their ſimple or component words, as <hi rend="italic">up-on, in-to, ne-ver-the-less, nοt-with-stand- ing,</hi> &amp;c.</p><p>SPELMAN (Sir Henry), an eminent Engliſh antiquarian, was deſcended from an ancient family, and born at Cengham, near Lynn in Norfolk, about the year 1561. He was knighted by king James I. who had a particular eſteem for him on account of his known capacity for buſineſs ; and he employed him ſeveral times in Ireland on public affairs. When he was about 50 years of age, he went to reſide in London ; where falling into a ſtudy to which his own genius had always inclined him, he collected all ſuch books and MSS. as concerned the ſubject of antiquities, either foreign or domeſtic. In 1626, he publiſhed the firſt part of his well-known Gloſſary, which he never carried beyond the letter L ; becauſe, as ſome have ſuggeſted, he had ſaid things under “ Magna charta,” and “ Maximum conſilium,” that could not then have appeared without giving offence. Upon his death all his papers came into the hands of his son Sir John Spelman, a gentleman who had abilities to have completed his father’s deſign, if death had not prevented him. The second part was afterwards publiſhed by Sir William Dugdale ; but with all the marks of a ſcanty unfiniſhed performance. The next work he entered upon was an edition of the Engliſh Councils, of which he publiſhed the firſt volume about two years before his death, leaving the second volume, as well of this as of his Gloſſary, to be publiſhed by Sir William Dugdale. Sir Henry wrote ſeveral other things, all relating to ancient laws and cuſtoms, and died in 1641. His Poſthumous Works were publiſhed in folio, 1698, under the inſpection of Mr Gibson, afterwards biſhop of London.</p><p>SPELTER, in metallurgy, the same with <hi rend="smallcaps">Zinc.</hi></p><p>SPENCE (Joſeph), was fellow of New College, Oxford, where he took the degree of A. Μ. in 1727. About that time he became firſt known as an author, by an <hi rend="italic">Essay on Pope's Odyssey, in which ſome particular beauties and blemiſhes of that work are considered</hi> ; a work of great merit, and which for found criticiſm and candid diſquiſition is almoſt without a parallel. He was elected profeſſor of poetry by the univerſity in 1728, and held that office ten years, which is as long as the ſtatutes will allow. His Hiſtory of Stephen Duck was firſt publiſhed in 1731 ; but it was afterwards much altered, and prefixed to an edition of Duck’s poems.</p><p>About this time he travelled into Italy as tutor to the earl of Lincoln, afterwards duke of Newcaſtle.— In 1736 he republiſhed Gorboduc, at Mr Pope’s desire, with a preface giving an account of the author, the earl of Dorſet. He quitted his fellowſhip in 1742, upon being preſented by the Society of New College to the rectory of Great Harwood in Buckinhhamshire.— He never reſided in his living; but paid it an annual viſit, diſtributing large ſums of money among the poor, and providing for many of their children. The ſame year he was made profeſſor of modern hiſtory at Oxford. In 1747 he publiſhed <hi rend="italic">Polynutis;</hi> or an inquiry concerning the agreement between the works of the Roman poets and the remains of ancient artiſts, being an attempt to illuſtrate them mutually from each other. This work was treated by Gray with a contempt which it did not deferve. He raiſes objections becauſe the author did not illuſtrate his ſubject from Greek writers ; that is, becauſe he failed to execute what he never undertook. He was inſtalled prebendary of the ſeventh ſtall at Durham the 24th May 1754. He publiſhed the ſame year, “ An Account of the Lite, Character, and Poems, of Mr Blacklock, ſtudent of philoſophy at Edinburgh ;” which was afterwards prefixed to his Poems. The proſe pieces which he printed in the Muſeum he collected and publiſhed, together with ſome others, in a pamphlet called <hi rend="italic">Moralities,</hi> by Sir Harry Beaumont Under the ſame name he publiſhed “ Crito, or a dialogue on beauty,” and “ A particular Account of the Emperor of China’s Gardens near Pekin, in a letter from F. Attiret, a French missionary now employed by that Emperor to paint the apartments in thoſe gardens, to his friend at Paris.” Both theſe treatiſes are printed in Dodſley’s fugitive pieces, as is alſo “ A Letter from a Swiſs Officer to his friend at Rome ;” which Mr Spence firſt publiſhed in the Muſeum. In 1758 he publiſhed “ A Parallel, in the Manner of Plutarch, between a moſt celebrated man of Florence and one ſcarce ever heard of in England.” This was alſo inſerted in the fugitive pieces. The ſame year he made a journey into Scotland, which he deſcribed in an affectionate letter to Mr Shenſtone, publiſhed in Hall’s Collection of Letters, 1778. In 1764 he was very well deſcribed by Mr James Ridley, in his admirable Tales of the Genii, under the name of <hi rend="italic">Pheſoi Ecneps</hi> (his name read backwards), derviſe of the groves. A letter from Mr Spence to that ingenious moraliſt, under the ſame signature, is preſerved in the 3d volume of “ Letters of Eminent Perſons.” In 1768 he publiſhed “ Remarks and Dissertations on Virgil, with ſome other claſſical obſervations, by the late Mr Holdſworth." On the 20th of Auguſt the ſame year he was unfortunately drowned in a canal in his garden at Byfleet in Surrey. He was found flat upon his face at the edge of the canal, where the water was ſo ſhallow as not even to cover his head. The accident, it was ſuppoſed, for he was quite alone, was owing to a fit.</p><p>The duke of Newcaſtle poſſeſſes ſome manuſcript volumes of anecdotes collected by Mr Spence, from which Dr Johnſon was permitted to inſert many extracts in his Lives of the Poets.</p><p>SPENCER (Dr John), an eminent divine, was born in Kent in 1630, and educated at Cambridge. He was choſen fellow of his college, and took a doctor’s degree in 1663. In 1667 he was choſen maſter of Corpus Chriſti College, and preferred to the deanery of Ely in 1677. He died on the 20th of May 1695. His works are, 1. The Righteous Ruler ; a ſermon on Proverbs xxix. <hi rend="italic">2.</hi> preached June 28. 1600.	2. A Diſcourſe concerning Prodigies, wherein the vanity of preſages by them is reprehended, and their true and proper ends asſerted and</p></body></text></TEI>