<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-04-20T21:23:53Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>them in cloſe vessels, which he called <hi rend="smallcaps">digesters,</hi> ſo as to acquire a great degree of heat. For it must be obſerved in this place, that it had been diſcovered long before (in 1684) by Dr Hooke, the moſt inquiſitive experimental philosopher of that inquiſitive age, that water could not be made to acquire above a certain temperature in the open air ; and that as ſoon as it begins to boil, its temperature remains fixed, and an increaſe of heat only produces a more violent ebullition, and a more rapid waste. But Papin’s experiments made the elaſtic power of ſteam very familiar to him : and when he left England and settled as profeſſor of mathematics at Marpurgh, he made many awkward attempts to employ this force in mechanics, and even for raising water. It appears that he had made experiments with this view in 1698, by order of Charles Landgrave of Heſſe. For this reaſon the French affect to consider him as the inventor of the ſteam-engine. He indeed publiſhed ſome account of his invention in 1707; but he acknowledges that Captain Savary had alſo, and without any communication with him, invented the ſame thing. Whoever will take the trouble of looking at the deſcription which he has given of theſe inventions, which are to be ſeen in the <hi rend="italic">Acta Eruditorum, Lipsiae,</hi> and in Leupold’s <hi rend="italic">Theatrum Machinarum,</hi> will see that they are most awkward, abſurd, and impracticable. His conceptions of natural operations were always vague and imperfect, and he was neither philoſopher nor mechanician.</p><p>We are thus anxious about the claim of thoſe gentlemen, becauſe a moſt reſpectable French author,
                Mr Boſſut, ſays in his <hi rend="italic">Hydrodynamique,</hi> that the firſt notion
                of the ſteam-engine was <hi rend="italic">certainly</hi> owing to Dr Papin, who had
                not only invented the digester, but had in 1695 published a little performance
                deſcribing a machine for railing water, in which the piſtons are moved by the vapour
                of boiling water alternately dilated and condenſed. Now the fact is that Papin’s
                firſt publication was in 1707, and his piſton is nothing more than a floater on the
                ſurface of the water, to prevent the watte of ſteam by condenſation ; and the return
                of the piſton is not produced, as in the ſteam-engine, by the condenſation of the
                ſteam, but by admitting the air and a column of water to press it back into its
                place. The whole contrivance is ſo awkward, and ſo unlike any diſtinct notions of
                the ſubject, that it cannot do credit to any perſon. We may add, that much about the
                ſame time Mr Amontons contrived a very ingenious but intricate machine, which he
                called a <hi rend="italic">fire-wheel.</hi> It conſiſted of a number of buckets
                placed in the circumference of a wheel, and communicating with each other by very
                intricate circuitous passages. One part of this circumference was expoſed to the
                heat of a furnace, and another to a ſtream or cittern of cold water. The
                communications were ſo diſpoſed, that the ſteam produced in the buckets on one side
                of the wheel drove the water into buckets on the other side, ſo that one side of the
                wheel was always much heavier than the other ; and it must, therefore turn round,
                and may execute ſome work. The death of the inventor, and the intricacy oſ the
                machine, cauſed it to be neglected. Another member of the Parisian academy of
                ſciences (Mr Deſlandes) alſo preſented to the academy a project of a ſteam-wheel,
                where the impulſive force of the vapour was employed; but it met with no
                encouragement. The Engliſh engineers had by this time ſo much improved Savary’s
                firſt invention, that it supplanted all others. We have therefore no heſitation in
                giving the honour of the firſt and complete invention to the marquis of Worceſter ;
                and we are not diſpoſed to refuse Captain Savary’s claim to originality as the
                construction of the machine, and even think it probable that his own experiments
                made him ſee the whole independent of the marquis’s account.</p><p>Captain Savary’s engine, as improved and simplified by himſelf, is as follows.</p><p>A (fig. 6.) repreſents a ſtrong copper boiler properly built up in a furnace. There proceeds from its top a large ſteam-pipe B, which enters into the top of another ſtrong veſſel R called the <hi rend="smallcaps">receiver.</hi> This pipe has a cock at C called the <hi rend="smallcaps">steam-cock.</hi> In the bottom of the receiver is a pipe F, which communicates ſidewiſe with the rising pipe KGH. The lower end H of this pipe is immerſed in the water of the pit or well, and its upper part K opens into the cittern into which the water is to be delivered. Immediately below the pipe of communication F there is a valve G, opening when preſſed from below, and ſhutting when preſſed downwards. A ſimilar valve is placed at I, immediately above the pipe of communication. Laſtly, there is a pipe ED which branches off from the rising pipe, and enters into the top of the receiver. This pipe has a cock D called the <hi rend="smallcaps">injection-cock.</hi> The mouth of the pipe ED has a nozzle f pierced with ſmall holes, pointing from a centre in every direction. The keys of the two cocks C and D are united, and the handle <hi rend="italic">gh</hi> is called the <hi rend="smallcaps">regulator.</hi></p><p>Let the regulator be ſo placed that the ſteam-cock C is open and the injection-cock D is ſhut ; put water into the boiler A, and make it boil ſtrongly. The ſteam coming from it will enter the receiver, and gradually warm it, much ſteam being condenſed in producing this effect. When it has been warmed ſo as to condenſe no more, the ſteam proceeds into the rising pipe ; the valve G remains ſhut by its weight ; the ſteam lifts the valve I, and gets into the rising pipe, and gradually warms it. When the workman feels this to be the caſe, or hears the rattling of the valve I, he immediately turns the ſteam-cock ſo as to ſhut it, the injection-cock ſtill remaining ſhut (at leaſt we may ſuppoſe this for the preſent). The apparatus must now cool, and the ſteam in the receiver collapſes into water. There is nothing now to balance the preſſure of the atmoſphere ; the valve I remains ſhut by its weight ; but the air incumbent on the water in the pit preſſes up this water through the ſuction-pipe H G, and cauſes it to lift the valve G, and flow into the receiver R, and fill it to the top, if not more than 20 or 25 feet above the ſurface of the pit water.</p><p>The ſteam-cock is now opened. The ſteam which, during the cooling of the receiver, has been accumulating in the boiler, and acquiring a great elasticity by the action of the fire, now ruſhes in with great violence, and, preſſing on the ſurface of the water in the receiver, cauſes it to ſhut the valve G and open the valve I by its weight alone, and it now flows into the rising pipe, and would stand on a level if the elaſticity of the ſteam were no more than what would balance the atmoſpherical preſſure. But it is much more than this, and therefore is <hi rend="italic">presses</hi> the water out of the receiver into the rising</p></body></text></TEI>