<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-04-20T21:26:23Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>us, that they erected a ſtone-bridge over the Forth, upon the ſummit of which a croſs was raiſed, with the following inſcription in monkiſh rhyme.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Anglos a Scotis ſeparat crux ista remotis ;</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Armis hic stant Bruti, Scoti Jiant hic, cruce tuti.</hi></p><p>Which is thus tranſlated by Bellenden.</p><p>I am free marche, as paſſengeris may ken, To Scottis, to Britonis, and to Ingliſmen.</p><p>None of the ancient Engliſh hiſtorians mention this conqueſt. The whole ſtory, as well as the inſcription, wears much of a monkish garb ; yet its authenticity is not a little confirmed by the arms of the town of Stirling, upon which is a bridge, with a croſs, and the last line of the above Latin diſtich is the motto round it.</p><p>We muſt not, however, imagine, that in thoſe times that fortreſs bore any reſemblance to the preſent structure, which is adapted to the uſe of fire-arms. Its ſize and form probably reſembled thoſe caſtles which, under the feudal conſtitution, the Engliſh and Scottiſh barons uſed to erect upon their eſtates for dwelling- houſes; and which, in thoſe barbarous ages, they found neceſſary to fortify for their defence, not only againſt foreign invaders, but often againſt the attacks of their own neighbours. It is directly ſuch a Gothic figure as this which repreſents the <hi rend="italic">Castrum Strivelenſe</hi> upon the arms of Stirling.</p><p>This fortreſs, after it had continued in the poſſeſſion of the Northumbrian Saxons about 20 years, was, together with the whole country upon the ſouth side of the Forth, reſtored to the Scots, upon condition of their aſſiſting the Saxons againſt their turbulent invaders the Danes. Upon the arms of Stirling are two branches of a tree, to repreſent the <hi rend="italic">Nemus Strivelenſe;</hi> but the situation and boundaries of that foreſt, which was probably a wing of the Caledonian, cannot be aſcertained. Upon the ſouth of Stirling, veſtiges of a foreſt are ſtill diſcernible for ſeveral miles. Banks of natural timber ſtill remain in the caſtle park, at Murray’s wood, and near Nether Bannockburn ; and ſtumps of trees, with much brushwood, are to be ſeen in all the adjacent fields.</p><p>When Kenneth III. received intelligence of the Danes having invaded his dominions, he appointed the caſtle of Stirling to be the place of rendezvous for his army ; and he marched from thence to the battle of Loncarty, where he obtained a victory over thoſe rovers, in the end of the 10th century.</p><p>In the 12th century, this caſtle is ſpoken of as a place of great importance, and one of the ſtrongeſt fortreſſes in the kingdom. In 1174, a calamity, not unuſual amongſt the Scottiſh monarchs, befel William, who at that time occupied the throne. He was taken priſoner in an unsucceſsful expedition which he made into England ; and, after having been detained 12 months in captivity, was releaſed, upon stipulating to pay a large ſum of money for his ransom ; and, until payment thereof, delivering into the hands of the Engliſh the four principal fortreſſes in the kingdom, which in thoſe days were Stirling, Edinburgh, Roxburgh, and Berwick. This was the firſt great aſcendant that England obtained over Scotland ; and indeed the moſt important tranſaction which had paſſed between theſe kingdoms from the Norman conqueſt.</p><p>Though the Scottiſh monarchs, in their frequent perambulations through the kingdom, often visited Stirling, and held their courts for ſome time in the caſtle; yet <hi rend="italic">it </hi>did not become a royal residence till the family of Stuart mounted the throne, and it was from different princes of this family that it received its preſent form. It was the place of the nativity of James IL; and, when raiſed to the throne, he frequently kept his court in it. It is well known to have been the place where that prince perpetrated an atrocious deed, the murder of William earl of Douglas, whom he ſtabbed with his own hand. The royal apartments were at that time in the northwest corner of the castle, and are now the residence of the fort-major. The room where the murder was committed still goes by the name of <hi rend="italic">Douglas’s room.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Scotland,</hi> n⁰ 304, 305.</p><p>James III. contracting a fondneſs for the caſtle on account of its pleaſant situation, made it the chief place of his residence, and added ſeveral embelliſhments to it. He built within it a magnificent hall, which in thoſe days was deemed a noble structure, and is still entire. It now goes by the name of the <hi rend="italic">parliament-houſe,</hi> having been designed for the accommodation of that ſupreme court. It was covered with an oaken roof of exquisite workmanſhip, which, though very little decayed, was a few years ago removed to make way for one of more modern structure, James alſo erected a college of ſecular priests in the caſtle, which he called the <hi rend="italic">chapel-royal,</hi> and which proved one cauſe of his own ruin. As the expences neceſſary for maintaining the numerous officers of ſuch an institution were conſiderable, he annexed to it the revenues of the rich priory of Coldingham in the Merſe, which at that time happened to become vacant. This priory had for a long time been holden by perſons connected with the family of Hume ; and that family, considering it as belonging to them, ſtrongly oppoſed the annexation. The diſpute ſeems to have lasted ſeveral years; for one parliament had paſſed a vote, annexing the priory to the chapel-royal, and a ſubſequent one enacted a statute prohibiting every attempt that was contrary or prejudicial to that annexation.</p><p>James V. was crowned in the caſtle of Stirling ; and the palace, which is the chief ornament of it, was the work of that prince. This is a ſtately and commodious structure, all of hewn, ſtone, with much ſtatuary work upon st. It is built in form of a ſquare, with a ſmall court in the middle, in which the king’s lions are ſaid to have been kept ; and hence it ſtill goes by the name of the <hi rend="italic">lions den.</hi> The palace contains many large and elegant apartments ; the ground-ſtory is now converted into barrack-rooms for the ſoldiers of the garriſon ; the upper affords a houſe for the governor, with lodgings for ſome of the ſubaltern officers.</p><p>Oppoſite to the palace, upon the north, stands an elegant chapel, which was built by James VI. for the baptism of his ſon prince Henry in 1594. In this chapel is preſerved the hulk of a large boat, which that whimſical monarch cauſed to be built and placed upon carriages, in order to convey into the caſtle the provisions for that ſolemnity.</p><p>A ſtrong battery, with a tier of guns pointing to the bridge over the Forth, was erected during the regency of Mary of Lorraine, mother to queen Mary. It is called the <hi rend="italic">French baιtery,</hi> probably becauſe conſtructed by engineers of that nation. The last addition was made</p></body></text></TEI>