<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-04-20T21:26:05Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>to have been the author of the excellent book intitled “ The Whole Duty of Man.” Laurence inherited nothing of his anceſtor’s manner of writing, but rather reſembled Rabelais, whoſe wit he carried with him even into the pulpit.</p><p>In 1722 he was ſent to ſchool at Halifax in Yorkſhire, where he continued till 1732, when he was removed to Jeſus College in Cambridge. How long he reſided in college, or what progreſs he made in literature or ſcience, is not known : his works diſplay rather native genius than profound erudition. Upon quitting the univerſity he went to York, and being in orders was preſented to the living of Sutton by the intereſt of his uncle Dr Sterne, a prebendary of that church. In 1741 he married, and was ſoon afterwards made a prebendary of York, by the intereſt alſo of his uncle, who was then upon very good terms with him ; but “ quickly quarrelled with him (he ſays), and became his bittereſt enemy, becauſe he would not be a party man, and write paragraphs in the newſpapers.” By his wife’s means he got the living of Stillington, but remained near 20 years at Sutton, doing duty at both places. He was then in very good health, which, however, ſoon after forſook him ; and books, painting, fiddling, and ſhooting, were, as he tells us, his amuſements.</p><p>In 1760, he went to London to publiſh his two first volumes of “ Triſtram Shandy;” and was that year preſented to the curacy of Coxwold. In 1762 he went to France, and two years after to Italy, for the recovery of his health ; but his health never was recovered. He languiſhed under a conſumption of the lungs, without the ſiighteſt depreſſion of ſpirits, till 1768, when death put a period to his terreſtrial expence.</p><p>The works of Sterne are very generally read. They conſiſt of, I. The Life and Opinions of Triſtram Shandy; <hi rend="italic">2</hi> Sermons; 3. A Sentimental Journey; 4. Letters, publiſhed ſince his death. In every ſerious page, and in many of much levity, the author writes in praiſe of benevolence, and declares that no one who knew him could suppoſe him one of thoſe wretches who heap misfortune upon misfortune : But we have heard anecdotes of him extremely well authenticated, which proved that it was eaſier for him to praiſe this virtue than to practiſe it. His wit is universally allowed ; but many readers have perſuaded themſelves that they found wit in his blank pages, while it is probable that he intended nothing but to amuſe himſelf with the idea of the ſage conjectures to which theſe pages would give occaſion. Even his originality is not ſuch as is generally ſuppoſed by thoſe loud admirers of the Shandean manner, who have preſumed to compare him with Swift, Arbuthnot, and Butler. He has borrowed both matter and manner from various authors, as every reader may be convinced by the learned, elegant, and candid comments on his works publiſhed by Dr Farrier, in the fourth volume of the Memoirs of the Literary and Philoſophical Society of Mancheſter.</p><p>STERNOCOSTALES, commonly called the <hi rend="italic">muſculi triangulares sterni,</hi> in anatomy, are five pairs of flelhy planes, diſpoſed more or leſs obliquely on each side the ſternum, on the inſides of the cartilages of the ſecond, third, fourth, fifth, and ſixth true ribs.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">STERNO-H</hi>YOIDÆUS, in anatomy. See <hi rend="italic">Table of the Muſcles,</hi> under the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Anatomy.</hi></p><p>STERNOMANTIS, in antiquity, a deſignation given to the Delphian prieſteſs, more uſually called <hi rend="smallcaps">Pythia.</hi>—Sternomantis is alſo uſed for any one that had a propheſyino demon within him.</p><p>STERNOMASTOIDÆUS, a muſcle. See <hi rend="italic">Table of the Muscles,</hi> under <hi rend="smallcaps">Anatomy.</hi></p><p>STERNOTHYROIDEUS, a muſcle. See <hi rend="italic">Table of the Muscles,</hi> under <hi rend="smallcaps">Anatomy.</hi></p><p>STERNUM. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Anatomy,</hi> n⁰ 37.</p><p>STERNUTATIVE, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Sternutatory,</hi> a medicine proper to produce ſneezing See <hi rend="smallcaps">Sneezing.</hi></p><p>STETIN, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Stettin,</hi> a ſeaport town of Germany, in the circle of Upper Saxony, and capital of Hither Pomerania, with the title of a duchy, and a caſtle. It had long a famous school, which the wars of Germany never diſturbed. The ancient dukes of Pomerania reſided here ; and it was taken by the elector of Brandenburg in 1676, but given to Sweden by the treaty of Nimeguen. In 1713 it ſubmitted to the allies ; and then the ſaid elector was put in poſſeſſion again of this important place, which is a bulwark to the Marche of Brandenburg ; and the fortifications have been greatly improved. It is now a flouriſhing place, and carries on a considerable trade. It is ſeated on the river Oder, 72 miles north of Francfort, and 70 north by eaſt of Berlin. E. Long. 14. 38. N. Lat. 53. 35. The duchy is 125 miles in length, and borders upon Mecklenburg, and partly upon Brandenburg. The breadth is from 17 to 25 miles, and it is divided by the river Oder into two parts.</p><p>STEW, a ſmall kind of fiſh-pond, the peculiar uſe of which is to maintain fiſh, and keep them in readineſs for the daily uſe of the family, &amp;c.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Stews</hi> (from the French <hi rend="italic">estuves,</hi> i. e. <hi rend="italic">thermae, balneum),</hi> thoſe places which were permitted in England to women of profeſſed incontinency, and that for hire would proſtitute their bodies to all comers; ſo called, becauſe disſolute perſons are wont to prepare them ſelves for venereous acts by bathing ; and hot baths were by Homer reckoned among the effeminate fort of pleaſures. Theſe ſtews were ſuppressed by King Hen. VIII. about the year 1546.</p><p>STEWARD <hi rend="italic">,ſeneſcallus,</hi> compounded of the Saxon st<hi rend="italic">eda,</hi> i. e. “ room;” or ste<hi rend="italic">ad</hi> and w<hi rend="italic">eard, “ </hi>a ward” or “keeper”), an officer appointed in another’s ſtead or place, and always taken for a principal officer within his juriſdiction. Oſ theſe there are various kinds. The greateſt officer under the crown is the lord high-ſteward of England, an office that was anciently the inheritance of the earls of Leiceſter, till forfeited by Simon de Mountfort to King Henry III. But the power of this officer is ſo very great, that it has not been judged ſafe to truſt it any longer in the hands of a ſubject, excepting only <hi rend="italic">pro hac vice,</hi> occasionally : as to officiate at a coronation, at the arraignment of a nobleman for high- treaſon, or the like. During his office, the ſteward bears a white ſtaff in his hand ; and the trial, &amp;c. ended, he breaks the ſtaff, and with it his commiſſion expires. There is likewiſe a lord-ſteward of the king’s houſehold, who is the chief officer of the king’s court, has the care of the king’s house, and authority over all the officers and ſervants of the houſehold, except ſuch as belong to the chapel, chamber, and ſtable.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Steward,</hi> an officer in a ſhip of war, appointed by the purſer to diſtribute the different ſpecies of provi-</p></body></text></TEI>