<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-04-20T21:21:12Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>29th, about midnight, the candles went out, ſomething walked majeſtically through the room, and opened and ſhut the windows ; great stones were thrown violently into the room, ſome of which fell on the beds, others on the floor ; and at about a quarter after one a noiſe was heard as of forty cannon discharged together, and again repeated at about eight minutes diſtance. This alarmed and raiſed all the neighbourhood, who coming into their honours room, gathered up the great ſtones, fourſcore in number, and laid them by in the corner of a field, where, in Dr Plot’s time, who reports this ſtory, they were to be ſeen. This noiſe, like the diſcharge of cannon, was heard through all the country for 16 miles round. During theſe noiſes, which were heard in both rooms together, the commiſſioners and their ſervants gave one another over for lost, and cried out for help ; and Giles Sharp, ſnatching up a ſword, had well nigh killed one of their honours, miſtaking him for the ſpirit, as he came in his ſhirt from his own room to theirs. While they were together, the noiſe was continued, and part of the tiling of the houſe was ſtript off, and all the windows of an upper room were taken away with it. On the 30th at midnight ſomething walked into the chamber treading like a bear ; it walked many times about, then threw the warming-pan violently on the floor ; at the ſame time a large quantity of broken glaſs, accompanied with great ſtones and horſes bones, came pouring into the room with uncommon force. Theſe were all found in the morning to the aſtoniſhment and terror of the commiſſioners, who were yet determined to go on with their buſineſs. But on the firſt of November the moſt dreadful ſcene of all enſued : Candles in every part of the room were lighted up, and a great fire made ; at midnight, the candles all yet burning, a noiſe like the burſting of a cannon was heard in the room, and the burning billets were tossed about by it even into their honours beds ; who called Giles and his companions to their relief, other- wiſe the houſe had been burnt to the ground ; about an hour after the candles went out as uſual, the crack as if many cannon was heard, and many pailfuls of green stinking water were thrown upon their honours beds ; great ſtones were alſo thrown in as before, the bed curtains and bedſteads torn and broken, the windows ſhattered, and the whole neighbourhood alarmed with the moſt dreadful noiſes ; nay, the very rabbit- ſtealers that were abroad that night in the warren were ſo terrified, that they fled for fear and left their ferrets behind them. One of their honours this night ſpoke, and, <hi rend="italic">in the name of God, aſked what it was, and why it disturbed them ſo ?</hi> No anſwer was given to this ; but the noiſe ceaſed for a while, when the ſpirit came again; and, as they all agreed, <hi rend="italic">brought with it ſeven devils worse than itſelf</hi> One of the ſervants now lighted a large candle, and ſet it in the door-way between the two chambers, to ſee what paſſed ; and as he watched it, he plainly ſaw a hoof ſtriking the candle and candle- ſtick into the middle of the room, and afterwards making three ſcrapes over the ſnuff, ſcraped it out. Upon this the ſame perſon was ſo bold as to draw a ſword ; but he had ſcarce got it out when he felt another inviſible hand holding it too, and pulling it from him ; and at length prevailing, ſtruck him ſo violently on the head with the pummel, that he fell down for dead with the blow. At this inſtant was heard another burst like the diſcharge of the broadſide of a ſhip of war, and at about a minute or two’s diſtance each no leſs than 19 more ſuch : theſe ſhook the houſe ſo violently, that they expected every moment it would fall upon their heads. The neighbours, on this, as has been ſaid, being all alarmed, flocked to the houſe in great numbers, and all joined in prayer and pſalm-ſinging during which the noiſe still continued in the other rooms, and the diſcharge of cannons was heard as from without, though no viſible agent was ſeen to diſcharge them. But what was the moſt alarming of all, and put an end to their proceedings effectually, happened the next day as they were all at dinner, when a paper, in which they had ſigned a mutual agreement to reserve a part of the premiſes out of the general ſurvey, and afterwards to ſhare it equally amongſt themſelves, (which paper they had hid for the preſent under the earth in a pot in one corner of the room, and in which an orange-tree grew), was conſumed in a wonderful manner, by the earth’s taking fire with which the pot was filled, and burning violently with a blue fume, and an intolerable ſtench ; ſo that they were all driven out of the houſe, to which they could never be again prevailed upon to return.</p><p>This wonderful contrivance was all the invention of the memorable Joſeph Collins of Oxford, otherwiſe called <hi rend="italic">Funny Joe,</hi> who having hired himſelf as ſecretary, under the name of <hi rend="italic">Giles Sharp,</hi> by knowing the private traps belonging to the houſe, and the help of <hi rend="italic">pulvis fulminans</hi> and other chemical preparations, and letting his fellow-ſervants into the fcheme, carried on the deceit without diſcovery to the very laſt; inſomuch that the late Dr Plot, in his Natural Hiſtory, relates the whole for fact, and concludes in this grave manner, “ That though tricks have been often played in affairs of this kind, many of the things above related are not reconcilcable with juggling ; ſuch as the loud noiſes, beyond the power of man to make without ſuch inſtruments as were not there ; the tearing and breaking the beds ; the throwing about the fire ; the hoof treading out the candle ; and the ſtriving for the ſword, and the blow the man received from the pummel of it.”</p><p>SPECULARIS <hi rend="smallcaps">lapis,</hi> in natural hiſtory, a genus of talcs, compoſed of large plates viſibly separate, and of extreme thinneſs ; and each fiſſile again ſeparated into a number of plates ſtill finer. (See <hi rend="smallcaps">Talc.) </hi>Of this genus there are three ſpecies : 1. The white ſhining ſpecularis, with large and broad leaves, commonly called <hi rend="italic">iſinglaſs and Muſcovy glaſs</hi> ; its lamellae, or leaves, are extremely thin, elaſtic, and tranſparent ; it makes not the leaſt efferveſcence with aquafortis, and is not eaſily calcined in the fire. It is imported in great quantities; the miniature-painters cover their pictures with it ; the lantern-makers ſometimes uſe it instead of horn ; and minute objects are uſually preſerved between two plates of it, for examination by the microſcope. 2. The bright brown ſpecularis, with broad leaves ; a very valuable ſpecies, though inferior to the former. 3. The purple bright ſpecularis, with broad leaves, which is the moſt elegant of all the talcs, and not leſs beautifully tranſparent than the firſt kind.</p><p>SPECULATIVE, ſomething relating to the theory of ſome art or ſcience, in contradiſtinction to practical.</p><p>SPECULUM for reflecting teleſcopes, is made of a kind of white copper conſiſting of 32 parts fine</p></body></text></TEI>