<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-04-20T21:22:43Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>on being opened, the entire head of a man was found in ’ his ſtomach. The ſcalp, and fleſh of the face, were macerated to a ſoft pulpy ſubſtance ; which, on being touched, ſeparated entirely from the bones. The bones were ſomewhat ſoftened, and the futures looſened.”</p><p>The following extraordinary inſtance of intrepidity and friendſhip is well worth recording. It is given on the authority of Mr Hughes, who publiſhed a natural hiſtory of Barbadoes. About the latter end of Queen Anne’s wars, captain John Beanis, commander of the York Merchant, arrived at Barbadoes from England. Having diſembarked the laſt part of his lading, which was coals, the ſailors, who had been employed in that dirty work, ventured into the ſea to waſh themſelves ; there they had not been long before one on board eſpied a large ſhark making toward them, and gave them notice of their danger ; upon which they ſwam back, and all reached the boat except one : him the monſter overtook almost within reach of the oars, and griping him by the ſmall of his back, ſoon cut him aſunder, and as ſoon ſwallowed the lower part of his body ; the remaining part was taken up and carried on board, where a comrade of his was, whoſe friendſhip with the deceaſed had been long diſtinguiſhed by a reciprocal diſcharge or all ſuch endearing offices as implied an union and ſympathy of souls. When he ſaw the severed trunk of his friend, it was with an horror and emotion too great for words to paint. During this affecting ſcene, the inſatiate ſhark was ſeen traverſing the bloody surface in ſearch of the remainder of his prey ; the rest of the crew thought themſelves happy in being on board, he alone unhappy, that he was not within reach of the deſtroyer. Fired at the light, and vowing that he would make the devourer diſgorge, or be ſwallowed himſelf in the ſame grave, he plunges into the deep, armed with a ſharp-pointed knife. The ſhark no ſooner ſaw him, but he made furiouſly toward him ; both equally eager, the one of his prey, the other of revenge. The moment the ſhark opened his rapacious jaws, his adverſary dexterouſly diving, and graſping him with his left hand ſomewhat below the upper fins, ſucceſsfully employed his knife in his right hand, giving him repeated ſtabs in the belly ; the enraged ſhark, after many unavailing efforts, finding himſelf overmatched in his own element, endeavoured to diſengage himſelf, ſometimes plunging to the bottom, then mad with pain, rearing his uncouth form, now ſtained with his own streaming blood, above the foaming waves. The crews of the ſurrounding veſſels ſaw the unequal combat, uncertain from which of the combatants the ſtreams of blood iſſued ; till at length the ſhark, much weakened by the loss of blood, made toward the ſhore, and with him his conqueror ; who, fluffed with an aſſurance of victory, pushed his foe with redoubled ardour, and, by the help of an ebbing tide, dragged him on ſhore, ripped up his bowels, and united and buried the severed carcase of his friend ”</p><p>“ It is evident (says Dr Moſeley, to whoſe valuable work we are indebted for the ſtory of the American related above), that digeſtion in theſe animals is not performed by trituration, nor by the muſcular action of the ſtomach ; though nature has furniſhed them with a ſtomach of wonderful force and thickneſs, and far exceeding that of any other creature. Whatever their force of digeſtion is, it has no effect upon their young ones, which always retreat into their ſtomachs in time of danger.</p><p>“ That digeſtion is not performed by heat in fiſh, is equally evident. Being on the Banks of Newfoundland in Auguſt 1782, I opened many cod-fiſh, and ripped up their ſtomachs juſt as they came alive out of the water ; in which were generally found ſmall oystiers, muſcles, cockles, and crabs, as well as ſmall fiſhes of their own and other ſpecies. The coldneſs oſ the ſtomach of theſe fiſhes is far greater than the temperature of the water out of which they are taken ; or of any other part of the fiſh, or of any other ſubſtance of animated nature I ever felt. On wrapping one of them round my hand, immediately on being taken out of the fiſh, it cauſed ſo much aching and numbneſs that I could not endure it long.”</p><p>SQUAMARIA, in botany. See LATHRÆA.</p><p>SQUAMOUS, in anatomy, a name given to the ſpurious or false sutures of the ſkull, becauſe compoſed of ſquamae, or ſcales like thoſe of ſiſhes.</p><p>SQUARE, in geometry, a quadrilateral figure both equilateral and equiangular. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Geometry.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">SQUA</hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps">re-</hi><hi rend="italic">Root.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Algebra,</hi> Part I. Chap. iv. and <hi rend="smallcaps">Arithmetic,</hi> n⁰ 33. and 34.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Hollow SQUARE,</hi> in the military art, a body of foot drawn up with an empty ſpace in the middle, for the colours, drums, and baggage, faced and covered by the pikes every way, to keep off the horſe.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Square,</hi> among mechanics, an inſtrument conſiſting of two rules or branches, faſtened perpendicularly at one end of their extremities, so as to form a right angle. It is of great use in the description and menſuration of right angles, and laying down perpendiculars.</p><p><hi rend="italic">SQUA</hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps">re-</hi><hi rend="italic">Rigged,</hi> an epithet applied to a ſhip whoſe yards are very long. It is alſo uſed in contradiſtinction to all veſſels whoſe sails are extended by ſtays or lateen-yards, or by booms and gaffs ; the usual situation of which is nearly in the plane of the keel ; and hence,</p><p><hi rend="italic">SQUARE-Sail,</hi> is a ſail extended to a yard which hangs parallel to the horizon, as diſtinguished from the other sails which are extended by booms and ſtays placed obliquely. This ſail is only uſed in fair winds, or to ſcud under in a tempeſt. In the former caſe, it is furniſhed with a large additional part called the <hi rend="italic">bonnet,</hi> which is then attached to its bottom, and removed when it is neceſſary to <hi rend="smallcaps">scud.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Scudding.</hi></p><p>SQUATINA. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Squalus.</hi></p><p>SQUILL, in botany. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Scilla.</hi></p><p>SQUILLA, the name of a ſpecies of cancer. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Cancer.</hi></p><p>SQUINTING. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Medicine;</hi> n⁰ 383. SQUIRREL, in zoology. See <hi rend="smallcaps">ScIurus. </hi>STABBING, in law. The offence of mortally ſtabbing another, though done upon ſudden provocation, is puniſhed as murder ; the benefit of clergy being taken away from it b ſtatute. (See <hi rend="smallcaps">Murder). </hi>For by Ja. I. c. 8. when one thruſts or ſtabs another, not then having a weapon drawn, or who hath not then firſt ſtricken the party ſtabbing, to that he dies thereof within six months after, the offender ſhall not have the benefit of clergy, though he did it not of malice aforethought. This ſtatute was made on account of the frequent quarrels and ſtabbings with ſhort daggers between the Scotch and the Engliſh, at the ac-</p></body></text></TEI>