<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-04-20T21:23:07Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ate. He told his treaſurer one day to put a certain officer on his list, to whom he was very much attached : “ In what quality (ſaid the treaſurer) ſhall I mark him down ?” “ As my friend” (replied the monarch.) A young painter conceiving hopes of making his fortune if his talents were made known to Staniſlaus, preſented him with a picture, which the courtiers criticiſed ſeverely. The prince praiſed the performance, and paid the painter very generouſly : then turning to his courtiers, he ſaid, “ Do ye not ſee, gentlemen, that this poor man muſt provide for his family by his abilities ? if you diſcourage him by your cenſures, he is undone. We ought always to aſſiſt men; we never gain any thing by hurting them.” His revenues were ſmall; but were we to judge of him by what he did, we ſhould probably reckon him the richeſt potentate in Europe. A ſingle inſtance will be ſufficient to ſhow the well judged economy with which his benevolent plans were conducted. He gave 18,000 crowns to the magiſtrates of Bar to be employed in purchaſing grain, when at a low price, to be sold out again to the poor at a moderate rate when the price ſhould riſe above a certain ſum. By this arrangement (ſay the authors of <hi rend="italic">Dictionaire Historique), </hi>the money increaſes continually, and its good effects may in a ſhort time be extended over the whole province.</p><p>He was a protector of the arts and ſciences ;he wrote ſeveral works of philoſophy, politics, and morality, which were collected and publiſhed in France in 1765, in 4 vols, 8vo. under the title of <hi rend="italic">Oeuvres du Philoſophe Bienfaisant,</hi> “the works of the Benevolent Philosopher.” STANITZAS, villages or ſmall diſtricts of the banks of the Don, inhabited by Cossacs.</p><p>STANLEY (Thomas), a very learned Engliſh writer in the 17th century, was the son of Sir Thomas Stanley of Cumberlow-Green in Herefordſhire, knight. He was born at Cumberlow about 1644, and educated in his father’s houſe, whence he removed to the university of Cambridge. He afterwards travelled ; and, upon his return to England, proſecuted his ſtudies in the Middle Temple. He married, when young, Dorothy, the eldeſt daughter of Sir James Engan of Flower, in Northamptonſhire. He wrote, 1. A volume of Poems. 2. Hiſtory of Philoſophy, and Lives of the Philosophers. 3. A Tranſlation of Eſchylus, with a Commentary ; and ſeveral other works. He died in 1678.</p><p>STANNARIES, the mines and works where tin is dug and purified ; as in Cornwall, Devonſhire, &amp;c.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">STANNARY courts,</hi> in Devonſhire and Cornwall, for the adminiſtration of juſtice among the tinners therein. They are held before the lord-warden and his ſubſtitutes, in virtue of a privilege granted to the workers in the tin-mines there, to ſue and be ſued only in their own courts, that they may not be drawn from their busineſs, which is highly profitable to the public, by attending their law-suits in other courts. The privileges of the tinners are confirmed by a charter, 33 Edw. I. and fully expounded by a private ſtatute, 50 Edw. III. which has since been explained by a public act, <hi rend="italic">16</hi> Car. I. c. 15.@@ What relates to our preſent purpoſe is only this : That all tinners and labourers in and about the ſtannaries ſhall, during the time of their working therein, <hi rend="italic">bona fide,</hi> be privileged from suits of other courts, and be only pleaded in the ſtannary court in all matters, excepting pleas of land, life, and member. No writ of error lies from hence to any court in Weſtminſter-hall ; as was agreed by all the judges, in 4 Jac. I. But an appeal lies from the ſteward of the court to the under-warden ; and from him to the lord-warden ; and thence to the privy-council of the prince of Wales, as duke of Cornwall, when he hath had livery or inveſtiture of the ſame. And from thence the appeal lies to the king himſelf, in the last resort.</p><p>STANNUM, <hi rend="smallcaps">tin.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Chemistry-Index,</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Tin.</hi></p><p>STANZA, in poetry, a number of lines regularly adjuſted to each other; so much of a poem as contains every variation of measure or relation of rhyme uſed in that poem.</p><p>STAPHYLEA, <hi rend="smallcaps">Bladder-nut,</hi> in botany: A genus of plants belonging to the claſs of <hi rend="italic">pentandria,</hi> and order of <hi rend="italic">trigynia;</hi> and in the natural ſyſtem arranged under the 23d order, <hi rend="italic">trihilatae.</hi> The calyx is quinquepartite. There are five petals. The capſules are three, inflated and joined together by a longitudinal future. The ſeeds are two, and are globoſe with a ſcar. There are two ſpecies, the pinnata and trifolia. The <hi rend="italic">pinnata, </hi>or bladder-nut-tree, is a tall ſhrub or tree. The leaves are pinnated ; the pinnæ are generally five, oblong, pointed, and notched round the edges. The flowers are white, and grow in whirls on long pendulous footstalks. This plant flowers in June, and is frequent in hedges about Pontefract and in Kent. The <hi rend="italic">trifοlia,</hi> or threeleaved bladder-nut, is a native of Virginia.</p><p>STAPHYLINUS, a genus of animals belonging to the claſs of insectae<hi rend="italic">,</hi> and order of <hi rend="italic">coleοptera.</hi> The antennæ are moniliform ; the feelers four in number ; the elytra are not above half the length of the abdomen ; the wings are folded up and concealed under the elytra; the tail or extremity of the abdomen is single, is provided with two long vesicles which the insect can ſhoot out or draw back at pleaſure. Gmelin enumerates 117 ſpecies, of which five only are natives of Great Britain ; the murinus, maxilloſus, rufus, riparius, chryſomelinus.</p><p>1.	<hi rend="italic">Murinus.</hi> The head is depreſſed. The colour is grey, clouded with black. The length is six lines. It lives among horſe-dung. 2. The <hi rend="italic">maxillοsus</hi> is black, with aſh-coloured ſtripes, and jaws as long as the head. It inhabits the woods. 3. <hi rend="italic">Rufus</hi> is of an orange-colour ; but the poſterior part of the elytra and abdomen is black, as are alſo the thighs at their baſe. 4. <hi rend="italic">Riparius </hi>is of a reddiſh brown colour ; but the elytra are azurecoloured ; and the head, antennæ, and two laſt rings of the abdomen, are black. It is frequent on the banks of rivers in Europe. 5. <hi rend="italic">Chrysomelinus</hi> is black ; the thorax, elytra, and feet being teſtaceous. It is found in the north of Europe.</p><p>The infects have a peculiarity to be met with in almoſt every ſpecies of this genus, which is, that they frequently turn up their tail, or extremity of the abdomen, eſpecially if you chance to touch them ; in which, caſe the tail is ſeen to riſe immediately, as if the infect meant to defend itſelf by stinging. Yet that is not the place where the inſect’s offensive weapons are situated.@@ Its tail has no sting, but in recompenſe it bites and pinches ſtrongly with its jaws ; and care muſt be taken, especially in laying hold of the larger ſpecies. Their jaws are ſtrong, ſhoot out beyond the head, and are subſervient to the animal in ſeizing and deſtroying</p><p>@@@[mu] Blackstone's Comment. vol. iii. p. 79 and 80.</p><p>@@@[mu]Barbut's Genera Insectorum.</p></body></text></TEI>