<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-04-20T21:26:42Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p><hi rend="italic">Artificial </hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Stone.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Stucco.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Elastic </hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Stone.</hi> See <hi rend="italic">Elastic </hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Marble.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Philosopher's </hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Stone.</hi> See PHILOSOPHER'S <hi rend="italic smallcaps">Stone. </hi><hi rend="italic">Precious </hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Stones.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Gem.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Rocking </hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Stone,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Logan,</hi> a ſtone of a prodigious ſize, ſo exactly poiſed, that it would rock or shake with the ſmalleſt force. Of theſe ſtones the ancients give us ſome account. Pliny says, that at Harpaſa, a town of Asia, there was a rock of ſuch a wonderful nature, that if touched with the finger it would ſhake, but could not be moved from its place with the whole force of the body@@*. Ptolemy Hepheſtion mentions @@* a gygonian ſtone near the ocean, which was agitated when (truck by the (talk of an aſphodel. but could not be removed by a great exertion of force. The word <hi rend="italic">gygonius</hi> ſeems to be Celtic ; for <hi rend="italic">gwingog</hi> ſignifies <hi rend="italic">motitans,</hi> the rocking- ſtone.</p><p>Many rocking ſtones ate to be found in different parts of this iſland ; ſome natural, others artificial, or placed in their poſition by human art. In the pariſh of St Leven, Cornwall, there is a promontory called <hi rend="italic">Caſtle Treryn.</hi> On the western side of the middle group, near the top, lies a very large ſtone, ſo evenly poiſed that any hand may move it from one side to another ; yet it is ſo fixed on its baſe, that no lever nor any mechanical force can remove it from its preſent ſituation. It is called the <hi rend="italic">Lοgan-stone,</hi> and is at ſuch a height from the ground that no perſon can believe that it was raiſed to its preſent poſition by art. But there are other rocking ſtones, which are ſo ſhaped and ſo ſituated, that there can be no doubt but they were erected by human ſtrength. Of this kind Borlaſe thinks the great Quoit or <hi rend="italic">Kam-lehau,</hi> in the pariſh of Tywidnek, to be. It is 39 feet in circumference, and four feet thick at a medium, and ſtands on a single pedeſtal. There is alſo a remarkable ſtone of the same kind in the iſland of St Agnes in Scilly. The under rock A is 10 feet 6 inches high, 47 feet round the middle, and touches the ground with no more than half its baſe. The upper rock C reſts on one point only, and is ſo nicely balanced, that two or three men with a pole can move it. It is eight feet six inches high, and 47 in circumference. On the top there is a baſon D hollowed out, three feet eleven inches in diameter at a medium, but wider at the brim, and three feet deep. From the globular ſhape of this upper ſtone, it is highly probable that it was rounded by human art, and perhaps even placed on its pedeſtal by human ſtrength. In Sithney pariſh, near Helston, in Cornwall, flood the famous logan, or rocking ſtone, commonly called <hi rend="italic">Men Amber,</hi> q. d. <hi rend="italic">Men an Bar, </hi>or the <hi rend="italic">top-stone.</hi> It was eleven feet by six and four high, and ſo nicely poiſed on another ſtone that a little child could move it, and all travellers who came this way deſired to ſee it. But Shrubſall, Cromwell’s governor of Pendennis, with much ado cauſed it to be undermined, to the great grief of the country. There are ſome marks of the tool on it, and, by its quadrangular ſhape, it was probably dedicated to Mercury.</p><p>That the rocking ſtones are monuments  erected by the Druids cannot be doubted ; but tradition has not informed us for what purpoſe they were intended. Mr Toland thinks that the Druids made the people believe that they alone could move them, and that by a miracle ; and that by this pretended miracle they condemned or acquitted the accuſcd, and brought criminals to confeſs what could not otherwiſe be extorted from them. How far this conjecture is right we ſhall leave to thoſe who are deeply verſed in the knowledge of antiquities to determine.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Sonorous </hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Stone,</hi> a kind oſ ſtone remarkable for emitting an agreeable found when ſtruck, and much uſed in China for making musical inſtruments which they call king.</p><p>The various kinds of ſonorous ſtones known in China differ conſiderably from one another in beauty, and in the ſtrength and duration of their tone ; and what is very ſurpriſing, is, that this difference cannot be diſcovered either by the different degrees of their hardneſs, weight, or fineneſs of grain, or by any other qualities which might be ſuppoſed to determine it. Some ſtones are found remarkably hard, which are very ſonorous ; and others exceedingly ſoft, which have an excellent tone ; ſome extremely heavy emit a very ſweet ſound ; and there are others as light as pumice- ſtone which have alſo an agreeable ſound.</p><p>The chemiſts and naturaliſts of Europe have never yet attempted to diſcover, whether ſome of our ſtones may not have the same properties as the ſonorous ſtones of the extremities of Aſia. It however appears, that the Romans were formerly acquainted with a ſonorous ſtone of the claſs of <hi rend="italic">hiang-che.</hi> Pliny (says the Abbé du Bos, in his Reflections on Poetry and Painting, when ſpeaking of curious ſtones) obſerves that the ſtone called <hi rend="italic">chalcοphοnas,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">brazen ſound,</hi> is black ; and that, according to the etymology of its name, it sends forth a ſound much reſembling that of braſs when it is ſtruck. The paſſage of Pliny is as follows : <hi rend="italic">Chalcophonas nigra est ; sed elisa aeris tinnitum reddit.</hi></p><p>Some ſonorous ſtones were at length ſent into France, and the late Duke de Chaulnes examined them with particular attention. The following are ſome of his observations : “The Academy of Sciences, Mr Rome de Liſle, and ſeveral other learned mineralogiſts, when aſked if they were acquainted with the black ſtone of which the Chineſe king was made, for anſwer cited the paſſage of Pliny mentioned by Boethius de Bott, Linnaeus, and in the Dictionary of Bomare, and added what Mr Anderſon ſays in his Natural Hiſtory of Iceland reſpecting a bluiſh kind of ſtone which is very ſonorous. As the black ſtone of the Chineſe becomes of a bluiſh colour when filed, it is probably of the ſame species. None of the reſt who were conſulted had ever ſeen it. The Chineſe ſtone has a great reſemblance at first tight to black marble, and like it is calcareous ; but marble generally is not ſonorous. It alſo externally reſembles touchſtone, which is a kind of baſaltes, and the baſaltes found near volcanos ; but theſe two ſtones are vitrifications.”</p><p>The duke next endeavoured to procure ſome information from the ſtone-cutters. They all replied, that blue-coloured marble was very ſonorous, and that they had ſeen large blocks of it which emitted a very ſtrong ſound; but the duke having ordered a king to be conſtructed of this kind of ſtone, it was found that it did not poſſeſs that property. By trying the black marble of Flanders, a piece was at length found which emitted an agreeable ſound : it was cut into a king, which is almoſt as ſonorous as thoſe of China. All theſe obſerva-</p>
<p>@@@[m]<gap/>Lib. ii. <gap/></p>
    <p>@@@[m]<gap/>Lib. iii. <gap/></p>
</body></text></TEI>