<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>translated from HTML to TEI</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Even more ominous of coming danger was the extent to which the European’half of the empire was becoming barbarized.</p><p>The policy which had been inaugurated by Augustus himself of settling barbarians within the frontiers had been taken up on a larger scale and in a more systematic way by the Illyrian emperors of the 3rd century, and was continued by their successors in the 4th. In Gaul, in the provinces south of the Danube, even in Macedon and Italy, large barbarian settlements had been made —Theodosius in particular distinguishing himself by his liberality in this respect. Nor did the barbarians admitted during the 4th century merely swell the class of half-servile <hi rend="italic">coloni.</hi>  On the contrary, they not only constituted to an increasing extent the strength of the imperial forces, but won their way in ever-growing numbers to posts of dignity and importance in the imperial service. Under Constantine the palace was crowded with Franks.@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi>  Julian led Gothic troops against Persia, and the army with which Theodosius defeated the tyrant Maximus (388) contained large numbers of Huns and Alans, as well as of Goths. The names of Arbogast, Stilicho and Rufinus are sufficient proof of the place held by barbarians near the emperor’s person and in the control of the provinces and legions of Rome; and the relations of Arbogast to his nominee for the purple, Eugenius, were an anticipation of those which existed between Ricimer and the emperors of the latter half</p><p>of the 5 th century.</p><p>It was by barbarians already settled within the empire that the first of the series of attacks which finally separated the western provinces from the empire and set up a barbaric ruler in Italy were made, and it was in men of barbarian birth that Rome found her ablest and most successful defenders. The Visigoths whom Alaric led into Italy had been settled south of the Danube as the allies of the empire since the accession of Theodosius. But, like the Germans of the days of Caesar, they wanted land for their own, and Alaric himself aspired to raise himself to the heights which had been reached before him by the Vandal Stilicho at Ravenna and the Goth Rufinus at Constantinople. The jealousy which existed between the rulers of the western and eastern empires furthered his plans. In the name of Arcadius, the emperor of the east, or at least with the connivance of Arcadius’s minister Rufinus, he occupied the province of Illyricum, and from thence ravaged Greece, which, according to the existing division of provinces, belonged to the western empire. Thence in 396 he retreated before Stilicho to Illyricum, with the command of which he was now formally invested by Arcadius; he thus gained a base of operations against Italy.@@<hi rend="sup">2</hi> In 400 he led his people, with their wives and families, their wagons and treasure, to seek lands for themselves south of the Alps. But in this first invasion he penetrated no farther than the plains of Lombardy, and after the desperate battle of Pollentia (402 or 403) he slowly withdrew from Italy, his retreat being hastened by the promises of gold freely made to him by the imperial government. Not until the autumn of 408 did Alaric again cross the Alps. Stilicho was dead; the barbarian troops in Honorius’s service had been provoked into joining Alaric by the anti-Teutonic policy of Honorius and his ministers, and Alaric marched .unopposed to Rome. The payment of a heavy ransom, however, saved the city. Negotiations followed between Alaric and the court of Ravenna. Alaric’s demands were moderate, but Honorius would grant neither lands for his people nor the honourable post in the imperial service which he asked for himself. Once more Alaric sat down before Rome, and the citizens were forced to agree to his terms. Attalus, a Greek, the prefect of the city, was declared Augustus, and Alaric accepted the post of commander-in-chief. But after a few months Alaric formally deposed Attalus, on account of his incapacity, and renewed his offers to Honorius. Again they were declined,</p><lb/><p>and Alaric marched to the siege and sack of Rome (410).@@<hi rend="sup">3</hi> His death followed hard on his capture of Rome. Two years later (412) his successor Ataulf led the Visigoths to find in Gaul the lands which Alaric had sought in Italy. It is characteristic of the anarchical condition of the west that Ataulf and his Goths should have fought for Honorius in Gaul against the tyrants@@<hi rend="sup">4</hi> and in Spain against the Vandals, Suebi and Alani; and it was with the consent of Honorius that in 419 Wallia, who had followed Ataulf as king of the Visigoths, finally settled with his people in south-western Gaul and founded the Visigothic monarchy.@@<hi rend="sup">5</hi></p><p>It was about the same period that the accomplished fact of the division of Spain between the three barbarian tribes of Vandals, Suebi and Alani was in a similar manner recognized by the paramount authority of the emperor of the west.@@<hi rend="sup">6</hi> These peoples had crossed the Rhine at the time when Alaric was making his first attempt on Italy. A portion of the host led by Radagaisus@@<hi rend="sup">7 </hi>actually invaded Italy, but was cut to pieces by Stilicho near Florence (405); the rest pressed on through Gaul, crossed the Pyrenees, and entered the as yet untouched province of Spain.</p><p>Honorius died in 423. With the single exception of Britain@@<hi rend="sup">8</hi> no province had yet formally broken loose from the empire. But over a great part of the west the authority of the emperors was now little more than nominal; throughout the major part of Gaul and in Spain the barbarians had settled, and barbarian states were. growing up which recognized the supremacy of the emperor, but were in all essentials independent of his control.</p><p>The long reign of Valentiman III. (423-55) is marked by two events of first-rate importance—the conquest of Africa by the Vandals @@<hi rend="sup">9</hi> and the invasion of Gaul and Italy by Attila. The Vandal settlement in Africa was closely akin in its origin and results to those of the Visigoths and of the Vandals themselves in Gaul and Spain. Here, as there, the occasion was given by the jealous quarrels of powerful imperial ministers.</p><p>The feud between Boniface, count of Africa, and Aetius, the “ master-general ” or “ count of Italy,” opened the way to Africa for the Vandal king Gaiseric (Genseric), as that between Stilicho and Rufinus had before set Alaric in motion westward, and as the quarrel between the tyrant Constantine and the ministers of Honorius had paved the way for the Vandals, Suebes and Alans into Spain. In this case, too, land-hunger was the impelb'ng motive with the barbarian invader, and in Africa, as in Gaul and Spain, the invaders’ acquisitions were confirmed by the imperial authority which they still professed to recognize. In 429 Gaiseric, king of the Vandals, crossed with his warriors, their families and goods, to the province of Africa, hitherto almost untouched by the ravages of war. Thanks to the quarrels of Boniface and Aetius, their task was an easy one. The province was quickly overrun. In 435 @@<hi rend="sup">10</hi> a formal treaty secured them in the possession of a large portion of the rich lands which were the granary of Rome, in exchange for a payment probably of corn and oil. Carthage was taken in 439, and by 440 the Vandal kingdom was firmly established.</p><lb/><p>@@@    Amm. Marc. xv. 5.</p><p>@@@    Hodgkin<hi rend="italic">op. cit.</hi>  1. 66i.</p><lb/><p>@@@    For the treatment of Rome by Alaric, see Hodgkin i. 798; Gibbon iii. 321 sqq.; Ranke iv. 246. Allowance must be made for the exaggerations of the ecclesiastical writers.</p><p>@@@    For these tyrants, see Freeman in the<hi rend="italic">Eng. Hist. Rev.</hi>  i. 53-86.</p><p>@@@    The capital of the new state was Tolosa (Toulouse).</p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">6 </hi>Jung,<hi rend="italic">Die Romanischen Landschaften, 73</hi>  seq.</p><p>@@@    For the connexion between his movement and those of Alaric and of the Vandals, see Hodgkin i. 711; Gibbon iii. 262 seq.</p><p>@@@ The Roman troops were withdrawn from Britain by Constantine in 407; Mommsen,<hi rend="italic">Chron. min.</hi>  i. 465.</p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">9 </hi>Hodgkin vol. ii. bk. iii. chap. ii.; Gibbon ii. 400 saq.; Jung, 183. The leading ancient authority is Procopius. See Ranke iv. (2) 285; Papencordt,<hi rend="italic">Gesch. d. Vandal. Herrschaft in Africa.</hi></p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">10 </hi>Prosper 659; Ranke iv. (l) 282.</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>