<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>translated from HTML to TEI</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>limitation, and in many the deduction of new doctrines from the actual <hi rend="italic">jus scriptum,</hi>  and their development and exposition. An event that did much to diminish the influence of the pontiffs in connexion with it was the divulgcment in the year 304 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.,</hi>  as already mentioned, by Cn. Flavius, of a formulary of actions and a calendar of lawful and unlawful days, which got the name of <hi rend="italic">Jus Flavianum. </hi>The practice adopted in the beginning of the 6th century by Tiberius Cornneanius, the first plebeian chief pontiff, of giving advice in law in public had a still greater effect in popularizing it; and the <hi rend="italic">Tripertita</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">Jus Aelianum,</hi>  some fifty years later—a collection that included the Tables, the <hi rend="italic">interpretatio</hi>  and the current styles of actions—made it as much the heritage of the laity as of the pontifical college.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Subsequent Legislation.—</hi>Of legislation during the 4th and 5th centuries that affected the private law we have but scanty record. Tbc best-known enactments are the Canuleian law of 445 b.c. above mentioned; the Genucian, Marcian and other laws about usury and the rate of interest; the Poetilian law of 326 b.c. abolishing imprisonment of nexal debtors by their creditors; the Silian law, probably not long afterwards, which introduced a new form of process for actions of debt; and the Aquilian law about 287 b.c., which amended the decern viral provisions for actions of damages for culpable injury to property, and continued to</p><p>regulate the law on the subject even in the books of Justinian.</p><p>iii. <hi rend="italic">Development of the Substantive Institutions of the Law.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">The Citizen and his “ Caput.”—</hi>The early law of Rome was essentially personal, not territorial. A man enjoyed the benefit of its institutions and of its protection, not because he happened to be within Roman territory, but because he was a citizen,—one of those by whom and for whom its law was established. The theory of the early</p><p>Romans was that a man sojourning within the bounds of a foreign state was at the mercy of the latter and its citizens, that he himself might be dealt with as a slave, and all that belonged to him appropriated by the first comer; for he was outside the pale of the law. Without some sort of alliance with Rome a stranger had no right to claim protection against maltreatment of his person or attempt to deprive him of his property; and even then, unless he belonged to a state entitled by treaty to the international judicial remedy of <hi rend="italic">recuperatio, </hi>it was by an appeal to the good offices of the supreme magistrate, or through the intervention of a citizen to whom he was allied by the (frequently hereditary) bond of <hi rend="italic">hospitium,</hi>  and not by means of any action of the <hi rend="italic">jus civile</hi>  set in motion by himself. A non-citizen—originally <hi rend="italic">hostis,</hi>  and afterwards usually called <hi rend="italic">peregrinus</hi>@@<hi rend="italic"/>in time came to be regarded as entitled to all the rights recognized by so-called jmj <hi rend="italic">gentium</hi>  as belonging to a freeman, and to take part as freely as a Roman in any transaction of the <hi rend="italic">jus gcntium\</hi>  but that was not until Rome, through contact with other nations and the growth of trade and commerce, had found it necessary to modify her jurisprudence by the adoption of many new institutions of a more liberal and less exclusive character than those of the <hi rend="italic">jus civile.</hi></p><p>A citizen’s civil personality was technically his <hi rend="italic">caput.</hi>  The extent of it depended on his family status. It was only among citizens that the supremacy of the <hi rend="italic">paterfamilias</hi>  and the subjection of those <hi rend="italic">in manu, potestate</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">mancipio</hi>  were recognized—only among them therefore that the position of an individual in the family was of moment. While in public life a man’s supremacy or subjection in the family was immaterial, in private life it was the <hi rend="italic">paterfamilias</hi>  alone who enjoyed full jural capacity. Those subject to him had a more limited personality; and, so far as capacity to take part in transactions of the <hi rend="italic">jus civile</hi>  was concerned, it was not inherent in them but derived from their <hi rend="italic">paterfamilias*,</hi>  they were the agents of his</p><lb/><p>will, representatives of his <hi rend="italic">persona</hi>  in every act whereby a right was acquired by them for the family to which they belonged.</p><p>Whenever a citizen cither ceased altogether to be a member of a Roman family or passed, either permanently or temporarily, into subjection to some <hi rend="italic">paterfamilias</hi>  outside his own family,@@  there was technically<hi rend="italic">capitis minutio</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">deminutio.</hi>  To harmonize with the gradually established conception of jural personality in non-citizens, and perhaps  also from their partiality for tripartite divisions, the jurists about the end of the Republic divided <hi rend="italic">capitis deminutio</hi>  into three degrees, viz. <hi rend="italic">maxima, media</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">minima—</hi>a division unknown to lawyers of an earlier period when <hi rend="italic">civitas</hi>  was theoretically identified with <hi rend="italic">libcrlas.</hi>  When a citizen forfeited his freedom, his <hi rend="italic">capitis deminutio</hi>  was said to be <hi rend="italic">maxima}</hi>  he lost all capacity, whether under the <hi rend="italic">jus civile</hi>  or the <hi rend="italic">jus gentium.</hi>  When, retaining freedom, he went into exile or joined a Latin colony, or otherwise became a peregrin, the loss <hi rend="italic">{deminutio}</hi><hi rend="bold">  of </hi>his capacity was only <hi rend="italic">media</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">minor}</hi>  it was his rights and privileges under the <hi rend="italic">jus civile</hi>  that alone were affected. When both freedom and citizenship remained, and there was produced merely the severance of connexion with a particular family <hi rend="italic">(familiae mulatto},</hi>  the loss was said to be <hi rend="italic">minima.</hi>  Illustrations of <hi rend="italic">c. d. minima</hi>  present themselves in the case of a <hi rend="italic">paterfamilias</hi>  becoming <hi rend="italic">filiusfamilias</hi>  by adrogation, or a <hi rend="italic">materfamilias</hi>  passing into the hand of a husband by confarreation or coemption; in both cases he or she who had been <hi rend="italic">sui juris</hi>  thereby became <hi rend="italic">alieni juris.</hi>  It was immaterial whether thechange was from a higher family position to a lower, or from a lower to a higher,@@ or to the same position in the new family that had been held in the old—as when a<hi rend="italic">filiusfamilias</hi>  was transferred by his father into the <hi rend="italic">potestas</hi>  of an adopter, or when the <hi rend="italic">filiifamilias</hi>  of a person giving himself in adrogation passed with him into the <hi rend="italic">potestas</hi>  of the adrogator: in every case there was <hi rend="italic">capitis minutio.</hi>  It was not the change of family position that caused it, but the subjection to a new <hi rend="italic">potestas.</hi>  Thus the civil personality of Titius while a <hi rend="italic">filiusfamilias</hi>  in the <hi rend="italic">potestas</hi>  of Sempronius, <hi rend="italic">e.g.</hi>  the expectancy of succession, the agnatic relationships, the derivative capacity for being a party to a mancipation or a <hi rend="italic">sponsio</hi>  that resulted from the relationship, all came to an end through the subjection to a new <hi rend="italic">paterfamilias,</hi>  temporary or permanent. He might acquire another and independent capacity on becoming 53/i <hi rend="italic">juris</hi>  by emancipation, or another derivative capacity on passing into the <hi rend="italic">potestas</hi>  of Maevius by adoption; but while subject to a new <hi rend="italic">paterfamilias</hi>  his old personality <hi rend="italic">quoad civilia</hi>  was extinguished. This is what some of the jurists mean when they say that <hi rend="italic">capitis deminutio was. </hi>civil death.@@</p><p>An important consequence of <hi rend="italic">minima capitis deminutio</hi>  was that it not only extinguished <hi rend="italic">patria potestas</hi>  where it existed, but severed the bond of agnation between the <hi rend="italic">capite minntus </hi>and all those who had previously been related to him as agnates. There was no longer any right of succession between them on intestacy; their reciprocal prospective rights of tutory were defeated, and the <hi rend="italic">minutio</hi>  of either tutor or ward put an end to a subsisting guardianship, assuming always that it was a <hi rend="italic">tutcla legitima</hi>  or agnatic <hi rend="italic">cura furiosi.</hi>  Very remarkable, yet quite logical, was the doctrine that the <hi rend="italic">minutio</hi>  extinguished the claims of creditors of the <hi rend="italic">minntus}</hi>  their debtor, the person with whom they had contracted, was civilly dead, and dead without an heir, and therefore there was no one against whom an action of the/ms <hi rend="italic">civile</hi>  could be directed in order to enforce payment. But equity eventually provided a remedy, by</p><lb/><p>@@@Neither " alien ” nor “ foreigner ” is an adequate rendering of<hi rend="italic">peregrinus.</hi>  For <hi rend="italic">peregrini</hi>  included not only citizens of other states, independent or dependent, but also ¿7r6Xi5«,—men who could not call themselves citizens <hi rend="italic">{cives)</hi>  at all, as, for example, the <hi rend="italic">dediticii</hi>  whom Rome had vanquished and whose civic organization she had destroyed, offenders sent into banishment, &amp;c., and also, until Caracalla's general grant of the franchise, the greater portion of her provincial subjects.</p><lb/><p>@@@This is Mommsen’s theory.. Sec<hi rend="italic">Staatsrccht,</hi>  iii. 1. p. 8.</p><p>@@@Children who became<hi rend="italic">sui juris</hi>  by their parent’s death, as they came under no new <hi rend="italic">potestas,</hi>  were not regarded as <hi rend="italic">capite minuti.</hi></p><p>@@@Owing to the ill-defined views among the Roman jurists themselves regarding the nature of<hi rend="italic">cap. dem.</hi>  various theories more or less divergent have been maintained about it by modern writers, of none of which can it be said that it has been generally accepted. Mommsen's theory, above adopted, seems to present fewest difficulties. Sec the subject discussed and authorities cited by Goudy in 2nd edition of Muirhead’s <hi rend="italic">Historical Introduction,</hi>  pp. 422-27.</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>