<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>translated from HTML to TEI</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>those who were to enjoy in future the privileges of quiritarian right, —and
                multiplying the sources of future disputes that would have to be determined by the
                tribunals. The nature of thd jurisdiction created by him, if any, to meet the new
                aspect of things is much controverted. He has been credited with the institution of
                the collegiate courts of the <hi rend="italic">Centumviri</hi> and the <hi
                    rend="italic">Decemviri (stlitibus judicandis)</hi> as well as the private judge
                    <hi rend="italic">(unus judex),</hi> but the arguments in support of this view
                are not strong, and arc, of course, based wholly on presumptions. However, it will
                be convenient to say a few words about each of these courts here.</p>
            <p>The centumviral court@@ is often referred to by Cicero, and the range of its
                jurisdiction in his time seems to have included every possible question of<hi
                    rend="italic">manus</hi> in the old sense of the word— status of individuals,
                property and its casements, and inheritance whether testate or intestate. By. the
                time of Gaius the only matters apparently that were in practice brought before it
                were questions of inheritance by the <hi rend="italic">jus civile, </hi>though
                theoretically it was still competent in all real actions., and the lance, the emblem
                of quiritarian right generally, was still its ensign. During the later Republic the
                    <hi rend="italic">Centumviri</hi> formed a quasi-corporate body of private
                judges selected originally from the tribes (afterwards from the ordinary list of <hi
                    rend="italic">judices)</hi> annually by the urban</p>
            <p>praetors.@@ Some writers identify the centumviral court with the omulian senate of
                ioo; others attribute its institution to Servius Tullius and hold that it was a
                plebeian court at first; others make it contemporaneous with the All. Tables; others
                bring it down to the 6th century of the city; while the weight of recent
                authority is in favour of the view that it is not earlier than the beginning of the
                7th century.. The arguments in support of these several views cannot be gone into
                here. It is enough to say that we have no positive proof of its existence earlier
                than the 7th century, though presumptions are in favour of its having been somewhat
                earlier. In the exercise of their office the<hi rend="italic">Centumviri</hi> acted
                more independently than private judices ventured to do, and even introduced some
                considerable reforms into the law.</p>
            <p>There was a court at Rome during the Republic called the <hi rend="italic">Decemviri
                    stlitibus judicandis.</hi>@@<hi rend="italic"/> These decemvirs in historic
                times constituted a quasi-corporate body of judicial magistrates, whose duty it was
                to try certain kinds of actions, especially those relating to personal liberty.
                During the Princi-pate, while ceasing to. act as a separate court, they presided
                over the divisions into which the centumviral court had been under Augustus divided.
                Their origin is quite unknown. Pom-poni.us indeed says that they were originally
                created soon after the institution of the peregrin praetorship in 242 <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi> for this very purpose of presiding over centumviral
                cases,@@ but this statement is generally discredited and, if true, their practice of
                so presiding must quickly have gone into disuse. Those writers who attempt to trace
                back the centumvirs to the regal period give, as a rule, a like antiquity to the<hi
                    rend="italic">Decemviri stlitibus judicandis.</hi> On the other hand, some
                authorities identify them with the <hi rend="italic">decemviri
                judices </hi>mentioned by Livy@@ as having been declared by the<hi rend="italic">lex
                    Valeria-Il or alia</hi> to be as sacrosanct as the tribunes of the <hi
                    rend="italic">plebs.</hi> But these latter judices seem to have been a purely
                plebeian court which early went into desuetude, and there is really no evidence
                of identity.</p>
            <p>So far back as historic evidence goes we find that actions were tried and judgments
                pronounced by <hi rend="italic">judices</hi> and <hi rend="italic">arbitri.</hi>
                There never was more than a single judge <hi rend="italic">(unus</hi> or <hi
                    rend="italic">unicus judex) </hi>appointed to try a case, but there might be
                more than one arbiter, and frequently there were three. All kinds of actions, even a
                sacramental action <hi rend="italic">in rem,</hi> could be brought before the <hi
                    rend="italic">unus judex,</hi> but especially appropriate to him were
                all personal claims of alleged indebtedness, whether arising out of a legal or
                illegal act, denied either <hi rend="italic">in toto</hi> or only as to the
                amount. Matters of that sort involved as a rule no general principle of law but
                rather mere disputes as to facts, which could well be decided by a. single
                individual. There is much more reason for crediting Servius with the institution of
                the single judge (the arbiters may have been a creation of the Xll. Tables) than
                with either of the collegiate courts. If we believe that in the early regal period
                the king acting with the pontiffs kept all jurisdiction in his own hands, it is
                plain that this must have become a practical impossibility after the admission of
                the plebeians to citizenship. For the trial of disputed facts it would be necessary
                to delegate jurisdiction, and the earliest <hi rend="italic">judices</hi> may have
                been the king’s commissioners for such cases. If this be right, it was the beginning
                of a system that bore wondrous fruit in after years, and that, as will be shown
                in the sequel, helped the praetors to build up, through <hi rend="italic"
                    >formulae, </hi>the whole body of equity.</p>
            <p>@@@Literature: Huschke,<hi rend="italic">Servius Tullius,</hi> pp. 585 seq.;
                Keller-Wach, <hi rend="italic">Rom. Civil Process</hi> (1883), § 6;
                Bethmann-Hollweg, <hi rend="italic">Geschichte d. C. P.</hi> i. § 23; Wlassak, <hi
                    rend="italic">Process-Gesetzc,</hi> i. 125 seq. and ii. 201 seq.; Girard, <hi
                    rend="italic">Organisation judiciaire des Romains,</hi> i. 23 n.; Martin, <hi
                    rend="italic">Le tribunal des centumvirs</hi> (Paris, 1904). In this
                last-named work a succinct account of the court and the various theories about it is
                given.</p>
            <p>@@@On the question of their election, see Greenidge,<hi rend="italic">Legal Procedure
                    in Cicero's Time,</hi> pp. 41 and 264.</p>
            <p>@@@ Girard,<hi rend="italic">Organisation judiciaire,</hi> i. 159; Pauly - Wissowa,
                    <hi rend="italic">Lncyktopädie, s.v.</hi> “ Decemviri.”</p>
            <p>@@@<hi rend="italic">Dig.</hi> i. 2, § 29.</p>
            <p>@@@Livy, ix. 46, 5; Karlowa,<hi rend="italic">Rom. R.G.</hi> i. 118.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>Under the kings it is not improbable that several of the <hi rend="italic">legis
                    actiones,</hi> more or less undeveloped, were already in use, but the nature of
                these actions will be more conveniently considered later on <hi rend="italic"
                    >(infra,</hi> p. 566).</p>
            <p>II. The Jus Civile</p>
            <p>(From the establishment of the Republic until the subjugation of central and southern
                Italy.) i. <hi rend="italic">ConstiMional Events affecting the Law.</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Jus Civile contrasted with Jus Quiritium.—</hi>The term <hi
                    rend="italic">jus civile,</hi> as used to designate this chapter, though almost
                synonymous with, may be taken as somewhat more comprehensive than, <hi rend="italic"
                    >jus Quiritium.</hi> It is a term of later origin than the latter. <hi
                    rend="italic">Jus Quiritium</hi> was based entirely on old custom and
                legislation, finding, one might say, its culmination in the XII. Tables; whereas
                in the <hi rend="italic">jus civile,</hi> as here understood, there appears the
                element of doctrinal interpretation of both statute and custom—the magistrates and
                jurists (particularly the pontiffs) adding much to the earlier law by introducing
                into it this element. We can say that the <hi rend="italic">jus civile</hi> in this
                sense is <hi rend="italic">jus Quiritium </hi>as developed by interpretation. It is
                as yet, however, little influenced, as was the more comprehensive <hi rend="italic"
                    >jus civile</hi> of later periods, by the elements of <hi rend="italic">jus
                    gentium</hi> and equity. Still : nowhere, we must note, are the terms <hi
                    rend="italic">jus Quiritium</hi> and <hi rend="italic">jus civile</hi> placed in
                contrast by the jurists; they were each <hi rend="italic">jus proprium civium
                    Romanorum.</hi> In the classical law the term <hi rend="italic">jus
                    Quiritium</hi> seems to be used principally in formulae framed in accordance
                with old custom.</p>
            <p>Though our information regarding the present period is less legendary than that of
                the kings, it is still far from being completely authentic, as no original
                documents belonging to it are extant. There is little dispute among critics that
                Rome was sacked and burned by the Gauls about 387 b.c. or a few years later, and it
                is probable that the original pontifical annals <hi rend="italic">(annates
                    maximi) </hi>upon which Livy and other Roman historians have presumably based
                their narratives of early history were destroyed at that time along with all other
                written records. What credence, then, we may give to the ancient historical
                narratives, for the period of the Republic antecedent to this event, depends largely
                upon how far the pontífices managed to have their lost records restored. In any
                case, however, there is sufficient presumptive evidence to warrant belief in such
                prominent events of the early Republic as the creation of two annually elected
                patrician consuls, with <hi rend="italic">potestas</hi> similar to that of
                the kings, the creation of tribunes of the <hi rend="italic">plebs,</hi> the
                enactment of the decemviral code, and periodic struggles between patricians and <hi
                    rend="italic">plebs,</hi> the one to keep and the other to gain political power.
                To know the exact dates of these events is relatively of little importance.</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Legislation in Favour of the Plebs.—</hi>In their uphill battle for
                social and political equality the plebeians conquered stage by stage. The more
                important of their successes may here just be mentioned, with all reserve as to
                credibility, in the order of their traditional dates. By the <hi rend="italic">lex
                    Valeria (de pro-vocatione)</hi> of 509 b.c. it was provided that no Roman
                citizen should be deprived of life, liberty or citizenship <hi rend="italic"
                    >(i.e.</hi> suffer <hi rend="italic">poena capitis),</hi> or be scourged, by any
                magistrate within the city, without an appeal <hi rend="italic">(provocatio)</hi> to
                the <hi rend="italic">comitia centuriata. </hi>This statute was often referred to by
                later Romans as a sort of Magna Carta; Livy calls it <hi rend="italic">unicum
                    praesidium libertatis. </hi>In 494 or 471 b.c. the tribunes of the <hi
                    rend="italic">plebs</hi> were created with right of intercession, and about the
                same time plebeian <hi rend="italic">aediles </hi>and <hi rend="italic">judices
                    decemviri</hi> (the latter to act as judges or arbiters in litigations); the
                persons of all these officials being declared inviolable during their tenure of
                office. About 471 b.c. the <hi rend="italic">concilium plebis</hi> became
                legislatively recognized, the tribunes</p>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
