<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>translated from HTML to TEI</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Zinc in sheets is a material largely used as a roof covering, and if care be taken to ensure metal of good quality, it proves itself light, strong and durable, as well as inexpensive. Zinc is stronger weight for weight than lead, slate, tile and glass, but weaker than copper, wrought-iron and steel, although with the exception of the two last mentioned it is not so durable when</p><p>exposed to the weather. It is not liable to easy breakage as are slate, tile and glass. It is usually supplied in flat sheets, although it can also be had in the corrugated form similar to corrugated sheet-iron. When exposed, a thin coating of oxide is formed on the surface which</p><p>protects the metal beneath from any further change, and obviates the necessity of painting. In laying the sheets, the use of solder and nails, should be avoided entirely except for fixing clips and tacks which do not interfere with the free expansion and contraction of the sheets. The reason for this is that zinc expands freely, and sheets laid with soldered seams <hi rend="italic">or</hi>  fixed with nails are liable to buckle and probably break away owing to movements set up by changes of temperature. The usual sizes of zinc sheets are 7 ft. or 8 ft. long by 3 ft. wide. The thickness and weights of zinc are shown in the following table, which compares the Vieille Mon-tagne Gauge with the Old Belgian Gauge and the British Imperial Standard Wire Gauge.</p><p>The best method of laying a zinc flat roof is with the aid of wood " rolls ” of about 2 in. X2 in. in section, splayed at sides and spaced 2 ft. 8 in. apart and fixed to the roof boarding with zinc nails. Iron nails should not be used as this metal affects, the zinc. The sheets of zinc are laid between the rolls with their sides bent up ii in. or 2 in. against them, and held firmly in position by clips of zinc attached to the rolls. A cap of the same metal is then slipped over each roll and fastened down by tacks about 3 in. long soldered inside ’ it so as to hook under the same clips that hold the sheet down. Drips of about 2$ in. are made in the slope at intervals of 6 ft. or 7 ft.—that is, the length of a sheet—and special care must be taken at these points to keep the work waterproof. The lower sheet is bent up the face of the drip and under the projecting portion of the upper sheet, which is finished with a roll edge to turn off the water. The end of the roll has a specially folded cap which also finishes with a curved or beaded water check, and this in conjunction with the saddle piece of the roll beneath forms a weather-proof joint (figs. 17 and 18). The fall between the drips is usually made about 1 j in.,</p><p>but where necessary it may be less, the least permissible fall being about 1 in 80. Felt laid beneath zinc has the effect of lengthening</p><p>the life of the roof and should always be used, as the edges of the boarding upon which it is laid are, when the latter warps, apt to cut the sheets. It also forms a cushion protecting the zinc if there is traffic across the roof.</p><p>Sheet-lead forms a much heavier roof covering than zinc, but it lasts a great deal longer and more easily withstands the attacks of impure air. Lead must be laid on a close boarding, for its great ductility prevents it from spanning even the smallest spaces without bending and giving way,. This characteristic of the metal, however, conduces largely to its usefulness, and enables it to be dressed and bossed into awkward corners without the necessity of jointing. The coefficient of expansion for lead is nearly as great as that for zinc and much higher than in the case of iron, and this fact requires precautions similar to those affecting zinc to be taken when laying the roofing. The manner of laying is with rolls and drips as in the case of zinc, the details of the work differing somewhat to suit the character of the material (see figs. 19, 20 and 2l), Allowances must be made for expansion</p><p>and contraction, and the use of nails and solder avoided as far as possible. Contact with iron sets up corrosion in lead, and when nails are necessary they should be of copper; Screws should be of brass. Lead is supplied in rolls of <hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">25 to 35 ft.</hi></hi>  long and 6 ft. to 7 ft. 6 in. wide. That in general use varies from one-fourteenth to one-seventh of an inch in thickness. The weights most suitable for employment in roofing work are ,7 or 8 lb per square foot for flats and gutters, 6 lb for ndges and hips, and 5 lb for flashings.</p><p>As a roof covering copper is lighter, stronger and more durable than either zinc or lead. It expands and contracts much less than these metals, and although not so strong as wrought-iron and steel it is much more durable. From a structural point of view these qualities enable it to be classed as the best available metal for roof covering, although its heat-conducting properties require it to be well- insulated by layers of felt and other non-conducting material placed beneath the metal. On exposure to the air copper develops a feature of great beauty in the coating of green carbonate which forms upon its surface protecting it from further decomposition. Perhaps the chief disadvantage in the use of copper lies in its first cost, but against this must be set the almost imperishable nature of the metal and the fact that by reason of its light weight less substantial framework is required for its support. Copper roofing should be laid in a similar manner to zinc, with wood rolls at intervals of about 2 ft. 4 in. It is, however, often laid with welted seams. The general stock sizes of sheets are from 4 ft. to 5 ft. 3 in. long and 2 ft. to 3 ft. 6 in. wide. The thickness almost invariably used is known as 24 S.W.G. and weighs 16 oz. per square foot. Thinner metal would suffice, but owing to the increased cost of rolling very little would be gained by adopting the thinner gauges.</p><p>In the United States of America “ tin ” roofs are quite commonly used. Sheets of wrought-iron coated either,with tin or zinc are used of a size usually 14 in. by 20 in., though they may be had double this size. Preparation for laying is made by fixing an insulating foundation of somewhat stout paper or felt; this must be dry, else it is apt to spoil tne impermeable covering laid upon it by causing it to rust. Junctions between the sheets are made by welted seams in which the four edges of the sheets are turned over so as to lock together, thus forming one large sheet of tin covering the roof. In high-class work of a permanent nature the seams in addition are soldered, rosin only being used as a flux. Each sheet also is secured to the roof with two or three tin cleats. The life of such roofs may be practically doubled by the application of a good coat of paint, which, however, adds considerably to the cost.</p><p>Slate is a strong and veiy impermeable material, and these</p><p>?|ualities and the fact that it is easily split into thin plates suitable or laying, as well as its low cost, cause it to be by far.the <hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">slate, </hi></hi>most generally used of all materials for roof covering..</p><p>Some of the best known varieties of slates, classed according to their colour, are as follows:—</p><p><hi rend="italic">Blue .    </hi>. North Wales (Penrhyn, Festiniog, Dinorwic, &amp;c.),</p><p>France, Norway, Germany.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Blue-grey</hi>     . Cornwall (Delabole).</p><p><hi rend="italic">Grey .    </hi>. North Wales (Penrhyn, Dinorwic).</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>