<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>translated from HTML to TEI</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Gallery, London, “Mercury and the Dishonest Woodman,” <hi rend="bold">and </hi>three others; in Raynham Hall, “ Belisarius ”; in the Grosvenor Gallery, “ Diogenes <hi rend="sup">6</hi>; in the Pitti Gallery, a grand portrait of a man in armour, and the “ Temptation of St Anthony, which contains his own portrait. This last subject appears also in St Petersburg, and in the Berlin Gallery.</p><p>The satires of Salvator Rosa deserve more attention than they have generally received. There are, however, two recent books taking account of them—by Cesáreo, 1892, and Cartelli, 1899. The satires, though considerably spread abroad during his lifetime, were not published until 1719. They are all in terza rima, written without much literary correctness, but remarkably spirited, pointed and even brilliant. They are slashingly denunciatory, and from this point of view too monotonous in treatment. Rosa here appears as a very severe castigator of all ranks and conditions of men, not sparing the highest, and as a champion of the poor and down-trodden, and of moral virtue and Catholic faith. It seems odd that a man who took so free a part in the pleasures and diversions of life should be so ruthless to the ministers of these. The satire on <hi rend="italic">Music</hi>  exposes the insolence and profligacy of musicians, and the shame of courts and churches in encouraging them. <hi rend="italic">Poetry</hi>  dwells</p><p>on the pedantry, imitativencss, adulation, affectation</p><p>and indecency of poets—also their poverty, and the</p><p>neglect with which they, were treated; and there is a</p><p>very vigorous sortie against oppressive governors and</p><p>aristocrats. Tasso’s glory is upheld; Dante is spoken</p><p>of as obsolete, and Ariosto , as corrupting. <hi rend="italic">Painting</hi></p><p>inveighs against the pictorial treatment of squalid</p><p>subjects, such as beggars (though .Rosa must surely</p><p>himself have been partly responsible for this mis</p><p>direction of the art), against the ignorance and lewd</p><p>ness of painters, and their tricks of trade, and the</p><p>gross indecorum of painting sprawling half-naked</p><p>saints of both sexes. <hi rend="italic">War</hi>  (which contains the</p><p>eulogy of Masaniello) derides the folly of hireling</p><p>soldiers, who fight and perish while kings stay at</p><p>home; the vile morals of kings and lords, heresy and</p><p>unbelief also come in for a flagellation. In <hi rend="italic">Babylon</hi></p><p>Rosa represents himself as a fisherman, Tirreno, con</p><p>stantly unlucky in his net-hauls on the Euphrates;</p><p>he converses with a native of the country, Ergasto. Babylon (Rome) is very severely treated, and Naples much the same. <hi rend="italic">Envy</hi>  (the last of the satires, and generally accounted the best, although without strong apparent reason) represents Rosa dreaming that, as he is about to inscribe in all modesty his name upon the threshold of the temple of glory, the goddess or fiend of Envy obstructs him, and a long interchange of reciprocal, objurgations ensues. Here occurs the highly charged portrait of the chief Roman detractor of Salvator (we are not aware that he has ever been identified by name); and the painter protests that he would never condescend to do any of the lascivious work in painting so shamefully in vogue.</p><p>As authorities for the life of Salvator Rosa, Passeri, <hi rend="italic">Vite de' Pittori,</hi>  may be consulted, and Salvini, <hi rend="italic">Satire e Vita di Salvator Rosa;</hi>  also Baldinucci and Dominici. The <hi rend="italic">Life</hi>  by Lady Morgan is a romantic treatment, mingling tradition or mere fiction with fact. The novel, <hi rend="italic">A Company of Death,</hi>  by Albert Cotton, 1904, gives an interesting picture of Salvator Rosa at Naples.    (W. M. R.)</p><p><hi rend="bold">ROSACEAE, </hi>in botany, a large cosmopolitan family of seedbearing plants belonging to the subclass Polypetalae of Dicotyledons and containing about 90 genera with 2000 species. The plants vary widely in manner of growth. Many are herbaceous, growing erect, as <hi rend="italic">Geum,</hi>  or with slender creeping stem, as in species of <hi rend="italic">Potentilla,</hi>  sometimes sending out long runners, as in strawberry; others are shrubby, as raspberry, often associated with a scrambling habit, as in the brambles and roses, while apple, cherry, pear, plum and other British fruit trees represent the arborescent habit. Vegetative propagation takes place by means of runners, which root at the apex and form a new plant, as in strawberry; by suckers springing from the base of the shoot and rising to form new leafy shoots after running for some distance beneath the soil, as in raspberry; or by shoots produced from the roots, as in cherry or plum. The scrambling of the brambles and roses is effected by means of prickles on the branches and leaf-stalks.</p><p>The leaves, which are arranged alternately, are simple, as in apple, cherry, &amp;c., but more often compound, with leaflets palmately arranged, as in strawberry and species of <hi rend="italic">Potentilla, </hi>or pinnately arranged, as in the brambles, roses, mountain ash, &amp;c. <hi rend="bold">A </hi>difference in this respect often occurs in one and the same genus, as in <hi rend="italic">Pyrus,</hi>  where apple (P. <hi rend="italic">Malus),</hi>  and pear (P. <hi rend="italic">communis)</hi>  have simple leaves, whereas mountain ash or rowan (P. <hi rend="italic">aucuparia)</hi>  has pinnately compound leaves. In warm climates the leaves are often leathery and evergreen. The leayes are stipulate, the stipules being sometimes small and ’ shortlived, as in <hi rend="italic">Pyms</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">Prunus</hi>  (cherry, plum, &amp;c.), or more important structures adnate to the base of the leaf-stalk, as in roses, brambles, &amp;c. The flowers, which are regular, generally bisexual, and often showy, are sometimes borne singly, as in some species of rose, or of the cloudberry <hi rend="italic">(Rubus chamaemorus),</hi>  or few or more together in a corymbose manner, as in some roses, hawthorn and others. The inflorescence in agrimony is a raceme, in <hi rend="italic">Poterium</hi>  a dense-flowered spike, in <hi rend="italic">Spiraea</hi>  a number of cymes arranged in a corymb. The parts of the flowers are arranged on a 5-merous plan, with generally considerable increase in the number of stamens and carpels. The shape of the thalamus or floral receptacle, and the relative position and number of the stamens and carpels and the character of the fruit, vary widely and form distinguishing</p><p>features of the different suborders, six of which may be recognized.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Suborder</hi>  J. <hi rend="italic">Spiraeoideae</hi>  is characterized by a fiat or slightly concave receptacle on which the carpels, frequently five in number, form a central whorl; each ovary contains several ovules, and the fruit is a follicle. There are five sepals, five petals and the stamens vary from ten to indefinite. The plants are generally shrubs with simple or compound leaves and racemes or panicles of numerous small white, rose or purple flowers. This suborder, which is nearly allied to the order Saxifragaceae, contains 17 genera, chiefly north temperate in distribution. The largest is <hi rend="italic">Spiraea, </hi>numerous species of which are cultivated in gardens; 5. <hi rend="italic">salicifolia </hi>occurs in Britain.apparently wild in plantations, but is not indigenous. The native British meadow-sweet (5. <hi rend="italic">Utmaria)</hi>  and dropwort (5. <hi rend="italic">Filipendula)</hi>  have been placed in a separate genus, <hi rend="italic">Vlmaria, </hi>and included in the Rosoideae on account of their one-seeded fruit. <hi rend="italic">Quillaja saponaria</hi>  is the Chilean soap tree; the bark contains saponin.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Suborder II. Pomoideae</hi>  is characterized by a deep cup-shaped receptacle with the inner wall of which the five or fewer carpels are united (fig. 1, 3); the carpels are also united with each other, and each contains generally two ovules. The fruit is made up of the large fleshy receptacle surrounding the ripe ovaries, the endocarp of which is leathery, or stony and contains one seed. The plants are shrubs or trees with simple or pinnately compound leaves and white or rose-coloured often showy flowers, with five sepals and petals and indefinite stamens. The 14 genera are distributed through the north temperate zone, extending southwards in the New World to the Andes of Peru and Chile. The largest genus, <hi rend="italic">Pyrus,</hi>  with about 50 species, includes apple (P. <hi rend="italic">Malus),</hi>  pear (P. <hi rend="italic">communis)</hi>  (fig. 2), wild service (P. <hi rend="italic">torminalis),</hi>  rowan or mountain-ash (P. <hi rend="italic">aucuparia), </hi>and white beam (P. <hi rend="italic">Aria). Mespilus</hi>  (medlar) and <hi rend="italic">Cotoneaster</hi>  are also included. (See separate articles for most of the above.)</p><p><hi rend="italic">Suborder III. Rosoideae</hi>  is characterized by the receptacle being convex and swollen (fig. 1, 1), as in strawberry, or cup-shaped, as in.rose (fig. 4), and bearing numerous carpels, each of which contains one or two ovules, while the fruit is one-seeded and inde-hiscent. The 39 genera are grouped in tribes according to the form of the receptacle and of the fruit. The Potentilleae bear the carpels on a large, rounded or convex outgrowth of the receptacle.</p><p>In the large genus <hi rend="italic">Rubus</hi>  (fig. 3) the ripe ovaries form drupels upon the ary receptacle; the genus is almost cosmopolitan, but the majority of species occur in the forest region of the north temperate zone and in the mountains of tropical America. <hi rend="italic">R. fruticosus</hi>  is blackberry, <hi rend="italic">R. Idaeus,</hi>  raspberry, and <hi rend="italic">R. Chamac-morus,</hi>  cloudberry. In the flower of <hi rend="italic">Potentilla, Fragaria</hi>  (strawberry) and a few allied genera an <hi rend="italic">epicalyx</hi>  is formed by stipular structures arising at the base of the sepals. The fruits consist of numerous dry achenes borne in <hi rend="italic">Fragaria</hi>  on the much-enlarged</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>