<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>translated from HTML to TEI</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>the so-called <hi rend="italic">lasbik</hi>  has 33, 66 or 99 beads, and is used for the repetition of the 99 names which express the attributes of God.</p><p>See the critical dissertation in the <hi rend="italic">Acta sanctorum, Aug.</hi>  1,422 sqq ; Quetif and Eehard, <hi rend="italic">Script. Ord. Praed.</hi>  i. 411 sqq.;. Benedict XIV olim Prospéra de Lambertini, <hi rend="italic">De festis B.V.M-</hi>  i. 170 sqq.; H. Holzapfel, O.F.M., 5/ <hi rend="italic">Dominikus u. der Rosenkranz</hi>  (Munich, 1903); Pradel, <hi rend="italic">Rosenkranz-Büchel</hi>  (Trier, 1885); D. Dahm, <hi rend="italic">Die Bruderschaft vom hl. Rosenkranz</hi>  (Trier, 1902). For the indulgences attached to the devotion consult Beringer, S.J., <hi rend="italic">Die Ablässe,</hi>  nthed. 292 ff., 354 ff. (Paderborn, 1895). For the corresponding devotion among lluddhists, consult Waddell, <hi rend="italic">The Buddhism of Tibet, or Lamaism </hi>(London, 1895), and an article by Monier Williams in the <hi rend="italic">Athenaeum, </hi>9th of Feb. 1878; for that of the Mahommedans, see L Petit, <hi rend="italic">Les Confrères musulmanes</hi>  (Paris, 1899), and E. Arnold, <hi rend="italic">Pearls of the Faith, or Islam's Rosary</hi>  (London, 1882). There is an excellent article “ Rosenkranz/’ by Zöekler in Herzog Hauck, <hi rend="italic">Realency-klopadie,</hi>  3rd ed. vol. 17, pp. 144-50.    (C. H. Ha.)</p><p><hi rend="bold">ROSAS, JUAN MANUEL </hi>(1793-1877), tyrant of Buenos Aires, was born on the 30th of March 1793, in the city of that name. His father, Leon Ortiz de Rosas, was an owner of cattle runs <hi rend="italic">(estancias)</hi>  and a trader in hides, who took an active part in defeating the English attack on the city in 1807. Juan Rosas received so little education that he had to learn to read and write when he was already a married man and a successful cattle breeder. From a very early age he was left in charge of one of his father’s establishments. When he was eighteen he married Maria de la Encarnacion Eseurra. His mother having suspected him of appropriating money, he left his parents, and for some time subsisted by working as a <hi rend="italic">vaquero</hi>  or cowboy, and then as overseer on the estates of other owners; but he accumulated money, and by the help of a loan from a friend he became possessed of a cattle run of his own, Los Cerrillos. The anarchical state of the country since its independence of Spain had favoured the Indians, who had taken the offensive and raided up to within forty miles of Buenos Aires. Rosas obtained leave to arm his cowboys. Under his management Los Cerrillos became a refuge for adventurers, whom he paid and fed well, but from whom he exacted implicit obedience. His followers became a fighting force of acknowledged efficiency, and Rosas took practically the position of an independent ruler whose help was sought by contending political parties. By attending to his own interest only, and by astute intrigue, or savage fighting when necessary, he grew in power from 1820 onwards, and from 1835 to 1852 ruled as dictator (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Argentina).</hi>  It is probable that he would have continued to govern in Buenos Aires till his death if his ambition had not led him into wars with all his neighbours. He wished to extend the authority of the Republic over all the territory which had belonged to the Spanish viceroyalty of Buenos. This led him directly into wars with Uruguay, Paraguay and Chile, and into “ warlike operations ” with England and France, with whom he had other causes of quarrel arising out of the complaints of traders and bondholders. His government was overthrown in 1852 by a coalition of his neighbours and the defection of several of his generals, and even members of his own family who lived in fear of his suspicions and violence. He took refuge in England, and lived at Swaythling, near Southampton, till his death on the 14th of March 1877. A portrait taken in 1834 and reproduced by Sir Woodbine Parish in his <hi rend="italic">Buenos Ayres and Provinces of the Rio delà Plata</hi>  (London, 1852) represents Rosas as a fine-looking man of the handsome Spanish type.</p><p>See 0. Martens, <hi rend="italic">Ein Caligula unseres Jahrhunderts</hi>  (Berlin, 1896), which contains a full bibliography.</p><p><hi rend="bold">ROSCELLINUS </hi><hi rend="smallcaps">(Rucelinus,</hi>  or <hi rend="smallcaps">Rousselin) (c.</hi>  1050-c. 1122), often called the founder of Nominalism (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Scholasticism), </hi>was born at Compiègne (Compendium). Little is known of his life, and our knowledge of his doctrines is mainly derived from Anselm, Abelard and John of Salisbury. He studied at Soissons and Reims, was afterwards attached to the cathedral of Chartres, and became canon of Compiègne. It seems most probable that Roscellinus was not strictly the first to promulgate nominalistic doctrines; but in his exposition they received more definite expression, and, being applied to the dogma of the Trinity, attracted universal attention. Roscellinus maintained that it is merely a habit of speech which prevents our speaking of the three persons as three substances or three Gods. If it were otherwise, and the three persons were really one substance or thing <hi rend="italic">(una res),</hi>  we should be forced to admit that the Father and the Holy Spirit became incarnate along with the Son. Roscellinus seems to have put forward this doctrine in perfect good faith, and to have claimed for it at first the authority of Lanfranc and Anselm. In 1092, however, a council convoked by the archbishop of Reims condemned his interpretation, and Roscellinus, who was in danger of being stoned to death by the orthodox populace, recanted his error. He fled to England, but having made himself unpopular by an attack on the doctrines of Anselm, he left the country and repaired to Rome, where he was well received and became reconciled to the Church. He then returned to France, taught at Tours and Loc-menaeh (Loches) in Brittany (where he had Abelard as a pupil), and finally became canon of Besançon. He is heard of as late as 1121, when he came forward to oppose Abelard’s views on the Trinity.</p><p>Of the writings of Roscellinus, nothing is preserved except a letter to Abelard, mainly concerned with the doctrine of the Trinity (ed. J. A. Sehmellcr, Munich, 1850). See F. Piearet, <hi rend="italic">Rosselin, philosophe et théologien</hi>  (1896), and authorities quoted under Scholasticism.</p><p>ROSCHER, WILHELM GEORG FRIEDRICH (1817-1894), German economist, was born at Hanover on the 21st of October 1817. He studied at Göttingen and Berlin, and obtained a professorship at Gottingen in 1844 and subsequently at Leipzig in 1848. Omitting preparatory indications and undeveloped germs of doctrine, the origin of the “ historical ” school of political economy may be traced to Roscher. Its fundamental principles are dated, though with some hesitation, and with an unfortunate contrast of the historical with the philosophical method, in his <hi rend="italic">Grundriss zu Vorlesungen über die Staat swirth-schaft nach geschichtlicher Methode</hi>  (1843). This short study was afterwards expanded into his great <hi rend="italic">System der Volkswirlh-schaft,</hi>  published in five volumes between 1854 and 1894, and arranged as follows: vol. L, <hi rend="italic">Die Grundlagen der Nationalökonomie,</hi>  1854 (trans, by J. J. Lalor, <hi rend="italic">Principles of Political Economy,</hi>  Chicago, 1878); vol. ii., <hi rend="italic">Die Nationalökonomie des Ackerbaues und der verwandten UrProduktionszweige,</hi>  1859; vol. iii., <hi rend="italic">Die Nationalökonomie des Handels und Gewerbfleisses, </hi>1881; vol. iv., <hi rend="italic">System der Finanzwissenschaft,</hi>  1886; vol. v., <hi rend="italic">System der Armenpflege und Armenpolitik,</hi>  1894. His <hi rend="italic">Geschichte der Nationalökonomie in Deutschland</hi>  (1874) is a monumental work. He also published in 1842 an excellent commentary on the life and works of Thucydides. He died at Leipzig on the 4th of June 1894.</p><p>See T. Roscher, <hi rend="italic">Zur Geschichte der Familie Roscher in Niedersachsen</hi>  (Hanover, 1892); Brasch, <hi rend="italic">Wilhelm Roscher und die sozial-wissenschaftlichen Strömungen der Gegenwart</hi>  (Leipzig, 1895).</p><p>ROSCIUS GALLUS, QUINTUS (r. 126-62 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.),</hi>  Roman actor, was born, a slave, at Solonium, near Lanuvium. Endowed with a handsome faee and manly figure, he studied the delivery and gestures of the most distinguished advocates in the Forum, especially Q. Hortensius, and won universal praise for his grace and elegance on the stage. He especially excelled in comedy. Cicero took lessons from him. The two often engaged in friendly rivalry to try whether the orator or the actor could express a thought or emotion with the greater effect, and Roscius wrote a treatise in which he compared acting and oratory. Q. Lutatius Catulus composed a quatrain in his honour, and the dictator Sulla presented him with a gold ring, the badge of the equestrian order, a remarkable distinction for an actor in Rome, where the profession was held in contempt. Like his contemporary Aesopus, Roscius amassed a large fortune, and he appears to have retired from the stage some time before his death. In 76 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi>  he was sued by C. Fannius Chaerea for 50,000 sesterces (about £400), and was defended by Cicero in a famous speech.</p><p>See H. H. Pflüger, <hi rend="italic">Cicero's Rede pro Q. Roscio Comoedo</hi>  (1904).</p><p>ROSCOE, SIR HENRY ENFIELD (1833-    ), English</p><p>chemist, was born in London on the 7th of January 1833. After</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>