<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>translated from HTML to TEI</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>political system, was at first exclusively military in its nature and objects.@@ It amounted, in fact, to the formation of a new and enlarged army on a new footing. In this force, excepting in the case of the centuries of the horsemen, no regard was paid either to the old clan divisions or to the semi-religious, semipolitical curiae. In its ranks were included all freeholders within the Roman territory, whether members or not of any of the old divisions, and the organization of this new army of <hi rend="italic">assidui</hi>  was not less independent of the old system with its clannish and religious traditions and forms. The unit was the <hi rend="italic">centuria </hi>or company of ioo men; the <hi rend="italic">centuriae</hi>  were grouped in <hi rend="sup">a</hi>  classes ” and drawn up in the order of the phalanx.@@  The centuries in front were composed of the wealthier citizens, whose means enabled them to bear the cost of the complete equipments necessary for those who were to bear the brunt of the onset. These centuries formed the first class. Behind them stood the centuries of the second and third classes, less completely armed, but making up together with those of the first class the heavyarmed infantry.@@In the rear were the centuries of the fourth and fifth classes, recruited from the poorer freeholders, and serving only as light-armed troops. The entire available body of freeholders was divided into two equal portions, a reserve corps of<hi rend="italic">seniores</hi>  and a corps of <hi rend="italic">juniores</hi>  for active service. Each of these corps consisted of 85 centuries or 8500 men, x.e. of two legions of about 4200 men each, the normal strength of a consular legion under the early Republic.@@  It is noticeable also that the heavy-armed centuries of the three first classes in each of these legions represented a total of 3000 men, a number which agrees exactly with the number of heavy-armed troops in the legion as described by Polybius. Attachedto the legions, but not included in them, were the companies of sappers and trumpeters. Lastly, to the six centuries of horsemen, which still retained the old tribal names, twelve more were added as a distinct body, and recruited from the wealthiest class of citizens.@@  The four “ tribes” also instituted by Servius were probably intended to serve as the bases for the levy of freeholders for the new army.@@  As their names show, they corresponded with the natural local divisions of the city territory.@@</p><p>The last of these Etruscan lords to rule in Rome was Tarquin the Proud. He is described as a splendid and despotic monarch.</p><p>His sway extended over Latium as far south as Circeii. Aristodemus, tyrant of Cumae, was his ally, and kinsmen of his own were princes at Collatia, at Gabii, and at Tusculum. The Volscian highlanders were chastised, and Signia with its massive walls was built to hold them in check. In Rome itself the Capitoline temple and the great cloaca bore witness to his power. But his rule pressed heavily upon the Romans, and at the last, on the news of the foul wrong done by his son Sextus to a noble Roman matron, Lucretia, the indignant people rose in revolt. Tarquin, who was away besieging Ardea, was deposed; sentence of exile was passed upon him and upon all his race; and the</p><lb/><p>people swore that* never again should a king rule in Rome. Freed from the tyrant, they chose for themselves two yearly magistrates who should exercise the supreme authority, and thus the Republic of Rome was founded. Three times the banished Tarquin strove desperately to recover the throne he had lost. First of all the men of Veii and Tarquinii marched to his aid, but were defeated in a pitched battle on the Roman frontier. A year later Lars Porsena, prince of Clusium, at the head of all the powers of Etruria, appeared before the gates of Rome, and closely besieged the city, until, moved by the valour of his foe, he granted honourable terms of peace and withdrew.@@Once again, by Lake Regillus, the Romans fought victoriously for their liberty against Tarquin’s son-in-law Mamilius, prince of Tusculum, and chief of the Latin name. Mamilius was slain; Tarquin in despair found a refuge at Cumae, and there soon afterwards died.</p><p>So, in brief, ran the story of the flight of the kings, as it was told by the chroniclers whose story Livy reports, though with explicit and repeated notes of reserve. Its details are most of them fabulous; it is crowded with inconsistencies and improbabilities; there are no trustworthy dates; the names even of the chief actors are probably fictitious, and the hand of the improver, Greek or Roman, is traceable throughout.@@ But there is no room for doubting the main facts of the emancipation of Rome from the rule of alien princes and the final abolition of the kingly office.    (H. F. P.; R. S. C.)</p><p><hi rend="bold">II. </hi><hi rend="italic">The Republic.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Period A: 509-265 b.c.@@—(a)</hi><hi rend="italic">The Struggle between the Orders. </hi>—It is characteristic of Rome that the change from monarchy to republic@@  should have been made with the least possible disturbance of existing forms. The title of king was retained, though only as that of a priestly officer <hi rend="italic">(rex sacrorum}</hi>  to 'whom some of the religious functions of the former kings were transferred. The two annually elected consuls, or <hi rend="italic">praetores </hi>@@<hi rend="italic"/>  were regarded as joint heirs of the full kingly authority, and as holding the    and the correlative right of taking</p><p>the auspices, by direct transmission from the founder of the city. They were, it is true, elected or designated by a new assembly, by the army of landholders voting by their classes and centuries <hi rend="italic">(comitia centuriata) ,</hi>  and to this body was given also the right of passing laws; nevertheless it was still by a vote of the thirty curiae <hi rend="italic">(lex curiata)</hi>  that the supreme authority was formally conferred on the magistrates chosen by the centuries of landholders, and both the choice of magistrates and the passing of laws still required the sanction of the patrician senators <hi rend="italic">(patrum auctoritas).</hi>@@<hi rend="italic"/>Nor, lastly, were the legal prerogatives of the senate altered, although it is probable that before long plebeians were admitted to seats, if not to votes, and though its importance was gradually increased by the substitution of an annual magistracy for the lifelong rule of a single king. But the</p><lb/><p>@@@This is recognized by Mommsen, Genz and Soltau, as against Niebuhr, Schwegler and Ihne. Even in the later<hi rend="italic">comitia centuriata </hi>the traces of the originally military character of the organization are unmistakable.</p><p>@@@he eentuiy ceased to represent companies of one hundred when the whole organization ceased to be military and became exclusively political.</p><p>@@@The property qualification for service in the first class is given at 100,000 asses (Livy'), for the second at 70,000, third 50,000, fourth 25,000, fifth 11,000. It was probably originally a certain number of cows, afterwards translated into terms of money; cf. W. Ridgeway,<hi rend="italic">The Origin of Coinage and Metallic Currency</hi>  (Cambridge, 1892), p. 391. The same scholar, in his <hi rend="italic">Who were the Romans?</hi>  p. 17, has pointed out the ethnical meaning of the varieties of armature in the early army.</p><p>@@@Polyb. vi. 20; Mommsen,<hi rend="italic">Rom. Trib.</hi>  132 seq.</p><p>@@@Livy i. 43. Dionys. (iv. 18) and Cic.<hi rend="italic">(De Rep.</hi>  ii. 22) ascribe the whole eighteen to Servius. But the six older centuries remained distinct, as the “sex suffragia ” of the <hi rend="italic">comitia centuriata;</hi>  Cic. <hi rend="italic">De Rep.</hi>  ii. 22.</p><p>@@@Dionys. iv. 14, ei?<hi rend="smallcaps">tAs</hi>  /caraypa^as <hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps">t&amp;v (rTpartwrutv.</hi></hi></p><p>@@@Livy i. 43. The four were Palatina, Suburana, Exquilina, Colli na.</p><lb/><p>@@@Livy ii. 9-14. Pliny<hi rend="italic">(N.H.</hi>  34, ia) and Tacitus <hi rend="italic">(Ann.</hi>  iii. 72) imply the existence of a tradition, possibly that of “ Tuscan annalists,** according to which Porsena.actually made himself master of Rome. The whole story is fully criticized by Schwegler (ii. 181 seq.) and Zoller <hi rend="italic">(Latium</hi>  w. <hi rend="italic">Rom,</hi>  p. 180).</p><p>@@@See the exhaustive criticism in Schwegler (ii. pp. 66-203).</p><p>@@@The traditional account of early republican history, given in annalistic form by Livy, has been subjected to severe criticism in recent times, notably by Pais in his<hi rend="italic">Storia di Roma,</hi>  vols. i. and ii. It is true that the dearth of contemporary documents, especially for the period before the sack of Rome by the Gauls (390 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.),</hi>  must have led to the filling of gaps by episodes drawn mainly from popular traditions, and it is therefore impossible to guarantee the accuracy of the narrative in details. Nevertheless, the general truth of the story of Rome’s early wars and constitutional growth cannot be seriously impugned.</p><p>@@@Schwegler (ii. 92) suggests that the dictatorship formed an intermediate step between the monarchy and the consulate; cf. Ihne,<hi rend="italic">Rom. Forsch.</hi>  42.</p><p>@@@That the consuls were originally styled<hi rend="italic">praetores</hi>  is stated by Varro, <hi rend="italic">ap.. Non.</hi>  p. 23, and Liv. iii. 55; cf. Cic. viii. .3, 8. When additional praetors were created, the two originally appointed were called <hi rend="italic">praetores maximi</hi>  and hence <hi rend="italic">ffTparqyol facaroi</hi>  or simply ibrarot in Greek.</p><p>@@@The view of the<hi rend="italic">patrum auctoritas</hi>  here adopted is that taken by T. Mommsen <hi rend="italic">(Forsch.</hi>  i.).</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>