<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>translated from HTML to TEI</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>the religious and the moral life will vanish, and the Christian state, as the highest sphere of human life representing all human functions, will displace the church. “ In proportion as the Saviour Christianizes the state by means of the church must the progressive completion of the structure of the church prove the cause of its abolition.” The decline of the church is therefore not to be deplored, but recognized as the consequence of the independence and completeness of the Christian life. It is the third section of his work—the <hi rend="italic">Pflichtenlehre—</hi>which is generally most highly valued, and where his full strength as an ethical thinker is displayed, without any mixture of theosophic speculation.</p><p>Since Kothens death several volumes of his, sermons and of his lectures (on dogmatics, the history of homiletics) and a collection of brief essays and religious meditations under the title of <hi rend="italic">Stille Stunden</hi>  (Wittenberg, 1872) have been published.</p><p>See F. Nippold, <hi rend="italic">Richard Rothe, ein christliches Lebensbild</hi>  (2 vols., Wittenberg, 1873-74) î D. Schenkel, “ Zur Erinnerung an Dr R. Rothe,” in ,the <hi rend="italic">Allgemeine kirchliche Zeitschrift</hi>  (1867-68); H.Holtz-mann, ” Richard Rothe,” in the <hi rend="italic">Jahrbuch des Protestantenvereins </hi>(1869); K. H. W. Schwarz, <hi rend="italic">Zur Geschichte der neuesten Theologie </hi>(4th ed., Leipzig, 1869, pp. 41J-44); Otto Ffleiderer, <hi rend="italic">Religionsphilosophie auf geschichtlicher Grundlage</hi>  (2nd ed., Berlin, 1884, vol. i. pp. 611-15); cf. <hi rend="italic">The Development of Theology in Germany since Kant</hi>  (1800); W. Honig, <hi rend="italic">Richard Rothe, sein Charakter, Leben und Denken</hi>  (1898); Adolf Hausrath, <hi rend="italic">Richard Rothe und seine Freunde</hi>  (1902).</p><p>ROTHELIN, JACQUELINE DE ROHAN, <hi rend="smallcaps">Marquise de </hi>(c. 1520-1587), daughter of Charles de Rohan and Jeanne de Saint-Séverin. Her husband, François of Orleans-Longueville, marquis de Rothelin, died in 1548, and in watching her son’s interests in Neuchâtel she was brought into contact with the reformers in Switzerland. She then embraced Protestantism and turned her château at Blandy, in Brie, into a refuge for Huguenots. In 1567 she underwent a term of imprisonment at the Louvre for harbouring Protestants.</p><p>ROTHENBURG-OB-DER-TAUBER, a town of Germany, in the kingdom of Bavaria, 49 m. by rail S.W. of Nuremberg. Pop. (1905) 8436. It is beautifully situated on an eminence 200 ft. above the Tauber. It is flanked by medieval walls, towers and gates, and its antique appearance has been carefully preserved. Perhaps the most interesting building is the town hall, one part of which dates from 1240 and the other from 1572. The latter is a beautiful Renaissance structure, with a magnificent façade and a delicate spire, and contains a grand hall, the Kaisersaal, in which every Whit Monday a play, <hi rend="italic">Der Meislertrunk,</hi>  which commemorates the capture of the town by Tilly in 1631, is performed. Other buildings are the Gothic church of St James, with curiously carved altars and beautiful stained-glass windows, and containing in the Toppler chapel the tomb of the burgomaster, Heinrich Toppler; the 15th-century church of St Wolfgang; the Franciscan church; and five other churches. The town has many picturesque houses, and possesses a library with some interesting archives. It has manufactures of toys and agricultural machinery, electrical works and breweries.</p><p>Rothenburg-ob-der-Tauber, mentioned in the chronicles in 304 as <hi rend="italic">Rolinbure,</hi>  was probably a residence of the dukes of Franconia. It first appears as a town in 942 and until 1108 was the seat of the counts of Rothenburg-Komburg; when this line became extinct it passed to the family of Hohenstaufen, one member of which took the title of duke of Rothenburg. In 1172 it became a free imperial city and it attained the zenith of its prosperity under the famous burgomaster Heinrich Toppler (1350-1408). It took part in the movements in South Germany during the 15th and 16th centuries. In 1631 Rothenburg was stormed by Tilly, and the cup of wine presented by the burgomaster, which, according to tradition, saved the town from destruction, is annually commemorated in the play mentioned above.</p><p>See Bensen, <hi rend="italic">Beschreibung und Geschichte der Stadt Rothenburg </hi>(Erlangen, 1856) ; Merz. <hi rend="italic">Rothenburg in alter und neuer Zeit</hi>  (2nd ed., Ansbach, 1881); Schultheiss, <hi rend="italic">Rothenburg, ein Städtebild</hi>  (Zürich, 1892) ; and <hi rend="italic">Das Festspiel zu Rothenburg-ob-der-Tauber</hi>  (Munich, 1892); and W. Klein, <hi rend="italic">Führer durch die Stadt Rothenburg</hi>  (Rothenburg, 1888).</p><p>ROTHERHAM, THOMAS (1423-1500), archbishop of York, also called <hi rend="smallcaps">Thomas Scot,</hi>  was born at Rotherham on the 24th of</p><p>August 1423; he was educated in his native town and seems to have been connected with both the universities of Oxford and Cambridge. Having entered the church he became rector of Ripple, Worcestershire, and later of St Vedast, Foster Lane, London, and it was probably when he was chaplain to John de Vere, earl of Oxford, that he made the acquaintance of Elizabeth Woodville, afterwards the queen of Edward IV. In 1467 Rotherham became keeper of the privy seal to this king; in 1468 he was appointed bishop of Worcester, in 1472 bishop of Lincoln and in 1475 chancellor of England. Several times he went to France on public business; in 1475 at the treaty of Picquigny he received a pension from Louis XI. of France, and in 1480 he was chosen archbishop of York. When Edward IV. died in April 1483 the archbishop remained true to his widow Elizabeth, and consequently lost the chancellorship and was put into prison by Richard III. He was soon set at liberty, and he died in 1500 at Cawood, near York. At Oxford Rotherham built part of Lincoln College and increased its endowment; at Cambridge, where he was chancellor and master of Pembroke Hall, he helped to build the University Library. He founded a college at Rotherham, which was suppressed under Edward VI., and he was responsible for the building of part of the church of All Saints there.</p><p>ROTHERHAM, a market-town and municipal borough in the Rotherham parliamentary division of the West Riding of Yorkshire, England, 5 m. N.E. of Sheffield, on the Midland, North-Eastern and Great Central railways. Pop. (1891) 42,061; (1901) 54,349. It lies in the valley of the Don, where that river is joined by the Rother, and has communication by water with the Humber. The Don is crossed by a bridge on which is a small ancient building, formerly a chapel. The parish church of All Saints, occupying the site of a building dating from Anglo-Saxon times, was erected in the reign of Edward IV., and is among the best specimens of Perpendicular in the north of England. The town possesses iron, steel and brass works, railway wagon works, potteries, glass-works, breweries, saw-mills and rope-yards. At the township of Masborough, opposite Rotherham across the Don, works were established in 1746 by Samuel Walker, a successful ironmaster. The municipal borough, incorporated in 1871, is under a mayor, 6 aldermen and 18 councillors. Area, 6012 acres.</p><p>The town was of some importance in Anglo-Saxon times, and at Templeborough, on the S.E. side of Rotherham, there was a Roman fort, but its traces are effaced. In the time of Edward the Confessor, Rotherham possessed a market and a church. During the Civil War it sided with the Parliament. It was taken by the Royalists in 1643, but after the victory of Marston Moor was yielded to a detachment of the Parliamentary forces.</p><p>ROTHES, EARLS OF. The first earl of Rothes was George Leslie, son of Norman Leslie of Rothes in Moray, and of Ballinbreicb in Fife. In 1445 he was created Baron Leslie of Leven, and about 1458 earl of Rothes in the peerage of Scotland. His grandson George, the 4th earl (d. 1558), whose father, William, the 3rd earl, was killed at Flodden, was accused, but acquitted in 1546, of complicity in the murder of Cardinal Beaton, in which his brother and his two sons were undoubtedly implicated; he was one of the Scottish commissioners who witnessed the marriage of Mary queen of Scots with Francis, the dauphin of France. His son Andrew, 5th earl of Rothes (d. 1611), took an active part with the lords of the congregation, first against the queen-mother, Mary of Guise, when regent of Scotland, and afterwards against Mary queen of Scots in opposing her marriage with Darnley, and in devising the murder of Rizzio. He was, however, one of the peers who acquitted Both well of Darnley’s murder; and going over to the side of the queen, he fought for her at Langside. He continued to occupy a position of some prominence in Scottish affairs until, his death in 1611. His great-grandson, John, 7th earl of Rothes (1630-1681), held a command in the Royalist army at the battle of Worcester in 1651, and accompanied Charles II. to England at the Restoration, when he became</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>