<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T20:45:32Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p><hi rend="italic">hijo, hoja).</hi> A very marked feature is the habitual “mouillure” of <hi rend="italic">l</hi> aud <hi rend="italic">n</hi> as initial letters : <hi rend="italic">lleche, lleer, lluna, llutu ; non, ñunca, nueve, ñube.</hi> With respect to inflexion the following forms may be noted :—personal pronouns: <hi rend="italic">i (illi), yos (illos);</hi> possessive pronouns : <hi rend="italic">mió,</hi> pl. <hi rend="italic">miós ; to, tos ; so, sos</hi> for both masc. and fem. ; verbs : 3d pers. pl. imp. of the 2d and 3d conjugations in <hi rend="italic">in </hi>for <hi rend="italic">ien</hi> (Cast. <hi rend="italic">ian) ; train, tenin, facin</hi> (from <hi rend="italic">facer), fiin</hi> (from <hi rend="italic">fcr), </hi>and even some instances of the 2d pers. sing, <hi rend="italic">(ab is ; </hi>Cast. <hi rend="italic">habias)</hi> ; instances of pres. subj. in <hi rend="italic">ia</hi> for <hi rend="italic">a (sírvia, métia, sépia). </hi>The verb <hi rend="italic">ser</hi> gives <hi rend="italic">yes</hi> (sometimes <hi rend="italic">yeres)</hi> in the 2d pers. sing., <hi rend="italic">ye </hi>in the 3d. Facere appears under two forms—<hi rend="italic">-facer</hi> and <hi rend="italic">fer,</hi>—and to the abridged form correspond <hi rend="italic">feis, fiendo, fiin,</hi> &amp;c. Ire often appears under the form <hi rend="italic">dir (antes de diros = antes de iros),</hi> which it is not necessary to explain by <hi rend="italic">de-ire</hi> (see Schuchardt, <hi rend="italic">Ztschr. f. rom. Philol.,</hi> v. 312).</p><p><hi rend="italic">Naνarrese-Aragonese.—</hi>In its treatment of the post-tonic vowels this dialect parts company with normal Castilian and comes nearer Catalan, in so far as it drops the final <hi rend="italic">e,</hi> especially after <hi rend="italic">nt, rt (mont, plazient, muert, fuert, parents, gents)</hi> ; and, when the atonic <hi rend="italic">e</hi> has dropped after a <hi rend="italic">ν,</hi> this <hi rend="italic">ν</hi> becomes a vowel—<hi rend="italic">breu</hi> (brevem), <hi rend="italic">grieu</hi> (*grevem), <hi rend="italic">nueu</hi> (novem). Navarrese-Aragonese has the diphthongs <hi rend="italic">ie, ue</hi> from tonic <hi rend="italic">ĕ</hi> and <hi rend="italic">ŏ,</hi> and adheres more strictly to them than normal Castilian does,—<hi rend="italic">cuende</hi> (cŏmitem), <hi rend="italic">huey </hi>(hŏdie), <hi rend="italic">pueyo</hi> (pŏdium), <hi rend="italic">yes</hi> (est), <hi rend="italic">yeran</hi> (ĕrant), while Castilian says <hi rend="italic">eonde, hoy, poyo, es, eran.</hi> The initial combinations <hi rend="italic">cl, pl, fl, </hi>have withstood the transformation into <hi rend="italic">ll</hi> better than in Castilian : <hi rend="italic">plano, pleno, plega, clamado, flama</hi> are current in old documents ; and at the present day, although the <hi rend="italic">l</hi> has come to be “mouillée,” the first consonant has not disappeared <hi rend="italic">(plluma, pllora, pllano— </hi>pronounced <hi rend="italic">pljuma,</hi> &amp;c. ). Lat. <hi rend="italic">ct</hi> gives <hi rend="italic">it,</hi> not <hi rend="italic">ch</hi> as in Castilian : <hi rend="italic">nucyt</hi> (noctem), <hi rend="italic">destruito</hi> (destructum), <hi rend="italic">proveito</hi> (provectum), <hi rend="italic">dito</hi> for <hi rend="italic">diito</hi> (dictum). <hi rend="italic">D</hi> between vowels kept its ground longer than in Castilian : documents of the 14th century supply such forms as <hi rend="italic">vidieron, νido, hudio, ρroνedir, redemir, prodeza, Benedit, vidiendo, </hi>&amp;c. ; but afterwards <hi rend="italic">y</hi> came to be substituted for <hi rend="italic">d</hi> or <hi rend="italic">dj : veyere </hi>(videre), <hi rend="italic">seyer</hi> (sedere), <hi rend="italic">seya</hi> (sedeat), <hi rend="italic">goyo</hi> (gaudium), <hi rend="italic">enueyo </hi>(inodium). Initial <hi rend="italic">f </hi>does not change into <hi rend="italic">h</hi>:<hi rend="italic"> fillo, feito.</hi> Navarrese- Aragonese does not possess the guttural spirant <hi rend="italic">(j)</hi> of Castilian, which is here rendered according to circumstances either by <hi rend="italic">g</hi> (Fr. <hi rend="italic">j)</hi> or by <hi rend="italic">ll (l</hi> mouillée), but never by the Asturian <hi rend="italic">x</hi>. Certain forms of the conjugation of the verb differ from the Castilian : <hi rend="italic">dar, estar, haver, saber, poner</hi> readily form their imperfects and imperfect subjunctives like the regular verbs in <hi rend="italic">ar</hi> and <hi rend="italic">er,—havieron</hi> (Cast. <hi rend="italic">hubieron), estaron</hi> (Cast. <hi rend="italic">estubieron), sabió</hi> (Cast. <hi rend="italic">supo), dasen</hi> (Cast. <hi rend="italic">diesen), poniese</hi> (Cast, <hi rend="italic">pusiese)</hi> ; on the other hand, past participles and gerundives formed from the perfect are to be met with,—<hi rend="italic">fisiendo </hi>for <hi rend="italic">faciendo</hi> (perf. <hi rend="italic">fiso), tuviendo</hi> and <hi rend="italic">tuvido</hi> for <hi rend="italic">teniendo, tenido </hi>(perf. <hi rend="italic">tuvo).</hi> In the region bordering on Catalonia the simple perfect has given way before the periphrastic form proper to Catalan : <hi rend="italic">voy cayer</hi> (I fell), <hi rend="italic">va fié</hi> (he has done), <hi rend="italic">vamos ir</hi> (we went), &amp;c. ; the imperfects of verbs in <hi rend="italic">er, ir,</hi> moreover, are found in <hi rend="italic">eba, iba (comeba, subiba,</hi> for <hi rend="italic">comia, subia),</hi> and some presents also occur where the Catalan influence makes itself felt : <hi rend="italic">estígo</hi> (Cat. <hi rend="italic">estich), vaigo</hi> (Cat. <hi rend="italic">vaig), veigo</hi> (Cat. <hi rend="italic">veig).</hi> Navarrese-Aragonese makes use of the adverb <hi rend="italic">en</hi> as a pronoun : <hi rend="italic">no les en daren pas, no'n hi ha.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Andalusian.—</hi>The word “dialect” is still more appropriately applied to Andalusian than either to Asturian or Navarrese- Aragonese. Many peculiarities of pronunciation, however, are commonly called Andalusian which are far from being confined to Andalusia proper, but are met with in the vulgar speech of many parts of the Castilian domain, both in Europe and in America. Of these but a few occur only there, or at least have not yet been observed elsewhere than in that great province of southern Spain. They are the following. <hi rend="italic">L, n, r, d</hi> between vowels or at the end of a word disappear : <hi rend="italic">sá (sal), só (sol), viee (viene), tiee (tiene), paa </hi>and <hi rend="italic">pa ( para), mia (mira), naa</hi> and <hi rend="italic">na (nada), too</hi> and <hi rend="italic">to (todo). D</hi> is dropped even from the beginning of a word : <hi rend="italic">e (de), inero (dinero), on (don).</hi> Before an explosive, <hi rend="italic">l, r, d</hi> are often represented by <hi rend="italic">i : saiga (salga), vaiga (valga), laigo (largo), maire (madre), paire (padre).</hi> Lat. <hi rend="italic">f</hi> is more rigorously represented by <hi rend="italic">h</hi> than in normal Castilian, and this <hi rend="italic">h</hi> here preserves the aspirate sound which it has lost elsewhere ; <hi rend="italic">hablá, horma (forma), hoder,</hi> are pronounced with a very strong aspiration, almost identical with that of <hi rend="italic">j</hi>. The Andalusians also very readily write these words <hi rend="italic">jabla, jorma, joder.</hi> This aspirate, expressed by <hi rend="italic">j,</hi> often has no etymological origin ; for example, <hi rend="italic">Jándalo,</hi> a nickname applied to Andalusians, is simply the word <hi rend="italic">Andaluz</hi> pronounced with the strong aspiration characteristic of the inhabitants of the province. <hi rend="italic">C, z</hi> are seldom pronounced like <hi rend="italic">s</hi> ; but a feature more peculiar to the Andalusians is the inverse process, the softened and interdental pronunciation of the <hi rend="italic">s</hi> (the so-called <hi rend="italic">ceceo) : zeñor (senor),</hi> &amp;c. Before a consonant and at the end of a word <hi rend="italic">s</hi> becomes a simple aspiration : <hi rend="italic">mihmo (mismo), Dioh (Dios), do reales (dos reales).</hi> In the inflexion of the verb there is nothing special to note, except some instances of 2d pers. sing. of the perfect in <hi rend="italic">tes</hi> for <hi rend="italic">te : estuvistes, estuvites,</hi> for <hi rend="italic">estuviste,—</hi>evidently a formation by analogy from the 2d pers. of the other tenses, which all have <hi rend="italic">s</hi>.</p><p>It is with the Andalusian dialect that we can most readily associate the varieties of Castilian which are spoken in South America. Here some of the most characteristic features of the language of the extreme south of Spain are reproduced,—either because the Castilian of America has spontaneously passed through the same phonetic transformations or because the Andalusian element, very strongly represented in colonization, succeeded in transporting its local habits of speech to the New World.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Leonese. —</hi>Proceeding on inadequate indications, the existence of a Leonese dialect has been imprudently admitted in some quarters ; but the old kingdom of Leon cannot in any way be considered as constituting a linguistic domain with an individuality of its own. The fact that a poem of the 13th century (the <hi rend="italic">Alexandro),</hi> and certain redactions of the oldest Spanish code, the <hi rend="italic">Fuero Juzgo, </hi>have a Leonese origin has been made too much of, and has led to a tendency to localize excessively certain features common to the whole western zone where the transition takes place from Castilian to Galician-Portuguese.</p><p>III. <hi rend="smallcaps">Portuguese.</hi>—Portuguese-Galician constitutes the second branch of the Latin of Spain. In it we must distinguish—(1) Portuguese <hi rend="italic">(Portuguez,</hi> perhaps a contraction from the old <hi rend="italic">Portugalez=</hi>Portugalensis), the language of the kingdom of Portugal and its colonies in Africa, Asia, and America (Brazil) ; (2) Galician <hi rend="italic">(Gallego),</hi> or the language of the old kingdom of Galicia (the modern provinces of Pontevedra, La Coruna, Orense, and Lugo) and of a portion of the old kingdom of Leon (the territory of Vierzo in the province of Leon). Portuguese, like Castilian, is a literary language, which for ages has served as the vehicle of the literature of the Portuguese nation constituted in the beginning of the 12th century. Galician, on the other hand, which began early in the Middle Ages a literary life,—for it was employed by Alfonso the Wise in his <hi rend="italic">cantigas</hi> in honour of the Virgin,—decayed in proportion as the monarchy of Castile and Leon, to which Galicia had been annexed, gathered force and unity in its southward conquest. At the present day Gallego, which is simply Portuguese variously modified and with a development in some respects arrested, is far from having as a dialect the same importance as Catalan, not only because the Spaniards who speak it (1,800,000) number much less than the Catalans (3,500,000), but also because, its literary culture having been early abandoned in favour of Castilian, it inevitably fell into the vegetative condition of a provincial patois. Speaking generally, Portuguese is further removed than Castilian from Latin ; its development has gone further, and its actual forms are more worn out than those of the sister language, and hence it has, not without reason, been compared to French, with which it has some very notable analogies. But, on the other hand, Portuguese has remained more exclusively Latin in its vocabulary, and, particularly in its conjugation, it has managed to preserve several features which give it, as compared with Castilian, a highly archaic air. Old Portuguese, and more especially the poetic language of the 13th century, received from the language of the troubadours, in whose poetry the earlier Portuguese poets found much of their inspiration, certain words and certain turns of expression which have left upon it indelible traces.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Vowels. —</hi>Lat. 8, 8 with the accent have not been diphthongized into <hi rend="italic">ie, uo, ue: pé</hi> (pedem), <hi rend="italic">dez</hi> (decem), <hi rend="italic">bom</hi> (bonus), <hi rend="italic">pode </hi>(potet). On the other hand, Portuguese has a large number of strong diphthongs produced by the attraction of an <hi rend="italic">i</hi> in hiatus or the resolution of an explosive into <hi rend="italic">i : rαibα</hi> (rabia), <hi rend="italic">feira</hi> (feria), <hi rend="italic">feito</hi> (factum), <hi rend="italic">seixo</hi> (saxum), <hi rend="italic">oito</hi> (octo). A quite peculiar feature of the language occurs in the “ nasal vowels,” which are formed by the Latin accented vowels followed by <hi rend="italic">m, n,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">nt, nd : b</hi>ẽ (bene), <hi rend="italic">grã</hi> (grandem), <hi rend="italic">bo</hi> (bonum). These nasal vowels enter into combination with a final atonic vowel: <hi rend="italic">irmão</hi> (germanus); also <hi rend="italic">amão </hi>(amant), <hi rend="italic">sermão</hi> (sermonem), where the <hi rend="italic">o</hi> is a degenerated representative of the Latin final vowel. In Old Portuguese the nasal vowel or diphthong was not as now marked by the <hi rend="italic">til </hi>(˜)<hi rend="italic">,</hi> but was expressed indifferently and without regard to the etymology by <hi rend="italic">m </hi>or <hi rend="italic">n : bem</hi> (bene), <hi rend="italic">tan</hi> (tantum), <hi rend="italic">disserom</hi> (dixerunt), <hi rend="italic">sermom </hi>(sermonem). The Latin diphthong <hi rend="italic">aU</hi> is rendered in Portuguese by <hi rend="italic">ou (ouro,</hi> aurum; <hi rend="italic">pouco,</hi> paucum), also pronounced <hi rend="italic">oi</hi>. With regard to the atonic vowels, there is a tendency to reduce <hi rend="italic">a</hi> into a</p></body></text></TEI>